<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/83/0 images: 446-455</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).SECRET.COPY NO.CABINET    87 (36).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10, downing street, S.W.I., on MONDAY, 6th APRIL, 1936,at 12 noon.AGENDUM.THE INTERNATIONAL SITUATION.The Italo-Abyssinian Dispute.Germany and the Locarno Treaty.(Signed)    M.P.A.  HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.,6th April, 1935.
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJBSTYtS GOVERNMENT).SECRET. COPY NO.CABINET   27 (36).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.I.,  on MONDAY,6th APRIL, 1936, at 12 noon.PRESENT:The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.      (in the Chair).The Right Hon.J, Ramsay MacDonald, M.P, ,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Lord Chancellor,The Right Hon.^Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, CCS. I.,K.CV. 0. ,  O.B.E. , K.C., M.P. ,Secretary -of State for HomeAffairs.The Right Hon.Anthony Eden, M.C , M.P. ,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon.A. Duff Cooper, D.S.O., M.P. ,Secretary of State for War.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland,CCS. I., C C I.E. , Secretaryof State for India.The Right Hon.Walter Runciman, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.Sir Thomas Inskip, CB.E. , K.C ,M.P., Minister for theCo-Ordination of Defence.The Right Hon.Oliver Stanley, M.C., M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Ernest Brown, M.C , M.P. ,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K.C,CCS. I. , CO. 1.E. ,Lord Privy Seal,The Right Hon.Malcolm MacDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon.J.H.  Thomas, M.P. ,Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.The Viscount Monsell, G-.B.E. ,First Lord of the Admiralty,The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M,C, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Y/ood, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P.,First Commissioner of Works.Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B., G.C.M.G., G.CV.C,  ...... Secretary
fpFE ITAL0-BYS8IITIANISPUTE.(previous reference:cabinet 25 (36)Conclusion 4),3c (*0 31.      The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that he had received a visitfrom a special envoy of the Abyssinian G-overnmentwho had come from Paris and had reported that themilitary situation of the Abyssinians was nowdesperate. This had been confirmed by a telegramhe had received that very morning from Addis Ababaand by other sources of information.       Consequently,on Saturday, April 4th, he had advised the abyssinian envoy to get in touch with SenorMadariaga with a view to an early meeting of theLeague Committee of Thirteen,        He, himself, had also sent a message to Senor Madariaga recommending a meeting of the Committee which had now been called for Wednesday, April 8th. The Committee wouldhave to consider two questions, namely: (l) conciliation and (2) the use of gas by Italy, It was reportedthat the Italian Government intended to deny usinggas (see Conclusion 2), He reminded hiscolleagues that a Debate would take place in theHouse of Commons that afternoon. The line he wouldtake, subject to the agreement of his colleagues, wasthat a meeting of the Committee of Thirteen was t4; beheld at Geneva, mainly sn our initiative, on Wednesday next to consider the possibilities of bringing aboutconciliation between the two belligerents:    thesubject could not be pursued indefinitely and if noresult was achieved it would be necessary to summonthe Committee of Eighteen to consider furthersanctions. He would like to add that so far as   *
measures of an economic or financial character which the other nations were prepared jointly toapply. He also wished to consider at Genevawhether anything positive could he dene toassist Abyssinia.The Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs admitted that the action proposed was not likely to prove effective.       The only effective action at the present stage would be the closing of the Suez Canal. Moreover, France was likely to oppose any further sanctions, but he wishedto take the attitude he had suggested in order tosatisfy British public opinion.In the course of the discussion thatfollowod    it was suggested that to propose somonew sanction,such as an oil sanction now when itwas too late, would be regarded by public opinon as futile. It was suggested that it would bobetter to lay emphasis rather on conciliation andto leave sanctions out of mind.       That Italy had won and the League had failed to st^P her werefacts that could not be concealed.While it was recognised that the situation had changed with the Italian success anothersuggestion was that some stress might be laid onthe fact that sanctions were in force and thatthere was no intention of raising them, though inthe new circumstances,  such as the imminence ofthe rains, and the possibility of negotiations,it was not considered worth while to put on newsanctions which could not operate sufficientlyrapidly to affect the situation.-        What public- 2 -
opinion would wish to know was, how theLeague was to urevent impossible terms beingforded on Abyssinia?     In dealing with thataspect the maintenance of sanctions which wereimposing a good deal of pressure on italy might, it was suggested, be a big factor,though it might not be sufficient to setAbyssinia up again.In order to narrow the issue thequestion was raised whether the Cabinet were willing to consider closing the Suez Canal.This,  it was recognised, would involve warwith Italy, which the Prime Minister stated(and without contradiction) he was unwilling to envisage in the present state of Europe.It was recognised that the Governmentwould be criticised on the ground that it had failed to use the machinery of the League ofNations to save Abyssinia.        It was suggestedthat the reply should be that at no time hadthere been a reasonable prospect of applyingmethods that might achieve success unless wehad been prepared for the risk of war with italy. Oil sanctions were a possible exception, but we had expressed our willingness to agree to oil sanctions which had been postponed in the hope of a successful effort atconciliation. At the present time, however,,an oil sanction would, it was suggested, onlybe an impotent gesture as it would be too slowin operation to save Abyssinia.
A 9 9Lk -J (4Another suggestion was that it would he desirable not to state that Abyssinia was in adesperate situation as this would encourage Italy andweaken the prospects of conciliation. A point that could be made against Italy was that the oil sanction had been dronped for the reason that theItalians had accepted conciliation, taut their methodof carrying cut their promise had been an intensification of their war effort.The Cabinet agreed:That in the Debate the same after-noon the Secretary of State for Por-eign Affairs should be authorisedto state that,largely on Britishinitiative ,the League of nations committee of Thirteen was to meet at Geneva on Wednesday, 8th April:That if no success were achieved in the direction of conciliationthe Committee of Eighteen wouldprobably be summoned:That we, as a nation, were preparedto take part in any extension of sanctions which other nations wereprepared jointly to apply.      He mightadd that some lessons could be derived from these events, for example,the League,  owing to its incom-pleteness, was unable to enforceeconomic sanctions that would produce any early effect.(For decision re poison gas, see conclusion 2).
t? wGAS WARFARE.[previous reference:Cabinet 2b (36)Conclusion 4).2. In the course of the discussion partlysummarised in Conclusion 1 above, the questionof the Italian use of poison gas was discussed at some length.The Italian action was recognised to have greatly shocked public opinion in this countryand the same was true to some extent in France,The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs -said it was reported that the Italian Governmentwere going to deny having used gas.        The cabinet discussion showed however that the evidence from theRed Cross and other sources proved conclusivelythat poison gas had been used extensively by theItalian Air Force,      In the circumstances, it was recognised that public opinion would ask how, ifpoison gas could not be prevented in this war, itcould be prevented elsewhere, e,g,  in Europe.Indeed, the use of gas in this campaign might become a great historic fact,      Italy,  it was pointed out,could not justify the indiscriminate use of gas.The Treaty which ruled it out did not provide anyexception justifying its use as a method of retaliation for other outrages.        It was suggestedthat to point out the ineffectiveness of the Leagueto prevent a breach of a Convention of this kind wouldbe a good way of introducing that part of the speech of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,Some discussion took place as to whether itwould be wise for the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs, in introducing the question of gas, to saythat the subject was being inquired into by theLeague Committee of Thirteen, or, alternatively, -to
state that our evidence on the subject was over-whelming.      It was suggested that to state thelatter and to admit that nothing could be done tosecure compliance with the terms of the Convention,would be a very weak position to take.      Indeed,it was recognised that the position would be a weakone even though it v/ere   stated   that the subject was being inquired into by the Committee of Thirteen.After further discussion the Cabinet agreed:That, so far as gas warfare was concerned,the Secretary of State for Foreign&apos;Affairs should be authorised to propose an impartial inquiry through the Leagueof Nations since this was a question which affected every nation in the world, andmore especially nations of Europe.In the course of his remarks in theHouse of Commons he might point out thatConventions of this kind were not sufficient, and to render them effective,it would be necessary to prevent manu-facture.      If all the countries of theworld were democracies this might be easier.
THE ITALO-abyssinian dispute.Ipyssinian1 desire for a loan.3.      The Chancellor of the Exchequer reportedthat an Abyssinian representative was trying to induce the Treasury to assist him in the issue of a loan on the London market.      The position was thatno-one could issue a foreign loan without obtaining the authority of the Chancellor of the Exchequer.Of course if permission for such a loan were given,it would, in accordance with the invariable practice,be announced that the Government took no responsibilityof any kind as to the prospects of its success.Nevertheless, public opinion would be inclined toassume that the loan had received the blessing of theGovernment, and if people subscribed to it and lostthey might blame the Government.After a short discussion the Cabinet agreed:That the Treasury would not be justifiedin refusing the issue of a loan as there might be people who were willing to subscribe for sentimental or other reasons, but that it would be an advantage if the issue could be postponed for a week or two.
A O f*(LooGERMANY ANDTHE locarno treaty.The Meetingat Geneva.&apos; previouslReference:Cabinet 26 (36)Conclusions 2and 3).4.     The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that the Locarno Powers would meet at Geneva during the sessions arranged inconnection with the Italo-Abyssinian dispute.In the House of Commons he proposed to take aline calculated to steady public opinion as to what could be done in the direction of &quot;getting back to geneva&quot;.      He did not want to encourage the FrenchGovernment to revive the Geneva Protocol.      He proposedtherefore, to ask some questions, for example, as towhether it was thought that we were prepared to give guarantees to countries in Eastern Europe and whetherthe Scandinavians would accept obligations in SouthernEurope.The Cabinet approved the above line and agreed:(a) To approve the issue of a White paper on relations with Germany during thelast two years, as proposed by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs.(b) To take note that the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs would proceedto Geneva on the following day, Tuesday,7th April.(c) To leave to the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs to settle with the lord privy Seal whether the latter should accompany him to Geneva.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.,6th April, 1936.

</content>
</cab>
