<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/83/0 images: 482-487</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).SECRET. COPY NO.CABINET    29 (36).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held in the Prime Minister&apos;room, House of Commons, on THURSDAY, 9th APRIL, 1936,at 12 Noon.AGENDUM.PROGRAMME OF NEW CONSTRUCTION FOR 1936. &apos;(Reference Cabinet 10 (56) (b) to (e)).Memorandum by the First Lord of theAdmiraltyCP. 105 (56)    - circulated herewith.(Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.8th April, 1956.
&apos;(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET. COPY NO.CABINET    29  (36).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cahinet held inthe prime Minister&apos;s room, House of Commons,on THURSDAY, 9th APRIL,  1936, at 12 noon.PRESENT:The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin,- M.P. ,Prime Minister.      (in the Chair).The Right.. Hon.J. Ramsay MacDonald, M. P. ,Lord president of the Council,Tie Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P. ,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. . &apos;.Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I.,K.C.V.O., O.B.E., K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for HomeAffairs.The Right Hon.A. Duff Cooper, D.S.O., M.P.,Secretary of State for War,The Right Hon.Malcolm MacDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hen,The Viscount Swinton, G.B.E.,M.C., Secretary of State forAir,The Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland,G.CS.I., G.CI.E. , Secretaryof State for India.The Right Hon.Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.E.,CM.G. , M,P. , Secretary ofState for Scotland.The Right Hon.J,H,  Thomas, M.P,,Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.Walter Runciman, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade,The Right Hon.Sir Thomas Inskip, C.B.E., K.C.,M.P., Minister for theCo-Ordinatien of Defence.The Right Hon.The Viscount Monsell, G.B.E.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C., M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hen.Oliver Stanley, M.C., M.P. ,President of the Board efEducation,The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.P. ,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.W.  Ormsby-Gore, M, P. ,First Commissioner of Works.Secretary, i
qC-RAMME OP 1.      The Cahinet had hefore them a Memorandum by thejf CONSTRUC-ON FOR 1936. First Lord of the Admiralty (CP. 103 (36)) proposing the following Programme of New Construction for 1936.-pevious 2 Capital Shipsinference. 5 Cruisersibinet 10 9 Destroyers36)  (b)  to 4 Submariness)).   - 1 Aircraft Carrier/ 5 Sloops ..4&amp;C&amp;k*)ii a number of small craft viz.-1 River Gunboat1 Trawler2 Motor Minesweepers2 Small Surveying vessels5 Boom Defence Vessels2 Special Service Vessels6 Coastal Motor Boats(in future to be called MotorTorpedo Boats)3 Tug s.An Appendix to the Memorandum showed that thetotal estimated cost of this programme would be 38,345,450,  of which only  3,139,000 was expected to fall in 1936.In reply to questions, the First Lord explainedthat the new capital ships v/ould be of 35,000 tons as the United States of America had refused to agree toa lower figure.      The ships would be armed with 14&quot; guns,The Minister for Co-Ordination of Defence gavesome account of the progress made with the inquiry intocapital ships as affected by aircraft.      The cabinet were reminded that the new capital ships could not belaid down until January 1937, so that there would betime to taxe into account any conclusions that might result from the inquiry.In reply to comment on the large cost of theproposed aircraft carrier ( 3,800,000), the First Lordsaid that it had been intended to provide a smallerand cheaper carrier, but the design was not yet
in case it became necessary to &quot;build a largecarrier.The Cabinet agreed:To approve the programme of new naval construction for 1936 proposed by theFirst Lord of the Admiralty in cp.  103 (36) and summarised above.
THE ITALO-abyssinian dispute.Abyssiniandesire fora loan.(previous reference:Cabinet 27 (36)Conclusion 3).2.    The Chancellor of the Exchequer said he hadreceived a telegram from the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs asking that, in view ofAddis Ababa telegram No. 167 and the situation at Geneva the issue of the loan, which Abyssinia wishedto place on the London money market, might be facilitated.      He was not proposing to oppose theissue of the loan.The suggestion was made that the advertisementof the loan would probably contain a statement thatthe Government had approved it. The cabinet were informed, however, that the advertisementwould probably be submitted to the Treasury.      It wassuggested that in that event the advertisement should contain no mention of Government approval, to the loan,but that, if the question was raised in Parliament,it should be explained that all that had been done wasto arrange that the issue was not blocked by an artificial obstacle.The Cabinet agreed:(a) That the Chancellor of the exchequer should facilitate the removal of the obstacles to the issue on the Londonmoney market of a loan to Abyssinia.(b) To leave to the Chancellor of theExchequer the arrangements as to what should be said in the advertisementof the loan in regard to the Govern-menfs attitude.
fnp 433THE BUDGET.(previous reference:cabinet 23 (35))F.8.3.    The Chancellor of the Exchequer communicatedto the Cabinet full details of his financial proposals for the forthcoming Budget, which were approved by the cabinet.      He took the opportunityto describe his present views as to how theDefence Programmes should be financed.In view of the great importance of secrecy,the financial details, in accordance with precedentare not recorded in the Cabinet Minutes.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.,9th April, 1936.

</content>
</cab>
