<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/77/0 images: 162-166</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.P.(55) 13220th September, 1955CABINETLOCAL AUTHORITIES CAPITAL expenditure memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer the capital expenditure of local authorities (United Kingdom) is nearly  600. millions a year - one-quarter of total investment.    This isan element of decisive importance in the programme of anti-hiflationaryaction.2.        The measures to deal with it are:-(a) The reduction in subsidised housing.(c) Stabilisation of local authorities other capitalexpenditure at the 1954-55 level.(c) Certain changes in the conditions under which localauthorities borrow from the Public Works Loan Board(P.W.L.B.).3.        These are complementary, and should work effectively withoutsubjecting the local authorities to more detailed control from the centre and weakening their financial responsibility and discretion.Housing4.       This is nearly 65 per cent of the authorities total capitalexpenditure.    It may be helpful if I set out my views on the proposalsof the Minister of Housing and Local Government.5.        I agree with the rates of subsidy of  24 and  10.6.       I agree also with the freeing from allocation, on the under-standing that a watch is kept so that if the numbers are likely to exceeda certain figure, the alert is sounded and prompt action taken, either by reduction of the subsidy or otherwise.    It is important to be clearon this limitation, and in my view it would give unnecessary hostagesto fortune to give the public the impression of unlimited freedom.7,        On the numbers proposed by the Minister, I agree that theoutput of subsidised houses should be reduced as quickly as possible to120,000 (England and Wales).    But I cannot agree that this should beregarded also as a minimum and further action (presumably an increaseThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limitedt     -      -It is issued for the personal use of...........................TOP SECRET Copy NoJ^
of subsidy) taken if output tended to fall lower.    Our political commitments on slum clearance, etc., do not imply an output of more than 100,000 andI see no valid case for going beyond this.8.        I agree also that we should let the total output of houses (GreatBritain) fall to 270,000, but I should again feel that it would be dangerous to begin regarding this as a minimum.   I must emphasize that every20,000 houses represents investment (including ancillary services) ofabout  40 millions, and it can be strongly argued that there are otherneeds for social investment which would be of much more importance than marginal houses between, say, 270,000 and 250,000.9.        I conclude therefore that our aim in subsidised housing (Englandand Wales) should be a maximum of 120,000 and a minimum of 100,000.Other capital expenditure10.       I undertook to circulate a draft message to those of my colleagues who are directly concerned.    The re-draft art Annex A incorporates anumber of suggestions which have been made, but I have not of course beenable to discuss points which have been raised.    This message would besent to every local authority in England and Wales over the signaturesof the Minister of Housing and myself, and to every authority in Scotlandover the signatures of the Secretary of State and myself.    It would betimed to reach the authorities as soon after the statements in parliament as possible.11.       The essential point of the message is that the local authority is asked to review its capital expenditure (other than housing) and thatits aim should be to prevent it from rising above the 1954-55 level.    Weare bound to accept the consequence that this may lead to a postponement of projects which have already been authorised;  and it follows that wehave to accept the local authority&apos;s judgment of what is most important in the locality (except where a choice is being made between elements inthe same Departments programme).    Some of my colleagues may find it desirable to issue circulars themselves setting out the priorities to befollowed between projects within their own sphere of responsibility.12,      Some authorities are likely to find it easier than others tocomply with this request; the decline in housing will have considerableeffects upon the demand for other capital expenditure (e. g. water and sewerage), and this will in many cases make it easier to expand otherparts of the programme,    A preponderant part of the expenditure ofCounty Councils, however, is on educational building.    I am aware of thepublic pronouncements made by the Government, especially on ruralre-organisation.    I hope to discuss with the Minister of Education thepossibility of authorities delaying the least urgent part of their educationalbuilding programmes in order to comply with the terms of the message.13.      A table in Annex B shows the distribution of local authoritiescapital expenditure in England and Wales; these are totals for the whole country covering all types of authority,14.      Some of my colleagues have suggested that certain items ofexpenditure should be excluded from this message, on the grounds that national programmes have already been authorised.    While I appreciate
the force of the arguments put forward, I feel that the exclusion ofimportant elements would frustrate the purpose of the message,.   Housingis excluded because housing is a declining programme j if we excludedthe expanding programmes also, there would be no further point in the message.Public Works Loan Board15,      I propose to ask the P.W.L.B. to confine their lending to authorities which cannot borrow on the stock or mortgage markets, andto lend at rates based not on Government but on local authority credit,I have circulated a separate paper explaining this measure   in detail(CP. (55) 131).Conclusion16.      To sum up, these three series of measures - reduction &quot;insubsidised housing, stabilisation of other expenditure, and change in conditions of lending - are all parts of our approach to the problem oflocal authority capital expenditure.    My colleagues will be taking decisions on housing and P.W.L.3, separately,17,       I ask my colleagues agreement accordingly to arrange, inconsultation with the Secretary of State for Scotland and the Minister of housing and Local Government, for the distribution of the message at annex A to all local authorities.R.A.B.Treasury Chambers, S. W. 1,20th September, 1955.
DRAFT MESSAGE TO LOCAL, AUTHORITIES1. /^Reference to Chancellor&apos;s statement and (in England and Wales)to Minister of Housing&apos;s statement about housing policy.^2.        We are writing to you, and to all other local authorities, on behalfof the Government to ask you to undertake an immediate review of yourcapital expenditure for the period from now to   31st March /^Scotland,15th Mavy7l957.    We also ask you to review your current expenditure inorder to secure economies wherever possible, and to refrain, save incases of exceptional need, from undertaking new services which will involve additional expenditure either from Government grants or from therates.3.        The reason for this request is that in recent months it has become clear that the productive resources of the nation are carrying too heavy aload.    The consequence of this is seen in the upward movement of costs and prices at home, as well as in the pressure on sterling abroad.4.        The Governments policy is designed to bring the total demandwithin the capacity of the nation&apos;s productive resources.    It has alwaysbeen recognised, from the Full Employment White Paper of 1944 (Cmd, 6527)onwards,       that the maintenance of full employment involves a continuing process of adjustment, particularly in the capital expenditureplans of public authorities, in order to keep the economic affairs of thecountry on an even keel.5.        The aim should be to ensure that your authority&apos;s capitalexpenditure (other than on housing) in each of the years 1955-56 and1956-57 does not exceed that of 1954-55, and that within this limit no new -works, even those already authorised, are undertaken unless yourauthority are satisfied that these works are urgently necessary to meetthe needs of the area.    For some authorities with special problems,particularly those with rapidly expanding populations, some increase ofcapital expenditure above the 1954-55 level may be inescapable.    Someauthorities, on the other hand, may well be able to secure a reduction intheir capital expenditure below the level of 1954-55,6,        In this process of review, questions of the priority to be givento the claims of different services are bound to arise, and should bedecided in the light of the local circumstances in your own area.    Wherethere are considerations of national policy which should be taken intoaccount in choosing between projects within the field of responsibilityof one Government Department, you will be informed by the Department.The Departments will not press local authorities to provide services ofa more expensive standard than the authorities would regard as being necessary in the light of local conditions.7.        It is appreciated that to give effect to the requests in this message may result in the postponement of improvements which localauthorities would like to make in the standards of their services.    Butthe essential condition for all future progress is to,secure and maintainthe nation&apos;s internal and external economic stability now.    Failure totake the necessary action for this purpose would involve a much more serious setback to employment and the standard of living.
ANNEX BCAPITAL EXPENDITURE; LOCAL AUTHORITIES(ENGLAND AND WALES)195^-55  m.Total 473.7Housing 291.other than housing 182.education 62. 7Water and sewerage 42. land drainage and coast protection 9. 9Town and country planning 9* 2Highways 12.0Harbours, docks and piers 6.public lighting 2. 5Private street works 2. 1Passenger transport 3,4-Police and fire 10,health and welfare and child care 5, other 16.3182.3

</content>
</cab>
