<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/77/0 images: 167-178</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS   GOVERNMENTSMALLER COLONIAL territories memorandum by the Secretary of State for the ColoniesThis paper has been prepared in consultation with the Financial Secretary,Treasury, following discussion of an earlier, and substantially similar, version ofit in the Ministerial Committee on Malta. M.C. (55) 2nd Meeting.2. Since the Parliamentary Conference on Malta is being told, in evidence given on behalf of Her Majesty&apos;s Government, that representation of Malta at westminster is not thought likely to stimulate early pressure from any othersmaller colonies for similar treatment, the Conference may wish itself to considerthat possibility fairly closely and, in particular, it may ask what alternativeconstitutional development there is which could suitably be offered to the territories in question.3. Some members of the Parliamentary Conference will know that the futureof the smaller colonial territories was examined, on a confidential, basis, in 1949-51by a Committee appointed by Mr. Creech Jones. A copy of that Committee&apos;ssummary of recommendations is attached at Appendix A. The opinions of anumber of Colonial Governors were sought on those recommendations which, ingeneral, attracted so little support that action taken upon them has, in the event,been negligible.4. Although the ideas in the Report of this Committee thus proved, in theview of the Governors concerned, to be unacceptable, the question of the futureof the smaller colonial territories has been reviewed from time to time and, in thecourse of a debate on the 21st June last, I told Parliament that I would study withcare the problem of those territories. Recent studies in the Colonial Office have resulted in the scheme of which an outline is given in Appendix B. This takes account of the Report of the Committee of 1949-51 and attempts to meet the mainobjections raised by the Colonial Governors to the proposals in that Report.5. The scheme outlined in Appendix B is, of course, not intended for those territories which, either on their own or as members of Federations can beexpected to move gradually towards the achievement of a fully independent status and to become candidates for full Commonwealth membership. A list of those territories is given in Appendix C. The three main East African territories havebeen included since, although their political future is still uncertain, they obviouslycannot be regarded as &quot; smaller territories &quot; in the present context.6. A list of the remaining Colonial territories (except Malta) is given inAppendix D. A copy of the new scheme (Appendix B) was sent recently to theGovernor of each of these territories (except Cyprus, whose Governor wasconsulted personally), who was asked to give (after consulting, if need be, his principal official advisers but no one else) his view on the two following questions:  (a) to what extent is the scheme thought likely to be acceptable, on its merit,in the particular territory; and(b) if the scheme would otherwise be acceptable would it be likely to be rejected (as being inferior treatment) if Malta is given representation at Westminster?Primed for the Cabinet.   September 1955SECRETCopy No.   69CP. (55) 13327th September, 1955CABINET
m0!7. The replies from Governors are summarised in Appendix E. It will beseen that only three of them (Gambia, Gibraltar and Mauritius) consider that pressure for representation at Westminster might follow if that were granted to malta. But in two cases (Gambia and Mauritius) the main purpose of that pressure would be to obtain financial help from Her Majesty&apos;s Government to raisethe levels of wages and social services either to, or substantially towards, UnitedKingdom standards assuming that such help were granted to Malta. Gibraltarwould be unlikely to press for representation if that was conditional on a graduallevelling-up of taxation to United Kingdom rates. It is not however contemplated that the rates of direct and indirect taxation in Malta should be raised in the foreseeable future to United Kingdom levels; and the possibility cannot be excludedthat the kind of settlement which might be.reached for Malta would eventuallystimulate demands in at least Gambia, Gibraltar and Mauritius for similar treatment, including representation at Westminster. Nevertheless it does notappear likely that representation for Malta will stimulate immediate pressure for similar treatment in any of the territories, andT think that it should be possiblefor Her Majesty&apos;s Government to present any radical solution to Malta&apos;srelationship with the United Kingdom as appropriate to Malta&apos;s uniquecircumstances.8.   The replies of Governors can be classified, broadly as follows:  (a) Those territories for which &quot; Statehood &quot; has immediate attractions. Theyare: Aden (Colony), British Honduras, Mauritius, Gambia, Gibraltar,Fiji, North Borneo, Falkland Islands, Sarawak, Seychelles.(b) Those for which it has longer-term attractions.   They are: Bahamas,Bermuda (in the sense that public opinion there does not appear actuallyinterested in any change from their present status), Western PacificHigh Commission territories (in the sense that they are still at tooelementary a constitutional Stage).(c) Those for which it is not regarded, in the foreseeable future, as suitable.They are: Brunei, Hong Kong, Somaliland Protectorate, aden protectorate, Zanzibar, British Guiana and St. Helena.This classification omits Sierra Leone, I share the Governor&apos;opinion that it is doubtful whether any status which appeared to impairSierra Leone&apos;s opportunities to achieve, eventually, independence within the Commonwealth would be politically acceptable.9. My colleagues may consider that the degree of favour for the schemeshown by Governors, the possibility that public opinion in some of the territoriesmight eventually ask for representation at Westminster for economic reasons and perhaps for political reasons which Governors could not be expected to foresee,the likelihood of public and Parliamentary interest here being increased by thevery fact of the Malta Conference, and the example of the developing tempo of constitutional advance in the larger colonial territories, make it desirable to give further early consideration to the scheme outlined in Appendix B. The purposeof that study would be to get the proposals into concrete form in the context ofcertain selected territories. This would be done in the first instance in consultationwith the Governors, local unofficial leaders being brought into the discussion whenthe issues had been sufficiently clarified. The manner and timing of the announce-,rhent of policy would be considered when it had been established that a workablescheme acceptable to at any rate some territories Could be produced.10. As a separate, though related, exercise I consider that we should have it in mind to convene, some time next year, a conference of Chief Ministers (orthe equivalent) of those territories (not only the smaller ones) which now havea Ministerial or quasi-Ministerial form of government. The primary purposeof such a conference would be to discuss generally with these leaders the policies and aims of Her Majesty&apos;s Government, but it would enable us to test opinion,as to the value of setting up any regular consultative machinery such as is pressedupon us in Parliament from time to time. (The Financial Secretary wishes to reserve his position on this suggestion.) 1 ;;11. Should members of the Round Table Conference enauire about our attitude to the question of the future of the &quot; smaller territories,&quot; I consider thatwe should say that that is not a specific matter for this Conference, but that weare very fully aware of the importance of the question arid are giving it earnest
consideration. If, as is likely, we are pressed to&apos; be more forthcoming, I would propose to circulate to the Conference a&apos; note of the recommendations of theSmaller Territories Committee (Appendix A) and a note (Appendix F) stating inGeneral terms the position which we shall have reached if my colleagues approvemy present suggestions. It would not, I think, be desirable to circulate to this conference the detailed scheme set out in Appendix B.&apos;.&apos; .12. . I should like to emphasise that. the Colonial Office study which has produced the scheme outlined in Appendix B at no time contemplated bringingMalta within the scheme; nor would it be appropriate to do so now. In many waysMalta has, and is dissatisfied with, a constitutional status similar to that to whichaspirants to &quot;Statehood&quot; have yet to progress. &quot;Statehood&quot; is. neither&quot;integration&quot; nor &quot; dominion status,&quot; nor even.&apos;&quot; quasi-dominion status,&quot; andtherefore would not interest either of.the main political parties in Malta. Theexistence of the scheme outlined in Appendix B should not, therefore, be revealedto any of the Maltese representatives at the Conference.: .. -. A. L-B.Colonial Office, S.W. 1,21st September, 1955.APPENDIX ASUMMARY OF MAIN RECOMMENDATIONS OF SMALLERTERRITORIES COMMITTEEI (a) A new constitutional status should be established by the creation ofIsland States and City States of the Commonwealth, and this status should be between that of a dependency and an independent member of the Commonwealth.(6) While there would be different classes of Island and City States, theyShould all be given the greatest possible degree of internal self-government and thatgovernment should be vested in a State Council.(c) The basis of membership of the State Council should be election either directly or by local government bodies.id) In the simpler type of City or Island State constitution, the State council should administer local government as well as central government services. Inother types, there should be separate local government bodies, but since these would have the responsibility of electing the State Council, there would be intimateassociation between local and central government.ie) Except in the more complex type of Island or City State (Class III), theState Council should combine executive and legislative functions.(/) As far as possible the State Council should be regarded as the executive and should function as such. For executive matters which must remain vested inthe Governor he should be assisted by one or more consultative bodies, whichwould be purely advisory and for specified subjects.ig) In larger and more complex territories there should be a small executivebody, selected from and responsible to the State Council, to be termed a Councilof Government.ih) Members of the Council of Government would be termed Ministers andwould assume responsibility for one or more functions of Government.(/) The Council of Government should be primarily an executive body, butshodld also, to a limited extent, carry out the functions of a second Chamber.(/) Civil Servants, with the exception of the holders of the three State offices of State Secretary, Attorney-General and Financial Secretary, should, in practice,be the servants of the State Council, and their position should be analogous tothat of the staff of a local authority,; ik) Financial responsibility should be vested in the State Council and the delegation of financial power to the Council should be as complete as possible.
(/) Territories which are solvent should&apos;not be required to submit their annualestimates to the Secretary of State for approval, and territories which are insolventowing to unavoidable causes should receive assistance in the form of a block grantcovering a period of years.(m) A Colonial. Consultative Council should be., created, associated inconception with the Privy, Council. Such a purely advisory body should, in anycase, be set up for Island and City States and, if limited to these territories, shouldbe designated His Majesty&apos;s Council of Island and City States, but in the view ofthe majority of us such a Council should include representatives from allnon-self-governing territories of the Commonwealth.\n) The snialler territories should be encouraged to follow the practice of someof the larger territories in appointing accredited representatives in this country.id) PotentialqTeaders of the new City and Island States should be brought tothe country in greater numbers than at present for training, and a specialdepartment in the Colonial Office should co-ordinate all matters connected withColonial visitors.(p) The conversion Of the smaller colonial territories into Island and CityStates if decided oh should not be done piecemeal. It should be announced as anew departure and, after the necessary instruments had been prepared and theoffer of the new status had been explained to and accepted by the peoples concerned,it should be confirmed simultaneously on several territories by His Majesty theKing.APPENDIX BSMALLER COLONIAL TERRITORIES1. The proclaimed policy of Her Majesty&apos;s Government is &quot;to help theColonial Territories to achieve self-government within the Commonwealth,&quot; butobviously the term &quot;self-government&quot; does not mean the same thing for allterritories, irrespective of their characteristics. It is, however, generally assumed,notwithstanding at least one explicit statement to the contrary, that at present allcolonial territories are on one and the same ladder leading up to a common goal of&quot; Dominion &quot; status; and unless a clear preliminary understanding is established that certain territories cannot in fact reach the top, there is an obvious risk that atsome stage most probably when some specific demand has to be rejected in an atmosphere of controversy Her Majesty&apos;s Government will be accused of a breach of faith.2. The problem of the smaller territories may therefore be stated as one of devising a status (combining internal self-government with dependence upon theUnited Kingdom for defence and external affairs) which is accepted both as theproper aim of British Colonial policy, and as a desirable object for the aspirations of their peoples. In the following paragraphs there is described a conception of&quot; Statehood,&quot; as a possible solution. It takes account of the Report of the &quot;SmallerTerritories Committee &quot; in 1951 and attempts to meet the main objections whichhave been made to it.(i) A hew designation (&quot;State&quot; is provisionally suggested) would beestablished as a recognised technical term to denote a country self-governing in its internal affairs, but dependent upon the United&quot;Kingdom to the extent that it would be presided over by a&quot;&apos;:    representative of the Crown appointed on the advice of Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom and armed with reserve powers!-.&apos;, &apos; sufficient. to enable him to guarantee fulfilment of Her Majesty&apos;s;  V ,        Governments continuing&apos; responsibilities in defence, security, foreign&apos;/&apos;.&apos; relations and financial stability.  Such&apos;powers would include the right&apos;s &quot; : \  f   to assume direct administration of the territory in an emergency. The\v:&quot;;&quot;&apos;.&apos;,.:&apos; creation of the new category of &quot; State &quot; would be a public act of thev ;  ; -    Sovereign on the advice of Her Ministers in the United Kingdom, andthe title would, be an honourable distinction to be conferred by the&apos; Sovereign upon such territories as desired it and were considered to possess the necessary qualifications.
ij   :(ii) The qualifications for admission to Statehood would broadly consist of - (a) reasonable economic stability; i   m   , .(b) an established form of representative government, in which theExecutive. Council is the principal instrument of policy, with;     Ministers  responsible  to   an  elected  legislature or : Somecomparable arrangement giving unofficial representatives apredominant say in government;(c) proof of capacity for self-government in domestic affairs.(iii) Since Statehood should not be cheapened by conferring it upon verysmall or backward territories it should be limited, at least at the outset,to units of a certain size and importance.. (iv) Practical marks of distinction would need to accompany the grant ofStatehood, if it were to make any significant appeal. The most effectivewould be formal recognition of States&apos; legislatures as sovereignParliaments within the scope of their allotted responsibilities^ an appropriate adjunct, if it could be devised, would be a special relationship. between these legislatures and the CommonwealthParliamentary Association. A. further possibility would be the alteration of the title of the Sovereign^ representative from&quot; Governor &quot; to &quot; High Commissioner.&quot; Other &quot; marks &quot; could be devised, e.g., the right to fly a &quot; State &quot; flag,(v) Some form of central Council Meeting in London could also be established,but whereas the initiative in offering abandonment of Parliament^ rightto discuss the domestic affairs of the territories would have to comefrom the United Kingdom, it would be desirable to let the initiative fora central body come from the territories. Regional differences are somarked that any attempt by the United Kingdom to impose a central body would be impolitic. Such influence as the United Kingdomexercised in this matter should be confined perhaps to favouring aConference of Chief Ministers t of States, which would be in some sensea parallel organisation to the Meetings of&apos; Commonwealth PrimeMinisters, and would meet under the Chairmanship of the Secretaryof State as and when the opportunity existed for a profitable discussionof subjects of common interest.3. For the United Kingdom the most important implications of grantingStatehood in these terms may be stated in the form of questions of which thefollowing are principal examples:-id) Will the United Kingdom Parliament abandon its right to discuss the actsand decisions of State legislatures in their domestic affairs? In other words, will Parliament agree to treat the legislatures of States as it nowdoes the Parliament of Southern Rhodesia?(b) Will Parliament accept some limitation on its right to discuss the external relations of States in cases where (e.gr, an I.L.O. Convention) the subject matter falls largely within the scope of a State legislature?(c) Will Her Majesty&apos;s Government be prepared and able to maintain in theUnited Nations that it no longer has the authority to transmitinformation about the matters within the scope of State legislatures?4. The conception of Statehood outlined in this paper implies a kind ofdiarchy, but it is not proposed to make this explicit by introducing, as between states and the United Kingdom, a formal division of functions and responsibilitiessuch as exists to-day in the constitution of Malta and was formerly practised inIndia. Such formal diarchies have been found in practice to provoke rather thandiminish opportunities for controversy between the parties.What is in fact proposed here as the relationship between States and theUnited Kingdom \yould resemble that at present obtaining for the Gold Coast plus the abnegation by Parliament of itsi right:, to discuss the domestic matters of states. In handling domestic matters the Governor (except when using reserve powers) would i act; in i accordance with the advice of his Ministers in ExecutiveCouncil,    In dealing with the continuing responsibilities of Her Majesty&apos;s.,   * The..only limitation of such sovereignty being the.reserve legislative power of Governors.t The title &quot;Prime Minister&quot; in &quot; States &quot; should not be;. granted;;;..&quot; Chief Minister&quot; or&quot;Premier &quot; is more suitable.
Government,, the Governor would normally ask for the advice and assistance of his ministers, but would be empowered to act in his own discretion.   A State&apos;legislature would, not be debarred from debating or legislating upon any subject,domestic or otherwise, but legislation affecting United Kingdom responsibilities would not be effective without the consent of Her Majesty&apos;s Government.Summary5. (i) It appears desirable to forestall misunderstanding by re-affirmingclearly that Her Majesty&apos;s Government^ Colonial Policy of self-government withinthe Commonwealth cannot mean eventual sovereign independence for allterritories.(ii) Such a statement should however be accompanied by a positive declarationof policy about the status which territories which cannot qualify for full independence may expect to achieve.(iii) Examination of a suitable status has yielded the following proposals:  (a) A new category of &quot; State &quot; should be established, to denote a territory ofsome size and importance which is dependent upon the UnitedKingdom for defence  and  the conduct of external affairs but:.: self-governing in its domestic affairs.(b) Inclusion in this category should be regarded as an end in itself for,-b- territories which cannot aspire to full independence; it would not, ofcourse, preclude the eventual achievement of independence if new circumstances should arise which would make this possible in aparticular case.(c) A ;&apos; State &quot; should be granted suitable marks and privileges; the mostimportant of these is that its conduct of domestic affairs should not beopen to question in Parliament..  id) Her Majesty&apos;s Government should encourage the idea of holdingConferences of the Chief Ministers of &quot; States&quot; but should not&apos;-&apos; themselves take any initiative to secure the establishment of a Central, .-. . Council representative of such territories, leaving that to come from ther i places themselves.APPENDIX CTerritories which can aspire to full independence, or are in no sense &quot; smallerterritories &quot;: -Gold Coast.Nigeria.Northern Rhodesia    1 ag part of Centrai African Federation.singapore \ as part of a Malaya Federation (possibly,in time, covering Borneo territories also).Federation of Malaya jJamaicaBarbadosTrinidadLeeward IslandsWindward IslandsKenya.Uganda.Tanganyika.as part of a Caribbean Federation.APPENDIX DTerritories whose Governors were, consulted about the scheme inAppendix B:  Aden (Colony and Protectorate).Bahamas., Bermuda.
*British Guiana.*British Honduras.Cyprus. ;  rj Falkland Islands.Fiji.Gambia.Gibraltar.Hong Kong.Mauritius.North Borneo. iSt. Helena.Sarawak (including Brunei).Seychelles.Sierra Leone.Somaliland Protectorate.Western Pacific High Commission Territories.Zanzibar.* The possibility still exists of their joining a Caribbean Federation.APPENDIX ESUMMARY OF GOVERNORS&apos; REPLIESAden (Colony)&quot; Statehood &quot; would be generally acceptable to present political opinion inthe Colony; and would probably still be acceptable if Malta is givenrepresentation at Westminster. But &quot; Statehood &quot; would not be a suitable statusfor the Protectorate. The Governor has stressed the point that this estimate ofopinion in the Colony is contemporary. Public opinion there is changeable,and might alter radically under pressure of any propaganda from any other arab countries which depicted &quot; Statehood &quot; as a new form of imperialism.BahamasNo responsible opinion in the Colony seeks &quot; dominion status.&quot; Indeed thereis little articulate opinion in favour of a greater degree of responsible governmentthan Bahamas has long enjoyed. &quot; Statehood&quot; would be acceptable as providing as much self-government as the people of Bahamas would wish to achieve, and representation for Malta at Westminster would not be likely to arousejealousy or to prejudice acceptance of.&quot; Statehood.&quot; The Acting Governor suggeststhat long experience of representative government (such as Bahamas has enjoyed)might rank as a qualification for &quot; Statehood.&quot;BermudaBermuda opinion is perhaps more content with the title &quot; Colony &quot; than someother territories, and therefore there is unlikely to be any widespread demand for m&quot; Statehood &quot; but others would not accept tho implication that British-Guiana was^H- icC ******offer &quot; Statehood &quot; to Bermuda it would probably be acceptable.  If, however, a ty&amp;msj^broader franchise than at present exists in Bermuda were made a qualification for it*. tyfu&amp;tadmission to &quot; Statehood,&quot; this might give an incentive to coloured politicians to ^^vi^L.^/seek such a broadening, thus bringing relationship of &quot; Statehood &quot; to Bermuda into &quot;active local politics.  Representation for Malta at Westminster would not affectfeelings about &quot; Statehood &quot; in Bermuda.British GuianaThat part of the public opinion in favour of joining a British CaribbeanFederation would regard &quot; Statehood &quot;as a less preferable alternative to eventualfull self-government within the Federation. Some anti-Federationists might like&quot;Statehood,&quot; but others would not accept the implication that British Guiana was,incapable of obtaining complete independence, having regard to its size1 ariddevelopment potentialities. On one or other of the above grounds the majorityof Opinion in the Colony is unlikely to favour &quot; Statehood.&quot; It is unlikely that opinion in British Guiana would make any comparison with Malta.
British Honduras&quot; Statehood &quot; would be acceptable only to the extent that it represented animprovement on the present status of British Honduras as a colony. It would notbe acceptable as the Colony&apos;s final status. This acceptability would not be affectedby grant of representation to Malta.CyprusThe Governor of Cyprus, with whom the matter has been discussed during his visit to London for the Tripartite Conference, has confirmed that neitherrepresentation at Westminster nor &quot; Statehood &quot; would at present have the leastattraction for any considerable section of the Greek population of Cyprus. Also hedoubts whether either would have much attraction for any but a few of theTurkish population of the Island.Falkland IslandsAlthough small, the Falkland Islands are inhabited almost exclusively bypeople of British descent, who feel themselves capable of handling their own internal affairs. It is hoped that their small size would not preclude them from&quot; Statehood.&quot; Once that was understood &quot; Statehood&quot; would be locallyacceptable. The people of the Falkland Islands would not wish to send representatives to Westminster.Fiji&quot; Statehood&quot; would be popular and not prejudiced by the grant of representation to Malta. Nor is there likely to be pressure from Fiji for similarrepresentation. Nevertheless local feeling for some form of closer link withWestminster may result, and to meet such feelings Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentshould take a stronger initiative in creating and summoning a conference of ChiefMinisters.Gambia&quot; Statehood&quot; would be generally acceptable, provided that, to meet the feelings of local politicians, it were not presented as debarring further progress to eventual full self-government. However, a few ambitious individuals might fancythemselves as Members of Parliament, and a larger number might see in representa-tion at Westminster a means of averting eventual domination by the Gold Coast or some other large West African territory. Further, any feeling that suchrepresentation could secure for Gambia social and other services up to UnitedKingdom standards would arouse a certain envy. It may be hard for her majesty&apos;s Government to convince Gambians that the decision to confinerepresentation at Westminster to Malta is not in part based on race and climate;and it is possible that such a decision may raise dissatisfaction which could be stimulated so as to have a considerable local political effect. The idea of conferences of Chief Ministers of States in London is welcomed. It is emphasised that were Her Majesty&apos;s Government to hold that Gambia did not measure up toan immediate grant of &quot; Statehood &quot; this would lead to immediate agitation by thepolitically-minded for constitutional advance and that such agitation would be widely. supported.Gibraltar&quot; Statehood &quot; would be acceptable on its merits to Gibraltar as an advance on its present constitution. It is not likely to be rejected in Gibraltar if representa-tion at Westminster for Malta is to be coupled with increases in taxation to bring them to United Kingdom levels. But Gibraltar opinion would be attracted byrepresentation without taxation at United Kingdom rates and if there were any prospect that that might be conceded &quot; Statehood &quot; might be rejected.Hong KongAn all-elected legislature is, in present circumstances, out of the question for Hong Kong; nor is there any responsible local pressure for this. &quot; Statehood &quot;would therefore be inappropriate. Nevertheless, local feeling on the &quot; superiorstatus&quot; of Hong Kong, as a city comparable in many ways to Singapore, is
sensitive. This, however, could be effectively recognised, even if the colony werenot given &quot; Statehood,&quot; if senior unofficial members of the Executive and legislative Councils were invited to any conference of Chief Ministers in London.Mauritius &apos; ;iv&quot;Statehood&quot; appears both suitable and likely to be acceptable, but if theimpression were given that representation at Westminster for Malta would entail a commitment by Her Majesty&apos;s Government to subsidise Malta in order to hasten the development of social services up to United Kingdom levels- pending thedevelopment of its economy to. a stage at which it could bear commensuratetaxation there would be some danger of local pressure for similar treatment,particularly from the Mauritius Labour Party. If, however, it were made clearthat the development of social services depended on the ability of Malta to financethem, the attraction of &quot;Statehood&quot; would probably prevail/Reasonablesafeguards for minorities are suggested as a qualification for &quot; Statehood,&quot; where local conditions make such an arrangement desirable.North Borneo&quot; Statehood &quot; would not only be generally acceptable; it might well be greetedwith profound relief by more responsible people who are apprehensive of over-rapid general progress towards colonial self-government. Nor would acceptanceof &quot; Statehood &quot; be prejudiced by representation at Westminster for Malta. Whilerecent political events in Singapore and the Federation of Malaya appear likelyto delay rather than hasten the growth of closer association between North borneo and these territories, events there are likely to cause some pressure for more rapidpolitical development in North Borneo. Thus development of the territory toa condition which would qualify it for &quot; Statehood &quot; may be expected. The term&quot; State &quot; has a long history, with quite a different connotation, in North Borneo,as in other British territories in the Far East. North Borneo indeed was a &quot; State &quot;before it became a Colony. This position should be borne in mind in presenting the new conception of &quot; Statehood.&quot; Regional conferences of Chief Ministers ofState might be preferable to holding them in London, at any rate in the early yearsof Statehood, since there might be insufficient common interest or understandingto make effective a gathering in London of experienced Ministers from different parts of the world.St. HelenaIn the remote contingency of the qualifications for &quot; Statehood,&quot; as proposed,being established in St. Helena, the status would be acceptable; it would not be prejudiced by representation for Malta.Sarawak and Brunei&quot; Statehood&quot; would be a suitable and acceptable status for Sarawak.Although at present representative government on the Parliamentary model iselementary, it would be unwise to withhold &quot; Statehood &quot; for long from a countrysuch as Sarawak which, for one hundred years of its history, was a &quot; State &quot; andran its own domestic affairs.,. Refusal of &apos;.&apos; Statehood &quot; to Sarawak because of.the elementary character of its representative institutions would create localdisappointment and create pressure for immediate constitutional adjustment. Butrepresentation at Westminster would not be sought provided that some acceptablealternative was offered. Regional conferences meeting either in London or in the-Far East seem desirable. Too firm an announcement by Her Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment that some small territories in the Commonwealth cannot aspire to full self-government and independence might lead to dissatisfaction with the Common-wealth, as it might produce unfavourable comparisons between such a policy and the independence which has been obtained by other countries in &quot;SouthWEastAsia.Brunei is already a sovereign State, in treaty relationship; with her majesty^Government, and appears unsuitable for &quot; Statehood.&quot;Seychelles,: -..:/,.;.b^uw^yiH, n.k&quot;Statehood &quot; would appear to be acceptable on merits to the people ofSeychelles; and Maltese representation at Westminster would riot be likely to arouse dissatisfaction with &quot; Statehood &quot; as inferior treatment. &quot; *
APPENDIX FFUTURE OF SMALLER COLONIAL TERRITORIES(OTHER THAN MALTA)Note by Secretary of State for the colonies in this context &quot; Smaller territories &quot; means Colonies, &amp;c, which are too smallor remote to be able to look forward to independent national status, either alone or as components of a regional federation.2. The problem of devising a status for such territories which would satisfylocal aspirations while preserving the interests of Her Majesty&apos;s Government was examined confidentially by a Committee which sat between 1949 and 1951. TheCommittee made a number of recommendations (Appendix A) which have since been under continuous examination in consultation with Colonial Governors.3. Most of these recommendations were aimed at giving the people of the territories a greater measure of self-government in local affairs. From the pointof view of relationship to Her Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom, themost important recommendation was the establishment of a standing consultative council. This recommendation, however, found little favour with the Governorsconsulted. The general view was that the individual territories were more interested in their own status and relationship to the United Kingdom than incollective machinery, and that there would in fact be little matter of common concern for such a Council to deal with.4. In fact, since 1951, much has been done to promote the development in individual territories of a greater degree of local self-government along lines suited to local circumstances. There has been little or no indication of any real interestin the question of &quot; Status &quot; relative to the United Kingdom. (Even in british honduras, where the avowed policy of the Party now in office is to end&quot; Colonialism,&quot; this is presented as an ultimate rather than an immediate objective.)5. On the other hand, there is some pressure in this country, if not as yet inthe territories concerned, for Her Majesty&apos;s Government to proclaim a constructivepolicy for these small territories. In spite of at least one Ministerial statement tothe contrary, there is a widespread impression that &quot; self-government&quot; meanseventual independence.  Some territories are getting near the limit of practicableSierra Leone&quot; Statehood &quot; would be suitable for Sierra Leone, and perhaps acceptable toconservative public opinion. It is feared, however, that less conservativepoliticians, who may obtain a majority in Legislative Council in the next elections,could not openly admit to being satisfied with an inferior status to the Gold Coast unless Her Majesty&apos;s Government made clear that &quot; Statehood &quot; was not a barto eventual full self-government. Sierra Leone politicians would not be interestedin representation at Westminster.Somaliland Protectorate&quot; Statehood &quot; would not be acceptable to the Somalis, whose hopes lie in thedirection of eventual association with other neighbouring Somali territories. as yet development of representative government in the Protectorate is elementary.Western PacificEventual &quot; Statehood &quot; might be suitable and acceptable, but present politicalconsciousness is so elementary that forecasts must be most tentative.Representation for Malta at Westminster does not affect the above opinion.Zanzibar&quot; Statehood &quot; would not be appropriate to Zanzibar, nor acceptable locally,because of its special treaty relationship with Great Britain. This position wouldnot be affected by the grant of representation to Malta.
constitutional advance. It is highly desirable that that limit should be presentedand regarded as being in itself a worthy object of aspiration rather than asa compulsory halt half-way up a ladder. Apart from this general argument, it isclearly likely that any new development in regard to Malta may stimulate interestin the question of &quot; status &quot; and lead to demands not indeed for other territoriesnecessarily to be treated in exactly the same way as Malta, but for their particular problems to receive the same intensive and sympathetic attention as has been givento the problems of Malta.6. With these considerations in mind, plans are already being worked out fora new kind of status which could be offered to certain territories immediately orprospectively, according to their degree of political maturity. In effect, these plansenvisage a modified form of the &quot; Island and City States &quot; idea put forward by the1949-51 Committee. So far they have been discussed only with selectedGovernors; the next stage will be to get them into more concrete form and takelocal political leaders into consultation. It would therefore be premature to discussdetails in this paper.7. At the same time, although the objections noted above to establishing a standing Consultative Council are weighty, it is thought that now that many ofthe Colonial territories have during the last few years developed a Ministerial orquasi-Ministerial form of government there may be value in convening aconference of Chief Ministers (or the equivalent) in the fairly near future. the primary object of such a conference would be to provide an opportunity for givingthese leaders some insight into general policy; but their opinion could also be tested as to the existence of any substantial demand for setting up machinery for regular collective consultation.


</content>
</cab>
