<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/88/0 images: 35-59</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
9.9(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNM]iS &apos;E C RE T. COPY NO.CABINET     14  (57)Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10, downing street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,  7th APRIL, 1937,at 11.0 a.m.AGENDA.1.    FOREIGN AFFAIRS.The Situation in Spain   -   (if required)(Reference Cabinet 13 (37) Conclusions 1-7)2.    DOCKYARD DISCHARGES;    MEETING OF THE JOINT INDUSTRIALCOUNCIL *(Reference Gabinet 12 (37) Conclusion 6)Statement to be made   by the First Lord of theAdmxralty,S.    JAPANESE REJECTION OF 14-INCH GUN MAXIMUM FOR capital ships.(Reference Cabinet 75 (36) Conclusion 9)Statement to be made   by the First Lord of theAdmiralty.4o    AIR RAID PRECAUTIONS:    PROPOSED HOUSEHOLDERS* HANDBOOK.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.CP. 108 (37) - already circulated.5,    METHYLATED SPIRITS  (SCOTLAND) BILL.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Scotland,CP. 107 (37) - already circulated.6.    PROPOSED WIRELESS TELEGRAPHY BILL.(Reference Cabinet 58 (36) Conclusion 9 and Appendix)Memorandum by the Postmaster-General.CP. 103 (37) - already circulated.
TO TAKE HOTS OF;7.    PROVINCIAL MINISTRIES IN INDIA.(Reference Cabinet IS (37) Conclusion 13)Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.CP. 106 (37) - already circulated.8,    MAINTENANCE OF ORDER IN PALESTINE,(Reference Cabinet IS (37) Conclusion 12)Memorandum by the Secretary cf State for the Colonies,CP. 109 (37) - circulated herewith.(Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY.Secretary to the Cabinet.fC Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1. j3rd April, 1937.Q- S -
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.)SECRET. COPY NO.cabinet    14 (37).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.1.,  on WEDNESDAY,the 7th APRIL,  1937,  at 11.0 a.m.PRESENT:The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P. ,Prime Minister.     (in the Chair).The Right Hon. The Right Hon.J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P., Neville Chamberlain, M.P. ,Lord President of the Council. ;      Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon,  CCS.I.,K.C.V.C ,0.B.E. ,K.C ,M.P. ,Secretary of State for HomeAffairs.The Right Hon.Anthony Eden, M. C. , M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K.G. ,CCS.I., G.C.I.E., lord privy Seal.The Right Hon.Malcolm MaoDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon.A. Duff Cooper, D.S.C, M.P. ,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt, , CCS. I.,CB.E. , C.M.C , M.P., FirstLord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.W.S. Morrison, M.C., K. C , M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and^Fisheries.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.The Earl Stanhope, K.G. ,D.S.C,M.C, First Commissioner of work  the FOLLOWING WE?The Right Hen.W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P.,Secretary of State for theColonies.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland,CCS. I. ,CCI.E. ,Secretary &apos;of State for India.The Right Hon.Waiter Runciman,  M.P.,President of the Board ofTrade.The Right Hon.Sir Thomas Inskip, C.B.E,,K.C., M.P., Minister forCo-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon.Oliver Stanley, M.C, M.P.,President of the Board efEducation.- The Right Hon.Ernest Brewn, M. C, M.P.,. Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.L. Hore-Belisha, M.P.,Minister of Transport.ALSO PRESENT;Major The Right Han.  G.C. Tryon, M.P.,Postmaster-General.(For Conclusion 8).Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B., G.C.M.G., GCV.C    ...    Secretary.
TEE KING&apos;SBIRTHDAYDINNER.(previous reference:Cabinet 25(35), Con-clusion 2. )1. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that, with the approval of HisMajesty The King, the usual annual Dinner to the diplomatic Corps would be held at the Foreign office on Wednesday, June 9th.    Invitations would be issuedlater, but in the meantime he asked his colleagues tomake a note of the date.
1 rjd fTHE SITUATIONIN SPAIN.(previous reference:..   Cabinet 13&apos;    (37), Con-clusions 1to 7.)2. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs said that the situation in regard to Spain was somewhateasier, though he could not say how long the imp rove-ment would last.    The control scheme was now approved and should be in operation next week.    After thatthe Government should have better sources of informa-tion as to breaches of non-intervention, throughreports to the Non-intervention Committee.Turning to the position of the belligerents in spain, the Foreign Secretary said that he had seen mr Forbes on his way to Berlin.    Mr Forbes had reported that the Spanish  Government&apos;s position was somewhat Improved and that the situation was nowfairly balanced.    On the whole, Mr Forbes thought thattime was on the side of the Government.    From aninternational point of view the danger of this wasthat Signor Mussolini might send further reinforcements to Spain.    On the other hand, the Italian Ambassadorsin London and Paris had assured the British and french governments respectively that there was no suchintention.    He himself had raised with Signor Grandithe question of the recall of volunteers from Spain.He had pointed out to the Italian Ambassador that nomeetings of the Non-intervention Committee had takenplace for a week in order to allow the strainedsituation to subside.    Instead of summoning a freshmeeting he had approached the Ambassador direct.   the ambassador had expressed appreciation of the foreign secretary&apos;s consideration and had promised to refer the question of the recall of volunteers to Rome.&quot;The First Lord of the Admiralty said that he had seen Admiral Backhouse, the Commander-in-Chief of theHome Fleet, who took rather a different view fromMr Forbes of the Spanish situation.    The Admiralconsidered that the Valencia Government had almost-2-
ceased to exist, as -sdrl- the control was exercised by Committees.    Although General Franco had organiseda fair administration in the part of Spain which hecontrolled, the peasants were, on the whole, infavour of a Government of the Left.    If things wentbadly with General Franco&apos;s forces the peasantsmight, give him trouble.    The Commander-in^Chiefthought that General Franco&apos;s military machine was better than that of the Government, and that the war was likely to be a long-drawn-out affair without a decisive victory on either side.
9tit,SPAIN.Protectionof british shipping.FR. IS(37)3. The First Lord of the Admiralty, continuing the statement summarised on the previous page,recalled that hitherto General Franco had notattempted to interfere with the passage of food toports in Government occupation.    During the last two days, however, food was &quot;being interfered with.    Inthe past we had.protected British ships (other thanthose carrying munitions) on the high seas, &quot;but notinside territorial waters.    On the previous day, atBilbao, a Spanish Cruiser had threatened to stop an english Ship, which had only made port because three british Destroyers had interposed themselves betweenthe Spanish and the British ship.    An incident had only just been averted.    There might easily have arisen a position in which a British ship was captured by a Spanish Cruiser in the presence of three BritishDestroyers.    In consequence the Commander-in-Chiefof the Mediterranean Fleet was much concerned at theposition.    He reported that the blockade of Bilbaowas in fact effective.    The First Lord suggested,therefore, that the situation should be re-considered,more particular!;/ as eight 01 nine British ships carrying food were reported to be on their way toBilbao.    Possibly, for example, the Cabinet might be willing to consider again whether we should not havean Agent with General Franco&apos;s Government.    The risein freights to Spain had attracted ships to the trade.One firm was even considering the purchase of Spanishships, which would then be put back under Spanishcontrol but run under the British i lag.-  The President of the Board of Trade said that hehad not been warned that this question was going to arise.    He hoped it would not be assumed that british shipping generally v-as running after Spanish business.
The ships being drawn to Spanish ports were virtuallyblockade-runners who took the risk for the highfreights.    He had information to show that somemisuse of the British flag was being made in theMediterranean as well as in the Atlantic.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that itappeared to be agreed that on the high seas general franco was not entitled to stop ships, as he did not possess belligerent rights.    If. we intervened insideterritorial waters, General Franco would say thatwe were assisting a besieged town.    Would it not bepossible for us to announce that we would defendBritish ships on the high seas, but not in territorial waters?The President of the Board of Trade said thatthat was the sort of warning that ought to be givento such adventurers.In the course of the discussion which followed,doubts were expressed as to the legal position.There was no doubt that, as General Franco&apos;s Govern-ment had not been recognised, his ships were not entitled to exercise belligerent rights on the high seas.    There appeared to be some obscurity, however,as to what rights, if any, his ships possessedinside territorial waters.    For example, was heentitled to exercise a blockade;   to sink a foreignship carrying foodstuffs;    to capture a foreign shipcarrying foodstuffs;   to take a ship to another port and requisition the cargo;    and if, on the voyage toanother port, he had to pass outside territorial waters, were our ships entitled to extricate a Britisrship?
The Cabinet agreed : (a) That the question should be considered in its legal, political and practicalaspects by a Committee composed as follows the Lord Chancellor (in the Chair),The Home Secretary,The Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs,The President of the Board of Trade,The First Lord of the Admiralty,The Minister for Co-ordination ofDefence,&apos;The Attorney-General:(b) That the above Cabinet Committee should decide the question if possible, but,if they considered necessary, should ask the Prime Minister to assemble a special meeting of the Cabinet:(c) That the Committee should meet in theForeign Secretary&apos;s Room at the Houseof Commons the same afternoon at 4 p.m. :(d) That the Meeting of the United kingdom delegation to the Imperial Conference,arranged for 4.30 p.m. in the PrimeMinister&apos;s Room at the House of Commons,should not be cancelled, but that thesituation should be met either by an adjournment of the Committee on SpanishTerritorial Waters or by a postponement of the Imperial Conference Committee,whichever might prove the more convenient.
.1 9TJNDESIEiiBLEEMPLOYEES INGOVERNMENTESTABLISHMENTS.Meeting with theJoint IndustrialCouncil.$previous reference;Cabinet 12 (37)Conclusion 6.)4.    The First Lord of the Admiralty reportedto the Cabinet that, in accordance with his intentionannounced at the meeting of the Gabinet referred toin the margin, he had seen the Joint IndustrialCouncil on the subject of Dockyard Discharges,He had made clear that the Government, irrespective of what party was in office, must keep in reserve powers for discharging employees in case of necessity without giving reasons.     But grantedthose powers, in many cases,  the Government would beable to take into confidence the representative ofthe Trade Union concerned.     The Joint IndustrialCouncil had appeared content with his statement andthey had parted on good terms.     Moreover, thesituation had been eemewh&amp;t eased in the Dockyards.
5.     The First Lord of the Admiralty reportedthat the Japanese Government had now definitelyrepudiated the 14-inch gun limitation for capital ships.      Consequently, under the London Naval Treaty,the 16-inch gun would he come the normal armament.The Admiralty were not yet sure whether the Japaneseintended at once to arm their new ships with 16-inch guns-.     They thought it possible that the Japaneseattitude was a mere affirmation of prestige.     He didnot yet know the attitude of the United States ofAmerica hut the Naval Staff thought   it probable thatthe 16-inch gun would be adopted, as American Navalopinion was predominantly in favour of it.     TheSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs had agreed tomake some enquiries with the American and JapaneseGovernments with a view to ascertaining their intentions.     If the United States were to decide infavour of the 16-inch gun, it would be no use arguingwith them as they were entitled to take that decision.The Naval Staff, however, advised that ,for a35,000 ton ship, the 14-inch gun was a better weapon/and that as at the present time the European situation was our first consideration, the most immediate need was to create a unit of 5 Capital Ships armed with14-inch guns.     In reply to a reminder that not very long ago      35,000    tons had been fixed as theminimum size for a Capital Ship which was to include16-inch guns, the First Lord explained that thesituation had changed in recent years.     The latestdesigns of Capital Ships provided, for very heavyarmour to resist bombs dropped from aircraft and, ifarmament of 16-inch guns were adopted, it would be at
the expense of that essential armour.      If the germans were to mount 16-inch guns in their new Capital Ships,it would be at the expense of armour and speed.      TheNaval Staff did not consider that Capital Ships witha primary armament of 14-inch guns would be at any greatdisadvantage in meeting ships armed with 16-inch guns.The difference in range was only about 1,000 yards.He added that the Admiralty were also concerned aboutthe cruiser holiday.      It would be most embarrassingif the Japanese insisted on building 10,000 toncruisers.      The Foreign Secretary had also undertaken to question the Japanese Government as to their intentionson this point.So far as the Treaty was concerned, the FirstLord of the Admiralty said that he would still, as things were at present, advise ratification, providedthat Germany and Russia had first concltided bilateraltreaties with us.      The United States of America hadalready ratified the Treaty and France had declared that she would ratify at the same time we did.If we were to ratify we should have to rely on the&quot;Escape Clause&apos;&apos; in case our position was menaced.Summing up, the First Lord said the position .was that enquiries were being made as to the intentions of the United States of America and Japan:    that thepresent intention of the Admiralty was to adhere totheir- present proposals in this year&apos;s programme for ships armed with 14-inch guns and thirdly that theywere prepared to ratify the Treaty provided theEuropean Powers came in.
AIR RAID 6.    The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum byPRECAUTIONS.-- the Home Secretary (C.P--108 (37)) circulating forProposedHouseholders&apos;    their approval copies of the Handbook which the AirHandbook.Raid Precautions Department had prepared for issue to(Previous the general public, setting out the information theyReference:Cabinet 13       should possess to enable them to provide such protec-(37), Con-clusion 11.)   tion in their homes as might be possible.    At therequest of the Treasury the Home Secretary put before his colleagues the question of the inclusion of advertisements on the cover of the Handbook, as towhich he recommended that in the first place efforts should be made to use the available space for adver-tisements by certain Government Departments, e. g., thePost Office or the Milk Marketing Board; but that ifthe whole space could not be disposed of at a fairrate in this way, offers should be accepted from commercial firms or other bodies of first-classreputation.    He also asked for discretion as to theactual time of issue.In the course of a discussion certaincriticisms and suggestions of the proposed Householders&apos;Handbook were made, including the following:-(l)    That many people would say that they couldnot meet the expenditure contemplated for theRefuge Room (page 9 of handbook) and that theycuight not to be endangered owing to theirpoverty.(3)   That the last words of the Preface on page 1of the book, viz.    &quot;There is a duty on everycitizen to bear his part in these civilprecautions, but those who for any reasoncannot take them for themselves need not beworried.     They will, not be overlooked.&quot;,might be interpreted as a guarantee.(3)    That the proposal that children, invalids,elderly members of the household and petsshould be sent to relatives or friends inthe country (page 12 of the handbook) wasadvice of. doubtful wisdom.
That as in the event of emergency many ofthe original issue of handbooks would havebeen mislaid, it would be advisable tomaintain an ample stock, since a reprintwould take a long time.That resort might be had to broadcasting and cinema films in an emergency.The Gabinet agreed:(a) To approve in principle the ,Householders&apos; Handbook attachedto CP. 108 (37) for issue by theHome Secretary at such time as he might deem expedient:(b) That before issue,  the HomeSecretarjr should consider the criticisms and suggestions made atthe meeting of the Cabinet and anyothers that might be communicatedto him by his colleagues andshould, if he deemed necessary,report again to the Cabinet:(c) That there was no objection to theinclusion of advertisements onthe cover of the Handbook on thelines proposed by the Home Secretary,provided that offers should beaccepted only from GovernmentDepartments or Commercial firms or other bodies of first classreputation^
TITS METHYLATED 7a The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by-SPIRITS(SCOTLAND)        the Secretary of State for Scotland (CP.-107 (37))BILL.relating; to the Methylated Spirits (Scotland) Bill,(Previous to be considered by the Scottish Standing CommitteeReference:Cabinet 11       of the House of Commons on April 13th.    For(34), Con-clusion 16.)   reasons advanced in his Memorandum the Secretary ofState proposed that during the Committee proceedings and the further stages of the Bill the government spokesman should maintain a non-committal but notunfriendly attitude;    and that he should be authorisedwithout in any way committing the Government tosupport of the Bill, to co-operate with the promotersin framing any amendments necessary to ensure thatif it reaches the Statute Book it does so in a workableform.The Cabinet were informed that the passageof the Bill would involve the customer signing anundertaking for every purchase.The Cabinet approved the proposals of theSecretary of State for Scotland as set forth in CP. 107 (37) and summarised above.- IS -
WIRELESS TELEGRAPHY.

Proposed Bill.

8. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the Postmaster-General (C.P.-103 (37)) seeking the approval for the introduction of a new Wireless Telegraphy Bill which could make provision -,

(Previous Reference Cabinet 58 (36), Conclusion 9 &amp; Appendix.)

(i) To consolidate the present Acts, viz., the Wireless Telegraphy Act, 1904, the Wireless Telegraphy (Explanation) Act, 1925, and the Wireless Telegraphy (Blind Persons Facilities) Act, 1926:

(ii) To bring their provisions up to date -- in particular by extending their scope to cover television -- and to make them permanent; and

(iii) To empower the Electricity Commissioners to make regulations to suppress interference with radio reception and to empower the Postmaster-General to enforce these regulations.

In the course of a statement on his proposals, the Postmaster-General said that the Bill would take some time to prepare and could not, he thought, be introduced during the present Session. In connection with electrical interference, decisions would have to be taken as to who was to pay for alterations required (e.g. to an electrical lift) to eliminate interference. In this connection, reference was made to the cost of the remedial measures which would be necessary to eliminate interference due ? causes as the electrification of railway signally systems.

The Cabinet agreed:

(a) To approve in principle the preparation of a new Wireless Telegraphy Bill on the lines proposed by the Postmaster-General in C.P. 103 (37) and very briefly summarised above:

(b) That the question of detail involved would require consideration when the Bill came before the Cabinet:
That all Government Departmentsconcerned should he consulted inconnection with the preparationof the Bill (e.g. if it was toinclude powers for controllingwireless telegraphy in emergency&apos;The Home Office, The Admiralty,The Board of Trade and any etherDepartments concerned)?That, in reply to a question whichhad &quot;been addressed to him on thesubject, the Postmaster-general should be authorised to statethat the preparation of the bill was under consideration, but thathe could not hold out hope of its introduction this Session.
soMINISTERS&apos;SALARIES.PAYMENT OPM.P&apos;s.(previous references:Cabinet 12(37), Con-clusion 10:Cabinet 25(24), Con-clusion 3r&amp;, )9. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that theParliamentary Secretary to the Treasury had been approached by Mr Lees Smith on the subject of the ministerial Salaries Eill.    The parliamentary opposition had been consulted at an early stage, andthe Government had gathered that they viewed the Billwith favour.    Apparently, however, the soundings -hadnot been pursued very far, and when the question came before the Opposition Labour Party&apos;s Executive on theprevious evening they had been very divided.    some members, apparently, had taken the line that the ministerial Salaries Bill was very favourable tothose who had prospects of reaching office, but didnothing for the ordinary Member of Parliament.Mr Lees Smith had given him some particulars, whichthe Chancellor communicated to the Cabinet, of thestraits to which some M.P&apos;s had been reduced owingto the inadequacy of the salary.    The OppositionLabour Executive had felt that these were ratherdifficult matters to put from the Opposition Benchand had asked Mr Lees Smith, who was in bettercircumstances than some of his colleagues, to put the matter to the Government.    Apparently the labour opposition would like to address a Question to thePrime Minister during the present week, as to whetherthe Government were prepared to consider the remuneration of Members pi Parliament, and if they received an answer to the effect that the matter would be considered it might facilitate the passageof-the Ministerial Salaries Bill.    The Chancellorof the Exchequer had then pointed out that a question had already been put down on the subject      bySir Assheton Pownall, who had suggested the raising of the salaries of M.P&apos;s to  515 per annum.
Mr Lees Smith had suggested that  600 would he a more suitable figure.The Chancellor of the Exchequer then read the draftof a reply to a Parliamentary Question, which he had prepared and which was to the effect that he could see no clear analogy between the question of salaries&apos; ofMinisters and the payment of Members of the House ofCommons:    that he would not like to commit himself to a statement in favour ef increased salaries withoutfurther inquiry.    If a Supplementary Question was thenput as to whether there should be a further inquiryhe proposed to answer in the affirmative.The Prime Minister said that the Leader of theOpposition Labour Party had raised the same point withhim a month ago.    He had replied that the salary ofM.P&apos;s was a matter for the House of Commons ratherthan for the Government, but that if a case were madethe Government would not refuse to examine it, and thatthe first step appeared to be some inquiry as to thefacts.Some discussion took place as to what would be thenature of any inquiry.    There was general agreement that inquiry by a Parliamentary Committee was inappropriate-priate and that it would be better that any inquiry-should take the form of consultation by the Governmentwith the Leaders of Parties.A suggestion was made that in his draft reply theChancellor of the Exchequer should use the plural form&quot;inquiries&quot;, instead of &quot;inquiry&quot;.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had deliberately avoided suggesting &quot;an inquiry&quot; and had spoken simply of &quot;inquiry&quot;.    He undertook to considerthe proposal to use the plural form.
The Home Secretary suggested that the Chancellorof the Exchequer&apos;s reply should state that he wouldnot like to commit himself to a statement now, butthat the Government proposed to make certain inquiriesinto the matter.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defencesuggested &quot;without further consideration, in whichI hope we may have the co-operation of Membersopposite&quot;.One suggestion was that the public ought to beprepared for the possibility of a raising of Members&apos;salaries:    otherwise hostile critics would allegethat Ministers wanted to increase their salaries andwere going to obtain Parliamentary sanction by raising the payment of Members.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had sufficient indications of the view of the Cabinet tobe able to deal with the matter.
INDIA. 10. The Cabinet took note of a Memorandum by theProvincial Secretary of State for India (CP.-106 (37)) reportingMinistriesin. to his colleagues the nature of the negotiations insix Indian Provinces where, as the result of the recent(previous reference: Provincial Elections, the Congress Party had aCabinet 12(37), Con- majority, which had led to the refusal of office byelusion 13.)the person approached by the Governor in each of theProvinces as the leading Congress representative.The Secretary of State for India made a statement in amplification of his Memorandum.    He recalled that,as the result of the Provincial Elections in Indiaunder the Act of 1935, Congress was found to have an absolute majority in 5 out of the 11 Provinces.Speculation had then arisen as to the attitude towardsacceptance of office of the Congress Party.    A CongressCommittee had met and had passed a resolution whichat first had been interpreted to mean that Congresswas prepared to accept office.    It was only when the governors of the Provinces sent for the congress leaders and invited them to form Ministries that it had become clear that, under the directions of Congress,the Governors were being asked for assurances whichthey could not possibly give.    The whole situation,therefore, had been changed.    Many Congress men had themselves been bewildered.   Mr Gandhi had then issued&apos; a statement in which he claimed the authorship of theCongress formula and said he could not understand whythe Governors could not fall in with it, as they were only asked to do something quite small, which he allegedthe late Secretary of State had agreed to and which waswell within the competence of the Governors.    Thatattitude confused the situation still more.    TheSecretary of State for India therefore proposed, inreply to a Question by Lord Lothian, to make a state-in the House of Lordsment/in order to clarify the situation.    He proposed-18-
to make it clear -(i) That it was not open to Governorswithin the framework of the Consti-tution to give the assurances askedfor, namely, that the Governors shouldnot use their special powers in ful-fulfilment of their responsibilities:(ii) To stress the fact that even if ithad been possible the Governors wouldnot have been able&apos; to give the pledgefor the reason that it&quot;would have beena gross breach of faith to minoritiesand others who looked to the Governorsto safeguard their lights:(iii) That, while he would welcome any gestureby the Congress Party which would &quot;leadto the possibility of their acceptingoffice, the Government could not giveCongress a privileged position in a feature of the Constitution which applied to all Parties.He hoped such a statement would clear the air and give some time in which it would be seen if Congresswas prepared to modify its attitude.    In six Provinceswhere Congress had a majority, leaders of minorityparties had formed Ministries, and in the remainingProvinces Ministries had been formed in the ordinary way either from the Majority Party or from a coalitionof Parties which would   be able to command support inthe Legislature.    The Secretary of State had suggestedthat in the Provinces where a Minority Government wasin office the Governors should take advantage of their powers not to summon the Legislature for six months;otherwise the Minority Ministries would be thrown out.He paid a tribute to those persons who had been willingto form Minority Governments.In the course of a short discussion it was strongly urged that a statement of a similar character shouldbe made in the House of Commons on&apos; the same day as inthe House of Lords.
The Lord Privy Seal made some suggestions inregard to the statement, viz:-(l) That the Secretary of State for India,in referring to the Congress resolution,should quote its actual terms (which theSecretary of State explained was his intention):(2) That he should emphasise the point in -paragraph 5 of CP.-106 (37) that itwould be quite impossible for anyGovernor to give any undertaking whichwould amount&quot;to a promise not to exercise the special powers vested in him by theAct, etc.:and(3) That any suggestion that the Viceroyought to send for Mr Gandhi would haveto be rejected, but that if Mr Gandhiasked to see the Viceroy he should notrefuse.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve the general lines of thestatement to be made by the Secretaryof State for India in the House ofLords on Thursday, April 8th:(b) That a corresponding statement shouldbe made in the House oi Commons on thesame day.
The Lord Privy Seal made some suggestions inregard to the statement, viz:-(l) That the Secretary of State for India,in referring to the Congress resolution,should quote its actual terms (which theSecretary of State explained was his intention):(2) That he should emphasise the point inparagraph 5 of CP.-106 (37) that itwould be quite impossible for anyGovernor to give any undertaking whichwould amount to a promise not to exercisthe special powers vested in him by theAct, etc.:and(3) That any suggestion that the Viceroyought to send for Mr Gandhi would haveto be rejected, but that if Mr Gandhiasked to see the Viceroy he should notrefuse.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve the general lines of thestatement to be made by the Secretaryof State for India in the House ofLords on Thursday, April 8th:(b) That a corresponding statement shouldbe made in the House oi Commons on thesame day.
PALESTINE.Maintenanceof Order in.(previous reference:Cabinet 12(57), Con-clusion 12. )11. The Cabinet took note of a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for the Colonies (C.P.-109 (37))circulating the text of a Secret Despatch he hadreceived from the High Commissioner regarding thepresent situation in Palestine and the measuresbeing taken for the maintenance of order, togetherwith a paraphrase of his own telegraphic reply.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,April 7,  1937.

</content>
</cab>
