<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/88/0 images: 328-351</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT. )S E C. R E T. COPY NO.CABINET    27 (37).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street,  S.W.I. ,  on &quot;WEDNESDAY,the 30th JUNE, 19g7,  at 11.0 a. in.PRESENT:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (in the Chair).The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.C.3.I.,G.C.V.O.,O.B.E.,K.C.,M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K. G.,G.C.S.I., G.O.I.E., lord president of the Council.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.C.S.IG.B.E.,C.M.G.,M.P., Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Anthony Eden,  M.C.,  M.P. ,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.Malcolm MacDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Right Hon.V/.  Ormsby Gore, M.P.,Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.A. Duff Cooper, D.S.O., M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.The Viscount Swinton, G.B.E.,M.C.,Secretary of State forAir.The Right Hon.Oliver Stanley, M.C. , M.P.,President of the Board ofTrade.The Right Hon.The Earl Stanhope, K.G.,D.S.O.,M.C , President of the Board*f Education,The Right Hon.Ernest Brown, M.C., M. P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.The Earl De La Warr,Lord Privy Seal.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland,G.C.S.I.,G.C.I.E., Secretaryof State for India.The Right Hon.Sir Thomas Inskip, G.B.E.,K.C., M.P., Minister for-Co-Ordination of Defence.The Right Hon.L. Hore-Belisha, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Eon.Walter Elliot, M.C., M.P.Secretary of State forScotland.... \L-The Right Hon. V.W.S. Morrison, M.O.,K.C.,M.P.Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.P.*Minister of Health.The Right Hon.E.L. Burgin, M.P.,Minister of Transport.Colonel Sir M.P*A. Hanlcey, G.C.B., G.C.M.G., G.C.V.O.,    ...    Secretary
0 9(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.)SECRET. .   COPY NO.__C. A B I N E T    27  (37).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No.  10,Downing Street,  S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,30th JUNE,  1937,  at 11.0 a.m.AGENDA.1.  FOREIGN AFFAIRS.Situation in Spain.(Reference Cabinet 26 (37),  Conclusion 2).2.   DEFENCE EXPENDITURE.(Reference Cabinet 7 (37),  Conclusion 13).Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.CP.  165 (37)    -    already circulated.3.  PALESTINE:    REPORT OF THE ROYAL COMMISSION, 1936.(Reference Cabinet 23 (37),  Conclusion 5).Memoranda by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.CP.  163 (37)    -    already circulated.CP.  156 (,37)    -   circulated herewith.CP. 169 (37) - circulated herewith.4-  THE IMPERIAL CONFERENCE.(Reference Cabinet 24 (37),  Conclusion 5).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.CP.  161 (37)    -    already circulated.5.  RATIFICATION OF THE LONDON NAVAL TREATY,  1936.(Reference Cabinet 26 (37) Conclusion 1).Joint Memorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs, and the First Lord of the Admiralty.CP.  162 (37)    -   already circulated.
6. AIR RAID PRECAUTIONS IN SCHOOLS-(Reference Cabinet 16 (57), Conclusion A).Joint Memorandum by the President of the Board ofEducation and the Secretary of State for Scotland.C.P.  167 (37)    -   already circulated.7.  LONG TERM MILK POLICY.(Reference Cabinet 26 (37), Conclusion 3).Question to be raised by the Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries.8.   CONCLUSIONS OP HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.10th Conclusions (37) of the Committee ofHome Affairs - to be circulated.Milk (Amendment) Bill.(Reference Cabinet 26 (37) Conclusion 3).Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture andFisheries,  covering draft Bill.H.A-. 28 (37)    -    already circulated.(Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.,26th June,  1937.-P.-
t* 21)SPAIN.(previous reference:Cabinet 26(37), Con-clusion 2 .)Bell igerentRights.F.r1z.1. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs saidthat he had had. a difficult time over the Spanishquestion since the last Meeting of the Cabinet.At the Meeting of the Non-intervention Committee onthe previous day the representatives of the Germanand Italian Governments had. not made a definitepronouncement, but from other sources it was  clearthat those Governments were not likely to agree tothe Anglo-French proposals for filling the. gap in theNaval patrol.    Consequently on the previous evening he had sent to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassadors at berlin and. Rome the telegram reproduced in the Appendix,which he read to the Cabinet.The suggestion in the last part of the telegram,that &quot;no recent developments of the conflict havetaken place which could be held to justify&quot; the grantof belligerent, rights, led to  considerable discussion on this subject.&quot;&quot;he grant of belligerent rights commended itselfto some members of the Cabinet, as the best method ofdealing with the situation in the near future, evenif it could not be adopted at the present moment.mhe Prime Minister said, that the Foreign secretary had  consulted him about the telegram and. he had suggested some modifications, although he had not seen it in its final form.   As he saw the positionwe ought to make every effort to get the Germans towork with us .    ,-nhe Italians were perhaps less important.   He was anxious, however, not to get. intoopposition   to    Germany.   He had therefore urged theForeign Secretary to try and get the Germans to agree in our impartiality an^ even to reconsider theirattitude.    He had thought that if belligerent rightshad been indicate^, in the telegram as a possible alternative the Germans would be sure to press for
that solution.   From our point of view, however, thecontinuance of the Naval patrol vas probably better.He pointed out that the refusal to agree to grant-belligerent rights was qualified by the words  &quot;at thisstage and in these conditions;    no recent deA^elopmentsof the conflict have taken place which coulJ be held to justify t-i&quot;&apos;. If belligerent rights were accorded to both sides General Franco would, have the advantage,since his naval forces were superior, and he would beable to obtain munitions with certainty.    That was probably why the Germans and Italians supported theproposal.    If His Majesty&apos;s Government wrere to grantbelligerent rights at this  juncture, however, it wouldbe said, by their opponents that this revealed theGovernment&apos;s policy in its true light, which,       theyhad always  claimed, was support  for Franco.    It wasonly if there were no other alternative that the grantof belligerent rights  could be defended,   The militarysituation in Spa.in was, o^ course,  constantly fluetuat-ing, and even by Friday next might, necessitate a re-consideration of policy.,The Chancellor of the Exchequer recalled that theobject of the Government.&apos; s policy had always been to limit, the war to Spain. He raised the question as towhether &quot;&apos;&quot;he grant of belligerent, rights would or wouldnot increase the risk op the conflagration spreading.The Lord Chancellor asked whether the Foreign Secre-tary contemplated that, if the gap in the Naval patrolwas not filled, not only the patrol scheme itself but.also the whole non-intervention scheme would break down.In the latter contingency the French frontier would, be opened up for the supply of munitions, and this mightnot be at all acceptable to the German and italian governments .
The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pointedout. that the Spanish struggle was not an ordinarycivil war.   What made it so dangerous was the extent offoreign participation.    mhe grant of belligerent rights would help General Franco, and the possibility couldnot be excluded that his friends might transfer naval forces to his  control.   One inconvenience in the grantof belligerent rights would be that we should have toagree with General Franco a contraband list, which might become as wide as in the late War and include food-stuffs.   He had been considering whether, as an alter-native course, we might not say, when the Non-Interven-tion Committee met on Friday, that we were sorry thatthe German and Italian Governments did not agree withour proposal, but that, rather than see non-interventionbreak down, we would carry it on provided that thosecountries would  co-operate to the extent of allowingtheir merchant ships to comply with the provisions ofthe patrol scheme.    If they refused we might say thatin the circumstances we did. not see how the non-intervention scheme could continue:    that the landfrontiers woul^ be thrown open&apos;    and that we should, haveto re-consider our attitude on the whole question.In that event the courses open to us would be either togrant belligerent rights or, without granting belli-gerent rights, to license exports of war material to spain.    In stating this we might give a hint that ifforeign volunteers were withdrawn from Spain our attitudetowards the question of belligerent rights might be different.   The Foreign Office had learned from varioussources that General Franco was not very keen on theretention of volunteers but was anxious to obtainbelligerent rights.   The Secretary of State thoughts    -3-
that some result might be obtained by adopting thatline, accompanied by an offer to  continue co-operation in non-intervention if we could get agreement.The proposed mention   of a possibility of ourlicensing the export of arms to Spain was  criticised onthe ground, that we had no arms to spare and that theGerman Government knew that this was the case:    also for the reason that it would raise difficulties of anew kind.The Lord President of the Council expressed ahope that in dealing with the tactical situation weshould not lose sight of the main desideratum of notallowing our relations with Germany and Italy to deteriorate. He suggested that the right course was toplay for time, keeping in view the grant of belligerentrights as a possibility.mhe Prime Minister said, that that was very muchin his mind.The Home Secretary suggested that, as the resultof the Cabinet discussion, it might be desirable to give his Majesty*ammbassadors in . Rome and. Berlin rather more background as to the Cabinet&apos;s view.   He thoughtthat the telegram in the Appendix indicated, a morerigid attitude than was the case.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said.that he understood the general impression of the cabinet was that if the Naval Patrol Scheme should break down,the non-intervention scheme might become impossible.The Prime Minister said he did not. want to be forced into a policy of recognition of belligerent-rightsunless a^ position was reached in which it could be defended, onthe ground that there was no alternative. He pointedout that, as so often happened, in connection with theSpanish situation, difficulties were liable to arise at-4-
Pthe end, of the present week, owing to the fact that theNon-intervention Committee was meeting on Friday next.He thought, however, that he and. the Foreign secretary had now a sufficient indication of the mind of the Cabinetto deal with any question that might arise.
2. The Cabinet, had before there a Memorandum bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer ( CP.-165 (37))containing a brief exposition of the relation of theDefence Programmes to Exchequer resources availableout of taxation or loans.    In the circumstancesoutlined, in his Memorandum the Chancellor thoughtthat the time had come both for a general review ofthe position and. for the introduction of a. procedureadditional to the normal arrangements for Cabinet-approval, and the ordinary processes of Treasurycontrol, of expenditure on defence.   He accordingly recommended.:-(a) that the Defence Departments should beasked,  in consultation with the Ministerfor Co-ordination of Defence,(l)  to estimate anew the period of time required for the completion of their programmes,(2) on the basis of the programme as nowsanctioned and. of the rising trend ofprices to submit estimates of their total requirements of voted money yearby year during that period., and.(3) on the like ba.sis to submit estimates of their normal total annual expenditurein the years following the completionof the programme;(b) that these general estimates should thenbe examined, by the Treasury;;( c)  that, after such examination the estimates,together with the observations of theTreasury, should be submitted to the defence policy and. Requirements Committee of theCabinet (with possibly extended terms ofreference), which would, in the light ofall the circumstances ,  determine prioritiesbetween conflicting claims and recommend tothe Cabinet maxima for the expenditure byea ch Department year by year during theperiod of the programme, such maxima notto be exceeded except by further authority;(d.) that, in the meanwhile decisions on new projects of major importance should be postponed.as (including man-power,, productive capacity,and the maintenance of the balance of our general trade .)DEFENCE EXPEN-DITTJRE.(previous reference:Cabinet 7(37), Con-clusion 13 .)
In the course of a statement in amplification ofhis Memorandum the Chancellor of the Exchequer suggestedthat the cost of Air Raid Precautions would have to be taken  into account at the same time as the expenditureof the Defence Departments.   After the necessary datahad been prepared, a Committee of the Cabinet would haveto examine the Papers and work out how the rationing ofthe Defence Services was to be accomplished.    If somecheck of this nature had not been introduced we might,find in time of crisis that we had incapacitated cur-selves from the ability to make the necessary effort.Some discussion took place as to the extent to whichthe Defence Policy and Requirements Committee was theright body for undertaking the reviews proposed by theChancellor of the Exchequer.    While that Sub-Committeewas deemed appropriate for such matters as the co-ordination of the Departmental estimates of the periodof time required, for the completion of their programmes,a.nd the total requirements for those programmes of voted,money year by year, and.       the normal total annual expend-iture in the years following the completion of the pro-grammes, it. was suggested that, when it came to a matterof priorities involving large questions of policy theDefence (Plans) Policy Committee was a. more appropriate body .The Prime Minister said that when the matter hadbeen before him a? Chancellor of the Exchequer, what hehad. in mind was that, it would be necessary to arrivefirst, at a global total of the expenditure contemplated,by all the Defence Services,  including Air Raid Precautions.The next stage would be to obtain from the Treasury some idea as to the amount that  could, be spent,    mhe comparison between the two fipures, he had. thought, might then be made
by the Defence Policy and Requirements Committee.-Probably a. discrepancy would be shown between the twofigures, and then a. second, process would arise as to howbetween the various Departments,the available money was to be sub-divided/   and he had thought that the Defence Policy and. Requirements Comrait-tee might undertake that.    Then each Government Departmeitconcerned would have to say for itself which itemswithin its own estimates should be reduced.The Secretary of State for Air pointed out that astrategical review would probably be necessary in order,to determine what items of Defence expenditure could/beArelinquished, and for this purpose the Defence (Plans)Policy Committee appeared to be the right body.Strategical decisions would be necessary even to enablethe Departments to decide on their own reductions.The Minister for Go-ordination of Defence, whileappreciating the difficulties of the Chancellor of theExchequer, wanted to be sure that the procedure nowproposed would not result in reopening questions that were already decided.   The existing system at any rateresulted in getting things done-   ^hat was his first-fear.   His second fear was that all new decisions wouldbe held up until the global sum had been arrived, at and decided.   Perhaps it. was not realised, how much prepara-tion was required   e,g., by the firms concerned  before orders could be carried out.,    In these circum-stances every month4 s delay wa.s serious.The Secretary of State for War, while not contestingthe necessity of financial  control, pointed, out the needfor the Defence Departments to reach their Objectivewith speed and efficiency.    For this it. was necessaryfor the Departments  concerned to know&apos; where they stood .The constant production of new-estimates was apt to holdup the business of the Departments.   He would like to be
reassured that the War Office programme held the &quot;field.This was especially important in the case of his Depart-ment, which had come last, into the scheme of defence programmes.   He asked, therefore, that there might he nogoing back on decisions that had already been taken.The Chancellor of the Exchequer, replying to theMinister for Co-ordination of Defence and. the Secretaryof State for War, said that the procedure he proposed was not intended to slovir down the process of re-armamentin ma.matters whe^e decisions had already been taken.   his intention was not to affect the carrying out of definitedecisions.   He thought that there was a difference between those items of the programmes that had. been approved inprinciple by. the Cabinet and. in detail by the Treasury,and other items which had. been approved in principle bythe Cabinet (or CT.D. or DCP,R,) but had been reservedfor approval in detail by the Treasury inter--services committee.   Perhaps it rais?ht be necessary for theService Departments, in making their estimates, to distinguish between the two ea.s es .   He expressed, willing-ness to consider suggestions as to which Committee or.Sub-Committee should he used, at the different stages ofthis inquiry, to which he attached great importance fromthe point of view of our financial position.The Home Secretary hoped that, account, would, be taken of certain matters in which our preparations had laggedsomewhat&apos;    for example, Air Raid. Precautions.    It was very important to reach an agreement as to the division ofresponsibility (including financial responsibility)between the Government and *he Local Authorities.    If thiswas not done at an ea.rly date the co-operation even ofthe most friendly Local Authorities might be lost.   he also pointed out that, if the figures of Defence expenditure
had increased rapidly, this had heen by deliberatedecision of the Cabinet on a review of the whole inter-national situation.The First Lord of the Admiralty recalled that theAdmiralty had recently put forward, proposals  for a new standard of Naval Strength.    These had been referred tothe Defence (Plans) Policy Committee, but no decisionhad yet been reached.    In the circumstances he proposedto make two estimates:    one based on the approved pro-gramme and the other on the proposed new standard..The Secretary of State for Air said that he would work out his estimates on a corresponding basis.Some discussion took place as to whether estimates should, be made for the cost of food storage, but theCabinet were reminded that the question had first beenheld, up while a Bill was drafted, and that the eventualdecision was affected by the Government&apos; s proposals for improving the fertility of the soil.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve generally the proposals ofthe Chancellor of the Exchequer as setforth in C.P.-165 (.&quot;57) and. summarised above, subject to the following:-( i) Re-consideration by the Chancellorof the Exchequer,  in consultationwith the Prime Minister and. theMinister for Co-ordination of Defence,of the Committees by which the succes-sive stages of the examination shouldbe considered:(ii) &quot;&quot;he preparation by the Home Office of estimates for Air Raid. Precautions onthe same lines as those asked for fromthe Service Departments:(b) That the decision recorded above in (a) wasnot intended to reverse decisions governingDefence expenditure already taken by theCabinet, or to prevent the Service Depart-ments from carrying out those decisions.
PALESTINE.Report ofthe RoyalCommission,193 6.(previous reference:Cabinet 23(37) , Con-elusion 5 .)F.r. 2*^37)&apos;3. The Cabinet had before them the following memoranda by the Secretary of State for the ColoniesC.P.-163 (37)  circulating an advancecopy of the Report of the PalestineRoyal Commission, together with aSummary which had been prepared for eventual issue to the Press&apos;CP.-166 (37)  dealing with proposedprocedure and policy, at the end ofwhich he submitted, as a tentativebasis for the discussion of the ques-tions raised in his Memorandum, thedraft of a Statement of Policy, prepared with a view to publication simultaneously with the Report itself, on the 7th July,in the form of a Command Paper,   He also asked authority to send copies of theReport and Summary in strict confidence to Mr Churchill, Mr Lloyd George, Mr Amery,Mr Attlee, Mr Greenwood, Sir archibald sinclair, Lord Samuel and Lord Snell:CP.-169 (37)   circulating for the inform-ation of his  colleagues, in connectionwith the draft Statement of Policy referredto above, an extra.ct from a letter fromthe High Commissioner to the AssistantTJnd.er-Secreta.ry of State in the ColonialOffice enclosing one to the High Commis-sioner from the General Officer commanding in Palestine, in which the latter expressedthe opinion that peace in the near future in Palestine could best be promoted by aperiod of recuperation precedent to theestablishment of His Majesty&apos;s declaredpoli cy oThe Secretary of State for the Colonies paid .a warm tribute to the work of the Royal commission which had produced a document of first class historicalimportance, and then proceeded to comment on the report and on his own memorandum cp 166 (37).Referring to paragraph 17 (3) cn page 5 ofhis memorandum, he suggested the omission of the last sentence, namely -&quot;They do not think it necessary to comment onthe details of the scheme except to state their conclusion that the period for whichHaifa and Acre and their environs should remain under mandatory administration shouldbe not less than ten years, and that at theend of that period the question of theirincorporation in the proposed Jewish state should be open to consideration in the lightOf the circumstances of the time,&quot;
The above passage had been put in to meet a suggestion madeby General Dill who had not at the time seen the Reportof the Royal Commission,,     He thought it would do harm toinclude this passage at the present time, because itselected one detail for comment out of many which wouldrequire to be taken  up  later, and the passage in questiondid not conform exactly to the Royal Commission&apos;s Report.To publish this one detail in the manner he had proposed would, he was on reconsideration convinced, causedifficulty.In the course of the discussion on thestatement of policy in paragraph 17 of CPs 166 (37),various suggestions were made including the following:-(i)    That paragraph (3) rather tended to signifyacceptance of the boundary of the Jewish andArab States respectively proposed by the RoyalCommission and that a less committal languagewould be preferable:(ii)    That the intention to support the principle of partition on which the draft statement was based, was somewhat weakened by such phrasesas the following:-Paragraph (4):&quot;in the hope that an effectivemeasure of consent will be forthcoming on the part ofthe communities concerned.&quot;Paragraph (5): &quot;Until this hope is realised&quot;Paragraph (6): &quot;while the possibility of partition is being explored&quot;Paragraph (7):  &quot;in the event of the schemeof partition not provingpracticable.&quot;(iii)    That care should be exercised to prevent theJewish immigrants mentioned in paragraph (6)from settling in the area contemplated for theArab State   as otherwise Arab opinion would beput in opposition to the scheme:(iv)    That the proposal at the end of paragraph (5)that steps should be taken to enforcedisarmament was impracticable and, in the opinionof the General Staff, could only be carried outby means of &quot;Turkish methods&quot;.      It was suggested to delete the words following &quot;General OfficerCommanding&quot; in line 8 of the paragraph and to -substitute &quot;who will be&apos; given complete discretion as to the measures to be taken&quot;:
(v)    That from the point of view of the Chancellorof the Exchequer, it would have been preferable to omit paragraph (8), but that,if it was essential to include it as one of the attractions of the schemes for the Arabs, hewould not oppose its retention.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,while paying a tribute to the work of the Royal Commissionand not objecting in principle to the partition, hadquestioned the method adopted in the Report.     this involved the creation of a very small Jewish State with aweak frontier and small powers of defence as well as thecreation of an Arab State without independent access tothe sea.     He also criticised the position of Haifa and suggested that ten years was not sufficient time for itsretention under mandatory administration.     He doubted whether a time limit was desirable at all.     He alsoquestioned the desirability of a policy of placing theArab State under the Emir of Transjordania who was veryunpopular with the rulers of Iraq and Saudi Arabia.He agreed with other criticisms that paragraph (3) shouldbe redrafted on less definite lines,  for example, by thesubstitution for the phrase &quot;and that a scheme of partition on the lines recommended by the Commissionrepx^esents the best and most hopeful solution of the deadlock.&quot; of the following:    &quot;that a scheme of partitionon the general lines of that recommended by the Commissionrepresents the best and most hopeful solution of the deadlock!&apos;The Secretary of State for India, while approving the principle of partition as the only method of realisingJewish aspirations, pointed out that the great difficultylay in the transfer into Arab territory of some 250 ,000- 13 -
Arabs now located in the territory proposed for the jewish state.     It was clear from the Report of the RoyalCommission that land was not available for them in theproposed Arab State in present conditions and that a great dealof preparation would be necessary.     What was to happen tothese quarter of a million Arabs in the interval?   He alsocriticised the attribution to the Arabs of the port ofJaffa at the apex of a corridor under mandatory control andwith Jewish territory all round as liable to create &quot;a newDanzig&quot;.     He asked if a new Arab port could be constructed.The Secretary of State for the Colonies saidthat it would be possible to construct a port at Gaza, butit would be very expensive.     Jaffa was inhabited by theArabs, which had no doubt   led the Royal Commission totheir conclusion.The Cabinet agreed:(a) That when the Report of the RoyalCommission on Palestine was published,a statement should be issued at the samet^ime making clear that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment approved the principle of partition in principle, but that theyare not committed to details until theyhave had time to make their own enquiries:(b) That the Secretary of State for theColqnies should at once prepare a revised draft statement of policy for publicationsimultaneously with the Report:(c) That the Cabinet should meet on Monday next, the 5th July, at 5.0 p.m. in thePrime Minister&apos;s Room at the House ofGommons to consider the revised statement:(d) That the Secretary of State for theColonies should have discretion as tocommunicating advance copies of the Reportconfidentially to such persons as he might deem in the public interest and to makeappropriate arrangements for itscommunication to the Press.w 14
90o 6THE IMPERTALCONFERENCE.(previous reference:Cabinet 24(37), Con-elusion 5 .)40   In accordance with, the Conclusion referred to inthe margin, the Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs (CP.-161(37)), prepared, in consultation with the Minister forCo-ordination of Defence, the Secretary of State forAir and the President of the Board of Trade respectively,containing information as to certain conclusions ofthe Imperial Conference relating to Munitions and food supplies, Civil Aviation, Empire Trade, and.. Shipping,which had. not been published.The Cabinet took note of the memorandum.
THE LONDON naval treaty, 193 5.Ratification of.(previous reference:Cabinet 26(37), Con-clusion 1.)PR. 5^ (37)5,   The Cabinet again had under consideration the Joint Memorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs and the First Lord of the Admiralty(CP.-162 (37)) on the subject of Ratification ofthe London Naval Treaty, 193 6, upon which a decisionhad been postponed at the Meeting mentioned in the margin pending consultation by the Prime minister with the Parliamentary Secretary to the treasury on the Parliamentary time-table.The Prime Minister informed the Cabinetthat Parliamentary time could not be found forpassing a London Naval Treaty Bill before the recess unless the Opposition Parties in parliament were willing to give up a Supply Day for thepurpose.     He did not think it would be wise to ratify the Treaty without Parliamentary approval.The Lord Chancellor suggested that if a discussion could take place and should reveal generalagreement in the House of Commons, it might bepossible to ratify the Treaty.The Prime Minister said that he would seethe Leader of the Labour Opposition in parliament and try to otc&amp;ain  some agreement.
AIR RAID PRT3-CAUTIONS WSCHOOLS.(previous reference:Cabinet 16(37), Con-el us ion 4 .)F-P 2^(57)7.6.     The Cabinet had before them a; Joint Memorandumby the President of the Eoard of Education and theSecretary of State for Scotland (CP.-167 (37)),covering a draft Circular to Local Authorities on air Raid Precautions in Schools.    The Circular hadbeen examined by the Treasury and the Air Raid Pre-cautions Department of the Home Office, and, subject-to the approval of their colleagues, the Ministersproposed to issue it in the near future, with suchverbal changes in the copy sent to Local Authoritiesin Scotland as may be necessary in view of Scottishconditions .The above memorandum was reserved until thenext regular weekly meeting of the Cabinet,,- by which time it was hoped that the Report of Sir Warren Fisher&apos;s Sub-Committee on Air Raid Precautions Services wouldbe available.
3,1 95    7.     The Minister of Agriculture and fisheries said he would he glad if a Cabinet Committee could beappointed to assist him in drawing up a Long TermMilk Policy which concerned other Departments besideshis own.     He would like it to become a Committee on agricultural Policy.The Prime Minister reserved the question until the meeting of the Cabinet arranged for Monday next, the 5th July.
THE MILK(AMENDMENT)BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 26(37), Con-elusion 3 .)8.   The Cabinet had under consideration.a joint memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and fisheries and the Secretary of State for Scotland. (H.A.-28 (37))covering the draft Milk (Amendment) Bill, the objectof which was to continue with certain amendments for afurther year, from October 1, 1937, the temporary provisions of the Milk Acts, 1934 and 1936:    togetherwith the following recommendation by the Committee ofHome Affair? thereon (H.A.C. 10th Conclusions (37)):-&quot;To authorise the introduction forthwith in the House of Commons, with a view toits passage into law before the summer recess, of the Milk (Amendment) Bill inthe form of the draft annexed, to H.A.-28(37), subject to any drafting or other minor alterations that ma.y be foundnecessary or desirable.&quot;The Gabinet approved the recommendation ofthe Committee of Home Affairs as set forth above and authorised the Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries to hand in hisFinancial Resolution   the same evening.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,30th June, 1937.
APPENDIX.Cypher telegram to S ir N.  Render son (Berlin) No.118.Sir Ec Drummond (Rome) No.223.Foreign Office..    29th June,  1937.    9.50 p. m.IMMEDIATE.(To Berlin only)       Your telegram No.  156 (ofJune 23th).His Majesty&apos;s Government greatly regret to learn thatat to-day&apos;s meeting of the Non-intervention Sub-Committeethere were indications that the attitude of the GermanItal ianRepresentatives was by no means favourable to the oroposalswhich they put forward for filling the gap created in thenaval patrol scheme by the retirement of the German andItalian elements.His Majesty&apos;s Government frankly find it difficult to appreciate that this attitude can be dictated by thesuggestion that the proposals for filling the gap are un-satisfactory from the point of view of general impartiality,nor can they really believe that the German GovernmentItalianhold this view.      His Majesty&apos;s Government have put forwardthese uroposals in a sincere wish to meet the difficulty which has arisen by the fairest possible -means available;and in order to give the greatest confidence in respect oftheir intentions, they have declared their willingness toaccept neutral observers on board their patrol ships.      Pleaseexplain to the German Government therefore that our onlyItaliandesire   has been to seek to satisfy all parties of theimpartiality of our scheme.      In these circumstances we muchhope that the German Government will yet reconsider theirItalian
attitude and help us to find an early solution of the problem which confronts us.     The chief aim of His Majesty&apos;s Governmentcontinues to be to maintain the policy of non-intervention inorder to avoid the conflict spreading beyond the borders of spain.     They feel justified in asking the German. Government1 sItaliancollaboration to meet this danger.If, however, the German Government persist in theirItalianpresent attitude His Majesty&apos;s Government hope that they willat least themselves put forward alternative proposals at themeeting on Friday which have a reasonable prospect ofgeneral acceptance.For your own guidance it would not be possible forHis Majesty&apos;s Government to agree to grant belligerentrights at this stage and in these conditions;    no recent developments of the conflict have taken place which would beheld to justify it.      It is also extremely desirable that theGerman Government should state their position clearly at theItalianmeeting on Friday for the present uncertainty cannot, beallowed to continue beyond that date.Repeated to Paris No.11?, Lisbon No.108.

</content>
</cab>
