<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/20/17 images: 156-163</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY,----. it Is requested that special care may be taken to ...,.**ensure the secrecy of this document.tS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS 3RITAHITIC majesty&apos;s S , GC \f ERNMENT&apos; &apos;     &quot; &apos;   &apos; COPY NO.   W___i^P.(4l) 294.1st December 1941.VjAR CABINET.TREATMENT OF THE NATIONALS IN THIS COUNTFYOF HUNGARY, RUMANIA, FINLAND AND JAPAN INTHE EVENT OF WAR WITH THOSE COUNTRIES.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.I have had under consideration the question of whatsecurity measures by internment and otherwise should be taken against the nationals of Hungary, Rumania, Finland and japan in the event of war being declared against these countries,and there has been consultation between the Home Office,Foreign Office and the Security Service on this subject.1. The following figures show the approximate number ofmales between the ages of 16 and 65, excluding seamen, whoare at present in this country:-Hungarians - approximately 1,400Rumanians - &quot;                1,300Finns - &quot;                    250Japanese - &quot;                   600;These people like all other aliens are registered with thepolice and subject to the general requirement applicable to allaliens that they must be in their registered places of residenceat night.     On the declaration of war with any of the countries mentioned the nationals of that country will automaticallybecome subject to the further special restrictions in the  A3icr.V?Order applying to enemy aliens.     These special restrictionsprovide that an enemy alien must not travel more than fivemiles from his place of residence without a police permit andmust not without a police permit be in the possession of a motor car, camera and various other prescribed articles.2, Neither the Security Service nor the Commissioner of Policeof the Metropolis (where a high proportion of these personsreside) think that it is necessary in the event of thedeclaration of war for all male nationals of these countries tobe interned.     General measures of internment are open tothe objections that (a)  apart from the trouble and expenseinvolved they arc liable to create resentment in the mind?,such aliens as are friendly to this country, and (b) they arcliable to provoke retaliatory&quot;actionj    this is a considerationespecially affecting British nationals in Japan.It is of course very necessary that effective security measures shall be taken, but having regard to the information given to me by the Security Service and the police as to theharmless character of large numbers of these people, I do not propose at the outset at any rate to adopt general measuresof internment.     The question whether general measures of
internment or extensive measures of internment may have-to be taken can be considered later.3. Lists have been drawn up by the Security Service ofall those about whom suspicions are entertained^ and itis proposed that in the event of the declaration of warall the persons, on such-lists shall be interned at once.These lists will comprise a comparatively small proportionof the total number of males.4. The police will be told to report at once any other cases about whom there are grounds for suspicion, in orderthat such individuals may be interned without delay. .5. All seamen who are nationals of the countries mentionedwill be interned immediately on the declaration of war,to prevent the possibility of their getting back to theirown countries.1 note is attached setting out in detail the plansproposed.     I think it right to let the Vvar Cabinet know of these plans and to ask for their concurrence to theseproposals.HOME OFFICE.1st December 1941.
PROPOSED POLICY FOR DEALING WITH HUNGARIANS,ROUMANIANS,  FINNS AND JAPANESE IN THE EVENT OP A DECLARATIONOF WAR BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT AGAINST these four COUNTRIES.A.Conference was held at the Home Office of the Departmentsinterested in this question to consider what policy His Majesty&apos;sGovernment should be advised to adopt in the event of adeclaration of war on Hungary, Roumania, Finland and Japan.    TheDepartments represented were the Foreign Office, Home Office, theSecurity Services, the Ministry of War Transport, the commissioner of Police,,  and Colonel Robertson, who acts as Liaison Officerbetween the Home Office and the military authorities-.Plans had already been prepared for dealing with HungariansRoumanians and Japanese, and they were based on tho policy whichhad boon adopted in tho case of tho Italians, namely, that allmale Hungarians, Roumanians and Japanese between.the ages of 16and 65 should bo automa&apos;cically intornod on tho outbreak of war,though cortain categories of persons would be exomptod - forexample, the    ill and the unfit and persons who had obtained a permit to engage in work of national importance and had boonspecifically vetted for this purpose.      No such plans had beenprepared in the case of the Finns,Tho Conference agreed that it would be desirable that the samepolicy should be followed regarding the internment of nationals oftheso four countries,    Tho difficulty is that whereas in the caseof Hungarians and Japanese there is a presumption that thesonationals are more likely to be hostile to this country, there isno similar presumption in the case of tho Roumanians^      On thocontrary the Security Services and the Police take the view thatthere are only a few Roumanians whose immediate internment on thooutbreak of war would bo necessary in the interests of national security.    As regards tho Finns, it is not at present certain how they would react to a declaration of Avar, but it is considercdreasonably safe to limit the internment of Finns to smallproportions,  at any rate in the first instance, but the Finnishpopulation in this country will be carefully suporvisods  andfurther measures would bo taken if necessary.    On the other hand,to adopt.a policy of automatic internment in the case ofHungarians and Japanese while a policy- of selective internmentwas adopted in the case of tho Finns and Roumanians might causes considerable embarrassment to His Marjosty&apos;s Government and inparticular to the Home Secretary * who would have to -justify      .the differentiation.which had boon mado.It was agreed after a full discussion that the policy to beadopted should bo on the following lines.(l)    Civilians.There Bhould bo no automatic internment of the nationals of. any of theso four countries in the event of a declaration ofwar.    So far as Japan is concerned there is tho special consideration that a policy of general internment might result Inthe Japanoso taking similar action against British Nationals inthe Far East.Tho policy should be a policy of selective internment,that is to say only those persons should be interned to whomattached some olomont of suspicion on personal grounds, or who byreason of their knowledge are in a position to damage thenational interests.On this basis it ij estimated that not more than tonFinnish nationals would bo interned, a similar number ofRoumanians, about 100 Hungarians, and about 50 to 100 Japanese(out of a total of 600 male Japanoso resident in this country).. Only malos botwoon the ago of 16 and 65 would bo selected for. intornmont and, of course, internment would bo subjoct to/tho gonoral
tho general direction that no person would be arrested who wasmedically unfit to bo interned.The Security Services will prepare a list of tho persons tobe interned, and those lists will bo examined by the ForeignOffice with a view to the exclusion, unless there were any very strong security considerations of the name of any person Whosointernment might cause ombamassment to His Majesty&apos;s Government.In solecting persons for internment tho Security services will exclude the name of any of those nationals who have rocoivoda permit for employment in work of national importance as well,      &quot;\of course,  as the names of any persons who ought to receiveprivileged treatment on diplomatic grounds.(2)    Seamen.It would clearly be impossible, after tho declarationof war to allow any seamen of those nationalities to continue their sea-going employment, and the existing policy is thataliens of enemy nationality are not allowed to be employed on ships plying from this country.    On the other hand it would be extremely dangerous from a security point of view to allowseamen    who had boon deprived of thoir livelihood to be at largoin this country unless and until their individual cases had been examined,  and an estimato had been formed as to thoir attitude and sympathies.Tho Conference accordingly agreed that all seamenbelonging to those nationalities should bo automatically internedon the declaration of war, and the samo policy should be adopted as regards seamen of these nationalities who subsequently came to this country.    It is estimated that this will involve theimmediate internment of about 200 Finnish seamen and very small numbers of Hungarians and Roumanians.(3)    Hungarians?r Roumanians,, Finns and Japanese, loft at large.The nationals of these countries would, of course on adeclaration of war, be subject to the special restrictions applicableto enemy aliens (that is to say restrictions would be placed ontheir movements and on the possession by them of certain specified articles).      Amy of these nationals who at presentenjoy exemptions from restrictions will continue to enjoy thoseexemptions.Tho Conference did not consider it necessary that thocases of all these persons left at large should be reviewed bya Tribunal or an? Advisory Committee.    On the other hand it isproposed that Chief Constables should be advised that it is opento.thorn to bring before a Regional Advisory Committee (which willbe re-constituted for the purpose)  tho case of any of thosenationals about whose conduct, activities or loyalties the chief constable has any reason to feel doubt.(h)    Hungarians, Roumanians. Finns and Japanese who aro internedin pursuance of this policy.The nationals interned under this policy will be removedto the Isle of Man and placed in internment camps as soon aspracticable.    The numbers involved are such that it is not likely  Jthat the difficulties experienced in enforcing the policy ofinterning the Germans, Austrians and Intalians will be experiencedon this occasion.It will clearly be necessary to sot up some machineryfor reviewing the cases of tho Hungarians, Roumanians and Finnsinterned with a view to releasing and finding suitable employment for any of the internees who could be allowed to be at largowithout danger to the national security.      Such a roviow will necessarily take some time since it is important that thointernoos should remain in internment for a sufficient length oftime to enable the Security Service to conduct a proper examination/of their
1%0of their cases.    It may be possible to use the existingAdvisory Committees in the Isle of Man for the purposeof reviewing the cases of these internees, but it isnot anticipated that there will be any difficulty in working out adequate machinery for this purpose.As regards the Japanese,  it is hoped that theJapanese Government will agreo to a policy of reciprocalrepatriation and if so all the Japanese interned underthis policy would be repatriated eventually when shippingaccommodation becomes available




</content>
</cab>
