<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/84/0 images: 113-113</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document b the Property cfSecret.909Fvwn Viceroy, Army Department, to Secretary of State for India, &apos;    &apos;       im Jvly 1919.(Received 17th, 11.45 a.m.)9662.   16th July.  No. 60.Part 1..1. Chitral reports that 300 Kafir refugees from Bashgul have entered Ohitral, more are expected.2. Reference to my 9510, 14th instant, para, 1, Afghans in Tirali now reliably reported-to be party of officers under Shaghasi Khwaja Muhammed, whose activities in Ningrahar have been reported previously, vide my 8206 of 17th June. He held meeting at Bagh on 12th July and is reported to have collected 800 militia deserters and about 2,000 ex-sepoys and young men as recruits for Afghan Army. He asked whole Afridi jirga to meet him in Bazar on 14th to decide line of action. Up to the morning of 14th July no tribal contingents are reported to have left for Bazar.3. Mangal and Chilzai gatherings at Peiwar and Kharlachi have been dismissed to their homes and told that they are not required at present.4. Small party of Mahsuds on return from Khost are now holding Boya post and purchasing supplies ostensibly to-day (? for) Afghan troops.5. Most of the Achackzai tribesmen who had joined Abdul Qudus have now returned home.6. Kabul Agent, 5th July, reports Amir at Durbar on 4th July asked assembly what policy they advocated. Decision to send Peace delegates was arrived at. He also reports personnel of five newly-raised battalions have been temporarily disbanded.7. Cavalry reconnaissance north of Hindu Bagh led to some fighting with tribesmen on 14th, in which we lost three killed and (? corrupt group) wounded.8. Cholera has recurred at Nowshera in epidemic form; 16 cases have occurred amongst British troops, but no particulars. Since beginning of campaign there have been 14 cases with 516 deaths, of which 92 and 17 respectively amongst British troops. Weather conditions have much improved. On .12th and 13th maximum shade temperature dropped from 115&quot;6 to 91&apos;4 at Peshawar.and from 106&apos;5 to 79&apos;1 at Rawal Pindi.Para. 6 not communicated to Press. Para. 2 communicated in general terms, omitting numbers recruited. -Part 2.

</content>
</cab>
