<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/84/0 images: 381-382</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
epartment of Agriculture and Technical Instruction for Ireland.   1This Document &apos;o Vie Property of H!3 Britannic Majesty&apos;? Government289FOOD PRODUCTION 301-IRi&amp;AlTD. bail gM^-^Memorandum-prepared in compliance with Chioi&quot;^Seoretary*BMinuto of 17th March, 1917.Week ended 23rd July, 1919.The following is a brief statement on the work of the Department during the past week in furtherance of increased Pood Production in IrelandLOANS FOR AGRICULTURAL IMPLEMENTS.The number of applications for loans for the purchase of machinery received during the past week was 108, and the total value of machinery ordered to date is  36,485,TILLAGE   SECTION,In connection with the work of checking declarations, made by growers, under Part 1 of the Corn Production Aot, 1917, 58 Senior Inspectors have boon assigned to districts and the ma.jor.tty of these Inspectors are now at work.   In additional 265 Temporary Suft-Inspectors have boen appointed and allocated to districts in which they will take up&quot; work in the course of the next few days.   It is anticipated that the appointment of the additional Temporary Sub-Inspectss required will be concluded this week,PROGRESS OF FARM WORK.Farm crops bonefifcod considerably by rain which fell on two days during the week,From one of the principal potato-growing areas it is reported that the yield of this crop is likely to be below average, the growth of foliago being poor, so far5 owing to the long period cf cool dry weather.   The demand for potato spraying materials has been good, and numbors of now sprayors have been bought -indicating a more genoral adoption of this preventive nBasure,   In many districts, however, spraying has been deferred owing to the anxiety of farmers to utilise the favourable weather for the early butting and saving of hay.The bulk og the hay orop is now saved, and in ricks or field cocks, except where the crop is being harvested for seed. Though the yield is not heavy, the crop has teeon well saved, and for his reason itB feeding bulk should compare favourably with that f the past two seasons.
i . 2JOGrain &quot;or-op^ jjapr-cnroa--oo-rddorably durinir^ne week. XJlaj?lyw*am^     and oats aro very prwu^^s^hut^-orf many farms a Kseftk ^rather low yield of oats is anticipated,FARM-LABOUR,The Ifcabour dlsputo in Oo. Kildare haa assumed a serious aspeot, and threatens, if continued,, to havo a disastrous effect on   -harvest prospects in the district.   The farmers and labourers are both woll organised and show.little tendency to reach an amioable settlement of the matters in dispute,cattle feeding- stuffs,The important question.of supplies of feeding stuffs for the coming winter is engaging the attention of.the Department, who &apos;are in correspondence with tho Ministry of Food and other Depart- &apos; ments concerned.   Reports indicate that., with the exception of lin- &apos; seed cake, fair quantities of imported feeding stuffs are now reaching Ireland in the ordinary course of trade.flax.Prop  Prospects.      Flax-pulling is beginning in an early district in the South, but it will not be general for another week 6r so.Flax Lxperiments.   A quantity of seed,produced from Japanese seed grown in Canada last year, and imported into Ireland this season, was not allocated for sowing in Ireland,   The Department, however, arranged to have the seed SffeSEa tested this year on their flax plots and by a number of influential.farmers.    Reports on the  ^ growth of, th$s orcp have,npw been received.   In the Department.tyjf  plots the orop early in fcjK*g*appearod to be   slightly wnre back-ward than the crops fro$ ftu&amp;sian, English, South of Ireland, or Dutch seed, but was quite as promising as the crops from either Japanese or Canadian (fibro   variety from Ontario),   The flax ; on tho farmers1 tost plots had made as good progress at the end of Juno as flan from any other of the varieties of imported Beed,MAINTENfiNCE OF LIVE STOCK.During the peried from 8th tg 14th instant, inolusivo, applications for licences woro received as fallowsi-To slaughter or export heifers To slaughter bulls or bullocks T* slaughter voaj. oalves...,,.215 44 13,

</content>
</cab>
