<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/6/52 images: 592-601</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)107th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 107 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, April 29, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The    Right    Hon.     Winston    S.The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.RightChurchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,   The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Secretary of State for War. Bt., M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Hankey, &apos;Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson, ! The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,M.P.,  Secretary of  State for the !    Secretary of  State  for  dominion home Department and Minister Of j    Affairs.Home Security.The Right Hon. Sir John Reith, M.P.,   The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Minister of Information. Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.   Admiral  of  the  Fleet  Sir   DudleyNewall, Chief of the Air Staff. Pound, First Sea Lord and Chiefof Naval Staff.   -General  Sir W.  Edmund  Ironside.Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Mr. F. Hemming.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.&quot;Wing Commander W. Elliot.Lieutenant-Colonel E. I. C. Jacob, R.E.-   Mr. L. F. Burgis.[21232]b
WAR CABINET 107 (40).Contents.minute no.                                       Subject. page 1      The Air Situation     ..................    455Enemy activity.Bombing of Andalsnes.Stavanger aerodrome.2      The Naval Situation..................    455British submarines.Attacks on U-boats.Cargo of a captured German trawler.Magnetic mines.Enemy attacks on shipping.3      Operations in Norway ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...    456Narvik area.Namsos area.Fleet Air Arm attacks on Trondhjem.Andalsnes and the Southern Front.4      Italy     ........................    457Probable intentions.Suggested approach to Signor Mussolini.Action in the event of Italian aggression against Yugoslavia.Economic relations.5      Italy     ........................    458Naval dispositions in the Mediterranean.Suggested diversion of Australian and New Zealand convoy.6      Italy     ........................    459Measures to deter her from entering the war.7      Shipping losses ...       ....      ...      ...      ...      ,..    460Method of publication.
The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 106thConclusions,Minute 8.)Enemy activity.Bombing ofAndalsnes.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 105thConclusions,Minute 1.)stavanger aerodrome.1, The Secretary of State for Air said that there was verylittle to report. Owing to bad weather only a very limited numberof patrols and convoy escorts had been flown on the previous day.No enemy air activity had been reported near our coasts.Our Air Attache at Oslo had just returned home viaNorway and Andalsnes, and had emphasised the very heavy scale ofthe German bombing attacks on this place. These attacks usuallystarted at 9 in the morning and went on continuously until about in the afternoon, but, in spite of these attacks, the Attacheconsidered it possible for us to hold on there.It had been stated that 180 German bomber machines, attackingin successive waves, had taken part in the attacks on our Gladiatorson Lake Lesgeskogen.In answer to a question by the Prime Minister regarding areport in the Intelligence Summary that the aerodrome at Stavangerwas unusable and irreparable, the Chief of the Air Staff said thatthis report had been received from a French source. The latest information showed that the aerodrome was still in constant use.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The Naval 2.   The First Lord of the A dmiralty said that HAL SubmarineSituation. Tetrarch had reported that on the 23rd April she had attacked a(Previous large southward-bound convoy.  She had then been hunted and had reference: had to remain below for 43 hours.W.M. (40) 106th        H.M. Submarine Swordfish had attacked a northward-boundConclusions, convoy of three merchant ships with six torpedoes.Minute 9.) H.M. Submarine Sterlet was now 24 hours overdue and it wasBritish feared that she must be considered as lost.submarines.Attacks on H.M.S. Imogen, escorting H.M.S. Furious, had carried out aU-boats. most hopeful attack on a submarine on the 27th April, 130 miles north of the Shetlands.The anti-submarine trawler Northern Isles, when 5 miles southof the Faroes, had sighted a periscope 250 yards on her port bow.She had attacked with four depth charges.   As a double explosion1 had followed, it was believed that the U-boat had either been sunk or badly damaged.Cargo of a cap- The German trawler which had been captured on the 25th Apriltured German was now at Scapa. This trawler had contained depth charges, fourtrawler. magnetic mines, two field guns, A.A. ammunition, two.torpedo tubes(Previous and explosive stores.Reference:W.M. (40) 105thConclusions,Minute 2.)Magnetic mines.        Two magnetic mines had been exploded near the Sunk Light-vessel and one near the Shambles Light-vessel.Enemy attacks S.S: Scottish American (5,999 tons), which had been torpedoedon shipping. off Cape Wrath on the 27th April, had now been towed into LochEribol, where a tug was standing by. The cargo of oil could be discharged.[21232]
Operations in Norway.(Previous Reference: W.M. (40) 106th Conclusions, Minute 10.) Narvik area.

3. The War Cabinet were given the following information:--

(1) The 24th Guards Brigade headquarters had arrived at Strand on the previous afternoon. The First Battalion of the Scots  Guards, less two companies, were at Harstad and the two companiesat Forsnakken. The First Battalion of the Irish Guards, less two companies, were at Liland with one company at Lenvik and another at Bergvik. The second battalion of South Wales Borderers was at Ballangen.

(2) Two battalions of Chasseurs Alpins had begun to disembark at Sag Fjord at 1 A.M. that morning. One of these battalions would be taking over from the First Battalion of the Irish Guards in the Lenvik-Bergvik area.

(3) The Norwegians had succeeded in pushing the enemy back from Laphaugen and also in the area Dalsetten-Gratangen. The enemy was reported to be retiring from Hestvand.

(4) Lord Cork had reported that he hoped to occupy Ankenes on the following day.

(5) A telegram had been sent that morning from the Chiefs of Staff to Lord Cork, saying that it was of the utmost importance to prepare facilities for the operation of the land-based squadrons of the Air Force in the Narvik area, and informing him of the essential measures which should be taken immediately to prepare for the reception and operation of squadrons. These measures included the following:--

(a) That the existing aerodrome at Bardufoss and any other possible sites for landing grounds should be made secureby military occupation.

(b) The preparation of two or more aerodromes with surfaces clear of snow and with adequate and secure road communications.

Lord Cork had also been informed that a Royal Air Force reconnaissance party was proceeding to Narvik immediately and should be given every facility for inspecting and preparing sites.(6) A thaw had started in the Narvik area. General Bethouart, who was in command of the French troops, had arrived from Namsos.

Namsos area.

(7) The French transports Saumur and Amienois had embarked one French battalion the previous day and had sailed for Scapa.

(8) Capitaine de Brantes of the Anglo-French Military Mission, who had returned from a visit to Namsos, had reported that the dispositions of Allied troops in that area on the 26th April had been approximately as follows:--

146th Infantry Brigade--

H.Q. Rya, about 9 miles east of Namsos.

1/4 K.O.Y.L.I. Namdalseidet.

Hallams}

1/4 Lincolns} billeted in area Ranem-Opdal.

General Carton de Wiart had been at Spillum (2 miles south of Namsos).

French Forces--

H.Q. near Romstadmoen (6½ miles south-east of Bangsund).

Three battalions on general line Berghausen-Bjornberget

(i.e., a line running north-east from Namdalseidet).

General Audet had been at Kleppen (1 mile north of Namsos).

Air attacks on Trondhjem.

(9) In a daylight raid on Trondhjem the Skuas from the Ark Royal had shot down five Heinkels and damaged as many more. All the hangars at Varnes aerodrome had been destroyed and


fifteen seaplanes at anchor had been successfully attacked. OneJunker 88 had been shot down by H.M.S. Ark Royal. Our lossamounted only to one Skua,(10) The Vice-Admiral reported that no fighter opposition hadbeen encountered in this raid and that the Germans had consistentlyavoided giving battle wherever possible, even against inferior forces.The Ark Royal had been attacked but not hit.Andalsnes and (ll) All ships in this area and to seaward of it had beenthe southern      heavily bombed all day.fronfc- Molde had also been heavily bombed.H.M.S. Black Swan had been hit by a bomb, which had passed through her, and had sailed for Scapa during the previous night,having expended nearly all her ammunition. She was being relieved by H.M.S. Fleetivood.&apos;(12) The military position at Andalsnes was very confused. Areport sent via Norwegian Headquarters on the evening of the27th stated that two Companies of the 15th Infantry Brigade, withanti-tank guns, had been sent towards Hjerkinn, and that two battalions of the 15th Infantry Brigade were still holding a positionbetween Kvam and Otta.A telegram had been received from General Paget during theprevious night, reporting that his troops were in good heart, but were in urgent need of artillery support.A record of the further discussion which ensued is containedin the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.The War Cabinet took note of the above discussion.Italy.probable intentions.(previous reference:&quot;W.M. (40) 106thConclusions,Minute 1.)Suggestedapproach to signor mussolini.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 104thConclusions,Minute 4.)Action in theevent of ItalianaggressionagainstYugoslavia.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 105thConclusions,Minute 7.)4. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto telegram No. 435, dated 28th April, 1940, from His Majesty&apos;charge d&apos;Affaires, Rome, reporting that crops in Italy had sufferedbadlv from the severe winter.The Foreign Secretary drew attention also to telegram No. 51DIPP, dated 28th April, 1940, from His Majesty&apos;s Minister, the vatican, regarding the suggested United States approach to signor Mussolini : Mr. Osborne understood that, as President Roosevelt had recently addressed a communication to the Duce in the sensesuggested, he did not propose to join with the Pope in a jointapproach to Signor Mussolini.Mr. Osborne believed that Signor Mussolini no longer con-templated any immediate military initiative, though this mightbe because Italy was not prepared for war. It was important,in Mr. Osborne&apos;s opinion, that Signor Mussolini should not befurther incensed by a tightening of the blockade measures.In further discussion, the Foreign Secretary said that theAllied plans in the event of an act of aggression by Italy againstYugoslavia were not sufficiently advanced. He proposed to circulate a Paper on this subject for early discussion.
economic relations.(previous preference:W.M.. (40) 102ndConclusions,Minute 9.)The Chancellor of the Exchequer questioned the wisdom ofincreasing our order for ships to be built in Italian shipyards. he felt that, by doing so, we should be placing a hostage in the handsof the Italians, since they would undoubtedly appropriate the shipsif they went to war against us.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that the WarCabinet had approved a policy of strengthening that element in italian life which desired to make money out of the war, ratherthan to take part in it. This could best be done by increasing thenumber of profitable commercial transactions between the twocountries.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.Italy.Naval dis-positions in theMediterranean.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 106thConclusions,Minute 3.)Suggesteddiversion of australian andNew Zealandconvoy.5. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that itwould have a steadying effect if the Admiralty could inform thePress, at an appropriate moment, that, now that the German fleethad been so greatly reduced, we had been able to give orders for the redistribution of our Naval forces.The First Lord of the A dmiralty agreed with this suggestion.We should not, of course, say anything about naval forces in theEastern Mediterranean until the necessary dispositions had beenmade.The First Lord then said that orders had been given that.M.S. Royal Sovereign and H.M.S. Malaya should proceedeastward for a period of 36 to 40 hours, by which time the positionwould be clearer. An adequate escort of destroyers had beenprovided. It was proposed that H.M.S. Warspite should remain at Gibraltar as part of the Allied Naval squadron which it was proposed to assemble in the Western Mediterranean.It was thought that H.M.S. Ramillies, which was nowapproaching India with a convoy of Australian troops, should be ordered to leave the convoy and to proceed to Alexandria as quickly as possible, where she would arrive on the 12th-13th May.Behind the convoy which H.M.S. Ramillies was escorting wasthe fast convoy, now on the point of leaving Australia, carrying-further Australian and New Zealand contingents. In the circum-stances, it was not thought right to allow these vessels to proceed upthe Red Sea. The possibilities of diversion of these contingentswere being studied.The Chief of the Air Staff said that the use of the overlandroute from Basrah was impracticable. These contingents must therefore be diverted either (1) to England, or (2) to India, or (3) tothe Cape.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that thepresent contingent, amounting to 20,000 men, was much larger thanthe earlier contingent. If it was impossible to send this contingent to Palestine or Egypt, we ought to consult the Australian and NewZealand Governments. Again, if HALS. Ramillies must now beremoved from convoy duties, the Australian and New zealand governments should be informed, since they had attached greatimportance to this ship being employed on these duties.The Chief of the Naval Staff said that in the outer seas the convoy could not encounter anything more than an armed merchant cruiser, which could be dealt with by a cruiser escort. The twoDominion Governments should be informed that we would send up^a fresh escort from Cape Town.The Chief of the Naval Staff added that Italian merchantshipping was moving normally, and that special arrangements hadbeen made to ascertain if orders were given for the Italian liner Rexnot to sail from Genoa on the following day.
459 W.M. 107 (50).The War Cabinet-(1) Took note of the statement by the First Lord of theAdmiralty.(2) Invited the Admiralty and the Foreign Office to consult inregard to the issue of a statement to the effect that,owing to the reduction in the German fleet, it was proposed to redistribute our Naval forces.(3). Agreed that orders should be given that H.M.S. Ramilliesshould leave the Australian convoy and proceed as rapidly as possible to Alexandria.(4) Agreed that the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, inconsultation with the First Lord of the Admiralty,should concert the terms of a communication to theAustralian and New Zealand Governments informing them (a) That it had been necessary to give  orders  with.M.S. Ramillies to leave the convoy which she had been escorting, but that the existing escortwas fully adequate.(b) That, in view of the uncertain attitude of Italy, itmight well be impossible to allow the australian and New Zealand convoy to enter the Red Sea,and enquiring the views of the Australian andNew Zealand Governments as to alternativedestinations for their contingents.Italy.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 102ndConclusions,Minute 8.)Measures to deter her from entering the war against us.6. The War Cabinet had before them a Report by the Chiefsof Staff Committee on measures which could be taken to deter italy from entering the war against the Allies (W.P. (40) 138).The Chief of the Air Staff said that, of the measures suggestedin paragraph 7 of the Report, the Chiefs of Staff particularly wishedto carry out the following : Paragraph 7 (i). The move of 1 Battalion to Gibraltar.Paragraph 7 (iii). The move of a battalion from India toAden.Paragraph 7 (vi). The move of 2 Bomber Squadrons from india to Egypt.Those measures with which the French were also concerned werebeing discussed with them. In particular, the Air OfficerCommanding-in-Chief, British Air Forces in France, had been ordered to discuss with the French air authorities plans and preparations for air attacks on the industrial areas in North Italy.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that the battalionfor Gibraltar would be a Regular battalion now doing pioneer workin France: The use of a territorial army battalion for this purposehad been considered, but there was not one fully equipped and available. The Indian Government had agreed to provide anadditional battalion for Aden.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs welcomed theproposal to move two Bomber Squadrons from India to Egypt, andenquired whether the move of the Rhodesia Squadron now in Kenya,and the three South African Squadrons, could be accelerated. TheEgyptian Government were particularly nervous of air attack.The Chief of the Air Staff said that he did not wish to denudeKenya entirely, and the Rhodesia Squadron was not equipped with modern aircraft. The move of the South African Squadrons wouldtake place as soon as their re-equipment was complete probably inJune or July.
In reply to an enquiry by the First Lord, he said that plans were fully prepared to supply rifles and ammunition to the tribesin Abyssinia after war had broken out.The First Lord of the Admiralty drew attention to the largenumber of troops in Palestine, which included a Yeomanry division and 11 Regular battalions, and urged that better use should be madeof the fine material available.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that all theRegular battalions in Palestine except one were earmarked to move to Egypt in case of emergency.The War Cabinet: Gave general approval to the recommendations containedin the Report by the Chiefs of Staff (W.P. (40) 138), and,in particular, authorised the following action :  (a) the move of one Regular battalion from the B.E.F. to gibraltar;(b) the move of one Indian infantry battalion from Indiato Aden;(c) the move of two Bomber Squadrons from India to egypt;(b) and (c) being subject to the concurrence of theGovernment of India.Shipping 7.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the losses. First Lord of the Admiralty (W.P. (G.) (40) 113) in regard toMethod of publication of shipping losses. The present arrangement was to publication. release the information for publication immediately, except when(Previous some special reason existed  for withholding publication.    in reference: addition, the Admiralty issued a statement each week giving theW.M. (40) 101st numbers of British, Allied and Neutral ships lost by enemy actionConclusions, in tne seven days ending on the preceding Sunday, and giving alsoMinute 2.) &apos; tne n&amp;me and tonnage of each British ship lost with, the dateof loss.For the future, it was proposed that publication of losses ofships by enemy action should be confined to a weekly statement, seven days in arrear, giving the numbers of British, Allied and neutral ships lost, with a total tonnage for British ships, but not thename, the tonnage of each ship, the date or the cause of loss.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the present wasa suitable time for introducing the new procedure, since the shipping situation had been more satisfactory in the last few weeks.The Minister of Information said that he was in agreementwith the new arrangements proposed.The War Cabinet: Approved the new arrangements proposed for thepublication of shipping losses in W.P. (G.) (40) 113.Richmond Terrace. S. W. 1.April 29, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
