<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/30/20 images: 148-161</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(&apos;&apos;HI?..?0S1^T--IS- THB PRQ^EHTY 0P HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT).TO BE KEPT UNDeFlOCK aFdT( y&quot;&quot;It is requested that sin-., in&apos; i-v. r, may be taken toensure the sow ecy of&apos; Uiid uouument.MOST SECRET.COPY NO,.     W.M ,( 42 ) 73RD CONCLUSIONS .Confidential Annex.(llth June, 1942 - 11 &apos;a.m.)ITUEE THE PRIME MINISTER gave the T/ar Cabinet a generallERATIONS   review of the state of planning in all theatres.CDCONTINENTAL OPERATIONS.reviouslef erence:H.M.(42) The Prime Minister explained that he had made alo til Con- most careful examination, in consultation with the Chiefs ofplus ions.)   Staff, of the action which we could take in 1942 and 1943to help Russia.As a result of this study, he had reached theconclusion, with which the Chiefs of Staff were in full agree-ment, that operations in 1942 should he governed by thefollowing two principles:-(i) No substantial landing in Prance in 1942 unless we are going to stay:    and(ii) No substantial landing in Prance unless theGermans are demoralised by failureagainst Russia.He had handed the previous evening an Aide Memoire(copy annexed) to Mo Molotov summarising the action which we proposed to take and this had been well received.Broadly speaking, the operations divided themselvesinto three phases;   first, the immediate future;   next, what we could do in the Autumn of 1942 and finally, the operations -for 1943.(a) &quot;Rutter&quot;.This would take place shortly.    It was a &quot;butcherand bolt&quot; raid on the Continent of about 24 hours&apos; duration,employing some 6,000 to 7,000 men.(h) &quot;Sledgehammer&quot;.This was a large scale operation employing six divisions, or possibly more,.if circumstances were favourable,The carrying out of this operation was entirely dependent onthe situation on the Rucsian front, and was only considered tobe practicable if German morale had st ,.rted to crack.   It

would take two months to assemble the necessary shipping and September would be the last month in which it could becarried out, owing to weather conditions.    It had been explained to H. Molotov that a landing on the Continent$ this year which was doomed to failure,-, and resulted in another Dunkirk with.considerable slaughter, would do nothing to help the Russians and would, moreoverP prejudice the larger scale operations planned for 1943*The Prime Minister, emphasised that in his talks withthe      -Russians ho had not committed us in any way to do&quot;Sledgehammer&quot;o   The conditions in which .e might undertake the operation had been clearly explained to and understood by them.    In his own view, it seemed unlikely that theseconditions would obtain, but it was clearly right that allpreparations for the operation should go ahead0In the ensuing   discussion, there was generalagreement -(a) That we should not attempt any major landing onthe Continent this year, unless we intended to stay there,(b) That all plans and preparations for &quot;Sledgehammer&quot;should be pressed forward with the greatestvigour, on the understanding that the operation would not be launched, except in conditionswhich hold out a good prospect of success,(c) That the Chiefs of staff should have authority toask for the necessary shipping to be taken up for&quot;Sledgehammer&quot; on the 1st July, withoutfurther reference to the War cabinet(c) &quot;Imperator&quot;,This operation had been planned as a large scaleraid to follow &quot;Ruttor&quot;o   The forces employed were to haveamounted to one division and some armoured units, which wereto remain on the Continent for three or four days.   their objective was to have been ABBEVILLE or AMIENS, and it hadbeen hoped to bring on an air battle in which we mightsubject the German Air Force to considerable wastage.The Prime Minister said that he was strongly opposed to this operation.   He had explained his views tothe Chiefs of Staff and the latter had expressed theircomplete agreement with them.   The operation had therefore&apos;been cancelled, This decision met with,general approval asbeing in accordance with the policy sec out under (,d;.(d) &quot;Roundup&quot;.This operation was one of grand conceptioninvolving an assault on the Continent employing no less thanone million American troops, together with about twenty-one british Divisions, of which six or seven would be armoured.The enemy coast line would be assaulted in force at many points.   There was no limit to the scope or objectives.

The operation would probably not be  ^egunat the date contemplated in the original Marshall Plan, i*e,1st ApriL3943o It was unlikely-that the American forces wouldbe trained in time.    Some hold-up in training would beoccasioned by the preparations for &apos;&apos;Sledgehammer&quot;, and the weather would be much better a little later in the SpringeMoreover, by postponing the date of the assault from the1st April to the 1st May, we should have by the later date,nearly 30 per cents &quot;lore landing craft available.There was general agreement that &quot;Roundup&quot; shouldnot take place before the 1st May,,(e) Northern NorwayoThe Prime Minister said that he had given muchthought to an operation in Northern Norway,,   Clearly wecould not do &quot;Sledgehammer&quot; and a Norway operation at thesame time.   Nevertheless, as in his view   it was unlikelythat &quot;Sledgehammer&quot; would take placeP it was all the moreimportant to give careful study to what could be done in thisstrategically important area in the far Northo   A firmfoothold in Northern Norway would immensely increase thesecurity of our Russian Convoys and would open the highwayto the South and enable us to start to unroll Hitler&apos;s mapof Europe from the tope   The chief bar to action at thepresent time was the presence of a considerable German airforce in Northern Norway which was menacing our sea communications round the North Cape to Russia,,   If we could get ashore and obtain the us. of tho aerodromes for ourselves?the tables would be turnedoContinuing, the Prime Minister thought we mast not be .unduly influenced by our experiences in the 1940 Norwaycampaign.   Even then we had landed and re-embarked aconsiderable force with little or no Anti-Aircraft defences0A successful operation in Northern Norway would have greateffect on opinion in Finland and Sweden.    The Prime minister asked the Chiefs of Staff to give the most earnestconsideration to the possibility of a landing in northern norway on the broad lines that he had suggested,(f) &quot;Jackpot&quot;oThe Prime Minister said that the Chiefs of staff had now reconsidered the situation and were of theopinion that an occupation of &quot;Jackpot&quot; was not essential for the protection of our convoys to Russia.   He outlined the circumstances leading up to the present situation and explained that the suwivcrs of Da Sverdruu&quot; s expeditionwere now prepared, provided they could obtain certainreinforcements, to evict a small German party now installedin one of the fiords.     The proposal was that the Norwegiansshould provide this reinforcement.It was reported that the Norwegians had not shown themselves very taken with this idea, and it had. therefore beenagreed that, if necessary, British volunteers should becalled for to augment the Norwegian expedition,.   Every effort must be made to give the small force all necessary equipment, particularly L.A*Ao guns0

The Prime Minister read out to the War cabinet a telegram which he had sent to C-ensral Auchinleck(0Zh20 of 9/6) offering him the 8th Armoured and UhthBritish Divisions for the Middle East., and GeneralAuchinleck1 s reply (CS/1230 of 10/6)He mentioned that it had beer., suggested to theCommander-in-Chief, that, on the arrival of the 8th armoured division and ^;hth Division^   he might send back to India oneIndian division and an Indian armoured brigade9   No finaldecision need, however, yet bo ta* on on tho latter movement0The War Cabinet were informed that the questionof sending one or possibly two more divisions to theMiddle East after the 51st Division had left at the endof this month, was being considered.   This could be done without any serious prejudice to &quot;Roundup&quot;0(3) ASSISTANCE TO CHINA.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had recently givenmuch thought, in consultation with the Chiefs of Staff, to measures to assist China and, in particular, to thepossibility of offensive operations in the late summer orautumn to re-open the supply line through Burma0   There were now in India, Or shortly would be, three entirely british divisions.Future allocation of troops to India would dependon whether the Russian Front held or brokeo If the former,then more troops could be sent to General Wave11*(h) MALTA.THE PRIME MINISTER said that General Marshall had now agreed that a force of about 20 American Liberators,which had been sent to the Middle East for a specificoperation which was due to take place that day, could beused for attacking the Italian Battlefleet, if they should attempt to interfere with the Convoys HARPOON and VIGOROUSsThis was most satisfactory, particularly as the negotiations had been carried through oh the Staff level and it had notbeen necessary to invoke the President&apos;s assistance.THE WAR CABINET were informed of the general scopeof HARPOON and VIGOROUS 9(5) &quot;BOLERO&quot;.THE MINISTER OF LABOUR AND NATIONAL SERVICE saidthat valuable time was being lost in making ready for the reception of the American forces in this country becausethe plans for their accommodation had not yet been settled.   If advantage was to be taken of the fine weather and long hours of daylight, it was of great importance thatthe plans should be completed as a matter of urgency, so thatthe construction arrangements for the camps, etc., could proceed without further delays

AIDE MEMOIRE.After a most thorough and comprehensive examinationall possible steps which We could take to draw the weightRussia, we have reached the following conclusions:-(i) In accordance with our agreement\. we will, tothe best of our ability, continue to sendsupplies of aircraft, tanks, and other warequipment to Russia by the hazardous Northernroute and by the Persian route.(ii) In the air we are already containing in thevarious theatres of war about one half of theGerman.fighter strength and one third of theirbomber strength.   With a view to forcing theGermans to make further withdrawals from theirair strength in the East, we shall continue ourbombing of German towns and industry, and alsoour day bomber and fighter offensive overOccupied Prance9(iii) We have despatched, and will continue to despatchconsiderable reinforcemenos to Libya,, where v/ehave confronting us 11 Axis Divisions,including two German Armoured Divisions andone German ,Motorised Division.   We intend tokeep the enemy fighting hard in this theatre0Malta has for the last four months containedconsiderable German air forces in Sicily.   Atone time they&apos;had over i+00 first-line -, aircraftpounding the Island.   We have sent, arid willcontinue to send, large fighter reinforcements to keep the air battle going there0(iv) We shall continue our policy of raids againstselected points on the Continent.     These raidswill increase in size and scope as the summergoes on.   By this means we are preventing theGermans from transferring any of their 33.   &apos;-Divisions in Y/estern Europe&apos; to their eastern front, and keeping them constantly on thealert, never knowing at what point the nextattack may come.(v) -We are making preparations for a landing on theContinent in August or September 194-2.   as already explained- the main limiting factor tothe size of the landing force is the availability of special landing craft.    Clearly,however, it would not further either theRussian cause or that of the Allies as a wholeif, for the sake of action at any price, wetag

embarked on some operation which ended indisaster and gave the enemy.an opportunity forglorification at our discomforture.    It isimpossible to say in advance whether thesituation will be such as to make this operationfeasible when the time comes0   We can thereforegive no promise in the matter, hut, providedthat it appears sound and sensible, we shallnot hesitate to put our plans into effect0(vi) We are prepared$ if the idea appeals to theRussian Government, to send a force of 4fighter and 2 fighter-bomber squadrons to murmansk, v/ith a view to releasing russian air forces for operations on other parts of theRussian front.   The British squadrons could arrive about the end of July,   Does this project appeal to our friends?(vii) Is the Russian Government still attaching any importance to a combined Russian--British,operation in the Petsamo area, such as has been previously suggested?    If so., we should bepleased to start conversations&apos; with the RussianStaff on this subject.,&apos;Finally, and most important of all, we areconcentrating our maximum effort on theorganisation and preparation of a large scale invasion of the Continent of Europeby British and American forces in 1943 o   We&apos;are setting no limit to the scope and objectives of this campaign., which willhe carried out in the fir st instance by over a million ment British and American,with air forces of appropriate strength.( viii)




</content>
</cab>
