<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/8/0 images: 15-19</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0. 11. (45 ) 92nd Conclusions, Minute 429th october , 1946 - 11.0 a. in.&apos;M]D The Cabinet had before them memoranda by theLord President (CP. (46) S8l) and the Secretary ofPreviouspence: State for Dominion Affairs  (CP. (46) 39l) regarding,;,f.(45) 33rdonclusions,        conversations which the Lord President had held with[minute 5)Irish Ministers during his recent visit to Eire andNorthern Ireland.Discussion turned mainly on the conversations which the Lord President had had with Mr.  de valera and, after his return to London, with the Prime Ministerof Northern Ireland on the question of Partition.THE LORD PRESIDENT said that  it was evidentfrom his conversation that Mr.  de Valera believedthat Partition was now the outstanding issue preventing the restoration of fully free and friendly relationsbetween this country and Eire and that it would be agood thing if this issue could be settled.      He had clearly implied that,  if we were ready to accept theprinciple of a United Ireland - apparently this wouldhave to come first - he would for his part he readyto agree that Northern Ireland should have her ownParliament, provided that the powers in respect ofNorthern Ireland which were now reserved to theGovernment at Westminster were transferred to the new government of the United Ireland.      He would agree thatsuch a United Ireland should remain a member of theBritish Commonwealth,  though he would insist that itshould have the status of a I^epublic.      He could not
accept the status of a Dominion or the concept of allegiance to a common Grown.      Pie would,  however, he prepared that a United Ireland should enter into agreements for military co-operation with other membersof the Commonwealth.The Lord President said that Mr.  de valera had clearly expected him to say something on thisquestion.      After making it clear that he had no authority to discuss the matter on behalf of HisMajesty&apos;s Government and was expressing only his personal views,  he had said that in his opinion the wisest course for all concerned was to avoid precipitating the issueof Partition.      There was no prospect of securingNorthern Ireland&apos;s consent,  in anything like the earlyfuture, to any scheme for a United Ireland,      Nor hadthe atmosphere for discussion of this issue been improved by Eire&apos;s neutrality in the war and &quot;by herdenials of allegiance to the common Crown.      He would therefore prefer to maintain a policy of developingclose co-operative relations in matters of common concern but to avoid precipitating the issue of partition.      This,  if raised, would lead to violentcontroversy which could bring no advantage to any ofthe parties concerned.      Mr.  de Valera had indicated that in that event the difficulties in the relationsbetween this country and Eire would have to continue.The Lord President said that he had subsequently been able to give an account of this conversation to the Prime Minister of Northern Ireland.The latter had said that, if the issue were raised,there would he a storm in Ulster.      Public opinion
there would insist on two points:-    (i)    that, &quot;before a United Ireland was established, Sire should enter theBritish Commonwealth,  declare allegiance to the Crown,and undertake specified military obligations;    and (ii)that,   some provision should be made to ensure thatRoman Catholic priests would no longer interveneimproperly in State affairs.      For their part,  theNorthern Ireland Government would be resolutely opposedto the opening of any discussions on the Partitioniss ue.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DOMINION affairs said that he was grateful to the Lord President forgiving the Cabinet this account of his conversations,and he congratulated him on the skill with which hehad conducted his interview with Nr.   de Valera.The Secretary of State strongly endorsed theview that it would be inopportune to raise the Partitionissue.      As a result of Eire&apos;s record in the late war,Mr.   de Valera was in difficulties, particularly withthose who had previously supported him in the UnitedStates;    and it would ohviously suit him to revive theIrish controversy on a basis which would enable him torally his earlier sympathizers and supporters.      This,no doubt, was among the considerations which influencedhim in seeking to raise again the issue of Partition.From our point of view,  however,  it was equally clearthat we should be well-advised to avoid a revival ofthis controversy.
The Secretary of State recalled that,  soon after the Government^ assumption of office, he had submitted, a memorandum (CP. (45) 152) recommending that our general policy towards Sire should he quickly and unobtrusively to restore friendly relations by losingno opportunity of promoting intercourse and co-operation in practical matters.      The Cabinet had approved that policy on 18th September,  1945;    and he was glad to beable to report that satisfactory progress had since beenmade along these lines.      He hoped that Ministers would continue to take such opportunities as offered for promoting closer relations with Eire..    In particular,he hoped that the Ministry of Agriculture would be readyto advise or assist representatives of the Eire Governmentvisiting this country with a view  to increasing the levelof food production in Eire,THE HOME SECRETARY said that he saw no prospectof any softening of Northern Ireland&apos;s attitude towardsthe conception of a United Ireland,      He strongly supported the view that we should do nothing to precipitatediscussion of the Partition issue.THE MINISTER OP HEALTH pointed out that therewere some sections of opinion in Eire which would be opposed to the creation of a United Ireland,      Theprotectionist policy adopted by the Eire Government had had the effect of creating,  in Dublin and other industrial centres, vested interests in the retention of Partition.
The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the memorandacirculated by the Lord President and theSecretary of State for Dominion affairs and of the statements made in the courseof the discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W.I.Copies V-6 ;- VWsVe,-.

</content>
</cab>
