<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/94/0 images: 200-204</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  September 1958C. (58) 182 Copy No.9th September, 1958CABINETEUROPEAN FREE TRADE AREAFINANCIAL ASSISTANCE TO THE UNDER-DEVELOPED COUNTRIESNote by the Paymaster General1The attached paper by officials deals with the problem of financial assistanceto the under-developed countries. We have, up to now, resisted any proposals ofthis kind, but we felt all along that in the end something would have to be done.I agree with officials that the time has now come to hold some discussions withother European countries and I invite my colleagues to endorse the general lineset out in this paper.K. M.Office of the Paymaster General, S.W.1,8th September, 1958.54009a
EUROPEAN FREE TRADE AREAFINANCIAL ASSISTANCE TO THE UNDER-DEVELOPED countries memorandum by the Official Steering GroupOfficials have considered the attached memorandum on the question of finance for the under-developed countries of Europe: the Irish Republic, Greece, Icelandand Turkey. They are of the opinion that if a Free Trade Area Convention is tobe adopted by O.E.E.C. it will be necessary to make some finance available for thedevelopment of the peripheral countries in order that they may, at the end of an extended transitional period, play their full part in the Free Trade Area. We know that Germany and other European Governments accept this and are beginning toconsider the means by which finance should be given.2. In these circumstances we do not think it practicable for the UnitedKingdom to stand out and it would be to our advantage to discuss with Germanyand other contributing countries in Europe the basis on which finance might beprovided and how the amounts can be kept to reasonable proportions. Unless weenter into such discussions soon we shall have lost the opportunity of influencing the development of thought on provisions to which we think we shall eventuallyhave to adhere and to contribute.3. More thought needs to be given to how any finance might be administeredand we do not at this stage ask Ministers to reach decisions on this question.4.   We seek authority:  (a) to discuss with other European countries how, and how much, financemight be provided for the development of the so-called peripheralcountries on the understanding that any arrangements made would besubject to:  (i) the negotiation of a satisfactory Free Trade Area;(ii) satisfactory arrangements for the administration of any financeprovided;(iii) the contribution of the United Kingdom, having regard to the already great responsibilities of the United Kingdom for thedevelopment of the Commonwealth, being small.(b) To inform the Commonwealth at Montreal that:  (i) in our view some provision of finance for the development of theperipheral countries will have to be made and that other european countries accept this;(ii) we shall be discussing with other European countries how this can best be handled;(iii) we do not yet know what machinery is likely to be set up for dealingwith it;(iv) we shall seek to keep the United Kingdom share very small.54009
MEMORANDUMFREE TRADE AREAFINANCIAL ASSISTANCE TO THE UNDER-DEVELOPED COUNTRIESIntroductionThis paper deals with the questions:  (a) should we now agree in principle that we cannot avoid putting up somethingfor the so-called peripheral countries Greece, Turkey, Iceland and theIrish Republic as part of the price of getting a Free Trade Area;(b) if so, what institutional and administrative arrangements should we try tosecure?Timing2. If we are to depart from our existing line that we can afford to do nothing for the peripherals, in terms of the Free Trade Area negotiations, there are strong reasons for taking decisions now:  (a) In order to keep our commitments to an absolute minimum and to ensureas far as possible acceptable institutional arrangements, we would need to talk urgently to other developed countries of Europe so as to influence their ideas at the formative stage and to present a common front to the peripherals (the Six Powers are meeting on 17th september to settle their policy, and proposals have been made in O.E.E.C. for the setting up of a development agency, which are due for discussion inParis also in September).(b) We should need to explain our policy to the Commonwealth and the montreal Conference offers the obvious opportunity. Failing this theFree Trade Area negotiations might get held up while such explanationstake place.Should the United Kingdom help?3. So far our line has been that we cannot afford to do anything. On financialand economic grounds the case for sticking to this line is overwhelmingly strong.Our external financial position still needs further strengthening and our commitments already existing or in prospect are uncomfortably large. In any case if we have reserves to spare we are under obligation to give priority to investment in the Commonwealth, including the Colonies. The Commonwealth will surelyresent any help we give to the peripherals.4. On the other hand the peripherals are being asked to take on the fullobligations of the Free Trade Area within a specified period and it is reasonablefor them to ask for the means to develop to enable them to do so. It seems certainthat the peripherals will veto a Free Trade Area in O.E.E.C. if they do not getfinancial help, and for political reasons a Free Trade Area which excluded theperipherals is hardly a starter. Secondly, we know that Germany is prepared togive assistance to the peripherals and that other European Governments accept thatsome help for these countries cannot be avoided and is not in itself unreasonable.We clearly cannot veto the giving of help by other countries and our position wouldbe acutely embarrassing if we alone of the developed countries made no contribution.5. If the United Kingdom is to help, that help must be very limited. an effective additional commitment of [ 20 million] spread over as long a period aspossible and in any case not less than five years is the most which should becontemplated.Institutional and Administrative Arrangements6. If we now decide that the United Kingdom cannot avoid some contributionwe need arrangements designed so far as possible(a) to limit the United Kingdom contribution and contingent liabilities so faras possible and to prevent pressures building up which might force usto do more in the future;
(b) to get as big contributions from other O.E.E.C. countries, particularlyGermany, as possible;(c) to get substantial assistance from the United States;(d) to avoid antagonising or duplicating existing institutions, e.g., international bank for Reconstruction and Development (I.B.R.D.) and theInternational Monetary Fund (I.M.F.).7. Proposals have been made in Paris by a group of experts for a Free trade area development agency. A summary of these proposals and of the objections wehave to them is given in the Annex. Also outlined in the Annex is an alternativeconcept modelled on the arrangements recently made to help Turkey. This seemsinfinitely preferable to the proposals for an agency and we would now try to persuade other prospective helpers of the peripherals to accept it.conclusion.   The essential points are:  (i) Do we consider that in principle we cannot avoid giving some financial help to the peripherals? There are powerful negotiating reasons for deciding now.(ii) Any such help would have to be very limited on the lines of paragraph 5.(iii) An Agency of the sort proposed in Paris would be to our disadvantage;we should try to persuade other countries to accept something modelledon the arrangements recently made to help Turkey.annex the Proposed agency in their Report to Working Party 23, the experts have recommended the settingup of a new Agency. This Agency in their view would have a capita! of about$1,000 millions, of which one-third would be paid up. The Agency would borrowon the world market. It would make loans for a wide range of projects, not confined to infrastructure development. It might also give grants or loans at very low interest rates; and might participate in financing projects jointly with other institutions orguarantee loans by other institutions or private investors. The Agency would be independent of the European Payments Union (E.P.U.), reporting to the Councildirectly, and would operate on lines similar to the I.B.R.D.; it would have a staff ofeconomic advisers and would also call on expert advice from outside.Objections to the Proposed Agency2. (i) It would surely involve the United Kingdom in contributing more directly or indirectly than any other arrangement.(ii) The under-developed countries would see it as a bottomless purse fromwhich if they made enough nuisance of themselves they would get almost unlimitedmoney.(iii) Such an Agency would tend to supplant rather than encourage private investment in under-developed countries and would provide little incentive to theperipherals to put their own houses in order.(iv) It would be difficult to present to the Commonwealth in view of itssimilarity to proposals for a Commonwealth bank.(v) It would probably be directly competitive with existing international institutions for loan capital and lead to strong pressure for the opening of theLondon market as a source of loan capital.An Alternative Possibility3. The arrangements now being made to help Turkey provide a frameworkwhich meets the objectives in paragraph 6 very satisfactorily. They have been negotiated within the O.E.E.C., but are far from being confined within E.P.U. They
include the I.M.F. and provide for an American contribution equal to that ofEurope. No new Agency has been required, and no question of antagonising theI.B.R.D. has arisen. Lending is not tied to projects.4. An arrangement on these lines would avoid the establishment of a newbanking institution and would rely instead on the present Managing Board ofE.P.U., or something like it, to administer the available resources. Lending wouldbe direct to Governments and could be confined to infrastructure on the basis ofbroad development plans thus avoiding the need for detailed administration and extensive supervisory and expert staffs.

</content>
</cab>
