<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/62/0 images: 10-16</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. July 1953CONFIDENTIALC. (53) 20321st July, 1953.cabinet internation CONVENTION ON GENOCIDEMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home Department and minister for Welsh AffairsThe Cabinet at their meeting on 4th September, 1952, considered a memo -randum by the Foreign Secretary and myself on the International Convention onGenocide (C. (52) 271) and invited me to prepare a draft of the Bill which wouldbe required if the United Kingdom acceded to the Convention, and then to bringthe matter before the Cabinet again (C.C. (52) 78th Conclusions, Minute 7). I now circulate a draft Bill which has been prepared for this purpose.2.   The effect of the main provisions of the Bill is:  (a) any act falling within the definition of &quot; genocide &quot; in Article II of theConvention, whether or not it is already an offence under any otherenactment or at common law, becomes a felony, punishable by deathif it involves the killing of any person, and in other cases by imprison-ment for a term not exceeding fourteen years;(b) genocide, and any attempt or conspiracy to commit genocide, are madeextradition crimes for the purposes of the Extradition Act, 1870;(c) the protection given by the Extradition Act, 1870 to persons whoseoffences or alleged offences are of a political character is removed ifthe offence is genocide.3. There are objections to adding new offences to the criminal law of theUnited Kingdom in this way. Some, though not all, of the acts classed as genocideare already punishable under our law, and there will thus be some overlapping,since the same act when committed with a genocidal intention will be punishablealso as genocide. The language of the Convention, which is reproduced in theschedule to the Bill defining the acts constituting genocide, is not so precise as itwould be if we were creating new criminal offences in the normal way. Moreover,genocide is a crime which is likely to be committed only by Governments, and inthis country, if it can be supposed, that any Government would ever intend to commit such an offence, they could first repeal any legislation on the lines of thepresent Bill which stood in the way. In my view, however, it will be necessary, ifwe accede to the Convention, to enact legislation on the lines of the Bill. Acces-sion would place us under an obligation to extradite persons accused or convicted of committing genocide in other countries, and it is important to maintain theprinciples that a person is not extraditable for any act unless that act would be acrime here, and that a foreign Government cannot try a surrendered person forany crime other than that for which he was surrendered. In my view, therefore,there is no alternative to making genocide as such a crime under our law. A safe-guard against unjustifiable prosecutions for genocide in this country would beprovided by the requirement that no proceedings should be instituted except by or with the consent of the Attorney-General.4. To make genocide an extradition crime, and to remove from personsalleged to have committed it the protection given by the existing law to thoseaccused or convicted abroad of an offence of a political character, would mean4452765
abandoning, to this extent, our traditional policy of granting asylum to personswho are accused in their own countries of political offences. This is inevitable ifwe accede to the Convention, since Article VII provides that genocide, conspiracy,attempts and direct or public incitement to commit genocide, and complicity ingenocide shall not be considered as political crimes for the purpose of extradition.5. Although 42 countries have now acceded to the Convention, the UnitedStates of America have not yet done so and I understand that it is now a matter ofsome doubt whether they will.6. I submit this Bill in order that my colleagues may see the kind of legisla-tion which, in my view, would have to be passed before we could accede to theConvention. The question for determination is whether we should introduce aBill next Session to enable us to accede to the Convention on its becoming law, or should decide not to accede to the Convention.D.M.F.Home Office, SWA,20th July, 1953.
confidential &amp; 2 Eltz. 2Genocide Convention1DRAFTof atoEnable effect to be given to the Convention on the a.d. 1953Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide.HEREAS the Convention on the Prevention and Punish-ment of the Crime of Genocide (in this Act referred to as&quot; the Genocide Convention &quot;) was unanimously adoptedby the General Assembly of the United Nations on the ninth day5 of December, nineteen hundred and forty-eight:And whereas it is expedient, with a view to the accession ofthe United Kingdom to the said Convention, that provision should be made for the punishment of persons committing anyoffence falling within the definition of &quot;genocide&quot; in the said10 Convention, and for the extradition from the United Kingdomof persons committing such offences in foreign countries.Be it enacted by the Queen&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by andwith the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal,and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the15 authority of the same, as follows: 1. (1) Any act falling within the definition of &quot; genocide &quot; in PunishmentArticle II of the Genocide Convention as set out in the Schedule of 8enocide-to this Act shall, whether or not it is an offence under any otherenactment or at common law, constitute an offence under this20 Act which shall be punishable on indictment and shall be afelony under the law of England and Wales; and- any suchoffence is hereafter in this Act referred to as an &quot; offence ofgenocide &quot;.39-3 A
2Genocide Convention1 &amp; 2 Eliz. 2a.d. 1953Court martialproceedingsin respect of offences ofgenocide.Extraditionof personscommittinggenocide.(2) A person convicted of an offence of genocide shall (a) if the offence consists of the killing of any person, sufferdeath;(b) in any other case be liable to imprisonment for a termnot exceeding fourteen years. 5(3) If, on an indictment for an offence of genocide consistingof the killing of any person, the jury are of opinion that the accused is not guilty of that offence but is guilty of the murderor manslaughter of that person, they may find the accused guilty of murder or manslaughter, as the case may be, and thereupon 10he shall be liable to be punished as if he had been convictedon an indictment for murder or manslaughter, as the case may be.(4) A person sentenced to death on conviction on indictmentfor an offence of genocide shall be dealt with in like manner as persons convicted on indictment for murder. 15(5) Proceedings for an offence of genocide shall not be instituted except by or with the consent of the Attorney General.(6) A court of quarter sessions shall not have jurisdiction to try any person charged with an offence of genocide.[(7) An enactment passed after the commencement of this Act 20shall not be construed as repealing, suspending or excluding thepreceding provisions of this section, in whole or in part, unlessthe enactment contains an express provision to that effect, norshall any prerogative of the Crown be taken as authorising orjustifying any act constituting an offence of genocide.] 252. The provisions of the Naval Discipline Act, the Army Actand the Air Force Act specified in the first column of the second schedule to this Act (which provide for the punishment of personssubject to those Acts for offences against the ordinary law ofEngland) shall extend to offences of genocide and accordingly 30shall have effect subject to the modifications specified in thesecond column of that Schedule; and any reference in thoseamendments to an offence of genocide shall be construed as including a reference to any act which, if committed in England,would be an offence of genocide. 353. (1) The Extradition Act, 1870, shall be construed as ifthe list of extradition crimes in the First Schedule to that Actincluded any offence of genocide and any attempt or conspiracyto commit such an offence or any direct and public incitement to commit such an offence. 40(2) For the purposes of paragraph (1) of section three, sectionseven and section nine of the Extradition Act, 1870 (which contain provisions protecting persons from extradition for offences of a political character), no offence which, if committed in
1 &amp; 2 Eliz. 2Genocide Convention3England, would be an offence of genocide shall be regarded a.d. 1953as an offence of a political character; and, for the purposes ofsection twenty-four of &quot;the Extradition Act, 1870, and section five of the Extradition Act, 1873 (which provide for the taking5 of evidence in the United Kingdom for the purposes of foreigncriminal proceedings), proceedings in respect of any such offenceas aforesaid shall not be regarded as a criminal matter of apolitical character.4. (1) This Act may be cited as the Genocide Convention short title,10 Act, 1953. extent and&apos;commence-(2) Section one of this Act shall not extend to Northern ment.Ireland.(3) Section three of this Act may be cited together with theExtradition Acts, 1870 to 1935, as the Extradition Acts, 187015 to 1953.(4) This Act shall come into operation on the dayof , nineteen hundred and fifty-three.
Genocide ConventionI &amp; 2 Eliz. 2a.d. 1953 schedules first SCHEDULEArticle II of the Genocide convention in the present Convention, genocide means any of the followingacts, committed with intent to destroy in whole or in part a national,  5ethnical, racial or religious group, as such: (a) Killing members of the group;(b) Causing serious bodily or mental harm to members of thegroup;(c) Deliberately inflicting on the group conditions of life calculated 10to bring about its physical destruction in whole or in part;(d) Imposing measures intended to prevent birth within thegroup;(e) Forcibly transferring children of the group to another group.SECOND SCHEDULEAmendments to the Naval Discipline Act, theArmy Act, and Air Force Act15Section forty-five of theNaval Discipline Act.Section forty-six of theNaval Discipline Act.Section forty-one of theArmy Act and sectionforty-one of the AirForce Act.Section fifty-seven of theArmy Act and sectionfifty-seven of the AirForce Act.After the words &quot; Every person subject tothis Act who shall be guilty of murdershall suffer death &quot; there shall be inserted 20the words &quot; If he shall be guilty of an offenceof genocide consisting of the killing ofany person, he shall suffer death:If he shall be guilty of any other 25offence of genocide, he shall sufferimprisonment exceeding two years or imprisonment   not   exceeding   twoyears &quot;.At the end of the section there shall be 30inserted the words &apos;&quot; Provided that an offender shall notbe tried and punished under this Actfor an offence of genocide committed in the United Kingdom &quot;. 35After paragraph (2) of each section there shallbe inserted the following paragraphs &quot; (2A) If he is convicted of an offenceof genocide, consisting of thekilling of any person, he shall 40suffer death; and(2B) If he is convicted of any otheroffence of genocide, be liable to suffer imprisonment;   and &quot;.In the proviso to each section after the word 45&quot; murder&quot;,  in  each  place  where  itoccurs, there shall be inserted the words&quot; an offence of genocide &quot;.In subsection (1) and in subsection (2) ofeach section after the word &quot; murder &quot; 50there shall be inserted the words &quot; or foran offence of genocide &quot;.
CONFIDENTIALGenocide ConventionDRAFTof aBILLTo enable effect to be given to the Con-vention on the Prevention and Punish-ment of the Crime of Genocide.CCLXXXIX-J (3)21th March, 195339-3(77789)

</content>
</cab>
