<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/62/0 images: 63-68</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1953SECRETCopy No.8C. (53) 21024th July, 1953CABINETPROVISIONAL LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME:  1953-54 session the Future Legislation Committee have examined the proposals of Depart-ments for legislation in the 1953-54 Session and have invited me to submit for the cabinet&apos;s approval the provisional programme embodied in the annexed lists, inwhich Bills have been classified as follows:  A. Bills which must be enacted by Christmas, 1953.B. Bills which must be enacted by Easter, 1954.C. Bills which must be enacted before the 1954 Summer Recess.D. Other Bills which should be enacted during the Session (including bills to replace emergency powers).E. Bills unlikely to be introduced except on presentation of a special case.F. Bills suitable for Private Members.Within each list the Bills are shown in alphabetical order (except that in List the Bills to replace emergency powers are grouped together at the end of the list).Consolidation Bills are not included.2. I feel that I must ask my colleagues to refrain from making public pro-mi ses of legislation on the strength of the inclusion of any subject in whateverprovisional programme may be approved by the Cabinet. Authority to make suchpromises should continue to be sought in respect of each proposed measure in thenormal way.The Programme Generally3. The provisional programme has been drawn up with due regard to theimportance of relaxing, so far as possible, the strain on Members of the House ofCommons. Apart from the Housing Bills (D (15) and (16)), it contains fewmeasures likely to engender serious controversy between the Parties but consistsrather of a number of useful measures of a practical character. It is a dull pro-gramme; the keynote could be &quot;consolidation.&quot;The Programme in the House of Lords4. The following measures seem likely to be ready for introduction in theHouse of Lords at the opening of the Session: -Charitable Trusts-D (2).Food and Drugs-D (27).Food and Drugs (Scotland)-D (28).Patents and Designs (Crown Use)-D (29).Licensing (Canteens)-D (30).National Art Collections D (11).National Museum of Antiquities (Scotland) D (12);It would also be the intention that the proposed Road Traffic Bill (D (17)) shouldbe introduced in the House of Lords as early as possible in the Session. On this basis the House of Lords should find themselves well supplied with business fromthe outset.Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal44563b
The Programme in the House of Commons5. The principal legislation to be taken in the House of Commons after the debate on the Address will be the Housing Bills. For the rest, time in the Houseof Commons before Christmas can be occupied with the Navy, Army and AirForce Reserves Bill (C (7)) (including the Committee Stage, which will have tobe taken on the Floor of the House); Category A Bills; those Bills to replaceemergency powers which are not to be introduced in the House of Lords; and anyother Bills from Lists B-D inclusive which may be ready and for which time maybe available. Although the Navy, Army and Air Force Reserves Bill does not need to become law until midsummer 1954, it will be convenient to take it at aboutthe same time as the debate on the affirmative resolution in respect of the proposed national Service Order in Council which is required to take effect before31st December, 1953.6. Two of next Session&apos;s major measures will be the responsibility of theMinister of Housing the Housing Bill and the Town and Country Planning Bill(D (22)). It is, as the Cabinet will be aware, the intention to proceed with theHousing Bill immediately after the Debate on the Address, in which case progress with the Town and Country Planning Bill will have to be deferred until ratherlater in the Session. It is important that at least one of the other proposed majormeasures the Leasehold Bill (D (8)) or the Safety in Mines and Quarries Bill(D (19)) should, if possible, secure a Second Reading before Christmas. TheFuture Legislation Committee agreed to invite the Home Secretary and the Ministerof Fuel and Power to expedite the preparation of these Bills accordingly.conclusion. On the Committee^ behalf I invite the Cabinet to approve the provisionallegislative programme for the 1953-54 Session outlined in the lists annexed to thismemorandum.H. C.Gwydyr   House, S.W.I,23rd July, 1953.ANNEXProvisional Legislative Programme 1953-54 SessionA. Bills which must be enacted by Christmas 1953(1) Cinematograph Film Production [Special Loans) (Amendment)To extend the powers of the National Film Finance Corporation for afurther period.(2) Expiring Laws Continuance(3) Post Office and Telegraph (Money)(4) Public Works LoansB.-Bills which must be enacted by Easter 1954(1) Armed Forces (Housing Loans)To increase the sums available under the Armed Forces (Housing Loans)Act, 1949, to finance the provision of married quarters for theServices.(2) Libya (Financial Agreement)To give effect to a financial agreement with Libya.(3) Overseas Resources Development Acts (Amendment)(a) To extinguish the Overseas Food Corporation as a United Kingdomstatutory body and transfer its assets to a Tanganyikan organi-sation.(b) To reduce the Colonial Development Corporation^ liability to repay capital.
C. Bills which must be enacted before the 1954 Summer Recess(1) Agriculture (Miscellaneous Provisions)To deal with:  (a) lime subsidy;(b) land drainage and water supply grants;(c) agricultural land tribunals under the Agriculture Act, 1947;id) collection and processing of waste food;(e) control and trapping of rabbits;(/) contracts between seed merchants and farmers;ig) sugar beet levy for research and education;(h) imports of diseased bees;ii) carriage of animals by air under the Diseases of Animals Act;(/) amendment of the Agricultural Wages (Regulation) (Scotland)Acts.((e) and if) would be suitable subjects for Private Members&apos; Bills andwould be included in the proposed Government Bill only if not adoptedby Private Members (See List F).)(2) Army and Air Force (Annual)This will be the normal Bill and will not implement recommendationsof the Select Committee.(3) Cotton (Centralised Buying) (Amendment)If developments necessitate a Bill.(4) Development of InventionsTo extend the period during which the National Research development corporation can borrow from Government funds and to effectcertain minor amendments to the Act of 1948.(5) Finance(6) Isle of Man (Customs)(7) Navy,. Army and Air Force reserves to define the liability to recall in a major emergency of NationalService and Class Z and G Reservists.D. Other Bills which should be enacted during the Session(1) Air Corporations (Borrowing and Pensions)To. increase, the statutory limit on borrowing by B.E.A. and B.O.A.C.and to permit pensioning of their Chairmen.(2) Charitable TrustsTo give effect to the recommendations^ in Chapter 12 of the Report ofthe Nathan Committee on Charitable Trusts.(3) Electricity (Scotland)To transfer Ministerial responsibility for electricity supplies in Southernc. Scotland from the Minister of Fuel and Power to the Secretary ofState; im: Scotland;, &amp;e.(4) Hill Farming (Amendment)To enable grants to be paid in respect of service cottages, under the HillFarming Act.(5) Industrial Court (Amendment)To provide, a* pension for the President of the Industrial Court.(6) Judges&apos; Clerks&apos; pensions to provide pensions for Judges&apos; Clerks.(7) Judges&apos; Salaries.To improve Judges&apos; emoluments.(8)&apos;- Leasehold44563 b 2
(9) Long Leases (Scotland)To effect comprehensive leasehold reform.(10) Local Government (Exchequer Equalisation Grant) (Scotland)To revise the Scottish grant arrangements.(11) National Art CollectionsTo separate the National and Tate Galleries and to regulate transfers ofpictures between the two institutions and to deal with powersof transfer, lending and sale.(12) National Museum of Antiquities (Scotland)To give effect to the principal recommendations of the Philip Committee.(13) Night BakingTo carry out the proposals in the Rees Report.(14) Pneumoconiosis and ByssinosisTo empower the Minister to make a benefit scheme for people partiallydisabled by these diseases.(15) Repairs and Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions)(16) Repairs and Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) (Scotland)To deal with rent restriction and slum clearance.(17) Road traffic to include provisions designed to improve safety on the roads, &amp;c.(18) Royal Irish Constabulary pensions to improve the pensions of certain categories of widows of membersof the Royal Irish Constabularies.(19) Safety in Mines and QuarriesTo reform the law relating to safety in mines and quarries.(20) telegraph to provide for an increase in the telegraph tariff and some modificationto the legislation about telegraph facilities.(21) [TelevisionIf developments necessitate a Bill.](22) Town and Country Planning(23) Town and Country Planning (Scotland)To amend the financial provisions of the Town and Country PlanningActs, 1947.(24) [West Africem FederationIf developments necessitate a Bill.]Bills to replace emergency powers[Note.-It is desirable that as many as possible of these Bills should beintroduced before the debates on the renewal of emergency powers due tobe held in November.](25) Currency and Bank Notes.To replace two of the Defence (Finance) Regulations.(26) Exchange control to replace one of the Defence (Finance) Regulations.(27) Food and DrugsTo provide protection against the use in food of injurious chemicalsubstances and to replace Defence Regulations.(28) Food and Drugs (Scotland)An amending and consolidating Bill which will include similar provisions to those in the English Bill.
(29) Patents and Designs (Crown Use) ,^ ;To replace certain of the Defence (Patents, Trade-Marks, &amp;c.) Regula-tions and some of the powers given by Section 49 of the PatentsAct, 1949, and paragraph 4 of the First Schedule to the RegisteredDesigns Act, 1949.(30) Licensing (Canteens)To enable local licensing authorities to authorise the sale of intoxicantsin canteens provided for seamen in substitution for the wider pro-vision of Defence Regulation 60AA, which enables Ministers toauthorise the sale of intoxicants in canteens for seamen and warworkers.(31) Transport Undertakings (Control of Charges)To regulate the control of charges by tram, trolley vehicles andomnibus undertakings and dock and harbour authorities and to clarify the position arising from the rates relief under the LocalGovernment Act of 1929. Bills unlikely to be introduced except on presentation of a special case(1) Adoption of Children.(2) Aircraft Production.(3) Aircraft (Recording of Rights).(4) Atomic Energy.(5) Betting, Lotteries and Gaming.(6) Borrowing.(7) British Films Production Fund.(8) British Museum.(9) Cereals.(10) Civil Defence.(11) Closing Hours of Shops.(12) Cocos Islands (Transfer).(13) Criminal Justice Administration (Lancashire).(14) Dentists.(15) Education (Scotland).(16) Employment of Children.(17) Fee-charging Employment Agencies. &apos;(18) Friendly Societies.(19) Geneva Conventions.(20) Genocide Convention.(21) German Conventions.(22) House of Commons (Disqualification).(23) Imperial War Museum.(24) Indian Pensions.(25) Land Drainage (Scotland).(26) Law Reform.(27) Local Government (Public Order) (Scotland).(28) Local Land Charges.(29) Maritime Conventions.(30) Merchant Shipping.(31) Milk in Schools.(32) National Health (Committee of Enquiry).(33) National Health (Proprietary Medicines).(34) Oil Pollution.(35) Old Metal (Sale).(36) Petroleum (Amendment).
(37) Rating (Gas Boards).(38) Police (Negotiating Machinery and Representative Organisations).(39) Representation of the People.(40) Savings Bank.(41) Teachers&apos; Superannuation.(42) Tithe.(43) Town Development.(44) Trustees.(45) Weights and Measures. Bills suitable for Private Members(1) Coroners (Fees and Allowances)To revoke the present inadequate scale of Coroners&apos; fees and to enablethe Secretary of State to prescribe a more appropriate scale.(2) Forcible entry to regulate the powers of entry of gas and electricity inspectors.(3) Hire Purchase \To increase the value limits under the Hire Purchase Act, 1938.(4) JurorsTo enable the amount of payment for jury service to be fixed by regulation instead of by Statute.(5) Licensing Hours (Airports)To relax the permitted hours for the sale of intoxicating liquors atinternational airports.(6) Local GovernmentTo enact some of the unanimous recommendations of the LocalGovernment Man-Power Committee on Land.(7) Rabbits (Control)To strengthen the existing powers for the control and trapping of rabbits.[Might be included in the Agriculture (Miscellaneous Provisions)Bill see Group C](8) Seeds (Contracts)To safeguard contracts between seed merchants and farmers where therehas been failure to comply with the obligation to give the purchasera statutory statement. [Might be included in the Agriculture(Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill see Group C](9) Wild Birds (Protection)To amend the law relating to the protection of wild birds and then eggs.

</content>
</cab>
