<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/62/0 images: 73-74</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.(53) 213COPY NO.28TH JULY, 1953CABINETJAPAN AND THE GENERAL AGEEMENT on tariffs AND trade memorandum by the Commonwealth secretary as I shall be in Rhodesia when this subject is taken, it may be useful if I circulate my appreciation of the probable Commonwealth reactions to theproposals.2,        The papers which have been before the Ministerial Committee onTariff Policy on Japan set out in admirable detail all the trade the Common-wealth countries do with Japan.    This trade is not only important in itself,but steady large-scale buying by Japan of Commonwealth raw materials helpsto keep up the world price.    All Commonwealth countries have a common interest in maintaining these sales;  but it does not follow that they all feelalike as regards Japan or would adopt the same policy towards her,3. Whether Japan is admitted to the General Agreement on Tariffs andTrade (G.A.T.T.) or not the Asiatic countries will play their hand in their own way. Pakistan will continue to do bilateral deals on cotton, as it is the only way she can sell a large part of her cotton crop. India will support anotherAsiatic country on principle, but will adapt her practice to suit her convenience.Nehru is an adept at this form of inconsistency. India is afraid of japanese competition in cotton goods and would protect her own textile industry.4.        Australia and New Zealand will do their best to maintain their sales of wool and other commodities;  but Japan has got to buy the wool and probably the barley and some other things anyhow.    Both countries will take moreJapanese goods, if that is the only way they can get paid for their wool, etc.But these countries will certainly protect their own secondary industries against japan.    If Japan became a member of the G.A.T.T, and Australia and NewZealand did not reserve the right to discriminate against Japan under Article 35,they would have to put up their tariffs against all the world in order to keepJapanese goods out, and this would hit United Kingdom exports very badly,5.        Australian and New Zealand sentiment as regards Japan is quite different from that of the Asiatic countries.    Wartime dislike and fear of Japanhave persisted.    For example, Mr. Menzies has repeatedly told us that a defence pact which included Japan would be politically impossible in Australia.I think both countries would wish to keep Japan out of the G. A, T.T. and wouldbe prepared to claim the benefit of Article 35, unless we took a different line.If the United Kingdom pressed for the admission of Japan into the G.A. T.T.without claiming the benefit of Article 35, I. think Australia and New Zealandmight follow suit;  but they would do little to help United Kingdom industries,saying that we had brought this trouble upon ourselves.
6.        I would guess that South Africa would be opposed to bringing Japaninto the G. A. T. T. and would keep her own freedom of action.7.        Canada would be in favour of bringing Japan in, because this is in line with her general policy and with her desire to do nothing which would give theUnited States an excuse for not admitting Canadian goods.8.        On the more general issue, I do not believe that Article 23 would be effective.    We could not act effectively without the agreement of other countries,who would have no particular interest in giving us that permission;  and, even ifwe got their agreement, it would probably be too late, as the mischief would havebeen done.9.        Our domestic political difficulties in supporting the entry of Japan intothe G.A.T.T. are so obvious that I need not stress them.    I would, however,like to emphasise one aspect.    A considerable section of our Party continueto press us to denounce the G. A.T.T. altogether.    We have got to resist this and carry our Party with us on the line that unilateral denunciation would be wrong and that we must act in concert with the Commonwealth.    Our next step should be to try and get agreement on the abrogation of the no-new-preferencerule, which all the Commonwealth have agreed to support.    It would be verydifficult to get the Party to accept our continuing membership of the G.A. T.T. ,if at the same time we ask them to swallow the unqualified admission of Japan.I think, too, that we should risk alienating the support of Australia and NewZealand over the no-new-preference rule.10.       For all these reasons I am in favour of playing for time;  or, if wecannot get time, of saying that we must reserve our rights under Article 35.SWINTONCommonwealth Relations Office, S. W.l.24TH JULY, 1953.-2-

</content>
</cab>
