<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/62/0 images: 76-77</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJEST Y&apos;S GOVERNMENT)confidential.(53) 215 COPY NO. ^2STH JULY, 19533ABINETJAPAN AND THE GENERAL AGREEMENT on tariffs AND TRADENote by the Chancellor of the exchequer wish to draw the attention of my colleagues to the attached notes onthis subject which have been prepared by the Economic Secretary.    These areonly an outline, and I will supplement them orally when the matter is discussed in Cabinet.R.A.B.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.27TH JULY, 1953.JAPAN AND THE GENERAL AGREEMENT on tariffs AND TRADENotes by the Economic Secretary, TreasuryThere are obviously great disadvantages both economic and politicalinvolved in the admission of Japan to the General Agreement on Tariffs andTrade (G.A.T.T.).   A strengthening of Japanese competition, combined with the probability of increased tariffs over a wide area, will present certain of our industries, particularly cotton, with most serious problems.    The industries themselves are well aware of this and their fear of Japanese entry into theG.A.T.T., based on the economic dangers, is highly charged with emotionalreaction to Japan past and present.2.        Clearly, therefore, what would serve our interest best would be ifJapan remained outside the G.A.T.T.    This however is most unlikely.    Japan will enter the G.A. T.T. in the end and the main question open to us is how wecan postpone and minimise the damage that we are liable to suffer thereby.3.        It is also clear that any steps we take to impose special conditionsupon Japan&apos;s entry will, of themselves, cause us considerable difficulties.What is most important is to avoid a situation where we get the worst of bothworlds, i. e. where we insist on a safeguard which causes us ill-will all roundwithout, in practice, being effective.
4.        What we fear is low-priced Japanese competition and what we are seek-ing is protection against this competition.    It is clear that we cannot for longdefend such protection on balance of payments grounds.    It is also clear that wecannot in the long run deny to other Commonwealth countries the right to buyJapanese goods if they want to do so.5.        Continued opposition to Japanese entry has the following disadvantages(i)    It is obviously inconsistent with our whole approach to theproblems of trade and payments and in particular to ouremphasis on &quot;good creditor&quot; policies.    (The ratio betweenJapanese and United Kingdom wages is roughly the sameas the ratio between United Kingdom and United Stages wages.)(ii)    The political consequences for our position in the Far Eastand our relations with the U.S.A. are serious.(iii)    We shall not have the united support of the commonwealth and the Colonial territories and, in many cases, we shallbe regarded as attempting to maintain the position of our industries at the expense of living standards in overseasCommonwealth territories.6.        The immediate problem is the attitude to be taken in September.Obviously, the best thing would be if we could avoid showing our hand at all.This must be our first objective.    But we may be forced to show our hand if adecision is required on the Report of the Inter-Sessional Committee.7.        The difference between our attitude and that of the Inter-SessionalCommittee is in effect that, while we wish to retain the right to take anyprotective measures  we would like against disruptive competition from Japan,the Inter-Sessional Committee&apos;s Report would make such action subject to theapproval of the G.A.T.T.8.        If we insist on our point of view, we shall be in a minority.    Japan will then be admitted to the G. A. T. T. and we shall be in the position ofdiscriminating specially against her.    But we shall not be able to maintain this position for long, because consumers in both the independent commonwealth and the Colonies will demand the right to buy Japanese goods.    Therefore, weshall, at the cost of ill-will all round and possibly of jeopardising our majorplans for the future of trade and payments, have achieved a safeguard of only alimited and temporary character.9.        On the other hand, by accepting the Inter-Sessional Committee^ Report,we shall avoid these major political and economic difficulties and we shall havea safeguard which, though limited, is likely to be more enduring and more effective, and in which we shall have the support of other countries threatened by disruptive competition.10.       Whatever we do, we shall be subject to much criticism in the UnitedKingdom.    But we shall be able to make it plain that we have done nothing to welcome the Japanese into the G. A. T. T.    We shall on the other hand have recognised the facts of life and taken the step which, in practice, is likely to be most effective in continuing to prevent disruptive Japanese competition in our commonwealth markets.    We obviously have no chance of preventing any other form of competition so long as we are adhering to an international body such asG.A.T.T. designed to promote the free flow of trade.27TH JULY, 1953 R.M.-2-

</content>
</cab>
