<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/62/0 images: 144-146</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos; Printed for the Cabinet.  August 1953SECRET Copy No.   67C. (53) 23012th August, 1953CABINETWHITE PAPER ON HOUSING policy memorandum by the Minister of works the Minister of Housing and Local Government asks for comments on hisdraft White Paper on Housing Policy (C. (53) 219).2. We must allow rents to rise. But in doing so we hazard the electoraladvantage of reaching the target of 300,000 new houses. So one object of the granddesign is to strike the imagination as a fine piece of constructive policy and thusreduce the unpopularity of the increase in rents. This strategy could be carried further by bringing to the front of the White Paper certain aspects of general interest.These are:  (1) An advance towards a Property-Owning Democracy.(2) The advantage of rehousing near the amenities which exist in the cities and towns.(3) A long-term assurance of high employment in the building industry.A Property-Owning Democracy3. Our supporters would probably like to see more definite action to secure an increase in house-ownership. In paragraph 80 of the draft mention is made ofthe terms on which money can be borrowed for the purchase of houses. It is worth considering whether more could be done to help.Some would-be purchasers of new houses are deterred by the cost of repairs.A scheme of-insurance to spread the cost of major repairs might be devised. TheChurch does this for parsons.Elderly people, many of them living on the old age pension, who own andoccupy a small house are especially in need of help with repairs. It would be agreat pity if the number of owner-occupiers in this category were to diminish.Possibly more could be done by way of tax-reliefs for maintenance of houses.Making the best use of amenities in the centre of cities4. Slum clearance, the conversion of large houses and the reconditioning ofdilapidated houses carry with them the popular advantage of keeping familieswhere they want to be near the schools, shops, cinemas, public houses and churcheswhich they have known all their lives. New housing estates, which call for a greatdeal of building besides the houses, become very expensive in materials and labour,and are often bad for the character of the rehoused, who lose the morality whichgrows with an established community.5. The White Paper might make more of the fact that dispersal can becarried too far. Agriculturalists would be glad to see less farm land built over.The more that fares increase the less a family wants to live a long way from estab-lished shops and places of entertainment and worship. Indeed a decision to buildround an existing complex of traditions and amenities, where this is at all reason-able, rather than to root up families and transfer them to new estates would pleaseall but the most bloodless planners.A long-term assurance of high employment in the building industry.   In this industry confidence is a particularly delicate plant because the jobin progress is always coming to an end.  The Minister of Housing has had a great44671
success with his slogan &quot; Build as fast as you can.&quot; But now that he has to take measures to level off the rate of new house-building at 300,000 a year there is some anxiety that the boom is over. Of course, while there is so much work waiting tobe done on other building programmes, there is no foundation for this anxiety.But it exists, and unless scotched, productivity will fall.It is important therefore that the White Paper should convince builders that,whatever may be the demand for other types of building, the new and imaginativehousing policy will be there to provide all the work that can be done for years ahead. We could go further and stress that a reason for asking Local Authoritiesto prepare programmes of slum clearance is to have ready plans to meet any signsof unemployment in building. Some such assurance that more work has been planned than can be carried out immediately is necessary to persuade the industryto get rid of out-of-date practices and to improve management. It would be agreat advantage if the White Paper set out both the benefit conferred on theindustry by the grand design and the obligation which the industry should assumeto put its house in order.The Load on the Building Industry imposed by the Grand Design7. The Minister of Housing and I did not have an opportunity to consider this in detail. Just as it is important to reassure the building industry about thefuture volume of work so it is to reassure the public that the new housing policy will not gobble up labour and materials needed for other programmes. In particularwe shall be expected to show that the recent expansion in industrial building willnot be checked.8. It would seem therefore that the White Paper should state the limit which,under present conditions, the new policy should make upon building resources.A convenient maximum might be the man-power at present employed in housingrepairs plus the 300,000 men needed to build 300,000 houses a year. (At present there are 308,000 men on new house-building which is running above 300,000houses a year.) The grand design would eat into these 300,000 men so that either the number of new houses must come down or the maximum resources proposed above would be passed. As things are to-day it would soon be passed for thefollowing reasons:  (1) The volume of repairs will rise as soon as it is known that to qualify foran increased rent landlords must have spent a certain sum after1st January, 1953.(2) The publication of the White Paper should iead to an increase in conversionsand reconditioning.(3) Distinct from the grand design and more serious in effect, the rate of newhouse-building cannot immediately be pulled back to 300,000 a year (i.e.,300,000 men employed). This overshooting the mark is the price ofsuccess. The Minister is taking administrative action to reduce LocalAuthority starts next year, but it is quite likely that these reductionswill be more than made up by the increase in private enterprise buildingnow expanding fast.9. It looks therefore as if further action is needed to make room for theincrease in repairs, conversions and private enterprise building, all of which we wish to take place. The obvious way to discourage building by Local authorities is to reduce the housing subsidies. This, if done in isolation, would be unpopular.But if included in the White Paper it might be accepted as a necessary move toprotect other building programmes and to carry out the grand design.(A difficulty arises from the fact that private enterprise building is so largelyconcentrated in the southern half of England. Special steps might have to betaken to keep up the rate of council building in the north of England and Wales.)The Test of Good and Tenantable Repair10. There is said to be a well-understood legal definition Of this test. But thehousewives, not the lawyers, will be in command of our proposals, and their con-ception Of a satisfactory house, like the conception of subsistence, is continuallyrising.The trouble will come from comparing &quot; good and tenantable repair &quot; with &quot; fit for human habitation.&quot; In paragraph 57 of the draft White Paper reference ismade to the Report on Standards of Housing Fitness.  In paragraph 23 of that
report a definition is given of &quot; fit for human habitation.&quot; This definition is not far from nonsense since it can be interpreted in as many ways as there are house-holders, but the fact remains that it gives an impression of modest comfort, and is sufficiently high to condemn many cottages where contented families now live.What then will be the acceptable definition of &quot; good and tenantable repair,&quot; whichis to be so far superior to &quot; fit for human habitation &quot; as to qualify for an increasein rent? It must be such that very large numbers of houses and flats, to whichrepairs should be done but will not be until the owners receive an increase in rent,will never rise above the category of &quot; fit for human habitation &quot; and thereforenever qualify for an increase in rent. It cannot be supposed that Local authorities will have the money or the desire to take over all these houses. It will, I think, beasked whether it is wise to spend much money on very bad property, when thereare still houses in reasonable repair, which can be saved by prompt action from falling into the category of unfit for human habitation.11. The test of good and tenantable repair should therefore be re-examined. Itwould be of interest to know how it would be defined in Scotland; if on a lowstandard there may well be organised rent strikes when the 40 per cent, increase isclapped on; if on a high standard there may well be very few houses that qualify,so that the main problem would remain untouched.Perhaps this test could be abandoned altogether and a definition of a minimum&quot; fit for human habitation &quot; be adopted together with a continuing (not a once-for-allas in the draft White Paper) obligation to spend all or part of the rent increase on repairs for a number of years. If during the period a house reached a standardsuch as that described as &quot; satisfactory &quot; in paragraph 17 of the Report on standards of Fitness referred to above then the obligation to spend a minimum sum on repairs would cease.Reduction in the limits of rateable value which govern the number of rent-restrictedhouses12. Rents are restricted to-day in respect of houses in London, the provinces and Scotland having a rateable value up to  100,  75 and  90 respectively. TheMinister of Health told the Sub-Committee on Housing Policy that rather than raisethe rents of the houses now controlled, he would prefer to lower these limits ofrateable value and set houses free from rent restriction. The Minister of Housingpointed out that there were comparatively few houses in the top brackets of therateable values now restricted. None the less I think we should make a move towards freedom from control which must be our ultimate object for all houses.I suggest, therefore, that in the White Paper a start should be made by reducingthe limits by some such figure as 25 per cent.War-time temporary bungalows13. Up and down the country there are mouldering groups of these temporarystructures, for which a policy of scrap-and-build is wanted, and this might finda place in the White Paper.Summary14. (1) Prominence in the White Paper might be given to paragraphs dealingwith- -(a) an advance towards a Property-Owning Democracy.(b) The advantage of rehousing near the amenities which exist in the citiesand towns.(c) A long-term assurance of high employment in the building industry.(2) Consideration should be given to fixing the maximum load which thegrand design should put on the resources of the building industry.(3) The test of &quot; good and tenantable repair &quot; should be looked at again;a simpler test of &quot; fit for human habitation &quot; might be more practical.(4) Some reduction might be made in the rateable valuations which now set the upper limit to the number of houses controlled.(5) A policy of scrap-and-build for war-time bungalows might find a place inthe White Paper.D. E.Ministry of Works, S.E.1,11th August, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
