<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/57/0 images: 89-90</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Copy No. 63CABINETCOMMON land memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and FisheriesAt their meeting on 24th October the Home Affairs Committee considered amemorandum on common land (H.A. (52) 133) and invited me to bring before theCabinet proposals for the establishment of a Royal Commission to enquire intothe need to amend the law relating to such land (H.A. (52) 28th Meeting, Item 3 [i]).The problem. There are something like 2 million acres of common land in England andWales. Some of this has value mainly as open space, but if the law allowed muchmore could be put to better agricultural use without detriment to amenity.3. 20,000 acres were requisitioned and cultivated during the war. Half thisacreage has been released, and much of it is already reverting to scrub.4. 3,000 acres are being bought under compulsory powers. The remaining7,000 acres will be kept under requisition as long as emergency powers exist but will then also have to be released.5. It is clear that a thorough examination of this complicated common landproblem in all its aspects is required. A policy can then be devised which will take account of the interests of the commoners and owners of the soil, the value of theland for recreation, housing and other public purposes, and the need in the national interest for making the fullest productive use of all our land, due regard being paidto modern planning requirements.6. My colleagues on the Home Affairs Committee considered it desirable thatthis examination should be conducted by a Royal Commission because of the greatcomplexity of the existing law and the variety of interests concerned. These includethe agricultural interests, the interests of those with common rights, and the interestsof rural and urban amenity.conclusion. I seek the approval of the Cabinet to the establishment of a RoyalCommission with the following terms of reference which I have discussed with theLord Chancellor:  &quot; (i) To consider how better use can be made of common land in Englandand Wales for food and timber production, or for enjoyment by thepublic for air and exercise, or for any other purpose in the publicinterest. For this purpose the term &quot;common land&quot; includes any land subiect to be inclosed under the Inclosure Acts, 1845-82, or subject to the provisions of the Metropolitan Commons Acts, 1866-98,and any town or village green, and any allotment set out as a fuelallotment or a field garden allotment under any Inclosure Act, and theNew Forest, and the Forest of Dean.confidential (52) 4261st December, 195243296Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1952
(ii) To recommend what steps should be talcen to promote the better use ofsuch land for the purposes aforesaid, and what provision should bemade in the interests of commoners, owners of the soil or any other persons who may be affected thereby.(hi) To report what additions to or changes in the law are necessary or desirableto give effect to the recommendations.&quot;8. Chairman. I would suggest that the Chairman should either be a prominent public man whose name would carry confidence, or a lawyer of con-siderable standing in view of the complex legal questions that will arise in thecourse of the inquiry. If the Chairman were not himself a prominent lawyer, Ishould propose that such a person should be included among the members. TheCommission should not, I think, exceed seven in all and should be composed of independent persons rather than representatives of any sectional interest or political opinion.T. L. D.Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries, S.W. 1,1st December, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
