<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/57/0 images: 216-219</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1952CONFIDENTIAL Copy No.    gC. (52) 44818th December, 1952CABINETSUDANMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs on 22nd October I told the House of Commons that Her Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment had informed the Governor-General of the Sudan that they approved, withsome small amendments, the draft Self-Government Statute for the Sudan whichhe had submitted to the British and Egyptian Governments as co-domini, and Iadded that Her Majesty&apos;s Government and the Governor-General would no doubtwish to consider any views which the Egyptian Government might express uponthe draft Statute. The Egyptian Government, who had, of course, been informed of our approval of the draft Statute, produced their views on 2nd November, six days before the Governor-General was in theory entitled to promulgate the Statute.2. Meanwhile, the Egyptian Government had made agreements with repre-sentatives of some of the Sudanese political parties. The first of these agreementswas negotiated by the Egyptian Government with the Socialist RepublicanParty in the Sudan (though it was only signed on 3rd November). The secondwas negotiated with the Umma, or pro-independence, Party led by Sir Saved AbdelRahman el Mahdi, and signed on 29th October. The third agreement, which canfor practical purposes be ignored, was with the pro-Egyptian National Party andwas only signed on 5th December. It has since become clear that none of the sudanese Parties, and least of all the Mahdi himself, had fully grasped the implications-tions of the agreements which they had signed; in any case, these agreementsdiffered from one another in certain respects, and each of them in turn differed from the Note handed by the Egyptian Government to Her Majesty&apos;s ambassador at Cairo on 2nd November which purported to contain the Egyptian views. this note itself was far too loosely drafted to constitute an acceptable working docu-ment; nevertheless, it has been upon the basis of the proposals which it containedthat we have had to negotiate with the Egyptian Government. My colleagues willunderstand that it has not been an easy task to try to reconcile our own views andthose of the Governor-General in Khartoum, who must take account of the senti-ments not only of the Sudanese political parties in the North but also of the South(whose representatives have signed no agreement with Egypt), with the impreciseand frequently impractical and even self-contradictory proposals put forward tous by the Egyptian Government. We have not yet fully succeeded in this task,but we have made enough progress to make it worth while trying to summarise themain issues at present before us.3. In the first place, it must be admitted that the present Egyptian proposalsdo mark a considerable advance on the position taken by previous EgyptianGovernments in regard to the Sudan. No previous Egyptian Government was prepared to accept anything less than &quot; the unity of the Nile Vailey,&quot; which meantrecognition of the sovereignty of the King of Egypt over the Sudan. The presentEgyptian proposals on the other hand expressly state that the sovereignty of theSudan shall be reserved for the Sudanese during the transitional period until self-determination is achieved.  They expressly recognise also the right of the Sudanese43413
to exercise self-determination at the proper time and with the necessary safeguards.Meanwhile, they accept that self-government should be applied during the transitional period, and they do in fact take the draft Self-Gpvernment Statute asthe basis upon which to work. They suggest a number of amendments to thisStatute, and they contemplate in addition the conclusion of an agreement between ourselves and the Egyptian Government which would be complementary to theStatute and would in effect regulate the exercise by the Governor-General of thediscretionary powers reserved to him under the Statute.4. All this is in accordance with Egypfs legal position as a co-dominus with us, a position which we have never denied despite the unilateral abrogation of the condominium Agreement of 1899 by the Wafd Government in October 1951.Indeed, we nave always maintained the illegality of that abrogation, since it is uponthe Condominium Agreement that our own position as co-dominus rests,Moreover, whatever the vagaries of Egyptian Governments, we have to take accountof the reality that there does exist a community of interests between Egypt andthe Sudan in view, among other things, of their common dependence upon the waters of the Nile.5. Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Cairo has had a number of meetings withGeneral Neguib, to discuss the proposed Egyptian amendments to the Statute andthe principles upon which the Anglo-Egyptian Agreement should be based.Throughout these discussions, I have kept in closest touch with the Governor-General in Khartoum^ who has been consulted on every detail, and whose viewshave naturally been given great weight. Agreement with the Egyptian Governmenthas now been reached on a large number of points. I list the most important ofthese below and also the main points which are still at issue between us.Points on which Agreement with the Egyptian Government has been Reached orseems Probable(i) The principle of self-determination for the Sudan and the introduction ofself-government meanwhile.(ii) The establishment and composition of two Commissions-(a) An Election Commission to supervise the elections for the newSudanese Parliament;   it shall consist of one British, oneEgyptian, one American and one Indian (who shall be Chairman). and three Sudanese.(b) A  Commission to  advise  the  Governor-General during  the transitional period of self-government, in regard to the exerciseof certain of his discretionary powers under the new draftStatute; the Commission shall consist of one British, oneEgyptian, one Pakistani and two Sudanese.(iii) The method of appointment of the Govecnor-Generafs Commission. Wehave agreed that it shall be appointed by Egyptian decree (on the analogy of the appointment of the Governor-General), provided that this decreeis so worded that there is no doubt that the Anglo-Eg3rptian agreement is the source of authority for this appointment.(iv) The retention of the special responsibility of the Governor-General forthe public service (this is essential if we are to retain British officials. in the service).(v) The procedure for fixing the number of direct, as opposed to indirect,elections.(vi) The form of choice for the Sudanese on self-determination.  It has beenagreed that the Sudanese shall be free to choose either unity with Egyptor complete independence: the latter would not. of course debar theSudan from applying thereafter for membership of the British Common-wealth if she wished, and we shall make it clear to General Neguibthat this is our interpretation. The original&apos;Egyptian phrase referredto &quot; a Sudan completely independent of the United Kingdom, Egyptor any other country &quot;; General Neguib has agreed to omit the wordsafter &quot; independent.&quot; ^(vii) The Governor-GeneraFs powers in an emergency.   The draft statuteprovides that the Governor-General may proclaim a constitutionalemergency in two sets of circumstances: first, if the Government of
the Sudan cannot be carried on &quot; by reason of political deadlock, non-co-operation, boycott&quot; or the like; we have suggested that in such acase he should act on the advice of his Commission, on the under-standing that a satisfactory solution is reached on his responsibilityfor the South and the public services. Secondly, he may proclaim a constitutional emergency in the event of &quot; imminent financial collapseor breakdown of law and order &quot;; in this case he should be free to actand seek the advice of his Commission afterwards and a special procedure for this purpose would be laid down. The Egyptians arethinking over these suggestions.Points on which no agreement is at present in sight(i) The  Governor-General&apos;s special responsibility for the  South.    the egyptians, who profess to fear that our insistence on this point springsfrom an aim of ultimately separating the Southern Sudan from theNorth, are trying to find a formula which will conceal the fact of suchresponsibility, while we are insisting that it must be made plain. Further-:more the Egyptians are insisting that the Governor-General shall exer-cise his responsibility in accordance with the normal procedure of theCommission (see (ii) below): we are insisting that his responsibilitymust be unfettered.(ii) The powers of the Governor-GeneraPs Commission.  The Egyptians wish that the advice of the Commission shall be binding upon the Governor-General, in regard to all his discretionary powers, unless both theBritish and Egyptian Governments agree to overrule the Commissionwithin a period of one month. We are trying to limit the field in whichthe Commission shall exercise such powers to a number of matters of constitutional procedure, and to secure the exemption of the Governor-General from overriding control by the Commission in relation to his responsibility for the South and the public service, and to obtain the compromise suggested above in relation to his powers in an emergency.If we are successful on these points, I think we can accept the powerssuggested for the Commission in the remaining matters.(iii) Termination of the transitional period. The Egyptians are trying to limit the period to three years &quot; subject to the completion of Sudanisation ofthe Administration.&quot; We know that the Sudanese wish to retain Britishadvisers after self-determination: the Egyptian formula would enableEgypt to veto self-determination on the grounds that British officials were still employed in the Sudan Service, and therefore to bring pressure to bear on the Sudanese to get rid of them. We are prepared to agreethat Sudanisation should be a factor in considering the date of self-determination, but we are not prepared to accept the Egyptian formula.(iv) Submission for approval to the Sudan Parliament when elected of thequestions of the establishment and powers of the Governor-General&apos;commission and any change in the safeguards for the South. TheGovernor-General feels strongly that the Sudanese Parliament shouldbe consulted on these points before the ratification of any Anglo-Egyptian agreement, but. the Egyptians argue that these are mattersbetween the co-domini and the Governor-General and are outside thescope of the Sudanese Parliament in that they do not relate to mattersupon which the Governor-General is obliged to act upon the advice of his Sudanese Ministers.   (See paragraph 8 below.)In addition to these major points, there are a number of minor points on whichwe have reached agreement with the Egyptians, and a few minor points on whichwe have not yet reached agreement.6. If we fail to reach final agreement with the Egyptians, the effect on Anglo-Egyptian relations will be very serious. This would be particularly unfortunateat a time when we are hoping to open negotiations for a settlement of the defenceproblem. A failure might also undermine further the position of General NeguhVsGovernment in Egypt. The effect on the internal situation in the Sudan wouldprobably be bad also, since the Sudanese are expecting to be able to go ahead withtheir plans for self-government on the basis of an Anglo-Egyptian agreement, asis evident from the fact that the principal Parties in the Northern Sudan havealready come to terms with Egypt.   We should probably have to go ahead with
the promulgation of the draft self-government Statute as it stands, and holdelections; but these elections would certainly be boycotted by ail the pro-Egyptianelements in the Sudan, and it is possible that they might even be boycotted by themajority of Sudanese. At any rate, the political differences in the Sudan wouldbe deepened and the atmosphere in which self-government was introduced wouldbe worsened. We should of course have to do our best to mitigate these ill-effectsin the Sudan by making plain the points on which we had failed to reach agreementwith Egypt, and the reasons for such failure, and we should have to restate publiclyour intentions regarding self-determination. But whatever we did, there is little doubt that the orderly progress of the Sudan in the political field would suffer a severe set-back.7. We must therefore not jeopardise the chances of an agreement except formatters which we consider essential. I suggest that the first of these is the provisionof adequate safeguards for the South. Whatever the wording finally agreed upon for defining the South and as to this I think we should allow our negotiators somelatitude the Governor-General must have a special responsibility to intervenewith the Sudan Parliament if necessary in order to protect the interests of theSoutherners, and this responsibility must not be subject to the overriding advice of his Commission. If the Egyptians will not modify their present attitude, this isa point upon which we shall have to maintain our insistence, even to the point of failing to reach agreement. The second point on which we should have to be equally insistent would be the issue of whether the date of self-determination (the egyptians suggest three years hence) should be made dependent upon the com-pletion of Sudanisation of the Administration. In my view Sudanisation is a matter for the Sudanese to decide. We may in the last resort be able to agree with the egyptians as to how it should be carried out. But the extent to which it is carriedout should not in my view be the sole factor on which self-determination should depend. I think we should be on comparatively strong ground in resisting this.Otherwise the prospects for the orderly transfer of power to the Sudanese will be greatly damaged, if not ruined.S. The next important issue is the question whether the establishment and powers of the Governor-GeneraFs Commission should be submitted to the SudaneseParliament. It is here a question solely of matters which are expressly withheldby the Self-Government Statute from the competence of the Sudan Parliament, thatis to say, the Governor-GeneraFs discretionary powers. The Egyptians therefore have a case when they say that these are matters between the Governor-Generaland the co-domini. The Governor-General himself has strong views to thecontrary, which I should be reluctant to override. On the other hand, I think itcan be argued that the interposition of the Commission between the Governor-General and the co-domini does not create any change in the status of the Sudanon which we should be obliged to consult the Sudanese. They should, of course,be informed of the terms of the agreement reached between the two co-domini. on balance, therefore, I doubt whether we ought to regard this as a point on whichwe would break if it stood in the way of a settlement.recommendations.   I would ask my colleagues (a) to take note of the position now reached in our negotiations with Egypt;lb) to confirm that we should treat the retention of adequate safeguards forthe South and the elimination of the formula which makes self-determination dependent upon the completion of Sudanisation asbreaking points if necessary;(c) to say whether they agree with my conclusion that on balance the questionof submitting to the Sudanese Parliament for approval the Governor-GeneraFs Commission and the safeguards for the South (provided thatthese are in my view adequate) should not be regarded as a breaking-point if it stands in the way of a settlement.A. E.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,18th December, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
