<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/57/0 images: 235-238</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JUS DOCUMENT IS THE  PROPERTY  OF  HER BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1952SECRET Copy No.C. (52) 45531 st December, 1952CABINETBECHU AN ALAND PROTECTORATE:   BAMANGWATO SUCCESSIONMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth relations should like to give my colleagues some report on Bamangwato affairs inrecent months. My predecessor, before handing over to me, was on the point ofmaking such a report.2. About a year ago Cabinet approved the following programme submittedby Lord Ismay (C.C. (51) 10th Conclusions, Minute 5):  (1) the effective exclusion of Tshekedi Khama from the political life of the bamangwato allied with his return to the Reserve as a private personat the earliest moment consistent with the peace of the tribe and hisown safety;(2) reconciliation between the tribe and Rasebolai Khama, chief lieutenantof Tshekedi and third in adult succession to the chieftainship, and hispromotion as a prospective nominee by the tribe for the chieftain-ship; and(3) the announcement, after an appropriate interval, of the permanentexclusion of Seretse Khama from the chieftainship of the tribe as a necessary preliminary to their nomination of Rasebolai.3. That programme has been largely accomplished, although the Bamangwatohave yet to be persuaded to designate a new chief.The exclusion order against Tshekedi Khama was finally lifted in august and he has since been formally readmitted to tribal membership. His rights andliberties have thus been restored subject only to the condition that he refrains frominterference in tribal politics, which he has faithfully observed.Rasebolai and others of Tshekedi&apos;s followers have been received back into the tribe and are resuming a normal part in tribal life.Seretse Khama&apos;s permanent exclusion from the chieftainship was announced on 27th March.4. A deputation of Seretse&apos;s followers came to London in April, and was informed by Lord Salisbury that the decision was final and permanent and couldnot be reconsidered. On their return their faction openly defied government authority and in the last throw incited a riot in Serowe on 1st June, in which threeAfrican policemen lost their lives.5. Later there were encouraging signs that some of the tribe were turningtowards designation of a new chief; and in October a meeting of over 80 headmenrecommended the calling of a tribal kgotla for this purpose. The immediate result of the kgotla was disappointing, since after some support had been shown for Rasebolai a story that Seretse was bound to return gained currency andprevented any decision. The High Commissioner reports, however, that the factthat Government did not, as was generally expected, impose Rasebolai as chief has lessened suspicions of its intentions. Feeling towards the administration is better than it has been for a long time, and there is reason to hope that, thedemand for a new chief will gradually gather strength.43455 B
.6. A fuller account and analysis of the year&apos;s developments is annexed tothis memorandum.7. While a great deal has thus been done to implement the governments programme for solution of the Bamangwato chieftainship dispute, there remains the wider question of strengthening Bechuanaland^ administration and economy.Development in the past has been severely hampered by straitened resources andlatterly by heavy expenditure on Bamangwato affairs. The small government services have had a trying time for over three years. The chiefs and the leaders,of other tribes feel neglected and frustrated. A comprehensive programme ofdevelopment would act as a tonic and be evidence of Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentscare for their well-being. My Department is examining the Protectorate^ needswith this in view.SWINTON.Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W. 1,31st December, 1952.ANNEXIn Memorandum C. (51) 21 of 19th November, 1951, the commonwealth secretary outlined a policy for the Bamangwato Reserve comprising (1) the effective exclusion of Tshekedi Khama from the political life of the bamangwato allied with his return to the Reserve as a private personat the earliest moment consistent with the peace of the tribe and hisown safety;(2) reconciliation between the tribe and Rasebolai Khama, chief lieutenantof Tshekedi and third in adult succession to the chieftainship, and hispromotion as a prospective nominee by the tribe for the chieftainship;and(3) the announcement, after an appropriate interval, of the permanent exclu-sion of Seretse Khama from the chieftainship of the tribe as a necessary preliminary to their nomination of Rasebolai.This programme was approved by the Cabinet (C.C. (51) 10th Conclusions, Minute 5).2.   This Annex indicates how far the programme has been implemented.3. Lord Ismay saw Tshekedi Khama in London in November 1951. Tshekedireadily accepted the condition of his exclusion from the political life of the tribe, andHis Majesty&apos;s Governments decisions regarding him were announced by the Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations in reply to a parliamentary Question on 6th December, 1951.4. The announcement was received quietly in the Reserve, though someBamangwato leaders protested to the High Commissioner against the decision and asked to be allowed to send a deputation to London to see the Secretary of State.They were informed that the Secretary of State would not see a deputation, andthat the use of tribal funds to cover its expenses would not be permitted.5. The first step towards reconciliation of Tshekedi&apos;s followers with the bamangwato tribe was taken when, on 25th February, 1952, Rasebolai returnedwith nine followers to the Reserve. Their readmission to the tribe was accepted in kgotla by the District Commissioner acting as Native Authority. Rasebolai,who has behaved with great discretion, has since successfully re-established himself as a leading member of the tribe. In the following month the High Commissionerfelt able to allow Tshekedi to undertake his first visit to the Reserve which tookplace without incident.6. By March it had become clear that the Governments decision aboutTshekedi and the return of his leading followers had been accepted without any realopposition, but that no further progress could be made until a final decision onSeretse&apos;s future had been announced. The Commonwealth Secretary accordinglyobtained Cabinet authority (C.C. (52) 31st Conclusions, Minute 4) to endeavour to persuade Seretse that his abdication would be in the interests of his people andthat he should accept the offer of a Colonial Service post in Jamaica. Failing this the Commonwealth Secretary was authorised to announce the government&apos;s decision permanently to exclude Seretse from the chieftainship.
7. At an interview on 26th March, with the Commonwealth Secretary andLord Ismay, Seretse rejected the proposition put to him and refused to renouncehis claim to the chieftainship. On 27th March, therefore, the Governments decisionpermanently to exclude him from the chieftainship was announced in both houses of Parliament and by the Resident Commissioner in the Bamangwato Reserve. (AnOrder-in-Council, for which Cabinet approval was given C.C. (52) 54th Conclu-sions, Minute 7 was subsequently made at the end of May to give legislative effectto the decision about Seretse and to confirm Tshekedi&apos;s renunciation of claim to the chieftainship for himself and his heirs.)8. The decision on the whole received a good press in this country. InParliament the Opposition found it difficult to put much force into an attack on adecision which followed logically from their own policy when in Office and couldbe defended with their own arguments. In the Reserve the decision was peaceablybut sullenly received.9. Shortly afterwards a delegation of six members of the Bamangwato tribearrived in London to request the Secretary of State to reverse his decision. the delegation was, apart from Keaboka (the senior tribal representative and leader ofthe pro-Seretse faction), composed of comparative nonentities in the tribe. the arrival of the delegation aroused considerable interest in the press and some dis-cussion in Parliament and, though it had previously been made plain that theSecretary of State did not consider the delegation^ visit and request for an interviewjustified, Lord Salisbury decided that refusal to grant an interview would merelyarouse unnecessary criticism. After hearing the delegation at length the Secretaryof State gave them a considered answer on 28th April, rejecting their request andemphasising that the Governments decision about Seretse was final and permanent.During their visit the members of the delegation were made much of by Left-wingParliamentary and other bodies. This gave them, unfortunately, a misleading impression of feeling in the United Kingdom on the Seretse issue and encouragedthem in their subsequent defiance of the Government.10. On return to the Reserve on 21st May they began with other leaders ofthe pro-Seretse faction open resistance to the Governments authority. An attempt by the District Commissioner to announce to a meeting in Serowe the Secretaryof State&apos;s reply to the delegation was thwarted by organised interruption andhooliganism. Since it was clear that the kgotla (tribal meeting-place) was being used by a minority group deliberately to obstruct the Governments decision, theDistrict Commissioner gave orders for it to be closed. In this he had the backingof many responsible elders who were disturbed by the hooliganism and shockedby the disrespect shown by the delegation to the Government.11. These orders were defied by a riotous mob which on 1st June attacked the small body of police stationed at the kgotla ground. The police were forced towithdraw after suffering three fatal casualties and many injuries. They showedgreat restraint and courage in face of a very ugly situation. Order was rapidlyrestored with the arrival of police reinforcements. More than 100 arrests weremade, including Keaboka and another member of the delegation.12. The prompt and effective measures taken by the Administration to restoreauthority and the sentences of imprisonment later passed by the courts on theringleaders brought about a marked change in atmosphere in the Reserve. Dis-satisfaction with the faction responsible for the riot and previous disorders grew.With their influence removed, the more moderate elements took courage.13. An indication of the change of feeling in the tribe is the ease with whichTshekedi Khama&apos;s resumption of residence in the Reserve was finally accomplished.His visits.to the Reserve had been without incident and at the end of August the exclusion order against him was finally lifted. This aroused no comment, and atthe beginning of October Tshekedi applied formally for readmission to the tribe at agathering of chiefs and headmen and was accepted without a dissenting voice.14. In October, following consultation with prominent tribesmen, theDistrict Commissioner called together a meeting of chiefs and headmen of theReserve to consider arrangements for a tribal kgotla. At this meeting, attended byeighty chiefs and headmen, it was unanimously decided to hold a kgotla inNovember at which the designation of a new chief might be discussed.
15. In the interval before the kgotla, which was held on 10th November, only two possible candidates emerged Rasebolai, who, with the extinction of Seretse&apos;sand Tshekedi&apos;s claims to the chieftainship, is by tribal custom next in succession,and Oratile, Seretse&apos;s half-sister. Rasebolai had the backing of conservative and pro--Government elements in the tribe. Oratile&apos;s sex, instability of character, and close relationship with Seretse would have made her an unsuitable candidate. Inthe event, she refused to allow her name to be put forward, and the issue at the kgotla became a simple one between the designation of Rasebolai and no designationat all.16. The result of the kgotla was disappointing. Support of Rasebolai was apparent at the outset, but failed to gain sufficient strength to secure his designation.The Seretse faction had been active and spread a story (based on misleading reports from London of the Opposition attitude) that Seretse was bound to return. TheDistrict Commissioner accordingly adjourned the kgotla until the present ploughingand planting season is over.17. It has, of course, always been clear that it would take time for theBarnangwato to come round to the idea of a new chief. The High Commissionerreports that eradication of the impression that Government would imposeRasebolai has done much to remove suspicions which have long been prevalent inthe tribe about the Governments intentions. There is now a better feeling towardsGovernment than there has been for many months. The kgotla was held in an atmosphere of friendliness and decorum, in contrast to many disorderly meetings in the last two or three years. In the three or four months before the next kgotlathe movement in favour of designation may grow. The Administration is makingevery endeavour to ensure the best use of this interval.

</content>
</cab>
