<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/203/13 images: 119-132</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CP(78) 88 COPY NO 8031 July 1978CABINETDECISIONS ON AEROSPACE policy note by the Secretary of the CabinetThe attached paper i6 to be considered by the Ministerial Group on AircraftPolicy (GEN 130) at its meeting on 1 August.    The conclusions of that meetingwill be reported to the Cabinet at its meeting on 2 August.Signed   JOHN hunt cabinet Office31 July 1978
CONFIDENTIALDECISIONS ON AEROSPACE policy note by the Central Policy Review staff. As Ministers are aware, decisions will need to be made before the summer break on the policy of British Aerospace (BAe), British Airways (BA)and Rolls Royce (RR) on civil aircraft around the 200 seater capacity and engines to power such aircraft.      The position on these is as described ingeneral terms in the following paragraphs.      Annex A, provided by theDepartment of Industry, gives details of the negotiating positions.     Annex Bdiscusses alternatives open to BAe.RR2. RR are anxious to extend downwards the range of their RB 211 familyof engines to an RB 211 535 which would be suitable for civil aircraft in the200 seater area.     The National Enterprise Board (not) has agreed toprqvide finance for the engine on condition that two launch customers havebeen obtained.    The 535 engine could be suitable for a number of aircraftbut it is bound to be in competition with at least one American engine of similar characteristics - from General Electric (GE).     The prospects for the 535 depend to an important extent on it being in the field ahead ofits GE competitor on a major airframe (something which has not happened in recent years) and it being available on aircraft which have the best prospect of wide sales.
\^J^V/m .     CPs 2 [ ; ; i, I3. The Boeing 757 is the only aircraft which meets these characteristics.Boeing have confirmed that they are ready to manufacture it - provided thereare launch orders.     Eastern Airlines and BA have confirmed that they bothwish to be launch customers for 757s with 535 engines and agreement byBritish Ministers is all that is required for the process to start.4. The alternatives  (either Airbus or a McDonnell Douglas (McDD)aircraft) provide smaller prospects for the 535.     Putting RR engines on different versions of the Airbus would produce only modest sales. waiting to see whether it is possible to launch RR engines on a McDD aircraft inthe 200 seater class would mean both losing the present lead advantage over GE and trying to sell RR engines to McDD customers, few of whomuse RR engines.     It is very doubtful whether the not would be willing to finance the development of the 535 on this basis.5. From the RR point of view, then, there is no alternative to an early and positive decision on BA&apos;s request to buy the 757 if the 535 engine is togo ahead.BA6. The Board of BA have now confirmed that the Boeing 757 is theaircraft which best suits their requirements in the 200 seater class. Theyhave formally asked the Government for permission to order 19 as the firsttranche of the 30/40 aircraft which they regard as their ultimate needs inthis area.7. BA are clear that, for their purposes, the B10 is by a long way not asuitable aircraft.     The choice between the Boeing 757 and the McDD ATMRis much closer.    But it has to be said that the characteristics of the ATMRare necessarily less precise at this stage than the 757.    However, RRinterests apart, BA&apos;s choice of the 757 is largely determined by the greatercertainty of that aircraft, particularly of delivery date.    BA need to starttaking delivery as early as possible in 1983.     The chances of achieving this
with an at mr seem slim.    No consortium has yet been assembled toproduce it;  the characteristics have not been agreed;  no launch customersare settled;  it is a brand new aircraft with a lot of new technology.8. In the light of the above, the interests of RR and BA are clear. they need an early and positive agreement to the 757 purchase and the 535 launch.It is difficult to see any combination of circumstances between BAe, AirbusIndustrie (Al) and McDD which could change that position.9. As for the timing of the decision, RR need it very soon indeed. Thedanger is that the other launch customer, Eastern Airlines, might shift theirpresent preference from RR to GE who could then be providing the launchengine rather than RR.     BA have not quite such a degree of urgency(though delivery in 1983 is important for them).    But if RR miss beingthe launch engine for this size aircraft and the 535 is not built, BA could find themselves having to add GE engines to their fleet.10. The handling of the decisions on the 757 and the 535 is importantIt would clearly be disadvantageous if in the middle of negotiations with AI -or even immediately following - it became public that Ministers had agreedto BA buying the 757.       If Ministers do decide now to agree to BA&apos;s request(and, on this basis, to the not financing the 535) it would be possible forthe Prime Minister or the responsible Secretaries of State to speak toSir Kenneth Keith and Sir Frank MacFadzean telling them that this was what was in mind, but that this information must be kept to the two chairmenpersonally for the longest period that Eastern Airlines and Boeing could bekept in play  (perhaps 3 weeks).BAe^11. The decisions on BAe are more complicated. Following the visit of the Secretary of State for Industry to Paris and Bonn, BAe have been in commercial negotiations with AI on the basis that BAe would wish to join
p\JAI as, from now on, full risk sharing partners in the B2f B4 and BIOAirbus family - provided suitable commercial terms could be agreed (see annex A).12. BAe negotiators have so far aimed at terms which show a reasonable prospect of at least breaking even on work on the Airbus family in the years to come.     The initial German position was quite close (but not yet fullyconsistent) with that objective.    The French ideas were quite unacceptable.Negotiations are still proceeding and, at the time of writing, it is not knownhow close the combined French and German position is to the requirementsof BAe.      The Secretary of State for Industry will be circulating a paper onMonday evening (31 July) giving the latest state of the negotiations. Atthe moment though, there is no proposition which BAe negotiators can put to their Board.meeting on Monday, still less anything which BAe wish toput to Ministers.13. If BAe are unable to obtain terms which they regard as satisfactorybut Ministers consider that there arc important wider advantages in joiningAli it would be possible to offer money to BAe under Section 45 of theAircraft and Shipbuilding Industries Act 1977 (maximum  50m.). Alsothe e.c. Commission has mentioned the possibility of financial assistancebut no details have been given.14. Financial terms apart, there are two. other important issues whichcould form part of the negotiations.    These are the possibility of BA buyingthe BIO, and the possibility of AI (with BAe as a member) negotiating withMcDD.15. It is said that President Giscard would want some kind of commit-*nent that if BAe join AI, BA would buy the BIO. As was said above, BAdo believe that the BIO is very much not the aircraft for them.    It would
cf* *y tt r f ^ r)Jobviously be difficult to get the BA Board to make a strong public state -ment to the contrary.      The best that could be done would be to find a form of words by which BA agreed to consider whether at some time inthe future it might buy some BIO aircraft to fill part of its requirements for 200 6eater aircraft after its first 757 purchase.     But this would bea form of words designed to be presentationally helpful to the Frenchposition rather than a commitment of substance.16. A8 for the possible negotiations with McDD, the Germans seemgenuinely willing and the French sceptical and resistant.    But both talk of a &quot;step by step&quot; approach under which the enlarged AI would be frimly established before any approach was made to McDD.      Also, neither has suggested that the approach should be in terms of the development of anATMR sized aircraft which could be uncomfortably close to the BIO. in short, there has been no negotiation on the basis that if BAe goes into AIthere would be an immediate approach to McDD over the joint developmentof the at mr,17. It would seem, therefore, that if the French and the Germansrequired a genuine commitment for BA to buy the BIO, we would find thatimpossible to accept, and if we required them to agree to immediatenegotiations with McDD to build an at mr, they would find such aproposition impossible to accept.     Collaboration between AI and McDDon a smaller aircraft and on a longer time scale (plus possible jointProjects in the military sphere) is not ruled out but the 535 would notbe suitable for smaller civil aircraft.basis some 20 -25 per cent of the 757, the position remains as before. BAeare not attracted by sub-contracting work on this scale with no design18.As for the negotiation with Boeing on BAe building on a sub-contractleadership;  by the requirements of Boeing in terms of possible larger
fluctuations in production volumes;  by the need to adopt Boeing productionmethods;  by the price which Boeing are offering on the contract. The30 per cent difference between BAe and Boeing on price is still unbridgedand though negotiations are not yet concluded, the chance of the gap beingclosed seems small.     But Boeing have also suggested that BAe mightprefer a sub-contract for a very much smaller quantity of work on the757 and if negotiations with AI fail, BAe might find such a possibilityattractive.19. BAe do not regard the negotiations with AI to build medium sizedcivil aircraft as their only alternative for the future (see Annex B). Alarge part   of their future business will be in the military field and inthe manufacture of smaller civil aircraft.     As for the larger aircraft,as we said above, they do not rule out some modest sub-contracting workfor Boeing and if negotiations with AI break down, BAe have it in mind tonegotiate immediately with McDD on the at mr.     If this happened, BAewould naturally like BA not to order the 757 but to wait and order theATMR..    (The difficulties this would pose for BA and RR have been described above.)      The Secretary of State for Industry will be seeingsenior management of McDD on Monday and will report the outcome ofthose discussions in the note which he will circulate on the progress of negotiations with AI.20. Against this background, there will be no proposition before ministers that BAe should be a substantial sub-contractor on the Boeing 757and any negotiations with McDD would take some time.    The urgent issue is BAe&apos;s negotiations with AI and on that Ministers may wish to discuss:(i)   Does the unlikelihood of AI collaboration with McDD on anATMR seriously affect the desirability of BAe joining AI?
(ii) If no proposition from BAe on joining AI is yet before ministers, by what method would such a proposition subsequently be considered -(a) a later meeting of GEN 130 ?(b) delegation to certain Ministers?(iii) If the decision has to be delegated to certain Ministers, underwhat guidelines would they operate?      Would BAe be expected atleast to break even on B2/B4/B10?        On what assumptions (sales,contract prices, etc.) should the calculations be made   - wouldBAe&apos;s   &quot;central case&quot; estimates be acceptable?      (See Table in annex A.)      Are subventions under Section 45 of the aircraft and Shipbuilding Industries Act ruled out?      Is any approach tothe e.c. Commission desirable?(iv) Is any political initiative contemplated to try to bridge anyremaining gap (or help smooth any breaking off of negotiations) -e.g.   Mr Varley seeing his opposite   numbers or the PrimeMinister contacting Chancellor Schmidt and President Giscard?Cabinet Office28 July 1978
ANNEX ABRITISH AEROSPACE AND AIRBUS INDUSTRIE1.     BAe currently manufacture the fixed parts of the wing of the B2/Bkversion of the A 300 on a cub-contract.   If they do not join Airbus Industrie(AI) they will probably lose this work.   However, because of the problems in finding alternative sources and 01 recertifying the aircraft during a periodof expected substantial sales, it is very unlikely that this contract couldbe lost for at least 5 years, and it is possible it would only go then ifthe B10 wing is considered suitable for the B2/B^.2.     BAe currently forecast a cash surplus of about  7^m a year on the B^l/B^wing - assuming 3 aircraft a month - averaged over the next 5 years.3-     Sales of the A3O0B2/B/t have been going well; and the market base is nowfairly firm (15 airlines) and is expanding, offering good prospects of sales of 300B2/B^ by 1992 and fair chances of.going as high as ^00.   The main salesare likely to be in the first 7 years of the period.Therefore if BAe continue on their present sub-contract they should beable to receive about  &apos;K)m cash surplus over the next 5 years and might continue at a rate of  7iJm or so a year for a period thereafter.5.     There is no doubt that if BAe join the B10 programme they will have toaccept the standard terms of AI membership in respect of this programme fromthe outset.   The B10 will be in direct competition with the Boeing 7^7* Itis likely to sell at least 200 copies; and there are reasonable prospects of300 plus.    (The BAe estimate is 310 aircraft by 1992 but this may be over-optimistic as a central case.)   If a substantial US breakthrough could besecured, sales might go as high as ^50; but this is not very likely and inthis event there would probably be adverse effects on sales of the B2/B**,with which the B10 will to some extent compete (reducing the possibilityof that aircraftfs sales approaching to)).Membership of AID*     BAe have been engaged for some months now in examining the financial implications of joining AI to take part in the B10 programme.   They retainedpeat Harwich to investigate AX9fl finances and can now make a fairly fullassessment of likely consequences of membership in relation to the various alternatives arising during negotiations.   Their assessment is, however,subject both to the normal and unavoidable uncertainties attending any newcivil aircraft project and to one special area of doubt (paragraph 7 below).7-     AI does not itself make a profit or a loss.   It receives all receipts from Airbus sales and both defrays central expenses   (eg costs of marketingand product support, and payments to subcontractors, such as BAe, and SuppliersThe B10
of centrally purchased equipment) and makes payments to the partners in theorganisation for the work they do themselves.   Any resulting surplus ordeficiency is shared out among the partners.   AI has admitted that it is atpresent making a loss on current costs against sales; and it is not clear -nor is AI likely to reveal to anyone except the partners themselves - howlarge the loss is.8.     However it has not been proposed by the AI partners that BAe should contribute to past losses - or to the very large development costs, recovery of which is a charge on future receipts.   Furthermore, although when is uncertain, it is likely that fairly soon AI&apos;s central loss will turn intoa profit because with higher Bales central costs can be spread over a largerbase and AI intends to raise prices in real terms (there was a D% increasein January 1978).   It should also be noted that AI&apos;s central profit or lossis independent of whether individual partners make a profit or loss on thework they do for AI-   AI&apos;s payments are determined on common cost assumptions;it is up to the partner to keep his production costs within that price andto make his own arrangements on financing within his country.BAgJs negotiating position9-     BAc hope to retain as much as possible of the B2/B&apos;t surplus by retentionof the main substance of the sub-contract1 a terms while accepting obligationsAI partnership.   They hope that their ability to produce at coot levels lower than the partnership average and their share in eventual profit on both theB2/B7+ and B10 will provide adequate compensation for surrendering their presenposition.10.   Broad calculations on what acceptance of the terms proposed by the Germanon the B2/B^ might represent, together with BAc&apos;s latest calculations on theB10, are in the table below.   The main assumptions are:-i BAe join AI with a 20% stake, which would have a vetoii On the B?./Bh wing BAe should retain the prices in the sub-contractiii IK all other respects BAe would be a full member of AI from1 January 1979 eg would contribute to central costsiv BAe&apos;s overheads on AI work would be less tlian at present due to higher outputNote: The assumptions in ii represent some improvement on what theGermans put forward on prices after the 150th set.
POSSIBLE COSTS OF AI MEMBERSHIPBROAD ESTIMATES BASED ON GERMAN TERMS			Proposed BIO			Current B2/B4		Sales	Sales	SalesConstant 1978	contract		200	310	450prices	(14 year totals)		units	units	units		 m	 m	 m	 mPeak negative cash					flow		0	200	200	200Outturn - undiscounted		+15	-50	4-5	+60- discounted					at 5%		+10	-75	-45	-10
Employment11-   Me expect work on the B2/B*t at the rate of 3 aircraft a month toprovide about 3500 jobs in their establishments (ie about another 1000 morethan at the present rate of production of about 2 a month) and there isother work in suppliers.   Employment on the B10 is estimated as followson the sane basis.The BAe employment would be mainly at Chester, and to a lesser extent atBrough (Humbereide).   To this should be added perhaps 3000-^000 jobs atUK equipment suppliers, giving a potential total of 8000-12,300 UK jobs onAirbus work, compared with a prospective level, including suppliers, of about^000/^500 on the B2/B**.12.   The B2/Btt is now available with cither General Electric (GE) CF6 orPratt &amp; Whitney (P&amp;W) JT9g.   The B10 is likely to be launched with CF6engines, as the B2 was, because Lufthansa, the main launch customer, andAir France use GE engines.   The JT9   was certificated only recently for theB2/B^, in order to meet the requirements of 5AS$   it is likely to be available on the B10 if the engine is specified by a customer (Swissair, a potentialearly buyer, may do so).13-   Rolls Royce have now stated that they are willing to install the RB211on the Airbus if they are given similar terms to those understood to havebeen made available to P&amp;W.   That is, RR will have to meet the basic enginecort   (probably about  ?m for the first aircraft type, say the B2/B&apos;l, and 2m for the next, cay the B10); the costs of developing the pylon (say  15mfor each aircraft type) will fall elsewhere; and the incidence of costs offlight testing and certification (say  5m on each aircraft type) would be aletter for negotiation between RR and AI.   The bulk of expenditure would be committed &quot;only after launch orders were secured; and the costs would be recovered over sales.200 copies310 copies^50 copies1500 jobs3750 jobs5350 jobsEnginesAir Division27 July 1978- k -
ANNEX BIf BAe do not join AI and the BIO programme, it is unlikely that they wouldbe able to play a leading role in other projects for several years, perhapslonger,a. It is unlikely that collaboration between AI, BAe and McDDon the at mr could be arranged.     McDD have said that they wouldnot be interested in bilateral collaboration on this aircraft; someother consortium involving other European or American manu-facturers might be negotiated, but in any event, the project wouldbe risky, since it would be in competition with both the BIO andthe Boeing 757 (which now seems likely to be launched soon).b. AI would not be willing to undertake the JET project for atleast another year, if at all:     the Germans have said that unlessBAe helps finance the BIO, they will not be able to participate inthe JET.     Moreover, market reaction to the JET has beenlukewarm;  and it is not certain that it or any modification of it,will be commercially viable.c. There is no reason to suppose that the difficulties of possiblecollaboration with Boeing (prices, fluctuation in production volume,etc.) can be overcome.Hence it is possible, even likely, that unless they join the BIO, BAe couldbe out of the civil aircraft market (other than for business jets and feederliners) for the foreseeable future, except to the extent that they could secure sub-contract work on acceptable terms, perhaps including minorwork on the Boeing 757.
Commercially, this is a perfectly viable option.     It would mean thatBAe, on the aircraft 6ide, would concentrate on military business,except to the extent indicated above:    they would resemble such USaircraft firms as Grumnan and General Dynamics, which are commerciallysuccessful.      Politically, however, it might be more difficult. TheGovernment would be criticised by the unions and in Parliament for having &quot;missed the bus&quot; and for opting out of the main civil aircraftmarket.      BAe v/ould also almost certainly have to cut its workforce.Existing projections suggest that by 1981 BAe employment would fall from current levels by about 8,000 (say 16 per cent) and by 12, 000 (25 per cent)by 1983, less whatever employment was provided by sub-contract work.Most BAe factories undertaking civil work would be affected, including those at Chester and Brough, and closure of some plants might benecessary.

</content>
</cab>
