<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/11/0 images: 40-49</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I   . -      20JfflHlS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY YS GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP. (US) 257 COPY NO.q-TH JULY,  19h6CABINETPETROL_RATIONINGMemorandum by the Minister of Fuel arid power at the meeting of the Cabinet held on the 29th april last (C.Mo(h6) 38th Conclusions, Minute 3) when a memorandum bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer (C.P.(h6) 168) on the import programmes for the second half of 19ho and the first half of19h7 was under consideration,  I pressed that the abolition of petrol rationing should be considered as soon as a decision hadbeen reached on the United States Loan.      The Cabinet agreed tothis suggestion.      The discussions on the American Loan in theU.S. Congress appear to have almost reached the final stage andI wish,  therefore,  to bring before my colleagues the reasons why,in my view, petrol rationing should be abolished immediately theLoan is approved.2. Since the end of the European war, some relaxationshave been granted, both as regards the basic ration and supplementary allowances for essential and &quot;semi-essential&quot;purposes.      In spite of these relaxations private cars in thiscountry are still consuming little more than hO per cent,  of thepre-war consumption for this class of motor transport - a very low figure.     As regards other classes of motor transport, theMinistry of Transport have been improving services for some time,but so long as petrol rationing remains, I am convinced that itis hindering the recovery of internal transport services.3. Apart from the pressure in Parliament,  there is a large volume of correspondence from all classes of the community whichbrings out clearly the hampering effect of rationing on all kinds of business and other necessary activities and the widespreadinconvenience which it causes.      I would particularly mentiontradesmens&apos; delivery vans.      The hard pressed housewife is stillhaving,  in a large measure,  to carry home her shopping and, withthe continued restrictions in other directions which are necessary,this is a sphere where an important amelioration ought to be made.h. There is also the need to improve travelling facilitiesfor holidays.      The number of people entitled to paid holidays isnow much greater than it was before the war.      Railways arecongested and,  although some alleviation has been afforded bythe restarting of coach services,  there is an urgent demand for additional petrol to enable those&apos; who have motor cars, and this includes many amongst the better paid wage-earners,  to take their families away.5. Apart from the mass of general correspondence to whichI have referred, I have received urgent representations within

the past few weeks from the National Union of Manufacturers,the National Association of Commercial Travellers,  an importantassociation representing the Hire Gars and Taxi-Cabs, and fromthe a. A. and. R.w,C.      There has also been considerable pressure in the Press,  and it is becoming more and more difficult to givesatisfactory explanations of the need for the cresentrestrictions.      if the American Loan is ratified, the main reason I have been giving - shortage of dollars - will become more difficult to justify.6. There are I think two reasons for  the strength ofpublic feeling on this subject, (a)    the character of the rationing system, and (b)    the difficulties of explaining thereasons for the shortage of petrol supplies.7. As regards  (a),  there is no doubt that petrol is far more difficult to ration than most other commodities.      It iseasy enough to set a basic ration for pleasure motoring, but togrant supplementary allowances so  that they are truly inaccordance with the needs of the applicant is virtually impossible.      It would mean individual assessment in each case,and even if this were administratively practicable, there wouldbe no adequate check on the use of the allowances granted.Under war conditions the rationing scheme worked tolerably well,and every effort was made, within administrative possibilities,to categorise classes of users, but inevitably there has had tobe a large measure of exceptional treatment.      In spite of allthe efforts to make the system work equitably,  it seems to meclear that the result has been that quite a lot of people getless petrol than  they require,  and a considerable number morethan they need for non-pleasure purposes.      Petrol^ unlike most other consumer goods,  is required by people in the course oftheir work.      This means that the consequence-    of the rationing-system is that some people cannot do  their work, and there is a*serious danger of development of industry,  which we all wish toencourage,  being restricted.8. Increasing the basic ration provides no solution.From the administrative point of view it would be a simple matter,but the effect would be to give a large percentage of privatemotorists nearly as much petrol as they normally used before thewar, while we should be continuing to employ a staff, costingnearly half a million pounds&apos; a year,   to ration the more essentialusers.9. An indication of the difficulty of continuing rationingis shown by the case of what is known as the semi-essential(&apos;S&apos; Class) motorists of which there are some 3h0,000.      they include Commercial Travellers, persons having to use their carsto drive from home to station, and in certain cases from home to business, etc.     Administratively, it is impracticable to dealwith this section in the way that we have dealt with the noreessential users - by investigation of individual needs - and inconsequence there is no doubt that considerable numbers in these -essential class are being hampered by the lack of petrolsupplies.      Yet if a substantial increase in allowances wereaccorded to the whole of the &quot;semi-essential&quot; class,  serious andjustifiable complaints would be received from any who are inthe essential user category.10. As regards (b),  the difficulty of explaining the needfor continued rationing is complicated by the fact thatpractically the whole of our trade in the Petroleum industry,

which is very large,  is based on the activities of British oil companies overseas.      I have explained in parliament that while we have  a large production of oil from British controlledsources we cannot use the whole of it for this country.      Itis required to meet the British military demand throughout theworld,  as well as the civilian needs of the Empire,  and it isimportant also to keep up the share of British trade in over-seas countries which has long been an important part of theactivities of the Petroleum Industry.      If all this foreign trade brought dollars to the British dollar pool, it would bemore easy to explain our situation.      But this is not the case.In many instances sterling oil,  and even some supplies purchasedfor dollars, are sold to foreign countries for sterling&apos;.      I amj not questioning the wisdom of this policy, but the result has been that in most countries petrol restrictions are less than   they are here.      This,  in my view, does justify now taking&apos; steps to supplement the supplies to  this country.11. It is still necessary, because of the need foreconomising in tanker transport,  to adhere in a considerable measure to  the policy which was adopted during the war of &quot;shorthaul&quot;.      The result of this is that most of the dollar suppliesof petrol and other petroleum products required in the sterling area,, come to this country.      When the American Loan is ratifiedit will be necessary to allow more freedom to exporters of oilproducts from dollar sources, than has hitherto been the case,and there will be some reorientation of the general supplyarrangements.      Nevertheless,  the major part of the dollarsupplies will still come to this country because of the shortertanker haul.12. I attach an Annex showing what is needed in the wayof additional supplies and additiona.1 dollar expenditure in1 order to  abolish rationing:.      The overall cost for the period up to the end of June,  19*4.7 is estimated to be about $50 million.It must not be  supposed, however,  that even if we did not abolishrationing, we could avoid extra dollar expenditure for petrolon a large scale.      We should in ay ca.se, be obliged,  in my view, to make so many relaxations in the existing scales of allowances that the difference in dollars between the result ofthese relaxations and the complete abolition of  rationing would- not be sufficient to justify all the hampering effects andadministrative difficulties which rationing, however, relaxed, .I involves.      Relaxations would indeed involve a new set ofI administrative problems and additional staff.13. If the Loan goes through I shall be at once pressedin Parliament to announce the Government&apos;s intention about a continuance of petrol rationing.      I recommend that we shouldabolish it on 1st August and make  an immediate announcement tothis effect.E.S.Ministry of Fuel and Power,7, Militant, S.W.  1.

ANNEXIf petrol rationing is abolished in this country itwill, of course, have to be abolished in the rest of the sterling area.      But already Canada,  South Africa and some parts of theColonial Empire, have abolished it,  and during the visit of-Dominion Ministers to London recently we had to agree  to itsvirtual abolition in New Zealand.      The figures given beloware based on the assumption that an all round abolition of rationing will be provided for throughout the Empire and India.assuming abolition on the 1st August,  the additional supplies of petrol which would be required would be of thefollowing order;-1st xoigusfc, 192+6/ 1st January, 19h7/31st December,  192+6 30th June, 19k7__(thousand tons)United Kingdom 578 6OhRest of Sterling Area 202 311780 915Owing to  the acute supply and tanker shortage last winter - due to strikes in the United States and to the continuinghigh rate of military, particularly naval,  consumption - stocksthroughout the sterling area fell to dangerously low levels atthe 1st January,  192+6.      The stock position has now been restoredand the United Kingdom estimated stock during August should amountto 1,100,000 tons,  at which level it is considered that supplies could be distributed against unrationed consumption.      Stocks inother areas are also sufficiently good to enable the earlyabolition of rationing to be contemplated.A substantial number of new tankers are now being constructed in British yards,  but the latest estimates show that united States tankers will still require to be chartered to a material extent in order to meet the total British programme basedon present consumption levels.      It follows that additional UnitedStates tanker  tonnage will require to be chartered for any increasein the programme which would result from the abolition of rationing.It is reckoned that 10 additional tankers in continuousservice would be required if petrol rationing were removedthroughout the sterling area on 1st August, 19h7.An increase in motor spirit consumption involves also an increase in the use of lubricating oil.      This can be put at approximately k per cent, of the additional consumption of motor spirit and as the sterling area is deficient in suppliesof lubricating oil,  the additional oil would have to be purchasedin the United States.      The amount would be 31,200 tons duringthe second half of 192+6 and 36,600 tons during  the first halfof 192+7.

The cost of the extra supplies required if rationing-were removed on 1st August,  19kb would be $15,83^*000 for thesecond half of 19d6 and $18,575*000 for the first half of19U7.    .The expenditure on tanker tonnage and luricating oil would amount to $5*000,000 and $1,872,000 respectivelyfor the second half of 19u7 and $7*000,000 and $2,196,000for the first half of 19U7 or a total of,  say, $50,000,000for the period up to the end of June,  19U7.


</content>
</cab>
