<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/11/0 images: 168-175</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1946.CONFIDENTIAL. Copy No.CP. (46) 273.16tlh July, 1946.CABINET.USE OF OFFICIAL INFORMATION IN PRIVATE  PUBLICATIONSBY SERVING AND FORMER CROWN SERVANTS.Note by the Prime Minister.1. On the 25th May the Cabinet considered a Memorandum (CP. (46) 188)on the publication, by persons who have held office as Ministers of the Crown,of information regarding Cabinet proceedings or based on Cabinet documents.The principles set out in this document were approved and it was agreed thata further Memorandum should be circulated dealing with the application ofthese principles to serving and former Crown Servants. I now attach aMemorandum on this matter prepared in the Cabinet Office in consultation withthe Treasury and other Departments.2. It is for consideration what steps should be taken to make it known thatformer Ministers and other persons who have held office under the Crown are under obligation to consult the Government of the day, or the Heads of their former Department, before they publish any information obtained by virtue oftheir official position. I have reached the conclusion that, as suggested in theMemorandum, the best method would be by way of an arranged Question and answer.  A suggested draft is to be found as the Appendix to the Memorandum.C. R. A.10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,16th July, 1946.[32104a]

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNMENTMemorandum prepared in the Cabinet Office.1. This Memorandum deals with the use which may be made, by servingand former members of the Crown Services (i.e., in the Civil Service, the foreign service and the Fighting Services) of unpublished official information in privatepublications.Serving Civil Servants.2. It is suggested that policy in this matter should be guided by thefollowing four, general principles :  (a) It is an established rule that a civil servant should not indulge in political or party controversy. It follows from this that he should not publishbooks or other works dealing with matters of current political con-troversy, even if none of the information in them came to him byreason of his official position; and a fortiori that he should not be permitted to use official information in such works. It is in this,respect that the position of a civil servant is different from that ofa Minister; since he has no public responsibility for the policy of his-Department, it is no concern of his to defend his official actions.*(&amp;) It is also clear that civil servants, equally with former Ministers, shouldnot be permitted to publish information which it is essential to keepsecret. The Cabinet have already approved a definition of such information, as follows : &apos;&apos; (i) In the international sphere information whose disclosure wouldbe injurious to us in our relations with other nations, includinginformation which would be of value to a potential enemy.&quot; (ii) In the domestic sphere, information the publication of whichwould be destructive of the confidential relationships on which our system of Government is based and which may subsistbetween Minister and Minister, Ministers and their advisers,and between either and outside bodies or private persons.&quot;(CP. (46) 188, paragraph 8.)(c) Thirdly, there may be occasions when it is not in the public interest that official information should be used in a private publication, eventhough it is not of the kind covered by definition at (&amp;) above, forthe reason either that if the information is to be published it shouldbe published officially or under official auspices, or that it should notbe published at the particular time proposed. This is a much lessclear-cut principle than either of the two former and one which calls for the greatest care in its exercise. It is nevertheless the case thatofficial information as such is the property of the Crown, and thatthe Government has therefore a legitimate discretion as to its use.In particular, this applies to the publication in extenso of official documents, including minutes and memoranda written by civil servants in their official capacity, which should normally be published, if atall, by the Stationery Office.id) As the field of Government activity widens and the need for specialist services increases, it will become increasingly difficult to resist ademand that specialists should be permitted to publish works in theirtheir own field, and, at the same time, less easy to maintain a distinc-tion between information which the specialist has obtained from hisposition in Government Service and information which he himselfbrings to the Service. It seems, therefore, that it will be necessaryto allow considerable freedom to publications of a specialist kind,whether by scientists, statisticians, lawyers, economists or administra-tors, always provided that the first three principles set out above arenot infringed.* There may be some exceptions to this rule in the case of certain civil servants withstatutory responsibilities; but this does not appear to invalidate its general application.[32104]
3. These principles apply as much to temporary civil servants as to permanent ones.Serving Members of the Foreign Service and Fighting Services.4. The Foreign Office and the Service Departments agree that the principles senout in paragraph 2 also apply to the Foreign Service and to the Fighting Services,with a proviso, in the case of the latter, that, in applying the first principle topublications by high military, naval and air commanders, account must be taken of the fact that such officers are personally and publicly responsible for the conductof operations under their command, and have therefore a corresponding claimto be allowed to publish defences of their conduct.Retired Civil Servants.5. It is suggested that the second, third and fourth principles set out aboveapply as much to retired Civil Servants as to those who are still serving. But theapplication of the first principle about political controversy is not so simple.Since a person who is no longer in Government service is not obliged to remainaloof from political controversy, it is difficult to see on what ground objectioncould be taken to a book by a former Civil Servant praising or blaming the policyof the Governments he had served, provided that no unpublished official informa-tion was used and that the matters dealt with were not those he had himselfhandled. Nevertheless, most career Civil Servants who have held responsiblepositions would feel that they were acting contrary to the traditions of the Serviceand were endangering its reputation for impartiality if on retirement they wereto publish anything which exceeded the bounds of the most restrained and objectivecriticism of the Governments which they had served. Certainly the Governmentwould be well within its rights in refusing permission to use official information in any book by a retired Civil Servant which dealt with matters of political controversy.6 Does the position of a former temporary Civil Servant differ from thatof a retired permanent Civil Servant ? Many persons who entered the Govern-ment Service during the war were well known to hold strong political opinions.Such persons, on leaviing the Government Service, clearly at once resume the fullliberty of expression of their views. But this does not mean that a formal dis-tinction should be drawn between what is allowable in this matter to a temporary and a permanent Civil Servant after retirement from the Service. So far as concerns the use of official information, they both stand on the same footing; any additional obligation which rests in this matter on retired career Civil Servantsis not one capable of formal definition.Retired former members of the Foreign Service and the Fighting Services.7. The Foreign Office agree that the position of former members of theForeign Service should be the same as that of other former civil servants; andthe Service Departments accept the position that inasmuch as the ultimatesanction for the principles described above is the Official Secrets Act, they apply equally to former members of the Fighting Services. They point out, however,that the tradition of silence on official matters does not, in the Services, extend to former members, so that in their case there is even less possibility of takingobjection to a work praising or blaming the policy of the Governments in powerduring the period of the author&apos;s service.General.8. The policy discussed above has necessarily been set out chiefly in the formof restrictions on the liberty of serving and former Crown servants. This is perhaps inevitable, since the most practicable way of delimiting a general policy on this matter is by defining what should not be permitted. It is not, however,suggested that the resulting policy should be a restrictive one; on the contrary,as the area of Government activity widens to cover more and more mattersformerly outside official scope, there should be increasing opportunity for crown servants to write useful works on subjects which now fall within the scope oftheir own or other Crown servants&apos; official duties; and, within the limitsindicated above, there seems to be every reason to encourage rather than restrictsuch a development.
[Procedure.9. If it is accepted that the principles set out above should be applied inthe way suggested to serving and former Crown servants, it will be necessary forall proposals to publish books or other works which fall within the scope of these principles to be submitted beforehand to responsible authority. So far as servingCrown servants are concerned, such arrangements are already in force, and require them to submit manuscripts to the Head of their Department or, in thecase of the Fighting Services, the Board of Admiralty, Army Council or air council, as the case may be. If the recommendations of this memorandum are approved by the Cabinet, the Treasury and the other Departments concerned will review these arrangements to ensure that the definition of the manuscriptsto be submitted covers the same field as the policy outlined above. As regards- persons who may leave the Crown service in the future, arrangements are in handwhereby their attention will be drawn to the relevant provisions of the official secrets Act and to the necessity of obtaining permission, if they wish to make use, in published works, of any information obtained owing to their officialposition. There is, however, no practicable means of communicating with allpersons who have already left the Government service, otherwise than by an authoritative public statement. If such a statement is made, it could convenientlyalso cover the position of former Ministers; the Cabinet have already decidedthat they should be informed of the policy as it affects them, and the difficulty of communicating with all of them by any other means -is equally great. It is accordingly submitted that a statement should be made in Parliament, in answer to a prearranged question, on the lines of the draft set out in the Appendix tothis note.10. If this procedure is approved, the principles set out above will becommunicated to Heads of Departments. It will have been recognised, however,that the suggested principles cannot be regarded as hard-and-fast rules or appliedwithout qualification to every case; it is therefore submitted that, for a year or so at airy rate, it would be useful to arrange for more or less systematic inter-departmental consultation on cases of this kind, so that a body of experiencemay be built up and a uniform policy followed, so far as practicable, throughoutthe Crown service.Summary op Recommendations.11.   It is submitted that the Cabinet should : (a) Approve the general principles, as set out in paragraphs 2-4 above, as constituting the policy to be followed in dealing with private publi-cations by serving Crown servants; and their application, as set outin paragraphs 5 to 7 above, to former Crown servants.(6) Agree that, subject to those limitations, the policy to be adopted in thismatter should be as liberal as possible.(c) Invite the Prime Minister to make a general statement on this matter in Parliament, covering the position both of former Ministers andCrown servants, on the lines of the draft annexed.(d) Authorise the establishment of interdepartmental machinery to securethe adoption, as far as practicable, of a uniform policy in this matterthroughout the Government Service.Appendix.Q. To ask the Prime Minister whether he has any statement to make aboutthe policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government towards the publication by formerMinisters and other persons who have held office under the Crown of books andother writings about their experiences during the war.A. Yes, Sir. It has long been recognised that ail persons who have heldoffice under the Crown are under an obligation to consult the Government ofthe day or the heads of the Departments affected in regard to the publicationof any unpublished information which they have obtained by virtue of their official position and to obtain formal permission in any doubtful case.Former Ministers who wish to make use of such information should applyto the Secretary of the Cabinet, who will consult any department concerned and
submit the matter to me. Other persons who have held office under the Crown,,including former members of the Foreign and Home Civil Services and theFighting Services, should apply to the head of their former department or tothe Board of Admiralty, Army Council, or Air Council as the case may be.In dealing with any such applications His Majesty&apos;s Government will distinguish between the position of a former Minister, who has been responsible toParliament and subject to public criticism, and other former Crown servants,who have not had a Minister&apos;s responsibilities. Further they will bear immind the fact that during the war much information that would ordinarily havebeen published had to be kept secret for reasons of military security; they will therefore be disposed to allow the greatest practicable freedom in the use of official information about the events of the war period and defence themes inthe years immediately preceding the war, subject to no matter being disclosedwhich would be clearly contrary to the public interest, or would impair the confidential relationships which subsist between Ministers, or between ministers and their advisers.



</content>
</cab>
