<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/11/0 images: 196-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   Jidy 1946.SECRET.   &apos; Copy No.CP. (46) 276.18th July, 1946.CABINET.POLITICAL  BROADCASTING.Note by the Additional Secretary.BY direction of the Prime Minister I circulate the annexed exchangeof letters with Mr. Churchill about Political Broadcasting.(Signed) NORMAN BROOK.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,11th July, 1946.ANNEX I.(Private.)28, Hyde Park Gate,London, S. W. 7.My dear Prime Minister, 8th July, 1946.YOUR letter of the 4th July in regard to broadcasting. I understandthere is to be a meeting on this subject between the Parties and the B.B.C., andI shall be very glad to nominate two or three of my friends to meet an equal number of yours. The exact scope of the discussion had better be arrangedthrough &quot;the usual channels.&quot;I am glad you agree with me as to the desirability of resuming politicalbroadcasting. I must, however, make it clear that the position in which we now stand is entirely different from that of the days of the Coalition. then there was a National Government based on the official representation of thethree larger or historic Parties. Now we have a purely Party Governmentinterpreted in the strictest manner. Also, in those days we were engaged in awar of a potentially mortal character. Now there is no fighting going on anymore. These two points of difference between the present and former positionare fundamental.We cannot admit that Mr. Morrison&apos;s broadcast was uncontroversial. Itwas no doubt a very good statement of the Government case. We requestopportunities for putting forward our own point of view.Of course, there may be topics on which there would be no controversy, andwe should welcome statements from the chosen representatives of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment. These ought to be agreed upon beforehand. It would be a verywrong thing if this modern and potent instrument of propaganda were usedunfairly or one-sidedly as between the two halves of the nation.Pray excuse me for putting these points to you, because I am sure you will feel they ought to be discussed between us in order to see if there is any chanceof agreement.Yours very sincerely,(Signed) WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, C.H., M.P.[32152]
ANNEX II.10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,My dear Churchill, 11th July, 1946.MANY thanks for your letter of the 8th July about broadcasting, whichI have now discussed with some of my colleagues. I am glad that you agreethat there should be a meeting between the Parties and the B.B.C. and arrange-ments for this will now be made through &quot; the usual channels.&quot;Yours sincerely,(Signed) C. R. ATTLEE.The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill,O.M, C.H., F.R.S., M.P.



</content>
</cab>
