<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/49/48 images: 473-480</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1973CM (71) Copy No.   0948th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, on Wednesday, 29 September, 1971,at 11.45 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. edward the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,m p,   Secretary  of  State  for  theHome department the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,qc, m p, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,m p, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for the Environ-ment the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries andFoodHeath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Secretary of State for Trade andIndustry and President of the Boardof trade the following were also present:Mr. Maurice Macmillan, mp, chief secretary, Treasury (Items 3 and 4)The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp.Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. E. ThorntonSir Philip adams mr. P. J. hudson mr. K. T. barnett mr. I. T. Lawman16a
ContentsSubjectOversea Affairs     ......Soviet UnionNorthern Ireland        .....Economic Affairs        .....London Transport FaresStructure Plans        .....Form of Inquiry
a 1.   The Prime Minister said that the Cabinet would understand why it had not been possible for the Governments decision toUnion request a large number of Soviet officials to leave the country to bediscussed beforehand with more than the Ministers most closely concerned. The problem represented by the presence of a largenumber of Soviet intelligence agents in London was not new. Thelast Administration had imposed a reduction in the size of the staffof the Soviet Embassy to 89; but the number of officials in ancillarydepartments had correspondingly increased. He had thereforediscussed with the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary the possible courses of action to remove this threat to our security; and it hadbeen decided that the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary should raise the matter with the Soviet Foreign Minister, Mr. Gromyko.He had accordingly indicated our concern to Mr. Gromyko and hadtwice written to him on the subject. But in the absence of anyresponse it had become necessary to take unilateral action to ensurethe removal of the individuals concerned. The departure of 90had now been requested; and a further 15, currently out of thecountry, would not be permitted to return. The timing of theoperation had been influenced by the obvious desirability to avoid any action which might prejudice the success of the quadripartitediscussions about Berlin and subsequently, when these were nolonger a complication, by the receipt from a defector of fresh andcompelling evidence against numbers of the Soviet agents in theUnited Kingdom.After the Soviet Government had been notified of our intentionsthe Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary had met the Soviet ForeignMinister at the General Assembly of the United Nations in new york. Mr. Gromyko&apos;s reaction suggested that the Soviet Govern-ment had not been entirely surprised that we should have required the removal of the intelligence officers but that the scale of theoperation had taken them aback. HM Ambassador in Moscow, towhom the Soviet authorities had made a formal protest, had been instructed to inform the Soviet Foreign Ministry that the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary&apos;s discussion with Mr. Gromyko in new york constituted our substantive reply to this protest and that our decision would not be reversed. Intending travellers to the soviet union were being warned, so far as possible, of the additional risks which they might now face; and HM Ambassador was takingsimilar precautions in relation to those British subjects who were already in Soviet territory. Public opinion in this country had ingeneral showed a ready understanding of the Governments action.In a short discussion it was agreed that Ministers who hadplans to visit the Soviet Union should allow these plans to stand, atleast for the time being.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers statement.
IrelandNorthernPreviousReference:CM (71) 47thConclusions,Minute 3CONFIDENTIAL2. The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet of the outcome ofhis discussions with the Prime Ministers of the Irish Republic and ofNorthern Ireland. The Cabinet discussion, and the conclusions reached, were separately recorded and circulated only to The Queen,the Prime Minister and those Ministers who had to take action.The conclusions are- recorded separately in the standard file heldby the Secretary of the Cabinet.EconomicAffairsLondonTransportFaresPreviousReference:CM (71) 47thConclusions,Minute  secret*3. The Secretary of State for the Environment said that, sincethe Cabinet had discussed the proposal to increase bus and Under-ground fares in London at their previous meeting, there had been further discussions with the Greater London Council (GLC) and theLondon Transport Executive (LTE). The Chairman of LTE was unwilling to reduce below 8 per cent the level of the wage increasein 1972 for which he had made provision in his budget, regarding anylower level as unrealistic and unacceptable in the context of hisstatutory duty and in the light of a pending claim for a 15 per centwage increase. The Chairman of the GLC was unwilling to presshim to reduce this provision. Nor would the Chairman of the GLCreconsider his refusal to subsidise fares from the GLC rates. after taking account both of a saving of  2 million by making no provisionfor a contribution to reserves in 1972 and of increases in revenue asthe result of the elimination of certain fare concessions, the level offares increase which was necessary to avoid a deficit in 1972 was now put at 11^ per cent. This could be further reduced to 10 per cent by the provision of a 50 per cent Government capital grant onreplacement rolling stock and signalling equipment. If the increasein fares were to be further reduced to 8 per cent, it would be necessaryto offer either a lump sum to reserves of about  9 million or relief from fuel tax. Since public transport was already relieved from any increase in fuel tax, it seemed a logical step to relieve them of the taxaltogether in present circumstances as a means of keeping down thecost of living.The Secretary of State for Trade and Industry said that a furthercomplication had arisen, in that the LTE wished very shortly toplace an order for new rolling stock for the Underground, worthapproximately  12^ million, with a French company. Although the&quot; basic&quot; bids of the French company and the most competitiveBritish company (Metro-Cammell) were comparable, the French bidwas much more attractive because it was a fixed price tender, whichwas made possible by a French Government scheme for insurance of export orders against cost inflation. He was advised that thescheme was compatible with the General Agreement on Tariffs andTrade and with existing rules on export subsidies within the european economic Community (e.c.). If Metro-Cammell, the only private sector company in this field, lost this order, they would probably
cease to manufacture rolling stock at all, with the result that 500 jobswould be lost in the Birmingham area. The only way of influencing the LTE to place the order in the United Kingdom against their commercial interests seemed to be by using the inducement of aninfrastructure grant in respect of rolling stock replacement.In discussion of the proposed fares increase there was generalagreement that an increase of 10 per cent or 11 per cent in London,with the adverse effect which it would have on prices policy and the confederation of British Industry initiative in this field, was unacceptable. Doubt was cast on the LTE&apos;s judgment of the levelof wage increase which it would be necessary to grant in 1972. an per cent increase would certainly be out of line with the general level of increase which the Government expected to be prevailingearly next year as a result of the de-escalation policy now being pursued. Moreover, the recruitment difficulties which had beenadduced in support of this level of increase did not seem to beborne out by the available information on staff vacancies in london transport. Rather than a fares increase of 10 per cent from1 January next, it was suggested that it would be better to excludeall provision for next year&apos;s wage increase from the present proposal and to link a second increase in fares in 1972 directly with the cost ofthe wage settlement. The proposal to reduce the LTE&apos;s costs by theextension of transport infrastructure grants to rolling stock andsignalling equipment, on which an official working party had justreported favourably, seemed sensible; but the national implications of the elimination of fuel tax on bus stage services needed furtherconsideration. There was a danger that such elimination would merely lead to the granting of larger wage increases by the busoperators unless suitable safeguards could be devised.In discussion of the proposal that the LTE should order newrolling stock in France the danger was pointed out that those whowere opposed to the United Kingdom&apos;s entry into the e.c. wouldadduce the resultant loss of jobs in this country as an example of theprobable effects, on a wider scale, once we were members of theCommunity.   Although the French Government might protest ifthe British Government were seen to intervene to ensure that the contract was placed in this country, the fact remained that the Frenchcompany concerned appeared to be receiving assistance from theFrench Government to quote more attractive terms than would otherwise have been possible.  In similar circumstances it was most improbable that the French Government would have permitted theorder to be placed outside France.  The order should therefore notbe placed abroad; and the use of an infrastructure grant as an inducement to the LTE to place the contract in this country seemedfully justified.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the size of the proposed fare increases to be announced by London Transport ought to be limited to 8 per cent at most and preferably to 5 per cent, and that they should not place the order for new rolling stock abroad.   To assist in both these
objectives the LTE should be offered a 50 per cent infrastructure granton the capital cost of the new rolling stock. Strenuous efforts shouldalso be made to persuade the Chairman of the LTE either to limit the provision for future wage increases in his proposal for increasedfares to 5 per cent or to omit altogether any provision for wage increases and to make a further application for a fares increase whenthe level of wage increase in 1972 had been established. TheSecretary of State for the Environment and the Secretary of State for employment should meet the Chairman of LTE that afternoon inorder to pursue these possibilities. The suggestion for general relief for national bus operators from fuel tax would need further considera-tion; and the Secretary of State for the Environment should pursue this proposal with the Chief Secretary, Treasury, and with theChancellor of the Exchequer on his return from abroad. If it wereeventually decided to give such tax relief, this would enable the GLCto make a corresponding reduction in whatever fares increase was proposed to them that week by the LTE.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion and invited the Secretary of State forthe Environment to be guided accordingly.CONFIDENTIALStructure 4.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the SecretaryPlans of state for the Environment on the form of inquiry into structureForm of        plans (CP (71) 102).InquiryThe Secretary of State for the Environment said that theDepartment of the Environment needed, within an acceptable time-table, worthwhile structure and local plans which would implement the new system in the Town and Country Planning Act, 1968, wouldgive effect to regional strategies, would devolve more responsibility tolocal authorities and would provide a basis for effective developmentcontrol and a fair system of compensation. Some administrative action had already been taken for these purposes; and there wasauthority for a Town and Country Planning Bill to simplify statutoryprocedures for preparing plans. These measures would not besufficient, however, unless public opinion was satisfied that structureplans, when submitted, would be dealt with expeditiously. It wastherefore proposed to add to the Bill provisions designed to makethe present inquiry process more relevant to the real character ofthese plans. It was envisaged that in future the Secretary of state should have the power to set out publicly in advance of inquiries intostructure plans the issues which he wished to see publicly examined;that there should no longer be a right for every objector to be heard;and that the Secretary of State should have the power to decide whichobjections were relevant to the issues arising on the plan to whichhis decision would be directed and which should therefore be heardat whatever form of public hearing he approved.
The Home and Social Affairs Committee had discussed theproposals and were in general agreement that they were sound. TheCommittee had been concerned, however, about the political andpresentational implications and about the effect of including theproposals in the Town and Country Planning Bill, since the legislative programme for the coming Session was already heavy andcontentious. Provided that the arguments were properly presented,however, the critics should be silenced and the proposals should be welcomed, since they would expedite the whole development processand would enable the Secretary of State to concentrate more effectively on the main strategic elements of the structure plan while retaining the full traditional inquiry process at the second, local plan,stage. The type of interminable process represented in its extremeform by the Greater London Development Plan inquiry could not bejustified. Moreover, his proposals would significantly reduce theperiod during which an individual^ property would be subjected to&quot;blight&quot; by the publication of broad strategic plans whose detailcould emerge only at the local plan stage; and for this reason alsothey should command the support of all those directly affected.In discussion it was suggested that to deprive an objector of theright to have his objection to a structure plan heard publicly would inevitably attract criticism. Moreover, the proposal that theSecretary of State alone should decide which issues were to be examined publicly was too severe a limitation; it should be possiblefor those conducting the inquiry to consider other issues if, in their view, they were relevant. In the Conservative Party Manifesto at theGeneral Election the infringement of individual rights and theassumption of wide discretionary powers by Ministers and civilservants had been criticised; and it would be difficult to refute thecharge that the present proposals were inconsistent with this attitude in so far as they would erode the rights of individuals and give theSecretary of State wider discretion. It would be unfortunate ifdispute on this issue were added to the other controversies in whichthe Government would be involved in the coming Session. On theother hand the proposals could be presented as a reinforcement of individual rights, since they would make it possible to lift morespeedily the &quot; blight&quot; caused by structure plans. Moreover, the rightof objection would be retained; and, since the structure plans wouldnot contain the degree of detail which previous development planshad included, the right to an individual hearing was less relevant.There was a growing body of opinion, particularly amongst theamenity societies and professional organisations, which was concerned about the prospect of a large number of inquiries on the pattern of the Greater London Development Plan inquiry. Many peopleobjected to planning proposals because they had proprietary interests which could be injuriously affected without compensation; and therewould therefore be presentational advantages in associating thepresent, proposals with proposals for a more generous system ofcompensation. On the other hand it had been established that verylarge sums would be involved in providing reasonably adequatecompensation for injurious affection; and it was unlikely to be possibleto devise proposals which would be sufficiently generous to warrant
delaying a decision on the procedural modifications now envisageduntil the issue of compensation had been further examined and decided.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the proposals in CP (71) 102 would expedite theadministration of town and country planning and would make it more effective. The right ^of individual objection to a structure plan andof individual hearing at a local plan inquiry would be retained; andthe removal of the right of hearing at a structure plan inquiry wouldbe offset by the shortening of the period of &quot; blight &quot;. The Secretaryof State was accordingly authorised to include provisions to give effectto his proposals in the Town and Country Planning Bill for thefollowing Session.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^ summing up of their discussion and invited the Secretary of State forthe Environment to proceed accordingly.Cabinet Office,29 September, 1971.

</content>
</cab>
