<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/30/33 images: 380-389</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF KIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  November 1942.SECRET. Copy No. 9W.P. (42) 503.November 2. 1942.WAR CABINET.EXTRA-TERRITORIALITY IN CHINA.Memorandum by Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I circulate herewith for the information of my colleagues the draft treaty on the abrogation of extra-territorial rights which I have instructedSir H. Seymour to present to the Chinese Government on behalf of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment and the Government of India. This draft is closely similar to thatwhich the United States Government presented to the Chinese Ambassador in washington on the 24th October, but of necessity includes provision for therendition of the British Concessions at Tientsin and Canton.2. The two draft treaties have emerged from consultation between HisMajesty!s Government and the United States Government on the basis of theUnited States proposal contained in W.P. (42) 448, which my colleagues had beforethem at their meeting on the 6th October. The fact that it has been possible both to arrive at almost identical texts for the two treaties and to make the twocommunications to the Chinese Government within a few days of each other(despite the necessity on our side to consult the Governments of the Dominionsand India) has been in great measure due to the most helpful and co-operativeattitude of Mr. Winant, the United States Ambassador in London. On certain points his assistance has, indeed, been invaluable, for example, in securing thatthe United States draft treaty should include a passage in the terms of the second sentence of Article 6.3. This is a point to which I attach importance, since it is designed toensure that during the interim between now and the conclusion of comprehensive and detailed treaties our nationals shall enjoy in matters of commerce, theadministration of justice and taxation treatment not less favourable than is granted to Chinese, just as Chinese in the United Kingdom enjoy at presenttreatment as favourable as that accorded to our own people. It may well be thatthere will be difficulties in securing unconditional Chinese acceptance of thisclause, but it seemed to me that the principle was one which should be raisednow and not allowed to go by default lest the position of our negotiators whencomprehensive treaties come to be made should thereby be prejudiced.4. It had been my intention to endeavour to obtain in connexion with thepresent negotiations a unilateral statement from the Chinese Government inregard to the future status of Shanghai, although, if they were unwilling to make such a statement, not to press them very strongly in the matter. But havingreceived various indications that the United States Government would not be willing to support us in putting this matter to the Chinese Government, I havedecided that it is better to leave the point to be dealt with separately on someother more favourable occasion.5. It will be seen that the Government of India will be a co-signatory ofthe treaty jointly with His Majesty&apos;s Government. The position of the Dominionsis that they have all approved the principle of the abandonment of extra-territorial rights and have raised no objection to the draft treaty which we are nowdiscussing with the Chinese Government. The Governments of Canada and australia propose to make separate treaties with the Chinese Government; the11887   [24569] . B
New Zealand Government will probably adhere to our own treaty by an exchangeof notes with the Chinese Government; and the South African Government have indicated that they would like to find some means of associating themselves with article 2 only of our draft treaty. Since there are specific restrictions on the immigration of Asiatics into the Dominions, some of the Dominion governments have expressed apprehension lest the draft treaty should raise this question, onwhich they are not prepared to make any concession at the present time. It hasbeen pointed out to them that the United States Government is in exactly thesame position, and that, as drafted, the provisions of both the British and UnitedStates treaties are designed to avoid raising this matter.6. Although the British treaty is being negotiated in Chungking and theUnited States treaty in Washington, it is my intention to keep in the closest touch with the United States Government to ensure that our negotiations followparallel courses.A. E.Foreign Office, November 2, 1942.
ANNEX.Abolition of Extra-territoriality in China.British Draft Treaty.(Third Revised Draft. October 27, 1942.)His Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and of the British dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and the President of the National Govern-ment of the Republic of China :Being desirous of defining more clearly in a spirit of friendship the general relations between them, and for this purpose to settle certain matters relating tojurisdiction in China;Have decided to conclude a treaty for this purpose and to that end have appointed as their plenipotentiaries :His Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and of the British dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India (hereinafter referred to as His majesty the King for the United Kingdom of Great Britain and NorthernIreland      .....................      ABfor India .....................      CD   -the President of the National Government of the republic of China    ...      .............     ......      XYWho, having communicated to each other their full powers, found to be in good and due form, have agreed as follows : -Article 1.(i) The territories of the High Contracting Parties to which the presentTreaty applies are, on the part of His Majesty The King, the United Kingdomof Great Britain and Northern Ireland, India, all colonies, overseas territories,protectorates of His Majesty, all territories under his protection or suzeraintyand all mandated territories in respect of which the mandate is exercised byhis Government in the United Kingdom; and on the part of the President ofthe National Government of the Republic of China, all the territories of theRepublic of China. Any reference in subsequent Articles of the present treaty to the territories of one or the other High Contracting Party shall be deemedto relate to those territories of that High Contracting Party to which the presentTreaty applies.(ii) In the present Treaty, the term &apos;&apos; nationals of the one (or of the other)High Contracting Party&quot; shall, in relation to His Majesty The King, mean all british subjects and all British-protected persons belonging to the territories towhich the present Treaty applies; and in relation to the Republic of China, allChinese nationals.(iii) The expression &quot; companies of the one (or the other) High contracting party &quot; shall for the purpose of the present Treaty be interpreted as meaninglimited liability and other companies, partnerships and associations constituted under the law of the territories of that High Contracting Party to which thepresent Treaty applies.Article 2.All those provisions of treaties or agreements in force between His majesty the King and the President of the National Government of the Republic ofChina which authorise His Majesty or his representatives to exercise jurisdiction over nationals or companies of His Majesty in the territory of the Republic ofChina are hereby abrogated. Nationals and companies of His Majesty The Kingshall be subject in the territory of the Republic of China to the jurisdiction of theGovernment of the Republic of China, in accordance with the principles ofinternational law and practice.Article 3.(i) His Majesty The King considers that the final protocol concluded atPeiping on the 7th September, 1901, between the Chinese Government and otherGovernments, including His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom,should be terminated, and agrees that the rights accorded to His Majesty&apos;s.[24569] b 2
Government in the United Kingdom under that protocol and under the agree-ments supplementary thereto shall cease.(ii) His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom will co-operate withthe Government of the Republic of China for the reaching of any necessary agree-ments with the other Governments concerned for the transfer to the Governmentof the Republic of China of the administration and control of the diplomaticquarter at Peiping, including the official assets and the official obligations ofthe diplomatic quarter, it being mutually understood that the Government of theRepublic of China, in taking over administration and control of the diplomaticquarter, will make provision for the assumption and discharge of the officialobligations and liabilities of the diplomatic quarter and for the recognition and protection of all legitimate rights therein.(iii) The Government of the Republic of China shall accord to His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom a continued right to use for official purposes the land which has been allocated to His Majesty&apos;s Government in the UnitedKingdom in the diplomatic quarter in Peiping, on parts of which are locatedbuildings belonging to His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom.Article 4.(i) His Majesty The King considers that the International Settlements at shangai and Amoy should revert to the administration and control of theGovernment of the Republic of China and agrees that the rights accorded to HisMajesty in relation to those settlements shall cease.(ii) His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom will co-operate withthe Government of the Republic of China for the reaching of any necessary agree-ments with the other Governments concerned for the transfer to the Governmentof the Republic of China of the administration and control of the international settlements at Shanghai and Amoy, including the official assets and the officialobligations of those settlements, it being mutually understood that the Govern-ment of the Republic of China, in taking over administration and control of thesesettlements, will make provision for the assumption and discharge of the officialobligations and liabilities of those settlements and for the recognition and protection of all legitimate rights therein.(iii) His Majesty The King agrees that the British Concession (includingthe whole British municipal area) at Tientsin and the British Concessionat Canton shall revert to the administration and control of the Government ofthe Republic of China and that the rights accorded to His Majesty in relationto those concessions shall cease.(iv) The administration and control of the British Concession (includingthe whole British municipal area) at Tientsin and the British Concession atCanton including their official assets and official obligations shall be transferredto the Government of the Republic of China, it being mutually understood thatthe Government of the Republic of China in taking over administration andcontrol of these concessions will make provision for the assumption and dischargeof the official obligations and liabilities of these concessions and for the recognition and protection of all legitimate rights therein.Article 5.(i) In order to obviate any questions as to existing rights in respect of or as to existing titles to .real property in the territory of the Republic of Chinapossessed by nationals and companies of His Majesty The King, or by HisMajesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom, and in particular questionswhich might arise from the abrogation of the provisions of treaties and agree-ments provided for in Article 2 of the present Treaty, the High ContractingParties agree that such existing rights or titles shall be indefeasible and shallnot be questioned upon any ground except upon proof, established through dueprocess of law, that such rights have been acquired by fraud or as a result ofconfiscatory action during the Japanese occupation, in which case the property:shall be restored on such terms as justice shall require to its previous owners.(ii) The High Contracting Parties also agree that if it should be the desireoi the Government of the Republic of China to replace by new deeds of owner-ship existing leases in perpetuity or other documentary evidence relating to real property held by nationals or companies of His Majesty The King or by HisMajesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom, the replacement shall be madeby the Chinese authorities without charges of any sort and the new deeds of
ownership shall fully protect the holders of such leases or other documentaryevidence, and their legal heirs and assigns without diminution of their priorrights and interests, including the right of alienation.(iii) The High Contracting Parties agree further that nationals or companies of His Majesty The King or His Majesty&apos;s Government in the UnitedKingdom shall not be required or asked by the Chinese authorities to make any payments of fees in connexion with land transfers for or with relation to any period prior to the effective date of this Treaty.Article 6.His Majesty The King having long accorded rights to nationals of theRepublic of China within each of the territories of His Majesty to travel,reside and carry on commerce throughout the whole extent of that territory,the President of the National Government of the Republic of China agrees to accord similar rights to nationals of His Majesty within the territory of theRepublic of China. Each High Contracting Party will endeavour to accord inhis territories to nationals and companies of the other High Contracting Partyin regard to all legal proceedings and in matters relating to the administrationof justice, the levying of taxes and requirements in connexion therewith, andthe carrying on of commerce treatment not less favourable than that accorded to his own nationals and companies.Article 7.The consular officers of one High Contracting Party, duly provided withexequaturs, shall be permitted to reside in those ports, places and cities of the territories of the other High Contracting Party which are or may be open toconsular officers of any foreign Power. The consular officers of one HighContracting Party shall have the right within their districts in the territories of the other High Contracting Party to interview, communicate with and toadvise the nationals and companies of the former High Contracting Party, andthe nationals and companies of one High Contracting Party within the territory of the other High Contracting Party shall have the right at all times tocommunicate with the consular officers of the former High Contracting Party.The consular officers of one High Contracting Party in the territories of theother shall be informed immediately by the appropriate local authorities whenany of their nationals are arrested or detained in their consular districts bythe local authorities. They shall have the right to visit within the limits oftheir districts any of their nationals who are under arrest or awaiting trial in prison. Communications from the nationals of one High Contracting Party in prison in the territories of the other High Contracting Party addressed to the consular officers of the former High Contracting Party will be forwarded to theappropriate consular officer by the local authorities. Consular officers of oneHigh Contracting Party shall be accorded in the territories of the other HighContracting Party the rights, privileges and immunities enjoyed by consular officers under modern international usage.Article 8.(i) The High Contracting Parties will enter into negotiations for theconclusion of a comprehensive modern treaty or treaties of friendship, commerce,navigation and consular rights upon the request of either of them or in anycase within six months after the cessation of the hostilities in the war againstthe common enemies in which they are both now engaged. The treaty or treatiesto be thus negotiated will be based upon the principles of international lawand practice as reflected in modern international procedure and in the moderntreaties which each of the High Contracting Parties have respectively concluded with other Powers in recent years.(ii) Pending the conclusion of the comprehensive treaty or treaties referredto in the preceding paragraph, if any questions affecting the rights in the territory of the Republic of China of the nationals or companies of His Majesty The King,or of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom or of the Governmentof India, should arise in future and if these questions are not covered by thepresent Treaty or by the provisions of the existing treaties, conventions and agreements between the High Contracting Parties which are not abrogated by orinconsistent with the present Treaty, such questions shall be discussed by repre-sentatives of the High Contracting Parties and shall be decided in accordance
with the generally accepted principles of international law and with moderninternational practice.Article 9.The present Treaty shall be ratified and the instruments of ratification shallbe exchanged at Chungking as soon as possible. The Treaty shall come intoforce on the day of the exchange of ratifications.In witness whereof the above-mentioned plenipotentiaries have signed thepresent Treaty and affixed thereto their seals.Done at Chungking this day of , 1942, in duplicatein English and Chinese, both texts being equally authentic.


ARMY STRENGTHS.THE Secretary of State for War has prepared a scheme for the reorganisa-tion of the Army for 1943, with which I am in full agreement. The attached paper shows the relation of this new layout to that described in my D.O. (41) 18.Of course, these requirements must be considered in relation to other sectionsof our war programme, and it may be that some compression will be necessary. I earnestly hope, however, that wre shall be able to achieve this plan, which is mostnecessary to our effective conduct of the war.W. S. C.November 1,1942.


</content>
</cab>
