<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/47/33 images: 314-323</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   February 1944.SECRET.W.P. (44) 133.25^/? February, 1944CIVIL CLAIMS AGAINST MEMBERS OF THE UNITEDSTATES FORCES.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.AS my colleagues are aware, this question has been under urgent considera-tion by the interested departments for some time. I have also had. the advantageof discussing it with the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Secretary of Statefor War.  The present position is as follows.2. Satisfactory arrangements have been made for the settlement ofcontractual and affiliation claims. Also &quot;training and manoeuvre&quot; claims(largely damage to crops, &amp;c.) are settled by His Majesty&apos;s Government as amatter of reciprocal aid.3. Satisfactory arrangements were made in 1942 for the settlement of claims in tort (largely arising from negligence in traffic accidents). A UnitedStates Claims Commission was set up with power to award compensation up to a limit of 5,000 dollars, claims for larger sums being referred to Congress. soon after the Commission was established an understanding was reached betweenthe Treasury Solicitor and the United States military authorities in this country that, any judgment within the 5,000-dollar-limit obtained in the United KingdomCourts against a United States driver would be satisfied from United StatesGovernment funds. In addition the Treasury Solicitor entered, into a number ofcollision and. other agreements with insurance companies on behalf of the UnitedStates authorities.4. The United States Government in September 1943 informed us that these agreements and the understanding on which they rested were incompatible withtheir law and practice and they accordingly lapsed. As a result British subjectsare left without any effective redress if they are dissatisfied with the arbitrarydecisions of the United States Commission. Moreover reference of all claimsover 5,000 dollars to Congress must lead to a serious delay in paying compensation.The present position is clearly unsatisfactory.5. Efforts were made by the Treasury Solicitor to induce the United states authorities to return to their original undertaking but without success. Afterconsultation among the interested departments the Foreign Office thereforeaddressed a note to the United States Ambassador at the beginning of november last recalling the undertaking which haH been given and urging that the UnitedStates Government should once more make themselves responsible for ensuring that judgments against members of their Forces would be satisfied. In view of -Parliamentary feeling on the matter strong pressure was put upon the UnitedStates Embassy to agree to this solution, and Lord Halifax took the matter up with Mr. Hull in Washington.6. A reply was received on the 20th January and considered by a meetingof officials.. The United States note, which does not deal directly with the point raised in our note, is in effect a request that His Majesty&apos;s Government should pay under reverse Lend-Lease all non-combat claims of third parties ....arising put of acts of personnel of the Armed Forces of the United States in lineof duty .... which the British Government considers not politically objection- .able.&quot; Read in conjunction with a letter of the same date from the United states embassy this request can only refer to all claims arising out of torts committed by members of the United States Forces on duty, except those which His Majesty&apos;sGovernment wish to exclude for political reasons.7.   The meeting recommended that, subject to a number of conditions, HisMajesty&apos;s Government should agree to this request by undertaking to settle under12288   [26989] &apos;     .Copy No.WAR CABINET.
reciprocal aid such claims against members of the United States Forces as wouldbe accepted by the British Claims Commission if British Service personnel had.been involved.   These are claims arising out of : (a) Traffic accidents.(b) Accidental shootings.(c) Accidental explosions.(d) Loss of or damage to chattels in premises requisitioned by United states forces.(e) Certain other accidents, e.g., practice gunfire, fires in billets, &amp;c.These claims could&quot;be accepted only if they arose out of acts or omissions of UnitedStates Forces in the course of their military duties and upon the following conditions : (a) His Majesty&apos;s Government would have complete freedom to settle these claims in exactly the same way as they settle similar claims of HisMajesty&apos;s Forces.(b) No claim brought by United States nationals or members of the UnitedStates Forces could be accepted.It was proposed that we should ask for full reciprocity as regards members ofHis Majesty&apos;s Forces in the United States and that we should point out that ifthese arrangements were adopted it would be particularly important that UnitedStates troops responsible for accidents should be suitably punished.8. All other claims in tort (i.e., in general claims arising out of actscommitted - off duty) would continue to be referred as at present to the UnitedStates Commission. The claimant in such cases would have no effectiverecourse to the United Kingdom courts but would in practice be in a better position than a person with a similar claim against a member of His Majesty&apos;forces, since the British Claims Commission recognise no liability to pay com-pensation&apos;in such circumstances whereas the United States Commission drawno distinction between on and off-duty claims.9. There are obvious political objections to the suggestion that the british public, who are in the main the victims of these accidents, should be asked topay compensation. On the other hand, His Majesty&apos;s Government have already made themselves responsible for the settlement of training and manoeuvreclaims and claims arising from aircraft crashes, and it is clearly desirable thatBritish subjects injured by United States service vehicles should be placed inthe same position as regards their remedy as those injured by British servicevehicles. The only alternative to proceeding in this way would be to make afurther attempt to persuade the United States authorities to honour their original undertaking, but I see little if any prospect of doing this and none of doing it without considerable delay. There is some truth in the United Statescontention that these claims are incidental to the presence of United states forces in the United Kingdom. Strong pressure has already been put upon them without success and even if they were prepared to agree they would be faced with legal and administrative difficulties which would make an early settlement on these lines impossible. It appears that further representations by us will lead to.a deadlock and meanwhile a number of claimants are being kept out of their money. Finally, public and Parliamentary irritation is increasing and the position is rapidly beqpming untenable. I therefore think it&apos;necessary that we should adopt as soon as possible the course suggested in para-graphs 7 and 8 of this paper and extend the procedure in use for settlingtraining and manoeuvre and aircraft crash damage to these classes of claims.10. If this is agreed there remains the question whether we should under-take responsibility for settling claims in these classes which are now outstanding.In their note the Americans asked us to take over outstanding and future claimswithout distinction and one Member of Parliament has urged that any settle-ment reached should be fully retrospective. Certainly it would be unfortunate if claimants who have instigated pressure in Parliament and have been told thatan early solution of their problem was in sight should now be informed that theironly recourse was a renewal of their application to the United States ClaimsCommission upon the same basis, whereas more favourable treatment would be accorded to later applicants. I consider, however, that if we took over all outstanding claims in these classes we should throw an intolerable burden uponthe British Claims Commission which must in arty case be expanded to deal withfuture American claims, and which I understand will require facilities and perhaps priority for this purpose.  By thus overloading the machinery we should
merely substitute delay by His Majesty&apos;s Government as regards both future andpast claims for delay by the Americans, besides seriously prejudicing theCommission^ existing work of dealing with claims against members of HisMajesty&apos;s Forces and prejudicing its good reputation with the public.11.   In these circumstances I recommend the following course of action : (i) We should assume responsibility for the settlement and payment of claims in the classes set out in paragraph 7 of this paper arising on and after the 19th March.(ii) We should: assume responsibility for the payment but not (except under(iii) below) for the examination of outstanding claims in these cate-gories. We should urge the Americans very strongly to clear up these claims satisfactorily and speedily and should undertake to help themto do so as far as we can. Since the responsibility for payment wouldbe ours it should be possible for the Americans to return for thepurpose of settling these claims to the arrangements which were reached in 1942. It would also be possible under these arrangements to revive the Collision and other Agreements referred to in para-graph 3 of this paper, which are now in suspense, and this would very substantially reduce the number of claims to be settled. In thesecircumstances the Americans would probably be able to settle thelarge majority of the outstanding cases within a reasonably short time.(iii) We should, however, assume at once responsibility for the examinationas well as the payment/of claims in these classes which are over the5,000-dollar limit, since if it were left to the Americans to settlethese, they would be forced to refer them to Congress with a conse-quent delay of many months,12. I believe that these proposals will be satisfactory to Parliament whichis, I think, more concerned that claimants should receive their money promptlythan it is with the method adopted to secure this end. I anticipate no difficultyin the settlement of future claims under these arrangements. There are possibledangers in the method suggested for settling outstanding claims, but I considerthat no difficulty should arise if the Americans work very closely with our ownClaims Commission and accept their advice in all material matters. In general  think we can rely upon them to use proper restraint in assessing these claims,even though it is net they but we who will pay the bills.13. I attach a draft statement which would be made in the House if these arrangements are approved.&apos; -      &apos;// . A.&apos; E.Foreign Office, 25th February, 1944.Draft Statement to be made in the House of Commons.I am glad to be able to announce the settlement of this difficult question.I should first explain that arrangements have been made with the UnitedStates authorities for the settlement of contractual and affiliation claims which appear to be working well in practice, and that &apos;&apos; training and manoeuvre &apos;&apos; claims -are also being dealt with satisfactorily by His Majesty&apos;s Government settling them as a matter of reciprocal aid.This leaves claims arising out of torts committed by the United States forceswhile on duty, of which by far the greater part arise out of accidents on the roads.It is about these claims that a decision is now urgently required and upon whichwe have now reached agreement with the United States Government.Before stating the broad terms of the agreement I should make it clear that satisfactory arrangements for dealing with this class of claims were originallymade on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government with the United States authoritiesin this country, and that these arrangements were working well until about Juneor July of last year. At that date, however, we were informed by the UnitedStates authorities that these arrangements were incompatible with American lawand practice and, as a result, they lapsed in September. I should also like tomake it clear that, although there are a number of claimants whose cases have inconsequence been seriously delayed, the United States Claims Commission have dealt with a very large number of cases to the satisfaction of the parties concerned.
With this background I can now give the House a short statement on the lines on which agreement has been reached with the United States Government. Asfrom the 19th March next His Majesty&apos;s Government will take over and settle,as a matter of reciprocal aid, all claims falling within certain specified classes(of which motor accidents are the most important) arising out of torts committed by United States service personnel on duty in the United Kingdom and NorthernIreland. As from the 19th March, therefore, all such claims will be taken overand dealt with by the British Claims Commission in exactly the same way asthey would be if they were to arise against British service personnel or the british service authorities. English law and practice will apply, and dissatisfiedclaimants will be just as much able to sue the defendants personally in court asthey would British service personnel, and His Majesty&apos;s Government will standbehind any judgments so obtained. We have chosen the 19th March, since Iunderstand that that is the earliest date by which the British Claims commission will be able to deal with all these claims as expeditiously and satisfactorily as they now deal with similar claims against the British service authorities. At the sametime, in order to deter American service personnel from conduct likely to giverise to these claims, the United States service authorities will continue to takestrict disciplinary measures in all instances where United States service personnel are found to be at fault. The United States Government have also promised togive us reciprocal facilities as regards claims arising against British service personnel in the United States. There are a number of other detailed conditions,but I need not trouble the House at present with these.This only leaves the question of accumulated or outstanding claims. It hadbeen suggested to me that any agreement made with the United States authorities on this matter should be retrospective. I have carefully considered the point, buta great difficulty with which we have to deal is the fact- that there are at presentsome 8,000 to 10,000 of such claims which the United States Claims commission have not yet been able to settle. If all these accumulated claims were to be taken over by the British Claims Commission, together with all new claims which a,rearising at the rate, I understand, of 1,000 a week, our machinery would breakdown and both past and future claimants with claims against both UnitedStates and British service personnel would suffer serious delay in getting their claims dealt with.I feel sure the House will agree with me that to take on these extraaccumulated claims and thus invite a breakdown in the whole machinery would be a serious mistake and far more unsatisfactory for the great bulkof these claimants. We have, therefore, agreed with the United States Govern-ment that as a condition of our taking over claims arising out of incidentsoccurring after the 19th March they will make every effort to settle all unpaidj iclaims outstanding at that date. Although, however, such claims will be dealti with by the United States authorities, payment will be made by us and betreated as a matter of reciprocal aid. From this arrangement all claims whichare likely to exceed $5,000 in amount are to be excepted, since the United StatesClaims Commission could not in any event pay them. It is therefore consideredbetter that the British Claims Commission should take over the negotiation ofthese large claims from the outset and make the appropriate payments.With the above exception the United States Claims Commission will make every effort to settle all outstanding claims as soon as possible. I have everyhope that with the assistance of the British Claims Commission, with whom they will work in close co-operation, and with the revival of the Collision andother Agreements which proved so useful earlier on, prompt and fair settlementsof the outstanding cases will be made.I should perhaps add a word about claims arising from acts or omissions ofmembers of the United States forces while off duty. Such claims are not coveredby the present arrangements and will not be taken over by His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment as a matter of reciprocal aid. The only remedy which will be open to theclaimant will be to apply to the United States Commission, who, I understand,often make ex gratia payments in such cases although they do not recognise any legal liability to do so.What I have said represents a brief outline of the arrangements which wehave now made with the United States Government and I hope that they will prove satisfactory. I appreciate that some time has been taken in reachingthese arrangement, but I am sure Members will realise that the question is very complicated and that owing to the interruption of the previous arrangements which were working satisfactorily up till last summer and to the great:accumulation of these claims in the intervening interval it has been impossibleto reach a satisfactory settlement with the United States Government until now.







</content>
</cab>
