<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/54/1 images: 6-11</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC majesty&apos;S GOVERNMENT .The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of..^rr......A^^^f?^.....^^^&apos; ^TOP SECRET Copy Mo......i^f!...CM. 1*4-5)  1ST CONCLUSIONS,  MINUTE 1C onfide at ial Annex(30th May, 1945 - 11.30 a.m.)END IAConstitutionalPositionPreviousReference :f.M. (us)56th(onclusions)The Cabinet had before them a Report &quot;by the india committee (77.F. (k-5) 27k) on the constitutional positionin India,  to which was appended the draft of a statement which, subject to the approval of the Cabinet, might bemade in Parliament by the Secretary of State for India.The Cabinet were reminded that there had alreadybeen preliminary discussion by the Coalition Governmentof this Report &quot;by the India Committee.      The Committee ofMinisters, of all parties, which had examined this matter on &quot;behalf of the Coalition Government had agreed that,if any further step was to &quot;be taken at this stage inrespect of India * s constitutional problem,  the statementappended to that Report represented the best course that could be taken.      Some members of that Committee had grave doubts as to the wisdom of taking any step at this stage,even&apos; on the modified lines proposed by the Report.      Onthe other hand, there would be great advantages if theIndian problem could be dealt with in a way which would command support from all political Parties and would avoidits becoming an issue at the Election, and this was a strong arguement for making a statement&apos; in Parliament on the lines recommended by the Committee.THF: SECRETARY OF STATE POP INDIA said that the Viceroywould be willing to accept the statement appended to theReport as his mandate for discussion on return to India.It was,  of course,  the case that the proposals now putforward were strictly conditional on their acceptance bythe main political parties in India.      There T/as noquestion of negotiation,  and the statement represented a firm offer not to be extended by any negotiation on theViceroy&apos;s part.      If the Indian political parties did not take advantage of this firm offwe should carry on as now, but with the advantage from the point of view of publicopinion in this country and abroad that we should clearly have gone to the utmost limits in the wffer -we had put forward.In reply to a question he confirmed that the offer,  if accepted, would not involve any disclosure of secretmilitary matters to the ViceroyrS Council,  or any inter-ference with the discretion of the Viceroy and Commander--in-Chief in operational matters.discussion showed that it was the general view of theCabinet that a statement should be made by the Secretary ofState for India in terms of the draft appended to&apos;.V.P. (k5) 27k,  and that the Viceroy should treat that statement as his mandate on the specific understanding thatit represented a firm, offer which was not open to any extension by negotiation.-1-

The Cabinet then proceeded to consider certain supple-mentary matters referred to by the India Committee inconnection with the proposed statement, as follows -Indianisation of the army the India Committee had expressed the view that,  if therecommendation put forward by the Secretary of State for Indiaand the Commander-in-Chief in India for the future officeringof the Indian armed services was accepted,  an announcement should be made at the same time as any statement on theconstitutional problem.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he saw the strongestobjection to making any statement at this stage as regards thefuture officering of the Indian Army.      The matter was one that required much closer investigation,, pending which he thought itwould be wiser that the Cabinet should not commit themselves.It was the view of the Cabinet that no public reference should be made at this stage to the further Indianisation ofthe Indian Army.External AffairsThe India Committee had recommended that it should bemade clear in the statement by the Secretary of State inParliament 3  as also by the Viceroy in any statement which he made in India,  that the delegates of British India at the Peace&apos;Conference or at other international conferences would be chosen by the Government of India, consequent on the appointmentof an Indian Member of Council in cdarge of the Portfolio of external Affairs.The Cabinet agreed that the Secretary of State and theViceroy in their respective statements should make it clearthat the Delegates of British India at future international conferences would be chosen by the new Government of India,&apos;Appointment of a United Kingdom High Commissioner in india the Cabinet approved the recommendation of the india committee that a United Kingdoms High Commissioner should beappointed in India to represent the particular interests ofthis country, and that an announcement to that effect shouldbe made by the Secretary of State  in his speech in the Houseof Commons.Release of Certain Political DetaineesThe India Committee had recommended that the Secretaryof State should make it clear,  if the proposals outlined in theReport were accepted by the Indian leaders,  that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment would be prepared to recommend the Central and provincial authorities in India to consider favourably therelease of persons still detained as the result of the Congressresolution of August, 19U2.It was the view of the Cabinet that the Viceroy should say nothing about the release of detainees when he went backto India;    but that,  if the Congress leaders wanted any individual released for purposes of diisaussing the offer ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government, the Viceroy should have discretion to release him and would not thereafter return him to confinement.The balance of the detainees would not,  however, be releasedunless and until the offer which was now put forward had beenaccepted by the Indian political parties and the Central and provincial authorities responsible were agreeable to releasingthem.Office, S..W.1.-2-




</content>
</cab>
