<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/183/23 images: 581-597</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0(75) 73 COPY NO       g r30 June 1975CABINETLEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76Memorandum by the Lord President of the council.    This paper sets out the recommendations of the Queen&apos;s speeches and Future Legislation (QL) Committee for next Session&apos;s programme.   Theproblem facing the Committee has been that the inclusion of all the Billswith strong claims for a place in the programme would require much moreparliamentary time than is available.   Our recommendations involveholding in reserve a considerable number of highly desirable Bills towhich the responsible Ministers rightly attach great importances but forthe reasons indicated below we have thought it essential to put forward a programme of realistic size, tailored to the parliamentary time available.The 1974-75 Session2.    Last Autumn we embarked upon the heaviest programme of legislation which Parliament has seen for many years,   I warned Cabinet then that wewere setting ourselves an over-large legislative target.   The result has been -a. the House of Commons has had to sit late night after night - anaverage of 2 hours after 10.30 pm during the Session - imposingthe quite intolerable strain on Government supporters which theChief Whip described in Cabinet on 15 May (CC(75) 24th Conclusions,Minute l);b. both Houses will have to sit for an extended spillover of some4 weeks starting after the Party Conferences, otherwise we shalllose a considerable number of major Billsf1THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY11 S GOVERNMENT
c. even so we shall fall short of our published legislativetarget, with some major Bills either not published (eg DevelopmentLand Tax) or having to wait until next Session to make progress(Aircraft and Shipbuilding Industries);d, the fulfilment of our programme is placed at the mercy of theOpposition in both Houses - without co-operation in the Lords wehave no hope of completing this Session the major Bills still inthe Commons; and it is not going to be easy to get them through their Commons stages early enough to give them a fair chance in the lords.3.    The Lord Privy Seal and I will do our very best to complete theremaining stages in both Houses of Government Bills now in progress.But the position is now excessively tight, and there can be no guarantee against further casualties.   An extension of this Session which delayedthe start of the new Session by more than one or two weeks would not bea feasible way out of these difficulties.   It would cut down the time available next Session, delaying the introduction or reintroductionand passage of major Bills and substantially reducing the size of nextSessions programme; the extension would have to be for several monthsif it were necessary to fit in a major Autumn Finance Bill.The Size of the 1975-76 programme.    It is against this background that the QL Committee have consideredthe size of next Session&apos;s programme.   We are firmly of the view that a repetition of the difficulties experienced this Session, and inparticular of the great strain which the present overcrowded programmeimposes upon our own supporters, must be avoided.   This object is of higher priority, in our view, than the inclusion in the programme of bills which, however desirable on political or other grounds, it is notvital to enact next Session.   There are indeed positive arguments for keeping some attractive legislation for the third Session of this parliament.   The programme which the Committee accordingly recommendsis estimated to take up fully the parliamentary time available in anaverage Session (which means that a slightly late start this November2
will havo to be made up by reduced time spent in Recesses in 1976).This programme allows no slack for unforeseen contingencies or to accommodate further casualties from this Session.   Therefore furtherBills oan be added to the Programme category only if other Bills areremoved from this category in order to make the necessary room and toprevent any net addition to the parliamentary time required.The Content of the 1975-76 programme.    The programme recommended by the QL Committee is set out in the appendices to this paper.   Bills have been divided into the following catergories -Appendix It   Essential Bills, all of which must be enacted next session because powers or finance would otherwise run out;Appendix lit Contijagent Bills, which may become essential and move into Category I;Appendix Tilt   ProgrammeMils, comprising those important bills which the Government intends to enact next Session.   For thereasons mentioned above, this category can only accommodate Billsthe enactment of which is vital.jjl,,19.7IJ-7.6.    But one point shouldbe mentioned: two Bills (Bail and Peyjelpjanent Board for Rural Wales)are included only on the condition that a Second Reading can beobtained in the House of Commons without the need for additionalfloor time.APi^sndixTV:   Reserve Bills, which would have been strong candidates for places in the programme if there were room.   It may be possiblefor some of these Bills to be brought forward if there isparliamentary time and if they are ready.   Whether authority canbe given for them to be drafted will depend in each case uponinstructions being ready and on whether drafting capacity can be spared from Bills of higher priority.Appendix V:   Scottish Grand Committee Bills, in order of priority.3
Appendix VI:   Other Bi11s, suitable for Second Reading Committeeprocedure or for introduction by a Private Member.   These Billsdo not qualify for the Programme or Reserve categories; theAppendix is attached for information as some of them may reach the Statute Book in 1975-76.6.    A considerable number of other Bills was bid for by departmental ministers, but they are not mentioned in the Appendices as they donot have sufficiently high priority to warrant consideration for next session.7.    I invite the Cabinet to agree -a. that next Session&apos;s programme must be of realistic sizejb. that the categorisation of Bills should be as in the Appendicec. that the list of Programme Bills should be as in Appendix IIIor, if Bills are added to the list, other bills must be removed toleave a programme of the size now proposed.E privy Council Office30 June 1975r I4
APPENDIXTitle of Bill	Department	Purpose	Length in clauses1   Armed Forces	MOD	To continue, and amend where necessary, the Naval Discipline Act 1975 and the Army and Air Force Acts 1955	under 502(a)Energy Supply      ) and Conservation ) ) (b)Amendment of        ^	Energy	To provide permanent powers for the United Kingdom to fulfil its obligations under the IEP, and to provide for the enforcement of. energy conservation measures	14Gas Act 1972        ) ] ]		To make permanent existing temporary relaxations on the gas industry&apos;s statutory obligations to supply industrial users	Short3   Coal Industry	Energy	To increase the NCB*s borrowing limits; to provide financial assistance to the pension scheme and the Redundant Mineworkers1 payment scheme; to provide enabling powers to protect the coal industry against short-term fluctuations in prices of competing fuels	6-8 i1h   Iron and Steel \ ii.	Industry	To extend bsc&apos;s borrowing limit; to increase the Secretary of State&apos;s power over the steel industry and to provide for a statutory Consumers&apos; Council	6-85   Northern Ireland (Emergency Provisons) Act \ (Amendment)	NIO	To amend the 1973 Act and to make provisions to deal with terrorism and subversion in accordance with the Gardiner Report	1&apos;5LE&amp;ISLATIVS PROGRAMME 1975-76I ESSENTIAL BILLS
TitleDepartment6   National Loans Fund(Northern Ireland)7. PricesCivil List9(a)0ECD Financial)Support Fund(b) international monetary FundNIODPCPTreasuryTreasuryPurposeTo increase the statutory limit on borrowings fromthe National Loans fund in respect of NorthernIrelandTo provide for the replacement of powers in Part II of the counter-Inflation Act 1973To amend the 1972 civil list Act and to authoriseincreases from votes to enable the United kingdom to participate in the OECDFinancial Support fund to enable the United Kingdom1sIMF quota to be increasedLengthin clauses-FairlyShort3-42-32-3LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76I ESSENTIAL BILLS
Title of BillLEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76II CONTINGENT BILLS1    Agriculture (Miscel-laneous Provisons)2    Fishery Limits3  *United Kingdom Volun-tary SafegaurdsUnder Non-Prolifera-tion Treatyk   Vehicle regulation and Taxation5   Anguilla6   Privy Council Appeals(Australia) Abolition7   Rhodesia8   Prevention of Terrorism(Temporary Provisons)9   Northern IrelandConstitution10   Regional EmploymentDepartmentPurposeMAFFMAFFEnergyDOEFCOFCOFCOHONIOTreasuryLengthin clausesTo provide additional funds for the AgriculturalMortgage Corporation; towind up the Sugar Board and topermit metricationTo extend fishing limits to 200 miles, and to giveeffect to e.c. fisheriespolicy if necessaryTo implement the UK/EURATOM/idea Safeguards agreement to change the basis ofvehicle taxationTo make provision forthe separation of Anguillafrom St Kitts-NevisTo abolish appeals fromAustralian State courts to the Privy CouncilTo provide for a settlementof the Rhodesia problem to re-enact the provisionsof the Prevention of terrorism (Temporary Provisions)Act 1974To make constitutionalprovisions for NorthernIrelandTo reform the REPup to 2010Short12up to 3013i not known10* q.Suitable for Second Reading Committee procedure3
LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76III BILLS RECOLffiENDID FOR INCLUSION IN THE PROGRAMMEOil and Gas FiredPower Stations(Restrictions of fuel)7    Agricultural TiedCottages8(a)Drivers* Hours and )Records )(b)Minimum DrivingAge etcEnergyDO!doerisks of introducingS&amp;HWR stations to implement EECdirectives forGovernment approval of construction of power stations using natural gas or petroleum products to give security of tenure to occupiers ofagricultural tiedcottages&apos;To bring United Kingdomdrivers1 hours into line with e.c. regulationsj To alter the minimumi driving age, in accordance&apos; with e.c. regulationsBills underlined are Manifesto or Queen1s Speech commitments.4Title of Bill                j		Department	Purpose	Length in clauses;1    Devolution		Privy Council	To establish elective assemblies for Scotland and Wales	long2(a)Parliamentary ] Pensions		CSD and Privy Council	To improve MP&apos;s pensions arrangements	20(b)Public Offices* (Salaries)		CSD	To link C and AG&apos;s and important&apos;s salaries to those of Permanent Secretaries	2-43    Education (Miscel-laneous Provisions)		DES	To require local authorities to introduce comprehensive education; to make provisions relating to school leaving dates, milk and transport	short4    Dockworkers1 Employment		DE	To extend and improve the Dock Labour Scheme , ,	20-255    Nuclear Power Stations (Financial Arrange-ments)		Energy	To authorise Government to share with CEGB and SSEB the extra costs and	320i        2
	CONFIDENTIAL LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76		Ill BILLS RECOffiffiNDED FOR INCLUSION IN THE PROGRAMME (oontinued)			Title of Bill	Department	Purpose	Length in clauses9   Road Traffic	DOE	To relate-bus and car licensing provisions to assist rural transport	5-1010 /official Information (Franks)	HO	To replace section 2 of the Official Secrets Act	short11    Police Complaints Procedure	HO	To establish a Commission with power to influence action taken in pursuance of complaints	612   Race Relations	HO	To strengthen the powers and machinery for dealing with race relations	50-6013  *Bail	HO	To reform bail procedures	1014   Aircraft and Shipbuilding	Industry	To take the aircraft and shipbuilding industries	55Industries		into public ownership	15   Post Office (Giro)	Industry	To provide for a capital reconstruction, financial objectives and widening of the banking powers of GIRO	10 1116   Trustee Savings Banks	Treasury	To provide for the exapanion of TSB&apos; banking services	4017   Development Land Tax	Treasury (inland Revenue)	To impose a tax on development values realised from land	50 +10 schedules18 -fDevelopment Board for Rural Wales	WO i i	To establish a Board to promote the co-ordinated development of rural Wales	20^ To be included in Queen&apos;s Speech without commitment to legislate Bills underlined are Manifesto or &quot;Queen&apos;s Speech commitments			* Place in programme dependent upon Second Reading Committee procedure			II* Place in programme dependent upon Welsh Grand Committee procedure or use of Welsh day for Second Reading 5 II &apos;,;			
LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76IV   RESERVE BILLSTitle of BillDepartmentPurposeLengthin clauses1   Public Lending Right2  Construction IndustryContracts (The Lump)3  Direct LabourOrganisations4 Landlord and Tenant5 *Local Government(General Powers)6 Maplin development authority Dissolution7 New Towns (Misoella-neous Provisions)3 PortsI (9 *Rent (Student Lettings)10 Town and Country PlanningDESDOEDOEDOEDOEDOEDOEDOEDOEDOETo establish publiclending rights forauthorsTo set up a statutoryConstruction IndustryManpower board to extend localauthorities1 powersto operate direct labour organisations to remedy anomalies inthe law dealing withleasehold reform and service charges to incorporate clausesfrom local acts ingeneral law to dissolve the MaplinDevelopment authority and to withdraw planningpermissionsTo transfer housing etcfrom new towns to localauthorities,To bring ports into public ownership and to establish a National Ports AuthorityTo provide for registeredlettings to students tobe excluded from Rent ActprotectionTo implement the Dobryreport on planningprocedures*Bills suitable for Second Reading Committee procedureBills underlined are Manifesto or Queen&apos;s Speech commitmentsunder 5short-medium3-440-50short806
LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76IV  RESERVE BILLS (continued)Title of BillDepartmentPurposeLengthin clauses11    Nurses12    a. Occupational   )Pension Scheme)(Registrationetc)h. Social Security)Amendment        )13    Private Practice14&apos;   Conspiracy15   Representation ofthe People (service voters)16    Co-oporatiyeDevelopment Agency17Administration ofJusticeDHSSDHSS18Congenital Disabilities19 Exemption ClausesDHSSHOHOIndustryLord chancellor lord ChancellorDPCPTo implement the 1972Briggs&apos; report on thetraining of nursesTo regulate the conductof occupational pensionschemesTo make miscellaneouschanges in arrangementsfor national insurance and supplementary benefits to abolish paybeds inNHS hospitals and toregulate the developmentof private practice to limit the penalties for conspiracyTo amend the provisions relating to the electoral registration of servicevotersTo establish a Co-operativeDevelopment agency to implement the PhillimoreReport on contempt of court and. the Payne Committee&apos;srecommendations on thetransfer of High Court-judgements to the county court, and to makemiscellaneous improvements to implement the LawCommissions Report onInjuries to Unborn Children8013ShortShort-mediumShort1030-35To limit the avoidance ofcivil liability for breach of contract and negligenceDills underlined are Manifesto or Queen&apos;s Speech commitments7
LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76IV RESERVE BILLS (continued)			Title of Bill	Department	Purpose	Length in clauses&apos; Fair Trading j  (Amendment)	i DPCP	To make miscellaneous amendments to the Pair Trading Act	30; heights and Meaaures i (Amendment)	DPCP	To make changes relating to imperial and metric weights and measures, and to extend consumer protection	6,;    &apos;Civil Aviation Act 1971 (Amendment)	Trade	To provide policy guidance to the Civil Aviation Authority	Under 10Companies Accounts, Returns and Registration	Trade	To improve the law relating to the accounts, information and registration of companies	25-30I ^Insolvency i,                        ,	Trade	To amend the law relating to bankruptcy	15Merchant Shipping I	Trade	To ratify the International Convention on Liability for Carriage by Sea snd to deal with other merchant shipping matters	up to 100Patents	Trade 1 1 ! 1 &apos; 11	To amend patent law and to enable the United Kingdom to join the Patent i Co-operation Treaty and Patent Conventions	100lills suitable for Second Reading Committee procedureiills Underlined are Manifesto or Queen&apos;s Speech commitments8&apos; &apos;      ; &apos;&apos;&apos;      I! 11
LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76V SCOTTISH GRAND COMMITTEE BILLSTitle of BillDepartmentPurposeLengthin clauses1    Electricity(Eorrowing Powers)(Scotland)2    Education(Scotland)(Amendment)3   freshwater fisheries (Scotland)4   Crofting Reform(Scotland)5    Complaints againstthe Police6   Registration of title to Land(Scotland)7    Marriage8   Licensing (Scotland)9   Damages for InjuriesCausing Death(Scotland)10    Fatal Accidents andSudden DeathEnquiries (Scotland)SOSOSOSOSOSOSOSOSOSOTo extend the borrowing powers of ScottishElectricity BoardsTo implement the proposals   I        12of the Boughton Reportrelating to negotiating machinery for teachers1 pay to improve and control S        10public trout fishing rights to reform the crofting 23tenure system to introduce an t 6independent elementto the investigation of complaints against the! police to introduce a system of 50registration of title to modernise the law of \ 50marriageTo reform the liquor ICOlicensing lawsTo implement the Law !        14Commission Report onDamages for InjuriesCausing DeathTo amend the Fatal 11Accidents etc Acts of1895 and 1906Bills underlined are Manifesto or Queen&apos;s Speech commitments
JLEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76VI OTHER BILLS(i) Bills possibly suitable for Second Reading Committee ProcedureTitle of bill    Gun Barrel Proof2   Offshore OperationsLiability for Pollution3   Ancient MonumentsAmendment andArchaeological Areask   Endangered Species(Restriction ofImports and Exports)5   Transport of Perishablefoodstuffs6   Housing (miscellaneous provisions)7   BurialDiplomatic Privileges(Special Missions)9   State ImmunityDepartmentMODEnergyDOEDOEDOEDOEDOEPCOFCOPurposeTo amend the Gun BarrelProof Act 1868 to enablethe united Kingdom tobecome a member of thePermanent international commission for the proof of Small FirearmsTo ratify the Autumn1975 Convention on compensation for damagefor pollutionTo modernise existingancient monumentslegislation and toprovide opportunities for archaeologicalinvestigation priorto development to consolidate existing law and to ratify the march 1973 Convention on international TradeTo ratify the convention on the Transport ofPerishable foodstuffs to make miscellaneousamendments in housinglawTo provide machineryfor maintaining andmanaging non-localauthority cemeteriesTo implement the UNConvention on the privileges of SpecialMissions1To amend the law on immunityand to ratify a Council ofEurope Convention on StateImmunityLengthin clauses25-3014152020-30id
LEGISLATIVE PROGRAM?&apos; 1975-76VI OTHER BILLS (continued)(i) Bills possibly suitable for Second Reading Committee Procedure (continued)Title of Bill10    Crimes againstInt international ionallyProtected Persons11    Colonial Stock Act1877 (Amendment)12   Foreign Compensation13   Extradition14    Criminal Appeal Act(Amendment)15   Domestic Proceedings16   Forgery andCounterfeit Currency17   Conversion andDetinue18   Rentcharges19   CinematographFilmsDepartmentECOPCOECOHOHOHOHOLordChancellorLordChancellorTradePurposeTo ratify the convention on the Prevention andPunishment of Crimesagainst InternationallyProtected persons to amend the ColonialStock Act 1877To tako over anddistribute Tsaristassets in the UKTo modernise the law governing extraditionTo remedy a defect insection 2 of the criminal appeal Act 1968iTo implement the law commission^ recom-mendations on matrimonialproceedings in magistratescourtsTo modernise and codifythe law on forgery andcounterfeit currencyTo implement the Lav/Committee&apos;s Reporton Conversion and DetinueTo give effect to theLaw Commission^ Reporton the extinction ofrentchargesTo provide for payments by the British Film FundAgency to the national film Finance Corporation,and for grants from the! NFFC to persons associatedI with film productionLengthin clauses11301-230-501910-15short
LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1975-76VT OTHER BILLS (continued)(ii) Bills possibly suitable for offering to a Private MemberTitle of Bill	Department i	Purpose	Length in clauses1    Youth and Community	DES             1 i 1	To implement proposals from the review of the Youth Service	5-7j 2   Medical Act (Amendment)	1 DHSS (with SO, WO and NIO)	To implement the Morrison Report	4-51 3   Control of fireworks I 1	DPCP	To improve control over the sale and use of fireworks	6-8j4   Presumption of Death (Scotland)	SO	To implement the Law Commission Report on presumption of death	201 5   Solicitors (Scotland)	SO	To provide for lay representation on disciplinary tribunals	201 6   Divorce (Scotland)	SO	To reform the law relating to divorce and aliment	15 ii&quot;1 7   Stock Account	Trade	To enable the Stock Exchange to introduce a new settlement and stock trawler system M	Under 10 j !Bills underlined are Manifesto or Queen!s Speech commitments12


</content>
</cab>
