<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/259/0 images: 72-76</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.Printed for the Cabinet, January, 1936SECRET.Oopr No.   &quot; &amp;CP. 12 (36)THE CABINETTHE IMPORTANCE OF ANGLO-JAPANESE FRIENDSHIPMEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WARI circulate for the information of my colleagues a Memorandum prepared by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff.D. C.The War Office,11th January, 1936.MEMORANDUM BY THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL staff at intervals during the past 18 months the Japanese Foreign Office has dropped hints to His Majesty&apos;s Representative in Tokyo that they would welcome closer relations between Britain and Japan. Within the past few days it has been reported that leading Japanese soldiers are of the same opinion. In view of the present high degree of control exercised by the Japanese General Staff over the destinies of Japan, this expression of opinion is significant.^2. The moment seems opportune, therefore, not only to put forward once more the reasons for believing that we ha^e now a chance to regain our friendly influence with Japan, but also to urge that such a chance should be seized before it is too late.3. In this connection the following extract from the Report of the Defence Requirements Sub-Committee (D.R.C. 14, dated 28th February, 1934) will bear repetition 8. &quot; We consider that advantage should be taken of any opportunity to improve our relations with Japan . . . We cannot overstate the importance we attach to getting back, not to an alliance (since that would not be practical politics) but at least to our old terms of cordiality and mutual respect with Japan . there is already some speculation as to the future extent of Japan&apos;s relations with Germany. Success on our part would not only bring us increased security, but might enable us to correct or obviate any unhealthy tendency of this kind in Japanese policy.&quot;And in the latest (third) Report of the Defence Requirements Sub-Committee (D.P.R. 52 dated 21st November, 1935, but not yet considered by the Cabinet) the following statement appears : &quot; The Relationship between Foreign Policy and Defence.16. We consider it to be a cardinal requirement of our national and imperial security that our foreign policy should be so conducted as to avoid the possible development of a situation in which we might be confronted simultaneously with the hostility, open or veiled, of Japan in. the Far East, Germany in the West, and any Power on the main line of communication between the two. So far as Japan is concerned, in our previous Report we emphasised strongly the importance of an ultimate policy of accommodation and neighbourliness with that country. Recent events accentuate the desirability of that policy, difficult though it may be to carry out,&quot;As far as the General Staff know, nothing has been done to implement these recommendations.* A selection of Japanese views will be found in the Appendix.
4. There is no doubt that Japan is feeling isolated, particularly since the hard words spoken against her at Geneva and her subsequent withdrawal from the League. At home, her financial situation, though not yet desperate, is very unhealthy ; her agricultural industry is acutely depressed, and her manufacturers are experiencing ever-increasing difficulty in finding new markets overseas for their goods. Abroad, her Manchurian adventure, whilst still a serious financial liability, is not yielding nearly as many assets in the way of raw materials as was expected. Russia, now a member of the League, is a constant source of anxiety, and is growing ever stronger. Japan&apos;s present adventure in North China has not so far gone according to plan ; and, the deeper she penetrates into China, the stiffer is Chinese resistance likely to become, and the more expensive will Japan find her search for raw materials and markets in that country. Finally, she must be aware of the risk that her pride, which has forced her to denounce the 5:5:3 ratio at the Naval Conference, may tend to drive Britain and the United States into each other&apos;s arms.5. On 5th November, 1935, Sir R. Clive wrote a despatch (No. 553) in which he analysed the state of Anglo-Japanese relations. Sir Robert makes it clear once again that, in his opinion any idea of Anglo-American co-operation against Japan would be deeply resented. He makes various quotations tending to show that amongst certain prominent Japanese there is a growing feeling of self-satisfaction in Japan, and a determination to dominate the Far East against all opposition. He adds that according to his information there is already a definite arrangement for the exchange of military information between the German and Japanese General Staffs.Sir Robert concludes by pointing out that the Japanese were extremely surprised at the strong stand recently taken by His Majesty&apos;s Government at Geneva, and that after the present crisis is over there may be &quot; less disinclination for co-operation &quot;. He points out that the stronger our forces are in the Far East the more we shall be respected.6. It is possible that in his final conclusion Sir Robert may be right. But the chances of being able permanently to station any large number of armed forces in the Far East appear so remote at present that the General Staff are of the opinion that other methods should at least be given a trial.Moreover, the above-mentioned despatch was written two months ago and Sir R. Clive has himself since reported quite different views as now being held in Japan. For example) in his telegram 350 of 27th December, 1935, he reported that senior Japanese Military officers have their own reasons for wishing &quot; to improve relations with Great Britain.&quot; These reasons, Sir Robert states, are their uncertainty as to the attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the event of another Russo-Japanese war, and the realization that &quot; an unfriendly England might be disastrous.&quot; They fear that &quot; we might induce America to stand in with us against them.&quot; Furthermore, the &quot; strong line taken over sanctions &quot; has &quot; surprised and upset them.&quot;And subsequently, on 11th January, 1936, he reported that the Japanese naval authorities had stated that they would prefer a political agreement with us to any naval treaty.For all these reasons it is easy to see why both civil and military leaders in Japan are ready to come to a political agreement with us. Nor does the moment appear any less opportune from our point of view.7. One of our greatest dangers would be a combination of Germany and Japan. This is not an unlikely result of existing conditions. Both countries have been compelled to leave the League and are in consequence feeling rather isolated ; both have an idea that their main enemy is Russia ; and there remain in Japan, and no doubt in Germany too, many cordial ties between the two armies, relics of the time when the Japanese Army was taught by German instructors. Only Anglo-Japanese friendship seems likely to deter Japan from entering into closer relations with Germany.8. It is true that Japan&apos;s actions, for some years now have shown an almost complete disregard for our interests in the Far East. Particularly is this the case as regards our trade, as, for example, the oil monopoly in Manchuria. Similar discrimina-tions are almost certain to be enforced in North China once the Japanese hold on that region is made good. Innumerable other instances might be cited, as, for instance, the prohibition of training for British troops last year at Shanhaikwan ; the agitation against the (mainly British) Municipal Council in Shanghai ; the building of an -aerodrome at Swatow ; the penetration of Japanese agents into Canton and Kwangsi ; the attempts to get a footing in Macao and Hainan Island ; or the bad manners of Japanese sailors in Hong Kong itself. These pin pricks, and worse, are more than anything symptoms of Japan&apos;s bewilderment and exasperation in the face of what she
regards as our equivocal, if. not unfriendly, attitude towards her Far Eastern problems. Under present conditions we are quite unable to make any effective protest against these pin pricks ; nor, in any case, do protests make much impression on the Japanese mind. It is suggested that a satisfactory solution, leading automatically to cessation of these annoyances, is only to be found in convincing Japan of our sincere desire for friendly co-operation, is.//.,*in China, where such a policy seems to offer the only chance of staving off the total extinction at Japanese hands of our trade and interests in that country.9. It is, however, from the strategic point of view that the most weighty arguments for maintaining friendly relations with Japan can be put forward.The present crisis in Europe has clearly shown the dangers to our Lines of Communication through the Mediterranean in face of the hostility of any Mediterranean Power. With a hostile Italy, for example, our Lines of Communication through the Mediterranean would, in time of war, become precarious if not impossible. It is possible that even in these circumstances the fleet might be able to force its way through the Mediterranean in order to get quickly to the Far East, and it is probable that after the present crisis is over, Italy will find it convenient for financial or other reasons to abandon her hostile attitude towards us. Be that as it may, it seems unlikely, in the present unsettled and inflammable state of affairs in Europe, that any British Government would allow the fleet to get so far away from the vital area in Europe. The conclusion is that, so long as affairs in Europe remain unsettled, our interests in the Far East, at any rate north of Singapore, are at the mercy of the Japanese. It would seem a reasonable precaution, therefore, to try, by every means and even at some cost, to safeguard, by an amicable agreement with Japan, interests which we are unable to protect by military measures. There is, needless to say, no occasion to present the matter to the Japanese in this (for us) unfavourable light, but rather as a step towards implementing the late Foreign Secretary&apos;s recent remark on the necessity (which we recognise) for securing a better and more equitable distribution of the World&apos;s supplies of raw materials. It will be remembered that at the time this utterance wa3 made it was seized upon with avidity by the Japanese.10. Another point arises which is pertinent to current events, and that is the question of the outcome of the Naval Conference. As matters stand&apos;at present, there appears very little hope of a successful result being obtained. Japan has made it clear that she has little or no interest in the size of the British Navy, appreciating as she does our very wide commitments and absence of any aggressive designs. It is in the United States Navy that she professes to see her danger, and what she fears most is an Anglo-American combination. It .seems highly probable, therefore, that the prospect of a political agreement with us, which would remove the latter fear, might lead Japan to take a far less uncompromising attitude at the Conference and give good hopes of a reasonable and satisfactory agreement being reached.11.. Events are moving fast in the Far East, and it is clear that we are already faced with the prospect of a gradual loss of our whole commercial position there by peaceful penetration on the part of Japan, and that without a shot being fired. A political agreement with Japan does, however, still appear to offer a chance of&apos; saving much of our position, and that too by peaceful means, if we will but seize the opportunity.But the opportunity will not wait indefinitely for us to seize it. If we are to forestall Germany, we must make up our minds forthwith and act quickly.12. Lest it be thought that the difficulties of the situation have not been fully appreciated, it must be stated quite definitely that it is realized that the problem is not an easy one to solve. The major obstacles which have to be overcome appear to be : (a) the recognition of Manchukuo and possibly of Japan&apos;s &quot; rights &quot; in NorthChina, in face of the attitude towards these questions of the League of Nations and America ;(b) the difficulty of dealing with a nation whose foreign policy is mainly dictated by soldiers.13. In view, however, of our extremely weak military situation in the Far East, it is felt to be essential on strategical grounds that every possible effort should be made to overcome these political difficulties.(9196)
As regards (a) in paragraph 12, it is undoubtedly true that Great Britain, relying on an historic and partly sentimental friendship, is in a better position to exercise a moderating influence over Japan than any other Power or combination of Powers. It is thus reasonable to hope that, in so far as we should be able to exercise a restraining influence on Japan&apos;s activities in China, the reopening of friendly relations between us and Japan wouid be of direct benefit to, and would not be Unduly opposed by, China. Failing opposition on the part of China, neither the League of Nations nor America would have much reason to interfere.As regards (b) it may be hoped that the recent changes in the higher command in Japan will have a moderating influence on military policy, whilst the desire of the General Staff for an agreement with us (vide paragraph f) has already been referred to.Thus it is thought possible that the political difficulties might be overcome ; the General Staff urge most strongly that at any rate an effort to do so should be made, and made soon.
APPENDIX1. Tokyo Telegram 172 of 3rd July, 1934.Reports that Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs stated that Japan would be ready to sign non-aggression pacts with England and America.2. Tokyo Telegram 209 of 30th August, 1934.Reports that Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs stated that &quot;there was a growing feeling in Japan in favour of friendliest relations with Great Britain.&quot;3. Tokyo Telegram 232 of 29th September, 1934.Reports that Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs, at a dinner in honour of the F.B.I. Mission, &quot; went on to talk of Japan&apos;s desire for closer relations of friendship,&quot; and that &quot; Japanese Government were very anxious in case Naval Conference failed that there should be no break in friendly relations with Great Britain and he would like to see some definite understanding.&quot;4. Military Attache, Tokyo, Memo. No. 332 of 29th November, 1935.Forwards a letter from Consul-General, Mukden, No. 270 of 2nd November, 1935, reporting a conversation with Major Yahagi, Assistant to General Doihara, head of the Kwantung Army special mission to Manchukuo. Major Yahagi stated that &quot; officers of his rank and age were the last representatives of pro-British feeling in the Army &quot;. He spoke of the bitter feelings of his juniors at what they considered the ill-treatment of Japan by us, and added that, although so far these sentiments had been suppressed by the older school, the influence of the latter was &quot;declining year by year&quot;, and soon it might be too late. He felt sure that &quot; if His Majesty&apos;s Government were alive to the real facts in the Far East, they would be anxious to co-operate with Japan, with whose goodwill the prosperity, and even, he might say, the existence of our Empire was inextricably linked &quot;.5. Tokyo Telegram 336 of 17th December, 1935.Reports that Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs stated that if no naval agreement resulted, he thought a &quot; political understanding between Great Britain, United States of America and Japan was essential &quot;.6. Tokyo Telegram 350 of 27th December, 1935.Reports that there are indications that senior military officers are anxious to improve relations with Great Britain for various reasons.7. Tokyo Telegram 13 of 11th January, 1936.Reports that the Secretary of Japanese Minister of Marine told the British Naval Attache that they would much rather have a political agreement with Great Britain than any Naval treaty.(b36/8)   60  1/36   w.o.p.  9196

</content>
</cab>
