<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/259/0 images: 139-193</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1936..SECRET. Copy No.CP. 14 (36).CABINET.THE ATLANTIC AIR ROUTE.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.ON the 4th December, 1935, the Cabinet approved of the proposals contained in memorandum CP. 222 (35), which set out the proposals provisionally agreed to by the delegations at Ottawa; and the Cabinet gave instructions that the British Delegation should be authorised to inform the other Delegations that the British Government were prepared to endorse the provisional agreement.I now circulate to my colleagues the Report of the United Kingdom Delegation on their mission. It will be seen that the details of the provisional agreement, as finally settled at Ottawa, are in accord with the Cabinefs decision; and I ask authority, in conjunction with the Secretary of State for the Dominions, to obtain the necessary agreement of the Dominion Governments to the proposed plan.I think the Cabinet will agree that the British Delegation have conducted a difficult negotiation with skill and thoroughness, and that it is&apos; an admirable example of team work. The Cabinet will also observe that the attitude of the Canadian Government was a great deal more forthcoming than might at one time have been expected. That of the United States Government was less forth-coming, but we had expected that they would decline, as a Government, to commit themselves, and would insist on the negotiations taking place between the two companies. These negotiations were, I think, as satisfactory as could be expected; and, of course, the Managing Director of Imperial Airways acted throughout in. the closest collaboration with his Government colleagues on the British Delegation.S.January 16, 1936.[12597]

confidential88ReportofUnited Kingdom Air Mission to North AmericaNovember December, 1935&quot;r-
TABLE OF CONTENTS.Pages1. Report of Mission.................      .. 1-9(a) Minute submitting Report to the Chairman of the Interdepartmental Committeeon International Air Communications        ..      ..      ..       ..       ..      .. 1(6) Constitution and purpose of Mission (paragraph 1)            ..       ..       ..      .. 2(c) Departure from England (paragraph 2)         ..      ..      ..       ....       .. 2(d) Discussions on board R.M.S. Montrose (paragraphs 3-8)     ..       ..       ..       .. 2-3(e) Arrival in Canada (paragraph 9)         ..       ..      ..      ..       ..      ..       .. 3(/) Discussions in Ottawa (paragraphs 10-19)      ..      ..      ..      ..       ..       .. 3-5(g) Departure for, and arrival in, Washington (paragraphs 20-21)      ..       ..       .. 6(h) Discussions in Washington (paragraphs 22-35)        ..      ..       ..       ..       .. 6-8(i) Departure for, and arrival in, England (paragraph 36)     ...       ..       ..       .. 9(j) Discussions in New York (paragraph 37)       ..      ..      ..       ..       ..       .. 92. Appendices to Report      f........      ......      ..      .. 10-49I. Telegam from the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs to the Secretary of Statefor External Affairs of Canada suggesting heads of discussion   ..       ..       .. 10-11II. Papers relating to the discussions in Ottawa, circulated by His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in Canada       ..      ..       ..      ..      ..       ..      ..       .. 12-33III. Text of letter from Colonel Sir Donald Banks to Colonel V. I. Smart      ..       .. 34-35IV. Announcement made to the Press at the conclusion of the discussions in Ottawa 36V. Aide-Memoire on postal questions communicated to Mr. J. Lamiell of theUnited States Post Office and Mr. P. T. Coolican of the Canadian Post Office .. 37VI. Documents drafted in Washington by Mr. G. E. Woods Humphery, Managing Director of Imperial Airways, and Mr. J. T. Trippe, President of Pan-american airways         ..      ..      ..      ..      ..      ..      ..       ..       ..       .. 38-44VII. Letters from the United States Secretary of Commerce to the United states secretary of State     . .       ..       . .       ..       ..       ..       ..       ..       .. 45-46VIII. Announcement made to the Press at the conclusion of the discussions in washington    ..       . .       ..       ..       ..       ..       ..       ..       ..       .. 47IX. Note of a discussion at the Offices of Pan-American Airways in New York onFriday, 13th December, 1935        .............. 48-49
Confidential1Sir Warren Fisher,We submit the accompanying report on the mission to North America which was under-taken following discussions in the Interdepartmental Committee on Civil Aviation.The report indicates that a full measure of agreement was achieved with the representatives of the Irish Free State, Canada, Newfoundland and the United States of America as regards the desirability of establishing a Transatlantic air service with these countries by means of a company operated by Imperial Airways and representative of the three Commonwealth countries on the one hand, and Pan American Airways on the other ; and the basic arrange-ments provisionally agreed upon for the operation of this service are set out in detail in the report and appendices.It now remains for the Governments of Canada and of the Irish Free State to approve these arrangements and for the United States Government to approve the application of Imperial Airways for landing rights.The decision of the Canadian Government will be influenced by considerations arising out of the necessity for nominating a Company to take up the Canadian shareholding in the Joint Operating Company. This presents a number of problems owing to the political atmosphere surrounding transportation in Canada and correlated questions of Trans-Canadian Air Services. Further steps in this regard should no doubt be undertaken through the medium of the Dominions Office.The decision of the Irish Free State Government, though it is understood to have been given in principle, is dependent on questions of the finance of the Irish Air Port, the subsidy contributions and the status of the meteorological services in Ireland. These questions seem appropriate to be pursued further by the Air Ministry in consultation with the Treasury and the Dominions Office.So far as the United States of America are concerned, further progress is dependent on the negotiations between Imperial Airways and Pan-American Airways, and it would seem advisable to await the return of Mr. Woods Humphery before the next steps are taken.In submitting this report we cannot fail to mention the superlative work done by all our colleagues in the United Kingdom delegation- by Mr. McClure, whose technical knowledge and keenness were invaluable in cultivating excellent relations both in Canada and the United States and in the collection of much important data, by Mr. Entwistle, who was successful in securing most useful collaboration in the important matter of meteorology, and by Captain Lumley, whose great knowledge and wide postal acquaintanceships were of the utmost assistance in complicated mail questions. Mr. Syers made an admirable Secretary, in addition to his contributions of a quasi-diplomatic order, and both to him and to Captain Lumley we owe a great deal for the way in which they smoothed our paths through the complexities of travelling and hotel existence.Nor would we fail to express our gratitude to Mr. Woods Humphery for his full and ready co-operation, and our admiration for the skilful and untiring way in which he conducted a series of exceedingly intricate and trying negotiations in New York and Washington.We are also indebted for the great assistance afforded to us by the High Commissioners Office at Ottawa and for the help of the Embassy at Washington. It is unnecessary to say that the personal interest of Sir Francis Floud and of Sir Ronald Lindsay afforded us much encouragement, but we should wish to pay a special tribute to the indefatigable efforts of Mr. Norman Archer in Ottawa and of Group-Captain Howe in Washington.Finally, we would like to record the happy impressions which we formed of the interest shown in this project wherever we have discussed it and of its great potentialities as a bond of union between the English-speaking peoples on both sides of the Atlantic. It is apparent that the conception of this aerial bridge between our respective peoples as a joint enterprise, designed and calculated to reduce the separation in space and understanding between us, is one that makes an exceedingly strong appeal to men of goodwill on all sides.DONALD BANKS,F. C. SHELMERD1NE.30th December, 1935.
Confidential.REPORT OP UNITED KINGDOM AIR MISSION TO NORTH AMERICA.(November-December, 1935).1. A Mission consisting of the following was empowered to discuss questions relating to the establishment of a trans-Atlantic air service first with representatives of the Governments of Canada, the Irish Free State and Newfoundland and later with representatives of the Govern-ment of the United States of America : &apos;Colonel Sir Donald Banks, K.C.B., D.S.O., M.C. (Director-General of the Post Office).Lieutenant-Colonel F. C. Shelmerdine, C.I.E., O.B.E. (Director-General of Civil Aviation).Mr. G. E. Woods Humphery, C.B.E. (Managing Director of Imperial Airways).Mr. D. O. Lumley, O.B.E. (Post Office).Mr. I. McClure    &quot;\ , a. ,,. . .   .y (Air Ministry). Mr. F. EntwistleJMr. C. G. L. Syers (Dominions Office).2. The main party left Euston on the morning of Wednesday, 13th November, 1935, and sailed from Liverpool in R.M.S. Montrose on the afternoon of that day. They were joined on board by the Irish Free State Mission, consisting of Mr. J. Leydon (Secretary of the Depart-ment of Commerce) and Mr. J. P. Walshe (Secretary of the Department of External Affairs), with whom friendly relations were quickly established.3. On the 14th November an informal discussion took place between the leaders of the Mission and the Irish Free State representatives, and private conversations continued at intervals throughout the voyage. Full meetings between the members of the two Missions were held on the 15th, 16th and 18th November. The opportunity afforded by these meetings was taken to explore the whole range of questions to be discussed in Ottawa and Washington and to secure as wide an agreement as possible between the Missions both on the question of procedure and on that of the attitude to be adopted towards the various problems which were likely to arise.4. The heads of discussion for the Ottawa negotiations suggested in the telegram (No. 84 of the 2nd November) from the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs to the Secretary of State for External Affairs of Canada (Appendix I to this Report) were taken as a basis for consideration and at the opening meeting (15th November) Sir Donald Banks outlined the principles underlying the proposals in that telegram and the general attitude to them of the United Kingdom Government. General agreement was reached at this meeting on the questions of (a) route, (b) duration of agreements, (c) the necessity for development of existing meteorological arrangements.5. At the second meeting (16th November) general discussion took place on the questions of (a) mail loads and (b) the position of foreign countries other than the United States of America. As regards (a), the United Kingdom representatives undertook to produce estimated figures with a view to closer consideration of the question at a later meeting ; as regards (b), it was generally agreed that, while it would be impossible to adopt a policy of exclusion for an indefinite period towards such countries, concessions to them could reasonably be confined to landing rights and need not involve commercial rights.6. At the third meeting (18th November morning) consideration was given to the pro-visional figures of mail loads prepared by the United Kingdom representatives and an attempt was made to estimate the residual annual cost of a service of two round trips per week, on the basis of a comparison of these figures with the estimated cost of operations, ground organisation, etc. It was recognised that two stages of development were envisaged for the proposed service experimental and regular. As regards the cost of the experimental stage (during which survey and experimental flights would be made and other investigations carried out, followed by services which might be seasonal and irregular), it was not possible to arrive at even an approximate estimate. As regards the regular flying stage (two round trips per week) the annual gross cost was very tentatively estimated at  500,000 and it was suggested that of
this amount payments for mail loads might in favourable circumstances produce  200,000  leaving a deficit of  300,000. On the assumption that agreement was reached at Ottawa to the effect that operations should be entrusted to a joint operating Company in which the Government of the United Kingdom, the Government of Canada and the Government of the Irish Free State should have holdings and that such holdings were proportionately divided as shown below, the United Kingdom representatives suggested that the proportional amounts of subsidy might be allocated as follows : United Kingdom, 50 per cent.     150,000 1Canada, 25 per cent.  75,000   Vper annum.Irish Free State, 25 per cent.       75,000 JThe Irish Free State representatives at once pointed out that so large a subsidy from their Government would be impracticable and Sir Donald Banks said that, in accordance with the indications of favourable treatment previously given by Sir Warren Fisher, he had no doubt that a smaller contribution might be agreed if no objection were raised in principle by Canada to the scaling down of the Irish portion in view of her smaller commercial interests as a transit country. He mentioned that, while no commitment could be made at this stage, net hought that a subsidy of the order of half the Canadian amount might prove acceptable. The Irish Free State representatives did not demur to this figure, though they indicated both in con-ference and in private conversation that they hoped to secure further abatements in this figure in subsequent negotiations by virtue of their assumption of the cost of the meteorological services. It was pointed out that similar considerations might also be urged by Canada; and, in view of the political considerations involved in the question of the transfer of meteoro-logical services from the United Kingdom to Irish Free State, the whole question was reserved for consideration on return to England.7. As regards the experimental period, Colonel Shelmerdine intimated that, in certain circumstances, the United Kingdom Mission would be prepared to recommend to the United Kingdom Government that the United Kingdom should accept sole financial liability for flying operations during this period, provided that the Dominion Governments concerned accepted liability for the necessary ground organisation, meteorological and radio services, etc. This suggestion was discussed and in the result assurances were given to the Irish Free State representatives that (a) while no definite term for this period could be fixed, every effort should be made to complete the necessary operations in the shortest time possible, and (b) the knowledge and experience gained by Imperial Airways would be unreservedly placed at the disposal of the Joint Operating Company immediately the latter was in a position to operate.8. At the fourth and final meeting (18th November afternoon) the principles involved in possible United States participation in the service were considered, with special reference to the question of relative mail-loads, and a general discussion followed on the policy to be adopted at Washington in the event of negotiations at Ottawa proving successful.9. The party disembarked at Montreal in the early morning of Thursday, November 21st, and reached Ottawa at noon. They were joined there by Mr. T. Lodge, C.B. (representing the Commission of Government of Newfoundland) and by Mr. F. Entwistle (who had been conducting meteorological enquiries in Newfoundland and Canada).10. The next morning (Friday, 22nd November), the representatives of the United King-dom, the Irish Free State, and Newfoundland met in Conference the members of the Canadian inter-departmental Committee which had been examining the question of trans-Atlantic air services. The Chairman of this Committee was Mr. V. I. Smart, Deputy Minister of the Department of Railways and Canals ; he was accompanied by representatives of the Depart-ments of Finance, External Affairs, National Defence and Posts, and by the Directors of Radio and Meteorological Services. The opening stages of the meeting were attended by the Honourable Mr. Elliott (Postmaster General of Canada), who welcomed the visiting representa-tives officially, and by Sir Francis Floud (High Commissioner in Canada for His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom). After general explanatory statements by representatives of the four countries concerned, it was agreed to constitute three sub-committees to report respectively on (1) Postal questions, (2) Operational and technical questions (including routes, meteorology, and radio), and (3) General questions of finance (see document 1 in Appendix II). The agreed recommendations of the first two of these sub-committees are reproduced as documents 5 and 6 in Appendix II.11. The third sub-committee was in effect the co-ordinating body of the Conference and in it were conducted the discussions as to the general nature of the proposed scheme which led eventually to the formulation of a draft Agreement. Thus at the first meeting of this sub-committee on Saturday, 23rd November (document 2 in Appendix II) Sir Donald Banks
outlined briefly the proposals of the United Kingdom Mission, particularly in regard to finance. At the request of the Chairman, Sir Donald Banks the next day forwarded a summary of these for consideration by the Canadian representatives. As will be seen from the text of the letter to Mr. Smart and its enclosures (Appendix III to this Report), the proposals covered : -(a) Main points for discussion.(b) Preliminary steps required for the establishment of a regular service.(c) Provisions for the carrying out of experimental flights by Imperial Airways.(d) Provisions for the formation of a Joint Operating Company to operate a regularservice.12. The Canadian representatives considered these proposals on Monday, 25th November, at a meeting of their inter-departmental Committee, during the course of which further . explanations were given by Sir Donald Banks and Colonel Shelmerdine.13. Conversations had in the meantime been proceeding, both openly and secretly between various members of the different delegations in the course of which the Irish Free State representatives made considerable efforts to secure that the basis of shareholding in a Joint Operating Company should be equal for all the three partners. The idea of participation in such a Company was new to the Canadians and had been dismissed summarily in their earlier deliberations, but it soon became apparent in the joint proceedings that, despite the political difficulties, there was a strong inclination on the part of Canada&apos;s principal repre-sentatives, backed presumably by the Ministers whom they consulted, to take a part in the Company. The efforts of the United Kingdom delegation were therefore concentrated to a large extent on avoiding a break-down on the question of shareholding and a strong line was taken in regard to the necessity for a majority of shares being held by Imperial Airways. These efforts, happily proved so successful that they resulted in the Canadian representatives turning their guns upon the Irish and at a special dinner for the Irish convened by the Canadians and held with the knowledge of, but without the attendance of, the United Kingdom repre-sentatives, the Canadians obtained the consent of the Irish Free State representatives to the controlling interest being held by Imperial Airways. The Canadians also were instrumental in securing an equal division of the residual shareholding between Canada and the Irish Free State after further private representations by the United Kingdom representatives as to the undesirability of Canada accepting a smaller proportion of the shares than the Irish Free State.14. The position was thus remarkably changed from that which had been envisaged by the Irish Free State representatives and resulted subsequently in a fresh rapprochement between the Irish Free State and the United Kingdom delegations which was of material value in subsequent negotiations when the Canadian Ministers proved reluctant to go as far as their officials in endorsing the provisional agreement.15. Meantime, on Tuesday, 26th November, the official representatives of the four countries met and recorded general agreement (see document 3 in Appendix II) on the following heads : (1) Establishment in principle of a joint air mail service between the four countries to be recommended to the respective Governments.(2) Carriage by air between these countries of all first-class mail to be the eventual objective.(3) Establishment of a regular air mail service on a surcharge basis with a minimum frequency of two round trips per week to be the immediate objective.(4) Except during the experimental period, the initial surcharge rate not to exceed 2s. per \ oz. or its equivalent.(5) Survey flights to be undertaken by Imperial Airways in 1936 and to be followed as soon as possible by a service which might be seasonal and irregular.(6) The regular flying stage to commence when a minimum of three months&apos; continuous flying (two round trips per week) was practicable.At this stage operational work to be transferred to the Joint Operating Company, which would be established on an agreed basis.(7) Preference to be given to the direct route (including an Irish Free State airport and Montreal), but alternative routes also to be developed as necessary.(8) During the experimental period the operations to be financed wholly by the United Kingdom Government.
(9) At the regular flying stage, CanadVs annual subsidy contribution to be 20 per cent, of the estimated residual costs of operation. The annual subsidy contributions of the Irish Free State and Newfoundland to be determined at a later stage.The general arrangements to be reviewed after fifteen years or when an &quot;all up &quot; mail service was instituted ; and provision to be made for reviewing the subsidy contributions every three years.(10) Arrangements to be made between the administrations concerned for the provision of meteorological and wireless facilities. Canada to provide such facilities in Newfoundland on a basis acceptable to the Canadian and Newfoundland Governments.(11) Landing rights exclusive to the trans-Atlantic service to be granted to the Joint Operating Company.(12) Exemption from fuef and oil taxes and duties on technical material to be granted to the Joint Operating Company.Moreover, at this meeting it was agreed inter alia that the holdings through national aviation Companies of shares in the Joint Operating Company should be 51 per cent, by Imperial Airways and 24J per cent, each by the respective Canadian and Irish Free State companies.16. Agreement had thus been reached between the various representatives but it remained for the Canadian representatives to secure the acceptance by their Ministers of even this provisional basis for an understanding. Owing partly to the absence from Canada of the Canadian Prime Minister and partly to the fact that the new Canadian Government had but recently taken office, difficulties arose at this stage which gave rise to an anxious and delicate situation. During the earlier stages the Canadian official representatives together with those of the Irish Free State had shown concern to secure a firm basis of agreement and the United Kingdom delegation had therefore been impelled to obtain the authority of their Government to agree to suitable terms as definitely as possible. The Canadian Ministers, however, now showed an unexpected disposition to hedge on the settlement and decided that the provisional agreement was to be accepted merely as a &quot; basis of negotiation.&quot; The Irish Free State representatives were at the same time being urged by their Government to press for further concessions of a somewhat radical character (such for instance as the rotation of the Chairman-ship of the Joint Operating Company) but were personally anxious to close firmly on the original terms if general acceptance could be obtained. In the circumstances it seemed highly perilous to leaVe the matter vaguely as little more than recorded conversations. Efforts were therefore made in a series of private conversations with Canadian Ministers and officials to secure a measure of compromise which, while not binding any of the Governments, would ensure that the arrangements arrived at should be safeguarded as far as possible against piecemeal alterations. These efforts were supplemented by even more emphatic representations by the Irish Free State representatives.At the same time a drafting committee under the Chairmanship of Mr. Loring Christie was actively engaged in drawing up the document of agreement a task which called for a high degree of tact and patience on the part of all concerned owing to the difficult attitude of the Irish Free State representatives.17. Negotiations continued intensively over the week-end and in the result a message was received on Monday afternoon, 2nd December, that the Canadian Cabinet had agreed to the formula which prefaces the signed agreement.18. A meeting of the full Conference was at once summoned and late that evening an agreement ad referendum was signed. It should be mentioned that, at the same time, the various representatives agreed to make certain recommendations to their respective Govern-ments with regard to various points which had been raised (mainly by the Irish Free State representatives) during the course of the discussions but were not thought suitable for inclusion in the provisional agreement. (For the text of the agreement reference should be made to the annex to document 7 in Appendix II and for the subsidiary points referred to above, to para. 5 of that document). A brief agreed statement (of which a copy appears as Appendix IV) was issued the same night to the Press after approval by the Canadian Minister of Railways and Canals.19. During these highly complicated discussions the Mission endeavoured to keep the authorities at home fully apprised of the main lines of progress though it was of course impracticable to enter into great detail or to keep pace with the rapid alterations in the situation.
20. The next day (Tuesday, 3rd December) the Mission left Ottawa for Washington, accompanied by the Irish Free State Mission and by a Canadian Mission comprising repre-sentatives of the Departments of External Affairs, National Defence and Posts. Mr. Lodge, who had been summoned to London, had already left the Mission at Ottawa.. The party, numbering 14 altogether, reached Washington, where they were joined by Group Captain Howe (Air Attache to His Majesty&apos;s Embassy), on the following day (Wednesday, 4th December).21. An opportunity was taken en route for Sir Donald Banks to see Dr. Skelton (Under Secretary of State for External Affairs of Canada) at New York and to enlighten him as to the situation. Mr. Walshe also saw him independently with a view to urging the desirability of pressing forward with Canada&apos;s participation in the scheme.22. On the evening of the day of arrival a meeting was held between the three British Commonwealth Missions to consider the policy to be adopted in the forthcoming discussions. Mr. Woods Humphery, who had visited New York during the previous week and conducted detailed discussions with Mr. Trippe, the President of Pan American Airways, reported his impressions of the general situation in the United States, so far as the establishment of a trans-Atlantic air service was concerned. In the first place, political considerations (particularly the importance of the large Italian and German votes at the forthcoming Presidential election) would make it quite impossible for the Government of the United States of America to con-template the conclusion of a formaf agreement with any foreign Government on an exclusive basis. Moreover it seemed certain that the United States Postal authorities, who were responsible for finding the necessary subsidies for air services, would be debarred legally from entering into any agreement with regard to the mutual exchange of air mails in advance of the establishment of a service ; in other words, it would be out of the question for them to bind themselves to employ any one American company without going through the form of inviting tenders. In these circumstances, Mr. Trippe and he were agreed that the best line of approach would be to continue negotiations between the two Companies with a view to producing a basis of common agreement which would be acceptable to all the interests concerned on both sides. Moreover, they felt it important that it should be made clear to the United States representatives that such a procedure did not represent a new negotiation but was only a continuance of discussions between the Companies which had already been proceeding for five years. For this reason, he emphasised the desirability of referring to Imperial Airways as the nominated British Company for the purpose of the trans-Atlantic service, rather than to their proposed successor, the Joint Operating Company.23. In the general discussion between the three Missions which followed it became clear that the value of the line of approach suggested was not immediately apparent to the Canadian and Irish Free State representatives, the former entertaining fears with regard to the develop-ment of the Southern route and the latter not relishing the relegation of the proposed Joint Operating Company to a position of comparative obscurity. However, the spirit of mutual confidence reflected in the joint agreement of Ottawa quickly reasserted itself and after further explanations had been given it was generally agreed that the question should be handled on the lines suggested by Mr. Woods Humphery.24. The next morning (Thursday, 5th December) the three Missions were received officially by Mr. Cordell Hull, Secretary of State of the United States, the United Kingdom Mission being introduced by His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Washington, and subsequently met the members of the United States Interdepartmental Committee on Civil International Aviation which consisted of the following : Judge Walton Moore (Assistant Secretary of State) :  Chairman. Mr. Gibbon (Assistant Secretary of the Treasury). Mr. Harllee Branch (Second Assistant Postmaster General). Colonel Johnson (Assistant Secretaty of Commerce).After the customary courtesies had been exchanged brief statements were made by represent-atives of the three visiting Missions. No general statement was made by the official United States representatives, who suggested that it was desirable in the first place for the represent-atives of all parties to know exactly what rights Pan American Airways on the one hand and Imperial Airways on the other were seeking. Mr. Trippe, thereupon, gave a brief historical statement of the relations between Imperial Airways and his company, stressing the fact that applications for landing rights in (1) the United Kingdom, Canada, the Irish Free State, Newfoundland and Bermuda, for the purpose of a trans-Atlantic service, and (2) Bermuda, for the purpose of a local service, had already been made to the United Kingdom Government through the diplomatic channel on behalf of his company.   The application was in each case
limited to two round trips per week, and it was a definite understanding that the grant of permits to Pan American Airways could only be expected if permits on similar lines were granted to Imperial Airways by the United States Government.25. During the course of the ensuing discussion it became evident that Mr. Woods Humphery&apos;s appreciation of the position had been a just one ; for the United States represent-atives made it amply clear that they could not contemplate (a) the grant to any foreign com-pany of exclusive rights or (b) the acceptance of a general principle of reciprocity. From this it followed that exclusivity could only be looked for through the medium of an inter-company agreement, and reciprocity attained on ad hoc basis.26. In pursuance of this policy, the United States representatives pressed that, as a first step, the representatives of the two companies should discuss the question of the form of the permits required of the respective Governments and that in the conduct of this discussion they should be at liberty to call for assistance from any of the officials taking part in the Conference. This suggestion was accepted and a Committee of officials was constituted to which Mr. Trippe and Mr. Woods Humphery were invited to refer as they thought fit ; the United Kingdom representatives on the Committee were Colonel Shelmerdine, Mr. Lumley, Mr. McClure and Mr. Entwistle.27. Mr. Woods Humphery and Mr. Trippe opened conversations immediately and con-tinued these unremittingly (often into the early hours of the morning) until the morning of the following Thursday, 12th December. During that time they met on two occasions the official Committee referred to above but the discussions were largely of a desultory character and confined to minor legal points raised by the United States representatives in connexion mainly with the application for rights to land in Bermuda. The really important conversations were conducted behind the scenes between Messrs. Woods Humphery and Trippe, supplemented by meetings between the Commonwealth representatives and Mr. Woods Humphery on the one hand and between Mr. Trippe and representatives of the United States Commerce and Post Departments on the other.28. As the discussions proceeded it became manifest that, although (as was repeatedly insisted) neither Pan American Airways nor any other company had any claim to be regarded as the chosen instrument of the United States Government for the trans-Atlantic service, that Company yet enjoyed exceptional influence and was in fact in the full confidence of the United States authorities.   Here again Mr. Woods Humphery&apos;s judgment, had proved correct,29. The week which intervened was an anxious one. As will be appreciated from what is said above, the complicated nature of the relationship between the United States authorities and Pan American Airways rendered negotiation both difficult and delicate. Numerous legal and constitutional questions were introduced on the United States side, the resolution of which called for the utmost patience.30. In particular the search for the basis of a postal understanding which might ultimately commend itself to the United States Postal Administration had to be pursued by somewhat devious means. Representatives of the United Kingdom and Canadian Missions accordingly sought an interview with Mr. Harllee Branch. The latter reiterated the difficulties of his Department in reaching any definite postal agreement and insisted that discussion must be of a purely informal character. The British Commonwealth representatives made it plain that any future arrangement for the interchange of air mail must be on a reciprocal basis. They proposed, therefore, that, assuming two Commonwealth and two United States round trips per week, the westward services under whichever flag should be regarded as Common-wealth services (Postal Union Convention Air Agreement Article 12(7) ), whilst those in the reverse direction would be regarded as United States services. The position of Canada was reserved. Under this arrangement both sides would be free to fix charges for the use of the services under their control and the arrangement had the merit of extreme simplicity. It was also urged that no precedent existed which could be followed in that this was the first occasion on which the air services of two countries or groups of countries would be operating-side by side along a common route. Mr. Branch promised to examine the question, which was evidently an entirely new one to the United States postal authorities.31. At a subsequent meeting with officials of the United States Post Office the proposal outlined above was further developed. The exceptional position of Canada was discussed. On the one hand the fact that that country was a partner in the Commonwealth group was recognised ; on the other it was appreciated that Canadian mail would be carried by the eastbound services which it was proposed to regard as United States services. The Canadian representative proposed therefore that payment should be made to the United States postal
limited to two round trips per week, and it was a definite understanding that the grant of permits to Pan American Airways could only be expected if permits on similar lines were granted to Imperial Airways by the United States Government.25. During the course of the ensuing discussion it became evident that Mr. Woods Humphery&apos;s appreciation of the position had been a just one ; for the United States represent-atives made it amply clear that they could not contemplate (a) the grant to any foreign com-pany of exclusive rights or (&amp;) the acceptance of a general principle of reciprocity. From this it followed that exclusivity could only be looked for through the medium of an inter-company agreement, and reciprocity attained on ad hoc basis.26. In pursuance of this policy, the United States representatives pressed that, as a first step, the representatives of the two companies should discuss the question of the form of the permits required of the respective Governments and that in the conduct of this discussion they should be at liberty to call for assistance from any of the officials taking part in the Conference. This suggestion was accepted and a Committee of officials was constituted to which Mr. Trippe and Mr. Woods Humphery were invited to refer as they thought fit ; the United Kingdom representatives on the Committee were Colonel Shelmerdine, Mr. Lumley, Mr. McClure and Mr. Entwistle.27. Mr. Woods Humphery and Mr. Trippe opened conversations immediately and con-tinued these unremittingly (often into the early hours of the morning) until the morning of the following Thursday, 12th December. During that time they met on two occasions the official Committee referred to above but the discussions were largely of a desultory character and confined to minor legal points raised by the United States representatives in connexion mainly with the application for rights to land in Bermuda. The really important conversations were conducted behind the scenes between Messrs. Woods Humphery and Trippe, supplemented by meetings between the Commonwealth representatives and Mr. Woods Humphery on the one hand and between Mr. Trippe and representatives of the United States Commerce and Post Departments on the other.28. As the discussions proceeded it became manifest that, although (as was repeatedly insisted) neither Pan American Airways nor any other company had any claim to be regarded as the chosen instrument of the United States Government for the trans-Atlantic service, that Company yet enjoyed exceptional influence and was in fact in the full confidence of the United States authorities.  Here again Mr. Woods Humphery&apos;s judgment had proved correct.29. The week which intervened was an anxious one. As will be appreciated from what is said above, the complicated nature of the relationship between the United States authorities and Pan American Airways rendered negotiation both difficult and delicate. Numerous legal and constitutional questions were introduced on the United States side, the resolution of which called for the utmost patience.30. In particular the search for the basis of a postal understanding which might ultimately commend itself to the United States Postal Administration had to be pursued by somewhat devious means. Representatives of the United Kingdom and Canadian Missions accordingly sought an interview with Mr. Harllee Branch. The latter reiterated the difficulties of his Department in reaching any definite postal agreement and insisted that discussion must be of a purely informal character. The British Commonwealth representatives made it plain that any future arrangement for the interchange of air mail must be on a reciprocal basis. They proposed, therefore, that, assuming two Commonwealth and two United States round trips per week, the westward services under whichever flag should be regarded as Common-wealth services (Postal Union Convention Air Agreement Article 12(7) ), whilst those in the reverse direction would be regarded as United States services. The position of Canada was reserved. Under this arrangement both sides would be free to fix charges for the use of the services under their control and the arrangement had the merit of extreme simplicity. It was also urged that no precedent existed which could be followed in that this was the first occasion on which the air services of two countries or groups of countries would be operating-side by side along a common route. Mr. Branch promised to examine the question, which was evidently an entirely new one to the United States postal authorities.31. At a subsequent meeting with officials of the United States Post Office the proposal outlined above was further developed. The exceptional position of Canada was discussed. On the one hand the fact that that country was a partner in the Commonwealth group was recognised; on the other it was appreciated that Canadian mail would be carried by the eastbound services which it was proposed to regard as United States services. The Canadian representative proposed therefore that payment should be made to the United States postal
authorities in respect of Canadian mail actually carried on United States aeroplanes at a rate to be agreed upon between the United States and Canadian postal administrations. Similarly, it was recognised that, when the Southern route was in operation, the United States Postal Administration might (contrary to the proposed general basis of understanding) expect to fix and collect payments for air mail placed on United States aeroplanes at airports in Europe other than those in the United Kingdom or the Irish Free State. A statement containing proposals on these lines was left with the United States postal authorities (a copy appears as Appendix V to this Report). In view of the particular interest of Canada and of the close relations obtaining between the Canadian and United States postal administrations, it was arranged that Mr. Coolican (Assistant Deputy Postmaster General of Canada) should maintain touch with the United States postal authorities on this question after the departure of the Missions.32. As regards the discussions between Mr. Woods Humphery and Mr. Trippe, it was realised at the outset that the question at issue turned on the drafting of documents showing the conditions on which permits would be granted (a) by the United States Government to Imperial Airways, (b) by the United kingdom.om Government to Pan American Airways for the operation of a trans-Atlantic service. It was clear that other permits would be required (e.g., from the Governments of Canada and the Irish Free State) but it was agreed that these would f of low the same general lines. A set of such of these documents as were finally completed at Washington is reproduced as Appendix VI to this Report, the leading documents being Nos. 9 (Conditions under which Pan American Airways would be granted permission by the United Kingdom Government to operate a trans-Atlantic service) and 12 (Conditions under which Imperial Airways would be granted permission by the United States Government to operate a trans-Atlantic service). The drafts of these two documents necessarily underwent numerous changes both as to form and as to substance as the situation developed, and it was not until the afternoon of Wednesday, 11th December, that document No. 12 was ready for submission to the United States authorities.33. The fatter lost no time in considering the matter and on the morning of the following day (Thursday, 12th December), a fullmeeting of the main Conference was held. After Mr. Woods Humphery and Mr. Trippe had expressed the joint desire of their Companies for the institution of a trans-Atlantic air service (including connexions to the West Indies) on reciprocal lines the United States Assistant Secretary of Commerce read out the text of two letters addressed to the United States Secretary of State by the United States Secretary of Commerce of which the first contained an expression of agreement to the establishment of air routes (a) across the Atlantic, and (b) between Bermuda and Puerto Rico and the second conveyed approval of the estabfishment of reciprocal air services subject to the adherence by the United Kingdom Company to United States air navigation requirements and to the grant of similar rights to such United States air company, as might be designated : the reciprocal agreement to be made for a period of fifteen years and to apply to air companies acceptable to the respective Govern-ments. (Copies of these letters are annexed to this Report as Appendix VII.) At this point Mr. Harllee Branch intimated that reciprocal landing and flying rights alone were in question and that the United States Postal Administration could admit no obligation to give a mail contract or contracts to any particular United States air company ; he wished it to be clearly understood that tenders for any air mail service which might be thought desirable must under United States law be invited before a mail contract could be placed.34. The question of the applications already lodged with the United States Government by Imperial Airways was therefore disposed of so far as the Conference was concerned, and it now remains for the United States Government to return a formal reply thereto in due course. As regards the corresponding applications by Pan American Airways, which had already been lodged with the United Kingdom Government but not with the Canadian and Irish Free State Governments, it was implied by the United States representatives that they regarded the matter as one between Pan American Airways and the respective Commonwealth Governments. The question of the conditions on which, it was suggested, those Governments might accord the necessary permits [i.e., document No. 9 and analogous documents) was not therefore discussed in open Conference, but it may be assumed that, as those conditions were known to the United States authorities, the latter would have demurred had any or all of them been unacceptable. Colonel Shelmerdine, however, stated at the meeting that, so far as he could judge, no difficulty need be anticipated in obtaining the assent of the United Kingdom Government.35. The Chairman, in bringing the Conference to a close, referred in exceptionally happy terms to the spirit&apos; of amicable cooperation which had marked the discussions and showed clearly that there was no lack of desire on the part of the United States authorities to work on the friendliest terms with the Commonwealth authorities for the early realisation of a
993joint trans-Atlantic service. He subsequently issued a statement to the press, summarising the understandings reached. The terms of this statement, which is reproduced as Appendix VIII, were agreed to by all parties.36. Immediately after the conclusion of the proceedings the Commonwealth Missions separated, the United Kingdom Mission leaving for New York whence the official members left for England at noon on Saturday, 14th December, on board R.M.S. Aquitania, reaching Southampton the following Saturday, 21st December. Mr. Woods Humphery remained in America to continue conversations with Mr. Trippe, and other negotiations.37. During the stay of the party in New York Colonel Shelmerdine and Mr. Woods Humphery discussed with representatives of Pan American Airways the questions of : (1) French participation in trans-Atlantic services via the Southern route. (2) French participation in the organisation of facilities in the Azores. (3) The use of Hong Kong by Pan American Airways.A note of the discussion is reproduced as Appendix IX.C. G. L. SYERS,D. 0. LUMLEY.30th December, 1935.
TELEGRAM FROM. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DOMINION AFFAIRS TO THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EXTERNAL AFFAIRS, CANADA.Sent 9.0 p.m., 2nd November, 1935.No. 84. Confidential-Your telegram No. 74 of 7th October. Transatlantic air service. Following are suggested heads of discussion.Begins : A. BRITISH COMMONWEALTH SERVICES.1. General Principles. The general principles underlying the Empire Air Mail Scheme already communicated in paper of October 1934 would form the basis of approach, but considerable modifications would be necessary to meet transatlantic conditions.2. Method of Development. Impracticable on account of impossibility of providing sufficient space except at prohibitive expense to contemplate carriage of all first-class mail at present. This should be regarded as an objective to be attained as soon as possible but for some years air mail would necessarily be surcharged, the surcharge being kept relatively low in order to stimulate traffic.3. Experimental Stage. Anticipated that this would cover 2 years and probably longer on direct route (Ireland Newfoundland). During this time services would probably be seasonal and irregular.   Their frequency would depend on progress made.4. Regular Flying Stage. When this is reached it is suggested that a service of two flights a week in each direction should be minimum to be contemplated.5. Routes. Three routes available :  1. Northern (via Iceland). 2. Direct (Ireland Newfoundland). 3. Southern (Bermuda Azores).Of these Northern offers economic advantages of short hops but climatic conditions are bad. Southern involves longer flying times and dependence on foreign interests. Direct route most promising for development but likely to be impracticable in winter for two or three years.Suggested that preliminary scheme should be based on study of a joint use of Direct and Southern routes, with all practicable preference to Direct route.Detailed consideration will be necessary of various political and other problems involved on both these routes.6. Finance. Proposed that the broad principles followed for the Empire Air Mail Scheme should form the basis of discussion, i.e.,(a) Mails to be paid for by respective Post Offices on basis of user.   Postagerates to be fixed by each administration concerned. (6) Residual cost of service less any estimated passenger and freight revenue to be contributed in suitable proportions by respective Governments.(c) Landing, meteorological and wireless facilities to be provided by respectiveadministrations concerned.(d) Exemption from fuel and oil taxes to be considered as in the Empire AirMail Scheme.7. Operational. Experience and facilities of Imperial Airways, who have already undertaken a number of preparatory steps and have experimental machines under consideration, to be fully utilised for operating.Possibilities of participation (if desired) by respective national aviation companies in a joint operating company and of inclusion of Canadian and Irish registered machines to be explored.
B. FOREIGN SERVICES.8. United States of America participation. Negotiations between Imperial Airways and Pan American Airways have taken place in the past on basis of joint flying of North Atlantic, but have not assumed concrete form.Size and importance of United States mail and Pan American desire to institute Atlantic service, however, make study of Air Mail to and from United States of America inevitable, though it need not necessarily be combined with Canadian service. Assuming, however, that such a service were instituted it should be advantageous both economically and for mail purposes if some interworking arrangements were effected.Proposed therefore for consideration that an offer be made to United States of America of participation in the Atlantic service during an initial period on a 50 : 50 basis of flying on a regular schedule of say two or three services a week. This arrange-ment would be independent of financial proposals in paragraph 6 and without prejudice to eventual Anglo-Irish-Canadian arrangements when &quot; all-up &quot; mail exchange insti-tuted.   Administrations concerned all to retain proceeds of their contributed mail.9. Participation by other countries. France has approached United States of America and Great Britain with particular regard to the Southern route and Germany is known to be studying possibilities on the direct route.Portugal is concerned with the Azores and Lisbon as an European entrepot, but is not likely to be interested in actual flying for some time.It is thought that when facilities and landing places in British Commonwealth territories have been provided it might be undesirable to attempt to deny these to other countries, but as costs of development at initial stages will fall mainly on United Kingdom, Canada, Irish Free State, Newfoundland and United States of America, there appears to be a case for an understanding between these countries for the period of development restricting the exchange of air mail on these routes as far as possible to the services contemplated above.France is perhaps a special case as she was granted landing rights in Bermuda some years ago, and it might be desirable to consider admitting a French service on the Southern route on suitable conditions and at an appropriate stage provided that the French Government undertook to collaborate in the costs of that route.All these arrangements would of course be dependent on suitable reciprocal rights being conceded.C. MISCELLANEOUS.E.g., duration of arrangements, shipping considerations, and the question of an air service to the West Indies. Ends.We propose to communicate these suggested heads of discussion to the Irish Free State Government, but otherwise we would ask that they should be regarded as confidential as between ourselves.
Confidential.DISCUSSIONS  ON  TRANSATLANTIC  AIR  SERVICES,  OTTAWA,NOVEMBER-DECEMBER, 1935.1. Minutes of first meeting2. Minutes of General, Finance, and Co-ordinating Sub-Committee3. Minutes of General, Finance, and Co-ordinating Sub-committee . Minutes of General, Finance, and Co-ordinating Sub-Committee5. Report of Postal Sub-committee. Report of Operating and Technical Sub-Committee..7. Minutes of finaf meeting ..       ..       ..22nd November, 1935 23rd November, 1935 26th November, 1935 28th November, 1935 23rd November, 1935 November, 1935 2nd December, 19351.1. The first meeting was held in Room 268, Centre Block, Parliament Buildings, on Friday, the 22nd of November, with the Honourable J. C. Elliott, Postmaster-General for Canada, in the Chair. Sir Francis L. C. Floud, High Commissioner for the United Kingdom, was present.2. The following representatives were present : Canada Mr. V. I. Smart, Deputy Minister, Department of Railways and Canals ;Mr. Loring C. Christie, Counsellor, Department of External Affairs ;Mr. J. A. Wilson, Controller of Civil Aviation ;Mr. P. T. Coolican, Assistant Deputy Postmaster-General;Mr. John Patterson, Director, Meteorological Service ;Mr. C. P. Edwards, Director of Radio ;Dr. W. C. Clark, Deputy Minister, Department of Finance ;Squadron Leader A. T. N. Cowley, Superintendent, Air Regulations Secretary. United Kingdom Colonel Sir Donald Banks, K.C.B., D.S.O., M.C., Director-General of the Post Office ; Lt. Colonel F. C. Shelmerdine, C.I.E., O.B.E., Director-General of Civil Aviation, Air Ministry ;Mr. G. E. Woods Humphery, C.B.E., Managing Director of Imperial Airways, Limited ;Mr. D. O. Lumley, O.B.E.. General Post Office ; Mr. Ivor McClure, Air Ministry;Mr. F. Entwistle, Meteorological Department, Air Ministry ; Mr. C. G. L. Syers, Dominions Office ;Mr. N. E. Archer, Secretary, Office of the High Commissioner for the United Kingdom.Irish Free State &apos;Mr. J. P. Walshe, Secretary of the Department of External Affairs ; Mr. J. Leydon, Secretary of the Department of Industry and Commerce.Newfoundland The Hon. T. Lodge, C.B., Commissioner for Public Utilities.Also present Mr. A. D. McLean, Acting Superintendent, Airways ; Squadron Leader L. F. Stevenson, R.C.A.F., Civil Aviation Branch ; Mr. George Herring, Superintendent, Air Mail Service, Post Office Department ; Mr. F. E. Jolliffe, Assistant Director, Administrative Services, Post Office Depart-ment.
3. The Honourable Mr. Elliott welcomed the representatives on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government in Canada and the Post Office Department in particular, wishing the conference every success in their deliberations. Sir Donald Banks thanked Mr. Elliott and expressed gratification at the welcome which had been given by the Canadian Government.4. The Honourable Mr. Elliott and Sir Francis Floud thereupon left the meeting and at the motion of Sir Donaid Banks, which was seconded by Mr. Leydon and unanimously approved, Mr. V. I. Smart took the Chair.5. Sir Donald Banks reviewed briefly the United Kingdom hopes in regard to an Empire Air Mail Service, which should ultimately carry all first-class air mail without surcharge. The institution of an air mail service across the Atlantic would complete the general scheme for linking up the countries of the Commonwealth by air and should bring advantages of the greatest importance to all the countries concerned. The consideration of the North American terminal was important, since, undoubtedly, if the traffic was centred at New York, the mail for the western points would tend to flow through the United States lines, whereas, if Montreal were utilized, the mail for western points would flow through Canada, both to western Canada points and to Detroit and Chicago, and from there to the western states. He presumed that the trans-Canada airway would be in operation to handle such traffic. Sir Donald Banks stated that, for the present, the carriage of all first-class mail at ordinary mail rates by air was prohibitive in cost and that though this should be the ultimate objective the basis of the present discussion would, no doubt, have to be that of a surcharged air mail.6. Colonel Shelmerdine supplemented Sir Donald Banks&apos; remarks and said that the present conference was a natural sequence to the work of the Committee set up by the Canadian Government in 1932 at Ottawa and subsequent conferences held in Newfoundland and Canada. . The stage had now been reached when experimental flights leading up to a regular transatlantic air service were possible, and the United Kingdom Government were taking all possible steps to expedite development with an important programme of experiment and research.Although the main object of the conference was the linking up by air of Canada with the Irish Free State, Great Britain, and Europe, it was necessary also to consider the truly inter-national aspect. Other European nations were keenly interested in transatlantic flying and it was now necessary for the British Commonwealth to decide what part they were to take, and to make definite plans for the future.7. Mr. Leydon expressed general agreement and hoped that Canada would be able to participate in a joint operation for the carriage of maiis across the ocean.8. Mr. Lodge stated that Newfoundland would be one of the main beneficiaries from a transatlantic service and was anxious to co-operate as fully as possible.9. The Chairman recommended the appointment of sub-committees to discuss the various subjects and report to the main committee. Some discussion ensued as to the subjects to be covered by the different sub-committees and views were expressed for their guidance. The following sub-committees were appointed : I. Postal Sub-Committee.Mr. P. T. Coolican Convenor.Mr. G. Herring.Mr. F. E. Jolliffe.Sir Donald Banks.Mr. D. O. Lumley.Mr. J. Leydon.II. Operating and Technical Sub-Committee (To discuss general operating questions, choice of routes, meteorology, and radio).Mr. J. A. Wilson Convenor. Mr. J. Patterson. Mr. C. P. Edwards. Col. F. C. Shelmerdine. Mr. I. McClure. Mr. F. Entwistle. Mr. J. P. Walshe. The Hon. T. Lodge.
III. General Finance and Co-ordinating Sub-Committee. Mr. V. I. Smart Convenor. Dr. W. C. Clark. Mr. L. C. Christie. Sir Donald Banks. Col. F. C. Shelmerdine. Mr. J. Leydon. Mr. J. P. Walshe. The Hon. T. Lodge.IV. Secretariat.Mr..L. C. Christie Convenor. Squadron-Leader A. T. N. Cowley.. Mr. N. E. Archer. Mr. C. G. L. Syers.10. The meeting adjourned at 12.45.A. T. COWLEY, Squadron-Leader,Secretary.2.SUB-COMMITTEE, GENERAL, FINANCE AND CO-ORDINATING.1. A meeting of the above sub-committee was held under the chairmanship of Mr. V. I. Smart, in Room 570, Centre Block, Parliament Buildings, at 11.00 hours, Saturday, 23rd of November, 1935.2. The following members comprising the sub-committee were present: -Mr. V. I. Smart Convenor. Dr. W. C. Clark. Mr. L. C. Christie. Sir Donald Banks. Colonel F. C. Shelmerdine. Mr. J. Leydon. Mr. J. P. Walshe. The Hon. T. Lodge.3. Sir Donald Banks outlined the proposals of the United Kingdom in regard to transatlantic air services.  These were based on a three-stage development -1. Survey and exploratory stage.2. An intermediate stage of irregular and seasonal services.3. Regular flying stage.The Mission would be prepared to recommend to the United Kingdom Government that during stages 1 and 2, since even approximate costs were incalculable, Canada should be asked to provide ground facilities only, including a temporary base or bases and radio and meteorological services on the Canadian end and that the United Kingdom should shoulder the entire cost of the flying involved, which would be done by Imperial Airways Limited, acting under the aegis of the Air Ministry. When stage 2 merged into stage 3, the services with all the experience and knowledge gained would be handed over to a joint operating company representative of the United Kingdom, the Irish Free State and Canada.4. Mr. Leydon stated that, subject to the approval of their Government, the representatives of the frish Free State were in agreement with the United Kingdom in this proposal and would provide meteorological and wireless services in the Irish Free State on the above understanding.5. Dr. Clark queried as to the scope of the survey and trial flights in stage 1.6. Col. Shelmerdine replied that the United Kingdom had no present intention of exploring the northern route further, but would concentrate on the direct and southern routes, preference being given to the direct route. -  .       . . .   .&apos; .
7. Following a discussion as to the advantages to both Canada and the United Kingdom of the direct route, the following formula was adopted: &quot; All practicable preference will be given to the direct route (including the Irish Free State and Montreal), but this should not prevent use of alternative routes for purposes of development.&quot;8. Mr. Leydon stated that the Irish Free State representatives were in agreement with this formula and were in fact largely responsible for its phraseology. They hoped to safeguard their interests by participation in the operating company.9. Sir Donald Banks advised that survey flights would be undertaken by Imperial Airways Limited in 1936, followed as soon as possible by an experimental service, this period to be subject to agreement. He undertook to supply the Chairman with notes as to the form of such an agreement with a view to further consideration.10. The regular flying stage involving the transfer of operational work to the joint company would commence when a minimum of three months&apos; continuous flying on a schedule of two services a week basis became practicable.Finance.11. Sir Donald Banks made a statement on the financial aspect of the scheme which the United Kingdom Mission had under consideration. He explained that the estimates must be regarded as purely provisional since they were necessarily based on factors which were at present incalculable.   The main points in his statement were as follows : (i) All estimates were based on a bi-weekly service throughout the year.(ii) The entire cost of the service, including depreciation, interest on capital, dividends,etc., had been tentatively estimated at  500,000 per annum.(iii) The revenue from freight and passengers was incalculable and had not been estimated.(iv) The revenue from mail had been conservatively estimated at  120,000, increasingto  150,000.  A more optimistic estimate was  282,000.(v) Assuming a reasonable average, the revenue from mail might be taken as  200,000per annum, leaving a deficit of  300,000. Cost..........      -. .       500,000Mail Revenue     . .       ........       200,000Deficit      . .       . .       300,000This deficit would have to be made up by the countries concerned, according to the advantages they gained from the service and according to their share of participation in the joint company.(vi) The tentative proposal of the United Kingdom representatives, not yet authorizedby Ministers, was for the following proportional responsibility for the deficit.United Kingdom.....       ......50 per cent. ( 150,000).Irish Free State...........25 per cent. ( 75,000).Canada      ............25 per cent. ( 75,000).Newfoundland- nominal.  To be carried by the United Kingdom.(vii) These figures would be subject to possible abatement during any year in which lessthan a certain amount of continuous flying was undertaken and revision every three years throughout a fifteen-year period was contemplated.12. Meeting adjourned at 13.00 hours.13. During the meeting Mr. J. A. Wilson, Convenor of the Operating and Technical Sub-Committee, asked for instructions in regard to costs and general policy. He was informed of the proposals made by the United Kingdom representatives and instructed to prepare his report accordingly.14. In regard to the joint company proposed, the Chairman asked for an all-Canadian meeting to consider the matter prior to further discussion with the other members. This was called for 11.00 hours, Monday, 25th of November, the members to be as follows : Mr. Smart.Mr. Coolican.Mr. Wilson.Dr. Clark.Mr. Christie.A. T. COWLEY,Squadron Leader,Secretary.
3.SUB-COMMITTEE, GENERAL, FINANCE AND CO-ORDINATING.1, A meeting of the above sub-committee was held under the chairmanship of Mr. V. I. Smart in Room 570, Centre Block, Parliament Buildings, at 15.00 hours, Tuesday, the 26th of November, 1935.2. The following members comprising the sub-committee were present : Mr. V. I. Smart Convenor. Sir Donald Banks. Col. F. C. Shelmerdine. Mr. J. Leydon. The Hon. T. Lodge. Dt. W. C. Clark. Mr. L. C. Christie. Mr. J. P. Walshe.3. Sir Donald Banks had presented to a meeting of the Canadian representatives held on Monday, the 25th of November, a memorandum entitled &quot; Main Points for Discussion.&quot; This memorandum had been considered first by the Canadian representatives only, and then by the Canadian representatives with the United Kingdom, the Irish Free State, and Newfoundland representatives called in consultation.4. In the meeting now being recorded the memorandum was reviewed, altered to meet Canadian and Irish Free State views as far as possible, and is reproduced in paragraph 6 below in the form agreed upon for submission to the partner governments.5. The financial basis insofar as Canada is concerned was agreed to by a sub sub-committee, consisting of Dr. Clark, Mr. Smart, Sir Donald Banks, and Colonel Shelmerdine.6. The Heads of Agreement are as follows :- (1) Agreement in principle to establish a joint air mail service between Canada, Irish Free State, Newfoundland and United Kingdom.(2) Eventual objective to be to carry all first class mail between these countries by air when technical and economic conditions permit. (Mail between Irish Free State and United Kingdom, however, to be considered separately from this agreement.)(3) In the meantime the immediate objective to be to establish a regular air mail service on a surcharge basis on a minimum frequency of two services a week in each direction.(4) Initial surcharge rate not to exceed 2s. per \ ounce or approximate equivalent (except during experimental period). Respective administrations to agree on common policy to reduce surcharge rates in approximate correspondence with reductions of mail carriage rates.(5) Survey flights to be undertaken by Imperial Airways in 1936, followed as soon after as possible by a service which may be seasonal and irregular. This period to be subject to agreement (see Appendix A).(6) Regular flying stage (involving transfer of operational work to joint company) to commence when minimum of three months continuous flying on a schedule of two services a week basis is practicable.(7) All practicable preference to be given to the direct route including the Irish Free State and Montreal, but this should not prevent use of alternative routes for purposes of development.(8) Regular operation to be undertaken by joint operating company to be established on basis detailed in Appendix B.(9) During experimental period the operations to be financed wholly by the United Kingdom Government, no subsidy being required from partner governments. When regular flying stage is reached Canada&apos;s contribution to be 20 per cent, of the estimated residual costs of operation, after deduction of such mail pay-ments as are made to the joint company, under the arrangements described in the postal agreement, and any estimated revenue derived from freight and passengers. The balance of payments due to the company, after allowing for the amounts received from the Irish Free State and Newfoundland under separate
agreements to be completed later, to be met by the United Kingdom. These arrangements to be subject to review after 15 years, or when &quot; all up &quot; mail service is instituted, whichever is the earlier, but provision to be made for triennial reviews of subsidy.(10) Meteoroiogical and wireless facilities to be provided as arranged by the respective administrations concerned. Canada to provide such facilities in Newfoundland on a basis acceptable to the Newfoundland government. Landing rights to be granted to joint operating company which would be exclusive for transatlantic service, except by mutual consent of partner governments.(11) Operating company to be exempt from fuel and oil taxes and duties on technical material in respect of actual operation of service.A. T. Cowley,Squadron Leader,Secretary.APPENDIX A.1. Steps to be taken immediately after conclusion of agreement for formation of joint operating company which shall be registered in each participating country.2. Programme of development of transatlantic air services visualizes two stages :(i) an initial period during which experimental survey nights will be made and otherinvestigations carried out, followed by a service which may be seasonal and irregular ;(ii) the establishment of a regular service.3. Investigations and experimental flights provided for under 2 (i) to be carried out by Imperial Airways in accordance with the undertakings given in Annex I.4. On completion of the initial period provided for under 2 (i), service provided for under 2 (ii) to be established as soon as possible. It is hoped that the first stage will be completed and a regular service established in 1938.5. As soon as a regular service on a twice-a-week schedule with a minimum of 3 months&apos; continuous flying can be established, the joint operating company would take over all responsibility for operation under contract with the partner Governments.ANNEX I TO APPENDIX A1. Subject to satisfactory arrangements being entered into with the United Kingdom Government, Imperial Airways will undertake to carry out experimental transatlantic flights on the direct route, and to pursue technical investigations in such directions as the company may consider desirable, with a view to facilitating the establishment of regular transatlantic services at the earliest possible date.2. Subject also to satisfactory arrangements with the United Kingdom Government the Company will undertake to carry out all necessary investigation, including experimental flights, within the shortest period practicable. While it is not possible, in the present state of technical knowledge, to give a binding undertaking as to the duration of the period required for such investigations, it is hoped that they will be completed by 31st December, 1936.3. The Company will undertake to place fully at the disposal of the Joint Operating Company the results of the investigations referred to above.APPENDIX B.JOINT OPERATING COMPANY-UNITED KINGDOM-IRISH FREE STATE-CANADA.1. Participation through national aviation companies, who would hold shares in an agreed proportion in the joint operating company, 51 per cent, to be held by Imperial Airways, balance to be equally divided by the Irish Free State and Canadian national companies.2. Board to consist of 9 Directors, 3 from the national Canadian company, 3 from the national Irish company, and 3 from Imperial Airways Limited, including in the last mentioned the Chairman and the Managing Director.(C199S1)D
3. (1) The Board of the joint company to have jurisdiction over questions of major policy, including the power to raise rates.(2) Subject to (1) above, control of commercial, technical and operating matters to be assured to Imperial Airways Limited through its stockholding and through the medium of the articles of association of the joint company.4. Original directors all to be agreed by the several national companies concerned on the formation of the joint operating company, one director nominated by each national company to retire annually and to be eligible for re-election. Vacancies to be filled by nomination from the national company concerned after acceptance by the Board.5. No shares to be sold by any of the partners without the unanimous consent of the Board.6. An Inter-Governmental Committee on Transatlantic Air Services to be established, to which shall be referred for approval decisions or proposals, relating to these services, which affect national policy or intra- or extra-commonwealth relations. The committee to consist of four members appointed respectively by the governments of the United Kingdom, Irish Free State, Newfoundland and Canada.4.SUB-COMMITTEE-GENERAL, FINANCE AND CO-ORDINATING.1. A meeting of the above sub-committee was held under the chairmanship of Mr. V. I. Smart in Room 570, Centre Block, Parliament Buildings, at 14.30 hours, Thursday, the 28th of November, 1935.2. The following members comprising the sub-committee were present :  Mr. V. I. Smart. Mr. L. C. Christie. Dr. W. C. Clark. Sir Donald Banks. Colonel F. C. Shelmerdine. Mr. J. Leydon. Mr. J. P. Walshe. The Hon. T. Lodge. Also Mr. P. T. Coolican. Mr. J. A. Wilson. &apos;   Mr. C. G. L. Syers.3. The minutes of the sub-committee meeting held on Tuesday, the 26th of November, were reviewed in detail, and adopted as corrected. They are to be reproduced and copies distributed to members.4. Mr. Leydon brought forward further points for consideration which were disposed of as follows : (1) Agreements between governments should be of a permanent character.   Agreed. (2) Agreements between governments and the joint operating company should be for fifteen years.   Agreed.(3) The joint operating company to be registered in the United Kingdom, the Irish Free State and Canada. In the opinion of the committee this presented many difficulties and is to be further investigated as to its feasibility.(4) A I reasonable proportion of the aircraft of the joint operating company to bear registration markings of each country. No objection was seen from the United Kingdom or Canadian point of view.(5) A reasonable proportion of nationals of each participating country to be employed at airports and in operations. This involves training in technical matters. The committee considered that the safeguarding of national interests might be pro-vided for by the wording of the lease of the various airports to the joint operating company. While agreeing in principle, the committee did not consider it advisable that such restrictions should be included at this time.(6) The Irish Free State to be the last port of call for westbound traffic before crossing the Atlantic, and the first port of call for eastbound traffic. Agreed, insofar as the direct route was concerned.(7) Optional transfer of passengers and traffic to be provided for at the Irish Free State port of call.   Agreed.
5. Mr. Christie suggested that a report be drawn up at the conclusion of the discussion on transatlantic air services as well as the actual agreement which would be submitted to all representatives for signature. The various points raised by Mr. Leydon might well be included in such a report.   Agreed.6. The Honourable Mr. Lodge submitted a memorandum outlining the attitude of the Government of Newfoundland in regard to the transatlantic air service. A copy of this memorandum is attached to these minutes. It was agreed that the ownership of radio and meteorological services established in Newfoundland would be expressly noted in the arrange-ments to be worked out between Canada and Newfoundland. The committee considered, however, that the meteorological service should be vested in the Government of Newfoundland, but that the existing marine radio stations now owned and operated by Canada should continue to be the property of Canada.7. A drafting committee was nominated to prepare a report of the conference and the agreement to be initialled by the representatives of each country, the drafting committee to* consist of : Mr. L. C. Christie. Squadron-Leader A. T. Cowley. Colonel F. C. Shelmerdine. Mr. C. G. L. Syers. Mr. J. P. Walshe. Mr. J. Leydon.A. T. COWLEY, Squadron-Leader,Secretary.Memorandum submitted by the Honourable Mr. Lodge.NEWFOUNDLAND AND TRANSATLANTIC AIR SERVICE.The Government of Newfoundland will allow the importation free of duty of gasoline and lubricating oil (? anything else) for the use of aircraft employed on the transatlantic service to or from Canada, the Irish Free State and the United Kingdom (? wide enough).The Government of Newfoundland undertakes that when a regular air mail is in operation it will contribute a proportion of the residual operating loss.Technical officers lent by the Government of the United Kingdom or Canada will be responsible to the Government of Newfoundland in all matters of ordinary administration.Subject to the overriding consideration of efficient service every effort will be made to employ Newfoundlanders in local administration.The Government of Newfoundland will be glad to avail itself of the assistance of His Majesty&apos;s Governments in United Kingdom and Canada in the establishment of the necessary ground facilities, radio communications and meteorological services required in connection with the proposed trans-atlantic air services during the periods of experimental flying and of regular operation.It is understood that the property in the fixed installations required for these services provided by the Governments of the United Kingdom and Canada will be vested in the Government of Newfoundland subject to such arrangements as may be deemed desirable to ensure that they shall at all times be available for the purposes for which they are intended.The Government of Newfoundland will undertake to transmit meteorological messages over its governmental telegraph system free of any internal charges.(C19%1)D2
5.REPORT OF THE POSTAL SUB-COMMITTEE.1. A sub-committee to discuss and consider the problems arising from the operation of the proposed service from a postal standpoint was formed under the joint chairmanship of Sir Donald Banks, Direct or-General of the British Post Office and Mr. P. T. Coolican, Assistant Deputy Postmaster-General of Canada.2. The following comprise the committee : 3. The main task of the sub-committee was to make recommendations acceptable to the participating Commonwealth administrations in regard to the postal questions involved.4. After exhaustive discussion, the sub-committee reached agreement on the following points : (I) The establishment of a joint air mail service between Canada, Irish Free State,Newfoundland, and United Kingdom.(2) The carriage of all first-class mail by air between these countries to be envisaged as and when technical and economic conditions permit.The question of the carriage of mails by air between the Irish Free State and United Kingdom would, however, be reserved for separate agreement.(3) That, in the meantime, the principle of surcharging should be adopted.(4) That (except during the period when nights are purely experimental and irregular during which the charges, et cetera, would be the subject of special agreement) the postage rates, including surcharges, should be fixed after consultation between the respective postal administrations.(5) That, while the desirability of fixing uniform postage rates is appreciated, it is recognized that this may not always be possible. It is, however, agreed that the rates should not exceed 2s. per half ounce or be less than Is. per half ounce.(6) That each participating postal administration should accept the principle of reducing surcharge rates as and when it is found possible to secure reductions of carriage rates from the operating company.(7) That the carriage rates per pound to he paid by the four participating countries should be uniform, and that similar rates should be offered to other Commonwealth countries.(8) That the carriage rates per pound to be charged to foreign countries should be uniform and subject to agreement between the four participating postal&apos; adminis-trations. It is, however, in contemplation that such rates would be materially higher than those to be charged to Commonwealth countries.(9) That, while it is recognized that the rates of payment per pound to the operating company may have to be the subject of negotiation, it is agreed that the surcharge rates must bear a definite relation to such air transport payments.(10) That, for the present, the question of the arrangements to be applied to mail originating in the United States should be reserved.(II) That from the postal point of view the minimum frequency of service should be twoflights per week in each direction.(12) That from the postal point of view the use of Montreal as the western terminus of the transatlantic route, in the event of the non-participation of the United States, or, as a port of call in each direction should such participation be arranged, is considered to be essential.Mr. D. O. Lumley Mr. G. HerringSir Donald Banks Mr. P. T. Coolican Mr. J. Leydon^(&quot;United Kingdom. ^Canada.Irish Free State.United Kingdom.Mr. F. E. JolliffeCanada. Canada.Ottawa, 23rd November, 1935.
6.REPORT OF THE OPERATING AND TECHNICAL SUB-COMMITTEE.I. Bases for Experimental Flights.1. The sub-committee recommend the use of bases at Botwood, Newfoundland, with Gander and Deer Lakes as possible emergency alternatives, and the St. Lawrence River at Montreal with Lake St. Louis as an emergency alternative.2. Provided daylight operations alone are contemplated, the only additional facilities required are moorings and motor boat tenders. These facilities will be provided in New-foundland by the United Kingdom and in Montreal by Canada. The expense is relatively small and can be met out of regular appropriations (Appendix &quot;A&quot;, paragraph 3). If night landings are contemplated, four standard landing lights (specifications to be supplied by the United Kingdom) will be required at each base.3. The sub-committee are of the opinion that the &quot;plane on the first experimental flight should proceed right through to Montreal with minimum delay in Newfoundland and that before returning should visit Ottawa and Toronto (Appendix &quot;A&quot;, paragraph 3).4. Winter Flying Tests. It is recommended that, on the termination of the flying tests in 1936, one of the flying boats should remain in Canada, if possible, in order that experimental flights in cold weather may be carried out. It is suggested the Royal Canadian Air Force base at Dartmouth would be a suitable station for these tests (Appendix &quot;A.&quot;, paragraph 5).II. Communications.5. The United Kingdom will establish a temporary comprehensive radio telegraph station at Botwood and this, in conjunction with existing stations established by Canada, will be ample to provide adequate communication and navigation facilities during the experimental period (Appendix &quot; B &quot;). The additional cost involved will be the salaries of one or two extra operators to maintain constant watch while the flights are in progress and can be met from ordinary appropriations.6. It is recommended that the officer in charge of radio for the Air Ministry, who is respon-sible for the radio equipment in the &apos;plane and her communications, be sent to Canada prior to the first flight so that all cis-Atlantic services may be properly co-ordinated.III. Meteorology .-7. Newfoundland. The present meteorological service in Newfoundland is regarded as inadequate and it is recommended that immediate steps be taken to strengthen it. The report of the meteorological section of the sub-committee, appended hereto (Appendix &quot; C &quot;) submits the following recommendations, which are concurred in : (1) To establish immediately a central office in Newfoundland in charge of a meteorologist with necessary staff, also 10 additional stations, and to supplement equipment at existing stations, at a capital cost of $2,575.00.8. The annual operating cost of the complete re-organized service for 1936 is estimated at $12,120.00.9. During the experimental flights it will be necessary to provide a skeleton forecasting staff in Newfoundland and to provide an augmented communication service at an estimated cost of $8,000.00.The total recommended expenditure in Newfoundland for 1936, is, therefore $22,695.00.10. Canada. In order to provide adequate meteorological service for the flights between Newfoundland and Montreal, the sub-committee recommend (Appendix &quot; D &quot;) the establish-ment of nine additional stations in Canada and the augmentation of equipment at nine existing stations at a capital cost of $10,755.00. The additional operating cost of the above for the year 1936 is estimated at $24,365.00. It will also be necessary to augment the staff at the headquarters of the Meteorological Service in Toronto at an estimated cost of $19,440.00.The total expenditure recommended for 1936 in Canada is $54,550.00The combined total for 1936 is : Newfoundland    . .       ..       ......       . . $22,695.00Canada    ..       ..       .......... $54,550.00$77,245.00
11. The sub-committee recommend that, when regular flights are inaugurated in 1937,. a forecasting staff be established at St. Hubert and the total expenditure for the service in Canada for the year 1937 is estimated at $59,805.00, while the cost in Newfoundland for the same year will be $56,140.00. The latter figure includes $20,000.00 for communications and the establishment of a permanent forecasting station in Newfoundland.Total cost for 1937-Newfoundland......       ..       $56,140.00Canada . .       . .       ......       $59,805.00$115,945.0012. The sub-committee attach importance to the recommendation of the Meteorological Section that a &apos;plane be made available in Newfoundland for the purpose of obtaining daily upper air observations.APPENDIX A.OPERATING AND TECHNICAL SUB-COMMITTEECOMMUNICATIONS AND BASES SECTION.1. Messrs. I. McClure, C. P. Edwards, and J. A. Wilson met at 10.00 a.m. on 25th November to consider existing facilities in Canada and Newfoundland and the requirements for the experimental stage.Radio.2. Radio communications were discussed with Mr. Woods Humphery. It was agreed that the present facilities were adequate for the experimental period, with the addition of a &quot; comprehensive &quot; station at Botwood, Newfoundland, which would be supplied and operated by the United Kingdom under arrangement with the Newfoundland authorities.Base Facilities.3. It was agreed, Mr. Woods Humphery concurring, that the only essential installations at the bases at Botwood and Montreal were adequate moorings. Drawings and specifications would be supplied by the United Kingdom for those required at Montreal so that they might be provided by Canadian authorities. The moorings at Botwood would be supplied by the United Kingdom under arrangement with the Newfoundland authorities. Motor boat tenders would also be required at these bases. It was considered that the tender now available at the Fairchild Company&apos;s seaplane base would be adequate for the experimental period. Mr. WoodsHumphery stated that if the Canadian Government wished the flying boat to visit other cities in Canada, such as Ottawa and Toronto, this could be arranged.   Provision would, in that case, be necessary for mooring and tenders.Canadian Base.4. Mr. A. D. McLean discussed seaplane bases in detail with Mr. Woods Humphery and Mr. McClure. Charts of the landing areas at Montreal, Ottawa, and Toronto were examined and found to provide suitable areas. Mr. McClure has also visited St. Hubert and seen the landing areas at Montreal and Ottawa.Winter Flying Tests.5. Mr. Woods Humphery suggested that it might be advisable, at the termination of the operations in the summer of 1936, to leave one of the flying boats on this side of the Atlantic to determine operating conditions for frying boats in cold weather. It was agreed that the Royal Canadian Air Force Station at Dartmouth, Nova Scotia, would be the most suitable base if the R.C.A.F. could co-operate.APPENDIX B.OPERATING AND TECHNICAL SUB-COMMITTEE.COMMUNICATIONS SECTION.1. With the addition of one comprehensive long wave, short wave, and direction finding radio station to be established by the United Kingdom authorities at Botwood, Newfoundland, the radio communication facilities now established and operated by Canada in Newfoundland and along the route to Montreal are regarded as adequate to provide first-class communication with the plane during the test flights.
2. It may be necessary to place an extra operator on one or two of the stations during the actual flight period, in order to provide uninterrupted radio watch, and it may also be necessary to arrange for a station for &quot; homing &quot; purposes at Quebec. This, however, can be done without involving any capital expenditure.3. Subject to further discussions with the officers of the Air Ministry, the communication set-up contemplates the &quot;plane establishing communication on short wave with Botwood, Newfoundland, immediately after leaving Ireland. Botwood, in turn, will maintain communication on short wave with the airport at Montreal and with Ottawa.4. The &apos;plane when approaching within five or six hundred miles of Newfoundland can secure accurate bearings from the Marine direction finding stations at Belle Isle and Cape Race, and when approaching Botwood, Newfoundland, should be able to make use of the direction finding station at St. Paul for cross bearings.5. On leaving Botwood the &apos;plane will maintain constant communication with the short wave station at the airport in Montreal.6. In addition the chain of Marine &quot; aid to navigation &quot; coast stations along the Gulf, approxi-mately 200 miles apart, will give the &quot;plane local communication, and if she is equipped with a direction finder, she can made good use of the marine automatic radio beacon system which is operated along the St. Lawrence waterway.7. Should the &apos;plane be fitted with a &quot; homing device,&quot; arrangements can be made for existing stations at certain stragetical points to give this service.8. It is suggested that the Air Ministry or Imperial Airways Officer-in-Charge of radio for the experimental flights, might, with advantage, visit Canada prior to the first flight, to discuss all the details of the communication set-up in order that there may be complete co-ordination in this reference.APPENDIX C.OPERATING AND TECHNICAL SUB-COMMITTEE. METEOROLOGICAL SECTION. (A) Preliminary Collection of Data in Newfoundland -1936. (1) Present Position.At the present time meteorological data are being collected from the following sources : (a) Telegraphic Reporting Stations : Belle Isle, Fogo, St. John&apos;s, Cape Race, Grand Banks,St. Georges, Millertown and Cartwright. (6) Secondary Stations :  Shoal Harbour, Bonavista, Botwood, Deer Lake, Channel andRamea.(c) Privately Owned Stations :  Grand Falls, Howley, Corner Brook, Corner Brook Dam andBuchans.(d) Canadian Light Houses :  Norman, Point Amour and Point Riche.(e) Fog Alarm Stations :  Cape John, Long Point, Cabot Island, Baccalieu Island, Cape St.Francis, Cape Spear, Point la Haye, Lamalire, St. Jacques Island and Francois.Observations from stations (a), (b) and (d) are organized by the Meteorological Service of Canada, those from (e) by Imperial Airways Limited through the Department of Natural Resources, and those from (c) by the Paper Companies or Mining Company. Long series of observations exist only in the case of certain of stations (a), certain of stations (c) and stations (d). No observations of visibility on the international scale exist prior to November, 1934, and then only in the case of stations (a) and (e). From two to three years&apos; pilot balloon observations are available from Belle Isle and Cape Race and it is only from these two stations, during the period of the upper air observations, that observations of cloud height are available.(2) Suggested Development.It is considered that a meteorologist should be stationed in Newfoundland, if possible, before the 1st of January, 1936, to re-organize the system of observations, carry out frequent inspections of the stations and collect and summarise their data.In order to ensure, as far as possible, an adequate supply of data regarding the meteorological conditions over Newfoundland from the point of view of aviation, it is considered that the following re-organization of observations should take place ;(a) Frequency of Observations. Observations at all stations should be made three times daily, including Sundays; at 8 a.m., 2 p.m., and 8 p.m. Newfoundland time. This is necessary in order to obtain sufficient information regarding diurnal variation, particularly of cloud and visibility.(6) Privately-owned Stations. The authorities at Grand Falls, Corner Brook and Buchans should be invited to contribute to the general scheme of observations at the five stations in paragraph 1 (c), and the stations should be equipped with official instruments which should be installed under the supervision of the meteorologist.
(c) Distribution of Stations. It is considered that the existing distribution of stations is almost sufficient to give a satisfactory network of observations. Additional stations are required, however, at the heads of bays which may form suitable alternative air bases and at sites which have been selected in the Gander Lake area.   Suggested sites for new stations are :Avalon Peninsula :  Colinet, Whitbourne, Holyrood, Fox Island, Cape Pine, Hopeall Head.South Coast:  Jude Island, North Harbour Point.Gander Lake :  Cobbs Camp, Gleneagles.(d) Visibility Observations. It is considered that all stations should make regular visibility observations according to the international scale. In the case of new stations visibility objects should be selected by the meteorologist.   In the case of existing stations visibility objects should be checked.(e) Observations of Cloud Height. The following stations should be equipped with hydrogen and. small balloons and should make regular observations of cloud height when the cloud is below 2,000 feet. They should also be encouraged to estimate the cloud height at other times.All Telegraphic Reporting Stations.Whitbourne, Shoal Harbour, Gleneagles, Botwood, and Deer Lake.(/) Pilot Balloon Observations. Regular pilot balloon observations should be made at St. John&apos;s and Deer Lake. It is considered that the personnel at Memorial College and at the Deer Lake Power Station will be competent to make these observations. If possible, observations should be made twice daily, but if this is not practicable, observations should be made once a day, preferably near the middle of the day.[g) Ice Observations. Stations at the heads of bays and on lakes should keep a log noting the times of freezing of the bays or lakes, the state of ice, and the times at which ice disappears. A special note should be kept of drift ice.[h) Classification of Stations. Stations would be classified as follows : (i) Pilot Balloon Stations St. John&apos;s and Deer Lake.(ii) Telegraphic Reporting Stations- as at present.(iii) Secondary Stations stations under paragraph 1 (b), (c), and (d) together with Whitbourneand Gleneagles. Observations : temperature and rainfall; eye-observations of weather, visibility, cloud forms and amount (cloud height in certain cases), wind direction and strength.(iv) Auxiliary Stations all other stations.   Observations : non-instrumental observationsunder (iii).(i) Collection of Data. Observations would be forwarded monthly to the meteorologist at St. John&apos;s who would summarize them, sending copies of the summaries to London and Toronto (and possibly Washington). It will probably be found necessary to provide clerical assistance for the meteorologist at St. John&apos;s for this purpose.   Such assistance could be recruited locally.[j) Payments to Observers. The following scales of pay are suggested for the different classes of stations : -(i) Pilot Balloon Stations (Pilot balloon observations only),$300.00 per year for 1 observation a day, $600.00 per year for 2 observations a day.(ii) Telegraph Reporting Stations (3 observations a day),$270.00 per year plus $30.00 bonus for satisfactory work.(iii) Secondary Stations (3 observations a day),$75.00 per year plus $15.00 bonus for satisfactory work.(iv) Auxiliary Stations,$60.00 per year plus $15.00 bonus for satisfactory work.(k) Cost of Service.-(i) Capital Cost.IPilot Balloon equipment at St. John&apos;s and Deer Lake ..       ..       ..       ..     1,200.00Equipment at 7 secondary stations ..       ..       ..      ..       ..       ..       500.00Hydrogen cylinders ..       ..       ..       ..      ..       ..      ..       ..       ..       875.00Total Capital Cost$2,575.00
(ii) Recurring Charges.Salary of staff at St. John&apos;s :  $Meteorologist             ..       . .       ............ 1,920.001 Clerk, Grade 1          ..........       ...... 1,080.001 Clerk, Grade 2         ................ 480.00Payments to Observers : 2 Pilot Balloon Stations        .........       ...... 1,200.006 Telegraphic Stations          ........     &quot; - -       .... 1,800.0016 Secondary Stations................ 1,440.0018 Auxiliary Stations............ 1,350.00TraveUing.................... 1,000.00Hydrogen      ..................       - - 100.00Balloons        ......      .. . 1..........       - - 750.00Transport of hydrogen and equipment     ..       ..       ..                         - - 1,000.00Total Recurring Charge      ......$12,120.00(B) ESTABLISHMENT OF FORECASTING ORGANIZATION, 1936-37.(1) The Newfoundland Terminus.Before a regular transatlantic air service is inaugurated it will be necessary to establish a fore-casting station at the air base in Newfoundland, responsible for the day-to-day study of meteorological conditions over the North Atlantic and for the issue of weather reports and forecasts for air navigation. For this purpose it will be necessary to collect, preferably by radio, synoptic messages issued by Canada, the United States and Great Britain and to interchange information with the terminal base in Ireland as well as collecting reports from local stations in Newfoundland. A twenty-four hour service will be required. It may be found necessary to extend the number of observations at telegraphic stations in Newfoundland and eastern Canada to four per day and to provide a more intense network of reporting stations.The cost of this service in the first, year would be $Staff.-Officer in charge............       ......     3,750.00Three Forecasters ..       ..       ..       ..       ..       ..       . .       ..       .;     6,250.00Clerks and Observers       ................   10,000.00Total cost of staff      ........$20,000.00Equipment. Instruments, furniture, etc. ..       ..       . .       . .       . .       ..     5,000.00Running Costs. Rent, light, travelling, etc.     ..       ..       ..       . .       . .       ..     2,500.00$27,500.00(2) Service for Experimental Flights, 1936.It will not be necessary to establish a full forecasting organization, as outlined in paragraph (1) for the experimental flights due to take place in 1936. - It will be essential, however, to provide a skeleton organization at the Newfoundland base before these flights commence. This would be arranged by posting temporarily to Newfoundland sufficient staff to prepare synoptic charts and issue forecasts. The staff would be provided by the meteorological service responsible for the meteorological organization in Newfoundland.It is estimated that the additional cost involved during the period of the experimental flights will not exceed $8,000.00, including telegraph charges and extra forecasting staff.(3) Telegraph Charges.On the establishment of the permanent service, consideration to be given to handling this weather traffic by radio direct from Toronto, provided same can show a swing in cost.(4) Additional Services.In addition to the organization outlined above it will be desirable, before the experimental flights commence, to arrange for regular daily observations of upper air temperatures and humidities from an aircraft stationed at some convenient point between Botwood and Corner Brook.Arrangements will also be necessary for the reception of reports from ships in the North Atlantic at a radio station in Newfoundland or eastern Canada and for the transmission of the reports to the terminal base in Newfoundland. This service will have to be arranged by the United Kingdom, Canadian and United States meteorological services in consultation.No estimate of the costs of these special services can be given at this stage.(C 19961)
(5) Summary of Costs.1936 Preliminary Collection of data Capital Cost (a)   . . Recurring Cost, Staff (6).. Other items (c)    ..       ..Skeleton Forecasting Organization (d) Communications (e)1937 Full Forecasting Organization  Capital Cost (/)   .. Recurring Cost (g)        .. Communications (h)TOTAL COST 1936 (a) (b) (c) (d) (e) TOTAL COST 1937 (c) (e) (g) (h)    .. TOTAL COST 1938 et seq. (c) (g) (h)2,575.00 3,480.00 8,640.003,000.00 5,000.005,000.00 22,500.00 20,000.0022,695.00 56,140.00 51,140.00(Signed) J. PATTERSON, F. ENTWISTLE.APPENDIX   D.OPERATING AND TECHNICAL SUB-COMMITTEE. METEOROLOGICAL SECTION.Additional Meteorological Service Required for the Route from Newfoundlandto Montreal.1. This additional service is necessary for the Newfoundland base as well as for St. Hubert (Montreal). The service given here will also be of great value to the work of the Meteorological Service of Canada in addition to that for the airway. The present meteorological establishment for eastern Canada is not included in this memorandum.(a) Two telegraphic reporting stations should be established on the north shore of the st. Lawrence to give an adequate distribution to the north as stations are not possible in the interior of north-eastern Quebec. There should also be established a station in northern New Brunswick and another as far north in Quebec as it is possible to get radio communication.   Suggested stations are : Clarke City and Natashquan (North Shore),Kedgwick  (northern New Brunswick), andMistassini (northern Quebec). These stations will be most valuable additions to the Canadian network in eastern Canada.(b) Secondary Stations : Secondary stations recording temperature, humidity, rain, wind (byestimation), weather and visibility are required at Boistown, Woodstock, St. Leonard, Riviere du Loup, Thetford, Pte\ des Monts, Havre St. Pierre, Pt. Amour and one station in the Park region of Quebec.(c) Auxiliary Stations : Lighthouse, fog alarm and signal service stations of the St. Lawrenceand Gulf, to record non-instrumental observations, including visibility (without pay).(d) Pilot Balloon Stations :   It is very necessary to get a wide distribution of these stations witha number well away from the route. The stations will be very valuable for the general forecasting of the service.   Suitable stations are : Sable Island, Halifax, Fredericton, Grindstone Island, Megantic, Quebec, South West Point, Father Point, Dolbean = 9 stations.(e) Ceiling Balloon Stations : Telegraph reporting stations : Charlottetown, Chatham, Clarke City, Harrington and Father Point ; Secondary Stations :  Heath Pt., Riviere du Loup, Pte. des Monts, Pt. Amour -- 9 stations.2. Frequency of observations. At. first, observations should be taken 3 times a day : 8 a.m., 2 p.m., and 8 p.m. E.S.T., the 2 p.m. observation to be recorded but not telegraphed.3. Scale of payment to observers : $I.   Telegraph reporting stations     . .       . .       . .       . .       . . 600.00 per annum.II.   Secondary stations (including ceiling balloons) ...       . . 175.00   ,,III. Secondary stations without ceiling balloon     . .       . .       . . 125.00   ,,     ,,IV. Pilot balloon stations (two per day).   (2 required to take theobservation).............. 900.00   ,,
4. Capital Costs :  $I.   Four telegraph reporting stations at $600.00 each    ..       .. 2,400.00II.   Nine secondary stations at $45.00 each         ..       ..       . . 405.00III. Nine stations for ceiling balloons, less cylinders         ..&apos;      .. 100.00IV. Nine stations with pilot balloon equipment at $600.00 each   . . 5,400.00 V.   Seventy hydrogen cylinders at $35.00 each...... 2,450.00Total...... $10,755.00Current Costs :  $(a) I.   Four telegraphic reporting stations at $600.00 each   ..       .. 2,400.00II.   Four secondary stations with ceiling balloons at $175.00     .. 700.00III. Five secondary stations without ceiling balloons at $125.00 .. 625.00IV. Nine Pilot Balloon stations at $900.00 each...... 8,100.00Total Salaries(b) Operating expenses other than salaries :  I.   Balloons II.   HydrogenIII. Freight on hydrogen cylindersIV. Telegrams from 4 stationsV.   Telegrams from 8 pilot balloon stations VI.   Inspection (Travelling expenses) VII.   Contingencies(c) Total current expenditure :  5 (a).   Salaries5(b).   Other operating expenses$11,825.003,000.00 1,750.00 1,600.00 730.00 1,460.00 2,000.00 2,000.00$12,540.00$:11,825.00 12,540.00Total$24,365.006. Summary of expenditure for 1936 :  $4.   Capital expenditures      ..       . . . .       ..       ..       . . 10,755.005(c).   Current expenditures      ..       .. ..       ..       ..       .. 24,365.00Total........ $35,120.007. In 1937 there will have to be a forecasting staff at St. Hubert (Montreal), the cost of whichI. 1 Officer in charge ............II. 1 Forecaster        .............. 2&apos; 05,05III. 2 Clerks, Grade 3 ($1,380)        .......... 2&apos;^&apos;H2IV. 1 Clerk, Grade 2   .............. 1,080.00V. 1 Clerk, Grade 1   .............. 720.00Total Salaries      ..............&quot; ?f40-00Contingencies      .............. VnnnmAdditional telegraphic charges .. o.ouu.uTotal    . .       ..       ..       .. $16,000.008. Estimated expenditure for 1937 :  $Current expenditure for 1936, as in 5 (c) . . ..       ..       ..       . .       . .   24,365.00Additional expenduiture for 1937 as in 7 ..       ..       . .       . .       . .   16,000.00Total for 1937 ..........$40,365.009. To put this service into effect will require additions to the head office staff which are not included in the above. It will be absolutely necessary to appoint immediately 5 forecasters at least to undergo intensive training for this work. They should have two years&apos; training before being sent out to the forecasting services and if the forecasting centres are to be established in 1937 the matter is extremely urgent. The administration staff will have to be strengthened, and an extra instrument maker added. The staff requirements would be at least : $5 Meteorologists, Grade 1, at $1,920       ............     9,600.00Additional administration and clerical staff       . .       ..       ..       ..       . .    9,840.00$19,440.00
4. Capital Costs :  $I.   Four telegraph reporting stations at $600.00 each    . .       .. 2,400.00II.   Nine secondary stations at $45.00 each         ...... 405.00III. Nine stations for ceiling balloons, less cylinders         ..&apos;      .. 100.00IV. Nine stations with pilot balloon equipment at $600.00 each   .. 5,400.00 V.   Seventy hydrogen cylinders at $35.00 each...... 2,450.00Total...... $10,755.00Current Costs :  $(a) I.   Four telegraphic reporting stations at $600.00 each..... 2,400.00II.   Four secondary stations with ceiling balloons at $175.00     .. 700.00III. Five secondary stations without ceiling balloons at $125.00 .. 625.00IV. Nine Pilot Balloon stations at $900.00 each...... 8,100.00Total Salaries  ..       .. $11,825.00(b) Operating expenses other than salaries :  $I.   Balloons    ..       .............. 3,000.00II.   Hydrogen................ 1,750.00III. Freight on hydrogen cylinders   ..       . .       ..       ..       .. 1,600.00IV. Telegrams from 4 stations        . .       . .       . .       ..       .. 730.00V.   Telegrams from 8 pilot balloon stations         ..       ..       .. 1,460.00VI.   Inspection (Travelling expenses)         ..       ..       ..       .. 2,000.00VII.   Contingencies      .............. 2,000.00$12,540.00(c) Total current expenditure :  $5 (a).   Salaries     ................ 11,825.005 (b).   Other operating expenses         ..       . .       ..       ..       . . 12,540.00Total........ $24,365.006. Summary of expenditure for 19364.   Capital expenditures 5 (c).   Current expenditures$10,755.00 24,365.00Total$35,120.007. In 1937 there will have to be a forecasting staff at St. Hubert (Montreal), the cost of whichwill be :- $ N.N.I..   1 Officer in charge          ............ 2,880.00II.   1 Forecaster        .............. 2,400.00III. 2 Clerks, Grade 3 ($1,380)        .......... 2,760.00IV. 1 Clerk, Grade 2   .............. 1,080.00V.   1 Clerk, Grade 1   .............. 720.00- $Total Salaries      .............. 9,840.00Contingencies      .............. 1,160.00Additional telegraphic charges . .       .. 5,000.00Total...... .. $16,000.008. Estimated expenditure for 1937 :  $Current expenditure for 1936, as in 5 (c) . .       ..       .. .. . .       ..   24,365.00Additional expenduiture for 1937 as in 7           . .       .. .. . .       ..   16,000.00Total for 1937 ..........$40,365.009. To put this service into effect will require additions to the head office staff which are not included in the above. It will be absolutely necessary to appoint immediately 5 forecasters at least to undergo intensive training for this work. They should have two years&apos; training before being sent out to the forecasting services and if the forecasting centres are to be established in 1937 the matter is extremely urgent. The administration staff will have to be strengthened, and an extra instrument maker added. The staff requirements would be at least : $5 Meteorologists, Grade 1, at $1,920      ............     9,600.00Additional administration and clerical staff       . .       ..       ..       . .       . .     9,840.00$19,440.00
10. General Summary.Estimated expenditure for 1936 :  $Capital expenditure (see paragraph 6) . .       ..       .. . . . . .. 10,755.00Current expenditure (see paragraph 6) ..       ..       .. . . . . . . 24,365.00Head Office requirements (paragraph 9) ..       ..       . . .. . . .. 19,440.00Total...... .. .. .. $54,550.0011. Estimated expenditure for 1937 : - $Current expenditure as in 1936 (paragraph 6)             ..       ..       ..       .. 24,365.00Additional for 1937 (paragraph 7)          ............ 16,000.00Head office addition (paragraph 9)         ............ 19,440.00Total    . .       ..       ..       ..       ..       .. $59,805.0012. One station at Great Whale River on the east coast of Hudson Bay would be of very great value to the whole service and trans-Canada and transatlantic flying. It would require the installation of a wireless station and two operators, who would also be the meteorological observers.13. Observations from ships will also have to be collected, but this will be undertaken as a part of the routine work of the Meteorological Service of Canada.(Signed) J. PATTERSON.7.MINUTES OF FINAL MEETING.1. The final meeting was held in Room 268, Centre Block, Parliament Buildings, on Monday the 2nd of December, with Mr. V. I. Smart in the Chair.2. The following representatives were present :  Canada Mr. V. I. Smart, Deputy Minister, Department of Railways and Canals ;Mr. Loring C. Christie, Counsellor, Department of External Affairs ;Mr. J. A. Wilson, Controller of Civil Aviation ;Mr. P. T. Coolican, Assistant Deputy Postmaster-General;Mr. C. P. Edwards, Director of Radio, Department of Marine ;Dr. W. C. Clark, Deputy Minister, Department of Finance ;Squadron Leader A. T. N. Cowley, Superintendent, Air Regulations Secretary.United Kingdom Colonel Sir Donald Banks, K.C.B., D.S.O., M.C., Director-General of the Post Office ;Lieut.-Colonel F. C. Shelmerdine, C.I.E., O.B.E., Director-General of Civil Aviation, Air Ministry ;Mr. G. E. Woods Humphery, C.B.E., Managing Director of Imperial Airways Limited ;Mr. D. O. Lumley, O.B.E., General Post Office ; Mr. C. G. L. Syers, Dominions Office ;Mr. N. E. Archer, Secretary, Office of the High Commissioner for the United Kingdom.Irish Free State Mr. J. P. Walshe, Secretary of the Department of External Affairs ; Mr. J. Leydon, Secretary of the Department of Industry and Commerce.Also Present Mr. George Herring, Superintendent, Air Mail Service, Post Office Department ; Mr.  F.   E.  Jolliffe,  Assistant Director, Administrative  Services,   Post  Office Department;Mr. F. T. Collins, Department of Railways and Canals.
3. A record of the conclusions reached during the conference had been prepared by the drafting committee and was submitted to the meeting for approval. Minor corrections were made to the record which was then accepted unanimously and signed by the following representatives : ^United Kingdom  Sir Donald Banks. Lieut.-Colonel F. C. Shelmerdine.Canada Mr. V. I. Smart Chairman.Irish Free State  Mr. John Leydon. Mr. J. P. Walshe.For the Representative of Newfoundland  Mr. Norman E. Archer.4. A copy of this record of conclusions is attached to these minutes.5. The representatives of the United Kingdom, Canada, the Irish Free State, and New-foundland, who took part in the discussions, further agreed to recommend to their respective governments as follows : (1) The Joint Operating Company should be registered in each country participating in the shareholding of the company, if there is no legal barrier to the adoption of that course, and provided that no registration fees or taxes are payable by the company in addition to those payable in United Kingdom.(2) A reasonable proportion of the Joint Operating Company&apos;s aircraft should be registered in each country participating in the shareholding of the company.(3) Subject to force majeure all east-bound aircraft on the transatlantic air service on the direct route shaU stop at the Irish Free State airport as first European port of call, and all west-bound aircraft on the direct, route shall stop at the Irish Free State airport.(4) Subject to prior consideration of the interests of the Joint Operating Company, and to reasonable consideration of the interests of the participating companies, east-bound traffic shall have the option of changing at the Irish Free State airport from the Joint Operating Company&apos;s aircraft and proceeding to its destina-tion in the aircraft of companies licensed by the Irish Free State Government for the operation of internal or international services and any necessary arrange-ments may be made for through booking facilities.(5) Subject to prior consideration of the interests of the Joint Operating Company, and to reasonable consideration of the interests of the participating companies, west-bound traffic shall have the option of joining the Joint Company&apos;s aircraft at the Irish Free State airport and any necessary arrangements may be made for through booking facilities.(6) A reasonable proportion of personnel employed by the Joint Operating Company shall be nationals of each country contributing to the subsidy, having regard to the amount of subsidy contributed. This is subject to personnel of the requisite standards being available ; the Joint Company will, however, use its best endeavours to afford such opportunities as it can reasonably offer in the course of its business for training such personnel.(7) All company and board meetings of the Joint Operating Company will be held in London, England.(8) Imperial Airways shall be paid by the Joint Operating Company reasonable fees for such services as they may perform on behalf of that company.(9) Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraph 18 of the Agreement, the United Kingdom will establish temporary radio facilities at the Newfoundland airport and operate them during the &quot; experimental stage.&quot;
6. The Chairman announced that the Canadian representatives to the discussions to be held in Washington would be Mr. L. C. Christie, Mr. J. A. Wilson, and Mr. P. T. Coolican.7. Before the conclusion of the meeting a vote of thanks to the Chairman, Mr. V. I. Smart, was moved by Sir Donald Banks, seconded by Mr. John Leydon and carried unani-mously. A vote of thanks to the Chairman of the Drafting Sub-Committee, Mr. L. C. Christie, was moved by Mr. J. P. Walshe, seconded by Lieut.-Colonel Shelmerdine, and also carried unanimously.S. In closing the conference the Chairman expressed his sincere appreciation of the very helpful attitude of the various representatives throughout the discussions which had now been brought to a successful conclusion.A. T. COWLEY, Squadron Leader,Secretary.TRANSATLANTIC AIR SERVICE.Ottawa, Canada,2nd December, 1935.Having met in conference in Ottawa to consider questions connected with the institution of Transatlantic Air Services for the carrying of mails and eventually passengers and freight, we, the representatives of the United Kingdom, Canada, the Irish Free State and Newfoundland, record the following conclusions unanimously reached by the conference which, subject to the final consideration and approval of our respective governments, it is agreed should form the basis of any arrangement entered into.-   Part I.Development Programme.1. The governments will co-operate in a programme of development of a transatlantic air service.    All practicable preference will be given to the direct route, including the Irish Free State and Montreal, but this understanding is not to be taken as preventing the - use of alternative routes for purposes of development.Two stages of development are contemplated  -(a) An initial stage, during which survey and experimental flights will be made and otherinvestigations carried out, followed by services which may be seasonal and irregular, this stage being hereinafter referred to as &quot; the experimental stage &quot; and(b) the establishment of a regular service, this stage being hereinafter referred to as&quot; the regular flying stage.&quot; This stage will commence as soon as a minimum of three months&apos; continuous flying on a schedule of two services a week is practicable.2. Flying operations and investigations during the experimental stage will be carried out by Imperial Airwa3?s Limited, under an arrangement to be made between that Company and the Government of the United Kingdom, as provided for in Part IV hereof. On completion of the experimental stage, the regular flying stage will be established as soon as practicable. It is hoped that the experimental stage will be completed and the regular flying stage established in 1938.3. As soon as the regular flying stage is reached, the responsibility for operations will be taken over by the Joint Operating Company provided for in Part II hereof under an agreement to be made between that Company and the four governments concerned.
Part II.Joint Operating Company.4. Steps will be taken by the governments of the United Kingdom, Canada, and the Irish Free State as soon as practicable with a view to the formation of a Joint Operating Company (hereinafter referred to as &quot; the Joint Company &quot;), which shall be constituted and organized in accordance with the following provisions: (1) The Joint Company will be incorporated at the instance of three companies acting in co-operation, namely, Imperial Airways, Limited, which is already incorporated in the United Kingdom and would be nominated by the government thereof for this purpose ; a Company incorporated or to be incorporated in Canada and nominated by the government thereof for the purpose ; and a Company incor-porated or to be incorporated in the Irish Free State and nominated by the government thereof for the purpose.(2) The capital stock of the Joint Company will be subscribed and held as to fifty-one per centum (51%) by Imperial Airways, Limited, twenty-four and a half per centum (241-%) by the proposed Canadian Company and twenty-four and a half per centum (24 %) by the proposed Irish Free State Company.(3) The Board of Directors of the Joint Company will be nine in number, of whom three will be nominated by Imperial Airways, Limited (the Chairman and Managing Director of the Joint Company to be chosen from these three) ; three by the proposed Canadian Company; and three by the proposed Irish Free State Company.(4) The Board of Directors of the Joint Company will have jurisdiction over questions of major policy, including that of increasing carriage rates. Subject to this provision, the control of commercial, technical, and operating matters will be secured to Imperial Airways, Limited, through its stockholding and through the medium of the articles of association of the Joint Company.(5) The original directors will all be agreed upon by the three participating Companies and the three governments concerned upon the formation of the Joint Company. One director nominated by each participating Company will retire annually and will be eligible for re-election by the shareholders subject to the provisions of sub-paragraph (3) of this paragraph. Any vacancy occurring will be filled by means of a nomination by the participating Company concerned after consultation with and acceptance by the remaining members of the Board.(6) No stock in the Joint Company will be offered for sale or sold without the unanimous consent of the Board of Directors.Part III.Postal Arrangements.5. The governments will agree to the establishment of a joint transatlantic air mail service between Canada, Newfoundland, the Irish Free State, and the United Kingdom.6. The governments contemplate the carriage of all first-class mail by air between these countries as and when technical and economic conditions permit. The question of the carriage of mail, other than transatlantic mail, by air between the United Kingdom and the Irish Free State will, however, be reserved for separate arrangement between these two countries.7. In the meantime, until the position contemplated by paragraph 6 is reached, the principle of surcharges will be adopted.8. During the period when flights are purely experimental and irregular, postage rates, including surcharges, for transatlantic mail carried by air will be the subject of special arrange-ments between the postal administrations concerned. Thereafter postage rates, including surcharges, will be fixed after consultation between the respective postal administrations.9. It is recognized that, while the fixing of uniform postage rates is desirable, this may not always be practicable. It is, however, agreed that the postage rates, including surcharges, should not, during the initial period of the regular flying stage, exceed two shillings per half ounce, or be less than one shilling per half ounce.
10. Each participating postal administration will accept the principle of reducing sur-charge rates as and when it is found possible to secure reductions of carriage rates from the Joint Company.11. The carriage rates per pound to be paid by the four participating postal administra-tions should be uniform, and similar rates shall be made available to the postal administrations of the Commonwealth of Australia (with Papua and Norfolk Island, and the mandated terri-tories of New Guinea and Nauru), New Zealand (with the mandated territory of Western Samoa), the Union of South Africa (with the mandated territory of South West Africa), India, or of any British Colony, Protectorate, territory under suzerainty, or territory under mandate administered by the Government of the United Kingdom.12. The carriage rates per pound to be charged to countries other than those referred to in paragraph 11 shall be uniform, and shall be subject to agreement between the four participating postal administrations, but may be materially higher than those to be fixed pursuant to paragraph 11.13. While it is recognized that the carriage rates to be paid to the Joint Company may have to be the subject of negotiation, it is agreed that the surcharge rates shall bear a definite relation to such carriage rates.14. From the postal point of view the minimum frequency of service should be two flights per week in each direction.15. From the postal point of view, the use of Montreal as the western terminus of the transatlantic route or as a port of call in each direction is considered to be essential.Part IV.Financial and other Commitments.16. During the experimental stage the flying operations will be financed by the Govern-ment of the United Kingdom. To this end the Government of the United Kingdom will enter into an arrangement with Imperial Airways, Limited, whereby that company will undertake (1) to carry out experimental transatlantic flights on the direct route and to pursue such technical investigations as may be considered desirable, with a view to facilitating the establishment of a regular transatlantic service at the earliest possible date ;(2) to carry out all necessary investigations, including experimental flights, within the shortest period practicable ; it being understood that, while it is impossible to give a binding undertaking as to the duration of the period required for such investi-gations, it is hoped to complete them by the 31st December, 1936 ; and(3) to place the results of such investigations fully at the disposal of the Joint Company provided for in Part II hereof.17. (1) It is recognized that before the Joint Company can assume responsibility for flying operations as contemplated in paragraph 3, it will have to be assured of financial assist-ance from the four participating governments. Such assistance shall represent the amount estimated to be sufficient to provide for the total cost of operation and a reasonable agreed profit after deduction of such mail payments as are made to the Joint Company pursuant to the provisions of Part III hereof and of any estimated revenue derived from freight and passenger traffic.(2) The contribution to be made by the Government of Canada shall be 20 per cent, of the amount arrived at by the method described in sub-paragraph (1) of this paragraph, but not more than  75,000 in any year.(3) The contributions to be made by the Government of the Irish Free State and the Government of Newfoundland will remain to be settled on mutually satisfactory terms between each of these governments and the Government of the United Kingdom as an integral part of the scheme.(4) The balance, after allowing for such amounts as may be contributed by the govern-ments of Canada, the Irish Free State and Newfoundland, will be contributed by the Government of the United Kingdom.(5) The arrangements made or contemplated by the foregoing provisions of this paragraph will be subject to review after 15 years ; but provision will be made, in the contract between the four governments concerned and the Joint Company, for triennial reviews of the subsidy.
18. Each government will arrange for the provision, within its own territory, of the air ports and the radio and meteorological services and the other aids to air navigation, which may be necessary for the transatlantic air service during the experimental stage and thereafter. It is understood, however, that the Government of Canada will provide for the radio and meteoro-logical services within Newfoundland, upon a basis to be agreed between the Governments of Canada and Newfoundland.19. Each government will grant to the Joint Company such landing and transit rights, within its own territory, as may be necessary for the transatlantic air service contemplated herein. Until otherwise determined by the consent of the four governments, such rights of the Joint Company will be exclusive in respect of transatlantic service.20. Provision will be made whereby the Joint Company will be exempt from all fuel and oil taxes and duties on technical material within the territory of each government in so far as such fuel, oil and material are required for the operation of the transatlantic service. Similar provision will be made for the experimental stage.Part V.Inter-Governmental Committee.21. An Inter-Governmental Committee on Transatlantic Air Services will be established, to which&apos; shall be referred for approvaf decisions or proposals (to be subsequently defined) relating to these services which may affect national policy or the relations of the governments concerned inter se or with other governments. The Committee will consist of four members appointed respectively by the Governments of the United Kingdom, Canada, the Irish Free State and Newfoundland, and its decisions shail be reached by unanimous vote. The Chair-manship of the Committee shall be held by the members in rotation, the period of office being one year.C19961)
LETTER FROM COLONEL SIR DONALD BANKS TO COLONEL V. I. SMART24th November, 1935.pear Colonel Smart,In accordance with your request, I send herewith the very rough headings of the basic points of the plan for the Anglo-Irish-Canadian service which we have had under discussion.I hope that it will be quite clear that these points were only intended to act as a general guide and in no way to limit discussion from any point of view that proved desirable. At the same time, you will notice that the document covers most of the ground we have traversed, and that in a great many cases we appear to have reached substantial agreement along the lines indicated.I should make it clear also that the document has not been agreed between ourselves and the representatives of the Irish Free State, though in most particulars the discussions we have had indicate that there is no marked divergence of view, except in the case of the question of shareholding in any Joint Operating Company arrangement.As I have already told you, my authorities attach the greatest importance to the principle of control of operation (i.e., management) being secured to the only body capable of exercising it effectively, namely, Imperial Airways, and I should find it quite impossible to agree on any arrangement that failed to secure a majority shareholding for Imperial Airways in any set-up that might be contemplated.Yours sincerely,(Signed)   DONALD BANKS.Colonel V. I. Smart,Chairman, Main Committee onTransatlantic Air Mail Services, Ottawa.OTTAWA.MAIN POINTS FOR DISCUSSION.1. Agreement in principle to establish a joint air mail service between Canada, I.F.S., Newfoundland and United Kingdom.2. Eventual objective to be to carry all first-class mail between these countries by air when technical and economic conditions permit.(Mail between I.F.S, and U.K., however, to be considered separately from this agreement.)3. In the meantime the immedate objective to be to establish a regular air mail service on a surcharge basis on a minimum frequency of two services a week in each direction.4. Initial surcharge rate not to exceed 2s. per \ ounce or approximate equivalent (except during experimental period). Respective administrations to agree on common policy to reduce surcharge rates in approximate correspondence with reductions of mail carriage rates.5. Survey flights to be undertaken by Imperial Airways in 1936, followed as soon after as possible by an experimental service.   This period to be subject to agreement in Appendix A.6. Regular flying stage involving transfer of operational work to Joint Company to commence when minimum of three months&apos; continuous flying on a schedule of two services a week basis is practicable.7. All practicable preference to be given to direct route, but this should not prevent use of alternative routes for purposes of development.8. Regular operation to be undertaken by Joint Operating Company on basis detailed in Appendix B.
851069. Finance. During experimental period the operations might be financed wholly by U.K. Government, no subsidy being required from partner governments. When regular flying stage is reached fixed payments to the joint operating company at the rate of  x per annum to be made by Canada. Fixed payments on a lower basis (to be considered later) to be made by I.F;S. Payments to be reviewed at 15 years or when albup flying commences, whichever is earlier.   U.R. Government to undertake residual financing of the operations.During any calendar year when less than 6 months&apos; continuous flying is undertaken, contributions from other partner governments to be abated by 50 per cent.10. Meteorological and wireless facilities to be provided as arranged by the respective administrations concerned and landing rights to be granted to joint Operating Company, which would be exclusive for transatlantic service except by mutual consent of partner governments.11. Operating company (including P.A.A. if U.S.A. participate) to be exempt from fuel and oil taxes and duties on technical material in respect of actual operation of service.APPENDIX A.1. Steps to be taken immediately after conclusion of agreement for formation of Joint Operating Company which shall be registered in each participating country.2. Programme of development of transatlantic air services visualises two stages :(i) an initial period during which experimental survey flights will be made and other investi-gations carried out, followed by services which may be seasonal and irregular ;(ii) the establishment of regular services.3. Investigations and experimental flights provided for under 2 (i) to be carried out by Imperial Airways in accordance with the undertakings given in Annex 1.4. On completion of the initial period provided for under 2 (i), services provided for under 2 (ii) to be established as soon as possible. It is hoped that this stage will be completed and regular services established within a period of after the completion of the investigationsprovided for under 2 (i).5. As soon as regular services on a bi-weekly schedule with a minimum of 3 months&apos; continuous flying can be established, the Joint Operating Company would take over all responsibility for operation under contract with the partner governments.ANNEX 1.1. Subject to satisfactory arrangements being entered into with the United Kingdom Government Imperial Airways will undertake to carry out experimental transatlantic flights on the direct route, and to pursue technical investigations in such directions as the company may consider desirable, with a view to facilitating the establishment of regular transatlantic services at the earliest possible date.2. Subject also to satisfactory arrangements with the United Kingdom Government the company to undertake to carry out all necessary investigation, including experimental flights, within the shortest period practicable. While it is not possible, in the present state of technical knowledge, to give a binding undertaking as to the duration of the period required for such investigations, it is hoped that they will be completed by . The company will undertake to place fully at the disposal of the Joint Operating Company the results of the investigations referred to above.APPENDIX B.JOINT OPERATING COMPANY-U.K. and I.F.S.1. Participation through National Aviation Companies, who would hold shares in an agreed proportion in the Joint Operating Company.2. Full management control [i.e. commercial and operating) to be assured to Imperial Airways in shareholding, and through the medium of the Articles of Association and by a Management Agreement.3. Board to consist of 6 Directors, 3 from Irish National Company, 3 from Imperial Airways, including in the latter the Chairmanship and the Managing Director.   Casting vote to Chairman.4. Original Directors all to be agreed. One of each class to retire annually and stand for re-election by shareholders. Vacancies to be filled by nomination from the National Company concerned after acceptance by the Board.5. No shares to be sold by any of the partners without the consent of the Board.6. An annual management fee of a sum to be agreed to be paid to Imperial Airways by the Joint Operating Company.In the event of Canadian participation, the above conditions to apply with 3 Directors added from Canadian National Company.(C 19961)
ANNOUNCEMENT MADE TO THE PRESS AT THE CONCLUSION OF the ottawa DISCUSSIONS.&quot; The conference between the representatives of Canada, the United Kingdom, the Irish Free State, and Newfoundland, which has been meeting in Ottawa to consider the establishment of a transatlantic air service, terminated to-day after eleven days of close consideration of the many problems involved. As a result of the conference, arrangements were unanimously agreed upon which, subject to the final approval of all the governments concerned, should enable survey flights to be undertaken next year and an experimental transatlantic air mail service to be established shortly afterwards and to be followed eventually by a mail and passenger service on a minimum schedule of two flights a week in each direction.The representatives of Canada, the United Kingdom and the Irish Free State are pro-ceeding to Washington to discuss various aspects of these questions with the United States authorities concerned, with a view to securing the fullest measure of understanding and co-operation with the United States of America in the development of transatlantic flying.&quot;
Aide Memoire.POSSIBLE BASIS FOR POSTAL UNDERSTANDING BETWEEN BRITISH COMMON-WEALTH AND UNITED STATES POSTAL ADMINISTRATION.(Copies handed to Mr. Lamiell of the United States Post Office and to Mr. Coolican of the Canadian Post Office.)1. East-bound mail (including Central or South American mail) for all destinations to be carried either on U.S. or on British planes but no charge to be made to the U.S.A. Post Office for the use of British planes.2. West-bound mail (including mail of European origin) for all destinations to be carried either on British or on U.S. planes but no charge to be made to the U.K. or I.F.S. Post Office for the use of U.S. planes.Note to 1 and 2. The British capacity east bound to be placed at the disposal of the U.S. Post Office would be equal to the U.S. capacity west bound to be placed at the disposal of the U.K. or I.F.S. Post Offices.3. Canadian and Newfoundland east-bound mail to be carried on U.S. or British planes but payment to be made to the U.S. Post Office in respect of such mails carried on U.S. planes at rates to be agreed on mutually by the postal administrations of Canada, Newfoundland, and the U.S.A.4. West-bound mail of European origin conveyed on the southern route and placed on board at a European airport (e.g. Lisbon) other than in the U.K. or the I.F.S. to be carried on British or U.S. planes. Payment to be made to the U.S. Post Office in respect of mail carried on U.S. planes at rates to be fixed by the U.S. Post Office : and payment to be made to the U.K. (on behalf of the partners) in respect of mails carried in British planes at rates to be fixed by the U.K. Post Office in consultation with the Post Offices of the partner countries.[Note. In order not to complicate the issue in discussing this matter with the U.S. postal authorities, no mention was made of mails originating in the West Indies, but it is understood that, in the view of Pan-American Airways, the following arrangements should apply : (i) East-bound Bermuda mails conveyed on the southern route:Payment to be made respectively to the U.K. or U.S. Post Offices in accordance with the service used.(ii) East-bound Bermuda mails conveyed on the direct route:All payments to be made to the U.S. Post Office.(iii) East-bound West Indian mails (other than Bermuda) conveyed on the direct orsouthern routes:Payment to be made respectively to the U.K. or U.S. Post Offices inaccordance with the service used. (This represents a concession by the Company to the partner Post Offices, but as it is contrary to the general lines of agreement proposed it seems likely that the U.S. Post Office would demand payment in respect of all such mails whether conveyed in U.K. or U.S. planes.) ]
DOCUMENTS DRAFTED IN WASHINGTON.Index.1. Application by Pan American Airways to British Government for Bermuda-New York service.2. Application by Imperial Airways to United States Government for Bermuda-New York service.3. Draft Conditions of permit for No. 1. 4. Draft conditions of permit for No. 2.5. Application by Pan American Airways to British Government for landing rights in United Kingdom, Newfoundland and Bermuda for Atlantic service.6. Application by Pan American Airways to Canada for landing rights in Canada for Atlantic serviced7. Application by Pan American Airways to Irish Free State for landing rights in theIrish Free State for Atlantic service.* 8. Application by Imperial Airways to United States Government for landing rights in theUnited States for Atlantic service. 9. Draft conditions of permit for No. 5. 10. Draft conditions of permit for No. 6* 11. Draft conditions of permit for No. 7.* 12. Draft Conditions of permit for No. 8.* Not drafted before the Mission left Washington.No. 1.- - Draft.APPLICATION FROM PAN AMERICAN AIRWAYS TO UNITED KINGDOM GOVERNMENT FOR UNITED STATES-BERMUDA SERVICE.11th December, 1935.Sir, :.. ,.jI have the honor to bring to your attention and respectfully request your consideration of the following matter : -It is requested that authority be granted this Company by your Government, arid by the Government of Bermuda : For the aircraft of your petitioner to fly into, through and away from Bermuda, for a period of fifteen years from the first day of May, 1936, and to land at and depart from and to pick up and discharge passengers, goods and mail from such points within the territorial waters of Bermuda as may be designated by the proper government authority, for the purpose of engaging in the operation of an air transport service between the United States and Bermuda, including the transportation of passengers, cargo, and mail on a frequency not to exceed two round trips per week, all subject to the provisions of applicable laws, orders and regulations, and to such operating conditions and restric-tions as may be imposed by the Governments of the United Kingdom and Bermuda.It is further requested that this Company be authorized for the said period of fifteen years under similar conditions, and on a frequency not to exceed two round trips per week, to conduct a similar service between Bermuda and Puerto Rico.I have the honor to be, Sir,Your obedient servant,J. T. TRIPPE, President.The Honourable,The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, of the Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, London, England.
No. 3. Draft.. CONDITIONS UNDER WHICH PAN AMERICAN AIRWAYS WILL BE GIVEN PERMISSION  BY THE  BRITISH  GOVERNMENT  TO   OPERATE  SERVICE BETWEEN UNITED STATES AND BERMUDA.(1) Pan American Airways is granted permission to fly into, through, and away from Bermuda for the purpose of conducting civil air transport service between the United States and Bermuda, for a period of fifteen years, under the following conditions : (a) that the frequency of service is not to exceed two round trips per week, (6) that the service lands at the appointed customs airport serving Hamilton, Bermuda, with authority to pick up and discharge passengers, goods, and mails,(c) that Pan American Airways conforms to all air navigation regulations laid downby the said airport of Bermuda or British authority to the extent applicable to Bermuda, and conforms to all applicable regulations and statutes in force in Bermuda,(d) that Pan American Airways conforms with the air-worthiness requirements laiddown by the United States Government for a United States international air service,APPLICATION FROM IMPERIAL AIRWAYS TO UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT FOR UNITED STATES-BERMUDA SERVICE.11th December, 1935.Sir,I have the honour to bring to your attention and respectfully request your consideration of the following matter : Imperial Airways Ltd., a British Corporation, requests that authority be granted to this company by your government, in the matter of civil air navigation as follows : For the aircraft of this company to fly into, through, and away from the United States for a period of fifteen years from the first day of May, 1936, and to land at and depart from such points within the territory and territorial waters of the United States as may be designated by proper government authority for the purpose of engaging in the operation of civil air transport service between Bermuda and the United States, including the transportation of passengers, cargo, and mail on a frequency not to exceed two round trips per week, all subject to the provisions of applicable laws, orders, and regulations and to such operating conditions and restrictions as may be imposed by the Government of the United States, with authority to land at and depart from and pick up and discharge passengers, goods, and mail in international traffic at one of the following customs ports as the United States terminal: New York City, New York ; Baltimore, Maryland ; Cape Charles or Norfolk, Virginia ; Charleston, South Carolina.It. is further requested that this company be authorised, for the said period of fifteen years, under similar conditions and on a frequency not to exceed two round trips per week, to conduct a similar service between Bermuda and Puerto Rico and for that purpose to have landing rights at a customs port serving San Juan, including authority to enter and clear from San Juan for other British ports under similar conditions.I have the honour to be, Sir,Respectfully yours,The Honourable,The Secretary of State of The United States of America, Washington, D.C.
(e) that Imperial Airways is authorised concurrently by the United States Government, and for a similar period and frequency, to conduct a civil air transport service between Bermuda and the United States, using therein the customs port used by Pan American Airways as the United States terminal for the reciprocal service contemplated herein.(2) Pan American Airways is also granted permission for a similar period of 15 years on similar conditions to the above where applicable, to conduct a civil air transport service on a frequency of not more than two round trips per week between Bermuda and Puerto Rico for the carriage of passengers, goods and mails ; on condition that Imperial Airways is granted similar permission for the same period to conduct an air transport service of the same frequency between Bermuda and Puerto Rico, and for that purpose to have similar landing rights at the customs port serving San Juan including authority to enter and clear from San Juan for British West Indies ports under similar reciprocal conditions with respect to such ports.Should the above reciprocal rights to be accorded to Imperial Airways by the United States Government lapse, the above rights granted to Pan-American Airways by the Government of the United Kingdom and Bermuda will lapse simultaneously.No. 4. Draft.CONDITIONS UNDER WHICH IMPERIAL AIRWAYS WILL BE GIVEN PERMISSION BY THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT TO OPERATE SERVICE BETWEEN UNITED STATES AND BERMUDA.(1) Imperial Airways, Ltd., is granted permission to fly into, through and away from the United States for the purpose of conducting a civil air transport service between the United States and Bermuda for a period of 15 years, under the following conditions : (a) that the frequency of service is not to exceed two round trips per week ;(b) that in the United States, Imperial Airways lands at and uses one of the followingcustoms ports : New York City, New York ; Baltimore, Maryland ; Cape Charles or Norfolk, Virginia ; and Charleston, South Carolina,as the United States terminal, with authority to pick up and discharge passengers, goods and mails at such terminal port only ;(c) that Imperial Airways conforms to all air navigation regulations laid down by theabove United States ports of call or by United States authority, and conforms to all applicable regulations and statutes in force in the United States ;(d) that Imperial Airways conforms with the airworthiness requirements laid downby the Government of the United Kingdom for a British international air service ;(e) that a United States air line company is authorized concurrently by the Governmentof the United Kingdom and to the extent necessary by the Government of Bermuda, and for the same period and frequency and under similar conditions, to conduct a civil air transport service between Bermuda and the United States, using the designated customs port in Bermuda.(2) Imperial Airways, Ltd., is also granted permission for a similar period of 15 years on similar conditions to the above where applicable, to conduct a civil air transport service on a frequency of not more than two round trips per week between Bermuda and Puerto Rico for the carriage of passengers, goods and mails, with landing rights at the customs port serving San Juan including authority to enter and clear from San Juan for other British West Indies ports under similar reciprocal conditions and on condition that a United States air line company is granted similar permission for the same period, to conduct a civil air transport service on the same frequency and under similar conditions between Bermuda and Puerto Rico.Should the above reciprocal rights to be accorded to the United States air line company by the Government of the United Kingdom and Bermuda lapse, the above rights granted to Imperial Airways by the Government of the United States will lapse simultaneously.
1No. 8. Draft.IMPERIAL AIRWAYS TRANSATLANTIC APPLICATION.11th December, 1935.Sir,I have the honour to bring to your attention and respectfully request your consideration of the following matter : Imperial Airways, Ltd., a British Corporation, respectfully requests that authority be granted this company by your government, in the matter of civil air navigation as follows :For the aircraft of its company to fly on a frequency of not exceeding two round trips per week, into, through and away from the United States via Canada, the &quot;Irish Free State and Newfoundland, or via Bermuda, for a period of 15 years from the first day of May, 1936, and to land at and depart from a suitable customs port serving New York, for the purpose of engaging in the operation of a civil air transport service across the Atlantic Ocean between the United States and the United Kingdom. Such air transport service may include the transportation of passengers, cargo and mails in international traffic and may include stops at intervening points in other countries, all subject to the provisions of applicable laws, orders and regulations and to such operating conditions and restrictions as may be imposed by the Government of the United States.I have the honour to be, Sir,Respectfully yours,The Honourable, The Secretary of State,The United States of America, Washington, D.C(C19961)PAN AMERICAN AIRWAYS TRANSATLANTIC APPLICATION.11th December, 1935.Sir,I have the honor to bring to your attention and respectfully request your considerationof the following matter : In order that the inauguration of scheduled transatlantic air service and the necessarysurvey flights incident thereto may be expedited, it is respectfully requested that authoritybe granted this company by your government, and, to the extent necessary, by the respective governments of Newfoundland and Bermuda :For the aircraft of your petitioner to fly on a frequency of not exceeding two round trips per week, into, through and away from the United Kingdom via Bermuda or via the Irish Free State and Newfoundland (and in the case of Newfoundland via a port of call in Canadian territory designated by the Government of Canada, such as shall neither reduce the efficiency, regularity and reliability of the service nor unduly increase the cost, or via Montreal, preference being given to the latter route, operating conditions and other factors being equal), for a period of 15 years from the first day of May, 1936, and to land at and depart from such suitable points within the territory and territorial waters of Bermuda, Newfoundland and the United Kingdom, with a suitable terminal point serving London all for the purpose of engaging in the operation of a civil air transport service across the North Atlantic Ocean between the United States and the United Kingdom. Such air transport service may include the transportation of passengers, cargo and mails, and may include stops at intervening points in other countries, all subject to the provisions of applicable laws, orders and regulations and to such operating conditions and restrictions as may be imposed.I have the honour to be, Sir,Your obedient Servant,J. T. TRIPPE,President.The Honourable,The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs of the Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, London, England.
CONDITIONS UNDER WHICH PAN AMERICAN AIRWAYS WILL BE GRANTED PERMISSION BY THE UNITED KINGDOM GOVERNMENT TO OPERATETRANSATLANTIC SERVICE.Pan American Airways is granted permission to fly into, through and away from the United Kingdom, Newfoundland and Bermuda, for the purpose of conducting a civil air trans-port service for the carriage of passengers, goods and mail between the United States and. the United Kingdom via Canada, Newfoundland, and the Irish Free State, or via Bermuda and other countries, for a period of fifteen years from the first day of May, 1936, under the following conditions : (a) That the number of round trips by Pan American Airways shall not exceed two per week, unless additional services are authorized by the governments concerned.(.&amp;) That the service terminates in the United Kingdom at a customs airport serving London and used by Imperial Airways, or a company in which Imperial Airways has a controlling interest, as the terminal for their reciprocal transatlantic service.(c) That if the route followed is generally via the Irish Free State and Newfoundland, Pan American Airways agrees that (1) all services east- and west-bound shall land at a port of call in Canadian territory designated by the Government of Canada, such as shall neither reduce the efficiency, regularity and reliability of the service, nor unduly increase the cost, or at Montreal preference being given to the latter route, operating conditions and other factors being equal ; and (2) all services east- and west-bound shall land at a customs port of call in the Irish Free State, nominated by that Government, for the purpose inter alia of picking up and discharging passenger, goods and mail traffic. (These ports of call to be the same as are used by the company performing the reciprocal transatlantic service.). id) That Pan American Airways conforms to all air navigation regulations laid down by the authorities at ports in the United Kingdom and, to the extent and when applicable, in Newfoundland and Bermuda, and to all applicable regulations and statutes in force in the United Kingdom, Newfoundland, and Bermuda.(e) That Pan American Airways conforms to the airworthiness requirements specified by the United States Government for a United States international air service.(/) That Pan American Airways agrees to carry, and carries, if tendered by the Postal Administrations of the United Kingdom (and the Irish Free State when the service is operated through the Irish Free State) up to 50 per cent, (but in no event more than Imperial Airways carries) of the total of the west-bound transatlantic surcharged air mail (including closed pouch mail) as is tendered by the Postal Administrations of the United Kingdom (and the Irish Free State when the service is operated through the Irish Free State), within a limit of capacity of 800 lbs. per flight, or such greater weight as may be mutually agreed ; and further provided that, when operating the service via the Irish Free State and Newfoundland, Pan-American Airways may not accept west-bound transatlantic mails other than those tendered by the United Kingdom and the Irish Free State Governments.The foregoing agreements of Pan American in paragraph (/) are subject: (1) To Imperial Airways agreeing to carry reciprocally, and carrying, if tendered by the United States Postal Administration, up to 50 per cent, (but in no event more than Pan American Airways carries) -of the total east-bound transatlantic surcharged air mail of the United States, including closed pouch mail, other than closed pouch mails of iCanada, Newfoundland and Bermuda, and British Colonies in the Caribbean area including the Bahamas, British Honduras, Jamaica, Trinidad, the Wind-ward and Leeward Islands, Barbados and British Guiana (hereinafter termed British closed pouch mails), within a limit of capacity of 800 lbs. per flight, or such greater weight as may be mutually agreed.(The above reciprocal services shall be performed by Imperial Airways and Pan American Airways under bi-lateral arrangements made between Imperial Airways and Pan American Airways.)
No. 12. Draft.CONDITIONS UNDER WHICH IMPERIAL AIRWAYS WILL BE GRANTED PERMISSION BY THE GOVERNMENT OF THE UNITED STATES TO OPERATETRANSATLANTIC SERVICE.Imperial Airways Ltd., or a company in which Imperial Airways Ltd. holds a controlling interest (either of which companies is hereafter referred to as Imperial Airways), is granted permission to fly into, through and away from the United States via Canada, the Irish Free State, and Newfoundland, or via Bermuda, for the purpose of conducting a civil air transport service between the United States and the United Kingdom for the carriage of passengers, goods and mail, for a period of 15 years from the first day of May, 1936, under the following conditions : (a) That the number of round trips by Imperial Airways shall not exceed two per week unless additional services are authorised by the United States Government.(5) That the service terminates in the United States at a customs port serving New York and used by the United States air line company as the terminal for its reciprocal transatlantic service.-   11(2) To the Governments of Canada, Newfoundland, and Bermuda agreeing to tender and tendering to Pan American Airways approximately 50 per cent, of all east-bound Canadian, Newfoundland and-Bermuda transatlantic surcharged air mails, at carriage rates to be mutually agreed upon.(3) To the governments concerned agreeing to tender and tendering to Pan American Airways at the United States terminus of the transatlantic route approximately 50 per cent, of the east-bound transatlantic British closed pouch mails referred to in paragraph (/) 1 above, at carriage rates to be mutually agreed upon.(g) That Pan American Airways may carry passengers, goods and mail between any ofthe territories traversed, except local traffic between the United Kingdom and the Irish Free State ; and that Pan American Airways may land, for the purpose inter alia of picking up and discharging passengers, goods and mails, at designated ports of call in Newfoundfand or Bermuda, as the case may be, being the same ports of call used by Imperial Airways Ltd., or a company in which Imperial Airways Ltd. has a controlling interest, for its reciprocal transatlantic service.(h) That Imperial Airways, or a company in which Imperial Airways has a controlling interest, is authorised concurrently by the United States Government for a similar period of fifteen years to conduct a similar reciprocal civil air transport service of the same frequency of two round trips per week for the carriage of passengers, goods and mails between any of the territories traversed on the route between the United Kingdom and the United States, using as the western terminal of the trans-atlantic route a customs port serving New York City and any other ports of call in the United States used by Pan-American Airways for their reciprocal trans-atlantic service.(i) That if the above reciprocal rights to be accorded to Imperial Airways, or a company in which Imperial Airways has a controlling interest, by the United States Govern-ment lapse, the above rights granted to Pan American Airways by the Governments of the United Kingdom, Newfoundland, and Bermuda will lapse simultaneously.(j) Notwithstanding that this permit is valid for a period of fifteen years, the rights and privileges afforded herein to Pan American Airways shall not be available unless and until Imperial Airways, or a company in which Imperial Airways holds a controlling interest, shall operate its reciprocal scheduled transatlantic service.
(c) That Imperial Airways conforms to all air navigation regulations laid down by the above United States port of call or by United States authority, and conforms to all applicable regulations and statutes in force in the United States.id) That Imperial Airways conforms with the airworthiness requirements laid down by the Government of the United Kingdom for a British international air service.(e) That a United States air line company is authorised concurrently by the Governments of the United Kingdom, Canada, the Irish Free State, and to the extent necessary by Newfoundland and Bermuda, for a period of 15 years, to conduct a similar reciprocal civil air transport service of a frequency not exceeding two round trips per week, under similar conditions, between the United States, Canada, Newfound-land, the Irish Free State and the United Kingdom, or via Bermuda and other countries, including the right to carry passengers, goods and mail between any of the above territories except local traffic between the United Kingdom and the Irish Free State.(/) That if the above reciprocal rights to be accorded to the United States air line company lapse, the rights granted to Imperial Airways by the Government of the United States will lapse simultaneously.(g) Notwithstanding that this permit is valid for a period of 15 years from the first day of May, 1936, the rights and privileges afforded herein to Imperial Airways shall not be available unless and until the United States air line company shall operate its reciprocal scheduled transatlantic service.
LETTERS FROM THE UNITED STATES SECRETARY OF COMMERCE TO THEUNITED STATES SECRETARY OF STATE.12th December, 1935.The Honourable, The Secretary of State, Washington, D.C.My dear Mr. Secretary :The Secretary of Commerce presents his compliments to the Secretary of State and acknow-ledges receipt of copies of letters, dated 11th December, 1935, addressed to the Secretary of State by the Imperial Airways Limited, a British corporation, in which the said corporation requests authority from the United States Government to navigate foreign civil aircraft into, over, and away from, certain Atlantic coast ports of the United States and Puerto Rico.By provision of paragraph 3 of Executive Agreement, Series No. 76, entitled, &quot;Air Navigation Arrangement between the United States of America and Great Britain,&quot; effective 5th May, 1935 no regular air route of service may be established or operated to, within, or over, any territory of one of the signatory powers without prior consent of the other.It is understood that the applications of the Imperial Airways Limited contemplate the establishment of airways in foreign air commerce between London, England, and New York City, New York or Baltimore, Maryland, Cape Charles, or Norfolk, Virginia, or Charleston, South Carolina, via Canada, Newfoundland, and the Irish Free State ; or via Bermuda and other countries. It is also understood that the applications of the Imperial Airways Limited contemplate the establishment of an airway from Bermuda to San Juan, Puerto Rico, which shall be extended from San Juan to other British ports.In view of the very great importance of developing transatlantic air commerce, the Secretary of Commerce will be most willing to join with the British Government and the other governments whose territories are to be traversed, in the designation of the above-described civil airways.The airways from New York, or from one of the other specified Atlantic coast ports of the United States, to London are to be considered through routes , one via Canada, Newfoundland, and the Irish Free State ; the other via Bermuda and other foreign countries. The airways from Bermuda to San Juan, Puerto Rico, will be considered a separate and distinct route to be extended to include other British ports at the request of the British Government, subject to the approval of the United States.Sincerely yours,Secretary of Commerce.12th December, 1935.The Honourable, The Secretary of State, Washington, D.C.My dear Mr. Secretary :The Secretary of Commerce presents his compliments to the Secretary of State and acknow-ledges receipt of copies of letters, dated 11th December, 1935, addressed to the Secretary of State by the Imperial Airways Limited, a British Corporation. The Imperial Airways Limited makes three requests for authority to navigate its aircraft into, over, and away from, certain territory of the United States in foreign air commerce, landing at one of the following ports on the Atlantic seacoast of the United States : New York City, New York; Baltimore, Maryland; Norfolk or Cape Charles, Virginia ; Charleston, South Carolina; and San Juan, Puerto Rico. It appears that the company desires to engage in the international transportation of passengers, goods, and mail between England and one of the ports of the United States designated, either via Canada, Newfoundland, and the Irish Free State, or via Bermuda and other countries, and also from Bermuda to Puerto Rico and thence to other British ports. It requests that the permission be granted for a period of 15 years from 1st May, 1936 on a frequency not to exceed two round trips per week. The Company agrees that it will abide by ail laws, orders, and regulations of the United States applicable to aircraft in air commerce.The Department of Commerce has already indicated in letter of even date, addressed to you, its willingness to join with England and the other countries involved in the designation of the airways necessary to this project.
The Department of Commerce is eager to advance the development of transatlantic air commerce and as soon as such airways have been jointly designated by the United States and the other countries concerned, this Department will be pleased to approve the application -of the Imperial Airways Limited, or that of any other British company acceptable to Great Britain, to land at such ports of the Atlantic coast of the United States not to exceed a frequency of two round trips per week for a period of 15 years commencing 1st May, 1936, while engaging in foreign air commerce between London and the United States, whether via Canada, New-foundland, and the Irish Free State, or via Bermuda and other countries. The Department of Commerce will also approve the application of said company, or any other company accept-able to the British Government, to land at Puerto Rico from Bermuda on a frequency not to exceed two round trips per week for a period of 15 years commencing 1st May, 1936.Said approvals will be subject to adherence by the Imperials Airways Limited, or other company acceptable to the British Government, to the applicable laws, orders, and regulations of the United States now in force or those hereafter to be made and promulgated.These approvals would also be subject to Great Britain&apos;s granting full reciprocal rights in all particulars, including the period and frequency designated, to an air line company of the United States acceptable to the proper authority of the United States.Sincerely yours,Secretary of Commerce.
DEPARTMENT OF STATE.12th December, 1935.For the Press.STATEMENT BY ASSISTANT SECRETARY OF STATE R. WALTON MOORE, CHAIRMAN OF THE INTERDEPARTMENTAL COMMITTEE OF CIVIL INTERNATIONAL AVIATION, AND AS SUCH CHAIRMAN OF THE AVIATION CONFERENCE.&quot; As a result of the conferences which have been in progress since Thursday, 5th December, between representatives of the United Kingdom, the Irish Free State, Canada and the United States, understandings have been reached which it is confidently hoped will bring about the early establishment of transatlantic air transport services connecting these several countries. These understandings are based upon the principle of full reciprocity between the countries interested. They do not operate to exclude similar arrangements between the United States and other countries.The Department of Commerce has given its approval to the establishment of trans-atlantic airways by way of Canada, Newfoundland, and the Irish Free State to England, and by way of Bermuda to England, and from Bermuda to Puerto Rico, the latter route to be extended by mutual consent. The Atlantic seaboard ports in contemplation as termini, are New York City; Baltimore, Maryland ; Cape Charles or Norfolk, Virginia; and Charleston, South Carolina, any one of which may be designated as ports of entry, but no final determination with reference to places has yet been made.It is recognized that the northern route is much shorter than the southern route and therefore will have the advantage of more economical operation, but this fact does not preclude the possibility of considerable use being made of the southern route. It is expected that experimental flights will be begun early in the srrmmer of 1936, and it is hoped that scheduled services will begin by the summer of 1937. When the full regular service is inaugurated, it is provided that there will be four round trips per week.The matter of the carriage of mails is necessarily postponed for future consideration.All of the conferences were characterized by a spirit of whole-hearted co-operation and the conclusions arrived at received unanimous approval of the conferees.&quot;
Confidential.NOTE OF A DISCUSSION AT THE  OFFICES OF PAN AMERICAN AIRWAYS,, CHRYSLER BUILDING, NEW YORK, ON FRIDAY, 13th DECEMBER, 1935.Present :Lieut.-Col. F. C. Shelmerdine, Director-General, of Civil Aviation. Mr. G. E. Woods Humphery, Imperial Airways Ltd. Mr. J, T. Trippe &quot;i .1. French participation in transatlantic services via the southern roicte.During the course of the discussions in Washington, it had been stated that a French mission would arrive there on or about 11th January, to discuss matters relating to a trans-atlantic service.Mr. Trippewished to ascertain the views of Colonel Shelmerdine and Mr. Woods Humphery as to the line to be taken by Pan American Airways if they were consulted by the U.S.A. Government. He thought that the U.S.A. Government would probably wish to offer the French exactly the same facilities as those offered to the United Kingdom.Colonel Shelmerdine expressed the view that a good case could be made out for limiting the facilities to be afforded to the French to one service only in each direction per week on the following grounds : -(a) that the facilities offered to the United Kingdom for two services per week werein return for facilities to be afforded by four separate countries, viz.,.the United Kingdom, Canada, the Irish Free State, and Newfoundland.(b) that two separate and distinct routes were involved, i.e., the direct route and thesouthern route.Mr. Trippe agreed that these points might be represented but adhered to his view that the U.S.A. Government would probably wish to accord similar facilities. From his point of view he did not wish to antagonise the French as he used one of.their ports, viz., Cayenne in French Guiana on his South American route, and he did not wish to lose this facility, which would involve flying a long stage.Colonel Shelmerdine also mentioned that we should require refuelling facilities at Bordeaux or some other French port when operating the southern route and that it was also important from this point of view not to antagonise the French.It appeared therefore that it would be undesirable for Pan American Airways to make any strong representations on the subject. It was, however, understood that there would be no question of Pan American Airways associating themselves with the French project.2. French participation in the organisation of facilities in the Azores.This question arose mainly as the result of enquiries made on the subject in telegrams Nos. 175 of the 2nd December, (to.the United Kingdom High Commissioner in Ottawa) and 381 of the 4th December (to the British Ambassador in Washington) containing messages for the United Kingdom Mission.It was decided that no action could be taken until permits had been granted by the Portuguese Government to Imperial Airways and to Pan American Airways. The first step then was to have a comprehensive survey carried out by a firm of consulting engineers experienced in harbour works, with a view to deciding exactly what action should be taken. Pan-Americarf Airways would be associated in this survey as they had under consideration a plan for securing an area of smooth water for landing and taking off, by using compressed air pumped through tubes. Having reached conclusions as to the work to be carried out, estimates of cost would be prepared, and it was considered advisable that at this stage the French should be asked whether they would wish to co-operate and to bear a proportion of the cost.It was thought most undesirable to bring the French in at an earlier stage ; to do so would inevitably result in delay and the French would probably make strong representation^ that they should place the contract and supervise the work.
3. Use of Hong Kong by Pan American Airways.This question had been the subject of telegraphic correspondence between the Secretary of State for Air and the United Kingdom Mission, resulting finally in instructions from the former that facilities at Hong Kong should not be offered to Pan American Airways without complete reciprocity.Mr. Trippe pointed out that he had two objectives in view : (1) to effect an interchange of traffic with Imperial Airways&apos; service to Hong Kong ; (2) to effect an interchange of traffic between Pan-American Airways and China National Airways, in which Company Pan American Airways were largely interested. Facilities in Hong Kong were therefore of little use to Pan American Airways unless similar facilities could be given to China National Airways.Mr. Trippe realised that he could not expect facilities except on a basis of reciprocity. He did not therefore expect Great Britain to allow China National Airways into Hong Kong as he was aware that Imperial Airways had been unable to obtain reciprocal facilities in China. Furthermore, he realised that he could not expect facilities in Hong Kong for Pan American Airways unless reciprocal facilities could be given to Imperial Airways at Manilla. This was impossible without allowing the Japanese similar facilities, which the U.S.A. Government wa.c not prepared to do.Mr. Trippe stated that he had been able to obtain facilities at Macao from the Portuguese Government without payment. This island afforded satisfactory facilities for the operation of flying boats but there was no possibility of constructing a land aerodrome there. He hoped to be able to obtain landing rights in Macao for China National Airways when this Company could be equipped with.amphibian aircraft. He suggested that connection with Imperial Airways might also be made at Macao.Colonel Shelmerdine said that he would consider this suggestion. He pointed out, however, that the inability of the U.S.A. Government to afford reciprocal facilities in the Pacific would lead to a difficult situation. The United Kingdom Government was not prepared to afford facilities to a U.S.A. Company except on a basis of full reciprocity. He mentioned that Pan-American Airways had been able to obtain facilities in New Zealand largely owing to the good offices of His Majesty&apos;s Government but that these facilities were subject to withdrawal if reciprocity were not afforded. He enquired whether the same objections existed in the case of facilities which might be required by Imperial Airways in Honolulu and in other U.S.A. islands in the Pacific.Mr. Trippe replied that so far as he was aware the same difficulties did exist.Colonel Shelmerdine stated that an application for reciprocal facilities would no doubt be made on behalf of Imperial Airways or some other British company and suggested that Mr. Trippe would be well advised not to incur the heavy expenditure necessary in organising a route to New Zealand if these reciprocal facilities could not be granted.Mr. Trippe said that he fully appreciated the position. He was afraid, however, that the Defence Departments of the U.S.A. would not agree to facilities being afforded to Imperial Airways if this meant letting in the Japanese. He mentioned that on his first Trans-Pacific flight, the Japanese had sought and obtained permission to send a machine with newspaper correspondents to Manilla. When this machine arrived, it disgorged large quantities of mail and its flight had been advertised in Japan as the first air mail service between Japan and the U.S.A.Incidentally, he also mentioned the fact that the French had offered facilities for China National Airways in Hanoi without any demand for reciprocity. He had refused this offer, thus, he said, incurring the displeasure of the Chinese participants in this Company, who were anxious to establish this connection with the French service.

</content>
</cab>
