<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/259/0 images: 239-244</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
T^^QpJJMg-.13 &apos;I^E..pa0PER&apos;I&apos;Y OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJBSTOfS GOVERNMENT.Copy No.36).C A B  .J. N. E T THE PROPOSED ENQUIRY INTO YTORONG-OLASS EXPErroiTUEE, AND REVISION OP &apos;2HE BASIS OF THE OFFICIAL COST OF living index NtMBER.Memorandum &quot;by the Minister of Labour.I.    The Possible Repercussions on the Wages Position.1.     As the wages of workpeople in a number of industries are regularly adjusted, under the provisions of collective agreements between the employers1 organisations and the trade unions concerned, by the movements of the present cost-of-living index number, proposals for revision of the basis of that index would no doubt be closely scrutinised from the point of view of their effect on those agreements.2,     At the j)resent time such agreements are in existence in industriesemploying over 1,100,000 workpeople,  though in certain of these industries,employing over 200,000 workers, the operation of the agreements is at presentsuspended,   for various reasons.    The principal industries in which such agreements are actually operating are the following:Building (except certain districts).Textile Bleaching, Dyeing, Printing, Finishing, etc.Ho si c ry Manufacturc*Y/ool Textile Industry in Scotland and in Leicester. Silk Manufacture at Leek. Electrical Gable Manufacture. Boot and Shoe Manufacture. Felt Hat Manufacture.Furniture Manufacture (certain districts).Bobbin Manufacture.Coopering.Brush and Broom Manuf acture.Hair, Bass,, and Fibre Trade.Railway Service (certain classes a).Local Authority Services (certain districts).There are also a considerable number of smaller industries, or sections of industries, covered by such agreements.3.     Some years ago, during the period of rapid changes in cost of living,similar agreements were in operation in a much wider range of industries and services, including the Civil Service, but the tendency in recent years hasx   In the railway service, the cost of living sliding scale at present affects only about 20,000 workers, mainly in the lower paid grades;    but a considerable rise in the cost of living index would increase the number affected.
been to abandon the principle of automatic adjustment of wage rates in accordance -with changes in cost of living.    In the Civil Service the regulation of salaries on this basis was discontinued as from 1934. 4,     It is only in very rare cases that the wage arrangements tinder these cost of living sliding scale agreements are related to pre-war wages or pre-war cost of living.     In almost all cases basic rates of wages have been fixed, at some date within recent years, and these rates are varied, from time to time, in accordance with the subsequent movements of the cost of living index.   For example, in the building industry standard hourly rates of wages were fixed in July, 1935, and the rates payable are revised, in February of each year, in accordance with a scale under which wages are altered by -g-d. an hour for each variation of 6-g- points in the cost of living figures, averaged over   a year*. The important thing therefore is the number of points by which the index-number varies as between one date and another.5.     If a revision of the cost of living index, were to involve a complete break with the existing series of figures, it would of course, destroy the basis on which the wage adjustments, provided for in these agreements, are made. It is obviously important that any such changes as might render these agreements invalid should be avoided and that arrangements should be made which will ensure the maintenance of continuity between the present index number and any new series which may be instituted on a revised basis.6,     As was pointed out, however, by the Economic Advisory Council Committee, which reported on this subject in January, 1931, there need be no difficulty in maintaining continuity between the two series of figures.     Suppose, for example, the change from the present basis to a new basis is made in October, 1937, and that in September, 1937,  the present index, based on the cost of the average budget of 1934-, stands at 14-7 (i.e., 47 per cent, above the level of 1914.    The cost of the revised budget can be ascertained both for September and for October, 1937, and the percentage increase, during the intervening period of one month can be calculated.     Suppose that this increase works out at 0.57 per cent.     This increase can be applied to the old figure of 147 (for September), in order to compute a corresponding figure for October, which will be 147 plus 0.57 per cent, of 147, showing an increase of 0.84 points, bringing the index number to 147.84, which would be announced as 148.   As the2.
Committee recognised, it may be desirable that the monthly changes in the cost of living as compared with the now basic price-date should be published;   but if prominence is given to the figure which is continuous with the existing series of index numbers, there should be no need for revising the cost of living sliding-scale agreements,7.     Attempts will no doubt be made, in some quarters* to utilise the results of an investigation into working-class family expenditure for purposes of propaganda by directing attention to the relatively small amounts available, in the lower paid sections of the working-classes, for the purchase of food and other necessaries.    It may be also that the figures will be quoted as evidence in support of claims for increases in wages.     In fact, however, the budgets will have no relevance to such a point, since all they will show is how various totals of expenditure are divided among particular items;    they will not show what expenditure is necessary to provide an adequate standard of maintenance.    It should be observed moreover that a considerable amount of unofficial information as to worlcing-class expenditure has already been provided by a number of localised enquiries which have been made, in recent years, by various individuals or organisations.    This information though not representative enough to provide a satisfactory basis for generalisations, is quite sufficient for purposes of propaganda, and has in fact frequently been utilised to influence public opinion.    In the absence of trustworthy official statistics such enquiries -are likely to be repeated, frequently without the precautions and safeguards which are necessary to eliminate bias and to ensure accurate re suits.8,     The Ministries of Health and Agriculture have a special interest in the collection of information as to working-class expenditure.    The Advisory Committee on Diet and Nutrition, appointed in July last by the Minister of Health and the Secretary of State for Scotland to enquire into the facts in relation to the diet of the people, and to report as to any changes which appear desirable, have found that the available data are insufficient for their purposes and have forwarded to the Minister of Health a resolution urging that early steps should bo taken to collect family budgets and to undertake dietary surveys.    In forwarding this resolution to the Ministry of Labour, the Minister of Health has stated that he is in agreement with the Committee as to the importance of collecting such information.    The
proposed enquiry would also be of great value in providing data as to theconsumption of particular foods.    The Agricultural Marketing Boards are anxiousto obtain further information on this subject, and have hitherto been compelled to rely on the results of partial and unofficial enquiries which donot provide adequate data for their purposes.    Hie League of Nations are alsoinvestigating the subject   of nutrition in relation to public health and theconsumption of agricultural products, and it is clearly desirable that such &apos;investigations,  so far as they relate to Great Britain,  should be based onrepresentative arid we 11-authenticated information, obtained by means of officialenquiries, rather than on the incomplete and possibly misleading data atpresent available from other sources.II,   The Report of the Committee appointed by the Economic AdvisoryCouncil.9.     The Committee appointed by the Economic Advisory Council, which recommended in January, 1931, that an enquiry into working-class expenditure should be made, and that the results should be used to provide a revised basis for the cost of living index number, made a number of suggestions as to the principles by which the enquiry should be governed and the methods by which it should be made.10.    It is proposed that the principles and methods outlined by the Committee should be generally adopted, subject to reconsideration of certain points. For example, the Committee inclined to the view that budgets should be collected (front 10,000 families) for four successive weeks in either April or October, and (from a smaller number of families) for three other weeks at quarterly intervals.    It is doubtful, however, -whether 10,000 families could bo found who would be willing to undertake the labour involved in an enquiry for four successive weeks, followed, in some cases, by three others at quarterly intervals, and the question whether the suggested period of four weeks could not be reduced without materially impairing the value of the results seems to require further consideration.11.   The Committee also recommended that as the purpose of the enquiry was to provide a new basis for the Ministry of Labour cost of living index number, families in which the principal wage-earner is unemployed should be excluded. If this were the sole object of the enquiry now proposed, it would be unnecessary to obtain budgets from the families of unemployed persons, and such budgets, if collected, will no doubt have to be excluded in constructing
a new basis for the cost of living index.   But information is now urgently required for the purpose of investigating the problems, with which the Ministries of Health and Agriculture are concerned, of nutrition and diet, and actual and potential food consumption, in different sections of the community, and for these purposes it will be essential that the families of unemployed persons shall be included.    The question of obtaining information for these purposes was not within the purview of the Committee which reported in 1931. For the same reason it is desirable that the enquiry should cover agricultural as well as urban workers.Ill,    The proposed Advisory Cog.rnJ.ttee, 12o   With regard to the question whether the proposed. Advisory Committee is desirable or necessary, it should be observed that the Trades Union Congress General Council, to whom the Report of the Economic Advisory Council Committee was referred before it was signed, stated that as regards the general lines of the Report they were in substantial agreement with the procedure suggested, but that they were of the opinion that there should be a &quot;Central Committee to advise the Ministry of Labour on the inquiry as a whole, and on this Central Committee the Trades Union Congress General Council should be adequately represented&quot;.     It is essential that the material to be collected for J&amp;OT use as the basis of a revised cost of living index should be generally accepted as statistically sound, and there is little prospect of its acceptance by the Trade Unions unless -they are given the opportunity,  through representa-tion on such a Committee, to satisfy themselves that all the details of the enquiry are so planned as to ensure that the information obtained is free from bias.The proposed Committee is very similar to the Advisory Committee which has been operating very successfully for many years in connection with the Census of Production,13..   it is not intended that the Committee should duplicate the work of the Committee which reported in 1931, or indeed should involve itself in general questions of policy.     The function of the Committee would be limited to considering detailed proposals, for the conduct of the enquiry, which would be placed before them by the Ministry of Labour.    They would be asked to give their advice and opinion on specific questions relating to such points as
x   Professor Bowley and Professor Jones are statisticians and economists of high standing, and they are members of the &apos; Board of Trade Advisory Committee for the Census of Production.methods and procedure, the instructions to be given to the officers collecting the budgets, and the drafting of the enquiry schedules.    They would, be asked to regard the general plan of the enquiry as governed by the recoramendations of the Committee which reported in 1931, except as regards the few points (such as those referred to in the preceding section of this Note) which appear to require further consideration.    They would in fact be precluded from extending the enquiry to obtain information other than that which Is required by the Ministry of Labour for the purposes of a new basis for the cost of living index, and by the Ministries of Health and Agriculture for the investigation of their own problems,14-.    It is proposed that the Committee should include a representative of each of the C-overnment Departments directly concerned, of the Trades Union Congress General Council, of the National Confederation of Employers&apos; Orgarisations, of the Co-operative movement (the assistance of which is necessary in matters of detail);    together with Professor A. L. Bowley and Professor J. H. Jones h, and a representative of one of the leading women&apos;s organisations.    It would probably be necessary to add a representative of the retail traders&apos; organisations.(Intld.)   E. B.30th January, 1956.

</content>
</cab>
