<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/259/0 images: 268-363</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.SECRET.CP. 24(36)COPY NO.CABINET. BROADCASTING. Report of the Ullswater Committee j.955. Memorandum by the Postmaster General.In April last my predecessor (Sir Kingsley Wood) appointed a Committee under the Chairmanship of Lord Ullswater &quot;to consider the constitution,  control, and finance of the broadcasting service in this country and advise generally on the conditions under which the service, including broadcasting to the Empire, television broadcasting, and the system of wireless exchanges, should be conducted after the 31st December 1936&quot;.The Committee have now reported and their report (a copy of which is circulated herewith) has been communicated confidentially to the British Broadcasting Corporation for observations, which have been furnished in a memorandum, of which I append a copy.The outstanding feature of the Committee&apos;s report is, as the Corporation point out, the unanimous recognition that the constitution of the Corporation has worked well and the complete endorsement of the Corporations general policy and of the various activities to which that policy has given rise. Indeed there can be little doubt that the Committee is right in thinking that there should be no radical change in the existing system, and that any modifications should be directed to
to strengthening and securing it.      The Committee1s constructive recommendations are partly concerned with-matters directly affecting the relations between the Corporation and Government and partly with matters of internal administration and management, which generally speaking fall outside the scope of governmental action.The recommendations are summarised on pages 42 to 47, but reference should be made, where necessary, to the main body of the Report,  as in certain cases the full context is really required.      I think it desirable to draw special attention to the following pointsParagraphs 8 and 143 (a)  of the Report.      The Committee recommend that the Corporations Charter should be extended for 10 years,   while the Corporation asked in evidence for a longer period, namely 20 years.      The Committee, however, unanimously rejected the Corporations arguments in favour of an extension for a longer period,  on the ground ,that the present state of broadcasting is itself an example of the rapid development of modern invention, and that for this reason an opportunity of further review should be afforded at not too remote a date&quot;.It would be of considerable advantage to all concerned, including the B.B.C.,  if the new Charter could receive the approval of the House without a division.      If an extension beyond ten years were proposed,  opposition might be anticipated from all parts of the House,  as there were members of all parties on the Committee, which included Major Attlee, and they would probably be reinforced by. others who, for a variety of reasons, were dissatisfied with the B.B.C.There are, however, more weighty considerations.      The power entrustad to the B.B.C. is enormous and no one canforesee
foresee the developments,  technical, political and social, that may occur in the course of the next ten years.      Changes may be needed by the end of ten years and it is easier to make a new Charter to replace one that has expired than to break in upon a Charter that has several more years to run.On these grounds I am in favour of adopting the Committee&apos;s recommendation that the Charter should be extended for a period of rO years.2* Paragraphs 12, 13 and 145 (b).      The Committee recommend that the number of Governors should be seven.      The present Charter leaves it open to the Government,  if it so desires, to appoint additional Governors beyond the number of five named originally in the Charter, but this power has not been exercised.     It is understood that the Committeers object in recommending an increase in the number of Governors was to make it easier to avoid undue homogeneity of age or opinion and to secure, width and variety of outlook in the controlling body.     On the other hand the limitation to five has worked quite satisfactorily up to date and it is the general experience that the efficiency of a Board or other such body tends to vary inversely with its numbers.I do not think that the arguments adduced by the B.B.C. in favour of a smaller Board are sufficiently strong to justify the rejection of the Committee&apos;s recommendation..3. Paragraphs 53* 56 and 143 (f).      The Committee recommend that the extent of the control exercised by the Government over the Corporation^ activities should continue as it is at present, but that ministerial responsibility for exercising; that control should be divided between the Postmaster General, who in future would be concerned solely with technical control under the Wireless Telegraphy Acts (together with the administrationof
of the wireless licence system,  the collection of revenue, and the investigation of complaints of electrical interference), and a Cabinet Minister in the House of Commons free from heavy departmental duties and preferably a senior member of the Government.I support this recommendation for I consider that wherever Government guidance or control of the B.B.C. is needed it would be better exercised by a Cabinet Minister of high rank, who would be in constant touch with the Cabinefs policy, and in possession of its confidential information. Paragraphs 67,  69 and j.45 (g).      The principle first enunciated by Lord Crawford&apos;s Committee in 1925 and endorsed by the present Committee, that the first charge on the licence revenue collected from listeners (after deduction of sum- sufficient to reimburse the Post Office the cost of collection etc.) should be the payment to the Corporation of uan income thoroughly adequate to ensure the full and efficient maintenance and development of the service&quot; will no doubt be readily accepted.      The Treasury had indeed anticipated that it would be necessary in the forthcoming decade to allocate to the Corporation a larger share of the net licence revenue than it has hitherto received;&apos;    and the presence, on the Committee of Sir William McLintock who investigated on behalf of the Committee the Corporations financial arrangements and administration lends a special authority to their recommendations.      It is proposed by the Treasury,  therefore,  to accept in principle the Committee&apos;s recommendations although loss of revenue in the circumstances of the present time presents difficulties for the Exchequer.In
In one particular, however,  the Committee&apos;s proposalsfor the application of the principle are not altogethersatisfactory.      The initial assignment to the Corporation of75^o of the.net licence revenue is fully justified;    butthe following procedure is proposed as regards the balanceof 25$ of the net licence income which the Committee recommend should be potentially available for the needs of broadcas tings-If and when the Corporation consider that 7o-p of the net revenue has not proved sufficient for their various services they will be at liberty to raise the question with the Treasury when,  in a friendly review of the Corporation^ financial position and requirements as a whole,  the amount of any supplemental payment can be satisfactorily settled.I am in agreement with these proposals. Paragraphs 102 and  143 (n).      The proposal that the Central Council for School Broadcasting and the Scottish Sub-Council, to which the Corporation has hitherto entrusted the direction of the programmes transmitted weekly for schools,  should be given independent status with power to determine the school educational programme to be broadcast and the ancillary leaflets and pamphlets to be issued is, no doubt,  designed to give a de jure recognition to the de facto situation now obtaining.      But the fundamental responsibility for allocating broadcasting time to this service must clearly rest with the Corporation.      It is also presumably not contemplated that the broadcast service should be financed otherwise than from the Corporation^ share of the licence revenue.      It would seem therefore that the true standing of the Councils, however established, must be that of agents of the Corporation empowered to act with complete discretion within limits
172defined &quot;by the Corporation, and, as the Corporation itself agrees,  subject to the overriding responsibility of the Corporation.6. Paragraphs 117,  3.22,  126,  127 and 143 (p)  and (q.) .      The Committee attach great importance to the development of Empire broadcasting and recommend that in future it should be regarded as an important normal function of the broadcasting organisation and that this service as well as television broadcasting should be expressly authorised in the new Charter.     Moreover, the appropriate use of languages other than English is contemplated.     The additional funds required for the development of Empire broadcasting will be provided by the Corporation from its increased share of the licence revenue.      The finance of television broadcasting, on the other hand, is to be re-examined in the autumn of this year in the light of experience which will then be available, and can then be considered in consultation with the Treasury as explained above.7* Paragraphs 134,  135,  136 and 145 (r).      The Committee recommend that the ownership and operation of relay exchanges and the technical development of wire broadcasting in general should be undertaken by the Post Office and the control of relayed programmes by the Corporation.      It seems clear that when the State created a broadcasting monopoly it cannot seriously have intended that an independent vested interest should as a result come into being and proceed not only- to take advantage of the broadcasting organisations services but also, by the arbitrary selection of British andforeign
foreign programmes, in effect to become a competitor. In these circumstances, while the Committees recommendations on this subject are likely to meet with strong opposition by the present vested interests, and possibly by the wireless trade as a whole,  I consider that they should be accepted in principle.      The precise method and time of assuming responsibility for the relay service are matters&quot;of some difficulty;    and it is proposed to proceed so far as possible empirically in the light of the technical developments in the matter of wire transmission, which are being&apos; investigated by the Post Office, and of the practical considerations involved in undertaking the operation of existing Relay services. (This procedure appears to be consonant with Lord Selsdon&apos;s reservation on the subject).General.      As regards the various recommendations affecting the Corporations internal administration the course recommended by the Committee is in a number of cases already the established practice of the Corporation.      In certain instances there is an implied though probably unintentional reflection on the Corporations administration,-- but it is clear from the Corporations memorandum that they have given the most careful consideration to the Committees recommendations and I should propose that any public statement issued by the Government should be limited to an intimation that the Government is satisfied that the Corporation can be relied upon to give due consideration to the views expressed by the Committee on these detailed questions of administration.The reservations, particularly those made by the Leader of the Opposition, reflect a difference in emphasis and methodrather
rather than a dissension from the general framework; of the Committee&apos;s findings and it should he possible to deal with them by an intimation that the fact that such views are held in important quarters cannot fail to have due effect both with the Government and with the Corporation in the administration of the service.Subject to the reservation regarding the balance of the net licence revenue referred to in paragraph 4 above, which does not appear to be at variance with the recommendation of the Committee, I recommend that the report be accepted in principle.      There are great advantages in debate and in practice of accepting without modification all the main proposals of the Committee,      They have the authority of a unanimous recommendation and have presumably been worked out as a consistent and balanced whole.(Initialled)   G. C. T.General Post Office, 5 March 1936.
confidential  175OBSERVATIONSBY THEBOARD  OF  GOVERNORS OF THE B.B.G.ON THEREPORTOF THEROADCASTING COMMITTEE 1935
176The Corporation notes the unanimous endorsement by the Committee of its general policy and of the various activities to which that policy has given rise, their recognition that its constitution has worked well and has served as a model elsewhere, and their desire to strengthen and secure the position already attained.The Corporation notes the Committee&apos;s references to the organisation system and independence of management; to the &apos;&apos; notably complete form and good order &quot; of the accounts, and the propriety of the capital expenditure policy; to the satisfactory management of publications; and to the development of the Regional system and the provision of Advisory Committees. It notes the recognition of the merits of the Home and Empire news service, and the possibilities of expansion therein; of the value of School Broadcasting as con-ceived and developed; of the significance of the Empire Service; and of the absence of valid criticism of programme policy. It notes the Committee&apos;s testimony to the &apos;&apos; outstanding independence&apos;&apos; with which it has exercised its responsibility in controversial matters and the &quot;wisdom&quot; with which it has handled the problems of their presentation; to the &quot;prudence and idealism&apos;&apos; which have characterised its operations and enabled it to overcome the many difficulties encountered ; and to the &quot;intellectual and ethical integrity which the broadcasting system in this country has attained.&quot;
-    177The Corporation further notes with satisfaction that in all major points, on which it was led by experience to make recommendations, its views have been accepted.   These include :That Ministerial responsibility for policy should be transferred to a senior Cabinet Minister free from heavy Departmental responsibilities.That a substantially larger portion of the licence revenue should be made available for &quot;sound broadcasting&apos;&apos; and that receipts should be cal-culated to a current date.That the balance of licence revenue should be regarded as potentially available, especially for television.That the use of school broadcasting should be encouraged and that a large measure of inde-pendence should be secured to the Central Council and Scottish Sub-Council.That the Empire Service, should be expressly authorised and developed and the appropriate use of foreign languages encouraged.That Relay Exchanges should be owned and operated by the Post Office, and their programmes controlled by the Corporation.That the Post Office and Foreign Office should be active to prevent the broadcasting from foreign countries in English of programmes including advertisements.
178In the review of such a large field it is perhaps inevitable that certain features, to which the Corpora-tion attaches high importance, should pass without mention, such as the technical achievements of its Engineering Division, and the pioneer work in the development of broadcast religion, drama, variety and special feature programmes. Moreover, many measures are recommended for adoption which are already part of the normal practice of the Corporation, particularly the methods of recruitment of staff, the development of the regional system, the employment as broadcasters of persons critical of the B.B.C., the use of Advisory Committees and the practice of consulting the political parties in connection with political broadcasting.There are certain other points of lesser but of considerable intrinsic importance to which the Corpora-tion desires to call attention. It feels that many of these acquire undue prominence in the Summary of Recommendations, which, in the Corporation^ opinion, if read without continuous reference to the text, may prove in several places definitely misleading. This, no doubt partly due to brevity, is unfortunate, since, on publication of the Report, it is anticipated that the Summary alone will be widely reproduced. It will be the more regrettable in that among the points in question are some which lend themselves to undue and even sensational emphasis when taken from their con-text and treated in isolation for special propaganda purposes. There are also points in the Report itself which, while made as part of a declared policy of strengthening and securing the existing position, are likely to have a contrary effect.
The Corporation hopes that the following state-raent of its views may be carefully considered by the Government before coming to its decisions.Para. 8 and Summary (a).The Corporation regrets that the extension recom-mended is ten years only. It notes the reasons but feels that they are outweighed by the advantages of a longer period. On the lowest terms there is less cause for hesitation now than in 1925 when a ten-year term was recommended.13 and (b).The present Charter permits of seven Governors. The limitation to five was considered and endorsed in 1933 by the Prime Minister and Postmaster General of the day in consultation with Mr. Whitley. Since the principle of specialist Governors has been rejected by the Committee, the Corporation cannot see any need for, or advantage in, the increase. Collective wisdom does not grow with numbers, and a small Board is generally more efficient than a large one. The Corporation believes that it should be possible through a Board of five Governors to secure that variety and width of outlook to which the Committee justly attaches importance.15 and (b).The Board is of opinion that (as implied in the Report) the remuneration of Governors should be fixed by the Charter and that they should not be left as at present with the invidious duty of deter-mining. within limits what it should be.
The Chairman is of opinion that, having regard to the requirements of his post, as defined on appointment and as confirmed by experience, the salary is too high, and should be substantially reduced. Whether or no this view be adopted, the Governors are of opinion that their existing remuneration is adequate.The Board hopes that the present system of appointing a Vice-chairman will be continued rather than that they should elect one of their number to act ad hoc in the absence of the Chair-man.19.The reference to the formation of an additional Region in North-Eastern England is mistaken. The proposal, already being put into effect, was confined to the installation of additional trans-mission facilities.28 and (c).In the Summary there is no reference to the fact that &quot;Wales would have been a separate Region many years ago had it been technically possible.34, 35 and (d).It is recommended that vacancies should be adver-used, and appointments, except of minor staff, made on the recommendation of a Selection Board, which should include a representative of the Civil Service Commission and possibly an independent member. At least 50 per cent, of staff vacancies have for two years been notified by public adver-
tisement and in almost every case appointments are made by the machinery of Appointments Boards. These Boards consist of a nucleus of administrative officials, with other members such as the Head of the Department in which the vacancy exists. There are, however, occasions where experience of special conditions is necessary to supplement the Corporation^ knowledge of its own requirements, and B.B.C. Appointments Boards have sat with external assessors. For example, most of the School and Adult Education appointments have been handled in this way, and last April a complete Welsh programme staff was appointed with the help of three distinguished assessors. The Summary indicates nothing of this, nor of the external investigation into methods of recruitment undertaken on the Corporation^ initiative in 1934. The Corporation is satisfied that it already secures, but with flexibility of working, the ends which in the opinion both of Committee and Corporation are desirable. It feels (i) that there will always be a considerable per-centage of appointments which it would be useless to advertise; (ii) that the compulsory addition of a Civil Service Commission representative or of an independent member to its Appointments Boards is incompatible with its independent status, and productive of no good results. Only by a whole-time attention to the widely varying conditions and requirements of the B.B.C.&apos;s different activi-ties could anyone assess justly the qualifications required. The fact that the Committee in the body of the Report endorse the findings of the Corpora-tion&apos;s investigators referred to makes their recommendation the more unexpected if it is to be read as going beyond those findings.
18237, 38 and id).The Corporation is willing to consider sym-pathetically, if and when expressed by any sub-stantial group among its staff, a request for the formation of a staff association and will make this known to its staff. But it still doubts, for the reasons indicated in 38, the appropriateness of such a measure, as did the late Mr. Whitley, notably inclined to such a development in suitable circumstances, when he examined the question. It has no evidence of any desire for such an organisa-tion and is satisfied that considerable numbers of its staff, by reason of their diversity of functions, cannot be organised in this way. The comparison with Post Office conditions is obviously invalid. Here again the Summary is less than fair to the Corporation or to the text. In this connection the Corporation regrets that the remarkable percent-age statistics of staff with five and ten years&apos; service, supplied to the Committee, are not quoted as well as those of University graduates.39 and (d).The closing sentence suggests that the staff are unwarrantably interfered with by the Corporation. The Corporation does not concern itself with the private lives of its employees, except in so far as their personal conduct affects or may affect the performance of their duties as servants of the Corporation. The State itself is not indifferent to the private activities of those who serve it. No good private employer can afford to disregard con-duct of an employee which may affect the efficiency of himself or his colleagues, or the good repute of his concern.   Still less can such a public authority
as the B.B.C., with a service whose activities enter the great majority of the homes of the country, disregard such conduct. During the thirteen years since the establishment of the British Broadcasting Company in 1922, dismissals of staff on account of personal misconduct of all kinds have numbered only 31; and, in a majority of these cases, the cause of dismissal has been financial difficulties of a character which neither the B.B.C. nor any other reputable employer could afford to disregard. Only six were of the character which the Committee are understood to have had in mind. None of these was a case of merely &apos;&apos; private 5&apos; bearing; in all of them the Corporation was affected. Every one of these 31 cases was considered individually and sympathetically. The Corporation has experienced much deliberate misrepresentation of its exercise of this difficult responsibility and regards it as regrettable that the Committee should, by this casual reference, appear to condemn the Corpora-tion and expose it to further misrepresentation, inviting conclusions which it cannot believe the Committee would accept.40 and (d).This paragraph, particularly as worded in the Summary, cannot fail to suggest to those unfamiliar with actual B.B.C. practice that the Corporation has been reluctant to accept criticism, and has debarred from the microphone persons who have criticised it. Both implications are unfounded. Intelligent, responsible criticism has always in fact been welcomed and encouraged. The large listener correspondence, critical as well as appreciative, is carefully dealt with.   And so
far from critics who are qualified to broadcast being debarred from the microphone they have in a number of cases been brought to it, the Corpora-tion merely protecting itself against those who seek to create for themselves a &quot;nuisance value.&quot;44 and (e).The Corporation is dubious about the recommenda-tion that there should be set up a complete system of General and Specialist Advisory Committees in all Regions. It has experimented with Regional Advisory Committees. Some nowr exist and func-tion satisfactorily; others languished through lack of material for deliberation. While future experience and development may disclose oppor-tunities for extending, in the Regions and elsewdiere, the number of advisory bodies already established, to which the Corporation attaches much importance, it would deprecate any attempt to compel, for uniformity&apos;s sake, the comprehensive-sive system here envisaged.53 and (/).It is uncertain, from the wording of this para-graph, whether the Committee contemplate that the ministerial office, to which such of the Postmaster General&apos;s present responsibilities as attach to the policy and cultural aspects (as distinct from certain technical aspects) of the Corporation^ service are proposed to be trans-ferred, should be liable to change with succes-sive Governments. For reasons of administrative continuity and to keep the B.B.C. divorced from
politics the Corporation trusts that the responsi-bility will be attached by the Charter permanently to some one stated office.Another illustration of the disadvantage of sum-mary statements occurs here. While the text gives a reasonably clear indication of the existing posi-tion, the Summary recommends that &quot; technical control should remain with the Postmaster General.&quot; This obviously suggests that the whole of the Corporation^ technical service is in fact now controlled by the Post Office, which is not the case. This is likely to give rise to much misunder-standing in the &quot;Empire and in foreign countries.54, 57 and (/).There is a confusion here. It is usual to announce the Government Departmental origin of a routine notice referred to in 54. The Corporation asked that specific instructions (e.g. the introduction or the veto of an item), as recommended in 57, should be announced as such, and believes that this is what the Committee intended to recommend.74 and (g).The Committee remark that there has been some criticism as to the wisdom of certain items of the Corporation^ capital expenditure in the past. No such criticism has been addressed directly to the Corporation, and Sir William McLintock, in a Reservation, states that he observed none in Evidence. While the Corporation is always ready to give full information to Parliament on contem-plated developments, it feels that an obligation to submit annually to Parliament the major items ofr
186contemplated capital expenditure would, as Sir William McLintock states, tie its hands and involve an undesirable encroachment on its inde-pendence, which elsewhere the Committee seems anxious to preserve and to which the Corporation attaches the utmost importance.76 and (/).The Corporation presented its 1935 Accounts in the slightly amplified form suggested.92, 93, 94 and (It).The recommended consultation has been the invarh able practice from the beginning of political broadcasts. The dissatisfaction expressed in Mr. Attlee&apos;s Reservation with the opportunities afforded to members of his Party, was at least equalled by that of his opponents.100 and (m).Sunday programmes have been progressively lightened, and the process continues. The Cor-poration knows, however, that there are great numbers of listeners who desire that the character of the Sunday programmes should not be assimilated to those of weekdays.The Governors have recognized with much satis-faction the high commendation implied in the Report of the work and influence of Sir John Reith. He has known how to inspire an able and devoted staff with vision as well as enthusiasm, in a pioneering adventure fraught with difficulties, which has become highly significant in the life of the nation.
CONFIDENTIAL PROOFReport of the broadcasting COMMITTEE1935Presented by the Postmaster General to Parliament by Command of His Majesty, January, 1936LONDONPRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: Adastral House, Kingsway, London, w.c.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2; York Street, Manchester 1 ; 1 St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any BooksellerI936Price Qit. NetCmd.      ]
THE BROADCASTING COMMITTEE, 1935The Right Hon. The Viscount Ullswater, G.C.B. (Chairman) Major The Hon. J. J. Astor, M.P..1Major The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P. E. Clement Davies, Esq., K.C., M.P. The Lord Elton.Sir William McLintock, Bart, G.B.E., C.V.O. The Marchioness of Reading. The Right Hon. The Lord Selsdon, K.B.E. H. Graham White, Esq., M.P.Secretary : H. G. G. Welch, Esq.,General Post Office, London, E.C.1.Note. The expenses incurred in preparing this Report are estimated at ........, of which  ........represents the estimated cost of printing and publication.
CONTENTSParagraphs1-6      Introductory  ..7-46    Constitution	8	Extension of Charter	10-16	Governors	17-18	Internal organisation	19-29	Regions	30-40	Staff matters	41-46	Advisory Committees47-57	Control .	58-77	Finance .	78-114	Programmes		80-84	News	85-86	Controversy	87-94	Political broadcasting	95-99	Music	100	Sunday programmes	101-107	School broadcasting	108-114	Advertisements115-123   Broadcasting to the Empire124-129   Television       ...........130-136   Relay Exchanges137-142   Miscellaneous ..       . .       ..       ..137      Publications 138-140   Electrical interference 141      Receiving sets 142      Inconsiderate use of loud-speakers143-145   Summary of Recommendations and ConclusionReservations   .. Appendices, : A. List of witnessesB. Royal CharterC. Licence and AgreementD. Royal Supplemental CharterE. Supplemental AgreementF. Membership of B.B.C General Advisory CouncilG. Form of annual account (expenditure)H. Form of byelaw (loud-speakers, etc.)
THE BROADCASTING COMMITTEE1935REPORTMajor the Right Hon. G. C. Tryon, M.P., His Majesty&apos;s Postmaster GeneralINTRODUCTORY1. Terms of reference. We were appointed by your predecessor in the Office of Postmaster General, Sir Kingsley Wood &quot; To consider the constitution, control, and finance of the broadcasting service in this country and advise generally on the conditions under which the service, including broadcasting to the Empire, television broadcasting, and the system of wireless exchanges, should be conducted after 31st December, 1936 &quot;.Our appointment was announced in the House of Commons on 17th April, 1935.2. Proceedings of the Committee. We issued to the Press on 1st. May, 1935, a notification that we were prepared to receive evidence or representations in writing from any person or organisation, and a request that such statements should be sent to us not later than 31st May. We have examined 79 witnesses, representing many different points of view. A list of witnesses who have appeared before us is set out in Appendix A. In addition we have considered numerous letters and memoranda. We have held, in all, 35 meetings.3. Historical outline. Broadcasting in the United Kingdom began in November, 1922 thirteen years ago. The British Broadcasting Company was formed by the principal British manufacturers of wireless apparatus ; and the Postmaster General agreed to issue, at an annual fee of not less than ten shillings, licences for the use of wireless receiving apparatus bearing the B.B.C. mark, and to pay the Company half the proceeds. Difficulties arose from the use of apparatus not bearing the B.B.C. mark, and the first comprehensive review of the scope and potentialities of broadcasting was undertaken in 1923 by a Broadcasting Committee
appointed by the late Lord Brentford (then Postmaster General) under the chairmanship of Major-General Sir Frederick Sykes. Rejecting alternative suggestions, the Committee recommended in their Report (Cmd. 1951) that the bulk of the revenue required- for the service should be obtained from the receiving licence fee.4. Progress was rapid, and in 1925 a second Committee was appointed, under the chairmanship of the Earl of Crawford and Balcarres, to advise as to the arrangements to be made after the expiry of the Company&apos;s licence at the end of the year 1926. In accordance with the first of the principal recommendations in the Crawford Committee&apos;s Report (Cmd. 2599) &quot; that the broadcasting service should be conducted by a ptiblic corporation acting as Trustee for the national interest, and that its status and duties should correspond with those of a public service &quot; the British Broadcasting Corporation was established by Royal Charter.1 The Corporation took over the service from the British Broadcasting Company and began to operate on 1st January, 1927, under Licence2 issued by the Postmaster General.5. Only two modifications of the Corporation^ Charter and Licence/kave-been made ; by a Royal Supplemental Charter,3 the Corporation has been empowered to utilise for capital expenditure the sums set aside to meet depreciation ; and by a supplemental agreement,4 the share of wireless receiving licence revenue accruing to the Post Office (to defray the cost of the licensing system and of other work undertaken in relation to broadcasting) has been reduced from 12J per cent, to 10 per cent.6. Present position. A brief description of the existing state of affairs will be found in subsequent paragraphs under the following headings  ConstitutionInternal organisationRegionsStaff mattersAdvisory Committees   -.ControlFinanceSchool Broadcasting Advertisements Broadcasting to the Empire Television broadcasting Relay Exchanges Electrical interference  ..Paragraphs 9, 10,11617.. 19-22,24 32-34 41-43 .. 47-52,5560, 62-65, 73, 74 .. 101-106 108-110, 113 115-117, 119, 120 124-126, 129 .. 130, 131 ..   138, 1391 Appendix B. 3 Appendix D.2 Appendix C. 4 Appendix E.
CONSTITUTION7. General approval. We are impressed, as were the members of earlier Committees, by the influence of broadcasting upon the mind and spirit of the nation, by the immense issues which are consequently involved, and by the urgent necessity in the national interest that the broadcasting service should at all times be conducted in the best possible manner and to the best advantage of the people. We feel that a great debt of gratitude is owed to the wisdom which founded the British Broadcasting Corporation in its present form, and to the prudence and idealism which have characterised its operations and enabled it to overcome the many difficulties which surround a novel and rapidly expanding public service. That the work of the B.B.C. has been widely approved may confidently be inferred from the remarkable absence of general criticism in the oral and written evidence which has been submitted to us. Its constitution has been taken as a model in other countries. Our recommendations are directed towards the further strengthening and securing of the position which the broadcasting service in Great Britain has happily attained in the few years of its history.8. Extension of Charter. We recommend that the period of the Charter (which is due to expire, unless its continuance be authorised, on 31st December, 1936) should be extended for a term of ten years, subject to the modifications which we propose in succeeding paragraphs. We have considered whether the emergence of the service, as a public utility, from the experimental stage to the status of a permanent institution should be signalised by a longer extension than this ; but we feel that the present state of broadcasting is itself an example of the rapid development of modern invention, and that for this reason an opportunity of further review should be afforded at not too remote a date.9. Constitution of the B.B.C. Cardinal points of the constitution of the Corporation are specified in the Royal Charter.1 There are five Governors (concerned administratively with major questions) and a Director-General (the chief executive officer). Authority is devolved, without formality, from the Governors to the Director-General.10. Governors. -The duties of the Governors are defined in the Royal Charter, which begins by affirming the recommendation of the Crawford Committee that the broadcasting service should be conducted by a public corporation &quot; acting as Trustees for the national interest.&quot; With this as the primary conception of their status and duty, the Governors have to see that the purposes for which the Corporation has been established are carried out. They should be able to judge of the general effect of the broadcasting1 Appendix B.
service upon the. public, and they are finally responsible (within the Constitution and subject to the Ministerial responsibilities and duties recognised and imposed by the Charter) for its conduct.11. Notwithstanding recommendations put to us from various quarters that one of the Governors should be appointed as an expert or specialist in this or that activity of the broadcasting service or as the representative of a local or sectional interest, we cordially endorse the conclusion of the Crawford Committee1 &quot; It has been suggested in evidence that the Board should be composed of persons representing various interests, such as music, science, drama, education, finance, manufacturing, and so forth. We cannot accept this view, since compromise and even conflict might ensue owing to division of allegiance. On the contrary, we hold that the actual Commissioners2 should be persons of judgment and independence, free of commitments, and that they will inspire confidence by having no other interests to promote than those of the public service.&quot;12. In the appointment of governors we trust that full attention will be paid to width and variety of outlook. It is well that there should be, within the Board of Governors, knowledge of men and affairs and experience both of public service and of financial and commercial matters ; but we think it important that any undue homogeneity of age or opinion should be avoided. While new scientific developments are constantly occurring, and changes of opinion and of practice are so rapid that each successive generation is brought up in a different world of experience, the Board should be as ready to entertain new ideas as it is to be guided by mature judgment.13. We recommend that the number of Governors should be increased to seven. We submit that they should be nominated by the Crown on the recommendation of the Prime Minister, and that the term of office should continue to be five years, but a retiring Governor should not be re-nominated.14. Those members of the present Board who will not have served a full term of five years at the end of 1936 should, we think, be eligible for re-nomination for the remainder of that term.15. The Chairman of the Board will naturally, during his term of office, find his main interest in the business of the Corporation and give a very substantial part, though not necessarily the whole, of his time to it. The salary of the Chairman should, we consider, remain as at present ( 3,000), and that of other Governors be fixed at  1,000. They should have power to elect one of their number to act as Deputy Chairman when the Chairman is unable to act.1 Cmd. 2599, section 8,(i,e., the Governors.)
16. We understand and this is in accordance with our conception of their proper functions that the Governors have a joint respon-sibility, not divided for purposes of departmental supervision; and that they decide, after discussion with the Director-General, upon major matters of policy and finance, but leave the execution of that policy and the general administration of the service in all its branches to the executive officers.17. Internal organisation.-With.iu the Corporation, authority is devolved at the present time from the Director-General to a Deputy Director-General and to four Controllers, each the head of a Division. Below these high officers the organisation is partly functional, the four Divisions dealing respectively with Administration,Engineering,Programmes, andPublic Relations, and partly regional, comprising-Headquarters Departments, the Engineering Division, and Regional Establishments.18. The internal organisation of the service is a matter generally within the discretion of the Corporation. All the evidence submitted for our consideration points to the conclusion that the organisation has been established on sound lines and has worked successfully.19. Regions. Apart from London, there have in the past been five Regions, namely :  the Midlands ; the North of England ; the West of England, and Wales ; Scotland ; Northern Ireland.We do not wish to specify what should be the number of Regions for broadcasting purposes, especially as the allocation and use of wave-lengths involves technical questions ; but it is clearly undesirable that large populations which differ widely in their character and culture should be combined within a single Region. The evidence strongly suggested that two additional Regions (namely Wales, and North-Eastern England) were necessary, and we are glad to note that they are in process of formation.20. Each Region is controlled by a Regional Director, assisted on the administrative side by a Chief Executive Officer and on the creative side by a Programme Director. The Regional Directors are responsible to the Controllers of the four Divisions, and have access to tfie phector-General and the Deputy Director-General.
The powers of a Regional Director do not extend to technical matters, which are controlled by the Engineering Division. They are limited financially (a) by an average weekly programme allowance, fixed quarterly after consultation between the Region and Head-quarters, which may be exceeded in any given week provided that the excess is saved within the quarterly period: for exceptional programmes involving abnormally heav3? expense recourse may be had, by agreement, to a general reserve fund :(b) by limitations upon fees which may not be exceeded with-out approval by Headquarters.Recruitment, pay, and dismissals of salaiied staff are arranged by co-operation between the Regions and Headquarters.21. The limitations, within which the Regional Directors have sole authority within their Regions, have been gradually relaxed during the existence of the Corporation. The position of the Regional Directors in relation to Broadcasting House has just been strength-thened by the appointment of a Director of Regional Relations. We approve the gradual enlargement of their responsibilities, subject to the maintenance of a consistent policy for the service as a whole and to ultimate, control by the Corporation itself and a very small group of its highest officers whose duties are of national scope.22. We have been informed of the procedure by which the pro-grammes of the B.B.C. are built up. Programmes which are due to be performed in a Region and are likely to have a national appeal are reported weekly to the Director of Programme Planning. An outline of the National and Regional programmes for the week in question is then constructed, sent to all Regions, and used by each Regional Director and Regional Programme Director as the basis for the construction of their own Regional programme. In this work there is ample co-operation and consultation with Head-quarters and with other Regions.23. Music and talks from the studios and concert-halls of all Regions, and events from all quarters, are included in the National programme. Various parts of the country differ, naturally, in the extent and variety of the resources available. It is convenient that certain elements in the programmes for example, weather forecasts, general news, dance music, recitals of gramophone records should be largely centralised ; and it is desirable that a high standard of excellence should be maintained in every variety of programme. Broadcasts of events taking place outside the studios add freshness and topical interest but are costly. Listeners are by no means exclusively interested in their own districts. All these factors affect the proportion of Regional programme time which can with advan-tage be devoted to material of local origin.
24. At our request the programme time of a representative recent week and that of the corresponding week a year ago, in a Region which we selected as an example in which the proportion of regional matter is not above the average, were analysed and found to comprise approximately the following percentages : 1934.     1935.Items originating within the Region . .       25 33Items originating in London . .       . .       ..       52 43Items originating in other Regions   ..       ..       23 24100        100Apart from the centralised types of programme mentioned in para-graph 23, the percentages were found to be approximately : 1934.     1935.Items originating within the Region . .       30 42Items originating in London . .       ..       . .       38 25Items originating in other Regions   . .       ..      32 33100       10025. Taking into account the limiting factors already mentioned, we consider that a satisfactory proportion of the Regional pro-grammes is made up of the work of regional authors, performers and speakers and of other material of regional interest; but we conceive the future of the broadcasting service to depend upon the main-tenance of a good proportion of regional matter through the develop-ment of regional resources including &quot; outside broadcasts &quot;, and upon constant attention o$ the needs, events, and interests of indi-vidual Regions. We trust therefore that the Corporation will continue to follow that policy which has increased the material originating within the Regions.26. Wales. Evidence in regard to the broadcasting service afforded to Wales has been laid before us on behalf of the Welsh Parliamentary Party, the Council of the University of Wales, the Nationalist Party of Wales, and the B.B.C.27. Among the claims put forward was a suggestion that a separate Welsh Broadcasting Corporation should be set up with an independent charter. After examining this and other recommen-dations made to us we are satisfied that this proposal would not help to meet the ideals of Welsh listeners : it would not make any easier the solution of existing physical difficulties, and it would be contrary to the interests of Wales, We cannot regard the suggested change as desirable at the present time.
2S. That Wales (hitherto associated with the West country) should as soon as possible be constituted as a distinct broadcasting Region has already been recognised in principle by the B.B.C. There are technical difficulties as to the provision of an independent wavelength and as to ensuring satisfactory receiving conditions in some parts of the Principality; we urge that every effort should be made to solve these difficulties and to satisfy the national demands of the Welsh people with a minimum of delay. With a view to the ultimate needs of Wales as a separate Region, appointments of Welsh-speaking officers have already been made. We recommend, in Wales as in general, an increasing devolution of programme control and an increase in the broadcasting of material of regional origin, performance, and interest.29. We cannot endorse the suggestion that one of the Governors of the British Broadcasting Corporation should be specially appointed as a representative of Wales : as we have explained above, this would be inconsistent with our conception of the Board of Governors. On the other!hand, in accordance witli our recommendations in a later paragraph, we favour the establishment of a Genera] Advisory Committee for the Welsh Region-this function is already very largely performed by a Broadcasting-Committee set up by the Council of the University of Wales and the continuance or creation of Advisory Committees on special subjects, linked with the appropriate Central Committees.30. Staff matters. The staffing arrangements of a public corpora-tion require careful consideration. Beside being justly administered and leading to efficiency of service, they should afford evident grounds for public confidence in the system itself ; otherwise it will be difficult to avoid criticism and suspicion. Moreover, as the B.B.C. is one of a number of new and recently created forms of public institution standing between Government Departments on the one hand and commercial undertakings on the other, its practice may have some influence in each of these directions and be looked upon as a pattern for future institutions.31. We recognise that the staffing arrangements of the B.B.C. differ in two essential respects from those of the Civil Service. One of the purposes of com^rring upon the,B.B.C. a large degree of independence is, we assume, to obviate the direct public control through Parliament, to which the Civil Service is subject in every detail of remuneration and conditions. And in the second place the B.B.C. personnel is so much smaller in number as to bring the requirements of individual positions and the administration of staff matters in general more readily within the grasp of a single Board of Governors and a single group of administrative officers.32. Recruitment. -The methods of recruitment were examined in 1934 at the Corporation&apos;^ request by two eminent and independent
investigators (Professor Ernest Barker and Mr. D. B. Mair ; recently a Civil Service Commissioner), whose report contained the following conclusions : &quot; Generally we are of the opinion, from the evidence we have taken, that there is a fair field and no favour in the recruitment of the staff of the Corporation, and that posts are filled with a sole regard to the capacity and promise of the candidates. We think that there is a good proportion of women to men on the staff; and we are also of the opinion that the staff is recruited from a variety of sources, and in a way which collects a variety of experience for the service of the Corporation. Our recom-mendations turn on points of comparative detail.&quot;133. These conclusions appear to be borne out by the enquiries which we have made. One point put before us in evidence was a suspicion that in appointments an undue preference was given to candidates with Oxford or Cambridge degrees. That, however, is disproved by the following analysis of monthly-paid non-engineering staff :-With no degree . .       ..       . .       . .       . .       204Graduates of: Oxford ..       ..       ..       ..        76Cambridge     ..       . .       ..       ..        40Other universities    ..       . .       .,        75Total . .       ........       39534. The staff of the B.B.C. are not recruited through the Civil Service Commission nor, except in certain instances, by public advertisement. The sources of supply have been explained to us as being : (1) Independent application.(2) Recommendation by a friend.(3) Recommendation by a University Appointments Board, a technical body, or some authority with technical knowledge.(4) Public advertisement.(5) Selection from the existing staff.35. We recognise that in a rapidly growing and expanding service still to some extent in the pioneer stage there must be a period of experiment before settling down to routine. We realise also that some appointments must be temporary, and that the varied and novel character of many of the positions makes any uniform method of recruitment difficult. We have had no evidence of undue influence, but it is clear that the existing practice leaves to its We are informed that the changes recommended have been carried into effect,.
administrators the responsibility for avoiding patronage and prejudice. We think that the time has come when recruitment should be systematised, and we accordingly recommend that the positions to be filled should be advertised, and that appointments (except those of minor staff) should be made on the recommendation of a Selection Board comprising officials of the B.B.C., together with one of the Civil Service Commissioners or their representative and possibly an independent additional member.36. Remuneration. The remuneration of the lower ranges of the staff appears to be adequate, and we understand that there is little, if any, complaint on that score. The salaries of those in the higher positions do not, we are informed, exceed those paid in similar positions under private enterprise, but they are in excess of those paid in the Civil Service. To determine in what relation the salaries paid by the B.B.C. (and possibly by similar organisations) should stand to those paid by private enterprise on the one hand, and in the Civil Service on the other, would raise difficult problems and involve a wider enquiry than we are called upon to undertake.37. Staff representation. We have been informed that there is no desire for any form of staff representation and that the late Mr. Whitley, who would naturally have been in favour of it, came to the conclusion that there was no need for it. It has been represented to us that by informal means of consultation, together with the right of appeal to the Director-General or the Governors, the staff can make known their views, higher officers can keep in touch with them and any grievances can be redressed. We cannot accept this contention as necessarily disposing of the] need for organised machinery. A similar right of appeal to the Postmaster General exists in the Post Office, but has not precluded the need for staff representation. The large measure of freedom from direct Parliamentary control which is accorded to the B.B.C. seems to us to increase this need.38. Such representation might take one of two forms : (a) the intervention of external Trade Unions, or(b) the constitution of one or more internal associations.In the employment of the B.B.C. a wide diversity of occupations is represented there are musicians, entertainers, novelists, journalists, administrators, office staff, house staff, and so on ; the work is specialised ; and the number of persons engaged on the same work at any place is as a rule small. For these reasons it is difficult to foresee any comprehensive solution on the lines of the first alternative (a). As to the second (6), we think that the Corporation should make it clear that it will provide all necessary facilities for any representative organisation, whether a single staff association or smaller bodies representative of appropriate groups, which its employees may wish to set up.
is39. We observed in the course of our enquiries that while members of the Corporation^ staff should have the right to their private religious and political convictions and indeed the advantage of a comprehensive diversity of opinion in certain departments is recognised by the Corporation itself it seemed at the same time desirable that the staff concerned with Programme work should follow the general tradition of the Civil Service in refraining from any prominent public part in matters of controversy1; but apart from this we consider that the staff should be free from any control by the Corporation over their private lives.40. There is one class of persons to whom it seems impossible to give any formal protection, that is, those who are engaged to broadcast for remuneration. It is clear that the B.B.C. with its monopoly of broadcasting in this country is in a position to exclude particular individuals from its programmes. It would for instance be possible to exclude a critic of B.B.C. programmes from ever obtaining an engagement to broadcast. The abuse of such power would tend dangerously to stifle public criticism, and we think that the B.B.C. should make it clear that it welcomes criticism and that on no consideration would it exclude any person from an opportunity of engagement merely because he had expressed adverse opinions on its activities.41. Advisory Committees. The B.B.C. is specifically invested by Charter with power to appoint Advisory Committees, and the following Committees have been appointed : General Advisory council:1 (Central). Religious Advisory Committees :1 Central;6 Regional. Music Advisory Committees :1 Central;2 Regional. Appeals Advisory Committees :1 Central;5 Regional. Spoken English Committee :1 (Central). Councils for School Broadcasting :1 Central;1 Scottish. Adult Education :1 Central Committee ;7 Area Councils.1 We understand that action has been taken on the lines of this suggestion.1 The present membership is shown in Appendix F;,-
42. We note that the General Advisory Council and the specialist Advisory Committees established by the Corporation will naturally come to an end, with the term of the Charter, at the end of next year, and we have given consideration to the future constitution of such committees. In our opinion provision for Advisory Com-mittees was wisely made and the Corporation has endeavoured to make good and increasing use of the system. But we see advantages in a more precise definition of the Committees and their membership.43. The status of the Committees is clear. Their function is to advise. Their resolutions are not binding, and they have no executive powers. It is obviously desirable that the executive should work in harmony with the advisory bodies, but final decision and responsibility must rest with the Corporation and its officers. (Paragraph 102 contains exceptional recommendations in respect of the Councils for School Broadcasting.)44. We recommend that the General Advisory Council should be continued and that there should be in each Region a similar general Advisory Committee, broadly constituted, and consulted by the Regional Director in matters of local interest just as the General Advisory Council is consulted by the Corporation on general issues. Also that there should be in each Region, as well as at Headquarters, specialised Committees widely representative and appointed by the Corporation after consultation with the General Committee of the Region. Each of the Committees in the Regions should be in com-munication with its counterpart at Headquarters. This system we consider to be the proper development of the arrangements now partially in force, and while recognising that there must be a tran-transitional period, we are anxious that it should be fully established as soon as possible. Our recommendations are not intended to preclude the Corporation or a Regional Director from seeking advice in any quarter where they may think it useful to do so.45. All appointments to such Committees should be made by the Corporation. The term of appointment to an Advisory Committee should, we think, in no case exceed four years ; but there should be no bar against the re-appointment of a retiring member. In the interest of continuity the first appointments might be made for varying periods from 1st January, 1937.46. Our concern as to the composition of the Advisory Committees is derived from an interest which we regard as vital the benefit of listeners. We trust that this will be the end towards which the endeavours of all Committees will be primarily and constantly directed. We are anxious to secure representation for the views of the general public as well as of experts in each category of broadcast subject the views, that is to say, not only of recognised leaders in their respective spheres and professions (this will apply particularly to the specialised committees) but also of listeners ; not only of
public speakers but of their audiences ; not only of the older, but of the younger generation; not only of celebrated teachers and exponents of the arts but of those who appreciate them, though perhaps without skill as executants ; not merely of the educational specialist, but also of the parent with children at school. We are confident that among public-spirited people ways and means will be found for securing a fully representative balance of opinion, and for expressing it in helpful and constructive advice ; and with this object in view we recommend that the membership of the Advisory Committees should be as comprehensive and varied as possible. Their work is inevitably hampered where this balance is lacking.CONTROL47. Relation of the B.B.C. to His Majesty&apos;s Government. Estab-lished, as the Royal Charter1 specifies, for the purpose of developing and exploiting the broadcasting service to the best advantage and in the national interest, the B.B.C. stands in an unusual relation to the Government of the Country. Set up by the State, it is yet different in kind from the Government Departments which transact the State&apos;s business. Subject by Charter and Licence to the same potentialities of supervision as the Company which it succeeded, and held liable to State control, both positive and negative, the Corporation has exercised in practice a high degree of independence, in pursuance of the Crawford Committee&apos;s recommendations &quot; that the prestige and status of the Commission should be freely acknowledged and their sense of responsibility emphasised; that, although Parliament must retain the right of ultimate control and the Postmaster General must be the Parliamentary spokesman on broad questions of policy, the Commissioners2 should be invested with the maximum of freedom which Parliament is prepared to concede.&quot;48. Under Sections 3 (a) and 18 of the Charter1, the Corporation is strictly bound to observe the provisions of any licence granted by the Postmaster General and any instructions which he may from time to time issue. Under Section 4, sub-section (2) of the existing Licence3, the Corporation is bound to broadcast any matter (inter-preted in practice as any official announcement) which any Government Department may require. The announcements issued by request include Police and &quot; S.O.S.&quot; messages and weather reports. Under sub-section (3) of the same Section, it is required to refrain from broadcasting any matter (either particular or general) which the Postmaster General may specify. The only restriction in force in recent times has been a veto upon the broadcasting of the Corporation^ opinions by way of editorial comment upon current affairs4. Matters of controversy were for a time excluded,1 Appendix B. 3 Appendix C.2v(i.e., the Governors.) 4 Seejxlso paragraph 79.
but are now left to the discretion of the Corporation. There is provision for Government control in case of national emergency ; other matters dealt with in the Licence are mainly technical or financial.49. The relation in which the B.B.C. should stand to His Majesty&apos;s Government has more than once been discussed in Parliament. When the establishment and financing of the Corporation was first brought before the House of Commons on 15th November, 1926, the Postmaster General (Sir William Mitchell-Thomson, now Lord Selsdon) said : -&quot; While I am prepared to take the responsibility for broad issues of policy, on minor issues and measures of domestic policy and matters of day-to-day control I want to leave things to the free judgment of the Corporation.&quot;50. This policy was re-affirmed on 22nd February, 1933, when the House of Commons resolved, after debate &quot; That this House, being satisfied that the British Broad-casting Corporation maintains in general a high standard of service, is of opinion that it would be contrary to the public interest to subject the corporation to any control by Government or by Parliament other than the control already provided for in the charter and the licence of the corporation ; that con-controversial matter is rightly not excluded from broadcast programmes, but that the governors should ensure the effective expression of all important opinion relating thereto ; and that only by the exercise of the greatest care in the selection of speakers and subjects can the function of the corporation be fulfilled and the high quality of the British broadcasting service be maintained.&quot;51. The position of the Corporation is thus one of independence in the day-to-day management of its business, and of ultimate control by His Majesty&apos;s Government. We find that this line of demarcation has been observed in practice, and we are convinced that no better can be found. We agree with those who in recent years have examined the question that the constitutional indepen-dence of the B.B.C. brings advantages to the general public and to listeners which could not otherwise be secured. Our proposals under this heading are designed to make both sides of this two-fold position simpler and more evident.52. It is inevitable that the State, in establishing a sole broad-casting authority, should reserve to itself these powers of ultimate control; but we have no reason to suppose that, in practice, divergent views of the lines of public interest have been held by the Corporation and by Government departments, or that the Corporation has suffered under any sense of constraint or undue interference. Where the interests of the State appear to be at all closely involved, it is
mOpen to the Corporation to consult a Minister or Department informally and of its own accord. This method leaves decision and discretion in the hands of the Corporation and is consistent with the independent status which was formulated ten years ago as the desirable objective.53. Ministerial control. By reason of the technical control of wireless communications vested in him by the Wireless Telegraphy Act of 1904, the Postmaster General is the Minister upon whom responsibility for the broadcasting service has fallen in the natural process of evolution. By the same natural process the service itself has acquired within fourteen years a high and certainly unforeseen degree of educative and cultural importance. While recognising the important part which the Post Office has played, through its Ministers and officials, in the successful establishment and working of the service, we have felt obliged to examine with an open mind whether the ministerial office to which the technical control and the collection of revenue are (and must remain) attached is necessarily the office most appropriate and best qualified to supervise the policy of the service, to answer to Parliament for its conduct, and to direct its destinies. We have given special consideration to this question, and we recommend that while technical control under the Wireless Telegraphy Acts (together with the administration of the wireless licence system, the collection of revenue, and the investiga-tion of complaints of electrical interference) should remain in the hands of the Postmaster General, responsibility for the cultural side of broadcasting should be transferred to a Cabinet Minister in the House of Commons, preferably a senior member of the Govern-ment, and free from heavy Departmental responsibilities. We refrain from specifying any individual office and we think that it should rest with the Prime Minister to select a suitable Minister for the purpose. The powers of veto over programmes at present resting with the Postmaster General would naturally, under this proposal, be transferred to the Minister selected.54. There are public advantages in the broadcasting of official notices at the request of Government Departments and existing arrangements work satisfactorily. We recommend that the Corpora-tion should have a discretionary power to announce that any given notice is broadcast at the request of a named Department.55. Parliamentary control. Opportunities for a Parliamentary review of broadcasting have been presented every year by the Expiring Laws Continuance Bill, providing inter alia for the renewal of the Wireless Telegraphy Acts under which the Corporation and its listeners are licensed, and by the Post Office Estimates, in which is entered for approval the amount of Licence revenue to be allocated to the Corporation for the financial year. Notable discussions have also occurred in the House of Commons on a specific Resolution or on a Motion for the Adjournment.
56. When, however, the Expiring Laws Continuance Bill or the Post Office Estimates are before Parliament, broadcasting has been only one among a numerous variety of subjects brought within the scope of possible discussion. In the future, if our recommendations in the preceding paragraphs are approved, the Estimates for broad-casting will be presented separately/by the controlling Minister. The Corporation^ Annual Report and Accounts will also be presented to Parliament, and the opportunities for discussion will be adequate. We do not wish to suggest that the extent of Parliamentary criticism and control over details should be enlarged, but we think it advantageous that the occasions for discussion on broad matters of policy should be regular and adequate.57. Emergency control. The Licence at present provides for broadcasting to be taken out of the Corporation^ hands by His Majesty&apos;s Government in any emergency in which that procedure is, in the opinion of the Postmaster General, expedient for the Public Service. We envisage two possible degrees or stages of emergency. In the event of a minor emergency it might be sufficient that the Government should instruct the Corporation to broadcast specific messages, while normal powers of discretion and decision in all other respects remained unimpaired in the hands of the Corporation. We think that this method should-be adopted and continued for the longest time possible before recourse is had to a more drastic form of control. In serious or national emergencies we recognise that full governmental control would be necessary. We recommend that this should be announced as soon as imposed, and that the action taken should at once be reported to Parliament.FINANCE58. Licence fee. We have received and examined estimates of future revenue and of prospective expenditure upon the broadcasting service (apart from Television). In view of these estimates and of the proposals to be made later in this Report, we recommend that the annual broadcast receiving licence fee should remain at ten shillings. We note with pleasure the concession of free licences to registered blind persons, but we regard as impracticable a similar concession to any other class of listener, however deserving of sympathy.59. Licence receipts. The annual revenue from licences already exceeds  3,500,000, and is growing. Evidence laid before us suggests that in a few years&apos; time a sum of  4,500,000 is likely to be attained.60. Post Office share of licence revenue. The first charge upon the revenue collected in respect of wireless receiving licences is the cost of the licensing system maintained by the Post Office and of the ancillary services rendered by that Department in connection with the licensing system (notably the detection and prosecution of unlicensed receivers and assistance in alleviating electrical inter-ference).   To defray the cost involved, a proportion of the gross
To the Post Office, to cover expenses To  the Post Office,  for  conversion of coastal radio stations I from spark toi.c.w. system To   the   Exchequer,   under   the   scalementioned below (paragraph 65)2 Surrendered by the B.B.C., out of thereceipts to which it was entitled underthe scale, to the Exchequer by way ofspecial contributions in aid of nationaleconomyPaid by the B.B.C. to the Exchequer in Income Tax       . .       ..       ..Net share remaining to the B.B.C.3Totals31,000 0-18 4,963,000      29-61575,000568,000 8,788,0003-433-39 52-43 16,761,000    100-0063. In dealing with the main principles of the finance^of broad-casting we are upon ground which has been surveyed on previous occasions in the reports of earlier Committees and in Parliamentary discussion. General recognition has been given to the principle enunciated by the Sykes Committee that no part of the cost of1 Appendix E.2 After deduction of ^40,000 for Opera. s After addition of ^40,000 for Opera.receipts is allocated to the Post Office. This proportion was fixed by agreement in 1926 at 12  per cent. The Post Office income from this source, and the costs incurred, are reported annually to Parliament in the Post Office Commercial Accounts. In the financial year 1930-31 the costs fell for the first time below 10 per cent, of the gross revenue, and for succeeding years the Post Office share has been fixed by supplemental agreement at 10 per cent. For the year 1934-35 the costs incurred by the Post Office amounted to  322,050, and the sum payable to the Post Office to  348,410.61. We approve the principle of fixing the Post Office payment as a percentage of the gross revenue collected, but we recommend that the matter be reviewed and the appropriate unit or half-unit per cent, to cover prospective costs be fixed for periods of two years, the first of which should begin on 1st January, 1937.62. Allocation of net revenue from licences. During the eight calendar years 1927 to 1934 the total income collected from licences was in effect allocated in the following proportions : Approximate Percentageamount. of total  amount.1,836,000 10-96
broadcasting should be borne out of public funds. The same Committee laid it down that the Post Office should obtain sufficient revenue from licence fees to cover administrative expenses with a safe margin. There then remains a net figure to be apportioned between the Exchequer and the B.B.C. The Sykes Committee considered &quot; that the Government should not aim at making a profit on the control of the service.&quot; The Crawford Committee pronounced it to be &quot; the duty of the Postmaster General to pay to the Commissioners from the licence fees an income thoroughly adequate to enable them to ensure the full and efficient maintenance and development of the service &quot; ; and added that &quot; on these con-ditions, and when the adequate service has been assured, but not until then, it is expedient that the surplus should be retained by the State.&quot; The surplus so retained has in fact been measured by a scale of percentages1 and has reached proportions which were never anticipated : it was  1,135,000 in the year 1934 and will exceed  1,200,000 for the year 1935. In addition, the Exchequer has in the past received the special contributions already mentioned, and will continue to receive Income Tax on all sums devoted by the Corporation to capital expenditure or set aside as reserve (e.g., on a sum of about  219,900 for the year 1934).64. B.B.C. income. During the year 1934 the Corporation, as shown in its eighth Annual Report (Cmd. 4813), derived its income from the following sources : Percentage Approximate       of total amount.     B.B.C. income. B.B.C. share of wireless receivinglicence revenue         ..       ..     1,710,286 83-06Net revenue from publications ..       347,707 16-89Interest........ 990 0-05Totals...... 2,058,983       100-0065. Of the net revenue (after deduction of the Post Office per-centage) from the licences in force on 31st March in any year, the B.B.C. is under the existing Licence2 entitled to receive during the succeeding financial year (1st April to 31st March), under a sliding scale, the following proportions : P Hi (a) In respect of the first million licences : 90 per cent.(b) In respect of the second million : 80 per cent.(c) In respect of the third million : 70 per cent.(d) In respect of alb additional licences : 60 per cent.* Cf. paragraph^65.&quot;Appendix C.
66. We believe that the B.B.C. would in the past have been able to provide more varied programmes and a more rapid extension of service, if its income had been larger. In view of this fact and of the expansion and improvements recommended elsewhere in this Report, which the Corporation is prepared and anxious to undertake so soon as. adequate revenue for the purpose can be provided, we are satisfied that a substantially higher proportion of the sums paid by listeners should be allotted to the Corporation for the service.67. We do not think it defensible that the Exchequer should retain any part of the net revenue collected from listeners unless the Corporation has first received &quot; an income thoroughly adequate to ensure the full and efficient maintenance and development of the service.&quot; The estimates presented to us indicate that the income required during the next few years for purposes other than Television (after 1936) will amount to approximately 75 per cent, of the net licence revenue remaining after deduction of the proportion to cover Post Office costs ; and we recommend that the proportion of net revenue to be allocated to the B.B.C. under the new Charter and Licence should not be less than 75 per cent.68. The amount to be paid to the B.B.C. in monthly instalments during each financial year (e.g., April, 1934 to March, 1935) has hitherto been calculated upon the number of licences in force at the end of the preceding financial year (e.g., on 31st March, 1934). In order that the appropriate amount may be included in an Estimate to be presented to Parliament, a forecast has to be made two or three months before the year begins (viz., in January, 1934, to take the example above quoted). The number of licences which will be in force on the succeeding 31st March can be foreseen within reasonably narrow limits; but there would be an element of speculation in an attempt to predict the number to be issued for a year or more ahead. None the less we are of opinion that the Corporation should receive its percentage in respect of the number of licences actually issued month by month. If this had been so in the past, the B.B.C. would have received additional sums amounting during the eight years 1927-1934 to a total of more than  1,100,000. We propose that the Estimates should be formed for this purpose on the basis of the best forecast that can be made at the time and that the sums estimated to fall due should be paid to the Corporation monthly, as a payment on account. So soon as the actual sales are known month by month, any necessary adjustment should be made forthwith, except that if such adjustments over the financial year as a whole should take the form of an excess payment to be made to the Corporation, the necessary provision should be included in the Estimate for the following financial year, and payment of the excess should fall to be made in that year.69. The balance of the sums collected from the public for the purposes of broadcasting should be regarded as available for those
purposes so far as it may be required. Our recommendation in a later paragraph (128) as to Television is an example of the application of this principle. We agree with the Crawford Committee that the final surplus, after all needs have been met, may equitably be assigned to the State, which has conferred a monopoly upon the B.B.C. and safeguards both the listener and the service.70. The new Charter will presumably take effect from the begin-ning of the year 1937, and it is in respect of that and subsequent years that our recommendations are especially sought. But in order to provide for the early introduction of the changes which we propose, a modification of the financial arrangements is required during the year 1936 ; and after considering the views expressed on behalf of both the Treasury and the B.B.C. we think it equitable that the share of receiving licence revenue to be paid to and retained by the Exchequer in respect of the year 1936 should be arbitrarily fixed at  1,050,000 (exclusive of the Income Tax payable by the B.B.C.). After deduction of this amount and of the percentage to cover Post Office expenses, the balance of the licence revenue collected during the year should be paid to the B.B.C. in such monthly instalments as may be convenient, on the understanding that the whole cost of Television for that year should be borne by the Corporation from the share so allotted to it. The instalments would presumably be smaller in the months January-March, for which provision has already been made as part of the current financial year, and larger in the months April-December.71. Payments to authors and others. We have heard evidence as to the fees paid to authors, composers, and the owners of performing rights. Broadcasting has opened a new market for musical and literary work at a time when the demand in other quarters may be fluctuating or falling. It brings the artisfs works to a very wide audience, without necessarily stimulating the distribution of copies of those works or the demand for their performance elsewhere. But it is not on this ground alone that a liberal treatment of creative artists is to be recommended. It is open to the Corporation, by selection and encouragement, to exert a strong influence upon future artistic production, and we feel that a generous policy will beneficially affect both the immediate future of the arts in this country and the broadcasting service itself. We have no doubt that the Corporation, in settling fees by agreement, will take these considerations fully into account.72. At the same time weforesee the possibility of disagreement at some future date if the bodies which control a large volume of musical or other material for performance should advance claims which the Corporation would not feel justified in conceding. If that contingency should arise, it would be right for the dispute to be settled by reference to an arbitration tribunal agreed upon by the parties and the B.B.C.&apos;f should endeavour to secure this; but if
1 Appendix D,agreement as to arbitration cannot be reached, we recommend that the. question should be decided by a tribunal set up by Parliament for the purpose.73. Revenue expenditure. An analysis of the revenue expenditure of the Corporation for the year 1934 will be found in Appendix G. The bulk of the cost was incurred in respect of programmes (44*44 per cent, of the total shown in the account) and engineering expenses (16-27 per cent.).74. Capital expenditure. The Corporation, when it was formed, took over without expense to itself assets then valued at  175,000, and has met subsequent capital requirements, amounting to a total of  2,129,682 up to 31st December, 1934, from surpluses of revenue over current expenditure (either by direct, appropriation or- -under the authority of a Royal Supplemental Charter1 by the use of sums set aside to meet depreciation of wasting assets), with the temporary help of one loan which has now been repaid. We consider that this is the right and the best course for a public body constituted and financed as the Corporation is. We understand that the Corporation wishes to avoid borrowing so far as possible, and in case of need would contemplate nothing more than a short-term loan to allow abnormal capital expenditure in a given year to be defrayed from succeeding surpluses. We endorse this policy and, subject to its continuance we consider, having regard to the scale of the Corpora-tion&apos;s finance, that the limit of borrowing powers might be raised to  1,000,000. There has been some criticism as to the wisdom of certain items of capital expenditure in the past, and while we recognise that the remarkable development of the service has rendered the task of the Governors in this respect one of extreme difficulty, we consider that in future opportunity should be taken, upon the annual presentation of the Estimate for broadcasting, to inform Parliament and the public of the major items of capital expenditure contemplated in the ensuing year.75. Annual Account. We have considered suggestions that current expenditure should be shown in greater detail in the published Annual Account of the Corporation. To criticise this Account by comparison with the detailed Estimates presented to Parliament for Government services would be to overlook the constitutional difference between the two cases, and we accept the view that publication of details (whether of payments to individual artists or of staff salaries or of any other category of expenditure) would tend to impair independence of day-to-day management and would serve no useful purpose unless Parliament wished to withdraw that independence from the Board of Governors and to establish instead a system of direct control as in the case of a Government Department.  The Corporation^ accounts, it should be remembered,
can at any time be investigated by the responsible Minister ; and, as our enquiries have shown, the accounts are kept in notably complete form and good order, so that information on any point can very readily be obtained. We note that under the existing Charter the form of Account to be published is not prescribed or made subject to the approval of any external authority. The obligation which rests upon the B.B.C., as administering a public service with funds raised from the public and entrusted to the B.B.C. by Parliament, is in our judgment not to disclose details, which in some instances might actually prejudice its current commercial transactions, but to present a clear and intelligible picture of its activities in broad outline.76. The past Accounts, in which large amounts have been shown without sub-division, have not been fully consistent with this view. We recommend that sub-headings and sub-totals should be separately shown, and we have attached to this Report a schedule (Appendix G) illustrating the degree of development which seems to us appropriate at the present time. The amounts spent (by way of capital and revenue expenditure) upon specific services such as Television and Empire broadcasting could not conveniently be shown in such an account since, as pointed out in a later paragraph (128), much apportionment of common expenditure would be involved&apos; but are of sufficient importance to receive mention in the Annual Report. An expansion to this extent of the information given would seem to us sufficient to satisfy all legitimate public interest in the financial working of this public institution.77. Financial forecast. Forecasts of revenue and expenditure over a period of eight years (1935 1942) have been drawn up, examined, and revised at our request. The resultant forecast, which after consultation we are prepared to accept as the best that can be made, indicates that if the foregoing recommendations are completely approved the revenue of the Corporation will cover its anticipated expenditure on operation, development, and renewals, and leave a small surplus as a general reserve against contingencies. That is apart from any allowance after 1936 for Television, to which we shall recur in later paragraphs (127 and 128). Meanwhile we record the opinion that if our proposals are adopted there should be, so far as can be foreseen, a sufficient sum available for the needs of the broadcasting pi sound.PROGRAMMES78. General approval. Our invitation for the submission of evidence obtained wide publicity in technical and popular papers during May, and we have received correspondence relating to every aspect of the subject. Having regard to the immense number of listeners, the infinite variety of taste, and the many types of
programme which are being broadcast at all limes, we regard it as no small tribute to the B.B.C., and as proof of general satisfaction, that the volume of adverse criticism from listeners has been remarkably small and that in matters of taste and opinion there has been a very even balance between the comments put forward from opposite points of view.79. Editorial opinion. We think it right that the Corporation should refrain, as in the past, from broadcasting its own opinions by way of editorial comment upon current affairs.80. News. The influence of broadcasting on the political life of the country is brought to bear not only by speeches, talks and reports, but also by the provision of news. It is, therefore, of the utmost importance that the news distributed by the B.B.C. should be a fair selection of items impartially presented.81. The present arrangements for the collection and presentation of news appear on the whole satisfactory. It is evident that a copious supply of news is received from all parts of the world. The B.B.C., it is true, is dependent for the bulk of its news on four commercial agencies which are primarily designed to cater for the Press. It is obviously possible that the selection of news for the B.B.C. may be influenced by the weight of opinion, whether political, economic, religious, or social, temporarily predominating in the Press. Fears have been expressed by witnesses on this score, with special reference to the relations of Capital and Labour, but it is fair to say that any such suggestion of bias is denied by the News Agencies.82. We have considered, in a general sense, how the broadcast news service can best be safeguarded against the risk of extraneous influences. It is in our view important that freedom of choice as to the sources of news should be maintained, and the Corporation should continue to supplement the service obtained from agencies by sending out its own correspondents and by drawing information from other authoritative sources.83. We regard it as vital that the B.B.C. should maintain a strong and impartial editorial staff. In the presentment of news, simplicity is desirable and the B.B.C. should be as impersonal as possible.84. We regard the existing arrangements between the B.B.C. and the newspapers, agencies, etc., as satisfactory, but we are anxious that there should be no bar to variations as future circumstances may require. Television, for example, must be free from&quot; restrictions as to hours ; and it is possible that at some future date news bulletins may be wanted at times when they are not now given. We have received representations in favour of a restriction of certain kinds of news to a time later than that at which the news is now given, but we do not consider this justified in the public interest.
85. Controversy. We think it important that controversial topics should continue to be discussed. If broadcasting is to present a reflection of its time, it must include matters which are in dispute. If it is to hold public interest, it must express living thought. If it is to educate public opinion, it must look upon the questions of the hour from many angles.86. In our opinion the B.B.C. has exercised ^the responsibility confided to it with outstanding independence and has handled the problems of presentation with wisdom. In the trust that this policy will continue, we make no special suggestions, except with regard to political broadcasting, but would leave to the B.B.C. the responsibility for choosing speakers and subjects, ensuring any necessary consultation, preserving an impartial and representative balance, and arranging that controversial opinions are expressed in a proper context.87. Political broadcasting. The control of political broadcasting is one of the most difficult and important problems which the advent of &quot; wireless &quot; has created. It is obvious that a medium whereby expressions of political opinion can be brought into seven or eight million homes needs very careful safeguarding if it is not to be abused. It would be possible for those in control of broadcasting to maintain a steady stream of propaganda on behalf of one political party or of one school of thought. They could to some extent make or mar the reputations of politicians, and by a judicious selection of news items and the method of their presentation they could influence the whole political thought of the country.88. It was only after some&quot;; hesitation&quot;&quot; that matters of political controversy were allowed on the ether, but from the time of their admission in March, 1928, political broadcasting has become increasingly important. It has been the avowed policy of the B.B.C. to hold the scales even between the various political parties and in this, though there have been occasional criticisms from quarters widely separated, it has on the whole been successful.89. It must^be recognised as inevitable that more prominence is given to the leaders of the. political party in power than to the. Opposition. There are numbers of occasions on which Ministers of State are called upon to make important pronouncements. These necessarily have some political flavour and tend naturally to stress the beneficence of Government activities. There is an equally inevitable tendency in the general programmes of the Corporation to devote more time to the expression of new ideas and the advocacy of change, in social and other spheres, than to the defence of orthodoxy and stability, since the reiteration of what exists and is familiar is not so interesting as the exposition of what might be. We have been informed by the B.B.C. that criticism on the ground of political, inteUectual, and artistic bias comes both from the Right and from the Left.
90. It has been said that Parliamentary institutions are on their trial. If that be so, broadcasting is an instrument of great potential value in keeping Parliament before the minds of the people. It is in the Parliamentary contest that the issues before the country should emerge, and while the amount of Parliamentary news in the popular Press is small and diminishing we think it all the more necessary that broadcasting should look towards Parliament as the focal point of political thought.91. Any direct broadcasting of Parliamentary proceedings we regard as impracticable, but we consider that the B.B.C. has done well in giving space to those proceedings in its news bulletins. The experiment of sending a reporter to a Parliamentary debate in order that he may broadcast an account of it seems to us excellent in intention, though there are difficulties which have not yet been overcome. The task is one demanding special skill and experience on the part of the reporter, who should endeavour to give an objective account rather than a personal impression, taking particular care to avoid any distortion due to individual bias or to the desire for descriptive effect. If the experiment is to be pursued, the reporter should be given all necessary parliamentary facilities, especially as regards admission and note-taking.92. Our recommendations with reference to broadcasting during a General Election campaign will be found in the two succeeding paragraphs, 93 and 94. At other times, though we are far from implying that all broadcast treatment of political questions should be controlled by the political party organisations, we recommend that on the major political issues of the day there should be close co-operation and consultation between the B.B.C. and the authorised spokesmen of the recognised political parties. The B.B.C. must, of course, continue to be the judge of the amount of political broadcasting which the programme will stand, and while recognising in the allotment of time, according to current Parliamentary practice, the preponderating position of the main political parties, should allow adequate expression to minority views, however unpopular.93. For the conduct of political broadcasting during a General Election campaign, the B.B.C. should, we consider, -first offer for election speeches such time as may seem appropriate. The allocation of this time between the Government, the official Opposition and other parties should then be arranged by agreement between them, in default of which the Speaker of the House of Commons might perhaps be asked to make an arbitral decision.94. The broadcaster who has the last word during an electoral contest is in a position of great advantage, because there can be no adequate reply to whatever he may say. In the fear that this advantage might be unfairly used in the production of a surprise issue at the last moment, it has been, suggested to us that all political
broadcasting should cease for three days before the Poll. There is force in the suggestion ; the General Election of 1935 has shown it to be practicable ; and we recommend its adoption.95. Music. With regard to the broadcasting of music we have received a large amount of evidence. For the sake of clearness we differentiate certain purposes among which some order of priority must be established : (a) to encourage the enjoyment and active making and cultivation of music throughout the country;(b) to present systematically to listeners the best music with the highest attainable standard of performance ;(c) to improve popular taste ; and(d) to minimise any hardship caused to composers and performers by reduction of employment and remuneration as a result of the recent and rapidly increasing application of mechanical and electrical (including wireless) science to the reproduction and transmission of music.96. Serious music. If an undue and exclusive emphasis is placed on any one of these purposes it may become inconsistent with the rest. Subject to this, the purpose which a broadcasting organisation should regard as paramount is that fine music, played under the best conditions, may be heard and appreciated over the whole country to the vast extent which broadcasting alone has made possible. To this end, performance is rightly supplemented by educational courses and explanatory and introductory talks. We support the policy of a full development of studio performances by the B.B.C. orchestras and their judicious use in public concerts not necessarily confined to London, together with the relaying of the best performances of outside organisations in any important class of music.97. We do not regard these activities as inconsistent with the other purposes which we have mentioned. On the contrary, broadcasting may well be one of the strongest forces aiding the active cultivation of music generally : by affording employment to performers ; by offering to composers a prospect of the performance of suitable works ; by relaying, as mentioned above, the best performances and contributing towards the cost ; by pursuing a considered scheme of collaboration with active and efficient local societies, in order to supply what each region most requires for its own musical development ; and by other methods, such as visits, lectures, and broadcast announcements directing attention to local musical enterprises.
98. Light music. The importance of light music in broadcasting is shown by an analysis of the programmes for 1934. The proportions of time occupied by various classes of programme were1 : We regard it as important that in the selection of light music attention should be continuously directed to &quot;reproducing material of good musical quality and to the improvement of public taste. There is clearly a demand for dance music as an alternative programme.99. Encouragement and help to musicians. For the fourth purpose (d), of minimising hardship, we can make no specific recommendation: the position is too complex and too many factors other than broad-casting are involved. Recent years have witnessed not only the immense innovation of broadcasting but also a succession of other changes in the practice and appreciation of music by the people and in the ways in which music is publicly supplied. If the lines, of policy indicated continue to be followed] and the desirability&apos; of avoiding hardship is kept sympathetically in view, the Corporation will have done its best for the musical profession. It employs a large number of musicians, and the first three entries in Appendix G comprise a heavy expenditure on music.100. Sunday programmes. We IJhave little doubt] that something has been lost in the past by a lack of attractiveness in the programmes broadcast on Sundays (apart from the religious services). We think it an advantage that one of the alternative programmes should be of a lighter and more popular character than the other, and that the contrasting programme though in more serious mood should be of interest to a good proportion of thoughtful listeners. We are glad, to notice that the B.B.C. has recently been working on these lines.101. School broadcasting. An extensive programme of weekly broadcasts for schools is provided. These broadcasts are intended to supplement, not to take the place of, the work of teacher and pupil, and to provide a mental stimulus beyond the ordinary resources of the school. We are satisfied as to their value, and look forward to the time when every school will have wireless receiving apparatus as part of its normal equipment, to the benefit both of the children and of the teaching staff.Light music    .. Serious music Dance music Gramophone records . .33^ per cent. 14\ per cent.9J per cent.8 per cent.Music (total) All other matters65J per cent. 34\ per cent.1 The figures quoted do not include Empire transmissions.
102. The direction of the programmes has been entrusted to a Central Council for School Broadcasting and a Scottish Sub-Council. The functions of these Councils are thus executive, unlike those of the Advisory Committees mentioned in paragraph 41 above ; and we have received evidence that the Board of Education, the Scottish Education Department, and the B.B.C. do not wish to be directly responsible for the nature of the broadcast material presented to schools. It has accordingly been recommended to us that each of these Councils should be given independent status, with power to determine the school educational programme to be broadcast and the ancillary leaflets and pamphlets to be issued. If this proposal, which we view with favour, is approved by the Education Depart-ments, they will no doubt arrange with the B.B.C. the conditions of broadcasting time and of finance. The Corporation would then act in these matters as an executive body on behalf of the Councils. We see no reason why the cost should not continue to be borne by the B.B.C. within reasonable limits, regard being paid to the propor-tion of licence revenue at present devoted to this purpose. No similar Council is yet in existence for Wales and Monmouth ; we recommend that one should be established.103. More than 3,500 schools in England, Scotland and Wales are regularly listening ; but among the rest technical or financial difficulties are preventing headway. Satisfactory participation depends on a number of conditions :(a) choice by the head teacher ;(b) financial provision;(c) selection of a suitable receiving set;(d) proper arrangements for maintenance.104. (a) Head teachers are free, within wide limits, to organise their schools according to their own ideas, and we are assured that broadcast lessons cannot be successful except as an integral part of the work of a class. The experience of schools where such lessons are given under proper conditions seem likely to ensure the readiness of an increasing number of schools to participate, if difficulties can be removed.105. (&amp;) The evidence received suggests that the financial difficulty affects Elementary schools in all districts and Secondary schools in Scotland and Wales. In some of these schools a set is used which belongs to a member of the staff or has been bought with funds specially raised. Apart from such private initiative, responsibility for the provision and maintenance of apparatus rests with the Local Education Authority, which can count upon a specific grant of 20 per cent, of the cost of the set in England and Wales, and in Scotland can draw upon a block grant not calculated as a percentage of local expenditure but depending on other factors. We are informed that though reception is satisfactory in some schools, there are a
great many others where it is, as yet, so poor as to prevent the service from being properly appreciated; that good reception involves the expenditure of more money than is at present devoted to this object ; and that the Council would welcome any public action which might be taken at this stage with a view to accelerating the equipment of schools, on a wide scale, with suitable apparatus. Certain Education authorities in Scotland are giving full financial facilities. It is for the Education authorities, local and central, rather than for us, to decide upon the degree of importance to be attached to the matter and the extent of the effort to be made ; nor do we regard the allocation of funds for this purpose as a function proper to the B.B.C. ; but we offer under the next heading a suggestion which we hope may make progress easier and more rapid.106. (c) A list of sets on the ordinary market which are considered suitable for school use, is published by the Council twice a year and circulated to all Local Education Authorities, some of whom limit their approval to sets shown in the list. As, however, all that is wanted is good reception of the National and the local Regional station, we recommend that the B.B.C. or the Council, in consultation with the manufacturers, might design a set specially for school use (or if necessary a small range of sets differing in power but similar in other respects), and might endeavour to arrange for its adoption by Local Education Authorities in such total numbers as will enable it to be produced by the manufacturers at a comparatively small price. By this means a good standard of reception should be ensured, and the cost reduced.107. (d) Arrangements for maintenance might as a general rule be made with a competent local dealer, though there will doubtless be schools where a member of the staff is expert enough to keep the apparatus running in perfect order. Standardisation of pattern should simplify the maintenance problem.108. Advertisements.- As was pointed out by the Sykes Committee on Broadcasting in 1923,1 and by the Television Committee a year ago,2 a broadcast programme may contain either- -(i) direct advertisements for which time is bought by the advertiser, or(ii) &quot; sponsored &quot; items, with which is coupled an indirect advertisement for example, an announcement that an artist is broadcasting by the courtesy of such and such a person or organisation.109. (i) Direct advertisements. The possible admission of direct advertisements in the ordinary broadcast service was discussed by the Sykes Committee1 and rejected.   This conclusion was approved1 Cmd. 1951, paragraphs 40 and 41.        2 Cmd. 4793, paragraph 65.
and has remained in force, being embodied in the Corporation^ Licence.1 We in our turn confirm the same conclusion, and are most anxious that the intellectual and ethical integrity which the broadcasting system in this country has attained should be preserved.110. (ii) &quot; Sponsored &quot; programmes. It has been represented to us that in the early stages of Television broadcasting it may be necessary to resort to sponsored programmes. A similar possibility was envisaged in 1923 in regard to sound broadcasting, and the Sykes Committee considered &quot; that there would be no objection to the operating concern being allowed to accept the gift of a concert and to broadcast a preliminary announcement giving the name of the donor.&quot; Power was accordingly reserved to the Corporation on its establishment in 19271 &quot; to broadcast matter provided gratuitously by any person with or without an acknowledgement of such provision by means of the broadcasting service.&quot;111. In the actual use of this power, discreet judgment has been shown. While recommending the continuance of the power, we hope that any increase in its use will be limited to the initial stages of Television broadcasting. There is an obvious danger that if the Television system should be based on sponsored programmes, and if Television should become more and more a usual accompaniment of sound broadcasting, sponsored items might come to occupy a considerable part of the B.B.C. programmes.112. B.B.C. powers. We recommend that the relative clause in the Licence1 should be renewed in its existing form with the omission of sub-clause (2) permission to receive a consideration for broad-casting names of publishers and prices of matter which is broadcast.113. Programmes from abroad. It has been widely recognised that the practice of excluding advertisements from broadcast programmes in this country is to the advantage of listeners. In recent years, however, this policy has been contravened, and the purposes sought by the unified control of broadcasting have been infringed, by the transmission of advertisements in English from certain stations abroad, which are not subject to the influence of the British authorities except by way of international agreement and negotiation. As long ago as May of 1933 this matter was brought before the Council of the International Broadcasting Union, which passed a resolution to the following effect : &quot; The Council . . . holds that the systematic diffusion of programmes or communications which are specially intended for listeners in another country and have been the subject of a protest by the broadcasting organisation or organisations of1 Appendix C, Clause 3, pages 65-66.
that country, constitutes an inadmissible act from the point of view of good international relations. It calls upon the members of the International Broadcasting Union to avoid such trans-missions, which constitute an improper use of broadcasting ; and it requests the Government Administrations which control broadcasting organisations not adhering to the Union, to take steps so far as may be possible with such organisations in order to induce them also to submit to these principles of good inter-national understanding.&quot;114. We understand that the Post Office and the Foreign Office take all the steps which are within their power with a view to preventing the broadcasting from foreign countries in English of programmes which include advertisements and to which objection has been taken. We approve this policy, but it is obvious that co-operation with all foreign countries is necessary to make the policy internationally effective.BROADCASTING TO THE EMPIRE115. The question of establishing a station for broadcasting to the Empire was considered in 1926 and discussed at a conference of Colonial Authorities. At the end of 1927 the B.B.C. established a short-wave transmitting station at Chelmsford, by arrangement with the Marconi Company, for the purpose of experimental broad-casting to the Empire. At the Colonial Conference of 1929 and the Imperial Conference of 1930 the hope was expressed that an Empire service might be developed ; but for some time it was found difficult to finance a suitable scheme. In the autumn of 1931 the B.B.C. agreed to construct and work an Empire station from its ordinary revenue. Special transmitters were erected at Daventry, and the Empire broadcasting service was inaugurated on the 19th of December, 1932, with ten hours of transmission daily divided into five periods.116. At the present time there are six transmissions daily, covering a total of sixteen hours or more. The following list shows to what quarter of the globe each transmission is directed, in order to give evening (or late afternoon) reception in the countries mentioned ; it should be understood that the programmes reach other countries within the sector of transmission from Great Britain, and may be heard elsewhere when meteorological conditions are favourable : (1) To Australia, New Zealand, etc. : 2 hours, between 4.30 and 10.30 a.m. G.M.T. according to the time of year.(2) To Malaya and the Far East : 2 to 3 hours between 11 a.m. and 2 p.m.(3) To India, Burma and Ceylon : 3 hours, 2 to 5 p.m.
(4) (a) To South and East Africa, and (b) to West Africa and the British West Indies : 5^ hours between 5 and 11 p.m., in two parts divided by a short interval.(5) To Canada, Newfoundland, the West Indies and North and South America : 2 hours, 11 p.m. to 1 a.m.(6) To Western Canada : 1 hour, 3 to 4 a.m.117. We attach great importance to the maintenance and develop-ment of the Empire service. The world-wide transmissions of broadcasts by His Majesty the King/at Christmas and of the Jubilee celebrations have been outstanding examples of the importance of linking the Empire by broadcasting, and interest in the day-to-day programmes is constantly growing. There has been a conspicuous development of broadcasting in English from certain foreign countries, and these services are received in all parts of the British Empire. It is all the more important that what has been called &quot; the projection of England &quot; should be effectively carried out by a steadily developing Empire service of our own.113. We are told that there is reason for a further extension of transmitting hours, to provide an adequate daily broadcast at a convenient time for every part of the Empire ; that additional engineering expenditure is needed; and that the programmes could be improved if funds were available.119. We are glad to note that facilities exist for the interchange of broadcast programmes with the Dominions and India and that progress is being made with the establishment of wireless or wire distribution systems in the Colonies over which B.B.C. Empire programmes can be relayed. Certain minor contributions which have been received from Colonial Governments towards the cost involved in the B.B.C. Empire service are warmly to be welcomed as evidence of goodwill and appreciation ; but we consider that the Empire service should be recognised as an important normal function of the broadcasting organisation in this country.120. The news bulletins which form part of this service are the subject of agreements with the Empire Press which appear satis-factory, and we do not suggest any change in this respect at the present time. We should regret to see any further limitation imposed either upon the time or extent of these messages or upon their subject matter. For the re-broadcasting of news bulletins or other matter which may be the subject of copyright, the consent of the holders of the copyright is required, but it may be hoped that this will not be a source of difficulty. The B.B.C. for its own part imposes no restrictions on the relaying or re-broadcasting of any Empire broadcast or on publication of the programmes in Empire papers.
121. We recommend that the Empire service should be expressly authorised in the new Charter, and that the additional funds required for its development should be provided by the Corporation from its increased share of licence receipts.122. In the interest of British prestige and influence in world affairs, we think that the appropriate use of languages other than English should be encouraged.123. We trust that the effect of these recommendations will be to foster mutual understanding within the British Commonwealth of Nations and beyond it.TELEVISION BROADCASTING124. The field of Television broadcasting has recently been reviewed by a Committee under the Chairmanship of Lord Selsdon, whose report was presented to Parliament in January, 1935, and approved by the Government. That Report shows that licences for research and experimental work had been issued for some time past, with the intention that as soon as public transmissions were justified the B.B.C. should afford facilities for a trial service on a limited scale, and that since the autumn of 1929 experimental transmissions have been given by the Baird Company both independently and in conjunction with the B.B.C. During the past year Television broadcasts occupied two periods weekly (of 30 to 45 minutes), with accompanying sound on a separate wavedength. These broadcasts have now been discontinued in view of the impending introduction of a public service.125. In accordance with recommendations in the same Report, the Government has decided that the B.B.C. shall be charged with the duty of conducting a Television broadcasting service, and the Television Advisory Committee has been constituted, under the Chairmanship of Lord Selsdon, to assist you and the Corporation in the &quot; planning and guiding &quot; of this new service.126. You are therefore aware of the progress up to date, and we accordingly content ourselves with recording that the Alexandra Palace has been selected as the site for the London Station, from which transmissions are to take place with apparatus supplied by Baird Television Ltd. and the Marconi-E.M.I. Television Company Ltd., respectively, under more or less competitive conditions ; that contracts for the supply of this apparatus have been placed ; that installation is in progress ; and that it is hoped to start test trans-missions in March, to be followed by a regular public service as soon as the tests are completed. It will presumably be desirable specific-ally to empower the B.B.C. to broadcast visual images, as well as sound.1 Cmd. 4793.
127. As regards finance, we find ourselves in the same difficulty which faced the Television Committee in their Report,1 namely, that at this stage it is wholly impossible to forecast over a number of years the expenditure likely to be incurred upon this service, since that depends upon a host of unknown factors. We are, however, informed that in the opinion of the Television Advisory Committee the cost of providing the proposed London station and a service therefrom up to the 31st of December, 1936, is likely to coincide approximately with the estimate of  180,000 given in the Television Committee&apos;s report. We can therefore only recommend that the position should again be considered in the autumn of 1936, when the Advisory Committee will have had the experience of some six months&apos; working of the London Station and when accordingly they hope to be in a position to forecast the probable expenditure up till the end of 1938. That would therefore seem to be a more appropriate moment to determine the general methods of finance and, in par-ticular, whether any special licence fee is to be imposed upon the users of this service or whether it is to continue to be &quot; thrown in &quot; with the ordinary 10s. licence. On this point, we will only observe that, while the imposition of a special licence has considerable logical justification, it is evident that, at least for some years, it cannot possibly provide more than a fraction of the cost of the service.128. We may, however, add that, in recommending that the balance of wireless licence revenue accruing to the Exchequer should be regarded as potentially available in future years for the purposes of broadcasting (paragraph 69), we had in view, apart from other possible contingencies, that Television broadcasting is likely to require increasing funds, and that a further proportion of the net receiving licence revenue might well be used towards this purpose, over and above the 75 per cent, now recommended to be utilised for sound broadcasting. We should add that it will be obvious that no hard and fast line can be drawn between Television broad-casting and ordinary broadcasting expenditure, since with the development of the former a considerable and increasing portion of annual expenditure will become common to both types of service.129. We think it well to point out that what has been entrusted by His Majesty&apos;s Government to the B.B.C. is the conduct of a &quot; public broadcast service of Television,&quot;2 and that other applica-tions of this new art, such as the transmission for commercial purposes of visual images from point to point, remain entirely within the sole competence and control of the Postmaster General.lCmd. 4793.2 Cmd. 4793, paragraph 3.8,
RELAY EXCHANGES130. Relay Exchanges are organisations for receiving broadcast programmes and distributing them over a local wire net-work to subscribers ; they are not allowed to originate any programmes or (except within strict limits) any announcement. The first Exchanges were licensed by the Post Office in 1927 ; five years ago there were about 60 Exchanges with 14,000 subscribers ; there are now approxi-mately 340 Exchanges with more than 200,000 subscribers. The system appeals specially to those who find wireless reception difficult or who wish to avoid the expense of buying, or the trouble of looking after, a wireless set. It requires at the receiving end a loud-speaker only. Each subscriber must take out the. ordinary broadcast receiving licence, and the charge made for the service is usually about Is. 6d. a week if the subscriber provides his own loud-speaker. For an additional weekly charge a loud-speaker can be obtained on hire-purchase from the relay exchange Company, whose agents call periodically to collect rents and dues.131. The licences first granted for relay exchanges were terminable at the end of 1932. Since then new licences and extensions up to the 31st December, 1936, have been given, but power to terminate the licences on that date has been reserved in order that future policy may be entirely unfettered. The licences include express provision that on their termination the Postmaster General may require the licensee to sell to him such portions of the plant and apparatus as he may specify, at a price &quot; equal to the value thereof at the date of purchase as plant and apparatus in situ exclusive of any allowance or compensation for loss of profit compulsory sale goodwill the cost of raising capital or any other consideration.&quot; Thus all existing relay exchanges are, with the full cognisance of their proprietors from the start, liable to termination of licence and expropriation at the end of 1936.132. We have already remarked that the system is particularly useful to listeners who find wireless reception difficult or who wish to avoid the expense of buying a wireless set or the trouble of looking after it. There are over 200,000 subscribers in this country, and the system is well developed in some countries abroad. We recognise a considerable public value in the system provided that it is conducted under conditions which will ensure its development in the public interest, good technical equipment, and a programme policy in accordance with B.B.C. standards. Present conditions have a contrary effect. A system of separate privately owned exchanges naturally results in the provision of service only to those centres of population where conditions are most favourable for making a profit, whereas the endeavour of a national service would be to meet public needs with as wide a measure of equality as possible.   It is claimed that the apparatus and wiring of the larger
companies arc equal to those of the public telephone service, but many of the undertakings are small and less efficient. We have had evidence from many quarters that the proprietors of relay exchanges are in a position materially to damage the Corporation^ programme policy by taking a large proportion of material from foreign sources, selecting some parts of the Corporation^ programmes and omitting others, and upsetting the balance upon^which those programmes are constructed. Anxiety has been expressed lest the system should be used to disseminate advertisements or betting news from stations abroad, to colour the religious or political outlook of subscribers by a one-sided selection from home programmes, and to lower the level and lessen the impartiality of the broadcast service.133. On the physical side account should be taken of certain factors in addition to those already mentioned. The number of relay exchanges increased by 50 and the number of subscribers by 60,000 during 1934 ; experience abroad suggests the possibility of further extensive transfers from wireless to wire reception. Under private ownership this would involve extensive wiring networks, duplicating the telephone network but uncoordinated with it. There is a prospect of future distribution by trunk lines from the B.B.C. stations to the relay centres, with advantages in improved quality and the avoidance of fading and interference. Such trunk lines should clearly be part of the telephone system and associated with the trunk lines at present set aside for the use of the B.B.C. A similar arrangement is already in use in certain countries abroad. There is also a prospect of the future local distribution of broadcast programmes over the telephone system itself by means of high-frequency carrier currents which could convey two or more alterna-tive programmes without in any way interfering with the normal use of the telephone. We have heard evidence, too, as to possible distrhmtion by similar means over electric light and power mains. We see no good purpose in the independent development of these various methods of broadcasting by wire, but consider that the time has come for unification and coordinated development in the hands of the Post Office.134. We recommend that the ownership and operation of Relay Exchanges should be undertaken by the Post Office and the control of their programmes by the Corporation. The considerations on which we base these conclusions are in brief those which have led to the establishment of the postal, telegraph, and telephone services, and indeed the broadcasting service itself, as unified national undertakings in public ownership and control.135. It should be understood that, though the prospects of wire broadcasting are promising, the lines of development are not yet certain. The audio-frequency method used by the existing exchanges has the great advantage of requiring in the subscribers premises jiothing more than a. switch and a loud-speaker ; but it involves
special wiring from the exchange to the subscriber. If, on the other hand, the telephone or electricity network is utilised, the need for additional wiring in the streets is greatly reduced, but the subscriber must have a receiving set and electric power (or accumulator and batteries), as well as a loud-speaker. Whatever method or methods of supply may be used, the best prospects for the future lie in a system managed centrally and in conjunction with the telephone. Though extension to rural areas and other districts where the number of subscribers obtainable is small will necessarily be a matter of time, the Post Office is the organisation best qualified, by reason both of its traditional policy and of its equipment, to solve the problems arising.136. We do not suggest that any responsibility for the choice of programmes to be relayed should rest with the Post Office. It seems clear to us that the control of the programmes for the relay system, as well as for the broadcasting system as a whole, should be in the hands of the B.B.C. We regard it as incumbent on the B.B.C. to take into consideration any desire of the subscribers for a selection from foreign programmes.MISCELLANEOUS137. Publications. We have heard evidence as to the nature and subject-matter of the B.B.C. publications and as to the policy followed in regard to them. We regard the present system as satis-factory : the B.B.C. has hitherto observed reasonable limits in the exercise of its powers and we have no reason to suppose that it will do otherwise.   We do not recommend any alteration.138. Electrical interference. The increasing use of electric apparatus-tus for transport, domestic, and commercial purposes is a growing-cause of interference with wireless reception. In the course of a year the Post Office investigates as many as 40,000 complaints, and&quot; in a large and growing number of instances (about 24,000 at present) faulty reception is found in fact to be due to this cause. A satis-factory remedy can sometimes be applied at the listeners premises, but in other cases the trouble cannot be removed except at the source.139. The practice of the Post Office is to investigate the&quot;complaints and point out what action is required. Usually the appropriate remedy is to add a small piece of apparatus, either to the interfering-instrument at the expense of its owner, or to the wireless receiving set at the expense of the listener. The cost usually ranges from 5s. to  1 ; but in the case of certain special types of electrical apparatus the application of corrective measures may cost as much as  20 or even  50.   Most of these troubles are settled in accordance
with Post Office recommendations ; but in about 4,000 cases in a year, where the listener for his part has no effective means of remedy-ing the trouble, the owner or user of the interfering apparatus declines to take action or to incur the necessary expenditure. Com-pulsory powers are at present lacking.140. We trust that the technical investigations and discussions of this matter, which have extended over two years, will be com-pleted as soon as possible ; and if the result is to show that the Postmaster General (or other appropriate Minister) needs further powers for the purpose of protecting the listener, subject to suitable safeguards, we trust that the requisite powers will be sought.141. Wireless receiving sets. It is not easy to make an exact comparison between the prices of receiving sets in one country and in another, but it seems fair to say that the average price for a set of medium quality in this country is somewhat high. We are informed that in Germany, by co-operation between the broadcasting authority and the wireless trade, a standardised receiver has been designed and is sold at a low fixed price, and that this procedure has enabled a larger proportion of the population to become listeners. A similar procedure in this country might well be of benefit to the poorer classes, and would be in accordance with our recommendation regarding sets for use in schools (paragraph 106). We suggest that its adoption should be seriously considered by the B.B.C. and the wireless trade.142. Inconsiderate -use of loud-speakers. We sympathise with protests which have been brought to our notice against the inconsiderate use of loud-speakers in houses, flats, and vehicles, in gardens and streets, on rivers, and in riverside and country resorts. We find that the Home Office has issued a form of byelaw (repro-duced in Appendix H) for the guidance of local authorities, and we trust that this will be widely adopted in order that the nuisance may be restrained not only by the force of public opinion but if necessary by recourse^to law.SUMMARY OF RECOMMENDATIONS 143. Our recommendations are summarised below : (a) CharterThat, in view of the wide-spread approval of the broadcasting service in this country, in which we fully concur, the Charter of the British Broadcasting Corporation should be extended for a term of ten years from the 1st of January, 1937 (para-graphs 7 and 8) ;(b) GovernorsThat the Governors should not be specialists or repre-sentatives of particular interests or localities (paragraph 11) ; and that the outlook of the younger generation should be reflected in some of the appointments made (12) ;
143 (contd.)That the number of Governors should be increased to seven ; that they should be nominated by the Crown, on the recom-mendation of the Prime Minister ; that the normal term of office should be five years ; and a retiring Governor should not be re-nominated (13), that the salary of the Chairman should be  3,000, and of each other member  1,000 (15) ;(c) RegionsThat the present policy of decentralisation (21) and of including a good proportion of regional programme material (25) should be continued ;That Wales should, as soon as possible, be constituted as a distinct broadcasting region (28) ;(d) Staff matters that major staff vacancies should be advertised and appoint-ments made on the recommendation of a specially constituted selection board (35) ;That all facilities should be given for any representative organisation which the staff may wish to set up (37 and 38);That the programme stafflshould abstain from any prominent part in public controversy, but that the private lives of the staff should in other respects be free from control by the B.B.C.. (39) ;That a critic of the B.B.C. should not be disqualified from broadcasting (40) ;(e) Advisory Council and Committees That the General Advisory Council should continue and thereshould be a general Advisory Committee in each Region as wellas a full system of central and regional specialist AdvisoryCommittees (44) ; - That the term of appointment should be four years but thereshould be no bar against re-appointment (45) ;That the Committees should be as widely representative ofvaried interests as possible, so that not only experts but thelistening public also and the younger generation in particularshould find a place on them (46) ;(f) ControlThat minor issues, measures of domestic policy, and matters of day-to-day management should be left to the free judgment of the Corporation (49 and 51) ;That the Minister responsible in respect of broad questions of policy and culture should be a selected Cabinet Minister in the House of Commons, free from heavy Departmental respon-sibilities and preferably a senior member of the Government ; that this Minister should have the right of veto over programmes,
143 (contd.) dcbc*ry*h^U ^and the duty of presenting &quot;the Broadcasting Estimates 4e Parliament; but that technical control should remain with the Postmaster General (53 and 56) ;That the B.B.C. should have the right to state when it is broadcasting an announcement at the request of a Government Department (54) ;That the right of direct Government control in case of major national emergencjf should be maintained (57);(g) FinanceThat the licence fee should remain at 10s. (58) ; That the share of licence revenue allocated to the Post Office should be a percentage to cover costs, reviewed every two years(61);That the share of the remaining net revenue to be allocated to the B.B.C., for purposes other than Television, should be not less than 75 per cent, of current receipts (67 and 68) ;That the balance should be regarded as potentially available for the needs of broadcasting, and that when all needs have been met any surplus remaining may equitably be assigned to the State (69) ;That the Exchequer share for the year 1936 should be limited to  1,050,000 (exclusive of the Income Tax payable by the B.B.C.) (70) ;That payments to authors and composers should be generous (71), and that fees payable in respect of copyright, etc., should be settled, in default of agreement, by arbitration (72) ;That capital expenditure should be defrayed from surpluses of revenue over current expenditure, but the limit of short-term borrowing might be raised to  1,000,000 ; and that major items of contemplated capital expenditure should be stated when the Broadcasting Estimates are presented to Parliament (74) ;That current expenditure should be shown in a limited degree of detail in the Annual Account, and supplementary particulars be given in the Annual Report (76) ;(h) Editorial comments That, continuing present practice, the B.B.C. should refrain from broadcasting its own opinions on current affairs (79) ;(i) NewsThat the broadcast news service should be unbiassed and dispassionate (80 and 83) ; that the B.B.C. should have a free choice as to the sources and methods of obtaining news (82) ; that existing arrangements are satisfactory but there should be no bar to variations for the purpose of meeting such demands as the future may bring (84) ;
(j) controversyThat controversial broadcasts should continue, discretion remaining in the hands of the B.B.C. (85 and 86) ;(k) Political broadcastingThat attention should be directed towards Parliament as the natural centre of political interest (90), that Parliamentary news should hold its place in the news bulletins, and that, if broadcasts by a Parliamentary observer are continued, the observer should be provided with adequate facilities (91) ;That the B.B.C. should regularly consult the Parliamentary parties on major political issues (92);That during a General Election campaign the time available for political speeches should be allotted by agreement between the parties (93), and that all political broadcasting should cease three days before the Poll (94);(1) MusicThat, as hitherto, B.B.C. orchestras should be used freely in the studios and considerately in public, concerts, and the best performances by other organisations should be relayed (96);That the wider cultivation of music should also be assisted by collaboration in various other ways with outside institutions (97);That light music selected for broadcasting should be of first-class quality and directed to the improvement of public taste (98);(m)]Sunday programmes That one of the alternative Sunday programmes should be such as to appeal widely to serious listeners, and the other should be of a lighter and more popular character (100) ;(n) School broadcasting That wireless receiving apparatus should in our opinion come to be regarded as part of the normal equipment of every school (101) ;That broadcasting to schools, in England, Scotland and Wales, respectively, should be controlled by independent Councils, the B.B.C. continuing to bear the cost within reasonable limits (102) ;That one or more types of receiving set for use in schools might be specially designed, ordered in quantity by Local Education Authorities, and manufactured at a low price (106) ;That arrangements for the maintenance of school sets might normally be made with local dealers (107) ;
(o) AdvertisementThat direct advertisement should remain excluded from the broadcast service (109) ;That &quot; sponsored &quot; items need not be entirely excluded, especially in the earliest stages of Television broadcasting, but that their admission should be carefully regulated by the B.B.C. (111 and 112) ;That the responsible Departments should take all the steps which are within their power with a view to preventing the broadcasting from foreign stations of advertisement programmes, intended for this country, to which objection has been taken (114) ;(p) Empire broadcasting That the Empire service should receive express authorisation and should be fostered and developed (117 and 121) ;  and that the appropriate use of languages other than English should be encouraged (122) ;(q) Television broadcasting That Television broadcasting should be expressly authorised (126) ;That its finance for two years ahead should be reconsidered by the Television Advisory Committee in the autumn of 1936 (127) ;That Television should have a claim upon a proportion of the surplus remaining after deduction of 75 per cent, of the net revenue from licences (128) ;(r) Relay Exchanges That the ownership and operation of relay exchanges (134) and the technical development of wire broadcasting in general (135) should be undertaken by the Post Office, and the control of relayed programmes by the B.B.C. (136) ;(s) PublicationsThat no change is called for in respect of B.B.C. publications (137) ;(t) Electrical interference That the technical investigation of interference with broad-cast reception should be expedited, and compulsory limiting powers sought if necessary (140) ;(u) Receiving sets That the B.B.C. and the wireless trade should jointly examine the possibility of designing and putting on sale at a low fixed price a standard receiving set (141) ;
a Subject to the annexed reservation concerning paragraphs 111 and 112.^ Subject to the annexed reservations concerning paragraphs 12, 38, 57, 81-82, 91, and 93-94.c Subject to the annexed reservation concerning paragraph 141.* Subject to the annexed reservation concerning paragraph 74.e Subject to the annexed reservation concerning paragraphs 132-135.(v) Loud-speaker nuisance That local authorities should take powers in approved form to deal with annoyance due to the persistent misuse of loud speakers, etc. (142).144. Conclusion. We wish to express our thanks to the many correspondents who have addressed us and to the witnesses who have so readily helped us with information and advice. We acknowledge in particular the valuable assistance given us by the Post Office and other Government Departments, and we are especially grateful to the Governors and officers of the B.B.C., who spared no pains in providing us with the fullest information.145. We cannot conclude our report without putting on record our high appreciation of the services of our Secretary, Mr. H. G. G. Welch, of the General Post Office, whose knowledge and assiduity were invaluable to your Committee both during the examination of the witnesses and m the preparation of our report.(Signed)   ULLSWATER (Chairman). J. J. ASTOR a-C. R. ATTLEE h- c-CLEMENT DAVIES c-ELTON a&apos; c-WILLIAM McLINTOCK^-STELLA READING. SELSDON e-GRAHAM WHITE a-H, G. GORDON WELCH (Secretary). 31st December, 1935.
RESERVATION BY LORD ELTON, MAJOR ASTOR, AND MR. GRAHAM WHITEWe cannot agree that the admission of &quot; sponsored &quot; items  that is, items provided by private persons or organisations whose names are announced in the programme is either necessary or desirable. The costs of a public service such as Television should be met out of public funds. And in making our financial recom-mendations we have in fact expressly stated that we &quot; had in view, apart from other possible contingencies, that Television broadcasting is likely to require increasing funds&quot; ($ 128). This being so, the Television service should surely be able to develop adequately without any dependence upon financial contributions from private firms in search of publicity. The similar power of admitting &quot; sponsored &quot; programmes reserved during the early stages of sound broadcasting has in fact been used so little that it may be said to have proved superfluous. In the future of Television broadcasting it may well prove equally superfluous. On the other hand, it is possible that extensive recourse may be had to these subventions from private sources : in which case, since it is obvious that it will be increasingly difficult to draw a hard and fast line between Television and sound broadcasting, there is a real danger that advertisement may intrude itself over the whole range of B.B.C. programmes. We believe that this would be contrary both to the public interest and to the wishes of a great majority of listeners.(Signed) ELTON.J. J. ASTOR. GRAHAM WHITE.RESERVATIONS BY MR. ATTLEEWhile I am in general agreement with my colleagues in their views on the manner in which the British Broadcasting Corporation has carried out the duties entrusted to it in the past and on the recom-mendations made for the future, I find it necessary to make the following reservations.Paragraph 12. In my view it is undesirable that the Governors should be drawn solely from persons whose social experience and background is that of the well-to-do classes. It is one of the functions of the Board to represent the general public for whom the Corporation caters. If the Governors represent the general outlook of a minority only, this function will not be properly fulfilled.
I desire to emphasize the desirability of including among the Governors persons who share the outlook of the younger generations. Hitherto the average age of the Board has been too high, with a consequent over-emphasis on the outlook of the past. While experience of affairs is desirable, there must be also an alert appreciation of possibilities of new developments and of the changing conditions of the time. Other things being equal, the majority of the Governors should be persons in the prime of life. I recommend that there should be a definite provision for retirement at sixty. This rule should also apply to the Board&apos;s officers.Without in any way reflecting upon the capacity and impartiality of those who have held the office, I think it undesirable that in practice the Chairmanship should be regarded as a suitable post for a politician who has retired from full activity.Paragraph 38. I do not regard the present attitude of the Corporation towards Staff Representation as at all satisfactory. While it is stated that no inquiry is made as to whether or not an employee belongs to a trade union, it is my clear impression that trade unionism is not encouraged and that the general tendency is in the direction of autocracy and paternalism. I consider that the Staff should be given full opportunities for ventilating any grievances collectively, that the B.B.C. should definitely recognise the right of every employee to join an appropriate union and that a proper system of consultation and collective agreement should be instituted.Paragraph 57. The control of the B.B.C. by the State in an emergency is obviously necessary, but there is a point where it is difficult to decide whether the emergency is really that of the State or of the Government as representing the political party in power. The outstanding instance is that of the coal mining dispute of 1926. In my opinion there is no doubt that the way in which the broad-casting system was used by the Government of the day created in the minds of a very large section of the community grave suspicion which has prejudiced the Corporation ever since. The B.B.C. should have sufficient independence to resist being made the instrument of one side in a national controversy. Where the Government definitely takes over, the listening public should be informed that the Corporation is no longer responsible. A difficult situation is likely to arise should this country ever find itself engaged in war. Hitherto in time of war there has been no absolute suppression of all adverse criticism in the Press. Broadcasting is now of equal if not greater importance in the formation of public opinion than the newspaper. I think that even in war-time the B.B.C. must be allowed to broadcast opinions other than those of the Government.
Paragraphs 81-82. In my view it would be desirable that in course of time the B.B.C. should build up its own news service or take over the existing.agencies. An impartial agency would serve the purpose of the newspapers, which could make the selection as they do at present, while it could enable the B.B.C. to give the public fair and impartial information.Paragraph 88. Political Broadcasting. While I agree that on the whole the B.B.C. has endeavoured to hold the scales even between the various political parties, there have been outstanding instances to the contrary.During the economic crisis of 1931 a series of tendencious talks, all making for one point of view, was given, and the whole tendency of broadcasting throughout this period was in support of the policy of the National Government. It is just on occasions when there is a division of opinion in the country that it is most necessary for the B.B.C. to act impartially. In my view there was a serious failure to do this throughout the second half of the year 1931.I consider that in conducting political broadcasting, the B.B.C. should follow out as fully as possible the practice that prevails in the House of Commons. When a speech is made on behalf of the Government, the official Opposition&apos; should have the right to reply, and other sections should be given such opportunities of expressing their opinion as may be due to their importance. This has not been done in the past. On many occasions the Government of the day have been allowed to make broadcast speeches of a political character without the Opposition being given any opportunity to reply. It is of very little use to suggest that some days after an. opportunity might be given. It is essential for real political discussion that statements made should be replied to at once. The B.B.C. should also exercise great care in deciding the occasions which in the interests of the country call for a ministerial statement to be made, for there have been instances where broadcasts, professedly based on the need of giving information to the general public, were in fact merely partisan speeches.Paragraph 91. I am not in agreement with the practice of sending a reporter to Parliamentary debates in order that he may on the same evening broadcast an account. I do not believe that it is possible to find a person who can at the same time give a vivid per-sonal impression and free his mind from political bias. The experi-ment in this direction made by the B.B.C. does, I think, bear out this point of view, and I am of the opinion that it should not be repeated.Paragraphs 93-94. Broadcasting during a General Election.  While I agree with the recommendations of my colleagues as to the control of broadcasting during a General Election, and while I recognise that in the General Election, of 1935 the practice suggested
was actually carried out, it is necessary to recall that in 1931 the Government of the day were given far too large a proportion of broadcast talks, were allowed to give a final talk in circumstances which did not. admit of mis-statements being corrected before the poll, and that there was a serious lapse on the part of an announcer who suggested to the electors the importance of voting in terms strongly reminiscent of a slogan of one side in the contest. As pointed out above, it is essential when political feelings are roused that the B.B.C. must be most careful to preserve impartiality. The B.B.C. members should be persons of sufficient independence to resist the specious plea of a &quot; national emergency.&quot;(Signed) C. R. ATTLEE.RESERVATION BY MR. ATTLEE, LORD ELTON, AND MR. CLEMENT DAVIESParagraph 141. When a public service is established, it is, we think, necessary that, the public interest should predominate throughout the whole range. If private profit is allowed a loophole, a proportion of the advantage of the system will be lost to the com-munity. The weak spot of broadcasting is in the provision of receiv-ing sets by private industr3r. There are strong trade organisations although there is still a considerable amount of competition. Evidence has been given that there is a combination in the manufacture of valves which keeps prices unnecessarily high. There are obviously-further possibilities of the formation of other associations. The position in regard to the provision of service by retailers is also unsatisfactory.We understand that the B.B.C. has in fact the power to manu-facture and provide receiving sets which are technically receiving stations. We consider that the B.B.C. should make an enquiry at the earliest possible moment into the possibility of either using this power itself or, perhaps preferably, coming to an arrangement with the Post Office for manufacturing receiving sets and supplying them to the public.(Signed) C. R. ATTLEE. ELTON.CLEMENT DAVIES.
RESERVATION BY SIR WILLIAM McLINTOCKParagraph 74. I dissent from the two statements which are combined in the last sentence of this paragraph. In the first place I have not observed in the evidence brought before us any criticism of the capital expenditure incurred by the Corporation in the past. Secondly, I do not think it advisable that the hands of the Corpora-tion should be tied in making their arrangements for future capital expenditure by having to submit schemes to Parliament before embarking on them.(Signed) WILLIAM McLINTOCK.RESERVATION BY LORD SELSDONI disagree with the conclusions and recommendations in paragraphs 132-135 that the ownership and operation of existing wireless exchanges should forthwith be transferred to the Post Office. In my view, the future development of this type of service in suitable areas is likely to be found in the use of high-frequency rather than audio-frequency. The latter has definite limitations as regards quality of reproduction and normally requires a separate pair of wires for each programme offered. The former makes use of carrier circuits superimposed on telephone lines (without interfering with the normal use of the latter), is adapted to give real high-fidelity reproduction, and can provide for three, or even more, alternative programmes and possibly also for the much higher frequencies required for Television. Moreover, it appears probable that, at least in certain areas, arrangements could be made to give non-telephone subscribers the benefit of such a service.These potentialities are now being studied and, having regard to the progress already made, I think it would be in the highest degree improvident for the State now to incur the heavy cost of taking over from the existing relay companies plant and apparatus much of which will, if my view is correct, rapidly become obsolete. Moreover, in such an event, it would be difficult for the State to discontinue any existing service, even in an unsuitable area, and it would stand committed to the maintenance .of both audio- and high-frequency systems with consequent duplication and expense.I therefore recommend that the licensing system be continued for audio-frequency relay exchanges for two years from 31st December, 1936, and that any future licences should be granted only up to 31st December, 1938. It should be made abundantly clear on the face of the licence that at the expiry of that period the Post-master General has the right, but not the obligation, to acquire all or any portion of the Companies&apos; plant at its value as apparatus
in situ, but without any other element of compensation whatsoever and especially without compensation for severance. In the interval the Post Office should actively prosecute the development of high-frequency and, if experimental results justify it, establish a service in suitable areas, even though this involves for the moment some duplication. In my opinion this course will, in the final event, be better for the listener and cheaper for the State.I am not much impressed by the contention that such maintenance of the existing arrangements impairs the &quot; programme balance &quot; of the B.B.C. The owner of an ordinary wireless set has within the limits of the power and selectivity of his set full freedom to receive B.B.C. or foreign programmes at will, and I do not see why, within reasonable limits, a similar freedom should not be vicariously enjoyed by subscribers to exchanges. There must, of course, be some limits set in the licence in order to prevent possible abuse; e.g., it might be prescribed that if one of a set of talks or speeches be given, the whole series must be included. Further, it should be definitely laid down that, during British Broadcasting hours, all stations *shall relay one of the B.B.C. programmes, whether they provide an alternative programme or not. I see no valid reason for &quot; censoring &quot; (except in regard to propaganda) the&apos;make-up of such alternative programmes or of material broadcast out of British hours. After all, the relay Companies, if they are&apos;to succeed, must give their public what that public wants and, in r trying so to do, they have the advantage that, by measuring the relative loads, they can estimate with some approximation to accuracy how many of their subscribers are listening at any given moment to one or other of two altei-native programmes.(Signed) SELSDON.
APPENDIX Alist op witnesses and of organisations representedGeneral Post office treasury. . Foreign Office   . . Colonial^Office  . .Board of Educationf Col. Sir Donald Banks, K.C.B., D.S.O., M.C. j F. W. Phillips, Esq., C.M.G. &apos; 1 Sir Henry N. Bunbury, K.C.B. [Lt. Col. A. G. Lee, O.B.E., M.C., M.I.E.E. /Sir Warren Fisher, G.C.B., G.C.V.O., D.C.L. &quot; \F. P. Robinson, Esq.R. W. A. Leeper, Esq., C.M.G., C.B.B. &quot;R. V. Vernon, Esq., C.B. E. B. Bowyer, Esq. /S. H. Wood, Esq., M.C. \E. G. Savage, Esq., C.B.Scottish Education Department!&apos; J. W. Peck, Esq., C.B.British broadcasting corporation.Australian BroadcastingCommission.National Council of LabourWelsh Parliamentary PartyWestminster CatholicFederationReuters/Ltd.Press Association, Ltd. Exchange TelegraphCompany, Ltd. Central News, Ltd. ..Governorsf Rt. Hon. Viscount Bridgeman, D.L., J.P.(Chairman). R. C. Norman, Esq. (Vice-Chairman). Harold G. Brown, Esq., B.A., LL.B. Mrs. Mary A. Hamilton. Rt. Hon. H. A. L. Fisher,F.R.S.,^&apos;LL.D., DXitt.Director-General Sir J. C. W. Reith, G.B.E., D.C.L., LL.D.ControllersVice-Admiral Sir Charles D. Carpendale,C.B.Col. A. G. C. Dawnay, C.B.E., D.S.O.Regional Directors P. F. Edgar, Esq., O.B.E. (Midland). Melville Dinwiddie, Esq., O.B.E., D.S.O.,M.C., M.A., B.D. (Scottish). E. G. D. Liveing, Esq., M.A. (North).Director of Music Dr. AdrianX. Boult, Mus.Doc.,[LL.D.Arthur Mason, Esq.fRt. Hon. Arthur Greenwood, M.P. \Sir Walter McL. Citrine, K.B.E. / Capt. R. T. Evans, M.P. \D. R. Grenfell, Esq., M.P.W. J. 0&apos;Donovan, Esq., O.B.E., M.D., M.P. Rev. Bernard E. Grimley, D.D., Ph.D. f Sir Roderick Jones^K-BX. \W.JL. Murray, Esq.^ H. C. Robbins, Esq. Sir Wilfred^King.H. Herbert, Esq.
JRoyal College of Music . .    Sir Hugh P. Allen, G.C.V.O., D.Mus.4 Royal Academy of Music . .    Sir John B. McEwen, D.Mus.I Guildhall School of Music . .    Sir Landon Ronald., . . , fMajor Ian Hay Beith, C.B.E., M.C.Incorporated       Society of J xhomas F. Dunhill, Esq.Authors,    Playwrights   and^ H- p RubinsteiU) Esq 4Composers. [w. A/Euller, Esq.t, ,      r,    .       . j. fT. Graham Young, Esq.Relay Services Association of I   H Lyon, Esq Great Britain. I T t? m;      ^StRadio Manufacturers&apos;Association,J. E. Morris, Esq.J. H. Williams, Esq. W. W. Burnham, Esq. D. Grant Strachan, Esq.-r, ... -i y     , .  , n . ,     t I,    /B. Welbourn, Esq., M.I.E.E. British Insulated Cables, Ltd.   ^Capt p p Eckersley, M.I.E.E.Incorporated Society of British jjwj!! G^wSburtoh. Advertisers. ^Alan whitworthj Esq.International   Broadcasting   Capt. L. F. Plugge, M.P. Company, Ltd.andSir Thomas&quot; Beecham, Bt.Sir Harry Brittain, K.B.E., C.M.G.Sir H. Walford Davies, C.V.O., O.B.E., Mus.Doc, LL.D. Sir Hamilton Harty, Mus.Doc.Empire Press Union    . .       . .   Sir Stanley Reed, K.B.E., LL.D.(Southam Newspapers ofCanada)   A. C. Cummings, Esq.(Australian PressAssociation).   Taylor Darbyshire, Esq.(Argus South AfricanNewspapers).   N. K. Kerney, Esq.H. E. Turner, Esq., C.B.E. (Secretary).(&quot;The Hon. Esmond C. Harmsworth. Newspaper Proprietors&apos; J Col. the Hon. E. F. Lawson,Association.&quot;) D.S.O., M.C., T.D.[Sir Thomas McAra.. , (&quot;Sir Tames G. Owen.Newspaper Society .. \E. W. Davies, Esq.^  .  ,.   , ^   .,     - , f Lord Iliffe, C.B.E.Periodical Trade   Press and   Edward EvanSj Esq.Weekly Newspaper Pro-^ g c Huggill, Esq.proprietors&apos; Association. (,E.rO. Norton, Esq.(&quot;Leslie Boosey, Esq. Performing Right Society, Ltd.-^ C. F. James, Esq.[G. H. Hatchman, Esq.sir Edward C. Bairstow, D.Mus., F.R.C.O. Incorporated Society of J George Dyson, Esq.,Musicians.&quot;) D.Mus., F.R.C.M., F.R.C.O.[Frank Eames, Esq.
THE BRITISH BROADCASTING CORPORATIONROYAL CHARTER OF INCORPORATIONGEORGE THE FIFTH by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and of the British Dominions beyond the Seas KING, Defender of the Faith, EMPEROR OF INDIA,TO ALL TO WHOM THESE PRESENTS SHALL COME GREETING&quot;:WHEREAS it&apos;has been represented to Us by THE RIGHT HONOURABLE SIR WILLIAM &quot;LOWSON MITCHELL-THOMSON Baronet K.B.E., M.P., Our Postmaster General that the Broadcasting Committee appointed by him to advise as to the proper scope of the Broadcasting Service and as to the management control and finance thereof after the expiry of the existing Licence on the 31st day of December 1926 has after sufficient enquiry and due deliberation recommended that the Broadcasting Service hitherto carried on by the British Broadcasting Company Limited should after the expiration of the Company&apos;s Licence on the said 31st day of December 1926 be conducted by a public corporation acting as Trustees for the national interest,AND WHEREAS it has been made to appear to Us that more than two million persons in Our Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland have applied for and taken out Licences to instal and work apparatus for wireless telegraphy for the purpose of receiving Broadcast programmes AND WHEREAS in view of the widespread interest which is thereby shown to be taken by Our People in the Broadcasting Service and of the great value of the Service as a means of education and entertainment, We deem it desirable that the Service should be developed and exploited to the best advantage and in the national interest,AND WHEREAS We believe that it would greatly promote these objects and be for the public benefit if a Corporation charged with these duties were created by the exercise of Our Royal Prerogative,NOW KNOW YE that We being desirous of promoting the establishment and organisation of the said Corporation have by Our Royal Prerogative and of Our special grace certain knowledge and mere motion given and granted and by this Our Charter for Us Our Heirs and Successors DO HEREBY give and grant as follows : Incorporation1. THE RIGHT HONOURABLE GEORGE HERBERT HYDE EARL OF CLARENDON, THE    RIGHT    HONOURABLE    JOSEPH    ALBERT    BARON GAINFORD,SIR JOHN GORDONjiNAIRNE, BARONET,Dr. MONTAGUE JOHN KENDALL, M.A.,j[LL.D., and mrs. ETHEL SNOWDENand all other persons who may pursuant to this Our Charter become members of the Corporation established by this Our Charter shall be a body corporate by the name of THE BRITISH BROADCASTING CORPORATION with perpetual succession and a common seal with power to break, alter and renew the same at discretion ; willing and ordaining that the said body corporate hereinafter referred to as &quot; the Corporation &quot;) shall andmay^sue and be
sued in all Courts and be capable in law to take and hold real or personal property and do all matters and things incidental or pertaining to a body corporate, but so that the Corporation shall apply the whole of its surplus revenue (if any) and other income solely in promoting its objects. The members of the Corporation are hereinafter referred to as &quot; Governors.&quot;Term of Charter2. THE Corporation shall be established for a term of Ten years commencing from the 1st day of January 1927.Objects of the corporation . THE objects for which the Corporation is established and incorporated are :  J(a) To carry on a Broadcasting Service within Our United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland (but not including therein the Irish Free State) the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man and for that purpose to acquire from time to time from Our Postmaster General for the time being a Licence or Licences in such form, and subject to such terms and conditions as he may from time to time prescribe, for the erection, establishment, maintenance and operation within Our Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man of stations as a public utility service for the broadcasting to the public by means of wireless telephony of any matter which for the time being may be permitted by or be within the scope or ambit of any such Licence ; and to develop and exploit the said broadcasting service and any such Licence as aforesaid in any such other directions and by any such other means and methods as may for the time being be permitted by Our Postmaster General for the time being and from time to time to obtain or agree to a renewal or extension of or any modifications of the terms and conditions contained in any such licence as aforesaid as Our Post-master General may from time to time be willing to grant or agree to.(b) To acquire on such terms as may be agreed, arranged or sanctioned any undertaking, stations, plant and assets which may be necessary or convenient for carrying out the objects of the Corporation.(c) To erect, equip and instal stations with all such plant, machinery and other effects as may be requisite or convenient to permit of the same effectively receiving and transmitting for broadcasting purposes.(d) To compile and prepare, print, publish, issue, circulate and distribute, whether gratis or otherwise, such papers, magazines, periodicals, books, circulars and other literary matter as may seem conducive to any of the objects of the Corporation.(e) To collect news of and information relating to current events in any part of the world and in any manner that may be thought fit and to establish and subscribe to news-agencies.(/) To acquire by registration, purchase or otherwise, copyrights in any literary, musical and artistic works, plays, songs, gramophone records, news and other matter and any trade-marks and. trade names and to use, exercise, develop, grant licences in respect of, or otherwise turn to account the same with a view to the furtherance of any of the objects of the Corporation.(g) To purchase or otherwise acquire and turn to account in any manner that may be thought fit any Letters Patent or patent rights or any interest in any Letters Patent or patent rights, brevets d&apos;invention, licences, concessions, and the like conferring an exclusive or non-exclusive or limited right to use any secret or. other information as to any invention in relation to any device or machine serving or calculated to serve any useful purpose in connection with any of the objects of the Corporation.
(h) Subject as hereinafter provided- to enter into any arrangement with any governments or authorities, supreme, municipal, local, or otherwise that may seem conducive to the Corporation^ objects or any of them, and to obtain from any such government or authority any rights, privileges and concessions which the Corporation may think it desirable to obtain, and to carry out, exercise and comply with any such arrange-ments, rights, privileges and concessions.(i) To establish and support or aid in the establishment and support of associations, institutions, funds, trusts and conveniences calculated to benefit employees or ex-employees of the Corporation, or the dependants or connections of such persons, and to grant pensions and allowances, and to make payments towards insurances, and to subscribe or guarantee money for charitable or benevolent objects, or for any exhibition, or for any public, general or useful object.(j) To purchase, take on lease, or in exchange, hire or otherwise acquire any real and personal property and any rights or privileges which the Corporation may think necessary or convenient for the purposes of its business or the furtherance of its objects, and in particular any land, buildings, easements, machinery, plant and stock-in-trade.(k) To invest and deal with the moneys of the Corporation not immediately required in such manner as may from time to time be determined.(/) Subject as hereinafter provided to borrow or raise or secure the payment of money in such manner as the Corporation shall think fit, and in particular by mortgage or charge of all or any parts of the property or rights of the Corporation or by the issue of debentures or debenture stock, charged upon all or any of the Corporation^ property or rights (both present and future), and to purchase, redeem or pay off any such securities. Provided always that the aggregate amount of the moneys so borrowed, raised or secured and for the time being outstanding at any one time shall not exceed ^500,000.(m) To sell, improve, manage, develop, exchange, lease, mortgage, enfranchise, dispose of, turn to account, or otherwise deal with all or any part of the property and rights of the Corporation.(n) To do all such other things as the Corporation may deem incidental or conducive to the attainment of any of the objects or the exercise of any of the powers of the Corporation.Power to Acquire Land4. WE do hereby for Us, Our Heirs and Successors, license, authorise and hereafter enable the Corporation to purchase or otherwise acquire any lands, tenements or hereditaments within Our United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland (but not including therein the Irish Free State), the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man and to hold all or any such lands, tenements or hereditaments or any interest therein in perpetuity or on lease or otherwise and from time to time to grant, devise, alienate or otherwise dispose of or deal with the same or any part thereof. And We do hereby also for Ourselves, Our Heirs and Successors give and grant Our Licence to any person or persons and any body politic or corporate to assure in perpetuity or otherwise or to demise to or for the benefit of the Corporation any lands, tenements or hereditaments or any interest in any lands, tenements or hereditaments whatsoever within the limits aforesaid. But the Corporation is hereby prohibited from acquiring or holding any land situate outside the limits aforesaid or any interest therein.
Restriction on Dominion and Foreign Concessionsr5. WE do hereby declare that the Corporation shall not seek any Concession, right or privilege from or enter into any negotiations or arrangement with any Dominion or -Foreign Government without having first obtained the consent in writing of Our Postmaster General.Organisation]6. (i) THERE shall be a Chairman of the Corporation who shall be entitled to preside at the meetings thereof.(ii) There shall also be a Vice-Chairman of the Corporation who shall be entitled to preside at the meetings thereof in the absence of the Chairman.(iii) The Chairman or other officer authorised by him shall, subject to such regulations as may be made by the Corporation as hereinafter provided, summon all meetings of the Corporation for the despatch of business.(iv) The First Chairman of the Corporation shall be the said Right Honourable George Herbert Hyde, Earl of Clarendon, who shall be entitled to hold office as long as he continues to be a Governor of the Corporation.(v) The first Vice-Chairman of the Corporation shall be the said Right Honourable Joseph Albert Baron Gainford, who shall be entitled to hold office as long as he continues to be a Governor of the Corporation.(vi) If at any time there shall be a vacancy in the office of Chairman or Vice-Chairman of the Corporation it shall be certified to Us by Our Postmaster General under his hand, and such vacancy may be filled at Our will and pleasure by Us in Council and We may determine the period for which and the terms upon which the Chairman or Vice-Chairman so appointed by Us shall hold office.(vii) The chief executive officer of the Corporation shall be called the Director General. The first Director General shall be John Charles Walsham Reith Esquire.7. THE Corporation shall appoint such officers and staff as they may think necessary (including any Director General who may be appointed in succession to the first Director General) for the efficient transaction of their business and shall fix such rates of remuneration, including that of the Director General herein appointed, as they shall think proper. Subject to the provisions of any contract between the Corporation and any officer, the Corporation may remove any officer (other than a Governor) however appointed.8. THE Corporation shall meet for the despatch of business, and shall from time to time make such regulations with respect to the summoning, notice, place, management, and adjournment of such meetings and generally with respect to the transaction and management of their business, as they may think fit, subject to the following conditions : (a) The first meeting of the Corporation shall be held on such day after the date of this Our Charter, and at such place, as may be determined by the Chairman, and, subject to the provisions of this Our Charter, the proceedings at any such first meeting of the Corporation shall be conducted in such manner as may be directed by the Chairman.(6) The quorum for a meeting of the Corporation shall consist of three Governors, or such other number as the Chairman with the concurrence of the Corporation may from time to time declare.(c) Every question shall be decided by a majority of votes of the Governors present and voting on that question. In case of an equality of votes at any meeting the person presiding at such meeting shall have a second or casting vote. A Governor of the Corporation shall not be entitled to vote upon any question respecting his own remuneration except in regard to any remuneration payable under Clause 13 of this Our Charter,
Power to Appoint Committees9. THE Corporation may appoint a Committee or Committees (including District Committees) to advise them with regard to all or any matters connected with the Broadcasting Service and the business operations and affairs of the Corporation. Committees (including District Committees) shall have power to appoint advisory Sub-Committees. Committees shall^be appointed for such purposes and on such conditions as the Corporation may decide. The Corporation may from time to time make regulations with regard to the meetings and proceedings of any such Committees or Sub-Committees, and subject thereto the provisions of this Our Charter with respect to the meetings and proceedings of the Corporation shall mutatis mutandis apply.Governors10. (i) THE first Governors of the Corporation shall subject to the provisions as to disqualification hereinafter contained be entitled to remain in office for five years from the date of their appointment.(ii) GOVERNORS appointed subsequently to those herein appointed shall subject to the provisions as to disqualification hereinafter contained be entitled to remain in office for such period as We may direct which shall not exceed a period of five years.(iii) A retiring Governor shall be eligible for reappointment.(iv) THE number of, Governors. may from time to time be increased by Us in Council.Disaualificationjof Governors11. A Governor of the Corporation shall ipso facto cease to be a Governor thereof (a) If his Governorship be terminated by Us in Council, or(b) If he becomes of unsound mind or bankrupt or compound with his creditors, or(c) If he send in a written resignation of his Governorship to Our Postmaster General, or(d) If he shall absent himself from the meetings of the Corporation continuously for six months without the consent of the Corporation and the Corporation shall resolve that his office be vacated.12. IF and whenever any vacancy shall arise among the Governors of the Corporation by reason of the retirement, resignation, disqualification or death of a Governor or for any other reason it shall be certified to Us by Our Postmaster General under his hand and such vacancy may be filled at Our will and pleasure by Us in Council.r 13. THE Governors of the Corporation may retain by way of remuneration for their services as Chairman, Vice-Chairman or Governor as the case may be out of the revenue of the Corporation such sums (to be deemed to accrue from day to day) as the Corporation may from time to time resolve not exceeding the sums following, that is to say : -To the Chairman ^3,000 per annum.To the Vipe-Chairman ^1,000 per annum.To each of the other Governors per annum.The Governors may in addition retain out of the revenue of the Corporation expenses properly incurred by them in the due performance of their office,
Financial14. THE Corporation is hereby authorised and empowered : (i) To receive all funds which may be granted annually or otherwise by the Legislature in furtherance of the purposes of this Our Charter.(ii) To administer all funds which may be granted as aforesaid and to receive and administer all other sums and revenue which may be obtained by or given to the Corporation or derived from any other source not hereinbefore mentioned exclusively in furtherance of the purposes of this Our Charter, with power, subject to any conditions which may be attached to any such grant or gift, as aforesaid, to treat all such funds either as capital or income at its discretion. Except as in this Our Charter expressly provided no revenue or other moneys derived from any source shall in any event be divided by way of profit or otherwise amongst the Governors of the Corporation.Sinking and Reserve Funds15. (i) WE do hereby declare that in the event of the Corporation exercising the power hereinbefore contained of borrowing or raising money upon the security of or otherwise charging all or any part of its property or rights (otherwise than for the purpose of obtaining temporary Banking accommoda-tion and facilities) it shall set aside yearly out of its revenue and invest in Trustee securities and accumulate as a sinking fund which shall be applied towards the repayment of such moneys and redemption of such securities such sums as in the opinion of the Auditors of the Corporation will be sufficient after bringing into account the estimated value for purposes of redemption of any assets acquired or to be acquired or additions or improvements made or to be made by means of the money so borrowed or raised as aforesaid to provide for the repayment of any sums so borrowed or raised by the Corpora-tion otherwise than as aforesaid and the redemption of any securities for sums so borrowed raised or secured by the Corporation prior to the expiration of the term of this Our Charter or any extension thereof. For the purposes of this Clause assets acquired or additions or improvements made by means of temporary loans repaid out of moneys so borrowed raised or secured as aforesaid shall be deemed to have been acquired or made by means of such last-mentioned moneys.(ii) THE Corporation shall likewise set aside yearly out of its revenue and invest in Trustee Securities and accumulate as a sinking fund such sums (if any) as in the opinion of its Auditors are adequate and proper to meet depreciation or losses or contingencies or to repair maintain or improve any property of the Corporation and such sums may be applied for the purposes aforesaid from time to time in such manner as the Corporation shall determine.(iii) THE Corporation may set aside out of their revenue such sums as they think proper as a reserve fund for such purposes (other than those provided for by the said sinking fund) as the Corporation may think conducive to their objects or any of them, and the same may be applied accordingly from time to time in such manner as the Corporation shall determine, and the Corporation may, without placing the same to reserve, carry over any revenue which they may not require or may think it inexpedient to expend in any year.(iv) THE Corporation may invest the sums so set aside for reserve in pursuance of Sub-Clause (iii) of this Clause upon such securities or investments as they may think fit, and from time to time deal with and vary such invest-ments and dispose of all or any part thereof for the benefit of the Corporation, and divide the reserve fund into such special funds as they think fit, with full power to employ the assets constituting the reserve fund in the business of the Corporation and without being bound to keep the same separate from the other assets.
Annual Report and Statement of Accounts16. (i) The accounts of the Corporation shall be audited annually by an auditor or auditors, who shall be chartered accountants, and shall be approved by Our Postmaster General for the time being.(ii) THE Corporation shall, once in every year at least, prepare a General Report of their proceedings lor the year preceding, and attach thereto a duly certified Statement of Accounts and of the finances of the Corporation.(iii) THE Chairman shall, on the completion of every such annual General Report and Statement of Accounts forthwith submit the same to Our Postmaster General for the time being.(iv) THE Corporation shall at all reasonable times upon demand made give to Our Postmaster General and all other persons nominated by him full liberty to examine the accounts of the Corporation and furnish them with all information and documents which they may require with regard to the receipts and expenditure of the Corporation.General17. (i) THE Corporation may at any time, and from time to time, apply for and accept a Supplemental Charter, or an Act of Parliament, if it appears to it that such Supplemental Charter or Act of Parliament is required for carrying into effect any of the purposes or powers of this Our Charter.(ii) No act or proceeding of the Corporation, or of any Committee established by the Corporation, shall be questioned on account of any vacancy or vacancies in the Corporation or any such Committees.(iii) No defect in the appointment of any person acting as Chairman Vice-Chairman or Governor of the Corporation or of a member of any Committee established by the Corporation shall be deemed to vitiate any proceedings of the Corporation or of such Committee in which he has taken part, in cases where the majority of members parties to such proceedings are duly entitled to act.(iv) Any instrument -which, if made by a private person, would be required to be under seal, shall be under the seal of the Corporation and signed by the proper officer of the Corporation. Any notice issued by or on behalf of the Corporation shall be deemed to be duly executed if signed by the proper officer ; but, subject as aforesaid, any appointment made by the Corporation and any contract, order, or other document made by or proceeding from the Corporation shall be deemed to be duly executed either if sealed with the seal of the Corporation and signed by the proper officer, or if signed by two or more Governors of the Corporation authorised to sign them by a resolution of the Corporation and countersigned by the proper officer.(v) The proper officer of the Corporation shall be any officer authorised by the Corporation to sign such notices and documents as he is required to sign as aforesaid.18. (i) THE Grant of this Our Charter is made upon the express condition that the Corporation shall strictly and faithfully observe the provisions prescribed therein and also the provisions prescribed by Our Postmaster General in any licence or instructions which he may from time to time grant or issue to the Corporation.(ii) IF it is made to appear or appears to Our Postmaster General either on the representation of any person or body politic or corporate appearing to be interested or in any other manner howsoever that there is reasonable cause to suppose that any of the provisions of this Our Charter or of any such Licence or any instructions of Our Postmaster^General have not been observed or complied with Our Postmaster General may require the Corporation to satisfy him that such provisions have been complied with and if within a time specified by him the Corporation shall fail so to do Our Postmaster General may if he thinks fit certify the same to Us under his hand, and upon
such certificate being given it shall be lawful for Us, Our Heirs and Successors, if We shall be so minded, by writing under Our Great Seal, absolutely to revoke and make void this Our Charter, and everything therein contained Provided nevertheless that the power of revocation so hereby reserved shall not have or be construed to have the effect of preventing or barring any proceeding by scire facias, or by the Writ of quo warranto, or otherwise according to law, to annul or repeal this^Our^Charter.19. AND WE do further will and declare that on the determination of the said term of ten years the business so to be carried on by the Corporation shall cease, so far as the same may depend upon or be carried on under or by virtue of the powers and provisions herein given and contained, unless, We, Our Heirs or Successors, shall, by writing under Our Sign Manual declare to the contrary, and shall authorise the continuance of the said business under the provisions of this Our Charter for such further term, and under such provisions and conditions as We, Our Heirs and Successors, shall think fit, and any term for which this Our Charter is so renewed shall be construed to be part of the term of this Our Charter.20. IT shall be lawful for the Corporation to surrender this Our Charter subject to the sanction of Us, Our Heirs or Successors and upon such terms as We or They may consider fit and to wind up or otherwise deal with the affairs of the Corporation in such manner as may be approved by Our Postmaster General.21. UPON the voluntary or compulsory dissolution of the Corporation the property and assets of the Corporation shall be applied in satisfaction of the debts and liabilities of the Corporation and subject thereto shall be disposed of in accordance with the directions of Our Postmaster General.22. LASTLY WE Mo by these Presents for Us Our Heirs and Successors grant unto the Corporation hereby established and their successors that these Our Letters Patent or the enrolment or exemplification thereof shall be in and by all things good firm valid sufficient and effectual in law according to the true intent and meaning thereof and shall be taken construed and judged in the most favourable and beneficial sense for the best advantage of the Corporation and their successors as well in all Our Courts of Record as elsewhere by all and singular Judges Justices Officers Ministers and other subjects whatsoever of Us Our Heirs or Successors any non-recital mis-recital or any other omission imperfection defect matter cause or thing whatsoever to the contrary thereof in anywise notwithstanding. And this provision shall apply to this Our Charter as altered amended or added to in manner aforesaid.IN WITNESS whereof We have caused these Our Letters to be made Patent.WITNESS Ourself at Westminster, the 20th day of December in the 17th year of Our Reign.BY WARRANT under the King&apos;s Sign^Manual.Dissolution andlWinding-upGeneral Declarationschuster.
LICENCE AND AGREEMENT between His Majesty&apos;s Postmaster General and the Governors of the British Broadcasting Corporation, LICENCE AND AGREEMENTTHIS INDENTURE made the 1st day of January 1927 BETWEEN THE RIGHT HONOURABLE SIR WILLIAM LOWSON MITCHELL-THOMSON, Baronet, K.B.E., M.P., His Majesty&apos;s Postmaster General (hereinafter called &quot; the Postmaster General &quot;) on behalf of His Majesty of the one part and THE BRITISH BROADCASTING CORPORATION whose Chief Office is situate at Savoy Hill, Victoria Embankment in the County of London (hereinafter called &quot; the Corporation &quot;) of the other partWHEREAS the Corporation has been incorporated by Royal Charter under the Sign Manual dated the 20th day of December 1926 for the purpose of carrying on a Broadcasting Service within the British IslesAND WHEREAS by reason of the provisions of the Telegraph Acts 1863 to 1925 it is unlawful to establish any wireless telegraph station or instal or work any apparatus for wireless telegraphy in any place except under and in accordance with a licence granted in that behalf by the Postmaster General and it is also unlawful save as in the said Acts provided to transmit telegrams within the United Kingdom.AND WHEREAS the Corporation has applied to the Postmaster General for a licence to establish and maintain certain wireless telegraph stations in the British Isles for the purpose of transmitting to persons holding a licence from the Postmaster General entitling them to receive bv wireless telegraphy messages of the description hereinafter referred toAND WHEREAS the Postmaster General has agreed to grant such licence to the Corporation upon and subject to the conditions and restrictions hereinafter containedAND WHEREAS the Postmaster General and the Corporation have agreed to enter into the arrangements hereinafter containedNOW THIS INDENTURE W1TNESSETH that in consideration of the premises and of the matters hereinafter appearing IT IS HEREBY AGREED AND DECLARED between and by the parties hereto and the Corporation (as to the covenants and agreements hereinafter contained on its part) doth hereby COVENANT and AGREE with the Postmaster General and the Postmaster General (as to the covenants and agreements hereinafter contained on his part) in exercise of all the powers and authorities enabling him in this behalf doth hereby COVENANT and AGREE with the Corporation in manner following (that is to say) : 1. IN these presents the following words aiid expressions shall have the several meanings hereinafter assigned to them unless there be something either in the subject or context repugnant to such construction (that is to say) :-The expression &quot; the Postmaster General &quot; includes his successors in theoffice of His Majesty&apos;s Postmaster-General. The expression &quot; wireless telegraphy &quot; has the same meaning as in the wireless Telegraphy Acts 1904 and 19.25,
The term &quot; telegraph &quot; has the same meaning as in the Telegraph Act 1869.The. term &quot; telephone &quot; means and includes any telegraphic transmitting or receiving instrument used or intended to be used for the purpose of transmitting or receiving spoken messages or communications or music by electricity.The expression &quot; transmission &quot; means sending and receiving.The expression &quot; Naval signalling &quot; means signalling by means of any system of wireless telegraphy between two or more ships of His Majesty&apos;s Navy between ships of His Majesty&apos;s Navy and Naval Stations or between a ship of His Majesty&apos;s Navy or a British Naval Station and any other wireless telegraph station whether on shore or on any ship or aircraft.The expression &quot; Army signalling &quot; means signalling by means ;of any system of wireless telegraphy between units of His Majesty&apos;s Forces between any unit of His Majesty&apos;s Forces and any wireless station and between any Army Council Station and any other wireless station.The expression &quot; Government aircraft signalling &quot; means signalling by means of any system of wireless telegraphy between two or more Government aircraft between any Government aircraft and any wireless station or between any Government aerodrome and any other wireless station.The expression &quot; the Admiralty &quot; means the Commissioners for executing the Office of Lord High Admiral of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and ^Ireland.The expression &quot; Army Council &quot; means the Secretary of State for War in Council.The expression &quot; Air Council &quot; means the Council established by theAir Force*Constitution Act 1917. The expression &quot; the Radiotelegraphf&quot;Convention  1912 &quot; means theConvention signed at London on the 5th day of July 1912 and theService Regulations made thereunder and includes any convention and Regulations which may from time to time be in force in substitutiontherefor or in amendment thereof. The expression &quot; British Isles &quot; means England Scotland Wales andNorthern Ireland the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man. The word &quot; person &quot; includes persons and any body of persons corporateor unincorporate.The expression &quot; Broadcast Matter &quot; means &quot;concerts lectures speeches addresses weather reports news information entertainments of any kind or description and any other matter transmissible by wireless telegraphy.2. THE Postmaster General hereby grants to the Corporation for a term of TEN YEARS from and including the 1st day of January 1927 hereinafter called &quot; the term &quot; (but subject as is hereinafter provided) licence and permission (a) to establish and/or maintain at such places in the British Isles as may from time to time be approved in writing by the Postmaster General wireless telegraph stations the sending and receiving instruments of which shall be telephones (hereinafter called &quot; the Stations &quot;)(b) to send broadcast matter by means of the Stations(c) to receive messages by means of the Stations.3. THE Corporation shall not without the consent in writing of the Postmaster General receive money or any valuable consideration from any person in respect of the transmission of messages by means of the Stations or any of them.
PROVIDED that nothing in this Clause shall be construed as precluding the Corporation from (1) Broadcasting matter provided gratuitously by any personTwith or without an acknowledgement of such provision by means of the broadcasting service.(2) Receiving a consideration for broadcasting&quot; names of publishers and prices of matter which is broadcast.(3) (So far only as the licence of the Postmaster General is required) from using for broadcast purposes without payment concerts theatrical entertainments or other broadcast matter given in public in London or the Provinces.4. (1) THE Corporation shall unless prevented by circumstances beyond their control send efficiently from the Stations on every day (including Sundays) during the term and during such hours as may from time to time be prescribed in writing by the Postmaster General programmes of broadcast matter.(2) The Corporation shall whenever so requested by any Department of His Majesty&apos;s Government at the Corporation^ own expense send from all or any of the said Stations any matter which such Department may require to be broadcast.(3) The Postmaster General may from time to time by Notice in writing to the Corporation require the Corporation to refrain from sending any broadcast matter (either particular or general) specified in such Notice and the definition of broadcast matter hereinbefore contained shall from time to time be read construed and take effect subject to the provisions of any such Notice or Notices which may have been given by the Postmaster General. The Postmaster General may at any time or times revoke or vary any such Notice as aforesaid.5. THE ^height of the aerials and theXwave-lengths used for sending at each Station and the type of waves emitted therefrom shall be such as shall be approved from time to time by the Postmaster General in writing. The normal or carrier wave-length essential for each station shall be maintained constant during transmission and from day to day. Each Station shall be worked with a power input to the main high frequency generator to be fixed by the Postmaster General after consultation with the Corporation^ engineers. The modulation and aerial systems shall be designed so as to utilise effectively the power input. The apparatus used at each Station shall be of such a character that the waves emitted are as pure and as little damped as may be reasonably practicable^having regard to technical considerations.6. THE Stations shall be subject to the inspection and supervision of any engineer for the time being nominated for the purpose by the Postmaster General but so that the Corporation its engineers and officers shall not be interfered with in the general conduct and operation of any of the Stations.THE Corporation shall afford all requisite and proper facilities for such inspection and supervision and shall secure to the Postmaster^General the right for the purpose aforesaid or for any other purpose of these presents of entry from time to time into and on such of the Stations and premises as may be in the possession or occupation of any person or persons other than the Corporation.EXCEPT with the approval in writingfof the Postmaster General every officer or servant of the Corporation employed in the conduct of the service Shall be a British subject.
7. THE stations shall not without the previous consent in writing of the Postmaster General be used by any person on the Corporation^ behalf or by permission of the Corporation for the despatch or receipt of messages other than messages for the time being authorised by this Licence.8. THE Corporation shall so soon as it commences operations make application to the Postmaster General for the Stations to be connected with the Post Office Telephone system (including the trunk telephone system) and the Postmaster General shall accede to such application upon the same terms and conditions as those upon which he would supply a private subscriber similarly situated and the Corporation shall enter into with the Postmaster General the usual subscribers Agreement for the provision and maintenance of the necessary connection and shall during the continuance of this Licence observe and perform the provisions of such agreement and pay to the Postmaster General all sums due to him thereunder.9. (1) THE Corporation shall not by the transmission of any message by means of the Stations or any of them or otherwise by the use thereof knowingly interfere with Naval signalling Army signalling or Government aircraft signalling and the Corporation shall use its best efforts at all times to avoid any such interference.(2) THE Corporation shall at all times use its best efforts to ensure that whenever the operators at any of the Stations become aware through the medium of the instruments used by them or otherwise that Naval signalling Army signalling or Government aircraft signalling is being interfered with such operators shall refrain from using the licensed apparatus until such operators are satisfied that all indication of interference with Naval signalling Army signalling or Government aircraft signalling shall have ceased.(3) IF the Admiralty the Army Council or the Air Council are of opinion that the working of the Stations or any of them is inconsistent with the free use of Naval signalling Army signalling or Government aircraft^signalling the Corporation shall when required in writing by the Postmaster General close such station or stations.(4) These provisions for the protection of Naval signalling Army signalling and Government aircraft signalling shall be construed to be without prejudice to the generality of any other provisions of these presents.10. THE Corporation shall comply in all respects with all such directions and regulations as may from time to time be given or made by the Postmaster General and in particular will if so required cease to work the Stations or any of them during any Naval Military or Air Force manoeuvres or other operations.11. THE Corporation shall observe the provisions &quot;of i the Radiotelegraph Convention 1912 so far as they are applicable to the said Stations.12. THE Corporation shall observe the provisions of any Regulations from time to time made under the provisions of the Telegraph Acts 1863 to 1925 by the Postmaster General with the consent of the Treasury in relation to the conduct of wireless telegraph business.13. (1) THE Corporation shall so work the Stations as not to interfere with the working of any wireless telegraph station established in the British Islands or the territorial waters surrounding the coasts of the British Islands (whether on shore or on any ship) or in any aircraft by or for the purposes of the Postmaster General or any Department of His Majesty&apos;s Government or for commercial purposes and in particular so as not to interfere with the transmission of any messages between wireless telegraph stations established as aforesaid on land and wireless telegraph stations established on ships at sea or on aircraft.
(2) With a view to preventing such interference as aforesaid the Corporation shall comply with all directions which shall be given to them by the Postmaster General and with all rules prescribed by the Postmaster General for observance by his licensees -(a) With respect to all arrangements to be adopted for the purpose of securing syntonised apparatus or for enabling the messages transmitted by means of the Stations to be distinguished from those emanating from any other wireless telegraph station ;(b) Generally with respect to avoiding interference between one wireless telegraph station and another.14. THE Corporation shall at all times indemnify the Postmaster General against all actions claims and demands which may be brought or made against the Postmaster General or his officers by any person in respect of any injury arising from any act of the Corporation or its agents licensed or permitted by these presents.15. NO person acting on the Corporation^ behalf or by its permission shall divulge to any person (other than properly authorised officials of His Majesty&apos;s Government or a competent legal tribunal) or make any use whatever of any message coming to his knowledge and not intended for receipt by means of the Stations or any of them.16. (1) THE Stations shall be so worked by the Corporation as not either directly or indirectly to interfere with the efficient or convenient maintenance working or user of any telegraphic line of the Postmaster General whether or not such telegraphic line already exists at the time when the Stations respectively commence to work or to expose any such line to risk of damage or to risk of interference with the efficient or convenient working or user thereof.(2) In case any such telegraphic line of the Postmaster General shall be damaged or the efficient working or user thereof shall be wholly or partially interrupted or otherwise interfered with and the Engineer-in-Chief of the Post Office for the time being shall certify in writing under his hand that such damage interruption or interference has in his opinion been caused directly or indirectly by the construction maintenance or working of any of the Stations or by anything done by or on behalf of the Corporation in relation thereto the Corporation shall on demand pay to the Postmaster General all costs that shall be reasonably incurred by him in repairing such damage and in removing or altering such telegraphic line so as to restore the same to efficient working order and in adding thereto or substituting therefor either temporarily or permanently any other telegraphic line if the said Engineer-in-Chief shall certify in writing under his hand that in his opinion such addition or substitu-tion is reasonably required in consequence of the construction maintenance or working present or future of any of the stations.(3) If and whenever the Engineer-in-Chief shall by writing under his hand certify that by reason of the construction maintenance or working of the Stations or any of them it has been necessary for the Postmaster General to place any telegraphic line in a position other than that in which he would otherwise have placed it or to insulate or otherwise protect any such telegraphic line then the Corporation shall on demand pay to the Postmaster General any additional cost incurred by him on account thereof.(4) For the purposes of this Clause the expression &quot; telegraphic line &quot; has the same meaning as in the Telegraph Act 1878 and the expression &quot; telegraphic line of the Postmaster General &quot; includes a telegraphic line belonging to or worked or used by the Postmaster General or constructed or maintained by him for any Department of the Government or other body or person.
17. THE Corporation shall pay to the Postmaster General a royalty of  10 per annum in respect of each of the Stations. The said royalty shall be paid in advance on the 1st day of January in each year the first payment to be made on the 1st day of January 1927.18. (1) THE Postmaster General shall (subject as is and in manner herein-after provided) out of such aids and supplies as may from time to time be appropriated by Parliament for that purpose pay to the Corporation in respect of every year of the term a sum equal to the following percentages of all sums received by the Postmaster General from his licensees in respect of fees payable under or for the grant of Licences issued by him during the immediately preceding year for the establishment maintenance or working of wireless telegraph stations in the British Isles for the purpose of receiving messages (hereinafter called &quot; Licences &quot;) after deducting the 12  per cent, referred to in Sub-clause (2) hereof that is to say : [a) In respect of the first million licences or fractional part thereof issued against payment iii the year 90 per cent.(6) In respect of the second million licences or fractional part thereof issued against payment in the year 80 per cent.(c) In respect of the third million licences or fractional part thereof issued against payment in the year 70 per cent.(d) In respect of all additional licences issued against payment in the year 60 per cent.(2) A deduction of 12  per cent, on account of the cost of collection and administration shall be made from the amount of all sums received by the Postmaster General in respect of licences before the calculation of the percentages referred to in sub-clause 1 hereof.(3) In this Clause the expression &quot; year &quot; means the period of twelve calendar months commencing on the 1st day of April in one calendar year and terminating on the 31st day of March in the next calendar year.(4) The sum payable by the Postmaster General to the Corporation in respect of each year of the term shall be paid by him on the 16th day of each month in monthly instalments as nearly equal as may be and any adjustment between the parties shall be made as soon as conveniently possible after the end of each year.(5) The Postmaster General shall in respect of the months of January February and March 1927 pay to the Corporation sums equal in the aggregate to one-fourth part of the sum which calculated in accordance with the provisions of this Clause would become payable to the Corporation in respect of the year of the term ending 31st March 1927.(6) For all the purposes of this Clause the last year of the term shall be deemed to be the period commencing on the 1st day of April 1936 and ter-minating on the 31st day of December 1936 and the sum payable by the Postmaster General to the Corporation in respect of that year shall be three-fourths of the sum which would be payable to the Corporation in respect of the last year of the term if the term ended on the 31st day of March 1937.(7) The Postmaster General undertakes to give consideration to any application which may be made to him by the Corporation at any time after the 1st January 1929 for an increase in the amount of the sum payable by the Postmaster General to the Corporation in respect of any unexpired part of the term on the ground that the sum for which payment is provided by this Clause is insufficient for the performance by the Corporation of its obligations under these presents.(8) The Postmaster General shall not be under any obligation to take any action to recover payment of any fees payable to him under or in respect of Licences and may if he thinks fit so to do waive payment of any fee or fees due to him or any portion thereof,
-    255(9) Nothing contained in this Clause shall have any application to fees received by the Postmaster General under or for the grant of Ship and Aircraft Licences Private Businesses and Commercial Licences or any Licence issued by the Postmaster General for the establishment maintenance or working of wireless telegraph stations for the purpose of sending and receiving messages or the use of wireless telegraph apparatus for any purpose save that of receiving messages only.(10) Any account of any sum payable by the Postmaster General to the Corporation certified by the Comptroller and Accountant General of the Post Office or the Deputy Comptroller and Accountant General under the provisions of this Clause or under any other provision of these presents shall be final and conclusive for all purposes.(11) The Postmaster General may set off any debt due to him by the Corporation under any of the provisions of these presents against any sum due from him to the Corporation under the provisions of this Clause.19. (1) IF and whenever in the opinion of the Postmaster General an emergency shall have arisen in which it is expedient for the Public Service that His Majesty&apos;s Government shall have control over the transmission of messages by means of the Stations it shall be lawful for the Postmaster General to direct and cause the Stations or any of them or any part thereof to be taken possession of in the name and on behalf of His Majesty and prevent the Corporation from using them and also to cause the Stations or any of them or any part thereof to be used for His Majesty&apos;s service and in that event any person authorised by the Postmaster General may enter upon the Stations or any of them and the offices and works of the Corporation or any of them and take possession thereof and use the same as aforesaid.(2) The Corporation shall not be entitled to claim compensation from the Postmaster General in respect of any loss sustained by them on account of the exercise by the Postmaster General of the powers conferred on him by sub-clause (1) hereof or for the use of the Stations in pursuance thereof or otherwise howsoever. PROVIDED ALWAYS that the Postmaster General shall repay or allow to the Corporation a proportionate part of the royalty payable by the Corporation for any Station in respect of which such powers as aforesaid shall be exercised in respect of the period or periods during which such powers shall be exercised. Provided further that the Postmaster General shall make to the Corporation on re-delivery to the Corporation of the Stations offices and works proper compensation for damage actually done thereto during the period of the emergency.(3) If and whenever the Postmaster General shall exercise, the powers conferred on him by sub-clause (1) hereof he may deduct from the sums payable by him to the Corporation under the provisions of Clause 18 hereof in respect of the period or periods during which such powers are exercised such amounts as shall be appropriate having regard to the period or periods during which such powers are exercised.20. IN any of the following cases (that is to say) (a) if at any time during the term the Corporation shall not in the opinion of the Postmaster General have adequately performed the covenant on its part hereinbefore contained to send efficiently from the Stations a programme of broadcast matter ; or(b) in case of any breach non-observance or non-performance by or on the part of the Corporation of any of the conditions contained in the said Royal Charter of the Corporation or of any of the other covenants or conditions herein contained and on the part of the Corporation to be observed and performed which shall not be remedied made good or desisted from within a reasonable time of the attention of the Corporation being drawn to the alleged breach non-observance or non-performance in question ; or
(c) in case the Corporation shall pass a resolution for voluntary winding up or in case an Order shall be made by the Court for the winding up of the Corporation compulsorily or under the supervision of the Court or in case a Receiver or Manager for any debenture holders shall be appointed or any debenture holders shall enter in possession of any part of the Corporation^ property ; then and in any of the said cases the Postmaster General may at any time thereafter by notice in writing revoke and determine these presents and the licences powers and authorities hereinbefore granted and each and every of them and thereupon these presents and the said licences powers and authorities and each and every of them shall (subject and without prejudice to any right of action or remedy for breach of any of the covenants and conditions herein contained which shall then have accrued to either of the parties) absolutely cease determine and become void.21. THE Corporation shall not without the consent in writing of the Postmaster General assign underlet or otherwise dispose of these presents or of the powers or authorities granted by the Licence hereinbefore contained or the benefit or advantage of the covenants and provisions herein contained or except as provided in the said Charter assign or charge any sum or sums payable by the Postmaster General to the Corporation hereunder or any of them.22. (1) ANY Notice request or consent (whether expressed to be in writing or not) to be given by the Postmaster General under these presents may be under the hand of any of the Secretaries or Assistant Secretaries or the Director of Telegraphs and Telephones for the time being of the Post Office or any other duly authorised officer of the Post Office and may be served by sending the same by registered letter addressed to the Corporation at its registered office for the time being and any notice to be given by the Corporation under these presents may be served by sending the same by registered letter addressed to the Secretary of the Post Office at the General Post Office London.(2) Any Notice given by the Postmaster General to the Corporation under the provisions of these presents may be revoked or varied by any subsequent Notice in writing given by him.IN WITNESS whereof the Postmaster General has hereunto set his hand and seal and the Corporation has caused its common seal to be hereunto affixed the day and year first before written.SIGNED SEALED AND DELIVERED by Sir George Evelyn Pemberton Murray K.C.B. Secretary to the Post Office for and in the name and as the act and deed of His Majesty&apos;s Postmaster General by virtue of the power in that behalf con-ferred by the Post Office Act 1908 in the presence of &apos;D. O. LumleyPrivate Secretary G.P.O. (N.) E.C.THE  COMMON  SEAL  of  the  British&quot;]Broadcasting Corporation was hereunto W. C. W. REITH, affixed in the presence of j        Director General., W. L. MITCHELL-THOMPSON byG. E. P. Murray.- 0
WIRELESS BROADCASTINGROYAL SUPPLEMENTAL CHARTER(1931)GEORGE THE FIFTH, by the Grace of God, of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas King, Defender of the Faith, Emperor of India.To all to whom these Presents shall come,fGreeting !WHEREAS on the 20th day of December, 1926, by Warrant under Our Sign Manual We granted unto the British Broadcasting Corporation (hereinafter called &quot; the Corporation &quot;) a Charter of Incorporation for the purpose of carrying out the objects therein stated :AND WHEREAS it has been represented to Us by Clement Richard Attlee, Our Postmaster General, that it is in the public interest that certain modifications should be made in the said Charter as hereinafter appears :NOW KNOW YE that We have by Our Royal Prerogative and Our especial grace certain knowledge and mere motion given and granted and by this Our Supplemental Charter for Us Our Heirs and Successors Do hereby give and grant as follows : 1. Clause 15 of the said Charter shall read as if the following sub-Clause (v) were inserted therein : (v) PROVIDED ALWAYS that the Corporation may instead of investing in Trustee securities sums set aside to meet depreciation of assets as provided in sub-Clause (ii) of this clause apply the same and any Sinking Fund representing accumulated depreciation reserves in expenditure certified by its Auditors to be in the nature of capital expenditure, or in the repayment of any sums borrowed or raised by the Corporation otherwise than for the purpose of obtaining temporary banking accommodation and facilities, or towards the provision of a Sinking Fund for the purpose of such repayment.2. In all other respects We confirm Our said Charter.IN WITNESS whereof We have caused these Our Letters to be made Patent.WITNESS Ourself at Westminster the fourteenth day of August in the twenty-second year of Our Reign.BY WARRANT under The King&apos;s Sign Manual.SCHUSTER.
SUPPLEMENTAL AGREEMENTTHIS INDENTURE made the Eleventh day of June One thousand nine hundred and thirty-one Between CLEMENT RICHARD ATTLEE, M.P. His Majesty&apos;s Postmaster General (hereinafter called &quot; the Postmaster General &quot;) on behalf of His Majesty of the one part and THE BRITISH BROADCASTING CORPORATION whose chief office is situate at Savoy Hill Victoria Embankment in the County of London (hereinafter called &quot; the Corporation &quot;) of the other part.SUPPLEMENTAL to an Indenture dated the First day of January One thousand nine hundred and twenty-seven made between The Right Honourable Sir William Lowson Mitchell-Thomson Baronet K.B.E. M.P. then His Maj.esty&apos;s Postmaster General on behalf of His Majesty of the one part and the Corporation of the other part (hereinafter referred to as &quot; the Principal Agreement &quot;).WHEREAS the Corporation has arranged with the Covent Garden Opera Syndicate (1930) Limited for the presentation of Grand Opera at the Royal Opera House Covent Garden and at suitable Theatres in the Provinces upon terms which permit the Corporation to broadcast the performance of such operas.And whereas the Postmaster General has agreed with the Corporation (subject to the necessary funds being voted by Parliament) to contribute to the cost of such undertaking in the manner provided in Clause 1 hereof.And whereas the Corporation has made application for an increase in the amount of the sum payable by the Postmaster General to the Corporation under the terms of Clause 18 of the Principal Agreement.NOW   THIS    INDENTURE   WITNESSETH   and   IT   IS   HEREBY AGREED AND DECLARED as follows :-1. (1) The Postmaster General will subject to the conditions herein contained and out of such aids and supplies as may from time to time be appropriated by Parliament for that purpose in addition to the sums for the payment of which provision is made in Clause 18 of the Principal Agreement pay to the Corporation the sums following that is to say : (i) in respect of the Opera produced at Covent Garden during the Autumn Season One thousand nine hundred and thirty and in respect of the period ending Thirty-first December One thousand nine hundred and thirty the sum of Five Thousand Pounds.(ii) for a period of Five Years from the First January One thousand nine hundred and thirty-one the sum of Seventeen Thousand and Five Hundred Pounds per annum.(2) Subject to the necessary appropriation being made by Parliament as hereinbefore provided the said sum of Five thousand pounds and the said sum of Seventeen thousand five hundred pounds payable in respect of the year One thousand nine hundred and thirty-one shall be paid not later than the Sixteenth day of August One thousand nine hundred and thirty-one and thereafter the annual sum of Seventeen thousand five hundred pounds shall be paid by equal quarterly instalments on the Sixteenth day of January April July and October respectively the first payment in respect of the period commencing on the First January One thousand nine hundred and thirty-two to be made on the Sixteenth day of January One thousand nine hundred and thirty-two.
C R. ATTLEE byG. E. P. murray(3) In the event of the determination of the Principal Agreement or of the Corporation ceasing to pay to the Grand Opera Syndicate (1930) Limited the annual sum of Twenty-five thousand pounds for the presentation of Grand Opera at the Royal Opera House Covent Garden and at suitable theatres in the provinces in order to secure the right to broadcast the performances of such operas as aforesaid (hen the said annual pay men Co f Seventeen thousand five hundred pounds shall cease to be payable. The decision of the Postmaster General upon any question arising under this clause shall be final.2. As from the First day of April One thousand nine hundred and thirty-one Sub-paragraphs (1) and (2) of Clause 18 of the Principal Agreement shall be read as if &quot; Ten per cent.&quot; were substituted for &quot; Twelve and a half per cent.&quot; as the deduction to be made by the Postmaster General on account of the cost of collection of licence fees and administration.3. If the Principal Agreement shall be determined this Agreement shall cease to have effect.in witness whereof the Postmaster General has hereunto set his hand and seal and the Corporation has caused its Common Seal to be hereunto affixed the day and year first before written.signed sealed and delivered by sir &quot; GEORGE evelyn PEMBERTON MURRAY k.c.B. Secretary to the Post Office for and in the name and as the act and deed of His Majesty&apos;s Postmaster General by virtue of the power in that behalf conferred by the Post Office Act 1908 in the presence of. v. sturdeePrivate secretary general Post OfficeLondonthe common seal of the British Broad-&quot;&apos;)casting Corporation was hereunto affixed v j&apos;l.sin the presence of jJ. H. WHITLEY.GAINFORD.C D. CARPENDALE.
APPENDIX FMEMBERSHIP OP B.B.C. GENERAL ADVISORY COUNCILHis Grace the Lord Archbishop of York [Chairman). The Warden of All Souls.Professor Ernest Barker, Litt.D., DXitt, LL.D.Sir William H. Beveridge, K.C.B., LL.D.The Rt. Hon. Margaret Bondfield.The Rt. Hon. the Viscount Charlemont.Sir Walter McL. Citrine, K.B.E.The Rt. Hon. the Earl of Crawford and Balcar,,&apos;s, K.T., F.R.S., LL.D. Sir H. Walford Davies, C.V.O., O.B.E., Mus.D.   , LL.D. Joseph F. Duncan. Miss Grace E. Hadow.The Rt. Hon. David Lloyd George, O.M., D.C.L., LL.D., M.P. The Most Hon. the Marquess of Lothian, CH. The Rt. Hon. the Lord Macmillan, LL.D. Sir Walter H. Moberley, D.S.O., DXitt. John Murray, LL.D.Sir George Newman, G.B.E., K.C.B., M.D., D.C.L. Professor J. H. Nicholson.The Rt. Hon. the Lord Peel, G.C.S.I., G.B.E. principal Sir Robert S. Rait, C.B.E., LL.D.The Rt. Hon. the Lord Rennell, G.C.B., G.C.M.G., G.C.V.O.The Lord Rutherford, O.M., F.R.S.Professor Sir J. Arthur Salter, K.C.B.Professor J. A. Scott Watson.George Bernard Shaw.Dame Meriel Talbot, D.B.E.Dame Sybil Thorndike, D.B.E., LL.D.Dr. W. W. Vaughan,M.V.O., DXitt.The Rt. Rev. the Lord Bishop of Winchester.
REVENUE ACCOUNT (EXPENDITURE) IN FORM RECOMMENDED(paragraph 76)(In this appendix the expenditure figures of .1934 are given as an example.)EXPENDITURE[Headquarters and Regional)Programmes :   Artists, speakers, etc.      . .       . .       . .       ..       . . 330,537Orchestras.............. 168,557Performing rights, copyright fees, and news royalties . . 148,886Simultaneous broadcast telephone system       . .       . . 47,773Salaries and wages           . .        . .       . .       . .       . . 186,745Travelling,   stationery,   postage,    and   miscellaneousexpenses            . .       . .       . .       . .       . .        . . 32,527915,025Engineering : Maintenance of plant, power, development, and research,etc.         .............. 83,225Salaries and wages           . .       . .       . .       . .        . . 221,427Travelling,   stationery,   postage,   and   miscellaneousexpenses            . .       . .       . .       . .       . .       . . 30,307334,959Premises : Rent, rates, taxes, and insurance          ..       ..       . . 44,247Heating, lighting, and telephones          . .       . .       . . 23,848Alterations to and maintenance of premises, furniture,etc.          ......       . .       ...... 95,141163,236A dministr aiion : Salaries and wages           . .       . .       . .       . . . . 76,460Travelling, legal, audit, stationery, postage, and mis-cellaneous expenses       . .       . .       . .       . . . . 16,41692,876Contributions to^Staff Pension Scheme and Benevolent Fund        . . 31,297Governors&apos; Fees . .       . .       . .       . .       . .       . .       - . 6,100Provision for depreciation and renewal of premises, plant, furnitureand fittings, etc...............        182,000Provision for Income Tax    . .       . .       . .       . .       . .       - .        113,000Balance carried down, being Net Revenue for year . .       . .       220,490^2,058,983
77APPENDIX HFORM OF BYELAW RECOMMENDED(paragraph 142)FORM OF BYELAW issued by the Home Office for the guidance of County Councils and Borough Councils who may have occasion to make good rule and government byelaws under section 249 of the Local Government Act, 1933, with a request that any proposed byelaw should be submitted to the Secretary of State in draft.Wireless Loudspeakers&apos; Gramophones, etc. No person shall(a) in any street or public place or in or in connection with any shop, business premises, or other place which adjoins any street or public place and to which the public are admitted, or(b) upon any other premisesby operating or causing or suffering to be operated any wireless loud-speaker, gramophone, amplifier, or similar instrument make or cause or suffer to be made any noise which shall be so loud and so continuous or repeated as to cause a nuisance to occupants or inmates of any premises in the neighbourhood.Provided that no proceedings shall be taken against any person for any offence against this byelaw in respect of premises referred to in paragraph (6) thereof, unless the. nuisance be continued after the expiration of a fortnight from the date of the service on such person of a notice alleging a nuisance, signed by not less than three householders residing within the hearing of the instrument as aforesaid.Penalty Clause. Any person offending against any of the foregoing Byelaws shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding. ... ** The fine must not exceed  5. There is no power to impose any higher penalty than this for a second offence.(c19519)   is   is &apos; 43   s4   1/38

</content>
</cab>
