<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/259/0 images: 548-550</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
9   ^     /.31      d y ^ i/IS pOOUMEHjT IS THE PROPERTY IF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENT.EGRET..P .31(36)COPY NO.CABINET.EXPORT CREDITS FOR RUSSIAN ORDERSMEMORANDUM BY THEPRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE.1.   For some time past the Russian Trade Representative in London has made it clear that his Government would he ready to purchase capital goods in this market to a greater extent if they can be given a reasonable and moderate period of credit.    It is known that the Soviet Government have, amongst other needs, considerable arrears of railway re-equipment to overtake,and it is believed that if the difficulty as regards the length of credit can be met, considerable orders might be obtained   for this country.2.    Two methods have been suggested for increasing the export of our manufactures to that country:    viz. an extension of the facilities afforded by the Export Credits Guarantee Department, or the guarantee of a long-term loan to the Soviet Government.3.    I prefer the former method.    The Department could by means of guarantees, for which it already possesses the necessary statutory authority, finance the orders which the Soviet Government are ready to place, given the requisite amount and length of credit.    Further,  it appears to me that, by use of the Export Credits Guarantee Scheme, we can obtain any orders the Soviet Government may be able to place as easily as by means of a loan guaranteed by the Government.    A loan would involve H.M. Government in a financial obligation to the holders in the event of default by the Soviet Government at any time in the next 20 years, the period for which the loan is suggested.
6 0 a4. At present the Export Credits Guarantee Department is precluded &quot;by a Cabinet decision of 1932 from guaranteeing credits for Russia if they exceed 18 months., The Department&apos;s Advisory Committee, on whose recommendation the Department operates within limits laid down by the Board of Trade and the Treasury, are for their part prepared to cover credits up to five years.     They have not as yet been asked to consider any longer period.5. The charge made by the Export Credits Guarantee Department for undertaking the risk need no longer be an obstacle.     The Advisory Committee have been prepared for a considerable time to reduce it in the case of Russia. The Soviet representatives are understood to be willing to pay 5 or 6 per cent, per annum for 5 year credits.     This would be enough to cover the Department&apos;s charge of, say, 2% per annum for incurring the risk of a default and to leave a margin of 3 to 4$ for discounting, which would be ample for hills carrying, as these would, the guarantee of the United Kingdom Government.6. The Department&apos;s &quot;business &quot;being in the nature of insurance, it attaches great importance to its charges, from which it   has &quot;built up a fund against losses.     This fund now exceeds  1,500,000.     If the facilities now required by the Soviet Government are provided by means of the Department&apos;s guarantees, at least some provision will be made for the eventuality of default, a possibility which, however   well-intentioned the Soviet Government may be, it is impossible to ignore, having regard to the widespread defaults of Governments in other countries^ The loan proposal on the other hand provides no fund for meeting possible losses.
30 007- The credit proposal would in my view have the following advantages over a guaranteed loan;-(a) Wo legislation.(b) A shorter risk and a smaller degree of risk.)(o) Some provision against loss in the event of Russian default.(d) Greater elasticity.(e) It would have immediate results in orders for thiscountry.     The loan proposal, however, would certainly involve considerable delay for negotiation and legislation. 8.  The Russian Trade Representative unofficially informed the Export Credits Guarantee Department so recently as February 5th that on the basis of five years1   credit and subject to agreement on terms, he could place orders here probably in   -the neighbourhood of  1,000,000 in the near future,  and that these orders would certainly be followed by others.9. With the concurrence of the Chancellor of the Exchequer, I therefore propose that the Export Credits Advisory Committee should be informed that they are free to consider proposals for credits for Russia in exactly the same way as for other countries.    In practice this means removing the limit of 18 months previously imposed by administrative action on guaranteed credits for exports to Russia, while still leaving the operations of the Department for Russia,  as for other countries,  subject to Treasury approval.10. A decision by the Cabinet to the above effect is urgently required not only because immediate business would result, but also because it is desirable to anticipate as far as possible the German proposal to offer Russia a loan of 500 million marks.w.r.Board of Trade.10th February,  1936.

</content>
</cab>
