<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/48/0 images: 72-87</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS TOOIJMBNT 18 THE PROPERTY 0? HIS BRITANNIC MAJSSTY:S GOVEHEMENT)S E G RET, COPY NO0 A B I N E T    30 (24)Meeting to be held at NOo 10, downing street, S.W.(1), on Wednesday, May 7tha, 3 924,at 11 a0moA S E H D A,JOBBIGH POLICY - THE PRESENT POSITIONllC i^OuTT0&quot;ME&apos;^ETTLEMR^(To be raised by the Prime MinisterJa2cGOVERNMENT POLICY IN REGARD TO NEW BILLS0(To be raised by the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies)oIMPERIAL WIRELESS SERVICES .(Reference Cabinet 27(24), Conclusion 7)memorandum by the Postmaster-General(CP,280(24)    -   already circulated)..WeU *Y%* -J^c^-Tm.        O? 236 (tm)IRISH POLITICAL PRISONERS.(Reference Cabinet 24(24), Conclusion 6).Memorandum by the Home Secretary.(CP. 214 (24)    -   already circulated).QUOTA DOR IvgGRANTS TO THE UNITED STATESOg&quot;i^0ii&quot;RrcZa&apos;.        &quot;        &quot; &quot;&quot;&apos;     :Memorandum by the Secretary of State forthe Colonieso(CP, 277(24)    -   already circulated).Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.(CP. 278(24)    -   already circulated).INDUSTRIAL UNREST.Interim Report of Committee.(CP. 273(24)    -   already circulated)..7S      ROAD PUND FINANCE,Doint Memorandum by the Minister of transport and the Financial Secretary, Treasury.(CP, 263(24)    -   already circulated).Report of Unemployment Committee,(CI\282(24)    -&apos;to be circulated).2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,2nd Hay,  1924.(Sd)    M0P.A. KAiJREY,Secretary^ Cabinet.
AIRSHIP DEVELOPMENT . / Q     \,Report of Cabinet Committee,(CP.  285 (24)    -    To be  circulated).9.    FACTORIES BILL      HOLIDAYS WITH PAY AND NIGHT BAKING.Memorandum by the Home Secretary covering a Draft Bill.(Pages 7 and 8 of CP.  281  (24)  - Already circulated)Memorandum by the Home Secretary,(CP.  281A  (24)    -    Already circulated). /
The Secretary.(THIS IX3CUMENT IS THE PROPBRTY OF HIS BRIT4JJNIC MAJESJT Y1S GOVERN MEN^)S  E C R E &quot;&apos;.f.COPY NO. 1,oC A B I E E T   30(24)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10,  Downing Street,  S.W.I.,on WEDNESDAY, MAY 7th. 1924, at 11 A.M.PRESENTThe Right Hon.  J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister and Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs. (In the Chair).The Right Hon.Lord Parrnoor of Frieth,K.C.V.O.,K.G,,    lord president of the Council.The Right Hon.Viscount Haldane, E.T.,0.M.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.J.R. Clynes, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. .A. Henderson, M.P.t Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Stephen Walsh, M.P., Secretaryof State for War.Brig.-General The Right Hon.Lord Thornson * C.B.E.,D.S.O.,Secretary of State for Air.She Right Hon.Sidney Webb, M.P., Presidentof i the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.Charles Trevelyan, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.the Right Hon.Tom Shaw,  C.B.E.,M.P. ,Minister of labour.[Ihe Right Hon.vernon Hartshorn,  C.B.E.,M.P.,2pst ma s t e r- Ge neral.The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.J.H.  Thomas, Secretaryof State for the Colonies.&apos;2he Right Hon.Lord Olivier, K.C.M.G.,C.B.Secretary of State for India.&apos;The Right Hon.Viscount Chelmsford, G.C.M.G.G.C.S.I. ,G.C.I.E.,G.B.B.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.John Wheatley, M.P.,Minister of Health.&apos;2he Right Hon.Noel Buxton, M.P., Ministerof Agriculture &amp; Fisheries.&quot;JEhe Right Hon.William Adams on, M. P.,Secretary for Scotland.Col.  &apos;fhe Right Hon.J.C. Wedgwood,  D.S.O.,M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy ofjLancaster.The Right Hon. F.W.  Jowett, M.P.,First Commissioner or Works.tueut.-Col. Sir M.P.A. Hankey,  G.C.3.......Secretary.
(TIiis^ Dooument^Is the^ Property of Ills Britannic&quot;&quot;liaj e slTy^&quot; s*&quot; Gove rnment. T&quot;CABINET 50- (24).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet,held at 10, Downing Street, S.W. 1, OnWEDNESDAY, MAY .7, 1924, at 11 a. in.1.    The Prime Minister, as Secretary of State forForeign Affairs, made a statement to his colleagues in regard to important outstanding questions of ForeignPolicy.The Prime Minister stated that he had got rid of the deadlock which had arisen owing to the policyof insisting on considering the questions of Jubalandand the Dodecanese as part of a single whole, byagreeing to treat them separately.In regard to Jubaland, the Prime Minister said he had agreed to carry out our obligations under theTreaty of London of April 26, 1915, Article 13.    Inthe previous negotiations the proposed cession had beendiscussed in regard to three triangles of territoryknown as &quot;A&quot;, &quot;B&quot; and &quot;0&quot;.    The Italians had desiredto acquire the whole of this territory.    He had notbeen able to agree to this, but had offered to cedethe considerable tract of territory comprised in thetriangles &quot;A&quot; and &quot;3&quot;, the determination of the boundari
DODECANESE.(previous reference:Cabinet 59(23)i Con-elusion 1EGYPT.The Gash-Raver.(previous reference\Cabinet 29(24), Con-elusion 3. )INTER-allied debts&apos;.&apos;previous reference:Cabinet 5(2-0, Con-elusion 1.)being referred to a Commission.    The Italian Govermenthad accepted this offer.The Prime Minister said that he had received aletter from Signor Mussolini, who apparently&quot; wished tokeep all the islands known as the Dodecanese which were of any value,   and .    deprecated handing backislands to Greece, owing to Turkish objections.The Prime Minister explained that the Gash Rivertraversed Italian territory, and the Italian Governmenthad recently started schemes of irrigation which wouldhave the effect of cutting off all the water from theKassala region.    He had made enquiries and had ascertained that the supply of water from the Gash River was suffl-cient to irrigate the Italian territory as well as thecotton-growing region   of   Kassala.    He had proposed tothe Italian Government that an Expert Commission shouldbe appointed to investigate the question, and the italians had accepted.    He contemplated that the Governments ofthe Sudan and probably also of Egypt would be represented on the Commission, as well as Great Britain and Italy,and in all probability some notable irrigation engineerwould be appointed.    He hoped that an agreement &quot;would bereached that would be profitable in the best sense ofthe word.The Chancellor of the Exchequer drew attentionto a Parliamentary Question which had been put down for answer by him, in regard to the Italian Debt.The Prime Minister pointed out that this was partof the whole question of international indebtedness,which he did not wish to raise until the experts&quot; report had been dealt with.    He had reason to believe that someof the Mlied Governments shared this view.    He hoped,
therefore) that a non-committal answer would be giver.The Prime Minister gave his colleagues a summaryof his conversations with Me Theunis and M. Eymans at chequers on Saturday, May 3rd.    He undertook to cireu-late a full Memorandum on the subject, the text of whichhe had just approved.    He drew the attention of hiscolleagues to the especially secret character of thisreport.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should circulate as soon as pos-sible a report of his recent conversations with the Belgian Prime Minister and ForeignMinister at Ohequei^s.(b) That, in view of the great importance ofthe subject, a special meeting of theCabinet should be held to discuss thisreport on WEDNESDAY , MAY 14th, at10-30 a.m.REPARATION,,Uonve rs e/russians.(previous reference:Cabinet 26(24) , Con-elusion 1.)
2. The attention of the Cabinet was drawn to theimportance of careful consideration of the parliamentary time-table at the present stage , in order to avoid thenecessity of giving up important and useful Bills inthe interests of the Parliamentary holiday.    It was further pointed out that the whole matter was closelybound up with the question of the Parliamentary Year,and whether * as desired in many parts of the House, itshould not begin in the Autumn and end in July or earlyAugust.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the question should be discussed at a Meeting of the Cabinet on THURSDAY,MAY 15th, at 11 a ma.(b) That the Lord Privy Seal should prepare and circulate a Memorandum in regard tothe state of Parliamentary business upto Whitsuntide, together with a list of bills which had been approved by theCabinet for introduction.parliamentary business.(previous reference:Cabinet 23(24) , Con-elusion 12.)
IMPERIALWIRELESSSERVICE.(previous reference:Cabinet 27(24), Oon-clusion 7o)3. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by thePostoaster-General (Paper 0*P.-280 (24-)) containing the recommendations of the Cabinet Committee in regardto the Imperial Wireless Service, together with a Notethereon by the Secretary of State for Air (Paper C.P.-286 (24)).The First Lord of the Admiralty, as Chairman ofthe Imperial Communications Committee, stated, withreference to the Secretary of State for Air1s Note,that the comments of the Air Minister on the detailed proposals of the General Post Office had now been communicated to the Imperial Communications Committeeand that the subject would be considered as soon as allthe necessary material was available.The Cabinet agreed -(a) That the Rugby station should becompleted as arranged (with 16 masts):(b) That,    if possible, the completion ofthe Rugby station should be carried out without a Supplementary Estimate, andthat this question should be settled byThe Lord Privy Seal,The Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Po s tmast e r-Gene ral:(e) That the Imperial Communications Committeeshould consider the proposal for enlargingthe Leafield high-power station in relationto the objections referred to in the Noteby the Secretary of State for Air:(d) To take note that the Dominions and india had already been communicated with on thelines of the telegram attached to thePostmaster-general s Memorandum (paper&quot;P.-280 (24):(e) That the question of Empire WirelessPolicy should be settled independently of any other matters, and before any concessions are given to the marconi company in respect of foreign communication-tion:*(f) Thau a Committee, on the lines of theDona,Id. CoMnittee , should be appoint to consider the business organisationof the new State Wireless Service which
is being set up;   that Mr Donald shouldbe asked to take the Chair, and that theCoiiMittee should include Sir George Barstow,of the Treasury, in plaoe of the Solicitor-General;   Mr Brown, of the Post Office;and one or more business men;   but thatits exact composition should be settled by the Cabinet Committee:(g) That the Cabinet Committee Should continue in existence for the consideration ofthe following questions:-the composition of the organising committee, referred to above in (f);the nature of the communication, whetherwritten or oral, to be made to the marconi company;   the terms of the announcement to be made in Parliament and the date when that announcement should be made;the replies of the Dominions and Indiaand the action to be taken thereon;   andany other questions which might be refer-red to them on the subject of the Imperial Wireless Service.
4.    After- very careful consideration of a Memorandimby the Home Secretary on the subject of the Irish&quot;political&quot; prisoners (Paper C. P. -214 (24)), theCabinet agreed  To recommend that Mr Art 01Brien andMr Sean. mcgrath should be transferredto the First Division for the remainder of their term of imprisonment..
THE FACTORIES 5. After consideration of Memoranda by the HomeBILL,Secretary in regard to the Factories Bill (PapersC P. -281 (24) and CoP.-281A (24)), and more especially4to the proposed Clause 44 providing for annual holidayson full pay for factory workers, the Cabinet agreed  (-a) (By a, ma jority) That the proposed Clauseproviding for an annual holiday on fullpay for factory workers should not beincluded in the original Bill:(b) That the Committee of Home Affairs should. examine the Bill as soon as convenient&quot;\      and report to. the Cabinet the various points on which a Cabinet decision wouldbe required.
G.After considernation of Memoranda by the SecretaryUNITEDSTATES OFAMERICA,of State for vie Colonies (Papethe Minister of Labour (Paper CPaper CP.-277 (24-)) andor Co P.-278 (24)) on thesubject of the quota for migrants to the United Statesof America, the Cabinet agreed  That the Secretary of State for theColonies should take immediate stepsto sound the Irish Free State Govern-ment as to whether they would agreeto the following proposal, namely, -That representations, should bemade to the United StatesGovernment with a view to secur-ing, if possible, that powers are taken in United States legislationinregard to immigration to enabletrie British Is lards quota of immigrants to be treated asundivided In any year in respectof which the Government of GreatBritain and Northern Ireland, andof the Free State, both asked thatthis should be done.
ROAD FUNDFINANCE.(previous reference:Cabinet 29(24), Con-elusion 7. )7i   After consideration of a joint Memorandum by the- Minister of Transport and the Financial Secretary tothe Treasury (Paper CP.-263 (24)) and the Report ofthe Unemployment Sub-Committee of the UnemploymentCommittee thereon (Paper CP.-282 (24))j the cabinet agreed -(a) That authority should be given for chargingupon the Road Fund its share (estimated at 10,400,000) of a further programme of 13,500,000 (to be devoted to works to beput in hand earlier than would otherwise be done with a view to affording employ-ment) by anticipating its future revenuesup to 31st March, 1931, on the understand-ing (i) that recourse will not be had toborrowing, (ii) that the future revenues of the Fund are not at present to be anti-cipated for such works to any greater extent than the new programme entails,and (iii) that the Treasury guarantee offinancial &quot;cover&quot; given to the Fund inconnection with previous programmes vailbe extended to include the new programme&apos;.. (b) That the Minister of Transport should beauthorised to proceed as expeditiouslyas circumstances permit with the initiative-tion and carrying out of the various workscomprised in the &quot;new programme.
AIRSHIPDEVELO?-MENT./1eviousinference:Cabinet 29(24) , Con-elusion 1.)Approyed bythe CabinetKay 1st&apos;, 1924.8,    After consideration of the revised Report ofthe Cabinet Ocrjmitx.ee on Airship Development (paper.R.-285 (24)), the Cabinet agreed  To approve the following recommendationsof the.Cabinet Committee:r(HOTS:    Those which had alreadybeen approved before thequestion was referred bachto the Committee are shownin the margin)(a) Having regard to its complicatedfinance, involving interlockingCompanies, the Oortiaittee recommendthat the original Burney scheme should bo rejected.(b) In substitution for that Scheme theCommittee are of opinion that -Approved bytheMayCabinetlst&apos;,19&apos;24.(i) The Air Ministry should be authorisedto proceed with research and experi-mental stages in regard to Airships,and the simultaneous constructionof a 5,000,000 cubic feet capacityairship at Cardington, whose primaryfunction should be naval reconnais-sance.    The design of this airshipto be based on results obtained fromthis research and experimental work.(ii) It is felt, however, that some assist-ance should be given to the develop-ment of airships on the commercialside.    In view of his services inconnection with airship research,It Is considered that CommanderBurneyfs Group (Vickers) should begiven the first offer of a contract for the construction of a commercialairship.    This ship to be handed overto the Air Ministry on completion.After satisfactory trials have beencarried out, the Burney Group tohave the option of re^-purchasing it for the sum of  150,000, providedthat it is to be used for the purposesof an approved British Airship Serviceand thai, it is available for use bythe State as required..    The total sumchargeable against public funds onaccount of this commercial airshipnot to exceed  350,000 5 spread overa period of three financial years.The terms of the Burney contract to besettled by a Committee of representativesTreasury (Sir G. Barstow) , Air(Sir S. Dannreuther), with the for Air in the Chair,of theMinistrySecretax-&apos;y ol uduud j.wx        j-uin consultation with Commander Burney.-11-c1
Cd) The Air Ministry should he authorised to expend a sum not exceeding  400,000 onairship construction during the financialyear 1924-25. &apos; This sum would include pay-ments made on account of the commercialairships and should not he exceeded inany subsequent year without specialauthority from the Cabinet.(e) In order to ensure co-ordination -(l) An Advisory Board should be set upincluding representatives of theTreasury, Admiralty, War Office,Air Ministxy, Colonial Office and post Office:(li) Also a Technical Board including representatives of the admiralty and Air Ministry, with power toco-opt other technical assistance.The functions of these Boards to be laiddown by the Committee of Imperial Defence.(f) If satisfactory terms cannot be arranged with Commander Burney, the Air ministry should commence research work, etc. , atOardington as in Cb)(i), and the sameoffer of Government assistance for asimilar airship should be made to other firms.(g) Conditions for training of personnel, etc.,should be- determined by the Committee ofImperial Defence.-12-t
9.   As already mentioned in Conclusions 1 and 2,the Cabinet agreed to meet on the follovd.ng dates:-(a) Wednesday, May 14th, at 10-30 a,m. ,for a discussion on FOREIGN POLICY.lb) Thursday, May 15th, at 11 a,m. &apos;, forthe discussion of current business.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,May 7, 1924.- lo-(V)     FURTHERMEETINGSOF THECABINET.

</content>
</cab>
