<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/48/0 images: 549-553</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
eon N0..v...OABIimg 51 (24)MEITIHG of the Cabinet to be held at 10 downing street, SJ7.1., on !Hiursday, October 9th. 1924 at 11 a*nuAGMWJil.THB POLITICO, SlWmOlh-......-.............-................ --i1&quot;&quot;.....&quot; (Signed) K. P. A* MMM,Secretary to the Cabinet.2, &apos;7hitehall Gardens, 3.7.1*.October 9th. 1934,
jlS nnCTTMEMT^lS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT) .EGRET. COPY UP.    /CABINET    55T24),CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downing Street, SaWnl-.,, onTHURSDAY,  OCTOBER 9th.  1924, at 11 A.M*PFESENT  I-The Right hon  Ja Ramsay Mac-Donaldf Mbp.. 9Prime Minister and Secretary ofState for Foreign affairs (&quot;In the Chair)Right Hon.viscount Haldane, KM&apos;o tPrd ChancellorjRight Hon,hllip Snowden, MnPoffhancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.JeRo Ciynos, McPo,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon..A.0 Henderson, M.P..,Secretary of State forHomo Affairs.Right hon;.Ho Thomas j M0P.y secretary State for the - Colonies.Right Hon.prd Olivier, Z,C.H.G.,C4B9,-ecretary of State for IndiaoRight Hon. -idneyWebb, M0P.., Presidentf the Board of Trade-,The Right Hon.St eph en Wa Ish, M.P..,Secretary of State for Wa:Brigc-General The Right &quot;Hon,lord Thomson, C.B.E.,DoS.Secretary of State for AiThe Right Hon.John Wheatley, M.P0,Minister of Health^&apos;Right Hon.barles Trevelyan, map,iSsidert of the Board ofducat ion.Height H0nopm Shaw,  CBcE. yMoPsinister of labour.Right Hon.ftnon Hartshorn, CoB.E0,M.Pcpstmaster-General.The Right Hon.Noel Buxton, M.P0, Ministeof Agriculture &amp; fisheries the Right Hon.William Adamson, 1LPC,Secretary for Scotland.Colo The Right HonoJ.0o Wedgwood, D.S.0o. ,M.P&apos;i,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. F.W.  Jowett, M.P.,First Commissioner of Works.o o  i a  a o  aTHE FOLLOWTNfl WERE ALSO present mr. Ben Spoor, M r P., Pa r^a^eE^ q1^ ^ e c re t p^m^       5^ c ret ary [Sir Claud Schuster, X.C.0B. ,CV.0p ,K.C., chancellor s Office.&quot;Mr, P.R. Laird,&apos;Scottish Office^. ^ t-, ........Secretary&apos;*.-Col. Sir M.P.A. Hankey,. G.C.B. * - * * *............
(This r Do^umejat^s^^the Property of His Britannic0 esty s Gove:rnment.)SECRET-CABINET 55 (24).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet,held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.1, onTHURSDAY, OCTOBER 9, 1924, at 11 a.rruTHE POLITICAL!&apos; SITUATION-.j prorogation and Dlssoiu-Ition.1.    The Prime Minister informed his colleagues that the King was v,rilling to grant a dissolution, butthat, in view of the desirability of avoiding frequentElections, His Majesty proposed to send to the PrimeMinister, for purposes of record, a Memorandum (whichHis Majesty would show the Prime Minister in advance)to which, equally for purposes of record, the PrimeMinister, with His Majesty&apos;s consent, would reply.After discussing all aspects of the Electiontime-table, including the necessity of avoiding a clash with the date of the Municipal Elections (Saturday,November 1st in Great Britain), and after hearing fromthe Permanent Secretary of the Lord High. Chancellor&apos;department, the Clerk and Deputy Clerk of the Council,and Mr P.R, Laird, Assistant Secretary, Scottish Office,particulars of the technical considerations involved,the Cabinet agreed  (a) That, as a General Election had becomeunavoidable, it was essential, in thebusiness interests of the country, thatit should take place at the earliestpossible date:
(b) That, if the General Election were held at the earliest possible date,it would be unnecessary to pass the expiring Laws Continuance Bill.or the Law of Property Act (Post- .ponement) Bills during the present session of Parliament&quot;.(c) That, in the circumstances, the king should be asked to hold Meetings of &quot;His Majesty&apos;s Privy Council on thesame day (Thursday, October 9th)first for proroguing parliament on the same da,y (Thursday, October9th) and, second (after prorogationhad taken place), for the purpose ofdissolving. Pa,rliainent:(d) That the President of the Board ofTrade , in consultation with suohDepartmental officials as he might think desirable., should immediatelyprepare a draft- for the king&apos;s speech to be read on the prorogation ofParliament the same afternoon:(e) That the King1 s Speech should deal,as briefly as possible, with suchmatters as Foreign Affairs (theLeague of Nations Protocols onArbitration and Limitation ofArmaments, the Anglo-Soviet Treaty,Iraq, the London Conference onReparation,1 etc. ) ;   the Budget;the Government1s programme to stimu-late the industry of the country andto encourage trade, thus dealing withthe fundamental problem of Unemployment;and perhaps the proposed Conference withrepresentatives of the Dominions;   Housing;Agriculture,, etc.:(f) That the date to be inserted in the proclamations for the Meeting ofParliament should be Tuesday&apos;, November18th.
NEXT MEETING 2. The Cabinet agreed -0? CABINET.To meet on the following day,Friday, October 10th, 1924, at10 a.m, for the disposal of anyessential business.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,October 9, 1924.

</content>
</cab>
