<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/6/52 images: 636-643</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
imports.The total imports were 377,400 tons, an increase of 10,400 tons on the: previous week.   This is the largest amount so far recorded during the war.   Importson Admiralty account were the largest  cr- a considerable period,   There is a difficulty at the moment in forecasting probable iiports during the next four weeks.Normally sane 90 tankers carrying 920,000 tons of oil : tight bo expected to arrive.U.K. storage is, however, practically full owing to the heavy imports during thelast few weeks and the diversion to this country of t nkers programmed fox- Prancewhich could not be unloaded there.   Arrangements have recently been ;.sade to hold asa mobile reserve some tankers at suitable points in this country and at convoycollecting points on the other side of the Atlantic.I CONSUMPTION.Consumption by the Service Departments, home and overseas&apos; showed in theaggregate a decrease of 23,600 tons compared with the previous week.   Admiraltyfigures mainly account for the difference.   Those of the War Office and theAir Ministry were practically the same &quot;as those shown in the previous week.Civil consuitp&apos;ion increased by 9,000 tons bompired with the previous week,the increases being mainly in respect of gas, fuel and diesel oils. Petrol conaunptwas 4,000 tons lower.[STOCKS.(a) Services.Total Service stocks showed an increase of 53,000 tons compared with theprevious week.   Admiralty stocks of fuel oil, at home and overseas, were 28,000 tonshigher.   Air Ministry stocks of aviation spirit in the U.K. A/ere 11,000 tons higherand War Office stocks of motor spirit in the U.K. increased by 10,000 tons.   Thebalance is accounted for b3r other products.(b) Civil.Civil stocks improved as compared with the previous week &quot;by 198,000 tons(tina lock     rjjEgs propi^ty of hi?. iHpra^ic : Ajzijn*6 gcvp^jjkt)sgcp^iT. copt uo.   /?vf.pl (R) (AO) 172.\8th June, 1940.&amp;WAR 0ABII13T.oil position.Forty-first Weekly Report covering the period up to midnight on the16th Juno, 1940, submitted by the Secretary for Petroleum.(Previous Report:   Paper w.?, (R) (ao) 168.)
Contracts Tor building protective walls referred to in the last reportof the Oil Control Board have now been let in ten centres.   The worlc vd.ll takefrom about four to iourtsen i/eeks to coatplete,&apos; the tine varying according to t ..eamount of tonnage to bo protected and felxe material and labour&apos; available. the scheme arranged by the trade frr providing compensation to garagesput out of business under the policy of thim-JLhg &apos;out the supply joints in an area,demarcated by the Hilitary Authorities on the System \nd Southern side of the counhas now bee:-: caapleted.   All oil will be sold &quot;by the authorised su_.pl;&apos; points on an agency basis! for the Petroleum Board, and out of tdo ca adssions ordinarily p..3rableto the garages, a distribution will be ais.de by the trade organisations for thebenefit of the garages displaced from.business.On the night of the 18th June bombs were dropped at Canve;- Island when a boiler house was hit but otherwise little damage was done.   On the night of the19th,   bombs, fell at Billinghan and Saltend, but also causing   fortunately little damage to tap plant and installations.   At Billingham the laboratory and sportsground were hit as well as an unimportant section of the plant, which was restartedthe following afternoon.G. L.Richmond Terrace,Whitehall, 3.W.1 .105.
Monthly Average.June - August, 1939September, 1939October, 1939November, 1939December, 1939Monthly Average: Sept,-Dec.January, 1940February, 1940March, 1940April, 1940Monthly Average: Jan.-AprilMay,   1940Week-ended.1st June, 19408th June, 194015th June, 1940Total imports to dateAdidralty Fuel Oil		Other Purposes		TOTAL.	Tankers Ho.	Cargoes Tons	Tankers No.	Cargoes Tons	Tankers Ho.	Cargoes Tons.4	32)., 000	128	1,106,000	132	1,140,000			J           7 525,700	52	-	64,600 124,900 285*500	52			525,700 r- .-- /*\      c\ /-i rt7 12 28		49 60 68	494,200 657,300 670,500 586,900	56 72 96	553,800 782,200 956,00012	-   113,800	57		&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;69	705,70020 15 14,    . 13	195,300 165,100 . 140,900 171,500	72 68  6 81	735,000 694,900 923,400 867,700	92 83 110 99	930,300 860,000 1,062.;., 300 1,039,20017	168,200 ,	79	805,300 1,074,900	96	973,50015	153,700	103		118	1,233,6004 4 7	47,400 2,-3,000 68^600	28 30 29	273,500 324,000 300,800	32 34 36	320,900 367,000 ,577,400-139	1,418,100	709	7,284,300	82j.3	3,702,2,-00
Weekly Average far1938Weekly AverageSept,-Nov. 1939Dec. 1939 - Feb. 1940liar. - May, 19404 weeks ended.8th June, 1940.Weekending:1st June, 19408th June, 194015th June, 1940Scrvi(:esTlhiited Kingdom and. Overseas^&quot;admiralty fuel OilUnitedKingdomTons7,60045,70045,20060,40056,60066,40047,00052,600OverseasTonsIMOO.34,00030,00027,90042,90034,00058,50029,500Air Ministry ;&apos;War OfficeAviation Spirit.   I Motor Spirit^United   j OverseasKingdom j (West ofjSuez)Tons1,6003,7003,2005,4007,2008,000 )7,900 ])7,700 )Tons40200 .200900Not yetavailableTotalJailUnited&quot;&quot;&quot;] &quot;Overseas Grades.Kingdom  j (B.E.F.)Tons4002,7002,9003,7004,800Not yet j(5,000available! (,(5,000l((5,500Tons2,1002,0003,3004,3002,4502,4502,450(a)Tons23,10089,60084,800103,300120,100119,700124,300100,700niot&quot;oFxOtherSpiritCiviTons95,000.71,50054,50062,30061,50059,40064,20060,300KeroseneTons15,40019,50016,70013,20012,60011,90012,300I (United Kingdom)&quot;Gas,      lubricating-Fuel &amp;   eating    (TotalDiesel   OilsOils      (b)Tons66,00059,60066,10061 ,2:-0056,70060,40052,70064,100Tons9,000   ,185,00013,70010,00010,30010,3009,50011,70012,400160,200150,100150,700141,700141,900140,500149,600GrandTotalT&quot;ons&quot;*203^100249,800234,900254,000261,800261,600262h,300250,300note:(a) Details are given under the three Services for the main product used.   Theconsumption of other products is aggregated in the &quot;Total&quot; column.(b) Includes deliveries,to the Array and Air Force.
ABLIC III.STOCKS.Quantities in thousands of tons.At outbreak of war end of Oct.1939&quot;   &quot;  Dec,. 1939&quot;   &quot;   Feb. 1940&quot;   &quot; April,19AOOn 30th May, 1.940&quot; 6th June, 1943&apos;.&apos; 13th-June. 1940A&amp;niralty-J^-LP.?-!...Unitedgdom______Services (United Kingdom &amp; OverseasjAir Ministry[aviation.ti.oi-x Spirit.3,0502,6702,6862,6672,4432,3222,31812*334.,United ;OverseasOverseas.KLngdomj (West of suez).2,9362,7532,6222,5742,5642,4992,4812,493(a)(h)(c)War office motor S&apos;oirit.TotalallUnited j Overseas Grades(h)I Kingdom; (B.E.F.)476       (a)       J145458       (a)        1122       23476       23 124       295,26      26 142      43607      26        j142       62(o)592       20 1189       38&apos; i&apos;599 )    Not      (196 )    Not)     yet       (      )     yet. 6jj02   avail able (2062.......j .^^.^i(.5 J89 .6,6446,0736,0196,0525,926j 5,7481(5,736j(MotorandOtherSpiritiivil   (United Kingdom)&quot;1,051899-9931,0701,1621,2401,242J.,307 j;Gas    . lubricating-,CrudeKerosene Fuel i&amp;cating jandjDiesel Oils jProcessI Oils  ! I Oils241151267194206215218247983 255 433964 188 222776 154 212509 184 243583 234 222677 284 271733 292 303L794... J33__345^...Under 1,000 tons.Details are given under the three Services for the main product used.The stocks of other products are aggregated in the &quot;Total&quot; column..B.E.F, figures include Base depots only.Total2,9632,4242,4022,2002,4072,6872,7882,936GHAHD TOTALUnitedKingdom6,6675,7155,7355,5975,6685,8715,9766,215Overseas,2,9402,7322,6862,6552,6652,5642,5432,560COCD




</content>
</cab>
