<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/6/36 images: 456-461</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;tHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERHMEBT.50SCRETo.pJJL) (40) 156.Rth May, 1940 war CABINET.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.Copy NOoIt is requested that special cai-ts may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.SHIPPING.Thirty-eighth Weekly Report covering theperiod ended midnight Sunday/Monday26th/27th May. 1940.(Previous Paper W.P.(R) (40)151)vessels of 500 gross tons and over. Tonnage figures in thousands.British Vessels on 2nd September.1939a500/1599 gross tons1,600 gross tons and over total:-,osses in week ended 26th May, 1940Sinkings:       Enemy actionVessels captured toy EnemyOther total losses.Total;-Gains in week ended 26th May, 1940&quot;ew vesselsnemy vessels capturedanish vessels transferred toBritish flagother gains.Total;-Ict Gain(4-) or loss(-) in weekotal net gain or loss to date. jjish vessels on 26th May, 1940.fessels engaged on Naval, Militarylor Royal Air Force Services:-(i) Government-owned vessels(ii) Requisitioned or Chartered(a). On Permanent Service(to) On temporary service balance:-Total:-RSTRY OF SHIPPING.TankersNo.67453520GrossTonnage653,21111-1-36164183745173,276-1-292834111122, 441OthersNo.1,0602,5233,58391616GrossTonnage^1,02514,39015,4151212514926+10-15252142403,0893,247381522203+19+2S781,3701, 19512,7973,568   115.440R.H.C.

&apos;THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERMMEMT.jk(r) (40) 156.?atji May,  1940.TO BE KEP&quot;WAR CABINET.UNDER LOCK AND KEY.Copy No.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.SHIPPING.Thirty-eighth Weekly Report covering theperiod ended midnipfrt Sunday/Monday26th/27th May, 1940.(Previous Paper W.P*(R) (40)151)Issels of 500 gross tons and over. Tonnage figures in thousands,British Vessels on 2nd September.1939 a500/1599 gross tons1,600 gross tons and over total:-TankersOthersNo.67453520GrossTonnage653,2113,276No.1,0602,5233,583GrossTonnage,1,02514,39015,415Losses in week ended 26th May, 1940Sinkings: Enemy actionVessels captured &quot;by EnemyOther total losses.Total:-Ifiains in week ended 26th May, 1940pew vesselsSnemy vessels capturedDanish vessels transferred toBritish flag.)ther gains.Total:-irct Gain(4-) or loss(-) in week total net gain or loss to date.PltjLsh vessels on 26th May. 1940.Jessels engaged on Naval, military or Royal Air Force Services:-(i) Government-owned vesselsii) Requisitioned or Chartered(a), On Permanent Service(b) on temporary service balance:-Total:-111191616149-1-3-1-2926+10-1512125381522206164183745172834111122, 441252142403,0893,2473, 568+194-25781,3701, 19512, 79715.440folSTRY OF SHIPPING.R.H.C.

SHIPPING.Addendum to W.P.  (R) ,(40) 156.STATEMENT OF FRENCH TONNAGE.(Derived from figures submitted by the French Delegation to theAnglo-French Permanent Executive Committee for Shipping.)Vessels of _500_gross_tons_and_over_ . Tonnage^figH SS-.i5-ili2\i2SS t2i.) French Vessels  on 2nd September1959.500/1599 gross tons1,600 gross tons and overTotalTankers.No.84755GrossTonnage5315320Others.No.93455548GrossTonnage1002,3092,409) Losses in week ended 26th May,&quot; 1940.Sinkings: Enemy action other total lossesTotalGains in week ended 26th May,--New vessels enemy vessels capturedDanish vessels transferred to french flag.Other gainsTotalNet gain (*) or loss (-) inweekTotal net gain or loss to date-1-6-5-1+11-2+Z7French vessels on 26th May,1940.Vessels engaged on Naval or military ServicesBalanceTotal55553153157848155938620602446It has not been possible to obtain details of transferswhich have taken place since the last Report.


</content>
</cab>
