<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/27/17 images: 122-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT &apos;Printed for the War Cabinet.  August 1942.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (42)101st Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET 101 (42).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W.1, on Saturday, August 1, 1942, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also present:The Hon. W. Nash, Accredited Repre-sentative of the Government of theDominion of New Zealand (items-4).The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer(Items 4-5).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air (Items 1-4).The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary, HisMajesty&apos;s Treasury (Item 5).Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 1-4).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security (Item 5).The Right Hon.  Sir James &quot; Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War(Items 1-4).The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P.,    Minister    of    Information(Item 5).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Items 1-4).Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-4).Lieutenant-General A. E. Nye, Vice-Chief of the Imperial General Staff(Items 1-4).Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings IsmaY.Brigadier Hollis.Colonel E. I. C. Jacob.[24182]
WAR CABINET 101 (42).Contents.minute no. . Subject. page 1      General War Situation and Future Operations........    1772      Parliament    ............................    177Supplies to Russia.3      Parliament     ...........................     177Shipping Losses.4      Naval Construction Programme   ....      ....      ....      ....     1785      The Press      ...............&apos;.      .............178The Daily Worker.
177W.M. 101 (42),General WarSituationand future operations.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 95thConclusions,Minute 3.)1. The War Cabinet had a discussion on the general war situation and on future operations.A record of the discussion and of the Conclusions reachedis contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.Parliament.Supplies toRussia.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 96thConclusions,Minute 4.)2. The War Cabinet were informed that Mr. Shinwell, M.P.,had stated that in the Debate on the Consolidated Fund Bill he proposed to raise certain matters connected with the last convoy to north Russia. There was also a possibility that this question mightbe raised in the Lords.After a short discussion, the War Cabinet decided asfollows : (1) If matters relating to the convoys to Russia were raised,the House should at once move into Secret Session. an indication to this effect should be given to Mr. Shinwell.(2) If, nevertheless, the matter was raised and the House went into Secret Session, the line to be taken by the Govern-ment Spokesman should be as follows : He could make certain general observations asto the dangers attendant upon these convoys, but should make it clear that the operational details inregard to the arrangements made for their protec-tion could not be disclosed, even in Secret Session.He should add that the Government, after investi-gation, were satisfied that there had been no lackof care or resolution in this matter on the part ofthe responsible officers.(3) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs was asked totake up with M. Maisky the question of certain rumoursin regard to the recent convoy which, it was believed,emanated from Soviet quarters.Parliament.shipping losses.(previous references:W.M: (42) 91stConclusions,Minute 7, andW.M. (42) 86thConclusions,Minute 6.)3. The War Cabinet were informed that Mr. Shinwell, M.P.,had also stated that he intended to refer in Parliament to thequestion of Shipping Losses, particularly in regard to the questionwhether this country and the United States had reached any decision to adopt a common policy about publication of such losses.The War Cabinet-    vDecided that, if this point was raised, the House should move info Secret Session, when the answer given should&apos;be that the matter was still under discussion, and that thefigures of losses published by the United States Govern-ment were in some respects misleading; but that, sincethe institution of more extensive convoy arrangements bythe United States naval authorities, snipping losses had declined.
i784. The War Cabinet were informed that the First Lord ofthe Admiralty thought that certain modifications should now bemade in the programme of Naval construction approved by the WarCabinet in the previous April. *The main points were as follows: (1) That nine intermediate aircraft-carriers should be laiddown in addition to the four approved in the last new construction programme. This would mean that fourcruisers, a mine-sweeper and two cargo liners wouldhave to be cancelled; the cruisers would not have beencompleted for four years in any case. It would also involve delay to four other cruisers, six destroyers, somemine-sweepers and about twelve merchant vessels.(2) It was also proposed to cancel four twin-screw corvettesand to replace them by seven single-screw corvettes.The Prime Minister said that he was in general agreementwith these measures, but thought that the First Lord of theAdmiralty should, perhaps, go further and cancel the laying down of the very large type of destroyers, which would take two years tocomplete, the capacity thus released being used to build a larger number of smaller destroyers, which could be completed withinabout a year&apos;s time. He thought that there would be an over-whelming need for an increase in anti-submarine convoys in thefollowing year.The War Cabinet-Agreed that this matter should be investigated by aCommittee of Ministers, a report being made to the WarCabinet.[Note. Subsequent to the Meeting, it was decided that theCommittee should be composed as follows : .The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs,The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,The Minister of Production, andThe First Lord of the Admiralty.]naval construction programme.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 53rd .Conclusions,Minute 4.)The Press.The &quot; daily worker.&quot;(previous reference:W.M. (42) 70thConclusions,Minute 6.)5. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theHome Secretary and Minister of Home Security (W.P. (42). 323).The discussion and Conclusions reached are recorded in theSecretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.Great George Street, S. W. 1,August 1, 1942.



</content>
</cab>
