<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/173/2 images: 10-12</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DISTRIBUTION OF RATE SUPPORT grant memorandum by the Secretary of State for Northern ireland,        At the Prime Ministers request a small group of Ministers metunder my chairmanship to consider the issues relating to the distributionof rate support grant which were discussed by the Cabinet at their meetingon I November (CM(73) 52nd Conclusions, Minute 7).2.        We agreed on the following conclusions:a. It would be impossible for the Secretary of State for the environment to refrain from making changes in the distributionscheme which applies at present.b. Given that a new formula must be found, we consider thatthe arrangements which would on balance be most satisfactoryare as follows:-i. Domestic elementTo be fixed at lOp, with further additions in areas whererates would otherwise go up because of loss of grant or theeffects of the reorganisation of water and sewerage.ii. Needs elementThe formula to contain the special allowance for theSouth East proposed in CP(73) 118; but the weighting for london itself to be lower than the proposed 5 per cent andto be fixed at a rate which will result in the assistance whichLondon receives from it not exceeding this year&apos;s level.A further special weighting comparable to that for theSouth East to be introduced for the benefit of non-metropolitan local authorities in the West Midlands.copy NO67CP(73) 1225 November 1973CABINET
iii0       Resources elementTo be fixed at 27f per cent of total grant.c.        Having regard to the danger that the higher resourceselement and the greater protection proposed for domestic rate payers will encourage increased expenditure by local authorities,the spending Departments should issue a joint circular in the moststringent terms (which should be agreed with the Chancellor of theExchequer) enjoining those local authorities which gained from thenew distribution arrangements not to make corresponding increases in their spending programmes,3.   .     We concluded that the Secretary of State for the Environment shouldopen his negotiations with the local authorities on the basis described above.W WNorthern Ireland office November 19732


</content>
</cab>
