<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/43/17 images: 140-147</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   August 1944.SECRET. Copy No.  52W.M. (44)101st Conclusions.WAR CABINET 101 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the cabinet war Room on Friday, 4th August, 1944, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The Right Hon. the Earl of Halifax,His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador to theUnited States.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Colonel the Right Hon. oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies (Items 1 and 2).The   Right   Hon.    Sir   archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P.,  Secretary ofState for Air.The- Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade(Items 4 and 5).Colonel    the   Right    Hon.    J.    J.Llewellin, M.P., Minister of Food(Items 4 and 5).The  Right  Hon.   Lord   Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. &apos;Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., Minister of Supply (Items 4and 5).The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport (Items 4and 5).The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Items 1 and 2).Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[28044]b
WAR CABINET 101 (44).Contents.minute no.                                      Subject. page 1 Future World Organisation ....      ................ 2472 Ethiopia................................ 2473 Employment of German and Italian Prisoners of War .... 2494 Supplies from North America in Stage II ....      ....      .... 2495 Lord Halifax......................      .... 250
Future world organisation.(previous reference:W.M.(44)88thConclusions,Minute 4.)&apos;:X.&quot;1. The War Cabinet had before them a Report by theArmistice and Post-War Committee (W.P. (44) 406) on certain points which had been referred to them by the War Cabinet(W.M. (44) 88th Conclusions, Minute 4) in connection with theproposals for Future World Organisation which had been putforward by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (see.P. (44) 370 and W.P. (44) 220).The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs invited the WarCabinet to agree that the recommendations of the Armistice and post-War Committee should be taken as the instructions to theOfficial Delegation under Sir Alexander Cadogan which was about to proceed to Washington.Since the Committee reported we had received the text of thedraft scheme which the United States Government intended to lay before the forthcoming meeting. It was very satisfactory from our point of view. One point only was left in doubt. The Americanscheme contained a reference to arrangements for territorialtrusteeships, the details of which had not been filled in. It mightbe that the United States Government had omitted them merely because they wanted to see the turn which discussions might take.Our position as regards our Colonial territories was, however,perfectly clear. We should take our stand on the policy already approved by the War Cabinet (W.M. (44) 58th Conclusions,Minute 2). He recommended that Sir Alexander Cadogan&apos;s instruc-tions on this should be that, if proposals were put forward whichconflicted with that decision, he should say that he had no instruc-\ tions and must refer to London.The Prime Minister referred to the importance of bringing theFrench, and also the Dutch, in at the next stage in these discussions with the Americans. The instructions to Sir Alexander Cadoganshould, he felt, be in terms that the meeting which he was attendingwould be for preliminary exploration and discussion on the official level. The issues involved in the forthcoming discussions were ofgreat importance, and it was to be regretted that pressure hadbeen so great that the War Cabinet had not been able to devotecloser attention to them. He felt sure that the War Cabinet would wish Sir Alexander Cadogan all success in his Mission.The War Cabinet-(1) Took note of the above statements.(2) Approved the report by the Armistice and Post-war committee (W.P. (44) 406) as the basis for preliminaryand exploratory discussion on the official level.(3) Agreed that if the question of territorial trusteeship was raised, Sir Alexander Cadogan should act as proposedby the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs at &quot; X.&quot;Ethiopia.    , 2.   The War Cabinet had before them the Report of the(Previous Committee on Policy in Ethiopia (W.P. (44) 416) which had been reference: appointed at their meeting on the 28th June, 1944 (W.M. (44)W.M.(44)83rd 83rd Conclusions, Minute 2), under the chairmanship of theConclusions, Chancellor of the Exchequer. The Report recommended the minute 2.) reopening of negotiations with the Emperor of Ethiopia and contained detailed proposals as to the line to be taken by our representatives on the resumption of negotiations.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the recommendationsof the Report were summarised in paragraph 16 of W.P. (44) 416and represented the unanimous view of the Committee. The report made it clear that the question of the precise degree of further financial assistance to be given to the Emperor should be left open,pending investigation by the Delegation which it was proposed tosend to Ethiopia.[28044], &quot;    b 2
The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs raised two points onthe Report: (a) Paragraph 13 (c) (iv) provided that the surrender of the franco-Ethiopian Railway should be conditional upon its being-held by the Ethiopian custodian of enemy property until the endof the war. He would prefer that no reference to this should bemade in any agreement with the Emperor. He felt that.we should aim at an arrangement by which joint control over the Railwayshould be exercised by the French, the Ethiopians and ourselves.This would be more likely to ensure the efficient running of theline.The War Cabinet agreed.(b) The Minister at Addis Ababa, without instructions from theForeign Office, had in discussion with the EmperOr indicated that wewould be ready to negotiate on the basis of the Emperor&apos;s own proposals. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs thoughtthat, quite apart from Mr. Howe&apos;s statement, we should find it easier to negotiate on that basis or, at any rate, to relate our negotiations to the proposals which the Emperor had put forward,and recommended that we should so proceed.After discussion the War Cabinet Agreed that it would be preferable to use the phrase &apos;&apos; inconsequence of the Emperor&apos;s proposals&quot; rather thancommit ourselves to basing our negotiations on them.(c) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs felt that if, as seemed likely, the United States were to take an interest in the ethiopian question, he would like to encourage them so-long as it did not interfere with our desiderata.The Prime Minister suggested that our policy should be tohelp the Americans and to work with them in this matter.The War Cabinet agreed.(d) The Secretary of State for Air pointed out with referenceto paragraph 13 (d) of the Report of the Committee that while nodifficulty arose as regards the requirements of the R.A.F.. in theterms of the Emperor&apos;s draft, the draft contained no provision forBritish civil air transport. He suggested that, in consultation withthe Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, he should adjust thedraft so as to secure facilities for our civil aviation, though thereshould be no question of our endeavouring to obtain exclusive rights.The War Cabinet-^Accepted the proposal of the Secretary of State for air and invited him to arrange the precise terms of the redraftwith the Secretary of&quot; State for Foreign Affairs.(e) The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs thought thatit would be well to inform the Dominions of what we were doingas regards Ethiopia, though he did not suggest that there shouldbe any question of consultation with them.The War Cabinet agreed.Subject to the points raised in the discussion, the WarCabinet-Approved the recommendations of the Committee on Policyin Ethiopia as set out in W.P; (44) 416.
Employmentof Germanand ItalianPrisonersoi War,(previous reference:W.M!.(44)90thConclusions,Minute 1.)3. At their meeting on the 12th July, 1944, the War cabinet invited the Minister of Labour and National Service to examine,in consultation with other Ministers, the possibility of employingGerman prisoners on agricultural work.The War Cabinet now had before them a Report by theMinister of Labour and National Service (W.P. (44) 421). Depart-ments had stated that they could employ up to 17,200 german prisoners. These would have to be housed in prisoner-of-war camps and the only suitable camps available were now occupied by non-co-operating Italians. In order to make room for the 17,000Germans, an equivalent number of non-co-operating Italians wouldhave to leave the camps and be given alternative accommodation.This could only be done if they changed their status and becameco-operators. The memorandum made recommendations for improving the amenities of co-operators in order to induce as manynon-co-operators as possible to change their status.In discussion the question was raised whether the precautionsfor guarding the German prisoners whilst at work were adequate.The Secretary of State for War gave an assurance on this point and added that no prisoners holding extreme Nazi views would beused; such prisoners were sent either to Canada or the UnitedStates.The War Cabinet-Approved the proposals in the Memorandum - by theMinister of Labour and National Service (W.P. (44) 421).Supplies from 4. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theNorth America Chancellor of the Exchequer and the . Minister of Productionin Stage II.     (W.P. (44) 419) about&apos;Supplies from North America in Stage II.This memorandum summarised the.more important questions whichwould have to be raised in forthcoming discussions with theCanadian Government and the United States Administration.Attached to the memorandum was a fuller paper, dealing in detail with the British requirements after the close of the European war,and setting out the line of argument which it was suggested shouldbe adopted.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the view seemed tobe held in some quarters in the United States that the release ofman-power from the forces, which would follow on the defeat ofGermany, would ease our position very greatly, and that there couldbe a very great restriction in the scope and volume of supplies madeavailable to us under Lend-Lease. Our first task was to convince them that the supplies we intended to ask for would give us no morethan the minimum required to enable us-i(a) to play our part in the Japanese war;(b) to begin as soon as possible in Stage II the recovery and expansion of our export trade; and(c) to do what was urgently necessary by way of&apos; rehousing andrestoration and some slight improvement in the meagrestandards of our civil economy.We had to convince the Americans and Canadians that such provision properly qualified for Lease-Lend or Mutual1 Aid; thattheir promises of supplies should constitute a firm- commitment onwhich we could plan effectively the disposition of our man-power;and finally that in the long run it was to their interests that weshould receive assistance to this extent and on these terms in stage II.
Lord Halifax. 5. . The Prime Minister said that Lord Halifax would shortly be returning to the United States. His presence at War Cabinetmeetings had been of the greatest value. He and his colleagueswished Lord Halifax a continuance of the success which had attended his mission at Washington and warmly congratulated himupon the high honour recently conferred upon him by The King.Lord Halifax thanked the Prime Minister for what he had said.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,Uh August, 1944.In the course of discussion, which showed general agreementwith the point of view set out in the memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer and Minister of Production, the following points were made.(a) The figures in the memorandum about the size of theServices in Stage II assumed that our forces one year after the defeat of Germany would be between 65 and 70 per cent, of theforces at mid-1944. These figures would, of course, require modifica-tion in the light of the Prime Minister&apos;s directive on man-power in Stage II (W.P. (44) 431).(b) The Prime Minister said that it was important that weshould let the Americans know the extent of the forces which we intended to deploy against Japan in Stage II, and should ask them whether they wished those forces to be supplemented in any respect,making it clear that, since the whole of our resources were fullystretched, we should have to continue to rely on their aid in regardto shipping, for example, and munitions. The position would beclearer when certain decisions had been reached as to our far eastern strategy.(c) Lord Halifax said that we should have to make great efforts to persuade the Americans that we were not seeking to gain an undueadvantage by continuing to receive, in Stage II, Lend-Lease goods which were not essential from the point of view of winning thewar. It was essential that the broad lines of the picture set out inthis paper should be brought home to those in the highest authority in the United States administration.(d) It was explained that the statement on page 12, paragraph40 (a), that the food programme contemplated would permit of some small easement on the present rations was inaccurate. Theprogramme in question permitted no suqh easement.(e) It was generally felt that the most difficult part of the case to put across was our requirements for continued supply of rawmaterials on Lend-Lease. In the end we might have to agree that,while we should continue to get on Lend-Lease the raw materialsrequired for explosives and munitions. Lend-Lease procedure would not cover raw materials required for general civilianmanufacture.(/) It was pointed out that in the long run it was, of course, inthe best interests of the United States that we should build up our export position in Stage II, since otherwise our purchasing power would be gravely diminished, and this would have a serious effect on united States export industries.The War Cabinet-Gave general approval to the memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer and the Minister of Produc-tion (W.P. (44) 419) as indicating the general line to betaken in the forthcoming discussions and as a brief for use by Ministers in these discussions.



</content>
</cab>
