<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/222/0 images: 35-39</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO  BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care.may be taken to ensure the seci&apos;8cy oi this document.(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC KAJESTY&apos;3 GOVTiRNMENT] SECRET..CP.   154  (51)  A* COPY NO.,CABINET.MINES DEPARTMENT EMERGENCY ORGANISA!IONCOMMITTEE.Note by the Home Secretary.I circulate herewith a Memorandum prepared by the Mines Department, setting out the emergency organisation of that Department for consideration in connection with the Report of the Cabinet Committee (paper CP. 154 (31))   (item 4 of the Agenda for the meeting of the Cabinet on June 17th, 1931).(Sgd. )    J.R.CLYNES.Home Office,16th June, 1931.
IffilEb DJ^ARTMEIH: EMERGENCY ORGANISATION.The Mines Department is responsible for providing an organisation to deal with all matters relative to tne conservation, distribution, and,  if necessary, importation of fuel during an emergency.On the declaration by Royal   Proclamation of a state of emergency, the Emergency Powers Act, 1920,  comes into operation.       Regulations are issued under that Act eqp^ering th Secretary for Mines to issue Directions with regard to fuel supplies.These Directions provide for(i)  The maintenance of priority arrangements for meeting the essential requirements of house-holders, industries producing food and drink, 1 hospitals, gas works,  electrieitj? works, sewage works and other public utility under- . takings.(ii) The restriction of the supplj&apos; of fuel to households.(iii)  The curtailment of industrial coal consumption.(iv) The restriction of railway and steamship services.(v) Economy in the use of gas and electricity.The detailed administration of the Directions is placed upon the Local Authorities, but in order to secure propercontrol and co-ordination of the work the Mines department has set up an organisation as follows  :-Distribution -    11 Divisional Coal Officers each incharge of a group of counties.124 Coal Emergency Officers,  each in charge of a group of Local Authorities areas.These officers are Civil Servants appointed by and directly responsible to the Secretary for lanes, and their function is to co-ordinate the work of administering the Directions with regard to coal distribution.
Committees of coal merchants and factors, serving in a purely advisory capacity, supply the Local Authorities and the Goal Emergency Officers with technical advice on coal distribution.supplies the national control and co-ordination of the available supplies of coal for inland purposes are in the hands of an officer at the Headquarters of the Mines Department appointed by and responsible to the Secretary for MInes*In each coalfield there is a Supplies Officer (a Civil Servant) who is the Chief Executive Officer and a uember of a District Coal Emergency Committee which supervises the sending forward of the coal which is in the hands of the coal owners.. Representatives of producers and distributors, appointed by the Secretary for Mines, also serve on these Committees,Goal for export or btmkers is controlled&apos; by a Shipping Sub-Committee at Headquarters and local Shipping Committees at the five principal ports.      These Committees are appointed by the Secretary for Mines and consist of Civil Servants representing Government Departments,A chart setting out the Mines Department Emergency Organisation is attached.It will be noted that all sections of the organisation are appointed by and directly responsible to the Secretary for Mines, and that all the key positions are held and the executive control exercised by Civil Servants.        The machinery of coal distribution is, however, so complex that it is essential to secure the goodwill of producers and distributors    /
and to use existing trade machinery to the fullest extent in times of emergency.      For- this purpose coal owners, factors, merchants and exporters are brought into the organisation where necessary in an advisory capacity./lines Department.June 16th,  1931.
COSecretary for Minos.Central Coal Emergency Committee (dealing with fuel questions affecting more than ono Government Department).Shipping Subcommittee,Local Coal Shipment Emergency Committees at five principal ports.Local Authorities.Advisory Committees of Local Coal Merchants.11 Divisional Coal Officers.124 Coal EmergencyOfficers (assisted &quot;by AdvisoryCommittees of CoalMerchants).Inland Supplies Officers at Headquarters.Local Supplies Officers.District Coal - Emergency Committees inthe c^alproducingareas.DMH.16.6.31.

</content>
</cab>
