<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/222/0 images: 531-545</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toononrfi thethe secrecy of this document.In March;, I950s 1 requested Sir John Snail; the Chairman of the TSXeotrlcity Commissioners, to undertake an investigation Into the present methods of distributing electricity in Great Britain and to advise mo &quot;by what methods technical and other Improvements could he effected with a vie?? to reducing the cost of transmission and di atributiont. making supplies in rural areas ao.ro generally available v standardising systemss pressures and methods of charge f, s-oduoing costs to the consumer and simplifying the organisation of the Industry. Sir John Snail was also instructed to indicate-s what legislation vras neeijsrs-ary In order to give effect to such improvementso     He has-, not mads 5-1 review of the position and certain general conclusions ct-n fcs drawnoIt -will be re-called that while the Report of Lord 19&apos;oir&apos;s Committee In 1986 and the legislation based upon it (Ekestricity (Supply) Act., 1925) , havo provided for a national scheme of generation of electricity.s no comprehensive consideration has hitherto I)eon given to the problem of distrlbutiono     Yet in order to sscure a progressive d ovelopaent of the national electricity supply on modern lifts s an efficient distributive system is of no less Importance than an efficient system of gene rot ion.The cost of distribution (including capital charges) is on the average CoO^d. for each unit sola to consumers,, while the total cost (including capital chargers) averages X.83do so that distribution counts for 50 per cent of the price of electricity soldo   - fhsre tha terms &quot;cost of distribution&quot; op &quot;total cost&quot; are used in this Memorandum they include in the case of Local Authorities intwreat and Sinking Fund charges or. capital borrowed and in the  as** of Compahieo depreciation on and renmncration of capital employodo
- 2 -This figure is? of oouras, the average for the country and includes the large industrial supplies which are given at a very low price.     In supplies for other purposes including domestic, small power9 agricultural, etc, vhere the cost is much higher, the proportion attributable to distribution is also increased..Moreover while the oost of generation is falling and under the Grid system of the Central Electricity Board will continue to fall steadily, the cost of distribution is remaining practically stationary with a tendency in some cases actually to rise.The fundamental defect in the present system of distribution is that the areas are too small.     This hampers technical development and militates against efficient management0 Under the Electric Lighting Acts it has been the custom to grant powers to loeal authorities or to oompanies to supply electricity within the limits of Local Government Districts;    in modern technical practice such boundaries have no relevance but under existing legislation it is almost impossible to escape from them.     At present there are over        separate undertakings.     Of these no less than 135 have been created since 1920, the majority of which possess small distribution areas but under existing conditions the only alternative would have been to refuse the applications for powers and thus deny to residents in the areas affected the advantages of an electrical supply by a statutory undertaker at all.Although a tendency exists for some of the smaller company undertakings to be absorbed by their larger neighbours, this is. oounteraoted by the provision that the right of the public to purchase company undertakings at the end of their franchise ia conferred on individual local authorities, and thus existing homogeneous areas may in the next few years be broken up by the exercise on behalf of the public   of the rights of purchase held by individual local authorities.TlHIWIIIIiIII-Mil II.....IBIIIIIIIIIIIIillilllllllilW
This severance of urban centres from the surrounding rural areas is technically a retrograde stepa     For instance at the moment the Town Council of Cirencester are considering purchasing their undertaking which forms an integral part of the technical development of the area round0      Similarly,, Ilacclesfield is contemplating separating itself from the adjoining territorys and Oxford has recently cut itself off from its own suburbs.Under existing legislation therefore purchase by a public authority is often wholly wrong from a technical stand-point and local authorities are often obliged to choose between the continuance of a private company&apos;s tenure and the damage to the electrical development of an area entailed in piecemeal purchase.While the authorised distribution areas cover 90 per cent of the urban population and 82 per cent of the rural-populations more or less satisfactory development has only been attained in the more densely populated areas.     If improvements are to be rapidly effected, it will be neoessary to break down the existing division of the country between over 66*0 distribution undertakings, many of them extremely small, and to overcome the difficulty which arises in making electricity generally available throughout the country by reason of the independent development of the more densely populated  areas and their separation from those in which it is economically more difficult to provide an adequate supplyoA few figures may be of interest at Jlst March, 1930, there were 668 separate authorised undertakers, with areas of supply covering a total population (1921 Census) of approximately 40,000,000*     The total number of oonsumers supplied was 5,470s000 which on the basis of 4=5 persons per dwelling represents about Ip^000?000 persons or upwards of one-third of the total population of Great Britain^
- h. -Out of 59ij- undertakings giving supplies in 1928/29? in respeot of which particulars &quot;both as to sales and also population of area of supply are available, no less than 25k sold under 50 units of electricity per head of population in their respective areas, sold under 100 units per head and501 sold under 200 units per heado     Thus only 93 undertakingss or about one-sixth of the totals sold over 200 units per heado The areas of supply of these 95 undertakings contain a population of over 1^,000,000 and the number of consumers supplied 1,218,000 which on the same basis of persons per dwelling represents a population of 5sk.o0v0QQ persons supplied,,Many   undertakings which have &quot;been operating for over 25 years are still selling under 60 units per head.On the technical side there are many undertakings still giving supplies by both alternating and direct current   and in 1928/29j, 159 undertakings were still supplying direct current aloae,     &quot;While the majority of under takings operated within a range of some 8 principal voltages, there &quot;were,still 44 declared voltages in operation between the limits of 100 volts and 4-80 voltso     The scope end need for standardisation, in this matter is obvious;    an aspect of considerable importan.ee to the manufacturing industry,Financially, one result of the establishment of so many small undertakings is a high investment of capital In distribution.     In the case of 155 undertakings, each of which sold between 1,000,000 and 5,o0o200o units, the average investment was about  59 per 1,000 units sold, whereas for !$ . undertakings, each of which sold over 5,000,000 units9 the average was only  21-g-.-.ISxaxainatlon shows that in spite of improvement in many undertakings, the distribution costs per unit averaged over the whole country are remaining almost stationary, although it must
not be overlooked that costs are temporarily increased by the cost of improvements during the transitional period and by the faot that a proportion of recent capital has been expended in the leas remunerative districts,.     There has also been a marked increase in rates and tsxesoThe effect of price upon consumption le strikingly exemplified in electricity supply.     In the case of the smaller undertakings each selling under 5,000,000 units the number of units sold per 51 of distribution capital amounted, on an average, to 21*5 only and the cost of distribution averaged l,2i-26dc per unit soldo     Many of the smaller undertakings, whose distribution costs exceed 2^-d. per unit sold, cannot hope to improve greatly so long as they continue on a self-contained basis since they cannot offer supplies at a figure likely to attract new customs in sufficient amounteBroadly, it maybe stated that the sales of eleatrloity per consumer8 or per head of population, bear an inverse ratio both to the average revenue per unit sold and to the distribution oosts per unit sold, increasing in each case as the latter deoreases.     Increased output invariable accompanies a reduction in the price charged to consume rs0While, in my opinion, a great deal more than is   being done oan be done by efficient salesmanships the framing of suitable end attractive tariffs and a confident policy of advance upon the part of this growing industry - considerations which I have constantly pressed upon the industry - we shall not obtain the best results for the country as a whole unless a reorganisation takes place ^hich will lower the distribution costs of the smaller undertakers and enable consequential reductions in charges to be made to the consumer,,     Hitherto olectricity supply has been largely regarded as an engineering
problem.     We have now reached the stage when a sound economic organisations, a go-ahead sales and service policy end proper commercial development must be brought fully into play.I may illustrate the unsatisfactory state of present organisation by reference to a single instance taken in the area of the Yorkshire Electric Power Company, In the town of Brighouse the sales of electricity by the local undertaking in I929/5O amounted to 9^6,000 unite. The Power Company sold in the same area 1,212,000 units. It is not surprising that the distribution sosts in Brighouse amounted to the high figure of over l^d. per unit.Recognising that the pr;.ee charged to the industrial power user should be at the low rate charged by the Power Company the fact that two classes of supply.are given by two separata undertakers in the same place must obviously result in unnecessary duplication of mains and capital expenditure and have an adverse of foot upon development and the ability to attract domestie consumers.I may add that the number of units sold by the local undertaking has remained almost stationary sinoe 1920 and even now represents only 21 units per head of population,,Again, in the areas of the      authorised undertakings of the Electrical Distribution of Yorkshire, Ltd. , the sales in 1929/30 by the Distribution Company were 18,000,000 units, whereas the Power Company sold over 104,000,COO units direct to consumers for power purposes.     The result is that the eapital expenditure on distribution averaged over those ;?8 undertakings about  95 per 1,000 units sold and the distribution costs ?,226d. per unit sold.The general conclusions drawn by Sir John -Snell from his survey of the existing position are as follows;-
POOR QUALITY OF IMAGE





(I) i.n the gr 3 at.&apos; mr*3 orl ty of the. undertakings ibariff &amp; are too high.; .fS:) Sales per cohauw.es&apos; or per head hear an ij&amp;vorse relation ft ^ the average revenue pez* unit, soldi;(.3) The cost per unit is necessarily ^Hf^ii^-d tij the eest of generation and distribute vn-.The Aoi of 1926 *vill have the effect of atsadily reducing and evening out the cost of generation throughout the whole countrys out the cost of&apos; 0 i.:j&apos;&apos;i?-\brit&apos;t w ipe/aeins dependent on the operations of some oOO individual mdartakers.:[J;-) with csrtain exceptions s the coat of distribution ih &apos;he smaller undertakings is so much higher than is* the ease of the larger under-takings that the -arxffs to consumers auot remain too . high to secure a Rapids e&amp;expansion and t&amp;e most ia.porta!?.t cause of this high eost is the actual of the vmiertaking.-,Xn Siff John Brae 11113 8 opinion? with *hieh the ElectrieitGosscii saioxiere? generally agree ? amalgamation into larger are sowouvd reduce the cost of die tribut ion by savings nndes&apos; thefollowing heads/-(1)   Technicals    (savings on high tension distributionmams 9 ete)g12)   Administrative-.; (savings due to uniform!ty of tariffs from simplifleaiien of legal procedures, etc,)?(5)   Managerial-,  (savings in higher staff end improvedmanegementhis to she appointment of better qualified off leers)!,-In considering the savings      be anticipated by n eo&amp;pletS reorganir0ntien of disW^lbuticnj Sir John Shell hae pointed out that these cannot be estimated with the same degree if rslrri&amp;ility fts in the ease vf generation aa there are many intangible factors which will all eontrihnte. towards impeoveme^ and saving but e^anot c.p. calculated with, sufficient prseioien to allcslF of - any useful i estimate.!He Siaa made a detailed examination of the probable r* sir.lt 0 of essaigaxaatlosli ox&apos; the *js ^n^eatkkinRs in- Mid fSastiSBgi,fj\na operating wves* an atvA,o^ upware-w of /"pfjOO a?ojuar*j &amp; &apos;J2(jOXa&apos;kii.tf aoent 4"? million   inhabitants^
Without assuming any marked improvement as regards larger undertakings within that area, he estimates that in the year 1955-56 there would &quot;be a saving in capital expenditure of about  2,000,,, 000 under amalgamation as contrasted with individual development? an. output (sales of electricity) of 1*8.53 million units under combined working as compared with I559^ million unit&amp;; under separate operations and an average revenue (i^e, average costis to the consumer) of loOldo per unit sold as compared with lol08dfl in the case of independent operation     This in effect will secure an anticipation in development of nearly four years and thus greatly assist the Central Electricity BoardoOn the output (sales) in 1955^\5  under amalgamste-i workings the savings to consumers in the Mid East England area la that year would thus be equivalent to about  750,000a     If similar savings resulted from amalgamated working in the remaining portions of the country, the savings to consumers on the basis of the estimated total sales in 1955^569 namely 11,500 million units, would be of the order of  k,500,.000 per annum0     In this connection it may be noted that there is scope i other portions of the country for larger savings on distribution than those estimated for the Mid East England areas. and this estimate does not make any allowance for the increased rate of growth due to the better management oIn considering possible methods of reform three courses have suggested themselvess^A complete reorganisation of t-h* whole supply industry involving the consolidation of all authorised undertakers as now constitutedc whether Power Companies, Distribution Companies, Local Authorities or Joint Electricity Authorities, into new regional public boards, under national directIon$ responsible for all distribution and commercial development over large area so 2o A reorganisation involving a redistribution of present
Q   - iri ,authorised, areas end some disturbance of ownership, &quot;but based.as far as possible on existing conditions and allotting to the predominant interest in each area the adjacent undertakings. The Iresult would be that in some areas the Power Companies would fcakeliover other Companies and the undertakings of local author!tieao   I In other areas existing   local authority undertakings would become the distribution authority for the whole district, taking over&quot; by exercise of existing rights of purchase, or otherwises, the Company undertakings and absorbing the minor local authority undertakings.A position would then emerge in which distribution wouldbe organised in large areas under -(1) Distribution Boards or Joint&apos; -Electricity Authorities,       and(2): Power Companies (subject to increased measures of public control).A less complete reorganisation might be contemplatedfollowing as closely as possible the existing structure butsecuring the compulsory amalgamation of suitable groups of smalldistribution undertakings into larger undertakings and/or the absorption by existing larger undertalcings of their smallneighbourSoThis scheme would involve some transfer of local authority undertakings to companies and also transfers in th-opposite directiono&quot;I may say at once that I greatly prefer Scheme lo    it isa complete solution of the problems it secures the maximum degree of technical efficiency and of economy and, therefore, of de:slopes it is also in full accord with, the lines on which, politically,, % should wish to ace reorganisations proceed.   A limited number- of regional boards linked up in a national scheme with the Central Electricity Board, which is now the generating and main transmission authority, would be &apos;bsjond dispute the most effective organisation from a technical point&apos; of view-., She Distribution Boards being responsible for all local
secondary transmission lines and for the development of all distribution mains within their area would be able to give a uniform system of supply at the standard frequency and at one or two uniform voltages declared to the consumers,,     They would adopt so far as practicable a uniform two-part tariffs whioh would be a favourable one to consumers;    they would secure all the advantages of large seals operation,, whilo the disappearance of tho existing purchase rights of individual local authorities would remove what is no doubt a hampering influence on rapid development on the part of companies whose franchise lss 03? appears to them to bef expiring.     Moreover the operations of the Central -Electricity Board would be greatly simplified.On the other hand it cannot be disguised that such an ambitious scheme would give rise to formidable opposition,, Hot only are the Power Companies likely to object to being expropriated (however fair and reasonable the financial terms of transfer proposed might be), but the large municipalities might and, I fears, would object violently to losing the control of the many important local distribution systems now in their hands.     We should have tc. utilise all our powers of appeal to national as against local and vested interests,A further consideration which the Chairman of the Central Electricity Board has impressed upon me is that? from the point off view of the development of the Grid, any disturbance of the electrical industry at this moment is to be deprecated.     This objection would not be so strong if any scheme once launched were certain of successp but a scheme of reorganisation which threw the Industry into a state of turmoil and nevsrr reached the Statute Book would undoubtedly have adverse reactions upon normal developmento.
At this stage I do not think It necessary to enter in detail upon the financial questions which would arise in connection with the     formation of any such regional hoards as I have indioateds but8 as in the case of the London Passenger Transport Board8 I think we should proceed upon the basis that the scheme should be self-supporting and should not require the backing either of the local rates or the national Exchequero     It would, howevers he essential that in any new legislation the terms of acquisition of the undertakings of the Power and Distribution Gompanies and the terms of transfer of Public Authority undertakings should be clearly laid down in order to avoid the protracted delays and great expense which would arise from a series of contested arbitrations..The magnitude of the financial operations involved is indicated by the following figures which are of a tentative character onlyi-The issued capital of the Power Companies at the end of 1929 was of the order of  415,900,000 and the capital expenditure of the remaining Company undertakers (other than the London Companies) was approximately  ^Ij,700,000j   while the outstanding debt of all the Public Authority undertakings at the end of 1928-29 was approximately  llJf j,000,0009 making a total of about  187s600s000oAssuming a besis of 18   years purohase for the transfer of the Company undertakings9 the cost to the Regional Boards of th$se undertakings (including generating stations) would be approximately  849500,000$   while the transfer of the net debt in the case of Public Authority undertakings (including generating stations) would represent a further  114,000,000 as above, making  198,500,000 in all.
It la probable that under any such Scheme of reorganisations the selected generating stations and financial obligations relating thereto would be taken over by the Central Electricity Board.&apos;     But it is clear that when account is taken of the further- expansion of the Electricity Supply Industry since the dates referred to above a reorganisation of the Industry would involve a transfer or disturbance of capital of the order of  200.000s000, apart from any additional amount- involved if we were also to deal with the fourteen London&quot;Companies.Without further enquiriesp which I have been unable to make9 I do not know what reception such a Scheme would receive from the more powerful interests affected and as I have already indicated, I doubt whether we should be able to present anything in the nature of an agreed measure even if we were prepared to devote a year to negotiations.       Given Liberal support (and the Yellow Book commits them) we&apos;should have to go forward and either fight or conciliate them.As regards Scheme 2, namely, a reorganisation with Distribution Boards and power  Companies, I feel that we should encounter much of the opposition(including resistance to transfer of municipal undertakings to private ownership) which would face us In connection with Scheme 1P though, of courses, not perhaps to the same degree..     The effect on the operations off the Central Electricity Board would also be similar.   While I do not deny that substantial advantages might   be gained from a reorganisation on these lines, I should feel difficulty in recommending a proposal which would transfer municipal undertakings to companies and might be represented as likely to entrench the Power Companies to an extent which would make
it more difficult to proceed In the near future with the full national reorganisation at which,, I think, we should aim.Scheme * Is a proposal to take a first step towards amalgamation by eliminating the smallest of the undertakings in which the most serious of the difficulties due to inadequate si e of area arise.      Under this Scheme, while no drastic changes will b-? mode in the larger areas, powers would be taken for the preparation of Individual schemes in various parts of the country by which the smaller undertakings would be compulsorily amalgamated with their larger neighbours., In so far as these small undertakings are companies or are small municipalities which can be united for electrical purposes with other neighbouring municipal undertakings little difficulty would ar:is* but in order to complete the process we should be faced with the problem of the transfer of some publicly owned undertakings to companies, offset to some extent but not entirely by corresponding transfers elsewhere of company undertakings to local authorities or public distribution boards..     This Scheme while possessing somes advantages as a first step is, if it is regarded as a final measure, less attractive from a technical and financial point of view, and would not; altogether avoid political difficulties. Regarded as anything but a first step I should not be in favour of this policy but I am exploring it further to ascertain to what extent it can be regarded as a useful beginning,,I have also under consideration the desirability of a measure strengthening and rendering more effective the powers of the Minister to control the prices charged by companies.     While in general the Minister has power to fix
maximum prices, the present method is somewhat clumsy and may he capable of considerable improvements.     It ia also desirable to attain some powers for securing uniformity so far as possible between methods of charge in adjacent areas. Suggestions as to the points which might be covered   are contained in the Appendix to this memorandum.If a measure is introduced for this purpose it might be most useful to couple with it a power to require the amalgamation of the small areas whose isolation makes it impossible to introduce reasonable prices,I have not in this memorandum thought it advisable or necessary to go into any question of finance or to discuss tho type of organisation which might be appropriate for the various Boards which would be formed under any of the three schemes mentioned,     I merely wish to Indicate to my colleagues that, if we desire in the present Parliament to deal with the problem of distribution of electricity it would be possible to formulate legislation for introduction in the course of next Session,I recommend that we should in any case keep open the possibility of introducing a Bill and, if desiredj 1 will submit a further memorandum indicating in brief outline what would be necessary under the full Scheme 1 and also the heads of an alternative Bill strengthening the Minister9s powers to control the charges made bt, the Electrical IndustryP and giving compulsory powers for the amalgamation of small existing undertakings on a basis which would conform to the ultimate requirements for the national scheme of organisation.(Intd) H,M,8/7/51.
Suggestions for more effective control of lleotricity prices.lo   On any price revision the Minister should have power to fix a maximum for each class of supply whether separate prices are contained in the original Order cr note29   The Minister should have power to order an undertaker to adopt a two-part tariff and following on the previous suggestion to fix maximum prices under that tariff.3o   The Minister should have p$wer, on the recommendation of the Commissioners, to alter the maximum at shorter periods than three years, though no power should &quot;be given to local authorities or consumers to initiate proceedings for price revision at shorter- intervals.     The object of this provision is to enable the Minister, if ho sees fit, to impose as a maximum price the aetual^^rlce which ho thinks ought to be charged without leaving the accessary margin for contingencies which cannot be excluded if the price has to bo fixed for a period of three years.4.   Borne power might be given to the Minister to insist on greater uniformity of methods of charging for adjacent areas, a.go West London.     It is difficult to see how he could be given power to enforce a mi form tariff but he could insist on uniform methods.So    The Minister might have power to jUneist on the adoption of schemes for assisted wiring and hire purchase on terms approved by himself.8th July., 1931

</content>
</cab>
