<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/222/0 images: 623-627</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1931.CONFIDENTIAL.CP. 182 (31).CABINET.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs on Discussions in Paris, July 15-July 19, for Meeting of a Conference in London to consider German Financial Situation., 1931.I. Meeting of a Conference in London.1. ON the evening of my arrival in Paris (the 14th July), I received a &apos;&apos; Most Immediate &apos;&apos; telegram addressed to the Foreign Office (No. 424) by Sir R. Lindsay to the effect that the United States Government considered that the financial position of Germany had become so serious that the immediate summoning of a conference in London was necessary.2. Anxious to be informed of the views of His Majesty&apos;s Government in regard to this proposal before meeting the French Ministers on Wednesday, the 15th July, I telephoned to the Prime Minister and ascertained that it would be in accordance with his wishes that I should persuade the French Government to agree to a meeting of a conference in London after our return from Berlin.3. The result of my first meeting with the French Ministers was reported in Paris telegram No. 164 of the 15th July.4. In that telegram I made it clear that the French Ministers were not at that moment prepared to take any immediate decision as regards the meeting of a conference as they felt that it would be a mistake to summon a conference Avithout a preliminary decision as to its objective. The French Prime Minister expressed himself as strongly in favour of our adhering to our intention of visiting Berlin, but felt that the French Government must await our report on the situation in Berlin before coining to any final decision in regard to a conference.5. After the meeting with the French Ministers I received a visit from the German Ambassador, wdio informed me that the position in Germany had slightly improved, but it was still so serious that Dr. Bruning had requested him to ask my opinion as to whether he should not at once come to Paris for purposes of consultation with the French Government. I replied that I could not at the moment advise such a course in view of what had been said by M. Laval and other Ministers in the course of the conversations which had taken place that day.6. I then saw Mr. Stimson and informed him of the result of my discussion with the French Ministers. We agreed that we should meet the French together on the following day at 11 o&apos;clock to continue the discussions.7. Such was the position on the evening of Wednesday, the 15th July, when I left for the Colonial Exhibition to dine with the French Minister of the Colonies, who had arranged a dinner in my honour.8. During the evening a message reached me from the Embassy trans-mitting the Prime Ministers message to me which had been telephoned by Sir F. Leith-Ross, indicating that a serious situation was developing in London as a result of which it was necessary that immediate action should be taken. Having considered the position, I decided to consult the French Prime Minister without delay. Fortunately he was at hand as he had been one of the guests at the dinner.5961   [5753] copy No.    5this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s government
9. I told M. Laval that the situation appeared to be such that a decision to summon a conference was urgently required, and I pressed him to agree to come to London for that conference. M. Laval strenuously resisted my proposal, supported by the French Minister of the Colonies, whom he had summoned into the consultation. He urged strongly that I should agree to a conference in Paris. Finally, after a discussion lasting over an hour, I induced M. Laval to agree, subject to the approval of the French Council of Ministers, to attend a conference in London on the following Tuesday (the 21st July) on the condition that the German Ministers would first visit Paris with a view to discussion with the French Ministers. M. Laval made it clear that, without such preliminary discussion in Paris, he had no hope of being able to induce his colleagues to agree to participate in a conference in London.10. I told M. Laval that, while it might be necessary in the new circuiii-stances for the Prime Minister to postpone his visit to Berlin. I would go there on the following afternoon if onlv for the purpose of inducing the German Ministers not to delay their departure for Paris.11. On returning to the Embassy with a view to reporting my conversation with M. Laval to the Prime Minister, I was informed of the arrival of a further message which had been received from Sir R. Vansittart, to the effect that the urgency of the situation permitted of no further delay and that invitations had accordingly been issued to the Powers concerned for a conference in London at 6 p.m. on Monday, the 20th.12. Though the hour was late, I immediately got into touch with M. Laval on the telephone and informed him of this fresh development. He did not appear to take any exception to the alteration of the plans which I had agreed with him only ah hour or so before; but he emphasised the fact that the proposal would only be acceptable to the French Government if the German Ministers first came to Paris.13. It was past midnight before t was able to get into touch with London and speak with the Prime Minister, when I informed him of the position reached as a result of the action I had taken on the receipt of the latest telegrams.1-1. After speaking to the Prime Minister I saw the German Ambassador, whoni I had asked to call upon me at the. Embassy. I told him that I had just informed M. Laval that a conference had been called to commence on Monday next, and that he had informed hie&apos; that the French Government could only go to London if preliminary discussions took place with the German Ministers in Paris. This had caused me to change the opinion I had expressed earlier in the evening, and t now considered vital that the German Ministers should come at once to Paris. M. von Hoesch undertook to communicate by telephone with Berlin and let me know the decision of the German Ministers in the morning.15. On Thursday morning (the 16tli) M. von Hoesch informed me that he had received a reply from Berlin, and that he was communicating with M. Briand to the effect that, if the French Government issued an invitation to the German Ministers, they were willing to come to Paris, but could not leave Berlin before Friday evening (the 17th).16. After a further conversation with the Prime Minister reporting this -development. I proceeded to the Ministry of the Interior for the meeting with the French Ministers and Mr. Stimson, which had been arranged on the preceding day.17. After elaborating proposals for the assistance of Germany, which he said he intended to submit for the consideration of the Council of Ministers, which had been summoned to meet at 5 P.M. that afternoon, Mr. Laval stated that, after the Ministerial Council had taken place, M. Briand would invite the German Chancellor and Dr. Curtius to come to Paris immediately. M. Laval ;sa,id that the first act on their arrival would be a Franco-German conversation. This was essential in the present State of French public opinion&apos; Then would follow a general conversation in which British, French, Americans and Germans would participate. M. Laval stated that it would be essential, so far as his Government was concerned, that a decision of principle should be taken.
Ministers could then proceed to London to settle the details of application of these principles. I then said care would have to be taken; only America, Great Britain, Germany and France would be represented in Paris, and other Powers might feel aggrieved if the general lines of agreement were reached in their absence.18. That afternoon I received the Prime Ministers telegram in response to a suggestion I had made that Sir F. Leith-Ross might come to Paris, urging me to resist any tendency in the direction of the development of the Conference in Paris, and deprecating a visit by Sir F. Leith-Ross to Paris lest it should confirm or strengthen that tendency.19. I replied that I had throughout resisted any idea of the transfer of the Conference from London to Paris; but that the chances of the French Ministers attending the Conference in London would be seriously prejudiced if any attempt were made to interfere with the arrangement under which the French and German Ministers would first meet in Paris in order to secure agreement in principle, and would then take part in a general conversation at which Mr. Stimson and myself would be present.20. On the following morning, Friday, the 17th, I attended a further meeting with the French Ministers at the French Ministry of the Interior, in company with Mr. Stimson. In the course of this meeting there was considerable discussion as regards the programme and character of the conversations in Paris. Mr. Stimson and I both made it clear that we had no authority from our Govern-ments to allow the meetings to take the place of the Conference which had been summoned to meet in London, and that we could not participate in any discussions which might have the effect of anticipating the decisions of the London Conference.21. M. Laval said that he appreciated the position and was prepared to accept our conditions, although he made it clear that, unless agreement was reached in principle between the French and German Ministers, the French Government could not be present at the London Conference.22. I thought it better to reserve any final decision as regards participation in the joint conversations arranged for Sunday, the 19th. with the German Ministers, pending consultation with the Prime Minister.23. On informing the Prime Minister by telephone of the events of the morning&apos;s proceedings, I received his authority to tell the French Prime Minister that I would attend the joint conversations on Sunday on the conditions whiei. had been laid down at the meeting on the previous day.24. I duly informed M. Laval of this decision on the following morning and that it was my intention to leave Paris by the 4 o&apos;clock train on Sunday (the 19th).25. M. Laval said that this arrangement would meet the views of the French Government and assured me that he would do everything possible to reach agreement with the German Ministers.26. The German Ministers arrived in Paris at 2-5 p.m. on the afternoon of the 18th July, and after a preliminary and private conversation with M. Laval and M. Briand, a Franco-German conversation took place at 4-30 p.m. at the Ministry for Foreign Affairs. A communique issued at the end of the meeting&quot; stated that it had had &quot; a most frank and cordial character, and had dealt not only with the measures necessary to meet the&quot; financial crisis, but also the whole field of Franco-German relations, in the mutual desire to establish a lasting collaboration between the two nations.&quot; The communique added that the Franco-German conversations would be continued this afternoon, the 19th July.27. Early to-day I received the German Chancellor at the Embassy, and a few minutes later Signor Grandi. A joint conversation then took place at 10 a.m. at the Ministry for the Interior. This was attended by the French and German Ministers, by myself, Mr. Stimson and Mr. Mellon,- Signor Grandi. M. Hymans and the Japanese Ambassador in Paris. The German Chancellor gave a brief outline of the economic and financial crisis in Germany, and indicated the need of a loan of 2 milliard marks as cover for the German notes circulation [5753] b 2
and further important short-term credits in place of the large amount of capital which had recently fled abroad. M. Laval stated that the Franco-German conversations had reached a stage which would make it possible for the French Government to be represented in London, particularly in view of the fact that the German Ministers had accepted the view originally expressed by Mr. Stimson, that the conference would be confined to the discussion of the question of the financial situation in Germany.II. French attitude to Financial Assistance to Germany.28. I will now summarise the information derived from the informal conversations in Paris as to the conditions on which the French Government will be disposed to participate in financial aid to Germany. The first object of the French, as appears particularly from my conversation with the French Ministers on the 15th July, was to obtain from the German Ministers definite information on conditions in Germany, both financial and political. &quot; We must know,-&apos; said M. Laval at the meeting of the 15th July, &quot; exactly what the situation is. Can the present Government commit itself in the name of the country? Does it represent her ? Is there a danger of its being replaced by Ffugenberg and Hitler 1 Is Germany ready to accept our conditions? :.&apos; From this and subsequent conversations with the French and American Ministers on the 16th July and with M. Flandin on the 16th July, I gathered that these conditions those of the grant of financial assistance included German acceptance of some financial supervision destined to watch the use made of that assistance, and German offers of adequate security for the service and amortization of the loan and of an assurance respecting a &quot; political moratorium.&quot;29. On the assumption that these conditions were fulfilled, the French Ministers indicated to me, notably in the interviews of the 16th July, that they would be ready tc^nroceed to London to discuss the question of the grant of financial assistance&apos; to Germany. In their view, formed before meeting the German Ministers, \ this assistance would most suitably be a loan of some 500 million dollars, the object of which would be to restore confidence. The loan would have to be issued (1) As an international loan in New York and London as well as in Paris;(2) In respect of the French portion under the French Government&apos;s guarantee, without which it could not be subscribed;(3) Against a security covering the loan as a whole and preferably the German Customs receipts;(4) To form a kind of reserve fund placed at the disposal of the Bank for International Settlements to be used for the support of the Reichsbank under the supervision of a committee composed of representatives of the lending countries; the special function of this committee would be to report any attempt by Germany to grant foreign loans or credits or generally to continue her present extravagant expenditure. (N.B. M. Laval specially mentioned increases in military expendi-ture and the building of new warships.)30. On learning from me on the evening of the 15th July of the serious repercussions on the London Market of a German financial collapse, M. Laval made it clear that the French Government would be anxious to do what was in their powTer to assist in preventing any such development. Beyond this the French Ministers told me that France herself has momentarily little direct financial Interest in Germany, and M. Laval quoted on the 16th July the case of the Credit Lyonnais, which was supposed to be deeply involved in German credits, but the German holdings of which, in fact, amounted only to some 80 million francs. According to the French Ministers, the immediate French interest in German financial stability was the resumption of reparation payments at the end of the Hoover postponement year. On the 16th July M. Laval stated that the French view was that the loan would imply no abandonment of the Young plan, and that the London Conference would not be competent to discuss the Young plan or the treaties of peace.
31. Mr. Stimson stated at the meeting of the 16th July that the London Conference would only be attended by American representatives on condition that its task was limited to consideration of the German financial crisis and that a public statement to that effect by His Majesty&apos;s Government was necessary. His view was that the conference could not take cognisance of the Treaty of Versailles or of war debts. On the other hand, in indicating the probability that American banks would be willing to take up part of the loan provided that part had not to be subject to . a Government guarantee (N.B. this proviso was accepted by M. Laval) he claimed that the service of the new loan should have priority over reparation payments.   M. Laval refused to admit this priority.32. The statements made by the German Chancellor and M. Laval at the general conversation on Sunday morning show that Germany requires not merely an immediate loan of 500 million dollars to cover German note circulation, but also important short-term credit to replace the milliard of marks recently with-drawn abroad. Mr. Stimson took the view that equally important with the task of raising this money was that of finding means to prevent a fresh drain on German credit. It was agreed, however, that the only question to be considered at the London Conference was financial crisis in Germany.Foreign Office, July 20, 1931.

</content>
</cab>
