<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/203/25 images: 355-381</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
document is the property of her britannic majesty&apos;s government cp(78) 100 copy no 8011 October 1978cabinetNAMIBIAMemorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth affairs. The Five Western Foreign Ministers on the Security Council will beholding talks next week with the South African Prime Minister and ForeignMinister in tne attempt to resolve the serious impasse now reached overNamibia.    These talks may confront us with some difficult and far-reaching decisions.2. The South African Government accepted that Proposal under whichNamibia would come to independence after elections under United Nations (UNsupervision, following a ceasefire between the South African forces andthe South West African People&apos;s Organisation (SWAPO).    SWAPO eventuallyaccepted our proposal also.    But when the Secretary-General prepared a detailed plan to give effect to it the South Africans backed off, at the sametime as there was political manoeuvring for the succession to Mr Vorster.3. The South Africans have objected that the Waldheim plan differsmaterially from our Proposal on a number of points.    Their mainobjections concern the size of the proposed UN force for Namibia, and the lack of consultation with them over it;  and the postponement of the elections(and thus of independence) beyond the target date of 31 December 1978.The only point of substance is the lack of consultation, which we feel is a genuine grievance.4. The South Africans decided in the light of this, to go aheadunilaterally with elections for a constituent assembly which could decide whether to go straight to independence or whether to implement the UN plan.The Security Council reacted on 29 September with a resolution whichapproved the Waldheim plan, called on South Africa to co-operate in implementing it, declared that any unilateral election in Namibia would beregarded as null and void, and asked the Secretary-General to report onthe implementation of the resolution by 23 October.    The South Africanshave since maintained the line that while they have not closed the door onthe UN plan, it will be up to the Namibians elected in early December todecide whether it should be implemented.
5. If by 23 October there is no evidence that the South Africans areprepared to co-operate in implementing the United Nations plan, but persistin going ahead with the unilateral elections, we must expect overwhelmingpressure in the Security Council for strong measures against the south africans, for defying the Council&apos;s authority and to force them to acceptthe Waldheim plan.    Time is thus very short.    The first objective of theFive Foreign Ministers in Pretoria next week will be to persuade the SouthAfrican Government to cancel the unilateral election and to declare their acceptance of the UN plan.    We are seeking to influence the views of themain internal political party in Namibia, and we have been able to secure some changes in the details of the UN plan (on the size of the UN force) inorder to go some way towards meeting the South African position and savingtheir face.    Nevertheless, the chances of persuading the South Africans to reverse or significantly modify their declared policy are not good.6. If we fail, the five Foreign Ministers will have to decide whetherthey should give the South African Government a direct warning about theconsequences of a continued refusal to co-operate.7. It was with this eventuality in mind that officials of the Five have beenmeeting in New York to study a range of measures to force South Africancompliance.    They have drawn up, without commitment, a list of 12possibilities (most with variants) and have ranked them in categories againsta set of criteria according to their impact.    Copies of the report with itscovering paper and the criteria are annexed.8. I believe that the time has come when we may have to undertake a selection of these measures.    None will be without cost to ourselves, butthe cost of failing to act decisively may be greater in the long run.9. The officials have placed in the top category of effectiveness twomeasures:  a mandatory embargo on air transport to and from South Africa,and an embargo on imports of agricultural and food products from SouthAfrica.    The officials do not consider that a mandatory oil embargo wouldmake the same immediate impact.    But if the South Africans defy theSecurity Council I regard it as inevitable that the Africans will call for a mandatory oil embargo and I cannot see the Americans or the Frenchvetoing it or the Germans or Canadians voting against it alone.    To pointout the inevitability of an oil sanction would be another powerfu? pressure on the South Africans.10. Although our partners do not consider the imposition of a visarequirement of much value (the United States and Canada already requirevisas), I think it would well serve our purpose if we were prepared toimpose this control, preferably in conjunction with France and Germany.It would no doubt result in a reciprocal requirement of visas by the south africans but we could live with that.
11. Accordingly I seek my colleagues&apos; agreement that I should explore the views of my four fellow Foreign Ministers on the basis that without taking the initiative we should be prepared to join in all of these measuresif they do so too.    Present indications are that they may not all be readyto commit themselves to a list we could specify in our talks with the south africans, but would prefer to make clear to the South African Prime minister that very serious consequences (meaning a range of measures at least asserious as those outlined in the preceding paragraph) would follow if they donot do what we insist they should.12. I seek my colleagues&apos; agreement to the above course of action, andthat if, contrary to expectation, the other four Foreign Ministers are readyto make an explicit threat of the two high priority measures (air communica-tions and a selective import embargo) I should join them;  that I should beauthorised to take the line on an oil embargo set out above;  and that Ishould add a threat to impose a visa requirement, in company with theFederal Republic of Germany and France.D A L OForeign and Commonwealth Office11 October 19783
HPS 380DE3KBY 050800ZCfVK^ACXT ARl UKMIS NEW YORK 050500ZSECRETDESKBY 05O800ZTO  IMMEDIATE FCO TEL NO 2068 OF 5 OCTOBER 1978INFO IMMEDIATE PRETORIA     WASHINGTON     OTTAWA     BONN PARISM. I.P.To : NAM IB IAFOLLOWING  IS THE DRAFT TEXT OF CRITERIA;OBJECTIVESHOULD THE DECISION TO TAKE MEASURES AGAINST SOUTH AFRICA BE TAKEN,ITS PRIMARY OBJECTIVE WOULD BE URGENTLY TO OBTAIN SOUTH AFRICANCOOPERATION  IN THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE WESTERN FIVE PROPOSAL INACCORDANCE WITH THE REPORT AND EXPLANATORY STATEMENT OF THE UNSECRETARY GENERAL. OUR OBJECTIVE IS NOT SIMPLY TO RESPOND TO united nations PRESSURE: NOR SIMPLY TO DEMONSTRATE A WILLINGNESS TO TAKECOME ACT IONx NOR TO PUNISH THE SOUTH AFRICANS: NOR TO AIM ATAPARTHEID OR THE RHODES IA SITUATION.iCRITER1AAMY MEASURE TAKEN MUST DEMONSTRATE OUR SERIOUSNESS OF PURPOSE AND BESO EFFECTIVE AS TO SECURE COUTH AFRICAN COOPERATION SOON ENOUGH to preserve CUR PROPOSAL AS THE BASIS FOR SETTLEMENT. MINIMAL measures would BE  INEFFECTIVE: THEY WILL ALSO SERVE TO REINFORCE THE SOUTHAFRICAN BELIEF THAT THEY NEED FEAR LITTLE  IN PURSUING THEIR PRESENTCOURSE  IN NAMIBIA. THUS ANY MEASURE TAKEN SHOULD:1) HAVE AN   IMMEDIATE AND SHARP   IMPACT. MEASURES WHICH REQUIRE TIMEFOR THFIR APPLICATION OR FOR THEIR  IMPACT TO BE FELT ALLOW ADAPTA-TION AND ARE MORE LIKELY TO LEAD TO SANCTIONS-BUSTING AND IN TIME TOREBOUND POLITICALLY WITHIN OUR OWN COUNTRIES. MOREOVER,  Sv/APO ANDFRONTLINE ACCEPTANCE OF THE SYG&apos;S REPORT MAY NOT SURVIVE PROLONGEDSOUTH AFRICAN INTRANSIGENCE./ 2) BE SOMETHING
2) BE SOMETHING WHICH SOUTH AFRICA CANNOT ADAPT TO WITHOUT difficulty and PR!VAT JON EITHER THROUGH ADVANCE PLANNING OR SUBSTITUTION.3) HAVE A SIGNIFICANT IMPACT ON THE PEOPLE OF SOUTH AFRICA AS WELL -AS THEIR GOVERNMENT WITHOUT SOLIDIFYING SUPPORT FOR THE SOUTHAFRICAN GOVERNMENTS CURRENT POSITION.  ANY MEASURE TAKEN SHOULD cause a CHANGE IN THE DAILY LIFE STYLES OF THE PEOPLE OF SOUTH AFRICA ANDNAMIBIA LEADING THEM TO QUESTION WHETHER THEIR GOVERNMENTS POLICYTOWARD NAMIBIA IS WORTH THE COST.4) BE RESTRICTED TO SOUTH AFRICA  INSOFAR AS POSSIBLE, BEARING INMIND THE PARTICULAR VULNERABILITY OF BOTSWANA,  LESOTHO, ANDSWAZILAND.5) PROVIDE AN   INCENTIVE TO ENCOURAGE SOUTH AFRICAN COOPERATION, ANDTHEREFORE SHOULD BE LIMITED IN DURATION, RENEWABLE, AMD REMOVABLEWHEN SOUTH AFRICAN COOPERATION WITH REGARD TO NAMIBIA HAS BEENOBTAINED;RICHARD/ iii[COPIES SENT TO NO 10 DOWNING STREET]LZPARTMEITTAL DISTRIBUTION ADDITIONAL DISTRIBUTIONCSAD EID SOUTHERN AFRICAOADS OIDUND IPDDEF D E S &amp; S DACDD NEWS DK AM D CABINET OFPICEWED
GRS 1020I MEDIATECYPHER CAT/afin UKMIS NEW YORK 092355ZSECRET .    ; ..TO IMMEDIATE FCO TELEGRAM NUMBER 2118 OF 9 OCTOBERINFO IMMEDIATE PRETORIA BONN WASHINGTON PARIS OTTAWAMYTEL NOS 2112 AND 2114 i NAMIBIA IWORKING PARTY ON POSSIBLE MEASURES .\.*y 11.      FOLLOWING IS JOINTLY AGREED COVERING PAPER TOTHE SCHEDULE possible MEASURES AGAINST SOUTH AFRICA IN THE context of NAMIBIA.introduction. THE PURPOSE OF THIS NOTE IS TO SET FORTH VIEWS ENDORSED &quot;BY THE WORKING PARTY IN ANALYSING A NUMBER OF POSSIBLE MEASURESWHICH NIGHT BE TAKEN TO INFLUENCE SOUTH AFRICA TOWARD ANINTERNATIONALLY ACCEPTABLE SOLUTION OF THE NAMh-lBlAN PROBLCM. &apos;2. THE ANALYSIS, WHICH HAS NO OFFICIAL STATUS,   IS therefore not CONCERNED WITH POLITICAL JUDGEMENTS AS TO WHETHER ANY or all OF THE MEASURES EXAMINED SHOULD IN FACT BE ADOPTED. THATWILL OF COURSE BE FOR GOVERNMENTS TO DECIDE. . V&quot;ft THOD OF ANALYSIS3. FOR EASE OF PRESENTATION THE MEASURES DISCUSSED HAVEBEEN TABULATED UNDER 7 HEADINGS.     THESE ARE LARGELYSELF-EXPLANATORY AND HAVE BEEN PREPARED ON THE BASIS OF AGREEDCRITERIA (MY TELNO 2068) DESIGNED TO TEST THEIR EFFECTIVENESS.CATEGORIZATION4. AN ATTEMPT HAS ALSO BEEN MADE TO SEPARATE THE MEASURES    /&quot;k .INTO THREE CATEGORIES WHICJH DISTINGUISH BRCAStY- BETWEEN the speed AND WEIGHT OF  IMPACT ON SOUTH AFRICA.TMCcr Anr: Ao roM,owc, secret *******
A. MEASURES WITH EFFECTIVE,  IMMEDIATE &apos;MPACT ON SOUTH - :AFRICAN ECONOMY AND LIVES OF SOUTH AFRICAN CITIZENS:.11A     EMBARGO ON AIR TRANSPORT (PEOPLE AND CARGO) TO [ . -AND FROM SOUTH AFRICA AND ALL AIRCRAFT OF SOUTHAFRICAN REGISTRY AND AIRCRAFT CHARTERED BY SOUTH   -&apos; / :^AFRICAN NATIONALS.v    &apos; \- - &quot;-&apos; -V       ...&quot;      * .i . ...-:&apos;&apos;****&apos;9B     EMBARGO ON IMPORTS OF AGRICULTURAL AND.FOOD PRODUCTS &quot;FROM SOUTH AFRICAB. MEASURES WHICH ARE DEFECTIVE IN ONE OR MORE ASPECTS,   .    .&apos;. ^(IE IMPACT AND/OR EFFECTIVENESS OF IMPLEMENTATION): ,2.    EMBARGO ON MEW INVESTMENT , &quot;;-3B.    BAN ON LOANS TO SOUTH AFRICAN BORROWERS BOTHPUBLJC AND PRIVATE3C.    EMBARGO ON OTHER SOURCES OF FINANCE EG.. BOND OREQUITY ISSUES ./:; s4B.    COMPLETE WITH DRAWL OF EXPORT CREDIT FACILITIES . ,. . - &apos; ...-. .v&apos; yj**$-  - .9A.   TOTAL EMBARGO ON ALL IMPORTS FROM SOUTH AFRICA.&apos;.,.9C.    SELECTIVE EMBARGO ON IMPORTS OF CERTAIN KEY SOUTH VAFRICAN COMMODITIES WHICH ARE MAJOR SOURCES OF :FOREIGN EXCHANGE FOR THEM&quot;&apos;&apos; &apos; .&apos;v&quot;8A.    A ^OTAL EMBARGO ON EXPORTS TO SOUTH AFRICA \10.    EMBARGO ON TRADE IN OIL AND OIL PRODUCTS &quot;   &quot;&apos; &quot;. &apos;f*ftf,8B.    EMBARGO ON EXPORT OF HIGH TECHNOLOGY GOODS &apos;   -      - ..v(EG..COMPUTERS) AND CERTAIN CAPITAL GOODS(EG..HEAVY CONSTRUCTION MACHINERY AND MININGMACHINERY, AIRCRAFT AND A!*CRAH* PARTS) -C    MEASURES WITH LIMITED OR LITTLE REAL IMPACT; .1A.    DISCOURAGEMENT OF NEW INVESTMENT ; -   .       :i - &apos;SECRET wi-hM&quot;^
ib;   WITHDRAWAL OF INVESTMENT INSURANCE FACILITIES     . i&apos;* 1. &quot;&apos;&quot;* *3A.    DISCOURAGEMENT OF LOANS TO SOUTH AFRICAN .BORROWERS BOTH PUBLIC AND PRIVATE . .[.4A.    LIMITATION OF EXPORT CRED!T FACILITIES&apos;( TO AMAXIMUM OF FIVE YEARS AND A FIXED AMOUNT PER ANNUM).5.     USE OF TAX SYSTEMS.    &quot;. * ; IS 136A-D DIPLOMATIC. MEASURES .. ;11B. DENIAL OF REFUELING RIGHTS FOR ALL AIRCRAFT OFSOUTH AFRICAN REGISTRY AND AIRCRAFT CHARTERED BYSOUTH AFRICAN NATIONALSEMBARGO ON TRANPORT OF AIR CARGO TO AND FROM SOUTH -AFRICA AND CARGO CARRIED BY ARlCRAFT OF SOUTH AFRICANREGISTRY OR CHARTERED BY SOUTH AFRICA &apos;12.    STOP OFFICIAL PROMOTION OF COMMERCE WITH SOUTHAFRICA (EG.. TRADE FAIRS, ETC.) . V.:.7B.    RESTRICTION OF TRAVEL . &apos; , .* \   -it ..... &apos;-&apos;7A.    IMPOSITION OF V ISA REQUIREMENTSGENERAL CONSIDERATIONS5.     THE ANALYSIS BY INDIVIDUAL ITEMS HAS ALSO REVEALED ANUMBER OF GENERAL CONSIDERATIONS!. *v. -.(0 REPRISALSS.A. HAS THE CAPABILITY TO RETALIATE IN FIELDS UNRELATED V\/TO THE MEASURE TAKEN(II)    PSYCHOLOGICAL IMPACTIT IS DIFFICULT TO MEASURE THE PSYCHOLOGICAL  IMPACT OFVARIOUS MEASURES ON THE S.A. POPULACE AND WHETHER THEiR EFFECT .WOULD BE TO WEAKEN POPULAR SUPPORT FOR S.A. POLICIES TOWARD V;NAM IB A OR WOULD INSTEAD TEND TO EVOKE A SEIGE MENTALITY AND;,-.STRENGTHEN SI&apos;&quot; o0RT FOR THE GOVERNMENTS POS IT ION. - -L/c my.
(III) PRECEDENTSTHE RISK THAT MEASURES TAKEN IN RELATION TO CIVIL AVIATION ,AND OIL MIGHT LATER BE USED BY STATES OR GROUPS OF STATES :EVEN OUTSIDE THE CONTEXT OF MANDATORY UN SANCTIONS.(IV) CHAPTER VIIIT WOULD IN MANY CASES BE NECESSARY FOR THE MEASURE TO BE &apos;MADE MANDATORY UNDER CHAPTER VII OF THE UN CHARTER  IN ORDER.%TO OVERRIDE PREEXISTING INTERNATIONAL COMMITMENTS SUCH AS VVGATT, ETC.(V) LEAKAGES AND EVASIONSIT HAS NOT BEEN P0SSI3LE IN THE TIME AVAILABLE TO GO INTO -DETAIL ON THE PROBLEM OF PREVENTING NON-COMPLIANCE. /(VI) EXISTING CONTRACTSDECISIONS WOULD HAVE TO BE TAKEN ABOUT THE TREATMENT OFEXISTING CONTRACTS OR THOSE &quot;IN THE PIPELINE&quot;   IN RELATIONTO AN EMDARGO.(VII) SECURITY COUNCIL RESOLUTIONANY SECURITY COUNCIL RESOLUTION  IMPOSING MANDATORY SANCTIONSSHOULD BE FOR A FIXED TIME PERIOD SUBJECT TO RENEWAL BY -FURTHER RESOLUTION.     THIS PROCEDURE IS NECESSARY TO AVOID-VA SITUATION IN WHICH THE REMOVAL OF SANCTIONS IS SUBJECT TO-VETO. .... .(VII J) NAMIBIATHE POSSIBILITY OF TRADE ACTIONS TARGETED EXCLUSIVELY AT ^ ,NAMIBIA WAS EXAMINED.    IT WAS CONCLUDED THAT BECAUSE THE    &apos; .:FORMAL ESTABLISHMENT OF NAM IB I AN ORIGIN  IS NOT POSSIBLE,the FEASIBILITY AND EFFECTIVENESS OF ANY SUCH MEASURE would depend ON WHETHER ITEMS OF SIGNIFICANT TRADE INTEREST&apos; COM IngONLY FROM NAMIBIA AND NOT ALSO from SOUTH AFPICA COULD be identified. V(ix)    sea TRANSPORT - *      &apos;    . &apos;. $,the POSSIBILITY OF AN EMBARGO ON SEA TRANSPORT VMS NOT \ &apos;, \SEPARATELY CONSIDERED BECAUSE !t was REGARDED AS ESSENTIALLYSIMILAR TO A GENERAL EMBARGO ON TRADE WITH SOUTH AFRICA.. : ;.Richard . .   . -.     - ; rv;departmental distn &apos; additional Distn       &quot; ,&apos;csad        -    wed southern africaoads    &apos;        eidUNO OlD /copies sent to no 10 downing st/.defence D    ipd -acdd news D 1- n W D        cabinet OFFICEes k sd *Ji-
nature  of   ;     does   it   meet how  would   it beeasure      f     criteria c*)2   identified?implemented (i.e.,nvestment. a.-i scour-cement ofjewnvestmentCOmo-335.e.withdrawal)f invest-1ENT[nsurancefacilities(*) 1.2.3.may  have somepsychological effect in  short  term (though in  absence ofstronger measure would probablyreinforce southafrican  view  that westwill  take  no seriousaction)minimal  effect/ butlogical  extension of1.a.     (only  uk andfrance  currently have-this  little usedfacility  available for south africa.)voluntary orMandatory)collective voluntarystep  by  the  5  or more]countries  in  form ofa  statement bygovts; unenforceable.could  not   form onlyitem in  sec. councilres.individual govtaction voluntarystep(could  also bemandatory);enforceablefeasibility ofeffectiveimplementationeasily implementedbut createscontradictions .if   govts continueto  provide ex.control consentsor other facilities(where  these applyeasily implemented in  sense  of  new  capital  inflows  to  south africafor  criteria see separate paper;&quot;reversible&quot; applies to the technical or administrative procedures/not the effects of the measure which may continue after measure hasbeen withdrawan.ease ofreversal(*)3easilyreversedeasilyreversedwider implications for countriesinvolveda) western countriesb) neighborly statesmarginal  a  and bminimalprobabilityof retaliation-tion   in thisfieldnoneC/)monone
iMBARGO)N NEWINVESTMENTWOULD  HAVE PSYCHOLOGIC,IMPACT  AND AFFECTBUSINESS  CLIMATE but little immediate effect.     LEVEL of investment  IS  LOW ANDMOST  INVESTMENT ISALREADY BEINGFINANCED FROMRETAINED  PROFITS. IFAPPLIED  OVER time would  RESTRAIN RATEOF GROWTH.(*)   SEE  PAGE 1HOW WOULD  IT be implemented (I.EVOLUNTARY ORMANDATORY)L WOULD  HAVE  TO be under  CHAPTER VIIMANDATORY ACTIONFEASIBILITY OFEF.ECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONDELAYS  BECAUSE of probable  NEED FORFOLLOW THROUGHLEGISLATION INSUBSCRIBINGC OUNTR IE .EASE OFREVERSALEASILYREVERSEDWIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIESB) NEIGHBORING STATESMARGINALPROBABILITYOF retaliation-TION  IN THIIFIELDPROHIBITIONOR FURTHERRESTRICTIONON REPATRIA-TION  OF FUNDS
loans bybanks orCOmO3Dotherprivatefinancialinstitu-tions3.a.discour-agementof loans to southafricanborrowersbothpublicandprivate3.b.ban onloansto southafricanborrowersbothpublicandprivatein  view  of   south africancurrent financialposition/  this wouldhave  a psychologicalimpact  and  thus affecta  sensitive  area forthem  and  be  a cause for  concern/   at least in  the  short term.would  have animmediate  and sharpeffecthow would  it be implemented (i.evoluntary ormandatory)voluntary statement by individualgovernments unlikely to  feature  as majoritem  in  sc res.have to be mandatoryunder  chapter viifeasibility ofeffectiveimplementationeasily implementedbut  puts state-owned  banks  in an awkward position.would   require swis$compliance. also possible leakagesthrough unregulatefinancial enclaves,would  take timefor individual countries  to passany necessary legislation and regulations whichwould  vary fromcountry tocountry.ease ofreversalno administrativeproblemcan bereversedwider implications for countriesinvolveda) wester?! countriesb) neighboring statesa) probably  little  on theassumption  that this measure  did  not  have amarked  effect  on thescale  or  terms  of lendingto  south africa.b) nila)   and  b)   an effectiveban would  be  likely to result   in  default omoutstanding  bank loans/which  in  view  of theirscale  would entailsubstantial  losses forseveral internationalbanks  and  could  lead tofurther damaging consequences   for theinternational financialsystem.these  adverse  effects canextend  to  export creditguaranteed  by  govts orprobabilityof retaliation-tion  in thisfieldvery littleCOmo30high (seepreviouscolumn)
3C.EMBARGO ONOTHERSOURCES OFFINANCEE.G. BANON BOND OREQUITYISSUESfC EXPORTUJ CREDITCO FACILITIES4A.LIMITATIONOF TERMS(TO A MAX-minimun OF5 YR.CREDITSAND  A FIXEDAMOUNTPER ANNUM)AS  FOR  EMJARGO  ON BANKOF  RETALIATION  IF TAKENPROBABLY  HAVE LITTLE EFWOULD  TAKE  TIME  TO HAVEEFFECT BECAUSE OF the relatively  FEW CASES(I.E.  LARGE PROJECTS)WHICH  WOULD BE INVOLVEDHOW  WOULD   IT be implemented (T.EVOLUNTARY ORMANDATORY)FEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONEASE OFREVERSALWIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIESB) NEIGHBORING STATESENDING.     WOULD  PROBABLY  INCREASE  THE  EFFECTS  BUT  ALSO  !rHE RISKTOGETHER  WITH  THE  BANfrJ LENDING  MEASURE.   ifF  IMPOSED AL()NE WOULDECT.WOULD  HAVE  TO  BE INFORM OF concerted action BY  ALL MAJOREXPORTERS/ (POSSIBLYUNDER  CHAPTER  7 OR INOECD CONTEXT)EASILY IMPLEMENTEDBUT  IN EXPORTCREDIT MATTERSCOUNTRIES ALWAYSWISH TO HAVE THERIGHT  TO MATCHCOMPETITIVE OFFERSTECHNICAL question would  ALSO arise as  HOW  TO  VALUE ACOMMON LIMIT INDIFFERENTCURRENCIES.EASILYREVERSEDFEW  IN  SHORT  TERM but would  CLEARLY  HAVE IM-PLICATIONS   FOR EMPLOY-MENT  IN exporting countries  OVER longer term  DEPENDING ON THEAMOUNT OF CREDITPERMITTED .probability of retaliation-TION  IN THISFIELDoUJCONIL
IB.COMPLETEWITHDRAWAL3F FACILI-TIESCOm5.  USE of tax SYSTEMS(E.G. TER-MINATION of double TAX-AT ION AGREEMENTS/WITHDRAWALOF TAXCREDITSAGAINST S.a tax/ WITH-DRAWAL of tax .INCENT-IVES TOINVESTMENT/ELIMINATIONWOULD  HAVE IMMEDIATEPSYCHOLOGICAL effect and  ALSO A CUMULATIVEFINANCIAL EFFECT(DEPENDING ON  EXTENT TOWHICH   S.A. IMPORTERSSUCCEEDED  IN OBTAININGUNINSURED CREDIT/THOUGH  THIS WOULDPROBABLY  BE more expensive)  AMOUNTING INSOME  CASES  TO LIQUIDITYDIFFICULTIES  OR BANK-RUPTCY   FOR INDIVIDUALFIRMSMINIMAL  IMPACT ONS.AFRICA  IN SHORT TERMOVER TIME WOULD TENDTO  DISCOURAGE NEWINVESTMENTHOW WOULD  IT be implemented (I.EVOLUNTARY ORMANDATORY)AS ABOVECHAPTER VII action would BE NECESSARYIN MOST CASESFEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONAS ABOVE (EXCEPTFOR TECHNICALQUESTION)ADMINISTRATIVELYDIFFICULT ANDSLOW TO TAKEEFFECTEASE OFREVERSALAS above as PREVIOUSCOLUMNWIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIESB) NEIGHBORING states in TIME -:LIKELY TO RESULT INLOSS OF EXPORTS ANDEMPLOYMENT:WOULD DISPROPORTION-ATELY  AFFECT THOSECOUNTRIES WHICHCURRENTLY  HAVE  A LARGEJPROPORTION OFOFFICIALLY INSUREDEXPORTSINCREASES  THE  RISK OFDEFAULT AND claims arising ON VEuY SUB-STANTIAL  VOLUME of outstanding CREDIT.ADVERSE   EFFECT ON PASTINVESTORS  AND COUNTER-PRODUCTIVE   INSOFAR ASIT  ENCOURAGES REINVEST-MENT IN S.AFRICAPROBABILITYOF retaliation-TION  IN THISFIELDRISK OF RE-PAYMENT BEINGBLOCKED  ON OUT-STANDING COMMIT-MENTS  OF THEORDER  OF SEVERALBILLION DOLLARSCOmOmCONSIDERABLERISK  OF some form OF FISCALRETALIATION
diplomaticmeasures___6.withdrawalof certainSategoriesf staff of(jmbassiesand&quot;Consulatesa) tradepromotionstaffb) militaryserviceattachec) withdrawalof ambassadord) closure of embassiesandconsulatesDOES  It MEETCRITERIA IDENTIFIED?minimum psychologicaleffectlittle psychologicaleffectconsiderablepsychological effectstrong psychologicaleffectJhow would   it be implemented/(i.evoluntary ormandatory) / Ivoluntary -governmentmentthroughannounce-voluntary  - throughgovernment announce-mentvoluntary - throughgovernment announce-mentvoluntary - throughgovernment announce-mentfeasibility ofeffectiveimplementationeasyeasyeasyeasyease ofreversaleasyeasyeasyeasy,considerablepracticaldifficultieswider implications for countriesinvolveda) western countriesB) neighboring statesa) noneb) nonea) noneb) nonea) could impair politicaldialogueb) nonea)   loss  of benefits of direct representation;(information and protection of nationalsetc. )b)   afeects countrieshaving multipleaccreditation from south africaprobab .ityof retaliation-tion  in thisfieldguiCOirrelevantto ourinterestsirrelevantto ourinterestsirrelevantto ourinterestsirrelevantto our interests
7A.impositioiof visarequire-mentsCOmO3i RESTRICTIONI  OF TRAVELdoes  it meetcriteria identified?COULD  HAVE PSYCHOLOGIIMPACT   (ESPECIALLY IFVISAS  WERE  USED to restrict TRAVEL)C ACSTRONG PSYCHOLOGICALEFFECTHOW  WOULD   IT be implemented (I.E./VOLUNTARY ORMANDATORY)VOLUNTARYVOLUNTARYFEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONEASE OFREVERSALiiiWOULD  PRESENT        [NO SPECIFICLEGAL  AND PRACTIiPROBLEMSCAL  PROBLEMS   FOR JTECHNICALLYSOME COUNTRIESiiiWOULD PRESENTLEGAL ANDPRACTICALPROBLEMS FORSOME COUNTRIESNO SPECIFICPROBLEMSTECHNICALLYWIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDa) WESTERN COUNTRIESb) NEIGHBORING STATESA) WERE  VISAS  USED to restrict  TRAVEL this could  RESULT  IN  LOSS OFBUSINESS  AND TOURISTREVENUEB) COULD  INCREASE SOUTHAFRICAN  TOURISM INBOTSWANA/ LESOTHOAND  SWAZILAND -A) WERE  VISAS  USFD to restrict  TRAVEL this could  RESULT  IN  LOSS OFBUSINESS  AND TOURISTREVENUEB) COULD  INCREASE SOUTHAFRICAN  TOURISM INBOTSWANA/   LESOTHO ANDSWAZILANDProbabilityof retaliation in thisfieldCERTAINSTRONGCOmo3Dm
A.OTALMBAR GON EXPORTS0 SOUTHFRICAIN  THE  VERY  SHORT TERM,ITS  ECONOMIC IMPACTWOULD NOT BE SHARP. ITCOULD  HAVE  A PSYCHOLOG-ICAL  IMPACT.    THERE ISA PARTICULAR RISK THATIT  WOULD STRENGTHENRATHER  THAN WEAKENPUBLIC   SUPPORT   FOR THESOUTH african governments POSITION,ALTHOUGH  THERE   IS DOUBTTHAT  THE GOVERNMENTWOULD  BE  WILLING to incur A TOTAL EMBARGOOVER  THE  ISSUE OFNAMIBIA.     OVER the longer  TERM, SOUTHAFRICA  HAS SIGNIFICANTABILITY  TO SUBSTITUTEIN  ALMOST  ALL fields of   IMPORTS,  BUT ATADDITIONAL ECONOMICCOST  AND  DISTORTION. .AN  EFFECTIVE EMBARGOWOULD  PROBABLY RESULTIN A LOWER RATE OFECONOMIC  GROWTH for south  AFRICA OVERTHE  LONGER TERM.HOW WOULD  IT be implemented (I.E.,VOLUNTARY ORMANDATORY)MUST  BE MANDATORYAND  UNIVERSAL TOBE EFFECTIVEFEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONWOULD  BE EXTREMELYDIFFICULT TOENFORCE WITHOUTBLOCKADE ACTIONEASE OFREVERSALTECHNICALLYEASILYREVERSIBLEWIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIESB) NEIGHBORING STATESA.(1)  SIGNIFICANT losses of  EXPORT EARNINGS FORMANY  COUNTRIES  AND LOSSOF  IMPORTANT  MARKETS FORMANY   INDIVIDUAL companies for  A WIDE  RANGE of products  WITH CONSEQUENTEFFECTS  ON EMPLOYMENT.THESE  EFFECTS  WOULD BZINCREASINGLY  DIFFICULT to reverse  OVER  TIME BECAUSEOF  THE  ESTABLISHMENT OFNEW  INDIGENOUS industries in SOUTH AFRICA.i(2) SIGNIFICANT LOSSESFOR  SHIPPING industries of  SEVERAL COUNTR.IES.(3) DEMAND   FOR COMPENSA-TION  FROM GCVTS BY FIRMSWHOSE  ORDERS  ARE FRUSTRA-TED.(A)   PROBABLE  PAYMENT of guarantees  BY NATIONALCREDIT  INSURERS FOr:EXPORTS  CONTRACTED FORBUT  NOT DELIVERED.JB.     DEPENDING  UPON the duration  OF  THE EMBARGO,IT  COULD  PREJUDICE THEECONOMIC  DEVELOPMENT OFTHE  NEIGHBORING STATESBECAUSE  OF  THE  LOSS OFTHEIR   LARGEST  POTENTIAL M/jRKETPROBABILITYOF retaliation-TION  IN THISFIELDWOULD  BE ASTRONG POSSI-JBILITY OFRETALIATIONTHROUGH embarrassing-GO  ON STRATE-strategic RAWMATERIALS,particularly as  THEIR OWNNEED   FOR REV-ENUES WOULDBE substantially reduced BYTHE embargo on  EXPORTS TOTHEM.
moam8B.EMBA  50 on export of high TECH-NOLOGYGOODS (E.GCOMPUTERS)AND CERTAICAPITALGOODS (E.GHEAVY CON-STRUCTIONMACHINERYAND MININGMACHINERY/aircraft and AIR-CRAFT PARTS)DOES  IT MEETCRITERIA IDENTIFIED?IT  COULD  HAVE ALIMITED PSYCHOLOGICALIMPACT  IN  THE SHORTTERM.     IT WOULD PROB-ABLY  NOT  HAVE any immediate ECONOMICIMPACT ALTHOUGH the embargo OF  SOME capital goods  SUCH AS COMPUTERS!/FOR WHICH  SOUTH AFRICAHAS LITTLE OR NOABILITY  TO SUBSTITUTEDOMESTIC EQUIPMENT/COULD  HAVE  A MARKEDEFFECT OVER TIME.HOW WOULD  IT be implemented (I.E.VOLUNTARY ORMANDATORY)MUST BE MANDATORY/UNIVERSAL  AND  PRE- .CISELY  DEFINED ASTO  PRODUCT COVERAGETO BE EFFECTIVE.FEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONOVER TINE/ the likelihood OFAVOIDANCE  OF  THIS jSANCTION BY  DIVER- ISION  THROUGH  THIRD jCOUNTRIES  WOULD  BE jCONSIDERABLE and increasing.EASE OFREVERSALWIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIESB) NEIGHBORING STATESTECHNICALLY! A) SOME LOSS OF EXPORTEASY- i EARNINGS,THE SEVERITYJ OF  WHICH WOULD DEPENDI UPON THE PRODUCTSI EMBARGOED.   OVER time THERE  COULD  BE SOMEI LASTING  DISTORTION OFI SOUTH  AFRICAN DEMAND.1I B) NONEPROBABILITYOF retaliation-TION  IN THISFIELDNO POSSIBILITYOF SYMMETRICALRETALIATION BUTPOSSIBILITY OFSOUTH AFRICANEMBARGO on exports of strategic RAWMATERIALS.COmo30mH
9A.TOTALEMBARGOON ALLIMPORTSFROMSOUTHAFRICAoLUCODOES  IT MEETCRITERIA IDENTIFIED?IT  WOULD  HAVE ANIMMEDIATE  AND SHARPIMPACT.     IF  IT WT RELEAK-PROOF/   IT WOULDBE  SOMETHING TOWHICH  SOUTH AFRICACOULD  NOT ADAPTWITHOUT difficulty and  PRIVATION  AND WOULDCERTAINLY  CAUSE ACHANGE  IN  THE LIFESTYLES  OF  THE SOUTHAFRICAN PEOPLE.HOW WOULD   IT be implemented (I.E.,VOLUNTARY ORMANDATORY)IT  WOULD  HAVE  TO BEMANDATORY ANDUNIVERSAL INAPPLICATION  IF ITWERE  TO BE EFFECTIVEFEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEEASE OFREVERSALIMPLEMENTATIONITS EFfECTIVENESS/i.TECHNICALLYEVEN  IF  MANDATORY EASY.AND UNIVERSAL/WOULD CLEARLYDIMINISH  OVER time&apos;AS  BLACK  MARKETS IWOULD DEVELOPFOR SOUTHAFRICAN  PRODUCTS/ IPARTICULARLYMINERALS WHICHARE  IN HIGHDEMAND.WIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTE  N COUNTRIESB) NEIGHBORING STATESA)  THE  ADVERSE  IMPACT on western  COUNTRIES COULDBE  CONS IDERABLE  BUT would depend  UPON  THE duration of  THE  EMBARGO  AND WOULDVARY   FROM  COMMODITY TOCOMMODITY  AND FROMCOUNTRY  TO  COUNTRY. SOUTAFRICA  IS  THE LEADINGWORLD PRODUCEI;ANTIMONEY/  CHROMIUM ORE/GEM  DIAMONDS ANDVANADIUM/  AND  ONE OFTHE  TOP  THREE producers of  ASBESTOS/ MANGANESE/URANIUM/  AND PLATINUM-GROUP  METALS. inasmuch as THE  USSR  IS THELEADING  ALTERNATIVE FORMANY  OF  THESE strategic materials/   SOUTH AFRICA&apos;SROLE  IN  RELATION to non-COMMUNIST PRODUCTIONAND  SUPPLY  IS EVENMORE  IMPORTANT THANINDICATED BY ITSPRODUCTION VOLUME. MANYWESTERN  COUNTRIES are particularly DEPENDENTON  SOUTH AFRICA FORCERTAIN OF THESEPRODJCTS, AND  AN EMBARGOWOULD  CAUSE  STRONG UPWARDPRESSURES  ON  THEIR PRICESCONTINUED  ON  NEXT PAGEPROBABILITYOF retaliation-TION  IN THISFIELDTHEY COULDRETALIATEEITHER through a GENERAL MBARGO OR/AS would perhaps BEMORE LIKELY/SELECTIVEEMBARCOS.UJCO
9A. CONTINUED11-(CONTINUED   FROM PREVIOUS PAGE)NATURE OF &apos;MEASURE fDOES  IT MEETCRITERIA IDENTIFIED?COmo33HOW WOULD   IT be implemented (I.EVOLUNTARY ORMANDATORY)FEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONEASE OFREVERSALWIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIESB) NEIGHBORING states in  ADDITION  TO a significant  LOSS of access  TO SPECIFICCOMMODITIES,  A TOTALEMBARGO  ON imports would  RESULT  IN a significant REDUCTIONIN SOUTH AFRICANPURCHASES  OF WESTERNPRODUCTS.OVER  TIME  THERE COULDBE  SOME  LASTING EFFECTSAS  NEW  SOURCES  OF SUPPLY!AND  PATTERNS  OF TRADEARE DEVELOPED.(B)   IT  WOULD  HAVE AMARKEDLY  ADVERSE EFFECTON NEIGHBORING COUNTRIES;BECAUSE:   (1)  A HIGHPERCENTAGE  OF their imports  COMES   FROM SOUTH]AFRICA;  AND  (2)  A DECLINEIN  SOUTH AFRICANMINING  AND other industrial ACTIVITYWOULD  CERTAINLY  BE FELTIMMEDIATELY   IN UNEMPLOY-JMENT.     IN PRACTICALTERMS,  THE dependence of   CERTAIN NEIGHBORINGSTATES   IS  SO  GREAT THATTHEY  COULD HARDLYCOMPLY  WITH the embargo.probability of retaliation-TION  IN THISFIELDCOmO33
9B,embargo on IMPORT?OFAGRICUL-TURALANO FOODPRODUCTSFROMSOUTHAFRICAccoujtoDOES   IT MEETCRITERIA IDENTIFIED?IT  WOULD  HAVE ANIMMEDIATE  AND SHARPIMPACT/ depending on  THE SEASONALCYCLES  OF the products INVOLVED.IT WOULD  HAVE a particularly DIRECTIMPACT  ON SOUTHAFRICAN FARMERS.IF  EFFECTIVE/   IT WOULDBE  SOMETHING  TO WHICHSOUTH AFRICA COULDNOT ADAPT without difficulty ANDPRIVATION.HOW WOULD  IT be implemented   (I.E.sVOLUNTA-Y ORMANDATORY)TO BE IMPLEMENTED/IT  WOULD  HAVE  TO BEMANDATORY;   IT WOULDNOT necessarily have  TO BE UNIVERSALTO BE EFFECTIVEBECAUSE  ONLY  A LIMITNUMBER OF MARKETSIS INVOLVED.FEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONit  could be implemented ;effectivelysince  the origin of these products could4d    be easilyestablished andi   since  there are! alternativei  sources  for these products.EASE OFREVERSALTECHNICALLYIT  COULD BEEASILYREVERSED.WIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIESB) NEIGHBORING STATESA)   THERE  WOULD  BE SOMESHORT-TERM DISRUPTIONOF  SUPPLIES ANDIMPACT  ON PRICES in western MARKETS.OVER  THE  LONGER TERM/AS  TRADE PATTERNSCHANGED/  THE measure would  NOT  BE EASILYOR  COMPLETELY REVERSIBLEB)   UNLESS  THEY WEREEXCUSED  FROM THIS,THE IMPACT WOULD BEHEAVILY ADVERSE.OF retaliation-TION  IN THISFIELDSOME RETALIATIONIS POSSIBLE/BUT  IT  WOULD IN-VOLVL  A  COST to south AFRICA.SOUT!, AFRICACOULD ALSORETALIATE by refusing  TO f-EXPORT  TO THOSEUJNEIGHBORINGCOUNTRIES WHICIfjjMIGHT   BC EXCUSEODFROM  THE EMBARGO.
9C.SELECTIVEEMBARGO on imports OFCERTAIN KEYSOUTHAFRICANCOMMODITIESWHICH ARE.1AJOR SOURCE3F FOREIGNEXCHANGEFOR^THEM.mO33DOES   IT MEETCRITERIA IDENTIFIED?AND  IF  NOT/  WHY NOT?HOW WOULD   IT be implemented (I.E./VOLUNTARY ORMANDATORY)IF   IT  WERE EFFECTIVE,IT  WOULD  HAVE ANIMMEDIATE  AND SHARPIMPACT  ON  THE SOUTHAFRICAN  ECONOMY and indirectly  ON the daily  LIVES  OF SOUTHAFRICAN CITIZENS.IF  EFFECTIVE,   IT WOULDBE  SOMETHING TOWHICH  SOUTH AFRICACOULD  NOT  ADAPT  WITHOUT jDIFFICULTY ANDPRIVATION.I  it  wou!D  have  to bej mandatory andi universal inj application.FEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONi it would  be &apos;j difficult  if notl impossible toi implementj effectively,i because controlsj could  be easilyj circumvented fori these commoditiesj for  which  it isi difficult to! establish origin.j if  the embargoi were not  Successful,j actual southi african earnings tI,could increasej as  the worldl market price! reacted.ease OFreversalYESWIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIESb) NEIGHBORING STATESA) WE  WOULD  BE DENYINGOURSELVES COMMODITIESFOR  WHICH WE  HAVE ADEMAND WITH SOMERESULTANT  DISRUPTION TOOUR  ECONOMIES, DEPENDINGUPON  THE SPECIFICCOMMODITIES INVOLVED.IN  THE  CASE  OF an embargo ON  GOLD, GOLDPRICES  COULD STEEPLYRISE  POSSIBLY CAUSINGSOME  INSTABILITY in international FINANCIALMARKETS.B) DEPENDING ON WHETHERSOUTH AFRICA REDUCESITS  MINING ACTIVITY,IT  COULD  HAVE  AN adverse effect  ON NEIGHBORINGSTATES.probability of retaliation-TION  IN THISFIELDTHE likelihood of RETALIATIONCOULD  BE QUITEHIGH. SOUTHAFRICA COULDINDEED RETALIATEBY EMBARGOINGEXPORTS OFSTRATEGICCOMMODITIES, not subject TOOUR  OWN IMPORTEMBARGO.mO33q
10,NATURE OFMEASUREEMBARGODCoLUCOON  TRADE IIN  OIL IAND OILPRODUCTS.i(THIS  IS jASSUMEDNOT  TO   . IINCLUDE jBUNKER INGiOF  SOUTH !AFRICANSHIPS ANDiAIRCRAFT jOUTSIDE ISOUTHAFRICA.) jDOES  IT MEETCRITERIA   IDENTIFIET ?AND  IF NOT, why NOT?COULD HAVE AN IMMEDIATEPSYOfJLOGICAL  IMPACT IFDEMAND RESTRAINTMEASURES  were taken which  WOULD AFFECTTHE  DAILY  LIVES of citizens/   SUCH ASGASOLINE RATIONING.HOWEVER^   ITS ECONOMICIMPACT  WOULD  BE DELAYEDFOR A VERY considerable period/  DUE  TO SOUTHAFRICA&apos;S relatively low DEPENDENCE  ON OILAND  THE  EXISTENCE OFLARGE STRATEGICSTOCKPILES  OF OIL.ALSO  THE EXPECTEDDEVELOPMENT  OF ASECOND SYNTHETICFUEL  PLANT would further  DELAY and reduce  THE ECONOMICiIMPACT.how would   it be implemented (i.e./voluntary ormandatory)must be mandatoryand  universal  to be effective. (iranis  the majorsupplier  of crudeto south africa&apos;and would be unlikely  to wish to cooperate  in voluntarmeasures.)FEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONWOULD  BE EXTREMELYDIFFICULT TOENFORCE OVER THEPERIOD  OF time required  TO HAVEAN ECONOMICIMPACT. THEGENERAL AVAILABILIOF  CRUDE and products  IN WCjRLDSPOT MARKETSTOGETHER with south AFRICA&apos;disability TOFURNISH  ITS OWNTRANSPORT through its  OWN FLEETOR CHARTERSWOULD MAKEENFORCEMENT VERYDIFFICULT WITHOUTACTUAL PHYSICALSURVEILLANCE.EASE OFREVERSALPROVIDED ARESOLUTIONCOULD BEOBTAINEDLIMITINGTHE measure to  THE CASEY OFNAMIBIA/ ANDNOT ALSOENCOMPASSINGRHODESIA/IT COULDBE QUICKLYREVERSED.WIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIES jB) NEIGHBORING  STATES &apos;a) some  loss  of remittedprofits  by  western oil companies&apos; subsidiariesin  south  africa. iran&apos;soil  revenues  would bereduced  by  the  loss oftheir  south africanmarkets assuming theycould  not  sell thatoil elsewhere.b) the  impact  could be severely  adverse  if southafrica  embargoed thesupply  of  oil products to those neighboringstates which  it currentlysupplies. swaziland/however/  could almost certainly arrangealternative  supplies frommozambique.probability of retaliation-tion  in thisfieldsouth africawouldcertainlyseize controlof thewestern oil companies&apos;refining anddistribution!?]facilities ocin the coun-o
11AEMBARGOON AIRTRANSPORTi(PEOPLEANDCARGOES)TO ANDFROMSOUTH$FRICA0*ND ON3jLL AIR-[flRAFT OFSOUTHAFRICANREGISTRYANDAIRCRAFTCHARTEREDBY SOUTHAFRICA.DOES  IT MEETCRITERIA IDENTIFIED?AND   IF  NOT /  WHY NOT?IT WOULD  HAVE ANIMMEDIATE  AND SHARPIMPACT  ON THEPEOPLE  OF SOUTHAFRICA (particularly the  MORE INFLUENTIALPORTION  OF THEPOPULATION)   AND ONTHE  SHIPMENT  OF CERTAINGOODS  FROM SOUTHAFRICA.     THE impact on  SHIPMENT  OF GOODSCOULD DIMINISHOVER  TIME THROUGHSOUTH AFRICANADAPTATION.HOW WOULD   IT be implemented (I.E./VOLUNTARY OR.MANDATORY)IT MUST BE MANDATORYIN  ORDER  TO be effective  AND FORSOME  COUNTRIES TOBE  ABLE  TO COMPLY.IT  WOULD  HAVE  TO BEUNIVERSALLY applied in  ORDER  TO be effective.FEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONIF  MANDATORY/ ITCAN BE EFFECTIVELYIMPLEMENTED/UNLESS SWITZERLANDREFUSES  TO apply the EMBARGO.FLIGHTS TOSWITZERLAND COULDBE  PREVENTED IFOVER-FLYINGRIGHTS WEREDENIED  UNDER THERESOLUTION BYSURROUNDINGCOUNTRIES.EASE OFREVERSALtechnically!easilyreversible.WIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIESB) NEIGHBORING STATES&apos;probability of retaliation-TION  IN THISFIELDA) IT  WOULD DEPRIVECITIZENS  OF western countries  RESIDENT INSOUTH  AFRICA  OF THEPOSSIBILITY  OF FLYINGFROM  SOUTH africa and  WOULD  INCONVENIENCE WESTERNBUSINESSMEN AND   THE  EXPORTING OFCERTAIN  GOODS to south  AFRICA. financial implications  FOR .WESTERN AIRLINECOMPANIES  WOULD RANGEFROM MARGINAL to serious.B) IT  WOULD  HAVE ANECONOMIC   IMPACT ONNEIGHBORING states which  ARE DEPENDENTON SOUTH AFRICANAIR SERVICE.lLESOTHO&apos;S ACCESSJTO  THIRi COUNTRIESICOULD  BE AFFECTEDI by   south african(retaliationi against overflights.C/)mO3
ccoUJCOnature of &apos;measureIII11B.denial of jrefuelingrightsfor allaircraftof southafricanregistryand AIRCRAFjcharteredby southafricaIdoes  it meetcriteria identified?and  if not/  why not ?it  would  have onlylimited  real  impact but could  have  some psycho-logical  impact insidesouth africa. southafrica  could  adapt tothis measure  in a relatively  short timebecause  foreign airlineswould  continue  to flyto and  from  south africasiiow  would   it be implemented (i.e.voluntary ormandatory)it must  be mandatoryin order  to be effective  and   in order for  some countries to  comply. itwould  also  have tobe universallyapplied  to beeffectivefeasibility of(effective,implementationease ofreversalthe  risk of  signi-j technicallyficant  weakening    &quot;(  easily re-through  the  non-     i versible.participation ofswitzerland  could jbe  even greaterthan  in  the  case Iof  a  total  embargo jon air transportsince  south  africa jcould probablyredirect flightsthroughswitzerlandwider implications for countriesinvolveda) western countriesB) neighboring statesa)  none/  except   in theevent that southafrica retaliate]) in kind  and  that african countries  could denyrefueling  rights to western  airlines flyingto  south africa.b) none of retaliation-tion  in thisfieldSOUTH AFRICACOULD CON-conceivably RE-TALIATE in kind BUTONLY  AT SUB-STANTIAL hAND  DIRECT [tiCOST  TO IT-qSELF BECAUSBJTHE COMBINE^EFFECT OFBANS  ON RE-FUELINGWOULD AMOUNTTO  A TOTALEMBARGO ONAIRTRANSPORT
11C.embargo on TRANS-PORT OFAIR CARGOTO ANDFROMSOUTH^AFRICAO AND30 .CARGOJJj CARRIEDBYAIRCRAFTOF SOUTHAFRICANREGISTRYORCHARTEREDBY SOUTHAFRICA.DOES  IT MEETCRITERIA IDENTIFIED?AND   IF  NOT,  WHY NOT?COULD  HAVE SHORT-TERMEFFECT  ON  THE MOVEMENTOF  CERTAIN  GOODS BUTSOUTH  AFRICA COULDADAPT  TO  IT almost completely  WITHIN ASHORT  TIME. could have  MODEST PSYCHOLOGICIMPACT  BUT WOULD HAVENO  EFFECT  ON DAILYLIVES  OF  SOUTH AFRICANCITIZENSHOW WOULT.   IT be implemented (I.EVOLUNTARY ORMANDATORY)IT WOULD  HAVE TOBE MANDATORYAND UNIVERSALIN APPLICATION.FEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONIF  NOT applied by SWITZERLAND,SOUTH AFRICACOULD EASILYDIVERT  AIR CARGOTHROUGH THATCOUNTRY. THEPOSSIBILITIESFOR EVASIONTHROUGH SMUGGLINGWOULD be considerable.EASE OFREVERSALCOULD BEEASILYREVERSEDWIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIESB) NEIGHBORING STATESA) WOULD INCONVENI ffJCEEXPORTS OF SOME goods from WESTERN countries to SOUTH AFRICA ANDWOULD ENTAIL SOME LOSSOF REVENUE. FOR WESTERNAIRLINES.B) &apos; DEPENDING UPON .THEIR DEPENDENCE Of.AIR  TRANSPORT from south  AFRICA,  COULD CAUS^SOME  DIFFICULTY INOBTAINING CERTAINPRODUCTS, E.G.,PERISHABLE goods of retaliation-TION   IN THISFIELDNOT APPLICABLECOmO30mH
NATURE OF &apos;MEASUREuUJco12:STOPOFFICIALPROMOTION iOF COMMERCE(E.G.*TRADE FAIR$,ETC.)ItIIIIIDOES  IT MEETCRITERIA IDENTIFIED?AND  IF NOT/ WHY NOT?NO.     WOULD  HAVE ONLYMINIMAL PHYCHOLOGICALAND  ECONOMIC EFFECTWITH NO  IMPACT ON the daily  LIVES  OF SOUTHAFRICAN CITIZENSHOW WOULD   IT be implemented (I.EVOLUNTARY ORMANDATORY)VOLUNTARYFEASIBILITY OFEFFECTIVEIMPLEMENTATIONCOULD BEIMPLEMENTEDEFFECTIVELYIN CONSULTATIONWITH INDUSTRYEASE OFREVERSALYESWIDER implications for COUNTRIESINVOLVEDA) WESTERN COUNTRIESB) NEIGHBORING STATESA) SOME adverse effects  ON exports are POSSIBLEB) NONEPROBABILITYOF retaliation-TION  IN THISFIELDNONE4&quot;?CCoujco

</content>
</cab>
