<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/54/14 images: 160-174</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERN!/IENTCC(74) 14thConclusionsCOPY no cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 2 MAY 1974at 4.45 pm present the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon Edward Short mp lord President of the Council (Item 1)The Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-jones lord chancellor the Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon James Callaghan mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth Affairs (In the Chair for items 2 and 3)The Rt Hon Roy Jenkins mp secretary of State for the home department the Rt Hon Anthony Crosland mp secretary of State for the Environment(Item 1)The Rt Hon Barbara Castle mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp secretary of State for Education and science
The Rt Hon Merlyn Rees MP The Rt Hon Fred Peart. mp secretary of State for Northern Ireland Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Rt Hon Harold Lever mp chancellor of the Duchy of LancasterALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Samuel Silkin QC mp attorney GeneralSECRETARIATSir John hunt mr P D Nairne (Item 2)Mr H F T Smith (Item 2)Mr J Anson (Items 1 and 3)Mr D Evans (Item 2)Mr R L Baxter (Items 1 and 3)contents item                                                         Subject page 1 STATUTORY PAY CONTROLS: USE OF CONSENT POWERSArmed Forces Pay 1General 42 FOREIGN AFFAIRSPortugal 8European Community: Renegotiation 83               1974 UPRATING OF SOCIAL SECURITY BENEFITS 9ii
STATUTORY PAY      1.        The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the SecretaryCONTROLS: USE       of State for Employment (C(74) 33) on the use of his consentOF CONSENT powers under the Counter-Inflation Act 1973.    They also hadPOWERS before them a minute dated I May from the Secretary of State for defence to the Prime Minister about the pay of the armed forcesin Northern IrelandArmd Forces Pay       THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DEFENCE said that, in response to a request by the Prime Minister, he had put forward a number of proposals for improving conditions for the armed forces in Northern Ireland.   Some of these proposals related toallowances and entitlements, but the root of the problem waspay.    The Armed Forces Pay Review Body (AFPRB) was expected to produce within the next 3 weeks or so a report onarmed forces pay to be applied from 1 April.    The review body had to work strictly within the limits of the Pay Code,and it was difficult within those limits to take account of theparticular pressures under which the army was working inNorthern Ireland.    Under the 1970 arrangements there was already an &quot;X factor&quot; of 5 per cent to take account of the specialcircumstances of the armed forces, including danger, familyseparation, and their total commitment to the job.    The Pay Codealso provided some scope for payments for &quot;unsocial hours&quot;,but there had been difficulty in reaching agreement with the pay board on its application to the forces, and the maximum whichthe Board were likely to allow was about  30 million.    Thiswould make possible a 4 per cent increase in the &quot;X factor&quot;generally, plus an additional payment of 35p a day for thoseserving in Northern Ireland.    He thought that any payment of less than 5Op a day to those in Northern Ireland would seemderisory, and at the same time the forces needed and deserved anincrease in the &quot;X factor&quot;1 of about 5 per cent generally.    Thecost of this would be  38. 5 million and the extra  8. 5 million could only be authorised by the Secretary of State&apos;s power ofconsent under the Counter-Inflation Act 1973.    He proposedtherefore to indicate to the AFPRB that if in their report theychose to recommend an increase of 5 per cent in the ;&quot;X factor&quot;and an extra payment of 5Op a day for those in Northern Irelandand if the Pay Board found these additions inconsistent with the code, Ministers would give the necessary consent.This concession would apply equally to the Ulster DefenceRegiment; beyond that he did not know of any other group who could claim that their own conditions in any way resembledthe onerous duties of the forces in Northern Ireland.1
THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN IRELAND saidthat he supported the case put forward by the Secretary of Statefor Defence, for the armed forces in Northern Ireland, but he did not agree that there would be no repercussions.    The royal ulster Constabulary (RUC), although their duties were not thesame as those of the armed forces, had suffered a high casualtyrate and worked extraordinarily long hours, often side by side with the army.    He thought they had a similar case for anincrease in their pay.In discussion it was argued that itwas disturbing to find that theforces in Northern Ireland, which were at present the onlyoperational units in the army, were being treated worse thanthose elsewhere.    For instance, those in Germany were notexposed to the same dangers, and could be accompanied by their families, but also received an overseas allowance and betterallowances for dependants.    For the sake of the morale of thearmy in Northern Ireland it was urgent to remedy this situation,even if it meant taking special measures.    On the other hand,it was argued that the reason for the higher allowances inGermany was the much higher cost of living.    While full account should be given to the undoubted hardships suffered by the troopsin Northern Ireland, it was also necessary to have regard to thepossible repercussions; for instance, in addition to the RUC,a case could also be made out on behalf of the firemen andambulance services in Northern Ireland.     Every other case that had been put to the Cabinet had been scrutinised in detail for itsrepercussions by the Sub-Committee on Pay Negotiations of the ministerial Committee on Economic Policy (EC(P)).    Thesuggestion that the Government should indicate in advance to theAFPRB specific recommendations which Ministers would findacceptable was inconsistent with the independent status of the review Body; and to do so at this late stage might only lead to a delay in the presentation of its report.In further discussion, it was suggested that an alternative procedure for handling the case would be to ask the AFPRB to produce itsreport as quickly as possible, and at the same time to make a careful study of the way in which consent powers could be usedwithout undue repercussions elsewhere.    There were grounds forhoping that the report might be ready in a week or 10 days; andthe Government might then at once announce that, whereas the review Body had been limited by the constraints of the Pay Code,the Government would set aside those limits by the use of theconsent power and make certain additions to the increases recommended in the report.    In that way no time would be lost,and the resulting settlement would have been more carefully considered by the Government from the point of view of its
repercussive effects.    In order to pave the way for this procedure, there might be some advantage to the government if the AFPRB report included a passage to the effect that the stage 3 limits had prevented the Review Body from recommendingas much as they would have otherwise thought right, but on balance it would be better not to press the Review Body to do this, since they might put it in a way which would embarrass the Government by justifying still wider concessions.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up this part of the discussion,said that the Cabinet agreed that the forthcoming pay settlement for the armed forces should take special account of theparticular difficulties under which they were working in NorthernIreland.    They also agreed that, while the Review Body shouldnot be pressed to include specific recommendations in itsreport, the Chairman should be asked to deliver the report as quickly as possible,    In the meantime, the Ministerial Sub-Committee on Pay Negotiations should examine in detail the improvements in pay that had been proposed, and consider howadditional help for the armed forces in Northern Ireland couldbe given and justified in a way which would minimise therepercussive effects.    The Secretary of State for defence should report to the Cabinet, by Monday 13 May, on theprogress which had been made on this issue and on the otherimprovements in conditions in Northern Ireland which were currently under discussion.The Cabinet -1.      Took note, with approval, of the summing upof their discussion by the Prime^Minister.2.      Invited the Secretary of State for employment to arrange for the Ministerial Sub-Committee on pay negotiations to examine fully the proposed improvements in the pay of the armed forces in Northern Ireland, witha view to limiting the repercussive effect of anyMinisterial consent that might need to be given.3.      Invited the Secretary of State for Defence -ix       to ask the Chairman of the Armed forces pay Review Body to produce his report as quickly as possible;ii.       To circulate a report to the Cabinet by13 May, as indicated by the Prime Minister inhis summing up., 3
THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said that theannounced policy of the Government was to move smoothly fromthe statutory pay controls to voluntary methods, using the limited power of consent to ease the most exceptional difficulties,while getting those who had made settlements to stick to them andothers to settle at much the same level as hitherto.    the ministerial Sub-Committee on Pay Negotiations had been considering a number of difficult pay problems as candidates forthe use of consent powers.    As regards the major cases their conclusions so far fell into 2 categories.    The Sub-committee agreed that the Government should be ready to give consents forGovernment scientists, the railways, and the London underground;and a consent for the London underground might have to beextended to the London busmen.    On the cases for teachers,nurses and postal workers, the Sub-Committee had been divided,and his memorandum set out the arguments on both sides.Teachers, nurses and postal workers had undoubtedly fallenbehind other groups in recent years, but the Sub-committee agreed that a general pay review for these 3 groups would be toocostly and too repercussive.    They had therefore consideredproposals for selective action for each of the 3 groups, at a total public expenditure cost of about  40 million.    The proposal fornurses was for selective improvements in pay, to be linked tothe recommendations of the Briggs Report on nursing.    the improvements would be designed to remedy the shortage of nurseteaching staff, to attract the additional staff needed to replace thereduction in work contribution by the learner in the hospital, andto maintain the morale and image of the profession.    About40 per cent of nurses would benefit.    The proposal for teacherswas to extend the existing system of selective pay additions toimprove the staffing of schools in stress areas; about 10 per cent of teachers would benefit from this.    His memorandum suggestedthat this action might be so limited, and liable to be taken by the teachers as divisive, that it might do more harm than good; buton that question the Cabinet would wish to have the views of theSecretary of State for Education and Science.    Finally, for the postal workers, the proposal was for selective improvementsaffecting a minority of postal workers, mainly members of theUnion of Post Office Workers (UPW).    It could not be linked to any advance in social policy, and could raise problems for other tradesunion leaders who wer , trying to avoid pressing their own claimsas special cases.Some members of the Sub-Committee had taken the view thatconsents for these 3 selective increases would do little to allaydiscontent and might increase it among those who did not benefit.The main effect would be to add to the difficulty of holding pay4
increases at about Stage 3 levels for the rest of the pay round.Many union leaders would privately prefer a minimum of consentsbecause special cases added to their difficulties with their ownmembers.    On the other hand some of the cases, for instancethe railways, the London underground and Government scientists,seemed overwhelming, and action on the selective proposals fornurses, teachers or postal workers could help to combat theimpression that the power of consent was to be used mainly for those who had power to injure the economy.    Those who took thisview believed that the selective proposals would afford a constructive approach, taking account of social considerations aswell as industrial power,    which would help the Government inurging others to hold back.   He himself shared the latter view ingeneral, but in view of the difficulties attending the proposedimprovements for teachers and postmen, he had recommended thatthe use of the consent power, apart from the railways, Londonunderground and Government scientists and certain other minorcases, should be restricted to the selective improvements for the nurses.    If the Cabinet agreed, he would announce this decision in the House of Commons on Monday 6 May on the lines of thedraft annexed to his memorandum.In discussion of the proposed selective increases for particular groups, the following main points were made -a. Nurses.    It was argued that the nurses had aparticular grievance because they had been told by theprevious Government that their case would go to theproposed Relativities Board after that of the miners.The growing practice of employing agency nurses earningup to  75 a week was a particular irritant to thepermanently employed nurses earning far smaller amounts.Although the union leaders took a responsible line, feelingswere rising.    The nurses were also concerned at thefailure to act on the Briggs report, which had been commisioned by the previous Labour administration and presented in 1972.    The selective increases that had been proposed, taken together with the acceptanceof the recommendations in the Briggs report, could be presented as part of a planned social policy which would improve morale in the profession and should not createrepercussions outside it.b. Teachers.   It was argued that over the last 8 years the increases in salary received by teachers had amountedto only 60 per cent of the average increase in all salaries.The resulting staff, shortages were bringing some schoolsunder particular stress; and in some London boroughs theservice was now approaching a breakdown, with large
numbers of children receiving only part-time education.This was an unprecedented situation,    In some Scottishschools the teachers were already working to rule.    Whilethe proposed selective increases would not satisfy theNational Union of Teachers as a response to their more general pay demandsj they would have difficulty in rejecting the increases if these were presented as a social and educational measure.    Teachers generally wouldprobably accept the increases as better than nothing,whereas they would be particularly resentful if the consentpower was exercised in favour of nurses but not for them.c.        Postal workers^   It was argued that as a result ofthe application of the pay policy the postal workers were now worse off in real terms than they had been in 1971.They had been disappointed in their expectation of benefiting,as the Civil Service had done, from the anomalies provision in the Pay Code;  and they had then fixed their hopes on theprovision for relativities, which the present Government had rejected.    If nothing were done for them now they might therefore complain that the present Government had adopted a more rigid stance than the previous Administration.Because of the difficulties in limiting the repercussions,it was suggested that a preferable course might be to agreewith the UPW and the Trades Union Congress (TUC) that their case would be the first to be considered after the end of Stage 3 ofthe pay policy.    On the other hand it was argued that the TUCmight find difficulty in conceding this as a special case.    More-over, the UPW had not taken a militant line, .and could be relied on to co-operate in carrying out a voluntary policy providedthat the present decline in the relative position of their members could be remedied.In general discussion of all the cases it was argued that, in a statutory system that was heavily based on the principle of comparability, it was difficult to change the relative position ofany group without giving rise to demands from other groups withinflationary consequences.    So long as this attitude persisted themembers of the General Council of the TUC would prefer a minimum of consents to be given, so as to avoid consequential difficulties with their own members,    In working out a voluntary policy withthe TUC it would be right to take more account of recruitmentdifficulties, particularly in the larger cities, so as to avoid thedanger of progressive industrial stagnation and the collapse ofpublic services.    Meanwhile there was a strong social and moralcase for each of the groups that had been discussed.6
THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed with the proposals by the Secretary of State for employment for the use of the consent power for Governmentscientists, the railways and the London underground.    They also agreed with the proposed selective increases for the nurses, the teachers and the postal workers.    The question whether theproposed consent for the London underground should be extended tothe London busmen should be considered further in the ministerial sub-Committee on Pay Negotiations.    The Secretary of state should make a general announcement about the use of his consentpowers on Monday 6 May, in consultation with the ministers responsible for the various groups concerned.The Cabinet -4.        Took note, with approval, of the summing upof their discussion by the Prime Minister, and invited the Secretary of State for Employment toproceed accordingly.5.        Invited the Secretary of State for employment to arrange for the Ministerial Sub-Committee on pay negotiations to consider whether the consent for theLondon underground should be extended to coverLondon busmen.7
FOREIGN 2. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidAFFAIRS that the Junta, under the leadership of General Spinola, appearedto have been successful in bringing the whole of Portugal under its control;  and the support which it was receiving from the armedPortugal forces in the Overseas Provinces had so far kept the position steady-there.    We were recognising the new regime.    Senhor Soares, theGeneral Secretary of the Portuguese Socialist Party, had been sentto London by General Spinola as his emissary, and had been seen by the Prime Minister and himself.    Senhor Soares had told themthat the Socialist Party would take part in a Government which itwas hoped to form in the course of the next few weeks, and were seeking the post of Prime Minister.    The Communist Party alsowished to participate.    Forces of the right wing were disorganised.The new regime had indicated that they would welcome our advice on the problems of carrying out a policy of decolonisation and hewas sending a message to General Spinola offering any help wecould give in this connection.    It was clear that the Portuguesewould face great problems in attempting to move quickly from themethods and machinery of a totalitarian state to a democracy, butrecent events had created a hopeful opportunity.    The consequences for the political situation in Southern Africa could be profound.The Cabinet -1.      Took not a (si the statement by the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary.European THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY informed theCommunity: Cabinet that at a meeting of the Ministerial-Committee on EuropeanRenegotiation       Community Strategy on 25 April there had been a full discussion ofour objectives in the renegotiation of our terms of membership ofthe European Community.    Since the meeting of the Council ofMinisters (Foreign Affairs) on 7 May would take place between thefirst and second rounds of polling in the French presidential election, and there was a consequent risk that our case might,if presented at that Council meeting, become an issue in the Election,the Committee had concluded that we should wait until the subsequent meeting of the Council of Ministers (Foreign Affairs) on 4 June.There would be no loss of momentum in the work on renegotiationsince the additional period \wuld be used for bilateral consultationsat official level with other Community countries and the Commission;and with Canada, Australia, New Zealand and the developing countries of the Commonwealth Sugar Agreement (CSA).    The basicaim in these bilaterals would be to present our problems and to demonstrate the strength of our case to the Community;  officialswould not be proposing solutions, though they might lift a corner ofthe veil from our ideas.    In the light of the outcome of the bilateral8
consultations and further detailed consideration of our objectiveshe would be putting to the Cabinet before the Whitsun recess amemorandum setting out our negotiating stance for the council meeting on 4 June.    This would be concerned with the three basicareas of the Community budget, the Common Agricultural Policyand Commonwealth and developing countries and with our generalaim of removing the illiberal characteristics of the Communityarrangements.i A   MlThere seemed an increasing prospect that our renegotiation ofterms of membership might take,.place against the background ofa major crisis of confidence within the Community resulting in part from economic difficulties exacerbated by increased oil prices.The decision of the Italian Government to introduce an importdeposit scheme had caused a considerable shock in the Community.This underlined the inability of the Community in its present form to deal with the major problems which confronted it.    It alsoreinforced the general feeling that the time had come for are-examination of the Community&apos;s role, future purpose and objectives, on a more realistic basis than had been apparent todate.The Cabinet -2.      Took note.3.        The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Social Services.    Their discussion and the conclusions reached are recorded separately.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT1974 UPRATINGOF SOCIAL,SECURITYBENEFITSPreviousReference:CC(74)12thConclusions,Minute copy NO31-cabinet confidential annex cc(74) 14th Conclusions Minute 3Thursday 2 May 1974 at 4. 45 pmThe Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Social Services (C(74) 34) proposing recognition for extraeffort by staff of the Department of Health and Social Security(DHSS) who were involved in the uprating of pensions and other social security benefits.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SOCIAL SERVICES said thatshe had inherited a discontented and militant staffs, who had reactedbadly to the tight timetable for pensions uprating (13 weeks insteadof 18), at a time of year including the Easter and Spring BankHolidays and the start of the summer leave season.    The staff side had put forward proposals on which they had asked forsatisfaction before their members would undertake the extra work.Besides covering staff numbers, accommodation and careerprospects, the proposals included a request for a once only cashbonus over and above the normal overtime.rates.    She had told them that this was out of the question.    She had then consulted theSub-Committee on Pay Negotiations of the Ministerial Committeeon Economic Policy (EC(P)) about a proposal for giving one additional day&apos;s leave for every 30 hours of overtime worked inconnection with the uprating.    This would cost nothing since theleave would be taken when the work load was slack.    The Sub-Committee had however not been prepared to endorse this proposal.Consequently the Civil and Public Services Association (CPSA),representing 70 per cent of the staff in local offices, had now decided to ban all overtime work, to refuse to co-operate with anycasual staff recruited to help with the uprating, and to ban work onthe uprating even in normal hours.    The last decision, if persisted in, could lead only to a sharp confrontation with the management,with the possibility of disciplinary action.   At the same time theAssociation had written a letter to the National Federation of old Age Pensions Associations (NFOAPA) explaining that although
they were in favour of the uprating they could not undertake itbecause of the staff shortage.    She hoped that the new national aggreement on Civil Service overtime rates, which would offer a worthwhile improvement, would be announced soon, but this wouldnot be enough to end the dispute.    The Secretary of State for employment and the Minister of State, Civil Service Department,had both seen continuing difficulties about any grant of leavebecause of the repercussive effects and because of the political difficulties of making an award for this group of staff.by means ofthe consent procedure.    The Secretary of State for Employmenthad suggested as an alternative the possibility of asking theNational Staff Side to agree to the use of a part of the flexibilitymargin under the Pay Code, but to put forward such a proposalformally would effectively commit the Government to a cashpayment even if the proposal were refused by the National staff side.    For this reason she thought that a leave bonus was the only practicable solution.    She could not be sure that the unions would accept it; but she v/ould attend their Annual Conferences, whichwould take place very shortly, and would try to persuade them to change their attitude.    If they persisted in the face of this additionaloffer, the Government would at least be on strong ground inarguing that the blame for any delay in the uprating must be placedon the staff.    Accordingly she invited the Cabinet to agree that every effort must be put into reaching some agreement during theweek beginning 6 May, preferably by the offer of a leave bonus,to be coupled, if possible, with the announcement of the new national overtime agreement.In discussion it was argued that       for the staff to choose whatthey should do in working hours must be regarded as a grossbreach of discipline.    Before considering the detailed nature of possible concessions, the Cabinet should consider as a matter ofprinciple whether any concession should be offered.    It would beimpossible to differentiate this case effectively from other peakload situations.    For instance, the Inland Revenue had a similarproblem, partly arising out of the same pensions increase; and intheir case the staff shortages were so bad that the offer of extraleave might be impossible.    A case for a leave bonus for civilianworkers employed by the Army in Northern Ireland had beenresisted by the Government for 2j years.   If the Cabinet gaveway to pressure in this case, they would be unable to resist the pressure for many other similar cases.    If, on the other hand,they stood firm, the likelihood was that the pensioners would notblame the Government but the staff associations.    The letter fromthe CPSA to the NFOAPA showed that the union were aware of theirvulnerability.2
In further discussion it was argued that either a cash bonus or aleave bonus would have to be taken into account under the Code,and would consequently require the use either of part of the flexibility margin or of the power of consent.    The use of the powerof consent for a concession to civil servants in such circumstances could have far-reaching effects which would make it more difficultto hold the line against other claims for special consents.    In anycase it was not open to the Government to use the power of consentuntil a case had been rejected by the Pay Board;  and the Pay board might well take the line that so long as the flexibility margin was available any special payment or leave bonus should be found from it.    These difficulties might be overcome if the National Staff Sidecould be persuaded to agree to the use of part of the flexibilitymargin, on the basis of a confidential understanding that if they wished to propose any other use of the flexibility margin later in theyear the Government would see that the amount that they had given up would somehow be made good to them.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY, summing upthe discussion, said that although a strong case could be made against giving any special concession, the Cabinet felt that theimportance of the uprating timetable justified some exceptionalaction in this instance.    Subject to the concurrence of the PrimeMinister and the Lord President, they favoured the suggestedapproach to the National Staff Side seeking their agreement to theuse of the flexibility margin to accommodate the notional cost of aleave bonus, on the confidential understanding that the amountsurrendered would be made good if the National Staff Side wishedto put forward alternative proposals for its use later in the year.The Secretary of State for Social Services should explore thissuggestion urgently with the Lord President and the Secretary ofState for Employment with a view to implementing it if possible before the annual conferences of the staff associations concerned.If it was not possible to solve the problem on this basis, theSecretary of State should circulate a further report to the Cabinet.The Cabinet -1. Took note, with approval, of the summing upof their discussion by the Foreign and commonwealth secretary.2.        Subject to the concurrence of the Prime Ministerand the Lord President, invited the Secretary of Statefor Social Services to seek a settlement on the lines indicated by the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary inhis summing up, and to report further if a settlement on these lines could not be achieved.Cabinet Office3 May 1974


</content>
</cab>
