<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/77/0 images: 143-149</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CXcuucla. lOcm issued /)iitItHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)E CRET. COPY NO.C A B I N E T      55  (55).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.&apos;v7.1., on WEDNESDAY,25th OCTOBER, 1953, at 2.30 p.m.PRESENT:The Right Hon.  J. Ramsay MaoDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister.      (in the Chair).The Right Hon. The Right Hon..Stanley Baldwin, M.P., Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Lord President of the Council. Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right HornSir John Gilmour, Bt., D.S.O.,M.P., Seoretary of State for home Affairs.The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.B.E.,C.M.G., M.P., Secretary ofState for India.The Right Hon. &apos;Sir Philip cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E., M.C., M.P,j Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hon.Sir Godfrey Collins, K,B.E.,C.M.G., M.P* , Seoretary ofState for Scotland.The Right Hon.The Viscount sankey, G.B.E, ,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. I &apos;Sir John Simon, G. CS.I. ,   \K.C.V.O. , O.B.L. , K..C. , M.P.VSecretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.J.H.  Thomas, M.P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Most Hon.The &apos;Marquess of Londonderry,K.G. , M.V.O. , Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Sir Edward Hilton Young,G.B.E., D.S.O.,  D.S.C., M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Walter Runciman, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.Lord I rv/inj K.G. , G.C.S.I. ,V      G.C.I.E., President of theBoard of Education.Tae Right Hon.Sir Henry Betterton, Bt.,CB.E. , M.P., Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Sir Bolton Eyres Monsell,G.B.E,, M.P., First Lordof the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.Major The Right Hon.W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., first commissioner of Works.Golon.el Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B. , G.C.M.G. ,.............  Secretary.
THE UNEMPLOYMENTBILL.UnemploymentInsurance.Unemp1oyme ntAssistance,(previous reference:Cabinet 55(3?), Con-elusion 8.)1*   The Cabinet resumed, consideration, begunthe same morning,  of the Unemployment Pill attachedto C^P.,-832 (33),    ^heir deliberations were in thenature of a. &quot;Second Reading&quot; discussion, prior tothe consideration of the Bill in detail by a CabinetCommittee,The Minister of Labour gave the Cabinet acomplete exposition of the Bill and described itssalient points.While no decisions were taken, the followingpoints for the gtiidance of the Minister of Labourand the Cabinet Committee emerged from the dis-cussion;-(1)  Juveniles under age of 18,The scheme was criticised on twogr ounds:-(a) That the contributions&apos; (2d.) of theJuveniles were to be paid into theUnemployment Insurance Fund,, butthat half the cost of the TrainingCentres (which were part of thebenefit available to unemployedJuveniles) was borne by theUnemployment Fund and half by theExchequer.(b) In regard to the provision (Clause 9)that &quot;Unemployment benefit is not.to be paid to boys and girls under16, but the dependantTs allowancepayable to persons on insurance benefit is to be extended so as tocover boys and girls up to age 16attending Centres or unemployed-1-
it for reasons outside their control&quot;,it was pointed out that the parentor guardian would receive no suchextension of the dependant&apos;s allow-ance unless he or she happened tobe unemployed and entitled to benefit.This,  it was suggested, would be unpopular,The Cabinet Committee was askedto consider this point, with abias towards the payment to anyparent, whether employed orunemployed,  in respect  of anyunemployed juvenile .(2) Duration of Benefit.    (Clause 3.)The Chancellor of the Exchequer said he would discuss with the Minister ofLabour whether the maximum figure forthe duration of benefit could not beraised from 47 weeks to a year.(3) Agriculture.    (Clause 20.)mhe provision that &quot;&quot;he Statutory Com-mittee is to be required to enquire andreport within a specified period as to thenature of an Unemployment Insurance Schemesuitable for agriculture&quot;, and. that  &quot;TheMinister will be required within a furtherspecified period to lay a draft of a schemebefore Parliament which, when confirmed by resolution of both Houses, will become effec-tive&quot;, did not commend itself to the cabinet it was pointed out that it would virtuallycommit the Cabinet in advance to accept
a plan drawn -up by a Statutory Committeeon a subject of a most controversialcharacter on which the wishes of theindustry itself, both in England and scotland, had not been accuratelyascertained.    It was suggested that itwould be better to drop the Clause andto announce that the subject would beenquired into, not by the StatutoryCommittee, but by some independent body with a wide term of reference,  e.g.,  &quot;Toconsider the question of agricultural labour and make recommendations thereon&quot;.Further,  it was suggested as desirablethat the body to make this enquiry shouldbe announced when the Bill was Introduced.The Minister of Labour and theCabinet Committee were asked toconsider this proposal,(4)  Share Fishermen,The Secretary of State for Scotland was authorised, if he thought fit, tosubmit a scheme for the inclusion of&quot;Share Fishermen&quot; to the Minister ofLabour and the minister:er of Agricultureand Fisheries with a view to its consider-ation by the Cabinet if the three ministers agreed.(5) The Live Register.The Cabinet felt that the increase inthe Live Register which the Minister ofLabour anticipated would follow theintroduction of the Scheme would create a bad impression in the minds of the
public,  notwithstanding that itwould not really be due to any actualincrease in unemployment.The Minister of Labour was askedwhetherby the Cabinet to consider/any new method of presenting the unemployment figures could be devised, for intro-duction at the same time as the new scheme, which might stress^ evenmore than the existing form of presentation, the numbers of personsin employment as compared with thoseout of employment,( 6) ,The Increase of Officials.It was felt that the increase of officials and their cost would be thesubject of public criticism, but theCabinet were given to understand thatthere would be a transitional period during which the existing staffs ofLocal Authorities would be utilisedto a considerable extent, and that experience during this transitional period would enable suitable adjustments to be made.   There would also be avail-able towards the cost of the officials of the central Government the sum of 750,000 which had hitherto been paidto Local Authorities in respect.ofPublic Assistance work.   nevertheless it was realised that, even from thefirst,  in large centres it would benecessary to appoint Officials and tohave separate accommodation&apos;-4-
(7 ) Post-Training Scheme,,A scheme, explained by the Ministerof Labour, whereby Local authorities who were undertaking special workmight be invited to employ for short periods men who had completed their training at Training. Centres inorder to give them some experienceof working at their new trade at current rates of labour, commendeditself to the Cabinet,he Cabinet agreed  To refer the Unemployment Bill attachedto C.P.-232 (33) for detailed considera-tion to the Unemployment InsurancePolicy Committee, the composition ofwhich is as follows:-mhe Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Secretary of State for HomeAffairs,The Secretary of State for DominionAffairs,The Secretary of State for Scotland,The Minister of Health,The Minister of Agriculture andFisheries,,   The Minister of Labour,The First Commissioner of Works,
ALLOTMENTSAND SMALL-HOLDINGS *(previous reference:Cabinet 11(32),  Con-clusion 3(d) .)2, At the end of the discussion recorded inthe preceding Conclusion, the Prime minister informed the Cabinet that the number of allotmentswould be increasing very considerably in the coming year, owing largely to voluntary efforts.   Themovement was also extending to small-holdings.One of the leaders of this movement, which was organised by Quakers, had pointed out that in thecase of a man receiving unemployment benefit, but was in the first stages of becoming a producer froma small-holding, it was difficult in the existingcircumstances to assist him without his losing hisbenefit before he was able to support himself.    he asked the Minister of Labour to consider whether itwas possible to obtain any general powers which wouldenable him to deal equitably with such cases.2, Whitehall Gardens,October 25. 1933-6-

</content>
</cab>
