<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/77/0 images: 158-169</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
civ- fcOa-aCcdnu&amp;V,147OCUMENT IS THE&apos; PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).COPY NO.CABINET    58  (35)-CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street,  S.W.1., on THURSDAY,26th OCTOBER, 1935, at    3,0 p.m.PRESENT:The Right Hon. J&quot;. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P,,Prime Minister,right Hon.Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,lord President of the Council.fRight Hon.gir John Gilmour,- Bt., D.S.O.,It.P., Secretary of State forpome Affairs.fpRight Hon.the Viscount Hailsham,jffecretary of State for War.BRight Hon.M.H.  Thomas, M.P.Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.\ ;fe .:Most Hon.[The Marquess of Londonderry,l.G. , M.V.C,  Secretary ofstate for Air,fjjRight Hon.&quot;gir Edvreird Hilton Young,I.B.E., D.S.O., D.S.C, M.P.Minister of Health.gRight Hon.I Sir Bolton Eyres Monsell,ll[.B.E., M.P. , First lord of the Admiralty.fcight Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C , M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andfisheries.(in the Chair).The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P. ,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.The Viscount Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, CCS.I,&apos;,K.C.V.C, O.B.E., K,C, M.P. ,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E., M.C., M.P.,  Secretary;of State for the Colonies.liThe Right Hon.Sin Godfrey Collins, K.B.E.,,C.M.G., M.P.,  Secretary ofState for Scotland.The Right Hon.Walter Runciman, M.P.President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.Lord Irwin, K.G., G.C.S.I.,G.CI.E,, President of theBoard of Education.The Right Hon.Sir Henry Betterton, Bt.,CB.E. , M.P., Minister ofLabour.Major The Right Hon.W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P.* first commissioner of Works.gnel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B., G. CM.G. ...... .............  Secretary..x Present for latter part of Meeting only.
THE AMERICAN-DEBT.1. The Chancellor of the Exchequer recalled that &quot;before the departure of Sir P. Leith Ross, forAmerica it had not been possible to arrange a(previous cabinet 41 (33) Cabinet meeting so he had circulated a MemorandumConclusion 1.)on the policy to be adopted.      He had invited anyof his colleagues who had comments to communicate them in writing and,  in the absence of comments, hewould assume that the proposed instructions were approved.     (CP.-222  (33) Most Secret).       TheChancellor took this opportunity to inform theCabinet of a talk he had had with M. Bonnet,  theFrench Minister of Finance,  just before the endof the World Conference.      He had told M. Bonneton broad lines of the kind of offer we might get(as set forth in CP.-222 (33)) and M.  Bonnethad replied that in those circumstances we oughtto accept.      In reply to Mr.  Chamberlain M.  Bonnethad said that the French Chamber took the viewthat France ought not to pay anything, but.thathe personally thought that an offer conceivedon similar lines ought to be accepted by France.The Chancellor had reminded M. Bonnet that Franceowed us money and that it would not be right for     her    to distinguish between her creditors.M. Bonnet had admitted that this was not at allunreasonable, the more so because the United states had treated the French badly and we had treatedthemwell.Sir F. Leith Ross had left for Yfashingtonknowing that we wanted a permanent settlement ifpossible.      He had had many conversations withMr. Acheson. .   The latter had shown himself friendly and had seemed to give general approval to the lineSir F.  Leith Ross was taking, but in this he hadnot been supported by his superiors.      Mr.. Acheson.
was reported to nave orfered his resignation owing todisagreement with the latest development inPresident Roosevelt&apos;s financial policy, but theChancellor had not yet heard that his resignationhad been accepted.      As time went on it became clear that the American President was being influenced by the difficulties of his political situationand that in order to escape rebuff, he would haveto avoid any controversial settlement.      He hadalready rejected as out of the question the schemeknown as the &quot;Warburg Plan&quot;.      The President&apos;s line was that it was all nonsense to suppose that wecould not pay    that we could pay three times thesum we had in mind;    and that the difficulty withand notus was political/eoonomic.    Our reply was that itwas both political and economic;  that our people were becoming more and more reluctant to pay, andthat/it was wo who had to take the action of payment. President Roosevelt had to offeracceptable terms.      The latest communicationindicated that Sir P. Leith Ross and Sir R.  Lindsaydid not think that a permanent settlement could bea chieved.The Chancellor of the Exchequer recalled that as stated in CP.-222  (33) he had alwaysstipulated that if we were to be the first tonegotiate for a new settlement with America, we mustbe protected against the possibility that otherdebtor countries subsequently should get morefavourable treatment, and that if at any time morefavourable terms were granted by the U.S.A.  Governmentto any other debtor, they should be automaticallyextended to us.      The   President said that this condition was out of the question.     Apparently
he wanted to base credit operations on bonds to beissued by this country and could not do so if they/ere liable to variation.      The conclusion to whichthe Chancellor of the Exchequer had come was that have towe should/drop the idea of a permanent settlement and instruct Sir P. Leith Ross to try for a temporarysettlement.      He was opposed to a settlement fortoo long a time.      He did not want us to be boundwhen our debtors were not bound to pay us.      Conse-quently, he contemplated a settlement for about threeyears which should be effected hy the payment of a lump sum.      The object of paying a lump sum was toget away from the routine of half-yearly payments,the effect of which might be for the Americans tosay/Vhy should not those payments continue for fifty years?&quot;     A further advantage of the lump sum wasthat it might be paid out of any possible surplusthat might be available at the end of the financialyear which otherwise v/ould go towards the Sinking Fund.Referring to the period the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer said it might be for two years, butbusiness houses would prefer the longer term.If four years were taken we ran the risk of having committed ourselves to a fixed paymentalthough circumstances might in the intervalhave altered to our advantage.      On the whole,therefore, he preferred to put a limit of threeyears.
In the discussion which followed the chancellor the Exchequer&apos;s statement it was generally recognised that a permanent settlement v/as hardlylikely to be reached at the present time, and threepossibilities were mentioned:-(1) That we should make no payment at all:(.8) That we should have a temporarysettlement, based on token payments for a period of three years,  oreven five years:(3) that we should undertake to maketoken payments either for a. year or even ad hoc for six months ata t ime .On the first of these three propositions it waspointed out that so long as we continued to make payments we encouraged the hope that we could continue to do so more or less indefinitely.    Bystopping all payments we might perhaps get better terms when the moment arrived at which America was prepared to make a permanent settlement.   This hadbeen the French attitude, and very likely france would get better terms than ourselves.   mhesepayments were becoming more and more unpopular.The rising generation- took the view that the people to whom the debt had originally been owed no longerexisted, and that those people who had come lateinto the War had obtained great benefits.   The lastinterim payment,  it was pointed out, had been madein the belief that it would pave the way to a final settlement.    That expectation had not been realised.To make no payments until a permanent settlement could be reached would show the President of theUnited States that if he pushed its too hardhe would pet nothing. It was recalled thatthe moratorium which had preceded the lausanne conference had resulted in removing from people&apos;s
minds the idea of regular reparations payments andhad prepared the way for a settlement.   To continuetoken payments tended to destroy our own argumentto other debts,that War Debts were on a different footing/,    ^heCabinet had only been given a very short time toconsider C.P.-S82 (33), and the fact that no protesthad been made against it ought not to be reckoned as a final Cabinet decision.The Cabinet were reminded, however, that theresult of our paying nothing would be a violent attackon this country in the United States of America,where we should be described as a fraudulent bankrupt..,,We should probably also have laid at our door the blame for the possible failure of President Roosevelt&apos;financial and economic policy .    In this country anumber of people would be made extremely unhappy,and everywhere there would be serious loss of prestige.Ultimately other nations who owed us money mightwithhold payment and excuse themselves by allegingexactly the same reasons as we had given.    The IrishFree State, though their debt was not on all fourswith the War Debt, would certainly use it as a prece-dent^. and our argument would be adopted by thoseextremists who favoured repudiation of the NationalDebt ,It was recalled that the token payment made last june had been welcome to America and had not evokedmuch adverse cr-iticism here, though perhaps this was due to the expectation that it would lead-to apermaneht settlement.    Public opinion in America wasmoving, even though slowly, in the right direction,,and eventually we minht obtain from America a remission of the Debt:    but this desirable result could not beobtained if we stopped payment.
These views, however, were not advanced as an argument for payment to America of &quot;the full poundof flesh&quot;, &quot;but rather to justify the making of some reasonable payment in order to avoid, very serious consequences.    It was even worth making some payments to get rid of the &quot;nuisance value&quot; of the question.The proposal for a token payment over a period ofthree years was found to be open to the objection that it would terminate during the critical monthsthat precede a Presidential Election, which would bepeculiarly unfavourable to the discussion of a perman-ent settlement.    It was unlikely that a President whointended to stand, for re-election could afford tomake a settlement.   Token payments for five years would result in discussions for a final settlement ata better moment, but were open to the objection ofto a four-year period the Chancellor of the Exchequer/referred to above .The Chancellor of the Exchequer did not refuse toconsider the third course of continuing token payments for a year or by ad hoc monthly instalments, although,as already mentioned, he did not like the idea of getting the American public accustomed to such tokenpayments and to the assumption that  they could bemade for ever.   That was one reason why he preferredthe idea of a lump sum payment to cover three years .The question was raised as to what should be theamount of future token payments, if made.    It was recalled that originally the Cabinet had contemplatedJune paymentthat they should be limited to ^5,000,000.   This sumhad been raised because the Cabinet had been givento understand that President Roosevelt considered around sism of ^10,000,000 would be far better understood by American public opinion and would make it easier
for him to prepare that public opinion for a permanent settlement.    It was suggested, that if it had been contemplated that token payments should be continued the Cabinet would probably have agreed to the smallersum..    As against this the Cabinet were reminded thatthe ^10,000,000 had been agreed to as necessary toobtain from the President a certificate, so to speak,that we were not defaulting.    It would, not be worthwhile to make a payment which would not obtain for usa similar certificate.Some discussion took place as to whether it mightnot be advisable to present to President Roosevelta document, partly financial and partly political in character,, pointing out that we had made proposalsfor a permanent settlement but these had been rejected^asking if the United States Government could not find some way of helping us, and making quite clear thatthere were limits to what public opinion would stand.It was urged, however, that the moment had not comefor so decisive a step, which would be in the natureof a last resort, and it would be better for Sir P.Leith-Ross to continue his unofficial soundings.Another suggestion discussed was that Sir P.Leith-Ross should be recalled to London for discussion,but this was rejected,on the ground that after recallit would be unlikely that he would return to washington and the Press  of both countries would become agitated.The general tenor of the discussion revealedsome hardening of opinion on the subject of payments.It was suggested that it must be put to president roosevelt that if he did not come -to agreement with
us we could not give him any help.The Cabinet was informed that that was precisely the line that Sir P. Leith-Ross had taken.The Cabinet agreed  (a) ^hat Sir P, Leith-Ross should remain for the present in Washington tocontinue his conversations:&apos;V;.;(b) That the Chancellor of the exchequer should give him instructions in the lightof the discussion summarised above:(c) that the subject should remain onthe Agenda of the Cabinet.
EDUCTION ANDIMITATION OPRMAMENTS.he Germanithdrawal.british Policy.previousReferencelabinet 54 (33)lonclusion 1,)m.2. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that the arrangements to besubmitted to the General Commission of the DisarmamentConference would be on the following lines:      theGeneral Commission was to adjourn until not later than December 4th.      In the meantime, the Bureauwas to make arrangements for the future course ofwork with a view to being able to present a reviseof the Draft Convention to the General commission by that date.      The Chairman of the Conference had told Mr. Eden privately that he intended after a preliminary meeting of the Bureau on Friday, to adjourn it until November 22nd.      During the intervalMr. Henderson would himself pursue negotiationswith certain Powers.      It was probable, however,that the French Delegation would oppose thissuggestion.      It was possible that a proposal mightbe made for a small committee of the principalPowers to meet to consider the work to be done bythe Bureau.      Some wished to draft a Convention and present it to Germany for signature, while others,headed by Italy, opposed this course as likely tomake ultimate German acceptance more difficult.
POUSE OP lords reform-f previous reference:Cabinet  563. The time available did not permit the Cabinetto take up the discussion of House of Lords Reform.A proposal was made that the matter should, be discussed in the first instance at a Cabinet Committee, but it(28),  Con-clusion 3.)    was considered advisable for the Cabinet as a whole to have a general discussion before appointing aC orrmitt ee .The Cabinet agreed  That the subject of House of lords reform should be considered at aMeeting of the Cabinet to be heldon THURSDAY,  NOVEMBER 2nd, at 2-30 p.m.
NEXT MEETING- 4, The Cabinet agreed  OP CABINET.(a) That the ordinary weekly Meetingof the Cabinet should not be heldon Wednesday next, November 1st:(b) &quot;o meet  on THURSDAY, NOVEMBER 2nd,at 2-30 p.m., as already mentioned,for consideration of the questionof HOUSE OP LORDS REFORM.2, Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.1,October 26, 1933.

</content>
</cab>
