<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/148/0 images: 34-50</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION OF THE ATTACHED  WESTERN AND GENERALREPORT No. 52,PART II. -FOREIGN AND GENERAL.Peace Discussions.General. The Germans continue to assume the attitude of conquerors towards the Russians, and seem to be pinning their faith upon military successes against other enemy countries.There are various reports about differences of opinion between parties both in Germany and in Austria-Hungary on the subject of war aims.The policy of encouraging nationalism in Germany is being continued in order to counteract propaganda by Bolshevists, and others,&apos; who work upon international ideals in order to shake national resolve to continue the struggle.German policy being dominated by military considerations, quotations from the authority (von Clausewitz) who has inspired German military thought are given in an Appendix to this Report. In the light of these quotations, it is interesting to study the German manoeuvres to bring about a victorious peace.The Freedom of the Sean.-- As President Wilsoh&apos;s reference to the freedom of the seas, referred to in last week&apos;s Report, is likely to bring about further allusions to this subject in peace discussions, a paper on this question, as affecting the British Empire, is appended to Part I. ,German Internal Affairs.The opinion of an eminent authority on economics that only military success against the German armies can avail to lower the prestige of the military caste is worthy of notice,Influence of Propaganda.The news received during the week gives an indication of the influence so far gained by propaganda which is intended to substitute a war of classes for a war of nations, and so to shake the resolve of ourselves and our Allies to continue the struggle. This subject is engaging the attention of the War Cabinet.January 24th, .1918.G-. G. A.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War CabinetSECRET. For Reference only.WESTERN   AND   GENERAL   REPORT.No. 52.    Week ending 23rd January 1918 (night).PART ii. FOREIGN AND GENERAL. Contents.Allied Affairs.Far East: Russian altitude, and policies of Great Britain, Japan, and United States. France.Caillaux case.   Criticism of Great Britain. Belgium1.German manipulation of Flemish nationalism; Italy.Enemy aliens.   Import of oats. Portugal;Causes of revolution.   Co-operation in East Africa. Enemy Allied Affairs.Austria : Reported resignation of Prime Minister ; postponement of Parliament; severity of censor-ship ;  friction   with Germany;   commercial relations with  Germany;   military irregularities. Hungary : Reconstruction of Cabinet ; policy. . German Internal Affairs.Resignations from Civil Cabinet. &quot;Compromise between Civil and Military.   Views of Dr. Dernburg. Popular dissensions:    Explosions and hoods.    Prices.   Traffic.   Morals.   Necessity of military defeat. Holland.Sand and gravel.    Export of horses. Switzerland.Allies and Swiss exports.   Sir H. RumbohVs views on import restrictions. Norway.Activity in commerce and shipbuilding.   Dislike and fear of Germany. Sweden.King&apos;s speech.   Harvest.   Export of horses.   Fear of Germany.   Peace rumours. Denmark.Active and passive pro-Germanism. Finland.Recognition.   Indian Nationalist propaganda.    Bolshevism.   Relations with Scandinavia.   Aland Islands.   Neutrality.Spain.Internal difficulties and German propaganda. China.Netherlands Legation and - Germaiyfunds.   Enemy aliens. Argentina.Wheat Convention.    German plots. Colombia.- Unrest and German intrigue. British Honduras.Reported German plot. Mexico.Carranza and Pelaez.   United States policy.   Mexican Mission to Japan. Cuba.Obligatory service and foreigners.   President and railways. United States.Attitude of Jews.    Drastic Fuel Order.   Dissensions over War Cabinet Bill.   Anxiety about Irish Convention. Shipping Situation.Sinkings.    Anglo-American proposals in regard to Danish tonnage.   Germany and Swedish tonnage. United States and Greek supplies.   Coolie imports.   Problem of cei*eal imports.   Coal supply to Italy.   Enemy sailings. Peace Discussions.(Classified in the text.) General.Hospital ships : Spanish refutation of German allegations.    Enemy families in Britain and British in. Belgium.   Bread for prisoners interned in Holland.Appendix : The Basis of German Policy.(33)4701-46   Pk        100   1/18   K &amp; S A
part ii.-foreign affairs.AT. LIE! * A I:&apos;FA IRS.Far Fast. Sir (j. Greene reports the Japanese Foreign Office as declaring the readiness of Japan to undertake protection of Allied interests at Vladivostock. and on behalf of the Allied powers to oppose enemy activities along the Siberian railway, should such intervention become imperative. For her own protection she is prepared to go as far as Irkutsk. Intervention either by America or Great Britain, especially the former, is deprecated.Mr. Bindley and the Japanese Ambassador in Petrograd have received notes from the Bolshevist Assistant Commissary for Foreign Affairs demanding explanations of the arrival of warships at Vladivostock without notification. The Commissaries are taking up the question seriously and. are sending a representative to Vladivostock. The British and. Japanese representatives have replied that the ships were sent to Vladivostock to protect the lives and property of the Allies, which appear to be threatened by the prevailing anarch)- and by the presence of large numbers of enemy prisoners in Eastern Siberia. Sir 0. Greene learns that the arrival of the Iwami caused resentment and - suspicion, and that the Municipality of Vladivostock protested. to the Japanese Consul-General that such arrival without notice infringed the sovereign rights of Russia and was injurious to the Russo-Japanese treaty. On the other hand, H.M.S. Suffolk was well received, and her presence is regarded as a guarantee against- aggression by Japan. The Asahi and a store ship have now arrived. 1Jis Majesty&apos;s Consul at Vladivostock is of opinion that the internal situation is quiet and that any demonstration of force is undesirable. Sir 0. Greene learns from, a British officer &quot;who has arrived, in Japan via Korea that the casualties at Irkutsk have been greatly exaggerated. The better classes, however, throughout Russia and Manchuria are in favour of Allied intervention, or even intervention by Japan, alone, rather than none. The Japanese Foreign Minister has informed Sir G. Greene that a Bolshevist agent (aged 23) has recently arrived in Tokyo, but has not yet claimed, and would in no case receive, official recognition. Sir 0, Spring Rice reports that while the United States Govern-ment is adverse to Japanese intervention at Viadivostock, it appreciates the impos-sibility in the last resort, of disregarding geographical rights and duties such as the United States itself would assert, iE necessary, in the case of Mexico. Such assertion, however, should not extend to permanent occupation or preferential claims by the power in question, but should conform to military necessity alone. The Foreign Office on January 16th communicated to Sir 0. Greene, for the information of the Japanese Government, the basis of British policy in Siberia and in South-East Russia.&apos; It is recognised that it may be necessary for the Allies at some future time to take action in support of those in Siberia who maintain the Allied cause; and in such a case the British Government will communicate with the Japanese, of whose co-operation in the interest of the Allied cause it is assured.FRANCE.Cadlaux Case. Lord Bertie reports the arrest of MM. Loustalot and Comby on January 16th upon fresh information received from America regarding their journey to Switzerland. In reply to a Socialist objection that Caillaux&apos;s safe at Florence was illegally opened, it was answered that the Italian authorities had complied with Italian law, and that in any case the French Government could not have been held responsible. Humanite attributes the American discoveries to Lord Northcliffe, and remarks : &quot; The Roman Imperialism of Spnnino joins internationally, across the &quot; Channel, with the Mercantile imperialism of Lord Northcliffe.    European reaction
&quot; is in movement.&quot; The Intelligence Bureau points out that the evidence from America appears to show that while in the Argentine Caillaux intrigued with Count Luxburg, the German Minister, and attacked both England and the Government of France, while the Florence safe is said to have disclosed a plot to seize power in France. The documents in each case would seem, as impartial witnesses, to be an important corroboration of allegations which in many quarters were regarded as due to prejudice. The position of M. Clemenceau has certainly been strengthened by these discoveries. . It may be observed also that there is a gradually progressing split in the old Radical and Radical-Socialist Party which Caillaux used to lead.Criticism of Great Britain. Libellous statements in regard to Great Britain&apos;s contribution towards the war are still to be noticed here and there, and it is to be wished that an authoritative refutation could be given by the French Authorities.BELGIUM.Germany and Flanders. The German Wireless Press reports that on January 15th the &apos;&quot;&apos; Council of Flanders&quot; was received at Brussels I) y Dr. Wallraf, the German State Secretary for the Interior, to whom it presented an address of which the following is an extract: &quot;Siqmorted by the expressed will of the German Kaiser &quot; that Flanders must be assured of free development, and supported by the proved &quot; efficacy of the separated administration ; supported also by the inflexible will of the &quot; Flemish nation not again to bend its national existence under the Walloon yoke, &quot; the Council waits hopefully for the hour which is to bring to the Flemish nation &quot; the development oE its independence, and to the Council itself the strengthening of &quot; its position.&quot;ITALY.Enemy Aliens. In a despatch dated January 5th, Sir R. Rodd reports that Poles, Czecs and Slovaks, for whom guarantees are forthcoming, as well as Italians of the irredente provinces, are being exempted from the measures taken against enemy aliens in Italy.Oats. In view of the special requirements of Italy, His -Majesty&apos;s Government is considering the desirability of diverting to that country a portion of the imports of oats originally destined for the United Kingdom. It is proposed that similar action should be recommended to the French Government.PORTUGAL.Y-ieics on Revolution. In a despatch dated December 17th, Sir Lancelot Carnegie reports that, judging from the attitude of the Provinces, it appears fairly certain that the movement has been approved by all except the Democratic Party and their partisans. The Monarchists appear to be puzzled as to what course to pursue, but they certainly rejoice at the overthrow of Dr. Costa. There is no doubt that the country Avas heartily sick of the late Government and of their leader. The harsh and illogical censorship of the Press and the drastic mode of dealing with the grievances of the clergy, educational institutions, and postal employes, coupled with persistent rumours of gross corruption, all combined to increase the number of its enemies. On the other hand, the late Government must be credited with the loyal performance of its obligations under the Alliance with Great Britain.Co-operation with British Navy. On the request of His Majesty&apos;s Government the Portuguese Government has instructed the local authorities at Port Amelia (East Africa) that full liberty of action should be given to His Majesty&apos;s ships operating oh the coast.
ENEMY ALLIED AFFAIRS.Reported resignation of Prime Minister. - Sir W. Townley reports an announcement, in the Dutch Press that the -Austrian Prime Minister, von Seicller, has resigned, arid that Count von Toggenheim has been charged with the formation of a new Cabinet.. The Vienna Correspondent Bureau denies this rumour.Austrian Parliament. Sir VV. Townley reports that according to a Berlin-telegram official circles are making efforts to postpone the opening of Parliament in Vienna, fixed for January 31st, as they fear the excitement which would be provoked by a discussion of recent events, and especially of the questions of food supply and. the Brest-Litovsk negotiations.Censorship. Sir W. Townley learns on reliable authority that no Austrian papers-appeared on January 20th except the Arbeiter Zeitung, which was allowed to publish one sheet calling upon the people to remain quiet.Austria and Germany. - Sir W. Townley reports that feeling between the Central Empires is shown by the German and Austrian press to have become acute. The Vienna Fremdenblatt (of January 17th), the semi-official organ of the Austrian Foreign Office, declares that the two Empires are now joined like Siamese twins, and that. Austria-Hungary has therefore an interest in the person chosen as joint negotiator for peace. She is therefore disturbed by the rumour that Prince Bulow is intriguing to replace Kuhlmann. The former is distrusted owing to his Italian policy, whereas Kuhlmann enjoys the complete confidence of Austria. A. considerable-section of the German press takes this opportunity to release its pent-up animosity towards Austria in a number of bitter articles, and roundly resents such interference in German affairs by a country which &quot;simply owes her existence to Germany.&quot; The German press endeavours to attribute the numerous riots and strikes now taking place in Austria as being solely due to a reduction in the flour ration, but reports indicate that the real cause of trouble is political discontent and anxiety for peace. On January 17th Count Czernin declared to a representative of the Vienna Imperial Telegraph Correspondence Bureau that he-would answer and go bail for the fact that peace on the Austrian side would not fail through any intention of conquest. This declaration would, in the opinion of vorwarts, seem to amount to a withdrawal of the &quot; Austro-Polish solution.&quot;Commercial Relations with Germany. Sir W. Townley reports that at a plenary meeting of the German Austro-Hungarian Commercial Union the impression was expressed that in commercial negotiations with Russia future relations with Austria should obtain, clue consideration, and that the most favoured nation clauses to be negotiated with Russia should not prejudicially affect the special Customs relations to be established between Germany and Austria-Hungary. Since, in the political and commercial negotiations with Russia new questions had arisen in connection with future commercial relations with Poland, the plenary meeting decided to determine anew its attitude towards the creation of a new Customs union with Germany. In any case it demanded to bo kept informed of all political and commercial negotiations between neighbouring monarchies and Russia in order that it might consider them and have opportunities of collaborating therein.Military Irregularities. The Austro-Hungarian Military Attache at the Hague, in a letter to the Dutch press, denies reports of cruelties to the Slav populations at the beginning of the war, but is sorry to say that there have been &quot;irregularities.&quot;Hungary.-The Kblnische Zeitung of January 17th published a Wolff telegram from Budapest, announcing that the members of Wekerle&apos;s Cabinet would offer their resignations and Wekerle would be charged with the reconstruction of a new one.Sir W. Townley learns that a Wekerie-Tisza coalition&apos; is aiming at support of. Germany as against Austria in regard to economi c union.
GERMAN INTERNAL AFFAIRS.Resignations. The German. Wireless Press announces the resignation of von. rVaientinij Chief of the Imperial Civil Cabinet, and the appointment of von Berg, First President of East Prussia, as his successor.   A. Berlin telegram to The Hague states that farther resignations in the same Department will follow.Policy. - Sir H. Rumbold learns that Generals Hindenburg and Ludendorff are now united in determination to press on the war with a view to unlimited annexations and a German peace. On the other hand, the Social Democrats and Forfcschrittliche Volkspartei are prepared to accept the proposals of Mr. Lloyd George and President Wilson as the basis of a reasonable peace. Kuhlmann steers a middle course, but is (like czernin) embittered by the belief that General HoffmamPs blunt speech at Brest-Litovsk was an insult aimed at himself by Ludendorff. It is now, however, agreed that tlie civilians (IIerthing and Ivuhlmann) are to have a free hand in the West, while large &quot;concessions&quot; are made to Hindenburg and Ludendorff in the East. The Foreign Office learns that the German General Staff is insisting on annexation up to the Narew line. The Centre Party will support Hertling at all costs. The question of&apos;Alsace Lorraine will be treated as a pure matter of bargain, and the German. Government will not concern itself with regulations of the Austro-Italian frontier.Views of Dr. Dernburg. Sir W. Townley reports that in a speech delivered at Frankfort-on-Main, Dr. Dernburg, formerly German Colouial Minister, bitterly attacked the &quot; war-prolonging agitation of the Fatherland Party,&quot; and ridiculed the pan-German, demands for annexation and indemnities. In regard to the demand of the annexationists that the French mineral producing region of Briey and Longwy should be retained by Germany, he said that the district had probably a value of .150 million pounds, that is, the cost of the war for 25 days. Though, a great believer in colonies, he admitted that colonial gains scarcely came into serious consideration as compensation for war costs. The great capital outlay required from Germany by her colonies before the war brought in a yearly profit of only five million pounds, that is, the cost of war for one day from six in the morning to eight at night. By annexations in the East, Germany would create a hostile Russia which would be a permanent danger. He insisted on the urgent need for disarmament, showing that armaments are now so expensive that the aerial weapon alone at the present day swallows up as much money as did the whole army budget before the war.Dissensions. The Intelligence Bureau, alludes to the unprecedented scenes at meetings of the Fatherland Party, where anti-annexationist ex-soldiers were insidted and beaten. As a consequence many have returned their Iron Crosses to the Central Committee of the Fatherland Party. Further discontent will be caused among the workers in large munition and industrial establishments by the promised impartial enforcement of food distribution. It appears that these establishments have been buying food wholesale from the producers, to the detriment of the food supply of the poorer classes. The workmen who find this privilege removed will probably go over to the Minority Socialist Party: Sir H. Rumbold learns that the negotiations with Russia have caused a remarkable change in the German middle classes, which unanimously declare against any concession being made to the Russians. This is because they dare not make any peace which cannot be represented as a victory. Unless this legend of a German victory can be maintained there will be no heart in the projected Western, offensive. The attitude of the men towards their officers is already very hostile. Moderate men of all parties regard Hindenburg as the one bulwark against revolution. This state of affairs may easily drive the Majority Socialists into open defiance and thus pave the way to revolution. Sir W. Townley reports that on January 20th, 14- mass meetings took place in Cologne, of which the principal theme Avas peace.The Frankfurter Zeitung of January 15th has, a bitter article against the pan-Germans, whom it blames for creating the general impression abroad of Germany&apos;s aggressive intentions. The article concludes, &quot; The German people do &quot; not yet know the extent of the damage done to them by the pan-Germans, but the &quot; hour of reckoning for them is coming.&quot;-J701-4b B
Sir W. Townley reports that Bavaria is sending a representative to Brest-Litovsk,.. and that the German press is much excited over this, as tending to suggest antagonism between the South German States and Prussia, and. also to insinuate that the Kaiser and Chancellor are considered incapable of representing Germany&apos;s interests as a whole.For relations with Austria, see under &quot; Enemy Allied Affairs.&quot;Explosions. Mr. Midler points out (November Report) that by the destruction of the Griesheim factory, Germain&apos; has for the moment been deprived of one-sixth of her capacity of producing high explosives and of a still larger proportion of synthetic-nitrates.The Kolnisclie Zeitung of January 18th publishes news of an unexplained explosion at the &quot; Allgemeine Electricitaets Gesellschaft &quot; Factory in Brunnerstrasse,. Berlin.Floods. The same paper reports serious floods in Germany, causing in one instance the loss of a train in a river and in another the destruction of a factory containing 15,000 cwt. of jam and a large quantity of fat.Prices. Information received by the Minister of Blockade goes to show that conditions in Germany are appalling in comparison with those obtaining in this country. For example, butter, where surreptitiously obtainable, costs 27s. per lb. Beef is rationed at the rate of i-lb. per week, but very few people can obtain it. Milk is only supplied to invalids with a doctors certificate or receipt, and even then it is almost unobtainable. Leather boots are non-existent: the tops of boots are made from soldiers&apos; old uniforms and the soles and heels of wood. A penny reel of sewing yarn costs is. 6d. Tea can be obtained, in very small quantities at 31. per lb.. A twopenny tablet of toilet soap now costs 8s. Beer is reduced, to 1 per cent, alcohol and. is almost uudrinkable.Paralysis of Traffic. Mr. Midler reports for November 1917 that the shortage of coal is at once the result and in a certain measure the cause of the congestion of the railways which is at present paralysing all traffic. A German railway official states-that at the present rate of deterioration, two-thirds of the German locomotives will be worn out by August, and that it will then be quite impossible for Germany to maintain her railway traffic on anything like the present scale.Moral Degeneracy. The problems of future man-power and present food supply are each contributing increasingly to the moral degeneration of the German people ; and semi-official sanction appears to be given alike to polygamy and to municipal hoarding. Corruption, selfishness, and lack of patriotism begin to pervade all classes,, and in the result the masses are becoming exasperated.Necessity of Military Defeat. Mr. Midler point outs, however, that valuable as the blockade is, a real defeat of Germany can only be brought about by the military victory of the Allies, which alone will lower the prestige of the Militarist caste in the eyes of the German people.HOLLAND.Sand, and Gravel. The Foreign Office learns that Dutch sand to the amount of&apos; 3,200 tons per day was exported from the Netherlands via Hanswert from December 29th to January 8th inclusive. Owing to shortage of sand in the country, the Dutch Press has taken up the matter. There is reason to expect a satisfactory solution in the near future of the differences existing between His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment and the Netherlands Government upon the questions of transit and export of sand, and gravel.Export of Horses. Sir W. Townley reports that the Minister of Agriculture has stated in.the Second Chamber that permission is being granted for the exportation of 5,000 fully grown horses, and that j^ermission was given on October 26th for the exportation of 17,000 one and a half year horses, provided it took place soon.
SWITZERLAND.Export Restrictions. Mr. Barclay reports that the United States Minister at Berne has been instructed to press the Swiss Government for severer restrictions upon the exportation of cotton goods to Germany. The United States Government is also 10 participate with the French and British Governments in negotiation for a reduction in the export from Switzerland of cotton and rubber goods.The Foreign Office instructs Sir II. Rumbold to investigate the system of control exercised over the exportation of jaite sacks from Switzerland.Import Restrictions.--Sir .11. Rumbokl deprecates the stoppage of importation into Switzerland of raw and semi-manufactured material, pending the adoption of an unfriendly attitude by the Swiss. Such stoppage would tend to prejudice British exchange, and, by disorganising Swiss industries, give a handle to German propaganda.NORWAY.Prosperity.-The Intelligence Bureau reports the formation during 1917 of new companies with a capital of some 20,000,000Z. sterling, which sum is about double that of 1916 for the same purpose. The capital raised in 1916 was mostly for shipping companies, but the 1917 undertakings are mostly commercial. The increases in the receipts of Norwegian shipowners are fantastic. The official figures, which are probably below the mark, give 11,000,0001 for 1914, 26,0O0,O0OZ. for 1915, and 58,000,0001. sterling for 1916. Shipbuilding of all sorts, even of concrete vessels, is being pushed forward ; contracts for the building of 800,000 tons of shipping have been made in England, and a National Steel Works is about to be started in Narvik, where it is said that Spitzbergen coal will be used.Norway and Germany. So much ill-feeling has been aroused against Germany by the sinking of ships and consequent loss of life, by the discovery of bombs apparently left by Baron Rantenfels, and by acts of espionage and incendiarism, that the &quot; Norwegian Waters Association &quot; has passed a resolution proclaiming a complete boycott of Germany, German trade, German shipping, and German citizens in Norway. It is authoritatively denied that the Scandinavian-American shipping lines will, as has been stated, join the German North Atlantic combine.Meanwhile, according to reports from Sir M. Findlay, the Germans continue to intimidate the Norwegians into refusal of the Allied offers of supply, and are endeavouring at the same time to increase German exports to Norway with the double object of improving exchange and establishing a claim for compensation. Although Germany is in fact unlikely to risk bringing Norway into the war, her threats appear to have considerable effect.SWEDEN.Kinfs Speech. Sir E. Howard reports that at the opening of the Riksdag on January 16th the King, after urging a united front against the hardships caused to Sweden by the war, expressed his determination to maintain neutrality and to continue his efforts in common with other neutral states, especially Norway and Denmark, to prepare for a permanent peace and new international order. At the meeting with the Kings of Norway and Denmark at Christiania, the policy of co-operation had been extended and confirmed. He had gladly recognized the independence of Finland, as soon as circumstances permitted, and hoped she would join Sweden and the rest of Scandinavia in the common work for peace and progress, and that her independence would facilitate a solution of the Aland question satisfactory to Sweden. He had already.y taken steps towards preparing the way for such a solution. Certain military establishments were still necessary to secure the maintenance of neutrality. The reduced production, of the world and the blockade measures of belligerents had increased, the difficulties of import and of commercial relations with foreign countries.
He was making most serious efforts to overcome these difficulties and had concluded certain limited agreements. He was negotiating about the resumption of Swedish commerce on the high seas on terms consistent with neutrality and independence.Harvest. According to the Stockholm Dagblacl, the Swedish harvest is relatively the worst for 50 years, and the hay crop is also very disappointing. On the other hand, there is a record potato crop of 2,279,000 tons, and the crop of fodder roots is above the average.Export of Horses. According to the Swedish Press, however, the National Economy Commission has recommended to the Minister for Agriculture the desirability for increasing the export of horses owing to shortage of fodder.Fear of Germany. The Foreign Office learns that the clanger of German encroachments tipon the Baltic is now being realised in Sweden, even amongst the pro-German upper classes.Peace Humours. -According to the Swedish Press, Petrograd newspapers have reported negotiations as taking place between the Austro-German Delegation and the Swedish Legation in Petrograd, with a view to mediation by Sweden between the Central Powers and the Entente. On January 15th the Svenska Dagblad published a statement by the Swedish Foreign Ministers expressing ignorance and incredulity in the matter.DENMARK.Denmark and Germany. The Intelligence Bureau reports that the Swedish Socialist Press has noticed with strong disapproval a communication made by the Danish Social Democracy to the Dutch Socialist, M. Troelstra, requesting the Netherlands members of the International Socialist Bureau to try to hasten the convo-cation of an International Peace Conference at Stockholm. The initiator of this step was Mr. Stauning, one of the Ministers without portfolio now in the Danish Cabinet ; and the fact that a Cabinet Minister should have a private foreign policy is severely criticised by a prominent Danish newspaper. The Socialist Party in Denmark has throughout the war been notoriously pro-German, and it is probable that some of the leaders are in the pay of international Jew financiers. Possibly Mr. Stauning has in this matter been incited from Berlin. In regard 1o the question of an independent Iceland (see Reports Nos. 50 and 51), the Danish Socialdemokraten suggests that Great Britain has designs to bring that country under her influence. This notion also perhaps originates from Berlin. Sir E. Howard reports that the Germans are at considerable sacrifice supplying the Danish press with paper in order to gain influence. An arrangement for exchange of necessaries (to last for four months) lias been made between Denmark and Germany. Denmark is to be furnished with coal, lubricating oils, iron, steel,&apos; shipbuilding materials, and salt, while Germany is to receive agricultural produce.Sir R. Paget learns that the French. Government is proposing to the Governments of Great Britain, Italy, and the United States that joint representations should be made to the Danish Government in connection with the reproduction in a Danish newspaper of an article in a German paper accusing the French Military Attache of committing acts of espionage and sabotage with the approval of the French Minister. It is believed that the Danish Government will take legal proceedings against the newspaper in question. Sir R. Paget suggests that, in view of the rather unsatisfactory attitude of the Danish Government in permitting Socialist activities to the prejudice of the Allies, it might be desirable to make public the efforts made by the. Allies to meet Danish requirements.FINLAND.Recognition. The Foreign Office learns of the recognition by Austria-Hungary and Switzerland of the independence of Finland. Lord Grairville reports that the Greek Government, learning from Paris that the French Government, &quot; in agreement with
&apos;   %     9 I.:the Allies,&quot; had recognised the Government of Finland, has also given recognition. Sir E. Howard reports that Professor von Wendt and the Finnish ex-Senator Wtiolijiki published on January 18th a declaration of deep and heartfelt disappoint-ment at Great Britain&apos;s non-recognition of Finnish independence, in which it is remarked that the maintenance of this attitude will entirely counterbalance the influence exerted by the action of France. The Finnish Delegates, who have now arrived in London, have informed the authorities in Finland that their reception has been very friendly and sympathetic ; and that the British Government, which has already recognised Finland&apos;s de. facto independence, observes that the continued presence of Russian soldiery in Finland is inconsistent with the Bolshevists&apos; recog-nition, and renders it difficult to recognise Finland&apos;s independence de jure.Indian Nationalist Propaganda. The Foreign Office learns that the Indian National Committee, of 28, Artillery Street, Stockholm, has telegraphed in the name of the National Revolutionary Party of India to the President of the Finnish Senate, congratulating Finland on the attainment of her independence and claiming Finnish sympathy^ for &quot; 315 million Indians who for more than 150 years-have been victims of oppression and exploitation under a selfish foreign rule.&quot;Bolshevism. Sir E. Howard reports that as the result of the Finnish Lancltag&apos;s resolution to authorise the Government to take all necessary measures to establish order, the Council of the Finnish Socialist Party issued a manifesto calling upon the Proletariat to unite against the Government under the leadership of a Delegation representing Socialists and Red Guards. It declares the Red Guards necessary for the protection of the working parties. It seems not improbable that a Bolshevist move-ment may break out in Finland.Relations with Scandinavia. In an interview in Dagens Nyheter of January 12th, Director Nylander, of the Swedish Export Association, advocates a commercial treaty between the Finnish and Swedish Governments, and participation by Finland in a Scandinavian Economic Organisation. He suggests that as Finland has large stocks of sawn timber, it is important that she should join with Sweden and Norway in keeping up prices at the end of the war.Aland Islands. The Dagens Nyheler of January 20th reports a statement by Professor von Wendt, that the refusal of Finland to assent to the request of the Alanders for reunion with Sweden was likely to prejudice Swedo-Finnish relations. He therefore suggested that the Aland Islands should become an independent Republic under Swedo-Finnish suzerainty, with its neutrality internationally guaranteed, and with guarantees against fortifications. This new Republic would have one representative at Stockholm and another at Helsingfors.Neutrality. According to the German Wireless Press, the Berliner Tageblatt reports that the Minister, President Swinhufvucl, speaking in the Finnish Administrative Assembly, announced the firm resolve of the new Finnish State to maintain neutrality.SPAIN.General Difficulties. The Foreign Office learns that a general strike has begun at Malaga in consequence of persons having been killed during a demonstration of women who were demanding cheaper food. Fears are felt that if, as seems likely, the drought of last year results in partial starvation during 1918, there will be grave trouble in Spain: It also appears that the shortage of cotton imports from America is likely to bring about a serious state of affairs in Catalunia. Complaints are also being made that the utilisation of Spanish ships for Spanish purposes is being restricted by the Allies. All these difficulties, together with the movement for soldiers&apos; juntas, will no doubt be exploited by the German propaganda.4-761- 46 C
CHINA.German Funds. Sir J. Jordan reports that enquiries are being made of the Chinese Government by the French Charge d&apos;Affaires and himself as to whether the German Bank at Shanghai, at the time of the rupture between China and Germany, transferred the whole of its assets (taels 7,000,000) to the account of the Netherlands Legation, thus escaping liquidation by the Chinese Government.Enemy Aliens. Sir J. Jordan reports that the Chinese Government still hesitates to order the deportation of enemy subjects, on the grounds, first, of the danger of reprisals, and secondly, that such drastic action has not been taken by the United States Government.   A definite decision will be reached within a few days.ARGENTINA. .Wheat Convention. Sir R. Tower reports that the Wheat Convention passed the Deputies on January 18th and was to be submitted on January 21st to the Senate, whose unanimous acceptance was expected.German Plots. The Foreign Office learns that the Germans are taking active steps at Buenos Ayres to prevent the shipment of foodstuffs to the Allies.COLOMBIA.Unrest and German Intrigue.-Mr. Wyndham reports considerable unrest in Colombia caused by the approaching presidential election and the general financial situation. It is suspected that German influence is promoting disorder against British interests.   A state of siege has been proclaimed.B Li FITS LI HONDURAS.German Intrigue. The Foreign Office has received information of a German scheme for raiding British Honduras.MEXICO.Carranza and Pelaez. Mr. Cummins reports on January 19th that Carranza has returned to Mexico City. Pressure is being steadily exerted from the Forth against Pelaez, who is retiring without much resistance.United States of America and Mexico. Sir C. Spring Rice reports that in the last resort the United States Government would feel itself justified in intervening on grounds of military necessity such as might warrant Japanese intervention at Vladivostock, though in neither case should the geographical advantage give a claim to permanent territorial or commercial preference. Meanwhile it is probable that Mexico is endeavouring to concert with the Argentine Republic against the Entente and the United States. The dependence of both upon the United States for necessary supplies operates, however, to impede any effective action.Mexican Mission to Japan. Mr. Barclay reports that the Mexican Mission to Japan (see Report No. 50) has recently passed through San Francisco. The members stated they were to buy arms and ammunition and to make commercial arrangements.
1125CUBA.Obligatory Service. Mr. Leech learns that the President has assured the Ministers of France and the United States that under the Obligatory Service Bill (see Report No. 50) there is no intention that foreigners shall be compelled to serve.Railways. Mr. Leech reports that the powers asked by the President in respect of railway matters (see Report No. 51) are stated to aim not at the exercise of actual control, but at allowing of financial assistance being rendered to such railways as may need it.UNITED STATES.Jews. Sir C, Spring Rice, in despatches of December 17th and 21st, reports that the United States public is becoming aware of the danger, which threatens them as it has threatened Russia, from German propaganda acting on ignorance. An important element in the situation is that the Bolshevist party is controlled and dominated by the New York Jews, the same class which came out in support of the Socialist candidate Hillquist in the New York election. Jewish feeling general by was not being expressed in a strong and definite sense in favour of the Allied cause, and indeed it appeared to be bitterly opposed to the Zionist leaders themselves. This attitude is remarkable in face of the hospitality, security, and protection afforded to Jews by the American Government, which actual!)- compromised its good relations with the Russian Government by advocating the Jewish cause. On the other hand the subsequent Zionist demonstrations at Baltimore and New York have done much to consolidate Jewdsh pro-Entente elements in America. So far as the American attitude is concerned the process of national unification continues, together with the gradual disappearance of the traditional anti-English feeling.Fuel. Mi-. Barclay reports that under an order of. the Fuel Administrator which went into force at midnight, January 18th-19th, preference in the sale of fuel is to be given in the following order : railways, domestic consumers, camps and hospitals, public concerns such as the telegraph and telephone systems, bankers, factories engaged on strictly governmental purposes (but not factories engaged in Government contracts), State and municipal authorities for public use, and food manufacturers. From January 18th till January 22nd and every following Monday till March 28th fuel may only be consumed by plants which would be injured by ceasing operations, and (to a limited extent) printing establishments. On Mondays from January 2 1st till March 25th fuel is not to be used by any business offices except Government Departments, banks or doctors, nor by any shops except those selling medical supplies or food, nor by places of public amusement. Underground and street surface railways are on these days limited to the amounts consumed on Sundays. Under these regulations the entire industry of the country (including munition factories) east of Mississipi is closed down for five consecutive days and for one day each week for ten weeks. The order was signed in spite of violent and general protests, and in the face of a resolution of the Senate demanding a postponement for five days. The Controller justifies it by the necessity for relieving congestion.Political Dissension. -Mr. Barclay reports that a Bill proposing the creation of a War Cabinet has been introduced by Senator Chamberlain, a Democrat and chairman of Committee on Military Affairs. The objects of the Bill are supported by Mr. Roosevelt, who has arrived in Washington. President Wilson has expressed his determination to defeat the Bill.Irish Convention.  Mr. Barclay learns that feeling in the United States would be gravely affected by failure of the Irish Convention to reach a solution. In the first place nearly all Americans are historically and by sympathy Home Rulers. Secondly, Catholic influence, which is very great in the Navy and Army, and is thoroughly organised in the country, can easily affect, both the political situation and the war spirit, of the nation.
SHIPPING SITUATION.Sinkings. According to the War Trade Intelligence report, the total tonnage of 500 tons gross in the case of steamers and 100 tons gross in the case of sailing ships reported lost owing to the malice of the King&apos;s enemies during the period January 1.1th 17th, 1918, inclusive was 45,018 tons gross, of which 12,676 were British, as compared with .1.00,646 tons gross, of which 76,092 were British, reported last week.German Claims. The German Wireless Press of January 22nd stated that by the military measures of the Central Powers during the month of December 1917 a total of 702,000 gross registered tons of mercantile ship-space at the disposal &quot;of their enemies was destroyed, thereby increasing the successes of unrestricted submarine warfare up to date to 8,958,000 gross registered tons.Danish Tonnage. The War Trade Intelligence Department reports that whereas the Danes wish to retain 150,000 tons of their shipping for Danish service, the United States Government proposes that they should keep only 350,000 tons, plus 50,000 tons engaged in the Anglo-Danish coal trade. Of the remaining 265,000 tons of Danish shipping available, the United States Shipping Board proposes to put 35,000 tons into the Anglo-French coal trade to replace losses by submarines, and to allot 15,000 to the British for general service, retaining 215,000 tons. These amounts, plus 165,000 tons already put into the Anglo-French coal trade, make an aggregate of 430,000 tons of. Danish tonnage available for Allied service, which amount is thus shared equally between Great Britain and the United States, losses to be pooled. Failing a satisfactory settlement within a reasonable time of the points at issue, the United States Government proposes to requisition the 70,000 tons of Danish shipping in American ports.Swedish, Tonnage. Sir E. Howard reports a campaign by the Svenska Dagblad and other papers against the chartering of Swedish tonnage to the Allies. This campaign has attracted the favourable notice of the Milnch.en.er Neueste Nachrichten and the Hamburger Fremdenblad, which play upon Swedish fears accordingly.Greek Supplies. Mr. Barclay reports that the United States Government, while it has every desire to assist the forwarding of supplies to Greece, does not find itself able to allocate tonnage for that purpose.Proposed Cessation of Coolie Imports. The Ministry of Shipping submits a proposal that the vessels now employed in the shipment of coolies should be taken, over for the transport of American troops. It is estimated that if the coolie traffic were entirely stopped, 10,000 additional troops per month (without baggage) might be transported.Cereals.  The Ministry of Shipping reports that the present programmes of the Departments are in excess of estimated carrying power by at least two and a half million tons. This dehcit, aggravated by various unsatisfactory conditions at present existing in America, seriously affects the importation of cereals. It is further pointed out that, to the extent to which French and Italian vessels are inadequate to lift their minimum requirements of cereals, the deficit must be added to the British deficit. In viewr of the arrangement to give general priority to food, provisional orders have, therefore, been issued to make certain reductions in the import of other materials.CoaZ. The Ministry of Shipping reports that by arrangement with the French Government, 150,000 tons of French coal  is to be supplied monthly from the South of France to Italy, to start immediately. Of this quantity, all. but 10,000 tons will go by rail. This represents an immediate relief to British shipping of about 100,000 tons per month. Later on, the French expect to increase the quantity to 350,000 tons per month, and this, when eifecteel, will constitute a saving to British shipping of .250,000 tons per month.Enemy Sailings. The Admiralty reports that nine enemy merchant ships arrived at and ten sailed from Norwegian ports outside the Cattegat during the week ending January 12th. None entered or left Rotterdam, and only four are reported as having left Delfzyl with enemy coal during the week.
PEACE DISCUSSIONS.brest-litovsli. Reports of the conferences at Brest have been received chiefly through German and Russian wireless stations. There have been strong differences of opinion on the Commission for regulating territorial and political questions. Bolshevist, German, and Austro-Hungarian Delegates have taken&apos; part in these discussions. The Germans have continued to adopt the attitude of conquerors, and references have been made to the presence of victorious German troops on Russian soil.Mr. Lindley reports that von -Kuhlmann on January 16th was compelled for the first time to declare openly that the German Government can give no obligation of any kind as to the date when troops will be withdrawn from the occupied provinces.On January 16th Sir R. Paget reported a rumour that the Germans were likely to agree to end their Conference with the Russians, and that a treaty with them would probably be signed at Copenhagen.Mr. Lindley reported on January 19th, a summary of the reply said to be offered by the Germans to the Bolshevist peace proposals. This reply is described as the last possible concession, and the following are its principal points : (1) The Central Powers have no intention of absorbing the occupied territories. They have no intention to force them to admit anjr form of Government, but reserve for themselves and the peoples of those territories liberty to conclude every kind of treaties.(2) The withdrawal of troops is impossible until a general peace. National gendarmerie might be created. Regarding the return of refugees and evacuated persons, each particular case will be examined.(3) Elected representatives of the people should take a great part in the direction of general peace negotiations. The Central Powers agree that the popular will organised on a broad base should give its sanction to the question of allegiance of those provinces. A referendum is considered unnecessary, and it was not taken in Finland or the Ukraine.Peace discussions, as applying particularly to Russia, to the Balkans, and to all States bordering, on the Black Sea, Adriatic, and Eastern Mediterranean, are now being dealt with in the Eastern Report. The following points have been noted in special Reports received from countries still dealt with in the Western Report : Germany. With reference to the outcry against &quot; Imperialism &quot; raised in connection with peace discussions, Sir C. Spring Rice reports that, in President WilsoAs opinion, the Germans are quite unable to understand the difference between British and German ideas of Empire ; especially the^British idea of an association of free nations, acting unitedly on their own free impulse.German wireless, especially on January 10th, endeavours to make the most of all differences of opinion that they can detect in countries of the Entente Alliance about war aims, especially differences in the French and Italian Press about M. Pichon&apos;s recent speech in the French Chamber.Italy. Sir Rennell Rodd reports on January 18th, an interview with the Minister of Foreign Affairs, who advocates the policy of breaking up the Bolshevist influence as affecting peace dismissions lest it should spread to other countries.The Intelligence Bureau reports on January 11th that some of the Italian papers find the reference in the British Prime MinisteFs speech to Italian Avar aims somewhat inadequate.Vatican.  Sir H. Rumbold reports on January 20th that the Vatican was much pleased with Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s and President Wilson&apos;s speeches on Avar aims, which seemed to have caused a considerable change in the attitude adopted by the German Legation. The Papal Agent seemed anxious about the forthcoming reply by the Imperial Chancellor, aviio he thought Avas managed by the Military Authorities ; these -authorities build great hopes in the military position, and are confident in a complete success.The Intelligence Bureau reports on January 11th that Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s speech on War Aims has been very favourably received by the Vatican organ UOsservatore4701-4b D
Romano, which says that it will be beginning of the end, since now it is finally known-what Great Britain wants. It reduces the aims of the Entente to certain points which admit of discussion by the enemy, and it now behoves the Central Powers to reply. Another Vatican paper, the Corriere d&apos;Italia, is still more enthusiastic in its praises. Count de Salis on January 8th wrote in a similar sense.In a despatch dated January 10th Sir E. Podd writes : &quot;The satisfaction of the &quot; clericals has been so strongly expressed that it gives some ground for careful &quot; reflection.&quot;United States.   Sir C. Spring Bice was informed by the Foreign Office on January 5th of rumours having reached the American Embassy that the British and other Allied Governments were discussing, or were ready to discuss, peace with the representatives of enemy Governments.[Similar rumours have appeared from other quarters, widely distributed about the world, during the past week. In view of the probability of their being inspired, from enemy sources, a special Appendix &quot; On the basis of Gierman policy &quot; is added to this Report.]Siccden. In a Report dated December 27th, Sir E. Howard stated that leading Swedish Finns. Were,throwing cold water on the proposal to cede the Aland Islands: to Sweden, and it was improbable that the Swedish Government would, press for such a solution, though later on they might ask for a national guarantee against the-fortification of the Islands.Austria-Hungary. Sir W. Townley reports on January 18th, that the Arbcitcr Zeitung of January 12th has a very useful summary of divergent views as follows : (a) Anti-Annexaticnists:-(1) Opponents  of  all annexation.   (2) Opponents  of austrian annexationists who hope for Western aggrandisement, especially national Liberals and Catholics.(b) Austro-Polish solution (i.e., Poland be converted either into an appanage of austrian Crown, or inheritance of younger son, Courland and Lithuania to-be annexed by Germany after farcical application of principle of self-determination,- based on votes of non-representative bodies of German or German ophile notables).(c) Military solution (i.e., abandonment without disguise, by Germany of principleof self-determination). Annexation by Prussia of such parts of Courland, Lithuania and Poland as may appear militarily desirable (military con-siderations include some economic, such as coal.) without consulting native population.   Surrender of all the rest to Russia to do as she pleases.On January 21st he reported an interesting situation in the Austrian Press,, including rumours that Prince Below is intriguing to get von Kuhlmann out of his post in -order to get it. himself. Bulow does not enjoy the confidence of the Dual Monarchy on account of his formerattitu.de on the Italian question. These statements have given offenco in the German Press, which shows animosity towards Austria at objectionable interference with personal questions in &quot;the German Empire. The feeling in Austria is said to be running extremely high, the reduction of the flour-ration causing riots and strikes in German and Lower Austria. According to the Vorwartz of January 20th, public opinion in Austria, even in the German portion, is against the open or secret aunexationist basis of German policy.. Sir H. Rumbold reported on- January 20th, on the authority of the Papal Agent, that Austria is ready to come to an agreement with Italy about the Trentino, but. would not surrender Trieste.On January 22nd Sir W. Townley reported a rumour that Count Czeruin would soon offer new peace proposals based on the lines of President Wilson&apos;s speech, which, has  been favourably received in Vienna, but  the Austrian interpretation of the principle of &quot; no annexations &quot; will be maintained.France. Lord. Bertie reports on January 21st that the Minority members of the-Socialists at the Council of the Seine have been attacking M. Thomas for his attitude-in England towards war aims, and have charged him with misrepresenting Socialists&apos; views, and thoughtlessly pledging the whole party.   M. Thomas, in reply, defended himself against the reproach of Imperialism, and adhered to the view he had already expressed, that Alsace-Lorraine must be returned to France.
GENERAL.Hospital Ships. With reference to allegation made in the Cologne Volhszeitung, and published by the German Wireless Press, to the effect that Spanish officers delegated for inspection and control of British hospital ships had in certain instances protested against the improper use of such ships, Sir A. Hardinge reports that the Spanish Prime Minister has no knowledge of any such-protests. He has offered to make a public declaration that the allegation is entirely without foundation, and has already advised the Spanish Ambassador in Berlin accordingly.- Families of Enemy Civilians. The Foreign Office is considering a procedure under which the transport of German civilians&apos;wives and families, to Holland for internment might be made conditional upon the release of British women and children from Belgium. .Bread for Prisoners interned in Holland. Sir W. Townley reports that the Netherlands-Government proposes to supply to interned British prisoners bread of the same consistency and quality as the current ration allows, subject to the replace-ment at the end of each month of an equivalent amount of grain from the United Kingdom.The Intelligence Bureau report on January 17th that in the debate in the Chamber on Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s speech M. Thomas pressed for a new joint statement of the Avar aims of the Allies. M. Pichoii replied that he had proposed that course to the-Allies, who had preferred to make separate statements. M. Thomas demanded that France should press the Allies further on this subject, which demand has been widely supported in the French Press.
appendix to&quot;Western and General Report No. 52.  Part IT.THE BASIS  OF GERMAN POLICY.On account of the continued complete predominance of the military authorities over German policy, it is thought that the following quotations merit consideration, because the-mentai attitude of the Great General Staff at Berlin has been permeated for many years by the opinions of their author, von Clansewitz.The adoption of the principles set forth in the first two quotations resulted logically in the violation of Belgian neutrality, and the horrible cruelties perpetrated upon the Belgian civil population. The U-boat and other&apos; outrages may be traced to the same influence. The third quotation throws a light upon the present German endeavours, direct and indirect, to bring about a peace based upon victory of the Central Powers,&apos; and it may be found valuable as an interpretation oi their policy : i.  The &apos;: Scrap of Paper &quot; Policy.&quot;Self-imposed restrictions, almost imperceptible and hardly worth mentioning, termed usages of international law.&quot;ii. The German Conduct of Warfare:&quot; War is an act of violence which in its application knows no bounds.&quot; Compare : &quot; What is permissible includes every means of war without which the object of the war cannot be obtained.&quot; (German War Book.)III. --The German Peace Offensive (1910-18).&quot; If a preponderance on the side of the attack, although daily diminishing, is still maintained until Peace is concluded, the object is attained. There are strategic attacks which have led to an immediate peace but such instances are rare ; the majority, on the contrary, lead only to a point at which the forces remaining are just sufficient to maintain a defensive, and to wait for peace. Beyond that point the scale turns, there %s a reaction ; the violence of such a -reaction is commonly much greaterthan the force of the blow.....To overstep this point is more than simply auseless expenditure of power, yielding no further result, it is a destructive step which causes reaction ; and this reaction is. according to all general experience, productive of the most disproportionate effects .... The greatest danger of a reverse is often just at the moment when the offensive ceases and passes into the defensive.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
