<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/148/0 images: 95-112</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION OE THE ATTACHED WESTERN AND GENERALREPORT No.  55.part ii. foreign aid general.Peace Discussions.General. The&quot; most interesting features of the situation this Aveek are (1) the conclusion of peace with the Ukraine representatives at Brest by Germany, Austria-Hungary, Turkey and Bulgaria, (2) the attitude of Rumania (of great importance for transport of goods between the Ukraine and tire Central Powers), and the reports of concessions in Bessarabia offered to her to make peace, and (3) the ending of a state of Avar between Russia and the Central Power Alliance. It is too early as yet to appreciate the result which these events are likely to have upon the military situation. While a, demobilisation has been decreed by the Bolshevists in Russia, arrangements have been made for young soldiers to guard the frontier. There are indications that the Bolshevists are making renewed efforts to raise revolutions in enemy countries, and it is interesting to note that, in the wireless propaganda, purporting to emanate from Russian workmen, British workmen are sometimes bracketed with those of Germany and Austria-Hungary in the appeal. The inter-allied Socialist Conference in Paris on may DOth should help to clear up the situation.Meanwhile the Germans are pursuing their policy of pressing for extension of their economic influence over all territories that the)7 can bring under their domination by military conquest or by diplomacy. The report from Holland of the supply of German ploughs to the Ukraine is of interest in this connection. The KaiseFs pronouncements are increasing in. truculenee, interspersed with what reads to us as blasphemy, and, should the Reichstag be allowed to assemble, it will bo increasingly difficult for the Government speakers to avoid confessing the purely aggressive aims for which the Avar was begun, and for which it is still being fought by Germany. The confidence of the Kaiser and his military advisers, who still maintain their dominance over the national policy, appears to be based, upon the prospect of a decisive military success on the Western Front. Failure to obtain a success in the immediate future will undoubtedly have a. far-reaching effect upon the internal situation, in enemy countries. Information before the War Cabinet points to the improbability of such success being gained.Official reports of President Wilson&apos;s latest speech on Avar aims have not yet been received, but a full account has appeared in. the Press. It is proposed to deal with this subject in an. Appendix to next week&apos;s Report, especially in. so far as it.affords a reply to Count Czernihs overtures to America, and to the prospects of detaching AustriaTduugary from her subservience to German aggressive policy.Netherlands.Difficulties with this country about the transit of sand and gravel and the cable embargo appear to be in the course of: settlement.February 14th, 1918. G. G. A.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s government^jPrinted for the War Cabinet. AQSECRET. For Reference only.WESTERN   AND   GENERAL   REPORT.No. 55.   Weeh ending Volii February 191S (night).PARrL If-FOREIGN AND GENERAL. Contexts.Allied Affairs.Allied Socialist Conference.   Far East.   Allied Military Committee:  new Italian representative. American grain supply to Allies.    Daylight saving in France. France.Gases of Caillaux, Malyy, and Bold.   Food conditions.   Desire for economic offensive. -Belgium,Preferential food distribution, by Germans. Italy.Italo-Slav Entente.   War loan.   Arrest of Socialist official. Portugal.Portuguese Minister to Bondon. Enemy Allied&apos; affair rs.Count Czcrnin&apos;s visit to Berlin)   Austrian Government : the Estimates ; popular demands.  Possi-bility of supplies from Russia.    Effects of coal shortage.    Hungarian Government : pro-Gorman leanings.   Hungarian Army. German Internal Affairs.The strikes:   suggested motive ;,  Austrian view; continued claims for free speech ; arrest of editor of Vorwarts ; effect on parties ; Federal States and Prussia, ; general reliance on military offensive. Supplies: encouragement by British Press; doubts of adequate supply from Russia ; trade with Russia. Netherlands.Withdrawal of cable embargo.   Export of horses to Germany. Switzerland.Military concentrations near German frontier.    Gorman coal and Swiss cement exports.    Grain supplies.   Allies and Swiss cotton exports. Norway.Norwegian reply to United States proposals. ySweden.Sweden and the Baltic.    Aland Islands : Sweden and Germany.    Allied propaganda. Denmark.Exports to Germany. Finland.Great Britain and recognition.   Sweden and intervention.   Progress of fighting. Spain.Wheat supply and submarines.   Internal position.   Torpedoed ships.    Provisional Spanish-American agreement.China.Plague.   Japan and wireless stations in China.   Proposed liquidation of enemy property.   Exports to Russia. Argentine Republic.Railway strike : effect on wheat supply.   Northern neutrals and wheat purchase. Brazil.Censorship. Bolivia.Allies and enemy tin mines. Honduras.United States and German trade. Mexico.Banger to oilfields.   Chapultepec wireless station. United States.Arrival of Lord Reading.   War administration : Bill by President Wilson. Shipping Situation.Sinkings.   Comparison of half-yearly losses of world&apos;s tonnage.   Convoys:  percentage of losses. Allied coal distribution.   Effect of labour troubles on shipbuilding.   Tonnage for bunkering stocks abroad.   Brewing and tonnage.   Risks to Norwegian ships.   Negotiations to secure enemy ships in Uruguay and Chile. Peace Discussions ^classified in text).General.Exchange and transfer of combatants : German delays.   Germany and merchant seamen.   Appeal by International Bed Cross against use of poison gas.(33)4985-26   Pk       100   2/18   IS &amp; SA
PART XL-FOREIGN AFFAIRS.ALLIED AFFAIRS.Allied Socialist Conference. The Foreign Office advises Sir R. Rodd that the British. Labour Partyds making arrangements for an Allied Socialist-Conference to he held in London on February 20th for the discussion of war aims. Representatives are being sent on February 15th to Paris to hold, a preliminary meeting with French and Italian Delegates, and for this purpose passports are being granted by His Majesty&apos;s Government.Far East. The Foreign Office learns that the principle of sole intervention by Japan as mandatory of the Allies in the Far East (see Report No. 53), while accepted by the French Government, is criticised by the Italian Government, which is of opinion that participation by the United States and representation by the Allies would be preferable from the point of view both of prestige and of the full effectuation of a general scheme. Sir J. Jordan reports that German influence is spreading in Siberia, and that German agents are buying up large stocks of hides and other goods. The Japanese Foreign Minister has expressed anxiety at the eastward advance of Bolshevist influence, and it appears that the Japanese Government would desire to arrest the Bolshevist and pro-German wave by occupying the junction of the Vlaclivostock. and Amur Railways. Reports from Sir C. Greene and Sir J. Jordan remark, upon the suspicious behaviour of certain Danish and Swedish officials in China and Siberia.Allied Military Committee. -Sir R. Rodd reports that the Italian. Government has recalled General Cadorna from Versailles in. connection with the military enquiry now proceeding, and that General Giardino, late Minister of War, has been appointed as Italian representative on the permanent Allied Military Committee.American Grain Supply to Allies.&apos; Mr. Barclay reports that as the result of a joint telegram from the Premiers of Great Britain, France, and Italy to President Wilson, heroic measures are being taken to free the United States railways for the supply of grain for the Allies. There is now a prospect that the inter-allied programme for February and March may be fulfilled.Daylight Saving. Lord Bertie reports the decision of the French. Government to fix summer time from Sunday, March 10th, to Sunday, October 1st, and transmits the request that His Majesty&apos;s Government will meet this arrangement so far as it affects military and naval co-operation.FRANCE.Caillaax Case. The Intelligence Bureau points out that Caillaux&apos;s defence substantially consists, not in a denial of the authenticity of the documents discovered, but in a justification of the policy they disclose. The document entitled &quot; Rubicon &quot; describes a plan for limiting the powers, both of the Senate and the Chamber in favour of a new &quot; Council of State.&quot; General Sarrail was to command the Army, and there was to be a new Ministry of Police for all France with &quot; a safe man of the type of Ceccaldi (a great friend of Caillaux) at its head.&quot; It is said also, that relations with the Vatican were to be resumed and the Orleans princes recalled. &quot; Rubicon &quot; was the name written on the document handed by Louis Napoleon to Mor$y before the coup d&apos;etat of December 2nd, .1851, and it would appear that the new stroke, like the old, would have been turned by a hero of the Extreme Left to the profit of the Right. It is noticeable that not only is the Army officers and men alike hostile to Caillaux, but the Socialists also are inclined to draw away from him.Malay. The Senate has begun, and then adjourned, the trial of Malvy.Bolo. The trial, of Bolo is proceeding.
Food. The Intelligence Bureau notes that bread cards were introduced in Paris ton January 29th, limiting each consumer to 300 grammes, which it is honed to raise by March 15th to 350 grammes.    The French Press admits the easiness of. food con-ditions in France as compared with those obtaining in England, and&apos;recognises the sacrifices made by her Allies in this respect.Economic Offensive. The Intelligence Bureau observes that certain newspapers are laying much stress upon the necessity of an economic offensive by the Allies  &quot; the only kind of offensive which, at this moment, can promise a decisive result.&quot;BELGIUM.    .Germans and Food Distribution. The Foreign Office learns that the German Authorities in Belgium have for some time followed a policy of preferential distribution of native foodstuffs to Belgians working in German interests. Lord Bertie and Mr. Barclay ane instructed to request the French and American Governments to support His Majesty&apos;s Government in protesting against such action &quot;and in advising the Dutch and Spanish Ministers that, unless it is abandoned, no foodstuffs will be sanctioned for importation into Belgium without an undertaking that the relief organisations will be permitted to control and distribute equivalent native supplies.ITALY.Jialo-Slav Entente. The Intelligence Bureau notices that the movement towards an entente eorcllale between Italy and the Slav and other subject races of Austria appears to be gaining ground. It is supported not only by the Liberal Corrlere delta Sera and the Radical Secolo, but further by the Gazzetta del Popolo of Turin (Liberal), the ex-Giolittian Trlbuna, and the usually Chauvinistic and Clerical Mattinooi Naples, while even L&apos;tdea Nazlonale, the most extreme champion of Italian pretensions in all fields, and hitherto the bitter enemy of the Jugoslav Committee, shows signs of relaxing its hostility. On the Slav side La Serble, the organ of the Jugoslav Committee, warmly welcomes the Italian movement, while Dr. Trumbitch, President of the Jugoslav Committee, has addressed a letter to the Secolo in the same sense.War Loan. The Intelligence Bureau reports that, in the last week of January Signor Nitti delivered at Milan a forcible address in promotion of the new War Loan, naming six milliards (about 240,000,000L) as the amount required. He spoke very warmly of the services rendered to Italy by Great Britain.Socialism. The Intelligence Bureau reports that the Secretary of the Official Socialist. Party has been arrested and imprisoned, having been denounced on various counts, one of which is that of organising a general strike.^   PORTUGAL.Portuguese Minister to London. Sir L. Carnegie has informed the Portuguese President that His Majesty&apos;s Government has approved the appointment of Senhor Vasconcellos as Minister in London, on the understanding that he should not present credentials to the King until formal recognition has been accorded to the new Government.ENEMY ALLIED A.FFA.IRS.Count Czerniiis Visit to Berlin. The Berliner Tageblatt of February 7th announces that, on the occasion of his recent visit to Berlin, Count Czernin reached complete accord with leading German circles on all current political and economic questions, especially that of food supply^Austrian Government. -Sir W. Townley reported on February 9th that the Austrian Government had tendered its resignation on the ground, that factions of the
German party had refused to vote the estimates, but that the Emperor had declined&apos; to accept it. The Vienna correspondent of the Nieuwe Rotterdarnsche Centrant states--that efforts are being made to secure a majority for the estimates by effecting a reconciliation between, the Poles and the Government. The cordial tone of the-emperor&apos;s letter to.Doctor Sefdler is taken as proof of his approval of the Prime Ministers attitude during the strikes. The Kolnisehe V olhszeitung of February 7th speaks of a &quot; democratic breeze &quot; blowing from the Vienna Court ; and on February 11th the Intelligence Bureau reports : &quot; It is quite clear that Count Czernin is making a. &quot; desperate bid for the popularity of the working classes in Austria-Hungary, and &quot; that he realises that the only hope of internal peace is to press for external peace.&quot;Supplies from Russia. Mr. Muller reports (on January 26th) that though it is highly improbable that the exaggerated Austrian expectations of imports from Russia will be realised., it is at the same time possible that the efficacy of the Allied blockade may be seriously affected should Austria-Hungary obtain access via the Danube to the-ports and granaries of Southern Russia.Coal. Mr. Muller reports (on January 26th) that coal shortage is having disastrous effects in Austria and Hungary upon heating, cooking, lighting, and industry of all kinds.Hungarian Government, The Intelligence Bureau observes that the inclusion in Dr. Wekerle&apos;s new Cabinet of Dr. Alexander Popovics, as Minister of Finance, and Mr. Szte^enyi, as Minister of Commerce, is a clear sign that the governing class in Hungary is rallying in support of the German alliance.Hungarian Army. Mr. Muller reports (on January 20th) that the rejection by the Austrian Emperor of the proposal of the Hungarian Government for a separate Hungarian Army has caused disappointment and fury in Hungary.GERMAN  INTERNAL  AFFAIRS.Comments on Strikes. The Swedish Socialist paper Arhetetstates that, according to a Swede who returned from Berlin at the end of January, the object of the strike was to prevent an offensive, on the Western Front, as the working classes refused to allow a fresh massacre. The Vienna Arbeiter Zeitung of 5th February comments in a leading article on the fact that the German strike fizzled out without its leaders having extracted a single concession from the Government and. without having wrung from them a definite pronouncement of war aims. The paper considers this &quot; the result of sham German democracy and of the poverty and, antiquated character of German political thought.&quot; On the other hand, Sir H. Rum bold reports on the same date a well-informed opinion to the effect that a revolution was now possible in Germany and that the Socialist leaders had lost control. This is to some extent corroborated by Mr. Lindley, who learns that the Germans, through fear of revolutionary infection, have not been allowing Austrian prisoners to leave Russia through, the German lines. The inutterings of democracy are certainly somewhat insistent&quot;. In an. article dated February 5th, Voricarts blames Count Hertling for regarding the strike as a criminal outbreak rather than a political manifestation. He should not he content to have suppressed it, but should consider its causes and. remedies. By yielding to the promptings of the reactionary Press he would only strengthen and increase the causes which provoked the late happenings; with the breaking out of these, social democracy was not concerned. The deferment of discussion of the workers&apos; claims in the Franchise Bill was the last link in a chain of similar circumstances which had provoked unrest among the people. The same newspaper, in commenting on the arrival of Kuhhuan, Ludendorff, Czernin, and Wedel in Berlin, remarks that the Reichstag is not so inquisitive about it as the. Press ; that it does net appear to desire further information ; and that it lias actually, through its majority, requested permission to stay at home. The Tagliche Rundschau of February 5th animadverts upon the presence of Herr Erzberger at the recent Council of the &quot; big-bugs &quot; in Berlin, and observes: &quot;It is astonishing to see with what temerity &quot; the Government holds on to the presence of that confidential adviser &quot; in  whom, thank   God,   the   German  people  as   a  whole  reposes   no   trust.&quot;
oThe Bremen Buergcr Zeitung of February 7th states that Erich Ivuttner, editor of Vorwarts, has been arrested on a charge of high treason.   A Wolff telegram dated February .1.0th to the Dutch Press announced that the restrictions imposed by the German   Government  upon  public -discussion of  political  questions   have been , withdrawn.The Intelligence Bureau concludes that the strike, the measures of the military authorities, and the attitude of the Government, have resulted in driving the Majority Socialists into opxnosition, and that this result is altogether acceptable to the Fatherland Party, the Conservatives, the Prussian Junkers, the Pan-Germans, and Militarists, who now expect a policy freed from Socialist support and permitting of repression at home and annexation abroad. Meanwhile the obstruction and. highhandedness of the Prussian reactionaries is exciting resentment in other German states, notably in Baden and Bavaria. It remains to be seen what will be the effect of this domestic - dissension upon the men at the front.Sir II. Rumbold learns that German opinion, nevertheless, expects the projected&apos; offensive in the West to be &quot; another Italy&quot; and the decisive&apos;triumph of the war. If it is a failure, or even if it only offers a negative result, there are very few. trumps left in the hands of the general staff. The only Germans who genuinely -want, a peace on the lines of. President WiisoiPs Message to Congress are a handful of middle-class idealists very closely muzzled. There is little sincerity in the professed peace parties, whether moderate or extreme ; and even more slippery is the Goveru-ment, which, while pretending to adhere to the programme of the Moderate Peace Party, is in effect pursuing the aunexationist ambitions of the Moderate War Party.Economics. Mr. Midler (in a Report dated January 26th)  is of opinion that conditions in Germany are really serious, and that rex*orts to the contrary are due to German inspiration.    He   emphasises the folly of  advertising the British  food shortage in the Press, and points out that this affords the strongest possible induce-ment to the German people to hold out to the last.   An article by Hans Vorst in the Berliner Tageblatt of January 19th, 191.8, gives a warning against exaggerated expectation of supplies from Russia in the event of a separate peace.   &quot; Owing to the &apos;&quot; shortage of agricultural labour, machinery and fertilisers, both the area under &quot;&quot;&quot;cultivation and. the yield decreased year by year.    During the last year tire &quot; insecurity of agricultural conditions has probably  added to these  difficulties. &quot; It would, indeed, appear doubtful whether the crops, even with efficient organisa-&apos;&quot; tion, will  be   sufficient   for  the  needs  of  the Russian  people, and   whether &quot; famine is not imminent.   In any case there can be no question of considerable &quot; visible and tangible stocks of cereals or animal products.&quot;    The only chance of inducing the Russian peasant to part with his stocks is to be able to offer in exchange the goods of which he stands in need.   &quot; This of course could only be done .^ &quot; to a limited extent.   We ourselves are in sore need of manufactured articles and &apos;&quot; leather, and the production of machinery, tools and hardware will only be brought &quot; up to the necessary output when German industries no longer have to devote all &apos;&quot; their resources to the production of war material.   . - .   .   It therefore follows &quot; that even after a peace wdth Russia the Central Powers will have to rely on their &quot; own resources.&quot;    The Tagliche Rundschau of February 5th, in an article entitled &quot; Sinking Prices in the Smuggling Trade,&quot; observes that the east wind does not seem to suit it, and states that the fall in prices which began in. the occupied Baltic provinces and Poland has now spread to East Prussia, Posen and Silesia.   In Warsaw and&apos;Vilua, fur, leather and woollen goods are to be had at one-third to one-half less than a few weeks ago.   Sir J. Jordan learns that German agents are buying up huge stocks of hides and other goods in Siberia.   Sir W. Townley learns that the Central   j Powers have stopped the exportation of ploughs to the Netherlands and are reserving   j them for use in the Ukraine. iNETHERLANDS.Gable Embargo and Transit of Sand and Gravel. The Foreign Office informed Sir W. Townley, on February 9th, that in view of the provisional prohibition of the transit of sand and gravel from Germany via Holland to Belgium and of an under-standing that it will not be resumed before March 15th, His Majesty&apos;s Government was giving immediate orders for the withdrawal of the embargo upon Dutch commercial cables.   Meanwhile negotiations for a final settlement will proceed, and it-1985-26 B
is hoped that a settlement will be reached before March 15th&apos;, failing which both. Governments will be free to take such action as they may deem proper.Export of Horses to Germany. Sir W. Townley reports that 2S0 horses left Tiel on February 7th for Germany. The Foreign Minister has explained that such export is contemplated in the proposed, agreement with the Allies, and has undertaken to expedite the conclusion of negotiations. Sir W. Townley has, however, been instructed to point out that such exportation is considered by His Majesty&apos;s Government as being in breach of the Hides Agreement.SWITZERLAND.Germany and Switzerland. Sir H. Rumbold learns that the concentration of Swiss troops at Bulach and Winterthur is giving much annoyance to the Germans.Goal for manufacture of Cement. Sir If. Rumbold learns that the Germans have objected to the employment of German, coal l)3r Swiss firms in the manufacture of cement for France. The French have already agreed to supply two-thirds of the amount necessary for this purpose, and the manufacturers are now asking that the-remainder should also be supplied by them.Grain Supplies. The Foreign Office advises Mr. Barclay that in view of the importance of keephrg Switzerland independent of German supplies, and the safety of voyages made on Swiss account, it is very desirable that the United States Government should press the Dutch to charter their ships for the round voyage from the United States to the Argentine, thence with grain to Cette, and. back to the United States. The French Government is returning the 15,000 tons borrowed last-year at the rate of 3,000 tons a month.Cotton Exports.   Sir H. Rumbold reports that the French Ambassador has now presented a Joint Note to the Swiss Government in regard to the exportation of: cotton (see Reports Nos. 51, 52 and 53),NORWAY.Negotiations with United States. The War Trade Intelligence Department reports that the Norwegian Government has nowr replied to the proposals of the United States War Trade Board. They would agree not to export more than 48,000 tons-per annum of fish and fish products to the enemy; but they ask to be left at liberty to supply Germany with large quantities of calcium carbide, calcium nitrate,, ferro-silicon, molybdenite and pyrites. This counter-proposal is regarded by the-German Minister as unsatisfactory, but it will not satisfy the United States. The first four commodities in the Norwegian list are materials used in the manufacture-of munitions, and pyrites is chiefly valuable to the enemy as a source of sulphuric acid.   (And see- under &quot; Shipping Situation.&quot;)SWEDEN.Sweden and the Baltic.- The Svenska Dagbladet (Conservative and pro-German) of February 7th, points out in a leading article that the situation, in the Baltic has changed profoundly, and that probably several new Baltic States will exist at the end of the war.   It is the chief interest of Sweden that no power should become supreme-in the Baltic.   She should, therefore, support the new States, both now and after the war, and promote -commercial relations with them.   For the same reason Sweden must hope that Finland will not be compelled to ask for German intervention to save her from anarchy.   Politiken on the same date publishes an interview with Trotsky, in which he states that the Germans intend to fortify the islands of Mohn and Dago, which would become a Baltic Gibraltar.   The interests of Russia, Finland, Sweden,, and Denmark coincide in this matter.Aland Islands. Politiken of February 7th published a statement made by Trotsky to the Swedish Extreme Socialist, Hoglund, disclosing a secret treaty made in 1907&apos;
between Russia and Germany, in which the Germans recognised Russia&apos;s right to fortify the Aland Islands, and declared they would not consider this a breach of the Paris Treaty of 1856. In a long reply the German Minister has endeavoured to show that this treaty was not in prejudice of Sweden, whose true friend has in fact been Germany. The Liberal Dagens Nyheter of February 8th, in an article entitled &quot; The true friend,&quot; observes that it is now seen that Germany betrayed Sweden over the Aland question in 1907. The Social Democrat is similarly outspoken, and the Conservative&apos; Sven-skq. Dagblad admits to some surprise. The Swedish press reported on February 9th the receipt of official telegrams from Aland to the effect that the situation demanded immediate measures for the effective protection of the islands. Sir E. Howard learns that Swedish troops have been warned that they maybe ordered to Aland at short notice.Allies and Propaganda. The French Minister has handed a Memorandum to the Minister for Foreign Affairs in the sense indicated in Report No. 54, and has since been informed that the Swedish Government considers the reply satisfactory. In view of the reiterated demand by a Conservative paper for an explanation, the Swedish Foreign Office has issued the memorandum to the Press.(And see under &quot;Shipping Situation.&quot;)DENMARK. &apos;Exports to Germany. The War Trade Intelligence Department reports that the Danish exports of cattle to Germany reached, in December and January, the high weekly average of 11,000 head. It is now stated that the Germans are to receive an additional 2,000 head a week,,in compensation for supplies of mineral oil. The United States War Trade Board insists, as a condition of its proposed agreement with Denmark, that the exports of cattle to Germany shall not exceed a weekly average of 6,000 head. They will demand that any excess over this figure as from January 1st shall be balanced b)T a corresponding reduction of the exports after the agreement is signed. The exports of Danish produce to Germany are still enormous. In the four weeks ending January 16th the average weekly consignments of pork and bacon were 180 tons ; of fresh meat, 136 tons ; of butter, 236 tons ; of eggs, 102 tons. There were also smaller but still considerable exports of salt and preserved meat, milk and vegetables.FINLAND.Recognition. The Foreign Office has instructed His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Consul at Helsingfors to transact necessary business unofficially with the de facto authorities, explaining if necessary that His Majesty&apos;s Government is prepared to recognise any Government which can demonstrate that it represents the considered public opinion of the country.Sweden and Intervention. The Foreign Office learns that agitation for and against volunteer intervention continues in Sweden. Colonel Linder, commanding the Swedish Horse Guards, has resigned, his commission to serve in Finland, and it is reported that many officers have followed his example. The extreme Socialists declare that any attempt by the Swedish Bourgeoisie to crush the Finnish Revolutionary Government will bring about a revolution in Sweden in the spring and they are opposed even to mediation which is suggested, by Mr. Branting and the Social Democrats. The situation is rendered particularly difficult by the facts that Moderate Socialists in Finland have joined the Reds, and Bolshevist agents have been agitating among the Swedish working classes. Fear is felt that if the Reds succeed in Finland the movement will spread throughout Scandinavia. Unrest in Copenhagen has already been reported. Moderate Liberal papers which reflect the attitude of the Government are in favour of temporising. The Swedish Government realises that by actively intervening it may be drawn into a sort of alliance with Germany. At the same time it is permitting the export and transit of arms. Two Finnish steamers have left Stockholm for Hamburg to fetch arms and ammunition.Progress of Eighting. The White Forces have taken Tornea and now hold the whole of the north of Finland.   Several thousands of Russian soldiers and sailors have
arrived at Helsingfors. Russian warships have arrived outside Sveaborg. The Finnish ice-breaker Sairipo has been sent by the Reds from Gefle to fetch arms from Germany and Denmark.. SPAIN.Germany and Spanish Wheat Supply. In a despatch dated January 31st Sir Hardinge reports that the estimated wheat harvest for 1918 will, with good luck, amount to 3,000,000 tons, which is 1,000,000 below the annual average output. The idea is to supplement the deficiency with wheat from the Argentine, and efforts are being made to obtain an undertaking from Berlin that ships bringing wheat from still neutral Argentina and coal from the United States will not be torpedoed before reaching Spain Whether or not the Germans ultimately agree, it is probable they will employ the negotiations so- as to hamper financial arrangements between Spain and the Allies.Internal Position. In the same despatch Sir A. Hardinge observes that the Army is generally considered to be still loyal. Disaffection in the non-commissioned ranks has been checked by the judicious pardon of the sergeants who were recentl)7 convicted of plotting and mutiny. ft is also believed that the Republican leaders are still resolved to defer any organised attempt at revolution, whether by parliamentary or violent methods, so long as the European war continues.Torpedoed Ships. Sir A. Hardinge learns that the Spanish note to Germany on the torpedoing of the S.S. Giralda is not in the nature of an ultimatum, and permits of an evasive reply. The Italian Ambassador has called the attention of the Spanish Government to the sinking in Spanish territorial waters of the S.S. Duke of Genoa. The Spanish Press is showing considerable indignation at the recent submarine outrages.Spanish-American Agreement. Sir A. Hardinge reports an agreement in principle between the Spanish and American Governments, under Avhich the United States will provide monthly 35,000 bales of cotton and 8,000 tons of petroleum, conditional upon the prior conclusion of a financial agreement between Spain and France and an agreement by Spain to place a certain amount of Spanish tonnage at the disposal of the American Government. Some difficulty is anticipated in connection with the latter condition.CHINA.Plague. Sir J. Jordan reports that the plague (see Report No. 5Pj has now spread from the Kueihuating district in Northern Shansi eastward as far as Tingchow in Chih-li and southward to a point 50 miles north of Taiyuanfu in Shansi. As a result of effective measures already taken, it is hoped that the situation is being brought under control.Wireless Installations. :The Foreign Office learns that-the Japanese Government has made representations to the Chinese Government in respect of an agreement made between the Chinese Minister &quot;of Marine and a Danish subject for a wireless telegraph concession. The Japanese Government has requested and obtained the cancellation of this agreement, and has expressed the hope that in future the Chinese Government will consult with Japan before coming to any decision in regard to wireless telegraphy in China. The Japanese Government has suggested to His Majesty&apos;s Government that under a proposed arrangement between the Japanese and Chinese Governments the dislodgment of an existing German concession will he effected; and has referred to an assurance given by Lord Grey in January .1916 regarding German concessions in China. The Foreign Office instructs Sir J. Jordan that the Japanese contention, which amounts to a claim to a monopoly, would seem to involve the official support promised by His Majesty&apos;s Government to the Marconi Company, and that Lord Grey&apos;s assurance should not be deemed to cover the Japanese project, seeing that the Marconi negotiations commenced before the war and concern new stations.
Enemy Property. The Foreign Office instructs Sir J. Jordan to concert with other Allied Ministers in approaching the Chinese Government with a view to the liquidation of enemy property. , &apos; .Exports to Russia. The Foreign Office has advised Mr. Lindley that the acquiescence of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the Chinese prohibition of exports to Siberia was entirely due to its apprehension that supplies might ultimately reach the enemy. The Foreign Office has instructed. Sir J. Jordan that while not objecting to the complete withdrawal of the prohibition of exports to Russia, it hopes that the Chinese Government will take steps to prevent Chinese produce from reaching enemy hands.ARGENTINE REPUBLIC.Railway Strike. Sir R. Tower reports that a strike has broken out on the Central Cordoba and Southern and Central Argentine Railways. Should this become general, the removal of the grain crop will be impeded. Public opinion is largely against the strikers and the majority of the men themselves do not favour the extreme demands of the Federation. Society. The President of the Republic, whose chief concern is the forthcoming elections, is likely to avoid action tending to alienate labour. The strikers, who are possibly assisted by German funds, are taking advantage of the Government^ weakness, in view of the extravagance of the claims made, it would seem that, they must be resisted by the railway managers, even if this course should involve closing down indefinitely.Wheat Purchase. With regard to the proposed purchase of wheat by Northern neutrals (see Report No. 54) the Foreign Office instructs Air. Barclay that purchase through the Wheat Executive should be represented as a favour and not imposed as an obligation.   It would not be necessary to specify the source of supply.BRAZIL.Censorship. The Foreign Office has instructed Sir A. Peel to impress upon the Brazilian Government the importance of examining closely all mails passing between Brazil and Spain and all passengers and crews embarking for Spain at Brazilian ports.BOLIVIA.-Enemy Tin Mines. The Foreign Office instructs Air. Barclay to discuss-- with the United States Government the advisability of cancelling licences which permit of the importation into Great Britain and the United States respectively of tin supplied from enemy-owned mines in Bolivia. At present, owing to the high prices at present ruling, these enemy concerns are prospering at the expense of the Allies. Their isolation might result in their enforced sale to Allied interests. The desirability or otherwise of the measure proposed is dependent on the Allied situation in regard to tin supplies.HONDURAS.United States and German Trade. The Foreign Office learns that as a result of the refusal by two German companies at Amapala to afford lighterage facilities to American trade the United States Government has demanded from the Honduras Government the expulsion of all Germans from that port and from Tegucigalpa. It wordd appear that the Germans have refused to leave and that the Honduras Government has endeavoured to meet the wdshes of the United States Government by confiscating the launches. It is further reported that the United States Government is pressing the Honduras Government to undertake to refuse reinstate-ment of the Germans at Amapala after the war, and that the Honduras Government is unwilling to agree to this, fearing an. American mining monopoly.49S5 -26 C
MEXICO.Cavranza and the Oilfields. Mr. Barclay reports that the United States Government has urged upon the Mexican Government the dismissal of Germans serving in the Mexican Army, and warned it of the grave consequences which would attend any disaster to the oilfields. The Foreign Office has proposed to the French Government that joint action should be taken with the United States Government in an offer to support Carranza conditional upon the cessation of intrigues with. Germany and upon suitable guarantees being given. Meanwhile Government forces are.reported to have reached the oilfields, and according to a well-informed opinion, work may soon become impossible. There is, however, still a chance that Caballero may join Pelaez.   Such a coalition might seriousby affect the prospects of Carranza.Wireless Installation. -Mr. Cummins reports that the wireless installation at Ohapultepec is being increased to 250 horse-power.UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.Lord Reading. Mr. Barclay announces the arrival at New York on February 9th of Lord and Lady Reading.War Administration. ml-. Barclay reports the introduction, at the instance of President Wilson, of a Bill evidently designed to supplant the War Cabinet and Munitions Bill. Under it&apos; the President would be empowered to consolidate and redistribute the powers and functions of all executive Departments, and would be given control of all functions appropriated by Congress for any executive purposes. The Bill is certain to be strongly opposed, inasmuch as it would very greatly strengthen the President at the expense of Congress, and would-leave him the uncontrolled appointment of a War Cabinet without any guarantee that he would carry out recommendations made by Congress. The Bill has been unfavourably received, and there appears to be small probability that it will be accepted in its present form.SHIPPING SITUATION.Sinkings. According to the War Trade Intelligence Bureau the total tonnage of 500 tons gross in the case of steamships and 100 tons gross in the case of sailing ships reported lost owing to the malice of the Kmg&apos;s enemies during the period February 1 st-7th inclusive was 112,181) tons gross, of which 76,63-1 were British as compared with 58,719 tons gross, of which 32,423 were British reported last week.World1 s Tonnage. Comparison of Losses. The Admiralty reports that the world&apos;s mercantile tonnage, including new construction and enemy tonnage in control of the Allies, amounted on December 31st, 1917, to 39,622,000 gross tons as against 42,441,000 (excluding enemy tonnage) existing on August 1st, 19.14. The net loss, therefore, if tonnage in German ownership be excluded, is 2,819,000 gross tons or 6&apos; 6 per cent. If ocean-going tonnage only is reckoned the loss works out at between 8 and 9 per cent. The total workhs losses for the half years ending-January 31st, 19.17, July 31st, 1917, and January 31st, 1918, were 939 ships (1,765,085 tons), 1,683 ships (3,816,817 tons), and 909 ships (2,272,725 tons) respec-tively. Thus, the losses for the last half-year of unrestricted submarine warfare .represent a reduction of about 46 per cent, in number and 40 per cent, in tonnage on the figures for the first half of the year, whilst, compared with the six months preceding the policy of sinking at sight, there is an actual reduction of 3 per cent, in number sunk, though the tonnage lost exceeds the figure for the earlier period. The British tonnage sunk by enemy action during January 1918- only slightly exceeded the figure for the month of November,, which was the lowest since the commencement, of unrestricted submarine warfare.
L56Convoys. The Shipping Controller reports that of 5,430 ships (26,592,813 gross registered tons) employed on convoys outward and homeward up to February 2nd,. 59 (425,000 deadweight capacity) have been. sunk. This represents a percentage of I-07 of ships and .1&apos; 1 of tonnage.Allied Coed Distribution. The British Representatives of the Inter-allied Council on Tonnage and Passports have recommended that, of 600,000 tons of coal required. monthly by Italy, 350,000 (or so much of this amount as possible) should be supplied from French mines, and the remainder from the United Kingdom. His Majesty&apos;s Government is prepared to make good small French deficiencies by diverting to that purpose vessels now in other French services, and any other suitable tonnage that-may become available. It is pointed out that the civilian consumption of coal in France amounts to more than the whole of Italy&apos;s needs, and that in Italy civilian consumption has been practically stopped.Labour and Shipbuilding. The Board of Admiralty reports that the output of completed merchant vessels for January 1918 has been seriously affected by extended holidays, strikes and exceptionally bad weather. The principal causes of unrest have been the desire to have the 12i- per cent, bonus made general, food shortage and housing difficulties.Tonnage for Bunkering Stocks Abroad. The Shipping Controller reports that owing to shrinkage of tonnage and the increased allocation of tonnage to the carriage of wheat, the shipping available for supply of coal for the bunkering stocks abroad is much restricted, and an adjustment &quot;will soon have to be made between competing demands.Brewing and Tonnage. -The Shipping Controller reports that the complete prohibition of brewing would effect a direct. saving of tonnage for other imports equivalent to 749,000 tons carried in 1918, and would also indirectly release coastal shipping by freeing the railways for other traffic,Norwegian Tonnage. Sir M. Fiudlay reverts to the serious political objections to exposing certain Norwegian ships to risks such as caused the loss of the S.S. &quot; Elsa.&quot; He has reason to believe that the question has been the subject of discussion by the Norwegian Foreign Office with the Swedish, Dutch, and Danish Ministers probably with a view to common action.Enemy Ships in Uruguay.--Negotiations are in progress for time chartering German vessels at Montevideo, recently taken over by the Uruguayan Government. Tenders have been made by the Governments of Great Britain and the United States through firms nominated for the purpose.Enemy Ships in Chile. Lord Reading reports that the United States Government has practically concluded negotiations for purchasing vessels of the Hamburg-Amerika Line now in Chilian ports. The Foreign Office had already prointed out to the Chilian Government their importance in connection with the exportation of Chilian nitrates.Licensing. The Shipping Controller reports that on feburary 11th the system of licensing, which has hitherto applied to British steamers registered in the United Kingdom over 500 tons employed outside the limits of the coasting trade of the United Kingdom, was extended so as to apply to all. British ships, irrespective of size, proceeding from the United Kingdom, and to all ships of whatever nationality in the United Kingdom coasting trade.PEACE DISCUSSIONS.General. Sir W. Townley reported on good aTithority on January 19th that the real German war aims in the East include a more or less imonounced annexation of the territories occupied, though it suits von Kuhhuann to pretend to be a non-annexationist.
Russian Wireless of February. 9th gave what purported to he a transcript of the-shorthand notes of the Session at Brest on January 31st. The substance of this-discussion has already been reported.German Wireless of February 6th continued their report of the debate at Brest on February 1st on the Ukrainian question. This report gives Count Czernin&apos;s summary in the following words : &quot; We consider ourselves additionally obliged already to &quot; recognise the Ukrainian National Republic, at the present moment, as an inde-&quot; pendent, free, and sovereign State, which is in a position to conclude international &quot; agreements independently,&quot; and adds that M. Trotsky briefly remarked that he had not changed his former conception of the Ukrainian question.Mr. Lindley on February 5th communicated a message from the Military Attache to the Director of Military Intelligence reporting that telegraphic communication, between Brest and Petrograd was resumed in the afternoon of February 4th. It was anticipated that the Germans would threaten to seize Reval within three days, for which purpose they had a force ready, if M. Trotsky did. not accept their terms.Russian Wireless of February 10th reported the arrival at Brest on February 6th. of von Kuhlmarin and Count Czernin, and the following morning a sitting was held to discuss a settlement of political and territorial questions between the German, Russian, and Austro-Hungarian Commissions.German Wireless of February 10th reported that at the sitting at Brest on the same day the Russian Delegation announced that Russia, while desisting from signing-a formal Treaty of Peace, declared that the state of. war between Germany, Austria-Hungary, Turkey and Bulgaria was at an end. At the same time it announced the order for a complete demobilisation of the Russian forces at the fronts. The conditions of the Peace Treaty between the Central Powers and the Ukraine, embodying ten articles, were announced briefly in German Wireless of the same day. These appeared fully in German Wireless and in the Times of February 12th.German Wireless of February 11th contains a report of the meeting at Brest which concluded in the early morning hours of February 9th at which, von Kiihlmann, as president, used the words : &quot; May this peace be the first of a series of blessed peace &quot; treaties, blessed both for the Allied Powers and also for the Ukrainian Republic, for the future of which we all cherish the best wishes.&quot; The President of the Ukrainian Delegation, in. reply, said that they were concluding peace in the interests of their great democratic masses, and that this peace will contribute to the general ending of the great Avar. After this announcement, extracts from German, Dutch and English papers followed, and attention is drawn to an announcement in the Manchester Guardian that France lent the Ukraine .180,000,000 francs and sent a military commission for the reorganisation of the army.[Further details of the conclusion of peace by the Central Powers with the Bolshevist Russian Government, and with the Ukraine, are given under those headings.]German Wireless of February 8th reports that the train in which Messieurs Kameneif and Saalkind started their journeys to France and Switzerland could not leave Finland, and did not get beyond Tammerfors.Russia. Air. Lindley on February 3rd reported that, before closing, the All Russian Congress of Soviets passed a resolution iii the following words : -&quot; Besolu-&quot; tion respecting peace confirms all statements made and all steps taken up to date &quot; by Soviet Governments to conclude a universal Democratic peace, and declares the &quot; attitude of Austria and Germany towards Lithuania, Poland, Ukraine, Livonia and &quot; Esthonia to be contrary to the principles affirmed by them in their declaration of &quot; December 25th, 19 L7.&quot;Russian Wireless of February 6th published a strong appeal in German to the working classes, especially of Germany and Austria-Hungary, stating that it is now clear to every working man that in this war there can be no question of the &quot; defence of the Fatherland &quot; ; that the mask has been torn, off, and the real, aims of all Imperialistic Governments have at last been unmasked. &apos; The only solution is an International Socialistic Revolution.Mr. Lindley on February 6th. forwarded a report from Mr. Lockhart, said to be based on good authority, that it was more than probable that the Bolshevists would conclude a separate peace, but that Trotsky would not do so if the Germans
did not&apos;agree to recall their military forces - now in Courland. On. February 7th. Mr. Lindley furnished proofs that the Bolshevists&apos; policy was to sacrifice Rumania to secure peace. On. February 8th he reported that the Germans in Petrograd had&apos;been ordered to get ready to leave, by a telegram sent en clair, because of the rupture of negotiations for peace.Russian AVireless of February 11th publishes a manifesto, signed at Brest on February 10th by M. Trotsky and the other Russian delegates, stating that peace negotiations are at an end. German capitalists, bankers and landlords, &quot; supported by the silent co-operation of English and French bourgeoisie,&quot; submitted conditions which could not be subscribed to by the Russian Revolution. The delegates state further that the German and Austrian Governments desire to possess countries and peoples vanquished by the force of arms. To this Russian workmen and peasants could not give their acquiescence. While unable to sign a peace, &quot; they cannot, will not, and must - not, continue a war which was begun by Czars and capitalists in alliance with Czars and capitalists.&quot; Russia declares the present war with Germany, Austria-Hungary, Turkey, and Bulgaria at an end. The manifesto is followed by an unsigned statement in the first person, dated February 11th, ordering a general demobilisation, but that some detachments of the younger soldiers must be left for the defence of the frontier.Russian AVireless of February .11th publishes a resolution adopted at a meeting of Avar prisoners appealing to brothers at the front to unite to stop the war.Ukraine. Russian Wireless of February 10th gives a transcript of the shorthand notes of the Peace Conference on February 1st. M. Trotsky on this occasion is reported to have said : &quot; Those conflicts which we had with Ukrainia, and which, &quot; unfortunately, are not yet ended, can in no way restrict the right of the Ukrainian &quot; people to self-determination, and are in no way hindering us from recognising the &quot; Independent Ukrainian Republic.&quot;German Wireless of February 9th reported that at 2 a.m. on that day peace was signed between the Quadruple Alliance and the Ukrainian Republic.Sir W. Townley and Mr. Lindley both reported on February 10th that the Quadruple Alliance had signed peace with Ukrainia. Sir W. Townley quoted from the Lolial Anzeiger the opinion that &quot; the peace is essentially an economic one.&quot; On February 8th he quoted an article from the Essen Allgemeine Zeitung, containing statements that peace concluded with Ukrainia would deprive Rumania of all future prospects of gain.Russian Wireless of February 10th publishes a full report of the speeches by the Ukrainian delegates, delivered before the Peace Conference was adjourned for von Kuhlmann and Czernin to visit Berlin, ending with Count Czernirhs acknow-ledgment of the Ukrainian Republic as an independent free sovereign State on behalf of the Central Powers. After Count Czerniirs speech, M. Trotsky said : &quot; The objection which I have made retains all its force.&quot;The Foreign Office on February 11th informed Mr. Bagge that the French Government had issued a declaration that they will not recognise the peace made separately with Germany and Austria-Hungary by the Ukrainians. The Foreign Office instructed Mr. Bagge to make a similar declaration on behalf of Great Britain in association with his French colleague.Russian Wireless of February 1.1th issues a proclamation by the People&apos;s Commissary to the effect that the ivieff Rada had fallen, and all authority is in the hands of the Councils. &quot; The adventure of the Kieff bourgeoisie is at an end.&quot;German Wireless of February 11th published, a notice in the Russian language embodying news received by the respective newspapers in foreign countries of the announcement that peace between the Ukraine and the Central Powers had been declared.The terms of peace were published in full in the Times of February 12th. Special interest is attached to the VIItk Article, in which the contracting parties &quot;undertake &quot; mutually, without delay, to enter into economic relations and to organise the &quot; exchange of goods, &amp;c.&quot; .On February 12th Sir 11. Rumbold reported on reliable authority- that, in a secret treaty, the Germans have promised military help to the Ukraine against Russia.   ,4985-2?) U
Poland. Russian Wireless of &quot; February 7th published an incomplete message-expressing the belief that provisional representation could be made of independent Poland to participate in peace negotiations at Brest, and added: &quot; We on our side are ready to-recognise completely, without any restrictions, such representation.&quot;&apos; This course is adopted because such a peace would enable the Polish Rada to declare openly in the face of the whole Polish people its attitude to such a question as the-evacuation of Polish territory by foreign troops, and the alteration of Polish frontiers.[The above appears to be an extract from a speech by M. Trotsky at Brest.   It is followed by the report of a speech by von Kuhlmann on the same subject.]Esihpnia. Mr. Liiidley reported on February 5th that a telegram had been received, signed by practically all parties in Esthonia, protesting strongly against the-German occupation of the Esthonian Islands, Oesel, Dago and Moon, and demanding further, in order to assure a free vote, that the troops of Germany and Russia shall evacuate both the islands and the country of Esthonia. On February 7th he reported a visit paid to him by Esthoiiiaus on- that day to leave a)Memorandum on Esthoniau war aims, of which he gave further details.Sir C. Greene on February 7th reported the support of the Japanese Government for a proposed encouraging reply to the Esthonian delegation to the Emperor of Japan, assuring support of the independence of States coming into being through the-war, and of the prevention of Germany from annexing provinces in the Baltic.Rumania. Sir R. Rodd on February 6th reported that the Italian Foreign Minister was strongly against Rumania making a separate peace without the Allies&apos; consent, as this would set a very bad precedent for others who had entered into similar agreements, and. would afford encouragement to pacifists in. Italy and possibly elsewhere.Sir W. Townley reported on feburary Gth, on the authority of the Vossische of January 5th, that there -would soon be negotiations at Sinaria between the four-Powers find Rumania to conclude an armistice.The Foreign Office on February 7th sent instructions to Sir G. Barclay to convey encouragement to M. Bratiano to dispel his alarm. Grounds were added for hopeful-ness in the situation, and the hope was expressed . that the Rumanian Army wordd fight, on in co-operation with her Allies for a successful issue of the war.The Intelligence Bureau on February 7th reported that President WilsoAs speech on -war aims caused consternation in Rumania where it was considered to be an entire-abandonment of Rumanians national aims.Sir W. Townley reported on February 7th on good authority that news about approaching peace negotiations were confirmed. The basis for discussion would be that Rumania should have part of Bessarabia, and that part of -Dobrudja should go-to Bulgaria. It was reported that the representatives of the Central Powers, after their recent meeting at Berlin, had agreed to offer an ultimatum to Trotsky based upon peace for Ukrainia and Rumania on these lines, and that the Central Powers would still refuse to withdraw their troops from occupied territories until a general peace. Ukrania may object to Rumania&apos;s frontier claims.On February 9th Sir if. Rumbold reported that Rumania would probably make peace as soon as the Ukraine did, and that the Ukraine would agree to her getting Bessarabia, the Dobrudja going to Bulgaria.The Foreign Office on February 9th, in explaining to Sir G, Barclay the attitude of the British Government, pointed out the extent to which Rumania would benefit by anything which would either put off or stop the conclusion of a separate peace by the Bolshevists with Germany and Austria-FIungary.Telegrams between Lord Bertie, Sir G. Barclay, and the Foreign Office between, the 6th and 9th of February, reported General von AIackensen&apos;s threatening declara-tion to the Rumanians at Focsani, giving four days for opening peace negotiations, which was followed by the resignation of the Government and the formation of a new one, with General Averescu as Prime Minister, to enter into negotiations for peace.On February 11 Sir G. Barclay forwarded a message from the Military Attache at Jassy to the effect that the new Prime Minister is not prepared to accept peace at.
all costs. Negotiations are to be opened to discover the enemies&apos; intentions, and also to gain all possible time.Finland. Russian Wireless of February 8th reports a speech by M. Trotsky at Brest explaining the non-withdrawal of Bolshevist troops from Finland, in spite of the independence of that country having been recognised. The message has been mutilated in transmission.Germany. Sir W. Townley reported on January .19th that the role of the Kaiser had become that of a mediator between the reactionary and the progressive parties. He interests himself more in claims which have as an object the widening of an economic influence rather than the military adjustment of frontiers.   -Sir W. Townley on February 8th drew attention to an article in the Essen Allgemeiue Zeitung containing the passages : &quot;We went to Brest-Litovsk to conclude peace, not to assist Trotsky to heap coals on his fires of revolution &quot; and &quot; the &quot; development of mob rule in Russia proves to Western. Europe that a Maximalist &quot; Government is just as great a danger as fallen Tsardom.&quot; On February 9th he quoted from Germania of February 8th the view that King George&apos;s words reveal a deep chasm between British and German war aims. On February 9th he gives from the Berliner Tageblalt Dr. Brandenburg&apos;s views in favour of German frontiers being &quot; extended as far as German military leaders think necessary for the defence of the Fatherland.&quot;German Wireless of February Sth published an account of an article in the Norddeiitsclie Allgemeine Zeitung about the Brest negotiations, denying the announce-ments made by Russian wireless stations, and adding that no further talking can shake the Central Powers in their firm and unalterable decision not to evacuate the Western regions of Russia in the manner expressed by M. Trotsky, and further compromises on the question of the right of self-determination appear to be impossible. German Wireless of the same date, issued in the Russian language states that Germany sees in the resolutions of the War Council at Versailles a new, declaration of war by the Entente Powers.German AVireless of February 11th. transmits a message from the Kaiser to the Burgomaster at Homburg which contains the words: &quot;The enemy, who has been &quot; beaten by our armies, and realises that it is no longer any use to fight, and who &quot; holds out his hand towards us, will receive our hand in return.&quot; And, &quot; We wish &quot;to live in friendship with our neighbouring nations, but first the victory of the &quot; German arms must be recognised.&quot;Austi&apos;ia-Hangary. Sir W. Townley reported on February 5th a statement in the Arbeiter Zeitung of February 2nd that the British&apos; workmen will not endure the needs and sacrifices of the war for an indefinite time, and only when the working classes in every country are in a position, to exercise sufficient pressure on their Governments, wdll those Governments be forced to make peace, finding the necessary compromises.Bulgaria. German Wireless of February 11th stated that Bulgaria is expecting that Rumania will join with the Ukraine in a peace with the Central Powers, and is declaring its sympathy towards the Ukraine, which will be independent of Great Russia.France. Lord Bertie reported on February 6th that the French, had decided to allow Mr. Huysmans to go to France if the Belgian Government did not object. The Foreign Minister has ascertained that the Belgian Government has no objection. M. Renaudel had informed the Foreign Minister that the London meeting could not be arranged as early as February 20th.The Intelligence Bureau on February 6th reported a general feeling in France .that neither Count Hertling nor Count Czernin in their speeches on war aims had said anything that brought the prospect of peace any nearer, and that there was still some desire for a joint statement on war aims by all the Allies, including the United States.On February 11th Lord Bertie reported that, by a majority of about three to one, the Socialist Federation of the Seine passed a resolution subscribing to the peace4985-26 E
]g-formula of the Russian revolution, and advocating a referendum on the Alsace-Lorraine question. On February 12th he added that this is styled a &quot; Bolshevist &quot; resolution by principal newspapers.Italy. Sir Rennell Rodd reported on February 7th an application by a Socialist deputy. M. Modigliani, for facilities in granting vise of passports for five labour deputies, including well-known pacifists, for England to attend the February 20th Conference. Sir R. Rodd said that they should apply through their Government. M. Modigliani was ready to substitute other names for any of the proposed repre-sentatives thought undesirable in England.The Intelligence Bureau of February 8th reported that the Italian interpretations of Count Hertling&apos;s and Czernihs speeches did not differ from those of the Allied countries. Taken together, they are regarded as a skilful blending of cajolery with defiance. The speeches of the British Prime Minister and President Wilson, as referring to Italy and Austria, have depressed the spirit, and puzzled the minds of the patriotic, and have delighted and strengthened the Clericals and Giolittians, while making distressingly difficult the task of the Interventionalists, our best friends. The official communication about the result of Signor Orlando&apos;s visit to London has not entirely allayed Italian, apprehensions about the intentions of the Allies.Sir R. Rodd on February 12th sent an account of the re-assembly of the Chamber. The Prime Minister announced that the feeling of anxiety about Avar aims &quot; had been entirely dispelled.&quot;   The declaration Avas very cordially received.Serbia. According to a report from Sir C. Des Graz dated February 7th, the Prime Minister, Avhile encouraging other Serbian Socialists to go to England, could not countenance the journey of Kazlerovitch. from Stockholm to attend a conference.United States. German AVireless of February 8th publishes a statement that President Wilson does not consider himself bound by the negative attitude assumed at Versailles toAvards Count Czernin and Count Herding, and reserves to himself the right to reply on behalf of America.[President Wilsohs new speech to Congress on AA*ar aims was reported in the Times of February 12th as follows :  &quot;The President laid clown the following - principles as necessary for a just peace :  &quot; (1) Each part of the final settlement must, he based on the essential justice of that particular case.&quot; (2) Peoples and provinces must not be bartered as chattels or paAvns, even in thediscredited game of the Balance of Power. &quot; (3) Territorial settlements must be made in the  interest of the populationsconcerned.&quot; (4) Satisfaction,  of  all   avell-defined  national  aspirations,   which Avould  not introduce or perpetuate antagonisms likely to break the peace.&quot;Until peace on such a basis could be secured the United States had no option but to go on. The principles he had set forth appeared to be accepted everywhere &apos; except among the spokesmen of the military and annexationist party in Germany.&apos; &quot;]China. Sir J. Jordan, on February 9th, reported an apparent wish on the part of the Chinese Government to issue a joint declaration that China will not make peace separately. Lord. Bertie on the same day reported that the French Ambassador at Peking had received instructions to act with his colleagues in giving certain assurances to the Chinese GoA-ernment about the consideration which will be given to Chinese interests when the time comes for a peace conference.Sweden. Sir M. Findlay reported on February 6th that the idea provisionally announced that Sweden would send a representative to Brest would be given up.Great Britain.- The Foreign Office &quot;on February 10th sent information to Mr. Lindley about the propaganda being carried on in Great Britain by M. Litvinoff, and on the same date informed Mr. Lindley that M. Petroff should not be allowed to come to England.
GENERAL.Exchange of Prisoners. The- Foreign Office lias instructed Sir W. Townley to transmit an immediate protest through the Netherlands Minister at Berlin in regard to the unsatisfactory manner in which the exchange and transfer to Holland of British combatants is being carried out by the German Government.Merchant Seamen. The Foreign Office learns that the German Government considers officers and men captured on armed or unarmed merchant ships as military prisoners.Poison Gas. Sir H. Rumbold reports that the International Red Cross has issued an appeal to the belligerents against the use of poison gas, as being in breach of the Hague Convention and causing suffering not only to combatants but to civilians behind the lines. The Foreign Office has suggested that an identic reply should be returned by the Allies. Sir H. Rumbold learns that Professor Foerster, of Munich, and Professor Lammasch, of Vienna, are endeavouring to obtain in the Central Empires a favourable reception of the appeal. It is believed, however, that the German Government will ignore it.

</content>
</cab>
