<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/148/0 images: 492-510</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.254APPRECIATION-  OF THE ATTACH PI)  WESTERN AND GKMRRAL-REPORT No.  75,PART ii. FOREIGN AND GENERAL.Peace Discussions (see page 15).These are -summarised under pence discussions, General, on page 15. The report that the petroleum industry in Russia has been &quot; nationalised &quot; is of interest, There have been other reports of the nationalisation of industries in countries over which the Germans are in a position to exert pressure in order to obtain financial control, and. future developments in this direction, will be watched with, interest, as affecting the coining economic struggle. This subject is also referred to under Germany, below.Generar, (see page 2). The latest information about the Siberian problem is reported.Allied Countries.Belgium (see page 2). Special attention is drawn to the very subtle proposal, put forward in the Kdlnische Zeitung, for the partition of Belgium, without &quot;annexation&quot; or &quot;forcible Germ ami sation. &quot; of Flanders, but with. &quot; close economic relation with, her natural, hinterland, Germany.&quot; flow long the. tortured. Belgian nation will be able to hold out against such proposals, unless delivered from German dominance, is a matter for conjecture.Brazil (see page 3). Steps are reported to secure the country against German, economic pressure. Sir Maurice de Bnnseids Mission appears to have had good results.China (see page 3). The question of deportation of Germans is reported to have formed the subject of prevarication by the German Foreign Minister in the Reichstag.France (see page 4). The attitude of M. Albert Thomas is of interest.Panama (see page 4). Colon and Panama have been occupied by United States troops.Portugal (see page 4). The internal situation appears to be unstable.United Slates (see page 5). The importance of British propaganda is emphasised. [p.t.o.
Enemy Oountrtes.Austria-IIuncjary (see page 6).  Reports under ad headings (Austrian offensive, the United States and the subject races, and. the attitude of the Poles) are important,Germany (see -page 7). Interesting details are given of the public attitude towards the war, and also important matter indicating the German attitude in economic policy.NeUtI!At:, (&apos;.&apos;OIJNTRTES.Chile (see page 9). The Germans are clearly desirous for Chilean neutrality to be&apos; maintained.Denmark (see page 9). A report is given of the recent Scandinavian Conference.Finland (see page 9). All reports are important, as affecting the acute question of the Murman coast. The altitude of the Government towards the Swedish party, and the possible split between Monarchists and Republicans may be significant.Netherlands (see page .11). The East Indies convoy negotiations have reached a critical stage.   Arrangements about the Limburg railway remain unsatisfactory.Norway (see page 13). The German attitude towards Norwegian shipping is interpreted.Spain (see page 14). German propagandists are again very active.Vatican (see page 15).- The Press disclaims, on behalf of the Vatican, all responsibility for the action of the Irish priests.G. G. A.July 4th, 1918.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government&quot;Printed for the War Cabinet. ggSECRET. Fort Reference onlv.IfWESTERN and general  report.No. 75.    Week ending 3rd July 1918 (night).PART IT. FOREIGN AND GENERAL. Contests.General.Sinkings.   Far IjJhst.   Hospital ships.   Reported employment of Allied prisoners in Berlin streets. Allied Group.Belgium. Germany and Flanders.   Gorman economic pressure. Brivssi 1.-Enemy trade. Gliina.. Enemy aliens.Cuba. Prohibition of sailings to Mexico.Prance. -M. Thomas and the New Socialist group.   German propaganda.   July 4th. Italy. Negotiations for enemy ships in Spain. Panama. United States and the political situation.Portugal. Position of the Government.   Portugal and Great Britain.   Portugal and the Vatican. Si am.-Tin mining royalties.United States. -British propaganda in the United States: the British, army : Ireland. Enemy Group.Austria-Hungary. Convocation of the Reiehsrat. The resignation of the Austrian -Cabinet. The Austrian offensive. Allied pronouncements regarding Czecho-Slovaks and Jugo-Slavs. Poles and Czechs.   Hungary : reported request for recall, of Germans.Germany. Present attitude towards the war. Von Kuhlmann&apos;s speech. Study of, and propaganda regarding, Allied peace and economic policy. Central Powers and the Ukraine. Purchases of cotton in Turkestan. Purchases of rubber from Russia through  inland. Purchases of iron pyrites in Spain:   Exploitation of Bulgaria.   Germany and the Black Sea.   Mark exchange.Neutral Group.Chile. Chilean neutrality.Denmark. Scandinavian Conference.    Butter.Finland. Finland and the North.    Finland, and  Sweden.     Finnish-German treaties.     General situation.   Aland fortifications.   Interchange of supplies between Aland and Sweden.Mexico.  Pro-German activities.   Economic conditions.Netherlands. Projected convoy to Butch Bast Indies. Limburg railways. Exports to Germany. The Kurmicjin Begentes.Norway. Germany and Norwegian, shipping.   Spitsbergen.Peru. Announcement regarding British provision of aircraft to Chile.Spain.-German propaganda regarding Morocco, Gibraltar, Roman Catholicism, and neutral repre-sentation at the Peace Conference.   Tangier.   Strike at Malaga.Sweden. General conditions.   Imports of metals and hemp from Russia.Vatican.  I re la ncl.Peace Discussions (classified in text).(33)fi07S--lp   PL-       500   7/18   K &amp; S
PART II. FOREIGN AND GENERAL.GENERAL.Sinkings.-According to the War Trade Intelligence Bureau, the total tonnage of 500 tons gross in the case of steamers, and 100 tons gross in the case of sailing ships, reported lost owing to the malice of the King&apos;s enemies during the period June 21st-27th, inclusive, was 11,976 tons gross, of which 31,028 were British, as compared with 39,079 tons gross, of which 19,116 were British, reported last week.Far East. The War Cabinet learns that, consequent on an attempt by the Bolshevists to send munitions westward, a general disarmament took place on June 28th at Vladivostock. Some of the principal members of the Soviet were arrested. The only resistance offered by the Bolshevists was made by a band of. Red Guards, who were ultimately overcome after a lively encounter in which 10 Czechs were killed. A Coalition Siberian Government has declared, itself and has met with the sympathy and support of the population. The town is at present in the occupation of the Czechs. In addition to the Japanese and British patrols, landing parties were sent from Russian and American ships for the protection, of general interests. Mr. Hodgson reports that the Czechs&apos; National Council has requested the Allied Consuls to represent to their Governments the necessity of assisting the Czech troops in Western Siberia, who are threatened by enemy prisoners in conjunction with Bolshevist forces. The Allied Consuls at Irkutsk confirm&quot; that these troops are endangered. Reports from Western Siberia combine to indicate that only by the overthrow of the Bolshevists will the whole of Siberia be saved from. German penetration ; the opinion is expressed that Bolshevist power is maintained solely by the enemy prisoners. (Mr. Lockhart reports that the Bolshevist Government, as a result of German pressure, contemplates replying to the establishment of Allied forces at Murmansk by a declaration of war. Mr. Lindley considers that, though the Bolshevist leaders may fall, there is still a strong feeling in favour of the system of government by Soviet.) Air. Lockhart reports upon the admirable spirit and discipline and. intelligence of the Czechs, who are comparable with French troops. The Foreign Office is informed that public opinion in Washington appreciates increasingly the practical importance of the Siberian problem. The British, French, and Italian representatives on the Supreme War Council are com-communicating to their Ambassadors in Washington certain unanimous recommendations for the consideration of president Wilson.Hospital Ships. The Foreign Office has notified His Majesty&apos;s Representatives in the Neutral States of Europe of the torpedoing on June 27th by a German submarine of the British Hospital Ship Handovery Castle, with the loss of 234 out of 258 lives ; this being the fourth case in the present,year alone in which a hospital ship) has been deliberately sunk without warning in waters in which the German Government has undertaken that hospital ships shall be respected.Reported Employment of Allied Prisoners in Berlin Streets. The Foreign Office is enquiring into a report, received from a good source, that British and French prisoners are being employed to sweep the streets of Berlin, and that they are there subjected to abuse by the populace.ALLIED  GROUP.BELGIUM.Germany and Flanders. German Wireless of June 27th observes : &quot; In connection with the already reported declaration of the Council of Flanders (see Report  No.   74   and   Reports  therein  cited),   containing  the  demand   tor   the
-establishment of a Flemish State with its own administration and own Parliament, the Iiolnische Zeitung publishes an article which, says :-&apos; Such a separation of. Flanders and Wallonia, rendering them independent, naturally would not prevent the two States from entering into an agreement together which would make it possible for them, to regulate by means of a mutual legislature those affairs which -especially need regulation on account of the close economic relations -between, them.. Idle example of Austria-Hungary in. this case shows perhaps a possible way. For Germany such a regulation would bring about a &quot;real guarantee&quot; that the present French influence in. Belgium would be pushed to the background. Thus also for Germany one of the absolutely necessary guarantees mentioned by the Imperial Chancellor, Count Hertling, in his speech of February 25th, 191.8, will have -been established, namely, that this country shall not be used against us as a territory for the advance of our enemies. For a free Flanders, constructed on Germanic principles, just as for Germany, it is a life interest to keep the French or the English army from her frontiers. Eroteetive measures against this indirectly also protect Flanders. In an economic sense such an independent Flanders would, however, need to lean on the German Empire because of natural conditions. Firmly defined stipulations of the peace treaty must render this approachment easier and guarantee it lastingly. They must also include Wallonia, whose economic force neither Flanders nor Germany wish to, or can, do without. This does not prevent that the two States should establish and develop their political life in accordance with their own. wishes. No annexation, no forcible Germanisation of blanders no, a blenders free and Flemish in close economic relation with her natural hinterland, Germany, is an aim ecpially worth both striving for, and. one which will serve the welfare of all parties interested.&apos; &quot;German Economic Pressure. Sir w. Townley learns that on account of the great destitution in the occupied regions of Belgium, (and Northern France) there is a danger that the population may be forced into the service of Germany. (And see Reports Nos. 67, 68, 70, 71 and 7-1.)BRAZIL.Enemy Trade. According to the Brazilian Bress, steps are being taken by the Brazilian Minister of Finance for the registration of German firms and companies in Brazil ; returns are required of name, capital, nature of business, domicile of the concern and its branches, nationabty aud holdiug of partners and shareholders individually, and details of assets. This would seem to be an extension of the registration of German subjects which has been in force since a state of war was declared.   It is thought possible that the measure foreshadows sequestration.CHINA.Enemy Aliens. The statement by the German Foreign Minister in the Reichstag that the Anglo-German Conference at The Hague lias put an end to the idea of deporting Germans from. China is reported by Sir W. Townley to be untrue. The German Delegates Pave been informed in writing that the matter is outside the terms of reference of the British Delegates, who understand, however, that the proposal is in suspense. The German delegates have now requested a promise that such deportation shall not lie effected. Sir J. Jordan reports that the Chinese &quot;Government is at present preparing to intern the more important enemy aliens at Fangshan and Chusan Island. Sir J. Jordan, expresses the opinion that the most effective place would be the Island of Linkungtao at Wei-hai-Wei. The general question is, however, still under discussion.CUBA.Prohibition of Sailings to Mexico. Mr. Leech reports that under orders issued by the President of the Cuban Republic, Cuban vessels have been prohibited from going to Mexico ; nor. is coal to be provided for any Spanish vessel intending to proceed to Mexico.-   (And see Reports Nos. 70-72 under &quot; Mexico.&quot;)
FRANCE. ..M. Thomas and the New Socialist Group. The French Press of June 25th announces the adhesion of Ah Albert Thomas, formerly Minister of Munitions, to the Right Wing of the Socialist Party headed by Ah Varenne (see Reports Eos. 68 and 72).. Great satisfaction is expressed by the Iloinmc Libre and the Gaulois. The Echo-de Paris (June 28th) states that at the demand of several sections of the Unified Socialist Party, Af. Albert Thomas will be summoned to appear before a committee from the Party. The former Minister is reproached with having, in agreement with M. &quot;Ribot, rejected Austria&apos;s peace proposals without first taking the. opinion of the Cabinet. M. Thomas is also blamed by some members of the Party for his participation in the.Congress of Oppressed Nationalities, his statements regarding peace, and finally, his adhesion to tire new &quot; forty &quot; group of Socialists.German Propaganda.  German Wireless of June 27th proclaims as follows the decline of French man-power as compared with, that of Angio-Saxondom :  &quot; France&apos;s sinking national strength is no longer able to balance the ravages of the war. Under Napoleon, France possessed more inhabitants than Great Britain and the United States together. In the period of the Second Empire she Avas behind these two countries, but at least surpassed England. But after 1871 this superiority also-disappeared, while the inhabitants of the countries of the Anglo-Saxon race increased to three or four times the French population. After the world Avar England and the United States will number almost 160 millions, France at the utmost 36 millions. France, which a century ago railed the history of the world, will in future range after Italy.&quot; Propaganda on similar lines in regard to the respective economic resources of France and the Anglo-Saxons is;quoted under &quot; Germany.&quot;July 4A. Lord Derby reports that a proposal for the celebration of July 4th as a French National fete has been, enthusiastically accepted by the Chamber and &quot;Senate.&apos;    &apos; ITALY.Negotiations for Enemy Ships in Spain. The Foreign Office instructs Sir a. llardinge that His Majesty&apos;s Government has no objection to the resumption of negotiations by an intermediary for acquisition on behalf of the Italian Government of enemy ships (other than those required by the Swiss Government see Report No. 72) in Spanish ports.   (See also Report No. 58.)PANAMA.United States and the Political Situation. Sir 0. Mallet reports that in the complicated situation resulting from the death of President &apos;Yaldez (see Report No. 72), the Vice-President took the course of postponing the elections indefinitely in order to avoid the possibility of a defeat on June 30th. In the view of the Opposition and of the United States Government such an order was unconstitutional, justifying military intervention for the maintenance of order at the elections, which the former were determined to bold, and which the latter unsuccessfully pressed the Vice-President to permit. Consequently, on the afternoon of June 29th United States troops occupied Colon and Panama.PORTUGAL.Position of the Government. In a despatch dated June 7th Sir L. Carnegie reported that no date had yet been fixed, for the meeting of -the Parliament elected
last April. The President is stated to don bt how far the -Assembly will approve the Constitution which he has formed and the powers lie has assumed. The allegiance of the army, on which he depends, is uncertain. Meanwhile his opponents continue to plot against him ;. a fresh revolution, fixed for June 3rd, was nipped in the bud by the Government, which arrested hundreds of persons in Lisbon and the provinces. The alarm was great, and has caused the Monarchists to rally again to the support of the President, whose fall (as they know well) would bring disaster upon them, ddie difficulties of the Government were increased by a strike on the principal railways from Lisbon to the North, which began on June 4th and ended on-June 6th. It was no doubt fostered by political agents in connection with the projected rising-, but the alleged cause was the discontent provoked hy a regime arbitrarily imposed not-long-ago by Sen Lor Machado Santos, Secretary of State for Supplies and Transports. The Portuguese Press of June 8th announces the resignation of this Minister. The prestige of the Government has also been adversely affected by a transaction (resulting in the resignation of the Secretary of State for Finance) by which the Government purchased at an unaccountably high price 33,500 shares in the Portuguese Railways Company, through the intermediary of an unknown group headed by the Commercial Bank of Oporto.Portugal and Great Britain. ddie notification of the1 intention of His Majesty&apos;s Government eventually to raise His Majesty&apos;s Legation at Lisbon to the rank of an Embassy has been received with general satisfaction by the Portuguese Press. A. Monarchist paper, however, describes the change as &quot; an honour without advantage,&quot; and the organ of . the ultra Democrats, 0 Mundo, has ignored the announcement altogether.Portugal and, the Vatican. Sir L. Carnegie reports that the Papal. Nuncio at Madrid is visiting President Paes with friendly messages from the Vatican. It is probable that diplomatic relations between the Portuguese Government and the Vatican will result. This, in the opinion of the Portuguese Foreign Minister, will have an important effect on Portuguese internal, affairs, but will not affect foreign policy.SLAM. -Tin Mining Royalties. Sir Id. Bering draws attention to a complaint by the British, ddn Alining Company of the high royalties levied by the Siamese Government, and. suggests various grounds upon which representations might be made in the matter.   -UNITED STATES.British. Propaganda in the United States: the. British, Army: Ireland. A Memorandum (G.T. 4954) dated June 25th, intimates the desirability of giving wider publicity in the Linked States to the true proportions of the fighting done and losses incurred in France by troops from the United Kingdom. Reporting on the discontent or disappointment still felt in various circles in the United States over the latest pronouncements of British policy in regard to Ireland, Mr. Bayley suggests the importance of emphasising the existence of two antagonistic Irish Parties and the anxiety of England to compose their differences. (In a despatch dated May 30th, Lord Reading observes: &quot;The traditional friendship of America for Ireland dies hard, but there are already evidences in the Press of a growing impatience with Ireland. Most of the leading articles in the Eastern Press refuse to discuss Ireland&apos;s so-called &apos; wrongs.&apos; Their attitude is well exemplified in the following&apos; extract from an article- contributed by ex-President Taft to the Philadelphia Public Ledger: &apos; ddie sympathies of the United States were with the Nationalists represented by Redmond &apos; till his death, ddie pleasure with which the American people heard of his earnest efforts to recruit the British Army extended to most of our citizens of Irish origin. American sympathy has not been with the Clan-na-Gael, the Physical Force party of the Irreconcilables of the Sinn Fein variety. If there were any doubt about this at any other time there can be no doubt now. Now the intense patriotism of the American people is being roused by the great.war, they feel the overwhelming necessity for the concentration of all our national energies and of those of our Allies to bring the Hohenzollern dynasty to its knees.007;: it) I B
The quarrels in Ireland, the difficulties and blunders of. the British Government;, the equities of the Irish Nationalists, the obstinacy of the Unionists of Ulster do not rouse our active interest. What we seek is a war of effectiveness from every part of the United States, of Great Britain, of France, and Italy, to hold back the German scourge and. to stamp out German militarism and. lust for world-power. We cannot stop to listen and discuss an incidental question when, the one overshadowing issue is whether we can avert the black threat of German domination. This would, make hopeless not only Ireland&apos;s future, but that of all the countries engaged in this struggle for Christian civilisation. We hope that, the Administration, if called upon, will make clear the real attitude of our people.&apos; &quot;) And. see under &quot; Vatican.&quot;ENEMY GROUP.AUSTRIA-HUNGARY.Convocation of -the Tteiehsrat. According to a Vienna telegram of -Bine 29th, the Emperor Karl has informed the Austrian Prime Minister of his intention to convoke the Eeichsrat for July 16th.The Resignation of the Austrian Cabinet. A. Memorandum (G.T. -1-990) by the Political Intelligence Department discusses the recent resignation of the Austrian Cabinet,   (See.Report No. 74.)The Austrian Offensive. According to a report received by the Foreign Office, the Austrian offensive upon the Italian front was undertaken, by the Austrian Government (in order to influence the internal situation.) contrary to the wishes of the Germans, who had. designed thai, it should take place later as part of a general scheme, Relations between the two countries are stated to have become, for this reason, still, further embittered. Another report communicates a German opinion (which, may perhaps reflect the views of the General Stall) that, since it is impossible for Germany to go continually to the help of her various Allies, the best course in present circurn-stances will, be to concentrate upon some achievement in the West (such as the capture of Paris), which, in addition to other advantages, would impress her Allies with her strength.    (And see under &quot;Germany.&quot;)Allied 1&apos;ronouvcements regarding Czecho-Slovaks and Jugo-Stiivs. The following statement was issued on dune 28th by Mr. Lansing: &quot;Since the issuance by this Government on May 29th of the statement regarding the nationalistic aspirations for freedom of the Czecho-Slovaks and Jugo-Slavs, German and Austrian officials and sympathy have sought to misinterpret and distort its manifest interpretation. In order that there may be no misunderstanding concerning the meaning of the statement, the Secretary of State has to-day further announced the position of the United States Government to be that all branches of the Slav race should be completely freed from German and Austrian rule.&quot; German Wireless of July 3rd quotes the Stockholm Dagblad of July 1st as disparaging this announcement.On the occasion of the presentation (on June.1st) of Colours to Czeelio-Slovak troops in France, Mr. Ballonr has telegraphed to M, PicliOn assuring him of the recognition by His Majesty&apos;s Government of the wide significance of the occasion, as representing &quot; a stage in the struggle for the freedom of small nations, and not least of those who in all parts of the Austro-Hungarian Empire live under the tyranny of an alien minority. In this great cause ail the Allies are concerned ; and we rejoice to think that side by side with them are to be found not merely Czecho-Slovaks, but Jngo-Slavs and Poles bravely fighting in the cause of freedom.&quot;Poles and Czechs. A report received by the Foreign Office indicates that there &apos; is now a very considerable co-operation between the Poles and Czechs in Austria, and that the influence of the Austrophil Poles is declining.
Hungary : He/ported Request for Recall of Germans. -According to a report-received by the Foreign Office, the Hungarian Government has represented to the German Government that the Hungarian people requests the recall of all German officers and. men. from Hungary.G RE MANY.Present Attitude towards the War. The opinion of three German professional men of some importance as to the present attitude in Germany regarding the war is reported as follows to the Foreign Office : They agree that the recent offensive on the Western front has yielded, very disappointing results in spite of some spectacular successes. The losses, especially in the last attack on the French, have been exceedingly heavy, and. educated-people have begun to understand that the offensive will never bring peace. The General Staff, on the other hand, are absolutely determined, to go on. They expect that the war will last several years yet, and their imaginations are fired by the prospect of invading India through Persia. (Another report also expects an early resumption of the offensive, and states that German military circles rely upon the return, of prisoners to balance American reinforcements in 1,919. It is argued that, though the Allies will be numerically superior in 1920, they will not accomplish more than in 1.910, and that it will be found economically impossible to carry on the war beyond that time.) There is much speculation as to what Ludendorff will do next. Many think that his next stroke will be determined by political rather than by military considerations. It is thought that he will make a push in the direction of Paris and then offer the French alluring terms of peace as soon as their capital is threatened. Put the more general opinion is that he will strike for Calais and the Channel ports. This plan is regarded as the more promising if it can be carried out. Also it satisfies popular hatred of the English. Immediately Ludendorff has finished everyone expects a new peace-offensive to he launched. The General Staff are determined that its terms shall be unacceptable by the Allies, and. no sensible man believes in its success. The people, however, need, encouragement, and the Government are nervous about the success of the ninth war loan, which is to be launched next August. Hence arrogant peace proposals, will be made, probably by Hertling- in person. Something must be done, because both the political and economic situation are graver than they have been at any time since the beginning of. the war. Although the Reichstag is outwardly united, Radical, currents are gaining strength both in the Centre and Progressive Parties, in the Centre, Erzberger still counts for something, though the real force is the Catholic Labour leader, Giesberts. He dins into the ears of the Centre Party managers that they will lose their hold on the masses unless they adopt a Radical policy, which will compete in attractiveness with the Socialist policy. Similarly, there is a probability of a definite split in the Progressive Party. Many of the intellectuals of the party, especially those outside the Reichstag, are disgusted at the sycophantic attitude of the party leaders; and Maximilian Harden is at the head of an extremely clever extra-parliamentary move-ment for reforming the party in a Radical direction. A skilfully disguised propaganda is carried on with great effect. The economic danger, however, is far more serious than the political. . Food conditions are very serious (this is corroborated in the report above interpolated, which also mentions the prevalence of considerable depression). The Bavarian expert, Dr. Georg I hum, has declared that the supply of flour will not last beyond next August. The weather has recently been exceptionally cold. The crops, especially the potato crop, will be at least three weeks late this season. The lack of agricultural labour has been seriously enhanced by the in sub-ordination of the Russian prisoners of war, who have become infected with Bolshevism. They have to be guarded much more strictly than used to be the case, and cannot be sent out to work in large squads. No one now believes in the possibility of corn from the Ukraine. It is known that the brutal conduct of the German officials has thrown the whole country into seething revolt. The authorities now realise what a mistake they made, hut now it is too late to change. (And see under &quot; Austria-Hungary.&quot;)Yon Kuhlmann&apos;&apos;s Speech.. Referring to the speech made by the German Foreign. Secretary on June 24th, in which, he referred to the possible prolongation of the war beyond next year and the necessity of supplementing military with diplomatic efforts,
sGerman Wireless of June 26th (Serial. No. 0150) observes that these statements have been explained by tlie Imperial Chancellor (in his speech of June 26th) as not signifying any weakening of the German confidence in a decisive victory. Serial No. 5.157 of the same date quotes the Neue Freie Presses description of von Kuhhnanibs speech as &quot;an avowal of the understanding of peace. The Secretary &quot; of State showed the very deep reasonableness of the German people, which, after its &quot; great successes, offers to her enemies the hand of conciliation.&quot;Study of, and Propaganda, regarding, Allied Peace aud Economic Policy. The Foreign Office learns that the Germans have established a special bureau at The Hague to follow the indications of the British Press regarding the attitude of the Empire towards peace and a post-war economic offensive. German Wireless of June 27th observes: &quot;Lyons Wireless of June 19th praises the Anglo-American domination of raw materials, which threatens Germany with a lasting boycott and says, &apos; it will remain under the just Anglo-American control, and for that very reason the United States, together with England, will be the arbiters of the world&apos;s shipping&apos; and of the employment of raw materials.&apos; The French author may safely leave the care for Germany&apos;s future to Germany. Middle Europe, with. Asia Minor and the whole of Russia, that is to say, three-quarters of the European Continent, are for ever withdrawn from any interference of the Anglo-Saxons. France, of course, and also the other satellites of the Anglo-Saxons will be subject to their domination over foodstuffs, raw materials, finance, and transport routes. France could not for four days resist the pressure which the Central Powers have been resisting for almost four years. As the Cri de Paris admits, France would immediately succumb without resistance to an Anglo-Saxon blockade. The French author therefore rightly emphasises the superiority of the Anglo-Saxon Powers. What a contrast with the times when France fought successfully against England in every part of the world for the place of first Power in the world ! &apos;.&apos;   (See also under   France.&quot;)Central Powers and the Ukraine.- A Memorandum (G.T. 5010), dated July 1st, by the Political Intelligence Department, discusses the conflicting policies of the German Militarists and. Austria regarding the Ukraine, and the unsettled relations between that country and Russia.Purchases of Collou in Turkestan. By telegram dated June 14th from Moscow, the Foreign Office was informed that cotton was being purchased in Turkestan by a German agent, but that hostile bands were preventing its transport to Krasnovodsk. (Russian Wireless of June 28th instructs &quot;Smirnoff&quot; at Tashkent to facilitate the transmission &quot;to places as indicated&quot; of cotton stored at Krasnovodsk.)Purchases of Rubber from Russia through Finland. A report received Indicates that considerable quantities of rubber and rubber goods are being sold by an important Petrograd firm to Finland, where they are regularly secured by the Germans.Purchases of Iron Pyrites in Spain. A. report received mentions a German offer for Spanish iron pyrites to be delivered after the war against payment in Swiss francs.Exploitation of Bulgaria.- It is reliably reported, that Germany has obtained a fifty-year lease on the Bulgarian coal mines ; also a monopoly of all railway and harbour construction in Bulgaria for a period of ten j^ears, to date from the conclusion of peace.Germany and the Black. Sea. The Ranneulro reports a rumour that Krupps have purchased the Nikolaev shipyards.Mark Exchange. During the week ending June 25th there was a rapid fall of the Mark Exchange in neutral countries. The exchange on Amsterdam fell from 87 &apos; 15 on June 19th to 34&apos;65 on June 25th. The exchange on Zurich fell during the same period from 75&apos; 30 to 68&apos; 00 ; at Copenhagen, from 60&apos;00 to 55&apos;00; at Stock-holm, from 54&apos; 40 to 49&apos; 00 ; at Christiania, from 60&apos; 00 to 55&apos; 50. This general fall is apparently due to the Austrian offensive, and to von KuhlmamPs speech in the Reichstag.
rTEUTKAL GROUP.CHILE.Chilean Neiitrglily. German Wireless of June 20th reports: &quot;The Vossische Zeitung learns that the President of Chile read a message at the opening of Congress which said : &apos; With quite especial care, inspired by a high sense of justice as to the international, duty of the Republic, we have continued to develop our friendship and trade relations with, other countries of the world, ddie world war, which is destroying the living forces of the great nations friendly to Chile, and the prolongation of which all Chilians deeply regret, induced the Government to follow a strictly neutral, policy, and this has been rigidly followed hitherto and will continue to be followed, ddiis line of conduct in regard to our attitude I shall follow with the greatest determination, and f cherish the hope that nothing will happen to disturb our peace with foreign countries.&apos; &quot;DENMARK.Scandinavian Conference. ddie following official communique was issued at Copenhagen on June 28th: &quot; At the invitation of the Danish Government, meetings took place here from June 26th to 28th of the Danish Minister of State, the Danish Minister of Foreign Affairs, and the Scandinavian Ministers. A certain number of questions were discussed concerning the common interests of the three countries. All were in absolute agreement concerning the preservation of friendly and intimate relations between the three countries and the pursuit of the same fine of conduct, that is to say,&apos; a policy of impartial, neutrality. Thus, the subjects treated comprised one question already touched upon at former meetings, namely, the collaboration between neutral States in order to safeguard their common interests at the end of the world war and. afterwards. Idle Governments continue to exchange views on this subject on the basis of the reports of the committees instituted, by the three countries concerned. Information was also given relative to the development of the situation of the three countries as regards their commercial policy during recent times, ddie good results of the economic agreement of the three countries during the war were noted with much satisfaction, as well as measures taken for the continuation and development of this work. On the basis of experience already acquired, agreement was reached regarding the means of collaboration on this subject also after the Avar, ddie question of collaboration between the three Scandinavian countries on a political and social basis was also discussed, and an address from, the inter-Parliamentary Council, gave rise to the decision to nominate representatives from the Governments to study the possibility of such a collaboration, ddie two following questions were also discussed, namely, the steps to be taken concerning restrictions to be imposed upon the admission of foreigners into the three countries, because of the difficulties of order, provisioning, and residence. It was agreed to try to institute corresponding regulations as regards the question of knowing in what cases foreigners should he taxed. Finally, as at previous meetings, there was perfect agreement concerning the advantage of continuing the fruitful collaboration of the three Governments for their common interests.&quot;Butter. In view of the imminence of Danish-German negotiations (sec Report No. 74), and of the continually increasing insistence by Germany on a larger share of Danish butter, Sir R. Paget suggests the desirability of an early decision regarding British purchases thereof. At present Germany is receiving 49 per cent, of the exportable surplus, including two-fifths of the share distributable to Great Britain-. The remaining 51 per cent., including three-fifths of the British share, is going to Norway and Sweden, ddie Swedish Press of July 1st announces that negotiations will soon take place regarding the renewal of the commercial treaty between Denmark and Sweden, as the present treaty ceases to be valid at the end of July. It is said that the price of Danish export butter will probably be raised..     FINLAND.Finland and the North. On June 27th the Finnish Charge d&quot;Affaires in Stockholm handed to Sir E. Howard a formal statement of the Finnish claim (underG07:&apos;.-li- C
.1.0a Russian decree of February loth, .1864) to a certain part of the Murmansk coast, coupled with a protest against British assistance oi Bolshevist bands and Finnish rebels who had opposed the assertion of this claim, and a demand for the cessation of such assistance and the immediate recall of. the British troops. Sir E. Howard pointed out that (1) the Russian decree referred also to the alternative of rectification of the Southern Finnish frontier ; (2) not only British forces, hut French also, had occupied the Murmansk coast, and such occupation had been effected by agreement, with all. the Allies.; (3) the present, note, which amounted to an ultimatum, was of the most serious moment ; and (4) if Finland were driven by Germany into overt hostilities against the Allies (who were most benevolently disposed towards her) she must not look for their goodwill, when the time arrived for a general settlement. The Swedish Press reports that the Germans have practically threatened to place Finland under a German Military Governor unless the Diet accepts the Monarchy Bill. (According to the local Bolshevist organ at Murmansk, M. Passikivi has been appointed Minister President of Finland, and in declaring himself a Monarchist has stated that the Diet does not agree to re-establish the Monarchy, but that this will be done by the troops. The paper adds that on. this ground conflicts have taken place, amongst both, the civil, population, and. the White Guards, ft is reported in Karelia that civil war has broken out between Monarchists and Republicans and. that a Bourgeois Republican Green Guard has been formed, from amongst the White Guards.) A most severe censorship lias been introduced, and drastic restrictions have been placed upon the use of railways. Sir E. Howard sees in these measures, and in the German insistence upon the prosecution of Finnish, claims to the Murmansk coast, the determination of Germany to secure her hold over the country and to compromise it beyond rehabilitation with the Allies. Owing to the unwillingness of Finnish troops to participate in operations against Murmansk, the Germans are collecting volunteers so that the Finnish Govern-ment can later on disown responsibility and protest its neutrality. It is reported that active preparations continue for a military expedition, and that, from. S,000 to 10,000 additional German troops have recently arrived in Finland. According to one statement an expedition was begun on June 26th. According to information from Russia, the Germans are mobilising near Pskov, probably with the Object of occupying Petrograd and the railway to Vologda concurrently with the advance from Finland against the Murmansk line. Svenska Dagbladet learns front Helsingfors that a revolt against the Bolshevists has broken out in the Government of Olonetz, and that the rebels who have seized the town of Olonetz are demanding help from Finland. Novaya Zhizn of June 18th mentions German forces as being in this neighbourhood. The Bolshevist Official Gazette reports from Moscow that a German submarine flying the Finnish flag has been observed in Fake Ladoga. A further report from Helsingfors (see also Report No. 74) indicates that in Finnish military circles war with the Allies is thought to be inevitable. Sir F. Howard considers that such an eventuality would not, be likely seriously to affect Allied relations with Sweden, at any rate so long as the present administration remains in power.Finland and Sweden. Svenska Dagbladet learns from Helsingfors that tlie Constitution Committee of the Finnish Landtag has resolved by a majority of 10 to 7 to propose the rejection of the clauses in the New Constitution securing linguistic and cultural rights to the Swedish element in Finland. The rejection of a proposal to form special Swedish-speaking units in the army was also moved by a majority of I. It is said that Senators Ren wall and Arthur Castren will resign. Svenska. Dagbladet&apos;s own correspondent telegraphs that the Swedish Landtag group will attempt to cause tin; resignation of the Senate if the proposals of the Committee are adopted, as the Swedish element will refuse to recognise the Constitution if these clauses are omitted. The paper observes that great indignation will be caused in Sweden, and. threatens reprisals in the form of a less yielding attitude on the Aland question.Finnish-German Treaties.- German Wireless of June 26th reports the ratification on June 25th at Berlin of the peace treaty and the Trading and Shipping Agreements concluded between Germany and Finland on March 7th. (See. also Report, No. 59, and, for particulars, the Daily Review (N.P.S.) of June 28th.)
General Situation. In a memorandum (G.T. 4015) dated June 19th, the Political Intelligence Department discusses the main political problems regarding Finland.A land Fortifications. An official communique in the Swedish Press of June 27th states : &quot; An agreement having been reached between the Swedish, Finnish, and German Governments respecting the demolition of the fortifications on,Aland and the immediate opening of negotiations for the conclusion of an agreement regarding the carrying into effect of this demolition, the following are appointed Swedish delegates in these negotiations: Trolle, Provincial Governor; Sandgrerr, Permanent Under Secretary and Head of Department in. the Foreign Office; General. Sylvan, of the General Stall; Major Wibon, of the Coast Artillery ; and Major of Fortifications, Bjuggren. The Svensha Dagblad learns that the Finnish delegates will be M. Gripenberg, Charge d&apos;Affaires at Stockholm, and Colonel Hjellman, and that Germany will be represented, by the German. Naval Attache at Stockholm, Captain Reinhold von Fischer.Interchange of Supplies between Aland and Sweden. The Swedish Press reports that the Finnish Senate has granted the local authorities in Aland permission to export to Sweden in the next three months 75 tons of fresh iish as compensation for 59 tons of sugar and 209 tons of salt already received from Sweden,-    . MEXICO.Pro-German Activities. Mr. Thurstan reports that strong pro-German feeling-prevails along the Yucatan coast, where suspicious activities have been noticed.Economic Conditions. A report received states that, owing to abnormal drought in Mexico for the past three years, all foodstuffs are scarce, and maize, on. which the working classes absolutely depend, has risen to thrice its cost in pre-revolutionary times. The attitude of carranza has precluded him. from obtaining financial assistance from the United States, and German assistance has not sufficed to rectify the situation ; consequently taxation of mining and agriculture lias been raised, which the majority of the properties are unable to meet. All classes thus tend to be embittered against the present administration.And. see under &quot;Cuba.&quot;NETHERLANDS.Projected Convoy to Dutch. East Indies. With reference to the proposed Dutch Convoy to theEast Indies (see Reports Nos. 70-74) a Hague message of June 29th states that the Ministry for Foreign Affairs has issued the following official statement: &quot;As a result of the requisition of Dutch ships by the Associated Governments, there was a suspension of communication with the Dutch Indies, and the Government decided, in the interests of the service to those parts, to seize the opportunity presented by the departure of a warship to the Indies to form a convoy to enable the transport of Government officials and their families and also war supplies and Government merchandise. The principal object of the convoy was, in view of the prevailing insecurity of the seas, to assure a free passage and prevent the ships being taken into belligerent ports to exercise the right of examination. During the latter part of April the belligerent Powers received an advice of the composition of the convoy, as well as measures that had been taken. The Nether-lands Government offered, of its own free will, guarantees and proof that the transport would not affect the. military interests of the belligerents. The preliminary production of papers took place according to precedent on the principles which apply to an ordinary commercial convoy namely, that the flag only covers the cargo as long as such cargo does not consist of any merchandise forbidden by the belligerents, and that the commander- of the convoy shall be ready to produce&apos; manifests of cargo and other&quot;papers in case of a meeting with a belligerent warship. At the same time it was explained that it was not a cpiestion of an ordinary commercial convoy, but of an extraordinary kind of convoy serving exclusively for the conveyance of
passengers and Government merchandise, and was, therefore, purely a communication between die mother country and the colonies.    Before even tlie Dutch Governments communication had reached the Dutch Minister in London, the British Minister at The Hague, with regard to a statement made on. April 1.6th in the First Chamber&apos; of the States General by the Minister of Marine, delivered a Note on April 26th, explaining the British point of view, and stating that Great Britain had never recognised convoying as a right of neutrals.   This Note crossed the Dutch communication to the British Government, to whom the British Minister was referred.   It was not until June 8th last that the British Government replied to the above-mentioned communication addressed to it by the Netherlands Minister in London, &quot;formally maintaining its attitude not to recognise ,,the right of convoying.   Nevertheless, the British Government announced its intention as a tangible proof of its friend-ship for Holland, not to create difficulties in the way of the convoy, in certain conditions, in view of the fact that the Netherlands Government had probably already announced, that it would despatch the convoy.   The Netherlands Govern-ment --replied  that what   the British Government,  termed   conditions  practically accorded with   its   intentions,  as   was   proved  by the guarantees  spontaneously given by her which showed that there, was nothing to hide from, the belligerents concerning the character of the convoy and its cargo.   The list of cargo of the steamer Noordam was not ready until June 14th, immediately after which date the  list was  communicated to the interested Ministers at The Hague,  while  the opportunity was afforded them to examine the list of passengers.   On June 17th a list was also delivered to them of the merchandise which was on board the auxiliary cruiser Tabanau, and the collier Bengkalis.   In the meantime the date of  the convoy&apos;s sailing was fixed for June 19th.   On -June 1.8th the British. Minister, by order of his Government, objected that although it was understood that no goods of German origin should be carried, the Noordam. contained dyestuffs of purely German origin, as was indicated by the communication of the Netherlands Government oil-June 4th.   The contents of this communication reached the British Government after the latter had made known its point of view concerning the convoy to the Dutch. Minister in London.   The British. Government now announced that it would, only not oppose the carriage of these German dyestuffs if it coidd lie shown that this material could not be obtained from countries other than those with whom it was at war, and referred to a letter from the British Legation of April 28th, 1.918, asking for information concerning the quantities of dyestuffs annually imported by the Dutch. Indies in order to ascertain the possibility of obtaining these articles from other countries than, those at war with Great Britain.   A reply was made to this letter on May 23rd, and the information demanded was furnished.   The British Ministers Note was replied to the following day to the effect that dyestulfs should not be regarded of themselves as among those things the British Government regarded as merchandise of enemy origin since, in connection Avith these products, a special agreement had existed for a long-time, permitting the free transport of them to the Dutch Indies, provided that they were consigned to the Government of the Indies, and. were distributed by it, and the principle was reaffirmed in a letter from&apos; the British Legation on June 20th, 19.10, and in a Note from the Netherlands Minister on June 26th, 1.9.10.   The above-mentioned letter from the British Legation of April 20th. contained only a request for information in view of an examination which was being conducted by the British Government. It in nowise altered the existing agreement.   In a, memorandum of June 19th the British Legation requested still further information, which was procured for it. Considering   that   the   very   decisive   opposition   of   the   British   Government concerning dyestulfs is based on the interpretation of an existing comrention, the Netherlands Government does not care to assume the responsibility for despatching the convoy before the existing differences have been cleared tip.   Seeing that a telegram, received on Saturday, June 29th, from the British Government, indicated, that an agreement cannot be reached, the convoy will sail after the removal of the dyestulfs.&quot;On June 25th the Netherlands Foreign Minister assured Sir \V. Townley that none of the merchandise (other than the dyestuffs) carried in any of the ships was of foreign origin or owed more than 25 per cent of its value to German labour. Sir YV. Townley, however, on information received, requested further particulars regarding certain consignments and passengers. The Dutch Press on the evening of July 2nd announced that the convoy would sail next day. Sir W. Townley, on protesting to the Foreign. Minister, was informed by him that the Netherlands Government had satisfied itself upon the matters in question ; that the Aloordam would sail on July 3rd
NORWAY.Germany and Norwegian Shipping. -The conditions which the Germans are seeking to impose upon Norwegian shipping companies in&apos; connection -with safe-conducts (see Report No.  72) seem designed to invalidate the operation of the6073-lb Hand die convoy on the 4th. Sir W. Townley pointed out that His Majesty&apos;s G-overn-ment had not been given an opportunity to express an opinion in the matter ; that it had made a very great concession in permitting the convoy to sail at all, and that if the prescribed conditions were not fulfilled the consequences might be most unfortunate. It was arranged that a further discussion should be held on July 3rd. The Foreign Minister is clearly alarmed about his own position; the Minister of Marine has already resigned, and the Prime Minister has explained this resignation as due to the opinion held by that Minister that the convoy should sail regardless of the objections raised by His Majesty !s Government ; this opinion, added the Prime Minister, was not shared by the Cabinet, It may he observed that the Queen has appointed the late Minister a Naval A ide-de-Oamp.Limburg Railways. The Netherlands Foreign Minister has handed to Sir W. Townley a Memorandum on the precautions taken by the Dutch Authorities to supervise traffic over the Limburg Railways. A Hague message of June 29th states : &quot; A semi-official reply to the British statement regarding the question of German traffic over the Limbing Railway argues that the Dutch Governments attitude is in no way in contradiction with, the spirit of accord reached with the Associated Governments. It protests that the Dutch Foreign MinisteFs original statement on tlie dispute with. Germany made it clear that the goods to lie transported were not restricted to goods for civil use in Belgium. The Government, it says, would have had no reason whatever specifically to exclude the transit of foodstuffs for army use if it were intended to exclude all goods for army use. The declaration made at the time by the Associated Powers that the conclusion of an arrangement with Germany would not give rise to fresh difficulties on their part, cannot possibly be interpreted in the sense that they had in view the restriction of transit of goods destined, for the civil population of Belgium. If that were so, where would the con-ciliatory attitude of the Associated Powers have been, seeing that there could have been no objection whatever to the transit through Limburg of such goods ? As regards goods other than the four categories which were specially excepted, from transit, the agreement with. Germany leaves no room, for making the transit of them -as, for example, timber dependent on special guarantees regarding their use.&quot; (Information received establishes that during the week ending dime 22nd there was an average of seven trains daily from Germany to Antwerp, carrying principally hay, straw, and wood.) Sir W. Townley submits the desirability of an early reply to the Dutch communique, making clear the extent of the concessions accorded by His Majesty&apos;s Government, and at the same time, the consistent opposition of the Associated Governments to the use of the railways for the carriage of certain commodities. (See also Reports Nos. 07, 73 and 74.) *Exports to Germany. The Netherlands Foreign Minister has informed Sir W. Townley that his Government does not consider the export of horses (see Report No. 72) to be contrary to the Hides Agreement. The Foreign. Office have instructed Sir AY. Townley to protest against this attitude, and to point out its probable effect on Dutch imports of hides and tanning materials. Sir W. Townley reports that the Germans, in their negotiations, are particularly insisting upon hides as a means of exchange. Other prospective exports to Germany include bone-grease, potatoes, cattle, and cheese. According to a semi-official statement, the Germans are threatening to prevent Dutch vessels from fishing for home consumption, unless Holland agrees to permit the export of fish to Germany.The &quot; Koningin RegentesT The Foreign Office learns that the German military authorities, greatly angered by the comments of the Dutch Press regarding the sinking of the Koningin Regentes (see Reports Nos. 72-74).are designing to work up a newspaper campaign in Holland against alleged violations of Dutch neutrality by British airmen.
Nbrwegian-American Agreement (see Reports Nos. 68 and. 70); the Associated Governments are therefore consulting with a view to appropriate action. -Spitzbergen. A. Memorandum (G.T. 4997), dated June 29th, summarises certain considerations regarding Spitsbergeni   (And see Reports Nos, 60 and 61.) And see under &quot; Denmark.&quot;PERU.Announcement regarding British provision of Aircraft to Civile. Mr. Rennie has made a statement to the Peruvian Government (in the sense recorded in Report No. 74), regarding the attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government.towards future relations between the South American. States. Great satisfaction has been, expressed by the President and the Foreign Minister, ddie latter has accordingly issued a communique to the Press identifying the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government with the principles recently enunciated by President Wilson, ddie announcement has been well received by the Press and the general public.   (See also Report No. 7&apos;3 under &quot; Chile.&quot;)SPAIN.German  Propaganda,   regarding Morocco,  Gibraltar,  Roman Catholicism, and Neutral Representation at the Peace Conference. German Wireless of June 29th remarks: :1 With regard to Spains participation in the peace negotiations the Swiss newspaper Nene  Zuericher Nachrichteu  writes: &apos;Having regard to the political situation in Europe there can be no doubt that the Central Powers will invite Spain to the peace negotiations.   The newspaper points out that Spain since April 1914 has been pushed back systematically in North Africa and that by the restoration of Spain in her historical regions of colonisation the rivalry in North Africa would at least be lessened. Moreover, Gibraltar is an. important point in the question of the freedom of the seas. If after the war Spain was re-established in. her old colonial rights in Morocco and were to give the European Great Powers an open door, the only possible understanding in the North African question would be reached,   ddie whole question has become acute because the French closed the harbours of Morocco to the. merchants and industrials of other countries:   ddie fundamental trouble  in the  Morocco crises consisted    of   the   secret   diplomatic   agreements   which   were    concluded,    in. almost   every  case   in addition to the- official treaties and   which were  disclosed later.   Therefore naturally the wishes  of  Spain,  with  regard   to  Morocco  and Gibraltar are strongly supported by the interested Central  Powers.&apos;   ddie  Swiss newspaper added   to these  representations further   considerations regarding  the question how the European neutrals could and must be allowed to take part in the Peace Conference,   ddie numerous questions which will have to be settled on the conclusion of peace concern the vital interests of all neutrals, such, for instance, as questions of Customs, commercial freedom, traffic-freedom, as well as reciprocity in. social guarantees and the freedom of the seas, and the exclusion of the possibilities of an ultimate economic war.   It is true that Lord R. Cecil in the English House of Commons proclaimed the exclusion of neutrals from the peace negotiations.   There-fore the idea of a combination of all neutrals is very important, and it must aim at bringing about that neutrals shall obtain the right of participation in these negotia-tions and that this right shall refer to certain questions in which they should have a voice&quot;.   Also from the Catholic point of view the exclusion, of neutrals  would be deplorable.   It is true that the solution of the Roman question might be settled on the conclusion of peace between Power and Power, but other questions, like that of freedom for missionaries, would then be neglected.&quot;   (And see Reports Nos. 62, 64, and 74.)Tangier. Sir 11. White reports the receipt by himself and. the French Represen-tative at Tangier of protests by the Spanish Government against the alleged infringement by British seaplanes of the neutrality asserted by the Spanish. Govern-ment for the Tangier zone.Strike at Malaga.  Mr. Villiers reports that a strike of dock labourers and carters began on June 28th at Malaga, which is expected to continue for some days, paralysing all. shipping in the harbour. It is probable that die Germans have provoked difficulties at this particular time in anticipation of the arrival of vessels to fetch lead.
SWEDEN.General Conditions.-A. Memorandum (GET. 5002), dated June 29th, reports on present, conditions in Sweden, ddie result oi the very severe food conditions is general apathy. How the Avar ends has become only a secondary consideration, people just live from day to day longing for the time when peace will come. Faith in German military stqieriority is still prevalent, but the clanger of economic domination by Germany is beginning to be realised, and business men, even some of those whose sympathies remain pro-German, appreciate the urgent necessity of an economic approach towards England, and the Allies. If the supplies promised by the Associated Powers materialise, the political situation is likely from the Entente point of vieAv to improve. Very noticeable is the hatred, of the Germans amongst the working classes. (Meanwhile the general anxiety for strict neutrality is indicated by the criticisms which the Swedish Press, both Conservative and Liberal, pronounces upon reports of pro-Ally utterances by Mr. Branting in England.)Imports of Metals and Hemp from Russia. ddie Swedish Press of July 1st reports the recent arrival from Petrograd of the S.S. Angermanland (Svea Line) with 115 tons of copper. It is stated that the S.S. Greta has left Petrograd for Stockholm with 500 tons of metals and hemp received in compensation for agricultural machinery.And. see under &quot; Denmark &quot; and &quot; Finland.&quot;THE   VATICAN.Ireland. Commenting on reports of Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s speech of June 25th upon the situation in Ireland, and particularly on the allusions to the opposition of the Roman Catholic Church to conscription, the Osservatore remarks : &quot; It is evident &quot; that these Avords of the Prime Minister refer exclusiAreIy to the attitude of the Irish &quot; clergy.&quot; . ddie Tempo observes that his statements &quot;could not be, as they appeared &quot; to be, applicable to the whole Church, since the Church that is the Holy See  &quot; not only has not defined its attitude towards this purely internal and. political Irish &quot; question, but has not even had an opportunity of pronouncing an opinion in regard &quot; to it,&quot;And see under &quot; Portugal,&quot; &quot; Spain,&quot; and &quot;United States.&quot;PEACE DISCUSSIONS.General. Rumours of a Germ an-Bolshevist agreement about Poland are again current, and again contradicted.   They haA^e reached a more circumstantial phase.Under Rumania, the reports about Bessarabia are of interest. German anxiety about the attitude of the British Empire towards the raw material problem, as affecting peace discussions, is indicated under Germany.Russia. The following reports have been received, referring to the Conference with the Ukraine&apos; at Kieff :--On June 22nd (received 28th) Mr. Wardrop reported a disagreement about frontiers. ddie Russian representatives protested that the Ukraine scheme deprives Russia of coal and metals&quot;, thereby making her economically dependent upon the Ukraine, and the Ukraine representatives claimed territory and railway control which would contain elements of future aggression. On June 27th, Russian Wireless announced- that the German Higher Command had agreed to form mixed commissions for the settlement of incidents occurring along the boundary line. Both parties agreed to a referendum about the frontiers among the populations of the disputed regions. The referendum Avould be carried out under the control of mixed commissions, after the ratification of the Peace Treaty, and after the armies of both sides had retired from the regions affected. On June 27th, German Wireless reported that an agreement had been come to as to the principle for the settlement of all1 A Memorandum by the Political lntelligeiice&quot;Department, dated July 1st, on recent events in the Ukraine, brings up to date the history of the Kieff negotiations, and draws the moral, as affecting the general war situation.    [G.T. 5010.]- Mr. Wardrop&apos;s report of June 2.1st, received subsequently (June 30th), gives details of the respective demands for foodstuffs and goods made by the Russians and the Ukrainians (Germans ?). 6073-It &apos;      E
conflicts about frontiers, after the war, by a Court of Arbitration. On June 28th, Russian Wireless gave a long account of the attitude of the Ukraine delegates, clearly designed to bring about delay in the negotiations. The President of the Russian Delegation announced that the Russians remain on the basis of international conventions and appealed to the Ukraine, as also belonging to. the family of nations, to submit themselves to these laws. At the same time he protested against acts of violence committed against the Russian authorities in the Don region, during the occupation of that region by the Ukrainians, quoting definite examples. On tlie same date, Russian Wireless announced details of the Russian and Ukrainian contentions about, the frontier lines, as marked on their respective maps. On duly 2nd, German. Wirelsss reported that the representative of the Ukraine Republic, Baron Steinheil, had just, arrived in Berlin, and bad made a statement to Press representatives to the effect that the future relations of the Ukraine towards Gejinany would take a form tending to &quot; federal relations,&quot; which, would be satisfactory to both sides.   He added that the Ukrainian policy Avas based upon German policy.On the subject of the Russian Black Sea war vessels, Mr. Wardrop forwarded a report from the Moscow Press on June 22nd, issued on M. OhicherirPs authority, that Germany promised not, to use the fleet returned to Sebastopol, and that she would restore it after the Avar ; she had also promised not to cross the demarcation line. Only on those conditions had she stopped her advance on Novorossisk. Ou June 22nd (received 25th) Mr. Wardrop forwarded a further Press report to tire effect that: the German demands for the Black Sea Fleet to lie sent to Sebastopol showed unmistakably that, the Germans intend to use it. With the Crimea as a naval, base, the Germans were everywhere masters on the Black Sea. English influence in Persia and Mesopotamia was thereby threatened. An intercepted Wireless message showed that the Soviet, by issuing an order to the Fleet to proceed to Sebastopol, had thereby committed suicide.On June 22nd (received 28th) Mr. Wardrop drew attention to a notice in the Official Journal, nationalising the whole petroleum industry. (No details are given, but it seems necessary to devote special attention to any developments, in view of the apparent German design to control the output of petroleum in Rumanian and Russian, territory, and also, if possible, in Southern Persia, in the hope of ultimately being in. a position to use such control as a weapon in the economic struggle, during the transition period following hostilities.)A report from Mr. Wardrop dated June 19th. (received 27th) gives the information that a German financial commission, representing the Ministries of Finance, Industry, and Food, was expected at. Petrograd in. a week. The same report quotes a. Press notice about the injustice of the German insistence upon the man for man principle in exchange of prisoners now that Russia and Germany Avere considered to be at peace.Poland.  On July 1st, Mr. Wardrop reported that M. Chicherin had published in tlie Press a denial of the statement that Germany had contracted a secret treaty with the Soviet Government of Russia, allowing Germany control over Poland, and annexation of the Dombrowo coal district and the Galiciah oil-fields. He added that the Soviet considered that Poland was forcibly torn from Russia, and the Polish. Regency Council is simply an organ of the German occupation, not representing the will of the Polish people.The Times of June 28th quoted from the Nations Voice of Cracow (June 18th) the text of an alleged secret convention concluded at Brest between the Bolshevists, and the Germans,   lire following is said to be the substance of that treaty : I. Polish policy shall be conducted by Germany. 11. The Russian  Government  jdedges   itself not  to  interfere  iu questions relating  to the organisation of Poland.III. The Council of Commissioners of the Russian people has the light, to remain in touch with the democratic and revolutionary clubs existing in Poland, sending there agitators whose names are on the lists of the German Information Bureaux at Petrograd and Warsaw. I A&quot;. The despatch of agitators to Germany and Austria shall be suspended by the Council of Commissioners.V. The Council of Commissioners shall exercise strict vigilance over the Polish national groups,in order to prevent their enlistment us &quot;volunteers in the territorial army iu Russia. VI. Russia shall consider the violation of the frontiers of Lithuania aud the Ukraine by Polish troops as a declaration of war on Germany and Austria, and Russia shall, aid in crushing such armies.VII. The Council must prevent Russian citizens from investing their own, or French, English, ar american capital in any industrial undertaking in Poland. VIII. The Council pledges itself to recognise the eventual new state of things created by Germany and Austria in Poland, and to defend it against the former Allies of Russia.
A Memoraiidum (June 27th) by the Political Intelligence Department, on the resignation of the Austrian Cabinet, contains interesting notes upon the effect upon the Poles of promises made to the Ukrainians at Brest-Litovsk about Eastern Galicia, and upon the Polish question generally, as affecting the situation in Austria-Hungarv. (G.T. 4990.)Rumania. On June 28th, German Wireless reported that in the sitting of the Chamber on June 25th the Rumanian Government presented the text of the Peace Treaty with the Central Powers. On June 29th, Lord Derby quoted a telegram from the Allied Ministers at J army, dated June 27th, which affects the German prospects of obtaining supplies from Rumania under the Bucharest Treaty. For various reasons stocks of food produce will be exhausted before the harvest, and prospects are poor about the likelihood of production sufficing for the needs of the Rumanian population.On. June 13th (received. July 2nd) Mr. Wardrop forwarded a report that, a delegation from Bessarabia had. arrived at Kieff desiring -to unite Bessarabia with the Ukraine, and begging the Austrian Embassy to bring about the removal from Bessarabia &quot;of the atrocious Rumanian armies, replacing them by Austrians.&quot; They added that Bessarabia can, by the autumn, supply IT million, poods of grain.[In view of the undoubted German control over the Ukraine, and possibly over Bessarabia, it is interesting to recall the telegram from 1VJ. MarghiIonian to Berlin, published abroad by German Wireless of April 1.1th, and quoted on page 17 of Western Report No. 04 : &quot;After conferences lasting 20 days, the Diet, of Bessarabia on April 9th solemnly accepted the union between Bessarabia and Rumania by 86 votes to 3, and. the union has been proclaimed in Rumania amidst indescribable enthusiasm. . . . Tremendous crowds.   Endless jubilation, &amp;c, &amp;c.&quot; !]Germany.  German Wireless of June 26th and 28th contains further reports of the debate in the Reichstag on von Kiildmanns recent pronouncement on German war aims.   These have been published and commented upon at length in the Press.In. connection with the British Empire control of raw materials in the economic struggle during the transition period following hostilities, and during peace discussions, it is important to note a cable from Sir W. Townley (June 26th) reporting the establishment, at the German Legation at The Hague of a special, department to watch for information published in the Press about the coming economic struggle, the attitude assumed by the nations of the British Empire as affecting this subject, and anything indicating a desire to make peace.On June 27th Sir 11. Rumbold reported, apparently from a reliable source, Ludendorff&apos;s desire lo control all unofficial peace advances, especially as affecting the Pan-German attitude. Von KuhhuanAs attitude in the Reichstag towards the prospects of a speedy and decisive victory on the Western front is said to be attributable to Ludendorff &apos;s opinion of these prospects. The German Legation in Berne is reported (June 29th) to have been told to endeavour to glean details about the war aims of each, (sic) of the Powers of the Entente Alliance.Austria-Hungary. On June 29th Sir 11. Rumbold forwarded a report, based-on fairly reliable authority, that it is realised that Austria-Hungary cannot get out of the Avar without breaking with Germany, which could only be brought about if the Austrian army suffered a severe reverse ; if American troops were engaged in achieving this result, the result would probably be especially beneficial.(See also under Poland.)Great Britain. In a report for the week ending on June 26th, the Ministry of Labour reports that the publication of Lord Grey &apos;s pamphlet on a League of Nations has reopened discussion, and the Labour Press is deeply interested in the idea.A great deal of space is devoted, to the Labour Conference in London. Sir R. Rodd reports from Rome (June 29th) a good deal of misapprehension there as to the meaning of the i esolution suspending the truce between political parties. German Wireless of July 2nd states that M. Troelstra has received a telegram from &quot; Henderson, B raft ting, Albert Thomas, Reiiaudel, Longuet, Huysinans and other delegates &quot; expressing regret that he Avas refused a passport to England, and that the delegates on that account Avere unable to co-operate with him &quot; for obtaining a just peace which all desire.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
