<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/43/38 images: 322-335</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   November 1943.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (43) 538.26th November, 1943.WAR CABINET.OFFICE OF THE MINISTER OF RECONSTRUCTION.Note by the Prime Minister.1. The Office of the Minister of Reconstruction wili be the focal point forall plans for the transitional period.2. Primary responsibility for formulating plans, and for their executionwhen finally approved, necessarily rests with the Departments concerned.3. It will be a function of the Minister of Reconstruction and of his staff to see that the plans of Departments are brought into relation with each other;to make sure that no gaps are left between Departmental schemes and that thereis no overlapping or conflict between them. It will also be within the scope ofthe Ministers duties, on behalf of the War Cabinet, to call the attention ofMinisters to any part of the field which in his view has not been adequatelycovered by existing preparations.4. This task of bringing the whole range of preparations for the transitional period into a single coherent whole will necessarily bring to light a number of points calling for decisions, some of them on matters of principle. It will be theduty of the Minister of Reconstruction and his staff to arrange for meetings tobe held at which points not involving decisions of principle can be settled; andto arrange that matters involving points of principle are brought before the WarCabinet or its appropriate Ministerial Committee. The examination of schemes will probably also throw up a number of points on which the definition of departmental duties and responsibilities requires clarification.5. I ask that work on transitional plans should proceed on these general lines, and I should be glad if a more detailed scheme could be prepared and submitted for my consideration in the light of experience of the working of thenew organisation.w. s. c.10 Downing Street, S.W, 1,26th November, 1943.[26415]

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY:S GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of.SSLiI 5Si  &apos; copy no...WAR cabinet confidential Record of a discussion between Membersof the War Cabinet held at No.  10,  Doming Street,S.W. 1,  on THURSDAY,  25TH NOVEMBER,   1943 at theConclusion of the 161st Meeting of theWar CabinetPRESENT:The Rt.  Hon.  C. R.  Attlee,Deputy Prime Minister.M. P. ,(In the Chair).The Rt.  Hon.  Sir John Anderson,M. P.,  Chancellor of theExchequer.The Rt.  Hon.  Oliver Lyttelton,M. P. ,  Minister of Production.The Rt.  Hon.  Lord Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The Rt-.  Hon.  Ernest Bevin, M. P.MinisterService.of Labour and national the Rt.   Hon.  Herbert Morrison^M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Rt.  Hon.  Viscount Crariborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.SECRETARIAT:Sir Edward BridgesMr.  Norman. BrookTHE- DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER said that he thought-it would be useful if members of the War Cabinet could have an informal discussion of the draft of a Note bythe Prime Minister on the Office of the Minister of reconstruction.      (This was subsequently circulated as W.P.(43)  538).In discussion the following points were raised.:&apos;(a) The last sentence of paragraph 5 of the draftread as follows:-

&quot;It will also &quot;be within the scope of theMinister&apos;s duties,  oh &quot;behalf of the WarCabinet, to call on Departments to -prepare plans for any part of the field which inhis view has not been adequately coveredby existing preparations&quot;.It was pointed out that this might be interpreted as empowering the Minister of Reconstruction to callon the officials of other Departments, without reference to the Departmental Minister,  to prepare plans for his consideration.      This,  of course, wasnot the intention.      It was contemplated that,  insuch a case,  the Minister of Reconstruction wouldapproach the Departmental Minister concerned.      But,if this approach did not yield satisfactory results,it would always fte open to the Minister of Reconstructionto bring the matter to the notice of the War Cabinet.It was agreed that,  in order to avoid rnisunder-standing,   it would be preferable that this sentence should read: -&quot;it will also be within the scope of theMinister&apos;s duties,  on behalf of the WarCabinet,  to call the attention of ministers to any part of the field which in his viewhas not been adequately covered by existingprepa rations&quot;.(b) In paragraph 4 of the draft it was stated to hethe duty of the Minister of Reconstruction &quot;to bringmatters involving points of principle before the WarCabinet or its appropriate Ministerial Committee&quot;,This might be  Interpreted as  implying that thiswas an exclusive duty of the Minister of Reconstruction.In practice it would often be more appropriate that heshould suggest to the Departmental Ministers concerned that they should bring the matter before their colleagues.      It would be preferable that the draft should leave open the question whether,   in such a., case,the matter should be brought forward by the Minister of reconstruction or by the Departmental Minister or ministers concerned.It was agreed that it would be preferable thatthis sentence should read:-&quot;.* ...  and to arrange that matters  involvingpoints of principle should be brought beforethe War Cabinet or its appropriateMinisterial Committee. &quot;(c) THE MINISTER OP PRODUCTION thought that thetime had come when his Department should be considering?together with the Ministry of Labour and NationalService, the Board of Trade and the Service and supply departments,  how our productive resources should be distributed, after the end of hostilities with Germany,between the needs of the war against Japan,  the demands for relief and the re-establishment of our home and export trades.      If his functions were interpreted asextending only to war production,  it would beimpossible for hira to plan effectively the allocation of our productive resources after the end of the war&apos;with Germany.

According to the first sentence in paragraph 3of the draft Note,   it would be &quot;a function of theMinister of Reconstruction to see that the plans of departments are brought into relation with each other&quot;.Were these words  intended to imply that the Ministerof Reconstruction should take the initiative in framing plans in this field?THE MINISTER OP LABOUR AND NATIONAL service said that he was confronted with much the same problem from the demobilisation angle.      As he saw it,  itwas the duty of his Department,  in co-operation withthe Departments mentioned by the Minister of Production,to plan, and when the time came to   carry out,  there-absorption and re-settlement in industry of the menand women demobilised from the Services and from war production.      For  this purpose his Department must workin the closest co-operation with the other Departmentswho could say what numbers could be released,, and at what stages,  and in what industries they would berequired,      Was it intended that the Minister of reconstruction should formulate these plans?     or could a ruling be given that these problems ofdemobilisation and re-settlement were to be regardedas outside the duties of the Minister of reconstruction and as matters to be dealt with by the departmental ministers immediately concerned.In discussion it was  generally agreed thatdemobilisation could not be excluded from the scopeof the duties of the Minister of Reconstruction.      Atthe same time,  it was explained that the Minister of reconstruction would not himself formulate, still lessattempt to carry out,  plans for administrative actionfalling within the responsibilities of existingDepartments.      As  stated in paragraph 2 of the draft note    &quot;Primary responsibility for formulating plans,and for their execution when finally approved,necessarily rests with the Departments concerned&quot;.But it would be a function of the Minister of reconstruction to satisfy himself that due progress was being made in the formulation of such plans, andto see that the plans were properly related to  thoseof other Departments.-As regards the particular group of problemsmentioned by the Minister of Labour and National Serviceand the Minister of Production,  the immediate need was for some statement of the respective functions of theDepartments concerned with the re-adjustment ofindustry to the two-stage ending of the war and the subsequent transition from war to peace.      If,   forexample,  a Directive were issued defining the responsibilities of the Ministry of Production and theother Departments  concerned with the demobilisation ofindustrial capacity,  and the responsibility.responibilities of theMinistry of Labour in respect of the demobilisation oflabour,   it would be possible for those Departments togo ahead with the preparation of plans - on the basis that the Minister of Reconstruction would be broughtinto consultation at  the outset regarding the broadobjectives to be aimed at, and would thereafter be kept in close touch with the progress of the work.

jl &apos;j it wo. s agreed th :.t it would be helpful if adraft Directive on this matter could he prepared for s libra is si o-n to the Prime Minister.(d) THE MINISTER OF LABOUR AND RATIONAL service said, that, -&quot;hen the primary responsibility for anyparticular subject had been definitely allocated toa Departmental Minister, it would be preferable thatthe Minister of Reconstruction should avoid discussingthat sub :j ect wi th repros representative ives o:? th e i nt erestsaffected..      For example,  he had himself been inconsultation with the Trades Union Congress about the demobilisation plans, but had found it  necessary tobreak off these consultations when,  after theappointment of the Ministerial Committee on Demobilisation,the Trades    Union Congress had acldressed the irrepresentations direct to the Minister without Portfolio0THE CHANCELLOR OP THE EXCHEQUER said that it was most important that a Minister with co-ordinatingfunctions such as those of the Minister of Reconstructionshould avoid direct dealings with outside interests on matters clearly falling; within the jurisdiction of a departmental Minister.      Outside interests were quickto exploit any suggestion that it was open to   them toby-pass the Departmental Minister,  or to  appeal fromhis decision to another Ministerial authority.      this consideration applied, not only to receivingdeputations, but also to answering parliamentary questions or letters from outside interests.      The onlysafe rule was to refer all such enquiries or represent-ations to  the Departmental Minister concerned.This principle could not be applied so easilyto matters concerning two or more Departments.      Inthose cases it was sometimes difficult to deny toManbers of Parliament, or important representativebod-ies, the convenience of placing their case before a single Minister who was known to have functions ofco-ordd nation in a matter affecting a number ofdifferent Departments.      Even in those cases, however,it was essential that action should be closely concertedwith the Departmental Ministers concerned;    and when,for example, a deputation had to be  received,   it wasadvisable that the other Ministers concerned should bepres ent.THE MINISTER OP RECONSTRUCTION, said that he wasin full agreement with these views.      He would like hiscolleagues to understand that his work would, dependentirely on their co-operation.      His aim was to help them,  so far as he could.,   to formulate the plans which-they would have to carry out, when the time came;    andhe had no desire to  encroach in any way upon their responsibilities.      At the same time,  if he was tohelp to bring all the Departmental plans into a singlecoherent whole,  it was  essential that he should be korptfully informed of all the projects which departments had in view and of the progress made in the preparationof their plans.      Looking at the plans as a whole fromhis central position,  he would be able to  give guidancewhich he thought would be helpful;    and on occasionwoul d no    doubt have to  suggest raodif ic ati ons wl 1 i chwere required to  secure a proper harmony between thevarious plans.

(e) It was further agreed that the Minister of reconstruction must have the right to go into matters where progress appeared to he impeded by a lack ofco-operation between Departments in the preparationof post-war plans.      Equally, he must be able to approach the Minister concerned where the post-warplans  of a single Department seemed to be laggingbehind0      And in all such cases he must have the right,if his initial approach to the Minister or ministers concerned had not yielded satisfactory results,  tobring the matter before the war Cabinet or one of its committees,(f) The draft Paper load been designed for domesticcirculation,  for the guidance of Departments.      It was recognised that, if it was  to be made the basis of any public statement regarding the functions of the newMinister,  its phraseology would have to be reconsidered.It was agreed that the amendments notedat (a) and (&quot;b) above could be incorporated in the Note without further reference tothe Prime Minister,  as they merelyclarified what had been the intention ofthe document.      The Secretary of the WarCabinet &quot;was  invited to   arrange for the Note,as so amended, to b-e circulated as a WarCabinet Paper.The Meeting then considered the draft terms ofreference of the proposed War Cabinet Committee onRe cons t r u c t i o a0It was  explained that the Prime Minister had decided that reconstruction questions should in future be handled, under the War Cabinet, by a new Committee,which would be known as the Reconstruction Committeeand ^ould replace both the Reconstruction priorities committee and the Reconstruction Problems Committee.The membership of this new Committee would be the. sameas that of the existing Reconstruction priorities committee,  save that the Minister of Reconstruction wouldbe added to the Committee and would take the Chair.It was suggested in discussion that the terms ofreference should make it clear that they implied no restriction of the functions of the Minister of reconstruction.      It was pointed out, with reference tothe concluding paragraph of the draft,  that international economic problems, though they were properly excluded.from the scope of this particular Committee, were notoutside the sphere of the Minister&apos;s duties..      Indeedthere was probably room for the appointment of a  secondCommittee to handle, under the War Cabinet,   theseexternal economic problems,,It was agreed that the draft terms of reference should be   amended  to make it clear that the -restrictive reference in the final paragraphwas without derogation to the responsibilities of the Minister of Reconstruction;    and that thePrime Minister should be invited to agree tothe establishment of a second Committee to handle, under the War Cabinet,   questions of-post-war financial and economic policy in theint erna tional f i eld.Offices of the War Cabinet,S. W. 1. ,lot December, 1943. --5-




</content>
</cab>
