<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/2/53 images: 612-623</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   December 1939.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (39)119th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 119 (39).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Tuesday, December 19, 1939, at 11-30 a.m.Present :The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C., M.P., Chancellor of theExchequer (in the Chair).The  Right  Hon.  L.   Hore-Belisha^M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,   The Right Hon. Sir Samuel IIoareM.P., Secretary of State for Air. Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   HankeyMinister without Portfolio.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService (Item 1).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of  State  for  DominionAffairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.Secretariat.Sir Rupert Howorth.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Lieutenant-Colonel E. I. C. Jacob, R.E.Mr. G. N. Flemming.[205.18Jb
WAR CABINET 119 (39).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Calling up of Men for the Armed Forces ...      ...       ...     4652      Industrial Man-Power ...............     466Dilution and Training.3      The Air Situation     ..................     467Bomber Operations in the Heligoland Bight on the 18th December.4      The A drniral Graf Spee       ...............     470Question of a message to the Uruguayan Government.5      The Naval Situation..................     471
1. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Labour and National Service (W.P. (G.) (39) 152)setting out a proposal that, instead of proclaiming each successiveage-group as required and at the same time proclaiming those whohad reached 20 years since the last Proclamation, there should be one Royal Proclamation on the 1st January, 1940, making liable theage-groups which were expected to be required to be called up for service under the National Service (Armed Forces) Act, 1939, duringthe whole of the year 1940.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that he had nothing to add to his Memorandum except to point out that hislegal advisers had now discovered that, in order to secure the desiredresult, the Proclamation should be made on the 31st December, 1939,and not on the 1st January, 1940. The respective age-groups wouldprobably be registered and called up at intervals through the year as and when required by the Forces. The statement to be issuedwould make this point clear and also that men in the age-groupsconcerned would have to register only as and when called upon todo so. If, as seemed likely, five age groups were in fact called up during the year, this would give the Armed Forces some 850,000men, but the number of registrations would probably exceed,000,000 and it might be possible to use this figure in any statement issued, so as to increase the effect on public opinion at home andabroad.The Chancellor of the Exchequer suggested that a short state-ment should be issued at roughly the same time that the Proclama-tion was made, which would need to be very carefully drawn up,to explain exactly what its purpose was, and that in addition itwould be very desirable if speeches to be made by members of theWar Cabinet later in January could be used to develop the widerimplications of the proposal and its relation to our requirementsof labour power for industrial purposes. The object of the firststatement must be to expound the proposal clearly and to correct the impression in France and elsewhere that we were not contri-buting our fair share of man power to the common struggle.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that he hadin mind to issue an explanatory statement at the appropriate time,and to consult the Service Departments as to its drafting. Hewould take steps to see that it received the widest possible publicity.The Secretary of State for- War asked whether it would bepossible to explore the practicability of applying in this country the principle adopted in France under which men of military agenot called up for service were made liable to special taxation onthis account; but it was generally agreed that it would be premature to consider such a suggestion, which would in any case be difficultto apply in the very different circumstances of this country. he also referred to the position of young men under the age of 19,who might find it difficult to obtain employment because they were about to be called up for service in the near future. As he had given  an undertaking that no men would be sent to France under theage of 20, he wondered whether some means could be found of using the services of these young men where they were needed, e.g., inagriculture, whilst giving them at the same time preliminarymilitary training.The Minister of Labour and National Service pointed out thatthe age of 18 was always one of unsettlement in the labour market,but that as the shortage of labour became more acute in industry,it was likely that these young men would all find that their services were in request.The Chancellor of the Exchequer suggested that in so far asthey were not already skilled, they would be likely to be used in[20518] b 2Calling Up ofMen for the armed Forces.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 32ndConclusions,Minute 19.)
employment which did not require a lengthy training, but that thedemand of agriculture would be for skilled men.The War Cabinet :-(i) Approved the proposal of the Minister of Labour and national Service, as set out in his Memorandum(W.P. (G.) (39) 152), that one Royal Proclamation shouldbe made making liable for service in the Armed Forcesmen aged 23, 24, 25, 26 and 27, as well as the 19-20age group, subject to the substitution of the31st December, 1939,* for the 1st January, 1940, as thedate for the Proclamation.(ii) Invited him to consult the Service Departments with regardto the drafting of an explanatory statement regardingthis Proclamation, which should be given as wide publicity as possible.IndustrialMan-Power.Dilution andtraining.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 54thConclusions,Minute 9.)2. In connection with the discussion on the previous item,the First Lord of the Admiralty said that he hoped that thestatement to be issued in regard to the calling up of five age-groupsunder the National Service (Armed Forces) Act would make it clearthat one result would be to make it possible for industry to retainkey men required for the production of munitions and materialsrequired by the Fighting Services. It would be better to call up an additional age-group than to interfere with these men. later on it might be necessary to comb out some of these key men, butthe important thing at the moment was for the firms to realise thatthey were not going to lose them.There was general agreement with this view, but the Secretaryof State for War urged that it was no less important that industry should realise the need for carrying dilution of their man power as far as it was effectively possible by bringing in women, trainingnew skilled men, &amp;c, so as to increase production and at the sametime to make men available for the armed forces. He gathered that progress in this field was not very rapid and they had, for example,been told by the Minister of Supply that if women were allowedto work a night shift, the output of small arms ammunition couldbe increased by 20 per cent. The First Lord of the Admiraltyreferred to the great services rendered by women in the munition factories in 1917-18.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that, asregards dilution, it was his responsibility to negotiate agreementbetween the Employers and the Trade Unions and the responsibilityof the Minister of Supply to secure the adoption of the agreedmeasures. He thought it desirable that labour officers should beappointed in the various areas for this purpose, but he must emphasise that no measures could be of universal application, andthat it was always a question of finding out what would be most appropriate in the case of any particular firm or industry; forexample, there were considerable differences of opinion as to theadvantages of employing women on night shifts. The need forfurther training was a matter which he had very much in mind and in which he was doing all that he could.With reference to the suggestion that he had given a rulingthat women could not be employed on the night shift in munition factories, the Secretary of State for Home Affairs said that thiswas not the case.   He had himself initiated an enquiry into, this* Note. As a result of further consideration, it was subsequently decidedat the request of the Minister of Labour, to revert to 1st January, 1940, as thedate for the Proclamation.
point and, in view of the misunderstanding which had arisen, hewould confer with the Minister of Supply in regard to it.The Lord Privy Seal stressed the importance of pressing on with the policy of dilution in the various localities and also withthe policy of bringing in the smaller firms for the production ofmunitions. He felt that the comparatively slow progress that wasbeing made in this matter was due to the fact that local Committeeshad not executive powers, and he understood that this was due toa Treasury fear of extravagance. The Chancellor of the exchequer said that on the Economic Policy Committee he was pressing for action in this matter.The Minister without Portfolio mentioned that the shortage of skilled labour would certainly make itself felt in connection withthe ship-building programme and that means of securing dilutionin this sphere ought to be explored. It was agreed that this shouldbe looked into in connection with the forthcoming examination ofthe shipping situation.The War Cabinet took note of this discussion.The air situation.Bomber Opera-tions in theHeligolandBight on the18th December.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 118thConclusions,Minute 1.)3. The Secretary of State for Air informed the War Cabinetthat a force of 22 Wellington aircraft had been despatched on the morning of the previous day with instructions to attack enemy warvessels at sea and in the Schiilig Roads or Wilhelmshaven.Sweeping in from the North, the Wellingtons had been engagedby 15 Messerschffiitts 110 and 10 Messerschmitts 109 between helicopters-goland and the Jade Roads at a height of 15,000 feet. Thirty tofifty attacks had been made by the enemy, as a result of which atotal of 12 Wellingtons were missing details of which were asfollows :-4 Wellingtons shot down by Fighters.3 Wellingtons hit in the petrol tanks and last seen headingfor Holland.3 Wellingtons missing.2 Wellingtons down in the sea off the English Coast.Of the last-mentioned, one was reported to have been forced toalight 40 miles East of Cromer, and a trawler was said to haverescued the crew complete.Losses to the enemy reported by our crews who had returnedincluded 6 Messerschmitts 109 shot down.6 Messerschmitts 110 shot down.In addition 2 Messerschmitts 109 and 4 Messerschmitts 110 were reported to have been shot down by crews of aircraft which weremissing.The formation of Wellingtons, when it arrived over Wilhelms-haven, had seen 1 Battleship and 2 Cruisers, but had been unableto attack because of the close proximity of buildings. Six bombs,however, had been dropped on 4 large Fleet Auxiliaries in theSchiilig Roads.   The results had not been observed.The Secretary of State for Air said that the new facts whichhad emerged since the issue of the Air Ministry communique to thePress were the additional six Messerschmitts which had beenreported as having been shot down by the crews of the aircraft which had not returned and the bombing of the German FleetAuxiliaries. He was, therefore, considering the advisability ofissuing a supplementary communique. Our own losses hadintentionally been given as seven, as the other five were missing,and there was no reason for believing that the enemy were aware of the latter[20518]b 3
The Chief of the Air Staff said that his preliminary reflectionson this engagement were as follows : (i) It was not to be assumed that, aircraft for aircraft, theGerman Fighter had any marked superiority over our bombers. In the circumstances of the engagement onthe previous day, it had to be remembered that theFighters began with considerable advantages. Theypossessed numerical superiority and were waiting forus when we arrived. They had the initiative; werefaster; were fighting at home with the full support oftheir local defence organisation, and had no long and difficult return journey to make,(ii) The German problem of having to defend only 100 miles of coast was in striking contrast to our own, in having to defend 700 miles. With no particular air activitygoing on in France, the Germans were able to concen-trate on the defence of their Fleet in this restricted area.(iii) The aircraft belonging to the squadron which had themost highly-trained crews and had carried out the mostgunnery practice had suffered fewer casualties a fact which definitely confirmed the great importance whichwas attached to the training of crews, not only as individuals, but as a team. In this connection, the modern aircraft differed considerably from its predecessors-cessor in the last war, being more comparable to a ship,of which the crew required to be &quot;worked up.&quot; Thisunderlined two points in particular first, the urgent need for overcoming the difficulties which everywhereconfronted the R.A.F. in obtaining the ranges which itrequired for live practise-firing; and, secondly, thataircraft could not go straight from production intofirst-line since they were equally needed for the finaltraining of crews as teams.(iv) We must find means of dealing with the Flak-ship.  these ships were part of the German warning system. Theywere small merchant vessels fitted with wireless and armed with pom-poms and machine guns. They were distributed along the Frisian Coast and otherwisesuitably disposed to give warning of approachingaircraft (the War Cabinet were shown a map on whichthe locations of sixteen of these ships were marked on a given date in December) and were protected by theminefield. In some cases they carried neutral flags. Itwas most desirable that action should be taken toeradicate this Flak-ship system, but the R.A.F. couldnot do this by themselves without naval assistance, asthey had the appearance of merchant ships and theirnationality was uncertain.(v) Finally, the experience of the previous day raised a doubt as to the wisdom of sending our Bombers into the&quot;hornets&apos; nest,&quot; unless we definitely knew that therewas a target there which they could profitably attack.Otherwise, as on this particular mission, these big and heavy Bombers found themselves with no target thatthey were permitted to attack and thus relegated to the role of long-range Fighters, for which they were neithersuitable nor economical.In reply to various questions the Chief of the Air staff explained : (a) The Wellington was not as good a Fighter as the convertedBlenheim, being slower and heavier.
(b) The objection to escorting our Bombers with BlenheimFighters was that it was a very long way for them togo, fight and return.(c) Even if, in terms of aircraft, the German losses were equalto our own, it was to be remembered that whereas theMesserschmitt 109 was a single-seater and M.E. 110 a two-seater, the Wellington carried a crew of six, andmoreover that these comprised very highly-trained personnel.(d) Self-sealing petrol tanks were rapidly being made ready,but none of our aircraft was yet equipped with these.The Wellington would be fitted with these; meanwhile,it would have to rely on armour.The First Lord of the Admiralty regarded the engagement asa very gallant exploit, his only regret being that, in suffering suchheavy casualties, the Royal Air Force had been denied the satisfac-tion of finding more targets which their orders would permit themto bomb.The problem of dealing with the Flak-ship was one which would undoubtedly be of interest to tJhe Naval Staff, by.whom he wouldhave it examined. It might be possible to combine an attack by coastal Motorboats with a simultaneous demonstration by the RoyalAir Force.In view of the serious difficulty of attacking the large unitsof the German Fleet under the present embargo, which precludedour bombing them except under conditions which would not causeloss of civilian life, he asked whether, as an alternative, it would notbe possible to make an example of Borkum or Sylt.The Secretary of State for Air mentioned that 8 Whitleys had,in fact, been sent over Borkum and Sylt on the previous night. all had returned, some bombs having been dropped on lights seen onthe water at these bases.The First Lord of the Admiralty explained that he had more in mind than the mere patrolling of these bases. They were fortifiedislands, and as such were legitimate military targets. He suggestedthat we might attack the seaplane bases with the object of destroyingthem.The Chief of the Air Staff said that the possibility of suchan operation had been studied by the Air Ministry, but that atpresent it came within the War Cabinet prohibition against anybombing which might cause loss of civilian life. He suggested thatany departure from this ruling in favour of attacking the mine-laying seaplane bases should be considered with due regard to theimportance which we attached to the sowing of German mines asa decisive factor in the war. Furthermore, it should be appreciated that these seaplane bases were poor targets in themselves, and thattheir destruction would in no way compensate for the damage whichmight be done in retaliation, for example, to Chatham.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that he did not base hisargument for stronger measures on the score that the German minewas a critically dangerous threat, but rather on his belief that german morale was becoming shaken, and that a few blows of thiskind might be just sufficient to destroy it. If justification for thesestronger measures were required, it could be found in the unwarrant-able murder of fishermen, of which the Germans had been guiltyand which provided ample provocation. We could thus associatea specific operation with a specific crime.The Secretary of State for Air felt that it might be unwise to disturb the present situation, since by doing so we might lose morethan we might gain; but suggested that the subject was one which
could be very suitably discussed at the meeting arranged for thesame evening between representatives of the Admiralty and theAir Ministry.There was general agreement with this proposal.The Chancellor of the Exchequer thought that it would be undesirable to issue a supplementary announcement correcting theAir Ministry communique, as had been suggested by the Secretaryof State for Air.The War Cabinet :-(i) Agreed that the Admiralty and the Air Ministry should examine at the meeting arranged for that same eveningthe possible alternatives open to the R.A.F. to the air attacks on units of the German Fleet when at their bases,including the suggestion of the First Lord of theAdmiralty that Borkum or some other enemy seaplanebase should be heavily bombed,(ii) Agreed that in all the circumstances it would be undesirable that the Air Ministry should issue a supple-mentary announcement correcting and amplifying the communique regarding the air battle in the heligoland bight.(iii) Took note that the First Lord of the Admiralty and theSecretary of State for Air, in consultation, would examine the question of action to deal with tbe Flak-ship matter.The &quot; AdmiralGraf Spee.&quot;Question of a message to theUruguayanGovernment.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 118thConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The Chancellor of the Exchequer drew the attention of hiscolleagues to the third paragraph of telegram No. 172 fromMontevideo, dated the 18th December, in the course of which mr. Millington Drake had submitted &quot; that, in the present temperof the nations and of the Governments of the Americas as a whole,great moral and political advantage will be accredited to GreatBritain and the Allies by a frank and prompt communication to theUruguayan Government, conveying a handsome and gratefulacknowledgment of the manner in which that Government hadupheld the spirit of international law in connection with the case ofthe Admiral Graf Spee. A little later in the telegram, Mr. Milling-ton Drake had added that he had been in consultation with hisFrench colleague, who entirely concurred in his view, and wasreporting in the same sense to the French Government, with a viewto their making a similar communication to the Uruguayan Govern-ment, if there was agreement between them and His Majesty&apos;sGovernment.The Chancellor observed that this did not appear to be a matter in which the French were very much concerned, and he suggestedthat, in the absence of the Foreign Secretary, it might be helpful tothe Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs if hecould be given a,n indication of the War Cabinet&apos;s first reactions tothis proposal. He (the Chancellor) was bound to say that he viewed the proposal with some apprehension. It was true that the Govern-ment of Uruguay had behaved correctly; in addition to maintaining a neutral attitude in a difficult situation, they had displayedconsiderable moral courage in the face of strong German pressure.It might be desirable, therefore, that Mr. Millington Drake shouldconvey privately to the Uruguayan Minister for Foreign Affairs ourgratitude for the stand his Government had taken. It would be avery different matter, however, if anything in the nature of a publicmessage of gratitude was contemplated. Such a message might,indeed, be highly embarrassing to the Uruguayan Government inpresent circumstances.
The First Lord of the Admiralty agreed that any publicmessage would be an embarrassment to the Uruguayans. In thisconnection the First Lord referred to telegrams Nos. 353 and 355from Buenos Aires, dated the 18th December. In those telegramsSir Esmond Ovey had reported, among other matters, his view thatthe Argentine Government would be embarrassed by a visit byH.M.S. Achilles to Buenos Aires immediately after the victory.The landing of our sailors in either a Uruguayan or anArgentine port at this particular juncture would probably be thesignal for pro-British demonstrations on a large scale, and suchdemonstrations might give the Governments of those countries theappearance of being something less than impartial neutrals. TheAdmiralty had accepted Sir Esmond Ovey&apos;s view with regret, forthe men were badly in need of a day or two on shore, and the ship had been ordered to proceed to the Falkland Islands for the purposeof giving short leave on shore. Possibly it might be practicable toarrange a visit to Uruguayan and Argentine ports a little later.The War Cabinet Instructed the Deputy Secretary (Civil) of the WarCabinet to inform the Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs that their first reaction toMr. Millington Drake&apos;s proposal was that it would be advisable that any expression of gratitude to theUruguayan Government should take the form of a privatemessage conveyed by His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Montevideoto the Uruguayan Foreign Minister.5.   The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the homeward-bound Norwegian convoy was waiting to sail.   Strong forces wouldbe placed to protect it, as the Germans might possibly attempt a raid.In the last 48 hours, 29 fishing boats and merchant vessels hadWM (39) 118th Deen attacked with bombs and machine-guns by enemy aircraft.  of conclusions       these, 20 were fishing trawlers engaged on their daily avocations,and 6 of them had been sunk in circumstances of the utmostbrutality.This action on the part of the Germans might provide a usefulbackground to retaliatory measures later on, if such were required.The City of Kobe (4,000 tons) had been mined off Lowestoft. It-was not definitely known whether she had sunk. The Bogo(1.214 tons), a Danish vessel, had been sunk East of May Island.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The naval situation.(PreviousReferenceMinute 2.)Richmond Terrace, S.W.1,December 19, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
