<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/9/11 images: 114-119</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fThis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.BE KEP2,UNDER LOCK AND KEY.it is prequested that special care may be taken ensure the secrecy of this document.(f.P.(40)251)WAR CAB WET.Situation in Syria:   proposed declaration by His Majesty&apos;s Government.Memorandum by Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.As my colleagues will be aware,.:!. Puaux, the HighCommissioner for the French Mandated Territories in the levant, and General Mittelhauser.. the Commander-in-Chief ofthe French forces there, at first declared their intentionof Carrying on the war on the side of Great Britain., inspite or the armistice between France and Germany and Franceand Italy.     In the last day or two there have been signs that their resolution was wavering and every possible efforthas been made to encourage them or,,if these efforts failed,to ensure that they would at least not give public expression to their determination to defer to the Bordeaux government until His Maiesty&apos;s Government had had time to decide upon acourse of action.2. &apos;   It is now announced, however, that GeneralMittelhauser has declared that hostilities have ceased in syria, although the French flag will continue to fly there;and the question of what His Majesty&quot; s Government are to doin the face of this situation becomes one on which an urgentdecision is necessary.5.     From the strictly practical point of view, no immediate change in the situation will necessarily take place.The terms of the armistices with Germany and Italy say nothingabout the occupation of Syria or the Lebanon and I assume that even if Germany and Italy were to attempt to occupy thosecountries, they would have difficulty in doing so in the face of our Fleet in the Eastern Mediterranean,,4.   &apos; But the psychological, as well as the practical,aspects of the question have to be considered,   Everyone inthe Arab world will now be asking what His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment mean to do.     So - and this is almost equally important -will the Turkish Government. .   It is essential that HisMajesty&apos;s Government should say something, and say it quickly,which will make it clear that they do not intend that Syriaand the Lebanon should become a vacuum from which the british position in the Middle East might be threatened.5.     But, whatever they say. His Majesty&apos;s government must take account of the susceptibilities of those Frenchmenstill fighting for the Allied cause outside France, and makeallowance, so far as they can, for the ultimate rights and interests of France in the Levant. .   They must also considerthe susceptibilities of the Arabs and of the TurkishGovernment.     The former are naturally pressing for actionin regard to Syria and the Lebanon which vrould probably beFremature and unwise at the moment, .e.g. declarations ohatranee will grant them their independence after the war*. . Thelatter/

latter are reported to have said that they could not allow an Italian occupation of Syrias since this would be thebeginning of the encirclement of Turkey.     But althoughTurkish assistance in defending Syria might be welcome incertain circumstances, it would be suspect by the Arabs unless their acquiescence were obtained beforehand and this factorwould have to be taken into account if the question of turkish co-operation arosea60     In the circumstances I suggest that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment should as soon as possible make a declaration onthe lines set out below, subject to the views of His Majesty&apos;ambassador at Angora, who has warned us that unless we givea lead the Turkish Government may themselves do or say some-thing inconvenient, and to whom it should be telegraphed.In suggesting this? I have assumed that, v/whatever our military difficulties in the Middle East might be, it wouldbe essential to our whole strategic position there to preventanything in the nature of a German or Italian occupation andthat it would be a question of preventing such occupation orof abandoning our position altogether.     At the same time I fully realise that we have already given guarantees enoughand do not want to add to theme     The emphasis should there-fore be on our own interests.7e     The declaration I suggest is as follows:-&quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdomunderstand that General Mittelhauser, the Coxmiander-in-Chief of the French forces in the Levant,, has stated thathostilities have ceased in Syria,,     His Majesty1 sGovernment assume that this does not mean that, if germany or Italy were to demand the right to occupy Syria or the lebanon and were to try to do so in the face of Britishcom land of the sea, no attempt would be made by the french forces to oppose thema     In order, however, to set atrest doubts which may be felt in any quarter, HisMajesty&apos;s Government declare that they could not allow,Syria or the Lebanon to be used as a base for attacks upon those countries in the Middle East which they arepledged to defend, or to become the scene of such disorderas to constitute a danger to those countries.     they therefore hold themselves free to take whatever measuresthey may in such circumstances consider necessary in theirown interests,.     Any action which they may hereafter be obliged to take in fulfilment of this declaration will be entirely without prejudice to the future status of the territories now under French mandate&quot;.80     While I consider it necessary to make ourposition clear in this way, I sincerely hope that, no actionon our part will be required in practice.     So long as theFrench authorities can maintain their position, and are reasonably helpful towards our requirements, economic and otherwise, we shall have no particular interest in disturbingthem, even though they are not actively persecuting the war onpur sidea     Whether Germany, Italy and the Arabs of Syria andthe Lebanon will leave them in peace is another matter.Foreign Office,28th June, 1940o




</content>
</cab>
