<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/106/0 images: 133-137</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1961The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of..............................................................Copy No.   4 1C. (61) 11425th July, 1961CABINETJOMO KENYATTAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the ColoniesBackgroundThe Cabinet will recall that the Governor, Sir Patrick Renison, made a full statement on 1st March in which he expressed the view that Kenyatta should notbe kept in restriction indefinitely. He added, however, that he did not propose to release him until the new Government were working well and until he thoughtthat the security risk could be accepted and contained and that the danger whichhis return presented to the economy and administration and to Kenya&apos;constitutional progress towards early independence had been minimised. TheGovernor also announced that Kenyatta would be moved to Maralal. In April,on the formation of the new Government, the following further statement wasmade:&quot; The Governor has agreed that the Government will now begin to build a house for Mr. Jomo Kenyatta and his family on a site to be agreed inKiambu District in readiness for Mr. Kenyatta&apos;s return from Maralal to his home in Kiambu in due course.&quot;The Governors proposals. The Governor has now informed me that he proposes that Kenyatta shouldbe moved to Kiambu in the middle of August (when the house will have beencompleted), and that he should be released from restriction a few days thereafter.In support of this proposal, Sir Patrick Renison has indicated that, having regardto the competence and strength of his security forces, and having regard also tothe performance of the new Government, the conditions which he laid down inMarch are within sight of fulfilment. He has no doubt that the balance ofadvantage lies in now taking the risk of Kenyatta&apos;s release. The Governor^ viewshave the support of his Council of Ministers (which includes his most senior officials),of senior members of the Administration (including the Provincial commissioner in the Central Province), of the Commissioner of Police and of representatives ofKikuyu loyalists. In this connexion I attach at Annex A a minute of a meeting ofthe Central Province Advisory Council held on 16th June, 1961.3. The Governors proposal is a logical consequence of previous decisions ofthe Governor and Her Majesty&apos;s Government. The Colonial Policy Committeeagree with his conclusions. It is essential to face this issue from strength and I doubt whether we shall ever be in a better position to do so now when there iswide acceptance both in Kenya and the United Kingdom that Kenyatta&apos;s early release is inevitable.59385THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of.............................................................Copy No.   4 1C. (61) 11425 th July, 1961CABINETJOMO KENYATTAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the ColoniesBackgroundThe Cabinet will recall that the Governor, Sir Patrick Renison, made a full statement on 1st March in which he expressed the view that Kenyatta should notbe kept in restriction indefinitely. He added, however, that he did not propose to release him until the new Government were working well and until he thoughtthat the security risk could be accepted and contained and that the danger whichhis return presented to the economy and administration and to Kenya&apos;constitutional progress towards early independence had been minimised. TheGovernor also announced that Kenyatta would be moved to Maralal. In April,on the formation of the new Government, the following further statement wasmade:&quot; The Governor has agreed that the Government will now begin to build a house for Mr. Jomo Kenyatta and his family on a site to be agreed inKiambu District in readiness for Mr. Kenyatta?s return from Maralal to his home in Kiambu in due course.&quot;The Governor^ proposals. The Governor has now informed me that he proposes that Kenyatta shouldbe moved to Kiambu in the middle of August (when the house will have beencompleted), and that he should be released from restriction a few days thereafter.In support of this proposal, Sir Patrick Renison has indicated that, having regardto the competence and strength of his security forces, and having regard also tothe performance of the new Government, the conditions which he laid down inMarch are within sight of fulfilment. He has no doubt that the balance ofadvantage lies in now taking the risk of Kenyatta&apos;s release. The Governors viewshave the support of his Council of Ministers (which includes his most senior officials),of senior members of the Administration (including the Provincial commissioner in the Central Province), of the Commissioner of Police and of representatives ofKikuyu loyalists. In this connexion I attach at Annex A a minute of a meeting ofthe Central Province Advisory Council held on 16th June, 1961.3. The Governors proposal is a logical consequence of previous decisions ofthe Governor and Her Majesty&apos;s Government. The Colonial Policy Committeeagree with his conclusions. It is essential to face this issue from strength and I doubt whether we shall ever be in a better position to do so now when there iswide acceptance both in Kenya and the United Kingdom that Kenyatta&apos;s early release is inevitable.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  July 196159385
Disqualification from Legislative Council4. There is a further point of policy to be considered. Kenyatta is at presentprecluded from standing for election to Legislative Council by two provisions inthe Constitution. The first disqualifies anyone who is under restriction from being elected; the second disqualifies anyone who has served a sentence of imprisonmentexceeding two years imposed by a Court in any part of Her Majesty&apos;s Dominions.The second will still operate after Kenyatta has been released and, as was to beexpected, there has been pressure in Kenya for this provision to be amended.A motion to this effect has been debated and carried in the Kenya LegislativeCouncil. If this provision were revoked or appropriately amended, it may beassumed that an opportunity would soon be found for Mr. Kenyatta to stand asa candidate for the Legislature, and that he would get in. There would then be strong pressure for him to be made Chief Minister. The Governor^ view is that,although the greater part of the British in the Civil Service are ready to acceptKenyatta&apos;s release from restriction, very many of them would feel unwilling on present knowledge to continue their work if he came to a position of authority.He considers that it is, therefore, necessary for Kenyatta to &quot; work his passage &quot;before he can feel confident that there would not be an exodus of British staff ofsuch proportions that it would endanger the whole administration of theGovernment; and he accordingly proposes that (assuming that Kenyatta is nowto be released) his behaviour should be watched for a further period before he,the Governor, makes a recommendation regarding the disqualification in theOrder in Council. I am sure that this is the right line.Presentation5. The Governor has at my request put his proposals regarding Kenyatta&apos;smove to Kiambu and his release from restriction in a despatch suitable for publication. The draft of the despatch is attached as Annex B. If the Governor^recommendations are accepted, there is clearly great advantage in publishing his despatch as a White Paper, particularly in view of the fact that it would make itclear that, on these matters, the Governor has the support of senior members of theAdministration.6. I think it is important that, assuming that the Governor^ recommendations are agreed by the Cabinet, I should make a statement before the House rises. Ithink that it would be wrong to make the statement during the Southern Rhodesianreferendum (since it might affect the outcome) and this would entail making astatement in the week beginning 31st July. I, for my part, would have preferred to make the statement several days before the House rises but it is now clear thatthe dates proposed for the Common Market debate will preclude this; and I accept that it will not be possible to make the statement before Friday, 4th August. Ihave in mind a short statement to the effect that, in a despatch, which I am layingas a White Paper, the Governor has proposed that Kenyatta should be moved toKiambu about the middle of August and that his restriction order should be revokeda few days thereafter; and that with the full support of Her Majesty&apos;s Governmenthe is making a statement to this effect in Nairobi.conclusion.   I now invite my colleagues to agree:(i) that Kenyatta should be moved to Kiambu about the middle of August:(ii) that his restriction order should be revoked a few days thereafter;(iii) that a decision covering the above two decisions should be made in Kenyaon 4th August;(iv) that, at the same time, I should make a statement to the House and lay a white Paper publishing the Governors despatch;(v) that, as proposed by the Governor, consideration of amending the disqualification provision in the Order in Council should be deferred.I. M.Colonial Office, S.W.1,25 th July, 1961.
ANNEX a minute of a Meeting of the Central Province Advisory Council heldon 16th June, 1961Members discussed at length the dilemma of Kenyatta&apos;s release. They andall those who have resisted Mau Mau from the start had hoped Kenyatta would never return to Central Province. They could never therefore themselves sponsorhis return, but in the changed political circumstances in Kenya they have now cometo realise Kenyatta was bound to be released unconditionally on the day of independence if he was not in fact set free earlier. They considered the lesser ofthe two evils was to release him before independence. Members realised also that whereas in their opinion Kenyatta would still constitute a real danger if he wasreturned to the Province, he was also a danger to good government while restrictedin view of the clamour for his release. They considered however that his returnto his homeland should not occur before the new Government was firmly in thesaddle and that on first arrival back in Kiambu District he should be subject to aperiod of local restriction in the same way as other ex-detainees.Members had not been at all happy to hear the Government was to build a house for Kenyatta; nevertheless they noted with satisfaction that it would be aGovernment building on Government land. They were anxious that neither thehouse nor the land should be handed over to Kenyatta as a gift from theGovernment: on the contrary, an alternative to this must be found, e.g., a gift fromKadu, as otherwise a dangerous precedent would be set and other ex-detaineeswould claim similar privileges from the Government.ANNEX draft DespatchRelease of Jomo KenyattaSir,I have the honour to address you on the subject of the release from restriction of Jomo Kenyatta. In 1953 he was sentenced by due process of law to seven years&apos;imprisonment for managing an unlawful society and being a member of it, and theCourt recommended that a restriction order should be made for such a period -asthe Governor-in-Council should decide, to succeed the term of his imprisonment.An order was made accordingly by my predecessor.2. Since I was appointed Governor of Kenya I have informed you in advanceof action which I proposed to take in this matter. On 31st March, 1960, and again on 10th May, 1960,1 stated publicly that it was my view that in the then prevailingcircumstances the release of Jomo Kenyatta would be a danger to security. On1st March, 1961, immediately after the general elections, I said that it was not my view that he should be kept in restriction indefinitely; I did not however proposeto release him until the new Government was working well and until I thought thatthe security risk could be accepted and contained and that the danger which his return presented to the economy and administration and to our whole constitutional progress towards early independence had been minimised. I also then announcedthat he would be restricted at Maralal instead of at Lodwar and that more people would be allowed to visit him. At the time of my formation of the new Governmentbased on elected members of the Kenya African Democratic Union and the NewKenya Party on 18th April, 1961, the following further statement about hisrestriction was issued:&quot; The Governor has agreed that the Government will now begin to build a house for Mr. Jomo Kenyatta and his family on a site to be agreed in Kiambudistrict in readiness for Mr. Kenyatta&apos;s return from Maralal to his home inKiambu in due course.&quot;The house is now nearly completed and is expected to be ready for occupation in about the middle of August.
3. Since his move to Maralal, Kenyatta has spoken freely to the many people who have visited him, journalists, politicians, diplomats, churchmen, writers,relations and friends, of all races and political persuasions. His words and expressedintentions have been moderate and constructive and he has spent much time in trying to effect greater unity among the African political parties and leaders. Hisvery early release is now widely expected throughout Kenya.4. Your predecessor as Secretary of State for the Colonies and my predecessoras Governor of Kenya stated with reference to the Mau Mau rebellion thatirreconcilables would not be allowed back to the Kikuyu Reserve. Only eventscan establish the facts, but since his move to Maralal Kenyatta has given every,indication that he is now in no way irreconcilable to the maintenance of law andorder and to the association of all the peoples of Kenya with its progress to independence in an East African setting based on a sound economy.5. My new Government in Kenya has completed its first meeting the Budgetmeeting in the Legislature with credit and is working well. Within the limits ofthe finances which are available it is also tackling with sound sense the day-to-dayproblems and policy planning in the Ministries and Council of Ministers. It is determined to support me in maintaining law and order. It is making some progressalready in the consideration of the major problems which require honourablesolution before a transfer of power in Kenya, and steps have been taken to initiate,under my Chairmanship, discussions with representatives of the Opposition on constitutional advance and the restoration of confidence in land titles and propertyrights.6. My Security Forces are highly competent and liaison with the Army and royal Air Force in internal security duties has never been better. I am confident that, with my Government behind me, I can accept and contain any extra securityrisk which now remains on Kenyatta&apos;s release. It is arguable that the economy islikely to be more damaged by the uncertainty caused by his continued restriction.The officials in the Government Services are among those who are now widelyexpecting his release and there is general agreement among my senior officers at headquarters and in the field that the timing is correct. We must not endangerby his continued restriction the hopes of a political rapprochement leading towardsearly restoration of confidence and sound constitutional progress. Even those and there are still many who have deeply felt anxieties about the possible consequences of his release have come to realise that in the changed politicalcircumstances in Kenya the wiser counsel is to release him at a time when GreatBritain is responsible for law and order. They realise also that his continuedrestriction is an impediment to good relations and orderly progress.7. The African Elected Members of my Government have continuouslyadvised me that Kenyatta should be unconditionally released. Indeed, they agreedto join the Government in the belief, which was certainly correct, that the formationof a Government would lead to his earlier release. All other members of theGovernment join them in recommending that Kenyatta should be returned toKiambu as soon as the house which is being built for him is ready for occupation.The Council of Ministers recommends that he should be released after only a fewdays&apos; period of limited restriction in Kiambu which will be necessary in order thatthe Police may control the immediate public excitement on his return.8. You will appreciate how much anxious thought I have given to thisquestion which has such weighty consequences for the future of Kenya. I now propose that, if there is no deterioration in the security position, Kenyatta shouldbe moved to the new house, which is being built for him in Kiambu, as soon as it is ready; that he should be under minor restrictions there for a short period only, toenable the authorities to deal with the public excitement which will no doubt be caused by his return, and that thereafter he should be released from restriction;and that I should shortly make an announcement to this effect.

</content>
</cab>
