<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/106/0 images: 164-165</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
tSECRETTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  July 1961C. (61) 119 Copy No.   5827th July, 1961CABINETFINANCIAL SITUATION OF THE UNITED nations memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs when the financial position of the United Nations Organisation was considered on 22nd June, the Cabinet thought it undesirable that the United Kingdom should provide assistance in the-form of loans at a time when our balance of payments wasprecarious. If other countries were to take the initiative in proposing loans, we might perhaps agree to contribute, but our contribution would be considerably less than $15 millions. The Cabinet in conclusion (i) Agreed not to join in any initiative for providing interest-free government loans for the United Nations.(ii) Invited the Foreign Secretary to suggest that the Secretary-General ofthe United Nations Organisation should give further consideration toraising capital funds commercially, possibly by mortgaging the united nations building.(iii) Invited the Foreign Secretary in consultation with the Chancellor of theExchequer to consider the extent to which we should contribute towardssustaining the United Nations operations in the Congo (C.C. (61) 35thConclusions, Minute 5).2. The United Kingdom Mission in New York have discussed with the united nations Controller the prospects of raising funds commercially as a means of tidingthe Organisation over their present difficulties. The present position can besummarised as follows:(i) The Secretary-General would need authority from the General assembly to borrow commercially. At the end of 1960, when certain New Yorkbanks were ready to put up short-term money against the large UnitedStates contribution normally passed in July, an attempt to secure this authority was unsuccessful.(ii) Although authority to seek commercial loans might be obtained at theSixteenth Session this autumn, it is doubtful whether even short-termaccommodation would then be forthcoming to help over the turn ofthe year without some guarantee or security or, at any rate, without some evidence that the Organisation^ finances were on the mend.(iii) There is no reasonable expectation of obtaining long-term commercialloans without guarantees from Governments or collateral security.(iv) The prospects of being able to mortgage the United Nations Headquartersbuilding as security for a commercial loan are not good. This wouldrequire the consent, of the United States Administration, which wouldinvolve Congressional difficulties, and the approval of the general assembly by a two-thirds majority, which might well not be forthcoming.3. My conclusion is that commercial borrowing offers no solution to thefinancial problems of the United Nations, and that the only practical means ofaverting the bankruptcy of the Organisation at the end of this year lies in advances59400
or loans by Governments. This view is shared by the United States Mission to the (United Nations.  They believe also that such loans must be interest free and forlong terms.  If this is to be the solution, we must look to the United States toprovide most of the money.4. An earlier estimate that $75 millions would be needed must now be revised and it seems that, by the end of 1961, it will cost up to $120 millions to put theUnited Nations in the clear that is, to enable them to pay off their currentcjbljlations and to repay money borrowed from the Working Capital Fund, theSpecial Fund and other accounts under the control of the Secretary-General.5. The Americans know that it would be very difficult for us to participate in this kind of solution; but they have told us that if the United Kingdom does not participate they see little chance of other countries doing so; and if no one elsewill participate it is highly unlikely that Congress will vote the money to enablethe United States to bear the cost alone. There is therefore a danger that if west and aside it may be impossible for the United States Government either to lendon an adequate scale themselves or to attract the support of other Governments.6. In these circumstances, our attitude should not be entirely negative. i know that we cannot undertake any commitment which makes new and heavy demands on our foreign exchange resources. On the other hand it is almost impossible to contemplate a break-up of the United Nations on the top of everythingelse which is happening in 1961. I therefore suggest that our Mission in New Yorkshould tell their American colleagues that, while we must leave the initiative tothe United States, we should be prepared to participate to a modest extent in asolution involving long-term loans by several Governments to the United nations organisation. In order to avoid misunderstanding, we should tell the Americansconfidentially what our limit was. I suggest that our Mission should also say thatany long-term loans would be easier to defend if they were not interest-free; andthat a solution on these lines would need to be carefully presented so as to avoid the appearance either of simply making good the defaults of other member governments or of attempting to buy control of the Organisation.7. The financial difficulties of the United Nations are caused primarily by heavy expenditure on the operation in the Congo on top of that incurred by theUnited Nations Emergency Force in the Middle East, unmatched by an adequatefinancial contribution from member States. The reason for the deficit is the refusal of the Soviet bloc and France to pay their shares of the costs in the Congoand of the Soviet bloc and many other countries to contribute their assessed shareof the costs of the United Nations Emergency Force. The measures proposed bythe Americans would not end the Organisation^ difficulties as long as the operations in the Congo and the Middle East continue and the Soviet bloc and others refuseto contribute to their costs. But they would avert the threat to the United Nations&apos;existence and provide time for progress to be made in reducing the need for peace-and-security expenditure on the present scale.H.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,26th July, 1961.

</content>
</cab>
