<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/106/0 images: 192-194</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET&quot;1651   0(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C. (61) 1272nd August, 1961TRADE WITH Japan Memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer at their meeting on 31st July the Economic Policy committee considered two papers by the President of the Board of Trade on tradewith Japan (E. A. (61) 64 and 69).   The Prime Minister has asked that,in view of the political implications of the Presidents proposals, Ishould report the Committee&apos;s conclusions to the Cabinet.Annual Trade Arrangements2.        The agreement made last year with Japan, which ran forthe twelve months ending 31st Miarch, 1961, and was subsequentlyextended to 30th September, 1961, has given us much more and theJapanese much less than we expected.   Japan has progressively removedrestrictions on her imports, and in the first half of this year our exports were 60 per cent up on the same period of I960.   In the sameperiod Japanese exports to us increased by only 20 per cent, and trade:between us now almost balances, whereas in 1958-60 Japan sold us 10-15 millions of goods more each year than we sold to her.3.        The Economic Policy Committee therefore agreed with thePresident that in the negotiations for a new agreement, due to beginlater this month, we must offer the Japanese substantially greater opportunities for thsir exports.   The Committee generally endorsed the proposal to remove all restrictions on a wide range of Japaneseimports - about half of those approved by the Cabinet last year inthe context of a commercial treaty - and to offer considerableincreases in the quotas for most other, goods on which we impose restrictions.   This is on the understanding that the Japanese agreethat the new arrangements should last until 30th September, 1962.4.        Some of these concessions will be criticised by domesticinterests, and in one case - artificial flowers - the President agreedto reconsider, in consultation with the Minister of Agriculture, his proposal to remove all import restrictions.   But the Committeewere clear that most of these criticisms would be unjustified, thatthe Colonies would not suffer and that the proposals as a whole were essential to the continued growth of our exports in the rapidly ex-panding Japanese market.-1-iffCOPY NO. b V*CABINET
Commercial Treaty5. The Cabinet have already agreed that we should resume negotiations for a commercial treaty giving Japan most-favoured-nationrights in respect of quantitative import restrictions, subject to the safeguards that we should maintain restrictions on certain sensitiveproducts and that both sides would have the right in the last resort toimpose or reimpose restrictions on other products if this was necessaryto deal with disruptive competition.   We attached importance to twofeatures of this proposed arrangement -(a) a.ction under it should not be subject to arbitrationunder the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade(G. A. T. T. );   and(b) it would continue so long as either side required.6. The Japanese have now said that they can accept (a), though they want some link with the G. A. T. T.    This might consist of a procedure for consultation with the G. A. T. T.   in the event of disputes,with the possibility of G. A. T. T. recommendations.     But the japanese would not regard it as a breach of our obligations under the commercial treaty or the G. A. T. T. if we were to apply the safeguards inthe face of a G. A. T. T. recommendation to the contrary, and the committee agreed that this Japanese modification of our proposal could be accepted.7. On (b), the Japanese say that they cannot accept a safeguardsarrangement without a time limit.     But they agree that the safeguardsshould form part of the commercial treaty, and propose that it shouldbe valid for five years, with provisions for automatic extension from year to year if neither side denounced it.    They also propose thatrestrictions on items in the sensitive list should not be maintained for more than five years.8. If the Japanese did denounce the treaty and began to floodour market with low-priced goods, we should undoubtedly be justifiedin reimposing quantitative import restrictions whatever our G.A.T.T.obligations might be.    It might also be possible during the course ofthe treaty to work out a procedure for agreed controls by the Japaneseon their exports to us.    The President therefore proposes that he should try to secure a firm life for the treaty of at least seven years and aim toget the best possible terms as regards the duration of restrictions onitems in the sensitive list.9. The Committee agreed with these proposals.    they recognised that certain United Kingdom interests might feel that their protection against cheap Japanese goods was not sufficiently certain;but most of these goods will be subject to a tariff and, if we join theCommon Market, we shall find our partners likely to want to adopt asimilar approach.    The political importance of all this is that theconclusion of a commercial treaty would enable us to disinvokeArticle XXXV of the G. A. T. T. (which enables a member to refuseto apply its provisions to a new member).     For Japan this would be a sign that we no longer regarded her as an outcast.     Economically, acommercial treaty would dispose of the danger of retaliatory-2-SECHE&quot;f
discrimination against us and would enable industry to mount with confidence an effective export promotion campaign in Japan.10. The President of the Board of Trade intends to delaya firm reply to the Japanese proposals until he has consultedindustry.    But he wants to authorise those who will be negotiatingthe annual trade arrangements later this month to tell the Japanesethat we are sympathetically considering their proposals but cannotreach a conclusion until industry has been consulted.    This would help to improve the atmosphere for the negotiations on the tradearrangements.    The Committee agreed with these tactics.Conclusion11. I invite the Cabinet to endorse the Economic PolicyCommittee&apos;s conclusions.S. Li.Treasury Chambers, S, W. 1.2nd August, 1961.-3-

</content>
</cab>
