<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/106/0 images: 272-274</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1961C. (61) 147 Copy No.     583rd October, 1961CABINETANNUAL MEETINGS OF THE INTERNATIONAL MONETARY FUND,THE INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION ANDDEVELOPMENT, THE INTERNATIONAL FINANCE corporation and THE INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT association in 1961Memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer in my capacity as Governor of the International Monetary Fund and of theInternational Bank and its affiliated organisations I was in Vienna for the16th Annual Meetings from 18th to 22nd September. My colleagues may liketo have a brief note of what took place.I. International Monetary Fund2. As regards the I.M.F. our main object at Vienna was to maintain the momentum of the plans for increasing the Fund&apos;s resources on lines put forward by Mr. Jacobsson, the Managing Director, with our support and that of the UnitedStates. His proposals envisage a network of credit arrangements between theFund and the industrialised countries which would enable the Fund to obtainadditional supplies of those currencies particularly needed to finance drawings.3. In spite of the work already done by the Fund staff and the ExecutiveDirectors and the energy with which Mr. Jacobsson himself tried to convince the Press beforehand that success was assured it was not plain sailing. A numberof potential lenders stressed first the need to confine the use of these special creditarrangements to a situation where there was a major threat to a reserve currency and, secondly, that there should be a special procedure to determine when this situation existed. They also stressed the need for &quot; safeguards &quot; to ensure thatcalls on them would take account of their reserve position and not be automaticbut that repayment to them should be immediate if their situations changed. TheFrench were particularly cautious and M. Baumgartner, their Minister of Finance,indicated only that France &quot;could possibly go a little beyond its present outlay,but under certain conditions &quot;. His attitude reflected the usual French suspicion of the Fund as a body dominated by the United States and the United Kingdom.The French have from the first been suspicious of the Jacobsson proposals, whichthey regard as having been put forward as a result of an Anglo-American initiative.The Dutch also emphasised their reservations, but it was noticeable that, withinthe Six, the Germans and the Italians were far more forthcoming.4. There has been some suggestion in the Press that the United Kingdomremained in the background. I do not think this was so. We were able to makea reasonable contribution to the public and private discussions and can be reasonably satisfied with the outcome. Moreover it should be remembered thatthe Jacobsson proposals are very much in accord with the general line which I took in my speech at the Annual Meeting of the Fund a year ago, which was followed up in discussions between the Prime Minister and President Kennedysubsequently.59719HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
^ 5. Intensive work on the details of new arrangements will now start in theFund Board, and !Mr. Jacobsson&apos;s aim is to produce a cut and dried scheme by1.5th December. If he is successful the United States President will be able to announce in his January Message to Congress that the United States is to takethe necessary powers during 1962. Legislation will also be required here if, as now seems certain, the United Kingdom is to take part in the scheme from the outset. But the Bill will be short and, so long as our balance of payments difficultiescontinue, there is no likelihood of any substantial call on us.II. The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and its AffiliatedOrganisations6. One day of the Vienna Meetings was devoted to the affairs of theInternational Bank and its new affiliate the International Development Association(I.D.A.), which has now been in existence one year. While the Bank makes loanson conventional terms, the I.D.A. is now extending 50-year interest-free credits.7. Most of the speakers from under-developed countries stressed their needfor more soft aid of this kind and urged an enlargement of the I.D.A.&apos;s funds.Mr. Eugene Black, the President of the International Bank, and Mr. George Ball,of the United States Administration, also referred to this as something which might become necessary before long. For the United Kingdom, I said that we were bound to be cautious about any immediate new commitment of this kind but thatI hoped we would be in a position to join in increasing the I.D.A.&apos;s resources whenit became necessary.8. Another recurrent theme was the desirability of stabilising commodity prices. The United States and Australia made this point, as well as many of the under-developed countries. But strictly speaking this is a matter outside thecompetence of either the International Monetary Fund or the International Bank.9. The Annual Meeting of the International Finance Corporation completed the proceedings. This is another affiliate *of* the International Bank. It has a capital of $100 millions, and is devoted to helping investments in private enterprisesin under-developed countries. This year the Governors amended its Articles sothat the Corporation can now make equity investments in such enterprises. TheEconomic Secretary, Treasury, among others, had spoken in favour of this course at last year&apos;s meeting. We think this is a useful move and will make theCorporation^ activities more flexible, but of course it is a relatively smallorganisation and of limited importance.S. L.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1,29th September, 1961.
5. Intensive work on the details of new arrangements will now start in the.Fund Board, and Mr. Jacobsson&apos;s aim is to produce a cut and dried scheme by15th December. If he is successful the United States President will be able to announce in his January Message to Congress that the United States is to takethe necessary powers during 1962. Legislation will also be required here if, as now seems certain, the United Kingdom is to take part in the scheme from theguhset. But the Bill will be short and, so long as our balance of payments difficultiesontinue, there is no likelihood of any substantial call on us.II. The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and its AffiliatedOrganisations6. One day of the Vienna Meetings was devoted to the affairs of theInternational Bank and its new affiliate the International Development Association(I.D.A.), which has now been in existence one year. While the Bank makes loanson conventional terms, the I.D.A. is now extending 50-year interest-free credits.7. Most of the speakers from under-developed countries stressed their needfor more soft aid of this kind and urged an enlargement of the I.D.A.&apos;s funds.Mr. Eugene Black, the President of the International Bank, and Mr. George Ball,of the United States Administration, also referred to this as something which might become necessary before long. For the United Kingdom, I said that we were bound to be cautious about any immediate new commitment of this kind but thatI hoped we would be in a position to join in increasing the I.D.A.&apos;s resources whenit became necessary.8. Another recurrent theme was the desirability of stabilising commodity prices. The United States and Australia made this point, as well as many of the under-developed countries. But strictly speaking this is a matter outside thecompetence of either the International Monetary Fund or the International Bank.9. The Annual Meeting of the International Finance Corporation completed the proceedings. This is another affiliate *of- the International Bank. It has a capital of $100 millions, and is devoted to helping investments in private enterprisesin under-developed countries. This year the Governors amended its Articles sothat the Corporation can now make equity investments in such enterprises. TheEconomic Secretary, Treasury, among others, had spoken in favour of this course at last year&apos;s meeting. We think this is a useful move and will make theCorporation^ activities more flexible, but of course it is a relatively smallorganisation and of limited importance.S. L.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,29th September, 1961.CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
