<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/114/0 images: 105-105</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONTROL OP IRISH BUTTER DURING THE WHITER MONTHS iCTORANDM BY THE FOOD CONTROLLER .In order to conserve the supplies of butter for Ireland during the winter months, an arrangement was made by the Irish Department of Agriculture under which it was agreed that about 4,000 tons of butter should be put into cold store at a price which would enable the butter to be retailed at 5/4d per lb. The price of butter in Ireland is now advancing substantially and the Irish Department of Agriculture are of opinion that the holders of the cold store butter will not adhere to the agreement hut will attempt to obtain excessive and unfair profit by selling at a higher retail price than was implied in the agreement.Under a decision of the Cabinet, there has been since February no control over the prioea of Irish butter, but the Irish Department of Agriculture feel that In the circumstances referred to above, it is very desirable to reimpose maximum prices for sale in Ireland and restriction of export from Ireland except under licence.   The Profiteering Aot is stated to be inoperative in Ireland and, therefore, no help can bo obtained in that way.It should be remembered that Ireland does not receive any supplies of the foreign and colonial butter imported by the Ministry of Pood.    Before the war Ireland did receive supplies of imported butter.    The maximum retail price of Government butter in Greet Britain is 3s* 4d. at present, arid it, therefore, soems desirable that Ireland should be helped towards the aohiovement of a prioe somewhere in that neighbourhood.The Chief Secretary for Ireland ooncurs in the recommend-ation which the Department has made.I ask. therefore, that the Irish Department should be givon authority to relmposo the specified restrictions.(sgd,) CHARLES A, MoCURET25th October 1920,ADDENDUM,Since the above memorandum was prepared, I have been informed by the Department of Agriculture that their fear has been realised, and that three of the largest wholesalers of butter have disregarded the voluntary arrangement and exported their butter, thus aggravating the Irish shortage.

</content>
</cab>
