<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/114/0 images: 152-156</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic MajestyPrinted for the Cabinet.  October 1920.jesty&apos;s Government.]SECRET. C.P.-2015.CABINET.SPECIAL WEEKLY REPORTS ONUNEMPLOYMENT.No. 2.WEEK ENDED OCTOBER 22, 1920.T. J. MACNAMABA,Ministry of Labour.
NOTE ON UNEMPLOYMENT SITUATION IN UNITED KINGDOM ONOCTOBER 22, 1920.The Trade Union figure of unemployment for July 1914 was 2-8 per cent.; throughout 1919 it ranged between 1-6 per cent, in September and 3-2 per cent, in December, and averaged 2-4 per cent, for the year. The figures for 1920 are: for the end of January, 2-9 per cent,; February, 1-6 per cent.; March, 1-1 per cent.; April, 0-9 per cent.; May, 1-1 per cent.; June, 1-2 per cent.; July 1-4 per cent.; August, 1-6 per cent.; and September 2-2 per cent.Numbers on Registers of Employment Exchanges.	..... 1920.					27th Aug.	24th Sept.	8th Oct.	15th Oct.	Men  Civilians Ex-service men Boys Women Girls	86,476 142,600 17,608 58,982 17480	73,644 178,488 16,226 61,149 17,135	82,609 186,711 17,004 68,922 18,034	85,451 190,136 17,135 - 74,416 18,216	Figures for October 22 not yet available.Total  ..	818,096	346,642	373,280	.    385,354	Summary of Claims to Out-of-Work Donation or Unemployment Insurance.Division.	8th October.	22nd October.London and South Eastern..	98,655.	. 113,470South Western	25,173	&quot;26,529South Midlands and Eastern	18,392	21,316West Midlands   ..	26,814	44,055Y orkshire and East Midlands	18,970	35,662North Western	39,619	64,661Northern	11,081	25,298Wales	6,025	13,351Total: England and Wales.....	244,729	344,342Scotland  ..	19,656	27,575Ireland	23,906	26,858Unemployment has greatly increased throughout the country owing to the coal strike. The trades first affected have been iron and steel, engineering, and ship-building. The number unemployed may be expected to increase rapidly so long as the strike lasts.&quot; Apart from&apos; the increase in unemployment indicated by the exchange figures, short time is being extensively worked as a result of the strike.The slackness in other trades which had already been reported continues, and the improvements in the boot and shoe trade which had been expected have not yet taken place.
Summary of Reports of Works Closed, Staff Reduced, and Workpeople on short Time up to October 22nd, 1920.,(Establishments employiug 200 workpeople or over.)Industry.Discharged at Works closed.Discharged through Staff reduction.Placed on Short-time.Iron and steel manufacturing Engineering and shipbuilding Textile trades Other trades29,525 6,29510,303 8,10074,851 24,792 2,515 12,1754,620 30,600 83,415 24,721Totals54,223114,333143,356Press announcements have been made indicating the Governments policy for the construction of arterial roads, and arrangements are being made for the allocation of the labour supply for the scheme among the districts concerned.Note.-In the reports that follow with regard to the various districts the detailed notes on towns with greatest unemployment are omitted this week, and attention in confined in the main to the effects of the coal strike.[4648]B 2
SALIENT FEATURES OF REPORTS FROM DIVISIONALCONTROLLERS.Week ended October 22, 1920.(1.) LONDON AND SOUTH-EASTERN DIVISION.Total Live Register is as follows : Men.........    86,074     Previous, week         ... 84,598Women       ......    27,995     Previous week...... 25,689Juveniles.......    12,397     Previous week ...     ... 11,784126,466 122,071. Unemployment still increasing in this division but no evidence that the coal strike has had very considerable effect as yet. Factories of all descriptions are discharging workers or adopting short time. Among the principal discharges are Warne and Company (indiarubber merchants), Barking, 700 workpeople; Messrs. Pinks (jam manufacturers), Borough, 1,000 women. Short time is being adopted by Ediswan Electric Company, Ponders End, affecting 4,400 workers; Indiarubber and Gutta Percha Company, Silvertown, affecting 3,000 workers; and Lyles Sugar Refineries, Silvertown, affecting 2,000 workpeople. Depression in the shipping trade is causing increased unemployment at Tilbury Docks. Serious unemployment still prevails among juveniles.The events of Monday the 18th in Whitehall are known to the Cabinet. A smaller procession visited Camberwell Town Hall on 21st October and sent a deputation to the Council. The International Ex-Service Men&apos;s Union visited Shepherds Bush exchange during the week with regard to the discharge of civilians, and a threat was also made to burn the exchange at Willesden.(2.) SOUTH-WESTERN DIVISION.This division at present hardly affected by miners&apos; strike. Live Register increased by 221. Several large firms expected to close down shortly in Bristol. Prohibition of export of coal is holding up ships at Southampton, Portsmouth, Weymouth, Plymouth and Avonmouth. No other developments expected before next week. A number of clothing firms working short time.(3.) WALES.Transport workers and coal trimmers are affected by prohibition of coal export and their position is becoming serious. Steel and tin-plate trades are also affected but no large discharges are taking place at present. Donation claims have risen from 2,217 to 4,905 between the 15th and 20th October, and Unemployment Books lodged have increased from 3,325 to 7,369 in the same period. Five fuel works, 3 steel works and 1 brick works have closed down. A number of other factories are partly closed.(4.) NORTH-WESTERN DIVISION.Apart from increases directly due to the coal strike, reports indicate unemploy-ment increasing less rapidly, and 13 exchanges reported decreases in Live Register on the 15th October. Total Live Register was 40,535 on the 15th October as against 39,337 for the previous week. Coal strike has severely affected iron and steel smelting industries and&apos; extensive stoppages have taken place in Warrington (2,000 men discharged by Pearson and Knowles, and 3,500 by Partington Steel and Iron Works). St. Helens (British Insulated and Helsby Cable Company discharged 3,500).  The restriction of coal consumption to 50 per cent, has resulted in a large
number of firms adopting short-time working in the engineering industry. Textile trades have also adopted short time to a very large extent. It is expected that early next week, the whole of the cotton industry will be on short time and serious effects will be felt in engineering.(5.) SCOTLAND.Unemployment created by miners strike so far mainly confined to Lanarkshire Glasgow only partially affected, and employers are doing everything possible to maintain work. Engineering and shipbuilding industries expected to continue for some weeks. Iron and steel industry seriously affected (6,000 steel workers unemployed at Motherwell, 2,000 at Rutherglen, 2,500 at Springburn, and 4,000 at Parkhead). Additional discharges will take place next week. Seven hundred workers discharged from sugar refineries at Greenock and 1,000 from calico printing works at Alexandria. Short time working is being introduced in jute industry, and similar measures expected in woollen and hosiery trades next week. Two paper works in Mid-Lothian are discharging all employees, and another paper firm at Musselburgh is on short time. The total number of persons claiming out-of-work donation has risen from 17,000 to 35,000 in a week.(6.) NORTHERN DIVISION.This division seriously affected by strike. Consett iron works have damped down blast furnaces, thus rendering 6,000 men unemployed. The Darlington Forge Company have discharged 700 men and boys. Considerable unemployment prevails at Middlesborough, where 15,000 claims for donation have been made, South Bank, Stockton, Thornaby, West Hartlepool, and Workington.(7.) YORKSHIRE AND EAST MIDLANDS DIVISION.Unemployment produced by coal strike not as yet so serious as anticipated, being largely confined to iron and steel industry.&apos; On the 15th October, Live Registers showed 25,027 applicants, and figure was increased by nearly 8,000 on the 21st October. Exchanges principally affected are Sheffield, Attercliffe, Leeds and Armley, Rotherham and Scunthorpe. Increases mainly due to discharges from iron and steel works. Engineering employers working short time wherever possible. Increase of short-time working is also reported in woollen and worsted industries Employment in tanning had taken a turn for the better, but, owing to shortage of coal supplies, the recovery will be retarded. Short time is increasing in lace industry, where strike in plain net section has just been settled.(8.) WEST MIDLANDS DIVISION.The total number of workpeople claiming donation and unemployment insurance benefit on the 21st October had risen to 42,314 (an increase of 16,571 since the 15th October). Coal strike has not yet had very serious effect in this division, but unemployment gradually increasing. Iron and steel industries and pottery works principally affected, and many are closing down or resorting to short time working.(9.) SOUTH MIDLANDS AND EASTERN DIVISION.General trade depression has been accentuated by coal strike, but no considerable unemployment as yet. The anticipated improvement in the boot and shoe industry has been postponed by coal strike. General slackness in hosiery, wholesale clothing, and straw hat industries continues. Several firms are working short time. It is anticipated that all iron stone mines in the Northampton area will have to close down shortly. In all districts where abnormal unemployment occurs L.E.C&apos;s are being urged to appoint special sub-committees on which local authorities are invited to appoint members.

</content>
</cab>
