<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/114/0 images: 284-288</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
A, f &apos; i) .&apos;    237(THIS DOCUMENT IS TEE PROPERTY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOTOHNLMT).Enquiry into the olasses of ex-Service men in the gristol area receiving Cut-;of-\7o^ Donation at15th September,1920.secret note by the Minister of Labour.With reference to Cabinet 43 (20) Conclusion 4 (b), CP. 036.     i circulated in CU?. 1966 and 1966(a) the results of an examination of the classes of ex-Service men in the London area who were in receipt of 0ut-of-7/ork Donation on the 15th September.    An analysis has now been made on similar lines in the case of Bristol, and I attach for the information of my colleagues a memorandum detailing the main results. The memorandum shows clearly(a)       The cases examined at Bristol are drawn from the various branches of the Service in proportions substan-tially similar to those which obtained in the London cases The details of servioe abroad also show substantially similar results.    The conclusion reached in the case of London, that the men in receipt of Out-of-work Donation cannot be regarded as a class whose War service has been of a comparatively privileged nature, is borne out in the case of Bristol.(b) Again a very large.proportion of the men are unskilled, and their distribution by ages is very similar to the distribution in the London cases.(c) The average amount of unemployment(excluding furlough) whioh has been experienced by the men receiving Out-af-Work D6nation at Bristol is 28 weeks as against 25 weeks in the case of London.Ministry of Labour. (3gd.) I. J. M4CKAMARA.30th October,1920.
EX SERVICE lO ON OUT-OP-WORK DONATION A?15th SgPgjggR, BRISTOL.The number of oases dealt with of persons on Out-of-Work Donation at Bristol at 1.5th September, 1920 was 2,60$, of whom 721 were disabled and 1,888 non-disabled.   In the following Table these are analysed according to the main Branches of the Forces in which they served :-&apos;................&quot;............. Branch of Servioe. ,V i-   i lji .,- . &apos;in u i&apos;a        ir&apos;i 11      tit   Ti    &apos;v &apos; &apos; &apos; n&apos;-  -4	Disabled.	-Non-Disabled.	- Total,. ,,,,            :.....,. .,.-,-rrHavy	40	134	174-Infantry.	457.	c.&apos;: &quot;i -* ^ i.	1448Departmental Oorps.	75	229	30*Artillery.	30	127,	167hngineers.	57	im	185Other Array Jorps.	32	149	181Labour Ooros.  -	j       30	bo	1        S3 i i                              \lierchant Seamen.	i	r 51 I	-51Women1s Corps.  -	i	i 1 6	6TOTAL i7211888260(.The greatest proportion was naturally furnished by the infantry,, both among disabled (infantry 63;3 as against olp in the case of London), and non- disabled (Infantry 52$ as against 51g in London).An analysis of the extent to which these persons served abroad is given below;-
23.9j plsabled,		M on-Disabled .	Total,No servioe abroad,,	129	i r	604Servioe abroad			Under 6 months	93	55	1486 and under 18 months	111	180	2941 year and under 2 years	117	 35	452P      IT            It            tl         ft         II	131	347	4783 1 -n      &quot;      &quot;     4     &quot;	85	292	3774 years and over.		Btfl     -	256.Total, Servioe abroad.	&quot; 692	1413	2005Grand Total,                                J	721	1888	2609Of the total, 76 per oent served abroad, tho proportion being 75 per oent for non-disabled and 82 per,oent for disabled (London 8&amp;jo served abroad,80/6 of the non**&amp;isable&amp; and 892 of the disabled).      As in the oase of London thoio was no greet differenoe in the proportions of those serving abroad for 1, 2 and 3 years respectively.The figures are further analysed in tho following Table to show the type of polioy held	Holding original polioies.	Holding extension polioies.	Total,Disabled Non-disabled-	187 534	772 1116	959 1650TOTAL.	721	1888	2509 &apos;About two-thirds of the total were holding extension polioies, but whereas among non-disabled the percentage was 59, among disabled it was 74.&apos;   The proportion holding extension polioies is therefore considerably higher than.in the oase of London, where slightly less than a half were holding this type of polioy.
Tho 2,6()(j persons were also analysed according to the prinoipal industries under v,hioh they have been classified sinoe their return to oivil life.       nearly a quarter of the total were classified as general labourers, whilst, of a further fifth in the transport groups most would also be unskilled.   It may safely be assumed that more than 50&apos; per cent of the total were unskilled.In the following Table the 2,609 persons are distributed by age groupsAge Groups,	Disabled.	,- U on-disabled,	Total.Under 20 years.	10	53	63 120 to 24 years *	211	811	i 1022,      j25 to 29 years.	148	388	47330 to 39 years.	174	356    &apos;	530^40 years and over.	178 mi    J.U1  nil mi in i &apos; n i rji ii liil	343	521Total.	7E1	1888	2609   - -tm ii,..Mil.ru   i   &apos; m ., , .HM.I  i iIt will be seen that the greatest proportion of persons on donation was among those of under 25 years of age, nearly 42 per oent. of the total being in this group (as against 38.3$ in the case of London), but while among disabled men the per-oentage was only 30, amongnon-disabled men it amounted to 46. The proportion of the total number under 30 years of age was 60 per cent.(London 60 o 5yli)The following Sable gives a brief sugary of post-discharge unemployment:&quot;&quot;period of ^employment.	BuTIdTng&quot; &amp; Oonstn. of Works.	Engineering and Ironfounding,	Trans-port. i.i*(r***^ i(.ji. ^ju .i if	General Labour-ers.	Others.	Totalader 10 weeks.	37	59	50	57	175	3780 &amp; under 20 weeks	22	47	60	82	166	3770 &quot;      &quot;   30    &quot;	40	68	67	103	199	4770 &quot;      w   40    it	23	54	72	70	181	4000 &quot;      &quot;   50    &quot;	31	36	-53	68	123 ,	3110 &quot; -    &quot; 100    &quot;	35	39	120	206	169	569!0 weeks &amp; over.	4	4	29	36	24	97* Total. __	192	307	451	622	103? L_____________.........	i 2609A
/Taking the moan    of eaoh duration group   for whioh figures ere available it Is found that nearly 100,000/weeks of unemploy-ment have been experienced by the 2,609 persons on Out-of-work Donation at Bristol at 15th September, an average of 38 weeks, excluding the month&apos;s furlough,   (This is ^^^^^ ^Tlg^eT than the average in the London fjMj^ exoluHnffTurloupFi.)     I3.i&quot;tne oase oFno5T*5tIa oXecTijien ^e average, after aITowInJ&quot;for furlough, was 30 weeks (Lcndon E  weeks), while in the oase of disabled men it rose to 44 weeks (London 36 weeks). The percentage who   experienced up to 20 weeks unemployment&apos; was 29; for 20 and under 30 weeks  3; for 40 and under 100 weeks 34; and for 100 weeks and over 4.    In 569 oases or more than one-fifth of the total, the amount of unemployment extended over a period of between 50 and 100 weeks, while in 97 oases over 100 weeks unemploy-ment had been experienced.   It is noticeable that among general labourers and in the transport trades, whioh consist largely of unskilled labour, the highest percentage was in the duration groups of 5o and under 100 weeks unemployment.An analysis of the extent to which men have remained in their pre-war oooupations has been made in 2071 oasea, and it is found that in only 1311 oases are the men registered in their pre-servioe oooupations.   The proportion of men still in pre-service oooupations is 67 per oent in the oase of non-disabled men, and 53 per oent among disabled men.   There is a noticeable .increase iff the number classified as labourers,&quot;&quot;the Yoiais for men now regTsTeTeT a &quot;&quot;&apos; builders1 labourers, engineering labourers and general labourers showing an increase of nearly 34 per&apos; cent, aa compared with the pre-servioe members registered as such.     It will be remembered that the London analysis showed a similar marked tendency to change from skilled to unskilled work.

</content>
</cab>
