<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/114/0 images: 309-311</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
:iHIS DOCUMENT IS TH3.IR0EBBTY OF HIS BBIIAMMIC MfcJiSSEf&apos;S 30VERllMStra,)ONFIDBNTIAl. Copy No.  o30 A B I fl B t.^P.-P.04g.LEAGUE OS&apos;   NATIONS. DRAFT RULES OF PROCEDURE FOR THIi ASSEMBLY OFTHE LEAGUE OF NATIONS.Memorandum by the Foreign Office. 9E7/927/9B)        (circulated for information)The following draft rules of Procedure drawn up by the Secretariat of the League are the only ones calling fur comment from the Foreign Office. Article 9,m-mMm^_^    The Secretary General or his deputies may bring before the Assembly reports on any question under discussion. If this means, as it appears to do, that the Secretary-General is authorised to present his own views on any   subject he chooses, the arrangement is, it is suggested, dangerous and improper and would go a long way towards constituting the Secretary-General the chief adviser of the League,   It is most important      prevent this against the time when the post of Secretary-General may be held by a person belonging tc a Power not friendly to us and not averse from intrigues.   It is suggested that when the draft rules come up for discussion, the British representatives should propose to make it clear that whilst the Secretary-General should naturally bring up any paper or re-, orts communicated to the League, he should have no authority to put forward reports en his uwn unless charged by the Assembly or the Council t* do so. Article 15._provides that the proceedings of the committees should not be recorded in Minutes. . The wisdom of such a rule is doubtful.   There are sure to be Committees of whose proceedings it will be important to havo an authoritative record.   At the Peace Conference in Paris the whole of the frontier settlementswer e
were worked out in the Committees, and it would have been most unfortunate if no minutes had been kept.   The quo sti on whether minutes can or should be dispensed with in any particular Committee depends upon the nature oi&quot; its work.   The British representatives at the Assembly should, it is suggested, propose that the Committee themselves should, in each case, decide whether their proceedings should be recorded or not.   Alternatively, the point could be decided by the Assembly when appointing the Committee. Article 20.^_____      The first paragraph provides that the decisionsof the Assembly shall be taken by a unanimous vote of the members of the League represented at the meeting &quot;unless otherwise provided by the Covenant, or by the provisions of a Treaty&quot;oThis differs from Article 5 of the Covenant, which reads:-&quot;except where otherwise e snares sly provided in this Covenant or by the terms of the present T:.^:ly;;*As the Covenant is inserted in a XL the Peace Treaties the Covenant version, in effect, requires unanimity except where provided in one of the Peace Treaties; whereas the wording of the draft Rules of Procedure contemplates something clearly different.There is, it is true, a similar modification made in the Rules of Procedure of the Council, but in that case the provision was convenient, because there are clauses in certain of the Treaties, other than the Peace Treaties, signed at Paris, which provide for a decision of the Council to be taken by a majority. This slight alteration in wording in tho Council rules was there-fore necessary In order to enable the provisions in the Treaties in question to be worked.   As far as is known, however, there is nc provision in any existing Treaty, (other than a peace treaty) which provides for a decision to be taken by a majority of the Assembly, so that a similar modification in the Rules of procedure for
for the Assembly is unnecessary, and it is of doubtful wisdom to encourage States to insert in future Treaties a provision whioh would be contrary to Article 5 of the Covenant.mti OFFICE. S.tf.1.27th October, 19 30.

</content>
</cab>
