<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/114/0 images: 612-637</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY.New Series, Vol. II, No. 20. 13 11.20.orI L t ! 1h l--[ihis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.]INISTRY OF labour weekly REPORT.13th November, 1920.PART I.-THE LABOUR SITUATION. PART II.-THE WORK OF THE MINISTRYPrepared by Intelligence Division.CONTENTS.Part I.-The Labour Situation.Week ending the 9th November, 1920.The General Situation- page general Survey of the Week   ...... 552Features op the Week General Topics............ 553Industrial and Other Organisations   ... 554Trade Union Topics    ......... 555Features op the Week continued.Ex-Service Men.........International Kelations of LabourNegotiations and Disputes Demands and NegotiationsStrikes and Lock-Outs......Settlements and Agreements. ...page555 556.557 557558Part II.-The Work oe the Ministry.Week ending the 6th November, 1920.Industrial Relations Department. pageArbitration and Conciliation  Awards   ...............Agreements and Settlements   ...Interpretations and Rulings   ......Questions Pending and Miscellaneous ...Industrial Councils  Joint Standing Industrial Councils-Reports.........   . ...Interim Industrial Reconstruction Com-mittees Reports...............General Department. Trade Boards-Proceedings of Trade Boards ......Fixing and Variation of Minimum Rates (b 16626)  1100  11/20 h &amp; s Ltd.560 560 560 560561563563 564pageEmployment and Insurance Department Employment Exchanges       ...... 566Local Employment Committees ... 568 Discharged and Disabled Sailors andSoldiers        ...     ......... 569Out-of-work Donation and Unemploy-ment Insurance Benefit      ...... 569Juvenile Branch............ 570Appointments and Civil Liabilities Department General   ......     ;........     570Appointments   .........     ...     571Business and Professional Training   ...     571Training Department Industrial Training     ...     ......     571Appendix     ...............     575
PART I-THE LABOUR SITUATION.THE GENERAL SITUATION.General Survey of the Week.The resumption of work in the coal mines of Great Britain, in the course of the six days with which this Beport deals, has proceeded on the whole quietly, and is now practically complete. In one or two pits, however, difficulties have occurred, and the resumption of work has been delayed. Trouble has been threatened in Manchester, and a strike has taken place in the Potteries, in the tramway services,Jon the question of Ithe resumption, after the close of the strike, of the working of the guaranteed 48-hour week.The resignations of Messrs. Brace and Hartshorn from all their offices, both local and national, in the miners&apos; movement, illustrates the severe strain of the coal strike upon the internal machinery of the miners&apos; organisation.Several other events of importance in the purely industrial sphere have taken place in the course of the week. The position of railway shopmen. An important agreement has been arrived at between the Electrical Trades Union and the National Federation of Electrical Associations have come to an agreement with regard to conditions of apprenticeship. Much progress has been made towards a final agreement in the wages negotiations in the printing trades, which have been proceeding since the . beginning of last month. In the commercial road transport industry no further strikes have occurred, and amicable negotiations are proceeding in many centres. The position in the West Riding of Yorkshire is complicated.* Attention may be drawn to the strike of members of the Guild of Insurance Officials employed by the General Accident, Fire and Life Assurance Corporation, Ltd., which is the second strike organised by this union.There are two events of importance to record with regard to the progress of the various measures intended to remedy the unemployment position. The 8th November was the day on which the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920, came into actual operation ; and &quot; Obligation Week &quot; was inaugurated by H.R.H. the Prince of Wales in his speech at the Mansion House on the 5th November. The unemployment position, as a whole, is causing much anxiety.Negotiations with the building trades operatives are still proceeding with a view to securing the further employment of eX-Service men on the National Housing Scheme.In the House of Commons, on the 9th November, the Ministry of Health (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill received its second reading and was committed to a Standing Committee. The Minister of Transport introduced, on the 8th, an Unemployment (Relief Works) Bill, to make better provision for the employment of unemployed persons by facilitating the acquisition of, and entry upon, lands required for works of public utility. The Women and Young Persons (Employment in Lead Processes) Bill passed through the remaining stages in the House of Commons on the 5th November and was read the first time in the House of Lords on the 9th.* See p. 558 below.
FEATURES OF THE WEEK.General Topics.Labour and Ireland. In consequence of the situation created by the refusal of railway employees to handle or convey Government traffic, and by a strike of boilermakers, which has now lasted for two months, and has prevented the execution of necessary repairs, the Midland Great Western Railway Co. have announced their intention of closing down on the 21st November, and have issued notices to approximately 3,800 of their staff, terminating their employment by that date. A general conference of all grades of railway workers and others has been convened by the Irish Labour Party and Trades Union Congress for the 9th November, when the situation will be considered with the assistance of representatives of the national executive of the National Union of Railwaymen.The situation in Belfast remains practically unchanged. The Monthly Journal for November of the Amalgamated Society of Carpenters, Cabinet Makers and Joiners reports that a certain number of their members obeyed the instructions of the executive, and withdrew their labour from the yards where victimisation had taken place. In the case of one firm, Messrs. McLaughlin and Harvey, Ltd., the union have been informed that the restrictions are withdrawn, and that their members may work there without being sub-mitted to any political or religious test. The report also states that the members who are now expelled from the society have placed their case before a solicitor, who is secretary to the Ulster Unionist Council, and who intends to challenge the right of the society to expel these members.Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920. Negotiations are proceeding between the National Union of Railwaymen and the Ministry of Labour, as the railwaymen desire exclusion from the Act. Mr. C. T. Cramp, the industrial secretary of the union, has circularised branches advising members to withhold application for unemployment books, and not to sign any documents in connection with the scheme. Before an employment can be excepted, the Minister requires to be satisfied that the railwaymen concerned are not subject to dismissal,. except for misconduct, or for neglect in the performance of their duties, or unfitness to perform them, and that the terms and conditions on which they are engaged make it unnecessary that they should be insured.  Difficulties have arisen in this connection^Mr. J. Bromley, of the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen, and Mr. A. G. Walkden of the Railway Clerks&apos; Association, are also taking part in the negotiations.At a mass meeting of the Stock Exchange Clerks&apos; Guild, on the 8th November, a scheme for contracting out of the Act was adopted.The National Alliance of Employers and Employed, in view of the prevailing unemploy-ment and the possibilities of an increase in the near future, are urging the Government to take action as follows&quot; (1) To pass immediate legislation to enable unemployment benefit to be paid as from the 8th November under the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920, irrespective of the contributions payable under Section 5 of the Act, and to make the restrictions of 8 and 15 weeks, respectively, inapplicable until the 31st December, 1920, extending this privilege from time to time during the industrial emergency; (2) to make special arrangements for the supply of available unemployed labour to schemes or contracts, whether under the control of the Government, municipalities or private persons, which are of a sound economic nature, where such schemes or contracts are held up for want of labour, and that union rates of wages be guaranteed in all such cases; (3) to call upon each industry to measure its own unemployment, compared with its nearest normal period, and to urge upon employers and trade unions concerned that they must come together and arrange schemes foT the division of available work; (4) to arrange that any balance of labour still unabsorbed be referred to district councils, which shall consist of employers and trade unionists, and which the National Alliance are prepared to provide, to arrange for temporary measures of employment in conjunction with municipalities and district authorities.&quot;Cotton Textile Industry. On the 5th November a meeting of the General Committee of the Federation of Master Cotton Spinners&apos; Associations was held at Manchester to discuss the subject of short-time working in spinning mills.t Early in October a ballot was taken, and in the Egyptian section, the owners of 86 per cent, of the spindles voted in favour of short time, but in the American section the owners of only 79 per cent, of the spindles so voted.  Consequently, as the votes of the owners of not less than 80 per cent, of the* It has now been decided that railwaymen who are excepted from unemployment insurance under Part II. of the Insurance Act, 1911, shall also be excepted from the provisions of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920.t See this Report, Vol. II, No. 17, 23rd October, p. 482.(b 16626) 4 B 2
spindles are required to carry such a proposal, the Egyptian section alone went on short time. The position was reviewed at the meeting on the 5th November, and it was decided that, in view of the stoppages that had already occurred, chiefly because of the miners&apos; strike and the restriction of coal consumption, the question should be deferred for another month. It was also decided that &apos;a special meeting of the members of the General Committee interested in the Egyptian section should be held on the 9th November to consider whether it is desirable to extend the organised curtailment of production after the 15th November.Relief of Unemployment. It is reported that the Ministry of Health have asked the London County Council to permit H.M. Office of Works to undertake the development of the Castelnau housing estate, and to employ for the purpose unskilled ex-Service men, who would thereby receive the necessary training. The project depends upon an agree-ment being arrived at between the Government and the trade unions.In the Isle of Thanet unemployment is very serious owing to the closing down of the port of Bichborough. At a conference of local authorities and labour organisations at Eamsgate on the 6th November, Sir Frank Howard, chairman of the Disposals Board, stated that there were proposals for the sale of the port. A resolution was passed calling upon the Government to take steps to develop the port in order to absorb the unemployed.Industrial and Other Organisations.National Federation of Building Trades Operatives-Tine outcome of the meeting between the deputation of the Emergency Committee of the Federation and the Minister of Health, which took place on the 3rd November, to discuss the government&apos;s proposals to introduce a large number of ex-Service men into the building industry, * was the appoint-ment of a committee representative of both sides. The committee is to go fully into the details of the proposals, and into the demand of the operatives for adequate guarantees against future unemployment if the principle of dilution is admitted, with the object of arriving at an agreed scheme for presentation to a further joint conference on the 9th November. A scheme of guarantees in the shape of insurance against unemployment has been drafted on behalf of the Government. If this is accepted at the joint conference, it will then have to be submitted to the unions affiliated to the National Federation of Building Trades Operatives.The death took place last week of Mr. William Bradshaw, general secretary of the Federation.  His successor has not yet been appointed.Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain. The resignation of Mr. W. Brace, M.P., and Mr Vernon Hartshorn, M.P., from their official positions in the Federation has been announced. Mr. Brace, who was president of the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation, has agreed to accept the post of Labour Adviser to the Department of Mines, under the Board of Trade, and will take up his duties almost immediately. Mr. Hartshorn was a member of the executive council.of the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation. It is generally understood that the resig-nation of these two officials is largely due to the hostile attitude of the rank and file towards the leaders - conduct of the miners&apos; case during the recent strike, and to the indication of a fundamental difference of opinion by the results of the ballot in South Wales on the proposed terms of settlement. Mr. Brace&apos;s acceptance of a post under the Government will involve his retirement from the Labour Party and a by-election in his constituency, Abertillery. Mr. Hartshorn, it is believed, intends to retain his connection with the Labour Party, and to devote his time to the political rather than to the industrial side of the party&apos;s programme.Union of Post Office Workers. The Postmaster-General has recently been asked by the executive of the union to put into force a resolution passed by the members at a national conference, to the effect that, in future, any concessions or increased remunera-tion obtained through the action of the union should be granted only to those postal workers who are members of the union. During the past two years this policy, known among trade unionists as the policy of &quot; benefits for members only,&quot; has been the subject of constant discussion among associations of Post Office workers. It was adopted by the Australian Post Office in 1914, and has also been accepted by other Government depart-ments in Australia. The Postmaster-General has refused to accede to the union&apos;s request, on the ground that such action is both undesirable and impracticable. The union, however, are still pressing their claim, and contend that a policy which has been adopted
elsewhere, and is still in force after some years&apos; trial, can hardly be impracticable. It is not expected, however, that the Postmaster-General will be induced to alter his decision.The Post Office Engineering Union, the second largest of the postal associations, would appear to have accepted the Postmaster-General&apos;s decision, as their reply to the suggestion that the union should adopt the policy of &quot; benefits for members only &quot; has been, in accordance with the decision of their recent conference, to inaugurate a campaign for the elimination of non-unionists from the engineering section of the postal service.National Union of Teachers. A national delegate conference of the union was held in London on the 6th November, to consider the Burnham Committee&apos;s report on the salaries of teachers in elementary schools. * The delegates, who attended from all parts of the country, had before them the alternative of accepting or rejecting the report. The proceedings were private, but it is announced that Miss F. J. Wood, the president of the union, presided, and that the adoption of the report was moved and seconded on behalf of the executive. There was considerable opposition from the National Association of Schoolmasters, who, at a meeting on the previous night, had passed a resolution con-demning the report! It was finally decided to submit the question to a card vote of the various districts of the union. The result was that 64,982 voted for the adoption of the report, and 37,547 against, giving a majority in favour of 27,435.Labour College. The development of the Labour College was considered at a joint meeting of the executives of the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation and the National Union of Railwaymen, held in London on the 4th November. The meeting agreed to a scheme unifying the system of maintenance, methods of examination, and qualification for admis-sion. A sub-committee of representatives from each organisation, and of the Board of Governors, was appointed to draw up details of the scheme.Industrial League and Council and National Alliance of Employers and Employed.-It is reported that the fusion of these two bodiesf is now practically accomplished. Several joint meetings of the executives have been held under the chairmanship of Admiral Sir Reginald Hall, M.P., to discuss details of the amalgamation, and the main points have now b een agreed, although a few details are still unsettled... **Trade Union Topics.Health Services. A movement is being made towards the federation of organisations catering for workers employed in the public and general health services. The organisations concerned are the National Asylum Workers&apos; Union, the Poor Law Workers&apos; Trade Union, the Professional Union of Trained Nurses, and the Medico-Political Union. A conference of the two last-named associations has recently been held, when a resolution was unani-mously adopted urging the immediate formation of a Federation of Health Services. The Professional Union of Trained Nurses has only been in existence since March.The Poor Law Workers&apos; Trade Union and the National Asylum Workers&apos; Union are completing their terms of amalgamation, and have reached agreement on certain points. The association of the Medico-Political. Union with the movement is of interest as marking the first step taken by doctors towards an alliance with organised labour.National Sailors and Firemen&apos;s Union. The ballot on the amalgamation of the National Sailors and Firemen&apos;s Union, the British Seafarers&apos; Union, and the Hull Seamen&apos;s Association began on the 18th October, and will close on the 19th March, 1921, unless a further extension of the date proves necessary. As it is extremely difficult to take an effec-tive ballot in the case of seamen, elaborate regulations have been laid down. Crews will, as far as possible, be visited on board ship by the union delegate as soon as they reach port, and will be given an opportunity of recording their, votes there and then. It is expected that by this method the requisite number of votes will be secured. At least 50 per cent, of the membership must vote. It is considered practically certain that there will be a very large majority in favour of amalgamation. ,Ex-Service Men.Out-of-Work Donation. A further extension of the out-of-work donation scheme is dealt with on p. 569 below.* See this Report, Vol. II, No. 17, 23rd October, p. 482, and No. 18, 30th October, p. 506. t See this Report, Vol. II, No. 15, 9th October, p. 434.
13.11,20.566Employment of Ex-Service Men. A meeting representative of business men was held at the Mansion House on the 5th November to inaugurate &quot; Obligation Week.&quot; The Lord Mayor of London presided over the meeting, which was addressed by H.R.H. the Prince of Wales, the Minister of Labour, Major-General Sir Frederick Maurice, Viscount Burnham, Captain Touse, V.C., chairman of the Council of the Comrades of the Great War, Mr. J. R. Griffin, general secretary of the National Federation of Discharged and Demobilised Sailors and Soldiers, and Sir Montague Barlow, M.P.The position of unemployed ex-Service men in Coventry was discussed at a meeting of the local Joint Council of Ex-Service Men&apos;s Organisations last week. A letter was read from the Coventry branch of the Engineering and the National Employers&apos; Federations, assuring the Council that the Federations would do all in their power to assist in placing as many ex-Service men as possible, and adding that the question of the employment of married Women in federated firms was being considered by the executive committee.Officers&apos; Association. A provisional committee for the furtherance of the interests of the Association has recently been appointed in Birmingham. Officials were elected at a meeting of the committee on the 3rd November. It was decided to invite the Lord Mayor of Birmingham to become the president; and sanction was given for the establishment in Birmingham of an organisation upon the lines of the central authority. Under this scheme a Central Council will be set up, and it is proposed to invite leading citizens representative of various interests to serve on it. It is proposed, eventually, to make an appeal for funds from which it is hoped, when a scheme of amalgamation of officers&apos; and men&apos;s societies has been carried through, to meet the needs of all the ex-Service men and their dependants in the district.Comrades of the Great War. The Devon Divisional Grand Council discussed the ques-tion of amalgamation of all ex-Service men&apos;s organisations at a meeting on the 2nd Novem-ber. The principle of amalgamation was unanimously adopted ; but certain amendments to the draft constitution which has already been formulated were proposed and carried. These will be forwarded for consideration by the National Grand Council, who are meeting in London this week. The Staffordshire Divisional Grand Council have also held a meeting and voted in favour of the general principle of amalgamation as laid down in the draft constitution.National Union of Ex-Service Men. The London and Home Counties Divisional Coun-cil of the union are endeavouring to convene a national conference to discuss the reorganisa-tion of the union on a national basis. At the next meeting a proposal will be submitted asking the late headquarters to hand over all books, accounts and records of the Union to the Council officials, as temporary trustees, pending such a reorganisation.International Relations of Labour.International Labour Office. The fifth session of the Governing Body of the Inter-national Labour Office was opened at Geneva on the 5th October, under the chairmanship of Mr. Arthur Fontaine, the French Government delegate, and the sittings were continued on the 6th and 7th October. The British Government was represented by Sir Malcolm Delevingne, K.C.B.The position in each country as regards the ratification of the Conventions adopted by the Washington Conference was discussed; and it was pointed-out that, if the Conventions adopted by the Conference were not ratified, the Office would fall short of the hopes placed in it by the working classes. The members of the three groups of the Governing Body, however, affirmed their respect for the engagements. entered into at Washington, and expressed their desire to collaborate fully with the work of the International Labour Organisation. It was decided to communicate as soon as possible to all the Governments concerned the minutes of the sitting at which this matter was discussed, so that they would be able to realise the close interest taken in the punctual ratification of the Washington Conventions.It will be remembered that the International Miners&apos; Congress, held at Geneva-in August last, passed a resolution calling for the creation of an International Office for the distribution of fuel, ores and other raw materials, and asked the International Labour Office to consider this problem jointly with the Sections of the League of Nations concerned. After some discussion, the Governing Body decided to authorise the Director to continue negotiations with the League of Nations for the institution of inquiries and the collection
NEGOTIATIONS AND DISPUTES.Demands and Negotiations.Building Trades Operatives (Brighton). Brighton building trades operatives have demanded an immediate settlement of the application for increased wages in the Southern Counties Area.Electricians (National). A conference was held at York last week between the National Federation of Electrical Associations and the Electrical Trades Union. It is reported that an agreement was arrived at on the question of educational facilities for apprentices. No agreement was come to with regard to the rates of pay of apprentices. With regard to out-of-town allowances, overtime conditions and night shift allowances, the employers made offers which the trade union representatives agreed to submit to their members with a recommendation that they be accepted. ,-Aluminium Workers (National). The National Federation of General Workers have submitted a claim for increases to workers in the aluminium industry, of 205. per week for workers over 18 years of age, and 10s. per week for workers under that age, overtime at the rate of time-and-a-half, except week-ends, which shall be at double time, and six days&apos; annual holiday with pay.Commercial Road * Transport Workers (Various Areas). In London and Plymouth negotiations have proceeded during the week. In Plymouth, the men&apos;s leaders have been instructed to approach the employers again, but they are authorised to call a strike at any moment in the event of the latter declining to reconsider their decision, or to submit the claim to arbitration before an industrial court. The London employers have offered to concede an advance in wages from the 1st December, if the cost-of-living index number for November proves to be as high as that for October.Strikes and Lock-Outs.Tramwaymen (Staffordshire). A strike of the men employed by the Potteries Electric Traction Company took place on the 8bh November. The strikers, who number about 400, demand the reinstatement of the guaranteed 48-hour week granted under an agreement of 1919. This was abrogated during the coal strike ; and the company refuse to withdraw the emergency arrangements on the ground that the reduction in the number of passengers continues, and that, if the agreement is restored, it will involve a reduction in staff.Insurance Officials. The national conference of the Guild of Insurance Offi.officials* was held on the 7th November, to receive the result of the ballot on the question of with-drawing members from the employment of the General Accident, Fire and Life Insurance Corporation, Ltd., and to make arrangements for the conduct of the strike. The ballot showed a vote of 10,933 in favour of a withdrawal, and of 2,807 against.   The conferenceof statistics in regard to prices and supplies-the first section of which might deal with coal-by, or in connection with, the Economic and Finance Section of the League of Nations, the International Labour Office being invited to nominate a representative to be associated with the inquiries.The establishment of a technical section for the study of questions of safety, and the prevention of industrial accidents, was also considered and approved; and it was decided that an annual summary of the Labour Inspection Reports of each country should be drawn -up by the International Labour Office, the special object being to ensure the dissemination of information on the matters dealt with by the inspectors.The next session of the Governing Body will meet at Geneva on the 11th January, 1921.
Negotiations and Disputes-continued.decided to withdraw immediately all their members employed by this assurance company. The interesting feature is the decision to impose a compulsory levy of 5s. on senior members, and 2s. 6d. on junior members, in order to pay the members on strike a strike benefit equal to their ordinary pay. Instructions were immediately issued in accordance with these resolutions, but it is not possible at the moment to state how many employees of the company are involved.Settlements and Agreements.Shipwrights (Liverpool). The strike of Mersey shipwrights, which took place on the 26th August for a minimum wage of  6 per week,&apos;has now been settled, the men deciding by ballot to resume work at the old rates of pay.Railway Shopmen. On the 5th November a meeting was held of railway managers and representatives of the National Union of railwaymen and the craft unions. An under-standing was arrived at on the principle of grouping places at which railway shop workers are employed, and fixing rates of pay for the different classes of railway shop workers under each group. A joint sub-committee representing the railway companies, the craft unions and the National Union of Railwaymen, has been appointed to go further into the question, to classify the various places of employment, and to consider the rates of pay.The National Union of Railwaymen and the craft unions have arrived at an under-standing concerning the problem of district rates of pay versus a national programme.Railway Policemen.-r-After protracted negotiations between representatives of the General Managers&apos; Committee, acting on behalf of the Minister of Transport, and elected delegates of the Railway Police Forces, an agreement was reached on the 29th September in regard to the standardisation of rates of pay and other conditions of service for all police-men employed on railways under Government control. The agreement has been ratified by the Minister of Transport and has been put into operation.The salient points in the agreement may be briefly mentioned. The weekly rate of pay for a uniform constable increases from 755., in the first year of service, by Is. per week in each succeeding year of service, until, in the eleventh year, men in this grade receive 85s. This rate of pay is to correspond with the Labour Gazette cost-of-living index number of 150, and will be increased or decreased by Is. per week for every rise or fall of a full five points. No reduction, however, below these basic rates may be made until a meeting has been held with a view to an agreement with regard to any necessary readjustment. Uniform constables working at stations and depots within 10 miles from Charing Cross, will receive an additional 3s. per week, and no man is to receive under the new scales a rate of pay less than his existing wages plus war wage.The ordinary working hours of duty will be 48 per week of six days, one of which may be Sunday. Payment for overtime worked on weekdays beyond 48 hours per week will be calculated at the rate of time-and-a-quarter, and all time worked on Sunday at the rate of time-and-a-half. Uniform constables will be allowed six weekdays per annum as annual holiday, with full wages. The agreement is to take effect as and from the 1st January, 1920.Tramwaymen (Manchester). A threat of the tramwaymen employed by the Manchester Corporation to come out on strike on the 6th November if the Corporation refused to restore the 1919 agreement of a guaranteed 48-hour working week Was withdrawn at the last moment, the Tramways Committee agreeing to revert to the agreement as from the date of the termination of the coal strike, namely, the 3rd November.Commercial Road Transport Workers (Yorkshire). The strike of carters and motor drivers in the West Riding of Yorkshire was settled on the 5th November on the following terms : One-horse drivers to receive an increase of 75. per week on the standard rate; two-horse drivers, 6s.; small motor-waggon drivers, 5s. ; other motor drivers, 4s.; drivers&apos; mates, 3s. These terms were agreed upon at a joint conference held in Leeds between employers representing the area, and the officials of the three unions concerned. It does not include the Bradford area, where the local co-operative society and several other firms offered an increase of 15s. per week. This offer was accepted, but about 500 men remain on strike. They refuse to accept the terms agreed upon at the Leeds conference, and have not so far been offered the 15s. increase.The strike also continues in Skipton, where the employers have refused to accept the Leeds settlement on the ground that they are unable to pay any advance at all. They threaten to fill the places of any carters who do not return to work immediately.
Negotiations and Disputes-continued.Coal Tippers (South Wales). On the 4th November, a conference was held at the Great Western Hotel, Padclington, of representatives of the railway and dock workers concerned in the negotiations for increases in wages. The case for the men was in the hands of Messrs. Williams and Bevin, of the National Transport Workers&apos; Federation, and T. Hudson, of the National Union of Railwaymen. Local officials of these two unions were present. The case submitted on behalf of the men was that an advance should be granted, equivalent to the increased cost of living, on the pre-war rates of the tippers concerned. The dock companies offered an additional 25 per cent, advance on the tonnage rates. The men&apos;s representatives eventually agreed to accept this offer as an interim settlement of their claims ; and the additional 25 per cent, will come into operation as from the 1st September: Fresh negotiations will be entered upon for completing new conditions between the present date and December next, and a new settlement will come into operation on the 1st December.Printers (National). For developments in this dispute see p. 562 below.[Other disputes, negotiations and settlements are referred to in the Industrial Relations Departments section of the Report, pages 560 to 563.](b 16626)4C
PART II-THE WORK OF THE MINISTRY.INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS DEPARTMENT.ARBITRATION AND CONCILIATION.AWARDS.The number of awards received during the week was five, ail under the Industrial Courts Act.Engineering and Foundry Trades: Gas Meter Makers (Manchester). The Court gave an interpretation of Awards No. 180 and No. 180a, showing which of the various percentage advances on piece-work earnings should not be subject to the advance of 15 per cent, granted under Award No. 180.  (Award No. 513.)AGREEMENTS AND SETTLEMENTS.Moulders&apos;&apos; Piece-Work Rates (Tipton). A strike of about 100 moulders occurred at the works of Messrs. E. D. Hale, Ltd., Tipton, oh the 27th October, the firm having informed the men that piece-rates must be reduced owing to the depression in trade. A conference was arranged by the Chief Conciliation Officer, Birmingham, at which the firm produced their wages books showing that wages for a normal week of 47 hours had been from  9 to  17 per week. The union officials pointed out that the proposals would reduce wages by from 33-1 Per cen^- ^0 *f ^ per cent., but the managing director stated that, if the firm were to continue, wages would have to be reduced. Although a circular had been issued on the 30th March, promising that no reduction would be made in piece-prices for at least two years, an agreement, drawn up with the assistance of the Chief Conciliation Officer, was finally reached, to the effect that all existing piece-prices should be abolished, and new prices fixed so that men of average ability might earn at least  6 for a full week of 47 hours.Stevedores [Millwall). A strike occurred at the Millwall and Surrey Commercial Docks on the 25th October over the loading of a vessel for the Ministry of Shipping. In this dock, by old custom, members of the stevedores&apos; union should have the first claim on any work, and not until every man with a stevedore&apos;s ticket has been called is other labour taken on. The stevedore in charge was unaware of this custom and employed members of the dockers&apos; union. A meeting was arranged between representatives of the Ministry of Shipping, the War Office and the unions concerned. It was arranged that the vessel should be ordered out into the river to load, and that the stevedores&apos; union should take over the work. The men resumed on the 28th October. The future division of work between members of the various unions has been left to the union officials.INTERPRETATIONS AND RULINGS.Interpretations of Industrial Court Awards. The practice of the Industrial Court in respect of applications for the interpretation of an award* is as follows. When applica-tion is made by one party to the award, the Court inquire of the parties whether they desire a hearing or are prepared to agree to the Court giving a decision after consideration of state-ments submitted by the parties in writing. If one party objects, the Court nevertheless arrange for a hearing, but forward the notes of the proceedings to the objecting party for comment. A decision is not withheld if such comment is not forthcoming. When applica-tion is made by the Minister of Labour, the consent of the parties is not sought, but they are asked to attend the hearing. The Court have come to the conclusion that in such cases the previous consent of the parties is not necessary.QUESTIONS PENDING AND MISCELLANEOUS.Insurance Officials. The Guild of Insurance Officials, after taking a ballot, have called a strike of about 300 members employed by the General Accident, Fire and Life Assurance
* See this Report, Vol. II, No. 17, 23rd October, p. 488. (b 16626) 4 C 2Corporation, Ltd. They allege that the Corporation have dismissed certain employees for joining the Guild. The general manager of the Corporation declines to recognise the Guild and maintains that the staff are contented. He has declined the departments offer of mediation.  The offices in London and Perth will be most affected by the strike.Textile Printers, Bleachers, Dyers and Finishers (Yorkshire, Lancashire, Cheshire and Derbyshire). On the 3rd November the employers met representatives of the unions in Manchester, and placed before them a scheme for dealing with unemployment, under-employment and sickness. Eealising that to accept this scheme might prejudice considera-tion of their wages claim, the union representatives rejected it and re-affirmed their intention to press for the wages increase. The secretary of the National Society of Dyers and Finishers would not consider the intervention of the Ministry to appoint an umpire, and put forward the retiring Lord Mayor of Manchester a Labour man as suitable. The^employers rejected this proposal. The secretary thereupon handed in to the Yorkshire Dyers&apos; Federation a week&apos;s notice on behalf of his association. The Chief Conciliation Officer is in close touch with the case.Block Printers (Crayford). About 40 members of the Amalgamated Block Printers employed by Messrs. Swaisland&apos;s Fabric Printing Co., struck on the 22nd October, against the deduction of a timekeeping bonus of 6j per cent., when time is lost, and for the elimination -tion of the &quot; dead horse &quot; system. The bonus was instituted about 18 months ago by agreement with the union. At a conference with the negotiating committee of the union)1 the firm offered to eliminate the &quot; dead horse &quot; system, and to concede the bonus to workers who lost time through no fault of their own, which was to be decided by a committee appointed by the employees. The workers refused this offer, and pressed for payment of the bonus unconditionally. The matter is being considered further by the union executive, and the Chief Conciliation Officer has suggested reference to arbitration to both sides.Woollen Trade (West Wales). This dispute still continues.* The employers have agreed to restore the status quo if the strikers at Cwerchyr resume work. A meeting of the men is being arranged, at which an officer of the department will be present. If a resumption cannot be obtained on these terms, the employers are to be met to endeavour to formulate new proposals.\Inter-Union Dispute (Abertilleryj-The Electrical Trades Union recently persuaded 7 men in the electricity department of the Abertillery Urban District Council to leave the Municipal Employees&apos; Association and join their union. About 300 members of the Municipal Employees&apos; Association tendered notices, expiring on the 30th October, to compel the seceders to rejoin their union. The Chief Conciliation Officer persuaded the association to withdraw their notices, pending consideration of the question by the executive committees of both unions.   It is probable that the association will not pursue the matter further.Pottery Works (Torquay). The National Society of Pottery Workers applied on the 1st June for an increase of 20 per cent, in wages for workers employed by the Longpark Pottery Co., Ltd., the Watcombe Pottery Co., Ltd., and the Torquay Pottery Co., Ltd. The firms were negotiating with their workpeople, but refused to meet the union officials. The operatives at Watcombe and Allervale struck on the 11th October, but failed to induce those at the other two factories to join them. The employers, however, decided to give a week&apos;s notice to their employees, expiring on the 20th October. They subsequently withdrew the notices so far as non-union men were concerned, so that all the employees of the Torquay Pottery Co., and some of those with the Longpark Pottery Co., are still at work.A suggestion made by one of the employers at a conference with the Chief Conciliation Officer, that the Staffordshire piece-rate system should be introduced, was conveyed to the union organiser. He was not in favour of this unless the employers would offer the same modern plant and other facilities, but is consulting his headquarters.INDUSTRIAL COUNCILS. JOINT STANDING INDUSTRIAL COUNCILS.Reports.Bobbin and Shuttle Making. The Council met on the 26th October, to consider an application for an advance in wages, and also the grading of workpeople in the bobbin-making industry.  On the first point, the recommendations of an informal conference
between the chairman and the secretaries of the Council were discussed. The Council were ready to adopt the recommendations, with slight modifications, for the higher skilled workers, the less skilled workers and the women workers, but the representatives of unskilled labourers refused to accept the advances recommended for labourers, and demanded the same advances as the less skilled workers. The employers, after a further offer had been rejected, insisted that there ought to be some differentiation, and a deadlock was reached.On the question of grading it was agreed that a committee on each side should collect evidence and hold a joint meeting.Cooperage. The Council met on the 2nd November. An application for wage increases amounting to 3d. per hour, making a total of 25. 4d. per hour, with corresponding advances of 30 per acent. for piece-workers, was refused by the employers, principally on the ground that the &quot; limit of the ability to pay had been reached.&quot; The workers&apos; side made tentative suggestions that accounts should be produced, but these were not accepted.A representative of the Employment Department explained the provisions of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920. A sub-committee was appointed &quot; to consider the possibility of setting up a special scheme under the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920, with the desirability of bringing into the industry other classes of workmen employed in close association with coopers.&quot; There will be considerable difficulty in formulating a scheme, as a large majority of coopers are employed in close association with other trades, such as brewing or oil and chemical manufacture.No further progress was made in connection with the apprenticeship scheme, as some District Councils had prepared provisional schemes infringing the principles laid down by the National Council, namely, that all apprentices should be indentured; that no apprentice should be admitted after attaining the age of 16 years ; and that one apprentice should be allowed to every three journeymen. The schemes were referred back to tne District Councils, and the question will be considered again at the next meeting.Local Authorities&apos; Non-Trading Services, Manual Workers (England and Wales).  The Council met on the 5th November. It was reported that the District Council for the Eastern Counties had failed to reach agreement on a scale of minimum wages, and it was decided that the chairman and vice-chairman of the National Council should attend their next meeting and endeavour to assist them to reach a settlement. A full discussion took place on the failure of certain local authorities to adopt the recommendations of the National Council or the District Councils.Pottery. The Wages and Conditions Committee met on the 4th November. Major Wedgwood reported his interview with a leading plaster manufacturer on the present inade-quate supply. The committee were of opinion that a mere individual promise of assistance Wao not sufficient, and resolved that a deputation be sent to interview the Gypsum Asso-ciation. Good progress was reported in regard to the Interrupted Apprenticeship Scheme, and the present difficulties will be lessened by the fact that a representative of the Ministry has been co-opted on the committee. The operatives intimated that application will be made to contract out of the Unemployment Insurance Act.The Statistical and Inquiries Committee met on the same da^ and appointed Sir John Mann, as chartered accountant^to verify the returns of manufacturers for 1918. The relation of profit to turnover was discussed, and it was finally agreed that the manu-facturers should submit a memorandum for consideration at its next meeting.The sub-committee appointed by the Executive Committee to consider the draft constitution of the proposed Association of Joint Industrial Councils and Interim Indus-trial Reconstruction Committees met on the 4th November, and endorsed the recom-mendations of the provisional committee appointed at the conference held on the 15th January to consider the formation of such an association.Printing. The negotiations between the master printers and the various trade unions have been concluded. Both the Printing and Kindred Trades Federation and the Typo-graphical Association have decided to recommend their members to accept the employers&apos; offer of an increase of 5s. per week for men and 2s. per week for women. Learners&apos; rates are also to be adjusted. In London, night-workers are normally paid time-and-a-quarter, but when the last advance of 10s. Was given, it was agreed that night-workers should also get 10s. only.   The same provision applies to the present increase of 5s.Rubier Manufacture. The Edinburgh and East of Scotland Rubber Trade Concilia-tion Board, set up to deal with wages questions for the district pending a solution of the deadlock in the National Council, met on the 22nd October.  The application for a wages
GENERAL DEPARTMENT.TRADE BOARDS. PROCEEDINGS.Boot and Shoe Repairing Trade Board (Great Britain). The Administrative Committee considered the question of indentured apprenticeship. A draft form of indenture Was prepared, and it was agreed to recommend the Board to make it a condition of the payment of the minimum rates fixed for apprentices that indentures should be in that form, and that the number of apprentices to journeymen should be limited to proportions recommended by the committee. The committee also considered fche action which should be taken to secure the registration of all boot repairers, and agreed to recommend that the Board make representations to the Minister, and request him to forward them to the proper quarter.Upon consideration of an offer from the After-Care Association for Blind, Deaf and Crippled Children to assist the Board in considering applications for permits of exemption, the committee agreed to invite an official of this association to attend their next meeting to discuss the matter. Sub-committees were appointed to revise the general minimum piece-rates, and to report upon the feasibility of fixing general minimum piece-rates for machine finishing. ,Brush and Broom Trade Board (Great Britain). The Administrative Committee considered a letter from the ^nister on the definition of pan Work, and made a recommen-dation to the Board accordingly.  The question of the relationship between women&apos;s and increase from the trade union side was considered. The employers were unable to agree to any increase, owing to the extremely critical period through which the British rubber industry is passing. They also argued that the wages paid in that district would appear to be at least equal, if not superior, to those in any similar class of employment. The unions intimated that they would place the employers&apos; decision before their constituents.Local Authorities&apos; Administrative, Technical and Clerical Services (England and Wales).  Conferences of representatives of the local authorities and staff committees concerned were held at NeWcastle-on-Tyne on the 2nd November, and in London on the 4th November, to consider the formation of District Councils for the area of Northumberland and Durham and the Administrative County of London, respectively. Both conferences resolved that District Councils be formed. A similar conference for the North and East Ridings of Yorkshire was held at York on the 3rd November. It was resolved that it was desirable that a District Council be set up. A joint committee was appointed, with instructions to consider a constitution and to make suggestions as to the number of representatives and the method of allocation. These proposals, together with explanatory documents, are to be sent to all local authorities in the area, who will be requested to indicate approval, or otherwise, of the proposal to set up a District Council. A conference will then be convened as soon as possible, to give further consideration to the matter.INTERIM INDUSTRIAL RECONSTRUCTION COMMITTEES.Reports.Lead Manufacture. The Committee met on the 4th November. The claim for advances of 15s. per week for male workers of 18 and over, 105. for women, and Is. 6d. for boys, was again considered. The employers were unable to grant any increase and suggested that the case should go to arbitration. The trade union representatives agreed to recommend this course to their executive committees. It was decided that in the mean-time the Wages Sub-Committee should continue to discuss the proposed standardisation of wages.[Reference to matters of interest in connection with Industrial Relations will be found also on pages 552 to 569, 563 to 566, 570 and 573.]
men&apos;s rates of wages in the pan section of the trade was discussed, and separate proposals for classifying the various branches of pan work were put forward by the representatives of workers and employers.  The matter is to receive further consideration.Toy Trade Board (Great Britain). The Special Rates Committee received information as to the character of the work and the classes of workers employed in the wood and metal sections of the trade, and agreed to invite certain members of the Board concerned in other branches, together with selected operatives and employers who are not- members of the Board, to attend the next meeting and furnish similar information respecting these sections.Jute Trade Board (Great Britain).-The Learnership and Apprenticeship Committee prepared, for the consideration of the Board, a scheme of learnership for female weavers, and discussed the necessity for a scheme of apprenticeship for male tenters.The Skilled Workers Committee agreed to recommend the Board to fix general minimum piece-rates in Great Britain, except in certain areas, to be enumerated later, in which the settlement of piece-rates should be left to the operation of a piece-work basis time-rate of 9d. per hour.General Waste Materials Reclamation Trade Board (Great Britain). The Board resumed consideration of minimum rates, and resolved to adopt the recommendation of the Ship-breaking, Scrap Metal and Scrap Iron Committee that the general minimum time-rate for the lowest grade of male workers, 21 years of age, employed in that branch which is engaged in the collection, sorting, grading or breaking of scrap iron or other scrap metal, in connec-tion with which the collecting, sorting or grading of other waste materials is not carried out to a substantial extent, should be 70s. per week of 48 hours.The question of minimum rates for other male and female workers in the trade Was considered, and deferred for further discussion.An Administrative Committee was appointed. It was agreed that no action should be taken at the moment with regard to setting up District Trade Committees.Laundry Trade Board (Great Britain). In view of the letter from the Minister on the provisions of the Notices relating to weekly rates and deductions, the special sub-committee considered the action to be taken with regard to the outstanding short-time agreements and applications for permits of exemption, and agreed to authorise the issue of a number of permits.FIXING AND VARIATION OF MINIMUM RATES OF WAGES.Milk Distributive Trade Board (England and Wales). The Minister has made an Order, dated the 1st November, confirming the general minimum time-rates and overtime rates fixed for male and female workers, and has specified the 8th November as the date from which these rates shall become effective.The general minimum time-rates are, for male workers, namely, (i) sterilisers, other than assistant sterilisers, (ii) clerks, (hi) shop assistants, including pasteurisers and assistant sterilisers, 21 years of age and over in each case, and also for (iv) foremen: (a) in the City of London and the Metropolitan police district except areas included in (6) below, (i) 70s., (ii) 70s., (iii) 65s. and (iv) 80s. per week respectively ; (b) in the areas administered by Rural District Councils, but excluding towns with population exceeding 10,000, (i) 60s., (ii) 60s., (iii) 55s., and (iv) 65s. per week respectively; and (c) in all other areas, (i) 67s. 6c?., (ii) 67s. 6d., (iii) 62s. Qd., and (iv) 75s. per week, respectively; with lower rates in each case for workers under 21 years of age.For female workers, namely, (i) roundswomen, (ii) clerks, (iii) shop assistants, and (iv) all other workers, 21 years of age and over, for the areas specified above, the rates are: (a) (i) 52s. Qd., (ii) 48s., (iii) 42s., and (iv) 40s. per week; (b) (i) 40s., (ii) 38s., (iii) 33s., and (iv) 32s. Qd. per week, and (c) (i) 45s., (ii) 42s., (iii) 37s., and (iv) 36s. per week, respectively; with lower rates in each case for workers under 21 years of age.Where a class of whole-time workers work less than 48 hours but not less than 40 hours a week, the rate is in respect of the number of hours per week customarily worked by that class.Overtime rates have been fixed for all male and female workers, with separate rates for shop assistants and clerks. For this purpose the normal number of hours is 48 in any week; 6 on Sunday and customary public and statutory holidays ; and 7 on any other day.Laundry Trade Board (Great Britain). The Minister has made an Order dated the 2nd November, confirming the following minimum rates of wages as varied for female workers, and has specified the 8th,November as the date from which these rates shall become effective.The general minimum time-rates are l\d. per hour for workers 18 years of age and over, with rates ranging from 3d. to 6jcZ. per hour for workers under that age. For workers with less than six months&apos; experience, the rates are id. per hour for workers of 16 and under 17 years of age, and 5d.
tper hour for those of 17 and under 18 years of age. For workers, 18 years of age and over, with less than 12 months&apos; experience, the rates are $\d. per hour until the completion of the first six months&apos; experience, and Q^d. until the completion of the second 6 months.The piece-work basis time-rate for female workers of all ages is Is. 9d. per hour. The guaranteed time-rate for piece-workers, 18 years of age and over, is $\d. per hour, with rates ranging from 3d. to tyd. per hour for workers under that age. For workers with less than 6 months&apos; experience, the rates are id. per hour for workers of 16 and under 17 years of age, and hd. for those of 17 and under 18 years of age. For workers 18 years of age and over, with less than 12 months&apos; experience, the special rate, until the completion of 12 months, is %\d. per hour.For female workers employed casually or for emergency work, the general minimum time-rates are 8d. per hour for workers 18 years of age and over, and l\d. per hour for those under that age; and the piece-work basis time-rate for workers of all ages is %\d, per hour.The overtime rates for time-workers are, for female workers employed casually or for emergency work, \0d. per hour for those 18 years of age and over, and 9^. per hour for those under that age; for all other female workers, 9^. per hour for those 18 years of age and over, with rates ranging from 3f c?. to l\d. per hour for those under that age.Where a worker is exempted under the Factory and &quot;Workshop Acts, for all time worked iD excess of .9 hotirs on Saturday and Sunday the overtime rate is time-and-a-half. For the purpose of these overtime rates the Board have declared the normal number of hours of work to be 48 in any week, and 5 on Saturday or the weekly half-holiday.*The Board have issued a Notice of Proposal dated the 4th November, to vary the general minimum time-rates, piece-work basis time-rates, guaranteed time-rates and overtime rates for female workers.For all female workers, other than those employed casually or for emergency work, the general minimum time-rate proposed, for workers 18 years of age and over, is 8tZ. per hour, with rates ranging from 3^. to %\d. per hour for those under that age ; for workers of 16 and under 17 years of age, and of 17 and under 18 years of age, with less than six months&apos; experience, i^d. and 5^d. per hour, respectively; for those 18 years of age and over, with less than twelve months&apos; experience, until the completion of six months&apos; experience, %\d. per hour, and until the completion of the second six months, l^d. per hour.The piece-work basis time-rate proposed for the above female workers, of all ages, is %\d. per hour. The guaranteed time-rate proposed for piece-workers, 18 years of age and over, is id. per hour, with rates ranging from 3d. to 6d. per hour for those under that age ; for workers of 16 and under 17 years of age, and of 17 and under 18 years of age, with less than six months&apos; experience, i^d. and h\d. per hour respectively; for those of 18 years of age and over, with less than 12 months&apos; experience, until the completion of six months&apos; experience, %\d. per hour, and until the completion of the second six months, Id. per hour.For female workers employed casually or for emergency work, the general minimum time-rates proposed are 8^. per hour for workers 18 years, of age and over, and 8d. per hour for those under that age ; and the piece-work basis time-rate for female workers of all ages is 10c?. per hour.Overtime rates are proposed for all female time-workers.Milk Distributive Trade Board (Scotland). The Board have issued a Notice of Proposal, dated the 1st November, to fix general minimum time-rates and overtime rates for male and female workers.The general minimum time-rates proposed for all male workers, other than foremen and shop assistants, and for roundswomen, 21 years of age and over, are 62s. Qd. and 65s. per week according as the worker has less or not less than 12 months&apos; experience, with lower rates for workers under that age. For male shop assistants and male clerks, 21 years of age and over, the rate proposed is 67s. 6d. per week, with lower rates for workers under that age ; and, for foremen, 85s. per week.The general minimum time-rate proposed for all female workers, 21 years of age and over, other than roundswomen, shop assistants and clerks, is 35s. per week; for shop assistants, 38s&quot;. per week; and for clerks, 42s. per week ; with lower rates for workers under 21 years of age.Where a class of whole-time workers work less than 48 but not less than 40 hours per week, the rate is in respect of the number of hours per week customarily worked by that class.For the purpose of the proposed overtime rates for male and female workers of all ages, the Board propose to declare the normal number of hours work to be 48 in any week, and 6 on Sunday and customary public and statutory holidays.Grocery and Provisions Trade Board (England and Wales). The Board have issued a Notice of Proposal dated the 3rd November, to fix general minimum time-rates for certain classes of male workers.The rates proposed for workers, 21 years of age and over, employed as porters, or wholly or mainly as shop assistants, range in the City of London and in the Metropolitan police district from 57s. to 63s. per week for porters, and from 62s. to 70s. for shop assistants; in all rural and urban districts and municipal boroughs, other than those above, with a population of less than 5,000, from 52s. to 55s. for porters, and from 54s. to 58s. for shop assistants ; and in all other areas, from 55s. to 61s. for porters, and from 60s. to 68s. for shop assistants; with lower rates for workers under 21 years of age in each case.
EMPLOYMENT AND INSURANCE DEPARTMENT.EMPLOYMENT EXCHANGES.The Unemployment Position.Owing to the strike in the coal mining industry the usual figures of registrations, placings and vacancies are not available.Men!s Employment.General. Reports for the week ending the 29th October indicate that employers in all divisions have been making strenuous efforts to avoid general discharges by resorting to short time. The increase in the live register, while sufficiently serious, is on the whole smaller than was expected, and it is hoped that with the early settlement of the dispute a return to pre-strike conditions may rapidly take place.Local Reports. In London, unemployment in the riverside boroughs has undergone little change. At Bermondsey a new sewerage&quot; scheme has been started, and the erection of working-class dwellings has been commenced. At Camberwell it is expected that further relief work will shortly be put in hand. At Leyton the heavy discharges by Messrs. Peter Hooker, Ltd., have continued, and the position has been aggravated by the suspension of a large contract owing to the strike. At Poplar the graving dock workers discharged owing to a recent fire have resumed work. Stepney report a large increase of unemployment in the wholesale tailoring trade, and in the dock transport works unemployment is still acute. At Hendon, owing to the depression in motor and aircraft engineering, unemployment is acute, but Messrs. S. Smith &amp; Sons, Ltd., engineers, are expecting large contracts. A relief scheme for the repair of roads will shortly be undertaken. Woolwich report that progress has been made with the arterial roads scheme, on which local workmen have been employed. Unemployment at Brighton has been aggravated by a reduction of boarding house and hotel staffs.In the South-Western Division the winter service of the Cowes Southampton boats has been resumed. At Portland a number of coal heavers have started work on unloading colliers. The situation at Basingstoke has only recently become abnormal, due mainly to discharges by Messrs. J. I. Thorny croft &amp; Co., Ltd., engineers. At Bournemouth the Distress Committee continue to register applicants, and some men have been started on relief works.In the West Midlands it is estimated that 75 per cent, of those in receipt of out-of-work donation and unemployment insurance benefit are unemployed owing to general depression in the engineering, motor and jewellery trades, rather than to the effects of the miners&apos; strike. At Smethwick, Messrs. Chance Bros. &amp; Co., glass manufacturers, have shut down several furnaces, and will not be able to resume their normal activities for several weeks.The Birmingham City Council have commenced two road widening and repairing schemes. At Redditch unemployment continues to increase owing to trade depression. The needle and fishing tackle manufacturers complain that the high cost of production is keeping them out of Continental markets.Cotton Waste Reclamation Trade Boa) d (Great Britain). The Board have issued a Notice of Proposal dated the 4th November, to fix general minimum time-rates and overtime rates for male and female&apos;workers.The general minimum time-rates proposed for male workers, 21 years of age and over, in Great Britain, is Is. i%d. per hour, with lower rates for those under that age ; and for female workers, 18 years of age and over, in England and Wales, $\d. per hour, and in Scotland, 8fi. per hour; with lower rates for workers under that age in both cases.[References to matters of interest in connection with Trade Boards will also he found on pages 572 and 574.]
In the Yorkshire and East Midlands Division it is unlikely that employment will be normal for a fortnight from the resumption of work by the miners. The general depression continues to affect the textile and clothing trades, and the transport workers&apos; dispute is responsible for dislocation in Leeds and Bradford. The Kirkstall Forge Co., Ltd., Leeds, whose chief product is motor axles, have discharged 450 men owing to lack of orders, for which the coal strike is in no way responsible. It is understood that a road, 25 to 30 miles long, round the city of Leeds, is in contemplation. The widening of roads and the construction of new tramway tracks also form part of a scheme for the absorption of the unemployed.In the North-Western Division there are indications of coming activity in the textile engineering industry. There is a very wide demand, and well-known makers are already booked up with orders. With the settlement of the coal dispute, there are clear signs of an early improvement in the cotton industry. It is noteworthy that Messrs. Vickers, Ltd., Barrow-in-Furness, have been able to continue uninterrupted working during the coal crisis, and have continued to import labour.Messrs. J. Bibby &amp; Son, Liverpool, seed crushers, have been able to re-start 1,000 men on receiving 10,000 tons of coal. A general improvement is expected at Bootle, where unemployment has been continuous owing to the shipwrights&apos; strike. At Birken-head and Wallasey, notwithstanding the coal strike, the live register has decreased, owing to the engagement of a large number of riveters, holders-up and other workers by two firms who have received ships for repair. There is no sign of improvement in the engineering or motor industries in Openshaw.Unemployment at Blackburn, though still acute, shows signs of improvement. Five mills, closed for several weeks, have re-started their preparation departments, and will resume full work next week. Several textile mills have also re-started. At Preston depression in the cotton, rubber and soap industries still exists. Employers have been compelled to reduce output by short-time working as their stocks are large. Most persons out of work at Darwen are affected by the general depression in the textile trade. The position is becoming increasingly serious.In the Northern Division difficulty in obtaining supplies of coal has made the position of workers employed by the Darlington Forge Co., Ltd., very uncertain. Small dis-charges continue to be made by Sir W. G. Armstrong, Whitworth &amp; Co., Ltd., Elswick. The number of claims lodged at Jarrow tends to decrease, and, if a supply of coal is obtainable, the glass furnaces will be relighted. Many men at Middlesbrough are working-short time, and the total number suspended by Messrs. Bolckow, Vaughan &amp; Co., Ltd., is now about 4,500.In Scotland recent increases in the number of persons affected by the miners&apos; strike have been in the iron and steel industry, chiefly at Motherwell and Cambuslang. An increase of 1,000 was caused by suspensions by Messrs. Barry, Ostlere &amp; Shepherd, Ltd., Kirkcaldy, linoleum manufacturers. The firm, however, have now resumed normal activity., Although in South Wales a great majority of the miners voted against the terms offered by the Government, no active opposition has been shown to the resumption of work. Employers have made great efforts to continue operations. During the week only two works have closed down entirely, though 10 have closed partially.In Ireland the labour situation is resuming more normal conditions. Most of the shipping services have been resumed. In Belfast engineering and foundry firms continue to work a 5-day week, and the position as regards workmen unemployed owing to civil commotion remains unaltered. At Cork there has been a continued decline in the ship-building industry, but the dockyard authorities are postponing further reductions until after Christmas. At Lisburn and Londonderry the textile industry continues to decline ; most firms are working short time. There is considerable unemployment in the South and West of Ireland, due possibly to the political situation.Women&apos;s Employment.General Situation.-!^ the absence of detailed reports from the divisions it is only possible to give a general outline of the situation in so far as it affects women. The numbers of unemployment books lodged rose from approximately 37,000 on the 8th October, to 65,000 on the 3rd November. It has become increasingly difficult to ascribe the increase in unemployment to any one cause, and the efforts made all over the country by employers(b 16626) % 4 D
Employment and Insurance Department-continued.to work short time, rather than resort to wholesale discharges, have checked the rapid development of complete unemployment caused by the coal strike.From the Yorkshire and East Midlands Division it is reported that practically all the textile firm3 in the Bradford area are partially closed, but this is due as much to trade depression and the transport workers&apos; dispute as to the effect of the Coal Restriction Order. The depression described in all the staple industries for many weeks past increases. The revival in the boot and shoe trade in the South Midlands Division, for example, which was expected as winter approached, has not yet shown itself. Acute depression continues also in the clothing, hosiery and silk industries in this division.Seasonal Domestic Service. Reports have now been received from most divisions on the work of supplying seasonal domestic workers to hotels and boarding houses in holiday resorts. Arrangements for this work were made in February and March, and included a general canvass of employers, meetings with hotel and boarding house proprietors, the pre-paration of registers of local women suitable for seasonal work, and the linking up of suitable supply and demand areas. Great assistance was rendered by the Women&apos;s Sub-Committees of Local Employment Committees. Several divisions emphasise the number of inexperi-experienced women who have undertaken this work: box-makers, tailoresses, clerks, a laundry packer, a confectionery assistant, a woman tram conductor, a blouse maker, a cigarette maker, an aircraft worker, and a woman baker were successfully placed.The London and South-Eastern Division report that approximately 250 applicants from a distance were placed in the seaside towns. In addition a number of local applicants were placed. A special feature was the large number of daily workers placed. During the season about 820 daily helps were provided.Useful co-operation was undertaken between the West Midlands and the Wales Divisions. From various West Midland towns, 250 workers were sent to Welsh seaside resorts. Most were inexperienced, and many came from factory and munition work. A certain number were also recruited from women previously employed in the State services.The South Midlands and Eastern Division emphasise the value of the daily workers, and state that at Great Yarmouth alone 223 women were placed, and atSouthend233. Of the inland Exchanges in this division, that at Cambridge was the most successful in exporting women workers to the seaside.The Yorkshire and East Midlands Division state that the concentration of certain supply Exchanges on a certain seasonal demand office has been most successful. Nearly 600 appli-cants were sent to seasonal work. The North-Western Division report that of the. 300 applicants sent to seasonal work, over 100 had industrial experience only. In the Northern Division the season was exceptionally successful. Employers&apos; conferences were arranged in Windermere and Ambleside as early as February, and untrained women were placed early, to grow accustomed to the work before the season began. The linking up of each exchange with a demand area was also arranged very early, with the result that from Gateshead, for example, about 100 women were placed in the Kendal area.Complete reports have not yet been received from Scotland, but up to the end of June nearly 500 vacancies had been filled through the special section established at Glasgow alone. A recent report from the Inverness area states that the placings numbered 329 for the season, an increase of nearly 50 per cent, on the figures for 1919. A number of seasonal workers are entering private service at the end of the season.LOCAL EMPLOYMENT COMMITTEES.Activities of Committees.Procedure. A recent memorandum deprecating the reference of resolutions to members of Parliament is not being received with unqualified approval, several committees having objected to the principle enunciated.Employment and Resettlement. In connection with the request that committees should approach collieries with a view to absorbing labour discharged from the Cornish tin mines, Cannock report that the Littleton Collieries, Ltd., could employ about 500 men but for the housing shortage. The committee are urging the local authorities to expedite their building scheme, and request the department to take up the matter with the Minister of Health.Out-qf-Worh Donation and Unemployment Insurance. Redditch have considered the procedure for dealing with disputed claims to unemployment benefit. They are of opinion what avoidable delay does actually occur, and strongly recommend &quot; that insurance officers
tDISCHARGED AND DISABLED SAILORS AND SOLDIERS.National Scheme.Up to and including the 3rd November, 22,075 certificates have been issued to employers under the Scheme. The undertakings given by these employers cover 236,007 disabled ex-Service men.The Divisional Controller of the South-Western Division reports that, though much hampered by depressing industrial conditions, efforts to induce more employers to enrol are meeting with fair success. He adds that the recent appeals by the Lords Lieutenant, Members of Parliament and others, have aroused a great deal of public attention. A Bristol firm have substituted nine severely disabled men for women, at a commencing wage of  2 12s. Qd. per week. At Drayton, near Portsmouth, there is an excellent prospect of some 1,000 men being required shortly to break up old ammunition. All vacancies will be notified to the Portsmouth Exchange, and it is expected that a proportion of disabled men will be placed in employment.At Plymouth the Mayor and the chairman of the Employment Committee are taking up the cases of all disabled men on the live register, with a view to finding them employ-ment, if possible, during the Mayor&apos;s tenure of office.The Divisional Controller of the North-Western Division reports that, through the medium of the Liverpool Cotton Association, a number of firms in the cotton trade have been approached. So far, 30 undertakings have been secured, and more will probably be forthcoming.At Manchester the Lord Mayor has appointed a committee to be known as the &quot; Man-chester Debt of Honour Committee.&quot; It comprises a number of the most influential citizens of Manchester, and a determined campaign has been commenced with the object of inducing employers to engage ex-Service men, both disabled and non-disabled. The Employment Exchange machinery will be utilised in the actual placing of applicants. A large hoarding has been erected&apos;outside the Town Hall, showing progress in the absorption of ex-Service men in industry.OUT-OF-WORK DONATION AND  UNEMPLOYMENT  INSURANCE BENEFIT.Out-of-WorJc Donation. A further extension of the Out-of-Work Donation Scheme has been arranged. The extension applies to ex-Service men, certain numbers of the Women&apos;s Corps, and merchant seamen, on the same conditions as Special Extension No. 3, which expired on the 6th November. Donation is provided, as under Special Extension No. 3, at the rate of 20s. for men and 15s. for women, and may be drawn, for a period not exceeding 15 weeks, between the 8th November, 1920, and the 31st March, 1921. The Government have decided that thereafter any provision for unemploy-ment pay which is found necessary must be made through the Unemployment Insurance Act.Returns by the Finance Department, according to information received at the Claims and Record Office, Kew, for the week ending the 28th October, show 46,305 payments(b 16626) 4 D should be allocated at Divisional Offices, where, being in closer touch with the actualities of each case, they would he able to come to decisions with a minimum of correspondence,&quot; and also that the claim forms should he sent to the Divisional Office on the same day as they are received at the Exchange.Richmond are of opinion that domestic and agricultural workers should be included in the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920, especially as they come under the National Health Insurance Act, 1920.Training. Walsall are assisting in setting up a Local Technical Advisory Committee to supervise the training of ex-Service men in the iron and brass casting and coremaking trades. The committee hope that the training scheme will be put into operation without delay.Ex-Service Men. The Kendal and District Committee, at their last meeting, dis-cussed the question as to when a man should cease to be treated as an ex-Service man. It was agreed to recommend that, when a non-disabled man has had not less than six months&apos; employment in his own occupation,he should be regarded as a civilian for employ-ment purposes.It was reported at a meeting of the Grays Committee that the live register of disabled men at the Exchange had been completely cleared.
APPOINTMENTS AND TRAINING.APPOINTMENTS AND CIVIL LIABILITIES DEPARTMENT.GENERAL.Re-organisation-A re-organisation of the department took effect from the 15th October.Directorates 1 and 2 have been amalgamated, so that the whole of Scotland has become Directorate 1, with headquarters at Perth. Directorate 6 has been divided, the counties of Derby, Nottingham and Lincoln being transferred to Directorate 5, and the counties of Northampton, Leicester and Rutland to Directorate 9. Directorate 7 has been reduced by the transfer of Oxfordshire, Berkshire and Buckinghamshire to Directorate 9..to policy holders involving an amount of  52,086 2s. Id. Full information for the week, however, is not yet available; payments reported too late for inclusion in the figure given above will be reported next week.Unemployment Insurance Benefit.-Th.e number of payments of unemployment insur-ance benefit made during the week ending the 22nd October was 59,409, involving an amount of  31,124 8s. 3d.JUVENILE BRANCH.Care of the Mentally Defective (Lancashire). At the invitation of the Lord Mayor of Manchester a conference was held recently to consider setting up an association in South-East Lancashire for the care of the mentally defective and epileptics. Eepresentatives attended from various bodies, including Juvenile Employment Committees. It was decided to form an association, which will be linked up, through a joint central committee, with similar associations covering the rest of the county. The association will carry on work similar to that of the London After-Care Association for the Mentally Defective, who, for some time have co-operated closely with the London Juvenile Advisory Committee. It is not clear, however, how far the Lancashire Association will undertake to place the mentally defective in employment. The Bolton Juvenile Advisory Committee have already considered the question of setting up, as part of their after-care system, a special after-care committee for the mentally defective, to work in co-operation with the association when formed.Apprenticeship. The Dudley Committee are proposing to convene conferences with representatives of the various local industries to discuss the question of apprenticeship. As a preliminary step, they have requested employers to make a return showing the con-ditions under which apprentices and other juvenile workers are employed.The Portsmouth Town Council are being urged by the local Juvenile Employment Committee to consider the desirability of preparing a scheme of apprenticeship for the various departments of the Corporation works. Eepresentatives of the furniture manufac-turing trade in Swansea are being invited to discuss the conditions of training with the Juvenile Employment Committee. At Wimbledon a sub-committee has been appointed to consult the Wimbledon Commercial Union and Trades Association regarding the possi-bility of establishing a local scheme of apprenticeship for the distributive trades.The question of apprenticeship in the building trades is still engaging many committees. At Cheltenham, where the Juvenile Employment Committee have been in consultation with the master builders&apos; association; the association have decided to leave the question to individual employers. The Chester Committee have under consideration the scheme prepared, by the Joint Industrial Council. At their last meeting, one member, the president of the Building Trades District Committee, stated that there was little prospect of many of the proposals becoming operative in the district. The scheme adopted for the district in March provides for wages considerably below those recommended by the Industrial Council. The matter is to receive further consideration at the next meeting.[References to matters of interest to the Employment and Insurance Department will also he found on pages 552 to 554, 556, 557, 562, 563, 573 and 575.]
[&quot; 1 Directorates 5, 9 and 7 have been re-numbered as 2,6 and 5, respectively. Directorates 3, 4, 8 and 10 remain unaffected in area, but are re-numbered as 3, 4, 8 and 7, respectively. The new districts retain the headquarters of the old directorates, except that the head-quarters for Scotland are placed at Perth, and Edinburgh ceases to be a head office. Nottingham, on transfer to District 2, ceases to be a head office.Consequent on these changes the District Selective Committees have ceased to be known by numbers, and are now named from the town in which they meet.APPOINTMENTS.Statistics. During the week ending the 29th October, the Appointments Department placed 510 candidates for appointments, bringing the total number of candidates known to have been placed to 43,827. Of these, 5,962 were placed through the agency of the departs ment&apos;s Interviewing Boards. Applications were registered from 786 ex-Service men and 30 civilians. The total number of candidates available for appointments on the 29th October was 11,720 ex-Service men and 1,620 civilians. At the same date, 1,296 &quot; live &quot; vacancies were at the disposal of the department, 686 having been registered during the week.BUSINESS AND PROFESSIONAL TRAINING.Maintenance and Training Grants Scheme. During the week ending the 29th October, the Appointments Department received applications for training under this scheme from 121 officers or men of equal educational qualifications, of which 56 were for training of the: type provided by the department. Deducting cancellations and withdrawals, 28,238 applications for training of this latter type have been received in all, and 50,311 for training of the types provided by other Government departments. The Interviewing Boards have dealt to date with 27,299 applications, of which 22,914 have been recommended. The Grants Committee, dealing with applications so recommended, have received 21,781 applications, and sanctioned grants in 17,957 cases.Training of Disabled Officers under Pensions Warrant. The Appointments Department have dealt with a total of 898 cases, in 430 of which the training sanctioned is provided by the Appointments Department and in the remainder by other Government departments.. Candidates accepted by the Ministry of Labour have completed their training in 281 cases and abandoned training in 39 ; 140 are still in training, and 33 are awaiting training.TRAINING DEPARTMENT. INDUSTRIAL TRAINING.Disabled and Other Ex-Service Men.\ .&apos; ...     ,Statistics. On the 2nd November, 24,943 men were in training, as against 25,024 on the 26th October, and 25,049 on the 6th October. There were 17,262 men awaiting training, the corresponding totals for the 26th October and the 6th October being 17,198 and 17,326, respectively. The number of men whose training had been completed since the&apos;1st August, 1919, was 19,486, the totals for the 26th October and the 6th October being 19,030 and 17,744, respectively.The total number of men in training is again slightly lower than that for the previous week, and there has again been a slight rise in the waiting list. Slight reductions in the number in training have occurred in 11 out of the 17 divisions, and the rise in the waiting lists affects 9 divisions. The number of men placed in training during the week was 375, a figure which is slightly below the average.Of the 17,960 men on the waiting list on the 28th September, 4,407 had been accepted&apos; for training by a Local Technical Advisory Committee, or had been definitely approved for training in a non-special trade.Publicity. Accounts have recently appeared in the Press of the work done at Mr. Bernard Oppenheimer&apos;s diamond-cutting factory at Brighton. Accommodation will ultimately be provided for 1,750 workers, and, with the branches at Cambridge, Wrexham, and Fort William, the total should eventually reach 2,000. The factory has proved a commercial success and an exceedingly valuable asset from the point of view of the Ministry. Practically all the 600 workers, including about 200 who are training under the Ministry&apos;s; general scheme, are disabled ex-Service men, and many suffer from severe physical dis-ability.  All the factory arrangements have been planned to meet their special requirements.&apos;(b 16626) * 4 D 3
Government Instructional Factories. The Government Instructional Factory at Luton was opened during the week. The South Midlands Division is almost entirely agricultural, and, in the earlier days of training work, the possibility of a factory appeared somewhat remote. After protracted negotiations, the Luton Factory has at last come on the active list. A start was made on the 3rd November, with 48 men in various branches of the furniture-ture trade.  Next week it is hoped that 20 carpenters and joiners will begin training.The Ireland and the Devon and Cornwall Divisions alone have now no factory facilities of their own. It is hoped, however, that a factory will soon be in being in Belfast, and considerable use is made of the Bristol Factory by the Devon and Cornwall Division.Reports show a general increase in the number of men in Government Instructional Factories. At the moment the Cricklewood Factory has the largest number of men in training, the record having for a long time been held by the Forbesfield Factory, Aberdeen. There are now 511 men in training at Cricklewood; this is the first factory to exceed 500. In Wales good progress has been made. There are now over 400 men in training at the Cardiff Factory, and nearly 150 at the Newtown Factory. In Scotland the newly opened factories at Dundee and Edinburgh are both doing well.From the Twickenham Engineering Factory, up to date, 68 men have been placed in employment. Unfortunately, hardship has been reported by several trained men thrown out of work through the coal strike.The trunk and leather case class at Harlesden are carrying out an order for 125 leather brief bags and 600 compressed fibre attache cases. Sales at the Loughborough Factory during September amounted to  603 1 86*., and there are contracts in hand for the value of  4,294. Sales at Lancaster Street, Birmingham, during October amounted to  1,101. At Birtley there are contracts in hand to the value of over  4,000.Equipment and Supplies. Orders have been placed by the department with the Bristol Factory for French polishers&apos; kit boxes, and with the Harlesden Factory for hairdressing and painters&apos; kit boxes.National Trade Advisory Committees: Boot and Shoe Trade. A meeting of the Ad-ministrative Committee (Training) of the Boot and Shoe Trade Board was held on the 2nd November, when 32 applications for training were approved. The committee, however, were of opinion that the trade had reached its full capacity for absorption, and pointed out that only very rare and verified cases-could be considered in the future.Local Technical Advisory Committees : Boot and Shoe Trade. At the inaugural meeting of the Colchester Local Technical Advisory Committee, on the 28th October, the committee agreed to act as a selection committee for well authenticated cases from North Essex.Local Technical Advisory Committees : Engineering. At a meeting of the Derby Local Technical Advisory Committee, on the 29th October, which was attended by the secretary of the National Trade Advisory Committee, it was agreed that some 200 men should be accepted for training, and that Local Technical Advisory Committees should be established, if possible, at Nottingham, Burton and Chesterfield.Apprenticeships Interrupted by Service.Statistics. Up to the 3rd November, agreements had been received at headquarters in respect of 44,983 apprentices under the 41 schemes approved. Grants had been sanc-tioned in respect of 42,656 apprentices, employed by 16,768 employers. The total number of agreements lapsed on the expiration of the appropriate period of training, or by mutual agreement between the parties, is now 12,780.Prescribed Rate. Some controversy has arisen with engineering employers in the Leicester district, in connection with a recent award of the Industrial Court which was to apply only to men over 21, and the special arrangement under the engineering scheme, whereby those whose original apprenticeship terminates before that age are paid on the Same basis as an apprentice of 21. Local headquarters report, however, that the position has been adjusted and no further difficulty need be expected.The Scheme in Operation.Applications. An attempt is being made to provide for &quot; unmated &quot; engineering apprentices at Leeds by means of institutional training. Facilities for a course are available, and six firms have already agreed to accept apprentices under the scheme for the purpose, and to employ them at the close of the course.
Acceptance or N on-Acceptance. The question of apprentices on the Scottish railways, which was in abeyance owing to the unwillingness of apprentices at Glasgow to press their claims, has been re-opened by the National Union of Railwaymen at Edinburgh on behalf of apprentices in that district. The whole matter, therefore, has been taken up again with the unions concerned. At Glasgow, the apprentices&apos; apathy is attributed by the local secretary of the Amalgamated Engineering Union to fear of victimisation. He proposes, however, to approach the shop stewards on the matter.Non-Observance of Conditions. The cases reported are mostly concerned with under-payments. At Glasgow, after continued failure by Messrs.. Lowden Bros. &amp; Co., electrical engineers, to make the right payments, the case was referred to the Local Employment Committee, who found that over  128 was due to the apprentice, and awarded him an additional 1\ per cent, as compensation. It remains to be seen whether the firm will accept this decision.Training in Operation. Reporting upon recent inspections, local headquarters for the North-Western Division describe the training in small shops as better and more varied than in larger firms doing repetition work. They mention especially appren-tices who act as mates to journeymen, and those who work with master tailors and boot-makers. Those employed upon maintenance in mills, it is stated, do not receive a very good training in many cases, and appear to be regarded by the journeymen as of a some-what inferior class. A satisfactory feature in Wales is the keen interest often taken in returning apprentices by foremen and journeymen, who have been energetic in helping them.Building firms in the South Midlands and Eastern area are reported to be anxious to set apprentices to the right work, and to train them as completely and rapidly as possible, in view of the demand for fully skilled men.Unemployment. Reports indicate that the coal strike has had definite effects on the employment of apprentices. In the Northern area, about 250 had already lost their employ-ment for this reason by the 23rd October, In the North-Western area a number of appren-tices were suspended, some of whom have asked for transfer to other firms. In view of the unsettled state of industry, fresh employers are practically impossible to find.Institutional Training. The increase in applications in the London and South-Eastern area continues steadily, and is again attributed to increasing unemployment. So far, local headquarters for London believe that they have provided for the majority of the applicants. In the case, however, of 50 apprentices of Messrs. H. Lebus, Tottenham, furniture manufacturers, fear is expressed that their efforts will be unsuccessful owing to lack of facilities in the district.At Paisley both the ordinary and the advanced classes are progressing exceptionally well. Evening classes for painters, decorators, and plumbers will shortly be started at Preston. Financial support is being given by the local master builders&apos; association, and apprentices under the scheme are expected to take advantage of the classes.General Training.Apprenticeship (Building Trades).-The secretary of the London Master Builders and Aircraft Industries Association has circularised members asking them to notify vacancies for apprentices. So far there has been no definite result, but it is believed that, if suitable applicants were sent for interview, many, employers would be prepared to engage them. Firms at East Ham, who are mostly engaged on repairs and maintenance work, have few vacancies, and as a rule do not favour indentures. The president of the Nottingham employers&apos; association, however, advocates their use in all cases, and welcomes the interest taken by the department in apprenticeship questions.Nottingham employers condemn the wage scale of the Joint Industrial Councils scheme as too high and likely to deter employers from engaging apprentices, especially when trade istbad. They point out that the journeymen may favour a high rate as an indirect means of keeping down the number of skilled men. They suggest a lower scale, with discretion to the employer to increase it in suitable cases. At Haslingden the objec-tion is made that the Council&apos;s scale may prevent small country employers from taking apprentices at all. A Blackpool firm point out that pressure of work during the summer may make,it difficult for painters&apos; apprentices to attend day continuation classes, and suggest that the hours of attendance be lengthened during the winter, to allow of a longer vacation during the summer.
i3.n.2a574Defective Training (Printing). At Preston there is reported to be no proper super-vision of apprentices, so that, during five or seven years&apos; apprenticeship, the quality of the training may be very much a matter of chance. One local firm state that industrial training is as important as education, and should be supervised by a State department in conjunction with representatives of the industry concerned.Women&apos;s Training.Training of Registered Unemployed Women. All the schemes in operation before the 30th June, and extended after that date, have now terminated. There remain in progress only six schemes, with a total of 40 trainees. Four schemes provide training in nursery nursing, one in cookery and one in waiting.Training of War Widows. The closing date for applications has now passed. Since the Ministry undertook the administration of the scheme, 4,969 applications have been received in all, of which 1,190 were received during October. A small proportion have proved to be from the widows of members of the Canadian Forces or the merchant service, and others ineligible for training. Their cases have been referred to the Central Committee on Women&apos;s Training and Employment. A number of applications were also received from widows who, though eligible under the scheme, did not desire to be trained, but wished for grants for other purposes. There remain, however, 1,988 fresh cases, which are being dealt with as rapidly as possible. During October the panel have sanctioned train-ing in 103 cases, and 55 widows have commenced their training.Midwifery and home dressmaking are the most popular forms of training desired. Difficulty arises in the first case from the fact that, though there is a large unsatisfied demand, especially in. rural areas, training vacancies are comparatively few. It has been found necessary in most cases to postpone training. Vacancies in midwifery institutions are being reserved for many months to come.Training in home dressmaking presents even greater difficulties, except in large towns such as Liverpool, Birmingham or Blackpool, where special classes can be formed. In London, however, where classes are urgently required, suitable premises cannot yet be obtained. When applicants are widely scattered it is almost impossible to find a centre sufficiently accessible to justify a special class. Training in the workrooms of drapery firms or private dressmakers is hampered by the revised Trade Board minimum rate for learners,, which employers find too high to pay to widows desiring only short intensive training.It has been decided that applications for the training of sailors&apos; and soldiers&apos; depen-dants shall be provisionally considered by the Training Department. Only those in receipt of a dependants pension under the Royal Warrant, or Order in Council, are eligible, and in every case the pre-war dependence must have exceeded the present pension.A report from one of the women training officers points out the beneficial effect of training on the health and physical condition of the widows. Many widows have them-selves realised the change and to what it is due. It is often found, when an applicant is first interviewed, that she is apparently drifting rather hopelessly through life, and the incentive to effort and the assurance as to the future offered by a course of training give her renewed confidence in life.Training of Disabled Nurses. During October four applications received sanction, for training in embroidery, massage and Swedish remedial gymnastics, secretarial work, and midwifery, respectively.Five nurses have satisfactorily completed their training. One, as a health visitor, has obtained a post in the Public Health Department at Manchester. Another has a post in the X-Ray department at the Children&apos;s Hospital, Great Ormond Street, and a third, after a course in poultry farmining, is setting up in a small holding. The two others have taken diplomas in dispensing and radiography.[Reference to matters of interest to the Appointments and Training Departments will also be found on pages 556, 557, 562 to 564, 570 and 575.]
APPENDIX.QUESTIONS IN PARLIAMENT.The following extracts from the Official Report of the proceedings of the House of Commons relate to questions in which the Ministry is interested.Training Allowances (Cardiff).Mt.C. Edwards asked the Minister of Labour whether he is aware that great dissatisfaction-tion exists among the trainees under the Ministry of Labour scheme at Cardiff owing to the inadequacy of the allowances paid to them and their dependants, the short period of training allocated to the respective courses of training, and the desire for direct representa-tion on all committees concerned with their present and future welfare ; and will he give favourable consideration to these complaints so as to remove the cause of discontent.Dr. Macnamara : As a result of a recent visit to Cardiff, I am aware of the representa-tions made by the trainees there. As regards the scale of allowances, I am sending my hon. friend a copy of the reply given on the 26th October to a question by the hon. member for Burslem. As regards the duration of training periods, in practically all cases the length of the course has been settled in consultation with national committees fully representative of both the employers and employed of the trade concerned. I have, however, ordered a careful review of the whole of the courses. As regards the question of representation on committees concerned with the interests of the men, most of the institutions have welfare committees, exclusively composed of the trainees themselves. Further, ex-Service men are invariably represented on Local Employment Committees, which are concerned, amongst other things, with the employment of trainees. Difficulty has been experienced in securing representation for trainees on Local Technical Advisory Committees. The view is held that, as these committees deal with functions of a purely technical character, the presence of the ex-Service man could not add to the value and authority of the committees&apos; decisions. There is, of course, a great deal to be said for this view. Nevertheless, I hope the national committees will look at the matter afresh, and consider whether the representation sought should not be accorded.   (3rd November.)Unemployment Insurance Act.Captain Terrell asked the Minister of Labour how many trades unions and how many friendly societies have hitherto notified their intention of working the Unemployment Insurance Act; and whether in all parts of the country the response is adequate from these two sets of bodies.Dr. Macnamara: Up to the end of October the number of applications received was 169. Of these, 148 were made by trade unions, and the remaining 21 by friendly societies or associations specially formed in connection with friendly societies. The applications, which come from bodies connected with nearly every industry, indicate a fairly general desire on the part of bodies eligible to do so to assist in the working of the Act. (3rd November.)Unemployment: Relief Schemes.&apos;Mr. Malone asked the Prime Minister what progress has been made with the Govermnenfs proposals for dealing with the question of the unemployed.Dr. Macnamara : I have been asked to reply. The Government are pressing forward as rapidly as possible with the schemes announced by the Prime Minister on the 19th October. Arrangements have been completed with regard to some 25 road schemes, on which work will commence shortly. I understand that in certain cases work has actually started and will grow in volume rapidly. As regards public works other than roads, the possibility of putting schemes in hand is being actively investigated. Measures have s already been taken by the Ministry of Health to secure that road and sewer work in housing schemes shall be taken in hand at once to a much larger extent than had been contemplated.
Appendix- continued.In this way employment will be afforded to a large number of additional men, particularly in the housing schemes of the London County Council, on which work is already proceeding. Negotiations are in progress with the trade unions in the building trades for the admission of additional men in connection with the housing programme, and if, as I hope, work is resumed in a few days&apos; time in the coal mines, the question of the admission of ex-Service men into the other trades mentioned by the Prime Minister will be taken up at once. (2nd November.) .DEBATES IN PARLIAMENT.Women and Young Persons (Employment in Lead Processes) Bill.The Rome Secretary on the 1st November, in moving the second reading of this Bill, said that the recommendations of the International Labour Conference, which the Bill carried out, did not set up a maximum standard. So far as this country was concerned the Bill would make little difference, as where we differed from the recommendations it was for the better.Mr. Hogge welcomed the Bill, but asked in what respects it was better than existent legislation, dealing with the subject, and what attempt would be made to see that all nations within the League adopted these minimum conditions for the industry. Mr. Wignall, on behalf of the Labour Party, was sure the Bill would be of real service. Provisions had been made for the erection of baths, and cleansing places but he knew that there would always be neglect on the part of the workpeople themselves. He emphasised the necessity of enforcing the remedy both on the employer and on the workpeople. Some criticism of the International Labour Conference on the ground of interference in domestic legislation was put forward by Sir F. Banbury and Sir J. D. Rees.The Home Secretary, in closing the debate, said that Clause 1, which prohibited entirely the employment of women and young persons in certain processes, *had substantially the same effect as existent Regulations, but extended them to certain occupations in which women or children had never been employed. Clause 2 extended the provisions of existent Regulations to certain other industries, such as perambulator making and leather-button making, where they have not hitherto been in force. -The Bill was read a third time on the 5th November and passed without a division.

</content>
</cab>
