<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/92/0 images: 297-299</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
is document is the property of Hi3 Britannic Ma ;majesty&apos;s Government.) &quot;221QJtfFIDENTIALCP. 40.CABINET.PROPOSED CABINET QOMJ.committee Oil ECONOMIC QUESTIONS,(Uoto by tho Secretary)Mr.K.F.Wisc, who is tho British Representative on thePermanent Committee of the Supreme Economic Council, recentlycalled on me to discuss the difficulty which the Ministers, Membersof the Supreme Economic Council, have sometimes encountered inobtaining rapid Cabinet decisions on questions affecting theCouncil.     He adumbrated a proposal for a Cabinet Committee to dealwith such questions.     I suggested that he should discuss the matter with the Ministers mainly concerned end then forward a Memorandumembodying what they consider desirable.    He has now done so andI circulate herewith Mr.Wise1s Memorandum containing proposals forthe establishment of a new Cabinet Committee..(signed)   M.PoA.Hankey.Secretary.Whitehall Gardens,3rd November, 1919.h9Memorandum by Mr*E.F*lffis9fdated &quot;16,10,19.1. In connection with the periodical meetings of theSupreme Economic Council and the weekly meetings of the PermanentCommittee of the Council, questions frequently arise on which itis necessary to obtain a decision on policy in respect of a question in which two or three British Departments arc concerned.     During1the evening before the meeting of the Supreme Economic Councilin Brussels on the 20th September the four Ministers attending onbehalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government sat for several hours considering-1-tho policy
the policy they should adopt on various important matters.     Itwas felt strongly that before the next meeting of tho council a Cabinet Committee composed of the Ministers concerned shouldbe set up to discuss,some considerable time beforehand, all important questions, of policy,2. So long esttho Supreme Economic Council was sitting inParis, weekly meetings for this purpose were held of ministers or their chief official representatives.     It is frequently thecase that the Treasury, the Foreign Office, the Ministry of Poodand the Board of Trade ere, to a greater or lesser degree, allconcerned in a particular question of Inter-Allied economic policy.It is, of course, particularly important that the Foreign office should be kept closely in touch with all discussions on economic policy before decisions are taken which may effect political relations with Allies or Neutrals,3. In addition to the Supreme Economic Council, tijere are other Inter-Allied or International bedies for wlii-Cn&quot; consideredinstructions on Government policy in respect of economic questionsere necessary.    The border line between the work of theReparation Commission end of the Supreme Economic Council is incertain respects not very clearly drswn.Many of the questions which will arise in connectionwith reparationa affoct profoundly our International financial policy, our relations with our present Allies and our general trade policy.    With all of these questions the Supreme economic council is directly concerned.    Further, the work of theCommittee, which is to be set up to supervise the execution ofthe Treaty, will undoubtedly involve similar questions of economic policy.4. It is moreover, certain that at tho first meeting ofthe Assembly of tho league of Rations to be held in public in washington, probably in January next, International economic questions will play e very large part.     It is already clear that many
??3w w umany of the smaller countries will raise the question of theprovision of credits by the more powerful States and will urge that special assistance be afforded them in connection with thesupply of foodstuffs and raw materials.There nay bo propounded also general propositions inconnection with import end e:port duties which will require mostserious consideration for as long a time as possible before theactual meeting of the League.5. The form of the organisation, International as distinct from Inter-Allied, to be set up under the authority of theLeague of Nations to carry on the work which, until the meetingof the League will be performed by the Supreme Economic Council,will need most aareful consideration.6. In order to secure proper consideration by Ministers ofthese questions, it is suggested that a Cabinet Committee shouldbe formed to meet as often as may be necessary.     To thisCommittee should be referred all economic questions, affectingmore than o$a Department, arising out of the work of the supreme economic Council, of the Reparation Commission, of the commission for the Szecution of the Treaty and of the League of nations.This Committee should have power of decision without further reference to the Cabinet unless in an$ particular matter such reference is in its opinion necessary.7. The Committee should be composed as followsThe Chsncellor of the ExchequerPresident of the Board of TradeSecretary of State for Foreign affairs(represented by the Under-Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs)?ood ControllerShipping ControllerChancellor of the Itachy of Lancaster(who is also Chairman of the wheat commission and of the Inter-Allied(Consultative Food OommrVuoe).        &apos;Controller of the Department of Overseas Trade.

</content>
</cab>
