<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/92/0 images: 369-371</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
281(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS PRTTANNIC MAJESTYTS GOVERNMENT.)CONFIDENTIAL.. .  CA BIN KTfCPs 45tEMPIX7YMENT . OF. DISABLED EX &quot;SERVICE MEN IN THE POST OFFICE.(Memorandum &quot;by the Minister of Labour.)lc   The Report of the Committee, appointed by me and preside over by Sir Malcolm Ramsay, on the question of the employment ofdisabled men in Government Departments, which was laid before the. y&amp;tti     .        ...Cabinet In my memorandum G,T,$i5, and approved by the Cabinet on13th August, contains a paragraph, a copy of which is attached(Appendix), dealing with promises already made to regular soldiers,sailors and airmen.   The effect of the paragraph is that therecommendations in the Report are not intended to over-ride suchpromises.   The cases referred to in this paragraph are those arising under an agreement with the Post Office whereby 50$ of certain classesof vacancies in the Post Office (mainly those of postmen) are reservedfor ex-professional sailors and soldiers (in the proportion of ^ths to soldiers and -gth to sailors), &apos; ..2*   I understand that If effect is given to this paragraph the result will be that, in the classes of Post Office employmentreferred to (which are those in which disabled men are most easilyemployed) there will be few, If any, vacancies left for disabledmen other than ex-professional sailors -or soldiers.   In other words,-a preference will be given In a large,number of cases to a non-disabledman over a disabled man on the ground that the former Is an ex-professional sailor or soldiere   It will even have the,furtherresult0 if carried out strictly, that a number of disabled men whofire at present temporarily in the employment of the Post Office wouldhave to be discharged in order to make room for non-disabled,ex-nrofessional sailors or soldiers.
&apos;    2823,   This position seems to me to be one which cannot possiblybo faced.   The war has completely altered the relations which the personnel of the Forces previously bore to the civilian population,and promise given before the war to soldiers may reasonably be read now as applying to all men who have served during the war andas being, if necessary, limited by the claims of these men0   It isobvious that public opinion will require that disabled men shouldhavo the first chance.   The disabled ox-professional soldier might,be given a preference over other disabled men, but it uould beimpossible to maintain for a moment a system under which a non-dicabled man was definitely given a preference over a disabled man,4.   I understand that the Post Office, who are in accord withthe views I have expressed In tho previous paragraph, d .sire tomodify the arrangements accordingly, but that the Tar Office areunable to agree, as they regard any change in the arrangements as a breach of faith with the ex-professional soldier.   The Admiralty,who are also concerned as regards the ex-professional sailor, have,I understand, fallen in with the proposed new arrangements. -5.   The maintenance of the 50$ preference for ex-professlonalsailors and soldiers would not onlj be Indefensible on merits, butit would also have the effect of making it extremely difficult, ifnot Impossible, for the Civil Service as a whole to absorb thopercentage of disabled men, which, in my opinion, it should andmust absorb.   This arises because, owing to its special conditions,one of the largest fields for the absorption of disabled men in theCivil Service lies in these classes of Post Office employment whichare now under considerations   As Minister of Labour I am concernedin this question partly because the maintenance of this preferencewas supported by th3 Report of a Committee -&apos;hich I appointed, andpartly because the general question of the employment of qlisabledmen falls within my province.   The only possible solution, in myopinion, is to discontinue the 50/o preference for ex-professlonal-2-
283sailors and soldiers and to lay it down that disabled men shouldbo employed In every post for which they are qualified, subject only, to such limited exceptions as may be unavoidable,, but that within the class of disabled men the disabled ex-professionalsoldier might well be given a preference over otherse60   The matter is one of considerable urgency, and I ask,therefore, for an early decision by the Cabinet8(SGD.) RtS.HORNE04th November, 1919-,APPENDIX.-,PARAGRAPH;: 25 OF THE RAMSAY COMMITTEES REPORT.PROMISES ALREADY MADT5 TO REGULAR SOLDIERS, SAILORS and airmen NOT OVER-RIDDEN BY RECOMMENDATIONS, - Re desire itclearly to be understood that in making these recommendations we have not. intended to over-ride the promises of employment on their discharge which have rlready been made by theGovernment to soldiers, sailors and airmen serving onnormal (peace) attestations,.   No posts which in the pasthave been expressly reserved for this class should be allocated to disabled men when a qualified ex-regular soldier, sailor orairman is available-

</content>
</cab>
