<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/92/0 images: 544-544</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This baayrbert is the Property ofHis Br,...?v&quot;   tVai&apos;, )oty&apos;s Government,-.--- -, ^ c lonGHUJ8$3T*Military Secret. J141421, From Viceroy, Army Department, to Secretary of Slate for India,&apos; Id November 19.19.(Received filli, 10.10 a.in.)14838. 3 1st October. Your -1118 of.20th october. Mallusun already has onoregiment of cavalry and one battalion of infantry at and around Meshed, and we are sending one battery&apos;of mountain artillery and another battalion of infantry to joinhim.2. The maintenance of aeroplanes at- Meshed presents great difficulties, and itAvould.be impossible to guarantee services of the machines and regular supply of petrol oil and spares at a distance of 600 miles from the railhead without a completesystem of motor convoys. This will take time to establish and will involve considerabletax on our present resources.Proposals would involve addition of one flight to our present establishment olaircraft, for we would not spare either machines or personnel from India. Nor could we provide personnel for mobile workshops and other necessary accessories of detachedflight,3. Although, as we told you in our 12358 of 10th September, we can maintain this force with our present organisation, we think it desirable to point out that, if theoccupation of Meshed by this force is likely to be prolonged, the extension of therailway from Duzdap to Neh would probably prove an economy.4. This section of road has grave climatic and topographical disadvantages. Itis at present fit for light motor traffic, but owing to great physical difficulties,particularly want of water for consolidating, Its improvement to proper motor transportstandard would present great difficulties and involve heavy expenditure. Cost ofcamel transport employed in this section is Rs. 43 lakhs a year, and owing to climate conditions rate of wastage is high. Health of personnel also suffers. Cost of railwayis estimated at Rs. 1,37,800 per mile, including rolling stock, or Rs. 238 lakhs for172 miles to Neh.5. Strategical advantage of extension in relation to our position at Meshed isobvious. In addition to facing actual operations, railway should produce good moral and steadying effect in Southern Afghanistan. Possible strategical objection is itsproximity to frontier and consequent liability to raids. Recent war has shown thatinhospitable belt of country between frontier and railway is adequate safeguard, and proposed extension will (corrupt group) additional protection of Hamim-i-Helinaiid.If extension is to be carried out, we consider that, owing to great distance of Meshed,only broad gauge would satisfy military requirements.0. We understand that commercial possibilities of East Persia route are already under examination by you. We- believe that, given good transport facilities, con-si considerable   trade could be attracted, hut, under present conditions, gap between Duzdapand Neh destroys utility of whole road.

</content>
</cab>
