<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/277/0 images: 69-74</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0 A B I N E T.SECRET. Copy No. MSCP.125(58) .    ELECTRIC IT Y DISTRIBUTION BILL.MEMORANDUM 3Y THE MINISTER OF TRANSPORT.(l)    I think it is necessary that I should lay before my colleagues a brief summary of the position reached in the preparation of and the negotiations upon this Bill,  and an appreciation of its political prospects.     The Bill is in process of being drafted in accordance with the decisions of the Cabinet - 9(37)&apos; Conclusion 9 and 39(37) Conclusion 16.(2)    The following are the events leading up to the present position.      In March 1937 the Government announced its intention of adopting the principles of the McGowan Report.      In April 1937 an outline of the Government&apos;s legislative proposals was issued.      Steps were then taken to draft a Bill but, owing ^to pressure upon Parliamentary Counsel, the Bill is not yet ready for submission to the Cabinet.     Meanwhile the Bill had been given a prominent place in the King&apos;s Speech, but the evident congestion of the Parliamentary time-table led to the Prime Minister&apos;s statement in Parliament, in March last, that -he saw no prospect of being able to proceed with the Bill this Session but hoped it might be possible to. take it early next Session.(3)    The object of the Bill is to carry into effect, with certain modifications which the Cabinet has approved, the recommendations of the McGowan Committee, of which the guiding principle is to concentrate in fewer hands the functions of the 600 separate statutory undertakings now responsible for the distribution of electricity.(4)    The Bill provides for the preparation or adoption of schemes together covering all parts of the country, each of which shall create a region of supply and shall establish for
that region a selected supply authority.     The machinery established in the Bill is designed to provide a sufficiently elastic method of dealing with the varying circumstances of different undertakings,and different parts of the country, after a full investigation of technical and other considerations. While schemes are to be prepared covering all parts of the country, it will be possible to establish existing authorities as selected authorities without change of area where that course is justified.      Grouping is to be determined upon merits and with reference to various governing considerations, the most important of which is that no scheme shall be made unless the Electricity Commissioners are satisfied that the scheme, when fully in operation, will^conduce to better conditions of supply including lower charges.      The original proposals strictly limited the circumstances in which a Joint Board of groups of local authorities could be formed, but are now to be extended to enable a Joint Board to take over areas from other undertakings (whether municipal or company) where a better grouping can thus be secured, provided the transfer will not prejudice the operation and development of the remaining area of any undertaking which is itself retained.(5)    I need not recapitulate the many arguments in support of the Bill such as, for example, the necessity for revising the obsolete boundaries and overlapping powers which have their origin in past history and are not defended by any competent opinion as being appropriate to present needs.      I would, hoy/ever, draw attention to the risk of actual disintegration of existing areas now served by many of the Supply Companies into smaller and more numerous units if steps are not taken to deal with the existing purchase rights vested in local authorities up and down the country.(The McGowan Committee in their Report - paragraphs 69-71 draw special attention to this important point).
(6)    The action which the Government has taken in setting-up the McGowan Committee and in announcing its intention of adopting the principles&apos; of the Committee&apos;s Report, has created an expectation that steps were to be taken at an early late to deal with the admittedly unsatisfactory state of electricity distribution.      The delay in the introduction of the Bill has undoubtedly fostered the view that the opposition of certain vested interests is deterring the Government from dealing with the matter.(7)    The Industry is at present living in a state of uncertainty.      This must inevitably favour a waiting policy, so that in certain areas much needed extensions and development may be delayed.     Moreover, there have already been difficulties and there will be increasing difficulties in dealing with present changes of structure in the Industry such as voluntary amalgamations and the exercise of purchase rights.     There is an increasing danger of attempts to manoeuvre for position before reorganisation takes place.      It is essential. that any transaction now taking place should not prejudice the future reorganisation, but it is difficult to attain this end. As their purchase rights mature, certain local authorities naturally apply for consent to exercise them and,  as further rights mature, there will be an increasing number of difficult cases with which it is impossible to deal satisfactorily without prejudging or appearing to prejudge the scheme of the Bill.      In addition, delay must be against the consumer.      In so far as systems and voltages can be standardised by consolidating undertakings, the longer the Bill is delayed the greater will be the development in the meantime of non-standardised systems and the greater the ultimate expense. There is also a great deal of dissatisfaction in the rural areas both with rates and development and the Government&apos;s only answer to this is the hope that amalgamations may
encourage a more progressive policy.(8)    In support of the Bill I can claim -(a)    The fact that no responsible body of opinion in the Electricity Supply industry denies- the urgent need for some scheme of reorganisation.      This is true of the Committee of Smaller Municipal Authorities itself. The whole industry is expecting and has for some time been expecting the Government to act. (h)    The demand of consumers (particularly in agricultural areas) for legislation designed to secure lower charges and extended services.     Consumers may be looking to the Bill to afford them more substantial advantages in these directions than can immediately accrue, but there will no doubt he a stimulus to development in rural areas and simplification and reduction of tariffs as the schemes come fully into operation.(c) The benevolent neutrality of the larger municipalitieswho are confident that their position will he maintained and perhaps enlarged.(d) Hg..,strong opposition from the Companies in principle(and some support) provided they are satisfied on terms of purchase and length of franchise.It may be that the Companies as a whole are so concerned at the possibilities of the exercise of purchase rights by the local authorities that they are more favourably disposed to the Bill than they have indicated.The Managing Director of one of the Power Companies recently stated publicly that &quot;the Report of the McGowan Committee has pointed a way to overcome these difficulties and to secure a still cheaper and more abundant supply of electricity, by the
retention and utilisation of large and efficient organisations such as that which the Company has built up, by the absorption of smaller undertakings and by granting to the Company an assurance of tenure of a unified scheme11. (9)    Against the Bill are ranged -(a)    Political Labour, opposition, who desire reorganisationon a regional basis in public ownership and under national control. (D)    Many of thesmaller municipal undertakings, who arestrenuously opposed to any compulsory loss of theirseparate identities.(c) Any Municipal undertakings likely to be acquired bya Company, unless they are satisfied on terms of purchase.Negotiations on this matter have been carried to a sufficient point to show&apos; that much of this objection can be met.(d) The general argument of municipal interests that public municipal ownership ought not only to be maintained but extended and extended immediately by transferring companies to municipalities and that only in exceptional circumstances should any municipal undertaking be transferred to company ownership. (10)    Politically, the chief reactions seem to me to be -(a) Surpise on the part of the industry generallyif bo steps are taken to implement the McGowan Report.(b) Consumers generally, and agriculturalists inparticular, will be disappointed if the Bill is dropped or postponed, and the Government will he exposed to the charge of having been deterred from an admittedly necessary reform by pressure
27th May, 1938.on the part of vested interests, (c) The main opposition will he from the smallerMunicipalities owning electricity undertakings.vvhile I have indicated my willingness to consider any reasonable additional alternative basis of reorganisation, the Committee representing these interests have not hitherto been able to submit any proposals which I could regard as satisfactory or even workable. (11)    In this note I have set out the position as I see it and I now seek the further guidance of my colleagues.(Intld.)      E.L.B.

</content>
</cab>
