<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/277/0 images: 484-487</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
9 9  TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY. 0tiIt is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.SECRET.CP.  154 (38). Copy No.    ^CABINET.MAINTENANCE OP THE ADVANCED AIR STRIKING- FORCE ON THE CONTINENT.Memorandum by the Minister for Co-ordinationof Defence.At their 328th Meeting, held on the 30th June, 1938,  the Committee of Imperial Defence had under consideration a Report by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee on the Maintenance of the Advanced Air Striking Force on the Continent (Paper No. D.P. (p) 30. 2. The Committee of Imperial Defence agreed:-&quot;(a)    To approve the Report by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee on the Maintenance of the Advanced Air Striking Force on the Continent (Paper No*  D. P. (P) 30).(b)    That the Report by the Chiefs of Staff, together with the above conclusion thereon, should be submitted to the Cabinet.,f3. In accordance with Conclusion (b)  above Icirculate herewith for the information of my colleagues a copy of the Report by the Chiefs of Staff (Enclosure No.  l) and the relevant extract from the DRAFT Minutes of the Committee of Imperial Defence (Enclosure No.  2).(Intld. )    T.W.H.I.2, TShitehall Gardens, S.W.I. 1st July, 1938.
Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   June 1938.SECRET.Copy No.    $2IXP. (P.) 30. -&quot;*mm*w**.(Also Paper No. C.O.S. 735.)TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.MAINTENANCE OF THE ADVANCED AIR STRIKING force on THE CONTINENT.(Previous Paper No. D.P. (P.) 29.)Report by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee.IN our Report on Staff Conversations with France and Belgium (Paper No. C.O.S. 727,* paragraph 19), we pointed out that &quot;if an advanced air striking force is employed in the same theatre as the field force, the base and L. of C. units required by the former can be found within the existing resources of the army.- If, on the other hand, the advanced air striking force and the field force have to operate in different theatres, additional units must be formed, for which no provision exists at present.&quot;2. The Cabinet, at their meetingt held on the 25th May, 1938, considered our Report on Staff Conversations, and recorded, inter alia, the following conclusion : * * * * * *      -&quot; (/) That the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence should call the attention of the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee to the following passage in paragraph 19 of their Report* : &apos; If, on the other hand, the advanced air striking force and the field force have to operate in different theatres, additional units must be formed for which no provision exists at present.&apos;The Minister should invite them to consider what action should be taken to correct this deficiency to which the representatives of the French General Staff are likely to call attention.&quot;In accordance with instructions from the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence, we have examined this question further, and our views are as follows : 3, It appears to us that there are, broadly speaking, three sets of circum-stances to be considered. First, there is the possibility that the advanced air striking force might be sent to France immediately war had broken out, in advance of any decision which might subsequently be taken as to the despatch overseas of a field force. In these circumstances, there would be no difficulty in providing the necessary base of L. of C. troops, amounting to about 5,000 men, which would be required for the maintenance of the advanced air striking force.* Paper No. D.P. (P.) 29; also Paper No. C.O.S. 727. f Cabinet 26 (38), Conclusion 4 (/).[17445]
4. A second possibility is the simultaneous, or almost simultaneous, despatch of the advanced air striking force and of the field force to the Continent. The maintenance of these two forces, even if they do not necessarily operate in the same area, presents no insuperable difficulty.5. There is, however, a third possibility. It might be that, owing to a deteriorating situation in the Middle East, e.g., vis-a-vis Italy, or owing to major disturbances in Palestine, the field force, or a considerable part of it, might be despatched to that area. If, subsequently, we became involved in war against Germany and the advanced air striking force were despatched to France, base and line of communication troops would be inadequate for its maintenance on the Continent.6. In these circumstances some delay in the despatch of the Advanced Air Striking Force would occur before the necessary troops could be made available.Conclusion.7. To sum up, the contingencies envisaged in paragraphs 3 and 4 can be met, while the contingency envisaged in paragraph 5 seems to be so remote that it would not be justifiable to raise additional units for the specific purpose of maintaining the advanced air striking force on the Continent, even though there is the risk that there might be some delay in the despatch of this force. In the meanwhile, the Chief of the Imperial General Staff is considering what steps can be taken.(Signed) CHATFIELD.C. L. N. NEWALL. GORT.2 Whitehall Gardens, S. W. 1, June 20, 1938.
Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   June 1938.SECRET. ^ ^        j Copy No.    g to BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.Extract from the DRAFT Minutes of the 328th Meeting, held on June 30, 1938.kit. .JL. -V. m. -it- Ji.&apos;7i- *7l- &quot;A&quot; ^,      *7T -TV- TC-(4) MAINTENANCE OF THE ADVANCED AIR STRIKING force on THE CONTINENT.(Paper No. D.P. (P.) 30.)(Previous reference : C.I.D. Minutes of the 325th Meeting, Minute 3.)THE COMMITTEE had under consideration a Report by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee on the subject of the maintenance of the advanced air striking force on the Continent (Paper No. D.P. (P.) 30).SIR CYRIL NEWALL, introducing the Report at the request of the Chairman, said that the question had arisen out of a Report which the Chiefs of Staff had submitted to the Cabinet on staff conversations with France and Belgium. Three contingencies were envisaged. In the first case, the advanced air striking force might precede the despatch of a field force to the Continent. The second possibility was the simultaneous or almost simultaneous despatch of these two forces. In both the above eventualities, no maintenance difficulty would arise. There was, however, a third possibility that the field force might be despatched to the Middle East, and subsequently it became necessary to send the advanced air striking force to France. In this contingency some delay would occur before the necessary maintenance troops could be made available. The Chiefs of Staff were agreed that it was unjustifiable to raise additional units solely to meet this remote contingency, but the Chief of the Imperial General Staff was considering what steps could be taken to reduce the delay.Conclusions. The Committee of Imperial Defence agreed :-(a) To approve the Report by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee on themaintenance of the advanced air striking force on the Continent (Paper No. D.P. (P.) 30).(b) That the Report by the Chiefs of Staff, together with the above conclusionthereon, should be submitted to the Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1, June 30, 1938.[17482-3]

</content>
</cab>
