<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/277/0 images: 510-510</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
With, regard to the&apos;   Minister of Agriculture&apos; s memorandum (C.P.147(38)t I agree that the Sydney   Resolutions are evidence of a more enlightened attitude than we have hitherto seen on the part of Dominion producers (and incidentally that the representatives of the National Farmers&apos; Union deserve great credit for bringing the change about).      I agree also that there ought to he a general statement of the Government&apos;s views on the issues which have been raised.    At the same time I feel that any such statement ought to be very cautiously worded.      Discussions as to its precise terms have been proceeding between the Departments concerned and have not yet been concluded, but I understand that the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries and the Secretary of State for Scotland are anxihus to obtain authority to make a statement as early as possible.-We should all agree that as an alternative to import regulation the &quot;commodity council&quot; system has everything te commend it;    but   &apos; the draft statement appended to Co P.147(38) appears to me to be open in some respects to misinterpretation.      It might be read as implying (a) that we approve of the commodity council system for all foodstuffs without distinction, even those such as butter of which we are relatively small producers and in which our predominant interest is as consumers;    and (b) that where a commodity council is not set up the Government always will be prepared to regulate imports themselves.      I do not think that we could undertake to regulate imports except where, as in the case of beef, substantial United Kingdom interests are at stake.I think, therefore, that further consideration should be given to the precise terms of the statement which it is proposed that the Government should make.C A B I N E T.THE BRITISH EMPIRE PRODUCERS&apos;  CONFERENCE,  SYDNEY.COMMODITY COUNCILS.Note, by the  resident of the Board of Trade.O.F.G. S.card of Trade.5th July, 1938.

</content>
</cab>
