<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/7/10 images: 136-151</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-us document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s governmentTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY. - -       ^It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this.document.S E C R E T. /w^P.(itO) 13.Q. 1/TXlso Paper No.n.f)..s.(uO) &quot;297).ifrPH APRILn 19L0. -   COPY NO.  2 ^WAR CABINET.-MEASURES TO DETER ITALY FROM ENTERING THEWAR AGAINST THE ALLIES.Report &quot;by the Chiefs of Staff Committee.rWe set out below brief notes on the military andeconomic measures which might be adopted if the WarCabinet should decide to make a show of force against italy, with the idea of deterring her from interveningon the German side..2o     The Linistry of Economic Warfare has been consultedwith regard to the economic measures.NAVAL MEASURES.3.     The most effective naval measure for indicating ourfirm intentions to Italy would be to concentrate strongnaval forces in the Eastern lviediterranean and Red Seaareas.     The reasons for this are:-(a) It would threaten Italian coiaiaunications with(i)   Her African Empire, and(ii)    Her important Black . Sea. trade--route.&quot;(b) The show of naval strength should stiffenTurkey&apos;s attitude vis-a-vis Italy.4.     Complementary naval action by the French Fleet in theWestern basin would complete the threat to Italian sea communications.5* The provision of adequate Naval Forces in the eastern mediterranean and Red Sea areas could, only be made

by considerably reducing the forces available for operations against Germany in the North Sea, a course ofaction not practicable at the present moment.6.     Diversion of through Mediterranean shipping, while a necessary measure, if war with Italy was imminent, would,it is thought, be too drastic a measure for our purpose,since it might make Italy think that we had already made up our minds to go to war with her.     Furthermore, we shouldbe handicapping ourselves by the increased shipping commitment...LAND AND AIR MEASURES,Europe..7.     Certain measures might be taken to create theimpression that active operations., on the Franco-1 tali anfrontier are under consideration.      It might be possiblefor the French to make certain troop movements for thispurpose. .8.     The Italians are particularly sensitive to any threat to their industrial area in the North West.     Some activity on aerodromes in south east France, including perhapsreconnaissances by R.A.F. officers and discussion, not toocarefully concealed^    of administrative preparations forthe reception of British units, might have valuable results

jqorth Africa.g It is understood that the French have withdrawn fromTunisia the majority of the troops and aircraft which wouldbe necessary for offensive action against Libya-      The re-constitution of these forces would have a deterrent effect,though it could probably only be at the expense of theircollaboration in the Caucasus plan.Hlcrypt.   Land Forces.10.       A concentration of troops might be made in advancedpositions in the Western desert.      The effect of this would depend on French co-operation referred to in paragraph above.Egypt.    Air Forces.11.       Any measures we could take to increase our air forcesin Egypt and Palestine would prove a valuable deterrentwithout affording direct provocation. - &quot;&quot;&quot;The^ollowijig mov* smight be made:-(a) The two Indian bomber Squadrons at Singaporecould be brought baclc to Egypt instead ofto India, as now intended,     Their returnto India was designed to meet a possibleRussian threat.      From Egypt they could bereturned to India in approximately 14 days and Singapore in 21 days.(b) The South African Government have agreed toprovide three squadrons for service in Kenya,but the offer is conditional on our providingmodern aircraft.   -24 Gladiator and 24 Battleaircraft have been offered to the South african government for one fighter and one bombersquadron respectively, and they have beenasked to re-equip the G.R. Squadron with Alisonswhich are already en route to South Africa.(c) The arrival of South African Squadrons in Kenyawill release the Rhodesian squadron in Kenyafor service in Egypt.(d) An Australian Army Co-operation Squadron from-Australia to Palestine. Move dependent onprovision by us of Lysander aircraft whichare unli] aly^ to be available before July.Ostentatious arrangements could be put in hand forthe move to the Sudan of ono or both of the infantry&quot;brigades at present held .in   reserve   in   Palestine.

The political effect of this measure as effecting itnly!position in Abyssinia might be &quot;appreciable.Jibuti.23,       The French might be prepared to send Hadagascantroops-, possibly one infantry brigade,  to Jibuti.      Thisis the place from which any offensive into Abyssinia wouldbe launched, a point which oho Italians, would quicklyrealise.Kenya.14,       Two brigades from West Africa, and possibly afurther brigade from -South Africa, could be sent to reinforce the two brigades now in Kenya, and so demonstrateAllied strength on the southern frontier of Abyssinia.A concentration of air forces iri*T3?rry&amp;^wxu2jX add to this effect.  (See-,para^i-l.(b.l..above),Somaliland.15,       One battalion has already been ordered to Somaliland from Kenya and is expected, to arrive there in April.Additional effect would be given by the despatch, orarrangements for the despatch,&apos; of a second battalior?from the same source.Nigeria.16.      The French are believed to have had a project for moving African troops via Nigeria to threaten Libya fromthe south.      The move of these troops would be significantto the Italians.

Dodecanese Islands.17.&apos;      Turkish action in the preparation of troop movements into south-western Anatolia opposite the dodecanese Islands would have some effect, especially if their activities included apparent arrangements for  &apos;collecting light craft and for organising a combined operation.ECONOMIC&quot; MEASURES.18.       We could bring pressure to bear on Italy bytightening up the Allied contraband control againstG-erman imports and exports at the Mediterranean, bases,which has so far been applied somewhat leniently whereItaly is concerned.      The degree to which this couldbe done would depend on the availability of naval forces at any particular time.19.       Stricter control would delay Italian shipping,and would generally impede the flow of her trade.      Itwould also deny her some of the profits which she is,at present, making through the carriage of goods onGorman account. .20.       In tightening up control we could enforce a &quot;Black-List&quot; policy against Italian traders and demand satisfactory &quot;Certificates of Origin&quot;.21.       More severe economic measures which we might take are :&apos;-(a) Limitation of Italian imports of essential commodities to the quantities necessary to meet herdomestic needs,  (55$ of Italian imports normallycome through Gibraltar),,

(b) Irap,o&amp;i2^.fJj^2i^jdsX^ej&amp;restrictions on Italy, suohas denying sterling and franc credit, refusing re-insurance in the London market, reducing Alliedpurchases in Italy and introducing a &quot;Cash and Carry&quot;principle for our trade with Italy..(c) Finally as an extreme measure, we couldcompletely sever trade relations between the Britishand French Empires and Italy, by refusing export licences and prohibiting imports.General Comments.22.       The measures set out above would in many casesnecessitate a departure from the policy we have so farfollowed of not offending Italian susceptibilities.In deciding whether to put any or all of them intoeffect at any time, the following factors should betaken into account.(a) We should study Signor Mussolini&apos;s personalreactions, as well as the mentality of the Italianpeopleo     Any provocative action on our part, andanything calculated to re-awaken the &quot;sanctions&quot;bogey would be very likely to have an effect quiteopposite to that at which we should be aiming.(b) Our aim would best be achieved by the cumulative effect of a number of unobtrusive measuresto improve our strength in the Mediterranean,  ratherthan by any more striking&apos;gesture.(c) If it were decided to give effect to anyof the above measures, they should be woven into a carefully co-ordinated plan, and full use shouldbe made of the Inter-Service Security Board, working in collaboration with the French, The co-operationof the Turks should also bo sought.

(d) Finally, we should not take any drasticsteps to tighten up our economic pressure on Italyunless we were in a position to hack them up withthe necessary naval strength in the Mediterranean,(Signed)    H.R.S. MASSEY.   for C.I.G.S.R.E,G. PEIRSE for C.A.S.G.  BLAKE for C.N.S.Richmond Terrace, S.W.I.




</content>
</cab>
