<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/60/15 images: 136-141</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   December 1944.SECRET. / Copy No.W.P. (44) 765.29th December, 1944.WAR CABINET.UNDER-RIVER TUBES.Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council.THE Lord Presidents Committee at their meeting on the 22nd December,1944, considered memoranda* by the Minister of War Transport and the HomeSecretary and Minister of Home Security about the question whether an arrange-ment should now be made to give the London Passenger Transport Board a warning which would enable them to close the flood gates of the under-rivertubes when a rocket is approaching this country, t This could be done with littleinterference to traffic. The flood gates would be closed for about 3 minutes, and passengers would not be turned out of the trains.2. It was agreed that if it were decided to give this warning as a privatearrangement with the London Passenger Transport Board there should be no mention of the arrangement in the press, but guidance might be given to thepress.3. There would, however, be a risk that, if it became widely known that aprivate warning system had been introduced for the London Passenger transport board, there would be a demand for a general warning when rockets are approaching this country. The answer to such a demand might be that, while a warning of 90 seconds might enable protection to be provided against a seriouscalamity such as would be created if 57 miles of tubes were flooded, it would do little to protect the victims of a rocket incident of the ordinary type and wouldoccasion great waste of working time.4. It is also necessary to consider the position of the 4,500 people who make use each night of shelter accommodation in tube stations which, if the worsthappened and there was a major breach of the under-river tubes, would be liableto be flooded within 15 minutes. The Committee generally agreed that if andwhen the warning system was brought into operation, steps should be taken totransfer to other accommodation the shelterers in these tubes. The HomeSecretary and Minister of Home Security pointed out. however, that this step would be likely.to lead to some difficulties with shelterers, and might result inloss of confidence-in the safety of the tube shelters generally.5. Discussion also showed that there was some divergence of opinion among experts as to the behaviour of rockets falling into water. The lord presidents Committee accordingly invited the Paymaster-General, in consulta-tion with experts of the Departments concerned, to prepare a report on thismatter.  His report is annexed to this memorandum.6.   The Lord Presidents Committee (i) Agreed that the necessary work for the installation of the proposedradar warning system should proceed, but that the operation of the warning should be deferred pending consideration of the Paymaster-General s report.* L.P. (44) 205 and 206.t Under present arrangements the flood gates are closed when there is red warning fromnying bombs.[28912]
(ii) Agreed that, when the warning system was brought into operation, steps should be taken to transfer to other accommodation the shelterers inthose tube stations which were liable to flooding within 15 minutes inthe event of a major breach,(iii) Agreed that the matter should be reported to the War Cabinet, and thatin this connection attention should be drawn to a suggestion made in discussion that it might be possible to effect a considerable reductionof the risks in question if heavier attacks were made on the depotsin which the rockets were stored and the areas from which they were launched.7. The matter is accordingly submitted for the consideration of the WarCabinet.On behalf of the Committee :C. R. A.Privy Council Office, S. W. 1,29th December, 1944.ANNEX.Preliminary Report by the Paymaster-General.I was asked at the Meeting of the Lord Presidents Committee on the22nd December, 1944, to &quot; prepare a report, in consultation with representativesof the Admiralty, Air Ministry and the Ministry of Home Security, on thequestion-whether if a rocket fell in the river near one of the under-river tubesthe explosion was likely to breach the tube.&quot;   I consulted that day Dr. Bullard (Admiralty)Group Captain Menzies (Air Ministry)Squadron Leader McPherson (Air Ministry)Dr. Stradling (Ministry of Home Security)Dr. Christopherson (Ministry of Home Security)Brigadier Jefferis (M.D. 1)Dr. Davis (Road Research Laboratory)and telephoned to the Ministry of Home Security that there seemed to be aconsensus of opinion that while there was little danger during high tide, theevidence available suggested that a serious breach might occur at low tide.2. Such evidence as there is derives from two incidents in which rocketsexploded in shallow water. One case occurred at Sunbury reservoir, in whichthe depth of water was 10 ft. and the bottom consisted of 2 ft. of sand on top of 10 inches of concrete : the explosion caused a crater 15 ft. in diameterand extending 18 inches below the concrete. In the other case a V. 2 explodedin about 12 ft. of water in the Thames Estuary at All Hallows : a crater22 ft. in diameter and 5 ft. deep was caused. The measurements in this casewere not actually made until two tides after the event, but it is not believed thatthis will have had any appreciable effect. In addition to these two cases thereare unconfirmed reports of V. 2 explosions in Antwerp docks having caused no damage to the bottom. On the face of it serious damage would not be expectedthrough 30 or 40 feet of water, but Dr. Bullard has requested SHAEF torender an official report on these incidents.3. The four tubes which cross the river at Hungerford Bridge are laid 15 ft.below the river bottom, the depth of water averaging 6 ft. at low tide and 26 ft.at high tide. They are 12 ft. in diameter and the walls consist, in the case ofthe Northern Line pair, of f in. cast iron and, in the case of the BakerlooLine pair, of the same with an inner lining of \ in. steel. Although the evidence before us is that a crater Avould not reach the tubes even at low tide, a thin-walled cast iron tube would certainly be broken at some distance from the crater.The question is how far below the crater the tubes would be liable to seriousrupture.  As full-scale experiments to test this would take a long time, the Road
P 9ydResearch Laboratory is trying to link up our knowledge about the effective down-ward explosive force of the rocket, derived from observed incidents, with information obtained from ia number of previous experiments on the vulnerabilityof the tubes, based on the German 250 kilogramme bomb. These experiments arein progress and it is hoped that they may be concluded in 10 days or so. It isquite likely, however, that the answer will not be a categorical yes or no, but thatit will merely say that, if a rocket falls in a given part of the river, the chanceof its causing a serious breach will be x per cent.4. There seems every reason to believe that any bursting layer, e.g., over-head wires carrying a comparatively light net, would be sufficient to set off therocket above the water, in which case there would be no danger to the tubes what-ever. I think this point should be further examined before any decision is takento close the tubes, having regard to all the serious secondary complications thatthis step would involve.5. A.D.G.B. now believe that it should be possible to predict in whichparticular locality a rocket is likely to fall if two special G.L. stations wereinstalled for the purpose. It might be worth while to explore whether this couldbe done in time to warn those concerned to shut the tube gates. If the warningcould be confined to the few occasions on which the rocket fell within a reasonablyshort distance of the tubes, the number of times on which traffic had to beinterrupted would be very greatly reduced.*6. On the other hand this procedure might have certain dangers. If it became known it might create a public demand that warnings be provided for particular localities over the whole of Southern England.7.   The salient facts may be summarised as follows : (i) There is little risk of a rocket which does fall in the Thames Over thetube fracturing the tube at high tide; only experiments now in handcan show what the risk is at low tide.(ii) A bursting layer would eliminate all risk and, in spite of the obviousdifficulties, this might be preferable to causing public alarm by closingthe tubes several times a day.(iii) A.D.G.B. now believe it possible to predict the fall of a rocket in aparticular locality; if this can be done in time to close the gates,warnings to the tube might be confined to the comparatively rarecases when an impact near the danger area was expected.C.28*A December, 1944.* Only 17 rockets out of 230 reaching the United Kingdom have fallen within 3 miles ofring Cross.




</content>
</cab>
