<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/92/0 images: 170-173</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1958C. (58) 65 Copy No.21st March, 1958CABINETEUROPEAN FREE TRADE area memorandum by the Paymaster-GeneralThe negotiations on the establishment of a European Free Trade Area havereached a crucial stage, and I need the advice and guidance of my colleagues.2. The 17-nation Committee have been working on the basis of a comprehensive agenda, every item on which has been discussed. The positionsheld by all the countries are now clear.3. The time factor is important. Our object is to ensure that the tariff reductions in the Free Trade Area coincide with those under the Treaty of Rome,which begin on 1st January, 1959. To do this we must ensure that we have reachedsubstantial agreement before the summer holidays. In any case, failure to reach agreement by then is likely to mean that public support for the whole project will grow cold. There are, it is true, many points of difficulty. But the fact is that nocountry has been prepared to embark upon a real negotiation on details while thequestion is still open whether there can be any basic agreement at all. Once it hasbeen established that the major Powers can agree on the major issues, then people will begin to negotiate and rapid progress can be made.4. The three major issues remain as they have been throughout-agriculture,what is known as the question of origin, and the problem of France. I dealt withthese points in my paper (C. (58) 27) which was discussed by the Cabinet on 4th February (C.C. (58) 14th Conclusions, Minute 6). Developments since then have been as follows.agriculture . There is little more to report on this score. The difficulty has been thatwhile other people have been prepared to criticise our ideas, they have not producedcounter-proposals. There are now signs that they are beginning to do this. At thenext meeting in Paris on 31st March I hope to have papers available from several members of the Committee, including, I hope, an agreed paper from the &quot; Six &quot; France, Germany, Italy and the Benelux countries. I shall be in Copenhagen on20th and 21st March and I hope next week to be able to give my colleagues orallythe latest news about agriculture.Origin6. We had a useful discussion on this subject in Paris last week. Two facts in particular were established:  (i) that there is no support for the French attempt to use the rules of originto protect themselves against competition from products producedentirely within the Free Trade Area;(ii) that no serious practical problems can arise from the absence of aharmonised external tariff for at least four years from the start of theFree Trade Area.Subject to this the fact remains that there is still a great division of opinion between two schools of thought.   The first, comprising France, Italy and to some extent53188THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY 0* HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT
Belgium, wishes to maintain a high tariff structure on a wide range of raw materials and semi-manufactures and therefore considers it necessary to have strict originrules defined in advance. The remaining members of the Committee do not believe in a high tariff policy of this kind, but consider that the practical problems likelyto arise will not be great and cannot be defined beforehand and that what is neededis some simple institutional provision for dealing with any problems as and whenthey do emerge. The Italian representative, Professor Carli, produced a new plan as an attempt at a compromise. The plan as it stands would be quite unacceptable to both sides, but expert study is being given to it and there is just a possibility thatif drastically altered it might make some contribution to solving the problem.France7. The French attitude remains as hostile as ever. Based as it is on a combination of deep-seated protectionism and violent jealousy of Britain, andfanned by the vigorous propaganda activities of the French employers, it presentsa formidable obstacle to agreement. The French have produced a plan which theyhave put to their colleagues in the Six; as it stands it is acceptable to none of them,but urgent attempts are being made to produce a revised plan. The aim is that this plan should be approved by the Ministers of the Six at a meeting on 22nd april and then transmitted to the Paris Committee for immediate consideration by the&quot; Seventeen.&quot;The British Position8. We entered these discussions with very limited room for negotiation.We are not prepared to give any commitments of a specific character on agriculture; we have declared our intention of maintaining our special relationswith the Commonwealth; we are not prepared to accept any of the provisions for harmonisation of industrial, social and commercial policy that are an essential feature of the Treaty of Rome. The Free Trade Area proposal is in fact tailor-made to suit British requirements.9. We have been able to make minor concessions on one or two points.For example, we have agreed that agriculture should be discussed, though noton the same basis as industry. The Commonwealth countries will lose suchpreferences as they enjoy, compared with Europe, in industrial products. Wehave recognised that a Free Trade Area will mean closer co-operation between member countries in economic and financial policy and will involve an implicitobligation in each country not to use its commercial freedom so as to damage itsneighbour or, at any rate, if damage proves inevitable, to provide somecompensation. So far we have been able to retain the general impression thatthe British are being reasonable and accommodating and genuinely seekingagreement. It is we who have been holding the initiative, and it is the French,with occasional support from the Italians and other members of the Six, who havebeen the negative factor. Our objects in the crucial phase that is approachingmust be:  (a) to achieve success at some acceptable cost;(b) if the cost proves unacceptable, not to give the impression that it is ourintransigence that has caused the breakdown.We must not under-estimate the blow to the whole of Europe that would follow a breakdown in the negotiations now they have progressed so long and so far.Courtship so prolonged has reached a stage where a break between the partnerswould leave a deep and bitter scar.10. It is possible to classify our allies and our opponents on roughly thefollowing lines:  Our Allies(i) The ScandinaviansDenmark has a problem with agriculture and Norway with fish.But, in general, the UNISCAN solidarity is being weir maintained.(ii) The Swiss, who possess the two great assets of a trade deficit with the six and an extremely strong currency.(iii) Austria
(iv) The Benelux countries. They support us by reason of sentimentalattachment, because as small countries they feel rather lost and alone in the Common Market with Germany, Italy and France, and becauseof their low tariff traditions.(There is developing a very interesting connection between thecountries mentioned in (i) to (iv) above. It is a kind of small country,low tariff, Social Democrat network, which may be very useful,particularly as their ideas seem generally sympathetic to us.)(v) All those, in every country, who share the general political urge to european unity.(vi) Professor Erhard, and those other Members of the German government who believe in Free Trade and low tariffs and who think they havealready paid France too high a price for the Treaty of Rome.Our Opponents11.   These are:  (i) The protectionists everywhere. They are at their strongest and most powerful in France, but French protectionism strikes chords in Italyand in the Benelux countries, and there is some reason to suppose that a good deal of European protectionism is hiding under France&apos;sskirts.(ii) The European Establishment. This consists of European senior officials and civil servants, men like Hallstein, Marjolin and Monnet, who exertan enormous influence. They regard the Common Market, the coal and Steel Community and Euratom as their own triumph (as, indeed,they are). They fear that our ideas may disrupt this great new system and they are also inclined to say that the British, who were stand-offishat first, might just as well be left now to cool their heels in the lobby for alittle while. The influence of this group of people is very considerableindeed and might become decisive if by reason, for example, of ourapparent intransigence their Ministers should waver in the politicalsupport that they seem generally to give to the Free Trade Area.(iii) The Francophil Germans, led by Dr. Adenauer himself.(iv) The French.--T\\Q\x hostility, based, as I have said, on the combination ofprotectionism and jealousy, is fanned by the propaganda of theemployers and supported pretty well throughout French political life.The Free Trade Area proposal has no organised support whatsoeverfrom any Party in the Assembly at the present moment. But the fact remains that the French, like all of us, have now a vested interest in thenegotiations. A breakdown in the negotiations would mean not only a rupture with us but also a very severe strain indeed on their new-foundfriendship with Germany.12. These seem to me to be the factors in the equation. Our bargaining position probably is weaker than the French because the mass is more immovablethan the forces are irresistible.Future Tactics13. The question is how we should play the hand now. There are three possible results that may emerge from the consideration of the French plan by theTreaty of Rome countries:  (i) They might produce a plan v/hich we could accept. This is, to say the least,extremely unlikely.(ii) They might fail to agree among themselves.   Though superficially this might suit us, in the long run I fear it would be very dangerous because it would produce a disruption in Europe.(iii) They might agree on a solution that was unacceptable to us.  This also would be very dangerous because by the very act of agreement amongthe Six they would have done much to freeze their negotiating position.14.   The main elements in the French plan to which we object are:  (i) the proposed industry-by-industry approach;(ii) the proposal that there should be prior harmonisation of many of theeconomic factors affecting competition;
(iii) the proposal that the Free Trade Area tariff reductions should start someyears later than the reductions in the Treaty of Rome;(iv) the French desire to share in our Commonwealth preferences.15. I think we can probably rely on the other Treaty of Rome countries to reject the industry-by-industry approach, which is quite impracticable and really isa disguised way of wrecking the negotiations. I think we can also rely on them toreduce the French proposals on harmonisation to something relatively innocuous.There remain the two other points: the delay and the Commonwealth preferences.It is relevant that it would be to the benefit of Germany, in particular, to accept theFrench proposals in tuese matters. The Germans would like to have two or threeyears&apos; clear run in the French and Italian markets ahead of us, and they wouldcertainly like to share in some of our Commonwealth preferences. It is thereforelikely that we shall be pressed on both these points.16. I feel sure my colleagues will agree that there can be no question of meeting in any way the French demand for a share in our preferences. It is in anycase not a matter within our gift, and, if the demand comes in this form, it wouldbe quite irreconcilable with the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade. We musthold to the conception of the Commonwealth as a balanced system of rights and duties and not merely one of unilateral advantage to the United Kingdom. But, inthe long run, I imagine we would argue that the Free Trade Area should have as one of its aims a closer association between the Commonwealth as a whole and continental Europe, and it may be that this is a line of thought that we should develop.17. So far as the delay in starting the tariff reductions is concerned, I am sure we must not accept this as a general principle. All our allies in Europe outsidethe Six are strongly opposed to it, and the Belgians and at any rate some of theGermans themselves regard it as a bad idea. But it may be possible to make special arrangements with France. Indeed, I am being driven to the conclusionthat the only solution will be some special protocol for France. Already she hasspecial conditions in the Treaty of Rome, which will have to be continued in theFree Trade Area. Every country in Europe would be prepared to make a specialconcession to France if only the French were prepared to accept it. At the momentthey are entirely opposed, on the theoretical grounds that this would destroy the unity of the Six. Their real grounds are probably a reluctance to being furtherisolated and a fear that the offer of special terms would make the negative attitude&apos;l&apos;^rtJt&amp;&amp;&amp; seem even more immovable. It will be a major question of tactics when, and in whatway, we should float the idea of a special protocol for France if we decide that thisis the right way to handle the problem.18. The next two or three months should see the decision one way or theother whether we can have a Free Trade Area or whether we have to abandon the project. One of the most important events will be Dr. Adenauer&apos;s visit toLondon, because Germany is in a key position and Dr. Adenauer alone appears tohold the key to German policy. 1 believe myself that what we should aim at isto get some sort of Free Trade Area off the ground on its first flight, even if this involves all sorts of limitations and conditions and some special treatment for france. Once it has made its first flight we can set about making it a really powerful and effective machine. If we try to achieve too much perfection in advance wemay fail to get agreement altogether.R. M.Office of the Paymaster-General, S.W. 1,20 th March, 1958.

</content>
</cab>
