<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/92/0 images: 174-178</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERN MEN!Printed for the Cabinet. March 1958C. (58) 66 Copy No.    6125th March, 1958CABINETSTEEL : SITE OF NEW WORKSMemorandum by the Chancellor of the ExchequerBackgroundThe Economic Policy Committee are satisfied that the growth of demand forsheet steel and tinplate will be such that, unless a new strip mill is constructed inthe United Kingdom, there will be a substantial deficiency some time in the first half of the next decade. The initial planning, construction and running-in of a newmill will take five to six years. The Committee have accordingly agreed inprinciple that a new strip mill should be constructed, on the basis that a finaldecision on the timing of the project should be made at the next investment review.2. The new mill will have an initial capacity of 1 million ingot tons, but it is envisaged that this will be enlarged as the demand for sheet steel grows. The capital cost of the initial project is likely to be at least  120 millions.3. The Economic Policy Committee considered that Richard Thomas and baldwins Limited would have to undertake the project. This firm is the only majorsteel-making company remaining nationalised, and enquiries have shown that thereis no possibility of de-vesting it in the next few years. And since the exchequer would certainly have to put up almost all the money, it would not be easy to defend the provision of public funds on this scale to any company other than the one whichremains under Government control. This conclusion has the drawback of making it still more difficult to sell Richard Thomas and Baldwins. The only alternativev/ould be that the new strip mill should be owned separately by the Government and perhaps operated under an agency arrangement but it is by no means clear thatthis would be feasible.4. A factor which will have influenced the attitude of the de-nationalisedcompanies towards the project, and which is of considerable importance inconnection with the location of the mill, is the profitability of the scheme. Even onthe most favourable assumptions, the highest return on capital envisaged is 10-5 percent, before depreciation which means 6 or 7 per cent after depreciation: while this will be increased if the mill is expanded beyond its initial 1 million ingot tonscapacity, it is much lower than the normal commercial return on a project of this sort.5. The Committee have failed to agree on the site of the new mill. Fourpossible sites have been considered, Newport (Monmouthshire), Grangemouth(Stirlingshire), Kidwelly (Carmarthenshire), and Immingham (Lincolnshire). the basic capital cost of providing the mill would be about the same at each of the foursites (though Grangemouth might be  2-3 millions cheaper in this respect thanNewport). But the capital expenditure on certain ancillary work, e.g., port facilities,railways, housing, is estimated to cost  9 millions at Grangemouth,  10 millions at newport,  .14 millions at Kidwelly and  18 millions or more at Immingham.6. The Committee narrowed down the possible choices, in the course of their discussions, to Newport and Grangemouth (but have not finally discarded Kidwelly:see paragraph 11 below). A clear conflict of view has arisen as between these twosites, based on economic a nd social considerations; and it was decided that I should set out the opposing arguments adduced by Ministers in favour of each of them forthe consideration of the Cabinet.53198b
ECONOMIC FACTORSThe Case for Newport7. The economic case for Newport is based on a detailed evaluation of theproblem by the Iron and Steel Board, in consultation with the Ministry of Power,Richard Thomas and Baldwins Limited, the British Transport Commission and theNational Coal Board. The validity of this case is challenged by the Scottish Council(Development and Industry): I have set out their views in paragraph 8 below.. TheMinister of Power, however, has examined the Scottish CounciFs case, inconsultation with the interests mentioned above, and has made it clear that he can accept neither the calculations put forward by the Scottish Council nor thedeductions which are drawn from them. The following is a summary of the Ironand Steel Board&apos;s assessment:  (i) The return on capital at Newport, before depreciation, would be 10-5 percent, without taking into account the capital expenditure on ancillarywork: the Grangemouth figure would be 8-8 per cent.(ii) At Newport the ex-works cost, based on ingot production of 1 million tonsa year and finished steel production of 730,000 tons a year, would belower than the Grangemouth cost by an average of  3 2s. 67/. a ton. Thisdifferential of 4-V per cent, in the ex-works cost is regarded as decisivefor a project where the return on capital is in any case very low. the calculations on which these figures are based assume that the mill willbe working at full capacity. In practice this will not always be the case:in such event the differential would be more marked and more important.The differential would also increase as production was expanded beyondthe initial annual level of 1 million tons.(iii) Their detailed study of the economic factors has led the British Iron andSteel Federation, the Iron and Steel Board and Richard Thomas and baldwins Limited, to the view that Newport is the best site. Indeed, theeconomic arguments in favour of Newport are regarded by the interests concerned as so strong that no company or group of companies can befound that will consider building a new mill at any site other thanNewport.(iv) The Newport site is close to good dock facilities, whereas the existing dockfacilities at Grangemouth are inadequate: to enlarge them would requireexpenditure of  5 millions (included in the  9 millions referred to inparagraph 5).(v) Newport is close to the best remaining supply of coking coal in the UnitedKingdom, whereas at Grangemouth coal costs would be considerably higher, since local supplies are limited, are of poorer quality, and costmore. This is the major factor in the cost differential between the twosites.(vi) At Newport there are no coal deposits directly beneath the proposed site,whereas at Grangemouth large deposits of coal (65 million tons) liebelow the proposed site, and it would be impossible to mine them if the mill were built there.(vii) The delivery charges for finished steel would be lower from a mill at newport than they would be from Grangemouth, since Newport iscloser to the main consuming areas in the Midlands and London.Experience suggests that there is little likelihood of sheet and tinplateusing industries moving from their traditional areas in order to be neara new strip mill in Scotland.The Case for Grangemouth8. The economic case for Grangemouth is based on a study made by theScottish Council (Development and Industry). As stated above, the Minister of power rejects the case in detail and in toto. The Scottish CounciFs assessmentcan be summarised as follows:  (i) At Grangemouth the return on capital would be 10 per cent., beforedepreciation, a difference of only 0-5 per cent, from that for Newport.
At Grangemouth the ex-works cost per ton of finished steel (assuminga production of 730,000 tons a year) would be higher than the Newportcost by only  1. 4.v. \0d. a ton.  The chief factors are:  (a) In practice, it would be possible to bring about a substantial reduction in the cost of providing coal for steel production atGrangemouth: 60 per cent, of the coal required could be supplied from Scottish sources, and transport charges would also be lessthan those suggested by the Iron and Steel Board.(b) Delivery charges from Grangemouth would not necessarily be higher than those from Newport, since accessible markets forfinished steel already exist.(c) After discussion with the Scottish Gas Board the Scottish Councilconsider that the credit allowed to the Iron and Steel Board&apos;scalculations for gas works breeze and for coke-oven gas couldbe increased.These factors leave a difference in cost of the order of only 2 per cent.,which should not be decisive.(iii) If it were decided on grounds of national policy that the mill should be built at Grangemouth, it should be possible to persuade a consortiumof steel companies to undertake the project there, since the commercialdisadvantages of Grangemouth are not overwhelming.(iv) The coal deposits lying beneath the Grangemouth site are at a greaterdepth than the National Coal Board have worked hitherto; and no good agricultural land would be sterilised as would be the case at Newport.(v) Fabricating industries would be attracted to Scotland if the mill were built there.SOCIAL FACTORSThe Case advanced by those who favour Newport9. Those who support building the mill at Newport, on social and other grounds, advance the following arguments:  (i) It is already publicly known in Wales that the Iron and Steel Board andRichard Thomas and Baldwins Limited favour the Newport site. Ifthe mill is built at Grangemouth, it will be manifest that this is aGovernment decision and will be regarded throughout Wales as apiece of deliberate discrimination by the Government against Welshinterests.(ii) Although there is no unemployment problem in Newport itself, theunemployment rate in Wales is 3-8 per cent., approximately doublethat in Great Britain as a whole. There are particular black spots,e.g., in West South Wales, where the rate is well above this level.(iii) Many sections of the traditional industries in the remoter areas of SouthWales are becoming uncompetitive and are closing down (e.g., thehandmill sheet and tinplate works). This will result in substantialunemployment and discontent unless large-scale and imaginative efforts are made to drain off redundant labour from the valleys into industriescentred on the coast and along the railways. Newport is ideally placed to act as the focal point for a major development of this sort; andthe new mill would both provide direct employment and also stimulate the diversification of industry in the area. If remedial action is not taken in good time, costly development projects will be needed to dealwith the problem.(iv) While it is the case that virtually all the country&apos;s strip milt production is already sited in Wales, it is not concentrated in one area but is fairlywidely dispersed.(v) There is still great resentment in Wales over the support given by theGovernment to Liverpool^ Bill for flooding part of the TrywerynValley in Merionethshire to provide much-needed water for Liverpool,and there is continuing criticism of the decision not to appoint a secretary of State for Wales. If the Government were now to stop the building of the strip mill in Wales, criticism of the Governmentwould be greatly intensified and Welsh nationalist feeling aroused.The dangers of such a situation must not be under-rated.53198
The Case advanced by those who favour Grangemouth10. Those who support building the mill at Grangemouth, on social andother grounds, advance the following arguments:  (i) The unemployment rate in Scotland is 3-6 per cent.   It is increasingsteadily, largely as a result of Government action (e.g., the closuresof Service establishments and the contraction of the shale oil industry).As in Wales, there is a considerable number of black spots where theunemployment rate is well above the average. There is a large pool of unemployed labour within travelling distance of Grangemouth.  .(ii) The mill would not only relieve local unemployment, but would help tobroaden the basis of the Scottish economy, which is demonstrablyin a condition of persistent imbalance: any tendency towards arecession hits Scotland particularly hard. Short-term solutions have proved ineffective. The mill would provide an opportunity ofdiversifying industry as industries fabricating sheet steel would develop in the industrial belt of Scotland if the mill were built at Grangemouth.It would be a psychological and economic blow of great magnitude to scotland if Newport were selected, and would shatter the country&apos;confidence in the Government^ economic and social policies. It is significant that migration has increased from an annual post-war rateof 24,000 to 35,000 in 1957: the annual figure in the immediatepre-war years was 8,500.(iii) If the mill is not built in Scotland, other measures will need to be taken ona massive scale to diversify the Scottish economy: these would bedifficult to devise and might prove very expensive for the Exchequer.(iv) It would be entirely contrary to the Governments distribution of industrypolicy to grant an Industrial Development Certificate for the project at newport, which is one of the most prosperous areas of full employmentin the country, unless there were overwhelming economic arguments in favour of this course. No ordinary commercial firm would be grantedsuch a certificate: it would be highly embarrassing to breach theGovernment^ announced policies in favour of a project financed by theExchequer. It would in any case be contrary to any sound policy forthe distribution of industry to increase the instability of South Wales by concentrating in that area the country&apos;s entire production of sheet steel and tinplate. Although Newport forms part of the South Wales and monmouthshire Development Area, so much new industry has beenattracted there and local industry has expanded to such an extent thatthere is now a shortage of male labour. At times recently this has been as severe as almost anywhere in the country.(v) Experience has shown that unemployment in the upper part of the Welshvalleys which are distant and inaccessible, has continued in the face ofan intense shortage of male labour at Newport. All the evidence points to the conclusion that an intensification of the labour shortage at newport would give no relief to these local problems, nor to thedifficulties of the Swansea /Llanelly area (which, unlike Newport, isWelsh speaking) and where male unemployment is currently in the region of 8 per cent.(vi) The provision of employment for men on this scale, and the housing andother developments associated with it, would be an invaluablecontribution to the biggest overspill problem in the United Kingdom,that of Glasgow. To this extent, part of the capital expenditure referredto in paragraph 5 could properly be regarded as expenditure whichwould otherwise have to be incurred elsewhere. The dock expenditurereferred to in paragraph 7 (iv) would also be of value to the existingchemical industries as well as to the steel mill.THE KIDWELLY SITE11. If social and political considerations are to be regarded as outweighingdifferences of profitability, the possibility of siting the mill at Kidwelly might need to be reconsidered. While Kidwelly suffers from certain disadvantages, e.g., theabsence of nearby dock facilities, and the existence of large deposits of coal directly
beneath the proposed site, it has a slightly stronger claim on economic grounds thanGrangemouth; while, on social grounds, it is on the edge of a declining industrial area with a significant rate of unemployment (7-7 per cent.).GENERAL12. In sum, the Economic Policy Committee are satisfied that a new stripmill must be constructed in time for it to be in operation by the mid-1960s. Butfor obvious reasons no public announcement can be made of the governments intentions until a decision has been reached on the site.. The question of the siteis already a matter of political controversy and public debate. Ministers havereceived numerous deputations from both Wales and from Scotland during thepast few months. One thing is clear, namely, that whichever location is eventuallychosen a strong adverse reaction must be expected from the supporters of thealternative site.13. In these circumstances there are some attractions in the idea that theGovernment should seek to fortify themselves against the certainty of criticismsby securing the advice of a small body of independent and authoritative persons on the relative merits of the possible sites. Such a course would, however, lead to delay and might prove dangerous in itself, since in reaching their decision theGovernment will need to pay some regard to the political and social aspects ofthe question: an independent advisory body, on the other hand, would be largelyconfined to the economic factors.14. These factors suggest quite clearly that, on any economic basis, Newportenjoys an advantage over Grangemouth. On the basis of the Iron and Steel Board&apos;s figures, the advantage might be regarded as decisive, bearing in mind the already lowreturn on capital expected from the project, notwithstanding the strong socialarguments in favour of Grangemouth. Moreover, the Government would be opento justifiable criticism if they attempted to run counter to the advice of the interests concerned and sank  120 millions into a strip mill at Grangemouth which turned out to be uneconomic. There might be cheaper and more effective ways than this of bringing about a measure of diversification in Scottish industry, though in fairness itshould be said that no one has yet worked out what these could be.15. On the basis of the figures provided by the Scottish Council (development and Industry), however, it might be argued that the cost differential is not large enough to outweigh the powerful social arguments in favour of Grangemouth.Moreover Scottish public opinion would never believe that total rejection of theScottish CounciPs figures was justified. In this connection, the difficulty of issuingan Industrial Development Certificate for the project at Newport must be given full weight.16. Whichever site is chosen, the timing of any announcement and its presentation will need to be considered with the greatest possible care.D. H. A.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1.25th March, 1958.

</content>
</cab>
