<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/92/0 images: 194-202</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETfHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1958C (58) 71 Copy No. g Q1st April, 1958CABINETPENSIONSMemorandum by the Prime minister if legislation on a new pensions scheme is to form a major item in our programme for next session, we cannot defer much longer a decision on the natureof that scheme. I have been giving some thought to this question in consultationwith the Ministers immediately concerned and I should like to put forward somesuggestions for the Cabinefs consideration.2. The possible schemes from which we must make our choice were described in C. (57) 211. At the one extreme is the May Plan, a scheme which merely offersadditional State facilities to those who wish to supplement the existing State schemebut find it difficult to do so by the means at present available to them. At the otherextreme is the August Plan, which eliminates the existing compulsory flat-rate state scheme and substitutes for it another compulsory State scheme, based on theprinciple of graduation. Midway between the two stands the September Plan, whichretains the existing compulsory flat-rate State scheme but superimposes on it a compulsory graduated State scheme from which however contracting out would be permitted if certain conditions were satisfied.3. In choosing between these possible courses of action we must be clear about our objectives. These are :  (a) To provide a solution for the problem of the emerging deficit under theexisting State scheme, which is already significant in Budgetary terms and is imposing on the Exchequer a burden which will becomeunmanageable in the relatively near future.(b) To substitute for the present scheme alternative arrangements which haveregard to the principle of graduation, which can be argued to befinancially sounder than the &quot; Crossman Plan &quot; and which can be presented to our own supporters in a politically attractive light.4.   Judged by these criteria, how do our three possible schemes appear?5. The political advantage of the May Plan is that it involves no extension ofthe present field of compulsion, and leaves supplementary provision to be carriedout voluntarily as at present. Its disadvantage, however, is that, precisely for thisreason, it provides no significant relief to the Exchequer. On this ground we have,hitherto, provisionally rejected it; and although we have done so with regret, I donot imagine that the Cabinet will wish to change their decision.6. If so, the choice lies between the August and the September Plans. Thememorandum at Annex I compares these two plans in terms of our first criterion,i.e., their impact on the Exchequer. It appears that, on any reasonable assumptionabout the probable rate of growth of earnings and the possible degree of contracting out, the August Plan provides greater relief to the Exchequer than the SeptemberPlan. But the assumptions are necessarily speculative, and the Cabinet may feelthat, since either plan would be more advantageous to the Exchequer than thecontinuance of the existing scheme, the final choice between them should bedetermined more by political than by financial considerations.53218a
weekly earnings 8AugustSeptemberTotal initial weekly contribution rate byemployer and employee(Employee&apos;s shareshown in brackets)s.   d.13*18.s.   d.9A)11)Single rate of pension on retirement at 65for a man who on commencementof the scheme was aged55 45 35 25 16years     years     years     years     years(In shillings)50 50 50 50 5050 50 50 50 50 10AugustSeptember1702( 8 6)( 9 11)54505650585060506050 11AugustSeptember1819( 9 4)(10   8i)56515953625565596562 12AugustSeptember202154(10 2i)(U   6)58526256666070687074 15 or moreAugustSeptember2526(12 9)(13 11)6455716578758595* Existing flat rate adopted as minimum on earnings up to  10 a week.851108. The reaction of the employer, on the other hand, may depend largely on whether he would regard the August Plan as being, on balance, materially lesstolerable for him. without contracting out, than is the present scheme; or whether he would rather have the right (which the September Plan gives him) to contract out of any change in the present national scheme, given that, in order to exerciseit, he would have to submit his own scheme to certain adaptations and controls.Annex II describes, in paragraphs 5-14, the criteria which any occupational scheme would have to satisfy if it was to be permitted to contract out and the machinery which would have to be created to consider applications for this purpose and tomaintain a regular scrutiny of schemes which had been allowed to contract out.No doubt these arrangements could be operated, so far as the Government areconcerned, though only at the cost of an increase in clerical staff. But wouldthose responsible for administering occupational schemes regard them as acceptable? Would they prefer either to cut back their existing schemes or tocarry them in addition, rather than comply with the conditions for contracting out? So far we know only that representatives of the Life Offices, who have beenconfidentially consulted, have said that they would regard the September Planwith contracting out as &quot; much less desirable from every point of view &quot; than the august Plan; but they do not speak for the whole field.9. Our comparative ignorance on these points is a great handicap to us in seeking to reach a decision. If it emerged that there was likely to be relatively littledemand for contracting out on the conditions envisaged, it would probably be not worth while to embark on the complex arrangements described in Annex II inorder to satisfy a marginal need. Equally, if those arrangements proved to be administratively unworkable from the point of view of the interests concernedwith the administration of occupational schemes, we should be compelled, howeverreluctantly, to abandon the conception of contracting out.7. The reaction of the average man in the street will be liable to depend onhis judgment of the relative attractiveness of the two plans, in terms of thecontributions which they would demand and the benefits which they would provide.The following table illustrates this comparison:
10. How can we clarify this point? I think that there are two possible methods of proceeding:  (a) We could publish a White Paper, indicating that our consideration of alternative pension arrangements (which was mentioned in The Queen&apos;sSpeech) is now well advanced, that we accept in principle the concept of graduation but that, before reaching a final decision, we think itnecessary to ascertain the public reaction: (i) to the alternatives of altering the present flat-rate scheme to a graduated basis, without contracting out, or keeping it as it isbut adding a graduated tier from which contracting out wouldbe permitted;(ii) to the acceptability of the conditions for contracting out.The White Paper would then describe in some detail the manner inwhich contracting out would have to be operated (on the lines of thememorandum at Annex II).(b) We could arrange possibly after a suitable statement in Parliament to conduct confidential discussions with the various interests affected,in order to ascertain their reactions to contracting out.On either assumption, drafting could be put in hand on those clauses ofthe Bill which would probably be common to either Plan.11.   There are certain obvious objections to a White Paper.   Thus:  (a) It would probably provoke a demand for a debate, in which we shouldnot be able to make any definite or convincing statement of our intentions.(b) Although it would concentrate primarily on the administrative implications of contracting out, dealing relatively briefly with the other differences between the August and the September Plans and containing theminimum of information about rates of contribution and benefit under each Plan, it would inevitably result in the main features of the twoPlans becoming known to some extent. It is not necessarily desirablethat, before the Government have made their own decision and havedecided how it should be presented, the general public should be encouraged to discuss this complex subject on the basis of hypotheticaland inaccurate assumptions about the details of our proposals.(c) It is doubtful whether, in a matter of this complexity, public opinion couldbe relied upon to provide any clear and definite expression of opinion in the relatively brief interval between the time when we could hope to publish a White Paper and the time when we should have to reachour final decision if the Bill is to have its Second Reading before christmas.12. Confidential discussions with the interests affected would be more likelyto produce a definite reaction towards contracting out. On the other hand, itwould be more difficult to avoid disclosing, during such discussions, the preciserates of contribution and benefit which we envisage, since they are highly relevantif any informed reaction is to be obtained; and, however much we might maintain that the figures were purely illustrative, the detailed content of the two Plans wouldbe bound to become widely known.13. In C. (58) 73, the Minister of Pensions has circulated a preliminary draftof a possible White Paper, together with the draft of a memorandum which mightconstitute the basis of informal discussions with the private sector. The cabinet will need to consider these alternative documents before reaching a decision on the tactics to be pursued.H. M.10 Downing Street, S.W. I,31st March, 1958.
ANNEX 1PENSIONSTHE AUGUST AND SEPTEMBER PLANS-EFFECT ON THEEXCHEQUERMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer the cost to the Exchequer of any of the pensions schemes we have been considering consists first of the Exchequer supplement to the scheme (at present 125 millions) which is borne on Votes, and second, of any deficit in the fund in a particular year, which must also be borne on Votes unless it is met by borrowing. These figures together give the cost to the Exchequer above the line.The overall effect on the Exchequer is the same, except that it would take credit for any surplus in the Fund in a particular year. In the case of the SeptemberPlan this is a distinction without a difference, because after the first year the fund is never in surplus. But under the August Plan surpluses appear (intermittentlyat first) from the 5th year onwards, and they will open the way to some relief of the above-the-line position (see, e.g., paragraph 4 below). In the following paragraphs, therefore, the overall figures are used, the above-the-line figures,where different, being shown in brackets.2. On certain assumptions, which have been used for illustrative purposes,the effect on the Exchequer of the present scheme, the August Plan and the september Plan with contracting out is as follows:  TABLE a cost to the Exchequer (  millions)7960-6&quot;/       1965-66       1970-71        1980-81      2000-present scheme     ... 211 298 387 528 533August       ...... 142 132 (161) 161 (184) 160 (225) 205 (232)September (one-thirdcontracting out)... 116 (124) 143 177 211 2823. It is important to note that the costings of the August and SeptemberPlans assume four quinquennial increases in the rate of contributions. The costto the Exchequer would therefore be greater in the intervening years than in theyears shown in the table.4. Under the September Plan the fiat-rate contribution is increased by Is. aweek (6d. a side) every five years, but there is no increase in the rate of theExchequer supplement. Under the August Plan, the graduated contribution is increased by -V per cent. (  per cent, a side) every five years, and the exchequer supplement is also increased by J per cent. If, under the August Scheme, as underthe September Scheme, there were no increase in the Exchequer supplement, the overall figures would remain as shown above and the above-the-line figures would generally approximate to them, because there would be a smaller exchequer contribution but also a smaller surplus in the Fund.5. There is a doubt under the August Plan about the treatment of thoseearning less than  8 a week. They might be charged as a minimum the contribution appropriate to  8 a week. In that case, all the above figures would stand. They might, on the other hand, be given an option between paying thatcontribution and paying a lower contribution which would earn lower benefits.In that case, the above figures would stand only on the assumption that everyonechose the first option. If, say, only half did so, the overall cost of the August plan to the Exchequer would be initially about  15 millions more than the figures in the tables, the corresponding reduction in liability not being material for many years.6. The September Plan is costed above on the assumption that schemescovering about one-third of the present potential field of employees earning morethan  10 a week would contract out initially.  The following are the figures forSECRET53218 b
	Cost to the Exchequer (  millions)					1960-61	1965-66	1970-71	1980-81	2000-1One-sixth contracting					out	91 (124)	116(125)	148	180	267One-quarter contract-					ing out	103 (124)	129	162	195	274One-third   contract-					ing out	116 (124)	143	177	211	282One-half contracting					out	140	171	206	242*	297*Two-thirds contract-					ing out   ......	165	199	235*	274*	312*7. An increase in the number contracting out has the immediate effect of removing contribution income from the Fund, and therefore adding to theExchequer cost. There is a corresponding reduction in eventual liability for benefit, but it does not become material for many years.8. There is a further important point to note about contracting out.Although occupational schemes are expanding, they still cover only about81 million employees out of a total of 22 millions. The above costings make some allowance for an increase, after the start, in the loss of contribution incomedue to greater numbers of &quot; contracted-out &quot; employees earning more than  10a week: but they do not make any substantial allowance for the effect of anygrowth, after the start, in the present scope of occupational cover, except thatthe figures marked with an asterisk could be right only if there were some growth of this kind. If there were a substantial increase in the initial number of schemes approved for contracting out, the cost of the September Plan to the Exchequermight be materially higher than the above figures show. (As a rough measure,every million employees contracting out represent contribution income of about 12 millions a year.)9. The costings assume that the level of earnings in 1960 will be 5 per cent,above the level in mid-1957. This may be on the conservative side. If the levelwere 8 per cent, above the mid-1957 level, the effect would be as follows:  TABLE CCost to the Exchequer (  millions)1960-61 1965-66 1970-71 1980-81        2000-1August       ......      134 (140) 121 (162) 150 (185) 150 (226) 198 (233)September (one-thirdcontracting out) ...      112(124) 140 171 208 28010. The costings also assume that from 1960 onwards the level of real earnings would increase at the rate of H per cent, per annum. If the rate of increase were different from this, a considerable difference is made to the costings,greater in the case of the August Plan than in the case of the September Plan.For instance, if it were 2 per cent, per annum Table C would be converted tothe following:  TABLE DCost to the Exchequer (  millions)1960-61 1965-66 1970-71 1980-81 2000-1August       ......      134 (140) 113 (163) 122 (186) 119 (229) 163 (235)September (one-thirdcontracting out) 112 (124) 136 157 195 27411. Conversely, if the rate of increase in the level of real earnings were only  per cent, per annum instead of \\ per cent., Table C would be converted to thefollowing:  TABLE ECost to the Exchequer (  millions)1960-61 1965-66 1970-71 1980-81 2000-1August       ......      134 (140) 128 (161) 173 (183) 195 (225) 261September (one-thirdcontracting out) ...      112 (124) 142 181 227 301the September Plan on alternative assumptions about the initial scale of contracting out:  TABLE B
Conclusion12. These figures suggest that, on the assumptions underlying Table A, theeffect on the Exchequer of the August Plan would be less good initially than thatof the September Plan, but would be rather better after the first four years onoverall account (and after the first decade or so on above-the-line account alone),with greater improvement in the longer term. The comparison would be morefavourable to the August Plan if either the scale of contracting out of the september Plan or the rate of expansion of the economy were greater than assumed in Table A (see Tables B and D). The comparison would be more favourable to the September Plan if either of these factors were smaller than assumed inTable A (see Tables B and E).(Intld.)        D. H. A.26th March, 1958.
ANNEX 2PENSIONSTHE IMPLICATIONS OF CONTRACTING OUTMemorandum by the Minister of Pensions and National InsuranceThis memorandum examines the implications of contracting out, including itsadministrative feasibility and the problem of transferability of rights.The Broad Implications2.   The main requirements would be:  (1) minimum standards of equivalency of occupational schemes which appliedto contract out with the upper tier of the State scheme;(2) a measure of supervision of the financial soundness of occupational schemes which contracted out;(3) provision in contracting-out schemes for a measure of transferability ofaccrued benefit rights;(4) the creation of an authority to adjudicate on applications and to act as aregistrar of approved schemes.3.   The membership of occupational schemes is divided as follows:  The memberships of the Public Services&apos; and Nationalised Industries&apos; schemes are almost all in some 30 substantial schemes (or groups of schemes), most of them verylarge. There are about 37,000 private schemes and the bulk of them havememberships of less than 50.  About one in 11 has a membership of 200 or more.4. The total membership of occupational schemes exceeds the field in which(even with maximum adaptation of schemes to fit the suggested criteria forapproval) there could be contracting out of the upper tier of the September Plan.Substantial numbers of workpeople earning less than  10 a week (below whichfigure no graduated contributions would be payable under the September Plan) are members of occupational pension schemes, particularly in the Public Services and nationalised Industry.The Proposed System of Administration5. Some adaptation of schemes would have to take place to meet therequirements of contracting out, particularly in respect of transferability. schemes which did not elect to adapt themselves to the requirements of contracting out would still, in most cases, have to adapt themselves to take account of the additional contributions and benefits of the State scheme.6. Occupational schemes, having been set up to suit particular firms andemployments, show a wide variety in conditions, contributions and financial structure. These variations are the primary reason for suggesting a flexible systemof administration. Rigid rules would lead to unnecessary difficulties for schemes.The other important reason is the desirability of avoiding provisions which would look like an unreasonable measure of State control in the occupational field.7. The system of administration envisaged is that applications to contract out would be made by employers to an independent Registrar of Schemes who would apply broad tests indicated below to schemes submitted to him for approval. Onceapproved, a scheme would be required to submit returns and actuarial valuationsat intervals to the Registrar, whose agreement to any material change in the rules of the scheme would also have to be obtained. The sanction for enforcement of the registrar^ supervision would be withdrawal of his approval and the consequentcollection of contributions to the graduated State scheme.MillionsPublic ServicesNationalised Industries   ......Private Industry and Commerce...14-5&quot;Total53218b 2
8. The need for adaptation of schemes and the examination of applicationsmakes it essential that a substantial period should be allowed between the date whenthe conditions of approval became known to employers, and the imposition of thenew State contributions. This has been put at two years. But a period not muchshorter would in any case be needed for changing over the machinery of the state scheme to any scheme of graduated contributions.9. It is not thought it would be practicable (as suggested by the Labour Party)to base contracting out on a system of options by individual employees. It is reasonable to assume that a decision to seek approval for a scheme would be preceded by industrial consultation between the employer responsible for thescheme and the employees affected, and further safeguards to the individual wouldbe-(1) that the employer should give those affected by an application due noticeof any intention to apply;(2) that where there were trustees of the scheme (very often the employees are represented among the trustees) their consent should be a prerequisiteof any application;(3) where the scheme itself was voluntary, or any individual employee (e.g.,because he was in the employment when the scheme started) had theright not to belong to it, he would be entitled to be in the graduated partof the State scheme.These considerations should reduce difficulties which might otherwise be felt in making the employer, as sponsor of the scheme, responsible for the application in respect of the employees covered by it.The Criteria for Approval10. For purposes of comparing a given occupational scheme with the uppertier of the State scheme the primary test suggested is a minimum financial outlay byemployer and employee together in the occupational scheme. This has been put at 4s. a week i.e., half the maximum joint contribution to the upper tier of theState scheme on the assumption that a certain degree of tolerance in comparing the end product in benefit is acceptable. Where there were no contributions by the employee or a scheme did not satisfy the &quot; outlay&quot; test, an alternative testcomparing the benefits undertaken by the occupational schemes with those of theupper tier of the State scheme would be applied. These alternative tests are more precise than a broad formula such as was applied under the former contributory pensions Acts for purposes of exception, e.g., that the provision should be &quot; on thewhole not less favourable &quot; than that of the State scheme. Though the testssuggested will give rise to technical complexities such as the evaluation ofemployers&apos; deficiency payments, they avoid adjudication by the Registrar onpotentially awkward issues of relationship between benefits and contributions e.g.,whether the benefits offered are &quot; value for money.&quot;11. The Registrar would also need to be satisfied on the financial soundnessof schemes seeking to contract out. Satisfaction of this criterion would normally be automatic so far as public services and nationalised industry schemes, and lifeoffice schemes, were concerned. While among the remainder-i.e., the privatelyadministered schemes there are some which at present appear to possessinadequate safeguards of solvency (a consideration which suggests that some degreeof general state supervision of schemes may now be due) the great majority ofthem would need no formal adaptation to satisfy reasonable requirements in thisrespect.12 Transferability of pension rights for purposes of contracting out requires that such rights should be transferable only to the extent that they have beencounted as equivalent to those of the State scheme. Even so, few, if any, schemes would satisfy this condition without adaptation. The requirement could, however,be satisfied by providing either for the payment of an appropriate capital sumfrom the old occupational scheme to the new (or to the State scheme if the newemployer had no approved scheme), or for the old fund to credit the employeewith a &quot; cold storage &quot; pension when he retired and corresponding to his service in the old employment.
13. Insistence on transferability of pension rights, however short the periodof service involved, might be considered unreasonable. A possible solution wouldbe to accept a qualifying period before rights were preserved in the occupational scheme, but to require that the employee should, during the qualifying period,be covered by the State scheme.14. Transferability of rights would also require a limitation of the rightson the part of the employee who leaves to receive a lump sum, representing hisown contributions, to that part of his contributions which exceeded the amounttreated as equivalent to the graduated contribution of the State scheme. Some costto the employers would also be involved since most.funds at present derive benefit from retaining the employers&apos; contribution in respect of members who leave.Response of Employers15. No consultations have so far taken place with employers or withemploying authorities outside the central government machine. The degree towhich contracting out would take place under the conditions outlined must therefore be a matter of speculation, as must the exact technical form in whichthe conditions should ultimately emerge if they are to work smoothly. So faras the public services and nationalised industries are concerned it has however been estimated by officials without consultation with employing authorities, &amp;o,that &quot; on balance and with all reserve it seems likely that the majority of theauthorities concerned would, after taking account of the views of their workers,wish to contract out.&quot; Such contracting out would be effective only in thatproportion of the membership of schemes so far as they were contracted out who earned more than  10 a week; and it is clearly recognised that, of the two major schemes for manual workers in nationalised industry, the British transport commission Wages Grade Scheme (325,000 members) certainly, and the national coal Board Mineworkers&apos; Scheme (562,000 members) probably, would not qualify.16. So far as private schemes are concerned opinion would probably be divided, and some employers would doubtless not wish to assume the responsibilityof taking employees out of any part of a State scheme. Some employers, moreover,especially those with non-contributory schemes, might see advantage in leavingmore of the pension provision for their workers to be made through the State,cutting down their own schemes as might be appropriate.17. On the other hand a substantial number of employers and workpeople,faced with the necessity of adaptations designed either to reduce their scheme or to make it fit the conditions for contracting out, might prefer the latter. Nofirm estimate can be made, but for planning purposes it has been assumed thatthe number of workers affected would be something like one-third of the membership of schemes.Conclusion18. Although undoubtedly a number of technical problems would arise whenthe time came for detailed discussions with industry, it appears, as indicated above, that it is feasible to construct a system permitting of contracting out. Butit is impossible to do more than speculate as to the extent to which those responsiblefor occupational schemes would think it worth while to make the necessaryapplications, and adjustments to their schemes, in order to secure permission to contract out. Officials have suggested, subject to reservations, that it is likely that a number of public service and nationalised industry schemes would in factdo so. But so far as private industry is concerned it is very difficult to form any firm view until at least the broad outline of the new State scheme and of theconditions for contracting out are known to those directly concerned.J. A. B.-C.25 th March, 1958.

</content>
</cab>
