<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/92/0 images: 216-217</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)0.(58) 74 COPT NO.i2ncLi April. 1?58CABINETPENSIONSMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer have taken steps to ascertain the views of the ministers concerned on the probable reactions to contracting out of participantsin occupational schemes in the public sector.2. The great majority of employees in the public sector wouldbe eligible for contracting out, and it is thought that all of them,except possibly police and firemen in Scotland, would wish to do so.The only detailed points to which I need draw attention are:-(a) The position of the armed forces was not-considered .(b) The Minister of Health considers that thecondition of transferability might lead tosome loss of staff in the National health service, but that it would be difficult forthe management to refuse on this account tointroduce transferability in order to contract out of the September Plan.(c) It is not thought possible in the local govern-ment services to allow different localauthorities to choose different ways.     Asingle option would he.ve to apply to localgovernment as a whole, and it is thought thatthe majority desire vrauld be to contract out.(d) The mine-workers&apos; scheme in its present formis probably not large enough to qualify for contracting out, but the Minister of Powerthinks that the roineworkers would insist thatit should be so extended as to qualify.(e) The British Transport Commission scheme for wage grades vrould probably not qualify either.But it is thought that, whether it does or not,the employees would not want to contract out.3.        These views can be provisional only at the present stage,in default of consultation with all the interests concerned, butthere is no reason to think that they are not well founded.     Ifthey are in fact accurate, they make a considerable difference tothe position.     The working assumption hitherto has been that underthe September Plan only about one-third of the potential field in thecountry as a whole would be contracted out.     It now appears thatvirtually the whole of the eligible part of the public sector (which represents about 40 per cent of the whole field) would be contracted out.     It is not certain that private employers would react in the
same way as public employers. but it seems clp.ar that the assumption,of one-third contracting out is likely to be considerably too low.If, say, three-quarters of the whole field (public and private sectors together) were contracted out? the initial loss of contribution income to fche Fund wov. Id appear to be about 70 millions per annum more than on the assumption of one-thirdcontracting out.     The cost to the Exchequer of the September plan would therefore, for many years, be about  70 millions per annumhigher than is shown (on the one-third assumption) in the tablescontained in my memorandum annexed to the Prime Minister&apos;s paper(0.(58) 71).D.H.A.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.2nd April, 195S.-2

</content>
</cab>
