<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/92/0 images: 238-250</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
confidential this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMEXTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1958C. (58) 78 Copy No.   58llth April, 1958CABINETBRITISH TRANSPORT COMMISSION: RAILWAY STAFFNote by the Secretary of the CabinetBy direction of the Prime Minister I circulate the decisions of the NationalTribunal-numbers 21 and 22 on railway staff.(Signed) NORMAN BROOK.Cabinet Office, S.W. I,10th April, 1958.
BRITISH RAILWAYSRAILWAY STAFF NATIONAL TRIBUNALDECISION No. 21.   CLAIMS FOR IMPROVED RATES OF PAY FORSALARIED AND CONCILIATION STAFF.   10th APRIL, 1958IntroductoryI. The Railway Staff National Tribunal is established under Part VI of theAppendix to the Memorandum of Agreement dated 28th May, 1956, known asthe &quot; Machinery of Negotiation for Railway Staff, 1956,&quot; made between the british transport Commission of the one part and the National Union of Railwaymen,the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen, and the TransportSalaried Staffs&apos; Association of the other part.2. The function and duty of the Railway Staff National Tribunal is to hearand decide, in respect of employees to whom the Machinery of Negotiation is applicable, issues as to standard salaries, wages, hours of duty and other standardconditions of service, which have been agreed, or decided in the prescribed manner,to be issues of major importance, and which have been previously considered bythe Railway Staff National Council.3. The following constituted the Railway Staff National Tribunal duringthe consideration of the present case:  Sir John Forster, K.B.E., Q.C., Chairman.Mr. A. J. Espley, C.B.E., J.P., selected by the British transport commission.Mr. E. Hall, J.P., selected by the Railway Trade Unions parties to the issues.4. It is provided in the Machinery of Negotiation that at the desire of theparties to the issue the Tribunal may be assisted by representatives of the partiessitting as Assessors.   On the present occasion the Assessors were:  Nominated by the British Transport CommissionMr. C. H. Brazier.Nominated by the National Union of RailwaymenMr. C. W. Evans.Nominated by the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and FiremenMr. J. Lawrence.Nominated by the Transport Salaried Staffs1 association mr. R. J. Gunter.5. Under the procedure prescribed by Part VI of the Machinery of negotiation for Railway Staff, 1956, the terms of reference and the statements of claim and defence were forwarded to the Tribunal and the Tribunal were requested to hear the parties.6.   The terms of reference were as follows:  &quot;To ask the Railway Staff National Tribunal, established underAppendix, Part VI, to the Agreement in regard to the Machinery of negotiation for Railway Staff dated 28th May, 1956, to hear and decide thefollowing claims: &apos;From the National Union of RailwaymenThat the rates of pay of all Salaried and Conciliation gradesemployed by the British Transport Commission on British Railways andcovered by the Machinery of Negotiation for Railway Staff should be substantially increased.
BRITISH RAILWAYSRAILWAY STAFF NATIONAL TRIBUNALDECISION No. 21.   CLAIMS FOR IMPROVED RATES OF PAY FORSALARIED AND CONCILIATION STAFF.   10th APRIL, 1958IntroductoryI. The Railway Staff National Tribunal is established under Part VI of theAppendix to the Memorandum of Agreement dated 28th May, 1956, known asthe &quot; Machinery of Negotiation for Railway Staff, 1956,&quot; made between the british transport Commission of the one part and the National Union of Railwaymen,the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen, and the TransportSalaried Staffs&apos; Association of the other part.2. The function and duty of the Railway Staff National Tribunal is to hearand decide, in respect of employees to whom the Machinery of Negotiation is applicable, issues as to standard salaries, wages, hours of duty and other standardconditions of service, which have been agreed, or decided in the prescribed manner,to be issues of major importance, and which have been previously considered bythe Railway Staff National Council.3. The following constituted the Railway Staff National Tribunal duringthe consideration of the present case:  Sir John Forster, K.B.E., Q.C., Chairman.Mr. A. J. Espley, C.B.E., J.P., selected by the British transport commission.Mr. E. Hall, J.P., selected by the Railway Trade Unions parties to the issues.4. It is provided in the Machinery of Negotiation that at the desire of theparties to the issue the Tribunal may be assisted by representatives of the partiessitting as Assessors.   On the present occasion the Assessors were:  Nominated by the British Transport CommissionMr. C. H. Brazier.Nominated by the National Union of RailwaymenMr. C. W. Evans.Nominated by the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and FiremenMr. J. Lawrence.Nominated by the Transport Salaried Staffs&apos; association mr. R. J. Gunter.5. Under the procedure prescribed by Part VI of the Machinery of negotiation for Railway Staff, 1956, the terms of reference and the statements of claim and defence were forwarded to the Tribunal and the Tribunal were requested to hear the parties.6.   The terms of reference were as follows:  &quot;To ask the Railway Staff National Tribunal, established underAppendix, Part VI, to the Agreement in regard to the Machinery of negotiation for Railway Staff dated 28th May, 1956, to hear and decide thefollowing claims: &apos;From the National Union of RailwaymenThat the rates of pay of all Salaried and Conciliation gradesemployed by the British Transport Commission on British Railways andcovered by the Machinery of Negotiation for Railway Staff should be substantially increased.
From the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and FiremenThat the existing standard rates of pay of Drivers, Motormen,Firemen, Assistant Motormen, Engine Cleaners, Shed Enginemen, ShedEnginemen&apos;s Mates and Shed Chargemen Category &quot; A,&quot; employed bythe British Transport Commission on British Railways and covered bythe Machinery of Negotiation for Railway Staff should be increasedby 10 per cent.From the Transport Salaried Staffs&apos; AssociationThat the rates of pay of Railway Salaried Staff employed by theBritish Transport Commission on British Railways and covered by theMachinery of Negotiation for Railway Staff shall be improved, the objectat this time being to maintain the purchasing power of salaries.&quot;7. The Tribunal heard the parties on 17th, 18th and 20th March, 1958.The cases were submitted by Mr. S. F. Greene on behalf of the National Unionof Railwaymen, Mr. A. Hallworth on behalf of the Associated Society of locomotive Engineers and Firemen, and Mr. W. J. P. Webber on behalf of theTransport Salaried Staffs&apos; Association. Mr. A. B. B. Valentine replied on behalfof the British Transport Commission.
Part IRAILWAY STAFF NATIONAL TRIBUNALDecision No. 21, dated 10th April, 19581. During the present hearing the Tribunal have had to consider claimspresented by the National Union of Railwaymen, the Associated Society of locomotive Engineers and Firemen, and the Transport Salaried Staffs&apos; Association.2. The claims are set out in the terms of reference in paragraph 6 of theintroductory part of this Decision. They are, in brief, in varying terms, for improvements in the rates of pay of all Salaried and Conciliation Staff employedby the British Transport Commission on British Railways and covered by theMachinery of Negotiation for Railway Staff.3. The staff in grades covered by the claim amount to about 426,000, made upof some 343,000 Conciliation Staff (including 83.000 Railway Locomotive Staff) andsome 83,000 Salaried Staff.4. The claims were submitted respectively by the National Union of railwaymen on 12th September, 1957, the Associated Society of locomotive engineers and Firemen on 30th September, 1957, and the Transport Salaried Staffs&apos;Association on 11th November, 1957. The claims of the two first named unions were discussed at a meeting of the Railway Staff Joint Council on 24th October,1957, and that of the Transport Salaried Staffs&apos; Association at a meeting of theCouncil on 29th November, 1957. At a further meeting of the Railway Staff joint council on 12th December, 1957, the representatives of the British transport commission stated that the claims for improved rates of pay were not justified.The claims were then considered by the Railway Staff National Council on14th January and again on 24th January, 1958, when the Commission^representatives stated that they could not make any offer. No agreement wasreached and the Unions therefore asked that their claims should be referred to theRailway Staff National Tribunal.5. In examining the claims the Tribunal have had before them the evidence and arguments presented by the parties both in a series of documents and in oralhearings. The main arguments common to all the three Railway Trade unions and advanced in their support may be summarised as follows:  (1) Railway wages and salaries are generally lower than those in comparableindustries;(2) the increase in the cost of living justifies a further improvement in railway wages and salaries.The National Union of Railwaymen, in support of their claim for a substantial increase in rates of pay, contend also that:  (1) Railway wages and salaries have fallen further behind those of otherindustries;(2) it is no answer to the claim for the British Transport Commission to saythey have not got the money. Their financial difficulties have been caused by unreasonable statutory controls and Government interventionwhich the Commission have not opposed sufficiently vigorously;(3) it has not been established that a wage increase for railwaymen would beinflationary;(4) the successful fulfilment of the Commission^ Modernisation Plan dependsprincipally on the co-operation they receive from their staff: they areentitled to expect that co-operation only if they pay reasonable and fairwages.The Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen in support oftheir claim for an increase of 10 per cent, in standard rates of pay of LocomotiveStaff contend that:  (1) the current rates of pay are inadequate recompense for the exceptional,highly skilled and responsible duties performed;(2) the increase sought is necessary for the retention and future recruitment of the right type of personnel to meet the requirements of the modernisation Programme.
The Transport Salaried Staffs&apos; Association contend that:  (1) account should be taken of the rise in the retail price index since october 1956;(2) it is necessary to improve railway salaries in order to attract (and retain)the right type of recruit to the Service;(3) in view of the contribution made by the Salaried Staff to the increasing efficiency of the Railway Service, the real value of their salaries shouldbe at least maintained.6. The main arguments advanced on behalf of the British transport commission may be summarised as follows:  (1) it has not been established that railway salaries and wages or earnings are too low compared with those in other industries, but on the contraryin the last three years they have been three times substantially improved and are no longer lagging behind;(2) apart from certain areas where special difficulties are experienced by all employers, because of the shortage of labour, British Railways areholding their own in the recruitment and retention of staff;(3) the increase in the cost of living since the last settlement in March 1957is only 3-2 per cent.;(4) an increase of pay at this time in an attempt to restore the purchasingpower of the staff to the March 1957 level would be largely self-defeating because it would inevitably give rise to a general round of wage increases causing a further rise in prices;(5) further additional staff costs would adversely affect the stability anddevelopment of the railways under the Modernisation Plan and would seriously impede the current efforts to increase business. TheCommission would be compelled to seek special means to meet thosecosts, including the curtailment of services, and these measures would adversely affect the future prospects of the Commission and thelivelihood of railwaymen;(6) an increase of railway salaries and wages at this juncture would destroy the prospect that prices may keep steady or fall if nothing is done to start another round of rising wages and prices.Finding by the Chairman and Mr. A. J. Espley7. In September 1956 the Transport Commission prepared and submittedto the Minister of Transport and Civil Aviation a review of its policy and prospectswith special reference to railways. This review was subsequently embodied inthe Government White Paper on &quot; Proposals for Railways &quot; (Cmd. 9880) whichwas presented to Parliament by the Minister of Transport and Civil Aviation inOctober 1956.The review referred to, which dealt in Chapter II with the financial pioblemof the Commission, showed, infer alia, that in comparison with the years immediately preceding its issue there had been a financial shortfall in the working surplusduring 1955 of very considerable magnitude. This shortfall was due in the mainto losses incurred during the railway strike, to the lapse of several months inputting up railway charges, and to the sudden increases in prices (chiefly coal)immediately after the process of re-adjusting charges had been completed, whichlosses together amounted to  27 millions. At the same time the Commissionpointed out that against any surpluses earned Central Charges, mainly the charges for remuneration of capital, had averaged about  50 millions per annum, with atendency to rise in later years principally because of the need to replace assetsbooked at pre-war values by assets purchased at the new levels of cost and thatthe exceedingly poor results of 1955 prompted the view that one could no longerexpect the lean years to be safely recouped out of the better ones in the future,With the level of the accumulated deficit kept to. negligible proportions inconsequence. There were, it was stated, growing indications as 1955 closed that,though it was a year of financial unbalance, it was not a year of fundamentaleconomic weakness. The review showed, however, that early in 1956 the positiondeteriorated further. With the general drive throughout the country to halt further increases in the price of basic goods and services it became doubtful whether thelast general increase could, or should, be recouped forthwith in higher transport charges. On the railways in particular the general merchandise traffic had continued
to decline, partly because they were not equipped to improve their standards ofservice in step with their competitors and in the event it had been decided to limit the amount and nature of proposed increases in transport charges for sixmonths and to use that period for making a review of the whole position. allowing for the increases of charges which were authorised there was a gap in theCommission^ budget of the order of  35 millions a year and since then therehad been further increases in costs and other changes in the position which meant that the probable rate of deficit would be about  45 millions a year.At the end of 1955 the accumulated deficit was already  70 millions. Bythe end of 1956, however, the accumulated deficit would, it was anticipated, beof the order of  120 millions assuming no further increases in wages or other costs. The Commission stressed the importance of realising what its positionwould be in a few years1 time if appropriate measures were not taken to relieveit. The total deficit carried forward, it was pointed out, would reach unmanageableproportions and ultimately a default on the Commission^ obligations would beinescapable, with serious effect on the services provided to the trader and tc the travelling public.It was in the circumstances appearing in the Commission^ review that, asshown in the White Paper, the Government proposed &quot; that for a specified numberof years, broadly until the revenue account of the Commission was expected tobe in balance, special advances should be made to the Commission out of the consolidated Fund equal to their revenue deficits for the years from 1956 to 1962inclusive but limited as to total amount which might be of the order of  250millions.&quot;The effect of the Government proposals was to freeze for the time beingthe Commission^ accumulated deficit, which at the end of 1955 stood at i&apos;70 millions and to permit of borrowing sums as required, but not exceeding a total of 250 millions to meet deficits incurred between 1956 and 1962 inclusive, duringwhich period the Commission^ Modernisation Plan would be proceeding.It was to give effect to these proposals that the Transport (Railway Finances)Act, 1957, was passed.There is no provision in the said Act which limits the annual rate at whichthe Commission may borrow against  250 millions made available to it.During 1956 the Commission had a deficit of  57-5 millions on its railwayundertaking, while on its other activities there was a surplus of  3 -1 millions. Tocover the net deficiency for 1956 the Commission borrowed  54-4 millions, roughly1 / 5th of the maximum sum of  250 millions made available to it.The year 1957, we were informed, was an unsatisfactory year for the railways.Expenses were considerably higher, mainly as a result of the increase of salaries and wages arising from the March settlement. Further, there was a tendency for freight traffic, on which profit margins are narrow, to fall, and even though the results ofthe year included the benefit of a non-recurrent windfall for the railways, due to additional traffic directed to rail as a result of the restrictions of liquid fuel duringthe Suez crisis, it was already clear that the deficit for 1957 would exceed the 1956figure of  54-4 millions. The borrowings against 1956 and 1957 deficits, whichtogether must inevitably total a sum in excess of  110 millions would seriousiydeplete the  250 millions which had been calculated as necessary to cover theCommission^ deficits for the period 1956 to 1962 inclusive, of which there werefive years still to run.The claims by the National Union of Railwaymen and the Transport SalariedStaffs&apos; Association are for increases of unspecified amounts. The associated society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen on the other hand have asked for anincrease of 10 per cent, for their members. Using this latter claim merely as ayardstick, an increase of this order applied to wages grades covered by the claimsgenerally would involve raising the wages bill of the Commission by somes 30 millions a year, and this without taking into account the cost of otherapplications made by the Unions which, if granted, would, it is estimated by theCommission, add a further  17 millions a year. Competition on both the freightand passenger side is proving &quot;fierce&quot; and, in consequence, the advisability ofagain raising freight charges, which were last raised in August 1957, or passenger fares, which were raised last September, was open to serious question. If, however,it were to be held practicable and commercially prudent to obtain additional receiptsin 1958 from higher charges, these would be needed, we were informed, to keep the1958 deficit within the maximum limit originally contemplated, at the present levelof costs, and would not be available for meeting increased costs whether for wagesor anything else.
Increases in salaries and wages at the present time could, we were informed,only be met by drastic and damaging curtailment of the Commissions activities and services beyond those contemplated in its review and this, it was claimed, would be contrary to the interest of the railways, and the staff who served them, and contrary,too, to the interest of the customers and of the country.The modernisation plan which is now being implemented is both bold inconception and comprehensive in application and is already producing a resurgenceof the pride and interest which was an outstanding attribute of railway staff. It is felt that results which should flow from its implementation will develop a serviceof which the Nation and the staff will be justifiably proud and the staff, as has been indicated to us by the Commission, should share in the benefit which may beexpected to accrue from the plan both financially and in their conditions of service.The evidence before us shows that the basic rates of staff covered by the presentclaims are low in comparison with those cited to us as applying in other nationalised industries, public services and certain private undertakings.It is impossible for us to forecast what may be the order of the annual deficitswhich will be incurred by the Commission this year and in the years up to 1962.But in the light of the circumstances outlined above and of the fact that to coverdeficits incurred up to 1962 the Commission is, by statute, prevented from borrowinga sum in excess of  250 millions, against which sum it has already been compelled,or will be compelled, to draw sums which together will exceed  110 millions for1956 and 1957, we feel ourselves unable to recommend an increase of wages at thepresent time.(Signed) JOHN FORSTER, Chairman.A. J. ESPLEY.Finding by Mr. E. Hall8. The evidence before the Tribunal was unanimously accepted as showing that the basic rates of staff covered by the present claims were low in comparisonwith those cited to us as applying in other nationalised industries, public servicesand certain private undertakings.It is not disputed by the Commission that there has been an increase in the costof living. The only difference between the Parties on this heading being on thequestion of amount. The Tribunal unanimously agree that there has in fact been an increase in the cost of living as shown by the Index of Retail Prices since the19th March, 1957, the date of their last Award.In paragraph 11 on page 4 of the Government White Paper presented to theHouse in October 1956, it was stated:  &quot; The setting up in 1955 of the British Railway Productivity Council v/as a recognition of all concerned that the successful operation of the Commissionsundertaking and its prosperity are dependent in a high degree on the efficient and willing co-operation of every member of the staff. It is an important factor in any consideration of the Commissions position that two-thirds of their total expenditure is accounted for by wages and salaries.&quot;I cannot accept the view that the deficits incurred by the Commission in theirattempts to modernise and subsequently reorganise the British Railways should be partially recouped through the worsening of the standard of living of the employees of this undertaking.I cannot accept that when under the Transport (Railway Finances) Act, .1957,the Government undertook to finance the Commissions deficits on its revenue account to the extent of a sum not exceeding  250 millions during the seven years from 1956 to 1962 inclusive it was intended that the said Act should be used as an instrument or reason to prevent the employees of the Commission from maintaining their then existing standard of living, nor can I accept the said Act as a reason for refusing to improve basic rates to ensure their reasonable comparability with thosepayable to employees of similar grades in other nationalised industries or public services.It would be impossible to obtain the efficient and willing co-operation of anystaff whose basic wages are admittedly low as against similar grades in other nationalised industries and/or public services, who could not rely upon anIndependent Tribunal to restore their declining purchasing power.
We were told by the Commission, as for the present, their ability to raiseadditional revenue by increasing fares and charges is restricted by purely commercialconsideration. I do not hold that the Terms of Reference in this claim makes theTribunal competent to say how the Commission should obtain the necessary financeto meet the claim.Having regard to the above, I feel justified in dissenting from the majority report, and recommend :  (1) The immediate restoration of purchasing power of Wages and Salariescovered by this claim, to the same level that obtained following the20th Award, dated March 19th, 1957.(2) The Tribunal having accepted that the Basic Wages are low in comparisonto similar grades in other Nationalised Industries and Public Services:The contending parties should meet again in an endeavour to resolve this problem using the rates as submitted to the Tribunal asa basis for settlement.(Signed) EDWIN HALL.10 th April, 1958.
BRITISH RAILWAYSRAILWAY STAFF NATIONAL TRIBUNALDECISION No. 22.   CLAIM FOR A 40-HOUR WEEK FOR RAILWAYLOCOMOTIVE STAFF.   10th APRIL, 1958IntroductoryI. The Railway Staff National Tribunal is established under Part VI of theAppendix to the Memorandum of Agreement dated 28th May, 1956, known as the&quot; Machinery of Negotiation for Railway Staff, 1956,&quot; made between the british transport Commission of the one part and the National Union of Railwaymen, the associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen, and the TransportSalaried Staffs&apos; Association of the other part.2. The function and duty of the Railway Staff National Tribunal is to hear and decide, in respect of employees to whom the Machinery of Negotiation is applicable,issues as to standard salaries, wages, hours of duty and other standard conditions ofservice, which have been agreed, or decided in the prescribed manner, to be issues of major importance, and which have been previously considered by the railway staff National Council.3. The following constituted the Railway Staff National Tribunal during theconsideration of the present case:  Sir John Forster, K.B.E., Q.C., Chairman.Mr. A. J. Espley, C.B.E., J.P., selected by the British transport commission.Mr. E. Hall, J.P., selected by the Associated Society of locomotive engineers and Firemen.4. It is provided in the Machinery of Negotiation that at the desire of theparties to the issue the Tribunal may be assisted by representatives of the partiessitting as Assessors.  On the present occasion the Assessors were :  Nominated by the British Transport Commission.Mr. C. H. Brazier.Nominated by the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen.Mr. J. Lawrence.5. Under the procedure prescribed by Part VI of the Machinery of Negotiationfor Railway Staff, 1956, the terms of reference and the statements of claim and defence were forwarded to the Tribunal and the Tribunal were requested to hear the parties.6.   The terms of reference were as follows:  -To ask the Railway Staff National Tribunal, established under Appendix,Part VI, to the Agreement in regard to the Machinery of Negotiation for railway Staff dated 28th May, 1956, to hear and decide the following claim ofthe Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen :  That a 40-hour week be substituted, without any reduction in rates of pay, for the 88-hour fortnight now applicable in the case of Drivers,Motormen, Firemen, Assistant Motormen, Engine Cleaners, ShedEnginemen, Shed Enginemen&apos;s Mates and Shed Chargemen, Category &quot;A,&quot;employed by the British Transport Commission on British Railways andcovered by the Machinery of Negotiation for Railway Staff.7. The Tribunal heard the Parties on 21st March, 1958. Mr. A. Hallworthsubmitted the case on behalf of the Associated Society of Locomotive engineers and Firemen and Mr. W. P. Allen, C.B.E., replied on behalf of the British transport commission.53264c
BRITISH RAILWAYSRAILWAY STAFF NATIONAL TRIBUNALDECISION No. 22.   CLAIM FOR A 40-HOUR WEEK FOR RAILWAYLOCOMOTIVE STAFF.   10th APRIL, 1958Introductory1. The Railway Staff National Tribunal is established under Part VI of theAppendix to the Memorandum of Agreement dated 28th May, 1956, known as the&quot; Machinery of Negotiation for Railway Staff, 1956,&quot; made between the british transport Commission of the one part and the National Union of Railwaymen, the associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen, and the TransportSalaried Staffs&apos; Association of the other part.2. The function and duty of the Railway Staff National Tribunal is to hear and decide, in respect of employees to whom the Machinery of Negotiation is applicable,issues as to standard salaries, wages, hours of duty and other standard conditions ofservice, which have been agreed, or decided in the prescribed manner, to be issues of major importance, and which have been previously considered by the railway staff National Council.3. The following constituted the Railway Staff National Tribunal during theconsideration of the present case:  Sir John Forster, K.B.E., Q.C., Chairman.Mr. A. J. Espley, C.B.E., J.P., selected by the British transport commission.Mr. E. Hall, J.P., selected by the Associated Society of locomotive engineers and Firemen.4. It is provided in the Machinery of Negotiation that at the desire of theparties to the issue the Tribunal may be assisted by representatives of the partiessitting as Assessors. On the present occasion the Assessors were:  Nominated by the British Transport Commission.Mr. C. H. Brazier.Nominated by the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen.Mr. J. Lawrence.5. Under the procedure prescribed by Part VI of the Machinery of Negotiationfor Railway Staff, 1956, the terms of reference and the statements of claim and defence were forwarded to the Tribunal and the Tribunal were requested to hear the parties.6.   The terms of reference were as follows:  To ask the Railway Staff National Tribunal, established under Appendix,Part VI, to the Agreement in regard to the Machinery of Negotiation for railway Staff dated 28th May, 1956, to hear and decide the following claim ofthe Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen:  That a 40-hour week be substituted, without any reduction in rates of pay, for the 88-hour fortnight now applicable in the case of Drivers,Motormen, Firemen, Assistant Motormen, Engine Cleaners, ShedEnginemen, Shed Enginemen&apos;s Mates and Shed Chargemen, Category &quot; A,&quot;employed by the British Transport Commission on British Railways andcovered by the Machinery of Negotiation for Railway Staff.7. The Tribunal heard the Parties on 21st March, 1958. Mr. A. Hallworthsubmitted the case on behalf of the Associated Society of Locomotive engineers and Firemen and Mr. W. P. Allen, C.B.E., replied on behalf of the British transport commission.53264c
Part IRAILWAY STAFF NATIONAL TRIBUNALDecision No. 22 dated 10th April, 19581. The Tribunal have had during their present hearing to consider a claimpresented by the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen.2. The claim is set out in the terms of reference in paragraph 6 of theintroductory part of this decision, and is briefly for the introduction of a 40-hour week, without reduction in rates of pay, for Railway Locomotive staff.3.  The staff in grades covered by the claim number approximately 83,000.4. At the present time, the standard hours of Railway Conciliation staff,including Railway Locomotive staff, are 44 per week; this arrangement came into operation on 30th June, 1947, following a recommendation by a Court ofEnquiry appointed by the Minister of Labour and National Service to deal with applications made by the Trade Unions for an improvement in wages and for areduction in the weekly hours of work.5. The present claim on behalf of Railway Locomotive staff was submittedby the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen on 25th July, 1957.A similar claim by the National Union of Railwaymen for a 40-hour week for railway Conciliation staff was submitted on 15th May, 1957. The two claims were discussed at a meeting on 9th October, 1957, between the Railways StaffConference on the one hand and the Associated Society of Locomotive engineers and Firemen and the National Union of Railwaymen on the other hand, when theUnions explained the grounds on which their claims were based. The reply ofthe British Transport Commission declining to concede the claims was given ata meeting of the Railway Staff Joint Council on 12th December, 1957. The claims were then considered by the Railway Staff National Council on 14th January, 1958,and 24th January, 1958, but no agreement was reached. On 1st February, 1958,the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen asked for their claimto be referred to the Railway Staff National Tribunal.6. In examining the claim the Tribunal have had before them the evidence and arguments presented by the parties both in a series of documents and in oralhearings. The main arguments advanced by the Society in support of the claimmay be summarised as follows:  (1) the intensification of railway working necessitates that footplate staff shallhave an adequate rest period;(2) the exceptional circumstances surrounding the railway transport servicejustify the claim;(3) the staff are entitled to a shorter working week as a basic requirement in absorbing the large numbers of men who will be made redundant asa result of the Modernisation Plan;(4) the staff are entitled to consideration in view of the greater productivityobtaining within the industry.7. The main arguments advanced on behalf of the British transport commission may be summarised as follows:  (1) the present standard working week of 44 hours is fairly general in majorindustries, and there is no evidence to demonstrate that any unduestrain or increased responsibility has been placed upon locomotiverunning staff;(2) a reduction of working hours could only be achieved at a cost of increasednumbers of staff with a reduction of productivity per head;(3) it is unrealistic to endeavour to seek a shorter working week at a timewhen increased productivity within the present working week is the paramount need in the interest of all;
(4) if the claim were conceded repercussions on other sections of railway staff would be unavoidable. The cost of meeting the claim would be no less than  3,800,000 a year; if applied also to other sections of railway staff it would result in an increased annual cost of  20,000,000;(5) the effects of a shorter working week for locomotive running staff at thepresent time would in all probability defeat the objective of the commissions Modernisation Plan and hinder the achievement of the aim of financial stability by 1962.8. We have given careful consideration to the evidence and submissions ofthe parties and we find and so award that the claim of the Associated society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen has not been established.-(Signed)     JOHN FORSTER, Chairman.A. J. ESPLEY.EDWIN HALL.10th April, 1958.

</content>
</cab>
