<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/92/0 images: 288-290</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CAB INETSTEEL:   SITING OF NEW WORKSMemorandum by the Minister of Housing and Local Governmentand Minister for Welsh affairs it was agreed after the meeting of the Cabinet on 24th April that Ishould circulate a paper giving the up-to-date facts about Kidwelly in west South Wales, which is referred to in paragraph 11 of C. (58) 66 bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer as a site that might need tc be reconsidenif financial profitability was not to be the sole criterion.2.      Kidwelly would be a less profitable site than Newport, but a moreprofitable one than Grangemouth.    The sociological and political case for Kidwelly is as strong as for Grangemouth.    To put the steelworks atKidwelly would sterilise rather more coal under the site (coal which Iunderstand that the National Coal Board have however no present plans to work) than to put it at Grangemouth.3.      The latest Ministry of Labour figures show 8.4 per cent ofunemployment in the Llanelly and Kidwelly area;  the male figures forneighbouring areas are given in the Appendix.4.      Much of this unemployment has been caused by the recent closing of hand tinplate and sheet works in the area, and steelworks whichserved them.     The resulting situation appeared so serious that inFebruary my colleagues immediately concerned agreed that I should appoint a four-man team (consisting of representatives of my Department,the Board of Trade, the Ministry of Labour, and the Iron and Steel Board)to examine what the steel industry might itself be able to do to assist in maintaining employment in the area and offsetting the heavy redundancies.I have just received the team&apos;s unanimous report.     It says that theremaining hand tinplate works still open are likely to close soon:  thatthe remaining hand sheet works cannot be expected to survive the cominginto operation of additional modern capacity at Margam, Ebbw Vale andShotton by the end of 1959:  that some of the remaining steelworks willprobably close down, and that the few which may survive are unlikely toprovide additional employment.5.     The four-man team accordingly foresee a substantial furtherdecline in employment in the next two or three years.     If the newstrip mill were sited at Kidwelly, the situation would be saved.     If it isnot sited there, they say that the only hope for West South Wales lies in the introduction of new and different industry:   but past experience in trying to persuade new industry to go so far west affords little ground for optimism.C.(58) 8&quot;28th April, 1958(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)COPY NO. ^li
6.      The other basic industry of the area is anthracite mining.     Ifthere should be any falling off in the demand for anthracite, the futureof the area would be bleak indeed.7.      The political results if the building of the new strip mill in wales is vetoed and it is diverted to Scotland or England are set out inparagraph 9(i) and (v) of the Chancellor&apos;s paper.H.B.Ministry of Housing and LocalGovernment, S. V/.1.Z8th April, 1958.-2-SECRET
APPENDIXMALE Uro;IPLOI^rEI&apos;tt FIGURES IN WEST SOUTH WALESAPRIL. 1938Area	Number	Per centLlanelly and Kidwelly	2,969	8.4Sivansea t	2,841	6.5Pontardawe and Ystalyfera	417	5.7Amnianf ord and Gamant ^_____.......        ^___i   ___	273 ______________.....	3.8

</content>
</cab>
