<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/125/0 images: 5-11</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
FARM PRICE review memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and. food the Prime Minister has asked me to report the results of thediscussions which he and I have had with Sir Harold Woolley.Sir Harold said that an award of  20 million was quite impossible, andthat he would be bound to denounce it.    He confirmed that such ahaward would cause great bitterness among farmers who, after all thehigh hopes raised by the Plan, would feel completely disillusioned.2.      Nevertheless it is clear from our discussions, and from theattached memorandum which Sir Harold left with the Prime Minister,that, unless there is an eleventh-hour change of heart by the Unions,there is no prospect of an agreed settlement at  28 million.     I have always taken the view that it would only be justifiable to go above 20 million if this could secure agreement.    I am, therefore, nowsatisfied that it is right to stand firm at  20 million.3.      I am grateful for the discretion which my colleagues gave to rneand the other agricultural Ministers to vary the individual commodity prices, and we have made some changes, in particular on cattle, to achieve the balance which we think is most defensible agriculturally.I attach the schedule that has now been sent to the Farmers&apos; Unions.4.     I have also considered with the Secretary of State for Waleswhether anything could be done to give special help to farmers in wales and elsewhere who have suffered from flooding.    I am afraid that itwould not be possible to do this as part of the Review.    I am, however,in touch with the River Authorities concerned about the action needed tocontrol flooding in future, and I hope that I shall have the support of mycolleagues when later on I seek approval for the Governments contribu-tion towards the cost of the necessary works.5.     Sir Harold Woolley warned the Prime Minister that he would notbe able to keep his militant members in check.     We must, therefore,expect that a disagreed Review at  20 million will come under very strong attack in rural constituencies.    But I think that the award can be defended as a reasonable one, and will be accepted as such outside the rural areas.    My agricultural colleagues and I will do our best to convince the more reasonable farming opinion that we have been fair to the agricultural industry.T. F. P.Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, S. W. 1.4th March, 1966IIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)66C(66) 51 COPY NO. i__^4th March, 1966CABINET
AMIS INOTE ON THE FINANCIAL POSITION OF BRITISH agriculture the Government1s decisions at.this Review&apos;will he crucial forthe future of the farming industry.    The Plan sets out the positiverole for agriculture;    the determinations made now will undoubtedly be assessed by the industry as a significant indication of theGovernment&apos;s intentions as regards providing the additional financial resources required to enable the programme of selective - expansionto bo carried through.Farmers have been working under an increasing financial andpsychological strain.    The financial strain is the struggle tomaintain and increase capital investment out of prices which havebeen consistently held at levels out of all proportion to increasingcosts.&apos;   The psychological strain arises from the frustration of a situation in which the farmers&apos; real reward bears no relation totheir increased production and productivity.Unless this state of affairs is tackled in a realistic way atthis Review a widespread bitterness will develop, and however this may be expressed, the results cannot be other than bad for thecountry.In limiting their submission, to a figure which represents no more than an average increase of 3i&quot; por cent on the present value ofthe guarantees, the Farmers&apos; Unions have had regard to the minimumimprovement   required in farmers&apos; resources to enable them to giveeffect to the selective expansion envisaged in the Plan.It will be a difficult task to convince farmers that increases in the various commodity prices within the Unions&apos;  overall.figure areat all adequate, but I believe we can do it provided the 1966determinations also embody features of a longer term nature.    Throematters in particular need to bo covereds-1)    The Government must make clear its intention to make financialdeterminations in the years ahead of such a nature as to enable\he industry to maintain its momentum&apos; and .continue to play   itsrole in a vigorous import substitution policy.11)    It is essential that for certain key commodities there should belong &quot;term guarantees to establish confidence in farmers1 mindsthat in committing themselves to the higher level of investmentpostulated by the Plan they will have a sound prospect of earningan adequate return.
2.111) The Unions attach groat importance to the additional data nowfeeing collected for Annual Reviews, designed to throw lighton the issue of proper remuneration and an adequate return on capital invested and seek an assurance from the Government thatthey, too, will regard this data as an essential relevantfact or.additional onalCapital Re quirementsThe Farmers&apos; Unions estimate that up to  800 mn. .(at 1964/5prices)  of additional tenant typo assets will he needed during theperiod of the Plan to enable the industry to expand in such a way as to make possible the projected additional net import saving of nearly  200 mn. per annum by 1970.Net income for agricultural policy purposes farm net income is defined as the reward for the manual and managerial labour of the farmerand his wife and for the use of the occupier&apos;s investment.    Out ofthe figure of net income as calculated, farmers have also to find the money to cover the excess of replacement cost over original.costof certain assets (slaughter stock, cultivations, growing crops,etc,) used up in the course of the year&apos;s production and trade.Thus? some  46 mn. out of the industry&apos;s estimated not income of 463-g- mn. for 1965/6 has to he appropriated for this purpose,  .Related to the capital development needs postulated.above,and to any reasonable objective of &quot;proper remuneration .... and anadequate return on capital invested (Section 1 agriculture act 1947)? net income is demonstrably low.looking at the last five years and comparing 1965/6 forecastwith 1960/1, the volume of net output has increased by 1 Tfr;   net income in real terms has not risen at all,looking at the current year, net output has increased by 2^5real net income has fallen by nearly 7$.&apos;    The additional data compiled for the 1966 Review has enabled us to make an approximate calculation of the sumremaining to remunerate full time farmers and wives after allowing varying rates of interest on their investment asoccupiers.     Using the Government&apos;s estimate of 220,000 fulltime farm businesses in the United Kingdom and making
3.appropriate adjustments to both the estimate of the industry &apos;total net assets and net income for part-time farm businesses,the following figures emerge as the balance of income per fulltime farm business after allowing the rates of return on investment as shown;Balance per full timeInterest Rate farm businessfo &quot;                     20 - 15615 41110 979To see these figures in perspective it should be noted that onthe basis of the Ministry of Labour&apos;s Earnings and HoursEnquiry (October 1965) the current earnings of an adult maleindustrial worker are now averaging  1,019 a year.Cost IncreasesCosts this year, are up by the highest figure since1957 -  42 mn. of which  32 mn. falls on the reviewcommodities.   Here is the sequence of cost increases on reviewcommodities in recent years:Review   mn.1961 191962 19*1963 131964 241965 291966 32The rising bill of costs makes it extremely difficult to finance the maintenance, let alone expansion, of production.Had the value of the guarantees in 1964 not been increased by some  31mn. against costs amounting to  24 mn. ,the deterioration in the industry&apos;s financial position wouldhave been considerably worse - and at that time the Governmentof the day had no intention of pursuing an expansion programme.This year we have increased costs of some  32 mn.and we have an agreed policy of selective expansion.Cont &apos;d..
4.Credit SourcesBank advances, which have more than doubled in the past ten years, have grown rapidly in relation to output and capital employed.    If real income continues to decline in. relation tooutput and productivity, there is a risk of outside financebecoming more difficult to obtain and of existing advancesbecoming vulnerable.The plain fact is that unless the existing ratio ofprices to costs is significantly improved the achievement ofthe selective expansion programme will be seriouslyprejudiced.3rd March, 1966.-IX.
ANNEX IIILKIncreased s.q.Guaranteed Price (gal.)attleGuaranteed Price (cwt.)Beef Cow SubsidyheepGuaranteed Price (lb.)Hill Sheep SubsidyTOOLGuaranteed Price (lb.)IGSIncreased middle bandCut in quality premiums(per score)!&amp;GS(Hen)Guaranteed Price (doz.)$HEATIncreased s.q.Guaranteed Price (cwt.)PARLEYIncreased s.q.Guaranteed Price (cwt.)POTATOESGuaranteed Price (ton)touching grantlimej [lO-OPERATIONfarm RECORDSft. I. SPECIAL GRANTPTHER GRANTS(Grassland Renovation,Rabbit Clearance;Scottish Islands).TOTAL:ScheduleChange(b)Addition of 50m. gallons to U.K. standard quantity4- id.+ 10s. Od.Introduction at rate of  6. 10s. per cow* Id.Increase of 1s. Od. per ewe- 2d,Increase of 0.4m. pigs&quot;AA&quot;   - 1s. Od.)&quot;AA+&quot; -        6d.)1d.Increase of 0.20m. tons)- 3d.)Increase of 0.45m. tons)3d.)net effectnet effect+ 5s. Od.Reduction of  2. 10s.ReductionExtensionExtension to rest of U.K.IncreaseNet effectValue( m.)+ 4.286* 4.502+11.960+ 2.400+ 1.540+ 0.259- 0.696+ 2.736- O.676- 3.804- 0.039+ 0.018+ 1.172- 3.715- 1.500+ 0,250+ 0.750+ 0.500- 0.004+19-939(a) No changes in price guarantees for duck eggs, rye, oats and mi^ad corn and sugar beet.(b) Net increase after taking account of automatic adjustments due to changesin liquid sales.M&apos;h March 1966ANNUAL REVIEW&quot; 1966in Price Guarantees and Production Grants


</content>
</cab>
