<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/125/0 images: 259-264</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PARLIAMENTARY COMMITTEESMemorandum by the Lord President of the council when the Cabinet considered on 20th April the wider use ofSelect Committees (CC(66) 19th Conclusions, Minute 4) I.was invited toarrange for the Committee on Parliamentary Procedure to consider theprocedure which might be adopted by the proposed new Committees andother practical problems arising from the experiment.    The PrimeMinister subsequently announced in the Debate on the Address that weshould propose for discussion that &quot;a Committee or Committees be setup responsible to the House, representative of the House as a whole, to review any issue which might be considered appropriate within the field of administration of some of our great social Departments, and that indue course these Committees should report their findings to the House&quot;.2.       The Ministerial Committee have now considered the procedures which might be suggested in discussion with the Opposition Parties.Relationship of Ministers to Parliament3.      The Ministerial Committee considered that the problem of theprocedure to be adopted, and indeed of the form of the Committees,were inseparable from the fundamental question: do we want to see achange in the relationship between Ministers and Parliament?    It is arguable that the concept of Ministerial responsibility to parliament has become unreal, because the House lacks effective means of exercising continuing and informed criticism and control of theexecutive, and that the balance should be redressed by providing theHouse with organs for this purpose.    if this argument is accepted, itseems to follow that we should contemplate a type of Committee with power at its own discretion to scrutinise the administration and consider the policy of the Department or Departments with which it isconcerned; and once we accept a shift in the balance of real power asbetween Parliament and the Government it is not easy to see how wecould in the long run resist the appointment of Committees to scrutinisethe work of the Overseas and Defence Departments, or prevent theconsideration of topics which v/ere acutely; controversial on party lines.Nevertheless, some members of the Committee thought that it was right in principle to strengthen the authority of Parliament and that the risksshould be accepted.    There is likely to be pressure in the House for usto move in this direction.-1-13 DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY18 GOVERNMENT)C(66) 71 COPY NO.    6717th May, 1966CABINET
4.      A possible alternative which does not seem to involve so muchchange in the relationship betv/een Parliament and the executive is toenable Members to participate effectively in the formation of policy sothat the House of Commons is seen less as a critic over against theGovernment than as a partner in the development of policy and the meansof executing it.    My Committee took the view that in launching ourexperiment we should be clear which of these purposes we wished thenew Committees to serve and should be careful lest procedures intro-duced at the outset should create precedents which we might find later to be in conflict with our long-term intentions.5.      Opinion in the Ministerial Committee tended on the whole towards a system of Committees which the Government could use to secure theassistance of Members in the investigation of problems and the develop-ment of policy rather than one which would develop a critical functionwholly outside Government control, though they recognised that anyCommittees would in time press for greater freedom of initiative.Possible types of committee.      Against this background of principle, my Committee consideredthat a choice should be made between three types of Committee:-(a) Committees specialising in the work of a particular department, or, as a preferable variant, in a specifiedfield of work v/hich would include topics which are not atpresent the responsibility of any one Department, such ascivil science or the social services;(b) Standing Committees analogous to Standing Committees forthe consideration of public Bills, to v/hich topics could bereferred by the House on the Motion of the Government,the membership, or part of it, being changed with eachreference;(c) Advisory Committees of Members appointed to considerquestions of future policy within the field of a particular department.7.      Type (a) would go furthest to enhance the authority of Parliament.It might at the outset be content to deal v/ith topics specificallyreferred to it within its field, but would be likely in time to develop anindependent initiative; it might also tend to focus its attention more onthe investigation of current administration and the consideration of current policies than on the formation of new policies for the future.8.       Type (b) would give the Government through the House complete control over the selection of topics for consideration.    But theCommittees would have no continuity and would develop no body of knowledge in a particular field.    If they were given at the outset topicsof real substance to consider they might satisfy current Parliamentarydemand for a greater share in policy-making; but they might not be of asmuch help to Ministers as type (c) in creating a body of informed andsympathetic opinion on the problems of a particular Department.-2-
Vu* \mf my * m %Jtm mSL I Bjf^-Hgii9.     Type (c), which might possibly be appointed by the minister concerned and report to him rather than to the House v/ould, like (b)give Members the opportunity of participating in policy-making; itwould also enable them to accumulate specialised knowledge and experience, and hence to present more valuable reports.    a continuing Committee would no doubt in time wish to select its owntopics for consideration; but the Minister should be able to establishwith it a relationship of confidence which would enable him to exertconsiderable influence on its choice; he could, for example, offer theCommittee several topics among which to choose, or himself chooseamong topics proposed by them; and he would be able to explain why itwould be inopportune to consider particular topics at a particular time.How attractive this type of Committee would be to Members, andconsequently how much time they would be prepared to give to it,might well depend on how far they felt they were in fact able to bringan independent influence to bear on the formation of policy on topics of real importance, and in some areas (particularly perhaps in the HomeOffice field) it might not be easy to reconcile this with the avoidance of subjects of party controversy,10.     My Committee considered that the key to the extent of any transfer of power from the executive to Parliament lay in the controlof the selection of topics for consideration by the Committees.     In thelong run control, or a decisive influence, is more likely to be retainedwith the (b) or (c) type of Committee than with type (a).    Moreover, ifthe Committee system spread to oversea affairs and defence, type (a)might well be the most embarrassing form of Committee to haveoperating in these fields.11.     My own view is that types (b) or (c) are more compatible withthe system of government v/hich v/e have evolved in this country thantype (a), v/hich has developed in the United States in a quite differentcontext as virtually the only means of bringing Ministers and Congressinto contact, and there it is not concerned, except indirectly, in the positive formation of policy.    In our system Parliament already hasmeans of scrutinising administration in the Public Accounts Committeeand the Estimates Committee.    T  Parliament is to move into the field of policy, otherwise than in debate in the House, I believe it should doso through partnership rather than confrontation.12.     Whatever type of Committee were adopted, it would be desirableto ensure that Committees did not embark on a topic on which theGovernment had already promised legislation, and that they did notconsider themselves free to recommend major public expenditure.It would plainly be embarrassing to resist a recommendation for expenditure endorsed by the House of Commons.    And yet theGovernment could not act on such recommendations without disruptingits own system of priorities and opening the way to the developmentof powerful lobbies operating through Committees sympathetic to their interests.    We thought, therefore, that it should be made clear,perhaps by a statement by the Prime Minister, that, since theGovernment were responsible for determining priorities and had fixedexpenditure limits for each Department, they would be unlikely to beable to accept recommendations involving increased expenditure on particular services.    If this were not effective, it might be necessaryfor Committees to be formally excluded by their terms of referencefrom recommending major increases in public expenditure,GONFDDENTIAL
14.     The Ministerial Committee considered a proposal that the newCommittees might be served by an officer of the House, who might bea senior ex-civil servant, with a staff of three or four which might alsoserve the Estimates Committee.    It has been suggested that the workof all these Committees would be facilitated if they could call upon theadvice of an officer with experience of the Government machine whowould stand in much the same relationship to them as that of the comptroller and Auditor General to the Public Accounts Committee(PAC).    But the Ministerial Committee were doubtful about thisproposal.    In relation to Committees concerned v/ith the formation ofpolicy, the parallel with the Comptroller and Auditor General would notbe very close; and the arrangement might be resented as an attempt toderogate from the status and independence of the Clerks.    My committee thought that at the outset of the experiment it would be preferable toprovide the Committees with joint secretaries - a Clerk and an officerof the Department concerned - following the precedent already established in the staffing of Speaker&apos;s Conferences.    This worsild not preclude the development of more elaborate arrangements if the newCommittees progressed from experiment to permanency.-4-Procedure13.     My Committee consider that the new Committees should be encouraged to adopt informal procedure.    They should avoid takingvotes, which would  emphasise divisions on party lines, and theyshould not feel bound to publish all their evidence: it might be appropriate, for example, that they should publish written evidencebut not normally oral.    We thought it better that Ministers   shouldnot take the chair of the Committees; this would clearly be inappropriate for type (a) Committees, and for the other two typesmight be interpreted as an attempt by the executive to exerciseexcessively tight control: chairmanship would in any event imposetoo great a burden on busy Ministers.    We thought, however, that theMinister responsible for the topic or Department under consideration should be an ex off icio member of the Committees, but should be free to be represented, and normally would be represented, by a juniorMinister.    This would enable him to engage in inforrnal discussion withthe Committee which would give him a better opportunity of explaining the consideration affecting his thinking on the topic in question than would a formal appearance as a witness.    It should be open to him togive formal evidence if he or the Committee so desired; normally such evidence should not be published, but, since publication would sometimesbe desirable, there should be no formal ban on publication.    TheCommittees should have power to send for officials and other witnesses,but it would need to be established that officials would not answer questions on policy and they should also be able to talk to the Committeeinformally and without their oral evidence being published.    TheCommittees should be free to travel and to take evidence^ formally orotherwise, anywhere in the country.Staff
Relationship between the new Committees and the Public accounts committee and the Estimates Cgnxmittee15.     There is clearly some risk of overlap between the work of thenew Committees and that of the PAC and the Estimates Committee,rather more perhaps with type (a) Committees than with either ox the others, but increasing to the extent that Committees of any sort are able to obtain a measure of control of their own programme of work.There are some topics aspects of which could legitimately be of concern to both the existing Committees and to the new Committees;but it would be important to avoid more than one dealing with aparticular topic at a given time, not least because duplication mightadd intolerably to the extra burdens which the new Committees will inevitably impose on the Ministers and Departments with which theyare concerned.    It may be possible during the experimental period to persuade the Estimates Committee to observe a self-denying ordnancewith regard to Departments whose problems are being considered bythe new Committees; as a permanent arrangement a co-co-ordinating committee of Chairmen may be necessary.Conclusion16.     We must shortly put specific proposals for an experiment to theOpposition parties.    I invite the Cabinet to consider on which of thethree types of Committee suggested in paragraph 6 they wish to seethe experiment based; and, as to procedure, to agree -(i) that the Government should at the outset retain control oftopics to be referred to the Committees;(ii) that it should be made clear to Committees that they shouldnot make recommendations for significant increases in public expenditure;(iii) that relevant Ministers should, be ex officio Members, with discretion to be represented by a junior Minister but shouldnot be in the Chair;(iv) that the procedure should be informal allowing for off-the -record discussions with both Ministers and Officials;(v) that Committees should be free to travel and take evidenceanywhere in this country;(vi) that at the outset the Committees should have joint secretaries,a Clerk and a civil servant from the relevant Department;;(vii) that during the experimental period the Estimates Committeeshould be asked not to investigate Departments on topicswhich were currently the subject of the Committee&apos;s workand that we should consider, in consultation with the chairmen, the establishment of a Chairmen1 s Committee.H. B,Privy Council Office, S. W, 1.16th May, 1966


</content>
</cab>
