<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/125/0 images: 501-506</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C(66) 82 COPY NO.       6 /17th June, 1966CABINErJ    PRICES AND INCOMES;  PAY REVIEW MACHINERYMemorandum by the First Secretary of State and secretary of State f or Economic AffairsThe Cabinet invited me recently to put forward proposals on thefuture status and functions of independent review bodies in relation toour policy on prices and incomes (CC(66) 21st Conclusions, Minute 4).It is desirable to consider at the same time arbitration and othermachinery for determining pay and conditions.2.       I think that our general objectives should be:-(a) to strengthen the authority and influence of the National board for Prices and Incomes (NBPI) over the whole field of prices and incomes;(b) to ensure that other bodies which continue to haveresponsibilities for determining or advising on pay questionstake account of the national interest and apply, in so far asthey Can, the agreed criteria, set out in last year&apos;s white paper (Cmnd. 2639);(c) to limit and, as opportunity arises, to reduce the number of separate bodies undertaking this type of work.    otherwise it will be very difficult to achieve consistency in interpretingthe White Paper criteria.    This is likely to mean graduallybringing more pay review functions within the purview of the nbpi.Existing review bodies3.       There are at present two independent review bodies for thepublic services - the Standing Advisory Committee on the Pay of theHigher Civil Service (Chairman:  Lord Franks) and the Review body on the Remuneration of Doctors and Dentists (Chairman:Lord Kindersley).    Their purpose is to provide the Government withindependent advice on the pay of groups of public servants who do nothave normal negotiating machinery or access to arbitration.    While Ibelieve that it would be logical, in the light of the general objectivesmentioned above, to transfer the work of these bodies to the NBPI,any immediate move in this direction would meet with strong opposition and would, in my view, be unwise.    On the other hand itwould be wrong to leave things precisely as they are.    I propose thatwe should make, after consultation with the staff interests concerned,three changes:--1-
(i)  The Franks and Kindersley Committees should be formallyrequested by the Government to take account of the national interest, and in particular the general principles of prices and incomes policy set out in Cmnd. 2639.    (This wasspecifically suggested, in respect of the Franks Committee,in the NBPI report on the pay of higher Civil Servants. )(ii)  There should be some element of common membership ofthe NBPI and the two review bodies in order to establish a positive link betv/een them and to help secure consistencyof approach to pay questions and to the interpretation of theWhite Paper criteria.(iii)  The Secretariat of the review bodies should be providedjointly by the Cabinet Office (as at present) and the NBPIin order to secure access to NBPI expertise in pay matters.4.      Although they will doubtless prove controversial, I do notthink that these changes could be reasonably opposed by either themedical and dental professions or by the &quot;Higher Civil Service.    Ishould regard them as a useful step in the direction of securing the objectives stimmarised in paragraph 2 above.University teachers&apos; pay.      A related question calling for early decision is the form ofmachinery which should be developed for determining the pay of university teachers.    The recent history of this question and the main considerations which seem to me relevant are summarised in the Annex.It seems to me clear that we cannot agree to set up another independentreview body for this purpose en the Franks-Kindersley pattern and thatthe right course is to lay on the NBPI (or perhaps a special panel of theBoard containing an element of outside membership) responsibility for keeping university teachers1 pay under review.    The Secretary of Statefor Education and Science, who has already told the University teachersthat an independent review body is out of the question, has indicated thathe is prepared to accept this proposal.    Its presentation to the unversity teachers will, of course, be helped by the changes proposed inparagraph 3 above.    It will be further helped if we can also make it clear,as seems in any case desirable, that the proposed panel of NBPI will beavailable to review not merely the pay of University teachers but also thatof other public services which have in. the past been undertaken by royal commissions, -^epartms ntal Committees, etc.    In addition, I suggestthat the panel might undertake regular reviews of the pay of the armed forces, and when appropriate look at the pay of other grounds paid outof the Exchequer (e. g. MPs, Ministers and the Judiciary).     It could thus develop into an independent body responsible for investigating payquestions throughout the public services.
Courts and Committees of Inquiry6.      When a Court or Committee of Inquiry is appointed to investigate matters of productivity, pay or other labour costs, Ipropose that;&quot;(i) They should be required by their terms of reference to take account of national economic considerations, where appropriate by a specific mention of the White Paper.(ii) A member of the NEPI should normally be appointedto the Court or Committee of Inquiry set up to investigatesuch questions.The recent Committee of Inquiry into the seamen&apos;s case has set a usefulprecedent in both these respects.Wages Councils7.       I do not think that the Wages Councils (and Agricultural WagesBoards) present a major problem for incomes policy at the presenttime.    Although they cover a very Large number of workers (between3 and 4 million) their rates of pay - and in many cases their earnings -are relatively low.    But it is disappointing that we still rely onstatutory wage regulation on this scale.    I suggest that we ought to try to secure greater progress in establishing voluntary negotiating machinery to replace the statutory machinery.Arbitration8.       The main function of arbitration tribunals is to reach a decisionbased on the facts and arguments laid before them by the parties which  /ill be acceptable to the parties.    There is no formal requirement that they should pay any regard to the wider national interest, nor is there any tradition or generally accepted view that this is part of theirfunction.    Arbitration is not in practice of great importance in theprivate sector, where only a tiny proportion of wage increases are settled at arbitration.    It is much more important in the public services,particularly in the Civil Service and other public services in which theGovernment is a party to the negotiations, because the Staff Side canalways take the Official Side to arbitration and the Government feelsbound to implement arbitration awards except in the most exceptional circumstances.    Thus the role of arbitration is important in the context of incomes policy in the public services, not so much becausearbitration awards necessarily breach the policy but also because ofthe influence of what amounts to &quot;unilateral&quot; arbitration on the official side negotiators.9.       There are some signs that the agreed policy is in fact havingsome influence on arbitrators as it is on public opinion generally.    Butit would be helpful if we could make it clear beyond doubt that arbitratorsare expected to have regard to the national interest, and in particular the White Paper criteria.    The best course v/ould be to secure a jointdelcaration with the various organisations most concerned to this effect.It will not be easy to reach agreement on this.    But I should like to trybecause I believe that a declaration on these lines would have a usefulpsychological influence both on arbitrators and on negotiations.-3-CONF1DENT1AL
10.     I think that this should be the first step.    But there are other possible developments in connection with arbitration.    For example,the TUC have been pressing the Minister of Labour to reinstitute some form of compulsory arbitration;  and it is for consideration whether in time the NBPI might be given a general responsibility for keepingunder review arbitration awards and wage settlements.   I think thatthese developments still lie some way ahead and I would propose tobring them before the Cabinet at a later stage, if they seem, promising.G. B.Department o  Economic Affairs, S, W, 1.16th June, 1966\\-4-
ANNEXUNIVERSITY TEACHERS&apos; PAYUniversity teachers1 pay has to date been settled directly bythe Government after consultation with the University Grants Committee,which is in turn responsible for consulting with the Committee ofVice Chancellors and the Association of University Teachers.    Therehas been no provision for arbitration.    All the parties concerned haveagreed that this machinery is unsatisfactory.    The two alternativeswhich have already been canvassed with them by the Secretary of Statefor Education and Science, after consultation with his colleagues are(a) direct negotiations with provision for arbitration and (b) a reviewtype of procedure to be carried out by the NBPI.2.      The main disadvantage, from the point of view of incomes policy, of instituting direct negotiations in this field is that it would alsobe necessary to extend to university teachers arbitration arrangements on the orthodox pattern and this would make it more difficult to ensurethat due regard was paid to the White Paper criteria.    There wouldalso be problems in constituting a management side for the negotiating machinery, since the Vice Chancellors are themselves unversity teachers and are neither the employers nor the paymasters, whilst the Government v/hich is paymaster is not in any sense an employer.The essential link between the two is the University Grants Committee(UGC) which is itself neither employer nor paymaster and which doesnot wish to have a more formal role in the determination of universitysalaries.3.       The first preference of both the Vice Chancellors and theAssociation of University Teachers (and indeed of the UGC) is apparentlyfor a review body procedure similar to that which already exists for higher civil servants and doctors and dentists.    The Secretary ofState has however told them that a new review body on the Franks andKindersley model is out ox the question, and has suggested that the nbpi might take on the function of reviewing university teachers1 pay.Both parties reacted against this proposal but indicated that theywould be prepared to consider some common form of machinery todeal with public service pay or at any rate that part of it which isalready based on a review body procedure.    The Secretary of state is now due to resume his discussions with the parties very shortly witha view to establishing new machinery to review university teachers1pay from April, 1967.-5-GOMFSOEIMTIAL


</content>
</cab>
