<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/88/0 images: 33-41</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. July 1957SECRET Copy No.C. (57) 15812th July, 1957CABINETPOST OFFICE finance memorandum by the Postmaster GeneralBecause of wage awards I must raise Post Office tariffs to produce an additional 63 millions in the 18 months to 31st March, 1959. Otherwise Post Office financeswill fall into chronic deficit.2. If my colleagues agree, I propose to make a statement, as at Annex A,in the House on 17th or 18th July, and to support it by circulating the details in annexes B, C and D.3.   My two objectives have been (a) to avoid a further major tariff increase during the life of this Parliament(this will be the third big increase in under two years);(b) to put the increases on those services which are most heavily in deficit.The draft statement shows how I have endeavoured to do this.4. The increases are severe and will be unpalatable. They include 3d. foran inland letter and increases for overseas letters. On the telephone side my mainproposal will make the rental paid by all subscribers reflect the full cost. This will mean an increase of  3 a year for many residential subscribers, who will also lose their free calls.5. The timing of the increases and the method of announcing them poseproblems. On timing, unless the increases take effect from 1st October they mustbe even greater than proposed. And in the meantime the burden would falldirectly on the Exchequer. On announcing, I am sure my statement ought tofollow as quickly as possible on the publication of the main pay awards to associate cause and effect.6.   If there is a demand for a debate the position will be (a) Postal and telegraph charges, these are not subject to prayer.(b) Telephone regulations are subject to negative resolution.(c) Postal order poundage requires legislation.Therefore the Opposition could not have a debate over the whole field unless theyuse a supply day.7. The Economic Policy Committee have considered and approved my proposals. I now seek the agreement of the Cabinet to my making the statement.Post Office Headquarters, E.C. 1,12th July, 1957.
Annex ADRAFT STATEMENT TO THE HOUSE OF commons the recent Civil Service pay award plus other increases we are making tobring Post Office wages and conditions into line with industry add nearly 30 millions a year to the cost of running the Post Office. Other cost increases have to be provided for.2. By increased efficiency we shall make new economies of about  3 millions a year. Even so, taking both this and other budgetary prospects into account,we must raise an extra  63 millions in the 18 months to 31st March, 1959.Eleven-twelths of this huge sum is for wage increases. It means that we mustincrease tariffs to get  42 millions a year more as from 1st October next  24 millions from Posts and  18 millions from telecommunications. Thatrepresents 11 per cent, of the total income of the Post Office. This clearlydemonstrates the magnitude of the wage increases.3. A comprehensive statement will be circulated in the Official Report, butthe House will want to know the main changes.Posts4. I can see no way of getting enough money without increasing the basicinland letter rate from 2\d. to 3d. This is the one case where a service showing a profit is being touched, but that profit is a rapidly diminishing one. Postcardswillbe 2\d. Inland printed papers weighing more than 2 ounces will go up. so will newspapers and parcels, although we will still be carrying these at a loss.5. Overseas letters, printed papers, and parcels will be increased, but notsurcharged air mail. The rates for Forces correspondence are being consideredby the Service Departments.6. Poundage on postal orders will go up, and legislation will be necessary.Telephones7. At present telephone subscribers outside London pay lower rentals, andon many of them we lose as much as  4 per year. Details were given in the house on 8th July. Geographical differences can no longer be justified, and all residentialsubscribers with exclusive lines will be charged  12, and business subscribers will pay  13. But the shared service concession will be increased from 30s. to  2. Thefree call allowances will have to be discontinued.8. Charges for private branch exchanges, connections and removals will beraised to bring them more into line with the cost to us. Ordinary local calls will go up to 3d., but from 1st January next this will be offset by a big extension ofthe distance over which the charge will apply. The Ad. call from a public box willnot be increased.Telegraphs9. Overseas telegrams will be increased so that they will be about two-thirdsabove prerwar. For the present the Commonwealth Press rate of Id. a word isbeing maintained.10. Although we lose a lot of money on the inland telegraph service I donot propose to increase the present charges.51871
Annex BPROPOSED INCREASES IN CHARGESI.-POSTAL CHARGESCategory of correspondenceor serviceInland and to Irish Republic1. Letters   .........2. Postcards Single.........Reply Paid  ......3. Printed Papers, Samples4. Newspapers     ......5. Business Reply ...6. Private Boxes and Bags7.Present charges	New charges	Full year yield   millions2\d. for 2 oz. then \\d. for 2 oz.	3d. for 1 oz. A\d. for 2 oz. then \\d. for 2 oz.	12-4Id. 4d.	2\d. 5d.	j.       0-52d. for 4oz. then Id. for 2 oz.	2d. for 2 oz. 4*/. for 4 oz. then Id. for 2 oz.	2-32d. for 6 oz. then Id. for 6 oz.	2\d. for 6 oz. then \\d. per 6 oz.	0-4\d. per item	Id. per item	0-1Various	Double present Charges	0-1InlandIrishRepublicParcels 		d.	5.		s.	d.Up to 2 lb.......	1	4	1	4	1	63 lb.......	1	6	1	10	1	94 lb.......	1	9	1	10	2	05 lb.......	2	0	1	10	2	36 lb.......	2	3	2	7	2	67 lb.......	2	6	z	7	2	98 lb:......	2	9	2	7	3	011 lb.......	3	0	3	0	3	315 lb.......	3	0	3	3	3	61-5Overseas 8. Letters-Surface and &quot; All Up &quot;Foreign*      ......      ...Commonwealth     ......9. Postcards-Surface and &quot; All Up &quot;Single Foreign*Single CommonwealthReply Paid Foreign*Reply Paid Commonwealth...10. Printed Papers and Samples   ...11. Commercial PapersAd. for 1 oz.then2\d. for each oz.2\d. for 1 oz.then id. for each oz.2\d.2d.5d.Ad.\\d. for 2 oz.then\d. for 2 oz.Ad. for 12 oz.then\d. for 2 oz.6d. for 1 oz.thenAd. for each oz.3d. for 1 oz:then\%d. for each oz.Ad.2\d.%d.5d.2d. for 2 oz.then id. for 2 oz.6d. for 10 oz.then id. for 2 oz.1-30?1* Will be charged henceforward for correspondence to all non-Commonwealth countries, including those to which Commonwealth rates have hitherto applied.
Category of correspondenceor service12. Small Packets......13. Insured Boxes (postage only)14. Printed Papers (reduced rate)15. Printed Papers (bulk) ...16. Canadian Magazine Post17. Registration     .........18. Insurance        .........19. Parcels Surface and AirMiscellaneous Services 20. Commission on repurchase ofunused or spoiled stampsCustoms Clearance Fees21.22.23.Special Services in connectionwith overseas mailStamped Stationery (sellingprices inclusive of postage)24. Fine for item posted out of course and transferred to Parcel Post&apos;25. Search Fee      .........26. Certificate of posting for un-registered letter27. Certificate of posting for un-registered letter (bulk posting)28. Postal Orders.........29. Overseas Money Orders-Poundage    .....30. Inland Money Orders Advice of payment......31. Inland and Overseas Money Order-Stop Payment       ......32. Telegraph Money OrderSupplementary Fees Inland .........Overseas      .........Present chargesl\d. for 10 oz.then\\d. for 2 oz.10 oz. for Is. 3d.then2 oz. for 3d.Id. for 2 oz.then\d. for 2 oz.4\d. per lb.Id. for 6 oz.\\d. for next 18 oz.then\d. for 8 oz.6d.8d. to 65. 2d.Various5% of face valueminimum charge Id.6d. and Is.VariousPostcard charges from 2\d. for 1 cardto 2s. for 11 cardsLetter Cards3d. eachEnvelopes A. and C.3d. each or 2y. for apacket of 8 (thisarrangement has notyet been broughtinto force)Id.3d.Is. for 1,000 itemsthen2d. per 1,000lid. poundage for6d. and Is: Orders2d. for Is. 6d.-5s.3d. for 6s.-21s.6d. for  2- 5Up to  1: 6d.Up to  2: Is.Up to  3: Is. 6d.then3d. per   to  40(105. 9d.)3d.6d.3d.6d., Is. or Is. 8d.(Cuba only)New chargeslOd. for 10 oz.then2d. for 2 oz.Is. Sd. for 10 oz.then4d. for 2 oz.l^d. for 2 oz.then id. for 2 oz.Sid. per lb.As 14 or 10Is.Is. 2d. to 6s. 8d.Increased to economiclevels10% of face valueminimum charge 2d.Is. and 2s.Increased to broadlyeconomic level3d. for 1 card to2s. 8d. for11 cards4d. each or 2s. 6d.for a packet of 84d. each or 2s. 6d.for a packet of 83d.6d.Id.2s. per 1,000 itemsthen4d. per 1,0002d. poundage for6d. and Is. Orders3c?. for Is. 6d. 5s.4d. for 6s.-2ls.6d. for  2- 5Up to  2: 2s.Up to  5: 3s.Up to  10: 4s.Up to  20: 6s.Up to  30: 8s.Up to  40: 105.6d.9d.6d.Is. 6d.Full yearyield  millions0-80-60-20-20-90-1*2-4Total (including  0-1 million from minor items)* Not including increased yield from postage.5187124-0B2
II. TELEPHONE CHARGES(a) Exchange RentalsLondonExisting TariffFour LargeCitiesProvincesProposed TariffAll Areas	 	s.	d.	 	s.	d	 	s.	d.	 	s.	d.1. Business Lines												Exclusive    ......	12	0	0	11	10	0	11	0	0	13	0	0Shared      ......	10	10	0	10	0	0	9	10	0	11	0	02. Residence Lines												Exclusive	10	0	0	9	10	0	9	0	0	12	0	0Shared       ......	8	10	0	8	0	0	7	10	0	10	0	03. Auxiliary Lines												Business     ...      ...	10	0	0	9	10	0	9	0	0	13	0	0Residence   ......	9	0	0	8	10	0	8	0	0	12	o.	04. Business Small User												Exclusive	11	0	0	10	10	0	10	0	0	13	0	0Shared       ......	9	10	0	9	0	0	8	10	0	11	0	05. Exchange Lines Con-												nected to PBX Owned												and    Maintained    by												Subscriber												Business												Exclusive	11	5	0	10	15	0	10	5	0	12	0	0Auxiliary	9	5	0	8	15	0	8	5	0	12	0	 note 1. There is a very small number of subscribers connected with exchanges each of whichhas three or less connections. Rentals for such subscribers are being increased by  2 (Business)and  3 (Residence) a year.Note 2. Existing residence rentals include 100 free calls a year, v/orth  1 0*. 10d.; this allowance will be abolished.Note 3. The new tariff increases the allowance for shared service from  1 10s. to  2 butabolishes the following differentials:  London / Four Large Cities / ProvincesAuxiliary LinesBusiness Small UserThe current 50 per cent, surcharge on the first 240 calls a year made by Business Small Usersubscribers will also be abolished.Note 4. The excess mileage rentals for exchange lines exceeding 3 miles (2 in the case ofexchanges to which less than eight subscribers are connected) will be increased from  1 10*. perfurlong per annum for exclusive lines and 15s. per furlong a year for shared lines to  2 and  1respectively.(ft) Private Branch Exchange (PBX) and Extension Rentals1. Private Manual Branch Exchange Rentals. Fixed annual payment for switching and power equipment Capacity not exceeding 2 exchange lines and 4 extensions.........3 exchange lines and 9 extensions.........5 exchange lines and 20 extensions ...      ...15 exchange lines and 50 extensions      ......20 exchange lines and 160 extensions    ......Each section of type CB 9 switchboard     ......Each section of type CB 10 switchboard   ...Each section of type 1A switchboard.........PresentProposed  s. d.	 	s.	d.	r  8	0	0	16	0	0Included in	32	0	0Rental for   -	64	0	0Extensions	100	0	0	100	0	0	L loo	0	015  0  0	100	0	0
2; Private Automatic Branch Exchange Rentals.   Fixedannual payment for switching and power equipment Type No. 1-Capacity not exceeding 30 extensionsCapacity not exceeding 50 extensionsType No. 2-Capacity not exceeding 30 extensions    ......Capacity not exceeding 50 extensions     ......Type No. 3     ...      .........Types other than Nos. 1, 2 and 3 Capacity not exceeding 30 extensionsCapacity not exceeding 50 extensions3. Extension (internal or external) connected to PBXs(manual or automatic)   ...............Present  s. d.1 fI  84 (plus shareY   of rental of  6-per extension).Proposed  s. d.200 0 0280  0   0240 0320   0VariousTo be assessed.f 84 (plus shared. J    of   rental   of I   140   0   0. ]     3 As. to  6 f&quot; 220   0   0per extension). J2 14  0to6   0  02 14  0(c) Connection Charges Note. Where several items of apparatus are ordered at the same time the connection chargeslevied will be the highest connection charge for any item concerned plus 50 per cent, of the connectioncharges for the remaining items.		Present		Proposed				     s.	d.	 	s.	d.1.	Standard exchange line connection charge   .........	3    0	0	5	0	02.	Transfer charge (exchange line)        ............	7	6		15	03.	Plan extensions   .....................	10	0	2-5	0	04.	Each extension other than a plan extension         ......	10	0	2	0	05.	House Exchange System 						&apos; For each multiple station        ............	10	0	5	0	0	For each non-multiple station............	10	0	2	0	0	For each extension between a HES and a PBX	10	0	2	0	06.	*Private Manual Branch Exchange (switching and power						equipment) 						Capacity not exceeding: 						2 exchange lines and 4 extensions  ...      ......	Nil		4	0	0	3 exchange lines and 9 extensions   ..v-     ......	Nil		8	0	0	5 exchange lines and 20 extensions.........	Nil		16	0	0	15 exchange lines and 50 extensions.........	Nil		32	0	0	20 exchange lines and 160 extensions        ......	Nil		50	0	0	Each section of type CB9 switchboard.........	Nil		100	0	0	Each section of type CB10 switchboard.........	Nil		100	0	0	Each section of type 1A switchboard    .........	Nil		100	0	07.	*Private Automatic Branch Exchange No. 1 (switching and						power equipment) 						Capacity not exceeding 30 extensions    .........	Nil		200	0	0	Capacity not exceeding 50 extensions    .........	Nil		280	0	08.	*Private Automatic Branch Exchange No. 2 (switching and						power equipment) 						Capacity not exceeding 30 extensions    .........	Nil		240	0	0	Capacity not exceeding 50 extensions    .........	Nil		320	0	09.	Private Automatic Branch Exchange No. 3 (switching and						power equipment) 						Post Office-owned switching equipment 						For every 50 extensions or part thereof       ......	Nil		180	0	0	For each manual position     ............	Nil		100	0	0	Subscriber-owned switching equipment 						For every 50 extensions or part thereof   ......	Nil		30	0	0	For each manual position     ............	Nil		15	0	0* When a PBX is replaced by one of larger size the connection charge to be levied will normally be 50 per cent, of that for the larger Exchange.
power -15s. per extension( 3 minimum)(d) Internal Removal Charges Note. Where the internal removal of several items is ordered at the same time the internalremoval charges will be the highest charge for any one item, plus 50 per cent, of the removal charges for the remaining items.Present Proposed    s.    d.            s.    d.1.   Exchange line telephone ...............       1    0    0       20    02.   Private Manual Branch Exchange (switching andequipment) Capacity not exceeding: 2 exchange lines and 4 extensions   ...3 exchange lines and 9 extensions   ...5 exchange lines and 20 extensions ...15 exchange lines and 50 extensions ...20 exchange lines and 160 extensionsEach section of type CB9 switchboard ...Each section of type CB10 switchboard ...Each section of type 1A switchboard3.   Private Automatic Branch Exchange No. 1 (switching and power equipment) Capacity not exceeding 30 extensions    ......Capacity not exceeding 50 extensions    ......4.   Private Automatic Branch Exchange No. 2 (switching and power equipment) Capacity not exceeding 30 extensions    .........Capacity not exceeding 50 extensions5.   Private Automatic Branch Exchange (switching and powerequipment) Types other than Nos. 1 and 2: Capacity not exceeding 30 extensionsCapacity not exceeding 50 extensions6.   Private Branch Exchange extension On telephone............On socket     ...............7.   Plan extensions ............8.   Minor miscellaneous apparatus.........2	0	04	0	08	0	016	0	025	0	050	0	050	0	050	0	0100	0	0140	0	0120	0	0160	0	070	0	0110	0	0:::)15    012    0    0per telephoneor socket10s. to 305.From 105. to 305. From  1 to  3(e) Changes in Call ChargesPresent Proposeds. d. 5. d.1. Subscribers&apos; local callsUp to 5 miles......................... 2\ from 5 to 1\ miles..................... 5 6From 1\ to Xl\ miles.................. 1\ 9From 12^ to 15 miles        ...      ............... 10 102. Subscribers&apos; trunk callsFull rate 10-30 p.m. to 6 p.m.15-20 chargeable miles    .................. 10 10Cheap rate 6 p.m. to 10-30 p.m.15-20 chargeable miles    .................. 10         1020-25 chargeable miles    .................. 10         103. Call Office local callsFrom 5 to 1\ miles ... ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 6 8From 1\ to 12  miles .................. 9 10From 12.\ to 15 miles ...............      ... 10 134. Call Office trunk callsFull rate 10-30 p.m. to 6 p.m.15-20 chargeable miles    ...      ............      ...      1   1        1   3Cheap rate 6 p.m. to 10-30 p.m.15-20 chargeable miles    .........      .........      11 1320-25 chargeable miles    ..................      11 13
	Present	ProposedCoin box subscribers&apos; local calls (charge to subscriber)	s.   d.	s. d.From 5 to 7  miles ...      ...............	5l&apos;	7 ;From 1\ to 12^ miles      ...      ...      .........	71	From \2\ to 15 miles       ...............	10i	1 1Coin box subscribers&apos; trunk calls (charge to subscriber)		Full rate 10-30 p.m. to 6 p.m.		15-20 chargeable miles    ...      ...      ^........	1   0	1   2Cheap rate 6 p.m. to 10-30 p.m.		15-20 chargeable miles	1   0	1   220-25 chargeable miles    ...............	1   0	1   2Alarm calls		Ordinary subscriber  ...      ......	5	6Call Office    ...............	6	8Coin box subscriber ...	Si	7Commonwealth  ordinary telegrams(flat rate)Other telegrams and ancillary servicesIII.-OVERSEAS TELEGRAPHS CHARGESPresent ChargesIs. Ad. a wordProposed ChargesIs. lOd. a wordVariousIncreased by about40 per cent.Yield from Increases in Telecommunications ServicesTelephones (a) Exchange Rentals(b) Private Branch Exchange and Extension Rentals(c), (d) Connection and Internal Removal Charges(e) Call Charges (including abolition of free call allowance)Overseas Telegraphs* Plus non-recurrent yield of  1-5 millions (1957-58).Full YearYield  millions1004-0102-0*0-217-2*Annex CIncome, Profit and Loss on Principal Services, Annual Rate for Second Half-Year, 1957-58(Allowing for pay awards, &amp;c, but before tariff changes)service. Postal Inland LettersPostcards ...      ......Printed papers, samples, newspapers  ...Parcels    ...............RegistrationMiscellaneous    ............Overseas Surface and &quot; all up,&quot; letters and postcardsSurcharged air mails    ......Printed papers, samples, newspapersParcelsRegistration and insuranceForces Mail      .........Remittance Services Postal Orders    ............Money Orders   ............Services to other Government DepartmentsTotal    ......Income  MillionsProfit or Loss  Millions58-32-133-023-04-52-8281&apos;;3026-51-827-6178-92-80-33-55-72-10-20-50-24-20-90-50-30-816-4
III,Service	Income	Profit or LossTelephones 	  Millions	  MillionsRentals including PBX&apos;s, extensions, connection and		removal charges	55-1	- 13-6Subscribers&apos; local calls...............	40-0	-2-0Subscribers&apos; inland trunk calls.........      ...	46-6	+ -Q-OCall Offices (including calls)   ............	11-2	- 3-5Inland private wires    ...............	10-5	4-  14Other inland services	5-0	- 6-4Overseas services	4-6	+ 1-3Total    .........	173-0	- 78-Telegraphs 		Ordinary inland telegrams      ............	2-9	- 4-0Inland private wires	3-8    &apos;	4- 1-2Inland Telex     ...      ...............	0-9	4- 0-other inland services	2-5	-  11Overseas services        ...............	8-7	4- 0 1Total     ............	18-8	- -3-annex DSummary of Estimates, 1956-57 to 1958-59(After Tariff Changes)(  Millions)1956-57Cumulative	Postal	Telephone	Telegraph	total income	174-2	163-5	18-3	356-0Expenditure          ...      ..	177-5	164-5	20-3	362-3Surplus         ...	-3-3	-1-0	-2-0	-6-3		1957-58		Income      ...      ...	190-3	183-2	18-9	392-4Expenditure	190-9	178-5	22-2	391-6Surplus	. .   -0-6	4-4-7	-3-3	4-0-8		1958-59		Income	205-2	193-0	19-0	417-expenditure     r   ...1;	199-8	184-4	22-5	406-7Surplus.                ..	4-5-4	4-8-6	-3-5	+ 10-5&quot;&apos; Cumulative Total	.      4-1-5	4-12-3	-8-8	4-5-04-3-5

</content>
</cab>
