<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/88/0 images: 116-118</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
BRITISH TRANSPORT commission memorandum by the Minister of Transport, and Civil aviation the attached memorandum will be considered under item 5 of the Cabinefs agenda for Thursday, 18th July, 1957.Cabinet Office, S.W.1.17th July, 1957
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE property OF HER BRITANNIC MA JEST Y&apos;S GOVERNMENT)confidential.(57) 17018th July, 1957CABINETBRITISH TRANSPORT commission memorandum by the Minister of transport and Civil aviation thought my colleagues would like to have this short note on the&quot;Gethin&quot; case as a background to our discussion in Cabinet.   Mr. Gethinwas previously Deputy Chief Contracts Officer for the Central electricity authority.   In February 1955 he applied, amongst many others, for theposition of Supplies and Production Adviser at the British transport commission and was selected for this post.   In this position, although a responsible officer, he was subordinate to the two Purchasing committees of the Commission which took final decisions on supplies and contractsmatters.   I have no reason to suppose that the Commission foundMr. Gethin behaving improperly in any way but there is no doubt that hecreated a great deal of bad feeling amongst those with whom he worked in the Commission, and it was decided, in April of this year, to dispense with his services.   In the terms of the agreed Press Statement whichwas issued at the time his services were terminated by agreement andhe was, I understand, treated fairly by the Commission for loss of office.   Since then I understand he has been trying to find sponsors forhis case that the Commissions buying policy is inefficient.   I understandthat it is only latterly that he has found support from certain industrialistsand even then I think the Press would have taken little notice had it notbeen for the speech made by Mr. George Strauss in winding up for theOpposition in the recent debate on the Commission reports.2.      Since then the Daily Herald, and thus I presume the Socialist Party,have taken the line that a public enquiry is called for.   This attitudemay well have relation to the fact that the decentralisation of railwaymanagement into a regional pattern, as opposed to the centralisationimposed by the 1947 Act, is proving a great success.   In other words,the policy laid down in the 1953 Act is beginning to pay off.3.     I have felt that it would be wrong for me to become closelyinvolved in an argument between Mr. Gethin and his late employers.   Itis obviously, however, for me and for the Government to be satisfiedbeyond any shadow of a doubt that his allegations are untrue.   I have therefore obtained what evidence I can of his specific allegations - theyhave, of course, been much exaggerated by the Press - and have asked theChairman of the Commission to give me specific and detailed answers tothem.   This the Chairman has promised to do and he has said that theyhave a satisfactory answer to the specific cases raised by Mr. Strauss andothers.   These I understand are all based on allegations made byMr. Gethin.COPY NO.
4.     I have also examined the question of general purchasing policyand here the Commission appear to have a more than adequate defence as they have re-planned the whole of their purchasing policy on soundlines and had indeed implemented it by a plenary meeting of theCommission on 30th May.   It looks, therefore, as if the Commission willbe able to provide me with a fairly complete rebuttal but I realise thatthis may not be enough in view of the wide publicity that has been givento these allegations.   I am, therefore, discussing with the Commissionhow best to present this matter, both in the House of Commons and inthe country.5.     I should like to consult my colleagues about the alternative ways of presenting the Commissions report which should be in my handsshortly.H.W.Ministry of Transport and civil Aviation, W.l.17th July, 1957

</content>
</cab>
