<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/88/0 images: 130-131</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1957The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of ............. .................................................TOP SECRET Copy No.C. (57) 17622nd July, 1957CABINETPENSIONSMemorandum by the Prime minister have been thinking over the pensions problem. Certain points occur to me.2. There can be no new pension scheme (whether on the graduated basis or onany other of the plans which have been under discussion since the Chequersweekend) which although on the Statute book will become effective, as regardseither contributions or benefits, before the General Election. The schemetherefore will at that time be one in posse but not in esse. Everything is in thefuture.3. It follows from this that there is no need to draft every word of a comprehensive Bill for introduction in November; for instead of having one Billwe can easily have two Bills. The first Bill should deal with increasing the benefits to the present old-age pensioners and the necessary contributions. There will be quite an argument about what these should be, and this we must resolve. Thesecond Bill will deal with the drafting of the new scheme. This should beintroduced and passed before the end of the 1958 session.4. As regards the old-age pensions. I would like to propose that we should now state that we will introduce a limited Bill. This announcement might be madein the Debate on Thursday by the Chancellor. &apos;
5. We must also consider whether to decide the amounts and details beforethe recess. There is much to be said for agreeing on the amount before we part,and setting the printing in motion, so that the old people can get their money just before Christmas. (If by any chance anything went wrong there would be an awkward printing bill, but I do not see that it would be worse than the petrolcoupons. I think it is a risk which we could take.) In my view the figure shouldbe lOs. for the single person and 155. for the married couple. I am not persuadedthat it is our duty to increase contributions too scrupulously, partly because thesecond Bill will affect the calculation (as the Lord Privy Seal explained to us) and^  partly because the distant dates are so distant. &quot; One step enough for me.&quot; Anactuary has been described as &quot; a man who is dead on time.&quot; In the long run weshall all be dead, and before some of these calculations mature we may well be a communist society or destroyed by a bomb. So do not let us bother too much aslong as we do not spend too much for the next two or three years.6. The only other question is about the tobacco concession. Of course the correct thing is to abolish it, but I am not at all sure that this is a wise thing to do.It could either be abolished (in which case I think we may have to go to 125.), orbroadened i.e., coupons for tobacco, snuff, or tea. But since there is no duty onmost tea this may be difficult.H. M.10 Downing Street, S.W. 120th July, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
