<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/88/0 images: 191-194</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.(57) 186 COPY NO. U-lst August, 1957CABINETPENSIONSMemorandum by the Chairman of the national insurance CommitteeThe National Insurance Committee have given further considera-tion to the issues raised in the discussion in Cabinet on 29th July(C. C. (57) 58th Conclusions).2.     Our views on the timing of increases in National Insurance benefits and associated increases in war pensions and National Assistance are set out in the annex to this paper.    This time-table depends on firm decisions being taken now on the changes to be made in basic pensionsand contributions.3.     The following is the best advice we can give on the other main issues - namely the increases to be made in basic pensions and contribu-tlons, and the principle and form of a graduated scheme.Increase in basic pensions and contributions4.     We all agree that the National Insurance pension should be increasedby not less than 10s. and that the tobacco concession should at the sametime be abolished.    After carefully considering the arguments for a 12s.rise, we have been impressed by the objections that this would look like a hedge against inflation and would itself be very onerous.    We therefore recommend, subject to individual Ministers reserving their position atthe Cabinet, a 10s. rise.5.     As regards contributions, if the increase in pensions is to be 10s. ,we agree that the level of contributions should be within the range of17s. 6d. to 18s. 4d.    (The appropriate level of contribution, if no additional over-load were to be imposed, would be 16s. 5d.)   At whatpoint within this range the level should be fixed depends on whether a firm decision is taken to introduce a graduated scheme on a basissatisfactory to the Exchequer.    We have considered the possibility of printing two alternative sets of stamps.    But this seems most undesirable.    In the circumstances there is a difficult decision for theExchequer.    The extra burden on the Exchequer in 1958/59 and 1959/60as compared with the present year would be as follows:-1958/59       1959/60        Total  millions      millions     millions10s. rise, 18s. 4d. contribution        35 34 6910s. rise, 17s. 6d. contribution        44 75 119h i
(if a 12s. rise were envisaged, account must be taken of the facts:-(a) the contribution would have to be fixed at 18s. Id.at the minimum;(b) it would be necessary to re-cast the whole of the graduated scheme, which is at present basedon the assumption of a 10si rise.)There is nothing sacrosanct in any particular degree of over-loadin the new rate of contribution.    We recommend that the contribution fora 10s. rise should be such as would envisage a graduated scheme -namely 17s. 6d.Graduated pension scheme.     The Committee found that the question whether contracting out from a graduated scheme should be allowed needed further examination.We all recognise that contracting out is desirable in principle, but manyof us are increasingly impressed by the practical difficulties, and by its serious effects on the finances of the scheme.    The practical benefitof contracting out to the individual contributor would in any event be small; the amount of contribution which would be excused would be approximately as follows:-Man earning  8 a week or less    -   Nil        )   Plus theMan earning  12 a week -   Is. 7d.  )   same fromMan earning  15 a week or more -   2s. lOd.)  employersFrom such consultations as we have had it appears that a graduated scheme without contracting out would not be opposed by the private sector so long as the schemed contributions and benefits were limitedas at present proposed.7.     The Minister of Pensions is of the view that if we are to have a graduated scheme at all, it is essential on grounds both of principle andof practical politics that provision should be made for contracting out.While not himself convinced that there is any need to obtain from theExchequer all the additional revenue contemplated in the scheme asput forward by officials, he points out that any loss of immediaterevenue (which etsuld in any event be offset by a reduction in ultimateliabilities) ^^muM be met by modifications in the scheme, such as not making the proposed reductions in the present level of liability by thelower-paid workers, or by continuing to pay unemployment or sickness benefit on a flat-rate basis, or by bringing the increases in contributionpostulated by the scheme to be made five years hence into effect at once.He has undertaken, after the necessary consultations, to submit detailed proposals for consideration by the National Insurance Committee assoon as possible.8.     We have indicated that a decision in principle should now betaken in favour of the adoption of a graduated scheme, leaving it forfurther consideration whether or not it will be desirable or practicable to include in that scheme provision for contracting out.    If in the event
it is decided to exclude contracting out, consideration should then begiven to the possibility of encouraging the development of pension schemesthrough the private sector by other means.R.A.B.Home Office, S.W.1.1st August, 1957.ANNEXTIME-TABLE FOR NATIONAL INSURANCECHANGES1.      The Minister of Pensions has advised us, on the basis that:-(a) preparatory administrative action involving a riskof leakage of the detailed rates must be deferred until mid-October;(b) the announcement of the Governments detailed proposals on National Insurance and War Pensionsis made on 29th October;(c) Royal Assent for the National Insurance Bill is obtained by 23rd November;the earliest practicable date for putting into payment the increased ratesof War and National Insurance pensions is the week beginning 27th January.Sickness, unemployment and other National Insurance benefits would go up the following week.    The higher rates of contributions would be payable from 3rd February.    Announcements calling in National insurance retirement pension books would be made in the week beginning25th November, i. e. , just after Royal Assent.2.     To fulfil this time-table, a good deal of preparatory work willbe necessary during August, which can however confidently be expectednot to involve any leakage.Some risk of leakage will be incurred from 14th October onwards,at which stage it will be necessary for the Ministry of Pensions and national Insurance to undertake operations involving divulgence of detailed rates to substantial numbers of clerical, printing, and other staff.    Even so, deferment of the start of these operations till14th October will add to the risks of failure to achieve the final datesdue to causes outside our control (such as epidemics or strikes).
3.      Certain other complicating factors are to be noted, as follows:-(a) It is essential that abolition of the tobacco concession should be simultaneous with the introduction of theincreased benefit rates.    We are advised that thenecessary legislative provision can and should beincluded in the National Insurance Bill.(b) There can be no certainty that Royal Assent to theBill can be secured by 23rd November, butprovided the Committee Stage in the House ofCommons has been passed by then, there need beno substantial objection to proceeding with theadministrative arrangements, including calling inpension books in the week beginning 25th November.(c) There would be considerable political advantage in announcing the proposed changes in The Queen&apos;sSpeech on 5th November, as part of a majorreform of pension arrangements, rather than during the carry-over period on 29th October.If this course Were firmly adopted at this stage, itmight be desirable to defer for a week from14th October the start of operations which areliable to lead to leakage, and hence to set back thefinal dates also by a week.    But a decision on thedate of the announcement can be left till nearer the time, leaving the rest of the time-tableunaltered;  if no leakage occurs before 29th October,then the announcement can be made in The Queen&apos;sSpeech.

</content>
</cab>
