<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/88/0 images: 221-222</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.(57) 19024th August, 1957JORDAN:  SUPFLY OF CENTURION TANKSMemorandum by the Minister of State forForeign AffairsThe Jordanians have been trying to persuade the Americans to finance (out of their   10 millions military aid for this year) the purchaseof a regiment of Centurion tanks (48 tanks, plus 6 in reserve) which withtheir spares would have cost about $7^- millions.    The Americans havebeen unwilling to do this but have now, after renewed pleas byKing Hussein, told the Jordanians that they agree to the inclusion of15 Centurions in the list of material to be supplied but of United states military aid.    The estimated cost of 15 tanks at  42,000 each plus15 to 20 per cent for one year&apos;s spares would come to rather more than$2 millions.2.        From our point of view this represents an attractive exportorder.    So far as production is concerned, I understand that, although wehave several other orders for Centurions (including a recent one for86 tanks to be bought by the United States for Holland (66) and Iraq (20),and a Swiss order for 50 from Vickers) the production of an extra 15 by august, 1958 would cause no particular difficulty and would not affectcurrent plans for the run-down of the ordnance factories.3.        It is on the political side that difficulties arise.    If we producethese 15 tanks for the Americans to give to Jordan, the Israelis may renewrequests for Centurions.    Six of these tanks were promised to Israel(who would pay for them, as they always do when purchasing British arms,in sterling) in February, 1955 but almost immediately after it wasdecided as a result of the massive Israel raid on Gaza to cancel our agreement to supply.    This has been a major Israel grouse ever since.4.        The general American intention is to work for the maintenance of jordan*s forces at approximately their present level, and for themaintenance of the United Kingdom as the normal source of supply.They do not appear disposed to consult us about the detailed break-down of the military aid which they are now giving to Jordan.    They areproviding the money, and it is primarily their responsibility to ensurethat its expenditure is on sound lines.    They estimate that givingCenturions even on this reduced scale to Jordan will have a valuableeffect on the morale of the Jordanian Army, a conclusion which we shouldnot dispute and which is important in the light of present circumstances in Syria.    Since the Americans have how, without consulting us, promised15 Centurions to the Jordan Government, the blame for failure to supply will rest squarely on us and, if we were to refuse to provide the tanks,COPY NO. CoCABINET
we should be regarded by the Jordanians in particular and the Arabs ingeneral as sabotaging, probably for sinister pro-Israel reasons, Americanattempts to enable their Arab friends to maintain their defences.    this might well have serious consequences in view of the Syrian situation.5.        I therefore recommend that we should go ahead and providethese 15 tanks for Jordan and that we should determine now what our attitude should be towards consequential requests from Israel for Centurions.Here I feel strongly that we should continue to refuse to sell Centurions to Israel.    If we were to agree to let Israel have Centurions (even if it were only the six promised in 1955) we should lose much if not all of the groundwe have regained in the Arab world since Suez.    Our own action wouldmoreover appear in sharp and unfavourable contrast with that of the americans, who will be supplying Centurions to the Arabs while we shallbe supplying them only to Israel.6.       A decision to supply Jordan with Centurions without any compensa-ting deliveries to Israel could be justified on the following grounds:-(a) The Communist threat to Jordan has increased as a resultof events in Syria.    The Israel Ambassador has already said (quite probably speaking on instructions) that inview of the situation in Syria we ought to do everything possible to bolster up Jordan.    The Israelis are there-fore in a poor position to complain.(b) Jordanfs defences against the Communist threat have beenweakened as a result of the withdrawal of British forces.The armoured regiment at Aqaba was itself equipped with 54 Centurions so, even if the Americans supply 15,there will be 39 Centurions less in Jordan that therewere up to June, 1957.(c) It is important to ensure that the other Arab States arenot tempted to follow the example of Syria and egypt and turn to the Soviet Union for arms.(d) We estimate that Israel has some 350 Sherman tanks fit for operations and has received over 100 light tanksfrom France.    Moreover, she captured plenty ofmilitary material, including about 50 heavy T. 34 tanks,from Egypt.    Her tank position is therefore farsuperior to that of Jordan (who at present has only about 50 old Charioteers) and is still superior to anyother Arab State (e. g. Syria or Egypt).(e) Since it is in any case the United States Government whoare providing the Centurions for Jordan, no questionof &quot;balancing&quot; purely British deliveries arises.R ecommendation7.        I accordingly recommend that we should agree to supply the15 Centurions for Jordan by off-shore purchase, without making anycompensating delivery to Israel.D.O.-G.Foreign Office, S.W.1.23rd August, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
