<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/88/0 images: 223-223</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   September 1957SECRET Copy No.C. (57) 1912nd September, 1957CABINETJORDAN: SUPPLY OF CENTURION TANKSMemorandum by the Minister of State for Foreign affairs on the 27th August (C.C. (57) 63rd Conclusions, Minute 5), the cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (C. (57) 190)regarding a proposal that the United States Government should finance, as partof their military aid programme, the supply of 15 Centurion tanks to Jordan.They authorised me to inform the United States Government that we should be willing to supply 15 Centurion tanks to Jordan on the basis that payment wouldbe made in dollars from their programme of military aid to Jordan. Theyreserved their decision on the question whether this need entail a compensatingsale of British tanks to Israel.2. The Foreign Office have now been informed by Her Majesty&apos;s embassy in Washington that the United States Government have decided to supply insteadUnited States M.47 tanks to Jordan. These tanks are much less powerful thanCenturions and consequently less likely to attract attention. The United StatesGovernment are however intending to supply about 30 to 36 of them as against15 to 18 Centurions.3. This change is regrettable in that it means the loss of a valuable dollarorder and a changeover from British to United States heavy equipment in the jordan Army. On the other hand it relieves Her Majesty&apos;s Government of the dilemma of having to decide whether to make compensating deliveries to Israel.The Jordanian list of requirements to be provided by the United States government still includes some British equipment (heavy guns, armoured personnel carriers,and tank spares and ammunition).4. The suggestion that United States instead of British tanks should besupplied came from King Hussein. It has already been approved by the UnitedStates Government. It would therefore be very difficult for Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment to question the decision even if they wished to do so.Recommendation5. I accordingly recommend that we should take note of the position as setout above, and take no further action.A. N.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,August 30, 1957.52162

</content>
</cab>
