<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/88/0 images: 252-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I.r.a. v/nlntj ti-Jiil &apos;i)i.mil)io Di ,-nnii v] hm, &apos;/i!i:ini&apos;ii &apos; . 7lr.il IrjIiuU r-iij/mini.)-.) t Printed&apos;&apos;f or&apos; the &quot;Cabinet&apos;. ^September-1957 I \\&apos;n\ \ mfiii   i. w .i ii ii iiSECRETJ.11Copy Nq.C. (57) 198 1   ;;&apos;titiiriii:&apos;I \\\\Vi ml to Ii; ill II/if/z September, 1957   ,-...!!i;,-n!i11ml.111 *. 11 /.1 I&quot;   &quot;CABINET. ;&quot;(11 ,&apos;.\v;t vin;&quot;! mil .1 Uj-MINISTERIAL: RESPONSIBILITY FOR UNESCO &apos; AFFAIRS .&apos;lMemorandum by the Minister of education. The 9th General Conference of Unesco held at.New Delhi in November1956 was even more unsatisfactory than earlier conferences. Much time wasgiven to purely political debates and the conference took a very irresponsibledecision to increase the size of the budget.2. A Working Party of officials* has been considering a number of questionssuggested by this experience and has recommended that the direct benefits whichthe United Kingdom can expect to receive from Unesco&apos;s activities are negligible,but that withdrawal would place us at a serious political disadvantage and would therefore be undesirable. They had in mind in particular that withdrawal would prevent us from defending ourselves from political attack, that it would be criticised in the &quot; new&quot; Commonwealth countries, and that none of the &quot; old&quot;Commonwealth countries or of our partners in Nato who in general share our attitude towards Unesco contemplate withdrawal. Withdrawal by the UnitedKingdom would be unpopular with our friends as reducing still further the element of sanity in the organisation.3. The Working Party also recommended that, as the main reasons for continued membership are political, we should base our policy on Unesco matterson our overall political aims in the field of cultural relations; and that the foreign secretary should assume responsibility for Unesco, instead of the Minister ofEducation, subject to proper arrangements for inter-departmental consultation.This would include transfer to the Foreign Office of responsibility for the workof the United Kingdom National Commission for Unesco. This consists of a largenumber of committees, composed mainly of non-official members, constituted togive advice on special Unesco activities such as adult education, youth work,libraries, &amp;c.4. All the Ministers whose departments were represented on the working party have endorsed these recommendations, but in my view the recommendation in regard to transfer of responsibility from the Minister of Education to theForeign Secretary raises issues which should be considered by the Cabinet before it is carried out.5. The chief reasons put forward for the change are that political considerations should be predominant in relation to our Unesco policy, thatUnesco&apos;s programme ranges far outside the normal departmental competence ofthe Ministry of Education in such matters as university education, scientific research, mass communications, &amp;c, and that membership of Unesco can best be regarded as only one aspect of Her Majesty&apos;s Governments cultural relationswith foreign countries. (The cultural aspects of Western European Union andthe Council of Europe and the activities in foreign countries of the British council are the responsibility of the Foreign Office.)6. But if the change is made it will certainly attract a good deal of publicnotice, if only because of the many non-official people involved in the UnitedKingdom National Commission. It is true that many friendly countries, including* From the Foreign Office, Treasury, Commonwealth Relations Office, Colonial Office, Ministryof Education and British Council.52235
the United States, Italy, Germany and France, co-ordinate their policy on Unescoaffairs from their Foreign Offices, but the point that critics in this country will makeis that responsibility for all other United Nations special agencies rests with theMinister directly concerned, e.g., the Minister of Health and the World health organisation.7. It will be easy enough to answer critics of one type by showing that thereis little substance in their idealistic assumptions as to what Unesco is, and wecan also show that our policy is to take the cultural aspects of foreign relationsseriously and to provide the best possible organisation for that purpose. But,whatever we say, the conclusion will be drawn that we expect political considerations to predominate in our handling of Unesco affairs, and my firstreaction to the report of the Working Party was to doubt whether it will be toour ultimate advantage to advertise this.8. Those of my colleagues whom I have consulted do not however sharemy doubts, and I have now agreed with them that I will accept the transfer ofresponsibility provided that the Cabinet endorse the proposal.HMinistry of Education, W. 1,11th September, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
