<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/5/8 images: 98-115</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.W.P. (40) 28SECRETCOPY WOW A RC A B I N E TAIR OPERATIONS AND INTELLIGENCETWENTIETH WEEKLY REPORT BY THE SECRETARY OF STATEFOR AIR.(Previous Report Paper W.P.(40) 19).The accompanying report on Air Operations and intelligence for the week ending midnight 21st January, 1940,is submitted to the War Cabinet.(Sgd. )    KINGSLEY WOOD.Richmond Terrace, S.W.T.22nd January, 1940.

JBCRBTj. COPY NoWEEKLY REPORT (No.SO) ON AIR OPERATIONS AFP INTBLLIGENCEFOR THE WEEK ENDING MIDNIGHT21 ST JANUARY,   1940.Bomber Command.1.       Activity both from British and from French aerodromeshas been much restricted by the weather,  and the operationsundertaken have been carried out without incidents of particular interest.    The offensive patrols over Borkum and Eylt were rendered almost unnecessary by conditions which in themselvesmade it exceptionally difficult for enemy seaplanes to operate.The patrols have been suspended as a result of weather reportsevery night except that of 20th January,  when one aircraft was over enemy bases for one and a quarter hours in thick cloud, and returned safely to England.    A sweep by seventeen bombers overthe Western part of the North Sea was carried through without incident on the same day.2.        Leaflet raids were carried through by five aircraft on the 18th and by two on the 19th,  covering Hamburg,  Bremen,Hanover and Brunswick.    Some slight searchlight activity and anti-aircraft fire was encountered.Fighter Command.3.       After the burst of activity during the previous week there was a return to quieter conditions,  and of the 193patrols flown a large proportion were routine patrols for convoy,  leave-boat and trawler protection.    The only enemy aircraft intercepted was a Heinkel 111 which came some sixmiles inland near Peterhead, flying south,  shortly after mid-day on the 19th, and turned seaward again before reachingAberdeen.    It was overtaken at 20,000 feet,  about 20 miles out^o sea, &quot;by three Spitfires which engaged it until theirammunition was exhausted.    The enemy tooik no evasive action and the return fire from its rear gun was ineffective.    Beforethe action was broken off it was seen that the Heinkel&apos;s/retractable

retractable under-carriage had dropped and that its speed hadbeen considerably reduced, but no definite success is claimed,4.        The attention of our pilots was drawn to this aircraft by its trail of white smoke or vapour,  which was veryconspicuous at a distance,  though it somewhat handicapped the attack at close quarters,    A similar smoke-trail was seen on 18th January by three of our aircraft on trawler protectionduty off the Norfolk coast.    They climbed to 30,000 feet in pursuit and it was then 2,000 feet higher and about a mileahead.      Even then,  no enemy aircraft was actually visible,  andas our aircraft were now 100 miles out to sea and fuel was shor^they were compelled to turn &quot;back without further investigation.5.       Apart from these two incidents one other hostileraid was identified,  off the North East coast,  on the 17th.This raid does not appear to have come within 20 miles of thecoast, and a patrol which was diverted to search for itreturned without success.Coastal Commando6.        The week has been marked mainly- by a substantialrevival of submarine activity,  and aircraft of Coastal Commandhave co-operated in searches off practically every part ofour coasts.7.      . Two attacks were delivered.    The first of these wason 15th January about 120 miles off the Aberdeenshire coast,on a submarine submerged at about 20 feet whose track was clearly visible.    Two 250 lb., bombs were dropped in a dive-bombing attack,  and burst about 25 yards astern and 10 yardsto starboard of the estimated position of the submarine.    Agreasy patch about 40 yards in diameter appeared after the attack, and a number of bubbles were seen approximately overthe submarine, but there was no more specific evidence of damage.

8.        The second attack was delivered on the 21st January.A submarine was sighted at conning-tower depth 60 miles north of Cape Wrath,  almost in the track of an approaching Britishcruiser which it apparently Intended to attack.    The submarinesubmerged at &apos;once when sighted,  and one bomb was dropped about20 yards from it.    The position was then marked and the cruiserwarned by lamp and Verey lights before the aircraft proceeded with its patrol,9;        There have also been considerable special activities in connection with naval operations.    On the 15th January,a patrol was maintained off the Dutch coast between Terschellingand the Maas Light;    and early on the 20th there was a reconnaissance into the Heligoland Bight to report on possibleenemy salvage operations in connection with the three missingBritish submarines.    On this latter occasion one of our aircraft came upon four enemy patrol vessels 15 miles west of Horn&apos;s Reefs, and was challenged by pyrotechnic signals.It came down to within 50 feet of the water and flew betweenthe vessels to inspect them.    One pair of vessels at leastappeared to be armed with one 4&quot; gun forward,  an anti-aircraftgun amidships and some form of smaller gun astern.    Accuratefire was opened from the stern guns with incendiary and tracershells as the aircraft passed astern,  and it then took avoidingaction and climbed to 2,000 feet.    Its first dive-bombing attacks were hampered by a defect in the release mechanism,hut in a second attack four 250 lb., bombs were dropped and fellsome 25 yards from the enemy vessels.    It was impossible toestimate whether damage had been done.    On the 21st Januarythere were further special patrols in connection with a reportof the arrival of the German cruisers &quot;Leipzig&quot; and &quot;Nuremberg&quot;at Borkum for an operation ofl the North Sea.10.       Routine work has continued at high pressure underweather conditions which increased the strain on crews.    Forty-one convoys were escorted,  and two mines were sighted and sunk/by

by machine-gun fire.Royal Air Force Component of the British Expeditionary Force.11.       Continuous fog and snow conditions have madereconnaissance impossible,  and there has been no activityexcept for the usual fighter patrols.    Seventeen patrols^involving forty-six aircraft, were sent out, but enemy activity has been as restricted as our own and no interceptions were made.Overseas Commands.12.        The Mediterranean Command continued to take its partin the work of tr^de protection and eight convoy escorts were provided.    Except for limited air activity in Palestine,  thereis nothing to report from the other Commands.INTELLIGENCE.German activity.13.        German activity has been below normal throughout theweek, and there is little to record beyond the usual forenoonmeteorological reconnaissances, over the North Sea,  which wereregularly maintained.    Only one raider was identified overEngland, there were no further attacks on shipping, and therewere no verified cases of mine-laying.    Some signs of animpending activity appeared on the 18th,  when the number of wireless beacons in service was suddenly doubled, but no majoroperation ensued.14. The following are the latest data for enemy aircraftlosses during the week 7th-14th January, which was that of thesecond series of attacks on shipping:Confirmed: 9.    2 Messerschmitts 1091 M 1101 Dornier 172 Heinkels 1113 unknownPossible: 5.      1 Messerschmitt 110 reported to haveforced landed in Denmark.1 Heinkel 111 attacked off Cromer.

Later reports of a forced-landing in denmark may relate to it.1 unknown aircraft reported to havecrashed off Aldeburgh.15.        Recent reports indicate that the standard methodadopted by German aircraft in attacking small vessels has been to open with machine-gun fire along the length of the ship ifthey had any reason to suspect that the vessel was armed (e.g.if the bridge was protected by sand-bags),  in order to ^provoke a reply.    If none were forthcoming,   the aircraft would then proceed to bombing attacks at a low altitude from abeam.16.        The organisation for the examination of capturedenemy aircraft has now been completed, and the results of thefirst examinations,  in particular of the Heinkel 111 whichwas brought down in the Lammermuirs on 16th October,  1939, arenow available.    The general conclusion drawn from them is that german equipment is well and solidly constructed, with no signsof insufficiency in workmanship or material, but that it is notsuperior to our own and is in some cases considerably heavier.The only item of special interest so far discovered is the self-sealing petrol tank,  which is elaborately contrived andhighly effective against machine-gun fire,  though somewhatheavier than our own designs.    There is no armour-plating inany of the aircraft so far examined.French Activity.17.       Activity was very slight during the earlier part ofthe week, but increased later with improved weather conditions on 19th January, there were five photographic reconnaissancesover the German lines,  and two night flights, which included the dropping of leaflets.    Fighter patrols were also active,  and one enemy fighter was shot down.    The Press reports of a german aircraft brought down by two French fighters after a runningfight over the Channel during this week refer in fact to aHornier 17 which was shot down on 13th January and was includedwithout details in last week&apos;s report./Russo-Finnish

Russo^Finnish War.18.       The week has been one of widespread and continuousraids on nearly every town of any size in Finland.    The raidshave extended to Mariehamn in the Aaland Islands and to Torneawhere the railway line from Ulea crosses the Swedish frontiersOn this latter occasion it is reported that nine bombs were dropped without damage on a small island South of Lulea,  theiron-ore port, which lies some 60 miles inside the Swedishfrontier.    Flights of Soviet planes have also taken place overNorwegian territory on the Finnish frontier in the far North19.        It is impossible to give any estimate of the resultof these raids,  which have had. no very marked material successagainst specific objectives such as railways and factories.    Itis however possibly that they are intended also to counteract theeffect of Finnish victories    on civilian morale and to take allthe advantage possible of the interval before reinforcementsof aircraft can arrive from abroad.20.        Twelve out of the thirty-six Swedish aircraft whichare to accompany the volunteer force have reached Finland, -aridsix of these have been in action on the Salla front.    these have shot down three Russian aircraft,  and bombed communicatioas0but have lost one aircraft in action and have had forced landingswith other two.    The Finns themselves have employed no aircraftNorth of Kajaami,  in the &quot;waistline&quot; area,  and the defencefurther North,  in the Kemijarvi and Petsamo sectors, has beenwithout air support.    The Finns have utilised their older andslower types (Fokkers 0.V,  and C.X.) mainly for night operations^as the Russians are themselves averse from night flying.21.        It is claimed that up to 18th January,  239 Sovietaircraft have been brought down,  and that the wreckage of 205of these had been located.Thg^Ghinese War..22.        In the recent fighting in the South-East of China,Japanese bombing attacks on the Haiphong-Kunming railway played a

a considerable part, and showed a great advance in techniqueon any previous Japanese attacks on railways, which have hitherto been very sporadic.    It is reported that passenger traffic willbe interrupted for a month,  and goods traffic for two months.23,     Russian aircraft and pilots continue to be employedin considerable numbers by the Chinese,  with some success.There are however reports that the attitude cf the Russianpgreornel    has become markedly less friendly and shows somesign of a turn toward sympathy with Japan,




</content>
</cab>
