<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/15/2 images: 16-21</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  February 1941.4TO BE KEPT UMBER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (41) 29.February 10, 1941.POLITICAL AND ECONOMIC RELATIONS WITH BELGIUM.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.NEGOTIATIONS have been in progress with the Belgian Government, in common with the other Allied Governments, for the use of their gold at presentin this country. The Belgian Government are disposed to help, but take the line that if they are to be asked to give up their nest-egg and pool their resources,with us during the war they need some assurance that we are prepared to take similar action in their favour after the war.2. The Belgian Government have asked for certain political assurances,such as the right to participate in the peace negotiations, which present little difficulty and which in substance have already been promised to Belgium. Butthey have also asked that after the war Belgium and her colonies may receive from the United Kingdom the same tariff treatment as Empire countries.3. This request was first put forward by the Belgian Minister for Einancein a letter to the Chancellor of the Exchequer of which the relevant extracts areto be found in Annex I.4. To this letter a reply was sent to the Belgian Government by my predecessor, sympathetic in tone, but non-committal in substance (Annex II). Itwas also intimated to the Belgian Government that economic collaboration couldnot easily be dissociated from political collaboration.5. The Belgian Minister for Foreign Affairs recently left with me amemorandum (Annex III) in which he offered to let us have the use of the goldbelonging to the Belgian National Bank in return for assurances similar to thosewhich had already been asked for by the Finance Minister. He also expressed a desire for close political association with us af ter the war. The political assurancescan in substance be given, but the request for equality of treatment for belgian and Belgian Congo products in the United Kingdom and assistance in obtainingthis equality of treatment from the Dominions presents greater difficulty. It isclear that, whatever the future of the Ottawa Agreements may be, we cannot atthe moment give any undertaking for their modification. Nor can we givepledges now in regard to the methods of economic collaboration after the war.It therefore seems impracticable to give the Belgians more concrete assurancesthan they have already received on this point.   -6. I therefore propose to give the Belgian Minister for Foreign Affairs amemorandum (draft in Annex IV) which in effect repeats in rather differentlanguage what the Belgians have already been told. I should hope that theBelgian Government will be satisfied with the formula now proposed in regardto economic co-operation. If they are not satisfied, it is, I think, for them tosuggest another form of words.[11289]   [22213]
ANNEX I.Extract from Letter from Belgian Minister of Finance to Chancellor of theExchequer, October 16.IN the conversation we had on the 11th October, you suggested that weshould transfer to Great Britain the gold beloging to our Bank of Issue anddeposited in the British Empire, this&apos; gold to be used for the war, i.e., for our common victory.I gave you my immediate and personal reaction : we are in together, for better or for worse. What is ours to-day should be yours to-day. What is yoursto-morrow should be ours to-morrow.I am now giving you the considered opinion of the Belgian Government onthis point. As you will see, it entirely corroborates the one I expressed. As thismatter goes decidedly beyond an immediate financial settlement and is of far-reaching importance, I think it useful to make that opinion quite clear.We called upon Great Britain on the 10th May to fulfil her guarantee, which she admirably and unreservedly did.One month later, speaking in the House of Commons, your Prime minister stated that it was &quot; the unswerving aim of His Majesty&apos;s Government to secure for Belgium the effective restoration of her freedom and independence. We fullyrely upon Great Britain for that as well as for the economic and financialrestoration of our country.As I told you above, you and we are certainly not to be deluded in the futureby mere words, or by pious hopes about the economic reformation of the world.We have got to reform and improve it ourselves. You know that Belgium hasseveral times tried to start an economic understanding in Europe, and failed.We will not try this time to embrace such a vast field. But we would want toobtain in Great Britain, for Belgian and Belgian Congo products, the same treatment as her Dominions and her Colonies, and in the Dominions and Colonies,the same treatment as Great Britain. In other words, we would want the economic community created during the war to be maintained after the war. We would ask them from now on to set aside any discrimination in Great Britain againstthe products of the Belgian Congo.I know that such a decision does not depend on the British Government alone,but we would ask them to support our claim vis-a-vis the Dominions and Colonies.I am not putting forward any political aim. Our policy in international affairs has never been in conflict with that of Great Britain. Our only ambitionis to be in future as immune as possible from savage aggression, and we know that this wish will be strongly shared by your Government. We only want to sitat the table where the peace terms will be discussed.This may seem expressed in a somewhat general way, but I think that atthis juncture it is quite precise enough to avoid any misunderstanding as to ourposition. My Government would be glad to know that His Majesty&apos;s Government-concur with the views set forth.7. It should be added that, even if, legally, we ai*e in a position to vest theBelgian gold in the Custodian of Enemy Property or buy it from him for sterling(which is doubtful), it would be undesirable, in view of the not unreasonableattitude which the Belgians have adopted, to proceed to such a drastic step.A. E.,. Foreign Office, February 10, 1941.
ANNEX II.Extract from Letter from Lord Halifax to Belgian Ambassador, November 22.WE are deeply appreciative of the generous spirit in which M. Gutt&apos;s letteris written and of the determination with which he declares that Belgium willfight on with, all the forces- at her command until victory is assured. We are.indeed, sensible of the contribution which Belgium has already made to theAllied cause, and your Ministers will have seen since their arrival in this countrysomething of the resolution of the British people to prosecute the war untilvictory is won and to do so in the closest co-operation with the Belgian government-ment and the other Allied Governments. We have, in particular, given certainundertakings to the Belgian Congo which have the effect, for practical purposes,of placing the Belgian colonies during the war in a position not less favourable than that of British colonial territories.As for the post-war position, we have, as you no doubt know, given an assurance that, if Belgium stands in need after the war of economic andfinancial assistance, we shall include her in such assistance as it may be in our power to render. More than that, we hope that the close co-operation in theeconomic and political fields which binds us during the war will continue todevelop not only through the negotiations for peace, but in the work of reconstruc-tion and in the better ordering of international life. It is difficult at the present stage to enter upon concrete plans or proposals, but you may rest assured thatHis Majesty&apos;s Government are ready to consider with interest and sympathy any suggestions which the Belgian Government may wish to put concerning Anglo-Belgian collaboration, whether political or economic (and these, of course, cannotbe easily dissociated) now and in the future.ANNEX III.Memorandum left by the Belgian Minister for Foreign Affairs on January 17.(Translation.)His Majesty&apos;s Government have invited the Belgian Government to place at their disposal the gold belonging to the National Bank of Belgium, which isat present in England.The Belgian Government desires to afford Great Britain the maximum aidin the present struggle, and, with the common victory in view, is wholly disposed to lend this gold to His Majesty&apos;s Government.The Belgian Government regards this loan as the most important and themost complete act of collaboration which it has in its power to perform.In taking this measure the Belgian Government joins the destiny of belgium to that of Great Britain not only in war but in peace.In point of fact Belgium, on the morrow of the conclusion of peace, will haveurgent need of this gold both for the restoration of its financial and economic position and to pay for its food supplies. The Belgian Government can onlylend the gold to Great Britain if they are certain that His Majesty&apos;s government intend to pursue, after the war, a policy of close collaboration, of which the loan of the gold belonging to the National Bank of Belgium is an example, and if,as a result of this collaboration, the Government will have at its disposal themeans of payment which it needs.The Belgian Government are, for their part, prepared to undertake this close collaboration with His Majesty&apos;s Government at the conclusion of the war.Above all, they consider that Western Europe will have to be reorganised, so thatits countries can offer effective resistance to German power. The BelgianGovernment are ready to assume the necessary obligations in.this respect. Theyare, however, convinced that such re-organisation can only be effected within the
framework of an economic understanding, and they trust that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment will give them an assurance that in the economic field they will grantequality of treatment for Belgian and Belgian Congo products in the UnitedKingdom and assistance in obtaining such equality of treatment from theDominions.The Belgian Government request that His Majesty&apos;s Government, in thespirit of the declaration made to the House of Commons by Mr. Churchill on the6th June, 1940, will undertake to associate Belgium in the peace negotiations;to guarantee Belgium her colonial possessions; and, as soon as the liberation ofher country is accomplished, to lend her the most complete assistance in therestoration of her financial and economic position and in producing food supplies,more particularly by placing at her disposal the necessary means of payment andtransport.ANNEX IV.Draft Memorandum for the Belgian Government.HIS Majesty&apos;s Government have studied very carefully the Belgianmemorandum of the 17th January, and note with satisfaction that the BelgianGovernment are willing to give His Majesty&apos;s Government the use of their gold.The Belgian Government can at once be assured that it is the desire and theintention of His Majesty&apos;s Government to pursue the closest collaboration withthe Belgian Government, both in the political and economic field after the war;and they ^observe with pleasure that this is also the wish of the Belgian-Government.In particular, His Majesty&apos;s Government will naturally desire the participa-tion of Belgium in the peace negotiations; they intend to do their utmost to main-tain the integrity of Belgium and her colonial possessions; and in so far as may bepossible in the circumstances which prevail at the conclusion of hostilities, they wish to give to the Belgian people, in common with the other Allies, financialand economic assistance in the reconstruction of their country.As for economic relations in the future, His Majesty*s Government are anxious to co-operate as closely as possible with Belgium and her colonies, butthey feel that it is scarcely possible at the present stage of the war to give under-takings in any particular form. While it is not too early to begin considering thevarious ways in which economic co-operation could develop after the war bothamong the Allied countries and between the Allied countries and other countries such as the United States of America, it is not possible to.be dogmatic as to theform which that co-operation could best take. His Majesty&apos;s Government would therefore find it difficult to add substantially to the assurances which havealready been given to the Belgian Government, most lately in Lord Halifax&apos;sletter to the Belgian Ambassador of the 22nd November last.



</content>
</cab>
