<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/21/38 images: 429-434</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS 1 BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT).E C R E T.ff/P.  (42) 58.&quot;2nd FEBRUARY.  1942,COPY NO.&quot;1TAR CABINET.CONSIDERATION - FOR LEASE-LEND AID.Messages from the United States Department of State.(Circulated by direction of. the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs.)Great George-Street, S*W.l.,2nd February, 1942*
A.MESSAG2 FROM . THE DEPARTMENT OF STATS DAT3D9TH DB03MB5R, 1941.The President since the outbreak of war withJapan has emphasized his determination to continue in fullvigor the lend-lease program.    It is of the highestimportance that no factor such as the absence of a Lend-Lease Agreement between the two Governments should operateto cause in Congress any reluctance to furnish the necessaryfunds or cause differentiation &quot;between appropriationsnecessitated by the outbreak of hostilities with Japan andthose needed in the broad view of the war.    It is highlyimportant also that the terms of the agreement should bekept on the broad plane of our draft, and encouragementshould not be given to narrower conceptions which will notredound to both countries&apos; long basic interest.The draft of Article .7 handed to Lord Halifax isgeneral in nature and is obviously of mutual benefit.    Itdefines basically the economic objectives of the twoGovernments and provides for the opening of conversations indetail to reach agreement concerning ways and means ofarriving at these objectives-.    In essence Article 7 charts abroad course and commits the two Governments to co-operatein making headway along that course.   The new pursuance ofthe agreement proposed will be based of course upongoverning economic conditions.    It is difficult to see what-more could be done to meet the difficulties which from theBritish standpoint have been presented.The provision envisaging the participation ofother&apos; nations and the reiteration of the objectives of theAtlantic Charter render the article a declaration ofpurpose around which all peoples of similar mind may rally.The interests of both countries would be served bya speedy agreement.-1-
&apos; B.* &apos;. t -MESSAGE FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF STATEDATED 9fhDECEMBER, 1941.The first sentence of Article 7 is self-explanatory in.its statement of purpose, namely, to find terms that will notburden commerce between the two nations but will ratherpromote mutually advantageous economic relations between themand between other nations.     The balance of the Article givesassurance (1) that the final settlement will be arrived at bynegotiation, and (2) that it will be of such a character thatas a forward step toward world-wide reconstruction othernations can join in it.The Article on the negative side provides that the finalsettlement shall not be an incubus upon relations betweenourselves and the British but will be an instrument forimproving relations mutually and our relations with othercountries.     On the positive side it commences by recognizingthe primary importance of increased economic activity, bothnational and international, in employment, production and theconsumption and exchange of goods.     It is against thisbackground and in conjunction with it that there are added theobjectives of eliminating discriminatory treatment, reducingtariffs and achieving the other objectives of the AtlanticCharter,     Recognition explicitly is given in the Articlethat the liberalization of commercial policy is a questionwhich requires action by all participants and that highstandards of productivity and consumption are required tosucceed in it.V The Article does not lay down self-executingsubstantive provisions but points a broad course and commitsthe two nations to co-operate in making headway along thatcourse.     The Governments will, in collaboration, recognizethe governing^ economic conditions in seeking the best meansaf making the goals attainable.     No attempt whatever is madeto impose a formula which itself will be the touchstone tosolve ail problems, but rather to provide that they shall besolved by agreement and consultation.     It is obvious thatthere will be,a difference in the problems confronting thetwo nations as well as those confronting other nations.     Nouniform solution is imposed by the Article which does providefor common counsel and agreed action rather than the principlethat at the end of the war each nation for itself will attemptto carry out a position.As imparted to us on numerous occasions, Britishpre-occupations with their current and post-war problems,have been prominently in mind in preparing this draft.     Theyhave been met by providing (l) that whatever Is determinedunder Article 7 shall be determined by agreement attained,after the conversations provided for;    (2) that thedeterminations shall be arrived at in the light of governingeconomic conditions so that, for instance, if the removal ofdiscriminations and reduction of trade barriers should befound in fact impractical save by gradual stages, there isnothing in this agreement to prevent adjusting action to suchfindings;    and (3) that the field of questions to beconsidered and included in the final settlement shall not be
limited to questions of commercial policy only, but shallembrace all measures for promoting increased employment,production, consumption and exchange of goods.     Thus there &apos;is no ground for the argument that the conversations proposedand the scope of the final agreement would ignore orprejudice the problems of the British position after the war.The agreement, on the contrary, furnishes the best methodpossible of solving them.The draft is not only moderate in that it confinesitself to a statement of objectives but from the Britishstandpoint the objectives themselves are reasonable.     Werequest from Britain no unilateral commitment but impose onourselves identical obligations.     Nor do we ask Britain tojoin with us in seeking the attainment of objectives, whichwould be beneficial to us but injurious to Britain.     What issought on the contrary is the creation of conditions in theperiod after the war which would operate not merely to ouradvantage but to their advantage and that of all peoples.      Itmight indeed be argued that inasmuch as the prosperity of   .Britain depends to an even larger degree on the condition ofinternational trade than does that of&apos;the United States, theyare even more vitally concerned in the conditions we areseeking.     The objectives which are laid down are those whichare set forth in Point 4 of the Atlantic Declaration, to whichthe Prime Minister undoubtedly subscribed because he consideredthem in the best interests of the British as well as of others.As regards the provision concerning discrimination, allthat we ask is that the British sit down with us to work outthe problems which lie ahead so that we may avoid substitutingtrade warfare in peace time for the present co-operation inwar time.Article V lays down a broad programme about which allliberal forces in both countries cah rally and which caninspire hope for the future of the British, American andother peoples if developed with sufficient vigor.
Ifg. iTUTORS AGE FROM THE DEPAPTMT OV STATE DATED JANUARY 50TH,1942.The preoccupation with urgent military matters andwith the co-ordination of the British and American war effortsin-the spheres&quot;of supply and strategy has prevented until nowfurther progress being made with the interim lend-leaseagreement.     However, the President feels strongly now thatan agreement ought to be concluded without further delay.     Hehopes that the. present draft, modified by. minor- verbal, changesto accord with the existence of a state of war (see firstwhereas clause and article two) will be accepted by the BritishGovernment promptly.      &apos;The President weighed a suggestion that article sevenbe entirely eliminated, but after the most careful considerationhe felt that an agreement with this article left out would notprovide any indication of the general nature of the finalarrangements and therefore would be unsatisfactory to the UnitedStates and would leave the British in a much more difficult anduncertain future economic situation.     The President for thisreason strongly hopes that the present draft will be accepted.The United States Government believes that further attemptsto refine the language of article seven would be time-consuming -and wholly unprofitable.A request has been made of the Department of State tobe prepared about the middle of this week to testify on the statusOf lend-lease agreements before the Appropriations Committeeof the House.       It is most important that the representativeof the Department be in a position to make a definite statementregarding the British negotiations.It is important also that as soon as possible arrangementsbe made relating to the facilities and articles which the British.. Government and the Dominions Governments may furnish the UnitedStates in connection with expeditionary forces, naval forces orotherwise.     Agreements-of this nature will, within the frameworkef the lend-lease agreement, be subsidiary agreements.A certain amount of confusion seems to have been createdby a recent discussion in the press and elsewhere which suggested&quot;that the lend-lease basis of handling these matters as betweenGreat Britain and the- United States has been displaced by a newconcept relating to the pooling of resources, etc.     The?2nfu?i2n appears to arise by failure&apos; to keep in mind clearlythe difference between (a) a policy which will guide the twoGovernments, as allies in the war, in the disposition of theirresources;    and (b) the actual legislative basis and terms ofsettlement for the transfers of materials and services made backand forth between them.      The Lcnd-Lease Act is the only presentlegislation establishing authority in this Government to furnishSJSpSSiKJiS St   * ?0licy o . &quot;Pooling resources&quot;;    and the Act issufficiently flexible to achieve our policy and purpose.      ItiL?S!untlal that\the provisions of this Act be observed and *ag&apos;reements contemplated and required by it be madeprompt JLy.


</content>
</cab>
