<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/17/8 images: 56-65</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  January 1941.SECRET. Copy No. 4W.M. (41)8th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 8 (41).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Cabinet war room, S.W. 1, on Monday, January 20, 194L at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council,The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right HonErnest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and Minister ofNational Service.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right, Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the admiralty.The   Right   Hon.   Sir   archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P.,  Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade (Items 5 and 6).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. H. D. Margesson,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., Minister of Supply (Items 5and 6).The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.Secretariat. &apos;Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.
WAR CABINET 8 (41).Contents.M minute no.                                     Subject. page 1.      Naval, Military and Air Operations........      ....      ....      39Air Operations::   .;&apos; Naval Operations:. Shipping losses. &apos;.Military Operations:Libya.Abyssinia.2.      The Balkans   ............................      39Assistance to Greece.3.      France................      ................      39Relations with the Vichy Government.4.      Chemical Waifare     ....      ........      ....      ....      ....      39;. Precautionary Measures.5.      Man Power     ....      ....      ....................      40Measures to meet Production requirements.6.      War Aims      ............................      41
Naval, Militaryand AirOparations.(previous reference erence:W.M. (41) 7thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.naval operations.Shipping losses.MilitaryOperations.Libya.Abyssinia.1. The Chiefs of Staff gave the following reports in amplification-tion of the information contained in Cabinet War Room Records502-505.A cheerful telegram had been received from the A.O.C., Malta.In the recent heavy air attacks our fighters had brought down about25 enemy aircraft and anti-aircraft guns about 12.The Prime Minister emphasised the importance of maintaining a strong air defence at Malta. Adequate fighter reinforcementsmust be sent. He asked the Chief of the Imperial General staff to ascertain the state of the AA. ammunition reserve.The Chief of the Air Staff undertook to make enquiries as tothe damage suffered by the Hipper class cruiser at Brest.Particulars were given of the damage sustained by Illustriousfrom the dive-bombing attacks on the 10th, 17th and 19th January.During the previous four days we had lost ten ships, three by -boat action, one by mine, two by enemy aircraft and three byraider action.In discussion as to measures to reduce losses the First Lord ofthe Admiralty undertook that statistics should be worked outshowing the losses of stragglers from convoys (a) as included among ships sailing in convoys;(b) as included among ships sailing independently.Preparations for the attack on Tobruk had been delayed owingto sand storms.The Italians were falling back on the Kassala front.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.The Balkans.Assistanceto Greece.(Previous ,Reference:W.M. (41) 7thConclusions,Minute 2.)France.Relations withthe vichy government.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 311thConclusions,Minute 5.)2. The Lord Privy Seal reported the decisions taken by theDefence Committee (Operations) on the 16th January.A record of the discussion is contained in the Secretary&apos;standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.3. The War Cabinet were given the latest information as tothe attitude of the Vichy Government. :,A record of the discussion is contained in the Secretary&apos;standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.Chemical 4.   Discussion took place on the state of readiness of our anti-Warfare, gas preparations.   The following points were made : Precautionary ^ The Minister of Home Security said that civilian gas-Measures, masks had been examined in the previous summer and(Previous found in good condition. The whole question of our reference: anti-gas preparations was being discussed by the CivilW.M. (41) 7th Defence Executive Sub-Committee on the following day.Conclusions, - He would report later to the War Cabinet.Minute 6.) (ii) There had been reports that the Germans were putting newingredients into the filters of their gas-masks.  We had
WAR CABINET 8 (41).Contents.minute no.                                      Subject. page 1.      Naval, Military and Air Operations................      39Air Operations:v.:,&apos;:       .      Naval Operations: -Shipping losses. .Military Operations:Libya.Abyssinia.2.      The Balkans   ............................      39Assistance to Greece.3.      France................      ............      ....      39Relations with the Vichy Government.4.      Chemical Waifare........................      39i. Precautionary Measures.5.      Man Power     ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      40Measures to meet Production requirements.6.      War Aims      ....      ........................      41
Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference erence:W.M. (41) 7thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.naval operations.Shipping losses.MilitaryOperations.Libya.Abyssinia.1. The Chiefs of Staff gave the following reports in amplification-tion of the information contained in Cabinet War Room Records502-505.A cheerful telegram had been received from the A.O.C., Malta.In the recent heavy air attacks our fighters had brought down about25 enemy aircraft and anti-aircraft guns about 12.The Prime Minister emphasised the importance of maintaining a strong air defence at Malta. Adequate fighter reinforcementsmust be sent. He asked the Chief of the Imperial General staff to ascertain the state of the A.A. ammunition reserve.The Chief of the A ir Staff undertook to make enquiries as tothe damage suffered by the Hipper class cruiser at Brest.Particulars were given of the damage sustained by Illustriousfrom the dive-bombing attacks on the 10th, 17th and 19th January.During the previous four days we had lost ten ships, three by -boat action, one by mine, two by enemy aircraft and three byraider action.In discussion as to measures to reduce losses the First Lord ofthe Admiralty undertook that statistics should; be worked outshowing the losses of stragglers from convoys (a) as included among ships sailing in convoys;(5) as included among ships sailing independently.Preparations for the attack on Tobruk had been delayed owingto sand storms.The Italians were falling back on the Kassala front.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.The Balkans.Assistanceto Greece.(Previous ,reference:W.M. (41) 7thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Lord Privy Seal reported the decisions taken by theDefence Committee (Operations) on the 16th January.A record of the discussion is contained in the Secretary&apos;&amp;Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.Franee.Relations withthe vichy government.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 311thConclusions,Minute 5.)3. The War Cabinet were given the latest information as tothe attitude of the Vichy Government.A record of the discussion is contained in the Secretary&apos;standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.chemical warfare.precautionary measures.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 7thConclusions, .Minute 6.)gas4. Discussion took place on the state of readiness of our anti-preparations.   The following points were made: (i) The Minister of Home Security said that civilian gas-masks had been examined in the previous summer and found in good condition. The whole question of ouranti-gas preparations was being discussed by the civil defence Executive Sub-Committee on the following day.He would report later to the War Cabinet.There had been reports that the Germans weiedients into the filters of their(ii)mgiputting newjictn-mctsi&apos;
taken similar steps, but it, would be as well that theCivil Defence Research Committee should look into thematter again. .(iii) If we were to give special publicity to anti-gas precautionsin this country, the enemy might treat this as a pretext for starting gas warfare, on the ground that ourprecautions showed that we meant to use gas ourselves.The suggestion was made that the accounts ofGerman gas preparations might be allowed to becomepublic in the United States of America.The War Cabinet-(1) Took note of the above discussion.(2) Invited the Chiefs of Staff to consider the suggestion in (iii)above.Man-Power. 5.   The War Cabinet had before them a Note by the MinisterMeasures to of Labour and National Service (W.P. (G) (41) 8), covering ameet Production Memorandum on Labour Policy submitted by him to the ProductionRequirements.   Executive.The main features of the scheme were that the Minister ofLabour, after consultation with the Supply Department concerned,might declare the work of any undertaking to be national work;that restrictions were placed on the termination of employment insuch undertakings, subject to appeal to an Industrial Tribunal;that the Minister would use his powers of direction and of registra-tion to the extent that might be necessary to ensure an adequate supply of labour on national work; and that the scheme of reserva-tion from military service should be recast with a view to basingreservation increasingly on the actual work done by each man, aswell as on his age and occupation.The Minister of Labour said that the scheme had been approvedthat day by the Production Executive, subject to amendments to paragraphs 3, 6 (ii) and 10.In discussion, the Minister of Labour said that the proposals in the Paper would be referred to the Advisory Council ofEmployers and Trade Unions. If the scheme was accepted by theWar Cabinet, he proposed to include the main features of it, butnot the details, in the speech he was to make in the House ofCommons on the following day in the Debate on Production.The Minister added, that he would not use his powers under paragraph 6 to assume responsibility for the payment of full wages- to persons compulsorily transferred if found to be incompetent.The Prime Minister said that he favoured the adoption of thisbold and comprehensive scheme: It was clear that in the ensuingmonths we were bound to feel an increasing stringency of labour for munitions production.;;&apos;. T     &apos; The War Cabinet-Approved the scheme set out in the Minister of Labour&apos;s&apos; Memorandum, subject to the following amendments :-(1) The substitution for paragraph 3 of the following:-rThe Minister will use his powers of registration and of direction through National Service officers to whatever extent may be;necessary to ensure anadequate supply of labour on national work. In theexercise of these powers the Minister is authorisedto satisfy himself that the wages and conditionsof work-are-suitable and.that adequate provisionexists for the housing, feeding and transport of the workpeople concerned.
. (2) The insertion of the word &quot;exceptional&quot; before&quot; hardship &quot; in paragraph 6 (ii).(3) The substitution for paragraph 10 of the following : If in regard to any undertaking declared to benational work the Minister is satisfied that the managers are unable or unwilling to make suitable arrangements for personnel management Or work-shop consultation, he may report the matter to theSupply Minister concerned, who may in his discretion either (a) appoint a personnel controllerfor that undertaking with whom shall rest respon-sibility for ail engagements and terminations ofemployment and for such other matters touchingthe welfare of the employees as he may determine;or (b) replace the managers by others; or (c) take such other steps as he thinks fit.War Aims. 6.   In connection with a Question by Mr. Mander, for answer(Previous by the Prime Minister on the following day, the War Cabinet had reference:       a short discussion on War Aims.W.M. (40) 292nd One view put forward was that any statement which confinedConclusions, itself to generalities would not strike home. (In this connectionMinute 8.) it was suggested that the draft statement circulated as W.P. (G)(41) 1, while admirable in many respects, would not, in its present form, impress public opinion.) On the other hand any statement which put forward specific proposals would be bound to give rise to difficulties.Another point of view was that there was a considerabledemand in many sections of opinion for a statement, expressed ingeneral principles, of what we were fighting for. No such statement had been issued by the present Government.It was also pointed out that, on the last occasion when thismatter had been discussed, it had been urged that a statement should be made on behalf of this country before president roosevelt&apos;s Inaugural Speech. The inaugural speech had now beenmade, and there was a good deal to be said for waiting to see how the position developed in the United States. Would the &quot; Lend-Lease Bill&quot; pass into law in the United States within, say, thenext month, and without substantial modification?The Foreign Secretary informed the War Cabinet thatMr. Maynard Keynes was at work on material to rebut the economicand financial aspect of Germany&apos;s propaganda for a new WorldOrder under German domination.The War Cabinet-Invited the Prime Minister to reply to Mr. Mander&apos;question in such a manner as to leave the way open for astatement of our War Aims to be made in general termson behalf of the Government, but without implying thatsuch a statement was likely to be made in the immediatefuture.- Great George Street, S.W.1,January 20, 1941.




</content>
</cab>
