<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/78/9 images: 91-104</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCOPY NOCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 8 MARCH 1984at 10.00 amPRESENTL td The Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MP Prime MinisterHon vi&quot;tesidPi!C0Unt ^itelaw k d6nt ^ the Council^ *  M !        6 for Fore^n Atfairs&lt;e*lthThe Rt Hon Lord Hailsham Lord Chancellorgn and6 Rt 13 Ve,??n Nigel^yy\The Rt Hon Leon Brittan QC MP ^^C\ ecretary of State for the Home Department* RteU0r of8ei Lawson MP   ^e Exchequertate for Northern IrelandI&apos;6 *tHon^ RtGeorjbtate for Scotland6tar7 of s*?e Y unger MP Se;:Hon Patt5rV of ?Ck Je*kin MPthes6c&gt;Plt Hon nO ---L LTe for the Environment* !  MP \ * ate f r Social ServicesThe Rt Secretary{t Hon Sir Keith Joseph MPiry of State for Education and ScienceMichael Heseltine MP f State for DefenceLcholas Edwards MP tate for WalesThe Rt Hon .Win Biffen MP Lord Privy SealThe Rt Hon Norman Te^hit MPSecretary of State//f&quot;ornTrade and IndustryRtni te! n MichCockfieldDuchy of Lancaster 0d* of&apos;r!ael Jopling MPCulture, FisheriesThe Rt Hon Tom King Secretary of State fo}The Rt Hon Peter Rees QC Chief Secretary, TreasuryjymentThe Rt Hon Nicholas Ridley MP Secretary of State for Transport
CONFIDENTIALThPe 8^ohn Wakeham MPSecretary, TreasuryItTHE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTemMr John Gummer MPMinister of State, Department of EmploymentThe Rt Hon Alick Buchanan-Smith MP Minister of State, Department of EnergySECRETARIATSir Robert ArmstrongMr A D S Goodall    (Items 2-4)Mr D F Williamson    (Items 3 and 4)Mr M S Buckley    (Item 5)Mr C J S Brearley    (Items 1 and 5)Mr R Watson    (Item 1)CONTENTSSubjectPARLIAMENTARY AFFACoal Industry:.osuresDefence NORTHERN IRELANDFOREIGN AFFAIRSIran/Iraq Lebanon Angola Gibraltar El SalvadorCOMMUNITY AFFAIRSCo Uy Bud et and United Kingdom   **. ,983 Refunds:   Link  Ub Energy Measures &lt;CPossible Behest by the Coa-ission fox Advene Agriculture EnvironmentEDUCATION IN LONDONiiCONFIDENTIALPage11 122 2 2 3 3
I CONFIDENTIAL1- The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the House of Commons during the following week. HE MINISTER OF STATE, DEPARTMENT OF ENERGY, said that the National \al Board (NCB) had held a meeting earlier in the week with the Lonal Union of Mineworkers (NUM) to discuss the prospects for pitSubsequently an Order had been laid in Parliament providing redundancy terms for miners;    those under 50 years of age able to receive.  1,000 for each year of service.    The NUM was meeting on 8 March to discuss the situation against the vof widespread strikes in Scotland and Yorkshire. The miners were meeting the following day to determine their ~?ion.   There had been some words of caution from the Thire miners&apos;  leader, but the position there and in othercountry was far from clear.    It was possible that industrial action could become widespread, although NUM leadership seemed likely to want to avoid a_pit-head ballot on the issue of a strike.mming up a brief discussion, said that the lly different to that in 1981 when serious eatened as a result of proposals to close NCB should be allowed to handle the matter onstables had been alerted to theing pickets.    She would arrange for aTHE PRIME MINIS ^ position was subst| trouble had last b Pits.   The Chairman as he thought best. possibility,of violenc small group&apos;of MinistersThe Cabinet -ltor developments.Tooknote.The Cabinet considered certain issue Cate for Defence.    The Cabinet&apos;s dis%\ed by the Secretary of is recorded separatelyCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALLuetic2-     THE PRIME MINISTER said that the report of the Dublin &quot;Forum for a New Ireland&quot;, to which it would be necessary for the Government to make a considered response, was not now expected to be published before April.taq8th2The Cabinet -Took note.FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that Iran was PrepVri^ a further offensive against Iraq which was expected within the nfeSJe&amp;w days.    Efforts to promote mediation at the United Nations continui$r/wlth little prospect of success.    Iran&apos;s request for a United KV^ons investigation into the use of chemical weapons by Iraq vas due toXbe considered at an informal meeting of the United Nations Security Council that day.   The United Kingdom would support the request and was taking vigorous action in Tehran and elsewhere torebut Iranian a .weapons had bee registered merch a result of an Ira&apos; in which ships of crew had been serious^ the Government nor ask Office was urgently seekin and was investigating the&apos; ^ Protest to the Iraqi Gover . consultation with the Lord P statement about the incidenttions, which were without foundation,  that chemical lied to Iraq by the United Kingdom.    A British p had been severely damaged and abandoned as attack near the port of Bandar Khomeini, untries had also been damaged.    None of the ured and the owners had neither notifiedofficial help.    The Foreign and Commonwealth ller information from Baghdad and Tehran, position with a view to a formal He would be considering in ,eal the desirability of making a House of Commons that afternoon.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETA^^d that the reconciliation talks between the parties to the LebaS^fdispute were due to resume in Switzerland the&apos;following week, foT  ?g        V^EiS  A -abrogation of the 17 May Agreement.   Th^cease-fire in Beirut was holding better than usual.   Following th&gt;&gt; Soviet Union s veto of the draft French resolution at the United Nations, ^ &quot;tf^ !^ in British ideas for expanding United Nations ojb^ver forces in Beirut.    It seemed likely that both Israeli an^ian forces would remain in the Lebanon for the foreseeable futu talks might result in the formation ofGovera new, moit the reconciliation cdfterent Lebanesenment under Syrian domination.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that there w^  clear indication of the whereabouts of the 17 Britons tak hy the Union for the Total Independence of Angola tUNllA,) 23 February.    There was no confirmation of reports that tne&gt;N taken northwards to Zaire and it seemed likely that they were, forced-marched to a UNITA base in southern Angola.   Nor was it vhat conditions UNITA would seek to impose for their release.CONFIDENTIAL
the Government&apos;s request the International Committee of the Red Cross ClCRC) had met UNITA representatives on 29 February with little result:    the ICRC thought release might take from three to six months. Angolan Ministers had been reminded of their assurance that they would do nothing to endanger the lives of the hostages and of the need to  VX\ensure the security of the British staff remaining in the area concerned, \V Ja        had been visited by Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Angola on ^--^^sFebruary.    Information was also being sought from the authorities v^j\ aire.    Action was being taken through a number of channels to VjPg ess on the leader of UNITA, Dr Savimbi, that the United Kingdom accede to the demands of hostage-takers and that the action wa^da^ging his own cause.    Care had to be taken to avoid becoming invo(&gt;tfedWn negotiation with Dr Savimbi about the release of the nostagj^ j&gt;p, of being drawn into a relationship with him which would attrac^CKe hostility of the Angolan Government.THE ^FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that he had discussed the Political situatiertNin Gibraltar the previous day with the ChiefMinister of Gib Gibraltar, now I and likely to be m handling of the - conk and Sir Joshua Hassa the timing of the rele_ from Ministry of Defenc Gibraltar&apos;s economic diff earliest possible removal shared the British Governmen context of Spain&apos;s accession , was being given to the possibi restrictions might be lifted m Spain and Gibraltar were to agree rights which they must give each oth would not include free movement of W enjoyed an unrestricted right to purch Sir Joshua had also indicated a wish 1feting between the Foreign and CoSir Joshua Hassan.    The Opposition Party in r Bossano, was radical socialist in character itical than its predecessors of the Government&apos;s lisation of the dockyard.    This was proceeding, be raising with Ministry of Defence Ministersa number of important waterfront sites i^tship.    Sir Joshua had also discussed s and the importance of securing the frontier restrictions with Spain. He w that this might best be achieved in the European Community, and consideration an arrangement by which Spanish of Spain&apos;s accession if both jnt reciprocally in advance the rn^the day of accession. This Spanish companies already  operty in Gibraltar. i present at a future bilateralForeign Minister, Senor Moran.&apos;mmonweavth Secretary and the SpanishJHE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thatd accepted an official invitation from the Salv&apos;u ^0send two official observers to the Presidential t   Salvador on 25 March, although they did not expecto3 solve the country&apos;s problems.    The British observe Sir James Swaffield, who had recently retired as Directo^ ^e Greater London Council, and Dr David Browning of 0xfO&gt; The decision to send British observers was less controversy 1982 when the United Kingdom had been the only member of th Community to accept the invitation.   This time there would observers from the Federal Republic of Germany, Belgium andThe Cabinet -Took note.ritish Government Government ns in lections beral of yersity.rlandsCONFIDENTIAL
tfundshi Usin8 Cosi)V.     THE PRIME MINISTER said that in her discussions with the French President, Monsieur Mitterrand, on 5 March she had again emphasised that the United Kingdom would not agree to any increase^ in the Community&apos;s own resources unless there was a revised and fair method of financing the budget.    There had to be a limit on the united Kingdom&apos;s net contribution.    President Mitterrand had indicated that in his view no other member state would accept that the United ^&apos;ngdom&apos;s net contribution should be reduced to the level she had &apos; ested.   .He had said that, if there were no agreement, there was sk that the Community would begin to break up.    She had replied &apos; e responsibility for any failure to agree would rest with other &quot;tates and that she did not expect the Community to break up.binet -ok note,THE FOREIGN AND . United Kingdom&apos;, 1983 budget ref Ministers (Foreigv conciliation meeti 13 March.    It was no&apos; their refunds unlessc al, which was needed as linking the proposed reg a wider energy package. and to accept the coking coa agreement on all the regulat^ 1983 budget refunds to GermanyiONWEALTH SECRETARY said that it was in the erest that all the regulations implementing the ~ puld be agreed, if possible, by the Council of :iairs) on 12 March. &apos; This would allow for arequired, with the European Parliament on however, that the Germans could not get ere also a regulation on aid for cokingegal base.    The United Kingdom had been on coking coal with other elements in now essential to give up this link osal, in order to make possible an cessary for the payment of the e United Kingdom.THE MINISTER OF STATE, DEPARTMENT&lt;e^/E*ERGY, recognised that the United Kingdom&apos;s 1983 refunds (750 million^^net) must take priority and that the proposal on coking coal sho^^herefore be accepted. The coking coal regulation would involve a$W payment of just under _ 1 million ecu a year by the British Ste&amp;r Corporation to the Community and there was some dispute about similar^levy payments which had been made to the Treasury, not to the Community, from 1980.   Acceptance of the coking coal proposal, however, would reduce^e United Kingdom s negotiating leverage in the energy package, an attempt should be made to obtain at the sa^  ne other element in the energy package, namely measures, which would benefit the United Kingdom.^ should also continue to stress the need for action^ and should seek whatever assurances could be obtaine states on this point.THE prime MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said thatv tne priority to be given to obtaining the regulations nec^ Payment of the United Kingdom&apos;s 1983 refunds, the United Ki^ now be ready to accept the proposal on coking coal outside a Package.    At the same time the United Kingdom should try for  n the proposed coal social measures.CONFIDENTIALleast, therefore, an agreement on al social United Kingdom id fuels,other memberiew of for the hould
The Cabinet -2.      Invited the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary to indicate within the Community the United Kingdom&apos;s agreement on the proposed regulation on coking coal and to be guided by the Prime Minister&apos;s summing up of the discussion in relation to coal social measuresCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that the Commission was very funds and might be seeking an advance from member states. ps with Mr Tugendhat, the Commissioner responsible for the th* United Kingdom Permanent Representative had been seeking the Commission not to make a request at this time. If, he latest information, the Commission did make an early an advanced payment, there would be difficulties both of hd timing.    Parliamentary authority would be required.Will3THE MINISTER OF . meeting of the Coconsisted almost ----Presidency and membe Monsieur Rocard, had monetary compensatory amo and to leave other issues however, Monsieur Rocard covering the whole agricult meeting of the Council on 11 very difficult.TURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD reported that the of Ministers (Agriculture) on 5-6 March had of bilateral discussions between the  es.    The Chairman of the Council,isolate the questions of milk and in preparation for the European Council later.    In response to pressure, ^undertaken to produce a document ckage for discussion at the next lefech.    This negotiation would beiton&quot;tentTHE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE ENVI^gMC reported that good results had been achieved at the Council of MiMj^rs (Environment) on 1 March at which the Parliamentary Undersecretary of State, department of the Environment (Mr Waldeg^ve) , had represented the United Kingdom.   A framework directive on the control of air Pollution from industrial plants other than foodprocessing plants _ had been adopted.    This entirely accorded with^jted Kingdom practice, The United Kingdom had also succeeded in redudfagtoding of a new Regulation on certain environmental measures fr^TTp to 13 million ecu.The Cabinet -3.       Took note.CONFIDENTIAL
3-     The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary of State for Education and Science and the Secretary of State for the Environment (C(8A)  10) about education in London.    The Cabinet&apos;s discussion and the conclusions reached are recorded separately.
secretJTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCOPY NO27ARYCABINETLIMITED CIRCULATION ANNEX CC(84) 9th Conclusions, Minute 1 Thursday 8 March 1984 at 10.00 amTHE SEC since th merged in merger had i~ allocation of and it had beenSTATE FOR DEFENCE said that it was now some 20 years e Navy, Army and Air Force departments had been le Ministry of Defence (MOD).    The objectives of the better control of defence policy, improved pes and the rationalisation of service administration sdng^t the time as a first step towards further structural rationalisation.    But the objectives had not so far been uHy achieved, anakpie^e had been a tendency for the old separate Service structures tq^Hpive within the unified MOD framework. This was wasteful of manpower, especially at senior levels, blurred the t-^neS  ^ accountability and made it difficult to get full value for e substantial resources which the Government was devoting to defence, ter careful consideration, therefore, and in consultation with the rime Minister, he had provisional Wlthin the Ministry under whi^%^kly decided on a reorganisationa.     The Chief of the Defei? full authority over the Ch services, who would however c the efficiency and morale of th The Chiefs of Staff Committee wou but its advice to Ministers would CDS, who would be in overall charge(CDS) would be given he three fightingto be responsible for ividual services, inue as at present, nelled through theDefenct&gt;.     There would be a single, unified defence Staff, which would be formed by merging the present single service staffs with the CDS&apos;s own staff and would incorporate senior civilian officials from the Permanent Under Secretary  f State&apos;s organisation so as to produce an agre^^overall view on defence policy and operational issues,o.     Financial control would be centralised in a office of manpower and budget.d. The personnel and logistics functions of the sep services would also be combined into a single organisat^ n.secret
SECRETThis reorganisation would in no sense call into question the separate&amp;identities of the three fighting services, which he continued to believe were of paramount importance to morale and effectiveness. Nor would it affect the legal position of either the Defence Council Jk r.the Service Boards.    Its purpose would be to provide an integrated, ^l^fcTl-service framework within which each individual service could be ? Jjpaged more effectively.The Queen had been informed of the proposals, as had the CDS; but knowledge of them had been confined to the narrowest possible circle and there had as yet been no public speculation about them.    It was for the Cabinet to judge whether they should be proceeded with and if;imetable.   The proposals were bound to attract controversy, an evident danger of leaks occurring if too long an 1 between notifying the proposals to senior staff at Lng them public.    It was important that the Chiefs of ir should be given time to consider the proposals ^iews on them before any public statement was made, right course would be for him to inform the Brtain senior officials at the MOD of the proposals  .ctly personal and confidential basis, with a ^m%jt in the House of Commons on 12 March. Theso on wh and the! interva the MOD a Staff in p and express He believed   Chiefs of Staf that afternoon view to making a s purpose of the state----  ,  w^ ^_^ould be to outline the proposals andemulate a public debate in the light of which he would aim to bring rward detailed recommendations to Cabinet later in the year.Tn discussion there was a general welcome f was agreed would represent an the purposes for which the th1 into a single Ministry of Def revised administrative structur R yal Navy which would continuearrthe United Kingdom. As against , foran8ements would provide a more efan objective assessment of the Unx erests in which due attention would c nsiderations.or the proposals, which it rtant further step towards achieving ice departments had been merged oncern was expressed that the work to the disadvantage of the ucial to the effective defence was thought that the new framework than at present ngdom&apos;s strategic defenceTHE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that the Cabinet orsed the Secretary of State for Defence&apos;s proposals which, if a th should attract widespread support from informed opinion incountry and would make an important contribution to effective9&gt;ion, saresources.management of the United Kingdom&apos;s defence appropriate for the Secretary of State for Defence Ch-iefs of Staff and certain senior officials m conf intent of his proposals that day, and to make a stat^   the House of Commons on 12 March.   If knowledge of t became public before that date, he should make it clear J* making a statement on 12 March, and should take sueSt be available to him to prevent any discuss ion of the matter meantime from being distorted by biassed or cwould be the &gt;f the &gt;out them josals wouldmightSECRET8
SECRET%The Cabinet -Invited the Secretary of State for Defence to proceed in accordance with the Prime Minister&apos;s summing up.SECRETs
HlS D CUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCONFIDENTIAL |^.^Ui^ tm^fcw^.COPY NO9CABINETLIMITED CIRCULATION ANNEX CC(8A) 9th Conclusions, Minute 5ci^&gt;Thursday 8 March 1984 at 10.00 amtv,e Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary of State for Ration i (C(8A) 10)Education and Science and the Secretary of State for the EnvironmentonSECRETARY OF . Jnner London Educel e Greater Londonion in London.FOR EDUCATION AND SCIENCE said that the thority (ILEA) was a special committee&apos; of (GLC).    When the GLC was abolished it would rangements for running education in inner Streamlining the Cities&apos;  (Cmnd. 9063) L     Government had propos_e ^at this should be done through a jointbe. necessary to make London.    In .its WhiteboardCity of Londoncomposed of repres&lt;e^at)i)ves of the inner London boroughs i^  run the service through at.,B ct rate of inner London anc wasHe no&amp;favoured by the great majosupported by a clear maiorit &quot;ember?  r ______ , .iTher  of Parliament and 10 ofdered that it would be preferable ority directly elected by the ing its own rate.   Such a course responses to Cmnd. 9063. It e 12 inner London Conservative ^1^2/&gt;o roughs (including Westminster)be v,     ountability of a directly-ele^eiJ-^ody to the electorate would moreey nd ^uesti n&gt;    Though there was&apos;^w&apos;dQubt that such a body would e       tten than not have a Labour majov &lt;^committed to excessive that QltUre&apos; t^ie existence  f a directlyXelected body would ensureat Sucb times there was an effective Conservative group on the Ijq       Which could formulate and nubliciRe alternstivp tiudcpfs  inrlirafiquestion.    Though there wa! ian not have a Labour ma; the existence of a directl; times there was an effecti&quot; could formulate and publicise alternative budgets indicatingd.    It could be &apos;the?)ILEA would lead to int boards when theLEA would account  eadily rgued that, as notw more realistic spending levels coulc be ach* argued that to provide for direct elections to; requests for direct elections to the single-se vh-ich would run certain services in metropolitan Levant countv councils had been abolished. But for far higher&apos;volumes of expenditure than, and Qi*tinguishable from, those bodies. Secondly a   Erectly-elected body, responsible for a single serv f/oing the need to balance conflicting claims for expen ^ would be unconstrained in pressing for higher spend be within the scope of rate limitation;   and^in iti years, like the joint boards, it   ul* b  &apos;^J^ \ 0 . Uncial and manpower controls.    It would he ^Sirable to 1 pessary statutory provisions in the abolition Paving Bl. produced later in the current Session of Parliament the Government&apos;s decisions in outline forthwith.1CONFIDENTIALand to an
THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE ENVIRONMENT said that he strongly supported the arguments advanced by the Secretary of State for Education and Science.    It was particularly desirable to include Provision in the abolition Paving Bill.    This was a necessary condition tor holding elections in May 1985.   Without such elections it would he necessary to make elaborate transitional arrangements to cover the eriod between May 1985, when the membership of county councils in &apos; ropolitan areas, including London, would be reconstituted_from &apos; esentatives of the borough or district councils, and April 1986,he new statutory bodies to be set up by the main Abolition Bill,  *r&lt;*ssume power.   Drafting the necessary provisions would entail_ e^e^av in the introduction of the abolition Paving Bill.   The aim sho&apos;Mra^g^d.ii be to introduce the Bill before the House of Commons rose &lt;^5&gt;32\e Easter Recess;   but even if that did not prove possible it shouW/W feasible to secure Royal Assent by the end of July. However delay would make it even more essential than on presentPlans to Sv^ke the Committee Stage on the floor of the House.sd*n discussion the following main points were made -a. AlthohfeV course reco potential dartre, inevitably&apos; have It was virtually opponents would c control might often They would claim a opposition to the Gov of their expenditure time to assess the balanere were evident attractions in thein C(84)  10, there were considerable A directly-elected body would authority than an appointed one. in that the Government&apos;s political it most of the time; indeed, with those of extreme opinions, tic mandate for systematic&apos;s policies and to its control Id be desirable to have more advantage.b.     To provide for educati^ a directly-elected body would&lt; aspects of the Government&apos;s run counter to the general appr&lt; the boroughs and districts in met not be easv to defend refusing to for other services, particularly areas..nner London to be run by ;e difficulties for other proposals.    It would /of devolving powers to^ltan areas.    It would ^ke similar arrangements .ic transport, in thoselevy its own : aable to the e newc.     It was essential that the new body rate, with billing separate from the boro\  precepting body would not be sufficiently aqec electorate.    It was not clear, however, whet body would be able to levy different rate pouri different boroughs, which could well have undes consequences;   nor was it clear how any new arraffge would fit into the London rates equalisation schem would in any event need to be extended as a result abolition, as had been pointed out in Cmnd. 9063.d-     It appeared that if elections were held in would be elections for membership of the ILEA as a_special committee of the GLC.    This would be hard to explain; it might also create legal and other difficulties.CONFIDENTIALa
e.     There was a risk that it would not be possible to resolve the necessary technical questions quickly enough to meet the timetable indicated by the Secretary of State for the Environment.    The House of Lords would need to have the Paving Bill early in June if it, and therefore the House of Commons also, was not to be required to sit well into August.f&gt;     Although there were important technical and other uestions which needed to be answered before a final vCision could be taken,  it would be important not to lose i1_t of the fact that the setting up of a directly-elected i to run education in inner London might well be an *ial condition for securing the passage of the abolition ion.    The opposition to the Government&apos;s existing 1 for a joint board was strong and widespread in both of Parliament.g&gt;      Several of the inner London boroughs would prefer to become educ^K&amp;n authorities themselves rather than rely on the ILEA(fov the provision of education.    If the ILEA were a dire! replace it sh1 would be essen a review at an a m inner London.S ;RIME MINISTER, ta  been right, in view offurthSSU6S 3t the present 1ected authority it would be harder to &quot;lat seem desirable at some stage. It make provision in the legislation for late time of educational arrangementsSeerler study.    The Cabinet wthe discussion, said that, although it &apos;ght legislative timetable, to discuss a number of questions required t yet ready to take decisions. The &quot;  ion with officials of thehe Cabinet with a note on the scussion;    this should be iroe their discussion on Thursday en the possibility of making ^\n the abolition Paving Bill,tetary of the Cabinet, in c departments concerned, should pr matters that had been raised in to circulated in time for the Cabinet 15 March.   Meanwhile, in order to kee Provision for direct elections to the u^J^m theth-e Cabinet authorised the Secretary of\ tate for the Environment to arrange for drafting of the necessary precisions to proceed.The Cabinet -1. Took note, with approval, of the Pri, Minister&apos;s summing up of their discussionAgreed to resume their discussion on Thursday 15 March.J-     Instructed the Secretary of the Cabinet, in consultation with the Departments concerned, to circulate a note on the lines described in the Prime Minister&apos;s summing up in preparation for that resumed discussion.cabinet Office 9 March 19,84CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
