<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/184/23 images: 506-509</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(75) 98 COPY NO22 September 1975CABINETCOMPLETION OF THE 1974/5 LEGISLATIVE programme memorandum by the Lord President of the Council andthe Lord Privy SealGENERAL position. Last October we embarked upon a very ambitious legislative programme and by the Summer Recess 57 Bills had been placed upon theStatute Book.    This is a substantial achievement.    The remaining bills which we must get to Royal Assent by the end of the Session, however,include several which are of paramount political or economic importance.This memorandum outlines where matters now stand.2. The meeting between Government and Opposition &quot;Whips in both Housementioned at our discussion on 29 July (CC(75) 38th Conclusions, Minute 1),had the following satisfactory outcome:a. The Opposition agreed that the Lords would sit alone for theweek beginning 22 September.b. The Opposition in the Lords undertook to do their best toensure that the remaining stages in the House of Lords of outstandingBills, including Community Land, were completed in time for the session to end on 7 November.c. The Chief Whip in return entered into a personal understandin(which colleagues will wish to note) that, provided the new Sessionstarted on 12 November, no major Government Bills would beintroduced next Session after Easter unless in an emergency or byagreement.3. The House of Lords have a great deal of business to complete, butwe believe that the official Opposition in the Lords will do their best to keep their side of this bargain, and that it provides a reasonable assurance,though not a guarantee, that those outstanding Bills which we are determined to pass this Session will be through by 7 November.    Problems may,nevertheless, arise in completing the Session&apos;s legislative programme,and these are summarised below.1
DISAGREEMENTS BETWEEN LORDS AND COMMONS4. On a number of our major Bills disagreements between the two houses have arisen, or may arise, which could prove difficult to resolve.Some of the potential differences concern issues where there is no scope for compromise and there could be no question of the Governments givingway.    The three Bills on which the risk of such clashes is greatest are:a. The Trade Union and Labour Relations (Amendment) Bill.Lord Goodman will probably seek to insist on his version of the lords amendments, making the proposed charter on the Presslegally enforceable.    This view is likely to attract majority support in the Lords but will remain unacceptable to the Government.    Theissue may of course be affected by the outcome of the NationalUnion of Journalists ballot which should be known early next month.b. The Housing Finance (Special Provisions) Bill.    It ispossible that, despite the acceptance by the Commons of theremoval of Clause 4, there will be a majority in the Lords for retaining the unacceptable amendments enabling the courts todisqualify and to impose a financial penalty on councillorsresponsible for a surchargeable loss, and removing the option to charge lost rent income to the rates.c. Community Land Bill,    Amendments to be brought forward at Report Stage in the Commons should go a long way to meet someof the Opposition^ major criticisms of the Bill.    But theOpposition have committed themselves publicly to an all-out attackon this Bill, and may decide to pursue damaging - perhapswrecking - amendments in the Lords with a view to frustrating its passage this Session,It is also possible, but less likely, that similar problems will arise on theIndustry Bill, and the Petroleum and Submarine Pipelines Bill.    There isnot thought to be a serious risk of this kind on the Employment ProtectionBill, or the Scottish and Welsh Development Agency Bills.5. There is a reasonable chance that in the event the Lords will drawback from any direct confrontation with the elected House over the fulfilment of our election pledges.    But the Lords are not a body whoseactions can readily be predicted, or controlled.    The agreement with theOpposition relates only to the completion of the remaining Lords stages ofthe outstanding Bills, not to the form in which the Lords pass these Bills.We cannot exclude the possibility that the Lords will insist on unacceptableamendments to one or more Bills, and that we will then have to decide ineach case whether to reintroduce the Bill next Session and to use the parliament Act so as to pass it in a form acceptable to the Government, orto accept the Bill this Session in the form in which it is passed by the lords and to introduce an amending Bill next Session to put right the damage2
THE COMMUNITY LAND bill. There is a special problem on this Bill, which is expected to leavethe Commons on 14 October,,    Committee Stage in the Lords cannot startbefore 21 October and should finish early in the week beginning 27 October,leaving less than two weeks for Report and Third Reading in the Lords,Commons consideration of Lords amendments, and the resolution of any differences between the two Houses.    The Opposition will do their best tokeep to this very tight timetable, though the number of backbenchamendments and the length and number of backbench speeches mightstretch out the Committee Stage.    If, however, the Opposition seek to persist in making unacceptable amendments, the possibility of using - orthreatening to use - the Parliament Act next Session will depend on whenthe present Session ends.    The Parliament Act does not apply to a bill which has not been sent up to the Lords at least a month before the end ofthe Session.    Thus, keeping open the option of using the Act on this bill would mean extending the present Session by at least a week beyond7 November, which would cut into the time available for next Session&apos;programme.E S.privy Council Office22 September 19753


</content>
</cab>
