<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/21/0 images: 23-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PERSONAL 21st June, 1950.

Dear Percivale,

At their meeting on 15th June the Cabinet considered whether, if Field Marshal Smuts died, tributes to his memory should be made in both Houses of Parliament.

As the Field Marshal was still alive, it scarcely seemed decent to record this discussion in the Cabinet minutes. I have, however, made a "No Circulation Record"; and I think you should have a copy of this for reference when the Field Marshal dies, whether this occurs in the nearer or the more distant future. I therefore attach a copy.

I have also sent a copy of the record to Rickett.

Yours ever

(Signed) NORMAN BROOK

Sir Percivale Liesching, K.C.B., K.C.M.G.,

Commonwealth Relations Office.


HP.. KICKEITAt their meeting on 15th June the Cabinet con-sidered whether, if Field Marshal Saiuts died, tributes tohis memory should be made in both Houses of parliament.As the Field Marshal was still alive, itscarcely seemed decent to record this discussion in theCabinet minutes.     I have, however, made a &quot;No CirculationRecord&quot;;   and I think you should have a copy of this for reference when the Field Marshal dias, whether this occursin the nearer or the more distant future.     I thereforeattach a copy.I have also sent a copy of the record to theCommonwealth fuel &amp;tions Office (Liesching).1 21st June. 1950
i\iO CIRCULATION RECORDCM. (50) ^6th conclusions(15th June, 1950 - 10.0 a.m.)FIELD THE PRIME MINISTER said that the latest reports on theMARSHALSMUTS course of Field Marshal Smuts&apos; illness were disquieting;   and hehad been considering whether, if the Field Marshal died, it would be appropriate that tributes to his memory should be made in both houses of Parliament.     The practice in the House of Commons was to paysuch tributes only on the death of Royal Personages, Heads of state,former Prime Ministers or Party Leaders, and Ministers dying while in office.     It was arguable that, on this practice, suchParliamentary statements should not be made on the death ofField Marshal Smuts.     On the other hand, as the Field Marshal was an outstanding contemporary figure, such a mark of respect to hismemory would be welcomed by large numbers of people throughout theCommonwealth, and it could be brought within the recognisedpractice of the House of Commons on the ground that in the first world War he had been a member of the War Cabinet.In discussion the point was made that, if this were doneon the death of Field Marshal Smuts, an awkward precedent might beestablished.     If this were done, and if Dr. Malan should die while still holding office as Prime Minister of South Africa, might it not seem invidious to refrain from paying respect to his memory in thesame way?     Andi if this were justified on the basis that field marshal Smuts had been a member of a War Cabinet, should it not beborne in mind that Mr. R.G. Casey, who was now a member of theAustralian Government, had also been a member of the War Cabinetduring the.Second World War?     It was, however, the general view ofthe Cabinet that public opinion would find no difficulty in drawinga distinction between Field Marshal smuts and either Dr. Malan or
Mr. Casey.     It was also pointed out that Mr. o&amp;sey&apos;s membership of the War Cabinet had been on quite a different basis from thatof Field Marshal Smuts:   in particular, he had not at the time been a member of the Australian Government.The point was also made that much would turn on thegeneral wishes of the House of Commons at the time.     It would be most undesirable for the Prime Minister to find himself in theposition of rejecting a request that Parliament should show thismark of respect to the Field Marshal&apos;s memory.     The cabinet agreed that it must be left to the Prime Minister&apos;s discretion todetermine this question, in the light of such informal soundingsas he might be able to make to ascertain the general feeling inthe House of Commons.     It was the provisional view of &quot;theCabinet that, having regard to the outstanding contribution whichField Marshal Smuts had made to commonwealth affairs and to thefact that he had been a member of the War Cabinet in the first world War, the Prime Minister would be fully justified in proposing that on the occasion of his death tributes to hismemory should be made in both Houses of Parliament by the leadersof the principal political Parties.Cabinet Office, S.W.I.


</content>
</cab>
