<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/208/5 images: 38-44</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALjUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTC(80) 5 COPY NO22 January 1980CABINETSPECIAL EMPLOYMENT MEASURES 1980-81Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Employment1. The programme of special employment measures operated by theDepartment of Employment (DE) and the Manpower Services Commission(MSC) is reviewed annually against the unemployment prospect. Decisionsare now required ox the programme for the year from 1 April 1980. Themain question is the future of the three DE measures on which a range ofoptions is set out in Annex 1.ROLE OF THE MEASURES2. The special employment measures operating this year are listed inAnnex 2.    Their purpose is not merely to reduce the general level ofunemployment but to provide specific help to groups and areas which areparticularly hard-hit by high levels of unemployment - for example byproviding work experience and training courses for the least qualifiedunemployed young people.    The schemes, apart from the now tiny SmallFirms Employment Subsidy (EFES), no longer involve the payment ofemployment subsidies.    The measures cannot solve the unemploymentproblem but they can make a useful contribution at the margin and at anextremely low net Public Sector Borrowing Requirement (PSBR) cost. Theaverage gross cost of the measures per person taken off the unemploymentregister is about  2, 500 a year but the net cost, after allowing for savings inunemployment benefits etc, is only about  1, 000.    In addition some of themeasures attract significant financial support from the European Social Fund.3. The scope of some of the measures was substantially reduced inJune 1979 as part of our 1979-80 expenditure cuts, mainly by concentratingsome of them on the areas of highest unemployment.    This reduced thetarget impact of the measures on registered unemployment in March 1980from about 300, 000 to just over 200, 000.1CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALTHE PROGRAMME IN 1980-814. The MSC have proposed that their Special Temporary EmploymentProgramme and Community Industry (CI) should continue in 1980-81 at theirexisting scale of 12-14, 000 and 6, 000 filled places respectively and that, in theface of a Hkely very sharp increase in youth unemployment, the YouthOpportunities Progr?mme (YOP) should be increased from 82, 000 to100-105, 000 filled places.    I endorse these proposals for the three MSCschemes which can be financed from within the much reduced MSC budget for1980-81 and beyond.5. The main issue for decision is the futur* of the three DE measures -the Job Release Scheme (JRS), the Temporary Short-Time WorkingCompensation Scheme (TSTW) and the SFES.    In my view, with unemploymentexpected to increase sharply over the next year, we should continue thesemeasures in 1980-81 in their present forms which, along with the MSCmeasures, should keep the impact on unemployment of the measures above200, 000 through 1980-81, reaching about 220, 000 by March 1981.    If I had tofind some further reductions in the scope of the special measures, the SFESis the least cost-effective measure and would have a very small impact onunemployment in 1980-81.    I am anxious to avoid any reduction in the scope ofJRS which is a very cost-effective early retirement scheme to open up jobs forthe unemployed, or TSTW which provides a valuable but strictly limitedbreathing space to companies in temporary difficulties and helps to keep teamsof skilled workers together.6. There is one secondary issue and that relates to the taxation of the JRSallowance.    When JRS was extended to 62-year-old men this year ourpredecessors announced that the JRS allowance would become taxable for thefirst time from 1 April 1980.    People have been entering the scheme during1979 with an assurance that the allowance will be grossed up to compensate forthe taxation.    This change would require increased public expenditure of 34 million in 1980-81 and an extra 120 staff to collect the tax at source. Ipropose that we should avoid these extra requirements, which have no effecton the scheme other than to make it more complicated and less attractive, bydeferring taxation of the allowance for one year and reviewing the matter12 months from now.EXPENDITURE AND MANPOWER REQUIREMENTS7. The MSC&apos;s proposals for their measures can be met from within theiroverall budget.    No advance public expenditure provision is made for the DEmeasures, and the Chief Secretary, Treasury, accepted earlier in his paper toCabinet on our expenditure plans that if Cabinet decided to continuemeasures of this kind, the cost would have to be found from the ContingencyReserve.    The costs of continuing the three DE measures for one year isshown in Annex 1 including alternative options for JRS and TSTW.    The totalgross costs of my proposal to continue them in their present forms if the JRS2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALallowance is taxed are estimated as  78 million in 1980-81 and  91 million in1981-82 with substantial but falling costs on JRS in subsequent years.    If myproposal to defer taxation of the JRS allowance for one year is accepted thetotal gross costs would be reduced to  44 million in 1980-81.    Because ofsavings in unemployment benefit etc the net PSBR cost is about one half of theexpenditure required for the measures.8. The Treasury point out that the proposal to extend these measureswould add to public expenditure in 1980-81 and beyond when current effort is tosecure substantial reductions.    As a technical point, if any addition wereagreed now it would appear in the next White Paper as an addition to the DEprogramme.    The question of charging the Contingency Reserve does notarise since all programmes are currently under review.9. The staff required for the continuation of the DE measures if the JRSallowance remains untaxed would be 185 at 1 April 1981 for which there isalready sufficient provision in the existing public expenditure Surveyallocation for DE staff.    One hundred and fifty extra MSC staff on top ofcurrent levels would be required for the proposed expansion of YOP, the costof which can be contained within the existing financial provision foradministration.    Staff requirements for the special measures are whollyoffset by consequential reductions in staff otherwise needed to payunemployment benefit.    There is already provision for the further 120 staff inDE and Inland Revenue which would be required if the JRS allowance is taxed.EUROPEAN COMMUNITY CONSIDERATIONS10. Substantial support from the European Social Fund is obtained for YOP( 38 million in 1979) for CI ( 3| million in 1979) and SFES (about  2 million ifextended in current form).    Extensions of SFES have to be notified to theCommi s sion.TIMING OF ANNOUNCEMENT11. It would be desirable to make an announcement before the end ofJanuary to allow sufficient time for receiving applications and planning theprogrammes to take effect from 1 April 1980 and to notify any proposals onSFES to the Commission.CONCLUSION12. With the prospect of a sharp increase in unemployment over thecoming year and major redundancies in the steel, shipbuilding and otherindustries, in my view we should not make any further reductions in ourspecial employment measures.    The DE Group has already found majorsavings on planned expenditure for 1980-81 of about one-third (over 550 million), and through the special measures we can make an important3CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALcontribution to helping hard-hit groups and areas at a very low cost to theExchequer when savings of unemployment benefit, increased tax and nationalInsurance receipts and support from the European Social Fund are taken intoRecount.13.       I therefore recommend that:i. We should continue the DE special employment measures in1980-81 in their present form and agree to the MSC proposals for theirprogrammes.ii. Taxation of the JRS allowance should not come into effect from1 April 1980 but should be deferred for a year in order to save bothpublic expenditure and staff.J PDepartment of Employment22 January 19804CONFIDENTIAL
  millionSurvey Prices)1.   SHORT-TIME WORKING SCHEME(a) Continue throughout  the country(b) Restrict  to Assisted Areas2. SMALL FIRMS EMPLOYMENT SUBSIDY-    Continue as now3. JOB RELEASE SCHEME1(a) if eligibility ages remainat 59/62 with allowances taxed(b) if eligibility ages changed to59/63 with allowances taxed(c) if eligibility ages  changed to59/6*1 with allowances untaxed 3(d) scheme abolished and allowances tocurrent beneficiaries remain untaxed1980/81261610k219-14-28Notes on JRS:1.  This range of options assumes that paymentsbe taxable as long-term benefits but that paymentsthe pension ages would    be exempted from tax.1981/821591982/831983/8^Effect   of  conti nu i gfpl imeasures onUnemployment RegisterMarch 198111,0007 ,0003 ,0007022-317535-6-61133,000ik ,00010,000under a scheme paying allowances for more than one year wouldunder a  scheme restricted to people within one year of2If taxation of the JRS allowance were deferred for one year as proposed by the Secretary of State forEmployment this figure would be reduced by  3** million to  8 million.If the eligibility age for disabled men were retained at 60 under this option and their allowances taxedthere would be an extra cost of  4 million in  1980-81  and  7 million in  1981/82,   1983/83 and  1983/8*1 andan extra register effect of 3,000.    There would be  similar but lesser amounts if the special provisionfor disabled people were maintained with 59/63 eligibility ages.    The expenditure figures for the 59/62option include the  costs of continuing the  special provision for disabled people.lb   m&amp;      . *  A      1    in  i 
wiNi lib/ANNEX 2OF SPECIAL EMPLOYMENT MEASURESpecial employment measures currently in operation are outlined below,ach scheme DE estimates are given of the gross and net cost per personhe register per annum and of the expected impact on the unemploymentter in March 198O.easures operated by the MSCi) Youth Opportunities Programme:   provides a range of work experiencend training courses for unemployed young people as an alternative tonemployment and to improve their prospects of finding permanent jobs.ost per person off the unemployment register per annum - Gross  1800, Net  950umber off unemployment register March 1980 - 80,000ii) Community Industry:   provides temporary jobs on projects mainly inreas of high unemployment for unemployed young people who are particularlyersonally or socially disadvantaged and are finding it difficult to findnd keep jobs.ost per person off the unemployment register per annum - Gross  2700, Net  1350umber off unemployment register March 1980 - 5,500iii) Special Temporary Employment Programme:   provides temporary jobsn projects for long-term unemployed adults (aged 19-24 unemployed forore than 6 months, aged 25 and over unemployed for more than 12 months)n the Special Development Areas, Development Areas and designated innerity areas.ost per person off the unemployment register per annum - Gross  3^00, Net  1^00umber off unemployment register March 1980 - 12,000easures operated by DEiv) Job Release Scheme:   offers allowances to women aged 59, disabled menged 60 to 6k and men aged 62 to 6k throughout the country provided theyetire from employment and their employers agree to recruit a replacementrom the unemployment register.ost per person off the unemployment register per annum - Gross  2500, Net  900umber off unemployment register March 1980 - 77,000v) Temporary Short-Time Working Compensation Scheme:   designed to encourageployers to adopt short-time working as an alternative to redundancy byffering them compensation for a period not exceeding 6 months for paymentsde to employees on short-time.   The scheme covers the whole country,st per person off the unemployment register per annum - Gross  3700, Net  1100mber off unemployment register March 1980 - 11,000
CC.\riDEh!Ti&apos;AL(vB   Small Firms Employment Subsidy:   designed to encourage the creationofMdditional employment in small firms by providing a subsidy of  20 perweek for six months for each extra job provided in manufacturing firms withless than 200 employees in Special Development Areas and Development Areas.Cose per person off the unemployment register per annum - Gross  5200, Net  1700Nurr|)er off unemployment register March 1980 - 3,000

</content>
</cab>
