<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/50/0 images: 325-326</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property ofHis Britannic Majestyfs Government.)SECRET.IFlERDEiARTMENTAL DIjJOttSSION BgffORB CIRCULATION OP LGiiMORAEDA TO THE \.-AR CABINET.Note by the Minister of Munitions.The Secretary to tho War Cabinet has circulated a papor (G. T. 4434) datod the 4th May urging Departments to settle differences among themselves beforo circulating memoranda to tho War Cabinet.     This has always been done by tho Ministry of Munitions.   Tho only casos where memoranda are circulated to the Cabinet are those in which there is no prospect of obtaining any agreement betv/een Departments.     Since the Ministry of Munitions came into existence the divergence of policy between tho Admiralty and the Labour Department of the Ministry of Munitions has been a fertile causo of difficulty.   The Admiralty, fortified by a War Cabinet decision according them absolute priority and immunity, have steadily declined to assimilate their practice in dilution and substitution to that of tho Ministry of Munitions.   No means exist for carrying tho discussion any further. Quite x&apos;ecently Mr. Barnes suggested a conference on this vory subject between tho Admiralty, the Ministry of Munitions, and the Ministry of Labour; but was unable to get any acceptance from tho Admiralty for his proposal. Meanwhile the War Cabinet themselves decided that the whole question was again to be brought beforo them, and It is in consequence of this decision, to which, I may add, no effect has yet been given, that any memoranda have been circulated by my authority.     No great demands have/
have been made upon the time of the War Cabinet in this connection.   Beyond a quarter of an hourrs discussion a fortnight ago. I do not remombcr any occasion In the last three months when these questions have been discussed.     The ovil, however, has been continuous and progressive, and the paralysis of remedial aotion complete.     In the^e circumstances it is necessary(a) the facts should be laid before the War Cabinet, and(b) that individual Ministers should have an opportunity of placing their views en record.      It would be quite impracticable to rule that ne momr-racdum should be circulated to the War Cabinet without its text having previously boon discussed with other Departments concerned.     The only oeneequenco of such a ruling w^uld be additional friction and delay.(Sgd.) WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.8,5,18

</content>
</cab>
