<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/34/20 images: 142-147</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
to be kept under lock and key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET 66 (S3).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W.1, on Friday, May 7, 1943, at 1 p.m.The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M-P-,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs,The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State, for the- Home Department and Minister ofHome Security.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air, :&apos;:Air Marshal Sir Douglas Evill, Vice-Chief of the Air Staff.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cabogan,- Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Vice-Admiral Sir Henry Moore, Vice-Chief of Naval Staff.Liputenant^Ceneral A- E. Nye, Vice-Chief pf the Imperial General Staff:Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Brigadier L. 0. Hollis.Contents.Minute ,No. Subject. page 1 &apos;   ....   &apos; ....    : .... &apos;   ....     .18/.-1     Rus^p-PblishRelations      ....      ....     .... ....      18$     PeML........ ........ .   .........   .....     18^Qt^faofrtk-. ^J^^interesii8:i!e the Soviet, tTpion.
JE&amp;fpfcy; &apos; 1,   The War Cabinet.again considered the position in Egypt,Constitutional and had before them a telegram from the Commanders-in-Chief,Crisis. Middle East, to the Chiefs of Staff (No. CC. 228.of the 5th May)(Previous as tothe military implicationsxrf the useof force, should this proveReference: necessary.&apos;W.M. (43) 65th The Yice-Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that, if onlyone conclusion .) paSgjve non-co-operation on&apos; the part of the Egyptian army was contemplated, the situation could easily be dealt&apos; with by theConunanders-in-Chief. The only situation which need thereforebe considered was a position in which the.&apos;Egyptian armywasactively hostile and had to he&apos;disarmed.The view of the, . WarK,Cabinet was that this heed not be envisaged as a serious contingency.TbVWlr Cabinet also took the view that paragraph 10 of the telegram from the Commanders-in-Chief did not attach sufficient importance to the serious labour difficulties which we should haveto face if the Wafd Went out of office and became hostile to us:The War Cabinet- .(1) Invited the Secretary of State, for Foreign Affairs to send a telegram to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador confirming theinstructions issued to him in the telegram sent after the&apos; Meeting of the War Cabinet on the 5th May (telegramNo. 767). The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs would add that the War Cabinet wished to be kept informed of the position, and that, if the situationpermitted, they would wish to have an opportunity ofcommenting on the course of action proposed by HisMajesty&apos;s Ambassador before action was taken.(2) Invited the Chiefs of Staff to inform the Commanders-in--    Chief of the above decision.Basso-PolishRelations.(previous reference:W.M. (43) 63rd-Conclusions,Minute 3.)2. The Secretary of State for Foreign- Affairs referred toa further telegram from M. Stalin to the Prime Minister (T. 656/3).This telegram made it clear that, while there was no intention of setting up an alternative Polish Government in Russia, the U.S.S.R.would press strongly that General Sikorski&apos;shauld re-constitute hisGovernment before the breach could be healed. The telegram alsocontained a statement that the Russians had never prevented the families of Polish soldiers from leaving Russia.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he thoughtit would be very difficult for General Sikorski to re-constitute hisGovernment, in view of the attitude taken by the Soviet Govern-ment. He was, therefore, increasingly disturbed about the position.It was suggested in discussion that the statement in M. Stalin&apos;telegram might afford an opportunity for pressing that the families of Polish troops now in Russia should be allowed to leave in the nearfuture.The War Cabinet-^&apos; Took note of these statements.Poland. 3.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theProtection of United States Government and the Canadian Government hadPolish interests . declined to undertake the protection of Polish interests in the Sovietin the Soviet Union&apos;. Australia had been asked, but it was fairly certain that sheUnion. would not see her way to do it. No satisfactory alternative arrahge-(Previous ment was in view.Reference:       .....   The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs said thathe thoughtW.M. (43) 63rd we could not possibly allow-a situation to come about -in which conclusions, &quot;                                                                    ( , 4-1 /.Minute 4.) &apos;&quot;.               &apos;
i Polish interests were hot represented. In the circumstances, hej thought that we should inform General Sikorski that we were willing to undertake the formal representation of Polish interests inI the Soviet Union for the time being; but it should be made clear to General Sikorski that it would be impracticable for us to take any active part in dealing with day-to-day matters while we were engaged in negotiation with the Soviet Government on the broaderissues of the Soviet-Polish dispute. It would also be made clearthat we hoped that before long some other arrangement could bemade for the protection of Polish interests in Russia: He believedthat an. arrangement on these lines would be acceptable toGeneral Sikorski.The War Cabinet- &apos;Authorised the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs toact on the lines proposed at &quot;X.&quot;Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,; May 7, 1943/




</content>
</cab>
