<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/100/0 images: 10-13</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this document is the property of her britannic majesty&apos;s governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1960C. (60) 2 Copy No.:c 3 5f95th January, 1960 1 5 -CABINETCARAVANS AND PLANNING ENFORCEMENTMemorandum by the Minister of Housing and Local Government and minister for Welsh AffairsThe Prime Minister has asked me to submit to the Cabinet my proposals for aBill about caravans.2. The position so far is that the Cabinet agreed (C.C. (59) 54th Conclusions,Minute 5) that a Bill on this subject should be included in this Session&apos;s programme.The Home Affairs Committee have considered my preliminary proposals for legislation. In the light of the Committee&apos;s views, further consultations have been taking place with the interests concerned; and, with the Home Secretary&apos;s approval,instructions have now been given for the drafting of a Bill.3. Sir Arton Wilson&apos;s report on &quot; Caravans as Homes &quot; (Cmnd. 872) shows that about 150,000 people are living in caravans in England and Wales: that, most of the sites leave something to be desired, some being very bad: and that .10,000 caravansare on sites for which no planning permission has been given. In addition, a large and ever increasing number of caravans are used for holidays.4. The existing powers governing the siting of caravans and conditions on the sites have plainly proved ineffective. Representatives both of the local authoritiesand of the caravan interests agree that fresh legislation is urgently needed; and my discussions with our backbenchers indicate that proposals on the lines of those setout in this paper are likely to be acceptable and indeed welcome to our Party.5. Two things are needed-more adequate powers of control, and a more constructive attitude to caravan problems on the part of local authorities.Powers of Control6. The purpose of the legislation will be to tighten up both the planning and the licensing powers. The main points are as follows:  (a) New Sites(i) The question whether a proposed site may be used for caravans should besettled as a planning issue. When this has been settled, it will benecessary for the site operator to obtain from the borough or districtcouncil a licence which will stipulate what must be done to ensureproper equipment and adequate maintenance of the site.(ii) It will be an offence to allow land to be used for caravanning without a licence. The free period allowed under the existing law will go-although there will be exemption from both planning and licensingcontrol for very small numbers camping temporarily.(b) Existing SitesThese are a real problem.  In contrast to the new sites, where authorities must be able to stop unauthorised squatting quickly, the aim here must be to56328
give time for the sites either to be improved, if they are not altogetherunsuitable, or to be run down over a period without causing wholesaleeviction of caravanners with nowhere to go. I contemplate that the totalclearance of any existing site should be possible only through the planningmachinery but this is subject to approval of my proposals in paragraph 10below. There will then be an opportunity for appeal to me in enforcementcases, and my confirmation will be needed where the local planning authorityI $] makes an order requiring the use of a site to be discontinued. In either casetherefore I shall be able to give time for a gradual run-down of a site if satisfactory alternative accommodation is not available. Only if the ultimatepower is in the hands of the Minister can we avoid the risk of further dangerouscrises as at Egham.Positive Attitude by Local Authorities7.   I have in mind the following points:  (a) Planning permission should not be refused for holiday or residentialcaravan sites merely because the authority does not like caravans, butonly where some definite planning objection can be shown against them.(b) Planning permission, where given, should normally be for a fairly long term(10 to 15 years) so that reasonable capital expenditure on facilities and improvements is worthwhile.(c) Local authorities should be given powers to provide caravan sites themselveswhere necessary, and in the last resort to buy land compulsorily forthe purpose if tine local problem can be solved in no other way (althoughthe local authorities have so far been most reluctant to go in for providing sites themselves).(d) Where existing sites are to be discontinued or numbers of caravans reduced,the availability of alternative accommodation or sites must be takeninto account.8. Most of the proposals in paragraph 7 will need a change in the law; butwe shall also need to see a change of heart on the part of some local authorities.Given powers which are really effective to prevent unauthorised caravanning, Ihave reason to believe we can count on this happening.Overcrowding9. At the Home Affairs Committee, the possibility was raised of including some provision in the Bill to prevent overcrowding in caravans. I do not thinkthat we should attempt this. Apart from the difficulty of defining a suitablestandard, no standard could be enforced without the provision of alternative accommodation; and lack of alternative accommodation is, in the majority of cases,the reason why the family is living in a caravan. Some improvement will beachieved if the licensing system encourages responsible management by the siteoperators; and local authorities can in general be relied upon to preventovercrowding on the sites which they manage directly.Planning Enforcement10. The proposals set out above will work only if the machinery for enforcingplanning decisions is improved and speeded up. The weaknesses in the present law have long been evident; they have been criticised in the Courts, and the localauthority associations have pressed for amending legislation. The problem ofdealing with existing caravan sites raises the difficulty in an acute form, and I thinkit essential that this opportunity should be taken to improve the law. My proposals,with which the Lord Chancellor and the Attorney-General are in broad agreement,subject to one or two points which I will discuss with them, are set out in the Annex.In brief, it is proposed to put an end to the position whereby a person served withan enforcement notice can pursue two independent remedies at the same time, and can succeed in staving off action against him for months, sometimes years; andto replace these with a direct right of appeal to the Minister against an enforcementnotice. This would involve taking away a right of appeal to the magistrates&apos; court,but provision would be made whereby a question of law could be taken to theHigh Court.
Scotland11. I understand from the Secretary of State for Scotland that, whilelegislation on the subject of caravans is not immediately required for Scotland hewould not like at this stage finally to exclude the possible application to Scotlandof the proposed Bill, at least in part. His consultations with Scottish localauthorities are on the point of completion, and he expects to reach a firm view onthis question before drafting of the Bill has to begin.Conclusion12. I hope that my colleagues will agree that the Bill should include provisionsimproving the machinery of planning enforcement; and I hope that I may be given authority to announce that the Government intend to introduce during the present session legislation on the subject of caravans and planning enforcement. until we definitely announce our intention to legislate, we shall not get the co-operationof the local authorities which we badly need if further evictions of caravannersare to be avoided.H. B.Ministry of Housing and Local Government, S.W.I,4th January, 1960.
ANNEXPLANNING ENFORCEMENTAt present, under section 23 of the Town and Country Planning Act, 1947,the first step is for the local planning authority to serve an enforcement noticespecifying the nature of the contravention and the steps required to put mattersright.   The notice cannot take effect for at least 28 days.2. During this time, a developer has two concurrent remedies. In the firstplace, he may apply to the local planning authority for planning permission (eventhough he has previously applied and has been refused); and if his application isturned down he then has a further month in which to appeal to the Minister, and can insist on a hearing. The enforcement notice is postponed until his appeal is decided. In the second place, the developer may also appeal within the 28 days to a magistrates&apos; court against the validity of the enforcement notice; and then hecan appeal against their decision to quarter sessions. The provisions for recourse to a petty sessional court were presumably meant to give an opportunity for legalissues to be dealt with summarily before the notice came into operation, butexperience has shown that the powers of the courts were not closely enoughdefined.3. It is quite possible for a developer to stave off enforcement action forseveral months, even in the case where a development is harmful to the community and should never have taken place. If a development is moveable or easilydismantled, the developer can virtually afford to ignore planning control. He getsthe use of his new development for a long period of time, and when the law finallycloses in, he can move his development [e.g., a caravan) and start again somewhereelse.4. The proposal is to eliminate the duplicate procedure in section 23; and to eliminate also the provision about applying to the local planning authority for planning permission on receipt of an enforcement notice.5. It is proposed, instead, that there should simply be a direct right of appealto the Minister against an enforcement notice, both on the merits of the development(that is, on the issue whether or not planning permission should be granted) andalso on questions of law or fact arising on the notice.6. The questions of law which might in this way come to the Minister on anappeal against an enforcement notice would be like those which he already hasjurisdiction to decide under section 17 of the 1947 Act. Section 32 of the Townand Country Planning Act, 1959, now provides that any party dissatisfied on apoint of law with a decision taken by the Minister under section 17 may appeal tothe High Court or require the Minister to state a case for the opinion of the HighCourt; and it is proposed that there should be a similar remedy in respect of adecision taken on an appeal against an enforcement notice. In addition, it isproposed that the Minister should be given a discretion to refer a legal issue to theHigh Court without his first having to come to a conclusion on. that issue or onthe appeal himself.7. These proposals involve taking away a right of appeal to the magistrates&apos;courts; but it is difficult to believe that any bench of magistrates would regret theloss of this jurisdiction, since the questions which it throws up are not veryappropriate for those whose main work lies in the administration of the criminal law. It seems preferable that opportunity should be provided for any questions oflaw that arise to be determined by the High Court.January 1960.

</content>
</cab>
