<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/100/0 images: 21-22</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this document is the property of her britannic majesty&apos;s governmentPrinted for the Cabinet. January I960C. (60) 5 Copy No.      5 214th January, I960CABINETTHE IMPERIAL AND NATIONAL SERVICES GRANT TO THEMETROPOLITAN POLICEMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home department on 23rd July, 1959, I circulated a paper (C. (59) 119) to Cabinet in which I proposed that the special annual payment to the Metropolitan Police Fund in respectof the imperial and national services which are carried out by the MetropolitanPolice should be increased from the  100,000 at which it was fixed in 1909 to 475,000, at an annual cost to the Exchequer of  187,500. The Chancellor of theExchequer circulated a paper (C. (59) 140) in which he outlined the case againstincreasing the grant. At our meeting on 28th July we decided that the matter shouldbe left over until a later meeting (C.C. (59) 47th Conclusions, Minute 6).2. Since July this matter has been further considered by the Home Office andthe Treasury, but it has not been possible to reach agreement and I am now bringing the point before the Cabinet again. An early decision is required since we haveto settle the provision to be made in the estimates for 1960-61.3. I see no proper way of avoiding an increase in this special grant. TheMetropolitan local authorities have been pressing for an increase, and their case isas simple as it is convincing. The Government undertook in .1910 to pay for these services. The cost was then estimated at  100,000, and is now about  760,000. Thelocal authorities agree to a narrower definition of &quot; imperial and national &quot;, whichreduces the cost to  475,000. The services covered by this definition are theprotection of members of the Royal Family and of the Government and foreigndignitaries and embassies; the internal protection of Royal residences, both inLondon and elsewhere; the additional cost of the regulation of traffic nearParliament when the Houses are sitting; the protection of Government buildings;and part of the cost of the Special Branch. The Metropolitan ratepayer cannot beexpected to pay for these services; and the view of the local authorities is likely towin general support if the matter is raised in Parliament. I understand that it islikely to be raised if the grant is not increased for 1960-61.4.  The Chancellor of the Exchequer opposes any increase in this grant:  (a) because he considers it to be an anomaly, which would not be paid at all ifwe were dealing with the situation de novo;I am not, however, able to deal with the situation de novo, and Iam on weak ground in trying to maintain the grant at the level fixed50 years ago.(b) because he considers that the Metropolitan ratepayer gains more fromthe fact that London is the Metropolis than the cost of these services.Argument on this point is bound to be somewhat speculative, butthere may be some misunderstanding. The cost of the imperial and national services is a substantial item, but it is by no means the greaterpart of the additional cost of policing that falls on the London ratepayerbecause London is the Metropolis. Because London is the Metropolisit has special and complex police problems which it would not otherwise56385secret:
have, and this is reflected in the fact that it has a larger establishment ofpolice in relation to population than anywhere else except Liverpool.(The establishment would be greater in proportion to population thanLiverpool^ if: more men could be recruited in London.) Any conclusion on this point can only be speculative, but my impression is that theadditional cost of policing London which arises because it is the: . o Metropolis is very substantial indeed, and that this off-sets the fact that-\ there are higher rateable values in certain parts of the MetropolitanPolice District because London is the Metropolis.5. I seek the support of my colleagues for an increase in this grant to 475,000 a year.R. A. B.Home Office, S.W. 1,13th January, 1960.

</content>
</cab>
