<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/100/0 images: 45-58</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYGOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1960C. (60) 12 Copy No.      g 31st. February, 1960CABINETCHANNEL tunnel memorandum by the Minister of TransportOfficials think the Tunnel would be to the Advantage of United Kingdom trade on 23rd July the Cabinet asked that officials should examine the problems raised by the tunnel project (C.C. (59) 45th Conclusions, Minute 6). their conclusions are summarised in paragraph 32 of their repont (annexed). Broadly,these are that the tunnel would have advantages for United Kingdom trade; itwould be advantageous to motorists and would fit in with our motorway policy.Its effect on the ports of Dover, Folkestone and Newhaven would be serious, buton balance this would need to be accepted. The tunnel should be privately financed.2. The report shows that there are no overriding abjections to the project.If it proves to be a commercial proposition there would be considerable politicaland economic advantages. But a final assessment cannot be made until theInternational Study Group has completed its report, probably in February. I am now seeking the views of industry. The officials&apos; report covers all aspects except the political one, on which I understand that the Foreign Secretary will be circulating a separate memorandum.We can say we will look Sympathetically at a Feasible Scheme3. Meanwhile I must reply to Sir Ivone Kirkpatrick, the co-Chairman of theInternational Study Group, who asks me what the Governments attitude is likelyto be. He says the French Government are not opposed in principle to theformation of an international channel tunnel company. They are reserving their position in regard to any agreement which might be reached for the exploitation of the tunnel. There might be advantages if the United Kingdom&apos;s reply to the consortium (which should probably be shown to the French Government in advance)could be in slightly warmer terms than the French reply. I suggest that if mycolleagues accept the conclusions of the report of officials, Sir Ivone Kirkpatrickmight be told that the Government is prepared to look sympathetically at the project, if the International Study Group produce a feasible and commercially viablescheme capable of attracting the necessary capital. I understand that the foreign secretary in his memorandum will be bringing out the importance of the timing of any statement of the Governments attitude so as to obtain the maximumadvantage from it. I will let the British Transport Commission know theGovernment^ attitude, and will continue to keep in touch with the InternationalStudy Group.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY *$ GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1960C. (60) 12 Copy No.      g 31st. February, 1960CABINETCHANNEL tunnel memorandum by the Minister of TransportOfficials think the Tunnel would be to the Advantage of United Kingdom trade on 23rd July the Cabinet asked that officials should examine the problems raised by the tunnel project (C.C. (59) 45th Conclusions, Minute 6). their conclusions are summarised in paragraph 32 of their repont (annexed). Broadly,these are that the tunnel would have advantages for United Kingdom trade; itwould be advantageous to motorists and would fit in with our motorway policy.Its effect on the ports of Dover, Folkestone and Newhaven would be serious, buton balance this would need to be accepted. The tunnel should be privately financed.2. The report shows that there are no overriding abjections to the project.If it proves to be a coimmeroial proposition there would be considerable politicaland economic advantages. But a final assessment cannot be made until theInternational Study Group has completed its report, probably in February. I am now seeking the views of industry. The officials&apos; report covers all aspects except the political one, on which I understand that the Foreign Secretary will be circulating a separate memorandum.We can say we will look Sympathetically at a Feasible Scheme3. Meanwhile I must reply to Sir Ivone Kirkpatrick, the co-Chairman of theInternational Study Group, who asks me what the Governments attitude is likelyto be. He says the French Government are not opposed in principle to theformation of an international channel tunnel company. They are reserving their position in regard to any agreement which might be reached for the exploitation of the tunnel. There might be advantages if the United Kingdom&apos;s reply to the consortium (which should probably be shown to the French Government in advance)could be in slightly warmer terms than the French reply. I suggest that if mycolleagues accept the conclusions of the report of officials, Sir Ivone Kirkpatrickmight be told that the Government is prepared to look sympathetically at the project, if the International Study Group produce a feasible and commercially viablescheme capable of attracting the necessary capital. I understand that the foreign secretary in his memorandum will be bringing out the importance of the timing of any statement of the Governments attitude so as to obtain the maximumadvantage from it. I will let the British Transport Commission know theGovernment^ attitude, and will continue to keep in touch with the InternationalStudy Group.
Summary4.   I invite my colleagues:  (i) To note the present position of this project.(ii) To endorse the findings in the official report summarised in paragraphs 1and 2 above.(iii) To approve the lines on which a reply might be sent to the InternationalStudy Group about the attitude of Her Majesty&apos;s Government as suggested in paragraph 3 above.(iv) To note that I will report further when the International Study Group has completed its report, probably during February.E. M.Ministry of Transport, W. 1,29 th January, 1960.
ANNEXCHANNEL TUNNELReport by Officials on Certain Questions Raised by the Tunnel ProjectIntroductionThe Minister of Transport submitted to the Cabinet in July a memorandumstating the current position on the Channel Tunnel Project (C. (59) 123) and theCabinet asked that officials of the departments concerned should study certain of theeconomic, political, defence, finance and administrative problems to which theMinisters memorandum referred.The Study2. Officials from the Treasury, Foreign Office, Board of Trade, Ministry ofDefence and Ministry of Transport and Civil Aviation (as it then was) have accordingly examined these questions. It has not been possible to make a full examination, partly because the International Study Group which is preparing the scheme has not yet completed its work, and has not yet decided on firm proposals on some of the points in question, and partly because the time availablefor the examination is limited. The conclusions set out below must therefore beregarded as provisional, and reached in the light of the incomplete information at present available. Information as to the projected tunnel and its performancehas come indirectly from the International Study Group, and is summarised inparagraphs 3 to 8 below.Description of the Project3. It would consist of two tunnels, each of about 23 ft. diameter and equipped with an electrified railway. The railway would be connected with British andFrench railways on each side, but would also have specialised rolling stock running incircuit in the tunnel to carry road vehicles, principally private cars. Most of the expected traffic would be accompanied private cars and passengers, but about one-third would be freight. Motorists would be able to use the tunnel withoutadvance booking. Trains would run at high speeds (up to 70 m.p.h.) and at peakscould be at five-minute intervals, catering for 1,000 cars an hour initially. Withthe approaches at either end, the total length of tunnel would be about 40 miles.The United Kingdom terminal will be in the Folkestone area, and the Frenchbetween Calais and Boulogne. Extensive railway terminals will be required at both ends, as well as road approaches. The tunnel would take about five years to build. Its cost, with the terminals, is tentatively estimated to be not muchmore than about  100 millions.4. It is estimated its net revenue before meeting capital charges would beabout  12-5 millions a year, soon after its opening, assuming this was not longafter 1965. This would be divided as to  5 million from passengers,  5 millions from accompanied cars, and  2^ millions from freight.5. The level of passenger fares is assumed to be about equivalent to the presentsea crossing rates, or a little below. For cars, the rates would be cheaper than thepresent sea rates.6. Much of the traffic would be newly generated by the tunnel, particularly the cars, where 80 per cent, might be fresh traffic. All the short-sea passengers-(from Dover, Folkestone and Newhaven) and most of the Harwich and southampton passengers would use the tunnel, and one-third of the air passengerswould be diverted. All the short-sea car traffic, and 50 per cent, of the air cartraffic over similar routes, would be diverted.7. For freight, the catchment area would be West Germany, Belgium,Luxembourg, the Netherlands, France, Switzerland, Austria and Italy.   TotalSECRET56453 B 2
freight traffic between the United Kingdom and this area the International study group estimate at about 10-J- million tons a year. About one-third of this wouldby its nature be capable of tunnel transit, and about one-third of this third wouldbe likely to be diverted to the tunnel at optimum rates, Le., rates which wouldmaximise receipts. The resultant tonnage might be 1^ millions a year, and the biggest single item would be food, mainly fruit and vegetables (380,000 tons).Other traffics would be, e.g., chemicals, glass, machinery and mails.8. Freight rates will be quoted as through-rail rates and will be very flexible.They will cover the cost of moving the tonnage through the tunnel, but, subject tothis limit, will be designed to be competitive with through-road rates, and withcomparable sea liner rates. In other words, they should generally show areduction on existing charges, and will be cheaper than the existing train ferry rates.They will not be attractive for bulk traffics and the tunnel is not expected to handleany coal. The theoretical capacity of the tunnel to handle freight would be verymuch higher than the tonnages quoted above, but the limiting factors will be the classes of traffic which can be attracted to the tunnel at rates which will pay itsoperators.Economic Effects9. Since the tunnel would primarily cater for cars and tourists, it might, sofar as balance of payments is concerned, be considered to work to the disadvantage of the United Kingdom because more British than foreign motorists would use thetunnel. But it seems likely that the facilities for a through land journey providedby a tunnel, without the need to book passages in advance, would operate on the potential travelling public in Europe (which is larger than in the United Kingdom),so that the balance of advantage might be slightly in favour of the United Kingdom.The arguments are set out in detail in Appendix A. A tunnel would therefore be unlikely to increase our adverse tourist balance, and might improve it slightly.10. The tonnages of freight suggested by the International Study Group are considerably in excess of the present level of train ferry freight, and might be about one-fifth of the general-cargo type of traffic between the United Kingdom and the assumed catchment area. It might well be that the psychological impact of thenew and easier facility would in fact attract or generate a higher tonnage than theInternational Study Group suggest. Consideration was given to the possibility that this increased ease of transit might increase the flow of imports which aresensitive politically, such as agricultural products and particular horticulturalproducts. The Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food were consulted. Intheir view food and other agricultural products might be more affected thanindustry in general by easier handling, but on the other hand existing facilities are adequate to carry the trade, and the volume of traffic from some of our principalEuropean suppliers, for example, Denmark and Holland, should be little affected.The tunnel might well be used for horticultural products from France and Italy,but even for these the effect on the general flow of traffic should be small. It doesnot seem that this difficulty need be taken too seriously. At Appendix B is a background note from the Board of Trade on United Kingdom trade with theContinent.11. The general conclusion as regards trade, therefore, is that, in so far as a tunnel-would provide a cheaper and more convenient transit for higher grademerchandise, although it might assist the import of foodstuffs from France andItaly to some small extent, it would be an undoubted advantage in strengthening ourlinks with an area with which our trade was growing and might provide a valuablepsychological stimulus to trade.12. As regards the views of trade and industry about a tunnel, the Federationof British Industries have been approached informally, and their position is that theyhave not, as yet, given consideration to the project. They are, however, interested and have kept in close touch with the work of the International Study Groupthrough one of its members. They are awaiting the Group&apos;s proposals at the end ofthe year, when they intend to consider the scheme. Neither the National &quot;Union-of manufacturers nor the Association of British Chambers of Commerce have givenconsideration to the project.
Effect on Existing Services; 13. The tunnel, by superseding the short-sea route shipping services for passengers and cars, would practically eliminate Dover, Folkestone and Newhavenas packet ports, and would affect Harwich but to a less extent. Most of the portinstallations, particularly in Dover, would become redundant. Local interests couldbe expected to object.14. The British ships which would become redundant are owned by theBritish Transport Commission who stand to benefit from the tunnel. If a decision were taken to build a tunnel, the Commission would no doubt allow its cross-Channel fleet to run down, accordingly. Those ships which have a remaining usefullife at the time when the tunnel is built could mostly be employed on the remainingcross-Channel services from Harwich and Southampton, and on the Commission^other short sea services to Ireland and the Channel Islands.15. British European Airways (B.E.A.) passenger services to Paris and Brusselswould be affected. There might be a steep drop in traffic immediately after theopening of the tunnel, and the rate of recovery thereafter would be slower, thoughB.E.A.&apos;s traffic over a period of years would nevertheless continue to increase. Thelong-term effect of the tunnel would be to slow down the rate of increase of air traffic.The time taken to plan and build the tunnel would be sufficient for the corporation to make any small adjustments which might be necessary to its aircraft programme.Other B.E.A. services are unlikely to be materially affected.16. As regards the independent operators, the main impact would be on those companies specialising in cross-Channel services and particularly in car-ferryoperations. The two main companies would be Silver City and Air Charter, and silver City might lose as much as 50 per cent, of their traffic. What will in any case be the position of the independent operators by 1965 or later it is difficult to predict.The period of the construction of the tunnel would be long enough to enable those companies to adjust their plans, though it would undoubtedly be a serious blow.17. The diversion of air traffic to the tunnel might put out of business someof the smaller airfields such as Ferryfield, though the investment involved here isnot very large. The tunnel is unlikely to have any material impact on the long-termemployment of Gatwick.18. Given the time to make the necessary adjustments which the building ofa tunnel would allow, and given the overall expansion of traffics, it does not seem that the effect on existing services across the Channel need prove a serious objectionto a tunnel.Attitude of France19. As regards France, the Foreign Office understand that the FrenchGovernment have not advanced very far in their thinking about a tunnel, and inparticular they have not seriously considered whether they would wish to participatefinancially.20. There seems, however, little doubt that the French Government will ultimately favour the scheme if only for the economic benefits to be obtained from it. Some freight and passenger traffic may be diverted from the Belgian and toa less extent Dutch ports to the French tunnel entry (between Calais and Boulogne),thus benefiting French forwarding, handling, transport and entrepot trade andassisting the depressed Pas-de-Calais area.Defence Considerations21. The Ministry of Defence are satisfied that there are no military advantagesor disadvantages in a Channel Tunnel of sufficient weight to sway the balance of decision. A tunnel would speed the flow of reinforcements to our forces on theContinent during a warning period or in war, but at the same time it would bevulnerable to enemy action.. It is not regarded as a defence liability as it couldreadily be blown up and flooded in emergency.
Finance22. As indicated above, the International Study Group expect the tunnel to cost something not much above  100 millions, and to earn, at an early stage, about 12-1 millions. Those represented on the Study Group regard the scheme as a sound one, and it is their present intention that the tunnel should be financed mainly by a market flotation. Possibly one-quarter would be subscribed in France(including the Suez Finance Company), one-quarter in the United Kingdom, andthe rest in other European markets and America. The interests who have supported the study would receive shares in recognition of their services.23. On this basis there would be no objection to capital issues on the london market and no question of the need for official approval on grounds of investmentcontrol arises. For the project to be financed wholly by private monies without government assistance would be the best public proof of its economic validity.Nor would exchange control be used to prevent the raising of money if the investment were thought to be desirable. In other words, if and when ministers decided that it was desirable on other grounds, exchange control authority would follow, though it would be necessary to consider the form which the UnitedKingdom investment should take.24. As long as Her Majesty&apos;s Government retain their one-third shareholdingthey are of course interested in what the Suez Finance Company do; that is, inthe extent of their contribution to the capital. But until a concrete proposal is presented it is impossible to advise on what their attitude should be.25. The British Transport Commission have raised the possibility of a contribution from Her Majesty&apos;s Government: this does not appear to be a partof present sponsors&apos; ideas, and we understand that up to the present the FrenchGovernment have formed no intention to participate. Nor, so far as we canascertain, do the French Railways wish to do so. The British transport commission may wish to participate in the financing of the terminals to the tunnels,since these will include marshalling yards and other facilities readily integrated with the national railway systems. So far as the British Transport Commission isconcerned this might amount to some  7 millions over a period of years. Any suchparticipation would have to be considered in relation to the very large investment programme already proposed by the British Transport Commission for the nextfew years and the yield expected from it.Organisation for Building and Operating the Tunnel26. The International Study Group have not yet worked out their ideas onthis subject, and it has therefore been impossible to do more than consider someof the broader issues involved.27. The Foreign Office Legal Adviser has given preliminary considerationto the question of sovereignty and legal status raised by the project, and his broadconclusions are that &quot;there would be no legal objection to the occupation of partof the subsoil beneath the Channel for the purpose of constructing the tunnel, andthat the rights of sovereignty and jurisdiction of Great Britain and France in thetunnel should be capable of settlement without too much difficulty by a bilateral agreement between them &quot;. A Memorandum prepared by the Foreign Office legal adviser is attached as Appendix C.28. As indicated in C. (59) 123, the possibilities are the creation of aninternational company to build and own the tunnel, or less desirably the settingup of two companies, one British and one French, to build and own half thetunnel each. The operation of the services through the tunnel would be suitatblefor a joint British Railways-Societe Nationale des Chemins de Fer Francaisorganisation, which could lease the route from the owning companies, and couldbe responsible for the maintenance of the railway equipment as well. It isunderstood jthat these questions are now under active discussion between theBritish and French Railways, and that they are likely to produce solutions agreed at the technical level. Discussions between the interests sponsoring the tunnelstudy are also in progress as to the nature of the building and owning organisation,though these are proving more difficult. In the absence of any concrete proposals,it is only possible to recommend that the Ministry of Transport should keep intouch with the International Study Group&apos;s deliberations and that the ForeignOffice should keep in touch with the French Governments view.
Engineering Resources29. Consideration has also been given to the impact on United Kingdomengineering resources of the construction of the British half of a tunnel. The roadworks involved present no serious problem, and the tunnel would fit well with the projected Channel Ports motorway.30. The British engineering advice to the Study Group comes from a consortium of three of the major British consulting engineers. Tunnelling throughthe chalk should be a simpler proposition than, for example, driving a tube throughLondon clay, or than the rock tunnelling involved in the Scottish hydro-electricschemes. The tunnelling machines themselves would need to be constructedspecially in any case and so would not compete for machines with any othertunnelling work such as a London tube. (This would be relevant if it is decided togo ahead with the Victoria Line.) The total labour requirement, including &quot; campfollowers&quot;, would not exceed 500 men and there are a number of sources fromwhich the tunnelling specialists could be recruited. The work involved in driving theBritish half of the tunnel would not be beyond the resources of any one of the fourleading British tunnel contractors.31. The British engineering consultants see no reason to justify bringing in american help, either for &quot;&apos; know how &quot; or for resources, although for reasons of attracting American capital it may be necessary to associate some American firmor firms with the construction. A.merican resources would, however, be availableto fall back on though the present assessment is that they would not be necessary.Summary of Conclusions32. This study is based on the project which the International Study group is considering (paragraphs 3 to 8) for a tunnel carrying accompanied cars,passengers and freight by train. The conclusions reached are:  (i) The tunnel would reduce passenger fares, charges for cars, and freight rates for the higher-class traffics (paragraphs 5 and 8).(ii) It would replace nearly all the short-sea-crossing passenger shipping services and about 30 per cent, of the present corresponding air services.This would hit the ports of Dover, Folkestone and Newhaven, andcertain independent air undertakings (paragraphs 13 to 18).(iii) It would have little effect on the United Kingdom tourist balance of trade(paragraph 9).(iv) It would have advantages in strengthening trade links with an area of growing trade (paragraphs 10 and 11).(v) There are no defence objections to a tunnel in conditions of modern war(paragraph 21).(vi) There are no objections in principle to the financing of a tunnel by international flotation, or to the United Kingdom market taking, say, a25 per cent, share, though there would be objections to any substantialUnited Kingdom Government participation either directly or throughthe British Transport Commission (paragraphs 22 to 25).(vii) The questions of sovereignty and legal status involved should be capableof settlement by agreement between Her Majesty&apos;s Government and theFrench Government (paragraph 27).(viii) Not enough is yet known about the proposals for the organisation -of thebuilding of the tunnel; it seems that the operating iorganisation is being planned on acceptable lines; Her Majesty&apos;s Government should keep intouch with the International Study Group&apos;s discussions on these points(paragraph 28).(ix) The tunnel should create no demand beyond the capacity of UnitedKingdom engineering resources (paragraphs 29 to 31).General33. The broad conclusion reached is that a tunnel would :have advantages&amp;rUnited Kingdom trade. Provided it.was built as a ^private -venture involving -jioUnited Kingdom Government commitment, it would not foe objectiona-fetefinancially. It should-create no problem of defence, or of resoMree;^ for this-counfoy:
Appendix ATHE EFFECT OF A CHANNEL TUNNEL ON THE BRITISHTOURIST TRADETourist movements between this country and the Continent (which includebusiness visits) have been increasing at rates of 8 to 15 per cent, per annum in thepast five years and seem likely to go on increasing at these kinds of rate. Britishtourists have increased in number rather faster than European tourists and in 1958accounted for more than three-quarters of the total tourist traffic on these routes.The building of a tunnel, therefore, might simply add another method of crossing the Channel which would have the effect of reducing the rate of expansion of the surface and air carriers to something less than it would otherwise be, and leavingunaffected the relationship of the number of outgoing United Kingdom tourists tothat of incoming visitors: the former remaining very much larger.2. The high car-owning population of the United Kingdom might lead to thesupposition that, if anything, the tunnel would intensify the adverse balance oftourist traffic, and this is the view which was advanced at the earlier meeting of theCommittee. There are, however, a number of factors which might operate in theother direction. They are as follows:  (i) Far more British motorists go abroad with their cars than foreign motoristsarrive in the United Kingdom. This is partly because a British motoristaccepts that he must cross the sea if he wishes to drive in a foreign country, whereas a motorist in a Continental country can visit many other countries without having to surmount any such obstacle as theChannel represents. A tunnel might then encourage a larger flow oftraffic to than away from the United Kingdom.(ii) A great deal of the motor traffic between Continental countries derives from impulse journeys. For a large part of the year the Channel ferryspace for car rules out impulse journeys to the United Kingdom by car.The Channel Tunnel might alter this situation.(iii) A higher proportion of the United Kingdom population have been accustomed to taking holidays abroad than is the case on the Continent,and the long-term scope for expansion in our tourist trade is perhapsgreater than the Continental expectation of receiving visitors from theUnited Kingdom.(iv) According to the Organisation for European Economic Co-operationAnnual Report on Tourism in Europe there are 27 million internationaljourneys by &quot; European tourists &quot; travelling in Europe outside theircountry of residence but little more than 2 in 100 come to Britain.(v) The system of cruise trains operated by Europe railways is more likely. to be extended to Britain, given a tunnel.(vi) Other marginal factors are:  (a) That a few timorous people who would not cross the Channel by air or sea might be encouraged to come via the tunnel.-(b) That the reduction in the time of the railway journey might generatesome extra travel.Both these arguments cut both ways, but given that the potential travelling public inEurope outweighs our own, the balance of advantage might be slightly in favour ofthe United Kingdom.3. It is impossible to evaluate the importance of these factors, though it is fairly certain that none can be of more than marginal importance. However,collectively they probably justify the conclusion that a tunnel is not likely toincrease our adverse tourist balance of payments. and is more likely to improve itSlightly. &apos; :-V-1    &apos;&apos;4. It is difficult to assess the effect that a Channel Tunnel would have on theforeign currency earnings of the operations of British carriers without a good deal more information about how the tunnel would be operated. At present about half the European inward sea traffic (excluding Scandinavian traffic) is carried byBritish ships and 63 per cent, of the inward air traffic by British carriers. If someof this traffic were diverted to rail there might be a slight loss of British earnings.January, 1960. ; : .SECRET
Appendix BVALUE OF TRADE WITH THE CONTINENTOver the 10 years 1948-58 our total exports to the world increased by valueby some 8 per cent, a year, and within this total our exports to the european economic Community countries, Austria and Switzerland increased by about10 per cent, a year. During the same period the value of our imports was increasingby 6 per cent, while our imports from the above European countries were increasingby 11 per cent. Our trade with the countries most likely to be directly affectedby the Channel Tunnel has thus been growing appreciably faster than our tradewith the world as a whole during these 10 years. During the three years 1954-57there were similar rates of growth, except that the value of our imports from thecatchment area increased by about 9 per cent, a year.2. The volume of our total exports (other than coal and petroleum) increasedby 3 per cent, on average in the period 1948-58, but this average includes twoperiods of decline (1950-52 and 1957-58) and a much larger rate of growth insome years. In the years 1954-57, for instance, the rate of increase was about-1- per cent. This concept of volume consists simply of writing down the valuefigures by the increases which have taken place in prices. What is perhaps mostrelevant for the present purpose is figures of tonnage. The annual average increasein tonnage of total exports in 1948-58 was about 3 per cent, (about 3i per cent, inthe 1954-57 period) and reached 16 million tons in 1958. While there is no certainrelationship between changes in volume and changes in tonnage, it would seem that when trade, especially in manufactures, is, as in 1954-57, expanding rapidly,tonnage increases tend to be somewhat less than volume increases.3. No figures are available of the volume or tonnage of our trade with thecatchment area. The commodity composition of our exports to Europe is, however,fairly representative of our total export trade, especially if coal and petroleum are excluded, and it is reasonable to infer that the relationships between the value,volume and tonnage of our exports to the world will hold good for our exportsto Europe. As the value of our exports to the catchment area grew faster, bothin the 10 years 1948-58 and in the three years 1954-57, than the value of our exports to the world, we may assume that the volume and tonnage increases tothe catchment area will have been correspondingly greater than the volume and tonnage increases to the world.4. The rate of increase in our total export trade in, say, the next 10 years should be above the average for the last 10, but somewhat below the average forthe years 1954-57; say 5 per cent, by volume.5. During the last 10 years the rate of expansion in Europe has been very rapid, and though there may be some falling off in their rate of economic growthduring the next 10 years, it is likely that it will be greater than that of the world as a whole and that our trade with Europe will continue to expand at a somewhatgreater rate than our world trade, if we assume neutral consequences from theFree Trade Area negotiations. On this basis the value of our exports to the markets most likely to be affected by the Channel Tunnel might increase by, say,6 per cent, a year. This suggests an increase in the tonnage of goods carried ofroughly 4-5 per cent, a year. (In 1958 the weight of dry cargo exports to thesecountries probably amounted to 4 million tons, of which 1 - 6 million tons were coal.)6. It should be pointed out that the assumption made about a Free trade area is neutral. At present it seems impossible to take any other. But it is, ofcourse, both arbitrary and artificial. If there is a Free Trade Area the suggestedvolume increase of 6 per cent, might well be much too low. If there is noFree Trade Area, but the European Economic Community develops as its membersintend, the increase could disappear.7. As our imports from Europe are not similar in composition to our importsfrom the world, it is not possible to make similar assessments of their volume ortonnage growth by reference to total figures. As shown above the value of our imports from the catchment area has been increasing appreciably faster than thevalue of our total imports. It seems likely that over the next 10 years the rateof increase in the volume and tonnage of our imports from these countries willbe at least as great as the increases suggested above for our exports to them:Board of Trade, S.W.1,January, 1960.SECRET ,4 4 .56453 j;&apos;;.;;; &apos; -* --V-^&quot;&apos;-^ c
Appendix CLEGAL PROBLEMSMemorandum by the Legal Adviser, Foreign office the question of constructing a Channel Tunnel has a long history in the courseof which a good deal of attention has been given to the legal problems which arise and the Reports of the various Commissions and Committees, national and international, which have considered the matter will probably repay study in due course.2. Legal questions arise both in connexion with the construction of the tunneland in connexion with its operation after it has been &quot;opened for use.3. The basic question, of course, is that of the legal status pf the seabed andsubsoil. On this depends whether there is any legal impediment to the building ofa permanent structure of this kind through the seabed, particularly through that part of it which lies beneath the high seas, or whether the consent of any third states is necessary. It also governs such matters as the acquisition of sovereignty overthe tunnel and the soil surrounding it and the exercise of jurisdiction within it.4. It is well recognised that every State has sovereignty over the seabed andthe subsoil beneath its territorial waters. Therefore, subject to the navigationalrights of other States through the waters themselves (see below), there could beno objection to the construction of the tunnel as far as the outer limits of territorial waters.5. The high seas are res extra commercium, incapable of appropriation by any state. Much of the legal discussion on the construction of the tunnel in past years has been concerned with the question whether the seabed and subsoil beneath thehigh seas have the same legal status or whether they are res nullius over whichsovereignty may be acquired by occupation. The conclusion reached appears tohave been that there was no legal impediment to the construction of the tunnel bythe United Kingdom and France, without obtaining the prior consent of third countries, provided that their common rights of navigation and fishing in the high seas were not interfered with. I understand that a draft Convention was negotiatedin 1876 under which each country would have sovereignty over its end of the tunnelup to a point half way between the low water marks on the two shores.6. We should have to consider whether thjs is still the law, particularly in thelight of the Conventions drawn up in 1958 at the first Geneva Conference on theLaw of the. Sea. One of these Conventions concerns the rights of the coastal state in the continental shelf beneath the high seas outside, territorial waters. The concept of the continental shelf is a fairly recent development in international law and was certainly not in the minds of the officials and others who considered the tunnel project in 1876 or even in 1930. Article 2 (1) of the Geneva Convention on theContinental Shelf provides that -&quot; The coastal State exercises over the continental shelf sovereign rights for the purpose of exploring it and exploiting its natural resources &quot;.Qn the face of it, tunnelling for the purpose now contemplated does not come within these rights. However, Article 7 states that. &quot; The provisions of these, Articles shall not prejudice the right of the coastal State tp exploit the subsoil by means of tunnelling irrespective ofthe depth of water above the subsoil&quot;.J have not yet had time to go into the history of tjhjs Article but it appears to preserve, so far as the continental shelf is ppnoerngd, P^^elV^fte^ghj to tunnelwhich was thought tp exist in 1876! - -7. There is nothing that I can see in the Convention on the High Seas, whichwas also drawn up. a,t Geneva in 1958, which throws any light on the legal status of the subsoil beneath the high seas beyond thecpntinentai shelves of Britain andFrance (if there is such a zone in the Channel), but I think we can conclude thatthere is little doubt that the legal status of the suhsojl gives, rise JtP -no seriousimpediment to the building of the tunnel. &apos;&apos;     &apos;      &apos;&apos;&apos;
8. I do not know how the tunnel would be engineered, but, if it involved any considerable operations above the seabed or if any part of it was to rest on theseabed and not pass through the subsoil, this might create problems with regardto the navigational and fishing rights of other nations. It follows that every effort should be made to minimise the interference with such rights.9. As I have mentioned, another question dependent on the legal status of the subsoil is that of the acquisition and exercise of sovereign rights in regardto the tunnel. It appears from references which I have seen to the draft convention of 1876 that it was drawn up on the basis that Britain and France were entitled toassume sovereignty over the whole of the tunnel, including that part of it whichlay below the high seas outside territorial waters, and possibly also over part ofthe soil surrounding it, but not over the high seas above it. Under the draftConvention the two countries would each exercise sovereignty over half the tunnel(which, incidentally, was to be constructed and operated by two companies), butit was expressly provided that it should &quot; not in any way affect any question ofthe navigation of, or any rights of navigation, fishing, anchoring, or other rights in, the sea above the tunnel, or elsewhere than in the tunnel itself &quot;. I think wecould go at least so far as to say that Britain and France, having constructed thetunnel, would be entitled to exercise exclusive jurisdictional rights in regard to itand that the boundary between them for this purpose and the limits of thoserights should be defined by bilateral agreement. The question of the assumption of sovereignty or of a lesser degree of control over the subsoil in the immediatevicinity of the tunnel for such purposes as defence, security and maintenance wouldalso have to be carefully considered and might present rather more difficult legalproblems than those discussed above.10. It would be necessary to establish a legal regime, both civil and criminal,applicable within the tunnel. I understand that under the 1876 Convention thedetails of the exercise of such jurisdiction were to be regulated by a supplementaryConvention. Each State would presumably apply its own laws in its own half ofthe tunnel, but some matters, such as traffic regulations, would undoubtedly requirejoint action and consultation. Arrangements would also have to be made forthe exercise of usual police, customs and immigration controls.11. Another set of legal problems, which should perhaps also receiveattention, concerns the status of the tunnel in time of war. There has in the past been discussion of the possibility of giving it some sort of neutral status and ofguaranteeing its security in wartime by means of a multilateral Convention. Itseems unlikely, however, at first sight, that such a scheme would be veryadvantageous in this modern age. In the case of a war not involving Britain andFrance in Europe, the chances are that there would be little or no threat to thesecurity of the tunnel. In the case of hostilities in Europe involving Britain andFrance, one side or the other would blow it up.12. My broad preliminary conclusions, therefore, are that there would be no legal objection to the occupation of part of the subsoil beneath the Channel forthe purpose of constructing the tunnel, and that the rights of sovereignty and jurisdiction of Great Britain and France in the tunnel should be capable of settlement without too much difficulty by a bilateral agreement between them.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,January, 1960.
RECEIPTPlease detach, fold and return imme-diately to the address shown overleaf.(no envelope required).I acknowledge the receipt of the followingdocument:  TOP SECRET13Copy No.   ^ifSignature...........................Department  ..........................Date   .................................45677[P.T.O.
Second fold.DISTRIBUTION ROOM,CABINET OFFICE,   &apos;GREAT GEORGE STREET, S.W. 1.Third fold (and tuck in).

</content>
</cab>
