<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/100/0 images: 154-155</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C. (60) 33 COPY NO.20th February, I960CABINET -RESALE PRICE maintenance memorandum by the Paymaster-GeneralThe proposal of the President of the Board of Trade in C.(60) 26,paragraph 9, to ask an eminent lawyer to enouire into the extent and effect of individual resale price maintenance seems to me to be adombtful proposition.2.      The extent of the practice of course is ascertainable - though an extensive public enqui^r by the Board of Trade would probably be involved.3.      The effect of individual price maintenance must be a matter of opinions which would have to be canvassed from all those concerned - andin the end depend upon the difficult assessment of such opinions.4.     I doubt whether such a report could have much value, but in anycase the procedures would have much publicity.5.      If it were decided to have such an enquiry, an Accountant wouldappear to me to be more suitable than a lawyer.6.      The following considerations might be taken into account in considering the proposals in C. (60) 26 possibly leading to the abolitionof individual resale price maintenance:-(a) It is only four years since the Restrictive Trade PracticesAct which, under Clause 25, permitted Individual resale price Maintenance. Is it wise to reconsider the matterafter such a short interval?(b) Competition between manufacturers of similar goods should be adequate to keep prices at reasonablelevels.(c) Competition in price between retailers would tend to favour the big concern at the expense of the smaller.The small suburban and village shops could besufferers.( d)    The abolition of individual resale price maintenance &apos;could lead to unfair competition - marking downindividual items of standard goods in order to attract the public to a particular store.
(e)    In goods requiring service,    prices are generally-fixed having regard to this necessity.    Free retail.price competition could result in the reduction of thelevel of service.7.     As against the considerations in paragraph 6 above there is anincalculable reduction in price to the public, a similar reduction in retail profits and of course some reduction in tax receipts.    (I amaware of the guesses of Professor B. S.  Yamey, published to-day.)M.Office of the Paymaster-General,S. W. 1.19th February, I960.-c-

</content>
</cab>
