<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/100/0 images: 264-266</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  March 1960C. (60) 43 Copy No.7th March, 1960CABINETMEDICINES FOR PRIVATE PATIENTSMemorandum by the Minister of HealthPre-occupation with the Pilkington Report has lowered the temperature of theBritish Medical Association in this matter. But this has been more than offset bya sharp rise in the political temperature. Before the Election, with the results atthe hazard, the temperature was tepid: now it is torrid.2. I must therefore once again seek the guidance of the Cabinet on thismatter which dates back to the Right Road for Britain and beyond.Position in 19593. In February 1959 the Secretary of State for Scotland and I sought the viewof our colleagues in the Home Affairs Committee. In July the matter was further considered by the then Committee on National Health Service Finance; and on17th July the Home Secretary, as Chairman of the Committee, submitted aMemorandum (C. (59) 125) to the Cabinet inviting them to agree that &quot; for thetime being we should not concede the provision of medicines for private patientson National Health Service terms &quot;. The Cabinet did so agree, but not so as to exclude the possibility of concession at a later date (C.C. (59) 44th Conclusions,Minute 1).Policy Statement4. With this end in view the Home Secretary and I devised the formula setout in the Annex in the form used by me in the House of Commons. It puts themain stress on the preservation of private practice; but there is, of course, alsothe interest of private patients to be taken into account.General Merits5. On general merit (i.e., apart from economics and competing claims) thearguments for are:(a) It is in line with original Conservative thinking in the late 1940&apos;s.(b) It helps those who are helping themselves at any rate to the extent of paying their own doctors bills.(c) It should help to ensure the continuity, and enhance the attraction, ofprivate practice, and to assist good relations with the medical profession.The arguments against are:(i) It might create two varying standards of general practice and bethought to increase the preferential treatment for private patients.(ii) It might have repercussion in wider fields, e.g., there is an obviousanalogy with books in independent schools.(iii) We have not yet succeeded in containing the drug bill, and this concession might tend to increase it.The feeling is sincerely held in a good many quarters that there is a real dangerof (i). But it is a danger that should be mitigated by the procedural safeguards thatwe have, been able to agree with the British Medical Association.56666
Cost6. It is difficult to quantify the cost precisely. It has been put up to 1\ millions. It may be, having regard to the extent of private practice as suggestedby the Report of the Royal Commission on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos; Remunerationunder, the Chairmanship of Sir Harry Pilkington, that it might be more. The chanceof eo&quot;jnpensating, abatement to the Exchequer has not been promoted by the report which has:(a) Refrained from recommending that doctors remuneration should be basedon the number of patients instead of the number of doctors.(b) Recommended the discontinuance of the deduction from the Central pool of  2 millions in respect of private earnings.Estimates7. The published Vote on Account for the National Health Service (for england and Wales) shows a total estimate of  519 millions. Of this  67 millionsis for the drugs, an increase of  6-7 millions on the original Estimate of 1959-60.(We have had to present a supplementary estimate for this year of  5-7 millions for drugs.) We are taking a variety of steps to try and contain the drug bill, but itis far from easy to do so. This being so, it is probable that the expenditure on private drugs in the coming financial year consequent on immediate legislation could not be contained in the existing Estimate; and a supplementary estimatewould be required.in respect of it.Timing8. If this concession is made, however, I suggest that the earliest practical timefor legislation will be in the next Session, with provision made in the Estimate for1961-62. This should be better financially and presentationally than actioninvolving the coining financial year, which will carry the special burdenconsequential upon the Pilkington Report.Special Problems9. Certain special problems arise in the event of a decision to make the concession.   In particular:(a) The Formula. The decision will have to be related in some degree to theformula in the Appendix. The British Medical Association are giving further consideration to evidence; but it may be that short of instituting a special canvass of National Health Service patients, whichwould be open to objection they may not be able to adduce anyconclusive, or even convincing formal evidence. They are, however,sincere in their belief that the present system is prejudicial to private practice and say, not unreasonably, that the evidence of this consistsmainly of oral communications which cannot be formulated.Concession would therefore probably involve accepting their generalstatements as evidence in lieu of precise or statistical evidence.(b) Prescription Charges. Our undertaking to review prescription chargesonly comes into effect at the end of the two-year trial period of voluntarylimitation of prescriptions, i.e., January 1962. There may well bepresentational difficulty if this date is adhered to and action is takenin respect of private patients a year earlier.(c) Announcement. Government supporters are pressing for a commitment in respect of legislation; and without some assurance are unlikely tobe willing to take the pot off the boil. Any public announcement would,however, lead to demand for debate in Parliament and enable theOpposition to campaign against the concession in the coming months in advance of legislation. Careful consideration therefore would haveto be given to the content, timing and occasion of any statement toGovernment supporters.Conclusion10.   I think that we should now:(a) Decide, at the least, whether or not, at the end of the road, we are mindedto make this concession.
(b) Recognise that, due to political pressure and the course of negotiation with the British Medical Association, the end of the road is near.(c) Conclude that if we decide to make the concession, the necessary legislation should be introduced in the next Session, preceded by the minimumannouncement required to deflect the public demands of Government,supporters.11. The Secretary of State for Scotland is in agreement with the terms ofthis paper.D. W.-S.Ministry of Health, W. 1.4th March, 1960.annex extract from Hansard, House of Commons, for Wednesday, 4th November, 1959(Written Answers, Column 63)Answer by the Minister of health the Government attach importance to the preservation of private practice and the right of patients to resort thereto, and would certainly consider makingdrugs available to private patients on National Health Service terms, in the context of available resources and competing claims, if it were shown that the presentposition was endangering the existence of private practice or preventing anysubstantial number of people from availing themselves of it, who would otherwisewish to do so. But they have no present plans for legislation on this subject.

</content>
</cab>
