<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/100/0 images: 299-305</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1960C. (60) 47 Copy No.      ,11th March, I960 ** ^cabinet economic SURVEY 1960Memorandum by the Chancellor of the ExchequerEarlier in the year the Economic Policy Committee gave some thought tothe form in which the Economic Survey 1960 should be prepared. The committee agreed in principle that the Survey should be divided into two parts: the first to consist of an assessment of the economic outlook for 1960, the second to contain a factual account of economic developments in 1959. It was agreed that onlythe first part need be considered by Ministers collectively.2. At the time some doubt was expressed about whether the first part shouldbe published at all, on the grounds that the prospects for 1960 and the Governmentsbroad economic policies for that year would in any event be dealt withauthoritatively in the Budget speech. It was agreed that the question should beconsidered further when an actual draft of the first part was available.3. At a meeting of the Economic Policy Committee on 9th March a draftof the first part of the Survey was considered. There was still hesitation on thepart of some Ministers about the desirability of publishing Part One at all. It wasagreed that in any event a number of changes should be made in the draft ascirculated to the Committee.4. I now circulate a revised draft which incorporates suggestions made bothby the Economic Planning Board and at the meeting of the Economic PolicyCommittee. I invite my colleagues to consider whether this should be published on 30th March.  My own view is that it should be published.D. H. A.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,11th March, 1960.56688
ECONOMIC SURVEY 1960This Economic Survey is divided into two parts: in the first an assessmentis made of the present position ; in the second, economic developments in1959 are reviewed in some detail.PART ONEIntroduction1. The United Kingdom enters the nineteen-sixties in a position to benefit from the strengthening of the economic structure of the country during thelast decade. There are good prospects for a continued rise in the standardof living at home; and at the same time the United Kingdom should beable to play an important part in helping the less-developed countries ofthe world. The achievement of this dual objective will require a strongupward trend in production coupled with a general steadiness of prices and a sound balance of payments. These things call for prudent economic policy, for enterprise in business and for moderation on profits and incomes.The country will need to go on saving enough to support a high rate of productive investment at home and overseas and must above all keep pricescompetitive.2. In the main 1959 was a good year for the United Kingdom economy.The expansion which began in the last quarter of 1958 gradually gatheredmomentum and spread to most though not all sections of industry andtrade. By the last quarter of 1959, the country&apos;s total output of goods and services was 7 per cent higher than a year earlier and its industrial produc-tion alone was 10 per cent higher. An increase in the working population and a decrease in unemployment provided a rise of T3 per cent inemployment. Most of the increase in output was, however, achieved through the fuller use of existing capacity. But the distinguishing mark of this expansion was that it was accomplished with virtually no increasein prices as a whole.3. The increase in industrial activity and in general demand led to higherimports and so to an increased charge on the balance of payments. Inaddition the country repaid some of its overseas debt, increased its sub-scription to the International Monetary Fund and also increased its loans and grants to overseas countries ; largely because of these transactions,the reserves fell and overseas sterling holdings rose.4. Part Two of this Survey shows that no single factor was responsiblefor the combination of expansion and steady prices. An increase in home demand was brought about by the removal of restrictions on credit, bythe increase in public investment authorised in 1958 and by the reductionin taxation in 1959. The recovery of world trade provided a new opportunityto increase exports. Industrial production responded rapidly to this rise
in home and overseas demand partly because unused resources of man-power and productive capacity were available,in the economy. Prices werestable partly as a result of the cut in some taxes on expenditure but also because there was only a moderate increase in rates of pay.5. At the beginning of 1960 it seemed likely that investment and exports would continue to expand, with a further, though perhaps slower, increasein consumption. There were signs, however, that if the growth in totalhome demand were left altogether unchecked too much strain might beput on some productive resources and on the balance of payments. Itwas partly for this reason that Bank Rate was raised from 4 to 5 per centon 21st January 1960 ; this also brought short-term interest rates in Londonmore into line with those of other financial centres. The following sectionsexamine in turn the world outlook, the growth of demand, the scope for increasing production, prices, and the external prospect.World outlook6. In industrial countries it seems likely that expansion will continue in1960 though probably not as rapidly as in 1959. In the United States total production increased by 7 per cent in 1959 but part of that represented a recovery from the recession of 1957/58 so that the growth in 1960 maybe smaller. In Germany and some other European countries, where therewas a rapid expansion in 1959 (and no recession in 1958) governments have recently taken or are proposing to take action to moderate thegrowth of demand. Nevertheless the general trend should be stronglyupwards and should lead to further expansion in trade between industrial countries.7. In addition the primary producing countries can be expected to con-tribute more to the growth of world trade in 1960 than in 1959. Theirspending power should be higher as a result of the rise in the export earnings of some of them and the increased flow of international capital in the past year, both of which should be sustained in 1960. This increase, togetherwith the recent relaxation in their import restrictions, should lead to amarked rise in their imports this year. The increase in world demand for rawmaterials, resulting from the expansion in indiuistttiial countries, may lead toa rise in prices, but the productive capacity of primary producing countries has been greatly extended in the past few years and they should be able toincrease the supplies of many commodities.8. The substantial reductions in import restrictions made by several countries in 1959 should lead to a larger flow of international trade. Afurther round of tariff negotiations, within the framework of the GeneralAgreement on Tariffs and Trade, will begin in September 1960. Mean-while, on 1st July 1960, the countries of the European economic community and those of the European Free Trade Association will eachbe making tariff reductions for the fellow members of their respectivegroups. * The longer-term outlook is uncertain but in 1960 these tariffmovements are not likely to have a significant effect.* The countries of the European Economic Community are Belgium, France, Germany,Italy, Luxembourg and the Netherlands. The countries in the European Free Trade Associa-tion are Austria, Denmark, Norway, Portugal, Sweden, Switzerland and the United Kingdom.
9. On the whole, therefore, the world prospect is reasonably favourable for the United Kingdom. Firms in this country should be able to seize the opportunity for a further substantial expansion of their exports.Growth of domestic demand10. From 1958 to 1959 public consumption (the current expenditure ofthe Government and local authorities on goods and services) rose by 3 percent in real terms. The corresponding rise in the consumption of theGovernment between 1959 and 1960 is likely to be about 4f per cent. (TheEstimates for the financial year 1960/61 imply that the Government&apos;sconsumption will be 5J per cent higher than in 1959/60, but some of this represents a rise in wages and salaries.) The main reasons for the rise inthe Governmenfs consumption in real terms are the rise in defence expendi-ture, resulting from the increasing real cost of providing modern Forces andthe weapons and facilities they require, and the expansion of health andother services. There will also be an increase in local authorities&apos; consump-tion, reflecting in particular the improvement and expansion in the education services.11. Public investment (the capital expenditure of the Government, localauthorities and nationalised industries) is likely to reach about  1,575million in the financial year 1959/60. This is less than originally expectedas it was some time before public investment responded to the increasesauthorised in the summer and autumn of 1958. In the financial year,1960/61. public investment is likely to be about  1,655 million or 5 percent higher than in 1959/60. Expenditure on housing by local authorities is likely to rise by about  15 million and. all other public investment byabout  65 million. Public investment was on a strongly rising trend duringthe second half of 1969 in the fourth quarter it was 15 per cent higher thana year earlier. It is likely to remain at a high level this year but not to be such an expansive force as in the second half of 1959.12. Private investment (excluding housing) is likely to increase rapidly in 1960, after two years of little change. The results of the enquiry madeat the end of the 1959 into investment intentions indicate that firms in manu-facturing industry exDect to raise their capital expenditure by 14 per cent between 1959 and 1960 and that the greater part of the increase will befor plant, machinery and vehicles. Much of the additional investment willbe accounted for by the iron and steel industry and by the motor industry,both of which plan to soend about half as much again as in 1959. Theresults of the enquiry also suggest that investment in distribution andother services will continue to rise and will be substantially higher in 1960than in 1959. Private expenditure on housing rose by nearly one-quarter in real terms between 1958 and 1959. The large increase in orders receivedby contractors in 1959 suggests that this expenditure will continue to risein 1960.13. Taking these forecasts of private and public investment together, it looks as though total fixed investment may rise by nearly one-tenth in thecourse of 1960, ice. the same as the increase during 1959.14. Personal consumption, which accounts for more than half total demand, rose during 1959 by just over 3 per cent in real terms, partly because of the Budget. The growth of real incomes and the development
of hire purchase and other forms of lending are difficult to foresee, but itseems probable that consumption will anise rather less in 1960 Itihian in 1959.15. In 1959 investment in stocks rose rapidly and was an important factor in the expansion of total demand. By the end of the year stocks weregrowing so rapidly that it seems unlikely that the rate of accumulation willbe so fast this year.16. To sum up, during 1960 public consumption and total fixed investmentare each likely to rise by about the same amount as they did in 1959 and demand for exports should also increase. Some rise in personal consumptionmay be expected but it seems improbable that rate of investment in stockswill continue to increase as compared with the high rate of increase inthe latter part of 1959.Scope for increasing production17. There should be a small increase in the labour force this year fromthe ordinary growth in the population of working age and probably froman increase in the proportion of older married women who are seeking work (which has been rising steadily in recent years). The other possiblesource of labour is from a further decrease in unemployment. In February1959, the unemployment rate in Great Britain was 28 per cent but it began to fall soon after output started to expand and in February 1960, it wasdown to 2 0 per cent.18. Increased demand will create new employment opportunities and sothere is the prospect of a further reduction in unemployment. In Londonand the South-East, the Midlands, the East and West Ridings and theEastern and Southern region, which together contain nearly 60 per cent of the employed population, unemployment was down to 1-3 per cent inFebruary and was no higher than the number of registered vacancies ;in these regions the labour force, especially the skilled part of it is alreadyfully engaged. On the other hand, in the North-Western region unemploy-ment was 2-4 per cent, in Wales 3-3 per cent, in the Northern region 3-5per cent, in Scotland 4-7 per cent and in Northern Ireland 7-9 per cent.The Government is opening up new employment opportunities in these areas by vigorous exercise of existing powers to which will be added the powergiven by the Local Employment Act.19. A significant feature of 1959 was that total employment rose by300,000 to 23,300,000. But because of that growth in employment, therewill be less scope this year than last year for increasing the numbers atwork in the country as a whole. Thus the possibility of meeting the increasein home demand depends primarily on the scope for increasing the output-per-head of those already in employment. In the nineteen-fifties the aver-age increase in output-per-head was about 2 per cent per year. During1959 output-per-head rose by 5 per cent. That was an exceptionally large increase because, as orders and sales picked up in different industries, itwas possible to take up much of the slack which had developed in 1958.Longer production runs and fuller working led to the more efficient useof resources; short-time working was reduced and overtime was increased.In addition, output-per-head was raised by advances in technology and in organisation.
20. In I960 the increased demand for plant and machinery should fall onindustries which have not yet shared fully in the expansion and which still have some unused capacity. In the economy as a whole, continuedtechnical progress has been assisted by the high rate of investment inrecent years. There should therefore be scope for a larger increase in output-per-head (this year than the average for the past decade. But, as there are fewer unused resources available now than a year ago, theincrease in 1960 is not likely to be as large as in 1959. Order books insome industries are already lengthening and, as the year proceeds, it may become increasingly difficult to increase employment, particularly of skilled labour, in some areas. This underlines the need to train more skilledpeople. Pric S21. Disregarding the downward effect of the Budget changes, 1959 was ayear in which the upward trend in prices was small. It was also one inwhich the increase in productivity was larger than the increase in earningsso that there was a slight fall in labour costs per unit of output. In 1958there had been a substantial rise in labour costs per unit of output whichwas not however reflected in rising prices. In consequence the rise inprofits per unit of output in 1959 was mainly a recovery from the fall in1958.22. The disturbing feature is the outlook for costs in 1960. In thewinter of 1959/60 there were a number of agreements to increase wages and salaries or to reduce hours of work which may raise hourly rates of payby nearly 5 per cent. (A reduction in the working week from44 hours to 42 hours without a change in total pay would mean a rise ofroughly this size ; or if hours actually worked remained the same, thehourly rate of pay would rise by 6 or 7 per cent depending on overtimerates.) To the extent that productivity rose, unit costs would not increase as much as hourly rates of pay. But the growth of national productivity in the foreseeable future is unlikely to reach 5 per cent per annum:increases of pay on the scale of these agreements, if they were to spreadright through the economy, would therefore be likely to bring about a risein unit costs.23. Other industrial oountries are also faced with the problem of how to avoid rising prices. The Government shares the view given by theOrganisation for European Economic Co-operation in its recent Review ofthe United Kingdom economy that &quot;future stability will, to an importantextent, depend on the attitude of all concerned in the determination ofindustrial prices and wages . . .&quot; But labour costs are not the only problem.It is right that all should share in the benfits of increasing productivity.It is wrong that any one section of the community should obtain a disproportionate share. Profits are needed to provide for further expansion,as well as for ia return on capital invested and they may also be affectedby the expectation of higher costs ; but they should not be allowed to claimso large a share of increased productivity that benefits cannot be spread to the consumer through the level lof prices. Lower prices are particularly important not only because they benefit consumers, but also because price stability reduces the pressure for wage increases. When decisions have tobe made about wages, prices or profits and dividends, all concerned havea part to play in moderating claims and so helping to make sure that the
benefits of higher productivity are well spread. The Governments respon-sibility is to ensure that the total claims on the economy do not exceed thetotal likely to be available from production.External prospect24. In 1959 -the United Kingdom&apos;s reserves fell while the overseas startingholdings rose. This was, however, mainly a result of special transactions, themost important of which was the increased subscription to the international monetary Fund. This step was taken as part of a general increase inthe subscriptions of (member countries in order to expand by about one-halfthe resources available to tide over short-term fluctuations in the balance ofpayments of these countries. The United Kingdom^ other long-term capital transactions, including Government lending to overseas countries,were somewhat larger than its surplus of  162 million on current accountso that there was a deficit on the balance of payments as a whole.25. Expenditure from United Kingdom public funds on economic andtechnical assistance to overseas countries has been rising fast, mainly asa result of increased loans to the Commonwealth following the arrangementsannounced at the Montreal Conference in 1958. Total overseas loans and grants from public funds have doubled in the past three years and arelikely to rise further this year. Private investment overseas is also rising.Thus the total flow of capital from the United Kingdom to overseas countries will be higher in 1960 than in 1959. This outflow of capital is likely to leadto a deficit on the combined capital and current account of the balance ofpayments this year, as in 1959, though the size of the deficit will dependon whether the current account surplus can be increased.26. From 1958 to 1959, the value of imports rose 6J per cent while thevalue of exports rose 4^ per cent. In 1960 the volume of imports can beexpected to rise at least as fast as in 1959, and there may be a slightdeterioration in the terms of trade. Thus there is a need for an even larger increase in the volume of exports this years than last year. Such anachievement will only be possible if the United Kingdom^ export prices are competitive, if home demand does not hold back exports and if firms in this country take full advantage of the favourable world conditions.27. Our aim in 1960 must be to achieve a further steady increase in investment and production but without damage to price stability or to thebalance of payments. Success will depend on the maintenance of theright balance between total demand and output, on vigilance about costs and prices, and thus on the securing of favourable circumstances for theexpansion of our export trade. Given these conditions the country canlook forward to a year of continuing progress.

</content>
</cab>
