<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/57/0 images: 20-38</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 QOVLRNMT^T) .S E C R E T. COPY NO.CABINET    3  (28) .Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at 10 downing street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,  January 25th,1928,  at 11.30 a.m.AGENDA.1* FOREIGN AFFAIRS (If required).it2.  PROGRAM.E OF GOVERNMENT BUSINESS FOR THE SESSION.(Reference Cabinet 1 (28) Conclusion 4).Note by the Secretary covering List of proposedBills,CP. 12 (28)    -      circulated herewith.Statement, prepared by the Acting Chief Whip,showing Parliamentary time available up to theend of July, 1928,CP. 11 (28)    -     already circulated.Memorandum by the Minister of Health,CP. 9 (28)      -     already circulated.5* THE FUTURE OF BRITISH COMMERCIAL AIR TRANSPORT.(Reference Cabinet 52 (27) Conclusion 8).Report of Cabinet Committee,CP, 327 (27)    -     already circulated *4.  PROPOSAL TO WITHDRAW THE 2ND BATTALION,  COLDSTREAMGUARDS, PROM CHINA.Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of Statefor Ear,CP. 10 (28)      -     already circulated.5* EXPENDITURE ON PUBLICITY FOR THE BRITISH INDUSTRIES FAIR.Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade,CP. 14 (28)      -     circulated herewith..(Signed) M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, 3.W.I.January 24th,  1928.s This question would appear to be closely connected withthe subject discussed by the Cabinet last Prlda3r.M.?.A .H.
CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10 Downing Street, S,1.&quot;/,!., on WEDNESDAY,January 25th, 1923,  at 11.30 a,in.PRESENTThe Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.     (In the Chair).The Right Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G.M*?., SecretaryForeign Affairs.P., Secretary of State to the Right Hon.Viscount Cave, 6.C.M.G.,Lord Chancellor,The Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,K.G,,-G,C.V,0.tCoB.f Lord Privy SealeThe Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State for india the Right Hon.Tr.S, Churchill, C.3.9M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Eight Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt. ,G.3.E.,C.M.G.,M.P.f Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt.,D.S.O.,1M.P., Secretary of Statefor Scotland.The Right Hon.W.C. Bridgeman, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty*The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B,E.,M.C,,M.P.,  President ofthe Board of Trade-The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.W.E, Guinness-, D.S.0.,M.P,,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland, Bt.,M.P., Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Viscount Peel, G.B.S.,First Commissioner of Works,mumThe Right Hon,Sir Douglas Hogg, K.C.,M.P,,At t orney-G enera I.THE FOLLOWING vJERB ALSO PRESENT:-The Right Hon.W.G.A. Ormsby-Gore, M,P. ,Parliamentary Under-Secretary,Colonial Office.(For Conclusion 7),,Stv- M*P.A. Hankey, G.C.B.Secretary-secret c r 5 t, copy no._cab I net   3 (28).
EGYPT.elusion 2.)1. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs made a secret statement to the Cabinet regarding(Previous .Reference: the obstacles that were being encountered in cabinet 1(28)    Con- completing the negotiations for the signature of the Treaty ^ith Egypt.
TALY. 2. The President of the Board cf Trade reportedSupply to the Cabinet that the arrangement made by ItalyCoal to.for taking a larger amount of reparation coal fromGermany was calculated to tell against Britishshipments of coal to Italy, which was particularlyinconvenient at a time when great efforts werebeing mads to revive the coal industry.   The Boardof Trade were in touch with the Foreign office with a view to any action that might prove prae-ticable now or later to alleviate the situation.-2-
*1 rvNATIONALEXPENDITURE ,(previous reference:Cabinet 62(27), Con-clusion 3) ,OIL FUEL FORTHE NAVY.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 49(27), Con-elusion 5.)3. The Chancellor of the Exchequer recalled that on December   15th,  1927, he had made astatement to the Cabinet in regard to national expenditure, Then the Cabinet had agreed that,in the present political situation, it was outof the question to contemplate an increase in income Tax for the financial year 1928-29, andthat every possible effort must be made to achieve the economies required to balance theBudget.   As the result of this meeting he had circulated to his colleagues.es proposals for reductions in expenditure.    In some directionsprogress had teen made, but in others theposition was less satisfactory.   He ashed foran opportunity at the next meeting of theCabinet, or else at a Special Meeting, to devotean hour to a review of the present situation.The First Lord of the Admiralty reportedthat,  so far as the Admiralty were concerned,economies depended to a considerable extentupon the investigation to be made by LordBirkenhead&apos;s Committee into the oil fuel require-ments of the Navy.The Secretary of State for India said hewas prepared to hold a meeting early next week.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That an opportunity should begiven to the Chancellor of theExchequer to set forth theposition in regard to NationalSxpendi.tu.r9 early next week,and, if possible, at the outset of the Cabinet Meeting onWednesday, February Is t:(b) That the Secretary should arrange a meeting of Lord Birkenhead&apos;sCommittee on the Naval Programmeearly next week for the consid-eration of the Admiralty&apos;sOil Fuel Programme.
A . The Cabinet had before them the following documents pr-pared    for th-ir consideration inconnection with the programme of Government busi-ness for the coming Session of Parliament:-A list of Bills which Ministerswished to have considered for introduction during the comingParliamentary Session (paper cp .-12 (28)):A statement (Paper C.P.-11 (28))prepared by the Acting Chief Whip,showing the amount of Parliament-(jh*s$      ary time available to the end ofJuly, 1928, including an estimate that 22 full   sittings would beavailable for the chief   Billsof the Session:A Memorandum by the Minister ofHealth (Paper C.P.-9 (.28))  inregard to the provisional programmeof legislation of the Ministry ofHealth:    urging, inter alia, thatthe Local Authorities (FinancialC  *v Provisions) Bill must in any event be passed:    that the national health Insurance Bill is most desirable, both politically and on public health grounds;    and thatths Valuation (Amendment) Bill ispolitically necessary.The conclusions reached as the result of a detailed examination of the bill  proposed may besummarised as follows:-(a) That Parliamentary time will haveto be found for the passage of thefollowing compulsory Annual Bills:PUBLIC WORKS LOAN BILLCONSOLIDATED FUND BILL (Moist passbefore end of March, 1928)FINANCE BILL
ISLE OP MANCUSTOMS BILL,(previous reference:Cabinet 42(27) - Con-elusion 7.)ISLE OP MAN CUS &quot;CMS BILL.EXPIRING laws continuance BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 52(27), Con-elusion 2.)ARMY AND AIRFORCE ANNUALBILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 18(27), Con-elusion 18.)REPRESENTATIONOF THE PEOPLE(EQUAL FRANCHISE)BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 1(28), Con-clusion 4.)APPROPRIATION BILL.EXPIRING LAWS continuance bill.    (Must pass before end ofDee ember, 1928 0)ARMY AND AIR FORCE ANNUAL BILL.(-Must receive Royal Assentby April 30, 1928.)(b) That it would be necessary tointroduce in some form: a Repre-sentation of the People (EqualFranchise) Bill.(e)30USE OF lords reform BILL.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 1(23), Con-elusion 4.)THE FACTORY SILL,(previous ous* Reference:Cabinet 41(27), Con-elusion 2.)That, in order to give time forthe compilation of a Report bythe Committee set up at the last meeting to examine the Chancellorof the Exchequer&apos;s proposals inC.P*-8 (.28) and for its considera-tion by the Cabinet, the decision should be reserved until nextWednesday, February 1st, as towhich/of the following bills should, be adopted as the otherprincipal measures of the Session:HOUSE OF LORDS REFORM BILL.THE FACTORY BILL.
THE CHILDREN BILL.(Pr evi previous reference:Cabinet 1(28), Con-clusion 4.)THE CHILDREN BILL   (Home Secretary)THE CHILDREN BILL (SCOTLAND)THE SHOPS BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 1(28), Con-elusion 4.)THE SHOPS BILL,THE ROAD TRAFFICBILL0(previous reference:Cabinet 61(27), Con-clusion 9 &amp;Appendix.)THE ROAD TRAFFIC bill the LONDON TRAFFIC THE LONDON TRAFFIC BILL.BILL.(Previous ^Referenc e:Cabinet 22(24), Con-clusion 9 ( c).)and/or the legislation involved inthe Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;splan, which includes, before october 1929, measures of:-(i)  altering the basis of ratingindustrial property and pro-viding for a levy of a nationalrate to be paid with the pro-ceeds of the Liquid Fuel Taxto a central fund;(ii)  abolishing the system of AssignedRevenues to clear the way for the block Grants Scheme of theMinistry of Health;(iii) providing for the new distribu-tion of the revenue from thecentral fund to make good the deficiencies in local revenuesdue to the exemption of indus-trial property and also toprovide the new Block Grant;(iv) carrying through the Ministryof Health&apos;s scheme of Poor law reform, including the adoptionof the County and County Boroughas the future areas of adminis--tratlon;
agricultural credits BILL.(FreviousRe ferene e:Cabinet 7(27), Con-elusion l(a) .)(v)  transferring from the district councils to the County councils the responsibility for highwaysother than residential streets(Paper CP.-8 (28), para.22i.-(d) That, subject to a time-table(in regard to which the PrimeMinister undertook to consult the Acting Chief Whip), Parlia-mentary time should be found, ifpossible,after thethe Committeefor the following Billsusual consideration by of Home AffairsAGRICULTURAL CREDITS BILL.REMARKSRABBITS BILL.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 15(27), Con-elusion 9.)RABBITS BILL,To- -too - -int 3?o due- edAGRICULTURAL PRODUCE(TRADING etc.) BILL.INDUSTRIAL ANDPROVIDENT SOC IE-TIES ACT (AMENDMENT)DILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 61(27), Con-clusion 8.)INDUSTRIAL AND PROVIDENTSOCIETIES ACT  (AMENDMENT)BILL.THE NAVAL PRIZE FUND Not to be men-BILL. tioned in theKing&apos;s Speech.THE POST OFFICE THE POST OFFICE SITES BILL.SITES BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 18(27), Con-elusion 10.)THE TELEGRAPH THE TELEGRAPH MONEY BILL.   Must passMONEY BILL. before then Previous Summer RecessReference:Cabinet 39(24), Con-clusion 16.)
THE PETROLEUM BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet    52(27), Con-elusion 1 &amp;Appendix.)SECURITY OPRESERVOIRS BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 15(27), Con-clusion 6.)TEACHERS (SUPER-ANNUATION ACT,1925) amendment bill.(previous reference:Cabinet 16(25), Con-clasion 12.)RE-ORGANISATIONOP OFFICES(SCOTLAND) BILL.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 52(27), Con-elusion 1 &amp;Appendix) .RATING (SCOTLAND)AMENDMENT BILL.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 52(27), Con-clusions 1 &amp; 4.THE PETROLEUM BILL.SECURITY OF RESER- )VOIRS BILL )Prime minister unertook to consult the HomeOffice about the urgency of these bills .TEACHERS (SUPERANNUATION     To be introducedACT., 1925) AMENDMENT BILL, in the House ofLords, unless itis introduced asa Private MembersBill..RE-ORGANISATION OF OFFICES(SCOTLAND) BILL.RATING (SOOTLKND) amendment bill.EDUCATIONAL ENDOWMENTS (SCOTLAND)BILL.BILL TO ALLOW SOLEMNIZATIONOF MARRIAGES IN MILITARYCHAPELS.OFFICIAL SECRETS ACT (AMENDMENT)BILL.)To be intro-)duced as and)when the)Chief WhipJean find an)opportunity.)Not to bo)mentioned in)tbe King7s)Speech.
BILL TO AMEND T&quot;TE GOVERNMENTJUDICATUREBILL.(previous reference:Cabinet IS(24), C on-elusion 1 &amp;. Appendix.)OP INDIA ACT, TTrELOANS ACTS AND O^13&apos;AST INDIA:R ACTS.JUDICATURE BILL )and )DISTRICT PROBATE REGIS- )TRIES BILL. )Aral, ts thepassage of theReserve BankBill shortly to be placed before theLegislaturein India.To be amalga-mated by theLord chancellor in a sinsleBill.ARBITRATION BILL,(previous reference:Cabinet 17(24), Con-elusion 10) .ARBITRAmTON BILL.JUDICIAL COMMITTEEBILL.I previous reference:Cabinet- 52(27)    Con-elusion 1.)JUDICIAL COM - ITTEE BILL,To be introduced in the House ofCommons.iESOLUTION FORIWC EXTRA. JUDGESIPrevi previous reference:Cabinet 59(27), Con-clusion 8.)RESOLUTION FOR TWOEXTRA. JUDGES.THE british guiana BILL.(previous reference:-Cabinet 56(27), Con-elusion 4.)THE STRAITS SETTLE-MENTS AMD J OH ORETERRITORIAL WATERSBILL.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 7(27), Con-clusion 1 &amp;Appendix.)THE BRITISH GUIANA BILL.,THE STRAITS SETTLEMENTS ANDJOHORE TERRITORIAL WATERSBILL.The Prime Minis-ter undertook toascertain ifthis is anessential Bill.LOCAL AUTHORITIES(FINANCIAL PRO-VISIONS) BILL.Previous Reference:Cabinet 59 f27) Con-elusion 5.)LOCAL AUTHORITIES(FINANCIAL PROVISIONS)BILL.Must be passed.
NATIONAL HEALTH   - WAmTmTaT m.TmrrINSURANCE BILL. BILL HEALTH INSURANCE(previous reference:Cabinet 7(27),  Con-clusion 10)VALUATION AMEND- VALUATION AMENDMENT BILL.MENT BILL,(previous previous reference:Cabinet 54(25), Con-clusion 2.)COMPANIES BILL.(Frovi previous reference:Cabinet 52(27), Con-clusion 1 &amp;Appendix.)PATENTS and designs BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 52(27), Con-clusion 5.)MINING industry bill.(previous reference:Cabinet 49(26), Con-clusion 6.)COMPANIES BILL.PATENTS AND DESIGNS BILL,MINING INDUSTRY BILL.To be intro-ducsd in theHouse ofmo be included inthe King&apos;s Speech,In Autumn Sessionif legislation is found essential,COTTON INDUSTRY BILL,Second Readingmight be after11 of clock.BILL TO TRANSFER the parliament SQUARE ROADSTO THE WESTMINSTERCOUNTY COUNCIL.BALANCES BILL. BALANCES BILL.(previous previous reference:Cabinet    52(27), Con-clusion 1.)NORTHERN IRELAND NOTEISSUE BILL.TRUSTEE SAVINGS BANEBILL. ,(Also two Bills which may berequired by the Chancellor of
the Exchequer, but arenot yet ready for con-sideration by theCabinet.   They will not require mention in theEing*s Speech.1)REMARKS.THE SUPER A NNUA.- THE SUPERANNUAT TON ( DIPLOMATICTION (DIPLOMATIC SERVICE) BILL.SERVICE)  BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet    35(27), Con-clusion 7.)PENSIONS (GOVERN-ORS OP DOMINIONSE&quot;&quot;0S    ACT)  AMENB-MENT BILL.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 7(27), Con-clusion 1 &amp;Appendix.PENSIONSETC(GOVERNORSACT)  AMENDMENTOP DOMINIONSBILL.INTESTATESBILL.(NORTHERN IRELAND))Subject to)further in-)formation asJto their)urgency, onWhich the)Prime Mini s t e)undertook to)inquire.POOD AND DRUGS CONSOLIDATIONBILL.THE ALIENS BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet    52(27), Con-clusion 1 &amp;Appendix.)(e) That there was no prospectof finding time for thefollowing Bills:-THE ALIENS BILL.LEGISLATION TO DEAL WITHCHARGING POWERS OPTRANSPORT UNDERTAKINGS.LONDON (VALUATION AND RATING)BILL.To be continuedund er the expiring Laws(Continuance)Act.RAILWAY RATINGBILL.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 7(27),  Con-clusion 1 &amp;Appendix).LUNACY BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 21(24), Con-clusion 5.)RAILWAY RATING BILL.LUNACY BILL.REMUNERATION OP. REGISTRARS
IRISH TREATYPENSIONERS.(PrevionsReference:Cabinet 60(27), Con-elusion 4.)(f) That the following Hillsshould stand over for later consideration if necessary:-LEGISLATION RESPECTING IRISHTREATY PENSIONERS.INTERNATIONALMART&quot; IMS CON-VENTION   BILL.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 15(87). Con-clusxon 1.)SLUM CLEARANCE.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 1(28), Con-clusion 4.)THE TOTALISATOR,(previous reference:Cabinet 54(27), Con-cl-conclusion 4.)INTERNATIONAL MARITIME CONVENTION BILL.No Billunless undo?the Gonven-tion we are bound tointroduce it(g) To take note that the Ministerof Health&apos;s plans for dealingwith Slum Improvements are not sufficiently advanced toenable a Bill to be introduced in the present Session.(h) As regards the Totalisator,that the Chancellor of theExchequer should have discre-tion to inform the supporters of this proposal that the;/ willhave to ballot for an opportunity-nity to introduce a private member&apos;s Bill, and, failingsuccess,, for introducing aResolution^  vi ttJ- /$L  ^wkJ-CtruJJ-  1**t&apos;  tn^A.    ffCi^- s-Ms^a    k **-A.   Mill    J[ ITUW ft*-     ^&quot;UJ&apos; J\
THE FUTURE OF 5. The Cabinet had before them the Report ofBRITISH 00M-MERGIAL AIR the Committee on the Future of British CommercialTRANSPORT.Air Transport (Paper C.P.-327 (27)), the(Previous recommendations of which are summarised in the reference:Cabinet 52 Report as follows i^.(27), Con-clusion 8.) (a) That the policy of concentratingair transport in the hands of asingle company   Imperial AirwaysLtd, - be continued.(b) That the Air Ministry be author-ised, in consultation with theTreasury, to enter on negotiations-tions with Imperial Airways tomodify the existing agreementsso as to provide:-(l) For giving the companysecurity of tenure overa reasonable period ofyears.(2)  For the development, in lieu of the less remunera-tive continental services,of long-distance Imperialroutes, commencing with a london-Calcutta mail service.(o) For the renewal of the com-pany&apos;s fleet at frequent intervals with the most up-to-date aircraft.(4)  For the Government to securemore favourable participationat an earlier stage in thecompany&apos;s profits.(c) That the Post Office should take special steps to promote the successof the London-Calcutta Mail Service.(d) That over a 10-year period a suffi-cient amount should be provided on the Civil Aviation Vote of AirEstimates to permit of the policy outlined at (l),  (2), (?) and (4)of (b) above being carried intoeffect   the figure to be settledannually between the Air ministry and Treasury, to whom each year&apos;programme will be communicated forprior scrutiny and concurrence inthe ordinary course.fe) That machinery should be set upto secure the closest possibleliaison between the Air Ministry,Imperial Airways, and the aircraftmanufac turing indus try .117
After the President of the Board of Trade(as Chairman of the Cabinet Committee)  and theSecretary of State for Air had made statements in regard to the Report, the Chancellor of theExchequer stated that he would not resist theproposals of the Committee,  which made no immediate addition tfe Government expenditure.He wished it to be understood, however,  thatthe financial details must be settled betweenthe Treasury and the Air Ministry, and he gavewarning that it would be necessary for him topress for a diminishing element in the cost ofany new arrangement.The Secretary of State for Air accepted this statement.Subject to the above, the cabinet approved the Report of the Com-mittee on the Future of british commercial Air Transport (paper cp.-527 (27)), the recommenda-tions of which are summarised above.
CHINA. 6.   The Cabinet had before then:! a MemorandumReduction of by the Acting Secretary of State for War 1 PaperBritish Forcesin the Far C.P.-10 (28)) covering a proposal of the ChiefEast.of the Imperial General Staff to withdraw the(Previous 2nd Battalion Coldstream Guards  from ShanghaiReference:Cabinet 62 and bring it home at an early date on account of(2V), Con-elusion 1.) the unsatisfactory state of health of the battalion, and at the same time asking approval for the route to be via the Suez Canal and forthe Transport &quot;ASSAYE&quot; to be used and dispensed with on the completion of the voyage.In the course of a discussion the Chancellorof the Exchequer expressed the hope that eventhough it might be impossible.,  owing to the stateof health of the Battalion, to transport theColdstream Guards through Canada,  the ScotsGuards might later on be brought home by this route.    In view of its importance from the pointof view of Imperial policy, he was willing tofind a small additional sum for this purpose.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,while regretting, in the present very uncertainstate of affairs in China, that a Battalionshould be withdrawn, said that,  in view of the health of the Battalion, he would not oppose itswithdrawal, on the understanding that in ease ofemergency in China one or more Battalions couldbe despatched from Hong-Kong.Subject to the above the cabinet approved the proposals of the acting Secretary of State for Warand the Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff for the withdrawalof the 2nd Battalion of ColdstreamGuards from Shanghai, and for theTransport &quot;Assaye4 to be used forthe purpose and dispensed with onthe conpletion of the voyage.
7. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the President of the Board of Trade asking the Cabinet to confirm a proposal of theChancellor of the Exchequer that the treasury should be relieved from finding a direct grantof  25,COO in 1928-29 for the British IndustriesPair and that the Empire Marketing Board shouldbe asked to subscribe this euro.Mr Ormsby-Gore, Acting Chairman of theEmpire Marketing Board, reported that the accouting Officer had informed him that theabove proposal was definitely outside the termsof the Empire Marketing Board&apos;s Vote.   Conse-quentlyB before effect could be given to itthe terms of the Vote would have to be altered.In addition, to use the Empire Marketing Board&apos;sfunds for   the purpose proposed would be contraryto the objects of these funds, as indicated toParliament by the Prime Minister himself andthe Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.Moreover, the proposal would excite real resent-ment among the overseas members of the Boardand the Dominion Governments ,,   Some of therepresentatives had already been sounded andhad objected strongly, and were bound tocontinue th^ir objections unless instructed tothe contrary by their respective Governments.He recalled that the Empire Marketing Board hadbeen given complete control over the grant0The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs was responsible to Parliament for its operations,but its expenditure was not subject to ordinaryTreasury or other Departmental control.
9 C0 0The Empire II- rketlng Board was limited by its terms of Reference to expenditure on promoting the sale of Umpire (including British) foodstuffs and raw materials in Great Britain.    This new proposal would involve the Board in expenditurewith the object of promoting the sale of Britishmanufactured goods abroad as well as at home.He strongly urged postponement of the question,at any rate until the Dominions Prime ministers had been consulted, and,  if possible, until thereturn of the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs .In the course of the discussion it waspointed out that the expenditure proposed was really in the interests of the Empire MarketingBoard itself, in order to counter the criticisms of British manufacturers that money subscribedwholly by the British taxpayer was being devotedentirely to promoting the sale of Empire food and raw materials, and that except in respect ofagricultural produce Great Britain&apos;s industryreceived no benefit.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Prime Minister should send a telegram to the PrimeMinisters of the Dominionsasking for their assent tocharging to the Empire Market-ins; Board a direct grant of 25,000 for the British IndustriesPair, and urging the adoption ofthis course in the interests ofthe Empire Marketing Board itself:(b) That the Dominions Office should submit the draft of a telegram tothe Prime Minister., 1,Tbitehall Gardens, S.W.1,January 25, 1928..

</content>
</cab>
