<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/57/0 images: 339-358</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE FROPBRTY OF HIS BRITANNIC K.AJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)S E CRJJ.Copy NoC A B I N E T    24  (28).MEETING of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10,Downing Street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,April 25th, 1928,  at 11.30 a.m.ADDENDUM TO THE AGENDA.THE UNITED STATES OF A, ERICA - ARBITRATION PROPOSALS(Item 2).       Add. the following papers :-Multilateral Treaty for the Renunciation of War,French Draft.(CP.  134 (28)    -    circulated herewith).Revised. Draft Treaty. Memorandum by the FirstLord of the Admiralty.(CP.    135 (28) circulated herewith).(Signed)    M.P.A. HAWKEY, !Secretary, Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens,   S.W.I.24th April,  1928.
0 9 fltl *) 1pnrjTMEST IS THE property OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) .COPY NO.CABINET 24  (23),MEETING of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10,Downing Street, S.C1., on WEDNESDAY,April 25th,  1928, at 11.30 a.m.AGE N D A.1. FOREIGN AFFAIRS -  (IF REQUIRED).2. THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA - ARBITRATION PROPOSALS.&quot;(IF ftEADYT.(Reference Cabinet 20 (28) Conclusion 18).Memorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs,(CP. 22 (28) - already circulated).Memorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs, covering Memorandum bySir Cecil Hurst.(CP. 35 (28) -   already circulated).Note by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs  covering despatch from H.M. Ambassador. at Washington.(CP. 53 (28) - already circulated).Despatch, from the Secretary of for ForeignAffairs to H.M. Ambassador at Washington.(CP. 58 (28)  - already circulated).Memorandum by the Historical Adviser, ForeignOffice.(CP, 73 (28)  - already circulated).Letter from Foreign Office to Dominions Office,covering two Memoranda by Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.(CP. 76 (28)  - already clrculaied) .Letter from Foreign Office to Dominions Office,covering amended Treaty.(CP. 115 (28) - already circulated).Revised draft Treaty of Arbitration.(CP. 117 (23) - already circulated).Memorandum by the Home Secretary.(CP. 132 (28) - to be circulated).
3.ANTI-AIRCRAFT RESEARCH.Note by the Secretary, covering proceedingsof the Committee of Imperial Defence.(CP.  129  (28)    -    already circulated).4.      EMPLOYMENT OP EX-REGULAR SAILORS,  SOLDIgRS and airmen.Report of Interdepartmental Committee.(CP. 106  (28)    -    already circulated).5.      PRIVATE MEMBERS&apos;   BILLS FOR FRIDAY,  4th MAY,  1928.(I) The Hire-Purchase System Bill:    2ndReading: (Sir J. Agg-Gardner  (C)).(ii) The Seditious and Blasphemous Teaching to children Bill:    2nd Reading:(Sir G, Hume  (C)).(iii)  The Blind Persons Bill:    2nd Reading:(Mr. Nay lor (La. ) ) .(Signed)    M.P.A. KANKEY,Secretary,  Cabinet.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.23rd April,  1928.
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT).o        H &apos;B T.Copy No.CABINET    24  (28).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downins Street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY,April 25th,  1928,  at 11.30 a.m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (in the Chair).The Right Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G.,M.P.. Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The M-st Hon.Thd Marquess of Salisbury,K.G.,G.C.V.0.,C.B.,  lord privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt.,M.P., Secretary of Statefor Home Affairs.I The Right Hon.Sir Lamina: Worthington-Evans,Bt.,G.B.E.,M.P., Secretaryof State for War.\The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,G.B.E.,C.M.G.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.iThe Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E.,M.C.,M,P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.[The Right Hon.W.E. Guinness, D.S.0.,M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and( Fisheries .[The Right Hon.The Viscount Peel, G.B.E.,First Commissioner of Works.The Right Hon.Lord Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W.S. Churchill, C.H.,M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Right Hon.L.S. Amery, M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies.j6 The right  Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State forIndia.The Right Hon.W.C. Bridgeman, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.Lord Cushendun, Chancellorof the duchy of Lancaster.f$   For Conclusions 1 and 2 only,
Armistice day.(previous reference:Cabinet 21(28), Con-conclusion 8.)1. The Home Secretary informed the Cabinetthat he had taken the Eing&apos;s Pleasure;    thatHis Majesty had been pleased to approve of theproposals made for the celebration of Armistice day and had indicated his intention of being present at the Cenotaph Service.   The HomeSecretary proposed, therefore, to inform theBritish Broadcasting Corporation forthwith thatthey would be allowed to broadcast the Service,on the condition that no visible apparatus was employed on the ground except one microphonein the form of a lectern.9*j i&quot;l
IRISH FREEATE.0Iapensationlairas undertide 10 ofe Artioles of-re-inforcement, 1921,aviousReference:Cabinet 16(28)Conclusion 8,2.   The Secretary of State for India informed the Cahinet that he had shown to Lord CarsonLord Cave1s letter to the Prime Minister inregard to the decision of the Judicial Committeeof the Privy Council in the matter of the IrishCivil Servants.      Lord Carson was too farcommitted to certain interests to withdraw hisMotion in the House of Lords that afternoon,even if he had wished to do so.      Moreover,there would not be much advantage in a postponement of the Debate, since sooner or later legislation will be necessary and a Debate would have totake place which would cwver the same groundas that involved in Lord Carson1s Motion.      he therefore raised for the consideration of theCabinet the question of the line he should take,in regard to which he offered certain suggestionsaccording closely with the conclusion set forthbelow.In the course of the discussion it transpired that Viscount Ealdane and Lord Dunedin,who had been Lord. Cave1 s colleagues on theJudicial Committee of the Privy Council, agreed with Lord. Cave that an error had been made, moreparticularly in regard to an essential date,and. that they were prepared to state this in theHouse of Lords the same afternoon.      There wasalso general agreement in the Cabinet that itwas extremely difficult to defend the Government1spolicy except by the admission that the JudicialCommittee had made a mistake.      The principal
t) 0 9questions at issue therefore, were -(I) whether, having regard to the importanceof maintaining the prestige of theJudicial Committee of the Privy Councilthroughout the British Empire,  it wasjustifiable, and if so, desirable, to admit that a mistake had been made;(ii) whether it would be desirable in thecourse of the Debate that Lord Cave&apos;sletter to the Prime Minister shouldbe read to the House of Lords.After considerable discussion, the Cabinet(a) That in all the circumstancesof the case the best course wasto make a frank admission thatthe Judicial Committee had madea mistake,  an admission which twoof the Members who had subscribedto the Judgment were themselvesprepared to make;(b) That in view of the willingness of the two Judges to admit themistake it was desirable in justice to the late Lord Cave,  as well asin all probability in accordancewith what he himself would have wished, that his concurrence withthe views of his two Judicialcolleagues should be made known.(c) That the Secretary of State forIndia and the Lord Chancellor shouldhave authority to use Lord Cave&apos;sletter to the Prime Minister in -such manner as seemed best, havingregard to the course which the debate might take, and to read it if they thought desirable.(d) That the Secretary of State forIndia should be careful not to commit himself as to the precise
form of the legislationvrtaich would have to be intro-duced to rectify the matter.(The Secretary of State for Indiawithdrew from the Cabinet at thispoint in order to prepare a statementtor the House of Lords on thissubject).
9 ft 1ti 4 irjgg JUDICIALCOMMITTEE OPtpflB privy council.(previous reference:Cabinet 13(28), Con-elusion 8.)S. Arising out of the consideration of thequestion referred to in the previous Conclusion,attention was drawn once more to the desirabilityof strengthening the Judicial Committee of the privy Council and bringing down the average ageof its members.The Lord Chancellor informed his colleagues of his intention to give careful consideration &apos;to the question during the next few months, andin due course, if he thought desirable, to bringproposals before them.
4. The Secretary of State    for Foreign affairs recalled that, when the negotiations for theTreaty of Alliance with Egypt had failed, he had warned the Egyptian Government that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment must stand by the Declaration of 1932,and had afterwards insisted that the AssembliesBill, the effect of which would be to paralysethe power of the police forces in Egypt to main-tain order, must not be proceeded with.    It was clear that Nahas Pasha, the Egyptian Prime Minis-ter, and his Party found t?a ems elves in difficul-ties as to how to extricate themselves from theposition,    A telegram received that morning from lord Lloyd (No. 233, of April 24th) indicated the possibility of a split in the EgyptianCabinet on the subject.Sir Austen Chamberlain proposed to authoriseLord Lloyd, 24 hours before the reconsideration of the Assemblies Bill by the Egyptian Senate,to issue a further warning to the Egyptian PrimeMinister on the lines of the proposals in lord lloyd&apos;s telegram. Fo. 250, insisting on hispreventing the Bill from becoming law.    If this further warning proved ineffective, Lord Lloydwould be authoi^ised^ within 72 hours of hisNote,  to send for ships to Alexandria and. to seize the Customs.   This firm, action appearedto Sir Austen Chamberlain essential, as to allow the Bill to pass would be to incur a heavyresponsibility not only towards our own people in Eg^pt but also towards foreigners whoseGovernments we did*not permit themselves to take measures to protect their atibjects.
The Cabinet agreed(a) To approve the course proposedby the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs as indicated above:(b) That the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs should notify the Dominions.e)   ei(The Chancellor of the Exchequer withdrewat this point.)
rprg UNITEDS^TES OP$ERICA.ArbitrationproposaIs.(previous reference:Cabinet 20(28), Con-elusion 18,5.The Cabinet had before them the following memoranda referring either to the American draftof an Arbitration Treaty to replace the Anglo-American Arbitration Treaty of 1908 or to theproposed multilateral Treaty for the renunciation of war, or to both:-A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs, datedJanuary 24, 1928, on the Franco-American Draft Pact of PerpetualFriendship and the American draftof an Arbitration Treaty to replace the Anglo-American arbitration treaty of 1908 (Paper CP.-22 (28)):A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs covering a Memorandum by Sir Cecil Hurst,the Legal Adviser to the ForeignOffice, dated February 7, 1928(Paper CP.-35 (28)):A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs dated february 15, 1928, covering an extract from a despatch by Sir E.Howard (Paper CP.-55 (28)):A Despatch from the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs to theBritish Ambassador at Washington,dated February 23, 1928 (paper c.P.-58 (28)):The british  Government and Arbitra-tion   an Historical Review by the historical Adviser, Foreign Office(Paper C.P.-73 (28)):A Letter dated March 7, 1928, fromthe Foreign Office to the dominions office, covering two Memoranda bythe Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs on the subject of the franco-American draft Pact ofPerpetual Friendship and the UnitedStates draft of an arbitration treaty to replace the Anglo-AmericanArbitration Treaty of 1908 (paper cp.-76 (28)):A Letter from the Foreign Officeto the Dominions Office, dated March28,  1928, containing amendments pro-posed by the United States Governmentto the United States draft of a Treatyof Arbitration (Paper CP.-115 (28)):
9 * f04 uA Revised Draft Treaty of Arbitra-tion with the United States,circulated by the direction ofthe Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs at the Meeting of theCabinet referred to in the margin(Paper C.P.-117 (28)):A Memorandum by the Home Secretary(Paper C.P.-1S2 (28)) in regard to paper G.P.-117 (28):A Memorandum by the First Lord ofthe Admiralty (Paper C.P.-155 (28))in regard to Paper C.P.-117 (28)):A French draft prepared as an alter-native to the American draft of a multilateral Treaty for the renunciation-tion of War, circulated by theSecretary of State for ForeignAffairs (Paper C.P.-134 (28)):The Memoranda by the Home Secretary (paper c.F.-132 (28)) and by the First Lord of theAdmiralty (Paper CP.-135 (28)) expressed appre-apprehensions in regard to the Revised Draft Treatyof Arbitration with the United States to replace the Treaty of 1908 circulated by the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs (Paper CP.-117 (28))The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs stated that he did not wish to discuss this matter in detail on the present occasion.   The preliminar-ary studies of his Department indicated that thedid not safeguard our position in Egypt and proposed multilateral Treaty/was not consistenteither with the Treaty of Locarno, our old engage-ments to Portugal, or with our obligations underthe Covenant of the League of Nations.   The matteralso had to be considered very carefully from thepoint of view of Anglo-French co-operation andthe good working between the two Powers andGermany, on which European peace depended solargely.    Sir Austen Chamberlain proposed, there-fore, at once to place himself in touch with the
French. Ambassador and would try to arrange an informal discussion between Sir Cecil Hurst andM. Fromageot, the Legal Advisers of the twoGovernments.   He would also ask M. Stresemannnot to   reply until the two Governments badcompared views on the subject.     Ultimatelyinquiries would have to be made from the UnitedStates Government as to the effect they intendedtheir proposed renunciation of war to have on the traditional attitude of the United States Govern-ment to the &quot;Monroe Doctrine&quot;.The Secretary of State added that the solepractical result so far of M. briand&apos;s ratherindiscreet initiative had been to revive contro-versy between France and the United States ofAmerica and to leave their relations worse thanthey were before.   He was very anxious lest asimilar effect should be produced upon Anglo-American relations unless the American proposals were handled with great tact and care.   In due course he would ask the Cabinet to consider thema 11 e r further.
afti-air graftresearch.6.The Cahinet had hefore them a Note bythe Secretary (Paper CP.-129 (28)) covering the Proceedings of the Committee of ImperialDefence at the 234th Meeting, held on March 29,1928, in regard to Anti-aircraft Research, inwhich attention was drawn particularly to a recommendation to the Cabinet that the necessary funds ( 5,000) for the construction of an experimental &quot;Mirror&quot; for acoustical detectionshould be provided.The Cabinet took note of, and approved, the recommendationof the Committee of ImperialDefence that the necessary funds for the constructionof an experimental &quot;Mirror&quot;for acoustical detectionshould be provided.    the incidence of the cost was left for arrangement betweenthe Departments concerned.
9 o0^0DEPLOYMENT OP 7. The Cabinet had before them the ReportEX-SERVICE MEN.a of an Inter-Departmental Committee (Paper CP,(previous 106 (20)) in regard to the employment of ex-Re ferenoetCabinet 50 Service men, circulated by direction of the(26), Con-elusion 14.) Prime Minister (Paper CP.-106 (.28)).After a short discussion, the cabinet agreed  (a) That an Inter-DepartmentalCommittee, to be preside over by the Financial Secretaryto the Treasury, should be setup to consider the question of continous pensions for service in one or other of the FightingServices and subsequently inthe Civil Service, with a viewto a possible improvement in theprospects of ex-Service men andconsequently in recruiting men for the Fighting Services:(b) That the Secretary of State forWar, in consultation with theother Ministers concerned, should draft Terms of Reference forconsideration by the PrimeMinister:(e) That the Ministry of Labour shouldbe represented on the Committee:(d) That the Report of the Inter-Departmental Committee (paper cp.-106 (28)) should stand over until the completion of the inquiry referred to above.
THE HIRE-PURCHASE 8 . The attention of the Cabinet was drawnSYSTEM BILL.to a Bill to be introduced by a Private Member(Sir J.Agg-Gardner)  on Friday, May 4th, entitled the Eire-Purchase System Bill, providing thatgoods comprised in a hire-purchase agreement shall be exempt from distress for rent, rates,etc., and excluded in bankruptcy, and shall not become fixtures.The Cabinet agreed  That the Governments interestsin this Bill should be placed inthe hands of the Law Officers ofthe Crown.
TEE SEDITIOUSAND BLASPHEMOUSTEACHING to children BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 52(27), Con-clusion 1 and appendix) .9.The attention of the Cabinet was drawn to a Bill to be introduced by a Private Member(Sir G. Hume)  on Friday, May 4th, 1928, entitled the Seditious and Blasphemous Teaching to ChildrenBill.The Home Secretary said that, in accord-ar.ce with the attitude he had adopted on similaroccasions - in the past, he proposed to leavethis Bill to the House of Commons, though hewould express a personal view in its favour.
0 J10.The attention of the Cabinet was drawn to a Bill to be introduced by a Private Member(Mr Naylor) on Friday, May 4, 1928, entitled the Blind Persons Bill.The Minister of Health -undertook to coimnunicate with the GovernmentWhips in regard to this Bill.-15-
CIVIL SERVANTS.Inquiry arisingout&apos; of the caseIronmonger v.Dyne.(previous previous reference:Cabinet 12(28). Con-conclusion 10.)11.    The Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs informed his colleagues that he haareceived an appeal from Mr 0&apos;Malley forconsideration in connection with the &quot;Francs&quot;case, and after consulting the members ofSir Warren Fisher&apos;s Committee and the PrimeMinister he proposed to announce the same afternoon in the House of Commons that he didnot Intend to accept Mr 0&apos;MalleyTs resignationbut that he would be placed en disponjhilite&apos;for a year and v?ould lose five years&apos; seniority2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,April 25, 1928.

</content>
</cab>
