<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/57/0 images: 372-386</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
n, r* p0 0 bjgjS DOQJjMEFT IS  THE PROPERTY CP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)BJL-R E T. Copy No.C A B I NET    2.6  (28) .Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10,Downing: Street, S.W.I.,  on WEDNESDAY, 2ndMay,  1928, at 12.0 noon.A 0 E N D A.FOREIGN AFFAIRS  (If required).THE TOUTED STATES OF AMERICAARBITRATIONPROPC?  LSTHE MULTILATERAL TREATY.(Reference Cabinet 24 (28) Conclusion 5).FUTURE BRITISH GARRISONS IN CHINA.Note by the secretary of State for War covering memorandum by the Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff.(CP.  136  (28)    -    already circulated).LAND PURPHASE  IF NORTHERN IRELAID .Memorandum by the Home Secretary.(CP.  146 (28)    -    circulated herewith) .SILVER IN THE  IRISH FREr] STATE.Memorandum by the Treasury circulated by direction of the Chancellor of the Exchequer.(CP. 137 (28)    -    already circulated).IRISH CIVIL SERVANTS.Note by the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs covering copy of letter to Mr. Blythe(CP. 144 (28)    -&apos;   circulated herewith).ELECTRICAL DEVELOPMENT AND AMERICAN CAPITAL.(Reference Cabinet 14 (28) Conclusion 5).Report  of Committee of Civil Research.(CP. 145  (28)    -    circulated herewith).
8.      INDIAN C 0 TR13 UT ION FOR BOMS EPP50TIVE CHARGSSOP THE BRITISH ARMY.Memorandum &quot;by the Secretary of State  for War.(CP. 130*&apos;.(28)    -    already circulated).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India(CP. 131 (28)    -    already circulated).9.      SAFEGUARDING Op INDUSTRIES - HANDKERCHIEFS and household LINEN GOODS .Memorandum by the President of the Board ofTrade .(CP. 142  (28)    -    already?;- circulated).10.      MR.   RUCHAIMS DOG RACING BILL.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.(CP. 143  (28)    -    already circulated).111.      CONCLUSIONS OF COMMITTED OF HOME AFFAIRS.(I)  The Educational Endowments   (Scotland) Bill(ii)  The Agricultural Credits Bill.(Hi) The Bankers (Northern Ireland) Bill.(H.A.C.  Conclusions  (28)   (Draft)    -    circulated here with).(Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary,  Cabinet.Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1.1st May,  1928.
D QCUHBNT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT ) .Copy No._C A B I N E JT    26  (28).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.L, on WEDNESDAY,2nd May,  1928,  at 12 noon.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (in the Chair),ie Right Hon.Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G.,M.P., Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.fhe Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,K.G.,G.C.V.0.,C.B.,  lord privy Seal.lie Right Hon.L.S. Amery,  M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies.le Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State forIndia.Ehe Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt.,D.3.0.,M.P., Secretary of State forScotland.fcie Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.B.E.,M..C. ,M,P. , Presidentof the Board of Trade.B Right Hon.W.E. Guinness, D.S.O.,M.P.,/Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Lord Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bt.,M.P., Secretary of Statefor Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Laming Worthington-Evans,Bt.,G.B.E.,M.P., Secretaryof State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,G.B.E.C.M.G.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.W.C. Bridgeman, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Ron.The Viscount Peel,  G.B.E.,First Commissioner of Works.The Right Hon.Lord Cushendun, Chancellorof the Duchy of Lancaster.
1, The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairshanded round to the Cabinet, at the otitset of theMeeting, the following documentsLord LloydTs telegram No.260,of the 2nd May, containing a rough translation of theEgyptian Note dated lat May:The draft of a reply.When the membersof the Cabinet had read these documents, theSecretary of State for Foreign Affaire read to just receivedhis colleagues a telegram/from Lord Lloyd eon-taining his comments on the Egyptian Note, theeffect of which was that, in Lord Lloyd&apos;s view,the Egyptian reply was unacceptable and that we ought to insist on full compliance with the demandcontained in the ultimatum.   The Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs, while recognising that lord Lloyd&apos;s arguments, if well-founded, were very forcible, gave the Cabinet strong reasonsfor preferring the policy set forth in his owndraft Note (See below) ,   The information which reached him indicated that Nahas Pasha was deemedin Egypt to have drawn on himself an unnecessaryhumiliation.    The Bill which he had said would be passed had been postponed until Novembere   Thegreat patience shown by the British Governmentup to the present time had given good results.He was reluctant to do anything which would givethe appearance of provoking a continuance of thepresent trouble instead of settling     it -    our policy was to discredit Nahas and the extremistsunder whose influence he had fallen;    that, whencompletely discredited, he would have to give wayto a more friendly Government;    and that there
should be in existence people able and willingto form a Government to replace him.    If, however,as advocated by Lord Lloyd, we were to insist on egyptian recognition of our unilateral Declara-tion of 1922, this would be impossible.   TheBritish Government of that day had known thatit was impossible to obtain a bilateral agreement on the lines of the Declaration.   SubsequentGovernments had realised this and had adhered tothe Declaration as a xmilateral instrument.    to insist at the present juncture on recognitionof the Declaration was to court a refusal.Moreover, no Egyptian Government could be formedwhich would be willing to recognise the Declara-tion.    Sarwat Pasha had come nearer than anyother Egyptian statesman to recognising theDeclaration in the draft Treaty which was intendedto replace it, but neither he nor any otherEgyptian statesman could explicitly recognise it.If, therefore, the British Government did whatLord Lloyd desired, it would be Impossible tofind an Egyptian Government to take the placeof the present Government.   We shotild be confrontedvirtually with a strike of Egyptian politicians,which would be very formidable and put us in a difficult position.    Lord Lloyd had never made clear what alternative he contemplated to thepresent Constitution and Government in the eventof a complete breakdown, such as might occur if his policy were adopted.    Sir Austen Chamberlain,,therefore, supported the policy set forth inthe draft Mote.
The Cabinet agreed -(a) Subject to certain modifications in the third paragraph, whichwere accepted by Sir austen chamberlain, to approve thedraft Note.( A \oopy of,,the Note as . finally approved&quot;&apos;!^ a11ached on thefollowing pageTl(b) That as the Note, if despatchedat once, would reach Cairo very shortly, Sir Austen Chamberlainshould have authority to read itin the House of Commons the same afternoon:(c) That the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs should cororrruni-cate the Note at once to theDominions:(d) To take note that the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairsintended to send a full explana-tion to Lord Lloyd.
9 n 9&quot;Your Excellency,I duly conveyed to ray government by telegraphthe contents of Your Excellency&apos;s note of May 1st, andI am now instructed to state in reply that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment have learned with satisfaction that In com-compliance with the request of His Majesty&apos;s Governmentand in pursuance of the advice tendered by Your Ex-cellency and the Egyptian government the Senate decide-ed not to proceed witii the Assemblies Bill duringthe present session.      His Majesty&apos;s Government take note of your assurance that this decision has beentaken in conformity with the ardent desire of theEgyptian government to reach an understanding and theirconciliatory sentiments.     They are therefore entitledto assume that the Egyptian government will be careful to avoid any revival of the controversy which has ledto the present crisis.2.     His Majefety&apos;s Government observe, however, thatthe intentions of the Egyptian government respecting the future of this Bill are not explicitly stated inYour Excellency&apos;s note.      In these circumstances, theythink it well to make it clear, in terms which do not admit of misinterpretation, that they regard certain provisions of the Bill as calculated seriously to weaken the hands of the administrative authorities responsible for the maintenance of ord.er and for theprotection of foreign lives and property.     If,  therefore,the measure in question were to be revived, or if other measures were Introduced which in their view presentedsimilarly dangerous features, His Majesty1s Governmentwould again be obliged to intervene,  as in the present instance, to prevent their enactment.3.     His Majesty&apos;s Government can enter into no discussion respecting the Declaration of February 1922.One of the consequences of that instrument was to en-tail upon His Majesty!s Government the responsibilityfor the protection of foreign interests in Egypt.     Itwill be clear from the preceding paragraph, that HisMajesty&apos;s Government are resolved at all times to in-sist upon a precise discharge of its terms.      This Declara-tion embodies the conditions subject to which indepen-dence was accorded to Egyptj    and His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment will not permit it to be either modified or dis-regardedo&quot;    Ends.
THE UNITEDSTATES of America.Arbitrationproposals.(Pravi previous reference:Cabinet 25(38), Oon-clusion 2.)2. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs made a statement to the Cabinet in which he recalled the whole of the circumstances leading up to the American proposal for a multilateralTreaty.    He had just heard from the french ambassador (who had returned from a visit to paris) that the French Government were in favourof the proposal he had made for a preliminary meeting of the Jurists of all the Powers concerned at the present stage, including the United Statesof America;    also that the French government attached the very highest importance to securing agreement with the British Government, in regardto which Sir Austen Chamberlain gave corroborativeevidence from other sources.    Sir Cecil Hurstand M. Fromageot, the Legal Advisers of the twoGovernments, were about to meet on some questionrelating to Zanzibar, and it was proposed totake this opportunity for them to compare notesin regard to the arbitration proposals.    TheGerman acceptance in principle of the Americanarbitration proposals had proved to be more satisfactory and more in accord with our ideasthan had at first appeared probable, and sir austen Chamberlain had therefore telegraphed to berlin to cancel his earlier proposal for ameeting between the British and German legal advisers.After discussion the Cabinet agreed  (a)  To approve the following proposals made to them by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs:-(i) That he should proceed as soonas possible with the proposalfor a meeting of Jurists of
o *? all the Powers concerned at the earliest possible date:(ii)  That he should also follownip the suggestion made byMr Kellogg, the American secretary of State, for ameeting of the foreign ministers of the powers concerned, to take place after the ground had beenprepared by the Jurists:(b) That the first step m this policy should be for the Secretary of Statefor Dominion Affairs to send a tele-gram, prepared in concert with theSecretary of State for ForeignAffairs, to the Dominions, notifyingthem of this policy and ashing foran immediate reply:(c) That the general nature of theForeign Secretary&apos;s reply to Mr.Kellogg should be   - to welcomehis initiative;    to call attentionto the fact that we had incurredcertain obligations on which thepeace of Europe and, indeed, ofthe world depends;    to note thatin a recent statement Mr Kellogghas expressed his yiewthat the proposed multilateralTreaty is not inconsistent withthese obligations;    to state thathis views will be taken into themost careful consideration;    andto suggest that the procedurefollowed with success in the Locarnonegotiations might well be adoptedin this case, namely, a meeting ofJurists, followed by a politicalConference, as contemplated byMr Kellogg:(d) That a statement should, be made inParliament at the earliest possible date when the negotiations permit.
CHINA. 3.  The Cabinet had before them a Note by theBritish Secretary of State for War (Paper CP.-136 (28))garrisons in. covering a Memorandum by the Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff on the subject of Future British(previous reference: Garrisons in China, the conclusions of which areCabinet 20(28), Con- summarised in the last paragraph as follows:-elusion 3.)(a) The present system of temporarilyincreasing the garrisons in Chinaimposes unjustifiable hardshipson the troops and on their families,through the enforced and lengthyseparation involved.    The troops have also suffered a deterioration in health owing to the unhealthyclimatic conditions, particularly at Shanghai.(b) These conditions and the lack oftraining facilities at Shanghaiare affecting adversely theefficiency of the units involved.(c) To mitigate these disabilitiesannual reliefs are, under presentconditions, essential.   The costof these reliefs can be minimisedpro tanto by a reduction in the far eastern garrisons.(d) The situation has now improved toan extent which permits thefurther withdrawal of two infantry battalions and the field company,R.E.   These units should be broughtaway from China before July ofthis year.(e) This reduction will set freeaccommodation which can be usedto house the families of therelieving units:    this will improve the amenities of life of unitstemporarily stationed in China.( f) The reductions recommended will leave eight Infantry battalions(including one Indian battalion)and one armoured car company inChina, which garrison is suffi-cient to deal with any situationwhich may reasonably be expectedto arise In the near future.(g) As regards the future permanentgarrison of China, we should aim at the evacuation of Shanghai, andthe location of sufficient troopsin Tientsin and in Hong-Kong to obviate the necessity of sendingreinforcements from England shouldanother emergency arise.
o n ftThe Cabinet were informed that theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs hadalready telegraphed to the British Minister in peking to the effect that he was much ImpressedMemorandumby the very able/of the Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff, and proposed to agree ^fagpsfeaafift,subject to any observations which Sir miles lampson might wish to offer.The First Lord of the Admiralty undertook to send a similar telegram to the Naval Commander-in-Chief.The Cabinet agreed  That unless either the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs orthe First Lord of the Admiraltydesired to bring the matter backto the Cabinet, the furtherwithdrawal from China of two infantry Battalions and the FieldCompany R,E. should be approved,and that these units should bebrought away from China before july of this year.
9 1 10 i i5HB EDUCATIONALBKDOVMENTS(SCOTLAND)  BILL,(previous reference:Cabinet 6(28), Con-clusion 8 and appendix.)4-. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum(Paper H.A.-16 (28)) by the Secretary of Statefor Scotland covering the draft EducationalEndowments (Scotland)    Bill, the object of whichis to carry out a recommendation contained inthe Report of a Departmental Committee for theestablishment of an Executive Commission with powers to review the educational endowments ofScotland and to frame schemes for their betterapplication;    together with the recommendationof the Committee of Home Affairs thereon (H.A..C.6th Conclusions (28), Para.2).In accordance with the recommendation ofthe Committee of Home Affairs, the Cabinet agreedTo authorise the introduction inthe House of Lords of the Educa-tional Endowments (Scotland) BillIn the form of the draft annexed to H.A.-16 (28), on the under-standing that the further progressof the Bill must depend on Its be ingtreated as non-controversial.
THB agricultural credits BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 6(38), Con-elusion 8 and appendix.)5. The Cabinet had before there a Memorandumby the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries(Paper K.A.-i7 (28)) covering the draft Agricul-tural Credits Bill, which has been prepared togive effect to the Government&apos;s pledges toprovide improved facilities for obtaining creditin agriculture;    together with the recommenda-tions of the Committee of Home Affairs thereon(H.A.C. 6th Conclusions (28), Para.5).In accordance with the recommendations ofthe Committee of Home Affairs the Cabinet agreed(a) To authorise the introduction forthwith in the House of commons of the Agricultural Credits Billin the form of the draft annexed to H.A.-17 (28), subject to -(i) the Law Officers being satisfied as to the legalpoints of detail:(ii) the addition, if theChancellor of the Exchequeragrees, of a provisionexempting the instrumentcreating a charge underPart II from Stamp Duty;and(iii) any drafting or other minor alterations that may be foundnecessary or desirable:(b) To approve the Tabling of thenecessary Financial Resolution.The Cabinet also agreed thatthe Secretary of State for scotland should have authority to consult the Banks with a view to the pre-paration of a separate Bill forScotland.(MOTE:    Y/ith regard to (a)(ii) above, theMinister of Agriculture and Fish-eries has informed the Secretaryof the Cabinet that the Chancellorof the Exchequer has agreed to theaddition of a provision exemptingthe instrument   creating a chargeunder Part II from Stamp Duty.)
6. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum(Paper H.A.-18 (28)) by the Financial Secretaryto the Treasury, covering the draft Banters(Northern Ireland) Bill, the main objects ofwhich are to give effect to an agreement betweenthe Treasury and the Irish Banks for the reduc-tion of the aggregate amount of the fiduciarynote issues in Northern Ireland and to restrict the putting in circulation of notes issued outof the United Kingdom;    together with the recom-mendation of the Committee of Home Affairs thereon(H.A.C. 6th Conclusions (28), Para.4).In accordance with the recommendation ofthe Committee of Home Affairs, the Cabinet agreed -To authorise the introduction inthe House of Commons of the Bankers(Northern Ireland) Bill in the formof the draft annexed to H.A.-18 (28),on the understanding that the further progress of the Bill will depend onits being treated as uncontroversial.
safeguarding of INDUSTRIESHandkerchiefsand HouseholdLinen Goods.(previous reference:Cahinet 21(28), Con-clusion 4.)7. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the President of the Board of Trade (paper c.P.-142 (28)) covering the Report of aCommittee set up under the Safeguarding ofIndustries Procedure to enquire into Handker-chiefs and Household Linen Goods.    The Presidentof the Board of Trade proposed to proceed withthe publication of the Report at once, but,in view of the conclusions reached by theCommittee, did not recommend the imposition ofa Duty.The Cabinet approved the proposalsof the President of the Board ofTrade.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,May 2,  1928.

</content>
</cab>
