<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/28/21 images: 196-211</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESxVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   September 1942.SECRET.W.P. (42) 391.September 4, 1942.WAR CABINET.INDIA.Indian States :  Request by Chamber of Princes for Statement ofPolicy by His Majesty&apos;s Government.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.THE Chancellor of the Chamber of Princes (the Jam Saheb of Nawanagar)is very shortly arriving in this country and will almost certainly ventilate thismatter while he is here. It is very desirable to be in a position, whenever herefers to the matter (which he may take an early opportunity of doing), to saythat the Crown Representative is already composing his reply on lines whichcan be indicated broadly to him as set out in this paper. Unless, therefore,any of my colleagues wish the matter to be discussed in Cabinet, I propose to despatch the draft telegram (Annexure E) to the Crown Representative not later than the 8th September.2. The Chancellor, in his letter of the 1st June to the Viceroy&apos;s PoliticalAdviser (Annexure B), complains : (I) of the failure of the Draft Declaration of March 1942 to include an assurance that the British Government stands by its treaty obligations to the States, and of the apparent intention to impose a revision ofthese treaties on the Rulers;(II) of the Lord Privy SeaPs remarks in the House of Commons on the28th April [Hansard, Cols. 834 and 835), which the Chancellorinterprets as meaning that the Paramount Power intends to imposedemocratic institutions on the States;(III) of various smaller  grievances  in connection with  the   &quot; CrippsNegotiations,&quot; which, on the whole, need not concern the War Cabinet(except for the complaint that, by joining an Indian Union, they might involve themselves in secession from the Empire);(IV) of the absence of recognition of the right of non-adhering States likenon-adhering Provinces to form a separate Union of their own.3. In the view of the Viceroy and his advisers the Princes feel genuinelythat their interests were insufficiently considered both in the Draft declaration and in the discussions arising from it. The Viceroy accordingly suggests(Annexure A) that a considered reply, &quot;the nature of which can only bedetermined by His Majesty&apos;s Government,&quot; should be sent. I have accordinglyagreed with the Viceroy (Annexures C and D) on the following line of reply : I. The absence from the Draft&apos; Declaration of a special reference to theStates&apos; treaty rights is of no significance; the Prime ministers statement of the 11th March made quite clear that the fulfilment of treaty obligations to the States remains an integral part of HisMajesty&apos;s Government&apos;s policy. Moreover, these treaties will only be altered by negotiation and agreement;[24305] copy No.
II. The Lord Privy Seal said that the House would wish the british administration in India &quot; to do all it can to encourage and expedite the development of suitable representative institutions in all indian states.&quot; This does not necessarily mean the imposition of democracy(which in any case might be quite unsuitable). It means that the paramount Power will continue, as at present, to urge upon Rulersthe establishment of institutions for representing the views andgrievances of their subjects with a view to their being remedied(viz., administrative reformsj-constitutional changes (which might involve restriction on the Ruler&apos;s powers) may or may not be a sequel,but that is for the Rulers themselves to decide; no pressure tointroduce such changes will be applied by the Paramount Power on the ruler, as it is in the case of administrative reform. (This conformswith what has been said here in Parliament as recently as 1938 andwith the Viceroy&apos;s own pronouncements on the subject in India. the argument, though somewhat sophistical, is at any rate consistent withour declared policy in a matter on which the Princes are very sensitive.)III. Replies on the minor points need not concern us (the secession point is covered under IV);IV. Between now and the next Indian constitutional discussions the Princesmay certainly consider the outline of a scheme for a separate Union, ifthey wish. They might also consider what terms they might wish to demand of an Indian Union before they join it, e.g., the right to secedefrom the Union if the Union secedes from the Empire. Considerationof these points could certainly not be excluded from futurediscussions.[In actual fact, the Viceroy hopes and proposes that we suggestprivately to the Princes that the idea of a separate States Unionmight be used by them merely as a bargaining counter to secure better terms for accession to an Indian Union, and not as a serious objective.This seems sound.]- 5. The question arises whether a reply on these lines should be published.The Viceroy assumes it will; my view is that it should not, since it is in effect an explanation of why we consider that there should be no new declaration of policy towards the States at this stage. If the reply does not have the effect of satisfying the Princes, and if the Jam Saheb presses the matter strongly, it might conceivably be necessary to make some statement in Parliament, but I am anxious to avoidit since there is little we can say and it/might make matters worse for them bystimulating criticism in other quarters.6. Finally, the Viceroy/and I remain agreed that we should press on as vigorously as possible with measures (such as internal organisation, pooling of judicial and police services between co-operative groups of States, absorptionwhere possible of the administration of smaller by that of larger States, &amp;c.)towards making the lesser States more fit for survival in the modern world.The Viceroy hankers a little after a public pronouncement reaffirming theCrown&apos;s existing obligations to protect the States, linked, with a warning thatwe interpret this only to mean protection of such States as are fit to survive.I am against any more pronouncements, and particularly against a qualification of the treaty obligations. It is because internal reforms are in the States&apos; own interests that I think we should continue to urge the Rulers to adopt them.7.   The course of action I propose to authorise is therefore : (a) the issue in India, on behalf of the Viceroy to the Chancellor of theChamber of Princes, of a reply on the lines laid down in paragraph 4,indicating no change in our policy towards the States.(b) this reply to be expressly limited to confidential circulation among the princes (hints of its contents may no doubt leak out in due course,but it will not be in any sense a formal declaration).(c) the avoidance of any new formal declaration about the sanctity of the princes&apos; treaties at this stage, even though it is possible that we might have to make some reference to the subject in an Indian debate(even this however I should prefer to avoid).(d) the continuance and intensification, so far as this can be done withoutalienating the more important Rulers, of our present  policy of,   bringing the States into line with modern administrative standards.L. S. A.India Office, September 4, 1942.
ANNEXURE A.Letter from the Secretary to the Crown Representative to the India Officedated June 25, 1942, No. D. 494-P. (C.)/42.Subject.-Draft Declaration of His Majestys Government policy towards India.Sir,I AM directed to forward for the information of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment a copy of a letter dated the 1st June, 1942, on the above subjectfrom His Highness the Maharaja Jam Saheb of Nawanagar.2. His Highness&apos;s letter is carefully documented and it will be seen thatit is signed by him in his capacity as Chancellor of the Chamber of Princesand is described in the final sentence as an official letter. It concludes witha specific request that &quot;an authoritative and early announcement.&quot; should bemade by His Majesty&apos;s Government in order &quot; to eliminate the Princes&apos; serious concern and misgivings on these matters.&quot;3. His Excellency, the Crown Representative has little doubt that suchconcern and misgivings are in fact genuinely entertained by the great majorityof Indian Princes, particularly by the more conservative among them, and isnot inclined to attach any great importance to such public declarations in the opposite sense as have been made.by Their Highnesses of Kashmir and Indore.The Princes may to some extent derive comfort and- reassurance from thegenerous terms in which His Majesty has referred in his message to Indiapublished on the 13th June, 1942, to &quot; their traditions of loyalty and attachmentto his Throne&quot; and to their unstinting offers of men and money and personal services for the war. But they are not likely to be reassured by a referenceto the fact that Sir Stafford Cripps&apos;s offer was in terms withdrawn when thenegotiations broke down. The Princes probably feel that, should negotiationsbe resumed in the event of the great political parties in British India showinga more responsive attitude, the Cripps declaration would certainly form the starting point of such negotiations and would be r-egarded as the minimummeasure of concession and advance open to discussion.4. In particular, perplexity is expressed in paragraph II (a) of theChancellor&apos;s letter with regard to the statement made by the Lord Privy Seal inthe House of Commons to the effect that he was &quot; certain that this House would wish the British Administration in India to do all it can to encourage and expedite the development of suitable representative institutions in all Indian States.&quot; Itis impossible to reconcile this statement with the earlier declaration of policy ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government made in the form of replies to questions asked inParliament in 1938 and referred to in his Excellency the Crown Representative^address to the Chamber of Princes in 1939. On the first occasion, on the 21stFebruary, 1938, the Under-Secretary of State replied that &quot;it is not the policyof the Paramount Power in ordinary circumstances to intervene in the internal administration of full-powers States.&quot; This was confirmed on the 16th Decemberof the same year when the reply given to Sir John Wardlaw-Milne was that&quot; His Majesty&apos;s Government have no intention of bringing any form of-pressure to bear upon Rulers to initiate constitutional changes. It rests with the Rulersthemselves to decide what form of government they should adopt in the diverseconditions of Indian States.&quot;5. There thus exists a direct discrepancy in a matter of cardinal importance,which, in his Excellency&apos;s opinion, requires elucidation at the earliest possible opportunity, since, if the view expressed by the Lord Privy Seal is to be inter-preted as the considered view of His Majesty&apos;s Government as now constituted,our existing policy in regard to constitutional reforms in States stands in need of radical revision.6. I am also to invite particular attention to paragraph III (d) of theChancellor&apos;s letter which contains a brief and surprisingly restrained referenceto what is perhaps the most legimate of all, the objections which the Princes couldraise to the draft&apos;declaration, namely, that by acceding to  he new Union theywould be committed to a possible perhaps even probable severance of their[24305] B 2
cherished relations with the British Crown. His Highness has not. mentioned the obvious remedy, i.e., that in joining the Union the States should be allowedto reserve the right to secede from it if at any time the Union were todecide to leave the British commonwealth of Nations. His Excellency believes that, in the absence of such a provision, few, if any, of the great States would join the Union.7. In conclusion. I am to make it clear that his Excellency is strongly ofopinion that so fully documented a communication, emanating from such a sourceand couched in terms of genuine apprehension, clearly calls for a definite answer, the nature of which can only be determined by His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment.(Signed) K. S. FITZE,Secretary to His Excellency the Crown Representative.ANNEXURE B.Letter from H.H. the Maharaja Jam Saheb of Nawanagar to Sir Henry Craik,Political Adviser to the Crown Representative.Council House,My dear Sir Henry, New Delhi., June 1, 1942.THE Indian Princes have no desire to raise any controversial issues in the -duration of the war and wish to concentrate all thought and energy on ensuring a speedy and decisive victory. Accordingly, as you are aware, it has been mypolicy as. Chancellor to postpone all avoidable matters which have no directbearing on war effort and which may be inconvenient to meet at this juncture.Nevertheless, certain recent happenings, arising out of the Cripps Mission, have caused, and are bound to accentuate, grave anxiety to the Princes and their loyalsubjects, and have occasioned intense feeling of profound disappointment in theStates. These developments, I must state in all frankness, have been a particularshock to the Indian Princes who feel special personal attachment to His majesty the King Emperor, and have full faith in Britain&apos;s respect for Treaties and in thebona fides of His Majesty&apos;s Government and His Excellency the crown representative. I feel confident that it could not have been the intention of HisMajesty&apos;s Government to create an impression which, unfortunately, has been created and is being exploited by those who are opposed to war effort and who wishto put a damper even on the unconditional and spontaneous war effort of theStates. Accordingly, I deem it my duty to state briefly but in all frankness themore important of these points, so that you may submit them to His excellency the Crown Representative with the request that he may urge upon His Majesty&apos;sGovernment the necessity of reassuring the States, unequivocally and withoutdelay, on these points and thereby dispel the misgivings which are apt to dogreat harm : 1. (a) The Indian Princes regard their Treaties and Engagements and theprotection guaranteed thereunder as the sheet-anchor of their relationship withthe British Crown.(b) The scrupulous respect for these Treaties and Engagements has beensolemnly assured to the States by Her Majesty the late Queen Empress Victoria,by the Emperors who succeeded her and by successive Viceroys on behalf of HisMajesty&apos;s Government. In this connection, attention niay be invited, by way ofillustration, to the following solemn declarations lest they be forgotten : (i) Her Imperial Majesty the late Queen Victoria gave the followingassurance in her famous Proclamation of 1858 : &quot; We hereby announce to the Native Princes of India that all treaties and. Engagements made with them by or under the authority of the Honour-able East India Company are by US accepted and will be scrupulouslymaintained . . . We shall respect the Rights, Dignity and Honour of NativePrinces as Our own.&quot;(ii) The following significant words were used by Lord Morley, thenSecretary of State for India, when referring to the aforesaid Proclamation of
Queen Victoria at the Second Eeading of Indian Councils Bill. House of Lords,the 23rd February, 1909 :-&quot;... the noble promise in Queen Victoria&apos;s Proclamation of 1858-a promise of which every Englishman ought to be for ever proud if he triesto adhere to it, and ashamed if he tries to betray or to mock it .(iii) In a message, on the outbreak of the Great War, 1914, His majesty the late King Emperor George V announced that &quot; Paramount regard for treaty, faith and pledges, words of rulers and peoples is the common heritage of England and India.&quot;Later in his Proclamation of 1921, His Majesty the late King George was pleased to state &quot; In My former Proclamation I repeated the assurance given on many occasions by My Royal predecessors and Myself of My determination ever tomaintain unimpaired the privileges, rights and dignities of the Princes ofIndia. The Princes may rest assured that this pledge remains inviolate andinviolable.&quot;(iv.) Lord Halifax, a former Viceroy of India, in a recent speech statedwith reference to Princes &apos;&apos; They and their States do not fit easily into the picture of India as theCongress Party would like to draw it. Yet the independence of the Princesis enshrined, in solemn treaties with the King Emperor and as such are onlyalterable by negotiations. To scrap these or any other treaties unilaterallywould be to scrap one of the principles for which we went to war withGermany.&quot;&quot; The Congress, the Muslim League, the Depressed Classes and the princes were four major factors which must combine if India was to be suffiently united to assume the rights and duties of full manhood amongnations.&quot;(v) The Montagu-Chelmsford Report stated as follows in paragraph 305 :  &quot; . . . . we think that the Princes should be assured in the fullest andfreest manner that no constitutional changes which may take place wrillimpair the rights, dignities, and privileges secured to them by treaties,sanads, and engagements, or by established practice.&quot;(vi) The following relevant and important statement was made by theButler Committee (1928-29) :-&quot; 58 . . . . the States demand that, without their own agreement, therights and obligations of the Paramount Power should not be assigned to persons who are not under its control, for instance, an Indian Government inBritish India responsible to an Indian legislature. If any government inthe nature of a dominion Government should be constituted in British India,such a Government would clearly be a new Government resting on a new andwritten Constitution. The contingency has not arisen; we are not directly concerned with it; the relations of the States to such a Government would raise questions of law and policy which we cannot now and here foreshadowin detail. We feel.bound, however, to draw attention to the really graveapprehension of the Princes on this score, and to record our strong opinionthat, in view of the historical nature of the relationship between the Para-mount Power and the Princes, the latter should not be transferred without their own agreement to a relationship with a new Government in british india responsible to an Indian legislature.&apos;&apos;&quot; 106 .... we hold that the treaties, engagements and sanads havebeen made with the Crown and that the relationship between the ParamountPower and the Princes should riot be transferred, without the agreement ofthe latter, to a new Government in British India responsible to an Indianlegislature.&apos;&apos;(vii) It will be conceded that Princes and States are not a hindrance but anasset to the Empire, both in peace and war. As stated by Lord Canning, in a despatch dated the 30th April, 1860, to the Secretary of State for India &apos;&apos; The safety of our rule is increased, not diminished, by the maintenanceof Native Chiefs well-affected to us. . . . .&quot; In the Mutiny &quot; these patchesof Native government served as breakwaters to the storm which would other-
wise have swept over us in one great wave. And in quiet times they have their uses; .... and should the day come when India shall be threatened byan external enemy, or when the interests of England elsewhere may require that her Eastern Empire shall incur more than ordinary risk, one of our bestmainstays will be found in these Native States. But to make them so, wemust treat their Chiefs .... with consideration and generosity, teachingthem that, in spite of all suspicions to the contrary, their independence is safe.....It was long ago said by Sir John Malcolm that if we made allIndia into Zillas it was not in the nature of things that our Empire shouldlast fifty years; but that if we could keep up a number of Native States ....as royal instruments, we should exist in India as long as our Naval superiority in Europe was maintained.&apos;&apos;(c) His Excellency the present Viceroy also has, in his public addresses as also in private conversations, repeatedly assured us of the scrupulous respect forthe Treaties and Engagements which bind the Indian Princes and their loyalsubjects to their beloved King Emperor. Moreover, the Indian Princes have beeninspired by the fact that His Majesty&apos;s Government has gone to war for the highprinciples of civilisation which specifically include respect for Treaties andEngagements.(d) It was, therefore, with particular satisfaction that the Indian Princesnoted that the Declaration of August 1940, as elucidated authoritatively inParliament by the Secretary of State for India, was intended specifically toensure the Crowivs treaty obligations to States. As such, it has been a great disappointment to the Indian Princes that the new draft Declaration brought bySir Stafford Cripps which, in the words of the Prime Minister, sought to clothewith precision the Declaration of August 1940, omits altogether the reference toCroAvn&apos;s Treaty obligations to States which had been one of the basic planks ofall previous Declarations relating to the constitutional advance of India. Thisinexplicable and unexpected omission, of the Crown&apos;s obligations to States, inthe Draft Declaration has not unnaturally caused great misgivings in the minds of the Princes and their loyal subjects. In fact, it has openly been asked whetherthe Princes were being ignored as they had no nuisance value; while the Princesthemselves feel that their spontaneous and unconditional war effort deservedbetter than the deletion in the Draft Declaration of the express guarantee of theCrown&apos;s obligations to them assured in the Declaration of August 1940.(e) Moreover, it has given occasion to Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru and others to declare publicly with great flutter that these Treaties must be scrapped, and,in fact, he (Pandit Jawaharlal) has recently gone to the extent of declaring thatthose who talk of Treaties with Indian States are &quot; lunatics, knaves or fools.&quot;He appears to have forgotten, of which he was reminded in a published statement by my Secretary, that even the All-Parties Report, presided over by the latePandit Motilal Nehru (father of Pandit Jawaharlal) and signed among othersby the Rt. Hon&apos;ble Sir Tej Bahadur Sapru, specifically recognised that the States&apos;Treaties must be respected in any future constitution of India.(/) It is significant that the Draft Declaration makes special&apos;mention ofthe protection of &quot;racial and religious minorities,&quot; and in referring to thispoint Sir Stafford in his recent statement in the House of Commons stated that &quot; In view of our pledges, we could not leave the minorities to rely upon this alone. We, therefore, inserted an express clause as to the treatygoverning minority protection, which will be found in paragraph c (2) ofthe Draft Declaration.&quot;The States are surely entitled to claim even more than the minorities that thesolemn undertakings with them must be scrupulously respected, particularly asthey have the honour of alliance and friendship with the British Crown andhave consecrated it by their unconditional assistance and co-operation in all crisiswhich faced the Empire.(g) In this connexion, attention may also be invited to the provision at theend of clause (c) of the Draft Declaration that &quot; Whether or not an Indian State elects to adhere to the Constitutionit will be necessary to negotiate a revision of its treaty arrangements so faras this may be required in the new situation.&quot;This statement has created the impression that it is proposed to have a compulsoryrevision of treaty arrangements whether or not the States concerned consent tosuch revision.  In later elucidation we were told that this provision was intended
to apply to economic matters of common concern to British India and the States,but this has not been clearly stated in the Declaration itself. Moreover, even ifit be so, it is obvious that the objective in view could be secured by negotiatingsupplemental Treaties with regard to these economic matters arising out of thenew Constitution without affecting or revising the whole of the original Treatiesor Engagements. Besides, it should be made clear that the execution of thesesupplemental treaties would obviously be subject to free consent of the states concerned.(A) Apart from considerations of Treaty obligations and faith in plightedword which bind the British Crown and the Princes in relationship which isinviolate and inviolable, the Princes are imbued with genuine and deep loyalty to the. person of His Majesty the King Emperor. As such, I personally, andmany others who share my views, decline to believe that the Crown wishes togive up its obligations to States or has no further use of them or finds theiralliance, their loyal co-operation, services and assistance of no value, or that theCrown is advised that it will not be in a position effectively to discharge its obligations towards States.(i) Nevertheless some of these recent utterances have caused grave concernand personal shock to many of us, and it is felt that if matters are left as theyare in the present position, they are bound to have serious repercussions onthe younger and future generations of Princes, a consequence which must bedeplored in the interests of the British Commonwealth of Nations as muchas in the interest of India and the States. Moreover, the situation is already being exploited by some of the British Indian political parties who are hostile to the British connection.(;&apos;) In view of the aforesaid considerations, I would urge with ail the emphasis at my command that the earliest opportunity may be utilised to assure the States, through an authoritative statement on behalf of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment, that the British Government stands true to, and firmly by, itsTreaty obligations to the States and will continue to protect them accordingto these solemn obligations.II. (a) The other matter which has recently caused grave concern to theIndian Princes is the following statement reported to have been made bySir Stafford Cripps in the course of his recent speech in the India Debate inthe House of Commons on his return from India : &quot; Unfortunately in my view representative institutions have not yetdeveloped in a great majority of the Indian States .... I aim. certain this house would wish the British administration in India to do all it canto encourage and expedite the development of suitable representativeinstitutions in all Indian States.&quot;If this report be correct, you will appreciate that Sir Stafford appears to havebeen misinformed, and his statement is in conflict with the unequivocaldeclaration on this subject made on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government byHis Excellency the Viceroy at the Session of the Chamber of Princes held in1939.(&amp;) In this connection attention may be invited to the following extracts : (i) In the course of his address to the Chamber Session 1939, His excellency the Viceroy stated as follows : &apos;&apos; Your Highnesses will have seen the declarations recently made inParliament on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government, declarations &quot;which Ihave myself repeated in public utterances, in regard to constitutional changes or developments in the Indian States. Those statements will havemade clear the attitude in this matter of His Majesty&apos;s Government, whichis, I repeat, that the decision as to the constitution best suited to the needsof his people and his State rests with the Ruler himself to take, and thatno pressure will be brought to bear on him in this respect by the paramountPower. Nor will any obstruction be placed in his way by the paramountPower should he wish to give effect to constitutional advance consistently with his Treaty obligations.&quot;&apos;(ii) In the statement of constitutional and administrative reformsintroduced in the States since the 1st January, 1936, up to the 15th April, 1942,issued by the Political Department, it is stated that &quot;In regard to Constitutional developments, the policy of the paramountPower has been clearly laid down and repeated in recent declarations in
Parliament. It is for the Ruler himself to decide what form of constitution is best suited to the needs of his subjects, and the Crown representative and his officers refrain from offering advice in this respect unless they areinvited to do so. Several Indian States already possess highly-developedconstitutions, and the general tendency is to advance in a genuine attemptto associate the subjects on the State with the administration.&quot;(iii) In the course of my review at the last Chamber Session, following figures were cited by me &quot;90-5 per cent, of the population of our States possess local bodieswith non-official majorities. States with 72 per cent, of the populationhave got Legislative Assemblies, out of which 35-3 per cent, have majorityof elected members and 5 per cent, have equality of elected and nominated members of the Assembly. States representing more than half of, our total population have recently reviewed and enlarged the scope of associationof their subjects with their administrations.(c) The aforesaid statement of Sir Stafford has caused anxious concernamongst the Indian Princes, who had already been seriously perturbed over the omission of any reference to the Crown&apos;s Treaty obligations to States in theDraft Declaration brought by Sir Stafford Cripps and by the recent loose talk about the revision of treaties.(d) I feel confident that the Indian Princes can rely on His Majesty&apos;sGovernment and His Excellency the Crown Representative to reassure them, atthe earliest opportunity, that the aforesaid statement, of Sir Stafford does notin any manner prejudice the sacred assurances given by the late Queen Victoriaand successive Emperors and Viceroys and confirmed in the declaration madeon behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government by His Excellency the Viceroy asreproduced in sub-paragraph (&amp;) of this paragraph.III. Let me also refer briefly to a few other factors which have contributed to the aforesaid anxiety of the Princes: I am citing them in the confident hopethat the view-point of the Princes will be kept in view if and when similar circumstances recur again.(a) Certain important matters relating to defence, were discussed inconnection with the Cripps Mission, and representatives of the Congress andMuslim League were brought into consultation with His Excellency theCommander-in-Chief to evolve proposals connected with the appointment of an indian Defence Member. You will appreciate that, both under their treaties and otherwise, the States are vitally concerned in this matter, and yet in these negotiations the States have entirely been ignored.(&amp;) Various important references, made in connection with the CrippsMission both in India and in the House of Commons, have been confined toBritish India and Indian leaders as if the Indian States did not matter. Somuch so, that it was stated that representatives of certain parties andcommunities, which were specifically mentioned, had expressed their readiness to stand by Great Britain in the defence of their country. No reference tothe spontaneous and unconditional support of the Indian Princes and their loyalsubjects was made in this authoritative statement by the Lord Privy Seal.(c) Throughout the R.T.C. and previous constitutional discussions, the rulers and their Ministers where treated by His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;and theirrepresentatives, as they should be treated, as the sole accredited representativesof the States. This time, however, presumably through the efforts of PanditJawaharlal Nehru and others, Sir Stafford Cripps received a British Indianas representative of the so-called State Subjects Conference, which is an adjunctof the Congress and generally speaking is a self-assumed tribune of the verysmall minority of disgruntled elements in the Indian States. We do not knowwhether this step was taken with the concurrence of His Majesty&apos;s Government,but at any rate it has placed the Princes in a very awkward position vis-a-vistheir loyal subjects. In this connection, it may be pointed out that even the All-Parties Report of 1928, to which reference has been made in sub-paragraph (e) ofparagraph I above, recognised &quot; that the Rulers of the Indian States alonerepresent their governments.&quot;(d) It seems authoritatively indicated that once a State adheres to theproposed Indian Union it will have to remain there even if the Union shoulddeclare itself a Republic, or decides to break away from the British Empire, ordecrees that monarchical rule in the States should be replaced by Republics.
(e) We have been told that the proposed constitution-making body would be free to discuss internal affairs of the States, though on previous occasions it was clearly understood that constitutional discussions will be limited to matters ofcommon concern to British India and the States which appertain to the Centre.In this connection, let me invite attention to the resolution (copy attachedAppendix A)t passed unanimously at the last Session of the Chamber of Princesand the relevant extracts (copy attached Appendix B)t from my speech in movingthe aforesaid Resolution, which would show that the Indian Princes aresympathetic to, and are prepared to make every reasonable contribution for, theconstitutional advance, of India. They desire, however, that they should be keptfree from purely British Indian controversies and that British India should not interfere with the internal affairs of the States.(/) During the Cripps Negotiations, reference has been made to only &quot; arepresentative of India on the Imperial War Cabinet,&quot; and the names of certain british Indian leaders were openly canvassed for it. In this connection, it maybe pointed out that in the Imperial War Cabinet and Conference of 1917 as also at the Peace Conference of 1919, both Indian States and British India wereseparately represented.IV. It is appreciated that in the interests of India and the Empire as &amp;.wmole, a single Union would undoubtedly be the best solution of India&apos;s constitu-tional problem; at the same time, it may be that unforeseen circumstances maycompel a large number of States or groups of States not to adhere to the newUnion. Accordingly, the States Delegation asked Sir Stafford Cripps that inthat contingency, the non-adhering States should be accorded the option of having a Union of their own with full sovereign status in accordance writh asuitable and agreed procedure devised for the purpose. It was pointed out that provision to that effect had been made for non-adhering Provinces. We were told that this eventuality had not been considered in connection with the draft declaration. This shows that apart from receiving treatment better than theProvinces to which the States are entitled on constitutional and historic grounds,they were not being treated even on a par with the Provinces in respect of future constitutional developments.2. Many of the aforesaid points have already formed subject of my talks with His Excellency the Crow-n Representative and yourself, and some of them have also been intimated to you under my directions by my Secretary. Moreover,they have recently been taken up by His Highness the Maharaja Sahib ofBikaner, with his characteristic thoroughness and ability, personally with HisExcellency the Viceroy. At the same time, in view of the importance of thismatter both to the future of the Empire, India and the States, as also to thesuccessful prosecution of the war, I have felt it my duty to address this officialletter in the confident hope that His Excellency the Crown Representative willbe pleased to impress it, with his personal support and authority, on the urgent and sympathetic consideration of His Majesty&apos;s Government, so that an authoritative-tive and early announcement on this subject may be forthcoming to eliminate the princes&apos; serious concern and. misgivings on these matters.Yours sincerely,(Signed) DIGVIJAYSINHJI, Chancellor,Chamber of Princes.ANNEXURE C.Telegram, from Secretary of State to Crown Representative, dated august 16, 1942.14395. Your Secretary&apos;s letter of 25th June, D 494-P (C)/42. I confessthat Chancellors letter seems to me to consist largely of debating points, but Iof course accept your judgment as to feeling of Princes generally. I note thatyou leave nature of reply to His Majesty&apos;s Government, but before they are askedto take final decision I should like to let you know line I have provisionally inmind on which I shall be grateful for your comments. I will of course have tohave informal talk with Jam Sahib here, as regards which see paragraph 9 below,but reply to Chancellor will no doubt be made formally by your Political adviser to whom letter is addressed.t Not reproduced.[24305] . . c
2. Point I. As regards (a) to (/). answer to the Chancellor is contained inPrime Ministers statement on 11th March (to which he himself refers) and inhis own letter of 10th April to Sir S. Cripps. - These appear in White Paperpresented to Parliament in April, and make it quite clear that (1) fulfilment of treaty obligations to Princes is an integral part of His Majesty&apos;s government&apos;s policy, (2) this was recognised and welcomed by the States&apos; representativesthemselves. No public declaration at present stage could add anything to what has already been said, and absence of specific mention in draft declaration has nosignificance. As regards private assurances, the Chancellor has apparentlyoverlooked the answer by Sir S. Cripps to question 5 of States Delegation of2nd April, see summary sent by Turnbull to your Private Secretary and toChancellors Secretary on the 5th April. Presumably important Princes will havebeen, informed privately of this discussion, and nothing can be clearer thanstatement that &quot; we will provide for everything necessary to implement our treaty obligations with non-adhering States.&quot; Cripps&apos;s answers 3 and 4 indicate thatin the absence of any provision or reservation a Ruler&apos;s adherence to Union would,under the terms of the declaration, automatically dissolve the existing mutualobligations of the Crown and the States, and that any subsequent relationsbetween the Crown and the Ruler would be through the Union. I do not under-stand that this was accepted by the Princes in all its implications, but whiletransference to the Union of the major part of the mutual obligations wouldresult from adhesion, the Princes might, of course, propose as a condition ofadhesion that certain specific matters (e.g., in connection with succession) remainreserved to the Crown Representative. See also my comment on point 3 (d). Asregards (g) word negotiate which was used in draft declaration shows that nounilateral denunciation is intended. Moreover, Cripps himself, in answer to question 9, made it clear that treaties of non-adhering States will not be revisedwithout their consent, (h) is of course covered generally by King Emperor&apos;message broadcast by Duke of Gloucester on 12th June. Moreover, there has been no suggestion that any State would be under compulsion to adhere to Union.3. &quot; Conclusion, with reference to (i) and (j), is that formal pronouncementat this stage on lines suggested would not only be superfluous, in view ofassurances already given publicly and privately to Princes, but would confusesituation and immediately raise question why it was being made, what it addedto previous statements, whether it heralded some new move by His Majesty&apos;sGovernment, &amp;c. His Majesty&apos;s Government can hardly believe that the participation by the Princes and their subjects in the defence of their country could be in any way affected.4. Point II. I think Chancellor reads too much into Lord Privy Seal&apos;remarks. He takes &quot;representative institutions&quot; as necessarily synonymouswith &quot; democratic system of goverment.&quot; Sir S. Cripps did not disguise hisown personal view that ideally representatives of States in constituent body should be &quot; popular representatives.&quot; But he also made it clear that HisMajesty&apos;s Government recognise that they must deal with matters as they are,and that what is hoped for is the development of a system of representativeinstitutions that -is suitable. Sir S. Cripps&apos;s -remarks are therefore not inconsistent with what we have consistently urged upon Princes in their own interest in regard to internal reforms. For instance, in your speech to an informal meeting of Princes on 13th March, 1939, when referring to the establish-ment of methods and institutions by which the subject may express his wants,you added &quot; and the more closely these arrangements approximate to repre-sentative institutions, the more effective.&quot; The phrase need not therefore alarmthe Chancellor. It remains His Majesty&apos;s Governments policy, not in their own interests so much as in those of the Princes themselves, to urge strongly uponRulers the establishment and effective maintenance of machinery &quot;whereby the legitimate wants and grievances of subjects oan be brought to notice so that theymay be freely and promptly set right.&quot; (I quote from your speech at Jaipur on28th February, 1939.) Whatever the ultimate outcome may be. there is nothing in Lord Privy Seal&apos;s words to indicate a change of policy by His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in regard to abstention from the imposition on States of constitutional reform.5. Point III. (a) So long as the fundamental responsibility for the controlof the Armed Forces remained in the hands of the Commander-in-Chief, theinterests of the States were not affected. As there was no intention of departing from this position. Sir Stafford Cripps did not consider it necessary to consult the States Delegation in regard to the Defence formula. 1
(.6) is of course covered by His Majesty&apos;s message broadcast on 12th June.(c) The British Indian in question was not received as a representative ofthe States : Sir S. Cripps saw many people, e.g., M. N. Roy, opposed to theexisting order of things in British India, and was ready to see informally as many people as possible who expressed a sectional point of view.(d) In the absence of any provision to the contrary in the body of the Union&apos;sconstitution or in the terms of adhesion of any particular unit, this is no doubt the case. The possibility is one which the States must take into account when considering the desirability of their adhering, but there would be nothing toprevent Rulers making, as the price of their adhesion to the Union, a stipulationeither as regards the constitution as a whole (e.g.. that it declares for irrevocableunion with the Crown, or that it can only sever that union subject to specificprovisions such as a two-thirds vote of two-thirds of the Provinces and States),or as regards their Own right to secede from a Union which severed its connectionfrom the Crown. (It is, of course, for careful consideration how far it isjudicious to put these points into the minds of Princes at this stage.)(e) It is difficult to see how the constitution-making body can be debarred from discussion of internal affairs of States so far as concerns the machinerywhereby the Union Government would function. In any case, it would hardly bepossible to lay down in advance the procedure which the body would adopt. Butthe function of the body would be to frame a constitution, and it would be opento the States&apos; representatives to refuse to take part in any discussions outsidethat limit.(f) has of course been answered by the Jam Saheb&apos;s mission.6. Point IV. Formation of a separate States Union would of course raisemuch more difficult and complicated problems than formation of Unions based ongeographically compact British Indian areas. Point has not been considered byHis Majesty&apos;s Government, but should not be regarded as ruled out. Indeed, if a plan on the lines of draft declaration again comes under consideration, HisMajesty&apos;s Government would have no option but to discuss question of separateUnion with Princes, if they had a practicable proposal of that nature to putforward, and there is of course no reason why in meantime they should not try to work out among themselves some scheme as basis of discusison.7. Subject to any comments from you I would propose that your PoliticalAdviser&apos;s reply to the Jam Saheb should follow above lines. Two major points of policy arise. First, as reply hints, I feel it is essential in interests of Statesthemselves that introduction of administrative reforms generally, including ofcourse representative institutions for reporting wants and grievances to Durbars,and. particularly effective arrangements for the grouping of smaller States, shouldbe pressed forward and that impetus created by yourself and Wylie should bemaintained. To slacken our efforts on the ground that we should not upset the princes at this juncture would be a disservice to them and a dereliction of our duty. Whether they come into a Union or stay out, or even if no Union is created,they will inevitably depend, for their continued existence on the efficiency andliberality of their administration. Whatever our interest in their survival, itcan hardly be as great as their own. Secondly, the question of a separate StatesUnion or in the light of geographical considerations of several such Unionsseems to be one that, however reluctantly, we must face. Clearly, we cannot beexpected to produce a ready-made scheme or even to say off-hand whether the thingis possible. But on the assumption that it should be a cardinal feature of our policy to assist the States in standing up to the stresses and strains of- politicaldevelopments in British India (see my letters of the 16th May, 1941, and 27th May,1942) the Princes&apos; own suggestions to Cripps for facilitating this deservesympathetic consideration. I would be very grateful for the benefit of your views and those of your expert advisers, who indeed might be able in due course toconsider the possibilities on broad lines in conjunction with the StandingCommittee of the Chamber. This seems to me to be the most honest and profit-able way in which we can endeavour to salve any wounded, feelings of the Princes.8. As time is short before Jam Saheb arrives here I have thought it well to telegraph. You will, of course, understand that any apparent cuftness is dueto desire for brevity; reply sent on your behalf to Chancellor would, of course,need to be more elaborate.9.   As you are aware, necessity for amendment of Section 93 will mean ageneral Indian debate in Parliament in October, and. if circumstances so demandI would endeavour to say something to reassure the States.   This will largely[24305] * - - d
depend, no doubt, on attitude of Jam Saheb, to whom, if he raises the matter,I will, of course, give a sympathetic hearing. But any talk I have with him wouldbe quite informal and without prejudice. I would not be drawn into any generalexposition of the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government towards States nor treatJam Saheb as having come here as the accredited representative of Rulers&apos; viewson this subject. I should say that of course he will get reply to his letter throughPolitical Adviser and subject to your comments that I expect it will be on above lines. Needless to say I would decline to be drawn into a discussion of the precisemeans by which His Majesty&apos;s Government would discharge their treaty obligations to non-adhering States in the various hypothetical possibilities thatthe future may hold.10. In order that I may be in a position to deal with Jam Saheb on his arrival I shall be glad of your very early comments.ANNEXURE D.Telegram from Croivn Representative to Secretary of State for India,dated August 25, 1942.2591-P. Am grateful for your telegram 14395 of 15th August andmaterial supplied therein to enable me to meet misgivings entertained by Princes,who, in my judgment, had no desire to raise debating points, but were genuinelydisturbed by extent to which in Draft Declaration and throughout negotiationscentre of stage was reserved for British Indian elements whilst rights and merits of States, received little, if any, open acknowledgment. In particular, onlyreference&quot; to treaties in Draft Declaration announced necessity for their compre-hensive revision.2. Admittedly, position was further elucidated in discussions with sir S. Cripps, but his assurances remain unknown to elements hostile to Statesand were in some important respects not regarded as satisfactory by Princesthemselves. For instance, his reply to question 5, which you say was apparentlyoverlooked, was, in fact, specially brought to notice of Maharaja of Bikaner in personal discussion with Political Adviser. His Highness then observed thathe found difficulty in placing confidence in such an assurance, since Sir S.Cripps&apos;s replies to supplementary questions on the same point showed that hehad no practical ideas as to where necessary force would come from. This lackof faith will probably persist in the minds of Princes generally until it isdispelled by detailed exposition of actual intentions.3. In the same connection Princes are probably anxious as to who is toprovide for supply of such force, as also for financing Political Department,maintenance of which will be necessary for non-adhering States. No new IndianUnion could be expected to do so. Have His Majesty&apos;s Government consideredassumption by themselves of these liabilities?4. Subject to your approval, my Political Secretary will now send toMaharaja of Bikaher as pro-Chancellor reply, on the following lines toChancellors letter (with copies by air mail for yourself and Jam Saheb), making it clear that its contents have been authorised by His Majesty&apos;s Government: 5. Point I. (a) to (/). Princes should be sufficiently reassured by clear statement that fulfilment of treaty obligations to States remains integral partof His Majesty&apos;s Governments policy, and that absence, of specific mentiontherefore in draft declaration has no significance. Reference would also bemade to Prime Ministers statement of 11th March. Points (g) and (h) will bedealt with on lines suggested by you. As regards (i) and (j), I presume thatobjections stated in paragraph No. 3 of your telegram to &quot; pronouncement &quot; atthis stage would not be applicable to assurances wnich we are now in position togive in reply to major apprehensions of States as expressed by Chancellor. Suchreply must be sent, and, though not&quot; amounting to public pronouncement, will certainly be widely circulated to Princes and published outside Princely Circlesby Chamber&apos;s organisation, on whom we could hardly enjoin secrecy in such a.matter.
6. Point II. Relevant speeches by me have been carefully phrased to advocate responsible rather than democratic Government, and I need not stressdiffei &quot;ences between remarks made to strictly private and informal gathering- of princes, the proceedings of which were never to be circulated, and views expressed in Parliamentary debate by Leader of House. Also, we have hithertoscrupulously refrained from any language calculated to affect or question thefull discretion of Princes in regard to selection of representatives of States atconstitution-making or similar bodies. However, I think reply as in last sentence of paragraph 4 of your telegram should allay misgivings.7. There need now be no difficulty over Point III (a), (&amp;), (e). and (/). Ipropose to ignore III (c), as I doubt if explanation suggested by you would carryconviction.8. Point III (d) and IV may be taken jointly together with relevantobservations in paragraph 2 of your telegram. I propose replying that adherence to Union would be for their discretion, but that it would, of course, be open toStates to endeavour to negotiate terms which would set at rest the apprehensionswhich seem to have prompted III (d) of Chancellors letter.I would point out, with reference to Point IV, that it is open to them duringsuch time as may be available before future political structure of India againcomes under active discussion to consider comparative advantages from their point of view of (a) separate union of their own, and (b) securing by negotiationterms of adherence to Indian Union, which would meet such apprehensions asthey may entertain in regard to such matters as possible severance of the irrelations with Crown and future regulation of their personal and dynasticaffairs; and I should like to add that neither of these alternatives need be regardedas necessarily inadmissible, though, as regards former, nothing more thantentative formulation of a scheme which could serve as basis for discussion is atpresent suggested.9. For His Majesty&apos;s Governments information, I have following furtherobservations to offer : Of two alternatives set forth in preceding paragraph, I regard second as definitely preferable, because any attempt to set up separateUnion of States side by side with one or more Unions of Provinces, quite apartfrom obvious and probably insuperable difficulties presented by geography, &amp;c,must inevitably lead to trial of strength as between popular and monarchicalforms of Government, and that, too, in a form which would embroil the Crownin its capacity as guarantor of Princely India, despite its more modern functionas champion of democracy. In such circumstances, prospects of continued existence of States in anything like present form must soon become moreprecarious than if they entered all-India fold on terms designed to protectminimum essentials.I suggest, therefore, that our line should be to encourage Princes to use theidea of separate States Union not so much as end in itself, but as the powerfulbargaining factor for negotiating reasonable terms on which they could adhere to new Union with some or all of the Princes.10. If you agree I trust you will take this line in discussions withJam Saheb. I suggest also your impressing upon him vital necessity that allinfluential elements in Princely India should in their own interests do the utmost to secure that schemes for co-operative administration are taken seriously and carried into early effect. This is important because His Highness, in his capacityof Chancellor, has shown tendency to associate himself with selfish and&quot; short-sighted objections raised by rulers in Eastern States and elsewhere to such schemes. Obvious purging and strengthening of weaker elements and some formof regional combine affecting all States, except very largest, would be essentialpreliminaries if States as a whole are to attempt formation of Central Unioninter se or to puil their weight inside any Union with other elements. For thisreason I cordially endorse view expressed in paragraph No. 7 of your telegramthat our efforts in that direction should not be slackened subject always to proviso that it would be most unwise in present emergency to do anything likely seriouslyto antagonise the more important rulers, whose goodwill and co-operation are atthe moment an asset of special value to us. I suggest, however, that strong and authoritative advice in favour of combine would carry more weight if combined with some sort of equally authoritative pronouncement reaffirming sanctity of treaties, subject to its being understood that our liabilities will not be interpreted as applicable to protection of anything unworthy of survival in modern conditions.
11. Subject to your approval my advisers will take the first opportunityof expounding these ^doctrines to Standing Committee. Meantime you will nodoubt consider possibility of propagating them in your private or public-utterances.ANNEXURE E.Draft telegram from Secretary of State to Crown Representative.MANY thanks for your telegram of &quot;25th August, 2591-P. His Majesty&apos;sGovernment agree with conclusions in paragraphs 4 to 10, subject only tofollowing reservations, and letter on these lines may issue forthwith.2. - Paragraph 5, last sentence. They notice that Jam Saheb&apos;s letter wasmarked &quot; Secret &quot; and assume reply will also be so marked. They quiteappreciate it will receive wide circulation, but consider this should be onconfidential basis and that it should be made clear that publication is not intended.Indeed, object of letter would be (a) to remove as far possible genuine apprehen-sions felt by Princes, particularly those mentioned in I (i) of Jam Saheb&apos;s letter,(&amp;) to show that His Majesty&apos;s Government do not recognise any need for public statement at this stage either to reaffirm treaty rights, or to gloss Sir S. Crippsremarks on reforms, or in regard to separate States Union. As I said in para-graph -9 of my telegram of 15th August, there might be opportunity in Octoberfor reference to subject in parliamentary debate if reactions to present replyrendered that imperative. But His Majesty&apos;s Government see great danger of anything they may be able to say (a) not satisfying Princes, (b) stimulatingcriticism in other quarters and embarrassing discussion as to real meaning ofour pledges.   I propose to take this line if necessary with Jam Saheb.3. Your paragraph 10. I am very glad that you accept the view expressedin paragraph 7 of my telegram 14395 as to taking opportunity to stress necessityfor improved methods of States&apos; administration in Rulers&apos; own best interests.But rather than that, as suggested in last sentence, your advice to them on thismatter should be linked to a pronouncement regarding sanctity of treaties (forsuch conjunction might be open to interpretation that treaty position was beingqualified by new condition), would it not be better to take the line that the crown representative to whom the Princes look for support must expect from them, intheir own best interests a conformity with world opinion in regard to adminis-trative standards as it has developed since relations with them were originallyestablished and as exemplified in the administration of British India ?



</content>
</cab>
