<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/63/54 images: 578-581</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[S DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT-ikiti V&quot;.cp i- p Printed-jor the&apos;War Cabinet.   March 1945.SECRET. / Copy No.W.P. (45) 199. /27th March, 1945. war CABINET.TRADES UNION INTERNATIONAL AND SAN FRANCISCO.    -Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I circulate herewith a record by the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs of a meeting in the Foreign Office about Trade Union repre-sentation at the San Francisco Conference, held in accordance with the decisionof the War Cabinet (W.M. (45) 33rd Conclusions, Minute 4 (2) ).2. As I understand it, the position is that the United States are not prq-posing to invite to San Francisco as observers representatives from any non-governmental body of any kind. Thus they are contemplating issuing invitations to the League of Nations, the International Lahour Office, and one or two other international organisations, but to nobody else. Even here the principle is thatinvitations to send observers can only be issued if all the &quot; sponsoring &quot; Govern-ments agree. In other words, one blackball excludes. Flence, if the Soviet union should not agree to the suggestion that the I.L.O. should send an observer, weshall have to acquiesce : and in no case could we, even if we so desired, successfullysupport a request by the new Trades Union International to send an observer,since this would be opposed by the United States.3. On the other hand, I understand that the United States Government takethe view that they cannot prevent anyone from sending their own representatives to San Francisco provided such representatives make their own arrangements.No facilities would, however, be granted to such representatives. yr4. So far as the Trades Union International is concerned, therefore, thesituation seems completely clear They can if they so desire send representatives to San Francisco, but they would have to make their own arrangements and nofacilities would be given to them.A. E.Foreign Office, 27th March, 1945.ANNEX.Meeting at the Foreign Office on 22nd March, 1945.Present:The Foreign Secretary, the Lord President of the Council,Sir Walter Citrine and Mr. George Hall.Sir Walter Citrine enquired whether a decision had been arrived atconcerning the application on behalf of the Trades Union General Council thatthe British representatives of the World Trades Union Congress which recentlymet in London should be allowed to make representations to the four major Powersmeeting at San Francisco. The decision of the Cabinet on this matter wasconveyed to Sir Walter Citrine by the Secretary of State and the Lord President,and he expressed himself as being very dissatisfied with it.12723   [29528]
2. In the course of the discussion Sir ;WaJ.tei? submitted a request that arepresentative of the T.U.C. should be officially attached to the British delegationas an observer, particularly to deal with matters concerning the Economic and social Council. Sir Walter referred to the Ottawa Conference, when the T.U.C.and the British Employers&apos; Federation had had representatives appointed asadvisers to the Government delegation; he thought that this arrangement had worked very satisfactorily, and he could see no reason why similar official repre-sentation would not be equally successful at the San Francisco Conference. It waspointed out to Sir Walter that, if such a British Trades Union delegate were allowed to attend the Conference, the British Employers&apos; Federation^ applica-tion to be represented also would have to be conceded. Sir Walter said he wouldhave no objection to this.3. Sir Walter again repeated the application for the Joint InternationalTrades Union Organist-ion to be allowed to make representations to the fourmajor Powers at San Francisco. He was informed that this could be done inwriting. He strongly protested, as he thought their representative should beallowed to have access as he had suggested and to make verbal statements.Sir Walter was insistent that these matters should be reconsidered by the Cabinet,for he thought (on what evidence I do not know) that the other major powers would agree to the requests which he was making to the British Government.He was of the opinion that the British representatives would find themselves ina position inferior to that of the other International Trades Union representa-tives. Both the Secretary of State and the Lord President pointed out to him that they could hold out no prospect that the Cabinet would reverse the decision which had already been made.4. In the course of the discussion the question of the relationship betweenthe International Trades Union Conference and the International LabourOrganisation. was raised. Sir Walter maintained that the I.L.O. as a bodywas separate from the new International Trades Union body. The functionsof the I.L.O. were in his opinion very limited, and he understood that the negotiating body of the I.L.O. would be present at San Francisco, when the relationship between it and the new International Security Organisation wouldbe fully considered. In his view, however, even if the functions of the I.L.O. werestrengthened and its independent powers retained, he could see no reason whythere should be a clash between it and the International Trades Union Organisa-tion. Their interests were quite separate and distinct, particularly as regardsthe proposed Economic and Social Council to be set up under the world organisation.G. H. H.Foreign Office, 23rd March, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
