<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/257/0 images: 270-272</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS^OCUM^ OF HIS BRITAJ1HIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).SB OS E T.m^P9(55% COPY NO.     4 I .FINAL COPY.CABINET.THE KING&apos;S SPEECH ON THE OPENING OF PARLIAMENT.3rd December,  1955.The accompanying copy of the King1s Speech on the Opening of Parliament, which has now heen approved &quot;by His Lajesty,    is circulated in substitution of the draft version which was before the Cabinet at their meeting on 27th November&apos;,  1935 (Reference Cabinet 49(35), Conclusion 5).(S signed d) Ivl. P. A.  HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.-1, 2nd December, 1935. -
The King&apos;s Speech on the Opening of Parliament.December 3, 1935. .My Lords and Members oe the House of Commons,MY relations with foreign Powers continue to be friendly.My Governments foreign policy will as heretofore be based on a firm support of the League of Nations. They will remain prepared to fulfil, in co-operation with other members of the League, the obligations of the Covenant. In particular, they are determined to use at all times the full weight of their influence for the preservation of peace.In pursuance of these obligations My Government have felt compelled to adopt, in co-operation with some fifty other States Members of the League, certain measures of an economic and financial nature in regard to Italy. At the same time they will continue to exert their influence in favour of a peace acceptable to the three parties in the dispute, namely, Italy, Ethiopia, and the League of Nations.My Government have issued invitations to the Governments of the other countries which were parties to the Washington and London Naval Treaties to attend a Conference in London this month with a view to the conclusion of a new international treaty for the limitation of naval armaments. I have learned with satisfaction that all the invitations to this Conference have been accepted, and I trust that its labours will be crowned with success.Members of the House of Commons,The Estimates for the Public Service will be laid before you.The fulfilment of our international obligations under the Covenant, no less than the adequate safeguarding of My Empire, makes it urgently necessary that the deficiencies in My Defence Forces should be made good. My Ministers will in due course lay before you their proposals, which will be limited to the minimum required for these two purposes.My Lords and Members of the House of Commons,The policy of My Ministers, while continuing to foster the general recovery of trade, industry and agriculture, will pay special regard to those areas in which the burden of unemployment is greatest and to the development of any measures likely to be advantageous to them.The problem of securing improved conditions in the coal-mining industry is receiving the anxious consideration of My Ministers. Active steps are being taken to co-ordinate the selling arrangements of the industry and the necessary orders under Part 1 of the Coal Mines Act, 1930, will be laid before you.In pursuance of the policy of re-organisation, a Measure will be introduced to provide for the unification of coal royalties under national control.In the opinion of My Government the time has come when the existing provisions for the safety of workers in mines should be reviewed in the light of modern scientific knowledge. I shall, as soon as possible, appoint Commissioners to inquire fully into this important matter.12384
Proposals for making improved arrangements for assistance to the unemployed and for the insurance of agricultural workers against unemployment will be laid before you.A Bill will be introduced to authorise the guarantee by the State of a loan to be raised for the&apos; purpose of enabling the Railway Companies to carry out special developments which will add to transport facilities and to the convenience of travellers. :      ,A Measure will be submitted to you for promoting the further development of our civil air communications, both in this country and throughout the Empire; and for dealing with other matters relating to air navigation.It is the intention of My Ministers to proceed at an early date with the proposals laid before the last Parliament for dealing with the problem of surplus productive capacity in the spinning section of the cotton industry.My Government are convinced of the need for an early and substantial development of the educational services of the country. A Bill will be introduced to amend the law in England and Wales relating both to the age of compulsory school attendance and to assistance from public funds towards expenditure on Voluntary School buildings. Action will also be taken, in co-operation with Local Authorities and others, to increase the effectiveness of the other educational services. In particular, the improvement of the school medical arrangements, the extension of physical education, and the development of Technical Schools, will receive the attention of My Government.My Ministers will continue to promote actively the development of the social services, and to take vigorous measures to improve the health and physique of the nation. They will press forward the work of slum clearance in order to ensure that the programmes submitted by local authorities are carried out within the period contemplated, and they will encourage the active administration of the Housing Acts of 1935 which enable local authorities to make a direct attack upon the evils of overcrowding.Careful consideration has been given by My Government to the organisation of the maternity services with a view to providing better care for women in child-birth, and a Bill will be introduced for the provision by local authorities in co-operation with voluntary associations of an organised service of salaried midwives.My Ministers will continue to give close consideration to the further improve-ment of conditions in Scotland and among Measures to that end a Bill will be introduced providing for the raising of the school age.Other Measures of importance will be laid before you and proceeded with as time and opportunity offer.And I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may rest upon your deliberations.

</content>
</cab>
