<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/257/0 images: 325-335</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT^;Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1935.CONFIDENTIAL. Copy No.CP. 217 (35).CABINET.GERMAN REARMAMENT.Note by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I CIRCULATE to my colleagues three recent despatches from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Berlin Nos. 1129, 1160 and 1178 on the rearmament of Germany and German expansionist aims. These despatches emphasise the tremendous efforts and sacrifices which are being made in Germany in the cause of rearmament. They point out that the peace which Germany desires is a German peace; that in certain National Socialist quarters the possibility is contemplated of successful action for the rectification of the German frontiers before even rearmament is complete; and that the present imbroglio in Abyssinia is mere child&apos;s play compared to the problem with which these German claims will in.some not very distant future confront His Majesty&apos;s Government.The Foreign Office have long urged that these tremendous preparations&apos;, which embrace not only the fighting services, but the whole body of the nation, were not being undertaken without a definite purpose in view; that they might well be completed more rapidly than has at times been estimated; and that, in any case, there Avas no guarantee that Germany would await the absolute completion of her preparations before demanding satisfaction on certain of her claims.These despatches fully justify the warnings of the Foreign Office, and I think that they will convince the Cabinet that there is no time to lose in the preparation and completion of our own defensive arrangements. That is not to say that defensive measures and counter-armaments are the only reply which we can make to what is in progress in Germany. But they are the essential accompaniment and, so far as possible, prelim.in.ary of any agreement to discuss with the German Government the changes which, in Herr Hitler &quot;s own words, are almost certainly necessary to prevent &quot; an explosion in the future.&quot;I hope shortly to be able to circulate a further paper about the German situation.S. H.Foreign Office, November 25, 1935.(1)Sir E. Phippsto Sir Samuel Hoare.(No. 1129.)Sir, Berlin, November 6. 1935.IN his despatch No. 890 of the 13th September, 1933, Mr. Newton reported on a mass meeting of school-children held with the explicit object of spreading the cult of pan-Germanism. The principal feature of the gathering was the formation by the children of a living map of Germany, outside which stood detachments representing the Saar, Memel, Danzig, &amp;c. At a given signal the frontiers opened and engulfed the German communities abroad. The same idea was expressed by means of another simile in General Goring&apos;s speech at saarbrucken reported in my despatch No. 1124 of the 5th November. He likened Germany to a giant magnet with an irresistible attraction for Germanism abroad.
2. It is a favourite Nazi theory that the unification of Greater Germany will come about not through aggressive outwards pressure by Germany herself, but by the pressure on the German frontiers of the German communities abroad. In other words, Germany will take no active steps to absorb these communities because they will herd themselves irresistibly into their mother&apos;s arms.3. From this point of view some interest attaches to the enclosed copy of a minute by the military attache on the views held in certain Nazi circles regarding the rectification of the German frontiers. There is little doubt that consideration has been given to the situation which would arise if a revolt against the existing Government were to break out in the German districts over the frontiers, either spontaneously or with unofficial help from the Reich. In such a case, if the rising were successful, no action on the part of the army would probably be necessary, except to ward off any threat of foreign intervention. In other words, the action of the German army would be purely defensive or precautionary, as was that of the Italian army after the murder of Dr. Dollfuss in July 1934.4. It appears from paragraph 3 of Colonel Hotblack&apos;s minute that the army probably do not approve being cast for the role described above. Nevertheless, since, in the opinion of the military attache, the German army will &apos;&apos; very soon &quot; be in a position to defend the frontiers, I have thought it well to -draw your attention to the fact that Nazi circles contemplate the possibility of successful action for the rectification of the German frontiers before the reconstruction of the army for all purposes has been fully carried out.I have, &amp;c.ERIC PHIPPS.The Germans Outside Germany&apos;s Eastern Frontiers.Chancery.1. I find that some individuals of the voluntary S.S. (black-uniformed Party guard) have visited privately during the recent months Memel and Western Czechoslovakia. Those selected seem to have been well-educated university graduates.They have been told that it is not Hitler&apos;s wish to raise the question of the eastern frontiers at present, but that the terrible treatment being accorded to Germans outside Germany may compel him to take action at an earlier date.They understand that their task will be to go to the assistance of their ill-treated comrades, whilst the role of the army will be a purely defensive one to prevent the invasion of Germany by other Powers.2. They believe that the army will not be ready &quot; for all purposes &quot; for several years, but that it will very soon be in a position to defend frontiers.3. As far as I have been able to ascertain, army officers do not like the idea of semi-political action, and consider that only a fully-equipped army with adequate reserves can solve the problem of Germany&apos;s eastern frontiers.ELLIOT HOTBLACK, Military Attache.Berlin, November 1, 1935.(No. 1160.)Sir, Berlin, November 13, 1935.AS you will have gathered from my reports, the salient feature of German social, economic and political life is the reconstruction of the armed forces. It is difficult to drive along any road in this country without seeing striking evidence of the truth of this statement. On every side giant military establishments are springing up. There are few towns of any importance where barracks or military schools are not being built, some of them still far from completion. Enormous aerodromes either finished or under construction march, sometimes for miles, with the main road. The armed&apos; S.S. sentries at the gate of many factories and the high barbed wire fence surrounding them proclaim their military character. The streets of provincial towns are gajf with uniforms; military cars and lorries painted in camouflage colours mix with civilian traffic. In the air the ceaseless hum of aeroplanes bears witness to the expansion of the German air force.
2. In every German circle military service is a staple subject of conversation. Friends and relations are being called up for short courses or, in the case of young men. for their regular period of service. The relative merits of the respec-tive arms or of garrison towns are eagerly canvassed. The press plays its part in stimulating public enthusiasm. The departure of recruits for their new units is written up. Photographs of smiling soldiers in the barrack rooms advertise the jollity of the military life. Articles describe the material prosperity which has descended on the garrison towns; farmers, cobblers, barbers, butchers and tradesmen of every kind gleefully welcome the incoming troops. Bands play on the market square, and military displays are organised for the grateful townsmen. The armed forces and their creator, Herr Hitler, are the heroes of the day.3. Germans complain that English public men, in particular Mr. Winston Churchill, are apt to concentrate their attention exclusively on German rearmament. They never, it is said, refer to the social achievements of the German Government, to the reduction of unemployment, for example, or to the improvement in labour conditions or to the work of the &quot; Kraft durch Freude &quot; organisation. To depict the German Government as engaged solely in rearmament shows a lack of balance and sense of proportion. The error, if error it be, is one of which the Nazi leaders are almost equally guilty. Since March of this year the members of the Government have not ceased to exploit to the full the enthusiasm of the people for their new toy. Relatively little has been heard of social policy; the trump card has always been the crowning mercy of German rearmament. At Nuremberg and Btickeberg the army topped the bill. In the admonitions of Dr. Goebbels on the food shortage, in General G6ring&apos;s recent speeches at Breslau and Saarbrucken and in the press the nation is urged to endure all for the sake of rearmament. You cannot have butter and an army, says Dr. Goebbels; be grateful that the Government have made the decision for you and given you the army.4. It is not disputed even by Government spokesmen that rearmament will require serious sacrifice on the part of the population. There is no published budget, and it is impossible to make a reliable estimate of military expenditure. The Hungarian military attache, who occupies a somewhat special position here, states that the barracks for the German army and air force this year were estimated to cost 2 milliard reichsmarks ( 100 million at par). This sum, he says, has already been exceeded, apparently as a result of the cost of the new Air Ministry, with its 2,500 rooms. The Daily Telegraph correspondent has received information from what he believes to be a good source to the effect that the military estimates, exclusive of capital expenditure on buildings, &amp;c, amounted this year to 2^ milliard reichsmarks ( 125 million at par). The naval attache calculates the cost of new construction for this year on the basis of the normal programme at 200 million reichsmarks ( 10 million at par). This programme does not represent even half the total required to bring the German fleet up to full strength under the London Agreement, even supposing that England builds no new ships. In addition, there is the normal &apos;&apos; recurring expenditure &quot; to be met. In 1934 the vote for this item was 130 million reichsmarks. There are now more ships and more personnel, and it would be surprising if this sum had not been doubled. Finally, there is the air force. Here it is impossible even to hazard an estimate. All that can be said with certainty is that the air force is large., and that money, material, and, indeed, human life, are being prodigally spent. The army complain of General Goring&apos;s extravagance, and the air force openly demand a special standard of comfort in view of the dangerous character of their peace-time occupations.5 It may be asked : For how long will the people bear material privation in order to maintain this enormous military machine ? A German diplomatist, hostile to the present regime, expresses the opinion that the average German is a gross materialist who can always be got at by his stomach. The Nazi party is; also showing signs of anxiety. The issue of food cards, for which preparations have been made, has been postponed, and may be definitely ruled out by Herr Hitler as politically undesirable. Every effort is made to allay discontent and to avoid the spread of alarming rumours. An Englishman in Leipzig was recently interfered with because it was erroneously believed that he had
photographed a food queue. Nevertheless, although discontent may be rife, it cannot become articulate or effective under a regime which is backed by force, and which in Herr Hitler5 s words is plainly determined to exterminate its enemies with &quot; brutal ruthlessness.&quot; Above all it must be remembered that the country is virtually living in war conditions, a state in which the Government has unlimited power, and in which the people are prepared to endure more than in time of peace.6. Except that battles are not being fought, Germany may be said without exaggeration to be living in a state of war. Everything is subordinated to the needs of the defence forces. The Government controls the distribution of raw materials and the output of the factories. The military chiefs are in complete control of the armed forces; there is no parliamentary or civilian interference. A high degree of secrecy is still preserved. To quote the words of the liaison officer at the War Ministry, officers may not enter the houses of foreign diplomatists except by special permission, which in principle is not granted. The American service attaches now ring up the War or Air Ministries to ask if so and so can come to lunch or dinner before they approach the officer in question. The discussion of military matters is prohibited. It is high treason to impart information even of a nature not considered in the least confidential abroad. The death penalty is inflicted for the betrayal of official secrets; it is also inflicted on Communists and may be inflicted on all who obstruct &quot; the work of national regeneration.&quot; The political police is powerful, numerous and as well supplied with funds as secret services usually are in war time.7. It is not surprising that in these conditions discontent caused by the food shortage and the rise in prices cannot be articulate. Perhaps the most discouraging feature of the position is the fact that, so far as I can ascertain, the populace are prepared to make considerable sacrifices to rebuild the army. The average citizen remarks ruefully that so long as Germany fulfilled the stipulations of the treaty she got nothing but kicks and cuffs. No sooner had she taken matters into her own hands than Berlin began to enjoy the visits of foreign statesmen. References to Germany to-day by European political leaders are respectful and guarded. In a word, there is general agreement with General Goring.that the sacrifice of a quarter of a pound of butter in order to &quot; recover the national honour &quot; is not only good sentiment but good business. .How long the docility of the country will continue depends on too many unascertainable factors. During the war German opinion withstood the strain for at least two years longer than foreign observers expected. But even then the Government was hampered by the latitude given to the parliamentary parties, and later to persons more or less openly promoting disaffection. Dr. Scheffer, discussing this very point with a member of my staff, remarked that with the present Govern-ment in power Germany would never have been driven into surrender. Herr Hitler, you will recollect, made a somewhat similar observation during his conversations with Sir John Simon and Mr. Eden. At Munich on the 9th November. last Herr Hitler said in his speech that in 1914 the outbreak of war involved no difficult decision on the part of the individual in Germany; on the contrary, it involved the decision to march out, &quot;to the infinite joy of millions.&quot; If war were to break out to-day, I have little doubt that the order to march would be received with infinite joy again. In any event, if public resent-ment at the present state of affairs were to increase, and if the Nazi party were to fail in its task of maintaining internal peace, the army, for whom the nation is tightening its belt, would see to it that there was no effective interference in the execution of its plans.8. It is difficult at present to. say when the process of rearmament will be judged to be complete. Meanwhile, as a German lady living in a garrison town remarked : &quot; If war came I don&apos;t think I should see much difference, except that I might be woken at night by bombs instead of by these endless squadrons of low-flying machines.&quot;9. That military expansion will be followed by territorial expansion goes without saying, though Germans in private conversation often say it. The question asked is where and not whether Germany should expand. Dr. Schacht, reasonable and moderate as ever, confines himself, for the present at any rate, to demanding that Great Britain and France should present Germany with Togoland
and the Cameroons, in order that he may be able to buy raw material with marks instead of &quot; Devisen.&quot; He deigns to recognise (always for the present), that there might be difficulties in the way of a return of &quot; South-West &apos;? or of Tanganyika. General von Reichenau, however (see my despatch No. 472 of the 15th May last, copy enclosed), and other military authorities advocate expansion in the east of Europe, with a transfer of populations. General von l31omberg told me last month that if Germany were not allowed to expand &apos;&apos; the kettle would some day burst&quot; (see my telegram No. 228, Saving, of the 10th Oetobov-. copy enclosed).10. All Germans agree in considering any attempt, whether by the League of Nations or by general pacts of &quot;collective security,&quot; to stabilise the status quo and to prevent Germany&apos;s expansion as highly reprehensible and, indeed, immoral. Such attempts, they hold, can only end in war and in a war waged by Germany at any rate in the most righteous of causes.11. It will be seen that the present Ethiopian imbroglio is mere child&apos;s play compared to the problem that will, in some not very distant future, confront His Majesty&apos;s Government.I HAVE the honour to transmit to you herewith in original a very interesting despatch addressed to me on the 11th May by Colonel Thorne, the retiring military attache to this Embassy, summarising the gist of two conversations which he had with General von Reichenau whilst introducing his successor to the Reichswehr Ministry. -2.   I would draw your particular attention to the following points : (a) In paragraph 2 General von Reichenau is reported as advocating a transfer of populations in the east of Europe as a means of reconciling a policy of expansion towards Russia with the Chancellor&apos;s declara-tions that Germany does not wish to annex territory populated by another race.(b) In paragraph 3 General von Reichenau is reported as making thesuggestion which has found an echo in certain English circles that the best policy His Majesty&apos;s Government could pursue would be to admit Germany&apos;s hegemony on the continent and to give her a free hand in Europe in return for German non-interference in the rest of the world. This is a view which is widely held in Germany to-day.(c) In paragraph 4 General von Reichenau is stated to have referred to thepossibility of Germany being one day obliged, in order to break the hostile ring around her, to compose her quarrel with Russia.(d) In paragraph 5 Colonel Thorne describes his discussion of the questionof a reduction in the number of divisions proposed for the new German army, and you will notice that, while considering it unlikely that the German Government would agree to reduce the number of these divisions, General von Reichenau suggested that they might be prepared to discuss the strength of each division.(e) In the same paragraph Colonel Thorne explains the desire of the GermanGovernment to arrange the future territorial organisation of Germany into &quot; Gaue &quot; on a military basis.(/) In paragraph 6 Colonel Thorne reproduces General von Reichenau&apos;s account of the dispute between the Reichswehr and the Labour Service regarding the term of service in the Labour Corps.(g) In paragraph 9 Colonel Thorne describes General von Reichenau&apos;s views on the future organisation of the German Cabinet views which seem to give some confirmation to the suggestion that the Chancellor will,, sooner or later, himself assume direct responsibility for the conduct of foreign affairs, leaving a Staatssekretar in nominal charge of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs.I have, &amp;c.ERIC PHIPPS(No. 472.) Sir,Berlin, May 15, 1935.
3). I desire to take this opportunity of placing on record my warmest appreciation of Colonel Thorne&apos;s services as military attache to this Embassy. He has\ been able to establish quite unusually good relations with Germans of every class, and the information he has collected with excellent judgment on political^ as well as military matters has been of the greatest assistance to me. I view hfis departure with the utmost regret.,; I have, &amp;c.ERIC PHIPPS.Enclosure. Colonel Thome to Sir E. Phipps.(No. 3.)Sir, Berlin, May 11, 1935.I HAVE the honour to forward the gist of two conversations with General von Reichenau which occurred during the process of introducing Colonel Hotblack to representatives of the Reichswehr Ministry. Lately I have found a tendency amongst officers in the Reichswehr Ministry to suggest that the influence of General von Reichenau with both the Reichskanzler and General von Blomberg is on the wane, but General von Reichenau gave no indication that he felt his position or power was in any way diminished, and described the measures he intended to take to bring about a number of important alterations. He remarked once that employment in a post, which was mainly political, for nearly two and a half years of great anxiety and responsibility made him look forward to employment in the future which was purely military, but that was the only indication that his activities and influence in the Reichswehr Ministry might not last for very long.   I think, therefore, that his ideas are worth recording.2. In discussing, the objectives which Germany might have in a future war in the East, it was interesting to find that, unlike most Reichswehr officers who claim there were no satisfactory objectives for the German forces in Russia, the general pointed out how a successful invasion could be followed by the evacuation of the Russian population further eastwards and the resettlement of this territory by another people, perhaps by Poles, and this could be done about as far as the line held by the German troops in the last war. Presumably, though he did not say so, General von Reichenau&apos;s intention was that these Poles for settling in Russia would be made available by their evacuation of some, if not all, of the Corridor to make room in their turn for German settlers. He took the line that this policy should not trouble Britain; on the contrary, it should calm the apprehensions of those Britishers who had apparently been misled by the French into believing that Germany&apos;s objectives lay in the West. Her need, however, was for empty spaces for expansion and settlement, while France and Belgium were already so thickly populated that no empty spaces could be created.3. Both in the matter of Russia and elsewhere in his conversation the general suggested, but without making a definite statement, that the best course of action would be for Britain to give Germany a free hand in Europe in return for German non-interference with Britain outside the continent of Europe. He stated that he thought that the only means of keeping order in Europe was for one Power to dominate, and he seemed to be convinced that the Power most suited for this task was Germany.4. The alarm felt in Switzerland was also not justified, as if Germany did not want to invade France, she obviously would not want to march through Switzerland. Evidently the general had not considered the possibility of German penetration by force into Switzerland or by the method adopted successfully by the U.S.S.R. when expanding into Turkestan. He harped on &quot;the terrible encirclement of Germany,&quot; and said this must lead to war, as it was essential to Germany to break the circle. For this purpose, though he hated and mistrusted Russia, he would be prepared to try to contract some form of alliance with that country and detach her from France. If Germany should succeed in carrying out such a course, he suggested that it would be a great blow to Britain.5. In discussing the possibilities of limiting German armaments, the general did not seem to think that any reduction would be made in the actual number of divisions (e.g., thirty-six), but he considered that their establishment
would be open to negotiation. It must be remembered that the total of thirty-six divisions was an all-inclusive figure. At the same time, the strength of the corps and army troops was no less important, and it might be possible to arrange that all corps and army troops, particularly mechanised formations, could be reckoned on the basis of so many divisions. The figure of a total strength of 550,000 given by the Reichskanzler to Sir John Simon was not intended as an exact number, but simply as an illustration; the total might be as low as 330,000 or as high as 660,000, though it was obviously easier to fix the figure at a low level if the men had not been recruited and equipped. The German army to-day consisted of twenty-one * infantry divisions, two cavalry and one armoured division; in addition, there were seven &quot; Inspektionen &quot; of the &quot; Landespolizei &quot; waiting to be absorbed by the army. A fair estimate of the army and Landespolizei together would be twenty-seven to twenty-eight divisions. General von Reichenau informed us that there were now ten army corps headquarters (&quot; Wehrkreis &quot;) in existence (see Appendix for location). It was their intention to create the XIth Army Corps area in Bavaria, while the location of the XHth Army Corps depended to a large extent on the final decision to be arrived at in the subdivision of Germany into &quot; Reichsgaue.&quot; Originally it had been the intention of the authors of the Reich Reform Law to create twenty-six Reichsgaue; this figure was reduced this winter to twenty-one in order to co-ordinate them with the number of infantry divisions. It will be remembered that the Minister of the Interior in his speech in January explained that &apos;&apos; the Reichsgaue &apos;&apos; were to be formed on a geographical, ethnographical and economic basis, which best corresponds with the welfare of the people and the Reich. About twenty territories will thus be established with an average population of 3 to 4 millions each, the frontiers of which will correspond as closely as possible with those necessary for the organisation of the army.&quot; Now that the number of infantry divisions is to be increased, General von Reichenau is very anxious to adopt the principle of making the Reichsgaue correspond with the areas of the army corps. The Reichswehr Minister at present considers that some sixteen to fourteen are necessary, but General von Reichenau hoped that he would shortly agree to his proposed figure of twelve.6. General von Reichenau is now engaged in a contest with Colonel Hierl, the Kommissar of the Labour Service, over the period to be served. Colonel Hierl, who was described as an honest but very obstinate man, is convinced that a whole twelve months&apos; service is essential for every young German. In view of the fact that the cost of the Labour Service is now 200 million reichsmarks, or approximately 1,000 reichsmarks per head per annum, the expense of putting the whole of next year&apos;s annual class through would be prohibitive. Moreover, the Reichswehr Ministry are of the opinion that all the benefits of the Labour Service training can be obtained within six months, and they are determined that no more military training is to be given by the Labour Service leaders and instructors. It has been found that the recruits who have attended camps where there was little or no actual military drill made much better soldiers in a shorter time than those who came from a camp where military drill was practised.7. General von Reichenau instanced that the 1915 annual class at present consists of 470,000 males; of these, only 250,000 will be required on the 1st October, 1936, by the three services, so that the other 220,000 will have to be content with six months in the Labour Service. At one time it was suggested that these, at any rate, should be given a full year&apos;s training in the Labour Service, but the idea had to be abandoned, chiefly on the ground of expense, and partly also because this arrangement would tend to stigmatise the Labour Service as something very inferior.8. In connexion with the subject of the intake of 250,000, one of my colleagues was informed by General von Reichenau that one-half of the array intake on the 1st October, 1935, would be required to stay on at tlx :cr,., /&quot;-&quot; September 1936 either for employment as n.c.o.&apos;s or for technical duties. It was&apos; hoped that these numbers would be produced by voluntary re-engagement; this arrangement would tend to reduce the weak period after the intake on the 1st October.9. General von Reichenau said that the principle of having every Govern-ment department represented in the Cabinet by a Minister was under revision.
His proposal (we could not gather to what extent it was likely to be adopted) was to reduce the number of Cabinet Ministers to one which could usefully discuss together round a table when problems came up for solution. He proposed to replace all except four Cabinet Ministers by Permanent Under-Secretaries (&quot; Staatssekretaren &quot;) and group them as under : (a) Minister of the Interior, taking Propaganda, Health, Ernahrung and education.(b) Minister of Economics, taking Reichsbank, Post Office, Agriculture and transportation.The Cabinet would consist then of the Reichskanzler (who would direct Foreign Affairs as chairman), the Ministers of the Interior, Economics, Finance and Defence as members. In addition, the &quot; Stellvertreter des Fiihrers &quot; would have to be added for the present as a sop to the Partei, but later it might be possible to drop him. He considered that a deputy chairman should be appointed, and suggested that Herr Goring would likely hold that post if it were to be created immediately.10. Both General von Blomberg and General Beck, Chef des Truppenamts, on whom we called yesterday, were very friendly and told Colonel Hotblack in a convincing manner that they would let him see as much as possible of the German army. Both general officers expressed their bewilderment that every step in rearmament should be taken as a threat to British security; General von Blomberg assured us that the Wehrmacht harboured no hostility at all against England. It was obvious that they, no less than General von Reichenau, are greatly worried by the encirclement of Germany and. surprised that their every action should invariably be considered as unfriendly to Britain.I have, &amp;c.ANDREW THORNE, Colonel, G.S., , , Military Attache.Appendix.No. of Army Corps .-	Location of Headquarters.	Remarks.I	Ktinigsberg	No change.II	Stettin	HI	Berlin	Less Silesia but plus Magdeburg.IV	Dresden	V	Stuttgart	Now only southern portion.VI	Mtlnster	VII	Munich	No change.VIII	Breslau	All Silesia from W.K. III.IX	Kassel	Northern portion of W.K. V.X	Altona	Taken from W.K. II, W.K. 1 and W.K. VI.Notes.  (i) W.K. XI is likely to be Bavaria north of the Danube.(ii) W.K. VII is likely to be Bavaria south of the Danube.(iii) It is difficult to see where W.K. XII will be interpolated.    Should the Demilitarized Zonedisappear, it would be likely to have its headquarters at Koblenz and its area west of the Rhine.Sir E. Phipps to Sir Samuel Hoare. (Received October 11.)[By Bag.](No. 228.   Saving.)(Telegraphic.)   En clair. Berlin, October 10, 1935.,: &apos; AENERAL von BLOMBERG lunched with us on 8th October, and I had soAA; conversation with him afterwards.He said that what Signor Mussolini felt especially bitterly was the fact that all Communist and extreme Socialist elements throughout the world were banded against him; this made it peculiarly difficult for him to extricate himself from his present position. General von Blomberg deplored this anti-Fascist wave, although he remarked that the mobilisation on the Brenner had been a childish and quite
unnecessary proceeding. He added that Signor Mussolini complained that he had not been sufficiently warned regarding the real feelings of His Majesty&apos;s Government or of the British public.I replied that public opinion in Great Britain was unanimous in condemning the attack on Abyssinia, but the reason was, apart from the Extreme Left, anti-aggressor and anti-war, not anti-fascism. As for insufficient warning, Signor Mussolini had been solemnly and repeatedly warned from February onwards, both in London and in Rome.General von Blomberg thinks that Italy has undertaken a task beyond her powers, and that the very large number of troops that she has thrown into East Africa may prove fatal for her, owing to the possibility of terrible and widespread epidemics amongst them. He remarked, however, that Signor Mussolini&apos;s real excuse was the vital need for expansion, and that applied to Germany as well as to Italy. If Germany were not allowed to expand, the &quot; kettle would some day burst.&quot; He recalled your words at Geneva regarding raw material, but said that was not enough. Germany must have colonies again. I reminded my guest how little raw material Germany had drawn from her colonies before the war, and how few colonists, apart from officials, she had sent there. The reply of the Minister for War was that Germany had not been sufficiently long in possession of those colonies to be able to develop them to the full; it was, moreover, intolerable for her to be considered unworthy to possess them now.General von Blomberg repeated, as he usually does when we meet, that the Chancellor&apos;s one wish is to cultivate friendly relations with Great Britain. Moreover, I would remember that that was what he advocated in Mein Kampf. I agreed, but, pointing to the French Ambassador, who was in earnest conversa-tion in another room with Herr von Ribbentrop, I observed that the French never forgot the violent hatred of France contained in that work. General von Blomberg replied that Mein Kampf was written in 1923, in very different circumstances to the present; but new editions appeared, I observed, and its sale continued. The reply was that Herr Hitler could not alter it by a series of postscripts or sequels. He therefore allowed its sale to continue, as showing his innermost thoughts at the time. His present thoughts would shortly appear in a volume containing a selection of his recent speeches, and these were full of genuine offers of reconciliation with France, but they had hitherto fallen on deaf ears. The last French note to Great Britain, for instance; was not agreeable reading for Germany, as it was so evidently directed against that Power.You will notice how convenient, and indeed soothing, a text-book Mein Kampf has become : its bellicosity and fanaticism faded away with the autumn roses of 1923, and only such sweet reason as it may have expounded is to remain to us as a joy for ever.Meanwhile, as I heard afterwards from the French Ambassador, he and Herr von Ribbentrop were reproaching one another for the German-Polish Agreement of 1934 and the Franco-Soviet Pact of 1935 respectively. Herr von Ribbentrop told M. Francois-Poncet that the French should never have allied themselves to a Communist and Asiatic Power, to which my French colleague replied that Russia had evolved since Peter the Great, she was as much European as Asiatic, and the French pact with her was merely the reply to the unfortunate German-Polish Agreement, which, concluded in an atmosphere of undue secrecy, had sown suspicion and distrust throughout Europe.(3)Sir E. Phipps to Sir Samuel Hoare.(No. 1178.)Sir, Berlin, November 18, 1935.I HAVE the honour to report that a mass meeting of officials of the Reichsluftschutzbund (Air Defence League) was held on the 14th November at the Sport Palast in the presence of General Goring.2. The president of the league, Lieutenant-General Grimme, announced that 7 million people had joined the league; in 2,200 air defence schools over 22,000 instructors had passed 4^ million people through an air defence course. The work of the league would be continued and extended.
3. In his speech General Goring emphasised that the German air arm which had recently been created was defensive and not aggressive. In the defence of the country against foreign air attack, however, it was not sufficient to possess aeroplanes and anti-aircraft guns. The German people, he continued, yearned for a genuine peace, all the more as they had not known internal peace through the fifteen years which had followed on the Great War. &quot; We desire a peace which gives the German people what is due to the German people, a peace of honour and equality of rights.&quot; (Thunderous applause.) To-day German peace was not assured by parliamentary chatter or international solidarity, but by the reawakened German might. Part of the German defence forces was the air force. The Air Defence League must see to it that in emergency the German population should be protected to the highest possible degree. The work of air defence had a high moral importance, for an army could only resist to the last if the nerves of the country behind them remained strong. In time of war the members of the Air Defence League would be as truly at the front as soldiers in the battle-zone.4. I would draw your particular attention to General Goring&apos;s statement quoted above, that the peace which Germany desires is to be a German peace, that is to say, a peace which satisfies the ever-increasing aspirations of this country. I am reliably informed that this passage of General Goring&apos;s was received with wild enthusiasm.I have, &amp;c.ERIC PHIPPS.o
3. In his speech General Goring emphasised that the German air arm which had recently been created was defensive and not aggressive. In the defence of the country against foreign air attack, however, it was not sufficient to possess aeroplanes and anti-aircraft guns. The German people, he continued, yearned for a genuine peace, all the more as they had not known internal peace through the fifteen years which had followed on the Great War. &quot; We desire a peace which gives the German people what is due to the German people, a peace of honour and equality of rights.&quot; (Thunderous applause.) To-day German peace was not assured by parliamentary chatter or international solidarity, but by the reawakened German might. Part of the German defence forces was the air force. The Air Defence League must see to it that in emergency the German population should be protected to the highest possible degree. The work of air defence had a high moral importance, for an army could only resist to the last if the nerves of the country behind them remained strong. In time of war the members of the Air Defence League would be as truly at the front as soldiers in the battle-zone.4. I would draw your particular attention to General Goring&apos;s statement quoted above, that the peace which Germany desires is to be a German peace, that is to say, a peace which satisfies the ever-increasing aspirations of this country. I am. reliably informed that this passage of General G6ring&apos;s was received with wild enthusiasm.I have, &amp;c.ERIC PHIPPS.o

</content>
</cab>
