<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/257/0 images: 485-487</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
l(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT). S E C R E to cp.   242 (55). COPY NO.   &quot;W.C A B. I H E T.ANGL0&quot;GERMAN-F5ENCH WAR QRAVES A&amp;REEMBI3T. Note by the Secretary of State for War.I circulate for the information of my colleagues in the Cabinet,  the attached, memorandum from the Vice-Chairman of the Imperial War Graves Commission.    I consider that Sir Fabian Ware is to be highly congratulated on the conclusion of this very satisfactory international agreement.(Signed)    DUPE COOPER.War. Office, S. Wo 1, 20th December, 1935.
Secretary of State for War,(Chairman, Imperial War Graves Commission).ANGLO-GERMAN-FRENCH WAR GRAVES AGREEMENT.1, The Imperial War Graves Commission have found it of great practical value in their work to he in direct communication with the Foreign countries in whose lands British sailors,  soldiers and airmen are hurled, through joint Committees composed of British representatives and of representatives of the foreign country concerned,2, International Agreements establishing such committees in ex-allied countries of the Great War have been in existence for many years, namely the Anglo-French Agreement dated 26th November, 1913, the Anglo-Belgian Agreement dated 13th June, 1919, the Anglo-Greek Agreement dated 27th August/9th September,1921,the Anglo-Italian Agreement dated 11th Kay, 1922.Hitherto there had been no similar Agreement in respect of ex-enemy countries and endeavours to enter into such an arrangement with Germany were not assured of that French approval which was essential to success.3. This year however it was possible to arrange a conference which was held in Paris on 26th June, andat which I met Dr.  Horning (the head of the German war graves Service - Zentralnachweiseamt fur Kriegerverlusteund Kriegergraber) and h.  1&apos;Intendant General Vineensini(head of the French Service des Sepultures Kilitaires).It was then fully explained to Dr.  Horning that theAnglo-French Committee had functioned very successfully,allowing as it did, under proper supervision, direct and constant communication between the technical servicesof the two countries,.      It was also suggested by myself,with the support of Intendant General Vineensini, thatsome of the questions regarding German graves in Britishcemeteries in France and British, graves in German territory,for which the Imperial War Graves Commission were directly or indirectly responsible, could be more promptly andsatisfactorily settled through such a Committee,  than bythe more complicated and circuitous methods hitherto adopted.These methods, in spite of mutual good-will, had left important questions outstanding.A. It was agreed at this meeting that Intendent GeneralVineensini and myself should go together to Berlin to discuss the matter more fully with the proper German authorities and the approval of the Imperial War Graves Commission, and the Governments which they represent, was given me to pursue the matter further.5c A conference accordingly took place in Berlin on 9th,10th and 11th October the arrangements for the meeting having been made by the Foreign Office through His IA iestyTs Ambassador in Berlin (Sir Eric Phipps) with whom I hi discussed the matter fully while he&quot; was in England.
/QIC? 3 7 36. This conference was attended by IntendentGeneral Vincensini and myself and by Herr Ministerial-direktor  Gaus  of the Auswaertiges Amt and other German representatives.      Sir Eric Phipps also arranged for me to meet before hand Herr von Pihbentrop, General von Blomberg and other prominent Germans.      At the conference the proposal for the establishment of a joint Committee was, after full discussion,  sympathetically received. We drew up a draft Agreement, following generally the lines of the Anglo-French Agreement, and we decided that this should be submitted to the Governments concerned -for their consideration and approval.7. The Agreement thus suggested has now received theapproval of the Governments of the United Kingdom, Canada, Australia, New Zealand,  South Africa and India, all of whom are represented on the Imperial War Graves Commission,  as well as of the French and German Governments, and, the necessary powers having been received from all these Governments,  it is understood that signature will take   place on 20th December in Berlin.8. Upon the signing of the Agreement an announcementwill be made simultaneous 13^ in all countries concerned on a date and in a form mutually agreed.9. The participation of the French in this agreement was necessitated,  and given a practical basis, by the presence of a number of German graves in the British cemeteries in France cared for by our Imperial War Graves Commission.      From a wider point of view than the administrative,  this Agreement has a special significance,      For,  in both Germany and in France,  as in the British Empire,  there are strong and deep currents of remembrance of the dead of the Great War, and&apos; it is thought that nothing but good can result from providing a common channel for these.      That is, perhaps only in a small and tentative way,  secured by this Agreement.10a        The Imperial War Graves Commission feel satisfaction in the knowledge that the mutual confidence which they have established with the French, through their work since the War, has brought them the support of the French Government in the negotiations leading up to the conclusion of this Agreement.11,        The Committee   will comprise two British Honorary Members,  two German Honorary Members, four official British members, four official German members, and one French Honorary Member and one French Official member.(Signed)      FABIAN WARE.V i c e - Ch a i r ma n.Imperial War Graves Commission, 38, Grosvenor Gardens, London,  S. W, 1,.19th December,  1935.

</content>
</cab>
