<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/52/15 images: 182-195</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE   PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cm(73) 37thConclusionsCOPY no cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street on tuesday 17 JULY 1973at 11. 30 am present the Rt Hon Edward Heath mp prime minister the Rt Hon Sir Alec Douglas-Home mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Hon Anthony Barber mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Lord carrington secretary of State for Defence(Items 1-4)The Rt Hon James Prior mp lord President of the CouncilTheRt Hon Lord Hailsham of St marylebone lord chancellor the Rt Hon William Whitelaw mp secretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon Robert Carr mp secretary of State for the home department  (Items 1-3)The Rt Hon Sir Keith Joseph mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Geoffrey Rippon QC mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Gordon Campbell mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon Peter Thomas QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher mp secretary of State for Education and science the Rt Hon Peter Walker mp secretary of State for Trade and industry the Rt Hon Maurice Macmillan mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Lord windlesham lord Privy Seal
ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Francis Pym mp parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat the Rt Hon Sir Burke trend sir John hunt mr P benner mr J anson mr H F Ellis-rees mr R L. BaxterCONTENTSItem Subject page 1. PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRSDate of Adjournment for the Summer Recess 1Statement on Wool Textile Industry 12. OVERSEA affairs rhodesia 2Portugal 23. COUNTER-INFLATIONARY POLICY 34. THE TAX-CREDIT SCHEME 45. COMPANY LAW REFORM: DRAFT WHITE PAPER 7
PARLIAMENTARYAFFAIRSDate ofAdjournmentfor the SummerRecess1. The Cabinet were informed that, subject to somerearrangement of outstanding business, it might now bepossible to adjourn the House of Commons for the summer recess on Wednesday, 25 July.Statement onWool TextileIndustryThe Cabinet were informed that a Parliamentary statement which was to have been made that afternoon, about assistanceto the wool textile industry under the Industry Act, would belikely to give rise to a demand for a short debate.    While themeasures proposed represented a soundly based plan tomodernise the industry and would be widely welcomed in yorkshire, they involved expenditure of the order of 15 million and might therefore attract criticism from someof the Governments supporters.    It would not be appropriate to announce the scheme during the Recess; and, since detailsof it were already widely known as a result of the consultations which had taken place with the interested parties, it would be unfortunate to delay an announcement until after Parliament hadreassembled.    It might be preferable, therefore, to defer theannouncement for a few days, in order that a debate - for whichin any case there was no formal or procedural requirement -might be avoided before the Recess but might be conceded, ifnecessary, on the return of Parliament in the autumn.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, saidthat the Cabinet agreed that the Statement should be deferred until Thursday, 19 July.
OVERSEAAFFAIRSRhodesiaPreviousReference:CM(73) 36thConclusions,Minute 32. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH secretary said that he had just learned that Mr. Smith, the leader of the regime in Salisbury, was proposing to discuss the situation with Bishop Muzorewa, the leader of the African national council (ANC),that day.    As a result he felt bound to reconsiderhis intention to announce in Parliament on 19 July that, in theabsence of any settlement of the constitutional dispute in rhodesia, the Government proposed to take the necessary steps in the autumn to maintain sanctions against the regime.    Itmight now be more politic to say that the recent visit to Salisburyby the Permanent Under-Secretary of State, Sir Denis Greenhill,had been to seek to promote discussion between the regime andthe African community;  that the meeting between Mr. Smith andthe leader of the(/N^C suggested that some advance in thisrespect might be in prospect, and that we must clearly maintainthe status quo so long as there was evidence of this kind that asettlement was actively being sought by the parties concerned,It would be desirable to avoid, if possible, elaborating this statement or indicating specifically at this stage that sanctionsmight have to be continued.Portugal THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thatthere were some indications that the Opposition might seek tobroaden the basis of that day&apos;s Parliamentary Debate onPortugal, which had been timed to coincide with the visit of thePortuguese Prime Minister, Dr. Caetano, to London.    It seemedHkely that they would no longer concentrate on the allegedatrocities in Mozambique but would seek to direct criticism atthe policies of the Portuguese regime as a whole, even to theextent of proposing that Portugal should be expelled from theNorth Atlantic Treaty Organisation.    It was unfortunate that thePortuguese Government had refused to agree to institute a specialinquiry into the alleged atrocities, as we ourselves had suggested,and that the Governments spokesman in the Debate would therefore be able to say no more than that the allegations would be investigated by the normal processes.    Even so, it should not bedifficult to expose the inconsistency between the Opposition^current hostility towards the Portuguese Government and theattitude which they had adopted while they were themselves in office; and it was reassuring that the demonstrations againstDr. Caetano had so far been relatively innocuous.The Cabinet -Took note of these statements by the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary.31:! .:::;r:
COUNTER- 3. The Cabinet considered arrangements for the followingINFLATIONARY day&apos;s Parliamentary Debate about Counter-Inflationary Policy.POLICY Their discussion and the conclusions reached are recorded separately.previous reference:CM(73) 36thConclusions,Minute 5
4. THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER recalled that the Government&apos;s intention to introduce a tax-credit scheme had been announced in the 1972 Budget.    A discussion paper had been issued in October.    Since then the proposals hadbeen under review by a Select Committee under the chairmanship of Mr. William Clark, MP;  and the Inland Revenue had consulted a number of representative bodies from industry,commerce and the professions.    The Select Committee was due to report on 19 July.    It was understood that it had dividedon Party lines, the Chairman and the Governments supportersendorsing the scheme but certain of the Opposition members,in a series of minority reports, recommending its rejection onthe grounds of its inflexibility and the insufficient weight whichit accorded to the needs of the less well-off.    The majority report would recommend, in particular, that child creditsshould normally be paid to the mother and that there should besco^e for the woman in regular employment, whether marriedor not, to receive a credit in her own right.    It would alsoendorse some important modifications in the administration ofthe scheme which had been advanced in evidence and would makeit significantly easier for industry to implement.The scheme had been widely welcomed on its introduction, by theTrades Union Congress (TUC) among others, both as a majorcontribution to the problem of child poverty and assistance tothe needy and as a major step in simplifying the tax system.It would reduce dependence on the means test, removing some 250 million of benefit from its scope.    To abandon it at thisstage would leave the Government without a comprehensivestragegy in these important areas of social and fiscal policyand would be liable to reopen questions about family support,provision for the elderly and the taxation of short-term benefits,the last of which was a question of particular concern among theGovernment1 s supporters.    The Opposition would no doubtcriticise its cost;  but it might well be no less expensive toincrease tax allowances in line with the forecast rise in prices.In any case, the Government could not be expected to commit themselves to a specific level of credits four or five years ahead;  and there was no reason to revise the judgment in thediscussion paper that the prospective growth of the national income should allow additional resources to be allotted to the elimination of poverty and that, given the right order of priorities, the cost of the scheme should be manageable.    It was important that the Government should keep the initiative in thismatter;  and it was therefore proposed, when the SelectCommittee&apos;s report was published, to issue a statement welcom-ing the majority report, accepting its views on the payment of child credits and (less explicitly) on working wives and making itclear that legislation to give effect to the scheme would beintroduced as soon as practicable.THE TAX-CREDITSCHEMEPreviousReference:CM(72) 32ndConclusions,Minute 14
In discussion it was suggested that the Government stood to gainsubstantial political credit from proceeding with this scheme.Decisions in favour of paying credits to working wives (despite the saving on present expenditure which this would involve) andof paying all child credits to the mother would be particularlywelcomed by women&apos;s interests, both among the government&apos;s supporters and more widely.    To abandon the scheme wouldnot exempt the Government from the need to take action in theareas of concern which it affected but would be criticised as a breach of faith with their supporters on the Select Committee;and the Conservative Party in the country at large would regard,it as a major retreat.    Although the possibility of having toincrease taxation to meet the cost of the scheme could not be excluded, it should prove possible to phase its implementationin such a way as to take account of the implications for public expenditure year by year.    On the other hand the effect ofassigning all child credits to the mother, as opposed to only that part which represented the existing family allowances, would beto increase the husband&apos;s taxation;  and, although the TUC had welcomed the scheme in general terms, individual male wage-earners and the unions negotiating on their behalf must beexpected to resist any consequential reduction in net pay.Indeed, although this proposal was designed to protect theinterests of the wife and children, it might seem at variance witha political philosophy which sought to promote a greater sense of personal responsibility on the part of the individual wage-earner.    None the less, public opinion was increasinglydisposed to support women&apos;s rights;  and, in view of the reactionwhich the alternative proposal in the discussion paper hadprovoked, it might well be expedient to proceed forthwith on thebasis now proposed.In further discussion it was suggested that for the Governmentto issue a statement as soon as the Select Committee publishedits report might imply that sufficient time had not been allowed for its recommendations to be digested.    On the other hand itwas known that the Government had had the proposals underconsideration for some time;  and the Opposition would undoubtedly seek to make political capital out of the minority-reports which their supporters on the Select Committee had entered and to exploit  any apparent hesitation on the part of theGovernment in endorsing the proposals in favour of women.Moreover, the Government would be expected to indicate their intentions about legislation;  and there would be political advantage in promoting a measure of this kind in the next Session.But, although the Government should avoid being drawn intoprecipitate discussion of the Select Committeefs report it wouldbe right that their initial reaction to its findings should first bemade known to Parliament rather than to the public at large;and this might best be arranged by means of a Written answer to a Parliamentary Question, combined with suitable publicity in the Press and on television.
THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed that the prospect of a divided report fromthe Select Committee on Tax Credit should not deter theGovernment from their endorsement of the scheme in principle.But the implications of its introduction for public expenditure would need careful examination;  and the proposal to pay allchild credits to the mother might not only arouse significantcontroversy but also have considerable repercussions on wage negotiations in the future.    The Chancellor of the Exchequer,in consultation with the Ministers concerned, should arrangefor the Government&apos;s reaction to the report to be conveyed toParliament by means of a Written Answer to a parliamentary question and for the Government1 s case to be vigorouslypresented in the Press and broadcasting media.    He shouldalso, in consultation with the Lord President, give furtherconsideration to the timiig and form of the legislation whichmight be needed in the next Session in order to bring the scheme into effect.The Cabinet -1. Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the PrimeMinister.2. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer -i.     in consultation with the Secretary ofState for Social Services, the Home secretary and the Lord President, to arrange forsuitable publicity to be given to the Government&apos;views on the Select Committee&apos;s report, inthe light of the Prime Minister&apos;s summing upof their discussion;ii.     in consultation with the Lord President,to consider the form and timing of legislation to implement the scheme.6
COMPANY law reform: draft white paper . The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister for Trade and Consumer Affairs (CP(73) 79), to whichwas annexed a draft White Paper oh company law reform.THE MINISTER FOR TRADE AND CONSUMER affairs recalled that the Cabinet had decided that a Companies Billshould be a major constituent of the legislative programme forthe forthcoming Session.    The matters which it was envisaged that it should comprise fell into three broad categories.    First,it would strengthen the existing law in order to deal with anumber of abuses which had attracted public attention during recent months, such as insider dealing and the covertaggregation of a dominant holding in another company in preparation for a take-over bid.    Seconds it would give effectto a number of recommendations made in the Report of theJenkins Committee in 1962, for which room had not been foundin the Companies Act, 1967.    Third, it would deal with a range of matters, mainly of a technical nature, which had come to attention as a result of the administration of theCompanies Act.    Of these the most important was the latefiling of company accounts.    A Bill on these lines would be awell balanced and important measure, which would satisfypublic expectations of a significant advance in companieslegislation and, if carefully drafted, need not be so complex asto imperil the smooth management of the legislative programme.It was proposed that a White Paper, on the lines of the draft which had been circulated, should be published at an earlydate, probably on 25 July, indicating the main matters to bedealt with in the Bill and discussing, in a section which wouldbe &quot;green&quot; in character, certain major issues on which therewas as yet no consensus of opinion and the Governments views had not so far been fully elaborated.    These included the socialresponsibility of companies, the rights and duties of institutionalshareholders and worker participation (on which it was proposedlater to issue a separate Green Paper).   It would be desirableto stimulate public debate on these topics, even thoughconclusions would probably not be reached in time for them tobe reflected in the Bill.    In addition, there were several matters which had recently given rise to public concern - relating, forexample, to possible tax evasion and abuse of exchange control -which could not be discussed appropriately in the White Paperbut should be dealt with in the presentation and Press briefingat the time of publication.The Cabinet -Approved in principle the proposals in CP(73) 79.Cabinet Office17 July 1973
SECRET &quot;3 *T ^u^rJc 7*2*HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy NO       1 3CABINETCONFIDENTIAL annex cm(73) 37th Conclusions, Minute 3Tuesday 17 July 1973 at 11. 30 amCOUNTER -INFLATIONARYPOLICYPreviousReference:CM(73) 36thConclusions,Minute 5THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had discussed with theMinisters directly concerned the measures which might betaken in preparation for Stage 3 of the Counter-Inflationprogramme and the extent to which an indication of theGovernments intentions should be given in the parliamentary debate on the Opposition Motion of Censure on 18 July.    Thesuccess attained by the Government in Stages 1 and 2 of theprogramme had derived largely from the fact that they hadretained the initiative throughout and had put forward proposalswhich had been accepted by public opinion as reasonable and fair.    It now appeared, however, that the introduction of stage 3 would probably be attended by a continuing rise in prices,due mainly to higher import costs, which was unlikely to slowdown until the Spring of 1974.    The possible steps which mightbe taken to deal with this situation had been considered by theCabinet on previous occasions.    A general policy of food subsidies across the board was open to substantial objections.They were open-ended and expensive; they would be contentiousin the European Economic Community;  and they would tend toimpair international confidence in sterling.    The Chancellor ofthe Exchequer had indicated these difficulties in a recent debate;and it was doubtful whether a policy of general subsidy nowcommanded strong support, even among the Opposition.    this did not preclude the possibility of selective subsidies on particular foodstuffs.    It would not be opportune, however, to announce such measures at the present juncture; and it wouldbe preferable to delay any announcement about them untilproposals had been prepared for Stage 3 as a whole.    similar considerations applied to social security benefits, where it mightbe desirable to consider an increase in the autumn, but therewould be considerable practical difficulties in any early change.As regards rents, it seemed desirable to adhere to the policy
previously endorsed by the Cabinet and to allow localauthority rents to rise in accordance with the Housing finance act but to mitigate the effect by a further increase in the needsallowance for rent rebates.    The proposed increase in the needsallowance would amount to  2. 50 for a family without children and  3 for a family with two children.    If this was to be effect-ive at the time of the October rent increase, it would need to be announced at once and could not be deferred until the proposalsfor Stage 3 were ready.    He proposed, therefore, to announce this increase during the Censure debate on the following day.The other m?.jor issue on which a statement could usefully bemade during the debate was the possibility of safeguarding pay increases against the rise in prices.    There was now a risk that the pay increase permitted in Stage 2 would be completelyeroded for some groups before the beginning of Stage 3.    Anumber of possible ways of dealing with this problem had been examined.    There were serious objections to the completeindexation of pay, which would create a demand for similar arrangements in a wider context, e.g. in relation to social security benefits and the return on Government securities.Threshold arrangements, on the other hand, were less open tosuch objections.    It seemed desirable, therefore, to indicatethat it would be Government policy to include in the Code for stage 3 a provision permitting such arrangements in principle,the details being settled after discussion with the Trades UnionCongress and the Confederation of British Industry.Additionally, there would be advantage in indicating that, in thelight of the recent steep rise in import prices, a similar safe-guard would be introduced during Stage 2.    Since the Stage pay limit amounted,  on average,  to about 7 to 8 per cent, itwas proposed that the threshold should be set at 7 per cent,with the result that a payment would be made if the retail price index (RPI) rose during Stage 2 to 8 per cent above the level atOctober, 1972, the last month before the pay standstill was imposed.    For each complete 1 per cent rise in prices abovethe threshold level during Stage 2 an increase of 30p a week would be permitted.    This would enable those earning  30 aweek or less to obtain complete compensation for the rise inprices beyond the level expected when Stage 2 was introduced;and it would be more generous than the compensation of 20penvisaged in the Governments proposals of September, 1972.If the current forecast of the RPI proved correct, the arrange-ment would be triggered only once, i. e, by the RPI figure for september which would be published in October.    If pricesrose more than was currently expected, however, the arrange-ment might operate a second time, giving a combined increaseof 60p.    The increases would continue to be paid until they weresubsumed in the next pay settlement for the group concerned.As an alternative, the possibility of a threshold arrangement
based on food alone, or on food, rent, rates and travel costs,had been examined; but this had been rejected because the resulting payments would be too small.    By contrast, thearrangements now proposed should help to retain the initiative in the Government&apos;s hands and to deal with the criticism thatthose who had accepted Stage 2 were faced with a decline intheir real standard of living.In discussion it was suggested that, although the proposedthreshold arrangements for Stage 2 might have little effect onwage bargaining, they could, if well presented, exert a usefulinfluence on piiblic opinion and help to ease the transition toStage 3.    On the other hand the payment of 30p might be criticised as too small, particularly if account was taken of theeffect of tax deductions and national insurance contributions.It was for consideration, therefore, whether it might be increasedto a figure equivalent to 1 per cent of average industrialearnings or whether the threshold might be reduced to 6 per centwith the result that it would be triggered by the RPI in August,and so justify a first payment in September.    Increases of60p, however, would add about if per cent to the wages bill;and anything more would seriously reduce the room for manoeuvrein Stage 3.    Alternatively, if 3Op was the maximum which couldbe offered, it might be preferable to withhold it until it couldform part of the settlement for Stage 3 and to say no more atthis stage about the Governments intentions than that some formof compensation for Stage 2 price increases would be provided.A merely general assurance of this kind, however, would eitherfail to carry conviction or be liable to arouse excessive expecta-tions.    Moreover, any announcement on threshold arrangementsfor Stage 2 would have to be very carefully presented to the public,since the natural expectation would be that these arrangements should compensate for the whole of the increase in the cost ofliving since the standstill.    The Government would also have tobe ready to explain why the same arrangements would not applyto the social security benefits for the short-term unemployed and the sick.In further discussior- the following main points were made:-a.    The effect of threshold agreements on consumerdemand should be to correct to some extent thereduction in demand caused by the increase in import prices.    The effect on the exchange rate should alsobe beneficial, in as much as international confidence inthe capacity of the Government to manage the economywithout industrial disruption should be reinforced.
b. It was unfortunate that the payments would not bemade direct to the housewife, who had to pay theincreased prices.    But that argument was valid inrelation to any form of pay increase; and there were serious practical difficulties in an early increase in family allowances.c. It was suggested that,  instead of a flat rate increaseof 30p, each 1 per cent increase in the RPI over thethreshold should be matched by an increase of 1 per centin pay.    This, however, would remove the bias infavour of the low paid;  and it could also createanomalies which would add considerably to the work ofthe Pay Board.d. Another course would be to revise the Stage pay limit from  1 plus 4 per cent to  1 plus 5 per cent.But this would involve retrospective payments to a degree which would cause serious difficulties for employers.e. The introduction of threshold agreements would reinforce the desirability of starting Stage 3 on 6 Novemberinstead of 1 November, in order that Stage 2 might endexactly 12 months after the beginning of the standstill.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed that, in the debate in the House of commons on the following day, he should announce an increase in theneeds allowance for rent rebates on the lines proposed     TheCabinet also agreed that he should say in the debate that a safe-guard, in the form of a threshold arrangement, would beintroduced for Stage 3.    They felt that it would be desirable tointroduce a similar safeguard in Stage 2; but a number of detailed issues had been raised in discussion about the form which that safeguard might take.    He would arrange, inconsultation, with the Chancellor of the Exchequer and theLord President, for these points to be examined further andwould discuss with them the best way in which the proposed arrangements should be presented in his speech the following day.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the summing upof their discussion by the Prime Minister.
b. It was unfortunate that the payments would not bemade direct to the housewife, who had to pay theincreased prices.    But that argument was valid inrelation to any form of pay increase; and there were serious practical difficulties in an early increase in family allowances.c. It was suggested that,  instead of a flat rate increaseof 30p, each 1 per cent increase in the RPI over thethreshold should be matched by an increase of 1 per centin pay.    This, however, would remove the bias infavour of the low paid;  and it could also createanomalies which would add considerably to the work ofthe Pay Board.d. Another course would be to revise the Stage pay limit from  1 plus 4 per cent to  1 plus 5 per cent.But this would involve retrospective payments to a degree which would cause serious difficulties for employers.e. The introduction of threshold agreements would reinforce the desirability of starting Stage 3 on 6 Novemberinstead of 1 November, in order that Stage 2 might endexactly 12 months after the beginning of the standstill.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed that, in the debate in the House of commons on the following day, he should announce an increase in theneeds allowance for rent rebates on the lines proposed     TheCabinet also agreed that he should say in the debate that a safe-guard, in the form of a threshold arrangement, would beintroduced for Stage 3.    They felt that it would be desirable tointroduce a similar safeguard in Stage 2;  but a number of detailed issues had been raised in discussion about the form which that safeguard might take.    He would arrange, inconsultation, with the Chancellor of the Exchequer and theLord President, for these points to be examined further andwould discuss with them the best way in which the proposed arrangements should be presented in his speech the following day.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the summing upof their discussion by the Prime Minister.

</content>
</cab>
