<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/9/0 images: 30-39</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government.]14Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1919.SECRET.WAR CABINET. 517.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.fon Friday, January 17, 1919, at 12 noon.Present :The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of Kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.(in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, ALP.The Right Hon, Sir E. Geddes, G.B.E.,G.C.B., M.P.The following were also present :The Right Hon. W. Long, M.P., First Lordof the Admiralty (&quot;for Minutes 1 to 3).Admiral Sir R. E. Wemyss, G.C.B.,C.M.G., M.V.O., First Sea Lord and chief of the Naval staff (for minutes to 3).The Right Hon. Sir A. Stanley, M.P.,President, Board of Trade (for minutes and 4).The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (for minutes and 4).The Right Hon. E. Shortt, K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs (for minutes 3 to ti).The Right Hon. C. Addison, M.D., M.P.,President, Local Government Board (for minutes 3 and 4).The Right Hon. Lord Inyerforth,Minister of Munitions (for Minutes 3and 4).Mr. Thomas Jones, Acting Secretary.Lieutenant G. M. Evans, Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. S. Storr, C.B., Assistant Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, C.B., Assistant Secretary.GovernmentPurchase of 1919Flax Crop.[826]-561. With refereuce to War Cabinet 516, Minute 6, the Chancellorof the Exchequer said that, after consultation with Lord Colwyn andSir Albert Stanley, he had agreed to the guarantee of 25s. to 35s.per stone proposed by the Flax Control Board for the 1919 crop.It had further been agreed amongst them that, in view of this guarantee, the control on the import of flax should be retained, inorder to avoid, until the question was further considered, such a fall of prices as would throw a heavy loss upon the Treasury. TheChancellor of the Exchequer said that, in agreeing to the guarantee,he had b&quot;en mainly influenced by the fact stated by Lord Colwyn,that the guaranteed price was no more (probably rather less) thanthe equivalent of the guaranteed prices of cereals, and that, havingB
2Battle CruiserProgramme.regard to the profits obtainable by growing cereals at the presenttime, there was every reason to believe that without a guarantee forflax the whole of the increased acreage would be lost. It was thought extremely unlikely that any large quantities of flax wouldbe available from Russia or Belgium, and unlikely that in point- of fact any loss would be incurred to the Treasury. It had been agreedthat the arrangement was in itself undesirable, both in character and form, and was only justified by the exceptional circumstances of theWar period.2. The War Cabinet had before them an Admiralty memorandum(Paper G.T.-6653) in regard to the question of resuming work onthe &quot; Anson,&quot; the &quot; Plowe,&quot; and the &quot;Rodney.&quot;The Chancellor of the Exchequer pointed out the impossibility of coining to a decision in regard to this question until it was knownwhat line would be taken at the Peace Congress respecting naval armaments.In these circumstances the War Cabinet decided-To postpone the question.Oil Fuel Reserve.3. With reference to War Cabinet 515, Minute 13, the WarCabinet had before them a memorandum by the Admiralty(Paper G.T.-6594), together with a memorandum by Mr. Long(Paper G.T.-6634), in regard to the oil-fuel reserve for the navy in home waters.In the Admiralty memorandum it was pointed out that thenavy was now dependent upon the United States of America for itsvital supplies of oil-fuel to the extent of 80 per cent., and that thisdependence must continue unless and until alternative supplies could be devoloped. So far as could at present be foreseen, therewere only two sources of supply which might be sufficiently developed to cover any large proportion of our naval requirements. these were (1.) Home production. &apos;(2.) The Persian and ,Mesopotamian oilfields.The supplies now available, or likely to be available, from anyother sources were so deficient either in quantity or quality thatthey might be regarded as negligible. We had therefore no visiblemeans of avoiding absolute dependence on the United States ofAmerica except by providing adequate storage and maintaining largepost-war reserve stocks. The Admiralty were of opinion that theminimum reserve which it was safe to provide should be twelvemonths&apos; consumption on a war basis.The First Sea Lord said that it was not possible to furnishaccurate figures until the future standard of the navy was decided on, but in all probability the expenditure, spread over a considerable period, would not be more than about 400,000Z. a year.Mr. Long said that he fully concurred in the proposals containedin the Admiralty memorandum. When he had taken charge, at therequest of the War Cabinet, of oil questions some eighteen monthspreviously, the situation was one of grave anxiety. We had inthis country such inadequate provision for storage that we wereliving from hand to mouth. At that time the navy were hamperedin their movements, the army had only just enough for their needs,while civilian supplies in some places were non-existent. At onecritical moment it had been necessary to deprive the oil consumersin the south and west of England of their petrol in order to send thenecessary supplies to France. He added that he did not want to embarrass the Chancellor of the Exchequer hy pressing the question,
Surplus Govern- 4. With reference to War Cabinet No. 500, Minute 9. the Warment Property in      Cabinet had before them the following papers : France.. Memorandum by the War Office (Paper G.T.-6542).Memorandum by Sir Eric desire (Paper G.T.-6563)       &apos;Memorandum by Sir Albert Stanley (Paper G.T.-6657).In the Memorandum by the Secretary of State for War it waspointed Out that the French Government, through M. Claveille, had expressed a desire to purchase certain transport material held by theBritish Army in France. The magnitude of the question was such that a decision of the War Cabinet was sought on the followingpoints : but he was convinced that the policy of storing large stocks of oil inthis country was a vital necessity.Lord Curzon said that, in addition to the two sources of supplymentioned in the Admiralty memorandum, there wasalsothe possibilityof obtaining oil from Baku. The oil-wells there were the greatest in asia, and were in the possession of Armenians and Tartars. Therewas a pipe-line from Baku to Batum, and now that the railwaysand shipping in that part of the world were in our hands thereajjpeared to be a possibility of making a purchase of oil in our own interests. Another possible source of supply was the oilfields of burma.The First Sea Lord undertook to examine the question of theBaku oilfields, and to submit a paper to the Cabinet on thesubject.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he regarded theprovision of adequate storage of large stocks of oil as a matter ofvast importance. A strong case had been made out for theextension of storage accommodation. He hoped that the Ministerof Supply would consider the question of increasing also the amountof non-Government storage. Subject to consideration of the NavalEstimates later he agreed provisionally to the proposals containedin the Admiralty memorandum.With regard to co-ordinating the demands of the various departments, Mr. Long said that, before the Petroleum Executivewas set up, each Department had been in the habit of helping itself.The Executive had consolidated the work, and in future he hopedthat the policy of the Government would be to continue the central control of purchases.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the question of themaintenance and expansion of supplies of oil for the use of thiscountry appeared to be one for the newly-created Ministry ofSupply. He therefore suggested that the Minister of Supply should confer with Mr. Long and obtain the benefit of Mr. Long&apos;s wide experience in these matters. He further suggested that the Boardof Trade- and the India Office should also be represented in anyconference that might be held.Mr. Long said that he gratefully accepted the suggestion thatthe Minister of Supply should confer with him.To sum up, the War Cabinet decided (a.) To approve the proposals contained in the admiralty memorandum in regard to the oil-fuel reserves.(6.) That the Minister of Supply should confer with the FirstLord of the Admiralty, the President of the Board ofTrade, and the Secretary of State for India in regard tothe whole question of the supply of oil.(c.) That the First Sea Lord should submit a paper in regardto the possibility of obtaining supplies from Baku.
a(a.) Whether M. Claveille was to be informed that the transportmaterial, less certain items, was at his disposal on terms to be agreed ;(6.) Whether M. Claveille was to be told that all equipment was required at home, and that it was proposed to transportit to England ;(c.) In the event of (a) being accepted, who was to negotiate thesale.The President of the Board of Trade, in his Memorandum,suggested that the French Government might be informed that theEnglish railway companies would want their rolling-stock returned(possibly with some small exceptions), but nothing else; that asregards the light railways, neither the rails nor the stock would bewanted in this country ; that nearly all the cranes and similar plantin connection with port equipment could be used in this country ;that some of the tugs and barges might be of use on the largerEnglish canals ; that it was unlikely that the railway engineeringplant would be wanted here; and that the whole of the road plantwould be wanted in this country. Sir Albert Stanley added thatwhile Sir Eric Geddes was in a better position to deal with questionsof the future of transj^ort in this country than himself, he was ofopinion that the chances of a large development of light railwaysfor agricultural purposes were very remote. Already there werehuge arrears to be made good in other directions. The Englishrailways were showing a deficit of some 90,000,000/. a year;the canals also were in a bad way financially ; the Irish railways were bankrupt; the schemes for standardisation of rolling-stock and electrification would involve large sums of money; and it seemed to him that it would be a long time before there was anyquestion of using thousands of miles of rails for light lines in thiscountry.Sir Eric Geddes said that, in the main, he agreed with SirAlbert Stanley that the prospect of laying thousands of miles of light railways was a remote one. In his Memorandum (Paper G.T.-6563)he had expressed the opinion that, so far as light railway rails were concerned, on the whole. it would be advisable to dispose of these,or the major portion&apos; thereof, to the French. As regards broad-gauge rails, these were generally of a lighter section than used inthis country at present, but were suitable for colonial railways tosome extent, and the Colonial Office would no doubt wish to putforward their demands. He considered it desirable, as a. preliminarystep, to catalogue, with the necessary specifications, the whole ofthe important plant in question, and ascertain.from the authorities concerned the Board of Trade, the Colonial Office, the India Office,the Railway Executive Committee, the Dock Authorities, the RoadBoard, and Port Cmservancy Authorities. &amp;c. information as towhat plant and materials they would wish to obtain from France.Sir Eric Geddes also drew attention to the political treasons whichmight exist to the effect that we should assist the French in the rehabilitation of their destroyed country. There was also thequestion of finance, e.g., the increase of the indebtedness of France tothis country, and the further question as to whether we were in anyway justified in sacrificing ourselves to make up for the shortage ofrailway equipment in France prior to the war. - ;The Minister of Supply said that his Department was at workupon a complete plan for disposing of all surplus stores in all thetheatres of war, and he hoped to have the scheme complete on thefollowing day. A catalogue Avould be drawn up, and the different departments would be asked as to what stores they required. Afterthe Departments and Authorities concerned had notified him inregard to their requirements, he would then sell the rest of the stocks. He was already selling for cash to some extent in France,,and had so far realised about 10,000,000 francs in this way from private buyers.
Repatriation of 5.  The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by LordEnemy Aliens, Cave on  the Return of Enemy Aliens (Paper G.T.-6496).    ThePaper suggested that the time had come when the repatriation of civilian alien enemies who were in internment camps might be commended, the ships now emplojed in bringing prisoners of war tothis country being utilised for sending enemy aliens back to Germany.The Army Council had been consulted, and had no objection to theproposed repatriation, provided that information was given to theWar Office before any action was taken in respect of those enemy subjects who were of interest to the German authorities.The Home Secretary said that the above Paper had beenprepared and submitted by his predecessor in office, but he himselfconcurred in the proposal.Sir Eric Geddes pointed out that a certain number of enemy aliens were essentially pivotal men, and these could certainly not be spared. He suggested that such pivotal men as were employedoutside the internment camps should not be repatriated until theMinistry of Labour had been consulted.The War Cabinet decided (a.) To approve the proposal of the late Home Secretary regardingrepatriation of enemy aliens from internment camps.(b.) That as regards aliens employed outside camps, these shouldnot be repatriated without reference, in the first instance,to the Ministry of Labour.Employment inGovernmentDepartments ofPersons not whollyof BritishExtraction.[826-56]6. The War Cabinet had before them a note by Mr. Bonar Law,submitting a memorandum by Sir Thomas Heath regarding theemployment in Government Departments of persons not wholly ofBritish extraction (Paper G.T.-6378).    (Appendix.)Mr. Chamberlain said that the Paper had been circulated by his predecessor without any expression of opinion. In the previous July,the War Cabinet had decided (War Cabinet 444, Minute 7) that noone should be employed in Government Offices or Departments unlessbe is the son of natural-born British or Allied subjects, butexception might be made for definite reasons of national importance.Sir Thomas Heaths present suggestion was that the various Depart-ments might be authorised to suspend all action in regard to the dismissal of alien-descended persons, pending any report by LordJustice Bankes&apos; Committee to the Prime Minister.Sir Eric Geddes said that one of the principal difficulties withwhich Departments had. been faced in dealing with this question wasthe fact that so many officers and officials in His Majesty&apos;s services were concerned. He fancied that, since Lord Justice Banke s-Committee had been appointed to enquire into individual cases, t hDepartments had taken no further action themselves to sort out and dr. Addison took the view that the material for light railways should not be disposed of until the requirements of local authoritiesin this country had been considered.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was entirely infavour of selling for cash, on the lines mentioned by the Minister ofSupply; if, however, it was merely a question of credit, there wouldbe a balance of disadvantages to be considered. He agreed with SirAlbert Stanley that it would be a mistake to bring to this country,and store large quantities of material when there was considerable uncertainty as to Avhen that material could be used.The War Cabinet decided that The Minister of Supply should be given a free hand in disposing(in consultation with the Departments concerned) of surplusGovernment property.
(a.) Whether M. Claveille was to be informed that the transportmaterial, less certain items, was at his disposal on terms to be agreed ;(b.) Whether M. Claveille was to be told that all equipment was required at home, and that it was proposed to transportit to England;(c.) In the event of (a) being accepted, who was to negotiate thesale.The President of the Board of Trade, in his Memorandum)suggested that the French Government might be informed that theEnglish railway companies would want their rolling-stock returned(possibly with some small exceptions), but nothing else; that asregards the light railways, neither the rails nor the stock would bewanted in this country; that nearly all the cranes and similar plantin connection with port equipment could be used in this country ;that some of the tugs and barges might be of use on the largerEnglish canals ; that it was unlikely that the railway engineering-plant would be wanted here ; and that the whole of the road plantwould be wanted in this country. Sir Albert Stanley added thatwhile Sir Eric Geddes was in a better position to deal with questionsof the future of transport in this country than himself, he was ofopinion that the chances of a large. development of light railwaysfor agricultural purposes were very remote. Already there werehuge arrears to be made good in other directions. The Englishrailways were showing a deficit of some 90,000,OOOZ. a year;the canals also were in a bad way financially ; the Irish railways were bankrupt; the schemes for standardisation of rolling-stock and electrification would involve large sums of money; and it seemed to him that it would be a long time before there was anyquestion of using thousands of miles of rails for light lines in thiscountry.Sir Eric Geddes said that, in the main, he agreed with SirAlbert Stanley that the prospect of laying thousands of miles of light railways was a remote one. In his Memorandum (Paper G.T.-6503)he had expressed the opinion that, so far as light railway rails were concerned, on the whole it woidd be advisable to dispose of these,or the major portion thereof, to the French. As regards broad-gauge rails, these were generally of a lighter section than used inthis country at present, but were suitable for colonial railways tosome extent, and the. Colonial Office would no doubt wish to putforward their demands. He considered it desirable, as a preliminarystep, to catalogue, with the necessary specifications, the whole ofthe important plant in question, and ascertain from the authorities concerned the Board of Trade, the Colonial Office, the India Office,the Railway Executive Committee, the Dock Authorities, the RoadBoard, and Port C mservancy Authorities, &amp;c. informatiou as towhat plant and materials they would wish to obtain from France.Sir Eric Geddes also drew attention to the political reasons whichmight exist to the effect that we should assist the French in the rehabilitation of their destroyed country. There was also thequestion of finance, e.g., the increase of the indebtedness of France tothis country, and the further question as to whether we were in anyway justified in sacrificing ourselves to make up for the shortage ofrailway equipment in Prance prior to the war. s - -The Minister of Supply said that his Department was at workupon a complete plan for disposing of all surplus stores in all thetheatres of war, and he hoped to have the scheme complete on thefollowing day. A catalogue would be drawn up, and the different departments would be asked as to what stores they required. Afterthe Departments and Authorities concerned had notified him inregard to their requirements, he would then sell the rest of the stocks. He was already selling for cash to some extent in France,,and had so far realised about 10,000,000 francs in this way from private buyers.
Dr. Addjson took the view that the material for light railways should not be disposed of until the requirements of local authoritiesin this country had been considered.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was entirely infavour of selling for cash, on the lines mentioned by the Minister ofSupply; if, however, it was merely a question of credit, there wouldbe a balance of disadvantages to be considered. He agreed with SirAlbert Stanley that it would be a mistake to bring to this country,and store large quantities of material when there was considerable uncertainty as to when that material could be used.The War Cabinet decided that -The Minister of Supply should be given a free hand in disposing(in consultation with the Departments concerned) of surplusGovernment property.Repatriation of 5. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by LordEnemy Aliens, Cave on the Return of Enemy Aliens (Paper G.T.-649tJ).    ThePaper suggested that the time had come when the repatriation of civilian alien enemies who were in internment camps might be commended, the ships now employed in bringing prisoners of war tothis country being utilised for sending- enemy aliens back to Germany.; The Army Council had been consulted, and had no objection to theproposed repatriation, provided that information was given to theWar Office before any action was taken in respect of those enemy subjects who were of interest to the German authorities.The Home Secretary said that the above Paper&apos; had beenprepared and submitted by his predecessor in office, but he himselfconcurred in the proposal.Sir Eric Geddes pointed out that a certain number of enemy aliens were essentially pivotal men, and these could certainly not be spared. He suggested that such pivotal men as were employedoutside the internment camps should not be repatriated until theMinistry of Labour had been consulted.The War Cabinet decided (a.) To approve the proposal of the late Home Secretary regardingrepatriation of enemy aliens from internment camps.(b.) That as regards aliens employed outside camps, these shouldnot be repatriated without reference, in the first instance,,to the Ministry of Labour. .Employment inGovernmentDepartments ofPersons not whollyof BritishExtraction.[826-56]6. The War Cabinet had before them a note by Mr. Bonar Law,submitting a memorandum by Sir Thomas Heath regarding theemployment in Government Departments of persons not wholly ofBritish extraction (Paper G.T.-637 8).   (Appendix.)Mr. Chamberlain said that the Paper had been circulated by his predecessor without any expression of opinion. In the previous July,the War Cabinet had decided (War Cabinet 444, Minute 7) that noone should be employed in Government Offices or Departments unless he is the&apos; son of natural-born British or Allied subjects, butexception might be made for definite reasons of national importance.Sir Thomas Heath&apos;s present suggestion was that the various Depart-ments might be authorised to suspend all action in regard to the dismissal of alien-descended persons, pending any report by LordJustice Bankes&apos; Committee to the Prime Minister.Sir Eric Geddes said that one of the principal difficulties withwhich Departments had been faced in dealing with this question wasthe fact that so many officers and officials in His Majesty&apos;s services were concerned. He fancied that, since Lord Justice Banke s-Committee had been appointed to enquire into individual cases, t hDepartments had taken no further action themselves to sort out and
dismiss employees of alien descent. Sir Thomas Heath&apos;s paperreferred only to the action to be taken during the war, and in regardto this he concurred in Sir Thomas&apos;s proposal. He thought,however, that it might be well to look ahead, and to ask LordJustice Bankes&apos; Committee to go into the post-war aspect of thequestion and to submit their recommendations, with a view toregulating the employment of such persons in the future.The War Cabinet decided (a.) To approve the proposal that all action in regard to the dismissal from Government Departments of persons not wholly of British extraction employed therein should be suspended pending any report by Lord Justice Bankes&apos;Committee.(b.) To ask the Chancellor of the Exchequer to look intoSir Eric Geddes&apos; suggestion as to possible regulations for the future.(Initialled) C. of K. .2, Whitehall Gardens, 8.W. 1,January 17, 1919.
APPENDIX.G.T.-6378. --Government Departments.The Employment of Persons not wholly of British Extraction.I CIRCULATE the following memorandum by Sir Thomas Heath for considerationby the War Cabinet at an early date.(Signed)      A. BONAR LAW.Treasury, S.W.,November 26, 1918.In July last the War Cabinet decided that no person should be employed in any government office during the present war who is not the child of natural-born subjects of this country or of an Allied country, unless there is a definite national reason for such employment. A letter was sent out from the Prime Ministers Private Secretary onthe 13th August to Departments notifying them of this decision, and of the appoint-ment of Lord Justice Bankes&apos; Committee, and asking- the Departments to ascertain the names of all persons employed in them who were not the children of natural-bornsubjects of this country or an Allied country, and to refer to the Committee the casesof those persons whom they desired for definite national reasons to retain.The Committee issued a circular asking Departments to furnish a list giving thefull names and addresses of all persons coming under the exclusion, and, as to any such persons whom it was desired to retain, the reasons for that desire.This was taken to mean that the Committee was to consider in some way all thecases and not only the cases recommended for retention.Consequently, as I understand, no Department has yet dismissed anyone, allthe Departments having waited for the Committee to report on the whole matter.This being so, and the armistice having altered the situation, it would seem verydifficult now. to send away any of the alien-descended persons, and I have been appealed to, especially by the Post Office and the Customs and Excise, as to whether they mightnot suspend all action in the matter.I think myself that they might be authorised at all events to suspend all actionpending any report by the Committee to the Prime Minister and any action taken,thereon.


</content>
</cab>
