<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/9/0 images: 86-97</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is.....the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.    February l&apos;.)i9.SECRET.27WAR CABINET, 525.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, downing Street, S.W., on tuesday, February 4, 1919, at 1L30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, KG., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P.The following were also present:The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G., Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (for minutes-4).The Right Hon. Sir A. Stanley, M.P.,President, Board of Trade (for minutes-3).The Right Hon. Sir A. C Geddes, K.C.B.,M.P., Minister of Reconstruction and national Service (for Minute 1-8).The Right Hon. Sir R. S. Horne, K.B.E.,K.C., M.P, Minister of Labour (for minutes 1-3).Sir D. J. Shackleton, K.C.B., permanent secretary, Ministry of Labour (for minutes 1-3).The Right Hon. E. Shortt, ICC... M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs.The bight Hon. J. I. Macpherson, M.P.,Chief Secretary for Ireland (for minutes-S).The Right Hon. Sir j. Maclay, Bt.,Shipping Controller (for Minutes 1-4).The Right. Hon. A. H. Illingworth,M.P., Postmaster-General (for minutes-4).Major-General j. E. B. Seely, C.B.,C.M.G., D.S.O., M.P., Under-Secretaryof State for the Air Force (for minute ).Vice-Admiral S. R. Fremantle, C.B.,M.V.O., Deputy Chief of the naval staff (for Minute 4).Mr. Thomas Jones, Acting Secretary.Captain L. F. Burgis, Assistant Secretary.Brigadier-General S. H. Wilson, C.B., C.M.G., Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. Storr, C.B., Assistant Secretary.Mr. G. M. Evans, Asdstant Secretary.[826)-126
21. With reference to War Cabinet 524, Minute 6, Mr. bonar law said that when the question of the recognition of the RailwayClerks&apos; Association last came up for discussion, the War cabinet decided to appoint a small Committee to go into the question. ThisCommittee had met on Sunday last and again on the previous night,and he understood that all present, with the exception of Sir albert stanley, had come to the decision that recognition of the Association,with certain conditions, should be given.Sir Albert Stanley said that, after the meeting of the Committeelast Sunday, he took steps, after consulting Sir Herbert Walker andSir A. Butterworth, to request Mr. Wardle, who was friendly withthe Association of Railway Clerks, to see the General Secretary,Mr. Walkden, and find out whether it was possible to arrive at a compromise. No instructions were given to Mr. Wardle, but bewas to obtain clearly the Association^ views. The compromise now suggested, as a result of Mr. Wardle&apos;s conversation, was that recog-nition should be given to the Association, and permission for themto represent all grades of employees; but with regard to station-masters and certain supervisory grades there should be autonomywithin the Union. This autonomy should ensure that when demands were put forward by the supervised grades they should not representthe views of the supervisory grades. This would, in effect, resultin the members belonging to the same Union, but there would beseparate sections, and these separate sections would safeguard, as faras possible, the vital question of discipline.Sir Robert Home stated that, if this question was being investigated afresh, his attitude would be in sympathy with SirAlbert Stanley. He thought it very detrimental to discipline if thesupervisors and the supervised belonged to the same Union, and thegeneral practice throughout the country had been not to allowUnions to speak for the former. This applied to the amalgamated society of Engineers and the Shipyard Unions. This was a soundprinciple. The present situation was rendered difficult iuasmuch asfive-eighths of the stationmasters were at present members of theRailway Clerks&apos; Association, and this fact made it possible for thecase to be presented to the public on the ground that the Govern-ment refused to recognise a Union. The Government could not hope to win through present and future labour battles unless theyhad the support of the Trade Union Executives, and if the Govern-ment took up the line which the Railway Executive wanted themto take up there was no doubt that the sympathy of the TradeUnions would be alienated. His predecessor in office, Mr. Roberts,was in favour of accepting the compromise suggested by Mr.Walkden. in the following week there was probably to be a TradeUnion Congress, and if the Government refused the suggestedcompromise there was no doubt that the discussions at that congress would go against the Government, and the men taking part in theCongress were those upon whom the Government relied. He there-fore recommended compromise, and if it was possible to segregatethe stationmasters and the supervisory grades in the Union andensure that these sections should, when they had demands to putforward, represent their own case and choose their own spokesmen,we should, in his opinion, have achieved most of our object.Lord Curzon asked what was the real value of completeautonomy.Sir Robert Home replied that the stationmasters and supervisorygrades were not asking for a separate Union, but that it was our suggestion that they should have autonomy. If the Association ofRailway Clerks decided on a strike, he doubted whether it would bepossible for the stationmasters not to come out.Mr Bonar Law said, he thought that it would be part of theattempted compromise that stationmasters should not join in a strikewithout their own approval.Sir Robert Home thought it would be difficult to achieve that,
although there was to be no compulsion for anyone to join theAssociation.i Lord Milner pointed out that the Secretary of the association had intimated that they would agree to a certain number of con-fidential clerks, &amp;c, who held high positions, not joining theAssociation.Mr. Illihffworth drew attention to Mr. Wardles remarks at theConference held at the Board of Trade on the previous afternoon, mwhich he said that this was the first time that there had been a bintof a strike in this Association. They did not want a strike, and itwas not their policy, and he (Mr. Wardle) doubted whether clerkscalling out station masters on strike would really arise in practice,adding that it might be possible to come to an agreement that thestationmasters should have the right to decide by themselves whetherthey should strike or not.Mr. Bonar Law said this was by far the most difficult labourproblem they had yet had to solve. Up to now, in any decisions theyhad had to arrive at with regard to industrial troubles, there had been no doubt as to what was the right action. In this case, whatever theGovernment decided was bound to cause considerable political trouble.The only chance of coming through was to have public opinion on our side. If recognition of this Union were refused, opponents of theGovernment would say it was the old trouble of refusing to recogniseUnions cropping up again. Hitherto a section of the press usuallyopposed to them had been on the side of the Government, but should the compromise be refused this press would turn against theGovernment, and there was no doubt that the bulk of Trade L nionistswould also be against the Government. He did not, however, over-look the seriousness of the position which would result from accepting the compromise. Employees would regard it as giving away the passand making it impossible for them to fight in the future a similardemand in other industries. there would be an outcry when thedecision was known, and they would lie accused of the same weakness of which thev were accused during the war. He had tried toexplain the position to the Prime Minister on tin- telephone, but this had nut been easy. On the whole, the Prime Minister had been strongly opposed to a strike on the refusal to recognise a Union.Mr. Bonar Law said that he had seen tin.- members of the railway executive, and thought that they exaggerated the seriousness of the concession. V. e must say either &quot; Yes&quot; or &quot; No,&quot; and on the whole he was of opinion that it was right to agree to the compromise.When the question had last come up before the Cabinet, it was not known that there would be a complete strike on the railways ifrecognition were not given to the Railway Clerks&apos; Association.Sir Albert Stanley had informed him that this would now happen.Perhaps the right course now was to allow negotiations to take placeon the basis that tin3 Government was ready to recognise the Unionprovided that safeguards were obtained regarding the maintenanceof discipline avid that strong guarantees were given in this direction.These negotiations with the Railway Clerks&apos; Association wouldprobably have some success, as Mr. Walkden would be delighted atthe recognition of his Association. The balance of disadvantageseemed to be in refusing to recognise the Association. This was attended by the danger of the employers saying that w e had givenaway the pass, but if we did not take the course he suggested thewhole of the Trade Union movement would be against the Govern-ment.Mr. Chamberlain said that he agreed with Mr. Bonar Law. a fight on the ground of refusing recognition was the worst that couldbe chosen. If we were attacked by the employers it might be pointed out them that the majority of stationmasters were nowmembers of the Union.Mr. Bonar Law, continuing, said he thought we should go thelength of saying that we recognise the Union in general terms, but
that recognition depended on receiving the safeguards considered necessary for the maintenance of discipline.Mr. Chamberlain thought that it should be explained that thisdiscipline was really a question of life and limb, and necessary forthe public safety. On the whole, he thought the presence of the older men, occupying responsible positions, would tend to exercise amoderating influence on the policy of the Association.Sir Albert Stanley said it was true that a large number ofstationmasters were members of this Association, and mixed up with other employees. This decision did not mean that station-masters alone would be allowed to join the Association ; the permis-sion would have to be extended to other supervisory grades. Whatwas true about stationmasters in this Association applied equally toforemen in other industries and Unions, it meant, in effect, notonly recognition of supervisory grades in this Association, but itwould raise the whole question of the position of foremen in therailway companies and in other industries.Mr. Bonar Law said that if we agreed to this compromise, ourbusiness was to minimise the effect of the decision as much aspossible, and to avoid its importance being magnified in the press.Sir Joseph Maclay said he was strongly in favour of the compromise. With reasonable safeguards he did not see that therewould be much danger.Sir Robert Horne said that the employers were frightenedbecause in certain industries the foremen fixed the amount of thepiece-rate on the spot, and if the foremen and the men belonged tothe same Union and the men were dissatisfied with the piece-rate and decided to deal with the foreman in a disciplinary way, an impossible position would result. He knew of cases where foremenhad been fined by their Union for reporting some of the menunder them.Sir Albert Stanley said that, when he was with the undergroundrailways,- a fatal accident had resulted from a foreman failing toreport one of his men. When asked why he did not report theman, the foreman replied that he would rather resign his position inthe Compaiw than face the censure of the Union.Mr. Bonar Law pointed out that, as the supervisory gradeswere now in the Railway Clerks&apos; Association, this evil would existwhether the Association were recognised or not.Sir Albert Stanley urged that the policy of unlimited recognitionwrould, in effect, make the officials servants of the Association ratherthan of the Companies, and it was impossible to control the conductof the Union. For example, in negotiations with the leaders of theNational Union of Railwaymen, agreements were arrived at, butthe leaders found that they could not control their different branchesand make them observe the agreements, Agreements had been arrived at with prominent leaders, only to be repudiated by theirExecutives.Mr. Churchill said that the Trade Union organisation was veryimperfect, and the more moderate its officials were the less repre-sentative it was, but it was the only organisation with which theGovernment could deal. The curse of Trade Unionism was thatthere was hot enough of it, and it was not highly enough developed to make its branch secretaries fall into line with the head office.With a powerful Union either peace or war could be made. He didnot see how this particular proposal Avould make it more difficult todead with the Railway Unions.Sir Joseph Maclay said he thought better discipline would result from having the older and more responsible men as members of theUnion.   We had been labouring under many delusions with regard .to the workmen of the country.Mr. Bonar Law thought that the Trade Union organisation wasthe only thing between us and anarchy, and if the Trade union organisation was against us the position would be hopeless.
5 WC 525Sir Albert Stanley held that this problem was not to be looked upon merely as a railway problem. It was quite an accident thatthis question of supervisory and supervised grades belonging to thesame Union had been put forward first by the Railway Clerks&apos; Asso-ciation. It was a matter which affected all industries. Then thisgrave question affected the Railway Executive in other directions, asthe Railway Company Chairmen were closely connected with otherindustries. It was not a question of the principle of recognition, buta question of the range of membership in the Union. There wouldbe no objection to the supervisory grades forming their own separateUnion.Lord Curzon thought that there was great force in whatSir Albert Stanley said, and that the present difficulty would extend to other industries, but, on the whole, he yielded to the way inwhich Mr. Bonar Law had stated the position.Mr. Illingworth said he shared the views expiessed by Mr. bonar law. He saw no satisfactory way out of the difficulty, except bythe compromise suggested. If the Goverment forced a conflict theywould be beaten, and a worse situation would arise.Lord Milner suggested that Mr. Walkden should be informedthat the Government were disposed to recognise the Union as representing the supervisory as well as the supervised grades, pro-vided that the Association was prepared to make internal safe-guards within their Association for the efficient maintenance of discipline and public safety.Mr. Bonar Law said that what they had now to do was to make sure that the case was presented to the public in a form that would do the least harm to other trades.The War Cabinet decided that-The President of the Board of Trade, together with theMinister of Labour, should inform the General Secretaryof the Railway (lerks&apos; Association that the Governmentwas prepared to recognise the Association as representingthe supervisory and supervised grades, provided that theAssociation would give the necessary safeguards withregard to the maintenance of discipline and public safetywithin the Association.Tube Strike. 2. With   regard   to the Underground   strike at present   inprogress Sir Albert Stanley informed the Cabinet that he hadreceived the following letter from Mr. T. Bromley, the general secretary of the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and firemen : &quot; 1 am instructed by my Executive Committee to inform you that my Executive have taken charge of the strike on theLondon Electric Railways caused by the departure from theterms of the eight hours&apos; day agreement by Sir H. Walkeracting, we presume, on behalf of the Railway Executive Com-mittee, and that we are making our headquarters at theImperial Hotel, Russell Square.&quot;Threatened London 3. Mr. Shortt informed the  Cabinet that he   had arrangedElectrical Strike.      with the Commissioner of Police and Sir Edward Ward to ascer-tain how many Special Constables would be available to work the electric pow^r stations in the event of a strike.Sir Robert Home said that, when there was a question of anelectrical strike during the war a Committee had been assembled totake the necessary measures to meet the situation (War Cabinet 492,[826] 126 C*
Minute 14). He was of opinion that some such Committeeshould be formed to meet the present emergency and make thenecessary arrangements.Some discussion then took place as to whether it would bepossible to employ the military to run the power-stations, now that the war was over and it was no longer a question of nationalsafety.Mr. Churchill said that he was not prepared to say that soldiers could not be obtained, but he had always tried to keep theArmy out of an affair of this kind, if possible. He understood thatthe Navy was in a position to break any strike affecting the publicmunicipal services. He could not see, however, the distinctionbetween the war and a great civil emergency, though thatemergency had not yet been reached. At a certain point he wouldnot hesitate to use soldiers if it was a question of saving lives. . it seemed to him that the Government should face this challenge, andhe had no doubt of the substantial loyalty of the mass of the nation.The threatened electrical strike was one of a. series of attempts of awell-organised minority to obtain extravagant concessions. If weallowed this sort of thing to go on, the day would arrive when allauthority would be discredited. He would fight in this instance,and use Parliament as the weapon. It was intolerable that a fewmen should be allowed to throw thousands into confusion. It was essential, however, to be backed by the people. He would framelegislation to deal with the situation, and make the agitatorsamenable to law by fine and imprisonment. If the addresses ofthese agitators were known, they would be visited by the public, andthe reverse of picketing would result. This happened in the railway strike of 19 LO.Sir Robert Home said that legislation such as that suggestedby Mr. Churchill was in existence under an Act of 1875. ThisAct enabled the Government to imprison any persons engaged inthe supply of gas and water who deserted their posts withoutreasonable notice. Under the Defence of the Realm Act it wouldbe possible to pass a regulation applying this section of the Act toelectricity.Lord Curzon thought that it was necessary to appoint notmerely a temporary but a permanent Committee to sit during thisperiod of labour unrest. The time of the War Cabinet was muchtaken up with settling details which might well be decided by aCommittee such as he suggested. Questions of principle would, ofcourse, come before the War Cabinet. This Committee might consistof representatives from the Admiralty, the War Office, the HomeOffice, the Board of Trade, the Ministry of Labour, and the Com-missioner of Police. He would like to suggest that this Committeeshould take in hand not only the preparations and organisationnecessary to meet a strike, but also publicity arid propaganda. Agood press was capable of influencing public opinion in favour of theGovernment. There was no doubt that the present agitations wereorganised by a men; handful of persons, and the community ingeneral supported the Government.Mr. Bonar Law said lie agreed with Lord Curzoifs suggestion,and thought the Committee should be set going that day in order tomake preparations for the situation which might arise next Thursday,and the Committee should ascertain whether the Navy would beable, if required, to run the electric power stations.Lord iVlilner said he thought that all agreed that the services ofthe Army and the Navy, and especially of the Army, should be usedfor the maintenance of order. They should not, unless the situation was desperate, be used for industrial, operations. If it was possibleto find civilians to operate voluntarily the affected services it wouldbe infinitely preferable, and it should be done.Mr. Churchill said that he thought the Government coulddepend on the loyalty of the Army.   So far as the trustworthiness
Proposed 4. The War  Cabinet   had   under   consideration   MemorandaCommunications prepared by the War Office (Paper G.T.-6449), the AdmiraltyBoard- (Papers G.T.-6538 and 6G80). the Air Ministry (Paper G.T. 6626),the Board of Trade (Paper G.T.-6635), and the Post Office (paper g.T.-6645), relative to a proposed Communications Board.Mr. Illingworth said that matters would be complicated if thecontrol of communications were to be given to any Departmentother than the Post Office, and he thought that the proposed board should be under the control of the Postmaster-(General. In this waythe consideration of all questions m connection with telegraph com-munication would be carried out under one roof. If the Board wereto be under the Committee of Imperial Defence, was it not possiblethat the three fighting Departments would be represented, and thatthe views of the other Government Departments would not carry thesame weight ? The situation as regards wireless telegraphy was atpresent very unsatisfactory.Mr. Chamberlain said that everyone was agreed as to thedesirability of having a Communications Board. Tne Treasury wasnot specially interested, but he thought the proposed Board possiblyought to be under the Post Office.Mr. Bonar Law reminded the Cabinet that three of the Govern-ment Departments had suggested that the Board should be aSub-Committee of tbe Committee of Imperial Defence. If it wasdecided that this should be so, it did not by any means necessarily follow that the views of the Civil Departments would not carry thesame weight as those of the fighting Departments, and he pointedout that on a previous occasion, when a similar question had beenconsidered by a Sub-Committee of tlie Committee of ImperialDefence, all the interested Departments were represented on theCommittee, i.e., the Admiralty, the War Office, the Indian Office,the Post office, the Colonial Office, the Board of Trade, the treasury and the Foreign Office.of the troops was concerned, conditions had improved considerablyduring the last fortnight. Tn dealing with recent disturbances thetroops had shown great steadiness.The War Cabinet decided that- A Committee should be appointed to make the necessary arrangements for dealing with any situation that might arise from industrial unrest both at the present moment andin the future, the Committee to consist of: The Home Secretary (Chairman),The President of the Board of Trade,The Minister of Labour.The Secretary for Scotland,and Representatives ofThe Admiralty andThe War Office.Mr. S. W. Harris, C.B., C.V.O., 1 0      ,    -r-^    i .   -ry Y secretaries.Captain Burgis, JThis Committee should have power to give decisions which did not involve important questions of principle. TheCommittee should devote especial attention to making any arrangements that might be necessary for dealing with the threatened electrical strike on the following Thursday, andshould immediately examine and report to the War Cabinetthe possibility of applying the Act of 1875 to the presentsituation.
Vice-Admiral Fremantle wvas of opinion that a GovernmentDepartment dealing with home affairs was not a suitable department under which to have a Board dealing with world-wide communi-cations. Whatever was done, it was most desirable to have some machinery for co-ordinating the work which was now going on.After some discussion as to the original Admiralty proposal thatcertain members of the Board should be permanent and othersnon-permanent, it was pointed out that there had been some misunderstanding as to the reason for this proposal, and it wasagreed that all Departments represented on the Board should be onexactly the same footing.Mr. Illingworth said that, in these circumstances, he was quite satisfied, and on the whole he thought it would be better to havethe Board free from any special Department, and to have a chairman appointed by the War Cabinet.Mr. Chamberlain said that, although one talked of the Com-mittee of Imperial Defence, it was not very clear how that body was going to be constituted under the new machinery of Government,and in this Lord Milner agreed, and said that the Committee ofImperial Defence was for the time being in abeyance.Mr. Bonar Law said his idea was that, by putting the board under the control of the Committee of Imperial Defence, it wouldbe in a stronger position, in so far as the Prime Minister wasChairman of that Committee.Mr. Churchill supported the Admiralty and War Office views,which were that the Board should be under the control of theCommittee of Imperial Defence, but on general grounds wras aversefrom taking away from Departments their responsibilities. More-over, as pointed out by Lord Milner, the Committee of ImperialDefence was in abeyance for the time being.Lord Milner said that, in any case, a Chairman must beappointed, and if he was to be selected from one of the Govern-rnent Departments he would suggest his being chosen from one ofthe fighting Departments.Mr. Chamberlain suggested that in the Admiralty memorandum the Terms of Reference to the proposed Committee were somewhatwide, and that their discussions should be confined to consideringthe Governments policy as regards wureless telegraphy, submarinecables, and visual signalling. He was in favour of all members ofthe Committee being on an equal footing, and it would be open tothe Committee to appoint a Sub-Committee of experts.The War Cabinet decided that -A Committee of the Cabinet, with. Lord. Milner as Chairman,and with representatives of The Treasury,The Foreign Office,The Admiralty,The War Office,The Air Ministry,The Colonial Office,The India Office,Tne Post Office,The Board of Trade,should be appointed to consider questions of policy asregards overland telegraphy, wireless telegraphy, submarinecables, and visual signalling.
Responsibility forthe Administrationof the civil liabilities Scheme.5. The War Cabinet had before them two Memoranda on thesubject of the Civil Liabilities (Demobilisation) Scheme; the first(G.T.-6740) by the President of the Local Government Board statedthat in the past the Civil Liabilities Scheme had been administered by the Military Service (Civil Liabilities) Department. This Depart-ment was an independent department and was not a branch of theLocal Government Board, although the President of the LocalGovernment Board had hitherto been responsible to Parliament forthe administration of that Department. The new scheme, however,was essentially one of demobilisation, and the hope was expressed that the Minister of Labour, who was responsible to Parliament forthe demobilisation scheme, would be prepared to take over theDepartment. As an additional reason for transferring the Depart-ment to the Ministry of Labour it was observed that the new schemewas closely connected with the question of Officers&apos; Resettlement.The second Memorandum (G.T.-6741) was by the Minister Co-ordinating Demobilisation, expressing agreement in the view thatthe scheme should be under the control of the Ministry of Labourthrough the Director-General of Demobilisation and Resettlement,and asking that the matter should be definitely settled withoutdelay, as the present uncertainty was hampering administration andwas prejudicial to the interests of applicants.Mr. Bonar Law sucrii&apos;ested that the War Cabinet should concur in the above proposal, provided that the Minister of Labour and thePresident of the Local Government Board were in agreement withthe proposals made by the Minister CoAfter a brief discussion the War Cabinet decided : -ordinating Demobilisation.That the question should be referred to themittee for early  settlement.Home Affairs Com-Eetai Business (. ^ ;u. (jahinet had  under consideration a MemorandumLicensing Order,        ,      . . .       . -T , .      .., - ,.iQlg by the Minister ot iNationaJ Service (vi. 1 .-6/ 3/ ) regarding the future administration of the Retail Business Licensing Order under theDefence of the Realm Regulation 8 a a, stating that hitherto theOrder had been adniinisu red  by the  Headquarters and RegionalStaffs of the Ministry of National Service, with the assistance of thepolice and various public bodies.    In view, however, of the cessation of the main functions of the above Ministry and tht^ consequent dis-bandnient of its officials, it was suggested that the administration ofthe Order ought, in the interests of public economy, to be carried outby the existing staff and   machinery of some other GovernmentDepartment.The War Cabinet decided That the question should  be  referred to the   Home  AffairsCommittee.7. The Chief Secretary for Ireland said that he had received that morning the following telegram from the Lord Lieutenant: Situation in Belfast. &quot; Please ask acting Prime Minister if he approves foliowdng :If gas remains stopped in Belfast I propose proceeding thereto-morrow and seeing Strike Committee. If they will come i will personally warn them that municipal works will be taken over by the Government on Thursday morning, and thatconsequences must be on their own heads. If necessary I will then proceed to secure the complete liberty of all citizens. Ipropose also to see picked bodies of working men, whom leadersselect, -urd address them on the situation without argument orpromises. If Government agree I wiU go to Belfast early to-morrow and return at night. In my opinion the time has.[826]-126 DStrike Situation in glasgow andBelfast.
Increased Supply    &apos; 8. With reference to War Cabinet 519, Minute 1, the Chancellorof Beer. of the Exchequer said that the following notice on the subject of thesupply and prices of beer had inadvertently appeared in the pressbefore he had an opportunity of laying it before the War Cabinet: &quot;It is officially announced that the War Cabinet hasdecided to allow an increase of 25 per cent, on the present per-mitted statutory barrelage and an increase of 2 degrees in the permitted average gravitv, to take effect as from the 1st January,1919.&quot; The schedule of retail prices, which will come into force on the 24th February, brings within its scope all gravities on a scale ranging from the rate of 3d. to 8d. a pint for draught beersin public bars. Bottle beers, which have hitherto been un-controlled, will be included, but on a separate scale.&quot;A part of the schedule deals with the prices that may becharged when beer is sold in parts of licensed premises otherthan public bars. 1&quot;The brewing trade should understand that the new scale of prices is sufficiently liberal to leave room for an increase induty if and when the Government may see fit to impose it.This position precludes the adoption of a still lower range of maximum prices, but the new regulations, as a whole, willprovide a larger supply of beer of better average gravity, atiows r prices than those now obtaining in the case of beer of very low gravity, and at the same time will limit the prices ofthe better beers, and more particularly those sold in bottle.&quot;The Chancellor of the Exchequer explained that, as requested by the War Cabinet, a Committee of the Treasury, the Board of customs and Excise, and the Ministry of Food, had agreed upon a schedule of prices. In coming to an agreement the Committee had decided that it was necessary further to increase the taxation onarrived when the law should be vindicated. Government may-think that my position as Viceroy precludes personal inter-ference. If so I am prepared to use force if Government willauthorise.    Situation in Belfast otherwise quiet and orderly.&quot;Mr. Macpherson, proceeding, said that he had taken theopportunity of consulting Mr. Bonar Law before the cabinet meeting as to the action to be taken in regard to this telegram,and that after some discussion Mr. Bonar Law had suggested thefollowing reply : &quot; I have shown your telegram to Mr. Bonar Law, whoafter consultation with his colleagues, is of opinion that it wouldnot be wise, at this stage at least, to take the course suggested.The view he had taken was that with patience there was a fairchance of the situation in Belfast coming right, and this was confirmed by the reports he had seen which have come toCraig.    What news do you get from Hackett-Pain ?&quot;Mr. Macpherson said that, just before the War Cabinet assembled,he had received a telephone message from the Lord LieutenantsPrivate Secretary to the following effect: &quot; All the Lord Lieutenant requires is authority to act in caseof necessity.&quot;The War Cabinet decided To approve the terms of the reply as proposed by Mr. bonar law.
beer in the forthcoming Budget, and they had considered carefullywhether the increase should be 10*. or 11. per standard barrel.They had decided to recommend to the War Cabinet that the taxation should be increased by 10s. per standard barrel, as anincrease of 11. per standard barrel would have the effect of reducingthe quality of the beer to a very low level, and this would cause agreat deal of unrest.The War Cabinet took note of the arrangements made by theChancellor of the Exchequer.(Initialled)      A. B. L.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,February 4, 1919.


</content>
</cab>
