<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/54/1 images: 20-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cc(74) 1stConclusionsCOPY NO79CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street on tuesday 5 MARCH 1974at 5. 00 pm present the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon Edward Short mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon James Callaghan mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Hon Sir Elwyn jones lord chancellor the Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Roy Jenkins mp secretary of State for the Home department the Rt Hon Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for energy the Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon William Ross mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon Frederick Peart mp minister of Agriculture and FisheriesMr Merlyn Rees mp secretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon Barbara Castle mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Anthony Crosland mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Harold Lever mp chancellor of the Duchy of LancasterMrs Shirley Williams mp secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon John Morris mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp secretary of State for Education and science
ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Robert Mellish mp parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat sir John hunt mr J A hamilton mr J An sonCONTENTSItemSubjectPage1MINEWORKERS&apos; PAY DISPUTE12STATE OF EMERGENCY43QUEEN&apos;S SPEECH ON THE OPENING OF PARLIAMENT5ii
MINEWORKERS1PAYDISPUTE1. THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had held discussionsduring the day with the Trades Union Congress (TUC) and with the confederation of British Industry (CBI).    The talk with the TUC hadbeen friendly and encouraging, and while no definitive conclusionshad been reached, the discussion had covered the way in which the mineworkers&apos; pay dispute might be settled and the general economicsituation.    The talk with the CBI had also been useful and constructive.    The Cabinet would wish at this meeting to give priority to two matters: the handling of the mineworkers&apos; dispute.,and the question whether the State of Emergency should be extended or allowed to lapse.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said that he had held discussions earlier in the day with the National Coal Board (NCB)and with the National Ur-ion of Mineworkers (NUM).    The claim bythe NUM would cost about  113 million on basic rates, together withother improvements which could add a further  20 million.    TheNCB were now putting forward fresh proposals worth about 95- 98 million.    There was some difference of view betweenthe NCB and the NUM on the shape of the settlement;  and therewas also a dispute as to whether some of the settlement shouldbe backdated to November 1973.    The relativities report by the pay Board, of which a summary had been placed before the Cabinet,proposed that the offer previously made by the NCB under Stage 3 ofthe Conservative Governments policy should be increased to a totalof around  98- 101 million.    The report proposed that someunderground workers should be given increases which were even higher than the NUM had claimed, but that surface workers shouldreceive less than their claim.    It also proposed that a distinction should be made between those surface workers who had previouslyworked underground and those that had not.    The NCB and the NUMhad been shown the Pay Board&apos;s report, which would be published thefollowing day.    The NUM had not yet reacted to it, but were anywaylikely to expect to get more than the Pay Board had recommended.He had told both sides that his talks with them were exploratory andwithout commitment.    He had informed them that the Stage 3 limithad been lifted, and had urged them to open negotiations with the aim off reaching an early settlement.    He had suggested that the NUMshould concentrate on basic rates and not insist on additional benefitsat this stage: these should be left for the further discussions whichthe NCB wished to hold with them before the NUM annual conference.The Cabinet would now wish to consider what guidance might begiven to the NCB.    In the first instance, it would be possible tosuggest that they should negotiate at around the level of the mfferwhich they were now proposing.    It would however probably benecessary eventually to go further than that in order to reach a final settlement.
In discussion, it was argued that although the TUC had undertakennot to quote the mineworkers&apos; settlement in other disputes, the surface workers were doing almost identical work to that performedin other industries;  and it had become clear in the talk with the tuc earlier that day that some trades unions would find it difficultto abstain from seeking higher increases if the surface workersreceived more than could be objectively justified.    The report bythe Pay Board was however unlikely to be helpful in bringing abouta satisfactory settlement.    The mistake had been made in theearlier negotiations of making a detailed offer which left no furtherroom for possible adjustment of differentials.    The danger now wasthat the NUM would seek to take all that the Pay Board had proposed for underground workers, but would still seek to improve on the pay Board proposals for surface workers.    The distinction whichthe Pay Board proposed to make between different categories of surface workers, although logically defensible, was also unlikely to be acceptable.    Moreover, if the mineworkers&apos; claim was settled on the basis of a relativities report, other trade unions would be under pressure from their members to seek a similarenquiry, with very serious consequences.    It would be desirabletherefore to make clear at the outset that in allowing the Pay Boardreport to be published the Government had not approved it as a basis for negotiation;  and indeed that they disagreed with the whole concept of settling wage claims by the relativities procedure.In further discussion it was argued that a settlement of the dispute should aim to achieve peace in the industry for at least two years.In order to avoid a further large claim being endorsed by the NUMannual conference in July, it might be necessary to concedevirtually all of the  113 million which the NUM were now asking onbasic rates.    It would also be necessary to satisfy the surface workers, who had been drawn unwillingly into strike action, andwould not now be prepared to see a settlement which was strongly in favour of the underground workers.    It might however be unwise to fix a firm limit within which the NCB could negotiate, since theymight concede this too soon, with the risk that the Government wouldthen have to move from their original figure to get a final settlement.It would be preferable to suggest to the NCB, without specifying a precise figure, that they should negotiate at around the level of theoffer which they were now proposing.    It could be pointed out to the mineworkers that this would more than double the increases in basic rates proposed in the earlier Stage 3 offer.    In the light ofthe negotiations, it would then be possible to decide how much moreneeded to be conceded in order to achieve a final settlement.    Asregards the other issues, such as pensions and health, the aim should be to try to exclude these from the present settlement, sothat they could be considered by the proposed Commission on thecoal industry.2
THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the Pay Board&apos;s relativities report should notbe used as a basis for negotiation, and the Government shouldreject the principle of the relativities procedure.    The NCBshould be invited to negotiate with the NUM at around the level ofthe offer which they were now proposing, with the aim of reaching an early settlement.    The Cabinet recognised that it might benecessary in the light of these negotiations to authorise the board to go further in order to reach a settlement.    On additional benefits such as health and pensions the objective should be to exclude these from the present settlement and take them up in subsequent discussions on the structure of the industry.The Cabinet - -Invited the Secretary of State for Employment,in consultation with the Secretary of State forEnergy, to give guidance to the National coal board on the lines indicated in the summing upof their discussion by the Prime Minister.
STATE OF 2. THE HOME SECRETARY said that the State of Emergency,EMERGENCY and the Emergency Regulations which had been made under it,would lapse at midnight on Wednesday 6 March.    A Privy council had been provisionally arranged for 6 March in case it wasdecided to renew the State of Emergency for a further period.    Ifit was renewed, Affirmative Resolutions would be needed not later than 13 March if the Regulations were not to lapse on that date.The restrictions on the use of electricity and oil were made underseparate powers, and there was therefore no inherent reason tocontinue the State of Emergency.    It was however for consideration whether it would be wise to declare the emergency over before themineworkers1 dispute had been settled.    It might be argued that itwas not yet possible to say what further powers might be needed,and that a termination of the State of Emergency might make it moredifficult to retain the voluntary co-operation of the public.    these arguments were however contingent and psychological, and it mightbe preferable to allow the State of Emergency to lapseaAlternatively, it would be possible to renew the State of Emergencyon 6 March, and then not ask Parliament to approve the necessaryResolutions,In discussion, it was argued that, with the exception of a Regulationconcerning drivers&apos; hours, the present restrictions were imposedunder other powers;  and the State of Emergency could thereforebe allowed to lapse.    Any action that might be needed subsequently,such as the possible allocation of steel supplies, could probably beachieved by other means.    A decision by the Government to renew the State of Emergency could attract unfavourable attention in thePress, and unless it was revoked before Parliament met, it would need to be mentioned in The Queen&apos;s Speech and debated.    On theother hand, the Cabinet had not yet had an opportunity to study theeconomic situation, and could not therefore form a judgment on themeasures that might be needed.    The general feeling among thepublic was that an emergency situation still existed, and it mightbe regarded as no more than common prudence to maintain theState of Emergency until a settlement of the mineworker s&apos; disputehad actually been achieved.    If the dispute had been settled by theend of the week, a further announcement could be made that theGovernment would not be asking Parliament to approve the necessaryResolutions.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the State of Emergency should be renewed atthe meeting of the Privy Council arranged for the following day.If the mineworkersT dispute had been settled before Parliamentneeded to approve the Affirmative Resolutions, the Regulationscould then be allowed to lapse.
The Cabinet -Invited the Home Secretary, in consultationwith the Lord President, to arrange for theState of Emergency to be extended at the meetingof the Privy Council arranged for 6 March.QUEEN!S SPEECH 3. The Cabinet considered the arrangements for preparingON THE The Queen&apos;s Speech on the Opening of Parliament.OPENING OFPARLIAMENT        In discussion it was argued that there might be advantage inpostponing The Queen&apos;s Speech in order to give more time for its consideration by the Cabinet.    While a postponement of a full weekmight give rise to adverse criticism, a delay of two days could bejustified on the grounds that the Government had not been able totake office immediately after the Election.    Any such delay would however leave less time for essential business and Supply Days,and could therefore have the effect of curtailing the Easter Recess,THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that ministers who wished to put forward proposals for inclusion inThe Queen&apos;s Speech should transmit them to the Lord Presidentby 3.00 pm on Wednesday 6 March,    It would be necessary to concentrate on measures which were essential or of high priority,such as increases in pensions and the repeal of the industrial relations Act.    In the light of these proposals, a ministerial committee would consider drafts of The Queen !s Speech, whichcould then be considered by the Cabinet later in the week.    the speech should in general give broad indications of policy intentionrather than a detailed description of individual measures.    It shouldbe based on the assumption of a Session lasting about a year.    Thiswould leave the Government free to decide whether to terminate the session in the autumn or to allow it to continue for a further period.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the summing upof their discussion by the Prime Minister,Cabinet Office6 March 19745


</content>
</cab>
