<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/25/0 images: 42-43</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document j3jJ2^^ P ^^L, His Britannic Majesty^ CovemmenJ:.)31.8.17* Handed in 4,30 a,m.From:-   General Delme Radcliffe, Italy. To:-       C.I.G.S., War Office.*358. August 30th.Situation this evening 10 p.m.The -weather is now fine although there was heavy rain last night and this morning.     There is little of special importance to report with regard to to-day&apos;s operat-ions .2nd Army.     The preparations for the resumption of&quot; the offen-sive continue and are likely to last some days more.       The attack made yesterday on St. Gabriele was not a success.   The Austrians have strongly counter-attacked and have succeeded in taking a small element of trench on the Veliki Krib shoulder. A little progress has been made by the Italian troops towards the saddle between St. Gabriele and St. Daniele.   The attack on St. Marco ?jas also disappointing but the Italian troops succeeded in holding and consolidating point 193.     The Italian losses on St. Gabriele and near St. Marco have been considerable and until Italian heavy artillery is in position on the Bainsizza plateau and adequate artillery preparations can be made, further attacks will be postponed.     Austrian heavy artillery is now in positions behind Kwbilca Ternova Schonpass line only field artillery and Mountain artillery remaining in front of that line except about St. Marco and south of it in the valley where many heavy batteries still remain.During
29During the day total prisoners 16 officers 408rank and file including 106 taken from the 6th Battalion 4th Bosnian-Herzogovina Regiment on the Lorn plateau;       Contact obtained with the 1st Battalion of the 63rd Infantry Regiment just arrived from Sugana valley in the Trentino and with 1 battalion of the 57th Regiment of the 12th Division on the Volnik, This Regiment was formerly part of 1st and not of the 182nd Mountain Brigade of the 17th Division.Departure is reported of the 33rd Hungarian Landsturm of the 71st Division in Roumania, believed to be for another front but direction unknown;   also of the 26th Schutzen brigade from the Trentino.3rd Army.   Except artillery practically no fighting today. About 100 prisoners taken.   Arrival reported of a new Hungarian and Roumanian division.       It is stated to be composed of March Battalions and the men all have new uniforms and equipment-. It is suggested that it is not formed of March Battalions but is 7th Division, since the middle of July at Kaliscz and last heard of on the Russian fronts     This Division now near Novelo 2 kilometres east of Castagnevizza.        Prisoners giving this information belong to 10th Division and left Carso on August 13th for Laibach whence they returned on August 19th.Austrian divisions in front line now are the 44th,17th,48th,9th 10th and 28th with the 41st,35th and 12th in reserve.   Italian 3rd Army has 2 Divisions at present in front line of each of the 4 Corps on the Carso.

</content>
</cab>
