<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/25/0 images: 83-90</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I. II.MEMOSAlIDUlvionIntelligence BureauDepartment of Information 82, Victoria StreetAugust 30. 1917Herr Michaelis1 &quot;Free Committee7&apos; Scheme.Proposals for making Alsace-Lorraine one of the Federated States of the Empire.I.Herr Michaelis has been to General Headquarters and has returnedwith a &quot;solution&quot; of the parliamentary deadlock which he communicatedto the Main Reichstag Committee on Saturday.     It is the solution whichhas been repeatedly hinted at since the Bethmann-Eollweg crisis.   Anew body is to be created, a &quot;Free Committee&quot;, consisting of 7 membersof the federal Council and 7 members of the Reichstag under the presi-deney of tho Chancellor.     The object is to obtain a closer contactbetween the Government and the political parties in the discussionand shaping of important current questions without sacrificing theconfidential character of such discussions.     Herr Michaolis explainedwhat is meant by this &quot;IPree Committee&quot;.    JJe said:&quot;What I meant is that it is out of the question that in every single instance Government or party representatives should join the Committoe w^.th instructions or should ice-port to their party after a council has been held, which are still in course of development and may undergo alterations and are not ripe for public discussion we nay and will discuss confidentially, and finally attain a so-lution which can then be made public.&quot;2.       The list of loaders of parties who are to belong to the FreeCommittee is published.     It includes Fehrenbaeh and Erzberger, (&quot;(Catholic Centre), Ebert and Scheidemann (Socialist Majority), Strese-mann for the National Liberals, Payer for the Radicals and Count
-   -vfestarp for the Conservatives.     Tho Representatives of the FederalCouncil will ho, first, Count Lerchenfeld for Bavaria, Herr von Mostiz-Drzewioeki for Saxony and Baron von Varnbttler for Vfarttemborg,     These Federal Councillors are the Ministers Plenipotentiary in Borlin for their several states and their seat on the Free Committee will be permanont. Iho other four Federal Council seats on the Committee will be divided between Mecklenburg and Baden;   Kesse and Oldenburg;   tho Thuringian States, Brunswick and Anhalt;   the Hanseatic Cities and Alsace-Lorraine. The States in each of these groups will in turn supply a delegate to the Committee.     The Chancellor had consulted the leaders of parties beforehand, so that when ho produced his scheme its adoption, although preceded by a long discussion, was a foregone conclusion. 3,    Tho only thorough-going denunciation of the scheme came from the Minority Socialists.     One of them - probably Eaa3e - said that the rights of the Reichstag would bo impaired by the new Committee and that he and his friends &quot;would have nothing to do with such political hocus-pocus,&quot;    The Minority Socialist Ledebour said that &quot;the new Conmittoe concerning whose powers no one knew anything, was a 7/hisked-up expedient and would damage the dignity of the Reichstag,&quot;    A fu&apos;il meeting of the Reichstag ought to have been called to decide the matter.     &quot;Members of the new Committee would be nothing but an appendage of the bureaucracy.&quot; Indeed one object of the scheme seems to bo to lessen the Governments responsibility and to fetter the freedom of the political parties.     Herr ^edebourS criticism touches the real kernel of tho matter.    Eerr 111-chaelis is unable at present to go further in the direction of &quot;par-liamentary government.&quot;    His speech is reported to have been largely an apology for postponing democratic reform during the war, and it was riticiscd in this aspect by various speakers.     The new 3/ree Committee, ^ said, was an attempt to proceed by way of gradual development.   But, &amp;s Herr Ledebour replied, it is development in the wrong direction from
Cie democratic point of view.     The old bureaucratic element has been fully maintained in the new ministerial appointments in Prussia and in the new appointments to the -citate .&apos;..ecretaryships in the &quot;jnpire. 4.       Supreme political power in the Empire nominally resides in the Federal Council, representing tlio separate German states.     In order to be a member of the &quot;Government of the Empire&quot; (Reichsregierung) it *ts necessary to be a member of the Federal Council.     If real parliament-ary Government is to be established in the Empire, this prohibition must be abolished so as to olear the way for the appointment of Secretaries of State who would be at once members of the Reichstag and of the Federal Council.    These Secretaries of State must, in the view of democratic reformers, ultimately attain the character of Ministers, whereas at present they have no real ministerial existence but are merely in the words of the constitution &quot;representatives of the Imperial Chancellor&quot; who is the sole Minister of the Empire,The status and character of the Federal Council itBelf would also have to bo changed.    The German Imperial Constitution was partly modelled on those of Switzerland and the United States of America.     But, instead of an elected Upper House, representative of the Separate States, de-liborating in public and publicly ratifying, revising or rejecting measures passed by the popular Chamber, Bismarck gave Germany a Council which is nominated by the different German Governments, ranging from autocracy in Mecklenburg to republics (of a sort) in Hamburg, Bremen and Mibeck.   The Federal Council initiates, revises and rejects legislation which comes before the popular Assembly (The Reichstag), but it does so in secret session like a Cabinet.     It is a sort of Cabinet, but it is moreover a diplomatic as well as a secret legislative body, the head of (;aoh State delegation in it being the diplomatic Plenipotentiary of that State at the Prussian Court.     Each delegation is therefore responsible only to the Government that appoints it, and it acts upon the instructions
of that Government.     Moreover the Federal Council embodies the pre-dominance of Prussia by virtue of the position of the Imperial Chancellor, its President and leader, who is at the same time Prussian Prime Minister, and also by virtue of tho veto (14 votes required) which Prussia with her 17 votes can always exercise against any ohange in the Constitution. The votos of each State are  ivon ia a lump according to instructions reoeived from the Government of that State.     The character and functions of the Federal Council thus in practice dpiite nullify the domocratic element in the Constitution v/hich at first sight seems to be provided by a Reichstag elocted by universal, direct, equal and secret suffrage. And on the top of all this thero aro the prerogatives of the Emperor, exercised directly or through his nominee, the Imperial Chancellor, who i3 douVly under his direction, first as Imperial Chancellor appointed and dismissed at the Imperial will, and secondly, as Prussian Prime Minister, i.o. tho servant of a Monarchy which is still in all essentials autocratic.    And the prerogatives of the Emperor including the declara-tion of war fin case of attack upon Germany - a situation easily con-structed as being actual or imminent, as at tho outbreak of tho prosont war) are constantly strained in word and deed.^Only the Conservatives appear to have received the new scheme with real satisfaction;   they regard it as an expedient to ward &amp;ff par-liamontary government.     A National liberal Deputy welcomed the proposed Council but deprecated any delay in constitutional reforms.     The Chan-oellor has given fresh assurances that the democratic reform of the Prussian franchise will not be delayed.1. The Chancellortis further repcrtod to have brought back fromhis conieronce with the Emperor at General Headquarters tho Imperial assent to the elevation of Alsace-Lorraine to the full position of a Federal State. -   The Alsace-Lorraine Constitution of 1911 was a step inII.
this direction..     It replaced the former very unrepreseiitatiTe-Pr^rTin-elal Assembly or Committee (Landesausschuss) by a Diet consisting of-&apos;U*JO houses, the Upper one partly elected by &quot;fancy&quot; franchises partly nom-inated by the Emperor, the Lower elected by universal secret, equal ana direct suffrage.    But it fell short of giving the country full. Federal v status in that:-(l)   Tho Emperor, without the assent of the Federal Council ofthe Empire, appoints the Statthalter and reoalls him. (S) The Emperor!s assent to all legislation is necessary. (3)   The Emperor appoints half the members of the Upper Chamberof the legislature. (4)  ,Alsace-IiOrraine has three votes in the Federal Council but the Statthalter, the organ of the Emperor, instructs the delegates how they are to vote. Per contra, the three votes of Alsace-Lorraine do not count, v/hen a Prussian proposal in the Federal Council which would otherwise-command only a minority would obtain a majority by their aid.     This provision was adopted out of consideration for the other German States, in order to prevent Prussia from gaining, through the Statthalterls instructions, an increase of three votes in the*Federal Council, 2. A Munich telegram to the Weser Zeitung says that the transfor-mation of the Eeichsland (Alsace-Lorraine) into a Duchy is contemplated. The Duchy was first offered to a Bavarian Prince^who refused it, and it is now reported that a member af the Catholic Ducal House of Uraoh (descendants of Duke William *f Wttrttemberg, 1761-1830) will be appoint-ed.     If this were true, (the truth of it has been questioned) it would indicate that the policy of the German Government is to clear Itself of the charge of &quot;Prussian!sin&quot; in the administration of the conquered provinces, where at present the imported officials are Prussian, and, further, to weld Alsace-Lorraine to the Empire by making it one of the
German states with an hereditary monarchy of its own.     It is clear that  ll3ace-Lorraino as an autonomous Federal State must be either a monarchy or a republic. -----5. Before the war many of the leaders of opinion in Alsace-Lorrainewere looking forward to a long period of peace and had abandoned the hope of the forcible recovery of the provinces by France.     They, therefore, outortainsd favourably the schemes for giving Alsace-Lorraine complete autonomy and the full position of a Federated State within the German Empire.     The Constitution of 1911 granted by tho Reichstag and the Im-.perial Government, as they urged, did not go far enough.     As a German state Alsace-Lorraine would have her own administration conducted by officials appointed by her own Government and taken from among her own people.     Through her full membership cf the Federal Council at Berlin she would, like Saxony, Bavaria, ^urttemberg etc., have a voico in tho management of the Smpire.     The Federal Council and the Reichstag never pass laws of a repressive character applying to one particular State. Indeed the existing Constitution of the Empire practically precludes such special legislation, for it provides (in Act 7) that &quot;whore a voteof the Federal Council is taken on a matter which.......... does notconcern the T-lmpiro as a whole, only tho votes of those States which the matter jointly concerns are to be counted;&quot;It is maintained that since the outbreak of war the* great ma-jority of Alsatians and Lorrainers would no longer be satisfied with any measure of autonomy, and that they demand reunion with Franco e     Thus Blumenthal, the Alsatian liberal Deputy, was be-ore the war an advocate of autonomy as being the best thing that could then be hoped for, but *n the outbreak of war ho fled to Paris, where he advocatos the complete restitution of the two provinces to France./4o In no French or German quarter is a plebiscite advocated.     The
-armans do not admit that an Alsace-Lorraine question exists.     TheTench point out:- .(a) That.while the provinces renain under German administration, no guarantee for tho fairness of a vote could ho obtained, while there is no neutral that is powerful and impartial enough to undertake the control of the voting,(b) That the 500,000 or 600,000 Germans who have settled in Alsace-Lorraine since 1871, (the immigrfes) and their descendants, would form an olement which would falsify the result.     (The total population of Alsace-Lorraine according to the last con-sus is about 1,900,000).(c) That those who left Alsace-Lorraine and &quot;opted&quot; for France be-tween 1071 and 1073 variously estimated from 150,000 (German estimate) and 260,000 (extreme French estimate) and thoir descendants now living in Franco as well as the Alsace-Lorrainers who are now serving with the French colours ought to have a voice in the decision, although it would be difficult to muster them for a popular vote even if the Germans agreed to their voting - which the Germans never would do.(d) That the question was decided once for all by the attitude of the population at the time when the annexation by violence was effected and by their protest through their Deputies, headed by Gambetta, at the French Xfetional Assembly at Bordeaux in 1071.5. The Germans allege that the Bordeaux Assembly was only tooglad to get the Peace of Frankfort (accepted by 546 votes to 147) and that the majority gave the cold shoulder to the Deputies from Alsace-Lorraine.    They further assert that the popular Chamber in Alsace-Lorraine has since the beginning of the War maintained a patriotic attitude in the German sense.     Eo doubt the Presidents of the two
- o -Chambers recently (last June) delivered patriotic German addressesj but, according to a Swiss paper, the Journal de Geneve, there were demonstrations against them.     It is true that the French Nationalist party, as such, in Alsace-Lorraine was completely defeated at the first and only election for the new popular Chamber in 1911.     The figures were Catholic Centre 24, liberal Democrats 9, Social Democrats 11, &quot;Lorraine Bloc11 10, Independents 6.     But, as was pointed out on page, many members of the Catholic Centre are really francophil, while the Liberals and the Social Democrats and most of the others have strong &quot;particularism $Tendencies, that is to say they want completeutonomy as the next best thing to complete independence, which wouldmp^y liberty to settle the question of the nationality of the pro-inces.G.S.

</content>
</cab>
