<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/25/0 images: 251-266</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Il(This Document is theHis Britannic Malesty&apos;s Government).1855. T. 1925.WAR CAB1MTTHEDEVELOPMENT 05? THE MILITARY PLANS OF THE ALLIES IN f3E PRINCIPAL THEATRES OF WAR DURING1917.Mil(Memorandum by the Secretary).1.    Although-the plan now in operation for an attack inFlanders dated from the decision of the late War. Committeexon November  1st, referred to by General Robertson in theMinutes of August 28th (War Cabinet 225a), the plans fav-rthe Allied offensive as actually carried out in the firsthalf of 1917 originated at a Conference of the Allied Commandsheld at Chantilly on November loth 1916.     Ihe proces-verbalof this Conference was read by Marshal Joffre to a Conferenceof representatives of the British, French, Italian, andRussian Governments On the following- day.   This proces-verbalrecords approval of the plan of action as defined in aMemorandum submitted to the Chantilly Conference, a plan havingthe object of giving to the campaigns of 1917 a decisive x xcharacter.    The Memorandum containing the plan was not read to-the political Conference and so far as I can ascertain from the records of the War Committee and War Cabinet was   * not, communicated to the BritishGove naoent.This decision does not appear in :the Minutes of the War Committee but is recorded in a letter sent b;v the Prime Minister (Mr, Asquith) to the Chief of the Imperial General Staff from which the following extract is taken: -&quot;There is no operation of war to which the far Committee would attach greater importance than the ^successful occupation, or at least tne deprivation to-&apos; the enem  of Ostend and specially 2eebrugge&quot;.x x&apos;les Conferents donnent leur approbation au plan aTaetioh de la Coalition, jbel- a&apos; ete definidans le memorandum gu1!!. leur a ete soumis plan ayant pour but de donher aux campagnes de 1917 un caractere decisif&quot;.
Government.      The proces-verbal provided that the Armies of the. coalition were to be ready to undertake their offensive simultaneously any time after the first fortnight in February, but the precise dates were to be fixed by agreement between the Commanders-in-Chief.    The proees-iverbal of the Chantilly Conference was provisionallyapproved, by-the political Conference ad referendum to thefour Governments concerned and without prejudice to thexresults of a Conference to be held in Russia. 2.      On December 9th the present British Government was formed and the War Cabinet replaced the War Committee. On December 13th Marshal -Joffre was superseded by General Mvelle, who, as he explained at a subsequent Conference,jettisoned Marshal Joffre&apos;s plans.   The first step required.. newfor the development, of General. 11 rvelle &apos;.s/plans was the extension of the British line in order to releaseFrench divisions, and. at a Conference held in London from/December 26-20 M. Ribot pressed, this on the British Government. The proposal -was received with complete sympathy by the British War Cabinet, but before a final decision was reached as to exactly hoy; far- the British line could be extended, the British ^ar Cabinet felt that the Commander-i-n-rChief of the British -Expeditionary Force must be consulted&quot; (1.0,-13 (1) ano War Cabinet 19 (l) ;)..   The Question was left for arrangement between Generals (afterwards Field l&amp;rshal) Sir Douglas Eaig and Mvelle., and it was decided that, if an arrangement satisfactory to :the French Government was not reached in the. immediate future by the two. Generals, the question should be raised again by the French Government..xThe main provisions of the Chantilly Conference were,practically:.reaffirmed at the Ru3Sian Conference,
On January 5th a Conference was opened at Rome. The Prime Minister circulated a Memorandum reviewing the whole situation, in which, inter alia, he drew attention to the danger of an attack by the enemy, and the potentialities for an attack by the Allies on the Italian front, and asked that these questions should be considered by the Governments and General Staffs of the Allies represented at the Conference(G - 106). After considerable discussion the following conclusion was recorded:-

"The Conference are impressed with the opportunities afforded by the Italian front for a combined offensive by the three Western Allies. They agree that the question of assistance being given by the Western Allies to the Italian army on the Carso? should be referred to the Military Advisers of the various Governments, with a view to a dicision by the three Governments concerned".(I.C.-15, Minute 7).

In his verbal report on the Conference, made to War Cabinet on January 10th. the Prime Hinistor made the following statement:-

"With regard to the proposal for an offensive by the Western Powers on the Italian Front, General Caderna had indicated that, if an advance were made, it would be through Laibach towards Vienna, and not in the direction of Pola. The Conference agreed that General Caderna should prepare plans and submit them to the Military Advisers of the other Allies. The next step was with him. There was no bargain as to our lending British guns for the Italian front. The whole question of Allied support to the Italians was left subject to General Caderna&apos;s producing a definite proposal which met with their favour. The Prime Minister mentioned that the French evidently had a poor opinion of the fighting value of the Italian troops". (War Cabinet 31. Minute 5. and Appendix 1.)

4. The next step in the development of the plans was the visit of General Nivelle to London to confer with the War Cabinet on January 15th. Field Marshal Sir Douglas Haig and General Nivelle had failed to reach an agreement as to the amount of line to be taken over by the British.


forces and as to the date of the offensive and for this reason General Nivelle was sent over by the French Government to discuss the question with the War Cabinet. He was not accompanied by any member of the French Government and the discussion was recorded as a War Cabinet Meeting and not as an Inter-Allied Conference. (War Cabinet 34 &amp; 35). 

5. This Meeting occupied the greater part of two whole days. The Secretary&apos;s notes of the Meetings, which cover some 40 pages of feelscap, show that the discussion centered largely on the question of taking over the line, but that a great deal of attention was given also to the nature of the offensive, and particularly to the ? of dates. General Nivelle and M. Camben, speaking with the authority of the French Government, pressed very strongly for an early date- February 15th was mentioned, though under pressure General Nivelle admitted that it was scarcely possible to be ready so soon-while Field Marshal Haig and General Robertson favoured a later date in April or May, in order to secure a better prospect of fine weather, to give time for fuller preparations and the Transport to France of further reinforcements from England, and to enable the Russians and Italians to strike in co-operation. The actual plan of operations is not mentioned in the Secretary&apos;s notes General Nivelle did not describe it to the War Cabinet, but Sir Douglas Haig communicatod it privately to the Prime Minister, who described it on a map to the War Cabinet, while they were deliberating among themselves on General Nivelle&apos;s proposals. A description of the plan is also contained in a letter addressed by General Nivelle to Sir Douglas Haig on December 21st, which was circulated to the War Cabinet later, and it corresponds approximately to the plan
plan actually attempted in April.6.     &quot;Eventually the question was remitted to Generals Mvelle, Robertson, and Field Marshal Eaig, W&amp;S arrived at an agreement among themselves, which received theapproval of., the War Cabinet (IVar Cabinet 35).   This agreement provided for - the taking over of an agreedportion of the French line by the first week in March;   an offensive not later than April 1st and earlier if possible, or, &quot;if the general situation necessitates it, conformably to the decisions taken at the Conference of Chantilly, the 15th November 1916&quot; (viz., any time after February 15th); the offensive to give effect, to a plan agreed on January 15th between Pield Marshal Eaig, and General iJivollo;    the e:-:ploitation of successes on the three points of attack to be pursued with all the vigour necessary,to obtain a decisive result, engaging, if necessary, all the disposable forces of the British and French Armies;    &quot;in case tho operations should not give tho expected success, which ought to be obtained very rapid^ly, the battle would be stopped by a common agreement in oi-cler to permit the British Armies to engage in other operations on a front further to tho north in co-operation with the Belgian Army and tho French forces at lieuport&quot;.   The agreement mentions that those dispositions which&apos; conformed to the directions given by the French &apos;7ar Committee to General Uivelle had been approved by the British &quot;/ar Cpmmittee (sic), and it provided also for modifications in the event of an enemy offensive.   The agreement was signed by General Kivelle, General Robertson, and j?icld Marshal Haig and by no one else.7.     -No specific mention of the possibility of a combined attack on the Italian front is to be found in the Secretary&apos;s
notes of.those meetings..    One of the arguments used by the British Military representatives in favour of a postponement of the offensive until May was to provide for a simultunoous offensive by tho Italians as well as by tho Russian Army; and cue cf tho reasons given by the Prime Kinistor for an earlier offensive was that &quot;there would be still time to make other plans if General iJivolloTs plans did not accomplish all that he hoped from itf!     It is also perhaps worth mentioning that General Hivelie, when pressed in tho oourso of tho discussion as to the effect oil his plans of a Gorman attack on the Italian front expressed doubt whether it would bo advisable to send troops to Italy, and preferred to precipitate his own offensive.8.      It is fairly clear that the Prime minister still had a thought for tho Italian offensive, but that both the British and French Generals, who had as yet received nt* word from General Cadorna, had their minds fixed mainly on the Western front, and wero net contemplating any joint offensive on thy Italian front09*       General Cadorna^s plan was received about -January 25. Ho copy was received at or circulated fro:.: the Offices of the War Cabineto     I have a personal noto that- I was shown a copy in tho original Italian by the Prime Minister at 10 Downing Street on January 23.     iiy recollection as to what occurred coincides with romarks on the subject of tho Chief of the Imperial General Staff at the War Cabinet on August 23. (War Cabinet 225a).     The War Cabinet, having agreed to General Hivollo^ plan only a weak before, the Prime Minister folt that thuy were committed in regard to the Spring offonsive and that, for.-tho moment, this put General Cadornafs proposals out of courts
10.    - On P0bruaiy---S6th--ancL..2Tth.. aQl^--a-Xtmfererico - was held at Calais, which was attended by the Prime Minister, General-Roberts-on and Field Marshal Haig on behalf of the British Government&apos;, and by M.Briand General Liautey, Minister of War, and General Mvelle on behalf of the French Government (l.C.17 -17(a) and 17(b).   General Nivelle then described his. plans at great length with the aid of maps, but by agreement, no notes were reproduced of these . plans.     Speaking from memory I have no doubt whatsoever that they were substantially the - same as those agreed to -between the British and French higher commands on January Ifeth, The conf erenoe also discussed the^jra4-ltfays and&apos; the rules which v/ere to govern the relations between Field Marshal Haig and General ITivelleduring the perid&amp;of the attack.11.        The agreement reached is worth reproducing in full:-rt&apos;Agreement signed at Anglo-French Conference held at Calais, February 26 and 27 1917.1.     The French War Committee and the British War Cabinetapprove of the plans of operations on the Western Front as explained to them by General Nivelle -and Field Marshal Sir Douglas Kaig on the 26th February 1917.2.     With the object of ensuring complete unity of command during the forthcoming military operations referred to above,the French War Committee and the British War Cabinet have agreed to the following arrangements:-(1)      Whoreas the primary object of the forthcoming military operations referred to in paragraph 1 is to drive the enemy from the French soil,and whereas the French Army disposes of larger effectives than the British, the British War Cabinet recognises that the general direction of the campaign   should bo in the hands of tho French Commander-in-Chief,(2)      With this object in view, the British War Cabinet engages itself to direct the Field Marshal Commanding the British Expeditionary Force to conform his plans of operations to the general strategical plans of the Commander-in-Chief of the French Army.
(3)   The British War Cabinet further engages itself to direct that dUring the period intervening &quot;between the date of the signature of this agree-inent, and the dato of the commencement of the operations, referred to in paragraph i, tho field Marshal Commanding the British Expeditionary-Force shall conform his preparations to the views of the Commander-in-Chief of the French Army, except in so far as he considers that this would endanger the safety of his Army,or prejudice its success, and, i$ any case where Field Marshal Sir Douglas Kaig may feol hound on these grounds to depart from General Hivelle&apos;s instructions, he shall report the action taken, together with the reasons for such action^ to the Chief of tho Imperial General Staff for the information of the British War Cabinet.(4)   The British War Cabinet further engages itself to instruct the Field Marshal Commanding the British Expeditionary Force that, after the date of tho commencement of the forthcoming operations, he shall conform to. the orders of the Commanding--in-Chief of the French Army in all matters relating to theconduct of the operations, it being understood that the British Commander will bo left free to chobse the means he vail employ and the methods .of utilising his troops in that sector of operations allotsd to him by the French Cojomand -er-in-chief in the original plan.       ;(5)   The British War Cabinet and Government and the- French Government)each so far as concerns its own Army, will be the judge of the date at which the operations referred to in paragraph 1 are to be considered as at an end.   When so endedh the arrangement in force before the commencement of tte operations will be re-established.(Signed) K.Briand. (Signed) lyautey. (Signed) RR, Nivelle.(Signed) (Signed) (Signed)Lloyd George.W.R.Robertson,CI,G.S.D.Haig, F.M.Calais, February 27th,1917.12, ITo trace is to be found in the notes .of the Conferenceof any mention cf the possibility of operations on the Italian Front. &apos;
5.   On Harch-lst-5.ignor&quot;3is-soiati,... a member of tiiCItalian Cabinet,c-companied by Prince. Teano,, attended a meeting of the War Cabinet.   Kisemarks were mainly directed towards an explanation, of the apprehensionsf the Italian Government of an attack by the enemy on the Italian front,,.ut he also raised the question of an offensive by the Allies on thatront *   The Cabinet, minute records that -&quot;The military aspects of this question were left for discussion between the Chief of the Imperial General Staff and General Cadorn:.,, but it was recognised that no decision relating to action would be taken without Conference between the three Governments concerned&quot; (War Cabinet 63, Minute 6).-,4.   On March 12 and 13 another Conference of the British and Frenchrovernments and their Military Advisers was held in London (I.C - 18,\ 18 (a) ).     The main subjects of discussion were the relations be-ween Field Marshal Haig and General Ifivelle during the offensive, andthe duties of the Eritish Mission at French General Headquarters, andan agreement was reached between the two Commanders-in-Chief as to theapplication of the Calais Convention of the 27th February.   The notesof the meeting record that, in the course of the discussion GeneralRobertson mentioned that he himself, Field Marshal Haig, and Generaliuvelle were in full agreement about the plan of operations (I .C.18 (a)p Z)15,   During March a good many representations were received from theItalian Government as to their apprehensions of an enemy attack on theirfront, and eventually the Chief of the Imperial General Staff paid avisit to General Cadorna.     General Robertson^ report (G.T. 309) doesnot mention any discussion, between General Cadorna and himself as tothe possibilities of a combined offensive on the Italian front, althoughit contains many references to the possibilities of a purely Italianoffensive, particularly on the Trentino front, which General Robertsonconsidered more favourable than the Carso.   On the very eve   of theAnglo-French offensive it is clear.that no definite plans could haveteen formed for joint operations on the Italian front,   General,.Robertson, reported.../
however, that transport and supply arrangements for the despatch of troops from the West front to Italy had been worked out and that General Cadorna was satisfied in this respect:16.   After reading the report of the Chief of the Imperial General Staff and hearing his views the War Cabinet decided on March 30th to offer the Italian Government the loan of ten batteries of 6 inch howitzers with their personnel (War Cabinet 109, Minute 5 (a).) This offer was accepted and in due course the howitzers were sent out arriving in time to be used in General Cadorna1s May offensive. 17.     The Anglo-French offensive commenced early in April, with results with which the War Cabinet are familiar. 18.    On April 10th (after the commencement of the Anglo-French offensive) the Prime kinister informed the War Cabinet that m, Painleve&apos; had paid hir^a visit and had appeared to desire that eight divisions (four British and four French) should be sent to Italy.   Not wishing to commit himself, he had given K. Painleve no encouragement.   The Chief of the Imperial General Staff advised the War Cabinet that it would be a mistake to send these divisions to Italy, where General Cadorna had all the infantry he wanted,   The British 6 inch howitzers would have gone to Italy by the end of the week, and if the French were anxious to assist Italy, their help should take the form of field artillery, (War Cabinet 116, Minute .12)
l4.   On May 1st the War Cabinet had a very full discussion as to the attitude to be adopted by the British representatives at a forthcoming Inter-Ally Conference at Paris on the subject of the military policy of the Allies on the Western front.   (War Cabinet 128f Minute l) .   After a very long discussion, during which attention was Called to the probability that the French Government   would oppose the continuation of a great offensive after the failure of General Elvelle&apos;a plan to achieve decisive results and particularly in view of the recent appointment of General Petain as Chief of Staff at the French War Office, it was decided:-&quot;(l)   That the British representatives at theConference should press the French to continue the offensive.(2)     If after hearing General Petainfs views, or after a Conference between the Chief of the Imperial General Staff and General Petain, they were not satisfied that the French offensive would prove   effective, they should insist on our entire freedom of action and on the French Army re-occupying the trenches recently taken over by the British forces&quot;.In the course of this discussion the Prime Minister gavea full exposition of the arguments likely to be raised by theFrench representatives against the continuation of ouroffenaive in the West.   In doing so he &quot;made it clear&quot;that he was not himself committed to the arguments that he&quot;had expressed, but he considered that they required earnest&quot;consideration&quot;.20.   At the Paris Conference on May 4 and 5 the PrimeMinister strongly supported the above decision of the WarCabinet and insisted on thorough and complete French co-operation.
&quot;We were ready&quot; he said &quot;to put the full strength of the IrUisSiLy into the attack, but it *aa no ^L^ Lin- so unless the French did the same-. S^nerwise^tne German would bring his be^t men and guns -2nd Si Vdb emmv.nition against the British Army and &apos; thenlateraSnst the pfench.     Tentative and feeble attacks were really more costly in the ena. (I.C-21, p.4,)21. The French Government professed concurrence in theBritish view and the following was included in the draftresolutions presented by the Prime Minister to the Conference :-&quot;The British and French Governments undertake to continue the offensive on the Western Front in accordance with the principles agreed by Generals Petain. ITivelle, Robertson, and Field Marshal Haig, set forth in the attached document, and. to devote he whole of their forces to this purpose,&quot; I.C.-21, po9.)The document referred to is important in the developmentof the offensive plans of the Allies and. is as followsStatement by General Sir William Robertson*&quot;I conferred this morning with Generals Petain and &apos;. tfivelle and Field Marshal Sir Douglas Haig. We revfowed the whole situation, including the situation in Russia and Italy, and the entry of America into the war, and we arrived at the unanimous opinion that it is essential to continue offensive operations on the Western Front.     A large portion of the enemy&apos;&apos;s reserves have aJ.ready been, exhausted by the French and British attacks.    If the enemy is given time to recover, the fiuits of this success will be lost.     He will be fvee to attack either Russia or Italy, neither of whom are a,t present in a condition to resist an attack ir^gceat force.     His present object is certainly to encourage his people to hold out until the submarine warfare has taken effect. and if he is left free to gain easy successes where he;Cari. and allowed to proclaim to the world that he has defeated his two principal enemies, he will attain this object.     This might be fatal to our chances of winning the war.     We are, : however, unanimously of opinion that the situation .        changed since the plan for the offensive begun in April, was agreed upon by the two Governments, and that this plan is no longer opera^ve.x     It is no longer a question- of aiming at breaking through the enemy&apos;s front and aiming at distant objectives.   It i.8 now a question of wearing down and exhausting the enemy&apos;8 resistance, and if and when this ig achieved to exploit it to the fullest extent possible.     In order to wear him down we are agreed that it is absolutely necessary to fight with all our available forces, with the object of destroying the enemy1s divisions, we are unanimously of opinion that therd i   no half-way oetween this course and fighting defensively, which,of te^in^?^ ^that the Words underlined would have the effect Sarah?? g   he a*range^t of Feb. 27th under which FieldIf       *ompaJed his plans t0 the general strategical the agreement fn    Co^nder-in-Chief.   (C.F,   -ciausf 5 ofA I
&quot;at this stage of the war, would he tantamount to acknowledging defeat.     Wo are all of opinion that our object can be obtained by relentlessly attacking with limited objectives, while making the fullest, use df our artillery.     By this.means we hope to gain our ends with the minimum loss possible.Having unanimously agreed to the above principles, we consider/tiiat the methods to be adopted to put them into practice, and the time and place of the various attacks, are matters which must be left to the responsible Generals, and that they should at once be examined and settled by them.&quot;Paris, May 5th, 1?17.It is believed that this was the turning point at which General Nivelle!s plan was   abandoned with the eventual result that Field Marshal Haig&apos;s plan for an offensive.in Flanders was adopted.22.        No mention was made of any offensive on the Italian front at this Conference, nor at the meeting of the War Cabinet, which immediately preceded it.23.        As some doubt was felt, owing to a letter from the French Government, as to whether the French Government had accepted the above draft resolution on the subject of the West-em front, the Secretary of State for War was asked to confer with the French Minister of War on the subject (War Cabinet 139, Minute 12), and Lord Derby, after a visit to Paris was able to give an entirely re-assuring account of the French intention to co-operate. (War Cabinet 14-4-, Minute 6).24. On May 30th the Chief of the Imperial General Staffinformed the War Cabinet that the Italians had sustained heavy losses and had been compelled temporarily to suspend their offensive owing to the lack of heavy artillery ammunition. Stepsj however, were being taken to accumulate a further supply of ammunition, and on its arrival the offensive would   &apos; be resumed. (War Cabinet 150,Minute 2.)2 . On June 8th the War Cabinet appointed a Committeem v* . composedm
&apos; composed of:-The Prime Minister Lord Curzon Lord Milner General Smuts . Mr.Bonar Law   (added subsequently). Sir Maurice Eankey (Secretary)to investigate the facts of the naval, military and politicalsituations, and present a full report to the War Cabinet.86.    The Prime Minister has asked me to report on the mattermentioned by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff that he wasnot present at many of the meetings of this Committee.   There werein all sixteen formal meetings.   The Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff was present at nine of these accompanied on five oocasions byField Marshal Haig.   Of the remaining seven, three were devotedwholly to naval and shipping questions, and two wholly to thetechnical development of the Taranto route, when Sir Guy Granetrepresented the War Office.     Only at the last two meetings weremilitary questions discussed without the presence of the Chief ofthe Imperial General Staff at any part of the Meeting and it hadbeen intended to invite his presence to one if not both of them,but the meeting had to break up prematurely owing to an urgentquestion necessitating the assembly of the War Cabinet.   As amatter of fact the military problems discussed at theoe two meet-inga mainly concerned the Balkan and Turkish theatres, and thedecision in the t?ro latter cases was postponed until the views ofthe Chief of the Imperial General Btaff were available (See pre-liminary draft of the Report of the Cabinet Committee on War Policydraft Conclusions 4 &amp; 5.    There *ere in addition two informal andunrecorded discussions at the residence of members of the Committee.Verbal and documentary evidence was supplied by the Chief of theImperial General Staff in all the military questions dealt with,and his advice, at any rate, so far aa immediate action isconcerned was /accepted.. //
accepted on every question.     The preliminary draft report was circulated to all Members of the Yfer Cabinet and to the Chief of the Imperial General Staff at the same time as to the members of the Committee, and the final conclusions were adopted at a meeting of the War Cabinet, which was attended by General Robert-son. (War Cabinet. 191(a) ).27, So far as military policy on the Western and Southernfronts is concerned, the conclusions of the T;ar Cabinet, based on the inquiries of the War Policy Committee were as follows(a) The Field Marshal Commanding the British --&quot;Expeditionary Force in France should be -authorised to carry out the plans for which &apos;-- he has prepared, &quot;as explained by him to theCabinet Committee on War Policy on June 19.th.(b) If it appears probable in the execution of these plans that the results are net commensurate with the effort made and the losses incurred,.the whole question should be .re-examined by the War Cabinet with a view to the cessation of this offensive and the adoption of an alternative plan.(o) Tha only alternative plan which at presont commends itself to the Cabinet Committee is General Cadorna&apos;g proposal   for a great offensive against Austria, supported by British and, if the French are. prepared \ to co-operate, by French heavy artillery.(d) In order that this alternative plan may be feasible in the event of a decision being talcen to desist from Field Msrshal Sir Douglas HaigTs plan of opera-tions, arrangements should be made forthwith for&apos;giving effect to it;   for a gradual accumulation of reserves of ammunition   for an eventual force of British heavy guns on the Italian front;   and for all other measures that can be taxen in advance to -facilitate the execution of the plan. ^(e) The Chief of the Imperial-General Staff should taxe.immediate steps to .give effect to these decisions. 4(f) Pressure should be put on the French Government to co-operate with all their forces in the forth-coming British offensive in Flanders; and to send heavy guns to Italy if the proposal in (o) is adopted.7   The.remainder of the conclusions of the War Cabinet contained some qualifying and explanatory passages in regard to the manner of giving effect..to. these two decisions.
28.   In the-oourse of a converBatiorfDetween-the repre-sentatives of the British, French, and Italian Govern-ments at the Paris Conference on July 25 - 26 the Prime Minister, during a discussion on the possibility of Russia being forced out cf the war, raised the question of an attempt being made to anticipate this contingency by forcing Austria out.   Diplomacy, however, he pointed ou/t* could not achieve this unless preceded by a military success, and on these grounds, he urged the study of a Combined Allied attack on the Italian front (l,C.-24(a)), 29.   These conversations were renewed on the same basis during the London Conference ,on August 7th and 8th when it was agreed that the British,-French, and Italian staffs should consult on.these questions and report at the next meeting, which is;fixed for September 15th.   This, however, belongs rather to the plans for 1918 than to 1917. 30.   On August 27th the War Cabinet had before them a letter from the Prime Minister (who was away) to the Chief of the Imperial General Staff suggesting the possibility of exploiting-General Cadorna%victdJrr on the Italian front by sending there further.batteries of heavy artillery. (War Cabinet 224, Minute 17).   The discussion was renewed on the following afternoon, and aB the result cf this Meeting (War Cabinet 225(a)) the Chief of the Imperial General Staff and Director of Military Operations visited the Prime Minister and Lord Milner on August 29th and a telegram to the British Ambassador in Rome was agreed on.   It is not necessary to give the gist of this telegram, which is fresh in the minds of Members of the War Cabinet,2 Whitehall Gardens,. S,W. 1st September, 1917,(Sd.)   M.P.A.. HAHKEY.

</content>
</cab>
