<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/25/0 images: 333-333</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*..C R 38 T*WAR CABINET.ASSISTANCE TO RUSSIA.(Copy of a letter from Admiralty to Secretary, War Cabinet enclosing a paraphrase of Telegram from Senior Naval Officer, Archangel regarding the Pood Situatio-n.)5th Sept1917The First Lord asks me to send you the enclosed paraphrase and extract from a telegram which he has received from Rear-Admiral Kemp, the Senior Naval Officer at Archangel A similar extract has been sent to the Shipping Controller.The First Lord is taking up with the Chief of the Naval Staff this question of the Icebreaker Fleet, but he thinks that the question of importing food rather than munitions into Russia during the winter is one which should be considered by the War Cabinet in conjunction with the Shipping Controller.PARAPHRASE AH) EXTRACT FROM TELEGRAM RECEIVED -ffRQllTHS SENIOR NAVAL. OFFICER AT ARCHANGEL.The serious food conditions in Russia lead me to submit to you for consideration the question of devoting to the import of. food into Russia some of the tonnage which is now.earmarked for the import of munitions.    Flour&apos;,: sugar, tea, rice and herrings are the principal requirements in Russia..As regards herrings, the British Government holdsa supply in Norway, and I understand that they could bebrought to Russia at the cost only of the freight.     There:seems to be little probability that the Norwegian Govern-&apos;ment could be persuaded to allow Norwegian ships to come ^?ufaiaiue?en^aJth0USk arrangements have definitely baen made for their being escorted by armed vessels front Vardo.*v,A       Thi&amp; question of assisting the Russians through-the winter by import of food I consider to be of supreme importance..    Another important matter is to make the ice-oreaker fleet-at Archangel efficient.     If Petrograd should r/?JSe?*0r,??e? se?i0?sly threatened during the next ranter it will be vitally important to keep up suoolv communication with Russia through Archangel and Vologda.

</content>
</cab>
