<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/25/0 images: 354-354</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0-6 i 2321j&apos; i    &apos;     -T -Waters Government.).SECRET  .9OPERATIONSFrom:-     General Delme Radcliffe , Italy To: -        C .1 .G .S . v office . 5.9. 1917 .379 cipher.Situation 10 to-night.2nd Army. Continued struggle for possession of St. Gabriele. Western sides and summit held by Italian troops, while Austrian?) are.still cn the northern and eastern sides and at St. Caterina. Italian troops are fighting with great dash and confidence. 1 battalion: of Austrian 43rd Division was sent from Chiapovano valley, to reinforce St. Gabriele, also 1 company from St. Caterinsu On 2nd Army front there is no indication of other reinforcements, Italians captured an Austrian Staff map. showing position cf a Gedeckter-Weg from Ternova northward and west through Se&amp;owec. it being main line of supply for St * Gabriele.   To-night this road is being bombarded. It is known that 106th, Division is known to be still very weak after reforming. 25th Landsturm Regiment only has the 1st and 3rd Battalions reformed with 3 and 2 battal-ions respectivelyo   Yesterday; General Schcnburg. Von Harten-stein addressed a parade at Ternova, inciting troops to fight on in spite of losses and informing them that, for the safety of Austria, the retention of St. Gabriele was indispensable. To-day about 100 prisoners taken.3rd Army. Austrians attacked again along the from 0astagnevi z za to the sea, after bombardment during the night. Italians counter-attacked at 9 and further heavy fighting took place this evening with result not yet known. Bombardment continues.Enemy said to have suffered very heavy losses, and his expenditure of men is difficult to understand, except on the assumption that he has close.at hand further reserves. A great many march battalions of other regiments have been brought from Carnia and Trentino,. and these have been absorbed. 12th and 9th Divisions have probably completed reforming, l\To contact obtained with 12th and 32nd regiments of the 41st Division.   16th Division has been again reported in reserve behind Hermada I   Of one batch of 75. prisoners taken between the Jamiano valley and the sea 70 belong to 13 different regiments and 3 different Divisions.whole front

</content>
</cab>
