<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/25/0 images: 363-374</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Page 1. Section II Disputes - line 5 - for &quot;3/6d a week&quot; read &quot;3/6d. per day&quot;.Page 8. Seotion IT - line 8 - for &quot;Derbyshire&quot; read &quot;Denbighshire&quot;.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.)

SECRET

WAR CABINET

REPORT ON THE LABOUR SITUATION FOR THE WEEK ENDING 5th September, 1917.

(Copy of a letter from Ministry of Labour)

No. M.L. 2435/16. 6th September, 1917.

Sir,

I am directed by the Minister of Labour to forward here with 58 copies of the Weekly Report on the Labour situation, for the week ending 5th September, and to invite your attention particularly to Part V, which deals with the subject of a memorandum submitted by Professor Arnold of Bangor, entitled "Labour in Revolt." (Paper No. G.T. - 1849).

I am, Sir,

Your obedient Servant,

(Signed) D. J.  SHACKLETON.


^Ketxxift from the Ministry $f labour on the labour 1 Situation fer the week ending 5th September 1917.1Q Q  ril. Strikes .Che week has been free ef sny strikes of ^np^rtanoe.   In a number of small collieries in South Staffordshire the miners came $ut for periods from 2 to 6 days, in support of the general demand for an increase, of 25yS in wages.   They have mostly returned to work pending deoisien of the national demand.Werk has been resumed at the Llanhilleth Colliery, ishere a strike was reported last week, the question at issue having been referred to arbitration.The demand that a Booth Liner should be treated as a standard ship for purposes of remuneration led to a strike of Bivetters at the Caladon Company&apos;s yard at Dundee; - work has been resumed * the Boilermakers society having agreed to arbitration.Several small strikes in support of increases in wages have been caused by members of the United Garment Workers Union.   Tho strike of Dyers at Pullars Dyeworks, Perth, continues but negotiations for settlement of the dispute are in progress.A number of serious oases of dispute exist, any one of which might cause extensive trouble.The negotiations with the Locomotive Engineers and Firemen failed on aooount of their insistence on a demand for an increase ff 3/6d a week in their wages, and there is some danger that the refuse.of that demand may result in &quot;direct action&quot; on the part of the Societyrs members,   $aeir intentions in the matter have not yet transpired, but the indications are that tjbe Society will not try another gall with the Government at presentsThe various associations of Colliery surface workmen have associated themselves with the miners in a general demand for 25$ advanoe.   The case is engaging the attention of tbo Coal Controller, who has arranged after consultation with the C*I.G. to take the case himself.Tho trouble in the Blastfurnace Industry,has been settled at a meeting of masters and men held at the Ministry of Munitions,   k general agreement on the subject of payment for holidays was reached, and the representatives of the men promised to use their utmost endeavours to ensure its acceptance.Local branohes of the N.U.B. are fjassing resolutions demanding a further increase of  1. in their wages to be added to the 15/-advanoe already received.   The Executive of the Union will doubtless move when the demand has beoome sufficiently widespread to support their action.The question whether the manufacture of eutlery, spoons and forks supplied to the 7ar pffice is Munitions work nor not has11. Disputes.
never been settled and this fact was givfcagrise to much dJUwmt^ent in the Sheffield Light Trades.    The National Amlgamafred Union oil labour has now decided to test the matter before a munitions tribunal and threatens a strike, if it loses the case.    This would stop all supplies of this kind to the War Office *I     The Scottish Colliery Enginemen have decided to hand in notices to cease work because of the refusal of the Coal Controller to accede to their demand for a Jar Bonus of l/- per shift.    The strike would throw 100,000 men out of work.It is reported that a meeting of the national Society of Woolcombers at Bradford unanimously resolved to cease work on 11th. September.     The strike would affect about 14.000 workers.    The resolution was passed in support of an application for       increase of wages and a 55j hours week, which is being considered by the Chief Industrial Commissioner.The Tramway workers employed by 19 authorities in Lancashire and Cheshire have tendered 21 days notice under the iJunit, ions Act. These authorities being federated, refuse to negotiate separately, and are submitting the dispute to the Committee on Production.. .The Shipyard Labour Department reports 114 cases of dispute of which .30 were settled by Officials of this Department t 14 referred to arbitration: the remainder are under negotiation or investigation. -&apos;.Cases, have also been reported Ibg the Ministry of Munitions, the Coal Controller, and the War Of floe Contracts Department.   Tho mopk important have been dealt with above.
III.   DISTRICT REPORTS.Conditions generally are quiet. All the deportees are now in em aoynent, including David Kirkwood, who h&amp;s been appointed foreman in a national projectile factory.a meeting of the Clyde Workers Committee was held at Glasgow on the Is t September at which HoHantis reported at length on the proceedings of the Shop Stowards Manchester Conference.    He complained of financial stringency, which appears to be hampering the national movement.In spite of official prohibition, a meeting of 4,000 persons assembled at Glasgow Green on the Snd ins t., to protest against the action of the Uilitary authorities in the case of Councillor Dollan, who had received exemption on condition that he obtained employment at least 50 miles from ftlas^ow.    Councillor Dollan/s conviction for failure to carry out the conditions has been upheld by the Sdinbur^h Hi h Court.This area is quiet.     The only feature of remark is the general opposition to pacifist propaganda whioh has manifested itself.    Many of the Hiners1 Lodges have passed resolutions protesting against the misrepresenta-tion of Labour by delegates at peace demonstrations.The question of housing at Barrow is the sub ject of considerable dissatisfaction and agitation.    It is thought that the Government measures to deal -/with the problem are inadequate and drastic action is demanded.A Shop Stewards&apos; Meeting ms held on 2nd September at Y/hich it was advocated that the efforts of the United liachiiie ,&apos;orkers to resist further oombin;; out should receive the support of the Liiflneers.The Boilermakers on the rersey are at work pending arbitration in their case and conditions are normal generally.In the Manchester area the scheme formulated by the Cotton Control Board is widely discussed.     The Operative Spinners1 anc. Cardroom V/orkers1 Amalgamation appear to approve of the arrangements made, but at Burnley both employers and employed would have preferred organized short time, as it is doubted whether the levy will provide sufficient funds to meet the requirements of the ltaeaployed.The situation is more satisfactory, though a !certain unrest exists among the Bradford /oolsorters and the National Society of /&quot;oolco^bers, both of which bodies are claiming substantial increases in images.An unauthorised meeting of delegates of the Engineering and Allied Trades was held at Leeds on the 1st September, to consider the advisability of action in protest against the national award of 5/-, which is considered inadequate.    it was resolved to proceed no further in the matter, but to demand a reduction of 50^ in the price of all necessaries.     If this demand is not conceded the question will again be considered at a&apos; &apos; meeting/
meeting to be held on 15th October.It is reported that though Xeeds has been eonstituted headquarters of the &quot;/orkers and Soldiers Councils and of other pacifist bodies, their views are not in fact by any means representative of local feeling.The Unrest in the coalfields gives cause My considerable anxiety.    The matter has been referred to in Section I.A mass meeting of local railway men was held at Birmingham which unanimously supported the resolution to demand  1. per week, advance of wa^es, in addition to the 15/- advance already secured.The.most prominent event of the week has been the Interallied Socialist Conference, which is dealt with in Section Iv&quot;, (infra).    The Conference was a decided failure.;Industrial conditions are generally normal.    Bad feeling is stated to er:ist among the skilled men in the gauge-room of the Royal Gun factory at noolwich on the ground that they are earning from  1. to Sg. .^cr week less than the semi-skilled piece-workers, and an application for increased raises is imminent.The Secretary of the   brkers1 Committee has issued an extremist leaflet &quot;To the Shop stewards and \ orders in London&quot;.    It calls for a meeting of Shoy stewards for the 16th September to deal vrith &quot;special an  urgent business&quot; including the London Delegate1s report on the national Conference of Shop Stewards held in ilanchester on the 10th and 19th August;The situation is unchanged. There have been one or two small strikes, but the decision on the national claim for Zfyo increase is awaited generally.One interesting case has been reported in which notices to terminate contracts have been served by Employers on 26 miners, on the r-round that they have failed to pay their contributions to the Miiiers1 Federation.In these areas conditions are normal.Sirtensive unemployment is reported.
IWK&amp;SS OPINIONS * - &apos; -1  :. \   &apos;. .    &apos;The Socialist fKe,meetin^ of the Socialist representatives of&apos;v^5on^erehoSs;.^sllied Countries in London on 28thv and S9th* Augttst and -1   the prospects? Of the International  onfereno^ atStockholm have furnished. the Pi-ess with much material   .   j for discussion during the week.,   The fortoer gathering took place-after the publication of the majority of the:   ; week1s Labour papers, whose comments may be expected       ; during the current week.   The proceedings were private, and as unanimity was not reached on any point in :   discussion, no formal resolutions were passed except one of congratulation On the Russian  evolution.The Times describes the- Official report as a &quot;recor? of failure&quot; but it&apos; is ojiestionahle whether unanimity on essential questions was expected,   ghe Daily Chronicle c deprecates the strong opposition manifested to the assemblihg of the Conference inro*ertain quarters.   It says:- &quot;V/hat Objection can there be to men acquainting themselves, with one another1s views by an oral conferencei? Exchange of opinion always does, tend to unity, and unity is just what the allies imist haye.^*.* ... It is the democracies of the Allies who are making the present war upon Prussian!sm andobscurantism, in ail co-entries, and it is; only they who .:Mli;^4ing it ;tb ,-a successful conclusion.&quot; The, - Yorkshire &apos;&amp;6B$&apos;:^ii&amp;ra$8&amp;d&amp; ,that &quot;The Russian Delegates axe disappointed&apos;;;.^tn:- ,   ^result of the.Socialist Conference in London and it is ^highly probable that the idea of the Stockholm:);.: ^Conference will be abandoned... The Pacifists are&quot;reconciling themselves to unpacking the hags which had/&quot;been got ready in anticipation of a sudden call to&quot;Stockholm.&quot;   Justice has an anticipatory article on the Conference/ entirely hostile/ which examines the status\ Of the representatives, and concludes - .Hwhat good can &quot;possibly come. out of this Inter^Aliied Conference &quot;called, by the. British Section of the ?jrS.3,: which Was &quot;originally to have been held before the. labour Party &quot;Itself decided what it was to dp: about Stockholm?   The &quot;most we can see Is the adoption of some dec!aration of &quot;compromise which will, please nobody,&apos; not event hose   ; 1 &quot;who pass it, or the;rising of the Conference&apos; y/ithont &quot;arriving at any definite decision^&quot; *   v - ; V .&apos;The British&apos; Citizen and Empire V/orker. has a characteristic attack upon the Conference in general, pointing out that &quot;the spirit of nationalism is *stronger, far stronger,, than the spirit of &quot;internationalism.&quot;- :THS LABOUR LEADER while the conference was.still Biffing&quot; says.-&quot; That ever, the decisions: Of the conference^ &quot;may be, one invaluable service has been donej in &quot;having secured from the various sections of the &quot;Allied Socialists, statements of their views on - / &quot;peace;Terms&quot;. - -\The Leicester Pioneer writes &quot;.. .It was a most Valuable meeting.&quot;It had to be gone through with.   -&quot;Withput.such a meeting nothing was possible.   The ^movements in&apos; the. various nations are divided and we .%ras&apos;t e;o on explaining.&apos; our views and challenging the &quot;people to think about themr   In any event, the I.L.E. &quot;had every reason to be satisfied with the Inter-^Allied Conference.&quot;
- 53he flew Statesman deals with the cbriferesbe ih ah. artieTe Headed &quot;AeB-liea Peoples&quot; pointing Q^ttle toto cdneepficnB as to its alms under which the -Hftp^ls tut cone Ming that the matter of the, St6a3tli61m (kmfaraqfri can hardly he reopened for some time, tbb^h the/yW^^J^ of Stance and of this-eourit^ at; a later date,-to allow&apos;th^The New Jbxe in its &quot;Notes of *tke week&quot;- &quot;agaiii d^als with  , the sFookSoim cfonference, and la;rs stress on the.argument that &quot;the submission of the 11 Labour movement in this, country, to-&quot;the policy diet at ed for it by:. tHe^orthclif f e Presses a. &quot;slap in the faoe for democratic opinion abroad, in friendly . . t &quot;no less than in enemy countries. - Above all It must &quot;necessarily weaken the hands of the Socialist Party in^-&quot;Russia, and of the minority socialists in Germany *** She &quot;heroic Minority Socialists can only regard the event as &quot;meaning that they can look for no support from Labour &quot;abroad in their efforts to democratize their own i^vernmontr* The article also describes as growing a conviction that the Government means to exclude Labour from anyshare in public policy, while tlie Call, in an article headed &quot;Kick them out&quot;, has a very violent attack on the present Government, based on the Henderson incident and the Russian Telegram;,     &apos;  &apos; v  &apos;The Herald in the course of an article on the Crisis in Russia&quot; allsges that a bour^dfc counter-revolution is threatened in that country, and calls upon the Trade Unions Congress &quot;by declaring unhesitatingly for Stockholm ..V*.i.tc &quot;stem the tide of re-action in nussia and to save the world nfor democracy and for peace&quot;.   It has a second alarmist article, entitled Labour and Kerensky, in which it attempts to throw the blame jBbr the latterrs difficulties iM the -Governmentrs refusal to support the Stockholm -Oonfarenoe and calls upon the T-jade Union Congress to save the Revolution     ;v by voting for participation. .   - r&quot;&apos;Justicer franlyiy hopes on the. ether: handj&apos; t^tjt^e^/^Sea&quot; ^ Conference, will now be definitely abandoned.of a Stocfyjtr and/- ...:    The Labour Party ftote on War aims has, been followed by Lfeace.&quot;     similar notes from the Independent Labour Party and the B.S. . The -former is examined in a spirit of hostile criticism by the British Citizen, which concludes &quot;In our- opinion this note of the I.L.P. reveals it to be, consciously or &quot;unconsciously a German, agency in this country.   Anything . &quot;more cynical, more monstrous, than these proposals, we could &quot;not.have imagined&apos;.&apos;   Comment in this journal on the.latter note also is most hostile.   It is equally bitter in the Clarion which points, out that the note of the B.S.P. is infiniteiy   i &apos; more tender -to German misdeeds and sentiment than a leaflet&apos; issued by Liebkhecht in 1916, and suppressed by the Kaiser. The Cail in a favourable article on xhe Pope*s peace       * proposals* says:-   &quot;the, advice of the Press,is a total&quot;rejection of the Pope *s offer; Clearly/therefore, the ^&quot;intentions of those who dictate the opinions of the Entente &quot;is to continue the war to the point, of crushing Germany, in --order to carry out in full their programme of conquest and innexation. : .   &quot;The -Herald prints an article ^Labour iinistersand a moral&quot; dealing with the subject of Labour and the present lent   Government , pointing out, first, how Labour in theGovernment has. been an impotent minority, and second that &quot;Labour men flung Dnto Govornment environment have begun to &quot;adopt a species, of protective colouring.   Mr. Henderson &quot;always honourably excepted, they have done precisely what &quot;our rulers expected of them,, precisely the opposite of what
"Labour intended." The moral urged is that "Joint Control "in industry is as impossible as in Politics. It cannot "endure , it can never really exist... co partnership is "fatal...Labour should accept no responsibility, should not "allow its representatives to join in a sham partnership "except and only upon the condition that it and they have "exclusive or at least pre-dominant control1".   The Call deals with the question of the "Labour Party and the ? alleging that the truce has been definitely broken on the part of the Government by its dismissal of Mr. Henderson, and supporting the view that official relations between labour and the Government should be severed.

The question of the reflection of Mr.G.H.Roberts has formed the subject of discussion in some of the papers, the Herald and the Cotton Factory Times including that he no longer holds his seat as a labour representative.

New Honours"

The order of the British Empire and the list of these decorated have boon received with, contumely by several of the Labour Papers, notable the Labour Leader and the Leicester Pioneer.

?

The decision that the Employment Department should of the remain with the Ministry of Labour has been approved in every quarter.

The statement issued by Rt.Hon.Geo. Barnes on the steps taken and to be taken by the Government to mitigate unrest has been well received by most Journals. The Woolwich Pioneer prints a long article on this subject of which the general Trend may be typified by the following extract:- "Despite its defects Mr.Barnes statement, is, in "intention, a useful and hopeful initiative...we welcome his "statement, as a stop towards a closer contact between the "Government and official Trade Unionism and Labour on the "one hand, and the great body of the workers on the other,"

The same paper gives a vorbatim report of Mr.Anderson&apos;s speech at the Plumstead Baths on the 21st August. The oration, which was of an extremist type, is headed "Government&apos;s Treatment of Industrial Workers, Masterly "review of Workers&apos; experience under war legislation." 

The question of Food control committees, their constitution and powers, has been much discussed during the week. Criticism has been directed to the number of fotail traders who have been appointed to these Committees, but the Food Controllers&apos; moasures have on the whole been welcomed, specially his action in obtaining assistance from the co-operative Societies. A demand has been voiced by the London Food Vigilance Committee that at least 50 1/2 of the personnel of the Committees should be appointed by labour organizations.

The Morning Advertizer reports a serious shortage of beer in the Swansea District which has resulted in the organization of a campaign of protest. Miscontent is also stated to exist in Birmingham on account of the shortness of supply of beer, its quality and its price.

Conditions at Barrow form the subject of very adverse criticism in the Manchester Guardian (August 29th), whose article describes a series of "Typical cases" of overcrowding of a most scandalous character. The correspondent states that, in the opinion of the medical officer of health, 3000 new houses are required for the accommodation.
9f the present popoJ^bicicu.  A cust^n of hire porfifcaeearisen which otttflaEukc the provi-sions. preventing increase of rent-, and enable3 tho new owner himself to inhabit a small portion of the hom^es and.to chaige excessive rents . to other tenantb, who aie treated as lodgers.   A similar system has f.o:?hiod the ^ub^eo-t of compj.aint in Glasgow and is attacked in the Oallo   A great scarcity of houses is reported from Sast Derbyshire where the requirements are stated to be 1700.
y. general scejarks;. : 301ftbottr ia        ^he Ilinister has received a copy of the memorandum IWoV&amp;S entitled &quot;Labour in Revolt&quot; (Secret a. 8.1849) submitted2--by professor Arnold of Bangor University, and hascarefully examined its contents.The existence, methods, aims and dangers of the &quot;shop stewards movement&quot; have been brought to the notice of the War Cabinet in the fifth section of tlie Weekly Report on the Labour Situation on frequent occasions (o.f. Report for the weeks ending 30th May, 13th June, 1st,. 8th. and 22nd August 1917.)     It is with that movement that the memorandum presumably deals,, but Profes3or Arnold confuses with it a number of other currents of opinion, which are really quite alien to it, and he thus produces a false and exaggerated picture both of its importance and its influence..    Certain weaknesses in the argument are revealed by Critical examination of the memorandum..    It is not apparent, for instance, how a movement ishich is said neither to have leaders nor to need them,, can be described as possessed of an organisation as :.?ewect,as that of the German war machine before the war.     $he want of coherent and discipline, which is one of the weaknesses of the movement, is not a proof that it does not require leaders7.-Again, it is probably not true that the movement has no constructive programme, but simply aims at destroying society.     Its essential aim is the betterment of industrial-conditions, by giving the worker a voice in the control of his conditions of employment.    Ho doubt some of its leaders&apos; think that this can only be done by a revolution in industry, but the body of their followers would bo content with much less than this.    It is likewise true that many of the leaders are indifferent to the war and that some of them are oaoifists, who would like to stop it by revolutionary means, brat the great mass of the \aorkers desire to bring the war to a successful end.Professor Arnold&apos;s estimate of the importance of the &quot;Revolt&quot; oan be effectively judged in the light of the facto.-    The shop stewards movement was originally inspired by a small but energetic body of young men, of whom .J. T.. Kurphy and TTf. 7v   atson have been tjie most prominent.    :The latter served as organising secretary of the &quot;Amalgamation Committee&quot; - which had as its ^ject ... federation of all the metal, engineering:        shipbuilding unions of the country, and which numbered $mong i% members all the chief leaders of the shop stewards./    vTatson has now dissociated himself from the movement on tho ground that success is Impossible in view of the hostility p  the Trade Union Leaders, and will in future serve under we Revolutionary banner of the Industrial Vorkers of the World.    Ramsey of Leicester lias been elected in his. stead, but refuses to aoqept the position until the accounts have been audited and financial support assured.On the 18th and 19th August the national ppnferegpe of Shop Stewards took place at Manchester.     It was H&amp;ely advertised and every effort w&amp;s put forth to ensure a strong and representative gathering, under the $airmanship of HoManus.    The meeting       a complete failure, anil, at .   one period, degenerated into confusion.     &apos;j?he Conference -.     was entirely abortive, no resolution save one of adjournment, sine die, beinr; passed. T &apos;
302!&apos; iEfcm- these facts it may be deduced both that the \    organisation, is loss perfect and the inffiienee lessimportant than Professor Arnold belleves to be the case.That the movement is hostile to Trade Unionism is not established.    Officially, the opposite is stated, and muoh insistence is placed on the function of the shop-stewards movement as a support of official unions in a recent pamphlet oy J. T. Murphy. , it is, however, undoubtedly the case that the present Trade Union leaders are regarded as retrograde and out of date by the shop stewards, wbb would like to dispossess them of their power..  Nevertheless, -   whenever the movement has come into collision withOfficial trade unionism, it lias failed.    The success on the Clyde in the spring of 1916 was achieved- y/ith the help of the trade union leaders.     The Engineers1 strike was certainly on the verge of collapse when the arrests were made and probably would not have lasted so lqng as it didj had not the sympathy of the trade unions boon largely with the men;:  9?he outstanding instance of collision, however,, has been in the effort made by the Amalgamation Committee. After repeated, but futile, attempts to induce the union ; offioials to support the Federation movement, the Committee j deliberately appealed to a ballot of the workshops.   That appeal resulted in a complete and disastrous failure,   Q?he result of the ballot has not been published, and Watson has admitted that nine years of work have been neutralised by the trade union leaders.The causes and progress of the shop stewards movement have been frequently discussed.    It is unnecessary that the discussion should be repeated.    At its best the movement is a &quot;spiritual&apos;&apos; movement,, a revolt against industrial conditions and a system of industrial control which admittedly require a remedy.    But any attempt at forcible repression, such as is adumbrated by Professor Arnold; would, in the opinion of the -Minister;&apos; lead to\. -, -&apos; :explosion and&apos;disaster.     The agitation viewed as a whole, &apos;;; is, a healthy movement. to wards, a. more human&apos; s tahdard of life and a broader outlook for tlie working classes, and calls for wise and sympathetic guidance rather than,for repression.     It.is, of course;.. essential: that any steps to regularise and guide the movement should be taken in the closest consultation with the official leaders of organised labour;, but if.the workers are convinced that the Government is earnestly, and. sympathetically socking a thorough remedy for the evils which undoubtedly, exist, and a real solution of the problems which confront them in the future it may be confidently expected that any need for repression and any li&amp;eiihood of revolution,which Profecsor Arnold fears, will disappear.Kinistry of Labour. j.s.6th September; 1917.

</content>
</cab>
