<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/25/0 images: 417-418</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
A-1Q7&quot;3        li Q: -.-tannic Majesty .s C/o^, War Cabinet. ...Leave for Hew Zealand troops after 3 years 1 service.-i\ Memorandum by \he Seeretary of State for War... .1.     The following&apos;t elegram from lew Zealand has been forwarded to the War Office by the Colonial Office.Paraphrase Telegram from the Governor General of Hew Zealand fro^ the Secretary of State for the Colonies. (Received Colonial Office 11.7 a.in., 28th August,. 1917),to by my Government tne Hew ZealandAn arrangement has been agreed whereby after 3 years service members of Expeditionary Force may return on leave to Dominion;   numbers to be United to 250 per month&apos; and leave to be reckoned as 6 months from departure from the front until return which would allow 2 months in New Zealand.     On receipt of your telegram 3rd August reducing reinforcements there was already at sea a surplus of 1,100 men over new requirements.     uy Government is providing an additional 400, to replace the 1,500 going on leave. They would be glad if 2 months leave of absence either in the United Kingdom or France could be granted those eligible for leave who do not wish to take it in Hew Zealand.     In this case men would be absent from the Front for 2 months only and cost of transport would be saved.In regard to ITew Zealand troops serving in Egypt similar arrangements are being made.    Detailed arrangements are being made direct with General Officer Commanding ITew Zealand Expeditionary Force and my Government trust that Imperial authorities will raise no objection to these arrangements.I circulate to :the War Cabinet for their consideration a notice by the Adjutant general on the foregoing telegram which, in hie-..view, indicates a very dangerous line of poliey.ttThe question of relieving men who have been a long time at the frent has been-exercising my mind for some tine past and to-day I received the first numbers from the Salonika Force. Those from the other theatres of war will follow shortly.     In Salonika there are over 20,000 men who have been out conti-nuously for 30 months,.I am unaware under what authority the New Zealand Government agreed to give leave after 3 years1 service, and if such is the case .1 can only say that it was extremely short-sighted policy, as it was imposeible at the time the promise was given to have foreseen the situation.If leave on this scale is to be given to the ITew Zealandera, irrespective of the military situation at the front, the same measure must be meted out to all troops,, Dominion orBritish,
British, and the result will he that the forces at the front will be completely depleted.     If the privilege is confined to Dominion troops a spirit of strong antagonism which will,. in,my opinion, result in bloodshed, will spring up between the British and Dominion troops, between whom already, on account of the . difference of pay, and the absence of the death penalty in the Australian Contingent, the feeling is not too friendly.I cannot too strongly urge in my official position, that all troops should be treated on an equality as regards leave, and that such leave should be granted equally according to the necessities of the situation at the front.and facilities for transport.Unless a very fIria line is taken in this respect, I anticipate that the results may be little less than disastrous&quot;.7th September, 1917DEK3Y.

</content>
</cab>
