<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/185/18 images: 410-441</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(75)118 COPY NO     g ji6 November 1975CABINETPUBLIC expenditure note by the Chairman of the Steering Committee onEconomic StrategyINTRODUCTION1. At their meeting on 22 May the Cabinet asked that the OfficialSteering Committee on Economic Strategy (SCE) should consider the 1975Public Expenditure Survey Report, identify the main issues for Ministers,and set out the options which were open.    This the Committee has nowdone and our conclusions are set out below.background. The Cabinet recognised, when the 1975 Public Expenditure survey was launched, that merely to cost an extrapolation of existing policies was likely to produce an unacceptably high level of public expenditure.    they therefore agreed that, without prejudice to final decisions, the Surveyshould display the consequences, in terms of expenditure and of departmental policies, of adopting for most programmes reductionsrelated to a stated formula, as well as setting out, for those programmes for which the formula was not appropriate, a wide range of policy optionsinvolving expenditure reductions.    The aim was to set out illustrativereductions of up to  3 billion at 1974 Survey prices in the &apos;focus year1(1978-79) as compared with what had been published in the January white paper (Cmnd 5879).    The figure of  3 billion was chosen on the basis that ministers might need to make reductions totalling at least  2 billion andthat they ought to have some choice in order that the reductions made couldreflect their general policy priorities.3.        When the Medium Term Assessment was available in July theCabinet considered the position further, and the Chancellor of theExchequer then explicitly proposed that Ministers should &quot;accept the needfor reductions of at least  2 billion .... and preferably up to  3 billion&quot;.But in the event no decision on this was reached either on 14 July when theproposal was discussed or on 4 August when the Cabinet considered1
expenditure priorities.    It was however agreed that the Chancellor shouldmake clear in the debate on the White Paper &quot;The Attack on Inflation&quot; on21 July that the Government would be seeking further substantial economiesparticularly in 1977-78 and 1978-79 and that there would at best be verylittle room for overall growth beyond the reduced level for 1976-77.THE MAJOR PROBLEM4. We are clear that the first problem to which Ministers should address their minds is the quantum of the total reduction they consider necessary.    In this connection there are two preliminary points to note:-a. The figures of  2- 3 billion were at 1974 Survey prices,At 1975 Survey prices they become  2f- 3f billion.b. On this price basis,, the &quot;formula&quot; reductions, if all were adopted, would yield just over  2 billion;  and the further policy options identified in the Survey would yield another  1.7- 2 billion.Yet further options, put forward by the Treasury alone, would yield an additional  1.1 billion.    Thus the possible cuts displayedtotal some  5 billion, from which an appropriate selection needs to be made.5. It is our judgment that the range of billion remains theorder of magnitude for the total cuts which need to be found;  and for anumber of reasons we recommend that Ministers go for the upper end ofthis bracket rather than the lower.    Our reasons are:-i. As column C of Table I of the attached Treasury papershows, the cuts resulting from the &quot;formula&quot; reductions of theorder of  2 billion would still leave privately-financed consumptiongrowing over the five years at an average annual rate of only .3 per cent.    There would be a significant increase ir? the taxburden equivalent to 5-9p on the income tax by 1979 on the assumpti&apos;that income tax allowances and bands move in line with inflation and that indirect taxes move similarly.    A basic rate of incometax of 40-44p, making the marginal rate on the average wageearner, after allowance for graduated national insurance contributions, nearly 50p in the pound, a rate associated in thepublic mind with wartime conditions, could it seems to us createvery serious difficulties on other fronts and, in particular,seriously endanger the counter-inflation policy.ii. Even this outcome is dependent on our securing annual increases in the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) averaging3.4 per cent per annum over the period.    This in turn assumes that despite our present economic problems productivity continuesto grow at the same rate as it has done in the past and that
inflation will be successfully controlled right through the periodso that the economy can return to much higher levels ofemployment,    These assumptions could well be optimistic, asthey have been so often in the past, in which case fewer resources would be available in the years ahead than are allowed for in thisassessment,    The risk here is in our view and on past experiencedefinitely a &quot;downside&quot; one,6. There are two principal reasons why the need for reductions now seems greater than when Ministers reviewed the position in May:-i. Some items of expenditure which were previously anunquantified potential charge on the contingency reserve have beencosted for the first time;  and estimating changes have inevitablyoccurred on a wide range of programmes, both up and down.Among the causes of estimating changes the most striking is thereduction, as compared with Cmnd 5879, in the assumed rate of inflation over the next few years.    This greatly affects the realcost of the social benefit schemes because of the way in whichmost of those benefits are, under present policy, linked to pastmovements in earnings or prices - the &quot;historical method&quot; ofuprating0    Upratings are based on the latest figures available atthe time the decisions are taken, 5 months or so before the upratingdate.    When inflation is slowing down the lag will improve therelative position of pensioners, because upratings will reflecthigher (past) movements of earnings or prices than are currently being experienced.    This effect will be very marked with an abruptslowing down of inflation of the kind now forecast for 1976-77.The improved outlook for inflation thus means that, on present policy, the real value of benefits and the resources devoted to them would rise faster than would otherwise be the case and than we had previously envisaged.ii. The huge increase, partly the product of inflation, in the forecast public sector borrowing requirement this year, and itsprospective level next year, add massively to the size of nationaldebt which will subsequently have to be serviced.   As a result, the forward estimates for debt interest have had to be sharply revisedupwards, the increase in resource terms being further compoundedby the effect of lower inflation noted in i. above.    Fortunately thedemand content of debt interest payments is relatively low, so thatthe big increase in the forecast real expenditure does not imposeanything like as large a demand on resources.
PRIOR CLAIMS7. Before Ministers accept the view we put forward concerning thescale of the reduction required they will wish to satisfy themselves thatthe resources available for the private consumer and the public sectorare as exiguous as the Treasury have suggested.    In the public expenditure exercise we set aside as a priority resources for the balanceof payments and for productive industrial investment.    It is the resourcesremaining after these priorities have been met that are available for theprivate consumer and the public sector (less that element which is devoted to industrial investment).    It is therefore of the first importance that these prior claims should be subject to rigorous scrutiny:-a. Balance of payments:  The scale of the resources allocated to the balance of payments is fixed by the policy assumption thatwe must eliminate the external deficit completely by 1978.    Tothe extent that we were able to postpone this target of externalbalance, we would have more resources available at home fordivision between public expenditure and the private consumer.Are we then being unnecessarily ambitious in seeking balance by1978, given the prospect that by 1980 and beyond we shall be self-sufficient in oil?    Our considered view is that our target is notin fact Unjustifiably demanding.    Even if we close the balance by1978 we shall have accumulated external debts in the post-oilcrisis period of the order of  10- 15 billion, the servicing ofwhich alone could well take up a very substantial part of our external income from North Sea oil.    If we take a more leisurelypath to balance we might find that the North Sea was more or lesstotally under mortgage.    More practical, perhaps, is the fact thatwe must now accept that the United kingdom s external credit isunder close scrutiny.    We are already experiencing somefinancing difficulties.    We shall do very well indeed to get all the external credit we need to reach 1978 without contemplating having to borrow beyond that year.    Put another way, if we make the target an easier one, we may well, sooner or later, provoke the crisis that would oblige us to change our strategy and cause allthe disruptions that a crisis change involves.    Better by far tomove of our own accord on a tenable path to viability.b. Productive investment: Allowance has been made for anaverage growth in fixed investment of very roughly 5 per cent perannum;  together with the projected rise in stocks this would takeone-third of the projected increment in national resources.    Thequestion here is whether we are making too much provision for theincrease in our national capital stock.    We do not think that thisis the case;  and we certainly do not think that it would be wise toassume that we shall not get investment on the scale assumed.The Government is currently launching a new industrial strategy4
which takes it as axiomatic that we need to develop and expand our industrial base.    It is under considerable pressure from theTrades Union Congress (TUC) to ensure that investment is increased substantially.    If, against this background, we were to plan our public expenditure programmes on the assumption thatour industrial policies were going to fail we should not only run the risk that we had pre-empted resources but should also have toreveal in the next Rlblic Expenditure &quot;White Paper that we had nofaith in those policies.THE CHOICE OF REDUCTIONS8. We stated above that we consider that Ministers should addressthemselves to the need to secure reductions at the upper end of the rangewhich they instructed us to examine, viz  3^ billion.    Annex B to theTreasury paper gives options which together total about  5 billion;  so asubstantial element of choice remains.    The options are classified under three headings viz:-i. Formula reductions (column a);ii. Other policy options identified in the course of the survey for programmes for which the formula reductions were notapplicable (column b);iii. Further options suggested by the Treasury but not agreed with Departments (column c)aAs between items in categories i, and ii, there is no presumed priority,and the fact that the Table in the Treasury paper shows the allocation of resources which might ensue from the adoption of items only in category i.is in no way intended to suggest that this category is to be regarded as apreferred candidate for reductions.    Category iii. is put forward only togive Ministers the further range of options which they may well findnecessary if they accept our recommendation to see aggregate cuts of theorder of  3^ billion.    Cuts of this order would reduce the average annualgrowth of other public expenditure (1974-79) in Table 1, from 1.4 per cent to 0, 7 per cent.    This increases the average annual growth allowed toprivately-financed consumption from 1.3 per cent to 1.9 per cent09.        How the selection should be made from the total range of optionsoffered is a matter of political decision.    Ministers will need to take intoaccount the preferences expressed by the Cabinet when they consideredpriorities in public expenditure (paragraphs 15 to 18 of the Treasury paper);the industrial impact of the proposed savings;  and the division of the programmes and the various reductions examined between direct purchases of goods and services and transfer payments (paragraphs 12 to 14 and annex D of the Treasury paper).
10.        Whatever answers may be given to these questions, it is aninescapable fact that reductions of the order of  3f billion cannot besecured unless big contributions are made by the main programmes.    Ofthe total reductions (about 80 items) discussed in the Survey exercise(that is to say the formula reductions and the other policy options in column b of Annex B) about three-quarters come from only five items,viz housing, health, roads, education and social security.    It might bea procedural help to Ministers if they concentrated first on these programmes, since without a resolute intention to reduce these, the totalcuts proposed cannot be achieved.Signed DOUGLAS WASSTreasury Chambers6 November 19756
PUBLIC expenditure note by the treasury this note summarises the main results of the 1975 Public Expenditure Survey andcomments on the main issues which it raises.Main expenditure figures2.    Ministers agreed on 22 May that for most programmes, instead of following thenormal course of, costing &quot;existing policies&quot;, the Survey should set out the results of applying guidelines to the programmes, consisting mainly of formula reductions in capital and current expenditure from 1977-78 onwards.   In those programmes not susceptible to, and therefore not covered by, formula reductions, they also agreed that policy options which would produce additional savings should be identified andexamined.    The broad objective was to illustrate possible savings totalling  2-3 billionat 197^ Survey prices (equivalent to  2-J-3JI billion at 1975 Survey prices), as comparedwith the programmes as they then stood.3.     The Survey broadly met this objective.   But other developments have produced a somewhat different final picture in the Survey.Expenditure programmes in 1975-76 - 1976-77k.    Expenditure in these two years was not subject to the formula reductions.   Sincethe cuts for 1976-77 announced in the Budget, the expenditure programmes in both years have increased.   Taking account of the changes included in the Survey and some other changes which were settled too late for inclusion, the programmes in 1975-76 are now estimated at about  1,200 million* higher than in the last Public Expenditure white paper, Cmnd 5879; and in 1976-77 about  600 million higher.   These increases exceed theamount which was provided by way of contingency reserve for these years.   As a result the expenditure programmes (excluding debt interest and contingency reserve) are now expected to grow by k.0 per cent in 1975-76 and by -0.^ per cent in 1976-77.   If account is also taken of the revised estimates of debt interest (see paragraphs 6 and 7 below)and of the contingency reserve and shortfall deduction, the increases in total public expenditure become h.k per cent and 2.8 per cent respectively.*Except where otherwise stated all figures are at 1975 Survey prices.
S E C E E T Iare5.     The main programme items contributing to this extra expenditure/set out in annex A.   For 1976-77 there are three principal reasons for the increases:-i. We did not make any provision for British Leyland, the national enterprise Board, the Scottish and Welsh Development Agencies or forBNOC in the White Paper.   We now think it necessary to allow for these items  750 millionii. The food and housing subsidies extended in July to help withacceptance of the counter-inflation policy will cost  150 millioniii. The effect of the counter-inflation policy, involving lowerassumptions about the rate of inflation in 1976/77? will increase thereal cost* of the social security programme by  ^60 millionTogether with a miscellany of other items the net increase of  1700 million more thanoffsets the cuts of over  1000 million announced in the Budget.Total Public Expenditure 1977-78 to 1979-806.     So much for the immediate period ahead.   For the later years and particularly1978-79i the focus year of the Survey, similar increases have occurred since Ministersconsidered the outlook in May and authorised the exercise to be conducted on the basisof alternative cuts of  2-J-3i? billion at 1975 prices.   There has in fact been a rise of about    1 billion , partly as a result of the inclusion of items costed for thefirst time (mainly in the industrial field) and partly because of the adventitiousgains to pensioners etc arising from the lower inflation assumption.     Two other itemshave been revised upwards.   The contingency reserve, which has constantly beeninsufficient to meet the many unforeseen calls made upon it, has been increased from*This is a complicated point. Pensions and other social benefits are adjusted to take account of inflation.   But because the adjustments are made (usually) only once a yearand inflation is continuous, any slowing down of inflation benefits pensioners.   BeforeCmnd 6151 we were assuming prices to be rising at 17 per cent pa during 1976-77.   we now put this figure at 9 per cent.SECRET
 950 to  1200 million in 1978-79.   Secondly a very substantial upward revision hasbeen made in the provision for financing the public sector debt.   Forward interestrequirements have always been difficult to forecast and      are now even more subjectto uncertainty.   This is not just because so little can be known about future interest rates; it is also because, with the public sector borrowing requirement having grownrapidly to its present level, estimates of the accumulated debt three or four yearshence have escalated considerably.    This year&apos;s borrowing requirement (probably overL1C   billion) will increase the financial burden of debt interest by at least 1   billion.   By 1978/79 we now believe that we shall have to make about  J billionmore provision than we estimated last year.7.     The debt interest increase is not however very significant in resource terms.The recipients have on average a low propensity to consume, and the need to make public expenditure adjustments to accommodate higher - and to some extent arbitrary -estimates is much less than is the case with changes in the programmes having asubstantial resource content.   It is reasonable to state however that the worsenedoutlook for debt interest is a factor at least qualitatively to be taken into account.It is certainly likely to affect the views of outside observers, including ourcreditors, when the scale of the interest requirement becomes known.8. Quite apart from debt interest, the Survey figures for 1978-79 haveincreased by about  1^: billion (for the reasons explained earlier in paragraph 6) abovethe levels at which Ministers commissioned the exploration of cuts of  2-J-jJ billion.This means that pressure on resources for that year has increased and the resources available for privately financed consumption have been reduced.Expenditure and Claims on Resources9.     The following table which has been constructed on the usual basis followingcompletion of the 1975 Medium Term Assessment show three alternative allocations of resources:-(A) Cmnd 5879(B) the Survey before formula reductions.(C) the Survey after formula reductions.
10.    This table calls for a number of comments.   First, the GDP growth rate.   This i?rather faster in column C than in columns A and B, because the lower level of public expenditure resulting from the formula reductions means that a larger proportion ofthe labour force works in industry and commerce.    In all three cases GDP growth alsobenefits from the relatively low level of activity in 197**-.   Secondly, as always, we regard the claims of productive investment and the claims of the balance of payments,if this is to be back in balance by 1978, as over-riding priorities in the sense thatthey have to be met before we can contemplate cutting up the cake for the privateconsumer and the public sector (other than nationalised industries&apos;  investment).Thirdly, the resources available for these two claimants - ie, the private consumerand the public sector - remain broadly what they were thought to be in July - a little less than  600 million a year in 1970-price terms.   Fourthly, comparison of columns Band C shows the consequences of the Survey formula cuts ( 2.1 billion in 1978/79 at1975 prices); in 1970 prices and in demand terms, the average annual rate of increasein public expenditure comes down to 1.^ per cent per annum, ?r.d that of privatelyfinanced consumption increases to 1.3 per cent per annum.   The figures do not, however,show the effect of including the other options explored in the Survey ( 1.7 billionto  2 billion in 1978/79).*   There is no policy reason why the formula cuts shouldbe regarded as being more or less necessary than the other options.11.   The implications of the Survey public expenditure projections for the tax burdenare likely to be severe.   Quantitative estimates have to be based on the pre-SurveyMTA work, and this adds a substantial extra margin of uncertainty to&apos; what is in anycase a speculative figure.   However, given these reservations, the increase in the tax burden, expressed as the rise in income tax rates, comes to 5-9 pence, on theassumption that income tax allowances and bands, as well as indirect taxes, would go up in line with inflation.   Even after the formula reductions, the basic rate of incciltax might thus, on this reckoning, be of the order of kO-kk pence; and after allowance for graduated national insurance contributions, the average wage earner might losenearly 50 pence in the pound on his marginal income.   These figures need to beconsidered against the background of an increasing income tax burden in recent years. I&quot;The &quot;formula&quot; reductions consisted broadly of a 10% cut in current expenditure and20% on capital programmes in 1978-79.   For programmes, mainly transfer payments, not susceptible to this treatment, options were to be explored between the Treasury and departments.   The consequences of this are shown in Columns a and b of Annex B.
Table 1Allocation of resources: Average annual increases 1974-1979(Demand terras at 1970 factor cost prices)ic	A.Cmnd 5879  m    per cent per annum		B. Survey before formula     /,,\ reductions^ &apos;  m     per cent per annum		C. Survey after formula reductions (1)  m     per cent per annum	&quot;Gross domestic product	1610	3.2	1610	3.2	1720	3.4less &apos;prior claims	i					Balance of trade	520	-	520	- Vi,	560	-I Private and nationalised industry fixed investment	320	4.8	320	4.8	330	5.0Private and nationalised industries 1 stock building	210		210		240	leaving Tree resources&apos;	560	1.3	560	1.3	590	1.4Of which Other public expenditure(2)	380	1.9	450	2.3	270	1.4Privately-financed consumption	180	0.8	110	0.4	320 i	1.3(1) Changes in public expenditure do not affect only the distribution of free resources.     A reduction of that part of public expenditure whichis spent on goods and services raises the growth rate of GDP becausemore of the labour force is assumes to be working in industry and commerce, and although prior claims would absorb part of this increase,the growth of free resources would still go up a little.     The higherGDP growth in column C reflects this effect.     There could be somereverse effect in column B but it would be small and has been ignoredin the table.(2)Excludes nationalised industry investment (included in &apos;prior claims&apos;).SECRET
Por a married man with two children on average earnings, the average income tax rateis now 20.6 per cent compared with 13.4 per cent in 1970-71 and 6.7 per cent ten yearsago; and the proportion of the working population paying income tax has risen to four-fifths compared with three-quarters in 1963-Economic effects of different types of public expenditure12.    The crude total of the public expenditure programmes plus debt interest cannotgive a complete picture of the impact of public expenditure on the economy, northerefore of the considerations which must be taken into account in considering thescale and distribution of necessary reductions.    The Chancellor explained the significance of different types of expenditure in relation to resources, taxation, andthe PSBR in his Cabinet paper for Chequers (C(75)87).   Annex D gives a breakdown ofpublic expenditure between goods and services; transfer payments; and acquisition ofexisting assets.   It also gives a similar breakdown of the totals of the categories of expenditure reductions mentioned later in this paper.13.    Expenditure in certain industrial fields is expected to increase very substantially over the next few years: for example, assistance to industry through theNEB and the Scottish and Welsh Development Agencies.   This expenditure is intended toensure that industrial investment does not fall short of estimated requirements.   insofar as these requirements are allowed for among the &quot;prior claims&quot; in Table 1, it should not reduce the level of &quot;free resources&quot; available for other public expenditure and personal consumption.   Other things being equal, the level of personal expenditure and the proportions publicly and privately financed should thus not be affected, butthere would be a full and direct effect on the borrowing requirement.1^.    Second, there are the costs of nationalisation measures which have essentially the same effect: aircraft, shipbuilding and ports nationalisation; participation in north Sea oil; and community ownership of land.   The community land proposals howeverwould significantly increase the public sector&apos;s demand for skilled (and scarce)manpower as well as having sizeable expenditure effects.Priorities15.    The main specific conclusions of the Chequers Cabinet discussion on public expenditure priorities were:-
a. that there should be greater selectivity in relation to expenditure on the social services;b. that housing investment, as distinct from housing subsidies should continue to have high priority;c. that a special attempt should be made to allocate extra resources to inner city areas;d. that a renewed effort should be made to reduce the manpower employedin central and local government administration.In addition, further studies, notably a review of the social services on the lines of jthe defence review, and an examination of methods of controlling local authoritycurrent expenditure, were commissioned but on a time scale which cannot affect theimmediate exercise.16.     From the point of view of the imperative need to secure large savings in theexpenditure programmes up to 1978-79 the only point at which these conclusionswould limit the room for manoeuvre is housing.   Housing expenditure has until recentlybeen almost entirely open-ended, as a matter of policy.   Some elements, includinglocal authority lending on mortgage, acquisition by &quot;municipalisation&quot; of existingproperty, and expenditure on improvements, have recently been made subject to limitsagreed between Treasury and housing Ministers.   Housing is one of the largest programme!and the major contributions to the necessary saving must inevitably come from theselarge programmes if adequate overall reductions are to be found.   Moreover, public expenditure on housing has shown an enormous expansion in the past 3 years.   Among theproposals is therefore the imposition of a limit on new building by local authorities,at a level below the existing estimate but high enough to avoid restricting thoselocal authorities who face the most serious housing needs, including those in inner-city areas.17.     As regards greater selectivity, this has two main implications.   The first isthe concentration of expenditure on those sectors of the population most in need, ratheithan the extension of general benefits and subsidies.   This approach is allowed forin the policy options, especially those for social security benefits.   The second isthat charges for social services should (apart from any remissions for the less well-off) meet a higher proportion of the cost: this affects, for example, school meals,prescription and other health charges, and council rents.
i8.    As regards the manpower requirements of central and local government, there isa conflict between the desire to reduce manpower employed in administration and theintroduction of greater selectivity.   Selectivity, whether in social or other fields,generally increases the administrative workload.   Administrative staff, along withother staff, would be cut in most programmes by a decision to implement the formulareductions on current expenditure on which the Survey has been based.   These reductions would apply with particular severity to programmes with a high proportion of staff such as,for example, education, health and the diplomatic service.Construction industry19.    The trough of the construction industry recession is expected this year withoutput below its 1973 peak.   Taking account of the reduced Survey figures, output isprojected to rise slowly from 1976-77 but to increase by 5 per cent in 1977-78 and by nearly 3 per cent in each of the last two years, reaching in 1979-80 a level marginallyabove 1973*   Decisions to implement the other options in the Survey or the further optionssuggested by the Treasury on housing investment or on roads would reduce this rate of growth and have consequences for employment.   There is also a risk that any further fall in output would reduce the industry&apos;s capacity to respond to an upturn in demandlater on, although against this it may be argued that given the heavy dependence onthe industry on the public sector it may need to adjust itself to some lower level of demand in any case.The issues for decision20.    The Survey report illustrates the effect of expenditure reductions in two ways.First, there are the formula reductions which are built into the Survey itself.   the impact of these reductions is described in the text of the Survey.   Second, in those areas (mostly transfer payments) not covered by the formula reductions, the reportindicates the policy options which, if adopted, would enable expenditure to be reduced below the Survey levels.   Both these categories are listed in Part 1 of the SurveyReport, the substance of which is reproduced in columns a and b of Annex B to this paper.21. r As stated above the Survey has been carried out on the basis that the implications of cuts of  2-^-3^ billion should be explored.   The formula reductions and the other policy options described in the Survey Report amount to  3.8- 4.1 billion and might bethought to provide a handsome margin, enabling some options to be dropped.   On the otherhand, because programmes have grown by some  1 billion since the exercise began, the
HM Treasury7 October 1975the formula cuts of  2.1 billion now leave privately financed consumption growing at only 1.3 per cent per annum with the taxation implications exhibited in paragraph 1\above.22.     When account is taken of the uncertainties of the economic prospects, includingthe uncertainty of the growth of resources over the period to 1978-79* the imperativeneed to make room for a reasonable growth of privately financed consumption and avoidan unacceptable increase in the tax burden, and also the desirability of getting public expenditure to a level which is more likely to be sustainable, there is a very strong case for seeking reductions at the top end of the range identified in the Survey, ie 3^ billion.   The greatly increased estimates of debt interest, about which there is admittedly much uncertainty, reinforce this case.23.     In the light of these considerations, it seems clear that in order to achieve the overall reductions which are required, it will be necessary to consider the formulareductions, except in any cases where it can be shown that they are simply not feasible,together with the widest possible range of other options.   For this purpose theTreasury propose that the list of policy options in the Survey, mainly compiled beforethe new developments described in paragraph       above were fully known, should beextended by the items shown in column c of Annex Bt and more fully described in the notes in that Annex.
Main changes in expenditure programmes since Cmnd 5879  million at 1975 Survey pricesBudget cutsBritish LeylandOther selective assistance to industryNational Enterprise Board(other than British Leyland)- provisional assumptionsScottish and Welsh DevelopmentAgencies - provisional assumptionsBritish National Oil CorporationGuaranteed price to AGP sugar refinersTemporary advances to sugar refiners - repaidwithin 197^-75 so no repayment now dueAgriculture; mainly CAP, including higher monetarycompensatory amounts (MRCA) and other estimatingNef^conffibutions to European Communities -mainly higher receipts from CAPSocial security estimating changes - mainlyeffect of Cmnd 6151Food subsidies announced in Cmnd 6151Housing subsidies announced in Cmnd 6151Nationalised industries:Increase in coal stocksInvestmentChange in shortfall deductionCompensation for nationalised industries&apos;price restraint (other than transport industries)Refinance of export credit - estimatingchangesChange since the Survey was completedNationalised industries - Economic PolicyCommittee decisions, including Budgetreduction1975-76260h5507100105150- 11290166150208531976-77- 1,000*70231513150068570801201.8131.5*Excluding the reduction made in nationalised industries capital expenditure which hadnot been allocated to specific industries when the Survey figures were finalised -see the final item in the table above.
SECRET(a)FormulaReductions**(b)policy options inSurvey1.    DEFENCEAccelerating Defence Review 123or   Application of &quot;Formula&quot;**The Ministry of Defence believe only 8501 could be achieved.2.    OVERSEAS AID AND OTHER OVERSEAS services   1 turns11 - 11 . .. 11  -   &apos;.. 1 . i! n1 ... ,, . 1        11.1 iii ,Reduction in growth rate of Aid Programme       kSClosure by 1978^79 of Embassies/^ighCommissions/Consular Offices and reduction in staff (home and abroad)slowing down Diplomatic Estatepurchasing and building programme 10,7Reduction in overseas information activities    4.7Reduction in military aid 0.3Reduction in grant-in-aid to CommonwealthWar Graves Commission 0*33.    AGRICULTURE f FISHERIES AND FORESTRYReduction of beef-cow and calf subsidies 11,6Administrative savings in other services 1.6Reduction in forestry programme 1.beef-cow subsidy terminated at next reviewSharper reduction in food subsidiesTRADE, INDUSTRY AND EMPLOYMENTSpread Scottish and Welsh DevelopmentAgencies expenditure over 6 yearsinstead of 5Cut Regional Development Grants by k: percentage pointsReduce expenditure on industrial innovationReduce Contributions to European Space AgencyIncrease minimum fixed rates for export credits4503013504M8(c)Further policy options suggestedby Treasury (seeexplanatory notesattached)See note (i)100(ii)*Except where otherwise stated, *h6?e an item appears in more than one column, thecosting in column b is additional to the savings in a; and the costing in c isadditional to that in the two preceding columns.secret
  million(1975(a)FormulaReductionsNATIONALISED INDUSTRIES (See Annex B)Post Office telecommunications investmentBritish Rail - See Roads and Transport belowROADS AND TRANSPORTMotorways and trunk roadsDelay in completing projects . .63Reduce value of new starts in 1976-77 &quot;and 1977-78Local Authority roads -&quot;&apos;Reduction in local road improvements .66Reduce new starts in 1976-77 and1977-78Road maintenance - - ;Reduction in standards 78Further 10%.reduction in local road - :-.....maintenanceLocal authority transport administrationAsk local authorities to cut back topre-reorganisation levelBuses . ,Reconsider 50% grantCar Parks: increase chargesBritish RailReductions in subsidies and investmentprogrammesCivil Aviation Authority: reduce grantrequirements by charging full cost foren route navigationHOUSINGSubsidies o;-&apos; ,      ,.Reduction applied to 1977-78 and following years 78Reduction by additional rent increases of.........about 30p per week on top of cost;of.living rises \ -^v-        w,..,,711026(iii)30(iv)33(v )1110(vi)(vii)i/t0(viii)S E C R E, T(b) ^      (c)Policy      n Pol^yOptions in   C*fcl?BB Su^teoSurvey       by Treasury (seeexplanatory notesattached)
SubsidiesFurther rent increases on top of those in col (b) (making rent increase in (b) and (c) about 23$)Capital expenditure1976-77 cuts on localauthorities&apos; mortgage lendingcontinued into later yearsReduction in house buildingapprovals by 11,000 a yearFurther reductions in approvals(making total reductions incols (b) and (c) of 27,000)Increased sales of localauthority and New Town housesReduction in l.a. mortgagelending, municipalisationand improvement investment(a)FormulaReductions(b)policy options inSurveyFurther policy options suggestedby Treasury52124246.124(ix)176(x )150(xi )8.    OTHER ENVIRONMENTAL SERVICESMaintenance of basic water and sewerage services only106Reduced standards and increased charges for supporting facilitiesfor new housing and environmental services        148Cut environmental research expenditureCommunity land scheme:-Impose a limit of  100 million onacquisitionProceed no further with legislation &apos; \   &apos;3510(xii .)or__^ 13r,(xiii)secret- .
(a)FormulaReductions(b)policy options inSurvey9.     LAW AND ORDERPrisons - smaller increases in staff and reduction in buildingprogramme39Probation - smaller increases in staff and new hostelsPolice - reduction in capitalexpenditurek9Fire - restriction of manpower and capital expenditureNo new Urban Programme projects203Home Office staff - 1900 less thanin Cmnd 5879Reduction in courts capital expenditure        12Reduction in jury size from 12to 10 persons   1Withdraw legal aid from some classes of divorcecases 110.   EDUCATION(a) . England and WalesNo expansion from 1976-77 of provision for under-fives 40Severe restriction on non-teaching costs      67No further reduction after 1975-76 inSECRETifFurther PoliJOptions suggest!by Treasury f
(a)FormulaReductions(contd  .,.)Increases in school meal chargesReduction in school building programme, except &quot;basic needs&quot;.Reduction in staff/standards and provision for higher and further education - consequently not meetingestimated full demand from qualifiedapplicants.    Intake to Open Universityseverely limited.&apos;Increase in higher and further education feesReduction in expenditure on locallibrariesk661196&quot;17Ik(b)ScotlandSlower expansion of provision for under-fivesEeduction in non-teaching costs andslower improvement after 1975-76 instaffing standards-;.Reduction in school building programmeReduction in staffing- standards and provision for higher and furthereducationReduction in expenditure on locallibraries362131(c)Great BritainReduction of provision for non-advanced further education to 96% of that envisaged in Cmnd 5879 *Slower development of in-service trainingof teachersIncrease the school meal charge by 7p insteadof 5p in September 1977 ;Hold student numbers- in higher education tothe level achieved for 1976-77Further increases in fees.-- v&apos;.Overseas students - increase to 50% ofeconomic costEvening classes , -v^-^&apos;includes UGC expenditure in Scotland. &quot;&quot;&quot;(b)policy options inSurvey(c)Further policy options suggestedby TreasurySECRET10(xiv)i6(xv )n(xvi )17(xvii )25(xiii).(xix)
  million saving in 1978-79(1975 Survey prices)(a)FormulaReductions11.     HEALTH AND PERSONAL SOCIAL SERVICESHospitals and community health services:Current 320.capital 64.other Health Services 7.5Personal Social Services 68.1Services for the disabled 2.6Increase in prescription charges12.     SOCIAL SECURITYUprating long-term benefits in line with prices instead of earningsor    Uprating long-term benefits by morethan prices but less than earningsor    Uprating long-term supplementary benefit alone in line with pricesUprating in line with current insteadof historical movement of earnings and .pricesRaising pension age 1 yr for men andwomenor     for women aloneCancel further increases in earnings rulefor pensionersPostpone child benefit scheme( 115-145 million in 1977-78)Increase from 3 to 6 waiting days forunemployment and sickness benefitNo/employment benefit for first 6 days offUnemployment Benefit- restricted for those with substantial occupationalpensionsRemove or restrict students&apos; supplementary benefit entitlementDefer new invalidity benefits due in 1976( 2m in 1976-77 and  l8m in 1977-78)Abolish maternity grantAbolish death grant(b)policy options inSurvey*Maximum figures.20*21410753508111197460191719*14Further PolifOptions suggestiby Treasury (selexplanatory notiattached)15(xx )SECRET.6
OTHER PUBLIC SERVICESIncrease in minimum purchases ofPremium Bonds and national savings Certificates and reduction in support staffReduction of expenditure on centralCivil Service administration,recruitment and trainingCuts in broadcasting capital progs.No improvement in statistical basis for social services planning andfewer surveys for Government Depts.Registration of electors every l8months instead of 12(a)FormulaReductions0.71.86.10.90.7(b)policy options inSurvey(c)Further policy options suggestedby Treasury (seeexplanatory notesattached)COMMON: SERVICESReduction in capital expenditure 22.8Reduced HMSO provisions 6.9Savings in Civil Service Cateringand Computer projects 6.2Economies in Publicity Programme l.kNORTHERN IRELANDReduced expenditure on housinghealth and educationReduced expenditure by NorthernIreland Office on Law and Order517TOTALS; (rounded)20701700-20001070SECRET- ,7   . -,(
SECRET8NOTES ON ITEMS IN COLUMN (c) - OPTIONS SUGGESTED BY THE TREASURYDEFENCE(i )     In the ground rules for the 1975 Survey, in the light of earlier reductions in defence expenditure following the Defence Review, the Defence Budget figures were not required to comply with the standard formula percentage reductions(though an indication was to be given by the effect of applying comparable reductions to defence); instead they were to comply with the Cabinet decision to initiatedetailed studies to attempt to accelerate the savings resulting from the defence review.   However, since the Defence Review decisions were taken, our economicsituation has deteriorated and we are faced with the imperative need to curtail allpublic expenditure programmes.   In this situation, when so many desirable features ofother programmes will have to be foregone, defence is bound to have to make a very substantial contribution to the savings that are needed.   The options should therefore include the application of the full formula percentage reductions to theDefence Budget, ie a cut of  ^50 million in 1978-79*   The precise means of achievingthese reductions would need to be considered and reported on urgently by theMinistry of Defence.AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FORESTRY(ii) The option.in the Survey Report is intended to reduce the food subsidyprogramme by 1979-80 to a residual amount to cover mainly subsidies which attractFEOGA money as well as involving a UK Exchequer contribution.   The new Treasuryoption would advance the run-down in the programme by one year to 1978-79.ROADS AND TRANSPORT(iii) Motorways and Trunk Roads - ConstructionThe formula cut in England was reduced by  20m (at the expense chiefly of LA road maintenance - see below) in order to protect to some extent the D0E&apos;s road programme.The restoration of this cut of  20m will delay the completion of the 3100 milenetwork of high-quality roads until the late 1980&apos;s.   It may affect the road construction industry.
SECRET ANNEX BThe Scottish and Welsh programmes were hardly protected from the formula cuts.This further cut will delay completion of the Central Scotland Motorway and the welsh Kk.   Oil-related roads in Scotland will however again bo completely protected.(iv) Local Authority Roads - ConstructionThese cuts, in addition to the formula cuts, would delay new schemes,particularly perhaps the larger ones since the very small ones are carried out  bythe LA&apos;s direct labour forces.   The cuts Mould not affect the provision for oil-related roads in Scotland, but that provision is considered insufficient and thereduction for non-oil related roads may induce LAs to cut back on oil-related roadsinstead.(v )   Local Authority Roads - maintenance in England this item suffered more than its share of the formula cuts, and DOEconsider that any further large reduction would have such a destructive effecton  the roads that much higher expenditure would be needed subsequently to restore them the proposed further cut, however, provided it lasted only two-or three years,might be tolerable without such effects.   90$.of the work is done by LA direct-labour forces, so that redundancies there would result.   In Scotland and Wales theapplication of the formula cuts has not been so severe, but the cost per mile ofmaintenance is already lower than in England. - The proposed further cut would havesimilar effects.(vi )Local Authority AdministrationThis is the transport element of LA admiriistrationn   The LAs are already being askedto hold their total manpower level; and their transport expenditure is expected to decline; so this modest cut seems reasonable provided there is similar treatment    forother services.(vii ) Local Authority Car Parks in EnglandDOE thinkthat the net income already in PES is optimistic, and that an increase would necessitate a relaxation of the Price Code (even then cars might switchto the private &quot;National Car Parks&quot; in many places).(viii)British RailThe provision for subsidies to BR passenger services of  326 million in 1975-76rising to  391 million in 1978-79 has alraady been overtaken by events.   On therV*V&quot;ITVf?rtl
SECRET ANNEX i;one hand the Board expect to lose  60 million on freight in 1975-76 not cateredfor in the above figures.   On the other paseenger subsidies now appear likely&apos;to be about  JO million less than provision   Furthermore Ministers have setobjectives of holding passenger subsidies in 1976-77 to the 1975-76 real leveland. of eliminating the freight loss.&quot;  If these objectives are met and passenger subsidies continued to be held without growth a saving of  90 million in 1978-79 would result.In so far as rail costs rise faster than prices generally and because scope for refare increases appears to be rapidly diminishing DOE consider that a saving of&amp;ih3 million would entail major withdrawals of services and cuts in investment.The scale and practicability of such cuts is under study but. firm conclusions arenot yet available.HOUSING(ix) Housing SubsidiesArguments against:(a) the announcement of two successive substantial rent increases of about 1.30 in money terms would lead to inflationary pressure, despite the availability of rent rebates, and might risk strong hostility both among localauthorities and among the general p\iblic, which v/ould react against the government&apos;s counter-inflationary policy.(b) Legislation would be required, in effect imposing rent control of a nature which, it would be argued, would be considerably harsher than thatimposed by the 1972 Housing Finance Act, which the Government has justrepealed in fulfilment of an electoral promise.(c) It would be necessary to make such an announcement, which would apply only to public sector housing, in advance of the conclusion of the housing finance Review.   It is one of the objectives of that Review, due to becompleted in the spring of 1976, to recomaand a series of measures which wotfmake the housing finance system more equitable as between &quot;different tenures,and particularly as between owner-occupiers and tenants.   An announcement, that local authority rents were to be steeply increased, would be regarded a:greatly inequitable.Arguments in favours(a)   Housing expenditure has risen very fast in the last two years, and ministers agreed at the Chequers meeting that subsidies should be reduced;10
(b) Substantial subsidies artificially stimulate demand for housing,in the same way that subsidies to the nationalised industries stimulate thedemand for their products.   A sharp reduction in subsidies is a necessarystep towards a better use of the existing housing stock and a more rationalhousing policy.(c) An. announcement now would herald a firm intention to get subsidies downover the next few years so that rents meet a. more reasonable proportion(say 55 per cent, compared with the present 43 per cent) of housing costs.(x ) New House BuildingArguments against:(a) Ministers agreed at Chequers that housebuilding should continue tohave high priority within the housing programme;(b) under the economic conditions now foreseen, private sector housing startsmay well continue at a low level;(c) it could do serious long-term damage to the house building industry.Arguments in favour:(a) the present public sector total (165*000) is much langer than the averageof the last five years (115,000) and, together with the subsidies to existingstock, is costing some  2,000 million a year; it is therefore difficult to make substantial cuts in housing expenditure without reducing new investment;(b) although locally, there are undoubtedly bad housing problems the nationalposition is of an excess of dwellings over households.If the size of reduction is considered too great, an alternative additional optionwould be to take a further  50 million from the municipalisation, improvement andlocal authority mortgage lending group of items for which a reduction of  246 million is discussed as an option in the PESO Report.(xi )Increased sales of public sector housesIt would be possible, by encouraging local authorities and New Town development corporations to sell to sitting tenants, to increase gross receipts by a further 150 million over the currently assumed level of about  45 million.SECRET. 11
The net effect on public expenditure would depend on the extent to which localauthorities or the building societies financed the purchases by sitting tenants.In the past local authorities have normally lent about 80 per cent of the purchase price.   But it might be possible to put to building societies a proposition for takingon at least a part of this lending themselves.OTHER ENVIRONMENTAL SERVICES(xii ) Cut environmental research expenditureExpenditure has increased sharply in recent years on the DOE*s research establishments(on roads, buildings and hydraulics), the extra-mural research programme and grants to research associations and other bodies.   From  12^ million in 1970-71 it has risen to 22^ million in 197^-75 and  30 million in 1975-76.   The Survey estimates for subsequent years, at about  33 million a year, imply a substantial reduction in plans for continued expansion.   However, a further saving of  10 million could be effected in 1978-79 without reducing spending below the level reached in 197^-75.(xiii)Community Land SchemeThere is a danger, on the one hand, that implementation of this scheme will produce an initial cost rising above the estimated  137 million for 1978-79; and on the otherhand that to hesitate now to implement it would produce uncertainty in the land market an;reduce the flow of land for house building.The first danger could be met by fixing a limit to borrowing by local authorities forland purchase.   Col (b) goes further by proposing a limit at a reduced level.The second danger could be met by coupling such a restriction with a much lower rateof Development Land Tax than the 80 per cent envisaged at present, so as to lessen the disincentive to private sales; or by announcing that the legislation would not becarried through.   The latter is reflected in col (c).   But to proceed as in col (c)would mean abandoning the Community Land Bill which is now near enactment, andcountermanding the introduction of the Development Land Tax Bill parts of which were published in draft in August.EDUCATION(xiv)Non-advanced Further education the Survey assumes an increase in the level of demand in line with recent experience,before going on to the conclusion that this higher demand cannot be fully met.   A more severe constraint - arbitrarily chosen - would be to require local authorities to meetonly 96 per cent of the Cmnd 5879 forecast demand.    But this may block a possible aeansof relieving the unemployment situation, and reduce the output of technically trainedpeople.
(xv ) In-service training ..o&quot;f teachers.Hie ultimate aim is to provide one term&apos;s training every seven years to keep teachersup to date and induction training for all new entrants, but progress towards the objectives has already been slowed down and could be slowed by local authorities by afurther year.   DES Ministers do however attach more importance to this service than egreducing class sizes, regarding this retraining as the more necessary with a reducedintake of newly trained teachers in order to avoid staleness and rigidity.(xvi ) School meal charge the cash increases required by the Survey formula are, the successive annual intervalsfrom 1976, 5p, 5pt 8p and 10p.   The proposal changes the sequence to 5p, 7pi 8p and 10p,thus adding 2p from September 1977i which would bring in about an extra  9 million in1978-79.   The proportion of the expected cost of school meals met from public funds would then be 32 per cent instead of the 35 per cent postulated in the Survey.(xvii ) Student numbersThis would be a further departure from the &quot;Robbins principle&quot; (by providing for about91 per cent of the qualified demand in 1978-79.(xvii i)Further increases in feesThe Survey report envisaged a saving of  22^ million from increasing fees.   The further increase would bring fees for overseas students to some four times their present levels(but still only about half the full cost).   There are diplomatic and educationarguments against such a big increase, but the case against subsidy is also strong andthe figures allow for increased provision under the aid programme for students from less developed countries.(xix)The Survey incorporated an increase in fees for evening classes, which thisproposal might double.   These fees are levied by local authorties and would need to betaken into account in settlements of rate support grant.SOCIAL SECURITYUx)  Abolition of death grant a death grant of between  9 and  30 is payable when a National Insurance contributoror his wife or child dies.   The money goes to the executor or to the relation who paysfor the funeral; the average cost of a funeral is now about  130.   The abolitionof  this contributory benefit, which at present goes to about 500,000 people each y*ar,would require legislation.   Supplementary benefit claimants who are responsible for thefuneral expenses of close relations would continue to be eligible for help withfuneral expenses.SECRET
ANNEX   CNationalised industries&apos; capital expenditure the nationalised industry programmes have been reviewed in the Ministerial Committeeon Economic Policy.   Ministers agreed that programmes for 1976/77 should be reducedby  125 million in accordance with the Budget Statement; this has not yet been takeninto account in the Survey figures (see paragraph 13 and Table C in Part 1 of theReport).Ministers also decided that &amp;5% and 70% of the programmes for 1977/78 and 1978/79respectively should be authorised except in the case of Railways and Telecommunications.Approval to commit 70$ of the British Railways programme in 1977/78 was agreed.   Thelimits for telecommunications are to be further examined bearing in mind that there isto be a review of future strategy.In hie paper EC(75)40 the Chief Secretary proposed reductions in the programmes forBritish Rail and telecommunications for the years from 1977-78 onwards which wouldresult in level programmes of  218 million and  809 million respectively from 1976/77.These proposals remain for consideration; and so does a final decision whether to approve the total programmes for the other nationalised industries for 1977/78 and beyond as they emerged from the review.SECRET
ECONOMIC ANALYSIS OF SURVEYPROGRAMMES AND OF FORMULA REDUCTIONS/POLICY OPTIONS1978-79  million 1975 Survey Prices	Goods ana Services	Trans fers	Acquisitions	TotalSurvey programmes before formula cuts	29153	17710	73k	^7597Formula reductions	1653	337	76	2066Policy options described in survey	695	969-1222	71	1735-1988Further policy options proposed by the Treasury	483	357	230	1070SECRET


</content>
</cab>
