<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/46/19 images: 162-166</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.       gjIt is issued for the personal use of.........S.ss^i*htff^..............Copy No.....?T.....TOP l-*W8T SECRET.W.M.(ijij.) 82ND CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE confidential Annex(27th June, 19W4- - 6 p.m.)AIR RAIDSim til(previous reference:W,M.(ii4)80thConclusions,Minute k)AttacksPlyingBombs.byftThe War Cabinet had before them -(i) a Note by the Home Secretary and Ministerof Home Security (W.P.(hh) 343) covering .reports by the Research and ExperimentsDepartment of the Ministry of home security, summarising the informationcollected by the Department on the subjectof flying &quot;bombs up to 20th June,     and(ii) a Memorandum by the Home Secretary and minister of Home Security (W.P.(kk) 348)on the flying bomb and the rocket.In the course of discussion the followingpoints of an operational character were raised the CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF gave the WarCabinet Information about the measures which were beingtaken to counter the flying bomb attacks.     The supreme commander had instructed that measures against the flying bomb should have first priority after the needsof the battle in France had been met. . Adequate numbersof fighters were available and everything possible wasbeing done to improve their performance, to secure atoettej? system of control and to train fighter   pilotsin high speed&apos;interception.     The deployment of anti-aircraft guns originally proposed was being substantially increased and the training of the gun crews was being pressed on.     When the full deployment had been carriedout, the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, Anti-Aircraft Command, was satisfied that a heavy toll wouldbe taken by the guns.     The arrangements for co-ordinating the use of guns and fighters had been improved,   ^uringthe day time the guns would fire so long as it was clearthat no fighter was within range.     At night the guns and fighters would each have belts allocated to them..y   the aim was to bring the deployment of balloons up to 1,750which should take a considerable toll, perhaps up to 20per cent.     It was hoped to make further improvements inthe detection of flying bomb sites by radar.     attacks on the launching sites and supply depots continued andintruder patrols were maintained over the areas where the sites were located.     Every effort was being made byreconnaissance to detect new sites.     Generally, it seemed clear that a very considerable improvement in the defences could be expected, but it had to be recognisedthat the scale of attack might well go up.     In particular the modified sites could be made or repaired very quickly and were difficult to identify.

THE JOINT PARLIAMENTARY SECRETARY TO THEMINISTRY OP SUPPLY summarised the position in regardto the, prospect of attacks &quot;by rocket. ,  There was agood deal of evidence to show that the enemy had   ,produced rockets and meant to use them as soon aspossible.,O - &apos;The War Cabinet were Informed that of the seven large sites which-were suspected to be rocketlaunching sites, two had been captured in theCherbourg area and a third had been abandoned.Although the remaining four had been frequentlyattacked, no guarantee could be given that they couldnot be used.     Once the rocket sites had been coveredover it was&quot; difficult to penetrate the concretecovering.     Nevertheless, by attacking the. approaches to the sites it might be possible to put them out ofaction for the time being.1 In discussion THE PAYMASTER GENERAL saidthat the production of a rocket on the scale suspectedwould be extremely uneconomical.     It did not follow,however, that the enemy.would not adopt this form of attack.     It might be that the large sites were designed for a larger type of pilotless aircraft,although the ease with which such a. weapon could be shot down suggested that this possibility was unlikely.With regard to the possibilities mentionedin the memorandum toy the Home Secretary (w*P.^Uh)3^8)THE PRIME MINISTER said that it was clear that every-thing possible was toeing done to attack the launchingsites and sources of production and transportation^and intruder patrols were toeing flown over the areas where the sites were located.     It seemed doubtfulwhether any help could toe derived from naval toomtoard-ment and the enemy1s dispositions ruled out thepossibility of Commando raids. xSome discussion ensued on the question of reprisals, mentioned in the Home secretary Memorandum.Summing up the discussion on this point,   THE PRIMEMINISTER said that for the present it would be unwise to threaten reprisals, but the matter might have tobe considered later, in the light of the coursetaken toy the enemy *s attacks.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1.



</content>
</cab>
