<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/45/19 images: 218-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1944.W.P. (44) 19.10th January,,1944.SECRET. / Copy No.war CABINET.THE POSITION IN YUGOSLAVIA.Memorandum by Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.MY colleagues have seen the Prime Ministers telegrams to me, Nos. 1184and 1187 Frozen, and my telegrams to him, Nos. 1240 and 1241 Grand, to whichhe refers;2. From this exchange of telegrams it will be apparent that the PrimeMinister proposes to send to Tito, by the hand of Brigadier Maclean, the headof our military mission to the Partisans, a letter, the text of which is given inthe annex to this paper, in answer to a message from Tito wishing him recoveryfrom his illness. It will be apparent also that our common object is to find abridge over the gulf at present separating King Peter from the Partisans, butthat, in the Prime Minister&apos;s view, there is little hope of building this bridgeuntil the King has cut himself free from Mihailovic.3. It may be useful at this point to present a brief explanation of the back-ground of the Yugoslav problem in order that my colleagues may be able to appre-associate the relevant factors in the situation. (I4. King Peter is the legitimate sovereign of Yugoslavia, who was entrusted with full powers as a reigning monarch, though still a minor, when in March 1941the pro-Ally cowp cVEtat took place which led to the German invasion of Yugo-slavia, the defeat of the Yugoslav forces and the flight of the King and his Govern-ment, to whom we gave refuge in London. The Yugoslav Government of thecoup d&apos;Etat which started by being representative of all three peoples of theTriune Kingdom Serbs, Croats and Slovenes with a predominance of Serbs,since it was the Serbs who were responsible for the coup d&apos;Etat, has, owing to a .series of futile dissensions, become less and less representative of the country asa whole and now consists of a Government of officials in Cairo. We are morallybound to continue to recognise King Peter and whatever Government he appoints. \5. In Yugoslavia, on the other hand, there are, apart from the Quisling,Governments of Pavelic in Croatia and Nedic in Serbia, two resistance move--ments, that led by Mihailovic in Serbia proper and the Partisans elsewhere.Mihailovic is Minister of War in the Yugoslav Government in Cairo. his forces, numbering some 15,000, are of little value to the war effort as Mihailovicis now mainly taken up with the &quot; Communist &quot; menace which he feels is represented by the Partisans and there is evidence that in his hatred of com-communism he is willing to accept assistance from the Nedic Quisling faction andeven from the Germans. Some of his followers; however, may be willing toco-operate with the Partisans. The Partisans, on the other hand, have a formidable organised army of perhaps 200,000 men whose principal effort is undoubtedly directed against the Germans. We are giving full military support to the Partisans and little or no support to Mihailovic, as he is not fighting theGermans.6. I was considering in December a plan to persuade the King to throw overMihailovic, whose continuance as Minister of War was a standing obstacle to any chance of uniting the contending factions, when on the 17th December &quot; Free !Yugoslavia&quot; radio, which is situated on Soviet territory, broadcast a claim for political recognition on behalf of the administration which Tito has set up in12246   [26705]
Yugoslavia under the title of Anti-Fascist Council of National Liberation, andalso attacks on the King and the Yugoslav Government in Cairo. The gulfbetween the King and the increasingly important Partisan movement was clearlywidening. I therefore proposed that the head of our military mission to the partisans should try to find out from Tito whether there was any possibility ofa modus vivendi between the Partisans and the King. If the King were toproceed to Yugoslavia and set up a new Government there in which the Partisanswould be represented this would give Tito the political recognition which hedesires and would solve our present dilemma of reconciling our political obliga-tions to the King and his Government with the military necessity of continuing to support Tito. An attempt to reconcile the King and Tito would be inaccordance with the professed wishes of the Soviet Government, who have told us that they want to find a means of bringing together the Partisans on the one handand the King and the Yugoslav Government on the other.7. It is worthy of note that the Soviet Government recognise the yugoslav government, to whom they recently accredited a representative, and have informed us that they intend to send a military mission to Mihailovic. I mayadd that, according to President Benes, the Soviet Governments attitude towardsthe Yugoslav problem is very reserved.8. This brings me to the exchange of telegrams with the Prime Ministerwhich I am circulating. We are both anxious to bring about an understanding between the King and the Partisans, but he feels that this can best be promotedif the King dismisses Mihailovic straight away in view of the known antipathywhich Tito has for Mihailovic and of the feeling among the Partisans that the monarchy is compromised by the King&apos;s continued association with Mihailovicand the Pan-Serb elements represented by Mihailovic and the yugoslav government in Cairo.   There is much to be said for this view.I have, however, inclined to the opinion that if the King were to get rid ofMihailovic before there is any guarantee that Tito is willing to accept him theKing will have sacrificed his last remaining link with Yugoslavia and willprobably in addition alienate quite a substantial section of opinion in Serbia,where the chief support for the monarchy resides. It might in these circum-stances be preferable to await the outcome of the Prime Minister&apos;s letter to Titoand of the attempts to bring about an understanding between the latter andthe King. If these were to be successful and the King were to go to Yugoslaviahe could then appeal to his Serbian supporters to co-operate with the Partisansand Mihailovic would then be got rid of at that stage on the ground that he was an impediment to Yugoslav unity. If we press the King to get rid of Mihailovicnow we shall need conclusive evidence of his treachery, and I have not yet received the evidence which is being collated in Cairo. Moreover, a breach withMihailovic will certainly attract a great deal of attention, and there is a danger that he will be represented as having been sacrificed by us in order to please theSoviet Government, with whom and with the United States Government I wouldin any case have liked to have kept in step in this matter. Finally, if the Kingwere to dismiss Mihailovic now the latter would probably maintain that the king was not a free agent and might refuse to acknowledge the decision, moreparticularly as it is impossible to summon him out of Yugoslavia and thendismiss him. The safety of our liaison officers in Mihailovic territory might alsobe endangered.A. E.Foreign Office, 10th January, 1944.
ANNEX.Text of Prime Minister&apos;s Letter as modified by Frozen 1057.Sir,I thank you very much for your kind message about my health from yourselfand the heroic Patriot and Partisan Army of Yugoslavia. From Major Deakin,who is a friend of mine, I learnt all about your valiant efforts. It is my mostearnest desire to&quot; give you all aid in human power by sea supplies, by air support and by Commandos to help you in the island fighting. Brigadier Maclean is alsoa friend of mine and a colleague in the House of Commons. With him at yourheadquarters will soon be serving my son, Major Randolph Churchill, who isalso a Member of Parliament. One supreme object stays before us, namely, tocleanse the soil of Europe from the filthy Nazi-Fascist taint. You may be sure that we British have no desire to dictate the future government of Yugoslavia.At the same time, we hope that all will pull together as much as possible for the defeat of the common foe and afterwards settle the form of government inaccordance with the will of the people. I am resolved that the British Govern-ment shall have no further dealings with Mihailovic, and we should be glad ifthe Royal Yugoslav Government would dismiss him from their counsels.King Peter II, however, escaped as a boy from the treacherous clutches of theRegent Prince Paul and came to us as the representative of Yugoslavia and as a young Prince in distress. It would not be chivalrous or honourable for GreatBritain to cast him aside, nor can we ask him to cut off all his existing contacts with his country. I hope, therefore, that you will understand that, in any case,we shall remain in official relations with him and his Government, while at thesame time giving you all possible military support. I hope also that there maybe an end to polemics on either side, for these only help the Germans. You m.&amp;be sure that I shall work in. the closest contact with my friends Marshal Stalinand President Roosevelt, and I earnestly hope the British and Soviet delegations to your headquarters may work in similar harmony. Please correspond with methrough Brigadier Maclean and let me know anything you think I can do to help,for I will certainly try my best. Looking forward to the. end of your sufferingsand to the liberation of Europe from tyranny, believe me,Yours faithfully,WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.






</content>
</cab>
