<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/107/0 images: 124-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
FOR INFORMATION. *  - 76(THIS DOCTfihNT I&quot; THI- PBOgSRTYJF HI^ BRITANNIC ,KAtHSTYtS[ OQvriRNlCNTj.SECR^. .   CABIII^T;CP. 1416. LEAGUE   0?   NATIONS.- .&apos;PHRHAPISNT ADVISORY COMMISSION FOR iUL ITARY, ,NAVAL AND ATR QTgSTION^,Resolutions adopted by the Council of the League of -Nations meeting in Rome on 19th ^,:g 19D0. .ffygylptts Papers i^l*iua92fi^ 1$ *l 13Q7AArticle 1.- The Commission prescribed by Article IX of the Covenant shall be entitled;   &quot;The Permanent Adviaory Commission for Military, Naval and Air Questions..&quot;    The Commission shall be formed of representatives from each nation represented on the Council of the League jvs follows:-1 military representative! 1 naval representative-, 1 air representative.The same representative may combine the duties of more than oneof the above, If his Government so desires.Article J3v- Any other States which are Members of the Leaguemay be invited to send a similar number of representatives to sit on the Commission temporarily when a question directly affecting-them is under discussion^.-Article 3.- Whatever the number of representatives from any nation attending the Meetings of the Commission, or of the Sub-Commissions referred to In Article 6.. no national delegation shallbe allowed more than one vote.roeg^e&apos;/ ;a.-&apos;veeh.&apos;   .        &apos;-&apos;&quot; -:g.aArticle 4The representatives laid down In Article 1 may be joined by such number of officers as may be necessary according to circumstances, or may call in any &quot;Service&apos;1 or civil experts whose experience may be useful.     In order-, however, to facilitate the
accommodation of the Oormnission, the Governments concerned are recommended not to attach more than two officers for each of the Sub-Commitaions laid down In Article 6. as permanent-assistants of the above-mentioned, representatives.Article 5a- The representatives of each State,&apos;together with the officers permanently attached, shall constitute the &quot;national delegation&quot; of each state     This delegation shall be placed at the disposal of the Come 11 cf the League in order to give advice as Is id down in Article IX of the Covenant, and in accordance with the procedure given below.The ordinary pay and allowances of the officers of the Commission will be furnished by their respective Governments.Article 6.- The Commission shall be divided into threo.Sub-Commissions, entitled:The Military Sub-Commission,The Naval Sub-Oommission, The Air Sub-Commission^Article 7.^ Eaoh Sub-Commission shall nominate a chairman for six months in the alphabetical order following that of the Treaty of Versailles,.When a meeting, cf the Commission is necessary, tho three chairmen of the Sub-Commissions shall select one of their number to preside at the sitting (or sittings) at which any particular question is to be discussed/,Article 8.- Representatives of a State which has been newly admitted to the Cou uc i .L c f the Lean,ue shall net be called to the chairmanship of the Cor,C!&apos;iss3cr: or Cu&apos;b-Commissions before six months have elapsed from the date of admission.Article 9.,- The Commission or Sub-Commissions shall meet on the demand either of the Council of the League or of one of their own members.Article 10.- In principle, reports of the Sub-Commissions shall be forwarded to the Council by the full&apos; Commission with its rcmar3cs.   The Council or the full Commission may, however&apos;,&apos; decide
that a. question raised by either, respectively, is of a purely technical nature^ and within the competence of one Sub-Commission onlye    In such case. the report of the Sub^Ccmmisalon shall be addressed to .the Council direct.- .Article. 11.- Representatives who a re absent&quot;, - or who are prevented from attending, may depute an assistant to represent thorn a- Article 12.- The secretarial work of the Commission shall be carried cut by three technical officers(an army officer for the Military Sub-Commission, a naval officer for the Naval Sub-Commission, an air officer for the Air Sub-Comriisalon) *   These officers shall be nominated by the Secretary-General and placed by him at the disposal of the.three Sub-OommissIcnSo   Together, these officers- will form the secretariat of the whole Commission^The Secretaries shall, as a rule, be appointed for one year, and may, at the wish of a Sub-Commission, be continued In their appointments for poripds of six months, provided that the total duration of such an appointment shall not exceed three years aThe remuneration of the secretariat and all expenses connected with it shall be met by the League of Nations,,.NOTE.- In order to promote- co-operation and to facilitate the exchange of information as- laid down in Article VIII of the Covenant of the League, it is desirable that the technical ex-parts (military, naval and air) should- be accommodated in the same building, or in buildings situated as closely as possible to each other0 .   ..&apos;.      11/ -  . -    .      ....The Council of the -League of Nations instructs, the Permanent Advisory-Commission for Military, Naval and Air Questions -to begin immediately the.study of such technical questions as are required for the execution of Articles I and VIII of the Covenant, and in particular:-;(1) To consider end draft regulations in accordance with
Article I of the Covenant in regard to the military., naval and air for roc and arraames&amp;s cf the follow inq States. whioh have applied for admission to the League:-Esthtnian Republic, Republic of Georgia, Iceland, Luxemburg^Republic of San Marino, Ukrainian republic and to forward a report to the Council on this subjooto(2)-To request the Governments signatories of the Aims TraffConvention of 10th September; 1919; and ether States Members cfthe League, to furnish all neoessary information regarding theexport of arms and munitions, in aocordanoe with the principles laid down in Article 23, paragraph (d) sf the Arms TrafficConvention, including the final proteocl, and to submit to theCouncil proposale for the formation cf a Central InternationalOffice.,2,, Whitehall Gardens. S^U June 7th, 1920*1   I.       .. -II     .T-I   I..     .      &apos; i -,, ,      .....

</content>
</cab>
