<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/107/0 images: 150-150</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE property OE HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT) .COPY NO.    jLSECRET. CP.1425.&quot; C A E I N E T.TRAINI-JO OF FIT EX-SERVICE MEN. Memorandum by the Chancellor&apos; of the Exchequer.1. I am completely opposed to the proposals put forward bythe Minister cf Labour on this subject In his memorandum (CP. 1.315) and I am doubtful whether the estimate of cost given in the offi-cial letter from the Ministry of Labour to the Treasury (a copy of &apos;,which is circulated with the memorandum) (CP.1515A) repre-cents the true measure of the expenditure which would ultimate-ly be involved.   It is assumed in that letter that 40,000 men would be concerned and that the period during which the trainees should be in receipt of full maintenance allowance (average 65s. a week) would be nine months; on this basis the cost of the scheme is calculated at  6,000,000.2. I fully realise the extreme difficulty of framing esti-mates In such a case, but I believe the figure mentioned is mucrfc too low.   That is the common experience with such training schemes.The cost of the training of disabled men was put orig-inally at  3^00,000 but the estimate now stands at  21,000,000 as the cost of training some 75,000 men.    (For technical reasons the two figures of six atid twenty-one millions are not strictly corn-parable but there is nc doubt as to the immense growth over the original figure.)    Similarly the sum provided (again  6,000,000) for training ex-officers at Universities etc. has been very great-ly exceeded.It is important to note that, as regards the scheme for training disabled men, much of tho excess over the original esti-metes has resulted from the substitution of training in Government Instructional Factories in large part for training in Employers1 Works (and in Technical Schools) .   A similar assumption - that training can be carried out in the main in employers&apos; workshops is now made in connection with the training of fit men.Moreover the estimate. of&apos; th^ number o*&quot; men to be trained appears to be very low, considering the vast number of demobilised men who belong to semi-skilled and unskilled trades and who of course greatly outnumber the disabled men.   A large proportion have found employment but nevertheless the number In receipt of out of work donation is still over 200,000 and,, in any period of temporary unemployment, many who had previously found work in their old trade would be greatly attracted by the training scheme3, It does not appear that the scheme oan be confined to semi-skilled trades and if once the principle were admitted I should not feel confident that the schema would prove loss costly than the present schema for training disabled men, now estimated at upwardo of 21 millions.     I consider that the schema must be ruled out completely on the ground of the prohibitive cost entailed.(Initialled)   A.C. Treasury, S.Y;. 1  &apos;June 8th, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
