<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/107/0 images: 186-190</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
pf.       .  ..... .jvms joctnic^ off.his;.britannic.majesty&apos;s ooverni^t) .,.-/aS I C R g T. CP. 1437.-,C A B I .N E T. HOUSING LIABILITIES. Memorandum by the gecietary for Scotland.*   1* With- reference to the Memorandum hy the Chancellor CP .1330    *f the&apos;exchequer regarding HousingLiabilities^, i hare to say that I can confirm from the, Scottish point of view the case presented by.him.   In view of the increase in wages, past and prospective, and the increase in the cost of materials, for house building, the seriousness of the financial position cannot well be exaggerated.   Unless some very drastic measures are taken, the Government will he facsd with a huge annual financial deficit,   so far as Scotland is con-cerned, the deficit per house in future is likely to exceed  60 per annum unless costs are reduced.ICREASE 2. in illustration it may be pointed out that sinceJ COST-        November last the. estimated average increase in the cost lER HOUSE.     of houses is over  200 per house.   The following table shows how the estimated costs, as shown-by&quot; tenders sub-mitted, have steadily risen  luring the past six months.	TYPE 05&apos; HOUSE.	ESTIMATED COST	ESTIMATED COST		IF N0VEh&quot;BER	ACCORDING&apos; 10 MOS&apos;		1919.	RECENT FIGHHPS.		 	 3	apartment cottage	709	936 .3	&quot;       Platted house	633	8504	&quot;        cottage	800	1,0355	&quot;        cottage	887	1,190These figures cover only increases in wages and materials to date.   Any subsequent increases will fall to be re-imbursed to the contractors, and to that extent the cost per house will be enhanced.f ES. 3. Since last Autumn, wages in the building trade have advanced approximately from 1/6 to 2/- per hour,, and even at the latter figure negotiations and strikes are on foot for higher rates. &quot;Wages in the building trade in Scotland to-day nin from l/loi to 2/- per hour. Although joiners only are actually on strike there is a movement to bring up the wages of all branches ih the&apos;building trade to 2/6 per hour - an increase equivalent to  5$ on existing rates.^PECT Otf 4. (a) It is estimated that the arera.;-e cost per houseVTONMENT is made up of 45$ of labour and 55$ of materials. Taking BSIITY OF the average cost per house at  1000, an advance of 6d. per &quot;CREASE hour in wages would amount to an increase, of not les3 than WAGES.       112 per house. . Under the rules for fixing rents thecapital cost of a house..does not fall to be considered, and m consequently all. increases&apos; fall on the Exchequer, the con-* tribution by xocal Authorities being limited by statute.Economic rents at the prices now ruling average from  90 to  100 per annum, and as. the average rental is between  20 and  25 per annum., the loss per house exceeds  60 yearly.
(b)   Taking 10$ as a fair rate to cover loan charges., repairs, insurance and supervision, the^extra^ annual charges if an increase of  d. per hour ^ere granted on eurrent rates will amount to  11 per house. On the Scottish programme of ft),.000 houses during th&amp; susbidy period, the&quot;annual contribution by the State would be increased by  6^0,000..AJWDAKD&quot; RATES.    5 (a)   The Scot-tLsh Bosrd of Health have hitherto :. set their faces against any increases of wages being^RMBKT       made a charge against a housing scheme, unless such&apos; in-PPROVALt crease has been authorised by&apos;the &quot;competent authority&quot;.It is feared, however,, that this policy cannot be maintain-ed if the English Kinistry continue to recognise any agreement made between employers and employees as -regulating uhe district rate of T&quot;ages in a particular district.     In a few cases the acceptance of tenders for housing schemes is hung up on account of con-tractors refusing to sign a contract unless they are to be guaranteed payment of all increases in wages agreed upon between them and their employees.   The need for an early solution of this difficulty must be apparent *(b)   In connection with the present strike of joiners in Scotland, the employers are making a strong point of the difference existing in the practice of the two countries.     A representative of the Scottish Board&apos; of Health recently had a meeting with representatives of the Scottish Builders&apos; Federation, who, apart from the question of the rate of wages, are insisting&quot; on the insertion of the English Clause in any contract for housing.( c)   The polrcy of allowing employers and employees to fix the district rate of wages without the approval of the liinistry of Labour or other recognised Government Tribunal is not, in view of the system of &quot;open con-tracts&quot; now obtaining, in my Judgment to be commended, as employers who will be reimbursed for the extra wages have no direct incentive to keep wages do^n.   Fuitfter, Local Authorities whose commitment is limited by statute have no direct interest in the matter.   Accordingly the polio;/ of the Scottish Board of Health has been to allo^ as a charge against subsidised housing schemes only such increases in wages as have been confirmed by a Government Tribunal.(d) . Since December last, the Board have regarded the Industrial Court as the appropriate Tribunal.   That Court reeently he\ard an application on behalf of the Building Trades for an increase of 6d.- per hour.   The Award of the Court was to the effect that parties had-failed to make out a aase for any morease whatever,   that Award was unacceptable both to the employers&apos;and the employees, who subsequently met and came to an agreement under&apos;which the employers agreed to pay immediately an increase of ltd per hour to all trades, and to refer bark . the difference of 4-jrd to the decision of the Industrial Court.     The Kinistry of Labour informed, parties tv^t, the Industrial Court having given its Award, it could not re-hear the application nor could the Ministry themselven review the decision of the Industrial Court.-I (e)   The present deadlock is, the Board understand,
JISRESAKD oi IF WAGES BY RACTQRS&apos;.IMITATION IF DSIiCIT.BPPLV 0? &quot;ABOUH.8(a). deficient, layers wereThe supply of labour in Scotland is hopelessly In the Glasgow Kennyhill schema, only to brick-available for 316 housese   The completion of houses for occupation in Edinburgh and Glasgow for the May term also been delayed on account of the Joiners&apos; etc.&quot;has(b)   The following table shows (a) the present amount of labour engaged at the moment on schemes being carried out in Scotland fthe number of houses for which tenders have been aocepted being 7,693) and (b) the amount of labour that should be engaged on these schemes at the moment to enable the above number of houses to be completed by the end of the present year:-Humber cf men at present employed.Bricks  $u*nonJ.Otfoerl&amp;yora. trades.l?o. of men who should Total,   be employed at present if houses to be com-pietad by 31.12.20. Briok-   joiners. Other layers. trades..601110      1751      2462.     27268576      12079.Total 173G0The estimated deficiency is therefore 14,918 men.attributed by both parties to the attitude of the   Ministry of Labour on this particular application-   It is understood that the Ministry of Labour are of opinion that no less a period than four month should elapse before the Industrial Court ought again to hear an application for an inorease in the trades affected.    Meantime, a8 already explained, the joiners have gone on strike aiir) there is every chance that the remaining branches of the building trades will follow suit at an early date.    The effect of the continuance of the strike on the housing programme over Scotland is, to say the least of it, disastrous, especially in view of the fadt that the, strike is taking plaoe during the best building,period of the year.    It is hot too much to say that, but for&apos;the ccntiiiu-anoe of the recent plumbers&apos; strike and the present joiners&apos; strike, something like 200 additional houses would have  sen ready for occupation by tho Whitsunday removal terna6o     In the absenoe of any State control over wages, it is open to any private firm to offer building ttradesmen more than the standard rate, with the result that labour is drawn from housing sohemes on whioh it has been the practice of the . Scottish Board of Health to insist on the payment of neither more nor less than the standard rate.    Cases of this nature have already been brought to the Board&apos;s notice at Grangemouth, A-lloa, Stirling and Renfrew.;It Has been reported that the Scottish Dye Company of Grangemouth have been offering a rate of 2/8 per hour for bricklayers, whioh ie 8d. per hour in excess of the standard rate current in the districts7-1    The suggestion in paragraph 6 of the, Chancellor of the Exchequer^ memorandum that &quot;no housing contracts shall be &quot;concluded which will Impose more than a stated amount of &quot;deficit, is, I am advised, not practicable.     I am informed that no looal authority in Scotland would prooeed with hous-ing under these conditions, and that any proposal to increase their statutory liability would be -resented and opposed.   At the present moment, it is impossible to get contractors to enter into a fixed contract, and, so long as this state, of affairs continues, it is not feasible to put a limit to the amount of the deficit.
The above calculation is made on the assumption that two i?en per house per annum is required to ensure the completion of tho houses tendered for by the date mentioned,9.   The Scottish Board of Health have been approached&quot; ttft %c the adoption of a system of direct labour by local authorities.    They have indicated that they are prepared to&quot;&apos;approve, on condition that local authorities are, willing to guaian+ec a basic price r;&apos;.ic;h is reasonably compare--able to pile es beiiar. oVeined by tencior, Local authorities urge in supper1., of this system that it rill attract additional labour to housing and probably also result in an increased outr put ftCOST AED loiaAs regards the cost and supply.cf materials,SUPPLY GFthe situation would appear to he equally critical, MATKHlALSlf possible, the Profiteering C omit tec&apos; s Report should beissued at an early date, to enable tho G-ovenra^nt to consider wheihbr a cane ho.&quot; been established for legislative action. It is estimated Th.at in- Scotland, the price of,building materials since Lajt Autumn has increased by b0$, and this of course adds considerably to the cost of the house3*(b) A3 regards the supply of building materials, it has transpired v/tthin the last for; days that a nhortago of bricks is inoritehle^ although the Department of Building material Supply repeatedly assured the Scottish Board of He a ath that for the next year at least a sufficiency of all kind3 of materaai had been arranged-for. The difficulty of obtaining .3u.oolies has already been brought. to the notice of the Scottish Board of Health by different local authoritiesJ It is possible, however, that that difficulty at the moment is due more to the lack of adequate transport than to lack of materials.KSCOMSNf       11. Te ease the situation many suggestions have been DATIONS.   made,     It has for example been suggested that legislative - action should bo taken t$ control wages and to prevent the indiscriminate   raising of the same on private contracts, whereby labour is enticed from, housing and an artificial district rate of vaaes is set up.To control the price of building materials through existing agencies or by means of legislative action.   The difficulties in the way of this course seem to me to be insuperable.It is, however, I think urgently necessary to take measures to secure (a) Dilution of Labour.*  Trades Unions have already made it -clear that they are opposed to dilution, until it can be proved that&apos; building, trade operatives now engaged in other occupations have been dram back to their ordinary occupation.. .   To bring this about operatives would recuire to be assured of equally good conditions to those obtaining in the employment-to whiehTthey have gone.    That uould include broken time, which uould of course Inevitably increase the cost of housing.
. (b) Increased output.(c) Additional power to local authorities to control the erection of buildingu of lews public import-ance than housing.In this connection the action of the Scottish Appeal Tribunal&apos;appointed to deal with appeals in regard to Local authority orders prohibiting the erection&apos; of buildings ,of less public importance than housing has beeh such as ttr indicate that no material help is to be expected from.the provisions of the Housing (Additional powers) Act&apos;of last year.Complaints- have also been received by the Scottish Board of Health from certain local authorities as to their inability to d$al with the erection of buildings of less public importance than housing in areas of other local authorities but closely adjoining the site of actual house building fcj? the complaining local authority.(Signed) EOBMT MUIEO.Scottish Office, 9th June, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
