<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/107/0 images: 315-324</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.   &apos;HOUSING LIABILITIES AND HOUSING LABOUR. r&quot;Memp^ by Dr* iiacnamara,C,P,   1463.The attached paper is circulated in connection with item 1, of theCabinet Agenda paper for the meeting to be held on Wednesday,.16th. June, 1920, at 12 noon,2, Whitehall Gardens, S.1.V, &apos;   15th, June, 1920,
1 ...241(This&quot;document--is the property of His Britannic Majesty1^ aovernment)I desireto make.the following remarks on&apos; the Memorandum by theMini;ster of Health, CP. 1396, dated 2.6.20;B.in this connection to bring to the notice of the Cabinetthe position respecting Labour in the Building Tradeand Unemployment amongst ex-i-ervice men, with animportant recommendation thereon.1. The second paragraph of the -Memorandum states that the increases of wages in the. Bu! Iding Trade are not abnormal as compared with those in other trades, and supports&apos;this statement by quoting the percentage increase in wages of skilled men in the, London District.     In fact, however, the particular case cited is practically the lowest percentage Building Trade increase in the country. .  The percentage increases as compared with 1913 (the last year before the Wau for which complete returns were available) vary in the case of skilled labour from 155$ to 250$ and in the case of labourers from 233$ to 254$.An appendix is given showing typical increases of wages in&quot; rthe building rate.Typical figures are also given in the appendix showing .increases of wages in other trades.   Although comparisons arebuilding trade are distinctly high.   Ho definite information isbut it is believed that there was no general increase, over the &apos;rates quoted for 1913.     Due regard must be taken however, in making comparisons to the possibility of a slight variation in not easy, it will be seen, that the percentage increases in theavailable regarding rates in the building trade In July,1914,.the/
the rates for July 1914, over those shown with a consequent reduction in the percentage - advance.,-   The high percentage increases granted to dock labour is to be explained; by reference . to Lord Shaw&apos;s report which dealt with the whole reconstruction of conditions of labour in docks, this being in part a consideration for the increases,   Similarly the jpercenta^e increase-to carters is explained by taking into, account the large reduction in working hours.In regard.to the building trade, the figures given in the Appendix shew a still more significant fact, namely that the movement for a greater increase in the building trade is .being acceleratedc2.     I agree in&quot;principle with tho suggestion in paragraph 6 that there should be an attempt to obtain a national settle-ment of rages and working conditions in the building trade,&apos; The National Conciliation Board in the building trade is a-t present considering a scheme on these lines, but, as the Minister of Health says, there may be some delay.   It is being placed before the constituents of the Board at the present&apos; time, but the. attitude of the plumbers, for instance, and the general condition of the building trade may prevent an early decision.   The present system under,which wages&apos;and conditions are regulated regionally with appeal to a National Board does not carry the same weight, as a genuine national settlement of wages would carry, but it must-be admitted thai, in view of what has happened since the institution of the area schemes, even a national settlement of wages would not prevent particular districts in certain cirCumstans.es from breaking away from it, although a national scheme might be expected to have some restraining effect.The/
The wa^B payable on housing contracts should be strictly in accordance with the national scheme and it might be made a condition of obtaining a licenoo for private buildings that the same condition should apply.   Tills latter provision is contemplated in Dr. Addicon^s Memorandum paragraph 6\(h).In addition it should be made clear that the Government will accept no financial liability in respeot of any housing scheme on which rates of wages are paid in exoess of the rates fixed for the district under the national Scheme.30 On the&quot;guaranteed week&quot; my adtisors tell me that they do not think that the Government should lead the way in establishing any form of guaranteed week in the trade.   Aotion of this character on the part of the Government in a particular trade, they says would inevitably lead to demands for similar concessions in other trades. In their opinion this is a matter which should be left for the trade itself to settleo Moreover any form, of guaranteed week on Government building work v/ould, they tell me, inevitably extend throughout the - whole building trade.4. Further, my advisers doubt whether it is feasible to secure the adoption of systems of payment by results in the builds ing trade; strong opposition is certain to be encountered from the Trade Unions if any attempt is made in this direction.5. I am in agreement with the proposals made in paragraph ,5 (d), (e), (f), (g), and (h) of the Minister of Healths memorandum.B* TIE POSITION HBSEEOEINS BUILDING LABOUR AMDt i .i.  i  i i -uav i. ii i  m.mi mi-......mm &quot;IKikf &quot;......fMEMPIOYMCHT AMONGST SK-SBHyiOB MSN. &apos; In regard to paragraph 5 of the Minister of Health&apos;s Memorandum, I am not sure exactly what is meant by &quot;mass dilution.&quot; I should think that the addition of apprentices and unskilled labour to the building trado could be successfully recommended. y.I afcree, however, that dilution inHhe sense of putting unskilled ... ...      ^wivfl Mr^fH&apos;wnrlr is difficult to bring into operation&apos;,
but, it,might,fie, put to the trade that bricklayers&apos; labourers should be placed on the simpler forms of,bricklaying and their places filled by unskilled labourers.I am supported in my view by a very useful anal &quot;significant&apos; recommendation which I have just received.My colleagues will remember that following discussions in the House of Commons at the beginning of this Session on&quot;the restrictions placed by certain Trade Unions upon the admission of ex-Service men, a Committee.was appointed to consider the best means of facilitating the re-employment of ex-Service men in.Industry, and upon this &quot;Committee there were representatives of the Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union Congress, of the National Confederation of Employersf Organisations, of Ex-Service men&apos;s Associations, and of my Department&apos;. ^At its last meeting, on June 10th, this Committee who are interested in the building trade position primarily in so far as it may offer prospects of employment for Ex-Service men, made, the following important recommendation-. &quot;While it is not within the province of this Committee to attempt to-lay down the.precisemethod whereby the supply of skilled building labour should be increased, they desire.to draw attention, to the ,following possibilities(a) There are now..unemployed some 7,.000 ex-servicebuilding labourers, with experience of the trade. Many of them have sufficient experience.to be  -&apos; adapted without great difficulty for the work of skilled men,(b)A large proportion of young ex-service men outside the building trade who are now unemployed are &apos; obviously suitable for training for the building trade/
1  trade.   It may be suggested that since these men joined the Army at the age of 18 they would already have gone into apprenticeship before that age if they had intended to oualify as skilled men.   It    &apos; should, however, be pointed out that during the War many youths failed to become apprentices bepause they expected to be called up for Military Service on attaining the age of 18, because there was a large demand for unskilled or semi-skilled labour on munitions work, and because certain trades were almost closed down while other trades were engaged on special work and did not provide instruction for apprentices.(c)   The temporary&apos;suspension of.the age limits in the Trade Union apprenticeship rules would facilitate the admission&quot; of young Ex&apos;-Servlc-e men. The Committee would suggest that the whole matter     , ; should immediately be considered in detail between employers and labour organisations in the building trade, and strongly recommend that in view of the fact that large numbers of unskilled Ex-Service men . could be absorbed in the building trades if additional skilled labour were available, immediate steps should be taken to secure an increase in the supply of-skilled labour of the types&apos; required&quot;.&apos; It appears to me that the recommendations of this Committeeafford a very favourable opportunity for the Government to againapproach the Industry.  -(Signed) T.J. MACNAMARA*Ministry of Labour.. .. 15c6.20.
APPENDIX TO THB MBIfflORAKDOTI BY 11HE MINISTER Of LABOUR ON HOUSING LIABILITIES.Wages Movements in the Building trade the following table gives figures for London and certain typical provincial towns whioh show how considerable the advance has been in hourly rates of wages in the building trade since 1913, the&quot; last year for which full statistics are available.Brio payers (June)Peroentag.6 advanceLabourersm$ U20percentages advance.don	11	2/4	1550		2/1	2330ningham	10	8/4	1800	7	2/l   ,	2570ling ton		8/4	,&apos; ,1950 &apos;	.&quot;.-6*	2/1	2850ooln	8	8/4	2500		2/1	3540sfleld	9	2/4	2110		; 2/1	2850rnemouth	Ql fa	2/-	1820		1/9	2820mouth	al	g/-;	1820		1/9	2820-port (I.w.)	V .	1/10	2140	4	1/7	3220Definite information as to the rates of wages in July 1914 is not available except in the oaso of London where the rates had advanced Id over the 1913 rates making the percentages for bricklayers 1500 and for labourers 2130*It is believed that there was no general increase of wages in the building trade in the period 1913/1914.It will be observed that the lowest percentage inorease is 155^in the case of London brioklayers, while labourers  advances have reached as high a figure as 354.     It must bo stated that the percentage would be somewhat lower if weekly wages, were takon, but owing to the system of payment of wages in the building trade comparisons on this basis aro difficult. The Minister of Health*s figures of 1430 (presumably referring to 1914) is based on hourly rates./The
fThe following &quot;table, -alrcw-typical, advances of wages in other trades:-		1914		Juno 1920		Peroentage increase.engineering London	Fitter	Ra^G	Hours	Rate	Hours	;            j 1 146$		9fd per Hoar	54	2/* per hour	47		I$br.	5d-6d per hour	54	1/6-i- l/7f per hour	47 *	216$-265$engineering Ilnoolr	i Fitter	6fd per hour	53	1/9* per hour	47	215$	Labr.	5d per hour	ti	l/5l per hour	47	. 255$t &amp; Shpe limum rates)	-	6w46d per hour	5Ei	1/5 por hour	48	163$&apos;kers	London	7d, .per hour	60	2/- per hour	44	243$	Glasgow	8d. per hour-	57	S/- per hour	44	200$&apos;ters	London	4e5d per hour	72	16,5a.	48 -	267$	Liver-pool	5.9ia.	65	17,75d	48	200$Initure	London	lli	54		^7	139$What is still more significant is that the movement towards increase in the building trade is accelerating.   For instance, since the beginning of Deeomber last flat inoreases covering the Yorkshire area have been given of 2d. per hour on 13th December, Id. on 3rd\ &apos;, &quot; &apos;:V&apos;January, Id, on 1st May and 4d. on 4th June, which exceed considerably and particularly in non-industricl areas any increase in the cost of liv ing even allowing for the reduotion in the number of working hours/per
;;r week.     The Linooln rates for skilled men have been inore&amp;sedporn l/9d. per hour on the 1st December to 2/4d - 330 and for labourersrom l/6d per hour to 2/- - 390,     Similar increases have taken place a the Birmiuigham Area since November.The following telegram from the Chesterfield Corporationas been referred to tho Department in connection with the latestncrcase in the&quot; Midland Are&amp;:--  &quot;Forbear   c/o Localise,   parl. Ldn.Recent Birmingham Award to skilled and unskilled.&quot;^labour employed in tho building trade in the MidlandsAre ft. nanely 4d per hour inoroaso all round received withconsternation hero this rise-plus the liay rise will addabout  100 to each house built bricklayers and labourersin this area havo not demanded any increase and we are at&apos;aless to know why Chesterfiold should pay the Birminghammt$ my Commit toe feel that; the Ministry-must realise what this means before t&amp;oy make any further commitment intheir housing scheme&apos;this increase aoutsfcLises yowincreased subsidy&apos; awaiting your instructions. &apos;&quot;:- &apos; Town Clerk, Chostertfleld*&apos;TIt is significant&apos; that in the circular letter issued by theidland Federation of Building Trade employers reporting, tho latest. ivajace of 4d. in the Midland /:rea, the-^deration&apos;s Secretary reportstat an operative member of the Council.stated that the Trade,union officials had quitt lost control of thomon.,1     A&apos;table, in the Labour  a so ttc for May ( ago  65) giving.thestimated cost of building for which plans wore passod in tho firstsartor of 1920 shows the following comparison,with tho correspondingbarter of 1919?- &apos;^      mv.-!:v19.20- 1919* -Houses        Factories &amp; Business Misc. Total.- premises; &apos;      -v-&apos;;0    6,267,000 5,320,000,;- 3,516,000      15,103,000P        135&quot;, 0Q.0 1*785, 000&apos;.V, 921,000        S.,891.,000I .    - .
The volume of work.may bo.expected to grow oonsidorably as tho housing programme develops.   Even so, at this early sta:;o, the figures&apos;when analysed show that housing accounts for 3/5 of the estimated cost In Scotland, ^ in Outer London and about \ in tho Northern Counties *   It is inevitable that tho execution of this greatly extended amount of business with tho present depleted labour strength must inevitably lead to still fiercer competition for labour in the near future.

</content>
</cab>
