<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/107/0 images: 430-439</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
jggRET.      For the information of Members of the Board.&apos;    WEEKLY APPRECIATION of matters OF NAVAL INTEREST.&apos;&apos;Vj*^&quot; \\For the week ended 12th June 1920.CP-11.5*8BALTIC. Cruise of Battle Cruisers.&quot;Hood&quot; and &quot;Tiger&quot; with &quot;Spenser&quot; and 8 T.B.D&apos;s, leTt Kalmar on 7th June and arrived at Nynashamn in the evening of the same day.   On 8th June, the destroyers proceeded to Stockholm.   The crews of the Battle Cruiser Squadron were given an enthusiastic reception at Stockholm.   H.M. the King of Sweden lunched on board H.M.S.&quot;Hood&quot; on 10th June -f-        accompanied by the Prime Minister and the Minister for Foreign Affairs.Rear Admiral, Battle Cruiser Squadron, has been directed to,postpone the date of his arrival at Copenhagen as may be necessary to avoid clashing with the entertainment of the Flensburg Force.The original programme for the Battle Cruiser Squadron was to visit Christiania first and other Scandinavian ports later.   Owing to political reasons this programme had to be modified and Christiania visited on the return journey.   This has caused an outburst in the Norwegian Press, which states that it is an indication of the position held by Norway in British official opinion.. H.M. the King of Norway and the Government were much annoyed at the article and agreed that the feeling which inspired it must be confined to a small clique who have worked orYffeelings of Scandinavian jealousy, for which the Editor in question is well known.   The. visit will be most welcome, and the Battle Cruiser Squadron will arrive at Christiania on 24th June.   The &quot;Aftenposten&quot; published on 7th June, an article attributing the presence of H.M.Ships in the Baltic to a threat   of the Soviet Fleet.   This should put the matter in its proper light, and is very near the actual facts.H.M.S.&quot;Carnarvon&quot; will visit Northern Norwegian ports between 5th August t:.nd 4th September.Flensburg.S.S.&quot;Steigerwald&quot; and H.S.&quot;Agadir&quot; arrived at Flensburg on 7th and 8th&apos;June respectively.Orders have been sent to the Vice Admiral to issue the necessary instructions for withdrawal on 15th June.&quot;Agadir&quot; will return to Southampton via Kiel Canal.Vice Admiral, &quot;Carysfort&quot;, reports that the Flensburg Force will be entertained at Copenhagen by the Danish Government on 17th and 18th June and nil! leave for England early on 19th June.H.R.H.Prince. Axel has concluded arrangements for the purchase of the sloop &quot;Asphodel&quot;.   The Danes request that a navigating party may take her to Harwich and there turn over to the Danish Crew.   All expenses will be paid by the Danish Government.
The rootowing of ammunition was completed on June 4th and the vessel released from naval detention on the 5th*   She then proceeded to Grangemouth to re-embark the 3&quot; guns pre-viously landed and to take in bunker coal,    he sailed for Brest on June 10th without escort,   in accordance with the wishes of the French Government.Latvia,The Lettish Press states that a peace protocol signed in Berlin on May 5th will come into force when the ratification documents have been exchanged,   The main conditions are that Germany recognises Latvia as an independent State after she has been recognised as such by one member of the Entente,   Both countries pledge themselves not to support hostile attempts against either of the contracting parties and Germany binds herself to make good the damage caused by German troops in Latvia, to hand over the war material which belonged to BermonVs force and to supply Latvia with goods on credit.The Soviet Government will not agree   to Lettish peace negotiations being transferred to Dorpat, giving reason that it would cause a bed impression in Moscow.   Lettish Government will, however; pursue the proposal.The Bolsheviks have forbidden their troops to cross the Dwina.   This points to their having no intention whatever to attack Latvia at present.   Skirmishes, however, are still reported on the frontiers.The S ... ;. !,l)anl;a&quot; at Chatham has developed engine room defects which will delay her about a fortnight.   Arrangements have been made to allow the officers to land and for the men to take exorcise on shore uncher surveillance, but no grounds are to be given for a complaint to be made that they are under arrest.Lithuania.Lithuania also wishes to transfer peace conference to Dorpat, but if Soviet Government refuses it will not necessarily mean an interruption of negotiations.Kara^ Sea Relief Expedit ion..The outstanding question with regard to the insurance, etc/, has evidently been settled between Norway and the Soviet Government, as the &quot;Sviatogor&quot; is reported to have sailed on June 9th from Vardo for Bielushya Bay, Novaya Zemlya, where she will coal from the collier &quot;Harde,! and then proceed to the Kara Sea.Finland.The Bolsheviks have agreed to recommence peace discussions with Finland at Dorpat on June 10th.   Finnish Minister for Foreign Affairs stated that decision to negotiate at Dorpat did not imply any desire to act separately from Poland, and it was hoped that Polandls reluctance to negotiate on neutral territory might eventually be overcome.The Aaland Islands Question is assuming a more acute phase and resulting in an exchange of notes between Sweden and Finland. Finland on June 5th entered a strong protest against Swedish Government championing the cause of the Aalanders and also against the reception of the Aaland Islands delegation to Stockholm by h.m. the King of Sweden.   Finland draws attention to the fact thatshe
she maintains her sovereignty over these Islands and must there -fore emphasise repudiation of all claims incompatible therewith.. Swedish Government replied on June 7th expressing astonishment and states that Aalanders have ever since the time of re-organi-s&amp;tion claimed with unanimity the right to determine their national status, and therefore  weden considers this claim perfectly legitimate, based on the principle of the right of so if-determination.   Several of the delegates who. proceeded to Stockholm have been arrested by the Finns on their &quot;return; due to their attitude towards the Finnish Ministers, v;ho went to the Aaland Islands to discuss the application of the new autonomous law.   The Aaland representatives curtly refused to meet Ministers on pretext that they had already laid their case before the Swedish Government and the Great Powers and had nothing further to discuss with the Finnish,Government.The Swedish Government has asked Finland officially whether this action has been taken as a result of the delegation1s visit to Stockholm.   Finland in reply states that the delegation by their action, have as Finnish citizens committed acts punishable by Finnish law and will be brought to trial.   Finland regards the matter entirely as an internal cuestion0Two extra battalions of Finnish speaking troops have been despatched to the Aala\d Islands to reinforce the permanent garrison, and conflict is anticipated with the Islanders.The Swedish Government is much perturbed at this step and fears its effect on Swedish public opinion.   Meanwhile a heated controversy is going on between the Swedish and Finnish Press on the   subject.It has been suggested that the strict Finnish prohibition law and the superior purchasing power of the Swedish crown are largely responsible for the&apos;Increased agitation.   The Aalanders are by no me ans prohibiti onist s.Finnish Minister of Foreign Affairs informed Mr.Kidston on June 7th that as no reply had been received from the Powers with regard to the &apos;de jure1 status of Esthonia, they presumed there was no objection to Finland granting such recognition and had taken steps accordingly.Poland.There is no definite news with regard to the Northern sector of the Polish front, but evidently positions are being held.   The Bolsheviks are stated to be preparing for an offensive early In Juihy   and cavalry reinforcements are being sent from Petrograd.League of Nations.The Soviet Government have replied to the Leaguefs note of May 22nd that they cannot in any way alter their former reply until the military situation created by the Polish offensive shall hsve changed sufficiently for the considerations of safety which the Soviet Government now have to take into account to   lose their present character of imperious necessity.BLACK SEA AND MEDITERRANEAN.Crimea,Vice Admiral Sablin has relieved Admiral Gerasimov as Commander-in-Chief of the Russian Fleet.In telegrams of 3rd, 5th and 6th June, the Commander-in -Chief, Mediterranean, reported that General Wrahg&amp;d. had stated that he would be forced to initiate an offensive against the Soviet, inorder
**** 4 u*&apos;   310order to obtain food producing territory for the support of the Crimea.Irahgol had also asked what guarantee H.M.Government could exact,, and enforce, from the Soviet Government for the observance of any agreement arrived at with the Soviet as a result of the proposed negotiations.WrangelVs forces took the offensive on 6th June, one corps embarking at Theodosia, passing the Kertch Straits, unobserved, by night, and landing atGoysloe, 20 versts south of Melitopol, which latter place has now been captured.A simultaneous advance took place on the Chongar Front, Reports to date indicate a complete success, and the advance continuesv   It is stated that 5,000 prisoners and 27 guns have been taken by tho three corps engaged, whose casualties are estimated at about 500.The War Office have given instructions for the British Military Mission bo be withdrawn as unobtrusively as possible; the withdrawal to be completed by 30th June,   The withdrawal of the Naval Mission is to be undertaken in conformity with the above.Instructions have been issued to the British Naval Forces that, in consequence of Wrangel&apos;s action in taking the offensive, strict neutrality is to be maintained and no support afforded to Wrangel In offence or defence.Batoum.General Milne has been instructed to prepare for withdrawal from Batoum and to await War Office order before commencing embarkation.    In reply he- states that evacuation can take place about June 20th if s,s.&quot;Ekaterinoslav&quot; for horses and &quot;Hospital ship &quot;Panama&quot; are sent at once from Egypt.   Also he reouires definite instructions re handing over Batoum to the Georgians. Question also arises whether Mission at Tiflis should be withdrawn at the same time, in order to reduce possibility of their being held as hostages in the event of Georgia becoming Bolshevik.The Cabinet on June 11th came to the following decision.-(1).   Colonel Stokes will start immediately for Batoum, entrusted with a special mission from H.M.G. to negotiate an agreement with the Georgian Government by which, under suitable conditions, the province and port of Batoum will be handed over by the Allied forces to that Government.(2). He will be accompanied by M.Gambashidze, the principal delegate cf the Georgian Government in BIngland.(5). He will call at Constantinople in order to see the High Commissioner and the G.0.C (General Milne).(4). He will proceed without delay to Batoum, where he will enter into Immediate communication with the Georgian Government.(5). He will endeavour to secure, in his arrangements with the Georgian Government, conditions of free transit over the Caucasian railway and free use of the port of Batoum for the Republics of Armenia and Azerbaijan.(6). Upon the conclusion of this agreement, the G.0.C will handover
over the port and province of Batoum to the Georgian Government? and will then withdraw the Allied Forces.In view of the above the War Office has instructed tho G.O.C., that the S.S0HIIomsee&quot; with munitions for Georgia and Armenia should be timed to arrive at Batoum when Colonel Stokes commences negotiations with Georgia, so that he can obtain guarantees for Armenian part of ammunition going to Armenia,   Armenian representative   here states&quot; that matter has been arranged satisfactorily with Georgia *   II,M.. S.. &quot;Ceres&quot; has been ordered to be at Marseilles by June 15th to?,,; embark Colonel Stokes.Georgia.Cheidze, a former Minister of Kerensky?s Government, pro-poses closer relations between Georgia and SovietThe majority are opposed to this but there appeared an increasing leaning towards Soviet influence.The Russian representative in Georgia asked Commander Luke to take charge of Russian interests,   Foreign Office has wired that acceptance must not bo considered.,     In Azerbaijan,&apos; Tartars are showing much dissatisfaction with Communist Regime..   Local risings have taken place, and have been suppressed with much bloodshed and retaliatory massacres. The British at Baku are under arrest and compelled to work on the roads.   There is a possibility that they may be removed to Astrakhan.   Comdr.Luke suggests that pressure be brought to bear on Krassin Mission for release of Baku prisoners.The Commander-in-Chief, Mediterranean, reported on 9th June that Georgians had concluded a weekVs armistice with the Reds, Falling agreement, hostilities would&amp;commence.   He stated that a promise of Allied help might even now turn the scale.Ukraine * %The Polos state that there are considerable stocks of grain in the Ukraine and that only a small area, comparatively speaking, has not been cultivated.   Prospects for this year&apos;3 harvest are exceptionally good.On the Polish Southern front on June 6th Budenniels cavalry with armoured cars broke through the Polish centre and took JItomir.   Kieff has been isolated.   In view of this danger, Marshal Pilsudskl has ordered Kieff to be evacuated and new positions taken up on the Teterev line.   It is hoped that by this movement Budennie!s cavalry will, be cut off.   There is&quot;a strong desire for peace, but Pilsudski himself wishes first to restore the military situation.Jews are hostile to Polish soldiers and at Bordichev are reported to have killed soldiers in Hospitals.   Much feeling is being stirred up by this.The military situation may be restored, but it is still serious, as Bolsheviks are reported to be bringing up 5 Infantry and 1 Cavalry divisions from the Caucasus.   The Polish offensive has also caused a great impetus to be given to the new Russian Nabiosnal feeling.Caspian.There are no indications of any withdrawal of Bolsheviks from Enzeli.The British evacuated Resht on 1st June, withdrawing through Manz11.Approval has been given for the transfer of the Volunteer fleet personnel from Kasvin to Mesopotamia.
W(        l\ ***TURKEY,Fighting between Nationalist and Loyal troops in the Ism-id Area has ceased-   The former are reported active in the Zcnguld jak and Shlle Areas.   The latter, said to be thoroughly untrustworthy in action, are now camped close to Ismid, where occasional shots are exchanged with weak Nationalists5 detachments.The Turkish Government is to be allowed an extension of 15 days from 11th June for consideration of the Peaces Treaty.The Ottoman Government evidently feels it is impossible to sign the Treaty.   But even if it does sign matters are not much advanced, as it will be powerless to get the Treaty enforced. Civil war at present exists in Turkey and is going in favour of the Nationalists-   The anti-Nationalist action of the Government has been a complete failure and it is Mustapha Kemal who controls the situation.As regards Turkish opposition to the Treaty this will be most active in respect of Armenia,   Smyrna.and Thrace.    It must be borne in mind that the Nationalist Headquarters at Angora has declared that the Treaty, as known, can never be accepted, In particular the possibility of Mustapha Kemal; (who claims to exercise power through the Nationalist Constituent Assembly at Angora on the ground that the Sultan cannot form a genuine Government owing to the Allied occupation of Constantinople), declaring the independence of Ti and. S.Thrace combined has to be considered.The Ottoman Government, amongst other expedients, may be expected to offer to sign in return for some assurances that a revision of the Treaty in their favour will eventually be made.   In this respect they no doubt count on the good offices of France and Italy, and are encouraged by recent -speeches of certain statesmen of those countries; notably MLBarthou and SeNittio&apos;Thrace.Tho Greek: proposal to land two divisions at Rodosto and Eregli for the occupation of E-Thrace Is in abeyance pending the approval which M.Veniaelos hopes to secure from the Supreme Council..All preparations have been made for this occupation, and M.Venizelos considers delay Increases the changes of opposition.   General Bridges, however, is of opinion that the Turkish forces in Thrace are more likely to dwindle than increase.MoMillerand strongly endorses the Greek proposal and considers that by approving such action the Allies will show the Turks that they are serious.The Greek Government has been urged to consult tho Commander-in-Chief before effecting the landing, r-.nd has replied that General Milne will be informed before any decisive step is taken.The Grand Vizier, who appears to be in ignorance of this proposal, is, nevertheless, extremely preoccupied by the possibility of a Greek occupation of E.Thrace before the signature of the Treaty, which he considers must inevitably provoke bloodshed, as it will be resisted by the followers of Jaffar Tyar.
Jaffaar Tyar holds no official position at Adrianople, but controls the situation there and the military and civil authorities work with him;   The situation appears to be that Jaffar Tyar will hold his hand unless the Greeks advance: if they do he will attack and the Central Government /will refrain from disapproving.   His efforts to induce ,his Bulgarian supporters to initiate hostilities against the Greeks appear to have tailed owing to action by the Bulgarian -Government -The Greeks?- however, are nervous about the Bulgarians, whom they acknowledge have never been properly disarmed.A whole series of &quot;incidents&quot; between Greeks and Bulgarians is reported from Thrace, and Bulgaria has evidently reason to complain that her frontiers have been violated and attempts made iyo carry off flocks and property, and will be justified in offering armed opposition if such&quot;proceedings continue.Constantinople and Thrace were reported quiet on the 10th instant.   The Turks in Asia Minor appear to be uniting against the Treaty.ARMMIA, -The U. S0 and Armenia, -President Wilson and his Secretary for Foreign Affairs are believed to be In favour of forcing tho U\S.Ao to undertake a Mandate for Turkey and of participating in the control of the Straits.To this end the President recently convened a secret meeting of representative   men interested In the.Middle East to devise means of effecting such a policy without reference to, and over the heads of, Congress and Senate. Two proposals were brought forward at this meeting.(l).(a).*   Negotiations to be opened with the Armenian Government to secure a contract for the supply of munitions and other supplies, including money and credits, via a given sea pert to a given interior point.(b). These supplies then to be despatched to the Black Sea in transports, convoyed by warships; marines for escort, after landing, also to be sent:-(c).   Supreme Council thon to be notified that despairing of Ottoman good faith U.S.Ao cannot accept a Mandate but is willing to aid the Armenian Republic,   At the seme time the expedition (b) to be notified and the President to announce that he accepted the duty of fixing boundaries.(d).   The Sublime Porte to be Informed that U.S.A. will view as an unfriendly act any aggression upon Armenia until her territory and frontiers are settled.(e).   The expedition then to be landed.   Officers to be sent to train the Armenian Army.(f).    Public opinion in U.S.A. to be organised to forceCongress to make the appropriations npcessary to carry on.
(2.).      The Allied Powers to be notified that:-(a).        The U.S. ^Government having recognised the armenian Republic cannot regard with Indifference any attempt to deprive Armenia of her independence,(b)o        Having accepted the office of Arbitrator on the Armenian frontiers the U%S*Ao occupy - a* peculiar position and will at all times be prepared to interpose to prevent any encroachment on or despoilment of Armenia0Such schemes are obviously surrounded by almost insurmountable difficulties, and no results can be counted upon.   At the same time, the men concerned in them form a remarkable combination, and. it is difficult to estimate the possibilities.,The above mentioned activities are reflected in a conver-sation between ou* Ambassador (who has been instructed to inform the U.S.A*Government emphatically that we should warmly appreciate American co-operation in support of Armenia) and the Secretary for Foreign Affairs when the latter asked if the Allies considered the arrangements for control of the Straits and of Constantinople satisfactory, and was told that they represented the best of the bad choice of possibilities left by the refusal of the U.S-.-A- to assume any responsibility.   On this the Secretary asked if the Supreme Council would re-open the cuestion if the U.S.A. were prepared to assume responsibility -for Constantinople.   The &quot;President is evidently in favour of this, as well as of assuming responsibility for Armenia.On the 1st instant the Senate adopted, a resolution declining to grant authority for an Armenian Mandate.The Armenian Government asks for an instalment of one million sterling and for large quantities of munitions as well as aeroplanes, armoured cars, mountain guns and lorries.   A shipload of arms has been, despatched to Armenia, a small proportion of which will be allocated to Georgia,A report of the 9th June states that Armenian troops met and defeated Bolshevist cavalry at Delijan,ITAItf.The &quot;Roma&quot; left Genoa on the 27th May for her cruise in South American waters,The &quot;Europa&quot;, a converted merchant ship formerly known as the &quot;Quarto&quot;, which has been used both as a seaplane carrier and a submarine depot ship in the Italian Navy, is being refitted for use as a merchant ship and will be shortly sold at Speaia Dockyard by order of the Ministry of Marine.   Her tonnage is 4,142 gross, and a reserve price of 5,500,000 lire has been fixed.The battleship &quot;Conte di Cavour&quot; &quot;has arrived in Cherbourg in connection with the distribution of enamy shipping concentrated in that port.ALBANIA,Press reports represent the situation of the Italian forces as extremely serious..   Santi Quaranta has been evacuated, Dulcigno and Antivari abandoned.    Small garrison posts have been captured and their officers ill treated.
Valona is besieged;   the heights round the town have been abandoned, and only the town itself is being held.The Italian Ministry for Foreign Affairs Informed the British Ambassador on the 10th that he did not believe Valona to be in any serious danger and that reinforcements were on their way. In this connection it is reported that the crews of  he ships chartered to convoy these reinforcements from Taranto, to Valona refused duty and had to be replaced by sailors from the fleet. This incident is yet one more example of the spirit prevailing throughout Italy.SYRIA.The Emir Feisal has addressed a further message to H.M. Government, In which, after calling attention to his previous reports regarding the discontent of the country, and especially the recent disturbances in the French zone, he expresses the fear that complete loss of public security throughout the Arab country would be the result of his leaving fOr the West.   He asks whether in the circumstances it is considered that he should accept the invitation, or whether it would not be pre-transferable that Delegates should be sent to him.   Lord Allenby, in forwarding his message, states that he has told Feisal that he considers it improbable that the Peace Conference will send a delegate to Syria.   As Lord Allenby considers, however, that the Emir:s absence from Syria would certainly lead to disorder, he has suggested to him that it would be better for him to choose representatives whom he can send with full powers to act for Mm.Northern Syria and Ci-licia.The French Government has informed H.IvLGovernment that there is no Question of the French withdrawing from Cilicia. It is admitted that one or two small exposed posts are being evacuated for military reasons.CHINA.The Commander-in-Chief has reported that H.M.S.&quot;Cairo&quot; has been sent to Hankow, as the situation in the Upper Yangtse may necessitate placing armed guards on board British steamers.MISCELLANEOUS HOME INTELLIGENCE.Defence of Coastguard Stations T3y Royal Marines.   The 8th Battalion, KbyaTTiOirInes, wr&amp;h headquarters in &quot;ft.M. S. Cumberland&quot; Haulbowline Dockyard, have now been distributed by Destroyers and Patrol Vessels among the more important Coastguard Stations in the Southern and Northern district of the Irish Coast,General Situation in Ireland.The railwaymen and dockers persist in their refusal to unload or handle, munitions or military stores for the forces in Ireland.   At North Wall, Dublin, all negotiations between the . men and the L,&amp; N.W.Railway Company have failed, and a complete lock-out prevails.   Barbed wire from the s. s*&quot;Eblana&quot; and motor lorries from the R.F.A.&quot;Bacchus&quot; were unloaded by the Naval and Military authorities at Cork under great dl fficultiea. Thesituation
The situation in S.W.Ireland has further deteriorated and illegal drilling is being carried out by the I.-R.A&quot;. on a larger scale than before.   Combined operations between.the Military and the R. I. C. are effecting an improvement in the morale of the latter, and the arrival of troops in many small towns and villages is having a steadying effect on the popula-tion generally.Attacks on Police Barracks and Coastguard Stations and the destruction of Court Houses continues unabated.   Mails were held up on eight occasions during the week and official correspondence confiscated.   On the 9th June military despatch riders were held up by armed men in broad daylight.The transfer^of H.M.S. &quot;Diamond;&apos; to the New Zealand Government TaaF^etc.^canceireoT.ADMIRALTY,  S,W.16th June 1920.

</content>
</cab>
