<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/107/0 images: 468-479</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.  June, 1920.SECRET. CP. 1491.THE LABOUR SITUATION.Report from the Ministry of Labour for the week ending16th June, 1920.CONTENTS.Part I: General. Nil.Part II: Departmental. Women&apos;s Training.Part III: The Labour and Socialist Press.Topics of Discussion; Ireland, Eussia and Hungary; The Labour and Socialist Movement; Government Policy ; International Labour Organisation.Part IV : General Topics.General Survey of the Week; The Unemployment Position; Russia, Ireland and Hungary ; Women, Young Persons and Children (Employment) Bill; The Cost of Living ;. Employment Exchanges ; Industrial Courts Acts, 1919 ; Trade Unions and Ex-Service Men ; The Trade Union Movement: &quot; General Staff &quot; Proposals ; International Labour Office ; Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain ; South Wales Miners&apos; Federation ; National Union of Railwaymen; Scottish Employers&apos; Federation of Iron and Steel Founders Trade Union Topics ; Communist Party ; American Federation of Labour.Part I: General. Nil.Part II. Departmental.Women&apos;&apos;s Training.Under the arrangements laid down at present, the training of women by the Ministry of Labour will be brought to a close on the 30th June. There are signs that this may interrupt this work at the time when the public are realising the full value of the schemes which the Ministry have organised. For some months after the arrangements of the Ministry had taken definite shape the number of women brought into training was comparatively small. This was due mainly to lack of vacant premises available in districts where training was needed. The last few months, however, have seen a very considerable rise in the number of women in training. On the 14th February there were 2,341 women actually receiving training. By the 1st May the number had risen to 4,025. The number has since declined somewhat, but this is due solely to the fact that as schemes in operation expired, it was,(0 2011)  150  6/20 h &amp; s 2 K
impossible to replace them by others giving adequate instruction before the 30th June. By the 8th May, 237 schemes had been sanctioned, of which 157 provided industrial training and 72 training in domestic courses, the remainder providing for single individuals. The number of women who had finished their training by that date was 2,882, of whom 1,597 had received industrial training, and 1,285 domestic training. There were then 3,876 women still receiving Draining, of whom 3,185 were receiving industrial training and 691 domestic training. A few short courses sanctioned since the 8th May have raised the total. In all between the 31st May, 1919, and the 22ncl May, 1920, the Ministry have been responsible for training 6,842 women. The range of women&apos;s occupations over which this training has been spread is very considerable. Courses have been provided for domestic service, children&apos;s nursing, waiting, laundry work, millinery, dressmaking and tailoring, glove making, the weaving of velvet, linen and cotton, boot closing, textile making, upholstery and carpet making, hosiery making, comptometer operating, buffing and burnishing, chemical work, and a number of other occupations. The demand has varied considerably in different parts of the country. In the London area, Yorkshire and the East Midlands, the demand has been far more for industrial training rather than for domestic training. In Scotland and Wales, on the other hand, more than twice as many women have taken up domestic courses as have taken industrial courses. In the aggregate, domestic service, presents the largest total of the whole country, 1,91.1 women having been trained for such work, but dressmaking and tailoring have run this number close, the figures being respectively 1,685 and 1,515. In clerical work, 366 women have been provided with training, in millinery 158, in laundry 129, and in hosiery manufacture 106.The general industrial position as regards the employment of women would seem to indicate that there is still a considerable field open for the continuation of women&apos;s training. In many occupations there is a shortage of skilled women&apos;s labour. Through-out Yorkshire and East Midlands Division, for example, there is a shortage of skilled textile workers and of skilled workers in the wholesale clothing industry. In the London and South-Eastern Division there is a shortage in a variety of trades, such as needlework, laundry work, cardboard box making, book sewing, while shortage of domestic servants throughout the country is too well known to require comment. The statistics of the Employment Exchanges show that despite the fact that the demand for women registered at the Exchanges is practically equally balanced by the number of women registered for employment, there is, as a matter of fact, a considerable shortage of suitable women workers. A large proportion of the applicants at the Exchanges are married women who, in the majority of, cases, cannot be considered as generally available for employment. It is necessary to bear in mind, moreover, that a very considerable number of women are still being discharged from Army Pay Offices and other Government services, who in very many cases require and are capable of training, but who will no longer find courses instituted by the Ministry open to them.Even if the work of the Ministry in this direction, however, is to be brought to a speedy close, its effects will not have been restricted to the training of some 7,000 women, however valuable this work may have been in itself. The Ministry have shown that it is possible by means of short intensive courses to train unskilled women and girls into workers with quite sufficient skill for ordinary industrial purposes, and there are indications that the lesson has not been overlooked. A good deal has been done to break down the theory commonly held that in order to produce efficient workers it is necessary to train girls fresh from school. Two examples may be given of such effects of the Ministry&apos;s activities. A damask weaving training course instituted in employers&apos; works at Dunfermline has proved so successful that five firms have asked for the institution of a further course to provide instruction for 150 women, in spite of the fact that the course cannot be finished before the 30th June ; they are willing to retain the women after that date at their own expense and paying the full learners&apos; rate until training is completed. At Hamilton, again, where courses have been provided in the making of women&apos;s clothing, laundry work and cookery, the results have been so successful that the local education authority are proposing to institute similar courses when the Training Department are no longer in a position to continue their work.
(C 2011)2K2Part III. The Labour and Socialist Press. Topics of Discussion.The reports of Lord Hunter&apos;s Committee of.Inquiry into the Indian disturbances,, which took place in the spring of last year, again receive much notice in the papers reviewed this week, but the principal question discussed is the conduct the trade union movement ought to adopt on the question of making and handling munitions, belonging either tpihe British or to the Polish Governments. It is remarkable that the award of the National Wages Board with regard to railwaymen&apos;s wages receives practically no notice in these papers.Ireland, Russia and Hungary.This question of munitions is mainly discussed in the light of the interview between the Prime Minister and the executive of the N.U.R. which took place on the 3rd inst., and of the action of the executive of the N.U.R. in withdrawing their embargo on Polish munitions and in recommending their Dublin members to return to work. The more moderate papers the &quot;Labour Leader&quot; and the &quot;Nation&quot; deal with the Prime Ministers statement to the N.U.R., while the more extreme papers devote themselves to bitter attacks upon the N.U.R. executive for their action.&quot; The Call,&quot; the &quot; Socialist &quot; and the &quot; Workers&apos; Dreadnought&quot; all contain bitter attacks upon Mr. J. H. Thomas. The first paper thinks that the withdrawal of the Polish embargo must have been due either to cowardice or to treachery. The second paper contains the astonishing assertion that &quot; the executive of the N.U.R. has basely betrayed the Labour Movement: in consideration for a few extra shillings per week, they have agreed to order railwaymen everywhere to raise the boycott on the transport of munitions to Ireland.&quot; The &quot; workers Dreadnought,&quot; however, has no desire that Mr. Thomas should be the only trade union leader to suffer obloquy on this account. It suggests that Mr. C. T. Cramp also should .either have fesigned his position or else have appealed to the membership of the union before he signed the second Polish circular. Further, this paper would like to see a strenuous rank and file movement started within the N.U.R. on the strength of these events. With reference to the protest of the executive of the National Transport Workers&apos; Federation to an appeal from the Hands-off Russia Committee to the members of its constituent bodies, to which attention was drawn in this Report last week (p. 259), the &quot; Workers&apos; Dreadnought &quot; agrees that the protest has touched a weak spot in the organisation of the Committee. The Transport Workers&apos; Executive drew attention to the fact that the notepaper of the Committee showed many prominent trade union leaders as titular heads of the movement. The comment of the &quot; Workers&apos; Dreadnought &quot; is &quot; that the Committee should not assist in maintaining the popularity of these leaders by handing to them unearned laurels.&quot; The policy of the National Union of Railwaymen. and the action of the executive of the National Transport Workers&apos; Federation do not receive much express approval in these papers except in the &quot; New Statesman,&quot; the &quot; Clarion,&quot; and the N.U.R.&apos;s own journal the &quot;Railway Review.&quot; The &quot;Railway Review&quot; defends the official policy of its union and protests against what it considers to be unfair criticism from the &quot; Daily Herald.&quot; The &quot; New Statesman &quot; rules that &quot; the matter is-one which ought not to be dealt with by isolated unions, but by the trade union movement as a whole.&quot; In the &quot; Clarion &quot; Mr. A. M. Thompson deals at great length with the annual conference of the National Transport Workers&apos; Federation and is unsympathetic to the claims of the Irish deputation.The more moderate papers avoid any criticism of the N.U.R. by expending their-critical energy entirely upon the Prime Minister. In a leading article the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; asserts that the Prime Ministers statement to the N.U.R. deputation was a specious argument, based upon a false statement of facts. In the view of this paper the railwaymen&apos;s action is not an attempt to influence political decisions by disorganising the industry of the country : it is merely a case of passive resistance to military measures for which the Government have ;no authority from the electorate of the United Kingdom.. &quot; There is a vital difference between passive resistance by industrial inactivity and active: resistance to the orders of the Government.&quot; It will be remembered that the argument that direct action was a form of passive resistance was very popular with the leaders of the I.L.P. when the question of direct action on intervention in Russia was being mooted last year. The opinion of the &quot; Nation &quot; is very similar, though emphasis is put upon the unrepresentative character of the present House of Commons rather than upon the doctrine of passive resistance.   This paper suggests that Labour should take advantage.
of the unexampled opportunity which is being offered to it, and should boldly demand the withdrawal of the British Army from Ireland. An article in the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; by Mr. Patrick Thompson shows the intimate connection between the conveyance of Polish munitions intended for use against Russia and of British Government munitions intended lor use in Ireland. Mr. Thompson wrote before the withdrawal of the embargo on Polish munitions, and contrasts the action of the N.U.R. in the two matters. The &quot; British Citizen &quot; whole-heartedly approves of the Prime Ministers statement.The boycott which the International Federation of Trade Unions has ordered to be imposed on Hungary on and after 20th inst. is commended in &quot; The Call.&quot; &quot;;,The Call,&quot;&apos; however, does not appreciate how little approval has been given to this measure in this country, and confuses the attitude of the International Federation of Transport Workers with that of the British National Transport Workers&apos; Federation. Mr. Philip Snowden expresses his disapproval of the boycott. He points out that if fully carried out it would stop the work of the Famine Relief Committees. He thinks that it will be the very people whose condition it is desired to ameliorate who will sutler most from the boycott.The Labour and Socialist Movement.The action of the Parliamentary Labour Party in refusing to adopt the proposal that Mr. Ramsay Macdonald should be appointed as technical advisor to the party* receives wide notice in the I.L.P. papers. Both Mr. P. Snowden and the London correspondent of the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; recommend the &quot; left wing &quot; of the Parliamentary Party to separate themselves out from the rest of the party and form a distinct group. Mr. Snowden says that they must take matters into their own hands and fight their own battles on the floor of the House, &quot; as did the I.L.P. group during the latter years of the last Parliament.&quot; Mr. Ramsay Macdonald, in his weekly article in &quot; Forward,&quot; makes an attack upon the present Parliamentary Labour Party. &quot; It adopts inefficient means for doing its Parlia-mentary work, and does not use the capacities at its disposal. If the reformation cannot come quickly from within: the party must be reformed from without.&quot; Mr. Ramsay Macdonald also urges the need for the continued separate existence of the I.L.P. within the Labour Party. He claims that the I.L.P. is the heart and life of the Labour Party and insists that it must preserve a distinct and separate individuality. The &quot; Workers&apos; Dread-nought &quot; criticises the agenda of the annual conference of the Labour Party and points out that only the reactionaries have been, nominated for the vacant positions on the executive. It observes that the British Socialist Party have not put forward a resolution setting forth a Communist programme and asks how they can justify their remaining in the Labour Party as Communists. In &quot; The Call &quot; Mr. F. Willis replies to remarks made by Miss Sylvia Pankhtirst, published in the &quot; Socialist &quot; last week, with reference to the proposed national conference to form a united Communist Party. He complains that Miss Pankhurst is adopting an impossible attitude in this matter and is unwilling to sacrifice her own personal prejudices for the sake of the Communist Party.fGovernment Policy.The Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Bill receives much atten-tion in view of the second reading debate. The &quot; Woolwich Pioneer &quot; gives a full report of Mr. Graham&apos;s speech in this debate. Mr. Philip Snowden criticises the Parliamentary Labour Party because only 20 of its members voted against the second reading. Mr. Tom Myers, M.P., in the &quot; Labour Pioneer,&quot; doubts whether the increase of rent proposed to be allowed by the Bill can be justified. His view is that the property owners&apos; hostility to the continuation of these Acts has been bought off by these provisions for increasing rents. He is prepared to admit, however, that the Bill contains many welcome features.The decision of the Government not to impose any levy on war wealth had been anti-cipated by these papers and would appear to be rather welcome to the Independent Labour Party writers, who believe that it will now allow them to proceed energetically with their campaign for a general levy on capital.International Labour Organisation.The &quot; New Statesman &quot; devoted a special article to the Genoa International Labour Conference which was to commence on the 15th inst. The agenda of the conference is dealt with in detail, and its importance is fully recognised. The &quot; New Statesman &quot; is of the opinion that the international regulation of conditions of labour in the mercantile* Cf. this Report last week, pp. 260-61. t Cf. below, p. 275.
Part IV. General Topics.General Survey of the week with regard to the industrial situation, the strikes actually in progress are relatively-unimportant, but a critical situation with regard to wages demands exists in several important industries. The position is most critical with regard to gas workers, but the position as to printers is taking a more hopeful turn. There is considerable discontent among agricultural labourers on account of the recent award of the Central Wages Board,, which is being exploited in competition by the Workers&apos; Union and the Agricultural Labourers&apos; Union, while conditions in the building trades are still unsettled. The Indus-trial Court will commence the periodical review of wages in the engineering trades on the 29th June. The annual conference of the N.U.R. will begin on 5th July, and of the M.F.G.B. on 6th July, and both these conferences will have to take important wages, decisions.The opening of the International Labour Conference at Genoa to discuss seamen&apos;s. conditions on the 15th June is perhaps one of the most significant events of the year.The most important question pending at the close of the week under review was the meeting of the Parliamentary Committee of the T.U.C. which decided to summon a special meeting of the Congress to determine the attitude of the trade union movement on the questions of Ireland, Russia and Hungary.The Unemployment Position.The number of H.M. Forces policies current for the week ended the 4th June, 1920,. was 193,383 (192,119 lodged by men and 1,364 by women). The previous week there were 196,508 policies current, 195,192 lodged by men and 1,356 by women.67,560 unemployment books (46,588. lodged by males and 20,972 by females) remained, lodged by workers under the Unemployment Insurance Acts at the 4th June, 1920, an increase of 663 since the 28th May. At the latter date 44,938 books were lodged by males and 21,959 by females (a total of 66,987).The total live register at all Employment Exchanges at week ended the 4th June was, 265,276 men, 45,669 women and 20,952 juveniles, compared with 264,199 men, 43,749&apos; women and 20,196 juveniles a week ago (the 28th May), and 275,926 rn^n, 48,443 women and 23,935 juveniles a month ago.Russia, Ireland and Hungary.With regard to the attitude of the trade.union movement on these three questions,, the most important developments have occurred during the week in connection with the Russian question. Mr. Ben Turner and Mr. Tom Shaw, M.P., who have been members, of the Labour Party and Trades Union Congress Joint Commission of Enquiry to Russia,, have returned to England, bearing an Interim Report for presentation to the annual conference of the Labour Party. Should the Parliamentary Committee of the T.U.C. decide to summon a special Trades Union Congress, it may be articipated that there will be Sufficient time for the whole of the Commission to return and for the T.U.C. to have before it a final report on Russia. Interviews with Messrs. Turner and Shaw have been given wide publicity in the press and it is sufficient to say that neither of them has been won over by the Bolshevists and that the reports of their experiences apparently will weaken rather than strengthen the position of the English extremists who so sedulouply cultivated the creed of Bolshevism.(b 2011) 2 K 3marine may lead the way to even more important developments in the direction of an international shipping code, which will facilitate the international regulation of questions relating to ports and harbours and even of the problem of the &quot; open door.&quot; The &quot; New Statesman,&quot; also, believes that international labour legislation cannot proceed very far so long as it is confined to dealing with industry in general terms. &quot; It must, if it is to be of real benefit, deal separately with the distinct problems which each industry presents.&quot;&apos; This Genoa conference is of course the first conference under the Labour Part of the Peace-Treaty to be held to consider the conditions of a particular industry. .
The actual Interim Report of the Delegation is signed by the T.U.C. and Labour Party members and is endorsed by the Independent Labour Party delegates. It is confined to matters of special urgency and states that the investigations of the delegation are still pro-ceeding. The report strongly condemns the blockade of Russia, and states that the hostile policy of the Allies has resulted in rallying practically all the parties in Russia to the support of the Soviet Government for the purposes of national defence. It recommends that the entire British Labour movement should demand the unconditional recognition of the present Russian government and the removal of the last vestige of blockade and intervention. *  1This report was published on the 12th inst., but much more remarkable is a manifesto addressed by Lenin to British workers which appeared on the 11th inst. Atten-tion may be drawn here to four points in this document. Lenin slights the Labour mission in two respects. First, he refuses to make any use of it as a third and neutral party in order to arrive at an agreement with the British Government; and secondly, by implications-tion he disputes its right to be* representative of the workers of this country. He refers to the delegation in every place as composed of workers, rather than as being representative of workers. He regrets that the bourgeois prejudices of the majority of labour, Parliamentary and trade union leaders found expression in the composition of the delegation. The third point is his statement that Miss Sylvia Pankhurst has been arrested, and is suffering from the &quot;white terror &quot; in this country. This is. of course, wholly untrue ; but Lenin&apos;s concern at this rumour shows how he has misjudged the position here. Finally, there is his answer to the request that he should prove the complicity of the British Government in the Polish offensive, which consists in the suggestion that it was the duty of the delega-tion to prove this by revolutionary means, and the seizure of Foreign Office documents. Provided that Trades Union Congresses and Labour Party Annual Conferences treat this letter as a guide to Bolshevist mentality, it may be judged that its influence will be strongly to reinforce the more conservative sections of these meetings, who are in a majority, and who have always been very reserved and guarded in their reception of Bolshevist claims.With reference to the position in Ireland, there is no change to report with regard to the railwaymen employed by the London and North-Western Railway Company at Dublin. Negotiations were opened in Dublin on the 7th inst. between the. Strike Com-mittee and the local officials of the Company with a view to a settlement of the dispute on the 9th inst. The position of the men was that they would resume work only in order to leave then? leaders free to act on their behalf, while the Company insisted that the men should agree, without any reservations, to handle all traffic. Mr. C. T. Cramp left for Dublin on the 12th inst., and arranged a further conference, which took place on the .14th inst. Both the men and the railway company adhered to their previous decisions, and no settlement was arrived at. Mr. Cramp has suggested in a public statement that he believes the Company to be acting under instructions from the - Government. The North Wall branch of the N.U.R. has passed a resolution regarding its grave disappointment at the attitude of their executive in refusing official support to their movement. Apparently, further developments will wait upon the Bristol Conference of the Irish branches of the N.U.R., to which reference has been made above.The executive of the Irish Trades Union Congress and Labour Party adopted a manifesto on the 8th June, which was issued in Dublin on the 9th. The manifesto states that the Transport Workers will be supported by the organised workers in every other Irish, industry in their (refusal not to be parties to the attempted reconquest of Ireland by British military forces. All Irish people are recommended to rally to the support of the men, and a fund has been opened by this body in order that this support may take a practical form. Attention has been drawn above to the resolutions of the M.F.G.B. conference on this matter. It is reported that the executive of this body has agreed to meet the Parliamentary Committee of the British Trades Union Congress in order to put its views before them.No action has been taken in this c ountry during the week under review with regard to the boycott of Hungary ordered by the International Federation of Trade Unions and several prominent people in Socialist spheres, notably Mr. Brailsford and Mr. Philip Snowden, have expressed doubts as to the wisdom of the boycott. The French confederation-tion Generate du Travail has issued an appeal to French trade unions to observe the order of the International Federation.In order to influence the attitude of the Trade Union movement on these matters the &quot; Daily Herald &quot; in the last few days has been putting forth a series of pseudo-academic -articles on the question of &quot;.direct action,&quot; intended to be an exposure of &quot; Parliamentary
&quot;Democracy.&quot; The Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union Congress have been reminded that their action last year in refusing to summon a special congress to deal with the questions of Russian intervention, conscientious objectors, and conscription, was censured by the Glasgow Conference in the September of last year.Women, Young Persons and Children (Employment) Bill.This Bill received its second reading in the House of Commons on the 10th June without a division, and has been referred to Standing Committee A.The Cost of Living.There is nothing further to report with regard to the Special Committee of Inquiry representative of the Trades Union Congress, the Labour Party, and the Co-operative Movement, which is to consider the cause of high prices and to discuss the ways and means of bringing down the cost of living.The City of London branch of the I..L.P. held a conference on the 12th inst., to which delegates from Socialist, Trade Union, Co-operative and ex-Service men&apos;s organisations were invited. The conference considered the question of high prices. Mr. Philip Snowden pleaded for a graduated capital levy as the first step towards this end, but argued that there was no final solution except by the destruction of the competitive system. The conference resolved that international action should be taken for controlling the opera-tions of international trusts, and for organising, the supply and distribution of raw materials and the supply of products for countries impoverished by the war; that there should be a complete cessation of wars for commercial and financial gain. A resolu-tion was also passed demanding freedom and justice for co-operative societies, and calling upon the working classes to support the co-operative movement.Employment Exchanges.The Minister of Labour has appointed a departmental committee of inquiry &quot;to examine the working and administration of the Employment Exchanges in Great Britain and to advise as to their future.&quot; The committee will consist of the following persons : The Right Hon. George N. Barnes, M.P. (Chairman), Sir Philip Lloyd-Greame, M.C., M.P., Sir Charles Sykes, M.P., Mr. A. Hayday, M.P., Mr. Trevelyan Thomson, M.P., Mr. Michael B. U. Dewar (Managing Director, Leeds Forge Company, Ltd., Leeds, and Director of T. F. Firth &amp; Sons, Ltd., Brighouse), Mrs. Herbert Lewis, Miss Julia Varley (Woman Organiser of Workers&apos; Union, Birmingham), Mr. W. J. Mair (Chairman of the Luton Employment Committee), Sir Robert Lockhart (Chairman of the Kirkcaldy Employment Committee), Mr. J. Vaughan Edwards, O.B.E. (Chairman of the Swansea Employment Committee), Mr. George Hearn, J.P. (Chairman of the Camberwell Employment Com-mittee), Professor D. H. MacGregor, M.C. (Professor of Political Economy in University of Manchester). Mr. J. S. Nicholson (Assistant Secretary, Ministry of Labour), will act as secretary to the committee.Industrial Courts Act, 1919. ^The Court of Inquiry appointed under this Act to inquire into the application of coal tippers and trimmers for the establishment of two continuous shifts instead of broken shifts in Bristol Channel ports has now issued its report. The men&apos;s claim for two con-tinuous shifts of eight hours each, viz. from 6 a.m. to 2 p.m., and from 2 p.m. to 10 p.m., has been conceded subject to specified reservations. The night shift is thus dispensed with. The Court recommend that the proposed system should be put into operation as from the 14th June, and that there should be reserved to the employers the right to claim that a third shift be put on should the requirements of the trade warrant it, the necessity of this, in case of a difference of opinion, to be referred to a Court of Inquiry to be constituted under the Industrial Courts Act.Trade Unions and Ex-Service Men.        &apos; ,The speech by Earl Haig at the thirty-fifth annual general meeting of the National Association for the Employment of Ex-Soldiers, which was held on the 8th inst., has attracted very wide notice. It has provoked the usual denials from trade union leaders, ,among which may be noted a statement by Mr. S. Bradley, the London District Secretary -of the A.S.E. Mr. Bradley states that the Government Training Scheme is a fiasco, and that employers only acknowledge it because it allows them to have the services of a man
at a cheaper rate than even a juvenile. He argues tliat employers are deliberately creating unemployment at the present time in order that they may be strong enough to reduce wages on the termination in September this year of the extension, under the Industrial Courts Act, 1919, of the Wages (Temporary Regulation) Act. It is interesting to observe,, however, that in&apos; some quarters an attempt is being made to press a neutral view on the matter. It is being pointed out that the.problem of finding employment for ex-Service men is not a temporary difficulty and will recur at all times of trade depression, and that it is, therefore, in the interest of both ex-Service men and trade unions that the whole question of fluctuations of employment should be tackled. In this connection some reference has been made to the Unemployment Insurance Bill.The Trade Union Movement: &quot; General Staff&quot; Proposals.It is reported that the Co-ordination Committee has now completed its second Interim Report to the Trades Union Congress.   This report is stated to cover the whole question of the reorganisation of the industrial side of the trade union movement, but postpones the questions of joint action between the industrial, political and co-operative movement,, and also of the organisation of research and other special departments for a later report,.International Labour Office.The Governing Body of the International Labour Office held its fourth meeting on the 8th and 9th inst. at Genoa, under the presidency of M. Fontaine (France).  At its sitting on the 8th inst. it appointed the Secretariat for the Genoa Conference, which opened on the 15th inst.  M. Albert Thomas was appointed Secretary-General.  At the meeting; on the 9th inst. reports were received from the British Government laying stress on the importance of the adoption of international regulations with regard to working hours for-seamen, and trusting that the forthcoming Conference would reach an agreement on this matter just to both officers and sailors, and with proper consideration for the special difficulties of service at sea.   It was added that the British delegates would do all in their power to secure the adoption of an international agreement with these aims in view.   On the suggestion of M. Albert Thomas the question of a weekly day of rest and the insti-tution of the &quot; English Week &quot; were put on the agenda to be submitted to the next Inter-national Labour Conference, which is to be held at Geneva next - year.   The questions of minimum rates of pay, State insurance, annual holidays, and the democratisation of industry, were left over for consideration at a later meeting of the Governing Body. On the request of an Hungarian Labour representative and under the terms of the Peace Treaty with Hungary, which authorises the International Labour Office to institute a. Commission of Inquiry into conditions of employment, the Director was instructed by the Committee to arrange for the appointment of a Commission of Inquiry into the alleged &quot; White Terror &quot; in Hungary.   In view of present circumstances nothing was done with regard to the appoint-ment of a Commission of Inquiry into conditions in Russia.   The seat of the InternationaL Labour Office is to be transferred to Geneva, where the Committee will meet again on the 5th. October.Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain.The special national conference of the Miners&apos; Federation to discuss the action to be taken in regard to the increase in the price of coal, which became operative last month, met in London on the 10th inst. The executive met on the previous day and decided to submit two proposals to the special conference : (1) that, with a view to securing an advance in wages for the miners, the executive be instructed to examine carefully the data regarding the finances of the industry, which it is understood the Coal Controller is about to publish ; (2) that a special day be allocated to the discussion of the executive com--mittee&apos;s report on this matter at the annual conference of the federation which will open at Leamington on 6th July. These two proposals of the executive were adopted by the full, conference. It is understood that representatives of the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation were actively opposed to the policy of postponing the claim for increased wages. In com-communicating the official report to the Press, Mr. Straker expressed his regret that the M.F.G.B. was being forced into making another wages demand, and stated that the Government and the House of Commons, by their action with regard to the cost of living,, were entirely responsible for the new movement. The conference also passed unani-mously a resolution protesting against British military domination of Ireland, demanding the immediate withdrawal of British troops, and urging the Parliamentary Committee of the T.U.C. to expedite the calling of a special Trades Union Congress in order that organised Labour might determine its attitude towards the production and handling of munitions.
of war destined for Ireland and Poland. A noteworthy feature of the conference was the fact that Mr. Smillie once more occupied the chair.-South Wales Miners&apos; Federation.The annual conference of the South Wales. Miners&apos; Federation opened on the 14th inst. The executive^ report recommends the adoption of resolutions with regard to the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Acts, that in future the amount of compensation shall &apos;he equivalent to pre-accident wages, which rule should also be applied to men already ih receipt of compensation. It is also recommended that the maximum compensation for fatal accidents should be increased to  600. The enlargement of the Schedule of Indus-trial Diseases is also urged and the extension of the seven-hour system to all workers in and about the mines. The conference has passed a resolution recommending the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain to modify the national strike rule so that a bare majority, instead of a two-thirds majority, should suffice for the calling of a strike. A resolution has also been adopted urging the abolition of &quot; summer-time.&quot; It is not obvious why the South Wales miners should object to &quot; summer-time &quot; ; but it is interesting to note that factory operatives in many parts of Italy have refused to observe the Italian &quot; summer-time &quot; regulations. With reference to the question of the payment of increased subscriptions-tions to the M.F.G.B., it should be noted that it has been decided by a special conference of the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation held in Cardiff on the 5th inst. to take another ballot on this question. The members of the federation will have before them an explicit official statement to the effect that, unless an increase be agreed upon the S.W.M.F. will auto-matically become dissociated from the M.F.G.B.National Union of Railwaymen.The annual general meeting of the N.U.R., which is the final governing authority of the union, will meet at Belfast on 5th July for its ordinary annual meeting. The confer-ence will have to come to a decision on two matters of considerable importance, namely, whether to accept or reject the award of the National Wages Board, details of which were given in this report last week, and whether to endorse or to reject the policy its executive has been pursuing on the question of Irish and Polish munitions. With regard to the National Wages Board, Mr. J. H. Thomas has defended the award before the mass meetings of railwaymen at Battersea and at Paddington. Mr. Thomas has put two arguments to the men : firstly, that the award gives the men the uttermost farthing of possible increase ; and secondly, that the railwaymen are public servants and every case respecting them is in the end judged and determined by public opinion. Mr. Thomas does not believe that continual threats of strikes, and such unofficial action as the &quot; work to rule &quot; movement, bring public opinion over the side of the men. Mr. C. T. Cramp has circulated the award of the National Wages Board to his branches for consideration at branch meetings. In his circular he points out that a strike is the only alternative to the acceptance of the award. Members are advised not merely to study the schedules of increases, but to go through the report and to study the proceedings which led up to it. With reference to the point made in opposition to the men&apos;s claim that increased wages would have to be levied upon traders and passengers, Mr. Cramp-suggests that economies and improvements might well be effected in railway working by the adoption of some form of national ownership. The award, therefore, should not be considered merely from the wages point of view, but members should weigh the question in their minds with a view to securing such changes in ownership and management as would secure the desired results. With reference to the question of conveying munitions, Mr. Thomas and Mr. Cramp, in speeches, and the executive of the union; in official resolutions, have been maintaining the position that the whole problem is too big and too serious to allow any one union to deal with it. They reject the view that the transport occupations have any greater responsibilities in such matters as these than the productive occupations. The special conference of the Irish branches of the N.U.R. will be held at Bristol on the 16th and 17th inst. and will deal specifically with the Irish situation.Scottish Employers&apos; Federation of Iron and Sted Founders.This Federation have expelled from their membership the firm of Messrs. Alley &amp; MacLellan, Ltd., Glasgow (which firm is mainly controlled by Messrs. William Beardmore .&amp; Co., Ltd.), on account of their action in conceding rates in excess of the uniform standard Tate which has been established throughout Scotland as the result of negotiations between the Associated Iron Moulders of Scotland and the Federation.  The effects of the expulsion
may be far-reaching as other founders, it is reported, have decided to refuse to transact1-business with this firm and certain other establishments controlled by Messrs. William. Beardmore &amp; Co., Ltd.Trade Union Topics.Amalgamated Engineering Umon.* Mr. J. T. Brownlie (A.S.E.) has been appointed, president of the Amalgamated Engineering Union; Mr. Tom Mann (A.S.E.) general secretary; Mr. A. H. Smethurst (A.S.E.) assistant secretary, trade union section; and Mr. C. A. Bamford (A.S.E.) assistant secretary, State insurance section.The new amalgamation will take over all the officials of the trade unions it is. absorbing, but from this allocation of the principal posts it is clear that in the new Amalgamated Engineering Union the very decided preponderating influence will be the old Amalgamated Society of Engineers.The figures of the second ballot taken by the National Society of Brass Workers and Metal Mechanics, on the question of amalgamation with the Amalgamated Engineering Union, showed a vote of 10,504 in favour and 10,199 against. The ballot, therefore, has not provided the necessary majority to effect a fusion.M.F.G.B. and A.S.E. A joint conference of the M.F.G.B. and A.S.E. was held on the 8th inst. to consider the position with regard to trade union demarcation of engineers employed at collieries. It is understood that proposals were put forward by the A.S.E. as a basis for agreement. These were that engineers working at collieries should remain members of the engineers&apos; union, but that M.F.G-.B. and its constituent bodies should have full control in industrial, as opposed to craft, matters. Thus, in case of a stoppage ordered by a miners&apos; union, these engineers would take similar action, and would be eligible for dispute pay from their own union. These questions of demarcation with regard to A.S.E. members employed in collieries have caused considerable trouble in the last two years, and the general question of demarcation is, of course, a vexed one. Any experiment in means of avoiding trouble on this score is, therefore, of interest, and if found practicable might have far-reaching effects.National Federation of General Workers. It is reported that this Federation has decided to establish an Irish Council,^with functions which will be mainly organising and advisory. It will not have power to call a strike without the sanction of the National Federation and the affiliated unions. In practice the activities of this council will be mainly confined to North-East Ulster. Friction may be expected with the Irish Transport and General Workers&apos; Union, should the Federation attempt any extensive organising cam-paign in the South and West of Ireland.National Federation of Professional, Technical, Administrative and Supervisory Workers.-The organisation of this Federationf is proceeding apace from 34, Eccleston Square. Mr. E. H. Walker (Association of Engineering and Shipbuilding Draughtsmen) has been appointed President, Mr. F. G. Walkden (Railway Clerks&apos; Association) Vice-President, Mr. J. Turner (National Union of Shop Assistants, Warehousemen and Clerks) treasurer, Mr. W. C. Keay (Association of Engineering and Shipbuilding Draughtsmen) temporary secretary. The Federation is advertising for applications for the post of full-time paid secretary, for which a minimum salary of  450 is offered. It is proposed to organise district committees of the Federation, apparently for propaganda purposes. The National Union of Clerks is not a member of the Federation, but it is stated that many of its branches are joining these district committees, which have power to admit branches of bodies not affiliated nationally to the Federation. A special sub-committee of the Federation has been appointed to deal with the position of professional workers under the Unemployment Insurance Bill. The Federation has also agreed to set up a joint committee with the Professional Workers&apos; Federation, to take action on matters of common concern.National Amalgamated Union of Shop Assistants, Warehousemen and Cbrks. It is reported that the Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union Congress, at the request of this union, has circulated to all its affiliated societies a special letter dealing with the conditions of employment of young persons in distributive trades. The object of the circular is, first, to persuade the unions to bring pressure to bear upon the Minister of Labour to expedite the application of the Trade Boards Acts to the distributive trades, including the fixing of minimum rates for young persons; and, secondly, to persuade the members of the various Trade Unions in their capacity as parents not to allow their children to accept employment in the distributive trades at less than the minimum scale of wages and. conditions laid down by the union.* For an account of the constitution of this body, see this Eeport, 26th May, 1920, pp. 241-2.f An account of the formation of this body was given in this Report, 18th February, 1920, p. 94.   .
British Funeral WorJcers&apos; Association. The difference with regard to wages now in existence between this Association and the Funeral Furnishers&apos; Association is illustrated by the attitude of the two bodies towards the provision of funerals for deceased disabled ex-Service men under the Ministry of Pensions scheme. The employers&apos; associations are refusing to enter into contracts with local Pensions Committees for the wholesale provision of these funerals. On the other hand, the trade&apos; union offers to assist local committees by supplying labour for &quot; direct labour &quot; schemes. Somewhat similar tactics have been adopted with regard to housing schemes in some towns in Scotland by the joiners.no.w on strike. &apos;&quot;Communist Party.Negotiations have been proceeding for some months between the more extreme socialist organisations for the purpose of forming a United Communist Party, affiliated to the Third International, in Great Britain.The parties originally concerned in the proposal were the British Socialist Party, the Socialist Labour Party, the Workers&apos; Socialist Federation, and the South Wales Socialist Society. The question of affiliation to the Labour Party has proved the main obstacle to agreement. The Socialist Labour Party came to an early decision not to have anything to do with a Communist Party which did not contain a provision in its constitution pro-prohibiting membership of the Labour Party ; and its place m the negotiations has now been taken by the &quot; Communist Unity Group,&quot; consisting of those members of the S.L.P. who have broken away from their party on this issue. The South Wales Socialist Society has also ceased to take part in the conversations. It lias ultimately been decided by the * joint negotiating committee of the remaining three bodies to refer the whole question of the organisation of a new Communist Party for settlement to a specially convened national convention, to which all organisations, groups and societies, accepting the three principles of the dictatorship of the proletariat, the Soviet system and the Third International are to be invited to send delegates. The first duty of the conference may therefore be to decide upon the question of Labour Party affiliation.The executive of the Workers&apos; Socialist Federation has, however, referred the question of participation in this conference to a ballot of its membership, and Miss Sylvia Pankhurst has further complicated the issue by writing to the Socialist Labour Party suggesting that they should attend the Conference and that the decisions of the Conference would not be binding upon the parties represented. This last statement is not in accordance with the decision of the joint committee, on which Miss Pankhurst represented the Workers&apos; Socialist Federation. A further effort of Miss Pankhurst has made the position still worse, from the point of view of Communist unity. She has issued an invitation to all those revolutionary organisations which accept the three principles of Communist unity, given above, and who are also opposed both to Parliamentary action and affiliation to the Labour Party, to attend a conference on the 19th inst. for the purpose of deciding whether or not to be present at the Convention which is to meet on 1st August.It may be judged that the Socialist Labour Party will have nothing further to do with these proposals and invitations ; that the &quot; communist unity group &quot; of expelled S.L.P. members may add themselves to the B.S.P.; and that the new Communist Party cannot include both the W.S.F. and the B.S.P. These negotiations indeed tend to become a quarrel between these groups for the possession of the coveted title of the &quot; Communist Party.&quot;American Federation of Labour.The 40th Annual Convention of the American Federation of Labour opened, at Montreal on the 7th inst. Over 100 delegates were present from all parts of the United States and Canada. Mr. Gompers presided. In the report of the Executive Council satisfaction is expressed that during the year the labour movement maintained a progressive and con-structive policy against the efforts of the extremists. The Report formulates a demand that the United States Government be authorised to buy standard commodities direct from the producers and that these commodities be distributed through regular retail channels at prices to be fixed by the Government. A demand is also to be made that the United States Government should ascertain the amount of excessive war profits taken from the American people from 1916-20, these profits to be taken by the Federal Govern-ment and applied to the extinction of the floating debt and the partial retirement of Liberty Bonds at par in order that the existing inflated structure of currency and credit may be reduced.  The Report favours the establishment of voluntary conference boards
in order to induce co-operation between employers and workers. It also suggests that the control of credit be taken from private financiers and placed in the hands of a public agency to be administered by voluntary and co-operative methods. The report finally declares that the influences which are restricting production are under the control of the employers and not of the workers. The most important decision of the Convention hitherto reported is the decision that all negro workers must be given full membership in the affiliated international unions. On the 12th inst. the Convention adopted a report pre-sented by Mr. Gompers condemning the United States Republican Convention for its refusal to adopt the demands of the American Federation of Labour as its programme., These demands would now be submitted to the Democratic Convention.T. J. MACNAMARA.All inquiries relating to this report should be addressed to :-Intelligence Division,Ministry op Labour,Montagu House, , Whitehall,London, S.W. 1^

</content>
</cab>
