<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/38/0 images: 86-91</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1963CM. (63)13th conclusions copy No.39CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W 1,on Tuesday, 17th December, 1963, at 10.30 a.m.Present:The right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. Quintin Hogg, Q.C.,M.P., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and for the colonies the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P.,    Minister    of    Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Michael Noble, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Joseph Godber, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P., Minister of power the Right Hon. William Deedes, M.P.,Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Lord Dilhorne.ChancellorLordThe Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Secretary of State for Industry, Tradeand    Regional   Development    and president of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Viscount Blakenham,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Chief Secretary to the treasury and Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. Sir Edward Boyle,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Anthony Barber, M.P.,Minister of health the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,M.P., Minister of Public Building and works the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Minister without portfolio the following were also present:The Right Hon. Julian Amery, M.P.,   The Right Hon. Hugh Fraser, M.P.,Minister of Aviation (Item 4) Secretary of State for Air (Item 4)The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . A. L. M. cary mr. P. A. Wilkinson
0 U0ContentsMinuteNo.                                      Subject page 1      Parliament       .....................       32      Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland     ......      ...       public Debt3      Foreign Affairs ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       3Organisation of Petroleum Exporting CountriesCambodia4      Indonesia ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       45      Pay of Members of Parliament and Ministers       ...      ...       5
Federation of rhodesia and nyasaland(previous reference:CM. (63) 10thConclusions,Minute I)Public Debt2. The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that, in the course of the debate on the Order in Council providing.for the dissolution of theFederation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, the proposed arrangementsfor apportioning the Federal public debt between the three territories which had comprised the Federation would be criticised as notproviding adequate security for the present stockholders. Therepresentatives of the stockholders, with support from the federal government, were still pressing their demand that the UnitedKingdom Government should guarantee the stocks concerned. Such acourse would not only constitute a damaging precedent but would be liable to impair the future credit of the Territories; and the proposal should therefore be rejected, it would be desirable, however, to indicatepublicly that the Government would be willing to support the legitimate claims of United Kingdom investors by all practicablemeans and that they were prepared to discuss with the territorial governments their economic circumstances, including the debtliability which they would assume on the dissolution of the Federation.In discussion there was general agreement with this view. It wouldbe necessary, however, to take account of the fact that, although the apportionment of the Federal public debt had been agreed by the-Territorial Governments, the Government of Northern Rhodesia had recently appeared to be dissatisfied with this settlement. It was to be hoped that they would continue to acquiesce, however reluctantly, inthe original agreement; but it would be advisable to seek confirmation of this point.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that no guarantee should be given by the Uniteo.Kingdom Government to the holders of the Federal stocks,the liability for which was now to be apportioned betweenthe Governments of Southern Rhodesia, northern rhodesia and Nyasaland.(2) Took note that the Prime Minister, in consultation with theother Ministers concerned, would give furtherconsideration to the terms in which the Governmentshould indicate the importance which they attached tothe preservation of the interests of the stockholders underthe new arrangements.ForeignAffairsOrganisationof PetroleumExportingCountries3. The Minister without Portfolio (Lord Carrington) said that members of the Organisation of Petroleum Exporting Countries(OPEC) were to meet at Riyadh on 24th December in order to decidetheir attitude in face of the refusal by the international oil companies to meet in full the increased payments demanded by the member states. If these negotiations resulted in deadlock, relations betweenthe United Kingdom and United States Governments on the onehand and the Middle Eastern oil producing countries on the otherhand might be seriously damaged. The situation should be kept underreview; and, meanwhile, those members of OPEC who favoured acourse of moderation should be given all possible encouragement.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the statement by the minister without Portfolio.CM. 13 (63)Parliament 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the first week after the Christmasadjournment.
Cambodia(previous reference:CC. (62) 73rdConclusions,Minute 3)The Cabinet (2) Took note, with approval, of the statement by the minister without Portfolio.Indonesia 4.   The Minister without Portfolio (Lord Carrington) said that(Previous        Decca Radar Limited and the Westland Aircraft Company had nowReference:       accepted the Governments request that they should terminate theirCM. (63) 10th   contracts with the Republic of Indonesia and should withdraw their conclusions,    technicians from Indonesian territory. It was proposed to announceMinute 3)       this decision in Parliament that afternoon and to inform in advance the Governments of Indonesia, Malaysia, the United States and theStates members of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation. her majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Djakarta had reported that, while he couldnot guarantee the safety of the technicians concerned, he hoped thatthe Indonesian Government would allow them to leave the country without molestation. But they might well take retaliatory action againstother British interests in Indonesia.In discussion the following points were made:(a) Terms had been provisionally agreed with the two companies for their indemnification against loss or legal action by the Indonesian government as a result of the withdrawal of their technicians and thetermination of their contracts.(b) Nevertheless we need not exclude the possibility that thesituation might improve sufficiently to allow the contracts to be resumed; and it would therefore be preferable that the public statement should describe the action to be taken as a suspension ofwork rather than a termination of contracts, provided that this wasnot inconsistent with the terms in which the decision had already beenconveyed to the parties concerned.(c) The statement would provide an opportunity to make public the Governments earlier decision to impose an embargo on the exportof arms and military equipment to Indonesia. It would be preferable,however, that this should be disclosed by means of the answer to a supplementary Question rather than that it should be included in thestatement itself.(d) The Australian Government had indicated that, while theysupported Malaysia in principle, they could not contemplate morethan a gradual increase in their military commitment in the Indonesiantheatre. The United States Government also continued to display a rather unsatisfactory attitude towards the confrontation betweenMalaysia and Indonesia.The Minister without Portfolio (Lord Carringtori) said that theCambodian Government had proposed that an international conference should be convened in order to guarantee Cambodianneutrality but had decided at the same time to withdraw theCambodian Embassies from London and Washington and had suggested that the United Kingdom and United States should withdraw their diplomatic representatives from Cambodia. despite this action, it would be advisable that we should endorse in principle the proposed international conference, since the Government of theSoviet Union had already declared their support for it and we shouldnot allow ourselves to be represented as indifferent to the continuingneutrality of Cambodia. But it would be necessary to make our agreement to the conference conditional on its being preceded byadequate preparatory discussions.
O PGOPay ofMembers ofParliamentand Ministers(previous reference:CM. (63) 12thConclusions,Minute 4)5. The Prime Minister said that he had now discussed with the leader of the Opposition, Mr. Harold Wilson, M.P., the most appropriate means of adjusting the pay of Members of parliament and Ministers. Mr. Wilson had agreed in principle that this question should be dealt with as a matter of priority by the Government which took office after the General Election; that the adjustment should bebased on a review of present emoluments, conducted by an ad hocbody consisting of the Chairman and Vice-Chairman of the national incomes Commission and a third individual selected by virtue ofspecial knowledge of Parliamentary and constitutional questions; thatthis body should look, for detailed information on the responsibilities of political life, to an advisory panel of Members of both Houses ofParliament; and that it should be instructed to report as early aspossible in the life of the new Parliament. It would now be necessaryto announce these proposals in Parliament in terms with which mr. Wilson would associate himself. For this purpose an early decision was required about the terms of reference of a review body on thelines proposed.In discussion the following points were made:(a) In view of the unique nature of the duties and responsibilities of Members of Parliament, it would be doubtfully wise to require the review body to have regard to the possible effects of any increases intheir remuneration in other fields.(b) It might also be undesirable to prejudge in the terms ofreference the extent to which the duties of a Member of parliament should now be regarded as constituting a full-time occupation. Onthe other hand all the adjustments in the pay of Members which hadbeen made up to the present time had merely preserved in real terms the value of the salary originally awarded in 1911, which had not beenappropriate, even at that date, to full-time service. If, therefore, the review body were to recommend an increase greater than would bejustified by the increase in the cost of living since the last review, theywould by implication recommend a fundamental change in the status of Members; and it would be appropriate that, before doing so, theyshould seek the views of the advisory panel on the extent to whichParliamentary duties constituted full-time employment. Alternatively,it might be possible to recognise Members&apos; varying degrees ofcommitment in this respect by prescribing that their basic salaryshould be supplemented by some form of allowance for service on parliamentary committees; and the review body&apos;s terms of reference should be sufficiently wide to allow them to consider this suggestion.(c) The review body should similarly be free to recommend achange in the form, as well as the amount, of the emoluments receivedby Members of the House of Lords; and they should have a wide measure of discretion in framing their recommendations about the remuneration of Ministers.CM. 13 (63)The Cabinet (1) Agreed that a statement should be made that day in the Houseof Commons, announcing the withdrawal from Indonesiaof United Kingdom technicians employed by Decca RadarLimited and the Westland Aircraft Company.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary, in consultation with theCommonwealth Secretary and the Minister of Defence, toarrange for the circulation of a memorandum examining the political and military factors affecting the UnitedKingdom policy of support for Malaysia.
(d) It was for consideration whether the review body should be encouraged to prescribe a definite relationship between the remuneration of Members of Parliament and Ministers on the onehand and the remuneration of some other sector of the community on the other hand or to propose that the former should be the subjectof some form of periodic or automatic revision. On balance, however,it would probably be preferable that the review now envisaged shouldbe completed without prejudice to the desirability of further reviewsin the future or to their form and timing.The Cabinet Took note that the Prime Minister, in consultation with theLord Chancellor, the Leader of the House of Commons, theChief Secretary, Treasury, the Leader of the House of lords and the Chief Whip, would give further consideration, in thelight of their discussion, to the terms of reference of the body which was to review the remuneration of Members ofParliament and Ministers.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,17th December, 1963.

</content>
</cab>
