<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/38/0 images: 92-97</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1963CM. (63) Copy No.     4 014th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 19th December, 1963, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,   The Right Hon. Quintin Hogg, Q.C,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs      M.P., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. Lord Dilhorne, lord chancellor the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Secretary of State for Industry, Tradeand Regional Development and president of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C,M.P., Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P.,    Minister    of    Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter.M.P., Chief Secretary to the treasury and Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. Sir Edward Boyle,M.P., Minister of education the  Right  Hon.  Anthony  Barber,M.P., Minister of health the Right  Hon.  Geoffrey  Rippon,M.P., Minister of Public Building and works the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Viscount Blakenham,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Michael Noble, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Joseph Godber, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P., Minister of power the Right Hon. William Deedes, M.P.,Minister without portfolio the Right  Hon. Lord Carrington,Minister without portfolio the following were also present:Mr. John Tilney, M.P., Joint Parlia- The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,mentary Under-Secretary of State for M.P., Parliamentary     Secretary,Commonwealth Relations and for the TreasuryColoniesSecretariat :Sir Burke trend . A. L. M. cary miss J. J. Nunn
contents minute no.SubjectPageForeign Affairs ...      ...      ...      ...      ......      ...       north Atlantic Council: Ministerial Meeting in ParisCyprusSouth AfricaTrade with the Soviet blocAgricultural Policy     ...      ...      ......      ...      ...       4
ForeignAffairsNorth atlantic council:ministerial meeting inParis(previous reference:CM. (63) 12thConclusions.Minute 2)Cyprus(previous reference:CC. (59) 51stConclusions,Minute 3)South Africa(previous reference:CM. (63) 4thConclusions,Minute 4)Trade withthe soviet bloc(previous reference:CM. (63) 4thConclusions,Minute 3)The Foreign Secretary said that in the course of the discussions which he would shortly be having with the United States Secretaryof State, Mr. Rusk, he would seek to avoid entering into detailed discussion of the Governments policy on the provision of long-termcredit facilities to countries of the Soviet bloc. It might be necessary,however, to warn Mr. Rusk in general terms that our views on thesubject had not altered.1. The Foreign Secretary said that at the recent meeting of the ministerial Council of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation(NATO) in Paris he had advocated the continuance of efforts to secure a further improvement in East-West relations. The Council had welcomed this objective and the French Foreign Minister had notsought to press his Governmenfs objections. The way was thus open for a continuation of negotiations when a suitable opportunitypresented itself. In the course of private discussion he had formed the view that the Federal Government of Germany would now beready to take a more active part in the search for a solution of theGerman problem, including Berlin. The United States Governmentwere also likely to be looking for fresh initiatives. He would keep theCabinet informed of developments.The Cabinet-(1) Took note of the statement by the Foreign Secretary.The Foreign Secretary said that all the proposals recently putforward by the President of Cyprus, Archbishop Makarios, for changesin the Constitution of the Island had been rejected by the TurkishGovernment. He had therefore encouraged discussion of the issuesbetween representatives of the Greek and Turkish communities in cyprus, in the hope that possibilities of agreement would emergemore readily from such discussions than from negotiations atGovernmental level. But the possibility of a further deterioration inthe situation could not be excluded.The Cabinet (2) Took note of the statement by the Foreign Secretary.The Prime Minister said that the Government were being subjected to increasing criticism for the continued supply to the SouthAfrican Government of war-like equipment, including spare parts and ammunition for tanks and armoured cars.In discussion it was noted that it could be plausibly argued that supplies of this kind would increase the ability of the South african government to take repressive action against opponents of apartheidand that to this extent they were inconsistent with the Governmenfsdeclared policy. Equally, however, it could be argued that a clear distinction could be drawn between, on the one hand, contracts for new equipment entered into after the date on which the Governmenthad declared their policy and, on the other hand, the continued supplyof items required to maintain the serviceability of equipment suppliedunder earlier contracts. To refuse to supply items of the latter kind could be represented as a breach of contract and would prejudice our prospects of obtaining further substantial orders for equipment whichwas not open to any political objection.The Cabinet-(3) Agreed that, for the time being, there should be no changein the Governmenfs policy as regards the supply of arms to South Africa.
agricultural policy(previous reference:CM. (63) 12thConclusions,Minute 6)2. The Cabinet resumed their discussion of a memorandumby the Minister of Agriculture (CP. (63) 31) on future agricultural policy. They also had before them a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Industry (CP. (63) 33).CerealsThe Minister of Agriculture said that it was essential to concludenegotiations with the oversea suppliers of cereals before embarking on the domestic Farm Price Review in February 1964. For thispurpose it would be necessary to arrange forthwith for discussions with the oversea suppliers during January. The principal question inthe negotiations would be the level of the standard quantity for home production. The 1963 harvest had yielded about 9-7 million tons;and, on the basis of autumn sowing, the farmers expected a yield of10 million tons in 1964. They would be unlikely, therefore, to accepta lower standard quantity than 10 million tons, unless the Governmentcould show that they had tried, but failed, to secure the agreementof the oversea suppliers to restrict their exports in conformity withdomestic production at that level. If negotiations were opened at10 million tons, however, it might be possible to reach agreement ata figure between 10 million and 9\ million tons, on the understandingthat there would be opportunities for further consultation if the oversea suppliers found in the event that they were deprived of theopportunity of sharing in the expansion of the market.The Secretary of State for Industry said that the combination ofa restriction on imports and the introduction of standard quantitiesfor the United Kingdom industry, which had originally been conceivedas a means of stabilising prices and limiting the liability of theExchequer, appeared gradually to have developed into a means of ensuring the domestic producer an increasing share of the market.The implications of this change in emphasis could be serious in termsboth of economic cost and of the potential damage to our relationswith our oversea suppliers. Moreover, the cost of agricultural support,which now represented a charge on the community&apos;s resources of some 400 million a year, had risen in step with increasing production:and the community now provided the whole of the net income of theThe Secretary of State for Industry said that, in view of current negotiations with the Soviet Government, it would be important notto give the United States Government any ground for supposing thatwe were prepared to withhold credit facilities in any case wherecommercial considerations appeared to justify them. Orders forterylene and fertiliser plants to a total value of some  100 million were now in prospect; and the outcome of the negotiations might turnon the nature of the credit facilities which we were prepared toextend.In discussion there was general agreement that the current negotiations with the Soviet Government should be determined bynormal commercial considerations. Although the Soviet government might regard themselves as being free to break any agreement into which they might now enter, they had never taken such a stephitherto and had always honoured the commercial obligations whichthey had accepted. It would be desirable, therefore, that Mr. Ruskshould be informed in general terms of the scope of the negotiationswith the Soviet Government which were in train.The Cabinet -(4) Invited the Foreign Secretary to inform the United states secretary of State in general terms of the trade negotiationswith the Soviet Government which were currently inprogress.
farming population. Productivity, however, had increased considerably less in farming than in other sectors of the economy; and it was clearthat the greater the proportion of the country&apos;s resources which was devoted to agricultural support, the poorer would be the prospects of achieving more rapid growth in the economy as a whole. the implications of allowing the British farmer to enjoy an expandingshare of the market were no less serious for our overseas trade.Negotiations had been opened with the oversea suppliers of cereals and meat on the basis of a limitation of home production, whichwould enable the oversea suppliers themselves to maintain their shareof an expanding market in return for a waiver of their treaty rightsof free entry. If we could not implement the offer to limit home production, we could not expect to reach agreement with the overseasuppliers; but to seek to impose restrictions on their exports indisregard of their treaty rights would expose our own oversea tradeto grave risks of retaliation and would seriously endanger theprospects of the forthcoming negotiations for the reduction of tariffsunder the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT). Itappeared to follow that, unless we could achieve agreementsacceptable both to the oversea suppliers and to our own farmers, itmight be wiser to allow the existing support arrangements to continuepending the negotiation of long-term agreements and, in the meantime,to examine the possibility of devising a new system of agricultural support which would provide an adequate standard of living for thesmaller farmers without insulating the larger and more efficient fromthe discipline of the market and would also maintain for our overseasuppliers the opportunities which both our international agreements and our trading interests required.In discussion it was suggested that, if negotiations were openedon the basis of a standard quantity of 10 million tons, both the farmers and the oversea suppliers might be brought to reach agreement on a figure of 9\ million tons, whereas a figure lower than this would be neither expected by the oversea suppliers nor acceptable to the farmers.Moreover, the alternative to reaching agreement with both parties would be either to maintain the existing support policy or to impose restrictions on the oversea suppliers; and either of these courses wouldbe more disadvantageous than the policy which the Minister ofAgriculture had proposed. Even on the basis of a figure of 10 million tons, the Exchequer would not be committed to the payment of morethan  78 million in subsidy; and there would be a counter-balancingsaving of foreign exchange amounting to some  10 million.On the other hand the oversea suppliers might be unwilling toreach agreement in advance of the general negotiations on tariffs later in 1964. In that event the Government might be justified in imposingrestrictions on imports as a temporary measure, notwithstanding thatthis would technically involve a breach of commercial agreements;and this course could be defended on the grounds that the restrictions would not reduce the access to our market which the oversea suppliersat present enjoyed but would merely stabilise the existing pattern ofsupply and that the restrictions placed on home production gave the oversea suppliers an advantage in the United Kingdom market whichwas not available to them in any other country of the GATT.Nevertheless, such a course would be condemned as a breach of treaty obligations and would be liable to expose our trade to damagingretaliation.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion, saidthat the balance of advantage appeared to lie in opening thenegotiations with our oversea suppliers on the basis of a standard quantity of 10 million tons for domestic production in the hope that agreement could be reached at a figure between 10 million and94- million tons. If no agreement could be reached on this basis, theCabinet would need to reconsider the situation.
SECRETMeatThe Minister of Agriculture said that, since the Cabinets previous discussion, the National Farmers&apos; Union had put forward proposalsfor standard quantities which might serve as a basis for agreementwith the oversea suppliers. The Scottish Farmers&apos; Union, however,were at present unwilling to agree to the introduction of standard quantities. It might be possible to secure their agreement on the basisof a standard quantity for beef projected three years ahead, whichwould offer them some security for their production; and, since theincrease in production of beef, at 2 per cent per annum, was scarcelyhigher than the increase in consumption, beef producers would have little to fear from the introduction of standard quantities and would gain from the quantitative limitation of imports. In default ofagreement with the farmers, however, the alternatives appeared to be either to impose standard quantity arrangements for fatstock at thenext Price Review and to introduce quantitative control of imports,if necessary, without the agreement of the oversea suppliers or to seek the co-operation of the latter in phasing their supplies to the UnitedKingdom market and to make only such changes in our domesticguarantee arrangements as would be acceptable to the farmers.In discussion it was emphasised that the opposition of the Scottishfarmers derived partly from a fear that restrictions might favour themore prosperous producers of beef and partly from a reluctance toaccept restraint on home production while beef continued to be imported from Europe and the Argentine Republic. There was a risk that, once the opposition of the Scottish farmers became known, hillfarmers in Wales and Northern England would adopt a similar attitude and the prospects of agreement with the National Farmers&apos; Union inEngland and Wales might be jeopardised.It was suggested that in these circumstances it would be desirableto arrange a conference with the oversea suppliers to discuss a broadrange of measures, including.not.only the introduction of standard quantities for home production in return for a quantitative limitationof exports to the United Kingdom market but also arrangements,short of limitation, for phasing those exports, coupled with onlyrelatively modest changes in the existing domestic guarantee arrangements. When the prospects of reaching agreement on the basisof either of these hypotheses could be more clearly judged it might be helpful if the Prime Minister, accompanied by the Secretary of Statefor Scotland and the Minister of Agriculture, discussed withrepresentatives of the Scottish Farmers&apos; Union their objections tothe Governments policies. If they remained unwilling to co-operatebut it had by then proved possible to reach a satisfactory agreement on cereals, the wisest course might be to defer the implementation ofthe Governments policy on meat until the following year.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Minister of Agriculture to seek to secure theagreement of the oversea suppliers of cereals to a limitationof their exports to the United Kingdom in conformity witha standard quantity for domestic production to be fixed at a figure between 10 million and 9  million tons.(2) Took note that the Minister of Agriculture, in default ofagreement on a standard quantity of at least 9-6 million tons, would invite the Cabinet to reconsider the situation.(3) Invited the Minister of Agriculture to discuss with the overseasuppliers of meat the limitation or phasing of supplies tothe United Kingdom on the lines indicated in their discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,19th December, 1963.

</content>
</cab>
