<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/38/0 images: 320-326</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 1G Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 21st April, 1964, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(Items 1-3)The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Dilhorne,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Secretary  of  State  for  the home department the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Secretary of State for Industry, Tradeand Regional Development and president of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P.,    Minister    of    Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Chief Secretary to the treasury and Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. Joseph Godber, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Anthony Barber, M.P.,Minister of health the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,M.P., Minister of Public buildings and works the Right Hon.Minister withoutThe Right Hon. Quintin Hogg, Q.C,M.P., Lord President of the Counciland Secretary of State for education and Science (Items 1-2)The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and for the colonies the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Viscount Blakenham,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Michael Noble, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P., Minister of power the Right Hon. William Deedes, M.P.,Minister without PortfolioLord Carrington,portfolio the following were also present:The Right Hon. Richard Wood, M.P.,Minister of Pensions and national insurance (Item 4)The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. rogers miss J. J. NunnPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1964CM. (64) Copy No.      3 624th Conclusions
203OContentsMinuteNo.                                      Subject page 1      Parliament       ...      ......      ...      ...      ...      ...       32     Resale Prices Bill       ..................       33      Foreign Affairs ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       3LaosCentral Treaty Organisation4     National Insurance and National Assistance       ...      ...       4Future Policy
ParliamentResale PricesBill(previous reference:CM. (64) 19thConclusions,Minute 1)ForeignAffairsLaos(previous reference:C.C. (63) 46thConclusions,Minute 1)3. The Foreign Secretary said that an attempt had been madeto overthrow the Government of Laos by a coup d&apos;etat led byRight-wing elements in the Laotian Army. The previous PrimeMinister, Prince Souvanna Phouma, however, had subsequently been invited to reconstitute the Government of National Union and hadthus returned to power.1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons in the following week.2. The Cabinet considered whether it would be expedient toaccept, during the Committee stage of the Resale Prices Bill, an amendment whereby, in accordance with the precedent of Clause21 (b) of the Monopolies and Restrictive Practices Act, 1956,exemption from the provisions of the Bill would be granted to resale price maintenance agreements the abolition of which would &quot; deprive the public of specific and substantial benefit &quot;.The Secretary of State for Industry said that the exemption inquestion had been accepted in relation to the Act of 1956 because itwas felt at that stage that considerations of &quot; the public interest&quot;should constitute a sufficient defence to a charge under the Act.Subsequent experience, however, had demonstrated that there wereobjections to a comprehensive exemption of this kind and that anyexceptions from legislation about restrictive practices should be defined and specific. Since the Resale Prices Bill had been published a considerable number of amendments of this kind had been accepted,dealing both with individual commodities and with cases wherethere was reason to believe that the abolition of a resale price maintenance agreement might lead to a rise in the price of goods. Itwas also proposed to enable industries which had already submittedtheir case to the Restrictive Practices Court to make full use of thedecision of that Court in claiming exemption under the new legislation. These amendments should suffice to dispose of all the specific cases where exemption could justifiably be claimed. by contrast, the scope of the amendment now in question was so wideand general as to jeopardise the whole purpose of the Bill.In discussion it was suggested that it might be difficult to presenta convincing case for rejecting an amendment which purported to exempt only agreements which provided specific and substantialbenefit to the public. On the other hand the amendments which hadalready been accepted covered all the cases where exemptionappeared to be justified; and it would be easier for the Court to dealwith individual cases by reference to specific criteria of exemptionthan on the basis of a general and undefined concept of &quot; publicbenefit&quot;. Moreover, the amendment, if accepted, would be liable to result in a considerable increase in the number of applications to theCourt for exemption; and the resultant pressure on the Court would seriously impede the implementation of the Act.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that, whileit would continue to be necessary to consider reasonable proposalsfor specific amendments to the Bill, there appeared to be generalagreement that any general exemption from its provisions, on thelines of the amendment under discussion, would seriously damage itseffectiveness.The Cabinet Invited the Secretary of State for Industry to be guided bytheir discussion in considering further amendments to theResale Prices Bill.
Central Treaty The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that during theOrganisation following week he would attend a meeting of the Council of theCentral Treaty Organisation. The United States Secretary of State,Mr. Rusk, would also be present; and he would take the opportunityof discussing with him a number of important issues of Anglo-American concern.The Cabinet Took note of the statements by the Foreign Secretary.4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer, as chairman of the Pensions and national insurance Committee (CP. (64) 83), on future policy in relation to national insurance benefits and national assistance.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the Committee on pensions and National Insurance had considered in what directionthe Governments policy should be developed in relation to national insurance and national assistance and had examined three groups of problems: the payment of preferential benefits to older pensioners;the improvement of the arrangements for graduated retirement pension and contracting out; and benefits for unemployment, sickness and widowhood related to earnings.Preferential benefits for the agedThe Committee had agreed in principle that, when a general increase was made in national insurance and national assistancerates, preferential national insurance and national assistancepayments should be introduced for older pensioners, for whomincreased dependence on the services of others, coupled withdecreased resources, created special problems. A similar case mightbe made for preferential treatment for the chronically sick; but, inview of the risk of repercussions, it might be better to confinepreferential payments to the old, for example those over 75. Thedetails would need to be further considered by the Committee.Contracting out of graduated retirement pensionThe existing arrangements for contracting out of graduatedretirement pensions were tending to produce inequity between onecontributor and another. Those who contracted out of thearrangements for graduated retirement pension paid a flatcontribution in respect of national insurance benefits other than the graduated pension, while those participating in the arrangementspaid a flat contribution lower than that of the contracted-out,together with a graduated contribution which rose with earnings between  9 and (currently)  18 a week. As a result the contracted-outwith low earnings paid more than those participating in the schemefor similar benefits; and those with high earnings paid less. Thesedisparities would be aggravated by any substantial increase inflat-rate benefits and related contributions, which should consequentlybe mitigated in relation to the contracted-out whose earnings werelow and increased in relation to those whose earnings were high.This adjustment would be easier to achieve if the basis of contributionwere so adjusted that the contracted-out were brought into thescheme of graduated contributions and benefits but their flat-rate contribution and their total national insurance pensions were abatedin consideration of the occupational pensions which had beenguaranteed to them as the condition of their contracting out. Thisarrangement would have the additional advantage of providing forthe first time a universal contribution base suitable for a scheme of earnings-related benefits.national insurance andNationalAssistanceFuture Policy(previous reference:C.C. (63) 3rdConclusions,Minute 4)
Earnings-related short-term benefitsA scheme for earnings-related short-term benefits could be basedon provision for fiat benefits, as at present, for those earning up to 9 a week and a graduated amount up to the same total on the next 9 a week. (A scheme which gave proportionately more on thesecond  9 than on the first would be open to criticism on the groundthat it provided relatively greater benefit for the better-off.) a graduated scheme on these lines could be applied only to unemployment benefit, or to sickness and widowhood as well. Therewas an economic as well as a social case for graduated unemploymentbenefit; but it might be difficult to differentiate between a suddendrop in income attributable to unemployment and a similar situationattributable to another cause equally outside the victim&apos;s control.There might also be pressure for transitional arrangements for persons reaching retirement age.The Pensions and National Insurance Committee had been unable to reach agreement on the introduction of earnings-related short-term benefits. On the one hand it had been argued thatearnings-related unemployment benefit was essential to the policy of modernisation, since it would increase the mobility of labour andwould reduce the fear of redundancy, together with the overmanning,the resistance to change and the restrictive practices which derivedfrom that fear. It would be complementary to a scheme of severancepayments; and the two together would probably be acceptable to both employers and the trade unions, although the latter would wishearnings-related benefits to be extended to sickness. It would alsobe consonant with the policy of relating benefits to need. On theother hand it could be argued that the proposal was not wellconceived, since the greatest beneficiary would be the single man,who was already the most mobile; that it was wasteful, in that lessthan 10 per cent of claims for unemployment benefit arose fromredundancy; that it would be relatively costly to administer and notnecessarily popular with either employers or the trade unions; andthat it could not be relied upon to produce a substantial reduction inthe fear of redundancy or encourage the unemployed to find new work.Cost and timingExpenditure on benefits and assistance ought to be containedwithin the forecast published in the White Paper on public expenditure for 1967-68, which contemplated an increase of 360 million under these heads by 1967-68. The annual cost of earnings-related benefits and preferential benefits for the old, whichwould depend on detailed decisions, would lie between  20 and 60 million and that for preferential benefits for the very old and long-term assistance cases would amount to some  50 million, anexcess in total of about  100 million over the forecast. It would hardly be acceptable to offset this increase by refraining from raising thegeneral benefits in line with earnings; and the only alternative wouldbe to postpone the increase in general benefits until April 1966 or, atthe earliest, the end of 1965. Unless, however, it was thought possibleto introduce the legislation necessary to provide earnings-related benefits in 1964 without providing increases for the less well-off, theearliest date at which earnings-related benefits could be introducedwould be 1966, since the alterations in the contribution arrangements,which were tied to the tax year, could not then be made until April1966. Under the National Insurance Act, 1959, contribution rates would rise in April 1965, with no extra benefit, in order to meet thecost of the growing number of pensions. It would be useful ifimprovements could be made at the same time; but, if not, it seemedpreferable not to introduce special legislation to defer the increases in contribution. A further item of increased expenditure not allowed for in the forecast for 1967, which might amount to some  30 million a year, was the cost of increasing the children&apos;s allowance to offset
the limitation of national assistance resulting from the reducedmargin between national insurance benefit and the wage of thebeneficiary in normal employment.In discussion it was pointed out that it would be difficult to exclude the chronic sick from preferential increases in national assistance payments which were related to the circumstances of prolonged dependence for which the normal scale of payments didnot provide. The cost of including the chronic sick would not be considerable; and. whereas it had at one time been thought thatdifferential payments unrelated to individual needs were notconsistent with the principles on which national assistance was based,there was now some reason to think that such a scheme would be acceptable to the National Assistance Board.There were considerable practical difficulties, however, indistinguishing those who should benefit from preferential payments on any basis other than age. These problems might be avoided if some form of guaranteed minimum income could be adopted. Theobject of such a scheme would be to increase prosperity by raising the incomes of those in real need; and, by holding the retirement pension at its existing level, it would be possible to secure sufficienteconomies to provide relatively generous payments for those at the bottom of the income scale. On the other hand a minimum incomescheme with a fixed retirement pension would bear hardly on the numerous people who were marginally above the national assistancelevel and depended on the arrangement whereby the pension rose in line with earnings to maintain this position. Moreover, such a scheme would tend to discourage thrift and continuance in work afterretiring age. It would also raise considerable practical problems, since it could not be operated on the basis of tax returns.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion, saidthat the Cabinet were inclined to accept in principle a scheme forpreferential benefits for both the very old and the chronic sick. TheCommittee on Pensions and National Insurance should examineagain the practical problems of including the chronic sick in such ascheme; and Chairman of the National Assistance Board shouldbe consulted in order that the matter might be further considered bythe Cabinet at a later meeting. It would also be helpful if theCommittee on Pensions and National Insurance would give furtherconsideration to a guaranteed minimum income scheme inconsultation with the Minister of Housing and Local Government.Memoranda submitted to the Committee on this and other aspectsof the issues concerned might with advantage be circulated to theCabinet as a whole.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrange for theCommittee on Pensions and National Insurance to give further consideration to the practical problems involvedin including the chronic sick in a scheme for preferentialbenefits for those dependent for a long period on national insurance and national assistance.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrange for theCommittee on Pensions and National Insurance to give further consideration, on the basis of a memorandum tobe submitted by the Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment, to the feasibility of a scheme for a guaranteed minimum income and for the memorandarelating to this and other aspects of the Committee&apos;s workto be circulated to the Cabinet generally.Benefits related to earningsThe Minister of Labour said that the introduction of wage-related benefits for unemployment was important not primarily in thesocial context but as the key to a group of problems raised by the
Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,21st April, 1964.modernisation of industry, including restrictive practices andover-manning, with which both employers and unions were reluctant to deal in view of the prevalent fear of redundancy and of the sharpfall in income associated with it. The fall in income could be considerably reduced by the payment of wage-related benefits; but such a scheme would not in itself be sufficient to mitigate the effects of redundancy and it was desirable that it should be accompanied byredundancy payments for the worker who had served for aconsiderable period in a particular occupation. An early decision onthe one issue was likely to make it easier to secure the agreement ofboth sides of industry on the other. The cost of wage-related benefits would not be high in relation to that of the other benefits underconsideration; nor would the beneficiaries who had becomeredundant be as small a proportion of the total number receivinggraduated benefit as was suggested in CP. (64) 83. Some 60 per cent of the total unemployed would not be qualified, for various reasons,for graduated benefit; and the proportion of the remainder who had become redundant would increase as the modernisation of industryproceeded. In view of the strong economic arguments for wage-related benefits it should be possible to secure the passage of the necessary legislation early in the new Parliament, in advance of the general review of national insurance benefits.In discussion it was suggested that, while the Government hadincurred no commitment, the impression had been created that theywere considering the introduction of wage-related benefitsfavourably; and a negative conclusion might be difficult to defend in public on the grounds advanced in paragraph 17 of CP. (64) 83.Wage-related benefits were not, however, the only means of reducingthe impact of redundancy; and the arguments for and against their introduction should be considered against the background of such other measures as provision for industrial re-training and the allowances paid to assist redundant workmen to move to a new area or to undertake longer journeys to a new place of employment. some consideration should also be given to the application of a wage-related scheme to women, who accounted for one-third of the labour force but would not for the most part be eligible for graduated benefitbecause their wages would fall below  9 a week.The Cabinet (3) Invited the Minister of Labour to submit a further memorandum on the introduction of wage-related benefits in the context of the other measures designed to reducethe impact of redundancy on individual workmen.(4) Agreed to resume their discussion at a later meeting.

</content>
</cab>
