<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/38/0 images: 442-452</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  July 1964CM. (64)38th conclusions copy No.CABINETThe Right Hon. Lord Dilhorne, LordChancellorCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 16th July, 1964, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. Quintin Hogg, Q.C,M.P., Lord President of the Counciland Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and for the colonies the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P.,    Minister    of    Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Chief Secretary to the treasury and Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. Joseph Godber, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Anthony Barber, M.P.,Minister of health the Right Hon. William Deedes, M.P.,Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Secretary  of State for  the home department the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Secretary of State for Industry, Tradeand   Regional   Development   and president of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Viscount Blakenham,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Michael Noble, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,M.P., Minister of Public Building and works the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Minister without portfolio the following were also present:The Right Hon. Julian Amery, M.P.,Minister of Aviation (Item 7)The Right Hon. Sir John Hobson, Q.C.,M.P., Attorney-General (Item 8)The Right Hon. Hugh Fraser, M.P.,Minister of Defence for the Royal AirForce (Items 6-7)The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. rogers miss J. J. nunn mr. P. R. Baldwin4932-1
322wContentsMinuteNo. Subject page 1      Parliament       .....................       32      Meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers       ......       33      Foreign Affairs.....................       4Iraq: Nationalisation of Commercial UndertakingsCyprusUnited States of America4     Economic Affairs       ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       55     Public Order    ...      ..................       56     Malta    ........................       57     vc10s   ........................       78      Landlord and Tenant..................      10Security of Tenure and Rent Control
Meeting ot 2.   The Prime Minister said that the outcome of the Meeting of commonwealth Commonwealth Prime Ministers which had ended on the previousMinisters had been reasoriabfy satisfactory. This was the more important in that the last Meeting, in 1962, had revealed considerable differenceswithin the Commonwealth on the issue of the United Kingdom&apos;proposal to accede to the European Economic Community, while theMeeting in 1961 had resulted in the withdrawal of South Africa fromthe Commonwealth. On the present occasion, despite significantdivergences between member countries on various issues, the meeting had been characterised by an evident desire on the part of allcountries to reinforce the Commonwealth connection and to give itnew significance.^ The Prime Ministers had examined several contentious issues.The Heads of the African States had been reluctant to allow their membership of the Commonwealth to appear to carry with it any specific commitment to the West as against the Sino-Soviet bloc.They had been concerned to maintain a policy of non-alignment;and some of them had not wished to be seen openly to associate themselves with us in our resistance to Indonesian aggression againstMalaysia. Nevertheless, we had finally secured unanimous endorse-ment of a statement in the communique that the commonwealth would support the Prime Minister of Malaysia in his efforts to preserve the sovereign independence and integrity of his country andto promote a peaceful and honourable settlement of currentdifferences between Malaysia and neighbouring countries. This was satisfactory.We had also had the support of all other Prime Ministers, apartfrom the representative of President Makarios, in confining the reference to Cyprus in the communique to the terms of the united nations Resolutions which we had already endorsed and in resistingany elaboration of those Resolutions which might be interpreted as indicating that we favoured the Greek, rather than the Turkish,community in the Island.The discussion on Southern Rhodesia had been difficult andprotracted. It had been impossible to ignore the insistence of mostof the African Prime Ministers that the African leaders at present in detention in Southern Rhodesia should be released and that a freshconstitutional conference should be convened in order to give effectto the principle of majority rule in the colony. The communique had therefore made it clear that these views had been advanced by somePrime Ministers. It had made it no less clear, however, that we had insisted throughout that, while we shared with all other PrimeMinisters the view that Southern Rhodesia could be grantedindependence only on the basis of sufficiently representativeinstitutions and would take into consideration all the other views which had been expressed, the responsibility for deciding theconstitutional development of Southern Rhodesia would continue to lie with the United Kingdom alone.The Meeting had also considered the future of British Guiana;and the different views which had been expressed about the mannerin which we should seek to deal with this problem were a sufficientindication that other members of the Commonwealth now appreciatedits complexity more fully than hitherto. It was clear that they wouldnot be without sympathy for us if we were ultimately compelled to revert to direct rule of the colony.Parliament 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.
The prospects of a settlement of the dispute between India and pakistan about Kashmir had not been significantly improved by theMeeting; but it had proved possible to include in the communiquea carefully worded reference to recent public statements by the Headsof Government of both countries, indicating their desire for animprovement of relations.The specific proposals which we had tabled for closer and more practical co-operation between Commonwealth countries had eliciteda satisfactory response; and it was indicative of the constructivenature of the discussion on the future of the Commonwealth that ithad revealed considerable support for the concept of a Common-wealth Secretariat, which other member countries had hithertoopposed. In general the Heads of Government of the newer member countries had undoubtedly been impressed both by the informalnature of the proceedings and by the underlying strength of the connection  which united all those around the table.In discussion the Cabinet extended their warm congratulations to the Prime Minister on the manner in which he had conducted theMeeting to a successful conclusion.Foreign.AffairsIraq:nationalisation of CommercialUndertakings(previous reference:CM. (63) 7thConclusions,Minute 3)3. The Minister without Portfolio (Lord Carrington) said thatthe Government of Iraq had introduced legislation to nationalisecertain banks, insurance companies and leading commercial concerns.Since the measure included provision for a degree of compensation,we could not object to it in principle. This step, however, might indicate a development in Iraqi policy which would be unfavourable to our interests and, in particular, might threaten our oil investments.Cyprus(previous reference:CM. (64) 34thConclusions,Minute 3)The Minister without Portfolio (Lord Carrington) said that atthe recent meeting of the Council of the North Atlantic treaty organisation the increase of Greek forces in Cyprus had beenuniversally condemned. This declaration might have a restrainingeffect on the Greek Government. On the other hand it seemed unlikelythat any positive results would follow from the confidential discussions between the former United States Secretary of State,Mr. Dean Acheson, the United Nations mediator, Mr. Tuomioja, and representatives of the Greek and Turkish Governments, which were still in progress in Geneva.The Cabinet (1) Took note of these statements by the Minister without portfolio (Lord Carrington).United Statesof america the Cabinet were informed that it now appeared virtually certainthat Senator Goldwater would secure nomination as the Republicancandidate in the forthcoming Presidential election in the UnitedStates.The Cabinet (2) Invited the Minister without Portfolio (Lord Carrington) to circulate a memorandum about the implications of a republican victory in the forthcoming presidential election in the United States.
EconomicAffairs5. The Cabinet were informed that the Prime Minister of kenya, Mr. Kenyatta, had been subjected to a personal assault onthe previous day, as he was leaving his hotel to attend the final sessionof the Meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers. Although he had accepted the apologies which we had extended to him, he had beenshocked by the attack and had indicated that it contrastedunfavourably with the reception which would be accorded to a european statesman visiting Kenya.In discussion considerable concern was expressed at this incident; and it was suggested that it might be desirable to review the security precautions which were adopted for the protection ofdistinguished international visitors to this country. It was also suggested that further thought might need to be given to the extentto which it should be permissible to arrange demonstrations designedto embarrass such visitors by the display of slogans and banners. Onthe other hand it would be necessary to refrain from any actionwhich might be interpreted as an attempt to prevent the peacefulexpression of opinion in a free society.In further discussion the Cabinet were informed that there were some signs that public opinion might be becoming uneasy about the alleged inability of the police to maintain order in an acceptablemanner. It might be desirable to consider whether any action was required in this regard.The Cabinet Invited the Home Secretary (i) to consider whether any action was required to intensifythe protection for visitors to this country againstmolestation or embarrassment;(ii) to give further consideration, in the light of their discussion, to the most appropriate means ofallaying public concern about the maintenance of lawand order.Public Order(previous reference:C.C. (63) 34thConclusions,Minute 5)Malta 6.   The Colonial Secretary said that negotiations with the Prime(Previous        Minister of Malta, Dr. Borg Olivier, about the independence of the reference:       Island appeared to have reached a virtually final deadlock. Dr. BorgCM. (64) 37th  Olivier still refused to accept that the proposed defence agreementConclusions)    should incorporate provisions enabling us to store nuclear weapons in Malta, if we found it necessary to do so; and he was equallyunwilling to acquiesce in an amendment of the Maltese electoral law which would prevent the Roman Catholic Church from exercisingundue influence over the conduct of elections in the Island. the cm. 38 (64)4. The Secretary of State for Industry informed the Cabinetthat the latest trade statistics, to be published on the following day,would disclose that imports were continuing to rise. This was contrary to earlier expectations; and the reasons were not clear. Itwould be advisable, therefore, to refrain as far as possible from public discussion of the implications of this phenomenon until the statistics had been examined in detail.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Secretary of State for industry.
present law, which had been introduced during our ownadministration of Malta, provided that any individual who inflictedor threatened to inflict moral or material injury on a voter wasexercising undue influence. On the other hand United Kingdom lawin this context referred not to moral or material injury but tospiritual or temporal injury. The difference between &quot; moral injury &quot;and &quot; spiritual injury &quot; lay in the fact that the Maltese courts didnot interpret the former as preventing the Church authorities fromthreatening voters with spiritual harm if they supported a particularpolitical party. While the authorities of the Vatican and the archbishop of Malta were willing to accept an amendment of the maltese law which would bring it into line with United Kingdomlaw, this change was unacceptable to Dr. Olivier on the grounds thathis recent victory in the referendum had committed him to maintainthe Maltese law in its present form and, if he conceded the point,the Opposition Party in Malta, led by Mr. Mintoff, would turn it totheir political advantage.There was some reason to believe, however, that Dr. Olivierwould accept a defence agreement which would be acceptable to us if we would forgo our demand for a change in the Maltese electoral law. On the other hand the Opposition in Parliament had made itclear they would oppose legislation to provide for the independence of Malta unless the electoral law were changed; and there was nolonger sufficient time in the remainder of the present session for the enactment of contentious legislation. It was now necessary, therefore,to decide whether we should accept a breakdown in the negotiationsor whether we should seek to bring them to a positive conclusion byabandoning the demand for the alteration of the electoral law inreturn for Dr. 01ivier&apos;s acceptance of a satisfactory defence agreement and by undertaking that legislation to give effect to theindependence of Malta would be introduced in the next Parliament.If all the other issues were disposed of, it would be necessary todecide the manner in which our offer of financial assistance to Maltaover a 10-year period would most appropriately be linked with thedefence agreement. During the last 7 of the 10 years the provisionof financial assistance should be specifically dependent on the satisfactory discharge of the Maltese obligations under the defence agreement. For the first three years, however, it should beunconditional, since financial support would have to be provided from United Kingdom funds for Malta for that length of time inany event.In discussion it was suggested that it might be wiser to let thenegotiations break down, since the Maltese Labour Party, who were known to be determined to repudiate the defence agreement, mightwell come to power in the next few years and it would therefore be unwise to appear to have secured an agreement which might bevalueless in return for the surrender of a point of principle as regardsthe exercise of undue spiritual influence in elections. On the otherhand it would be inconsistent with our general policy to withholdindependence from Malta on the score of a refusal by the Governmentof the Island to amend a provision in the electoral law which hadbeen introduced during our own administration of Malta and wouldnot, in any event, be regarded by public opinion in the UnitedKingdom as of critical significance. The increased importance of facilities in Malta to our strategic interests was such that, if asatisfactory defence agreement could be concluded, it would be contrary to British interests to allow the negotiations to break down.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that thebalance of advantage appeared to incline in favour of seeking to bringthe negotiations to a positive conclusion. The Colonial secretary should therefore endeavour to reach agreement with the PrimeMinister of Malta on the basis that we would be prepared to abandonour earlier insistence on a change in the Maltese electoral law
vc10s(previous reference:CM. (64) 33rdConclusions,Minute 7)7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Aviation (CP. (64) 141) about the Super VC.10 and amemorandum by the Foreign Secretary (CP. (64) 142) about theVC.10 and the South American services of the British overseas airways Corporation (B.O.A.C).The Lord Privy Seal said that the Chairman of B.O.A.C.,Sir Giles Guthrie, had concluded, as a result of a detailed study ofthe Corporation^ route pattern, that by the higher utilisation of aircraft he could maintain their services with 23 aircraft less than theCorporation^ planned strength for 1967. He had accordingly recommended that the most economic way of achieving this wouldbe to cancel the order for 30 Super vc10s and to buy six newAmerican Boeing 707s. This course was argued to be reasonablebecause the Boeings already in service had been largely amortisedand still had many years of life, while the running costs of a fleet of30 vc10s would be some  2 million more than those of an equivalentfleet of Boeings. The cost of cancelling the vc10s would be 65-70 million. When the problem had been considered by a small group of Ministers under the chairmanship of the Prime Minister ithad been agreed that the proposal was unacceptable but that, if.O.A.C. were to be asked to buy vc10s contrary to their commercial judgment, the Government should enable them to operatethese in a commercially profitable fashion. Further Ministerialdiscussions had subsequently been held to consider in detail thefinancial and other implications of not cancelling any of the order for vc10s or of cancelling only a limited number of them. ministers had agreed that the alternatives lay between no cancellation and the cancellation of 10. The first course would involve B.O.A.C. in taking27 vc10s, keeping 8 Boeings and selling 12 Boeings. The cost wouldbe between  106 and  114 million. The cancellation of the order for10 vc10s would involve a corresponding increase in the number ofBoeings which they would retain; and only two Boeings would thenbe sold. The cost of this course would be between  79 and  88-J-million. The Ministers concerned were divided in their views on thecourse to be followed. There was a possible compromise course,namely, to postpone a decision on the remaining 10; but before considering this the Cabinet might wish to consider the two mainalternative courses.The Minister of Aviation said that Sir Giles Guthrie would accept whatever decision the Government reached on the number ofVClOs to be ordered, provided that B.O.A.C. was enabled to operatethem economically by an arrangement whereby the extra costs wouldbe offset by a Government payment to the Corporation. Since the cm. 38 (64)provided that we secured a defence agreement which satisfied our essential requirements as regards the right to store nuclear weapons in Malta, if necessary. The provisions of the financial agreement could, if necessary, be as proposed by the Colonial Secretary. If afinal settlement was reached on this basis, the Government wouldhave to be prepared to introduce the necessary legislation in the nextParliament.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Colonial Secretary to seek to complete thenegotiations with the Prime Minister of Malta about theindependence of the Island on the basis indicated by thePrime Minister in his summing up of their discussion.(2) If negotiations were concluded in accordance with conclusion (1), to arrange for the agreements to beinitialled and published.
earlier discussions he had now informed us that his total requirement for a fleet of aircraft after 1968 would be 47 aircraft as comparedwith his previous estimate of 40. The financial gain of cancelling10 vc10s as compared with cancelling none was substantial. Itwould, however, make it very unlikely that further vc10s would be sold; and B.O.A.C. would probably seek to order further american aircraft in the future, with the result that we should in effect bewithdrawing from the market for long-range subsonic jet aircraft.Such a step would be most damaging to the United Kingdom aircraft industry. The cancellation of 10 vc10s would, moreover, involveB.O.A.C. in retaining all but two of the Boeing fleet; and it would bedifficult for public opinion to accept this. The matter must be looked at in the general context of our commercial competition with UnitedStates industry. The decision had been taken in 1958 to order theVC.10 for B.O.A.C It was an efficient aircraft and was technicallysuperior to the Boeing in certain important respects. It was admittedlymore expensive both in capital cost and in running charges; but thelatter might well be reduced by experience and be offset by the greaterappeal of the aircraft to passengers. A decision in favour of an allVC.10 fleet, i.e., cancelling none of the present order, would offer thebest chance of selling the VC.10 overseas and of developing itsconsiderable potentialities.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the immediate issuesfor decision must be viewed against the background of the positionof the B.O.A.C. The Corporation had ordered 13 too many aircraft.They had wished to cancel the order for vc10s completely; and,although this was not politically acceptable, it must be borne in mind.The difference in cost of the two courses outlined by the Lord privy seal was  30 million. The Government could not afford expenditureof this order, bearing in mind the very substantial rise in totalGovernmental expenditure which was forecast over the next few years.Nor should the cancellation of the order for 10 aircraft seriouslydamage the United Kingdom aircraft industry. The Boeing aircraftalready in service had many remaining years of effective life andwere economically very efficient aircraft. We could not afford to force B.OA.C. to sell them and to buy aircraft which they did not want.In discussion the following points were made in favour of adecision to complete the existing order for the vc10s:(a) The prestige of the United Kingdom would be enhanced if.O.A.C. were to operate a complete fleet of British aircraft.(b) It would be commercially unsound for the Corporation to operate a mixed fleet of vc10s and Boeings.(c) Since it appeared probable that B.O.A.C. would require futher subsonic aircraft in the 1970s, their commitment to VClOswould save possible subsequent dollar expenditure and so benefit theUnited Kingdom balance of payments.(d) the ability of the VC10 to land and take off on shorterrunways than could accommodate the Boeing offered the prospect ofa commercially and politically valuable extension of B.O.A.C.services in the future.(e) Exports by the United Kingdom aircraft industry were ofconsiderable economic importance; and their prospects would bedamaged if the United Kingdom Government were to show a lackof confidence in the future of the VC.10 In considering the potentialdamage to the industry of a partial cancellation of the order it shouldbe borne in mind that the Super VC10 would enter the service of.O.A.C. in 1965. Foreign operators would wish to observe its performance before committing themselves to an order. If there werepartial cancellations, production would have to be discontinued in1967. The best chances of export orders for the aircraft, therefore,lay in assuring, through the completion of the present order, thecontinuance of production until the end of 1968.
b(/) United Kingdom interests required that we should be in aposition to compete with United States industry in the field of advanced technology; and lack of support for the aircraft industry would result in a serious gap which would indirectly, as well asdirectly, damage our future competitive capacity. In the present case,as in others, we might fail to obtain the full advantage of the very heavy expenditure which had been incurred on research anddevelopment by hesitation in committing ourselves to the further expenditure involved in following through this work.(g) The payment from Government funds of  10-20 million forcancellation charges alone would be politically damaging.In favour of a decision to cancel 10 vc10s the following points were made:(h) The additional cost of completing the order, amounting to 30 million, was an unacceptable addition to government expenditure, the projected increase of which was already a matterof grave concern.(/) A decision to complete the order on the score thatnationalised industries should, as a matter of policy, buy british goods would be contrary to our wider commercial interests in that itwould inhibit us from dissuading other nations from pursuing asimilar policy. In particular, it was of great importance to us that theUnited States Government should be dissuaded from adopting a restrictive policy in this regard.(/) The United Kingdom aircraft industry should not be seriously damaged by a decision to cancel 10 vc10s. In so far as confidence in the future of the VC.10 might be impaired, the damage had alreadybeen inflicted by the publicity which the issue had now received.Greater damage would be done to the industry itself and to broaderUnited Kingdom industrial interests by the continued subsidisationof the industry. In so far as cancellation would involve any risk tothe future of the industry, it must be borne in mind that there wasin any case a conflict between the economic operation of the industryand the economic operation of B.O.A.C., which was also a matterof major concern.(k) In anticipation of the possible cancellation of the order work had already ceased on the 10 vc10s. Cancellation, by leading tothe maintenance of a mixed fleet of aircraft by B.O.A.C., wouldenable the Corporation to retain the option of expanding its fleet ofVClOs at a later date if, after experience of their operation, this seemed commercially desirable or, alternatively, of expanding itsfleet of Boeings if it did not.(/) The scale on which our resources made it possible for us to conduct research and development in the field of advanced technology meant that we could not hope to compete with the UnitedStates over the whole range. Our interests would be better served by concentrating our effort in a narrower field.(m) A decision to carry out the full order for vc10s despite the economies to be gained by partial cancellation would be damaging to the reputation of the Government for commercial judgment.In further discussion the Cabinet considered whether, as analternative to these courses of action, there might be advantage indeferring a decision on them. Against this course it was argued that:(n) This might increase the already high expenditure, despite theundertaking by the British Aircraft Corporation that they would not increase their cancellation charges in respect of a limited extensionof this nature.(o) Such a course might give the impression of timidity andindecision.
In favour of a postponement it was argued that:(p) The delay would offer further opportunity for technical discussions on the extent to which the capability of the aircraft mightbe enlarged.(q) It appeared that some uncertainty still remained about thefuture requirements of B.O.A.C. for aircraft. The Corporation hadclarified some aspects of this in the course of the previous twomonths; and a limited further delay might result in furtherclarification which would be material to the decision to be taken.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that thebalance of advantage appeared to lie in postponing a decision for afurther limited period. The manner in which this postponementshould be announced would require careful consideration. It shouldbe based on the factor of uncertainty about the future requirementsof the B.O.A.C. for aircraft and the need for further investigationsto be undertaken on this issue.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Minister of Aviation, in consultation with theChancellor of the Exchequer and the Lord Privy Seal, toconsider the terms in which a statment could be made inaccordance with the Prime Ministers summing up andto circulate the draft of such a statement for their consideration.(2) Agreed to resume their discussion in the light of conclusion (1).Landlord andTenantSecurity of tenure andRent Control(previous reference:CM. (64) 19thConclusions,Minute 8)8. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister of housing and Local Government (CP. (64) 137) about security of tenure and rent control, together with the draft of a statement whichthe Minister proposed to make in the debate on housing later in theday.The Minister of Housing said that it would be desirable to give some indication in this debate of the Governmenfs future policy on security of tenure and rent control, particularly in relation to London,where it was clear from information already available that it wouldbe essential to take some action as soon as the report of the fact-finding committee under the chairmanship of Sir Milner Holland,Q.C., was published. The release of more building land contemplated in the South-East Study and the increasing production of houses would in the long run provide a solution to the particularly acuteproblem of London; but it would be necessary to take short-term measures to relieve the distress of those who were either unable toobtain accommodation at all or were suffering from the continuouspressure of rising rents and insecurity of tenure. He had suggested to the Home Affairs Committee that all tenants should be given theright to a longer period of notice, ranging from 3 to 12 monthsaccording to the length of occupancy; that tenants should be subjectto eviction only by order of a court; and that in London tenants ofuncontrolled property should be given the same measure of securityas that enjoyed by tenants of controlled property. Since there couldbe no security without protection against extortionate rents, thiswould necessitate some form of rent control. The Committee,however, had seen objection to reintroducing any form of rent control in circumstances in which it did not already apply and had suggestedthat it would be unwise to do more at this stage than to undertaketo provide that there should be no eviction without an order of thecourt. But, since evictions otherwise than under court order were theexception, this would make little contribution to the problem andthere was a risk that it would be assumed to represent the limit of the
Governmenfs intentions. It would be preferable to indicate that theGovernment intended to give extended security of tenure to all tenants and to provide for eviction only by order of the court; and that, if theMilner Holland report showed that more drastic action was necessaryin London, they would be prepared to provide some greater measureof security for London tenants, coupled with a form of control overrents, so long as the acute pressure on housing continued. It wouldbe desirable to say, at the same time, that the level of rents currentlysubject to control would be increased on the basis of rateable values.In discussion it was pointed out that the reintroduction of any form of rent control would imply an admission that the Rent Acthad failed in its purpose and would be a reversal of the policies thatthe Government had pursued during the previous 12 years. Moreover,experience suggested that, even in the short term, rent control mightaggravate the problem; and, while the proposals put forward by theMinister of Housing might be welcome to the governments supporters in London, they would be likely to be criticised in otherparts of the country where, although the housing shortage was lessacute, it was none the less a lively issue. In the circumstances the best course appeared to lie in repeating previous assurances that, if theMilner Holland report showed the necessity for action, theGovernment would be prepared to take further steps to preventabuses and to strengthen the safeguards against exploitation. It wouldbe desirable to seek, at the same time, to focus attention particularly on the announcement that the Government were releasing at woolwich Arsenal an area of land sufficient to provide homes for50,000 people.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Housing and Local Government tobe guided, in the forthcoming debate on housing, by the considerations which had emerged during their discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,16th July, 1964.

</content>
</cab>
