<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/65/0 images: 104-104</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.)

SECRET.

G.T.5825

BATTLE SITUATION - NOON - 29th SEPTEMBER, 1918.

WESTERN FRONT.

British Front.

On the YPRES Battle Front.

There is no further news from the Belgian Front. The 2nd Army have captured MESSINES and KRUISEECK and are advancing on MENIN.

This morning we attacked from ST. QUENTIN to the SCARPE. On the CAMBRAI Battle Front.

We continue to make progress and have captured VILLERS GUISLAIN - GOUZEAUCOURT - LA VACQUERIE - East of MARCOING we have enlarged our bridgehead and have crossed the canal E. of CANTAING. Further north the line runs East of SAILLY - E. of EPIN0Y - E. of AUBENCHEUL-AU-BAC. North of the River we hold ARLEUX.

On the ST.QUENTIN Battle Front.

We are reported to have made good progress and have crossed the BELLIC0URT underground Canal. The weather is fine.

French Front.

Between the AILETTE and the AISNE progress has been made to the line SOUPIR - OSTEL CHAVIGNON - PINON.

On the ARGONNE Battle Front.

The Americans and French have made slight progress. 

MACEDONIAN FRONT.

The advance continues on the whole front. On the right, the line NEGRANOVCI - LIPOVIc - RADOVISHTA has been reached. The Serbians arE east of ISHTIB and their cavalry beyond KOCHANE are 10 kilometres from Bulgarian frontier. Towards USKUB they have passed KARABUNISTE and RUDNIK.

On the road to BROD the line MARGARI, ZRZE, SAZDOVO, JAKRENOVO has been reached by the French and Greeks.

The Italians have taken Mount CESMA on the BABA heights and their cavalry have reached the MONASTIR - KIOEVO road North of DEMIR-HISSAR.

The French have taken RESNA and CARIDVOR and between the Lakes PRESPA and OCHRIDA they have passed the enemy&apos;s front line.

ITALIAN FRONT. Nothing to report.

PALESTINE FRONT. Our cavalry have reached EL KUMEITRA and have joined up with the Arabs at DERAA. They are moving northwards towards DAMASCUS.

General Staff,

War Office, S.W.1.

29th September, 1918.

Issued at 1 p.m.

</content>
</cab>
