<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/65/0 images: 106-108</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property.of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s 1&quot;if llll iiimilllllmwiwiiiii 11     n ir 1M11 in &quot; i hi in i nil i m in i- ri n in n   i 111 il i...............i.....in.........nitiitn.....mm.....-      -    ---- ---      . - ---______.**___________&quot;.....Government.!Printed for the War Cabinet.   September 1918.77sSECRET.MAN-POWER 1918 AND 1919.Memorandum by the Minister of Munitions.I HAVE read Sir Auckland Geddes&apos; memorandum on man-power 1918-19, and desire to make the following observations upon it: 1. The Ministry of Munitions will do everything in their power to meet the requirements set out by Sir Auckland Geddes. While reserving a final decision on details, I consider that the numerical quota asked for should be maintained, and can, I trust, be even improved upon. It will be essential, however, that whatever combing and dilution measures are adopted by the Ministry of Munitions should be applied in the same degree to the establishments under the Admiralty.2. I disagree altogether with the view taken by Sir Auckland Geddes of the relative urgency of the needs of the various services. I do not know what reasons there are for assuming that the Germans have the power greatly to intensify the submarine warfare next year. Intensification, I presume, means an increase in the balance of world-sinkings of merchant ships over world-buildings. Are we really expecting this? It is certainly contrary to everything so far revealed by statistics, and to every statement that has hitherto been made on the subject by the First Lord and other representatives of the Admiralty. I understood that the success of Admiralty measures against submarines had resulted in the rate of destruction of submarines being greater than that of their building. I understood that submarine crews were even harder to find in Germany than submarine boats. The figures presented to us each month show that the diminution of the adverse tonnage balance is substantially maintained. Every estimate we have had contemplates an increase in the monthly world-buildings of merchant ships. Every month the number of our anti-submarine craft and the efficacy of their devices is augmented. Unless all these statements and figures are vitiated by some new facts which have never yet been brought to the notice of the War Cabinet, to raise a vague scare of some vast new submarine attack upon our ocean communications is, at this stage of our affairs, only to add to our difficulties.3. With regard to naval aviation, I consider, as is stated below, that the aviation programmes as a whole require reconsideration; but there is no part of our Air Force which so much requires searching overhaul as the naval section. There are in the Royal Naval Air Force at the present time 3,000 officers and 25,000 men, including an exceptionally high proportion of the most skilful mechanics in the country. No one will deny the splendid work of this force, or the high morale of its officers and men; but at the pass to which we are come, not actual but relative efficiency should be the test. A close comparison should be instituted between the work of the R.N.A.S. and the work of the R.A.F. in France in respect to (a.) The number of machines maintained compared to the total personnel;(&amp;.) The number of hours&apos; flight over the line or over the sea;(c.) The number of enemy machines destroyed, for which purpose a submarinemight well count as 25 machines; (d.) The weight of bombs dropped; (e.) The casualties sustained.It is quite understood that np comparison can yield precise results. There will still remain important services discharged by both branches, reconnaissance and artillery observation, on the one hand; the prevention of submarine attacks on shipping, on the other, which would not lend themselves to such an analysis; but I am confident that an honest survey of the two branches of our aviation wili show that a: surprisingly small result is reaped from the great volume of material and of personnel devoted to naval aviation.
4. The proposal to use aeroplanes for the purposes of inshore anti-submarine patrolling did not emanate from the Admiralty, but from a naval officer employed under the Ministry of Munitions, and I have personally always been a very strong believer in its importance and value; but as originally put forward, the proposal was to utilise aeroplane engines which were not suited for the intense fighting on the Western front, as an addition to all the other naval means of coping with the sub-marine. This has rapidly been expanded under the genial influences of absolute and unlimited priorities into a demand-for thirty-three squadrons of specially-manu-factured anti-submarine aeroplanes (apart from flying boats). It has, therefore, ceased to be a utilisation of spare resources, but a new drain on our limited resources. This fresh demand should certainly be scrutinised from the point of view of the results achieved.More than 27,000 men are employed in the lighter-than-air services, without counting the equivalent labour demand to supply those services. This compares with 27,800 men in the Tank Corps at the present time. How do the results compare so far as real use against the enemy is concerned ? The total reduced demands of the navy for aviation amount to a total of 122 squadrons (exclusive of lighter-than-air) as against 111 squadrons required for the armies in Trance (exclusive of the Independent Air Force). It is probably safe to say that of the whole of this enormous volume of high-class material and brilliant personnel claimed by the Admiralty, 75 per cent, will never in fact make contact with the enemy. Yet Sir Auckland Geddes proposes that an overriding priority shall be accorded to naval aviation against all men and machines required for our squadrons fighting on the battle-front or engaged in the bombing of Germany. One would at least have thought he would have been contented with &quot; share and share alike.&quot;So far as the Air Force as a whole is concerned, I knowr that great efforts are being made to increase the fighting output relatively to the men and material involved. But no one would assert that the limit of efficiency has yet been achieved. Very often in England things are started because they are necessary at the time, and then afterwards they are kept going indefinitely, eating up men, although the need which brought them into existence may have diminished or gradually changed. For instance, the Germans have built a few score of Gothas for raiding England, against which we have erected, rightly no doubt, an enormous organisation of defence, com-prising hundreds of guns and searchlights, a score of squadrons of aeroplanes, balloon services of various kinds, &amp;c, &amp;c. Thus the German Gotha menace has, although in itself costing them so little, abstracted from our available strength very possibly 20 or 30 times what it has cost them. Such arrangements should be reviewed, not only to see if they are now too big or if circumstances have changed, but in order that at the decisive moment, even at some risk of inconvenience in this country, these forces may be made to play their part in the decisive offensive.5. The difficulty ahout restricting any Admiralty demand which may be made lies in the absolutely vital character of the services rendered by the Royal Navy in all its branches. We have only to contemplate what would befall us if our battle fleets were decisively defeated, or if the submarine blockade became really effective, to decide that whatever is necessary must immediately be granted. That is no reason for falling into the other extreme and acceding to all kinds of demands which, however desirable in themselves, are not really necessary to the naval foundations of our existence. It is no reason for excluding naval requirements from a fair and searching scrutiny. While naval necessities must have the highest priority, there is no reason why all the luxuries of the navy should rank before the primary and none the less vital needs of other services.6. Yet this is what is happening now, and will continue to happen unless the Cabinet giA^e a much more refined and precise ruling upon the subiect of priorities. At the present time it is broadly true to say that the Admiralty take in man-power, in high-class materials, in available plant, in skilled labour what they choose, and that it is only after this that the other needs of the State are then considered. The same is true also of the American navy. Mr. Ryan, the United States Under-Secre-tarv for Aviation, informs me that the American Admiraltv claims absolute oriority over the Liberty motors, and that a great part of these precious engines, on which the whole of our offensive bombing programme depends, has up to date been swallowed bv the American naval aviation. What have they done with them? What war results have been produced from them?  How many Huns have they killed?7. There is no doubt that at the present time we are heavilv over-insured so far as the Navy is concerned. The total demand upon the available man-power of
September 25, 1918.WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.the country for fighting and labour of the Admiralty, including merchant ship-building, at the present time has been estimated in our official reply to Colonel Roure at more tnan two million men, representing the flower oi.the nation&apos;s manhood. Three-fourths of this demand is no doubt absolutely justified, but we must not be surprised that Allied nations, who have no similar reason for withholding an immense proportion of their manhood from the blood tax of this war, should view it with jealousy and suspicion, And surely it is an obliga-tion upon us to ask ourselves perpetually the question, at this stage in the struggle, whether we are really confining ourselves to what is necessary, and to no more than is necessary. If we compare the subtraction from our war effort on the decisive battle-front involved in (a) our battle fleets, &amp;c, and in (b) our anti-submarine arrangements with the similar subtraction from the German battle front involved in the maintenance of the German high-seas fleet and its submarine flotillas, we shall be amazed at the terrible effectiveness of the latter in reducing our power to end the war. If we add all that America is doing, and all that our other Allies possess in naval defence, it will be seen that the German navy and its submarine flotillas are probably at the present time &quot; containing &quot; twenty Allied war-power units for one that they themselves are forced to allocate. If, therefore, there is in this field any element of over-insurance, it is surely our most urgent duty to eliminate it.8. Further, once the fundamental naval necessities have been made, it is a question of balancing risks. We may over-insure in naval provision, and lose the war through undue weakness on land. While maintaining an excessive naval defence we may allow the war to be so prolonged that the foundations of our civilisation will collapse here, or in Allied countries. By allowing the war to drag on until 1920 we shall make certain that, even if victory is ultimately secured, the United States will be the supreme arbiter of the settlement. There are clangers in every direction; but it cannot be contended that the naval dangers at the present time are comparable, so far as the battle fleets are concerned, to those which existed at the outbreak of the war, or comparable to those which existed eighteen months ago in regard to submarine warfare. For these reasons I urge that the naval establish-ments should be reviewed; that services which are not yielding an effective war value should be restricted; that vessels which cannot play a part in 1919 should not be begun, or if only recently begun should be suspended; that work should be concentrated on finishing up vessels which are most nearly completed; that the manning requirements of new anti-submarine construction should be met to a considerable extent by reducing the older redundant vessels of the battle fleets and obsolescent types generally; that instead of diverting men from the Army and from the Royal Air Force, a loyal and earnest effort should be made by the Admiralty to assist the Army in its supreme need both of men and material.9. Differing diametrically from Sir Auckland Geddes, I think we should place first for 1919 the maintenance in the field of that splendid British Army which ever since the spring of 1917 has borne the brunt of the struggle in France, and will yet, if properly nourished, constitute next vear the most powerful offensive force in the field. To maintain that Army at its highest possible strength in divisions, to keep the battalions of those divisions at their full strength during the decisive battle months, to supply it with every form of munition and equipment which it can use, are the primary objects for which we should labour now.

</content>
</cab>
