<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/65/0 images: 164-167</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I     (This document is &quot;the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;b Government)W A&quot;R   CABINET. ,       JO?RECONSTRUCTION.AHC INDUSTRIAL CONDITIONS. (Memorandum by the Minister of Reconstruction).1, The Adult Education Committee have presented anInterim Report on the Industrial and Social Conditionswhich they consider to be an essential preliminary tothe proper development of our Educational System,   TheReport (Cel. 9107) has attracted widespread attention In the*Press and elsewhere, and I attach for the Information of my colleagues a summary of the recommendations:-2, SUGARY OF RECOMMENDATIONS:(a) That there should be a general shortening by law of the normal working day, and that, subject to the qualifications already suggested in the case of certain industries such as agriculture, it should not be more than eight hours(b) That la heavy and exhausting kinds of work, and work accompanied by special disabilities, the maximum legal working day should be shorter than the normal; and that heavy and exhausting occupations should be /specially regulated, and wherever possible mechanical devices introduced(c) That overtime should be more closely regulated by law and reduced to a minimum(d) That where t! shift&quot; work continues, the hours should be reduced below those of the normal working-day; and that, except where it is absolutely essential, regular night-work,- whether periodical or continuous, should be prohibited by laxv(e) That efforts should be made to meet the evil effects of monotonous labour by alternating forms of employment, by creating opportunities for the exercise of initiative, and by establishing works committees ior the consideration of matters affecting workshop life(f) That steps should be taken to guarantee to the worker some reasonable security of livelihood, either by such a reorganisation of industry as may prevent or &apos; minimise fluctuations In the volume of production, or, ;-here that is Impossible., by some extension of the principle of insurance, which would protect the wages-earner against the ruinous effects of such fluctuations as cannot be prevented5838 SECRET.
Note: The question of holidays which is&apos;referrefi to in ia.) above, is also dealt with in a Report I have received from the Civil War1 Workers&apos; Committee and I am making their proposals the subject of a separate memorandum (G.T&apos; 837) which I am presenting simultaneously with this.From whatever point of view the question is regarded It will, I think, be agreed that a large and comprehensive Industrial policy must be an integral part of the Govern-ment1s Reconstruction programme.   The proposals for Military Demobilisation, Resettlement of Civil War *orkers and Pensions discharge the immediate duties of the Government, but there is a demand for much more than these measures:The pledges which were given&apos; With regard to the restoration of trade union practices are becoming more rnd more difficult of literal fulfilment; and whilst it is hoped that alternative arrangements will be made by joint agreement between trade unions and employers&apos; associations, it is clear that the Government will not thereby be relieved(g) That wage-earners should be entitled by lev to wi annual holiday, with pay; and that the weekly hali-ftoliday should be extended by law to the worker In agriculture(h) That the preparation 61 schemes of housiag and tovn-pianning should be accelerated; that such scherr.es should be drawn up in consultation &apos;\ith the best expert advice available, and in co-operation-with representatives of the people for whom such schemes are intended; and that, particularly, representatives of women, who are the persons most concerned, should be included In the Housing end Town Planning, Public Health and other Committees dealing with this question(i) That adorrjiiate washing facilities should be required to be provided In all places of employment where the nature of the work makes it desirable(j) That special consideration should be given to the peculiar problems of rural housing(k) That a village institute/ or at least a hall, should be established in every village unoer public control.
of all itn responsibilities in this respect.as literal restoration has become well-nigh impossible even if it were desirable, legislation rendering statutory the promises of the Government is useful to the skilled unions only as a bargaining weapon, and not as e meaEs to restoration. It is suggested that in these circumstances the Government would be acting in the spirit of justice if it were to guarantee by law some of those improvements in standards and working conditions which trade unions in the past have endeavoured to obtain.   Such rction would in all probability facilitate the negotiation of new industrial agreements more in harmony with the new conditions and developments.   It would, moreover, do much to reconcile the lesser skilled men and women workers whose newly acquired status in industry must inevitably be threatened by the restoration of pre-war practices.   Lastly, there can be no doubt that a considerable improvement in working conditions will be demanded by trade unions after the war.   With their new sense of power, they will probably endeavour to achieve this end in the transition period following the war.     It would be unfortunate if these matters were to be bones of contention at a time when a swift and smooth transference to normal peace conditions is essential to the national interest.It cannot be denied that many of the conditions prevailing in pre-war industry left much to be desired. Indeed, they were not only a source of industrial inefficiency but they were also also a menace to social wellbeing.   The future of this country depends In the last resort upon the opportunities, prosperity, and social and economic standards of the people. , Mth the great development of trade unionism, during the War, and.the extension of the franchise, it is
4,130laeviifele that demands will be made for trie progressive improvement of industrial life and the social&apos;environment.So far as industry is concerned, there is, on a wide view, nothing to be feared from such developments,   Leading employers ore becoming more and more convinced of the wisdSm of high, standards both of wages end working conditions.   In the past some at least of our industries have moved in a vicious circle of inefficient conditions and inefficient production.   This circle must te&apos; broken.   The proper line of development is to rest competition upon scientific methods and machinery, ahd efficient organisation..   Our&apos; position in the markets of the world depends upon the intelligence end co-operation of labour as well as upon methodsj machinery and organisation, Labour will not give of its b st if its remuneration is low, and its working conditions unsatisfactory.The object of the present memorandum is simply to draw the attention cf my colleagues to the concrete proposals of the Adult Education Committee, which foi the reasons briefly indicated in paragraphs 3-5 above seem to me to merit very careful consideration of toe Government,I would suggest that the Cabinet sluould ask the various Department&quot; concerned in these questions to submit a statement of their views on the Committee&apos;s recommendations.iThese memoranda should form the basis for a further discussion in the Cabinet upon the policy to be -adopted by the Government in regard to the important Industrial questions involved..   If the Cabinet is then able to lay down certain guiding principles, I would suggest that the Departments concerned might endeavour to work out in detail the measures for giving effect to such reforms as the Cabinet approve,C. Addison.26.9.18.

</content>
</cab>
