<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/65/0 images: 251-258</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JThls Document is the Property of ,secr is t . &quot;j, -jjiment.) 0OFg HOt liJ.79/9707.li&apos;(L TROOPS REQUIRED FOR HOi;tE DEFEITCE. iJJOTliia question was last dealt with by the YJar Cabinet on the 7tli January 1918 when a paper by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff (G.T.3212) was considered, and the followins decision was arrived at&quot;To take the risk of reducing the forces allocated to &quot;Home-Defence to such strength as would deter an enemy force &quot;up to SO.,000 men from attempting a landing in this country, &quot;and tl^ey authorised the Army Council to make the reductions &quot;in the strength of the Home Defence Force indicated in the &quot;Memorandum by the Chief of the Imperial General Staff (Paper &quot;G.T.,3212),&quot;2i    Measures for effecting the necessary reduction were taken by the Army Council) but subsequently, and in consequence of the situation in France and of the necessity for reinforcing the garrison in Ireland, the mobile troops in Great Britain were reduced considerably below the force which the General Officer Com3&apos;:ianding-in-Chief considered necessary,r3, -In considering the possible soale of attack, the Represont-atives of the Admiralty War Staff and General Staff started from the following Hypotheses* &quot;&quot;(a) That sea transport is available in enemy harbours?(b) That the Admiralty could not guarantee effective interruption within 32 - 36 hours;(c) That the enemy disposed of the necessary military forces if he decided to make the attempt.The last hypothesis was no doubt true in January but I amstrongly of opinion that it Is no longer the case.    Takinginto consideration the fact that the communications of theraiding forces will inevitably be interrupted within 36hours it is not conceivable that provided the vital navaland Industrial centres are adequately guarded any objectwould/
8 $would be achieved Which would warrant tho certain loss of 30,000 men,? more especially In view of the fact that men required to take part in landing operations must, of necessity,- be specially trained and of the highest quality., Consequently I do not consider that there is the remotest prospect of the attempt being made in view of the great difficulties which the enemy is experiencing In maintaining his Armies on the Continent0    An analogous case would have been if dreeing the early summer we had attempted to--land a force between Ernden and Sylt with the object of stopping tho German advance in Prance e-   :At    A joint Naval and Military Conference has recently considered the matter and I attach a copy of their con-elusions (%)Pe^d-lx Q*) with which I concur a    The Conference states that tlae largest force that the enemy may reasonably be expected to hazard in a raid on this country is 5-,COO men, t*eg$ an operation similar in scope to our raid on Zeebrugge,-&apos;;: -   .&apos;- . -:;&apos;     -:--&apos;&apos;/-  &apos; - &apos; &apos; &apos;&apos;*&apos;- --- .&apos; - .&apos;. : -&apos;-vv -V :&apos; --:/ &apos; .:-       &quot;. -\ ; : .-&apos; - -: &apos;v,:&apos;&apos;:;-: V- &apos;.:    \ &apos;;-       : .&apos;; -.:&apos; - - &quot;    V.&apos;;&apos;:-1.&apos;&apos;- -      &apos;: &apos; &apos; . :-&apos;      /::&apos;&apos;        &apos;:   - ----- :&apos;.   -       :&apos;11:v./&apos;*&quot;      . &apos;   &apos;/ .&apos; &apos;.-      .&quot;.&apos;v-:     -:\&apos;&apos;        .&apos;   V .&apos; -V.-5*    Thie being the ease I think that the War Cabinet can   v aocept the risk of reducing the number of troops maintained for Home Defence In Great Britain0-69    I say Great Britain because the case of Ireland requires special consideration *    At the present time we are maintaining a force of over ioo.,000 all arnis*    In this XEsmbor are Included 60800 trained Cyclists of categories Aoic and B*io; who would be of considerable assistance In keeping divisions overseas up to strength, but at the present time^ in view of the intention to enforce conscripts Ion, I am not prepared to make recommendations for their withdrawal97* In the past it has been the custom to lay down a hard and fast scale of Invasion against which preparations mustbe
be made.    Whilst of value as giving a general indication ofthe forces required for defence it is not possible in prac-tice to adhere rigidly to this scale when allotting theavailable troops.I would, therefore, make the following recommendationsto the War Cabinet, assuming always that the Naval situationremains as at present * unassailable.(1)   That as a general principle troops in the United Kingdom be reduced to a draft-finding basis.   To this rule there must be certain exceptions, e,g-, Coast Defence Artillery and Engineers, Anti- Air* craft, Rcyal Defence Corps for guards, etc.,(2)   The namber of draft finding units maintained should be reduced to that which will be sufficient to receive and train for overseas the maximum number of recruits which is likely to be available,(3)   Draft finding units retained should be allocated and grouped in the most convenient manner for the purposes of repelling attack subject always to training considerations.8.    Appendix tAt shows the number of troops which have been available for Home Defence at different periods, and the number ^hich would be available if the above recommendations are endorsed by the War Cabinet.Appendix &apos;B&apos; gives an estimate of the numbers which will be saved by these proposals, a small proportion of whom would be available as drafts for combatant arms, and the remainder for substitution or return to civil life.9.     I should like to make clear to the War Cabinet what will be tho effect of the proposed reductions on Homo Defence. We must keep -it our Defended Ports on the East Coast sufficient troops to defeat any raid which may be anticipated; otherwisewo
19340we should be running the risk of allowing the enemy to destroy the valuable naval and industrial works at these portso   The balance of the Home Defense forces will not be strong enough to admit of the remainder of the Coast being either watched or protected, and must be kept at inland centres from rhleh they can be quickly moved to the threatened pointi   They, therefore, will not be able to prevent the enemy from landing^ although they will eventually crush him. Further, it must be remembered that if the situation alters and it becomes again necessary to provide against attack on a more extended scale we shall not be able to restore for some time the battalions which we are now reducing, but I consider that we are amply justified in taking whatever risk is thereby involved,,(Sgdo)   Henry Wilaon0C PI c Go So1General Staff,War Office, S;WB1. 2nd October, 1918,
S C    JR.   &quot;r^1    *jT -----APPENDIX_A.     to 79/9707Number of Troops available for HO^iE DEFENCE at different periods during 1917,  1918,and under the proposed-scheme of re-organisetiona	Jan.1917.	Dec.1917o	i March 1918.	August 1918.	Under proposed scheme of reorganisation.lc  iOBILE TROOPS.. ^a) Purely Home Defence,,	72 9459	74,097	73,784	33,219	14,470 (In Ireland)(b) Draft finding units available for. Home Defence0	140., 000	133,817	72,725	58,171	29,970(c)  Mainly draft finding Home Service Divisions.	160,000	123,650	74,987	79,611	63,960 (a)Mixed Brigadeso	\* *\			42,175	Nil2,  COAST DEFENCE. R0G-oA0 &amp; R0Eo  (Purely Home Defence)	15,131	23,305	17^453	15,965	15,705Draft, finding Bnscemployed in Coast Dsfence,	135,000	128,000	128,000	128,000	56,3005J A.-At, DEPENCEc	17,341	.19,495	23,679	11,792	12,470V                                   I40  PROTECTIONo R.DaC* &amp; Home Service Garrison Battalions0	70.422	41,725	28,716	35,447	35,000	610.553	544,089	419,344	402,380         1 i	227,875NOTE*- The Mixed Brigades at this period were not draft finding and are included under 1(a). (a).    Tne Home Service Divisions to become wholly draft finding.26o9ol8D
iAPPENDIX &quot;B&quot; to 79/9707.STATEMENT SHEWING NUMBERS MADE AVAILABLE BY:-I.   A.G&apos;a re-organization of Rooorvc Battalions.II.  Abolition of Home Dofonco Troops other than Coast and A.A.DefonceeIII *   The caving which will be effected in adminis-trativc services resulting from:-(a) Tho abolition of various Home Dofonco Units(b) The ro-grouping of those remainingoI *   Pormancnt Cadroa only.By the abolition of 96 Reserve &quot;A&quot; Bnc roleasing permanent cadresHott reduction in permanent cadro of &quot;B&quot; BattalionsReduction in cadres of othor arms and servicesTotal.19,183 11,217 4,200 34,600II.   H.D. TroopsPresent Strong theBy abolition of1 Cyclist Div.1 Cyclist Bcleo Divisional troops of 4 Dive. Troops othor than Infantryin Mixed Brigades^ 15 Cyclist Battalions 2 R.F0A* Batteries. 10 Heavy Batteries *4,924 1,199 14,9583,676 4,192 3502; 137III.  Administrative Services* (Rough estimate)TOTAL31,436 20,000 86,03626.9.18.
APPENDIX &quot;C&quot; to 79/9707-REPORT OF CONFERENCE HELD IN D.0.H.S&apos;fl ROOM ON 30TH SEPTEMBER, 1918, BETWEEN NAVAL AND MILITARY REPRESENTATIVES TO CONSIDER THE QUESTION OF INVASION IN THE LIGHT OF MOST RECENT INFORMATION.PresentJRoar Admiral Sydney R. Fremantlc, C.B., M.V.O.,Deputy Chief of Naval Staff. Major-General CP, Romor, C.B., C.M.G.,Chief of tho General Staff, Forces inGroat Britain * Colonol W.M.St. G. Kirko, C.M.G., D*S.O.,Deputy Director of Military Operations. Liout.-Colonol L.S.T.&apos; Halliday, V.C, CB*,Naval Staff, Representing Director of Piano. Lieut.-Colonol W.T-C Jones, D.S.O.,Naval Staff, Representing Deputy FirstSea Lord.The following gonoral statements on the situation were made -* 1.- Tho Naval Representatives stated that thero is no change in tho Naval considerations affecting tho subject under discussion.2*^ Tho Deputy Director of Military Operations stated that in the opinion of the General Staff, it is no longer possible for Germany to find troops necessary for oven a large scale Raid on the United Kingdo2n, in view of the fact that she is, known to bo short of men on tho Fostorn Front, whilst she must be receiving insistent demands from Austria, Turkey and probably tho Bolshovik Government which cho cannot meet.    The necessity for keeping her Allies in tho War is considered far more vital to Germany than any possible advantage to be gained by. a Raid on England, and it is therefore a reasonable assumption that no attempt to land a force of more than 5.,000 will bo made.The Conference,^ aftor considering the above statements, recommended that modifications to tho following effect should be made in tho conclusions arrived at by the Conference held in December 1917:-The maximum force with which our land forces mightreasonably
1972areasonably be oxpccted to havo to deal, from Cromarty (inclusive) southward to Solsoy Bill (inclusivo), might now bo limited to 5,000 without transport or artillery, tho risks to tho enemy increasing as the point of attempted landing is further to the north of the Wash or to the West of tho Straits of DoveroMoreover, as the forco landed would almost certainly be lost, the enemy would not attempt to land unless he could reasonably expect to inflict damage such as would compensate him for his loosese(S*R.Fromantle* (0 oF-Romero Signed   (WoKirkc.(L.S.T,Balliday (f .T*C.Jonos*

</content>
</cab>
