<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/65/0 images: 335-348</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i^llOocument is the Property of /His CnianET.[i^Li^i^s GovernmentMINISTRY  OF   FOOD.c ...t for Week ending Wednesday, October 2, 1918.PART I.-ACTION TAKEN.Food Council. A meeting of the Council was held on Tuesday, October 1st, Mr. Clynes in the chair.Mr. Beveridge reported that Captain Tallents had been charged with the preparation of a scheme of milk control and distribution. A re-allocation of the winter prices of milk charged to retailers was agreed to by the Council.A resolution of the Home Supplies Board on the subject of home cereals prices for .1919 was considered and it was decided that Mr. Wise should bring the matter before the Joint Officials Committee.Sir Alan Anderson reported that in view of the reduced imports programme it was not considered necessary to proceed with the provision of 5 million cubic feet of cold storage of the 8 million proposed to be built on Government account. It would probably be necessary to construct an insulated store of 3,000,000 cubic feet at Liverpool, but the difficulty was one of transport rather than of storage, and the Port and Transit Corporation were being asked to state a case for submission to the Priority Committee of the War Cabinet.Sir John Beale reported that the Imports Board would take charge of cabling and that Sir William Goode had therefore been invited to join the Board. This decision was approved.Mr. Wise reported that the proposed scheme for rationing feeding-stuffs had been discussed with Sir Daniel Hall and that the Board of Agriculture was favourable, and would appoint a representative on the Allocation Committee. It was proposed that the Chief Live Stock Commissioner should supervise the scheme, which would be worked through the Live Stock Commissioners with the help of local Farmers&apos; Committees approved by the Board of Agriculture.The Imports Board. The first meeting of the Board was held on September 27th, Sir John Beale in the chair.v It was agreed that the Board should act as the &quot; opposite number &quot; of the Allied Provisions Export Commission and the British Ministry of Food in U.S.A., and should ,be the sole channel of cable communication with those organisations and with other agencies of the Ministry abroad for the purchase of commodities other than cereals and sugar.While the detailed work of purchases will be left to the Supply Divisions as at present the Director of Imports will be fully informed of purchases made, progress of deliveries and shipments,, and will be supplied with such other information as may be found necessary so that the Board may be satisfied that the whole business in con-nection with imports of the Ministry is properly conducted.All cables from and to all parts of the world dealing with purchases on British account or in connection with any purchase will come before the Board.Full statements will be prepared for the Board showing the position as to shipping, imports, requirements, and stocks, and the Board will be responsible for ascertaining through its officers that the necessary imported supplies required by the Supply Sections, for the maintenance of the rations or of supplies at the agreed rate, are being purchased, brought forward and shipped at proper dates.The Board will also ascertain that the Financial Branch is fully informed of the progress of purchases and that the necessary financial sanctions have been or are being obtained.Meetings of the Board will be held daily at 11.0 a.m. until further notice.Home Supplies Board. The first meeting of the Board was held on Thursday, September 26th, Mr. Beveridge in the chair.A scheme for the rationing of feeding-stuffs was considered by the Board. The scheme had been approved by the Committee of the Agricultural Advisory Council appointed to consider the question and by the Joint Officials Committee.   It wasA   (33)6038-1   Pkl   140  10/18   E k S
2agreed in view of the urgency of the situation with regard to feeding-stuffs, that the scheme should be pressed forward with the utmost rapidity.It was decided that the Board should meet once, a week on Thursday at 5.30 p.m. Additional meetings may be called on Mondays at 4.0 p.m.The Central Agricultural Advisory Council. At the meeting of the Council, which was held on the 1st October 1918, the question of how to deal with the large number of cattle now being sent to market at the end of the grass season, especially in the north of England, was discussed ; it was stated that a serious situation had arisen since the railway strike took place at the time that these large numbers of cattle were being sent to market, and it had been extremely difficult to dispose of them ; there are no sufficient facilities for freezing meat in this country, and the question of labour for slaughtering is a very difficult one at present.A resolution was passed urging the Ministry of Food to * put at once into consumption or cold storage all stock really fit for slaughter, and to raise the price of cattle at the rate of Is. per cwt. per week from the 1st November onwards, with a corresponding increase in the price of sheep, to compensate the farmer for keeping on all the stock he can possibly hold, and to arrange at once for the release and distribution of a certain quantity of cattle cake, in order that stock may be kept fit during the winter and conserved until the spring.The scheme for the distribution and rationing of cattle feeding-stuffs was again discussed and read. After the meeting of the Council had been concluded, the Sub-Committee which had been appointed for the purpose, went through with the officials concerned, the draft form of application, and the proposed scale of rations for the various classes of stock ; these were agreed to by the Sub-Committee.Consumers&apos; Council. A meeting of this Council was held on Wednesday, October 2nd, Mr. Clynes in the chair. Mr. Hyndman moved :-&quot; That in view of the Order increasing the price of milk to the farmers to -        2s. od. per gallon, which necessitates large increases in the price of butter and cheese, while bringing the. retail price of milk up to no less than lOd. per &apos;        quart in the cities, the Consumers&apos; Council calls upon the Government to use our public funds for the maintenance of the retail price of milk during the coming winter at not more than 6c?. per quart, and further demands that ! similar steps be taken in regard to the price of butter and cheese.&quot; Meanwhile, the Consumers&apos; Council urges upon the Government the necessity for the immediate enforcement of the measures already sanctioned by the Ministry of Food to ensure an adequate supply of milk at the charge of the State and the municipalities and other public bodies for nursing mothers as well as for all children up to the age of five years.&quot;After considerable discussion the resolution was put to the vote in two parts, the first part of the resolution was lost, the second part was carried unanimously.The National Kitchens Movement. -The movement is showing signs of substantial progress in the provinces where some of the large towns have established kitchens, or are about to do so. Rotherham are opening one of the finest kitchens in the county, Ossett another. Yorkshire town opened their first kitchen in the town hall to-day.Leicester have decided to take over nine large coffee-houses, which are assessed at over 2,0001. These coffee-houses&apos; are paying their way, and the&apos; rentals which the Leicester Council are to pay to the local company will be well covered &quot;by income, and little capital outlay involved. This scheme provides for the centre of the town, or the inner ring as it is described. The outer ring is still to be provided for. This can only be done by using Sunday Schools. The Leicester Committee think that as there are so few premises available (a complaint which exists in nearly every district in the country) the Department should obtain powers to commandeer. In nearly every district the National Kitchens movement is handicapped for want of compulsory powers to acquire property.Coventry are putting their scheme a very excellent one into operation next week. Ripon have approved the principle and are establishing a scheme. Richmond, which has several kitchens, are to add to their number. Derby are to add two excellent kitchens. Preston have taken a shop as a National Kitchen on a five years&apos; agreement.   Hull is moving rapidly ahead with a large scheme, and it seems as
3257though Yorkshire would have a record number of kitchens for a single county within two months. Lancashire has shown signs of improvement, and before Christmas there should be excellent developments in this county. Glasgow are to establish four National Kitchens in good shops.American Meat Packers.It is understood that all the Government authorities of the United States have accepted the first three recommendations of the Federal Trade Commission on the Packers, and that they have joined in advising the President to take that course. The recommendations are: (1) The Government acquisition of all stock cars, that is the cars in which live animals are transported.(2) The Government operation of stock yards, - - (3) The Government acquisition of, and operation of, all refrigerator cars.It should be noted that by the Presidents proclamation of June 20th, 1918, the stock yards and packers were only authorised to carry on business under license to be granted under the provision of the American Food Act. The proclamation became operative on July 25th.The Federal Trade Commission, in their report, laid great stress upon the assertion that the five great American packing concerns, even if they owned no packing plants and killed no cattle, would still be equally strong on account of their ownership of the railroad stock and refrigerated cars and other means of. transportation and distribution. The contention of the Federal Trade Commission is that Government acquisition of the railroad cars will enable healthy competition between all the packing interests of the United States, and thus destroy the monopoly of the five great packers. The profits of the larger packers are already limited to considerably less than one-halfpenny per pound upon their animal products.Supplies and Prices.Bacon, Rams and Lard. Alterations in the constitution of the Bacon Advisory Committee are under consideration with a view to making the Committee more representative of the trade as a whole and avoiding over-representation of a particular branch.The decision to reduce the imports of lard will make it impossible to supply manufacturers as had been originally intended.Cheese. -Shipments from New Zealand are coming forward according to require-ments.A further shipment of 246 crates of Canadian cheese ex S.S. &quot;City of Vienna&quot; stranded off Halifax has been made. A small supply of cheese is still coming forward from the United States of America.Cocoa. The lists of raw cocoa available for distribution sent in by the grading committees amount to 10,723 bags. .At the request of the Foreign Office 2,600 tons of raw cocoa discharged from four Dutch ships, which were requisitioned by the Ministry of Shipping in the early part of the year, have been requisitioned by the Ministry, and will be graded and put into distribution forthwith.Coffee. The Admiralty Marshal, with the support of this Ministry, is making application to the Acting President of the Prize Court for orders for sale in respect of 100,000 bags of coffee seized as prize. If the order is made, the Marshal, on instructions from this Ministry, will be able to keep the market -supplied throughout the winter months when the demand on coffee is at its greatest.Dried Fruits. The prices fixed by the Mesopotamia authorities for Persian dates are so excessive (being nearly double those of last&apos;year) that it is not proposed at present to make any purchases. The S.S. &quot; Emanuel&quot; with about 4,000 tons of Greek currants has reached Liverpool. Further shipments are reported of Californian and Indian sultanas.Meat. The particular difficulty of the situation at the moment arises from the fact that more cattle are coming forward to the markets than can be absorbed&apos;by the ration on its present scale. This tends to create some small feeling of resentment in some districts that the ration should have been reduced at this particular juncture, but this feeling is by: no means general. On the. other band, pther grounds for complaint have been entirely removed by the cessation of the issue of frozen meat and the supply of the full ration allowance in home-killed, meat  In order to deal with the
t4surplus of cattle, arrangements have just been completed under which the Army in the United Kingdom will be furnished with home-killed meat. These arrangements will come into operation on Monday next, and it is anticipated that for the next four or five weeks at least the Army can be fed entirely on home-killed meat. This course should have the double advantage of absorbing the surplus cattle and of enabling the Army to build up to some extent the desired reserve stocks of frozen meat. It must still be emphasised that farmers are alarmed at receiving no assurances that feeding-stuffs will be available for them in the winter months, and this in a large measure explains the present rush to the markets. The absence of any inducement to keep back their stock may seriously affect the situation in the early part of next year, as the estimates of home-grown, meat to come forward in these months are not likely to be realised.The rigour with which the meat rationing Orders have been applied to the metropolitan area is now being extended to other parts of the country, and it is expected that this will bring the actual consumption into closer relation with the amount of the permitted ration.Food Prices. Considerable complaint is arising among Food Control Committees, Labour bodies, and from the general public, with regard to the increasing price of foodstuffs generally, and more particularly the increase in the price of milk, Govern-ment butter, and meat. The present price of fresh eggs and fruit also occasion considerable criticism.Divisional Reports.Scotland West. It is reported that since venison was made coupon free, additional quantities have come into the&apos;market, and that it has met with a ready sale at prices varying from Sd. to Is. Id. a lb.The Midlands-It is reported that at a demonstration recently held at Birmingham, at which practically all forms of war industry were represented, the exhibit of the Local Food Control Committee attracted considerable attention. Two lorries depicted the conditions prevailing in England and Germany respectively. On the one was a fine display of bread, bacon, ham, potatoes, &amp;c, all marked &quot; Coupon Free.&quot; On the other, milk, potatoes, cheese, bread, coffee and clothing were shown with the number of coupons required for their purchase, attached to each. The exhibit strikingly emphasised the disparity existing between the two countries after four years of war.Two very successful exhibitions have been organised at Leeds and Sheffield, in connection with the Allotment Holders&apos; Association, which, with Professor Thompsons exhibits of food values, and practical demonstrations in fruit bottling and drying, arranged by Representatives of the Ministry of Food, are said to have proved a valuable aid to propaganda work.Enforcement of Orders.The total number of prosecutions for the week is 575, 83 less than in the previous week.   The number of convictions is 529.The number of Orders in respect of which prosecutions were instituted was 62 ; the principal Orders being : Prosecutions.    Convictions.Rationing      ----- 63 62Bread -        -        -        -                 - 49 45Flour Restriction (Ireland)    -.       -        - 45 41Tea (Retail) Prices     -              -  -        - 37 30   &apos;Soft Fruit (Sales)      -        -               ... 36 36The average fine for England, Scotland and Wales has risen considerably (by 21. 4*. Id.) owing to somewhat heavy fines inflicted under the Bread Order and the Rationing Order.Orders under Defence of the .Realm Regulations. . The Public Meals (Ireland) Order, 1918, dated 21st September 1918, lays down certain regulations and restrictions for all public eating-places in Ireland^ other than canteens under the control of the Navy and Army Canteen Board.Imported Onions Order, 1918, dated September 25th, 1918, controls the price of onions imported into this country and fixes maximum wholesale and retail prices. No imported onions shall be sold in the first instance, except by a licensed dealer, and
2585the sale by retail is prohibited except by a registered retail dealer in potatoes. Certain restrictions are imposed on sales by brokers and wholesale dealers.The Jam and&apos;Syrup (Registration of Dealers) Order, 1918, dated September 26th, 1918, provides for the licensing of dealers in jam or in syrup.. The Margarine (Prices) (Ireland) Order, 1918, dated 27th. September 1918, fixes maximum wholesale and retail prices for margarine in Ireland. The retail price is to be Is. 2d. per lb.The Potatoes (Export from Ireland) Order&apos;(No. 2), 1918, dated 27th September 1918, prohibits any person, except under licence, from consigning or shipping any potatoes of the 1918 crop from Ireland to any destination outside Ireland.The Pig (Sales) Order, 1918, dated 27th September 1918, provides that pigs sold for slaughter must be sold in a market to a Government buyer at the controlled price. An exception is made in favour of the small owner, i.e., one who owns and sells for slaughter not more than three pigs in any year, and owners of pigs may be specially authorised to send their pigs direct to bacon factories. The maximum price remains the same except that a per head charge will be made to cover the cost of transport and distribution. The Order brings the sale of pigs for slaughter under the same, control as the sale of cattle and sheep.      - (! ,.,   ;The British-made Butter (Restriction) Order, 1918, dated 28th September 1918, introduces a new scheme for the distribution of butter, and restricts the purchases of British-made butter by retailers, caterers, and institutions. Purchases willbe permissible only on a permit form from. Local Food Control Committees, and&apos;the retailer&apos;s allowance of British-made and Government butter will not exceed 2 6zs. per week per registered customer.Order amending the Milk (Winter Prices) Order, 1918, dated 30th September 1918, substitutes the following maximum prices for those fixed by the Milk (Winter Prices) Order, 1918, on a sale by a wholesaler, when delivery, is made to the buyers&apos; premises,:  . .;2s. l\d. from October 1st to 7th.2s. Qd. from October 8th to November 21st.2s. l\d. from November 22nd to December 16th.2s. 8cl. from December 17th to April 30th.The Intoxicating Liquor (Output and Delivery) (Ireland) Order, 1918, dated 30th September 1918, lays down certain conditions for the supply of beer to license holders in Ireland by the- wholesalers, with. a view to the more equitable distribution of beer in the country.British&apos;Onions Order, 1918, dated 1st October 1918, fixes the maximum price of British eating and pickling onions of the 1918 crop on a gradually ascending scale from October 1918 to April 1919. Eating onions are those which will not pass through a II&quot; mesh, and pickling onions are smaller ones. Onions must be sold by weight, eating onions must not be used for pickles, nor must British onions be mixed with imported onions.PART IT-SUMMARY OF THE FOOD POSITION.. The greater consumption of bread and flour, to which special attention was directed in last week s Report, appears (from the enlarged issues to retailers) to be increasing:&apos; &apos;The rise in prices is attracting attention and in certain localities is leading to grave, discontent. L . . 6Imports.The improvement in total imports, indicated in last week&apos;s Report, has not been m^Dedrr&amp;e,total ,weight, of,ltthe principal foods and feeding-stuffs imported: falling from 205,700 to 164,200 tons.   During the first four weeks of the new cerealJS   6638-1 &quot;     M u c       -   &apos; -P.
6year the imports generally have been less than last year, due mainly to the reduced import of barley, oats, and maize, as will be seen in the following table :-September Imports (4 weeks).	1917.	1918.	Increase or Decrease.		1917.	1918.	Increase or Decrease.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.		Tons.	Tons.	.    Tons.Total    -    -	804,300	684,800	1 - 119,500-	Lard	1,900	12,600	-r  10,700Wheat   -	220,100	298,200	+  78,100	Butter   -	4,800	3,800	-   1,000&apos;Flour    -	66,200	59,200	-    7,000	Margarine	2,400	* -  	-    2,400Equivalent  in	307,100	372,000	4-  64,900	Cheese -	14,600	16,000	-f    1,400Grain.				Condensed milk	5,500	18,500	-f  13,000Barley,    oats,	220,500	82,100	- 138,400	Sugar	161,000	98,700	- 62,300and maize.				Tea      -	5,600	8,800	-H    3,200Rice	41,900	800	-&apos;. 41,100	Coffee   -	500	800	+      300Meat	39,400	32,900	-    6,500	Cocoa    -	1,300	6,200	4-    4,900Bacon    -   ; -	18,600	46,200	-f  27,600				Compared with the previous week there was, in the week ended 28th September, a slight rise in wheat but a fall in wheaten flour, the imports in equivalent grain (98,200 tons) being 15,000 tons lower. They were, however, very much higher than in the corresponding week of 1917 (61,200 tons). No rice arrived, and very little maize (1,300 tons). Bacon imports recovered somewhat, but the quantity (9,000 tons) is insufficient to meet current consumption. Beef and mutton dropped back from 13,300 tons to 4,400 tons ; but canned and other meat (3,700 tons) was above the average. There was a good import of lard (4,200 tons) and of condensed milk (3,600 tons), but butter (1,200 tons) and cheese (1,760 tons) were below the average. Sugar imports, which were up to the average in the previous week (26,900 tons) fell to 15,800 tons ; the imports a year ago were 55,400 tons. There was a larger import of tea (5,700 tons). Imports of coffee and cocoa were small, and the totals for the first nine months of the year have been far below those of the corresponding nine months of 1917.Consumption.. Bread and Flour. The marked increase in consumption for the four weeks ended September 14th (Table E) was emphasised in last week&apos;s Report. As compared with the four previous weeks the increase amounted to 4 per cent., and as compared with the corresponding period in 1917, to at least 10 per cent. The index number is now higher than it has been at any time since the record commenced in April 1916, with the exception of March 1917, when, however, there was a shortage of potatoes.Another index of consumption is provided by the deliveries of flour from mills plus the imported flour issued direct to agents. The average weekly supplies during four weeks ended August 17th were 91,100, August 24th 92,700, August 31st 95,200, September 7th 102,800, September 14th 104,500, and September 21st 105,500 tons. This steady increase confirms the conclusion reached on the basis of the bakers&apos; returns, and carries it to a later date.To some extent the increased consumption represents a normal seasonal variation, but it is also no doubt due to the improved palatableness of the loaf, and suggests that the need for strict economy is being less.generally recognised.Meat. Supplies of cattle at markets increased by a further 17 per cent, while sheep fell off slightly (Table C). The rate in both cases is approximately equal to that of September last year. The weight of meat produced, however, is less, and the total supply of home-fed butcher&apos;s meat of all kinds in Great Britain for the week, estimated at 19,400 tons, is about 20 per cent, less than the weekly rate for September of last year. , Issues of refrigerated meat fell to 3,600 tons. Owing to difficulties of transport, it will remain necessary to feed part of the population on imported meat even when home supplies become sufficient to meet the demands of the ration.Milk. The index number of milk carried by the principal railways is falling, steadily, but not out of proportion to the normal seasonal deliveries, and the September, 1918, index is above that of September, 1917. The latest live stock estimates for Great Britain show a satisfactory increase in the dairy herd, and the number of new animals added to the herd indicates the confidence of the farmer in the future of the dairy industry. As in the case of meat, however, mere numbers will avail nothing if sufficient feeding-stuffs are not obtainable;   :
Fish. Weekly arrivals of fish at Billingsgate and at several provincial markets in recent weeks show a steady decline. As compared with a weekly average of 4,061 tons for August, the figures for recent weeks are as follows : 	September 7th,	September Mth.	September 21st.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.Billingsgate     -	2,055	1,843	1,732Other markets   -	1,516	1,444	1,281Total   -	3,571 ..	3,287	3,013Stocks.During the third week of September stocks of meat and provisions have undergone few important changes. There has been a fall of 2,000 tons in the stock of mutton, compensated by a rise of 2,200 tons in beef, a fall of 2,000 tons in bacon, and a further fall of 2,200 tons in butter. There has been a continued increase in the stocks of condensed milk due to the policy of the Ministry in building up a reserve in anticipa-tion of the milk position in the coming winter. The stocks held by the Ministry now amount to 34,000 tons. Other Ministry stocks include bacon 62,500 tons, refrigerated meat 15,200 tons (apart from 5,200 tons held by the Board of Trade for civilian consumption), canned meat 10,000 tons, cheese 14,700 tons, butter 10,400 tons, lard 20,200 tons, and rabbits 4,000 tons. (N.B.-Certain figures appearing in last week&apos;s Report (Table F) have been amended to include a larger number of ware-houses.),   Prices.Recent variations in prices relate principally to meat a&apos;nd milk. Retail meat prices were increased by 2d. a lb., on September 22nd, the corresponding wholesale prices of beef increasing from 114s. 4d to 133s., and of mutton from 121s. 4d. to 140.&quot;;. per rcwt. Retail milk prices were increased on October 1st from Sd. to 9d. a quart, plus Id. per quart if delivered in bottles, provided the milk is bottled under proper sanitary conditions.
8Table A.-Imports of Principal Food and Feeding Stuffs.so y$*?&apos;:&apos;				Average Weekly Net Iraports* in 1913.	Average Weekly Imports.		Total Imports, ;	Article.	Week ending September 28th, 1918.	Week cnxling September 21st, 1918.	Week ending September 29th, 1917,		39 Weeks from Dec, 30th, 1917, to Sept. 28th, 1918.	Corres-ponding Period. 1917.	39 Weeks from Dec. 30th, 1917 to Sept. 28th, 1918.	Cones-ponding Period, 1917.1.	2.	3.	4.	5.	C.	7.	8.	9.1. Wheat-2. Wheaten flour 3. Rice   -4. Beef   (fresh and ref rige-rated). 5. Mutton (fresh and refrige-rated). 6. Meat, unenu-merated (re-frigerated and     pre-served). 7. Bacon     and Hams. 8. Lard   -9. Butter-10. Margarine 11. Cheese 12. Condensed milk. 13. Sugar (refined and      un-:. t   . refined). .14. Sugar, glucose	Tons. 91,335 5,455 2,801 1,617 3,723 9,018 4.207 1,203 &apos; 2 1,760 3,c84 15,757 46	Tons. 89,385 19,095 8,768 4,516 2,228 6,651 2,878 2,559 3,913 3,893 26,859 1	Tons. 47,865 10,110 11,162 5,309 547 2,280 3,156 127 2,755 22 8,031 1,690 55,415 58	Tons. 101,378 9,712 2,554 8,849 5,125 2,126 5,267 1,629 3,867 1,460 2,137 742 37,333 1,408	Tons. 42,544 30,583 9,321 7,076 2,195 2,793 12,550 2,749 1 1,731 392. 2,479 2,578 27,623 456	Tons. 106,919 12,808 5,418 5,540 2,478 2,615 8,195 &apos;;: 1,958 2,168 1,969 2,953 1,442 27,546 1,290	Tons. 1,659,205 1,192,730 : 363,510 275,965 85,592 108,948 489,460 107,208 67,521 15,300 96,682 100,545 1,077,311 17,794	Tons. 4,169,840 499,500 211,325 216,073 96,629 101,981 319,622 76,360 84,553 76,799 115,189 56,260 1,074,263 50,298Total	140,508	170,746-	148,527	188,587	145,070	188,299	5,657,771	7,148,69215, Barley -16. Oats   -17, Maize -	4,350 12,040 1,305	4,685 17,040 9,420	5,340 44,100 19,650	21,565 17,464 46,450	6,201 8,678 16,019	7,414 13,558 29,223	241,850 338,455 624,740	289,110 528,775 1,139,720Total	17,695	81,145	69,090	85,479	30,898	50,195	1,205,045	1,957,60518. Tea    -19. Coffee, raw -20. Cocoa, raw -	5,700 172 153	1,226 94 2,505	758 3 68	2,640 319 542	3,832 112 492	1,941 666 .  1,375	149,455 4,383 19,177	75,690 25,971 53,642Total	6,025	3,825	829	3,501	4,436	3,982	173,015	155,303Grand Total  -	164,228	205,716	218,446	272,567	180,404	237,476	7,035,831	9,261,600	Net Imports. *			Average Monthly Net Imports* in 1913.	Average Monthly Net Imports.*		Total Net Imports.*		Month ending August 31st, 1918.	Month ending July 31st, 1918.	Month ending August 31st, 1917.		8 Months Jan.-Aug., 1918.	Corres-ponding Period. 1917.&apos;	&apos; 8 Months Jan.-Aug,, 1918.	Corres-ponding Period, 1917.21. Oil seeds and nuts    and kernels. 22. Oilseed cake 23. Oils,    vege-table, relined and   unre-tined. 24. Oil, fish, train, blubber, and	Tons. 89,270 21 24,039 16,438	Tons. 89,898 -lot 19,416 8,845	Tons. 60,633 16,570 4,135 7,982	Tons. 120,314 29,436 6,690 5,424	Tons. 98,291 604 9,741 6,194	Tons. 90,471 18,924 3,131 4,416	Tons. 786,330 4,834 77,932 49,556	Tons. 723,767 151,394 25,052 35,327sperm. 25. Stearme	264	5	79	304	192	225	1,534	1,799* Imports less re-exports of Foreign and Colonial Produce and less exports of British Produce of the same kind, t Net export.
9Statistics illustrating Consumption of Meat.Table B.-Civilian Consumption of Meat in the United Kingdom (measured as Percentages of the Average Monthly Consumption in 1916).	Home Fed.			Foreign.				Home and Foreign. -; 1   Index Numbers .;   -   \ -combined..			1916, .	1917.	1918.	1916.	1917.		1918.	1916.	1917.&apos;	1918.January	116	94%	63i	106		94	31	115	941	58%February   -	- 1041	86	:  52&quot;:	1 .   95		88%	79-1	103 &apos;	&quot;86j	.551March	106	95%	.     54.1.	i;   102		77%	9.3%	1051	93	601April        -      -	94%	90	52	99		80*	98f	95l	88-1	58%May -      -      -	85-1	90	,   40	109		58%	127	89&quot;	851	52^June -      -      -&apos;	861	75	38	101		58	156-J,	88%	72j	54&quot;July -     -      -	84&quot;	831	481	122		67^	142&quot;	891	81%	62August	91	951	57	102		44&quot;	1451	92	88&quot;	691September -   , -	99	951		114		65		101	91	October     -   ! -	1051	108&quot;		86		65		102	101 \	November -   &apos; -	no%	1021		&apos; 86		501		107	95	December -   &apos; -	117	94		78		32		112	80	Table C. Index Numbers illustrating the Average Weekly Supply of FatCattle and Sheep in Great Britain.[Measured as Percentages of the Monthly Average in 1917.,	Cattle.			Sheep.			1916.	1917.	1918.	1916.	1917.	1918.January  .....	103	93	681 &apos;	84    &apos;	78	92February	1041	92	73&quot;	76	81	53%March     -      -      -	105&quot;	941	69%	.......70	81	60%April      -      -      -	941	98&quot;	681	..... 69	79	59%May       -            -	83%	...    95^	5l&quot; -	........ 74-1	..... 761	50June      -     -     -	781	80&quot;	42	104	931	i   74July.....	72	87	53		100&quot;	i  103August    -----	76	1001-	70	1361	123   -	115%September      -     -	961	109		125	i 126	October   -            -	97	121%		98	&apos; 125	November    V -	106	120		96	127	December -      -&apos;;    -     -.     -	99	109		77	110						Cattle,	Sheep. .Provisional estimate.&quot;-&quot;Week ended			-   September 7th; -		&apos; 1   84	118I                                    (ill 1 i &apos;   -      &apos;   ! %\  &apos; 00 i.:	! ;		September 14th		106&apos;	125			September 21st		124	120
10Table D.-Animals Slaughtered in 10,097 Private and Public Slaughterhouses in Great Britain in August 1917, July 1918, and August 1918.	Cattle,	Calves.	Sheep and Lambs.	Pigs.August 1917     -....... July 1918   -     -     -     -     -     ---	153,363 84,603 105,514	27,756 20,988 21,062	753,506 672,632 785,209	141.166 60,767 61,849Percentage Increase or Decrease : August 1918 compared with August 1917  -	-31 -2 \	-24-l0/0		-56-21August 1918 compared with July 1918	+24-71	+ 0-4o/o	+ 16-81	Index Numbers of Animals Slaughtered (measured as percentages of the levels of September 1917).	battle.	Calves.	Sheep and Lambs.	Pigs.1916-17.				September   -	96*	73*	921	134October .          -      -     -     -	102	n	84&quot;	154*  .November	104	75*	78*	161December   -     - ,   -     -     -      -	104*	61	68*	193*J anuary.....-	98 	66*	71*	163&quot;February     ......	90*	104*	65	142March       -     -      -     -     -	96*	157	70	140April -------	86	159	66*   .	130	93	152	67	124	87	.  121*	80	111July   -	84	119*	90	106August      -     -     -     -	106*	119	no*	1211917-18.				September......	100	100	100	100October	1154	106*	104	112November   -      -      -	115&quot;	97	101	1091December   -     -           f -	1161	77*	811	126&quot;January      ......	63j	81	71*	113*February    -     -      -     -     - , . -	604	121	35	.  91*March        -     -     -     -     -     -	63&quot;	183	43	59	.61*	.172	45	47*May   -     -     -     -     -	58	119	39*	48	38	83	53	48July   -     -     -     -     -	59	90	&apos; 98*	52August      -     -      -     -     -      -	73	90	115    .	53 .....Table E.-Index Numbers of Consumption of Bread, Milk, and Provisions.Retail Consumption of Bread and Flour (measured as percentages of the level ofMay 1917).		191&apos;6.	1917.	1918.		(4 weeks ended) 					January 5th      -      -		941	96		February 2nd    -----	-	99&quot;	100*		March 2nd -      -      -      -      -      -		102*	100J		March 30th.....	 	104*	100		April 27th -   . -      -      -	99	101	10C		May 25th......	100	100	98		June 22nd -      -      -	m &apos;	95	98		July 20th......	99&quot;	91*	96		August 17th	95	89i 901 (92)	98		September 14th -      -      -     -      -	94		102	i	October 13th     -      -      -      -	951	97&quot; (96)			November 10th  -	98&apos;	100			December 8th    -	101*	100		The numbers in brackets are adjusted for the probable cbangejn. the.stock pf flour heldat home before and after th* reduction in price on September 17th.
11Index Numbers of Quantities of Milk carried by Seven of the Principal Railway Companies in England and Wales.(Weekly averages measured as percentages of the level in September 1917.)1917.		1918.		1918.	September	100	January -		Week ended :	October -	97 	February	87*	September 7 th	103November     -:	93i 85J	March   -	93i	September 14th	102  ,December		April	&apos;97l-   .	September 21st	101		May	107&quot;				June	112				July	106				August -	104		Consumption of Provisions, based on returns from Multiple Shops and Co-operative Societies (measured as percentages, of the levels of October 1917).	Butter.			Lard,			1916.	1917.	1918.	-  1916.	1917.	1918.(4 weeks ended) 						January 19th	 	150	43		98	37February 16th   -		135	37	 	101	30March 16th      -      -		127	43	 	94	28April 13th -     -	-	141	67	. 	82	54May 11th -      -	-	154	78	 	84	58June 8th        ; -     -------		155	86	 	79	45July 6th   -   ; -	-	165	96	 	82	70August 3rd       -     -		171	108	  .	91	96!    August 31st     -	*213	168	108	85	96	.    , 89September 29th -	*207	191		85	95	October 27th	194	100		85	100	November 24th -	176	54		120	. &apos; 66	December 22nd -	175	54		.  113	.    43 ;&apos;:		Bacon and Hams. .			Cheese.		January 19th		135	67	_	102	54February 16th   -      -      -	-...	143	48		108	51March 16th      -     -     -	 	122	54	 	92	52April 13th -      -	 	120	70	 	86	43May 11th -   i -      -		129	137	 	91 .	27June 8th   -	 	139	196	 	96	42July 6th   ....	 	153	187	-	113	50August 3rd       -     -	 	149	168	 &apos;	&quot;&apos; 108	53August 31st      -     -     -.	*157 .	136	153	*146	.86	54September 29th -	*146	127		*140	107	October 27th , -     -	143	100		140	100	November 24th -     -	148	85		130	102	December 22nd -	165	85		124	92 &apos;	* For these months no returns were obtained from Co-operative Societies in England ancTiYales.&apos;0 3
12Table F.*-Stocks of the Principal Foods and Feeding Stuffs in theUnited Kingdom.Article.	September 1st, 1918.	August 1st, 1918.	September 1st, 1917.	Stocks in the United Kingdom including estimated Farm Stocks.		Wheat (including flour)$ -         -         -         -Barley^ .          -         -         -Oats$    -        -&apos;        -Beans ^   -        -        -Peas$    -         -       , -	Ions. 3,147,000 1,416,000 3,824,000 175,000 .  107,000	Tons. 1,567,000 220,000 149,000 59,000 51,000	Tons. 3,290,000 1,427.000 3,469,000 153,000 69,000- !           .	Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports, Warehouses, &amp;c.		Maize    -         -Rice (including ground rice and rice flour) Grain Meals      - - -Sugar    -       ] -        -        -        -	36,000 219,000 48,000 372,000	65,000 217,000 51,000 283,000	102,000 107,000 24,000 136,000Butter   -        -        -        -  &apos;MargarineLard      -Cheese   -Condensed MilkMeat: Beef (chilled and frozen)Mutton (chilled and frozen) Bacon and Hams ;      Poultry, Game&quot;, and Rabbits Other MeatFish      -        -        ...TeaCoffee CocoaOilseeds, &amp;c. I    -Oilseed Cake and MealStocks in the United Kingdom in Cold Stores aad &quot;in Importers&apos;Warehouses.15,900	22,700	13,7001,900	2,200	6,80024,100	19,300 20,700	27,10025,500		15,700 110,40029,800	22,100	23,700	28,100	26,10025,100	34,500	18,30093,900	108,200	29,4009,900	13,700	4,80030,400	29,600	21,00026,800	26,800	24,800Stocks in the United Kingdom, remaining in Bonded Warehouses, or entered to be Warehoused.44,700 39,900 ,     15,700	42,500 40,900 17,800		20,900 67,200 60,200Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports and in the hands of Millers, Crushers, and Cake Manufacturers.			226,200 73,600		234,800 51,800	.   351,100 129,700* The figures for wheat and flour include stocks in port granaries and warehouses, inland-warehouses, mills, aftd bakers&apos; shops, as well as estimated stocks on the farms ; ,those for barley,&apos; oats, beans, and peas include stocks in port granaries and warehouses and in mills, in maltsters&apos; hands, and estimated farm stocks. In regard to all other articles, home produce is, with very small exceptions, excluded, !t In manufacturers&apos; hands only. ;5 The figures for 1st September, 1918 and 1917, are inclusive of the new home crops, estimated to bo available for consumption, after deduction for seed, &amp;c.  These figures for 1918 are as follows :-Tons.Wheat   -        -        -        .        .        -  1,740,000 Barley   *       -       -       -       -       -  1,240,000.  &apos; - Oats      -        -        -        -        -        -  3.700,000Beans ... - - . 112,000 Peas.......: 56,000Number of Live Stock in Great Britain.		September 4th, 1918 (Estimated).J		June 4th	,1918.	June 4th, 1917.	June 5th, 1916.i Dairy- Cattle -Total Cattle i-Ewes kept for breeding Total Sheep i -Sows kept for breeding Total Pigs   i -		3,100,000 7,470,000 9,100,000 21,000,000 315,000 2,150,000		3,030,000 7,408,000 9,498,000 23,338,000 306,000 1,825,000		2,907.000 j 7,437,000 i 9,899,000 24,043,000 269,000 &apos; 2,051,000	2,870.000 7,442,000 10,066,000 25,007,000 301,000 2,314,000J. Estimates prepared by the Live Stock Committee of the Board of Agriculture,
26213Table G-. Percentage Increase in Retail Food Prices in the United Kingdom, at each of the Undermentioned Dates, as compared with&quot;Normal Prices in July .1914.&quot;[Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.]Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.Article.	1st Jan. 1915.	1st Jan. 1910.	1st Jan. 1917.	1st July 1917.	1st Sept. 1917.	1st Jan. 1918.	1st July 1918.	1st Aug. 1918.	1st Sept 1918.Beef:-									British Ribs	7-0!	35-3	64-2	96&apos;1	97-4	80-5	84-8	83-8	83-8Thin flank	11-2	45-2	83-5	132-2	130-9	100-9	98-2	98-1	98-2Chilled or frozen 									Ribs  -	16-3	46-7	85-4	119-6	122-1	116-4	147-9	147-9	147-9Thin flank -	26-7	63-1	101-2	156-5	157-9	137-3	164-7	164-7	164-7Mutton : 									British Legs	5-8	27-9	58-7	100-0	97-7	76-8	85-5	84-5	84-5Breast	11-7	413	84-2	142-2	138-2	92-5	80-8	77-7	77-5Frozen Legs	16-3	41-8	86-4	134-4	136-0	134-0	176-5	176-5	176-5Breast	24-8	62-7	122-0	190-8	190-9	161-8	168-5	168-5	168-5Bacon, streaky *	7-1	30-7	56-3	76-4	96-0	138-7	138-3	139-6	141-4&apos;Fish       -      -      -	40-9	96-7	131-1	127-1	136-1	195-9	189-7	188-7	-189-4Flour &apos;    -	20-3	49-0	88-5	109-3	109-2	51-8	52-1	52-1	52-0Bread	15-8	41-7	73-3	100-3	99-6	54-&apos;4	54-5	54-5	&apos;54-6Tea -      -      -      -	13-6	48-2;	50-9	73-7	78-9	98-2	73-3	73-3	73-3Sugar, granulated	67-0	93-3	170-0	187-7	190-0	189-3	240-3	241-2	241-0Milk       -      -      -j	6-7	28-8	56-6	59-7	61-0	99-5	77-3	88-0	95-2Potatoes  -	p6-l	U-8	121-7	144-3	38-9	37-1	57-1	113-6	66-4Margarine	4-4	6-9	25-0	73-5	66-0	65-9	68-8	97-0	97-0Butter, fresh	13-8	33-9	72-9	64-7	90-8&apos;	103-4	97-3	95-3	93-7Butter, salt	12&quot; I	31-5	70-6	65-3	90-1	105-4	102-4	99-2	98-5Cheese, Canadian or	10-0	31-7	74-8	108-0	94-7	91-3	93-6	125-5	129-2U.S.*									Eggs, fresh      -   . -	6S-4	104-9	175-0	95-3	142-4	.242-1	248-3	295-0	293-7* If this kind is seldom dealt with in a locality the Returns quote prices for another kind locally representative, t Decrease.1 iTable H. Retail Prices of Subsidiary Foods in April, 1917, and Subsequent Months compared with the Prices in July, 1914, in London andother large Towns. !.   [Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.] !   .    -;Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.Article.	April 1st,	July 1st,	Sept. 1st,	Jan. 1st,	April 1st,	June 1st,	July 1st,	Aug. 1st,	Sept. 1st,	1917.	1917.	1917.	1918.	1918.	1918.	1918.	1918.	1918.			7						Butter beans   -      -	160	140	110	113	113	113	113	113	113Haricot beans (white)	230	180	.140	140	140	140	140	140	140Peas, split (yellow) -	140	210	i   210	220	220	220	220	220	220Lentils, split (red)   -Oatmeal, Scotch	210	230	;     220	232	232	232	232	232	232	140	150$	150+	100	113	113	120	120	120Rice, Rangoon	90	100	100	103	117	117	117 .	117	117Sago	140 1	180	180	200	227,	245	251	264	282Tapioca -	120	160	150	170	185	205	210	223	238Condensed milk	65	110	110	139	143	152	152	152	152Lard, British  -	125	120	120	125	 	 	.:  	 	-TAmerican	130	110	120	139	164	166	168	186	186J-125 in Scotland,
Table J. Consumption and Sale-of Flour by Bakers and Retailers.   Comparison of Four-weekly Periods in 1917-18.(All measured as percentages of quantities used in May 1917.)Four Weeks endedFood Control Divisions.-																	Sept. 14, 1918.	August 17, 1918!	July 20, 1918.	June 22, 1918.	May 25, 1918.	April 27. 1918.	March 30. 1918.	March 2. 3918. &apos;	Feb. 2, 1918.	Jan. 5, 1918.	Dec. S, 1917.	Nov. 10. 1917.	Oct. 13, 1917. -	Sept. 15, 1917.	Aug. 18, 1917.	July 21, 1917.Neweastle           -       - &quot;     -Leeds -       -       -Manchester -Nottingham -                -Birmingham Cambridge  -       -       -London       -       -       -       -Home Counties, North -Home Counties, Sonth -Reading      -.       -      &apos;- . Bristol        -       -Carnarvon Cardiff -	101 96* 100* 104 100* 114 91 106* 110 116 103 120* 97	96* 93 97* 96 95 108 87* 103* 107 112* 99 117 92	93* -87* 94* 98 96 110 91 100 107 110 101 112 89*	95 91 97 100* 98* 108 95* ioo* 105 109* 103 108* 93*	94* 95* 95L 100* 97^ . 108 98 100* 103* 109* 102 102 921	99* 96 98 104* 99* 108 99 101 106 111* 104 104* 92*	103* 951 97* 103 101 109 981 102&quot; 104 110 101 1031 94*	99 96 99* 107^ 100 111* 1001 100&quot; 103* 110 102 99 95	1041 98* 98* 105 99* 111* 101 991 102* 106* 1011 99* 97	1001 92&quot; 93 100 93 108* 97 97 99 103 97 96 93*	110 100 961 104&quot; 96 111 101* 97h 1001 1041 101&quot; 981 97&quot;	1091 1031 971 104 96 1111 98* 971 iooS 1041 iooi 100* 98&quot;	.   96 96 96 98 931 108&quot; 931 95&quot; 981 102* 99 100 97	81 82 89 89 891 1001 87&quot; 91 97 981 92 96 90*	83 80 89 -    88 88 100 84 94 96 99 ^92 99 91*	821 82* 91 91 931 102&quot; 901 94&quot; 95 99 94 95 93*England and Wales	102	98	97	99	99	101	100*	101	101	96*	100*	1001	97	881	88	91Glasgow Edinburgh  -       -       -       -	95 97*	90 95	85 98	91* 98^	92 97*	95 100	96 99*	97 1021	98 104	92   . 101	95* 102*	.    96* 104	95 103	91 99	88 96 -   --	86 &quot;  99Scotland*     -      ..-  .   -	99	95	91	95	95	97*	98	100	101	96	98*	99*	98*	94	91	91Ireland -       -       -       -	101*	99	94*	95*	94	94*	96*	94	961	93*	98	97	96*	92*	92	93*United Kingdom   -       -	102	98	96	98	98	100	100	100J	100*	96	100	100	97	90*	89*	91*England and Wales : Boroughs,    other    than London, with popula-tion over 50,000. Smaller towns and rural districts.	97* 109	93  105	92 103	94* 104	95 102*	97* 104*	98 103*	98* 104	99 103*	93* 99	99 1011	1001 101*	95* 98*	86* 92	85 Q9i-	88 93** Including Inverness Division for which the returns are too few to allow a separate statement.

</content>
</cab>
