<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/65/0 images: 363-366</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SIC ?\ &apos;Z T.        ( This Document is the Property cfHis britannlc &quot;Majesty&apos;s government.)N.S.R. 40.The Application of the Military Service Acts ^0 jreland.Memorandum by tho Minister of National Service.In conjunction with the Irish Government and the ,:.far Office I have been considering the steps which if will be necessary to take in the event of its being decided to apply the Military Service Acts to Ireland by an Order in Council under Section 2 of the Military Service Act 1918.     A conference on the subject at which Lord Fronchjand :vir. Shortt were present was held at the &quot;.&apos;ar Office on the life instant, when it was thought best that the administration of compulsion; if adopted; should be carried out by the Ministry of National Service with the assistance where necessary of the military authorities:and the main outlines of executive procedure on this basis were settled.     In pursuance of the decisions of the conference a draft Order in Council has been prepared by Parliamentary CounseT&quot;ahdis attached (Appendix I)., , IT&quot;tW^0rder&apos;in Council is to be laid before Parliament when it       ,v meets on the 15th instant a number of preliminary arrangements-such, for instance, as the selection of suitable persons to serve on Tribunals and the constitution of special courts for the decision of questions of liability under the Military Service Acts-, must be taken in hand forthwith.It is therefore of the utmost importance that an immediate, decision should be arrived, at by the War Cabinet as to the policy which it is intended to pursue.     The present uncertainty, if allow-ed to continue, will undoubtedly give rise to serious difficulties whatever be the course that Is ultimately followed, and it is most necessary that the Departments concerned should be apprised of the V/ar Cabinet&apos;s Intentions without delay.I think it right to attach a memorandum (Appendix 2) by Mr. Stephen Gwynn- a member of the Irish Recruiting Council- contain-ing proposals for a gradual or partial application of compulsion to Ireland.     These proposals wero not before the conference re-ferred to above and if adopted would necessitate some modification    *$ of the procedure then suggested.It is most desirable that the decision, of the Government: should be reached by next Wednesday at latest as it will be necessary to summon a meeting of the London Irish Recruiting Council at the end of this week,A. C. GEDDLS.7.10.13. f
APPENDIX   I. provisional Sough ---,---AT THE COURT AT BUCKINGHAM PALACE27tThe day of October, 1918..&apos;PRESENT,THE KIHG!S ;;OST EXCELLENT mAJESTY IN COUNCIL,EREaS by the i ilitary Service (No.2) Act, 1918, (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the said Act&quot;), it is provided that H^s Llajesty may b?/ Order in Council extend the said Act to Ireland and that the said Act if so extended shall, subject to such modifications and adapta-tions as may be made b;; the Order for the purpose of making it applic-able to Ireland have effect accordingly:AND WHEREAS it is further provided by the said section that an Order in Council under the said section may, as respects the civil court before which proceedings in respect of any offence pimish-able on summary conviction under the Reserve Forces r.cts, 16!32 to 1907, the Army Act, the iilitary Service Acts, 1916 to 1918, or the said r-mt, or any orders or regulations made thereunder, arc lo be brought in Ireland -(a) make special provision *\ith respect to the constitution of the court;   and(b) assign any such proceedings to such civil court or courts as may be specified in tho Order;iiND &apos; :LREiiS it Is expedient that the said ^ct snould extend to Ireland.NOW, THEREFORE, His I ajesty is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, in pursuance of tho said Act and of all othor powers enabling him&apos;in that behalf, to order, and it is hereby ordered as follows:-1.     The i ilitary Service (No.2)Act, 1918, shall as from   the date of this Order extend to Ireland, and shall subject to the modifications and adaptations made by this Order and to the othor provisions of this Order have effect accordingly.2.     The power to make regulations under section four of the said Act shall as respects Ireland be exercised by the Lord Licutcn-ant.3.(1)Tho civil court for the trial of any such offence punishable on summary conviction as is mentioned in section two oi tho.said Act shall be constituted, according as the Lord Lieutenant may from time to time either generally or in any special case direct, either of a resident magistrate sitting alone or of such persons being justices of the peace as the Lord Lieutenant may by order appoint to hold tho c ourt;provided thit In the application of tho foregoing provision to the police district of Dublin metropolis and to boroughs for which m police magistrates are appointed, a divisional justice of that dis-* trict and a police magistrate appointed for the borough, shall respectively be substituted for a resident magistrate,,..(2)The proceedings in respect of any such offence as aforesaid may be hoard and determined before a civil court constituted in manner provided by this order sitting in any place in Ireland, whether or not the dofondant is resident or the offence was committed at a place v&quot;ithin the ordinary jurisdiction of the court.
277&apos; -2-f4.     Subsection (3) of section one of the said Act shall have )ffsct as though the following provision were inserted at the end thereof: -&quot;Provided that in the event of this *ot being extended to Ireland the following provisions shall have effect:(a) Tho said Acts and this Act shall have effect as if !the United Kingdom&quot; were therein substituted for ;&apos;Great Britain&apos;1 wherever that expression occurs:(b) Paragraph 6 of the Second Schedule to the Military Service Act, 1916, shall have effect as though the words &apos;&apos;0r as respects Ireland the^Lord Lieutenant&apos;&apos; were therein inserted after the words &quot;Secretary for Scot-land&quot; ,(c) Any provision in the said Acts or this Act empowering a court to require any person to give evidence shall have effect In Ireland notwithstanding any rule of law according to which in proceedings against any person for any offence the person charged with the offence is not a competent or a compeliable witness.(d) The powers given to Government Departments by subsections (2) and (5) of section two of the Military Service Act, 1916, shall not be exercised a; regard-&apos; any man to whom the . aid Act applies by virtue of this Order except with the con.ent of ths-Bir30tor-General of National Service.&quot;5,     Section thro-- of ths ^aid Act . hall have effect a., though ih-i following provi. ion wore inserted at the end thursof-(3)   In the event of thi. Act b-ing extended to Ireland, any proclamation mad- under thi.. action before the dat   on which thiS Act i? so wXt.;ndod --hall have effect go as to prohibit any application b^ing entertained in Ireland for the grant or renewal of a certificate, of -exemption if by virtue of the preceding provision.&quot;: of thi.. section tho application i^ of .*uch a kind as could not be entertained in Great Britain.Provided that for thi purpose of any provision in any . uch proclamation which enables applications to bu made in any -pecial ca..OL , L,uch dato      may be provided by rogula-tion- mad.-j &quot;under this Act shall be substituted for the date specified in the proclamation.&quot;6.     Subsection (6) of section four of the said Act shall.not apply as regards men to whom the caia Act applies by virtue of this Order.7.     Notwithstanding anything in thi;. Orcur, reference., in t.ub-^ection (1) of section one of the said Act.to the patting of the said jot shall in relation to Ireland be construed as references tc the Pghteenth day of April, nineteen hundred and eighteen, and. not as reference:, to the date of this Order,
If278API ENDIX II,A. The Government should announce when Parliament opens that the opportunity given to each Area to clear itself cf conscription by filling its quota will be extended to the date vhen the Order in Council becomes practically operative, which should be not earlier than November 1st.B. In my opinion Government should announce that conscription /ould be applied to secure in each Area a fixed multiple of the deficiency from the quota.   If for instance the quota vas 5,000, &amp; 2,000 men had been found, the levy should be for say treble the deficiency, i.e., 9,000.   This should be a principle operating throughout, &apos;C. I consider that the disadvantages of raising men in Ireland by conscription are so great as to outweigh the advantages given by conscription in power of selection.   Therefore, I advocate a course which might maintain voluntary recruitment In substance.   If Gcvern-ment proceeded by applying conscription in say two Areas selecting Areas which admittedly were gravely in default, they could still leave voluntary recruiting in progress in the other .^reas making it plain that the extent to which conscription .;as applied in each would depend exactly upon the amount of the deficiency remaining  . ;hen it came to be applied; *t is cuite possible that in face of a resolute attitude, several Areas if not all might decide to deal with the matter on a voluntary basis.   The same machinery would remain permanently in force and could be applied from time to time if necessary to complete the monthly drafts, a quota cf wh&apos;ch for voluntary recruitment,should be assigned to each Area, corscripticn applying in the same way for treble of each monthly deficiency,It is at least possible that a general change cf front mi -ht be effected by .this method *   the same privileges /hich no.: exist being extended to all voluntary recruits.(Signed) STEPHEN GVJYNN.

</content>
</cab>
