<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/32/0 images: 32-38</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1958CC. (58)      . Copy No.3rd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Sunday, 5th January, 1958, at 6-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General.Also present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.
SubjectGovernment Expenditure
government expenditure(previous reference:C.C. (58) 2ndConclusions)* The Cabinet resumed their discussion of the level ofGovernment expenditure in 1958-59.The Prime Minister said that the Cabinet must now seek to formulate a collective view on the two main aspects of the problem which confronted them first, the extent to which they should seek toimpose on the Governments own expenditure a discipline no lessrigorous than that to which public investment and the private sector-had been subjected ; second, the methods by which the necessaryeconomies would best be achieved.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, as regards the first ofthese questions, he remained convinced that the cardinal objective ofthe Government must be to maintain the strength of sterling both athome and abroad. If the Government failed to realise this objective,they would fail in every other aspect of their policy. The measuresto this end which they had adopted in the autumn of 1957 had beenunpopular and had been imposed only with great difficulty. Even so,they had proved barely sufficient to sustain sterling. Moreover, inview of the growth of international illiquidity and the acceleration inthe rate at which the holders of sterling balances were drawing them down, sterling would face renewed pressure in 1958. It would beimpossible for the Government to withstand this pressure unless theycould convince public opinion, both at home and abroad, that theywere adhering unreservedly to their disinflationary policy and were determined to subject their own expenditure to the same measures ofcontrol as those which they had imposed on the rest of the economy.It was, therefore, essential for the Cabinet to decide whether they wereprepared to take a firm decision substantially to eliminate the 153 millions which represented the probable excess of government expenditure in 1958-59 over the level of 1957-58.In discussion there was unanimous agreement on the importanceof curtailing Government expenditure by all possible means. But itwas emphasised that the Government would be unwise to appear to reject the policy of an expanding economy by insisting that in no circumstances should the level of Government expenditure rise. nor was there a unique significance in reducing Government expenditurein 1958-59 to precisely the same level as in 1957-58. In view of theextent to which this expenditure was determined by factors outside thecontrol of the Government-e.g., the increase in the numbers ofschoolchildren and old people a moderate increase in its level couldbe convincingly defended to public opinion; and the additionalpurchasing power which it would generate would be less damaging tothe economy than the renewal of inflated wage claims which wouldcertainly be provoked by reductions. in the welfare services. even further reductions in capital investment would be preferable toimposing on Government expenditure so arbitrary a limit as to jeopardise the wage stability which must remain the Governmentsmain objective.The discussion then turned to the individual measures which itwas proposed to introduce.The Minister of Labour said that, after discussion with theMinister of Pensions and National Insurance and the Minister ofHealth, he remained of the opinion that it would be unwise to abolish the family allowance for the second child and that the imposition ofan increased charge for school milk would encounter serious opposition from the school teachers. The introduction of a hospitalboarding charge would involve the employment of 1,000 additionalclerical staff, whom it would be difficult to recruit at a time when theGovernment had recently refused an increase of pay to the grades*Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.52960-5b 2
concerned. Nor would the hospital authorities themselves be willingto face the administrative difficulties of introducing a charge of thiskind in a period when they were being denied an expansion of thefacilities which they regarded as essential. The abolition of the supplementary ophthalmic service would be no more palatable. TheGovernment had given repeated pledges that this service would bemaintained ; and its suspension would in any case yield additionalincome of little more than  44 millions a year. An increase in thecharge for welfare milk to 6d. a pint might perhaps deserve furtherconsideration ; but it would be condemned by public opinion as ameasure directed against the family and would be liable to provoke a critical reaction from organised labour. If all these measures were rejected, there remained only the possibility of increasing that element in the National Insurance contribution which was attributable to theNational Health Service. It would be unfortunate to announce anincrease of this nature at the time when the civil Estimates were published, since it would then coincide with the date on which thelatest increase in the National Insurance contribution would comeinto effect. It would be preferable that it should be deferred forannouncement in the Budget speech, where it could be presented inits proper context, even although its implementation would be correspondingly delayed.In discussion it was suggested that the Chancellor of theExchequer had, if anything, understated the gravity of the threat to sterling, which was liable to increase in intensity in the months ahead.In order to overcome this threat the Government must pursue athreefold policy. They should seek to reduce government expenditure, to ensure wage stability and to maintain their ownpolitical position. An increase in Government expenditure of theorder of  150 millions would be very damaging to the prospects of sterling. On the other hand the abolition of the family allowance forthe second child would be no less damaging to the prospect ofmaintaining wage stability. Of the other measures envisaged which affected the welfare services only the increase in the National health service contribution appeared to be practicable, particularly if it was presented as a means of imposing an upper limit on the exchequer contribution to the National Health Service. If, at the same time, theemerging deficit of some  14 millions on the National Insurance fund was written off by realisation of part of the fund&apos;s invested balances,the charge for welfare milk was raised by 2d. a pint and further economies were secured on Service Votes, Government expenditurein 1958-59 might be reduced to a level which would be politicallyacceptable and publicly defensible. But it would be unwise to seek tosecure further economies in the welfare services at the cost ofprovoking industrial unrest which foreign opinion would regard asbeing at least as damaging to the potential recovery of sterling as amarginal increase in Government expenditure. Nor was it reasonablethat, for the sake of a relatively trivial sum, sterling should be exposed to the fresh pressure which would follow the fall of the government or the resignation of the Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Minister of Defence said that, in consultation with theService Ministers, he had made a fresh attempt to secure the further savings, amounting to  7 millions, for which the Chancellor of theExchequer had asked. It was clear, however, that an economy ofthis magnitude could not be achieved within the Service Estimatesotherwise than by some modification of the new scheme of service pay and allowances. Any form of postponement of this scheme would be dangerous. In the absence of a sufficient improvement inthe statistics of recruitment the Government would have no alternative to introducing legislation, towards the end of the present Parliament,to enable some form of compulsory National Service to continue. Theonly hope of avoiding this was to introduce the new scheme of pay and allowances at the earliest possible date.  The Service Ministers
had reluctantly accepted one deferment of the scheme in the autumn of the previous year ; they could not accept any further postponement.In discussion it was suggested that it would nevertheless be reasonable and consistent with the Governments wages policy thatthe new scheme should be announced when the Defence White paper was published but that its implementation should be postponed for ashort period. Alternatively, the improvements in pay might beintroduced forthwith, the improvements in allowances being deferred until, say, 1st October. Either course, combined with the economies in the welfare services which might prove, on further examination, tobe practicable, would reduce the increase in Government expenditure to the defensible figure of about  40 millions. On the other hand, itwas the announcement of the new scheme which would be liable toreact adversely on the pending wage claims ; the deferment of itsimplementation would be relatively unimportant from this point ofview, while it would impose a fatal check on the new campaign of recruitment.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he conceived it to be his duty not to accept Departmental Estimates foreshadowing anincrease of Government expenditure in 1958-59 over the level of1957-58. The course of the discussion had shown that the cabinet were not agreed, as he had hoped, on the importance of eliminatingthis increase. Reductions in the welfare services could, admittedly,be defended only if the Government were wholly determined to pressthrough their disinflationary policy. But, given that determination,a combination of possible measures could be devised. As regardsdefence expenditure he agreed that it would be impossible to announce the new scheme of pay and allowances but to defer itsimplementation. It would be reasonable, however, to introduce onlythe improved allowances, deferring any improvement in pay until after the Grigg Committee had reported. On these hypotheses, the cut of  76 millions which had already been secured would beincreased by savings of  30 millions on the welfare services and afurther reduction of some  22 millions on Service Votes. The totalof nearly  130 millions would represent an approximation to hispurpose of eliminating the whole of the  153 millions increase in expenditure ; but he would still require the support of the Cabinet insearching, over the whole range of the remaining civil Estimates, forfurther economies in an effort to approach still more closely to this objective.At this point The Prime Minister adjourned the meeting in orderto enable Ministers to give further consideration to the issues involved.When the discussion was resumed, The Prime Minister said thatthe Cabinet must seek to share with the Chancellor of the exchequer the heavy burden of managing an economy which, though potentiallyprosperous, was precariously balanced. The demands upon thateconomy, both as the source of livelihood for the citizens of the UnitedKingdom and as the centre of a major international system of tradeand finance, were unparalleled ; and the Chancellor was entitled toask his colleagues to give convincing evidence of their determination to support him in giving effect to the disinflationary policy which alone would enable the Government to discharge their manifoldresponsibilities. But disinflation, if enforced to the point at which itcreated a stagnant economy or provoked a new outbreak of industrial unrest, would defeat its own ends ; and, if the individual measures proposed by the Chancellor had been criticised, this criticism was evidence of the concern of other members of the Cabinet that a gain in respect of one aspect of the Governments policies should not be offset by a loss in respect of others.
The Cabinet could, and should, pledge themselves to achieve as nearly as possible the Chancellors objective of ensuring by all possible means that Government expenditure in 1958-59 should not substantially exceed its level in 1957-58. But it was doubtful whetherthe Government could hope to achieve a precise arithmeticalequilibrium without injury to their other purposes. It was alsoarguable whether, if some relatively small increase in expenditurepersisted, sterling would be seriously weakened. But the cabinet should spare no effort to eliminate the  153 millions as far as possible,being resolved to give the maximum of support to the chancellor and believing that it should be- practicable substantially to achieve hisobjective by legitimate means without provoking industrial unrest.As regards the individual measures to this end, it was unreasonable that Ministers should be expected, at very short notice,to give a firm undertaking to enforce economies of  30 millions in the welfare services together with further unspecified economies on theother civil Votes. To abolish the family allowance for the secondchild was neither politically nor socially desirable. It would be contrary to the tradition of the Conservative Party ; it would representto three million households a reduction of 5 per cent, in their weeklyincome; and it would give, to those elements of public opinion whichwere seeking a legitimate occasion for the formulation of fresh wagedemands, a genuine and concrete issue on which to base their claims.The imposition of a hospital boarding charge and the abolition of the supplementary ophthalmic service were open to serious objection. Anincrease in the charge for welfare milk would also be unpalatable,although it should be regarded as a possible contribution to thenecessary economies if no better alternative could be found. Anincrease in the National Health Service element of the national insurance contribution could hardly be made at the moment whenthe latest increase in that contribution took effect, although it could perhaps be adopted in the context of the Budget when it might bepossible and desirable to discuss in greater detail the Governmentsfuture policy towards the social services as a whole. For these reasons it was impossible for the Cabinet to undertake to enforce savings of 30 millions in the welfare services. But they could certainly resolveto increase the total of savings from  76 millions to at least 100 millions and possibly more, provided that the whole range ofcivil Estimates was regarded as available for this purpose and that ministers were given a little more time in which to consider how thefurther economies could be effected with least damage.The defence Estimates had already been severely cut, and it was doubtful whether they could properly and safely be expected to sufferany further reductions. Of the opportunities which lay before theGovernment the termination of National Service was not the leastvaluable, in terms both of political advantage and of the genuine relief to the economy which a system of voluntary recruitment should yield.Nevertheless, if it proved possible, by further scrutiny of the civil estimates, to reduce the level of Government expenditure in 1958-59by  100 millions or rather more, it would be reasonable to require theMinister of Defence to re-examine the Service Estimates yet once again, with a view to securing further savings of some  7 millionswhether by adjustments in the new scheme of Service pay and allowances or by some other means.In short, the Chancellor of the Exchequer could feel assured ofthe wholehearted determination of his colleagues to support him in hisdisinflationary policy. If it proved possible to reduce government expenditure by  100 millions and perhaps more, the residue of theincrease would represent a rise of no more than 1 per cent, in theoutlay of the Exchequer. An increase of this order, largelyattributable to factors over which the Government had no control,could not fairly be represented as indicating any weakening in theGovernments resolve to resist inflation and to support sterling by allpossible means.  At the same time the economies which would have
Cabinet Office, S.W.1,9th January, 1958.been adopted would be the least likely to provoke industrialdiscontent or to imperil the wage stability which must remain the primary objective of the Governments economic policies as a whole.The Government would be condemned, both by their own supporters and by world opinion, if, as the result not of someuntoward disaster but of their own failure to agree on the approach which he had suggested to resolve a minimal difference of opinion,they faltered in their course and failed to carry through the greatenterprise on which they had embarked only a year before. ministers should therefore weigh the issues, as he had summarised them, with afull sense of their collective responsibility. In doing so, they should bear it in mind that it was only the balance of the methods to beemployed which was in question and that, on the fundamental policy involved, the Cabinet were pledged to give the Chancellor of theExchequer their unreserved support.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had never waveredin his view that Government expenditure in 1958-59 should not substantially exceed the level in 1957-58 and that, although he waswell aware of the difficulties entailed by some of the measures to thisend which he had proposed, he must now consider his own positionin the light of the Prime Ministers summary of the issues at stake.

</content>
</cab>
