<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/32/0 images: 54-57</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1958C.C. (58)6th conclusions copy No.  5CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 14th January, 1958, at 3-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P., Secretary of State for the Home department and Lord Privy Seal (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Ialn Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Education.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and civil Aviation.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Pensions and national Insurance.The Right Hon. Derek Walker-Smith,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. H. O. Hooper.
SubjectGovernment Expenditure.
government expenditure.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 5thConclusions,Minute 10.)*The Cabinet resumed their discussion of the level ofGovernment expenditure in 1958-59. The following points weremade:  (a) The figure of  50 millions, representing approximately 1 percent, of Government expenditure, had by now become established in the mind of the general public as the maximum amount by whichthe Government were prepared to allow Government expenditure in1958-59 to exceed its level in the current financial year. If themeasure of economy implicit in this figure was not achieved, theGovernment would appear to be weakening in their resolve to combatinflation. The forthcoming Estimates must be seen, on publication,to be consistent with the objective which the Government were regarded as having established for themselves.(b) It had hitherto been accepted that the purpose of the reservesstanding to the credit of the National Insurance Fund was to providefor widespread and sustained unemployment and that a deficit onthe income of the Fund would be made good by the Exchequer.Nevertheless, the expediency of retaining reserves solely against the contingency of general unemployment was open to question, and inview of the estimated increase of  9 millions in the prospective deficit on the Fund in 1958-59, it would be legitimate to charge to reservesthe total deficit of  23 millions in that year. While such a decisions would be vulnerable to criticism by informed opinion, there wasadequate statutory authority for it. If this course was adopted,however, it would be necessary for the Government to indicate, atthe same time, the action which they proposed to take in order to restore the balance of the Fund on current account. Moreover,since this step would not represent a straightforward economy in expenditure, it would also be necessary to find further genuine savings which would reduce the rise in estimated expenditure in 1958-59 toa figure rather less than  50 millions.(c) The arguments for and against increasing the element in theNational Insurance contribution which was attributable to theNational Health Service were evenly balanced. On the one handsuch an increase, the third in the course of a year, would beill-received by public opinion and would expose the Government toa charge of indecision. The increase could not be imposed withoutfurther controversial legislation and the National insurance contribution was already near the maximum which the lower paid workers could be expected to bear. Moreover, it was doubtfulwhether the Government would be credited with achieving an economy in public expenditure merely by increasing a compulsorycontribution which was, in effect, a regressive poll-tax. Nevertheless,an increase in the National Health Service contribution appeared,in the circumstances, to be the least objectionable method of effectinga further reduction in Estimates. An increase of Ad. in this contribution, yielding  12 millions in 1958-59, could be justified onthe ground that it would cover the estimated increase in the costof the National Health Service itself. If the increase was limited tothis figure, however, the necessary legislation would bedisproportionately controversial in relation to the yield to beexpected; and it was for consideration whether, if this method of effecting economies was adopted, the increase should be larger. Onthe other hand, while an increase of Sd. could be imposed withoutinfringing the principle that not more than 20 per cent, of the costof the National Health Service should be met from contributions and charges, it could be criticised as achieving an undue proportion of thetotal economies needed at the expense of that particular Service.(d) A very substantial increase in revenue, varying from 20 millions to  50 millions according to the basis adopted, couldbe obtained by withdrawing the right to claim National Insurance* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.
contributions as a deduction in calculating income tax liability. Anincrease in revenue, however, could not be regarded as equivalentto a reduction in expenditure. Moreover, this proposal might have serious repercussions on the treatment for income tax purposes ofcontributions to, and benefits under, private pension schemes.(e) Despite the examination to which Departmental Estimateshad already been subjected, a further detailed scrutiny might yieldadditional economies which could legitimately be secured by a revision of the assumptions on which the original provision had been based without involving serious encroachment on the social services.It would also be desirable to reconsider the scope of the forthcomingSupplementary Estimates in order to ensure that they made adequate provision for all expenditure which could properly be regarded asfalling to be discharged in the current financial year.(/) The Minister of Defence reaffirmed his view that it would bevery unwise to defer, even until 1st June, the implementation of thenew scheme of pay and allowances for the Armed Forces which he proposed to announce simultaneously with the publication of theDefence White Paper. It would be necessary to assess not later thanthe end of 1958 the possibility of bringing National Service to anend by the date which the Cabinet had in mind, and a delay of eventwo months in the introduction of the improved scales of pay and allowances might discourage voluntary recruitment to an extent which would make it impossible for this assessment to be made on a realistic basis.The Home Secretary, summing up the discussion, said that thepossibility of securing further economies in defence expenditure of theorder of  7 millions should continue to be explored; and ministers in charge of civil Departments should re-examine their Estimates,as a matter of urgency, in an attempt to secure additional savings.It would then be necessary for the Cabinet to consider, at their next meeting, the amount by which Government expenditure would stillneed to be reduced if the rise in the 1958-59 Estimates was to be politically defensible, and the methods, including an increase in theNational Health Service contribution, by which this reduction would best be achieved.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to continue his consultations with Departmental Ministers in the light ofthe points made in their discussion.(2) Agreed to resume their discussion at a meeting on20th January.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,15th January, 1958,

</content>
</cab>
