<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/32/0 images: 160-165</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;^ GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1958C.C. (58)24th conclusions copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 18th March, 1958, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Education.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General.The following were also present:The Right Hon. The Earl of Selkirk,First Lord of the Admiralty (Item 2).The Right Hon. D. Ormsby-Gore, M.P.,Minister of State for Foreign Affairs(Item 2).The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. M. Reed.Mr. P. R. Odgers.
contents minute no. subject Farm Price Review     ......2 Territorial Waters       ......3 Foreign Affairs.........4 Meeting of Heads of Governments5 Wages policy Malta.........
Farm price review.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 22ndConclusions.)territorial waters.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 21stConclusions,Minute 3.)2. The Cabinet had before them Geneva telegram No. 89 of17th March in which the Attorney-General proposed that, in thediscussions in Committee One of the International Conference on theLaw of the Sea, the United Kingdom delegation should not oppose the United States proposal for the maintenance of the presentthree-mile limit for territorial waters and the extension of exclusive fishing rights to twelve miles; and that our own proposal for anextension of territorial waters to six miles, with adequate safeguards for rights of passage for warships and aircraft, should be held in reserve and only advanced as a last resort.Tn discussion there was general agreement that it would be undesirable to appear to acquiesce in the United States proposal in committee if we should subsequently need to oppose it in plenary session. This course would also be liable to weaken our case in any action in which we might become involved before the international court of Justice; and it would cause unnecessary alarm among ourown fishing industry. Without actively promoting opposition to theUnited States proposal, therefore, we should make it clear to theUnited States delegation forthwith that we could not support it. our delegation should continue to press for the maintenance of the presentthree-mile limit for all purposes.   But a six-mile limit for all purposes.1. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the national farmers&apos; Unions (N.F.U&apos;s) had indicated that they saw no purpose in prolonging discussion of the Governments proposal to reduce by 19 millions the guaranteed prices of agricultural products. Theprice determination on this basis would, therefore, need to be broughtinto effect as an imposed settlement.The Minister of Agriculture said that he proposed, however, inagreement with the Secretary of State for Scotland, to accept aproposal put forward unofficially by the N.F.U&apos;s that, without additional cost to the Exchequer, a small increase should be made inthe premium for quality bacon, which would benefit the specialistbacon producers.In discussion on the presentation of the Governments decision,there was general agreement that the following points should be emphasised:  (a) The Government had refrained from enforcing the maximumreduction permissible under the Agriculture Act, 1957.(b) The reduction of  19 millions was relatively insignificant inrelation to the total annual value of the price guarantees.(c) The money income of the farmers was increasing and theindustry could not, in any case, reasonably expect to be completelyinsulated against changes in the world prices of agricultural products.(d) The Act did not require the Government to reach agreementwith the industry in making their determination.In further discussion on the draft White Paper on the annual review, it was suggested that the reference, in paragraph 9, to areduction of gross output should be clarified. The government&apos;s policy had for some time been to secure, over the whole range ofagricultural products, a reduction in gross output but an increase innet output. The Minister of Agriculture undertook to reconsider the drafting of paragraph 9 or, if it was now too late to amend the text, to emphasise this point in his announcement of the government&apos;s decision.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Agriculture, in announcing theGovernments decision to reduce the total value of the price guarantees under the Agriculture Act, 1957, by  19 millions,to be guided by the points made in their discussion.
with a reservation of rights of passage for warships without priorauthorisation and rights of passage for aircraft outside the three miles,would be tolerable if it became clear that the maintenance of athree-mile limit had no chance of acceptance and that the only alternative was a breakdown of the Conference which would allowcoastal States to establish whatever limits suited their own purposes.It would be necessary, therefore, to be ready to advance our proposalfor a six-mile limit at the critical point in the negotiations.The Cabinet-Invited the Foreign Secretary to inform the Attorney-General that he should:  (i) tell the United States delegation at the international conference on the Law of the Sea that we couldnot support their proposal for a three-mile limit lorterritorial waters with exclusive fishing rights up to twelve miles;(ii) advocate the maintenance of the present three-mile limit for all purposes;(iii) seek the authority of the Cabinet or the PrimeMinister if, in his view, the progress of thediscussions made it necessary to propose a six-mile limit for all purposes with a reservation of rightsof passage for warships without prior authorisationand rights of passage for aircraft outside the three miles.Foreign 3.   The Foreign Secretary reported to the Cabinet on recentAffairs. developments in foreign affairs.The Meeting of the Council of the South-East Asia treaty organisation, from which he had just returned, had been a success nndhad revealed a growing confidence in the Alliance both among themembers themselves and among certain non-member States.In the Middle East, however, the situation in Iraq gave cause fordisquiet, and tangible evidence of United Kingdom and United states support for the Iraqi Government would be desirable. In Tunisia,on the other hand, there was now some hope that a settlement,acceptable to both the French and the Tunisian Governments, mightbe achieved.Meeting of 4.   The Foreign Secretary said that he had discussed with the heads of United States Secretary of State at Manila the draft statement of theGovernments, position of the Western Powers in relation to the proposed meeting(Previous of Heads of Governments which had been prepared by the PrimeReference: Minister and endorsed by the Cabinet. Mr. Dulles had proposedC.C. (58) 23rd certain modifications in the draft, designed to emphasise that theConclusions, initial stages of the preparatory work for the proposed meeting should minute 3.)       be carried out through the ordinary diplomatic channels, preferably in Washington, and should be followed by a meeting of foreign ministers.Discussion showed that there was general agreement that thedraft statement should be amended on these lines. It was suggested,however, that it would be desirable that it should also specify a date in the near future on which the preliminary diplomatic exchangesshould begin.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary to arrange for the draft statement of the position of the Western Powers in relationto the proposed meeting of Heads of Governments to be amended, before submission to the United States Secretaryof State, so as to specify a date in the near future on whichthe preliminary diplomatic exchanges should begin.
Malta. 6.   The Colonial Secretary said that, in his recent discussions(Previous        with the Prime Minister of Malta, he had endeavoured to secure the reference:       latter&apos;s agreement to the establishment of a working party toC.C. (58) 21st   examine the remedial measures which might be taken to deal with conclusions,     unemployment within the framework of the agreement on economicMinute 1.)       and financial arrangements consequent upon the integration of Maltawith the United Kingdom.   Mr. Mintoff had rejected this proposal and had made it clear that he had reverted to his original conception of integration as implying full economic equivalence between theUnited Kingdom and Malta.   He had also proposed that, at any timeuntil full economic equivalence was achieved, the Maltese people should retain the right to reject integration and to declare their independence of the United Kingdom.   He had been reminded ofWages Policy.        5.   The Cabinet had before them a note by the Prime Minister(Previous        (C. (58) 53) to which was annexed a report by officials on wagesReference:       policy.   This report examined various possible policies as regardsC.C. (57) 83rd   wages, prices and related matters which might contribute to securingConclusions,     stability in the value of the pound sterling.    It concluded that the minute 3.)      most effective policy might take the form of a declaration by theGovernment of a rate of increase in basic wages which was likely tobe broadly consistent with price stability.   Such a declaration wouldnot have any legal sanction but would constitute a guiding light for those concerned with the settlement of wages and for the public generally.   The report suggested that this proposal, together with thepossible introduction of certain modest measures for the restraint of dividends and prices, should be discussed as soon as possible withthe employers&apos; associations and with the trades unions.In discussion it was suggested that it would be unwise to attemptto discuss any new wages policy with the employers and the unionsuntil the wage claims which were still outstanding had been settled.Moreover, there would, in any event, be certain dangers inpromulgating, even if only as a guiding light, a permissible rate of increase in wages which would be interpreted by the unions as theminimum of the new wage increases which they could claim ratherthan as the average of the increases which they could properly expect to obtain. Whatever the method by which the amount of thepermissible increase was determined, the principle of a guiding lightwould tend to incorporate inflation permanently into the economic system.On the other hand, it was desirable that we should be able, indue course, to resume a policy of economic expansion withoutprovoking a revival of wage inflation; and the Government must therefore seek to devise, in collaboration with industry, means ofsecuring a reasonable degree of wage restraint and of revising incertain respects the traditional procedures of wage negotiation and arbitration. The latter question would be relevant to the decision,which the Cabinet would need to take later in the year, on the futureof the system of compulsory arbitration. Even if the present moment was not opportune for publicly establishing the principle of a guidinglight or for introducing any of the related measures, the issues involved should be further studied in order that the Government might be able,if necessary, to take some fresh initiative as regards wages policy andindustrial relations at a later stage.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrange for the issues discussed in C. (58) 53 to be examined in furtherdetail.(2) Agreed to resume their discussion of these issues in due course.
the conclusion of the Malta Round Table Conference about theimpracticability of full self-government for Malta, and it would benecessary to leave him in no doubt that the course which he apparentlyhad in mind would be unacceptable to Her Majesty&apos;s Government.In discussion there was general agreement with the views expressed by the Colonial Secretary. If the Prime Minister of Maltamaintains his extravagant demands, the Government should be ableto rely on the support of moderate opinion both in this country andin Malta.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of these statements.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,18th March, 1958.

</content>
</cab>
