<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/32/0 images: 234-237</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1958CC. (58) Copy No.37th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Friday, 2nd May, 1958, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Education.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Harold W Atkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P., I Mr. F. J. Erroll, M.P., ParliamentaryParliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretary, Board of Trade.Secretariat:Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. M. Reed.53440-3
ContentsSteelLocation of New Works
Steel.Location ofNew Works(previous reference :C.C. (58) 35thConclusions,Minute 4)The Cabinet resumed their consideration of C. (58) 66 and 87.In discussion there was considerable support for the proposal that Grangemouth, rather than Newport, should be selected as the site of the proposed new steel strip mill. No other industry would begranted an Industrial Development Certificate for the constructionof a plant at Newport, where unemployment was negligible; and theGovernment would invite well-founded criticism if, in the case of a project which they were themselves financing, they deliberatelyignored the criteria which, in the interests of ensuring a balanceddistribution of industry, they compelled private enterprise to observe.The progressive deterioration of ihe central industrial belt in Scotlandmade it increasingly urgent on social grounds to provide alternative employment in that area, and the location of the new mill atGrangemouth would be advantageous from this point of view. Adecision to reject a Scottish site and so to deprive Scotland of anystrip mill capacity would therefore be regarded as evidence that, theGovernment were not sincere in their recent declarations that they intended to take effective measures to anticipate the development oflocal unemployment; and it would subject the relations between england and Scotland to a new and severe strain.Moreover, the choice of a site at Grangemouth could be defendednot only by reference to social and political considerations but also oneconomic grounds. The estimated difference in the return on capitalwhich should be ensured by construction at Newport and constructionat Grangemouth respectively was no more than about 2 per cent.This figure was marginal and might well be reduced if, for example,the Scottish Council (Development and Industry) proved to be right in claiming that at least 60 per cent, of the coal required by the new plant could be supplied from local sources. It would also be reasonable to assume that the erection of a strip mill at Grangemouth would attract related industries to establish themselves in Scotland; and thesocial benefits which should flow from the reduction in unemployment would be reinforced by the economic advantages implicit in theexpansion and diversification of Scottish industry in general.In principle, the same arguments could be advanced in supportof a decision to select Kidwelly as the site of the new mill. It appearedprobable, however, that the Pressed Steel Company would shortlyagree to erect a new works at Swansea; and this should substantiallyreduce unemployment in West South Wales. A more detailed examination of the relative costs of production at Kidwelly andGrangemouth might be made; but, unless this enquiry showed thatoperation at Kidwelly would show a greater margin of profitabilityover operation at Grangemouth than at present appealed likely, theclaim of Grangemouth would remain very strong.On purely economic grounds, however, Newport should clearly be chosen as the site of the new mill; and in the case of a commoditywhich played so vital a part in our economy and faced such intensivecompetition as steel, it would be wise to allow the location of new capacity to be decided mainly by economic considerations. an effective distribution of industry policy could not afford wholly to set aside such considerations in favour of social arguments; and if wewere to remain a competitive trading nation, our economic policy must be sufficiently flexible to recognise and encourage thedevelopment of industries in the areas to which they were naturallyattracted by the play of economic forces. Moreover, the success ofthe new mill would be considerably affected by the quality of itsmanagement. No Scottish steel-making firm was prepared toundertake the management of a strip mill at Grangemouth and, ifthe mill was constructed on that site, it would probably be necessaryto direct Richard Thomas and Baldwins, Limited, to accept responsibility for its operation. There could be no assurances that in
these circumstances, the project would be easily or satisfactorilyestablished, whereas Newport represented the site which the Companythemselves had selected after a thorough survey of all the other possibilities.The Cabinet Agreed to resume their discussion at a subsequent meeting.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,2nd May, 1958.

</content>
</cab>
