<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/32/0 images: 293-296</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1958C.C. (58) Copy No.46th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Wednesday, 4th June, 1958, at 11 am.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd,M.P., Minister of Education.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General.Also present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat:Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. M. Reed.
contents minute no. subject      Industrial Disputes2      Foreign Affairs......Meeting of Heads of Governments.France.Middle East.3      Ceylon   ............
industrial disputes.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 45thConclusions,Minute 2.)The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of this statement.ForeignAffairs.Meeting of heads of governments.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 41stConclusions,Minute 1.)France.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 44thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Foreign Secretary said that, with our agreement, theUnited States Government were proposing that the meeting of experts to consider the technical implications of supervising the suspension of nuclear tests should take place at Geneva towards the end ofJune and that it should be confined to representatives of the UnitedKingdom, the United States and France on the one side and theSoviet Union, Czechoslovakia and Poland on the other side.Meanwhile, the discussions between the Soviet Foreign Minister andthe Ambassadors of the United Kingdom, United States and france in preparation for the meeting of Heads of Governments were makingonly slow progress. If a date could now be fixed for the proposed meeting of Foreign Ministers, this might serve both to accelerate the diplomatic discussions in Moscow and to compel the Western Powersthemselves to concert an agreed policy on some of the more debatableissues.The Cabinet (1) Took note that the Prime Minister, during his forthcoming visit to Washington, would discuss with the President ofthe United States the desirability of seeking to fix a date for the meeting of Foreign Ministers which was to precedethe meeting of Heads of Governments.The Foreign Secretary said that General de Gaulle appeared tohave selected the members of his Administration with considerablecare and skill. It was unlikely that the new Government would seek to make any radical modification in the political relations of Francewith the other Western Powers. Their economic policy, however,was less predictable. Their reserves of foreign exchange were likelyto reach a dangerously low level during the next few months and theymight be tempted to seek assistance from their other partners in theTreaty of Rome in return for the offer of discriminatory importquotas. If so, our own interests would be threatened; and, althoughaction might be deferred for a time until the intentions of the FrenchGovernment became clearer, it might become necessary to considerwhether we should seek to anticipate any attempt on their part to turn the Treaty of Rome to our disadvantage by being preparedourselves to offer some support to the French economy in concert,if possible, with the United States and Germany.1. The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that he had indicated to representatives of the Trades Union Congress (T.U.C.),at a meeting on 30th May, that, while the Government would not seek to influence the attitude of the British Transport Commissionand the London Transport Executive, they thought it should bepossible to settle the London bus dispute if the Transport andGeneral Workers&apos; Union were willing to accept the offer of theExecutive to implement the Industrial Courts award of a wage,increase of 8s. 6d. a week to bus workers in central London and toextend that award to the drivers and conductors of Green Line busesand were also prepared to enter into negotiations with the executive in order to fix the date at which the wage claim of the bus workersnot covered by the Industrial Courts award should be reviewed. Hehad received a further deputation from the T.U.C. that morning, attheir request, and had made it clear that the Government were notprepared to press the Transport Executive to make any further concession.
The Cabinet (2) Took note, with approval, of this statement.The Foreign Secretary said that there was some reason to believethat the pressure of the United Arab Republic against the Lebanonmight now be relaxed to some extent. But, although PresidentChamoun appeared to be maintaining his position, the situation in the lebanon remained uncertain.Egyptian infiltration in Kuwait was increasing rapidly. Wecould not afford to allow our position in Kuwait to be compromised;but, equally, we could not seek to compel the Ruler, as the iraqi government wished, to join the Arab Union. We should therefore continue to press the Ruler to enter into some form of relations withthe Arab Union which would be of benefit to Iraq without endangering the relations between the Ruler and ourselves. Theproblem implicit in this situation was also liable to arise inconnection with the other States in the Persian Gulf and to become increasingly acute as the spirit of Arab nationalism grew stronger.The Cabinet (3) Invited the Foreign Secretary to arrange for a further studyto be made of the objectives of our policy in relation tothe Persian Gulf States in the light of the growth of Arabnationalist sentiment.3. The Commonwealth Secretary said that the situation in ceylon had deteriorated. He had felt obliged to authorise the HighCommissioner in Colombo to agree, if so requested by the ceylon government, to their use of British aircraft for the transport ofpolice for the maintenance of public order, but there was no questionof British troops being employed for this purpose.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of this statement.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,4th June, 1958.Middle East.(previous references:CC. (58) 18thConclusions,Minute 2,and 44thConclusions,Minute 2.)Ceylon.(previous reference:CM. (56) 47thConclusions,Minute 10.)

</content>
</cab>
