<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/32/0 images: 325-331</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this document is THE property of her britannic majesty&apos;8 governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.  July 1958C.C. (58) Copy No.51st conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S. W. 1, on tuesday, 1st July, 1958, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P.. Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and Local Gov-ernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Education.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General.Also present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. M. Reed.53860-8B
2   . SECRET &quot;&quot;        310ContentsMinuteNo.                                       Subject page 1     France   ...      ......................       visit of the Prime Minister and Foreign Secretary to Paris.2      Nuclear Energy ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       3Amendment of United States Legislation.3      Foreign Affairs ...      ...............       4Meeting of Heads of Governments.The Lebanon.4      Egypt     ........................       4Financial Negotiations.5      Suez Canal       .....................       6Surcharge.6     Commonwealth Immigrants   .........      ......       7
nuclear energy.Amendment ofUnited StatesLegislation.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 48thConclusions,Minute 1.)2. The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that the Bill toamend the McMahon Act had now been passed by Congress. the bilateral agreement between the United States and ourselves about theexchange of information on nuclear energy, which was to be executedunder this legislation, would need to be initialled forthwith if it was tocome into effect before Congress adjourned after first being laid beforeCongress for the statutory period of thirty sitting days. At this latestage, however, the United States authorities had sought to insert inits preamble words defining its purpose as the promotion of themaximum advantage to both countries in the application of nuclear energy to both civil and military purposes. This reference to the civiluse of nuclear energy in an agreement to be concluded for military purposes was objectionable; for, although the wording of the preamble had no legal force, it might provide the United states authorities with a means of putting pressure on us to discloseinformation about the development of our civil nuclear power programme. He had therefore informed President Eisenhower thatthe amendment to the preamble was unacceptable; and he understoodthat the President had recommended the Atomic Energy Commission,with whom the final decision lay, to delete it. If they refused to do so,it was for consideration whether we should sign the bilateral agree-ment with an explicit reservation in writing that we should expectco-operation in the civil application of nuclear energy to continue tobe governed by existing agreements.In discussion there was general agreement with this suggestion.We must remain free, in the last resort, to disclose publicly the actionwhich we had taken. But in the interests of facilitating the passage ofthe bilateral agreement through Congress, we should avoid, if possible,any reference to our reservation, and any public discussion of theagreement as a whole, until the statutory thirty days had expired.The Cabinet (1) Agreed in principle that the draft agreement on the exchangeof nuclear information with the United States Governmentshould be initialled.(2) Took note that, if the final version of the preamble to thisagreement implied that the provisions of the agreement would extend to co-operation in the civil, as well as themilitary, application of nuclear energy, the PrimeMinister would inform the United States Government thatwe should expect civil co-operation to continue to be governed by existing agreements.53860-8France. 1,   The Prime Minister reported to the Cabinet on the visit to visit of Prime Paris which he had paid, together with the Foreign Secretary, duringMinister and the previous weekend. They had received a cordial welcome from theForeign general public and, although they had not been concerned to negotiateSecretary to on particular issues, their discussions with General de Gaulle hadParis. comprised a useful review of Anglo-French relations.  The GeneraPsmain preoccupations were to devise a scheme of constitutional reform,to promote a settlement of the North African problem and toestablish France as a nuclear Power in her own right. He was notwell-informed about the projected European Free Trade Area; butthey had impressed on him the dangers of continued Frenchintransigence in this context and there was some hope that he mightexert his personal authority to secure a resumption of practicalnegotiations in the near future.The Cabinet Took note of this statement.
Foreign Affairs.Meeting of heads of governments.(previous reference :CC. (58) 46thConclusions,Minute 2.)The Lebanon.(previous reference:CC (58) 49thConclusions,Minute 1.)The Foreign Secretary said that the situation in the Lebanonremained unsatisfactory. The Lebanese Government appeared to be unable or unwilling to crush the rebellion by force, while the Secretary-General of the United Nations was reluctant to take any action, apartfrom the despatch of the United Nations observers already in thecountry, to implement the resolution of the Security Council thatinfiltration of the Lebanon should be prevented. Moreover, theobservers had so far been unable to obtain evidence of infiltration onany significant scale.In discussion it was agreed that a situation which we had originally envisaged in terms of foreign subversion had developed intoa civil war for which a primarily political solution must be devised. it remained important, however, that the Lebanon should remain a stable and independent State, capable of resisting the pressure of theUnited Arab Republic; and the continued threat of intervention by theWestern Powers, combined with pressure by the United Nations,might succeed in inducing the opposing factions to agree upon asettlement which we could accept. It would be necessary, for thispurpose, to seek to persuade the Secretary-General to take more positive action to give effect to the resolution of the Security Council.We should also give further consideration, in concert with the UnitedStates Government, to the best means of ensuring that, when PresidentChamoun&apos;s term of office expired in the near future, he shouldbe succeeded by an individual who would be&apos; likely to maintain the lebanon in general alignment with the West.The Cabinet-Invited the Foreign Secretary to be guided by the considera-tions which had emerged during their discussion.Egypt.financial negotiations.(previous reference :CC. (58) 41stConclusions,Minute 8.)4.   The Cabinet had before them:  (i) A note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer (C. (58) 133)covering a memorandum by officials on the possible resumption offinancial negotiations with Egypt.(ii) A memorandum by the Foreign Secretary (C. (58) 134)discussing the administrative feasibility of distributing a iump sum payment of compensation by the Egyptian Government.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the egyptian government had now rejected the earlier concept of a limitedfinancial settlement, which would have excluded both the Egyptianclaim for compensation for &quot; war damage &quot; and our own claim for damage to our property in the Suez Canal Base, and had proposed a lump sum settlement which would be deemed to take account ofboth these claims. Such a settlement would be in full satisfaction of our claims in respect of Egyptianised property and damage tosequestrated property; and it would comprise both the restorationof the sequestrated assets to their owners and the release to theEgyptian Government of such part of their blocked sterling balancesas remained after the lump sum payment had been discharged.There would be advantages in resolving the present deadlockin negotiations as soon as possible; but the figure of  25 millions,which the Egyptian Government had privately indicated that they3. The Cabinet were informed that the Prime Ministers reply tothe latest letter from the Soviet Prime Minister on the proposed meeting of Heads of Governments would be published that day.Meanwhile, the Soviet Government were to be represented at theconference of scientists on the supervision of the suspension of nuclear tests, the first meeting of which was to be held that day at Geneva.
would be prepared to consider as the basis of a lump sum settlement,was inadequate. The total of the claims which British claimantsagainst Egypt could advance, even if reduced to a realistic level,was of the order of  40- 45 millions; and unless the egyptian government could be persuaded to increase their offer to a figure in the neighbourhood of  35 millions, there would be considerable political difficulty in defending a lump sum settlement. Moreover,the Government would be subject to heavy pressure to supplement the Egyptian lump sum payment from the United kingdom excequer, with the additional disadvantage that, until relationswith Egypt were restored, there would be no means of reliablyassessing the extent of the damage which the sequestrated Britishassets had suffered.In discussion it was agreed that a financial settlement would be advantageous in principle, in so far as it should enable us to resumediplomatic and commercial relations with Egypt. The tradingcommunity were increasingly concerned about the continued closure of the Egyptian market and the risk that British goods wouldgradually be supplanted by exports from other countries. Inaddition, public pressure for the satisfaction of British claims inrespect of Egyptianised and sequestrated assets was mounting; andit would not be possible to avoid an embarrassing parliamentary debate on this subject unless the spokesmen for the claimants couldbe assured that the Government intended either to negotiate a final settlement with the Egyptian Government in the near future or toprovide compensation from the Exchequer. The fact that thedistribution of a lump sum payment, though a lengthy and complexoperation, should be within the competence of the foreign compensation Commission was a further argument in favour of seeking to reach agreement with Egypt on this basis.On the other hand, there was little likelihood that a settlement would result in any reduction in the subversive pressure which theEgyptian Government were systematically exerting against Westerninterests throughout the Middle East and in Africa; and if We wereto contemplate reaching an agreement with Egypt without alienatingour friends in the Arab world we should need to present it as a purelyfinancial settlement based on practical considerations and not as theprelude to a political reconciliation between Egypt and ourselves.In particular, we should ensure, if possible, that it was not represented as concealing a concession to Egypt in respect of the Egyptian claimto compensation for &quot; war damage,&quot; which must be regarded asoffset against our own claim for compensation in respect of damage to United Kingdom property in the Suez Canal Base.   Moreover,the amount of the lump sum payment must be sufficient to enable us to demonstrate to public opinion in this country that we had secured reasonable satisfaction of British claims having regard tothe fact that we held blocked Egyptian sterling balances of the orderof  70- 80 millions.  Although it would be impossible to confiscatethese balances without severely shaking foreign confidence in the sterling area as a banking system, the amount applied in dischargeof the lump sum payment should bear a reasonable proportion tothe amount to be released thereafter to the Egyptian Government. Theowners of Egyptianised assets were, on the whole, substantialconcerns; and they might acquiesce, however reluctantly, in a levelof compensation which fell short of full satisfaction of their claims.The owners of sequestrated assets, however, were for the most partindividuals, whose claims to full compensation were likely to command greater sympathy.  If public pressure on behalf of Britishclaimants was intensified, it might become necessary to concede eithersome Exchequer supplementation of the Egyptian lump sum paymentor some extension of the present arrangements for making ex gratiaadvances to claimants.   For this purpose it would be advisable to
Suez Canal.(previous reference :C.C. (57) 82ndConclusions,Minute 6.)Surcharge.5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the foreign secretary (C. (58) 135) on the proposed Suez Canal surcharge.The Foreign Secretary said that the Secretary-General of theUnited Nations intended shortly to announce the arrangements for collecting the proposed surcharge of 3 per cent, on the transit tollsof ships using the Suez Canal. It had already been agreed inprinciple that the Government should reimburse British shipowners,provided that the Governments of other countries ensured that theirown ships would also pay the surcharge; and since there was evidencethat we might expect a substantial measure of co-operation in thisrespect he proposed to indicate, in answer to an arrangedParliamentary Question, that we endorsed the arrangements madeby the United Nations and were prepared to co-operate in puttingthem into effect on the understanding that we reserved our rightto review this decision from time to time in the light of the workingof the scheme and the extent of the co-operation afforded by othercountries.In discussion it was suggested that the Parliamentary statement should make it clear that, since the United Nations expenditure tobe recovered by the surcharge included the costs of the Anglo-Frenchsalvage fleet while it was under the command of the United Nations,these costs would themselves be reimbursed to Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment in due course.The Cabinet Approved the proposal in C. (58) 135 subject to amendmentof the proposed Parliamentary statementsuggested during their discussion.on it. -    i;____L11C    lUlcSkeep in being the Anglo-Egyptian Resettlement Board, who hadnearly completed their existing task.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that thebalance of advantage appeared to lie in seeking to effect anagreement with the Egyptian Government, provided that this was confined to an adequate settlement of financial claims and could notbe regarded as implying any modification of our political attitudetowards the Egyptian Government. The Cabinet should be given a further opportunity to study the detailed terms of such anagreement, which might thereafter be communicated to the egyptian government without commitment as regards the amount of the lump sum payment which we should be prepared to accept. Our objective in the subsequent negotiations should be to secure the maximumpayment from the Egyptian Government by indicating that the rate at which we should be prepared to release the remainder of the sterling balances would depend on the amount of the figure finally agreed for the lump sum. The negotiations should, if possible, be substantially completed during the summer recess in order that thesettlement of individual claims might have made some progressbefore Parliament reassembled in the autumn.The Cabinet (1) Approved in principle the resumption of financial negotiations with the Egyptian Government on the basis indicated in C. (58) 133.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to circulate the detailed provisions of the draft agreement to becommunicated to the Egyptian Government.(3) Invited the Home Secretary to circulate a report on thework of the Anglo-Egyptian Resettlement Board.
commonwealth immigrants.(previous reference :C.C. (57) 57thConclusions,Minute 5.)6. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the lord president and the Home Secretary (C. (58) 129 and 132) discussing the advisability of legislation to control immigration from theCommonwealth.The Lord President said that the Committee on colonial immigrants had come to the conclusion that legislation was not yetrequired to control coloured immigration from the Commonwealth.Administrative action should, however, be continued and, ifnecessary, intensified, in order to restrict emigration from India,Pakistan and the West Indies; and the Committee should keepdevelopments under review with the object of making a further report to the Cabinet in the early autumn.The Home Secretary supported these proposals. Legislationdirected against the Commonwealth would be controversial in itself and might need to be accompanied by no less controversial legislation on the immigration of aliens.Discussion showed that there was general agreement with thisview. But unrestricted coloured immigration might have serioussocial consequences in the longer term; and although it would bedesirable, if possible, to avoid legislation on this subject in the lastfull session of the present Parliament, the situation should be closelywatched.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that legislation to control immigration from theCommonwealth was not yet required.(2) Invited the Lord Chancellor to arrange for the Committeeon Colonial Immigrants to keep the question under closereview.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,1st July, 1958.

</content>
</cab>
