<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/32/0 images: 598-602</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET ^THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1958C.C. (58) . Copy No.88th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.1,on Tuesday, 23rd December, 1958, at 2-45 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.The Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Education.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P., i The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Postmaster-General (Item 3).Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Mr. C. J. M. Alport, M.P., Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State for commonwealth Relations (Items 1-2).Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. M. Reed.
contents minute no. subject      Commercial Policy     ......Free Trade Area.2     Commercial Policy     ......Butter.3     Civil Service     .........
CC. 88 (58)commercial policy.Free trade area.(previous reference:CC. (58) 86thConclusions,Minute 4.)1. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the counter-proposal which constituted our reply to the interim proposals of the six Powers had been formally tabled in the Organisation for european economic Co-operation (O.E.E.C.). It would now be subjected to technical analysis within the Organisation and the results of this examination would be available for consideration by the further meeting of the Ministerial Council which had been arranged for15th January, 1959. The main feature of our counter-proposal wasthe suggestion that all increases in quotas granted by members of theEuropean Economic Community (E.E.C.) to one another should beextended to all members of O.E.E.C. and that, in return, othermembers of O.E.E.C. should grant similar increases in quotas both to members of the ETC and to one another.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) It would be important to retain our freedom to extend such increases in quotas beyond O.E.E.C., if necessary at a subsequentstage, in conformity with our international obligations in this respect.(b) Our counter-oiler included the suggestion that, if themembers of the E.E.C. decided to increase quotas for agricultural products among themselves, we should be prepared to enter into discussions about the possibility of some multilateral arrangement inthis context in order to avoid discrimination. It would be undesirable,however, to give any indication at this stage that we were contemplating concessions on agricultural quotas; and we should reserve our position on this point more explicitly.(c) It had been suggested that, after the examination of ourcounter-proposal by O.E.E.C. had been completed, a meeting of heads of Governments of the United Kingdom, Western Germany,France and Italy should be convened before 15th January. Such ameeting, if hastily arranged and allowed little time in which to discussthe issues involved, might well fail to achieve any useful result. Itwould be preferable, if possible, to avoid this commitment.(d) By the time that the Ministerial Council resumed their discussion on 15th January, a new French Government would havetaken office. There were grounds for believing that they might benot unfavourably disposed towards our proposals; and a considerablebody of French opinion associated with General de Gaulle had also indicated some. sympathy with our initiative, mainly in reactionagainst the supra-national institutions which were an essential feature of the E.E.C. It was not impossible that the originalconception of the Treaty of Rome would be prevented from achievingfull realisation by this significant change of official opinion in France.But we should avoid, if possible, being manoeuvred into a positionin which we could be accused of being primarily responsible for sucha development.(e) We had already secured a favourable atmosphere for thediscussions on 15th January by refraining from any attempt to turn the deadlock in the Free Trade Area negotiations to our advantage in the recent discussions with the other Western Powers about a jointpolicy on the future status of Berlin. It would be wise to continue to refrain from provocative or retaliatory action and to be prepared I ienvisage some concessions, if necessary, to the political views of thenew regime in France in order to avoid endangering the chances ofestablishing a Free Trade Area on satisfactory lines.(/) We should also refrain for the time being from any further attempt overtly to promote a Uniscan Free Trade Area. Theinitiative which the Federation of British Industries had undertaken for this purpose with the industrialists of the Scandinavian countries,Switzerland and Austria might be allowed to continue, provided thatthe discussions were as unobtrusive as possible.SECRET54550-5 ii 2
commercial policy,Butter.(previous reference:C.C. (58) 41stConclusions,Minute 6.)2. The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations said that an announcement was to be made that day to the effect that the restrictions on butter imports which, at therequest of the New Zealand Government, had been introduced in theprevious May were in some cases to be removed and in othersreviewed. The Prime Minister of New Zealand proposed to make astatement immediately afterwards in terms which could be regardedas satisfactory. He had, however, sought, and been given, anundertaking that discussions would be resumed if changes in the butter market made it desirable to consider the reintroduction ofsome form of control.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of this statement.Civil Service.(previous reference:CM. (56) 26thConclusions,Minute 5.)Pay.3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (C. (58) 261) on pay claims submitted bythe Staff Side of the Civil Service National Whitley Council and bythe Post Office Engineering Union.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that a good case could bemade for a 4 per cent, increase in the salaries of Post Office engineers,based on corresponding pay adjustments in outside industry. Anincrease of this order, however, would stimulate the National staff side to reject any lower offer for the grades covered by their claim i.e., grades up to, and including, the level of Principal. Inaccordance with the recommendations of the Royal Commission onthe Civil Service, pay claims by civil servants should be dealt withclass by class on the basis of factual information, provided by theCivil Service Pay Research Unit, about the remuneration of personsin comparable employment elsewhere. The accumulation of thenecessary facts had, however, taken longer than had been expected and in these circumstances the principle of a central settlement, asclaimed by the National Staff Side, could be regarded as justified if(g) We should seek to associate the United States more actively   xwith our renewed attempt to establish a Free Trade Area.   The ( yAUnited States Secretary of State, Mr. Dulles, should be given a sdetailed description of the policy which we were seeking to pursueand of the reasons for which we believed that at a time when certaindivergencies of policy among the Six Powers might be emerging, ourown initiative might help to reintegrate the economic life of europe on a more sound and stable foundation.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrange for the&apos; United Kingdom spokesmen at the meeting of the ministerial Council of the Organisation for european economic Co-operation on 15th January, 1959, to be guided by the points made in their discussion.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary, in consultation with theChancellor of the Exchequer, to arrange for the UnitedStates Secretary of State to be informed of the policywhich we were seeking to pursue and to endeavour to enlist the active co-operation of the United States Govern-ment on the lines indicated in their discussion.(3) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrange for a white Paper, describing the course of our negotiationsfor the establishment of a Free Trade Area, to be preparedfor publication when Parliament reassembled.
Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,24th December, 1958.CC. 88 (58)the pay of civil servants was not to fall appreciably behind that of corresponding outside occupations. But an increase of 4 per cent,was not supported by such facts as were available. Enquiries of some52 undertakings employing staff comparable to civil servants had revealed that only 25 had given increases, amounting on average toabout 3^ per cent. If, however, the central claim was rejected, theindividual staff associations would submit separate claims whichwould, if necessary, be pressed to arbitration; and a series of settle-ments or awards for civil servants in the first half of 1959, possibly.involving increases of the order of 4- per cent, or more, might havedamaging consequences for the policy of wage restraint. TheCommittee on Wages Policy had therefore considered whether itwould be wiser to. accept the basis of a central settlement but to deferan offer for as long as possible by stipulating that additional information must first be obtained. The alternative course, whichwas favoured by the majority of members of the Committee, was tomake an immediate offer of 3  per cent, to both the National staff side and the Post Office Engineering Union. This increase wouldbe operative from 1st December and would cost some  16 millions.In discussion it was pointed out that an immediate offer wouldhave the advantage of being clearly associated with the current seriesof wage increases rather than with the early stages of a new series of claims in 1959. Moreover, arbitration could not be avoided if it wasdemanded by the Staff Sides; and the Post Office engineers had alreadyinvited the Postmaster-General to agree to arbitration. Since,therefore, some pay increase was unavoidable, the Governmentshould seek to select the least inopportune occasion for the concession.The cost-of-living index would probably rise further during thecoming months and the prospect of settling the two claims for 3^ percent, would then be less likely.On the other hand, it was in the interest both of the Governmentand of the Civil Service itself to adhere to the principles enunciatedby the Royal Commission, namely that Civil Service pay should bebased on comparisons with outside employment, that it should besettled class by class on the basis of ascertained facts and thatits adjustment should follow, rather than precede, changes in remuneration in outside employment. None of these criteria wouldbe satisfied if an immediate offer was made; and there would be some danger that such an offer would be regarded as an initiative by theGovernment in prompting the next round of pay claims throughout industry.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that,although the considerations were evenly balanced, the leastdisadvantageous course appeared to be to make an immediate offer of 3i per cent, to both the National Staff Side and the Post office engineering Union.The Cabinet Approved the proposal in C. (58) 261.

</content>
</cab>
