<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/211/2 images: 17-18</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTC(81) 28 January 1981PAY AND PERFORMANCEMemorandum by the Lord President of the CouncilSCOPE OF THE SCHEME1. Following an invitation by the Ministerial Committee on EconomicStrategy to pursue the introduction of performance-related pay for civilservants, I circulated to colleagues proposals to introduce, as a first step,and as a means of making an early start, a scheme for   the Under Secretarygrade from 1 April 1981.    The majority of colleagues reacted againstdealing with that grade alone.    The general feeling was that it would be betterto launch a pay and performance scheme at lower levels.2. So I suggest that we should begin by covering the three administrativegrades of Principal, Senior Principal and Assistant Secretary, and also lookto see how quickly we can bring in the specialist grades at this level as well.It will take longer to devise the more complex scheme necessary for thegreater number and diversity of staff involved. My intention would be tohave a scheme which could be implemented from 1 April 1982. But officialswould need to get on without delay with preparing proposals.THE PRINCIPLE3. We came to office with a commitment to reward incentive andinitiative.   We are agreed on the need to make the Civil Service moreefficient, and a feature of this should be greater reward for better performancePaying more for better work should provide a clear incentive;   so shouldpaying less for less good work.4. There are of course problems, some of which colleagues have alreadyraised.     Two obvious ones are firstly appraising performance equitably inDepartments of varying size, location and homogeneity, and secondly ofpreventing abuses such as unjustifiable merit pay increases for staff approach-ing retirement so as to boost their pensions.    But these do not detract fronthe Tightness of the principle;  nor are they in practice insuperable.Performance is already assessed annually:  although relating these assess-ments to pay adjustments introduces a new dimension, we should be able todevise workable criteria and procedures which provide the incentive we seekto improve performance.    The scheme must keep to the absolute minimumextra work involved in assessment.1COPY NO gCABINETCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALTIMING5. There is also the question of timing.    An effective scheme will needto provide for wide differentials.    We will have to start from the legalentitlement to the existing pay scales,     So if the rcheme is to be self-financing it will take some years for it to reach progressively the kind ofdifferentials necessary.      But we must make a   start and I propose thatwe shoul 1 work up a scheme which could begin in April 1982.INCREMENTS6. In addition, the legal difficulties involved in making a more generalchange to the present arrangements for automatic increments, involving awider range of grades, should also be examined.CONCLUSIONS7. I am seeking agreement now to officials preparing schemes on whichwe can form a judgment.    The relative merits of different kinds of schemessuch as bonuses, range pay and so on can be examined over- the comingmonths together with practices in other countries.    We shall also have thebenefit of the studies on outside practice here by the Office of ManpowerEconomics and the Pay Research Unit.8. I therefore invite colleagues to agree that:-i. I should instruct my officials, in consultation asnecessary with other Departments, to devise proposalswhich could be implemented from April 1982;ii. these proposals should cover the grades of Principal,Senior Principal and Assistant Secretary and examine thetiming of extending the scheme to equivalent specialist grades;iii. I should report back to colleagues in the summer.SCivil Service Department9 January 19812CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
