<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/82/0 images: 283-285</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.P.(56) 1951st August, 1956CABINETEGG MARKETING scheme memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Agricultural Ministers are now called upon to take decisions about the draft British Egg Marketing Scheme submitted by the threeFarmers&apos; Unions.    They are required to take into account the objectionsand representations made on the scheme and the report of theCommissioner who conducted the public inquiry.    Any modificationsformally proposed must be accepted by the promoters before the scheme can go further.2.     In the White Paper on &quot;Decontrol of Food and Marketing ofAgricultural Produce&quot; published in November, 1953 (Cmd. 8989) we saidthat:-&quot;It is the policy of the Government to consider sympatheticallyproposals for Agricultural Marketing Schemes and in appropriate cases to make use of producers1 Marketing Boards in theadministration of Part I of the Agriculture Act. &quot;3.     Before promoting this scheme the Farmers8 Unions asked about theattitude of the Government towards the establishment of an Egg MarketingBoa.rd with full trading powers; with the agreement of the economic policy Committee I informed Sir James Turner, the President of theNational Farmers&apos; Union, that, subject to certain conditions about theoperation of the price guarantee, such a scheme would be acceptable.4.     This provisional agreement would not have prevented us fromrejecting the scheme at this stage.    But the Commissioner concludesthat on balance the case for a scheme has been made out and proposes anumber of modifications to the scheme as submitted.    The HomeAffairs Committee have agreed that the scheme should not be rejectedand also, with one exception, on the main modifications that should berequired (H.P.(56) 15th Meeting, Minute 1).5.     Generally these modifications follow the lines of thoserecommended by the Commissioner but, in one case, go further.    Thisis on the important point of sales of eggs by producers to retail shops,for which the scheme at present makes no specific provision.    the modification proposed by the Commissioner would empower the board to decide whether licences for such sales should be issued and what conditions they should impose upon producers (including a requirement to grade, test and mark the eggs).    The Home Affairs Committeeaccepted instead the Agricultural Ministers&apos; proposal that any producershould be given a right to a licence and that this licence might requireCOPY NO.
him to mark his eggs but not to grade or test them.    There are strong arguments in favour of this course.    I believe also that it is the minimummodification necessary to secure support for the scheme from our sideof the House, and I think it likely that the promoters will accept it -though with some reluctance.6.     The point on which there is a difference of view in the Home-Affairs Committee relates to the pooling of transport costs.    Thescheme places an obligation on the Board, when determining producers&apos;prices, to pool transport costs incurred after the eggs have been throughthe packing stations.    Objections on economic grounds were voicedagainst this at the public inquiry, but the Commissioner specificallyrefrains from making a recommendation on the grounds that it is&quot;entirely a matter of policy&quot;.7.     In my view we should not give statutory force to a provision which requires the Board to give this degree of protection to remote eggproducers, although without this provision the Board would remain free to do so if they wished.    Although our present guarantee arrangementsfor eggs afford a uniform support price throughout the United Kingdom,the arrangements for almost all other guaranteed commodities allow forsome differential between the prices received by the more remoteproducers and those nearer to the market.    I recognise that the deletion of this provision would be most unwelcome to the Scottish andUlster Farmers&apos; Unions, but I find it difficult to believe that they would refuse to proceed with the scheme on this account, bearing in mind thatthe alternative would almost certainly be a system which would reflect,at least to some extent, transport differentials.0.     The Home Secretary and the Secretary of State for Scotland, onthe other hand, consider that insistence on this modification, about which no opinion is expressed by the Commissioner, would be virtually certain to kill the scheme, and that it v/ould be altogether the wrong issue onwhich to cause such a break.    The Scottish and Ulster Farmers&apos; unions would interpret the removal of this obligation from the Board as a veiledform of Government pressure to encourage the Board to discriminate against the remote producer.conclusion.     I would invite my colleagues to endorse our proposal to allow the draft Egg Marketing Scheme to proceed subject to modifications;and I seek a decision as to whether these modifications should includedeletion of the provision relating to the pooling of transport costs.D.H. A.Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food,S.W.1.1st August, 1956.


</content>
</cab>
