<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/82/0 images: 307-307</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET KJ\ :CoP. (56) 200 COPY NO, &quot;&quot;7--  ^-1 st August. 19,5,6I ICABINETANGLO-AMERICAN TELEGRAPH company memorandum by the Postmaster-general for some seventy years the telegraph cable service between the United Kingdom and the United States has beenoperated by two American companies,,   One of these, theWestern Union Telegraph Company, rents five of its eightcables from the Anglo-American Telegraph Company, a British,company, registered in England but with its seat of management and control In Rhodesia^   There is a ninety-nine year leaseexpiring in 2010 at an annual rental of  262,500*2,     Since 19/4.3 Western Union, which has a monopoly of theinternal telegraph system of the United States, has beenunder a statutory obligation to divest itself of its overseasassets,,   Western Union has been negotiating for the sale ofthese assets to another American company, the AmericanSecurities Corporation,   The negotiations involve purchase by American Securities of the Anglo cables.   Anglo have been offered a total payment of $10-g- millions but their directorsare holding out for $12^ millions,   I am told that thereare fair prospects of the gap of $2 millions being bridged,3*     The proposal will mean the disposal of a British assetto American interests,   Anglo are anxious to sell0   They know that the cables are old and that modern technical develop-merits must mean that their value will depreciate,,    I understandthat in the&apos;Treasury vie?; there is no power under UnitedKingdom law, and probably none under Rhodesian law, to preventthe transaction,km     I thought it right to put the issue to the Chancellorof the Exchequer before the deal was completed and he has asked that the matter should be placed before the Cabinet^The political issue apart, this is a sensible commercialproposition which will have no adverse effect on communica-tions, and is not in conflict with Post Office developmentpolicy.Co HoGeneral Post Office, EoC, 1,1st August, 1956*

</content>
</cab>
