<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/37/0 images: 31-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^ormmmj-S THE PROPERTY OF HIS BPITAPEIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT,.)0 E C R E T.J&amp;&amp;*Jr   sib SC A E I N E T .CONCLUSIONS c.f a Conference held at 10 DowninsStrest,  S.W. , on FRIDAY, NOVEMBER 14th,  1919at 3-30 p.m.o   a   f   0   0   &apos;&amp;   4   o   o   b  tPRESEPT:-The Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Rt.Hon.A.Bonar Law, M.P.;Lord Privy Seal.The Rt. Hori. A. JiBalf our, 0.1.,&apos; IE?.,Lord President cf the Council.the Rt.Hon.A.-Chamberlain, M.PA,Chancellor of tho Exchequer,Field Marshal ?he Rt. Hon.ViscountFrench cf Ypres, K.P. , 0 .11. , G. C. B. ,G .C.V.0. ,K.C.M.G, -Lord Lieutenantof Ireland.The Rt. Hon . j. LMaophereon ,K. C. ,MAP.,  Chief Secretary for IrelandBrig.-General Sir J.Byrne, K.3.E.,Inspector-General, Royal irish constabulary.      -   -   ;B.england. Smith, C.3.E., A/VputyInspect or-General, Royal Irish-Constabulary.The Rt.Hon.Lord Birkenhoad,Lord chancellor the Rt.Hon .W.S. Churchill, MAP. ,Secretary of State for War &amp; Air.The Rt. Hon. &quot;W. Long, M.P. ,First Lord of the Admiralry.The Rt.. Hon. E0 Shortt, K.C.,M.P. , Secretary of State for&apos;Home Affairs...&apos;The. Rt.Hon.E.S.Montagu, M.E. ,Secretary of State for India.The Rt.Hon.H.A,L.Fieher, MAP,,President of the Board ofEducation,Colonel &apos;W. Edgnworth Johnstons.C.B.E.,  Chief Co^raissionnr,Dublin Metropolitan Police.Lieut-onant-General Sir P.C. Shaw,K.C.B., Officer CommandingIrish Forces,-outenant-Colonel Sir M.P.A.Hankey, G.C.B.................Secretary,  CabinetCaptain L.F,Burgis...........................Assistant Secretary,    Cabinet.if. Philip Ke-rr.
IRELAND. 

DUBLIN METROPOLITAN POLICE.

With reference to Cabinet 6 (19) the Conference heard, reports on the present state of Ireland from the following:-

General Sir F.C. Shaw, 

Commander-in-Chief of the Forces in Ireland

General Sir F. Byrne,

Inspector-General, Royal Irish Constabulary.

Mr. T. J. Smith, Royal Irish Constabulary.

Col. Edgeworth Johnstone,

Chief Commissioner. Dublin Metropolitan Police.

These statements were to the effect that the proclaiming of Martial Law, either ever the whole of Irleand or in any part of Ireland, where an outrage had been committee, would be a little real assistance in bringing murderers to trial and that no powers existed under Martial Law that had not existed under the Defence of the Realm Act. Under the latter it was not possible to infliet the death sentence except on the charge of treason. It was also stated that the changing of the venue of a trial from Dublin to Belfast would not be an absolute guarantee of the jury being free from intimidation. In addition, it was the opinion of the Police Experts taht the deportation of murderers on suspicion would have a great effect in the country, but not as great as would be the ease if conviction could be obtained in two or three cases and the murders hanged.

With regard to the moral effect of these outrages in the Dublin Metropolitan Police, it was stated that on the whole force this was negligible, but that in regard to the political section of this Body, which consisted of then men only. It was having effect which was not surprising in view of the fact that out of this small number two men had been killed, one dangerously wounded and two had had attacks made upon them.


After the withdrawal of the experts, the Conferenceiiscuosed. the policy to be adopted and agreed :-(1)    That on the evidence before thera^ the best wayto secure, a cessation of murder ras by the con-viction and the infliction of a capital sentenceon some of the murderers *(2)    That the delay Involved in waiting until thenext as sisos was undesirable and pr in instances where a perfectly clear case existed, an earlier trial was desirable.(3)    That in two cases sufficient evidence which wouldnot be liable to fail through intimidation wasforthcomings to ensure a conviction.(4)    That the change of the place of trial from Dublinto Belfast owing to the doubt as to whethera jury could be empanelled In Dublin which wouldconvict, provided no guarantee of convictionand was undesirable? more particularly as it involved removal from a Roman. Catholic to aProtestant districts(5)    That a special tribunal of three judges shouldbe established for the trial of cases where a conviction .was reasonably assured^(6)    That the necessary legislation to carry this out should be prepared, for the consideration of, theCabinet with a view to early introduction inparliament.   This legislation should Include powerto dispense with unpaid magistrates and. givepower to judges to try in camera,?(V)    That a few suspected persons -should be deportedfrom Ireland to Great Britain where they shouldbe interned unless, they could find sone other country to harbour them., in which case their departure would be pemitteda   The Irish Cfovernmentshould have authority for tho immediate adoptionof this course.(8)    That the Irish Government withdraw the    ameliorationsand refuse to - yield to hunger strikes in the case ofconvicted men.2, Whitehall GardensP S*Ws*l*:,14th November? 1919.&apos;

</content>
</cab>
