<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/37/0 images: 130-132</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Oi? HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT&apos;).SECRET,K.JCONCLUSIONS of a Confaronoa of,Ministers held at 10 Downing Street.S.W. on Friday, January 23rd, 1920,at 3*15 p.m.Present:The Prime Minister      (in the Chair)he Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. B,S-Montagu, M.P.Seeretary of State for India.Right Hon. W.S..Chur chill, M.P*secretary of State for War &amp; Air.The following were also present;The Lord Hardinge of Sir S.J.Chapman, 3C.C.B.,C.B.B..,LshSstf^a.VF.0. .G.Q.B. .G.C ,3.1. ,    Joint Permanent Secretary, BoardG.C.M.S.,C.C.I.E.tC.C.y.0...I.3,C.,,        of Trade.Permanent Under Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Sir a,L.Barstowt K.C.B., controller of Supply Services, Treasury.Mr. H.F.Carllll, Assistant SecretaryBoard of Trade.Lieut.-Colonel Sir M.P.A.hankey, G.C.B.,.............. Secretary.Mr. Pembroke Wicks...........................Assistant Secretary.
(1)       With reference to Cabinet IS (1919), conclusion 18,the Conference had under consideration the situation inrelation to the proposed Anglo-French Oil agreement, which,had been repeatedly under discussion between the Frenchand British Governments,It Fas explained that there   as no objection to theproposed assignment of a percentage share of the interestin the oilfields of Mesopotamia to the French Government,but that nothing should be done which would result inthe transfer of the interests Ln the oil wells ofMesopotamia to joint Stock Companies.    It was Suggestedthat the oil resources of Mesopotamia were sc extensivethat sufficient revenue should be forthcoming from themto pay for the whole administration of the country, andthat for that reason private exploitation should be prevented.    It was further explained that the war office had started to eurvey the oilfields of Mesopotamia andhad also begun their survey of the desert &quot;for the purposeof advising on the practicability of having a pipe andra11way line through the British sphere of influence.The Foreign Office had intervened on account of thedifficulties v-hlch they felt would be raised on accountof tho exclusion of the Sta dard Oil Company of America.It was pointed out.that,inasmuch as the country was inBritish occupation and tho &quot;hole expense of the campaignhad fallen on the British Government the Standard oil company had no locus, stand! and no reason for complaint.The Coherence were of opinion that as a matter ofprinciple the profits arising from the exploitation of the oilfields   cf Mesopotamia should accrue for tho benefit ofthe State rather than for the benefit of Joint StockCompanies and decided.:-
(i)   That the War Office should proceed withthe survey of the Mesopotamia.! oilfieldsbut that all prospecting must be doneon behalf of the State and hot  or thebenefit of private Companies&apos;, and shouldbe undertaken in such a way. as to attractas little attention ae possible.(11)   That.the War Office should proceed withthe survey of the desert v;ith a view toadvising as to a pipe and railway&quot; linethrough the British sphere of influence.OIL IN (2) Attention waa called to the Persian oilfields whichPERSIA.It was.- stated were proved to bo very rich and ,were notworked to anything like their full capacity.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,,23rd January 1920*

</content>
</cab>
