<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/37/0 images: 180-184</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TEE PROPERTY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJ55TYT 3 GO vERNMBNT h ^ ^SECRET.CONCLUSIONS of a Conference of ministers held at 10, Downing Street   S.W., onMonday, February 9th, 1980 at 12 noon.PRESENTTHE PRIME MINISTER (in tho Chair).e Eight Hon.A*Bonar Law, M.P.,ord Privy Seal. &apos;e Right .HomA0Chaiaberlain, M.P.,sellor of the Exchequer.e Eight Eon-W.S.churchill, M.P.,aoretary of State for War &amp; Air.eEight HocuSlr E.Geddes, G.CB.,,B.E., M.P., Minister of Transport,e Right Hon.Sir A.c geddes, H.C.B..S.2., President, Board of Trade.The Right Hon.A. J*Balf our, SUM., M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon.the Earl Curzon ofKealaston, &amp;.C.3.I., G.C.I.B.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon.-.if. Long, M.P.. FirstLord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Sir Robert Home,K.C., K.P,i Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.H.A.L.Fisher   M.B.-,President, Board, of Education.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT 4-jLstanley Baldsrin, M.P.^financial Secretary, Treasury.p.P.B.Blacfcettt C.B., Con-jroller of Finance, Treasury.,e Right   Hon.the Earl Derby,:.(?., G.O.V.O., C.B., BritishImbassador, Prance.Captain Hon.Frederick Guest, C.B.E.,D.S.O.&apos;, M. P., Joint parliamentary secretary, Treasury.The right Hon.Lord Edmund Talbot,G.C.Y.O., D.S.O., M.P., joint parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.lout.-Col.Sir M.P*A.Hankey, G-.C.B...........................Secretary.Iptain L.F.Burgis.................................Assistant Secretary.Bent.-Col.L.Storr, C.B............................Assistant Secretary.I.F,JSLJ.eith Ross..................................Assistant Secretary-
ItLpplementaryEstimates.(a)(b)note on Accountor the Army.The rebate on the Address should probablylast the whole of the present week, and perhaps longer.The Supplementary Estimates (more than52 in number) were practically ready,and included three Votes which wouldrequire discussion:-(i) Coal Deficiency,(ii) Bread Subsidy,(iii) Cost of the strike,the last being taken by the Home Secretarycn the understanding that the several ministers responsible for the expenditure would be present to defend it.It was felt, however, that much time would, be wasted if the supplementary estimates were the first business taken after the Address, and. that it would bebetter to defer them till the Vote onAccount for the Army could be taken.It was provisionally agreed that theSecretary of State for War should, beprepared, to intrcrace the Vote on Account,if necessary,  on Thursday, Pebruary 19.(c)Debat eit.onThe Coal Mines! (Emergency)Pill.Merchant ShippingAmendment Bill.Pill for the Ratif1-[cation of the Austrian treaty.Phe Coinage Bill.Between the conclusion of thethe Address and the Vote on Account i&quot;orthe Army, the time should be devoted tos&amp;me or all of the following Bills,which, if not ready,  should be completed at an early date:-The Coal Mines (Emergency) Bill(       Board of Trade - dealing only with the finance of Coal Minesduring the past :;rear, subject to&apos;enquiry as to the necessity for aUinanciai Resolution.The Merchant Shipping Amendment Bill(Board, of Trade   has already passed the Home Affairs Committee):The Bill for the Ratification of theAustrian Treaty (Poreigii Office):The Coinage Bill (Treasury   under theTen Minutes Rule):l^be War Emergenciesfill.The War Emergencies Bill:as well as to the Supplementary Estimates(if their introduction was required).HliIA WEflTFARYfl) The Conferenoe discussed the question of ParliamentaryffSBJSSS.Business during the oarly days of the Parliamentary Session,and agreed that the programme shouild be drawn up on thefollowing data:-
I17Introduction&apos;f Bills.Government ofIreland Bill.Electricity Bill, (f)48-Hours Bill.      (g)Minimum Wage Bill.UnemploymentInsurance Bill.The Leader of the House of Lords(Lord Curaon) undertook to make enquiries as to the probable attitude of the House of Lordstowards the Electricity Bill,  witha view to its introduction in thefirst instance in that Hoixse if itappeared proi*able that it would begiven a fair reception.With a view to the re-introductionof the 48-Hours Bill next week.Par Emergencies (h)Pill.(i) the question ox includingagricultural labour within theprovisions of the Bill shouldbe left for decision to  The Minister of Labour,The Minister of Agriculture,The Secretary for Scotland:(ii) Subject to the concurrence of.the Chief Secretary, the Billshould not bs made applicableto Ireland,Subject to the settlement of these points, the Second Reading of theBill shoiild. be taken as soon aspossible.The Unemployment Insurance and MimumumWage Bills were deferred pending further discussion by the Minister of Labour withthe interests concerned;The War J&amp;emergency Bill, which was carried over from        last Session, should get SecondReading next week.jpepeal   ofHome Rule ActAgriculturalPillshould(i) The question / be considered of introducing a Bill to repeal the Home Rule Act   whichautomatically comas into force on the conclusionof    .eace with Turkey.shouldii) The Minister of Agriculture /    give noticeof the introduction of the Agriculture Bill(to settle new guaranteed prices.). . eh*uldijnti-Luraping        (k) The Anti-dumping Bill  / be deferred pendingreports of the two Parliamentary Committees -which were now considering it,shouldliquor Control     (1) The following Bills-/ be reserved until thefi11&quot; Cabinet have had time to consider them:-eform of thepse of Lords6 coal Mines Bill,(d) The Ministers at the heads of theDepartments concerned should he responsible that any necessary action is taken to give noticeof and-introduce the above Bills.(e) The Prime Minister should give notice to-morrow that he would askleave to introduce the Governmentof Ireland Bill at an early date.
VJ--- of Lords*The Liquor Control Bill:Reform of the House of Lords:The Coal Mines Bill.(na) The Leader of the House ofauthorised to state, shoulbe raised, that it was the of the Government, asin the King&apos;s Speech, to sposals for.the Reform of tof Lords, put that it wasto say more as to the natuproposals than that the retions of the&apos;Bryoe Committcarefully considered.Lords wasd the questioninton-announcedubmit pro-he Hou seprematurere of these,commenda-ee would belCKSS OFLAWS OS1e Kaiser,(2) With reference to Cabinet 9 (20), Conclusions 1 tn.dS, as matters of urgency, in view of the forthcoming Inter-Allied Conference in London, the questions of war criminalsand of. the Kaiser were very briefly discussed at the end ofthe meeting. On the former question the following alterna-tive px oposale were considered:-(a) An Inter-Allied Tribunal, as at presentsuggested:fb) A Court, composed exclusively of GermanJudges, to be held at Leipzig or someGerman town,(c ) An International Court, to includeGerman Judges, with a Chairman ap-pointed by a neutral country, to sit in Germany;&apos;d) An International Court, to includeGerman Judges, with a neutral Chairman,to sit in the occupied areas of Germany:(e) The French proposal that,  if the Germansrefused to hand over the accused personsnamed in the several Allied lists,  thelatter should be tried in absentia.While no decision was taken, in view of the absenceof the Lord Chancellor, the Conference we&amp;e unanimouslyopposed to the French proposal (e-), and in respect of theother suggestions the general trend of the discussion was infavour of alternative (d), viz.,/that an International court to Include German Judges, with a neutral Chairman, aa ouldsit in the occupied areas of Germany*The Conference agreedThat the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs, in consultation with the LordChancellor, the British Ambassador inParis, and the Attorney-Gene ral, should .prepare, for the consideration of theCabinet --
(i) An alternative xffarposal in regard. to the persons aceueed of breaches of the laws of war; &apos;(ii) An alternative to the Prench draftlW reply to. the Netherlands Governmentin reaps at of the Zaiser.IeATY OP (3)   With reference to Cabinet 8 (20),  Conclusion 8. theiACE with british Ambassador in Paris reported that it was M. l^lXaxandT1iBKEYiintention not to remain in London after the end of the week.He himself had not felt justified in warning M/. Millerand of-     the necessity Which might be imposed upon the British Govern-me?.t of making separate arrangements with Turkey,  since this-appeared to him to c&amp;nstitute a bre.ach tf the Pact of London,by which Great Britain, Prance,  Italy and Russia bound them-selves,  inter.alia, not to put forward peace conditions wiih-.sut previous agreement with each of the other Allies.In view of the great and growing urgency ef obtaining a settlement of theTurkish question. -The Secretary of State for Pc reign affairs was authorised at once .to warn the french ambassador in London of the necessity.which   might be forced upon the^ BritishGovernment (If the Prench Governmentwculd/sgree to press on with theTurkish Treaty) 5f   making their own arrangements for peace with Tu&apos;xkey0&apos;   -   &apos; &apos; : &apos; &quot;.        &apos; &apos;   &apos; - - &apos; - &apos; -It was generally felt that, should the British Govern-.....     . &apos; . ...meat feel impelled reluctantly to. take this line,  italy would almost certainly follow suit.PSH POLICY     (4)     With reference to Cabinet 7 (20), Conclusion 1,fpblA.before the Conference broke up there was a short discussionen British policy In Russia......Whitehall Gardens, B.W.1,Pebruary 9, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
