<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/37/0 images: 200-209</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IfSjS document is thb property of his br^tq^nnio majesty&apos;S government) .S EC RE T.Copy No.CONCLUSIONS of a Conference held at 10Downing Street, S.W.  on TUESDAY, MARCH16 oh, 1920 at 12 Noon.PRESENT:The Prime Ministerfhe Rt. Hon. A.Bonar Law, ample. ,Lord Privy Seal,fhe Rt. Hon. E.Shortt, K,,C.,M.P,Secretary of State for HomeAffairsfoe Rt. Hon. V/Long, MFirst Lord of the Admiralty.The Rt. Hon. R. Mmiro, K.C. ,M..PaSecretary for Scotland.She, Rt, Hon. Sir Robert Home,[.B.E. ,.K.C ,M.&apos;?a, Minister ofLabour.(in the Chair)The Rt. Hon.. A,Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer..The Rt. Hon. W.SC.Churchill, M,P,Secretary of State for War &amp; Air.The Rt. Hon. J.VIiMaopherson, SAG.,M.P.,Chief Secretary for Ireland.The Rt. Hon. C. Addison, M.P. ,Minister of Healta.The Rt.  Hon. H,A-,1-Fisher, MoP. ,President, Board of Education.The following were jAiso present:-She Rt. Hon. Sir A. Moxid, Bart. ,M.P.     The Rt. Hon. Sir J, Mac lay, Bart. ,first Commissioner of Dorics. Shipping Controller.The Rt. Hon. Sir L. Worthing ton The Rt. Hon... The Lord Inverforth,Brans, Bart., M.P., Minister of Minister of Munitions. jPensions.Sir J.C.G.Sy)ces, KACB., Secretary,Hr. C.A,McCurdy, K.C,M.P. Liquor Control Board.Parliamentary Secretary, Ministryof Food. Mr. F.G0Kellaway, M,P., parliamentary secretary, Ministry of Munitions.*he Rt. Hon. The Earl of Lytton,CiviD Lord, Admiralty. Mr, 0.   Nightman, Ministry of Food.^eutanant-Colonel Sir M.P.AJIamcey, G.C.B. ,..................Secretary.b. leith Ross *.................................Assistant Secretary.Thomas Jones....................................-Assistant Secretary-faptain L.F.Burgis................................. * .Assistant Secretary.ltr* T. St.Quintin Hill...............................Assistant Secretary,
198 ifGRAVITY     (X)   With reference to Cabinet li* (20), Conclusion fci,tho Conference had before them a Memorandum by theParliamentary Seorotary to the Ministry of Pood (paper cp.-848) and a Memorandum by the President of the Boardof Education (Paper CP.-858). calling attention to thedifficulties in which oertain brewers of high gravitybeers found themselves when trying to adjust theiraverage to the permitted individual average gravity of 10440.      Since the restriction on tho output n-* beerhad been abolished, the system of Transfer Certificatesarranged by the Ministry of Pood had disappeared, and unless the Government provided some way of escape the brewers were confronted with the necessity of brewinglar. e quantities of low-grade beer, which was unsaleable.The Ministry of Pood suggested that a system of pooling(a re-adjustment of the system which prevailed duringthe period of strict control) should be sanctioned, andit was stated for the Liquor Control Board that thearrangement proposed did not appear to be a real infringe-ment of the undertaking which the Government had givento maintain restrictions pending tho introduction ofthe Liquor Regulation Bill.     Tha proposed arrangement would not result in raising the strength of the beerbrewed by the high gravity brewers..   The Conference decided  (a) To adopt a system of pooling, under whicha brewer of high gravity beer and a brewerof low gravity beer would pool their gravityin accordance with a licence to bo issued bythe Pood Controller, In order to secure thattho average gravity of the two brewers wouldnot exceed in the aggregate 1044oj(b)    That the above decision was not to be oon-*        atrued as In any way departing from theright of tho Government to continue toregulate gravities.J3H LAND (2)   V/ith reforonoe to Cabinet 12 (20), Conclusion 5, theConference had oefore them a Memorandum by the Chief Secre-tary for Ireland (Paper CP,849) calling attention to the promise which had been given in the House of Commons tointroduoe a Bill for the completion of land purchase InIreland at the/
same time as the introduction of the Home Rule Bill.A suggestion wa^ made that the Land Purchase Billshould be based on the lines put forward by the Irish Con-vention, but the Conference agreed with the previous decisionof the Cabinet, which limited the gift of annuities to 3,600,000.The Conference appointed the following committee to prepare a Draft Bill forgiving effect to the Cabinet1s decision(Cabinet 12 (20), Conclusion 5):-The First Lord of the Admiralty (in the Chair),The Minister of Pensions,The Secretary of State for Home Affairs,The Chief Secretary for Ireland,The Law Officers of the Crown,Mr Pembroke Wicks (Secretary),LA.tion AND       (3) The Conference had before them correspondence whichSS OF IN-DUAL citizen-     had passed between the Chancellor of the Exchequer andLord Sumner,   the Chairman of the London Reparation Commit-tee,  together with a Memorandum by Sir Warren Fisher,  thePermanent Secretary to the Treasury, dealing with claims onaccount of losses suffered by private individuals in connec-tion with the War (Paper CP.-798).It was explained that,  in the opinion of Lord Sumner,the private individual had no claim directly on Germany for damage to civilian life and property caused by acts of war,but that the losses and sufferings of such individuals formed the subject-matter of a claim by the British Government as constituting a wrong to the State and not as private mattersor wrongs; further,  individuals had no claim in law on theBritish Government for anything it might receive from germany in respect of such claims; anything granted by the Governmentto the sufferer would thus be entirely a matter of grace.It was pointed out that, unless this view were maintained, the Government would be involved in innumerablecomplications of a most embarrassing description.The Conference gave their general approval to thefollowing recommendations made by the Chancellor &quot;of theExchequer:- -2-
(a) Ho legal claim by private individualsagainst the reparation monies to beadmitted, but any payments made to themto be as an act of grace on the part ofthe Government:(b) A lump sum of, say,  5,000,000 to be set aside out of the first receipts of repara-tion. monies allocated to the Exchequer ofthe United Kingdom (after payment of theoost of the Armies of Occupation) to create a fund out of which payments will be madeto individuals who have a moral claim to compensation;(c) A Commission to be appointed to examineclaims and to LJdee awards out of this fund,proceeding on the basis of the strength ofthe claim rather than on the amount for whichit was admitted by the Reparation Commission.BOISE OF   (4]l     Ihe Conference had before them a memorandum byHIDING-US IE        the Shipping Controller (C.P.668) drawing attention tothe right   of the Allies under the I-eaoe Ti&apos;treaty torequire Germany to build Merchant ofeips to an amountnot exceeding 200,000-tons gross in each of the fiveyears after the Treaty comes into force.     The decisions with regard to the first two years was required b^ theTreaty to be notified to the German Government before april 10th 19S0.      It was therefore suggested that theBritish representative on the Aeparation commission should be instructed to state that the British government proposes to exercise its share of these rights whichwould amount probably to 150,000 tons gross in each ofthe two years.     The vessels it was suggested should consist of Tankers, for vhich there was a great demand at present.Three guiding considerations emerged from thediscussion on the shipping Controller^ proposals:-Firstly the Conference were informed that theFrench press were conducting an unprecedentedly virulentoampaign against the United Kingdom on the ground thatthe xreaty vas framed for the benefit
of this country and directed against the  interest ofFrance.      The particular ground of complaint in theFrench press was the division, of German Shipping underthe Treaty.      It would be most desirable that steps should be taken by the British Government tobring the true facts to the knowledge of the french people in order that the press campaign in france might be countered.secondly it was alleged that as the congestion in transport in this country was relieved and conditionsbecame normal, there would be a surplus of shipping anda consequent collapse in shipbuilding.     While their ownyards Were idle British shipbuilders would see Germanyards busily engaged, not only in reconstructing theGerman Navy and the German Mercantile Marine but(if the present proposals were adopted) in buildingships at the order   of the British Government.     this could not but create a very bitter feeling.Thirdly it appeared to be doubtful wwhether a cash payment would not have to be made to theReparation Commission for the value of the ships.
in thie conn^rtA/ru ohe CoiaJ^e-r-erior Tere informedthat the British representation/e on the Reparation commission had been consulted on the qixestion whether,  if germany were required to build ships for the United Kingdom underthe Peace Treaty,  thin country would be liable to pay theircash value to the Reparation Commission;    and he had repliedthat, while the United Kingdom was becoming liable, to thereparation pool for a very considerable immediate sum inrespect of our share cf the existing German tonnage, the deliveries in kind to the other Powers seemed likely to fallvery seriously behind what was contemplated by the Treaty.It was probable, therefore, that,  on an early balance struckfor the purpose of Article 837 of the Treaty, the UnitedKingdom, would be^ somewhat heavy debtor   and might -find&apos; itdifficult to avoid having to provide cash for the cost or armies of Occupation and approved supplies of food and raw   &quot;materials,  and for the Belgian priority payments, if the cash assets of the reparation fund proved to be insufficient to cover these prior charges.    There was little doubt thatthe United Kingdom would,  for the time being,  have to take its share of the cost of Armies of Occupation in the form -of ships&apos;,    and if new ships as well as existing ships were taken we should probably put ourselves in t.he posxtxon otdebtors to the reparation fund over and above the amount ofour credit in respect of our own Armie-s^of Occupation, andwould run considerable risk of having to pay the value ofthe new ships in cash to provide money for the other allied armies of Occupation,  for food supplies and raw materials,and for the Belgian.priority.*As regards the  camoai-n in the Prench Press,  it was stated that the &apos;Prench wAr-e always difficult tc satisfy.
Moreover,  if the United Kingdom did not assert  its claim in this particular instance, the other Allies would doubtlessclaim the whole 200,000 tons of shipping involved each year;and if we were eventually to forego our just claims in anyway in favour of the French it would be preferable to do soin a manner which would reflect on us the greatest possibleoredit,  and not merely to allow our claims to lapse byreason of their not being pressed.As regards the shipbuilding position in this  country,while in five years&apos; time it might well be that British yardswould not have enough orders, those yards were generally fullup with orders for the next two years at least ,  and at themoment it was only proposed that the claim to the GermanGovernment should be made for a period of two years and thatthe Germans should be required to build oil tonnage, whiehwas extremely scarce and the value of which at the moment was about  60 a ton:.The Conference accordingly agreed.:-(a) That the British representative on the ReparationCommission should be informed by the Treasury thatHis Majesty5s Government  intended to exercise their share of the rights under the Peace Treaty to requireGermany to build merchant ships to an amount notexceeding 200,000 tons gross in eaoh of the two yearssucceeding April 10,  1920:(b) That while the claims of His Majesty&apos;s Government inthis respect should be stated.,  Bteps should net betaken actively to enforce it, but that it should beheld in reserve as a bargaining factor:( as) That the Shipping Controller should prepare, with aview to publication iv&amp; the press, a statement show-ing the actual situation in regard to the division,of German shipping amongst the Allies.(Note: This statement appeared in the &quot;Daily Telegraph-on&quot;&quot;the 17th March, 1926) .dJRE OP (5)    With reference to Conclusion 4 of a Conference held^MINISTRYJ MUNITIONS. on December 9i 19191 the Conference had under aonsidsrat iona Memorandum by the Minister of Munitions on the Future of woolwich Arsenal (Paper CP.. 372), and Memoranda by theFirst Lord of the Admiralty (Paper C..P.616), the Secretaryof State for War (Paper CP.  657),  the Secretary of State
for Air (Paper C.P.-764), together with a Memorandum, by th*&apos;Deoutv Miniate- of Munitions (Paper CP.-81.0) regarding^SMlforf&apos; i&apos;^ii^^nL^M^n&amp;am fey ^e First  Com-It was explained to the Conference that, in accord-anee with the decision of. the Cabinet Conference on December&apos;9th. the Fighting Departments had furnished to the Ministerof Munitions lists of articles which might be the subjectof eomruon ourchase and manufacture.    The Fighting Depart-ments, however, had come to the conclusion that it wouldbe better to create a Joint Committee to regulate government purchases,  since stocks would haTre to be held by the using-Departments,  and this would involve a duplication both of    &quot; .stocks and of inspectorate.    It was urged that during atime of peace the existence of a Ministry of Supply was unnecessary, although it was admitted that such a ministry was essential during a great war,in order to preventcompetition between Departments for material and labour.Moreover, in the case of the Navy, questions of disciplinewere involved,  and no Board of Adrairal+y would- it was alleged, be responsible for naval discipline if theywere not also charged-with the responsibility for the inspection and loading on board ship of articles such asexplosives.On the other hand it was urged that the experienceof the War had shown that a Committee would be an ineffect-ive method of co-ordinating the activities  of the War.Departments.    The pre-war system meant a duplication of -machinery,  and during the War, before the creation ofthe Ministry of Munitions,  the same factories wereinspected by officials of the Admiralty and the ?farOffice..    There were many instances of competition betweenthe Admiralty and the War Office in the.same factory.The result was the raising of prices and duplication of inspection and of ordinary staff.    It was quite possibleto provide for special brands of explosives,  as had been  ,
done in the ease of the sr^iaO^cojPdlte r^qaxjlre-d by theAdmiralty for warships.   (?ne great advantage of central control of purchase was that it enabled a scientific costsystem to be created^ which would result, in an enormoussaving.It was pointed out t* the Conference that a compromisewould be no settlement of the question, and that a decision was required between the old system and the system adoptedduring the War* which united the purchases of the FightingDepartments under the control of one Office.    If there wasto be a Ministry of Supply, all the benefits accruing fromits establishment would be lost unless the -ordering of every kind of article required by the Fighting Departments  except those required for purely experimental purposeswas transferred to it.The case of Woolwich Arsenal was referred to as being an extreme instance of the necessity of oo-ordination between.the Fighting Departments&apos;.    It had been impossible to take any steps to improve the situation at Woolwich because many of01 the Arsenalthe Departments/were not under the control of the Ministry ofMunitions but still remained with the Admiralty or the WarOffice.   Thus, in the 3ame place; there were five founders&apos;shops, three blacksmiths&apos; shops, four printing ^establishments,etc.    Some solution of the difficulties at Woolwich was urgently required in order to prevent, repetition of thescenes which occurred when the 10,030 men discharged frwnWoolwich recently visited London.The Conference accordingly decided  (a) That the First Commissioner of Works andPublic Buildings should, as soon as pos-* sible, convene a Conference of representa-tives of the three Service Departments.,the Ministry of Munitions and the Treasury,With a view&apos; to formulating a scheme for thefuture management of Woolwich Arsenal (on   ,the assumption that a Ministry of supply would not necessarily be created), theproposals of the Conference to be consideredby a further Cabinet Conference to be heldon Tuesday, March s3, 1930:(b) That the general question of the creationof a Ministry of Supply should be re-considered
when the proposals of the Conferencein regard to the partAjCiilar case of woolwich (referred to in (a) above)were before the Cabinet Conference..2-v- Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.1,March 16,  1920.

</content>
</cab>
