<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/37/0 images: 342-350</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONCLUSIONS of. r, Conference of TTinlstorsheld. at 10 Downing Strnot, . S, -onTtONiDAY, July 26th, 1920 at 11. 30   a..m.PRE S. E N Ti-Tho Prime Kinietor.&apos;    - ( in the. Chair&quot;)Ri^ht Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.Privy Seal;g&apos;Right Hon.A. Chamberlain, 1.1.P.-ice Ho r of the Exchequer.ic Right Hon. The Earl Curzon ofidlcston, K..G. ,G.C.S,I. ,G.C.I;E.,Rotary- of State for Foreignffairs.ie Right Hon. I.S.Churchill,ftj, Secretary of State for &apos;7ar.Air.le Right Hon. Six H^mnr Grecrrrood,irt., K.C., K.P., Chief Secretary\r$ Ireland.to Right Hon. H.A.L.Fisher, K.P.,Gsidont, Board of Education.The Right Hon.. A.J.Balfour, 0..H.,II.P., Lord president of theXounooJL.The Right Ron.E..Shortt, E. C. ,H,P&apos;. ,Secretary of State for Homo Affairs.The Right Hon. S.3. Montagu, M.p. ,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. V. Long, IS.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Robert Home,G.B.E, ,K.C, K.P., President, Boardof Trade.&quot;&apos;The Ri ht Hon, Sir !Hrio Geddes,G.C.B. ,G.B.E.,r.P. , Minister ofTrar**port.The Right Hon.Sir L,^orthington-Evans,Bart.,M,P.THE FOLLOWING &apos;7ER3 ALSO PRESENT: -Hncl Sir James Craig, Bart.,P., Parliamentary and Financialcretnry, Admiralty,ior Conclusions 4 &amp; $) .&apos;7...C.Briagcman, K.P. parliamentarycrctary, Board of Trade,or Conclusion 1.)Ja.R.Duncan^ Oonl Controller.H Conclusion 1.The Right Hon.Denis S,Honry, K.C.,M.P., Attorney-General for Ireland...( for. Conclusions 4 &amp; 5*)The. Right Hon.Sir John Anderson,-TC.C.B., Joint Under Secretary for ireland.(for Conclusions 4 &amp; 5).^Thonas Jones -., . .    &apos;-&apos;.&apos;*i.-. v............... V-... A meeting Soertvtary,p  ln 1&apos;P.Burgis . ,.       ..... *.. ...,............. Assistant secretary i&apos; ^cbrokc -/icks &apos;    &quot; &quot;        --------* m V ,w -6- A- V * o  *      j*................. Assistant S^cr-^tery,4 St.      Hill . w.. Assistant Secretary.
THE MINERS&apos; CLAIMS

(1)The Conference had under consideration a Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade (Paper C.P.-1652) in which the Cabinet were recommended to refuse the claims of the miners that the price of domestic coal should be reduced by 14s. 2d. a ton and that an increase should be granted in the wages of miners of 2/- per shift. A meeting between the President of the Board of Trade and the Miners&apos; Representatives had been arranged to take place that afternoon, and a decision of policy was therefore urgently required.

It was explained that the total cost of the miners&apos; proposals would be £63,000,000 per annum, and the miners argued that this should be met out of the profit of £66,000,000 on the price of exported coal.

It was pointed out that since the Sankey Award wages increases had more than compensated for the advance in the cost of living, but in addition to this the miners derived a considerable advantage in getting their coal either for nothing or at a privileged price. Moreover, the miners had received larger advances since 1914 than any other trade except builders and railwaymen. TO accede to their claims would amount to ever-ruling the decision of the Industrial Court upon the recent claim of the engineers, and would inevitably be followed by a new wage cycle. On the other hand, the Government were in a better position to meet a strike at the present moment than they had been throughout the War. The Railway, Gas and Electrical Companies, had sufficient stocks to keep in full running for six weeks. It was doubtful whether the miners in fact intended to strike, but on the assumption that they would do so the Government had a very good case to put to the public. In the view of the Board of Trade, the profits on the export of coal should be handed over to the Exchequer. The coal trade was the only one 
in respect of which no Excess Profits Duty was paid, since in point of fact all the profits in the coal trade up to the present time had been used to subsidise the British consumer It was estimated that if control were removed and prices allowed to assume their economic level, there would be a contribution to the Exchequer, in the form of Excess Profits Duty, of £110,000,000 on a conservative estimate, and it was therefore only right that the profit on exported coal (£66,000,000) should be handed over to the Treasury.

The Conference agreed:-

To authorise the President of the Board of Trade to refuse the miners&apos;  claims.

?RATION. ... ?Coming ?ting at ?eva

(2) The Conference had Under consideration the represent?tion of the British Government at the forthcoming meeting which was to take place at Geneva to discuss reparation with the Germans.

It was agreed:-

That the British Government should be represented by : -

The Chancellor of the Exchequer, Sir Laming Worthington Evans, Lord D&apos;Abernon.

Some discussion took place on a suggestion that the meeting with the Germans should be attended by the Reparation Commission. It was pointed out that the latter being a judicial body it would be a matter of some embarrassment if they were formally brought into the negotiations as a corporate body.

It was agreed:-

That it was undesirable that the Reparation Commission should attend the negotiations with the German experts, and that it was preferable that the Allied representatives should prepare their own recommendations on the German proposals, and submit them to the Reparation Commission for examination.

?USSIA. ... ? Negotiations with the ?vict Government.

(3) The Conference had under consideration Foreign Office Telegram No. 170 dated 24th July from the Soviet Government at Moscow, from which it appeared that the Soviet Government had reversed their previous decision and were prepared to come t?


London to discuss,   with repzvTsirntortJLvcm? of ihe lca^lng^PcrraTB.of ths Entente, a&quot; general basis of&quot; peace ootrween hussia&quot; andthe other Powers which participate in hostile aci-ons against their, or support such.&quot;(a)    ^he Conference agredd:-(i)    The draft of a reply we 1 coning thedecision of tho Soviet Government toenter into peace negotiations inLondon, end concurred in the proposal that the Prime Minister and the Secretaryof State for Fbheign Affairs should proceedto Boulogne to discuss the matter with M.Millorand on the following day:(ii)    That tho Prime Minister should be accompanied by Sir Laming Torthington Evans,for the purpose of d.iscussing tho Goalquestion with the Prench Government.(iii)    Tho Secretary of State for Foreign affairs undertook to forward copies of the reply totho Soviet Government ,to the Governments off inland, Roumania, and Gzecho-Slovakia.(b) The Conference agreed:-That the Prime Minister should see therepresent at ivc in London of GeneralWrangol, end explain to him that we didnot approve of the offensive undertaken by General Transcl j that once the Ami stieswas concluded with the Poles his positionwould be extremely precarious, and thrt  intho opinion of His Majostyls Government,General, wrangol should, on grounds of humanity, not reject the offer of tho SovietGovernment.
REFUSAL OF IRISH RAILWAYMEN TO GARRY POLICE, ETC.

(4) With reference to the Conference of Ministers held on Friday 23rd July l920, the Conference had before them a Memorandum by the Chief Secretary for Ireland (C,P.1657), together with a Note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer (C.P.1671), relating to the refusal of Irish Railwaymen  to carry soldiers, police and munitions on the railways.

It was stated that traffic had been tendered to the railways in the ordinary course and as a result of the refusal of a number of railwaymen to work the trains, a certain number of men had been dismissed: this had resulted in partial dislocation. The matter had been brought to a head by a letter written by the Chairman of the Great Northern Railway Company to the Chief Secretary(attached as Appendix to C.?. 1?57), in which it was stated that the company protested against an indefinite continuance of the existing state of affairs and suggesting that tho Government should formally intimate to the Irish railways that they (the Government) could not continue to contribute to the wages of men who refused to handle military traffic and that the companies must obtain an under-standing from their men to work all traffic and to give notice to terminate the services of such men as refused.

It was stated that the suggestion of the railway companies would entail negotiation with the leaders of the men and that the leaders would have to answer for tho men as to whether they wore willing to undertake the working of trains on which military or police etc., were on board, and it was suggested that affairs might be more quickly brought to an issue if it could be arranged for a whole serias of trains to/
to have either police, munitions or troops on board, and then if the railwaymen refused to work the trains they should be instantly dismissed.

The Conferenced agreed --

That the Minister of Transport in consultation with the Chief Secretary should send a letter to the Irish Railways, making it clear that any refusal to ?arry Government traffic was to be vigorously dealt with.

ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE IN IRELAND

(?) With reference to Cabinet 31(20) Conclusion 2(a)the Conference had before them a Memorandum by the Chief Secretary covering a draft Bill providing for the immediate extension of tho jurisdiction of courts martial in Ireland (C.P.1682) superseding the Draft Criminal Justice Administration (Iceland) Bi11 (C.P.1?37). It was stated that the object of the former was to bring all criminal offences under the jurisdiction of a court martial. It was ? proposed to supersede the ordinary courts Which would continue their functions, but the Bill ?power to bring all criminal offences under a court martial established by law and gave it power to impose the death penalty.

It was stated that courts martial were now functioning every day in Irsland and were not unsuccessful, but the Defence of the Realm Act under which they worked did not allow the inclusion of all criminal offences within their jurisdiction. A suggestion was made that while it was necessary to substitute some instrument to take  the place of the present jury system in Ireland, obtainable by using the machinery of the Defence of the Realm Act, yet it was a decision of the gravest moment to utilize machinery intended for time of war in time of peace, and considerable/

anxiety
was. expressed at thus ..h&amp;ttdiJog^&apos;&apos;^of the law to soldiers fIt was pointed out; however, that under the prcpo-sedBill the-discreticn af setting up a court martial was underthe authority of the Lord Lieutenant, though the composition-ofa couriimartial would he decided upon by the--Ct:vrmander^lhi&apos;.&apos;Cliiel?or other competent military a\rth-:rity.It was stated that whilst come advantage might heobtained in the Lord Lieutenant having to decide in whatdistrict a cnurtmartial shculd be formally declared, yetit was net clear from the proposed. Bill that shch a proceedingwould only be made use of ir the disturbed areas.    Further, in vie?,of the extreme step suggested of handing over the whole adminls-tratlon of justice to the military it might be better to associatein some form or another a competent civilian legal expertwith this military jurisdictionsGen^nval^agr-e-ement &quot;ws-s-- expressed with this view and itwas thought-that the Army (Courts of Enquiry) Act- 191.6    affordedi na suitable precedent,      This Act ehabled/all trials in which a civilian was Involved for a legal civilian expert to be associatedwith the Military administration of the law.    It was suggestedthat it might be desirable ta have available a small panel ofsuch experts who could he drawn upon by the President zf acourt martial in any district te assist him in administering thelaw.The Conference were informed that the Criminal Injuries(Ireland) Bill (CP, 1590), providing for the interception ofmonies payable to Irish local authorities and the use of suchmonies in compensation for criminal injuries had been introduced
into the House pf-Oommons. and that ewry**3pubI4^^had been .notifJLed that no public--money would be paid tothem unless they agreed to accept the audit of theIrish Local Government Board   and by statutory Rulesft&amp;&amp; Regulations, Payments- due in resiiect- of old Age Pensions,however, would not be withheld on the groundthat they were to be used for compensating crixoina&quot;!  injuries,but it was desirable that they should be stopped in viewof the frequent robberies which had taken place, and onthe ground that the cessation of the railways would render the transmission of money difficult.It was pointed out that with the limited time avail-able and for Parliamentary reasons it was most desirablethat any government.,measures affecting Ireland should be dealtwith as shortly as possible and in one Bill, and it wassuggested that use should be made of the system of orders in Council so that the Bill in question would merely give general powers, and all details would be dealt with by orders in Council.   It would then be possible to include in one com-prehen^w Bill the provisions of the Criminal Injuries(Ireland) Bill (CP.1590), of the draft Bill attached tothe Memorandum by the Chief Secretary for Ireland (CP.1682),and the further powers which were now desired by the irish executive, such as the power tc change the venue of a trialfrom Ireland to England.The Conference agreed :-(1)    That the Chief Secretary for Ireland shouldtake steps to withdraw the Criminal Injuries(Ireland) Bill (CP. 1590) from the House ofCommons;(2)    That the Chief Secretary for Ireland should draft a new Bill relating to Ireland? this bill to be as brief as possible and toprovide&apos; for(a)    the extension in Ireland of theDefence of the Realm Regulations toall crimes w fch the nrovljo that the punishment&apos; av^ni^ K* the punishmentassigned by tne o*&apos;diriary law.&quot;
(It)-) The enactment hy Order in Oouncilof pro vis ions inoideiitrtCk   to theextension of the jurisdiction of courts martial including the creating of howoffences.,(a) The interception of all grants as.proposed in the Orimin&amp;l Injuries Bill.-(3)     That each Court established to deal witheases triad under the Defence of the realm regulations should contain one oivilian legalmember of experience,  in all cases of a .very grave character which might possibly. involve the death, penalty, / i ,Whitehall Gardens, S.Vy.1.,26th July,.1920.

</content>
</cab>
