<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/37/0 images: 368-375</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1l(^IS.POOMPg.....IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS. BKITANigO MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).36&apos;;.:......* - Final Oqpy. Ho.jJCONCLUSIONS of a Conference of ministers held at 10, Downing Street. S.Y/.1. on Wednesday^September 8th. 1920 at 3 p.m.fEESEH.The Prime Minister       (in the Chair)The Rt. Has, A. Bonar Law,lord Privy Seal.UPi tThe Rt. Hon. Sir Hamar Greenwood,Bart., R.C t M.P., Chief Secretaryfor Ireland.The Rt. Hon. Sir Robert Horns,B.Bt ., K.C., M.P.. President,Board of Trade.The Rt. Hon. H.A.L. Fisher, M. .,President, Board of Education.THE FOLLOWIHG WERE ALSO PRESENT,The Rt. Hon. Lord Hardinge of Penshurst, K.G.,P*C* j        .-.Bt .;. G.C.S.I., G.C.M.G., G.C.X.E.,0.0.Y.X)., I.S.O., Permanent Under Secretary ofS^-ate for Foreign Affairs.pi&amp;utenaat-^colonel Sir LB^U 2unkoy, G.C.B;,  ...........-Secretary.3r* Thojsas Jones, ................... ,Pyinoipal Assistant Secretary&apos;,,W* JoCC. Davidson, ,
(1)  with -:rexex^3e^--ia^^ ixLJ&amp;JZi&amp;b&amp;i^held on September 2nd 1920,IJxS /   the Conference had under consideration certainisSaiEIOH.       reported breaches of the Russian Trade Delegationagreement to abstain from propaganda and other hostile action during their stay in this country.The question was considered as to whether theyshotild be asked to leave,The matter was postponed until the issue of the threatenedminers1- strike had become clearer.
(2)    with reference to Cabinet 49 (20) Conclusion 8,the President of the Board of Trade stated that witha view to removing all possible misunderstandingshe had invited the Sxecutive ox the Miners&apos; federation to meet him at the Board of Trade on the followingmoiuiing.      He proposed tc adhere to the positionhitherto taken up by the Government and to state thatno raiding of the export profits fund would be allowed?that in the interests of the general body of consumersit was preferable that the fund should be paid into theTreasury and in any caSo this question had already beendecided by i-arllament.     On the question of wages hewould state that   in the opinion of the Government no case had been made out for an advance, but that if the minersbelieved that the37 had a good claim it   $ould be submittedto the Industrial Court.      In any event it might be possiblefor the minors to make certain wage adjustments with theowners In the direction of absorbing tho recent flat rate,advance in the tonnage rates and in this way-directlyrelating the recent advances with the output of coal*The Conference approved the course which thoPresident  of. the Board, of Trade proposed to take.
IRISH 3s    Vlth. reference to the Conference of Ministers heldSITUATION,on the 2nd September 1920 it was agreed s-(1)   That the Chief Secretary should takethe necessary steps, through the divisional Commissioner of Policesto organize a force of special constables In w^ms&amp;* ^ci&amp;snei .(2) That the Chief Secretary should appoint an Assistant Under Secretaryfor the six counties of the NorthFast of Ireland,.
qq^XC 4,     The -Conference&quot; wpwroved a draft reply to a telegrampnisourRS.received by the Prime Minister with reference to the eleven untried prisoners in Cork Gaol who were hunger-striking..(Appendix)  &apos;It was agreedThat the reply, together vith particulars. a of each of tho cases, should be issuedby the Irish Office to the Press.
XABOURPSPUTATTOHTO RIGA.5&amp;     The Gonl^erence were informed that a telephonicmessago had been received at the Foreign Office fromMr. v\ Adams on, M.P., asking that he and. Mr. Purcellshould be granted passports to proceed to Riga in orderthat they might hold a watching brief over the peacenegotiations between tho Russians and Poles *     It hadnot been made clear in the nossage whether tho applica-tlon was on behalf of tho Trade Union Congress or onbehalf of the Council of Action, but the conference were informed that a Resolution of the Council of Actionappointing Messrs. Adamson and Pureell to this missionhad appeared In the Press*It was agreed s -That Mr. J*T* Davies should write toMr. Adamson asking that a writtenapplication for passports should be madesetting out the purpose of the mission and by whom It had been anoointed.2 &apos;Whitehall Gardenst 3A;*3optember 8, 1980.
APPENDIX.The Prime MInis-ter has. received the fallowing,telegram.JVom ?Jr P,H.Barry, ex High Sheriff of Go.Cork 4&quot;Prime Minister, 10 Downing Street, London,1 Impress most strongly on you eleven untriedand unconvieied men dying in Cork Gaol.   EvenHr*Bonar Law&apos;s letter in answer to LabourParty&apos;s appeal does not attempt to Justifythe detention of untried and unconvicted men.Issues at stake so far reaching inevitable result of delay disastrous.    immediate action imperative,,&quot;to which the following reply has been senttThe Government have given careful considerationto the appeal contained In your telegram ofSeptember 6th on behalf of the 11 untried prisonersnow on hunger-strike in Cork prison.   These men,all of whom are awaiting trial, were arrestedeither In the act of making murderous attacks upon police or soldiers j or upon direct andclear evidence of complicity in such attacks,or for other very serious offences.   It isclear that they are engaged in a combinedeffort, to make their trials impossible, asall ef them, though arrested on various dates,commenced to hunger-strike simultaneously onthe 11th August.   By tikis means they have reducedthemselves to a physical condition which rendersthera unfit for trial, and the Government are advised that it Is legally Impossible to try them,for the grave offences with which they are changed In their absence or until they arecertified to be fit to undergo trial.   But fortheir refusal to take food they would now all have been tried and would be tried forthwith ifthey consented to take food as soon as theyhad sufficiently recovered.The evidence In such case has received most careful Individual consider at ion *   It Is impossible,for the Government to allow men charged withsuch grave offences to escape trial by their ownact ^   If this were permitted there would be anend to any possibility of the enforcement oflaw and the administration of justice.
A list Is enclosed of the men inquestion and particulars of the offences forwhich they are awaiting: trial.Michael Fitzgerald Is charged with havingmurdered Private Jones at Fermoy on September7th, 1919.    He was arrested In September 1919and at Cork Assizes on July  1st a true bill was found against him, but it vma impossible,owing to the non-attendance of jurors, toproceed with the trial.    In consequence ofhis hunger-strike it was impossible to bringhim before the Court constituted under theauthority of the Restoration of Order inIreland Act.John Power.   qxi the night of the 6th Augusta&quot;mTXl.tary pa&amp;rol from Fethsrd alleges thatit found three men, of whom John Power wasone, lying behind a hedge with two gunsand cartridges from which the shot had beenextracted and replaces  by heavy lead slugs,He is awaiting trial by Court Martial, but his condition at the moment is such that heis not certified as fit for trial.Thomas Monovan, Matthew Reilly, John Crowley,Zertgr QrowTey, Christopher Upton.    OlvThe&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;^night of the 16th July a party 6T Policeentering Ballylanders were heavily fired uponfrom several houses.   A patrol of militaryand police attracted by the firing came totheir assistance, entering the houses fromwhich it is alleged the police were beingfired uponp and arrested several men, oneof whom was seriously wounded.    These menare awaiting trial by Court Martial in con-nectio.i with the occurence.Michael Bur Ice .   Arrested on August 9th undercharge of being found in possession of an    &apos;automatic revolver which had been taken fromConstable Maloney, whc was in company withSgt. Tobin when Tobin v..as murdered.   Burkelives about three miles from the scone of themuruer.    He Is awaiting tri-^l by Court Martial.J oh.. Hennessy.    Arrested on 28 th July andcharged in connection with v.n attack by a party of armed men &apos; n. a detachment of troops in chargeof a military lorry at Inchimore on the 28thJuly last.   The lorry was captured and burned.Joseph Murphy.     Arrested on 15th July andcharged&quot;with Being in possession of a bomb.Awaiting trial by Court Martial.Joseph Kenny.   Arrested on 15th July andcharged wiTiibeing in possession o:  servicerifle and revolver ammunition.   Awaiting trialby Court Martial.

</content>
</cab>
