<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/68/0 images: 68-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fijTilS DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY !S GOVERNMENT)Ie C R E T . Copy No.cabinet    51 (51) .Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10,Downing Street, S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY, 2ndSeptember, 1931, at 11 a.m.AGENDA.1. FINANCE COMMITTEE.(Recommendations to be communicated by theChancellor of the Exchequer).2- REPORT  OF ECONOMY COMMIT TEE.(i) Estimate to be furnished by the Minister ofLabour as to the amount produced by a uniformreduction of 10$ on unemployment benefits.(ii) Housing Subsidies.(Minister of Health to report his definiterecommendations if ready).3. DATE OF THE MEETING OF PARLIAMENT .4. GOVERNMENT ARRANGEMENTS FOR THE DEBATE ON POLICY.5. THE INDIAN ROUND TABLE CONFERENCE.(Reference Cabinet 48 (31) Conclusion 5).(Signed) M.P.A.  HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.1st September,  1931.
, QJ OrpffTg^DQ-CTlMEME  IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT )s BJULJLJL-Copy No.CABINET    51 (31).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY,September 2nd, 1931, at 11 a.m.PRESENT :-The Right Hon. J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister. (In the Chair)&quot;The Right Hon.Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.Sir Herbert Samuel, G.C.B.,G.B.E.,M.P., Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,,G.B.S.,C.Mi&apos;G.,M.P.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.,:UUJ-onel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B.,G.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Reading,G.C.B.,G.C.S.I.,G.C.I.E.,G.C.V.O., Secretary&quot;of Statefor Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs and .Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E.,M.C.,1VI.P.,President of the Board of Trade. 1.M.G.,.............. Secretary.
)autonomy,[employment&apos; juranoe.Jtes of BenefitId FinancialIsition.jbeviousInference:Cabinet 50hi), Con-conclusion  14)Kil.il(^)b.1.   At the outset of the meeting a Memorandumby the Minister of Labour (Paper No, CP. 215 (31)),dealing with rates of benefit and the financialposition, was handed round.The Prime Minister informed the Cabinetthat, since the circulation of this Memorandum,he had discussed the matter with the Minister ofLabour.     The latter had explained the objectionsof the Ministry to working on any rate that wasnot a multiple of 6d.     There were six days inthe working week, and in working out, say, twoor three days&apos; benefit, it was found important tohave a figure that was divisible by two or three.The Prime Minister had then suggested that theyshould try and work to the nearest 3d.     This mightbe accomplished by the preparation of a kind of&quot;ready-reckoner&quot;, to be sent to Labour exchanges and used in them.      The Minister of Labour had accordingly withdrawn the Memorandum which had just been circulated to the Cabinet, and was preparing a fresh Memorandum.      It was hoped that  12-g- millions would be saved by this scheme without touchingchildren.The Cabinet took note that afresh Memoiandum would be circulated in due course.
REPORT.(previous reference:Cabinet 48(31),Conclusion 1).2.    The Cabinet were informed of the circumstances in which the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs had found it possible to join the Finance Committee.At the first meeting of the Gabinet he had been obliged to refuse membership, as there wereurgent matters requiring his attendance at theForeign Office,      Subsequently these had been disposed of, and he had informed the PrimeMinister that he was able and would like to join the Finance Committee.      The Prime Minister,after consultation with the Chancellor of theExchequer, had approved this.The Chancellor of the Exchequer then gave the Gabinet full details of the taxation proposalsof the Finance Committee, which were subsequentlydiscuss ed.As the review of the subject was stillincomplete at 1.15 P*m*)  &quot;tbe discussion was adjourned until 5*0 P-m.  the same day.2* Whitehall Gardens, S.W.12nd September, 1951.

</content>
</cab>
