<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/68/0 images: 72-85</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
rpWTS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY TS GOVSRNMENT).g ft C RET.Copy No.CABINET    52  (31),CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10,  Downing Street, S.W.1.  on WEDNESDAY,September 2nd, 1931, at 5.0 p.m.PRESENT:The Right Hon. J.Prime Minister.The Right Hon.Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon.Sir Herbert Samuel, G.C.B.,G.B.E. ,M.P. , Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,G.B.E. ,C.M.G. ,M.P, ,Secretary of State forIndia,The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P,,Minister of Health.ay MacDonald, M.P.,(In the Chair).The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Reading,G0 Go Bo ,G..C. S. I. ,G0C. I. E. ,G.C.V.O., Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon.J.H, Thomas, M.P. ,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs and secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-rLister,G.B.E. ,M.C. ,M.P. ,President of the Boardof Trade.Colonel Sir M.P.A0 Hankey, G.C.B, ,G.C.M,G0 Secretary.
ECONOMY BILL.Arrangements for preparation of.(previous reference:Cabinet 48(31),Conclusion 1(c)).F.R.%)3.1.   After a short discussion with parliamentary counsel (Sir William Graham Harrison and Mr. Ram),the Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Gabinet Gommittee on parliamentary Procedure, withthe addition of the Attorney-General, should meet in theGabinet Room at 10, downing street, on the following day,Thursday, September Jrd, at11.30 a.m. to discuss with parliamentary Gounsel the first draft of the Economy Bill, whichhad been prepared in accordancewith paragraph J of the Minutesof the Parliamentary ProcedureCommittee attached to CP. 209 (31).NOTE:-   As the Secretary of Statefor Scotland was leaving forScotland the same night, theHome Secretary undertook totake his place for purposesof this meeting.     TheSecretary was instructed thatit was unnecessary to securethe attendance of Sir B. Eyres-Monsell for this particularmeeting.(b) That the above Gommittee should arrangefor appropriate Ministerial guidancefor Parliamentary Gounsel.\\
7 9* 0LIAMENTARYbGRAMME.J-^eviousgrerence;ffinet 48(31),liclus I on 7).The Gabinet agreed  (a) To approve the following parliamentary programme for the first week afterthe re-assembly of Parliament, whichis attached to the Minutes of the FirstMeeting of the Committee on Parlia-mentary Procedure (Paper No.CP. 209 (3*0):-Tuesday, September 8th.Motion to set up Committee of Ways and means - Statement by the Prime Ministerand general discussion.Notice of presentation of the EconomyBill handed in.Wednesday, September 9th.Resolution stopping Private Members&apos;Bills and Bills under the Ten MinutesRule.    Guillotine Motion for BudgetResolutions (Committee Stage).Thursday, September 10th.Economy Bill circulated (morning).Committee stage of Budget Resolutions,(one day only).    Statement by theChancellor of the Exchequer.Friday, September 11th.Economy Bill - Second Reading,Monday, September 14 th.Economy Bill - Second Reading.That the Prime Minister should introduce the Motion to set up theCommittee on Ways and Means on Tuesday,September 8th;    the Lord President ofthe Council should be prepared to speakmidway in the Debate;    and the HomeSecretary should be prepared to windup the Debate.That the Lord President of the council should move the Resolutions stoppingPrivate Members&apos; Bills and Bills underthe Ten Minutes Rule, on Wednesday,September 9th, and the Lord president should introduce a guillotine motion for Budget Resolutions (committee stage) on the same day.(d) That the Chancellor of the exchequer should make his statement on theCommittee Stage of Budget Resolutionson September 10th.(e) That the Prime Minister should move the Second Reading of the Economy Billon Friday, September 11th.(b)(c)
(f) That other questions relating tothe Parliamentary Programme,including other Bills to beintroduced, should be discussed by the Gabinet in the nearfuture.-3&quot;
flMANCEpMITTEEI previous reference:Cabinet 51C31)pnclusion 2).^ 60s-.3. The Gabinet then resumed discussion of theFinance Committee Report, and agreed  (a) To approve the taxation proposalsof the Finance Committee, subjectto certain modifications made inthe course of the discussion.(Note:-    In accordance with theusual custom of theCabinet, it was decided,in the interests of secrecy, that the cabinet minutes should contain noreoord of the taxationproposals approved.)(b) That acceptance of the presenttaxation proposals would not preclude members of the presentCabinet, if they should take part in some subsequent Government,from proposing, to Parliament an alteration in the system oftaxation.ROADCASE BY THE&apos;&quot;\NCELL0RTHEXCHEQUER.PreviousererencetaUnet 25(51),inclusion 3) .(c) To invite the Chancellor of the Exchequeto explore further a scheme that had been mentioned at the meetingthe same morning, and on which he had handed round a proposal at the outset of the present meeting, for giving a limited relief in certain taxationin respect of expenditure incurred in development by persons engaged inproductive industry.      The Chancellorof the Exchequer was invited to consult upon the subject with someprominent accountant, such as LordPlender, and to report the results to his colleagues of the finance committee, who might also have theadvantage of an interview with theaccountant.     Pending this enquiry,a decision on the proposal wasdeferred,(d) (At a later stage of the meeting).That in accordance with the customusually adopted after introducing aBudget,  the Chancellor of the exchequer should broadcast on the taxationproposals after his speech on thesubject in Parliament,-4-
II Sfa ofIk economieslinglidies.h &apos; *7I0US3rence:Inet 50(51)conclusion   1).4.   The Minister of Health said that he had given careful consideration to the proposal for reducinghousing subsidies, as a measure of economy, in the lightof a short discussion which had taken place at the meeting referred to in the margin.     In deference to views whichhad been expressed by the Prime Minister and certain ofhis colleagues, he had decided not to propose a reductionin housing subsidies.He        intimated that certain economies might beeffected by administrative action which would not onlysave money but would ensure that houses were allotted to suitable applicants, which had not always been the case.The Prime Minister thanked the Minister of Health forhis statement.mjfOMlESm .jff im. * * *fevioussrence:lhet 43(31),Jluslon 2(E)5.     The Minister of Health said that he had not had time to examine into the possibility of realisingeconomies from the modification of the derating arrangements.).
SCONOiuY.onekploymentI$SUBANCIL*Rates of benefit and FinancialPosition.t * o(previous reference:Cabinet 51(31)Conclusion 1).6.    At a late stage in the meeting the Cabinetreceived a revised memorandum from the Minister ofLabour on the question of Rates of Benefit andFinancial Position which had been mentioned at themeeting referred to in the margin as in course of preparation.      (C.P. 216 (31)).The Cabinet a greed;-To adopt a scheme (scheme D), providingfor a 10$ cut in rates of benefit, roundedoff to the nearest 3d. , which it was estimated would produce a total saving of 12,800,000.     The effect of this decisionon rates of benefit is shown by thefollowing Table:-ManWomanAdult DependantChild DependantOther classes:-Young manYoung womanJuvenilesA.Present rates.s. d.17/-15. -9. -2.  -14.  -12, -9. -7. 66. 05. 0D.Reduced ratesrounded off to nearest 3d.s. d.15, 3k13. 68. OxNo change12, 6k10. 9k8. Ok6. 95. 64. 6k   In these cases the cut is just slightly more than ten percent - compared with Column &quot;B,T (not reproduced).Q
SUMMARY OP 7.     A summary of the economies as approved by the economies.Cabinet is attached in the Appendix to these minutes.(previous reference:       Tlie S^an(3- total amounts substantially to  70,000,000.Cabinet 50(31) The Cabinet were reminded that a contrast wasConclusion 14).likely to be drawn in public discussion between theabove figure and the saving of  96,500^000 proposed bythe May Committee.      It was pointed out, however, thatsome  22,000,000 of the May Committee&apos;s economies onUnemployment Insurance was obtained by transferringexpenditure from the Exchequer to the rates.There was general agreement that this point should be brought out in explaining the economyproposals to Parliament.
OF THEBSTING OFARLIAMENT .8.     Having settled the main lines of their policy on economy and taxation, as set forth above, the CabinetKPrevious;        agreed:-rebinetC48(31) That Parliament should meet on September 8th, 1931,Conclusion 7).&apos; as Previously contemplated.Note:     The Prime Minister reported that theconsent of the Speaker had already beenobtained, and took immediate steps tosecure the consent of the Lord Chancellor.He gave instructions at once for allthe necessary action for the summoning ofParliament.
so the INDIAN 9.  Certain points affecting the indian round table conference. Round Table Conference were raised by the Secretaryof State for India, and the Cabinet agreed  (previous reference: (a) That the Prime Minister shouldCabinet 2f8 invite the Leader of the Labour(31), Con- Party to nominate five repre-clusion 5). sentatives.to become Members ofF.R.the Indian Round Table Conference:(b) That the Prime Minister, inconsultation with the Chancellorof the Exchequer and the Secretaryflflfe**cl      . of State for India, should arrangefor a representative of the treasury to replace the late FinancialSecretary to the Treasury,  to take part in the financial discussions atthe Indian Round Table Conference;(c) That, in principle, the represen-tation of political Parties in theIndian Round Table conference was a matter for those Partiesthemselves, but there was general agreement that it was undesirable&apos; to alter the existingrepresentation owing to the factthat many of the representatives had become Members of theGovernment;(d) That the nomination of alternatemembers of Committees of the RoundTable Conference, such as theFederal Structure Committee,which might be rendered desirableowing to the preoccupation ofMinisters or for other reasons,should be arranged by the Sec-re tar y of State for India with theCommittees concerned.(NOTE:- The Prime Minister,  as president of the Indian RoundTable Conference, undertook to give all possible assistance to the Secretaryof State for India on suchmatters.)(e) That the Secretary of State for india should be given full discretion to show such papers as he deemed desirable, includingCabinet Memoranda, to the right on. Sir John Simon.
(f) That the Secretary of State forIndia should discuss with thePrime Minister the chairmanship of the Burma Pound table conference, and in the intervalthat he should arrange forpreparatory work by experts.
NEXT MEETING * 10. The Cabinet agreed -OP CABINET.(a) To meet on the following day,Thursday, September Jrd, at.0 p.m.;(b) That the chancellor of theExchequer should arrange for representatives of the Bank ofEngland to attend and discussthe financial situation withthe Cabinet.   .2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.2nd September, 195^*
appendix summary OF ECONOMIES AS AGREED BY THE CABINET.(Cabinet Conclusions 49 (51), 50 (51) and 51 (31)).Items other than Unemployment Insurance.   .millions,Education (England and Wales)Local Authorities to be informed that, as from 1stOctober, 1931, grants will be calculated on a gross total for teachers&apos;  salaries, with a deduction of 15% from the present level; and thatthe present 60$ grant shall be reduced to 50% butthe grant regulations to be adjusted to ensure thatthis reduction does not involve a transfer of charge to rates.   Deficiency grant to be terminated.Growth of expenditure next year to be cut down. 9.education (Scotland)ll/80ths of saving in England and Wales. 1.3University Grants. .15Roads.Blowing down and postponement of schemes. 7.86Fighting Services.Recommendations of the May Committee were  4.1 m.In addition, the Admiralty will save  2 m. nextyear by postponement of commencement of building programme, the War Office  2 m. and the AirMinistry   i m. 8.6Police.(One half of a 12^ cut in pay in two instalments) .5Forestry. .48Unemployment Grants. .5Agriculture (England and Wales).   Various savings. .58Agriculture (Scotland).    Various savings. .07Health (England and Wales and Scotland)Reduction of doctors&apos;  capitation fee from 9/- to/-. Chemists.    Transfer, as from 1st January, 1928,of health insurance part of contributions in respectof persons in employment over age 65 from PensionsAccount to Central Fund of National Health Insurance.Slowing down of housing. ^ 1.25Empire Marketing Board.(in addition to savings on publicity and other expenditure included under Agriculture). .25Colonial Development Fund. -25Miscellaneous.The Treasury to review the remainder of the field,other than Unemployment Insurance, and to find savings which, with increase of Government income from broad-casting, and cuts in the salaries of Ministers, Judges,Members of Parliament and higher officers of the civil and Fighting Services, would produce  3 m. 5.TOTAL 34.19
Unemployment Insurance   millions.Reduction of &quot;benefits on schemeprepared by Ministry of Labourproducing approximately 10%rounded off to nearest 3d0(adult man 15/3 s&apos;adult dependant8/-5 children 2/- etc.)(Scheme D of CP.215 (3l)) 12.8Anomalies(As under Act already passed) increase of contributions (net) 10Cessation of benefit from Pund after25 weeks. (This merely transfersa charge from the Fund totransitional payment) -Assessment of transitional payment by public Assistance Authorities acting as agents of Ministry of Labour 10TOTAL 35.834.19GRAND TOTAL . ....  69.99 m.

</content>
</cab>
