<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/68/0 images: 109-128</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) .C R E T . Copy No,CAB I N E T    54 (31) .Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10Downing Street, S.W.1, on MONDAY,   -September 7th, 1931, at 5.0 p.m.AGENDA.1* FOREIGN AFFAIRS.      (If required).2. FINANCE COMMITTEE. j(Reference Cabinet 52 (31), Conclusion 3).Further recommendations to be communicated bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer.3. UNIVERSITY GRANTS COMMITTEE - PROPOSED ECONOMIES.(Reference Cabinet 49 (31), Conclusion 5).4. PARLIAMENTARY BUSINESS - Remainder of Programmenot yet considered, including -(Reference Cabinet 53 (31), Conclusion 4).(i) The London Passenger Transport Bill.(Reference Cabinet 48(31), Conclusion 3).Note by the Secretary covering DepartmentalMemorandum by the Ministry of Transport.(CP. 214 (31)    -   already circulated).(ii) The Statute of Yfestminster.(Reference Cabinet 48 (31), Conclusion 3).Memorandum by the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.(CP. 212 (31)    -   already circulated).(iii) The Educational Endowments (Scotland) Bill.(iv) A Bill to renew the Prolongation of InsuranceAct,(Reference Cabinet 50 (3l), Conclusion l).CP.209 ( (v)   The Expiring Laws Continuance Bill.6D para. 5(( (vi) The Public Works Loan Bill,(vii) The Appropriation Bill.
TO TAKE NOTE OF;5. CABINET PROCEDURE.(Reference Cabinet 48 (31),   (Appendix) Conclusion 3).Note by the Secretary.(CP. 205 (31)    -    already circulated).6 . THE FINANCIAL SITUATION.(i) Sterling and the gold standard.(ii) How England Lives.Note by the Secretary covering memorandacirculated by direction of the PrimeMinister.(CP. 219 (31)    -   already circulated).(Signed) M.P.A. HAN KEY,Secretary, Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.4th September, 1931.
BIHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRIT AN NIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT).S S C R E copy No.C A B I NET    54  (51)Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10Downing Street, S.W.1,  on MONDAY,September 7th,  1931, at 5.0 p.m.ADDUIONAL IT EM T 0 AGENDA.UNEMPLOYMENT  INSURANCE.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.(CP. 222 (31)    -    circulated herewith)(Signed) M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.15th September, 1931.
I (THIS DOCmtENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYTS GOVERNMENT&apos;)SECRET. Copy No.cabinet    54. ( 51 ) .Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10,Downing Street, S.W.1.,  on MONDAY,September JtYi, 1931 , at 5*0 P.ro,FURTHER ADDENDUM TO AGENDA.INDIAN ROUND TABLE CONFERENCE.(Reference Cabinet 52 (31) Conclusion 9).Question to be raised by the Secretaryof State for India.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,7th September, 1951.(Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet,
I:112DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRIT AIT NIC MAJESTY *S GOVERNMENT).CR ET. Copy No,CABINET     54  (51).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1,  on MONDAY,September 7th, 1931, at 5.0 p.in.PRESENT : -The Right Hon. J. Ramsay. MacDonald,Prime Minister.e Right Hon.jStanley Baldwin, M.P.,Lord President of theCouncil.le Right Hon.Sir Herbert Samuel, G.C.B.,G.B.E.,M.P., Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.e Most Hon.IThe Marquess of Reading,1G.C.B.,G.C.S.I.,G.C.I, E *,JG.C.V.0., Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.(In the Chair).The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.Lo rd S ankey, G.C.B.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,G.B.E.,C.M.G.,M.P.,Secretary of State for India.p.le Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, MSecretary of State forDominion Affairs and secretary of State for theColonies.TheThe Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-LIster,G.E ,E., M. C., M .P, ,President of the Board of Trade,colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G .C.B, ,G .C.M.G.,  ............ Secretary.
1.    The Chancellor of the Exchequer informed theCabinet that, as arranged at the meeting of theCabinet referred to in the margin, a Conference ofMinisters had met that afternoon to consider thedraft of the White Paper which had been circulatedto the Cabinet as CP. 221  (;51) .The Cabinet agreed  UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE.(a) To omit the following words in square brackets immediately preceding the table:-&quot;and what that rate would be ifa reduction of exactly 10$were applied&quot;.(b) To omit from the table the- columnheaded &quot;Rates on an exact 10$reduction&quot;.(c) To take note of a redraft of partof the paragraph headed -&quot; (k.) A needs test for transitional payments given after insurancerates have expired&quot;.(d) (After consideration of the Ministerof Labour&apos;s Memorandum,  (CP. 222 (J1)),to omit the following passage in square brackets under the same heading -&quot;(5) Provision will be made fordealing with the entitlement to insurance benefit in cases in which persons with brokenperiods of employment and unemployment draw substantialwages.     There are not suffi-cient data for estimating the saving under this head, which,however, will not be large in amount.&quot;(e) To take note that a new paragraph willbe inserted at this point, making clear the Government&apos;s decision that thereshould be no further recourse toborrowing for the Unemployment Fund.Any future deficiencies would have tobe met by a grant from the Exchequer.SUMMARY OP UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCEFINANCE.(f) After the words &quot;sum to be provided byExchequer&quot; delete the words &quot;or by borrowing&quot;, and after the words &quot;needstest for transitional payments&quot; omit the words &quot;administered through the agency of public assistance authorities&quot;.CONOMY,The white paper.(previous reference:Cabinet 53(51), Con-elusion jHc) *)
4  4*I hiROAD FUNS.(g) In the penultimate line, for &quot;manyschemes&quot; put &quot;certain schemes&quot;,andin the last line omit the words- &quot;on a large scale&quot;.MINISTRY OF HEALTH AND DEPARTMENT OFHEALTH FOR SCOTLAND.NOTE:-   A new proposal by the Ministerof Health was discussed, but did not lead to   the adoptionof any addition to thememorandum.      The matter is dealt with in a separateconclusion (conclusion 2).(h) Under the sub-heading &quot;Miscellaneous&quot;,to omit the words in the second line&quot;the rapid extension of housing&quot;.REDUCTIONS OF SALARIES OF MINISTERS, etc.(i) In the first line,  to omit the words&quot;during the period of the present emergency&quot; and to substitute thewords &quot;as from the 1st October&quot;.(j) From the revised paragraph beginning&quot;in the case of the Civil Service&quot; tomake the following alterations:-2nd line;    After the words &quot;in the193-1 Estimates&quot; insert thewords &quot;by the late Government&quot;.4th and 5th lines: Omit the words -&quot;the combined1 effect of thesedrops for 1951  is  4,000,000.FIGHTING SERVICES.(k) Throughout the White Paper to substitute for &quot;Fighting Services&quot; the term&quot;Defence Services&quot;.POLICE.NOTE:-    See separate Conclusion (Conclusion j57L /^A-, J^^^ 1EMPIRE MARKETING BOARD, and colonial DEVELOPMENT FUND./   &apos;,a    - h.       rtl) To take note that the Secretary of StateT^/r11 A for. Dominion Affairs and for theOU^ct UUU4&quot;^&apos; 7U^J Colonies hopes to find a saving ofJ  125,000.,LAND DRAINAGE.(m) To omit the passage relating toLand Drainage.
SUMMARY.(n) To omit the Note.RE-ARRANGEMENT OF HEADINGS.(o) To take note that the Conference ofMinisters had agreed to considerablechanges in the order, includingthe following:-(i) The Summary to come at thebeginning of the White Paper;(ii) This to be followed by the heading &quot;Reductions of salaries of Ministers&quot; etc.(iii) Unemployment Insurance to comelast.HOUSE OF COMMONS DISCUSSION.(p)  To take note that the Prime minister had arranged that, while    theessential part of the Budgetresolutions would be passed on thefirst day devoted to their discussion,there would be a second day on whichthe House of Commons would havefacilities for discussing all matters within the scope of theWhite Paper, notwithstanding thatthey were not referred to in the economy Bill, so long as the time limit was not exceeded.
m2.    The Minister of Health, during thediscussion of the section of the White Paperdevoted to Ministry of Health economies, raised the question of whether power should be takenby the Government to terminate the contractsbetween Local Authorities and their staffs,whether salaried officers or industrial employees.The Cabinet were informed that in thePresident of the Board of Education&apos;s discussionwith representatives of the teachers,  it had been pointed out that an anomaly would arise if the teachers sustained cuts in their salaries,while a highly paid director of educationsuffered no cut.     A similar point would arise in connection with medical officers.The Cabinet were reminded also that the economies effected in the pay of the policeaccrued both to the State and to the LocalAuthorities.      An anomaly would at once ariseowing to the fact that the Chief of Police hadhis salary reduced and no corresponding reduction was made in the salaries of other highly paidlocal Government officials.It was suggested that,  in order to dealwith such anomalies,  the Local Authorities mightbe empowered by legislation to cancel contracts,so as to enable them to negotiate new ones.If this were done, however, it was suggested thatit would also be necessary to safeguard theposition of Local Government officials, whetheragainst excessive cuts in their salaries, or
even dismissal (e.g.  in cases in which they hadresisted an extravagant Council), by, providing that reductions should be subject to review bythe Ministry of Health.      It was suggestedalso that the principle of cuts ought to belaid down centrally by the Ministry of Health.The subject was discussed at considerablelength, both in its political and practicalaspects.On the whole the view prevailed that itwould be better not to attempt to deal with thisquestion at the present stage.      The main objectof the economies now contemplated was to balance the national budget.    Although the scheme adoptedled unfortunately to some anomalies, due to thefact that some officials, such as teachers and police, were paid for partly by Government grant and partly by the Local Authorities,  it wasconsidered advisable to allow the Local authorities who found it necessary, to deal with the question asbest they could.      It was pointed out, for example,that in some cases Local Authorities might be ableto secure reductions in salaries by agreement withthe officials concerned, notwithstanding thattheir contracts had not expired.      In other casescontracts would be terminable within a comparatively short time.     Should Local Authorities desirefurther powers,  the question might have to beconsidered later by the Government of the day.
[police.Iie questionf pensions.3.    In the course of the discussion on theWhite Paper the Chancellor of the Exchequerread to the Cabinet a draft paragraph on PoliceExpenditure (C.W.P.  (31) 1), and the followingphrase at the bottom of the first page &quot;withoutaltering the existing rates of pensionable payor pensions&quot; opened up the question of policepensions.The Home Secretary informed the Cabinetthat at discussions with the Police Council every single authority concerned with the Police wasunanimous that pensions ought not to be cut.The Home Office and the Scottish Office bothsupported this view strongly.     At a meeting witha large number of representatives of the Police,he had found evidence of a good deal of unrestcreated by the recommendations of the May Committee,due partly to the fact that no evidence hadbeen taken from the Police.      The only point which all had applauded was his mention thatPolice pensions would not be cut.      He laid theutmost emphasis on this point.After considerable discussion the Cabinet -invited the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Home Secretaryto consider the wording of thisparagraph very carefully, inorder to ensure that pension rights of the Police that havealready accrued shall not be impaired.
rrjOMY 4.     With regard to the Economy Bill the cabinet took the following decisions(a) That in order to bring the Bill into line with the White Paper the followingheading should be omitted from the Schedule -&quot;Land Drainage&quot;.(b) That as far as possible the order of the headings in the Schedule should be re-arranged to correspond to the new order ofthe headings in the White Paper.(c) To confirm&apos; their previous decision that theperiod after the commencement of the Actwithin which Orders in Council   could beissued should be limited to one month.(d) That Parliamentary Counsel,    who    it was understood, desired guidance as to thelong title to the Economy Bill and othermatters should have resort to the CabinetCommittee.(e) That the Cabinet Committee should meet onthe following days     Tuesday, September 8th,1931, in the Prime Minister&apos;s Room atHo.  10 Downing Street at 11 a.m., in orderto consider the Economy Bill.tionaly Bill-.ousnee:t 53 (31),sion 3).
5.     The Chancellor of the Exchequer informed the-nil Tptp &apos; QqSALS. Cabinet that on further examination      the Scheme,mentioned in the Cabinet Minute referred to in theUsed ReliefExpenditure margin, for giving a limited relief in certainLiped InLlopment. taxation In respect of expenditure, incurred in development by persons engaged in productive industry,previous[fence&apos; had been found to present insuperablemet 52(31),elusion 3). difficulties.     A similar result, however, might bea.obtained by increasing the allowances now made forft^o- depreciation of plant and machinery, and by taking amore liberal view In future of allowances forobsolescence.He read to the Cabinet a draft, prepared as theresult of the meeting of the Finance Committee that morning, of what he proposed to say on these subjects in his Speech on the Taxation Proposals.      In theseremarks he included a statement that the firstmentioned proposal would be further explored.The Cabinet took note of and approved theproposals of the Finance Committee, summarised above, as reported by the Chancellor of theExchequer.
CATION-s/ersityits.previous conference :inet 49(51),elusion 5).a.6,     Referring to the Cabinet conclusion, referred to-in the margin, the Chancellor of the Exchequermentioned to the Cabinet that the sum of  150,000reduction on University Grants was not a reeurrentone.     The annual grant of  1,830,000 a year to the universities was wholly allocated and the sum whichwas available was only a lump sum of  150,000 saved from previous years.     The surrender of that sum i-rouldenable the grant-In-aid for 1932 to be subjected to anon-recurrent reduction of that amount.      In substitutlor.for the Cabinet decision, referred to in the margin,the Cabinet agreed:-As regards University Grants, to approve the surrender of this  150,000 and to take note that this would result In a non-recurrentreduction in 1932 of the University GrantsCommittee Vote from  1,830,000 to  1,680,000or a reduction for that year only of  150,000.
12?J.   Kl^IAMKNTARY. . &apos;finder ofcramme not considered.gviouserence:inet 53 (51),elusion 4) .7.     The Cabinet did not discuss this item on theAgenda beyond instructing the Secretary to add thefollowing Bills to the list:. Stf&amp;iW The Sunday Performances Bill,ft&apos;(3i)t3. The Shipping Conventions Bill.
6 08.    The Cabinet took note of the following documents circulated by the Secretary to theCabinet with CP. 205 (J1)* in accordance withthe Cabinet Conclusion mentioned in the margin:-(i) Existing instructions to theSecretary to the Cabinet;(ii) Existing instructions as regardsCabinet Committees and Conferences;(iii) A Treasury circular (C 364.7), dated25th February, 19J51 ,  on the submission of business to the Gabinet,  coveringan earlier circular,      dated 28thApril,  1924.;(iv) Economic Advisory Council   -    copy of treasury Minute of appointment,dated 27th January, 1930;(v) A Note on the Economic AdvisoryCouncil.
FINANCIALION.a  4 *previous reference:Cabinet 53(31),Conclusion 1) .a.9.    The Cabinet took note of two Memoranda,circulated by direction of the Prime Minister,which had reached him from a well-known outsidesource, entitled respectively:-(i) Sterling and the Gold Standard;(ii) How England Lives.At the end of the meeting a short discussionof a preliminary character took place as to thefinancial situation, which was as yet still farfrom satisfactory.     There was general agreement that the subiect would have to be discussed inthe near future In relation to the politicalsituation.
E INDIANUND TABLESiiFERENCE.* * *previous ousfersnce :.binet 52(31,),inclusion 9).a-10.    On the suggestion of the Secretary of Statefor India the Cabinet agreed :-(a) That a Cabinet Committee, similar tothat set up by the late Government butcomposed of members of the Cabinet,who are also members of the Round table conference together with the -Lord Privy Seal,The Chancellor of the Duchy ofLancasterandThe Member for Financial Questions(as soon^as he Is appointedto the Round Table Conference,and financial questions arise;,beshould/set up to  consider questions relating to the Round Table Conference.(b) That the Secretary of State for India,in consultation with the Lord Chancellor,should  decide questions as to thedistribution of papers connected withthe Round Table Conference.
supply andban SPORT30MMITT-EE.previous reference: ^Cabinet 56 (2a),Conclusion 2) .11.     The Home Secretary asked that the questionof the Supply and Transport Committee might be placedon the Agenda at the next meeting of the Cabinet.f-RL.
v?y$&apos; M3HCING 12.   The Cabinet agreed:--uTiVhT &apos;       To meet on Wednesday, September 9th,^       &apos; 1931, at 11 a.ra., at No.10 downing street, S.W.1.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.7th September,  1931.

</content>
</cab>
