<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/11/22 images: 402-407</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.toMOST SECRET.COPY NOPROPAGANDA INGERMANY,I Nazi views onrelativepotentialities ofAllied leaflet andbroadcast propaganda.(previous reference.W.M. (40) 19thConclusions,Minute l).W.M.  (40) 26th CONCLUSIONS MINUTE 9.Confidential Apxiexa(29th January, 1940).THE SECRETARY OP STATE POR FOREIGNAFFAIRS read the following report which he hadreceived from a secret source(1)   The Gestapo, the Ministry of propaganda and others immediately interested in thesubject have discussed at length relativepotentialities of enemy leaflets andbroadcasts,(2)   The Gestapo hates leaflets.    If a Germandeliberately turns on a foreign stationon his wireless set he knows that he isrunning a risk.    If he is caught listening-in he can be easily convicted.   But if aman finds a piece of printed paper on theground he may think it is an advertisementfor liver pills, and if he is found readingit he cannot easily be convicted of a deliberate act;   besides, it can be read without even being removed from theground,,(3)   At the beginning of the war there were some particularly sinister cases whichgreatly worried the Gestapo.       Leafletswhich had only been dropped in Northernor Western Germany were discovered insheltered spots in the mountains of theTyrol and Bavaria,    In one case in southern BavTia a leaflet was foundpinned to a -cree,     A well-trodden pathoff a main road proved that a largenumber of people had made a specialjourney to read it and led to itsdiscovery.     The culprits were neverdiscovered.

(4)   The Ministry of Propaganda considers thatleaflets are a dangerous addition to broadcast propaganda because Germans arenow somewhat tired of the spoken word.   Inworkshops, offices, restaurants, etc. theyare forced to listen to an endless streamof their own propaganda.     When the averageGerman comes home he is inclined to listen to music rather than to politics, and whenlistening-in to foreign broadcasts is adeci/fedly risky business, only the politicallyactive anti-Nazi   German is likely to takethe risk.(5)     On the other hand, any kind of printed matter has an attraction for the average German.The German is a born book-worm and has a natural penchant for reading.    The factthat the Germans themselves are usingleaflets in enemy and neutral countriesdemonstrates their belief in the effective-ness of this form of propaganda.(6)     The above does not of course mean that the gestapo or the Ministry of Propagandaunderrate the importance of enemy broadcasts.They can undoubtedly be effective and are taken very seriously by the authorities, asis proved by the severe sentences passed on people caught in the act of listeningto foreign stations.The War Cabinet took note of the above :--oportPRichmond Terrace, S.W. 1.




</content>
</cab>
