<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/143/0 images: 64-76</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION  OF  THE ATTACHED  EASTERN  REPORT,  No. IT.                                    POLAND.    THE proclamation, by the Emperor of Russia in regard to Poland should be noted,as reports and views will probably be influenced by it in future.                               TURKEY  IN  EUROPE.    The accession of Talaat to office as Grand Vizier may prove an anti-Enver move,but it will not influence matters in our favour.                                      SYRIA.    The trial by court-martial  of absent  Arab leaders may be a piece of bluff or theprecursor of further executions.  It  tends  to confirm the Arab-Turkish  split  moredefinitely.                               MOSQUE  AT BASBA.    The proposal to build a mosque for Indian soldiers only at Basra may,  if adopted,lead to anti-British  propaganda, as being  construed as an effort on our part to divideIslam.                              THE  &quot; MORNING POST.&quot;   &apos; Mr. Colling Cave&apos;s letter to the &quot;Morning  Post&quot; cannot assist anyone  but our enemies;  the  seditious  in India will make use  of it as an  unveiling  of our allegedhypocrisy.                            M. HANOTAUX&apos;S ARTICLE.    M. Hanotaux&apos;s article is singular rather  for the  things it does  not  say than thethings that it does.[898-29]
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s  Government]Printed for the  War Cabinet.SECRET.FOR REFERENCE  ONLY.EASTERN   REPORT.No. II.  February 7,  1917.(Incorporating  ARABIAN REPORT N.S. XXIX.)Poland.Rumania.    The Petrograd Conference.    British Corn in Moldavia.    The Question of the Evacuation of Jassy.Turkey in tfurope.    Conflict between Enver Pasha and Talaat Bey.    The German-Ottoman Society.Northern Africa.        Wireless communication between El Fasher and Ab.ssher.    Abyssinia;        Message for the Empress from the King.Anatolia.    The Italian Claims.The Caucasus Field of Operations.Arabia, Syria, Mesopotamia, and Irak.    Arabia.        General.        Ilejaz        Aden.        Koweit.        Nejd.    Syria.    Irak.Persia,    Ears.    The Bokhfciari.India and its Neighbours.    India.CONTENTS.PART I.Egypt.Jebel Shammar.&apos;Afghanistan.Indian Seditionari.es in Japau.PART II.FKOM THE PRESS.The Grand Sherif s Proclamation.The Kate of Turkey in Europe.[898-29]B
PART  I.                                    POLAND.    Reuter&apos;s  agent in Petrograd  telegraphing on the  4th February, said that thefollowing official announcement had been issued : ;         &quot; The Emperor, in accordance  with  the Order of the day to the Army and    Navy, in  which he made  known his august will  to create after the war a free    Poland to be formed of the threeregions which are to-day isolated, gave instructions    for the drawing up of  a scheme for the future political organisation of Poland and    its relations with the Empire.         &quot; His Majesty has now directed the  formation of a special committee for the    discussion of  the  above questions.  It will be presided over by the Premier, and    will be composed  of  the Ministers of War, the Interior,  Foreign Affairs, and    itfinance, the Chief of  the General Staff,  the presidents of the legislative bodies,    the Secretaries of State, and persons specially appointed, notably M. Goremykin,    the ex-Premier, and M. Sazonof, the new  Ambassador to Great Britain.&quot;                                   RUMANIA.                             The Petrograd Conference.    The Foreign Office telegraphed to Sir G. Buchanan on the 30th January [No. ] 97],approving his action in regard to the presence of the Prime Minister of -Rumania at the petrograd Conference.  [See Eastern Report No.  1, p. 2.]                             British Corn in Moldavia.    The Foreign  Office telegraphed on  the 31st January to Sir G. Barclay [No. 47]saying  that  it  was   understood  that  Colonel  Norton-Griffiths was  concludingarrangements for the sale of the British corn left in Moldavia (about  37,000 tons)and instructing him in regard to the payment of the purchase money.   Sir  G.  Barclaywas also asked whether  there was any other British grain left  in Rumania. - In reply,in a telegram dated the 4th February [No. 73] he said that this corn represented our total stock in Moldavia; but in addition the Rumanian Government had to returnabout 140,000 tons which had been lent.   The balance must be considered as lost.   he also said that he had been negotiating with the Russian army for the sale of our graineither against cash payment or against delivery of an equal  quantity at Odessa at alater date ; he asked whether he was to insist on cash  payment only.                     The Question of the Evacuation of Jassy.    Sir G. Barclay telegraphed  on the 1st February that he had been approached bya Russian officer with a view to ascertaining what accommodation would be needed for him and his staff at Kherson in the event of the evacuation of Jassy by the PvumanianGovernment.  He had been informed by  his Russian  colleague  that  this was only a precautionary measure and did  not necessarily imply  evacuation.  He believed hisRussian  colleague  to -  be  quite  sincere,  but  he feared  that  the Russian militaryauthorities in Jassy were entirely in favour of an early Rumanian evacuation and on asextensive a scale as possible.   General Berthelot had complained that they desired theevacuation of the whole of the Rumanian army in order that it  should be reorganisedin Russia.   He  recently proceeded to the Russian General Headquarters to urge theabandonment of the idea,  and came to a compromise with the chief of the general staff to the effect, Sir G. Barclay understood, that as regards  the  army  only  the wounded and recruits were to be  evacuated to Russia.
                               TURKEY  IN EUROPE.^                                   New Cabinet.       Reuter telegraphed from Amsterdam on the  5th December that, according to a   Constantinople telegram, the Grand Yizier, Said Halim, has  tendered his resignation   for  reasons of health.  The Sultan has  accepted  the resignation,  and has  entrusted   Talaat Bey with the formation of a new Cabinet, which is composed as follows : -       Grand Vizier,  Minister of the  Interior,  and temporarily Minister of Finance :            Talaat Bey.       Sheikh-ul-Islam  and  Minister  of  &quot;Wakuf (Pious  Foundations) : &apos; Hassakiazim            Effendi.       Minister of Foreign Affairs : Nessimy Bey.       Minister of Justice and President of the State Council:  Halil Bey.       Minister of  War : Enver Pasha.       Minister of  Marine : Jemal Pasha.       Minister of  Public Instruction, Posts, and  Telegraphs :  Shukri  Bey.       Minister of  Commerce and Agriciilture : Sheref Bey.       Minister of  Public Works ; Aii Murad Bey (Governor of the Lebanon).       The Sultan  has conferred  upon  Talaat Bey the title of Vizier and  Pasha.  The   telegram adds that the new Cabinet will energetically prosecute the war  in conjunction   with Turkey&apos;s allies until the attainment of final victory. Reuter.                       Conflict between Enver Pasha and Talaat Bey.       A grave conflict&apos;&apos; has arisen in  Turkey between Enver Pasha and Talaat Bey by   reason of the divergence of their views upon the recruiting laws.       Up to now, by means  of the payment of a special &quot; boclel&quot; tax, all those who paid   a sum of  T.40 per annum during the continuance of the war were exempt from military   service.  The new law now renders  military service compulsory for  all men between   the ages of 18 and  50.                                      ...       This new law, according to Talaat, does more harm than good.   It only adds about   100.000 men to the colours, and from then- wealth  and position, and  owing to the fact   that they have largely, relying upon the old law, embarked upon lengthy undertakings,   a great deal of feeling and  friction has been aroused.       Jemal Pasha has arrived in  Constantinople  in  order, it  is  said, to come  to the   support of Enver.   This would seem unlikely on  account of the bad feeling which  is   universally known to exist between the two men.        The general impression is that Talaafs views  will prevail.  He  has the populace   on  his  side  as well  as  the support  of many of the  prominent officials, amongst their   number Jambolaat, and  powerful  support  in  the  Committee &quot; Union and  Progress.&quot;   On the other hand, it is true  that Enver  Pasha  is  backed by Germany but  that in   itself now  even makes for unpopularity, since the feeling is growing that the country has   been  dragged into the war by the ambitions of certain politicians.        The candidate of Enver for the supplanting of Talaat will be Munif  Bey, the Vali   of Beirut.   But Talaafs popularity is generally expected to carry the da)&apos;.        Should affairs  become even more critical than they are at present, it is possible that   Ismail Hakki Pasha may take Enver&apos;s place.        There are many Turks who consider that  the proclamation of  the independence  of   Arabia and the projected campaign against Egypt  count for a good deal in the quarrel;   and they,  in any case, are  the probable explanation of the presence in  Constantinople  of   Jemal Pasha, the Governor of Syria.       . [The above  is taken from  a report  made  lately to the War Office  and should be    taken with reserve.]                               The German-Ottoman  Society.        Our representative  at the Italian General Headquarters has been informed by the    Italian Military Intelligence Department that  one  of the chief men in the above society-    is Professor Franz  Schmidt, who has been made councillor  at  the  Turkish Ministry  of    Education that  he may assist in the reorganisation of the Turkish schools.   Pie  is    also  the intermediary for  the transfer of  100 Turk students to  German educational    establishments,  which movement  is promoted by the society in conjunction with local    educational  authorities  in Germany.   From the first beginnings of the society, young
Turkish apprentices have been  drafted  into German  commercial  undertakings andsuch work is proceeding regularly.    From a reliable source it has been ascertained  that Schmidt has been ordered tocreate twenty  free posts and also student scholarships to the amount of 10,000 marksannually.     Whilst a  knowledge of Germany has been infused  into Turkey by the circulation of tens of thousands of pamphlets  in Turkish, the society  is now making every endeavourto educate Germany in Turkish ideas and life.  There are 4,000 members of the society in Germany and the greater part  of them are engaged in forming local leagues with theabove object.  In  Berlin and many other centres, Turkish language classes have beenformed.     The Turkish-German  Society has also founded  a special  bureau for  information regarding  economic  questions   between  the  two  countries  (&quot; Auskunftstelle  fairDeutsche-Turkische Wirtschaftsfragen&quot;), which is in direct communication  with thecompetent  Turkish and German  authorities for the supply gratis of information  of an industrial nature concerning the two countries.                             NORTHERN AFRICA.EGYPT.              Wireless communication between El Fasher and Abesher.    Sir R. WTingate telegraphed on  the  30th January [No.  83] that the erection  of intermediate  stations at Kebkebia and at either Dirjeil or Saitamayo, in Bar Masalit,was necessary for establishing wireless communication between El Fasher and Abesher.A station in the Masalit country would assist us to get into touch, with border chiefs,and to study local conditions ; but the French might try to impose conditions which theymight later use to support their very weak claims in  that region.   Subject to approvalhe proposed  to  inform  the French  Minister in  Cairo of the intention to erect  thisstation.ABYSSINIA.                      Message for the Empress from the King.    The Foreign Office telegraphed to Mr. Thesiger on the  3rd February [No. 82]instructing him to convey a message from the King  to the Empress on the occasion ofher coronation.   His Majesty offered his heartiest congratulations and good wishes, andmentioned  that  he  was sending gifts, in which Her Majesty would see a testimony ofhis cordial feelings and of his earnest desire to maintain and strengthen the relations of friendship and good understanding which had so long existed between her dominionsand his  own.                                   ANATOLIA.                               The Italian Claims.   . On  the  29th January the French and Italian  Ambassadors and  the Russiancharge  d&apos;affaires met  Mr. Balfonr at the Foreign  Office to discuss the course  that should be adopted in regard to Italian  interests in the Eastern Mediterranean.   Inthe course of the discussion the Italian Ambassador  made it clear that his Governmentgreatly   desired  Smyrna,  whilst  the Russian charge   d&apos;affaires thought that  hisGovernment  would  find it difficult to i^econcile itself to seeing Turkey-in-Asia deprived of its natural  outlet  to  the   Mediterranean.   Mr. Balfour did  not think that thetransfer of  Smyrna from Turkish  to  Italian  rule would  be  popular  in England.The Italian  Ambassador  reminded  him  that Mr. Balfour&apos;s  predecessor had promisedthe Italian Government that British claims should not be put  forward as an obstacle to  Italian claims.   Mr. Balfour promised that he  would at an early date submit ascheme   prepared by his  office, endeavouring  to  make out a region in  Sonth-WestAnatolia, west of Cape Anamour, equal  in value to the French sphere of influence value being determined not merely by measurements.                 THE CAUCASUS  FIELD OF  OPERATIONS.     Agents  report that Izzet Pasha, having given up the command of the 2nd army,has gone to  Constantinople; his place as commander of the  2nd army having  been
   taken by Jemal  Pasha from Syria.   There are also  agents&apos; reports  that  about  the   7th January 3,000 Turks from Aleppo, with artillery and machine guns, passed throughC) Kharput for Diarbekir; also that 8 German guns, 7-5-centim., and 4 machine guns are   being sent with German detachments to Bagdad from the 2nd army.ARABIA,  SYRIA,  MESOPOTAMIA,  AND IRAK.                                   ARABIA.GENERAL.    The following is a summary of the fighting strength and political tendencies of theprincipal tribes and confederates of Hejaz, Asir, Yemen, Fadli and Hadramaut: Confederation or tribe and ruler.	District.	Fighting strength.	Political tendencies.	Remarks.Huweitar. Chi f- Audeh Abu Tayyi. Atiyeh.(J) Chief Mohammed Ibn Atiya. Billi.(c) Chief Suleiman Ibn liafada. Kingdom of Ilcjaz. duheina, Harb, Ateibu. King Hussain. A dir. Chief Idrisi.	East and south-ea.-t of the Gulf of Akaba. East of the Gulf of Akaba. Occupy the Red Sea littoral, from 105 miles north of Wejh to 45 mih-s south of that place, and the hinterland as far as the Hejaz Railway. The authority of King Hnssain is recognized along- the lied Sea littoral from Yambo in the north to Comfida in the sou ih. and in the hinterland to the borders of Nejd. Red Sea littoral from Comfida in the north to Lahiyah in the south with corre-sponding hinter-Umd.	300-100 ? 400-500 22,000 (d) 25,000 0)	At war with the Shammar and formerly on bad terms with the B*jni Shakr (a). On the outbreak of the present war, fearing that their camels would be com-mandeered by the Turks the Huweitatmade up their differences with the Beni Shakr and retired eastwards with them into the Anazeh country.&apos; b) Abu Tayyi has recently been in communication &quot;with Faisal, who hopes to obtain his co-operation against the Turks. Maintain close friendship with the Huweitat whose pastures and feuds they share. Pro-Turk. Suleiman has recently been decorated by the Turks and rejected overtures made to him by Colonel Parker on the 16th Sep-tember, 1911). The capture of Wejh on the 24th January and the defeat of the Turkish garrison may result in the defection of the Billi from the Turks, whose difficulty in protecting the Hejaz Railway would be appreciably increased thereby. Pan-Arab. On friendly terms with the British and Ibn Saud. Hostile to the Turks and to the Imam of Yemen, though King Hussain is trying to reconcile him to the latter. Idrisi appears to be mainly pre-occupied with his own aggrandise-ment. He makes a condition of reconciliation with the Imam the	(a.) Nawaf lbu Faiz, chief of the Beni Shakr, has come to an under-standing with Nuri ShalaaD. chief of the Ruweilah Anazeh, to break . off re-lations with the Turks immedi-ately, but to await the progress of King- Hussain&apos;s operations before taking any action. (b.) Both the Huweitat arid Atiyeh are nomad. (c.) Partly set-tied, partly nomad and includes the Moahib, a nomad tribe numbering 80 fighting men. (cl.) This number, which represents the actual strength of King Ilussain&apos;s armies, includes a force of 1,000 Meccan &quot;volunteers&quot; recently raised. The King will not enroll men from Jeddah ou account of their poor fighting value. (c.) The inbahi-tants of Asir are mostly settled and are averse to leaving their par-ticular district. Thus for expedi-tionary purposes&apos; it is doubtful whether more than a small pro-portion of this number would be[89S-2&apos;J]   -                              .                       C
Confederation or tribe and ruler.District.fighting strength.Political tendencies.Remarks.Asir cont.      Yemen.Tribes    Amis.  Zaranik (g).  Hashid wa        Bakil (g).  Khaulan.  Muqatil.  Qurah.  Suleil.  Wazat (g). The  lied  Sealittoral     fromLahiyan  to  the boundary  of  the aden    Protec-torate and corre-sponding hinter-land.Chief--The Imam   Yahia.      Fadli.Sultan-Hussain      Ibn Ahmed. Littoral   fromImad,    Britishfrontier post east of    Aden    toMaqatin    and extending inlandto the  maritimeranges.Sultanate  of  (Ji)  Shiheir  (Shear)  and Mokalla.S ultan   Sir  Ghalib Ibn  Awad, K.C.I.B. Hadramaut  lit-toral. 3,00010,00012,000-20,000 7.00O- 8,000 2,500 3,000- 4,000 1,500 1,500- 3,0008,000  Permanent bodyguard of  1,000 men.    Haisesmercenaries as   required.ceding to himself of the YemenTehama (/&apos;) as far as Mokha, in-cluding  the  port  of  Hodeidah,which is not likely to be acquiesced in.   He does not appear inch Lied totake active operations against theTurks, but  fears a combinationbetween the Imam and the BritishGovernment which would result inthe  destruction  of  the   turkish troops in  Yemen and  impair hisvalue as  an  ally to  the BritishGovernment.  The dispute with Idrisi over theFarsan Islands was settled on the23rd January.  He has undertaken to occupy the islands effectively,and not to part with them to any foreign power.  The Imam adheres to the Turks,and has rejected British overtures.He is accorded an annual subsidy of   36,000/.   by  the  ottoman government,  and  his loyalty isprobably   dependent  upon   itsregular receipt.  In consequenceof the isolation of Yemen, and the interruption of foreign commerce,the  Turks  must be  finding  itdifficult to keep  up the paymentof so large a sum.  Disturbances have recently takenplace at Taiz,  Ibb and Jebel Jehafover the collection of taxes, andthe  British Indian merchants ofIlodeidah have been called on fora contribution  of 216,000/., thoughonly about  60 000/. appear to havebeen paid.  These incidents affordsome insight  upon  the  financialstraights of the Turkish adminis-tration.  The Imam is hostile to Idrisi ofAsir.   iIis  sou Mohammed Yahiais said  to be opposed to his  pro-Turkish sentiment,  which  is  not improbable  in   view   of   theinveterate hatred of the Yemenitesfor the Turks. The  Si)ltan&apos;s   attitudecompromise  between  an,                          is   a                          lophilesentiments and fear  of the Turksat Lahej.  He visited Said Pashaat  Lahej in January, 1916, and again this month, and is believed to  be  in receipt of a  Turkishsubsidy.   He  pleads force majeureas excuse for his  dealings with theTurks.   His British  stipend  hasbeen withheld, and  Shughrah. theprincipal  port of  Fadli,  placed under an embargo.  Anglophile.  On the 21st May,1916,  Said Pasha,  the  Turkishcommander  at   Lahej,  wrotedemanding  Sir  Ghalib&apos;s  submission-sion.   The  latter   ignored   theletter, and  forwarded it  to  thePolitical. Resident at Aden.   SirGhalib presses for some evidenceof  British  co-operation,  in  theavailable.    Somegunners have been trained  at  Adenfor Idrisi, and hehas been sent 3515-pr.  held  gnus.He is said to havea standing  forceof 500 negroes.  (f.) Tehama  isthe lowland stripbetween the red sea and the mari-tirne ranges. (,(/.) These tribesare openly hostile to the Turks.  TheHashid wa Bakil,of whose hostagesto   the   ImamMohammed Yahiasecured  the  re-lease, in Decemberprof erred   their services  io Idrisiin  the  event *.ofno  reconciliationtaking     place between  him andthe Imam.  (A.)  Close  con-nection is  main-taiued   betweenMokalla and  theArab   colony  inJava.  InDccem-ber, 1916,applica-tion was made for permission for 600
Confederation or tribe and ruler.	District.	Fighting-strength.	Political tendencies.	Remarks.Fadli cont. Kathiri (i). Sultan   Mausur Kathiri.	The country between Terira and Siyurn in the Llidramaut hin-terland.	10,000-15,000	shape of a subsidy, to enable him to conciliate his wavering tribes-men, and his application has been strongly supported by the Resi-dent&apos; at Aden. His authority is being undermined by the Kathiri Suit an who is intriguing with the Turks The Kathiri are hereditary enemies of the Kaiti family to which Sir Ghalib belongs. The Kathiri were dispossessed of Mokalla and Shiheir in the seventies of the last century by the Kaiti supported by the British. and consequently there is a feud between them and the Kai&apos;i. There is a Tuikish agent in the Hadramant, and the Kathiri are profiting by the moral, if not by the financial, support of the Turks, to weaken the position of Sir Ghalib. Nuie. In spite of the blockade intercourse is still maintained between the Turks in Arabia and their sympathisers in Africa. Small quantities of provisions reach them in this way, and communications pass to and fro. Said Pasha had correspondence with Negus Michael, and was expecting the dethroned Fmperor of Abyssinia, Lij Yasu, about the loth January.	Arabs to proceed to Mokaila from Java to see their relatives. This intercourse ia stated by the British consul at Batavia to be normal. (i.) There is a considerable colony of Kathiri Aiabi in singapore-pore, where they have important vested interest, which would poa-sib&apos;y be imperilled ia the event of hostilities di-lected by the Kathiri against t h e British Government.HliJAZ.                                 . English G.O.C.    Sir R. Wingate was informed by the Foreign Office on the 3rd February [No. 81]that, the Cabinet had decided that he should  be regarded as G.O.C. in Hejaz, and thatin that capacity he should be under the direct orders of the War Office.                      An Inquiry in regard to Colonel Wilson.     Mr. Balfour telegraphed to Sir  R. Wingate on the 3rd February [No. 83] sayingthat the French Government had inquired as to Colonel Wilson having asked for and obtained from King Hussain the original of the letter received by him from the french president.   Mr. Bnlfour proposed answering that Colonel Wilson had neither asked fornor received the original letter, but that it was understood that King Hussain had senthim a copy thereof:  he asked whether this was correct.  On the 5th February Sir R.Wingate replied [No. 106] that the proposed reply was correct.                          Arab Officers for King Hussain.     With reference to the enquiry in regard to the sending of Arab officers, prisonersof war in Russia, to King Hussain, the Arab Bureau  telegraphed  on the 4th February[A.B. 694] that since the first application for such officers  had been made conditionshad changed.  Experience showed; that, senior  or  elderly  officers  were unsuitable;qualified doctors, and young officers (politically sound) competent to instruct Arabdrafts at Mecca in artillery and machine gun duties were required.               Purchase of House in Mecca by the French Government.    Sir R.  Wiugate  telegraphed  on  the 29th  January [No. 79] that he  had received information that six days previously a large building  in Mecca had been purchased bythe French Government.
 ADEN.     The G.O.C. telegraphed on the  5th February [No. 233] that the importation of karbi into Aden from Lahej had been stopped  by the Turks for the past week.  There were renewed reports of political intrigues with tribes in the east of the protectorate. KOWEIT.                               Death of the Shayhh.     Sir P. Cox telegraphed on the 5th February  that the Shaykh of  Koweit died on that day.  On the 6th  February he telegraphed further [No. 910] that Shaykh Salim Ibn Mubarak, aged about 50,  had succeeded his brother  in  the  shaykhship subject to our concurrence, which there was no  reason  to  withhold.   He had intimated his readiness to accept all  his  predecessors obligations  towards the  British  Government. IT.MS. &quot; Bramble&quot; had arrived on the 5th, and all was quiet. NEJD.                          &apos;&apos;     Sir P. Cox telegraphed on the  1st February [No.766] that a number of letter from Ibn Saud had arrived for him and for the  Shaykh of Mohammerah.  Ibn  Saud also forwarded a letter from the  King  of Hejaz, signed &quot; Kine of Arabian countries,&quot; which he thought justified the suspicions he had  expressed.  He also  reported that  a certain Saiyid Mohammed Abdullah-al-Utq, who was at  Constantinople on  the outbreak of the war, tried to make  his way to Yemen, of which he was a native, but  was detained at  Medina.   He  appears to  have induced Sherif Haidar  to allow  him to leave on cOBdition that he delivered certain letters at Hail, which place he avoided and took the letters  to  Qasim.  Pie said  in a  letter to  Ibn Saud that  the Turks realised  his (Ibn Saud&apos;s) importance  and  greatly regretted having alienated him  and would  give &quot; half they possessed &quot;  to win him  back ; he (Ibn  Saud)  had only to say what he wanted and  he would get  it  at once.   He asked  for  a personal meeting  as he  had matters  to explain.   This seems to suggest that he had  a mission to Ibn  Saud ; if so, he might be connected with a mission recently reported to have been sent  from Medina with the object of protesting to Ibn Saud against the seizure of Ibn Faroon&apos;s camels. JEBEL SHAMMAR.     According to information from Nejef,  dated December 1916, a  confederation in opposition to the Turks  exists  among some  of the tribes in the vicinity of Nejef and Hillahj mostly subsections  of  the Khazail. &quot;Twelve  tribal  sections are mentioned as being  parties to  this confederation, and  they probably provide  a  fighting strength of between 2,000 and 3,000 men.                                     SYRIA.                            Court-martial at Damascus.     The newspaper &quot;El  share &quot; of the 11th December last reports  that  the  court- martial at Damascus on the 30th November charged  Abdel Sattar el-Senderusi, Plakki el-Azm, B,efik el-Azm, Shaykh Beshid Bida, and  his  brother Shaykh Saleh, Dr. Abdel Kahman Shahbandar, Abdel  Fattah  el-Yafi,  Hassan  Daher, Hassan  el-Bassrawi, Abaalla  el-Mosalli, Sherif Ahmed, Sherif Faisal,  Nessibel-Bakri, and  Fauzi el-Bakri, with the crime of organising a revolutionary society.   A  delay often days was granted them to report&apos; themselves at the said court for trial.   If they failed to obey this order they would be considered deprived of all rights of citizenship, would be  tried in default, and  all their properties  would be confiscated.     The Arab Bureau  notes  in regard to this that Plakki and Befik belong to the Damascus branch of the great and once  powerful  Azm family ; they are  cousins,  and both now in  Cairo;  they  are not  out-and-out  rebels; the first desires  a French protectorate in Syria,  the  other autonomy under  Turkish suzerainty.   Shaykh Beshid Rida, of Kalamun, near  Tripoli, now in Cairo, is the well-known Pan-Arab chauvinistic agitator and preacher, whose activities extend from  Cairo to India.  He  preached at the mosque at Mina before the Sherif&apos;during the last  Haj, but was checked when  his remarks became fanatical.   Dr. Abdurrahman  Shahbander, of Damascus,  has  been in medical charge of the  Meadi prisoners of war, and  is now on the staff of the &quot; Kawkab &quot; at Cairo.  Sherif Ahmed may  be Ahmed  el-Mansur, Emir of the  Plarb,  now helping the King of Hejaz.   Sherif Faisal is the third son of King Hussain, and will not be  easilycaught.
                                      IRAK.BASRA.                           The Proposed Indian Mosque.    In regard to the proposed  mosqus  of Indians  at Basra, for  which  the  Nizampromised a subscription of 25,000 rupees, certain questions  have been raised      ]. Is the mosque to be for Indians only ?    2. Are Arabs to be excluded therefrom ?    3. Is this to bj a permanent Indian Wakf in Basra ?                                    -PERSIA.FARS.    The Secretary of State for India telegraphed to the Viceroy on  the 30th January[No. 3436] saying that, to render the position of the South Persian Rifles  at  Shirazmore  secure, the Government of  India had been instructed to send  reinforcementsimmediately.  The Cabinet felt great  hesitation in  superseding Sir P. Sykes by ageneral on the active list ; such a change would affect his  position  so injuriously thatit was hardly likely that he would  consent to remain as  CP.O. to the general whosuperseded him.   The Cabinet  also  felt that such an  appointment  might give  to theSouth Persian Rifles and the whole situation a military appearance which might justlyexcite the suspicions of the Persian Government.    It has been  established beyond doubt that various  hostile khans  of the Bushirehinterland had formed a league against  us, and that  the recent coup on the Bushire-Shiraz road was the result of their united action.    Sir C. Marling on the 3rd February transmitted [No. 48] a telegram sent  by theBritish consul at  Shiraz on the previous day, in  the course of which he said that allposts  on the road towards Bushire were now  in  the hands of the enemy,  had  been evacuated by the South Persia  Rifles.  No posts  were moving on  the Bushire  road ;all posts from Shiraz for the south  went to Lingah and Bunder Abbas.THE BAKHTIARI.    The Secretary of State  for India telegraphed  to  the Viceroy on the 30th Januaryin regard to the Bakhtiari levies.  He said that  His  Majesty&apos;s Government wished itto be understood that the force was   not  intended  for  military operations ;  it was essentially civil, and its  movements must be governed  by  the views  of the british minister at Tehran.  On matters other than the  internal economy of the force, CaptainNoel should look for guidance  to the  consul-general at Ispahan, but  he should keep inclose touch with the G.O.C. at Basra, who would  defer execution of any plan which he might think  undesirable  on  military grounds.   Ou  the other hand,  Bakhtiari politicsare outside the sphere of the G.O.C., and Colonel Cox should be consulted in his capacity as Resident, not as C.P.O.                       INDIA AND  ITS  NEIGHBOURS.INDIA.                          Indian Seditionaries in Japan.    On the 2nd December last the British Ambassador at Tokio transmitted a despatch from the vice-consul at Yokohama in regard to Indian seditionaries in Japan; the vice-consufs despatch covered reports  from two  Indian secret service agents, which showthat Japan is  an active  centre  for  Indian  sedition, and  that the seditionaries areencouraged  by the  Japanese.   The  Ambassador  drew  attention  to  the insidiouscharacter of a soi-disant &quot;industrial and commercial mission&quot; from Southern India ;the individuals composing it were in sympathy with the seditionaries, but they bore ageneral letter of introduction to British consuls in Japan from the Resident in Mysore.AFGHANISTAN.    The Viceroy telegraphed  on  the  3rd February that a former servant of Wagners,bearing  a  German  message, had  been  captured.   The message  was  dated Herat,11th January, and signed &quot;Wagner.&quot;  Among other things,  it said that the Amirdared make no war preparations from  fear  of the English, who were said to threaten him with war.       [898-29]                                                         D
                                    PART II.                              FROM  THE  PRESS.                         The Grand Sherifs Proclamation.                        To the Editor of the &quot; Morning Post.&quot;Sir,     Some  months  ago, after defeating  the Turks, the Sherif of Mecca issued a mostimportant  proclamation, which was addressed by him to &quot; All our Moslem brothers.&quot;The  Proclamation  pointed out that the  heaviest share of the calamities which hadovertaken  the  Moslem world  were due to the Committee of Union and Progress  inTurkey (the Young Turk Party) who had attacked and desecrated the Holy Places ofthe Moslem Faith, namely, Mecca and Medina.   The Proclamation continues:          &quot;The Committee  of Union and Progress  have  done  three wrongs to the     Mohammedan religion.   Firstly,  the bombardment  of the  Ancient House which     God has chosen for Himself.  Secondly, they set fire to the Holy Carpet; and,     thirdly, the Tomb of Abraham was struck by their desecration.&quot;     The Grand Sherif&apos; ends his Proclamation with  these important words :          &quot; Our independence is complete and absolute ; our aim is the  preservation  of     Islam.   We trust  that in all  parts of the world each of our brethren will do his     duty as  is incumbent upon  him, so that the  bonds of  the  brotherhood  of Islam     may be confirmed.&quot;     The Indian  Government may have taken  some action  with regard to the aboveProclamation, though I much doubt it, judging from the fact that it has taken two anda-half years of war to force them into issuing a War Loan : but if they have not, may i suggest to them  that this  Proclamation of the High  Priest  and religious  Chief ofIslam should be  translated into all the dialects  of Northern India, and distributedbroadcast by our recruiting agents and others to  every Mohammedan in India?  Copiesshould also be issued to all  our Mohammedan soldiers in Mesopotamia, and to ourIndian regiments fighting in Africa  and elsewhere.     The Proclamation would carry great weight and  have a far-reaching effect, as it shows clearly that the British  Government is fighting, not  against Islam, but  against those who  have  desecrated the  Holy  Places and have attempted to overthrow theMohammedan religion.     The Indian Government cannot too forcibly point out to  our Mohammedan fellow-subjects that we are, in fact, fighting a  &quot; Jehad&quot; or Holy War  against the Turks  andtheir German masters.                                   Yours, Sic.                                       F. C.  CULLING CARR, Hon. Secretary.     The British Empire Union, 346, Strand             February 5, 1917:                          The Fate of Turkey in Europe.[This is a translation of an article in the  &quot;Figaro&quot; of the 22nd  January, written by         M. Gabriel Hanotaux, formerly French Minister of Foreign Affairs.]     There is one passage of  truly exceptional importance in the commentary added byMr. Balfour to the note sent by the Allies the passage regarding the expulsion of theTurks from Europe.   That England should have taken so firm a stand in regard tothis is a matter of considerable  historical significance.     For a  couple of  centuries  England and Russia  were absolutely opposed one to theother in regard to the fate of Turkey ;  and, as a matter of fact, this opposition was thewhole &quot;Eastern  question.&quot;  Not only did England  on every occasion  declare itself infavour of the maintenance of the Ottoman Empire, but in Turkey itself she persistently
                                         11 encouraged reforms which could save the empire by bringing it into line with European civilisation.   Trying to achieve this she lavished on Turkey not only advice and money,i but also the blood  of her soldiers and sailors.  England versus Russia in the East recalled the  famous fight of the whale and the elephant.     And now, Mr. Balfour, speaking in the name of a coalition government, declares that the idea of reforming Turkey to give it a continued existence is unrealisable, that the Turkey of the Yourig Turks (that is to say, of the soi-disant reformers) is at least as barbarous and much more aggressive than th&quot;t  of Abdul fiamid.   In  a word, the  old antagonism is dead,  and  from now  England regards as desirable the settlement  of  the Eastern Question  by the expulsion of the Turks and the predominance of Russia in those  parts.     International history and the diplomatic problem are thus moved to a new plane. Turkey has  herself denounced the treaties which  protected her, and one hastens to say, according its logical result to this imprudent act:  &quot; You only formed part  of  the European concert  in virtue  of these solemn  agreements ; you have withdrawn from them; very  well, you will never renew them.&quot;  The conscience  of civilised peoples  has thus  been freed  from  a  heavy  and  almost unbearable weight.   For  the  future Germany alone will be charged with the  full  and entire responsibility of maintaining in Europe a government which has been guilty, in Armenia and Syria, of the most terrible massacres recorded by history,  even  in  those unhappy countries.   It is  true that Germany does not  look at  the  matter  so closely.  Those responsible  for the Belgian massacres and deportations need not blush at walking hand-in-hand with their Oriental partners.  Prussian militarism has applied the janissary doctiae to Europe: squireen or pasha, it is all one.  Let uy keep them to the political  considerations.     From the fact that England and the western Powers, having accepted the Russian view,  are igreed that one  of the objects of the war is the expulsion of&apos; the Turks from Europe, it follows  that Turkey has lost her time-honoured defenders.   It needed  the impudence of an Enver Pasha to write (as he did  in the answer of the Porte to the note of the Allies) that  &quot; like her allies, Turkey would be obliged to take up arms to defend her territory, her liberty, and  her independence.&quot;  Who, one asks, threatened them at  the moment Turkey declared for war.     The truth  is that Turkey, having freely declared against the western Powers, will learn, when  peace comes in sight,  what their support meant for her.  It is quite evident that she will not manage by herself; and who is left to help her 1  Austria and German)-.     As for Austria, Turkey is an old foe, and  if she were i^econs-tiiuted in the  Balkan peninsula she would  become a dangerous enemy, for she would be a military power ; and Austria worked the great diplomatic intrigue which has thrown us all into war in order that she might not have a military power against her in the Balkans.   The Austria of the Plabsburgs never  has  been and never can be Turcophil.   And an Empire so weak that it can  only  be maintained  by the weakness  of  others would be a frail enough support for that of the Turk.   But what of Germany ?     Germany has  ambitions which stretch far into  the Ea,st, ambitions aiming at Anatolia, Persia, and even, it is said, India.   The only  means of working out this great plan is the economic, administrative, and political conquest of Turkey.   Germany then could  support Turkey,  but only as the rope supports  a man who is being hanged. Germany, moreover,  will never reach its end otherwise than by jumping over Austria, the Balkan Slavs,  and, finally, the Turks themselves.   This being so, will the influence of Germany  on the morrow of the war spread to those  regions, regions  whose future is so dubious?  Germany without doubt  will have plenty  of other fish to  fry without throwing herself into any costly and uncertain enterprise.  The idea of the partisans of &quot; greatest Germany&quot;  continuing  to annex the  world is now  simply farcical :  their ambitions have for long to come been set aside.  At the present price of the mark, Bagdad is too dear.   And  then, Turkey herself is so near collapse a poor affair !  The  safety of the Turkish Empire will  soon be a  matter of  but third-rate importance to German diplomatists.     If  she can once  extricate herself Germany will never again  wantonly plunge into the Balkan slough  ; doubtless she will come back  to Bismarcks teaching and his famous saying about the bones of the Pomeranian grenadier. ....  Plow many of those  bones are now lying bleaching in  Eastern fields, just as the old fox foresaid ?     The surest and the first victim of the  present war &quot;will  be Turkey.   Since  the Entente Powers have erased it from the  map  of Europe,  or rather since she has done away  with herself,  the Central Empires will have neither  wish nor power to re-establish her.  At the best,  in the event of an impossible success, they  would arrange between themselves to conquer her,  to enslave her, and to  divide her.41
    Mr.&apos; Balfour says wisely and authoritatively that tile disappearance of Turkey willbe a  great blessing  and a means of quickly reaching a  settlement  of the  terribleEuropean crisis ;  and what Mr.  Balfour says, everyone thinks.  The Government of the-United States has never been very enthusiastic in regard to the assassins of Syrians&apos;andArmenians; and this part of Mr. Balfour&apos;s note will fix  its attention.   It is said  thatGermany spontaneously offered Constantinople to Russia to  obtain  a  separate peace.The initiative then came from the friends of Turkey ; and it is only just that the Turksshould learn the true value of &quot;  a scrap of paper.&quot;PRINTED AT THE FOREIGN OFFICSt BT C,  E. HAKM30X.-21/2/1917.

</content>
</cab>
