<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/177/24 images: 231-233</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(74) 74 COPY NO15 July 1974CABINETV LONDON WEIGHTINGMemorandum by the Secretary of State for employment. We need to take stock of our position on the Pay Board&apos;s report inthe light of the various London weighting negotiations and the fresh fact ofthe Trades Union Congress (TUC) Conference called for next Wednesday,2,        The Governments position, as I stated it on 1 July, is to allow freenegotiation on London Weighting while commending to negotiators theprinciples of the Pay Board&apos;s report as affording the most comprehensivefactual basis for settlement which is fair to the rest of the country as wellas to London.    If those outside London think that London weighting is being increased beyond reasonable bounds they will try to follow with inflationary&apos;   effect.    This is what worries a number of manual unions who do not favourlarge increases in London weighting and this is the case for trying toencourage negotiators to keep to the principles of the report.3.        So far this position has been maintained in the public sectornegotiations.    The local authority employers have refused to exceed the kitty provided by the  400 and  200 figures; so have the Gas Counciland the Burnham Committee; and the police negotiators are due to make an offer consistent with the report next Tuesday.4.        There has, however, been no sign yet of any union involved being prepared to settle on this basis.   Indeed, the National and LocalGovernment Officers&apos; Association - who are concerned in severalnegotiations - seem less concerned at the moment to negotiate than to press employers to exceed the Pay Board figures under the threat of further industrial action.    With teachers the Government are in thefront line as employer and the National Union of Teachers are especiallyset on raising the  200 limit for outer London where most of their Londonmembers are.5.        There is the unhelpful prospect that the clearing banks - unless theycan be dissuaded - will, later this week, make an agreement with theNational Union of Bank Employees giving larger sums than  200 to peoplewithin a 10-mile limit.    They will thus breach the Pay Board&apos;s principles and the insurance companies will probably quickly follow suit.i 0w- . tir&apos;.&apos;&apos;r1
6.        A marked feature ofthe situation is the confusion which now appearsto exist about the Governments position.   London Labour MPs, employersand unions are all pressing to know whether the Government really mean that there can be free negotiation or whether the Pay Board&apos;srecommendations must be followed.    This question has arisensharply with the teachers where there is the possibility of using the Government veto to stop any settlement which breaches the pay board&apos;s report; and is expected to come to the fore at the Conferenceof unions that the TUC are holding next Wednesday on the subject.    Itis quite possible that the Conference will end with the TUC general secretary being commissioned to seek from me an explicit assurance that the Pay Board report is not seen by Government, either generally or as employer, as a strait-jacket but simply as guidance to negotiatorswho will have the responsibility of deciding whether and how it should applyto their particular circumstances.7,        With these developments, actual and prospective, in mind it seemsto me that:-I.        I should be prepared to give such an assurance to the TUC ifthey seek it.   This would be no more than a clarification of my statement of 1 July which left the responsibility squarely onnegotiators to reach settlements, even if these were not entirely in line with the Pay board&apos;s report; and since then; the localauthority employers have been told that there is nothing to stopthem exceeding the kitty given by the Pay Board&apos;s figures if theydecide that this is necessary for a settlement.   At the same time would repeat that; in so far as the case for London weighting isone of the compensation for additional cost, negotiators need to take account of the Pay Board1 s conclusions if increases in Londonweighting are not to favour Londoners at the expense of the restof the country,ii. The Government, as employer, should still try to getsettlements consistent with the Pay Board&apos;s principles and ought not themselves to lead the breach, eg with the teachers or police.So long as we can get other members of the management panels torefuse to go along with a breach of the Pay Board!s principles atthis stage, we should not be disturbed even if this does mean that negotiations run on or even break down for a time.    The teachers,for example, are in a weak position with the end of term comingsoon and they are the group which have had the most done for themby the Government.iii. Nonetheless, it will not do for us to adopt a rigid attitude byruling out in advance any possibility of some departure from the pay board&apos;s report.    To do that - for example, by contemplating a vetoin Burnham on any settlement which did so depart - would expose theGovernment to charges of not allowing free negotiation and put us inan untenable position if the banks or others eventually breach the pay board*s report.8.        I invite my colleagues to agree with the approach proposed in thepreceding paragraph.M department of Employment15 July 1974


</content>
</cab>
