<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/49/36 images: 375-379</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cm (71)36th conclusions copy No. 11CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1. on Thursday, 1 July, 1971,at 11.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,mp, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph,mp, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,mp, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for the Environ-ment the Right Hon. James Prior, m p,Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber,mp, Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,qc, mp, Chancellor of the duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Margaret Thatchermp, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,mp, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Secretary of State for Trade andIndustry and President of the Boardof trade the following were also presentThe Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Sir Peter Rawlinson,q c, m p, Attorney general secretariat :Sir Burke trend sir William nield mr. P. E. thornton mr. R. H. F. Croft
SubjectEuropean Economic CommunitiesDraft White Paper
ConclusionsMinutes 1 and european The Cabinet considered the text of a draft White Paper onEconomic       British membership of the European Communities circulated underCommunities   cover of a note by the Secretary of the Cabinet (CP(71)76).Draft white paper The Prime Minister said that the draft White Paper indicatedPrevious that it was the firm and considered intention of Her Majesty&apos;sj^erence: Government to seek the approval of Parliament in the early autumnSlfwLi3rd for a decision OI principle to take up full membership of the communities on the basis of the arrangements which had been negotiated with them. It was important that, if this statementreflected the Cabinefs view, they should record a formal decision in that sense. They would also need to consider whether they approved the broad structure of the draft and whether there were&apos; , any major points with which it failed to deal adequately. A numberof Ministers had suggested detailed drafting amendments; andthese, together with any further suggestions of this kind would betaken into account when the final text was produced.In discussion it was agreed that the White Paper should makeit clear that the Government recommended that the United kingdom should become a member of the European Communities on thebasis of the arrangements which had now been negotiated.In further discussion the following main points were made:(a) The section of the White Paper dealing with the economic consequences of our entry into the Communities made too muchof the costs of membership and not enough of the benefits. Therewas no need to provide specific figures for the costs in the 1980s,since any forecasts for a period so far ahead were bound to be highly speculative. Moreover, it was unnecessary to follow theprocedure adopted by the previous Government in the White paper of February, 1970, and to provide statistical estimates of the so-called&quot; impact&quot; costs of the tariff changes which would result from our entry. Instead, the White Paper should maintain that in the early years of our membership British industry would be affected by twoopposing influences. On the one hand, the gradual phasing out and sharing of our preferences in certain markets, especially in theCommonwealth and EFTA, would adversely affect our exporters&apos;competitive power. On the other hand, the wider marketopportunities and intensified competition afforded by membership would stimulate a greater dynamism and efficiency in industry.In the outcome our competitive power should be strengthened andwe should be enabled to meet the balance of payments cost.(b) Some parts of the draft appeared to gloss over some of theproblems which would be raised by our membership. For example,paragraph 30 of Part I went too far in suggesting that we should never face a choice involving in some sense a sacrifice of nationalsovereignty. The passages of the draft which dealt with the issue of sovereignty should be revised in order to make it clear that, as members of the Community, we should continue to exercise theright of a sovereign State to endorse collective decisions when itSECRET136611-6 B*
appeared to be in our own interests to do so. A paragraph should alsobe added to explain how the application of Community legislation to this country would affect our legal system.(c) A paragraph should be added to the draft explaining that membership of the Community would not prevent us from continuing to pursue vigorous regional development policies.(d) The section of the draft which explained the arrangements under which we would be joining the European Coal and steel community should be revised in order to deal with the criticismsmade in the course of the debate in the House of Commons on theprevious day.(e) We could not be certain about the outcome of the further discussions which the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster wouldbe having with Ministers of the Community countries on 12 Julyconcerning fisheries policy. We had hoped that Ministers of theother applicant countries would also attend this meeting; but theNorwegian and Danish Governments had declined to be represented.It appeared that they hoped in the autumn to obtain a morefavourable change in the Community&apos;s existing access provisions thanthe Community would be willing to give us on 12 July. Accordinglyit might become necessary for us for the present simply to seek agreement that we and the other applicant countries should maintain our existing fishing regimes until the enlarged Community could agree on a new common fisheries policy. Paragraphs 81 and 82of Part II of the draft should be redrafted accordingly.(/). Further thought should be given to the presentation of theprice increases likely to result from our application of the common agricultural policy. It should be made clear that for most of thepopulation these price increases should be more than offset by increases in real earnings resulting from more rapid economic growth.It should also be made clear that the next review of retirement pensions in early 1973 would take place before the price rises resultingfrom entry would occur, since we should not be taking our first steps towards applying the common agricultural policy until April to july 1973. But the White Paper should avoid any implication thatfamily allowances would necessarily be increased to compensate for price rises. It would be preferable to concentrate so far aspossible on the potentially favourable impact of accession on ourstandard of living.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the forthcoming White Paper should make itclear that Her Majesty&apos;s Government intended to seek the approvalof Parliament for a decision that the United Kingdom should join the European Communities. He would now arrange for a final text of the White Paper to be prepared, for publication on Wednesday7 July, taking into account the detailed amendments proposed by individual Ministers and the points made in discussion.The Cabinet-(1)  Took note with approval of the Prime Minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.
(2) Agreed that the forthcoming White Paper should make itclear that Her Majesty&apos;s Government intended to seekParliaments approval for a decision that the UnitedKingdom should join the European Communities.(3) Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for afinal text of the White Paper to be prepared, taking account of the points made in discussion and of otherdetailed amendments proposed by Ministers.(4) Agreed that the White Paper should be published onWednesday, 7 July.Cabinet Office,1 July, 1971.

</content>
</cab>
