<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/67/26 images: 170-173</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
3&apos;his document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government90Printed for the Cabinet, July, 1945TOP SECRETCP. (45) 7612th July, 1945The circulation of this  paper  has  beenstrictty   limited.     it   is   issued   for   the personal use of copy No.   J &amp;cabinet india: CONSTITUTIONAL position memorandum  BY THE SECRETARY  OF STATE  FOR WARI should like to put in writing what I have tried evidently unsuccessfully tomake clear both at the India Committee and the Cabinet for months past, viz., that whatever the Viceroy and the Secretary of State for India think they are doing with india they are in fact handing it over to the big Indian industrialists who have ever since the foundation of Congress in 1885 been the greatest enemies not only of theBritish connection but also of the true interests of the great Indian masses. So long asit paid these people, they pursued their ends by subsidising Congress in general and individual Congress leaders in particular to carry on an ultra-nationalist and anti-British agitation ending even in armed rebellion. Through Congress they exercisedpressure lor high protection, boycott of British imports, legislation making it moreand more difficult for British businesses in India to carry on, the extrusion of british personnel from Government posts and so on. But they have begun to get a bitfrightened of their own Frankenstein because at least one prominent Congress leader,viz., Nehru, is at heart anti-industrialist and probably Communist. They know thatNehru has only been kept from openly showing himself in his true colours towards themby his inherited personal devotion to Gandhi and they realise that even Gandhi is notimmortal.The industrialists have, however, been cunning enough to get Nehru tied up to oneheavy insurance in their favour, viz., the so-called Bombay industrialisation plan.This is a wild and chimerical scheme for spending thousands of non-existent croresin no time on lines very similar to the Soviet 5-year plans except that in India theindustrialists and they alone are to be exempted from totalitarian control.Now in the light of this let us look at the Viceroy&apos;s proposed allocation of Port-folios in his new Council.Finance. Mallhai. An Indian Christian personally well known to me. Fromignorance or vice he has been an extreme economic nationalist even when hewas a Government servant. He was at one time Chairman of the Indian tariff board and has usualty produced reports in favour of very high protection.When I was in India I suspected him of being venal and since I left he hasbecome a paid servant of the biggest industrial firm in India (whose mainbusiness incidentally was the subject of one of his Tariff Board reports).Technically he is quite unfitted to be Finance Member.Commerce. Palel. Possibly Gandhi&apos;s closest confidant. Venomously anti-British, probably the main instigator of the 1942 rebellion. Notoriously in closeliaison with the Bombay commercial interests.Planning and Reconstruction. Nehru. For some time he and Patel will marchtogether on the lines of the Bombay plan. When Gandhi dies the alliance may break but this old man looks after his life very carefully.I know that the Viceroy and the Secretary of State for India say &quot; but our avowedpolicy is to hand India over to Indians and we must face the consequences howeverunpleasant &quot;. For my part I cannot so easily reconcile myself to the shame of abandon-ing 400 millions of Indians to a few scores of men who have no social consciencewhatever and in comparison with whom the millowners and mineowners of the i8oo&apos;sin this country were angels of kindness. And we haven&apos;t even the consolation of being able to say that these people have been elected by the Indian people. In this sense theyarc not one whit more responsible than the Viceroy&apos;s present Executive Council.P. J. G.The War Office,nth July, 1945.(B45/O7)    no   7/45   W.O.P.   22955




</content>
</cab>
