<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/13/0 images: 97-98</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL-&apos;- WAR   CABINETG..T.709.Draft Statement on Imperial War Cabinet.It has been suggested that a statement should be made by the Prime Minister in the House of Commons, and by Lord Curson in the House of Lords, on the meetings of the Imperial War Cabinet.    . By direction of the Prime Minister the following draft Statement is circulated.     It has been approved by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.I wish to ask leave of the House to make a statement in r.egard to an innovation in our constitutional procedure, the session of an Imperial War Cabinet.     In this time of War it has been inevitable that this new procedure should not have attracted the public/attention -which would normally have been given to it,&quot;arid the Government feel that they should give the House as full information about it, as Is possible under present circumstances.You will remember that late In December last an Invitation was extended to the Prime Ministers of the self-governing Dominions to attend &quot;a series of special and continuous meetings of the War Cabinet to consider urgent questions affecting the prosecution of the War, the possible conditions on which, in agreement with cur Allies, we cou^^agsgnj-^to its termination,  aid the problems which would tneniarise.&quot;      An invitation was also sent to the Viceroy of ;iIndia asking him to send representatives from India to assist the Secretary of State..   These invitations were all accepted except in the case cf &quot;Australia, whose Ministers, to our very great regret, were unable to attend owing to an Impending general election,    The other delegates, at great personal sacrifice and risk to themselves, assembled In London during the early part of March.    Since then there have been 14 meetings of what has come to be called the Imperial War Cabinet to differentiate it from the ordinary War Cabinet of the British Isles,   There have also been a number of meetings of an Imperial War Conference under the chairmanship of the Secretary of State for the Colonies, to discuss such aspects of Imperial policy as were net-directly concerned with war and peace.   The resolutions passed by t/.;*.fj Conference have already been published.While the Imperial:War Cabinet has been in session its overseas members have had access to all the information which is at the disposal of His Majesty1s Government and have occupied a status cf absolute equality with that of the members of the British War Cabinet...
It has had prolonged discussions on all the most vital aspects of imperial policy,  and has come to important decisions in re-.?ard to them - decisions which will enable us to prosecute the War with increased unity and vigour, and which vail be of im-mense value when it comes to the negociation of peace.   The conclusions of the Imperial War Cabinet are of necessity secret, but there is one aspect of thorn which we feel ought to be comma-nicated to the House without delay.   The Imperial War     Cabinet was unanimous that the experiment has been of the greatest service, not only to all its members but to the Empire,  and that the precedent ought not to be allowed to fall into d suetude. Accordingly at the last session,  I proposed formally on behalf of the British Government,, that the meetings of an Imperial Cabinet should be held annually or at any intermediate time when matters of urgent imperial concern require to be settled,  and that the Imperial Cabinet should consist&apos;of the prime Minister of the United Kingdom,  ana such of his colleagues as deal specially with imperial affairs,  of the Prime Minister of each of the Dominions,  or some specially accredited alternate pos-sessed of equal authority,  and of a representative from India to be appointed by the Government of India.    This proposal met with the cordial approval of the Overseas Representatives and we hope that the holding of an annual Imperial Cabinet to dis-cuso Foreign Affairs and other aspects of Imperial policy, will become an accepted convention &amp;f. the British Constitution.I ought to add that the institution in its present form is extremely elastic.   It grew not by design, but out of the necessities of the War.   The essence of it is that the responsible heads of the governments of the.Empire., with those ministers who are specially entrusted with the conduct of imperial policy should meet together at regular intervals to confer about foreign policy and matters connected therewith, and come to decisions in regard to them, which subject to the control of their own. Parliaments, they will then severally execute.   By this means they will be able to obtain full information about ail aspects of Imperial affairs, and to determine by consulta-tion together the policy of the Empire in its most vital aspects, without infringing in any degree the autonomy which its part3 at present enjoy.   What the consequences of this development and especially what the relation of an Imperial Cabinet to the Imperial Conference should be, wo did not attempt to settle. The whole question of perfecting the mechanism for &quot;continuous consultation&quot; about Imperial and Foreign Affairs between the ^autonomous nations of an Imperial Commonwealth&quot; will be reserved for the consideration of that special conference which will be summoned as soon as possible after the &quot;War to readjust the constitutional relations of the Empire.   We felt however, that the experiment of constituting an Imperial Cabinet, and&apos;of admitting India to its deliberations had been so fruitful in cotter understanding and in unity of purpose and action, that it ought to be perpetuated, and we believe that this proposal will commond itself to the judgment cf all our peonies.12th May,  191^r

</content>
</cab>
