<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/13/0 images: 262-300</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
EDUCATION BILL, 1917.1. THE draft Education Bill which accompanies this Memorandum is, though some of its clauses cannot be regarded as settled, so far advanced as regards its main provisions that I may ask the Government to consider, and, if they think fit, to approve it. On the 20th February the War Cabinet approved generally the proposals set out in my memoranda of the 2nd and 5th February, and this Bill gives effect to those proposals which require legislation.The Bill does not deal with the question of religious instruction, nor is the position of voluntary schools affected, except by some clauses of minor importance which may fairly be classed as administrative provisions. They would undoubtedly conduce to convenient and efficient administration; but, if they prove highly controversial, they can be dropped without affecting the rest of the Bill. I am taking steps to ascertain the views of persons representing the interests of voluntary schools.The Bill also does not attempt to alter the system of Local Education Authorities established by the Education Act of 1902. Although the difficulty and inconvenience of organising the national system of education through so large a number of Authorities is great, and though the distinction between elementary and higher education, and the corresponding financial and administrative distinctions between Authorities possessing powers under Part III and under Part II of the Act of 1902 are illogical and involve much complication and embarrassment, I recognise that it would be unwise to expose this Bill to the risk of controversy and opposition which any attempt to deprive the existing Authorities of their powers, and to consolidate rating areas, would involve.Further, although the Bill incidentally places restrictions on the employment of children and young persons, it does so from the point or&apos; view of what is strictly necessary to give effect to the scheme of education which it embodies, rather than from the point of view of social reform.2. I append notes explanatory of the several clauses. As regards Clauses 10 (4), 13, and 14, I am in communication with the Home Office, which is speciaLy interested under the Employment of-Children Act, 1903; and, as regards Glauses 6, 15, 16, 17, 30, 31, and 35, with the Local Government Board, which is concerned partly in respect of arrangements for promoting the health and physical welfare of young children, and partly in respect; of its control over the finance of Local Education Authorities.3. Many of the most important features of my scheme for the development of education do not appear at all in this Bill, as they depend upon administrative and financial arrangements for which no new statutory authority is required. Among these I may mention the development of the organisation for the supply and training of teachers; the provision of scholarships and maintenance allowances; the development of university work, including medical and professional education, and the encouragement of students from the Dominions and Allied countries; and arrangements for relating the education system more closely to industry and/professions.The provision of a State system of pensions for teachers in secondary, technical, &amp;c, schools can most conveniently be dealt with in a separate Bill, which is in preparation.4. The principal features of the Bill are : (i.) (a.) The imposition, by Clauses 1 and 2, on Local Education Authorities of a duty to make provision for the progressive development and comprehensive organisation of higher as well as elementary education. Owing to the existing distinction between Part II and Part III of the Education Act of 1902, it is necessary to deal with Elementary Education, so far as autonomous Part III areas are concerned, in a separate clause ; but Clause 2 is complementary to Clause 1. By Clause 6 the limitation on the rating power of a County Council for higher education is removed. [608]
(b.) The establishment of the principle of educational administration on the basrj of schemes covering whole areas as distinguished from the basis of individual schools or particular branches of education.(c.) The establishment of the principle of co-operation between Local Education Authorities and the co-ordination and organisation of education in relation to areas larger than those of single Authorities. It is of course difficult to secure co-operation by Act of Parliament, but the specific provisions of Clauses 1, 2, and 3, together with the arrangements for the establishment of Provincial Associations contained in Clause 4, should, at all events, when backed by a broader system of State grants, contribute materially to advance in this respect.(ii.) The establishment, by Clauses 3, 10, 11, and 12, of a universal and compulsory system of continuation schools for young persons from the age of 14 to 18, involving attendance for 320 hours a year between the hours of 8 a.m. and 7 P.M. It has been represented to me that these provisions fall far short, especially as regards the amount of attendance required, of that which is desired by educational reformers, and particularly by that section of the industrial population which is represented by the Workers&apos; Educational Association. But, having- reffard to the fact that no nation has ever yet even attempted to establish such a system on a universal and compulsory basis, and to the great difficulty of securing the necessary supply of competent teachers, of providing accommodation, and of adapting the system to the conditions of industrial employment, and the new problems of administration involved, I am convinced that to aim at more in this measure would be to accomplish less. It is in my opinion very undesirable to place on the Statute Book an ambitious measure which may either remain as inoperative as a measure of Turkish reform or by its failure may bring discredit on the whole system and lead to reaction. In any case it will take a good many years to organise a really effective system of continuation schools for the whole population between the ages of 14 and 18 ; and, quite apart from the opposition of unenlightened employers (to some extent neutralised by the support which I am glad to think we shall receive from enlightened employers in the more highly organised and skilled trades), I feel that an extension of the system may safely be left to a future occasion. It will be observed, however, that in the proviso to Clause 10 (1) power is taken to increase the number of hours of attendance in any area with the consent of the Local Education Authority. The provisions regulating employment, so far as is necessary for attendance at continuation schools, are contained in Clauses 10 (4), 11, and 12. It will be observed that under these provisions an employer may be required not only to allow his employe sufficient time to reach and attend the continuation schools, but also sufficient time to secure that he may be in a fit mental and bodily condition to receive full benefit from attendance. i.e., so that he may not have to come to school dirty, hungry, or exhausted.(hi.) The raising, by Clause 8, of the age of obligator]&apos;&apos; attendance at public elementary schools to 14 (involving the abolition of &quot; half-time&quot;). Complementary to this are the provisions of Clauses 13 and 14 relating to the regulation of the employ-ment of children attending public elementary schools.These provisions must of course be read in connections with the provisions of Clause 2 for the development of elementary education, and Clause 19, in which it is proposed to abolish fees in public elementary schools.(iv.) The development of elementary education by means of central schools and classes (Clause 25).(v.) The provision (in Clause 17) for the establishment of nursery schools.(vi.) The extension (in Clauses 15 and 16) of the powers of Local Education Authorities relating to physical training and the school medical service.The importance of physical training is emphasised in the Bill (see Clause 3 (1) ), and the establishment oi a really national system of physical training is aimed at.(vii.) The provision (in Clause 21) for the collection of information as to the provision of education and the use made of it in the country as a whole. Apart from the general arguments in favour of such provision, it is of special importance in connection with Clauses 8 (4), 10 (2) (ii), (iii), and (iv), and iO (3). I carefully considered whether it would be possible to make all schools and educational institutions liable to inspection by the Board of Education, but I came with some regret to the conclusion that such a proposal would be too controversial. The Bill, however, includes (in Clause 20) a specific provision empowering the Board of Education to inspect any school or educational institution (not already liable to inspection) free of cost at the request of the governing body of the school.
^ii.) The provision for the future consolidation of grants for elementary educa-tion.5. I hope that the provisions of this Bill will, if it is backed by the necessary financial support from the Exchequer, go a long way to promote on broad lines that development of the public educational system which is generally recognised as essential to the strength and welfare of the nation. The new system of grants in aid of elementary education, for which 3,420,0001. has been provided by the Supplementary Estimate for the current year, is designed to be expansive. In my Memorandum of the 5th February 1 gave the following rough estimates of the cost of certain items :  Cost of raising the school age and abolishing half-time ..     about      500,000Cost of establishing nursery schools .. .. .. rising to     500,000Cost of compulsory continuation schools ou a 50 per cent, basis       ,,        3,000,000to&apos; &quot;V. 4,000,000-   -/Increased  grants  to  secondary  schools  and a reformed system of-&apos;-f     examinations . .. .. .. .. ..      500,000Establishment  of   a pension   system for secondary and   technicalteachers.   .. .. .. .. .. ..     about      130,000Training of teachers      .. .. .. .. ..        ,,        100,000Scholarships and bursaries .. .. .. .. ..      100,000rising to 300,000Increased grants for technical education    .. .. ..      100,000-,    - rising to200,000These are necessarily very provisional figures and the items are not exhaustive, but it is useless to think that the necessary development of education can be accomplished without the expenditure of very large additional sums by the State.6. It is indeed essential to recognise that this Bill, and indeed any Education Bill, can do little more than provide conditions favourable to development. The real work of development means years of continuous financial and administrative effort, and the work is not rendered less arduous by the division of functions between the State and the Local Education Authorities which is characteristic of the English sj^stem. I believe that the attitude of the nation towards education has changed, and that if the Government adopts and adheres consistently to the policy of going in advance of the immediate needs of the moment, instead of waiting till an accumulation of defects and grievances forces it into action, it will receive the support and even the applause of public opinion.H. A. L. F.May 16, 1917.. .PRINTED AT TElif FOKKION  OSTK1CK   By  C.  !:.  UAUiifSOS. 17/5/1&apos;.* 17.
[This Document is the Property cf His Britannic Majesty^ Government.]    221Printed for the use of the Cabinet.   May 1917.0_CONFIDENTIAL.EDUCATION BILL, 1917.Notes on Clauses (Draft 94-6).Clause 1. Progressive Development and Comprehensive Organisation of Education.UNDER the existing law Local Education Authorities are under no obligation to make provision for education other than elementary, and the only money which is ear-marked for the purpose is the residue under section 1 of the Local Taxation (Customs and Excise) Act, 1890. Clause 1 of the Bill imposes upon every Authority for higher education a duty to provide for the progressive development and conrprehen-sive organisation of education in respect of their area. The clause requires the Authority to submit to the Board a scheme showing how their duties will be performed, and for this purpose to act in consultation with the Authorities for elementary education.The objects aimed at are : (a.) Adequate provision of educational facilities.(6.) Comprehensive provision not only of schools, but also of scholarships, main-tenance allowances, and for the training of teachers, (c.) Co-operation with neighbouring Authorities. (d.) Co-ordination of elementary and higher education.The clause is closely connected with Clauses 2, 4, 5, and 6.Clause 2. Development of Education in Public Elementary Schools.This clause imposes a duty upon the Authority for elementary education so far as its powers extend to contribute to the organisation of a national system and, if necessary, to submit to the Board of Education a scheme for the purpose. The clause specially refers to the importance of affording children practical instruction in domestic subjects, handicrafts, and the like, and also of adapting the instruction in the upper pait of the school to the requirements of older children. In the past one of the commonest complaints made against the public elementary school has been that many children merely mark time after they have attained the age of 12. The Authority is required to co-operate with the Authority for higher education in arranging for the passage of children from the elementary school to a place of higher education, and also in making arrangements for the training and supply of teachers.The clause is specially important in view of the provisions for raising the elementary school age and establishing continuation schools.Clause 3. Establishment of Continuation Schools.The establishment of a system of continuation schools is an essential part of the provision of a national system of education, and this clause requires the Authority to prepare a scheme for the purpose of establishing a sufficient supply of continuation schools for all young persons who are required by a subsequent clause in the Bill to attend. The requirements as to attendance are contained in Clause 10 (see note thereon).Clause 4. Provincial Associations.The organisation of education has been considerably hampered in the past by the fact that there is no unit larger than that of the Local &quot;Education Authority to deal[608-1] B
with matters of common interest to several Authorities. Clause 4 enables the BoQl of Education to set up provincial associations, to define their constitution, and to assign to them functions. The main purpose of a provincial association is to give advice and assistance to the Board of Education and to the Local Education Authorities, but the association may, with the approval of the Board of Education, undertake any administrative or educational functions which may be delegated to it by a Local Education Authority.The clause is purposely drawn in very wide terms so as to admit of various types of association, the formation of which will probably be very gradual. They will not have rating powers, and the Local Education Authorities will retain their full existing powers except in so far as they desire ^with the Board&apos;s approval) to delegate them.Clause 5. Power to Co-operate.Clauses 1, 2, and 3 of the Bill, which impose upon an Authority a duty to make a scheme, all require that the various Authorities should act in co-operation with each other. The present clause gives a general power to Authorities to co-operate with each other, and is directly consequent upon the first three clauses. Certain powers of co-operation are given by various sections of the Education Acts, but the powers are limited and somewhat tangled, and subsection (3) repeals previously existing powers, which will in future all be contained in the new clause.Clause 6. Provision as to Amount of Rate Expenditure for Education.Under section 2 of the Education Act, 1902, a county borough can raise as much money as it requires for the purpose of higher education, but a County Council cannot raise more than the produce of a 2d. rate without the sanction of the Local Government Board. In recent years many County Councils have found this sum insufficient, and application has been made to the Local Government Board to sanction a higher amount. The effect of Clause 1 of the Bill making the provision of adequate higher education compulsory, and of the introduction of compulsory continuation classes will inevitably involve a considerable increase in expenditure for higher education, and it is consequently proposed to remove the limit.Under section 3 of the Education Act, 1902. the amount which a non-county borough or urban district may spend on education other than elementary is limited to Id. It is not proposed to remove this limit. These councils are not authorities for education other than elementary, and it is not desirable to encourage them to spend money independently of the Local Education Authority.Clause 7. Duty of Local Education Authorities to give effect to Approved Scheme.This clause refers to the first three chmses of the Bill, all of which require Local Education Authorities to submit to the Beard schemes showing how their duties will be carried out. The present clause imposes a duty to carry out the scheme when approved by the Board of Education.Clause 8. Provisions as to Compulsory. Attendance at Elementary Schools.Under the existing law it is roughly true that all children are required to attend elementary schools till the age of 14, except that (a.) All children at the age of 12 are entitled to go half-time into factory andworkshop employment; (h.) All children at the age of 12 are entitled to whole-time exemption if they passa standard which varies in the different elementary education areas of thecountry;(c.) In many areas children can work half-time not only in factories and workshops, .. but also in other employments, provided that they have either made certain attendances or passed a certain standard ;
 [d.) In about half the areas in the country a child can obtain full-time exemption at 13 if he is beneficially employed and has made certain previous attendances;(e.) In many rural areas children can obtain half-time exemption at 11 for purposes of agricultural employment.The new clause proposes by sub-section (1) to abolish all these exemptions below the age of 14 and to establish a general rule that ail children must attend up to that age. The subsection, however, does not apply to children legally exempt from the obligation to attend school at the time when the subsection comes into force.Sub-section (-) enables any Local Education Authority by bye-law to raise the age of compulsory whole-time attendance from 14 to 15. In many quarters there is a strong feeling in favour of the introduction of such a provision, and in fact many persons would like a provision saving that the school age should he raised to 15, say at the end of five years. On the other hand a proposal to raise the school age to 15, especially when combined with the drastic proposals contained in subsection (1) and with the proposals as to continuation schools, is likely to give rise to considerable alarm among employers and parents, and it may be doubted whether any Authorit)^ is likely, at any rate for some years to come, to exercise the power of raising the age.Subsection (3; introduces purely consequential amendments in the Factory and Workshop Act.Subsection (4) has been the subject of much consideration.Under the Acts relating to elementary education it is a reasonable excuse for 21011-attendance at school that the child is under efficient elementary instruction in some other manner. This provision has always caused difficulty owing to the existence of a number of inefficient places of elementary education which the Authority has no power to inspect. It is felt that the Local Education Authority should be the judges whether this alternative elementary education is efficient, and a clause to that effect has consequently been inserted. Such a provision is an almost necessary corollary of the similar provision making the Authority the judges in the first instance whether an alternative to a continuation school may properly be accepted. In order, howrever, to obviate any possibility of oppression the clause provides that the parent may if he wishes obtain the decision of the Board- of Education on the question. But he is not entitled to such a decision unless either the Board or the Local Education Authority have had an opportunity of inspecting the school.Subsection (5) should be read in connection with Clause 17 providing for the establishment of nursery schools (see note thereon).Subsection (6) is concerned with attendance at cookery classes, handicraft centres, and other forms of instruction which are given elsewhere than on the school premises of a public elementary school. There are two existing difficulties. The first is that there is some doubt avhether a child attending a public elementary school can be required to attend a class elsewhere than on the school premises. There is a legal decision that he can be so required, but it is desirable to put the matter beyond doubt.Secondly, there is a doubt whether a Local Education Authority can require the managers of a voluntary school to allow the children attending that school to go to classes outside. The subsection expressly states that such a direction may be given. The effect of.the way in which the subsection is drafted is that the direction must not be such as to interfere with reasonable facilities for religious instruction during school hours. The voluntary schools have objected that in some cases children have been asked to attend cookery classes during the period allotted for religious instruction. It is exceedingly difficult to avoid this, and the subsection as drafted, does not surmount such difficulty as exists.The legal position of &quot; centres &quot; for domestic and practical instruction is at present doubtful, and the opening words in Clause 2 (a) make it clear that the provision of such centres is within the powers of a Local Education Authority, and Clause 25.(2) further defines their status.Clause 9. Age to be ccdcidated with reference to school term.Considerable inconvenience is caused at present by the fact that children are under a legal obligation to attend an elementary school on the day when they attain 5, and are entitled to leave it on the day when they attain 14. Consequently, children are entering and leaving the school on every day of the school term. This clause provides
that a child need not be admitted to a school in the middle of a term, and, if jgj is attending a school, shall mot be entitled to leave the school until the end of the term. The effect is that the age for compulsory attendance at elementary schools may be as high as 14J, or in exceptional cases even a month or Wo higher.Clause 10. Compulsory Attendance at Continuation Schools.This clause requires all young persons to attend continuation schools for 320 hours in the year from the date when they leave the elementary school till they attain 18. As they leave the elementary school at the end of the term after they attain 1.4, the number of years&apos; attendance required is somewhat less than four. The idea is that the normal arrangement should be attendance for forty weeks in the year for eight hours a week, and that these eight hours each week should be distributed over two half-days in the week. Very many variations of this arrangement, however, are possible. In seasonal trades the whole attendance may take place during three months of the year. Again, though the normal arrangement will probably be to have two half-days a week devoted to continuation school, there will no doubt be many cases in which one whole day in the week will be devoted to the school, and other cases in which the school will take place on four days in the week for two hours each day.&apos; Owing to these possible .variations the Local Education Authority must have some discretion to say how much attendance shall be required in the case of a period of less than a year.The obligation is to attend such schools as the Local E lucation Authority of the area in which the young person resides may require.   Consequently the obligation does not arise until a requirement has been made, and it is probable that, in the early days of the Act, before the organisation of the schools is complete, many *a *A*ae children will escape attendance owing to the fact that no requirement has been roach1..   The question whether the deciding Authority should be the Authority of the place in which the rclmc^resides is one of some difficulty, since either solution gives rise to questions of jconsicterabie perplexity.   On the whole however, there can be little doubt that, e.g., j where a child lives in Willesden aud comes into London to work, the Willesden j Authority should settle what classes he shall attend.  It can do this either by requiring I the child to attend classes in Willesden, or, if it is more convenient, by arranging with the London, County Council for the child&apos;s attendance at classes in London.There is a very strong feeling in many directions that eight hours&apos; attendance at continuation schools is not sufficient, mid there are many advocates of half-time attendance. The first pro /iso to subsection (1) is devised to meet this objection. It enables the Board of Education after five years&apos; experience of work in continuation schools, and with the consent of the Local Education Authority, to increase the number of hours of attendance required.Subsection (2) deals with exemptions.The first exemption provides in effect that if a child has already been a year out of the elementary schools when the Act comes into force he shall be exempt. This exemption is introduced not ouly^ because of the difficulty of bringing back to school a young person who is already occupied full time as a worker, but also because it would be impossible, at the initiation of the system, to find continuation schools for all young persons between 14 and 18.   It is necessary to take in one year at a time.The second exemption is limited to youug persons above 16 years of age who have given evidence that they have received a satisfactory full-time education up to that age.The third exemption is in favour of those who, whether above or below 16, arc receiving full-time education ; and the fourth exemption is in favour of those who are receiving part-time education substantially greater, in amount than the amount of education required at continuation schools.Part-time continuation schools conducted by private persons do not at present exist, and it is not considered desirable to encourage their formation. Consequently while it is impossible to prohibit the education of a young person otherwise than in a recognised continuation school, it is felt that this alternative form of instruction should not be accepted unless there is a guarantee that it quite clearly replaces the instruction given in continuation schools. It is proposed that, in order that the alternative instruction may give a title to exemption, it should occupy at least 25 per cent, more hours than the compulsory instruction in continuation schools.In the foregoing list of exemptions the question whether a young person was receiving suitable and efficient full-time instruction was left to the decision of the Local Education Authority.   There is some danger that the Local Education Authority may
acCin an arbitrary or unfair manner to private institutions, and accordingly subsection (3) provides for an appeal to the Board of Education, who may overrule the Authority in the matter.Subsection (4) deals with the vexed question of the number of hours for which young persons may be employed. The purpose of the clause is mentioned in line 7. &quot; Time off &quot; is to be given in order that the young person may be in a fit mental and bodily condition to receive full benefit at continuation schools. This clause does not attempt to deal with the limitation of the hours of employment for young persons for any other purpose, it being considered that this would be outside the scope of the Bill. The Local Education Authority can direct that the young person should have two hours free on the day when he attends continuation school in addition to the time which the school itself takes. The free time may be either before or after the school, or at any other time which the Authority may think proper. For instance, it might be desirable to provide that the young person should not have to commence work at 6 a.m. on the day when he attends the continuation school. The Local Education Authority is not bound to make any requirement, and can maketless requirement than two hours. There is an appeal to the Board of Education ii the Authority make an unreasonable requirement.Subsection (5) provides that the time for attending a continuation school shall be taken from the hours of work by prohibiting the holding of a continuation school at any other time; that is to say, it must not be on a Sunday or holiday, whether legal or customary, or after 7 o&apos;clock in the evening, or before 8 o&apos;clock in the morning. The last-mentioned hours can be varied for night workers and other persons abnormally employed.Clause 11. Enforcement of Attendance at Continuation Schools.This clause deals with the penalty for non-attendance at continuation schools. The young person is liable to a fine of 5s. ; the parent, if he has connived at the non-attendance, is liable to a fine of 11., or a fine of 51. on a second offence. The employer is liable to a fineon a first offence of 71., and 51. on a second offence if he employs a young person at prohibited times.Subsection (4) enables the Board of Education to adapt the existing provisions relating to attendance at elementary schools to attendance at continuation schools.Clause 12.-Administrative Provisions relating to Continuation Schools.This clause, which follows the precedent which was established in the case of elementary education, provides for the issue of regulations necessary for carrying the Act into effect, and it will be necessary to establish somewhat elaborate machinery for notifying to the young person what schools he must attend and when and where, and for affording the employer an opportunity of making himself acquainted with the requirements affecting each young person whom he employs. These provisions have been purposely left vague in the Bill, partly because it is desirable to give all possible elasticity for working the Act, and partly because different systems may suit different areas and different employments.The purpose of subsection (2) is to provide that the 320 hours in the year for which the young person must attend continuation schools shall be reckoned from the date when he leaves the elementary school, and not by reference to the calendar year.Clause 13. Amendments of the Employment of Children Act, 1903.The Board of Education are at present in consultation with the Home Office on this clause. The excessive employment of children out of school hours is very detri-mental to the education of children in elementary schools, and it is felt that some amendment of the law is necessary to cope more effectively with the evil.At present the administration of the Employment of Children Act, 1903, under which such employment is regulated, is not a function of the Local Education Authority as such, or of its Education Committee. It is proposed under this clause to make the administration of the Act a function of the Education Authority and the Education Committee.   The City of London is at present an Authority under the Act, but is noti   [608-1] &quot; C
a Local Education Authority. The clause at present proposes that it should cease Hbe an Authority under the Act, but this may require further consideration.It is also proposed that the Board of Education should be the Authority which sanctions bye-laws regulating the employment of children under 14. This power is at present exercised by the Home Office.It is proposed to prohibit street trading under the age of 14. There is a strong case for prohibiting street trading for children under a much higher age, but it is considered desirable, as this is an Education Bill, to limit the prohibition to children attending elementary schools whose education may be said to be damaged by street-trading.Lastly, it is proposed to alter the hours within which children attending elementary schools may be employed. At present they may not be employed between 9 in the evening and 6 in the morning unless the Authority makes a special bye-law substituting some other hours. The Bill proposes that in future they shall not be employed between 8 in the evening and 7 in the morning, and the power to alter these hours is abolished. It would be possible to introduce a much more drastic provision, and many persons are in favour of forbidding the employment for profit of children under ll altogether. An alternative would be to prohibit the employment of children beJore 9 in the morning altogether. Proposals of this kind, however, would evoke very great opposition, and it does not seem desirable to imperil the chances of the Bill by exciting opposition on this clause.The Employment of Children Act, .1903, in addition to regulating the employment of children [under 14 also enables bye-laws to be made regulating street trading for children under 16, whether above or below 14. If the proposal to abolish street trading under 14 is approved, no question arises as to that. The Bill leaves unaltered the power of the Home Office to sanction bye-laws regulating street trading between 14 and 16. -Clause 14. Employment of Children attending Elementary Schools.This clause represents an attempt to meet the views of those who desire a more drastic regulation of the employment of children of school age. It enables a Local Education Authority, if they are satisfied by a report from the school medical officer that a child is unable to receive proper benefit from his work in the Elementary School owing to the character of his employment outside school hours, to make an order regulating the employment of that child.Clause 15. Power to promote Physical Training.This clause is purposely drawn in the widest j)ossible terms so as to cover all forms of physical training for children and young persons, whether attending schools or not, which may be developed after the war, and so as to enable,Local Education Authorities to co-operate freely with voluntary agencies and to contribute to any system which the Government may adopt on military grounds.Clause 16. Medical Inspection of Schools and Colleges.Under the existing law Local Education Authorities for elementary education have a duty to provide for the medical inspection of elementary schools and a power to make arrangements approved by the Board for the medical treatment of children in those schools. This clause proposes to confer similar powers and impose similar duties on Local Education Authorities as regards places of higher education provided by them, with the exception of some places of education in which medical inspection would be inappropriate.In addition to this the Authority is given power, on the request of the Managers of any place of education other than elementary, both to provide medical inspection and to give medical treatment. There are a large number of places of education other than elementary which, though not provided by the Local Education Authority, receive grants from and are closely associated with it, and no doubt this power would be widely used.Subsection (2) requires the parent to pay for medical treatment if he can afford to do so.   The same provision exists in connection with elementary schools.
rri6 Clause 17. Nursery Schools.(See also Clause 8 (5).)The development of health services for children which aim at the conservation of the population and the promotion of the physical welfare of the rising generation, coupled with the progressive exclusion of children under 5 years of age from the public elementary schools, has emphasised the necessity for the nursery schools. The desirability of such a type of school to complete the educational system was recognised in the Consultative Committee^ Report in 1908. Broadly speaking, it is agreed that if a young child under 5, or even under 6, has a good home, it is better at home than at school, but unfortunately this cannot be said of a very large proportion of young children. In the nursery school physical welfare and development would be a primary consideration, and it would aim at developing mental capacity indirectly rather than by direct or formal instruction, especially in the earlier years.It is most desirable that the system of management should be as elastic as possible, arid that every encouragement should be given to voluntary effort. It is not proposed to bring these schools within the statutory system of public elementary schools or the ordinary code regulating such schools, and it is not proposed to make attendance at nursery schools compulsory on anyone.It is recognised that in Parliament the clause may be criticised, on the one hand on the ground that it does not secure complete public control, and if the denominational question is raised it may Cause considerable embarrassment. These schools, however, may be regarded rather as special schools, which aim at preventing deterioration and &quot;arrested development&quot; of young children than as elements in the normal system of instruction for the population as a whole. Their administration will be closely connected with that of the School Medical Service.Clause 18. Powers for the Education of Children in Exceptional Circumstances.The primary object of this clause is to enable provision to be made for the elementary education of children in remote districts, such as the Cheviots and some parts of Wales, in cases where it is impossible for the children&apos; to walk every day to a public elementary school. But it is thought desirable to draw the clause in wide terms, as experience has shown that it is impossible to anticipate all the special arrangements which may be necessary to deal with exceptional cases.Clause 19. Abolition of Fees.Under the Elementary Education Act&quot;, 1891, fees in public elementary schools were abolished as a condition of fee grant, subject to a provision for their retention under certain conditions laid down in the Act. The effect of the abolition of fee grant is to abolish the only statutory provision which regulates fees, and consequently it is necessary to substitute some other provision in its place. The Board have come to the conclusion that there is no longer any reason why fees should be charged in any public elementary school, and consequently the Bill proposes to abolish fees altogether.In the year 1912-13 the total sum received from fees throughout England and Wales amounted to 66,5001 In London no fees are charged. Or this sum 14,000L was paid to the Managers of voluntary schools under section 14 of the Education Act, 1902, and the rest was applied in relief of the rates. In view of the largely increased grants which it is proposed to pay to most Local Educational Authorities, there is no reason why this revenue of 6d,00uA should be continued. But probably the proposal to abolish fees will excite some opposition owing to the fact that the charging of fees is a local matter, and in some districts the loss would be somewhat heavy, though under the regulations for Supplementary Grant the Authorities will be recouped to the extent of one-fifth of their loss.Though Local Education Authorities could probablv sacrifice their income from fees without any serious discomfort, there is no doubt that the Managers of some voluntarv schools will feel the loss of their fee income. The income is seldom very large, but it is of substantial assistance to them in paying their expenses.Under section 14 of the Education Act, 1902, a Local Education Authority have power at any time to abolish fees altogether.   In order to mitigate the disadvantage to
Managers of a sudden discontinuance of school fees, the Bill proposes that the Lwlal Education Authority may pay them out of the rates for a period of five years a sum equal to that which they have been receiving.Clause 20. Voluntary Inspection of Schools.Under section 3 of the Board of Education Act, 1899, the Board of Education may inspect any school supplying secondary education, either by their officers or after the taking of advice of the Consultative Committee by any university or other organisation. The section implies that the Board of Education shall charge a fee for so doing.The present clause extends the power of inspection to all educational institutions, whether secondary or not, and enables the Board to inspect without cost. The inspection can, of course, only be carried out at the request of the institution, if the Board have not already the right of inspection.Under the Act of 1899 the Central Welsh Board was recognised as the proper organisation for the inspection of any such schools as might be desirous of inspection under section 3, and the last words of the clause keep this provision alive.Clause 21. Collection of Information respecting Schools.The Board of Education has long felt the need for information relating to the educational provision of the country. Its knowledge is, at present, limited to schools under its inspection, and it has no powers for securing information with regard to other schools.The present clause enables this information to be collected by the Board.Clause 22. Provision with respect to Appointment of certain Glasses of Teachers.Under the Education Act, 1902, the Managers of a voluntary school have the appointment of all teachers, subject to the reservation that if there are more candidates for the post of pupil teacher than there are places to be filled the Local Education Authority may make the appointment. The effect of this provision is that technically the Local Education Authority has no right to send a lecturer to a school to lecture oil particular subjects. There is very little reason also why the appointment of teachers of cookery, handicraft, &amp;c, should be determined by any denominational consideration, and it is proposed that the Authority should have power to appoint in these cases.Pupil teachers and student teachers stand on a different footing. The proper training of teachers is one of the most important subjects which engages the attention of the Local Education Authority, and it is very undesirable that they should not be able to place a pupil teacher or a student teacher in any school which they think is best suited for the purposes of his training. Consequently it is proposed that the Authority should appoint pupil teachers and student teachers. Objection may be taken to this provision, not on the ground that it affects the denominational character of the school, but on the ground that it may diminish the power of a denomination to attract into and train for the teaching profession young persons in sympathy with the denomination.Clause 23. Provision as to Closing of Schools.Under the existing law the Managers of a voluntary school may, generally speaking, close it at any time they like at a moment&apos;s notice. This is an intolerable situation, because provision has to be made for the education of the children ; that provision cannot be made in a hurry, and requires, generally speaking, at least eighteen months, and, furthermore, the Local Education Authority cannot provide a Council school to take the place of the closed school except after giving 3 months&apos; not;ce of their intention to do s3.For these reasons there has long been a provision in the Code that no new voluntary school shall be recognised as a public elementary school unless security is given that the school will not be closed without eighteen months&apos; notice. The object of this clause is to make the provision in the Code statutory and to apply it to existing schools.
Clause 24. Grouping of Non-Provided Schools of the same Denominational Character.There are a considerable number of cases throughout the country in which the Authority are compelled to maintain two small Church of England or other denomina-tional schools which serve the same area, and each of which is organised as a complete school for boys, girls, and infants. Such an arrangement is often financially extravagant and educationally unsound. The clause proposes that in such a case it should be open to the Authority to require the distribution of the children to be rearranged. For instance, all the boys might be put into one school, and all the girls in another. Where such directions are given, the Local Education Authority may, with the approval of the Board, give directions for the constitution of a joint body of Managers. If these directions are disagreeable to the Managers, they are entitled to have the constitution of the body settled by the Board of Education.Clause 25. Provisions Relating to Central Schools and Classes.Clause 2 of the Bill refers to the duty of an Authority to give advanced instruction in public elementary schools by various means, including the provision of central schools.The first subsection of Clause 25 deals with one of the obstacles to the organisation of central schools, namely, that they must be managed by local managers in the manner prescribed by section 6 of the Education Act, 1902. This method of management is not necessarily superseded by the new clause, but the Local Education Authority are enabled, in the case of either a provided or a non-provided central school, to approve some other method of management if they consider that it is convenient, and if the Board of Education so direct.The second subsection attempts to define the legal status of centres for teaching domestic subjects and handicraft to children attending from more than one public elementary school. The subsection provides that they may be provided without the issue of notices of the intention to provide a new school under section 8 of the Education Act, 1902, and also enables the Local Education Authority to approve proposals for their management.Clause 26. Provision with respect to Education Powers of a Non-County, Borough, orUrban District.This clause enables the Board of Education, under certain conditions, to take away from a non-County, Borough, or Urban District its powers relating to elementary education, and to transfer them to the County in which the Borough or Urban District is situated.Under the Education Act, 1902, a Borough with a population of 10,000, and an Urban District with a population of 20,000, is an Authority for the purposes of elementary education. There are in England and Wales 128 Boroughs, other than County Boroughs, and 47 Urban Districts which are Authorities for elementary education. In a number of these small areas education is very badly administered, and it would be a public advantage that they should be absorbed in the County.The clause is likely to be somewhat controversial, and the question of preserving the autonomy of small urban areas led to acute discussion both on the Education Bill, 1902, and previously. There is, however, a very strong feeling in the country in favour of doing what the clause proposes, and probably in favour of doing it in a much more drastic fashion.Clause 27. Acquisition of Land hy Local Education Authority.This clause represents an attempt which has been made in other departments of local government to simplify the machinery for compulsory purchase of land for the purpose of the Education Acts. It is a clause to which the very greatest importance will be attached by all persons interested in educational administration.It has been considered best not to devise any new machinery for compulsory purchase, but to adopt that contained in the Housing, Town Planning, &amp;c, Act, 1909. Under that procedure an order for compulsory purchase can be made by the Board of [608-1] *        d
Clause 28. Power to Provide Elementary Schools outside Area.This clause is introduced to get over a small difficulty which has occurred in a number of cases. It sometimes happens, especially in urban areas, that the most suitable site for a school to serve that area is situated outside the boundary. Under existing law an Authority cannot provide a public elementary school outside its boundary, and this clause is introduced to meet that case.Clause 29. Amendment with Respect to the Allocation of Expenses toParticular Areas.Under section 18 of the Education Act, 1902, a county council is bound to charge not less than one-half or more than three-quarters of any loan charges or any capital expenditure in connection with elementary education on the parish served by the school in respect of which the expenditure has been incurred. This provision has acted in a manner very detrimental to the establishment of new schools, since strong local opposition to the provision of such schools is occasioned by the fact that it inevitably necessitates a very heavy increase in the education rate levied on the particular parish served by the school.Eor this reason it was at one time suggested that the obligation to make a special charge should be abolished, and that capital expenditure should be spread over the whole county just as expenditure e  maintenance is spread. There is, however, considerable difference of opinion upon the subject, and a number of county councils are in favour of the retention of the existing system, perhaps because they are afraid of extravagant local demands, if capital expenditure in the locality does not involve any corresponding burden&apos;. Consequently the clause as drafted provides that the county council may do what it likes in the matter, and either spread the charge over the whole county or charge it to the extent of not more than three-quarters on the parish. The section applies not only to new loan charges, but also to old.Clause 30. Provisions as to Expenses of Provisional Orders.This clause is purely administrative. It is inserted in the Bill with a view to removing certain doubts as to the statutorysprovisions under which a Local Education Authority should borrow money for the purpose of securing provisional orders for the acquisition of land.Clause 31. Expenses of Education Meetings, Conferences, &amp;c.This clause is at present inserted in a provisional form. It is designed to remove difficulties which have arisen as to the legality of paying expenses of delegates to educational conferences.Clause 32. Power to Pay Expenses of Prosecution for Cruelty.Under section 12 of the Children Act, 1908, it is an offence for a parent to cause injury to a child s health by failure to provide adequate food, clothing, medical aid, or lodging for the child.Under section 34 the power to institute proceedings is conferred in London on the County Council and elsewhere on the Guardians. It is desired to give the Local Education Authority, under whose cognisance offences of this kind often come, power to institute proceedings under section 12.Education without going to Parliament, except in cases where the land is situatea^m an urban area, and an impartial person appointed by the Board reports to the Board that the proposals should not be proceeded with. The clause also renders the pro-cedure for acquiring the land after the order has been made much simpler and less inexpensive.
Clauses 33 aud 34. Public Inquiries by the Board of Education.This is merely an administrative provisions clause. The holding of public inquiries is at present regulated by section 73 of the Elementary Education Act, 1870, and the section was drafted with special reference to the purpose for which public inquiries under that Act were to be held, Various difficulties have arisen in the administration of the section, more particularly with reference to the^charging of costs, and the proposed clauses have been drafted with a view to improving the machinery.Clause 35. Decision of Certain Educational Questions by the Board of Education.This clause is probably not in its final shape, and is at present under consideration by the Local Government Board. The provisions of the Education Act, 1902, as to the purposes on which an Education Authority may spend money are couched in very general language, and give rise to many difficult, questions as to the extent of the power given. The object of the clause is to enable the Board of Education to decide what is educational expenditure within the meaning of the Education Acts.Clause 36. Education Grants.The Board recently issued their regulations for supplementary grant (Cd. 8515) providing for the payment to Local Education Authorities, in addition to the statutory grants and other grants previously paid under the Minutes of the Board, of a supplementary grant calculated, in accordance with a formula which was explained on the discussion of the supplementary estimates. This was a merely temporary arrange-ment devised for the purpose of distributing the new grants on an area system as distinguished from a school system, without introducing legislation for the purpose of abolishing the statutory grants. The statutory grants, however, must be abolished sooner or later under the new system, and the present clause abolishes them as from an appointed day to be fixed by the Board of Education.The supplementary grant was designed so as to bring up the total of the ordinary grants and supplementary grant to an amount calculated according to the formula. Consequently, where the ordinary grants exceeded (as they did in some cases) the amount calculated according to the formula, the Authority receive no supplementary grant. The Authorities which receive more from ordinary grants than from the grant under the formula will naturally desire that the formula should not be applied to them. The proviso to the clause consequently provides that if an Authority raise a rate of Is. in the  and in the. financial year 1917-18 did not receive any supplementary grant (because its ordinary grant was greater than the grant calculated according to the formula) it shall receive for five years after the appointed day when the new consolidated grant is introduced a not less sum than it received in the financial year ending the 31st M^rch, 1918. The proviso is not strictly necessary, because it would be possible to achieve the same result by introducing a provision to the same effect in the minutes relating to consolidated grant.The consolidated grant is a grant to Local Education Authorities, and it is necessary to make provision for those public elementary schools which are not maintained by any Local Education Authority. These schools are known as institution schools, and grant will be paid to them in future under a special minute.The third subsection provides that the procedure which has since 1870 regulated the Board&apos;s minutes with regard to ordinary grants to schools shall apply to the hew consolidated grant.pbintkd at the foreign office by c. r. harrisok. 17/5/1917.
Education Bill.ARRANGEMENT OE CLAUSES.National System of Public Education.Clause.1.   Progressive and comprehensive organisation of education. 2.   Development of education, in public elementary schools. 3.   Establishment of continuation schools. 4.   Provincial associations. 5.   Power to co-operate.6.   Provision as to amount of expenditure for education.7.  Duty  of local education authorities to give effect to approved scheme.Attendance at School and Employment of Children.8. Provisions as to compulsory attendance at  elementary schools.9. Age to be calculated with reference to school term.10. Compulsory attendance at continuation schools.11. Enforcement of attendance at continuation schools.12. Administrative provisions relating to continuation schools.13. Amendment of Employment of Children Act, 1903.14. Employment of children attending elementary schools.Extension of Powers and Duties. 15.   Power to promote physical training.16. Medical inspection of schools and educational institutions. 17.   Nursery schools.18.   Powers  for   the   education of   children in exceptional circumstances.Abolition of Fees in Public Elementary Schools. 19.   Abolition of fees in public elementary schools.Administrative Provisions. 20.   Voluntary inspection of schools. 21.   Collection of information respecting schools. 94-6 A
General.ii Education. [7 &amp; 8Geo. 5.]Clause.22.   Provisions with respect to appointment of certain classesof teachers. 23.   Provisions as to closing of schools.24f.   Grouping of non-provided schools of the same denomina-tional character. 25.   Provisions relating to central schools and classes. 26.   Provision with respect to education powers of a non-countyborough or urban district.27.   Acquisition of land by local education authority.28.   Power to provide elementary schools outside area.29.   Amendment with respect to the allocation of expenses toparticular areas. 30.   Provisions as to expenses of Provisional Orders, &amp;c. 31.   Expenses of education meetings, conferences, &amp;c. 32.   Powrer to pay expenses of prosecution for cruelty. 33.   Provisions as to public inquiries by Board of Education. 34.   Costs of inquiries.35.   Decision of certain educational questions by Board of Education.Education Grants. 36.   Consolidated grant.37. Definitions. 38.   Short title.
draftof aBILLtoMake further provision with respect to  Education in a.d. 1917. England and Wales and for purposes connected therewith.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5 National System of Public Education.1. (1) With a view to the establishment of a national system Progressive of public education available for all persons capable of profiting ^nshTor-6&quot; thereby, it shall be the duty of the council of every county and ganisation of county borough so far as * their powers extend to contribute educatl0Q-10 thereto by providing for the progressive development and com-prehensive organization of education in respect of their area and with that object to submit to the Board of Education as occasion requires schemes showing the mode in which their duties and powers with respect to education are to be performed15 and exercised for the purpose, whether separately or in co-operation with other authorities.(2) The council of any county, before submitting a scheme under this section, shall consult the authorities having powers within their county under Part III. of the Education Act, 1902, 20 with reference to the mode in which and the extent to which any such authority will co-operate with the council in carrying &apos; out their scheme, and when submitting their scheme shall make a report to the Board of Education as to the co-operation which is to be anticipated from any such authority.25       2. In order that full benefit may be derived from the Develop-system of public elementary schools, it shall be the duty of a SSon0f1,ed&quot;&quot; 94-6 A 2
mentary schoolsEstablish-ment of continuation schools.3. (l) With a view to contintung the education of children 25 and helping young persons to prepare for the freedom and responsibilities of adult life it shall be the duty of the local education authority for the purposes of Part II. of the Education Act, 1902, either separately or in co-operation with other local education authorities, to establish and maintain or secure the 30 establishment and maintenance under their control and direction of a sufficient supply of continuation schools in which suitable courses of instruction and physical training are provided without payment of fees for all young persons in their area who are, under this Act, under an obligation to attend such schools.        35(2) Eor the purposes aforesaid the local education authority, after such consultation wdth persons or bodies interested as they consider desirable, shall before the appointed day and subse-quently so often as occasion may require submit to the BoardA-D-1917- local education authority, under Part III. of the Education Act,public ele-     1902 (a) to make adequate and suitable provision by means of central schools, central or special classes or other-wise  g(i) for including in the curriculum of public elementary schools, at appropriate stages, practical instuction suitable to the ages, capacities, and circumstances of the children; and(ii) for organising in  those schools courses of 10 advanced instruction for the older children in atten-dance   at   public   elementary   schools,   including children who stay at such schools beyond the age of fourteen; and(b) to make adequate and suitable arrangements for co- 15 operating with authorities exercising powers under Part II. of the Education Act, 1902, in matters of common interest, and particularly in respect of (i) the preparation of children for further ecluca-tion in schools other than elementary, and their 20 transference at suitable ages to such schools;(ii) the supply and training of teachers;and widen required by the Board of Education, to submit to them a scheme for the purposes aforesaid.
.,,m illJiMIBttTUlHHUIATiT&quot;&quot;&apos;of Education a scheme for the progressive organization of a A-D- 1917-system of continuation schools and for the purpose of securing general and regular attendance thereat.4. (1) With a view to the better co-ordination of educa- Provincial 5 tion and the provision of advice and assistance for the Board assOCmtlous-of Education and local education authorities, particularly in respect of matters of common interest concerning education which it is necessary or convenient to consider in relation to areas larger than those of individual education authorities, the 10 Board of Education may establish [and incorporate] or provide for the establishment [and incorporation] of provincial associa-tions for such areas comprising the areas of two or more local education authorities as the Board may direct.The association shall be constituted in accordance with a 15 scheme to be made by the Board of Education after con-sultation  with the authorities appearing to the Board to be concerned and shall be subject to the provisions of the scheme.(2) The scheme shall provide for the  representation  of authorities and may provide directly or by co-optation for the 20 inclusion of persons interested in the administrative or educa-tional work of the area, and representatives of universities and other bodies.(3) Any such association may, if they think fit, with the approval of the Board of Education undertake any administra-25 tive and educational functions which may be delegated to them by any local education authority within their area, and any such local education authority shall have power to delegate to the association, any such functions.(4) The JBoard of Education may, with the sanction of the 30 Treasury, out of moneys provided by Parliament, make to an association grants in aid of any expenses incurred by any such, association, including the payment of travelling expenses of members of the association, under the scheme constituting the association.    ..35 (5) The accounts of an association shall be audited as if the association were a separate local education authority and the enactments relating to the audit of the accounts of local education authorities (including the penal provisions of those enactments) shall apply accordingly.
A.p. 1917.        5. (l) Any local education authority having powers under PoweTto co- the Education Act, 1902, may arrange with any other council operate.      having powers under the Education Act, 1902, for co-operation * or combination with that council in the performance of anyduty or the exercise of any power relating to education on 5 such terms as they think fit, and any such arrangement may provide for the appointment of a Joint Committee or a joint body of managers, for the proportion of the contributions to be paid by each authority and for any other matters which appear to them necessary for the purpose of carrying out such 10 arrangement.(2) &quot;Where any such arrangement provides for the payment of an annual contribution by one authority to another the con-tribution shall, for the purposes of section nineteen of the Education Act, 1902, form part of the security on which money 15 may be borrowed under that section.(3) Section fifty-two of the Elementary Education Act, 1870, section four of the Education (Administrative Provisions) Act, 1907, section three of the Education (Administrative Provi-sions) Act, 1909, and subsection (2) of section one of the Education 20 (Choice of Employment) Act, 1910, are hereby repealed.Provision as 6. The limit under section two of the Education Act, 1902, to amount of on ^he amount to he raised by the council of a county out ofcx.i)Gricli-ture for       rates for the purpose of education other than elementary shall education.    cease to have effect. . 25Duty of 7. The Board of Education may approve any scheme (whichbcai educa-  jn  he first instance may be an interim scheme) submitted to rities to give them by a local education authority, either wdthout alterations -effect to ap-  or ^jth such alterations as they think fit after considering schemes      any representations made to them on the subject, and there- 30 upon it shall be the duty of the local education authority to give effect to the scheme as approved by the Board of Education.Attendance at School and Employment of Children.Provisions 8. (l) No exemption from attendance  at an elementary 35as to com- school shall be granted to any child between the ages of five and attendance fourteen years, and any enactment giving a power, or imposing a atelemen- duty, to provide for any such exemption, and any provision of a tary schools, i)yeiaw providing for any such exemption shall cease to haveeffect, without prejudice to any exemptions already granted.       40
Any byelaw which names a lower age than fourteen as the age up to which a parent shall cause his child to attend school, shall hare effect as if the age of fourteen were substituted for that lower age.5 (2) [The local education authority may make a byelaw under section seventy-four of the Elementary Education Act, 1870, extending the age up to which parents are to cause their children to attend school from fourteen to fifteen years].(3) Eor the purpose of the employment of a child in a 10 factory or workshop, a reference to a child within the meaning of this Act shall, as respects England and Wales, be substituted in section sixty-two of the Eactory and Workshop Act, 1901, for the reference to a child under the age of twelve years, and a reference to the appointed day for the purposes of this Act 25 shall he substituted for the reference to the commencement of that Act.In section one hundred and fifty-six of the Eactory and Workshop Act, 1901, the definition of child contained in this Act shall, as respects England and Wales, be substituted for 20 the definition child contained in that section.(4) The question whether a child is under efficient instruc-tion in some other manner within the meaning of the Education Acts, or any byelaws relating to school attendance made there-under, shall be determined by the local education authority, or, 25 in the case of a child attending a school or educational institution which the Board of Education or the local education authority are permitted to inspect, if the parent of the child so desires by the Board of Education.(5) If the Board of Education are satisfied on the repre-30 sentation of a local education authority that such adequate and satisfactory provision of nursery schools has been made in their area, or any part of their area, as to render it unnecessary to provide instruction in public elementary schools for children &apos; under the age of six, the Board may by order direct that the 35 age of six shall be substituted for the age of five as respects that area, or part of an area, as the age at which the obligation to attend school under the Education Acts begins.(6) The power of a local education authority under section seven of the Education Act, 1902, to give directions as to secular ^0 instruction shall include the power to direct that any child in attendance at a public elementary school shall attend during such hours as may be directed by the authority at any class, whether
A.D. 1917.Age to be calculated with refer-ence to school term.Compulsory attendance at continua-tion schools.conducted on the school premises or not, for the purpose of practical or other instruction, and for the purpose of any enact-ment or byelaw relating to school attendance, attendance at such a class shall, where the authority so direct, be deemed to be attendance at a public elementary school. 59. (1) If a child who is attending a public elementary school attains any year of age during the school term, the child shall not, for the purpose of any enactment or byelaw, whether made before or after the passing of this Act, relating to school attendance, be deemed to have attained that year of 10 age until the end of the term.(2) The local education authority under Part III. of the Education Act, 1902, may make regulations with the approval of the Board of Education providing that a child may, in such cases as are prescribed by the regulations, be refused admission 15 to a public elementary school except at the commencement of a school term.(3) Eor the purposes of this section, a school term shall be deemed to be the term as fixed by the local education authority with the approval of the Board of Education. 2010. (1) Subject as hereinafter provided, all young persons who are no longer under an obligation to attend an elementary school shall attend such continuation schools as the local educa-tion authority of the area in which they reside may require, for three hundred and twenty hours in each year, or in the case of 25 a period of less than a year for such number of hours as the local education authority, having regard to all the circumstances, consider reasonable :Provided that at any time after the expiration of five years from the appointed day the Board of Education may, with the 30 consent of the local education authority and after such inquiry as they think fit, by order increase in respect of any area or part of an area or any young persons or classes of young persons the number of hours of attendance at continuation schools required under this Act, arid the order shall, as respects 35 the area to which young persons to whom it applies have effect as if enacted in this Act.(2)  The  obligation to attend  continuation schools under this Act shall not apply to any young person (i) who is above the age of fifteen years on the appointed 40 day;
10(iii)15(ii) who is above,the age of sixteen years and either(a) has passed the Matriculation Examination of a University of the United Kingdom or an exami-nation recognised by the Board of Education as equivalent thereto or,(b) is shown, in the case of a young person educated in a secondary school [or other school] recognised by the Board of Education as efficient, to the satisfaction of the Board of Education, and, in the case of a young person educated elsewhere, to the satisfaction of the local education authority, to have been under suitable and efficient full-time instruction up to the age of sixteen;who is shown to the satisfaction of the local education authority to be under suitable and efficient full-time instruction in some other manner;(iv) who is shown to the satisfaction of the local education. authority to he under suitable and efficient part-time instruction in some other manner for a number of20 hours in the year (being hours during which, if notexempt, he might he required to attend a continua-tion school), exceeding by not less than twenty-five per cent, the number of hours during which a young person is   required under  this Act  to   attend   a25 continuation school.(3) If a young person in any school or educational institution, or the parent of any such young person, represents to the Board that the young person, is entitled to exemption under the pro-visions of this section, but that the local education authority have30 unreasonably refused to accept the instruction as satisfactory, the Board of Education shall consider the representation, and if satisfied that the representation is well founded shall make an order declaring that the young person is exempt from the obli-gation to attend a continuation school under this Act for such35 period and subject to such conditions as may he named in the Order; provided that the Board of Education may refuse to consider any such representation unless the local education authority or the Board of Education are permitted to inspect the school or educational institution in which the instruction is40 or has been given.94 B
Euforccment of attend-ance at continuation schools.A.u. 1917. (4) The local education authority may require in the case of any young person who is under an obligation to attend a continuation school that his employment shall be suspended on any day, when his attendance is required, not only during the period for which he is required to attend the school, but also 5 for a period not exceeding [two] hours at such times in any clay as the authority consider necessary in order to secure that he may be in a fit mental and bodily condition to receive full benefit from attendance thereat: Provided that if any question arises between the local education authority and the employer 10 of a young person whether a requirement made under this subsection is reasonable for the purposes aforesaid, that question shall be determined by the Board of Education, and if the Board of Education determine that the requirement is unreason-able they may substitute such other requirement as they think 15 reasonable.(5) The education authority shall not require any young -person to attend a continuation school on a Sunday or dining any holiday or half-holiday to which by any enactment regu-lating his employment or by agreement he is entitled, nor so 20 far as practicable during any holiday or half-holiday which in his employment he is accustomed to enjoy, nor between the hours of seven in the evening and eight in the morning, provided that the local education authority may, with the approval of tlie Board, vary these hours in the case of young 25 persons employed at night or otherwise employed at abnormal times.11. (1) If a young person fails except by reason of sick-ness or other unavoidable cause to comply with any requirement imposed upon him under this Act for attendance at continuation 30 schools, he shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding five shillings.(2) If any parent of a young person, by wilful default or by neglecting to exercise due care, has conduced to the commis-sion of an offence, under the immediately preceding subsection 35 or otherwise [or connived at] failure on behalf of the young person to attend continuation schools as required under this Act, he shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding-one pound, and in the case of a second or subsequent offence, whether relating to the same or another young person, to a fine 40 not exceeding five pounds.
(3) If any person employs a young person in such a manner A.D. 1917. as to prevent the young person attending the continuation schools which lie is required to attend or at times when in pursuance of any requirement of the local education authority, his employ-5 ment must he suspended, he shall he liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding two pounds, or in the case of a second or subsequent offence, whether relating to the same or another young person, a fine not exceeding five pounds.(4) The Board of Education may by order apply any of the 10 provisions of the Education Acts, 1870 to 1916, respecting the enforcement of attendance of children at public elementary schools subject to such modifications and adaptations as may be necessary to make the same applicable to the enforcement of the attendance of young persons at continuation schools under this Act.15       12. (1) The Board of Education may from time to time Administra-make regulations prescribing the manner and form in which notice shall be given as to the continuation school (if any) which relating to a young person is required to attend, and times of attendance g^*i0ijgatl011 thereat, and as to the hours during which his employment must20 be suspended, and providing for the issue of certificates of age, attendance and exemption and for the keeping and preservation of registers of attendance and generally for carrying into effect the provisions of this Act relating to continuation schools.(2) Eor the purposes of the provisions of this Act relating 25 to continuation schools the expression &quot;year&quot; means in the case :. of any young person the period of twelve months reckoned from the date when he ceased to be under an obligation under the Education Acts to attend an elementary school or any subsequent period of twelve months.30        13. The Employment of Children Act, 1903, so far as it Amendment relates to England and Wales shall he amended as follows:-    of Employ-(1) Subsection (1) of section three shall be repealed and the children following subsection shall he substituted therefor:    Act, 1903-A child shall not  be  employed between the 35 hours of eight in the evening and seven in themorning:(2) In subsection (2) of section three the words  &quot; under the age of eleven years&quot; shall be repealed:(3) In section four the Board of Education shall be sub-40 stituted for the Secretary of State, so far as relates94 B 2
A/D. 1917. to   byelaws   made  under  section  one  regulatingemploy meats other than street trading:(4) Section twelve shall be repealed and the following section shall be substituted therefor :-The powers and duties of a local authority 5 under this Act shall be deemed to be powers and duties under Part III. of the Education Act, 1902, and the provisions of the Education Acts for the time being in force with regard to those powers and duties and as to the manner in which the 10 expenses of an authority under that Part of that Act shall be paid shall apply accordingly:(5) For the definition of the expression &quot;local authority&quot; in the Act there shall be substituted the following definition:  15The expression &quot;local authority&quot; means the local education authority for the purposes of Part III. of the Education Act, 1902.Employment       14. (l) The local education authority, if they are satisfied of children    Dy a report of the school medical officer or otherwise that any 20 elementery   child is being employed before, between or after school hours schools.      in such a manner as to render him unfit to obtain the proper benefit of his education at school, may either prohibit, or attach such conditions as they think fit, to his employment in that or any other manner. . 25If any person after having received notice of any such prohibition or condition employs a child in such a manner as to contravene the prohibition or restriction, he shall be deemed to have taken the child into his employment in contravention of the Elementary Education Act, 1876, and shall be liable to 30 a penalty accordingly.(2) If the parent of a child has conduced to the commission of the offence by wilful default or by neglecting to exercise due care, he shall be liable on summary conviction to a penalty not exceeding forty shillings. 35(3) It shall be the duty of the employer and the parent of any child who is in employment, if required by the local education authority to furnish to the local education authority such information as to his employment as the authority may require, and if the parent or employer fails to comply with any 4,0
requirement of the local education authority or wilfully gives A.D. 1917. false information as to the employment, he shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding forty shillings.Extension of Powers and Duties.5       15. A  local   education   authority  for   the  purposes  of Power to Part III. of the Education Act,  1902, as respects  children jjjj^jj attending public elementary schools, and   a local education training, authority for the purposes of Part II. of that Act as respects other children or .persons may, without prejudice to any  other10 powers make arrangements approved by the Board of Education for promoting physical training, and for this purpose may, amongst other things, supply or maintain or aid the supply or maintenance of centres and equipment for physical training, playing-fields (other than the ordinary playgrounds of public15 elementary schools not provided by the local education autho-rity), school baths, school swimming baths, holiday or school camps, and similar facilities for such training.16. (1) The local education authority for the purpose of Medical in-Part II.  of the Education Act, 1902,  shall have the same sPectio,lof&apos; 3 - schools and20 powers and duties with reference to making provision for the educational medical inspection and treatment of children and young persons institutions, attending (i) secondary schools provided by them; (ii) continuation schools under their direction and control;25 and(iii) such other schools or educational institutions (other thanelementary) provided by them as the Board direct,as a local - education authority for the purposes of Part III. ofthe Education Act, 1902, with reference to children attending public30 elementary schools have, under paragraph (b) of subsection (1) of section thirteen of the Education (Administrative Provisions) Act, 1907, and shall also have the powers exerciseable under that paragraph as respects children and young persons attending any school or educational institution, whether aided by them or35 not, if so requested by or on behalf of the persons having the management thereof.(2) The Local Education Authorities (Medical Treatment) Act, 1909, shall apply where any medical treatment is given in pursuance of this section as it applies to treatment given, in 40 pursuance of section thirteen of the Education (Administrative 9 Edw. 7. Provisions) Act, 1907. c-13*
A.D.1917Nursery schools.Powers for the educa-tion of children in exceptional circum-stances.17. The powers of local education authorities for the pur-poses of Part III. of the Education Act, 1902, shall include power to make such arrangements as may he approved by the Board of Education for -(a) supplying or aiding the supply of nursery schools, for 5children over two and under five years of age (or such later age as may be approved by the Board of Education) whose home conditions are such that attendance at such a-school is necessary or desirable for their healthy physical and mental development; 10 and(b) attending to the health, nourishment and physical welfareof children attending nursery schools.18. Where a local education authority for the purposes of Part III. of the Education Act, 1902, are satisfied in the case 15 of any children that owing to the remoteness of their homes or the conditions under which the children are living, or other exceptional circumstances affecting the children, those children are not in a position to receive the full benefit of education by means of the ordinary provision made for the purpose by the 20 authority, the authority may, with the approval of the Board of Education, make such arrangements, either of a permanent or temporary character, and including the provision of board and lodging, as they think best suited for the purpose of enabling those children to receive the benefit of efficient elementary education. 25Abolition of fees in public ele-menlary schools.Voluntary inspection of schools.Abolition of Fees in Public Elementary Schools.19. (1) No fees shall be charged or other charges of any kind made in any public elementary, school, except as provided by the Education (Provision of Meals) Act, 1906, and the Local Education Authorities (Medical Treatment) Act, 1909. 30(2) During a period not exceeding five years from the appointed day the local education authority may pay to the managers of a school not provided by them in each year a sum not exceeding the average yearly sum paid to the managers under section fourteen of the Education Act, 1902, 35 during the five years immediately preceding the appointed day.Administrative Provisions.20. If the governing body of any school or educational institution, not liable to inspection by any Government depart-ment, or if there is no governing body the headmaster, requests 40
the Board of Education to inspect the school or institution and A.D. 1917. to report thereon, the Board of Education may do so, if they think lit, free of cost; hut this section shall he without pre-judice to the provisions relating to the Central Welsh Board 5 contained in subsection (1) of section three of the Board of Education Act, 1899.21. (1) In order that full information may be available as Collection to the provision for education and the use made of such provision 0finforma&quot;tion respect-ill England and Wales - ing schools.10 (a) It shall be the duty of the responsible person as here-inafter defined in respect of every school or educational institution to furnish to the Board of Education on a form to be supplied by the Board (i) in   the   case  of  a   school or   educational 15                   institution existing at the appointed day, withinthree months of that day;(ii) in the case of a school or educational institu-tion opened after the appointed day, within three months of the opening thereof;20 the name and address of the school or institution anda short description of the school or institution, and the Board shall provide such forms and publish notice of where such forms may be obtained:(Jj) It shall be the duty of every such responsible person 25 if and when required by the Board of Education tofurnish to the Board such further particulars with respect to the] school or institution as may be pre-scrihed by regulations made by the Board:Provided that the Board may by order exempt from both or 30 either of the above   obligations any schools or  educational institutions with respect to which the necessary information is already in the possession of the Board or is otherwise available.(2) If the responsible  person fails after due notice   to furnish any information required by this section, he shall be 35 liable on summary conviction to a penalty not exceeding ten pounds, and to a penalty not exceeding five pounds for every day on which the failure continues after conviction therefor.. (3) Eor   the purposes of   this section &quot; the   responsible person&quot; means, the secretary or person performing the duty of 40 secretary to the. governing body of the school or institution, or
A.D. 1917. if   there is no governing   body the  headmaster or  person responsible for the management of the school or institution.(4) Any regulations made by the Board of Education under this section with respect to the particulars to be furnished shall be laid before each House of Parliament as soon as may be after 5 they are made.Provisions 22. Notwithstanding anything in the Education Act, 1902,with respect ^  appointment of all teachers of secular subjects not attachedto appoint- rr Jment of cer- to the staff of any particular school, and teachers appointed foroTteach^re   the purpose of giving practical instruction, pupil teachers and 10student teachers, shall be made by the local education autho-rity, and it is hereby declared that the local education autho-rity have  power to direct the managers  of any  schools notprovided by them to make arrangements for the admission ofany such teachers to the schools. 15Provisions as 23. (l) The managers of a school not provided by the Bchools&quot;18 0f *oca* e^ucatiou authority, if they wish to close the. school, shall give at least eighteen months&apos; notice to the local education authority of their intention so to close the school, but a notice under this provision shall not be withdrawn except with the 20 consent of the local education authority.(2) If the managers of a school who have given such a notice are unable or unwilling to carry on the school up to the expiration of the period, the school buildings shall he put at the disposal of the local education authority, if the authority 25 so desire, for the whole or any part of the period, free of charge, but subject to an obligation on the part of the. authority to keep the buildings in repair for use by the authority for the purposes of a school provided by them. The use by the authority of the school buildings for the purposes of a school provided by them 30 during such period, shall&apos; not be deemed for the purposes of section eight of the Education Act, 1902, to constitute the pro-vision of a new school.Grouping of       24. Where there are two or more schools not provided by Schools of    the local education authority of the same denominational character 35 the same de- in the same locality, the local education authority if they pharacter01?al consider that it is expedient for the purpose of educational efficiency and economy, may, with the approval of the Board of Education, give directions for the distribution of the children in the schools according to age, sex, or attainments, and otherwise 40 with respect to the organisation of the schools; and may with
the like approval group the schools under one body of managers ^.D. 1917. constituted in the manner ;provided by subsection (2) of section twelve of the Education Act, 1902.25. (1) The Board of Education may direct that the provi- Provisions 5 sions of section six of the Education Act, 1902, as to the appoint- 1       to ment of managers shall not apply to any public elementary schools and school which in the opinion of the Board is specially organised classes, for the purpose of giving advanced instruction to older children, if such school is managed in such manner as may be approved 10 by the local education authority.(2) Notwithstanding anything contained in sections six and eight of the Education Act, 1902, the provision of premises for - classes in practical or advanced instruction for children attend-ing from more than one public elementary school shall not be 15 deemed to be the provision of a new public elementary school, and any class conducted in such premises may be managed in such manner as may be approved by the local education authority.   -26. (1) The Board of Education may, after such inquiry Provision 20 as they think fit, make an order providing that all or any of ^ltl^resP5ct the powers and duties under Part iii. of the Education Act, powers of a 1902, of the council of any non-county borough or urban district  ou-county in the county shall be relinquished in favour of the council of urban the county, and, as from the date specified in the order, the district. 25 powers and duties to which the order relates shall cease, and the area of the authority shall be deemed to be part of the area &apos; of the county councilas respects those powers and duties.(2) An order made under this section by the Board of Education shall, unless the council of the county and the 30 council of the borough or urban district concerned consent, be provisional only, and shall require confirmation by Parliament.(3) An order made under this section shall contain the necessary provisions for the adjustment of property, rights, and liabilities. as between the borough or district and the county in 35 which the borough or district is situated, and such incidental and consequential provisions as may appear necessary or ex-pedient (including the modification of any scheme with reference * to the system of education in force under this Act).(4) The Board of Education may submit to Parliament for 40 confirmation any Order which requires confirmation by Parliament under this section. . -.94 0
[.V&amp;8 Geo. 5.]:Acquisition of laud by local educa-tion autho-rity.Edw. 7. 44.A.D. 1917. (5) If when a &quot;Bill con firming ah Order under this sectionis pending in either House of Parliament, a petition is presented against any Order comprised therein, the Bill, so far as it relates to that Order, may he referred to a Select Committee, or, if the two Houses of Parliament think fit so to order, to a Joint .5 Committee of^ both Houses, and the petitioner shall he allowed to appear and oppose as in the case of. private Bills.27. (1) A local education authority may be authorised to purchase  land  compulsorily for the  purpose of any of tkeir-powers or duties under the Education Acts, by means of an iq order submitted to the Board of Education,  and confirmed by -the Board in accordance with the provisions contained in para-graphs one to thirteen of the Eirst Schedule to the Housing, . Town Planning, &amp;c. Act, 1909, and . those provisions shall have effect for the purpose, with the substitution of the Board of 15 Education for the Local Government Board and of the local education authority for the local authority, and . of references to the Education Acts for references to &quot; this Act&quot;:Provided that the Board of Education shall not confirm any such order even when unopposed if they are of opinion that 20 the land is unsuited for the purpose for which it is proposed to be acquired.(2) The powers given by this section in relation to the compulsory purchase of land by the local education authority shall be in substitution for any other powers existing for that 25 purpose, and section twenty of the Elementary Education Act, 1870, except so far as it incorporates the Lands Clauses Acts for the purpose of the acquisition of land by agreement, and except so far as it applies the School Sites Act shall cease to have effect. 3028. A local education authority may, with the consent of the Board of Education, provide a public elementary school, in cases where it appears convenient to do so, on a site outside their area for the use of children within their area, and for the purposes of the Education Acts a school so provided shall be 35 deemed to be situated within the area of the authority.Amendment 8 29. It shall not be obligatory on a county council to totheTlfo3-04 cliargs 011 particular areas any portion of such expenses as cation of      are mentioned in paragraph (c) or paragraph (cl) of subsection (1)Power to provide ele-mentary schools out-side area.expenses to  0f sectj0n eighteen of the Education Act, 1902, and accordingly 40particular 1 ?areas.each of those paragraphs shall have effect as if for the word
&quot;shall&quot; there was substituted,the word &quot;may&quot; and as if the A.D. 1917. words &quot; less than one half or&quot; were omitted therefrom; and .when before the passing of: this Act any portion of such expenses have been charged on or allocated to any area, the 5 county council may cancel or vary the charge or allocation.30. [Any expenses incurred by a council in connexion with Provisions as any Provisional Order for the purposes of the Education Acts, ^. pX^enses or any Order under this Act for the purpose of the acquisition visional of land shall be defrayed as- expenses of the council under the Orders, &amp;c. 10 Education Act, 1902, and the  council shall, have the same power of borrowing for the purpose of those expenses as they have under section nineteen of the Education Act, 1902, for the purpose of the expenses therein mentioned.]31. (1) Any council having powers under the Education Expenses of 15 Acts may, subject to regulations made by the Board of Education, education defray as part of their expenses under those Acts any expenses conferences, incurred by them in connexion with meetings or conferences &amp;c-held for the purpose of discussing the promotion and organi-sation of education or educational administration, and attendance 20 of representatives of the council at any such meeting or con-ference :   Provided that (a) The expenses of more than three representatives of a council shall not be paid except with the sanction of the Board of Education; and25 (b) Expenses shall not be paid in respect of any meeting or conference outside the United Kingdom [qu. Great Britain], except with the sanction of the Board of Education; and(c) No&apos; expenses for any purpose shall be paid under this 30 section unless expenditure for the purpose has beenspecially authorised or ratified by a resolution of the council, after special notice has been given to mem-bers of the council of the proposal to authorise the expenditure.35       (2) The School Board Conference Act, 1897, is hereby 60&amp;6ivict.. repealed. c-32-32. The power of a local education authority under Part III. Power to pay of the Education Act, 1902, shall include a power to prosecute exPenses of any person for an offence of cruelty to children under section forTrudty! 40 twelve of the Children Act, 1908, and pay any expenses incidental to the prosecution. ...... ..94 d
A.D.1917.Provisions as to public inquiries by Board of Education./:, 33.-(1) The Board of Education may hold public inquiries under this section in any case where they consider that such an inquiry is desirable in respect of any question of administration or any question arising in connexion with education.(2) The following provisions shall apply to any such public 5 inquiry, and also to any public inquiry held in pursuance of any provisions of the Education Acts : (a) The inquiry shall be held by such person as the Boardof Education appoint:(b) The Board of Education shall cause public notice to be iqgiven of the time and place at which the inquiry is to be commenced, giving particulars of the subject-matter of the inquiry:(c) The person holding the inquiry shall give any personwho appears to him to be interested in the subject- 15 matter of the inquiry an opportunity of attending the inquiry and making representations with respect to the subject-matter thereof:-(d) The person holding the inquiry shall make a reportof the proceedings at the inquiry to the Board of 20 Education, and the Board  of Education shall, on payment of such fee not exceeding as .may be fixed by the Board, furnish a copy of the report   to any person  appearing to  them to be interested, and may, if they think fit, publish the 25 report.(3) The Board of Education may, if they think fit, appoint two or more persons to hold an inquiry, and the provisions of this section shall apply accordingly.(4) Section seventy-three of the Elementary Education Act, 30 1870,   and  subsection (10) of  section twenty-three   of  the Education Act, 1902, are hereby repealed.Costs of inquiries.34. (1) Where an application is made for a public inquiry, and the Board of Education are of opinion that an inquiry is unnecessary, the Board may require the applicant to give security 35 for the costs of the inquiry and if they think fit order the applicant to pay those costs.If an applicant fails to give the Board may refuse to hold the inquiry.security required, the
&apos; (2) The Board of Education may order the payment of the A.D. 1917. whole or any part of the costs of the inquiry by a local education authority, in any case where the inquiry appears to the Board to he incidental to the administration of that 5 authority, and it appears reasonable to the Board that such an order should be made.(3) Any order  so made for  the payment of  costs shall certify the amount to be paid by the local education authority or the applicant, as the  case may be, and any amount so 10 certified shall be a debt due to the Crown from the authority or the applicant, as the case may be.(4) Nothing in this section shall affect any special provision of the Education Acts as to the. payment of the costs of an inquiry.15       35. If any question arises whether any purpose for which Decision ofCGrfc&amp;niany authority having powers under the Education Acts have educational exercised or wish to exercise those powers is within their powers questions by under those Acts, that question shall be referred to and deter- Education mined by the Board of Education, and their decision shall be 20 conclusive on the matter.Education Grants.36.- (1) The fee grant under the Elementary Education Consoli-Act, 1891, as amended by the Elementary Education (Eee dated glaQt&apos; Grant)  Act, 1916,  the  aid  grant  under  section  ten  of  the25 Education Act, 1902, and the small population grant under section nineteen of the Elementary Education Act, 1876, as amended by. the Education Code (1890) Act, 1890, and the Education (Small Population Grants) Act, 1915, shall, on the appointed day, cease to be paid, except so far as any sum was30 payable in respect of those grants during the month immediately preceding the month in which the appointed day falls, and the Board of Education may by minute provide for the payment to every local education authority under Part III. of the Education Act, 1902, out of moneys provided by Parliament of a consolidated35 grant of such amount and subject to such conditions and imitations as maybe prescribed, and nothing in any Act of Parliament shall prevent the Board of Education from paying grants to a local education authority under Part III. of the Education Act, 1902, in respect of any expenditure which the40 authority may lawfully incur:94 . ,  D 2
20 Education. [ [7 &amp;-.8; Geo. 5;]A.D. 1917. [Provided that any local education authority which in the financial year ending thirty-first March one thousand nine hundred and eighteen did not receive any supplementary grant as defined in a minute of the Board of Education, dated the eighteenth day of April one thousand nine hundred and seventeen, 5 and whose equivalent rate for elementary education as computed for the purposes of that grant was not less than one shilling in the pound shall, in respect of each of the first five years after the appointed day, receive by way of consolidated grant a sum not less than the sum received by the authority in the financial 10 year ending thirty-first March one thousand nine hundred and eighteen, in respect of the grants which under this section cease to be paid and any other grants in respect of elementary education which in the opinion of the Board are superseded by the consolidated grant, but this provision shall be without 15 prejudice to the power to make deductions in respect of failure to observe any conditions attached to the consolidated grant.](2) The Board of Education may provide by minute for the payment, out of moneys provided by Parliament, of grants to the managers of any public elementary school not provided or 20 maintained by the local education authority.(3) The provisions of section ninety-seven of the Elementary Education Act, 1870, with respect to the laying of minutes before Parliament shall apply to minutes made for the purposes of this section as they apply to minutes made for the purposes 25 of that section.General.Definitions. 37. In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires, The expression. &quot; child&quot; means any child up to the age when his parents cease to be under an obligation to *q cause him to receive efficient elementary instruction or to attend school under the enactments relating to elemen-tary education and the byelaws made thereunder; The expression &quot; young person&quot; means a person undereighteen, years of age, who is no longer a child; 35The expression &quot;practical instruction&quot; means instruction in cookery, laundrywork, housewifery, dairywork, handi-crafts, and gardening, and such other subjects as the Board declare to be subjects of practical instruction;Other expressions have the same meaning as in the 40 Education Acts.
38.-(1) This Act shall not extend to Scotland or Ireland. A.D. 1917.(2) This Act shall come into operation on the appointed Short title, day, and the appointed day shall be such day as the Board of Education may appoint, and different days may be appointed for different purposes and for different provisions of this Act, for different areas or parts of areas, and for different persons or classes of persons. -(3) This Act may be cited as the Education Act, 1917, and shall be read as one with the Education Acts, 1870 to 1916, and those Acts and this Act may be cited together as the Education Acts, 1870 to 1917, and are in this. Act referred to as the Education Acts.

Education.diiaetOP ABILLto make further provision with respect to education in england and wales, and for purposes connected therewith.LXXXVII.   (3.)Uth May 1917.94,-6

</content>
</cab>
