<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/13/0 images: 434-439</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MOST SECRET&apos; WAR t CABINET.G.T. 709The Naval Position in the Mediterranean.The Secretary f,WAR CABINET.In accordance with the decision of the War Cabinet, I attach a paper on the subject of the Naval Position in the Mediterranean,- together with proposals for the future conduct oi operations in that region.(Signed)   J.R. JELLICOE.-First Sea Lord,21 et May, 1917,
NAVAL   POSITION   IN   THE   MEDITERRANEAN.At the outbreak of war, under the terms Of an Agreement made between the Admiralty and the French Ministry of Marine, the general direction of operations in the Mediterranean- was placed in the hands of the French.      It was also arranged that,, after the capture or destruction of the &quot;G*eben&quot; and &quot;Breslau&quot;&apos;, the British Battle Cruisers and Cruisers would be released for general service, and that the remainder of the British Forces would-be placed under the orders of the Commander-in-Chief of the French&apos; FleetThe latter arrangement was carried out after the two-German ships had entered the Dardanelles, and had been sold to the Turks, except that the two Battle Cruisers under Vlee-Admiral Carden were retained in the Aegean Sea to prevent their escape,.After the entry of Turkey into the war the C-ommander-in-Chief, East Indies, was ordered to proceed to Port Said to conduct the naval defence of Egypt and the Suez Canal,When, the Dardanelles operation was decided upon, it was arranged that the Naval Forces engaged should act under the command of a British Admiral; and,-so far as this opera-ticn was concerned, that he should not be under the orders of the Frenoh Commander-in-Chief.-This arrangement has continued up to the present, in that the Vice-Admiral, Eastern Mediterranean Squadron, con-ducts all operations on the coasts of Bulgaria and Turkey, the Gallipoli Peninsula, .and Asia Miner, ae far as a line joining the Northern Cape of Rhodes Inland to Cape Marmarice.2..   On the entry of Italy into the war, control of all operations in.the Adriatic was vested in the Commander-in-Chief of the Italian Fleet under the terms of the Naval Convention of the 26th April, 1915, and in whioh it was also agreed that the Allied Fleets would work together in close co-operation.When the submarine campaign on merchant vessels had been started by the   Germans, an arrangement was made by which the Mediterranean was divided up int:^ zones and each of the allied nations became responsible for the protection of shipping within certain of the zones.Under these arrangements the Senior Naval Officers at Gibraltar and Malta, .the. Vice-Admiral, Eastern Mediterranean Squadron, and the Commander-in-Chief, .East Indies, are each in charge of one of the British zones, so that the French Commander-in-Chief has four British Naval Authorities with whom to communicate,German submarines operating in the Mediterranean make use of the Austrian.porta in the Adriatic for bases from which to work,and it has been recognised for some time that the most effective, means for dealing with them would be to cut them off from their bases by means of a barrage in the Straits of Otranto Under the terms of the Italian Convention,these Straits are under the Italian : Command, but, as the Italians had not the material required, the British have provided a large number of net-drifters and motor launches, -  For the protection of the drifters it has been arranged that the Italians should maintain patrol North of the drifter line and the French to the South,
Twolve French Destroyers and six Submarines were attached to. the Italian Fleet in accordance with the Gcnven-tion and are stationed at Brindisi.     These vessels should be available for these duties, but they do not appear to be used very effectively, with the result that the Austrians have carried out several raids on the drifter line similar to the one recently reported.It is believed that the Destroyers, both French and Italian, are continually being employed for other work, and the different Forces being under separate Commands there is an absence of real co-operation.Tho French and Italian Fleets in the Mediterranean in commission consist of :-French   Italian&apos;&apos; Dreadnought Battleships      7 5Older Battleships..,.&apos;.       13 9&apos; Cruisers ,,...........       11 -6Light Cruisers .......        1 10 (3 of which have speedexceeding 26 knots &amp; are equally well armed - as Austrians.There are 3 British - - Light Cruisers inaddition.)Flotilla Leaders...... 7 ( Very good armamentand high speed.)Destroyers ...........     67 43Torpedo Boats ........     15 81,Submarines ...&quot;........ &apos;. 21       -  49 ( including 3 British&quot;E&quot; Class &amp; 7 small Italian   submarines);while the strength of the Austrian Fleet, so far as is known, is as follows :-Dreadnought Battleships    &apos;4       &apos;  !Older Battleships .....   12Cruis ers ..............     &amp;Light Cruisers ........     9 (4 6f which have speed of26-28 knots:   only 4&quot; guns).Destroyers ............   16Torpedo Boats ....... ..C 69 lst.class.(28 2nd class.Submarines(including German) .. 40 (about).
3 **It is obvious then that the combined French and Italian Fleets are much more than a match for the Austrians if they worked together in ol-t^e harmony and co-operation and presided that correct dispositions are in force. Incidents such as the rdeent Austrian raid raise doubts on both these points, and tho matter is one oi very real importance to the Allied cause.As regards co-operation between the two Navies, certain incidents which have occurred give rise to misgivings. The command ef tha Otrante Barrage has bean a vexed question for some time, and it was hoped that a satisfactory solution had been reached when it was agreed at the London Conference to plaoe it in British hands under the general control of the Italian Commander-in-Chief.   But it is evident that, unless the British Senior Naval Officer receives adequate support from the two Navies, be cannot adequately guard the small vessels working the nets.   The recent ineident shows that he has not this support, and v/e have deemed it necessary, pending the institution of more satisfactory arrangements, to withdraw the small craft at night.At the London Conference it also became apparent in the course of the discussions which took plaoe that the Italians viewed with much disfavour the entry of the French Fleet into the Adriatic, especially if this involved placing the Italian Fleet under the command of the Franoh Commander-in-Chief.. Unity ef. command In fact was not obtained, and, until thityachieved, the heat results cannot be brought about by the great superiority of the Allied over the Austrian Fleet.3. The other point which directly affects the questionof the efficiency of the Otranto Barrage and the blocking of the Straits to the passage of eneiay submarines is the strategical disposition of the Destroyers, Torpedo Boats and Submarines of tha Italian Fleet.   This disposition appears to be affected by fear of coast raids.   A large force of Destroyers, Torpedo Boats and Submarines Is stationed at Venice and, if one can judge by the Inactivity of the 3 British submarines of the &quot;H&quot; Class also stationed there, it la doubtful if full use is made of so strong a force.   It is dlffloult to appreciate the necessity for the presence of the 19 Italian submarines which wore at Venice on April 21st (the date of our last return).     The employment suggested for these submarines is that of blockading the Austrians at Pola and Cattaro and working amongst the Islands on the Dalmatian Coast where they should find surface vessels as targets..   They should also be able to make such operations as the receat Austrian raid on the Otranto Barrage extremely hazardous.
AAt Brindisi and Valeria the return shows that, on the Slat April, there were present 11 French Destroyers, 3 Italian flotilla Leaders, 9 torpedo Boat Destroyers, 16 Torpedo   Boats and 9 Submarines, in addition to 3 British and 1 fast Italian Light Cruisers.    tt would seem that--such an operation as the recent Otranto raid should ndt be possible without heavy enemy losses provided full use is made of this force.     Italy possesses 3 Light Cruisers of a speed equal to that of the Austrians, but one was at Tarante on April  1st, and a second at Spezzia.   It is highly desirable that they should all oe concentrated either at Brindisi or Valoha,It is observed that the organisation of the Italian Destroyers and Torpedo Boats is much broken up;   boats of a division being scattered-amongst different ports.   This would in the British ITavy lead to a want of cohesion owing to the boats of a division not working together4.     It would undoubtedly tend to greater efficiency were the whole of the naval operations in the Mediterranean to come under one command.   At present the Italians command in the Adriatic, and the rrench outside:   obviously a bad arrangement. It is, however, most improbable that the Italians, would consent to operations in the Adriatic being under any other command than that of an Italian Flag Officer,, and, seeing that France possesses by far the most powerful Fleet in the Mediterranean, It is also very unlikely that the French Government would agree to the chief command being exercised by any other than a French officer.It would no doubt be greatly to the advantage of naval operations were a British Flag Officer to assume the chief command in the Mediterranean, in which case it would be necessary for aim to fly his flag afloat in a vessel of the Dreadnought type. The proposal if made to the French Government would, however, probably give rise to ill-feeling, which might *p-ae* injuriously on our relations with the French in naval luattere, ^hich are on the whole satisfactory;   and, after reflection, I consider it woula be better not to attempt to take over the command, although J am of opinion that we ehould put strongly before the French ana Italians the present unsatisfactory state of affairs in the Aoriatio,PBCTFCTICff Or MEBCHAFT SKIPPING.5.     Our interests in the Mediterranean in, regard to Mercantile shipping are very great and it would, I am sure, prove very beneficial if the control of the arrangements for the protection or shipping in the whole Mediterranean vere placed in our hands, and it is considered very neoes;iary that this should be arranged, v/hatever arrangement is made as to the control of major operations.There is no ground for objection on the part of the/
French or the Italians to such an arrangement., Cur interests in the protection of mercantile shipping exceed those or eitherof our Allies, and we have/^o guard lines of communication toSalonica and Egypt which are of great importance as the strengthof our military forces in those areas is far greater than thoseof either Franca or Italy.I therefore consider that we should insist on this control being placed in British hands.For the arrangement to be successful, it ivould be necessary for a British Admiral, of&quot;strong personality and gifted with tact to be plaoed in command of all the British- Forces in the Mediterr-anean, including those in Egypt.     He should he stationed at Malta and be the head of a Council -of Allied Flag Officers who would represent the Interests of their respective countries in regard to settlement of routes throughout the Mediterranean and patrol and escort work.   This would relieve the French Commander-in-chief, who is at present in general charge.     The present arrangement is not satisfactory as his main business is the control of his Fleet; he is usually at Corfu, which is not well placed for controlling traffic, and, should- the Fleet be at sea, the control obviously ceases.(Signed)       J.K. JISLUCOE,Slat May 1917.

</content>
</cab>
