<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/13/0 images: 440-442</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETWAR ;CABINET.G.T. 790Shipments to Russia.359Sir,I am directed by the Shipping Controller to advert tgjthe War Cabinet Minutes cf Oth Instant (War Cabinet 134) - No, (fif) in which the following passage occurs:- &apos; ^&quot;The War Cabinet were informed that ships were sailing to Russia half empty,that this fact was bound to create a bad impression,and that considerable pressure was being applied by the Russian Government and their representatives in this country to send more material.11This Information is quite without foundation in fact.   Apart from thirteen colliers,up to the present three ships only,belonging. to the summer programme have sailed from this country, and a note is attached of the cargoes of all sixteen vessels.   It is possible thct the inaccurate statement may have arisen from the fact that the S.S. &quot;CZAR&quot; has only loaded a half-cargo of munitions owing to the remainder of her space being occupied by passengers ae shown in the note.   The Shipping Controller would be very glad to learn the source of the information furnished to the War Cabinet,in order to prevent a recurrence,if possible, and Would suggest that in the event of such information being furnished in the future,he should be consulted in the matter before it is placed before the War Cabinet.   Eurther,the Shipping Controller would be glad if an entry could be made in the War Cabinet Minutes in contradiction of the statement made in the Minutes of 8th May.With regard to the statement as to the Russian Government applying pressure to send more material from this Country; this is also inacurzvt5,    As a matter of fact,owing to the withdrawal of the heavy artillery,cargo on Russian Government account has not come forward as freely as was anticipated.   Indeed opportunity was taken tt withdraw one steamer before loading as the Russian Severn-ment Committee were unable to supply cargo within the time allotted by the Shipping Controller as the moiximum for loading.   This back-wardness of cargo has made it easier to carry out the War Cabinet&apos;s ruling as to the postponement of the provision of tonnageywhich would otherwise have presented considerable difficulties.As regards the Russian programme generally:    the Shipping Ccn-troller has not placed any more tonnage at the disposal of the Russian Committee in America, and a somewhat serious position is arising there, owing to the fact that the U.S.A. Government have only furnished one ship up to the present, whereas something like 100,000 tons of cargo i3 now awaiting shipment in U.S.A   for which no tonnage has been provided.Steps are being taken to cut down the sailings of the Colliers to the 107/est limits compatible with not alarming the Russians, and during the weeks ending 19th and 26th May a total of 10 3teamera carrying about 50,000 tons of coal have been diverted to Italian service.I am,Sir,Your obedient Servant,Signed)   E. MANIFOLD RAEBUBN.
ENCLOSURE I.NOTE Q? SAILINGS FROM U.K.PORTS FOR ARCHANGEL SINCE COMMENCEMENT OF 1917 SEASON.I-   S/S &quot;FIRRAL&quot; from London 6th May.Tons deadweight available for cargo.........6?500 tonsFeight of cargo shipped.................----5,675 tonsB/L Tons shipped (including 515 tons of -  buoys and accessories, measurement ofwhich id estimated at 1,500 tons)......7,644 tonsH. S/S &quot;CZAR&quot; froji Liverpool 30th April j(called later at Glasgow for passengers)Tons deadweight available for Cargo.........4,000 tonsNOTE. Only the lower holds, however, were actually available for cargo, the upper and lower &quot;tween decks being fitted for passengers, viz:500 French Officers &amp; soldiers. 600 Russian sailors from &quot;VARYOG&quot;100 Russian political refugees, &amp; 200 miscellaneous passengers -1,400   of whom 900 sailed.Weight of cargo shipped.............&apos;........1,411 tonsB/L Tons shipped............................ .2,218 tons11- S/S &quot;ZINGARA&quot;   from Manchester 11th MayTons deadweight available for cargo........4,800 tonsWeight of cargo shipped........,...........5,545 tonsB/L Tone shipped................5,599 tons
1.2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. .8, 9.10. 11.12, 13.	ENCLOSURE II.		N0T3	so? COLLIER SAILINGS FOR		ARCHANGEL .s3	INCE COiHiSNCEiiENT	of 1917 season.	Ship.	Loading, Port,	Date of Sailing.	Approxii CargtTAPTON.	Tyne.	11/5/17.	4,000CHATton*	IT	12/5/17.	- 5,400WORON (Russian)	11	12/5/17.	4,400ROBERT CGV3RLALE-.	. Blyth.	13/5/17,	5, 000CLmiBElmALL.	Cardiff.	13/5/17.	5,200NOVIHGTON.	ti	14/5/17.	53000dalliNgtqn.		15/5/17.	3,800R0S3AN0.	Tyne.	do.	-5,500BASUTA.	Bli^th,	do.	3,800DGMIRA.	ti	do.	4,300CHISWICK.	Tyne.	do.	4,500BON CESAR.	. tt	do.	5,000ADALIA.	n	do.	5,00060,900

</content>
</cab>
