<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/36/0 images: 64-69</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet. January 1962C.C. (62) Copy No. 4 i8th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1, onThursday, 25th January, 1962, at 10-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department (Items 2-5)The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P.. Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Lord Mills, minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Ernest Marples,M.P., Minister of Transport (items-3)The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. The Earl of Home,SecreFary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations the Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of aviation the Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P., President of the Board of trade the following were also present:The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Pensions and national Insurance (Items 4-5)The Right Hon. J. Enoch Powell, M.P.,Minister of Health (Items 4-5)The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman brook mr. A. L. M. gary mr. J. H. waddell this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT
contents minute no. Subject page 1      Imperial Chemical Industries and Courtaulds        ......       32     Parliament       .........      ............       33      Economic Situation     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       3Planning4      Public Expenditure     ......      ............       4Estimates for 1962-635     Education............      .........       5Investment Expenditure
ImperialChemicalIndustries andCourtaulds(previous reference:C.C. (62) 7thConclusions,Minute 1)Parliament 2.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons in the following week.EconomicSituationPlanning(previous reference:C.C. (61) 65thConclusions,Minute 2)60500-43. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the general council of the Trades Union Congress had now agreed, subject to conditions, to be represented on the National Economic development council. The letter in which they had conveyed their decision wasnot as negative as might be thought from the reports published in thePress.   Their conditions were not unduly restrictive: it had alwaysSECRETA 21. The Cabinet resumed their discussion of the attempt by imperial Chemical Industries (LCI.) Limited to acquire control overCourtaulds Limited. They had before them alternative drafts,prepared in the light of their earlier discussion on 23rd January, of a parliamentary statement defining the Governments attitude towards this operation.Discussion showed that the Cabinet were now agreed that it wouldbe inexpedient for the Government to take any action designed toprevent or delay this attempt to bring under unified management themanufacture of man-made fibres in this country. This being so, thequestion remaining for decision was whether the Government should at once announce that they were not proposing to intervene, or whetherthis announcement should be delayed for a few days so as to avoid any impression that the Government had failed to give full considerationto any national interests involved. In favour of the latter course itwas argued that it would be useful if the Chairmen of the two companies could have an opportunity of furnishing furtherinformation, or making further representations, as they might desire.Nor was there any reason why the Board of Trade should not themselves seek from the companies such further information as they required. A statement of the Governments attitude should, however,be made in Parliament early in the following week.In the course of the Cabinets discussion it was recognised thatthe current dispute between LCI. and Courtaulds had crystallised the growing public anxiety about the effect which large-scale mergers ofindustrial or commercial companies might have upon the national interest. The Jenkins Committee were likely to report that mergersand take-over bids could assist towards the expansion of the national economy. Even so, the Government might well be pressed to assumefurther powers to control these operations. More thought would need to be given to the general questions of policy involved.The Cabinet (1) Decided that the Government should not take any actiondesigned to prevent or delay the attempt by LCI. Ltd. to gain control over Courtaulds Ltd., and agreed that astatement to this effect should be made in Parliament on30th January.(2) Took note that the President of the Board of Trade would arrange for the Chairmen of the two companies concerned to have an opportunity to make such further representa-tions as they might wish to offer to him before this statement was made.(3) Invited the President of the Board of Trade, in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster, theMinister of Aviation and the Minister without Portfolio,to prepare and submit for the Prime Ministers approvala revised draft of the statement to be made in parliament on 30th January.
been understood that their representatives on the Council would be free to report back to the General Council and that the latter wouldnot, by their membership, be debarred from expressing publicreservations about Government decisions. It had never been thought likely that they would be willing to give active support to a policy of wage restraint. The main objective had been to get the Trades UnionCongress to participate in the work of the Development Council, andthis had been achieved.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, would be making a short statement in Parliament that afternoon welcoming the decision of the general council. A further statement would be made later about the detailsof the planning machinery now to be established.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Chancellor of theExchequer.4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the chief secretary, Treasury (C. (62) 16) summarising the main facts and issuesfacing the Government on public expenditure.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that the prospect for the1962-63 Estimates was not encouraging. As compared with a totalof  5,187 million for the 1961-62 Estimates the figure for 1962-63 nowstood at  5,610 million, a rise of  423 million or over 8 per cent. when allowance had been made for increases in pay and prices and for increases due to book-keeping alterations under the new form of estimates, the gross increase of  423 million was reduced to anincrease of  244 million. The Chancellor of the Exchequer hadpledged himself to allow no more than a 2-V per cent, increase in real terms in the Estimates for 1962-63 as compared with those for1961-62; and  244 million was an increase of A\ per cent. To meetthe pledge savings of  110 million would be needed. Towards this figure the only proposals now before the Cabinet, for savings on welfare milk and on school meals, would contribute  37-J- millionleaving  72 million still to find. If no reduction could be made on this figure of  72 million the increase in real terms between the two years would be between 31 per cent, and 4 per cent.In discussion the following points were made:(a) The belief that it would be possible to restrict the increase in real terms between the Estimates for 1961-62 and those for 1962-63to 2\ per cent, had seemed reasonable in the circumstances at the time.But it was now clear that the cost of agricultural subsidies and of the deficit on railway operation had been seriously under-estimated.(b) The savings on welfare services which the Cabinet were now considering would produce comparatively small sums of moneycompared with the large sums at stake in other sectors, such astransport and agriculture, over which the Government had little or no control. The political effect of reductions in welfare services wouldbe considerable and in the light of the larger and less controlledexpenditures elsewhere it was not clear how much real economicbenefit they would secure.(c) There was no prospect of meeting the 2\ per cent, pledge infull. The question to be decided was how far short of it theGovernment could afford to fall without running a serious risk of afurther economic emergency. The greater the shortfall, the greater the need to show that the Government had strengthened their controlover the growth of public expenditure in the longer term.The Cabinet Took note of C. (62) 16 and of the points made in the cabinet&apos;s discussion.
EducationInvestmentExpenditure(previous reference:C.C. (62). 4thConclusions,Minute 3)5. The Cabinet resumed their consideration of memoranda bythe Chief Secretary, Treasury (C. (.62)-4). and; the Minister of Education(iC. (61) 221) on the level of educational investment, and by theMinister of Education (C. (62) 5) on educational policy.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that, as it now seemed unlikely that the Estimates for 1962-63 could be kept within the limits which had been announced as the Governments aim, it would be themore important that the Government should be able to show that public expenditure in the longer term had been brought under firmercontrol. Some progress had already been made in settling forwardprogrammes of public investment-for example, on roads and health on the lines which had been, forecast by the Chancellor of theExchequer in his Budget statement in 1.961, and further action wouldbe required on defence, agriculture, housing and the nationalised industries. A decision on educational investment was, however,particularly urgent because of its effect on the provisional programme for building starts in 1962-63 which had already been made known tolocal education authorities. He accepted the importance of economic growth and believed that educational investment would assist it in themore distant future. He had, however, felt obliged to propose some reduction in the rate of expansion of educational, investment in theyears immediately ahead because he considered that it should make its contribution to the task of avoiding financial crises in that period.In the past 10 years the gross national product had been expanding at about 3 per cent, per annum and a faster rate of increase in the nearfuture seemed unlikely. But the proposals put forward by the Ministerof Education would mean accepting an increase for education at a rateof about 4 - 6 per cent, per annum, which would call for correspondingrestraint in other programmes. An average annual investment of 121 million over the three years 1963-66 would be the appropriatemaximum.The Minister of Education said that he did not believe hiscolleagues would accept postponements in the programmes for teacher training and technical education. The school population was continuing to rise and, even if present policies were maintained, thepupil/teacher ratio, which now stood at 29-7 in primary schools,would worsen to 33-3 by 1965. Any interference with the supply of teachers would have a serious effect on this ratio; and it would be equally unfortunate politically to have to announce any reduction in expenditure by local education authorities on technical education. Asubstantial cut had already been made in expenditure on minor works,and the effect of any further postponement of investment expendituremust fall wholly on the schools programme. On this the Governmentwere committed by the White Paper of 1958 to expenditure totalling 300 million ( 320 million at currrent prices) over five years. Theprogramme of starts which was set out in the Annex to C. (62) 4 hadbeen designed to give effect to this plan and reductions could not bemade on the scale suggested by the Chief Secretary, Treasury, without making adjustments in programme starts which would be regarded asa serious breach of the undertakings given. He thought that a systemof starting controls would on that basis be inescapable. by administrative action, however, and without making any public announcement or establishing control of starts, it would be possible toreduce the starts proposed for 1963-64 and 1964-65 to  60 million foreach year, thus reducing the average annual investment over the threeyears 1963-66 to  13.1 million.In discussion the following points were made:(a) The proposal by the Chief Secretary, Treasury, involvedspreading over 28 months starts which on the original proposals of theMinister of Education would have been made in 24 months.  But it
involved postponements in the programmes for teacher training andtechnical education as well as for schools. In effect the only way of reducing education expenditure substantially would be to have fewerteachers and larger classes.(b) It would be unfortunate if the Government had to accept thatprovisional notifications made in July 1960 could not be reviewed inthe light of changing economic circumstances. Despite the badimpression which would be given by enforcing postponements theGovernment ought to be ready to effect economies in education as wellas in other long-term programmes.(c) In reviewing education expenditure, account should be taken of the very high rate of investment called for by the universityexpansion programme.(d) The Economic Policy Committee had begun an examinationof the investment situation in the building industry and the possibleneed for physical or other forms of control in the private sector. any form of building control would, however, have to contend with serious difficulties, including the fact that some forms of investment expenditure tended to give rise to much more current expenditurethan others. Within the public sector alone the Government had much difficulty in establishing priorities and it should not be assumed that priorities in the private sector could be determined more readily.(e) Any announcement of a decision to reduce the rate of educational investment should be made as part of a general statementdealing also with other investment programmes. It would be valuableif the gap between the proposals on education made by the chief secretary, Treasury, and the Minister of Education could be further examined with a view to an agreed proposal being put before theCabinet.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Home Secretary (i) in consultation with the Chief Secretary, Treasury,and the Minister of Education, to examine the rateof educational investment in the light of their discussion;(ii) to bring before them proposals for announcing theGovernments decisions on education and otherlong-term investment programmes listed inparagraph 6 of C. (62) 16(2) Took note that the Economic Policy Committee had in handan examination of investment in the building industry andwould take into account the possible need for physical orother forms of control over building in the private sector.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,25th January, 1962.

</content>
</cab>
