<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/36/0 images: 83-89</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1962C.C. (62) Copy No.11th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1, on tuesday, 6th February, 1962, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for  the home department the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secrefary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of aviation the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P.,  Secretary  of  State  for the colonies the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Lord Mills, minister without portfolio the Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P., President of the Board of trade the following were also present:The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury the Duke of Devonshire, joint parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState for Commonwealth Relations(Items 3-6)Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman brook mr. A. L. M. cary mr. J. H. Waddell
contents minute no. Subject page 1      The Queen       ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       32      Foreign Affairs.....................       3BerlinLeipzig Fair, 19623      West Indies      .....................       44      Antarctica        .....................       4Whaling in South Georgia5      Germany ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       5Deconcentration of Krupp&apos;s6      Farm Price Review, 1962-63...............       6t
Foreign 2.   The   Foreign   Secretary   said   that   the   United   StatesAffairs Ambassador in Moscow, Mr. Thompson, had now held threeBerlin discussions with the Soviet Foreign Minister, Mr. Gromyko, in(Previous        pursuance of his instructions to ascertain whether a basis could be reference:       found for negotiations on the future of West Berlin.   No progressC.C. (62) 5th    had been made, but Mr. Gromyko had shown no signs of impatience.Conclusions,     it was conceivable that the Soviet Government were less anxious for a minute 4)       new settlement on Berlin now that they had secured more effective control over movement between the two parts of the city.   But itmight be possible to probe rather more deeply into their attitude ifthe British Ambassador in Moscow were now to hold some separatediscussions with Mr. Gromyko.   Within the limits of the agreedinstructions to Mr. Thompson he should be able to ascertain whether mr. Gromyko was prepared to enter into detailed discussion on suchpoints as the status of Western troops in West Berlin and the basisof future dealings with the Government of East Germany.   TheForeign Secretary said that he was taking steps to ascertain whetherthe United States Government would favour such an approach.The Cabinet (1) Took note of this statement by the Foreign Secretary.Leipzig The Foreign Secretary said that it had been proposed in the fair, 1962 North Atlantic Council that members of the Alliance shoulddiscourage their nationals from supporting the Leipzig Fair, whichwas exploited for propaganda purposes by the East GermanGovernment. He had been considering with the President of theBoard of Trade whether any further action should be taken to discourage British firms from supporting this Fair.In discussion it was suggested that West German firms would notmiss this opportunity of expanding their business with East Germanyand that, short of an effective boycott by all members of the north atlantic Alliance, it seemed unreasonable that we should take further action which would penalise our export prospects. There was generalagreement that, while we should conform to any resolution adoptedby the North Atlantic Council, we should not take any separateinitiative to discourage British ifirms from attendance at this Fair.Any public statement on behalf of the United Kingdom Governmentshould follow the announcement of an agreement on this question in the North Atlantic Council, and should merely draw the attentionof British firms to that agreement.The Cabinet-(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary and the President of the Boardof Trade to deal with the problem of British representation at the Leipzig Fair in the light of the views expressed inthe Cabinefs discussion.C.C. 11 (62)The Queen 1.   The Cabinet invited the Prime Minister to send to her majesty The Queen a message expressing their loyalty andcongratulations on the tenth anniversary of her accession to the throne.
west indies(previous reference:C.C. (61) 52ndConclusions,Minute 4)3. The Colonial Secretary said that he would be expected tomake an early statement in Parliament on his recent visit to the west indies. His primary object had been to discuss with the leaders ofthe Governments in the Eastern Caribbean the situation arising fromJamaica&apos;s desire to leave the West Indies Federation. The main elements in the situation were that the Government had accepted thedecision of Jamaica to withdraw from the Federation; that trinidad and Tobago had decided not to participate in any federation of theEastern Caribbean; and that the Ministers in the Leeward andWindward Islands, while advocating a new federation between their territories, were agreed that the present Federation should bedissolved. He proposed to inform Parliament that in thesecircumstances the Government had decided, with regret, that theyhad no alternative but to arrange for the Federation to be dissolved;that legislation for this purpose would shortly be introduced and thatthe Bill would provide for an interim organisation to be set up undera commissioner appointed by the Government to administer thecommon services for the time being until more permanent arrangements could be worked out in consultation with the local governments It would be premature to describe the suggestedfederation of Barbados and the Leeward and Windward Islands as more than a promising development, and he would emphasise theneed for further study before any final decisions could be taken on it.In discussion there was general agreement in the Cabinet thatthe dissolution of the West Indies Federation could not be prevented.It was noted that officials of the Treasury and the Colonial Office were examining the economic problems involved in future constitutional developments.The Cabinet Authorised the Colonial Secretary to make an early statement in Parliament, on the lines which he had indicated,on future constitutional developments in the West Indies.Antarctica 4.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the MinisterWhaling in of State for Colonial Affairs (C. (62) 17) on whaling in South Georgia.South Georgia Thg Co!onjai Secretary said that two companies, one scottish and the other Norwegian, were now operating whaling stations from south Georgia. The Scottish company had been losing moneysteadily and now had an opportunity to dispose of its interests to a japanese company. If this company acquired the Scottish station, itwould probably acquire the Norwegian station also in course of time.The population of South Georgia would then be mainly Japanese.This might be awkward for our administration of the island; but hecould see no valid reason for refusing to allow the Scottish company to sell.In discussion the following points were made:(a) If this deal went through, the Scottish company wouldprobably discontinue its whaling operations altogether in the next fewyears. Whale oil was not important to our economy. The fourhundred Shetlanders now employed in this industry would be able tofind other employment as seamen.(b) If the Government sought to obstruct the sale, they would be pressed to subsidise these whaling operations.(c) It was thought unlikely that objection would be raised by theAustralian and New Zealand Governments. They should, however,be given an opportunity for comment. A change of ownership of thewhaling stations in South Georgia might increase our difficulties in maintaining our claims to sovereignty in the Antarctic.
Germany 5.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theDeconcentration Foreign Secretary (C. (62) 19) on the present state of the plan forofKrupp&apos;s       de-concentrating Krupp&apos;s industrial interests in West Germany.The Foreign Secretary said that the problem now centred on theRheinhausen Company, an integrated coal and steel enterprise whosepresent value would be well over  100 million. The federal government would not be willing, even if they were able, to introduce legislation to enforce the sale of this company by nationalisation orby other means. There seemed no prospect of a sale on any voluntary basis. It therefore seemed that the United Kingdom Governmenthad now no alternative but to join with the United States and french governments in relieving the Federal German Government of anyfurther obligation to carry through the deconcentration plan whichhad been agreed as part of the Bonn Settlement Convention. the timing of any announcement to this effect would need consideration;it might have an important bearing on negotiations for our entry intothe Common Market.In discussion the following points were made:(a) The logical time to announce the abandonment of this plan would be after a decision had been taken on United kingdom membership of the European Coal and Steel Community. Krupp&apos;scoal and steel interests were under the general control of theCommunity and it could be argued that, once the United kingdom had become a member of the Community, our interests would bebetter served by leaving Herr Krupp in control of the RheinhausenCompany than by putting him in a position to invest more than 100 million in other enterprises over which we should be unable toexercise any control.(b) If it became known that the Government were consideringrelieving the Federal Government of this obligation, this would haveembarrassing political consequences and might also be held to be insome way connected with the current negotiations with the federal government on support costs and arms purchases. There was in factno reason for the Government to take the initiative in this: the mixedcommittee of independent experts which had been set up to considerthe matter would almost certainly recommend a further extension ofthe time limit until 31st January, 1963, in default of any decision bythe French, United States and United Kingdom Governments toabandon the deconcentration plan.(d) The Japanese company should not be given any assurance that there would be no change in the duty on whale oil, which hadbeen adjusted to favour a British whaling industry.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Commonwealth Secretary to arrange for theGovernments of Australia and New Zealand to be given  an opportunity for comment on the proposed sale of thiswhaling station in South Georgia to a Japanese company.(2) Subject to Conclusion (1), agreed that no objection shouldbe raised to the sale of this whaling station to a Japanesecompany.
The Cabinet (i) Agreed that no action should be taken which might have theeffect of accelerating a decision to abandon the Kruppdeconcentration plan or of requiring the Government to declare their present attitude towards this.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to review the position in thelight of any further moves by the French and UnitedStates Governments and in any case before 31st January,1963.6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the chief secretary, Treasury (C. (62) 21) on short-term economies in the costof agricultural support and the Annual Farm Price Review.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that, in accordance withearlier decisions of the Cabinet, officials had examined the possibilityof securing further economies in the cost of agricultural support in the short term. It would be inexpedient at this stage to make the major change in policy which would be involved by applying the principleof &quot; standard quantities &quot;, which would limit the quantity of produceon which guaranteed prices were paid for certain commodities forwhich no such limits were at present fixed. It would, however, be practicable to abolish the general Exchequer subsidy on milk. Thissubsidy arose because the standard quantity on which the price of milk was guaranteed exceeded by some 100 million gallons the total amount of liquid consumption (including a margin to cater fordrought conditions), of which the cost was recovered from consumers.The Exchequer bore the loss on this difference of 100 million gallonswhich had been sold for manufacturing. Officials had recommendedthat if the subsidy were to be removed this should be done by raising the price of liquid milk to consumers by \d. a pint for four months in the year above what it would otherwise have been. The farm price Review Committee had considered this recommendation andhad agreed that, whether it could be accepted or not, consultations with the National Farmers&apos; Unions should be opened on the basis that there must this year be a minimum determination which wouldenable the value of the guarantees to farmers to be reduced by about 14i million.It seemed on the whole desirable that the Government should inthis year&apos;s Review take back an increase of 0 - 8d. per gallon on milk,which had been given in the previous year on the understanding thatthe unions would propose an alternative (which they had not in fact been able to devise) to the present support arrangements. The benefitof this change, however (amounting to about  6i million) would accrue to the consumer rather than the Exchequer, and the advantage to the Exchequer from a minimum determination would inconsequence be limited to  8 million. He therefore proposed that inaddition to taking back the 0-8d. per gallon increase,  8 million should be saved for the Exchequer by adopting the recommendationof officials that the general milk subsidy should be abolished. taken together with the  8 million saving on commodities other than milk,this would give a total saving to the Exchequer of  16 million.The Minister of Agriculture said that a decision on these linescould be criticised as unfair to consumers. It would require theconsumer of liquid milk to meet, not only the cost of the milkconsumed directly plus the cost of the margin for drought conditions,but also the loss on the 100 million gallons which were used for manufacturing purposes. The change would be represented asinvolving a tax on milk of %d. a pint for four months.
Cabinet Office, S.W.1,6th February, 1962.Discussion showed that it was the general view of the Cabinetthat, despite the difficulty to which the Minister of Agriculture had referred, it would be desirable to secure the full range of savings whichhad been proposed. It would be recognised that consumers of liquid milk were also consumers of milk products. Moreover, in view ofthe special difficulties which had been experienced over agricultural support prices in the past year, the Government would be consideredjustified in making every possible saving. This would hold even if,as in the present case, it could be said that withdrawal of the generalmilk subsidy might encourage farmers to produce more beef, whichwould further depress meat prices and increase the cost of support.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that in the forthcoming Annual Farm Price review the Government should aim at withholding the 0-8d. per gallon increase agreed in the previous review and securing 8 million savings on commodities other than milk.(2) Agreed in principle that the general Exchequer subsidy on milk should be abolished.

</content>
</cab>
