<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/36/0 images: 121-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1962C.C. (62)17th conclusions copy No. 4 cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 27th February, 1962, at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. viscount lord chancellor the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of aviation the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P.,  Secretary  of  State  for  the colonies the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and FoodKilmuir,The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,Minister of education the Right Hon. Lord Mills, minister without portfolio the Right Hon. JohnMinister of labour hare, M.P.,Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P., President of the Board of trade also present:The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne, M.P., Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman brook mr. A. L. M. gary mr. J. H. Waddell
contents minute no.                                     subject      Foreign Affairs............BerlinCongo RepublicLaosDisarmament2     Europe   ......      .........3      EducationBurnham committee      Uganda............5      Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland
Congo Republic       The Foreign Secretary said that the Prime Ministers of the(Previous        Central Congo Government and of Katanga had now agreed to holdReference:       a further meeting, without the mediation of the United StatesC.C. (62) 13th   Ambassador, and there seemed to be some prospect that they mightConclusions,     reach agreement.   Pending the results of this meeting, the united minute 2)        Nations authorities were not pursuing their project for stationingtroops in Jadotville and Kolwezi.   If, however, the meeting were unsuccessful, this project would be revived, and it might then beforcefully resisted by the Katangan Government.Laos(previous reference:C.C. (62) 7thConclusions,Minute 3)Disarmament(previous reference:C.C. (62) 13thConclusions,Minute 1)The Foreign Secretary said that the Pathet Lao were now operating near the cease-fire line in Laos, but fighting had not yet.broken out on any large scale. Despite pressure from the UnitedStates authorities, General Phoumi was still unwilling to join theGovernment proposed by Prince Souvanna Phouma; but the King ofLaos was intending to make a further attempt to secure the formationof a national Laotian Government.The Foreign Secretary said that there now seemed to be generalagreement that the opening stages of the Disarmament Conferenceat Geneva should be attended by Foreign Ministers. It was possible,however, that some meeting of Heads of Governments might takeplace at a later stage, either to advance some initial progress made bythe Conference or possibly to try to break through a deadlock.Europe 2.   The Lord Privy Seal said that in a statement made to the(Previous        European Economic Community on 10th October, 1961, he had reference:       indicated that the United Kingdom Government would at theC.C. (62) 10th   appropriate time open negotiations with a view to joining theConclusions,    European Coal and Steel Community and the European AtomicMmute 3)       Energy Community.   Informal soundings suggested that there was general agreement that the time was now ripe for such an approach.He therefore proposed that formal applications to join these twoorganisations should now be lodged on behalf of the United KingdomGovernment.   The detailed negotiations would then be opened in about two months&apos; time.The Cabinet-Authorised the Lord Privy Seal to submit on behalf of theUnited Kingdom Government formal applications to join the European Coal and Steel Community and the EuropeanAtomic Energy Community.Foreign Affairs 1. The Foreign Secretary said that since 22nd February the berlin Russians had ceased to harass Western aircraft in the air corridors(Previous into West Berlin. The United States Ambassador in Moscow was reference: continuing his conversations with the Soviet Foreign Minister; and,C.C. (62) 14th while no practical progress was being made, the Russians were conclusions, showing no signs of impatience. It now looked as though these minute 1) conversations would be drawn out until the Foreign Ministers met atthe Disarmament Conference in March.
Education(previous reference:C.C. (62) 8thConclusions,Minute 5)BurnhamCommitteefT3. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Minister ofEducation (C. (62) 34) covering a memorandum on the revision of themachinery for the negotiation of teachers&apos; remuneration.The Minister of Education recalled that it had been proposed tointroduce legislation in the current session of Parliament to enable him to prescribe new scales of remuneration for teachers. Such a power was required to enable him to deal with disagreements betweenthe local authority side and the teachers&apos; side of the burnham committee and also with agreed proposals which he could not regard as appropriate to the requirements of the schools or as consistent with the Government^ incomes policy. It had, however, become evident that early legislation for this purpose would be opposed by both the teachers and the local authorities, since the latter had promised to support the teachers if a Bill was introduced before theGovernments long-term policy on incomes had been more fullyworked out. In present circumstances there would also be pressure to provide for arbitration; and, since a concession on this point would be likely to endanger the Governments incomes policy, hethought there would be advantage in postponing the introduction ofthis legislation until the following session. He felt no doubt that inthe coming summer deadlock would be reached between the two sides of the Burnham Committee, and at that stage the local authorities would be less inclined to support a demand for arbitration and theprospects for the Bill would be much improved. In the following session the controversy about the Governments incomes policy wouldhave died down and the influence of moderate opinion among the teachers would probably have grown. If the Cabinet accepted his view he would make it clear to both sides of the Committee that ifproposals were submitted in 1962 which he judged to be contrary tothe national interest they would be rejected.In discussion it was generally agreed that a further increase in pay for teachers during the present year should be avoided and that legislation on the lines which had been intended must be enactedfairly soon. Whether the legislation should be introduced in thecurrent session depended to some extent on whether relations withthe teachers and the climate of Parliamentary opinion might beexpected to deteriorate when the teachers realised that negotiationsthis year would be most unlikely to result in any increases in pay.On balance, it seemed better to take the risk of deterioration in relations and to defer the legislation. There was at least a possibility that, in the event of a deadlock during the summer, moderate opinion among the teachers would bring a majority of them to the view thatthey ought not oppose the proposed legislation.In further discussion the following points were made:(a) It might be possible to secure the Ministers main objectives,for this year at any rate, by arranging with the Burnham Committeethat before submitting formal recommendations they should discuss their ideas informally with the Minister in advance. It would,however, be unwise to propose such a procedure, since it would encourage expectations of some concession being made and of similar arrangements being permitted to continue in future years.(b) Whatever course was taken in England and Wales therewould be difficulties in Scotland, where argument was continuing on certain aspects of the last settlement on teachers&apos; pay. The Scottishprocedure already included provision for arbitration, and there was some possibility that if an abitration award were made it would haveto be rejected. But if there were a deadlock on teachers&apos; pay inEngland and Wales the position of the Government in resistingincreases in Scotland would be strengthened.The Cabinet Agreed that legislation to revise the machinery for settlementof teachers&apos; remuneration should not be introduced in thecurrent session of Parliament.1
secret. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theColonial Secretary (C. (62) 40) on the extent of the financial assistance which might be offered to the Uganda Government.The Colonial Secretary said that Uganda was due to achieveinternal self-government on 1st March and to become independent inOctober. Discussions had been proceeding in London withrepresentatives of the Uganda Government on the payments to bemade by the United Kingdom Government towards the cost ofcompensating expatriate officers and towards further economic development in Uganda, and if these could not be brought to asatisfactory conclusion the date for the introduction of internal self-government would have to be deferred. It would be particularly unfortunate if postponement were caused either wholly or partly bydifficulties in settling the amount of the United Kingdom contribution towards compensation for officials. The discussions had been basedon proposals approved by the Treasury which in the case ofcompensation fell some  700,000 short, and in the case of developmentaid just under  2 million short, of what he himself had thought wouldbe a reasonable amount. On the two heads taken together, theamount required, in his judgment, to make a settlement probablewas  14.5 million and the offers so far made totalled  11.9 million.He believed that on a long view it would be to the advantage of theGovernment, both politically and financially, to improve upon theseoffers, which would be difficult to defend in the light of the more generous arrangements recently made for Tanganyika.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that in his view the Tanganyika settlement had been unduly generous and would prove to be an embarrasing precedent unless its effect could be corrected bya more economical settlement for Uganda. The development schemefor Uganda which had been prepared by the World Bank wasattractive but it would cost more than Uganda or the UnitedKingdom could afford in present circumstances. The developmentaid so far offered would enable more development to be undertakenthan had been carried out in recent years and, although it mightbe reasonable to improve the Governments offer under thecompensation head, an improvement in the offer of development aidwould be inconsistent with the Governments stated aim of containinggrowth in public expenditure at home and overseas.In discussion the following points were made:(a) It would not be practicable to settle the compensationquestion forthwith and leave development aid to be settled later.There might, however, be something to be gained in comparablenegotiations with other territories if the Government accepted full responsibility for compensation from the outset. This would enabledevelopment aid to be considered on its merits and in a lessemotional atmosphere.(b) Although the amount of Government expenditure overseaswas running ahead of the limit of  180 million which the Governmenthad approved, the amount attributable to Uganda would be 4 million less over the next two years than under the colonial secretary&apos;s earlier proposals.(c) Colonial territories generally paid close attention to theamounts of aid given on independence and it was difficult to contestUganda&apos;s claim to treatment not less favourable than that given to the neighbouring territory of Tanganyika. It was important, however,that in other cases yet to arise the Cabinet should have in advance a clear statement of the scale of commitments to be expected; for it seemed clear that in relation to economic conditions in the UnitedKingdom the financial assistance which was being provided overseaswas over-generous.
Summing up the discussion the Prime Minister said that, whilethe cost of relinquishing Colonial rule was proving to be high, it was probably better to accept definite, if large, financial commitments onindependence than to risk the indefinite and larger expenditure involved in prolonging Colonial rule against a risk of collapse of lawand order. There seemed to be no acceptable means of varying the offers already made to the Uganda Government which would fall far short of the total proposed by the Colonial Secretary. But it wouldbe intolerable if a further offer did not produce a settlement and hesuggested that, in continuing negotiations later that day, the UnitedKingdom representatives should indicate that if this offer were not accepted forthwith it would be withdrawn.The Cabinet Agreed that the representatives of the Uganda Governmentshould be offered the financial settlement proposed by theColonial Secretary in C. (62) 40 on the basis that if it werenot accepted forthwith it would be withdrawn.5. The Cabinet resumed their discussion of the northern rhodesia Constitution. They had before them a further memorandum (C. (62) 42) by the Colonial Secretary.The Prime Minister said that the question remaining for decision was that of the Asian seat. The Governments main objective was tosecure the co-operation of the African Parties in working the newconstitution. The abolition of the numerical alternative was in itself a major concession to the Africans, and it was a matter of judgmentwhether it was necessary to give up the Asian seat as well in order to gain their support. On the other hand there could be no doubt aboutthe reactions of the Federal Prime Minister, Sir Roy Welensky; hewould represent the abolition of the Asian seat as a breach of our agreement with him, and this would add to the difficulties which theGovernment would face in negotiating with him about Nyasaland and the future of the Federation as a whole.In discussion the following points were made:(a) In favour of abolishing the Asian seat it could be argued that, since the Asians themselves no longer wanted it, its justificationhad disappeared. It would be represented that its only practicalpurpose was to reduce the size of the anti-federal vote. This couldnot be defended in Parliament. If it was believed and this was certainly the Governors belief -that the retention of the seat would jeopardise law and order in the territory, it was the Governmentsduty to abolish it; and no prior understanding or agreement with theFederal Government should be allowed to affect the decision.(b) In favour of retention it could be argued that if the Africanleaders wished to co-operate in working the constitution, the majorconcession of abolishing the numerical alternative should make it possible for them to do so. The abolition of the Asian seat would however necessarily entail the removal from the upper roll of the500 African voters who had been added on account of it. TheGovernment were already committed to the view that these men werefit to vote, and it would be hard to explain why they should beremoved from the roll at this stage. If the Africans were looking for reasons to justify a refusal to co-operate the removal of the 500 voterswould present them with a more powerful and more convincingargument than the retention of the Asian seat. Nor was it possibleto ignore the reactions of Sir Roy Welensky. Even though he was unlikely to accept without protest the other changes now proposed inthe Constitution, the abolition of the Asian seat would make itimpossible to avoid a serious clash with him; for the abolition of the asian seat as well as the numerical alternative would mean that both
of the points in dispute in the June proposals had been settled in a sense unfavourable to him and this would be likely to create difficulties for him with his own supporters.The Prime Minister outlined to the Cabinet the form of the statements which might be made in Parliament to explain and defendeither the abolition of the Asian seat or its retention; the statementsalso covered the abolition of the numerical alternative, the setting ofthe percentage qualification at the first hurdle at 10 per cent, and, by implication, a decision to leave the number of racially reserved seatsunaltered.After further discussion the Cabinet (1) Agreed that the Asian seat should be retained.(2) Agreed that candidates should be required to obtain 10 percent, of the votes cast by both races as a condition ofeligibility for election and that the numerical alternativeshould be abolished.(3) Agreed to leave the number of racially reserved seatsunchanged at four.(4) Authorised the Colonial Secretary to announce these decisions in the House of Commons on the following day.The Prime Minister said that in the light of the decisions now taken on the Northern Rhodesia Constitution the Cabinet would wishto consider the terms of the communication to be made to Sir roy welensky. He should be informed of the decisions on theConstitution itself in advance of any public statement; but it was evenmore important that it should be made plain to him that theGovernment were not in any way committed to the plans for thefuture of the Federation which he had outlined to the commonwealth secretary during the latter&apos;s visit to Salisbury.The Commonwealth Secretary circulated the draft of a letter toSir Roy Welensky setting out the Governments position. he explained that the purpose of the draft was threefold: first, to put iton record that the tentative discussions which he had held in salisbury about the future of the Federation had revealed differences of approach which would make it difficult for the two Governments toreach early agreement on mutually acceptable changes in the federal constitution; secondly, to explain that in view of this the UnitedKingdom Government had felt unable to defer decisions on theNorthern Rhodesia Constitution until agreement had been reached on the future of the Federation as a whole; and thirdly, to conveyadvance information about the changes in the Northern RhodesiaConstitution which the Government had decided to make.The Cabinet (5) Agreed that the decisions taken on the Northern RhodesiaConstitution should be notified to Sir Roy Welensky, inadvance of publication, in a letter on the lines of the draftsubmitted by the Commonwealth Secretary; and took note that the Prime Minister would settle the precise termsof the letter in consultation with the Foreign Secretary,the Commonwealth Secretary and the Colonial Secretary.

</content>
</cab>
