<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/36/0 images: 167-171</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1962C.C. (62) Copy No.23rd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1, onThursday, 22nd March, 1962, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster-GeneralThe Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of aviation the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P.,&quot; Secretary  of State for  the colonies dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Lord Mills, minister without portfolio the Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P., President of the Board of trade the following were also present:The Right Hon. Lord Carrington,First Lord of the Admiralty (Item 3)The Right Hon. The Earl of Dundef,Minister of State for Foreign Affairs(Items 1-3)The Right Hon. Julian Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for Air (Item 3)The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat :
minute no.1234ParliamentDisarmamentNuclear TestsAircraft IndustryIncomes Policy ..ContentsSubjectPage3344
SECRET 3C.C. 23 (62)Parliament 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons during the following week.Disarmament(previous reference:C.C. (62) 22ndConclusions,Minute 1)Nuclear Tests2. The Prime Minister said that the discussions in theDisarmament Conference at Geneva were being conducted withrealism. The participation of the neutral countries seemed, on thewhole, to be useful; for they were helping to probe the Soviet position.On the other hand, there seemed to be little prospect of practicalprogress, especially in relation to the cessation of nuclear tests. Therepresentatives of the Soviet Government had shown themselvesunwilling to accept any proposals for international verification ofsuspicious incidents, and were taking the line that no national of any foreign country could ever be allowed to enter Soviet territory for thispurpose. If this proved to be the final Soviet position on verification,there was no prospect of concluding an international agreement forthe cessation of nuclear tests. In that event it would be important that the Soviet Government should be plainly seen to be responsiblefor the breakdown of these negotiations and that Mr. Khrushchevshould be personally identified with the Soviet decision. Thisquestion was likely to come to a head at a plenary meeting of theConference on 23rd or 26th March; and, if there were then no changein the Soviet position, it would probably be expedient that somedirect approach should be made to Mr. Khrushchev. It was forconsideration whether this should take the form of a joint message from President Kennedy and himself and, if so, whether this shouldtake the form of a final appeal for Soviet co-operation or whetherit should accept the failure of the negotiations and be designed solely to fix the responsibility on the Soviet Government. Alternatively,separate messages might be sent. President Kennedy might evenprefer that the United Kingdom Government should take some independent initiative. These alternative possibilities were nowbeing canvassed with President Kennedy.In discussion it was recalled that in his message toMr. Khrushchev the Prime Minister had envisaged that a meeting of heads of Governments might be held with a view to resolving a deadlock in the Disarmament Conference. It was the general viewof the Cabinet that, if it became clear that the Soviet government intended to maintain a wholly intransigent attitude towardsinternational verification, no progress was likely to be made by ameeting of Heads of Governments on disarmament. In those circumstances it might be preferable to reserve the possibility of sucha meeting for a discussion on Berlin, on which there might be moreroom for negotiation.It was further suggested that, if no progress could be made towards a nuclear tests agreement, it might be useful for presentationalpurposes to revive the earlier Anglo-American offer to conclude anagreement confined to tests in the atmosphere. It was generally feltthat in present circumstances the United States Government wouldbe unwilling to repeat that offer. In that event, it might at least be valuable to recall, in any final statement on the breakdown of thenegotiations, that the offer had been made at an earlier stage.The Cabinet Took note of the Prime Minister^ statement and of thepoints raised in their discussion.
1661/3. The Cabinet had under consideration memoranda by theMinister of Aviation (C. (62) 55) and the Chief Secretary, Treasury(C. (62) 56) on the letting of a contract to the British aircraft corporation for a project study on variable geometry aircraft.The Minister of Aviation said that research had been going on for a number of years into the principle of &quot; variable geometry &quot;,which was the name given in the aircraft industry to the possibilityof constructing an aircraft whose wing-angle could be varied in flight.This development seemed to offer the best prospects of improving the performance of very high speed aircraft. The stage had been reached at which it would normally be thought right to proceed with a projectstudy; and, following official discussions, he was now ready to awarda contract for this study to the British Aircraft Corporation at a costof some  500,000, spread over 18 months. Provision had been madefor the appropriate proportion of this expenditure in departmentalestimates for 1962-63. If he could announce this intention in thecourse of the debate that afternoon on the future of the aircraft industry, this would provide evidence of the Governments intentionto give effective support to the industry.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that the public announcementof a project study on a variable geometry aircraft would be likely to lead to increasing pressure on the Government in Parliament and bythe public to proceed with the development and manufacture of aparticular military aircraft. Normally, the discussion of a newgeneration of Service aircraft and of the difficult problem of timingits introduction would proceed over a period of months; and he doubted whether it would be right to pre-judge so important adecision for the sake of countering criticism in the course of a debate in Parliament.The First Lord of the Admiralty and the Secretary of State forAir confirmed the Services&apos; requirement for an aircraft of the variablegeometry type to replace both the Buccaneer and the T.S.R.-2 in the mid-1970s, and emphasised the advisability of proceeding as soon aspossible with a project study as the essential preliminary to further development.In discussion it was pointed out that the Gibb-ZuckermanReport, which the Government had endorsed, recommended the more widespread use of project studies before large sums of money were committed to the development of particular items of military equipment. It would therefore be inconsistent to withhold sanction for a project study on the ground that this would inevitably commit the Government to further heavy expenditure.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that a project study contract for a variable geometryaircraft should be awarded to the British aircraft corporation.(2) Invited the Minister of Aviation, in consultation with theChief Secretary, Treasury, to prepare a statement to bemade in the course of that afternoon&apos;s debate explaining the limited effects of this decision.aircraft industry(previous references:C.C. (62) 13thConclusions,Minute 5 andC.C. (61) 57ihConclusions,Minute 2)incomes policy(previous reference:C.C. (62) 15thConclusions,Minute 2)4. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was concernedby the extent to which Press reports of current wage awards in industry were distorting their effect and presenting them asinconsistent with the Governments incomes policy. One recent example was a wage settlement by Imperial Chemical Industries,which had been represented as involving increases of between 3 and per cent., whereas it had in fact involved an overall increase of2-7 per cent, with special arrangements for bonus payments.
Cabinet Office, S.W.1,22nd March, 1962.Another example was the Massey-Ferguson settlement, which hadbeen represented as an increase of 5 per cent., whereas it was in facta two-year settlement allowing for increases of 2\ per cent, on1st April, 1962, and a further 2\ per cent, on 1st April, 1963. Theeffect of such misrepresentation was to increase the feeling,particularly among employees in the public sector, that the pay pausewas being unfairly applied to certain limited categories of employees and that private industry was ignoring the Governments policy.While it would be unprofitable to criticise wage settlements reached by particular firms, it would be right to make every effort to see thatcurrent industrial agreements were accurately reported and properlyunderstood. There was still a widespread lack of understanding ofthe purpose of the Governments policy and of the gravity of thefinancial situation with which it had been designed to deal.In discussion the following points were made:(a) The lack of balance in current reporting on the governments incomes policy was mainly due to the fact that the policy itself, andsettlements made in accordance with it, no longer had news-value.Statements about it which were included in Ministerial speeches wererarely reported.(b) There was some reason to think that the public understood the need for the policy, though they disliked its effects and resentedin particular the inequities resulting from its application.(c) Against this background it was desirable that every opportunity should be taken of re-stating and re-affirming theGovernments policy in circumstances which would be likely to attract attention in the Press. In practice occasions of this kind were most likely to arise when the Government had been the object ofpublic attack. Ministers should be prepared to reply to such attacks and to take avantage of the resulting publicity at very short notice.(d) It would become increasingly necessary to emphasise, notonly the nature and purpose of this policy, but the positive benefits which were beginning to flow from it in terms, e.g., of lower interest charges and improvement in the balance of payments and in thestrength of sterling.After further discussion the Cabinet (1) Invited the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster to consider what steps could be taken to secure a fairer presentationin the national Press of current wage settlements suchas those in Imperial Chemical Industries andMassey-Ferguson.(2) Agreed that continued effort should be made to obtain betterpublicity for the Governments incomes policy and thatincreasing emphasis should be laid on the benefits whichit would bring to the national economy.

</content>
</cab>
