<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/36/0 images: 196-205</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  April 1962CC. (62) Copy No.  428th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 17th April, 1962, at II a.m.Present:The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P., Secretary of State for the Home Department(in the Chair)The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Lord Mills, minister without portfolio the Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations the Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of aviation the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P., President of the Board of trade the following were also present:The Right Hon. Lord Carrington,First Lord of the Admiralty (Item 5)The Right Hon. Julian Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for Air (Items 5-6)The Right Hon.The Right Hon. John Profumo, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Item 5)The Right Hon. J. Enoch Powell,M.P., Minister of Health (Item 5)Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat:THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
contents minute no. subject      Foreign Affairs ...Nuclear TestsBerlinCongo Republic2      Europe   ...3      Parliament4      Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland5      Incomes Policy ...Pay of Doctors and Dentists in the Armed Forces6      Portugal...............Anglo-Portuguese Alliance7      Middle East     ...............Kuwait
ForeignAffairsNuclear Tests(previous reference:C.C. (62) 27thConclusions,Minute 1)Berlin(previous reference:C.C. (62) 26thConclusions,Minute 2)congo republic(previous reference:C.C. (62) 25thConclusions,Minute 4)1. The Cabinet were informed that at the Geneva Conferenceon Disarmament the representatives of eight neutral countries had submitted proposals for an international system of detecting nuclear tests which contained some provision for verification. This wouldnot, as it stood, be fully effective; for it provided for inspection only at the invitation of the Government of a country in which a doubtfulevent had taken place. It was not therefore likely to be acceptable to the United States Government; and there was some risk thatdetailed discussion of it might reveal the existing differences of view between British and United States scientists on the extent to which on-site inspection would be required for purposes of verification.In discussion the point was made that, if this proposal had to be rejected, there would be tactical advantages in allowing the SovietGovernment to assume the responsibility for its rejection.The Cabinet were informed that the United States Secretary ofState, Mr. Rusk, had on the previous day resumed his discussions on berlin with the Soviet Ambassador in Washington. In view howeverof the attitude of the French and German Governments, he had not felt able to outline in this talk the new proposals which he hadformulated. He now intended to pursue these with foreign ministers at the forthcoming meeting of the North Atlantic Councilin Athens.The Cabinet were informed that the United Nationsrepresentative in Leopoldville had put forward for considerationcompromise proposals for an agreement between the Governmentof Katanga and the Central Congo Government. These proposals were now being considered by the Prime Ministers of the twoGovernments.Eorope(previous reference:C.C. (62) 17thConclusions,Minute 22. The Lord Privy Seal said that in his speech to the ministerial council of the Western European Union (W.E.U.) on 10th April hehad taken the opportunity of outlining the attitude which the UnitedKingdom Government would take towards political co-operation inEurope if they entered the European Economic Community. this statement of policy had been approved by the Common MarketNegotiations Committee, and the text had been circulated to membersof the Cabinet. The statement had been well received by the W.E.U.Council, and the Governments of the Six were now examining how the United Kingdom could best be associated with their furtherconsideration of the problem of political co-operation.The Cabinet considered whether it would be useful at this stage of the negotiations if, in Ministerial speeches, more emphasis were laid on the advantages which the United Kingdom would derive from membership of the Community. There was some risk that,unless Ministers began to take the initiative on this, public opinion would be unduly influenced by the arguments which continued to be deployed on the other side. There was general agreement that itwould be useful if Ministers could take a more definite line on thisquestion in their speeches over the coming months.The Cabinet-Invited the Lord Privy Seal to arrange for guidance to be circulated to Ministers on the points relating to theCommon Market negotiations which could usefully be emphasised in Ministerial speeches in the coming months.
Federationof: RhodesiaandNyasaland(previous reference:C.C. (62) 26thConclusions,Minute 3)4. The Home Secretary said that the Prime Minister of theFederation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, Sir Roy Welensky, had atfirst reacted favourably to the suggestion, approved by the cabinet at their meeting on 5th April, that a small mission of special advisers should consider with the Government of Nyasaland the consequences which would flow from Nyasaland&apos;s secession from the federation and the possibility of other forms of association, and should consider with the four Governments in the Federation the parallel questionof the future relations of Northern and Southern Rhodesia withNyasaland and with each other. The Federal Government had,however, felt that it would be inappropriate that any announcement should be made about the mission until the Federal elections were concluded on 27th April. The Home Secretary said that he had itin mind to make a statement in the House of Commons on 8th Mayin which he would explain the nature of the new initiative whichwas being taken by the United Kingdom Government in central africa. He also proposed to make a short visit to the Federationlater in May.The situation in Nyasaland gave much cause for uneasiness, not least because the economy of the country was so heavily dependenton assistance from the Federation and from the United Kingdom.But it was encouraging, in view of the known attitude of theMalawi Congress Party, that its leader, Dr. Banda, had accepted theplan for the inquiry and had nominated a representative to assist inthe work of the mission. Moreover, Dr. Banda had, for the timebeing at least, abandoned his intention of coming to this country andseemed disposed to acquiesce in deferment of a settlement on thesecession of Nyasaland until the inquiry had been completed. Astatement in the House of Commons on 8th May would be welcomed by Dr. Banda, and it was to be hoped that by that time further progress would have been made with arrangements for those aspectsof the inquiry which directly affected Northern Rhodesia.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Home Secretary.incomes policy(previous reference:C.C. (62) 24thConclusions,Minute 4)Pay of doctors and Dentistsin the ArmedForces5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Defence (C. (62) 64) proposing increased rates of pay for Service doctors and dentists. These rates had been framed onthe basis of a 16 per cent, lead over the emoluments of comparableposts in the National Health Service and were estimated to cost an extra  575,000 in the financial year 1962-63.The Minister of Defence said that the British Medical association had reaffirmed their advice that the Services would not be able to recruit doctors and dentists in anything like the numbers requiredunless they could offer rates of pay which provided a substantiallead over salaries in the National Health Service. Their ownestimate of the lead required had been set at 30 per cent.; by settingit as low as the 16 per cent, on which his present proposals had been based he was taking a calculated risk. The urgency of the recruitingsituation could not be over-emphasised; the Army had recruited onlysix doctors last year against a requirement of 125 by 1963. unless there was a very substantial improvement it would be necessary toconsider bringing married families home from overseas. He hadbeen asked to consider whether the total cost of the increases couldParliament 3.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the week following the end of the easter recess.
Parliament 3.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the week following the end of the easter recess.Federation01 RhodesiaandNyasaland(previous reference:CC. (62) 26thConclusions,Minute 3)4. The Home Secretary said that the Prime Minister of theFederation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, Sir Roy Welensky, had atfirst reacted favourably to the suggestion, approved by the cabinet at their meeting on 5th April, that a small mission of special advisers should consider with the Government of Nyasaland the consequences which would flow from Nyasaland&apos;s secession from the federation and the possibility of other forms of association, and should consider with the four Governments in the Federation the parallel questionof the future relations of Northern and Southern Rhodesia withNyasaland and with each other. The Federal Government had,however, felt that it would be inappropriate that any announcement should be made about the mission until the Federal elections were concluded on 27th April. The Home Secretary said that he had itin mind to make a statement in the House of Commons on 8th Mayin which he would explain the nature of the new initiative whichwas being taken by the United Kingdom Government in central africa. He also proposed to make a short visit to the Federationlater in May.The situation in Nyasaland gave much cause for uneasiness, not least because the economy of the country was so heavily dependenton assistance from the Federation and from the United Kingdom.But it was encouraging, in view of the known attitude of theMalawi Congress Party, that its leader, Dr. Banda, had accepted theplan for the inquiry and had nominated a representative to assist inthe work of the mission. Moreover, Dr. Banda had, for the timebeing at least, abandoned his intention of coming to this country andseemed disposed to acquiesce in deferment of a settlement on thesecession of Nyasaland until the inquiry had been completed. Astatement in the House of Commons on 8th May would be welcomed by Dr. Banda, and it was to be hoped that by that time further progress would have been made with arrangements for those aspectsof the inquiry which directly affected Northern Rhodesia.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Home Secretary.incomes 5.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by thePolicy Minister of Defence (C. (62) 64) proposing increased rates of pay(Previous        for Service doctors and dentists.  These rates had been framed on reference:      the basis of a 16 per cent, lead over the emoluments of comparableCC. (62) 24th   posts in the National Health Service and were estimated to cost an conclusions,    extra  575,000 in the financial year 1962-63.Minute 4)Pay of Doctors ^ ne Minister of Defence said that the British Medical association and Dentists had reaffirmed their advice that the Services would not be able toin the Armed recruit doctors and dentists in anything like the numbers requiredForces unless they could offer rates of pay which provided a substantiallead over salaries in the National Health Service. Their ownestimate of the lead required had been set at 30 per cent.; by settingit as low as the 16 per cent, on which his present proposals had been based he was taking a calculated risk. The urgency of the recruitingsituation could not be over-emphasised; the Army had recruited onlysix doctors last year against a requirement of 125 by 1963. unless there was a very substantial improvement it would be necessary toconsider bringing married families home from overseas. He hadbeen asked to consider whether the total cost of the increases could
Parliament 3.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the week following the end of the easter recess.Federationof RhodesiaandNyasaland(previous reference:C.C. (62) 26thConclusions,Minute 3)4. The Home Secretary said that the Prime Minister of theFederation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, Sir Roy Welensky, had atfirst reacted favourably to the suggestion, approved by the cabinet at their meeting on 5th April, that a small mission of special advisers should consider with the Government of Nyasaland the consequences which would flow from Nyasaland&apos;s secession from the federation and the possibility of other forms of association, and should consider with the four Governments in the Federation the parallel questionof the future relations of Northern and Southern Rhodesia withNyasaland and with each other. The Federal Government had,however, felt that it would be inappropriate that any announcement should be made about the mission until the Federal elections were concluded on 27th April. The Home Secretary said that he had itin mind to make a statement in the House of Commons on 8th Mayin which he would explain the nature of the new initiative whichwas being taken by the United Kingdom Government in central africa. He also proposed to make a short visit to the Federationlater in May.The situation in Nyasaland gave much cause for uneasiness, not least because the economy of the country was so heavily dependenton assistance from the Federation and from the United Kingdom.But it was encouraging, in view of the known attitude of theMalawi Congress Party, that its leader, Dr. Banda, had accepted theplan for the inquiry and had nominated a representative to assist inthe work of the mission. Moreover, Dr. Banda had, for the timebeing at least, abandoned his intention of coming to this country andseemed disposed to acquiesce in deferment of a settlement on thesecession of Nyasaland until the inquiry had been completed. Astatement in the House of Commons on 8th May would be welcomed by Dr. Banda, and it was to be hoped that by that time further progress would have been made with arrangements for those aspectsof the inquiry which directly affected Northern Rhodesia.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Home Secretary.incomes policy(previous reference:C.C. (62) 24thConclusions,Minute 4)Pay of doctors and Dentistsin the ArmedForces5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Defence (C. (62) 64) proposing increased rates of pay for Service doctors and dentists, rates had been framed onthe basis of a 16 per cent, lead over the emoluments of comparableposts in the National Health Service and were estimated to cost an extra  575,000 in the financial year 1962-63.The Minister of Defence said that the British Medical association had reaffirmed their advice that the Services would not be able to recruit doctors and dentists in anything like the numbers requiredunless they could offer rates of pay which provided a substantiallead over salaries in the National Health Service. Their ownestimate of the lead required had been set at 30 per cent.; by settingit as low as the 16 per cent, on which his present proposals had been based he was taking a calculated risk. The urgency of the recruitingsituation could not be over-emphasised; the Army had recruited onlysix doctors last year against a requirement of 125 by 1963. unless there was a very substantial improvement it would be necessary toconsider bringing married families home from overseas. He hadbeen asked to consider whether the total cost of the increases could
not be kept within a figure of  500,000, but this had provedimpracticable; it was necessary to improve substantially the pay ofthe younger doctors who were needed to meet active Serviceconditions but could not in many cases be offered a full career. a figure of  500,000 would have meant that, after allowing for the increases for the younger doctors, there would have been little or nothing left to provide increases for the more senior ranks. Evenon a basis of  575,000 the increases for senior ranks would be modest.This sum could be reasonably held to be available to the Services asthe result of the recent biennial pay review. It represented thedifference between the award actually made and the cost of theaward which would have been necessary if the increases justified bystatistical calculations of movements in outside earnings over thetwo-year period had been paid in full.The Minister of Defence said that the British Medical association had assured him that any award now made to Service doctors wouldnot be used as an argument to justify further increases for civiliandoctors whose salaries would shortly be coming under review. Ifthe Cabinet accepted his proposals it was intended that they shouldbe announced together with other changes and improvements in theorganisation of the Services Medical Corps by the Secretary of Statefor War when he met leading representatives of the medical profession later in the day. He would himself propose to make ashort statement in Parliament on 18th April.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that he was prepared toaccept this settlement as the best compromise solution to anadmittedly difficult problem. He had been satisfied onre-examination that a figure of  575,000 could reasonably be held tobe available as the result of the recent Service pay settlement. the presentation of the increases for Service doctors would however need careful thought and he would wish to be consulted about the termsof the statements to be made by the Secretary of State for War andthe Minister of Defence.In discussion the following points were made:(a) The main danger of so substantial an increase for certain categories of Service doctor was that it would be used as a precedent for similar increases elsewhere. It was likely to have a particularly unfortunate reaction on the position of the nurses, for whose claimthere was a wide measure of public support. It was, therefore, ofgreat importance to emphasise the fact that the increases for Servicedoctors had been calculated on the basis of a special supplement tothe normal National Health Service salaries; it should not, however,be presented as a percentage lead over the National Health Service,still less as a percentage increase over the present rates of pay in theServices.(b) Stress should also be laid on the need to deal with thesituation created by the ending of National Service. In the samecontext, it could be emphasised that Service pay had traditionallybeen regarded as posing special problems of its own, which set itapart from normal civilian criteria and demanded quite differentsolutions. There had been no evidence that the recent pay increases for the Services had had any repercussions on outstanding civilianwage claims; indeed, the main weight of criticism had been that theGovernment had failed to meet their obligations to the Services,rather than that they had been over-generous.(c) Pay was only one aspect of the problem of recruiting Servicedoctors. Radical improvements were being made in other aspectsof the Service doctor&apos;s career; greater opportunities would beprovided for obtaining a full range of clinical experience byorganising doctors on an area, rather than a unit, basis and theprovision of suitable quarters would be guaranteed.  Many of these
changes had already been announced, but they would bere-emphasised.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the rates of pay of Service doctors and dentistsshould be increased on the basis proposed by the Ministerof Defence.(2) Invited the Minister of Defence to agree with the chief secretary, Treasury, the terms in which these increases should be announced by the Secretary of State for Warand by himself.PortugalAnglo-PortugueseAlliance(previous reference:CC. (62) 24thConclusions,Minute 5)6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the foreign secretary (C. (62) 60) on the commitments of the United kingdom to assist in the defence of the Portuguese colonies.The Lord Privy Seal said that the Government were committed by several of the treaties comprising the Anglo-Portuguese Allianceto defend the Portuguese colonies. For both military and political reasons this commitment could no longer be honoured; and at thetime of the Indian attack on Goa this had been a source of acuteembarrassment. In view of the difference in the Colonial policies ofthe two countries, it was hardly conceivable that the obligationcould be honoured unless issues were at stake which involved notmerely the Anglo-Portuguese association but the partnership of thetwo countries in the North Atlantic Alliance. Anglo-Portugueserelations would remain unsatisfactory so long as the Portuguesebelieved that they could expect from us assistance which, in fact, wewere not in a position to give. The treaties contained, however, no provision for termination and it did not seem probable that thePrime Minister of Portugal would himself denounce them. In any discussions which might take place with the Portuguese it would benecessary to keep it in mind that in the event of trouble in aPortuguese territory we were as likely to be called upon to providetransit facilities as direct military aid, and that refusal of such facilities would be just as difficult and embarrassing. On the otherhand, we were ourselves dependent on transit facilities in variousPortuguese territories, particularly the Cape Verde Islands.In the light of these considerations it would be impolitic to propose a complete renegotiation of the alliance. But it would bepossible to take the opportunity of the forthcoming meeting of theNorth Atlantic Council in Athens to discuss informally with thePortuguese Foreign Minister how best to remove the embarrasment in current relations.In discussion the following points were raised:(a) The present regime in Portugal might not survive for longand any attempt to alter the basis of the relationship now would giverise to complex problems and arouse strong feelings on the part ofBritish residents in Portugal. In these circumstances it might be expedient to defer action for a time. On the other hand, there might at any time be occasion for the Portuguese to invoke our aid in some part of the world where our obligations of the Commonwealth couldnot, as in the case of Goa, be regarded as of overriding importance;and we might ourselves at short notice have need of facilities in portuguese territories which, in the absence of some better understanding, could be withheld to our disadvantage. If any suchoccasion arose, it would be difficult to explain why in the intervalafter the attack on Goa nothing had been done to put our relationswith Portugal on a more realistic basis. The suggested discussions in Athens would not be in the nature of negotiations: if there wereto be any negotiations they would have to be preceded by carefuldiplomatic preparation in Lisbon.
MiddleEastKuwait(previous reference:C.C. (61) 53rdConclusions,Minute 5)7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof Defence (C. (62) 63) proposing the delegation of authority to theCommander-in-Chief, Middle East, under certain stated conditions,to carry out attacks on Iraqi airfields in the Basra /Shaiba area inorder to ensure a favourable air situation over Kuwait in the early stages of an Iraqi aggression.The Minister of Defence said that plans for rapid reinforcement of Kuwait in an emergency depended on the use of airborne troops.These troops could not be landed without unacceptable risk unless we first secured a favourable air situation over Kuwait itself. Withthe introduction of modern types of Russian fighter into service withthe Iraqi Air Force, air superiority could not be guaranteed withoutbombing the airfields in the Basra/Shaiba area from which the Iraqifighter aircraft would operate. In the normal course, theCommander-in-Chief would request specific authority from Londonbefore any operations of this kind were undertaken. There were,however, periods of the year when communications with Londonwere liable to interruption; and, in order to provide for the possibility that an Iraqi aggression might occur at a time when communicationwith London was impossible, he proposed that the Commander-in-Chief should be authorised to bomb Iraqi airfields on his own responsibility provided that he had received a formal request forassistance from the Amir of Kuwait, that the Political Resident,Persian Gulf, had agreed to the action proposed, and that theCommander-in-Chief had tried but failed to establish communicationwith London.In discussion the following points were made:(a) In view of the United Nations interest in Kuwait and thepresence there of representative Arab military forces, it would benecessary to establish conclusively that a serious Iraqi aggression had occurred before taking counter action against the Iraqi Air Force.Every attempt would be made to argue after the event that british forces had committed the initial act of aggression and hadmisinterpreted Iraqi movements or maneouvres.  For this reason itC.C. 28 (62)(b) If negotiations should take place, it might be desirable thatthey should take the form of substituting, for the existing alliance,a more specific series of reciprocal agreements for staging andover-flying. It seemed unlikely that any such arrangements could include promises on our part to secure the use of El Adem to thePortuguese, but it might be possible to consider the use of ascension island. Staging facilities for the Royal Air Force at Sal in the cape Verde Islands were essential and we should try to ensure thatthey could be available at short notice.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary, in consultation with theSecretary of State for Air, to make an assessment of thestaging and over-dying requirements of the Royal AirForce in Portuguese territories and of the extent to whichsimilar facilities could be made available to Portugal inBritish territories.(2) Authorised the Foreign Secretary to raise informally withthe Portuguese Foreign Minister at the forthcoming meeting of the North Atlantic Council the possibility ofsecuring some improvement in Anglo-Portugueserelations.
was desirable that, within the limits set by operational necessity, asmuch time as possible should be left for an Iraqi attack to develop and to make its nature manifest.(b) The directive to the Commander-in-Chief, Middle East,should make it clear that, before exercising the authority delegated to him under these proposals, he should have made every attemptto establish communication with London. It should also be made clear that the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, could not be expectedto assume any responsibility for advising on specific militaryoperations; he could not do more than give his agreement to the taking of military action as such in order to meet a specific request from the Amir for assistance.(c) It was important that British intervention, once it had beendecided upon, should be effective. The availability and the readiness of our forces to deal with an Iraqi attack on Kuwait should be kept under close review.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that authority should be delegated to theCommander-in-Chief, Middle East, to attack Iraqiairfields in the Basra /Shaiba area provided that the amir of Kuwait had asked for assistance, that thePolitical Resident, Persian Gulf, had given his agreement and that it had proved impossible to establishcommunication with London.(2) Invited the Minister of Defence, in consultation with theLord Privy Seal, to revise the directive to theCommander-in-Chief accordingly, taking account of theviews expressed in the Cabinets discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,17th April, 1962.

</content>
</cab>
