<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/36/0 images: 258-264</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1962C.C. (62) Copy No.     4237th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1,on Monday, 28th May, 1962, at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Lord Mills, minister without portfolio the Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster General.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Secretary of State for the colonies dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P., President of the Board of trade the following were also present:The Right Hon. J. Enoch Powell,   The Right Hon. Richard Wood, M.P.,M.P., Minister of Health Minister of power the Right Hon.  Reginald Bevins,   The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Postmaster-General M.P.,     Parliamentary     Secretary,treasury secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman brook mr. A. L. M. gary mr. J. H. waddell this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JEST YS GOVERNMENT
ContentsSubjectFederation of Rhodesia and NyasalandIncomes Policy............
CC. 37 (62)Federationof RhodesiaandNyasaland(previous reference:CC. (62) 32ndConclusions,Minute 8)1. The Cabinet welcomed the Home Secretary on his return from his visit to the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland andcongratulated him on the success of his mission.The Home Secretary said that the Government of the Federationwere now more ready to look towards the future, and there seemedto be some possibility of working towards a settlement. He wouldbe glad to make a report on his visit at a later meeting of the Cabinet.incomes *2.   The Prime Minister said that in the light of the earlierPolicy discussions in the Cabinet and the Economic Policy Committee he(Previous        had formulated proposals for presenting an incomes policy in the reference:      wider framework of a plan for economic growth.   In the lastCC (62) 36th   10 years the country had made steady progress; the general standardConclusions)    of living was high and the economy strong; the emergency measures taken in July 1961 had averted what might have developed into aserious crisis in the balance of payments and had been amplyjustified by events.   But those measures had been negative in character; and it was now necessary to bring forward a new policy with a more positive content and a promise of continued and steady progress.The four objectives of economic policy were full employment,stable prices, a strong pound and a good rate of growth. It was arguable whether all were fully attainable in a free society. the choice for the Government was whether one of these objectivesshould be sacrificed in order to secure the others, or whether theyshould continue to try to achieve as much as possible of all four bya judicious mixture of controls and exhortation. A fully controlledeconomy was not practicable in a free society as had been provedby the experience of the Labour Government after the war. Thevarious methods of controlling wages in the private sector whichhad been mentioned in recent discussions, e.g., the manipulation of tariffs, selective taxation and the use of a pay-roll tax, were all opento decisive objections: they were complicated and unfair, they would tend to penalise the growing and efficient industries, they would belikely to lead to increased prices in the home market industries, andthey would probably not be effective even for the limited purpose for which they had been designed. And if controls could not beapplied to wages in the private sector, it would not be possible tocontinue them indefinitely in the public sector in their present form.The inequities for teachers, nurses, probation officers and civilservants would progressively be seen to be too great. For the timebeing, however, both in these sectors and in the nationalised industries it would be necessary to continue with a policy of restraint, until it became possible to replace the present policy bysomething which would remove the grosser inequities and command a greater measure of support.If it were accepted that compulsion could not be used as the continuing instrument of a long-term policy, either in the public orin the private sector, the Government had three alternatives beforethem. The first would be to abandon the idea of an incomes policyand accept a return to the economic anarchism of earlier years. Thesecond would be to abandon economic growth as one of the objects of economic policy and to deflate the economy to the extent necessaryto secure stable prices and a strong pound. The third would be totransform the present incomes policy into a much broader policy
covering every aspect of national life. Such a policy could be presented as the only effective and fair way of achieving the four aims of economic policy in a free society.It would not be difficult to find support in principle for the objectives of full employment, stable prices, a strong pound and agood rate of growth. Opposition would in practice arise from a small number of employers, who believed in a free-for-all economy or looked for personal gain in a policy of devaluation, and on a more serious and widespread scale from the trade unions who, while accepting thatthe objectives were sound in theory, would doubt whether they couldbe applied fairly in practice. This was the real problem to be overcome: it was by the possibility of convincing people of their essential fairness that any new proposals would stand or fall. If theworkers could not be persuaded that the proposals were fair, theywould fail: restraint would be abandoned, and wages and salarieswould move sharply up. Analysis had shown that the rise in pricessince 1956 had been entirely due to wage and salary increases, and.not to imports or to the level of profits.The elements of a new approach, which would have to be presented as a single coherent policy, might be grouped under thefollowing headings:(i) Status of the Manual workers real effort should be made to end the out-dated distinctionbetween the status of the manual and the &quot; white-collar &quot; worker.Day contracts should be abolished and replaced by weekly, and ifpossible by monthly, contracts. Redundancy arrangements shouldbe improved. Better arrangements should be made for re-training,for sick pay and &quot;for health and welfare generally. Responsibility forthese measures would rest partly on the employers and partly on theGovernment, whose powers might need to be increased by new legislation.(ii) The Middle ClassesThere was a growing feeling that the middle classes were beingsacrificed to the strength of the employers and of organised labour.This feeling must be corrected partly by the prospect of stabilitywhich a new and broader-based incomes policy would offer, partly by the achievement of steady prices, and partly by more specific measures of particular appeal to the middle-class employee such as lower long-term interest rates and the improvement of working conditions in offices and in shops.(iii) Special cases in a long-term policy room would have to be found for animprovement in the remuneration of special classes whose claims didnot rest on any increase in the volume of national production. Suchcases might arise either in the public sector or in the private sector.Means must be devised for dealing with these in such a way as to avoidconsequential demands elsewhere. The best means of commandingpublic confidence in such decisions was to clothe them with theauthority of an independent standing commission or tribunal.(iv) ProfitsNo policy on wages would command the support of the tradeunions unless the Government had pledged themselves to take actionto keep profits down to an acceptable level. The precise level would need consideration, but the first approach might be in terms of preserving a balance between increases in wages and increases inprofits. The Government must be prepared to take whatever fiscalmeasures might be necessary to maintain this position.
(vi) GrowthThe 4 per cent, target which the National Economic development council (N.E.D.C.) were studying had become accepted as a desirable and reasonable aim. The Government could not hope to gainwidespread support for a continuing policy of wage restraint if it werepublicly to abandon the attempt to secure this higher rate of growth.But growth could not be achieved without a comparable increase in demand, and the increase in demand would have to come first. Thebank rate and the level of the special deposits should be kept underreview. Government expenditure on schools, housing, slums and universities should also be reviewed and increased. It would probably not be possible to take all these steps at once, since for the time being a reasonable budget surplus would be needed. But Ministers shouldnot be inhibited by too nice a calculation of the economic effects of raising the level of demand and increasing Government expenditure.(vii) The PoorIt would be necessary to do something, as part of the new-approach, to improve the lot of the old and the poor. An increasein National Assistance scales was already under consideration;pensions increases should be pressed forward, including service pensions, and their might be other possibilities now under study whichcould be accelerated.Summing up, the Prime Minister said that, if the Cabinet acceptedthe broad sweep of the ideas which he had put forward, it would benecessary for the Departments concerned to consider them in detail and to prepare a plan for presenting them to the public. It wouldalso be necessary to consider separately two points of particular difficulty; the position of the N.E.D.C., and the general formula to beapplied to wage and salary increases in 1963. On the first point itwould be necessary to emphasise to the N.E.D.C. that theGovernment, in adopting and pressing forward a new approach to national problems as a whole, were not supplanting the Council orsetting its work on one side. There was still a great field of workahead of it, not only in the study of the detailed mechanics of a high rate of growth, but in such matters as the rationalisation of industry,the relations between management and labour and the internalorganisation of labour, e.g., on restrictive practices.In conclusion the Prime Minister said that, after having consideredthe Government^ present position and the trend of earlier discussions in Cabinet, he felt that a new approach on the lines he had outlinedoffered the best alternative to a relapse into economic anarchy. Ofcourse there was the risk that the new approach might fail: it couldonly be a success if it fired the imagination of the mass of the people and were accepted as a national movement and not as a policy dictated by the Government. But there would be few people who couldcriticise the objective or the means. If the Government failed, theycould hardly be criticised for trying. They would be severely andjustly criticised if they allowed their present interim policy to collapseinto chaos.(v) prices the Government should go forward with measures designed tosafeguard the interests of the consumer and to encourage competition.These might include the abolition of re-sale price maintenance,consumer council and consumer protection measures, legislation onweights and measures, further action to deal with monopolies andpossibly, at a later stage, further tariff reductions.
In discussion of the Prime Ministers proposals the followingpoints were made:(a) The new approach offered not only the best but the onlychance of being able to move forward constructively from a defensiveand negative policy of restraint in wages and salary increases to a stage in which, while incomes were being kept in line with the growth in productivity, restraint would be exercised by general consent and aspart of a larger forward movement in the economy.(b) It would be essential to build up from the start the conceptthat the new approach was a coherent and self-consistent policycovering all aspects of the nation&apos;s life. Its impact would be seriouslyweakened if it were presented piecemeal. For this reason strictsecrecy should be maintained about particular elements in the new approach until a concerted plan of action had been drawn up. Inspite of this there were certain steps, notably in relation to specialdeposits and to some of the other monetary restrictions imposed inJuly 1961, which might have to be taken on merits at an earlier date.(c) Special thought should be given to the question of exports -not only because exports were essential to continued or acceleratedgrowth, but because there was an obvious danger that the cost of someof the measures which the Prime Minister had put forward might be reflected in export prices and might thereby weaken our competitive position.(d) It was suggested that the position of the agriculturalcommunity should also be studied, and that help for the farmers or anew long-term policy for the development of farming should form part of any comprehensive scheme. It should also be rememberedthat Britain&apos;s entry into the European Economic Community would produce an increase in food prices which would run counter to thegeneral policy of linking price stability with continuing restraint inclaiming increases of wages and salaries. This would need carefulpresentation, and it might affect the criteria to be adopted in 1963.(e) Much work was already in hand on consumer protection, onthe revision of contracts of service, on re-training schemes, and onredundancy agreements in industry. There might be difficulties in finding room for the necessary legislation in a parliamentary time-table which was already crowded, but it should be possible toproduce comprehensive and constructive proposals in the sense of the suggestions which the Prime Minister had put forward.(/) The benefits which the new policy would bring to manual workers would be manifest. But those for the middle classes wouldbe less obvious; and it might be necessary to strengthen and elaboratethe proposals which were particularly designed to appeal to thissection of the working population. It would also be necessary overthe whole wage and salary field to consider what measures might betaken (other than appeals to responsibility and common sense) to keepthe results of collective bargaining and of arbitration, both of whichwould continue, within the limits dictated by the general state of the economy.(g) Some Ministers expressed doubts about the degree to whichit might be possible to stimulate demand by greater government expenditure or easier credit terms without at the same time starting aninflationary movement which might in turn call for further repressivemeasures of the kind which had proved to be necessary in 1961. Sucha development would deal a damaging blow to the new policy.(h) To give it the best chance of success the new policy should be presented to the country against as stable an industrial backgroundas possible. It would lose much of its impact and have less chanceof acceptance if it were presented when major strikes, e.g., on therailways, were in progress or in prospect. In practice, this wouldmean that the new policy ought to be worked out and presented as
CC. 37 (62)soon as possible. The next round of negotiations for increases in railway wages was, on present information, unlikely to reach a criticalstage until after the summer holidays, but could probably not be delayed much beyond that.(/) It would be desirable that the development of the new policy should be under the direct control of the Prime Minister. He would need two small groups of senior Ministers to assist him one to dealwith the technical aspects of the proposals and the other to considerthe manner and method of their presentation to the country.The Cabinet (1) Endorsed the Prime Ministers view that the best chance of ensuring the continuance of the Governments incomes policy as a permanent and accepted part of the national economy would be to present it in the framework of a wider and comprehensive plan. Such a plan would take account of social as well as economic considerations.(2) Agreed that the elements of such a plan, on the lines set outby the Prime Minister, should now be studied in detail and took note that the Prime Minister would invite theMinisters concerned to assist him, as necessary, in this task.(3) Agreed that the new plan would have to be presented as acoherent whole and that to this end complete secrecywould have to be preserved during the preparatory stages.(4) Took note that the Prime Minister, in consultation with theMinisters concerned, would consider the method andmanner in which the new plan might best be presented tothe country as a whole.(5) In spite of the need to present the different elements of thenew plan simultaneously, authorised the Chancellor of theExchequer in his discretion to take such further measuresof relaxation in the monetary field as might be justified by the general economic situation.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,29th May, 1962.

</content>
</cab>
