<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/36/0 images: 307-315</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1962CC. (62)43rd conclusions copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1, onThursday, 28th June, 1962, at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P.. Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. John Maclay,Secretary of State for scotland.P.,The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies (Items 1 and 2)Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster-GeneralThe Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations the Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Lord Mills, minister without portfolio the Right Hon.  JohnMinister of labour hare, M.P..The Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P.. President of the Board of trade the following were also presentThe Right Hon.  Reginald Bevins,M.P., Postmaster-General (Item 2)The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat :
contents minute no. subject      Parliament       ............2      Broadcasting Policy    .........3      Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland4      Aid to Countries Overseas    ......Egypt5      Economic Situation6      Sir Winston Churchill........
ParliamentBroadcastingPolicy(previous reference:CC. (62) 40thConclusions,Minute 6)1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons in the following week.2. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Home Secretary(C. (62) 102) covering the draft of a White Paper setting out the interimviews of the Government on the Report of the Committee on broadcasting (the Pilkington Report). They also had before thema memorandum by the Chief Secretary, Treasury (C. (62) 103) onmeans of financing possible developments in the services of the british broadcasting Corporation (B.B.C.).The Home Secretary said that, in accordance with the Cabinet&apos;conclusion of 8th June, the Committee on Broadcasting and Televisionhad considered the draft of a White Paper dealing with certain technical matters raised in the Pilkington Report. The Committeehad thought that a White Paper should be presented early in July;that its scope should not be limited to technical matters; that it should include a statement that the Government would wait to see howpublic opinion reacted before giving their own views on the structuralchanges in independent television recommended in the Report; andthat there would be no need for a separate statement of theGovernment^ position on these proposals at this stage. These views were reflected in the draft which had been circulated under cover ofC. (62) 102.In discussion there was general agreement that the tone of the pilkington Report was intemperate and that its criticisms of thequality of television programmes showed some bias against theIndependent Television Authority (I.T.A.). It did not sufficientlyacknowledge that some of its criticisms, particularly of triviality and violence in many programmes, applied at least as much to the programmes of the B.B.C. as to those of the I.T.A. Some Ministersfelt that there was, nevertheless, much substance in the criticisms andthat it would be a mistake to brush aside the main conclusions reached in the Report, even if its proposals for a reconstituted I.T.A. could be shown to be unworkable. Many people, it was suggested, dislikedwatching, or allowing their children to watch, programmes of poor quality and would expect the Government to take measures to remedy the defects which the Report attributed to the association betweenthe provision of entertainment and the making of profits from thesale of advertising time. Educationists, in particular, would supportthe Pilkington Committee in insisting that moral values and behaviourwere affected by television and that the broadcasting authoritiesshould acknowledge a responsibility to ensure that standards werenot debased.In further discussion the following points were raised:(a) The Government should take an early opportunity to announce in a White Paper their conclusions on technical pointsaffecting television transmissions the use of the Ultra HighFrequency (U.H.F.) bands, the adoption of the 625-line standard of definition and the introduction of programmes in colour. although there was no immediate need to deal with a number of the othermatters covered by the draft White Paper, and although theGovernments reservations about changes in the structure of independent television could be made in a statement in Parliament,it would on balance be better to cover all these matters in the white paper. In particular, it should be stated that additional programmes would be authorised, since viewers would not buy new sets capableof receiving U.H.F. transmissions on 625 lines unless it could be shown that they would, by doing so, obtain access to new material.The Governments supporters would, in general, be likely to welcome an early announcement of decisions on as many points as possible.
ParliamentBroadcastingPolicy(previous reference:CC. (62) 40thConclusions,Minute 6)CC. 43 (62)1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons in the following week.2. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Home Secretary(C. (62) 102) covering the draft of a White Paper setting out the interimviews of the Government on the Report of the Committee on broadcasting (the Pilkington Report). They also had before thema memorandum by the Chief Secretary, Treasury (C. (62) 103) onmeans of financing possible developments in the services of the british broadcasting Corporation (B.B.C.).The Home Secretary said that, in accordance with the Cabinetsconclusion of 8th June, the Committee on Broadcasting and Televisionhad considered the draft of a White Paper dealing with certain technical matters raised in the Pilkington Report. The Committeehad thought that a White Paper should be presented early in July;that its scope should not be limited to technical matters; that it should include a statement that the Government would wait to see howpublic opinion reacted before giving their own views on the structuralchanges in independent television recommended in the Report; andthat there would be no need for a separate statement of theGovernments position on these proposals at this stage. These views were reflected in the draft which had been circulated under cover ofC. (62) 102.In discussion there was general agreement that the tone of the pilkington Report was intemperate and that its criticisms of thequality of television programmes showed some bias against theIndependent Television Authority (I.T.A.). It did not sufficientlyacknowledge that some of its criticisms, particularly of triviality and violence in many programmes, applied at least as much to the programmes of the B.B.C. as to those of the I.T.A. Some Ministersfelt that there was, nevertheless, much substance in the criticisms andthat it would be a mistake to brush aside the main conclusions reached in the Report, even if its proposals for a reconstituted I.T.A. could be shown to be unworkable. Many people, it was suggested, dislikedwatching, or allowing their children to watch, programmes of poor quality and would expect the Government to take measures to remedy the defects which the Report attributed to the association betweenthe provision of entertainment and the making of profits from thesale of advertising time. Educationists, in particular, would supportthe Pilkington Committee in insisting that moral values and behaviourwere affected by television and that the broadcasting authoritiesshould acknowledge a responsibility to ensure that standards werenot debased.In further discussion the following points were raised:(a) The Government should take an early opportunity to announce in a White Paper their conclusions on technical pointsaffecting television transmissions the use of the Ultra HighFrequency (U.H.F.) bands, the adoption of the 625-line standard of definition and the introduction of programmes in colour. although there was no immediate need to deal with a number of the othermatters covered by the draft White Paper, and although theGovernments reservations about changes in the structure of independent television could be made in a statement in Parliament,it would on balance be better to cover all these matters in the white paper. In particular, it should be stated that additional programmes would be authorised, since viewers would not buy new sets capableof receiving U.H.F. transmissions on 625 lines unless it could be shown that they would, by doing so, obtain access to new material.The Governments supporters would, in general, be likely to welcome an early announcement of decisions on as many points as possible.
(b) No harm would be done by saying in the White Paper thatan additional television programme would be authorised for theB.B.C., so long as it was made clear that a second programme of independent television would also be authorised in due course.(c) The proposals in the Report about the future structure and responsibilities of the I.T.A. would probably be shown by publicdebate to be unworkable. At this stage, therefore, it would be inexpedient to give more than a general warning that there were difficulties to be considered. Any show of irritation at the tone ofthe Report should be avoided.(d) Pay-television would have particular attractions for thosewho wished to make their own choice of programmes. The references to this subject in the White Paper should indicate that the government did not at present feel able to accept the conclusion that schemes forpay-television should be given no encouragement; but attention should be drawn to the importance of the difference betweentransmission by wire and by radio.(e) The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that the Pilkington Reportrecommended that ihe B.B.C. should be financed solely from licence revenue, but paragraph 61 of the draft White Paper hinted that someof the necessary money might be provided by other means. Hesuggested that there was nothing to be gained by drawing attention toother possible ways of financing the B.B.C.; it was desirable to makeit clear that, if more programmes were wanted, the cost would haveto be met from licence revenue. If it were not thought right to acceptthe Pilkington recommendation as it stood, the White Paper should say nothing about it.The general view of the Cabinet was that it would be unwise atthis stage to refer to the possibility either of a substantially increasedlicence fee or of other means to finance the B.B.C. Furtherconsideration would have to be given to this question, and it wouldbe inadvisable to include reference to it in the White Paper.(/) The draft should be amended in the light of the cabinets discussion and a revised version should be considered by theCommittee on Broadcasting and Television. Subject to approval bythat Committee, the White Paper should be presented to Parliamentduring the following week.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Home Secretary to arrange for the Committee on broadcasting and Television to consider, in the light ofthe Cabinets discussion, an amended version of the draft white Paper annexed to C. (62) 102.(2) Subject to approval of the revised draft by the Committeeon Broadcasting and Television, authorised thePostmaster-General to present the White Paper toParliament in the following week.Federationof rhodesia and Nyasaland(previous reference:CC. (62) 39thConclusions,Minute 6)3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary (C. (62) 100) seeking the Cabinets approval of his proposalto suggest to the Leader of the Malawi Congress Party, Dr. Banda,that a constitutional conference should be held in the autumn todiscuss the grant of a substantial measure of self-government toNyasaland.The Home Secretary said that the Malawi Ministers in Nyasalandunder the leadership of Dr. Banda were in firm political control of thecountry and had recently shown a willingness to discuss its futured development on a constructive basis.   In order to preserve this
willingness to co-operate, it would be necessary to make certain concessions. Br. Banda&apos;s real object was the attainment of independence for Nyasaland and a necessary first step to this wouldbe its secession from the Federation. Dr. Banda was accordinglypressing for an early statement by the United Kingdom Governmentrecognising Nyasaland&apos;s right to secede. He would like this to be accompanied or followed by a statement promising the grant of full independence at an early date. A statement foreshadowing secession,if made at the present stage, would have damaging repercussions onthe forthcoming elections in Northern Rhodesia and should for thisreason be delayed until after those elections had been held. Astatement foreshadowing independence would have to be deferred for some time because of its effect on the Federation itself and onSouthern Rhodesia. There would be great difficulties in concedingindependence to the Federation or to Southern Rhodesia at themoment. It would not be right to promise independence toNyasaland while continuing to withhold it from the Federation andfrom Southern Rhodesia, which on grounds of responsibility and importance had a much better claim to it. The best prospect of reaching a compromise with Dr. Banda about independence andpersuading him to accept some postponement of a statement onsecession would be to promise him at an early date a substantial measure of self-government and to undertake to review the questionof independence after a self-governing constitution had been introduced and had had a chance to prove itself.The Home Secretary said that for these reasons he hoped that theCabinet would authorise him to offer Dr. Banda a constitutional conference later in the year. He had warned both the Federal PrimeMinister and the Prime Minister of Southern Rhodesia that this wouldbe a likely development and that he himself supported it.In discussion the following points were made:(a) In the forthcoming negotiations with Dr. Banda secessionwas likely to be a more important issue than independence becauseof the strength of his antipathy to the present Federal Government.If a suitable formula could be found to meet his views on secessionit was probable that independence would become a less live politicalissue and that he would be prepared to consider in a more favourablelight the possibility of some continued economic association betweenNyasaland and the other territories of the present Federation. Itwould be particularly difficult to refuse to agree in principle toNyasaland&apos;s right to secede because of the precedents for secessionwhich had recently been created in the West Indies.(b) In the wider review which would shortly be undertaken ofthe future of the Federation as a whole, it would be a main objectiveto retain a close association between Northern and SouthernRhodesia. This would be difficult and might prove to be impossible.The best hope of success would be to allow time for full considerationof the complex issues involved and for public recognition of theadvantages of such a continuing association.(c) In relation to Southern Rhodesia the issue of independence would be largely resolved if the Federation were dissolved. this might have the effect of intensifying pressure from Dr. Banda for independence for Nyasaland. He would not be likely to be swayedby the economic arguments, strong as they were. But the Britishsubvention to the economy of Nyasaland was very large; and a point might be reached, if Dr. Banda were uncooperative, at which therewould be a strong public reaction in this country against thecontinuance of aid on so large a scale.(d) There was a difference of view on the legal right of the UnitedKingdom Government to dissolve the Federation. This point wasunder examination by the Law Officers, whose considered opinion
Aid toCountriesOverseasEgypt(previous reference:CC. (62) 41stConclusions,Minute 4)4. The Foreign Secretary recalled that at their previous discussion the Cabinet had considered the possibility of making a loan of $12 million to the Egyptian Government, of which $3 million would be withheld for the payment of transfers at present outstandingand $9 million would be available to finance imports from the UnitedKingdom; the Egyptian Government for their part would have undertaken to pay the equivalent of $5 million in stages to meetfurther transfers; $2 million in October 1963, $2 million in October1964, and SI million in October 1965. After the Cabinets discussionhe had discussed with the Ministers concerned two alternative ways of proceeding; under the first, the loan would in the first instance be restricted to $6 million, the Egyptians for their part undertaking tomake an immediate payment of $3 million to meet outstandingtransfers, and a further $6 million would be provided by the UnitedKingdom in the two subsequent years. The disadvantage of thisproposal from the Egyptian point of view was that it would makeonly $3 million available to help with their short-term balance ofpayments problem. It was not therefore likely to have the effect of improving Anglo-Egyptian relations. The second alternative was fora loan of $12 million, of which $4 million rather than $3 million wouldbe held back at the first stage for the payment of outstanding transfers;the Egyptian Government would then undertake to make two further payments of $2 million each to meet the balance of the claims. H.M.Ambassador in Cairo, who had been consulted, had given it as his view that under this proposal the Egyptians might seek to defer theirpayment of the first $2 million until 1964.The Foreign Secretary said that in his view the choice beforethe Cabinet lay between a loan of $12 million, of which $3 million would be held back in the first instance, with subsequent payments by the Egyptian Government in 1963, 1964 and 1965 to make up thetotal of $8 million needed to meet outstanding claims; and a loan of$12 million, of which $4 million would be held back in the firstinstance, in which case the Egyptian Government might delaypayment of the remaining $4 million until 1964 and 1965.In discussion the following points were made:(a) While any loan to the Egyptian Government would be likelyto cause difficulty in presentation and would give rise to controversy,particularly in the House of Lords, neither the difficulty nor the degreeof controversy would be materially affected by the comparatively small difference between the two proposals. On either basis therewould be considerable relief at the prospect of a final settlement ofthe outstanding claims by British subjects against the egyptian government.(h) The best solution would be a loan of $12 million, of which$4 million would be held back in the first instance and further payments of $2 million each would be made by the Egyptianwould in due course be transmitted to the Federal Government. Itwas, however, to be hoped that this issue would not fall to be settledon the basis of legal argument but by mutual agreement.(e) Great importance would attach to the work which the SpecialAdvisers would shortly be undertaking into possible future forms of association between the member territories of the present Federation.The Home Secretary said that it had now been agreed that the team of Advisers should be led by Sir Roger Stevens; and he would beannouncing the composition of the team in a statement in parliament that afternoon.The Cabinet Authorised the Home Secretary during his forthcoming talks with Dr. Banda to offer a constitutional conference in theautumn to discuss the grant of a substantial measure ofself-government to Nyasaland.
5. At the Prime Ministers request the Chancellor of theExchequer made a report on the economic situation.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he saw no reasonto modify appreciably the forecasts for 1962-63 which had been made before the Budget. He still expected a rise in production of 4 percent, over the year: for the three months from February to april the index of production had risen by two points compared with thepreceding three months, and the figures for May and June were likelyto show a further improvement. This recovery of production was likely to be assisted by the resumption of stocking by manufacturers and by a decline in the cost of living, which would lead to increased expenditure on durable consumer goods. Demand would also be stimulated by the relaxation of hire purchase restrictions. On theother side, there might be some fall in manufacturing investment,because of surplus capacity; but this represented only about a quarterof total private investment, and the forecasts still showed no appreciable reduction in total private investment in the current year. International factors seemed unlikely to affect this picturesubstantially. No actual down-turn in the United States economy was likely within the next six months though there would be a checkto its expansion; and there was no reason to think that any recessionin the United States would be allowed to reach unmanageableproportions. Moreover, in Europe production was rising again.Therefore, although there might be some fall in our exports to north america in 1963, the latest foresast was that total exports in the year would be higher than in 1962. In the engineering industry export orders were now above the high level reached in the early months of1961; and, even in the shipbuilding industry, export orders werehigher in the past six months than at any time since 1957. For steelalso, new export orders were higher in the first quarter of 1962 thanin the corresponding period of I960 or 1961.Government in 1963 and 1964. If this could not be negotiated, thebalance of advantage would lie in proposing a loan of $12 million,of which only $3 million would be held back in the first instance, but under which the first subsequent payment of $2 million by theEgyptian Government would be made in 1963. To delay any furtherpayment by Egypt until 1964 would be likely to cause more criticismthan the difference of $ 1 million between the sums to be held back inthe first instance.(c) It was now necessary to take a very early decision, since loans to Egypt by the Italian and German Governments were likely to be concluded within the next week or so. The Italian Governmentwould probably make a loan of $12 million, and the GermanGovernment rather more.The Cabinet (1) Authorised the Foreign Secretary to instruct H.M.Ambassador in Cairo to propose to the egyptian government a loan of $12 million, of which $4 million would be retained to meet outstanding transfers, and theEgyptian Government would for their part undertake tomake further payments of $2 million in 1963 and 1964respectively.(2) Agreed that, if the Egyptian Government could not bebrought to accept this proposal, H.M. Ambassador in cairo should be authorised to offer a loan of $12 million,of which only $3 million would be retained in the firstinstance and the Egyptian Government would undertaketo make further payments of $2 million in 1963, $2 million in 1964 and $1 million in 1965.
The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that in these circumstances he thought it unnecessary to contemplate any further government action to stimulate expansion, in addition to the steps already taken on Bank Rate, special deposits and hire purchase. Other forcesmaking for expansion were still strong. Public investment was risingfaster than had been forecast; exports were growing satisfactorily;and personal consumption was likely to rise as prices dropped and the concessions on hire purchase produced their full effect. further government action at this stage might produce a situation in whichrestrictions would have to be re-imposed in 1963.In discussion the following points were raised:(a) Although the general economic situation might be improving,the special difficulties of particular areas were becoming more acute.In Scotland and the north of England these difficulties would beaccentuated by the measures about to be taken for increasing efficiency in the mines, the railways and the docks. These wouldinvolve the discharge of substantial numbers of workers over theyears ahead. It was important that, when these measures were announced, the Government should be able to show that they hadeffective plans for absorbing the displaced labour in other employment. More generally, there would be need for an effectivelong-term policy for dealing with the drift of population towards theMidlands and the south-east of England.(b) Some Ministers expressed concern about the general economic effects of the recent fall in industrial share prices, in Londonand New York. This stemmed originally from a lack of confidence in industry, and it would itself create a further loss of confidence.This was likely to create an atmosphere which would discourageeconomic expansion, and this would spread to other countries. Therewere already indications that in Germany and Japan, as well as in theUnited States, action would be taken which would have the effect of restricting international trade. A general economic recession would undermine the stability of the Western world.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that he was seriously concerned about the international economic situation. Ifeach of the main trading nations was left to take, in isolation, themeasures which seemed necessary to protect its own position, therewould be a downward spiral movement in international trade. Onthe other hand, any spectacular international action to avert this might have the effect of increasing the loss of confidence which hadbeen a main factor in producing the existing situation. His own view was that the world&apos;s credit structure was inadequate to support theexisting volume of international trade. This position had beenmasked, since the end of the war, by the vast outpouring of the reserves accumulated by the United States. But, now that the UnitedStates economy was itself in difficulties, the dangers of the situation were being revealed. This problem seemed to him to require furtherconsideration.The Cabinet Took note of the statement by the Chancellor of theExchequer and agreed to resume their discussion at a further meeting.6. The Prime Minister said that the Cabinet would be sorry to hear that Sir Winston Churchill, who had been spending a briefholiday in Monte Carlo, had fallen and fractured a bone in his hip.The Cabinet asked the Prime Minister to arrange for a message to be sent to Sir Winston Churchill on their behalf, expressing their concern at his accident and their good wishes for his recovery.Sir winston churchill

</content>
</cab>
