<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/36/0 images: 346-353</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1962CC. (62)48th conclusions copy No.   4 2CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at Admiralty House, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 19th July, 1962, at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,First Secretary of state the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for science the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and Secretary of State forthe colonies the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Christopher Soames.M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Chief Secretary to the treasury and Paymaster-GeneralThe Right Hon. J. Enoch Powell, M.P.,Minister of health the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, M.P.,Minister   of   Housing   and   LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Dilhorne,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Frederick Erroll,M.P., President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Michael Noble, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Sir Edward Boyle,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. William Deedes, M.P.,Minister without portfolio also present:The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman brook mr. A. L. M. cary mr. J. H. Waddell
contents minute no.1234SubjectParliament       ......Legislative Programme 1962-63Truck Acts      ......Commercial PolicyJapan5     Works of Art......Leonardo Cartoon6      EuropeCommon Market NegotiationsPage3345
Legislative 2.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theProgramme Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster (C. (62) 118) about the1962-63 legislative programme for the 1962-63 Session of Parliament.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster said that in preparing the programme set out in the Annex to C. (62) 118, the future legislation Committee had had in mind the need, in what might bethe last Session of the present Parliament, to accommodate some major measures which might be regarded as of special importance and to preserve some room for manoeuvre. It was helpful that thescale of the legislation required if the United Kingdom joined theEuropean Communities was not likely to be so formidable as hadbeen feared. On present estimates the Bill would consist of a clausegiving the force of law to the treaties, the texts of which would beset out in a schedule of considerable length, and perhaps 70 additionalclauses and three or four additional schedules.Parliamentary time would not be available to deal with all the nine Bills which had been listed as &quot; main programme &quot; or &quot; highly desirable &quot; and it would be helpful if the Cabinet could provisionallyagree that the first three of the &quot; highly desirable &quot; Bills (Television,Water Conservation and Criminal Justice (Scotland)) should be advanced to the main programme, which would then consist of sevenBills. No real prospect could be held out that any of the Bills in categories C and D (Bills in reserve and other Bills) could beintroduced unless they were found to be suitable for handing to aPrivate Member who had been successful in the ballot.In discussion the following points were raised:(a) There was now a formidable number of Bills which it wouldnot be possible to enact during the life-time of the present Parliament,and some of these were of considerable importance for political or administrative reasons. Preliminary thought had been given toadjustments in Parliamentary procedure which would enable moreBills to be enacted, and it might be possible at some stage to arriveat an understanding with the Opposition on a means of facilitating the passage of Bills of a non-controversial character. It would not however be expedient to open discussions on this subject at present.(b) There was general agreement that the main programme should include the four Bills which had been listed. The LondonGovernment Bill would be long and would present difficulty inParliament, but it should be proceeded with even if an allocation oftime Motion had to be applied at an early stage. The Weights and measures Bill would also be a source of difficulty.(c) It seemed possible that the Criminal Justice (Scotland) Bill,which had been expected to require 60 to 70 clauses, could be reduced in scale so that it would deal only with the provision of legal aid in criminal cases in Scotland.(d) It was suggested that there might be a substantial case, whichshould be further considered, for including in the main programme the two Bills (Children and Young Persons and Airports Authority)which the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster had proposed forexclusion.(e) Further consideration should be also given, in consultationwith the Ministers concerned, to finding a more promising place for the Bills at present in lists C and D on Public Libraries,CC. (48) 62Parliament 1.   The Cabinet were informed of certain adjustments in thebusiness to be taken in Parliament in the two weeks remaining beforethe Summer Recess.
The Cabinet (1) Agreed to include in the legislative programme for 1962-63the Bills listed in the Annex to C. (62) 118 as &quot; essential &quot;,&quot; contingent&quot; (subject to settlement of policy in due course) and &quot; main programme &quot;.(2) Agreed that the legislative programme should also includethe Television and Water Conservation Bills.(3) Invited the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster to arrangefor the Future Legislation Committee to consider further,in consultation with the Ministers concerned, the scopeof the Criminal Justice (Scotland) Bill, the position ofthe Children and Young Persons Bill and the airports authority Bill, and, in the light of their discussion, thepossibility of according a higher priority to certain ofthe Bills now shown in lists C and D of the Annex toC. (62) 118.Truck Acts 3.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof Labour (C. (62) 115) about the future of the Truck Acts.The Minister of Labour said that in March 1961 he had receivedthe report of the Committee under the chairmanship of Mr. DavidKarmel, Q.C., which had been appointed to consider the Truck Actsin the light of present conditions. The Karmel Committee had recommended the repeal of the Truck Acts (1831 to 1940) and their replacement by legislation which would cover not only those engagedin manual labour but all those who were employed under a contract of service, including Crown employees. Wages should be paid in cash or in one of the ways permitted by the Payments of Wages Act,1960, but legal obstacles to the provision of additional benefits in kind should be removed and employers should, in certaincircumstances, be permitted to make deductions from wages subjectto provision for appeal to local tribunals. Action on the lines ofthese recommendations would be in general accord with theGovernments desire to improve the status of all employed persons and, although it would have to be made clear that the recommendationscould not be accepted in all respects (for example, in regard to Crownemployees), he thought that both sides of industry would be favourably disposed. He therefore sought authority to consult a number of interested organisations before putting forward detailed proposals for legislation.In discussion there was general agreement that the repeal ofthe Truck Acts and their replacement by a more up-to-date measure would be beneficial. But, as there could be no prospect of early legislation, it would be injudicious to press forward too rapidly withthe proposed consultations.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Labour to open discussions withinterested organisations on the practicability of legislationbroadly on the lines recommended by the Karmel Committeeon the future of the Truck Acts.Administration of Justice (Funds in Court), Companies (Deposits),Underground Parking, Commonwealth Scholarships (Amendment),and Severn Bridge Tolls. It was recognised, however, that it wouldnot be practicable to introduce these Bills (unless any of them couldbe obtained without use of Government time) without displacingother Bills for which even stronger claims could be made.
CC. (48) 624. The President of the Board of Trade said that with theexception of woollen goods the Cabinet had approved in earlier discussion his proposals for the restrictions to be retained on importsof certain types of Japanese goods after the conclusion of a commercial treaty with Japan. The proposed treaty would provide two kinds ofsafeguards for British manufacturers; the inclusion of an item in the&quot; sensitive &quot; list meant that its import from Japan would in any event be subject to control; in the case of items not on the &quot; sensitive &quot; listthere would be provision for the imposition of quotas within a periodof 30 days if the level of imports from Japan could be shown eitherto be exercising a disruptive influence on British manufacture, orto be likely to do so. In the light of the discussions which the PrimeMinister had held with a delegation from the wool industry, he nowproposed that woven wool cloth should be included in the &quot; sensitive &quot;list, but that no more than the general safeguard should apply to wooltops, yarn and garments of woven wool cloth. It was important to conclude the treaty with Japan at an early date. British exports to japan were rising rapidly and the future prospects in this expandingmarket were good. If a treaty could not be concluded, we should beplaced at a serious disadvantage in relation to other exporting countries which were also trying to increase their share of theJapanese market.In discussion the following points were made:(a) The British woollen industry was competitive and had secured a strong export position. The absence of adequate protection from Japanese competition might have a damaging commercial effecton the industry and would certainly cause political resentment. Asagainst this, British exports of woollen goods to Japan were alreadysubstantial, and the imposition of a continuing quota for wool clothwould provide a fair measure of protection, similar to that whichthe Japanese had introduced in order to protect their own industry.There would be no question of freeing imports of Japanese cloth,particularly at the light end of the range, from quota restriction,unless and until the Japanese had reduced their own high protectivetariff. But in general it should not be assumed that the right toimpose quotas of other classes of woollen goods in the event ofdisruption of trade would be an ineffective safeguard.(b) It would not be practicable to propose at this stage theinclusion of all woollen goods in the &quot; sensitive &quot; list and at some later stage in the negotiations to withdraw wool tops, yarns andgarments from the list if it appeared that this was necessary in orderto secure the conclusion of the treaty. We had already informed theJapanese that the proposals now to be submitted to them would represent our final position; if it turned out that we were in factprepared to make concessions on wool, this would encourage theJapanese to re-open discussion on other items which had previously been in dispute. Moreover, the time factor was critical; we couldnot afford the delay which negotiations of this kind would involve.(c) In general the commercial advantages to us of concludinga treaty with Japan on the lines now proposed were overriding; itwould be necessary to accept as part of the price to be paid for thesemore general advantages a smaller degree of protection for the woolindustry than the industry itself had demanded.The Cabinet Authorised the President of the Board of Trade to proceedwith negotiations for a commercial treaty with Japan onthe basis that woven wool cloth would be included in the&quot; sensitive &quot; list, but that wool tops, yarns and garments ofwoven wool cloth would be excluded from it.
Works of ArtLeonardoCartoon(previous reference:C.C. (62) 45thConclusions,Minute 6)5. The Prime Minister said that following the cabinets discussion of the appeal by the National Art Collections Fund for money to buy the Leonardo da Vinci Cartoon, he had now ascertained that the Royal Academy would not agree to any substantial extensionof the appeal period. The Academy considered that they had already made a sufficient contribution towards securing the Cartoon for thenation by agreeing to sell it for  800,000. The appeal period wouldexpire at the end of July, when the Fund would probably stand at about  400,000. It was now necessary to decide whether to take special steps to prevent the Cartoon being sold by public auctionand, if so, how large a contribution it would be right for theGovernment to make towards the  400,000 which would still berequired.In discussion the following points were made:(a) The Royal Academy had taken an unreasonable attitude overthe sale of the Cartoon. Although they had not themselves made itavailable for general public showing, they had sought to takeadvantage of the inflationary market in works of art and had, as aresult, placed the Government in a difficult position. It did not,however, appear that there would be anything to be gained by bringing further pressure to bear on them.(b) A remarkable feature of the showing of the Cartoon in theNational Gallery had been the amount of interest taken in the Cartoonby the general public, who had plainly been deeply impressed by it.Account should also be taken of the importance of demonstratingthe Governments interest in retaining works of art in this country,notwithstanding current economic difficulties. To allow the appealto fail would be a grave disappointment to many people and therewould be much criticism because of the inability of the Fund toreturn a large proportion of the contributions which had been made.For these reasons it would be right that the Government should beprepared to make a substantial payment. But special care wouldhave to be taken to present this decision in a proper light, as a responseby the Government to a substantial body of public opinion.(c) The Cartoon would, on present intentions, become theproperty of the British Museum and would be on permanent loan tothe National Gallery. In these circumstances there would be grounds for allocating to the purchase a substantial part of the grant madeby the Treasury to the National Gallery for the purchase of pictures.The annual grant for this purchase was  100,000 (excluding special provisions for the purchase of French pictures) and if some part ofthis year&apos;s grant and the whole of that for the following year wereallocated, the additional amount which would have to be found bythe Government would be much reduced. It was possible also thatsome further contribution could be obtained through the Fund itself and that in the result the Governments special contribution wouldnot exceed  250,000.(d) Consideration should be given to the wisdom of the generalpolicy of not making charges for admission to the National Galleryand to other public art collections. If there proved to be difficulty about altering the system of free admission, some arrangement mightbe made whereby the National Gallery could make a special charge for admission to the room containing the Leonardo Cartoon.(e) It would be undesirable that the Cartoon should be put on public exhibition for some time after it had been acquired. In presentconditions there was a risk that it might be damaged or stolen bysomeone anxious to attract public attention.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Chief Secretary, Treasury, to negotiate with theNational Gallery, the National Art Collections Fund andthe Royal Academy, with the object of securing the
11tCC. (48) 62Leonardo Cartoon for the nation at a direct cost to theExchequer not exceeding  250,000.(2) Took note that no announcement would be made until asatisfactory settlement had been reached.(3) Took note that after the picture had been acquired, it wouldbe desirable to withhold it from public exhibition forsome time in order to minimise the risk that it wouldbe damaged or stolen.EuropeCommonMarketNegotiations(previous reference:CC. (62) 47thConclusions,Minute 6)6. The Lord Privy Seal informed the Cabinet of the progressof the negotiations for the entry of the United Kingdom into theEuropean Communities.European Coal and Steel community the Lord Privy Seal said that he had now made the openingstatement in the negotiations for our entry into the European coal and Steel Community (E.C.S.C.). Agreement had been reached on procedure; a meeting at Ministerial level of the existing members ofthe Community would be held in September to review the positionas it had by then emerged. This would be followed by a ministerial meeting in October, at which the United Kingdom would be present.The point of main concern to the existing members of the Communitywas the prospect of a greater volume of coal exports from the UnitedKingdom to Europe. The French Government would, however, belikely to raise other difficulties; they had already shown themselvesanxious to use the negotiations about our entry into the E.C.S.C. asa pretext for setting in hand a major revision of the Treaty of Paris,and they had also suggested that our entry should be made conditional on agreement to a common energy policy for Europe. Neither ofthese issues was relevant to the more limited question actually under negotiation, but it might be a matter of some difficulty to persuade the French Government to accept this.European Economic CommunityMinisterial negotiations in Brussels would shortly be resumed.The Minister of Agriculture would be present on this occasion and itwas hoped that some progress could be made with the difficult questions facing us in relation to domestic horticulture and agriculture.It would not unfortunately be possible to obtain firm decisions, sincebecause of other commitments, no French Minister would be present.A further series of Ministerial meetings would be held in the following week at which the position of the developed countries of theCommonwealth on temperate foodstuffs and the safeguards for exports from the Asian members of the Commonwealth would alsobe under discussion. In relation to India there had been encouragingdevelopments; Mr. Desai, the Indian Minister of Finance, was nowconvinced that United Kingdom entry into the European economic community (E.E.C.) would be desirable and seemed disposed toaccept the arrangements proposed to safeguard India&apos;s own position.On the other hand, very little progress had been made on the problemof temperate foodstuffs, largely because the existing members of theCommunity had been unable to reach an agreed position among themselves. In an effort to break the deadlock which seemed likelyto develop, a compromise solution was now under discussion inLondon and would shortly be put forward.The negotiations had now entered a critical phase. some european countries had come to the view that we did not want ageneral pattern of the conditions under which it might be possiblefor us to enter the E.E.C. to emerge until October, after the Meetingof Commonwealth Prime Ministers.   It was also thought that we
intended to present an initial set of proposals both to Parliament andto the Commonwealth in the knowledge that strong opposition wouldbe aroused and in the hope that the strength of the opposition wouldenable us to negotiate further concessions; and on this basis some european countries had argued that it would be against their interestto make any concessions at the present stage.The Lord Privy Seal said that he was now engaged in puttingboth these views into a proper perspective. So far from beinganxious to delay the negotiations we were more than ever anxiousto make real progress. If we could not at this stage secure reasonablecompromises on the main issues in dispute there would be no questionof negotiating further concessions later since all prospect of theUnited Kingdom being able to enter the E.C.C. at all would have dissapeared. Great damage had been done by the recent speech ofthe Leader of the Opposition, Mr. Gaitskell, to the European socialist parties. His approach had been entirely negative and he had made no mention of the United Kingdom&apos;s intention to play an active partin the work of the Community; his emphasis had throughout been on the need to continue to plan the economic and social developmentof the United Kingdom on a purely national basis. It would be important to counteract the impression thus created, and it was hopedthat Ministers would take every opportunity to emphasise our intention to play a full and positive part in European affairs.In discussion the following points were made:(a) In the light of Mr. Gaitskell&apos;s speech there was likely to be considerable public interest in the views of the Government on political development in Europe, and more particularly, on federalas opposed to confederal forms of organisation. It would be helpful if the Lord Privy Seal, in consultation with the Minister without portfolio, could provide Ministers with speaking notes on thissubject.(b) The problems of domestic agriculture would become increasingly difficult and might be decisive. The first and main problem was that for some very important products, includingmutton, beef and milk, the existing members of the Community hadnot yet decided their own policy and could not, therefore, conclude a final agreement with us or even enter into serious negotiation. Itmight be possible to reach agreement on a certain number of products,and negotiations to this end should be pressed forward; for other products the best that could be hoped for would be agreement ona general formula indicating the limits within which final agreements would be negotiated and the nature of the safeguards to be provided.This would not be an easy position to defend.(c) In view of these difficulties it would be important to avoidreaching a position in which so large a measure of agreement had beenreached about safeguards for the Commonwealth that we should be under pressure to make unjustified concessions on domesticagriculture. The European countries must be made to see thatsafeguards for domestic agriculture and safeguards for Commonwealthproducts were not in conflict, but were complementary and equally important; a healthy internal economy and a flourishing external trade would stand or fall together.The Cabinet (1) Took note of this statement by the Lord Privy Seal.(2) Invited the Lord Privy Seal, in consultation with the minister without Portfolio, to arrange for the preparation ofspeaking notes for Ministers on the Governments attitude to possible forms of future political association in Europe.

</content>
</cab>
