<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/95/0 images: 251-265</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT^Ig^THE J R^246g TT, G R E T.CABINET 45(88)COPY NO.CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet hold at10, Downing Street, S.W.I. , on Monday, 26thSeptember, 1938, at 12 Noon.P R E S E N T:-The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Prime Minister. (In the Chair),The Right H :n.Sir John Simon, CCS.I.,G.C.V.Q.,  O.B.E., K.C, M.P. ,Chancellor of the Exchequer.Th.* Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon.Lord Maugham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.C.S.I.,CB,E., C.M.G., M.P., Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K.G.,G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon.The Earl Be La Warr,Lord Privy Seal.The Most Hon.Tha Marquess of Zetland,G.C.S.I., CCI.E,,Sscr^tary of State for India,The Right Hon.Malcolm MacDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.Sir Thomas inskip, C.B.E., K.C. ,M.P., Minister for Co-ordinationof Dafenc-o.The Right Hon..L. Hore-Bolisha,. M.P.,Secretary nf State for War.The Right H^n.John Colvillo, M.P.,Secretary of State for ScotlandoTho Right hand.W.S, Morrison, M.C., K.C., M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C, M.P.,Minister of Health.Tho Right. Hon.% E.L. Hurgin, M.P.,Minister of Transport.The Right Hon.A. Duff Cooper, D.S.O., M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.P.,Secretary of State for AiijThe Right Hon.Oliver Stanley,. M.C , M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.The Earl Stanhope, K.G., B.S.O.,M.C, President of the Board nfEducation.The Right Hon.Ernest Br-;wn, M.C., M.P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Tho Earl Wintorton, M.P.chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.E.E. Bridges, M. c., .......................................... Secretary.
1.      THE PRIME MINISTER said that he hadreceived a message from President Roosevelturging him to continue negotiations up to thelast possible moment in order to arrive at a peaceful settlement.The Prime Minister said that effecthad now been given to the proposal which he had put to the Cabinet at the Meeting which endedearlier that morning that he should send a personal appeal to Herr Hitiere      Sir HoraceWilson had now left for Berlin with&apos;a personal message from him (the Prime Minister).     sir nevile Henderson had been instructed to seek an interview for Sir Horace Wilson and himself with Herr Hitler0     Although the Prime Ministerplaced no particular hopes on this last appeal,he thought there was just a chance that it mighthave some result.     The fact that the message wasbeing taken by Sir Horace Wilson was of great value, as Sir Horace Wilson could speakpersonally on behalf of the Prime Minister ashis Confidential Adviser.     We should know whatmeasure of success. Sir Horace had achieved whenHerr Hitlerrs broadcast was received at 8 o&apos;clockthat evening.&apos;.
THE INTER&apos;UTIONALSITUATION,hi amConversationswith repre-sentatives ofthe PrenchGovernment,previous references cabinet 44 ( 38).)2.     THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had againseen the Prench Ministers that morning.     Therehad been a perceptible change in their attitudesince the previous night.     In the hope of getting a better indication of their mind he had seenM. Daladier alone, with M. Oorbin to help ininterpreting.He had told M. Daladier about the message which he was sending by Sir Horace Wilson, andM. Daladier had agreed entirely with this course.The Prime Minister had told M. Daladier of thenature of the appeal which he had instructed sir horace Wilson to make on his behalf.     He had also informed him that if Sir Horace could get nosatisfaction from Herr Hitler, then he proposedthat he should speak in the following terms to theFuhrert-&quot;The Prench Government have informed us that, if the Czechs reject theMemorandum and Germany attacksCzechoslovakia, they will fulfill their obligations to Czechoslovakia,Should the forces of Prance inconsequence become engaged in activehostilities against Germany, we shallfeel obliged to support them,&quot;He had asked M. Daladier whether he had any commentsto make on the proposed oral statement or whetherit would embarrass him in any way.     M. Daladier had said that he was absolutely in accord with theproposed statement and had no comment to make on it.He had impressed on M. Daladier the importance ofmaintaining absolute secrecy in regard to this proposed message, but he had given a copy of it toM. Corbin.The Prime Minister said that he had then asked M. Daladier whether he wished to say anythingfurther.
M. Daladier had said that, speaking frankly,he did not feel that he had expressed himself wellon the previous evening.     He -fe*a&amp; stated that if germany attacked Czechoslovakia and hostilitiesensued, the French intended to go to war and to commence hostilities with Germany within five days.He had given certain details of the French dispositionsand views.(A copy of the statement which the PrimeMinister made on this point is includedin the Secretary&apos;s standard file ofCabinet Conclusions.)That, in essence, was the situation.     Therewas still one last opportunity for negotiation,but if that failed, France and this country stoodtogether.The Cabinet approved the action taken by thePrime Minister.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR raised thequestion of the Intermediate Contingent.     He saidthat it would facilitate the discussions with general gamelin if it could be assumed that the plan of despatchof the Intermediate Contingent could be fulfilled.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER thought thatthis matter could hardly be described as an &quot;assumption&quot;.He thought it was a decision of fundamental importance and must be regarded as an issue which was still entirelyopen and remained to be decided on its merits.THE MINISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OF DEFENCEmentioned that in a conversation he had had that morning&quot;wl^th General Gamelin he had gathered that the Frenchdispositions had been made independently of any british assistance by air or land.
THE INTER- 3.&apos;     THE PRIME MINISTER read a statement heNATIONALSITUATION.  - had received from the Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill,M.P.,  saying that Parliament should now he summoned.Summoning ofparliament. The Prime Minister said that it was clear(Previous     that Parliament must now &quot;be summoned.    The onlyReference:Cabinet       question in his mind was whether it should be39(38)).summoned for Tuesday, 27th September, or Wednesday,28th September.    On the whole, he favoured thelatter date.    The position would be much cleareron Wednesday, and there was much to be done in themeantime.THE SECRETARY OP STATE POR FOREIGN affairs suggested that it might be desirable that the debate in the House of Lords should take place aday after the Debate in the House of Commons, butit was agreed that the House of Lords should be summoned on the same day as the House of Commons.The point which the Foreign Secretary had in mindcould be dealt with by the House of Lords meetingformally and adjourning at once on Wednesday untilthe following day.The Cabinet agreed:-That Parliament should be summoned to meet on Wednesday,  the-28thSeptember. ,
THB INTER- 4.      THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR HOME AFFAIRSNATIONALSITUATION..       said that consideration should be given to thequestion whether the Defence of the Realm ActWar emergency legislation,    should be passed at once.    His View was that itwould   be better to postpone the introduction ofthis legislation until general agreement had beenreached with the Leaders of the Opposition,although this might involve a few daysT delay.This course was agreed to.
THE INTER-national situation.MobilisationMeasures.5.     Discussion took place in regard, tomobilisation measures and the introduction of thePreparatory and Precautionary Periods.THE MINISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OP DEFENCEmentioned that,  on the authority of the primeMinister, the Secretary of State for War had nowbeen authorised to call up the Anti-aircraftpersonnel of the Territorial Army, and that theSecretary of State for Air had been authorised tocall up the personnel of the Observer Corps.He explained that it was desirable that the Anti-aircraft personnel should be called up,  ifpossible, 48 hours before mobilisation, in orderthat the guns and searchlights should be placedin position.    This was important, since ifmobilisation was regarded by Germany as a hostile action we might be attacked before our anti-aircraft defences were in position.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR stated that steps were being taken to inform the Press thatthe measures taken in regard to Anti-aircraftpersonnel did not constitute general mobilisation.In regard to other precautionary measures,the need for steps to be taken to prevent sabotage,and the installation of censorship, were mentioned.The general view taken was that it was undesirable to deal with these matters individually.It was pointed out that the War-Book pre-scribed a number of steps which formed part of an integral scheme which should be considered as aWhole.The Minister for Co-ordination of defence had been authorised by the Prime Minister to assemble a Conference of Ministers at 3 p.ra. that afternoon to consider the measures set out in the-6-
Hote:     At a Meeting of Ministers held at 3.0 p.m.on 26th September, it was decided that certain other measures, included in the PrecautionaryPeriod, should be taken by Departments immediately on receip t of instructions from the Prime Ministerfor mobilisation, without further cabinet authority.&apos; ii report of the Co-ordination   Committee (CP. 208(38))with a view to -(i) Taking immediate decisions onsuch matters as, in their judgment,it was unnecessary to refer to theCabinet;    and(ii) Making recommendations in regard to those measures which required Cabinet authority.It was agreed -That the Ministers concerned shouldhave authority to take decisions in regard to these matters,subject to -(a) reference to the   cabinet of such matters as clearlyrequired Cabinet decision:i(b) submission to the Prime minister on matters of vital importance.Discussion took place whether it would be necessaryto summon a   Cabinet in order to reach conclusions inregard to mobilisation.      It was pointed out that herr Hitlex^s speech that evening would probably makeit clear whether immediate mobilisation was necessary.On the suggestion of the GHA1T0ELL0R OF THEEXCHEQUER,  the Cabinet agreed:That the Prime Minister, in consultation withthe Lord President of the Council, shouldbe authorised to make the necessary arrange-ments for obtaining the approval of HisMajesty in Council to the mobilisationProclamations and other documents, if heshould consider this course was necessarywithout summoning the Cabinet.It was agreed that if orders were given for mobility-sation, this involved giving effect to other measures86
set out in the War Book, which were essentially linked with mobilisation.      It v/as pointed out that should itbecome necessary to hold a meeting of the Privy Councilwithin the course of the next few days, this might interferewith the visit of His Majesty The King to Glasgow, and Itv/as agreed that a suitable message should be conveyed to theKing1 s Private Secretary.
SINGAPOREGARRISON.reinforcement of.(previous reference:Cabinet 5&quot;6. THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR INDIA referred tothe proposal contained in the Report of a Conferenceof Ministers held at the Admiralty on the 25th September,1938, that the War Office should have authority to take-......up the question of the reinforcement of the Singaporegarrison from India in consultation with the War Officewithout further reference to higher authority.It was agreed:-That if the Ministers concerned were unable to reach agreement on this matter it should be referred to the Committee ofImperial Defence.
THE INTER-national situation.Attitude ofthe Dominions.BR.u-C(5i)i7. THE SECRETARY OP STATE POR THE colonies reported that he had had a discussion that morningwith the Dominion High Commissioners.     They hadall said in the strongest possible terms that,&apos;in the view of their G-governments, if there was any possible chance of peace by negotiation theopportunity should not be lost.     In their viewacceptance of Herr hitler proposals was betterthan war.   At the same time they had little doubtthat if we became involved in war the dominions would join in too.     The Secretary of State addedthat he thought that while Australia and NewZealand might join us after a short delay, inthe case of South Africa and Eire the delaymight be rather considerable,THE PRIME MINISTER reported that he had hada telephone message from Mr. Lyons that morning,Mr, Lyons had expressed entire approval of theattitude which His Majesty*s Government had adopted, and had sa.id that he regarded thepresent issue as a &quot;method of procedure rather thanprinciple.&quot;poland.8. THE SECRETARY OP STATE POR FOREIGN affairs said that information had been received indirectlyfrom the French Government the previous eveningthat M, Benes had approached Poland and had offered to cede Teschen to Poland in exchange for a guaranteefrom Poland for non-aggression.
PROPOSAL to drop LEAP-LETS over germany.BROADCASTING.This matter had been put to the French ministers that morning and they had agreed that this was theposition.     They had also taken the view that theBritish and French   Governments should both send atelegram to their Ministers in Warsaw instructingthem to inform the Polish Government that, in thelight of M. Benes&apos; s offer, they would regard anyfurther action by Poland to use violent means tosecure their aims as unjustifiedoTHE FOREIGN SECRETARY stated that he hoped that,in this way, it would, be possible to put a stopto sinister designs entertained by Poland toaggrandise themselves at Czechoslovakia^ expenseduring the present situation9.    THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs mentioned that there were a number of difficult pointsinvolved.In the course of discussion, it was pointed outthat the action proposed ?/as a problem involving a technical act of war.^It was agreed that the matter should, bediscussed by the Ministers concerned, andthe Secretary of State for Foreign affairs should take the necessary steps to convene a meetingo10,    THE PRIME MINISTER mentioned that he thought that itwould probably be desirable that he should broadcast on tuesday evening.Some discussion took place as to what would be thebest technical arrangements for such a broadcast in orderto ensure. that it would reach the widest possible   numberof listeners both in this country, abroad and in Germany.If the Ministry of Information had been set up, thismatter would fall within their scope.
In the course of discussion, the Minister ofLabour and the Secretary of State for Airdeprecated the publicity given by the british broadcasting Corporation in their news broadcaststo rumours which, appeared in various journals,THE CABINET agreed: -that the Secretary should be instructedto invite.Sir Robert Vansittart,Sir Stephen Tallents and Mr, Steward to.consider, as a matter of urgency, andto make suggestions ,in regard to the. best arrangements for thePrime Minister&apos;s broadcast,.Richmond Terrace, S.W,1,26th September, .1938.
NOT, OmOULATED,.^meeting SECRET..STATEMENT MADE BY THE PRIME MINISTERTO THE CABINET ON MONDAY. 26th SEPTEMBER.cabinet 45 (58)) AS TO  INFORMATIONCONVEYED TO HIM THAT, MORNING BY general gamelin.If hostilities ensued and Germany, attackedCzechoslovakia, x,he Prench intended to enter the warand to launch an attack within about five days.    Thepoints in the line where this attack would take placehad been indicated, and General Game1in had said that recent German troop movements showed that they appre-ciated the weakness of this spot.Asked whether the Prench contemplated attack by air, General Gamelin had said &quot;Yes&quot;.   Prance was well aware that she would suffer heavily from air attacks.Nevertheless, she would take offensive action, pa.rticu-larly against industrial districts near the frontier.;:-;,Czechoslovakia had 34 Divisions, and germany had the same number opposite her.   Until recently thoseDivisions had been drawn up along the Czech frontiers.More recently, however, the Divisions had moved up tothe morth and south of the narrowest points of Czecho-slovakia.    In other words, the position of the troops had been changed from a covering position to a positionof preparedness for attack.    General Gamelin thoughtthat the Czechoslovak army would give a good account of themselves.    They had 500 aeroplanes of their own, andhad recently acquired 280 from Russia..   They would try to keep open the bottle-neck at all costs, so that evenif they were forced to retire their army would stillbe able to pass out from the western frontier to theeastern part of the country, and they would be able tomaintain a fighting force.The Prench had 23 Divisions on the western front.   Opposite them there &apos;were 8 German Divisions.
Richmond Terrace, S.W.1,26th September, 1938.The Siegfried. Line was far from complete.    In fact,in many respects it was improvised.    The French thought they were in a position to make an attack which would at least draw off troops from Czechoslovakia.   they proposed to make use of their aviation in connectionwith the Army.

</content>
</cab>
