<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/7/28 images: 222-223</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 ^jSTOGJME^ OF &quot;HIS BRITANNIC MAJESBY^S GOVERNMENT. )Oopy No.SEQHEHW.P. (G) (4-0) 178July 9th, 1940.WAR   CABINET.PUBLICATION OF AIR RAID CASUALTIES.Memorandum by the Minister of Information.On the 3rd July (192nd. Meeting, item 3. ) the War Cabinet agreed:-That reports of casualties oaused by German air raids should infuture be stated in general terms and should not give the detailsof the precise numbers killed and injured.Air raid casualties appear in the Press from two sourcesa) official communiquesb) reports from newspaper or News Agency reporters orcorrespondents.Official communiques would, under the Cabinet ruling, only refer to casualties by such vague terms as &quot;slight&quot;,    &quot;considerable&quot;   or   &quot;heavy&quot;.Ihere would be a natural tendency to avoid the use of &quot;heavy&quot;.     Thisdeparture from the existing system of announcing precise figures at theearliest possible time will have the following results(a) It is a contradiction of assurances which have been given on several occasions to representatives of the Press on behalf ofthe Air Ministry and the Ministry of Home Security.     these assurances are given effect to in the existing Defence notice on this subject which has been issued to the Press.     It hasalways been accepted that exact figures would be madeavailable, in order to allay rumour, and a change of policyin this respect will undoubtedly be taken by the Press asa sign of the Government *s lack of confidence in publicmorale.
(b) The public will hardly pay even perfunctory attention to official communiques which substitute vague andstereotyped adjectives for figures.     Rumour will he thoironly source of information as to the effect of raids in   other parts of the country.     Rumour unchecked by facts    1exaggerates rapidly and wildly.   This can be substantiatedby anyone who sees the Press submissions to the CensorshipIn the result the failure to give at onoe full figures     jflwhich the public can believe will demoralise the public moroithan any figures could; since (l) rumour will multiply the Itrue figures and (2) the public will be resentful and      Iperturbed that their own Government dare not trust them    Iwith the truth.Press reports of casualties must pass through the censorship,,Press submissions arising from an air raid will not however consist of onestory but of any number of different stories coming in from separatesources and at different times.     No single story may purport to give    Ifexact or precise numbers of the total casualties, but a pretty accurate   Ipicture can probably be obtained from all the stories taken together.To give effect to the Cabinet ruling it would be necessary for the censorship not only to suppress figures, but also accounts of air raiddeaths and injuries, and even the names of the casualties, as these wouldbe as revealing as figures.I suggest therefore that the Cabinet Resolution should bere considered in the light of the considerations set out above; and thatthe policy laid down should be:-(l) That precise figures of the &quot;killed&quot; should be given always;(2) That precise figures should also be given of personsseriously injured.     The only practical criterion of&quot;serious injury&quot; is admission to hospital; and we would suggest that injury figures should be restricted to personaadmitted to hospital.     There will inevitably be some littlefdelay (though not more than 24- hours&apos; delay) before precise Ifigures can be given of the numbers of persons admitted to Ihospital.     It may therefore be necessary to issue the first;announcement in the form &quot;xx killed, and a number of other Ipersons injured&quot;, and to follow this up later with precise Iinformation of the numbers of persons admitted to hospital,The Secretary of State for Air and the Minister for home Security, whom I have consulted, agree with these recommendations.Initialled D.C.9th July, 1940.

</content>
</cab>
