<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/39/0 images: 62-69</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Docnment is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government.]        4&apos;58Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1918.SECRET.A )SNAVAL WEEKLY APPRECIATION-No. 33. Week ended 5th January, 1918.NAVAL OPERATIONS.Mines have been laid in the Heligoland Bight, and the laying of a defensive minefield North Sea. off the East Coast of England has been completed.The weather has been generally unfavourable for flying, but a number of patrols and Flanders reconnaissances have been carried out from Dunkirk ; also a raid on Ghistelles aerodrome area an(* where 1,548 lbs. of bombs were dropped amongst the sheds and buildings. FranceDuring the period 2nd-15th December, 1917, R.N.A.S. Squadron No. 8 attached to   ran the R.F.C in France, has carried out 74 offensive patrols and 138 special operations. Thirteen combats took. place, during which six enemy machines were driven down out of control one of which is believed to have- been destroyed.  There were no R.N.A.S. casualties.The transport &quot; Osmanieh &quot; has been sunk, it is believed by mine, off Alexandria. Casualties. She had on board 47 officers, 885 troops, 37 nurses, 45 naval ratings and 128 crew, total 1,142.   The casualties, missing or dead, were 1 military officer and 199 other ranks, 7 nurses, 1 naval officer on passage and 6 naval ratings, and 9 of the crew, total 223.The naval hospital ship &quot; Rewa &quot; was torpedoed and sunk on January 4th seven miles from Tintagel. There were 251 naval and 54 military patients and 215 crew on board. All were saved except three Lascars.The armed drifter &quot; Golden Sunset&quot; was sunk by collision with a trawler about six miles east of Portland on January 4th.   The crew were saved.The armed whaler &quot; Hirpa &quot; has gone ashore near Buckie (Banff).   The crew were saved.The armed whaler No. 868 was torpedoed on January 3rd about 65 miles from Fife Ness.   Eight survivors were picked up.Four men have been killed, and 1 officer and 4 men seriously and 6 men slightly injured, on board the patrol boat &quot; P. 60,&quot; when attacking a submarine, owing to the premature explosion of a depth charge on striking the water.The Courts of Inquiry consider that the transport &quot; Aragon &quot; and the destroyer &quot; Attack &quot; (reported sunk in last week&apos;s Appreciation) were torpedoed, the latter while picking up survivors from the former.ATTACK UPON ENEMY SUBMARINES.During the week 16 to 18 large enemy submarines have been located, about 12 of Submarines which were operating to the South and West of Great Britain, the area of greatest activity operating, again being the Irish Sea and the English Channel.   Three of the converted Deutschland vessels have been operating this week, two in the vicinity of the Azores and Canary Islands and one on passage out.(C 893)  Wt.     55   1/18  H *S
(4ctions The following Table shows the number of actions with enemy submarines in Homewith enemy -Raters during recent weeks, and the nature of the craft which have been engaged, and su marine:. ajgo ^e number of submarines destroyed: Number and ton-nage of all vessels lost.	Week ended		&quot; Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		December 15th.		December 22nd.		December 29th.		January 5th.	Nature of Craft.									Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.	Actions.	j Results. - Actions.		j Results.								Special Service Ships    ......	2		1	_	1		_	T.B.D. and T.B..........	1	--	2	-	4	-&apos;-&apos;	4	 A.P. Vessels     .........	6	-   - -	5	-  -	2	--	7 .	 Aircraft   ...	1	 	3	 	2	- - &quot;-	4	A.P. Vessel and Aircraft        ...	-  -	 	1	-	 	 &apos;	 	r   Sloops and &quot;P.&quot; Class Vessels ...		 	2	-	1	1	2	  -Merchant Vessels.........	2	 	1	-	2	 	5	1       -Destroyed by Mine     ......	-	.    	 -	1		-   	 	 Total	12	- -&apos;-	15	1	12	1	22	1*&quot;Results&quot; indicates submarines definitely or probably sunk according to the reports of the actions received.   Submarines possibly sunk are not included.* The nature of the craft which achieved this result is not yet determined.MERCANTILE LOSSES BY ENEMY ACTION.The following is a Comparative Statement of the Number and Tonnage of all Merchant Vessels sunk in recent weeks by enemy action : -		British Vessels.			Allied and Neutral Vessels.				Total.	Week Ended	1,600	tons gross	Under	1,600 tons	1,600	tons gross	Under 1,600 tons		All sizes.		and over.		gross.		and over.			gross.			No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.1917.										November 24th	13	49,594	7	2,709	10	29,651	7	4,094	37	86,048December 1st...	16	59,533	1	179	7	25,946	6	3,641.	30	89,299December 8th	14	45,958	7	4,689	-7	22,801-	11	5,465	39	78,913December 15th	14	44,966	3	2,011	10	25,415	15*	10,957*	42*	83,349*December 22 ad	12	46,786	1	608	7*	24,253*	9	6,594	29*	78,241*December 29th	17*	67,172*	4*	3,969*	8*	25,372*	7*	7,127*	36*	103,640*1918.										January 5th...	16	.   68,750	2	1,391	7	24,865	 	 	25	95,006*Ad justed.It will be observed that the tonnage of British vessels lost this week is approximately the same as last week, and the same remark applies to Allied and Neutral Vessels of 1,600 tons and over.Losses of British steamships in trades.The table in Appendix I shows in detail the numbers and tonnage of sailings and of losses by enemy action, and the percentage of losses to sailings of British Merchant Steamships of over 500 tons gross register ; and the table in Appendix II shows by trades as regards such ships the percentage of tonnage sunk by enemy action to tonnage sailing to and from United Kingdom ports during the last four weeks.The percentage of losses to sailings as regards tonnage engaged in overseas trades this week is only 1.09 as against the high figure of 5.38 last week. The total tonnage afloat engaged in these&apos; trades has resumed the normal, having increased by nearly 50 per cent, on the previous week, while only three vessels have been lost in these trades as against 11 last week. On the other hand, the losses in Coasting and Cross-Channel traffic this week show a considerable increase, with the result that as regards all traffic the percentage of losses to sailings is this week 1.33 as against-1.94 last week.. f
The table in Appendix III is a comparative statement of all British Merchant Vessels Areas in sunk, damaged or molested, and of all Allied and Neutral Merchant Vessels sunk in the wnicl1 last two weeks by enemy craft and by mine classified according to areas. - vessels lost.The losses this week are entirely confined to the waters surrounding the United Kingdom and the Mediterranean, no vessels having been sunk and only one attacked in the Atlantic, Bay of Biscay or Gibraltar areas.The following statement shows the number and tonnage of all Merchant Vessels sunk Coni-by enemy action since the commencement of the iinrestricted Submarine Warfare  	British Merchant		British Fishing		Merchant Vessels		Merchant&quot; Vessels		Total	1917.	Vessels.		Vessels.		of other Allies.		of Neutrals.		of all Vessels.	Month.	No.	Tonnage	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.February  ...	105	313,486	30	3,478	60	84,280	69	135,090	264	536,334March &apos;    ...	125	355,446	43	3,586	62	81,151	92	165.225	322	605,408April	168	541,887	41	5,920	82 &apos;	134,448	122	189,373	413	871,628May......	120	349,344	19	1,448	70	102,960	96	139,605	305	593,357June	120	413,406	21	1,342	79	126,097	89	139,229	309	680,074July...      ...	98	364,430	18	2,736	70	110,990	56	70,370	242	548,526August	90	328,688	5	242-	61	125,482	34	53,018	190	507,430   .September ...	77	191,512	7	245	63	112,451	17	28,815	164	333,023October	85	274,973	5	227	52	125,003	30	54,432	172	454,635November ...	63	173,228	3	87	40	81,015	21	29,647	127	283,977December ...	80	247,845	4	242	43	86,625	34	48,711	161	383,423 :Total for 11	1,131	3,554,245	196	19,553	682	1,170,502	660	1,058,515	2,669	5,797,815months										parative Statement of monthly losses.The figures for December are less satisfactory than those for November and September but compare favourably with the losses in all other months since the commencement of unrestricted Submarine Warfare.A comparison of the losses in the first and the second half of the year 1917 show that up Half-yearly to the end&apos; of June 1,798 merchant vessels with an aggregate tonnage of 3,641,676 (854 losses corn-vessels representing 2,138,790 tons being British) were sunk ; while in the second half of Pare(i-the year the losses were 1,056 vessels with an aggregate tonnage of 2,511,014 (535 vessels representing 1,584,455 tons being British).   The losses for the last quarter of: 1917 show a considerable improvement on any of the previous quarters.The following Table shows the average&apos; daily tonnage of British Merchant Vessels Daily aver-which was sunk or damaged by Enemy Action or which escaped from attack for each age of month since the unrestricted Submarine Warfare commenced, standardized by taking Bntlsn ton&quot; 100 as the daily average for February in each case :-- attackedMonth.	Sunk.	Damaged.	Escaped.	Total Attacks.February ......	100	.100	100	100March     .........	102.4	75.7	89.4	93 3April       .........	161.3	82.7	137.6	140.3^Iay     - - .....v	100.6	. .45.5. .	115.8	98.2June	123.8	109.5	167.2	138.2July	105.0	56.1	120.1	103.5August    ..........	94.7	32.4	.   75.1	77.7September        ......	57.2	82.7	49.8	58.1October   ...      ...	79.2	. 47.3	34.4	57.0November	51.6	76.8	38.2	50.2December.........	71.4	65.8	51.0	62.6ENEMY MINES.During the week under review enemy, minelaying activity has been confined to the Minelaying. Aberdeen area.  It appears that a submarine, after laying a group of mines well to seaward of Aberdeen, operated for a time in the vicinity with torpedo, and then laid the remainder of (C 893) A 2
her mines, close in shore, after the lapse of a period within which it might be expected that we should have diverted convoys in shore, in order to avoid the first group of mines. No British casualty resulted from the laying of these mines, but the Swedish s.s. &quot;Eriks-holm &quot; was sunk.Casualties.        The following table shows the number of enemy mines destroyed and British Vessels sunk by mine in Home Waters in recent weeks : Week Ended.	Number of Enemy-Mines Destroyed.	Number of British Mine-sweepers and Patrols Sunk by Mines.	Number of British Merchant Steamships Sunk by Mines.December 8th ...	46	1	115th...	47	Nil	322nd......	24	Nil	Nil29th......	64	1	2January 5th, 1918	35	Nil	NilConvoy.DEFENCE AGAINST SUBMARINE AND MINE.During the week 681 ships engaged in Overseas, Scandinavia-Lerwick-Humber and the French coal trades have been convoyed, as compared with 633 last week. Four vessels were lost, one on inward convoy (from Dakar) and three on outward convoys (one from Milford Haven and two from Falmouth).During the same period 176 ships were convoyed locally in the Mediterranean, four of which were sunk.Fourteen additional merchant vessels have been fitted to take primary armament, and 19 to take supplementary armament.The number of howitzers and bomb throwers delivered to date is 526.Mine pro- 1.116 merchant vessels have now been fitted with Otter equipment, and the numbertectiongear. 0f warships fitted with Paravanes is 353.Defensive armament.Merchant-menRaider.Warship con-struction.MOVEMENTS OF ENEMY SHIPS.Seven enemy merchant ships have this week arrived at, and 10 have sailed from, Norwegian ports outside the Cattegat.  None have entered or left Rotterdam.The sailing vessel &quot; Lutece,&quot; which was reported east of the Tonga group at the end of October, had worked northward and was about the middle of December some 400 miles south-east of Hawaii.UNITED KINGDOM SHIPBUILDING.The following is a statement of British warships and auxiliary vessels completed during 1917 : Description of Vessel.	Number.	Displacement		, Tons.Battleships       .........	1	25,750Special Cruisers............	2	37,700Light Cruisers   ...      ......	/.          7	29,050Elotilla Leaders.........	8	11,574Destroyers       ............	61	67,102Patrol Boats	29	18,911Submarines      .........	27	48,573Depot Ships      ............	1	3,460Seaplane Carriers        .........	2	6,370Sloops    ...      ............	21	26,745Minesweepers (Twin Screw)   ......	.....20	15,000Minesweepers (Tunnel) ...	4	- 1,160Oilers     ..........     ......	29	148,395Trawlers ...	141	77,491Drifters   ...      ......      ...	2	\ 360Tugs      ......      ...      ...      ...	...          1	1 690Coastal Motor Boats    ...      ...      ...	10	100Salvage Vessels..........	2	1,200Total        ......	...    . 368	519,631
21 48,089January ... &quot; &quot;&apos;      &quot;&apos;        31 79,451February... -                         43 118,699March    ... - &quot;&apos;                 36 69,711April      ... -      - - -                 28 69,773May       - -      - -                         30 109,847June      ... -      - - -      &quot;&quot;        37 83,073July      - -     - - -                29       &quot;    102,060August   ... ..-      - - -                 30 63,150September - -                          48 148,309October  ... -                                   36 158,826November ...      - -28 112,486December...      .......Total .........       397 1,163,474Taking the ton of warship displacement as equal to two gross tons, the aggregate gross tonnage of all vessels completed in the United Kingdom in 1917 is equivalent to 2,202,736, which is within 3^ per cent, of the corresponding figure reached in the record shipbuilding year of 1913.The following Statement shows the position of British merchant tonnage of 500 tons Gains andgross and upwards at 31st December, 1917, compared with 30th November, 1917 :      * losses inDecember,Tons (Gross).Tonnage of British Mercantile Marine at 30th November, 1917(including vessels under repair) ...      ...      ...    ....      ...      ....      ...      ...      ...     15,521,234Gains.New vessels (British built) entered for service    ...      ...... 111,906New vessels purchased Overseas   ............... 6,989Vessels transferred from Foreign Flag     ......      ...      ... 13,311Enemy vessels captured and entered for service under BritishFlag ^    ...     ...     .........     ......... -Vessels coming under British Flag for causes other than thosementioned above        ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 17,817Vessels discharged and ready for service after repairs (10 days ,and over)........................ 830,761--- 980,784Losses.Vessels sunk by Enemy action (including Service Vessels 3,268tons gross).........      ...      ......... 258,415Vessels sunk by Marine risk         ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 49,325Vessels transferred to Foreign Flag............      ... 5,897Vessels lost to British Flag for causes other than those mentionedabove     ......      ...      ...      ......      ...... 8,443Vessels laid up during month for repairs (10 days or over)or damaged and not yet ready for permanent repair       ... 1,651,8441,973,924993,140Tonnage of British Mercantile Marine available for service at 31stDecember, 1917       ......      ...      .........      ...............    14,528,094Add vessels under or waiting heavy repairs ...      ...      ...      ...      .........        821,083Total tonnage of British Mercantile Marine at 31st December, 1917        ...     .........    15,349,177Net Loss during month (including Service Vessels 3,268 tons gross)       ... (     172,057The corresponding figure for November was a net gain of 10,500 tons. Nearly all the factors tended to produce the adverse balance in December; the new tonnage entered for service, purchases overseas and transfers from Foreign flags are all down, while the sinkings by Enemy action and from ordinary risk are considerably increased.The following statement shows the number and gross tonnage of merchant steamships Merchantof 100 tons and upwards reported as completed during each month of 1917 :  vessel construction.No. of Vessels.   Gross Tonnage.
ENEMY WARSHIP CONSTRUCTION.The following table shows the position of new German Warship Construction and the numbers available at the present date : 	Building.					Available.									Number	Type.	Laid down since 1st Dec.	Launched since 1st Dec.	Total Number on the Slips.	Total Number launched.	Total number building.	Number added since 1st Dec.	lost or destroyed as ascer-tained since 1st Dec.	Total number avail-able.Battleships (Dread-nought type only) Battle Cruisers Light Cruisers, in-cluding Minelay-ing Cruisers Torpedo Bo at Destroyers Submarines	3 3 10	6 20	4* 2 lot 24 70	2 2 4 12 122	6 4 14 36 192	6 10	1 10	19 5 32 193 179-* One of these has previously been treated as a Battle Cruiser, and one has possibly not yet beenlaid down, f Number approximate.Austro- The position of Austro-Hungarian warship construction remains the same as indicatedHungarian. in the Appreciation for the week ended December 1st, except that one 3rd class battle-ship has been lost, reducing the number of this class of vessel to two.FOREIGN NAVAL INTELLIGENCE. Russia,The negotiations opened at Petrograd between Russian and German naval officers, to decide the armistice conditions in the Arctic and on the Murman coast, have been broken off, as the Germans refused to accede to the Russian proposals.On December 31st two German warships with Austrian and Turkish troops, accom-panied by submarines, were reported off Odessa, and a further report states that Turkish and Bulgarian naval delegates have arrived at Kief! with a proposal to obtain possession of the Black Sea Fleet and littoral.The Black Sea Fleet has again mutinied at Sevastopol, and it is reported that 60 officers have been murdered and many more arrested. .NAVAL STAFF,10th January, 1918.[Appbmdices.
&quot;    ... APPENDIX 1.Statement of Numbers and Tonnage op SAILINGS and LOSSES of British Merchant Steamships ov over 500 tons gross register forthe Week ended 5th January, 1918.Tbadb United Kingdom, to and from 	Sailings.						Losses.						Percentage of Losses to Sailings.						In. ..		Out.		Total.		-.. In.		Out.		Total.		In.		Out.		Total. ,		No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons. *	No.	Tons.	No.	Tona.North America Coast ... Gulf and West Indies ...      ...    -...... Gibraltar...      ...      ... Dakar, St. Vincent&apos;, W. Africa and S. America. Bay, Portugal and Spain, West of Gibraltar Scandinavia Holland..........&apos;.. Russia   .........      ......... Total Overseas Traffic to and from United Kingdom Coasting........ ...      ...      ....... Cross Channel   ......      ,,,      ...... Total of Coasting and Cross Channel Grand Total of traffic to and from United King lorn  .........           _________.............._____	40 12 14 13 15 9 11	233,766 79,184 47,711 62,934 32,745 14,323 14,025	51 14 51 16 11 17 2	306,500 79,363 207,417 74,952 25,878 24,738 2^258	91 26 65 29 26 26 13	540,266 158,547 255,128 137,886 58,623 39,061 . 16,283	1	7,308	1 1	2,711 3,207	1 1 1	2,711 - 7,308 3,207	7.14	15.32	1.96 9.09	.88 12.39	1.09 . 1.54 3.85	.50 2.87 5.47	114 106*	484.688 494,642*	162 93*	721,106 358,083*	276 199*	1,205,794 852,725*	1 4*	7,308 16,704*	2 7*	5,918 29,190*	3 11* 4 5	13,226 45,894* 12,001 18,108	.88 3.77*	1.51 3.38*	1.23 7.53*	.82 8.15*	1.09 5.53* J	1.09 5.38*	260	496,714	249	500,054	589 509	1,044,852 996,768	2	8,506	3	9,602			.77	1.71	1.20	1.92	.68 .98	1.15 1.82	 	V	 	-	1,098 961* 1,374 1,160*	2,041,620 1,891,122*		 		 	9 4* 12 15*	30,109 7,450*	 	 	 	  1	.82 .42*	1.47 .39*	 	-	- -	.&apos; k - 		3,247,414 2,743,847*	 	- -	 	   ;		43,335 53,344* 26,710 15,066*	 	 	 		.87 1.29*	1.33 1.94*	Losses on other Trades									-    :   5 !  4* i							&apos;2*:&apos;\k      &apos;	Total Losses for Week.........							 	 	 	i	17 19*	70,045 68,410*						Figurea for previous week.
APPENDIX II.Statement showing by Trades as regards British Merchant Steamships of over 500 tons &quot;gross the percentage of tonnage sunk by Enemy Action to tonnage sailing to and &apos;  from United Kingdom Ports in recent weeks.; . ; ,TradbUnited Kingdom, to and from Week ended 15th Dec.Week ended 22nd Dec.Week ended 29th Dec.North America Coast.........Gulf and West Indies     .........Gibraltar    ...    -......Dakar, West Africa and South America Bay, Portugal and Spain, West of GibraltarScandinavia...     .........Holland     ...      ............It US S1 &amp; ... - &quot; a a * a m * a * * **Total of above Trades        ...  .   ...Coasting    ......      ......Cross Channel      ............Total of all United Kingdom TradesTotal fin   ... 1 Out ... L Total4.63 3.04 3.864.23 2.9224.60 6.37.1.79 3.25 2.53.45.67 .344.11 1.545.501.28 4.19 2.02 2.993.15 1.973.09 .61 1.571.08.371.19 .55.8565 3918.97 6.01 3.9511.69 8.17 8.036.17 9.765.387.91 3.723.38 8.15 5.38.07 1.12 .31 .741.94Week ended 5th Jan., 1918..5015.32 2.8712.39 5.471.51 .82 1.0915 71 92 821.33APPENDIX ILLStatement of the number of British Merchant.Vessels sunk, damaged or molested, and Allied and Neutral vessels sunk, during weeks ended 29th December, 1917, and 5th January, 1918, according to areas._-____Area.Arctic and White Sea Atlantic (North) Atlantic (South) Bay of Biscay Gibraltar  Azores North Sea  ... English Channel Irish Sea and BristolChannel ... MediterraneanTotalsBritish.Sunk.1,600 tons and over.Week endedUnder 1,600 tons.Week endedCMoId a*-3145 4176 516Damaged or Molested but not Sunk.1,600 tons and over.Week endedOS CMd1-2Under 1,600 tons.Week endeda1-31.   !   --	11	14	23	31	310	1014Allied and Neutral.Sunk.1,600 tons and over.Under 1,600 tons.Week ended   Week endedOSo&quot;a1-5CMo&quot;ft1-53 1 21 22 21 1 13

</content>
</cab>
