<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/39/0 images: 582-588</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
$// His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government)Intelligence Bureau,Department of Information,S3CRET .ffw/021.^7E3XLY   report   on   france, XXI.(Jan, 17th, 1918)The political interest in France has turned during the last fortnight on three speeches, those of Mr. Lloyd George, Mr. Wilson and M. Pichon, and on one startling event, the arrest of M. Caillaux, which took place on Monday morning.This latter marks another stage in the great duel between M. Clemenoeau and M. Caillaux.     It seems to prove what some people had begun to be nervous about,  that M. Clemeneeau has much stronger evidence against Caillaux than appeared in General Dubail&apos;s letter read in the Chamber, which did not appear to be a very conclusive document, and indeed is already in part commonly discredited.    It is understood that the arrest was decided upon in consequence first, of discoveries made at the opening of a safe left by Caillaux in Florence and secondly, of information forwarded by the United States Government through Mr. Lansing.     Part of the latter has been pub-lished and appears to show that while in Argentina Caillaux intrigued with Count Luxburg, the German Minister, and attacked both England and the Government of France, while the Florence safe is said to have produced evidence of a plot to seize power in France.All these statements must as yet be received with reserve.   But one thing may be noted with satisfaction.     Both the safe at Florence and the documents from America are impartial witnesses.     The pre-vious statements about Caillaux&apos;s intrigues in Italy were all re-ceived in many quarters with a certain caution, because it was thought they might have emanated from M.Barrere and the.Embassy in Rome, which was known to be almost madly hostile to Caillaux.     The new facts then, are very reassuring for those who feared that Caillaux,
however morally guilty, might be able to secure a legal acquittal. The arrest, too, comes as a final proof of the courage which has given M. Clemenceau the strong position he undoubtedly holds in France.     A man who will arrest an ex-Prime Minister is plainly afraid of nothing, and nobody now can suspect that anybody is being screened or anything hushed up.     It is.true that Caillaux is very unpopular - so unpopular that even his own friend the Pays has to report that an officer told one of its staff that the soldiery all believed him guilty and would shoot him at sight if he visited the Army.     But he is still a political power and a dangerous man to drive to extremities:   and the country does honour to M. ClemenceauTs courage in shrinking from no risks.     Of course if he fails to prove his i ccusations he will be ruined, and with him nrobably something more than he or any man or party.    But for the moment the best in-forjsation is, that in spite of Socialist attacks, he has the immense majority of his countrymen behind him.     The onl  persons embarrassed by the arrest were the friends of Oaillaux who no longer show the confidence they seemed to feel after his speech;    and the majority in the Chamber (369 - 103) remained unshaken.-     Clemenoeau&apos;8   whole attitude - even his actual gestures and behaviour - &amp;re those of a nun who is conscious of his power and means to h. ve his own way. In the debate which arose on the arrest he disdained even to rise to reply to criticisms, merely making a few remarks from his seat. And e still more striking proof of his strength and of the ascendency he enjoys is the fact that not only did he carry by a very large majority his recent most unwelcome demand that a large number of men who had been released from the Army should be sent back to the colours:   but he did not think it necessary to flatter the Chamber into acquiescence or even to plead with it:   his speech was brief and trenchant, almost brutal:    &quot;the man are needed:    I must have them&quot;
the speech of a man who knows his mind tind is not afraid of his. responsibilities.     For the moment there can be little doubt that prenoe as c- whole feels towards hojn as towards a master who promises also to be a saviour of the State.GeorgeAs to the speeches of Mr. Lloyd/and Mr. Wilson they have both, particularly the former, had a very enthusiastic reception from all sections of French opinion.     They met the demand, alluded to in the last Report, for seething at onoe more precise and more in the nature of a manifesto of political principles than earlier speeohes, es-peoially that of M. Pichon on Dec. 87th.     The speeches of French statesmen are soarcely ever reported in full in the French news-papers.     It is therefore interesting to note that Mr. Lloyd 5?eorge&apos;s speech was given practically verbatim in several papers.     President Wilson was leds fully reported, but at least his fourteen points were printed everywhere.     Comment on both speeches was very favourable, the only reserve of importance being as to the language about Asujtria-Hungary.     Fears are expressed that the principle of government by the consent of the governed may be set aside or not fairly applied in the case of the Slav populations at present under Austrian and Hungarian rule.     The Debits broadly declares that gratitude, justioe and care for our own security alike demand that we should secure for these peoples a government by consent, and that no such government is possible except through their independence.     The Temps is much less uncompromising, but warns Austria that if Austrian troops ap-pear on the Western front the present moderate attitude of the Allies would not be likely to continue.     It also takes oocasion to point out an important correction in the text of Count Ozeminfs speech as quoted by Jlr. Lloyd George.     Mr. George quoted, him as saying &quot;it is not the indention of the Central Powers to rob of its independence any nation which has lost its political independence during the war&quot;.
** 4 -The Temps shows frots the German text that it is only political independence which Count Csernin promises to restore:   military or economio independence are passed over in what the Temps calls an &quot;eloquent silence&quot;.The French showed a little annoyance that it had fallen te 1HT* Wilson and Mr, Lloyd George and not to any Frenchman to set out the aims and principles of the Allies in a way that could not be mis-understood in Russia or even in the enemy countries.    The conse-quance was that a debate took plaoe in the Chamber on the reassembling of Parliament, when the Socialists raised the question of M. Clemenoeau!s refusal of passports for them to go to Petrograd, and M. Thomas expressed a strong desire for a new joint statement of the war aims of the Allies and, on being told by M. Pichon that he had proposed tjrat oourse to the Allies who had preferred to make separate statements, insisted that Franoe should press her Allies further on this subject.     It may be added that this demand is widely supported in the French Press.     M. Pichon then made a general declaration of policy saying that France was fighting for a just and lasting peace of whioh the three conditions were respect for treaties, self-determination and limitation of armaments..   But perhaps the most notable thing in his speech was the uncompromising vigour with which he denounced the Bolsheviks, whom he described as &quot;a usurping power&quot;.     He said that the question of passports was not a ouestion of principle but of expediency and that the Govern-ment could not accept the responsibility of allowing Frenchmen to proceed to Petrograd and enter into conversations with men who had &quot;behaved abominably to France and thrown over all their obligations to the Allies, to say nothing of their having grossly insulted the very Socialists who were so anxious to visit them and so confident of being able to influence them..     He declared himself still more
opposed to any International Conference, which he described as the policy of those who are working against the Allies in Russia and in truth a scheme of the enemy.It is plain that language of this sort - and he used much the same in his last speech - is far more outspoken in condemnation of the present rulers of Russia than anything that has been said by any rosponsible man in England or the United States.    And the same difference is observable between the attitude of the majority of French Socialists and that of those English politicians and writers who correspond to the Extreme Left in France.     There has been far less denunciation of the Bolsheviks in England.    Some of the most Radical papers, notably the Pays, were for some time conspicuous for their violence against Lenin and Trotsky, though there has been some change of late.     The principal reason of this contrast between the French and English attitude is of course that the French alliance with Russia is much older than ours and that French opinion natur-ally feels the enormity of the Russian betrayal too much to make any of the allowances which some Englishmen have made so generously. There is also a feeling which has more than once found expression, that the Bolsheviks by their separate peace, if they ultimately make one, and by their anarchical extravagances endanger the whole democratic cause and may provoke a general reaction throughout Europe.     In that spirit the Socialist Hununite remarked only ten days   go that Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s speeoh would do more good in Germrny than nil the Bolshevik leaflets, because the condition to which the Bolsheviks have reduced Russia does not encourage anyone to follor their example.The only other matter worth noticing is perhaps the gradually progressing split in the old Radical and Radical-Socialist party which Caillaux used to lead.     Its Committee lately ordered the
circulation of Caillaux&apos;s speech as a pamphlet, and in spite of a protest from a meeting of deputies belonging to the party, insisted on maintaining the order.    How an important Committee, known as the Mascuraud Committee (from the name of the Senator who has long been its Chairman), has unanimously decided to sever its connection with the Radical Executive.     This Committee represents oommeroial and agricultural interests, has considerable-interest in the pro-vinces, holds advanced Radical views, ond has long been affiliated to the Radical party.     Radical Prime Ministers have often made its banquets the occasions of important disclosures of policy.     Its break with the official Committee, ostensibly because that body &quot;concerned itself rather with persons than with principles&quot; is a sign of the times.     It means that many of the old Radical party, particularly in the -provinoes, are in no way inclined to join in the campaign against M. Clemenoeau:   on the contrary, as interested spectators of the grefct duel, they lean rather to him than to Caillaux And it also means that they are not inclined to be pushed in the Socialist direction as some of the Radical leaders in Paris would like to push them.     The same gradual scission is also at work in the Socialist party, as may be seen in the attack now being made on M.Thomas for his utterances in England, and especially for having doubted the practicability of a plebiscite in Alsace-Lorraine. This will no doubt come to nothing, as the more serious differences at the Bordeaux Congress came to nothing - Socialist party discipline ife much stronger than Radical.    But the leaven of disruption is certainly there:   and if and when the Socialists return to office it will make itself felt - and perhaps much sooner.One other thing.     The complaints about England not doing more for France still continue.     The Socialist Mayeras renewed the old demands in the Chamber a week ago with the old rhetoric about France
finding after the war no peace but that of death.     The Pays a fortnight ago had a very mischievous artiole about the duty of England &quot;the least tried of the Allies, with her immense population and wealth&quot; to give Prance &quot;so rich in sacrifice, so poor in men&quot; her full, absolute and equal support.    And the next day, in the course of a much censored article, it compared the French people to a magnificent bull in the arena, urged on to fight to its last gasp by &quot;innumerable spectators sitting at their ease&quot;.     The facts are of course very much the other way, but no serious criticisms of France ever appear in the English press;   and it is much to be re-gretted that such outrageous comparisons, as that of the bull and the arena, are allowed to be printed in France.    But they will con-tinue to be printed until some French statesman of authority has the courage to tell his countrymen the whole truth about their debt to England.

</content>
</cab>
