<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/39/0 images: 617-622</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property ofHis Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.)iiiiijiimi i ii iiii &quot;&quot; ii   in     ir 111 ii i i iiiii....... i   i i i&quot;i 11&apos; i     .......I       i   i       i     ii.............111 rum niTiimir iSEC RET.        460General Headquarters, British Forces in Italy, G. 852.13th January, 1918.TO -The Chief of the Imperial General Staff,&amp;ted In my communication to you of the 14th December,I described the general situation as being,  vhile not altogether free from anxiety, distinctly hopeful.2.  ,     During the past month, except for a very successful attack by the French in the vicinity of Mt. Tomba, there has been no action of any importance carried out on either side, and within the last few days there has been a fall of snow, not indeed sufficient to render operations in the mountains impossible, but enough to make them increasingly difficult, and to decrease the probability of any offensive on a large scale being attempted by the enemy in the immediate future,3.        As the snow hardens, however, there will probably be local actions on both sides and the Italians have such in course of preparation: it is important&apos; they should carry them out, so as to regain the power of initiative at any rate to a small extent.   The French attack, which was carried out with very small loss to themselves, has encouraged, the Italians by shewing them that with careful Artillery preparation and good organization an attack can be successful without heavy casualties, and if during the next few weeks they can carry out one or two minor offensive actions with comparatively few losses they will have made a considerable advance.   At present some of their leaders hesitate to attempt such operations for fear of the casualties which theybelieve
believe to Toe inevitable.4.        The positions which our troops occupy with the R* Piave in their front preclude any minor offensive operation on our part such as was carried out by the French, but we have carried out some small raids successfully and our example has been followed by the Italians in other parts of the river sector.5.        In conjunction with the French and Italians we have prepared lines of defence on the foothills south of the range of mountains to be occupied if necessary by the troops of the two &quot;groups&quot; referred to in my communication of the 14th December.   In constructing these defences we have endeavoured to illustrate the principles of defence which we found from previous experience to be most effective, which differ in many material points from the methods hitherto adopted by the Italians.     The Italian Commanders whose troops have been detailed to occupy these positions and others who have visited them have agreed to the advantages which they have over their own system.6,        Similarly in the sectors of the front lines which we hold we have organised our defences very carefully so as to bring prominently to notice the value of a defence in depth and the wastefulness and folly of depending on single defensive lines into which all men, machine-guns, etc., are crowded.This sector has been frequently visited by Italian officers and the results are becoming apparent in improvements which are being effected in other parts of the line.   Already their front lines are being thinned and their reliefs properly organised, and they have taken up our system of the employment of machine-guns both for defence and offence,
7.       All our Artillery not required for the defence of our own line Is being used to assist the Italians.     A mobile reserve is being formed which will move to different parts of the line and co-operate with Italian Artillery.     It is hoped thereby to effect some improvement in their counter-battery work which at present is far from satisfactory.8.        Our R.F.C.. have set a very fine example.     Their record so far is excellent and in addition to our own front we have rendered the Italians help on many occasions.The Italians have plenty of A.A. guns and searchlights but lack co-ordination.     We are helping to get system into this matter, which should prove of value in defence of their towns.9.        We found that the higher commanders and staffs were not sufficiently in touch with the conditions in front and that there was not sufficient sympathy betv/een the front and rear authorities, which resulted in orders being issued which were not, and could not be, carried out.We have staff officers visiting all parts of the Italian lines daily, who have been very well received and who discuss matters with the Divisional, Brigade and Battalion Commanders and Staffs, throwing out suggestions as to laying out defences, machine gun arrangements, wiring, reliefs, defence In depth, etc., and our Corps and Divisional Commanders and their Staffs do the same.Consequently Italian Commanders and Staffs now visit their lines much more frequently and they have asked for copies of notes and suggestions made by our officers after their visits and have asked us for any Notes br Hints on Training which we will give them.I have
- - maskI&quot;have issued certain Instructions on the princi-ples of defence, etc., for our own troops, copies of which the Italians have asked for and received in large numbers.Similarly all our General Staff publications and lessons we learnt in France are being translated into Italian for Issue and we have just given them all the detail of machine gun barrages and a demonstration is now being arranged10. &apos;&quot;re are starting our Sch&amp;ols in a few days, whichcomprise the following :-G.H.Q. School.    Army T/ing.   For training Company Commanders &amp; Platoon Sergeants.2 Corps Schools. 2 Corps Reinforcement Camps. Signalling School. Musketry School.Sniping, Observation and Scouting School.Gas School.Artillery School.Trench Mortar School.Engineering Course.C. 0s! Course.All the above are being formed within a comparatively small area so that they can all be easily visited by the Italians.rre are also arranging in conjunction with the French and Italians for officers to go through courses at each other1s schools, which must have a beneficial effect.When the schools are established we hope to carry out demonstrations which will be of value to all.
mask was not proof and that they did not realise the seriousness of the situation.Muoh progress has been made in this matter and I am glad to say it is now being taken up seriously and we have offered to help In the training and instruction. 800,000 British masks have,- I understand, been asked for, of which 300,000 have been received.The Director of Italian Gas Services is visiting London next week.12. The organization of Intelligence work has not beeneasy.   The Italians had practically no regulations for the control of civil population, contre-espionage,&apos; censorship, etc.     They have now agreed to certain proposals which I think should work satisfactorily though they are not as rigid as those we had in France.13. All branches of our Staffs are working in veryclose relation and I think it may generally be said that a better system and better methods appear daily.14. In all these matters, however, it has been andstill is necessary to proceed very quietly and cautiously.The Italians are very proud and sensitive and although they deplore the behaviour of the 2nd Army they do not consider that there is much wrong with the remainder, and though they are willing to profit by our experienoe any attempt to force ourselves and our methods on them would result in nothing being done.I have issued instructions to all our officers that they are to be most careful to avoid any appearance of superiority or of imparting instruction.   Everything is to bedone
done by illustration and demonstration, and these instructions are being, I know, carried out.The most serious defect is their inattention to the serious training of the troops and their failure to appreciate the necessity for it.       It is a matter which is obviously of vital importance if the Italian Army is to attain a standard of fighting efficiency high enough to ensure success, and we hope to get the Italian Commanders to realise it.(Sd.) Herbert Plumer.General,Commanding British Forces in Italy

</content>
</cab>
