<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/39/0 images: 641-654</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
_____......j/\/   g\m  f* (This Document is the Property of      ^    a\His Britannic Majesty&apos;3 Government.) SECRET..  ,        ministry  of  food.482rt for Week eliding Wednesday, January 16, 1918.PART I. ACTION TAKEN. Control of Supplies and Prices.Allied Purchases.-Negotiations have been conducted by the Treasury and the Ministry of Food Avith Mr. Crosby and with the United States Treasury with a view-to arranging finance required for the purchase of the additional 35,000 tons of frozen meat, which Mr. Owen Smith estimates are available, and the 150,000,000 pounds of pork products, which Mr. Hoover is now in a position to export, and which were the subject of cablegrams contained in last week&apos;s Report.Lord Rhondda has cabled to Mr. Hoover as follows : &quot; Unless you are able to send the Allies at least seventy-five million bushels of wheat over and above what you have exported up to January first and in addition to ihe total exportable surplus from Canada I cannot take the responsibility of assuring our people that there will be food enough to win the war. Imperative necessity compels me to cable you in this blunt way. No one knows better than I that the American people, regardless of national and individual sacrifice, have so far refused nothing that is needed for the Avar, but it now lies Avith America to decide whether or not the Allies in Europe shall have enough bread to hold out until the United States is able to throw its force into the field. I have not minced Avords because I am convinced that the American people if they knoAv the truth will not hesitate to - meet the emergency.&quot;. ,.: Mr. Owen Smith cables that up to the 29th of December his total commitments on Government account for meats, fats, oleo oil, neutral lard, and dried fruits amounted to 85,844,000 dollars... Allotments bave been received from the United States Food Administration of 24,820,000 pounds of frozen beef for delivery up to 28th February, and contracts have been closed in Canada for 1,929,445 pounds of frozen beef.As there is a probability of supplies of butter being available in Siberia during the coming season, inquiry is being made as to the possibility of the United States and Canada releasing large quantities of butter from their East Coast for shipment to this country in the event of similar shipments being made from Vladivostok to the West Coasts of the United States and Canada.Mr. Owen Smith has been instructed that in the event of shipping space bein^ available for articles of food of secondary importance, the folloAving is the order of priority: -(1) Canned fish. (2) Dried fruit, (3) Eggs. (4) Canned fruit. (5) Dried fish.Bacon, Hams and Lard. The position in regard to these commodities is uoav very serious. On account of the extremely small December shipments the January arrivals will, it is anticipated, be about 10,000 tons, Avhich is less than the full requirements of the Army alone for one month. The latest completed Monthly Returns, however, show that home production was.slightly in excess of the amount which this -Ministry on other data had anticipated for the rjeriod. It is -proposed if on further examination by this Ministry and the Military Authorities it proves practi-cable, to requisition some home produced supplies for the Army, in order to release some of the imports for distribution for civilian consumption.The cause of the shortage is not quite clear ; six large liners leaving the United States of America between..the.12th. December, 1917J and the 9th January, 1918 carried only 760 tons of bacon, hams and lard altogether.
Preliminary proposals for the control of home produced supplies have been formulated, and a Conference with the bacon curers has been arranged for the 18th January, 1918.A deputation of wholesalers has been received to consider further control of the price of cooked hams.Butter and Cheese. A further purchase of nearly 250 tons of butter has-been made in the United States of America by the Inter-Allied Meat and Fats Executive Mission; approximately, the total so purchased is now 1,450 tons. The price is 44 cents per lb., f.a.s. in New York.The current prices for Dutch, cheese have been extended for the present, but will be reviewed by the Food Controller about the 31st March, 1918.CereaLs. Arrangements have been completed by which the Wheat Export Co. shall allocate to shippers the shipment of cereals from the United States to British West Africa and West Indian Colonies as licensed by the United States Food Administration.The Wheat Export Co. have been instructed to hold 30,000 tons of wheat at the disposal of. the Swiss Government for January loading pending a final decision as to the arrangements for future supply of that country.The Wheat Export Co. have been instructed to furnish 50,000 tons of wheat monthly to the Commission for Relief in Belgium, and the American Food Admini-stration have increased the monthly allocation of cereals to the Wheat Export Co. by a like quantity.The RovalCommission have secured 10,000 tons of Irish oats. &quot;&apos;&apos; &quot; It has been decided to. fix a maximum price of Ad. per lb. for Burma rice and (id. per lb. for all other rices, a condition of sale being- that the better quality rice should not be offered unless the cheaper rice was also on sale. &apos;.&apos;In order to encourage the use of potatoes in bread the limit of 121 per cent, admixture of potatoes has been removed, ;and a communication has been issued to the Press informing the trade that the Ministry of Food is likely to issue an Order making the use of potatoes in bread compulsory. Priority certificates have been alreadj^ secured for 3,700 machines, half of which have already been sold.The Wheat (Seed) Order, 1918, dated 10 January ,191,8, is designed to ensure farmers obtaining a. plentiful supply of suitable seed wheat for the extensive spring sowing that is anticipated. Until further notice no person in any part of the United Kingdom may use for purposes other than seed any wheat of the varieties White Marvel, Red Marvel, and April Bearded grown in the British Islands, or in Ireland the variety known as Red Fife. While the restriction is in force no one may buy or acquire wheat of. these varieties unless he ordinarily deals in them and obtains them for re-sale as seed, or requires them for the purpose of seed. Holders of stocks may not dispose of them except to persons coming in the above categories.The Order does not apply to wheat which . shall be determined to be unfit for seed by any person authorised by the Food Controller or by any of the three Departments of.Agriculture.Meat-fhe Sheep (Sales) Order, 1918, dated January 15th, 1918, has been issued, requiring all sheep for slaughter to be sold and bought in a market, and to be valued at a market, or some other authorised collecting centre, by a Valuation Committee appointed by the Area Live Stock Commissioner, or by a person authorised to grade in their place. The value of the sheep is to be ascertained on the basis of the dressed weight of the carcase as estimated by the Valuation Committee and assessed at the rate of Is. 2\d. per lb., including the offals ; the worth of the skin is to be taken at its current, market value. The owner of. the sheep will have the option of selling the sheep at the same rate on the actual deadweight based to be ascertained within 12 hours after slaughter. In this case the sheep must be sent to a special Govern-ment depot, where it will be slaughtered at an authorised Government slaughterhouse. The auctioneer members of Valuation Committees and Wholesale Meat Supply Associations may appoint a limited number of sheep dealers to act as agents, at a remuneration of not more than 9d. per head, plus costs. As in the case of cattle, a &quot;per head&quot; charge on every sheep sold for slaughter will be received by the Government authorised agent; this charge of 5s. will cover auctioneer^ charges, market tolls, valuation, railage, slaughtering charges, droving from market to railway and from railway to slaughterhouse, and various other expenses. Of this sum, Is. Qd. Will be deducted from the farmer&apos;s price, and 3s. 6d. will be paid by the buyer to the Government authorised agent.   In order to cover this charge on the buyer; a licence
lias been issued increasing the maximum wholesale price of mutton and lamb of Qd. per stone.The Edible Offals (Maximum Price) Order limits the wholesale and retail prices of home-killed and imported offals; where offals are sold by wholesale, delivery is included, and in the case of retail sale no additional charge may be made for packages or for giving credit or making delivery.The Meat (Retailers&apos; Restriction) Order prohibits any retail butcher from purchasing in any one week a greater number of cattle or quantity of meat than is prescribed in his case for that week under the authority of the Food Controller. Similarly, he cannot sell by retail in any week a greater quantity of meat than may be so prescribed. The Food Controller may thus revise the butcher&apos;s quota from week to week. During the next few weeks the butchers are being restricted to 50 per cent, of their October standard.Milk. The Milk (Registration of Dealers) Order, 1918, dated 8th January 1918, prohibits any person, other than a producer, from dealing in milk after February 9th, 1918, unless he holds, or has applied for, a licence from the Food Controller autho-rising him to do so. The Order also prohibits any person from dealing in milk by retail after February 23rd, 1918, unless he holds a certificate of registration granted by his Local Food Control Committee.Sugar. The situation as regards provision of tonnage remains very unsatisfactory in the West as well as in the East.Negotiations for the handling of Government-bought tea are still pro-ceeding. Outstanding points have been practically settled with the English Wholesale Distributing Trades both in London and the Provinces. A few questions still await settlement with the Scottish and Irish wholesalers.The question of permitting for Government-bought tea in Ireland a higher price than the uniform price fixed for Great Britain is being considered by this Ministry and the Food Control Committee for Ireland.        .It is not thought that there will be serious opposition to the policy of having a single grade of tea.Owing to the great congestion at the Liverpool Docks it is not certain that the wholesale distribution of Government-bought tea can begin at the beginning of February as had been anticipated. Five ships carrying tea entered Liverpool though this Ministry had tried to arrange that two or three should go to Manchester. The weather is hampering the handling of tea at the docks, but an effort is being made to secure the assistance of military labour.Transport and Cold Storage. In the House of Commons on January 16th, Mr. Clynes stated that at the outbreak of war the approximate amount of refrigerated space and various cold-air stores throughout the United Kingdom was estimated at 28,000,000 cubic feet net, and that this had recently been increased hy approximately 3,500,000 cubic feet. The estimated amount of further increase expected during the first half of the current year was 6,100,000.. . Local Authorities.Reports generally still show that a serious shortage of meat, margarine, tea, and cheese, exists.The rationing of meat supplies by reference to the October quotas is said to work out unfairly in some places, eg., in Edinburgh, owing to the number of soldiers and American sailors on leave in the city.In the Newcastle area the trouble arising from a shortage of beer is again pointed out, and it is suggested that the difficulty be met by the allocation of larger supplies for the consumption of working men. The Commissioner for the Home Counties Division reports that the question of supply needs careful watching, otherwise strikes and riots may result, The shortage of meat in certain parts of Scotland is referred to by the Commissioner for the Eastern Division as amounting to a meat famine.Distribution. A new section of the Ministry of Food has been formed for the purpose.of dealing with local schemes of distribution. It is now fully occupied in examining the details of submitted schemes, in grouping related areas and sanctioning any proposal which promises to restore some degree of normal and equitable distribution.
The following is a list of the most important grouped areas, for. which schemes-are in an advanced stage of preparation : (1) London and the Home Counties, aggregating districts with a population equal to nearly one-third of the country.(2) South West Midlands, with Birmingham as a centre. (3) The Tyneside District, with Newcastle as a centre. (4) The Cleveland District, with Middlesbrough as a centre. (5) North East Derbyshire, with Chesterfield as a centre.Proposals will shortly be submitted to the Ministry for the adoption of similar groups for the Manchester and Salford, Mersey side, Glasgow, South Wales, Teesdale and other large individual areas.Local schemes, which will probably rapidly develop into area schemes, are working or are about to come into operation at Sheffield, Leicester, Derby, Halifax, Nottingham, Rochdale, the Hartlepools, Peterborough, Reading, Bath, Cambridge and other places.Every scheme submitted includes butter and margarine in its proposed rationed foodstuffs ; other articles proposed to be included by particular districts are tea, meat, bacon, cheese and lard.Enforcement.The following cases of special interest have occurred during the week : -At Dublin, Messrs. W. L. Ryan &amp; Co., Ltd., Wholesale Tea Merchants, were charged with having on the 3rd October sold, by traveller, 125 lbs. tea, at 4s. Qd. per lb., and also 122 lbs. of tea at the same price on another occasion.   A fine of 10Z. in each of the two cases was imposed.Messrs. Regan &amp; Co., Ltd., were also fined 20Z. for selling 247 lbs. of tea at &amp;d. per lb. in excess of maximum.At the Penge Police Court, Charles Powell, licensee of the Palace Brewery, Anerley, and John K. Powell, a partner, were summoned for breAving 282 barrels of beer in excess for the quarter ended June 30th last, and 333 barrels of beer in excess for the quarter ended September 30th. H. Spurrier, manager, Avas summoned for aiding and abetting.The two partners were each fined 501. on each summons, making 2001. in all, AArith 25 guineas costs.   The manager AA^as fined 101. on each summons.At the Marylebone Police Court, the Author&apos;s Hotel, Ltd., proprietors of the Wigmore Hotel, in Lower Seymour Street, Port-man Square, and Reginald Harris, the managing director of the hotel, were fined 30L with 3 guineas costs, a total of 66L 6s., for failing to keep a register of meals and food as required by the Public Meals Order.At Conway the Star Tea Company were fined IL for selling \ lb. of coffee above the fixed price through their local manager.At Newcastle Borough Police Court, Mr. Frederick Harrison, Headmaster of Newcastle High School, was summoned for unlawfully acquiring sugar, on six occasions, in excess of the quantity required for ordinary consumption in his household.   A fine of 501., with 201. costs, AAras imposed.At Ingleton Petty Sessions, John Henry Gorril, Bentham, A\ras fined 101. and 1Z. 11s. costs for having 1 lb. 11 ozs. of bread in the swill tub.At Merthyr, Messrs. Wm. Harris Avere fined 501. for buying butter from the Lakelands Dairy Co., Ireland, at a price exceeding the maximum.At Marlborough Police Court, Messrs. Selfridge &amp; Co., Ltd., were fined 10Z. and 21. costs for selling &quot;Blue Band&quot; margarine at a price exceeding the maximum.
PART II.-SUMMARY OF THE&quot;FOOD POSITION,The two most prominent features recorded in the following paragraphs and the tables are the alteration in the rate of - consumption of bread and flour during the four weeks ended January 5th, and the figures relating to the supply and consumption of meat from the beginning of December or more generally from September onward.The former is dealt with below, where it is pointed out that the decrease in the rate of consumption as compared with that of the previous period amounts to 3^ per cent., but that in the corresponding period of last winter there was a decrease of 7 per cent.; under the circumstances it would be incorrect to assame that the decrease in the four weeks which ended January 5th, 1918, points to a decline in consumption which is likely to continue. The special circumstances of Christmas time appear to offer some explanation.Allusion was made in previous Reports to the nature of the scarcity in the meat supply. The account.now given suggests some improvement, but it must be pointed out that the temporary remedy, namely, the increase in the sheep coming into market, may lead to stibsequent reaction and to some reduction in the future supplies of mutton. The history of the movement which has now assumed an acute phase can be traced in the returns from slaughterhouses (Table D), and the market records of previous months (Table 0), which combine to show the heavy pressure on the supply of home-fed meat.   This was accentuated by recent circumstances set out last week.Imports.The aggregate weight of imports of principal foods (including rice and tea) was 135,000 tons in the week ending January 12th (Table A), as compared with 142,000 tons in the corresponding week last year. Though this is less than last week, it is -21,000 tons more than the average of the previous fortnight, and 17,000 tons more than the average of the previous four weeks.The imports of wheat and.flour, meat, bacon, &amp;c, cheese, sugar and tea did not differ much from the average of the previous four weeks.As compared with the corresponding week last year, sugar shows an increase of 3,200 tons, bacon and hams a decrease of 2,400 tons and cheese a decrease of 1,600 tons ; the quantities of wdieat and flour, meat and tea were nearly the same in the second weeks of 1917 and 1918.Oereals other than wheat show considerable, variations : Thousand tons.. Barle3r.			Oats.                      Maize. i				Rice.		1910-17.	1917-18.	1916-17.	1917-18.	1916-17.	1917-18.	1910-17. .	1917-18.-. 1&apos;   - --...... 4 weeks ended Sept. 29	77	25	-68	123	171	72		424 weeks ended Oct. 27	64	43	37	57	195	23		514 weeks ended Nov. 24	30	78	21	36	185	12	_	504 weeks ended Dec. 22	35	38	4	9	170	62	_	72 weeks ended Jan. 5	20	17	7 .	8	63	17	_	5 22Week ended Jan. 12 -	5	2	2	2	25	5	-	Total 19 weeks  -	231	203	139	235	809	191	68	177			_____________				(approx.)	^ The diminution in the importation of maize and the increase of rice should be noticed. The low importation of the former affects the supply of feeding stuffs for animals.Consumption.Meat. The supplies of home-fed meat at four principal meat markets (Table B) for the week ended January 5th were 16 per cent, less than in the previous week and 37 per cent, below those of the corresponding week last year. At Smithfield in the week ended January 12th there was an improvement, but the supply was still 30 per cent, below last year.The supply of fat cattle at 59 markets, though 6 per cent, better than the week before (the. first to which the new Order applied), was only 28 per cent, of the supplya   4703-3 10
last year (Table C). As a partial compensation the supply of sheep was abnormally great and 5.2 per cent, above last year. The actual excess was 36,900 sheep, while the defect of cattle was 12,100 battle.The supply of pigs at these markets no longer affords a good indication of the general supply, and the: figures from the slaughter-house returns are used in the&apos; place of ihe market returns for pigs in. computing the index-numbers of consumption in Table E. . The supply of- imported meat at four principal-markets (Table B) in the week ended January 5th was 990 tons more than in the previous week, and 10 per cent:; above the average for December, 1917, but the aggregate supply of home-fed and imported meat was 38 per cent, below last year. An improvement of 260 tons imported meat is reported at Smithfield in the week ended January 12th. -Bread and Flour.-The returns of flour Used or sold by bakers and retailers for the four weeks ended January 5th are nearly complete. They show a reduction of SI- per cent, over the previous four weeks, but an increase of 2 per cent, over the corre-sponding weeks a year ago (Table E). Last year the reduction in the period covering Christmas was 7 per cent. The reduction both years is no doubt due to increased consumption of other foods at Christmas time; this year other foods were not available in their usual quantities, and it is reasonable to assume that less bread and flour were saved from this cause. The saving this year was one days&apos; consumption; last year it was two days&apos;. In addition to the seasonal change the shortage of meat; margarine and butter occurred during the four weeks in question, and it is remarkable that the increase in the consumption of flour over last year should have been so small.For these reasons the index-numbers for these weeks should not be considered as indicating the commencement of a downward trend in consumption.Table L shows that the movement has not been uniform throughout the country. In particular, in the Home Counties and the South Midlands the reduction in consumption of bread between the four weeks to December 8th and the four to January 6th has been very slight, perhaps because of a more acute shortage of other foods in this part of England than elsewhere.The following table shows the position of bakers&quot;&apos; and retailers&apos; stocks.	Four Weeks&apos; Consumption to Jan. 5th, 1918.	Stocks, Jan. nth, 1918.	Number of Weeks&apos; Consumption   -held in Stock.	Corresponding Figures Four-   Weeks earlier? VY/orks., Lanes., and North of England -Rest of England and Wales Scotland   -      -      -	Sacks. 223,319 374.254 103,573	Sacks. 92,285 164,732 102.486	-    &apos; 1-6     &apos; 1-8 4-0	&apos; ;     1-6 1-8 3-3Ireland     -      -      -      --	82,477	33,032	1-6	2-0Total      -	783,623	392,535	2-0	1 -9The change in four weeks has been very slight in the aggregate.Wholesale Prices. &apos;-&apos; 1Except that the price of English mutton has advanced 2s. Gd. a cwt, followfng the increase of As. 6d. in the price of English beef recorded last week and that oitl rose 1 s. Ad. per quarter, there are no changes to report.
Table A. Imports of Principal Food and Feeding- Stuffs.				Average Weekly Net Imports* in 1913.	Average Weekly Imports.		Total Imports.	Article.	Week ending January 12th, 1918.	Week ending January 5th, 1918.	Week ending January 13th, 1917.		2 Weeks from Dec. 30th, 1917, to Jan. 12th. 1918.	Corres-ponding Period, 1917.	2 Weeks from Dec. 30th, 1917, to Jan. 12th, 1918.	Corres-ponding Period. 1917-1.		3.	i.	5.	6.	7,	8.	9.&quot;1. Wheat 2. Wheaten flour 3. Beef   (fresh, refrigerated and frozen). 4. Mutton (fresh, refrigerated and frozen). 5, Meat, unenu-merated (re-frigerated and     pre-served). 6. Bacon -7. Hams -8. Lard   -9. Margarine 10. Cheese 11. Butter -12. Sugar (refined and      un-refined). 13. Sugar, glucose	Tons. 39,390 20,635 14,890 1,514 2,962 4,363 624 467 106 1,298 93 23,134 460	Tons. 52,805 23,075 12,099 1,337 2,359 4,436 533 123 2,391 2,209 1,836 21,361 747	Tons. 50,560 7,360 14,910 1,945 2,524 6,454 957 1,118 3,403 2,914 3,967 1.9,936 252	tons. 101,378 9,712 8,849 5,125 2,126 1 5,267 1,629 1,460 2,137 3,867 37,333 1,408	Tons. 46,097 21,855 3,494 1,426 2,660 j   4,400 \     578 295 1,249 1,753 965 22,247 604	Tons. 62,762 7,773 4,598 1,713 2,937 8,217 1,112 1,330 2,967 2,908 3,422 23,739 291	Tous. 92,195 43,710 6,988 2,851 5,321 8,799 1,157 590 2,497 3,506 1,930 44,494 1,208	Tons. 125,525 15,545 9,197 3,425 . 5,874 .  16,434 2,225 2,659 5,934 5,817 6,844 47,477 582Total	99,936	115,311	106,300	180,291	107,623	123,769	215,246	247,53814. Barley -15. Oats    -38. Maize -	1,995 2,300 5,145	10,245 8,395 9,040	4,890 2,410 24,525	21,565 17,464 46,450	6,120 5,347 7,093	8,902 2,968 29,580	12,240 10,695 14,185	17.805 5,935 59,160Total	9,440	27,680	31,825	85,419	18,560	41,450	37,120	82,900All principal foods and feeding stuffs.	109,376	142,991	138,125	265,770	126,183	165,219	252,366	330,43817, Rice   -18. Tea    -	21,811 3,727	63 4,342	3,543	2,554 2,640	4,034	3,123	8,069	6,246	Net Imports.*			Average Monthly Net Imports* in 1913.	Average Monthly Net Imports. *		Total Net Imports.*		Month ending Dec. 31st, 1917.	Month ending Nov. 30th, 1917.	Month ending Dec. 31st, 1916.		12 Months Jan.-Dec., 1917.	Corres-ponding Period, 1916.	12 Months Jan-Dec, 1917.	Corres-ponding Period, 1916.19. Oil seeds and nuts and kernels. 20. Oilseed cake	Tons. 53,444 4,735	Tons. 62,855 20,679	Tons. 94,412 17,295	Tons. 120,314 29,436	Tons. 80,009 18,567	Tons. 110,588 23,204	Tons. 960,109 212,807	Tons. 1,327,054 278,445* Imports less re-exports of Foreign and Colonial Produce and less exports of British Produce of the same kind, f Including certain importations made in previous weeks, particulars of which could not lie given at the time.
Table B. Statistics illustrating Consumption of Meat.- - ^ . .   . . --- .     - , ... -   &apos; i    \-     ^^^-v&apos; Tons.Average weekly supplies during June and July 1913 :  ^   -Central Market, London   -        -        -        - ------- 8,245.....Manchester Market ....... -    -    -   -         - -       855Glasgow Market   -        -        -        -        - -       798Liverpool Market -        -        -        -        - -       221Total        -        -   10,11.9Supplies of Meat entering the Central Market, London, and Manchester, Glasgow, and Liverpool Markets.Period.;	Home-fed.		Foreign.		Home and Foreign.		Weekly Average.		Weekly Average.		Weekly Average.		1916.	1917.	1916.	1917.	1916.	1917.January  ------February -      -      -      -March     -      -April      -      -May       .      .      .      -      -J une.      -      -      -      -      -July.       -      -      -      -August   -      -      -      -      -September      -      -      -      -October   -      -November       -December -	Tons. 5,629 4,863 4,756 4,215 3,720 3,452 3,371 3,584 4,406 5,288 5,422 5,095	Tons. 4,401 4,422 4,546 4,211 3,919 3,369 3,345 4,396 4,844 5,670 5,656 4,702	Tons. 3,851 4,143 3,460 3,519 3,268 3,939 3,775 3.334 3,576 3,618 3,426 3,306	Tons. 4,279 2,977 2,971 2,957 2,537 2,986 2,844 2,350 2,300 2,197 1,825 2,099	Tons. 9,480 9,006 8,216 7,734 6,988 7,391 7,146    -6,918 7,982 8,906 8,848   -8,401	Tons. 8.680 7,399 7,517 7,168 6,456 6,355 6,189 6,746 7,144 7,867 7,481 6,801	1917.	1918.	1917.	-1918.	1917.	1918.Week ended :						5th January	4,496	2,811	3,764	2,317	8,260	5,128Table C-Supplies of Fat Stock at 59 Markets in Great Britain.		Fat Cattle.		Fat Sheep.		Fat Pigs.	Period.		Weekly Average, 1916.	Weekly Average, 1917.	Weekly Average, 1916. &apos;	&apos; Weekly Average, 1917.	Weekly Average, 1916.	Weekly Average, 1917.January  -February -      -      -March     -April      -     -     -May       -     -     ;-June      -July August   -      -      -September October   -November December		18,509 &apos; 18,292 19,232 18,347 18,123 16,944 14,487 15,864 16,222 16,981 16,118 13,954	16,234&apos; 17,259 18,184 17,479 18,201 14,642 15,672 16,424 16,728 18,134 16,613 13,735	68,923 65,729 66,126 73,590 70,026 77,721 68,848 81,857 75,425 68,676 61,673 51,246	64,462 58,630 66,454 63,260 60,014 61,777 71,896 78,228 74,452 78,688 -72,727 63,824	17,329 14,140 13,607 14,915 12,658 11,666 10,283 9;995 12,474 13,602 15,035 13,673	14,283 11,722 11,562 11,777 11,637 10,789 8,689 8,953 7,781 9,058 8,041 3,920		1917.	1918.	1917.	1918.	1917.	1918.Week ended :							9th January -	-                  m	16,760	4,625	70,476	107,330	16,198	3,603
Table D.--Animals Slaughtered in 8,035 Private and Public Slaughterhouses in Great Britain in December 1916 and November and December 1917.--	Cattle.	Calves.	Sheep and Lambs.	Pigs.	84,715 91,911 96,368	6,498 9,903 8,374	266,793 362,399 312,157	174,782 104.757 116,271Percentage Increase or Decrease : December 1917 compared with December 1916   -	4-14-0.%	-f28&apos;9%	4-17-0%	-33-5%December 1917 compared with November 1917  -	+ 5-1%	-15-4%	-13-9%	4-11-0%Index Numbers of Animals Slaughtered (measured as percentages of the levels of September 1917).--	Cattle.	[Calves.	Sheep and Lambs.	Pigs.1916. September ------	961	731	921	134October    -      -      -      -      -      -	102	77	84&quot;	1541November -	.   104	751	781	161December*	106	64	74	1831917. September-      -      -      -      -      -	100	100	100	100October    ------	1151	1061	104	112November ------	115	97	101	1091December *       -	1201	821	87	121$* Preliminary figures.
Table E. Index Numbersv of Consumption . of Bread, Meat, and Provisions.Retail Consumption of bbead and flour (measured as percentages of the level of May 1917),1916-7.(4 weeks ended)-March 31st-April 28th -May 26th  -June 23rd -July 21st   -August 18th September 15th October 13th November 10th December 8th January 5 th99 10097i99&quot;959495i98&quot; 101i94i1917-8.109 104 1009591189190i (92) 97 &quot;(96)100100 96iThe numbers in brackets are adjusted for the probable change in the stock of flour held at home before and after the reduction in price on September 17th.Consumption of Meat (measured as percentages of the levels of May 1917).	Home Fed. Fat Stock at 59 Markets in Great Britain.		Foreign. Central and Three Provincial Meat Markets.		Home and Foreign. Index Numbers combined.		1910.	1917.	1916.	1917.	1916	1917. -March     -      -      -      -	108	102	136	117	116	107April -------	109	99	139	117	118	104May        -      -      -      -	104	100	129	100	112	100June       -      -	102	87	155	118	118	96July	88	92	149 &apos;	112	106	98August    -      - . .  -September              -	98	98	131	93	108	97	99	97	141	91	112	95October   -      -      -	99	104	143	85	112	981November -	961	951	135	72	108	90December -      -      -      -	82	78&quot;	130	821	96	79iConsumption of Pjrovisions, based on returns from multiple shops and co-operative societies (measured as percentages of the levels of October 1917).	Butter.	Margarine.	Lard.	Bacon.	Hams.	Cheese.(4 weeks ended) 						September 2nd, 1916 -	213	 	85	179	119	146September 30th, 1916 -	207	 	85	166	110	140October 28th, 1916    -	194	 	85	160	114	140November 25th, 4916 -	176	 -	120	169	113	130August 4th, 1917	212	84	90	170	148	108September 1st, 1917   -	214	89	94	165	118	108September 29th, 1917 -	191	93	95	138	109	107&apos;   October 27th, 1917    -	100	100	100 -	100	100	100November 24th, i 1917 -	54	95	66	85	86	102
Table.F. Wholesale Prices of certain Food and Feeding Stuffs.The prices given in the-first column of figures are the latest available in each case, and necessarily relate to somewhat different dates in regard, to different articles. Those for imported cereals (other than rice) and for flour and for oilseeds and cake relate actually,to Monday, January 14th. The prices for rice, sugar, and tea relate to week ended Saturday, January 12th; those for beef, mutton, bacon, butter, and cheese to. the week ended Wednesday, January 9th, and those for home-grown cereals to the week ended Saturday, January 5th.The prices given for imported wheat and maize are Wheat Commission prices ; the prices for meat, butter, and cheese are taken from the Board of Agriculture^ Returns of Market Prices; for tea, sugar, and rice from the &quot;Grocer&quot;; and for oilseeds and oilseed cake from Broomhall and the &quot;London Grain, Seed, and Oil Reporter.&quot;Latest Price.Week before.Month before.I ear before.July 1914.WheatFlour BaileyOats Maize Rice BeefMuttonBaconButterCheese Sugar- British (Gazette average), perqr. (480 lbs.). No.    3   Northern    Manitoba (Liverpool), per qr. (480 lbs.)- Home Milled,  per  sack (280lbs.)- British (Gazette average), perqr. (400 lbs.). Canadian   (London),   per   qr.(400 lbs.). British (Gazette average), perqr. (312 lbs.). Plate (London), per qr. (480lbs.).Rangoon and Bassein, per cwt. -English, per cwt.    -Argentine, chilled, per cwt.English, per cwt.    -       -Argentine, per cwt.Irish, green and dried, per cwt. -Danish, per cwt.     ... Canadiau, per cwt. -Irish   creamery and   factory,per cwt. Danish, per cwt.     -New Zealand, at London, percwt.Cheddar (English), per cwt. Canadian, per cwt. -       -- English refined, Tate&apos;s Cubes, No. 1, per cwt. Granulated, fine, per cwt. Tea^ (in bond, duty Is. per lb.) Indian, Pekoe Soucnong, per lb.Pekoe, per lb.Ceylon, Pekoe Souchong, per lb.Pekoe, per lb.Oilseeds - Linseed, Calcutta^ at London, per ton.Cottonseed,     Egyptian,     atLondonj per ton. Palm kernels, at Liverpool, perton.Oilseed cake^ London  made  linseed,  at London, per ton. Egyptian cottonseed, at London,per ton. -----------Palm kernel, at Liverpool, per ton;5. d.71 274 044 358 246 976 028 3116 698 0121 6107 6190 6178 0178 0235 0152 0130 653 946 9A Is. Od, B1s.2^d fC Is.5^.1 D 25. Od.595   0550 0 380   0s. d.71 274 044 358 045 576 028 3116 698 0119 0107 6190 6178 0178 0&quot;235 0152 0 130   646 9 l\d.-\s. 6d lld.-\s. id. lld.-ls. 3d lld.-ls.6d. 595 0 380  0380   0s. d.71 272 044 358 043 x 668 0^28 3111 698 0121 6107 6190 6178 0235 0152 0 130   653   946   9Ud.-ls.6dUd.-ls.4dUd.-ls. Z\d. lld.-ls. 6d,595   0380   0 :380 0 300 0 275   0s. d. 75   8*59 6 f57   065 763 647 269 622 6109   0 87   6122   083   6127 0124 0109 6203 0 -217 0 212   0136 6 135   047   142   4\%d.-\s.2diiidj.-i5.ialls.0d-ls.3d 560   0 375   0 505   0 398   95. d.34 1J36 7*27 0124 324 1023 819 1026 1011 659 044 673 040 674 668 062 0107 6125 0115 070 662 618 016 4 302   6* New War Flour.t Country Straight Run.8d:-U 2d. 1\d.-9\d. !7jrf.-l5.2d. 152   0 165   0155   0 94  0ilnk^T i* ^?otDb^Possible to quote separate prices forlheliierent kinds of tea, owing to the ^vision of all tea the official classes a, b, C. and d, for which prices are here given. ail teainto&apos;given.
Table G *-Stocks of the Principal Foods and Feeding Stuffs in theUnited Kingdom.Article.	January 1st, 1918.	December 1st, 1917.	January 1st, 1917.	Stocks in the United Kingdom including estimated Farm Stocks.		Wheat (including flour) -Barley.    -         -         -         -Oats      ------Beans    -         -Peas      -         -         -         &quot;         &quot;	Tons. 2,239,000 t707,000 2,588,000 114,000 48,000	Tons. .   2,542,000 f830,000 2,807,000 124,000 46,000	Tons. 1,815,000 1464,000 1,612.000 124,000 24,000	Stocks in tbe United Kingdom at Ports, &quot;Warehouses, &amp;c.		Maize    ------Kice (including ground rice and rice flour) Grain Meals Sugar    -         -         -	46.000 125,000 43,000 209,000	33.000 144^000 47,000 212,000	215,000 84,000 19,000 79,000	Stocks in the United Kingdom in Cold Stores and in Importers&apos; Warehouses.		Butter    -         -Margarine         -Lard      ------Cheese   ------Condensed Milk$          -Meat: Beef (chilled and frozen) Mutton (chilled and frozen) Bacon  -         -         -Hams   -         -         -Poultry, Game, and Rabbits Other Meat      -         -         -         -Fish      -         -	1,200 2,600 3,600 17.100 11,900 45,600 22,800 7,700 1,600 5,500 19,100 20,700	5,100 4,300 6,300 18,400 14,100 48,300 23,900 7,500 1,800 3.600 20,100 19,600	5,300 5,200 5,400 11,700 8,400 26,800 23,200 15,900 6,100 5,200 12,400 *-	Stocks in the United Kingdom, remaining in Bonded			Warehouses, or entered to be Warehoused.		Tea      -Coffee    ------Cocoa    ------	16,600 55,600 45,500	16,800 59,100 49,100	58,000 -   68,500 44,700	Stocks in tbe United Kingdom at Ports and in the bands of Millers, Crushers, and Cake Manufacturers.		Oilseeds -        -        -        -Oilseed Cake	250,300 92,100	304,500 105,900	385,500 112,000* The figures for wheat arid flour include stocks in port granaries and warehouses, inland warehouses, mills, and bakers&apos; shops, as well as estimated stocks on the farms ; those for barley, oats, beans, and&apos; peas include stocks in port granaries and warehouses and in mills, and estimated farm stocks.  In regard to all other articles, home produce is, with very small exceptions, excluded. -   f Excluding stocks, held by maltsters.   Stocks in maltsters&apos; hands on 1st January 1918 were 221.000 tons, and on lst^December 1917, 208,000 tons. J Figures not available. 1 In manufacturers&apos; bands.   Includes both home and imported produce.			Number of Live Stock in England		and Wales.	-	December 4th, 1917 (Estimated).	June 4th, 1917.	June 5th, 1916.			Dairy Cattle      -         -         t         -   ,     -Total Cattle      - ,                r Ewes kept for breeding -Total Sheep .   -Sows kept for breeding  -Total Pigs        -.       .-         &apos;-	2,455,000 5,738,000 6,261,000 12,172,000 229,000 1,900,000	2,465.000 6,227,000 6,872,000 17,170,000 254,000 1,919,000	2,420.000 6,216,000 7,047,000 17,951.000 283,000 2,168,000
Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.Article.	1st Jan. 1915.	1st Jan. 1916.	1st July 1916.	1st Jan. 1917.	1st July 1917.	1st Sept. 1917.	1st Dec. . 1917.	1st Jan. 1918.Beef :-								pjritish Ribs	7-0	35-3	60-4	64-2	96-1	97-4	79-1	.  80-5Thin-flank	11-2	45-2	80-6	83-5	132-2	130-9	99-6	100-9Chilled or frozen-								Ribs  -	16-3	46-7	82-7	85-4	119-6	122-1	114-9	116-4Thin flank -	26-7	63-1	102-2	101-2	156-5	157-9	135-5	137-3Mutton : 								British Legs	5-8	27-9	55-4	58-7	100-0*	97-7	75-2	76-8Breast	11-7	4L3	79-8	84-2	142-2	138-2	91-3	92-5Frozen-Legs	16-3	41-8	85-7	86-4	134-4	136-0	132-7	134-0Breast	24-8	62-7	120-4	122-0	190-8	190-9	161-5	161-8Bacon, streaky*	7-1	30-7	37-5	56-3	76-4	96-0	133-8	138-7Fish -	40-9	96-7	80-7	131-1	127*1	136-1	190-9	195-9Flour	20-3	49-0	47-6	88-5	109-3	109-2	51-7	51-8Bread	15-8	41-7	44-3	73-3	100-3	99-6	54-5	54-4Tea -      -      -      -	13-6	48-2	50-2	50-9	73-7	78-9	106-8	98-2Sugar, granulated	67-0	93-3	158-0	170-0	187-7	190-0	188-5	189-3Miik       -	6-7	28 -8	33-1	56-6	59-7	61-0	95-7	99-5Potatoes  -	\16-1	]4-8	108-6	121-7	144-3	38-9	39-5	37-1-Margarine	4-4	6-9	17-5	25-0	73-5	66-0	65-4	65-9Butter, fresh	13-8	33-9	31-7	72-9	64-7	90-8	99-9	103-4Butter, salt	12-1 .	31-5	32-3	70-6	65-3	90-1	98-5	105-4Cheese,  Canadian or	10-0	31-7	51-4	74-8	108-0	94-7	&apos;91-5	91-3-   U.S.*								Eggs, fresh     -      -	63-4	104-9	45-3	175-0	95-3	142-4	238-9	242-1* If this kind is seldom dealt with in a locality the Returns quote prices for another kind locally representative, t Decrease.Table K. Retail Prices of Subsidiary Foods in April, 1917, and Subsequent Months compared with the Prices in July, 1914, in London andother large towns.[Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.&apos;]Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.									Article.	April 1st,	May 1st,	June 1st,	July 1st,	August 1st,	Sept. 1st,	Nov. 1st,	Dec. 1st,	Jan. Is	1917.	1917.	1917.	1917.	1917.	1917.	1917.	1917.	1918.Butter beans   -	160	230	170	140	110	110	113	113	113Haricot beans (white)	230	300	220	180	140	140	140	140	140Peas, split fellow) -Lentils, split (red)   -	140	170	190	210	210	210	212	212	220	210	255	230	230	220	220	232	232	232Oatmeal, Scotch	140	170	160	150$	150$	150$	141	141	100Rice, Rangoon	90	100	100	100	100	100	103	103	103Sago	140	160	170	180	180	180	189	189	200Tapioca	120	140	150	160	160&quot;	150	159	159	170Condensed milk	65	90	100	110	110	110	113	120	139Lard, British  -      -	125	130	125	120	120	:120	140	128	125,,  American	130	130	120	i ib	110	il20	139	139	139&apos;--$- -1-25 in Scotland,(Table H, Percentage Increase in Retail Food Prices in the United Kingdom, at each.of the Undermentioned Dates, as compared with&quot;Normal Prices in July 1914.&quot;[Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.]
Table L. Consumption and&apos;-SaLe of Flourjby Bakers and Retailers. Comparison of Four-weekly ^Periods in 1916-17 and 1917-18. All expressed as Percentages of Quantities used in May 1917.-*- i Tlie figures relating to the period June 1.916 to January 1917 are in, italics.				Four weeks ended												Food Control Divisions.	Jan. 5, -1 Q1-Q_______	reef, __i Cl 7	Nov. 10, 1 Q17	Oct. 13, 191-7.	- Sept. 15. Ll9l7. 1916.	. *&quot;     : -August 18, 1917. 1916:	July 21, 1917. 1916.	June 23, 1917. 1916.:               &apos;&apos;-            1 ;                             1	1917.	---j . J i .----- 1916.	1916.	1916.				Newcastle  -      -Leeds -      -      -. Manchestei -      -      z-...... -Nottingham       -      -     :-Birmingham.             -      -Cambridge -      -      - : London    , u.      -Home Counties, North -     -Home Counties, South     .&apos; -Reading     -  .  -      -      -Bristol       -&apos;&quot; &apos; &apos;-      -Carnarvon  -      -      -      -	1001 93 &apos;  92 91% 93 91\ 100&quot;    ; -95 93 93 109 104% 97 i -91 - -97 - 96 -99 -97% 103 100% - 97 ,    96% 96 93%	&apos; 110 108 100 -101% 961 V102 104 103 - 96&apos; &apos; 97 111 108 1011 106 &apos; 971 98 1001 106% I0i% 105 101 103% 98^ 96%	109^ 102% j 1031 96 971 971 104 90 96 96 1111 104% 981 104 971 99% 100-1; 102% 1041 103% 1001 98 100% 95	96 95 96 89 96 93% 98: 94 -931 951. 108 101 .931 991 95 : 96% 98% 100 1021 101&quot; 99 -97 100 90	- 81 95 :   82&quot; 881 89&quot; 92 89 . 951 891 94 100^ 98% 8.7:. : 931 91&quot; 99i 9.7 100 981 100 92.: 98 96 100	&quot; 83 981 80 951 89&quot; 94% 88 88 8.8 951 100&quot; 101 84 93 94 99 96 99% 99 101 92 ; 96 99 108	&apos;  B21 101 -   82i 93 91. 104 91 951 931 94&quot; 102 205i 90i ^  205&quot; 94 .   204 -    95 203 99 ^   102% 94&quot; 09^ 95&quot; 207	92 951 91 94 941 97&quot; 941 98 941 97&quot; 101 102% 9H 160&quot; 961 203&quot; 96 2051 98 203 961 00$ 98 106Cardiff.     -	931 93	97 101	98 96	97 94	94	911 96&quot;	931 05	95 98England and Wales   -	961 95&quot;	1001 102%	1001 99&quot;	97 96	881 94%	88 95	91 200	94 071Glasgow &apos;. -   . -      -Edinburgh -      -      -	92 91% 100 98	-   \95i 99 1021 99%	961 95% 104 99	.   95 95 103 981	91 90 99 97.	&quot;&apos;&quot; 88 89 96 94	-   86 .98 99 97l	96 96 98 971Scotland*    - .    -	-    951 94%	981 99%	&apos;991 97	98^ 9t?i	94 93	91 91	91 97	97 97Ireland&apos;.-	931 90&apos;	98&apos; 93	97 92	961 93	92% 93 -	92 91	931 941	95 97United &quot;Kingdom -; *:&apos;	961-94%	100 202-^	100 98	97 051	901. 04	89i 95 .	91i &quot;    99	95 97iEngland and Wales :  Boroughs,    other   than London, with popula-. tion over 50,000 Smaller towns and rural districts    -       -       -.	9Z% 91 99 98	99 101 1011 104	1001 97&quot; 1011 100	95i 93% 9 981 07	861 02 92 001	85 92 92^ 98&quot;	&quot;    88 ; . 98 &apos;   931 100	93 95 96 - 98%* Including Inverness Division for which the returns are too few to allow a separate statement.

</content>
</cab>
