<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/50/0 images: 37-38</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET---C, (52)58 COPY NO    U) -33rd MARCH, 1952CABINETBRABAZON AND PRINCESS aircraft memorandum by the Minister of supply have reviewed the present position of the Brabazon aircraft and Princess flying boat projects and invite the agreement of mycolleagues to the course of action set out below.2.     &apos;      Both projects were started as part of this country&apos;s post-war effort to establish a lead in civil aviation.   But, whereas we-are on thethreshold of success with the smaller types (notably the jet-enginedComet), the development of the giant types is taking much longer andcosting much more than was expected.   Moreover, civil operators have lost interest in these projects and the late Government decided in 1950that British Overseas Airways Corporation should not be required to operate either the Brabazon or the Princess.3. At present one Brabazon aircraft (an experimental versionwith piston engines) is flying.   A second (the operational version withpropeller-turbine engines) is being constructed by the Bristol aeroplane company for the Ministry of Supply, partly for experimental purposes and partly against the possibility of a future demand for very largelandplanes.   As an interim measure the second Brabazon was to be fitted with Proteus II engines pending their replacement by Proteus IIIengines when these become available.4. Three Princess flying boats are under construction at Saunders-Roe, Cowes.   The first of these, in which Proteus II engines are nowbeing installed, should be ready for experimental flights this summer.5. Work on the Princesses has been continuing with a view totheir possible use by the Royal Air Force as troop and freight carriers inwar.   This proposal was based on the assumption that they would be fitted with Proteus III engines.   However, there has been a serious delay inthe development of these engines which will not come into production until1955 or 1956.   In the meanwhile, only Proteus II engines, whose performanceis appreciably inferior, are available.   In these circumstances, and in viewof the need to make economies, the Secretary of State for Air informs methat the R.A.F. no longer have any requirement for these aircraft,6. Since there are no users in sight for either type of aircraft, atany rate so long as they are equipped with the Proteus II engine, I do notthink we should be justified on financial grounds, in installing this enginein the remaining two Princesses or in the second Brabazon.7. We are accordingly faced with the alternatives of scrapping(THS-BQGUME W-IS- -HE- P R OPE R T Y-O F HER - -BR-JHFA-NNIG ^A.-JEST-Y-tS-GOV-ER-NMEN-T )-O
these aircraft altogether or storing them until more suitable engines and more resources are available.   I am satisfied that it would be wrong totake the irrevocable decision to abandon entirely these two projectson which we have already spent or are committed to spend  14 millions.Although today the emphasis is on smaller jet aircraft for both militaryand civil transports nobody can say that there will not be a future needfor larger types.8. I therefore recommend:(a) that work on the second Brabazon and on the second and third Princess flying boats should cease, at anyrate until the Proteus III engine becomesx available;(b) that the three aircraft on which work is stopped shouldbe stored (at a cost of  60,000 initially, and thereafter 5,000 per annum);(c) that the first Brabazon aircraft should continue to beused for a limited programme of further development work, after which it will have to be scrapped ualess &amp;commercial or military use can be found for it;(d) that the first Princess flying boat should be completedwith Proteus II engines and should undertake experimentalflying.9. If this course is adopted, there will be a clear net saving ofS.Z\ millions, representing the cost of work on the Proteus II, whichwill no longer be required.   In addition, expenditure on the airframesand on coupling the engines which might be as much as  1 million perannum will be deferred for three or four years untij the Proteus IIIengines become available.lO. If the Cabinet approve these proposals, I will make an early -announcement, explaining that the decision has been taken on grounds-&quot;of financial economy and with a view to releasing capacity for theproduction of other mOre urgently needed aircraft, both military and civil.D.S.Ministry of Supply, W.C.2.3rd MARCH, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
