<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/50/0 images: 1-2</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
BtHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT JPrinted for the Cabinet.  March 1952SECRET Copy No2 8 ^|I 656th March, 1952^fl CABINETSWEDISH DEFENCEMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsIt is desirable that Sweden should co-ordinate her defence plans with the Westin peace-time in order to co-operate effectively with us in the event of a war withRussia, in which she is practically certain to become involved.2. Defence co-ordination could best be secured by Sweden&apos;s accession to^^fl          N.A.T.O.  But this would be provocative to the Soviet Union.  It is anyhowimpossible in view of the Swedish Government&apos;s policy of neutrality, which the^^fl Swedish people support.3. The best way of meeting our needs, at least partially, is probably by some^^fl         informal arrangement with Sweden.Form o/ Contact4. Two main conditions should be fulfilled. The first is secrecy. The secondis the tacit consent of the Swedish Government. The Swedish Service chiefs aremore anxious than their Ministers to co-operate with us and they might try todevelop planning contacts without the Government&apos;s knowledge. If this becameknown to the Swedish Government, the effect on our relations with Sweden would| be5. The best solution would be regular contact through established ServiceB     channels by which information could be exchanged with maximum secrecy. Beforeestablishing such contact it might be advisable to hold special talks between Serviceauthorities to discuss the arrangements.6. Another possible solution would be a direct Swedish connexion with^^fl         N.A.T.O.  But the risk of leakage would be great and this must diminish anyappeal which the scheme might have for the Swedish Government.7. A further possibility would be for the Swedes to establish a link with theWest through the Norwegians or Danes. This would probably be the easiestarrangement for the Swedes. For various reasons, including security, we have,however, hitherto considered that it would be best to start by Swedish-UnitedKingdom discussions.  The Norwegians have agreed with this view.8. If a direct Swedish-United Kingdom connexion is established, we shouldhave to decide how to adjust the position with N.A.T.O. (so far General Eisenhowerhas merely been told confidentially that we have had certain exchanges with theSwedes on defence). But we need not reject either of the alternatives mentionedabove should they prove acceptable to Sweden.Form of A pproach to the Swedes9. Early in 1951 it was hoped that some progress could be made throughpersonal Ministerial contacts. A memorandum outlining Sweden&apos;s defence planswas communicated to a member of the last Government by the then SwedishMinister of Defence. This paper revealed deficiencies in the Swedish armed forcesof such magnitude as to render them incapable of withstanding a Soviet attack. It41961
was hoped that this could be brought home to the Swedes, who might then beconvinced of the advantages-Of making plans with us.I 10.  But the Swedish Government&apos;s attitude became still more unfavourable II when in September the Government was reformed to include the Agrarian Party. IH (Hjts- Majesty&apos;s Embassy in Stockholm, reported that the new Government showedeven greater reluctance than their predecessors to enter into any new and closercommitment to the West. *111. In these circumstances, a direct approach to the Swedish, GovernmentI offers few attractions. It would be impossible to circumvent the Foreign Minister,I M. Unden, whose views on neutrality are uncompromising. Nevertheless, theI possibihty of such an approach should be borne in mind for a more propitiousI               moment.   Meanwhile Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Stockholm need not beprevented from discussing the defence problem with Swedish Ministers should theopportunity occur.12. Another line of action is to concentrate on developing Service contactsI with the Swedes, in the hope that a measure of defence co-ordination will develop.I              This course offers the best chance of achieving immediate practical results. TheI Swedish Service authorities appear willing to co-operate with us, within the limitsI of their authority, and to give us useful information.  But, if a planning connexionI seems likely to develop from such contacts, the matter should not be carried furtherwithout political authority and the agreement of the Foreign Office. . .j.&apos;.ConclusionI :S   13.  My conclusions, of which I wish my cqlleagues to are there-I fore as follows.  In our immediate policy we&apos; should niaiffly&quot;c%hn1Je^Ourselves tomaintaining and developing existing Service contacts with the Swedes. We shouldH still regard a direct Swedish-United Kingdom planning connexion as the arrange-ment most likely to be acceptable to the Swedes and therefore as our principalI objective.  At the same time we should not exclude the possibility of developinga connexion with N.A.T.O., preferably through the Norwegians or Danes; butwe should not take the initiative in raising the matter either in N.A.T.O. or withthe Swedish Government. ?&apos;/r &apos;    . Foreign Office,$.W. 1, ~. .y J* 6th March, 1952.H

</content>
</cab>
