<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/50/0 images: 89-90</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1952SECRET - - &apos;   &quot;Copy. No,71C, (52) 78\Ath March, 1952 1 )  &apos;CABINET;        EGYPT: MOTORISED GENDARMERIE   &apos;Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs at the end of my memorandum C. (52) 63 of 5th March, I referred to a proposal which I was submitting for the consideration of my colleagues that we should agreethat the Americans should meet the request from the E^gyptianl Government forthe equipment of a special force of Motorised Gendarmerie witlr armoured cars,jeeps and lorries.2. This question was first raised on 17th February by Her Majesty&apos;ambassador at Cairo when he reported plans by the Egyptian Minister of theInterior in the Ali Maher Administration for forming a guard of some 4,000 men(half of them Sudanese). This would be ostensibly under the control of the Ministerof the Interior, but in fact under the command of a Palace nominee. At the sametime the Egyptian authorities approached the United States Embassy in Cairowith a request for 22 armoured cars, 55 jeeps, 34 lorries and 55 motor cyclesto equip this force. The State Department decided to^ obtain Her Majesty&apos;governments views before reaching a decision. The equipment is however beinggot ready for shipment from the United States, and the United States Embassyis pressing me for an answer.3. The Governor-General of the Sudan was asked whether he would agreeto 2,000 Sudanese being recruited for this guard. He replied that there was noobjection to Sudanese going to Egypt and enlisting, although he would be strongly opposed to recruiting tours by Egyptian Army representatives and the Kaid wouldnot like recruitment to be such as to interfere with recruitment for the SudanDefence Force.4. Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Cairo has recommended that we complywith the Egyptian request to secure the goodwill of the Egyptian Government,and especially of King Farouk, and to help maintain public order and protect theforeign community in the event of further disorders. While the Ali MaherAdministration was in office, Sir Ralph Stevenson said that he was satisfied thatthere was no risk of this equipment being used against the British forces in the canal Zone, although the situation might be different if the Wafd returned to power or if a Government came in which was committed to an all-out attemptto force us out of Egypt. Even in the latter eventuality, it was doubtful whetherKing Farouk would allow it to be used against us.5. The change of Government in Egypt has altered the situation, in so far as:the new Administration is pledged to take action against those responsible for thedisorders of 26th January. There is therefore less chance (so long as the present government is in power) than there was even during the Government of Ali Maherthat the Motorised Gendarmerie would be used against us.6.   I consider that we should support King Farouk and any genuine efforts of the new Government to maintain law and order in Egypt themselves, thus limiting the chances of the British forces in the Canal Zone being called upon to enterCairo and Alexandria and protect the British community.   We should therefore42000
welcome steps taken to improve the police force to that end. The risk that this force might sooner or later be used against us remains, but the chances of thisseem remote if, as has been suggested, its Commander is a Palace nominee.recommendations.   I therefore recommend that (a) the United States Government should be informed that we agree to the shipment of the necessary equipment on the understanding that, if ata later date it looks as if we can no longer rely upon the assurances of king Farouk or if there is a change of Government in Egypt for the worse, the shipment of equipment and the recruitment of Sudanesewould be suspended;(b) the Governor-General of the Sudan should be asked to take what stepshe thinks.fit in order to facilitate the necessary recruitment of Sudanese;(c) Fler Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Cairo should be instructed to inform theEgyptian Government at the appropriate moment that we are in favourof the formation of this force of gendarmerie and that we have so informed the United States Government and the Governor-General ofthe Sudan.A. E.Foreign Office, S.W.1,14th March, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
