<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/50/0 images: 91-91</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
EXPORTS OF RUBBER TO RUSSIAMemorandum by the President of the Board of trade the Cabinet invited me on the 12th March (C.C. (52) 29th Conclusions,Minute 3)(i)  to refrain from licensing export of the 9,000 tons of rubber alreadybought by the Soviet Government until the beginning of the second quarter of the year;  and(ii)  to inform the Russians that this 9,000 tons together with the 6,000 tons for which licences against the second quarter had already been issued,represented the total quantity which would be licensed for export inthat quarter.(I do not refer to Minute 3(1) (iii) since it is not relevant to the matter whichI wish to raise.)2. In the light of (i) above the Soviet Trade Delegation have todaybeen informed that no further licences can be issued in the current quarter andthat licences for the further 9,000 tons will be issued on the 1st April.3. In connection with (ii), however, I think my colleagues may wish toknow the following facts.   On a review of the exports of rubber (from all sources) to Russia in 1951 and of shipments so far in 1952 (including the18,000 tons backlog), the Mutual Aid Committee (the interdepartmental Committeeresponsible for matters relating to American aid) decided that, in addition tolicences for 5,000 tons already promised to the Russians for the second quarterof this year, a further 15,000 tons should be licensed for that quarter, but thatno further licences should be issued for the first half of 1952.   The Russians were so informed in writing on the 20th February, and on two occasions since, on the1st and 8th March, there have been further references in writing to a total of20,000 tons for the second quarter of 1952.4. I should add that the Americans know about the backlog and about our intention to license 20,000 tons for the second quarter.5. If I inform the Russians in the sense required by (ii) above shall be going back on three official communications.   The Russians aremeticulous in keeping their word at any rate in commercial matters, and I myselfshould have thought it undesirable that the Soviet Government should be put in aposition where they could suggest, as the Polish Government in the matter of machine tools have been able to do, that official communications from Depart-ments of Her Majesty&apos;s Government cannot be relied upon.6. I think that my colleagues would wish to be aware of the position before i take action on (ii) above.P,T.Board of Trade, S. W. 1. ,14TH MARCH, 1952.COPY NO,hiSECRETC. (52) 7914TH MARCH, 1952CABINET

</content>
</cab>
