<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/56/19 images: 227-238</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cc(75) 19th COPY NO       ggConclusionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 10 APRIL 1975at 10o 30 amPRESE nt the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon Edward Short mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Roy Jenkins mp secretary of State for the Home department the Rt Hon Anthony Crosland mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for energy the Rt Hon Barbara Castle mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp secretary of State for Education and science the Rt Hon John Morris QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon James Callaghan mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Shirley Williams mp secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection the Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon William Ross mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon Merlyn Rees mp secretary of State for Northern ireland
The Rt Hon Fred Peart MP The Rt Hon Harold Lever mp minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food     Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Rt Hon Robert Mellish MP The Rt Hon John Silkin mp parliamentary Secretary, Treasury Minister for Planning and LocalGovernmentALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Joel Barnett mp chief Secretary, Treasury(Item 3)secretariat sir John hunt mr P D Nairne (Item 2)Mr H F T Smith (Item 2)Mr P Benner (Item 1)Mr J A Hamilton (Item 3)Mr E J G Smith (Items 1 and 2)Mr J A Marshall (Item 3)contents item Subject Fage1, PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRS 12. FOREIGN AFFAIRSCyprus, Greece and Turkey 1Vietnam 13. PUBLIC EXPENDITURE 2Defence 2Social Services 3Environment scotland 4
Subj e ctWalesMid-term CensusGeneraliii
parliamentary i.Ltairs h1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons during the following week.2.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH secretary said thatlurkeyvietnamMr Clerides seemed to be on the verge of resigning as the GreekCypriot negotiator in the inter-communal talks.    If the talks were resumed the prospects for a successful outcome were not favourable:there was no sign of flexibility on the Turkish side.    Meanwhilerelations between Greece and Turkey were exacerbated by thepresence of Greek forces in the Dodecanese in violation of the Greekobligation to keep the islands demilitarised.    The Turkish Governmenthad sent protests to the United Nations, and to us.    The situation waspotentially dangerous.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that theCommunist forces were now in a position to threaten Saigon itself.The survival of a Government under the continuing leadership of president Thieu seemed unlikely.    The Communists would howeverprobably prefer to aomplete their domination of South Tietnam by political rather than military means and this might happen ifPresident Thieu were replaced by someone who was prepared tonegotiate with the Provisional Revolutionary Government, with a viewto forming a coalition.    Such a coalition could not of course beexpected to endure: the non-Communist element would in due course be eliminated from it.    The implications of developments in Vietnamand Cambodia for the political future of other countries in the areamust be a matter of concern.The Cabinet -Took note of the statements by the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary.
3, The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (C(75) 46) on the results of the bilateral discussions about the distribution of the overall reduction in expenditure agreed by cabinet on 25 March,THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that agreement hadbeen reached on some  870 million towards the  1,00.0 millionsavings.     On defence the Secretary of State for Defence was onlyprepared to agree to a cut of  100 million instead of  200 million in1976-77 although he was willing to try to accelerate the savings of later years which would result from the recent Defence Review,Agreement had not been reached with the Secretary of State for the environment on a cut of  33 million in the expenditure on bussubsidies and grants or on postponing plans for introducing communityownership of development land, the cost of which was an unquantifiedcharge on the contingency reserve.    There was also disagreementabout two smaller amounts -  3, 3 million for certain oil-related roadinvestment in Scotland, and  3 million for motorway expenditure in&quot;Wales,    This left him with a gap of some  140 millionj and he invited the help of his colleagues in finding ways of bridging this.One possibility would be to abandon the mid-term census, which would save  15 million in 1976-77, and he recommended that this should bedone.In discussion the following points were made -a0 The proposed reduction was highly discriminatory.Whereas defence expenditure was only about 10 per cent oftotal public expenditure, a cut of  200 million represented20 per cent of the total cuts sought.    Against this it was argued that average reductions had little meaning, since theChancellor of the Exchequer had identified and excluded anumber of priority areas,b, A  200 million cut, coming so quickly in the wake ofthe recent Defence Review, would destroy any confidence our allies in the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation might have inour intentions.    In particular, the United States Administra-tion had expressed the view that the Defence Review reductionsrepresented the limit of what was tolerable.    It was clear thatto go further would severely strain our relationships with theUnited States, and this was an Important consideration giventhe probable need for American support in other ways in thefuture.
c. Further cuts could only be achieved by cutting outprojects;  and this would in turn mean causing redundancies inproductive industry.    Some firms were already avoidingredundancies by stepping up their work on defence production as work on civil production fell.    On the other hand it was argued that there was likely to be a masked increase in economic activity by 1976-77 and there was a risk of manpowershortages in manufacturing industry,d. Some of the assumptions in the current White Paper on defence were already in danger of being invalidated; forexample the withdrawal of forces from Cyprus had been delayed.    The extra costs thereby incurred represented afurther cut in the defence budget.e. The Cabinet had only recently accepted the concept putforward by the Chiefs of Staff of a &quot;critical level&quot; below whichit would not be possible to maintain the United Kingdom5smajor defence roles in the Eastern Atlantic and in Europe, aswell as Xesser roles in other parts of the world.    It was truethat this country was the only European power attempting tocover two such major roles; but it was also clear that areduction in expenditure in 1976-77 of the order of 200 million could only be achieved by strategic decisions which should not be taken by Cabinet on the basis of proposedblanket cuts without knowledge of the implications for thecountry&apos;s role in the world at large.Social The  75 million reduction proposed in health and personal social services services had been accepted by the Ministers concerned but it waspointed out that because the population was aging, an increase ofljT-2 per cent a year in expenditure in real terms was necessarysimply to maintain an unchanged level of service: as a result cuts in capital expenditure would have to be  41 million instead of the 36 million which the standard 10 per cent reduction in capitalspending would have required.    For some services capitalallocations for 1975-76 had already been announced, and these wouldhave to be called in and reduced - something which had neverpreviously been done.    There would be further pressures on health service expenditure later in the year.    Charges for dental services had been frozen, but fees to dentists were likely to have to beincreased, and unless charges were also to be raised this would mean the absorption of the cost - some  18 million - in existing totals.
EnvironmentOn the proposal to reduce bus subsidies and grants by  33 million in1976-77, it was argued that such a move was quite impracticable.Expenditure under this head was already planned to be very heavilyreduced between 1975-76 and 1976-77;  and one consequence of thiswould be a drastic increase in fares such that, if further cuts weremade, they would have to be trebled between early 1975 and 1977,The political implications of such increases were serious.    Theyimplied a total reversal of the Party!s policy of favouring public transport.    Furthermore, there was the danger that individual localauthorities, rather than increase fares or reduce services., would infact maintain the services at the expense of the rates.scotland on the proposal to cut  3. 3 million of oil-related roads investment inScotland, it was pointed out that in the 1974 public expenditureexercise it had been agreed that oil-related expenditure should be excluded from any reductions.     Oil developments led to the need, notonly for roads, but for houses, schools, water supplies, police, anda whole range of other services.    In further discussion it was maintained not only that the disputed cut of  3. 3 million in roadexpenditure should not be made, but that a further  2.4 million shouldbe agreed to enable the subsidy to McBrayne&apos;s lor transport to theWestern Isles, to be increased, since this could not be accommodated within the restricted programmes,wales cut of  3 million was proposed on motorway expenditure in WalesIt was argued that this would be wrong in view of the importance ofthe M4 to the Welsh economy.    It was unfortunate that the cost wasbunched in 1976, but even so the motorway would not be completedtill after 1980.    On grounds of regional support it should not bereduced - indeed there was a case for spending more.Mid-termCensusIt was argued that, although the information which would be obtainedfrom a mid-term census was important for a number of Departments,and not least for determining the allocation of expenditure to localauthorities, in view of present stringencies the proposal to hold sucha census should be abandoned.
In the course of discussion there was criticism of the way in which this and earlier, public expenditure exercises had been conducted.Ministers generally had had no proper opportunity to consider and discuss the economic considerations which led the Chancellor of theExchequer to propose cuts on the present scale, nor any opportunityto discuss in a considered way the public expenditure priorities whichshould shape the composition of such cuts.    In particular, it was desirable given the constraints    of short-term economic requirements for Cabinet to give thought to the social priorities they would wish tosee realised by, say, 1979, so that interim decisions could be taken inthe light of the longer-term objectives.    Even the Public expenditure survey system, which produced material for Ministerialconsideration each year, gave Ministers opportunity to do little morethan make small changes at the margins within a very limited time-table.    Some more satisfactory procedure was required - although itwas recognised that no procedure would be helpful if all spendingMinisters took purely Departmental attitudes, leaving the Chancellorof the Exchequer to judge between them.Criticism was also directed at the concept of the public sectorborrowing requirement, which, it was suggested, had been allowed tobecome something of a fetish, forming a barrier to the realisation ofsensible policies.    The doctrinal basis of the borrowing requirement,its definition and its significance, all deserved further study.    Itshould not be allowed to discourage a shift from private to publicfinancing of investment essential to the future health of manufacturing industry in the country.    There was also the question whether public expenditure discussions should not also cover those claims - such ashelp to ailing firms, the Crown Agents, the building societies - which made little demand on resources but increased the borrowing requirement.Concern was expressed about the lack of control over local authority expenditure, although it was recognised that a large part of the cutsproposed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer would in fact fall on localauthority services.    It was also true that much of local authority expenditure, particularly in the social service field, was the result of policies which had been urged by the Government themselves.    Theconsequences of this for rates were very serious.    After an average rate increase of 25 per cent this year, an increase of 40 per cent was likely for 1976-77, and it had to be recognised that there could be serious political consequences in local elections.    It was felt thatthere was a great deal of waste and extravagance by Ipcal authorities;and it was noted that payments to councillors introduced by the labour government were now being made even to meetings of Party caucuses,a development which should be stopped.
THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that, of the reductions of  1,000 million in 1976-77 proposed by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer and set out in Annex B to C(75) 46, Cabinet agreed to just over  900 million.    This was made tip of the programme cutsproposed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, with the followingexceptions.    Instead of a cut of  200 million on defence, there wouldbe a cut of  110 million;  but it was accepted that the Secretary ofState for Defence would initiate detailed studies to attempt to accelerate the savings in later years resulting from the srecentDefence Review.    The Secretary of State for the Environment had agreed to make savings totalling  10 million cut of the  33 million which had been in dispute on local authority subsidies to buses andnew bus grants to private operators.    The Cabinet agreed, however,that there should be no postponement of the introduction of communityownership of development land.    On the expenditure of the Secretaryof State for Scotland, it had been accepted that the disputed expen-diture of  3.3 million on oil-related roads investment should beallowed to proceed;  and moreover a further  2,4 million ofexpenditure on the subsidy to McBrayne&apos;s had been agreed, making atotal derogation from the savings sought by the Chancellor of theExchequer of  6 million.    The  3 million saving on Welsh motorwayexpenditure which the Chancellor of the Exchequer had asked forwould be set aside.    Furthermore it was agreed that the mid-termcensus should not be held, which would lead to a saving of 15 million in 1976-77.    The net effect of all these adjustments wasthat the total savings, as compared with the White Paper, which theChancellor of the Exchequer had to announce in his Budget statement,would be just over  900 million.    There was clearly somedissatisfaction among member s nfthe Cabinet about the way in which public expenditure decisions were taken.    He would himselfconsider what arrangements should be made to enable the Cabinet infuture to reach a collective view on its public expenditure strategy.There was also a need to re-examine the present definition andsignificance of the public sector borrowing requirement.    Thequestion of grants to bus operators to purchase new buses requiredreview in the light of the industry&apos;s inability to supply the growing demand for bus exports to developing countries.    The Treasury, theDepartment of Trade and the Department of the Environment should consider this question jointly.    The phasing out of private practice inthe National Health Service should be considered further in the social services Committee and, if agreement on policy could be reachedthere, subsequently in Legislation Committee.The Cabinet -1. Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinister &apos;s summing up of their discussion.
2n Agreed to the savings proposed by theChancellor of the Exchequer in Annex B to C(75) 46,with the following derogations;  Secretary of State for defence  90 million;  Secretary of State for the environment  23 million;  Secretary of State forScotland  6 million;  Secretary of State for Wales 3 million.    The intention to hold a mid-termcensus in 1976 was abandoned, with a consequentialsaving in 1976-77 of  15 million.    The net effect ofthese adjustments was to reduce the proposed savings in that year from  1, 008 million to just over 900 million.3. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, inconsultation with the Secretary of State for Tradeand the Secretary of State for the Environment, toconsider the justification for grants to bus operatorsin the light of the present inability of United Kingdombus manufacturers to meet rising export demand.4. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer toconsider the definition and significance of the public sector borrowing requirement, and to report backin duo course.5. Took note that the Prime Minister would consider the arrangements which should be made toenable the Cabinet in future to reach a collectiveview on its public expenditure strategy.Cabinet Office10 April 1975
tTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT10COPY no cabinet confidential annex cc(75) 19th Conclusions, Minute 3Thursday 10 April 1975 at 10. 30 amPUBLIC THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER reported to Cabinet that^EXPENDITURE        he proposed to announce in his Budget statement certain additional expenditure on retraining and restructuring.    In conjunction with theSecretary of State for Employment and the Manpower services commission arrangements had been made for an expansion ofindustrial retraining by an additional 30,000 places, at a cost of 20 million in the current year.    In conjunction with the Secretary ofState for Industry he had arranged for  50 million to be madeavailable for soft loans for major projects in development areas,which should lead to the generation of some  250- 300 million ofadditional manufacturing capacity;  and for  50 million to beavailable for restructuring the ferrous foundries and the machine tools industries,THE PRIME MINISTER said that these developments would be welcome; and he reminded the Cabinet of the need to maintain theircomplete secrecy until the following week&apos;s Budget statement.The Cabinet -Took note.Cabinet Office11 April 1975


</content>
</cab>
