<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/150/0 images: 19-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION  OF TIT F ATTACHED  WESTERN   AND GENERALREPORT No.  96.Peace Discussions (page 14).Voluminous German propaganda against the armistice terms is continued, chiefly on the plea of starvation of the civilian population. This plea is put forward by advocates who have a bad personal record for prevarication. There is interesting matter both under &quot;Peace Discussions&quot; on page .14, and under .&quot; Germany&quot; on page 8, in this connection, especially as affecting the Rhinelaiids.In connection with the report (page 15) of the attitude of the German industrial population towards the Colonial question, I understand that in 1912 only about one-half per cent, in value of the imports into the German Empire came from the German African Colonies.General (page 2). The repatriation of prisoners is dealt with.Information about Bolshevism is given under France, Austria-Hungary, Gerviany, Baltic Provinces, Denmark, Norway, and Siveden.Allied Countries.France (page 4).-There are Press demands for the ex-Kaiser&apos;s expulsion from Holland.United States (page 6). -Under The Future of American Shipping, there is interesting matter about the &quot; Freedom of the Seas&quot; question.Enemy Countries.Germany (page 8). It is still difficult to locate the executive power, if any, over the late German &quot; Empire.&quot; The Workmen&apos;? and Soldiers&apos; Councils seem to claim supreme authority from Berlin. Presumably whoever controls the still mobilised army will dominate the situation for a time. There are signs of resentment in Bavaria and elsewhere against the continued preponderance of Prussian influence. The expression &quot;Republic&quot; seems to have been quietly dropped. &quot;Empire&quot; and &quot; Imperial &quot; have been reintrodneed. Attention is drawn to the daily diary, and to the general statement preceding it on page 8. German Wireless reports for Novembsr 21st (page 9) and 25th (page 10) are of special interest.Neutral Countiues.Baltic Provinces (page .1.1).   Information about the Baltic Provinces, Scandinavian countries, and Finland, is of value in connection with the opening of the Baltic to Allied war vessels and merchant shipping.G. G. A.November 28th, 19.18.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.SECRET.For Reference only.WESTERN   AND   GENERAL   REPORT.No. 96. - Week ending 27th November 1918 (night).Contents;General.Sinkings.   Repatriation of prisoners.Allied Group.Belgium. The return to Brussels.   The British Legation.Brazil Liquidation of German banks.China. Internal situation.   The opium question.Franco. M. Longuet on Bolshevism.   M. Clemcneeau and Labour.   Alsace-Lorraine-   The Kaiser. Contracts for rails.Italy. The Austro-Hungarian mercantile fleet.   Occupation of Fiume.   Occupation of Laibach. Trent.   Recognition of new States.   Supplies for Germany.   Prisoners.Serbia.-A Balkan union.   Reconstruction.United States. Future of United States shipping.   Trade with Russia.   Restrictions on exports. Liberia.   Wireless stations.   Mr. MacAdoo\s resignation,   foreign Military Missions.Enemy Group.Austria-Hungary. Food supplies. German-Austria. Hungary. Bohemia. The Jews. Bolshevism. Germany. General.   Official information.   German Wireless.Neutral Group.Baltic Provinces. Chile. Enemy firms.Denmark. Bolshevism.   The Sohleswig question.   Gorman mines. Finland. Internal conditions.Netherlands. -Supplies.   Passage of German troops through Limburg. Norway. Bolshevism.    German firms. , Pern. The armistice.   Relations with Chile. Spain. -Internal politics.   Transfer of Gorman ships.Sweden. Bolshevism.   The Social Democratic Party.   Trade and shipping. ..&apos;Switzerland. Trade.   The recent strike.Peace Discussions (classified in text).tO  (38)0817-M   l&apos;k 120   11/18   .K&amp;-S A
WESTERN AND GENERAL REPORT.GENERAL.Sinkings, Between November 15th and 21stone British vessel of 1,721 tons was sunk by a mine.   No other losses are reported. vRepatriation of Prisoners. (1) Germany. On November 21st a supplementary message (vide Report No. 95) was sent by wireless to the German Government insisting that no British prisoner shall be employed underground in a coal or salt mine except with his full consent. The question of revictualling Germany depends upon compliance.On November 22nd the Foreign Of lice reported that the following scheme, drawn up by the German representatives at the Spa Conference, had been approved by the War Office. Some 8,600 prisoners on the left bank of the Rhine are to be handed over as the Allied Armies advance. Of the 100,000 prisoners in Germany east of the Rhine, 4,500 are to be sent to Switzerland, the remainder by river transport to ports on the North Sea. Food is to be sent to these ports under the charge of Allied and neutral Red Cross personnel. Some 32,000 prisoners in the immediate rear of the armies are already finding their way across the lines. On November 21st the German representatives stated that the Soldiers&apos; Councils had apparently taken matters into their own hands, and were evacuating prisoners without regard to instructions from Berlin.On November 22nd the arrival of the British Red Cross Delegation at Berlin was reported through the wireless stations of the German Government. The Director, Mr. Arthur Mayne, is represented as having expressed great appreciation of the obligingness of the German Foreign Office and War Ministry, with whose help lie hoped to overcome all difficulties of transport. On November 26th Lord Kilmarnock telegraphed that, according to a Wolffs Bureau report, Mr. j\layne, who is a Fabian Socialist, addressed a meeting attended by British prisoners. He warned them against revolutionary propaganda but advised them to vote for the Labour Party on their arrival in England. He was followed by Ledebour, who attacked the British and French Governments for their hostility to the Russian Bolshevists! The British prisoners shouted him down.On November 24th Lord Kilmarnock (Copenhagen) reported Mr. Abrahamson&apos;s return from Berlin. In an interview with Mr. Abrahamson, Dr. Solf suggested that the amount of rolling stock necessary for the transport 6f prisoners should be deducted from the amount to be handed over by the Germans under the conditions of the armistice. Erzberger stated that, in order to dissipate mistrust, the Government was prepared to hold an enquiry into the treatment of prisoners.In view of the latter statement, interest attaches to the German Wireless report of an interview7 between Erzberger and the representatives of the Deulselie Allgemeine Zeitung in which he said, inter alia, &quot; No country has done so much for the material and spiritual care of prisoners of Avar as the German nation. They Avere never molested, insulted or jeered at, but Avere pitied by the mass of the people because they Avere far from home. If real proof can now be produced that British prisoners of war have been treated in violation of International Law, I give my word that no guilty person shall escape punishment.&quot;Lord Kilmarnock learns that British prisoners, ill-fed and ill-clothed, are fraternising with Germans in Lubeck.(2) Holland. Sir W. Townley reported on November 21st that the. - Dutch railways would remain at the disposal of the British authorities bo long as prisoners could be removed from Rotterdam without delay. He expected to ship 3,000 men daily.   There&apos; was some fear of congestion, as tlie Germans, learning of the above
oarrangements, were evacuating British before French prisoners. On November 23rd Sir W. Townley stated that there were 14,000 prisoners in Holland awaiting transport.(3) Switzerland. Sir H. Rumbold reiiorts that the Swiss Government is anxious to wind \ip the entire internment organisation, and that therefore, in view of the similar policy in Holland, he will have to consent to the repatriation of German prisoners (vide Report No. 95;. On November 23rd he stated that repatriation trains had to be postponed till December owing to coal shortage.(4)&apos; Denmark. Arrangements have been made for the transport of British prisoners of war to Leith and Hull.(5) France. Lord Derby reports that military prisoners and interned civilians are straggling into Paris. He has been authorised to house and feed the latter at the public expense.   The former are to be handed over to General Headquarters.ALLIED  GROUP.BELGIUM.The Return to Brussels. On November 23rd the King and Queen of the Belgians were received by M. Max, the Burgomaster of Brussels, and Cardinal Mercier in the Chamber of Deputies amid scenes of great enthusiasm. In his speech the King rendered an account of his acts to those who, four years ago, entrusted him with the National Army in order to defend the country from attack. He declared that the former treaties which determined Belgium&apos;s position in Europe had not protected her against the most criminal attack. Belgium restored to her rights must settle her destinies according to her needs and aspirations in complete sovereignty. He ended by paying a glowing tribute to France and the British Empire and the other Allied Nations.It is reported through French Wireless Stations that the King will pay an official visit to the King of the Belgians after his Paris visit.The British Legation Sir F. Villiers reports that on November 21st he arrived at Bruges and reopened His Majesty&apos;s Legation.BRAZIL.Liquidation of German Banks.   On November 19th Sehor Lauro Muller had an interview with Sir A. Peel, and told him that in his opinion it was a mistake to ask the Brazilian Government what measures they intended to take in order to ensure the effective liquidation of German banks and firms (vide Report No. 95). He advised the British Government and Sir A. Peel considers this advice sound to furnish the Brazilian Government with a detailed report of the measures adopted in Great Britain with regard to enemy concerns, and to ask it, as a partner in the Alliance, to act likewise.CHINA.Internal Situation. Sir J. Jordan reports that on November 17th the President of the Republic ordered the cessation of hostilities between North and South. The South issued a similar order on November 22nd. Arrangements are being made for a meeting of delegates, from both sides.   It is considered of the
utmost importance that China should present a united front in view of the new international situation resulting from the Allied victory.The Opium Question. Sir J. Jordan has been requested to thank the President for his humanitarian action in inducing the Chinese Government to effect the destruction of the opium stock at Shanghai (vide Report No. 95).FRANCE.&apos; il/. Longuet on Bolshevism. M. Longuet, the Socialist Deputy, writing in ILumanite, attacks M. Thomas&apos; attitude towards Russian Bolshevism. He deplores the efforts of the &quot; bourgeois &quot; Press to erect Bolshevism into a species of scarecrow with which to frighten the bourgeoisie, and considers M. Thomas reponsible for an abominable campaign of counter-revolution. He quotes authorities to show that Bolshevism is &quot;essentially Russian &quot; and &quot; backed by the popular masses,&quot; that it is &quot; revolutionary in the governmental and superior sense of the word.&quot; It is impossible, he states, not to approve the protest of the Permanent Administrative Committee of the Socialist Party against the detestable enterprise of the Allies in Russia. In view of this article the visit of the delegates of the Prussian Revolutionary Socialists and the Democratic Socialists to the French Socialist Parliamentary Group is interesting. The Russian delegates, though they deprecated Allied military intervention in Russia, made scathing indictments of Bolshevism and advocated the despatch of an Inter-national Socialist Commission to Russia to inspect the situation.M. Clemenceau and Labour.  On November 22nd, delegates of the Socialist Parliamentary Group and the Confederation Generale du Travail asked M. Clemenceau whether the Government intended to permit the participation of delegates of the French working classes in the General Peace Conference, and whether it would oppose the meeting of the International Labour Conference to be held during the preliminary peace discussions. M. Clemenceau replied that it would be necessary to submit both questions to the Council of Ministers and to the Allied Governments.Alsace-Lorrahu. A French Wireless message gives the following extract from an article in the Koelner Zeitung : &quot; Hatred towards Germany is manifested throughout the whole of Alsace with the violence of a hurricane. The French are welcomed as liberators with delirious enthusiasm. The loss of Strassburg closes the period of German history commenced in 1S64. Bismarck&apos;s work has gone down to the grave.&quot;A new Municipal Council has been unanimously elected at Metz. It has sent a loyal telegram to the French President and has established a commission to abolish all designations which recall the German regime.The Kaiser. The Temps calls upon the Dutch Government to expel the Kaiser, who can then decide whether he will return&apos;to Germany or give himself into the &apos; hands of the Allies.Contracts /or Bails. To a telegram from tlie Foreign Office, Lord Derby replied on November 23rd that he had been informed that the French Government had no intention of placing any new contracts abroad for rails. Twelve hundred miles of rails had already been shipped from the United States and a further quantity remained to be delivered, but the Minister of Armaments, had ordered that no new contracts were to be placed abroad after November 11th. The Foreign Office, howeArer, learns that though some Government Departments favour delay in placing orders abroad with- a view to their execution in France, considerable pressure is being brought to bear by French Railways for a more speedy supply. The question will probably be discussed at the meeting of the Inter-Alliecl Steel Committee in Paris, which will be attended by British representatives.With regard to the supply of iron and steel, Lord Derby is informed by the Minister of Armaments that comprehensive enquiries are being made into the French needs for the next few years, though there are difficulties in the way of assessment with regard to Alsace and Lorraine. It is proposed to invite England, and the United States to estimate how much they can supply.
ITALY.The Anstro-Tlungarian Mercantile Fleet. The Foreign Office has informed His Majesty&apos;s Representatives at Washington, Paris, and Pome that it considers the requisitioning of Austro-Hungarhui merchant sliips by the Italian Government a necessary act of sovereignty consequent upon Italian occupation of tlie ports where these ships are located. This action, however, must not prejudice subsequent arrangements as to the control of these ships, which will be settled after discussion between Mr. Hoover and representatives of the Associated Governments.Occupation of Fiume. Lord Derby reported on November 23rd that the French Government concurred in the inter-Allied occupation of Fiume (vide Report No. 95) and that General Franchet D&apos;Esperey had in consequence sent French and Serbian troops there, it is understood that American troops are to follow. The French Minister for Foreign A (fairs informed Lord Derby that there Avere alarming reports concerning the relations between the Italians and Jugo-Slavs.It was reported on November 24th through the wireless stations of the Italian Government that several towns to the east of Fiume had been peacefully occupied. The road system is being improved, Austrian material collected, and food conditions ameliorated.Occupation of Laihach. Sir Arthur Evans lias informed Lord Derby that he has heard persistent rumours to the effect that the Italians intend to occupy Lai bach (Caruiola). In the event of such an attempt being made he predicts a clash between the Italians and the Jugo-Slav troops which are stationed there.Trent. It is reported through Italian Wireless Stations that the ex Mayor of Trent and Members of the Communal Council, which was dissolved at the beginning of the war, have been repatriated from Linz, where they have been interned. They have recommenced their functions in the Council.Recognition of New Stales.  In a conversation with Sir R. Rodd the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs gave his opinion that, in view of the many claims which the Allies had against enemy States as a whole, newly created States should not be recognised until after the Peace Conference.Supplies for German]/. Sir R. Rodd reported on November 2-lth that the Italian Government agreed with the proposal to make the revictualling of Germany dependent upon the withdrawal of German agents from neutral countries.Prisoners. On November 22hd Lord Derby forwarded a report from Jassy to the effect that 10,000 Italian prisoners still remained in Moldavia and Bessarabia and that there were also a large number in Wallachia. These men were ill-fed and ill-clothed and impatient to return to their own country. It was consequently difficult to keep order among them. The report suggests that, in view of the difficulties in the way of land transport in Rumania, steps should be taken to send these prisoners home by sea.SERBIA.A Balkan Union. M. Pashitch, M. Yenezelos. and-M. Jonescu have issued a joint memorandum to the effect that, though their three States are building their policy on the principle of their individual nationality, Serbia, Greece and Rumania are bound to live in close union with one another.Reconstruction. News has been received from Nish to the effect that the Serbian authorities are taking all possible measures to help refugees to return to their homes. Railways and roads are being repaired under the direction of the military authorities.(ss17-a h
flThe American Red Cross Commissioner, who has just carried out a tour of inspection in Albania, Montenegro, and Serbia, states that there has been rnnch exaggeration in the reports concerning food shortage. There is some shortage in towns, but very little in country districts.UNITED STATES.Future of United States Shipping. Sir R. Crawford gives the gist of conversations he has had with Mr. Hurley, in which the following points were discussed: (1; The creation of a large mercantile marine. It is the aim of the Government to build sufficient ships to conduct the whole of the trade of the United States with South America. The Government would like Great Britain to withdraw from that service altogether. Mr. Hurley, however, wishes to come to some agreement as to British and French shipbuilding programmes for fear of overbuilding. (2) Desertions from British to United States ships. Mr. Hurley states that it is unlikely that seamen&apos;s wages will be reduced. So long as conditions remain better in the United States than in the British mercantile marine, desertions from British ships are bound to take place. Mr. Hurley suggests the raising of wages and conditions in Great Britain to the American standard. (3) The Freedom of the Seas. Mr. Hurley states that, the President attaches great importance to this part of his Peace Programme, though he appears indefinite as to the exact interpretation of the phrase. Sir 11. Crawford suggests that Great. Britain&apos;s recognition of the principle might be made dependent upon the successful establishment of a League of Nations. The Hearst Press has been active in attacking our reserved attitude with regard to this question.Trade with Russia. A corporation has been organised under the auspices of the War Trade Board for the proper distribution and sale of commodities in Russia.Restrictions on Exports. Mr. McCormick has informed Mr. Barclay that, in the opinion of the War Trade Board, it will soon be possible to relax the existing restrictions on exports. If similar measures are contemplated in Great Britain, he suggests that any prospective relaxation of trade restrictions should be mutually communicated in order to avoid arousing any suspicion in commercial circles that one Government is using the situation to the disadvantage of the other.Liberia. The Assistant Secretary of State informed Mr. Barclay, on November 20th that the United States Government had reached the conclusion that the present system of control in Liberia had been a failure. Control by one Power seemed to be the only possible remedy, and since 1909 Liberia had constantly asked the United States Government to refund her indebtedness and make a new loan under American auspices only. The Government of the United States therefore requested the British Governments favourable consideration for a scheme establishing a credit of $5,000,000 for Liberia by the United States Treasury, together with measrires for the conversion of the 1912 loan and the administration of Liberian affairs.]\7ireless Stations. On November 25th Mr. Barclay reported that Bills had been introduced into both Houses of Congress to empower the Secretary of the Navy to acquire and operate all wireless stations in the United States. This is a permanent peace measure.Mr. MacAdoo&apos;&apos;s Resignation. Mr. Barclay reports that Mr. MacAdoo has resigned his position as Secretary of the Treasury and Director-General of Railways. Mr. Barclay suggests that this resignation, coming at a time when his reputation is at its height, will place Mr. MacAdoO in a strong jjosition if he stands as a candidate at the next Presidential Election.Foreign Military Missions. The Chief of the Stall directs that the officers and men of these missions now on duty with the Army of the United States shall be relieved of such duty at a date not later than December 1st.
ENEMY GROUP.AUSTRIA-HUNGARY.Food Supplies.- -On November 20th Prince Schomburg informed Lord Acton of a message he had received from Vienna to the effect that, if the revictualling of Austria and Hungary &quot;was dependent upon the Inter Allied Commission in Paris, it would probably mean delay. The position in Vienna was desperate, and it was therefore suggested that Entente representatives should meet an Austrian food expert at Berne. The assertion was made that there were large stores of food in Bohemia which could be released by the Czechs.On November 20th the Swiss Minister called on- Mr. Balfour and informed him that the coal situation in Vienna was extremely grave, while in Bohemia there were immense stocks of coal which, before the Armistice, had been destined for Viennese consumption.Lord Kilmarnock (Copenhagen) learns that armed soldiers are entering houses in Vienna in search of food, and that looting is taking place. The Austrian Legation at Copenhagen has asked the Danish Government, if possible, to forward food supplies through Germany.The Inter-Allied Food Council has recommended that, as soon as all Austro-Tlungarian merchant vessels have been placed at the disposal of the Adlies, supply ships should be diverted to Trieste. They require, however, full information as to the needs of the country, the stocks available, and the proposed method of distribution.German-Austria.  Sir H. Rumbold learns that, Baron Haupt, a German Moravian, has been selected to represent German-Austria at Berne. Baron Haupt is a pan-German.   There is said to be a strong German &quot; National&quot; influence at Vienna.According to an Amsterdam telegram of November 19th, the Vienna Mittags-zeitung states that the elections to the Austrian Parliament will take place in the middle of January. Another Viennese paper asks that Weimar should be made the capital of the new Central European Germany instead of Berlin.Hungary.  According to an Amsterdam message of November 20th the Berlin correspondent of the Tlandelsblad states that heavy fighting has occurred between Magyar and CzCcho-Slovak troops in the Slav part of Hungary. Count Karolyi has sent a protest to Dr. Kramarcz.Lord Derby reported on November 2Gth that Marshal Foch had ordered French troops to Budapest. The President of the Council, however, considered that their arrival would not be welcomed owing to the ill-feeling caused in Hungary by the surrender of Transylvania to Rumania. &apos; He has therefore asked Marshal Foch to reconsider the question of the occupation.Bohemia. According to a German Wireless message, Herr Bauer, the Austrian Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, has protested against the encroachments of the Czecho-Slovaks in the German portions of Bohemia. He declares that officials of the German-Austrian Republic have been forced, to take the oath of loyalty to the Ozecho-Slovak State.The Jews. Dr. Pinkus who before becoming a naturalised Swiss subject, was a German Jew from Breslau, has suggested to Sir H. Rumbold that in the event of a British Mission proceeding to Vienna he should accompany it for the purpose of explaining to the Austro-Hungarian Jews, who have been systematically misled by the German Zionists, the aims of the British and Allied Governments.Bolshevism. The late Austro-Iiungarian Consul-General at Moscow had an inter-view with Mr. Clive (Stockholm) on November 22nd. He dwelt npon the danger of Bolshevism and hoped that the Allies would prevent Rakovsky from going to Buda-Pesth where he had been accepted by the Hungarian Government as representative of the Russian Soviets. Mr. Cliye learns that Rakovsky is a dangerous Bulgarian agitator who has been working to dethrone the King of Rumania.
GERMANY.General. It is difficult at the present stage to locate the real authorities wielding power over Prussia, over other individual States, or over the late German &quot; Empire &quot; as a whole. Since the Government of united Germany made the war, it is of special importance to determine to what authority the sovereign powers of the Federal Council have passed. According to German Wireless, the Federal Council was abolished on November .17th &quot;in its character as a legislative body&quot; (Western Report No. 95, page 10). The &quot; Imperial &quot; Chancellor became the &quot; Chancellor&quot; on November 1.0th, and on November .1.8th the ollicc of Chancellor was abolished &quot; for all time.&quot; On November 18th we first find lierr Ebert referred to as &quot; People&apos;s Commissary&quot; (a Russian Bolshevist expression). Then to his decrees are added the signature of lierr Ilaase. the independent Socialist, leader. The Soldiers&apos; and Workmen&apos;s Councils seem now to wield power over the Social Democrat Government (see page 10 of Western Report No. 95 for their names). The Social Democrats took charge, temporarily, pending the elections for a national constituent Assembly, fixed originally for February 2nd, but subsequently postponed. The attitude of the Soldiers&apos; Councils towards this Assembly is not clear. They propose an &quot;Imperial Assembly of delegates of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils.&quot; The question arises, under whom are the Soldiers&apos; Councils acting? It is interesting to note two points the attitude, apparently hostile, of the llauseatic towns, of Bavaria, the Southern States, and the Rhinelands, towards the Social Democrat Government, and the fact that the expressions &quot;German Empire &quot; and &quot;Imperial&quot; have constantly reappeared in German Wireless since the Soldiers&apos; Councils assumed control on November 21th.   Ho it Ebert becomes &quot; People&apos;s Deputy&quot; on the next day.So far, the return of M. Joffc, the Bolshevist &quot;Ambassador&quot; to Berlin, appears to have been averted. Much depends upon the attitude of the demobilised soldiers, who have been advised by the Russian Bolshevists to retain their arms. Meanwhile, the Solf-Erzberger propagandists are endeavouring to throw upon the Allies the responsibility for a Bolshevist revolution, shoidd if occur, on the plea that the terms of armistice insist on the armies withdrawing so rapidly that orderly demobilisation is impossible. It is probable that the acknowledged disorderly flight of the. line of communication troops somewhat increased the difficulties of the German Head-quarters in complying with the armistice terms. The retiring armies have fed upon the civilian food supplies of the Rhinelands and carried oil&apos; what they could not eat. (8&apos;ee also under &quot;Peace Discussions &quot; for details on this point, and the extract from German Wireless of November 21 st, given below.)Official Information. (Owing to the still fluent and changing state of affairs in Germany, information is again given in diary form, instead of under subject headings.)November litli (received 16th&quot;). Sir F. Villiers reported &quot; utter insubordination &quot; amongst German troops retreating through Maastricht, On the same date Sir 11. Rumbold reported, on good authority that many of the leading Social Democrats were against the abolition of the Monarchy, so long as they were not certain of being able to rely upon the Army.On November 20/// the Bavarian Minister at Berne urged the appointment of another Minister to represent Germany as a whole in Switzerland. The relationship between the Bavarian and German Legations is undecided.On November 21st Sir W. Townley reported the Dutch Prime mini steps statement that, the Kaiser came as a private individual to Holland. He used the expression &quot; refugee.&quot;On November 22nd Sir If, Rumbold reported that the Germans were afraid of Prussian Poland being given up to the Poles, whom they therefore were trying to discredit,On November 23rd an agreement between Sir H. Rumbold and his French colleague was reported that it was not desirable to allow Press correspondents to go to Germany at present. Count de Salis, on the same elate, reported that the Archbishop of Cologne and others had appealed to the Pope for intervention to avert Bolshevism and famine in Germany.   The Pope passed on this appeal with his
support. Lord Kilmarnock forwarded reports emanating from Prince Max and a Socialist authority. These are to the usual effect about the severity of the armistice terms causing Bolshevism and food shortage, &amp;c. Liebknecht and the Spartacus party are said to be opposed to a Constituent Assembly, and to favour Dictatorship by the proletariat.   This group is said to favour confusion as favouring its objects.On November 24:1k the situation in Bavaria was reported on good authority to be getting worse (Count de Salis). A danger of a breakdown on the German railway system was reported (Lord Kilmarnook). Sir W. Townley reported the situation in Hamburg, whore the revolutionaries&apos; desire is to break away from Prussia, and establish a Hanseatic Republic. These revolutionaries control the principal German ports and the Kiel Canal. It is said to be generally believed in Germany that ,the Republic1 is really a sham, instituted to obtain better terms. The present regime (Social Democrats ?) were not expected to retain their power for long. (Compare Wireless news of this date indicating the domination of the Soldiers&apos; Councils over the Government.)On November 2blk the report of the Hamburg revolution was confirmed by Sir W. Townley. Heise is the name of the leader. British aid is sought. Armed naval detachments with machine-guns on lorries are said to control the situation. The establishment of a . Niede-Elbe Republic is intended.   Food is wanted.On November 26//t the late Daily Mail correspondent wires from Munich2 that the shortage of food in the West is genuine (chaos and imminent famine). [On this point, see under German Wireless information for November 21st.] On the same day Professor Nikolai was reported on his way to Berlin to oppose Liebknecht (Lord Kilmarnock).Proposals have been received from various quarters advocating the despatch of an Allied Mission to Germany to ascertain the truth. The suggestion has been made that such delegates should travel separately, not altogether in one body (Lord Kilmarnock, November 2bth).German Wireless. N.B. In view of the report of November 9th, that the Trans-Ocean Company, Berlin, had taken over the Berlin Wireless news service, and had undertaken to provide a news service independent of ail parties, the following message (serial No. 7321 of November 24th) is significant: &quot;To All. The Imperial Government (sic-) has created a Central Wireless Administration which shall control the whole wireless system of Germany in the interests of the people. Further particulars will follow by letter. The headquarters is at Berlin, \V. Prinz Albrechtstrasse 5. The Central Wireless Station for the German radio system is temporarily .L.P. Executive Committee of the Woricmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Council.&quot;[It will be observed that this message re-introduces the expression &quot; Imperial &quot; ; this and the expression &quot;Empire&quot; are used by various authorities, including Hindenburg, Ebert, and the Soldiers&apos; Councils.] The following, in diary form, are some items extracted from German WirelessNovember 21st. On account of its importance, as affecting the representations made by Herrein-Solf^ and Erzberger, the following extract is quoted verbatim : &quot; The German Commission for the armistice orders that stocks of provisions in. the hands of military authorities on the left bank of the Rhine must be placed at the disposal of passing troops. Every soldier must receive as many victuals as he can carry for himself to serve him for several days. It is further ordered that all possible effort ought to be used to carry off remaining stocks.&quot; Of other Wireless manifestoes of the same date, the most interesting are the women&apos;s appeal for mercy as &quot;innocent victims of an infamous system,&quot; and the resolution of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils at Frankfurt on November 19th, that &quot; the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils represent the highest political power&quot; and demanding an election for a National Assembly. Rigorous control is claimed over officials &quot; who have been in power up to the present.&quot; There are several other appeals by WorkmeiPs and Soldiers&apos; Councils and Social Democrats in Berlin for a Constituent Assembly, and February 2nd is again announced as the date for the elections.   Eighty trains full of1 It is noticeable that the word &quot; Republic &quot; seems to have been dropped Cor &quot; Empire &quot; recently 2 Through Sir H&apos;. Rumbold, who adds comments. 0817-46 C
troops and 20 with material pass daily through Frankfurt, where 10,000 meals are served daily at cue station.November 22nd. Seheidemann succeeds Landsberg in charge .of the Press Department; Landsberg takes over from him the post of Minister of Finance. Erzberger returns to the charge for alleviation of the armistice conditions. The &quot;German State Government&quot; invites the Governments of the individual German Free States to a conference in Berlin of November 25th. The formation of a &quot; German Democratic Party &quot; is announced. The ex-King of Bavaria returns to &quot; his Fatherland&quot; by permission of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Council. A &quot; Free German National Party&quot; is formed by a group from the former Centre Party. Rhenish members of the Centre Party form a &quot; Free German People&apos;s Party.&quot; The &quot; National Liberal Party&quot; fails to amalgamate with the &quot; Progressive People&apos;s Party.&quot; The &quot; Central Government of Berlin&apos;/ invites the &quot; different German Republics &quot; to a conference on November 25th (compare above). [Russian Wireless of the same date accuses Ebert and Haase of &quot; arresting the march of the international revolution against capital.&quot;   Liebknecht is praised.]November 23rd. The Grand Duchy of Oldenburg becomes the &quot;Free State of Oldenburg,&quot; under a &quot; Directorium &quot; of nine members. The Duke of Brunswick and family go to Augsburg. Liebknecht is said to support Bolshevism. Scheidemann claims to have abolished Press censorship, and advocates a National Constituent Assembly.Noveynber 2-PJi (the day when the Soldiers&apos; Councils took over control of Wireless see above). A Press report is quoted to the effect that the &quot; Government &quot; takes its stand on the position that the convocation of the Constituent Assembly is necessary for an early peace. The Government will not agree to any other form for the creation of definite legislation. Workmon&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils &quot; which are at the present time to some extent independent of Berlin,&quot; will send delegates there in mid-December to elect a Central Council, which will elect an Executive Council.On November 2oth, there are further references to demands for a National Assembly, as affecting finance matters. The &quot; Executive Committee of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Council and the Council of the People&apos;s Deputies &quot; adopts the following resolution : &quot; The Revolution lias created a new State judicature. The new conditions for the first difficult transition period find their expression in the following agreement between the Executive Committee of the &quot;\Vorkmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Council and the Council of People&apos;s Deputies : (1) The political power lies in the hands of the Workmeii&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Council of the German Socialist Republic. Their task is to maintain and consolidate the achievements of the Revolution as well as the frustration of a counter Revolution. (2) Until an assembly of delegates of the Worknien&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils of the German Republic shall elect an Executive Council, the functions of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Council shall be executed by the Berlin Executive Committee in agreement with the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils of the German Republic. (3) The appointment of the Council of People&apos;s Deputies by the \Vorkuien&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Council of Greater Berlin signifies the taking over of the Executive of the Republic ; and that the convocation and dissolution of tlie members of the Cabinet of the Kepiiblic and until the final adjustment of State relations-also of Prussia shall be effected by a Central Executive Committee, which shall also have tlie right of control. The Executive Committee is to be consulted before the convocation of the Expert Minister by the Cabinet. As soon as possible an Imperial (sic) Assembly of delegates of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils shall be convoked.&quot; In continuation of this agreement, which determines the basic relations of the Workmen&apos;^ and Soldiers&apos; Council to the Imperial (.iic) Government, the main principles of the Workmon&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils are to be notified forthwith.&quot;The Bavarian Prime Minister is stated to have said that the convocation of a National Assembly is a democratic duty. &quot; People&apos;s Deputy&quot; Ebert tells the Hessian Minister of State &quot;in the name of the Imperial (sic) Government,&quot; that the &quot; Imperial Government . . . attaches the greatest importance to the closest co-operation of the non-Prussian Federal States in the reconstruction of the Empire (sic).&quot; Plans for the creation of a &quot; German Socialistic Army&quot; by the Executive Committee of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Council, Berlin, are announced. The officers are to be elected, and only to wear badges of rank when on duty. Popular feeling in the Empire is referred to. The former Right Parties appeal for the formation of a &quot; German National People&apos;s Party.&quot; Their programme is given. It indicates their fear of expropriation of property and of land, without compensation.November 26th.  The &quot;Executive Committee of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Council of Greater Berlin issued a definite appeal for a meeting of delegates in Berlin not later than December lGth, to elect a provisional Central Council. This Council will decide about a future Constitutional Assembly.   The men of the still existing
great army units are to have double the representation accorded to the &quot; inhabitants &quot; (.1 for every 100,000, compared with 1 for 200,000;. Meanwhile &quot; close bodies of troops must be allowed to retain their arms under all circumstances, &quot; only &quot;isolated comrades &quot; being disarmed. &quot;The troops in the field want to share in the decision about the future reorganisation of the State.&quot;On the same clay, the &quot;Imperial (sic) Conference&quot; met in the &quot;Imperial Chancellory.&quot; Representatives of the Governments of &quot; all the German Free States &quot; were addressed by Ebert, who presided as &quot; People&apos;s Commissary &quot; and by Herr Soil&apos;. The former pleaded for co-operation on account of economic difficulties, the latter on account of foreign armies threatening the Empire. &quot; The speeches of all the repre-sehtatives clearly expressed the desire that the German Empire should be reconstructed on the Federal principle.&quot;November 27th. A disagreement between Erzberger and Eisner (Bavarian &quot; Minister President &quot; at the Imperial Conference, Berlin, is reported. The expression &quot; Government of the Empire &quot; (sic) is again employed. The Conference is referred to as &quot; Imperial,&quot; as a &quot; State Conference&quot; and as a &quot; Council of National Pleni-potentiaries.&quot; State Election Laws are discussed. German Freemasons appeal to English Grand Lodge on the pleas of innocence and of starvation.NEUTRAL GROUP.BALTIC PROVINCES.At the request of the Finnish Government Plis Majesty&apos;s Consul at Helsingfors has informed the Foreign Office that a Bolshevist fleet, together with submarines and transports, is preparing to leave Petrograd. It is thought probable that portions of this fleet are destined for Reval and Libau. On November 21st a Russian Wireless report stated that a Workmen&apos;s and Peasants&apos; Council had been formed at Reval. The new Esthonian Government, which was formed on November llth, has issued orders for general mobilisation in view of the Bolshevist menace.On November 21st Mr. Clive telegraphed that he had been informed by the Swedish Government that German troops were withdrawing from the Island of Osel and that Bolshevist excesses were feared. Mr. Manning, the Esthonian delegate, has informed Lord Kilmarnoek that the national army will number 25,000 men. German soldiers, who have formed Councils, refuse to oppress the native population, and are handing over some of their arms to Esthonians. The Esthonian Government desires (1) recognition by the British Government; (2) the presence of a British fleet at Reval; (3) the despatch of corn supplies. Mr. Manning pointed out that representatives of the Baltic Barons were trying to discredit the new Government.Mr. Clive learns that on November 21st Bolshevist forces, which have re-established their military front between Finland and Lake Peipus, carried out an attack which was repulsed by German troops. Esthonian forces are being sent forward to reinforce the Germans. Sir W. Townley has received a message to the same effect from Baron von der Heydt, of the German Legation at The Hague, in the form of a telegram in the latter&apos;s handwriting, headed &quot;From Dr. Solf to Baron von der Heydt. The telegram purports to be an appeal from the Esthonian Government, in which the need of an Allied fleet at, Reval is insisted upon. If this telegram is authentic it betrays German uneasiness as to the encroachments of Bolshevism in the Baltic Provinces.On November 27th a further appeal for Allied intervention was made by the Estbonian Government, which declared that the Germans were departing and that the Bolshevists were renewing their attack in the direction of Narva.CHILE.Enemy Firms.- His Majesty&apos;s representative at Valparaiso forwards a recom-mendation of the Central Inter-Allied Committee to the effect that existing restrictions imposed on enemy firms by Enemy Trading Acts should be retained. The Committee understands that German banks hold sufficient capital in bullion to reneAV operations should the present restrictions be withdrawn.
DENMARK.Bolshevism. On November 23rd the Minister for Foreign Affairs discussed with Ford Kilmarnock the question of the withdrawal of Danish representatives from Russia (vide Report No. 95). He stated that the Danish Minister in Petrograd was averse to leaving the country owing to the useful work he was doing in the interest, not only of many Russians, but of the French and British subjects whom he was protecting in Petrograd. Lord Kilmarnock told the Minister for Foreign Affairs that His Majesty&apos;s Government did not intend to intervene in the internal affairs of Denmark. The fact that the Danish Socialist leaders were hostile to Bolshevism precluded the necessity for outside pressure. The Minister for Foreign Affairs, however, replied that he did not wish Denmark to be the only nation which maintained relations with the Bolshevists. It is understood that a secret inter-Scandinavian meeting is to be held at Copenhagen for a thorough discussion of the question. On November 23rd Lord Kilmarnock reported that a curious rumour had appeared in the Danish Press to the effect that the Bolshevist Government contemplated flight to Brazil via Copenhagen.The Schleswig Question. The Danish Press states that Herr Haussen Norremolle, the Schleswig Deputy to the Reichstag, has handed to the Danish Minister at Berlin the appeal of the Danish population of North Schleswig for reunion with Denmark [vide Report No. 95).German Mines. Lord Kilmarnock reports that at the request of the German Government the Danish Navy, in conjunction with the Swedish Navy is watching the German submarine mines in the Sound. The location of the mines placed at the southern entrance of the Great Belt is not accurately known, but the Danish Govern-ment intends to take steps for their removal as soon as possible. Measures will also be taken to sweep for drifting mines.FINLAND.Internal Conditions. According to a communication received from the Finnish Government by His Majesty&apos;s Consul it is the opinion at Helsingfors that the Russian fleet (vide &quot;Baltic Provinces &quot;) Avill attack the town. Mr. Clive learns that the food condition is grave. Last week there was no bread distributed at Helsingfors. The Foreign Office has informed Mr. Barclay (Washington) that the British Government agrees with the suggestion of the United States Government (vide Report No. 95), but that the question should be held over for final discussion with Mr. Hoover, as part of the larger scheme for provisioning countries in need.Mr. Bell reports from Helsingfors that the new Finnish Senate contains seven Monarchists and six Republicans.NETHERLANDS.Supplies. -Mr. Barclay reports that licences have been granted by the War Trade Board for the consignment of 40,000 tons of bread stuffs to the Netherlands Government.According to a German Wireless telegram of November 23rd - the German Ambassador at The Hague has informed the Dutch Government that deliveries of coal to Holland will again be made to the full extent.Passage of German Troops through Limburg. The Dutch Government has declared in the foreign Press that the passage of German troops through Limburg was allowed with the consent of the Belgian, British and French Ministers at The Hague. Lord Derby states that this assertion is incorrect (vide Report No. 95). The Belgian Government has strongly protested.The Foreign Office is informed that in the opinion of the French Government, if it is found on the receipt of further information that a serious violation of neutrality has been committed, the Allies should demand in reparation either the occupation&apos; of Limburg by the Allies or the opening of the Scheldt as far as Antwerp to Allied -warships.
PERU.The Armistice. His Majesty&apos;s representative at Lima states that the news of the armistice was marked by great enthusiasm. The President of the Republic, Congress, and the Municipality of Lima sent representatives to the Legation to convey their congrattdations.   On November 19th a large demonstration took place.Relations with Chile. With reference to the above celebration Mr. Rennie said that very little had occurred, in spite of the public excitement, which coidd be interpreted as deliberately hostile to Chile. The Chilean Consul, however, had declared that the pro-Ally demonstrations were a threat directed against Chile. Mr. Rennie has been asked by the Minister for Foreign Affairs to draw the attention of His Majesty&apos;s Government to the anti-Peruvian riots which took place at Iquique on November 23rd. The Peruvian Government has recalled all its Consular officers from Chile. Sir F. Stronge reports similar measures on the part of the Chilean Government.SPA [N.Internal Politics.--Tii a despatch from Madrid, dated November 13th, Sir A. Hardinge traces the steps which led to the formation of the new Government under the Premiership of the Marques de Alhucemas. The Coalition Government had been weakened by the resignation of the Finance Minister, Sehor Alba. On November Gth, when Parliament was asked to vote the Budget, the Marques de Alhucemas, in reply7, stated what was recognised in the House as his own future programme of internal reform. This programme comprised (1) greater religious freedom, (2) extensive educational reforms. (3) development of provincial autonomy, (!) reform of the Senate. Upon the Republican members showing their intention to obstruct the passage of the Budget, the Prime Minister placed his resignation in the hands of the King. After failure to form a purely Conservative or Liberal Government, a Government was formed on November 9th upon the basis of a union of the three sections of the old Liberal Party : (1) the orthodox Liberals led by Count Romanones, (2; the Democratic Liberals led by the Marques de Alhucemas, (3) the Radical section of the Monarchical Left under Seiior Alba. Sir A. Hardinge states that the new Cabinet has not received a warm welcome from the Cortes. The Extreme Left still demands the abolition of the Monarchy. In view of the Allied, victories, it is probable that the pro-German element represented by the Marques de Alhucemas will give place to a purely Romanonist Government with a foreign policy based upon an understanding between Spain and the Allies.0817-46 nNORWAY.Bolshevism. His Majesty&apos;s representatives at Christiania, Stockholm, and Copenhagen have been informed that, whereas the question of the expulsion of Bolshevist agents from Scandinavian countries is a matter of internal policy to be dealt with by each Government, the British Government thinks it would be advisable if Scandinavian banks were prevented from transacting business with the Bolshevists (vide Report No. 95). Mr. Ovey reports on November 25th that a representative of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs has gone to Copenhagen to discuss that question. The Norwegian Legation at Petrograd has been ordered to leave Russia if such a course is necessary for the safety7 of its members.Mr. Ovey learns that a case has been opened containing Bolshevist propaganda in English.Mr. Ovey has been informed that a Jew named Danischevski with Bolshevist tendencies has had considerable success in getting control of the whole trade between Norway and North Russia. It is thought probable that he is acting iu German interests.German Firms. German firms-and among them Krupp&apos;s with branches or agencies in Norway are advertising an early resumption of business.
Transfer of German Skips. Lord Robert Cecil was informed on November 20th that, pending a final decision by the Peace Conference, the Spanish Government proposed to hoist the Spanish flag and the flag of the Allied Maritime Transport Council on all German and Austrian ships in Spanish ports and to man them with Spanish sailors.SWEDEN.Bolshevism. Mr. Clive learns that the Swedish Banks have not yet come to a decision with regard to rouble transactions (vide &quot;Norway&quot;). These are mainly conducted through the smaller banks. As the result of a recent bank inspection it was found that a sum of fifteen million crowns stood to the credit of Bolshevists. Mr. Clive thinks that the institution of a Black List might be effective in inducing Banks to divulge their rouble transactions.The Social Democratic Party. According to a German Wireless message of November 23rd, the Social Democratic Party of Sweden has congratulated the German People&apos;s Government on the achievements of the Revolution.Trade and Shipping. An official report has appeared in the Swedish Press to the effect that the German Government has annulled unconditionally all restrictions upon Swedish trade and shipping.SWITZERLAND.Trade. Sir IT. Rumbold discusses the advisability of mitigating the restrictions on the import of luxtiries into the United Kingdom in favour of Switzerland. There is danger of serious unemployment in the Swiss silk industry owing to the loss of the British market. Sir PI. Rumbold has fears as to the result of labour unrest caused by real economic difficulties. German agents are always at hand to ferment discontent, and the closing down of silk factories with the consequent unemployment; would pave the way for their endeavours.The Recent Strike. According to a Reuter telegram from Berne, the military prosecutor has been instructed by the Federal authorities to institute legal proceedings against the signatories of the proclamation issued hy the Olten Committee during the general strike, counselling soldiers to refuse to lire on the strikers and advocating the formation of Soldiers&apos; Councils.PEACE DISCUSSIONS.(N.B. Countries are arranged in alphabetical order under tliis heading.)There have been several amendments to the armistice terms given in the Appendix to Western Report No. 94. It is understood that a complete report on the subject is being prepared by the War Office.General. The Foreign Secretary has furnished a general paper upon European readjustments of territory as affected by the principles of &quot; Self-determination &quot; and of &quot;Nationality.&quot; Also important special papers on Alsace-Lorraine&quot;, the Baltic Provinces (with important map showing distribution of population by nationalities), the Czecho-Slovahs, and Poland (with similar map). [See also Appreciation of Report No.  6 of February 20th about the difficulty of applying the principle of self-determination if based on nationality.]An agreement has been come to between the British and French Governments (November 19th-20th:, G.T. G334) that most of Herr SolfVrequests for modifications in the armistice conditions are of a military or naval character, which are matters for
Marshal Foch and Sir Rosslyn Wemyss respectively. The essential condition for the revictnailing of Germany is the placing of German ships at the disposal of the Allies, and the Admiralty have advised the Germans to prepare their ships for sea. Revictualling Germany is part of a larger problem of revietualling all other nations in need, including Greece, Serbia, Finland and other original territories of Russia, and Austria, as well as France, Italy and the United Kingdom. [In this connection it is interesting to note that when the German line of communication troops deserted and went, home the retreating German armies were fed from the supplies of the German civil population, and the soldiers were incited to load themselves with as much, food as they could carry away. A real famine may thus have been created artificially in the Rhinelands. A report from Munich on the subject is given under &quot; Germany &quot; on page 9.]The question of representation at the Peace Conference is now assuming importance. On November 22nd the French, Italian, and United States Govern-ments were informed by His Majesty&apos;s Government that King Hussein was sending the Emir Feisal (his son) to Paris. The Emir left Beirut for Marseilles on that day. He is regarded by His Majesty&apos;s Government as representative of our belligerent ally, coming to look after the interests of his father (Foreign Office telegrams to and from Lord Derby, November 22nd-27th, and Sir F. Wingate, November 22nd).A committee has been appointed by the Imperial War Cabinet to consider questions connected with a German indemnity (I.W.C. 38).An Allied Squadron is on its way to Sebastopoi in connection with the German armistice terms (surrender of Black Sea war vessels). (Sir S. Calthorpe, November 24th.)Austria-Hungary. There are indications in Transylvania of a .break-away from Hungary to join Rumania.Baltic Provinces.--See under General, above.China.-Will probably be represented in Paris by Lu Cheng Hsiang (Foreign Minister), with four representatives of the Wai-Chaio-Pu, and by a Belgian legal advisor (De-Codt).Czecho-Slavaks. See under General, above.France. Lord Derby, between November 19th and 25th, quoted various Press articles affecting peace discussions, especially territorial questions.   The Temps deals&apos; with the question of publicity.   &quot; If negotiations are secret, they (the Germans) will wish to imitate Talleyrand ; if public, they7 will imitate Trotsky.&quot;The French Government is opposed to notice being taken of Herr solf&apos;s appeals, which they consider to be a method of getting out of the armistice conditions and of obtaining extra food for Germany (Lord Derby, November 23rd).Mr. Grahame on November 24th and Lord Derby on November 27th reported the official French attitude as affecting the status of the Emir Feisal, who is being-received at Marseilles by a special Mission sent by the French Government.Germany. The Political Intelligence Department has brought out the following valuable papers affecting peace discussions : November 14th (G.T. 5970, Revised Copy). Documents bearing on the diplomatic situation created by the German request for an armistice, &amp;c. November 15t/t (G.T. G339). Memorandum on German Colonies and popular feeling in Germany. The last-named concludes : &quot; It will be plain what the fear is which makes so many representatives of German Labour to-day regard the loss of the Colonies as meaning economic misery at home. If the new arrangement of the world be so devised that this fear is removed, it seems questionable whether the German working-class will continue to feel any7 strong interest in the possession of overseas Dominions.&quot;On November 21st Sir If. Rumbold forwarded, at the request of the German Government, some proposals made by the German Plenipotentiary at Spa about handing over locomotives and the evacuation of Luxemburg and of Lorraine under the armistice terms. On November 24th Lord Kilmarnock (Copenhagen) reported indirect advances from Solf and Erzberger on the same question of rolling stock,1 as affecting repatriation of prisoners, withdrawal of German armies, &amp;c.   Erzberger is1 On November 27th Erzberger announced that 3,000 locomotives and 100.000 wagons could bs handed over.
credited with an offer to hand over the 250,000,0001. in gold at ouCe, instead of on December 12th, as a sign of good faith over the armistice conditions, and offered to prove that the rolling stock demanded exceeded the amount taken from Belgium and France hy the Germans. Erzberger wanted the Allies to stipulate for a national assembly, properly elected within three weeks, as a condition for peace preliminaries, supply of food, and removal of blockade. These steps not to be taken until the peace terms had been accepted by the Assembly.The &quot; Minister for Foreign Affairs for the German Republic&quot; (Herr Solf) has recognised the right of the population of North Schleswig to choose their own future, and the &quot; Electors&apos; Union &quot; has asked the Danish Government to approach the Allies for recognition at the Peace Conference of their &quot;ardent wish for reunion with Denmark &quot; (Lord Kilmarnock, November 24th).German Wireless1 of November 23rd 27th contains matter of interest affecting the armistice terms and peace discussions, including protests by the German Commission at Spa, with Marshal Foch&apos;s flat refusal to make concessions. Also a special protest against German sick aud wounded left behind being-taken prisoner (25th). Hindenburg reports officially to the &quot;Imperial (sic) Administration &quot; that the &quot; German army, in consequence of the severity of the armistice conditions, and owing to events at home, is not in a position to resume the struggle.&quot; Herr Solf, as &quot; State Secretary of the Foreign Office,&quot; made another appeal by-wireless on November 25th against the armistice terms. On the same day the German Commission at Spa again tried to initiate a discussion of the terms.Great Britain. -The Home Secretary reported (November 18th) that, since the tremendous events of the previous week, the Pacifists had been busy tearing off their disguise, and reappearing in their proper garb as revolutionaries.Hedjaz. See under General and France.Japan. Sir C. Greene reported (November 24th) that Viscount Uchida, the Foreign Minister, would probably represent Japan at the Peace Conference, and would leave for Europe early in December.Poland. See under General.Transylvania. See under Austria-Hungary.For alteration in the authority controlling German Wireless, see under &quot; Germany,&quot; on page 9.

</content>
</cab>
