<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/150/0 images: 36-54</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION   OF THF  ATTACH Kl)   WESTERN   A N I.)  GEN FRALREPORT  No.  y?.Peace Discussions diage 13).A precis of the subjects dealt with at conversations between representatives oi&apos; France, Italy, and Great Britain, held in London on December 2ud-3rd, is given under this heading,   it is proposed to extend the German armistice lor a month.The question of representation at the Peace Conference by States in various categories is attracting general attention. .General (page 2). -ft is interesting to note that the percentage of losses of shipping dropped from about 10 per cent, to 1 15 per cent, after the adoption of the convoy system.The question of the repatriation of prisoners is dealt with in detail.Bolshevism is dealt with under Germany, Baltic Provinces, Finland, Netherlands, Norway, Spain and Sweden. (A powerful article on the subject appears in the New Europe for December 5th.)Allied Countries.France (page 4). His Majesty the King&apos;s enthusiastic reception in Paris is reported on by Lord Derby.Italy (page 5). The Press is reported to be tending towards greater moderation on the Jugo-Slav question.Southern Slavs (page 0).---Progress of the Jugo-Slav question is dealt with under this heading.United States (page 0). Enemy propagandists are again active.Enemy Countries.Austria-Hungary (page 7). There are proposals for convocation of a Constituent National Assembly in Vienna on March 1st.&apos; [ivr.o.
Germany (page 8). The situation has not yet crystallised. Interest centres in the proposed assembly of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Council in Berlin on December 1 Gt.li, and in the statement that the Constituent National Assembly, now fixed provisionally for February 16th depends upon the will of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils.German Wireless reports are given in an Appendix. Special attention is drawn to the resolution of the delegates from the still mobilised army, given under the heading December 3rd, on page 17.Neutral Countries.Baltic Provinces (page 9). Important information is given under this heading, especially as affecting the prospects of Bolshevist, rule in Esthonia.Finland (page 1.1). The election of General Mannerheim as Regent is probable.Netherlands (page 11). Pro-Germanism seems to be reviving in some quarters.G. G. A.December 5th, 1918.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet. 8SECRET, For Reference only.WESTERN   AND   GENERAL   REPORT.No. 97.   Week ending AIN December 1918 (night).Contents.General.Convoys.   Repatriation of prisoners.   Mr. Mayne&apos;s speech.   Trial of the Kaiser. Allied Group.Belgium. The future of Luxemburg. China. North and South.France. President Wilson. French unity. Franco-British solidarity. Responsibility for the war. Agricultural classes.Italy. Jugo-Slav relations. Occupation of enemy territory. The Austro-Hungarian mercantile fleet.Portugal. Portuguese requirements.Southern Slav States. The future of Jugo-Slavics. Italian relations. Croatia. Cattaro. Jugo-Slav prisoners.United States. Anglo-American relations. Presidents Address to Congress. German appeals. Military intervention in Russia. Mexico. Defence of the Panama Canal. Exports to neutral countries.Enemy Group.Austria-Hungary. Food supplies.    German-Austria.   Hungary.   Bohemia.   The Jews. Germany. General.   Bavaria.   Hamburg.   Bolshevism.Neutral Group.The Baltic Provinces. Esthonia.   Livonia. Bolivia.  Chilian relations. Chile. Internal conditions. Denmai*k. The Schleswig question. Finland. Internal situation.Netherlands. Pro-German feeling.    Invitation to Their Majesties.    Passage of German troops through Limburg; Norway. Bolshevist propaganda.   Trade with Germany. Spain. Bolshevism.   Resignation of the Cabinet. Sweden. Bolshevism.   Imports.   German exports.Switzerland. Coal supply. Inter-Allied control. Revolutionary plots. The ex-Emperor of Austria.Peace Discussions (classified in text). Appendix : Wireless Reports.10   (33)7001-lb   Vk 120   12/1S   E &amp; d A
WESTERN AND GENERAL REPORT.GENERAL;Convoys. The Ministry of Shipping gives some interesting information relating to convoys. Before the institution of convoys in June 1917 the percentage of vessels lost on the different routes was approximately 10 per cent. Between that date and November 9th, 191S, 586 homeward convoys, consisting of 8,040 ships (65,189,000 tons deadweight), were escorted through the danger zone and the percentage of losses was 1&apos; 15 per cent, of ships and 1&apos; 07 per cent, of deadweight. During the same period 524 outward convoys, consisting of 7,244 ships (51,316,580 tons deadweight), were escorted, and the percentage of losses was 0&apos;69 per cent, of ships and 0&quot;82 per cent, of deadweight.Repatriation of Prisoners.- (1) Germany.  On November 28th Lord kilmarnock forwarded a telegram from Mr. Mayne, the British Red Cross representative in Berlin, in which it was stated that there was fear of a mutiny at Kottbus Camp (Brandenburg), the prisoners having delivered an ultimatum to the effect that, unless they were at once repatriated, they would march out of the camp. Difficulties were largely chie to lack of food resulting from railway disorganisation. Mr. Mayne hoped that nothing-would be done at Spa to hinder the arrangements which were being made at Berlin for the prompt evacuation of prisoners&apos; camps. He has appointed Danish officers to visit the camps in the region east of the Elbe. On the 29th Mr. Mayne telegraphed that it was useless to send parcels of food to camps in Germany beyond the neutral zone, as many of them were being distributed among Russian prisoners of war in order to keep the latter quiet;Lord Kilmarnock learns that discipline at the camps at Hamburg, Bremen and Oldenburg is in a bad state and that men are leaving them of their own accord.On November 29th Lord Kilmarnock telegraphed that there was not sufficient neutral shipping available to transport prisoners of war from Germany as quickly as the circumstance demanded, especially as the French wished to include their men in the arrangements made for British prisoners. He suggested that the only remedy lay in the use of .a part of the rolling stock handed over to the Allies under the terms of the armistice for the transport of prisoners by rail to Denmark. The Netherlands Minister at Berlin has endorsed this suggestion. Mr. Abrahamson, however, in a conversation with Lord Kilmarnock, pointed out that Erzberger was evidently exaggerating the transport difficulty in order to obtain mitigation of the armistice conditions.Sir W. Townley has been asked to obtain from the Dutch Minister at Berlin a statement which will dispose of the rumours relating to the existence of secret prisoners&apos; camps in Germany.Some confusion has arisen with regard to the respective powers of the Dutch Legation and the British Red Cross representatives in dealing with the repatriation of prisoners. On November 29th Sir W. Townley was informed by the Foreign Office that the British Red Cross representatives were to act under the direction of the Dutch Legation at Berlin. They are to confine themselves to repatriation vid the Dutch ports and Denmark. His Majesty&apos;s Government has decided that the Spa Conference is to be responsible for the general policy with regard to the evacuation of camps. The German delegates have urgently requested that the British delegates may proceed to Berlin after the discussion at Spa.The German authorities have informed the Dutch Minister at Berlin that every-thing possible is being done to ensure the good treatment and prompt evacuation of British prisoners. If some of the latter arrive at the Dutch frontier in a wretched condition it is.clue to the fact that they have left their camps without permission or have been maltreated by revolutionary soldiers without the knowledge of the Central Authorities.
A Copenhagen wire dated November 28th says that the Berlin Council oil People&apos;s Commissaries has decided to appoint a Commission to investigate the charge that the treatment of prisoners of war in Germany was contrary to international law. The Commission will have authority to expel guilty parties from the army without pension and with the reservation that they may be prosecuted under criminal law.The Dutch Minister at Berlin has been informed by the German War Office that since November 25th no British prisoners have been employed in salt mines. For work in coal mines British prisoners are receiving the same rate of pay as German workmen. So soon as they can be replaced, this work will be discontinued also, but the German authorities point out that the whole repatriation problem depends on an adequate supply of coal.(2) Holland. On December 1st Sir W. Townley reported that a sufficient stock of clothing to meet all needs had been procured, lie has been asked, if possible, to make arrangements for the repatriation of a number of German invalid combatants and civilians from England to Germany via Holland.(3) Denmark. Lord Kilmarnock has arranged with the Danish Government for the permanent accumulation, pending the provision of transports, of 5,000 men in rest camps near Copenhagen. On December 4th Lord Kilmarnock telegraphed that, owing to delay in the provision of transport and the desperate condition of prisoners in Germany, this number would probably have to be increased to 10,000 or even 20,000.(4) Switzerland. Sir H. Rumbold has made arrangements with the French internment authorities at Berne whereby British prisoners will be included among the large, number of French prisoners who are to be evacuated from camps in Bavaria, Wurtemburg, aud Baden through Switzerland.(5) Belgium. It is proposed to form a committee of Russian officers to deal with the repatriation of several thousands of Russian prisoners who are at Liege.(0) Rumania.  Some 2,800 coloured French and British prisoners have been abandoned by von Mackensen&apos;s army in Rumania.(7) Roland. Mr. Abrahamson learns that a number of British prisoners have been taken over by the Polish Government from districts formerly German.Mr. Mayne&apos;-s Speech (vide Report No. 96, page 2). On. November 29th Mr. Mayue himself transmitted a telegram describing the meeting held under the auspices of the Council of Workmen and Soldiers for the Prisoners of War Department. The 500 British prisoners who attended the meeting were told that the new Germany regretted the past aud was friendly towards.the British, Mr. Mayne said that he explained the repatriation scheme to the men and warned them against improper propaganda. The meeting was orderly and the speeches, with the exception of M. Leclebour&apos;s, unobjectionable. In view of Lord Kilmarnock&apos;s subsequent testimony to Mr. Mayne&apos;s excellent work, it was finally decided not to recall him on account of anyjndiscretion which he was reported to have made in his speech.. Trial of the Kaiser. The Governments of France, Great Britain and Italy, at a Conference held in London on December 2nd, agreed to recommend that a demand should be made to Holland for the surrender of the person of the Kaiser for trial by an International Court on the charge of being the criminal mainly responsible for the war and for the breaches of international Law by the forces of Germany by laud, sea and air. It was considered (1) that justice required the punishment of those responsible for so much suffering inflicted on the human race; (2) that the certainty of inevitable personal punishment for crimes against humanity and inter-national right would prove a security against future violation of international law ; (3) that lesser criminals in Germany could not be brought to justice if the Kaiser, who was the sole arbiter of German policy, escaped punishment. A Committee of nine of the most eminent jurists of Great Britain has recommended the trial. Colonel House has informed Sir G. Graham (Paris) that he entirely concurs in these views, and thinks that the President will be favourable to them.
allied group.BELGIUM.The Future of Luxemburg. The Belgian Minister has informed Mr. Balfour that-the Grand Duchess of Luxemburg has decided to take no further part in affairs of State until the people have decided by means of a referendum in what form the State is to be reconstituted. In spite of the Socialists the Chamber has pronounced against the union of Luxemburg with Trance, but is favourable to a return to &quot;Belgium. The Grand Duchess, has asked the King of the Belgians to protect the rights and interests of the people of Luxemburg in the rpeace negotiations, to which request the Belgian Government has returned a favourable answer.CHINA.North and South. Sir J. Jordan reports that the Ministers of the five Allied Powers were received by the President on December 2nd. In handing him the Aide Memoire expressing Allied solicitude for an United China, Sir J. Jordan informed the President that the same document Avas being given to the Southern leaders, though the procedure in no way implied recognition of the Canton Government. The President replied that, of the 22 provinces of China, the 17 provinces which looked to Peking as the seat of Government ardently desired peace. The five Southern provinces had the same desire, but were held back by divergent views. Sir J. Jordan learns that His Majesty&apos;s Consul at Canton received a favourable reply from the Southern Government.FRANCE.President Wils 1. Merrheim, the Secretary of the Metallurgical Federation, comments in Verite on various speeches by President Wilson in which the latter declared that the United States had no&apos; quarrel with the German people, whom he carefully distinguishes from the German Government. M. Merrheim declares that the President has always absolved the German people from responsibility for the war,, and compares his &quot; courageous and noble &quot; attitude with that of the French leaders and &quot; infamous Press &quot; which has never ceased to incite hatred of the German people.French Unity. According to a despatch received from Lord Derby on November 23rd, M. Clemenceau&apos;s appeal to all Frenchmen to set aside all differences and work together in the great task of national reconstruction has been favourably received, not only by patriotic writers such as M. Barres, but by M. Herve, the Socialist editor of the Victoire and former anti-militarist. The latter declares that the only way for France to become strong again is for all decent Frenchmen of all social conditions, parties, religions, and philosophical sects to endeavour to prolong for a few years more the &quot; union sacree.&quot;These appeals have not produced the desired effect as far as religious differences are concerned. The France Libre comments bitterly upon the Archbishop of Paris&apos; denunciation of members of the Government for their absence from the Te Deuin Service held at Notre Dame on November 17th. It says, &quot; We are still a certain number of Republicans, Freethinkers and Socialists, who will know Iioav to oppose attempts at reaction destined to infringe the laAvs of secularisation.&quot;Franco-British Solidarity. On NoA^ember 28th Lord Derby reported that His Majesty the King had been accorded an. enthusiastic reception by great croAvds on his arrival in Paris. The French Press has used the occasion both of the King&apos;s Adsit to Paris and of the visit of Marshal Foch and M. Clemenceau to London to pay tribute to Englancfs part in the Avar and to acclaim the close alliance betAveen the tAvo nations.
;)Pertinax in an article in the Echo de Paris declares that close co-operation in peace nmst be assured in the same spirit as nnity of command in war. This is the only way to force Germany to discharge her debt to the Allies over a long period of years. The Temps considers that the Prime Ministers speech at Newcastle serves the cause not only of England but of France. France and Great Britain have identic interests in insisting upon &quot; a pitilessly just peace.&quot;On November 28th Lord Derby reported that he had been received hy the President of the Republic who bad conferred upon him the Grand Cordon of the Legion of Honour.Responsibility for the War. The French Government, which is collecting evidence to prove the enemy&apos;s violation of the rules of Avar and the principles of humanity, desires that, the Allies should come to some agreement whereby punishment may be meted out in the proper quarters. The Temps, commenting on the Munich revelations, declares that documents relating to the responsibility for the war must be published, and those who are guilty must explain their conduct publicly before an International Court of Justice.Agriexdlural Classes. M. Clemenceau has received a letter from certain French DexDuties and Senators of the Right and Centre claiming, in the event of Labour being-represented at the Peace Negotiations (vide Report No. 96, page 4), similar rights for the agricultural aud peasant classes.ITALY.Jugo-Slav Relations.  On November 23rd the Italian Ambassador had an interview with Mr. Balfour in which he described the historic enmity which existed between the Italians and the Jugo-Slavs. Statesmen like Baron Sonnino, he said, were openly hostile to the formation of a Jugo-SlaAr State, while Signor Orlando was barely friendly. There appeared to be considerable suspicion in Italian official circles that the British Government wished to modify the Pact of London in favour of the Jugo-Slavs. Mr. Balfour assured the Ambassador that as the conditions of the Pact represented the piice for which Italy consenled to come into the war, it would not be modified without Italian consent.The Corriere delta Sera has published an article advocating a treaty of peace between Italy and the Jugo-Slavs. The Press is beginning to show a new tendency towards moderation and reconciliation with regard to Jugo-Slav relations.Occupation of Enemy Territory.-lt is reported through the wireless stations of the Italian Government that the occupation of places in the Upper Valley of the Inn has been everywhere-welcomed by the inhabitants and civil authorities. At Brez in the Austrian Tyrol an enthusiastic proclamation has been issued giving vent to pro-Italian sentiments.The Austro-Hungarian Mercantile Fleet. Sir R. Rodd learns that the French Commandant at Fiume has hoisted the French, flag on the vessels of the Austro-Hungarian mercantile fleet in spite of the fact that the Italian Government was entrusted with the task of requisitioning them by the Inter-Allied Transport Council (vide Report ISIo. 96, page 5). -PORTUGAL.Portuguese Requirements. In - anticipation of the visit of the Portuguese Minister for Foreign Affairs to England the Portuguese Minister called on Mr. Balfour on November 24th and asked him to consider the following points : (1) The appoint-ment of an ambassador to Lisbon. (2) The ultimate retention by the Portuguese mercantile marine of the German ships seized by Portugal at the outbreak of hostilities. (3) British financial assistance for a scheme of colonial enterprise. The Minister repeated a story to the effect that Portugal had twice during the war been threatened by an attack from Spain.   He thought, therefore, that it would be a good opportunity7001-1 b B
to form, the army from France into the nucleus of an efficient permanent force. On being questioned by Mr. Balfour, however, the Minister was unable to support his statement concerning Spanish designs by facts.SOUTHERN SLAV STATES.The future of J ugo-Slavics. An assembly of representatives of all the South Slav parties held at Agram on November 23rd, proclaimed the union with Serbia and Montenegro of all the Jugo-Slav districts of Austria-Hungary. Lord Derby, however, learns from Sir Arthur Evans that M. Pasitch, the Serbian Prime Minister, has been intriguing against the joint Government which has lately been constituted (vide Rejjort No. 95). Meanwhile, the Dalmatian representatives at Agram have been responsible for sending a delegation to Belgrade in order to offer Prince Alexander the regency of Jugo-Slavia as Avell as Serbia. The marked pro-Serbian attitude adopted by M. Pasitch, who wishes to be the foremost figure in any scheme of government, is unfavourable to smoothing the way for a new constitution.Italian Relations. In a conversation with Lord Robert Cecil on November 21st, the Serbian Minister complained of the behaviour of the Italians in the occupied districts of Jugo-Slavia, which Avas bound to lead to hostilities. He alluded particularly to Dalmatia, stating that, if that country Avere to remain Italian, there was very little hope of a permanent peace being established (vide also under &quot; Italy&quot;).Croatia. According to a telegram from Prague, the leader of the Croatian Peasants&apos; Party, M. Saber, has begun an agitation for the establishment of a Croatian Republic.   The news has been unfaA-ourably received at Agram.Caltaro. The movements of American and Italian troops tOAArarcls Cettinje has caused considerable agitation among&apos;the Serbians at Cattaro. The Dalmatian Government has placed the Serbian and Jugo-Slav forces at Cattaro under the command of a Serbian Lieutenant-Colonei.Jugo-Slav Prisoners.-^. Korosets, the -President of the National Council at Agram, has written to Lord Derby to the effect that there are many thousands of Jugo-Slav prisoners of Avar in Russia and especially in Italy. These men, he states, voluntarily surrendered in order to help to destroy Austro-Hungarian Imperialism. Now the Avar is over they- are needed to Avork in their own country, and in the name of the Jugo-Slav Government at Agram, Dr. Ivorosets requests their immediate repatriation.THE UNITED STATES.Anglo-American Relations. Mr. Barclay draws attention to the appearance of insidious propaganda in the Press-especially among the Hearst papers AAdiich are influenced by German intrigue for the purpose of sowing discord between the United States and Great Britain. The question of the Freedom of the Seas forms the basis for this propaganda. In this relation an article by the manager of the Baltimore Sunday, reproduced in the New York Times, is interesting. He writes that &quot; though Great Britain Avants a just peace-, she wants to be the policeman Avith the club to enforce this peace.&quot; He declares that neither the British nor French love Americans, and that both are jealous of America&apos;s prominent position in regard to the coming Peace Conference. Mr. Bayley reports from NeAv York that German propagandists are seizing the opportunity to spread the idea that British ships will not be available for bringing back American troops to the United States, since they Avill be AvithdraAvn for the repatriation of Dominion troops and for trade purposes.   They also suggest that exorbitant prices are being charged.On the other hand, it should be noted that Republican critics of the President discountenance any extreme doctrines about the freedom of the seas in time of Avar. Mr. Roosevelt says: &quot;It is the British Navy and the French, British, and Italian
*&apos; Armies which have done most to bring about the downfall of Germany, and, there-&quot; fore, the safety of the United States . . . The British Empire imperatively &quot; needs the greatest navy in the world, and. this we should instantly concede.&quot; Unofficial meetings for December 7th and Sth have been arranged in New York, Philadelphia and other cities throughout the United States to celebrate Great Britain&apos;s part in the Avar.Presidents Address to Congress. Mr. Barclay states that the Presidents Address to Congress, fully reported in The Times of December -1th, Avas received . Avith applause by the Democrats, but in marked silence by the Republicans.German Appeals. Mr. Barclay is informed that the Government of the United States no longer replies to the appeals of Dr. Solf.Military Intervention in Russia. Pending a full discussion of the question on the Presidents arrival in Eiirope the State Department declare that no statement is to be made concerning the policy of the United States Government Avith regard to the Bolshevists. Meanwhile the military situation as far as concerns American troops in northern Russia Avill remain the same as before the signing of the annistice.Mexico. Mr. Barclay learns that the German Minister in Mexico has been recalled by the German Government which has also ordered the cessation of anti-American propaganda.Defence of the Panama Canal. Sir C. Mallet learns that the CrOArernment cf the United States intends to fortify Taboga Island (South of Panama) and that Morro Island Avill be used as a submarine base.Exports to Neutral Countries. Mr. Barclay states that the War Trade Board shows signs of yielding to pressure from various trade interests in favour of removing restrictions upon exports to neutral countries, though it desires to maintain the blockade as far as raAAr materials and. foodstuffs are concerned. The argument is used that the exclusion of manufactured articles, such as steel and iron products from export to neutral countries Avill only preserve the markets for German competition. Mr. Barclay Avili continue to urge the necessity of retaining control of imports to neutral countries.On December 4th Mr. Barclay fonvarded a summary of the scheme drawn up for (1) the removal of prohibitions on exports except in cases of shortage or for military reasons ; (2) increase in the export of manufactured goods; (3) a reduction in the Statutory Black Lists.ENEMY GROUP.AUSTRIA-HUNGARY.Food Supplies. On November 30th Lord Acton Avas informed of the arrival of Baron Haupt at Berne from Vienna. Baron Hennet, who accompanied him as commercial adviser, possessed statistics to prove that Vienna bad only sufficient supplies of food to last until December 20th. The same day Slatin Pasha called on Sir H. Rurnbold and laid before him information to the same effect, lie stated that in his opinion the despatch of 5,000 British or American troops to Vienna, to maintain order and control the distribution of food, would create an atmosphere extremely favourable to Allied policy in German Austria.The Austrian Food Commission at Berne has drawn up a scheme for the relief of German Austria, giving the amount of foodstuffs required. The Commission desires the Allies to release ships lying in the Black Sea, Adriatic and Spanish ports. It is stated that if the Jugo-Slavs persist in their intention to prevent the transit of food trains through their territory from Trieste to Vienna, an Entente military guard will be necessary for protection.
The Swiss President has received a letter from the Mayor of Vienna wherein it is stated that the Argentine Government is prepared to allow the sale of .160,000 tons of wheat and 100,000 tons of maize to the town of Vienna. It is urged that these supplies cannot be transported unless the Allies permit the release of confiscated ships lying in Spanish ports.German Arislria. According to a German Wireless message of November 30th, Dr. Ludo Hartmann, the diplomatic Minister of the German-Austrian Republic in Berlin, in an interview with Press representatives, declared that, since the Imperial interests of both the Hohenzollern and Hapsburg dynasties had disappeared, there was no real hindrance to all the German-speaking peoples in Germany and Austria uniting on the common basis of the right of self-determination. The Entente itself should approve of this policy, as otherwise the future peace of Europe would be jeopardised by German irriclentism.It is reported through the same source that at a sitting of the National Assembly at. Vienna on November 27th, a Bill was submitted by which the Constituent National Assembly is convened in Vienna for March 1st, .1910. The elections are to take place at the end of January.Hungary. According to a French Wireless message dated December 2nd, the National Council of the Rumanians of Transylvania and Hungary has issued a manifesto in which it is declared that the present Hungarian Government at Budapesth is but a continuation of the old regime of political oppression. It claims complete independence of &quot;Magyar intervention in the internal affairs of the Transylvanian and Hungarian Rumanians, who refuse to live in community7 with the Magyar State.Bohemia. It is stated through the wireless stations of the german Government that the Czecho-Slovaks have occupied German territory7 in Bohemia as far as Bruex. There was considerable lighting before the Czecho-Slovaks gained possession of the toAvn. The Government of German-Austria has handed a protest to the neutral representatives at Vienna complaining that the Czecho-Slovak troops have violated the territory of German-Austria, and have endangered the lives and property of Germans in Southern Bohemia and Moravia.The Pope has asked His Majesty&apos;s Government to urge the new Czecho-Slovak Republic to prevent acts hostile to the Roman Catholic faith. This request followed on a report in the newspapers to the effect that the statue of the Virgin at Prague had been destroyed and that monks of German nationality had been expelled from Bohemia.The Jeics. On November 27th the Jewish National Council in Vienna protested against the pogroms in Lemberg and asked the Entente for military intervention.GERMANY.General. The Foreign Office has received a letter from the correspondent of the Daily Chronicle at Geneva. He considers that the German spirit is unchanged and that the Revolution is unreal, brought about as a necessary7 preliminary to the estab-lishrnent of peace; The Germans, he states, do not feel any anger against the old regime, do not admit that they are beaten, and have the old inveterate hatred of the British.. With regard to the artificiality of. the revolution, the Home Secretary is informed by a correspondent in Holland (vide also under &quot;Netherlands&quot;) that in pro-german&quot;circles it is thought that the &quot;Imperial&quot; German Republic is being-organised by the military some of them officers in plain clothes in the Royalist interest. German Court circles look to Bolshevism and consequent disorder to bring-about a demand for the KaiseFs restoration.A Berlin telegram via Amsterdam states that the Council of the People&apos;s Commissioners has resolved to fix the elections of the Constituent German National Assembly for February 16th, 1919, srdjject to the approval of the Imperial Assembly of the Workers&apos; and Soldiers&apos; Council which will meet on December 16th. Commenting on this the Germania doubts the possibility of a Constituent Assembly meeting in
Berlin, where, it asserts, Liebknecht is master of the situation. At a sitting of the Delegates of the Federal States on November 25th a resolution was passed condemning all Separatist movements. A second resolution provided that the Workmeits and Soldiers&apos; Councils should represent the people&apos;s will until the meeting of the National Assembly. Some delegates declared for a dictatorship, others - for a Provisional Presidency.There is evidence to show that many Socialists are dropping their extreme views. According to the French Minister at Berne, Ebert strongly opposed a resolution passed by the Spartacus Group to the effect that the propaganda should be carried on among the Allied armies and in Allied countries in order to bring about a change in their forms of Government. Mr. Branting assured Mr. Clive (Stockholm) that Ebert and Haase had shaken off their Bolshevist tendencies. At a meeting of the Soldiers&apos; Council of Great Berlin Scheidemann declared that the Government had the full support of Marshal Hindenburg. Numerous articles have appeared in the Press to the effect that the soldiers returning from the front are strongly anti-Bolshevist, and are prepared to back up the Government.A Times correspondent, however, states that Haase is plajdng a double game between Liebknecht and the supporters of a Constituent Assembly.Attention is drawn to an able article in The Times of December 5th under the heading &apos;; German Cross-currents.&quot; The correspondent, who writes from Stockholm, deals with the balance of power between the various political parties in Germany.Bavaria. The Bavarian Governments publication of the documents relating to the responsibility for the war seems to have increased the exasperation against Berlin. According to the Korrespondenz Hoffmann the Executive Committee of the Workers&apos;, Soldiers&apos; and Peasants&apos; Council of Munich has sent a telegram to the Soldiers&apos; Council in Berlin demanding the removal of Erzberger, Solf and Scheideniann as counter-revolutionaries.A Berlin telegram to the National Tidende reports that at a meeting at Munich Eisner was hooted down by his supposed adherents.The Foreign Office reports that a note has been received through Berne from the Bavarian Government stating that the population of the Bavarian Palatinate are leaving their homes in view of the Allied occupation. The British Government has informed His Majesty&apos;s representatives at Paris and Washington that it is ready to comply with the request of the Bavarian Minister designate at Berne and issue a proclamation allaying the fears of the inhabitants.Hamburg. Sir W. Townley has been informed that His Majesty&apos;s Government cannot enter into relations with a Government such as that established by IJeise.Bolshevism. Lord Kilmarnock learns that, at the request of the Russian Bolshevists, German Bolshevists are showiug considerable restraint.NEUTRAL GROUP.THE BALTIC PROVINCES.Esthonia.-Esthonia is still in extreme danger from the Bolshevist attack. On November 29th Mr. Menning informed Lord Kilmarnock that, according to news received from the Esthonian Government, the Germans had retired from the Narva line, and that in consequence the Esthonian forces had withdrawn 20 kilometres to the West. Mr. Clive was informed by three Esthonian delegates who left Reval on November 26th that there was nothing to stop the Bolshevists advancing on Reval. On November 28th the Esthonian delegate at Stockholm told Mr. Clive that the German soldiers were coining under the influence of the Bolshevists, and Lord Kilmarnock was informed through a similar source that the Germans could no longer be considered a lighting force. The Germans have destroyed some 30,000 rifles, and the Esthonians have only been able to obtain 5,000 rifles and 20 guns from Finland.   With  regard  to  the  naval  situation,   Mr.   Clive7001-u C
reported on December 1st that he had received information of the presence of ]0 Russian warships off Reval. On the other hand Mr. Tonnissen told Lord Kilmarnock that the forts at the entrance of Reval had been partially- restored and that some heavy guns were in place. He thought that a Bolshevist attack from the sea could be repulsed.The Baltic Press Bureau at Reval telegraphs that a new Esthonian Cabinet, with strong. Socialist tendencies, has been formed, and also a Labour Council, with a Bolshevist majority.A manifesto from thcEsthonian Revolutionary Committee has been published through Russian Wireless stations. It exhorts the German Soldiers&apos; Deputies to assist in the suppression of the Esthonian White Guards, landlords and capitalists, and the re-establishment of an Esthonian Soviet Republic.On November 20th the Foreign Office informed Lord Derby of the British Governments policy with regard to intervention in Esthonia. As a result of frequent appeals from the Esthonian Government a British squadron is toeing sent to the Baltic. A political officer is to accompany the expedition. The Esthonians will be supplied with military material if it is thought that proper use will be made of it. No troops&quot;are to be sent. On November 30th Lord Kilmarnock reported that Admiral Sinclair had been ordered to proceed to Libau. He urged the prompt dispatch of the Fleet to Reval. Its presence, he thought, would be sufficient to overawe the Bolshevists.TAvonia. The President and Vice-Presidenl of the Republic of Livonia have asked Mr. Give to convey to His Majesty&apos;s Government their gratitude for its recognition of the Republic. They hoped that a British representative would be sent to Riga, and made a request for food supplies.BOLIVIA.Chilian Relations. Mr. Haggard (La Paz) states that there is a strong feeling of hostility towards Chile. The Bolivian Government has signified its intention of claiming the restitution of Antofagasta at the Peace Conference. Mr. Haggard points out that this is bound to create strong resentment in Chile, and urges that the Allied Governments should issue a declaration to the effect that they are considering how the rival claims of Chile, Bolivia, and Peru can best be settled.CHILE.Internal Conditions. Mr. Mitchell (Santiago) reports that the general feeling of social unrest at present prevailing in Chile is firmly believed to be, to a great extent, caused by Peruvian agents. - A Labour demonstration has taken place in Santiago to protest against the high cost of living. In view of the serious situation in Antofagasta the Government has ordered the mobilisation of a division in the North. It is pointed out that this is in no way intended as a threat against Peru. As a result, however, of an unpatriotic speech made in the Chamber by a Labour member, a demonstration took place at Santiago in which hostility to Peru was expressed.A Renter message from Santiago states that the papers are unanimous in the belief that all will be satisfactorily settled by the carrying out of the Treaty of Aucona of 18S3, by which the districts of Tacna and Arica, provisionally handed over to Chile, were later to decide their own destiny, by means of a referendum.On December 2nd Sir F. Stronge was able to report that the situation was calmer.DENMARK.The Schleswig Question. The Danish Minister for Foreign Affairs has handed Lord Kilinamock a note enclosing the resolution passed by the Electors&apos; Association of North Schleswig at Aadenraa, and asking the Associated Governments what steps should be taken to obtain a solution of the question.
His Majesty&apos;s Government suggest that the Danish Government should make a formal request for consideration of the matter at the Peace Conference.FINLAND.Internal Situation. According to General Mannerheim the danger of a Bolshevist invasion is still grave, an.dr;in the event of its occurrence, he foresaw a rising on the part of the Finnish Bolshevists unless the country could he supplied with cereals. He stated (November 15th) that a new anti-German Government was to be formed. Only 2,000 German troops remained in Finland. General Mannerheim was informed that the British Government must be satisfied as to the removal of German influence. Negotiations with Prince Freidrich Karl should be broken oil&apos;. As to the supply of foodstuffs, the whole question must be considered as part of a larger scheme for the revictualling of enemy and neutral countries. The recognition of Finnish indepen-dence would be discussed at the Peace Conference.Lord Derby learns that the Finnish Diet has agreed to elect General Mannerheim as Regent.His Majesty&apos;s Consul at Helsiugfors has informed Mr. Olive that food riots are expected at that place accompanied by a general strike.On December 2nd the Finnish Minister at Stockholm informed the Swedish Government that the Bolshevist attack on the Island of Bjorko was unsuccessful. The Swedish authorities learn that the Bolshevists have laid mines in the Gulf of Finland.LUXEMBURG.   (Vide under &quot; Belgium.&quot;)NETHERLANDS.Pro-German Feeling. The Home Secretary learns from a correspondent in Holland that there is a strong current of anti-Entente, and especially anti-English, feeling in Holland. Attempts are even being made to arouse the old Boer war sentiment in favour of the Kaiser and Germany. During a large Orange demon-stration at The Hague a decided pro-German tinge was noticeable, and flags of the House of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, though that State is now a Republic, were flown. The writer thinks that the organisation of the German Republic is being helped from Holland, and suggests that royalist influence is not lacking. He suggests that the German military party are using Troelstra for the purpose of spreading Bolshevism in other countries in order themselves to have a free hand in controlling the German revolution. The French Minister at The Hague has been instructed to inform the Dutch Government that their pro-German sympathies have not passed unnoticed by the French Government.Invitation to Their Majesties. Sir W. Townley has informed the Dutch Minister for Foreign Affairs that it is very unlikely that Their Majesties will be able to accept the Queeirs invitation to visit Holland. In view of the fact that the German Emperor is an honoured guest in Holland, Sir W. Townley thinks the present moment very inauspicious for a Royal visit.Passage of German Troops through Limburg. On November 28th Sir W. Townley reported that the Minister for Foreign Affairs had expressed his regret for the announcement which had appeared in the foreign Press (vide Report No. 96, page 12). In a conversation with Sir W. Townley on November 30th Mr. van Karnebeek again protested that the Dutch Government had intended to act in the best interests of Belgium and affirmed that all military accoutrements had been confiscated from the German soldiers. Sir W. Townley thinks that, though the Foreign Minister was probably influenced by his German sympathies, the action of the Government in allowing the passage of the German troops was clue to the inexperience of the new Cabinet, which at that time was harassed by the fear of internal revolution.The Belgian Minister has addressed a note to the Netherlands Government stating that in view of Dutch action in allowing the passage of German troops through Limburg the Belgian Government feels justified in sending military equipment and provisions to Antwerp vid the Scheldt.
NORWAY.Bolshevist Propaganda. Mr. Ovey lias been informed that a member of the     )! Mexican Legation is believed to be an agent in transmitting Bolshevist propaganda from Norway to Great Britain.Trade with Germany. On November 28th Mr, Ovpy ,reported that he had discussed the question of tonnage for trade with Germany with the Secretary of the Shipowners&apos; Association. The latter agreed that only Norwegian vessels should be allowed in this trade, which he suggested should be confined to four lines. Mr. Ovey thinks that the homeward bound trade could be controlled, as companies would unofficially alloAv inspection of their vessels by a representative of the Legation. Mr. Ovey learns that 500,000 tons of ships&apos; plates are lying in German ports ready for export.SPAIN.Bolshevism. A second telegram has been received from Sir Arthur Hardinge with regard to the Bolshevist propaganda emanating from certain Russian, Turkish, and Bulgarian refugees at Barcelona, who were formerly in German pay. The Minister of State has asked Sir A. Hardinge whether His Majesty&apos;s Government would have any objection to these persons, who constitute a public danger, being transferred in a Spanish ship to Odessa and Constantinople.Resignation of the Cabinet. A telegram from Madrid states that the Cabinet resigned on December 3rd, being unable to present a united front to the formal demand for autonomy- by Catalonia, which was to have been made in the Cortes the same afternoon. Sir A. Hardinge thinks that a new Government will be formed under Count Romanoues, but that he will have to go to the country on the question of Home Rule for Catalonia.SWEDEN.Bolshevism. Mr. Lindley (Archangel), in a telegram dealing with various aspects of Bolshevism, comments on Russian currency. lie states that the mainstay of Belshevist power is their unlimited supply of paper money, which enables them to build up credits abroad, mainly via Stockholm, for the purpose of conducting pro-paganda in civilised countries. He urges that efforts should be made to discover where these resources are accumulating and that they should be sequestered when found, while an international agreement should be made forbidding all exchange operations in roubles. (Vide previous Reports under the various Scandinavian countries for conversations concerning rouble transactions.)The Swedish Minister has informed Mr. Give that he only knew of one Bolshevist trading vessel in the Baltic. This ship is believed to contain a cargo of Bolshevist propaganda.Mr. Give learns that the Swedish Legation has been recalled from Petrograd.Imports. Mr. Give reports that the Italian Minister at Stockholm has proposed the cessation of inter-Allied co-operation in regulating imports into Sweden. Mr. Give uses the occasion to urge the necessity of retaining joint Allied control. If this were abandoned he thinks that the Swedish Government would play off the interests of one ally against the other. He suggests that any relaxation in the blockade should take the form of a gradual increase in foodstuffs allotted to Sweden and of other goods so soon as the situation in Russia and Germany is such that their re-export would be innocuous to Allied interests.Mr. Give learns that the United States Government has promised the Swedish Government a quantity of foodstuffs without the knowledge of the Allied Committee.German Exports. Mr. Give states that during October 110,000 tons of coal were exported from Germany to Sweden.
SWITZERLAND;Coal Supply. Air. Barclay reported on November 28th that the Swiss Govern-ment had asked for support in facilitating the supply of coal to Switzerland from the occupied parts ol Germany, whence their main supply is derived. The War Trade Board is against any definite arrangement being made, as Swiss requirements in this respect will furnish a useful lever when the general Swiss agreement is worked out at Paris.I liter-Allied Control. Mr. Barclav has been informed through the Foreign Office that the British Government is in agreement with the French Government on the necessity of keeping Switzerland dependent, even after the conclusion of hostilities, upon inter-Allied organisations for the control of tonnage and food distribution. The British Government has accepted the recommendation of the Allied Maritime Transport Council that the responsibility for providing tonnage for Switzerland should be shared between the French, United States and British Governments in the proportion of one-fifth, two-fifths and two-fifths respective^.Revolutionary Plots.  Sir H. Rum bold has been instructed to draw attention to the fact that revolutionary movements in neighbouring countries are prepared in Switzerland, and to warn the Swiss Government of the danger of allowing such machinations. Other Allied Governments are being requested to take similar measures.The Ex-Emperor of Austria. The President told Sir H. Rumbold on November 2(Jth that he had been informed by the Swiss Minister at Vienna of the ex-Emperor KaiTs desire to come to Switzerland with his family. The President thought that the Swiss Government would be willing to receive him into the country as a private individual.PEACE DISCUSSIONS.(N.B.   Countries are arranged in alphabetical order under this heading.)General. - On December 2nd the representatives of the British, French, and Italian Governments authorised Marshal Foch to renew the German armistice for one month, and Admiral Wemyss to waive the military occupation of the forts at the entrance to the Baltic (Article XXV.) on condition that the forts are destroyed to the satisfaction of the Allied Naval Commission. The hauling down of the German flag on board German warships while interned in British ports was approved (1.0. 00 (a)). His Majesty&apos;s Government has asked for the views of the French, Italian, and United States Governments about custody of tho Russian and Rumanian gold to be given up under Article XIX. of the German armistice (F.O., November 30th).The following additional subjects were dealt with during the Allied conversations which took place in London on December 2nd and 3rd : (1) An Allied Commission of Admirals in the Adriatic to report on the situation in territories occupied, or to be occupied, by Allied forces ; (2) communication to the United States of America of the conclusions arrived at; (3) demand of reparation and indemnity from the enemy ; (4) the attitude of the Allies towards the ex-Kaiser ; (p) preliminary arrangements for the Peace Conference; representation, at a Preliminary Interallied Conference, of the interests of (a) the British. Dominions and India, (b) the smaller Allied Powers ; also the question of representation at the Peace Conference of nations which have attained independence during the war, and of embryo nations ; (6) victualling and supply of enemy, Allied and neutral countries ; (7) reservation of some of the conclusions, for discussion with the United States of America ; (8) arrangements for the army of occupation in Germany; (9) the military occupation of Austria;, (10) the question of International, Labour, Religious and other Conferences having relation to the Peace Conference, if held in neutral countries.7001-lbD
Representation at Peace Conference. Plenipotentiaries can, in the opinion of the French Government, represent only States existing, recognised, or actually in process of formation (Mr. Grahame, December 1st). For British Empire representatives now in England see &quot;British Empire and Africa &quot;Report. (Sec also under General above.) Sir G. Grahame on December 3rd reported further upon the French official attitude towards representation of Neutral Countries, and States in process of formation.International Congress. The French Government does not think that there are any reasons for placing diffievdties in the way of such a Congress, if not held at the same place as the Peace Conference (Mr. Grahaine, December 1st). The British Trades Union Congress Parliamentary Committee and Labour Party Executive claim that a &quot; World Labour and Socialist Peace Conference &quot; shall be held &quot; at, the same time and in the same place &quot; as the official Peace Conference (November 11th, G.T. 63S4).   (See also under General, above.)Belgium. The question of Belgian claims for cession, at the Peace Conference, of Dutch territory on the left bank of the Scheldt was dealt with by Lord Curzon in a paper dated November I9th (P. 32).Brazil. Opposition is reported to the nomination as Brazilian representative at the Peace Conference of Senor Barbosa, an advocate of the naval supremacy of Great Britain (Sir A. Peel, December 3rd).China. Liang Chi Chao, an ardent pro-Ally, is expected to accompany the Chinese delegates to the Peace Conference (Sir J. Jordan, December 3rd).France. Lord Derby on November 2(5th drew attention to an article in the Echo de Paris advocating the presence of Marshal Foch at the Peace Congress, and on the 27th to an article in the Temps on hospitality to be offered to the Emir Feisal, whose arrival at Marseilles on November 27th was. reported by Colonel Laurence (Lord Derby, November 28th).On December 2nd, Sir G. Grahame drew attention to an important article by &quot; Pertinax &quot; in the Echo do Paris on the question whether the Allied policy should be (1) to encourage the establishment of a National Assembly in Germany before the conclusion of peace preliminaries, thereby strengthening&quot;the Ebert-Haase Government, or (2) to await patiently the opportune time for treating with the master of the hour, whoever he may be. The second alternative is preferred, for reasons given. In Austria and Russia, on the other hand, order should first be restored.Georgia. German Wireless of November 28th reported a demand by the &quot; Government of the Caucasian Republic of Georgia &quot; for recognition of its status at the Peace Congress.Germany. German Wireless of November 28th reported that war vessels in Dantzig had begun disarmament under the armistice terms. According to German Wireless of December 2nd, the Labour Office and Foreign Office in Berlin have received instructions to draw up social and political peace requirements.Another protest was inserted in German Wireless of December 3rd against the terms of the armistice, as affecting rolling stock, and a &quot;compromise&quot; was put forward by lierr Erzberger. The Gorman Government on November 20th appealed officially to His Majesty&apos;s Government, through the Swiss Government, against the enforcement of the armistice terms (P. 30).It is reported on good authority that 13 German merchant ships, to be returned to Germany under the Brest Treaty, were likely-to leave Petrograd shortly (Mr. Clive, December 3rd).Norway. -On November 30th Mr. Ovey (christiania) reported the temporary internment of a German submarine, pending decision about her disposal under the German armistice terms.Panama. Has appointed a representative to attend the Peace Conference (Sir A. Hardinge, December 2nd).Persia. His,Majesty&apos;s Government is in favour, provided non-belligerents are admitted,  of the representation of Persia &apos;at the Peace Conference (F.O.   020,
November 27th). The question is one for decision by the Conference (f.o. December 3rd).Rumania. The Rumanian authorities are reported to be disturbed by a proposal for Allied troops to occupy the Dobrudja, pending settlement of the question at the Peace Conference (Sir G. Grahame, December 3rd).Russia. The Russian Ambassador at Washington has taken steps with a view to Russian representation at the Peace Conference (Mr. Barclay, November 27th).Siam. Proposes to send delegates to the Peace Conference (Sir H. Dering. November 27th).Spain. The French Government has protested against German submarines evading, by internment at Barcelona, the terms of the German armistice (Sir A. Hardinge, November 30th).Switzerland. The question of participation of neutrals at the Peace Conference has been raised by the expression by the Swiss Government of their wish to he-represented (F.O., 192353/W/39, November 28th).Turkey. -Armenians living in Switzerland are said not to be satisfied with the Turkish armistice terms (Sir li. Rumbold, November 27th).The Turkish Government has given orders for the evacuation of Asyr and Medina in compliance with the armistice terms (Admiral Webb, November 29th). Delay at Medina has been reported (F.O. 1473, December 3rd). Delays in compliance with the armistice terms have also been reported from Samsoon and Sinope (Admiral Webb, November 30th).Eight thousand German and 1,500 Austro-Hungarian troops were reported still to be near Haidar Pasha on December 1st, and the Turkish Government has been requested to intern and disarm them (F.O. 56, December 1st).Admiral Webb has been instructed that the armistice terms (clause 19) should be applied vigorously to all Austrians and Germans in Constantinople and the neighbourhood (F.O. No. 62, December 2nd). On December 1st he reported that German and Austrian soldiers were being transported to Princes Islands and elsewhere.United States.- -The United States representatives at the Peace Conference will be President Wilson, Secretary Lansing, Colonel House, and General Tasker Bliss (Mr. Barclay, November 30th). The question of labour representation will probably be taken up after the President arrives (ibid.). There are indications that Irish in America may press the President to raise the Irish question at the Peace Conference (Mr. Barclay, November. 12th).7ooi-nE
APPENDIXtoWestern and. General Report No. 97.WIRELESS REPORTS.On November 2Sth, references were made in German Wireless to an article in the Norddeutsche, written in the old style, and reverting to the alleged &quot; encircling policy of King Edward VII.&quot; and &quot; intrigues and trickeries -which were revealed in the Belgian documents,&quot; &amp;c, &amp;c. Herr Wiirm was emoted as estimating a monthly requirement of 67,000 tons of fats, 180.000 tons of meat, and 120,000 tons of corn, flour, and rice, also condensed milk and foods for children, as the need for a &quot; moderate supply of food &quot; for Germany. The Soldiers&apos; Councils of the 8th and 10th Armies (Eastern) demand the admission of delegates from the Eastern and Western Army Groups to an immediate State Congress of Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils. The Soldiers&apos; Council of the Chief Army Administration convened a Congress of Army Soldiers&apos; Councils at Bad Ems on December 1st. The &quot; German Democratic Party &quot; appealed to President ^Wilson for salvation [from the results of German war policy]. Von Bethmann Hollweg replied to the Bavarian disclosures by throwing on Russia the blame for the origin of the war.On November 29th Russian Wireless referred to the publication by the &quot; German Workmen;s and Soldiers&apos;Council in Moscow&quot; of documents showing that German representatives had engaged in a flourishing trade in Russian property.November ZOtli (German Wireless). lierr Zimmermann supported Bethmann- -Ffollweg&apos;s contentions about the origin of the war. A sharp altercation was reported between the Executive Committee and the main body of the Soldiers&apos; Councils of Greater Berlin on November 28th. The Social Democratic Party met on the same clay and demanded the convocation of a National Assembly. The President of the Prussian Upper House protested against the abolition of the House, and the Vice-President of the Prussian House of Representatives against the dissolution of Parliament. The German Government proposed a neutral Commission to determine responsibility for the war. The American Hearst Press correspondents &quot;have convinced themselves that Germany actually needs provisions to the greatest extent.&quot; Herr EisneFs dis-closures about the origin of the war were criticised. An election for the Constituent Assembly in Wiirtemberg was announced for the middle of January.December 1st. The Hessian State Minister protested against Iierr EisnePs disclosures being made. The Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Executive Council of Greater Berlin announced the creation of new departments for National Politics, Prussian affairs, affairs of Greater Berlin, with an inner ring of four members for Executive Council affairs. Bavarians were accused of taking Bolshevist money.- The Council of Deputies proposed that elections for the Constituent German National Assembly shall take place on February 10th (postponed from February 2nd ?) &quot; subject to the assent of the National Assembly of Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils &quot; at their meeting on December 16th. The ex-Kaiser William&apos;s resignation of his own personal claim to the Throne was published. &quot;Joe Danziger&quot; reported further to Newton Baker, New York, that &quot; the immediate convening of the Constituent Assembly is of secondary importance,&quot; and recommended a strong Provisional Government.December 2nd. The ex-King of Wurtemberg issued a decree, taking leaVe of his people. The Council of people&apos;s Commissaries resolved to create a State Air Office. The formation of a society at Cologne was reported to oppose the separation of the Rhineland from &quot;Germany.&quot; [A movement to throw off &quot;Prussian&quot; dominance was previously reported.] Protests by the Workmen&apos;s Councils of Greater Berlin (November 29th) against the Soldiers&apos; Councils were reported. The Soldiers&apos; Councils on November 30th supported the immediate convening of the proposed National Assembly.
On December 3rd an announcement was made that Herr Erzberger presided on December 2nd over a Commission for investigating complaints against the treatment of prisoners of war in Germany. On December 1st soldier delegates representing about 220 divisions met at Baden and supported the convocation of a National Assembly.   The following announcement was made : &quot; The National Election Law accepted by the Central Government provides for altogether 433 deputies, who will be divided among all Germany and are to be elected in 3S proportional election districts, which extend very often beyond the present boundaries of single States. In case large concentrated bodies of troops still remain outside of Germany on election day, the issue of a special ordinance is to be provided for according to which members of these troop formations, after their return, as well as war prisoners who only after the election day come back, may vote for deputies in a special supplementary election.&quot;December 4dh. The surrender of von Lettow Vorbeck with his &quot; unoonquered forces &quot; was announced. A protest was issued against the French occupation of the Palatinate &quot;before the date fixed.&quot; Hindenburg sent a message to the General Staff and troops &quot; not to interfere with the public affairs of the Workmen&apos;s and Soldiers&apos; Councils.&quot; An appeal [made with amazing effrontery, in view of recent disclosures about the German cruelties to prisoners] was issued against the continued retention of German prisoners and internment of civilians. &quot;Ample provision of linen and warm clothes &quot;to be provided by the Allies, and other similar claims were made. The &quot; Soldiers&apos; Councils of all the troops&quot; in Hamburg supported a National Assembly.N.B. On December 4th Ebert and Haase announced publicly that &quot;none of the German wireless telegraph stations are in the hands of any special political group, and they are all, as hitherto, in the hands of men whose technical control has been exercised during the war, also   ....   [the message ends abruptly].G. G. A.December 4th, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
