<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/52/0 images: 5-9</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
12:-I0CEMEKT- IS,THIS PROPERTY OJi1 HIS BRITANNIC Mfl.JESJY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)JL WATJ   CABINET64601HORSE RACING.Notes of a Conference held at Lord Curzon13 Room in I  .     &apos; - thprivy Council Offie e&quot;mJHKBfZTnh&apos; Ma vjjlirat 5;,p,mr, to cons ider a. He port by the^Preiident of the-Boasa^^Qrade.....on HoTJQicjgg^ G/J^&apos;^T$t:&quot;rgg^&quot;- j^JMt,4Ig, Mjn, I),,        -        -^---^--.Vj. \-v   Present:-Lord Curzon (in the Chair)Sir Albert Stanley, M.P..- President of the Board of TradeLord Jersey- Senior Steward of the Jockey Club,Lord Penrhyn - Steward of the Jockey.ClubI Mr.B.M.Weatherby - Steward of the National Hunt CommitteeMr.Fr.ank Bibby - Steward of the National Hunt Committee- ,Ur^-Miirland - Steward of the National Hunt CommitteeW; . Colonel Leslie Wilson, MJ?.,.-..;:ry.fAssistant Secretary, War Cabinet.IL0HD&apos;.-GUBZ0H pointed out that the question of racing had been under the consideration of the War Cabinet about a year ago,, and he reminded the conference that a meeting had taken place at Downing Street then, at which Lord Rosebery had been present and stated, the views of the Jockey Club.    A satisfactory arrangement had., then been arrived at and Lord Curzon desired to express, his appreciation of the great fairness with which the Jockey Club had acted in inter-preting that arrangement.The situation, Lord Cur son explained, as the warrant along, became more acute and there was a certain section of public opinion which held,strong,views against racing. ,   In answer to questions    : in the House of Commons, a pledge had been given that this question &apos; sh/ouia be referred.to the War Cabinet,,    All departments concerned had been consulted.;   the War Office, the Board of Trade, :the Ministry k of Food, and the Board of Agriculture * &apos; A report had been presented by these departments, extracts from which Lord Curzon read to the conference.     The War Cabinet had arrived at certain decisions, which Lord Curzon said he had been instructed to communicate to the representatives of the Jockey Club, and National Bunt Committee. Those decisions were(t\ That no flat racing should be allowed, except at Newmarket-after the 31st f&amp;iy, 1918, .     - -l-Z) That race meetings under the rules of the National Hunt Committee should not be allowed during the ensuing winter season.(3) That no extra trains should be run to Newmarket for the conveyance of race-goers, or tickets sold to Newmarket, - beyond the capacity of the ordinary trains.With regard to (s), Lord Curzon pointed out that stress had &quot;been laid on the point that the greater.part of the-competitors at euch,H2ieetings were geldings. .
;VJX3CUMEK!C-ISJPKE. OT)PERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVBHMENT)I WAR   CABINETI SEOHBTHORSE RACING.6G.T. 4601Notes of a Conference held at Lord Curaon&quot;s Room in thTlgt^yy,, Council Ofi:ieo^n/&quot;Friday, 17th liay,19llT alH$T jp tnu ,, to ccms idor &quot;&quot;iT ReportTby the President of ,the Board, of Trade on HoFse&quot;RicinF^ 1BQ151]   rfeTTTar ffaHnat- 412j Minfl).     &apos;Present :-Lord Curzon fin the Chair)Sir Albert Stanley, M,P..- President of the Board of TradeLord Jersey - Senior Steward of the Jockey Club,Lord Penrhyn - Steward of the Jockey ClubMr.E.M,Weatherby -: Steward of the National Hunt CommitteeMr.Frank Bibby - Steward of the National Hunt Committee   ,Mr.fcMurland - Steward of the National Hunt CommitteeColonel Leslie Wilson, M.P, ,,-AssIstant Secretary, War Cabin et,LORD GURSON pointed out that the question of racing had been under the consideration of the War Cabinet about a year ago,, and he reminded the oonferenoe that a meeting had taken place at Downing Street then, at which Lord Rosebery had been present and stated the views of the Jockey Clhb.    A satisfactory arrangement had. then been arrived at and Lord Curzon desired to express, his appreciation of the great fairness with which the Jockey Club had acted in inter-preting that arrangement.The situation, Lord Curzon explained, as the war wit along, became more acute and there was a certain section of public opinion which held,strong.views against racing, ,   In answer to questions . in the House of Commons, a pledge had been given that this question . should be referred.to the War Cabinet,    All departments concerned had been consulted;   the War Office, the Board of Trade, the Ministryv of Pood, and the Board of Agriculture.    A report had been presented by these departments, extracts from which Lord Curzon read to .the conference.     The War Cabinet had arrived at certain decisions, which Lord Curzon said, he had been instructed to communicate to the representatives of the Jockey Club, and National Hunt Committee. Those decisions werefl) That no flat racing should be allowed, except at Newmarket after the 31st -Hay, 1918,.. ;:. .      -V:(S) That race meetings under the rules of the National Hunt Committee should not bo allowed during the ensuing winter season,(3) That no extra trains should be run to Newmarket for the conveyance of race-goers, or tickets sold to Newmarket, beyond the capacity of the ordinary trains,With regard to (2), Lord Curzon pointed out that stress, had &quot;been laid on the point that the greater part of the-competitors at 8jao2y-*meeting3 were geldings, .
LORD CUR20H then explained the number of days racing which would take place as the result of those decisions as compared with the two previous years - Appendix II.LORD JERSSy asked if the opinion of the Board of Agriculture rai$rt bo made known to the conference, and Lord Curzon read a memorandum ho had received from Mr.Prothero.LORD $1RSEY also asked whether the Food Controller realised th&amp;t a reduction in the number of days flat-racing would not entail any saving of oats, as the same number of horses would ho kept in training.In reply, LORD CUBZOfl said that the Pood Controller quite realised that fact, hut   felt that consideration of public opinion must be borne in mind.After a discussion as to the method by which an announcement of the decision of the Government should bo made, it was agreed that the best course to pursue would be that a   letter embodying the Government&apos;s decisions should bo written to Lord Jersey, as Senior Steward of the Jockey Club, by the President of the Board of Trade, which letter could be laid before the Jockey Club at a mooting which Lord Jersey said he would- call for Thursday next.    A similar letter should be written to the Rational Hunt Committee..   &apos;: (For copy of this letter see Appendix I.)LORD JERSEY asked if there would be any objection to the addition of two extra meotings being added to the Uowroarket pro-gramme already advertised, pointing out that no meetings had been arranged between July 16th and September 10th in view of the previous number of days racing allotted by the Government.LORD CURZON said that he saw no objeotion to this, but urged Lord Jersey not to announce the meetings as extra meetings to ba held as a concession from the Government, or as having anything to do with the Governments decision.In reply,to Lord Jersey as to the Governments attitude if pressure was brought to bear from other quarters to reconsider their deoisions snd extend the list of fixtures, Lord Curzon said that the Government would not yield to any aeuoh pressure.SIR ALBERT STAHLEY pointed out that the main difficulty was ,the railway accommodation and said that even to-day, it had been necessary to reruso railway tickets to people desirous of travelling to the seaside. The Railway Companies were feeling very bitter with regard to the provision of trains for race meetings at such places as Gatwick and Lingfiold, as it v/as necessary for them to run extra trains in order to clear their platforms.Questioned by Lord Curzon as to the opinion of the National  : Hunt Committee on the deoision of the Government as affecting steeplechasing, both Mr.Bibby and Mr.Murland expressed the opinion that as no fixtures for winter racing had yet been advertised, it was somewhat premature to come to or announce any decision at present.    They both were also strongly of opinion that steeple-6&apos;aasing was necessary in order to maintain the class of horse re-quired for Army purposes.LORD CURZON said that he would mention to his colleagues, the view jusf expressed, that a decision as regards steepleohasing was prematuro,    but he could hoia out no hope that the decision would be reconsidered.The conference closed.
Qojpjjr.....pfjlettgrj da,toQgnd May, 1916 ,r - from Pros!dent tBear Lord Jersey,In aecordance with tha decision of the War Cabinet, which Lord Curzon announced to you at the conference which he.and I had with yourself and. other representatives of the Jockey Club on the 17th inst, on the subject of horse racing, I now write to confirm  what Lord Cur2on -said at the&quot;meeting.The Government fully recognise the national importance of horse &quot;breeding and also realise thai to maintain the Thoroughbred Breeding Industry of this country, a limited amount of racing is essential,&apos; &quot;but in view of the great strain on the facilities available on the railways for dealing with essential trafficj it has been decidedThat-no flat racing should he allowed after the gist May, except at Newmarket, the dates for race meetings at Newmarket being fixed by the&apos;Jockey Club, subject to&apos; the approval of H(M,Government, and that no extra trains should be run to Hewmarket for the conveyance of race-goers, or tickets sold to Newmarket beyond the capacity of the ordinary trains *In conveying this decision to you, I desire to say how much I appreciate the loyal co-ope ration of the Stewards of the Jocket Club in dealing with these matters.   .Yours sincerely,(Sgd.)A.H. STANLEY.The RtoHon,The Sari, of Jersey, J.P.,Senior Steward of the&apos; Jockey Club, 15, Cavendish Sq,, W.  -
APOTDIX IIFLAT HACIHG.i[DateB,1915Comparative List of MeetingsMo. of Dates,days racing.1917fch 24th to June 1st (9 meetings).9th to Hov;3rd (13 meetings)23 36April 17th to May 4th (S meetings)Ho, ofdays raging7(Racing stopped by Government, resumed July 17th),July 17th to Mot,17th (SO meetings)Total. 5942-11&apos;.***V&apos;tTotal 49If no meetings are allowed, except at Newmarket, after 1st June, the following meetings only will take place:-Days.June 4-th - Hewmarket 1st extra meeting-I-     ..     .   .. .... mS tt&quot; 18th -;ndJuly 2nd - 1st July meeting&quot; 16th - End   &quot; &quot;SeptJ^Qth- Srd Hewmarket extra meeting Oct^lst   i 1st October meeting OctaSth. - 2nd      &quot; &quot;0ct*89th -&apos; Hqughton meeting3 3 4 &quot;8 4 4 4 429 daysCompared with 42 days racing 1 from July 17th to Uov,lYth, 1917 and compared -with 28 days racing at Hewmarket only from Jxily 17th to HovT6th,1917STEEPLECHASE MEETINGSList of Meetings 1915 - 1916, and 1916 * 1917,1915 - 19161916 - 1917raciniBo. ofat to Dec.31stst to Mar.31st (14 meetings)TotalMil2727Dec .1st to Dec.28th (5 meetings)Jan.3rd to Apl ,&apos;13th (14 meetings)28JJ6Under the proposals of the President of the Board of Trade there would he no steeplechase meetings during the ensuing winter.%, v?hi te hal 1 Gardens, S .W. 17th May, 1918

</content>
</cab>
