<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/52/0 images: 121-124</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Heport relating to the War Work of the Board of Agriculture for Scotland for the week ending 22n&amp; May, 1918.mi _.   FOOD PRODUCTION.During the week dry, warm weather has prevailed, but local thunder-showers have boen of considerable benefit.   The appearance of pastures and brairds continues to be satisfactory although is some districts wireworm is reported to be causing damage to grain, especially on land ploughed out of old grass. The rapid growth of the past few days will however tend to counteract the ravages.Lamb Orop 1918.    Hill lambings are practically complete and the crop of lambs is satisfactory, although not much beyond the normal.    Losses of lambs have occurred in some districts from &quot;trembling&quot;, and in practically all districts from &quot;milk sourness&quot;.    The lambs themselves are of good quality and ewes are milking well.    The death rate among, old sheep during the winter and spring months has been much below the average.2*   Improvement of Hill Pastures.    Representatives of the Board visited the Border District and interviewed representative farmers on the subject of Improvement of the Hill Pastures with a view to a greater head of cattle being bred and reared. These interviews took place at Roberton and Teviothead in Roxburghshire, at Langholm in Eskdalemuir, Dumfries-shire, and in the Ettriok and Yarrow valleys in Selkirkshire.3. Emergency Sub-Committee of Wason Committee. A meeting of this Advisory Committee took place on 18th instant and the following subjects, inter alia, were disoussed and considered:-(a) Allocation of Grass Parks in the season 1919.(b) The draft definition of &quot;seed&quot; potatoes submitted by theAdvisory Committee of the Ministry of Food.(c) Suggested control prices of cereals grown in 1918.(d) /
(d) The threatened dispersion of hill sheep stocks.(e) Land Drainage in Scotland with particular referenceto the application to Sootland of subsections (h) to (n) of Seotion 1 of Clause 2M of the Defence of the Realm Regulation.4*   Supply of Fertilisers for the season 1918-19.    Underthe Fertilisers Prices. Order 1918 the control of the distribu-:tion and the equalisation of costs of distribution of Super-:phosphate, Sulphate of Ammonia and Ground Basic Slag have been  -delegated by the Ministry of Munitions to the three Departmentsof Agriculture in the United Kingdom jointly.Following on this arrangement, three advisory Committees consisting of representatives of the Board and of the Scottish fertilisers trade have been formed to advise the Board with regard to the administration of the scheme for the distribution, as far as Sootland Is concerned, of the three fertilisers specified above.Under tho Order, maximum prices are fixed for the sale of. the above-named fertilisers as from 1st June 1918, to 31st May v . 1919.    These prices are, on the average, the same as those ruling in 1917, except that in the case of Basic Slag a small increase is made to cover Increased oost of manufacture.The Order also prescribes arrangements for distributing the fertilisers throughout the country and circulars stating partio-rulars of these arrangements are being sent by the 3oard to makers, merchants, dealers and co-operative societies.   Farmers -are being requested to place orders with the Merchants or Co-operative Societies from whom they usually obtain supplies.$he supplies of the fertilisers in question are not likely to be sufficient to meet all demands.    The sliding scales of prices rising according to date of delivery are designed to make/
make it worth the farmer&apos;s while to take early delivery, and the Board are taking steps to impress upon farmers that it ie only by so doing that they oan make sure of obtaining . supplies.II.   OOLLBOTION OF STATISTICS AND RETURNS RELATING TO AGRICULTURE.A table is appended showing the estimated number of eaoh class of live stock in Scotland at 4th May, with the usual comparisons.III.   RECRUITING OP AGRICULTURAL WORKERS. RELEASE OF MEN FROM SCOTLAND.The Board have dieousaed with the Director of National * Servioe (Scottish Region) the question of the quota applicable to Scotland of agricultural workers to be released for Military Servioe comparable with the 30,000 men whom it has been arranged to release from agriculture in England and Wales.IV.   S00TTISH WOMEN * S RURAL INSTITUTES.&quot; Steps have been taken to form an Institute at SpeanBridge.
compared with the Humber *t 4th June,  1917, and the ESTIMATED NUMBER at 4th April,  1918.	Total at 4th June 1917.	Estimate at 4th Hay.1918.	Difference between 4th May &amp; 4th June 1918.        1917.		Estimate at 4th April 1918.	Estimate a 4th May, 1918.	i    Difference t   4th May anc I                   191	between I 4th April L8.			Aotusl	Per float.			Actual.	Per sentCows la Omits, but not Heifers in Calf (i.e. with	So. 847000 46000 50000	Ho. 320000 79000 63000	No. -    27000 f   34000 f      3000	-   7.8 f 75.6 *   6.0	No. 285000 120000 57000	No. 320000 79000 53000	Ho. t   35000 -   41000 4000	% f 12.5 - 34.2 - 7.0f&apos;*.*oer Cattle:-^ yr&amp;.c.ld and a&amp;owe ...... 1 yr. &amp; under 2 yre.eld... Vnder 1 Vr.old (including calves) T a) Bom before 4th !   April 1918. (b)Born Binoe 4th April 1918. TOTAL OATTLB	442066 231000 892000 (24S00O (	452000 225000 301000 2560001	f    10000 6000 f     9000 f   11000	f    2.3 -   2.6 1   3.1 f   4.4	462000 225000 292000 * 194000) 68000)	452000 225000 301000 194000) 62000)	-    10000 f     9000 *V*W*W*V 6000	- 2.2 5.1 i - 8.8 i	1Z100OO	1234(360	f    24000	f    2.0	1241000	12S4OC0	7000              -   0.6	Kxea kept for breeding Other Sheep:- Under 1 yr. o\d Including lambe) 1 3Tr*old and above ..... TOTAL SHEEP	5087000 25541000 1212000	5156000 1650000 914000	f 109000 -1004000 - 298000	i    3.6 - 38.1 - 24.6	3147000 1030000 626000	31S3000 16S0000 914CC0	-    11000 i 600000 288000	-   0.3 f 58.3 4 46.0	6873000	5680000	-1193000	- 17.4	480b000	568CCG0	-;- 877&quot;D00&quot;	-t IS-3 own *ep% for breeding ***** Other Figs of all agee ***** TOTAL PIG8 **	16000 116000	15000 105000	-    13000	- 11.0	10000 93000	15000 305000	1000 f    12CC0	-    6.3 \  12.9	135000	.120000	-    13000	-   9.8	109000	120CC0	f    11000	t 10.1 i- -       -1* Born before 4th Karoh 1928* ** Born since 4th March 1913.

</content>
</cab>
