<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/52/0 images: 142-144</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(Thin DbcumAnf i* tn- . WMIM fl. if&amp;ujI, Mi tad^ A 8/A/a s^3/inn wBOARD OE AGRICULTURE AM) FISHERIES. Report for the week ended 21at May, 1918,Partner3 and Income Tax,In order to carry out the promises made in the House of Commons during the discussion on the Budget Resolutions, the Board, after consultation with the Board of Inland Revenue, have issued an explanatory memorandum in simple terms explaining how the new &quot;budget proposals would affeot farmers, and indicating a simple form of account which a farmer should keep if he desired to he assessed for income tax on his profits.    Thie memorandum was issued in the form of a press notice, through the Press Bureau, to all newspapers and it appeared on the 17th instant.Thousands of applications have been received from farmers for.copies of the notice.    Some two thousand copies have &quot;been issued to tHe Agricultural Executive Committees in England and Wales with a view to the information &quot;being brought to the notice of farmers, and the large number1 ot application^ received from individuals for copies of the notice indicated the lively interest taken by farmers in the matter.Land Division.ana.ll Holding Colonies.Heath Hill.    The weather has been good for cleaning the land and progress had/been made with potatoes, 22   acres having been tenanted,    34 acres of small seeds, clover etc., have been sown during the week; and all the spring corn has been rolled, viz, 214 acres.Holbeaoh.    The principal farming operations during the week consisted of horse hoeing and harrowing of potatoes, carrying out the farmyard manure and clamping in readiness to put on the land after harvest.     The sdttlers are all doing satisfactorily and are being employed on the Various farms on durrent farm work, all of which will be very beneficial to them when th^jrclaim holdings of their own. All the crops on the Colony are locking remarkably well.flax Production Branch.Weeding of the flax crop is now generally in progress and is being fairly satisfactorily carried out.    The work on factory premises and machinery proceeds on the lines indicated on previous reports.    Hews has just come to hand of an outbreak of a fire at Yeovil factory which has unfortunately destroyed the scutching shed.    The new scutching shed is nearing completion, so that it will soon be possible to rc-employ the scutching hands.    In the meantime they are being used to assist in the fields.Tithe, Commons, Copyhold and Survey Branch,Among the applications received during the past week were three for Altered Apportionment, one for Redemption and one for Merger of Tithe Rentcharge;   one for Enfranchisement of Copyhold Land and two for the Board1s approval to the levying of rates upon the owners of stints to meet the expenses incurred or to be incurred by the Conservators of Winter and Kaber, and Crosby Garrett Commons (both in Westmorland), while five Redemptions, three Mergers, and 8 Enfranchisements of Copyhold have been confirmed.
mJoint Committee of the Board of Agriculture and fisheries and the Minietry of J&apos;ood.The difficulty of seouring VToman labour in certain districts for work on the land has been brought to the notice of the Committee&apos;1 s Representatives at meetings they have attended.Evidence is accumulating that the response to the various appeals made for increased cultivation of the potato has been of a most satisfactory character and that the million acres asket for are likely to be forthcoming,      A considerable number Of applications for the Joint Committee&apos;s Leaflet Ho. 5* (&quot;The Potato Crop&quot;) has been received from the Agricultural Exeoutive Committees and others.As a result of the stimulus given to Home Cheese Production in Kent through Mr6 Blaekshawrs lecture at Tunbridge V?ells on April 12th last, the Joint Committee has been asked to secure Mr. Blackshaw-s services for certain districts in Lancashire,,    A lecture at Rye, Sussex, is also being arranged.At the request of the Ministry of Pood, the Joint Committee has been asked to lay special stress on the importance of keeping cattle back that can possibly put on weight, and at tho same time to urge that it is a patriotic duty to consume frozen meat.-     It is the Ministry&apos;s desire to overcome the reluctance, in certain quarters, to accept frozen meat of       which there is now a large supply in the country.Pig Production Section.A large amount of correspondence has taken place, some as to the formation of pig clubs and ereotion of sties, but the major portion has referred to the difficulty in obtaining feeding stuffs.    In many of the latter cases tho writers seemed to be unaware that they should obtain Priority Certificates.    There have been various interviews and communications with the Local Government Board as to the procedure in connection with the powers given by the aaondmont of Regulation 2(o) of the Defence of the Realm Act, and the Rules that have to be drawn up.    There have also been a fair number of callers asking for advice on various matters relating to pig keeping.Ordnance Survey..During the week ending 22nd May 1918, 53,000 maps were sent to France and 11,000 to the Admiralty.   8 relief models were sent to France.Publications Branch.The number of applications for ordinary issues of the Leaflets was 995, in response to which 4116 copies of Leaflets were despatched.     In addition 24,000 copies of leaflets were despatched to applicants for supplies in bulk for distribution.    A further supply of 21,000 leaflets was sent to the Government Information Bureaux as explained in previous Reports, while 11,200 copies were forwarded to the Railway Companies for distribution through Booking Offices.    During the week the revised edition of Leaflet No. 244 (The Destruction of Rats) was published and copies were distributed to 10,500 persons on the Leaflet List.    Th^ Kay issue of the Board&apos;s Journal was sent to Press.
Fisheries Division,.Administrative Section.    With the assistance of the Division an &quot;&apos;&quot;&quot;L ni.&quot; agreement&apos;has-been arrived at between the Lune Fishery Board and the Lancaster Corporation in connection with the water scheme now before Parliament, and the Promoters have agreed to pay over  1,000 to be devoted to the advantages of the fisheries in the district.    Enquiry is being made into questions which &apos; have arisen regarding alleged restrictions on fishing operations in Christohurch Harbour.   A memorandum with regard to the position as affecting the Freshwater Fish in this country has been, prepared for the information of the Consumers&apos; Council, Ministry of Food,    An Officer of the Board has conferred with the North Eastern Committee on the subject of the proposed Order relaxing,      fishing restrictions off the North East coast,.    A Conference with the Cumberland Committee with regard to similar action off thoir ooast is about to be held, and an Order relaxing trawling regulations on the North Wales Coast has been drafted.totorJLoan ^Section.    Another of the St. Ives bpats has now beenengined by the Coramitte---and has run a successful trial.    A very good account has been received from Brixharo of the successful fishing of two of the Special Service boats at that port during the recent fine weather, when very .large catches were brought in. Two fresh applications   have come in from Tenby, making six in all since the Committee recently installed an engine in a fishing boat at that port.Frosh Water giah Section.   Proposals have been made to the Corporation -     &apos;of ^eymouth&apos; regarding the installation of an Bel trap in waters controlled by the Corporation and designs for other straps are being pressed forward.    The elver fishery at Epney has come to an end on account of the closing of the Elver run, and operations there have been suspended until next year,.Pern^t,, Section.    77 Permits have been issued and 15 cancelled.Pi sh J pod Secti on.    The Admiralty have requested tha Committee to &quot;buy on tneir behalf large quantities of nets, ropes, salt, nails and other^articles required in connection with the scheme for fishing in the White Sea.There is still a large demand for light barrels, for the carriage of shell fish, but considerable difficulty is experienced in finding supplies, as the only barrels available are the Norwegian barrels which are, too heavy for the purpose, and such few lighter barrels as there are are being sold by the Salvage Department for other purposes at prices which are quite out of reach of the fishermen.The Post Office sacks have not proved entirely satisfactory as many have holes in them, and others are too small &apos;&apos; for the purpose, but the price is so low that the Committee do not anticipate incurring any appreciable loss, and it is worth spending a small   sum in order to meet the requirements of the trade.The Committee are engaged, at the request of the United . Kingdom Linseed Oil Consumers Association Ltd., who control the output on behalf of the Food Controller, in obtaining a census   of the quantity of oil, required in this country for oilskins in a year, with a view to a possible reduction of the output.The normal work of the Board proceeds on lines indicated in previous reports.24th Hay, 1918.Secretary.

</content>
</cab>
