<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/52/0 images: 158-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JThls DocMnwent Is the Property ofHis Brltanwlo Majesty&apos;s Government.&apos;.12Ho.   O.A.B./205.SECRETGeneral Headquarters, British Armies in Prance 22nd May, 1918.Sir,I have the honour to forward herewith a report received from the G.O.O., Royal Air Force, on the bombing raid carried out by the OCHBY Squadrons on the 18th instant.I have the honour to be, Sir,Your obedient Servant,(Sgd.) K. Wigram,Brig.&quot;Gen.for Field Marshal, Commanding&quot;in-Chief, British Armies in FRANCE.The Secretary, War Office,LONDON, S.W.
At 6.55 a,m. 6 De Havilland 4s. left to bomb the Railway Station and Sidings at COLOGNE.   The formation consisted of six. picked pilots, and reached 12,000 feet in 40 minutes. Crossing the lines at HOMENY and proceeding East of TREVES, where a heavy barrage was put up, to the RHINE which wag reached at BOM, the objective&apos; was reached at 9.0 &amp;.m. 6 - 112 lb., 24 - 25 lb. and 50 - 40 lb. (phosphorous) bombs, total weight 1,392 lbs., were dropped from 14,500 feet.   Four bursts were observed on the Railway Sheds, two on the Rail?/ay and many other bursts around the objective..6 Enemy aircraft followed the fermation from BONN and 4 -attacked over the objective.   One was immediately driven down under control clouds of steam and petrol being observed issuing from the machine.   The remainder broke off the attack.The return journey was set on a course West of the outward i journey.   6 Enemy aircraft again attached our formation East of i THIOWVILLE.   By skilful manoeuvring one pilot enabled his observer to fire a good burst at a range of about 30 yards into one Enemy aircraft when it was broadside on.   This machine was observed to go down completely out of control.   The fighting continued to the lines.   Just the other side of the lines one of our machines was attacked by two Enemy aircraft one of which the observer shot down completely out of control.   Unfortunately the other machine succeeded in mortally wounding this observer, and he died before he could reach the Aerodrome to give in his report.   When the pilot of this machine put his nose down to glide into the Aerodrome, the body of the observer fell on to the control stick, causing the machine to be wrecked, the pilot being severely injured in the head..All machines had returned by 11,20 a.m.A total of 47 plates were exposed, which show very good results. Approximately 1,400 rounds of S.A.A, were fired in combats.Anti-aircraft fire over the objective was very poor, the majority of the bursts being 5,000 feet below the formation.The Enemy aircraft which attacked were D3 or D5 Albatros Scouts and one or two Phalz Scouts with an armament of two synchronised guns per machine.   On the whole the attack of the enemy machines wero feeble, their tactics being to dive sn our machines and not remain in the combat longer than they could possibly help.The average time of the formation was 4 hours 30 minutes. The weather was chiefly clear with a few drifting clouds, wind only 1 m,p.h, S.E. between 11,000 and&apos; 16,000 feet.(Signed)   C.L.N. NEWALL.Brigadier-General, G.0.C, 8th Brigade. In the Field. Royal Air Force.19 th May 1918..DETAILED REPORT OK BOMB RAID CARRIED OUT 18th MAY 1918.

</content>
</cab>
