<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/52/0 images: 260-270</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
jmlfyj    *****Political Intelligence Department,dfidential.FOREIGN OFFICE!.U.S.A./008.May 23rd, 1918.MEMORANDUM&apos;  UNITED 3OTES;  ARTY POLITICS AND THE NOVEMBER EltECTIONS.&quot;There have been during this period (i.e., since thf ontry of lie United States into the war) very grave faults and shortcomings and days In governmental work.     But thoy were not due to the action of&apos;-; ongross:   and the action of the republicans In Congress was aonsist-vntly designed to correct them.&quot;We are pledged to the hilt as a naticn to put this war through\iithout flinching until we win the peaoe of overwhelming victory.&apos; e are pledged to secure for each well-behaved nation the right to ontrol its tv/n-destinies and to live undominated and unharmed by there so long as it does not harm others.&quot;This is the people&apos;s war.     It is not the president&apos;s war.   It s not Congress&apos;s war.  &apos; It is the duty of the republican party tohand like a rodk against inefficiency, incompetence, hesitation and elay no loss than against luko-warmness in serving the common cause:&apos; if ourselves and our allies,     To support a public -servant who does irong is as profoundly unpatriotic as to oppose a public servant whooes right...............,&quot;It is not only our duty to be prepared against war.    It is, if ossible, even more dur7duty to prepare for peaoe.    And we are almost s unprepared in one respeot as the other.    Moreover, in the affrirs f peaoe, as in the affairs of war, let us as grown men, as serious itizens of a great republic, impatiently brush aside the silly sham-.; rust in rhetoric as a substitute for aotion.j-    &quot;We cannot afford any longer to oontinue our present industrial social system, or rather no system of every-man-for-himself and levil-take-the-hindmost.     It is * our business as a nation seriously-1-/to
faoo our indue trial conditions, to realise tlvt no oennot without permit tham to go on unchanged, and yot thct wo arc worse than j)ls if wc permit their, tc be changed for evil.    Theroforo wo must in equally tho Bourbon reactionaries who invite disastor by refusing f*e*. and grapple with th of the hour, and the sinister domft-Juos and loosc-minacd visionaries who preach a rod folly that would ng us to cvon worse disaster...... It&apos;s the way wo shoot thet counts,the way we shout.&quot;These extracts from Colonel Roosevelt&apos;s spoech at the Republican pte Convention at Portland, Maine, at the end of March may fairly bo (ten as the keynote of the Republican campaign.    Vague, like all -fcha ^-President&apos;s utterances&apos;, they are not vaguer than were Mr. Wilstnrs prances in 1912 when he carried the Democratic Party out of the jjido8 of opposition on a programme which he himself said merely &quot;at-[apted te express the new spirit of our politics and to set forth in prge terms, which may stick in the imagination, what it is that must &apos; dtno if we are to restore our politics to their full spiritual jour again.&quot;All oppositions, when they bid for power, are critioal, not eon-ruotive,     A prominent member of the Republican Party in Congress ked the writer last November what could be done in the country to prove America&apos;a co-operation with the Allies in tho war.     On being Id that the worst obstacle to full co-operation at that time was o administration^ reluctance to call on tho country to mako saori-oes of business and comfort, and that the best thing the Republican jjrty, with Its large following among business men, oould do was to oach the necessity of suoh sacrifices and the country&apos;s willingness mako them, he repliod that it was tho duty of the party in power announce suoh a policy and, in effect, that tho opposition ctuld be expected to oxohange the safety of criticism for tho odium of popular appeals to patriotism.     Thus solf-condonmod to an attitudo/of
oritioism, tho success of an opposition depends not on the validity .^y.ts indefinite formulae but on the existence among tho people of a aeral dissatisfaction with the party in power.     Such dissatisfaction jjrmcated the country in 1912 and to it Mr. Wilson made his appeal, os a similar dissatisfaction exist to-day?Undoubtedly it does.     The President&apos;sadministrative record is t good.     There has been much muddling at Washington, resulting not ly in a patent unprb^aredncsD to meot the crisis of the war, but al-in much inconvenience and suffering throughout the country.     It is obablo that In December and January the prestige of the administra-.on had sunk very lew.     The Senate investigations had nearly made cretary Baker look like a fool, while the weather had entirely suc-eded in making Dr. Garfield, tho Fuel Administrator, look like one, Iring these months even i&apos;r. Hoover&apos;e prestige was tottering, while e breakdown of traffic, coming just at the moment when a vast pro-famme of ship-yard construction was in its most difficult stage, in-lived Mr. Hurley also in apparent failure.Since then, however, the Administration has somewhat recovered s position.     The taking over of the railroads, the organisation of ie Shipping Control Committee, tho re-organisation of.the War Depart-lent and reforms in the War Industries Board, Mr. Baker&apos;s visit to krope, resulting, as such visits often do^ in a sotft of indefinite ooess of prestige, -and a general  tilling together and opening out of he Departments at Washington, has created at least an apbearanoo of [rcster efficiency.     The President has two great assets - tho un-lounded admiration accorded by the country to his statements on the iar and foreign affairs, and the fact that his Cabinet contains one irst-class. administrator in Mr. MoAdoo.The net result o  these developments cannot be judged from the ^vo elections which respectively preceded and succeeded the winter low-water mark of the &apos;Administration.     Both the municipal,election  ; n Now York in November,. 1917,. and the Senatorial election in Wis-- r -       :     .       /      &apos;  /censin
&apos; jinsin in March, 1910, centred too much round local issues and peculiariEditions.     The only common feature of the two contests was a great icrease in the Socialist vote, comparable to that which marker! tho irosidontial election of 1912, only to fall away again in that of ,; This phenomenon is an interesting and difficult one, but it.os outside the scope of the present peper. The Socialist Party, latever its strength, cannot appreciably affect the elections next iivember or influence national policy fdr seme time to come.Perhaps, however, the opinion may be hazarded that both those actions indicated, or gave rise to, a Certain disgust at partisan iitics.     It is in this sentiment that the Republican Party will et its greatest difficulties,- 11The dissatisfaction of the country is by no means exclusively jrectcd against government officials,     The record of &quot;big business&quot;, &apos;edominantly Republican in its political affiliations, has been little I1 no better than that of tho administration.     In tho eyes of the Iorago man it can only escape the charge *f inefficiency by incurring io worse one of profiteering selfishness.     Neither accusation would i wholly unjust.     The dissatisfaction of the average man extends al-i, in tho present situation, to the action of Congress quite as much ! to the action of executive officials - Congress which so often ap-ars in the popular cartoons as a &quot;talking shop&quot; and a ,vhot-air utory&quot;.     Now, it is precisely to the average man, especially to tho orago man of tho Middle West, that the Republican Party has to appeal ! it is to attain success.     It was the strong divergence in sonti-nt and aims between this average man and tho leaders of finance and iidustry that led to the Progressive split in the Republican Party in ^__^.^1__. ijb_.__/1912__i)     In 1908 the Socialist candidate for President polled 420,793 tes, in 1912, 901,873, and in 1916, 590,415.     In tho recent-oloc-4ons in New York and Wisconsin the Socialist candidates togethor piled a total of nearly, if not quite, a ouartor cf a million votes.
^2 and, in the. words of a recent historian of contemporary politics, he one fact unmistakably established (by the Presidential olootion 1916) was thrt the Republican-Progrossivo broach of 1912 had not on healed&quot;.It is not hcalea yet.     Throughout 191V a great parade of healing s elaborately gone through.     Consorvativo-Ropublioan loaders like nator Smoot, visited Colonel Roosevelt at Oyster Bay.    Hires wore lied;   Mr. Taft was publicly reconciled to the Colonel;   tho shoop o had been divided from the goats with so much righteous indignation 1912 were hurriedly horded into tho same fold again.     The process inatcd in the mooting of tho National Committee of the Party in bruary.     There was a severe fight in which tho Progressive wing won, curing the election of their candidato, Hays of Indiana, as National airman.     But the viotory was won on a side issue - on the cxistenoe a letter showing that the candidate of the Conservative wing, who d been in Germany in August, 1914, had at that iimo been misled into e Gorman view of the origins of tho war.    Hays, himself a Middle stern Radical in sentiment, but before all things e judicious partyInager, is associated on the Committee with strong Conservatives, and e Democrats, as well as many independent Liberals, are loud in their fsertions that reactionaries like ex-Senator Crane and (to put it &apos;ankly) &quot;grafters&quot; like Senator Penrose, have re-established their ntrol over the party machine.In this situation, can the Republican party amalgamate the diver-nt views of its members into a clear issue for the electorate?    It rtainly could not in a Presidential Campaign, but a Congressional irpaign permits of the dressing up of local issues and. the shading of inions according to the exigencies of the particular constituency to degree impossible when the v/hole country is being asked to vo*te for single man.     That is partly why, at Presidential elections, the re-lilt of the vote for President is often widely different from that of tie vote for Congressmen.     This was a marked characteristic of the-5- /last
last election, when the Republicans only iris sod control of the Hous*/&apos;of jjjreeentativefl by a single seat in spite of the fact that Wilson pol-jod *yer 500,000 votes more than Hughes.     Wo prophecy as to the re-salts of the election next November would therefore be possible without m exhaustive nonsidoration of the records of individual Republicans jiu- Deraoorats in Congress and a &quot;thorough study of the range of local issues which can be raised.    When the writer left the &apos;0,S. at tho be-rinning of April, Republicans themselvfeB felt it impossible to hazard I my reliable prophecy, knowing that their ouooess or failure must de-lend wholly on the course of the war and the volume of the American ffort in it during the coming months.But, from the point of view of popular dislike of partisanship, his is just the point.     It is the war that counts in the election. ;he Republican Party has deliberately decided that it shall be the ping that counts.     Efficiency in the war is their platform.     It eems certain that last autumn the Democratic Party managers in tho iddle Y/est offered the Republicans fusion in certain States.     The :epublicans refused on the deliberate calculation that a coalition ad-inistration would be iutile without Republican control of the House f Representatives, while, such control once secured, a coalition couldforced on the President and would then constitute a severe blow c&amp;o is prestige.     It was probably as a basis for this strategy that the epublioans have on various occasions attempted the formation of a Con-ressional viar Committee on the analogy of the &quot;Committee on the Gonduet f the War&quot; set up in 1861.     A Party which adopts this attitude cannot ido off on looal issues:   sueh issues may save it but they cannot make t safe.     Nothing can make it safe but coherent action in regard to he war and in the absence of national Issues the campaign will tend o take on the tone of pettiness and bitterness common to all ill-de-IJilted contests.     That indeed is the real danger of the situation, for fvectives and.satires do not elevate morale.Colonel Rossevelt is justified in much of his claim on behalf of le Republicans in Congress.     They have in fact supported, war measures.-6- /For
or instance, when some of the Democratic loaders refused in April, ay, to father the conscription bill it was piloted through the Bouso 1/ Kahn, a Republican of German birth.     But on the othor hand their ppoals for drastic action by the administration have been mixed with ittor accusations that the President is seeking the power of a Tsar, hey have delayed the passage of the Overman Bill and are now critici-ing Mr, MoAfl ooTs proposals for an increase of direct taxation.   They illed the censorship provisions of the Espionage Act.     Thoy have made he no?/ sedition bill tho opportunity for much petulant criticism and olonel Roosevelt has attacked it violently as unconstitutional.   Their pposition to those latter measures was based on rooted distrust of one i the President&apos;s confidants, Mr. George Oreel, Chairman of the Com-ittee of Public Information, who in some measure controls orcss oen-jorship.     But, throughout, thoy have been unable to explain such ap-arent inconsistencies by any clear definition of their position, gainst tho cold clarity of the President&apos;s rare public statements hey can only oppose a medloy of speeches on the floor of tho House or nate, which have been on the whole impressive neither in their form jjor their temper.     Such speeches&apos;are not a strong record for a party hich, on another issue, attacks tho President for his empty verbosity.Moreover, the Republicans started their career as the party of jatriotic efficiency with tho handicap of their record in 1916.     Then,now, they were concerned mainly to take the opposite lino to the Resident and, while many concentrated their attacks on his weakness owards Germany, the strong anti-British elemont then existing in the arty found, expression through loaders like Mann and Cooper in senti-ents almost pro-German in their tendencies.     The logical result of his two-faced criticism was the muddled debacle of the Hughes cam-aign and Republican prestige has not yet recovered from that blow. m recent election in Wisconsin has already afforded the Democratic [arty an opportunity to bring up against their opponents the record of he Republicans who in 1916 voted, with Mr. Mclemore, to forbid Ameri-ins taking passage on armed ships./finally,
Finally, the greatest handicap to Republican success is the Absence of a leader.    The return to Colonel Roosevelt is for only a few the choice of an indomitable and inspiring leader;   for the many it is a confession of bankruptcy,     He is not ? back-number, but he is a trump already played.     His grestest strength was a quality of novelty and unexpectedness dear to the heart of so many jaded electors who, knowing their own insufficiency, hope only for a government which will surprise them.     This quality he no longer possesses;   even those who admire him most know exact-ly what kind of opinions and action they can expect from him. He is representative of the Republican Party only in his tempera-rnent - in a capacity for practical affairs, a muddiress of the speculative faculty, and a certain coarseness of tone and temper which are perhaps the dominant Republican strength and weakness. In those qualities and defects lies the real contrast between the Republicans and Wilson.     A large proportion of the American peo-\ pie would, probably like to see Republicans, and. especially Roose-I velt, in responsible administrative positions at Washington, but it is very doubtful whether they would wish to entrust the de-finition of American policy or the education of American opinion to anyone but Mr. Wilson.     The monotonous violence of Roose-velfs articles in the &quot;Kansas1 City Star ! have not excited ap-proval.     The lew York Tribune&apos;^ &quot;Roosevelt boom&quot;, launched on April 1, seems to have fallen rather flat.  . Cn the whole, in the absence cf a definite national issue or something like a national disaster, to neither of which the Republicans can yet point, the average man would, probably like to see fusion and will dismiss as unworthy partisanship any widespread effort by either party to win new seats,No safe conclusion is, then, possible about the coming election.     But the international aspect of the situation can be more clearly defined.     Both parties are wholeheartedly &quot;in-8- /the
jjthe war&quot;.    The elections will revolve round no broad issue of foreign I policy nor affect the strength of the United States as a belligerent, j So ifist opinion will have to seek refuge with the Socialists or with the &quot;Hon Partisan League&quot;, a new agrarian party in the Middle west; Us between the two great parties, there is, on the one hand very lit-&apos; tie to be hoped, from the Republicans in the way of increased Anierioan efficiency in the war.     There is more to be hoped from the younger Democrats in the House like Mr. Sherley than from any Republican mem-ber.    There is no personality in the United States remotely able to compete with Mr. Wilson&apos;s dominating influence.     His foreign policy may be wordy and ill-defined tut no one else has a policy at all. Moreover, he is too astute and too laoking in fixed principles of political action to be ]$.nned to any position where he would be ob-liged to take the defensive.     He covers those &quot;illiberal&quot; admini-strative acts inseparable from war by an evolving radicalism of social policy.    labile he censors criticism and penalises free speech, he writes to his Hew Jersey supporters about the &quot;economic serfdom&quot; of the present industrial system.     He will alwavs knowj both in his foreign and in his internal policy, how to appeal to labour,.     So long as he is the Democratic leader, it is with him and with his party that British policy has mainly to count.On the other hand, his figure has perhaps eclipsed too much abroad the existence of the other party.     The Republican Pariy is a great force which will not remain long in the shade.   Unless Mr. VJilson runs in 1920 for a third term the Democratic Party will also lack a satisfactory leader and in such a situation it has probably less natural and traditional capacity for cohesion anr] discipline than its opponents.     The most likely candidate for leadership at present is Mr. McAdoo, an administrator of great ability and a politician of come astuteness but a man with little grasp of policy or integrity of thought, who will never command the same respect in the country as Mr. Wilson.    VJe have
[in the past year done not a little to offend Republicans,    Colonel Jtoosevelt has more than once privately complained of our &quot;flattery&quot; )i the President and neither he nor his followers are rersonable nough to appreciate our position.     Encomiums of America&apos;s record, pronounced &quot;by Englishmen at moments when the Administration was ;mder severe investigation by its opponents, have created much bad feeling in the Republican ranks.     One leader said privately at the md of last year that if Britain &quot;stood, up for&apos;1&apos; a bungling Deme-sratio Administration he did not see why the Republicans should be jiore friendly to her after the war than they were &quot;before.    We have aot - to quote another American - &quot;left cards&apos;: on the Republicans, jmd they are correspondingly sore.All this is inevitable and. we can do little to avoid it. Party politics in the United States are not our &quot;business-     But there Is one way in which we might, by inadvertent action, give the Republicans the popular issue for which they are looking and almost ensure their eventual success at the polls.     The industrial, finan-sial ano commercial community always tends towards :epublioanisnu The Republicans have, as a party, a vastly greater aptitude for handling tariff and business legislation.     At the present moment the Democratic Party, thanks almost entirely to Mr. Wilson himself, has a record of constructive commercial and. financial legislation, Ihe Currency Act, the ^ebb Bill and other acts have enhanced their prestigo, and the business boom during the war has saved then from the unpopularity in.which the Sinmonds-Underwood Tariff mi $it have involved them.     But the drastic restrictions on commerce with ivhitfh, as a war government, they are necessarily identified, while accepted loyally by the bulk of the business community, cannot fail to bring with them the growing unpopularity which will always fin all countries attach to official regulation of trade.-Already there are signs of this unpopularity.     The puTcli-oation of the Government trade statistics foi February and the
months preceding gave rise recently to seme murmurs in the oom-loial press, while on April 3, in a press interview, the Manager JrThe National Association of Manufacturers, a powerful body repre-liting the most &quot;Bourbon&quot; section of American industrialists, at-Iked &quot;the thoroughly dangerous propaganda connected with efforts close many of our industries as non-essential&quot;, and pointed to example of &quot;England, wisest of nations in trade affairs who&quot;, he ,d, &quot;is doing all that is possible to maintain her foreign trade i supplant h^r enemies in international markets, and while doing is looking after her ov.n interests without taking others intoaount.&quot;      (This gentleman will assuredly vote Republican in Hfivem-lf and the Republican Party will not hesitate tc exploit any such bmercial discontent as it grows up.     That cannot be helped and p psychological moment for Republican championship of trade in-*ests has not yet arrived.     But we shall do well to remember at all this restriction of trade by the Administration inevlt-Ly takes the form of, and is indeed based upon, co-operation with jiand.    v.:e are endeavouring to attract the United States into )ser and closer co-operation with us both in war and post-war momic measures.     It is vital that we should, do everything to te such co-operation popular and to eliminate suspicions as to f pur-poses and misinformation as to the facts of our commercial sition.    If in any way, by silence, by inability to explain our siticn cloarly, or by inept words cr acts, we were to encouragettead of eliminating the suspicions which undoubtedly already st both in Hew York and. in the American Commercial community London, we might, and almost certainly should, enable the Re-jtlican Party to re-appear in its traditional role as the defen-p of American industry, on a programme calculated to revive the pent anti-British tendencies of some of its leaders, wipe out eh of the popularity we have recently acquired among its members roughout the Middle TTest, and carry it once more into power at shingtcn.&apos;    - -11-   &apos;    .  .

</content>
</cab>
