<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/52/0 images: 301-308</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel I, Dally JonesjMe&quot;Document is the Property.of His Britannic Maiestv&apos;s Government.&quot;! &apos;   \ &apos;dd2MhftS &quot;Document is the Rroperty.,of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]CONFIDENTIAL. Political Intelligence Department.Foreign Office.Russia /007.[May 17, 1918.]Aft)MEMORANDUMonTHE BALTIC PROVINCES.General.&quot;oFi IN Memorandum C-12 and B 11 of the Department of Information various historical and statistical data were brought together on the subject of Esthonia, Livonia, and Oourland. The following selected data are based principally upon more recent information of which the special sources are indicated in each instance : (A.) Esthonia. (Special data supplied by members of the Esthonian Delegation to Great Britain.)Esthonia: about 45,000 square kilometres; larger than Switzerland, Holland, Denmark, or Belgium ; to the original area the northern part of Livonia and the islands of Oesel and Moon were added by the Russian Provisional Government, and the district of Narva and a part of Ingermanland by the Bolshevik Government, (the island of Dago always formed part of Esthonia); \\ millions; capital, Reval.Resume of Political Events since the Russian Revolution. The Esthonian National Council or Diet (Maapaew or Maanoukogu) was established by the Russian Provisional Government by law under date of 30th March (13th April), 1917, and having been elected by universal suffrage, it met 1st (14th) July at Reval and formed an Administration which took over the whole direction of local government. Meeting again on the 15th (28th) November, the Diet, in view of the situation in Russia, declared Esthonia an Independent Republic, decided to convoke an Esthonian Constituent Assembly, and meanwhile proclaimed itself the sole depository of the supreme power in Esthonia until the convocation of the said&apos;Assembly which was to be elected on a more direct suffrage than the Diet. After the Bolsheviks came into power, however, they intervened with armed force and prevented the Diet from discharging its functions, and in the end forcibly prevented its meetings. As the conditions of anarchy in Russia grew rapidly worse and were tending to spread throughout Esthonia mainly owing to the activities&apos;of the undisciplined Russian troops quartered there, a Provisional Government, elected and empowered by the Diet to act during its suspension along with the Executive Committee&apos; of the Diet and the leaders of the political parties, and supported by detachments of troops, met on the 10th January, 1918, and, after careful consideration of the whole situation, came to the following conclusions : 1. That Esthonia ought forthwith to be proclaimed&apos; a democratic independent Republic; that this republic of Esthonia ought to be declared a neutral country, and that therefore to this end it should seek international guarantees from the Great Powers.2. The democratic Esthonian Republic should accord to national minorities (Russians and Germans. &amp;c.) all rights of autonomy in matters of national culture.3. In the interests of the neutrality and independence of the Esthonian Republic a special paragraph should be inserted in the Treaty of Peace whereby any other country would be forbidden to erect any sort of fortification on the territory of the Republic.4. In order to ensure that the claim confirming the independence of Esthonia is inserted in the Treaty of Peace, and that the questions concerning the country are decided in a manner conformable to Esthonian interests, representatives from Esthonia ought to take part in the Peace Conference.5. There should also be inserted in the Treaty of Peace a paragraph dealing with the holding of a genera] direct referendum of the inhabitants of Esthonia for the purpose of definitely settling the question of the mode of government [367-15] B
and of eventual union of the country with some other Power. This referendum ought to be carried&apos;out under the control of a neutral Power, e.g., Sweden, in such a way that the free exercise of the vote shall be guaranteed to every inhabitant of Esthonia who is of age and who has lived a year in the country before the outbreak of the war. 6. All the political parties of Esthonia affirm that the people of Esthonia as.a whole are opposed to any occupation of Esthonia by German troops, and would see in such occupation a violation of the lights of the nation. At the same time the whole nation demands that all foreign troops be at once removed from Esthonian territory.It may be taken that the Provisional Government represents some 65 per cent, of the population, 30 per cent, are Bolsheviks, and 5 per cent, of &quot; German &quot; sympathies.In opposition, however, to the will of the Esthonian people and its representative organs, the Esthonian nobility decided on the 28th January. 1918, to make an appeal to the German Government to occupy the country with German troops. It should be understood that this request could not be addressed by the nobility in any representative way so far as the country as a whole was concerned, for under the laws of the 30th March (12th April) and the 22nd June (5th July), 1917, the Diet was constituted the supreme authority in Esthonia, and the nobility were required to hand over all their functions of local administration to it. The nobility had ceased to exist as an official organ of administration, and remained now only as a social class composing 0*5 per cent, of the population, or a little over 5 per cent, if taken as representing the distinctly German element in all classes of society. More than 50 per cent, of all the land in Esthoiha forms a kind of latifundia in the hands of some 200 noble families largely of German origin, while 60 per cent, of the agricultural-population have sunk into the position of an unpropertied proletariat. Against this appeal those authorised represen-tatives of the Esthonian Diet who were in Stockholm made a protest to the German Government on the 4th February, 1918. Nevertheless, after the resumption of hostilities on the part of Germany against Russia, German troops crossed Moon Sound, and occupied Verdir, Leal, &amp;c. The avowed German motive in occupying the country was to combat the anarchy and free-handed actions of the Bolsheviks, who had declared all the Esthonian nobility to be outlaws. The Ksthonian Provisional Government had, however, already overthrown the domination of the Bolsheviks in February, and had succeeded in establishing legal order with the help of loyal Esthonian troops previous to the German invasion.On the 24th February the last representatives of the Bolshevik Government left the country, proceeding on warships to Helsingfors. Immediately afterwards the Provisional Government of the Independent Democratic Republic of Esthonia was reorganised under Constantine Pats, as Premier. This authorised Provisional Govern-ment of Esthonia has re-established order in the country. All the confiscations and requisitions made by the Bolsheviks have been declared null and void. All property has been restored to the former proprietors. The Germans, however, continued their advance, and soon afterwards occupied the whole country.According to the latest information the Provisional Government of Esthonia has been deprived of its power de facto; the Esthonian troops have been disarmed; a military censorship has been established, except for German papers working in the Pan-German interests; German money is being introduced into the country; the municipal Duma elected and established in L917 has been dismissed; in Reval a German has bsen appointed. Mayor, and a committee of eighteen Germans have been appointed to act with him, no Esthonian having agreed to serve on this committee. In Dorpat, likewise, a German merchant has been appointed Mayor, whilst in the villages the district Zemstvos, established on the bas.s of the common electoral laws, have been dismissed, and in their place the old local government bodies of 1914 have been re-established. Under such conditions the formation and summoning of an Esthonian Constituent Assembly were practical impos-ibilities, the more so that the elections were not completed before the German invasion. The election of a Constituent Assembly will only be possible and expedient alter the evacuation of the country by the German forces.Following on thy German occupation, the Nobility Landtags (formed finally in 1847) of Esthonia and Livonia issued invitations, on the 22nd and 26th March, to the German Government to take over their countries. This claim to speak on behalf of the whole country in expressing their desire for a personal union with Germany has in the opinion of all other parties no validity whatever.   A more detailed protest against
this unlawful attempt by the nobility was made to the German Government by the Esthonian Delegation in Stockholm on the 21st March, 1918. A. further protest against the resolutions of the so-called United Landesrat (National Council) of Livonia, Esthonia, Oesel, and Riga embodying a proposal of union with Prussia was made to the German Chancellor and Foreign Secretary of State by the Plenipotentiary Esthonian Delegation in Christ:ania on the 13th April, 1918. According to a telegram of the 14th April the Kaiser intimated that this request &quot;for union with the German Empire, under my sceptre, will be benevolently entertained.&quot;Conversation with the delegates disclosed that they were united on the basis of wishing to have nothing whatever to do with Germany.   Their present desire is for the recognition of their country&apos;s independence, leaving the question of its eventual return into a Federation of Russian States open for the present.   Twenty per cent, of their nation is in Russia; on the other hand, they feel that the return of Russia to a condition of stable order will be a long process.   It is worthy of remark that the elections to the Esthonian Constituent Assembly, so far as they had been completed, were de facto at the same time a referendum on the question of the independence of Esthonia.   Seventy per cent, voted for the absolute independence of their country, the remainder for its autonomy as anintegral unit in a Prussian Federation. The delegates are convinced that Germany will not willingly give their country back to Russia, but will seek to do with it as was done with Bosnia-Herzegovina ; nevertheless, they appeal to the right of national self-determination accepted by the German Chancellor on tho 25th February.   On the other hand, the Esthonians will not consider any administrative or territorial separation of Moon Soufcd and the adjacent islands from their country. They would like to be an independent Iree Trade country, perpetually neutral, a sort of gateway for the world into Russia, vi ose customs officers could even be located at their ports (Reval, &amp;c).   The present mo-German leaning of Finland makes a Scandi-navian orientation very unpopular, and union with the southern half of Livonia does not seem very desirable, as they fear that Germany intends to retain Courland and divide the Lettish people.   They feel sure of recognition of their independence by France and Italy, but would, apparently sincerely, value that of Great Britain most. Recognition has likewise been asked and the request has been sympathetically received by Norway, Sweden, and Denmark.   The Russian de facto Government has also been asked to declare forthwith its recognition of the independence of Esthonia, on the basis that the Esthonian Diet, or other general democratic Esthonian Parliament, should ^decide about the future political status and international position of Esthonia.Previous Relations of His Majesty&apos;s Government with Esthonian Delegations.On the 23rd January (No. 15424) Mr. Lindley received an Esthonian deputation at Petrograd, who stated that they had received a semi-official offer from the German Government of a guarantee of the independence, of Esthonia, provided that the latter accepted a German protectorate. They wished to know if they could rely on His Majesty&apos;s Government to support their desire for independence at the Peace Confer-ence. If they could look forward to such support they would risk the threat of German occupation. Mr. Lindley suggested that an assurance be given &quot; that we will do all we can at the Peace Conference to prevent Esthonia being annexed by Germany against her will and to secure some form of international guarantee for the independence of any States which may come into existence as the result of the war.&quot; In connection with this reply His Majesty&apos;s Government took steps to consult all the Allied Govern-ments. The Italian Government agreed to the first part of the proposed reply, but thought it inopportune that the Allies should pledge themselves to work for more than autonomy, on the ground that the eventual federation of States composing the former Russia would probably be more to the advantage of the Allies as a bulwark against Germany than a number of weak conterminous States. The United States Govern-ment appeared reluctant to agree, on the ground that the number of States that might come into existence as the result of the war might prove embarrassing. The Japanese Government agreed to the full reply.Meanwhile M. Tonisson, the representative of the Esthonian Diet at Stockholm, told Sir E. Howard on the 21st February that, in view of the approaching German invasion, it would greatly encourage the Esthonians in their determination not to be annexed by Germany, if the Western Powers would at least provisionally recognise the National Council as a de facto independent body until the Peace Conference took place, and state that the final settlement could only be made by the Conference. Sir E. Howard was accordingly instructed on the 25th February to inform M. Tonisson that His
Majestys Government were prepared provisionally to recognise the Esthonian Constituent Assembly * as a de facto independent body until the Peace Conference took place, when the future status of Esthonia ought to be settled on the principle of self-determination.On the 23rd April His Majesty&apos;s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs received MM. Wirgo, Piip, and Pusta, representing the Esthonian National Council or Diet, who laid before him a memorandum dealing with the political situation in. Esthonia, and asked for a favourable reception of the statement, of their national aims and aspirations. They presented the following requests to His Majesty&apos;s Government: .1. Eecognitiou of the independence of the Democratic Kepublic of Esthonia within her ethnographic frontiers, including the islands of Moon Sound.2. Recognition of the Provisional Government authorised by the Esthonian Diet as the only legal power in Esthonia.3. The granting to Esthonia of the right to participate at the General Peace Conference so as to be able to defend her interests, and raise the question of Esthonian perpetual neutrality and its international guarantees.They received a communication from the Secretary of State intimating that &quot; His Majesty&apos;s Government greet with sympathy the aspirations of the Esthonian people, and are glad to reaffirm their readiness to grant provisional recognition to the Esthonian National Council as a de facto independent body until the Peace Conference takes place, when the future status of Esthonia ought to be settled as for as possible in accordance with the wishes of the population.&quot; The communication further intimated that His Majesty&apos;s Government would do their utmost to secure that the above principle be given effect to in the final settlement. Meantime His Majesty&apos;s Government is glad to receive Professor Antonius Piip as the informal diplomatic representative of the Esthouian Provisional Government.In comparing the recent relations of His Majesty&apos;s Government with Finland and Esthonia it should not be forgotten that the history of these two countries since the Russian revolution has little in common; therefore these relations were bound to be different.   Particularly it should be noted (a.) That the recognition of the independence of Finland by the Bolshevik Government was made the condition of recognition by Germany. Esthonias independence has not been recognised by the Bolsheviks, and so any recognition of Esthonia by a Great Power does not involve recognition of the Bolshevik Government.(6.) Finland at the time at which she asked for recognition was not occupied by German troops; Esthonia is thus occupied, and any recognition of her is a definitely anti-German move, and indicates that Great Britain cannot consent to the German designs on the Baltic.(c.) The Finnish orientation has all along been chiefly German; that of Esthonia, Allied.(d.) There will be less reason for any German refusal to evacuate troops immediately from Esthonia than from Finland, because conditions are becoming more quickly settled in the former than in the latter. (Cf. Article YI, Brest-Litovsk Treaty.)(B.) Latvia or Lettland, covering some 63,000 square kilometres, comprising southern -&apos;- Livonia, Courland, and Latgalia (^ three north-western districts in the Government of; Yitebsk), accordingly larger than Bosnia-PIerzegovina or Switzerland; over 2\ millions, of whom nearly 2 millions are Letts. Capital, Riga. Additional sources of information: &quot;Latvia&quot; (1917), by Y. J. Olav; &quot;The Devastation of Latvia by the Russian Forces&quot; (1918), by I. P. Zalit; Letters from the Lettish Provisional National Council in Petrograd.Resume of History since the Russian Revolution.Although loyally participating in the war against Germany from the beginning, and showing their fighting value in the achievements of the Lettish brigades, the Letts always cherished the idea of an ultimate political reunion of the Lettish provinces Yidzeme (Livonia), Kurzeme (Courland), and Latgalia (a part of the Yitebsk Govern-ment) under the Russian sceptre.    Their formula during this period was vaguely* As it happened, the elections to the Constituent Assembly were never completed, and the Assembly has never met. -&quot;&apos;  &apos;  &quot; -: &apos; --:
&quot;Autonomy within Russia.&quot; It oven appears that the old Russian regime had elaborated a scheme of local autonomy in January 1917, on the very eve of the Revolution.After the fall of Tsarisra the first political- step taken by the Letts was the institution of Territorial or Land Councils in Livonia, Courland, and Latgalia. At the same time they asked the Provisional Government to accord these Councils, as i he highest institutions in the country, large powers of local administration, involving a considerable measure of cultural autonomy, leaving the wider and profounder issues to the decision of the Russian Constituent Assembly. The Lettish demands, in short, did not very appreciably exceed the powers vested in the most developed type of Russian Zemstvo ; nevertheless, they do not appear to have been altogether sympathetically received by the Provisional Government, whose aim, in the interests of a strongly held view of centralisation, was to bring all local questions within the range of Russian common law. The new administrative organs were, however, in the end recognised. There is little doubt that the continued failure of the Provisional Government, to declare its sympathetic interest in the rights of the smaller peoples forming part of the Russian State, and its inability to see the path of safety for Russia other than along a line of strong centralised government developed at their expense, served to increase the general feeling of restlessness. When the Provisional Government finally realised its mistake the mischief had to a large extent been done.Accordingly on the 30th July/12th August, 1917, a Conference was held at Kiga by the Committee of the Temporary Vidzem (Livonian) Land Council to deal with the question of the autonomy of Latvia, which was attended by representatives of all the Lettish administrative organs, democratic societies and political parties. The following resolutions were passed unanimously : 1. The Lettish nation, like all nations, has the right to complete settlement of its own affairs.2. Latvia must be indivisible, arid comprise a united Livonia, Courland, and Latgalia (the north-west section of Vitebsk&quot; Government). In border districts the local inhabitants shall decide for themselves whether they wish to belong to Latvia or not.3. Latgalia, as possessing the distinguishing peculiarities of a component section of Latvia, must be granted independent action on matters relating to local self-government, language, school, and church.4. Latvia must be a politically autonomous component part of the Kussian Republic, formed on democratic principles.5. The legislation of autonomous Latvia, the executive tribunals and the authority of local self-government are within the jurisdiction of the people of Latvia and its Diet, elected on the basis of universal; direct, secret, and proportional franchise without distinction of sex.6. The Conference protests against annexations, arid.in general opposes any attempt whatever to determine the legal position of Latvia or its separate parts without the knowledge and consent of the people of Latvia.The formula was now &quot; A united, undivided, politically autonomous Latvia within the Russian Republic.&quot;The German military success in Russia and the domestic chaos subsequently changed the situation radically. Latvia fell progressively into German bands, while each remaining portion previous to evacuation was devastated by the retreating demoralised Russian forces to an extent that compares with the damage wrought even in Belgium and Serbia. These circumstances have been used by the Lettish press to attempt to make the position of Latvia an international question, inasmuch as Germany has now become the deciding element on the Eastern front, Russia being unable, if,not unwilling, to defend her former provinces against German colonisation. On the Letts, as on the Finns and other small nationalities, the disorder and anarchy consequent upon the Russian Revolution produced the same desire &quot;,to get right away out of the Russian muddle,&quot; to use the phrase of one of their Nationalist leaders.On the other hand, after the Bolshevik coiip in November that party, owing to the same series of economic causes, gradually obtained the upper hand in Latvia also, with this difference-that the feeling of nationality did not reach so low an ebb as it did in Russia proper.   A local Lettish Bolshevik Administration was formed.   The[367-15] C ,
Bolshevik Lettish troops fought on in defence of their country to the end, while Lenin&apos;s bodyguard at Smolny was drawn from the same source. It is also a Lettish claim that the fact that peace was not signed sooner at Brest-Litovsk was in part due to the intervention of their Bolshevik compatriots. Lenin had, they state, asserted on several occasions that Courland should be sacrificed if peace could be obtained at that price. The Letts at once opposed this suggestion, and their opposition had force in it, inasmuch as a Lettish regiment was on guard at the Smolny Institute and the Commissary for Justice in the Bolshevik Government -was a Lett (Stutchka). He and Trotsky went to Brest-Litovsk when it appeared that the first Rusiu m delegates were too conciliatory, and Trotsky then made his declaration th it to sacrifice Oourland would be the betrayal of the revolution.On the other hand the Germans had made their intentions with regard to Latvia perfectly clear from an early date. Already on the 5th April, 1916, the German Chancellor declared in the Reichstag that the peoples of the Baltic Littoral who had been &quot; liberated &quot; by the German arms would never be released to revolutionary Russia. In a similar sense an article in the &quot;Deutsche Politik&quot; (the 1st October, 1916) indicated that the German intention in 1916 was to annex and assimilate Courland, thus dividing Latvia. By a process of intensive &quot; Kultur,&quot; by the introduction of German colonists, by the natural abandonment of the region by all ultra-patriotic Letts, it was assumed that the policy would be soon effected. It is obvious how such a policy in closing again in large measure the outlet for Russia to western waters would lead to the gradual suffocation and so possibly to the progressive dismemberment of that State. Accordingly the question of &quot;no annexation &quot; is peculiarly vital in this area, and the interest in small nations with which the war began means a very great deal to this corner of the Baltic Littoral. Unfortunately the behaviour of the Russian forces subsequent to the evacuation of Riga temporarily aided the German designs in a very marked degree. Bands of deserters from the retiring Russian troops were, on the testimony of the Russian Commissaries themselves, shown to be guilty of excesses which went far to destroy the loyalty of the Letts. It was clearly proved that buildings had been plundered, churches desecrated, crops pillaged and burned, Jive stock and other property carried off, archives destroyed, and endless outrages perpetrated on the population by methods and in a spirit that had no relation to the exigencies of war. The migration of the Lettish refugees (over 700,000 by the beginning of 1916) has been directed towards the Governments of Viatka and Perm and Western Siberia, a movement which seems to threaten the very existence of the Lettish nation, and has provided Germany with more reason than ever for colonising these lands with her own people. She immediately endeavoured to come to an understanding with such of the Lettish people as have remained, and circumstances which could earlier have been disregarded must now receive serious consideration. At the same time references to meetings of the Diet or Landtag of Courland as at Mitau on the 2.1st September, 1917, from which a petition was forwarded praying for &quot;the protection and support of His Majesty the German Emperor and of the powerful German Empire/&apos; need not be taken too seriously when regard is had to the composition of the said Diet. It appears to be a resuscitation of the old Landtag of the nobility who represented exactly 0&apos;06 per cent, of the population, with the addition of some representatives from the towns and villages; yet even in this arbitrary gathering-there was a minority of twelve out of thirty-one members who protested against a reunion of Courland with Germany. It is the increasing physical need and sense of desertion which may drive the remnants of the Lettish people into some sort of agreement with the Germans.The most recent developments of the national movement are as follows: The Provisional Land Councils of Courland and Latgale and the National bloc of the Provisional Land Council of Livonia, numerous Lettish social organisations, political parties, groups and military organisations, relying on the right of nations to self-determination, and relying on the principle of the ethnographical and territorial indivisibility of Lettland, constituted themselves on the 17th November, 1917, at Walk, in Livonia, as the Lettish Provisional National Council with headquarters there. The Council decided unanimously to organise elections to the Constituent Assembly of Lettland, and sent a declaration to the Allies in which the Council protested against the partition of Lettlaud between the belligerent States, and especially against the annexation of Courland by force to Germany. A second declaration was sent to the Revolutionary Russian Democracj^ in which Lettland, composed of Livonia, Courland, and Latgalia, was proclaimed an autonomous State.
The actual text of the resolution was as follows : &apos;&quot;Considering the aspiration of the Letts to political liberty and to the autonomy of Lettland, so evidently proved in 1905 by the struggles for liberty, and relying on the right of nations to dispose of themselves, the Lettish Provisional National Council &apos; &quot; 1. Protests most energetically against every kind of partition of Lettland, and especially against the annexation of Conrland or of Lettland as a whole, and, generally, against every kind of bond between Lettland or Lettish provinces and Germany ;&quot; 2. Proclaims Lettland, composed of Livonia, Courland, and Latgalia, an autonomous State, whose relations with other States and whose constitution are to be settled by its Constituent Assembly and a plebiscite.&quot;At a second session, held 15th to 19th January, 1918, at Petrograd, the following resolution was passed : &quot; Relying upon the right of self-determination of peoples, acknowledged and proclaimed by the democracy of the whole world, the Lettish Provisional National Council &quot;1. Recognises that Lettland is to be constituted an independent and democratic republic uniting Courland, Livonia, and Latgalia ;&quot; 2. Protests against any attempt to dismember Lettland accentuating the indivisibility of the Lettish nation and its territory as the capital and absolute demand of the Letts ;&quot; 3. Protests against any attempt to conclude a peace restricting the right of self-determination of the peoples;&quot; 4. Repudiates any kind of falsification of the people&apos;s will under the pressure of the occupying military forces and war circumstances.&quot;Since the Letts now feel that their question has become international in character, and as the present position of Russia appears to them hopeless, their thought for the future may be expressed in the formula &quot; An independent Latvia under the protectorate of the Western European Powers,&quot; forming a link in the chain Poland-Lithuania-Latvia. Other proposed possibilities are (a) union with the Lithuanians in , a Lithuania-Latvian Monarchy ; and (b) a larger union of the Baltic peoples Scandi-navians, Finns, Esthonians, and Letts at the moment the least likely of all. The first of these three solutions, although expressing the maximum hopes and highest realisation of the Lettish national ideal, would seem to be ultimately practically impossible. Sooner or later such a small unit must inevitably be swept economically into the orbit of some proximate larger unit; and, on the other hand, it may be doubted whether the multi plication of the numbers of small independent States is really the most advantageous way of combating German influence in Eastern Europe.On the other hand, it is of great importance for the Allies to take every measure that gives prospect of strengthening resistance to Germany even locally. Such a step undoubtedly has been the recent recognition of the Esthonian National Council by His Majesty&apos;s Government, Such recognition has had a very good effect in Finland, affording direct proof that the sympathies of Great . Britain are with the little nationalities contrary to the statements in the pro-German Finnish press and making a very difficult position for the Finnish Government when confronted with the same demand from the Esthonian Provisional Government. For tho Esthonians are of kindred race to the Finns, and their struggles for independence have always been regarded with the greatest sympathy in Finland ; yet to grant such recognition will involve the Finnish Government in a distinctly anti-German act. Accordingly if, as is probable in the near future, a representative Lettish Delegation comes to ask recognition of their Provincial National Council from the Allies, the success attending the recognition granted to the Esthonian National Council indicates that a corresponding treatment of the Lettish request will be not less fruitful.(C.)--Latvia and Lithuania. Letter, under date of the 16th March, 1918, from Dr. Szlupas, doyen of the Lithuanian representatives in Stockholm.&quot;From time to time we are able to get here real news from Russia as well as from Germany. Lately, when Lietuvos Taryba (Lithuanian National Council) in Vilnius has proclaimed independence of Lithuania (16th February, 1918), without
ohaving signed conventions (military, financial, traffic, and customs duties, &amp;c.) exacted by Germany, the members of the Taryba are not allowed to come to Berlin, and there-fore.our communication is getting scarce and more difficult. But then came Professor Voldemar, who was Lithuanian attache in Brest-Litovsk with the Ukrainian I )elegation, and we learned many things from him.&apos;&quot; A few days ago I have handed a memorandum to Mr. Howard, the British Ambassador in Stockholm. The memorandum gives in detail the evolution of the Lithuanian question almost to the present clay, and I requested (in the name of Lithuanian representatives in Stockholm) to transmit to London our request that the British Government recognises Lithuanians independence. The poor Taryba is pressed very harshly by the German Government, and I am afraid that, having no encourage-ment from the Entente Powers, it might give way.and submit to the demands of Germany. Really the position of Taryba is very difficult. Our people do not want to entertain any compacts with Germany before the&apos;Peace Congress takes place and adjusts all matters. The Germans contend that no Peace Congress shall take place; that they shall conclude peace separately with each nation, as they recently did with Ukrainia and Russia, and are doing with Roumania. At first they were willing (before the peace with Russia) to recognise Lithuanians independence, but now they only speak of &apos; Selbststandigkeit&apos; with an intimate leaning upon Germany, as Chancellor Hertling expresses himself in his answer to Taryba (of which a copy is now in my hands). Neither President Wilson, nor Clemenceau, nor Lloyd George have at any time expressed officially what they propose for the future of Lithuania and Lettonia. Among Lithuanians rumours are current, and many are convinced that Britain favours a Greater Poland, and that Britain has made promises to the Poles to compel Lithuanians to join Poland. If it should be true, such a step is very objectionable to Lithuanians all over the world, and if the Entente Powers should not recognise Lithuania^ independence, who can tell what Taryba might do in order to escape the danger of being forced into the Polish realm. My opinion is that the best solution to all concerned would be the establishment of the Lithuanian-Lettic Republic, with a custom-free access to the Baltic Sea of the Russian merchandise. I hope the Letts would be glad now to entertain such a solution of their future, though previously they demanded autonomy within the Russian federation. I had no chance lately to meet their repressntative men, but heard that in Switzerland they had a convention with Lithuanians, and discussed the feasibility of such plans.....&quot; My conviction is that Russia is gone for ever; I speak it from knowing the people of Russia from personal observation. Therefore Britain would do well in helping the new small States around the Baltic Sea which are willing to enter into a confederation with the Scandinavian nations. If Britain would support this project the Swedes would be won, and the smaller peoples (Lithuanians, Letts,. Esthonians, Finns) would be delighted. The northern union could some way counterbalance the German supremacy. Besides, the Lithuanians are in perfect harmony with Ukrainia, and it would not be difficult to make them join the northern union. Poles, on account of their aristocratic tendencies and the greed for other peopkVs possessions, have no friends all around ; they are isolated. In my opinion such a policy is the only alternative for Britain if Britain foresees the nearest future in Eastern Europe. The Great Russians will remain in. turmoil and anarchy for many years, and hone of the nationalities which have been able to get away from them shall voluntarily return into their fold; sooner they will revolt than submit to the domination of the semi-barbaric Russians.&quot;May 14, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
