<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/34/0 images: 246-247</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
itj3 THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC -MAJESTY&apos;S GQvEFJMSNT.       gqqC R E T.-&quot;-* war cabinet.2839.UTILISATION OF FACILITIES FOR THE &quot;   P&quot;ROJ)wlrXOH 5f&apos;airc3faffa(Copy of letter elated 30th November 1917, from the Hozio Director of the Aeronautical Institute of Great Britain addressed to the Secretary,War Council).THE AERONAUTICAL INSTITUTE OF GREAT BRITAIN. 3, Arlington Street, St.JamesTs,London. 30th November, 1917.The Secretary,The &quot;hr Council,10, Downing Street, 3. v. 1.sir,.On the 26th instant we had the honour to address a letter to the Ministry of Munitions, the Air Board and the Directorate of National Service, In the following terms:-November 26th, 1917.The Secretary,( Directorate of National Service( The Air Board( The Ministry of Munitions&quot;Sir,&quot;Owing to the pressing needs of the times we have, &quot;at very short notice, called a Conference of our &quot;Members and of representatives of some six or seven &quot;hundred smaller, engineering firms, with whom we are &quot;in touch, for Thursday, Eovember 29th, at 7o30 p*m3 &quot;at Central Hall&apos;., Westminster.n       The object of the? Conference is to put forward &quot;the proper means of placing at the disposal of the &quot;Government, for the pre duction of aircraft, some six &quot;thousand skilled workmen and a large amount of &quot;machinery not fully employed on war work-   At the &quot;Conference suitable methods will be indicated whereby &quot;the Government, without any interference with their &quot;existing arrangements, would be enabled immediately   -&quot;to take advantage of productive facilities which are &quot;now running to waste.We very much hope.thereforevthat (The Ministry of Munition?(The Air Board   &apos;:     r (The Directorate of (National Service
291&quot;will send to the Conference one or more representatives&quot;to obtain first hand information concerning the under-&quot;taking and be in direct touch with a patriotic practical &quot;war effortvI am,Sir,Yours faithfully,(Signer)   L. BUM&quot;D3SBIEDS.Hon.Director&quot;,The Conference alluded to in the above correspondence dulytook place and the following Resolution was unanimously carried:-&quot;     That this Conference approves of the object &quot;placed before it, which is immediately to utilise for &quot;the national benefit the productive facilities offered &quot;by engineering and other firms not fully occupied on &quot;war work; that a Committee be herewith formed with &quot;power to add to its numbers with authorisation to &quot;speak on behalf of the Conference and be provisionally &quot;entrusted with consolidating the body of firms already &quot;interested and of eEtending their-numbers, and of &quot;devising means for immediately carrying into effect &quot;the objects of the Conference as stated above; and that &quot;a copy &quot;of this resolution be forwarded to the Munitions &quot;Minister,  tho Air Minister and the War Council.:&quot;We shall, of course, be very pleased to give you any detailed information of what transpired at the Conference that you may desireI am, Sir,Yours faithfully,(Signed)    I. Bill DE3BL3DS.Hon.Director.

</content>
</cab>
