<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/34/0 images: 279-282</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 EGRETN.S.R.23.^MAINTENANCE   OF   THE   ARMED   FORCES. Nate by the Minister of National Service.As directed by the War Cabinet, I have endeavoured to estimate as nearly as passible the number of Category &amp;rrecruits over 18 years 8 menths who can be made available  of tho 30th June, 1918.(1)   If Government programmes are maintained and all pledges aro kept.(2)   If programmes are maintained, and the Government is relieved of all ple&amp;gec.(3)   13 programmes ether than shipbuilding are reauc*d, and the Government is relieved of all pledges.The quotas givon in Table A of my memorandum (G.174) assume, as stated on page 5, that all necessary negotiations with (Trade Unions are -carried out satisfactorily.     They are therefore based en tho second of the Cabinet alternatives.Taking the groups of industries successively, the results are as follows:-A. MUNITIONS   (Exoluiing Shipbuilding, Marine Engiiieoring andAncillary Services).First alternative....................25,000Seoond alternative........................... .60,900.This assumes that the Government is free to take diluteeo up to 41 in industries other than shipbuilding and aircraft;   and &amp;.1S9 to take skilled men below the ages specified in the Sohedule of Proteoted Cccupaticns, although dilutees are still left in shipbuilding and airoraft.Provided the Government is also released from the pledge that dilution may not be resorted to for recruiting purposes, It will be possible to obtain a further number of men whe are- striivtOy- j(jL-e--
9 9 Q &amp;   if- 2 -by age, occupation, etc.) within the Schedule by direct substitution of skilled men of low category released from the Army.   It is impossible to estimate an exact figure for this.Third Alternativet.   I give a table shOY/ing the numbers of men of military age engaged in munitions, (other than shipbuilding, etc) who would be left after the 60,000 given in the second alternative had been recruited.   The total category A men so left is    ... 108,000, It is, however, impossible to state in percentages what would be the reduction in output if any given number of these men were taken.	18-31		Over 31.		Total		Cat. A.	Other Cats.	Cat. A.	Other Cats.	Cat. A.	Other Cats.Aeroplanes	13,000	26,000	10,000	20,000	23,000	46,000Ministry of Munitions.	41,000	131.000	32,000	115,000	73,000	246,000V.rar Office Contracts.	7,000	23,000	5,000	17,000	12,000	40,000Total:-	6-1,000	180,000	47,000 152;000 108,000			332,000B. COAL MINES.I have already arranged for the calling lap of the post-war miners who are fit for any form of service, except men in barred classes and those who hold Tribunal exemptions on domestic grounds.   It is therefore.unnecessary to consider the first alternative.   Under the second alternative, I estimate that the number of Category a men who can be obtained is ...... 50,000.To meet this, it will be necessary to arrange for the release from the Colours of a very large number of miners of lower category.
Third alternative.     If tho total output of coal (240,000,000 tons) was reduced by 16^% it should bo possible to obtain approximately a further 100,000 men.This would involve tho prohibition of all expert a to neutrals, and very drastic reductions in home supplies.C. RAILWAYS &amp; TRANSPORT. (1)   Railways.There are no pledges except that Category A men aro to be taken first, and single men of Category A before married men of that Category,    I estimate t^s&amp; the quota obtainable fromRailways at ....... 6,000.      This, however, exceeds the numberwhich the Railway &quot;Executive Committee think they can roleace. It is impossible to gauge the effect of reduced Government programmes on Railway traffic.   A permit system for passenger traffic might slightly increase the number of men available, but a considerable staff would be required to work any such system.fe)   Fort Labour.Outstanding exemptions under the Board of Trade scheme total 4-A,707,   Of these probably approximately 22,000 arc Category A.The first alternative would probably yield 1,000. Speeding up, and assisted by Transport Worker Battalions to the extent I had originally anticipated, the ouota should be...... 4^000.If the Transport Worker Battalions are doubled in strength, the number released might be .. ...  . 8^000.   Reducing Governmentprogrammes would not materially affect these numbers.
3/12/17.A. C GEDDES.(3)   Other Transport Workers-.Total number of Category A - approximately 18,000.Unless legislation affecting Tribunals is introduced not more than 2000 of these would be obtained.   Reduction of Government programmes would not affect this.D. AGRICULTURE.In view of the fact that agriculture is a completely protected industry I have budgeted! for only 3,000.   There are, however, approximately 78,000 Category A men in agriculture. If the agricultural,-programme is to be largely curtailed, and agriculture is to cease to be. a certified occupation, the pro-portion of 78,000 who could be obtained for the Army would only be limited by Tribunals giving exemption on domestic grounds. In these circumstances the quota might be put at.....50,000.E. PUBLIC UTILITY &amp; OTHER CERTIFIED OCCUPATIONS.It is impossible to estimate at&apos;&quot;&apos;all the possible increases in the suggested levy of 6,000.     Public Utility Companies can spare very few men;    and they-would not be materially affected by partial abandonment of Government pro-grammes.     Tho number who could be made available from Certified Occupations must depend entirely on what contracts the Government dccider to abandon.

</content>
</cab>
