<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/34/0 images: 305-310</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. Intelligence Bureau,^ccabj/vc%^ Department of Information,2CRw/031.^__^-o^^ESKLY REPORT Oil RUSSIA. XXXI.Now that nearly a month has elapsed since the Bolshevik rising it is possible to analyse certain elements in the situation. The Bolsheviks have not shown any lack of activity and have left no stone unturned to gain widespread support among the poorer classes.     After a month&apos;s experience it can truthfully be said that they have failed in their   main purpose, though for the time being they are masters-of Petrograd and Moscow end most of the other industrial centres.      Their influence is greatest among (1) the workmen in the factories, (2) the garrisons in the big cities. The elements that are still doubtful, which the Bolsheviks are making great efforts to capture, are (1) the soldiers at the front, (2) the peasants. .   The attitude adopted by these two elements will be more or less decisive.Up to the present the soldiers at the front have not declared their attitude.   Krylenko, the new^C^)mmander-*-in&apos;-Chief, has not so far dared to visit any very wide section of the front outside the northern front, which for some time past has been the most dis-affected.   Ke and the   Government which he represents are relying on permeating the other parts of the frnnt by slow methods. Once they have succeeded in getting an armistice they rely upon gaining the support of the bulk of the army which has no desire * to face the rigours of the winter.An interesting example of the efforts made by the Bolsheviks to capture the votes of the peasants is to be found in the fact that Lenin, who has for more than 20 years upheld the Land Pro-gramme of the Social Democrats (his first book written by him while still a student at the University was on the Land Question)
has now accepted the Social Revolutionaries&apos; programme in deference to the wishes of the peasants.   The differences between the Social Democrats and the Social Revolutionaries on the land question are not vital, but it is significant that so   doctrinaire a Social Democrat as Lenin should give way.     Pravda (now a Government organ!) speaks of the peasants as already on the side of the Bolsheviks.     In an article comparing the Paris Commune of 1871 with the present situation in Russia, it says that the essential difference lies in the fact that in Russia the peasants are behind the Sovyet, whereas in Prance they were on the side of the bourgeoisie, Paris in 1871 only having the support of a few towns.The main propaganda of the Bolsheviks falls under two heads: (1) Peace,    (2) Land.    It is natural, therefore, that the two first measures of the Government should aim at securing both these desiderata.     They will stand or fall by their ability to succeed and to succeed quickly.The Question of Peace.The present Government of the People&apos;s Commissaries Is really the Government of Lenin aid Trotski.   Of these two men Lenin is the more fanatical, Trotski the more wily;   both are probably equally unscrupulous In their methods.   Nevertheless in spite of the underhand intrigues they may have resorted to in order to gain power there is nothing to prove that they will agree to any peace with Germany that is not in the interests of Socialism.     They are naive enough to think that the direct offer of a peace on the basis of no annexations or contributions and the right of self-determination will exert such pressure on the German Government that it will be   * forced to give way.     Their sole weapon is what they call social revolution;    the success of social revolution In Russia will, in
B 5 *3their opinion, inevitably lead to its success in Germany and Western Europe.     Pravda writes as follows:-     &quot;Social Revolution is our strategic plan for ending the war.   Having proclaimed a Government of peasants and workmen we have proposed peace to all the Governments, hut, at the same time, we   have turned to the peoples also, mobilising them In the struggle against the Imperialists.   For the Imperialist G overnments will only consent to lay down their arms when the peoples begin to show their political power and go against the wishes and interests of the Imperialists.   This will be the first signal of the beginning of social revolution in the Wes?. In Germany the Government is already yielding to the pressure of the people and is appointing a semi-parliamentary Ministry.   The same is the case in England where the question of revolution is an actual subject of discussion In the press&quot;.The only card they have to play is the hope of social revolution in other countries.   Many ignorant people may believe in their success, while others will remain passive, watching the progress of events.     On the other hand there will be a large, active and critical opposition which will profit by their failures as soon as they attempt to come to terms with the Germans.       The most interesting sign we have had so far of how the ground lies is to be found in the results of the elections for the Constituent Assembly.     The elections will presumably take   &apos;  *-   at least another fortnight to complete, but there seems no reason to expect that they will not be held over the greater part of Russia. The Assembly itself is to contain something over 700 members. The Bolsheviks hope to capture at most 300 seats and to gain the support of a large number of Social Revolutionaries with whose help they might be able to form a majority.     The news up to the present seems to show that they are likely to be disappointed. In the first place the votes they have gained in Petrograd are
9 nr qmuoh less than what might have been expected.     In Petrograd itself with universal suffrage there must be well over 1,000,000 voters. Of these only some 800,000 voted, the conclusion being that those who abstained were not in favour of the Bolsheviks.     On the other hand, in spite of the terror, in spite of the absence of propaganda and in spite of the fact that the Cadets stand for war till victory, their party secured well over 200,000 votes. If this is the result in Petrograd it augurs well for the results elsewhere.The second point which is important is that the Bolsheviks have not succeeded in forming a Socialist Coalition.    If they had succeeded it would greatly have complicated the situation. The latest news, however, shows that all attempts to do so have broken down.   The Bolsheviks have even gone so far as to suppress the other Socialist papers and to dissolve the Town Councils, which could not be accused of lack of revolutionary fervour. The isolation of the Bolsheviks will make their defeat all the    * quicker and will help the sound elements of the population to unite.The South of Russia.Southern Russia is now in the hands of two Governments: (1) The Ukrainian Rada,    (2) The Cossack Federation.     The question is whether these two   will come together and agree upon a common policy.     There are certain factors which ought to go a long way towards bringing them together, their common Interest being a Federal Republic in which both would have complete autonomy.The difficulty in the Ukraine is the antagonism between the extreme Ukrainian nationalists and the rest of the population which has no desire to emphasise its distinct nationality. The Ukrainians do, of course, differ from the Great Russians
(1) in speech,    (2) in nature and outlook,    (3) in the forms and traditions of life;   hut they do not for the most part take any interest in the nationalism of the intellectuals which has chiefly grown up in Eastern Galicia.   Where the Rada gains its support among the peasantry is not in its nationalism but in its provincialism.   This provincialism makes itself felt most strongly in the solution of the land question.     The peasant lands in the Ukraine are held by small peasant proprietors, not according to communistic methods.   The Ukrainian peasants are, therefore, violently opposed to the uniform land policy of the Russian Social Revolutionaries.Thus the Rada was politically in agreement with the Socialists as against the Cadets, who wished to restrict the Ukrainian demands for political autonomy, whereas as regards the land question they were opposed to the Socialists.     Their attitude towards the Cossacks was directly the reverse.   As regards the land question both the Rada and the Cossacks were opposed to interference from * Petrograd;    they differed in political questions.   Both desire a Federal Republic, but the Cossacks,who think first and foremost of Russia, recognise that each federal.unit must be subject to the Central Government.     The Ukrainians wish to play an international role, as part of their kinsmen live across the frontier in Austrian and Hungarian territory.     Since the Bolshevik rising, however, the chances of the Cossacks and the Ukrainians working together would seem to have improved.   Northern and Central Russia is no longer strong enough to impose conditions either upon the Cossacks or the Ukraine;   thus there is every chance of a guarantee of both their political and agrarian rights.     On the other hand it is to the interests both of the Ukraine and of the Cossacks that
258nt v wthe federal Republic tq which they both belong should be strong.3.12.17.Since this Report was written news has come that the Rada has declared in favour of independence.     This is the natural outcome of the breakdown of Government In Central Russia, but it does not imply a separate peace, nor need it necessarily mean the severance of friendly relations with the Cossacks,   The intellectuals in the Rada are forcing the pace in declaring for independence, but if the situation In Russia clears up as a result of the Constituent Assembly it is quite likely that they may be forced to return to the original idea of a Federal Republic, as the mass of the peasants have no desire for independence.

</content>
</cab>
