<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/28/0 images: 123-126</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1955SECRETC.C. (55)17th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime ministers room, House of Commons, S.W.1, on Wednesday, 23rd February, 1955,at 4-00 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmltr,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. A. T. Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Osbert Peake, M.P.,Minister of Pensions and national insurance.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.Duncan Sandys, M.P.Housing   and   Loca^The Right Hon.Minister   ofGovernment.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries and Minister of Food.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Sir reginald manningham-Buller, Q.C., M.P.,Attorney-General.The following were also present:The  Most  Hon.Reading, Q.C.,Foreign Affairs.the Marquess of minister of State for mr. H. A. Watkinson, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry ofLabour and National Service.Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. F. A. Bishop.ContentsEconomic SituationMonetary Policy.Hire-Purchase.Coal Prices.
2EconomicSituation.(previous reference:C.C. (55) 16thConclusions,Minute 4.)monetary policy.Hire-purchase the Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was now in aposition to submit his proposals for checking the drain on the gold and dollar reserves which he had reported to the Cabinet on theprevious day.   These were:  (i) A substantial increase in the bank rate;(ii) Re-introduction of control over hire-purchase facilities;(hi) Increases in coal prices;(iv) Use of the Exchange Equalisation Account to support therate of exchange for transferable sterling.He was satisfied that prompt action was necessary in order to restore confidence in the strength of sterling. He therefore wished to announce the first three measures on the following day. The first two would become effective at once, and the increases in coal prices would be brought into effect as soon as possible.The Chancellor said that the fourth measure was designed to check the trafficking in transferable sterling, which was resulting ina substantial loss of dollars. The Bank of England would be able to influence these operations if they were authorised to intervene in them with a view to supporting the rate. This intervention was not designed as a further step towards convertibility of sterling. TheCabinet should understand, however, that it would have the effectof bringing the transferable rate more nearly into line with the officialrate and, to that extent, would make it easier, when the time came,to take the next step towards full convertibility.In discussion there was general support for the Chancellorsview that prompt action should be taken to check the drain on the reserves. Continuing uncertainty, or any appearance of infirmityin the Governments purpose, would tend to shake confidence stillfurther. If unpleasant measures had to be taken there was muchto be said for announcing them all at the same time.The Cabinefs discussion then turned on the proposals relatingto hire-purchase and coal prices.It was proposed that control over hire-purchase facilities shouldbe re-established by an Order under Defence Regulation 55. Thiswould apply to a wider range of goods than had previously been covered: hire-purchase of furniture,in particular,woiild be controlledfor the first time; but the percentage of the purchase price to be deposited, and the period over which payment could be spread, wouldbe less stringently limited than formerly.The Cabinet were informed that this proposal would involvereviving an emergency power which the Government had only recently relinquished. It would be unwelcome to some government supporters, who had been led to believe that the recent limitation ofDefence Regulation 55 would make it difficult for a future Govern-ment to widen the area of economic control under emergency powers.And the Opposition would be able to claim that they had warned theGovernment, when the scope of this Regulation was reduced at theend of 1954, that some of the powers which were then relinquishedwould be needed if, as had now happened, the terms of trade turnedagainst the United Kingdom. It would help to meet these criticismsif the Government could say that it was their intention to introduce legislation, when opportunity offered, to provide permanent powersto control hire-purchase facilities, and that the emergency powers had only been revived to meet the urgency of the immediate situation.There was general support in the Cabinet for the view that permanentpowers should be taken for this purpose, as a complement to other means of restricting credit.In contrast with these Parliamentary difficulties, it was unlikelythat there would be much public criticism of the re-introduction ofcontrol over hire-purchase facilities. On the other hand, it shouldbe recognised that, as earlier experience had shown, this control was
difficult to enforce and was likely to be widely evaded. Even so, itwould go some way to support the other measures which would betaken to restrict credit.Coal Prices. The Economic Policy Committee had already considered aproposal by the Minister of Fuel and Power that Ministers shouldapprove increases in coal prices recommended by the National coal board in order to meet the deficit on their working which would otherwise arise in 1955 and 1956. As a result of the Committee&apos;discussion, the Minister of Fuel and Power had again consulted theCoal Board and a revised schedule of price increases was now submitted in a memorandum subsequently circulated as C. (55) 58.Under - the latest proposal there would be an average increase of12^ per cent, in the price of coal for industrial use, but the increasein the price of household coal would be confined to the higher grades.The Minister of Fuel and Power said that these price increases would encourage economy in the use of coal and reduce the needfor coal imports. It was appropriate for this reason that the chancellors statement on the balance of payments. should include a reference to the Coal Board&apos;s intention to raise coal prices.In discussion it was argued that increased coal prices, though they might secure some economy in the use of coal, would in thelong run tend to increase the inflationary pressure in the internal economy. They would eventually cause a rise in the prices of gas,electricity, and manufactured goods, as well as in transport charges,and this would increase the pressure for further wage increases.Although it could be argued that the price increases were justified oneconomic grounds to achieve a realistic relation between the prices of imported coal and of coal produced in this country, account must also be taken of the fact that they would eventually lead to anall-round increase in internal costs.On the other hand it was pointed out that, given the rising costsshown in the Board&apos;s estimated financial results for 1955 and 1956,some increases in coal prices were inevitable if the accumulated deficit of the Board was not to be further increased.In further discussion the view was expressed that it would bedifficult to make it clear to the public that increases in coal prices would help to adjust the balance of payments. They would directly affect the balance of payments only if they reduced demand for coal to an extent which made it possible to reduce coal imports. the argument that higher coal prices would reduce the spending powerof the consumer was valid only if it were assumed that wages wouldnot rise despite the increase in the cost of living resulting from highercosts. The price increases would certainly not improve&quot; the competitive power of our export industries.It was also suggested that it would be preferable to postponeany announcement of increased coal prices until the current negotiations on miners&apos; wages had been concluded. An earlierannouncement might lead the miners&apos; representatives to increase their demands. Moreover, if the announcement were made after the award,the price increases were more likely to be attributed to the increasein wages and other costs.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, since the cost of coal imports was an important item in the balance of payments, it wouldbe reasonable and helpful to make some reference to this in theannouncement of the measures which he was taking to meet theeconomic situation. He hoped that he might at least be able to saythat the implications of the cost of coal imports on the balance ofpayments were being considered and to foreshadow some increase in price. It could be made clear that the responsibility for proposingprice increases lay with the National Coal Board.
The Prime Minister said that there was general agreement thatthe measures to increase the bank rate and to restrict hire-purchasefacilities should be announced and brought into effect on thefollowing day. The Cabinet could consider further, at their meetingon the following day, whether any reference to the coal situation should be included in the announcement and, if so, what form itshould take.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals of the Chancellor of the exchequer for an increase in the bank rate, the re-introduction ofcontrol over hire-purchase facilities, and intervention bythe Bank of England to support the rate of exchange fortransferable sterling.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Minister of fuel and Power and the Parliamentary Secretary,Ministry of Labour, to consider further what could besaid, in the announcement of measures to meet theeconomic situation, about the implications of the coalposition on the balance of payments.(3) Agreed to consider, at their meeting on the following day,the results of the consultations to be undertaken inpursuance of Conclusion (2) above.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,24th February, 1955.

</content>
</cab>
