<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/28/0 images: 181-186</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC, MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1955SECRET Copy No.C.C. (55)26th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. I,on Wednesday, 23rd March, 1955, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. Sir Anthony Eden,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. A. T. Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries and Minister of Food.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home Department and Ministerfor Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Osbert Peake, M.P.,Minister of Pensions and national insurance.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,Minister of Education.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Item 4).The Right Hon. Sir Reginald Manning-ham-Buller, Q.C., M.P., Attorney-General (Items 3-4).The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation (Item 4).The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury.Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. R. M. J. Harris.Mr. F. A. Bishop.
contents minute no.                                       subject      Parliament       ...      ......2      Commercial Policy      ... .   ...Review of the G.A.T.T.3      Uganda Protectorate......4      Railways        ....Transport Charges.5     Cotton   ............6      Fleet Exercise in South-East Asia
Parliament. 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.The Prime Minister said that ten years had now passed sincethe death of Earl Lloyd George; and he proposed to invite the Houseof Commons on 28th March to present an Address to The Queenpraying that a monument to his memory be erected in the Palace of westminster.  The Cabinet endorsed the Prime Ministers proposal.Commercial 2.   The President of the Board of Trade said that he proposed policy. to present to Parliament a White Paper setting out the results of the review of the recent review of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade.  ThisG.A.T.T. could be presented before the Easter recess; and in the meantime no(Previous further statement need be made on behalf of the government reference: regarding the results of the review. Public reactions to the outcomeC.C. (55) 14th of the review had not so far been unfavourable.Conclusions,Minute 3.) The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the President of the Boardof Trade.Uganda 3.   The Colonial Secretary said that the Kabaka&apos;s daughter,Protectorate. who was suffering from poliomyelitis, had now been brought to this(Previous country for treatment. No question should therefore arise ofReference: allowing the Kabaka to return to the Buganda Province on accountC.C. (54) 77th of his daughters illness. The date of his return might be affected by conclusions, the outcome of a further enquiry into the constitutional problem,Minute 2.) which the Baganda had initiated since the Governments announce-ment of 16th November, 1954. The report of this enquiry, which wasabout to be published, might raise further constitutional difficulties.The Cabinet Took note of the Colonial Secretary&apos;s statement.Railways. 4.   The Cabinet resumed their consideration of the increases in transport transport charges proposed by the British Transport Commission.Charges. They had before them two memoranda by the Minister of Transport(Previous (C. (55) 67 and 78) and a memorandum by the Attorney-general reference;:        (C. (55) 80).C.C. (55) 25th The Cabinefs discussion turned on the timing of the proposedConclusions, increases. These fell into three categories. First, the CommissionMinute 8.) already had power, under the Passenger Charges Scheme approvedby the Transport Tribunal in 1954, to make the proposed increase of1\ per cent, in ordinary fares on main-line railways, which would yield  2-8 millions. Secondly, they proposed to apply to theTransport Tribunal for leave to make further increases in main-linefares and increases in fares on London Transport lines and on theLondon lines of British Railways. Application for these increases,which would yield  4 millions, would be made under the special procedure of Section 23 of the Transport Act, 1953. The TribunaFshearing of this application would be held in private and would belikely to take from two to four weeks. Thirdly, the Commission had sought authority under Section 82 of the Transport Act, 1947, for increases in railway freight rates and dock and canal charges, whichwould yield  17-7 millions. Authority for these increases must begiven by regulations and, before making such regulations, theMinister was required to consult with, and consider the advice of, thepermanent members of the Transport Tribunal, acting as a consultative Committee.It was the general view of the Cabinet that it would be preferable that the proposed increases of charges in all three categories should
be announced together, and that the timing of their announcement would need careful consideration. In these circumstances theGovernments next step should be to make the necessary referenceto the permanent members of the Transport Tribunal in respect ofthe proposed increases in railway freight rates and in dock and canalcharges. The Chairman of the British Transport Commission shouldbe informed that the Government were ready to make this referenceforthwith and to discuss the timing of action on the proposed increases in passenger fares when the views of the transport tribunal in respect of freight rates and dock and canal charges were known. He should also be reminded of the need to satisfy the travelling public that reasonable progress was being made in reducing redundancy and restrictive practices on the railways before they were asked to pay higher fares. The Cabinet were reminded that the figures relating to the financial position of the british transport Commission, which were quoted in C. (55) 67, hadallowed for further special economies, including staff economies ofthe order of  15 millions a year, and that the agreement of theRailway Unions to the establishment of a British RailwaysProductivity Council had already been announced in Parliament(House of Commons, Official Report, 15th March, 1955, Col. 1107).It was the general view of the Cabinet, however, that the Governmentwould be vulnerable to criticism if they allowed extensive increases in charges to be announced without, at the same time, providingfurther evidence that effective action was being taken to eliminateredundancy and restrictive practices on the railways.The Cabinet Agreed in principle that increases in railway charges of theorder indicated in C. (55) 67 would have to be accepted; butinvited the Minister of Transport to discuss the timing ofthose increases with the Chairman of the British transport commission on the basis (i) that the advice of the permanent members of the Transport Tribunal would first be sought in respect of the proposed increases in railway freight ratesand dock and canal charges; and (ii) that no action wouldbe taken to increase passenger fares until the way was clear to introduce the increased freight charges and until evidencecould be shown of satisfactory progress in reducingredundancy and restrictive practices on the railways.Cotton. \(previous reference:CC. (55) 21stConclusions,Minute 4.)5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by thePresident of the Board of Trade (C. (55) 76) on the current difficultiesof the cotton industry.The President of the Board of Trade said that, in preparation for the deputation which the Prime Minister was to receive on thefollowing day, the Cotton Board had submitted a memorandum(annexed to C. (55) 76) outlining the action which they wished theGovernment to take to relieve the difficulties of the industry. they proposed that the Government should take steps to end duty-free entry for manufactured cotton goods from the Commonwealth andshould in the meantime impose a quota on imports of grey cloth forthe home market. This action was designed to meet competition from imports in the home market. It was true that there had beena substantial increase in imports of cotton cloth in 1954, attributablealmost entirely to India and Hong Kong, and the rate of importsfrom these countries had increased still further in the current year.Lancashire could not compete with these imports, which were produced by cheap labour, so long as they enjoyed unrestricted andduty-free entry into the United Kingdom. But the plan put forward by the Cotton Board would not meet more than a part of theindustry&apos;s difficulties. By far the greater part of the problem arose from loss of exports, and for this the Board&apos;s plan provided no
remedy. The Board had not faced the fact that, whatever was done to check imports of cheap cotton cloth, some contraction of activity in the industry was inevitable and might be permanent.If the Government agreed to impose a quota, they would ineffect be committed to the permanent protection of the cottonindustry. This would lead to pressure for quota action to protectother industries from competition from many countries. If it proved impossible to resist the pressure for a quota, it would be preferable that the quota should be discriminatory so as to avoid retaliationfrom, and the use of unjustified restrictions by, non-commonwealth countries. The purpose of the quota would be to limit imports ofgrey cloth, so far as thev were retained for the home market, to the1954 level, pending discussions with India and Hong Kong on thepermanent regulation of their exports of cotton cloth. The immediatebenefit to the cotton industry would be small; and, in order to meet their loss of export markets, which would be aggravated by therestrictions which had just been imposed by Australia, there wouldbe increased pressure for the removal of purchase tax on textiles.The industry were convinced that this was the most importantmeasure that could be taken to assist textile exports, which depended on an expanding home market.In a preliminary discussion of this problem the following points were made: -(a) The Minister of Defence should review the possibility of placing forward orders for Government requirements of textiles.This remedy had proved valuable in 1952.(b) A further appeal should be made to the Prime Minister ofIndia to restrain voluntarily the flow of exports of grey cloth to theUnited Kingdom. It was unlikely that he would find himself ableto do this; but if the request were made, it might be more difficult for the Indian Government to raise objections to a quota or to takeretaliatory action if it were imposed.(c) If a quota were necessary, it might be preferable to imposeit on a non-discriminatory basis under Article XIX of the GeneralAgreement on Tariffs and Trade (G.A.T.T.). In any event the quotashould be presented as a purely temporary measure, taken in orderto hold the position until some permanent restrictions, e.g., by tariff,could be worked out. In this connection, it was again pointed outthat the Government had yet to give full consideration to theproblem of future tariff policy.(d) It was suggested that any interim action by quota might be accompanied by a promise of a full enquiry into the position and prospects of the cotton industry, including the case for abolishingpurchase tax on textiles or for altering its incidence. As against this it was argued that the Government might thereby become involvedin obligations to support, by financial or other means, the present level of activity in the cotton industry.(e) Apart from its cost to the Exchequer the abolition of purchase tax on textiles would be open to grave objections. Otherindustries could exercise even greater pressure for such relief; andany concession made to textiles would have to be extended to thecarpet and silverware industries and possibly to the motor carindustry. On the other hand, it was argued that exceptionaltreatment for textiles could be justified on the ground that, owingto the run of production, the cost of exports was determined largely by the volume of demand in the home market. Moreover, thepresent purchase tax arrangements bore heavily on better quality-textiles and were therefore hampering the natural development ofthe export side of the industry which ought now to concentrate onthe export of better-class cotton garments. It was doubtful whether anything short of the abolition of purchase tax would be regardedas any real help to the industry.(/) It was argued that a quota should not apply to imports from hong Kong, whose position was quite different from that of India.Hong Kong was a Colony into whose market United Kingdom goods
enjoyed unrestricted and duty-free entry. The increase in her exportsof textiles to this country was due to increased production directlystimulated by our action in reducing her entrepot trade, in pursuanceof our foreign policy. Hong Kong was exporting many other types of manufactures, and there would be pressure from other industries in the United Kingdom to restrict imports of these. It would bedifficult to justify restricting imports from Hong Kong withoutimposing a quota on all other Colonies, some of which, such asJamaica, were now developing textile industries. The imposition ofquotas on the Colonies would seem wholly inconsistent with theGovernments successful efforts to secure agreement to a Colonialwaiver in the recent review of the G.A.T.T(g) As regards Lancashire&apos;s export trade to the Colonies, theCabinet were informed that Colonial Governments had recentlybeen warned that they might have to be asked, on balance ofpayments grounds, to consider reducing their imports of Japanesetextiles.(h) The suggestion was made that Lancashire&apos;s export trade might be assisted by some form of subsidy. The view was expressed that experience had shown that, on balance, the use of export subsidies, even if concealed, would not be to our advantage. We had more to lose in the long run from a competition in export subsidies,since other countries, whose export trade was a smaller proportionof their total production, could use export subsidies with more effect.The Cabinet (1) Took note of C. (55) 76.(2) Agreed to resume their discussion of this problem at a later meeting, in the light of the representations made by thedeputation from the Cotton Board which the PrimeMinister was to receive on the following day.Fleet Exercise 6.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by thein South-East Minister of Defence (C. (55) 79) outlining the plans for holding in asia. June, off the east coast of Malaya, a Fleet exercise by units of theAustralian, New Zealand and United Kingdom Navies. It was statedin the memorandum that the value of the exercise would be enhancedif forces of the other Manila Treaty Powers took part in it. TheAustralian and New Zealand Governments were now being askedwhether they approved this suggestion and, if they did, the otherTreaty Powers would be asked to join in the exercise.The Cabinet Took note with approval of the plans outlined in C. (55) 79.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,23rd March, 1955.

</content>
</cab>
