<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/15/13 images: 150-161</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
J KEY.ioCUMBNT IS THE PRO BRTY OF HIS britannic MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).SECRET.w*gf(41. )4Q*24TH ,FEBRUARY,  1 941 .WAR    CABINET.POLICY IN THE MIDDLE EAST AND eastern mediterranean.COPY NO.N0te By the Secretary.The attached telegrams (a) from the Prime Ministerto General Wavell, dated 11th February, 1941, and(b) from the Chiefs of Staff to the Commanders-in-ChiefMiddle East and the Commander in Chief, Mediterranean,are circulated in connection with Item 2 of theCabinet Agenda for this evening&apos;s Meeting.(Signed)    E.E. BRIDGES *Secretary.Great George Street, S.W.I.,24TH FEBRUARY, 1941o

COPY OF A TELEGRAM DATED 12TH FEBRUARY,  1941,. FROMTHE &quot;&apos;&apos;7AR&quot;&quot;OFPlCE TOTHE CbiaiAHDBR-in-CHIEF . MIDDLE EAST.,,(51265.      11/2),,Prime Minister to General Wavell:.-1, &quot;Accept my heartful congratulations on this latestadmirable victory? and on the unexpected speed with&quot;whichCyrenaica has been conquereda    I have carried out yourwishes in mentioning Generals 0rConnor and Greagh.2. Defence Committee considered whole situation last night, comprising extremely favourable developments inUnited States supplies-..    Second, increasingly menacing attitudeof Japan and plain possibility she may attack us in the nearfuture.    Third,, undoubted serious probability of attemptinvasion here     In this general setting we must settleMediterranean plans03. We should have been content-with making a safe flankfor Egypt at Tobruk, and we told you that thereafter greece and/or Turkey must have prioritys but that if you could getBenghazi easily and without prejudice to European calls, somuch the better&apos;,,    We are delighted that you have got thisprize three weeks ahead of expectation, but this does notalter, indeed it rather confirms; our previous directive,namely that your major effort must now be to aid greece and/or Turkeyc    This rules out any serious effort againstTripoli, although minor demonstrations thitherwards would bea useful feinto    You should therefore make yourself secureat Benghazi and concentrate all available forces in theDelta in preparation for movement to Europe0&apos; 4. Both Greece and Turkey have hitherto refused ouroffers of technical. Units,, because they say these are too small to solve their main problem but conspicuous enough to provoke German intervention,,    However, this interventionbecomes more certain and imminent every day, and may beginat any time now,,    If Turkey and Yugoslavia would tellBulgaria they will attack her unless . he joins them in resisting a German advance southward$  this might create abarrieprequiring much larger German forces than are now availablein Roumania6    But I fear they will not do this, and willfool away their chances of combined resistance as was donein the Low Countries05. Our first thoughts must be for our ally Greece, which is&quot;actually fighting so we&quot;1, If Greece is trampled down orforced to make a separate peace with Italy, yielding also air and Naval strategic points against us  to Germany, effecton Turkey will be very bad...    But if Gre^co with Britishaid can hold up iw some months G^man advance, chances of turkish intervention b^ fuvovred.    Therefore it wouldseem that we should tr\y -co get in a position to offer the greeks the transfer to Gix-oco of r&apos;ix., Sghtvxng porttop. of the Army whichhas hitherto defended Egypt and make every plan for sendingand reinforcing it to the limit with men and material,6, We do not know what Greece will say to a great offer of this kindo We do not know what are her means of resistingan invasion from Bulgaria by German forces,, It is reasonable to assume that they have a plan to move troops from Albaniato hold the ?-----^ and line-&apos;3 of defence already builtalong or near the Gu l^r^an frontier.    They cannot surely

jiaw&quot;pursued their advantage in Albania without any thought of this mortal- danger to their right and almost rear.. . Ifthey have a good plan it would be worth our while to- backit with all our strength and fight the Germans in Greece,hoping thereby to draw in both Turks and Yugoslavs.,   you should begin forthwith plans and timetables as well as anypreparatory movements of shippings7,-        It is not intended that you should delay Mandibleswhich we regard as most urgent08^ In order to give the very best chance to concerting allpossible measures, both diplomatic and militarjr, against theGermans in the Balkans, we are sending the Foreign secretary and C.I.G.S.  to join you in Cairo0    They will leave on the12th February and should reach you 14th or 15th February*.Having surveyed the whole position in Cairo and. got allpreparatory measures on the move, you would no doubt go to athens with them and thereafter if convenient to Angora.,   ItIs hoped that at least four divisions, including one armoured-division, and whatever additional air forces the Greekairfields are ready for, together with all available munitions,may be offered in the best possible way and in the shortesttime.-9v We can form no opinion here as to what ports of Greecewe should use or what front we should try to hold or try toget them to holdc    That can only be settled on the spotwith the Greek Command.r.10.-       In the event of it proving impossible to reach any goodagreement with the Greeks, and work out a practical militaryplan, then we must try to save as much from the wreck aspossible.   We must at all costs keep Crete and take any Greekislands which are of use as air bases..   We could alsoreconsider the advance on Tripolic    But these will only beconsolation prizes after the classic race has been lost..There will, of course, always remain the support of Turkey^.11.- You will, of course, show this to Longmore and give himmy best regards,12*-       Operative orders are being sent by the Chiefs of Staffs&quot;

t  copy OF A TJSLEjGIbAIVi DATED 12TM FEBRUARY,   1941,FROM THE   &quot;AR    :&apos;.FJ&quot;C5 TO TEE COMMANDERS-IN-CHIEF,HIDDLJ EAST, AND QOQlfiKD:,2-IN-OHOF.  MEDITERRANEAN.(5126S    11/2),Following from C.0.S.No. .56% -The Defence Committee have^ re-examined, the policy set out in C.O.S.   telegram No. 49s as modified hy telegramNo.  55P in the light of -(a) The unexpectedly early capture of Benghazi;(b) The Turkish refusal to accept the immediate assistance of British forces (see Prime    inister&apos;telegram to the President of the TurkishRepublic);    and(c) The urgent request of the Greek Government(Athens telegram No,  194 of 8th February^pressing for info relation as  co the size and composition of the British forces which we would send to Greece in certain eventualities,20 The Committee agreed -(a) That no serious operation should he undertakenbeyond Benghzi which should, be held with theminimum forces that you consider necessary asa secure flank for Egy t;    and(b) That Operation &quot;Mandibles&quot; is still of thefirst importance, and. should, be undertaken at the earliest possible moment.3. With re ard to telegram No.  53 as it affectsparagraph 1 (c) of telegram No. 49, the position has b^enaltered by the Turkish refusal of our offer.      The DefenceCommittee consider that, if Greece were to yield, toGermany without fighting, Turkey would, only fight to resistattack on her own territory,  and consequently that theonly way of making sure that the Turks do fight is to give,sufficient support to the Greeks to ensure that they fight.Accordingly,  the Defence Committee have decided that it isessential for us to place ourselves forthwith in a positionto send the largest possible land and- air forces fromAfrica to the European Continent, in order to assist the greeks against a probable German attack through Bulgaria.4. It is clearly impossible to settle the precisesize and. composition of these forces, or their destinationin Greece, until information is available as to -(a) The Greek plan to meet an attack by Germanythrough Bulgaria, and:(b) The forces which can be m de available fromAfrica, having regard, to the commitmentsmentioned in paragraph 2 above.h Telegram No,(so)in Paper No. Hist.  (B) 2.j6 Telegram No. (l3.)/ Not reproduced.

S.        As regards the Greek plan, the Foreign ^ecretapy,accompanied by C.I.G.S..-, leave here 12th February to consult with you in Egypt and. would, like there to meet our Liaison Delegation, to Turkey,    . Please arrange.Thereafter the Foreign Secretary and. C.I..G.S. proposeto proceed, to Athens for discussions with the GreekAuthorities at  che earliest possible moment.      It willprobably be desirable for the Com.iand.ers-in-Ohief or theirrepresentatives to accompany them.6. As regards che size or che forces which can bemade available from Egypt.,  it is not possible to say moreat this stage than chat they should, be as strong aspossible, and. that the 10 Squadrons, R.A.F. which were originally earmarked, for Turkey, can be drawn upon.     you should, seriously consid.er the possibility of using theyeomanry in Palestine both on the Suez Canal and to guardfuture convosrs of prisoners to India..     77e also hope thatas soon as kismayu is captured, you will think it rightto send the South African Division to Egypt.7. It is not, possible to settle at this stage&apos;whether &apos;the British Forces would be based, on Salonika or thePiraeus.      The Greeks will undoubtedly press for theformer, but it may well be that, even if the Greeks retracttheir refusal to accept British forces until the germans have actually marched, and. we had sufficient forces available, it would be 1 possible for them to.arrive salonika in time  to be effective.      This, however,  canonly be seeded when we know the Greek plan.8. There is a further point.      Ye should cake the first opportunity of occupjring with the acquiescence of theGreek Government, Iviitylene, Lerimos and. Levitha   in orderto secure our communications to the Straits.     You should,be prepared to discuss proposals with the ForeignSecretars^.S. .       keanwhile 9 the object of this telegram is to letyou know the mind, of the Defence Committee, and to enableyou to make such preparations and pirns as are possible at this stage, including the collection of the necessary shipping, for the move of the maximum forces to Greece atthe earliest possible moment.      You should work out atime-table for discussion with Mr. -Eden and. C.I.G.S.- -10.Please pass to A.0.C.-in-C,, as from Air Ministry,




</content>
</cab>
