<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/205/4 images: 214-215</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCP(79) 422 January 1979COPY NO80CABINETSALE OF HARRIER   TO CHINAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign andCommonwealth Affairs1. A decision on Harrier has important strategic and commercialimplications,.    The commercial arguments are strong.    The sale of 70Harriers, with engines,  spares and support, would be worth about 600 million, and licensed manufacture of airframes and engines in Chinawhich would be an essential element of the deal could well add a further 600 million.    We have made it clear to the Chinese that we want a balancedpackage with a substantial civilian element in addition *o the Harrier. Thereare reasonable prospects for civil contracts worth several billion pounds,representing thousands of jobs, many in the most difficult areas, if we agreeto sell Harrier.    These are less likely to come to us if we refuse.2. The strategic arguments rest firstly on our view of China&apos;s future.Internally, the prospects for economic development and a more open societyhave improved.    Externally, the Chinese realise that their rapidindustrialisation will require a peaceful environment.    They are stillconcerned over what they see as the Soviet threat to them;  but they nowdownplay their thesis on the inevitability of war between the super powers.3. Soviet concern about China is directed not only at the United Kingdombut, as Mr Brezhnev&apos;s messages show, at the West as a whole.    We madeclear our wish to pursue detente and constructive relations in Moscow in1975 and signed the Helsinki Final Act in the same year.    But the Sovietdnion has to recognise that the extent of any influence they may wish toexercise with us depends on their actions.    Their increased defenceexpenditure;  their policies in Africa and Kampuchea;   and their attitudeover human rights demonstrates that their interpretation of detente is stilllimited, with the emphasis on sophisticated arms control negotiations andgeneral discussions of disarmament.4,sales andAt Guadeloupe there was general support for our approach to defence- - and our major allies are prepared to leave the Harrier decision to us.The Americans do not expect a Strategic Arms Limitation Talks (SALT) IIAgreement to be prejudiced by modest Western defence sales.    The mostlikely Soviet reaction to the sale of Harrier would be to prolong the presentrelative coolness in Anglo-Soviet relations.    It might mean losing1CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALcommercial contracts of the order of  100- 200 million in the nearfuture.   Against this the Soviet Union has taken up less than  500 millionof the  950 million line of credit we offered in 1975,,5t       Soundings in the region show that Japan, Association of South EastAsia Nations (ASEAN) countries and Australia have no criticism of aHariier sale0    The Indians may be less happy, but have not commented.We do not expect difficulties in the Co-ordinating Committee on theInternational Embargo, where we intend to use a &quot;no comment&quot; procedure.The French are ready to sell defensive weapons, including anti-tank andanti-aircraft missiles and advanced helicopters.    The Americans, like theGermans, do not intend to sell arms to China, but normalisation will face uswith staffer commercial competition from the United States in the civil field.6. In consulting our friends and allies we have stressed that we wouldnot sell China offensive weapons, eg Tornado.    Harrier is essentially ashort-range tactical aircraft with a defensive role in support of groundstroops, and a range, at low   altitude and with a typical payload,of between100 and 150 miles.     The line between offensive and defensive weapons isdifficult tc draw, but I do not believe we should in public presentation acceptthat Harrier is an offensive weapon system,7. A decision not to sell Harrier would be seen by the Chinese as arebuff, with political as well as commercial consequences.    We share theWest&apos;s interest in involving China closely in the international system,including disarmament, security and North/South problems. Developmentof our relations across the board, including defence sales, should help toachieve this.8. I invite my colleagues to agree that:-a. We should approve the sale to China of Harrier and themanufacture under licence of the aircraft and its engine, providedthat there is satisfactory evidence of substantial civil sales.b. The Secretary of State for Industry should be authorised toenter into commitments on the Harrier and to authorise BritishAerospace and Rolls Royce to awig^Heads of Agreement during hisvisit to China in February provided he is satisfied by the progresson civil sales.c. We should continue to make clear to the Soviet leaders thatwe want to maintain good relations and consolidate detente.D A L, Oforeign and Commonwealth Office22 January I979 2CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
