<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/156/16 images: 189-195</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JEST YTS GOVERNMENT62CP(71) 41 COPY NO    0 (026 March 1971CABINETRB 211Note by the Secretary of State for DefenceAttached Is a note by officials which provides factual background to my memorandum CP(7l) 40.Ministry of Defence SW126 March 1971
ANNEXRB 211Note by officials.     At this morning1s meeting of the Ministerial Group on Rolls-Royce,chaired by the Home Secretary, officials were asked to prepare a factualbackground note setting out, in particular, the fin ncial figures relevant to the position now reached in the negotiations between the United KingdomGovernment, the United States Government and the Lockheed Company.2.     We have tried to explain briefly in the following paragraphs why itis so difficult to produce precise figures for the various offers that havebeen made*   We suggest, however, that for the purposes of the decisions that have to be taken on Monday, the crucial figures on the expenditure side arethose summarised in paragraphs 5 and 6 so far as development is concerned and in paragraph 13 so far as the loss on production engines is concerned.So far as the financial benefits to be received are concerned, the main considerations are summarised in paragraph 15 below.3.     The financial figures particularly in relation to the additional cost to the United Kingdom for production engines are extremely complicatedfor a variety of reasons, the main ones being -a. The distinction between the 540 engines for which a firm andextremely unprofitable contract had been negotiated between theprevious Rolls-Royce Company and Lockheeds and engines additional tothe 540 in respect of which the previous Rolls-Royce Company were in process of negotiating with Lockheeds a much more satisfactoryprice.b. The negotiations which had been going on between Rolls-Royceand the Lockheed Company about the provision to be made forescalation between the present time and the time when the engineswere delivered.
4&quot;     In view of these complications any figures must inevitably be broadapproximations.   With this proviso the present position can be summarisedas follows.Development5.     To develop the RB 211 up to contract specification of 42,000 lbsthrust in hot conditions is likely to cost about an additional  100 million.Her Majesty&apos;s Government had made it clear to Lockheeds before theSecretary of State for Defence went to Washington that they were preparedto incur this expenditure themselves subject to an appropriate warrantythat the L loll aircraft would proceed.   The present position about awarranty is dealt with in a paper \which the Secretary of State for defence is circulating separately to the Cabinet.6.     Lockheeds have throughout the discussions made it clear that if the rb 211 project goes ahead they would expect, in due course to have anengine with a thrust in hot conditions of 45*000 lbs.   This is important for some of their customers such as Air Canada in order that the aeroplanecan become an economic Transatlantic aircraft.   The current view of Rolls-Royce is that 459000 lbs thrust in hot conditions can be achieved withoutany major redesign of the engine and that to meet this requirement wouldnot add anything appreciable to the estimate of  100 million for development.   The view of the Ministry of Aviation Supply is that the extra expenditure to meet this additional thrust might be as much as 30 million.   On the other hand, the position is completely open for thenew Rolls-Royce Company to negotiate an increased price for the developedengine to recover at any rate some of this additional R and D expenditure.Cost of Production Engines7.     There are 2 current assumptions about the true extra cost of completing 646 engines as compared with the original price negotiated by the previous Rolls-Royce Company and Lockheeds.2
8.     Cooper Brothers, the accountants employed by the Ministry of aviation/tionSupply to look into the whole Rolls-Royce position, originally expressedthe view that the additional cost would be of the order of  124 million.They have subsequently revised this figure to  114 million.9.     As against this, Sir William Cook who was one of the 3 &quot;wise men&quot;who looked into the whole RB 211 position recently on behalf ofHer Majesty&apos;s Government and who is now a Director of Rolls-Royce, estimatedthat the additional cost would be about  80 million.   Following the meetingof the Ministerial Group on Rolls-Royce held on Wednesday 24 March, atwhich Ministers asked that the latest view of the Rolls-Royce (l97l)Directors should be obtained, Lord Cole has indicated that the best estimate he can give at present of the additional cost of 646 deliveredengines over the original neogtiated price is  91 million.   (The effectof the difference is explained in paragraph 13a. iii. below.)10.   The offer on the price of engines which Her Majesty&apos;s Government had previously made to Lockheeds would have produced an additional return of 97 million.11.   It has now been estimated (and this has been confirmed, byMr Connally and Mr Packard of the United States Administration) that thefurthest that it is possible for the Lockheed Corporation to go, in viewpartly of their financial position and partly because of competition fromthe General Electric Company, is to offer an additional  50 million or 60 million.   Tho difference between these figures can be brieflyexplained as follows.   The Lockheed Corporation has offered to accept aprice increase for the committed engines (ie the 540 engines referred toabove, plus another 15 engines, as increased spares backing for 144aircraft, which would produce an increased payment of  50 million over theoriginal contract price.12.   Lockheeds have not made a definite offer for the price of enginesabove the 555 referred to above but have indicated that provided the rb 211 engine remains competitive with the General Electric engine theywould accept an additional price, which would have the effect of producing 60 million as compared with the  50 million quoted above.
Summary on the additional cost of production engines13o   Summing up these considerations, so far as the cost of productionengines is concerned, the picture is as follows -A. Additional cost to Her Majesty&apos;s Government of producing 555 engines(the latest variant of the figure of 540, quoted above) or 646 enginesis -i. Cooper Brothers figures ie the highest estimate,  114 million;ii. Sir William Cook&apos;s estimate ie the lowest estimate,  80 million?iii. the latest Rolls-Royce (l97l) estimate,  91 million,   (in the table below we have used the latest Rolls-Royce (l97l) figure.    if sir William Cook&apos;s figures were used the effect on the figures in sub-paragraph D below xrould be as follows:   As compared with the lossshown of  31 million- 41 million using the Rolls-Royce (l97l) figures,there would be a loss under the Cook formula of  31 million both inthe case of 555 engines and 646 engines.)B. The United Kingdom proposal to Lockheeds prior to Lord Carrington*visit to Washington was as follows -i. Cooper Brothers figure,  114 million- 97 million =  17 million lossii. Rolls-Royce (l97l) figures,  91 million- 97 million =  6 millionprofit.C. Lockheeds proposition prior to the Carrington visit -i. Cooper Brothers figures,  114 million- 42 million s  72 millionlossii. Rolls Royce (l97l) figures,  91 million- 42 million s  49 millionloss.D. Present position -Lockheeds offer ( 50-60 million)i. Cooper Brothers figures,  114 million- 50-60 million ^ .64 million- 54 million lossii. Rolls Royce (l97l) figures,  91 million- 50-60 million = 41- 31 million loss.14.   What this amounts to is that Her Majesty&apos;s Government have, as aresult of decisions already taken, said to the American authorities, bothgovernmental and industrial, that they are prepared to negotiate on thebasis of an additional  80 million above the original Rolls-Royce/Lockheed price for 646 engines.   Lockheeds have now offered  50 million- 60 million.4
Financial Advantages to the United Kingdom in proceeding with the RB 211Contract15o   The figures which have so far &quot;been given to Ministers are as follows -a.  40 million profit on the supply of spares for a number of years ahead for 646 delivered engines -  40 million (discounted).b. Savings on the additional overheads which would otherwise be applicable to the rest of the Rolls Royce business a  25 million.c. Savings on the pajmient of unemployment benefit, redundancy payetc =  25 million.This gives a total of  90 million.16,   On top of all this there are a number of imponderables of which ministers may wish to take account, eg -a. The extent to which the collapse of the RB 211 project woulditensify the anxieties already felt overseas in the confidence and stability of British industry? and b. whether if the RB 211 does not go ahead other sub-contractingfirms, essential for defence purposes, are likely to go intobankruptcy and will require to be rescued.5


</content>
</cab>
