<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/111/0 images: 21-23</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1962C. (62) 154 Copy No.&apos; g 19r/* October, 1962CABINETPENSIONS OF THE HIGHER judiciary memorandum by the Lord chancellor feel I must bring to the attention of my colleagues a point which was notraised on 10th July when approval was given to proposals by the then chief secretary, Treasury, for introducing a Pensions Increase Bill in the forthcoming session.  (C.C. (62) 45th Conclusions, Minute 3.)2. The question is whether the pensions of some judges who retired before1959 should be included in the Bill. It has been decided that, under the Bill, thepensions of retired County Court Judges should be increased but the position ofLords of Appeal, Judges of the High Court in England and of similar status inScotland who retired before 1959 was not considered; although it was decided thatthe Bill should provide for increase of the pensions payable to their widows andother dependants.3. It is anomalous and will no doubt be thought unfair if those judgeswho retired before 1959 do not benefit under the Bill. There are only 11 pensionersaffected in England and one in Scotland. No retired judge in Northern ireland would be eligible. The total cost of the increase for the 11 pensioners in Englandwould be  2,059 and for the pensioner in Scotland,  363.4. There was no need to include such judges in previous measures of thiskind before 1959. This v/as because there had been no change in the judges&apos;basic pensions so that judges retiring received no higher pensions than thosewho had retired before. In 1959 the Judicial Pensions Act increased the pensions of judges who retired in the future and by the same Act the pensions of judgeswho had already retired were increased by 12 per cent. This was equivalentto the maximum increase in the Pensions Increase Act passed earlier in 1959and it was given with effect from the same date as the increases given under thatAct. It would have been possible to increase the pensions of the older judgesunder the Pensions Increase Act. It was decided not to do so mainly because theincrease to the judges would have been very much higher than other increases inthe public services and might have caused difficulties in Parliament. They were therefore dealt with in the Judicial Pensions Act, 1959.5. The object of the present Bill is to give some compensation for the fallin the value of money since public service pensions were awarded or lastincreased. This fall has affected retired judges as much as other public service pensioners covered by the Bill. As I have said, County Court Judges are recovered and also the widows and dependants of judges who retired before 1959.6. It can be argued that, as the pensions in question are substantial, thesejudges have less need than most pensioners for compensation for the fall in thevalue of money. The largest pension of a judge who retired before 1959 is thatof Lord Wright, aged 93, who receives  4,200 a year and the lowest figure for anyjudge of the Supreme Court is  2,940.SECRET:ttitS fiOCtfMEM&apos; IS tHt: PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT
v; .--7. It can also be arguedand this is-the point oniwhich most difficulty was seen in 1959, that the size of the increases themselves when contrasted with thepensions received by others for public service would make the passage&apos;of the Billdifficult. Lord Wrights, increase would be  504, and judges of the Supreme Courtwho retired before 1959 would get a minimum increase of  353. In the CivilService the highest known increases are one of  316 and one of  258, though inpractice increases over  200 will be rare and most increases will be well below that figure. Such increases may well seem very high to some people and lead toadverse c&apos;criticfern&apos;during the passage of the Bill. &quot;8. Despite these arguments, the Secretary of State for Scotland and I are&apos;of the opinion that this category of pension should be covered in the Bill andthe Chief Secretary, Treasury, is prepared to acquiesce subject to the agreementof our colleagues.9. I invite my colleagues to agree that the pensions of the higher judiciarywho retired before 1959 should be increased by what the Chief Secretary agreesis the appropriate amount, namely 12 per cent., in the forthcoming pensions increase Bill.&apos; &apos; &apos; &apos;/HMif;;4M D.   vHouse of Lords, S.W. 1,9th October, 1962.


</content>
</cab>
