<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/111/0 images: 220-222</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
,       ,.    -;;! ,       Printed, for the Cabinet.   December 1962 .. \ -C (62* 185&apos;&quot; &apos;r r- .:;copy:Np: : 513rd December, 1962 : ...... -CABINETSPORT AND RECREATIONMemorandum by the Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster general. The Cabinet invited me (C.C. (62) 65th Conclusions, Minute 4) to circulate a revised version of a statement on this subject, taking account of the points madein the Cabinet discussion and in particular the possibility that the Lord Presidentmight be asked to take responsibility for co-ordinating action among Departments,with the help of some outside advice.2. I attach a revised draft of such a statement, which I understand is acceptable to the Lord President.J. A. B.-C.Treasury Chambers, S. W. 1,3rd December, 1962.PROPOSED STATEMENT1. I wish to make a statement about the Government^ arrangements forco-ordination and development of sport and recreation in the community.2. This important subject has, as the House knows, been considered by aCommittee set up by the Central Council of Physical Recreation under theChairmanship of Sir John Wolfenden.3. The House will remember that when on 8th May my Rt. Hon. and learnedFriend the former Chancellor of the Exchequer announced the willingness of theGovernment to approve substantial increases in local authority and educationalcapital expenditure on recreational projects, he added that the Government wasstudying this Report and that its suggestions on organisation required further thought.4. In the meantime considerable progress has been made with the provisionof sporting and recreational facilities. On capital account and this is the mostimportant aspect from the financial point of view publicly financed work onfacilities provided exclusively for sport has risen from  3-6 million in 1960-61, to 9 million in 1962-63. In addition, capital expenditure on sporting facilities inconnection with education will amount to about  18 million in the current year, and growing provision is made by industry and commerce for their employees. On therecurrent side, the annual grants to voluntary bodies such as the Central Council for physical Recreation, the National Playing Fields Association and the Scottish Council of Physical Recreation have more than doubled since 1959 and now total 366,000.5. These large and mounting expenditures are however contained in many different programmes for which responsibility is distributed between my Rt. Hon.Friends, the Secretary of State for Scotland, the Minister of Education-, and theCONFIDENTIAL1788 iJ-;f-:- -:THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
Minister of Housing and Local Government. The Wolfenden Committee were,in the Government^ view, right in drawing attention to the fact that this is a subject which cuts across the normal division of Ministerial responsibility.6. This is not a matter that can be solved, in the Government^ view, bycreating another agency that would be interposed between the responsible ministers and local authorities. Schools and their playing fields must be planned together;local authorities must be in a position to plan their priorities.7. The Government, therefore, while agreeing with the diagnosis of theWolfenden Report, do not agree with the remedy it proposes of establishing aSports Development Council. Co-ordination is of course required in thedevelopment of these facilities so that we can get the best value out of them.With this object the Government is establishing a standing group of ministers most closely concerned with sport and recreation. My noble and learned friend the Lord President of the Council will be Chairman of this group, which willsupervise the development of sporting and recreational facilities in the variousprogrammes. This group will have access. to expert advice from both outside and inside the Government service, including of course the voluntary organisations concerned with various games and sports.


</content>
</cab>
