<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/111/0 images: 244-249</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT51CL (62) 191 COPY NO.24th November, 1962CABINETLEASEHOLD REFORMMemorandumGovernment and Minister fox&apos; Welsh affairs am again under pressure to make a statement on the Government&apos;attitude to leasehold reform.     I shall have to say something when mr. Dennis HowelUs Bill comes up for Second Reading on 7th December.2,      In May the Cabinet considered a paper by my predecessor onthis subject (C.(62) 83) and invited him to formulate a scheme for the compulsory extension of long leases on market value terms(C.C. (62) 38th Conclusions, Minute 3).3.      Officials of the Departments concerned have been working out ascheme along these lines.    I am advised that such a scheme is \practicable, though it would be complex in detail and not free fromdifficulty.    But having considered the problem myself I cannot escape the conclusion that any proposal to give further security to lessees is extremely dubious, even politically.   I should welcome another discussionwith my colleagues before proceeding further.4.     Our dilemma is that the demands of leaseholders on the one hand,and the interests of landlords and the value of the leasehold system onthe other, are irreconcilable.     It may be convenient if I remincj, mycolleagues of the particular points where the conflict of interesfrismost acute.5.      The root of the trouble is that lessees cannot or will not under-stand the leasehold system and the limited nature of the interest forwhich they have paid.     The terms which landlords ask either for saleof the reversion or for an extension of the lease strike them as&apos;wildly unreasonable.     What they demand is a right of compulsoryenfranchisement or, failing that, compulsory renewal at any time whichsuits them, on terms considerably lower than market value.    But land-lords buy and sell reversions just as lessees buy and sell leases, andthe price which a purchaser pays for the reversion reflects the factthat he is entitled when the lease expires to have the house surrendered to him, to re-let to the tenant at a rack rent under the Landlord and-1-SECK.ET
Tenant Act, 1954 or, if he can defeat the 1954 Act, to deal with as he wishes.    If the lessee is allowed to enfranchise or renew at less thanmarket value, this is bound to involve an element of confiscation andpossibly some real hardship to small landlords.Egta;te ManagemenJL6.      The leasehold system is not simply a piece of mediaevaltyranny.    In the hands of good landlords it can produce a very high standard of management and amenity, higher than anything that can besecured by statutory planning control.     There are valuable advantages which are well shown, for example, in Kampstead Garden Suburb,the Calthorpe Estate, Birmingham, and Letchworth and YfelwyhGarden Cities.     Leasehold enfranchisement on any terms would destroy these benefits completely:   compulsory renewal would be lessdamaging.    On the other hand, the insecurity inherent in the systemundoubtedly discourages many leaseholders, during the last years ofthe lease, from maintaining their houses properly and still more from making desirable improvements.     Thus the system contains its; owncontradictions oRe-development ;7.     Another advantage of the leasehold system is that it helps re-development to proceed in an orderly fashion, as leases tend to fallin at the same time.    Our previous thinking on this subject has alwaysassumed that the good ground landlord who wished to re-develop atthe right time should be free to do so.     But he cannot in any case getpossession till the lease expires, and will not know whether he wants,or will even be able, to re-develop until shortly before this.     There-fore, if the landlord&apos;s right to re-develop is to be protected, the lessee cannot be given compulsory rights of his own until the last fewyears of the lease.     It is however clear that many lessees wantcompulsory rights when their lease has still 20 or 30 years to run,because it is at this stage that leases become difficult to sell.Moreover, as the expiry date draws near, the value of the leasediminishes rapidly and the value of the reversion correspondinglyincreases.     Consequently, the longer the lessee has to wait for hisrights to become effective, the more he will have to pay for them ifthe financial basis of his rights is to be market value.The 1954 Act8.     All the suggestions so far put forward have been designed to enlarge the leaseholder^ stake in his house.     We have hithertoassumed that any action on these lines must safeguard the integrity of the leasehold system and the landlord&apos;s right to re-develop if he wishes when the lease expires;  but any  solution which goes so far to protect landlords will correspondigly fail to appeal to lease?holders.9. This conflict of interest is seen in our previous attempt todeal with the problem - the Landlord and Tenant Act, 1954. Thisprovides that when a long lease expires the lessee is entitled to stay-2-SECKET
on at a rack rent with the protection of the Rent Acts (the rent is thecurrent value unless the house is within the present rateable valuelimits for rent control, in which case the rent must not exceed twice the gross value of the house, by analogy with the current rent limit for controlled houses).    The landlord can, however, evict the lesseeeither on the grounds already allowed under the Rent Acts or if he wishes to re-develop.10.    The Act therefore (in most cases) protects the lesseeagainst the threat af losing his home;  but it makes him pay a rackrent for the house which he thought he had already bought.     It doesnot give him a saleable asset, and it does not come into operation till the leasers about to expire.    It has completely failed to meet thegrievances of lease-holders.     The most that can be said for it is thatit has done something to strengthen their bargaining position.Compulsory Extension of Leases11.     A scheme for compulsory extension of leases, unlike the1954 Act, would give the lessee an assignable legal interest and preserve his status.    My predecessor thought that this was something which lessees would value a great deal more than a statutory tenancyand that a scheme for compulsory extension would be welcome on this ground alone.    Since the new terms would be arbitrable the lesseecould also have the consolation of being able to test whether theterms offered were fair.     But he accepted that the lessee mustpay market value for his rights and that the landlord&apos;s right to re-develop must be preserved.    In these respects his proposals wentjust as far to protect landlords as the 1954 Act, and to this extent they would still fail to meet the leaseholders&apos; current grievances.It seems to me questionable whether a right to secure extensions of leases would in the event prove appreciably more acceptable to lease-holders than the 1954 Act has been.12.     The third alternative is leasehold enfranchisement.     This,on confiscatory terms, is the only thing that will fully satisfy thepresent agitation.     But that, as I imagine all my colleagues will agree,would be unthinkable.     It would be an abandonment of principle, andirreconcilable with the treatment of decontrolled tenants under the rent Act.13.     Enfranchisement on market value terms would avoid injusticeand would be welcome to some leaseholders provided that the right could beexercised well before expiry ofthe^ease.  it would however be damaging to landlords who want to maintain their estates.    It would lead to break up of leasehold estates generally (some of them models ofgood management) and would preclude any prospect of orderly re-development, except through the intervention of local authorities.Against these arguments has to be set the fact that many landlordsare willing to sell reversions voluntarily, and only a minority seemto be seriously interested in re-development.
14.    We cannot, in short, give leaseholders any rights they willthink worth having and at the same time safeguard the existing rightsof ground landlords and the value of the leasehold system.     If we want to give any satisfaction to leaseholders, the question is whetherit is worth our while to offer them anything short of enfranchisement.If we continue to accept that a right to enfranchisement is undesirable,we ought to consider whether there is anything to be gained in goingfurther than we have already gone in the 1954 Act.    At this point Iwould remind my colleagues that legislative interference in therelations between landlord and tenant usually encourages both partiesto stand resolutely on their statutory rights.    At present many lease-holders get good terms from their landlords for purchase of thereversion or extension of their leases.    Only a small number oflandlords drive really hard bargains;  though these unfortunately include a big landlord in South Wales,     Legislation might well leave mostleaseholders worse, rather than better, off,compulsory Surrender15,    In paragraph 10 of his paper, my predecessor suggested thepossibility of giving lessees a right to surrender compulsorily a term with, say, less than 20 years to run.    I have been considering this suggestion and have come to the conclusion that it cannot bemade conditional on proof that the lease is unsaleable.     I think theright would have to be made unconditional except perhaps for a qualifying period of residence.     This solution is different in kindfrom the others discussed above.     Lessees would probably often be disappointed to find how little the remaining term was worth onsurrender:   but a right to surrender would help those who find real difficulty in disposing of a short term because a prospectivepurchaser cannot raise a mortgage on it.    It would not be unfair tolandlords, and would not damage the leasehold system.    Equallyit would not meet most of the grievances which leaseholders feelabout the system.Conclusions16.    In my view we ought not to contemplate enfranchisement on any terms.    It would mean the piecemeal destruction of the leaseholdsystem;  and, in spite of difficulties in the system, I think this wouldbe wrong.    It would not satisfy the leaseholders unless given interms which would be unjust to the landlords.17.    I am attracted by the idea of compulsory surrender of leaseswith short periods left to run.    It would do no harm and could helpsome people who are in real difficulty.18.     This alone would of course do little or nothing to remove the causes of the present unrest.     The question is whether we should seek to go further.    If we rule out enfranchisement, compulsoryrenewal is the only alternative open to us.    I have thought about this carefully, and have come to the conclusion that I ought to advisemy colleagues against it.    We shall undoubtedly be exceedingly
unpopular in some areas, notably in South Wales, if compulsory-surrender is all we are prepared to offer.    But on the other hand,compulsory renewal on the sort of terms which we could considerwould not go any distance to meet the wishes of those agitating for reform.     If we are not prepared to concede the substance of theleaseholders1 demands, that is, enfranchisement or renewal on special terms, I see no point and no advantage in offering them whatthey are bound to regard as the shadow,    Any form of compulsoryrenewal would be difficult to work and could hardly fail to threaten the integrity of the leasehold system and its contribution to good estate management.    Furthermore, we must recognise that to rescue ahandful of lessees from the implication of their bargain in a freemarket will inevitably lead to demands for us to cushion the impact of the market on short-term tenants   - wage earning and middleincome - in the great criies, where  he crunch of a market freed fromrent control is far more serious than the leasehold position inSouth Wales-.19.    If my colleagues agree with this view, I suggest that weshould produce a White Paper, setting out fcae facts about the lease-hold system, examining the pros and cons of the possible court.os and giving the Governments conclusions.    I would propose to ask for the rejection of Mr. HowelPs Bill on a promise that this will be done,K. J.Ministry of Housing and LocalGovernment, S. W.l.23rd November, 1962.-5-SEGRET


</content>
</cab>
