<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/111/0 images: 320-324</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
cabinet public expenditure memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Chief Secretaryto the Treasury and Paymaster GeneralThe Cabinet considered the 1963-64 Forecast Estimates on 1st August, and asked for a report in the light of the prospective development of the economy(C.C. (62) 52nd Conclusions, &quot;Minute 5).2. The Estimates now submitted by Departments total  6,177 million  100 million more than we expected in July. This is an increase of  570 million,or more than 10 per cent., over the Estimates for 1962-63 (see Annex A). Thiswould be the biggest increase in recent years (see Annex B). Nor is this the wholestory. There are further pay increases to come; and although the national insurance increases will not be decided in time for the Estimates, we shall haveto take account of them in the Budget.3. We are already well over double the expenditure in 1950-51, the last year of the previous Administration. The  6,177 million figure compares with 4,530 million in 1959-60-an increase of  1,650 million in four years (see annex C).4. In relation to Gross National Product (G.N.P.), expenditure is growingfast (see Annex C).Supply ExpenditurePercentage  million of G.N.P.1950-51        ...      ......... 2,705 22-51951-52        ............ 3,528 26-7 (Korea)1952-53         ...      ......... 3,670 25-81953-54         ............ 3,614 23-81959^0        ............ 4,530 21 0 (lowest point)1962-63 (estimated out-turn)       ... 5,730 22-61963-64 ............ 6,177Next year, we shall be back to the proportion of expenditure to G.N.P. of 10 yearsago.  And the trend is strongly upward.Are the 1963-64 Estimates Tolerable?5. Is this increase of 10 per cent, on Estimates tolerable? How should weexplain it next February?6. Of course we shall probably be able to justify some of this on reflationarygrounds (even though very little of the extra  570 million is in fact for thispurpose). On top of this, we have an increase of about  200 million in public investment (of which about  40 million would be included in the  570 million).Such an increase will certainly shock Conservative opinion and its effect abroadCopy No.51THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  December 1962C. (62) 20614th December, 1962
should not be overlooked. We shall have to explain how this fits the provision made (3-6 per cent, per annum in real terms in &quot; public consumption &quot;) in thereport of the National Economic Development Council.7. But the real difficulty is 1964-65. If our economic policy succeeds in1963, there will be no question of reflationary action in 1964. If expenditurecontinues to rise at this break-neck pace, we shall be faced with an utterlyintractable Budget situation in that year.The Control of expenditure. We do not press for major changes of spending policy this year although we must ask our colleagues&apos; support for the greatest possible compression of theEstimates; and we must insist that any reflationary expenditure which has beenapproved is confined to the year 1963, and rule out any proposal which would add to the 1964-65 problem.9. We can carry this year&apos;s decision only if the Cabinet adopt a definiteplan of action to contain the growth of expenditure in the future. It is not aquestion of reducing taxes; this traditional objective of our policy is far away(unless our economy is so stagnant and slowly-moving that a continuousrefiationary stimulus is required). It is a question of preventing the expendituregrowth from running away altogether, and forcing the Government into theimpossible position Of having to impose all-round higher rates of taxation, whichis unavoidable sooner or later if public expenditure continues to increase muchfaster than G.N.P.10. We must not drift into a position in which the only recourse is an&quot; economy campaign&quot; or arbitrary short-term cutting; this has never been successful, and has often been very damaging. But if we are not handlingexpenditure properly, this becomes inevitable.The &quot;Plowden&quot; Technique11. The Committee on the Control of Public Expenditure under theChairmanship of Lord Plowden recommend that the only way to get this right is to stop taking expenditure decisions piecemeal; and to take them in relation to expenditure as a whole, and to prospective resources in the years ahead. This is obviously sensible, and the Government have repeatedly endorsed it.12. We propose that the Government should start this now, and henceforthtake our chief expenditure decisions in this way. The decisions now govern theexpenditure in 1964-65, 1965-66 and later; and if we do not take the right decisionsnow it will be much too late to act when 1964-65 and 1965-66 come along.13. The proposal is that, for each of the big blocks of public expenditure, we decide for planning purposes upon an approved annual rate of expansion -different for each service according to its needs and to the importance which we attach to it. These would be fixed for three or four years ahead. The departments would plan the development of their services within these limits; if a Minister wishedto embark upon a course of policy which would involve increasing the rate of expansion beyond the approved limit, he could, of course, propose this to hiscolleagues accordingly. But we should then all look at this proposal in relation notonly to its own merits but in relation to its implications for the whole expenditure.14. We would propose that this should be done for defence, roads, education,health and welfare, police and prisons, housing, national insurance benefits; andthat rates of expansion should be set which would be broadly equivalent to those laid down by Departments (or agreed since) in the costing of current policy up to1966-67 which was carried out by officials last spring. For many other publicexpenditures (agricultural subsidies, assistance to industry, etc.) this techniquecannot be applied; here it is necessary to have qualitative policies which foster thegrowth and competitiveness of the economy.15. If rates of controlled expansion were determined on these lines, we should certainly not be keeping the growth of public expenditure in step with the prospectivegrowth of G.N.P. But we should have a reasonable prospect of keeping it withinbounds; and we see no other means of doing so.
Conclusion16.   We therefore propose the following:(a) the 1963-64 Estimates should be compressed as far as is consistent withagreed policy; &apos;rib) any reflationary expenditures should be strictly limited to the year 1963;(c) that future major expenditure decisions should be taken in relation to the prospective course of public expenditure as a whole in relation to theresources of the national economy;id) that we should submit detailed proposals for the establishment accordinglyof approved rates of expansion for the main services, on the lines of paragraphs 13 and 14.R. M.J. A. B.-C.13th December, 1962.Annex a comparison OF ESTIMATES, 1963-64 WITH BUDGET ESTIMATES,1962-631962-63	Budget	1963-64	Change		Percentage	Estimates	Estimates				  million	  million	  million		Defence Budget       ............	1,721	1,849	4-128		7-4Defence (Purchasing (Repayment) Services)	28	65	4-	37	132-1Commonwealth and Foreign       ......	143	166	-f	23	161Roads ..................	152	172	4-	20	13-2Transport Subsidies............	146	147	4-	1	0-7Atomic Energy        ............	68	69	4-	1	1-5Board  of Trade  (Promotion  of  Local					Employment)       ............	41	25	-	16	-39-0Agriculture (Guarantees and Subsidies)	333	374	H-	41	12-ministry of Aviation (Civil)	36	53	4-	17	47-2General and Rate-deficiency Grants	715	805	4-	90	12-6Education (Departments and Universities					and Colleges)       .........	213	265	4-	52	24-national Health Service    .........	661	715	1 &quot;T	54	8-housing Subsidies   ............	91	96	4-	5	5-5Police and Prisons   .............	97	110	4-	13	13-4Benefits and Assistance*    .........	627	675	4-	48	7-7Civil Superannuation        .........	38	44	4-	6	15-8Broadcasting............      ...	48	53	4-	5	10-4Others...............	453	494	4-	41	91	5,611	6,177	4-566		10-1* Does not take into account forthcoming national insurance legislation.
Annex BTOTAL BUDGET ESTIMATES (EXCLUDING POST OFFICE)Year	Budget Estimates (as shown in Financial Statements)   million	Percentage change on previous year1950-51  ...     ...	2,917	4 5-2(a)1951-52  .......	3,613	423-8(6)1952-53........	3,601	- 0-21953-54  ...      ...	3,586	- 0-51954-55  ...	3,856	4- 7-51955-5$  ........	3,859	-f 0-21956-57   ......	3,960	4- 2-61957-58  ...	4,070	4 2-81958-59......	4,259	4- 4-61959-60  ...	4,490	+ 5-51960-61   ......	4,907	4 7-2(c)1961-62  .......	5,187	4- 5-71962-63   ......	5,611	4- 8-21963-64.......	6,177 (provisional)	4-10-1(a) In 1950-51 Estimates exceeded out-turn by over  200 million. If the original Estimateshad been more tightly drawn, the percentage change might well have been a small negative figure.(b) Increase principally caused by Korean war rearmament and stock-piling.(c) Adjusted to take account of the transfer to Votes of the subsidy to the British transport commission.Annex CTOTAL SUPPLY EXPENDITURE (EXCLUDING POST OFFICE)Percentage of  million G.N.P.Out-turn for Year: 1950-51 ...... 2,705 22-51951-52 ...      ... 3,528 26-71952-53 ...... 3,670 25-81953-54 ...... 3,614 23-81954-55 ...... 3,665 22-71955-56 ...... 3,747 21-81956-57 ...... 4,046 21-71957-58 ...... 4,157 21-11958-59 ...... 4,302 21-21959-60 ...      ... 4,530 21 01960-61 ...... 4,986 21-91961-62 ...      ... 5,368 22.-.SEstimated Out-turn: 1962-63 ...... 5,730* 22-6Forecast Estimates:  1963-64 ...... 6,177 23-8* Budget Estimates:  5,611 million.


</content>
</cab>
