<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/1/0 images: 88-93</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   August 1945.SECRET. . Copy No.CP. (45) 115.15th August, 1945.CABINET.NEW ZEALAND.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.MY colleagues may be interested to read the annexed extract from a despatchreceived from the retiring United Kingdom High Commissioner in New Zealand.A.Dominions Offoce, Whitehall, S.W.1,15th August, 1945.ANNEX.My Lord, Wellington, N.Z., 20th July, 1945.TO-DAY I lay down office as High Commissioner for the United kingdom in New Zealand after a term of nearly six and a half years, the most eventful inthe story of the British Empire .... On laying down office it is perhaps fittingthat I should offer some general observations on the present position and futureoutlook of the Dominion, although any general appreciation of the positionformed while the war in the Pacific is still continuing may require modificationlater.2. The first thing that must strike any observer of New Zealand to-day is thegeneral prosperity of the country. Poverty, as we understand it, has been almost completely eliminated. The people are well dressed; despite the recent tighteningup of the rationing of meat and butter, food is still plentiful; the hotels and places of amusement are crowded; the shops comparatively full of goods; there appears abundant money to spend; and there is a general air of prosperity every-where. Were it not for such outward signs as labour shortage, petrol rationing,the continuance of certain security measures and evidences of military activitysuch as the appearance of uniforms in the streets and these evidences of courseare much less noticeable now that the United States troops have departed itwould be difficult to realise that New Zealand is at war. And even if we probedeeper, we find that, as compared with conditions before the war, New Zealandersare called upon for real sacrifice only in such matters as the restriction which isstill maintained on the freedom of the individual to change his employment,the very acute housing shortage, overcrowded transport and the inadequacy ofthe supply of coal and power. With the celebration of victory in Europe, theaverage New Zealander feels that the interest has died out of the war, and whileMinisters and newspapers continue to urge the full maintenance of the war effortuntil victory over Japan is achieved, there can be little doubt that the thoughts of the people at large are now returning to peace-time interests. The NewZealand people still seem more European than Pacific-minded, although I thinkthat this is more true of the older than the younger generation.3. On the political side, the weakness of the Dominion continues to be thebitter state of feeling between parties, and the mutual mistrust amounting to-antagonism between employers and trade unions, which give the outsider theimpression of a lack of unity in the country as a whole. These divisions are themore surprising in that the programmes of the two parties reveal no fundamentaldifferences of principle (see following paragraph) and that social conditions in[30364]
the Dominion generally seem remarkably uniform. After Dunkirk and the fall of France there was for a time a much greater sense of unity, reflected in theformation of the War Cabinet in which both parties are represented. TheJapanese attack on Pearl Harbour and Malaya, which left New Zealand herself in direct peril, also had a unifying effect, but with the feeling of immediate dangerremoved, there has been a recrudescence of bitter party strife. What effect thereturn of -the ex-servicemen will have on the politics of the Dominion it is stillimpossible to say.4. As regards the future of political parties in the Dominion, it is difficultto hazard any forecast. The Labour Government has now been in power for tenyears; the present Ministers, the majority of whom have held office during thewhole of that period, are growing old and tired, and there are no signs of anycapable young men in the party who might take their places. At the last generalelection there seemed some swing of the pendulum in favour of the Opposition.But the Opposition is still very weak in organising and debating ability (though some of the new members elected at the last election show promise) and theNational Party programme is little different from1 that of the Labour Party. Acall to &quot; blood and sweat and tears-&quot; is not a popular appeal in New zealand and the only programme which is thought to have any chance of success is onepromising further measures of State assistance.5. What, however, causes me the greatest anxiety regarding the future ofthis country is the economic and financial position. The prosperity ofNew Zealand and her standard of living are entirely dependent on her exportof primary produce, the only volume market for which is Great Britain. the critical financial position in which,New Zealand found herself just before thewar is well known to you. On the surface, the position to-day is considerablybetter. The state of the sterling funds in London looks at first sight remarkablygood, but in my opinion and in that of many competent observers, the presentamount of those funds, far from being sufficient for the Dominions needs, willShe entirely inadequate to provide her with the capital machinery and consumableI good of which she will stand in need after the war. The strain on sterling fundswill be still further increased if, as appears likely, the New Zealand Governmentcontinue their present policy of encouraging the establishment of looal manu-factures, all of which require some measure of equipment from overseas. Thecontinuance of some form of import control will clearly be necessary if financialdisaster is to be avoided.6. The continuance of some, form of import control will inevitably lead tosome complaints from British manufacturers that New Zealand&apos;s availablesterling balances are allocated by the New Zealand Government for the purchaseof those goods which the Dominion Government deem it essential that NewZealand should import rather than those which the British manufacturer has sold in the past or wishes to sell in the future. Some dissatisfaction on this scoreseems inevitable, but in the main we have no real ground for complaint inprinciple so long, as the total amount of &quot;imports from the United Kingdomremains as large as the state of sterling funds permits. As to this, I would refer to the public assurances given by Mr. Nash .... which he has frequentlyrepeated to me in private. Despite these assurances, we have had recently the unfortunate experience of the placing of a large proportion of the Maraetaicontract in the United States and Canada. In defence of his action in this case,Mr. Nash would argue that the whole order would have been placed in theUnited Kingdom had prices been quoted &quot; fairly approximate to those quotedelsewhere.&quot; The moral for the British manufacturer is that his prices must be suffiently low to afford the New Zealand Government no ground for placing orders outside the United Kingdom. I have not, of course, lost any opportunityto point out to New Zealand Ministers that if New Zealand orders continue tobe diverted to dollar countries which do not correspondingly increase theirpurchase of New Zealand goods or goods from other parts of the sterling area,the result must be that the United Kingdom will have less money with which to buy New Zealand primary produce.7. The outlook is undoubtedly difficult and will require very careful handling in the interests both of New Zealand and,the United Kingdom. Itmay be that another slump is needed to bring the facts of the situation home tothe people of New Zealand, but no friend of the Dominion would wish to see herfaced again with such a slump as led to the distress and confusion of the early30&apos;s.   I have sufficient confidence in the agricultural resources of New Zealand
and in the good sense and grit of her people to hope and believe that the Dominionwill find her way through the difficulties ahead, though it may be after a period oftrial and setback. -*8. If such a period comes, I trust that the utmost possible measure of sympathy and practical help may be given, by the United Kingdom. For reasons which it is unnecessary for me to detail here,&quot; New Zealand is likely to remain formany years to come one of Great Britain&apos;s most valuable markets. The UnitedStates is straining every nerve at present to secure for herself a much larger share of that market, and if we wish to retain it we must be prepared not onlyto sell goods at a competitive price but also to show a sympathetic insight into their problems. There are signs in many quarters here that &quot;the inter-dependence of the United Kingdom and New Zealand in trade matters is becoming more clearly appreciated, and we must clo everything in our power to encourage thatappreciation. ...9. The prestige of Great Britain in this part of the Pacific has undoubtedly been greatly increased by the victory in Europe and by the various evidencesrevealed recently of the important part which she played in bringing about thatvictory and of her achievements not only in fighting but in organisation, munitionssupply and engineering. The story of such British achievements as the floatingharbour which played so great a part in rendering possible the successful invasion of Normandy, the under-Channel oil pipeline, and the Bailey bridge, have had their effect on public opinion. As soon as peace comes again Great Britain, if she is to retain her prestige, must show that she belongs to the futui&apos;e and not tothe past, and that she is determined not to follow but to lead the world in all matters of social and economic progress, and especially in the vital matter of communications of all kinds, the speed and cheapness of which are essential tothe well-being of the Empire. There must be an end of such retrograde proposals as the use of sea transport for our mails after the war. Whatever the cost (andit may well prove that the direct cost would be more than covered by the revenueindirectly resulting) no effort must be spared in order, within the shortest possible time, to make British civil aviation as pre-eminent as her mercantilemarine has been in the past.10. If we do not make it plain by both deeds and words that Britain still leadsthe world, there is the danger that New Zealand may eventually feel in too great a degree the increasing attraction of the United States as a great and progressiveworld Power, democratic and English-speaking like New Zealand herself, with,she may feel, perhaps a greater stake in the Pacific even than the United Kingdom.The strength which that attraction may have for New Zealand was shown bythe honeymoon period which followed the first landing of United States troopsin New Zealand in the dark days of 1942. The honeymoon was soon followedby a reaction, but the reaction has now largely run its course, and in the result the Americans occupy a place closer to the hearts of the New Zealanders than before. Nor. do the United States authorities lose any effort to improve their advantage by propaganda, some of it injudicious, but much of it subtle and effective. Mr. Greenbie, the Special Assistant to the United States Minister,who has at times overshot the mark, is shortly to be withdrawn. The work of theUnited States Library of Information here, on the other hand work akin to thatwhich a British Council representative might be expected to do for us has proved of great value to the Americans. . . .11. The other competitor for New Zealand&apos;s favours is, of course, Australia.The Dominion has already gone further along the road to maturity which NewZealand will probably travel in her turn, though, we may hope, in an individualway. Australia, under the driving influence of Dr. Evatt, is now engaged ininciting her smaller sister to follow her example, and, in particular, in hasteningthe stirring consciousness of New Zealand that she is primarily a Pacific Power,albeit a small one, with interests similar to those of Australia, and onlysecondarily interested in Europe. The moral which Australia seeks to makeNew Zealand draw is that the latter-&apos;s best interests lie in close-co-operationwith her big sister Australia, and even in &quot; ganging-up &quot; to form a common front not only against the outside world, but even against the United Kingdomherself. The Canberra-Wellington &apos;&apos; Axis &apos;&apos; was originally accepted in Welling-ton because it embodied the common interests of the two British Pacific Dominionsand because it enabled two Labour Governments to give expression to their commonpolitical background.   The first of these tAvo aspects will remain, though with
the recession of the Japanese menace it may become less impelling. But even so, there are already indications that New Zealand may be reluctant to continue indefinitely signing on the dotted line presented to them by Dr. Evatt. Despiteappearances, New Zealand remains independent of Australia in outlook, andhas no intention of allowing herself to become an Australian satellite. And onceone of the two Labour Governments in the Pacific Dominions has gone, muchof the cement holding the &quot; Axis &quot; together will have gone also and we may look forward to a time when Australia and New Zealand, while still conscious ofthe extent of their common interests and anxious to give effect to that by close co-operation, will, instead of as at present seeking to &apos;&apos; gang-up &apos;&apos; in secret beforebroaching matters with the other Commonwealth countries, return to a more normal and less exclusive relationship.4fc -&amp; -y- ^ ja, m.-vf- ^I have, &amp;c.HARRY F. BATTERBEE,High Commissioner



</content>
</cab>
