<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/1/0 images: 124-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   August 1945.SECRET./Copy ;No.   tJ 6CP. (45) 123.20th August, 1945.CABINET.SYRIA AND THE LEBANON.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I should like, in order to clear the way to better relations with France, tomake a determined effort to settle the Levant problem.2. With the end of the war against Japan, it may be possible to secureFrench agreement to a simultaneous withdrawal of all French and British troops from Syria and the Lebanon. It has already been made clear that the Britishtroops will be withdrawn whenever the French troops go. There are indications that the French Government may now be prepared to agree to total withdrawal.3. The French, however, are suspicious of our intentions, and only halfbelieve our assurances to them that we have no desire to supplant them as the predominant Power in the Levant. They fear, moreover, that, however good our intentions may be, the withdrawal of all French and British troops will befollowed sooner or later by the breakdown of law and order, and probably bydisturbances endangering the Christian or other minorities; and the Frenchsuspect that, if the disturbances are on such a scale as to necessitate foreignintervention, the British troops from Palestine, being on the spot, will marchin, and then stay, so that in actual fact the British will take the place of theFrench, which French opinion would regard as intolerable. To meet this, Iwould propose to make it clear to all concerned that, if order breaks down ordisturbances take place against the minorities on a scale necessitating foreignintervention, it will be the French who will send troops to deal with the situation.The agreement of the United States Government will be required before any arrangement on these lines can be concluded, and it will obviously have to be understood that French troops cannot be sent back to the Levant, to restore orderon the initiative of the French Government alone; the Governments of the UnitedKingdom and the United States will also have to be agreed that the situationis such as to necessitate foreign intervention.4. This proviso would go some way to satisfy the sentiment prevailing in France that the protection of the Christian minorities in the Levant is anhistoric French tradition; and it would serve as an incentive to the LevantStates to maintain order and to treat their minorities decently.5. The Syrians and Lebanese must have security forces efficient enough toenable them to maintain order, and for this purpose they will require foreignadvisers. For the reasons in paragraph 3, these advisers should not be British.I therefore suggest that the Syrian and Lebanese Governments should beinformed that His Majesty&apos;s Government are unable to provide advisers andthat they would be well advised to apply to some disinterested country, e.g.,Sweden or Denmark, for assistance. (The Syrians have already applied to theUnited States Government for American officers to train their gendarmerie, butpresent indications are that the United States Government will refuse.)6. The problem of future military bases in the Levant should, I think, beleft over to be dealt with in due course by the World Organisation.7. Other questions affecting future French-Levant relations are primarilya matter for negotiation between the States and the French. I think that theSyrians and Lebanese should give assurances as regards the proper treatmentof legitimate French interests in the Levant, such as French schools, which shouldreceive treatment as favourable as that accorded to the American schools.12888   [30381]
, 8. The withdrawal of the French and British troops&quot; may well lead to alocal food crisis, as the wheat-buying and distributing organisation is at presentrun by the British military authorities. The Syrian and Lebanese governments should therefore be informed that British assistance cannot be continued afterthe withdrawal of our forces, and that they must at once put in hand arrange-ments for taking over full responsibility for this work. They should at the sametime be warned that His Majesty&apos;s Government can accept no liability (e.g., inrespect of additional imports) in the event of a breakdown in these arrangements.9. If my colleagues agree to this general programme, some points of pro-cedure will require further consideration. It is open to question whether thefirst step should be to approach the French, or whether we had better first bringthe United States Government into line. Every care, moreover, will have to betaken to avoid any understanding reached with France about the Levant being ofsuch a nature that we should be accused by the Arab world of having reached a separate agreement with France regarding the future fate of the Syrians andLebanese without having arranged for their participation in the negotiations.&apos;       . E. B.Foreign Office, 20th August, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
