<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/1/0 images: 132-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
WEEKLY RESUME(No. 312)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 16th August to0700 23rd August,1945[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War RoomSECRET . Copy No. \CP. (45) 125(Also CCS. (45) 181)23rd! August, 1945
NAVAL SITUATION.European Waters.1. On the 16th, Sperrbrecher 14 was damaged by mine and had to be towedinto Kiel.On the 17th an ammunition lighter which was being loaded at Gronlibrygge,near Oslo, also blew up. At least 28 men were killed and others injured, andthere were some British and Norwegians among the casualties.Damage was caused to the docks.Polish reports indicate that two berths for liberty ships are now available atDanzig.East Indies.2. Ships of the East Indies Fleet sailed from Ceylon to occupy Penang andother ports. The main ships taking part are H.M. Ships Nelson, Nigeria, Ceylon,Hunter, Stalker, Shah and Attacker.Pacific.3.   There have been no naval operations during the week.Japan.It was reported from Guam on the 21st that out of about 369 Japanesewarships no more than 49 were still afloat at the time of surrender, and themajority of these were damaged.Of 12 battleships only one, badly damaged, remains and of 9 large carriersonly one is afloat. Of 19 heavy cruisers only 2 badly damaged remain afloat, both at Singapore.Enemy Submarines.4. On the morning of the 17th another German submarine of 500 tonssurrendered to the Argentine authorities at Mar del Plata.Minesweeping.5. Swedish reports state that the whole of the east coast of Sweden is now considered to be free of mines.In Home Waters 43 British mines and 2 enemy mines have been destroyed.16 mines were swept off the Norwegian Coast.In the Mediterranean 267 mines were swept and 33 by the Turks in theDardanelles.The mine totals are German 19,980 and British 5,284.MILITARY SITUATION.Burma.6. Following the surrender of the Japanese Government on the 14th,Admiral Mountbatten ordered that offensive operations should be suspendedso far as was consistent with the safety of our own forces.There are still, however, no signs of the Japanese surrendering, but several large explosions were heard in the Mokpalin area on the night 15th/16th, whichsuggests that the Japanese are aware of the Emperor&apos;s order to surrender. Thisis supported by indications that the enemy has withdrawn from some of hispositions west of the Sittang River, although after surrender leaflets had been dropped on enemy positions in the Shwegyin area on the 18th the Japanesereplied with an attack on our own positions.Patrolling for observation purposes only, continues.Pacific.7. Philippines. Since the suspension of operations on the 15th, patrollingfor security and observation purposes has continued and a number of skirmisheshave taken place.On Mindanao, 130 Japanese surrendered on the 20th.[30392]
8. Borneo. Australian security patrols have been active. On Tarakan,45 Japanese surrendered on the 20th.9.   New Guinea. Active patrolling has continued.10.   Bougainville. 104 Japanese surrendered on the 19th.11.   Okinawa. Over 200 Japanese surrendered on the 20th.Manchuria and North China.12. The Russians continued their rapid advance into Manchuria whilenegotiations for the capitulation of the Kwantung Army were in progress.The cease fire was to take place on the 20th since when there has been noorganised resistance to the Russian advance. All the key points in Manchuriahave now been occupied including Ilsinking, the capital, Harbin, Mukden and port Arthur.So far the Russians have claimed the capture of 206,000 Japanese asprisoners-of-war.13. Sakhalin. On the 20th all resistance ceased on Sakhalin and theRussians began the occupation of the southern half of the island.14. Kuriles. On the 22nd, the Russians landed on the northernmost island of the Kurile group and received the surrender of the Japanese garrison.AIR SITUATION.South-East Asia.15. In the fortnight ended dusk on the 20th, Allied aircraft flew 948 sorties.In addition Dakota transport aircraft flew 2,009 sorties, carrying 3,373 menand 3,662 tons, while light transport aircraft flew 314 sorties. One Liberatoris missing.The only offensive operation reported was an attack on the 20th, by 24Thunderbolts on Japanese troops five miles north-east of Shwegyin, in SouthBurma.In addition, patrols and reconnaissances were flown and surrender leafletsdropped.China and French Indo-China.16. In the early part of the week, Allied aircraft attacked shipping off thecoast of China, sinking three coasters and several small craft and damaging a medium-sized freighter and a coaster.Japan.17. On the 14th and the night of the 14th/15th, a total of 743 SuperFortresses attacked the army arsenal at Osaka and the towns of Kumagaya andIsezaki (N.W. of Tokyo), dropping about 3,200 tons of bombs with good results.On the night of the 16th/17th, 63 Super Fortresses laid 383 tons of sea-mines offHonshu, Kyushu and Shikoku and in the approaches to the Sea of Japan. Onthe 14th, Thunderbolts flew offensive sweeps over Osaka.Liberators, Mitchells and fighter-bombers attacked enemy shipping offKyushu and Korea, sinking three medium-sized ships and five coasters.Enemy air activity was slight.Pacific.18. Allied aircraft flew patrols and reconnaissances over all areas through-out the week and dropped surrender leaflets.APPENDIX Y.Casualties to H.M. and Allied Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.Officers : 9 killed; 6 missing, 1 wounded.Ratings : 10 killed; 8 wounded.


</content>
</cab>
