<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/1/0 images: 200-207</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   August 1945.SECRET.CP. (45) 137.30th August, 1945.CABINET.FUTURE PROVISION OF OFFICERS FOR INDIAN ARMED SERVICES.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.THE Commander-in-Chief in India has submitted a memorandum, which I attach, in which he outlines his proposals for the future officering of the IndianArmed Services. These proposals are based on the premise that ultimately thecontrol of India&apos;s Armed Forces will be exercised by an autonomous indian government. They envisage the gradual and progressive replacement by Indiansof the British element in the officer cadre of the three fighting Services; thefuture maintenance of that diminishing British element in each Service bysecondment from the corresponding British Service instead of by the grant, as heretofore, of permanent commissions into the Indian Services; and the immediategrant of a limited number of permanent commissions to Indian officers who arenow holding temporary or emergency commissions.This last proposal has already been sanctioned and implemented. TheViceroy strongly supports these proposals and has pressed upon my predecessorthe need for an early decision in regard to the points still outstanding.2. We have, of course, for a long time been committed to a gradualIndianisation of the Indian Army. Before the war the Indianisation schemewas confined to twelve units, which were being gradually Indianised from the bottom upwards. This is all we were committed to apart from the generalundertaking to promote Indianisation as rapidly as circumstances permit.During the war, however, owing to the extreme shortage of officers, Indianisationhas been introduced throughout the Indian Army and Indian officers have beenposted as circumstances required and regarded as interchangeable with british officer personnel. Indian officers have successfully held the command of fightingbattalions and in one or two cases have commanded brigades and held appoint-ments up to the rank of Brigadier. Clearly, in the circumstances, a big step forward in Indianisation will be necessary after the war.3. It is clearly impossible under conditions of progressive Indianisationof the Services for His Majesty&apos;s Government to guarantee reasonable certainty of a military career to a young British officer whose preference is for service inthe Indian fighting forces unless his sheet anchor is in the comparable british service with frequent opportunities of service in the Indian Forces. (Theintention is to encourage the British officer to undertake several periods ofsecondment to Indian Army service, separated by intervals of a year or so; thiswill afford opportunity to preserve that close contact between British officers and indian other ranks which has been a great source of strength to the indian army.) In order to retain a sufficient number of the temporary officers who havebeen serving during the war as British Service Officers attached to the indian army, it is clearly advisable to put our cards on the table and let those who want to stay with the Indian Army know what the future is likely to hold for them.Moreover, the Commander-in-Chief argues that, from the point of view of professional efficiency under modern conditions, arrangements whereby officers canbe transposed between the British and the Indian Armies will be very important.4. The conditions of service governing arrangements for secondment from and reabsorption into the British Service of the British officers, a jDroportion ofwhom in the process of Indianisation would become surplus not only to the needsof the Indian Services, but also, probably in less degree, to those of the British[30340] b\Copy No.
Army, are matters which will require detailed examination by the Governmentof India and the Departments of His Majesty&apos;s Government. This will be under-taken forthwith if the broad principle proposed is approved, and it appears tome to be unnecessary to discuss them even in outline at this stage.5. From the political aspect I consider that a step of the kind outlined inparagraph 1 is desirable. There has always been unanimous feeling amongIndian politicians that the pre-war rate of progress in Indianisation was too slowand the maximum acceleration of the process consistent with military efficiencyis clearly desirable from the political angle. The continued grant to british officers of regular commissions in the Indian Army would, I feel, be regarded byIndian public opinion as a negation of our expressed intention progressively toIndianise the Army. Hence, from the political as well as the professional aspect,acceptance of the principle of secondment seems to me to be highly desirable.6. The Chiefs of Staff Committee have examined these proposals parti ea-larly with regard to the continuing efficiency of the Indian Defence Services.They consider that they are acceptable in principle subject to detailed examiha-tion by each of the Service Departments, in consultation as necessary with the india Office, and with the appropriate authorities in India.I therefore ask the Cabinet to approve the proposals in principle, leavingexamination of the details to be made subsequently, as recommended by theChiefs of Staff Committee.P.-L.India Office, 30t^ August, 1945.ANNEXURE.Proposals for the Future Officering of the Royal Indian Navy,Indian Army and Indian Air Force.Part I.1. His Majesty&apos;s Government is pledged to give India at least dominion status sooner or later, and this implies the control by an autonomous indian government of India&apos;s armed forces.2. The first concern of such a Government of India will certainly be toensure that these services shall be officered by Indians throughout as soon asmay be practicable.This assumption must therefore form the basis of all future plans for theprovision of officers for India&apos;s fighting Services.It can, however, be assumed with reasonable safety that the future Govern-ment of India is unlikely to jeopardise the efficiency of its armed forces byinsistence on too rapid a rate of &quot; Indianisation.&quot; It follows, therefore, that india is likely to require, for some time to come, the services of-British officers to hold those posts to fill which, owing to lack of experience and training, anadequate number of qualified Indian officers is not at present available.It may reasonably be assumed then that there will be a gradual and progressive process of replacement of the British element in the officer cadresof the three Services by Indians.It is not possible at the present time to foresee the rate at which replacementwill take place or to lay down hard.and fast rules to govern it, but the present proposals are based on the principle of planned replacement.The object of this paper, therefore, is to suggest how best to provide theBritish, officers required for the three Indian fighting Services during the interim period between the end of the present war and the time when the officer cadreswill be wholly manned by Indians.3. There are three main considerations which must govern the solutionof the problem Firstly, the need to maintain the general efficiency of the officer cadresat the highest possible level, not only during the interim period, but after&quot;Indianisation&quot; has been completed, so that the armed forces of India
may continue to take their full part in the defence of the commonwealth in the future as they have done in the past.Secondly, the need to convince the Indian leaders and the Indian publicof our good faith, that is of the sincerity of our intention to hand overfull control of her armed forces to the India of the future.Thirdly, the necessity for safeguarding the interests of the british officers who are willing to serve in the armed forces of&apos;India in the interim period before complete &quot; Indianisation &quot; can take place.A further important consideration is that in order to ensure that the transition from war conditions to those of peace shall be as smooth as possible,it is necessary to announce at a very early date the system to be adopted forthe future officering of the three Services and to initiate steps to provide the requisite number of regularly commissioned officers for the post-war forces.4. At present the three Services differ from each other in that, prior tothe present war, the Indian Army had a substantial cadre of regular officers,British and Indian, whereas the officer cadres of the Royal Indian Navy and indian Air Force were very small.Moreover, although the officer cadre of the Royal Indian Navy included bothBritish and Indian officers, being similar in this respect to the Indian Army,that of the Indian Air Force consisted solely of Indian officers, such british officers as were serving with it being attached to it and not of it. these differences affect the form of these proposals.It is considered essential that the general conditions of service for all three services shall be as nearly as possible identical in order to prevent competition and jealousy in the future.Part II.5. Of the three Services, the Indian Army is still by far the largest, andthe problem of providing officers for it in future is the most important, in viewof the large number involved.It will be convenient, therefore, to consider the problem from the Armyview-point in the first instance and then to examine it in respect of the navy and the Air Force.6. As already explained, the present officer cadre of the Indian Armyincludes British and Indian officers, the vast majority of whom are at present emergency commissioned officers.The regular cadre included, however, a number of Indian officers, the mostsenior of whom have now reached the status of lieutenant-colonels commandingunits while some will almost certainly attain to the position of brigade commander in the near future. The number of Indian regular officers is, however, smalland will require to be considerably augmented by the grant of regularcommissions to Indians now serving as emergency commissioned officers if a properly balanced cadre of Indian officers is to be produced.Up to the outbreak of the present war the British regular officer of the indian army, with comparatively few exceptions, has made the Indian Army his life&apos;scareer, joining it at a very early age on completion of his first year of service afterleaving Sandhurst, and remaining with it until he retired. At regular intervalsduring this service, usually after a period of three or four years,he would take long leave or furlough of from six to eight months&apos;duration in the United Kingdom or one of the other Dominions. this long-continued residence in India, with no experience of service in the UnitedKingdom, tended to make the Indian Army officer parochial in his outlook andbehind the times generally in his knowledge of his profession. Moreover, therecurring long periods of furlough, desirable as they were from the point of viewof health, were not in accordance with the strenuous tempo of modern armytraining and life, generally. Shorter and more frequent periods of leave out ofIndia were generally precluded because of the expense they would involve to theofficer.It cannot however be denied that the building up of the vast Indian Army ofto-day from the very small foundations was no mean achievement on the part ofthe relatively minute cadre of regular officers (3,052) in existence in 1939.There is little doubt that with the enormous advances made in militarytechnique during the war and the growing complication of military operationsgenerally, it will be essential in the future for officers of all the forces of theCommonwealth to keep fully abreast of progress and to associate with each otheras closely and as often as possible.[30340] b 2
This requirement is likely to increase in importance rather than decrease.To-day and for some time to come, it is thought that the United Kingdommust remain the fountain-head of military thought and development within theCommonwealth, and that all Dominion forces must be linked with it as closely asconditions of service and communications will allow.On these grounds alone, therefore, it is highly desirable that the future indian army shall in the immediate post-war years be enabled by a frequent turn-over ofthe British element of its officer cadre to keep abreast of modern militarytechnique.. 7. The perpetuation of the present system of the permanent posting ofBritish officers to the Indian Army for the whole of their professional careers mustappear to the Indian public as a negation of the declared policy of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment that India shall assume control of her own affairs at no very distantdate.The acceptance of the principle that Indians armed forces shall be eventuallycompletely officered by Indians demands that any future system for the provisionof the necessary British element in the officer cadre during the interim periodmust allow for the progressive and continuous increase in the Indian officerelement with a.corresponding decrease in the British element.Unless great hardship is to be caused to the British officer element, by their being forced to retire prematurely and so give up what they intended to make their life&apos;s career, some system of attachment of regular officers of the british army appears to be the only feasible solution. The secondment of British officers from the British Army should not only satisfy Indian public opinion as to thegenuineness of our declared intentions towards India but also safeguard theinterests of the individual British officer.As has been pointed out, it is most necessary that the armed forces of indian future shall have every opportunity of keeping abreast of developments in military science and equipment. It is therefore important that the association between them and the armed forces of the United Kingdom should be close.For these reasons it is considered that in future the British officers required,for service with the Indian Army should be provided by a system of secondmentfrom the British Army, and that the system of permanent appointment of british officers to the Indian Army should cease.8. Similarly to the Army, the Royal Indian Navy and the Indian Air force are, it is considered, likely for some time to come to need the assistance of British-officers until Indian officers can be obtained and trained in sufficient numbers totake their place, particularly in view of the likelihood of the progressive futureexpansion of these two Services.The arguments and considerations regarding the method of provision ofthese officers for the Navy and the Air Force are similar to those which have been set out in respect of the Army and need not therefore be repeated here. Theimportance of similar conditions of service for the British officers of all three services has already been stressed.Part III.9. The detailed conditions of service under which officers should be secondedfrom the British to the Indian Services will be the subject of separate correspon-dence after the principle of secondment has been settled, but it is desirable in this paper to enunciate the conditions broadly. It is considered that they should be asfollows : (a) a seconded British officer should remain on the British pay code anddraw Royal Warrant rates of pay plus a colonial allowance for India,plus an &quot; India Service pay,&quot; corresponding to the present indian army Allowance, for serving with Indian forces. When serving out-side India with Indian forces he would draw the colonial allowance of the locality plus his Indian Service Pay;(b) the period of secondment of a British Service officer with the indian forces should be not less than three or more than four years, and between periods of secondment he should be required to serve for an appreciable period (at least a year) in the United Kingdom in orderto bring himself up to date in his profession.(Note. An officer would not take long leave or furlough out ofIndia during his period of secondment, though he may be allowed to
accumulate leave to be taken at the end of a period of secondmentprovided this leave does not count against his period of service in theUnited Kingdom.)(c) so far as is possible a seconded British officer should be encouraged toserve for a second and further periods of attachment to the indian forces after completion of his first tour of service with them andshould earn an Indian element of pension after his second and subse-quent periods of secondment.(d) a seconded British officer should, on joining an Indian unit or corps, take his place on the roll of officers in accordance with his seniority in hisown rank, and British officers so seconded must, whatever their rank,be prepared to serve under Indian officers.(e) there should be no real grounds on which the Indian officers of the indian forces can complain of racial discrimination, so that the chances of full co-operation and comradeship between British and Indian officersserving side by side may not be jeopardised.(/) the Indian regulations for the grant of staff and command pay and forthe various allowances admissible to an officer should be assimilated as closely as possible with those obtaining in the United Kingdom for both Indian and British officers of the Indian Forces.Part IV.10. As a first step towards providing the anticipated requirements inofficers for the post-war Indian Armed Forces, it is proposed to grant a limited number of permanent commissions to Indian officers in these Forces during thewar.In all three Indian Services there are many young Indian officers holdingemergency commissions who wish to continue in the service to which they belongand make it their life&apos;s career. In order to encourage them to do so and thusretain their experience and knowledge for the benefit of the Armed Forces ofIndia after the war, it is most desirable to make an early public announcement tothis effect.In pursuance of the policy suggested for adoption in this note such corn-missions, being regular and permanent, can be granted to Indian officers only andnot to British officers.It is considered, however, that an exception must be made in respect of theRoyal Indian Navy, in that it will be necessary to offer a limited number ofpermanent special commissions to those European officers of the R.I.N.R. andR.I.N.V.R. now serving with the R.I.N.The reasons for recommending this departure from the principle laid downare : (a) that there are very few officers in the Royal Navy with the requisiteknowledge of India to suit them for secondment to the R.I.N.;(b) that the existing need for experienced officers in the intermediate grades of the officer cadre of the R.I.N. is very great at the present time;(c) that the number of experienced Indian officers at present serving withthe R.I.N. is relatively very small.Any requirement in European officers subsequent to the granting of these special commissions will be met in accordance with the principles recommended in this paper for adoption in respect of the Indian Army and Indian Air Force.It is clear that the number of permanent commissions to be granted duringthe war must be such as can readily be absorbed into the post-war forces, and it isproposed, therefore, that the number of such commissions to be granted now shallbe well within the minimum anticipated post-war officer strength of each of thethree Seiwices.It is recommended accordingly that the number of permanent commissions to be granted to Indian officers during the war shall be as follows : For the Royal Indian Navy      ...       ...       ...      Up to 100For the Indian Army    ......       ...       ...      Up to 450For the Indian Air Force        .........      Up to   90These recommendations are based on most conservative estimates of the probablepost-war officer strengths of the three Services and take into account the existingstrengths in pre-war regular officers.
Of the 100 commissions it is proposed to offer in the R.I.N., 40 should be offered to Europeans for the reasons set out earlier in this paragraph.Part V.11. The approval of His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Government ofIndia is therefore requested (a) to the principle that in future and until such time as the officer cadres ofthe Royal Indian Navy, Indian Army and Indian Air Force aremanned wholly by Indians, the required number of European officers for the three Services shall be found by secondment from the corres-ponding British Services, a special and temporary exception beingmade in the case of a small number of European officers immediatelyrequired to take up permanent commissions in the R.I.N.;(6) to the grant at the earliest possible date of a limited number of permanent commisions in the three Services to Indian officers now holdingtemporary or emergency commissions in the Indian Forces.



</content>
</cab>
