<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/15/0 images: 5-5</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 41 (56) 12th June, 1956

1. Trinidad Oil Company. [Enter E.H.

H.M. Rpt. by officials.

Two decisions needed i) what we do ii) timing &amp; presentn.

In view of emotional re-action, was wise to allow a little time for reflection.

Broadly, no room for small operators in oil – particularly because no distribution outlet. This co. must therefore merge in one other of the larger units. If we decline sanction for this, we shall have to find another protector or put up the money ourselves. Have therefore seen Shell and Anglo-Iranian. Neither co. is interested. Both are surprised Texas has offered so much : suspect real reason is to give outlet esp. in U.K. for M/E. crude oil. They have no interest in any of the co.’s activities except, slightly, the Canadian end. They don’t, in particular, want any larger share of distribn. in U.K. Anyway, they wdn’t want 50% share of it with Caltex. If they wanted to go into more development in Canada, they cd. get further concessions : they have spent 90 m. there already, cpd. with 10 m. by Trinidad. Both therefore favoured allowing the deal to go through. If we veto this, we shall have to finance Trinidad Oil ourselves. If any foreign co. is to take it over, Texas wd. be most acceptable.

Complication : Shell &amp; B.P. have joint interest with Trinidad Oil in submarine exploration – shares of 1/3 each. Shell are ready to handle this issue with &amp; among the oil cos. “T.N.A.” therefore is not quite cleared up.

H. No Canadian objn. to Texas acquiring it. May be adverse comment, but Govt. won’t make trouble.

H.M. Condns. of our agreement – set out in para. 15. Shd. have to put these to Mr. Vos. a) and b) are designed to protect U.K. in interests: c) – h) are desired by Trinidad.

A.L.B. It is not in Trinidad’s interest to obstruct this. Govr. is strongly of that opinion. I am reluctantly drawn to same conclusion. Genl. weight of opinion in Island will be in favour. This on assumption tht. conditions suggested are accepted.

P.M. On balance, I share that view.

Regret, however, tht. main source of wealth of Federation shd. be controlled by U.S.

Cdn’t ask Shell or B.P. to buy this. If Imperial interests requd. we shd. have to buy it ourselves. A way of doing that wd. be to sell some of our holding in B.P.

J.S. Rejection wd. also damage long-term relations with U.S.

21

H.M. Yes : and U.S. cd. make things v. awkward in our expansion of B. interest in American industry &amp; commerce.

Ll.G. Must insist on d) and c) – to prevent Texas using only the distribn. facilities &amp; letting Trinidad decay.

P.M. I regret U.S. control of the Canadian end, which looks promising.

R.A.B. Favour assent to the sale.

Agreed : 1) Assent to sale : consider timing &amp; presentation.

E.H. Feeling in Party : less excited, but still uneasy. They need guidance. Condns. in para. 15 wd. allay anxiety. They wd. welcome a mtg before announcement made.

H.M. I must see Vos to-day and invite his comments on condns. in §15. The 6 Trinidad condns. have bn. published. Mr. Vos has told C.O. that co. wd. accept them.

Thereafter, do we announce our agreemt. subject to these condns.? If so, when? Statement must be made in H/C. It must cover all conditions. Statement Wedy will be earliest opportunity. But, to avoid immediate debate on adjournment wiser to announce Friday a.m.

[Enter A.J.

Agreed: 2.) H.M. to ascertain wtr condns. in para. 15 wd. be

accepted by Vos &amp; by Texas Oil Co.

3.) Promise to-morrow a statement this week in H/C.

4.) No mtg. with Govt. supporters before announcement

because of risk of speculation, here and in U.S.

E.H. Shall be pressed to set aside some of assets fr. this sale for Comm. development elsewhere.

P.M. Cdn’t ear-mark this particular sum. Cd. say, however, that this sale will enable us to spread even more on C. developmt.

[Exit A.J.

[Enter H.W.

2. British Transport Commission.

H.W. B.T.C. are workg. on requests put by me : hope to meet them : if so, we shall have reasonable case to put in proposed W. Paper.

H.M. Raises v. big issues. Extra-ordinary, as well as ordinary, budget. Recognise, however, tht. inefficiency is encouraged if there seems no prospect at all of getting out of the red.

R.A.B. V. diff. conception to put forth in W. Paper.

22

Much concerned about future of natn. Shd. we not consider their future. V. large issue. But believe we shall have to face it. Party is v. restive.

H.W. In transport, organn. is now about right. But will be years before we work off results of the past.

W. Paper will contain stiff decisions for action – not a mere justification for fiddling the accounts.

R.A.B. If we can do this sort of thing w’out legn., I wd. much prefer it.

I.M. Don’t yet decide to publish : only to prepare : a W. Paper. May have to be considered by Cttee. of Ministers.

H.W. Wd. welcome such a Cttee. to help me in working it out.

Agreed : small Cttee. to help M/T. with this.

M/Labour : M/Agric. : Fin. Secy : K. (Chairman)

First a plan, then a draft W. Paper.

3 Employment : Redundancy.

I.M. Uncertainty in H/C. about powers, and extent of their use.

Powers exist and are adequate.

They are little used at present – mainly because emplt. has bn. full.

Re-training : i) Govt. centres ii) In industry iii) Thro’ educational system.

Criticism will be tht. we aren’t using powers enough. Awkward moment therefore for me to close training centres on economy grounds &amp; wd. like to discuss this further with Ty.

x/ Propose to discuss with N.J.A.C.I.

P.M. Agree with x/.

H.M. In full employmt. (general or transitional) it is duty of industry to train. They cd. undertake it – cf. their efforts to poach labour. Take a firm line with industry on this.

Will review decn. to close training centres.

K Firms will pay 3(a)(ii) – an allowable expense for taxation.

D.E. Will discuss with M/L. wtr technical colleges cd. take over task of retraining normal able-bodied – leavg. Govt. training centres to handle disabled &amp; ex-Service.

[Enter Att. G.

4. Capital Punishment.

Ll.G. As in memo.

23

S.Ll. On para. 5. suspension wd. be easier qua Colonies : wd. make it easier to resist extending it to Colonies.

A.L.B. Mght be a little better from this angle.

R.A.B. We have twice advised H/C. it wd. be wiser to abolish than to suspend.

Memo. approved – subject to no action on para. 5.

Att.G. Effect of Bill on U.S. courts-martial in U.K. under Visiting Forces Act. Wish to have opportunity to consider.

I.M. Para. 7 is controversial. Under considn. by Royal commn. on Lunacy. May decision on para. 7. be reserved.

J.S. If someone else puts down para 5 amendment, it will be difficult for us to resist it.

[Exit Att.G.

5. Parliament : Remuneration of Members.

Draft reply to Opposition Leaders approved.

Date of despatch to be settled with L.P.S. &amp; Ch. Whip.

[Enter J. Harding

6. Cyprus.

P.M. V. great effort put into this by C.P. Cttee.

My present feeling: neither of these alternatives will get us a settlement. A is easier for Gks : but dangerous for us.

B. is easier for Turks.

A third possibility is to confine ourselves to a-c., and go on working at possible solution.

Still hanker after Tri-Dominium idea.

A.L.B. That mght have had a chance a year ago. But Gk. Cypriots wd. not now accept statement of Br. sovereignty.

Of all the alternatives I prefer B. because decision it remits to outsiders is a v. limited one.

P.M. Gratitude to Govr. for selfless discharge of invidious task.

J.H. I look at these fr. angle of impact in Cyprus.

i) w’out such promises as A contains, we can’t hope to secure

their co-opn.

ii) anyconstitn. will be exploited to secure early Enosis : this

alternative sets discn. of that aside for period of years.

Must put this &amp; self-determin. into cold storage before any

new constitution-making is begun.

24

H.A. Is it practicable in fact to lay it aside for 10/15 years.

A.L.B. Evidence tht. Gks. wd. like to get of the hook.

J.H. Cd. also tell Gks. tht., unless they accept, we will do a deal with Turks : that wd. mean that Enosis wd. be out of court for all time.

P.T. Is Tri-Dominium – independent Cyprus – unattainable?

J.H. Wd. attract no support in Cyprus.

H. Why bring NATO into B? Is it a mere facade?

P.M. Decides on strategic situation. Under A. decision is more free but 15 years’ later.

After 12-15 years, Cyprus will be less necessary to us.

J.S. Tory opinion won’t like referring to N.A.T.O. an essential Br. interest.

S.Ll. Under B. decision will be in NATO as a whole, not in St. Group only. Pressure for that will be impossible to resist.

Possibly Mil. Cttee. with ⅔rds majority.

J.H. a)-c) alone wd. mean tht. constitution wd. be used only as means of securing quick change of sovereignty.

D.S. You cdn’t enforce condn. tht. no discn. of Enosis shd. take place. Once you promised decn. on self-determination after 10 or 15 years, you wd. be held to that date even tho’ talk of Enosis had gone on m’while.

J.H. Cd. you hope, with no constructive policy, to face out mounting weight of public opinion, world-wide, against a policy of merely restoring law and order.

R.A.B. Party will be concerned at 10 or 15 year period. Prefer a-c, plus first sentence of (d) : no period : &amp; fluff the internatl. advice. Unrealistic to suppose you can stifle discn. of Enosis for 10 yrs or 15 cf India.

P.M. x There have bn. periods since 1902 when it was quiescent.

Fear tht., if we go too far, Turkey will be alienated.

J.H. a-c won’t suffice, unless we can reach quick agreemt. on means of getting self-determination out of public discussion. Quick Enosis is incompatible with our strategic needs.

I.M. a-d with “some” vice “ten” years?

J.H. All pressure then wd. be for 3 years or so.

25

Wd. sooner say HMG. are trying to see how s-d. cd. be applied. Peake advised v. that.

P.M. Agree it is diff. to hold world opinion w’out some constructive move.

P.T. Must we rule out Tri-Dominium for a period with a vague reference to strategic determn. later.

J.H. “M’while efforts thro’ dipl. channel to reconcile views of 3 Govts on s-d.” – a formula of that kind, added to a-c., wd. suit me better : if Peake’s objns. cd. be overcome. So long as it is clear tht. H.M.G. will try to find an answer to ques of applying principle of self-determination.

A.L.B. Believe we cd. sell B to Tories.

P.M. If it were a choice between A &amp; B., general view of Cab. is in favour of B.

S. Public opinion is greatly distrurbed.

If we took B., we cd. even put in 5 years.

R.A.B. Prefer B., tho’ I don’t want to define N.A.T.O. machinery too precisely.

H. Don’t like surrendering our decision to an outside body.

J.S. Nor do I.

H. Not earlier than 10 years.

H.M. Prefer B. f) and g) conditions préalables – are v. important. Don’t think it’s practicable to hold it to St. Group. Wd. have to be Mil. Cttee. of N.A.T.O. by ⅔rds. majority.

P.M. Shall we put B. to Turks?

W.M. Try B. without (e) and (h)?

S. Omit para (a) in any event.

Agreed : C.P. Cttee. to consider again in light of discuss.

P.M. authd. to consult Turks in confidence.

1. Trinidad Oil Company. (contd).

H.M. Avoid negotiations. State condns. to Vos &amp; Texas. Therefore, say nothing until 2 or 3 hrs. before announcement.

26

Propose therefore to see Voss at noon Wedy. &amp; make statement that p.m.

P.M. Awkward day – Albert Hall Mtg.

H.M. Can I hold it until Thursday? Will consider. And wait if I can.

</content>
</cab>
