<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/15/0 images: 24-24</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 61 (56) 23rd August, 1956

1. Suez Canal.

S.Ll. 18 countries now likely to adhere.

Trying to persuade Scandinavians not to suggest unanimous concn.

May, however, be desire for unanimous communiqué.

Subsequent procedure : N.Z. will propose tht. U.S., Austr., Ethiopia, Iran Sweden with Mr. Menzies as Chairman to ascertain wtr E. will be ready to negotiate on basis of conference declaration.

Much turns on M.’s Chairmanship.

P.M. Gratitude to M. for his help.

Tried to get Dulles’ personal participn. He himself asked for M.’s Chairmanship, even tho’ he served on it himself.

M. India &amp; R. are clouding discn. by pretending tht. minority view is to be concealed. It will not.

P.M. Uneasy interview with Menon this a.m. Means of ending conference. i) communiqué : 18 actg. thereafter ii) 2 proposals be sent to E. iii) 18 to act alone, not on behalf of conference. Believe he wd. accept it i).

S.Ll. Want it on record of conference tht. the 18 favoured this procedure.

Expect to complete conference to-day.

Cttee. of 5 will then meet at once – with Dulles in person.

Hope Chairman will resist any suggn. of Cairo venue.

M. First task : ascertain wtr N. will meet us.

May Cttee. meet in Lancaster House?

P.M. Yes.

P.M. Will then be mtg. to consider action after an E. rejection?

S.Ll. Yes : to–morrow. Some of the 18 – who have power to influence action. Incldg. Norway. U.S. have agreed to meet. May be preceded by U.S./U.K./Fr. – this p.m. or early Friday.

H.M. If N. agrees to meet for elucidatn., he will ask what is meant by fair &amp; equitable treatment for E. Work done on this. E.C. 32.

Useful propaganda effect.

P.M. Mght be leaked. Copy to go to Menzies.

2. Parliament.

P.M. Diff. to decide to recall Parlt. when N.’s answer remains in doubt.

106

R.A.B. Agree. Wd. like to review this from day to day.

Agreed : E. Cttee. to decide, w’out further ref. to Cabinet.

1. Suez Canal (resumed).

S.Ll. Pilots. H.W.’s view. Pineau suggd. tht. M.’s Cttee. mght ask them to stay on.

H.W. Wd. help if some on leave wd. volunteer to go back. Morale of men on duty is dropping.

L.P. Favour giving them freedom to leave as soon as N. rejects offer.

H.M. Useful if M.’s Cttee. cd. say tht. U.K. &amp; Fr. Govts asked them to stay until end of Conference &amp; they had now, after consultg. those Govts., to ask them to stay until end of next stage.

M. In terms of foreign employees, not merely pilots.

S.Ll. On further stays, we don’t yet know U.S. attitude. But we do know tht. their prestige has now bn. deeply involved.

P.M. Gratitude to S.Ll. and M. for success of conference.

M.

Especially S.Ll.’s patient work behind scenes.

107



</content>
</cab>
