<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/15/0 images: 36-36</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 73 (56) 24th October, 1956

1. Parliament. [Enter E.H.

R.A.B. Business for next week.

Tues. &amp; Thurs. Debates on natd. industries.

Prorogation : Friday.

2. Government Expenditure : Economies. [Enter R.T.

B.H. Travelling Expenses. Made 4% requested &amp; hope to do more. But on this Sub-Head we can’t make savings.

A.L.B. Can’t do it.

D.S. Difficult to promise.

H.M. V. well : I won’t press it – for each Dpt. I will aim at 5% over-all – not a hard &amp; fast 5% for each. And do it in next round.

R.T. Para. 5. a) drafting amendments : accepted.

b) wd. wish to tell doctors in confidence – Thurs. a.m.

Agreed : 12.30.

D.S. Committed exp’re is difficult to cut.

Cd. we not look forward to see what economies cd. be made in longer run., e.g. 2 years’ time.

H.M. Ty. will take this over from Soc. Services Cttee. A new departure.

J.S. Includg. long-term future of N.H.S. Put it all on the stamp.

P.T. And look for cuts which wd. benefit engineering exports.

P.M. That is R. &amp; D.

H.M. Ratio betwn. Govt. expr’re and nat. income.

[Exit R.T.

3. Rent Restriction.

Definition of area of de-control – approved.

K. Application to Scotland. Valuation not available : pledges against increased rents because of Sorn. Hence different proposals for Scotland. Must defend diffce. on basis that conditions in Sc. are different.

162

J.S. Para 7 (3). Propose to take same figure as for Metropolis : there is precedent for tht.

There will be trouble over pensioners or widows being forced out of their homes by rising rents – with no possibility of appeal on hardship grounds. In “slice” section.

D.S. No greater in this area than in others. And whole purpose of policy is to reduce “under – occupn”. Labour Party wd. do it by direction. Is that preferred?

4. Oversea Broadcasting.

R.A.B. May Nutting &amp; P.M.G. speak to Jacob on following lines:-

B’casts to Europe. Propose cut of £1M. overall : restore part of it for services to M/E : but require B.B.C. to economise on services to Europe and S. America.

Leave B.B.C. with their existg. independence – but with F. O. adviser.

Use some part of £1M. for development of T.V. for oversea use by C.O.I.

P.T. Regret that whole cut shd. fall on services to Europe. We do need to put over Br. way of life to Europe.

H.M. General support for this approach.

D.S. Divert from defence to this – more useful.

S.Ll. Not happy at cuts : sense values (cpd with £500 M. on N.H.S.)

5. Price of Sugar.

H.A. Terminal loss of £2½ M on end of State trading in Jan. Can cover £1M of that – by handing it on. But remaining £1½ M. will have to be passed on to consumer. Involves increase in c/l. of 0.6.

H.M. Major part of increase is due to rise in freight.

Approved.

6. Agricultural Policy.

H.A. a) Varying rates. Recommend flat rate of 96% : but limit “cut in any one year to 3% proviso” to commodities other than cereals. Gives room for larger redns. in wheat prices.

b) Capital grants : differential basis. H.A. Cttee. saw diffies. : preferred flat rate of 33⅓%. Ready to start on that basis, reservg. right to come to Cab. if diffies. arise in helping small farmer on that basis.

163

H.M. Accept these conclns. Negotns. will be long – and concessions will be demanded.

7. Suez Canal.

S.Ll. Pineau agreed next move is for E. to make proposals.

Athos. Fr. have w’drawn their Amb. &amp; takg. issue to S.C. How then can we negotiate, with Fr., on genl. Suez ques. We may have to defer mtg.

P.M. But we can stand on posn. tht. 9:2 S.C. resoln. asked E. to produce proposals.

Action taken by Fr., on Athos makes it imposs. for them to use it as pretext for mil. action. They evidently don’t want latter.

S.Ll. Fr. are also in diffes. over arrest of 5 Algerian leaders – which wrecks Quai d’Orsay policy for negotns.

P.M. We shall need further mtg. with Fr. on further steps. Invite Cab. views.

Ultimatum to E. on terms mght produce (useless) affirmative answer.

S.Ll. Dilemma remains – negotiate or act. In latter event, how do we set stage &amp; what of reservists.

A.H. Hard to hold reservists w’out some internatl. incident.

Vehicles loaded have reached low condn. of efficiency.

Winter plan : reduce dependence on reservists. Release those in U.K. &amp; Germany &amp; more gradually those in M/E. Cd. be completed in about 1 month.

P.M. Cd. you say we were replacing them fr. Germany?

A.H. We wd say” : we mounted v. quickly. M’while have adjusted plans to reduce dependence on reservists. New plan to enable us to m’tain readiness over longer period. Cost : delay in mountg. landing v. opposn. – prs. 7 days.

Ships. Irresp. of trade, must unload to service vehicles. – 44 in all. Wd. prefer to hold vehicles on shore thereafter. That wd. reduce appearance of readiness. M’while L.S.T.’s wd. reduce need for merchant ships. To that extent, it wd. be re-loading.

Cd. make a case for difft. plan for long-term readiness than for emergency readiness. But wd. weaken our bargaining position.

Somethg. ought to be said to reservists by about end/week. More incidents wd. make our revision of plan more difficult.

P.M. Told Pineau I must see Mollet before end of week – for decision.

Ships : think some wd. have to be re-loaded.

164

I.M. Cd. this announcement be linked with negotiations – some “success” for us to warrant going over to long-haul approach. E.g. on submission of proposals by E., in response to summons by us.

H. Weak to appear to wait for E. to produce proposals.

D.S. Want to know i) more detail of mil plan ii) its political objective.

P.M. Objectives : destroy E. Air Force (2 days) : landing with a view to control over Canal – from D+5 onwards. Second pol. objective : to bring N.down.

B.H. Effect of mil opn. on i) M/E. ii) wider conflict.

P.M. On i) I wd. offset greater risk of N.’s success. His interferences elsewhere in M/E wd. be more diff. for us to re-act against.

B.H. But turns on quick success of mil. opns.

D.S. Must be v. quick because internatl. pressures wh. will develop. Cd. hardly bomb – and then do no more because pressures.

A.H. With large-scale I. attack when we bomb, we cd. land in a week.

H.A. Risks to B. subjects in M/E. on takg. mil. action?

S.Ll. Plans are made – w’in limits practicable.

J.S. If we phase back to winter plan before N. has submd. proposals our negotiatg. posn. will be weakened.

P.M. Fr. don’t want to launch mil. action on purely Fr. pretext – i.e. Athos.

Ll.G. Demand proposals with time-limit?

P.M. You wd. get proposals – not sufficient for our purposes.

H.M. You wd. need therefore to add somethg. unacceptable to E.

H. Cd. dues be made a brkg. point.

S.Ll. Fawzi wd. accept dues via SCUA.

Can’t see how to get clean break by ultimatum. Cd. get it after 3 or 4 days’ negotiation.

P.T. If you summoned E (sharply) to discussions, you cd. hold reservists.

H.A. Easier to act after a failure of next round of discns.

165

A.H. If you showed it was early &amp; quick, reservists cd. be held. And we mght then re-load ships – prs. in series.

H.M. Choice : do we frame our demand in such a way as to get a refusal

a) (&amp; act) or a humiliation for N. – so as to secure our 2nd. objective. or do we go merely for a satisfy. settlement of Canal, leaving

b) N. in posn. – with knowledge tht. we are unlikely to get a better opportunity to unseat him.

D.S. If we want N. to reject our demands, may be better to reduce our mil. preparedness – apparently.

L.P.S. Even tho’ we go for b., we must keep up our strength. M/E. will remain a threat.

Agreed : resume discussion later.

</content>
</cab>
