<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/15/0 images: 57-57</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 97(56). 7th December, 1956.

1. Suez Canal. [Enter E.H., P.M.G.

R.A.B. Excellent division – congratns. to Whips.

S.Ll. Attempts to restore situation.

i) 20 tanks for Lebanon. Charioteer – obsolete.

H.M. I Agree.

[S.Ll.] ii) Ruler of Bahrain – v. loyal – wants asylum for 5 members of his Cttee. arrested for treason. Want C.O. to find a place. He will pay.

A.L.B. St. Helena.

[S.Ll.] iii) Jordan. £800.000 instalment this month had better be paid – or we drive them at once into R. arms. Parlt. has voted for negotn. to end Treaty : but want to play this slowly – U.S. mght be ready to take over some of our obligns. Things are quietening. Prefer to re-negotiate Treaty under less unsettled condns.

A.H. C.O.S. re-appraisal of M/E. won’t be ready until after Xmas.

S.Ll. Ready to submit memo. on pros &amp; cons. political – but mil. side is needed too.

Indicns. tht. J. Govt. want to put on us the onus of breachg. Treaty. Presume they haven’t got the cash from elsewhere.

H.M. Agree we shd. not act precipitately – until our future policy is clear. Mil. value of these Treaties is small. We cdn’t hold n. tier v. R. from these bases. Wd. need to act by air – bomber bases &amp; carriers. That is only type of base wh. will be tolerated in M/E. in future – for clear they can’t be used for “colonial” purpose. Ready, however, to give them some cash fr. time to time.

S.Ll. They also ask for £¼ M developmt. loan – for road. Propose tht. this be delayed.

Agreed : F.O. &amp; M/D. to submit memo. on Jordan.

H.M. iv) Libya. Can we re-consider value of that base?

L.P. Preserve air base (?U.S.) for staging purposes?

L.P.S. Start with Jordan, but set in hand prepn. of pp. on whole ques of re-deployment in M/E.

212

Prisoners of War. [Enter 3 Serv. Ministers

A.H. 250 E. p.o.w. Proposed to hand over to Burns. But shd. we bargain them v. our contractors? (450 or so).

S.Ll. Our understandg. fr. Fawzi is tht. contractors will be released as soon as we are out.

L.P. Will be ill-received here if we surrender our bargaining card. Wd. prefer to negotiate.

H.M. Negotiate hand-over on last day.

Agreed. M/D. and F.O. to concert – for U.N. must be informed.

(Hail. Also 50 naval p.o.w. in Fr. custody.)

Casualties.

A.H. Norwegian won’t now go to inspect Pt.Said. Do we do any more?

W.M. K. needs help of lawyer in further investign. Ready to return, if desired.

L.P.S. Pity we can’t get an independent enquiry, before we leave. Wd. still prefer to have that. Cd. someone be persuaded to go with W.M.

H.A. Better if independent went alone.

S.Ll. Norwegian has returned now.

U.N. enquiry while we are there wd. be acceptable. Try to get official of U.N. to go at once.

R.A.B. Put our material at disposal of U.N. &amp; ask him to send someone to check it while we are still there.

S.Ll. Ask Burns to do it. Or ask H. to ask him.

P.T. Send a good lawyer at once : and rest on his report. Less risky. Consider Shawcross. Make best use of our one week.

Agreed : i) Shawcross if available. [In N. Yk.

Edwin Herbert if he isn’t. [K. to ask him.

ii) K. to consider wtr he cd. discuss his material with a

suitable officer of U.N. Force.

Air Reconnaissance.

A.H. Nos. of R. aircraft in N.E. Syria. C.A.S. wants to fly recce. to check accuracy of informn. Important to ascertain facts. Risk of detection is v. small, at 45.000 ft.

213

S.Ll. No objn. to this, need the informn.

L.P. Doubtful. No reason to suspect imminent action fr. Syria., wh. wd. justify it. Don’t want to look belligerent.

Agreed : Make the recce by air.

U.N. Force.

A.H. Gt. diffy. in providg. any admin. backing for U.N. forces. Even food is lacking. Now tht. our statement is made, U.N. are more co-operative.

Clearance of Canal.

Hail. As in memo.

All our salvage crews are Br. and most are naval crews.

A.H. They have always made difficulty about Service personnel.

Hail. Ready to put them under U.N. flag : blue ensign : civilian clothes.

A.H. Wait until Wheeler arrives. It’s up to him.

S.Ll. Agree we cdn’t allow vessels to be used w’out their crews.

Agreed : K. to arrange for Admy. salvage officers to discuss with

Wheeler.

F.O. and M/D. to follow up genl. ques of clearance.

Commonwealth Cemetery at Suez.

J.H. Egyptians have desecrated Comm. cemetery at Suez. Using it as car-park. Possible propaganda point.

L.P.S. Swiss shd. be asked to protest. [Exit P.M.G., K.

2. Germany : U.K. Forces.

A.H. Crux : para. 9.

Gruenther &amp; Monty believe tht. some redn. is eventually practicable.

Proposal here canvassed is 25% cut. 466 – 266 aircraft. Berlin Brig : 2 Divns. &amp; Amd. Brig. Group vice 4 Divn. &amp; Brigade.

Believe we mght get this accepted. If we proposed 50% cut, reaction in NATO mght damage Alliance v. seriously.

But, if we are to reduce, better do it all at once – rather than cut and come again.

214

H.M. Lucky this year : shan’t have to find more than £6 M. as cpd. with estimate of £36 M. Don’t want therefore to re-open support costs this year. But we must find means of cutting our expre. of £68 M. to £35 M. next year.

Expect heavy criticism of our def. exp’re. Can’t hope to avoid it.

How justify to U.S. 50% cut. Agree on bite at cherry. But 25% isn’t enough.

Paris Agreemt. – 4 Divns. for 50 yrs. Other countries believe in Divns. of 10,000.

A.H. But they count nos. as well as Divns.

H.M. Even so, smaller Divns. wd. honour oblign. in Paris Agreemt. If we present it as removing 2 Divns., there will be gt. trouble.

Wd. sooner say to U.S. – we must have 50% cut in cash, don’t care how it’s done, what do you say? Sound them out on that basis.

S.Ll. I wd. tell U.S. we can’t produce any money in b/p terms.

L.P. Don’t alienate U.S. over N.A.T.O. They may intend to build it up instead of U.N.

A.H. Favour arguing it on money – f. exchange money.

N.B. Agree – strategic arguments are v. phoney.

A.H. Not altogether. Increased weapon power does warrant some redn. in size of Forces.

Hail. R.N. want to w’draw Rhine &amp; Elbe squadrons – £500.000 p.a.

Agreed : H.M., S.Ll., A.H. to negotiate at N.A.T.O. in light of

this discussion.

</content>
</cab>
