<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/47/0 images: 42-48</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1971CM (70) Copy No. 23rd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Monday, 29 June, 1970,at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, mp, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,mp, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, mp,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,mp, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, m p,Secretary of State for Social services the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,q c, m p, Minister of technology the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,mp, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,mp, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Quintin Hogg, qc.Lord chancellor the Right Hon.- Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment and productivity the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,m p, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. James Prior, m p,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Michael Noble, mp,President of the Board of trade the following were also present:The Right Hon. Richard Wood, mp, The Right Hon. John Peyton, mp,Minister of Overseas Development Minister of Transport (Items 1 and 2)(Items 1 and 2)The     Right     Hon.     Christopher   The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Chataway, m p, Minister of Posts      Parliamentary Secretary, treasury and  Telecommunications  (Items  1and 2)The Right Hon. Sir Peter Rawlinson,qc, mp, Attorney-General
Secretariat:Sir Burke trend sir Robin hooper mr. P. E. thornton mr. J. CrockerContentsSubjectNorthern Ireland    .........The Queen&apos;s Speech on the Opening of ParliamentMembership of the European CommunitiesOpening Statement for 30 JuneCabinet ...     ......Committee Structure
11422b*secret. The Home Secretary said that the security situation inNorthern Ireland had deteriorated again over the week-end; andthere had been renewed outbreaks of disorder in both the belfast and Londonderry areas. In Londonderry the immediate occasionhad been the arrest of Miss Bernadette Devlin, m p, after the rejection of her appeal against a prison sentence. In Belfast the disturbances had arisen mainly in connection with the marches andprocessions traditionally carried out at this time of year by the orange Order. But there were some grounds for supposing thatthe Irish Republican Army (IRA) might also have been involved.A new and disquieting feature of the situation was the markeddecline in the morale of the Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC). Asa result the main burden of maintaining order was tending to fallincreasingly on the troops; and, if it proved impossible to enforceriot control by such means as CS gas, the Army might be compelledto use firearms. It was therefore all the more urgent that he should pay his proposed visit to Northern Ireland; and he intended to spend the following two days in the Province. He would examine with theNorthern Ireland Prime Minister, Major Chichester-Clark, and theGeneral Officer Commanding, Northern Ireland (GOC (NI)),General Freeland, the possibility of either banning further marchesand processions or diverting them to less provocative routes. Hewould also discuss with Major Chichester-Clark the possibility of thelatter&apos;s making a statement in support of the forces of law andorder, although its wording would require careful consideration inorder to avoid any implication that the maintenance of public security had now devolved exclusively on the troops.The Defence Secretary said that reinforcements consisting of six major units, a squadron of armoured cars and a brigade headquarters had been assigned to Northern Ireland. One battalionhad arrived on the previous day: three more would reach NorthernIreland on 30 June; and another two on 1 July. But, if further reinforcements were required, it would not be easy to provide them.Units might be made available from Germany; but they would nothave been trained in internal security duties. The deterioration inRUC morale had thrown a heavy burden on the troops; and,although it had hitherto been considered that a total ban on marcheswould cause the situation to become still more strained, this argumentno longer had as much validity in the light of the latest developments.The public statement by the GOC (NI) that individuals carryingfirearms were liable to be shot without warning had been intendedprimarily as a deterrent; the previous instructions to restrict theuse of force to the minimum remained in effect and the troops wouldnot resort to firearms unless they themselves had been fired at.
Nevertheless, there could now be no assurance that this would notbe necessary.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that the irish minister of External Affairs, Dr. Hillery, was visiting London andthat he would be seeing him that day.In the course of a brief discussion it was emphasised that:(a) The GOC (NI)&apos;s warning to carriers of firearms was likelyto arouse concern in Parliament and elsewhere: and it was essential,therefore, that the instructions under which the troops were operatingshould be both clear and generally known.(b) The deterioration in RUC morale gave cause for serious concern. Plans for reinforcing the RUC from police forces in GreatBritain at a rather later stage, when the circumstances were more appropriate, were under active consideration.The Cabinet Took note of the statements made by the Home Secretary,and the Defence Secretary and of the points made in discussion.The Queen&apos;sSpeech on theOpening ofParliament(previous reference:CM (70) 2ndConclusions,Minute 2)secret. The Cabinet had before them a Note by the Lord Presidentof the Council (CP (70) 3), to which was annexed a revised draft ofThe Queen&apos;s Speech on the Opening of Parliament.In discussion several drafting amendments were agreed; and thefollowing main points were made:(a) A tribute to the work of the Armed Forces in NorthernIreland should be included in paragraph 12.(b) In paragraph 20 it would be preferable to be less specificand to refer to the Governments principal aim as being animprovement in the position of the homeless and the badly housed.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet approved the revised draft of The Queen&apos;s Speech, subjectto the various drafting amendments which had been suggested andto the inclusion in the paragraph on Northern Ireland of a tribute to the work of the Armed Forces. It should be made clear to publicopinion that the proposals in The Gracious Speech represented onlythe first phase of the Governments programme for the new parliament; and any criticism that they fell short of the undertakings in the Conservative Party Manifesto for the General Election shouldbe rebutted. The Lord President should arrange the government speakers for the Debate on the Address as soon as the opposition had made clear their choice of subjects.
Membership ofthe EuropeanCommunitiesOpeningStatement for30 June(previous reference :CP (70) 2ndConclusions,Minute 4)confidential. The Cabinet considered a note by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs, to which was attached a revised draft of the Statement to be made by the Chancellor ofthe Duchy of Lancaster at the meeting in Luxembourg on 30 june to open negotiations for United Kingdom membership of theEuropean Communities (CP (70) 4).The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster said that the revisedOpening Statement was intended to strike a balance between, on theone hand, the need to demonstrate to the representatives of the member States of the European Communities our goodwill towardsthe Communities and our intention to negotiate in earnest for membership and, on the other hand, the need to avoid allowingdomestic public opinion to suppose that we were adopting an approach to the negotiations which was too enthusiastic andinsufficiently hardheaded.In the course of a brief discussion the draft Statement was generally approved, subject to certain drafting amendments to paragraphs 8, 9 and 14.The Cabinet Approved the Statement attached to CP (70) 4, subject tothe drafting amendments agreed in their discussion.confidnetial cabinet 4.   The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that the necessaryCommittee      Cabinet Committees were now being constituted on the basis of membership and terms of reference which in each case had his Cabinet (1) Invited the Home Secretary, in consultation with theSecretary of State for Defence, to suggest a revisedwording for paragraph 12 of The Speech, including a reference to the work of the Armed Forces in NorthernIreland.(2) Subject to Conclusion (1) above and to the amendmentsmade in discussion, approved the draft of The Queen&apos;sSpeech annexed to CP (70) 3;(3) Invited the Lord President to arrange the government speakers in the Debate on the Address as soon as theOpposition^ choice of subjects was known.
personal approval. Some Committees would be permanent; othersmight be dispensed with when their work was done. In all cases,however, he would seek to ensure, in the interests of the promptdespatch of business, that Committees were small and compact andthat they were not retained in being when they had completed thetask for which they were appointed. This would not, of course,derogate from the right of a Minister who was not a member of aCommittee to attend its discussions when these were of concern to his Department or, on occasion, to ask to attend a meeting ifhe judged it necessary to do so. But Ministers, who bore theresponsibility for the policies of their Departments, should make thenecessary effort to attend the meetings of Committees in person andshould not be satisfied to be represented by junior Ministers save in exceptional circumstances.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,29 June, 1970.


</content>
</cab>
