<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/47/0 images: 49-57</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cm (70)4th conclusions printed for the Cabinet.  March 1971Copy No. 2 cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 7 July, 1970,at 11 am.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, mp,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, m p,Secretary of State for Social services the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,q c, m p, Minister of technology the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, q c,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, m p, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Robert Carr, m p,Secretary of State for employment and productivity the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,m p, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, m p,Minister   of   Housing   and   local government the Right Hon. James Prior, m p.Minister   of   Agriculture,   fisheries and food the Right Hon. Michael Noble, mp,President of the Board of trade the following were also present:The Right Hon. John Peyton, mp,Minister of Transport (Item 3)The Right Hon. Francis Pym, m p,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Sir Peter Rawlinson,qc, mp, Attorney-General (Items 3and 4)Secretariat :Sir Burke trend sir Robin hooper mr. J. crocker mr. B. G. Tucker
contents subject parliamentary Affairs     ......Oversea Affairs     ...     ......Northern IrelandEuropean Economic CommunitiesMiddle EastNational Docks Dispute   ......Misuse of Drugs Bill
ParliamentaryCONFIDENTIAL1. The Cabinet were informed of the arrangements proposed for the remainder of the Debate on the Address and for the business to be taken in Parliament in the following week. They also took note of the need to initiate, before the Government entered into any public commitment, an early study of the number and nature ofthe Parliamentary Select Committees to be appointed during the new session and of the scope and timing of the legislation which mightbe required about various aspects of electoral arrangements. they agreed on the need to introduce an appropriate number of Bills inthe House of Lords; the projected legislation on Animals might be suitable for this purpose.OverseaAffairsNorthernIrelandPreviousReference:CM (70) 3rdConclusions,Minute 1SECRET2. The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary, referring to theunexpected and unannounced visit to Northern Ireland on theprevious day by the Irish Minister of External Affairs, Dr. Hillery,said that the Government of the Irish Republic had in generaladopted a responsible and constructive attitude in relation to the affairs of the Province. Dr. Hillery&apos;s action was therefore all themore surprising. In a reply to a Private Motion Question that day in the House of Commons, he proposed, while acknowledging the goodwill hitherto displayed by the Irish Republican Government, toexpress surprise and regret at the serious diplomatic discourtesyshown by Dr. Hillery in visiting Northern Ireland without consultingor informing the Government of the United Kingdom and to informthe House that he had asked Dr. Hillery, who would be in london on 8 July, to call on him that day.In discussion there was general agreement with the attitude which the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary proposed to adopt.The Government of the Irish Republic admittedly faced considerableinternal political difficulties in the light of the acquittal of the formerMinister of Agriculture and Fisheries, Mr. Blaney, on charges ofinvolvement in gun-running activities in Northern Ireland; and dr. Hillery&apos;s action might have been intended to try to relieve the resultant tension. But it was unlikely to achieve this object; and,more probably, the extremist faction would not be appeased, the moderate section of opinion would be alarmed and the final outcomemight be merely a further weakening of the position of the PrimeMinister, Mr. Lynch, and his Government. In view of the violentreaction from Protestant opinion in Northern Ireland to Dr. Hillery&apos;sill-considered visit to the Province, we could not allow the incidentto pass without comment. Nevertheless, we should avoid any action11423
EuropeanEconomicCommunitiesPreviousReference:CM (70) 3rdConclusions,Minute 3Middle east previous reference:CM (70) 2ndConclusions,Minute 3which would aggravate the existing strain and shake still more the already precarious position of Mr. Lynch, the continued existenceof whose administration was on balance in our interest.The Cabinet-(1) Took note of the statement by the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary and of the points made in discussion.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that later that day he would be seeing the Australian Deputy Prime Minister,Mr. McEwen, and the New Zealand Deputy Prime Minister,Mr. Marshall. In speaking to them about our application to join the European Economic Communities he would be guided by theviews expressed by his colleagues in discussion in the ministerial committee on the Approach to Europe on the previous day.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that there had so far been no direct response from either the Arab governments or the Government of Israel to the recent initiative by the UnitedStates Secretary of State, Mr. Rogers, to promote a settlement ofthe conflict in the Middle East. This initiative now appeared to have little prospect of success; and some other approach to the problemmight have to be devised.The Cabinet-(2) Took note of the statements by the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary.NationalDocksDisputePreviousReference:CM (70) 2ndConclusions,Minute 5SECRET3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theSecretary of State for Employment and Productivity (CP (70) 5) onthe threat of a national dock strike beginning on 14 July.The Secretary of State for Employment and Productivity saidthat a meeting of the National Joint Council of the Port transport industry had been arranged for that day, at which the port employersintended to reject the unions&apos; claim for an increase in the nationalweekly time rate from the present  11 Is. 8d., plus a  2&quot;modernisation supplement&quot;, to an inclusive  20; but they would offer to raise the minimum earnings guarantee from its present levelof  16 or  17 a week to  20, or  4 a day. If, as seemed likely, theunions refused this offer, the docks delegate conference on 9 Julywould decide whether to confirm the decision to strike or torecommend further negotiation. There had so far been no significantParliamentary or public pressure for the Government to intervene;but, if Thursday^ conference showed that negotiations had broken
down and confirmed the strike threat, he proposed that his department should call in the two sides for exploratory discussions.He would make it clear, however, that the Government would not press the port employers to go beyond such concessions as they themselves might wish to offer, in order to reduce the risk that theymight be tempted to concede an inflationary settlement and then to seek to attribute the responsibility to the Government. So far theemployers had maintained that their offer was sufficiently generousto enlist public opinion on their side and that they had every intentionof standing on this offer. The approach of the summer holidays andthe expense to the trade union of strike pay were additional factors which might persuade the Transport and General Workers union to try to settle the dispute without a strike and, if a strike occurred,might help to prevent it from extending to union members in, forexample, road transport. At a meeting of the Ministerial Committeeon Economic Policy (EPC) on the previous day there had been general agreement that a national dock strike, serious though it wouldbe, would be preferable to the series of unofficial strikes with separatesettlements at individual ports which might occur if employersconceded an inflationary pay increase in the present dispute and thatthe Government should do nothing to press the employers to make concessions against their own judgment.The Home Secretary said that the Ministerial Committee on emergencies had reviewed the plans for dealing with a national dockstrike. Troops would be needed to work in the docks for bothloading and unloading cargoes; and the Committee had authorised the Ministry of Defence to consult Commands about the availability of the men who would be required. The Committee also consideredthat it would be necessary to proclaim a State of Emergency andto issue a full set of Emergency Regulations as soon as a dock strikewas certain. Preparations had been made accordingly; but thedecision when to announce the Proclamation and the regulations should preferably be deferred until the latest possible juncture. TheRegulations would need to be confirmed by Parliament within seven days; and, if they were required for more than one calendar month,it would be necessary to recall Parliament.In discussion, there was general agreement with the proposalsendorsed by EPC and the Emergencies Committee. The following main points were made-(a) The Governmenfs determination not to be influenced bythe threat of industrial action needed to be brought home to theunions and workers as well as to the employers. It was important to encourage a new and more restrained climate of expectation inrelation to the pursuit of wage claims through industrial action.
(b) A national dock strike, once started, might persist for,perhaps, six to eight weeks. The assignment of troops to work in the docks for so long a period would impose a heavy burden on theServices, having regard to their other commitments, especiallyNorthern Ireland; and it might therefore be desirable to consider theuse of volunteers or reserve forces.(c) In view of the special guaranteed minimum pay privilegesenjoyed by the dockers, the rapid increase in their earnings in recentyears and the approach of the summer holidays, the use of troopsin the docks seemed unlikely to provoke sympathetic action by other workers, e.g. a refusal by lorry drivers to handle goods unloadedby troops.(d) Although the balance of payments was currently healthy, a prolonged dock strike could have adverse effects on the economy,since it was likely to reduce exports more than imports.(e) Under current arrangements men on strike might qualify for income tax refunds under the Pay As You Earn system; and these would become substantial in the latter part of a financial year.Strikers could also have the first  4 a week of strike pay disregardedin the assessment of claims for supplementary benefit. It would bedesirable to review these tax and benefit arrangements, together withOther entitlements which could be abused by individuals on strike.The necessary work was already in hand; but it would be unwise to make an abrupt change in current arrangements during the courseof a major strike.(/) During previous dock strikes special offices had been opened in the docks to facilitate the payment of State benefits to strikers.Consideration should be given to the possibility of dispensing withsuch arrangements on the present occasion.(g) The public presentation of the Governmenfs attitudetowards the strike would be of critical importance in terms of the impact on public opinion both at home and abroad.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that, subjectto the points made in discussion, the Cabinet approved the proposals outlined by the Secretary of State for Employment and Productivityfor dealing with the dispute in the docks and endorsed the plansmade by the Ministerial Committee on Emergencies to prepare for anational dock strike. The Emergencies Committee should considerthe precise timing of the Proclamation and Emergency regulations as soon as a strike became certain; and troops should&apos; be availableto move into the docks as rapidly as possible thereafter.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.
CONFIDENTIALMisuse of 4.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the HomeDrugs Bill      Secretary (CP (70). 9) on the reintroduction of the Misuse of DrugsBillThe Home Secretary said that the Misuse of Drugs Bill, whichhad been introduced by the previous Administration shortly beforethe General Election, had been based on extensive priorconsultations; and its broad principles and objectives had been generally endorsed by all Parties. But several important issues raisedby the Bill required further study and discussion; and theGovernment must be seen to have given them full consideration before endorsing the solutions proposed by their predecessors. Thequestion was how best to proceed. The Government could defer the introduction of legislation until the autumn, when their reviewof the issues should be substantially complete; but this might bethought to show a lack of urgency in dealing with a problem ofincreasing public concern. In his judgment, which was supported byhis discussions with interested Members of Parliament, the better course would be to reintroduce the Bill forthwith in its present form,while making it clear that the Government reserved the right to bring forward new proposals at the Committee Stage in the light of furtherconsideration. This would make it possible to arrange the BilfsSecond Reading before the Summer Recess and would thereforeprovide a further opportunity for sounding Parliamentary opinion and helping to focus public debate on the issues involved.In discussion it was suggested that it might be thought to be wrong in principle to invite the House to give a Second Reading toa Bill which was in need of substantial amendment. When in opposition Conservative spokesmen had frequently criticised the(2) Invited the Lord President, in consultation with the Ministersmainly concerned, to give early consideration to the most effective public presentation of the Governmenfs attitudetowards the threatened national dock strike.(3) Invited the Secretary of State for Social Services to reconsider the practice whereby special offices were opened in the docks to facilitate the payment of State benefits tostrikers.(4) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Secretaryof State for Social Services to review the currentarrangements for payment of income tax refunds and supplementary benefit to strikers, with a view toeliminating their abuse.
8CONFIDENTIALintroduction of ill-prepared legislation which had had to be substantially amended in Committee; and now that they formed theGovernment they should not expose themselves to similar criticism.On the other hand it could be argued that this was to exaggerate theextent of the amendments to the Bill which were likely to be needed,and that, by reintroducing as soon as possible a measure which hadbeen widely welcomed in principle on its first introduction, theGovernment would not only save valuable Parliamentary time butalso give a clear indication of their determination to deal promptlywith a grave social problem.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that on balance the Cabinet approved the proposal put forward by the HomeSecretary. In so doing, however, they would wish to reaffirm theimportance which the Government attached to the principle of notintroducing ill-prepared legislation.The Cabinet-Agreed that the Misuse of Drugs Bill should be introducedwithout amendment, subject to the reservations proposedin paragraph 4 of CP (70) 9.Cabinet Office, S.W.I.7 July, 1970.


</content>
</cab>
