<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/47/0 images: 148-164</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. June 1971CM (70)11th Conclusions ooCopy No. 6 cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 30 July, 1970,at 3 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, mp, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,qc, mp, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Michael Noble, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph,m p, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. Robert Carr, m p,Secretary of State for employment and productivity the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,m p, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Minister   of   Housing   and   local government the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister  of  Agriculture,  fisheries and FoodMr. John Davies, m p, Minister ofTechnologyThe following were also present:The    Right    Hon.    Christopher   Mr. Maurice Macmillan, mp, ChiefChataway, mp, Minister of Posts      Secretary, treasury and Telecommunications (Item 5)The Right Hon. Francis Pym, m p,   Lord Balniel, mp, Minister of StateParliamentary Secretary, Treasury for Defence (Item 1)The Right Hon. Sir Peter Rawlinson,q c, m p, Attorney-General (Items 1-4)
Secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. J. hudson mr. B. G. tucker mr. G. F. kear miss S. W. fogarty mr. C R. CannContentsItem                                    Subject page 1     The Rundown of the British Army ...     ...... 32     Aircraft Industry   .................. 3Concorde and BAC-311 aircraft     The Second Force Airline ...     ............ 64     Financial Assistance to Harland and Wolff Ltd. ... 95     British Broadcasting Corporation      ......... 11Local Radio Stations6     The Open University      ............... 13
TheRundownof theBritish Army(previous reference :CM (70) 8thConclusions,Minute 4)secret. The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that, as arranged at their previous discussion of this subject, further examination hadbeen made of ways of modifying the proposal outlined in CP (70) 26,concerning the rundown of nine major units of the British Army,in order to overcome the disadvantages which the Cabinet&apos;s earlier discussion had revealed. It was now proposed that, instead ofbeing offered the option of completing the disbandment plan or of continuing in cadre form with an establishment of 30-50 men, the units concerned could be allowed, if they wished, to remain atcompany or squadron strength, i.e., about 120 men. Specific rolescould be filled by the sub-units so formed; and the plan was thusmilitarily viable. The net cost to the Defence Budget of theproposal, which would fully discharge the Governmenfsundertaking to review the rundown plan of the previous administration, would for the next few years not exceed 1-4 million a year. About half of this sum represented the costof retaining at company or squadron strength the nine unitsnominated for disbandment or amalgamation; the other half wasthe cost of not proceeding with the rundown of the 10th unit asproposed in paragraph 9 of the Annex to CP (70) 26. In view ofthe imminence of various postings it was intended, subject to consultation with the Defence Secretary who was at present inthe Far East, to make an official announcement of the government&apos;s decision on 4 August.In a brief discussion there was general agreement with the plan and the proposed timetable for announcing it.AircraftIndustryConcorde andBAC-311Aircraft(previous reference:CM (70) 9thConclusions,Minute 4)The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^statement.secret. The Cabinet resumed their discussion of memoranda bythe Minister of Technology (CP (70) 15), the President of the Boardof Trade (CP (70) 23), the Attorney-General and the Solicitor-General (CP (70) 17) and the Chief Secretary, Treasury (CP (70) 25),about the Concorde aircraft project. They considered also amemorandum by the Minister of Technology (CP (70) 21) about the bac-311 aircraft.The Prime Minister said that the issues raised by thesememoranda affected the whole future of the British aircraft industryand could not well be resolved in the course of the presentdiscussion, particularly since some of the Ministers most closely
concerned had been appointed only very recently and had not had time to familiarise themselves with all the Departmental aspectsof the complex problems involved. In these circumstances theCabinet&apos;s discussion would best be confined to a review of the main issues of policy which were at stake and to some consideration ofthe means by which the matter might best be pursued before theCabinet reached a final decision. It might be desirable that ministers should have before them at that stage aninterdepartmentally agreed assessment of the range of problems involved and of the implications of the various possible courses ofaction open to the Government; and, if the Cabinet endorsed thissuggestion, he would seek to make the necessary arrangements intime for a resumed Ministerial discussion early in September.In discussion of the general issues of policy arising from theproposals before the Cabinet it was suggested that developments inthe United States could directly affect our own decisions.Congressional discussions in Washington on the provision of furtherfunds for the United States supersonic transport aircraft (SST) had reached a critical stage; and, if the eventual decision were againstproceeding with the venture, this could influence the attitude of theUnited States authorities to any adaptation of civil aviationregulations which might be necessary for operation by supersonicaircraft and so affect the Concorde&apos;s sales prospects. On the otherhand the abandonment of the United States SST aircraft might conceivably open the way to some form of United States association with the Concorde project, if we ourselves eventually decided toproceed with it. Similarly, the BAC-311 project and the Rolls-Royce engine which it was to incorporate were liable to be affectedin a number of ways by the United States decisions. In particular,the future of the Rolls-Royce RB-211 engine could be jeopardisedif the civil element of the Lockheed organisation went into liquidation, as was not impossible, and the Lockheed Tri-Staraircraft, for which the current version of the engine was designed,was abandoned.For the rest there could be no prospect of economic advantage in continuing with the Concorde. But there was a clear conflict between the financial attractions of cancellation and its seriousimplications for our relations with France, particularly as regardsthe French attitude to our application to join the european economic Community. The decision on the BAC-311, and on our attitude to the A300B project, would exert an equally far-reachinginfluence on the future size and structure of the aviation industryand would have important implications for employment, for Britishtechnology and for the balance of our future foreign exchangeearnings and payments. The industry&apos;s potential capacity for saving
foreign exchange was indicated by a recent assessment that theannual aircraft procurement programmes of the two British airlineCorporations might reach  250 million by the mid-&quot;80s. On theother hand there would be no advantage in supporting a policywhose sterling costs were so great as to imply the acceptance of adollar exchange rate significantly less favourable than the presentparity.In further discussion it was emphasised that the aviationindustry had already spent some  3 million on the BAC-311 project and that the best hope of securing substantial private participation in the remaining stages, if the project were allowed to go forward,would lie in making an announcement by the time of theFarnborough Air Show. But, whatever the decisions on theproblems before the Cabinet, there could be no profit fromprolonged uncertainty; and the Government should therefore seek to reach a conclusion during September. For this purpose, however,it would be undesirable to rely only on the conventional method of presenting the issues to Cabinet, whereby the technological andpolitical advantages of proceeding with advanced projects were merely set in opposition to the economic necessities of reducingGovernment expenditure. This procedure had produced successiveunsatisfactory results in both the military and the civil fields, inthe sense that many projects had been cancelled after heavy expenditure had been incurred and, of those projects which were completed, few had prospered sufficiently to recoup the development costs. Experience of this kind suggested that a fresh effort must bemade to reconcile, or at least to minimise, conflicting Departmentalevaluations of the factors involved and to enable the implications ofsuch projects to be considered in the wider context of the most effective use of our economic resources as a whole. The proposalsnow under discussion for the establishment of some form of centralcapability unit, capable of objective analysis of complex problemssuch as those now before the Cabinet, might in due course make animportant contribution in this respect.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that it would be inexpedient to seek to reach a finaldecision on the issues before them at the present meeting. but arrangements should be made to complete, as early as possible inSeptember, an objective and agreed analysis of the possible courses of action open to the Government and of their implications. this analysis should include not only an evaluation of the variousrelevant factors adduced in the memoranda now before the Cabinetbut also an up-to-date assessment of the uncertain intentions of theUnited States authorities as regards the development of a supersonic
aircraft (including their likely effect on the prospects for Rolls-Royce), an appraisal of the effect of the various possible decisions on the future of the British airframe, aero-engine and avionicsindustries and a fuller examination of the prospects of british participation in the Franco-German A300B Airbus project as analternative to unilateral support for the BAC-311. He would consider how, in the absence of an established central organisation for examining such problems, an analysis of this kind could best beprepared, using existing Departmental resources; and all Ministerswhose Departments would need to contribute to it should impress on their staffs the importance which the Cabinet attached to it.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^ summing up of their discussion.confidential the Second 3.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum (CP (70) 33) by force Airline   trie President of the Board of Trade about the possible establishmentof a &quot; second force &quot; independent airline.The President of the Board of Trade said that the Governmentwere committed to encouraging the creation of a second forceairline. The only means by which this could be ensured in the foreseeable future was the purchase of British United Airways Ltd.(BUA) by Caledonian Airways Ltd. (Caledonian). The lattercompany, however, could only finance the purchase if they couldsatisfy their financial backers that routes would be transferred tothe new airline on a scale sufficient to yield an additional profitbefore tax of about  800,000 in 1971. This would entail the transfer from British Overseas Airways Corporation (BOAC) of routesyielding a revenue of about  5- 6 million out of total currentrevenue of  200 million. The Corporation, however, had refusedto co-operate in a voluntary transfer of routes. The Law officers had advised that certain existing statutory powers could be exercised in combination, albeit in an unprecedented manner, to secure the compulsory transfer of the routes; but this would certainly be opposed not only by the unions concerned (who had threatenedstrike action) but also by BOAC and British European Airways(BEA) and, probably, by BUA and by the official Opposition inParliament. Meanwhile, the situation of BUA was deterioratingrapidly; and the unions had threatened to strike from 3 Augustunless the airline conceded parity of pay with BOAC and BEA.There was also a risk that Caledonian and their financial backerswould withdraw unless a statement of Government policy was made
urgently. The Ministerial Committee on Economic Policy had considered on 27 July his proposal to issue a statement on the linesof that annexed to CP (70) 33. They had attached considerable importance, however, to separating the wages issue (on which theunions were on strong ground) from the political opposition to thesecond force airline and route transfers (on which the unions hada much weaker case), as well as to avoiding any risk of industrial action which might exacerbate the situation in the docks. Theyhad suggested, therefore, that it would be preferable to delay astatement for a few weeks. Since then the Chairman of Caledonian,together with a representative of his backers had once againexpressed confidence that the second force airline could be a success. The funds to purchase BUA were available; but it wouldnot be possible to maintain that position unless a statement wasmade shortly in order that negotiations with BUA could start. Thelatter faced the threat of a strike from the following Monday,which would cost them each week a sum equivalent to their latestestimated annual profits. If the strike took place, BUA would go into liquidation; and it was unlikely that Caledonian and its backerswould then be able to construct a second force airline. BUA had offered comparability of pay, although not parity; and there was areasonable chance that the strike would not take place. Even if it did not, both BUA and Caledonian were likely to withdraw fromany possible deal if there were no Government statement withinthe next week. In the circumstances it was advisable that, if therewere no pay strike, a statement on the lines of the draft annexed to CP (70) 33 should be made within the next few days. If, however,a strike occurred and BUA went into liquidation, furtherconsideration would need to be given to the situation urgently.In discussion it was suggested that, even if the dock strikeended on 3 August and no pay strike took place at BUA, it wouldbe preferable to avoid any risk of precipitating an airline strike atthe height of the August holiday season by making an early statement about the compulsory transfer of routes, especially since it was unlikely that BUA&apos;s situation would deteriorateirretrievably in the next few weeks. On the other hand, if therewere a strike against a policy which had been recommended by theCommittee of Inquiry into Civil Air Transport (The EdwardsCommittee) and had been broadly accepted by both major political parties, the odium might be expected to fall mainly on the unionsrather than on the Government. The proposed takeover of BUAby Caledonian was the only opportunity which could be foreseenfor the implementation of this important aim of the government&apos;s policy; and there was a risk that, if there were no statement in the
next few days, BUA might go into liquidation or Caledonian mightfinally withdraw from the proposed takeover. In the circumstances it would be worth facing the risk of a strike on political grounds inthe hope that a successful second force airline could be established.In further discussion the following points were made (a) Since the power to make an Order under section 3 (5) ofthe Air Corporation^ Act, 1967, was exercisable by the Board ofTrade &quot; to such extent as they think desirable in the public interest &quot;,the Courts could be expected to reject any challenge to the validity of an Order on the lines proposed. Moreover, there was areasonable prospect that, if the Government made it clear that theywere prepared to transfer routes compulsorily if necessary, BOACwould in the end co-operate.(b) It might become necessary to make it clear to BUA&apos;principal shareholders that the Government would not in any circumstances authorise BOAC to buy the airline. But this neednot be considered unless and until they rejected reasonable termsfrom Caledonian.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that, ifthere were a strike against BUA over the pay issue or if the airlinewent into liquidation in the next few days, he would arrange, inconsultation with the Secretary of State for Employment and productivity and the President of the Board of Trade, for theposition to be considered urgently. The Cabinet agreed, however,that, if both these eventualities were avoided, the President of theBoard of Trade might make a statement in the middle of thefollowing week provided that there had by then been a generalresumption of work in the docks. This statement would set out the government&apos;s policy on the lines of the annex to CP (70) 33. the text should, however, be re-drafted in order to make it clear thatthe Edwards Committee had recommended the establishment of asecond force airline and, in so doing, had recognised that a once-for-all transfer of routes would be essential to ensure its success;that the previous Government had accepted the desirability ofestablishing such a second force and had intervened to prevent theproposed takeover of BUA by BOAC on the ground that thiswould have prevented any such development; and that theGovernment had had to consider whether it was right in thenational interest to forgo the only opportunity of forming a secondforce airline which could be expected to arise in the foreseeable future.The Cabinet 1.   Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister.
FinancialAssistance toHarland andWolff Ltd.confidential. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for the Home Department and the Minister of Technology(CP (70) 32) about financial assistance to Harland and Wolff Ltd.The Home Secretary said that the Belfast company of Harlandand Wolff had requested urgent financial assistance through the shipbuilding Industry Board (SIB) to enable them to carry on business. The firm was insolvent. If they were to stay in business,they required  1^ million immediately; up to  2 million by the endof the year; and up to  4 million in 1971 with possibly further assistance beyond, which could not at present be quantified. Theycould not raise the money immediately either from the market orfrom the sale of assets. Although the immediate outlook was poorbecause contracts had been taken at fixed prices which madeinadequate allowance for inflation, there were prospects for thesale or lease of the good, modern shipbuilding facilities. The SIBhad recommended a grant of  3^ million under the shipbuilding industry Act, provided that the Government undertook to make available any further sums required to keep the company viable.The Law Officers had advised that, given the insolvency of thecompany and the terms of the Companies Acts, the Governmentwere in no position to meet only immediate needs without acceptingan obligation to meet the further requirements of the company.The alternative was liquidation. In view of the present situation inNorthern Ireland this would entail the risk of very serious politicaland economic difficulty. The company employed about 9,500people in Belfast; and the loss of even half the jobs in the yardwould increase the unemployment rate from 4-6 per cent to 6-5per cent or more, with a much higher rate for males only. In thepresent disturbed state of Northern Ireland this could have apolitically inflammatory effect and, indeed, could seriously affect the stability of the Northern Ireland Government. In the circumstances2.   Invited the President of the Board of Trade:(i) to arrange for the draft statement annexed to cp (70) 33 to be amended on the lines indicated by the Prime Minister in his summing up of thediscussion;(ii) to arrange for the amended statement to be issued in the middle of the following week if no paystrike had taken place at BUA, if the firm had notgone into liquidation and if there had been ageneral resumption of work in the docks.
he agreed with the Minister of Technology that the SIB&apos;recommendation of a grant of  3  million for Harland and Wolffshould be approved but that only  H million should be madeavailable immediately, on the understanding, however, that theGovernment accepted that the financial needs of the company asforeseen would have to be met by one means or another. TheDepartments concerned should consider how best to meet thefuture financial requirements of the company, given the limitationof SIB funds and the desirability of associating this aid as closely as possible with the Northern Ireland Government. The Ministryof Technology would also actively explore, in consultation withother interested Departments, the best means of reinforcing themanagement and improving the future financial performance ofHarland and Wolff (including the possibility of association withforeign interests) and the conditions to be attached to any further assistance from public funds.The Minister of Technology said that there were certainprospects that the shipyard might be sold to one or other of twoforeign shipowners, who would operate it with the help of management expertise from abroad. But, if immediate assistancewere not provided, it would not be possible to complete a sale intime to avoid the closure of the yard. He hoped that, if  1^ million were provided now, a further  6 million would be the limit of theGovernments future obligations even if the yard were not sold oran alternative solution found.In discussion there was general agreement that the consequences of closure of the Harland and Wolff shipyard in Belfast would bevery damaging. It might be possible, however, for the Governmentto avoid assuming onerous and expensive obligations towardsHarland and Wolffs creditors if, instead of providing assistancedirect to the existing firm, they allowed it to go into liquidation and immediately agreed to provide the liquidator with funds to keep the yard working until the assets could be sold or a new organisation(with new management) formed to take them over. Even if nosale were possible, the establishment of a new company freed fromobligations to existing creditors would be less expensive than theproposals in CP (70) 32. Moreover, in this way the management and workers at Harland and Wolff and at other shipyards whichwere in financial difficulties would realise that the Government werenot prepared to continue supporting uneconomic firms. On theother hand, liquidation of Harland and Wolff Ltd., even if the shipyard were kept working, might have adverse repercussions onthe Northern Ireland economy and on the stability of the StormontGovernment. It was suggested, however, that, even if there were no alternative to direct assistance to Harland and Wolff Ltd., this might be provided by way of loan rather than grant in the hope that
BritishBroadcastingCorporationLocal radio stations(previous reference :CM (70) 8thConclusions,Minute 7)confidential. The Lord President of the Council said that, since the cabinet&apos;s last discussion of the subject, the Ministerial Committeeon Broadcasting had given further consideration to a proposal bythe Minister of Posts and Telecommunications that the british broadcasting Corporation (BBC) should continue to operate the eight local radio stations already in service and should provide the12 further stations for which the previous Administration had givenapproval.   The first of the new stations was due to come intothe Government would secure some return in the event of anoutright sale of the yard. Whatever method of providing assistance was selected, however, it should be such as to improve the chances of attracting a competent management.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that steps should be taken to ensure that the Harlandand Wolff shipyard in Belfast was not closed down. The Ministerof Technology should consider, in consultation with the HomeSecretary, whether it would be possible, by providing a loan ratherthan a grant, to protect the Governmenfs interest in the event ofa sale of the shipyard and, indeed, whether it would be possible, by allowing Harland and Wolff Ltd. to go into liquidation, to providesupport for the continuation of the yard without assuming onerousobligations towards the firm&apos;s existing creditors. Assistance should only be provided on condition that the company complied with anyrequirements as to the strengthening of their management. any announcement should make it clear that assistance was part of the help being provided for Northern Ireland, not part of a generalpolicy of supporting uneconomic shipyards. The Cabinet would wish to give further consideration at a later date to the government&apos;s policy in relation to the shipbuilding industry generally.The Cabinet-Invited the Minister of Technology:(i) in consultation with the Home Secretary and the attorney-General, to take whatever steps might benecessary to ensure the continuation in operation ofthe Harland and Wolff shipyard in Belfast in thelight of the points made in the Prime Minister^summing up of their discussion;(ii) to arrange for further consideration to be given to the government&apos;s policy in relation to the shipbuilding industry generally.
operation on 1 September and the last in February 1971. Thecapital expenditure on these new stations amounted to  975,000,d( which  837,000 was already committed. Their cancellation would therefore yield only a very small saving in public expenditure.Moreover, an increase in the broadcasting licence fee had beenapproved by the previous Administration, and the BBC were free to spend the proceeds on their local radio programmes if theypreferred to give those programmes priority over other services.The majority of the Ministerial Committee on Broadcasting agreedthat in these circumstances not only the eight existing stations butalso the next 12 should be allowed to proceed. Thisrecommendation, however, was subject to the provisos that these stations would operate only on very high frequencies; that the frequency assignments might later be reallocated when commerciallocal stations were established; and that it should be made clear thatthere was no commitment in the longer term to the BBCs operatingany local radio stations at all and that any or all of the 20 stationsmight therefore be subsequently withdrawn from the Corporation.The BBC were displaying a general willingness to co-operate in the preparations for a commercial radio network; and it would be unfortunate if, by cancelling the stations in question, the Governmentneedlessly alienated the Corporation^ goodwill.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that cancellation shouldnot result in any significant capital loss, since commercial radiooperators would probably be interested in buying the equipment fortheir own stations. In addition, the operating costs of about 100,000 a year for each station would be saved, to the advantageof the BBCs finances. It was the Governmenfs declared policy that, if the private sector was prepared to provide a service, this was preferable to its being undertaken by a State organisation; and inthis instance the policy seemed clearly to apply.In discussion it was suggested that, as against these considerations, the BBCs capital equipment could probably not be sold at once to prospective commercial radio operations, since acommercial radio network could not come into existence until early1972 at the earliest. If, on the other hand, the BBC proceeded withtheir plans, it would be possible for them subsequently to offer to commercial radio companies any equipment surplus to therequirements of their own programme. Moreover, in terms of operating expenditure the Corporation, if debarred from providing a local radio service, would probably wish to restore their regionalbroadcasting services; and this would entail the sacrifice of anopportunity to transfer a medium frequency to the externalbroadcasting services. If, however, the BBC were allowed to implement their plans, this would not necessarily involve a
The OpenUniversity(previous reference :CM (70) 8thConclusions,Minute 6)confidential. The Cabinet considered memoranda by the Secretary ofState for Education and Science (CP (70) 34 and 35) and by theChief Secretary, Treasury (CP (70) 36), about the Open University.The Secretary of State for Education and Science said that theCabinet had asked her, in consultation with the Chief Secretary,Treasury, to examine urgently the possibility of reducing the firstintake of students to the Open University.   They had also beensubsequent increase in the broadcasting licence fee, since theCorporation would be able at that juncture to choose whether thelocal radio service or some other programme should be reduced inorder to enable them to restrain expenditure within the limits oftheir income. On the other hand it could be maintained that toallow all 20 stations to proceed would be to risk incurring a commitment in practice to the BBC in the field of local radioservices, whereas there was no evidence that local radio stationsoperated by the Corporation would be meeting any expresseddemand for additional radio services.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that, on balance, the Cabinet agreed that preparations for the next 12 BBClocal radio stations were so far advanced that their cancellation atthis late stage would be liable to provoke an adverse reactionwithout achieving any worthwhile saving in public expenditure.Approval to the maintenance of the programme for all 20 stations,however, must be subject to all the conditions proposed by the ministerial Committee on Broadcasting; and the Governmenfsplans for a commercial radio network should meanwhile be pursuedwith all possible speed.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Posts and Telecommunications:(i) To convey to the British Broadcasting corporation the Governmenfs decision on the 20 local radio stations already operating or planned, in the termsindicated in the summing up of their discussion bythe Prime Minister.(ii) To   submit   to   the   Ministerial   Committee   on broadcasting at the earliest opportunity proposalsfor creating a commercial radio system.
asked to consider the possibility of making additional reductions in expenditure on the Open University and to report the outcomeby mid-September. The Open University had been granted a RoyalCharter, which could not be revoked without the University&apos;consent; it had been voted by Parliament the money which itneeded up to April, 1971; and it was authorised from 1 August toaccept up to 25,000 students for its first year of operation. In thesecircumstances she had agreed with the Chief Secretary, Treasury,that to reduce the first year&apos;s intake to 15,000 students would secureonly a negligible saving of expenditure in 1971 and would save only 1-6 million in 1973-74 and  1-9 million in 1974-75. They had also agreed that it was impossible to identify by mid-Septemberany way of securing significant economies except by arresting theUniversity&apos;s opening. This latter course, however, would requirethe Government to announce the decision before 1 August withoutany consultation with the University itself or with the educationalworld in general. It could not fail to provoke major controversy.The Governmenfs first reduction in public expenditure would beseen to fall in the educational sector; and a potentially economicmeans of providing at a later stage a University education for school leavers might be lost. Given that the Conservative party had avoided any commitment to cancel the project and had merelyindicated before the General Election that they would reservejudgment until it was clear how the project was developing, sherecommended that the University should be allowed to maintain its first year intake of 25,000 students but that she should consult the University authorities about the rate of entry in the second andsucceeding years, about the possibility of using the University toprovide for students under 21 who might otherwise follow other,more costly courses of higher education and about the prospects ofincreasing the University&apos;s revenue in order to limit the level ofpublic financial support.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that expenditure on the open University was estimated, at constant prices, to rise to about 11 million a year by 1975; and in the event costs could well prove to be higher. If the project was cancelled a course which neednot necessarily involve revocation of the Royal Charter, since theGovernment could simply refuse to provide finance the total public expenditure on the University would be some  8 million,including compensation, of which it might be possible to recoversome  1-4 million by selling the buildings. If the Governmentwere to achieve the economies in public expenditure which they hadenvisaged, they would have to eliminate projects which were in themselves desirable and would have to be prepared to face the resultant criticism. The Government had said that in the educationalsector they would give priority to primary schooling; and they were
not committed to the Open University project. To cancel it would indicate that they were serious in their declared intention to reducepublic expenditure.In discussion it was pointed out that the plans for the OpenUniversity were now far advanced and that the University was onthe point of accepting its first students. It had attracted powerful and influential support; and its estimated cost per student, even allowing for a high wastage rate, was likely to be considerablylower than that of conventional universities. It not only offered the prospect of providing re-education for mature students but might also provide a valuable and economic means of meeting thedemands of school-leavers for University education. On the otherhand it could be argued that the Open University was onlyexperimental and would not provide a genuine university education;that it did not necessarily represent the best means of investingpublic money in higher education; and that in any event it couldnot be automatically assumed that it would be necessary to providehigher education for a larger number of school-leavers and othersas had been so far envisaged. Moreover, most of the students ofthe Open University in the first few years of its operation would beearning; and they should perhaps be expected to be able, without additional grants from local authorities, to pay more than themodest fees currently proposed.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed, on balance, that, on the understanding that expenditure on the Open University would be taken into account in future consideration of the level of public expenditure on higher education, the project should be allowed to proceed with plans totake in 25,000 students for its first year of operation. But theSecretary of State for Education and Science should consider withthe authorities of the University, the most appropriate scale for its future operations, the rate of intake in subsequent years, the need to provide for students under 21 and the prospects for increasingthe University&apos;s revenue, particularly by an increase in fees without an offsetting increase in local authority grants.The Cabinet 1. Agreed that the Open University might proceed with plans for an intake of 25,000 students in its first year of operation.2. Invited the Secretary of State for Education and Science, inconsultation with the Chief Secretary, Treasury, to give further consideration to the future scale of the Open
University&apos;s operations, the number of students which itshould accept in its second and succeeding years, theneed for the University to provide for students under 21and the prospects of increasing the University&apos;s revenueon the basis suggested in their discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,31 July, 1970.


</content>
</cab>
