<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/47/0 images: 203-215</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. June 1971CM (70)16th conclusions copy No.   2 3CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Monday, 14 September, 1970,at 10.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, m p,Secretary of State for Social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, q c,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Michael Noble, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment and productivity the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,m p, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. John Da vies, mp,Minister of technology the Right Hon. Richard Wood, mp,Minister of Overseas Development(Item 2)The Right Hon. John Peyton, mp,Minister of Transport (Item 2)Mr. Maurice Macmillan, m p, chief secretary, Treasury (Item 2)The following were also present:The Right Hon. Julian Amery, mp,Minister of Public Building and works (Item 2)The Right Hon. christopher chataway, mp, Minister of posts and Telecommunications (Item 2)The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury
Secretariat :Sir Burke trend sir Robin hooper mr. P. E. thornton mr. B. G. tucker miss S. W. Fog artyContentsItem Subject page 1     Acts of Violence Against Civil Aircraft     ......       32     Public Expenditure..................       5w
Acts ofViolenceAgainstCivil Aircraft(previous reference:CM (70) 15thConclusions)121428A 2SECRET1. The Prime Minister, reviewing developments since theCabinet had last considered the situation on the evening of12 September, said that HM Ambassador in Amman had reportedthat the statement issued that day on the Governmenfs intentionsregarding the release of Leila Khalid had had a calming effect inAmman and that the situation there remained quiet for the present.There had been Press reports to the effect that the disturbances inAmman on Saturday which had resulted in the issue of our statement had not in fact occurred; but these reports had emanated not fromAmman but from Beirut and were inaccurate. Indeed, HMAmbassador had warned us during the previous day that LeilaKhalid had now become a popular heroine and a symbol ofPalestinian resistance; and if, as was required by the provisions ofthe Aliens (Places of Detention) Order as it then stood, she were transferred that day from police custody to prison, albeit withoutany change in her legal status, there was a risk that the Fedayeensupporters of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine(PFLP), misunderstanding our intentions once again, would provokefurther outbreaks of violence in which the lives of the remaininghostages would be exposed to renewed danger. The matter had accordingly been considered on the afternoon of 13 September bythe group of Ministers mainly concerned; and the Home Secretary,after seeking legal advice and with the agreement of his colleagues,had made an Order to amend the Aliens (Places of Detention) Order,the effect of which would be to permit Leila Khalid&apos;s continued detention in police custody.Meanwhile the great majority of the hostages held by the fedayeen had now been released and had left Jordan safely. Some56, however, remained in Fedayeen hands. Their exact whereaboutswas not known; but they were thought to be confined in a campnear Amman, under the sole guard of the PFLP. Of the total of 56,8 (5 passengers and 3 aircrew from the VC-10 aircraft) were Britishsubjects; 2 were German nationals; 6 were Swiss; and the balancewere Israelis, United States citizens and individuals of dual UnitedStates-Israeli nationality. While it was satisfactory that the greatmajority of the passengers and aircrew had now been released andthat our apprehensions about the possible ambiguity of the Fedayeenoffer had been shown to be unfounded, the matter could not beallowed to rest there; in particular, the impression should not beallowed to gain ground in the five-Power discussions in Berne and elsewhere that the problem had become any less urgent simply because a smaller number of hostages was involved. On thecontrary, those who remained in the hands of the PFLP might bein greater danger now than they had been before the release of themain body.  It was therefore increasingly urgent to re-establish an
effective channel through which to conduct negotiations with the fedayeen.   The Vice-President of the International Committee ofthe Red Cross (ICRC), M. Freymond, and the ICRC representative in the Middle East, M. Rochat, had now returned to Switzerland,leaving behind in Amman a small ICRC party under the directionof M. Jacquinet.  The latter&apos;s terms of reference were not entirelyclear; but it appeared that, although he would be concerned primarily with medical and humanitarian questions, he would beempowered and prepared to act as an intermediary with the fedayeen, at least to the extent of ascertaining their terms for therelease of the remaining hostages.   At a meeting of the five-Powergroup in Berne during the previous night, at which M. Freymondand M. Rochat had been present, HM Ambassador had been instructed to make a strong plea that the ICRC should resume fullparticipation in the negotiations with the Fedayeen.  The latter had indicated that the release of the remaining hostages would becontingent on the release by the Israeli Government of Fedayeenprisoners in their hands. But they had not so far given any specificindication of the numbers, categories or identity of the prisonerswhose return they would demand; and information on these essentialpoints could be obtained, if at all, only when a channel ofcommunication with the Fedayeen was re-established.   For their part, the Government of Israel had continued to maintain that theyhad already made a major concession in accepting that we, togetherwith the German and Swiss Governments, should intimate to the fedayeen that we were prepared, as part of a satisfactory general settlement, to consider the release of the Fedayeen prisoners whom we held; and that they therefore saw no reason for any further concession by Israel.   At the same time, they had arrested anddetained some 450 Arabs in Israel, without consulting or evenwarning the other participants in the discussions in Berne.   TheUnited States were still showing reluctance to press the israeli government to adopt a less rigid position, no doubt because fromtheir point of view the overriding consideration, to which they gavefirst priority, was the need to avoid any action which might prejudice the prospects for the resumption of negotiations between Israel andthe Arab States in relation to the Middle East situation as a whole;and this factor, together with their concern about the forthcoming meeting between the President of the United States, Mr. Nixon, andthe Israeli Prime Minister, Mrs. Meir, would make them hesitate tobring pressure to bear on the Government of Israel as regards the relatively limited issue of the release of the hostages in Amman.In these circumstances, however, it was likely to become increasingly difficult to ensure that the five Powers would remain united in refusing to contemplate a settlement except on a non-discriminatorybasis.   So far the German Government, despite rumours to thecontrary from Amman, had held firm, as had the Swiss Government.
public expenditure(previous reference:CM (70) 8thConclusions,Minute 6)SECRET*2. The Cabinet memoranda on public expenditure by theChancellor of the Exchequer (CP (70) 38) and the Chief Secretary,Treasury (CP (70) 39).But the longer the present deadlock continued, the more the pressurewas likely to grow, not only in Germany and Switzerland but inthis country also, for effective action to secure the release of theirand our nationals. If the Government of Israel remained obdurateand the United States continued to refuse to bring pressure to bearon them, resentment was likely to build up in the European countries on the ground that our hostages were being used as pawns in thegeneral Arab-Israel confrontation which was of no direct concern to us; and this resentment could not be contained indefinitely.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary confirmed that there appeared to be no prospect of further progress towards the releaseof the hostages unless the Government of Israel adopted a lessuncompromising attitude; and only the United States could exerteffective influence on them in this direction. Hitherto the UnitedStates Government had appeared not to appreciate the strength of feeling in the European countries or the very real danger that the unity of the five Powers in the discussions in Berne might be strainedto breaking-point. But, as a result of the discussions which had now taken place between HM Ambassador in Washington and the UnitedStates Secretary of State, Mr. Rogers, the latter now seemed to havea better understanding of the position. In particular, he was concerned that many of the non-European hostages were of dualUnited States/Israeli nationality; and he had taken note of ourwarning that, if the five-Power unity in the Berne discussions couldnot be maintained, the United States might find themselves isolatedin company with Israel. He still seemed to think, however, that itwas wiser, on balance, to proceed at a more cautious and deliberatepace than we ourselves believed possible.The Prime Minister, summing up a brief discussion, said that,although Ministers might need to consider the situation again at short notice, no further action on our part was required for the timebeing. We must now wait to see how far our representations in washington were reflected in the attitude of the United states representative in the discussions in Berne.The Cabinet Took note of the statements by the Prime Minister and theForeign and Commonwealth Secretary.
The Prime Minister said that the Cabinet had agreed on 23 Julythat their objective should be a net reduction in public expenditureamounting to  1,700 million, including  700 million from theabolition of investment grants, by 1974-75. It was important thatthe present survey should not be looked on simply as an exercise tosecure necessary savings in public expenditure. The Governmenthad been returned to office pledged to a radical review of the services which the Government should provide, with the aim of withdrawal from spheres where firms and individuals could more appropriatelyprovide for themselves with the additional resources released bylower taxation. The Government were committed to this major change of course and not simply to some transfer of the costs of publicly provided services from the Exchequer to the user. Theywere committed to reduce taxation in order also to provide newstimuli to individual initiative and economic growth.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, in order to put theGovernment into a position to make a statement on the first day that Parliament reassembled, the Cabinet would need to considerthe outstanding proposals by the Chief Secretary for public expenditure savings and any proposals for additional savings andnew expenditure during the week beginning 28 September. drafts of the proposed Parliamentary statement and accompanying white paper would need to be completed by 15 October for the Cabinefsconsideration on 20 October. The Government^ commitments werespecific and clear. The nation had been led to believe that theywould drastically reduce expenditure on services provided by government; and reductions on the scale which had already beenagreed were needed to enable them to carry out their generalstrategy. Under the previous Administration public expenditurehad risen from 43 per cent to 51 per cent of the gross national product and their future programme would have involved an increasein the present level of taxation by more than  300 million by 1974.A corresponding reduction in public expenditure was needed merely to prevent a rise in present tax rates and it was only by makingeconomies beyond that point that the Government could make room for the tax reductions to which they were pledged, as set out in thefirst paragraph of his memorandum. Meanwhile they had already agreed to additional public expenditure of  30 million in 1971-72.Although the yield of taxes at present rates increased, with inflation,year by year so did the costs of publicly provided services, and itwould be irresponsible to rely now on faster economic growth inthe future as the principal means of reducing taxation. Nor could the Government look to a value-added tax as a means of reducingdirect taxation and continuing to finance public expenditure atpresent levels: the introduction of a value-added tax would providethe revenue at present provided by purchase tax and the selective employment tax. The Exchequer would save  700 million from the
abolition of investment grants, but with sluggish investment, withcompanies in a tight liquidity position, and with continuing problemsof regional development, it must be assumed that the greater part ofthese savings would need to be returned to companies in some form:he and the Minister of Technology were at present discussing thisquestion and hoped to bring proposals on investment incentivesbefore the Cabinet in the week beginning 28 September. It wastherefore necessary to find savings of  1,000 million elsewhere.Though the specific proposals for cuts in services would appearunwelcome and some might be unpopular, public opinion had beenled to expect that many of them would be put into effect and, as thePrime Minister had said, there was no better time for a major changeof course than the beginning of a new Parliament. As the chief secretary would explain in introducing his own paper, it wasmoreover important to maintain a reasonable balance between cutsin social expenditure, which would impose burdens on those with low incomes, and other Government expenditure; but on the basisof the present response to the Chief Secretary&apos;s proposals the pattern of cuts would be seriously unbalanced. In discussion it was emphasised that there was a general expectation, both here andabroad, that the Government would shortly be putting forward majorproposals. Unless the reductions in expenditure were sufficient tomake room for substantial reductions in taxation, the credibility ofthe Governmenfs entire policies would be at risk. It was, therefore,essential that the original target of  1,000 million savings (apart fromthe abolition of investment grants) should be achieved. To ensurethis, it would be essential to include the prospective savings fromthe major changes proposed in housing policy and in the system Ofagricultural support. On the other hand, the proposed reductions in expenditure had not been forced on the Cabinet by an economiccrisis but arose from the redirection of priorities by a new government. While some of the proposed reductions in expenditure would not be popular, they could be presented as part of an overallstrategy and could be more easily undertaken now than at any othertime. It was, however, argued that it would be unfortunate if certain of the major policy changes, for instance on council house rents, were first presented as part of a general saving in public expenditure tomake room for reductions in taxation. The new housing policy should be presented rather as part of a new policy which wouldconcentrate direct help (through rebates) on those who really neededit while putting others in a position (through tax reductions) to paythe real cost of the services they required. Any announcement whichallowed the prospective average increases of  2- 4 per week in rentsto be reduced without relating them to the offsetting tax reductionsmight increase the rate of wage inflation and would certainly be
strongly opposed. The proposed change in agricultural support arrangements would in any event be troublesome to negotiate andit would be advisable to secure the maximum savings which wouldbe substantially more than the  150 million proposed in such negotiations. And, while it would be necessary for the Cabinet tosettle now the bases for the social security upratings in 1971 and1973, it would be unnecessary to reveal them so far in advance. Itmight also take time to work out how adequate offsets for poorerfamilies could be provided, as the tax system seemed unlikely toprovide sufficient scope without some additional public expenditure.In the circumstances, therefore, it might be helpful if the total savingsexpected in 1974-75 were given in only broad terms and theircomponents not spelled out in detail in the proposed statement and white Paper. The new strategies in particular fields could then be announced in policy statements setting them in their proper context.In further discussion concern was expressed about the balanceof the reductions so far agreed. To fit in with the Cabinefs overallstrategy, real reductions in Governmental activities were required.Yet the agreed items were largely increases in charges, together withcertain other cuts in the social services. Without additionalsubstantial savings on assistance to industry, research anddevelopment, and technological support public opinion would notconsider the outcome fair. On the other hand it was argued thatmajor cuts in assistance to industry and related fields depended ondetailed studies which could not be completed for some time. Itwould be unwise to accept that reductions of a particular order wouldbe feasible before the possibilities had been fully assessed. Moreover,substantial sums beyond those now allocated might be needed for investment in the steel industry, and it was not yet possible to be sure that they could be raised elsewhere. It was, however, argued that itshould still be possible to decide now the scale on which reductions in activities ought to be made to carry out the Governmenfs policyof making industry more self-reliant, and then to concentrate the studies on how, rather than whether, this should be done.It was suggested that scope for reducing personal taxation mightbe found in other ways than by reductions in public expenditure.Investment grants had originally replaced tax allowances and, giventhe present level of industrial investment and of company liquidity,the bulk of the savings would have to be returned to the corporatesector; some net savings might, however, be made here. An increasein personal and corporate savings consequent on the Governmenfseconomic policies would contribute to the scope for tax relief in the medium term, but it would not be right to anticipate it at this stage.The commitment to abolish the Selective Employment Tax (SET)without replacing it by a payroll tax did not rule out an increase inemployers social security contributions, or the possibility that theymight be proportionate to wages.   If a value-added tax were
121428bintroduced at a rate sufficient to provide equivalent revenue to thatreleased by both SET and Purchase Tax, it would already be as high as the comparable taxes in Europe. Only by raising it still highercould it contribute to a reduction in direct taxation.It was noted that the examination of possible reductions inCivil Service manpower had so far suggested that only very smallreductions in manpower could be made in 1971-72 and only modestreductions in the following year. In the longer term there wouldbe larger reductions as activities were reduced or discontinued. Inthe meantime, however, Departments might be instructed to reduce their administrative costs, by, say, 5 per cent. Ministers might haveto be prepared, in the interests of economy, to accept some reductionin thoroughness in briefing and cross-checking, as well as the elimination of minor activities. It was, however, important to handleany such proposals in the way least likely to damage the morale ofthe Foreign and Home Civil Services.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion, saidthat the Cabinet reaffirmed their July target of a net reduction of 1,000 million in public expenditure by 1974-75. A substantial partof this saving must be secured by reductions in the Governmentsuse of resources. It would be necessary to contain expenditure on defence and other external policies. The results of the review shouldbe presented to Parliament when they resumed, probably in astatement on 27 October, setting the public expenditure review inthe context of the Governmenfs strategy as a whole. To enable thistimetable to be met, the Cabinet would have to reach decisions inthe brief period between 28 September and the start of theConservative Party Conference on all the outstanding proposals for reductions in expenditure, including the uprating of social security benefits in 1971 and 1973, the interim scheme for agricultural levies,and how the total expenditure implications of the new housing and agricultural support policies were to be taken into account. It shouldalso be possible to consider in the same period both the Chancellorof the Exchequer^ proposals for replacing the investment grantsystem and any proposals for additional expenditure, including thosenecessary to offset the effects of the review on poorer families.Memoranda which Ministers wished to submit on any issues whichhad not been agreed with Treasury Ministers should be circulatedto Cabinet by 23 September. Arrangements should be made toenable the Cabinet to consider the rate support grant, if possible,immediately before the Conservative Party Conference and, at latest,in the week beginning 12 October. The draft statement and white paper would then be circulated on 15 October for consideration by cabinet early in the following week. In the meantime, the Chancellorof the Exchequer might let the Press know that a statement would
be made when Parliament resumed, but would not refer to this inhis speech to the forthcoming Commonwealth Finance Ministers&apos;Conference in Cyprus. The Chancellor would also give furtherconsideration to the possibility of presenting the figures for reductions in expenditure in 1974-75 in broad terms which would allow some flexibility and avoid premature disclosure of the outcome of thereviews of housing and agricultural policy. The Cabinet would wishto give further consideration to the idea of a general percentagereduction in administrative expenditure when they consider shortlya memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal on Civil Service Manpower.The Cabinet-(1) Took note with approval of the summing up of this part oftheir discussion by the Prime Minister.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer (i) to give further consideration to the presentation ofthe total reductions in expenditure in 1974-75 onthe lines indicated by the Prime Minister in his summing up of the discussion;(ii) to circulate a memorandum about the replacement ofthe investment grant system for consideration bythe Cabinet at the end of September;(iii) to be guided in any statements about the timing ofthe public expenditure review by the summing upof the discussion by the Prime Minister.(3) Invited Ministers to circulate by 23 September anymemoranda that they wished to submit on specificreductions or increases in expenditure on which they hadnot reached agreement with the Chief Secretary, Treasury.(4) Invited the Minister of Housing and Local Government tobring proposals for the rate support grant negotiationsbefore the Cabinet for consideration if possible at thebeginning of the week of 5 October and, in any event,not later than the week beginning 12 October.Expenditure The Cabinet then considered a memorandum by the ChiefProgrammes    Secretary, Treasury (CP (70) 39) reporting on his discussions withthe other Ministers concerned to achieve reductions in public expenditure.The Chief Secretary, Treasury, said that the Cabinet had invited him in July to discuss with the other Ministers concerned proposalsfor a net reduction in public expenditure of  1,700 million by 1974-75.On the assumption that the saving of about  700 million, whichmight be secured from the abolition of investment grants and whichwas included in the target of  1,700 million, would mainly have tobe returned to industry in other forms, he had, in his discussions,aimed at net savings from other sources of a little over  1,000 million
by 1974-75, of which a substantial part would be available for reducing personal taxation. The outcome of the present exercise,which was essentially one of switching resources from the public tothe private sector, would be announced and published separately from the usual annual White Paper setting out the public expenditure programmes for the five years from 1969-70 to 1974-75. He would consider carefully whether the total reductions agreed for 1974-75could be published without too precise a breakdown between individual programmes. He had regarded the Cabinet remit in Julyas precluding him from agreeing to any proposals for additional expenditure except those which were an inevitable consequence ofparticular savings. Thus, there were a number of outstanding claims for additional social expenditure to reduce the impact of the reductions proposed in this field on those with low incomes. Atpresent social services were not only provided indiscriminately tothose who could and to those who could not afford to pay to provide them for themselves, but there was also a disincentive effect for those on low incomes because increases in incomes led to correspondingreductions in, or disqualification from benefits: the latter effect was equivalent to a 100 per cent income tax on low income groups. new arrangements to confine benefits to those who really needed themand to avoid the present disincentive effects would reduce the grosssavings which could be achieved. The total reductions in public expenditure which had so far been agreed were not only far too small but were also seriously unbalanced by their heavy concentration on social expenditure. No significant savings had yet been offeredon expenditure on assistance to industry or on the investment programmes of the nationalised industries. These latter sectors must make a substantial contribution. A major contribution to the savings in both 1971-72 and 1974-75 would come from limiting the increases in social security benefits in 1971 and 1973: but the intended increases in those years would not be revealed under the conventions adopted for the presentation of public expenditure programmes. He accepted that major savings in expenditure by theMinistry of Technology on assistance to industry and for other purposes required prior detailed examination. The time requiredfor study and for decisions in this field would, however, be considerably reduced if the studies were confined to an examinationof how best to carry out the Governmenfs policy of withdrawingassistance to industry for example, by abolition of the industrial reorganisation Corporation and did not extend to a re-examinationof the merits of those policies. The present capital expenditure programmes of the nationalised industries for 1974-75 totalled 1,850 million. He had asked for a reduction of  25 million in these programmes for 1971-72 and of  100 million in 1974-75. To datehe had been offered reductions of only  6 million and  29 million
respectively and much of this was described as doubtful on practicalgrounds. It had been suggested, on the other hand, that the british steel Corporation^ investment programme required to be increasedbeyond the current programme. If any such increase were to be seriously considered it should be after completion of the presentexercise and it should not be allowed as an offset against the savingsrequired in this sector. The technological support programme for1974-75 amounted  108 million: this, of course, was in addition toGovernment assistance to aircraft projects, the coal-mining industry,the shipbuilding industry and other support schemes and projectscovered by Ministry of Technology Votes. He had proposed areduction of just under  10 million in this expenditure in 1971-72,rising to at least  25 million and preferably  50 million in 1974-75.So far he had been offered no more than a reduction of  5 million inthis programme for 1971-72. A substantial reduction in government expenditure on assistance to industry was required not only toprovide an adequate and balanced reduction in public expenditure but also in order to further the Governmenfs aim of leavingcompanies and individuals to meet more of their needs from theirown resources, which could then be increased by lower taxation.The Cabinet (5) Agreed to resume their discussion on the following day.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,14th September, 1970.


</content>
</cab>
