<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/47/0 images: 230-236</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. June 1971CM (70) Copy No.    2 318th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Wednesday, 16 September, 1970,at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudlingmp, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,mp, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, m p, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment and productivity the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,m p, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Michael Noble, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. John Da vies, mp,Minister of technology the following were also present:The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Sir Burke trend sir Robin hooper mr. P. E. Thornton
Subject:Acts of Violence Against Civil AircraftGeneral SituationMeasures for the Protection of british civil Airports and Aircraft
Acts ofViolenceAgainst civil aircraft(previous reference:CM (70) 17thConclusions,Minute 1)GeneralSituationSECRETThe Prime Minister said that on the previous evening a message had been received from HM Embassy in Berne to the effect that theInternational Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC) had now agreedto send two senior officials, M. Boissier and M. Boisard, to Ammanwith authority to negotiate with the Arab Fedayeen organisation,the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine (PFLP), for therelease of the hostages whom they held. This had now been publicly announced. M. Jacquinet, who had been in charge of ICRCoperations in Jordan after the departure of M. Freymond andM. Rochat, would now return to headquarters. During the evening of 15 September, M. Jacquinet had conveyed to HM ambassador and the representatives of the United States, Germany and switzerland the terms on which the PFLP were now prepared tonegotiate for the release of the hostages. These were as follows:(i) The three Swiss-held Fedayeen in return for all Swisshostages.(ii) The three German-held Fedayeen in return for all Germanhostages.(iii) Leila Khaled and the body of her male accomplice in returnfor all British hostages.The PFLP also demanded an official agreement in principle bythe Israeli Government to free the two Algerians taken off a british overseas Airways Corporation aircraft and arrested in Tel Aviv, andone Swiss boy at Haifa; the two Lebanese soldiers kidnapped by the israeli Army (this in exchange for the Israeli kibbutz guardRosenwasser); and an undertaking to exchange commandos againsthostages. The PFLP would then hand over a list of persons whoserelease they required in exchange for the hostages of Israeli and dualUnited States / Israeli nationality. It was clear that the United states citizens held as hostages were considered by the PFLP as falling intothis latter category, although the information now available to usindicated that the PFLP in fact held no individuals of Israelinationality, only two individuals of dual United States / Israelinationality and 35 United States citizens with no other nationality.After these contacts with the PFLP, there had been a further development which materially affected the prospects of a negotiation.Early that day HM Ambassador in Amman had informed us of the resignation of the Government of Jordan and its replacement by amilitary Government which had proclaimed martial law. So far thesituation remained quiet; but, if King Hussein and the military government could not hold the position, a major clash between theJordanian Army and the Fedayeen might not be long delayed.  The121444B*
outcome of such a confrontation was unpredictable: and the likelihood that it might occur strengthened the case for securing thereturn of the British hostages before hostilities made it impossible tomaintain contacts with the Fedayeen. The deterioration in theinternal political situation also raised the question of the safety ofthe remaining British subjects in Jordan. Service aircraft werestanding by in Cyprus, at Bahrain and in this country to evacuatethem, if necessary; and arrangements had been made for a message to be broadcast by the British Broadcasting Corporation, if fightingbetween the Jordanian Army and Fedayeen broke out, appealing forthe safety of the hostages and all foreign nationals. We had beenin touch with the United States Government who had so far taken no action but did not rule out the possibility of giving air support to the Jordanian Army if hostilities broke out.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that late on theprevious day the German representative at the five-Power discussions in Berne had indicated that his Government must insist that a clear and specific mandate for negotiation should be given to the ICRC,with &quot; appropriate participation from all Governments&quot; (astipulation which must be interpreted as requiring a realistic and adequate Israeli contribution to the exchange of hostages) by noon on 16 September. Failing this, the German Government would consider alternative action. The five-Power group would be holding further meeting at midday that day: and we had to consider urgently what instructions should be sent to HM Ambassador inBerne.In discussion the Cabinet agreed that, by maintaining a united front with the other Governments concerned and by standing out against the PFLP&apos;s successive ultimatum, we had secured the return of the majority of the hostages and had so achieved a situationconsiderably less menacing than the one with which we had originally been confronted. If possible, therefore, we should avoidtaking the lead in breaking up the five-Power front. If it dissolved,it would no longer be possible for us to exercise any influence in favour of the return of the United States and dual-nationalhostages; and piecemeal settlements on a country-by-country basismight be merely an invitation to terrorists to commit furtheracts of violence. Such a course could therefore be justifiedonly if we were convinced that there was no alternative. On theother hand we had from the outset made it clear to the Fedayeenthat we were ready to negotiate. We could not continue indefinitely to risk the lives of our nationals by deferring to theGovernment of Israel, who were still refusing, 10 days after theaircraft had been seized, to make any contribution to the release ofthe hostages. Moreover, the likelihood of a violent confrontationbetween the Jordanian Army and the Fedayeen, coupled with the
Measures forthe Protectionof british civil Airportsand Aircraftthreat to the safety of our hostages which this implied, created a new situation in which we could not risk the delays involved in either a continuance of the present position or a further protracted discussion in which the Israeli Government were brought reluctantly and underpressure to state the basis on which they were prepared to negotiate.It was already clear that neither of these courses would be acceptable to the German Government. But, if they now sought to negotiate a unilateral settlement with the PFLP, the Swiss Government might follow; and it would then be difficult to contain pressures in thiscountry for similar action on our part.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that much would depend on developments in Amman and on the course of thefurther meeting that morning of the five-Power group in Berne. Sofar as the latter was concerned, we should try to elicit from the israeli representative a clear indication whether his Governmentwere prepared to make a contribution which would constitute anadequate basis for negotiations with the Fedayeen. If his responsewere positive, it might be possible to maintain the attempt to achieve a non-discriminatory settlement. But, if the reply were negative oreven equivocal, we should have to consider, with the German andSwiss Governments, whether we should now attempt to reach asettlement with the Fedayeen as regards our respective nationals ona three-Power or country-by-country basis. In reaching this decision the three Powers would have to take into consideration thedeteriorating security situation in Amman and the desirability of reaching a solution while there was still time. HM Ambassador inBerne should be instructed accordingly; and he would considerwhether he himself should discuss the situation direct with thePresident of the United States, Mr. Nixon, after the meeting inBerne. It might well be necessary for the Cabinet to meet later inthe day in order to take stock of developments and to decide on anyfurther action which might be necessary.The Cabinet (1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.i (2) Invited the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary to instructHM Ambassador in Berne on the lines indicated in thePrime Minister&apos;s summing up.The President of the Board of Trade said that consideration hadbeen given to following the United States and Swiss example by introducing security guards on civil aircraft. This suggestion raiseda number of practical and technical problems, not least in terms of manpower; and the airline pilots were still opposed to it, on the
grounds of the implied risk to the safety of their aircraft. In thecircumstances, and given the need for immediate action, it might be advisable to concentrate on intensifying precautions at airports witha view to preventing undesirable individuals from gaining access toinstallations or to the aircraft themselves. If guards were to beprovided, it would be necessary to decide whether they should be armed. It should not be too difficult to equip them with arms(e.g. low-velocity pistols) which, if used, would not seriously damage the pressure hull of the aircraft. But it had to be borne in mind that their opponents would not be subject to any such limitations.A number of other possibilities were also being considered, includingthe isolation of the flight deck from the rest of the aircraft and the installation of closed-circuit television which would enable the crewto keep the passengers under observation.The Prime Minister, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthe matter was already causing considerable public concern, whichwould increase unless we were seen to be taking adequateprecautions. The working party of officials which was consideringthe problems involved should submit a progress report for furtherconsideration by the Ministers primarily concerned that evening; andan appropriate statement should be prepared for publication as necessary.The Cabinet (3) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^ summing up of their discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,16 September, 1970.


</content>
</cab>
