<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/47/0 images: 347-353</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  July 1971CM (70) Copy No. 2 328th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 13 October, 1970,at 11 a.m.Present:-The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph,m p, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment and productivity the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,mp, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,q c, m p, Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,mp, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Michael Noble, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Minister of technology the following were also present:The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Sir Peter Rawlinson,qc, mp, Attorney general secretariat :Sir Burke trend . B. G. tucker mr. G. F. Kear
ContentsSubjectOversea Affairs     ..................Kidnapping of United Kingdom Trade commissioner at MontrealEuropean Economic CommunityBermudaIndustrial Affairs..................Local Authority Manual Workers&apos; Dispute/
OverseaAffairsKidnapping ofUnitedKingdomTradeCommissionerat Montreal(previous reference:CM (70) 27thConclusions,Minute 1)EuropeanEconomicCommunityCM 28 (70)secret. The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary informed theCabinet that a meeting had now been arranged between lawyerswho were acting with perhaps doubtful propriety for the two sides in the negotiations for the release of the British trade commissioner and the Quebec Minister of Labour and immigration who were being held as hostages by the Front deLiberation Quebecois (FLQ) in Montreal. This at least indicated that the individuals concerned were still alive; but it was far fromclear on what basis any negotiations could take place or what theiroutcome could be.In the course of a brief discussion it was agreed that there wasno further action which we could expect the Canadian Governmentto take for the time being and that we must now await developments.But the incident was a fresh reminder of the threat to which, incurrent conditions, members of Governments and public services were exposed; and, although it would probably be impracticable toprovide police protection for all the individuals who might be thought to be at risk, it might be helpful for Ministers to be informed ofthe methods which political terrorists were likely to employ and the personal precautions which could be adopted against them. So faras Parliament was concerned, a new Security Officer was being appointed, who would be responsible to the Speaker and would assume the security functions which had hitherto been discharged by the Serjeant at Arms.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Home Secretary to circulate such informationas could be provided about the precautions whichindividuals might adopt against threats or attacks ontheir persons by political terrorists.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary informed theCabinet that the Committee on the Approach to Europe had agreed at a meeting on the previous day that in the forthcoming negotiationsfor our accession to the European Economic Community (e.c.) weshould seek to secure a transitional period of six years for agricultural and horticultural products.In discussion it was agreed that this would, no doubt, evokeprotests from farmers and horticulturalists, particularly perhaps asregards apples; but it should be possible to deal with these representations provided that we retained the maximum degree of flexibility within the six-year period.121681b*
Bermuda The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary referred to theserious disturbances which had occurred in Bermuda over the previousweek-end. In view of the impending visits of HRH the Prince of wales and the Speaker of the House of Commons to the Island itwould be necessary to keep a close watch on developments.The Cabinet-(2) Took  note  of  the  statements  by  the  Foreign  and commonwealth Secretary.IndustrialAffairsLocal AuthorityManualWorkers&apos;Dispute(previous reference:CM (70) 27thConclusions,Minute 2)secret. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary (CP (70) 82), discussing the possibility that an increasing number of local authorities might be prepared to make separatesettlements with their manual workers in excess of the 14 per centwage increase already offered which the Government considered tobe the maximum permissible basis of agreement.In discussion the Cabinet were informed that the situation was deteriorating. Pollution of the rivers was increasing; a criticalposition might shortly arise in Cardiff; and in some areas it might become necessary within a week to cut off the intake of river water,with the result that water would cease to be available for normalpurposes. There was particular cause for anxiety at Swindon, wherethe local authority had been advised that they might face substantialclaims for compensation in respect of damage caused by pollution;and, being conscious that such claims would represent a heavieradditional burden on the rates than a settlement of the wage claims on the basis of the unions&apos; demands, they were likely to capitulateto the unions. If so, however, it would be relatively easy for theunions to mobilise the same type of pressure against other localauthorities; the Governmenfs policy of resisting excessive wage claims would be seen to have suffered defeat in a critical case; andit would be virtually impossible to maintain that policy in relationto the pending wage claim in the National Health Service, wherethe Government themselves were directly involved.The Cabinet agreed that in these circumstances a renewed effort must be made to convince public opinion that the government intended to adhere to their policy and would take all reasonablemeasures to reinforce the local authorities in withstanding theunions&apos; demands. It was agreed that for this purpose action shouldbe taken on the following lines:
(a) Local authorities were exposed to the risk of both criminalprosecution, subject to the Attorney-General&apos;s consent, and civilaction for damages. In these circumstances the Government shouldmake it clear that, if necessary, they would introduce legislation to protect the local authorities against any legal consequences of actions which they had taken or failed to take as a direct result ofthe situation in which they had been placed by the unreasonableattitude of the unions. Any statement for this purpose, however,should seek to avoid creating the impression that the government intended merely to ignore well-founded claims for compensation orto deprive riparian interests of their rights at law.(b) This statement might be reinforced if appropriate by an indication that a worker might face criminal proceedings underSection 5 of the Conspiracy and Protection of Property Act, 1875,if he broke a contract of service or of hiring when he knew or hadreasonable cause to believe that the consequences of his doing so would be to endanger human life or to cause serious bodily injury or to expose valuable property to destruction or serious injury. Itmight also be indicated that the unions would be held responsiblefor meeting from their own funds any substantiated claims for damages from the present situation. On the other hand it might be preferable at the present stage to stop short of such further measures and to limit the proposed statement to an undertaking to introduceif necessary a simple Act of Indemnity, possibly coupled with an indication that the Government might provide a strictly limited sum for compensation in respect of serious loss or damage resulting fromthe present situation.^ &apos;&apos; it(c) It should also be made clear that the Government wereprepared to introduce troops as soon as it became necessary to doso in the interests of public health. To go further than this in the sense of indicating that troops might be used to deal also withpollution would be to introduce a new and dangerous principle intoindustrial relations and would in any case be unwise since therewould not be adequate troops to deal with pollution on a nation-wide scale. On the other hand the concept of &quot; public health &quot;should be interpreted as comprehensively as possible; and it should probably be deemed to comprise a situation in which water ceased to be available at all. No effort should be spared to mobilisespecialised personnel from the forces wherever they might be; andin the last resort the Government might need to appeal for civilianvolunteers.(d) Steps should be taken to secure greater public unstanding of the real nature of the wages dispute and of the scope of the offer
which the employers had made. In particular, it should be made clear that they had already offered a settlement which would provide an effective minimum wage of  16 10s. a week and that, although this offer had not so far been made public, it was still available.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that itwas essential that the Government should stand firm at the present justice and should do everything possible to ensure that the localauthorities continue to resist the unions&apos; demands. The employers were meeting that afternoon; and the Emergencies Committeeshould therefore consider worthwith the terms in which the HomeSecretary and the Minister of Housing and Local Government mightconvey to them, for simultaneous publication, the governments intentions as they had emerged during the Cabinefs discussion.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Home Secretary to arrange for the emergencies committee to meet forthwith on the basis described inthe Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Lord President to consider, as a matter of urgency, how the Governmenfs case could be mostrapidly and effectively presented to public opinion.Cabinet Office, S.W11,13th October, 1970.


</content>
</cab>
