<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/13/23 images: 256-263</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
* -----------.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY. jIt is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.3 L 0W.P.. (40) 445o15TH NOVEMBER,  1940. COPY NO.WAR CABINET.S.S.  CUBA.The attached draft telegram prepared&quot;by the Admiralty is circulated in connectionwith Item 4 of the Agenda for todays meetingof the War Cabinet.(intVd)   E.E.B.Richmcnrrace, S.W. 1.15TI-J NOVEMBER,  1940. .

SECRET.s.s. CUBA.Draft telegram prepared by the Admiralty.Address:    The Commander-in-Chief, South Atlantic, rom: Admiralty.Your 1853/L2K.     Present intention is that CUBA shallbe brought to the United Kingdom provided that -(a) satisfactory arrangements nan be -made to repatriatepro Vichy^ elements amongst crew and passengers tosome? Vichy territory where they will not constitute a danger, and(b) that a crew can be provided for CUBA from Freetownto the United Kingdom.If it is not possible to find a neutral ship for (a) aboveFrench ship now in United Kingdom will be sent under armedguard to Freetown to take men from CUBA.2,    CUBA should therefore be detained pending instructions.3.   Your 1721/7.     Request report of cargo in full detail and at what ports ship was intended to call.j4.    Part II follows giving financial terms for personnel&apos;;5.    This message should be passed to Governor.^Reproduced as Annex 1./Not reproduced.

SECRET.ANNEX I.1 ^MESSAGE.1853/13th Nov.IN.Date: 12.11.40.From: G. in CSouth Atlantic. Reed. 2356Addressed Admiralty.IMMEDIATE.177.     Your 1733/12 CUBA has now been rummaged by Customsstaff in co-operation with Naval Officers.      Certain cases,possible receptacles for gold have been opened and examined and cargoes in holds spitted and examined as far as possibleCargo is reported to be in order by Comptroller of customs and no trace Of gold or valuable cargo.     Captain has notbeen informed that ship will be released, but thinks there ia possibility of this.     Arrangements are being made inco-operation with the Colonial Government for interviewingthe Naval Officers and ratings in accordance with your2326/8 and as regards the merchant officers and crew inaccordance with Secretary of State&apos;s 636 referred to in my1929/9.      These arrangements have not been completed yet ascareful organisation is required to prevent intimidation by officers and large numbers involved.     Further signal will bmade about removal of cargo.     Request earliest informationas to financial terms for Naval and Military personnelwilling to join (A) Free French or (B) British Service.1853/L2




</content>
</cab>
