<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/20/0 images: 9-9</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 58(61).					26th October, 1961.

	1.	Foreign Affairs.		[Enter  M.R.

	a)	Berlin.
H.	E. Berliners insisted on U.S. personnel showg. passes – wh. they 
		have never had.  U.S. show of strength.  Mtg. to-day.  U.S. firm 
		because Gromyko agreed no change of practice while discns
		proceed.  Our practice is to show passes.
	b)	Congo.
	Tshombe sent 2 junior officials to Adoula.  T. not v. f’coming:
		but A. responsive because nervous of Gizenga.  We are urging
T. therefore tht. this is a moment to do a deal – better terms likely.
	c)	Laos.
	King has agreed to Phonma as P.M., but won’t say so publicly until
		all Govt. posts filled &amp; announced.
	d)	Nuclear Tests.
	U.N.	have passed resoln of disapproval.  Don’t yet know wtr. it was
		30 or 50 megatons.

P.M.	We shall have to state a posn on resumptn in Debate on Address.
	Provisional view:  no case for tests in atmosphere merely to out-do R.
		If needed to m’tain balance of deterrent (esp. on anti-missile
		weapon) we mght. have to do it.  This is only tenable moral 
		position.
	Reserve right to make tests:  but make foregoing negative point.

H.W.	Hope U.S. can get ahead with what they need to do by underground
		tests.

Hail.	No need to hurry one, even for military reasons:  lest it appear to be
		for mere propaganda purpose.
						[Enter  J.P.
	2.	Army Man-Power – Reserves.

J.P.	New voluntary reserve w’in T.A.  Liability:  maximum of 6 months in
		any year.  As individuals – or prs. in sub-units.
	Wd like authy to include provision for this in the new legislation.

P.M.	Advantages   a)  1st step twds. rationalisation of reserves as a whole.
			     b)  insists long-term element in what wd. otherwise
		seem to be stop-gap legislation.

H.B.	Ty. will be asked to approve cost at v. short notice.
	Permanent expre of £4 m. p.a.  Will this be w’in ceiling of		defence expre?  Cdn’t accept it as permanent addition.

H.W.	Hope to satisfy Ty. tht. it can be carried w’in existing total.

S.Ll.	Need full detail be included in Bill?

H.W.	A month in which to finalise it.

			Approved in principle.
			Details to be discussed with M/D., W.O., M/L. and Ty.
						[Exit  J.P.

	3.	Methane Gas.		[Enter  R.W.

R.A.B.	a)  Algeria:  money will be spent here on installns which cd. use
		supplies from Nigeria if Algerian source dried up.
	b)  If this denied they wd. import butane – at least as costly in 
		f. exchange.  To ban imports on all gases wd. be inconsistent
		with policy on natd industries.

P.M.	Butane wd. at least come from Br. companies.
	Believe they will lose much money over this.
		R.W. to break it to Ld. Robens.
		Any need for Parliamentary statement?

R.W.	Much interest.  Want oral, to give room for explann.  Will discuss
		with Leader H/C.
						[Enter  B.C.
	4.	Coal:  Price Policy.

R.W.	First:  ques. of principle:  shd. N.C.B. be free to vary differentials
		in prices in various parts of country.
	Second:  if so, shd. increased costs be covered by genl. increases of
		price or variable regional increases?  Chairman is v. much
		against general increases – reasons given.  Main one:  frustrates
		attempts to increase efficiency.

H.B.	Some action needed.  Sc. Divn now losing more than total loss of
		N.C.B.  We are heading for subsidy – as for rlways. – and Party
		wd. not accept that.
	Increases in some areas wd. not breach any existing principle.
		But 15/= p. ton. wd. be heavy blow in Scotland.
		Can’t be in interests of economy to go on subsidising miners’
		wages at £400 p. head p.a.
	Policy on natd indies re prices announced as recently as April.
		Quoted from White Paper.
	As politician wd. not press for full 15/= from 1st Jan.  Sensible time
		to increase is summer.
	Proposal for increase of 6/= in N.W.  What about 6/= all round in the
		summer?
	But economic arguments support M/P. plan.

J.M.	69.000 to 64.000 drop in man-power in Sc. is planned.
		New proposal wd. mean another 20.000 jobs wd. disappear
		by 1965 – tho’ believed redundancy wd. be only 3.000 or so.
	Industry.  Increased cost for Colvilles wd. be £1.2 m. or £1 p.ton of
		finished steel.  Cement 4%.  Domestic 12% - 1/= p. wk
		for pensioners.
	Price differentials are mainly on quality.  Coal-field differentials
		are historic, but not directly related to costs.  Wage structure
		in national.  This is therefore fundamental change in policy
		followed by N.C.B.  v. hard to reconcile with our D.I. policy.
	Social investment – serious waste.

H.B.	Eventual waste of it wd. be even greater, if sitn left to drift.

R.M.	Shattering blow to D.I. effort in Scotland.  Wd prob. reverse all our
		progress on this.

M.	A year ago £60 m. increase in coal prices authorised.  In spite of this
		loss of £1 m. overall is now expected.
	Small island:  wrong to base price on costs of individual coal-field.
		Prefer to follow principle of level prices, subject to only small
		variatns.

I.M.	Share this view.
	Cab. decn to put new strip-mill in Scotland.  Linked with that efforts 
		to draw other industries to S.  All this wd. be stultified by
		decision not recommended.  And D.I. policy pursued for 20 yrs.

E.M.	But failure to follow M/P. line wd. equally stultify recent W. Paper
		on natd industries.

M.	For rlways. we removed burden of old debt.  We may have to do same
		for N.C.B.

R.W.	Nearly £100 m. accumulated deficit.  Even if we wrote if off, there wd.
		be similar problem in a few years – unless we adopted policy
		now advocated.

H.W.          x/	Wiser to close uneconomic pits, more rapidly.

R.W.	Then imported coal – even from England it wd. be more expensive.

J.H.	This discn causes me to change my view – into support of x/ as 
		alternative.  We have persuaded Rootes to equip new factory
		for coal.  Press on with x/ and with getting new firms into areas
		where pits are to close.

F.E.	Support M/P. plan.

R.A.B.	i) write off deficits  ii)…………..
	I myself see no way out w’out increased prices.  But more phasing
		shd. be made.

R.W.	Agreement betwn. N.C.B. &amp; Minister tht. he will consult on prices
		&amp; will not act inconsistently with Minister’s expd wish.  But
		since Wh. Paper Minister wd. have to make public statement 
		of his reasons in writing.

Hail.	If Sc. is not affluent, wrong to allow them to cling to uneconomic
		production of uneconomic coal.

J.B-C.	This wd. prob. tip scales in favour if increasing assistance rates if
		done this winter.

Ch.H.	Better to accelerate p’mme for closing high-priced pits.

R.W.	Present p’mme will reduce pits in Sc. to 55 by 1965.  Diff. to 
		accelerate it.  But only 4 m. of 17½ m. t. of coal in Scotl. is
		produced at profit.
	Imported Engl. coal wd. be £2 m. p.t. more.

D.E.	Must subsidise Sc. in some way in order to prevent drift of labour
		to E.  But subsidising Sc. miners at £400 p.a. is silly way of
		doing it.  Better to subsidise if necessary new indies to wh. he
		cd. move.
	Action which is indefensible economically on one thing makes it
		diff. to be sensible in any field.

P.M.	Don’t believe you can run natd industry on same lines as private
		industry.
	There are differences already in prices between one area or another.

R.W.	Realistic closing of pits cd. not go far enough to cure the financial
		problem.

S.Ll.	Solution:  do a bit more of more things.  Don’t try to do it all by
		price – or so suddenly.

E.H.	Why shd. Scots pay less for coal when it costs more to produce it
		there?  Support S.Ll.’s view tht. combination of methods is
		preferable.

P.T.             1)	Consider posn of N.C.B., who want to compete where they can.  If we
force him to general increase, he is hampered all across the board.
                    2)	Don’t exaggerate effect of this on d.i. policy in Sc.

R.W.	Genl. increase will drive people to oil in England but delay the
		conversion to oil in Sc.

H.	Cd there be some general &amp; some local increase?

M.	He can’t plead principle when he made a genl. increase last year?

P.M.	Cd we work for package deal.  a) accept differential prices for regions
		b) increase Sc. coal by 5/=  c) but the other 10/= by other means
		&amp; phase it out (?)  d) special concession to those who can’t use
		hydro-electric power or oil.    [add increased pit closure.]

J.M.	a) is not really reconcilable with national wage structure.

S.Ll.	What view wd. T.U.C. take?

R.W.	There is also N. West &amp; anthracite problem.

		Agreed:	R.W. and H.B. to look at this again, with J.M. 
				    &amp; Mills in light of discussion.

J.M.	Cd we include ascertaining T.U.C. view on breaking
		down national wage structure.
						[Exit  R.W., P.T.

	5.	National Insurance:  Family Allowances for Apprentices.

J.B-C.	Economy proposal – wd. save over £1 m. – inevitably controversial.
	Explained proposal.
	T.U.’s wd. oppose this.  But socially it is justifiable.
	Suggn of taking power only wdn’t get us out of difficulty – for we shd.
		have to disclose the figure in debate on the Bill.  And to go down
		by stages wd. involve much adm. diffy and Parly controversial on
		each occasion.
	Wd it be disincentive to apprenticeship?  Only 8/= difference.
		N.A. scale for child of this age is only 32/=.

J.H.	Shortage of skilled labour.  Campaign for more apprentices.  This wd.
		frustrate those efforts.
	Is this socially justifiable.  Income tax allowances are given for these
		children.  They are foregoing large wages to be apprentices.

H.B.	Gap over apprenticeship is not enough openings offered by employers
		not shortage of applicants.
	How can we expect to get £100 m. savings if we reject this sort of
		plan?
	Figure of 87/6. – new factor introduced by Comms. not us – is not
		justifiable.

E.M.	B.T.C. have 8.000 apprentices &amp; don’t think this wd. affect them.

Hail.	Support J.H.

S.Ll.	Our figure, if we fixed it, wd. be 40/=.

H.B.	Nothing in I.T. point:  this wd. bring them into line .  £100 for I.T.

J.B-C.	Same amount of row even if a higher figure were proposed.

			Memo. approved.		[Exit  J.B-C.

	6.	Shipping:  Nuclear Propulsion.

P.M.	Announce in reply to P.Q. – written Answer.

S.Ll.	Don’t let it be assumed tht. this commits us to prototype.

C.S.	Para. 2. nuclear re-actor not propulsion.  “No re-actor system
		for marine purposes offers …….”

	7.	Wages Policy.

S.Ll.	We are hanging on.
	But to avoid Jan. 1. assumption as end of pause, we need some
		other dates.

J.H.	Last of pre-announcement commitments are related to Jan. 1.
		Now faced with awards w’out prior commitment:  &amp; propose 
		to relate these to April 2.

			Approved.

8.	Euston Station:  Doric Arch.

P.M.	Have now received influential deputation.  We shall be called
		Philistines.

Hail.	Bogus black Parthenon.

			Earlier decision confirmed.
</content>
</cab>