<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/20/0 images: 15-15</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 64 (61)					21stNovember, 1961

	1.	Coal.			[Enter R.W., M.R.

P.M.	Long-term:  re-organisation of industry.

R.W.	Suggest I shd. first discuss with Rubens &amp; then take guidance from E.P.C. or ad hoc Cttee.

H.B.	Under aegis of E.P.C. – prs. a Sub-Cttee:  after Ty. has worked with M/Power on the report of accountants.

P.M.	Let me have proposals on method of handling this.

	Short-term:  price increases.

R.W.	Issue now is betwn. selective increases and general increase.  Group of Ministers were divided on this ques. of principle.  If Cab. decide in favour of selective I have a modified schedule which N.C.B. cd. be persuaded to accept.

H.B.	History:  Cab. 2 yrs. ago rejected plan for higher prices in Scotl. &amp; lower in Midlands:  E.P.C. in 1960 again rejected proposal for higher Sc. prices.
We now see prospect of v. grave financial deficiency for N.C.B.  They are ready to meet it, but believe differential price increases are an essential part of their armoury to deal with it.
	Some Ministers wd., however, prefer to over-ride views of N.C.B. and go for genl. increase. I doubt if this wd. be in long-term interests of industry.  Each region protected by transport costs:  unremunerative to send coal to other regions: differential regional price will help to damp regional demand &amp; encourage closure of high-cost pits.  A uniform increase will mean selling less coal from low-cost pots (because competition of oil) and more than we need of high-cost coal.

J.M.	See this argument.  But efforts to make Sc. industry more efficient &amp; competitive will be frustrated by this.  More worried by this than by house-coal (wh. on Annex B. proposals wd. be tolerable).
Effect on steel can’t be assessed w’out discn with Colvilles.  Admit tht. effect on other industry wd. be more psychological than real.
	This might precipitate demand for review of Scotland’s future as whole.
	Colvilles will seek leave to import U.S. coal.

H.B.	Remedy for this is to press N.C.B. to temper wind to Sc. steel industry.

M.	Believe N.C.B. shd. continue policy of m’taining parity of pit-head price throughout country.  If it is to be broken, this plan is best that can be devised.

R.W.	Not true tht. pit-head prices have bn. uniform till now.  Coal-field adjustments have always bn. made to prevent coal from coming in from other regions.

F.E.	Now is time to abandon rigid principle.  Prices of delivered coal obscure the principle anyway.

I.M.	Support principle – mainly because I think we shd. not be harsh on Scotland.
If Cab. decn goes the other way, Sc. increase must be p’poned till May.

H.B.	Decn has not bn. taken on the principle in the past – only love for Scotland.
	Subsidy to inefficient pits is not the way to help Scotland.  Less wasteful to subsidise the right kind of industry to move to Scotland when labour is available.
	A general price increase wd. tend to keep less efficient pits going.

E.M.	Can’t deny Rubens what he needs – unless we have convincing reasons.
Support selection increases.

R.A.B.	So do I.  (no reason given).

P.M.	We directed steel industry to Scotland:  we shd. see tht. it gets its coal at reasonable rate.  Must get it from Scotland.  N.C.B. shd. make a special price for Colvilles.
	Other industries?

J.M.	New ones mainly rely on electricity.

D.E.	N.C.B. charged to run industry w’out subsidy, at maximum output.
He is bound to follow selective prices, for this is his only means of exploiting the “closed” markets near the coal-fields.  If we don’t allow him to do this, he must be free to ask for subsidy or to see competn of oil win.  On economics the case made by H.B. is unanswerable.

Hail.	In present circs. surely we shd. follow the better economic course.
Let us help Scotland certainly, but in the right way.

S.Ll.	Support R.W.  This is step in right direction – it may lead to differentials in wage structure. 

I.M.	You will never achieve that.
J.H.	I now favour modified plan for selective increases.
But we shd. know a) will this slow down closing pits.
			                     b) shall we let Colvilles import U.S. coal?

H.B.	a) No:  contrary.  b) Tell N.C.B. to make special deal for Colvilles.

S.Ll.	Timing?  

R.W.	Increases wd. have to be put to Industrial Consumers Council in early Dec.  I think they shd. go also to Domestic Council at same time.  I wd. hope to get house prices increased not until May.  Also (in reply to I.M.) I ought to make announcement on Wed. before my Borrowing Bill comes on for 2nd Rdg.

R.W.	N.C.B. will be sensitive to Colvilles because will fear request for U.S. imports.

P.T.	Impossible for Govt. to defend insistence on general price increase:
means requiring him to charge more for coal from efficient pits etc.

E.M.	In 5/10 yrs. balance will tilt strongly in favour of oil because pipelines.

P.M.	General feeling of Cab. in favour of Minister’s modified plan, subject to an assurance that some means will be found to temper the wind to [Colville’s] steel industry in Scotland.

R.W.	Easier if I refrained from insistg. on p’ponement of increase in “other large coal” in Sc. and N.W.  This wd. help me over Colville’s.

			Agreed.

	2.	Congo.

H.	Circulated draft U.N. resoln.  First para. mght. be read as encouraging U.N. forces to go in with Adoula to remove mercenaries from Katanga.
I’m nervous of this.

Hail.	Why shd. U.N. use force to remove T.’s political advisers?

H.	In resoln of 21/2 we deprecated presence of these advisers = tho’ force then limited to preservation of law &amp; order.

Hail.	The moral posn of U.N. in Congo will be destroyed by this.

H.	U.N. case:  so long as 60/70 people using airplanes…

I.M.	Wd prefer to abstain on these 2 paras.

M.R.	Agree.  Might be better to abstain on whole resoln.

H.	We shd. then be alone, with French

H.	Vote for resoln:  abstain on these 2 paras.
	This is supported by U.S. – with Liberia or U.A.R.

P.M.	If we abstained on whole resoln, we shd. be w’drawing fr. whole opern.
We have gt. interest in stability of Congo.  Cdn’t be right to dis-interest ourselves in its future.
	Party opinion cd. be satisfied by abstaining on these 2 paras.

Ch.H.	Is there same objn to 2nd para?

H.	But it wd. involve bombing aircraft on the ground.

R.A.B.	Wd be almost as unpopular with Party.

Hail.	Wd discuss aerial warfare in support of central Govt. of Congo.

H.B.	More difficult to defend abstaining on 2nd para.

P.M.	Can argue tht. both paras. give too heavy a responsibility to Secretariat.
Believe better approach is by conciliatory methods.  We still prefer approach followed h’to.

	3.	Nuclear Tests.

H.	R. have accepted our invitn to resume Geneva Conference.

	4.	O.E.C.D.

S.Ll.	Turned out well.  Target not v. unrealistic.
</content>
</cab>