<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/20/0 images: 44-44</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 18(62).					1st March, 1962.

	1.	Parliament.		[Enter  M.R.

I.M.	Business for next week.
		Budget:  Mon. 9/4.
					[Enter  P.M.G.
	2.	Post Office:  Giro System.

P.M.G.	D/E. give views of Joint Stock Banks, who believe their facilities 
		meet public demand.  I don’t believe that – nor even does B/E.
		There are 22 m. people with P.O. a/cs and only 7 m. with 
		bank accounts.  Publn wd. stir Banks up.

H.B.	Radcliffe Cttee said, unless Banks move, case for considering 
		P.O. Giro.  Did we take this recommn seriously?

R.A.B.	I’m against the system but in favour of publishing W. Paper to show
		we did act on R. recommn.

I.M.	Publn wd. lead to debate etc., &amp; then lead us into controversy with
		Banks.

H.B.	Then publish but with statement tht. we don’t intend to act unless the
		Banks fail to meet the need.  The Banks shd. do it, and need
		prodding.

F.E.             x/	Cd we not have a general paper discussing all the means of extending
		credit transfer, incldg. P.O. Giro.

E.H.	Cd debate it on Private Member’s day.

H.B.	And with my foreword you wd. not need to state a Govt. view.

P.M.	Favour x/.  Offls. to consider.  No publn until after 
			Easter.
					[Exit  P.M.G.
	3.	Nuclear Tests.

P.M.	Exchange of tells. with Mr K.
	Ques. of substance:  are these tests justifiable w’in terms of our 
		statements?
		After discussion with experts last night, I concluded they were.

H.W.	I agree.  If the doubt exists re R. anti-missile progress, we can’t risk
		not going on.  Western duty to go forward.  It is clear enough that
		R. are putting great effort into this.
	We can make a clear political case.  More difficult to sustain technical
		argument.

P.M.	On timing.  Can’t wait for agreement at Conference.  Awkward to do
		it while Confn is sitting.  Mr K. therefore concludes better to 
		announce it before Conference begins.

Hail.	Strong arguments for early statement.  But why need explosion be
		timed as early as April.

H.W.	Turns on prepns already standing by.  Task force is sea-borne:  can’t
		be poised indefinitely.

E.H.	8 months since R. tests:  and they continue underground.  Mr K. is
		justified.

Hail.	Still, will be represented as ultimatum.

H.W.	Even if R. are continuing to test?

Ch.H.	Will be seen as danger to success of conference.

D.S.	If you have to name a date:  bound therefore to have element of 
		ultimatum.  Does Mr K. really need to give a date.

S.Ll.	Unless you give R. some definite limit, you will get nothing from
		them.

H.	I agree.  They could conclude an agreement in 2 or 3 weeks, if they
		wished.

P.M.	Ask him to use language of appeal rather than of threat.

			Issue notice on Saty making it plain tht. it was done
				after consultn with us.
			Statement in H/C. by P.M. on Monday.  Cd be discussed
				in debate on Defence White Paper.
						[Exit  P.M., H.

	4.	Education:  Universities.

R.A.B.	Expansion:  agreed with Ty.
	Salaries:  majority favoured 3% from ¼ - L.P. dissenting.
		Hard but right in view of incomes policy.
		Cd be assumed tht. Univ. teachers wd. understand reasons for
			Govt. policy.

H.B.	8 or 9% wd. be justified &amp; wrong to treat this end of teaching so
		differently from others in teaching.  But, nationally, it wd. be
		fatal to incomes policy to give such an award in an area wholly
		w’in Govt. control.  Commend therefore 3% with promise of
		review in few years’ time.  Recognise it will be said this will
		cripple expansion p’mme.
	U.G.C. are unhappy but realise Govt’s diffies.  Responsible Univ.
		re-action will prob. be tht. it’s open ques. wtr. they will get
		teachers to match expansion.

Hail.	Calamitous.
	Our adminve apparatus depends on output of graduates, which is far
		too low.  We are committed to 30% increase of nos. – 40% in
		science &amp; 60% in technology.  Can’t hope to get recruitment
		needed on this basis.
	Element of pre-pause oblign.  This is corollary of teachers’ award.
	Cab. Cttee influenced by effect on workers – rlways., nurses etc.

J.H.	i)	Universities are getting their share of rare birds – scientists
			etc., because people want those jobs, irrespective of
			somewhat lower pay.
	ii)	Private enterprise re-action wd. be v. strong if we departed 
			from our policy in this sector w’in our control.

D.E.	Doubt if we shall man the expansion – not because 	[Exit  D.S., C.S.
		salaries but because inadequate no. of post-graduate
		opportunities.
	No means of telling what salary increase wd. be decisive.
	Univ. re-action:  I’m told they are most concerned about non-staff
		costs per student.  That wd. help to soften 3% for teachers.
		They will prob. hold special mtg. to re-consider expansion
		p’mme.

S.Ll.	Stress readiness to review next year.

M.	Unjust but inescapable.

Hail.	I submit, but without agreeing.
</content>
</cab>