<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/20/0 images: 54-54</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C. 28 (62)					17th April, 1962

	1.	Foreign Affairs.		[Enter M.R.

a)	Disarmament.

E.H.	U.S. draft treaty now tabled.  Neutrals plan for internatl cttee of scientists to supervise verification.  Doesn’t meet U.S./U.K. view.

D.S.	Useful if R. turn it down.  Better to avoid saying it doesn’t meet us.

H.W.	Not so easy.  R. cd. expose technical differences between us &amp; Americans.

b)	Germany:  Berlin.

E.H.	Rusk saw Amb. y’day in W’ton.  Cdn’t present any document because of diffies with Fr. &amp; G.  Now intended to discuss at Athens.

c)	Congo.

E.H.	U.S. Amb. has put a plan to T. &amp; A. – compromises.  They will examine it.

	2.	E.E.C. Meeting at W.E.U.

E.H.	My statement  well received by Six.  They are now considering how we cd. be associated with their discussion of the political problem.

Hail.	The leaks are awkward.  Cd we avoid this by disclosing text in advance?

E.H.	V. awkward.  This is first leak from W.E.U.
	Time-table for negotiations.  Ministers likely to come to grips by end/May.
Hope we can finish by end/July – or early August.

D.E.	Anti-C.M. Tories are getting ahead.  Shd Ministers speak more strongly on basis tht. we must go in if we can get the terms?

E.H.	Effect on negotiations:  varies:  but steady flow of strong speeches wd. help me now.

H.B.	Cd we have confidential guidance on new points to make.

J.M.	Esp. on Fouchet.
E.H.	Can give factual informn on Fouchet.  We have refrained from comment.
But the broad points made in my speech cd. be used by Ministers.

	3.	Parliament.

I.M.	Business for week following end of Recess.

	4.	Federation of Rhodesia.

R.A.B.	No statement needed before Easter.  Can wait until debate 8/5.
I will then go there for 2 wks:  can’t deal with R.W. by telegram.
	Composite approach was at first well received by R.W. – and I believe he will accept it in due course.  But his Ministers won’t agree because don’t want any statement by me during Fed. election:  not unreasonable &amp; I accept that posn.
	Fed. Govt. are worried about Nyasaland.  But we can’t keep it in existg. Fedn by force.  Propose therefore to have enquiry:  viability of Territory &amp; future form of association with the other territories.
Banda has accepted that.
	Trying to persuade R.W. tht. we must have parallel enquiry in N. &amp; S. Rhodesia.

R.M.	Satisfactory tht. Banda has accepted this &amp; refrained from coming to Ldn.

R.A.B.	Have reported accordingly to P.M., who is satisfied.
				[Enter C., J.P., J.A., E.P.    

	5.	Incomes Policy:  Doctors &amp; Dentists in Forces.

H.W.	Have seen Secy. B.M.A.  Agreed formula on lead.  Promised not to use it later to secure increases for N.H.S. doctors.

E.P.	Presentation – to avoid repercussions on N.H.S. salaries.
Must not be percentage – either of salary or of lead.
	Wish to keep in touch with Service Dpts. on numbers.

H.B.	More work has bn. done.  This plan is acceptable to me.
M/D. has shown there is rather more than £1/2m. lift from Grigg &amp; I am ready to accept £575.000.
	Serious emergency threatens which we must meet.

S.Ll.	Present as use of money accrued under Grigg formula.
Present also a unique – inapplicable, e.g. to Prison doctors.

J.H.	Wd have preferred to see this presented as bounty.

H.W.	Can’t do that.  But can say extra money will be paid as a lead over N.H.S. salaries as recommended by B.M.A.

I.M.	Repercussion on nurses.  Also:  must be a precedent.

H.W.	Criticism of Forces pay award was tht. it was mean.  Show that people do regard service pay as different.
	Not sure tht. even this is enough to get recruits needed.

S.Ll.	Present as new situation resulting from end/N.Service.

M.	Support J.H.  Cd it not be called a supplement?

H.W.	Cd do that.

Ch.H.	Basic difficulty:  work in R.A.M.C. is mainly administrative and non-clinical. That is real reason – not the money.

J.P.	We are re-organising also – areas vice units:  has administrative work.

R.A.B.	Use of N.H.S.?

J.P.	Studying this:  but inconsistent with giving R.A.M.C. a more interesting job.

R.A.B.	This will be noticed &amp; percentages will be worked out.  But stress Grigg money:  use “supplement”:  emphasise end of  N.S.
		         	                                               [Exit Service Ministers &amp; E.P.

	6.	Anglo-Portuguese Alliance.

E.H.	As in memo.  Salazar has said he is examining Treaty.  H. intends therefore to spk. to P. For. Minister at Athens mtg.  Para. 6.

J.A.	Staging at Sal. Cape Verde is vital to us.  Overlying Angola is also important.
	Wd like to discuss with F.O. possibility of a reciprocal agreement with them on staging &amp; over-flying. – in substitution for Treaty.

H.W.	Don’t mind so long as we exclude El Adem

Ch.H.	Is it wise to raise this?

D.E.	I doubt it:  this is a dying regime.  Goa was humiliating to P. Army, on whom S relies.  Shd we do better with successor Govt.  Unless it’s urgent, better to wait.
	Br. community in P. are v. Lièn with regime.  They wd. think we had let them down.

Hail.	P. will have social revolution in P. itself. That is their real problem.  An approach based on their Colonial position misses the real point.

P.T.	We can live with this for longer.

E.H.	Argument for action is tht. our relations with P. generally are v. Unsatisfy &amp; it’s embarrassing for us if we make no effort to improve them.

J.A.	Put it on basis, not of difference of our Colonial policy, but on future possibility of guaranteeing support when we relinquish sovereignty over Rhodesia, Singapore, etc.

S.Ll.	Wise for the For. Secy. himself to get involved?  Better to do it thro’ Ambassador?
	Doubtful about 2nd half of para. 6.

E.H.	At Athens talk by H. wd. be less committed than approach thro’ Ambassador.
			Agreed.  (i)         J.A. &amp; F.O. to explore possibilities of 
                                    reciprocal agreement.
(ii)	Authorise H. to have tentative talks.
(iii)	Warn him there are misgivings over getting too deep into this.

			(ii) to be done at Athens mtg of N.A. Council.
					[Exit J.A.
	7.	M/East Kuwait.

H.W.	Communications with Ldn. are liable to interruption.
	Flying-time for Iraq to Kuwait is virtually nil.
	Need therefore to authorise C-in-C to take out airfield, in event of aggression, if commn with Ldn. are broken.

E.H.	A large authy to delegate to mil. commander.
	We shd. need to be able to show tht. Iraq attacked before we acted.  Risk of appearing to have offered provocation.
		Awkward in U.N.
	This point shd. be brought out in instructions.
H.W.	During Kuwait operns communication with Ldn. was broken for all of one night.
	But cd. re-draft to meet some of E.H.’s point.

D.S.	Are we sure we can deal with Iraq attack.

H.W.	Yes:  but only if we can fly re-enforcements in.

			Agreed:  M/D to revise directive with F. O. in light of the
			                Cabinet’s discussion.
</content>
</cab>