<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/172/0 images: 136-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CIRCULATED TO THE CABINET.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.] ^ ^WESTERN EUROPE. ^                    , \ &apos; &apos; [February 20, 1925.]- ........-.....  ir if(c p   103 ^ )*i --&quot; &quot;CONFIDENTIAL        V^ %iL       ^VV Section 1.&quot;    &apos;    &apos;     &apos; ^TJHALLJ^^[C 2201/459/18] No. 1.BRITISH POLICY CONSIDERED IN RELATION TO THE EUROPEAN SITUATION.Memorandum by Mr. Harold Nicolson, of the Foreign Office ; prepared in pursuance of Directions from the Secretary of State.(February 20, 1925.)I.-General Conditions of Insecurity in Europe.(1.) Russia.EUROPE to-day is divided into three main elements, namely, the victors, the vanquished and Russia. The Russian problem, that incessant, though shapeless menace, can be stated only as a problem; it is impossible as yet to forecast what effect the development of Russia will have on the future stability of Europe. It is true, on the one. hand, that the feeling of uncertainty which is sapping the health of Western Europe is caused to no small extent by the disappearance of Russia-as a Power accountable in the European concert. On the other hand, the Russian problem is for the moment Asiatic rather than European; to-morrow Russia may again figure decisively in the balance of continental power; but to-day she hangs as a storm-cloud upon the Eastern horizon of Europe impending, imponderable, but, for the present, detached. Russia is not therefore in any sense a factor of stability; she is indeed the most menacing of all our uncertainties; and it must thus be in spite of Russia, perhaps even because of Russia, that a policy of security must be framed.(2.) The Minor ex-Enemies.The condition of Central and Western Europe, though scarcely less uncertain, is at least more definable. The main psychological factors in every case are almost the same. All our late enemies continue full of resentment at what they have lost; all our late Allies are fearful of losing what they have won. OUe-half of Europe is dangerously angry; the other half is dangerously afraid. The friction between these inflamed emotions is incessant, and acts as some septic irritant, poisoning the wounds which are yet unhealed. Fear begets provocation, armaments, secret alliances, ill-treatment of minorities; these in their turn beget a greater hatred and stimulate a desire for revenge, whereby fear is intensified, and its consequences are enhanced. The vicious circle is thus established.This action and counter-action of revenge and fear are visible to-day in every continental country, though their political, as distinct from their psychological, effect varies in essential proportions. The smaller ex-enemies, Austria, Hungary and Bulgaria, are so completely surrounded and overpowered by their neighbours that, for them, revenge has become a sullen subjective emotion rather than an objective political hope. In Austria, this feeling takes the form of a desire to fuse with Germany. Hungary and Bulgaria are recalcitrant, but for the moment overawed. If Turkey were again to have a European policy, her attitude might not be dissimilar. While, therefore, our minor ex-enemies are not strong enough to create a disturbance by themselves, yet they are ready to foment the causes of insecurity and to profit by any disturbance which may elsewhere ensue.(3.) The Attitude of Germany.Although Germany is at present quite incapable of undertaking aggressive action, it is certain that with her great military and chemical potentialities she will sooner or later again become a powerful military factor.   For the moment, it2698   [12729] b
may well foe true that the more intelligent German desires peace; he feels that Germany must first re-establish her economic and financial position; he realises that she can only do so in circumstances of comparative stability, and that such stability implies, in a broad sense, the execution of the Dawes scheme and even of the Treaty of Versailles.On the other hand, he is aware that one day Germany will again be strong. There are but few Germans who seriously hope to exert this strength, when reacquired, against the British Empire; it may be doubted, even whether the majority of Germans desire to-day a war of revenge against France; but it may be confidently asserted that so soon as Germany recovers, there will be a steady movement towards the righting of what are, for a German, the two most objectionable provisions of the Peace Settlement, namely, the Polish corridor and the partition of Silesia. These two;i questions are of such importance that they merit more substantial treatment  (1.) The Polish Corridor.By the Treaty of Versailles, not only was Poland restored to independence, but she was also, at the expense of Germany, given access to the sea and the use of the port of Danzig. The consequent readjustment of Germany&apos;s frontiers necessitated the complete severance of East Prussia from the rest of the German Empire by a narrow strip of territory known as the Polish corridor. A special regime was established in Danzig, which was declared a free city under the protection of the League of Nations. In this city, originally a German town-colony planted on conquered Polish soil, and even now having a population 94 per cent. German, special rights were secured to Poland, including control of foreign affairs, customs and external railway communications, and the port was placed under separate administration ensuring facilities for Polish trade and shipping.(2.) Upper Silesia.In Upper Silesia, after a plebiscite held amid turmoil and uproar, Poland, who polled 40 per cent., of the total votes, eventually received by a decision of the League of Nations a considerable tract of territory containing at least 80 per cent, of the developed and 95 per cent, of the undeveloped mineral wealth of Silesia and large enclaves inhabited by clear German majorities.There is obviously a danger that a nation of over 60 millions will not permanently acquiesce in being thus sundered from the province which was the cradle of the Prussian State, or in being deprived of those mineral resources on which the national prosperity was largely based.-(4.) The A attitude of France.France is afraid of Germany because  (1.) She is Germany&apos;s neighbour.(2.) She has within living memory been twice invaded by Germany.(3.) The birth-rate in France is declining. At present the population numbers 39^ millions. It is estimated that by 1940 it will have declined to 35 millions; by 1950 to 31 millions; by 1965 to 25 millions.(4.) The birth-rate in Germany is increasing. In 1922 the German population numbered 61^ millions.   In 1965 it may well number 80 millions.These circumstances have inevitably and justifiably led the French to place their own security above all other considerations. It may be well at this stage to summarise the history of the security question as dealt with since the armistice: (1.) Marshal Foch, having defeated Germany, insisted that if there was to be any security for France or peace for Europe, the German frontier must cease at the Rhine. That, he stated, was the only effective guarantee of French security. France did not want to annex the territory between herself and the Rhine : all she wished was that this territory should be detached from Germany proper, and that the Rhine should thus serve as an abiding barrier between France and her hereditary enemy.
(2.) This, the only safeguard, which would really have allayed French aprre-apprehensions, was refused them by their Western Allies. , In return,&apos; the French were given the following compensations :-(a.) A Treaty of Guarantee, under which Great Britain and America pledged themselves, in the event of any unprovoked aggression on the part of Germany, to come immediately to France-&apos;s assistance,(&amp;.) The occupation, for an extended period, of the Rhineland.(c.) The assurance, under articles 42 and 43, that any violation of the provisions for the demilitarisation of the Rhineland would be considered an act of war.(d.) The disarmament of Germany under the supervision of an Allied Commission.(3.) As Marshal Foch pointed out at the time, safeguards (b) and (d) above were but provisional in duration, whereas safeguard (c) was uncertain in effect. The Anglo-American guarantee, on the other hand, might well have given France a sense of security had it ever been put into effect. As is well known, however, it was rejected by the United States and, there-fore, lapsed altogether.^4.) The French were thus left under the impression that not only had they been refused the Rhine barrier, but that they had also been deprived of the only serious compensation offered to them in return for the abandonment of this ; their main desideratum. They determined, therefore, to create subsidiary safeguards to take the place of those refused them by their Western Allies.(5.) The first of these expedients was to supplement the - deficiency of French man-power by enlisting large numbers of coloured troops. At present 25 per cent, of the French army is composed of natives of North Africa and the French colonies, of whom some 60,000 are in France and on the Rhine to-day.(6.) The second expedient was the policy known as the &quot; policy of the Little Entente,&quot;^ under which the new States to the east of Germany were to be welded into a compact block, united to each other, and connected to France by a complicated system of alliances, subsidies and military missions. The complexity of this artificial connexus is best shown by the memorandum and diagram attached to this paper.(7.) The policy of the Little Entente, while securing the encirclement of Germany, and while redressing to some extent the balance of man-power, was none the less a policy of desperation. The solidarity of the Little Entente was not in itself very dependable; the exigencies of these satellites were liable to constitute a serious and increasing drain on French resources; and the precarious position of Poland and Roumania in relation not to Germany only, but also to Russia, constituted an element not of security but of added apprehension.(8.) It may well be that the realisation of this inherent instability of the Little Entente was what inspired the French Government to press upon the Fifth Assembly of the League of Nations the acceptance of the Protocol for the Pacific Settlement of International Disputes. They hoped by this means to fuse their specific responsibilities into more general responsibilities assumed under the aegis of the League of Nations. They now realise that it is most unlikely that the Geneva Protocol will, in its present form, be accepted either by His Majesty&apos;s Government or by the Governments of the Dominions.(9.) There are indications, therefore, that French public opinion is now reverting to the original thesis of Marshal Foch, and that1 it will be increasingly difficult for any French Government to evacuate the Rhineland unless and until they receive some compensating guarantee for the future security of France.(5.) The League of Nations.How far can the League be counted on to control a situation of such uncertainty ? As a clearing-house for international disputes, the League of Nations is a wholly admirable institution.  In many minor questions it has already played a most useful
part,,but at present, and probably for many years, it will be unsafe to count upon its authority being sufficient to restrain a Great Power in any case in which that Power &amp; considers its vital interests to be at stake. The time may come when the League will be able to deal not merely with incidental disputes, but even with more permanent and deep-seated rivalries. It is vain to deny, however, that this stage has not yet been reached, or to hide the fact that a sense of security cannot, in such vital matters, to-day emanate from Geneva,II. Conclusions regarding European Insecurity.The following conclusions may be drawn from the above analysis : (1.) The future development of Russia is still incalculable; Europe must work out her own security in spite of Russia.(2.) The&apos; minor ex-enemies are not likely by themselves to cause serious trouble, II since the lesser treaties are guaranteed by a superiority of force. The Treaty of Versailles possesses no such safeguard, since the preponderance of whatever man-power would be certainly and unhesitatingly available tells against, and not in favour of, the status quo.(3.) Germany will sooner or later recover. She will certainly desire to revise the Polish clauses of the Treaty of Versailles. If France were isolated, and British neutrality to be assured, she might also endeavour to attack France. -(4.) Unless France can be secured against this menace, she will be driven to expedients which in the end will only provoke the German revenge of which she stands in terror. ^Ill-British Interests.In a situation of such incertitude, the only sound line of British policy is the path of British interests. The road is too dark for any altruism or digression; it is our own security which must remain the sole consideration. What, then, are the essential conditions of the security of the British Empire ?Before answering such a question, it will be well to limit the scope of enquiry by the establishment of three axioms, namely :  (1.) That the policy known as &quot; splendid isolation &quot; is not to-day a practicable policy. For America, powerful and aloof, such a course is still, perhaps, a possibility. For the British Empire no such escape is feasible. History and economics show that isolation in present conditions spells danger, vulnerability and impotence. Geography and aeronautics show that isolation is not in our case a scientific fact.(2.) That, conversely, it would be unsound for the Governments of the Empire to commit Great Britain and the Dominions to responsibilities which are not direct necessities of Imperial defence, and of which the people of the Empire would not approve. No promise must be given which public opinion in Great Britain and the Dominions would not, in the last resort, be prepared to execute.(3.) If we are to contribute to general security, we must first establish certainty and conviction. It is far better to give restricted promises which Europe realises will inevitably be executed, than to enter into wide commitments, the ultimate execution of which would always allow of doubt. In order-to carry such conviction we must base our policy, not on possible tendencies, but on generally recognisable facts. We must be direct,, simple and explicit.What, therefore, in their simplest expression, are the needs of Imperial Defence T They may perhaps be summarised under three heads, namely : (1.) The defence of the individual Dominions.(2!) The defence of the sea communications between Great Britain and the-individual Dominions. (3.) The defence of Great Britain itself, being the heart of the Empire.
Nos. (1) and (2) are generally realised and are not for the present directly menaced. No. (3) is not perhaps so fully realised as an Imperial necessity, and is a matter which requires immediate consideration.IV. The Defence of Great Britain. The defence of Great Britain necessitates : (a.) That no single Power shall be in a position to occupy or to dominate all theChannel and the North Sea Ports. (&amp;.) That the hostility of France, Belgium, and, more incidentally, Holland,Germany and Denmark, who now possess these ports, or of any of thesecountries, and particularly the hostility of any combination of them, isto be avoided.(c.) That no third Power at war with France or Belgium should be allowed to invade those countries so as to threaten the status quo of the Channel Ports, or of such French and Belgian territory as would expose Great Britain to aerial invasion.(d.) That it is consequently a necessity of British, and therefore of Imperial, defence to reach some understanding with France and Belgium which may entail a guarantee on our part that these territories shall not fall into other hands.V. British interests as affecting European Security.So soon, therefore, as we realise that it is a necessity of Imperial defence to guarantee to France and Belgium the possession of their present territory, it becomes possible to show how this necessity, inevitable in any case, can constitute a very important contribution to European security. We have only to define publicly what we recognise privately as an essential condition of the future existence of the Empire, in order to secure the following very definite political advantages : &apos;(1.) Europe will then know where she stands. It is doubtful whether even in 1914 Germany would have risked the Great War had she known for certain that the British Empire would come to France&apos;s assistance. If she is now assured that by invading France she will inevitably incur the hostility of the British Empire, it is most unlikely that she will make any such endeavour.(2.) France will know that her ultimate security is regarded as of direct interest to the British Empire. The provocative policy inspired by her present uncertainty will tend to diminish; she will contemplate with less alarm the impending evacuation of the Rhineland; she will be less inclined to constitute the Little Entente as an armed camp to the east of Germany; she will be able to settle down to financial stabilisation and to a policy of debt-repayment.(3.) The smaller countries in Europe will learn that they must make peace with their neighbours, and that it is unnecessary to wait in uneasy expectancy for a second European conflagration.(4.) A nucleus of certainty, of stability, and of security will thereby be created. Such a nucleus can gradually be enlarged in expanding circles. There is nothing to prevent the eventual inclusion of Germany within the guarantees of security thus established.(5.) Although in the present mood of Europe it would be useless even to mention the revision of the peace treaties, yet if the concert of Europe can thus gradually be recreated, saner councils will prevail. It is conceivable, especially if Germany, with French goodwill, becomes a member of the League of Nations and obtains a permanent seat in the Council, that it may become possible eventually to revise by European agreement the dangerous conditions involved in the Silesian settlement and the Polish corridor.(6.) But until we can quieten France, no concert of Europe is possible, and we can only quieten France if we are in the position to speak to her with the authority of an Ally.[12729] c
-The essential interests of Imperial Defence are thus closely related to a policy of European security. The first hope of stability in Europe lies in a new entente between the British Empire and France.The form which such an entente might take is beyond the scope of the present memorandum.HAROLD NICOLSON.Foreign Office, February 20, 1925.//
ANNEX.MEMORANDUM.Political Treaties, Agreements, Alliances and Relations at present in force in Central and South-East Europe affecting the Question of Security.[The accompanying diagram only includes treaties or such other instruments, &amp;c, as are known in the Foreign Office to affect the security of the States concerned.]I.-THE LITTLE ENTENTE.RoiTMANIA, the S.C.S. KINGDOM AND czechoslovakia.THIS combination was built up mainly by the efforts of Dr. Benes, and the first stone was laid by the conclusion of the Czechoslovak-Jugoslav Agreement of August 1920 (Annex 1).The terms of this agreement were, shortly, that, in case of unprovoked attack by Hungary on one of the contracting parties, the other pledged itself to afford assistance in a manner to be agreed by the competent technical authorities. Neither party was to conclude an alliance with any third party without previous notification to the other. The agreement to remain in force for two years, after which time it could be denounced at six months&apos; notice.In April of the following year (1921) a similar agreement was made between Czechoslovakia and Roumania (Annex 2). This agreement was identical with the foregoing, except that it provides that the manner of affording assistance is to be defined &quot; in a military convention eventually to be concluded.&quot; An additional article also provides that &quot;in order to co-ordinate their efforts towards peace, the two Governments agree to concert together on questions of foreign policy affecting their relations with Hungary.&quot;This agreement was followed in June 1921 by an agreement between Roumania and the S.H.S. State in terms exactly similar to those of the Czech-Roumanian Agreement.The nucleus of the Little Entente was thus formed, and the next step was to pave the way for its extension to include other States. There followed the Polish-Czechoslovak (Annex 3), Polish-Roumanian (Annex 4) and Czechoslovak-Austrian (Annex 5) Agreements. These, although not on the same lines as the Little Entente Agreements, were more or less closely related to them, and constitute a first step towards bringing Poland and Austria within the system.Under the Czechoslovak-Polish Agreement of November 1921 each contracting party guarantees the territory of the other as defined in the Peace Treaties, In the event of one being attacked, the other will observe a benevolent neutrality, especially by assuring the free transit of war material. Czechoslovakia disinterests herself in Eastern Galicia and undertakes to suppress propaganda against Poland conducted in or from her territory. Poland assumes a similar obligation as regards Czecho-slovakia. Note is taken of the Czechoslovak-Roumanian-Jugoslav political, military and economic conventions, and of similar Polish-French-Roumanian conventions. Certain kinds of questions are to be referred to arbitration. No new agreement may be concluded with any other State which avould conflict with the present agreement. The agreement to remain in force for five years, but may be denounced after two years, at six months&apos; notice. An Annex provides for the amicable settlement of various local disputes.The Roumanian-Polish Agreement of March 1921 is of the nature of a &quot;defensive alliance against unprovoked attack from the East.&quot; The agreement remains in force for five years, but may be denounced after two 3rears at six months&apos; notice. Military questions are to be settled by agreement between military experts, and military action is to consist of mobilisation in case of attack from the East. Poland will assist against Magyar or Bulgarian aggression. Neither side may conclude a treaty with any third Power without previously notifying the other, and neither may conclude, without the prior consent of the other, any treaty with States2626   [12567] B
other than Allied and Associated States. Both parties will &quot;examine means for extending the alliance to other States,&quot; The agreement not to enter into force until the Treaty of Riga defining frontiers has been concluded. In return for diplomatic support on the question of Eastern Galicia, Poland promises to modify the frontiers of Bukovina and Galicia. .........By the Czechoslovak-Austrian Agreement of December 1921 (Treaty of Lana) (Annex 5) both parties undertake to put into execution all provisions of the Peace Treaties of Saint-Germain and Trianon. Each guarantees the territory of the other, arid tb ensure its inviolability undertakes to afford political and diplomatic assistance. Each undertakes, in the event of the Other being attacked, to observe neutrality. Both States undertake to protect each other mutually against all attempts to &apos;&apos; restore the former r6gime,&quot; and they promise to notify to each other formally the agreements made with other States. Arbitration of Certain questions is provided for. No agreement will be concluded which would conflict with the present agreement. The agreement to remain in force for five years, but may be denounced after three years at six months&apos; notice.A still further extension of the Little Entente may perhaps be said to have been effected by a somewhat vaguely worded exchange of notes between Dr. Benes and Count Sforza in February 1921 (Annex 6), At the time of the signing of the Rapallo Treaty in November i920, Italy and the S.H.S. State had signed a special agreement directed against the restoration of the Hapsburg, and taking note of the Czechoslovak-Jugoslav Agreement which had been framed (partly) for the same purpose. In the exchange of notes between Dr. Benes and Count Sforza, Czechoslovakia and Italy are mutually pledged to resist a Hapsburg restoration.The treaties which form the basis of the Little Entente were, as has been said, to remain, in force for two years as from the date of signature between the various States. In article 1 of the Protocol of the Pact of Rome (Annex 7) between Italy and the S.C.S Republic; reference is made to treaties still in force between the S.C.S. Kingdom and Czechoslovakia and Roumania of the 15th August, 1922, and the 7th July, 1928, respectively. The original pacts have therefore been renewed, A recent agreement, signed on the 7th May, 1923, at Prague between Roumania and the Czechoslovak Republic renewed the defensive convention between these two States in its present form for a further period of three years. Presumably, therefore, the treaties binding the Little Entente will be in force until 1926. As the ostensible purpose of the Little Entente was the formation of a defensive alliance against Hungary, it may be taken that the renewal of the original treaties indicates that Hungary&apos;s neighbours do not yet consider her as &quot;safe.&quot; During the last few months there has been much talk of the signature of A military convention between Roumania and the S.C.S. Kingdom aimed at Hungary (and possibly Bulgaria), and also of a Tripartite Military Convention between the three States forming the Little Entente. Further information is being sought on this subject, as the Foreign Office are not in possession of the actual texts of any such convention. It is certain, however, that conversations between the general &quot;staffs of the three countries have been proceeding ever since the signature of the Original treaties forming the Little Entente, but that the actual signature of such military conventions has been hanging fire. It would now appear that efforts are being made to&apos; put on paper military ententes parallel with the defensive treaties between the three States, either in the form of. a tripartite agreement or in the form of separate conventions. As far as is known at present, the provisions of the rumoured S.C.S-Roumanian military convention, Which may presumably be taken as typical of all such instruments; are : -(a.) No separate military agreements to be concluded by either of the three countries concerned.(6.) In the case of a RussO-Roumatiian conflict, the three countries will attackHungary if she declares war. (c.) Should Soviet Russia attack Roumania, Czechoslovakia and the S.C.S.Kingdom would each mobilise eleven divisions of infantry;   suchmobilisation to take place even in the event of Hungary remainingneutral.On account of the uncertain nature of such conventions, they are marked in the accompanying diagram with a dotted line. Hungary is said to be aware of these agreements and to be endeavouring to comte to a military understanding With Russia. No proof whatever is forthcoming as to the truth of such rumours, and the Foreign Office places no credence in them. &apos;        - . -    , ,
if:      9, -      -   -    -II.-FRENCH CONNECTION WITH LITTLE EAJTENTE. (A.) The Franco-Polish Treaty, February 19, 1921.During 1921 and 1922 no less than five conventions were signed between France and Poland : i 1. Political treaty (Annex 8). 2. An oil convention. 3. A commercial convention. 4. A convention on private prqperty. 5. A military convention.Although the present notes are only concerned with 1 and 5, it may be well to summarise 2, 3 and 4.The commercial convention assured economic advantages to Ppland by facilitating the export of her products to France, but on the whole it was more advantageous to France than to Poland. The duration of this treaty ended in the summer of 1924. Another agreement was substituted in its place, and is at present awaiting ratification.The oil convention was concerned with the exploitation of the Galician oil-fields. While it provided for an influx of capital to Poland, it was, like the commercial convention, more profitable to France than to Poland.The property agreement provided for the identical treatment of French property in Poland and Polish property in France.The political agreement is couched in the language usual to such instruments, and defines in a general way the conditions under which the two countries will work together to secure the defence of their territory as delimited by the Peace Treaties, and to maintain the status quo. It will be seen to be directed as much against Germany as against Soviet Russia. The important clause is No. 3, whereby both countries pledge themselves to act together in the case of unprovoked aggression from a third party. The existence of a military convention amplifying clause 3 was denied at the time by Lord Hardinge, who apparently was unable to obtain any information on the subject from the French Government. The Poles have, however, admitted its existence, but, while it is certain that such a military convention exists, it has proved impossible so far to obtain the text. From certain remarks of General Dupqnt (head of;the French Military Mission to Poland) to Sir W. Max Muller in February 1923, the convention appears to provide at least for-(a.) A French Military Mission to Poland. (b.) Credits for arms, munitions, &amp;c.In any case, the French Military Mission to Poland furnishes a sufficient guarantee that French military interests in Poland are supreme. There is close co-operation between the French and Polish military staffs, and visits have been exchanged between Marshal Foch and the Chief of the Polish General Staff.(B.) The Franco-Czechoslovak Treaty, January 25, 1924.   (Annex 9.)This treaty consists of a preamble and eight articles. The preamble contains a reference to mutual guarantees.between France and Czechoslovakia, but there is no reference to a pact of non-aggression and mutual defence. Articles 1 and 2 provide for mutual consultation over certain questions of security and concerted measures to be taken in the face of common danger. Articles 3, 4 and 5 specify these dangers, which are: any threat to Austria&apos;s independence by Anschluss or -otherwise, or Hapsburg or Hohenzollern restoration. Article 6 provides for the friendly settle-ment of questions in dispute by ordinary diplomatic methods or by reference to the Permanent Court of International Justice, &amp;c. Articles 7 and 8 stipulate that the two countries agree mutually to communicate their existing international obligations before entering on new ones, and to communicate the treaty to the League of Nations During the past year there have been many rumours of a separate military treaty between the two countries, and a copy of what purported to be such an agreement was handed to His Majesty V Embassy in Berlin. The War Office and the Foreign Office did not epnsidep that  he dqcuments were authentic, and both France and Czechoslovakia strenuously deny the existence of a separate military convention. On the other hand, the treaty itself appears to be so complete as ip render a separate [12567] &apos; b 2
iomilitary understanding unnecessary. A French Military Mission still remains the preponderant influence in the1 Czech army, and M. Benes has never denied that the Czech and French staffs have elaborated plans for a conceivable contingency. While M. Benes still aims at strengthening the power and influence of the League of Nations, he finds it profitable, especially while Germany and Russia remain outside the League, to rely on France.(C.) France and the S.C.S. Kingdom.In spite of rumours to the effect that a treaty was about to be signed between France and the S.C.S. Kingdom similar to that between France and Czechoslovakia, no such treaty has yet been signed. The Jugoslav Minister for Foreign Affairs has declared, however, that the friendly sentiments between the two countries render a definite treaty unnecessary. Meanwhile, France has provided the S.C.S. Government with military equipment.III.-ITALY AND THE LITTLE ENTENTE.(A.) The Italo-Jugoslav Treaty, January 27, 1924.   (The Pact oe Rome:Annex 7.)This instrument really replaces the Treaty of Rapallo (1920), which was merely a local agreement for the settlement of the Fiume question. It is described as a pact of friendship and co-operation, and consists of a preamble, five articles, an additional protocol and an unimportant additional agreement. The preamble states that the object of the treaty is the maintenance of the status qua, and article 7 makes it clear that what is meant is that both States agree to lend each other mutual support to enforce respect of the Treaties of Trianon, Saint-Germain and Neuilly. The important articles are numbers 2 and 3.  They provide for 1. The neutrality of each State if the other becomes the subject of unprovoked aggression.2. Reciprocal support, both political and diplomatic, should the security of either be endangered by incursions from a third party.3. Common action in the face of international complications affecting the common interests.The protocol provides for the presentation of the treaty to the League of Nations, and lays down that nothing therein shall contravene the alliance forming the basis of the Little Entente.It is strongly suspected that the provisions of this treaty are supplemented by some secret agreement regarding &quot; spheres of influence &quot; in the Adriatic and the Balkans.(B.) Italo-Czechoslovak Treaty, July 5, 1924.   (Annex 10.)This treaty was the outcome of the activities of M. Benes, who was anxious to draw up an agreement with Italy which would be parallel with the Italo-S.C.S. Treaty without imposing any special obligations on Czechoslovakia. It is probable for this reason that its terms were left rather vague. The great distinction between this treaty and the Franco-Czechoslovak Treaty is that no special mention is made of Germany.   This treaty is not considered of much importance.IV. JUGOSLAV-GREEK TREATY.The alliance concluded in May 1913 was denounced by Jugoslavia in December of last year. It will thus terminate in December 1925, and negotiations will during the next few months take place at Belgrade for a new treaty to take its place. We have as yet no indication as to the form which the new treaty will take, although it is expected that the Jugoslavs will exact very severe terms in respect of their economic outlet at Salonica in return for any renewal of the alliance in its old form.V.-POLAND, THE BALTIC STATES AND FINLAND.In 1922 a conference was held at Warsaw between Poland, the Baltic States and Finland with a view to concluding a definite alliance against Soviet Russia. An agreement was signed, but was not ratified by Finland, and it consequently lapsed.
In the event of an attack by Russia- on the Baltic States, therefore, there is as yet no obligation in writing on the part of Poland to come to their aid. Conferences of the Baltic States with Finland and Poland are held, periodically, but, from the military point of view, they do not produce any concrete results for the reason that, while the Baltic States have everything to gain from Finnish or Polish military support, they have little or nothing to offer in return.Central Department, Foreign Office, January 20, 1925.Annex 1.Convention de 1&apos;Alliance entre la Republique tchecoslovaque et le Royaume desSerbes, Croates et Slovenes.FERMEMENT r^solus de maintenir la paix acquise au prix de tant de sacrifices et prevue par le Pacte de la Societe des Nations, ainsi que l&apos;ordre etabli par le traite conclu a Trianon, le 4 juin 1920, entre les Puissances alliees et associees d&apos;une part, et la Ffongrie de 1&apos;autre, le President de la Republique tchecoslovaque et Sa Majeste le Roi des Serbes, Croates et Slovenes se sont mis d&apos;accord pour conclure une convention defensive.Dans ce but ont nomine1 pour leurs delegu^s plenipotentiaires, savoir :Le President de la Republique tchecoslovaque : M. Edouard Benes, son Ministre des Affaires  trangeres;Sa Majeste&quot; le Roi des Serbes, Croates et Slovenes: M. Momtchilo Nintchitch, docteur en droit, son Ministre du Commerce et de lTndustrie, Ministre des Affaires etrangeres par interim;Lesquels, apres s&apos;etre communique leurs pleins pouvoirs, trouves en bonne et due forme, sont convenus des articles suivants :Article lor.En cas d&apos;une attaque, non-provoquee, de la Ffongrie contre Tune des hautes parties contractantes, 1&apos;autre partie s&apos;engage a concourir a la defense de la partie attaquee de la facon determinee par 1&apos;arrangement prevu dans 1&apos;article 2 de la pr^sente convention.Article 2.Les autorites techniques comp^ententes de la Republique tchecoslovaque et du Royaume des Serbes, Croates et Slovenes fixeront, d&apos;un commun accord, les dispositions necessaires pour 1&apos;execution de la presente convention.Article 3.Aucune des hautes parties contractantes ne pourra conclure une alliance aveo une tierce Puissance, sans avis pr^alable de 1&apos;autre.Article 4.La pr6sente convention sera valable deux ans a partir du jour de F^change des ratifications. Ce terme expire, chacune des parties contractantes aura la faculty de denoncer la presente convention. Elle restera pourtant en vigueur six mois apres la date de la denonciation.Article 5.La presente convention sera communiquee k la Societe des Nations (Pacte de la Societe des Nations).
wAnnex 2.Convention d&apos;Alliance defensive entre la Republique tchecoslovaque et leRoyaume de Roumanie.FERMEMENT resolus de maintenir la paix acquise au prix de tant de sacrifices et prevue par le Facto de la Societe des Nations, ainsi que 1&apos;Ordre etabli par le traite conclu a Trianon, le 4 juin 1920, entre les Puissances alliees et associees d&apos;une part, et la Hongrie de 1&apos;autre, le President de la Republique tchecoslovaque et Sa Majeste le Roi de Roumanie se sont mis d&apos;accord pour conclure une convention defensive.Dans ce but ont nomme pour leurs deleguds plenipotentiaires, savpir :Le President dp la Republique tchecpslovaque : M. Ferdinand Veverka, Envoye&quot; extraordinaire et Ministre plenipotentiaire de la Repiiblique tchecpslpvaque a Bucarest;Sa Majest6 le Roi de Roumanie : M. Take Jonesco, son Ministre d&apos;Etat au Departempnt des Affaires ptrangerps;Lesquels, apres s&apos;etre communique leurs pleins pouvoirs, trouves en bonne et due forme, sont convenus des articles suivants :Article ler.En cas d&apos;une attaque, npn provoquee, de la Hongrie contre 1&apos;une des hautes parties contractantes, 1&apos;autre partie s&apos;engage a concourir k la defense de la partie atfaquee de la facon cleterminee par 1&apos;arrangenient prevu dans 1&apos;article 2 de la presentp convention. /yArticle 2.Les autorites techniques competentes de la Republique tche&quot;coslovaque et du Royaume de Roumanie fixeront, d&apos;un commun accord, les dispositions necessaires pour 1&apos;execution de la presente convention, dans une convention militaire a conclure filter ieurement.Article 3.Aucune des hautes parties contractantes ne pourra conclure une alliance avec une tierce Puissance, sans avis prealable de 1&apos;autre.Article 4.Afin de coordonner leurs efforts pacifiques, les dpux Gouvernements s&apos;engagent a se concerter sur les questions de politique exterieure qui ont trait a leurs rapports avec la Hongrie.Article 5.3La presente cpnventipn sera yalable deux ans a partjr dp jour de l&apos;echange dps ratifications. &apos; Ce terme expird, chacune dps parties contractantes aura la fapultd de denoncer la presente convention. Elle restera pourtant en vigueur six mois apres la date de la denonciation.Article 6.La pr,6sente convention sera communiquee a la Societe des Nations (Pacte de la Societe des Nations).La presente convention sera ratifiee et les ratifications en seront echangees a. Belgrade le plus tot possible.En fpi pie quoi les plenipptentiaires designds 1&apos;pnt signpe pt y pnt appose leurs sceaux.Fait a Belgrade, en double expedition, le 14 aout 1920.Dr. M. NLNCIC, m.p. Copie conforme a 1&apos;original: Dr. E. BENES, m.p.M. Mastny.
Protocole (B).Au moment de signer la Convention d&apos;Alliance defensive entre le President do la Republique tchecoslovaque et Sa Majeste le Roi de Roumanie, leurs plenipotentiaires sont convenus de la disposition suivante qui fait partie integrante de ladite convention:La convention militaire prevue a 1&apos;article 2 et qui restera secrete, contiehdra une disposition qui declare que, dans le cas ou la Roumanie se trouverait en guerre avec n&apos;importe quel autre Etat, la Republique tchecoslovaque ne mettra pas d&apos;obstacle a ce quo le Royaume de Rbumahie piiisse se fournir de munitions ou d&apos;autre materiel de guerre Oil Tbhecoslovaquie ou de le transporter par Tchecoslovaquie.Une f ois la convention militaire signee, ce protocdle n&apos;atira plus d&apos;existence.Fait a Bucarest, en double expedition, le 23 avril 1921.Dr. FERDINAND VEVERKA, m.v. TAKE JONESCO, m.p.Annex 3. &apos;Accord politique entre Id Republique tchecoslovaque et la Republique de Pologne.ECALEMENT soucieux de sauvegarder la paix en Europe et fermement desireux d&apos;organiser les relations entre la Tchecoslovaquie et la Pologne a base de la solidarity de leurs interets mutuels politiques et 6conomiques, le Gouvernement tehecOsiovaque et le Gouvernement polonais se sont entendus pour conclure un accord politique.Dans ce but, les Chefs des deux Etats ont nomine pour leurs plenipotentiaires :Le President de la Republique tchecoslovaque: son President du Conseil et Ministre des Affaires efrangeres, M. le Dr. Edquard Benes ;Le Chef de 1&apos;Etat poiohais : son Ministre des Affaires etfahgeres, Mi Constantm Skirmunt;Lesquels, apres s&apos;etre communique leurs pleins pouvoirs, reconnus en bonne et due forme, ont convenu des engagements suivants :Article lto.Les deux Etats se dohhent mutuellement la garantie de 1&apos;etat de possession, ayant pour base les traites sur lesquels repose 1&apos;iridependance et 1&apos;organisation d&apos;Etat de la Pologne et de la Tchecoslovaquie. Les.deux Etats vont se concerter, quaiid le be&apos;sdih et rOccasiori Fexigeroht, siir rappiication des traites sighes eh commun. \lArticle 2.Lies deux Etats s&apos;engagent a garder la neutrality bienveillante fen cas ou Fun d&apos;eiix serait attaque p4f un dfe leurs voisiris, et particulierement a assurer le libie transit dti materiel de guferre.1 La presente convention sera ratifiee et les ratifications en serdnt echangees a Bucarest le plus tot possible.En foi de qiioi les plehipbtentiaires design^s Font signee et y out oppose leurs sceaux.Fait a Bucarest, en double expedition, le 23 avril 1921.Dr. Ferdinand veverka, m,p.TAKE jonesco, m.p.
Reduction of Maximum Period of Imprisonment for Drunkenness on Active Service(Amendment No. 17). 36. Section 19 of the Act places no limit, other than the general limit of two years laid down by Section 44, on the maximum period of imprisonment which may be awarded by a court-martial for drunkenness on active service. The amendment would make 6 months imprisonment the maximum under this section.37. In view of the serious nature and the discreditable character of the offence of drunkenness on active service, we cannot recommend this concession.Certificate of Absence in Desertion Cases(Amendment No. 18).38. Desertion frequently begins with absence from a draft which is being sent abroad, and it was suggested to us that proof of such absence sometimes fails because the officer in charge of the draft is no longer available. The object of the amendment is to enable a certificate, purporting to be signed by the officer in question, to be taken in evidence.39. We are aware of the difficulty, but we think it has already been provided against in paragraph 1095 of the King&apos;s Regulations, 1923. This paragraph lays down that two or more senior non-commissioned officers, not themselves proceeding with the draft, shall attend and record the names of all absentees &quot; in order that at any future court-martial . . . one or other of these N.C.Os. may be available to prove in evidence the fact of the absence.&quot; In the circumstances we do not recommend any further action.Trial of Charges of Manslaughter by Court-Martiae (Amendment No. 19).- 4C. The effect of this amendment would be that manslaughter could be tried by court-martial in all cases, instead of, as at present, under restrictions.41. It appears to us that this change is open to objection not only on grounds of policy but as conflicting with the civil law, under which it is necessary for cases where a coroner&apos;s jury have brought in a verdict of manslaughter to be referred to the civil court. We therefore recommend no action.Proposed Establishment of Independent Tribunal to Investigate Complaints(Amendments Nos. 20 and 21).42. Under Section 42 of the Act any officer who thinks himself wronged can complain to the Army Council, or, at his own option, to His Majesty, and the arm;&apos; Council are required- to examine into the complaint, and, if necessary, to report through a Secretary
Annexe.Des la signature du present accord, les deux parties contractantes s&apos;engagent a mettre en execution les mesures speciales qui suivent:(a.) Le reglement des questions et des litiges locaux sur 1&apos;ancien territoire plehiscitaire de Cieszyn, Spisz et Crawa, sera effectue a Faide d&apos;une delegation speciale polono-tchecoslovaque, constitute de representants des deux Etats nommes en nombre egal. Cette delegation, 6tant munie de pleins pouvoirs ttendus et precis, prendra les dispositions necessaires en vue d&apos;etablir dans la region en question un ttat de legality, d&apos;equite&quot; et de justice, et de contribuer de la sorte k Fapaisement dans, les rapports entre Polonais et Tchehoslovaques.La delegation sera partagee en deux sous-delegations, polonaise et tchtco-slovaque. Chacune de ces sous-delegations sera tenue d&apos;appliquer sur le territoire relevant de sa competence les decisions prises en commun par la delegation..La Tchecoslovaquie declare son desintef essement dans la question de la Galicie orientale. En consequence de cet acte, elle prend 1&apos;obligation de dissoudre les formations ukrainiennes qui etaient internees en Tchecoslovaquie et de reprimer toute propagande active tendant a detacher un territoire quelconque de la Republique de Pologne.Des obligations analogues sont prises par la Pologne envers la Tchecoslovaquie.Dorenavant, chacun des deux Etats s&apos;engage a ne tolerer sur son territoire aucune organisation politique ou militaire, dirig^e contre 1&apos;integrite et la sehurite&quot; de Fautre Etat.Article 4.Les deux Gouyernements prennent note des conventions politiques, militaires et ehonomiques conclues entre la Tchecoslovaquie, la Roumanie et la Yougoslavie d&apos;une part, et des conventions analogues conclues entre la Pologne, la France et la Rotimanie de Fautre.Article 5.Une convention commerciale entre la Tchecoslovaquie et la Pologne r^glera entre ces deux Etats toutes les questions economiques et financieres ainsi que celles relatives au transit.Article 6.Les deux parties s&apos;engagent a ce que dans toutes les questions litigieuses d&apos;une plus haute portee les deux Etats auront recours a un arbitrage. Les questions devant etre resolues par un arbitrage pourront etre, par un commun accord des deux Gouvernements, soumises a des arbitrages choisis ad hoc ou bien seront portees devant le Cour de Justice internationale.Article 7.Engagement reciproque est pris par les deux Etats qu&apos;aucun accord nouveau qui contreviendrait au present accord ne sera conclu par eux avec d&apos;autres Etats.Article 8.La duree du present accord est de cinq ans, a partir de echange des notes de ratifications, mais chacun des deux Gouvernements est libre de le denoncer apres deux ans, tout en avisant 1&apos;autre Etat six mois d&apos;avance.Article 9.Le present accord sera ratifie et les instruments de ratification seront echanges dans le plus bref delai. 1En foi de quoi les plenipotentiaires ont signe&quot; le present accord et y ont appose leurs sceaux.Fait en double exemplaire a Prague, le 6 novembre 1921.
La delegation sera chargee d&apos; intervenir dans les cas ou une attemte serait portee aux libertes personnelles, aux droits des minorites nationales dans 1&apos;administration des communes et des districts politiques dans la vie scolaire, ainsi que dans tous les domaines de 1&apos;activite economique et specialement de 1&apos;orgahisation du travail.(b.) Le reglement dans un delai de six mois par 1&apos;entente directe et amiable des deux Gouvernements de la question de la commune de Jaworzyna.Fait en double exemplaire a Prague, le 6 novembre 1921.Annex 4. &apos;Traite conclu entre la Roumanie et la Pologne.Protocole 1. Les hautes parties contractantes concluent une alliance defensive-contre 1&apos;agression non provoquee venant de 1&apos;Orient. Elles s&apos;engagent de defendre les frontieres actuelles : roumaines, ainsi qu&apos;elles sont fixees par le traite&quot; relatif a la Bessarabie; polonaises, d&apos;apresle protocol ulterieur, ainsi qu&apos;elles seront fixees par le Traite&quot; de Riga. Le traite est conclu pour la duree de cinq ans et peut etre denonce&quot; apres deux ans. Les questions militaires seront etudiees par les experts militaires dans une stipulation speciale. Les deux parties s&apos;engagent de ne pas conclure de-traites avec les tierces Puissances sans communication reciproque prealable excep-tion faite de traites destines a assurer 1&apos;application des trait^s de paix et de ne pas-conclure, sans 1&apos;assentiment de 1&apos;autre partie contractante, de trait6s avec les Etats qui n&apos;appartiennent pas aux Etats allies et associes. Les deux parties ^tudieront les-moyens par lesquels 1&apos;alliance pourrait etre etendue aux autres Etats. La ratification doit avoir lieu dans le plus bref delai. -Protocole 2. ^Le present traite&quot; n&apos;entrera pas en vigueur tant que celui de Riga, contenant la fixation des frontieres n&apos;aura 6te conclu.Protocole 3. La conclusion du traite de commerce et Braila comme port de-transit sont promis.Protocole 4. En recompense de 1&apos;aide diplomatique dans la question de la. Galacie orientale, les Polonais promettent de modifier les frontieres de l&apos;ancienne Bukovine et de Galicie. L&apos;etendue des territoires ^changes ne doit pas etre neces-sairement la meme.La convention militaire ne contient que les details de caractere militaire des dispositions du traite : secours reciproque et mobilisation dans le cas de toute agres-sion venant de 1&apos;Orient, surtout de 1&apos;agression russe en general, non seulement bolcheviste.L&apos;alinea 3 stipule que la Pologne pretera son aide dans le cas de 1&apos;agression. magyare, meme dans le cas de 1&apos;agression bulgare.Ainsi les renseignements des milieux hostiles au traite qui croyaient les condi-tions du Traite de Riga suffisantes a empecher le casus foederis sont a corriger a fond.Le traite politique et la convention signifient les garanties r^ciproques de frontieres.Annex 5.Political Agreement between the Republic of Austria and the Czechoslavak Republic,done at Prague, December 16, 1921.THE Government of the Republic of Austria, on the one hand, and the Govem-ment of the Czechoslovak Republic on the other hand, with the view of maintaining-peace in Europe and regulating their mutual political and economic relations, have-agreed to conclude a political agreement, and with this object have named as their&apos; plenipotentiaries :  ,The President of the Republic of Austria, Herr Johann Schober, Federal. Chancellor and Chief of the Federal Ministry for Foreign Affairs;The President of the Czechoslovak Republic, Herr Eduard Benesch, Minister President and Minister for Foreign Affairs;who, having exchanged their full powers, found in good and due form, have agreed to the following provisions : [12567] c
., Basing themselves on the Peace Treaty concluded with Austria at Saint-Germain-en-Laye on the 10th September, 1919, and on the Peace Treaty concluded with Hungary at Trianon oh the 4th June, 1920, the two States undertake to put into execution to their full extent all provisions of the two above-mentioned treaties.Article 2.The two States guarantee each other&apos;s territories as they are specified in the Peace Treaties mentioned in article 1, and undertake further, with a view to maintaining peace and ensuring the inviolability of the said territories, to support one another politically and diplomatically.Article 3.The. two States undertake, in the event of one of them being attacked and compelled to defend itself, to observe neutrality^Article 4.The two States undertake to tolerate on their territories no political or military organisation directed against the existence and the security of the other contracting party. Both States further undertake to co-operate and protect each other mutually against all endeavours and attempts to restore the former regime, whether in respect of external or internal policy, or in regard to the form of the State and Government. The existing authorities of the two States will support one another, with a view to contending m this sense effectively against secret agitationArticle 5.The Czechoslovak Republic will inform the Republic of Austria with regard to the political and econoinic treaties, which it has concluded with the Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, the Kingdom of Roumania, and the Republic of Poland. Similarly, the analogous treaties concluded by the Republic of Austria will be brought to the knowledge of the Czechoslovak Republic.Article 6.The two States undertake to exercise vigilance in the due observance of treaties, already concluded or to be concluded, with regard to the regulation of economic or financial questions, or questions concerning minorities, and other questions; and further undertake to come to an agreement with one another as soon as possible with regard to all or any disputed questions, which up to now could not be settled.Article 7.In the event of disputed questions arising in future between the two States after conclusion of the present agreement, the two Governments will endeavour to reach an understanding by friendly agreement. Under circumstances they will bring the subject of the dispute before the Permanent International Court or before one or more arbitrators to be chosen by themselves.Article 8.The two States undertake to conclude no agreement of whatever kind with any other State, which is contrary to the present agreement concluded by both contracting parties. They further declare that the present agreement is not contrary to previously concluded agreements.Article 9.The present agreement is concluded for the period of five years, reckoned from the day of the exchange of the instruments of ratification. After the expiry of three years, reckoned from the said day, each of the contracting parties is free to withdraw from the present agreement, on condition that such intention is communicated six months beforehand to the other party.
Annex 6.Notes exchanged between Italian and Czechoslovak Ministers for Foreign Affairs.  (Communicated to Foreign Office by the Czechoslovak Minister in London.)(1.)(Translation.)M. le Ministre, Rome, February 8, 1921.I HAVE pleasure in confirming the fact that, in the conversations which I have-had with your Excellency, I have been able to assure myself that a complete identity exists between the views and aims of our two countries in the sphere of international politics. This is a consequence of the common interests of the two peoples, and it emerges with even greater clearness as regards the application of the treaties of peace and the policy to be followed towards the successor States of the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy, complete agreement having been reached as to the objects of which the attainment will best promote the safety and prosperity of the two nations.I take note of this fact with satisfaction, inasmuch as it is a guarantee of harmony and political collaboration between the two States, which is even more effective than any that could result from the special provisions of a convention.At the same time, since the definite fixation of the Italian frontiers is bound up with the stipulations of the Treaty of Rapallo between Italy and the Serbo-Croat-Slovene State, and since, in the circumstances, a special convention of a political character has been drawn up, the natural interpretation of the communication made to the Czechoslovakian Government, on the basis of article 4 of that convention, is that the provisions of that convention, and the obligations imposed thereby, are equally binding upon Italy and upon Czechoslovakia.I have, &amp;c. (Signed) C. SFORZA.(2.)(Translation.)M. le Ministre, Rome, February 8, 1921.I HAVE the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your note, which runs as: follows : (Here follows the text of the note from Count Sforza to Dr. Benes of the 8th February.)I am happy to be able to inform your Excellency that my Government fully concur in the contents of the note set out above.I have, &amp;c.v    (Signed) Dr. EDUARDO BENES..[12567JThe present agreement will be ratified, and the instruments of ratification will he exchanged, in Prague as soon as possible.Article 11.The present agreement will be brought to the knowledge of the League of Nations.In testimony whereof the two plenipotentiaries have signed the present agreement and affixed their seals thereto.Done at Prague on the 16th December, 1921, in duplicate.SCHOBER.Dr. EDWARD BENES.
iMrAd tf* mi^/isl       &apos;r&apos;&quot;&apos; Annex 7:    ,:.&quot;;y&apos; &apos;. &apos; 7,7&apos;&apos; . Texte des Accords conclus entre Vltalie et le Royaume des Serbes, Croates et Slovenes. f (I-) &apos;Pacte d&apos; Amitieet de Collaboration cordiale entre le Royaume des Serbes, Croateset Slovenes et le Royaume d&apos;Italie.LE Gouvernement de Sa Majeste le Eoi des Serbes, Croates et Slovenes et le Gouvernement de Sa Majesty le Roi dTtalie, fermement resolus a assurer la paix ainsi que les rdsultats obtenus pendant la grande guerre et sanctionnes par les Traites de Paix, sont tombes d&apos;accord pour stipuler la, presente convention, consequence naturelle soit de 1&apos;amitie existant entre les deux royaumes, soit de respect mutuel de leurs droits sur terre autant que sur mer, et ils sont convenus des articles suivants :it// Article rr.Les deux hautes parties contractantes s&apos;engagent reciproquement a se preter leur appui mutuel et leur collaboration cordiale pour le maintien de 1&apos;ordre 6tabli par les Traites de Paix conclus a Trianon, a Saint-Germain et a Neuilly, ainsi que pour le respect et Pexecution des obligations stipulees dans lesdits traites.Article 2.Au cas ou une des parties contractantes deviendrait 1&apos;objet d&apos;une agression non provoquee de la part de 1&apos;une ou de plusieurs Puissances, 1&apos;autre partie s&apos;engage a rester neutre pendant toute la duree du conflit. Au cas ou la securite et les interets d&apos;une des hautes parties contractantes seraient menaces par suite d&apos;incursions violentes provenant du dehors, 1&apos;autre partie s&apos;engage a lui preter par son concours bienveillant son appui politique et diplomatique dans le but de contribuer a faire disparaitre la cause extirieure de ces menaces.Article 3.Au cas de complications Internationales, et si les deux hautes parties contrac-tantes tombent d&apos;accord que leurs interets communs sont ou pourront etre menaces, elles s&apos;engagent a se concerter sur les mesures a prendre en commun pour les sauvegarder.Article 4.La duree de la presente convention sera de cinq ans et pourra etre denoncee ou tenouvelee un an avant son expiration.Article 5.Le present trait6 sera ratifie et les ratifications seront echangees a Rome. II entrera en vigueur immediatement apres 1&apos;echange des ratifications.En foi de quoi les plenipotentiaires respectifs 1&apos;ont signee en double original et y ont appose leurs sceaux.Fait a Rome, le 27 Janvier 1924.; .(2.) ;    : , . -Protocole additionnel au Pacte d&apos;Amitie et de Collaboration cordiale entre le Royaume d&apos;Italie et le Royaume des Serbes, Croates et Slovenes.Article 1&quot;. ;&apos;&apos; , &apos;Les hautes parties contractantes s&apos;engagent a se communiquer apres une entente prealable les accords qui interessent leur politique dans l&apos;europe centrale et elles declarent a ce sujet que, dans le Pacte d&apos;Amitie sign^ k la date de ce jour, il n&apos;y a rien
-qui soit contraire aux traites d&apos;alliance quele Royaume des Serbes, Croates et Slovenes a conclus respectivement avec la Republique tchecoslovaque et avec le Royaume de Roumanie le 15 aout 1922 et le 7 juillet 1923,Article 2.Le Pacte d&apos;Amitie conclu a la date dece jour et le present protocole additionnel seront prtsentes a la Societe des Nations pour y etre enregistrts conformement a 1&apos;article 18 du pacte.Fait a Rome, le 27 Janvier 1924.Annex 8.Political A greement between France and Poland.LE G-ouvernement polonais et le Gouvernement fran9ais, egalement soucieux de sauvegarder, par le maintien des traites qui ont 6t6 signes en commun ou qui seront ulttrieurement respectivement reconnus, 1&apos;etat de paix en Europe, la securite et la defense de leur territoire ainsi que leurs interets mutuels politiques et economiques, ont convenu ce qui suit :1. Ann de coordonner leurs efforts pacifiques, les deux Gouvernements s&apos;engagent a se concerter sur toutes les questions de politique exterieure int&amp;ressant les deux Etats et relatives au reglement des relations internationales dans 1&apos;esprit des traites -et conformement au Pacte de la Societe des Nations.2. Le relevement economique etant la condition primordiale du retablissement de l&apos;ordre international et de la paix en Europe, les deux Gouvernements s&apos;entendront a cet egard en vue d&apos;une action solidaire et d&apos;un mutuel appui.Ils s&apos;emploieront a developper leurs relations economiques : des accords speciaux et une convention commerciale seront conclus a cet effet.3. Si, contrairement aux previsions et aux intentions sincerement pacifiques des deux Etats contractants, ceux-ci ou Fun des deux se voyaient attaqu6s sans provoca-- tion de leur part, les deux Gouvernements se concerteraient en vue de la defense de leur territoire et de la sauvegarde de leurs interets legitimes, dans les limites precisees dans le prtambule.4. Les deux Gouvernements s&apos;engagent a se consulter avant de conclure de nouveaux accords interessant leur politique en Europe centrale et orientale.5. Le present accord n&apos;entrera en vigueur qu&apos;apres la signature des accords commerciaux actuellement en negociation.A. BRIAND. E. SAPIEHA.Paris, le 19 fevrier 1921.Annex 9.Traite d&apos;Alliance et d&apos;Amitie entre la France et la Tchecoslovaquie. (Communicated by Czechoslovak Minister, January 26.)LE Gouvernement de la Rtpublique francaise et le Gouvernement de la Republique tchecoslovaque,Fermement attaches aux principes du respect des engagements internationaux confirme solennellement par le Pacte de la Societe des Nations;Egalement soucieux de sauvegarder la paix, dont le maintien est necessaire a la -stabilite politique et au relevement economique de 1&apos;Europe;Resolus a cet effet d&apos;assurer le respect de l&apos;ordre juridique et politique international etabli par les traites qu&apos;ils ont signes en commun;Considerant que pour atteindre ce but des garanties reciproques de securite contre une agression eventuelle et en vue de la defense de leurs interets communs, leur sont indispensables,
Ont designe pour leurs plenipotentiaires, savoir :&apos;     Le President de la Republique francaise : M. Raymond Poincare, President du Conseil et Ministre des Affaires etrahgeres;      &apos; &apos; Le President de la Republique tchecoslovaque: Dr. Edouard Benes, Ministre des Affaires etrangeres;Lesquels, apres avoir, echange leurs pleins pouvoirs, reconnus en bonne et due forme, ont convenu des dispositions suivantes :   &apos;Article l6r.Les Gouvernements de la Republique francaise et de la Rdpublique tchecoslovaque s&apos;engagent a se concerter sur les questions exterieures de nature a mettre en danger leur securite et a porter atteinte a 1&apos;ordre etabli par les traites de paix dont ils sont run et 1&apos;autre signataires.Article 2.Les hautes parties contractantes se mettront d&apos;accord sur les mesures propres a sauvegarder leurs interets communs dans le cas ou ils seraienf menaces.Article 3.Les hautes parties contractantes, pleinement d&apos;accord sur 1&apos;importance que presentent pour le. maintien de la paix generale les principes d&apos;ordre politique contenus dans Particle 88 du Traite&quot; de Paix de Saint Germain-en-Laye du 10 septembre 1919, ainsi que dans les Protocoles de Geneve du 4 octobre 1922, dont elles sont toutes deux signataires, s&apos;engagent a se concerter sur les mesures a prendre au cas ou F observation de ces principes serait menacee.Article 4.Les hautes parties contractantes, prenant en consideration particuliere les declarations faites par la Conference des Ambassadeurs le 3 fevrier 1920 et le 1&quot; avril 1921, dont leur politique continuera a s&apos;inspirer, ainsi que la declaration faite le 10 novembre 1921 par le Gouvernement hongrois aux reprdsentants diplomatiques allies, s&apos;engagent a se concerter dans le cas ou leurs interets se trouveraient menaces par 1&apos;inobservation des principes enonces dans ces diverses declarations.Article 5.Les hautes parties contractantes confirment leur plein accord sur la ndcessite qui s&apos;impose en vue du maintien de la paix d&apos;adopter une attitude commune en presence des tentatives eventuelles de restauration de la dynastie des Hohenzollern en Allemagne et s&apos;engagent a se concerter sur les mesures a prendre dans cette eventualite.Article 6.Conformement aux principes enonces dans le Pacte de la Societe des Nations,, les hautes parties contractantes conviennent que, au cas ou il surgirait entre elles dans 1&apos;avenir, des questions litigieuses qui ne pourraient etre resolues par un accord amiable et par la voie diplomatique, elles soumettront ce litige soft a la Cour permanente de Justice interhationale, soit a un ou plusieurs arbitres choisis par elles.Article 7.Les hautes parties contractantes s&apos;engagent a se communiquer les accords interessant leur politique en Europe centrale qu&apos;elles ont conclus anterieurement, et a se consulter avant d&apos;en conclure de nouveaux. Elles declarent que, a, cet egard, rien dans le present traite n&apos;est contraire aux susdits accords, et specialement au traits d&apos;alliance entre la France et la Pologne, aux accords ou arrangements conclus par la Tchecoslovaquie avec la Republique federale d&apos;Autriche, la Roumanie, le Royaume des Serbes, Croates et Slovenes, non plus qu&apos;a 1&apos;accord constate par l&apos;e&quot;change de lettres intervenu le 8 f/jvrier 1921 entre le Gouvernement italien et le-Gouvernement tchecoslovaque.
DIAGRAM  ILLUSTRATING THE$EXPLANATION   OF SIGNHPolitical Treaties IUn absence of knoE \close collaboration[Treaties parallel 1 \ Entente( Mil it ary confer? tiM \( terms not accurMITreaty of lana Treaty of alliance^GERMANYFRANCEAUSTRIACZECHO-SLOVAKIAI TALY
If AT I N G THE LITTLE ENTENTEBtION  OF signs   used:- .Political TreatiesUn absence of known military conventions (close collaboration between Gen. Staffs[Treaties parallel with those of Little \ Entente(Military convention known to exist. ,(/ terms not accurately known)III Treaty of LanaTreaty of alliance  (Denounced)POLANDROUMANIAf JUGO SLAVIA &apos; (SCS)   &apos;&apos; iGREECE
Annex 10.Pacte de Collaboration cordiale entre la Republique tchecoslovaque et leRoyaume d&apos;Italie.LE Gouvernement de la Republique tcbecoslovaque et le Gouvernement de Sa Majeste le Roi dTtalie,Soucieux de sauvegarder la paix et desireux de collaborer en commun pour la stabilite et au relevement economique de 1&apos;Europe,Fermement resolus d&apos;assurer le respect de l&apos;ordre juridique et politique inter-national etabli par les Traites de Paix,Sont tombes d&apos;accord pour stipuler le present pacte de collaboration cordiale, consequence naturelle soit de 1&apos;amitie existante entre les deux parties contractantes, soit du respect mutuel de leurs droits.Pour atteindre ce but, ont convenu les dispositions suivantes :Article ler.Les hautes parties contractantes se mettront d&apos;accord sur les mesures propres a sauvegarder leurs interets communs dans le cas ou* tomberont d&apos;accord qu&apos;ils seraient ou pourraient etre menaces.Article 2.Les deux hautes parties contractantes s&apos;engagent reciproquement a se prefer leur appui mutuel et leur collaboration pour le maintien de 1&apos;ordre etabli par les Traites de Paix conclus a Saint-Germain-en-Laye, a Trianon, a Neuilly, ainsi que pour le respect et 1&apos;execution des obligations stipuiees dans lesdits traites.Article 3.La durte de la presente convention sera de cinq ans et pourra etre denoncee ou renouvelee un an avant son expiration.Article 4.Le present traite sera communique a la Societe des Nations conformement a Particle 18 du pacte.Le present traite sera ratifie et les ratifications seront echangees a Rome. II entrera en vigueur immediatement apres echange des ratifications.En foi de quoi les pienipotentiaires respectifs Pont signe en double original et y ont appose leurs sceaux.Fait a Rome, le 5 juillet 1924.* The printed text runs thus, but presumably &quot;elles&quot; has been omitted.Le present traite sera communique a la Societe des Nations, conformement a. 1&apos;article 18 du PacteLe present traite sera ratine et les instruments de ratification seront echanges a Paris le plus tot possible.Paris, le 25 Janvier 1924.

</content>
</cab>
