<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/172/0 images: 223-241</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   February .1925.SECRET. Copy No. ^ ^rg.P. -124.(25).CABINET.The Singapore Base.Memorandum by the Chairman of the Committee of &quot;ImperialDefence.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1, February 27, 1925.  -
Sub-Committee on Singapore.TERMS OF REFERENCE AND COMPOSITION OF SUB-COMMITTEE.Terms of Reference.THE Committee of Imperial Defence, at their 193rd Meeting, held on the 5th January, 1925, agreed That a Sub-Committee should be appointed. (i.) To re-examine the sites approved by the Committee of Imperial Defence on the 14th December, 1922, for the naval base, aerodrome and seaplane station, in which connection the Secretary was instructed to circulate the papers on which the previous conclusion had been reached, (ii.) To consider the rate at which the naval base and the defences necessary for its protection should be proceeded with.(iii.) To consider the programme of construction to be aimed at both for the naval base and the defences, including examination of deterrents as alternatives to heavy guns against attack by capital ships; the scale of defences required; the strength of the Military and Air Garrison; and the approximate cost of the proposals recommended.Composition of Sub-Committee.The Most Hon. the Marquess Curzon of Kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.,Lord President of the Council (in the Chair). The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, C.H., M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer. The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P., Secretary of State for the Colonies. The Right Hon.  Sir, Laming Worthington-Evans, Bart., C.B.E., M.P., ..   Secretary of State for War/ The Right Horn Sir Samuel Hoare, Bart., C.M.G., M.P., Secretary of Statefor Air.The Right Hon. W. C. Bridgeman, M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty. Admiral of the Fleet Earl Beatty, G.C.B., O.M., G.C.V.O., D.S.O., First sea lord and Chief of Naval Staff. General the Earl of Cavan, K.P., G.C.M.G., G.C.V.O., K.C.B., Chief of theImperial General Staff. ...Air Chief Marshal Sir H. M. Trenchard, Bart., G.C.B., D.S.O., A.D.C., Chiefof the Air Staff.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, G.C.B. (Secretary). Major L. A. Clemens, O.B.E., M.C. (Assistant Secretary).(Signed) L. A. CLEMENS(For Secretary).2, Whitehall Gardens, S. W. 1, January 9, 1925.[1-276S]
THE  SINGAPORE  BASE.Memorandum by the Chairman of the Committee of Imperial Defence.IN view of a question to be raised in the House of Lords on &quot;Wednesday next on the subject of the Governments policy in regard to the Singapore base, I desire to invite the assent of my colleagues to the interim Conclusions reached by a Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence which has been enquiring into the subject with the Terms of Reference given on the opposite page. These Conclusions refer solely to the site of the floating dock, which is to be sent to Singapore, and to the programme of work to be undertaken by the Admiralty during the next two or three years.2. The first question to which the Sub-Committee directed its attention was a re-investigation of the site on the Old Strait, suggested by the Admiralty and approved by the Committee of Imperial Defence in 1922, for the proposed naval dockyard and establishment. We felt that if the Government- were to be in a position to convince public opinion, we must be able to reassure the Committee of Imperial Defence and the Cabinet, not only that the site was the best from the point of view of naval and defensive requirements, but also that it could be justified from a financial point of view. In particular, we set ourselves to ascertain whether, : having regard to the statement* made by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to the Committee of Imperial Defence at the 193rd Meeting, on the political outlook in the Far East (which is being circulated to the Cabinet), naval requirements could be met, at any rate for some years to-come, &quot;by means of the commercial repair , facilities already existing in Keppel Harbour (to the south of Singapore Island) instead of creating an entirely new naval establishment in the Old Strait between Singapore Island and the State of Johore.3. After studying the earlier Papers on the subject, including the results of the &apos; very thorough investigation conducted by the Admiralty in 1921, we decided that the best plan would be to test the previous decisions by consulting certain high authorities with recent local knowledge who are now in this country. We also invited the Governor of the Straits Settlements to send us his views by telegram.4. Our first witness was Admiral Sir Arthur Leveson, the late Commander-in-Chief on the China Station. The Admiral, who was a strong supporter of the imperative necessity of a naval base at Singapore, while agreeing that the Old Strait offered the best site for a naval base if financial considerations were left out of account, considered that naval requirements could be met sufficiently, and probably more economically, by mooring the floating dock in Keppel Harbour and by developing the existing repair facilities of that harbour in co-operation with the administration of the local docks and wharves, which are the property of the Straits Settlements, but are conducted on purely commercial lines.5. I do not propose to enter at this stage into a full exposition of the pros and cons of Admiral Leveson&apos;s proposals in regard to repair facilities, &amp;c, on which the Sub-Committee has not yet reached a final conclusion. So far as the floating dock is concerned, however, we find ourselves unable to accept his view. Not only the present professional advisers of the Admiralty, but also Vice-Admiral Sir Laurence Power, the late Director of Dockyards at the Admiralty, and Admiral Learmonth, late Hydrographer of the Navy, both of whom were members of the Admiralty Committee which visited Singapore in 1921 to report on the possibilities of the formation of a naval base/gave convincing testimony in favour of the site at Old Strait and against any site in Keppel Harbour.* CP. 120 (25).[12766] I 2
4?S -6. The objections to Keppel Harbour may be summarised as follows:-  -(f.) All the possible sites atje objectionable from a defensive point of view, inasmuch as they are exposed to long-range bombardment. In addition, in all the sites but one, the floating dock would be exposed to attack from a submarine firing torpedoes from outside the harbour, and the hydro-graphic conditions are such that the establishment of any barrage defence is impossible except at prohibitive expense, (ii.) The only possible site which is not exposed to torpedo attack (viz., between Blakan Mati Island and Pulau Brani Island) is situated on the south side of Keppel Harbour, at a considerable distance from the wharves and repairing facilities. Moreover, in this part of the harbour, heavy dredging would&apos; be required in a bottom which, there is reason to believe, consists largely of rock, and the tides are particularly strong.(iii.) In all the possible sites capital ships would only be able to enter and leave the dock during the brief period of slack water, owing to the strong and uncertain tidal streams. In most of the sites the floating dock would obstruct navigation, which is not too easy in this narrow and restricted harbour, or would seriously interfere with the approaches to the wharves.(iv.) The selection of any site in Keppel Harbour for a floating dock would probably be strongly opposed by the commercial community and the various shipping firms, on the grounds that the harbour is already at times congested, and that there is no margin beyond commercial requirements.7. On the other hand, the evidence showed that the proposed site on the Old Strait is not open to any of these objections. It is well situated from the point of view of defence, being some miles in rear of the harbour entrance and immune from torpedo attack. There is a good depth of water, which would reduce to a minimum the necessary dredging to provide the hole for the floating dock, and probably without meeting rock. The tides present no difficulty, and the navigational difficulties are considerably less than in Keppel Harbour and the adjacent waters. The Admiralty are convinced that the cost of the installation would be less than if a site were selected in Keppel Harbour. Land on the Old Strait has also been provided free of cost by the Colony.8. While on purely naval grounds we felt that the technical objections mentioned above outweighed the possible but unproved financial advantages, on which Admiral Leveson&apos;s proposals rested, and that the balance of evidence was overwhelmingly in favour of the Old Strait, it was necessary to ensure that the site was equally satisfactory from.the point of view of military defence and more particularly against an enemy force landed on the coast of Johore. On this point the military evidence wTas reassuring. Not only the Chief of the Imperial General Staff, but also General Sir Neill Malcolm, the late General-Officer-Commanding, Malaya, assured us that the detailed military reconnaissance carried out in recent years had led to the conclusion that, owing to the difficulties of the terrain, the approach of an enemy force through the State of Johore would be attended with exceptional difficulties and that the conditions would generally favour the defence.9. Finally, we received from Sir Laurence Guillemard, the Governor of the Straits Settlements, the following telegram : &quot; Your telegram of the day before yesterday. The question of alternative sites for. the whole lay-out or for docking and repairing has, from time to time,.been discussed by me informally with Naval and Military authorities. To develop the only alternative sites mentioned to me, Le.,. those wholly or in part inside the commercial harbour, it would be necessary either to enlarge existing commercial facilities or to construct separate Naval accommodation.&quot; I have now come to the conclusion, having started with an open mind, that from the civil point of view the possible advantages of any-such alternative site would be altogether outweighed by the disadvantages, such as divided authority impeace and congestion in war. : &apos;&quot; &apos; &quot; I consider that the possibility of any difficulty arising from the status of Job pre can be disregarded, and Lhave no objection from the civil point of view to the present site.   .      ,       :. - -   -:&quot;Nor do I see any objection from the civil point of view if the experts should prefer an alternative site south or west outside the commercial harbour..&quot;
10. In view of the-above considerations the Sub-Committee felt that there was no necessity to institute a further enquiry on the spot, a course which at first they had been disposed to contemplate, and accordingly they have no hesitation in recbm-mending the site for a floating dock in the Old Strait proposed by the Admiralty and supported by the General Staff and Air Staff.11. For the present we consider that the programme of work to be undertaken by the Admiralty on the Old Strait should be limited to what is essential to enable the dock to be used after its arrival at Singapore, that is to say, to such matters as dredging, water supply, the provision of the necessary accommodation, a floating crane, and to other indispensable matters, such as anti-malaria measures, clearing the site, and borings required in order to obtain the necessary data for such future Avorks as may be decided on later. Our recommendations as regards the programme of work for the next few years are contained in the Annex.12. For the immediate future the ships using the floating dock will have to depend upon naval repair ships and the not inconsiderable repairing resources in Keppel Harbour.13. The Sub-Committee also came to the conclusion, irrespective of the choice of sites for the naval establishment, that the site previously selected for the aerodrome and seaplane station on the south shore of the Old Strait was the best available, and recommend it for approval. We are informed that it has not been considered necessary to include provision for the development of the aerodrome and seaplane station in the Air Ministry&apos;s Estimates for 1925-6.14. As already mentioned, we require further time for and shall proceed next to the consideration of the site and further programme of development of the naval establishments at Singapore, as well as of the question of its defence, which is at the moment before the Committee of Chiefs of Staff.15. With the approval of the Cabinet I propose to base my statement of the Government^ policy in the House of Lords next Wednesday on the conclusions summarised above.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1, February 27, 1925.Annex.Description of Works.	Expenditure.			Totals.	1925-26.	1926-27.	1927-28.	1. Floating dock and\V. 10&apos; connected works / V. 8        .. 2. Borings and  trial   pits,  anti-malarial work, clearing site, &amp;c. Totals	  184,000 10,000 10,000	  191,000 40,000 25,000 50,000	  201,000 35,000 4l&apos;,000	  576,000 75,000 35,000 101,000	204,000	306,000	277,000	787,000





1  &quot;:



Agents for the sale of maps -puMi5lLed&quot;by^&amp;eogrjpbical SectLo^Geiieral Staff.London. E.Stanford \7.0,l2,Loni*cre,W.C.   EMKBTOGH.   W*A.K. Johnston.Lt?, Easter S.&quot; London&quot;. SiFTON.PKAio&amp;C*.67.StJamesSuS.W.   LIVERPOOL.    Philip, Son 4 NEPHEW.2aCWcASt. London. T. Fisher Unwin. Mrfe/pA; Ter..W.C.   CHINA.. Mess. . Kelly &amp; Walsh, (thro&apos;London AgentMCG.Brinkworth. Cannon House,Breams Buildings.E.C.4. Crown Copyright Reserved.Price 3/- net

7&quot; .   1.E?r* Canning Signal Staff..............:...................................................................WfflGovernment Offices Initial Station,Trigonometrical Survey........................................................................................ jjjObservatoryMowit Faher.................................................................................... glj$Measured/Nautical mile South West end-at each end, there are two posts fifty feet apart in fijlline at right angles to the measured line.Bearing from True Meridian 71 &apos;2&apos;E......................................................WkThe map is divided,, for reference into squares, fead)-&apos; origiiiatingiromFort Canning Signal Staff
-: of tlie .1-AN P ITSJ uS1911.5 MilesHale of Ojxe Inch, to a MileNotelatitude North, 1&apos; 17&apos;31 60&quot; Longitude East 103&apos;50&apos;52-61&quot;....................do...........................1 &quot;1714-51&quot;..........................do.........................103&apos;51&apos;08&quot;..................do..........................r 16&apos;08-331........................do..........................103&quot; 49&apos;2386&quot;ppart in...do...........................ri8&apos;08&quot;...................................do.......................103&apos;54&apos;20&quot;(each side, being 2 Miles)( /^Pulsuu NbngssLWar Office, Feb. 1912, Revised Feb. 1916.K smi;


</content>
</cab>
