<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/172/0 images: 299-307</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
4 n I iTHIS POGUMgNT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT.political Outlook in the Far Bast. Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty.The Secretary of    State for Foreign Affairs made the following statement at the Committee of the C.I.B. on 5th January,1925 (vide CP.120 (25) - )&quot;On the whole therefore I dray/ the conclusion that there is, no danger of war with Japan in present circumstances.&quot;&apos;The Chancellor of the Exchequer issued a paper CP .554/24 on the Economic Situation In Japan.   The paper ignores history, real facts and the psychology of the people, so much so that the Naval Staff have prepared an answer to It which answer provides come explanation for the incon-trovertlble fact that Japan has built more modem cruisers, destroyers and submarines since the war than the rest of the world put together, and the Naval Staff cannot but view the fact with considerable concern.SEORBT.CP. 139/25.CABINET(Intd).W .C *B.Admiralty.5th March, 1925.
secret.       The Admiralty have read with Interest the paper of the Chancellor of the Exchequer - CP. 554 (24) - onthe economic power of Japan.     They have noted the figurescontained in paragraph 3 from which it appears that for thelast five years the Revenue and tho Expenditure on Armamentsof Japan have bean respectively as follows:-.   &apos; &apos;  &apos; -        &apos; .   :    -El Hi on MillionRevenue. Expenditure on Armaments.1919-20 133 541920-21 129 651921-22 137 731922-23 131 651923-24 128 432*       The percentage of Revenue spent on armaments is throughout amazingly high.   Why?     What is the motive for the large Naval and Military expenditure - expenditure moreover which must not judged by our Western standards when comparison is made between Japanese and European expenditure on armaments?       The system In force In Japan is that of conscription, and we have the authority of the report of H.M. Ambassador at Tokio for 1922 for the . statement that the Annual cost of a private soldier in Japan was then about  272:3.       Japan- has a strong nationalist cense, and In the words of the same Ambassador &quot;the whole nation have a deep if seldom expressed conviction, they are a race of soldiers with a mission&quot;-.       Her history within the present generation, during which she has climbed from a fourth-rate position to the position of a first-class power, has at once demonstrated and confirmed her belief in her mission&apos;; a set purpose has guided her local outlook in the East and her Internationalpolicy.....
m 2 - .policy generally and her armaments and her strategy have been and are among, if not, the main factors of her unparallel/rapidity of material and.political advancement i She has taken risks with courage i pbth when she embarked on war with China and again later with Russia, the general belief was that Japan would iose.     The war with Russia had towards its termination almost exhausted &quot;Japan, but the successful challenge to Russia was followed by economic expansion and material prosperity^     Today there is a large body of Japanese opinion which believes that victory in war is an efficient cause of improvement in National economy* There can be no doubt about the extraordinary recuperative capacity of Japan after a calamity or set-back.. 4.       Concurrently with the incentive of Japanese racial pride and &quot;full confidence in her National mission and National destiny&quot; (to use the words of Marquess Ito)f Japan has other incentives for a policy of expansion] there is a certain restlessness amongst the Japanese: the population of the mainland, having regard especially to the poor quality cf much of the soil, Is already very over-crowded and is growing rapidly.; the growing industrial sections in the large, towns for economic and social reasons require outlets:     In fact the need of outlets for the population and for increased commerce and markets, especially new sources of self-supply, will probably be among the most compelling reasons for Japan to push a policy of penetration expansion and aggression..5.       The figures mentioned in CP.554 (24) may according to post war standards appear indicative of the comparative poverty of Japan, but the progress that Japan has made inthe
-    5    -In the ten years from 1913 to 1922 should also be kept in view (see Appendix) j moreover in the years when the National. Debts of the other Great Allied Powers were being piled up.    Japan&apos;s National Debt advanced very, gradually.      Her National debt foreign and domestic in May 1914 was  253,000,000 of which  104,000,000 was domestic debt and  149,000,000 foreign debt.     During the war Japanincreased her commerce and shipping and established profitable trade connections in many parts of the world ousting both Germany and British interests.    Her national debt in April 1922 was  359,300,000 of which  223,400,000 consisted of internal loans and  135,900,000 in foreign loans (4 to 5 per cent), the debt being at the rate of  5. per head of the population.     Her present debt is stated in g.Pc554 (24) to be 381 millions.    The British National Debt in 1914 was  678,000,000 and was on 31st March 1924  7,707 , 537 , 545.6,       Whilst JapanTs Foreign Loan in 1924 cost her G% at 87g it is to be noted that the recent market price has been from two to four points higher.     Those responsible for the appreciation of the Loan have judged it from the cold calculating point of view of sound finance, unclouded by political moral or defence questions.     The Government of India Lean in 1921 cost India 1% at part 7.       It is noted also in paragraph 5 of CP.554 (24) that Japan has increased her reserve of Specie^ at home.     It Is believed that the Bank of Japan holds at least five times as much gold as before the war.&apos;The Admiralty are not aware whether this policy is a policy based solely on sound economic grounds, but in any case it has a potential military significance.The......
The Admiralty at least are aware that Japan owing to the Washington Conference obtained relief in the matter of the building of Capital Ships and that she has devoted very largo sums to the construction of Light Cruisers, Destroyers and submarinesi in fact, Japan has, since the Washington Conference, laid down more cruisers, destroyers and submarines than all of the 4 other signatory Powers of the Treaty put together and still has 6 cruisers, 15 destroy-ers, and 16 submarines authorised and due for completion by 1st April, 1929, but not yet laid down. 8*       The Admiralty are Inclined to distrust arguments which imply either that a country will not (foolishly) go to war because of resulting economic disorganisation or that a war will be soon ended because of the alleged economic weakness.of one belligerent,     Prior to the last war an idea was in vogue that wars could not last beyond a few months as economic factors would operate to such an extent that a nation would be forced to stop.the war.     The experience of the Great War, however, proved that nations in earnest could endure immense economic dislocation and that financial weakness could for years be associated with military expansion; Japan, whose population feeds at present mainly on rice, peas, beans, fish and is practically seIf-supporting and whose supplies of most essentials  including food if necessary) can be obtained from China, is particularly well situated for enduring the attrition of war; in any case the Japanese by tradition and patriotism are likely to show their bushide spirit both in endurance and in fighting.       With regard to the Oil Fuel situation,
-    5    -it is very noticeable that a large reserve storage for the Navy Is being accumulated.    Japan produces no oil fuel for naval purposes in her own territory - all of the 250,000 - 300,000 tons which is produced per annum la required for commercial purposes.     The Naval polioy Is to purchase large quantities of oil fuel from abroad (America and Borneo), roughly 250,000 - 300,000 tons per annum in excess of the annual naval requirements, and to erect storage tanks in Japan for the surplus.During the last 5 years a reserve of approximately It million   tons has been worked up and is stored in the country entirely for naval purposes, and it is believed that a total reserve of 2 million tons Is aimed at.(This is not the occasion to demonstrate the degree of vulnerability and the stupendous value of British trade and possessions in the East If Japan took the Initiative In attack, as she probably would, nor to deal with the difficulties of intercepting her communications on the High Seas) .9.       Certain conclusions are drawn in paragraph 7 ofC.P.554 ( 24).     Other conclusions that may be drawn are(l)    that Japan has continued to mortgage her wealth for the improvement of her armed forces and must have a motive.(2)    that her economic condition Is an incentive to Japan to pursue - for economic reasons -what has been her consistent policy, vis:-to extend her control over the Par East, its markets and its supplied.In carrying out her national policy, the past methodsof this strong naval and military Power have not beenabove reproach and indeed have often been sinister and dangerous:   the memory of comparatively recent events shouldnot......
not be forgotten and a blind trust, whether in economic arguments or pacific professions, is to be deprecated.10o      Bince the ahovs memorandum was prepared a reportdated 9th December 1924 has been received from theNaval Attache in Tokio, concerning the Japanese NavalManoeuvres of October 1924, from which the following is an extract!&apos;lt will be seen from the numbers and strength of the fleets engaged that the Japanese Naval Manoeuvres were carried out on a very big scalej in fact on a scale sufficient to cause comment in view of the serious financial state of the counti-y after the recent catastrophe.     The Manoeuvres extended over a period of fifteen days and the cost was estimated at Yen 5, 000,000.15   &apos;
not be forgotten and a blind trust, whether in economic arguments or pacific professions, is to be deprecated.105      Since the above memorandum was prepared a reportdated 9th December 1924 has been received from theNaval Attache in Toklo, concerning the Japanese NavalManoeuvres of October 1924, from which the following is an extract!&apos;lt will be seen from the numbers and strength of the fleets engaged that the Japanese Naval Manoeuvres were carried out on a very big scalej in fact on a scale sufficient to cause comment in view of the serious financial atats of the country after the recent catastrophe.     The Manoeuvres extended over a period of fifteen days and the cost was estimated at Yen 5,000,000.&quot;&apos;&quot; &apos;
0184JAPAN.1915Monthly Average.19811922Ships under construction. 48 - 145     &apos;   &apos; 94Value of Imports. 60,474,000 Yen. 152,481,000 Yen..157,001,000 Yen. Value of Exports.        52,593,000 Yen. 102,371,000 Yen.  132,884,000 Yen.Movement of ships . (vessels entered)Savings BankDeposits *2,060,000 Tons. 2,332,000 Tons. 2,988,000 Tons 197,000,000 Yen. 901,000,000 Yen. 976,000,000 Yen.Note     Yen2/-.

</content>
</cab>
