<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/172/0 images: 730-735</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i This Document is the Property of-His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government. 1    435 Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1925....... JCABINET.PROPOSALS   FOR   SUSPENDING   THE   OPERATION   OF   CERTAIN SECTIONS OF THE GERMAN REPARATION (RECOVERY) ACT, 1921.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.I CIRCULATE herewith, for the information of my colleagues, a draft Protocol for amending the method of administering the Reparation Recovery Act which has been provisionally agreed by the representatives of the British and German Governments.It will be remembered that, in connection with the Commercial Treaty, we promised the German Government to examine the possibility of modifying the existing Act so as to put the collection- of the Reparation Recovery levy on to a statistical basis. Prolonged negotiations have taken place on the subject, of which the present Agreement is the outcome.Apart from the undertaking which we gave in connection with the Commercial Treaty, it became a matter of much urgency to find another workable system, as serious difficulties had arisen in the Transfer Committee over the collection of the levy on the present basis, and there was some danger that, if no alternative system could be discovered, the Transfer Committee might stop the issue of funds necessary to reimburse the German exporters.The effect of the proposed Agreement is that, in place of the present procedure by which 26 per cent, of the value of German imports into Great Britain is collected by the British Customs from British importers, the principal German exporters undertake to deliver the sterling which they receive for their goods up to an amount sufficient to cover our share in the Dawes annuity which is available for the purpose of the Recovery Act.I am satisfied that the scheme proposed offers substantial guarantees that the sums due to Great Britain will be obtained, and, having regard to our undertaking to the German Government, we are bound to give it a trial if and when the necessary consents are obtained from the Transfer Committee and the Reparation Commission.The Transfer Committee passed a number of Resolutions which are satisfactory to us on the 25th instant, and the Reparation Commission is expected to pass similar Resolutions at its meeting on the 30th instant.Provided that this is done, Lord D&apos;Abernon should be authorised to sign the Agreement on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government.It will then be necessary, for technical reasons, to suspend the provisions of the Recovery Act providing for the collection of the levy by the Customs. For this purpose a Resolution will require to be passed by both Houses of Parliament, and I propose that we should take powers in this Resolution to suspend the provisions in question by an Order in Council.  A draft Resolution is annexed.In order that the Agreement may be brought into force as from the 1st May, it will be necessary to get this Resolution through Parliament before the Easter Recess.w. s. c.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1, March 28, 1925.SECRET.CP. 185 (25).[12908]
Resolution, for Suspending the Operation of Certain Sections of the german reporation (Recovery) Act, 1921.Whereas His Majesty&apos;s Government and the German Government have agreed that the existing procedure under the German Reparation (Recovery) Act, 1921, shall be suspended and replaced by an alternative method not involving payments by individual merchants in such a way as to be without prejudice to any right enjoyed by His Majesty&apos;s Government in respect of this Act under the Dawes Plan, the London Protocol of the 30th August, 1924, or otherwise:Now, therefore, it is hereby resolved that the operation of Sections 1, 2, 3 and 5 of the German Reparation (Recovery) Act, 1921, shall be suspended as from and on the tenth day of April, nineteen hundred and twenty-five, unless and until His Majesty shall revoke any Order in Council which he may be pleased to make giving effect to this resolution.
[This Document is the Property of  gig Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]CONFIDENTIAL. ^ .        ^ . -Draft Protocol for the Amending of the Method of Administering the Reparation Recovery Act in Force in Great Britain.WHEREAS it is desired to reduce the burden and to remove the disabilities which the present method of administering &quot; The German Reparation (Recovery) Act, 1921 &quot; (hereinafter referred to as &quot; the Recovery Act &quot;), places upon trade and commerce between Germany and Great Britain; andWhereas it is also desired to assure to the Transfer Committee the jurisdiction over payments under the Recovery Act contemplated by the plan of the First Committee of Experts (hereinafter referred to as &quot; the Dawes Plan &quot;) and the London Protocol executed on the 30th August, 1924;Now, therefore, it is agreed between the Government of His Britannic Majesty (hereinafter referred to as &quot; Great Britain &quot;) and the Government of the German Reich  (hereinafter referred to as  &quot; Germany&quot;)  that  the  present method  of administration shall be suspended and replaced, as from a date not later than the 1st May, 1925, to be mutually agreed, by a procedure substantially as follows : (1.) The present procedure under the Recovery Act by which a proportion of the value of German goods imported into Great Britain is collected by the British customs from the British importers will be replaced by a system under which an equivalent amount of sterling will be surrendered, of their free consent, by the German exporters in accordance with the provisions of paragraph (2) of this agreement.The amount of sterling to be surrendered by the German exporters during each month shall be equivalent to 26 per cent, (or such other proportion as may from time to time be in force) of the value of German imports into Great Britain during the preceding month.The value of German imports shall be calculated on the basis of the statistics supplied by the British customs and established on the same principles as are at present in force in regard to the definition of German goods to which the Recovery Act applies.(2) Out of the sterling proceeds accruing from German exports to Great Britain, the principal German exporting firms, to a number of not less than eight hundred (800) whose names and designations will be communicated to the British Government and to the Agent-General for Reparation Payments within fifteen days of the putting into force of this agreement, will each give an individual declaration to the Reich Minister of Finance, in the terms of the specimen declaration annexed hereto, undertaking to surrender in sterling to the Reichsbank each month, beginning with the 1st May, 1925, thirty per cent. (30 per cent.) of the invoice value of the exports of the firm in question to Great Britain during the previous month. (It is estimated that 30 per cent, of the value of the exports consigned by these firms should be approximately equivalent to 26 per cent, of the value of the total exports from Germany to Great Britain.)(3.) Out of the sterling sums thus surrendered, the Reichsbank will deposit during each month, at such intervals as may be agreed, to the account of the Agent-General at the Bank of England an amount in sterling equivalent to the Reichsmark credit held by him for account of the.British Government, and available for payments under the Recovery Act in accordance with the programme established by the Reparation Commission for the particular month after consultation with the Transfer Committee as contemplated by the Dawes plan.(4.) It is understood that, against telegraphic advice that the sums referred to in paragraph (3) have been duly deposited to his account at the Bank of England, thePROPOSALS FOR AMENDMENT OF REIPROCEDURE.I.FINAL TEXT :   INITIALLED AT BERLIN ON MARCH 24, 1925.[12898]
agent-general will reimburse the German exporters through the Reichsbank with, the equivalent in Reichsmarks of the sterling thus deposited. The equivalent in Reichsmarks will be calculated at the average rate of exchange in Berlin on the date of such deposit.    &apos;&apos;        1 &apos;    \ &apos;    ,(5.) It is further understood that, subject to the approval of the Transfer Com-mittee, the Agent-General will pay over to the British Government the sterling sums deposited under paragraph (3) above.(6.) If during the first or any subsequent month after the coming into force of this agreement the sterling sums surrendered by the German exporters are in excess of the, amounts deposited by the Reichsbank to the account of the agent-general under paragraph (3)-above, the Reichsbank -will transfer the surplus sterling (Uberschuss devisen) surrendered to the Devisenbeschaffungsstelle G.m.b.H.* to be placed in a speciali reserve fund up to an-amount equivalent to 10 million Reichs-marks. On the coming into force of this agreement, the Devisenbeschaffungsstelle G.m.b.H.! shall forthwith pay into this fund the above-mentioned sum in sterling, out of the sterling accruing from exports already in its hands, and it will undertake to secure that the fund is maintained at this level as provided below. The fund shall be under the supervision of the Reichs Finance Ministry, and it shall be open to the British Government and to the Agent-General to ask and obtain at all times any information regarding this fund which they may desire.   ; - -! &apos; If in any month the sterling Surrendered by the German exporters is less than the amount which should be deposited to the account of the Agent-General at the Bank of England under paragraph (3) above, the Devisenbeschaffungsstelle G.m.b.H. shall draw the sum necessary to cover the deficiency out of the Special Reserve Fund and deposit it to the credit of the Agent-General at the Bank of England, being reimbursed by him with the equivalent in Reichsmarks. Further, in that event, it will take steps to expedite the surrender by the German exporters of the sterling accruing from exports (Uberschuss devisen), so as to make up the fund again in sterling to the original level of 10 million Reichsmarks.It is understood that the surplus sterling surrendered by the exporters to the Devisenbeschaffungsstelle G.m.b.H; and deposited in the Special Reserve Fund shall not be reimbursed by the Agent-General nor be credited on account of the Dawes annuity, except as and to the extent that such sterling shall actually be drawn upon and used by the Agent-General for payments to Great Britain under paragraph (5).(7.) It is understood and agreed that this protocol merely provides for amending the method of collection of the levy on exports prescribed by the Recovery Act, that the payments made according to its terms shall accordingly be regarded for all purposes as a delivery pursuant to the terms of that Act, and that its provisions are without prejudice to any rights which may be enjoyed by Great Britain in respect of that Act under the Dawes Plan, the London Protocol of the 30th August, 1924, or otherwise.(8.) The British and German Governments both recognise the desirability of relieving trade and commerce from the burden of collecting a 26 per cent, levy from each transaction and of substituting for the system at present in force a method of administration which will permit the collection of the levy on a statistical basis. If the - present agreement should not prove satisfactory in its operation, both Govern-ments agree that in order to avoid reverting to the system at present in force, they with  appoint a joint committee of experts to explore and report on any other available and practical solutions which will meet the defects which may be revealed. Both-Governments agree to use their best endeavours to overcome the difficulties which may arise on the introduction of the new system during 1925.(9.) This agreement shall not come into force unless and until appropriate resolutions, giving effect to its provisions, have been passed by the Transfer Committee and by the Reparation Commission. Subject to the adoption of such resolutions, Great Britain and Germany will immediately take the necessary steps to put it into(Initialled) Hn. D&apos;Ab.-       -   &apos; - -      St.  .  - F. L. R.V x   March 24: 1925.    -r^V.&apos;*&apos; The Devisehbeschaffungsstelle G.iri.b.h. is the agency through which the German Government obtains the foreign currencies it requires.
II.   -Letter dated March 25, 1925, from Mr. Leith Ross to the Agent-General for reparation Payments. &apos;  -Dear Mr. Gilbert,      . British Embassy. Berlin, March 25. 1925.  .I ENCLOSE herewith the draft of an agreement between the British and German Governments for the amendment of the system of collecting of the Reparation Recovery Act levy, which has been initialled by the German and British representatives, subject to reference to our respective Governments.As you will see, the last paragraph provides that the agreement will be brought into force immediately on the adoption by the Transfer Committee and by the Reparation Commission of appropriate resolutions giving effect to its provisions.I hope that it may be possible for you to secure such approval by the Transfer Committee, so far as it is concerned, during its present session, in order that the agreement may be put before the Reparation Commission at its meeting on the 30th instant.The points on which the British Government desire an assurance from the Transfer Committee are the following     :(a.) That the Transfer Committee agrees that the payments under the procedure now proposed will be regarded, for all purposes, as enjoying the same rights as the present Reparation Recovery Act receipts.(&amp;.) That the committee Will authorise the Agent-General to make the transfers to the British Government under paragraph 5 without restriction so long as no restriction is imposed upon the transfer to other Allied Powers of their respective shares of the annuity.(c.) That the committee will endeavour to give the British Government reasonable notice of any intention to restrict transfer.id.) That in the event of such restrictions being imposed the: payments to Great Britain under this agreement and payments to other Powers in the form of deliveries in kind will be accorded substantially similar treatment.Special reference should perhaps be made to certain points in the agreement : (1.) The second clause of paragraph (1) refers to the possibility of a modification in the rate of the levy. This is a right under the Act which it is necessary to maintain, but I feel sure that, if the Transfer Committee so desires, the British Government would see no difficulty in giving an assurance that an increase beyond the present rate of 26 per cent, would not be effected without the previous agreement of the Transfer Committee.(2.) It is understood that you will keep the R,eichsbank informed of the amount of the monthly payments which should be made to your account under paragraph (A).(3.) It is understood that the debits against the British Government in respect of the Recovery Act payments made by you under paragraph 5 will be calculated at the third fine gold rate prior to the date of payment in accordance with the ordinary rules governing debits.I trust that the Transfer Committee may find it possible to adopt appropriate resolutions concerning the main points brought out above in order that the. draftDraft Declaration by the German Exporter.THE undersigned firm undertakes herewith to surrender immediately to the Reichsbank in sterling, against reimbursement of the counter-value in Reichsmarks, 30 per cent, of the invoice value of every export transaction to Great Britain. The surrender of sterling will be simultaneously accompanied by a declaration according to a prescribed form, whereon will be found the name of the firm surrendering the foreign currencies, the date of the surrender, and the amount in question.
agreement between the British and German Governments which it is.&apos;hoped may facilitate trade and commerce between the two countries may be brought speedily into effect.Yours sincerely,F. W. LEFTH ROSS.III.Resolutions adopted by the Transfer Committee.THE following resolutions were unanimously adopted by the Transfer Committee at its sixth meeting held in Berlin on the 23rd-25th March, 1925 :  (No. 1.)The Transfer Committee hereby takes note of the draft protocol initialled by the representatives of the British Government and the German Government, which has been submitted with the letter of the 25th March, 1925, from the repre-sentative of the British Government to the chairman, and recognises that the provisions of said protocol, if and when approved by the Reparation Commission and put into force by the two Governments directly concerned, will be regarded as amending the method of administering the &quot;German Reparation (Recovery) Act, 1921.&quot; and that, in so far as the Transfer Committee is concerned, the payments to be made thereunder to the British Government and/or by way of reimbursing the German exporters are to be regarded as enjoying the same position under the Dawes Plan and the London Protocol for all purposes of discharging the reparation obliga-tions of the German Government to the British Government as the payments and/or reimbursements made under the method of administering the Recovery Act hitherto in. force.(No. 2.)From and after the date of the coming into force of said protocol, the Agent-General for Reparation Payments is hereby authorised, out of any available funds in the Annuity, to make such payments by way of reimbursement to German exporters and such payments to the British Government as may from time to time become payable under the terms of said protocol, subject to such restrictions as the Transfer Committee may impose in the exercise of its powers under the Plan, in order to protect the German currency and exchange.-. (No. 3.)If at any time it becomes necessary to impose any such, restrictions the Transfer Committee will endeavour to give the British Government reasonable notice of any intention to restrict payments under said protocol.(No. 4.)If at any time it becomes necessary to impose any such restrictions on payments Under said protocol, the Agent-General for Reparation Payments and the Transfer Committee will also endeavour, with due regard to their duties under the Plan, to impose them in so far as practicable in such manner that all deliveries in kind (including payments under the Reparation Recovery Acts) shall receive substantially similar treatment,o

</content>
</cab>
