<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/24/0 images: 23-24</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MIIHJTES OF A MBgTIHG OF THE MAJjj POWER COMMITTEE (vide War Cabinet 201, Minute I) held at 2, Whitehall Gardens at 3.3Q p,m. on August 21st,1917.Present:lord Miner   (in the Chair) Lt.-Gen.eral J. C. Smuts. Mr. G. I. Barnes, Mi P.The following also attended :Sir Auckland C. Geddes, K.C.B. Mr.Geo. H. Roberts, M.P. . Mr .G.M.Hodgson. Mr.Sandford Fawcett.Captain The Eon.W.Ormsby Gore. M.P.(Secretary)The Committee considered the Memorandum (G.T.1736) by the Director General of National Service, dated 16th August,1917 entitled &quot;Payment of Substitution Volunteers&quot;, and a copy of a letter Ho.23517/17 dated July 18th, 1917 addressed by the Secretary to the Treasury to the Secretary of the National Service Department.The Committee decided that National Service Substitution Volunteers should be indemnified against loss of rates of pay on transfer in the same manner, and. should be treated in the matter of pay and allowances, as War Munitions Volunteers, and instructed the Secretary to draft a letter to the Treasury (copy attached) informing that Department of the Committee^ decision.W, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 22nd.August, 1917.
6/J/222Siid.Augu.st, 1917.Sir,I am directed to inform you that the Cabinet Committee, consisting of Lord Milner, Mr.Barnes and General Smuts, which was appointed loj Minute 1 of War Cabinet 201 to examine and decide on behalf of the Cabinet all questions of recruiting and man-power, have had under their examination the question cf the rates of pay to be given to National Service Substitution Volunteers, which formed the subject of your letter No.23517/17 of 18th July, 1917.     After giving careful consideration to thab letter and the communication enclosed with it from the Ministry of Labour, the Committee have come to the conclusion that it is impossible, having regard to the pledges given in this matter by the Government and to the urgent need of expediting the Substitution Scheme, to treat the national Service Sabstitution -Volunteers differently from the War Munitions Volunteers, and that the provisions as to rates of pay and separation allowance which prevail with regard to the latter class of Volunteers should be extended to the former.,A copy of this letter has been cent to the. Director-General of Hational Service.I amSir,.Your obedient servant, (Sgd). W. Ormsby Gore.Assistant Secretary,1. Heath, LCB, , E o.C * v. 0. , F .R. S.TREASURY,.   S.W..

</content>
</cab>
