<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/24/0 images: 155-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
P/HS/553SUMMARY OF BLOCKADE INFORMATIONAug. 17 - 23, 1917.ur tii,sEBSAinrA metallurgical expert of neutral nationality, whohas recently returned from Germany, reports that the monthly deliveries of steel are short of the quantities required by 100,000 to 150,000 tons.     There is still copper available for the essential war industries, and in many districts of the Empire this metal has not yet been requisitioned.     But the shortage of nickel constitutes the gravest problem which the metal industries have to face,The collieries are sbort of labour, although they employ Russian, Polish and Serbian prisoners on a great scale; the production of coal in Westphalia is 80fa of the normal, butPEMARg.      The Danish Government propose to supply Germany v.ith increased supplies of bacon in exchange for petroleum, and have declined a counter-proposal from H.M. Government to guarantee fixed prices for a definite percentage of the exports of Danish bacon.     The effect of the bargain with Germany is that she may receive as much as .50^ of the exports of Danish bacon over a definite period.   In view of the scarcity of imported fodder-stuffs the small Danish farmers have been ordered by the Victualling Commission to kill three-quarters of their sows and not to breed from the rest.     Consequently there will be, in the immediate future, an increased export of inferior bacon;   bat eventually the bacon exports will be much reduced.elsewhere seldom rises above 60/!This informant does notanticipate that German war industries will be seriouslyshort of materials before the spring of 1918.
Deliveries of German coal are likely to be exceptionally small in the autumn and Ydnter.     The Danes are anxious to obtain from us an additional 100,000 tons of coal a month, They hope that the German Government will undertake not to molest Danish colliers when sailing in ballast to the United Kingdom.It is reported that large quantities of dried vege-tables, fresh vegetables and tfruit are being licenced for export from Denmark to Germany.     The export of live cattle to Germany continues, at the rate of about 5,000 head a week.. Sir Iff. Findlay thinks that, if the United States per-sist in demanding the total cessation of export of fish from Norway to Germany, the Norwegian Government will give way on this point.    But he also thinks that we should, in that case, propitiate the Norwegian fishermen, whose good will is valuable to our naval forces, by purchasing a con-siderable part, say one half, of the herring catch at a fair price.Germany is refusing to permit the export to Norway of iron and other materials for ship building, on the ground that any new Norwegian ships would, directly or indirectly, be of service to Great Britain.     There is no reason to be surprised at this policy;   some time ago Germany came to a similar decision regarding the Danish ship building industry.is the Norwegian oanners decline to reduce their prices, our War Office will not purchase any canned goods, in Norway.&quot;    It is possible that the United States may pro-hibit the export of tin-plates to the European neutrals; in which case the canners can easily be brought to terms.
1463.EfBTHSRLMDS.       The German Government will not guarantee to supply the Netherlands with more than 100,000 tone of coal a month unless Dutch miners are sent to the German mines, The Dutch have been asked to provide a credit of 40 gulden on every ton of German coal exported to Holland in excess of 100,000 tons a month.     This credit would be used for German purchases is the Netherlands.     The Dutch are apparently un-willing to accept such onerous terms; but, like the Swiss, they will probably br obliged to do so, unless we can supply them with considerable quantities of British coal,SBAIK. Most of the mines in the Bilbao district have resumedwork, and on Aug. 19 it was reported that the Santander miners were returning to the pits&apos;.   The strikes are reputed to have been partly due to German Influence, but the evidence on this subject lacks precision.leogitations have been opened in London for a new agreement with Spain fin substitution for the Cortina Agree-ment).     We are ready to suooly Spain with coal, of Spanish^ ships are sent to fetch it.   In return we shall expect the Spanish Government to allow us to export iron-ore freely from Spain; we shall also expect them to requisition and place at our disposal a certain proportion of Spanish tonnage.&quot;ITZBRMND.       Sir E. Bumbo Id has warned certain of the friendlySwiss bariics that they may be exposing themselves to reprisals if they assist in. floating the German loan which is contem-plated under the new Gernan-Swiss Agreement. But the Swiss Minister for Foreign Affairs represents that, if the loan is not raised, Germany will charge 200 francs a ton, instead of 90 francs, for the eo$l which she supplies. Sir H. Eumbold
1474.fsuggests that we should waive our objections to the German loan on condition that the Swiss banks agree to place a similar credit at our disposal.GREECE. 2he recent fire at Salonica has destroyed about two-thirds of the walled part of the town, and most of the available supplies,     There will therefore be urgent need of further supplies from abroad.     We are assuring the Greek Government that we shall do everything in our power for the relief of the sufferers.UflTED STATSS.    Mr. Y/ilson is considering the advisability of pro-hibiting all exports to neutral European countries. But he has expressed his reluctance to starve any neutral country.   Hr. Hoover, the American Pood Controller, holds that Norway and Holland are in no urgent need of American cereals and that Denmark can feed her population for the next twelve months.   He therefore feels entitled to reserve practically all the available stocks for the use of the Allies.   He is anxious that the Allies should make all their purchases of all American food-stuffs through a common pur-chasing agency (preferably through the Wheat Commission) in order to defeat the manoeuvres of speculators, who are forcing up the prices of wheat, sugar and packers&apos; products. If prices continue to rise it may well happen that public opinion in the United States will demand drastic restric-tions on the export of food even to the Allies..   GERMAN SUBMARIITE CAMPAIGN.       The following is a summary of thelosses of merchant tonnage, due to enemy activity, which; were officially reoorted in the period Aug. 17 - 23, inclusive.     Smacks and trawlers are omitted:-
Steamships   (500 tons gross &amp; o^er)British   .......       94,480 tons gross,Allied &amp; ffeutral      38,023     &quot;       rtSailing        (100 tons gross &amp; over):-YesselsBritish   .......Allied &amp; Neutral 748   &quot;Grand Total   ...      133.S51   &quot;Total British 94,480   &quot;11H. V/. C D,oDo-War Trade Intelligence Department24. Aug. 1917,

</content>
</cab>
