<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/24/0 images: 160-161</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
\       -v-&apos;-/o / operations.Sf%&amp;^ yrom:-. General Delme Radcliffe, Italy.Operations.S E C R E T.yTo :-*C.I.G.SWar Office.24.8.17.3.15 a.itu338.     August 23rd.10 o&apos;clock this evening situation:-2nd Army.   On the Bainsizza plateau there is little change in the front line of the Italians,all units being engaged in consolidating positions held while preparations are in progress for further advance.       On account of steepness of ground and absence of roads by which to get troops, stores and heavy material on to the plateau it is exceedingly difficult but some batteries of field artillery have been already got to the top.     Meanwhile an immense amount of work is being put into road making.   Absence of water and the heat are additional difficulties and many men and animals have died of thirst.       Water is being taken up in barrels etc. and fortunately some strong springs have to-day been found from which water will be laid down on to the front,,   Enemy&apos;s artillery has shown little activity and enemy is evidently making efforts to withdraw what he can.     Austrian 21st, 106th and (?) 24th Divisions are considered practically destroyed while 50th and 1st Divisions have had losses.       It is now known that 10th Division is coming into line of the Bainsizza plateau and contact has been obtained.       3rd Army.        There has been practically no change during day on the Carso except thatft; some units have slightly improved and all are consolidatingtheir positions while 8.11 the brigades in 1st line are being relieved by fresh brigades.     Italian positions on right flank of the 13th Corps between Medeazza and the Seahave
2.have &quot;been especially improved though. Austrians still hold point 28 west of San Giovanni.     Austrians still keep the 73rd and 41st Divisions intact in reserve hut all the other divisions are known to have suffered very heavy losses. I shall forward tomorrow statements shewing changes and wastage of units on the Austrian front.     There were only a few prisoners taken on the 3rd Army front today hut the grand total counted so far exceeds 21,000, Much artillery material has been captured,     While Italian aircraft were very busy all today and have again dropped a large number of bombs etc. in the enemy&apos;s lines, enemy&apos;s aircraft is conspicuous by its absence. Morale of the Italian troops is excellent and prospects are very good;   C adorn a told me this   morning that the ammunition supply is his only source of anxiety as he is, not sure whether he has enough heavy ammunition to make the success of this offensive as complete as it would be were his ammunition supply more satisfactory.

</content>
</cab>
