<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/24/0 images: 164-165</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos;1153G.2.-1845WAR  . 0 A B I IT S 2.RETURN OFJ&amp;Oo 46 SQUADBOH ROYAL(Copy of letter from Chief of the Imperial General Staff * to Secretary,. V/ar Cabinet, forwarding.a despatch of PieId-Marshal Sir Douglas Haig).&apos; . .     I.    .Chief of the Imperial General staff to Secretary. War Cabinet?12l/Franee/l015. v/ar Office,London, S.iY-Secretary,&quot; War Cabinet.V&apos;-&quot;.       ..Please bring the attached communication from Sir Douglas. Kaig before the War Cabinet on llon&amp;ay next as it refers to - an -Urgent matterc     It is necessary that Lord French should attend and also the DcGUvLA-     She only question requiring Cabinet decision is the return of IJo9 45 Squadron to France, ;   ihe other questions raised are&apos; being dealt with by the far Office and. Admiralty, -  (Signed). V?.B.B0ESR!DS03Jf&apos;&apos;. &apos;      I ; General.24th August, 1917c Chief of the Imperial. General Staff,II.Field-Marshal jir Doiiglas. Haig to Chief of, the Imperial General Staff.Io.o 0:.BS/183Y.6 General Headquarters,British Armies in France.23rd August, 1917,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.In view of the communication from the First Sea Lord on the subject of maintenance of the Royal Haval Air Service Squadrons, a cop;? of which was -forwarded under cover of your Memorandum Ho,: 121/Frahce/1015&quot;of the 21st instant, I strongly . urge that ;Ho 9&apos; 46-Squadron, .Royal Flying Corps.-, which was sent to-England in July,, should be returned to France at once.
The increased air activity of the enemy on the &quot;battle front, combined with the decreased strength of the R.F.A.S. Squadrons renders it essential that the air forces of the British Armies in Prance should be strengthened at the earliest possible opportunity,, and I strongly recommend the following measures being carried out as early as possible :-(a) The immediate replacement of !-To. 10   R.N.A.S.. Squadron by No. 46 Squadron from England, the pilots and machines of ITo. 10   R.N.A.S. Squadron being transferred to the other R.1T.A.S. Squadrons to increase their strength.I shall be glad to hear by telegram whether this can be arranged.,(b) A second R.2J.A.S. Squadron to be replaced by Xo*84vSquadron, R.F.C., which is due to arrive about the end of September.It would be of the greatest assistance if the despatch of this squadron could be hastened.(c) A third R.N.A.S, Squadron to be replaced by Ho.6^ 64 or 28 Squadron, R.F.C, as soon as they can be sent to Prance.(d) The two remaining R.2T.A.S. Squadrons to be maintained in France till the middle of November.I fully realise that the measures proposed above will render the air forces in France considerably weaker than I had anticipated, but in the circumstances I had no option but to recommend the gradual withdrawal (or rather amalgamation) of the R.17.A.S. Squadrons in spite of the invaluable assistance they have already given.(Signed)     D. HAIG.Field-Marshal Commanding-in-Chief British Armies in France.

</content>
</cab>
