<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/24/0 images: 168-169</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
a(Copy of/Nnte frcm Foreign Office to Director of Military Intelligence and Telegram frcn Sii G. Barclay)(162478/W/19)       -Foreign Office to D.g,I. Y/ar Office. Very Urgent.The Under Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs presents his compliments to tha Director ofMilitary Intelligence and is directed by Mr. Secretary.Balfour to transmit to him, herewith, a copy of atelegram from His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Jassj&apos;, relativeSir G.     to the question of compensation for the plant and Stocks BarclayTel.463A which it may be necessary t? destroy in Koumania. Aug.14thMr. Balfour realises that in equity the Roumanian Government should themselves compensate private owners for the destruction rendered necessary by the Military situation, but it is clear that if this des-truction is really a vital military necessity and one which cannot be effected without the co-operation of the Roumanian Government, it may be necessary to sSouse this co-operation by some form of joint financial guarantee.* Mr. Balfour feels, indeed, that in that event the cost should be equally divided between Prance, Italy, Russia, and Great Britainf but in any case he is of opinion that the matter should be submitted for the decision of the War Cabinet before any reply is returned to Sir G. Barclay1s telegram,. Lord Hardinge of Pen*hurst is to suggest,therefore, that the Chief of the Imperial-General Staff should raise this question with the War Cabinet at the next convenient opportunity.Foreign Office,  .August 23rd,.1917.G.T. 1847 WAR 0A5IHET.COMPENSATION FOR THE PLANT AND STOCKS MICH IT MAY BS NECESSARY TO DESTROY IN ROUMANTA.
2T0.463A. TELEGRAM TROM SIR G. BARCLAYTO FORfiIGH OPFICii.Urgent---------- &quot;---&quot;       *&quot;14th August 1917.So far Roumanian (Government) seem disposed to-evacuate towards the rear (?gradually) and to arrange for eventual destruction of factories machinery and rolling stock that would otherwise fall into enemy hands in all of which they are accepting indications of our Of1&apos;e.rs *     But how far actual destruction will materialize later on, I am not sure,   It might depend a good, deal on whether Roumanian Government were let to expect compensation.Should it at any moment appear necessary am I authorized to make any (?declaration) to Roumanian Government as regards compensation for such destruction? If so in what form should I uake it?   It seems to me that there should be distinction &quot;between (l) Such destruction if carried out independently of our officers of. which of course they would have no knowledge, and (2) destruction carried out by thoir or under their advice or with thoir co-operation and again between destruction of privately owned property and that owned by Government, such as railway stocks and workshops.I would add that if our very small British force is to succeed efficiently in destructive work there will be no time to take more than.the most meagre notes even of destruction&apos;carried out with their co-operaticn.Please reply to this telegram .not only ta..me, but also Military Attache as may be compelled to leave earlier than he.

</content>
</cab>
