<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/24/0 images: 185-186</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SEC HE T.G.T.1855.WAR CiiBIlIET.174TRANSPORT OF ROUMANIAN REFUGEES ACROSS TEE -   NORTH SEA.(Letter from the Foreign Office to the SecretaryWar Cabinet.)Ho. 16410.6/30 /W.Foreign Office.Confidential &amp; Immediate.August 24th, 1917.Sir,I am directed hy Mir..Secretary Balfour to refer to the telegram No.436 (attached) dated the 7th.instant . from His Majesty-8 Minister at Jassy, containing a message-from Mr.Take Jonescu to the Prime Minister respecting the provision of transport for Roumanian refugees across the North Sea in the event of the evacuation of the whole of Roumania &quot;becoming necessary.Mr.Jonescu has expressed to Sir G.Barclay the hope that his appeal may receive early and favourable consi&amp;era-tion, and Mr.Bslfour would accordingly be glad to learn whether: the, War Cabinet have yet taken sny decision in the matter.Following from Mr.Take Jonescu for Mr.Lloyd (TGeorge, omitted.)I venture again to appeal to your generous sentiments.     Circumstances compel us to evacuate last portion of our territory.     In view of limited means of transport in..Russia we must begin to evacuate before danger becomes more imminent.     Otherwise nothing could be saved.    Families going to Russia are exposed to all the uncertainty of political situation in that country and to enormous coat, of living there.     Many Roumanians are asking to be enabled to go themselves and especially to send their wives and children to the West..     I under-stand restrictions on sea crossing so long as it was aI am etc.(Signed) R. Graham.The Secretary,to the War Cabinet.Telegram from Sir G.Barclay to Foreign Office. No.436 ( )     7th August, 1917.     .
question of what might appear to he merely a capricious desire to travel &quot;but now that it has become a necessity I beg you to take initiative and to accord means of crossing Hcrth Sea tc Roumanian fugitives of course at their own risk and peril.     Their case is worse than that of the Belgians and as only (those) who have consid-erable means would be able to cross the sea 1 do not think number of persons involved would exceed from 1,500 to 2,000 but it would be a great consolation to us to be able to toll those who sre really anxious about fate of their families that they can go to Western Europe,   We do not wish to leave to the Germans the elite of our nation nor to plunge others into acute anxiety as to the fate of their families.I address myself personally to you as a man of large views and of generous ideas.Repeated to Petrograd.

</content>
</cab>
