<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/24/0 images: 202-204</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
g.T. 1860. WAR CABINET.RBSfflRlCTIOE OF SHIPPIflS - PROPOSAL THAT JFRBIGgn? SKOUldJ BE SEFT DIRECT TO DESTINATION PROM PLACE Off ORIGIN.(Letter from Shipping Controller to Secretary, War Cabinet, and letter from Sir John Bllerman to thePrime Minister).Ministry of Shipping, Dear Sir Maurice, St,James1s Park, S.W.1,With reference to Sir John  Herman1 s letter dated August 1st (copy attached), which was sent &quot;by the Prime Minister to the First Lord and &quot;by him to me,. I have to say that the suggestions mado have been very carefully considered.     Yfe think that the most hopeful is the proposal that, as far as possible, supplied for the fighting forces shall he carried direct from the country of origin to the base of the forces, instead of as seems to &quot;be the case;now, coming, to a large extent, via England.This, however, is a proposal which touches the Supply &amp; Purchasing Departments of the War Office and Ministry of Munitions more directly than the Shipping Controller, and before effective action can be taken here It is considered that the Wer Cabinet should lay down the principle as one which is -to be followed..I suggest, therefore, that an instruction be issued by the Y/ar Cabinet. that the principle of direct shipment from source of origin to ultimate destination Is to be followed as far as practicable and that to bring this into effect the Depart-ments making demands for shipping should at once prepare state-ments as to:(1)   The places of origin of the commodities in which they are Interested, and(E)   the ultimate destination of these,and send them to the Shipping Controller, who will arrange the shipments in consultation with the Departments concerned.I am afraid that unless this is done, it will be impossible to get effective action within a reasonable time.The other points in Sir Johnrs letter are beingdealt with,Yours sincerely,(signed) J. P. MACLAY,Lt.Col,Sir M,P.A.Eankey, K.C.B. . Z\ Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.25th August, 1917.
2 Duke&apos;s Drive, Eastbourne.August 1st, 1917,Hear Mr. Lloyd George,Since attending the War Cabinet Meetings, I have had some discussions with Sir Joseph Maolay on suggestions I put forward, and others I should have put forward at the War Cabinet Meeting had there Veen time, some of which I&apos; foel confident he \s giving effect to.As you may remember, I drev; attention at the War Cabinet Meeting to the quantity of food having once come into this country which again leaves for the troops in Salonica, Malta, Egypt, India, and also to a.small extent for civilians at these aiid other centres, and pointed out that, in view of the extreme fbod shortage likely to arise prior to the termination of the War, this should be obviated by the adoption of other methods, so that plactically no food wa3 exported.   (The submarine menace is still constantly with us, and the preposition put forward by Sir Morman Hill, Lord Inchcape, and myself, that it was essential to do everything possible to mirimise the tonnage coming to this country, wiihin the limits of brirgjng the necessary food and essential cargoes, until reasonably/ adequate protection could be afforded to the steamers by the Kavy, made me urge upon the Shipping Controller a suggestion by which certain tonnage coming to this country might be minimised, and also kept out of the danger zone until reasonably adequate protection is afforded by the lavy to all steamers, and thus form a eertajn reserve ? and also leave convoys for more of the remaining steamers.I would respectfully urge for your careful consideration the fact that it is not only the destruction cf the stea:::&apos;.r by enemy submarine, but it is the consequential loss of voyages over a period this steamer was able to make., so that although a steamer may only carry 10,000 tons, if she made 5/6 voyages in the year, 50/60,000 tons of yearly carrying capacity is in reality destroyedTIt was obvious to me in the suggestions I have made to Sir Joseph Maclay that as a War Department comes into effect,, as well as other Departments, great difficulty would arise by the change of methods of these Departments, and the obstacles they would put forward may be sufficient to preclude the suggestions being given effect to, and I therefore consider the matter of such importance to the country that I trespass upon your very valuable time with the suggestions so that they may be thoroughly consideredAs stated by mo at the War Cabinet Meeting, and confirmed &quot;by Sir Joseph Maclay, many of the steamers now loading in the ilorth Atlantic will be unable to face v/inter voyages7 but meny of the steamers could go to the ITorth Atlantic prior to&apos;the extreme winter, and then lead from there in the manner hereinafter suggested, as the voyage they would then be called upon to under-take would be more of a fair weather voyage.Briefly, my suggestion is to the fullest extent practic-able, all the food, munitions, stores, &amp;c, required in Egypt. Mesopotamia, and Salonica. should be sent&apos; from India, Canada, or Australia via the Cape, to Port Said for Egypt and Mesopotamia, and in the case of Salonica by a ferry service from Port Said,   2hat &apos;&quot; these steamers should carry a portion of their cargo to South Africa,
and that the holds so discharged should &quot;be filled up with coal for Port Said, thus materially reducing the quantity of Coal now leaving this country for Port Said.     In order to find homeward employment for the steamers,that the Cotton and other Egyptian products, which at present come through the Mediteirane&amp;n, should he sent from.Port Said via the Cape to this country (or to America), and by the time of arrival, in this country fair weather conditions will he commenc-ing to accrue in the Horth Atlantic again, or homeward cargoes from East and South African ports.     Personally, I should even carry this a stage furtherj and have the Hospital arrangements at suitable points in South Africa and not let the Hospital ships go through the danger zone, and similarly (hut of course this is not a shipping matter) it appears to me that wherever possible the replenishing of drafts should go by the same route from Canada or Australia.I v/ould point out that if this method was adopted the steamers would only be going through the danger zone once, i.e, from Dakar home, whilst under the present operation a steamer is in the danger zone from America to this country (where the cargo is dis-charged, it is remade - entailing considerable handling, congestion of ports, and extra coal), and it is in the danger zone between England and Gibraltar, also between Gibraltar and Alexandria or Salonica, and the boat on the return is again in the danger zone in the Mediterranean to Gibraltar, and again between GibxsJ.tar and the United Kingdom, or five times in the danger zone as against once under the other method.The steamers going into the Mediterranean to be limited to the lowest possible number, consistent with the carrying of Coal to Italy and ports that cannot be served except by returning direct, and even the Stores for Gibraltar and Malta I should send direct from America or Canada, loading Ore from Spain home.The difficulties in the way, it seems to me, are, the question of proper checking, fixing time fuses, and supervision in making up the packages etc. in Egypt or in America, Canada, or Australia where the various munitions, stores etc could be made up for use in the trenches or canteens.     If it is possible to put in the fusos and check the gauges here on arrival from Canada or America, surely by organisation of the War Department the same methods could be pursued abroad so that the steamers could avoid the danger zone, and the same be done at Port Said etc., and similar, if not quite exactly the same, food and stores packed and used, as unless something radical is done the Germans will sink so many steamers as to make the position irretrievable .I trust you will pardon my writing you, but I feel I should not be doing ray duty, since I was asked to attend certain of your Meetings, if I did not put my suggestions forward for.your personal Consideration, especially as at the first Meeting I attended you stated you were always willing to receive suggestions.I return to town on Tuesday next.Yours faithfully,(Sgd)     J.R.ELL8RI*LAtf.The Right Hon. D. Lloyd George, 10, -Downing Street, -S.W.

</content>
</cab>
