<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/24/0 images: 295-295</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
G.T.1875. VISIT OF LORD NOETHCLIFEE TO PANADA.(Copy of telegram from J,PolIorgan &amp; Go. New York, to Ilorgan. Grenfell &amp; Co., londjon.   Keoelyed 28th. August, 1917 10 a.m.)9972. Lord Northeliffe requests following ho transmitted to &quot;i/ar Cabihc,t ad .7alte r Long.   Copy to 0. J.Phillips.205.   I have accepted an invitation to visit Canada.   Since then ir Robert Bordcn has suggested that he should publish the. following announcement:^Begins      It is announced that Lord Northcliffo accompanied by several leading members of his staff will shortly visit Canada for the purpose of conferring with several Departments of the Canadian Government and also with the Canadian Board of Grain Supervisors, the Food Controller, and the Fuel Controller with respect to important matters in which co-operation between corresponding services in Great Britain, in the U.S.A. and in Canada is essential,   Questions with regard to provision of food supplies, particularly grain, flour, meats and fats will be taken up and dealt with.   It: is anticipated that the supply of tonnage and its increase through full use of all Canada^ ship-building facilities will receive attention.   Other Questions of importance will doubtless arise and the general purpose of the visit is to ensure the utmost unity of purpose and of effort in all activities rendered necessary by the war.   Ends, ily intention was to pay a visit of courtesy to Ottawa and I had no know-ledge that the Canadian Government desired to discuss the matters mention-od in the proposed paragraph.   I am aware from what I have learned in Washington that there are now several pressing matters requiring negotiation.   The terms of reference of my mission make no mention of such a conference as is proposed.   I do not know whether such a natter is really within the province of the Ambassador.   I should be glad of instructions ae I must reply to Sir Robert Bordcn at once     If it is your wish that I should go into these matters I propose taking with mc Sir 8. Yardman Lever, Sir Charles Gordon, a llcmber of the &quot;Cheat Export Co, Ino: Hoyden or Sparks and anyone else you may suggest.

</content>
</cab>
