<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/24/0 images: 299-299</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
  OR ST.. G.T.-1878   -   - &apos;         -.     ^&quot;WAR. . C A B I -N E T.SUPPLY &amp; DESPATCH 0? NAVAL GUNS TO RUSSIA.(Copy of letter from Ministry:of Shipping to Secretary, War Cabinet).Ministry of Shipping, St. James.13 Park, London, S.W. 1.01105/17 28th August, 1917.Sir,I am-directed by the Shipping Controller to inform you that the decision of the War Cabinet is urgently required on the question of despatching Naval guns to&apos; Russia.In July last the Russian Government Committee requestod the Ministry of Shipping.to despatch to Russia six : 14&quot; Naval guns constructed by Vickers.   The matter was referred to the Board, of Admiralty in view of the unsettled state of Russia, and the decision given, was that the guns should not be shipped. ..Since that time the matter has been deferred&apos;on-dne pretext or another, but on the 25th August the Russian Govern-ment Committee made a formal request that the guns be shipped forthwith.;The Shipping Controller also understands that Messrs. Vickers7. workmen, have sent a deputation to the Managers of that firm pointing out that a great deal of. overtime was worked throughout the whole of last Winter to enable them to be ready for shipment on the opening of the Summer season, and after spending so much labour and time in completing them.they:now see the guns lying; about Vickers1 works unused.. -   MessrsVickers have repeatedly requested the Ministry of Shipping to deal with the matter by removing the guns from their works;even if they cannot be shipped.- The matter -has therefore again been referred to theAdmiralty, and the Shipping Controller is informed that the First 3ea Lord wishes the matter brought before the War Cabinet for decision..   A copy of this letter has been sent to Lord Milner^s Committee....I am&apos;   Sir,&apos;Your obedient Servant -(Signed)   ,. JOHN ANDERSON,Lt.Col. Sir Maur 1 ce Hankey, X.C.B. ; ^Secretary to the U&quot;War. Cabinet,&quot;Whitehall, S.W.

</content>
</cab>
