<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/24/0 images: 359-362</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.)WAR CABINET.THE PROPOSED I JITTER-ALLY TRANSPORT CONFERENCE. ( Note   hy   the   Secretary )At the meeting of the War Cabinet held on August 50th, (War Cabinet 226, Minute 6) a certain misapprehension appeared to exist as to the precise motives of the proposal made at the recent Conference of the Allies at Paris for the assembly of an Inter-Ally Transport Conference in Paris.     It will perhaps be useful to the War Cabinet to have a summary of the origin and progress of this proposal.2.7 The suggestion was made at a meeting of the naval andmilitary representatives of the Allies on July 25th, 26th, which had before it a review of the maritime situation by Mr.Graeme Thomson.    From this review the Conference drew the following conclusions :-&quot;        It appears from the above that the situation will only begin to improve from November 1918, and that until then the total available tonnage of the Allies may be insufficient to cover all their requirements.It is therefore indispensable to establish a general list of the available tonnage for each of the Allies and to put cgainst it the figure of their requirements..    Only then will it be possible to take a decision as to the amount and the nature of the restrictions which will have to be made in the various kinds of traffic.Further, the transport of the American Army to France, has created fresh needs which we have to face. On this particular account, it is indispensable to draw - ;    up a statement of the total Inter-Allied tonnage, andit is only when this Is done that it will be possible to get an idea of the amount of transport, if any, which can be put at the disposal of tho American ,Army In France ,     it seems, on a first examination, that these means will be limited solely to the resources of the American mercantile marine as supplemented by their shipbuilding programme.The members of the Meeting consider that it is a most important point which must be cleared up-without delay, and ask that tho Allied Governments should take at once the necessary measures to that effect; with this end in view, &quot;a meeting of the representatives of&apos; the Transport Services of the Allies should be held in London at tho earliest opportunity. &quot; (G.T. 1534)3. It is understood that the main consideration whichinfluenced the Conference was a statement by General Pershing to the effect that the Government of the United States of America were inclined to transport all the requirements of their Army from America, irrespective of what could be more easily obtained in France or the United ICingdom.     For exaoplegj) RE frh 1895.
I was informed in Paris that a great quantity of wooden piles required for the construction of a harbour, as well as material for a great system of railway construction, much of which could be obtained &quot;in Europe, was to be imported from the United States. I understand the Conference felt that the best means of bring- -ing the necessary pressure on the United States Government to curtail their transport requirements was to hold a Transport Conference.4. The proposal was accepted by the main Conferencewithout much discussion, except that on the initiative of the Italian Admiral di Revel the question of the construction of unsinkable ships was referred to the Conference, and on the initiative of the Prime Minister, the date of the Conference was fixed for August 10th. (I.C- 24 (b )  ).5. On July 30th, the question came before the War Cabinet,who were informed that the proposal had been made by the British representatives with c view to finding out how many United States troops could be transported and maintained on the Western front, as the present proposals of the United States Military Authorities were regarded as extremely high.     The War Cabinet felt that we should guard, as far as possible, against any attempt on the pert of the Conference to create a shipping pool, it being highly undesirable and dangerous that the control of shipping should be taken out of cuaf hands and placed in those of the Allies as a whole.It was decided(a) that the First lord of the Admiralty should be asked to act as Chairman of the Conference and should draw up the Terms of Reference, and communicate them to the United States of America:(b) that the Shipping Controller, in consultation with the Departments concerned, should prepare a state-ment of the British requirements up to August, 1918. (War Cabinet   198, Minute 11).6. On August 3rd. the First Sea Lord informed the V;arCabinet that the representatives of the United States could not reach England by August 10th, and that the Conference would have to be postponed.     No action was taken, however, to postpone the Conference, and on August 8th, the Italian representatives had arrived in London.     The failure to notify the Allies concerned appears to have been due to a misunderstandin
\j   ihe War Cabinet were under the impression that the First Lord would take the Chair..   Sir Eric Geddes had told the Secretary that he was too busy to do go, &quot;out no formal communication   had been received, and the Secretary hvi gathered from telephonic enquiries&apos; that the Admiralty had the natter in hand.   Hot much harm was done, however, by this misunder,atandlng, as the Italian delegates had arrived early in order to discuss the question of an unsinkahle ship and v/ere diverted on to this topic.?.     These facts were discussed at the War Cabinet on August 9-, when the Shipping Controller urged the undesirability of holding the Transport Conference.   The discussion was very brief, and the Minutes do not&apos; record the Shipping Controller&apos;s reasons, which so&quot;far as I can recollect were not developed at any length,. Presumably however his objections v/ere founded on the desire to avoid the extension of Allied control over British ships, a danger alluded to when the question was first discussed by the War Cabinet,   At any rate the Shipping Controller&apos;s view was supported- by the Far Cabinet, and Sir Joseph Maclay was asked to deal with the matter, and, if possible, to prevent the reprea-entatives of the other Allies from coming to London (War Cabinet 206, Minute 3).8,      In the Minutes of August 17th, it is specifically laid down that the forthcoming I?aval Conference &quot;must be distinguished from the Transport Conference, which would&apos; probably not take place&quot; (War Cabinet 217,. Minute 1.2),9..      The question was again discussed briefly on August 50th, when it was mentioned that the Allies are making enquiries as to when the Conference will take place, but no decision was reached (War Cabinet 226, Minute 6),10. _ It is suggested that if the matter is left where it is, the British Representatives will be placed in an awkward predicate in the event of the question beins raised at the Inter-Ally Con-ference due to take place in September.     This arises from the following considerations(i) The Conference was originally suggested by the British naval. and.-military representatives.(ii) The date was fixed on the initiative of the British Prime Minister for August 10th.(iii)The British&apos; Government failed to notify their Allies until the last moment of the postponement&apos;of the Conference,  from August 10th, with the result that the Italian delegates actually came to London.-(iv)The&apos; British Government have, apparently without any explanation dropped the whole thing.11.     The pros and cons of the two course open appear to be as follows:-The argument against holding the Conference is the riskthat the Allies may insist on the pooling of British Shippingamong all the Allies, with a consequent loss of British control.
The -arguments tor holding the Conference are, that as the military plans of the Allies for 1918 depend upon the amount of shipping available, it, is essential, before these plans can be decided to draw up a sketch transport programme;   that this will provide a means of bringing home to the United States of America the necessity for economising tonnage in every possible direction.(Initialled) M.P.A.H.Secretary.3 Whitehall Gardens, 8.W., 31st August 1917.

</content>
</cab>
