<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/179/14 images: 255-266</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY &apos;S Government p;i 0C(74) 104 COPY NO      ( 010 September 1974 lCABINETI iREVIEW BODY ON ARMED FORCES&apos; PAY -PAY OF SERVICE MEDICAL AND DENTAL OFFICERSNote by the Secretary of State for defence i attach for the information of my Cabinet colleagues the Supplement tothe Third Report by the Armed forces Pay Review Body.    This dealswith the pay of Service medical and dental officers, and is to be published as a White Paper tomorrow, 11 September.R MMinistry of Defence/ 10 September 1974
CONFIDENTIAL-FINAL REVISEREVIEW BODYONARMED FORCES PAYPAY OF SERVICE MEDICAL and dental OFFICERS[to be published as Command 5729 by her Majesty &apos;s Stationery office price lip net]Supplement to Third Report1974Chairman:H. W. ATCHERLEY
REVIEW BODY ON ARMED FORCES PAYThe Review Body on Armed Forces Pay was appointed in September 1971 toadvise the Prime Minister on the pay and allowances of members of Naval,Military and Air Forces of the Crown and of any women&apos;s serviceadministered by the Defence Council.The members of the Review Body are:H. W. Atcherley (Chairman)1Admiral Sir Desmond Dreyer, G.C.B., C.B.E., D.S.C., J.P.Ewen M&apos;EwenJ. E. MortimerMiss A. R. Murray, J.P.C. A. Roberts, C.B.E.J. R. Sargent2The Secretariat is provided by the Office of Manpower Economics.Mr. J. E. Mortimer did not take part in this review of the pay of Service medical and Dental Officers.1 Also a member of the Top Salaries Review Body.2 Also a member of the Review Body on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos; Remuneration.
PAY OF SERVICE MEDICAL AND DENTAL OFFICERS1. Medical and dental officers in the armed forces are a self-containedgroup for pay purposes, and their pay is considered in the light of the decisionsthat follow recommendations by the Review Body on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos;Remuneration as they affect General Medical Practitioners in the national health Service (NHS). For this reason, it could not be considered in ourThird Report.1 Certain of the recommendations in that Report were, however,of general application throughout the Services. As a result, in common withother servicemen and women, doctors and dentists already benefit from theintroduction of threshold arrangements and from certain new or revisedallowances, including the flat-rate daily payment for all ranks up to and including Brigadier who serve continuously in Northern Ireland for more than14 days. At the same time, the revised charges for food and accommodation which we recommended apply also to Service doctors and dentists.mk   - -::V:&apos; , -.  J&apos;/. jj- V:.:. ;s .&apos;   /    - &apos;2.&apos; We thought it right in our Third Report both to indicate the extent towhich the recognition of the special features of Service life fall short of what we believe to be justified, and to re-state in some detail the principles on which both the military salary and the charges for food and accommodation havebeen based since 1970.2 In the same way, we consider this a suitable occasion on which to describe again the standards by which the pay of Service medical and dental officers is assessed. The aim is to provide, over! a career fromCaptain to Colonel before the addition of the X factor, average earnings equalto the average net earnings3 of general medical practitioners in the national health Service. The pay of the medical and dental Brigadier is designed toprovide a reasonable differential over the maximum pay of the medical Colonel,and a logical progression to the pay of the medical Major General (which is outside our terms of reference). The criterion of &quot; the average net earnings ofgeneral medical practitioners in the National Health Service &quot; is necessarilyimprecise, if only because the average for a particular year cannot be knownwith certainty until long after it has ended. It follows, therefore, that in recommending Service salaries for a period ahead, we have to use the bestforward estimate of the average net earnings of general medical practitioners inthe NHS for the same period. The Review Body on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos;Remuneration itself provides an estimate of the average net remuneration1that its recommendations are intended to produce, and we make use of this,the most authoritative, estimate. If we are to do this, we have to defer our consideration of the pay of Service doctors and dentists until decisions havebeen taken on those recommendations.1 Review Body on Armed Forces Pay: Third Report 1974, Cmnd. 5631.&apos; ibid, Chapter 1.3 ie net of practice expenses.4 The &quot; intended average net earnings &quot; of a general practitioner is the amount the review body on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos; Remuneration calculate should be received, net of expenses,by the &quot; average &quot; practitioner as a result of their recommendations for fees and allowances for the items of his work for the National Health Service. These include standard and,supplementary capitation fees, basic practice allowance, a supplementary practice allowance for night and weekend responsibilities, fees for vaccinations, for treatment of temporaryresidents and for emergency treatment. A proportion of practice expenses are reimbursedby direct payments but the remainder have to be met out of the gross remuneration from fees and allowances.
3. Forward estimates are unlikely to coincide regularly and exactly withthe historic figures of average net earnings. But we would not expect to haveto make retrospective adjustment unless, taking one year with another, itcould be demonstrated that the method adopted did not provide the compara-bility with the NHS general medical practitioner that is its aim. Certain&apos;doubts have been expressed to us on the adequacy of the criterion as it hasbeen interpreted and applied since it was introduced in 1969-70. The british medical Association have told us that, in their view, the criterion should, and indeed was intended to, comprehend the total earnings from all sources ofgeneral medical practitioners in the NHS. The Ministry of Defence also havequestioned whether it is right to use earnings from the NHS alone as thestandard of comparison for the pay of Service medical and dental officers.14. We recognise that every pay system needs to be examined from time totime, so that change may be introduced where it is shown to be necessary: inthis case, the long-standing interpretation of the remuneration of the analogueof general medical practitioners in the NHS has been questioned, and we intend to examine the structure and pay levels of Service medical and dental officers in the light of present-day requirements during our next review, when we shall take into account the views that have been expressed to us. This will entail consideration of a range of factors on which we have no evidence atpresent.5. The BMA have emphasised to us the importance of an early report and,on this occasion, because this supplementary review is part of the review thatformed the basis of our Third Report and the increases will be effective from1 April 1974, our recommendations are made within the provisions of the stage 3 Pay Code2 in the same way exactly as in the main review. The recom-mendations in the Fourth Report of the Review Body on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos;Remuneration were also made in this context: they have been accepted bythe Government and the report has been published.3 They are designed toproduce an increase in the average net remuneration of general medical practitioners in the NHS and, in the same way as in the 1973 Report, to allow for a modest increase in earnings from other official sources.4 The recom-mended total increase in the average net earnings of the GMP is  377, ofwhich  335 falls within the pay limits and  42 is met from the flexibility marginpermitted by the Pay Code.6 The balance of the increase within the individualpay limit of  350&quot; which is estimated to be taken up by increased earnings fromother official sources is, therefore,  15. Because Service medical and dental officers are not in a position to earn additional fees from other official sources,we took the view last year that the increase justified by comparison with earnings1 The Report of the Defence Medical Services Inquiry Committee 1973 also drew attentionto the fact that some general practitioners in the NHS earn more than the average (para-graph 208 and recommendation (78)).&quot;The provisions are in Statutory Instrument 1973 No. 1785, The Counter-Inflation Officeand Pay Code) (No. 2) Order 1973.8 Cmnd. 5644, June 1974.4 A General Medical Practitioner in the NHS may receive fees from other official sourcesfor service outside his practice responsibilities: examples include locum work in hospitals,medical examinations for Government Departments and Local Authorities and for the Police.6 Counter-Inflation (Price and Pay Code) (No. 2) Order 1973, paragraphs 139 and 140.6 ibid, paragraph 138.
from the NHS should not be restricted on this account. We take the same view now, and we conclude that the increase in the average earnings of general medical practitioners in the NHS on which the increase in pay of Servicemedical and dental officers should be based is  392 (that is,  377 plus  15).6. A further adjustment has to be made. The most recent estimate ofthe average net remuneration of general medical practitioners in the NHSfor 1973-74 is  5,770V or  20 more than the intended average net remuneration of  5,750 which the recommendations in the Third Report (1973) of the review body on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos; Remuneration were designed to produce,and on which the recommendations in the supplement to our Second Report2were based. Under the provisions of the Pay Code, the increase recommended in the Fourth Report of the Review Body on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos; Remunera-tion has to be added to the base figure of  5,770, and an average increase of 412 in the pay of Service medical and dental officers can therefore be justifiednow on the basis of comparison with intended average net earnings of general\ medical practitioners in the NHS: Estimated average net earnings of GMPs in the NHS in1973-74 .........     .....&apos;.     ...      ... ;   ...       5,770Add the estimated increase in fees from &quot;other official sources&quot; in 1973-74 ...     ...     ...     ......... 10Add the increase recommended in 1974-75 (including  15increase in fees from &quot; other official sources &quot;)   ...... 3926,172Deduct the &quot; intended average net earnings &quot; from NHS in1973-74 ( 5,750) plus the  10 increase in fees from &quot; otherofficial sources &quot;, adopted in 1973-74 as a basis for the pay of Service medical and dental officers       ......      ...       5,760Overall difference...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...... 4127. We now recommend new rates of pay for medical and dental officers from Captain to Brigadier, for provisionally registered medical practitioners(PRMPs) and for medical and dental cadets, in the light of the recommendations for general medical practitioners in the NHS and taking into account evidence submitted to us by the Ministry of Defence and by the British Medical Associa-tion (who also gave oral evidence). We need to satisfy ourselves that the increases which we recommend comply with the provisions of the Stage 3 pay code, and we have therefore considered these calculations in relation to them.The pay limit under the Code, in terms of the maximum amount by which theaverage pay bill per head of a group may be increased in a 12-month period, is either i.  7 per cent of the average pay bill per head of the group for thepreceding 12-month period; or1 Cmnd. 5644, paragraph 48.&quot;Review Body on Armed Forces Pay. Pay of Service Medical and Dental Officers:Supplement to Second Report 1973, Cmnd. 5450; and Review Body on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos;Remuneration. Third Report 1973, Cmnd. 5353, paragraph 34.f&apos;\ ,3 &apos;
subject to a further limit of  350 a year for any individual2. An increase inthe pay limit of up to 1 per cent of the pay bill (or one-seventh of  2-25 perweek per head) is also allowed, inter alia where a settlement incorporates, changes in pay structures or grading structures or in systems of paymentdesigned to remedy anomalies or to secure specific improvements in efficiency3.8. The pay limit of 7 per cent of the average pay bill provides more thanenough for an increase of  350 for all Service doctors and dentists at all ranksfrom Captain to Brigadier as a principal pay increase. This leaves a balanceof  62 by comparison with the average increase of  412 which can be justified on the basis of comparison with the earnings of the general medical practitionerin the NHS. This balance can be met only to the extent that the requirements for the use of the flexibility margin are observed and within the financial provi-sion available under it4. It is not enough to point to the use of the flexibilitymargin by the Review Body on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos; Remuneration as themeans of modifying the fee structure applicable to general medical practitionersin the NHS, to claim equal justification for its use in the armed forces, where nosuch fee structure exists: we need to satisfy ourselves that the use of the flexibilitymargin is justified in armed forces terms.9. A flat rate cash increase of  350 at all points in the pay scales fromCaptain to Brigadier would be admissible under the Pay Code and can bejustified both by the external criterion and by the need to improve recruitment(a point to which the BMA attached great importance in evidence to us);but it would run counter to the principles which we have adopted hitherto indistributing increases in pay, and which we consider should continue. these principles recognise the need to provide incentives both to achieve higher rank and to transfer at appropriate stages from short service commissions to permanentregular commissions. In our view, rather higher increases in pay, commensurate with higher rank, are required and, on this occasion, we consider that this can best be achieved by superimposing on the flat rate  350 increase a series ofstepped additional increases which produce, on average, the additional  60justified by the external comparison and permitted under the flexibility margin.The X factor10. We explained the background to the introduction of the X factor in ourThird Report6: briefly, it is intended to compensate for the balance of advantage and disadvantage of Service life by comparison with civil life which cannot be precisely measured in financial terms6.  In that report7, we were able to1 Statutory Instrument 1973 No. 1785, The Counter-Inflation (Price and Pay Code) (No. 2)Order 1973, paragraph 118.2 ibid, paragraph 138.3 ibid, paragraphs 139 and 140.4 Flexibility margin (1 per cent of average pay bill per head)  104,680 divided by the numberof officers from Captain to Brigadier (1,741) average amount per officer:  60-13.6 Cmnd. 5631, Chapter 1.6 The Stage 3 Pay Code provided, for the first time, a standard against which payment forone of the elements which made up the basis of the X factor could be measured and quantified we refer to work done in &quot; unsocial &quot; hours.7 ibid, Chapter 2.
recommend an increase in the X factor for the generality of servicemen andwomen covered by it: the greater part of this increase, 3-75 percentage points,was based on detailed evidence of the extent to which they were required towork during &quot; unsocial&quot; hours and we regarded,it as right that the payment which we considered justified on this account should be added to the X factor.We limited our recommendation to an increase of 3-75 percentage points inorder to comply with the provisions of the Pay Code, but we made known in our report our general view on the levels of the X factor, and the Government took account of this and decided that it should be increased from 5 per cent to 10 percent for the men&apos;s Services and from 1 per cent to 5 per cent for the women&apos;services: the additional 1-25 percentage points is in recognition of the increaseddegree of turbulence in Service life, which applies to Service medical and dental officers in the same way as to other members of the armed forces.11. We are, however, unable to recommend that the X factor for Servicemedical and dental officers should (be increased by the same total amount,for the following reasons:(a) The average net earnings of general medical practitioners in the NHSinclude an amount (at present averaging  614-40)&apos;for out-of-hours services.Indeed, we were told by the BMA in oral evidence that this element recog-recognises the extent to which general medical practitioners are &quot; on call &quot; and,to this extent, an element of the X factor is already recognised in the pay ofService doctors and dentists. We have no firm evidence of the amount ofwork done in &quot; unsocial &quot; hours by Service medical and dental officers andwe are not convinced by the arguments put to us by the BMA that it is not already recognised, or that the Service doctor is called on to do more work during &quot; unsocial&quot; hours than is the NHS general medical practitioner.To increase the X factor for Service medical and dental officers on thegrounds of work done in &quot; unsocial&quot; hours would involve paying twicefor the same feature, and the &quot; unsocial &quot; hours provisions of the Pay Codedo not admit recognition of being &quot; on call &quot;.(b) Nor did the Review Body on Doctors&apos; and Dentists&apos; Remunerationrecommend increases in the payments for out-of-hours service the supplementary practice allowance, the supplementary capitation fee and the night visit fee under the &quot; unsocial &quot; hours provisions of the Code, becausethese payments form part of the average net remuneration of general medical practitioners in the NHS. In our view, it would be wrong to recommend anincrease in the pay of Service medical and dental officers by using provisionsof the Code that have been found inapplicable to their NHS counterparts.12. We conclude, therefore, that the X factor for Service medical and dental officers should be increased to reflect the amount of the general increase thatis attributable to increased turbulence only (ie by 1-25 percentage points).This recommendation1 reflects exactly the element of the X factor increasesthat was covered by a Ministerial consent for the armed forces as a whole underthe Stage 3 arrangements, and assuming, as we do, that this consent appliedto the whole of the armed forces within our terms of reference, the 1 -25 percentagepoints increase in the X factor can now be extended to Service doctors and1 It provides additional amounts which range from  4-46 to  6-25 per month for Captainsand higher ranks.
dentists. We recommend an increase in the upper limit of the X factor to 325, except for Brigadiers to whom the  300 tapered limit recommended inour Third report for the other branches of the armed forces should apply.We are, however, concerned about the problems that may be created by theexistence of different levels of X factor for different categories of servicemen,resulting from the application of different criteria in the determination of their pay, and we intend to review the matter as soon as we are in a position to do so.13. Taking all these factors into account, we recommend the introductionof the following pay scales for medical and dental officers from Captain to colonel with effect from 1 April 1974. (Current pay scales are shown for thepurpose of comparison.)Table 1Proposed military salaries, inclusive of X factor, for Service medical and dental officers: annual ratesRankProposed scale ofmilitary salary (from1 April 1974)Current scale(1 April 1973)Captain:On appointmentAfter 2 years ...After 4 years ...Major:On appointmentAfter 1 year after 2 yearsAfter 3 yearsAfter 4 yearsAfter 5 yearsAfter 6 yearsAfter 7 yearsLieutenant-Colonel:On appointmentAfter 2 years ...After 4 years ...After 6 years ...After 8 years ...Colonel:On appointmentAfter 2 years ...After 4 years ...After 6 years ...After 8 years ...4,0994,1654,2494,9385,0015,0705,1615,4135,5045,5665,6586,0856,2126,3406,4716,5967,0087,0927,1987,2827,3661 Cmnd. 5631, paragraph 43.
Medical and dental Brigadiers14. We recommend that the military salary of the medical and dentalBrigadier should be increased from  7,818 to  8,304 with effect from 1 April1974.Provisionally registered medical practitioners15. We recommend that the military salary of the provisionally registeredmedical practitioner should be increased from  2,416 to  2,785 with effect from 1 April 1974.Medical and dental cadets16. We recommend that the pay of medical and dental cadets should beincreased by 7 per cent with effect from 1 April 1974, as we recommended for university cadets who intend to take up commissions in other arms of theServices. We do not propose an increase in the education grant at the presenttime.&apos; \ 17. We have expressed the [recommended salaries as the annual amounts which approximate most closely to daily rates of pay. The detailed scales(prepared by the Ministry of Defence) are in the Appendix.The cost of our recommendations18. The pay limit calculated in accordance with the provisions of the stage 3 Pay Code amounts to  733,000 and this may be extended by a maximum of  105,000 to accommodate the proposal which we make under the flexibilitymargin provisions of the Code. The cost of proposals chargeable against these limits is:; &apos;  Principal pay increasesCaptain to Brigadier     ...     ......      .........     616,000PRMPs    ......     .........      ...     ...     ...      25,000Medical and dental cadets       ...............      17,000-658,000Flexibility marginCaptain to Brigadier     ...............     ...     105,000The cost of the proposed increase in the X factor is  118,000. The totalcost1 of our proposals is thus  881,000.H. W. Atcherley (Chairman)D. P. DreyerEWEN M&apos;EWENA. R. MurrayC. A. RobertsJ. R. SargentOffice of Manpower Economics i.23 August 19741 The figures have been rounded to the nearest  1,000.
APPENDIXALL SERVICESPAY OF MEDICAL OFFICERS AND DENTAL OFFICERSRankNew rates of payDaily*Cadet, Medical..................*Cadet, Dental     ......     ............Provisionally registered medical practitioners:Acting Surgeon Lieutenant/Lieutenant/Flying OfficerSurgeon Lieutenant/Captain/Flight Lieutenant:On appointment   ...     ............After 2 years in the rank............After 4 years in the rank............Surgeon Lieutenant-Commander/Major/SquadronLeader:On appointmentAfter 1 year in the rankAfter 2 years in the rankAfter 3 years in the rankAfter 4 years in the rankAfter 5 years in the rankAfter 6 years in the rankAfter 7 years in the rankSurgeon Commander/Lieutenant-Colonel/wing commander:On appointment   ......After 2 years in the rank ...After 4 years in the rank ...After 6 years in the rank ...After 8 years in the rank ...Surgeon Captain/Colonel/Group Captain:On appointment   ......After 2 years in the rank ...After 4 years in the rank ...After 6 years in the rank ...Colonel/Group Captain after 8 years in the rankSurgeon Captain with 8 years&apos; seniorityBrigadier/Air Commodore     ......... 2-787-6312-4612-6412-8814-83150115-2115-46161616-4116-5816-841802	6,57718-37	6,70518-73	6,8361909	6,96819-43	7,09220-58	7,51220-81	7,5962110	7,70221-34	7,78921-57	7,87322-75	8,304* Education Grant of  949 per annum ( 2-60 daily) is paid in addition.Printed in England for Her Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office by Oyez Press Ltd.3144509  Dd. 119078   K24  9/74


</content>
</cab>
