<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/41/39 images: 294-299</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1943.SECRET.W.P. (43) 439.5th October, 1943.WAR CABINET.RESISTANCE IN POLAND.Memorandum by Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I circulate to my colleagues herewith a paper prepared in the Foreign office on the Polish underground resistance movement. Subject to my colleague&apos;;?approval I would propose to be guided by this paper in my Moscow conversations and in particular by the provisional recommendations in paragraphs 13 and 18.A. E.Foreign Office, 5th October, 1943.General Background.1. Resistance in Poland is organised from Warsaw by the K.W.P.(directorate of all underground warfare) on which the competent Polish militaryand civilian authorities in Poland are represented.2. The Polish underground movement provides the essential framework for maintaining order and discipline in Poland during and after the period of liberation.3. There is very close contact between the Polish Government in London andthe K.W.P. both on the civilian and on the military side.4. The only dissident element in Poland is the Polish Communist party which takes its directives from Moscow. It also works closely with Sovietparatroops and partisans dropped, especially in Eastern Poland, to stimulateactive resistance against the Germans.5. The Soviet policy of incitement to immediate action in Poland is indirect conflict with that of the Polish Government, supported by His Majesty&apos;sGovernment, of damping down premature revolt on the grounds that it can atpresent only lead to useless bloodshed.Problem.6. The Russian advance is bringing the Russian armies very near to theformer Russo-Polish frontier which they may reach within the next few weeks.This is already causing the Polish Government anxiety since it will raise in an acute form the question what is expected at that moment of the Polish under-ground movement ? &apos;7. The danger cannot be ignored that clashes may develop between Polish and Soviet guerrillas in Eastern Poland, which both regard as their own territory.8. The Russians will clearly expect more active measures on the part ofthe Polish underground movement to harass the Germans, and it will be difficult for the Polish Government and ourselves to continue our policy of discouragingpremature risings, especially if Russian operations continue through the winter.9. Oil the other hand, no steps have been taken so far to arm adequatelythe Polish secret army estimated at some 65,000 men, and on the 17th September,1943, the combined Chiefs of Staff recommended that &quot; the steps necessary to equip the Polish secret army should not be approved at the present time.&quot;   The12171   [26195]Cojfy No.
Polish underground movement is therefore only equipped for sabotage, which itis already performing according to the resources made available to it.10. In addition there are good grounds for fearing that if the Polishunderground movement comes into the open in response to Russian appeals, theRussians may take the opportunity, when they enter Poland, to destroy theleaders and to break up the whole organisation, thus facilitating any designs theymay have of running Poland in their own way.11.   There is thus a short- and a long-term problem.Short-Term Problem.12. The short-term problem is: &quot;When the Russian armies reachformer Polish territory, is the Polish underground movement (a) to declare itself and (b) to go all out to harass the Germans at whatever cost? &quot;13. It is submitted that the only possible way of dealing with this problem is to discuss it frankly at the Foreign-Ministers&apos; Conference as part of the Polishproblem. The line to take might perhaps be that a general uprising this winterin Poland would be premature and would only lead to the smashing up of thePolish organisation. In our view the most the Polish underground movementshould do would be to step up sabotage and subversive activity to the maximum possible degree. It may well be that the Polish underground movement wouldbe wise to withdraw altogether from operations in Eastern Poland. But whetheror not it does so, it seems essential that it should declare itself to the Russians.To ensure this, it may be necessary for Elis Majesty&apos;s Government and the UnitedStates Government to make it clear to the Polish Government that we are inclose touch with the Soviet Government and that we should naturally use our influence to prevent any victimisation of the leaders of the Polish UndergroundMovement,Long-Term Problem.14. The long-term problem may be sub-divided into two interrelatedsub-sections :. i (i) Administration of &quot; liberated &quot; Poland, and(ii) should we equip the Polish underground army ?15. As regards (i). the Russians have recently proposed that the Politico-Military Commission at Algiers should deal inter alia with the whole problemof liberated Allied territory. From the Polish standpoint, this proposal liasmuch to commend it, since it would give us and the Americans some chance of seeing that Poland, anyhow west of the Curzon Line, was properly treated.However, there are many other considerations involved which are now&quot; underseparate consideration.16. As regards (ii), the Polish Government have just put in a request that immediate steps be taken to equip the Polish Secret army. The combined chiefs of Staff in Washington have already considered a direct approach fromthe Poles in this sense and decided on the 17th September against sending any supplies at the present time (other than for sabotage and intelligence purposes).Their reasons were primarily military and practical, viz., shortage of aircraft and the priority of the Balkans. But they may also have been influenced by political considerations, viz., possible Russian reactions. In this connexion the relevant section of a report by the Combined Intelligence Committee, CCS. 267/3of the 17th September, runs as follows : &quot; In present circumstances the Russian reaction to any attempt to equipfully the secret army in Poland would be violently hostile. The secretarm)&apos; is, however, not likely to be used until the war is almost over. If atthat stage of the war the Soviet and Polish Governments are still mutuallyantagonistic and the question of their post-war frontiers has not been settled, the Soviet Government (a) if not consulted, will probably assume that the Polish secret army will be used against themselves, and the equipping of such anarmy will be liable to cause serious trouble between the UnitedStates and Great Britain on the one hand and the Soviet Govern -ment on the other;
(.6) even if consulted, will question the value of such an operation, andit would be difficult to convince them that it was not designedto oppose the Russians beyond the 1939 frontier.&quot;&quot; Assuming that the Polish secret army obeyed the orders which it received from London (and we are assured that it would) it would certainlyfight against the Germans. If the political question regarding EasternPoland remained unsolved, the army would certainly be disposed to resistRussian encroachment within PolancTs pre-1939 frontiers.&quot;17. As against this, the Poles are vitally interested in the equipping of theirsecret army. It is for them their main army and capable, if given the necessaryarms, of playing a decisive part in the liberation of Poland and in the subsequentmaintenance of order there. Failure to supply full military equipment would bea grievous blow to them.18. This question cannot be dealt with properly by us unless there is somesatisfactory solution of the Soviet-Polish frontier question before the Sovietarmies enter Poland. It is therefore submitted that it will have to be reconsideredin the light of the decisions reached on the Polish-Soviet frontier question (see.P. (43) 438)&apos; and of the discussions at Moscow. Meanwhile, we shall no doubt have to temporize with the Poles.




</content>
</cab>
