<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/195/22 images: 319-323</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(77) 479 May 1977COPY NOCABINET1977 UPRATING OF SOCIAL SECURITY benefits memorandum by the Chief Secretary, treasury. We are committed to increasing pensions and other social security benefits in November. This is the largest expenditure programme and thedecision involving more money than any other single decision in the courseof the year, with major economic, financial and social consequences.2. We have treated pensioners and other beneficiaries very well so far.Last November&apos;s uprating brought pensions to more than 15 per cent abovetheir real purchasing power at the last Tory uprating;  and short-term benefits were worth more in real value also.    This November&apos;s uprating will maintain those values.    The Memorandum by the Secretary of State for social Services and the Minister for Social Security (CP(77) 45), however,recommends that we should go further than our commitment requires and adda large margin on top of the required uprating.3. It is only a few months since we were considering whether we could afford to adhere to our indexing commitment.    This was both because ofthe difficult expenditure decisions we had to take in the course of theInternational Monetary Fund (IMF) negotiations, and because of the increasingproblems of incentives caused by the overlaps between tax, wages and benefits.    These problems are still with us and I can see no justification forexceeding our statutory uprating commitment.    The following points are particularly important.INCENTIVES4. Although I hope we shall soon have stopped the decline in real living standards, there are still serious problems over the relativities betweenbenefits and wages.    While real incomes have fallen, pensions have improvedsubstantially in real value and our successive up ratings have progressivelyincreased them relative to net earnings.    Similarly, even the minimumuprating of short-term benefits - which are not taxed - will worsen theproblems of incentives and overlap and increase resentment against those onbenefit.    As it is, a man with 2 children needs to earn  65 a week to get only 5 more than he could get if out of work.    This is a cumulative process andthere is no case for compounding the difficulties by a margin on the upratingthis year.
PRICES5. I recognise that the forecast of price movements is necessarilyuncertain and have considered very carefully whether it would be right to baaethe iprating on the forecast published with the Budget.    My conclusion is thatit is right to do bo.    Recent developments are encouraging.    The mortgageinterest reduction forecast in February for the autumn is happening already,and a further reduction is now probable;  and the European economic community (e.c.) price review outcome is also better than forecast.    Theyear-on-year rates published each month will, of course, continue high fo::3 or 4 months yet, but the monthly rate of inflation is already falling and inFebruary and March has been running at 1 per cent a month.    Net cf theonce-for-all Budget increase the a/erage rate for April/May is likely to be similar, with the prospect of a lower rate from July onwerds.    There is noreason therefore not to stand by our Budget forecast and any increase beyondit would necessarily involve a claim on the contingency reserve.PUBLIC EXPENDITURE6. There is no provision in public expenditure programmes to do morethan the minimum uprating.    But even this will involve injecting another 1, 345 million into the economy in a mil year.    As regards the effect on the contingency reserve, a 16.3 per cent uprating would pre-empt over20 per cent of the uncommitted balance in 1977-78 and over 35 per cent in1978-79.    I already know of other specific bids amounting to more than70 per cent of the uncommitted balance in 1977-78 and more than 30 per centin 1978-79.    On top cf these specific bids v/e still have other potentialdemands;  in particular the Secretary of State for Social Services will himselfbe putting in a bid for a large child benefit uprating and we also have toconsider the recommendations of the Holland Working Party on youthunemployment.    We must surely not foreclose our options on these by pre-empting too much of the contingency reserve now.    I fear that to pre-emptso.much of our remaining reserve for this year and next at this saily stage would riuk destroying the credibility of our public expenditure control just as we have succeeded in restoring it.    We cannot control the numbers of thosequalifying for benefits; but we can certainly avoid going further than ourstatutory commitments on the benefit rates.PUBLIC SERVICE PENSIONS7. The public service pensions increase is likely to be larger since it isbased on an earlier uprating period for which the likely inflation rate is knownto be higher.    This is no reason for adding over  300 million to the cost ofthe social security uprating.    But I agree with tne Lord Privy Seal (CP(77)48)that further study of the position on public    service pensions is desirable.
recommendation. I therefore strongly recommend that the uprating should be by thepost-Budget forecast of price increases between November. 1976 and november 1977 (13. I per cent).    This conveniently gives a  2 increase in the single pension, with  3.20 for a married couple.    Short-term benefits shouldhave the same percentage increase as pensions, so that they would rise by 1. 70 for a single person and  2. 70 for a married couple.    As the attachedTable indicates, the actual difference in weekly cash to pensioners between my proposal and the Secretary of State&apos;s is not large, but the increase in public expenditure would be substantial.   I do not believe the higher figure for those receiving benefits can be justified at a time when there have beencut3 in real living standards for those in work.J treasury Chambers9 May 19773
COKFIDEMTIALTableedIk6fLf^cretary1&apos;J,\0/- i$2* long-terra )0 short-terra)Mrsssry ofOptlionDin5,j0; long-term )&apos;c short-terra)it rates( )short- long-term       terra12.90  ! 15.3020.90   ! 24.5014.60 i 17.30 j 2.7023-60   I 27.7O j  4.10Differ-ential2.403.6013.00  I 17.0024.3028.302.804.20Extra cost above present rates(  million)1977 Survey prices total PublicExpenditureCost1977/78fullyearClaim againstContingencyReserve1977/78fullye ar5061,2&apos;*9.6311, 55912!310


</content>
</cab>
