<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/47/0 images: 340-371</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PBOPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOViBNMENT)s s.c^a g t. a /%&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;        &quot; COPY NO.    /i (-yMEETING of the Cabinet to be held at 10 downing street, S.W.I.; on Thursday, March 27th, 1924,at 10.30 a.m.AG EN DA.1.      HOUSING PROGRAMME.(To asoertaln Progress).2-      THB COUNTY COURTS BILL.Memorandum by the Lord Chancellor,(CP. 206 (24)    -   already oiroulateaJ;S.      SUPPLY AND TRANSPORT ORGANISATION.Note by the Home Secretary covering Conclusionsof Sixth Meeting of Emergency Committee,(CP. 211 (24)   - already oiroulated).4.      INDIAN POLICY,Telegram to the Viceroy^(CP. 164^ (24)   -   already oiroulated).Telegram from the Viceroy,(CP. 203 (24)   -   already circulated).Report of Cabinet Committee        L**Jl &amp;42J ;   :-5.      IRISH REPRESENTATIVE PEERS.----Memorandum by the Lord Chanoellor,(CP. 207 (24)    -   already oiroulated). /yy&apos;
6 o      TRAMWAY AND OMNIBUS STB 1KB.Report of Emergency Committee       (if ready)7.      HOME AFlAlRS COMMITTEE.ConeHeration of Recommendations on thefoIIowing Subjeots:-(a) The National Health Insurance Bill(HoAoCo  7th Conclusions (24) Minute l).(b) The British Empire Exhibition (Amendment)Bill(EoAoC.  7th Conclusions  (24) Minute 2).(o)    The Imperial Institute Bill(IcAoC.  7th Conclusions (24) Minute 3).(d) The Borough Councillors (Alteration of number) Bill(RhA.Ca 7th Conclusions (24) Minute 4).(e) The Coast-Guard Bill(H.A..C.  7th Conclusions (24) Minute 5).(f) The Sale of Bread Bill(H.A.C.  7th Conclusions (24) Minute 6).(TEA. C ,  7th Conclusions (24) - already circulated).(Signed)    M.P.A. BAN EE Y,Secretary, Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S. W.I.,26th March,  1924..
Slc^^x^^    327&apos;^IS.JOCTOESKT IS TOE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC M/iJESTYhS GOYERHMBNT) .g JM3 3 E T.COPY HO.0./0 A B I- H E T   23(24).COHCLUSIOHS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at I0S Downing Street, Sar.r.I3,on THURSDAY, MARCH 27th, 1924,  at10*30- AeM.1The Right Horn  J, Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.&apos;Prime Minister and Secretary ofState for Foreign AffairSc      (In the Chair).She Right Hon..,lord Parmoor of Frleth,K.C.y0Oa,EoC..r    lord president of the CounciloShe Right Hon.J,R, dynes, M,P*,lord Privy Seal..Ehe Right Ron,A- Henderson, MoP,, Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Stephen Walsh, M.Po, Secretaryof State for War.,Brig a - General The Right - Ron.Lo rd Thomson,  C 0B.E*,D.S.0 s,Secretary of State for Air.She Right Hon,Sidney Webb, M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade-She Right Horn,Charles Trevelyan, M.Po,President of the Board ofEducation.She Right Hon.Tom Shaw, CB.E.,M.P.,   minister of labour.        &apos;fhe Right Hon.Vernon Hartshorn, CB.Ee ,M.Pe,Postmaster-General.The Right HonYiscount HL-rd Chancellor.Yis count Haldane, K.T., 5 CM.The Right Hon.,Philip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of the Erchequer^The Right Hon.,J.H.t Thomas, M..P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies,.The Right Hon.Lord Olivier, K.C.M. C ,CB,,Secretary of Stats for indian the Right Hon.Vis count Chelmsford,  C CM. 0.CCoSalo ,&amp;.&apos;CjIoEj jGnBcEt) ,Pirst Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Han,,John Wheatley,    M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon,Noel Buxton, M. P. ,    Ministof Agriculture and Fisheri 3The. Right Hon.William Ad-amson, M.P0,Secretary for Scotland/Colo The Right Hon,J.C.. Wedgwood, D-S.O. ,tt,P. ,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon., F0W,  Jowett, M,?o,First Commissioner of Works,j. Present for first two and last two Items only-O7   Present for first two Items only.-O   0    O   1   ?1000J3Ueuto-Col. Sir M.P.A. Hankey,C CB,....................Secretary*
(Thlg^ Document is tho Property of His Biitajonio&quot;&apos;Barfos&quot;tyTs government-SB    0 R E T -CABINET 23  (24)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet, heldat 10, Downing Street, S.W.1, on THURSDAY,MARCH 27, 1924, at 10-30 a.rmHE OMNIBUSAND TRAMWAYSTRIKE.Supply andTransportOrganisation,Report ofEmergencyCommittee.(previous reference *.Cabinet 22(24), Con-clusion 2.)1.  The &apos; Cabinet had before them the conclusions reached by the Cabinet Emergency Committee on theprevious evening in regard to the action required fordealing with the London omnibus and tramway strike(Paper CP.-218 (24)).During the Meeting, copies of a draft Proclama-tion and draft Emergency Regulations under the Emergencyflowers Act, 1920, were handed round.The Home Secretary, as Chairman of the Emergency Committee, gave the Cabinet particulars of the measures proposed.&apos;&quot;&quot;After considerable discussion the Cabinet agreed -(a) To approximately^rove the draft Proclamation of&apos;Emergency submitted by the Emergency Committee (Appendix, l) ? as well &quot;as thedraft Lies sage to Parliament (Apperdix. II):(b) To approve the Code of Emergency Regula-tions  (Appendix III) submitted by theEmergency Committee, subject to recon-side ration by the Cabinet Conaviittee of regulation 16 on the subject of Compen-savion (See the following conclusion):
(o) That the Cabinet CoiXiittee shouldmake further inquiry as to whetherit was necessary and desirable toinclude Regulation 10., on the subjectof Compensation, or whether some modification should be made therein:(d) That the Clerk of The Council should immediately take His Majesty&apos;s pleasureas to The holding of a meeting of the privy Council on&quot;the following day forthe purpose of approving the EmergencyOrder in Council and the. emergency regulations, and that The Lord Presi-dent of the Council and the Secretaryof State for Air should attend themeeting (which was to be held atknowsley)5(e) That in regard to the organisation of alternative transport facilities, theGovernment should, for the present,confine its activities to providingmeans for the transportation ofGovernment employes, hospital patients and similar essential services.    Thearrangement proposed by the Emergency Committee, that the Ministry of transport should organise xhe use of char-a-bancsbut not of omnibuses, should not be announced.    In any public announcementit should be intimated that all vehiclesthat might be found, necessary would beemployed:(f) That the Emergency CommiTtee should, ifpossible, include in the emergency regulations power to regulate omnibusfares, if necessary:(g) That as. regards the general public, apartfrom (f) above, the Government would offeradequate protection to any omnibus, Tubeor tram services that found themselves ableto run.    The proposal of the Committee tomake a general appeal to the motor-owningpublic to render any assistance in their power was not approved.     The Emergency Committee&apos; were asked further to considerthe provision of facilities, to Thegeneral public;
(h) That the protection which the Govern-ment could offer could not he supplied by the ordinary Police service-) andthat it would &quot;be necessary to employSpecial Constables:(i) That the arrangement made by the Emer-gency Committee, under which theAdmiralty were at once to begin pre-reparations for having the necessaryNaval Ratings ready for use in power-stations , should be confirmed5 butthat no emergency action should betaken until after the issue of the proclamation -CSee^ also Coup conclusion^ 2) :(3) That the Attorney-General should beadded as a permanent member of theEmergency Committee.
THE OMNIBUSAND TRAMWAYSTRIKE.AttemptedSettlement.2. After the decisions recorded in Conclusion 1 hadbeen taken, the Cabinet were informed that Mr Webband other representatives of the Electrical TradesUnion had called at 10, Downing Street.The Prime Minister, aooompanied by the HomoSecretary&apos; and the Minister of Labour, then left theCabinet and conferred with these gentlemen.On his return, the Prime Minister informed hiscolleagues that Mr Webb and his friends were anxiousto avoid being drawn into the Strike, and had intimated- that if i&amp;val Eatings were put into Lots Road elec-trioal power-station the disturbance was likely to spread to other power-stations.   After the attitude ofthe Government had been explained to them, Mr Webb andhis friends had made the suggestion that if the employeewould offer an increase in wages of 5/-s. a week to thewhole of the tramway men, with whom the Strike originatedreserving the additional 3/-s. demand as a subject for arbitration, the Electrical Trades Union might take theview that there was no Justification for continuing theStrike.   Eventually, Mr Webb and his friends had left to visit Mr Ernest Bevin, of the Transport and general works&apos; Union, and afterwards Mr Bromley, of theAmalgamated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Piremen.After some further discussion the Cabinet agreed -(a) That the Prime Minister should invitethe following representafives of theUnions directly or indirectly concernedin the Strike to meet him at the Houseof Commons the same evening at 6 pBm. ,namely,
Mr Ernest Bevinj the leader of the tramwayand omnibus wo rice rs ,Mr Bromley,of the Amalgamated society of Locomotive Engineers and firemen,Mr Oiaiup.of the National Union of railwaymen,Mr Webb,of the Elect ideal Trades Union,and that at This meeting the. PrimeMinister should, if he deemedexpedient, having regard to Con-elusion (b) below, sound them asto the possibility of a settlement on the lines of an immediate increaseof 5/--s. a week to the whole of thetramway men affected by the Strike,the additional demand of 3/-s. being reserved for arbitration:Cb) That the Minister of Labour should immediately get into touch with therepresentatives of the employersconcerned, with a view to soundingthem, either, personally or by arranging for an interview between the employers&quot;and the Prime Minister, as to whetherthey would be prepared to offer asettlement on the basis proposed in(a) above:(c) That in reply to a Private Notice question by Viscount Curzon, asking for further particulars as to the measures proposedby the Government for dealing with theStrike5 the Prime Minister should intimate that the Government had notabandoned hope of bringing together theparties to the dispute, and were confer-ring with all the organisations concerned.If possible, he would make a statementbefore the House rose-
COUNTYCOUBTSBILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 14(24), Con-clusion 11.)3.   After, consideration of a Memorandum by the LordChancellor, setting forth the serious results which-would follow if the County Courts Bill did not beoomelaw at a very early date (Paper 0.P--206 (24)), theCabinet agreed  That the Lord Privy Seal should explain the urgency of this Billto the Chief Whip, and should endeavour to arrange for thenecessary Parliamentary facilities.
IRISH KSPRE-SENTATIVBPEERS.(previous reference:Cabinet 23(23), Con-conclusion 8,)4. After considernation of a Memorandum by theLord Chancellor, drawing attention to the anomalousposition in regard to the representation of ireland in the House of Lords by Irish Representative Peers(Paper 0*Po-207 (24)), the Cabinet agreed  To accept the view of the LordChancellor that for the present no action should be taken.
NATIONALpALTH Ig-UIOE BILL.leviousIferenoe:cabinet 2114) j Con-fusion7.)5. After consideration of a Memorandum by the Ministerof Heal til, covering the draft National Health insurance bill (Paper C*P0-196 (24)) and the recommendation of theOoimnittee of Home Affairs thereon (ih A. Op 7 (24), Para, l)the Cabinet. agreed --To authorise the Minister of Health toarrange for the introduction forthwith in the House of Commons of the national health Insurance Bill, 1924, in the formof the draft ennexod to Co P.-106 (24),with a view to the passage into &quot;law ofthe Bill on the earliest practicable date.
Age BRITISH .6. After consideration of a Memorandum &quot;by the Parlia-feffiRE HXhl- lk-convention        mentary Secretary to the Department of Overseas Tra.de,BmSNDMENO?)Bijli. covering tire draft British Umpire Exhibition (Amendment)Bill, 1924 (Paper CP. -194 (24)), and the recommendationPreviousieforence,: 0f the committee of Home Affairs thereon (HiA.G. 7 (24),labiiiet 2124), Con- Para.2) , the Cabinet agreed  conclusion  1ii&apos;)-.) &apos;  To authorise the Parliamentary Secretaryto the Department of Overseas-Trade toarrange with the Parliamentary Secretaryto the Treasury for the introduction forthwith in the House of Commons of theBritish Empire Exhibition (Amendment) Bill,1924, in the form of the draft annexed to&apos; CP.-194 (24).
 BE IMPERIALINSTITUTEBILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 13(24) , Con-conclusion 1 &amp;Appendix I. )7. After consideration of a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for the Colonies, covering the draftImperial Institute Bill (Paper CP.-195 (24)),&apos; and therecommendation of the Home Affairs Committee thereon(H.A.C. 7 (24), Para. 3), the Cabinet agreed  (a) To authorise the Secretary of State forthe Colonies to arrange for the intro-duotion of the Imperial Institute Billin the form of the draft annexed toG.P.-195 (24):(b) To take note that the Goiamittee of HomeAffairs accept in principle the offer of the Secretary of State for theColonies to give the War Museum some additional space in the Galleries,if available.-10-
*&quot;*&apos;   &quot;V;.-..338THE BOROUGH        8. After consideration of a Memorandum &quot;by the HomeCOUNCILLORS(ALTERATION Secretary, covering the draft Borough Oounoillars&amp;F NUMBER)  - s,BILL. (Alteration of Nuaibor) Bill, (Paper CP.-103 (24.0, andthe recommendation of the Committee of Home Affairs(previous preference: thereon (H.A.C. 7 (24), Para.4), the Cabinet agreed -Cabinet 33(23), Con- To authorise the introduction of the elusion 4.) Borough Councillors (Alteration of number) Bill in the form of the draft annexed to CP.-103 (24), on the under-standing that it would not be possiblefor the Government to regard the bill as of so urgent a character as tojustify giving it any special precedence.-11-
jHB OOAST-gUABD BILL.previous reference:cabinet 823), Oon-conclusion 2I (ausion ;Hi).)9. After consideration of a femora ndum -by-the Presidentof tJie Board of Trade, covering the draft Coast-Guard Bill(Paper CP.-192 (24)), and the recommendation of the Committeeof Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C 7 (24), Para.5), theCabinet agreed  To authorise the President of the Board ofTrade to arrange for the introduction ofthe Ooast-Guard Sill in the form of tftedraft annexed to 0oP.-192 y24), on theunderstanding that it would not be possiblefor the Government to regard the Bill as of so urgent a character as to justify givingit any special precedence.
SALE 0?        10.After consideration of a Memorandum by theBILL.President of the Board of Trade, covering the draftSale of Bread Bill (Paper CP.-199 (24)), and the reeora-mendation of the Committee of Home Affairs thereon (II. A. C7 (24), Para.6), the Cabinet agreed -To authorise the President of the Boardof Trade to arrange for the introductionof the Sale of Bread Bill in the form ofthe draft annexed to CP.-199 (24).13-
ItlDXAc 11&apos;After consideration of a telegram to theViceroy of India (Paper ChPo-164 A (24)) , a telegramrevious . , ,ef  fences       from the Viceroy of India (Paper C.Po-203 (24)), aCabinet 20(34)3 Con-      Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India (Paperelusion 3.)G.Po-208 (24); and a draft telegram ... to the Viceroyproposed by the Cabinet Committee, the Cabinet agreed -That the Secretary of State for india should be authorised to send thefollowing Private and Secret telegram to the Viceroys-&quot;i have now considered with mycolleagues your private and secret telegram of 21st March,.The idea underlying my telegramof 12th March was desire of PrimeMinister and his Cabinet to estab-lish contact and understanding between themselves and the leadersof Indian opinion-   You and your colleagues do not agree to theplan we proposed with this object,but we imagine you are at one with us in desiring to attain it.    Canyou suggest any alternative plan which would seem to you preferable to that of His Majesty5 s Government?&quot;The Prime Minister, who was out of the room when this decision was reached, subsequently expressed his agreement in the terms of the telegram,14-
PARLIAMENTARY BUSINESS.



(Previous Reference: Cabinet 18 (24), Conclusion 20.)



WAR CHARGES VALIDITY BILL



Previous Reference: Cabinet 13 (24), Conclusion 7.)



WEST INDIES TELEGRAPHS BILL.



Previous Reference: Cabinet 16 (24), Conclusion 10 (Appendix.)



12. Arising out of the discussion of the Bills submitted by the Committee of Home Affairs, the attention of the Cabinet was drawn to the difficulty which was likely to be encountered, in the present state of Parliamentary business, in securing the passage of many of the measures already approved for introduction.

The Lord Privy Seal informed his colleagues that a programme of Parliamentary business for the present Session had been drawn up, and communications were taking place with the other Parties in the House of Commons with a view to expediting business, although up to the present time the other Parties had not been very accommodating.

The Cabinet invited the attention of the Lord Privy Seal to the importance of the following measures:-



THE WAR CHARGES VALIDITY BILL.



THE WEST INDIES TELEGRAPHS BILL (Which, the Cabinet were informed, was down in the programme for April 10th.)


HOUSING.(previous reference:Cabinet 11(24), Con-oiusion 5.)13.  The Minister of Health made to the Cabinet astatement as to the progress which had been made intheregard to/Housing Scheme.   He read to his colleagaos aMemorandum containing a forecast of the forthcoming report of the House-Building Committee.   He undertook to dirculate the latter Report to the Cabinet confidential -tially.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That it was desirable for the Ministerof Health to make a short general state-ment to Parliament in regard to thepresent position of the GovernmentsHousing Policy, as a preliminary toa discussion of these proposals withthe Local Authorities.    The statement should not be for purposes of Parlia-raentary debate, but merely to give theHouse information before it was givenoutside.    It oould be explained to theHouse of Commons that details couldnot be given until they had been dis-oussed with the Local Authorities:(b) That the Lord Privy Seal should endeavourto arrange for this statement at an earlydate:(c) To take- note that the Minister of Healthproposed to ask the Local Authorities toappoint a Committee to meet him, and toprepare his Bill after his discussions with the Committee.
MEETING        14. gt^e  rime Minister asiieu members oi the CabinetOP CABINET.to hold theirs elves in readiness for an emergency Meetingat any time during the next 4S hours if the develop-merits in connection with the tramway and omnibusstrike should render this necessary.Subject to this s the next meeting of theCabinet was fixed :-. or WEDNESDAY, APRIL 2nd, at 11 a.m.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,March 27, 1924.-17-
ABY   THE   KING.PR 3, C L A M A T I Q R.GEORGE R.I.WHEREAS by the Emergency Powers Act, 1920,  it Isenacted that if it appears to Us that any action has beentahen or is immediately threatened by any persons or body ofpersons of such a nature and on so extensive a scale as to be calculated, by interfering with the supply and distributionof food, rater, fuel or light,  or with the means of locomotion,to deprive the community, or any substantial portion of thecommunity,  of the essentials of life, We may, by proclamation,declare that a state of emergency exists:ARD WHEREAS the present withdrawal of certain transport services ordinarily available to the general public in andar*?und London does,  in Our opinion,  constitute a state ofemergency within the meaning of the said Act:HOW, THEREFORE, in pursuance of the said Act, We do, byand with the advice of Our Privy Council, hereby declare thata state of emergency exists. . .GIVER at Our Court at this in the year of our Lord one thousand nine hundred and twenty- , and in the year ofeur Reign.God Save the King.    .
APPENDIX   IIMESSAGE      TO      PARLIAMENTGEORGE R*IcThe Emergency Powers Act, 1920, having enacted that ifit appears to His Majesty that any action has been taken oris immediately threatened by any persons or body of persons of such a nature and on so extensive a scale as to be calculated, by interfering with the supply and distributionof food, water, fuel or light, or with the means of locomotion,to deprive the community, or any substantial portion cf thecommunity-, of the essentials of life, His Majesty may, by proclamation, declare that a state of emergency exists;    andthe withdrawal of certain transport services&apos; ordinarilyavailable to the general public In and around London having in His Majesty&apos;s opinion, constituted a state of emergencywithin the meaning of the said Act:His Majesty hss deemed it proper, by proclamation madein pursuance of the said Act and dated the day ofto declare that a state of emergency exists.
APPENDIX 111EMERGENCY REGULATIONS,   19 24.Arrangement of Regulation;1.  Power to take&apos;poosession of land,  etc.2. Road Transport3. Tramways and light railways.4. Power to direct traffic on highways.5. Priority in transport.6. Driving licences.7.  Gas,  water and electricity.8.  Lights.9. Motor Spirit.10.  Injury to property.11. Employment of Pis Majesty&apos; s Forces.12. Billeting.13. Obstruction of officers.14. Effect of notice of intention to take., posses15. Delegation of powers.16. Compensation.17. Penalties18. Arrest without warrants, &amp;c.19. Attempts to commit offences.20- Effect of regulations on contracts.21.  Interpretation.22. Printing of regulations.23.  Supplemental provisions.24.  Short title.
At the Court at present  SSiJT.The King&apos;s-.Most-Bxco.lle^t^.Ma,j&amp;s&quot;fcy iirijounail,IP &amp; 11 Geo. Whereas by the Emergency Powers Act, 1920, it is prwi&amp;ecL,5.c. 55.amongst other thingst as follows^-&quot;1.     (l) If at any tins it appears to His Majesty that any action has been taken or is immediately threatened by any persons orbody of persons of such a nature and on so extensive a scale asto be calculated, by interfering with the supply and distribu-tion of food., water, fuel, or light, or with the means of locomotion-tion, to deprive the community, or any substantial portion of thecommunity, of the essentials of life, His Majesty nay, bypreclamation   (hereinafter referred to as a proclamation ofemergency), declare that a state of emergency exists.&quot;Ho such proclamation shall bo in force for more than one month, without prejudice to the issue of another proclamation at or before the end of that period.&quot;(s) Where a proclamation of emergency has been made theoccasion thereof shall forthwith be communicated to parliament and,  if Parliament is then separated by such adjournment orprorogation as will not expire within five days, a proclamationshall be issued for the meeting of Parliament within five days,and Parliament shall accordingly meet and sit. upon the dayappointed by that proclamation, and shall continue to sit and actin like manner as if it had stood adjourned or prorogued to thesame day.n2.     (l) Where a proclamation of emergency has been made, and solong as the proclamation as in forces it shall be lawful for HisMajesty in Council, by Order, to make regulations for securingthe essentials of life to the community, and those regulations may confer or impose on a Secretary of State or other GovernmentDepartment, or any other persons in His Majesty&apos;s service oracting on His 1-Jajesty&apos;s behalf, such powers and duties as HisMajesty may deem necessary for the preservation of the peace,for securing and regulating the supply and distribution of food,water, fue.1, light- and other necessities, for maintaining themeans of transit or - locomotion^ and for any other purposesessential to the public safety and the life of the community,and may make such provisions incidental to the powers aforesaidas may appear to His Majesty to be required for making theexorcise of those powers effectivef&quot;Provided that nothing in this Act shall be construed toauthorise the making of any regulations imposing s.ny form of compulsory military service or industrial conscription;&quot;provided also that no such regulation shall make it an offence-for any person or persons to take part in a strike,- or
peacefully to persuade any ether person cr persons to take .ce partin a strike,&quot;And whereas a proclamation of Emergency under the said Acthas been made by His Majesty,  and is now in force;And whereas in pursuance of the powers.above recited it is expedient to make such provision as hereinafter appears;Now therefore, His Majesty is pleased,  by and with theadvice of His Privy Council,  to order,,  and it is hereby .orderedas follows:-power to take     1. It shall bo lawful for the Board of Trade, and any otherpossession of .land,  etc. Department approved by His Majesty for the purpose,  and anyperson duly authorized by a department on whom powers areconferred by or under this&apos; regulation, where it appearsnecessary to do so,  to take possession of any land,  buildions or works (including works for the supply of gas,   electricityor water and of any sources of water supply) and any property,(including plant, machinery,  equipment and stores) used or intended to bo used in connection therewith,Road 2.        (l) The Minister of Transport may by orders-transport. . .(a; regulate,  restrict,  or gxve directions with respect ,to,  theuse for the purposes of road transport or the sale orpurchase of any horses or vehicles in use or capable ofbeing used for the purpose of road transport:(b) take possession cf any such horses or vehicles as afore-said,  or require them to be placed at the disposal, of theMinister,  or of any person specified by the Minister inthat behalf,  either absolutely or by way of hire,  and either for immediate or future use?(c) require persons owning,  or having in their possession orunder their control,  any such horses or vehicles as afore-said to make to the Minister, or to any person specified bythe Minister in that behalf,  returns giving the proscribed
particulars with respect to those horses and vehicles,and require any such returns to be verified in theproscribed manner ;(d) require persons arming, or having in their possession orunder their control, any such horse or vehicles as afore-&apos;said to give notice in the prescribed manner before dis-posing thereof, ar allowing it to pass out of theirjiossession or control;(a) prohibit the carriage of goods of any class by road, :.ndprescribe the radius or distance within which goods orgoods of any class may. be carried by road;(f) provide for the giving of directions with respect to the carriage of goods on any particular vehicles, or by anyparticular route or to any particular clearing house or depot;(g) regulate the priority in which goods are to be carried bypoad and vehicles used for the purposes of road transport;(h) prescribe the conditions on which, ^.nd the rates at whichhorses or vehicles may be hired for the purpose of road transport and goods carried by road, and the conditions onwhich goods so carried or to be carried are to be loadedor discharged ;(&apos;) make such other provisions in relation to road transport as appear to the minister necessary or expedient.(?) .iiny order under this regulation may be made so as to applyeither generally to all horses and vehicles,  or to horses or vehiclesof any class, or to horses or vehicles belonging to any particular&quot;owner.(3) For the purpose of testing the accuracy of any return madeto the linister under this regulation, or of obtaining information in the case of failure to make a return, or to give any prescribednotice, any person authorised in that behalf by the Minister mayenter any promises belonging to or in the occupation of the person who has made or has failed to make the return^ or on which the personso authorised has reason to believe that any horses or vehicles withrespect to which a return has been required under this regulationare kept, and may carry out such inspection and examination (includingthe. inspection and examination of books) as he may consider necessaryfor testing the accuracy of the return, or for obtaining suchinf or rat ion.(4) .;o individual return or part of a return made, and \no informa-tion obtained, under this regulation, shall without lawful authoritybe published or disclosed by any parson except for the. purpose of a prosecution under this regulation,,(5) If in any case the minister is of opinion that it is expedient to obtain information from any person in connection with any horses orvehicles, the I inister may, without making an order for the purpose,require or authorise any person on his behalf to require that person   tofurnish him or any person so authorised with that information, and wherethe ? inister or any person so authorised so requires any information to
Id lightilwayspar to 4.Jfroot trafficlif highways.riority inran sport.*5wvi rigponces.6.Ill waterEf olootri-fty.be furnished the provisions of this regulation shall apply to information furnished and the furnishing of the information as they apply to returns made and the making of returns -(6) In this regulation the expression &quot;prescribed&quot; means proscribedby an order made under this regulation,   and tho expression &quot;horse&quot;includes &quot;mulo&quot;,&apos;l) The Minister cf Transport for tho purpose of making the most efficient use of tho materials or plant bfelonging to a tramway orlight railway undertaking may by order require the whole or any partof the rolling-stock, materials and plant,  including permanent way,of any such undertaking to be placed at his disposal or at the disposalof any person or body of persons named by him.Where any such order has been mad? the i-inister or any such person or body of persons may.take possession of suoh portions of thorolling-stock, materials or plant of such undertaking as they may require and may remove them and make use of them for the purposes ofany other tramway or light railway.(2) The Minister of Transport may by order restrict in such manner as may be specified in the order the traffic on-any tramway or lightrailway.(3) If any person fails to comply with the provisions of any order made under this regulation or wilfully hinders or impedes the executionof any such order he shall be guilty of an offonce against these regulations.&quot;Where with a view to   preventing congestion of traffic,  on,  orexcessive damage to, public highways the Minister of Transportconsiders it is expedient to do so, he may by order regulate orprovide for the regulation of transport on public highways,  and mayby such order provide for directions being given for prescribingthe routes to be followed and restricting the; typos of vehicles tobe used,  and if any person affected by the order fails to complywith the provisions thereof or.with any directions given thereunderhe shall be guilty of an offence against these regulations.Without prejudice to any other powers possessed by him,whether under these regulations-oar otherwise,  the Minister ofTransport may  by order regulate the priority in which passengers orgoods are to be carried by railway,  light railway,  tramway,  or canal.The Minister of Transport or any person appointed by him forthe purpose may grant to any person a licence to drive a motor carduring the period for which the Proclamation of Ehergency is inforce and such licence shall have effect as if granted under the motor Gar Act,  130 3.-  (l) It shall be lawful for the Board of Trad-,  the minister ofHealth and the minister of Transport respectively by order torequire the owners of any undertakings for the supply of gas.,  water,and electricity to comply with any directions given by tho board or Minister as to the supply thereof.
ights.otor&apos; spirit,.jury to^erty.(2) Where any such order has boon issued,  or where in pursuanceof the powers conferred by any of those regulations possession hasbeen taken of any works for the supply of gas,  water or elootricity,it shall be the duty of the owner of the undertaking and of everypfficor and servant of the owners and whore the owners are a company of every direotor of the company to comply with any directions whichmay be given by the Board or Minister,  and any person failing so tocomply shall be guilty of an offence against these regulations.(3) The powers of the Board of Trade and the Minister of Healthunder this regulation may in Scotland bo exercised by the Seoretaryfor Scotland.8. - (1) The Bo ard of Trade may by order direct that all lights of anyspecified class or description shall be extinguished or their userestricted to such extent,  between such hours, within such area,  andin such places of entertainment, hotels,  clubs,  or other premises asmay be specified in the order,  and if any person having control ofany light, or occupying or having control of, or managing, or being in charge of, premises in or in connection with which any light is used,  acts in contravention of any such order,  ho shall be guilty ofan offonoe against these regulations.(2)  The Board of Trade or the iViinistor of Transport may bo orderdirect that the uso of lights in public vehicles shall be restricted to such extent as may bo specified in the order,  and if any personbeing in charge of any public conveyance in which any light is usedacts in corrtravontion of any such order he shall bo guilty of an-offunco- against these regulations.9. *- (l) The Board of Trade may by order prohibit or regulate the sale,supply,  delivery or use of motor spirit,  and require any personsowning or having the power to sell or dispose of motor spirit toplace the same at the disposal of the Board or of any person authorised by them.(2) In this regulation the expression &quot;motor spirit&quot; includes anyinflammable liquid substance capable of being used for the purposeof driving motor vehicles.(3) If any person contravenes or fails to comply with any .provision of any order made under this regulation he shall be guilty of an offence against those regulations.10. - (l) If any person injures, or does any act calculated to injure,or to prevent the proper use or working of,  any public building,railway,  canal,  bridge,  road,  tramway, vehicle,  telegraph ortelephone line,   cable,  or plant, mine,  shop,  factory, waterworks,gasworks,  electric generating station, or any works or plant usedor adapted for uso for the production,  supply, storage, or transportof food,  fuel, munitions, water, light, heat,  or power, ho shall be guilty of an offence against these regulations.(2) If any person approaches or is in the neighbourhood of orenters any such place as aforesaid with intent to   injury theretohe shall be guilty of an offence against these regulations;    andnotwithstanding that no such act or injury is committed -by^hi-Sy^Jbe-&apos;
-7-&quot;    353EmploymentMajesty forces.Billeting.shall be deemed to be guilty of such an offence if by reason of his being in possession of any explosive or incendiary substance or lethalweapon or dangerous missile,  or otherwise from the circumstances ofthe case or his conduct or his. known character as proved, it appearsthat his purpose was to do such injury.11. - Where a Secretary of State by order has declared that any service is a service of vital importance to the community, it shall hi theduty of every person subject to the Naval Discipline Act or to military law or to the Air Force Act to obey any command given by anysuperior officer in relation to employment upon or in connection withsuch service,  and every such command shall be deemed to be a lawfulcommand within the meaning and for the purposes of the i\iavalDiscipline Act, the Army Act and the Air Force Act,12. -.-       During the continuance in force of these regulations the powers conferred by secti on 108A of the Army Act and section 108A of the AirForoe Act with respect to billeting may, notwithstanding thatdirections have not been given for embodying 3&amp;11 or any part of theTerritorial Army be exercised.in the same manner in all respects asif such directions had been given,  and shall have effect in relationto officers and men of the Royal fiavy and the Royal Marines actingwith or attached to any body of His Majesty&apos;s ^military or air forcesin all respects as if they were officers and soldiers or officersand airmen of such military or air forces.Obstructionor officers.Effect of notice ofintentionto &quot;takepossession&quot;&apos;-of property.delegation of powers.13*. If any person obstructs, knowingly misleads, or otherwiseinterferes with or impedes, or withholds any information in his possession which he may reasonably bo required to furnish from, anyofficer or other person who is carrying out the orders of any government Department or who is.otherwise acting in accordance withhis duty under these regulations he shall bo guilty of an offon00against these regulations.14. Where any department,  or any person authorised by a department,has, in pursuance of powers conferred by any of those regulations,issued a notice that that department or person has taken or intends to take possession of any movable property,  any person having controlof any such property who., without the consent of that department or person,  sells or removes or secretes the same or any part thereof,or parts therewith in any way contrary to any conditions imposed in any licence, permit, or order that may have been granted inrespect thereof,  shall be guilty of an offence against these regulations.1ft. Any Government Department on whom powers or duties arc conferredor imposed by these regulations may make arrangements with any other government Department for the exorcise by that Department of these powers or duties,&apos;- and in such case that Department and the officersthereof shall have and may exerciso the. same powers and duties asarc by these regulations conferred on the first mentioned department and the officers thereof;    and the Minister of Health, or as respects
Scotland the Secretary for Scotland, may.  by arrangement with any government Department on whom powers or duties are conferred orimposed by these regulations,  confer or impose on any localauthorities and their officers any powers and duties, in connectionwith the enforcement of these regulations,  and any powers and dutiesneoessary to provide for the due discharge of any functions assigned to local authorities by any Government Department under these regulations.- The&quot;compensation payable in respect of any property which isrequisitioned or of which possession is taken under these regulationssfoall be such as may be determined in default of agreement by asingle arbitrator appointed in England by the Lord Chancellor andin Scotland by the Lord President of the Court of Session,  and in assessing -the amount of compensation payable in any particular case,regard shall not be had to any increase in the value of theproperty which is due to the emergency nor to. any consequential loss.- (l) If any person contravenes or otherwise fails to comply withany of the provisions of these regulations or any order or directionmade or given thereunder, or is guilty of an offence against these regulations,  or obstructs any.&apos;police or ether officer or any other person in the execution of his duties under these regulations, he shall be liable on summary conviction to imprisonment with or without hard labour for a term not exceeding three months,  or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds,  or tu both such imprisonmentand fine.-   and shall be liable to forfeit to the Grown any goods ormoney in respect of which the offence was committed.(2) Where the person guilty of any such offence is a corporation,company or society,  any director,  officer,  or trustee,  or other person conoorned with the management thereof,   shall be guilty of the.like offence unless lie proves that the offence was committed without this knowledge or consent.(3)  For the purpose of the trial of a person for an offence against these regulations,  auch offence shall be deemed to have Veencommitted either at the place- in which the same actually was committedor at any place in which the offender may be.- (l) Any police constable may arrest without warrant any person whoso acts as to endanger the public safety,  or who is guilty, or issuspected of being guilty of an offence against those regulations.(2) Any police constable may,  if authorised by order of a secretary of State or of a chief officer of police,  enter,  if needbo by force,   any premises or place suspected of being used forpurposes so endangering the public -safety,  and may search any partof such place or premises and may seize and detain anything foundtherein which is suspected of being used for such purposes asaforesaid  ,!&apos;or the keeping of which in such place or promisesinvolves the commission of an offence against these regulations,and may deal with the things so seized in such manner as the     ;Secretary of State may determine.
(3) Any police constable may search any person whom he believesto be in possession of, or to be using or carrying any article, the possession, use or carrying of which by such person is an offence against these regulations,  and may seize and detain any such articlefound on such person.-(4) Any police constable may stop and search any vehicle which hehas reason to suspect to be used for any purpose prejudicial to thepublic safety,  or contrary to those regulations,  or to bo carryingany article,  the possession, use or carrying of which is an offence against these regulations,  and may seize and detain any such vehicleor any such article found therein.(5) In the application of this regulation to Scotland &quot;the Secretaryfor Scotland&quot; shall be substituted for &quot;a Secretary of State&quot;. &apos;ttempts to    19. - Any person who attempts to commit,  or solicits or incites., or    .oommitOffences.Jffect ofro-tnlationsOOti hivjo ho.endeavours to persuade another person to commit or procures,  aids,or abets or does any act preparatory tot  the commission of any actprohibited by these regulations,  or any order,  directions,  rules,  orother instrument made thereunder,  shall be guilty of an offence against these regulations.&apos;&apos;g0. - If the fulfilment by any person of any contract is interfered withby the necessity on the part of himself or any other person ofcomplying with those regulations or any order or direction thereunder,that necessity shall be a good defence to any action or proceedingstaken against that person in respect of the nonfulfilment of the contract so&apos; far as it is due to that interference.Interpro-*-.tiorr.&amp; 53ot.  c.63.Brinting ofgulations.21. The Interpretation Act,  1889,   shall apply to these regulations as though they were an Act of Parliament.22. -  (l) Whore by any Order in Council or by any Resolution of both houses of Parliament,  for the time being in force,  any regulations or wordsare directed tc be added to or omitted from these regulations,  or tobe substituted for any other regulations or words in these regulations,then copies of these regulations, printed under the authority of .&apos;His Majesty!s Stationery Office,  after such direotion takes effect,may be printed &apos; -mlations or words added or omitted orsubstituted for other regulations or words.,  as such direction requires-,and with the regulations and paragraphs thereof numborod inaccordance wi      such diveohionj    and those regulations shall beconstrued as if they had,   at the time when such direotion takeseffect,  been made with suoh addition,  omission or substitution.(2) A reference in any document to these regulations or to any provisions thereof shall, unless the context otherwise requires,be construed as referring to those regulations as amended by any order in Council or Resolution of both Houses of Parliament for thetime.being in force.^louteutal S3&apos;.&apos;&apos; visions.-  (l) The powers conferred by these regulations shall be in additionto and not in derogation of any prerogative right or other powervested in His Majesty.
-10-&apos;    356(2) Any powers conferred on any department or person by any ofthese regulations shall be in addition to and net in derogation of anyother powers of that department or person whether conferred by statute,regulation or otherwise.(3) Any order,  direction or instrument which may be made or givenby any government department or other authority under these regulations may be added to,  revoked or varied from time to&apos; time by such department or authority while these regulations continue inforce.(4) References in these regulations to a person authorised toact on behalf of any department shall include the holder for thetime being of any office designated for the purpose by the department.- These regulations may be cited as the Emergency Regulations,  19 24.9P.159-68.

</content>
</cab>
