<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/47/0 images: 372-385</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(&apos;THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OE HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVEB1MENT)COPY ffo.   % *Jg^E C g E T.CABINET  4  (24)MEETING of the Cabinet to be held at 10 downing street, 8.1.(1), on Wednesday, April bnd, 1924,at 11 a.m.AGENDA.1.      THREATENED INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES.(Reference Cabinet 22(24) Conclusion S).Note by the Minister of Labour(CP.216(24)       -       already circulated).2*      UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour covering draft Bill.(C.Pi325(24)       -       already circulated).Report of Cabinet Committee.(CP.224(24)       -      To be circulated).3.      IRISH POLITICAL PRISONERS-.Memorandum by the Home Secretary,(CP,214(24)       -       already circulated).4.      IMPERIAL WIRELESS  SERVICE..Memorandum by the Postmaster-General(CJ?.226(24)     -        to be circulatedh5.      AGRICULTURAL WAGES,.Memorandum- by the Minister of Agriculture &amp; Piaherieacovering draft Bill,(CP. 217 (24)       -       already circulated)Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.(CP.220(24)       -       already circulated).Notes by the Minister of Labour.(CP.220A(24)      -       already circulated),  iRecommendations of Home Affairs Committee,(H.A.C8(24) Conclusions 1(2)-       already circulated)Report.of Cabinet Committee.(CP.225(24)       -       to be circulated)
6.      DATE OF CA3IBTT DISCUSSION OH THE BUDGET.BENT AKD MORTGAGE INTEREST RESTRICTION BILL 1984. .__ReooimnencUttiona of Home Affairs Committee.(H.A.0.8(24) Conclusion 2,    -   already circulated)(Signed)     M.P.A .HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.(l)March 21et 19S4 AiLOJ T&apos; 24  (24) .358Meeting to be held at 10 Downing Street,&quot;S.W.1.on Wednesday, April 2nd,  1924,  at 11 a.?n.^SIII2JML.j;TEM FOR AGENDA.IRISH BOUNDARY J^^Tj^mq.(Tobe raised by the Secretary of State for theColonies).(Sgtf).  M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.1,,April 1st,  1924,
jhadj^   &apos;    360/(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY 0? HIS BRITANNIC -UkJESTT^S  GOVERNIdlNT) .SECRET.COPY NOCABINET&apos; 24(24).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.Wc1.  onWEDNESDAY:, APRIL 2nd, 1924,  at 11 A,M.PRESENT       &apos;The Right Eon,  J. Ramsay macdonald, M.P,Prime Minister and Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs. &quot;       (In the Chair)The Right Hon..lord Parmoor of Frieth,K,OcVoO* ,K.Co,    lord president of the Council.The Right Hon.J.R.  Clynes, M.P,&apos;,jiord Privy Seal,The Right Hon,Ac Henderson, M0P,o&apos;, Secretaryof State for Home Affairs .She Right Hon..Stephen Walsh, McP., Secretaryof State for War,Brig0-general The Right Hon.Lori Thomson,  C.B.E.,D.S,0.,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon.Sidney Webb, M.PS, Presidentof the Board of Trade.She Right Hon.&apos; varies Treyelyan, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation..The Right Hon.&apos;f om Shaw, C . B. E j , M. E,,,Minister of labour.The Right Hon.Yemen Hartshorn,. C.BtE. ,;.I.P*,Postmaste r-General.The Right Hon.Visccunt Haldane, E.T. ,0.M,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.,Philip Snowden, M.P. ,Chancellor of the Exchequer.-She Right Hon.JcH, Thomas, M,P.r Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hon.Lord Olivier, E.C.M.G,,C.B.secretary of State for India.The Right Hon.Viscount Chelmsford,  G.C.M.G.,GoCoS.1. ,G.C.I.E. j,GoB.Eo ,First Lord of the Admiralty.lire Right Hon.John Wheatley, M.P. minister of Health.The Right Hon.Noel Buxton, Mop.Ministerof Agriculture akd Fisheries.The Right Hon.William Adams on, Mtp.,Secretary for Scotland.Col.  The Right Hon.J.C. Wedgwood, D.S.O.,M,P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster..Th e Ri gh t Hon, F. W. J on e t i, M. P.,First Commissioner of Works.THE FOLLOWING WERE AIS0 present sir Patrick Hastings, E.C.M.P.,Attorney-General. (For Item l).LIeut0-Col. Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B.....................-Secretary.
ftl u X.(This Document jls the Property of His Britannicr    *       Ha^esTy5&quot;^ t?overnmen&quot;tT)&quot;-secret cabinet 24 (24)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet,hold at 10, Downing Street, S.W. 1, onWEDNESDAY, APRIL 2, 1924, at 11 a,E,IRELAND;boundaries of Ulster.(previous references cabinet 13(24), Con-elusion 2c)1.    The Secretary of State for the Colonies informed the Cabinet that it nor; appeared probable that the IrishFree State Government would agree to a renewal of theConference in regard to the boundary between Northernarxi Southern Ireland, but that the Government must beprepared for the possibility of failure to reach agree-ment at the Conference.    In this case it was of greatimportance to avoid giving any Impression that the BritishGovernment were not prepared to carry out the Treaty.It was almost certain, however, that if the appointmentof a Boundary Commission in accordance with Article 12of the Irish Treaty was proposed, the Government ofNorthern Ireland would refuse to nominate a Commissioner.The&apos; situation which would then arise required carefulconsideration.The Cabinet agreed  That the Lord Chancellor and the LawOfficers of the Crown should be askedto advise the Cabinet on the following question:-
Y/hen a Commissionei&apos; lias been aprjointedby the Government of the Irish Free Stateand the Chairman of the Commission hasalso been appointed by the BritishGovernment 3 but the Government ofNorthern Ireland persists in refusing to appoint a Commissioner, will the boundary Commission be sufficientlyconstituted so as to be oompetent todetermine the boundaries under Article12 of the Treaty?&quot;w2
2.    The Secretary of State for War brought beforethe Cabinet, as a matter of great urgency, the questionof certain amendments which were to be moved in the&apos;House of Commons to the Army and Air Force (Annual) Bill,1924, in regard to which a Memorandum was handed roundat the outset of the Meeting (Paper CP.-232 (24)).The amendments put down by four members of the LabourParty and one member of the Liberal Party provided forthe removal of the death penalty in the case of certainoffences, and their effect, if carried, on the discipline of the Army was regarded very seriously by the MilitaryMembers of the Army Council.After considerable discussion, the Cabinet-agreed That the Secretary of State for war should explain to the House of commons the very serious difficulties involved by the aixiendiaents , and that he shouldbe authorised to inform the House thatthe Government required further timefor consideration of the question and. were not in a position to introduceamendments in this direction in the bill now before the House.    Farther, that theArmy Council would be invited to examinethe question very fully, with a view tothe introduction, if possible, of someamendments next year, and Addition, toreport to the Cabinet what amendmentswould be required in the Army        andAir Force Acts in order to provide thatin time of peace a soldier charged witha crime punishable by ordinary law-shall be tried before a, civil.      tribunal.p ARMY ANDjs.8, FORCE(ANNUAL)BILL.previous reference:nabinet 13(24) , Con-clusion 1.)
TBS- GOVERNMENT       3. Arising out of the discussion on the Army and air and their departmental   Force (Annual) Bill, the Cabinet considered the questionADVISERS.- as to whether their advisers were entitled to ask thatParliamentaryPosition in    their views, if adverse to...^he policy of the Government,the Event of disagreement, should be stated in Parliament.In this connection the Cabinet were reminded that(previous reference:      this course had been followed in the case of the decisionCabinet 2fi(2^), Con- on the subject of the Singapore Base, but -it was explains! conclusion 1 &quot; &quot;&amp; ADoen^LX&apos;)   that a departure from&apos;&apos;nt?^.mal practice had been made inthis instance because the Government had only been a jvery short time in office and the views of their technical advisers were well known to their predecessors, who had reached a decision contrary to that of the present Gov-e moment.The Cabinet agreed  That, as a natter of principle, theGovernment ought not to announce the opinions of their advisers in Parliament*
THREATENEDINDUSTRIALDISPUTES/(previous reference:Cabinet 2.2(24), Con-clusion 3.)The strike at Wembley.4.   After taking note of a Memorandum by the Ministerof Labour on the present position of a number ofthreatened trade disputes (Paper CP.-216 (24)) and ofa Note by the President of the Board of Trade covering a Memorandum by the Secretary for Mines, on the wagesnegotiations in the coalmining industry (Paper O.P.-229 (24)), the Cabinet passed to a discussion on the causes and tendencies of the present industrial unrest.Attention was drawn in particular to recent instances of sectional strikes,not recognised by the Trades Unionsconcernedamong the shipyard workers at Southamptonand the builders at the British Empire Exhibition atY/embW, as well as to symptoms of Communist agitationand propaganda.   While recognising that the present industrial unrest is partly the result of a reactionafter a long period of trade depression accompanied bywage reduction and a lowering of the standard of living,the Cabinet agreed  (a) That, with a view to an early decision as to the best method by whioh theGovernment could bring home both to employers and workers the detrimentaleffect on the economic recovery of thecountry of industrial unrest and un-certainty (whether due to the action ofthe employers in refusing: timely dis-cussion of legitimate demands or tounjustifiable strike action by theworksrvs) , the Prime Minister should invite representatives of the TradesUnion Gen-era 1 Council to meet repre-sentatives of the Cabinet for an informal discussion on the industrial position:(,b) That the Prime Minister should selectsome of his colleagues to accompany him at the above meeting, whieh should behodd either at 10, Downing- Street * or in&apos;   the Houses of Parliament:That in reply to a Private Notice Question-%6 the Prime Minister by Ma 3 or Coif ox asto the protection which the. government intends to afford against.threats and violence at Wembl^, &quot;the Minister ofJ^abour should be authorised to reply
The CoalDispute.(previous reference:Cabinet 22(.24) , Con-clusion 1.)that &quot;The fullest measure of protection against violence will ho provided&quot;:(d) That the First Commissioner of works should circulate to the Cabinet a minute amplifying suggestions he had made to the effect that in negotiations-tions with their employes the Governmentshould deal with representatives of theTrades Unions concerned^ rather than with shop-stewards and others of theiremployes who at present were accustomed to represent the workers and who madeclaims in excess of what were recognised by the Trade Unions concerned;;(e) That as regards the Coal Disputej theTerms of Reference to the Court of inquiry proposed by the Miners&apos; Fedora-tlon were too narrow/ but that the ques-ticn at this stage should be left to bedealt with by the Mines Department ofthe Board of Trade.-6-
)UNEMPLOYMENTINSURANCEo  .(previous reference:Cabinet 21(24), Con-conclusion 2 a )5.    After consideration of a Memorandum by. theMinister of Labour, covering tv/o Unemployment InsuranceBills, Nose 2 and 3, one a comprehensive measure dealingwith a number of points, and the other a short stop-gapBill drawn 10 avert the cessation of benefit in a largenumber of cases on April 16th (Paper Co P.-223 (24)),together with the Report of a Cabinet Committee thereon(Paper C.Po-224 (24)), the Cabinet agreed  (a) To erpprove generally the Second Reportof the Unemployment Insurance Committee(Paper 0*Po-224 (24)), including therecomaendations in regard to JuvenileEmployment (which involves the reversal of the previous decision of the Cabinetthat payment of benefits for juvenilesbetween 14 arid 16 should be made direct to parents (Cabinet 21 (24) , conclusion (g)), subject to the question of theamount of the Exchequer contributionbeing remitted for consideration, inthe light of the Government Actuary8 sreport, and for decision, to:-The Prime Minister,The Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Minister of Labour:(b) That, subject to the above, the Ministerof Labour should be authorised to intro-duce the Unemployment Insurance No-2 Billarid the Unemployment Insurance No. 3 Billin the form of the drafts annexed toC*P0--223 (24), with;any drafting or othermodifications &apos; (not affecting the main principles of the Bills) which may befound necessary or desirable.
IRISHPOLITICALPRISONERS.(previous references:Cabinet ^9(23), Con-elusion 3andCabinet 31(23), Con-clusion 3.)6.  After consideration of a Memorandum by the HomeSecretary on the subject of Irish Political Prisoners(Paper CP.-214 (24)), the Cabinet agreed  That j in view of the effects which any alteration at this moment in thestatus of the Irish political prison-&apos;ers might have on the situation inIreland and on the action of theIrish Free State Government in theirattempts to apprehend the persons responsible for the recent outragein Queenstown, further considera-tion of this question by the cabinet should be adjourned for a month.
ff--.IMPERIALWIRELESSSERVICE.(previous reference:Cabinet 19(24), Con-clusion 3.)7. After consideration of a Memorandum by thePostmaster-General, circulated late on tlie previous evening, as to what would be involved in this countryand in the Dominions and India if the recommendationsof the Imperial Wireless Telegraphy Committee were carried out (Paper cp.-226 (24)), the Cabinet agreed -That, with a view .to a decision being reached at the next Meeting of theCabinet, the Postmaster-General1sMemorandum (Paper C*P.-226 (24))should be examined by the followingCommitteeThe Postmaster-General,The Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Secretary of State ior the Colonies,The First Lord of the Admiralty,The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.
DATE OF THECABIiStET DIB-OUSSIOI, ONTHE BUDGET.8.   The Cabinet were informed that the House ofCommons would probably rise on April ICtlu , and thatit would reassemble for the disoussion of the Budgeton Tuesday? April 29th.The Cabinet agreed --Tnat the Chancellor of the exchequer should make his statement to theCabinet on the subject of the Budgeton Saturday, April 26th j at 11 a.in.
NEXT MEETING 9. The Cabinet agreed -OP THE DABIMET.That their next Meeting should bheld on Monday, April 7, 1924, a11 a0ru*2, Whitehall Gardens, S.v/,1,April 2, 1924.-11-

</content>
</cab>
