<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/22/21 images: 314-317</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M. (41)  54th CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 1.Confidential Annex.(27th May, 1941 - 10.30 a.m.)CRETE. THE TRIME MINISTER read to the War cabinet a telegram (NOc 0/67710 dated 26th May) from General(Previous Wavcll to the Chief of the Imperial General Staff in reference: regard to the situation in Crete.     This telegramW.M. (41) 53rd stated that General Wavell had discussed the situationConclusions,     with Admiral Cunningham and Air Marshal Tedder and minute 1.)        General Blarney, the New Zealand Prime Minister also being present,,      General Wavell said that the present programme of land reinforcements during the next fewdays could not be increased without inadmissable lossof warships.      He had received a telegram from GeneralFreyberg which stated that the limit of endurance hadbeen reached by the troops and that the situation washopeless.      To this telegram General Wavell had repliedmaking certain suggestions for holding the situation.A further telegram (No. 0/67750) of the same date from General Wavell stated that our front on thewest of Canea had broken and our troops were comingback in disorder.    Casualties had been heavy.    Effortswere being made to stabilise the position temporarily.The Prime Minister said that all chances of winning the battle in Crete now appeared to have goneand we should have to face the prospect of the loss of most of our forces there.      There was no action that wein this country could take in regard to the matter.The Prime Minister added that our submarines in the Mediterranean had achieved some remarkablesinkings,  the UPHOLDER had claimed to have sunk theCONTI GRANDI and three other merchant ships whilst theURCHIN and another submarine had accounted for 21,000tons of enemy shipping.The Prime Minister added that he proposed inhis statement in the House that morning on thesituation in Crete to say that hard fighting was continuing in Crete, and to emphasise the advantage which the enemy held by having command of the air.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Great George Street, S.W.1.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toMOST SECRET. ensure the secrecy of this document. COPY NO.




</content>
</cab>
