<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/256/0 images: 7-42</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT 13 THii PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT),SECRET. COPY NO.   :0.P.141(35)*CABINET.REPORTS OF THE INVESTIGATORS INTO THE SPECIAL AREAS. Note by the Secretary of State for Scotland.I circulate for the information of the Cabinet proof copies of the Report of Sir Arthur Rose, the Commissioner for the Special Areas in Scotland.(Intd.)    G.P.C.13th July , 1935.
7ERRATA,Page 8, line 16, for 1933 substitute 1935. Page 8, line 21, for 3533 substitute 3553. Page 15, 9th line from foot, for &quot;and&quot; substitute &quot;add&quot;.Appendix I page 29In column 6 for 4,900 substitute 4,800.Page 34 should follow immediately on page 29.
Commissioner for the Special Areas in ScotlandReport for the period 21st December, 1934 to 30th June, 1935LONDONPUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses : Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2. j   120 George Street, Edinburgh 2 j York Street, Manchester 1 ; 1 St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff j 80 Chichester Street, Belfast ; or through any BooksellerCmd.
CONTENTSREPORT ON THE WORK OF THE  COMMISSIONER FOR THE SPECIAL AREAS IN SCOTLAND. 21st December, 1934, to 30th June, 1935.PART I.1. Introduction.2. Application  of the  Special Areas  Act and  General Organisation.3. Industrial and Employment Situation in the Special Areas.4. Plan of Operations.PART II.General Progress of Schemes.1. Industrial Development. General (a) Publicity.(b) Industrial Investigations.(c) Industrial Facilities and Services.(d) Research, New Processes, Etc.(e) Expenditure from the Special Areas Fund.2. Public Utility and Amenity Schemes.(a) Public Utility Services.(b) Amenity Schemes.(c) Volunteer Labour Schemes.(d) Special Public Services and Works.(e) Expenditure from the Special Areas Fund.(382)12385  Wt, go   7/35 a 2
3. Land Developments. General (a) Land Reclamation.(b) Arterial Drainage Schemes.(c) Experimental Farm Development.(d) Land Settlement, Small Holdings.(e) Unemployed Plot Schemes. (/) Allotment Schemes.(g) Special Experiment in Homecrofting.(h) Expenditure from the Special Areas Fund.4. Special Problems, Labour Questions, etc. 5. Social Service Schemes.(a) Physical Culture Schemes.(b) Welfare Work for Adolescents.(c) Welfare Work for Children.(d) Spare-time Occupation.(e) Health Services.(/) Holiday Camps for Unemployed Persons.(g) Expenditure from the Special Areas Fund. 6. Effect of Approved Schemes on Unemployment. 7. Financial Commitments of the Special Areas Fund.
REPORTON THEWork of the CommissionerFOR THE SPECIALAREAS IN scotland for the period from21st DECEMBER, 1934To30th JUNE, 1935To The Right Hon. Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.E., C.M.G., M.P., Secretary of State for Scotland.Sir,I have the honour to submit the following report of my work under the Special Areas (Development and Improvement) Act, 1934, for the period from the inauguration of my office to the 30th June, 1935. .PART I. 1. Introduction. Ori 21st December, 1934, I was appointed as Commissioner for the Special Areas in Scotland under the Special Areas (Development and Improvement) Act, 1934. This Act, in its application to Scotland, provides for the initiation, organisation, prosecution and assistance of measures designed to facilitate the economic develop-ment and social improvement of the Special Areas, which are defined in Part II of the First Schedule of the Act as follows : &quot; The counties of Dumbarton, Lanark (excluding the City ofGlasgow) and Renfrew. The parishes of Ardrossan, Beith, Dairy, Dreghorn, Dunlop, Fenwick,   Galston,    Irvine,    Kilbirnie,    Kilmarnock, Kilmaurs, Kilwinning, Loudoun, Riccarton, Stevenston and Stewarton within the county of Ayr. The parishes of Falkirk, Grangemouth, Muiravonside, and Slamannan within the county of Stirling so far as situated south of the London and North Eastern Railway line from Castlecary to Linlithgow. The parishes of Bathgate, Ecclesmachan, Kirkliston, Livingston, Linlithgow, Torphichen, Uphall and Whitburn within the county of West Lothian so far as situated south of the London and North Eastern Railway line from Linlithgow to Ratho. The parishes of Kirknewton, Mid Calder and West Calder within the county of Midlothian.&quot;
The Special Areas in Scotland as described above constitute one large area representing a more or less arbitrary sub-division of a part of Scotland which, with Glasgow as its natural centre, has become recognised as the Industrial West of Scotland.At the beginning of my operations I received a large number of representations from other parts of Scotland seriously affected by unemployment regarding their exclusion from the defined area, apparently owing to a misconception of my functions. In such cases I could only refer my correspondents to the definition of the Special Areas embodied in the Act and to the terms of Section I (6) thereof, which limits my prosecution of measures outside these Areas by the condition that I must be satisfied that such measures will afford employment or occupation for substantial numbers of persons from those Areas.2. Application of the Special Areas Act and GeneralOrganisation.In presenting this Report on the work I have endeavoured to carry out during the period of six months under review, it might be as well to indicate my conception of the nature of the task entrusted to me. There appeared to me to be two distinct functions : the first, and one in regard to which something might be done immed-iately, being the ameliorative, and the second, and much more difficult one, requiring intensive study, the constructive.In regard to both functions, however, I have tried to visualise the problems and work on the possible remedies on the lines of a research laboratory in the hope that some at any rate of the results of my experimentation might ultimately be applicable not only in a more comprehensive form within the Special Areas, but also to areas outwith the restricted limits laid down by the Act. To continue the analogy, in modern commercial practice it is not unusual to keep the research chemist in close touch with the commercial side of a business, in order that any parts of his work may be immediately available and be submitted to the test of practical experience at the earliest possible moment.To carry the analogy one stage further, my next problem was to select the necessary material for experiment and enlist the services of the most useful assistants and collaborators. The material was immediately available and consisted of the workless and the causes of their lack of opportunity for obtaining work ; the assistants and collaborators were equally available, and of a very high quality.My &quot; assistants and collaborators &quot; fall into three categories and commence with : (1) The Commissioners personal staff. Scotland being parti-cularly well served by a number of purely Scottish Administrative Departments, and sharing with England the services of the larger &quot; international &quot; Departments, it seemed to me essential to avoid the creation of duplicate machinery and consequently my personal
/staff has been kept definitely on the small side. I was most fortunate in obtaining, as my Principal Assistant, Sir William Goodchild, formerly of the Scottish Office, and, as my personal Assistant and Head of the Office, Mr. Leslie G. Bullock, of the Ministry of Labour, who had collaborated with me in the preparation of my Report as Investigator into the Derelict Areas. The Ministry of Labour also contributed various invaluable Officers and most efficient Clerks and Typists ; Exchequer and Audit Department, and the Lands Valuation Department of the Inland Revenue, let me have the services of experts, and the Department of Agriculture allowed one of their settlement officers to join me. My immediate staff was completed by a former colleague in the Department of Agriculture who emerged from his retirement to give me a hand.(2) The second category consisted of the purely Scottish Depart-ments, and those Departments common to the United Kingdom. May I say in a word that the Departments of Health and Agriculture have placed at my disposal, with unstinted enthusiasm, all their immense knowledge of conditions in Scotland and their most efficient technical personnel; the Ministry of Labour, apart from their great kindness in regard to Office staff, have rendered invaluable assistance inall matters relating to the complicated questions of the actual state of employment, apart from a special contribution to which I shall refer later. The Edinburgh Branches of H.M. Office of Works, H.M. Stationery Office, and the General Post Office, have repeated their magician-like efforts in producing suitable accommodation, equipment and communication almost at a momenfs notice, of which I have had former experience.(3) The third category consists of two sections, first the Local Authorities in the Special Areas and their highly efficient staff, and the second, existing Organisations such as the Scottish National Development Council, the Community Service Council, the Joint Committee of the Scottish National Union of Allotment Holders and Society of Friends, Youth Associations, etc., etc. The organisation of the work has been considerably simplified through the efforts of all these assistants and collaborators, and I have been able to avoid the lengthy and often unsatisfactory process of creating new execu-tive and administrative machinery on a scale which would otherwise have been unavoidable.Finally, I had many opportunities of testing the value of close association with the Secretary of State&apos;s new Office in Edinburgh, which has acted as an easily accessible medium for dealing with financial and policy questions relating to the Act.It may be necessary as the work develops in the future to con-sider expansions and variations of these arrangements, but the methods of organisation adopted have certainly facilitated the practical application of experiments so far devised.
3, Industrial and Employment Situation in the SpecialAreas.It is probably unnecessary to offer, in this report, any detailed observations regarding the problems of the Special Areas, as they are exhaustively considered in the Report of the Industrial Survey of the South West of Scotland (Board of Trade) (1932) and my report of the Inquiry into the Depressed Areas in Scotland (1934).In view more particularly of the exclusion of Glasgow from the Special Areas, and the use of a mixture of physical and administra-tive boundaties for describing the area, the available statistical and other data regarding them must be approximate and are quoted subject to this reservation.Figures showing approximately the extent of unemployment in the Special Areas have been supplied to me by the Ministry of Labour as follows : The insured population in the Special Areas is estimated as 328,270, and, of these, 26-8 per cent, were unemployed at 24th June, 1933. The unemployment percentage in respect of men was 29-2 at that date. In the case of menk the incidence of prolonged unemployment is greatest, 37-3 per cent, of the total number of unemployed men having been out of work for more than one year. The total unemployment in the Special Areas at 24th June was : Men.         Women.       Boys. Girls Total.71,228 8,822 4,279 3,533        87,882In so far as a comparison is possible between these figures and those recorded in my Inquiry in 1934 (conducted over an area with not quite the same boundaries), they indicate a certain reduction both in the total numbers of unemployed persons and in the incidence of prolonged unemployment since the inquiry. But the main fact which emerges is the persistence of a problem requiring further intensive research, ameliorative measures and long-term planning. The question before me when I assumed my functions at the begin-ning of the present year was, as indictaed in the Report on my Inquiry, how to deal with a surplys of labour amounting (in very rough figures) to approximately 60,000 men and boys, of whom some 40 per cent, may be regarded as the first reserve force for industry, another 40 per cent, consisting of older and less adaptable persons, as a second reserve, and the remaining 20 per cent, as verging, owing to age and other considerations, on the unemployable catefory. My main plans, therefore, have necessarily been directed not only to endeavouring to promote measures calculated to increase normal employment, but also, no the one hand, to devising methods, where necdssary, for training and keeping fit during unemployment our valuable reserve of labour, and on the other, to finding new and productive careers, if possible, for persons otherwise deemed to a life-tifne&apos;s idleness and constituting a dead-weight burden on public resources. ..... ....   ...... ,.
4. Plan of Operations.I kept the practical limits of my task, as briefly set out above, closely in view in planning my work, so as to avoid dissipation of energy in theoretical investigations likely to add nothing to the solution of the problem but another volume of statistics and good intentions. Inquiry was, of course, necessary, particularly in the early stages of my mission, but I always endeavoured to subordinate it to the practical side, and to harness it to some definite purpose which I hoped to achieve. With these considerations before me, I found that my work grouped itself naturally into certain categories; which are mentioned below, and which may conveniently be used for the purposes of this Report.(1) Plans which prepare the way for economic and industrial development. Under this heading I class Schemes of Public Utility and Amenity which are calculated to produce lasting assets to the community of a nature rendering the Special Areas more suitable and attractive to industry, with the added advantage of making them better places in which to live. Such schemes involve a measure of immediate employment, but their main purpose is to create con-ditions conducive to an extension of normal employment, and T would take this opportunity of saying that I have entertained no scheme of the nature of relief works, aiming merely at the provision of temporary employment as such.(2) Plans for industrial development comprising the stimulation of existing industries and the attraction of new ones.(3) Plans for the exploration and promotion of measures for providing alternative careers for unemployed persons unlikely to return to their normal industrial employment, or for providing subsidiary occupations for unemployed persons. These plans are primarily concerned with the utilisation of the land in one way&apos; or another, and I refer to them below under the general heading of &quot; Land Development.&quot;(4) Special Problems, Labour Questions, etc.(5) Social Service Schemes, which aim at keeping the un-employed fit in body and mind as a preparation for further employ-ment, and as a mitigation of the evils of unemployment.PART II. -General Progress of Schemes.Before entering upon the detailed Sections of my Report, I wish to add a few general observations.As I have already indicated, my work is, in my view, experi-mental in character, and, moreover, it is still in its first stages&apos;. It is, therefore, premature for me to attempt to draw any general conclusions at present, and I do not propose to do so. Certain broad facts have, all along, been obvious to all those who have studied the questions involved by industrial  depression.   Fox
instance, it is clear that a recovery in trade and commerce must be widespread and general for any effective relief of local depression to be experienced in an area concerned primarily with the heavy industries, and that, to this extent, local measures such as alone are within my competence must partake of the nature of a palliative rather than a remedy. Apart from these considerations, however, I feel that everything possible should be done to mitigate the effects of depression, and to prepare the way for recovery, and it is in this sense that I have endeavoured to act, within the closely circumscribed limits of my powers.As regards the general nature of my constructive proposals, I have endeavoured to base them as far as practicable on what I may term the long view. In consequence, the effects of certain of them will not be apparent for some time to come. A proposal, for instance, such as that for a Regional Gas Supply for the West of Scotland, to which I refer below, will require a considerable period of incubation before it could materialise as a practical measure in actual operation. In such cases I feel that I shall have achieved my task if I have laid the foundations for a successful future development, and I attach much more importance to a planned enterprise of this character, with far-reaching potentialities, than to individual local schemes, even if they provide immediate employment and are completed within my term of office.I do not wish it to be inferred, however, from these remarks, that I have neglected the latter type of scheme, or that I have not endeavoured to provide employment, consistently with the wider views to which I have referred.I may add that I have made no reference in this Report to the possibilities of emigration as a factor contributing to the relief of unemployment. Facilities for emigration to the Dominions will no doubt be revived in time. They are meanwhile in abeyance, and I regard the whole question as practically outside my competence.1. Industrial Development. General.I have placed Industrial Development, as the only real cure for unemployment, in the forefront of my programme, and I am pur-suihg measures to this end in so far as I am able to do so under the terms of my mandate, which is, as already pointed out, of purely local application, and which also restricts me from giving financial assistance to any undertaking carried on for the purpose of gain. I was fortunate in establishing, from the first, close relations with the Scottish National Development Council, which has as its primary object the promotion of Scottish business and industrial interests, and I arranged, in consultation with the Council, a system of co-operation which has already yielded satisfactory results, and gives promise of more in the future.
(a) Publicity.The main result achieved by the above-mentioned procedure up to the present date is a scheme devised to give publicity to the products of the Scottish Special Areas, in particular by the organisa-tion of a permanent exhibition of such products at British Industries House, London, which H.R.H. the Prince of Wales graciously consented to open, and which has already, I am informed, resulted in an increased demand for such products by commercial buyers and others interested. At the same time, steps have been taken, in conjunction with the Council, for the collection and dissemination, over as wide a field as possible, of information about the industrial products, facilities and resources of the Special Areas, through the Council&apos;s Journal &quot; Scotland&quot; and through other channels. A Scottish stand equipped with brochures about the Special Areas was set up at the British Industries Fair, Birmingham, and attracted considerable attention. Schemes for further participation, on behalf of the Areas, in Trade Exhibitions are in course of preparation, and an Information Bureau has been established with a view to ensuring that inquiries from all interested parties can be promptly met. Consideration is being given to the expansion of this general programme of publicity, and I expect to be able to announce further developments in my next Report.The fame of the basic industries has sometimes overshadowed the extensive activities of many other industries in the area which offers advantages, proved by practical experience, for the successful production of a large variety of products.The results so far attained clearly establish the fact that in other parts of the country and overseas there is still much misconception about the industrial structure of the West of Scotland and its variety of products, and the value of this experiment in co-operation is already being proved by the association in it of local authorities and individual undertakings, in the latter cases, without expense to the Special Areas Fund.(b) Industrial Investigations.In addition, I am benefiting by the Development Council&apos;s assistance in considering any specific proposals which come before me for the augmentation of existing industries, the establishment of new industries and the removal of difficulties in the way of industry, all, of course, within the Special Areas. I have also had the advantage of the co-operation of the Board of Trade and other Government Departments concerned in dealing with this Branch of my functions.Results in this connection are hard to show. The process involved is a lengthy one. To give some indication of the nature of this part of my work, I may mention that I have received inquiries, among others, directed to the establishment of a motor-car industry in Scotland and of an aeroplane industry, towards the
revival of the production of flax on a commercial scale, the extension of the canning industry and of the manufacture of tiles and bricks, and towards the increased utilisation of Scottish timber for pit props. In each case I consulted the Council and any other source of expert information available to me. In some cases it was clear that the existing position of the market for the product concerned was such that there appeared to be no practical chance of a successful development, and that if there were such an opportunity, industry, financed through the usual channels, would already have taken advantage of it. In other cases, I found that the appropriate Department of H.M. Government already had the matter in hand and was able to take over the proposals which had reached me, for consideration along with their current activities in that connection. Instances of this kind are furnished by the proposals about canning and flax production, which I was able to pass on with my observa-tions to the Department of Agriculture as a contribution to what they were already doing in the matter.In certain cases, the inquiries which I received in connection with new industries appeared to be based on the idea that help in starting an industry might be given from the Special Areas Fund. In such cases, of course, I referred those who approached me to the terms of the Special Areas Act.While at the present stage, as stated, I do not desire to put for-ward any general conclusions, two points have struck me when considering the very limited extent to which I can be of assistance, under the Act, in promoting industry or starting new industries in the Special Areas, and I should like to mention these points in a purely tentative manner. The first, and main point, is concerned with what may be termed Economic Planning and Research, the second, with the question of financing men in a small way who have what appears on the face of it to be a sound idea, or invention, which they desire to launch, but are unable to do so because they cannot offer sufficient security to attract the necessary capital.The field of Economic Planning and Research is so important to the nation as a whole that it appears to me there may be room for an authoritative Scottish Body with suitable experience and knowledge, equipped with an expert staff, financed by the Govern-ment, and endowed with powers to explore industrial conditions, make recommendations, and in general aim at introducing into our economic structure that element or orderly and planned develop-ment which in the past has in some considerable measure been overlooked.I will not elaborate this point further; I merely suggest it for. consideration.As regards the second point to which I referred, I am aware that certain agencies already exist for supplying the need in question. It may be, however, that just as a Government guarantee is given, in certain circumstances, by the Export Credits Guarantee Depart-
merit, in assistance of our export trade, so a similar guarantee might be given by the Government, under approved conditions, in assistance of enterprise at home.   Here again, I merely make a suggestion.I am conscious that the foregoing observations take me outside the limits of the Special Areas, but it is impossible always to discuss the area as though it were entirely dissociated from the rest of the country.(c) Industrial Facilities and Services.I have also given consideration to the question of the adequacy of the facilities available in the Special Areas for industrial develop-ment, and, in this connection, I have given special attention to questions of factory accommodation, supply and other services and the like.In certain cases the improvement of essential services, as already reported, is a matter for the Local Authorities, but in the course of the Inquiry in 1934 my attention was directed in particular to the question of gas supply, particularly in view of the development of gas production arising from the operation of the coking industry. Through the courtesy of the Secretary of the Department of Health for Scotland, I was able to obtain the services of Dr. Birkett Wylam, a Departmental Inspector, who, on my behalf, undertook a careful survey of the existing gas production and supply services and, after consultation with many experts, formulated a technical scheme for a regional gas supply. The results of this enquiry appeared so promising that I have recommended the appointment of an expert Committee for the purpose of examining the data already collected and formulating a complete administrative scheme. Although this matter may pass beyond the scope of my function, I venture to hope that a development in the use of this product, both for industrial and domestic purposes, made possible by a suitable scheme of co-ordination energetically pursued, will react widely in the interests of all concerned in local industry.(d) Research, New Processes, etc.I have received proposals from a large number of undertakings and interests concerned in processes for the extraction of oil from coal, but having regard to the terms of the Act and the steps already being taken by other Authorities, I have been unable to take any useful action. Scientific researches into local resources, however, appeared incomplete in the matter of certain classes of Coal which are found in large quantities in the Special Areas. Accordingly I was able to assist in the appointment of a scientist for the purpose of carrying out practical experiments which, when complete, will be considered by an Expert Committee on this subject appointed by the Scottish National Development Council and will ensure that any special advantages offered by the Special Areas for this class of development are substantiated upon scientific data.
Action was also taken to consider the possibility of assisting in the work of exploring new coal measures in the Special Areas to which some reference was made in the Report of the Inquiry (1934).It proved, however, to be unnecessary for me to proceed further with the matter, as practical steps have now been taken by parties principally concerned to ascertain the facts regarding new measures. I have also been approached to assist in a number of schemes for de-watering existing coal measures, but, after very full examination, I was not satisfied that a case for the action proposed had been established, quite apart from certain doubts which existed as to my competency to give financial assistance in a matter of this kind.(e) Expenditure from the Special Areas Fund.The estimated expenditure from the Special Areas Fund during the present financial year in respect of schemes for industrial development is  22,911.2. Public Utility and Amenity Schemes.(a) Public Utility Services.The prolonged depression in the Special Areas has placed a severe strain on the resources of Local Authorities, who have found it necessary to levy high rates and have in many cases experienced difficulty in providing satisfactory Public Services. The inadequacy of these services has not only tended to retard industrial development, but has also been detrimental to public health. I have, therefore, considered it necessary, among my constructive plans, to investigate the scope for assisting Authorities in these cases without impinging on the functions of other Government Departments.As I have already explained, it has appeared to me entirely outside my province to consider the adoption of Public Works Schemes solely as a means of creating some temporary employment, but. one is forced to recognise the fundamental importance of efficient public utility services as a foundation for the development of modern industry.One of the first steps I took upon my appointment was to circu-larise all Local Authorities for information about the work regarded as essential for the above purpose.In the matter of public utility services, an urgent need was clearly established for the modernisation and improvement of sewage disposal and water supply. In some cases services had actually been destroyed by industrial operations, while in others industrial development was rendered quite impossible owing to inadequate and out-of-date provision. The situation&apos; also pointed to a serious risk to public health.As shewn in Appendix I, I have found it necessary to afford assistance to a large selection of schemes for the improvement of sewerage and water supply, in spite of the rejection of a number of less urgent but desirable schemes.   The selection of schemes was
based principally upon considerations of urgency and in relation to the general importance of the affected district as a potential site for economic development. In all cases I have been satisfied that the Authority concerned was unable to perform the works unaided, having regard to the unemployment and rating position, but my assistance has invariably been limited to an amount sufficient to encourage the Authority to act in specific cases, and I have not offered anymerely general subsidies. It is particularly gratifying to record the general helpfulness and sense of duty and enterprise which have actuated all the Local Authorities with whom I have been in touch, and the earnest desire they have displayed to overcome any difficulties.The works now approved and in hand together represent a total expenditure from all sources of nearly  1,300,000.Many of the works for which assistance was offered have involved close and detailed consideration in order to ensure a selection of schemes of permanent value, and I have received valuable assistance and technical guidance from Mr. D. Ronald, Chief Engineer, Depart-ment of Health for Scotland, and his staff. The fact that so many of the schemes are already in hand reflects credit on him and on my other collaborators. Certain essential public utility schemes additional to those shewn in Appendix I to this Report are now being examined (see Appendix II), and 1 anticipate that there is still a need of assistance for such schemes within the area. With a view to ensuring uniformity in the operation of all schemes and making necessary provision for supervision and the employment of men in accordance with the terms of the Special Areas Act, I have adopted model terms and conditions for application to all schemes of this class. Grants offered to Local Authorities have been subject to the acceptance of these conditions, which are shewn in Appendix III. Certain conditions are of an experimental character. Some are intended to facilitate the employment of men who have experienced prolonged unemployment, and who might, on that account, suffer under ordinary conditions in competition with their fellows. In others, I have aimed at encouraging the use of local products, without unduly restricting the choice and provision of the most satisfactory materials. In other respects, however, I have regarded it as impracticable to impose conditions which would involve drastic changes from general practice and possibly and materially to the cost of the works without conferring commensurate advantages.(6) Amenity Schemes.I have made a number of investigations into amenity schemes and proposals designed with the object of improving the physical attractiveness of the area.Large areas of the countryside are disfigured with bings of waste products from shale and coal-mining operations, much of the ground is ruined by subsidence due to mineral workings, and derelict
factory sites are numerous. Proposals for dealing with the latter problem are under active consideration by selected authorities in specially affected localities, with a view to schemes being submitted to me in due course. Investigations were directed towards specific cases of &quot; bing removal &quot; with a view to the adoption of experiments, but so far it has been found impracticable to start a scheme of this kind for the following reasons : (a) the cost of removal is prohibitive, particularly if the schemeis used primarily as a medium for the employment of labour;(b) present mining operations are still depositing large quantitiesof new waste and thus would render the principal object of the scheme nugatory ;(c) the area upon which the waste is deposited often provides nospace for levelling and the chemicals present in the waste in most cases prevent planting and other forms of treat-ment or use of the area.This difficult question is still engaging my careful attention. On the whole, it seems to me to be outside the sphere of practical operations to repair, in any general way, the gigantic destruction of the countryside which has already taken place. Certain bings, which are sufficiently mature, might conceivably be terraced and1 planted with shrubs and trees, if any could be found which would grow on such a soil. I have not given this question up, but I admit to grave doubts as to the possibility of remedial measures on a scale sufficient to be worth while.There are, however, a number of positive immediate needs in the matter of amenities, particularly in certain thickly populated areas, which Local Authorities have been unable to provide in present circumstances. I regard the provision of recreation grounds, swim-ming pools and open spaces generally as not only desirable for the welfare of the working population, particularly the unemployed, but as contributing very materially to the attractiveness of the area for industrial development. Selected schemes for these purposes are under active consideration and in some cases have already been approved (See Appendix I).(c) Volunteer Labour Schemes.I have paid particular regard to the possibility of assisting small communities to provide amenities with volunteer labour. In my opinion such schemes must be limited to cases where the men performing the work, and their families, will be the principal beneficiaries. The Scottish Special Areas, however, are character-ised by the concentration of the industrial population in compara-tively large towns, surrounded by rural districts. In consequence, facilities are usually required, if required at all, on such a large scale that the organisation ,of volunteer labour schemes presents insur-
mountable difficulties, and could seldom be justified on the basis referred to above.Up to the present date only one small scheme has been sub-mitted where voluntary labour is appropriate, and this question is still under discussion.[d) Special Public Services and Works.The schemes referred to above are generally within the normal scope of individual Local Authorities, but in the course of various consultations suggestions have been forthcoming regarding new large scale public services, including specific schemes such as the provision of civil aerodromes, of an industrial estate, and the preservation of certain reaches of the Clyde. In these cases dis-cussions have been initiated between the interested Departments and the Authorities concerned, and I have indicated my willingness to consider specific proposals which may be jointly submitted as a result of these discussions and to take action in approved cases.I shall hope to furnish further particulars of such schemes in subsequent reports, but at this early stage it is not possible to give more than a general indication that new proposals of a wide bearing may be evolved, in conformity with the objects of my appointment.(e) Expenditure from the Special Areas Fund.The estimated expenditure from the Special Areas Fund during the present financial year in respect of approved public works schemes of all classes is  220,069, while the sum of  351,093 repre-sents the anticipated commitment in respect of these schemes in subsequent years.Works on the scale referred to above necessarily involve a vast amount of preparatory work, and there is inevitably delay in the initial stages. The number of schemes still under consideration is so large, however, that I anticipate a rapidly increasing expendi-ture, even when due allowance is made for the restrictions I have imposed as to the class of scheme which I can assist.3. Land Developments. General.In approaching the subject of land development generally, I have endeavoured to combine purely ameliorative efforts with a long term constructive policy for the progressive establishment on the land of unemployed persons, particularly those who have little hope of return to their former industrial employment. In the development of every type of scheme for the reclamation, improve-ment and utilisation of land, I realised that, whatever subsequent arrangements might develop, I could facilitate the application of my initial plans by relying upon the assistance and vast store of practical experience of the Department of Agriculture for Scotland,
which for many years has directly carried out large schemes for the settlement of families on Small Holdings and the provision of plots for unemployed men, and in other ways laid a firm foundation of service available even for new types of schemes which might still be evolved.As previously stated, the Department has afforded almost continuous assistance in connection with my plans and the schemes already in hand, as well as many still under consideration, are benefiting from a close and cordial collaboration.(a) Land Reclamation.I have always been impressed by the idea of undertaking experiments based upon land reclamation, and I took early steps with the object of testing the possibilities upon a suitable scale.My first attempt in this direction involved an intensive survey of a large tract of land in the Carnwath district of Lanarkshire which offered attractive possibilities for an experiment of a varied nature, as it included land liable to floods, an area of peat-bog, and certain agricultural subjects the value of which would have been enhanced by a successful scheme of land reclamation. While the expert opinion which I consulted was for some time favourable to the scheme, a closer examination shewed that the expense involved would be out of proportion to the results obtained,, even if the experiment were successful. I accordingly felt obliged to abandon the proposal.On. rejecting, this particular scheme I turned my attention to other projects of a similar type which, are, I am advised, more promising, and technical and other investigations are actively in hand with a view to the early submission of specific proposals. I may add that in dealing with this difficult subject of. land reclama-tion and improvement I have been able to obtain the co-operation of. Local Authorities and scientific and other Bodies,, including the Macaulay Institute of Soil Research, Aberdeen, and a number of well-known agricultural experts.I am hopeful that proposals of a definite character can be submitted at an early date to* enable&apos; me to- undertake experiments which will have a value, apart from their immediate results, as illustrating the possibilities of various types of land reclamation.(;&amp;); Arterial Drainage Schemes.-In the course of consultations the Department of Agriculture brought to my attention certain important schemes of arterial drairi&apos;-age which were likely to assist agricultural development in- the Special Areas and which they were unable to carry out owing to the impending expiry of the Land Drainage (Scotland) Act, 1930. Upon representations being made by me; this Act was&apos; extended for a further period and the Department are making plans- to put selected schemes in hand at an- early date.   In certain cases,
notably at Lampits Farm, Carstairs, the scheme will release from flooding certain areas of land required for developments of my own, which are referred to below, and will thus directly facilitate my plans. The expenditure on such schemes will be a matter for the Department.(c) Experimental Farm Development.Steps are being taken with a view to the acquisition of suitable land for the creation of an experimental industrial farm, the principal object of which is to provide employment and training in branches of agricultural production, for older men whose hope of return to industrial employment is remote and who, by reason of age, cannot, be expected to undertake the arduous responsibilities of independent Small Holdings or to acquire the skill necessary for success in general agricultural duties.Negotiations are still proceeding for this purpose.(d) Land Settlement,)Small Holdings.Taking advantage of the foct that comprehensive settlement programme, involving the acquisition of land, is being carried out by the Department of Agriculture, I have endeaboured to collaborate with the Department in extending the opportunities for settlement in a manner involving certain new departures. A scheme has been agreed for the settlement on Departmental Small Holdings, of 5. acres or more in extent, of selected unemployed men who, owing to lack of capital, are unable to qualify under the ordinary scheme. This experiment provides for the training of settlers for a period of one year, upon the holding which they will eventually occupy as ordinary tenants, and the rpovision of working capital, on a loan basis. During the training period arragnements have been made for the payment of allowances by the Unemployment Assistance Board, and a special training staff has been provided with assistance from the Special Areas Fund. The recruitment of men for this scheme represents an example of a progressive change from industry to agriculture and the majority will be selected from fthose who have successfully cultivated plots as a spare-time occupation and who have thus proved their capacity and desire to make a livelihood on the alnd.The scheme provides stock, equipment and rent for each trainee at a maximum cost of  250 per man, the responsibility for which will be accepted by the settler only after the period of training. Thus the risk of failure should be reduced to a minimum. The initial arrangements provide for the settlement of 70 men with their families and, if successful, the scheme can be extended without the provision of new machinery.(e) Unemployed Plot Schemes.The Department of Agriculture have developed v/ith marked success a scheme for the provision of plots from \ to 1 acre in extent
for unemployed persons, particularly miners. In view of the grow-ing dimensions of this scheme under present arrangements, particu-larly in the Special Areas, it was obviously desirable to augment the Departments efficient efforts rather than to endeavour to supplement them by other schemes. The number of plots at present under cultivation in the Special Areas is approximately 1,000, representing more than 60 per cent, of the total in Scotland as a whole. Arrange-ments had already been made in the case of one or two plot schemes for furnishing additional stock to established holders and for the provision of necessary communal buildings and equipment, through the medium of the Joint Committee of the Scottish National Union of Allotment Holders and Society of Friends, in consultation with the Department. I have been impressed by the possibilities of this form of assistance, particularly as a means of enabling enterprising holders to progress from the purely spare-time occupation to the initial stages of agricultural production as such. Accordingly I have made provision, by arrangement with the above bodies, for loans up to the limit of  10 per man, so that all established plot holders in the Special Areas who have successfully cultivated their plots for a period of one year or more may obtain this additional help to develop their plots. The assistance also includes the cost of communal huts and other equipment for group holdings. I anticipate that the provision made will assist between 500 and 600 plot holders.(/) Allotment Schemes.I have given particular attention to the extension of Allotment Schemes which, based on a restricted individual area of from one-sixteenth to one-quarter of an acre, afford the chance not only of a health-giving and pleasant spare-time occupation, but also of material benefit, to a large section of unemployed persons who may have neither the desire nor the ability for land occupation on larger scales. Under the auspices of the Joint Committee of the Scottish National Union of Allotment Holders and Society of Friends, as well as numerous Local Allotment Associations, allot-ment schemes have already taken a firm hold in Scotland and have developed satisfactory. Preliminary enquiries shewed that one of the principal difficulties preventing further development was that of acquiring suitable land, particularly in the more congested areas. Occasionally failure in this respect had led unemployed persons to lose interest in this activity.With a view to retrieving the position in both respects and extending the scheme generally while making use of the practical experience already gained by the Joint Committee, I have provided that Body with a grant both for additional administration and the acquisition of land, and I am hopeful, by this method, that the scheme, already large, will be considerably extended in the Special Areas.   In Scotland it has not been the normal practice for Local
1Authorities to create Allotment Associations, although in many cases they have taken such action. I have, however, invited their general co-operation in this scheme and have received universal assurances of their support.(g) Special Experiment in Homecrofting.Finally I have to report the completion of arrangements with the Ministry of Labour for the transfer of Lampits Farm, Carstairs, which I am utilising for the purpose of an experiment to demonstrate group production on a subsistence basis known as Homecrofting, a scheme which has been propounded by Professor J. W. Scott, of Cardiff University. This experiment, which includes as an essential element the cultivation of land and other agricultural undertakings, is being set on foot for the purpose of demonstrating to selected men the practical possibilities of creating in the Special Areas group settlements in which the members of the groups will aim at producing as many of their common requirements as possible for their own support and mutual exchange. The scheme has many points of similarity with the experiment at Upholland, and the present trial will be under the personal direction of Professor Scott, whose services I have obtained for the purpose.The preliminary plans are now in course of completion, and arrangements have also been made with the Ministry of Labour and Unemployment Assistance Board for the payment of un-employment allowances during the period in which the men will be taking part in the demonstration. This proposal is capable of considerable development, and, if sufficient interest is shown in it by the unemployed, it may well prove to be a sensible factor in mitigating the economic difficulties inherent in prolonged unem-ployment, while at the same time providing the unemployed with an interesting and active life. I hope to report further about this experiment in due course.[h) Expenditure from the Special Areas Fund.The estimated expenditure from the Special Areas Fund during the present financial year in respect of schemes of land development already approved is  49,500, but plans which have not yet matured, principally owing to the delays in obtaining suitable land, will involve, if they materialise, expenditure approaching the sum of  2,000,000 (see Appendix II.). Steps are being taken to advance these plans as rapidly as possible.4. Special Problems, Labour Questions, etc.The work of inaugurating the specific schemes to which reference is made above has entailed constant investigation and discussion, not only with various authorities and executive bodies, but with representative employers of labour, trade union organisations and officials, and other responsible persons who are intimately concerned
with the day-to-day aspects of unemployment. I am happy to be able to record that cordial relationships have been established in all cases, and I have received, and am receiving, much helpful advice and information, particularly on some of the larger problems which cannot always be dealt with by purely local measures. I have had occasion, during the period under review, to take some action which, at least indirectly, may contribute something to the solution of the main problem. Although a record of work performed would be incomplete without some reference to this type of work, it is not possible to give more than a brief indication of the steps taken.In the course of consultations with certain of the Bodies referred to above, mention has been made of problems regarding working hours, labour supply, and other difficulties which contribute to the problem of unemplojnnent and to the continuance of the depression in the Special Areas.Many of these questions involve issues of general importance with which I am not, in strict theory, competent to deal under the Special Areas Act, but the parties concerned appear to feel that my special position entitles them to approach me, often in confidence, so that I may act as a medium for submitting recommendations to the proper quarter or otherwise for ascertaining whether the problem admits of solution by agreement.I am glad to think that this position has been so accepted.In consequence, I have made a number of recommendations on questions of this nature to Government Departments or other appropriate Authorities. In certain cases action quickly followed ; in others, of a more complex nature, consideration is still proceeding.5. Social Service Schemes.If a narrow view is taken of the problem of industrial depression and unemployment, it is possible to conclude that schemes of social service are relatively unimportant, and to regard them solely as ameliorative, having an uncertain and temporary effect. It is, however, becoming universally recognised that both the betterment of social environment generally and the profitable employment of leisure will remain fundamental necessities even if the more direct employment schemes succeed, and all the signs go to show that even future industrial prosperity may be associated with an increasing proportion of leisure for the workers. I have, therefore, approached the subject of these schemes with the feeling that, while the opportunity they afford for checking some of the temporary social evils of unemployment has already been taken, they have not always been designed upon lines which will ensure for them a permanent place in the general life of the community. Some of my experiments are new, while others may be described as a blend of old and new methods of procedure.
(a) Physical Culture Schemes,I have nothing but admiration for the qualities of endur-ance and cheerfulness shown by members of the unem ployed sections of the community in their trying experience. Never-theless, persons suffering enforced idleness must be peculiarly susceptible to dangers which may, if unchecked, become a direct cause of the continuance of the conditions in which such dangers thrive. I have been able to observe the beneficial results of a few voluntary physical culture classes for unemployed men as conducted by the Ministry of Labour, and I decided as one of my first measures to commence, with the active help of the Ministry, a similar series of classes in every part of the Special Areas where a concentration of unemployed men in sufficient numbers offered scope for con-tinuous classes. I make no excuse for this development of a well-tried scheme and for demonstrating that unemployed men, if given the opportunity, can set an example which might be universally followed.   The results amply justify the trial.At the beginning of the present year sixteen classes were com-menced under skilled instructors, paid out of the Special Areas Fund, and the expenditure has included the rental of necessary accommodation, supply of equipment and a personal kit which is issued free to each man joining a class. Since the inauguration of this scheme, further classes for men have started as the demand increased, and arrangements are also being made to start classes for young women, as an experiment, in one or two centres in response to a demand. Between 2,000 and 3,000 men now regularly attend the classes and the numbers are steadily increasing.During personal visits of inspection, I was able to satisfy myself as to the enjoyment and benefit derived by the men, and I was greatly impressed by the resourcefulness of the instructors, under the efficient guidance of the Chief Instructor, Captain Lamb, in making the classes attractive. Some of the exercises successfully accomplished provided striking evidence of the keenness of the men and their admirable physical condition, and a visit from employers of labour and others interested would provide them with unanswer-able facts about the quality of reserve labour in the area. The curriculum is designed solely to maintain a sound body and an alert mind, and re-equip the unemployed in both respects to main-tain their place in the labour market. Purely physical exercises, are enlivened by competitive games involving rapid thinking, and, in fact, I have ensured that anything within the field of organised recreation should be encouraged, whenever practicable.From the -commencement of the scheme recruitment has been maintained at a satisfactory level through the efforts of Exchange Managers and other local officers&quot; of the Ministry of Labour. It is particularly noteworthy that, if a man leaves a class, as he -is entirely free to do at any time, it is usually for the satisfactory reason that he has found employment.
I propose to continue this scheme and to expand it to the greatest possible extent wherever a demand exists.(b) Welfare Work for Adolescents.After consultations which were ably conducted on my behal^ by Mr. G. E. Troup, Secretary of the Scottish Juvenile Welfare Office, who is one of the best known experts on Youth Welfare Movements, all the leading Scottish Organisations concerned with the welfare of Youth submitted schemes to be applied by them in the Special Areas. The proposals made covered a very wide field, and were designed principally as a means of enabling unemployed boys and girls to enjoy benefits upon an equal footing with their more fortunate fellows, and for the training of leaders, provision of camps and special clubs.I am glad to think that proposals initiated before the establish! ment of the King&apos;s Jubilee Trust will provide an immediate found-ation for developments in the Special Areas, as well as information which can be used for the promot;on of new schemes on a more permanent footing.The details of the Grants-in-Aid made to each of the Organisations are given in Appendix I.The transference, training and employment of adolescents are matters within the normal sphere of the Ministry of Labour, but in view of the difficulties observed during my Inquiry in 1934, I have examined the possibility of assisting in the provision of welfare hostels for youths transferred to employment in London and else-where. I regret that administrative difficulties which have been explained to me and legal doubts as to my competence in this matter have prevented me from taking practical measures. The urgent and complicated question of juvenile employment is so serious, however, particularly in view of the distressing surplus of young workers in the Scottish Special Areas, that I venture to hope that no effort will be spared to remove any difficulties which may detain youths from taking every opportunity of employment which presents itself. In the course of my efforts to assist in discovering ways and means, my attention has been directed to a certain measure of opposition to the transfer of young persons to other areas.While one has naturally sympathy with the idea of absorbing the large surplus of youths into satisfactory employment locally, I am more impressed by the practical consideration that, unless advantage is taken of every reasonable opportunity wherever it exists, many of these unemployed young persons will deteriorate into adult unemployables before purely local plans of a sufficiently comprehensive nature to absorb them could possibly mature, if, indeed, they could ever become a practicable proposition.I believe that the opposition to juvenile transfer arises largely from sentimental motives, coupled with ignorance of the facts. But there is also, no doubt, some feeling of quite legitimate appre-
hension on the part of parents and other relatives as to the welfare of youthful workers in novel surroundings. These grounds for opposition would be largely removed if schemes for juvenile transfer were accompanied by comprehensive welfare arrangements which made provision for all the difficulties and dangers to which young workers in a strange locality are peculiarly susceptible.It may be hoped that the increasing facilities of communication in the country generally may in due course tend to make departure from home seem a less formidable proposition.Meanwhile, as regards the question of hostels, I hope that, if I am debarred myself from providing them outside the Special Areas, for reasons which I must unwillingly accept, I may at any rate stimulate their provision from other sources, and I propose to pursue the matter further in this sense.(c) Welfare Work for Children.I have commenced discussions with the Department of Health for Scotland and the Scottish Education Department with a view to the establishment, under suitable auspices, of play and health centres for the children of unemployed persons in the Special Areas. I understand that most parts of the area have little or no provision for children of pre-school age, and for children of school age after school hours, and no action for social improvement can be complete without adequate provision in this respect.I shall hope to report details of specific experimental schemes in subsequent reports.(d) Spare-Time Occupation.Having recognised the growing importance of the proper use ,of leisure, particularly in connection with unemployment, I have taken steps to examine the provision of Community Service Clubs in the Special Areas. These Clubs fall within the sphere of the Scottish and Regional Councils for Community Service during Unemployment. It is apparent that the Scottish Council and Local Organisations, relying principally on voluntary funds, have been forced to restrict their operations within very circumscribed limits which often become an irreducible minimum in localities where the workers represent almost the total population.After consultation with the Council, I have provided a Grant for the creation in selected districts of a number of Occupational and General Community Service Centres on model lines. The Grant is primarily intended to meet the initial difficulties of obtaining satisfactory accommodation and equipment, on a scale which will admit of more permanent development.The formulation of each scheme is being entrusted to representa-tive Local Organisations, if necessary specially created for the purpose with the assistance of the Council, and these bodies will be responsible under the general control of the Council for the
subsequent operation of the Centres. The principal aim is to combine local effort with financial assistance, and so bring about a development adequate in its general conception to ensure that it will attract the active interest and co-operation of all sections of the community.The Grant provided also includes extra assistance to the Council for the. organisation of this particular development.In addition to taking these steps, I have initiated a special experiment in Social Service on the following lines.My attention was drawn to the existence of an estate, comprising a large mansion and forty acres of grounds, known as Carfin Hall, New Stevenston, which had recently been vacated as a Welfare Centre by the firm of Messrs. Stewarts and Lloyds, Limited. This property is situated in the centre of the Special Areas, being in close proximity to Bellshill and other congested industrial districts of Lanarkshire. Through the kindness of the firm in question, I was able to acquire the property on most favourable terms, and it is now undergoing development into a large-scale community service centre and residential settlement.Having regard to the exceptional possibilities of this property, I have directly controlled the organisation of the initial activities and have appointed a representative organising Committee to advise me upon the permanent establishment. The active interest already shown in this scheme by all sections of the community affords hope that it may become, by the combined efforts of all concerned, an important practical experiment in Social Service of considerable value for purposes of demonstration over a wide area, as well as for the immediate provision of cultural and recreational facilities for the community in the vicinity itself.The accommodation is adequate for all kinds of cultural and recreational activity, for both men and women, and consideration is also being given to the provision of special facilities for children. The Organising Committee will immediately proceed to issue an appeal for voluntary funds and service to supplement my assistance, and a number of voluntary Organisations have already undertaken the responsibility of providing auxiliary services.I regard this -scheme as a comprehensive experiment in Social Service, in which it is hoped to utilise the practical experience gained by a variety of social workers and Organisations. If the experiment succeeds, as I trust it will, it may result in a Model Centre of Social Service being evolved, which will have more than a local interest and utility.(e) Health Services.As a result of inquiries made on my behalf by the Department of Health for Scotland and the Queen&apos;s Institute of District Nursing, I obtained information which showed an unfortunate retrenchment in nursing services by District Associations in certain specially
depressed parts of the Special Areas. Proposals to assist these Associations were submitted to me by the Institute, and I am glad to record that a small Grant-in-Aid from the Special Areas Fund, administered by the Institute, has not only resulted in the provision of improved services, but has directly encouraged further local efforts.I have also under consideration the provision of hospitals and other medical services in cases where the existing arrangements are inadequate, and may be attributed to industrial depression, and the Local Authorities are being invited in the course of consulta-tions, in which the Department of Health are affording direct assistance, to submit specific proposals for my consideration.(/) Holiday Camps for  Unemployed Persons.In view of representations made to me by the Scottish Council for Community Service during Unemployment regarding the value, proved by experience, of short holiday camps for unemployed men, I have offered a Grant-in-Aid to the Council for the organisa-tion of a family camp. The camp at present being organised will provide a holiday for approximately 300 families of men who have experienced prolonged unemployment.In addition, the Council are organising, or providing facilities in connection with, camps for children and young persons, so far as these are outside the scope of the several Youth Organisations, and the Grant-in-Aid will assist in meeting expenditure on this account. I hope, in subsequent reports, to furnish details of the result of these experiments.(g) Expenditure from the Special Areas Fund.The estimated expenditure from the Special Areas Fund during the present financial year, in respect of Social Service Schemes of all classes already approved, is  67,000, of which  14,500 represents Grants (Subhead D.1) and  52,500 is provided as Grants-in-Aid (Subhead D.2), and further information regarding schemes still under consideration is shown in Appendix I.6. Effect of Approved Schemes on Unemployment.Having regard to the wide variety of schemes which have been adopted, or which are in course of preparation, a reliable estimate of their statistical effect on unemployment presents great difficulty. It will also be apparent that many schemes which offer the greatest promise of permanent improvements produce little or no immediate effect. It is a satisfactory feature of certain schemes for works of public utility that they do, in fact, contribute a measure of immediate amelioration of unemployment, but, in my opinion (as already indicated), their principal justification lies in the fact that they are essentially constructive and produce conditions tending to facilitate the future industrial development of the area.   The figures quoted
in Appendix I, shewing the estimated employment and other benefits directly arising from the approved schemes, should, there-fore, be regarded as minima.7. Financial Commitments  of the  Special Areas Fund.In respect of schemes of all classes already approved at the present date, the estimated commitment oi the Special Areas Fund is  736,222, including  9,800 for administration expenses in the current year. The above estimate necessarily excludes a large number of schemes still under consideration and proposals which are in course of preparation by Local Authorities and other Bodies prior to sub-mission. Although it is probable, having regard to initial adminis-trative difficulties which inevitably arise and may affect expenditure in the early stages, that some of the grants offered will not be wholly expended during the present year, every effort is being made to advance the actual operations in each case as far as practicable. Hence it is still possible that the Estimate will be exhausted at the end of the year and that further funds will be necessary before that time.As far as can be estimated at present, the actual expenditure from the Special Areas Fund during the present financial year will be  359,490, excluding administration.   (See Appendix I for details).In the case of certain public work and similar large-scale schemes, it has been necessary to offer grants outside the present Estimate, and in respect of expenditure anticipated in subsequent financial years.   Estimates of such expenditure are shown in Appendix I.With the exception of grants-in-aid, all expenditure from the Fund, whether direct or through outside agencies, is controlled by detailed conditions and is subject to the detailed supervision of my administrative staff. In this important matter I am also receiving assistance from the technical and finance sections of other Depart-ments, as already reported.I have the honour to be, Sir,Your obedient Servant,H. Arthur Rose,Commissioner for the Special Areas in Scotland.13 Carlton Terrace, Edinburgh. 8th July, 1935.
SCHEDULE OF SCHEMES FOR WHICH FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE FROM THE SPECIAL AREAS FUND HAS BEEN PROVIDEDSchemes Approved and in OperationAppendix IDescription of Scheme.	Scheme to be carried out by.	Total estimated cost of Scheme.	Approx. ., total commit-ment of Special Areas Fund.	Total estimated expenditure in financial year.			Persons directly employed.		Remarki.				1935-30.	1936-37.	1937-38.	No.	Period.	A. Industrial Development:  1. Publicity and Special Information 2. Extract of Oil from Coal (Research)	Scottish National Develop-ment Council. Do.	22^500 800	  22,500 800	  *22,500 * 411	  389	 	10 1	12 months 24    ,,	To be utilised as op-opportunity occurs. Experiment to be spread over 2 years.		23,300	23,300	22,911	389	-	12 men-years		B. Public Works :-1. Irvine Valley Sewage     ..      .. 2. Garnock Valley Sewage........ 3. Water Supply (Northern Ayrshire) 4. Blantyre and Bothwell Sewage...... S. Holytown and New Stevenston Sewage 6. Uddingston and Baillieston Sewage 7. Newarthill and Carfin Sewage   .. 8. Larkhall Sewage.......... 9. Shotts and Dykehead Sewage...... 10. Promenade Road 11. Sewage Purification and Outfall Sewers.. 12. Sewerage and Sewage Purification 13. River Wall and Recreation Ground 14. Sewage      ............ Clear Water Tank and Filter Beds 15. Sewage      ......      ..      ....	Ayr County Council Lanark County Council .. Motherwell  and  Wishaw Burgh Council. Hamilton Burgh Council . Do. Bathgate Burgh Council .. Do. Armadale Burgh Council ..	59,390 161,500 .  32,000 122,300 119,500 259,800 34,500 42,700 49,000 60,000 108,000 142,000 7,131 7,140 5,500 17,600	17,820 48,450 9,600 48,920 47,800 103,920 13,800 17,080 19,600 60,000 36,000 106,500 5,350 2,380 1,833 7,040	7,500 19,380 4,800 19,570 19,120 41,570 5,520 6,830 9,100 15,000 14,400 35,500 3,350 1,850 1,700 2,820	10,320 29,070 4,900 29,350 28,680 62,350 8,280 10,250 10,500 45,000 21,600 47,300 2,000 530 133 4,220	23,700	85 275 80 150 140 250 50 60 95 500 133 120 30 60 25 55	18 months 24    ,, 12     ,, 18    ,, 18     ,, 24     ,, 18     ,, 18     ,, 15     ,, 12     ,, 36     ,, 24    ,, 9 9    ,. 9 16    ,,		Carried forward	1,228,061	546,093	208,010	314,383	23,700	3,275 men-years		* Includes expenditure in 1934-35 Financial Year.JN3 *N3
SCHEDULE OV SCHEMES FOR WHICH FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE FROM THE SPECIAL AREAS FUND HAS BEEN PROVIDEDSchemes Approved and in OperationAppendix IDescription of Scheme.	Scheme to be carried out by.	Total estimated cost of Scheme.	Approx. , total commit-ment of Special Areas Fund.	Total estimated expenditure in financial year. - \-			Persons directly employed.		Remarks.				1935-36.	1936-37.	1937-38.	No.	Period.	A. Industrial Development:  1. Publicity and Special Information 2. Extract of Oil from Coal (Research)	Scottish National Dcvclop-ment Council. Do.	  22,500 800	  22,500 800	  *22,500	 	 	10	12 months	To be utilised as op-				* 411	389	-	1	24    ,,	opportunity occurs. Experiment   to   be. spread over 2 years.		23,300	23,300	22,911	389	-	12 men-years		B. Public Works :-1. Irvine Valley Sewage     ........ 2. Gamock Valley Sewage........ 3. Water Supply (Northern Ayrshire) 4. Blantyre and Bothwell Sewage...... 5. Holytown and New Stevenston Sewage 6. Uddingston and Baillieston Sewage 7. Newarthill and Carfin Sewage 8. Larkhall Sewage.......... 9. Shotts and Dykehead Sewage    ..      .. 10. Promenade Road........ 11. Sewage Purification and Outfall Sewers..       .. 12. Sewerage and Sewage Purification 13. River Wall and Recreation Ground 14. Sewage     ......      ...... Clear Water Tank and Filter Beds 15. Sewage     ........      - -	Ayr County Council Lanark County Council .. Motherwell   and   Wishaw Burgh Council. Hamilton Burgh Council . Do. Bathgate Burgh Council .. Do. Armadale Burgh Council ..	59,390 161,500 .  32,000 122,300 119,500 259,800 34,500 42,700 49,000 60,000 108,000 142,000 7,131 7,140 5,500 17,600	17,820 48,450 9,600 48,920 47,800 103,920 13,800 17,080 19,600 60,000 36,000 106,500 5,350 2,380 1,833 7,040	7,500 19,380 4,800 19,570 19,120 41,570 5,520 6,830 9,100 15,000 14,400 35,500 3,350 1,850 1,700 2,820	10,320 29,070 4,900 29,350 28,680 62,350 8,280 10,250 10,500 45,000 21,600 47,300 2,000 530 133 4,220	23,700	85 275 80 150 140 250 50 60 95 500 133 120 30 60 25 55	18 months 24     ,, 12     ,, 18     ,, 18     ,, 24     ,, 18 18     ,, 15     ,, 12     ,, 36     ,, 24     ,, 9 9     ,, 9     ,, 16		Carried forward	1,228,061	546,093	208,010	314,383	23,700	3,275 men-years		* Includes expenditure in 1934-35 Financial Year.
GENERAL LIST OF SPECIFIC SCHEMES UNDER ACTIVE CONSIDERATION IN WHICH DETAILS OF COST HAVE NOT YET BEEN FULLY ASCERTAINED.Appendix II.(In so far as estimates have been prepared the total approximate cost as at the present date is indicated.)	Type of Scheme.	No. of specific schemes.	No. of schemes in which cost is not	Schemes for which estimates have been prepared.				known.	No.	Amount.1.	Industrial Developments  West of Scotland Regional Gas Supply. Construction of Aerodromes	1 1	1 . T	._	 2.	Public Works  Sewage and Water Supply Recreation Grounds, Public Parks and other Amenities. Demolition of Derelict Property Hospitals	14 6 1	note	14 6 nown	277,870 98,5853.	Land Developments  Small holdings for plot-holders. . Large Scale Area Development. . Arterial Drainage Experimental Peat Reclamation Experimental   Farm   Develop-ments.	1 1 To be car ment of A 2 1	ried out b griculture land.	1 1 y Depart-for Scot-2 1	18,190 1,725,000 40,000 50,0004.	Social Service  Play Centres for Children		Not k	nown	Note. The costs shown cover estimated expenditure from all sources and not the actual possible commitment of the Special Areas Fund.
APPENDIX III.THE   COMMISSIONER  FOR  THE   SPECIAL   AREAS  IN   SCOTLANDTERMS AND&apos; CONDITIONS OF GRANTS FROM THE SPECIAL AREAS   FUND   FOR  APPROVED   SCHEMES   OF  WORK.Terms of Grant.The grant will be payable subject to(a) the fulfilment of the following conditions,(6) a written guarantee by the Local Authority to bear the mainten-ance cost of the work carried out, and of the service provided, and(c) aii&apos;understanding that no part of this scheme qualifies for a grant payable by any Government Department.The Commissioner reserves the right to discontinue or to disallow the Grant in any case where he considers that the conditions have not been fuhHedl or that the work is being or has been carried out negligently, or without adequate supervision and control or that the plans and specifications have been departed from without the sanction of the Commissioner. When the work is done by contract, the Local Authority is responsible for the observance by the Contractor of the condition imposed.Conditions of Grant.1. No part of the Overhead charges, transport charges and other normal expenses of the Local Authority shall be included in the cost of the scheme for purposes of grant, nor shall payment made to the regular employees of the Authority rank for grant.2. Except as provided in paragraph 3 below, all men engaged on the work must be unemployed men taken on through the Ministry of Labour Employ-ment Exchange in the area in which the work is undertaken.3. The Local Authority or its contractor will be at liberty to engage and employ for controlling and supervisory purposes, or on &quot; key &quot; duties, a number of employees not exceeding 10 per cent, of the total number of men employed on the work, according to the Wages Book.4. Before engagement, each man must satisfy the Employment Exchange that he has been a resident within the Special Areas as defined in Part II of the First Schedule o! the Special Areas (Development and Improvement) Act, 1934, for a period of six months within the year immediately preceding the commencement of work. Preference shall be given to married men over 35 years of age or to younger married men who have passed through a course of training at an Instructional Centre. This Clause will not be applicable to skilled or supervisory workers employed under paragraph 3.5. Men engaged under paragraph 2 shall not be discharged on the ground that they are unsuitable, without reasonable trial of not less than one fort-night&apos;s working time, but this clause shall not apply in the case of men guilty of misconduct, serious breaches of working rules, etc.6. The Local Authority will be required to submit periodically to the Commissioner or his representative a return respecting men employed in such form and at such dates as the Commissioner may require.7. The Local Authority shall provide working trousers and boots to work-men in whose case such an issue is considered necessary.8. All materials, including manufactured articles which are required for work, must be of United Kingdom origin, subject, however, to such exceptions as the Commissioner may find to be necessary or desirable in any particular case having regard to all the circumstances. Steps shall be taken by the Local Authority and/or Contractor, through appropriate agencies, to circulate
within the Special Areas invitations to tender for the supply of materials, including manufactured articles, required for the work.A report shall be sent to the Commissioner where no tenders are received from undertakings in the Special Areas or where tenders submitted are not successful, indicating the reason for rejection.9. Where the Local Authority undertakes the work by direct labour, the rates of wages paid shall be the Local Authority&apos;s rate to its own workmen on similar classes of work, or the recognised district rate for similar worke, whichever is the lowest. Where work is carried out by contract, the contract must include the Fair Wages Clause as inserted in Government Contracts.10. Overtime and special working arrangement shall not be resorted to except with the approval of the Commissioner or his representative.11. The books of accounts of expenditure of the scheme shall be audited by the person appointed by the Secretary of State to audit the accounts of the Local Authority and the annual and/or ffnal accounts duly certified by such Auditors, in a form approved by the Commissioner shall be furnished within three months of the end of the year or the completion of the work, whichever is earlier. Interim accounts shall be rendered to the Commissioner at such times as he may request, and the books and accounts referred to and all subsidiary records, work plans and other documents relating to the scheme shall be available, if required for examination by the Commissioner or by any official of any other Government Department acting on his behalf and by the Comptroller and Auditor General and his officers.12 The work shall be open at any time to any inspection required by the Commissioner or his representative.13. The whole works must be completely finished not later than the date stipulated in the Commissioners letter intimating the Grant, and no Grant will normally be paid on work remaining to be completed after that date, unless the Commissioner has previously given his consent to an extension of time.Plans and Specifications.14. [a) Before work is commenced there shall be submitted to the Commissioner, duplicate for his approval, such plans as are ordinarily necessary for works of that class showing the nature and extent of the work proposed, together with statement by the Local Authority showing in detail the total estimated cost of the scheme, and the work shall not be commenced before the Commissioner signifies his approval. One set of plans shall be retained by the Commissioner and the other set returned to the Local Authority duly docqueted by the Commissioner.(6) Where works are to be carried out by contract tenders shall be called for by advertisement in the local press and in appropriate technical papers and periodicals and before a tender has been accepted there shall be submitted to the Commissioner the three lowest tenders which may have been received for the work and a note indicating the tender proposed to be accepted. After approval by the Commissioner and acceptance by the Local Authority, a certified copy of the tender accepted and a copy of the specification shall be sent to the Commissioner.(c) No variation in the work except in minor details will be made without the approval of the Commissioner, and in no case shall works involving an increase in expenditure be admitted for Grant purposes, unless prior sanction for such increase in cost has been given by the Commissioner.
SUMMARY OF SCHEMESType of Scheme.Total Esti-mated Cost.Approx.Total Commit-ment of Special Areas Fund.total estimated Expenditure in financial year.1935-36.1936-37.1937-38.No. of personsem-ployedSchemes approved and in hand -A. Industrial Develop-ment.B. Public Works . ... C Land DevelopmentD. Social ServiceE. miscellaneous total 23,300 1,297,594 49,500 82,450 10 23,300 571,162 49,500 82,450 10 22,911 220,069 49,500 67,000 10 389 323,44315,45027,6501,452,854726,422359,490339,28227,650* These figures exclude all persons indirectly employed and also the considerable number of persons otherwise benefiting from particular schemes.
Description of Scheme.16. Sewage 17. California Sewage 18. Limerigg Sewage 19. Whitecross Sewage 20. Redding Sewage 21. Redding Outfall Sewage 22. Lay-out of two Public ParksC. Land Development: 1. Lampits Farm (Carstairs) (home craft Demori-stration Centre).2. Homecrofting      .......;      ...3. Special Allotment Schemes        ..4. Loans to PlotholdersD. Social Service:  1. Occupational Centres2. Physical Training Classes .3. District Nursing4. Holiday Camps.....;5. Carfin Hall Social Service Centre6. Welfare of Adolescents : BoysGirls.......e. Miscellaneous.:  ;Substitution of Irish Labour in Potato Fields. Rly.i fares to Ayrshire of men from Special Area.Scheme to be carried out by.Brought forward Dumbarton Burgh CouncilStirling County Council Airdrie Burgh CouncilProf. Scott for Commis-sioner.Do.Joint Com mi tee of the Scot-tish National Union of Allotment Holders and the Society of Friends. Do.Scottish Council for Com-munity Service. Commissioner with assist-.ance from Ministry ofLabour. Queen&apos;s Institute of DistrictNursing. Scottish Council for Com-munity Service. Commissioner and Govern-ing Body.^ Youth Organisations      ^Ministry of LabourTotal estimated cost of Scheme. 1,228,061 47,500 3,800 1,186 1,400 7,000 4,100 4,5471,297,59420,00010,500 14,0005,00049,50036,000 8,5001,200 5,000 6,00015,000 10,75082,450Approx.total commit-ment of Special Areas Fund. 546,093 15,830 1,267 395 467 2,333 1,367 3,41020,00010,500 14,0005,00049,50036,000 8,5001,200 5,000 6,00015,000 10,75082,45010Total estimated expenditure in financial year.1835-36. 208,010 3,950 1,267 395 467 2,333 1,367 2,28020,00010,500 14,00049,50036,000 t8,5001,200 5,000 6,0006,000 4,3001936-37. 314,383 7,9301,1309,000 6,4501937-38. 23,700 3,950Persons directly employed.Period.3,275 men-years 110 &apos; 15 15 14 -   32 &apos;   22No figures yet available18 months 6    ,, 4 3 6 63,483 men-years24 months28 men-years12 months 24    ,,24 ,, 24 ,, 24     ,,108 men-yearsRemarks.The proposals for Lampits are being recast* Grant-in-Aid.    ,t Includes expenditure in 1934-35 Financial Year,

</content>
</cab>
