<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/256/0 images: 170-172</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
LabourParty Resolution in House of Commons on Tuesday, 23rd July, on Reports of Commissioners for the Special Areas.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour,The terms of the Motion to be put down by the Labour Party on Tuesday next, 23rd July, with regard to Mr. Stewart&apos;s Report are not yet known, but subject to any reconsideration that may be necessary when the Motion is published I suggest that our reply should be on the following lines.We might begin by pointing out that the Opposition are in such haste to censure the Government for their treatment of the Special Areas that within a few days of the publication of Mr. Stewart&apos;s report they invite the   Government to announce their intentions in regard to a document which not merely analyses the problems of the Special Areas and describes what the Commissioner is doing to carry out his experimental functions, but propounds a number of varying schemes,  some new and some old, affecting not merely the Special Ar-eas but the country as a whole.    Some of his schemes are covered by Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s proposals and the Government&apos; s attitude with regard to them will be made known by Tuesday.     The time   at the disposal of the Government has clearly been insufficient to enable them to form an opinion of the consequences in the Special Areas and elsewhere of the   recommendations at the end of his Report.     There is no foundation whatever for the statements that were made within a few hours of publication of the Report to the effect that the Government proposed to take no action. At this point it can be reiterated that the secret. CP. 148 (35),CABINET.Copy No.       U I
problem of the depressed areas is an old one which has baffled all previous Governments and that, as the Commissioner points out, it cannot be solved quickly.     It shows no lack of,sympathy with the misfortune of those who live in these areas if, instead of rushing to adopt popular slogans which may harm the whole country including the Special Areas, the process of experiment which the Commissioner was appointed to carry out and is carrying out with gratifying success, proceeds pari passu with the steady, progressive improvement of general economic conditions which is being brought about by the Government&apos;s policy and the confidence which it engenders.We might then deal with the first part of the Report containing a review of what the Commissioner has been able to do, and if these are set out in detail they make a considerable story.As regards the limitations on his powers to which Mr. Stewart refers we can refer to the chancellor s speech of 14-th November and show how in each of the spheres suggested as a scope for the Commissioner&apos;s experiments, Mr. Stewart has been able to make useful progress, emphasising in particular&apos; what he has been able to do for land settle-ment and to extend the voluntary social services.   It will be pointed, out that the Commissioner is going on with his experiments and is not stinted for money for them.     In regard to transference the Government hayc already done much, a.nd whole-heartodly agree with the principle of transference as Mr. Stewart defines it.     They intend to support it in every practicable way.,   with due regard to the unemployment position in the receiving areas.     With the assistance of the Unemployment Assistance Board they hope to make still further progress.     The limitations on the Commissionerls powers may be shown in many cases, to flow from the principle which he quotes with approval, 1 that it is clearly uneconomical and inefficient for the Commissioner to initiate activities which can better he performed by existing Departments already possessing the necessary machinery and experience.1
As regards his being subject to orthodox financial control suit of his activities being under the general control of the Minister of Labour, it should not be difficult to convince the House of the desirability of reserving ultimate control for them over the activities of the Commissioners through the control which they can exercise over Ministers.     Limitation of areas raises a more difficult point and probably all we can say at this stage is that a line has to be drawn somewhere and difficulties will arise wherever it is drawn. It is important, moreover, not to dissipate the Commissioner&apos;s experimental activities over too wide a field.     The other limitations are of less importance and Departmental action can perhaps overcome their consequences. We can completely repudiate the suggestion which has been made in the Press and which will doubtless he voiced by Members of the Opposition, that there has &quot;been a stranglehold in Whitehall which has prevented the Commissioner from carrying out the limited mandate entrusted to him.In general we should go as far as we can in emphasising that it is the intention of the Government to neglect no method of assisting the Special Areas which is likely to be effectual in this direction.(Initd) E.B.19th July, 1955.H.Q. 647-65 H.E.

</content>
</cab>
