<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/256/0 images: 237-248</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
150CABINET.STATE OF TRADE - JUNE,  1955. Note by the President of the Board of Trade.I circulate to my colleagues a summary of the reports submitted to the Board of Trade Advisory Council on the state of trade in June, 1935.W.R.SECRET. Q-P. 154(35).Board of Trade,22nd July, 1935.COPY NO.   4 4
CONFIDENTIAL.A.C.328BOARD OF TRADE ADVISORY COUNCIL,STATE OF TRADE - JUNE, 1935.Summary of reports submitted by members of the Board of Trade Advisory Council (supplemented in some cases with statistical information from other sources).OVERSEAS TRADE.    Imports in June at  57.8 m. were  3.3 m. less than in June, 1934, imports of food, drink and tobacco decreasing by  1.9 m. and of raw materials by  1.2 m.    Exports of United Kingdom goods were  32.9 m. or  0.8 m. more than a year ago.    Exports of manufactured goods increased by  0.6 m. Re-exports amounted to  5.2 m. as compared with  4.3 m. a year earlier,EMPLOYMENT. The total number of persons on the registers of Employment Exchanges at 24th June was 2,000,110, a decrease of 44,648 as compared with a month earlier.The main variations were:-The estimated number of insured persons aged 16-64 in employment at 24th June was 10,361,000.    This was 27,000 more than a month earlier and 188,000 more than a year ago.An improvement in employment was recorded in building, public works contracting, engineering and iron-founding, shipbuilding and ship-repairing,  iron and steel and tinplate manufacture, hosiery and jute industries and certain food manufacturing industries.    There was a further increase in the numbers temporarily stopped in the coal mining industry and some decline in employment in most of the clothing trades, including boot and shoe manufacture and in the motor vehicle industry.London- 8,074- 11,473- 14,182 4- 832 4- 23,486- 11,937- 18,254South Eastern. South Western. Midlands......North Eastern. North Western. Scotland.....Wales5,040
152RAILWAY TRAFfflO.    During the four weeks ended 30th June railway traffic receipts increased by  458,000 (3.95$!) as compared with the corresponding period of 1934.    There were increases of 10.0$! and 0.1% respectively in the receipts from passenger traffic and coal,  coke    and patent fuel, while merchandises minerals and live stock fell by 2.47%0    The comparison, however,  is affected by the incidence of &quot;Whitsuntide. The total receipts for the 26 weeks ended 30th June amounted to  71.7 m,  as against  71.4 m.  for the same period in 1934.SHIPPING.    The index number   for shipping freights (1913 s 100)  was 75.90 in June as against 76.62 in May and 73*59 twelve months ago.    The amount of laid up tonnage at ports in Great Britain and Ireland at the 1st July, 1935,  is provisionally estimated at 588,000 net tons as against 706,000 net tons on the 1st April and 1,042,000 net tons a year ago.    The reduction is stated to be mainly due to scrapping and sales to foreigners.Tonnage under construction qn the 30th June, 1935, amounted to 560,000 tons as compared with 587,000 tons a year ago.    During the June quarter tonnage commenced amounted to 108,000 gross tons as compared with 147,000 gross tons in the same quarter of last year,BANKING.    Early in the month money was in some demand in spite of the release to the Market of  35 m. War Loan interest, but the position became easier later.    Discount rates showed a hardening tendency throughout most of the month, mainly owing to the probability of expensive loans having to be taken from the Bank over the half-year end.    The Treasury bill rate rose from ll/2d. on the 7th June to 16/ld.  on the 21st June but fell on the 28th to 12/ld.Apart from a franc scare at the beginning of the month the foreign exchange market was quiet.    In the middle of the month the formation of the Laval Government caused some firmness in the franc    and during the last week of the month the forward rate
narrowed to about Pcs. l  discount.    There has been a tendency for expatriated funds to return to the gold bloc countries, and the feeling is that their more urgent currency troubles are over until the Autumn although the fundamental position is unchanged.There was some nervousness in the gold market early in the month owing to the instability of the French Government which was reflected in the wider premiums paid for gold.    Later,, however,  the premium narrowed.The silver market has been unsettled during the most of the month,  mainly owing to selling from China and,  at the end of the month, from India, though the weakness has been less pronounced than it might have been owing to support from America. The price of cash silver varied between 31d. and 35fd,COAL.    The average wtekly output for the  quarter ended 25th May was 4.19 m. tons as compared with 4,14. m.  tons in the same period of 1934, an increase of Ifc.    The average number of persons employed during this period was 764,300 as against 781,400 a year ago.    Exports in June,  1935, were  3.06 m. tons as against 3.56 m.  tons in June last year.    Exports in June to the Irish Free State showed a considerable  increase over last year, while  there was also a small increase in shipments to Argentina, Iceland and Greece.    Most other markets snowed a decline as compared with Jutiu,  1934, Canada,  the Scandinavian countries, Germany, France and Italy buing particularly affected.IRON AND. STEEL.    The activity which developed in the iron and steel markets in May was well maintained during June,  though export business did not increase to the same extent as home demand.    Business in pig iron,  though satisfactory in volume, was mainly confined to small parcels until the  turn of the half year when a number of contracts were renewed.    The market for semi-finished material was busy.    The demand for finished steel was steady and most branches were making good deliveries against current contracts.
154Scotland..    Busy conditions continued at most works ir. the west of Scotland.    The &quot;bulk of business was on home account, coming from a wide range of consuming industries, though export business showed signs of expansion in some directions.    The tube trade continued busy.    The position of re-rollers has steadily improved and constructional engineers are better placed.    The restricted outlet for steel in the &apos;shipyards is, however, disappointing.Worth East Coast.    The position was satisfactory during June and at the end of the month all works had a good reserve of orders.    The semi-finished departments have particularly benefited from the new cartel arrangements.    Constructional engineers were well employed.,  although rolling mills were less active.    The overseas market in general still left much to be desired.Sheffield^    A high level of activity was maintained by most sections of the trade.    Special steel requirements were good and there was a considerable demand for aircraft and motor car steels.    The output of stainless steel increased. Export trade was a little better, but was    hampered by exchange-difficulties .South. Wales.    Conditions were somewhat more favourable than in May and the outlook is promising.    The  demand in the tinplate trade improved somewhat.    Constructional and general engineers were well employed, while ship-repairers were also busy.ENGINEERING.    Following on the slight recession at the end of 1934 engineering as a whole began to show a steady-improvement in 1935 which has been well maintained.    The volume of new business booked is very satisfactory and there has been a marked reduction of unemployment.    Exports of machinery in the first six months of 1935 showed a considerable improvement over a year ago and in particular there was a steady expansion in the exports of internal combustion engines.    A larger
proportion of exports &quot;both by value and by tons, went to Empire countries as compared with 1934 and 1933,    Among foreign, countries the Russian trade shows some recovery.    On the other hand, imports also show a considerable increase in value.    It should be noted that the import value per ton is greatly in excess of the corresponding figure for exports.MO TO R INDUS TRY.    The number of motor cars newly registered in May was 32,284 or 2,999 more than a year ago;  the increase comprised 2,739 private cars and 260 other vehicles.    In the home market manufacturers are somewhat disturbed by the increasing competition from high powered cars imported from North America.    In Empire markets,  tariff questions in Australia and New Zealand still remain unsettled,  though there is some hope that an agreed policy as to assembly in New Zealand may be reached;    In foreign markets, trade with Poland continues to improve as a result of the recent Trade Agreement.LIGHT METAL INDUSTRIES.    Trade in non-ferrous metals has been rather less active,  the slump in copper being partly responsible.    There has been a steady flow of orders both on home and export account in cutlery,  silverware and electro plate, though trade remains rather patchy.    Active conditions prevail in the various sections of the tool trade,  in press work,  in the lock and allied trades and in the foundry industry. The enamelled hollow-ware and metal smallwares trades are fairly satisfactory.    Architectural metalwork still remains very poor,  though there is some slight evidence of improvement.ELEOTRIOAL INDUSTRY.  In general the activity in the industry recorded in May was continued in June.    The demand for installation material and light apparatus is expanding and the demand for plant from the industrial works is still maintained. Exports show a tendency to increase especially to British countries.    The consumption of electricity during May was 1,326 in. units as compared with 1,125 m. units in May last year, an increase of 17.9 per cent.-b-
156LEATHER.    The world&apos;s hide markets  in June more or less maintained a firm front.    Salted South American frigorific hides and North American packer hides declined in the middle of the month hut subsequently recovered.    Trade with European countries    is still difficult in the face of export prohibitions.Reports from tanners indicate that the demand for leather has slackened in recent weeks,  and most sections of the leather industry were less active in June.    In boot leather,   the demand for sole leather fell away though the decline was not so marked in the case of upper leather.    In upholstery leather business was steady, but was variable in fancy leathers.    Export trade has been steady, but there is some danger that owing to anticipated developments in the Irish Free State part at any rate of that very good market may be lost.COTTON.    There was an appreciable decline  in production and employment during June as compared with May.    Average weekly deliveries of raw cotton to spinners    fell to 23.52 m.  lbs.  as against 24.82 m. lbs.  in May and were  the lowest this year. All the principal classes of- cotton, except Indian, were affected by the decline.    Raw cotton prices were fairly steady.Effective demand for yarn was on a small scale and, except possibly  in certain Egyptian yarns,  spinners&apos; margins probably showed further shrinkage.    Plans to set up an enforceable agreement regarding selling prices in the  ring spinning section are progressing.    A similar project amongst spinners of Egyptian type yarns failed, however, to obtain sufficient support and efforts are now being made to devise a scheme involving control of production instead of prices.Total exports of cotton yarns and manufactures during the month were valued at  4.56 m.  against  4.97 m.  in May and  4.74 nv.  in June last year.    Shipments of grey yarn showed some improvement over May, but those of other yarns declined.    The principal  increases were to Norway and Germany but there were substantial declines in exports to India, Australia,  Roumania,
157Exports of cotton piece goods during the month were 138,3 m.  sq. yds against 158.2 iiu  sq. yds in May and 14808 m. sq. yds in June last year.    Shipments during June of every class were lower than in May,  the decline &quot;being most marked in bleached goods.    As compared with June last year the  only class to show   any increase was coloured goods.    Exports of piece goods to India showed a considerable decline as compared with May and there was also some decline in the trade with New Zealand,  the British West Indies, Canada and the Irish Free State.    There were, however, larger shipments to British West Africa   and British Guiana.    In Europe,    the only market with which there was any considerable increase in trade was Norway. Among African markets,  exports to Morocco improved, but shipments to Egypt, French West and Equatorial Africa and the Belgian Congo were  smaller.    In the Far East,  there was some expansion in exports to China.    In Central and South America,  there was a decline in trade with Uruguay and a heavy drop in exports to Colombia, but shipments to Argentina increased.WOOL.    There was no material change  in the condition of the industry during June as regards general activity.    In the export trade there was an increase in shipments of tops and tissues as compared with the previous month, but exports of yarns decreased.    The upward tendency of raw wool   prices continued.    Reports indicate that new orders,  both on home and export account,  are scarce and there is a tendency for customers to buy only for immediate requirements and to  allow the shortest possible time for delivery..SILK AND ARTIFICIAL SILK.    Owing to the unseasonable weather the demand for yarns by the weaving and knitting trades has not been very brisk.    Exports of yarns during June showed little change as compared, with last year, but for the first six months are well in advance of those for the same
158period of 19-34.    The  improvement  in weather conditions took place too late for the manufacturers of piece goods to reap any material advantage.    There has been a slight increase  in exports to various Empire markets, hut this is understood to consist largely of goods left in the hands of manufacturers and merchants owing to the had weather which have been sold at a loss to the producer.There has been little change during the month in the price of raw silk.    The silk spinning industry is fully occupied with the production of silk yarns for the hosiery trade, but it is stated that the cheap  silk goods produced in this country as well as the better class rayon fabrics are affected by Japanese imports.CHEMICALS. Alkali deliveries in the home market though falling away from the high level of recent months were still satisfactory.    Sales of chlorine products to the home trade showed a slight decrease.    The home demand for dyestuffs improved and more than compensated for a slight fall in export sales. Creosote oil and refined coal tar continued in good demand;  trade in other coal tar products was quiet.    Business in wood distillation products has-been steady.PAPER.    The improved demand for paper and boards was well maintained in June and generally speaking the production of British mills was at a  satisfactory level.    Strong competition continues, however,   to be felt from overseas suppliers.    Exports for the first six months of 1935 show a slight improvement as compared with the same period of 1934,  due mainly to a partial recovery of the export trade  in newsprint to Australia.RETAIL TRADE.  The money value of retail sales  for May was 2.2f greater than in May, 1934.    The increase is small as compared with the April increase of 10.3??&apos; but the latter can be partly attributed to the Easter buying and to buying in preparation for the Jubilee celebrations.    The principal increases were in fancy-goods (7.0%&apos;) and furniture  (3-by),  while there were declines in
159the case of piece- goods (5.4$), women&apos;s wear (4.6%),  men&apos;s and hoys&apos; wear (6.2$) and hoots and shoes (6*4$)A    In the food departments the largest increases were in London (Surburban) and London (Central and West End), while in non-food departments there were increases in Scotland and London  (Central and West End).    Preliminary figures for June suggest that the final returns will show a satisfactory improvement as compared with June,  1954.CO-OPERATIVE TRADE.    The Co-operative Wholesale Society&apos;s sales for the four weeks ended 8th June,  1935,  showed an increase of 18.3;? over a year ago.    The weighted average of the wholesale prices of seven of the principal commodities showed an increase of 5.8$ as compared with last year and the weighted average of the retail prices of the same commodities has increased by 2.93$.POTTERY.    In general the activity noted in May continued during June.    The demand for general earthenware, glazed wall and hearth tiles,  and sanitary ware was satisfactory and prospects are good.    The demand for china ware declined somewhat, while there was a seasonal lull in orders for electrical ware.CANADIAN TRADE.    Economic conditions in Canada continued to show a marked improvement in May,  the  index of the physical volume of business reaching the highest point since the end of 1930.    Exports of copper and zinc increased, while imports of bauxite were high.    The food industries were more active,  gains being shown in sugar,  flour milling and in exports of cheese and canned salmon.    Newsprint production and exports of wood pulp and of planks and boards showed substantial gains.    The operations of the primary iron and steel industry were practically, maintained, but motor car production showed some decline.AUSTRALIAN TRADE.     2,823,000 bales of wool have been received into  store from July 1st,  1934,  to the end of May as compared with 2,665,000 a year ago-    Of these 2,639,000 have been sold for export, as against 2,488,000 last    season.    Wheat and
flour shipments for the period 1st December to the end of May are equivalent to 65.7 m. bushels of wheat as against 51*4 m. for the same period last year.    Exports of butter for the season now amount to 117,000 tons as against 107,000 tons last year.    Total imports of merchandise in May were valued at  7,9 m.  (Australian currency) as against  6.5 nu a year   ago.SOUTH AFRICAN TRADE.    In general business expansion continues, although at a somewhat slower rate.    Some anxiety remains, however, about the farming and rural populations after the devastation caused by the recent depression and the recurring droughts.    Total exports in April were  9,65 m. as against 7.215 m. a year earlier,  increased exports of gold accounting for a large proportion of the difference;   imports were  6.10 m. as against  4.89 m.  in April, 1934.    The output of gold continues to be well maintained, while the diamond market has been fairly steady.    Crops are regarded as fairly favourable, though the yields of certain products are expected to be lower than those of last year.    Exports of deciduous fruits for the past season were 3,268,000 cases as against 3,593,000 cases last year.SOUTH AMERICAN TRADE.    Economic conditions are on the whole still improving,  though the coffee producing countries are feeling the effects of low prices and of the restrictions on imports enforced abroad, especially in Germany.Exports from Argentina show an increase of 15.3$ by value for the  first five months of 1935 as compared with the sameperiod of 1934 and imports an increase of 12,0%.    Theproportion of British goods to total imports was slightly lowerat 22.0% as compared with a year ago.    There is a notabledecline  in imports from Italy and Germany.    Exports of wheatduring the period January - May amounted to 2.2 m.  tons asagainst 1.95 m.  tons last year and of maize to 2.29 m.  tons ascompared with 2.09 m.  tons in January - May,  1934.    The woolmarket has also shown a better tone.    There has been nochange of importance in the exchange situation.-10-
\  16 rBrazil.    For the first quarter of the year exports showed an increase of 0*&amp;% and imports of 48 v 9$ in value as compared with a year ago.    Stocks of imported goods continue below requirements, largely owing to the uncertainties of the exchange situation.    Coffee exports during May and June show some improvement.    There is,  however, a substantial surplus which the trade  itself is apparently being left to take can-; of, though, the Government have  stated they will take whatever measures may be necessary to maintain &quot;statistical equilibrium&quot;. The exchange position appears to be deteriorating and doubts have arisen whether Brazil will be able to maintain the exchange freedom granted last February.Chile. . Exports from Chile  in the period January - April show an increase of 2,9?2 and imports,  including gold,  an increase of 66 .ly-. by value over a year ago.    The Government intend to develop the  system of compensation treaties which are based largely on exports of nitrates.Peru.  Exports in the first quarter of 1935 show a decrease of 5.6% and imports an increase of 13.9% by value as compared with the same period of 1934.    The Government is interesting itself in increasing the home production of wheat.Uruguay.    The February returns of trade show a decrease of 35$ in imports as a result of the attempts to obtain a close bilateral balancing of international payments.    Efforts are being made to complete trade treaties with Spain and Peru,Colombia.      With the termination of the  1908 Treaty between Colombia and Japan imports of Japanese goods during the six months ending 31st October next are to be restricted to one-sixth of the total value imported in 1934.IQFQIQMVL&apos; The commercial position is unsettled. The cotton crop is late and other crops generally are poor.

</content>
</cab>
