<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/256/0 images: 283-293</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY:&apos;S GOVERNMENT).C RET.&apos;p^R  158(55).COPY NO.CABINET.UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE (NORTHERN IRELAND) AGREEMENT. Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.When the Government of Northern Ireland, was established in 1922,  it was anticipated that Northern Ireland would, be able to maintain the same standard of social services as Great Britain and to make a substantial contribution to Imperial expenditure.      One of the difficulties in Northern Ireland&apos;s financial position has always been that its two most important industries,  linen and   shipbuilding,  have been in a depressed condition since the European war and accordingly the burden of expenditure on unemployment in Northern Ireland has been disproportionately heavy.    This question was considered by the Cabinet in 1925.    Mr. Winston Churchill who was then Chancellor of the Exchequer was in favour of the amalgamation of the unemployment funds of Great Britain and Northern Ireland.   . The Cabinet, however, were unwilling to adopt this solution and the matter was dealt with by an agreement between the Treasury and the Northern Ireland Ministry of Finance, which was to operate from the 1st October 1925, until the 31st March,  1930.    Under this agreement the Exchequer of the United Kingdom paid to the Exchequer of Northern Ireland 75 per cent,   of the amount required to equalise per head of the population of the respective countries the payments from the  two Exchequers into  their respective unemployment funds.      The practical effect of this agreement was that the British Treasury contributed about two-thirds,  and the Northern Ireland Treasury contributed about one-third;.  to special payments which kept the Northern
Ireland unemployment find in parity with the British Unemployment fund as from October,  1925B      The agreement was confirmed hy legislation in hoth countries (C0P&amp;47 (26)),In December, 1928, a new agreement was made under which the provisions of the earlier agreement were continued permanently,,      This also was confirmed by legislation in both Parliaments (CP,  395 (28)).Mr, Pollock, the   Minister of Finance in Northern Ireland, before introducing his Budget in May last, approached the Treasury with a view to the conclusion of a new agreements      His proposals were:-(i)      that    the new agreement should cover Unemployment Assistance   as well as Unemployment Insurance; (ii)      that the expenditure of the two Exchequers onunemployment to be equalised should in future be the expenditure per head of the insured population instead of the expenditure per head of the total population;(iii)      that while the British Exchequer should continueto contribute 75 per cent,  of the excess expenditure of Northern Ireland,  if the unemployment percentage in Northern Ireland remained as high as 20 per cent., the contribution by the British Exchequer should be reduced by one-twelfth for each complete 1 per cent, by which the unemployment figure of Northern Ireland falls below 20 per cent,, so that if the unemployment percentage  in Northern Ireland falls to 8 per cent, no contribution by the British Exchequer will be made;(iv)      that if the expenditure on unemployment of theNorthern Ireland Exchequer should be less than the amount proportionate to such expenditure by the British Exchequer per head of insured population,
the difference will &quot;be paid over by the Northern Ireland Exchequer to the British Exchequer,, The total population of Northern Ireland is 2,7^ of the total population of Great Britain, while the insured population of Northern Ireland is 2.1$ of the insured population of Great Britain^      Therefore the main effect of these proposals was that Northern Ireland would receive a contribution from us if the Northern Ireland Exchequer spends more than  21,000 for each  1 million spent by the British Exchequer, whereas previously Northern Ireland did not receive a contribution until she had spent more than  27,000 for each  1 million of our expenditure.      The effect in the  current year is estimated to be that our contribution is increased by  375,000oAfter careful consideration I came to the conclusion that I should be  justified in authorising the Treasury to negotiate a nev/ agreement on the lines proposed by Mr,  Pollock, and I was able so to inform him before the introduction of his Budget.      The inclusion of Unemployment Assistance was obviously logical and unobjectionable.      The substitution of the insured populations; instead of the total populations as the basis of comparison seems on the whole a fairer way of carrying out the intention of the original agreement, which was to mitigate the higher level of unemployment among the industrial population of Northern Ireland.      The new basis means that the contribution of the British Exchequer is no longer reduced owing to the fact that the number of peasant proprietors and small freeholders is proportionately larger in Northern Ireland than in Great Britain.      But if this fact is taken into account it might well be said that it would be equally fair to take into account the fact that these small freeholders contribute very little in the way of direct taxation.
-  On more general grounds I felt that we are faced with the fact that Northern Ireland,  in vie?/ of the depression in the shipbuilding and linen trades,  is not really able to make both ends meet and to make even the most modest contribution to Imperial expenditure without some further assistance from us, and that a revision of the Unemployment Insurance agreement which could be justified on its merits would be far preferable to a special subsidy requiring a Vote by Parliament which was the only alternative. A special subsidy would of course be particularly undesirable at the present time in view of our relations with the Irish Free State.The new agreement has now been signed and requires to be confirmed by legislation in both countries.      It seems probable  that the necessary Parliamentary time can be found immediately after Parliament reassembles in the autumn.      For this purpose, however,  it is necessary that the Financial Resolution upon which the Bill has to be founded should be placed upon the Paper before the House rises.      I would therefore ask the Cabinet to authorise the Treasury to hand in the attached Resolution on Wednesday night (31st July), and to introduce a Bill on the lines of the attached preliminary draft as soon as opportunity offers in the autumn.(Intld,)      N.   CoTREASURY CHAMBERS, 29th July,  1935o
draft resolution.Mr. Chancellor of the Exchequer, -To move the followingResolution in Committee of the whole House under standing order No,  69 /King &apos; s recommendation to he signif iedy7:-Unemployment (Northern Ireland Agreement) /Money/P -That it is expedient -(a)to confirm and give effect to an Agreement datedtheday of July, nineteenhundred and thirty-five, made between the Treasury and the Ministry of Finance for Northern Ireland with a view to assimilating the burdens on the Exchequer of the United Kingdom and the Exchequer of Northern Ireland in respect of unemployment;(b)    to authorise the payment out of the consolidate fund of any sums payable under the said Agreement from the Exchequer of the United Kingdom;(c)    to repeal the Unemployment Insurance  (NorthernIreland Agreement) Act, 1926,  and the Unemploy-ment Insurance  (Northern Ireland Agreement) Act, 1929.
[25 &amp; 26 Geo. 5.] Unemployment[Northern Ireland Agreement).DRAFTOIF AB   I   L   LTOConfirm and give effect to an Agreement made A.D. 1935. between the Treasury  and   the   Ministry of     &quot; Finance for Northern Ireland with a view to assimilating the burdens on the Exchequer of the United Kingdom and the Exchequer of Northern Ireland in respect of unemployment.WHEREAS provision was made by the Unemploy- 16 &amp; 17 ment Insurance (Northern Ireland Agreement) ^eo- 5- c- 4-Act, 1926, for confirming and giving effect to an agree-ment made between the Treasury and the Ministry of 5 Finance for Northern Ireland with a view to assimilating the burdens on the Exchequer of the United Kingdom and the Exchequer of Northern Ireland in respect of unemployment insurance :And whereas provision was made by the Unemploy- 19 &amp; 20 10 ment Insurance (Northern Ireland Agreement) Act, 1929, Geo. 5. c. 18. for confirming and giving effect to an agreement made between the Treasury and the Ministry of Finance for Northern  Ireland for  continuing the  first-mentioned agreement:15 And whereas it has been agreed between the Treasury and the Ministry of Finance for Northern Ireland that the said two agreements should be superseded, as from the first day of April, nineteen hundred and thirty-five, by the agreement set forth in the Schedule to this Act.20 (in this Act referred to as &quot; the scheduled agreement &quot;) made between them with a view to assimilating the184-3 A
2 Unemployment [25 &amp; 26 Geo. 5.](Northern Ireland Agreement).A.T). 1935. burdens on the Exchequer of the United Kingdom and the Exchequer of Northern Ireland in respect of un-employment :And whereas it is expedient to confirm and give effect to the scheduled agreement, to provide for the 5 payment of such sums as may be payable out of the Exchequer  of the United Kingdom thereunder, and to repeal the said Acts :Be it therefore enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the 10 Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows : 1. (1) The scheduled agreement is hereby con-firmed and shall have effect as if enacted in this Act.     15(2) Any sums payable under the scheduled agree-ment from the Exchequer of the United Kingdom to the Exchequer of Northern Ireland shall be charged on and paid out of the Consolidated Fund of the United Kingdom or the growing produce thereof. 202. (1). This Act may be cited as the Unemployment (Northern Ireland Agreement) Act, 1935. meni;, repeal        ^ qijie Unemployment Insurance (Northern Ireland duration.     Agreement) Act, 1926, and the Unemployment Insurance(Northern Ireland Agreement) Act, 1929, are hereby 25 repealed.(3) This Act shall not come into operation -unless and until His Majesty by Order in Council declares that a corresponding Act has been passed by the Parliament of Northern Ireland, and shall cease to be in force if and 30 when His Majesty by Order in Council declares that the corresponding Act of the Parliament of Northern Ireland has ceased to be in force.Confirma-tion of scheduled agreement.Short title, commence-
[25 &amp; 26 Geo. 5.] Unemployment(Northern Ireland Agreement.)SCHEDULE. a.d.1935.Agreement made between the Treasury and the Ministry of Finance for Northern Ireland, with a view to assimilating the burdens on the 5 Exchequer of the United Kingdom and the Exchequer of Northern Ireland in respect of unemployment.The Commissioners of His Majesty&apos;s Treasury and . the Ministry of Finance for Northern Ireland, with a view to assimi-10 lating the burdens on the Exchequer of the United Kingdom and the Exchequer of Northern Ireland in respect of unemployment, have entered into the following Agreement, which supersedes as from the 1st day of April, 1935, the Agreements dated the 10th February, 1926, and 14th December, 1928.15 1. At the date when this Agreement comes into force and thereafter triennially the Government Actuary shall estimate on the basis of figures supplied by the Departments concerned (a) the total number of the persons insured under the Acts ofthe Parliament of the United Kingdom and of the Parlia-20 ment of Northern Ireland relating to UnemploymentInsurance, excluding persons insured under any special scheme made thereunder, and[b) the total number of the persons insured under theActs  of the said Parliaments relating to Widows&apos;, 25 Orphans&apos; and Old Age Contributory Pensions, excludingpersons insured as voluntary contributors and persons who have attained the age of 65,and shall certify in either case the proportion of the number so  estimated which represents the number of persons insured 30 under the Acts of the Parliament of Northern Ireland.The proportions so certified are hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Unemployment Insurance Proportion &quot;&apos;and &quot;the Unem-ployment Assistance Proportion &quot; respectively and in respect of any year shall be deemed to be those certified in the triennial 35 certificates current in that year.2. There shall be ascertained the payment (if any) necessary to be made as at the end of each financial year as between the Exchequer of Northern Ireland and the Unemployment Fund of Northern Ireland in order to bring the current account of that 40 Fund created by the Unemployment Insurance (Agreement)184 A 2
Unemployment [25 &amp; 26 Geo. 5.] (Northern Ireland Agreement).A.D. 1935.  Act (Northern Ireland), 1926, into parity with the Unemploy--       ment Fund of Great Britain : and for this purpose parity shallbe deemed to exist between the said current account and the Unemployment Fund of Great Britain when the balance of the current account of the Northern Ireland Fund bears to the sum 5 of the balances of the said current account and the said Unemployment Fund of Great Britain the proportion certified under Article 1 hereof as the Unemployment Insurance proportion.3. The Government. of Northern Ireland will cause to be 10 repaid out of the Unemployment Fund of Northern Ireland at the rate of  40,000 per annum the sum of  2,400,000 being the existing balance of the suspense account of that Fund created under Section 4 of the Unemployment Insurance (Agreement) Act (Northern Ireland), 1926, and the said  40,000 per annum together 15 with.interest on the balance of the suspense account for the time being outstanding shall be included as expenditure from the current account of the Northern Ireland Unemployment Fund for the purpose of calculating the balance of the current account of that Fund under the preceding Article. 204. (1) If in respect of any financial year the payments made by the Exchequer of Northern Ireland to the Unemployment Fund and&quot; Unemployment Assistance Fund of Northern Ireland (after taking into account any payment made for the purpose referred to in Article 2 hereof) shall together exceed the sum of  25(a) the Unemployment Insurance proportion of the pay-ments (after taking into account any payment as afore-said) made by the Exchequers of the United Kingdom and Northern Ireland to the Unemployment Funds of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, and 30(b) the Unemployment Assistance proportion of the pay-ments so made to the Unemployment Assistance Funds of Great Britain and Northern Ireland,the   Exchequer,   of   the   United   Kingdom   shall   contribute to  the  Exchequer  of   Northern   Ireland   three-quarters  of 35 the excess :Provided that if, according to a Certificate to be given at the end of each financial year by the Government Actuary, the number (based upon the average of the monthly returns) of unemployed persons in Northern Ireland between the ages of 16 40 and 64 (both inclusive) in that year is less than twenty per cent, of the estimated number of persons insured under the Widows&apos;, Orphans&apos; and Old Age Contributory Pensions Acts (Northern Ireland) (excluding the classes of persons referred to in Article 1 (b)), the contribution under this Article in respect 45 of  that   year  shall   be   reduced   by   one-twelfth   part   for .....
[25 &amp; 26 Geo. 5.] Unemployment(Northern Ireland Agreement).each complete one per cent, by which the said percentage is less A.D. 1936. than twenty. - (2) For the purpose of this Article a grant paid to a local authority under the Unemployment Assistance (Temporary 5 Provisions) (No. 2) Act 1935 or under any corresponding Act of the Parliament of Northern Ireland shall he deemed to be a payment to the Unemployment Assistance Fund of Great Britain or Northern Ireland as the case may be.5. If in respect of any financial year the payments by the 10 Exchequer of Northern Ireland referred to in the last preceding Article are less than the sum therein stated, the difference between the said payments and the said sum shall be paid by that Exchequer to the Exchequer of the United Kingdom.6. Payments on account of such contributions as may 15 ultimately be found to,be due under Article 4 or Article 5 hereof from one Exchequer to the other may be made of such amounts and at such times as the Joint Exchequer Board may determine to be proper, and for this purpose the Board may make pro-visional estimates of the percentage referred to in the proviso to 20 Article 4 (1) hereof.7. If at any time the classes of persons insured or of persons entitled to apply for an unemployment allowance the rates of contribution the rates or conditions of benefit or the regulations under which allowances are paid   or the general method of25 charging administrative expenses or the method of financing the Unemployment or Unemployment Assistance Funds differ in Great Britain and Northern Ireland there shall be made such adjustment, if any, in the amounts of the contributions from one Exchequer to the other as the Joint Exchequer Board, after30 consulting the Government Actuary, may consider just.8. Any question arising under this Agreement whether as to the amount of any payment for the purpose referred to in Article 2 hereof or of any contribution from one Exchequer to the other under Articles 4 and 5 hereof or otherwise shall be determined by 35 the Joint Exchequer Board, whose decision shall be final.9. This Agreement shall not come into operation until confirmed by Acts of the Parliaments of the United Kingdom and Northern Ireland respectively but upon being so confirmed shall apply as from the 1st day of April, nineteen hundred and 40 thirty-five.(Signed)N. CHAMBERLAIN.(Signed)JAMES BLINDELL.(Signed)H. M. POLLOCK.
Unemployment(Northern Ireland Agreement).DRAFTOF ABILLTo confirm and give effect to an Agreement made between the Treasury and the Ministry of Finance for Northern Ireland with a view to assimilating the burdens on the Exchequer of the United Kingdom and the Exchequer of Northern Ireland in respect of unemploy-ment.XL VI. (B.)   (3.)ml July 1935.184-3

</content>
</cab>
