<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/33/36 images: 238-245</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
wm. (my86th Conshasions.Copy Mos,TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special oare may be taken toiy of thiiWAR CAMKfET. 86 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, March 1, 1943, at 5-30 p.m.Present&apos;:&apos;The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in.the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden,, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right HoO. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.;       The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,.     M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. S. M. Bruce, Repre-sentative of the Government of theCommonwealth of Australia (items-7).The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer. .The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma(Items 1-7).The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P, Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Crd?ps,K.C; M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. BiirNDAN BrackedMlP., Minister of Information.[25111]Sir Ramaswami Mudaliar, Represen-tative of India (Items 1-7).The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt, M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. R. S. Hudson, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries (Item 5).The Right Hon. James Stuart^ M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Item 8)...   &apos; &apos;&apos;&apos; b
^dmiral1 of: the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea fed and Chief, ofNaval Staff (ItemsV-7).General Sir Alan Brooke, Chief of theMper^ General Staff (Items 1-7).Air Chief Marshal Sir&apos; Charles F. A.PpRXAL,  Chief of the  Air  Staff&quot;Xltms 1-7)V-  sir Orme Sargent, Deputy Under-Secretary of State; Foreign Office(Items 1-7).Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Lieutenant-General Sir Hastings IsmaY. . jMr. Norman Brook.Mr. L. F, Burgis.minute no.a466SContents.Subject.Naval, Military and Air operations air Operations.      &apos;Home Theatre.Mediterranean.naval Operations:Russian Convoy.,Military Operations:Tunisia.Russia.Supplies to Bussia   .......;&quot;Air Protection of Convoys..Prisoners of War     ....      ....      .....Prisoners of War     ....      ....      ....      ....Incident at Featherston Camp, New Zealand.Armoured Formations       ........Proposed use of Yorkshire Wolds as Training Area.Occupied Enemy TerritoryBritish Military Administration.France ....      ....  ., ....     .....The French Fleet at Alexandria.Parliament    ....      .... ....      ....Air Transport.Page141141142142143143143143
1-. i Tb:e Chiefs of Staff reported the principal events &quot;of thepast week.Bomber Command had attacked WilhelmshaVen, Nuremburg,Cologne and targets in the Ruhr.- On the previous night a mostsuecessfid attack had been made on St. Nazaire, when 1,100 tons&quot; of bombs had been dropped. We had lost 28 bombers in the Week.^^feFebruary had been the best month BomberiCommand &quot;had yet had. 10^737 tons of bombs had been dropped ancl 1,100 mines laidfor a relatively low rate of losses: vThe War Cabinet^! .;\v; V 5Invited the Chief of the Air Staff to convey their congratulate-latiohs to&quot;B6mber Command on this notable achievement.. Coastal Command had made two promising, and one possible,attacks On U-boats. .United States aircraft had dropped 250 tons of bombs on Brestand Wilhelmshaven.In the&apos;Mediterranean pur aircraft had attacked 15 merchant ships, 7 smaller ships, 1 cruiser and a destroyer. Enemy losses inthis area had been 57 aircraft destroyed, 19 probably destroyed and40 damaged. Our losses had been 50 destroyed and 18 damaged.These figures should be accepted with some reserve owing to therecent reorganisation of the Air Commands.Shipping losses for the previous week, including belated reports,amounted to 119,000 tons. The shipping losses for Februaryamounted to 285,000 tons for certain, but might be increased to355,000 tons. It was estimated, that 16 or 17 U-boats had been sunkduring the month.H.M.S. Sitssea had sunk an 8,000-ton enemy tanker off cape finisterre after having been directed to the spot by a United StatesLiberator.A convoy had arrived without loss at a North Russian port after having been attacked by aircraft.   &apos;Our counter-attacks had practically restored the position in central Tunisia. , Heavy casualties had been inflicted on theGermans during their withdrawal and a number of prisoners taken.A new German attack further north in the area of Goubellat had made some initial penetration, but the situation had now been pratically restored. Serious casualties had been inflicted and some800-900 prisoners taken. The situation on this front was distinctlymore favourable than a week ago. The Eighth Army was closing upto the Mareth Line. &apos;Russian progress had been slower. Owing to the thaw, Russianattacks south-west of Moscow had been hampered. Further souththe Germans had gained ground in the area Krasnograd-Losovava-Isyum. In the Taganrog area fighting continued, but the russians had made ho progress. The Russians had made some progress on thesouth of the Taman bridgehead.The War Cabinet- &quot;, A   -Took note of these statements.-^ft: (48) :33rdConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.Hom*e Theatre.Mediterranean.naval operations.Russian Convoy.MilitaryOperations.&apos; Tunisia.Russia.StepplieBto 2.   The Secretary of State, for Foreign A ffaifs said that, inBiMSfJa. - accordance with the decision reached by the War Cabinet on the^Protection 25th February, he had made strong representations to the^^gof Convovs Ambassador-regarding the difficulties whichtheRussmri au^onties(Previous- &apos;       W^reference: V.-J^is;:m^^^QB^^^ His Majesty s AmbassadorW M (43) 95th in Moscow bid also been instructed to make similar representationsCollusions, to the Soviet Government, Up to date there had been no responseMinute 2/*       tothese r^reseni^bh^.
me: war uaometTook note of these statements.(Previous.      : 3.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs referred to theterms of the communication delivered to the German government by the Protecting Power about&apos; the shackling -.bf prisoners&apos;:off -war.ThePrptecting^Power ha^w\M^48) 83rd   of it should be transmitted orally - rather than in writing.   TheConclusions,      discrepancies tp which the attention of the War Cabinet had beenMinuteS.) r     drawn were due to the exercise of this discretion; and the wholesubstance of the communication had beerimade, either orally or inwriting, to the German Government.y The War Cabinet-  &apos;took note of these statements.Prisoners ofySte.&apos; -incident at?eatherstonCamp,&quot;New Zealand.4. Attention was drawn to the telegrams exchanged with theNew Zealand Government about the mutiny at a Japanese&apos; prisonersof war camp in New Zealand, which had. resulted in about40; Japanese prisoners of war being killed and 50 wounded. A full,statement on the matter had been made by the New Zealand PrimeMinister, but had-so far been released for publication in NewZealand only. . His Majesty&apos;s Minister- at Berne had been asked to request the Swiss Government (as the Protecting Power) and theInternational Red Cross Committee not to pass on immediately tothe Japanese Government any reports received, but to hold them upuntil the results of the proceedings of the Court of Enquiry, whichhad immediately been instituted in New Zealand, were also available.The War Cabinet discussed the risk of a leakage to Japan ofinformation about the mutiny before the report of the Court ofEnquiry was available. If this happened, it might provoke a violentreaction on the Japanese Government, with unfortunate conserquences on pur prisoners in their hands.     *- The War Cabinet decided&apos;on the following action : (1) The Foreign Office should telegraph to His Majesty&apos;minister at Berne, instructing him to inform the swiss government and the International Red Cross Committeethat we wished to cancel our request that the news ofthis affair should be withheld from the Japanese Govern-ment pending-the receipt of the report of the CoUrt of/Enquiry.(2) The Dominions Office should telegraph td the New zealand government (on the lines agreed interdepartmentally),-suggesting that the news Of the incident should now be released to the world, and that this release shouldcomprise Mr. Fraser&apos;s statement, expanded to cover thetwo following points :-(a) That both the representative of the Protecting Powerand the delegate of the International red cross&quot;Committee were fully informed of the incidentimmediately it occurred, arid had already visited.s .&quot;the camp.-&apos; &apos;H:M!   1. -(h) That an&apos; oBfieiai&apos; enquiry- had&apos; been-convened by thecompetent military authority. .
&apos;S^S^--i-&apos;-&apos; &apos; a The War Cabinet had before them Memoranda by theFormations, Seeretary of State for War and the Minister of Agriculture and proposed[use bf Fisheries (W-P- (43) 80 and 77) regarding a proposal for takingYorkshire Wolds over, under the Defence^Regiilationsi 100,000 acres of the Yorkshirete Training       Wolds for use as a training area for armoured formations.r?B&apos;   - . The Secretary of State for War said that he fully realised theserious effect which this would have on agricultural production, buthe had been unable to find any alternative which would meet theArmy&apos;s needs. He suggested that the issues raised by the two memoranda should be submitted to arbitration by the lord president of the Council.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries said that he also would be willing -to accept the Lord Presidents decision in thismatter.The War Cabinet-Invited the Lord President of the Council to consider the issues raised in these Memoranda and to decide whetherthis area should be taken over by the War Office as a training area for armoured formations, or whether alter-native means could be found of satisfying the essential needs of the Army with less damage to agricultural production.OccupiedEnemyTerritory.BritishMilitaryAdministration.6, The War Cabinet took note of a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for War (W.P. (43) 84) giving an account of themilitary administration of enemy territories at present occupied by our Forces. *&apos;France.The french fleet at alexandria.(previous reference erence:W.M. (43) 22ndConclusions.)7. The War Cabinet were informed that it had been suggestedby the Minister of State (telegram No. 458) that the further negotia-tions with Admiral Godfrey about the position of the French fleet at Alexandria should be handled primarily by the French authoritiesin North Africa.It was pointed out that, before this could be done, various questions (e.g., the financial arrangements) would have to be con-sidered by the competent authorities in this country.The War Cabinet-Agreed that the issues involved should be examined by theForeign Office and the Admiralty, and that the matter should be considered at a later meeting of the War Cabinet.Parliament. 8.   The War Cabinet were informed that when the AirAir Transport; Estimates were discussed in the House of Commons on Tuesday, the9th March, there Would be an amendment by the Labour Party aboutAir Transport. There would also be a debate in the House of lords on Wednesday, the 10th March, On a Motion by Lord Londonderry.In view of the widespread interest which was being shown in bothHouses, early consideration should be given to the form of theGovernment statement to be made on this point.The War Cabinet decided as follows : (1) The Secretary of State for Air and the Minister without portfolio were asked to draft, in consultation with theMinister of Production and the Minister of aircraft production, a considered statement to be made by theGovernment Spokesman.
; draft might art In , ^3 GovermaenS\: &apos;  1 ,at,a]0U. - . &apos; ^____     .     ( KJpi i    enable    . i .;        J      ibhs .with Dominion G   &apos;  1&apos; 1 &apos;    1 meats-&apos;ok tii;, .,  zs of % iVoj .l 9   j,in regard to the design of the types of aircraft suitable(3) emoluments;!elr4$t; stoisiflLjit sliotfcl is cuhiaitisd eomaiclevatio-a, :J^Vfey\file;%ar ^ to^be^lieMlater-da^ai-%eek3 tfbto j ifeinsibn   ofild bs token as ,0 who ohoukl.&apos; / -   be^he/GoveraiiBehi^ofe^ \&apos; - Opens of the War Cabinet, S.W;. t,liillllllilii



</content>
</cab>
