<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/26/0 images: 25-26</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
P. fx^s -----AA, ASL^ ^\ \ tiUS Britann2006 0  ~    ;  ... .n**+ ,  rty ofgovernment) .SEC RET.prom:- GeneraT&quot;Barter, RussIa. To:-     C.I.G.S., War Office.9.9,17. ... 10.50 p.m.Clear the line.1238.   I was summoned this &apos;-.-afternoon tf G.H.Q. with the French and Italian representatives. .&apos;.We&apos;were received by the G.G.S., wh3 asked us  to keep his name secret.   The head of the diplomatic department was also present.   Resume of the note-which was communicated to us is as follows&quot;It has . been shown in the last few. months that .the Committee of Workmen and Soldiers is an insurmountable obstacle to the reconstitute ion of the Army, which in the course of two or three months will b* so dangerously .disorganised .as. to force: Russia to stop the; war, and will produce disastrous&apos;consequences in the interior.&apos;- of the country.In&apos;.view - of the situation Korniloff has continually and insistently represented to the Government the. absolute necessity of a strong government.which alone could re-establish order, save Russia, and assure success and fidelity to the Alliance.The Minister, President, and Minister of War. following upon negotiations which they themselves had recently initiated, agreed to Korni lo f f1 s pro gramme, and pro mi s e d to visit S TAVKA. to cone e rt : with him,&quot;-- ;.;;&gt;. -:V.~\ - &apos;&apos;&apos;;..     .-  ;They first announced their intention of coming today, September 9th.but after a conversation on the direct line with Korniloff. thty decided, to defer their arrival till tomorrow, September 10thj 0.in 0 , on the strength of this information, ?invited Rodzianka and several other leaders to come to STAVKA for the purpose of a combined   conference, having as its object the establishment of a strong national government, representative of the best elements of the country.    This morning, September 9th, Korniloff received an urgent telegi*hm telling him to go to Petrograd, after remitting the supreme command to General Lukcmski, C.G.S.   Latter-replied that in view of previous consent of the Minister, President*and the gravity Df the situation, military dispositions had been made and orders given which were called for by the gravity of the situation, and that these were in process of execution, and could net be countermanded.   He could not, in consequent; even for a brief period, assume the responsibility cf replacing Korniloff.Russian Haut Commandement does not consider it is justified.in accepting a responsibility in respect of the catastrophes to which thJ country might be subjected, should, the Provisional Government reverse Its decision to form in conjunction with Korniluff a government of national defence, representing a power strong and willing enough tc restore- order to the Army and country, and fulfil its obligations to the Allies-.Korniloff has given the Government his positive assurance that he ic inspired by no personal ambition, but is only eager to have a Government which is truly representative of the country, in order | to save Russia and her new libertyf&quot; .
The representatives were requested to transmit ?substance of this note to their respective Governments,and ambassadors,and evidently it was most highly desired that we should represent ta our-Governments the urgent necessity of bringing the strongest diplomatic -pressure to bear upon the Russian Government to induce it to accept I Korniloff1 s terms, if only in the interests of the Allies themselves, as the continuation of the war by Russia would otherwise be impossible,.It is expected here that Savonko,the virtual Minister of War, who, as reported, visited Korniloff on September 5th., will endeavour to deny the arrangements then arrived at, on behalf of his Government. .I am assured by the head of the diplomatic department that Kerensky proposed that Korniloff should form a Government, and that he himself would form part of it, or not, as thought best.  Korniloff replied that in his opinion Kerenski&apos;spresence would strengthen the Government, in which wore to be included Rodzianka, and other representative men of worth and patriotism. He also informs me that Korniloff has decided not to go to(Petrograd.Both Kerenski and Korniloff are afraid to place himself in the other&apos;s power.     There are now 4th? (4) divisions of Cossacks within 30 miles of Petrograd, and on these-divisions the course of events largely depends.I am entirely in aocord with my French and Italian colleagues in urging, respGot fully yet strongly, that combined diplomatic pressure of the most energetic nature be brought to bear immediately on the Pro- visional Government, which is showing itself hopelessly weak and vacillating.So long as the extreme left remains powerful, the situation oar-nob possibly improve. The only means of suppressing this party is military power, preferably with a Government which will include Kerenski, and one. or two of his best supporters; the Duma should also be restored to its proper legislative functions. Kerenski clearly is intensely nervous and undecided. The vigorous insistence of the Allies should be sufficient to weigh down the scale in favour of the only course which can yet save the country, but the sands are running out.I am persuaded absolutely that Korniloff is the only horse to back tc win, with Kerenski for a place in his government.The representatives are all asking their governments to repeat the official note to each other, and to ask for absolute secrecy as to sources of information.Later... ... .1 have just been informed on the best authority that Korniloff has refused to give up his post, alleging that the ftomont is too critical for a change. In this he is right. His dismissal at this stage would be a disaster to the common causo.   It however appears that negotiations between Korniloff and the Government arc in progress at the present moment. Kerenski maintains that the envoys did not represent his propositions correctly.I am communicating this message to the Ambassador.   Kindly acknowledge roceipt.

</content>
</cab>
