<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/26/0 images: 154-157</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.it)Intelli&amp;enee   Bureau,Department of Information.B.ll.SPECIAL   MEMORANDUMonTHE   BACT   OP   CORPU   OP.   JULY 20th.(15th September, 1917.)I have had an opportunity of discussing the details of the pact of Corfu with one of the Jugo-Slavs who signed it, and found that he was entirely satisfied both with the courae of the negotiations and with their result.     The discussions between the Juge-Slav Committee and the Serbian government at Corfu lasted for six weeks: they began with the old Coalition Cabinet, were suspended owing to the outbreak of a Cabinet crisis in consequence of the Salonika Conspiracy Trial and. were then resumed with Mr* Pas*ic&apos;s Old Radical government-     During these resumed discussions, however, the three Young Radical ministers who had resigned (MM. Draskovic, Marinkovic and Davidovic) were also present-     The only ministers not present all the time were General Terzic (War) and Mr. Ljuba.J vanovic (interior), the latter himself a Dalmatian Serb and in full sympathy with the movement.     Thus so far as Serbia is concerned the Pact represents the unanimous and considered view of every serious pa-fcty in Serbian politics.     The Jugo-Slav representatives may be fairly regarded as no less representative of the various currents among the Southern Slavs of Austria-Hungary, the Jugo-Slav Committee (among whose members are deputies and other prsmiaent leaders from every Southern Slav province and fraction) having after prolonged discussion in Paris delegated full powers of negotiation to six of its members.     It is important to note that just as the earlier programmes and manifestoes of the Committee
(in May 1915 to the British Parliament and in December 1916 renouncing allegiance to the Habsburgs on the occasion of the Budapest coronation) have never been repudiated or disavowed by any party or individual in the political life af Croatia. 3osnia, Dalmatia, Istria, et&amp;., sc. the Pact of Cwfu, though received with howls of rage in Magyar circles and with alarmed disapproval in Vienna, has never been repudiated by any of the Southern Slavs of Austria-Hungary, while the bold prenouncements of the peasant leader RadicThave received all the prominence possible.In view  f statements made by Mr. Pasic himself in the course of an interview with the Italian Deputy, Signer Bevione (to the effect that he is opposed to an application of the federal principle to the new State), it is interesting to learn that during the Corfu discussiens the Serbian Premier and other ministers accepted as an axiom the need for considerable local autonomies to meet the varying requirements of the various provinces.     They deprecated any extreme form of federalism, but were quite explicit in the assurance that if for instance Croatia or other sections s  the Jugo-Slavs insisted on a federal solution they would be prepared t  accept this.     In other words there was to be a settlement by amicable agreement and Serbia repudiated any idea of forcing her will upon the others.     All at the Conference were unanimous in the view that a strong Central Parliament was desirable.The various questions were thra,shed out at tremendous length in a truly Slav fashion: and speeches of several hours in length were delivered.     ISverything in the Pact was agreed upon unanimously. The only paint upsn \?hich differences of opinion arose was the agrarian question.     On this there were two rival views - (a) that at the moment when liberation became effective, all remains of the feudal system must be at once abolished, with the result that the Kmets (semi-serfs) would become proprietors in Bosnia and thein Crsatia-Slavcnia would become State property, while
the estates of the Church w.-uld not he seised hut placed under a certain State central, while all questions of compensation v/ould have, t&lt;- he deciced later on by legislation.     (b) The ether view, to which. Dr. Trumble and a minority adhered, was that 3uch a question could n-*t be solved administratively but must be left fcr the decision of a Constituent Assembly ur even the final legislative bedy.     All were agreed upon the principle of compensation.     Disagreement took a perfectly friendly form, but as both sides held to their opinion, the question, was emitted frGm the Pact, which  nly includes a general agreement.My informant learns that a detailed pamphlet on the Salonika Conspiracy Trial is being prepared by the Serbian Press Bureau. He evidently did not expect it to be a very goud production.     I learnt from him that in addition t  the officers directly implicated in the alleged plot no less than 60 officers have been placed on the retired list, many of them among the best in the array.     General Terzic\ though not tarred with the political brush, does not appear to enjoy much prestige in the army.     It is also extremely unfortunate that so fine a soldier as the Voivode Stepanovic should be practically shelved, not because he is directly implicated, but seemingly from political jealousy.I haise also learnt an extremely interesting detail regarding the man Malobabic, hitherto reported as a &quot;Bosnian exile&quot; who was executed with the two ringleaders condemned at Salonika. Malobabic was really a Serb from Croatia and was one of the 53 victims of the notorious Agram Treason Trial which was engineered in 1909 by the then Baron Aehrenthal, in collusion with the Hungarian government, in order to justify his policy of annexation in Bosnia.     Dr. Hinkovid, now one of the signatories of the Corfu agreement, was the leading advocate for the defence in the
Agram Trial and as such acted for and was in the closest touch with Malobabic as a client.     All the latter&apos;s fellow prisoners were against him and regarded him as an agent provocateur; and he actually admitted to Kinkuvic that he had had money relations with the authorities.     After the trial was quashed Maloba&apos;bic&quot; went to Serbia and even before this war had rendered himself suspicious to Mr. Protic then Minister uf the Interior and the strung man of the then Pasic Cabinet, who had him put under close police supervision.     This does not of course prove anything, as Malobataic with such a record might equally have, been an agent of Austria, a tool of military conspirators or a government instrument to confourtd them.     But it definitely establishes the fact that one ef the three persons executed was a thoroughly shady and disreputable individual.It may be added that the Jugo-Slav delegates had a more favourable opinion than ever of the Serbian Prince Regent, whom they regard as entirely devoted to their cause.     It appears that Dr. Trumbic intervened with him in favour uf a commutation of the death sentence upon Colonel Dimitri$:evic&quot;and the ethers and that the Crown Prince was m-.ved almost to tears: but this did not avail to change the decision.Dr. Trumbic cn his return had a long interview at the Vatican with Monsignor Tedeschini, of which I hope to&apos;learn the particulars when the former comes to London.R.W.S.W. 15/Q/3J7.

</content>
</cab>
