<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/26/0 images: 262-271</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
r 239THIS gOCmggT IS THE PROPERTY OF EIS BRIgMNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERflMBKT.S Hill.~- WAR CABIITST.   ...g.T. 2056,FORMAT IOU   OF   SEPARATE   AIR   MINISTRY.(Minute from the Chief of the Imperial General Staff, and observations by Sir Douglas Haig on the proposed formation of a separate Air Ministry.)1.War Office,London,    S.W.   &apos;0.1/118/340 .A.17th September, 1917.The Secretary,War Cabinet.I enclose copies of correspondence with the Field-Marshal Commending-in-Chief, France, regarding the formation of a separate Air Servico, which should be circulated to the War Cabinet.I em of opinion that the points raised by Field-Marshal Sir Douglas Heig are of great importance, and merit, in the interests of the effective prosecution of the war, most careful attention.(signed)   W. R. ROBERTSOIT,General.C.I.G.Se
fitB.E.F.3/21He Id-MarshalCommanding-in-Chief France.Precis for the Army Council No.886 of Aug.&apos;17.1.      I enclose a copy of a Paper which has just been considered and approved in principle by the War Cabinet regarding the formation of a separate  Air Service.     The Air Minister, assisted by certain Bavfcl and Military officers, is to work out a detailed scheme for giving effect to the principle.    This will be prepared in consultation with the Depar-tmertts^. concerned, and will probably take several weeks, and, of course, before it can be adopted legislation will bo required.2,        I should be glad If you would kindly forward .me, as early as convenient, your observations on theProceedings   subject.     I enclose a copy of the Army Council of the ArmyCouncil        observations, which have been placed before the War 28/8.Cabinet.24/August,/l917.(Sd) W.R. Robertson.GeneralChief of the Imperial General Staff.
Bo. O.B. 2097*General Headquarters,British Armies in Franoe&gt; 15th September,, 1917.The Chief of theImperial General Staff.In accordance with your J3o. B.&apos;E.F. 3/21, of the 24th August, 1917, I submit the following remarks.The principle of the formation of a separate Air Service having already been approved by the War Cabinet, my examination of the subject has been directed&apos; to the problem of ensuring that the efficiency of the Servico now existing with our armies in the field shall be maintained under the intended new organisation..   I have further limited my consideration of the matter to our requirements in this war, the winning of which demands the concentration of all our energies, while future needs can be foreseen more accurately and examined more closely after the war than is possible now.Aa a first step towards offering suggestions as to how to apply the proposed change of organisation to the Air Service with the armies in the field, without danger of causing loss of efficiency, I have carefully studied the report of the Committee, forwarded with your memorandum.Ae a result of that study I may say at once that some of the views put forward as to future possibilities go far beyond anything that can be justified in my experience.Apart from the question of advisability, from thepoint/
point of view of morality and public opinion, of seeking to end the war by &quot;devastation of enemy lands and destruction of industrial and populous centres on a vast scale&quot;,    I am unable to agree that there is practically no limit to such methods in this war, or that - at any rate in the near future - they are likely to &quot;become the principal operations of war, to which the older forme of military and naval operations may become secondary and subordinate&quot;.The first suggestion I have to offer, therefore, is that the limitations of long distance bombing and the results to be expected   from it may be very carefully examined in consultation with officers who have wide praotioal knowledge of its possibilities and of the general conditions affecting its development.The scope of this examination should include a thorough consideration of the relative importance of independent bombing operations and of work in the air in combination v/ith the older forms of military operations, as a means of winning this 7/ar.I have no doubt that a full examination of these problems will show that the views expressed by the Committee require very considerable modification^    and I desire to point out the grave danger of an Air Ministry,  charged with such powers as the Committee recommends,, assuming control with a belief in theories which are not in accordance with practical experience.Long distance bombing designed to cripple the enemy&apos;s naval and military resources and hamper his movements may certainly give .valuable military results.   The bombing of populous centres may also be justifiable, and may proveeffective,
effective, in order to punish the enemy for .similar acts-previously committed by him, and to prevent their recurrenoe. Once such a contest is commenced, however, we must be prepared morally and materially to outdo the enemy if we are to hope to attain oar ends.Whatever room there may be for difference of opinion as to the results to be expected from long distance bombing,, there are very evident limitations to the possibilities of its execution in this war.     The German air routes from Belgium to England are short and lie over the sea.     The distances we have to go to reach important German centres are much greater and our routes lie over hostile territory. Our raiding machines, therefore, are far more likely to be seen and reported, and defence against them is more easily arranged for, both from the ground and in the air.     In this-regard it is well to remember that the science of defence against aircraft attack may develop considerably in the future.Prevailing winds favour the enemy&apos;s return (the most dangerous part of the journey)   from raidB on England, whereas they will usually be against our machines returning from raids into Germany.     This is a factor worthy of consideration as regards proportionate losses likely to occur.The enemy&apos;s raids start from bases where he exercises absolute control.     Ours must start from bases situated in the territory of our allies which is already much congested by the troops   of the various allied powers operating in Prance.     It must be remembered in this connection that, in addition to landing grounds, every Bquadron in the air requires space for camps, workshops, etc.., and the use of
jB   4* &apos; *roads for the movement of transport.Even in the air itself there is a limit to the number of machines that can be employed under war conditions without confusion and regrettable mistakes, and experience shows that the chance of mistakes is so much increased when two or more independent ser\-ice^ are working simultaneously, that areas have to be carefully allotted to each.In addition to all other considerations, the primary question of the supply of machines and trained personnel seems likely to cause limitations in the near future.     After more than three years of war our aimies are still very far&apos; short of their requirements, and my experience of repeated failure to fulfil promises as regards prevision makes me somewhat sceptical as to the large surplus of machines and personnel on which the Committee counts in para. 3 of its report.     Moreover that surplus is calculated on a statement of requirements rendered 15 months ago, to which additions had to be made in November last and to which still further additions may have to be made.     Nor is it clear that the large provision necessary to replace wastage has been sufficiently taken into account.     The percentage of wastage has greatly increased this year as compared with last year and is likely to increase still further now that the enemy is straining every nerve to prevent our securing aerial ascendency.In regard to the general question of provision the views expressed by the.Committee as to the relative,importance of independent aerial operations and of the &quot;older forms&quot; of military operations are of moment. .     The tendency of any authority holding such views must be to regard provision for these older forms of war as secondary and subordinate.
The amendment made to para. 10, sub-para. i6.) , of the Proceedings claims for the War Office and the Admiralty the right of judgment as to the requirements of the Army and Navy.      It- appears to me that this in effect must mean that there will in future be three authorities, each with its own special interests to satisfy; and, as pointed out in paras. 3 and 4. of the Committee&apos;s report, it has proved impossible up to date to adjudicate effectively between the claims of two, all efforts to create an authority capable of doing so having hitherto failed.      In these circumstances there Is room for doubt whether co-ordination under the new scheme will not be even more difficult, than under the old, and whether the Air Ministry, claiming to be the supreme authority on aerial questions and to control the Air Services and holding the views quoted above, may not over-ride military opinion as to military requirements.It is so important that our armies in the field should be provided liberally with the means of gaining and maintaining supremacy in the air that the dangers I have outlined above of differences of opinion and conflict of interests ^cannot be too carefully guarded against.A clear understanding ig equally essential, firstly, as to the future relationship between a Commander of an Army in the field and the Air Services allotted to him; and, secondly, as to the relationship between him and any air forces working under an independent authority in or from the theatre in which &quot;he is operating .As regards the first point, I observe that the Committee recommends that air units &apos;&apos;attached&apos;5 to the Army for operations shall be subject to the military command for tne purpose of operations, during the period of attachment.  The Committee also reoommends, however3 that the Air Ministry
shall Vontrol and administer all matters in connection with aerial warfare of all kinds whatsoever,&quot; and that its air staff is to be &quot;responsible for the working out of war plans, the direction^of operations, the collection of intelligence, and the training of the air personnel.&quot;      In face of these latter recommendations it is very essential, before the Air Ministry assumes control, to be quite clear as to what is meant by subjection to military command for the purpose of operations .The air services with an army In the field are nOw as much a part of that army as are the infantry , artillery, or cavalry, and the co-ordination and combination of the effortsi of all these services must be controlled directly by the Commanders of Armies, Corps, etc. under the supreme authority of the Commander-in-Chief.To expect that the relationship between a Commander and the Army generally, on the one hand, and &quot;attached&quot; units on the other, can ever be quite the same as if these units belonged to the Army, and looked to the other arms as their comrades and the Army authorities as their true masters and the ultimate judges on whom their prospects depend, would be contrary to all experience.      Ho system of liaison or of seconding military officers to serve for a period of years with the Air Service can ever establish the same relationship as springs from community of Interests and the knowledge that all belong alike to one service .      It is therefore necessary to have a much fuller and clearer definition of the powers of military commanders in regard to air units placed at their disposal than is given in para. 10 of the Committee&apos;s report.The military commanders must, of course, have disciplinary powers; but (they should also, in my opinion have power of reward and of selection, and at least a voiceIn
in the question of the transfer of unite-to and from their commands.   Judgement as to the number of units required for each branch of air work - artillery observation, photography, fighting and reconnaissance, etc., - as well as to the aerial methods to be employed in the field., must also be left to them if they are to be. responsible for results.It iB also unsound to depart from the principle that the authority responsible for handling a servioe in the field should be ohar^ed with its training.The Committee proposes that the new air staff should be responsible for this* and, even apart from the principle involved, $he requirements of the Army are now so varied, and go so much beyond mere flying, that it is a matter for consideration whether an Air Ministry could undertake training in all its branches.- These already include gunnery, machine gunnery, observation of artillery fire, reconnaissance of troops, and other purely military subjects in addition to photography, wireless telegraphy etc.. As regards the relationship between the Air Ministry and the Commander in the- field in respect of &amp;ir units working under the former,in or from an area controlled by the latter* the problem is also difficult and important.. The allotment of objectives should bo *;asy of adjustment.   But ths allotment of areas for aerodromes, etc., and of roads behind the allied ..lines, in Prance, in. a country already much congested,- is a very, different matter.   In addition, the passage of aircraft controlled by an independent authority over the allied lines, through the areas where air activity is constant, day and. night and over anti*. aircraft defence,!,and the .avoi&amp;anct of confusion and mistakes, present difficulties to which at present I can oet no
satisfactory solution.   The matter will require to he threshed out thoroughly by competent officers possessing practical knowledge of the difficulties to be overcome, and I must point out that during active operations such officers cannot easily be made available for the purpose from France.Finally the question of kite balloons and the training of personnel for employment with them will require settlement .I urge the importance of a thorough consideration of all these questions, and others ? hich will doubtless arise, by a committee which shall include officers possessing considerable practical experience of the uses and conditions of employment of aircraft with an army in the field.   I also urge that this stop may be taken before the responsibility for our air service is transferred, in order to gtfard against the danger of any temporary disorganization oi the Air Services in the field during the transition period.In conclusion I desire to add that I am in entire agreement with the view that the full development of all the possibilities of aerial attack is of urgent importance and that we must expect to have to meet considerable pro-gress by the enemy in the same direction in the immediate future.   It is essential, however, that our development should be on sound lines and basec on practical experience, and it is with that object that I urge the need for a thorough investigation of the questions I have touched on above.(Sd.) P. HAIC.Field-Marshal Commanding-i n-Chi ef, British Armies in France.

</content>
</cab>
