<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/26/0 images: 384-387</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.Intelligence Bureau,Department of Information, EPW/016.Weekly Report on Poland. XVI. (20th September, 1917.)The rejsignation of the Polish Provisional Council of State on August 25 and the new decree published by the two Emperors on September 12 are spectacular event3 which naturally attract the attention of the Press and loom large, though in reality neither of these two events marks a really new departure.     The resignation of the Counoil of State, though hastened by highhanded action on the part of tixe Central Powers, was after all the resignation of a body which three months ago had already decided to make room for a successor.     The new decree of the Central Powers on the other hand does nothing more than embedy decisions which had been reached long before the Council of State resigned.On June 8 the Central Powers had declared their readiness to hand over to the Poles the non-political branches of administration -education, justice and public welfare, and also commerce, agriculture and food control &quot;with restrictions to be defined with a regard to the exigencies of the war&quot;.      But they refused to concede to Poland the moot essential attributes of an independent State, the power of raising and controlling an army of its own, of entering into diplomatic relations with foreign States, and lastly of exercising political administration at home.     The Polish Socialiets and Radicals, i.e. the parties of the Left, insistedthat these limitations should be disregarded in the drafting of a scheme for the future Polish government, but the Council of State,supported by ^the most prominent leaders of the Realists and National
Democrats, tamely accepted *hat was offered to them by the occupying Powers.     The Joint Committee, on which members of the Council sat together with men like Prince Z. Lubomirski and the well-known National Democrat leader M. da Stecki, agreed upon a series of proposals which were then passed by the Council of State on July 3 and discussed at the Warsaw conference in the last day&apos;s  f July with representatives of the German and Austrian governments.     The essence of these proposals la now embodied in the new decree of the Central Powers*The new Polish government is to consist of a Regency Council composed of three members; of a Prime Minister and a Cabinet; and of a Council of State.     It is obvious that an attempt is made to give this assortment of bodies the appearances of a government, but the quasi-sovereign in it i3 not a sovereign, the Cabinet has only a very limited control of the administration, and the Council of State has no popular democratic mandate and ho full legislative powers.The Regency Council cannot replace a figurehead of royal blood; if there was a wide-spread desire in Poland to get a Habsburg archduke for Regent, the reason for it was that the presence of such a Regent would have acted as a check on the occupying authorities - the different German and Austrian generals and governors - and that acting through him the Polish Cabinet or Council of State, or whoever would have represented the Polish nation, might have in time gained the upper hand over the occupying authorities.     But a   Regency Council composed of three Polish aristocrats or two aristocrats and a prelate, whoever these may be, will certainly never gain the upper hand over a German or Austrian Gov em or-General equal to them in status, superior to lOthem in power.     Theirs will be a place &quot;fit for fattening a pig&quot; er good for wasting a reputation, and it does not therefore seem at all surprising if the occupying Powers found some difficulty
r|in getting men to undertake those exalted functions.Concerning the functions of the Cabinet and the Council of Istate, i.e. of the central executive and legislative organs of the j new Polish government, the following points should be noted: (according to the scheme published in the British Press on September 18 their powers do net extend beyond what had been offered by &apos;the Central Powers to the Poles on June 8; and even within &quot;these limits their legislation can be vetoed by the German or the Austrian Gftvemor-General.     With regard to affairs &quot;the administration of which has not yet been handed over to the Polish authorities&quot; legislative propositions can be dealt with by the Council of State only with the permission ox the occupying Powers.     On the other hand the only limitation on the legislative powers of the occupying authorities in those matters is that they may issue rules of binding force only &quot;after having taken the opinion of the Council of State&quot;; but obviously no binding power attaches to those &quot;opinions&quot;.However little is conceded by this decree, which may be rightly described as the testament of the old Provisional Council of State, it yet marks considerable progress on the decree of November 26, 1916, by which the Provisional Council of State itself had been created.    According to that original scheme the Council of State was to be nothing more than an advisory body without any legislative or executive powers.It now remains to be seen who the people   will be to fill the places in the new government, though in reality this is a matter of comparative indifference; there ie very little to choose between the original pro-Austrians and the late friends of Russian autocracy who ceased to be pro-Russians as soon as Russia acknowledged Poland^ independence.     The most energetic champions of Polieh independence, $the leaders of the Radical Left, are in prison and they will certainly be given no chance of influencing the new Polish government.    Whichever of the other two groups gets in   will try to do
L.B.N.20/9/17.some honest work for the good of the country, hut will funk taking &apos; any strong measures against any one who has force behind him, will do all it can to maintain itself in office, will be blackguarded right and left by its opponents and will supply the necessary background and material for tall tales to Polish politicians and polish news agencies abroad.

</content>
</cab>
