<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/90/0 images: 4-12</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFJDENTJAL l.IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJEST Y&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C.(57) 25130th October, 1957 COPY NO. ?T iCABINETADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNALS AND ENQUIRIESMemorandum by the Lord chancellor the Committee on Administrative Tribunals and Enquiries - the&quot;Franks Committee&quot; - reported on 15th July and their report will be debated in Parliament on 31st October.   I need not recapitulate the considerations which led to the appointment of this enquiry in 1955,following the disputes over Crichel Down in the previous year.   TheCommittee^ terms of reference are attached at Annex B.2.     The Franks Committee addressed themselves to the formulation of principles which should underlie the constitution and working both of tribunials and of administrative procedures involving an enquiry or hearing,and they carried out an exhaustive survey of the operations of existingtribunals and the working of administrative procedures relating to land.The Committee arrived at three basic principles - the principlesof &quot;openness, fairness and impartiality&quot; - which, in their view, shouldmark the arrangements both for tribunals and for administrative pro-procedures involving enquiry.   They submitted a total of 95 recommendationsformulated in the light of these principles; 33 of these recommendations .are concerned with the constitution and procedures of tribunals in general;32 recommendations are concerned with the functioning of individual,named, tribunals; and the remaining 30 relate to administrative pro-procedures involving enquiry or hearing.   Some of the main considerations ofprinciple which guided the Franks Committee are given in quotation in annex C.3.     In preparation for the forthcoming debate, a Committee ofMinisters under my chairmanship have reviewed the Franks committee report for the immediate purpose of determining, in relatively general terms at this stage, the extent to which the Franks recommendations are acceptable and capable of application.   (We have not applied ourselves, atthis point, to the extent to which legislation will be necessary to giveeffect to the Franks proposals, or with the form and timing of any such legislation.   A good many of the proposals, however, can be put intoeffect by administrative arrangement. )4.     The Franks Report is in general accordance with Conservativephilosophy and principles, and it has been welcomed by our supporters.We have, therefore, been concerned to satisfy ourselves that as much aspossible of the Report can be accepted.   In doing so, we have given full weight to those considerations which must be more present in our mindsas a Government than in the minds of any outside Committee.-1-
First, the consideration that the Government must be able, inthe last resort, to discharge their responsibilities effectively.   TheMinistry of Housing, for example, deal with about 6,000 appeals cases ayear and any administrative procedure must be related to that basicfact, unless - by changes in policy - we take the alternative course of reducing the scope of the responsibilities falling on that Department.While the Franks Committee themselves recognised in principle theimportance of achieving equilibrium between the needs of soundadministration and the legitimate claims of the citizen, it is not unfair to infer that, as their enquiryproceeded, they became more preoccupied with the libertarian than with the administrative aspects of theirproblem.   Virtually all their 95 recommendations extend the rights ofthe citizen and impose some additional burden on administration.Second, the question of delay.   The Franks Committee did notaddress themselves to the problems of striking a balance betweenperfection and expedition, and they themselves volunteered the view thattheir recommendations are unlikely to contribute towards the speedierdespatch of business.   In fact their recommendations must lengthen thetime taken to reach decisions, and there can be little doubt that theysuspected this.   But the delay in settling cases is one of the two mainsubjects of public complaint, the other being compensation for land, withwhich the Franks enquiry was not concerned.Third, the striking of a just balance between the claims of the citizen, and the claims of the community as a whole, in an era in whichthe nation must be equipped with the resources of a fully competitiveeconomy.5.      Nevertheless, taking all these things into account, we are able torecommend, in purely numerical terms, that some 71 out of the 95recommendations are either completely or broadly acceptable; 8 are acceptable to a lesser or minor degree and 12 must be reserved (in whole or in part) for further consideration.   We propose that only 4recommendations should be rejected outright.   And, whenever we have felt  unable to accept a recommendation, or have accepted it with considerable qualification, we have wherever possible aimed at devisingsome compromise proposal which would comply with the spirit of theReport.6.      I am circulating separately, for the information of my colleagues,our findings on each of the 95 recommendations.   But the Cabinet will wish to be informed immediately of our conclusions on the minority of recommendations which might be regarded as fundamental or structuralin character.   These conclusions are set out in Annex A,   Naturally, itis in regard to these basic recommendations that we have frequently foundmost difficulty in accepting the Franks proposals precisely as they stand.7.      I recommend that the Home Secretary should take the line in the debate that the Government welcome the Report of the Franks Committeeand expect to be able to accept in large degree the detailed recommenda-tions in it.   Naturally, this acceptance must be qualified by reference tothe various considerations set out in the preceding paragraphs.   But theGovernment fully recognise the desirability of adjusting their variousprocedures wherever possible to conform with the basic principles which the Franks Committee have formulated, and where they are unable-2-
fully to adopt a recommendation they will try to offer some alternativewhich is in harmony with these principles and goes at least some partof ihe way to meet the problem.   This, of course, will not be practicable in every case but we do not expect to have to reject outright more thana small proportion of the total number of recommendations.   The HomeSecretary may then wish to announce the Governments attitude towardsthe main recommendations in the Report on the lines of the proposalsbelow, if these proposals are approved, and assure the House that theviews expressed in debate will be fully taken into account in reachingfinal decisions on the recommendations and in devising methods of applying them.K.House of Lords, S.W.1.29th October, 1957-3-
ANNEX a conclusions ON FUNDAMENTALRECOMMENDATIONST ribunals(i) Councils on Tribunals.    The Franks Committee recommended that two Councils on Tribunals should be established to exercise in an advisory capacity a comprehensive supervisory role over the activities and procedures of all tribunals.    (On this, see (iii) and (x) below. )    Weendorse this proposals    It is not necessary, however, to set up separatecouncils for England and Wales and for Scotland respectively.    Scotland&apos;interests will be better served by appointing for Great Britain as a wholea single council in which the Scottish members will not be isolated and out of touch with developments generally.(ii) Appointments to tribunals.     We accept the recommendation thatthe Lord Chancellor (in Scotland, the Lord President of the Court of session) should henceforward nominate the chairmen of all tribunalsappointed by the Government, with a few necessary exceptions.    But,after much reflection, we consider it impracticable for the Council onTribunals to be charged, as recommended, with responsibility for appoint-ing the members of tribunals.    These recommendations were, of course,designed to remove the power of appointing from the departmental minister concerned.    For practical reasons, and to preserve fullaccountability to Parliament, the power of appointing must remain with a minister and it is most convenient that this should be the departmental minister; but we propose as a compromise that he should appoint inconsultation with the Council on Tribunals.    This would go some way towards meeting the aim of the recommendation.    We are satisfied thatit would be practicable for the Council to offer advice on appointmentswhen it would not be practicable for them to undertake the full burdenof appointing.(iii) Procedure before tribunals generally.    The recommendations on.this are designed to extend the rights of the citizen before, during and afterthe tribunal hearing, and to define more closely the obligations of fDepartments.    Although it will be necessary to qualify acceptance ata number of points, the general tenor of these recommendations can be ?endorsed.    We are able to go further than the Franks Committee in recommending that all restrictions on legal representation beforetribunals should be abolished.    The Committee recommended that a code of procedure for each tribunal should be formulated by the Council onTribunals.    We endorse this in principle.(iv) Appeal and judicial review.    The recommendation that, generally^there should be a straight appeal from a tribunal of first instance to anappelate tribunal, with a further appeal to the courts on a point of law,is quite acceptable.    Its detailed application will, however, needconsideration.    The Franks Committee themselves rejected the case fora General Administrative Appeal Tribunal or an Administration Divisionof the High Court.m^mm

(v)     Legal aid and costs.    The Franks Committee were relatively-generous in their recommendations on these matters.    We do not thinkthat those recommendations should be accepted without much furtherconsideration.    There is a queue for legal aid, and the proposal thatthis service should be extended to appearances before tribunals must take its place in it.    Generous arrangements for awarding costs will be expensive and are not necessarily in the best interests of appellants,because of the certainty that they will lead to the much greater employ-ment of lawyers and eventually destroy informality of procedure.Sympathetic consideration can be given to awarding costs in cases takento appeal by Departments to obtain a clarifying decision on a point ofprinciple.    We recommend that the whole matter of costs should be remitted to the Council on Tribunals for advice.Administrative procedures relating to land(vi) Prior statement of the acquiring authority&apos;r case.    We agree thatit is an elementary principle of justice that the objector must know inadvance what case he has to meet.    We are satisfied, however, that theobligation of public authorities to provide such a case should be embodied in Rules of Procedure to be made by the Lord Chancellor and not, as recommended, in statutory provisions.(vii) Statements of policy.    It is considered impracticable, on manycounts, for the Departmental Minister to provide, as the franks committee recommend, a statement of Ministerial policy drawn up inrelation to each case going to hearing.    This recommendation, as it stands, must be rejected.    As a compromise, we can undertake that more effective steps will be taken to make more widely known the generalpolicy which affects particular cases and to review the working of thisafter an interval.(viii) Inspectors.    We are satisfied that, for purely practical reasons,Departmental inspectors cannot be divorced from their Departments and organised into a separate corps under an independent Minister,    As a compromise, we propose that inspectors should, henceforward, beappointed only after consultation with the Lord Chancellor and dismissedonly with his consent.    The Franks Committee themselves put up fewarguments of substance in support of their recommendation, which our proposal will go some way to meet.(ix) Publication of reports and correction of evidence.    We agree thatinspectors1 reports, inference as well as fact, should be published along with the Minister&apos;s decision.    This departure from present practice willbe both unexpected and generally welcomed.    We also agree that theappellant must be given an opportunity to correct his factual evidence.Acceptance of these recommendations will give rise to serious practical problems, of which the Franks Committee were not fully conscious, andthe method in each case will require much further thought.(x) Detailed procedures for hearings and enquiries.    The samecomment as to (iii) above applies.
(xi)   Procedures under which the Service Departments acquire land.There is at present no statutory right to a hearing or enquiry when theService Departments acquire land under the Defence Acts.    The franks committee recommend that the Service Departments should be deprived,except where security considerations are paramount, of the protectionof these Acts in any circumstances short of approaching emergency andshould operate under the ordinary civil procedures which provide forobjections and enquiries.    This recommendation is, in our view, based onfaulty premises and is not acceptable.    We agree, however, that somestatutory right of objection and hearing must be given and we propose thatthis should comprise a right to a private (not a public) hearing under an inspector of suitable status appointed by the Lord Chancellor,ANNEX BTERMS OF REFERENCE&quot;To consider and make recommendations on:-(a) The constitution and working of tribunals other thanthe ordinary courts of law, constituted under any act of Parliament by a Minister of the Crown orfor the purposes of a Ministers functions.(b) The working of such administrative procedures asinclude the holding of an enquiry or hearing by oron behalf of a Minister on an appeal or as theresult of objections or representations, and inparticular the procedure for the compulsory purchase of land. &quot;ANNEX CQUOTATIONS FROM THE REPORT OF THECOMMITTEE ON ADMINISTRATIVE tribunals and ENQUIRIESGeneral&quot;Since the war the British electorate has chosen Governments whichaccepted general responsibilities for the provision of extended social services and for the broad management of the economy.    It hasconsequently become desirable to consider afresh the procedures by whichthe rights of individual citizens can be harmonised with wider publicinterests.&quot;   (Paragraph 5.)-6-
&quot;It is noteworthy that Parliament, having decided that the decisionswith which we are concerned should not be remitted to the ordinary courts,should also have decided that they should not be left +0 be reached in thenormal course of administration.     Parliament has considered it essentialto lay down special procedures for them. &quot;    (Faragraph 20.)&quot;When we regard our subject in this light, it is clear that thereare certain general and closely linked characteristics which should markthese special procedures.    We call these characteristics openness, fairnessand impartiality. &quot;   (Paragraph 23.)&quot;To assert that openness, fairness and impartiality are essentialcharacteristics of our subject matter is not to say that they must be present in the same way and to the same extent in all its parts.&quot;(Paragraph 25.)Tribunals&quot;Reflection on the general social and economic changes of recentdecades convinces us that tribunals as a system for adjudication have come to stay.    The tendency for issues arising from legislative schemes to be referred to special tribunals is likely to grow rather than to diminish.&quot;   (Paragraph 37.)&quot;We agree.....that tribunals have certain characteristics whichoften give them advantages over the courts.    These are cheapness,accessibility, freedom from technicality, expedition and expert knowledgeof their particular subject.&quot;    (Paragraph 38.)&quot;Tribunals are not ordinary courts, but neither are they appendagesof Government Departments.....We consider that tribunals should properly be regarded as machinery provided by Parliament for adjudicationrather than as part of the machinery of administration. &quot;    (Paragraph 40.)&quot;In the field of tribunals openness appears to us to require the publicity of proceedings and knowledge of the essential reasoning under-lying the decisions; fairness to require the adoption of a clear procedure which enables parties to know their rights, to present their case fully andto know the case which they have to meet; and impartiality to require thefreedom of tribunals from the influence, real or apparent, of Departmentsconcerned with the subject-matter of their decisions. &quot;    (Paragraph 42.)&apos;ADMINISTRATIVE PROCEDURES INVOLVING an enquiry OR HEARING&quot;Although the statutory requirements are merely to hear and consider objections, it must surely be true that an objection cannot reasonably be considered as a thing in itself, in isolation from what isobjected to.    The consideration of objections thus involves the restingof an issue, though it must be remembered that it may be only a part ofthe issue which the Minister will ultimately have to determine.    If so,then the case against which objections are raised should be presented and developed with sufficient detail and argument to permit the proper weighingof the one against the other. &quot;    (Paragraph 271.)-7-
&quot;Our general conclusion is that these procedures cannot beclassified as purely administrative or purely judicial.    They are notpurely administrative because of the provision for a special procedurepreliminary to the decision - a feature not to be found in the ordinary course of administration - and because this procedure, as we have shown,involves the testing of an issue, often partly in public.    They are not onthe other hand purely judicial, because the final decision cannot be reached by the application of rules and must allow the exercise of a wide discretion in the balancing of public and private interest.    Neither view at itsextreme is tenable, nor should either be emphasised at the expense of theother.11    (Paragraph 272.)&quot;We shall not examine these procedures in the light of theconceptions of &quot;administrative&quot; and &quot;judicial&quot; because we do not thinkthem satisfactory instruments for dealing with the actual nature of thesubject-matter.    We shall instead directly address ourselves to the task of finding a reasonable balance between the conflicting interests.    On theone hand there are Ministers and other administrative authorities enjoinedby legislation to carry out certain duties.    On the other hand there arethe rights and feelings of individual citizens who find their possessionsor plans interfered with by the administration.    There is also the publicinterest.....&quot;    (Paragraph 276.)&quot;It is with these considerations in mind that we shall seek toapply the three principles of openness, fairness and impartiality - towhich we have referred in Part I - to the second part of our terms ofreference, but we must recall that the third of these three principles,impartiality, cannot be applied here without qualification. &quot;(Paragraph 277.)-8-

</content>
</cab>
