<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/90/0 images: 155-156</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE ^R^PERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENT)C,(57) 28121st November, 1957HOUSE OF LORDS reform memorandum by the First Lord of the admiralty agree with the Lord Chancellor and the Commonwealth secretary on the detail of the proposals which they make for legislating on the reform of the House of Lords (with the exception of the proposal for limiting the attendance of hereditary Peers).2.      But I find it hard to believe that it is wise to embark onlegislation for a reform which could be regarded as so insignificant.Most people regard the introduction of women as inevitable and, if any-thing, slightly funny rather than a desirable and important improvement.There will, it is true, be a certain number of people who will come inas life Peers and will strengthen the House but who would be very reluctant to accept hereditary Peerages.    It will inevitably be politicallyvery difficult to create three or four times as many Socialist life Peersas those from other Parties or no Party.   To my mind the result willbe a House which will inevitably be as open to attack as it is at thepresent time and with net much more authority.3.      This is generally recognised but anxiety is felt on two scores.Firstly, a wider measure of reform would be difficult to get through theHouse of Lords; and secondly, it involves controversy with the Socialistswho might internperately pledge themselves to some sweeping reforminstead of letting the matter pass through quietly.4.      So far as the House of Lords itself is concerned, the old and morerespected members are all for a wider measure of reform, as also arethe younger and more energetic ones.   The Liberals want to go further,and the Socialists hardly dare to express an opinion whatever theypersonally may think.   I believe it may prove difficult to prevent a morefar-reaching measure being carried against the Government and I have little doubt that the Government could themselves carry a measure forfurther reform if they so wished.5.      With regard to the second point, if the Socialists want to abolish the House of Lords they will do so whatever they do now.   One of thebenefits of a minor controversy is that it makes the Socialists and othersthink a little more closely as to what in fact they do want to do.   I am surethis is desirable as, apart from other things, there have been many new members of the House of Commons since the controversies of 1947.When they come to look at it more closely they will eventually find thatwith the final abolition of anhereditary element there will be no stoppingplace between the abolition of an hereditary element and (a) a singleCltumber Government, or (b) an elected Senate.   A purely nominatedChamber would never last in this country.-1-COPY NO.SOCAB INET
6.      I recognise that Lard Salisbury&apos;s proposals have been turneddown for the present.   T w*juld only ask that if during the committee stage some such proposals were put forward, the Government would not automatically commit itself to a blind negative.S.Admiralty, S.W.1.20th November, 1957

</content>
</cab>
