<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/90/0 images: 198-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-    191THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of.........----------------------TOP SECRET Copy No.JSJ?C.(57) 29730th. December, 1957CABINETDEFENCE EXPENDITURE, 1958/59Memorandum by the Minister of defence the Defence Estimates (excluding receipts from the United Statesand Germany) were  1,483 millions for the current year 1957/58.    actual expenditure is likely to be about  1,515 millions.    The excess is largely due to increases In wages and prices.2.      In a memorandum to the Defence Committee on 2 6th July,(D.(57) 13) I estimated that defence requirements in 1958/59 would belikely to cost about  1,500 millions.     However, in view of the country^economic difficulties, I undertook to try and reduce this to  1,450 millions on the basis of costs then prevailing.3.      This I have done.    However, since last summer there have been substantial rises in prices and wages which will have the effect ofincreasing the figure by between  40 millions and  50 millions.    As aresult, the total defence estimates for 1958/59 look like amounting toabout  1,490 millions as shown below:-	1957/58	1957/58	1958/59	(Estimates)	(Actual Forecast) (Sketch Estimate	Admiralty	316	341	343.4War Office	445	445	444.9Air Ministry	506	506	480. ministry of Supply	198	205	205Ministry of Defence	18	17	18	1 ,483	1,514	1,4924 .    The figure of  1,492 millions includes several new items, such as 35 millions for improvements in pay and allowances and about 2 0 millions for compensation to Service personnel who are prematurelyretired.    Notwithstanding this, it will be seen that the Estimates are some  22 millions below the level of expenditure expected to be incurredthis year.5.      Furthermore, I should point out that, owing to the progressivechange-over of the R.A.F, from non-dutiable to dutiable aircraft fuel,the Estia&amp;tes include no less than  20 millions in respect of import duty which will go back to the Exchequer.-1-
6.      The original proposals which I made for improvements in pay,allowances and amenities were estimated to cost about  39 millionsnext year.    The Chancellor cf the Exchequer has asked that expenditure should be limited to  30 millions.    I am willing to accept some reduction, but I am satisfied that  35 millions is the absolute minimumneeded to stimulate recruiting.7.      My discussions with the Service Departments are not yet entirelycompleted.    It may be possible to effect some small reductions on thefigures in paragraph 3, but no further large savings can be expected.8.      I invite the Cabinet -(a) to approve a Defence Budget of  1,492 millions for 1958/59, subject to such further smallsavings as may prove possible;  and(b) to agree to the inclusion within the overallfigure of a sum of  35 millions for improve-ments in pay, allowances and amenities.D0S.Ministry of Defence, S. W.l.30th December, 1957.2-

</content>
</cab>
