<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/4/22 images: 386-405</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
iTfp is THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)WAR      CABINET.  Economic Warfare.Seventeenth Weekly Report submitted &quot;by theMinister of Economic Warfare covering the &quot;period7th January   -   li+th. January 19^0.(Previous Report:    Paper No. W.P.  (R)  (Uo) 15 )T.(?.) (UO) 22.Copy No.    3Zo(Initialled) R.H.C.-^ond^Terrace.  r.w.1.

MINISTRY    OF    ECONOMIC    WARFARE.Seventeenth. Weekly Report on action taken for the period7th-lA\th January j  I9AO.I.        War Trade Negotiations and,RejLat ions with neutral countries,1,        Important agreements w*. th tne TurKisn Q-overtuaeniabout chrome and dried fruits were s\signed in Paris on the8th January, while the agreement with the Yugoslav government about minerals which had &quot;been negotiated in Belgrade inDecember, was signed at the Foreign Office on the 12th January.Negotiations with the Danish and Netherlands Delegationsare continuing,    The Norwegian Delegation is returning shortly to Oslo, and will be followed by representatives of theMinistry, who will hope to conclude the negotiations whichhave made good progress.    Negotiations with the GreekDelegation, which is now in Londonr  opened on. the 11th January.2.        The situation in the various countries is &quot;breifly as follows: -SWEDEN.3.        During the past week the situation as regardsSweden has been dominated by the question of Iron Ore.    Itis worth mentioning that all our reports go to show that theGermans are planning to take largely increased, quantities of swedish Ore from Narvik.    The figure of 325,000 tons hasQeen mentioned for the month of January, and it is believedthat of this quantity no less than 100,000 tons has beensnipped since the beginning of the year.Mr. Wallenberg recently returned to London, andit/

- 2 -it is hoped, to hold the first meeting of the Anglo-SwedishStanding Commission early this week and discussion withhim on a number of matters preliminary to the meeting hasalready been begun.DENMARK.rji.      Negotiations are continuing both for a payments agreement and a War Trade Agreement, and a letter has been addressed to M. Mohr proposing a restriction of Danishimports of feedingstuffs.ICELAND.6.      On the 6th January M.  Cveinn Bjbrnsson, the headcf the Icelandic Trade Delegation, replied to Sir GeorgeMounsey&apos;s letter of the 29th December (Weekly Report No. 15?paragraph 8).    After recording a protest against--the Britishview of neutral rights., the letter states that M. Bjbrn&amp;son-feels assured that his Government will not object to theforming of an Association, and setting up a Joint Committee.7,     Messages have since been received from HisMajesty&apos;s Consul-General at Rer/kjavik informing us that the icelandic Government is agreeable to the constitution ofthe Joint Standing Committee,  the Icelandic members of whichhave already been appointed,BALTIC STATES,8.      During the recent negotiations at Berlin threats-ere used and great pressure was brought to bear by theGerman Government on the Representatives of the Estonianaxd Latvian Trade Delegations to induce them to agree to stop trading with Great Britain.    This demand was categorically^ejected.    There is reason to be! leve that the LithuanianGovernment have adopted the same attitude,9.      Small consignments of flax arc on their way t;-lhe United Kingdom.ESTONIA/

- 3 -10.     The Representative of the Estonian Government,ho ngS been entrusted with the conversations regarding trade.veen the United Kingdom and Estonia,  is leaving Tallinnta-London on the 15th January,11.     A consignment of 300 tons of tinned meat productsis shortly expected in the United Kingdom,JOE WAY.12.     The Norwegian Delegation are returning to Oslocr. January l6th,    A German delegation is expected in Osloon January 22nd,  and represent at Lves . of the Ministry of economic warfare will arrive at Oslo on January 20th with a view toconcluding our negotiations which have made good progresscuring the past week.    Before the Norwegian Delegation leaveLondon they will he given the draft of a War Trade Agreementcovering all points, except iron ore and pyrites, which it ishoped-tordeal with subsequently by negotiation in Oslo.13.     After-vfurther consideration. hy^Government Departmentsit is felt that the - cost- -of pre-empt ing Norwegian fish-exports would net be justified, and we are proposing eventually to give way on this point after extracting the maximum in concessionselsewhere.lh.      One of the points that will require discussion atCslo will be the working of the shipping agreement which at theoment is not being effectively observed by the Norwegianshipowners.&quot;^STZERLAND.15.     Discussions between the French and British commercialePresentatives and the Swiss exports on the subject of the lists to be included in a War Trade Agreement, which wereer^ioned in the last Weekly Report, are proceeding satisfactorily.BELGIUM/

- h -33LGJUM16.     Negotiations for certain special agreements are continuing in Paris.    The views of the French Government onthe special agreements negotiated in London have not yet &quot;beenreceived.THE NETHERLANDS.17.     The negotiations for a War Trade Agreement are continuing, and progress is being made.SPAIN.18.     The United Kingdom Delegation at Madrid have recommended alterations in the proposed draft agreement on war Trade which, in its original form,  they thought it wouldbe impossible to induce the Spanish Government to accept.This recommendation was supported by His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador,who represented that the first and most important, ob-ject tobe gained by the present negotiations is to break down Spanish,suspicion and open the way for British as opposed to german influence, and that it would be -^undesirable to prejudice theacceptance of our terms for a commercial and financial settlement, which themselves may provoke some disappointment,by insisting on war trade conditions which would offend theSpanish sense of national dignity.    Certain modifications ofthe draft have been telegraphed to Madrid and Sir M. Petersonhas been instructed to report further if he considers thatinsistence on a war trade agreement on these lines will cause a breakdown of the general negotiations.19.     His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Faris has been informed by the French Minister of Commerce that instructions haveoeen sent to the French Delegation at Madrid which,  it wasbought, would enable them to bring the ^nco Spanishnegotiations to an early conclusion.PORTUGAL./

t^TUGAL - 5 -20.     His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador has reported that, in... opinion, the conclusion of a War Trade Agreement, as noworoposed, will meet with considerable difficulty.    He suggeststhat in place of the Export Licensing System envisaged by our^resent proposals, the Navicert system might be introduced for Portugal.    Before, however, making any definite recommenda-tions on these lines, he will await the Portuguese Government&apos;views on our proposals, which are expected shortly.GREECE.21.     The first meeting with the Greek Delegation whohave arrived in London to negotiate on war trade relations,was held on the 11th January, when the draft of a war trade agreement was submitted to them after a general explanation of His Majesty1 s Government&apos; s views on the scope of thenegotiations had been given0    The second meeting was held onthe 12th January when the Greek Delegation submitted a revised draft agreement, and discussions are being pursued.22,     The Greek delegates participating in the war trade negotiations are the Greek Minister, M. Simopoulos, the GreekMinister of Finance, M. Apostolides, the Governor of thenational Bank of Greece, M. Varvaressos and the Head of theCommercial Department of the Greek Ministry of Foreign Affairs,H. Kyrou.   Meanwhile the Greek Under-Secretary of Marine, M0Ziffo has been in touch with the Ministry of Shipping, and h s declared his intention to do his utmost to promote theMinistry&apos;s plans for chartering Greek shipping.23.     The agreements on c hrome and dried fruits describedRePort No. 16 were signed in Paris on January 8th, together11 several financial agreements between the United Kingdom,-nch and Turkish Governments,2ho  In/

- 6 -2k.      In view of reports that Turkey is intending torecpen trade with Germany, His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Ankaras urged the Turkish Government not to enter into anycommitments for the supply of key commodities to Germanyending further discussions to take place on the return oft:.e secretary General of the Ministry for Foreign affairs to Ankara.vhoosLAVIA.25.     The Minerals Agreement initialled in Belgradeon the 20th December was signed on the 12th January by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the Yugoslav(inister.    The substance of the agreement was indicated inparagraph 23 of Weekly Report No. lh- and paragraph 33 of Weeklyeport No.  15.TALY.26.     His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador reports that our proposalsfor a War Trade Agreement (see paragraph 18 of last week&apos;sreport) were unfavourably received in the Joint Standingommittee, where the Italian delegation described them as &quot;unetteinte contre la souverainete&apos; italienne&quot;.    The Ambassadorubsequently saw Count Ciano, who repeated the Italian objectionsn a less uncompromising manner, but reserved judgment untile had consulted Signor Mussolini.27.     No progress is reported in the Clearing negotiations,ut a communication which Sir P. Loraine has been instructed0 make on the subject of our inability to continue much longerheexemption from enemy export control still enjoyed by Italy&apos;s-&amp;-borne imports of coal from Germany may be expected toxpedite matters. .28.     Negotiations with Messrs. Parisi,  the forwardingtents of Trieste, Genoa, etc. who were suspected of engagingn contraband traffic, have been brought to a successfulElusion. 29. The/

liedand neutral exporters.CHINA/29.     The Italian Government has complained that theConte di Savoia was detained at Gibraltar for seven hours,a date when she was in fact in New York.    It is pleasant.he able to record a certain falling off in the quality as,U as in the quantity of their complaints.UN6ARY.30.     Monsieur de Podhorszky, Managing Director of thengarische Baumwolle Industrie A/G, and Monsieur Ehrmann,  of health  Ungarische Gummiwaren Fabrik, have visited the Ministryid have given satisfactory written assurances concerninghe constitution and operations of their firms, which hadeen regarded with a certain amount of suspicion.    They haveidertaken to submit their firms&apos; books to examination bypproved British chartered accountants and not to export toermany in the future,.S.A.31.     During the week the question of co-operation with the United States Government for the restriction of exportsi essential alloys to Germany, Russia and Japan has beenIE&apos;ther studied by the Departments concerned.    It is hopedit the experts who are to assist Mr. Purvis in his negotiations-1 be able to leave for the United States shortly.32.      Instructions have been sent to His Majesty&apos;siassador at Washington for his reply to the representations[fich he has received from the State Department about theorking of the Navicert system.    Lord Lothian has been authorisedassure the State Department that this system will not beeQ to discriminate against United States trade, and that ifs Navicert system is used to restrict the imports of aUiral country, the restrictions will be imposed alike on

II. Contraband Control.3h.     During the week ending 13th January, l6l newcases of ships were dealt with and 35 previons cases,  inregard to whose cargoes or items thereof enquiries had beencompleted, were disposed of.35.      In 11U cases entire cargoes were released, either on first consideration or after enquiries.36.     The system under which advance copies of manifestsof cargoes are received and considered, before the ships arrival at ports in this country resulted;  during the week under...review,in 6h cases being so dealt with and in l\3 cases of the shipsconcerned being released by the Committee subject merely tothe formal checking of the original manifests on their arrival   .at the Control Bases,    In addition to these immediate releases,in 29 other cases the Committee&apos;s decision to release was given within 5 days or less of the arrival of ships at the control bases. [avicerts.37.      Since the introduction of the Navicert systemil;082 applications for navicerts have been received up to the30th December.    Of these 7, hi 9 have been granted and 318refused, while 393h9 are pending or have not yet been presented for consideration.III. Enemy ExportsCHINA.33.     The presence of the British, French and AmericanAmbassadors in Chungking offers a useful opportunity for afurther investigation of the wolfram position.    It is understoodthat the French Ambassador is negotiating the purchase ofexisting stocks of the ore in China and Indo-China and isexploring the possibilities of a pre-emption policy.

- 9 -III. Enemy Exports.38.     During the week the Committee reviewed fiveships and ordered items of cargo from three to he placed in?rise.   An item of cargo from another had been referred bythe Contraband Committee to the Enemy Exports Committee,which referred it to the Exemptions Committee.    The itemwas ordered to be detained.39.     The Committee considered a hundred and fifty-oneapplications for exemption, refusing a hundred and three andgranting forty-eight (these included five applications madeon behalf of refugees and one on behalf of a neutral diplomat).During this week the Committee has observed a growing tendencyamong applicants to pay, or to say they have paid, for goodsbefore they were obliged, thus presumably hoping to presentan accomplished fact.    The Committee has seen no reason to treat applications of this kind with leniency.


</content>
</cab>
