<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/5/0 images: 138-152</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.  April 1918SECRET.G.-205.Report of the Committee on the Proposed New PensionsWarrant.THIS Committee was appointed by the War Cabinet (Minute 367 (21), of the 19th March, 1918) to deal with the proposed new Pensions Warrant. The Committee consisted of-The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P. (in the Chair). The Right Hon. W. Hayes Fisher, M.P., President of the Local Government Board. /A /?T.      . if. v&amp;d^^ *t ^j^^u^ c^r f^^^x^cx.The Right Hon. John Hodge, M.P, Minister of Pensions. The Right Hon. Sir Robert Chalmers, G.C.B, Secretary to His Majesty&apos;sThe Committee met on the 21st March, 1918, and discussed the general aspects of the Warrant. On the 25th March they held a meeting at which Sir A. Griffith Boscawen, M.P, Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Pensions, and the Right Hon. Sir Matthew Nathan, G.C.M.G, Secretary to the Ministry of Pensions, were present, when the new proposals were considered in detail. The draft Warrant as submitted to the Committee is reproduced below; the proposed changes from the Warrant now in operation being shown in italics. The decisions of the Committee on each article are printed irured. It is proposed that the new Warrant as amended should come into force on the 1st May, 1918,2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W., April 15, 1918.Draft of a Royal Warrant for the Pensions of Soldiers Disabled, and of the Families and Dependants of Soldiers Deceased, in consequence of the present War.January 10, 1918,Whereas We deem it expedient to make further provision concerning the pensions of preamble soldiers disabled, and of the families and dependants of soldiers deceased, in conse-quence of the present war, and to provide for their administration by Our Minister of Pensions, in accordance with the Ministry of Pensions Act, 1916 ;vOur Will and Pleasure is that Our Warrant of the 29th March 1917, concerning the pensions of soldiers disabled and of the families and dependants of soldiers deceased in consequence of the present war is hereby revoked^ and as from the date the provisions of this Our Warrant shall take effect in place of the provisions of Our said Warrant of the 29th March 1917, and that this Our Warrant shall, except in the cases stated in the Warrant of Her Majesty Queen Victoria of the 27th October 1884, be established and obeyed as the sole authority in the matters herein treated of; and that Our Minister of Pensions shall be the sole administrator and interpreter of this Our Warrant and shall be empowered to issue such detailed instructions in reference thereto as he may from time to time deem necessary.This Our Warrant shall apply to all soldiers and their families and dependants whose claims to pensions or grants of the nature dealt with therein arise out of theTreasury.Mr. G. M. Hodgson (Secretary).(Signed)G. N. BARNES   (Chairman).[366]B
fpresent war, and in the ease of new grants thereunder it shall have effect from the first weekly pay, day after the 1st day of April 1915. In the case of such persons whose claims to pensions or gratuities have been dealt with under previous Warrants the terms of this Our Warrant may, if more beneficial to them, be applied with retrospective effect from the above date, on such dates as Our Minister of Pensions may find it practicable and convenient to re-assess their claims in accordance with instructions to be issued by jiim., Such instructions shall also regulate the assess-ment of any case in which a gratuity has been granted, and shall determine the manner in which any arrears shall be paid.The grant to a soldier who has served before the date of this Our Warrant may be assessed under the terms of Our previous Warrants regulating disablement pensions for soldiers, if more favourable to the soldier than this Our Warrant, and no grant to a soldier or to the family or dependants of a soldier shall be re-assessed to their disadvantage.Nothing in this Our Warrant shall apply to any disabled soldier or to the family or dependant of any deceased soldier the terms of whose service make other provision &apos;1   on account of the disablement or decease of a soldier.Part I. SOLDIEBS.Disablement pensions to disabled soldiers.Pension to Ve temporary at outset.Minor dis-ablements.Service] pensions.Paid acting rank.1. (1) A soldier discharged as medically unfit for further service, or while suffering impairment, such unfitness or impairment being certified as either attri-butable to or&apos; agravated by military service in consequence of the present war and not being due to the serious negligence or misconduct of the discharged man, may, if he is disabled in any of the manners set forth in the First Schedule to this Our Warrant, be granted a disablement pension at the weekly rates therein shown as corresponding to the degree of his disablement. In the case of injuries not shown therein, and in the case of disease, the pension may be assessed at the degree in the schedule which is held most closely to represent the disablement corresponding to the injury or disease.(2) Except in those cases where the disablement has reached its final condition a disablement pension shall be temporary, at the rate appropriate to the temporary disablement, and the grant shall be reviewed from time to time until a permanent assessment can be made.(3) In any case where the degree of disablement is assessed at less than 20 per cent., or where it is considered more in the interests of the soldier, a gratuity or temporary allowance may be granted in place of any pension. The grant will be subject to such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine, and its amount will not exceed 2007. and will depend on the extent of the disablement and on the other circumstances of the case.(4) A Warrant Officer or Non-Commissioned Officer entitled to a service pension may receive either a disablement pension on the lowest scale, as in the First Schedule for Warrant or Non-Commissioned Officers so entitled, in addition to his service pension, or a disablement pension as in the First Schedule according to rank for Warrant and Non-Commissioned Officers not entitled to service pension, in lieu of a service pension, which ever is more favourable.(5) The disablement pension granted to a soldier who held paid acting rank at the time he was wounded, injured, or removed from duty in consequence of disable-ment, may be at the rate appropriate to that rank.The use of the words &quot; disablement pensions&quot; and the other alterations in this Article do not involve any additional liability, and the Article as modified agreed to.wasChildi-euV allowances to disabled soldiers.2. (1) A disabled man pensioned under Article 1 of this Our Warrant may be granted during the continuance of the pension a further allowance for each child under the age of 16 at such proportion of the following weekly rates as corresponds to the degree of disablement at which the man is assessed for pension:-For a first child For a second child For each child afterthe seconds. d.6 85 04 2Provided that the rate for any child shall in no case be less than 50 per cent, of the full rate for such child.
74After full discussion the new rates tor the children&apos;s allowances were agreed to, but the proviso that the rate for any child should in no case he less than 50 per cent, of the full rate for such child was deleted, the Article standing in this respect as in the existing Warrant. * - *(2) The allowance may (subject to the continuance of the pension) be granted or continued beyond the age of 16 in the case of young -persons receiving not mono than nominal wages, or of children being educated at secondary schools, technical institutes, or universities, and may be granted or continued between the ages of 16 and 21 in the case of a child incapable through mental or physical infirmity of earning a living, provided the infirmity existed before the child attained the age of 16.(3) In any case in which, in the opinion of the Minister of Pensions, it may become necessary to secure the proper care of a child on behalf of which an allowance is payable, the allowance instead of being paid to the parent may be administered under such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine.(4) In the event of a parent being wholly or partially relieved of the charge of any child by its maintenance in the Army or Navy, or in any institution wholly or mainly supported from public funds, the allowance granted on account of that child may be reduced by the extent of that relief.3. Any disabled man pensioned under Article 1 of this Our Warrant who makes Alternative application and shows that the disablement pension with children&apos;s allowances (if ^&quot;a3^^ft0 any) which he has been granted, together with the average earnings (if any) of soldiers, which he remains capable, are less than his pre-war earnings, may be granted, temporarily or permanently, in lieu of the disablement pension and children&apos;s allow-ances, a pension which, together with the average earnings (if any) of which he is judged capable, shall not exceed his pre-war earnings up to a maximum of 50s. a week, plus half of any pre-war earnings between 50s. and 100s. a week.Provided that in the case of a man who has lost both arms or both legs or the sight of both eyes, the average earnings (if any) of ivhich he may be capable shall not be taken into account.The proviso based on the promise made by Mr. Barnes in Parliament and pro-visionally agreed to by the Treasury that in the case of a man that has lost both arms or both legs or the sight of both eyes, the ^average earnings of which he may be capable should not be taken into account in the calculation of his alternative pension was agreed to.4. Half the pension and allowances (if any) awarded under the preceding condition as articles may be subject to the condition that the disabled man shall undergo medical j ^&quot;foing treatment in or at a sanatorium, hospital, convalescent home, or otherwise, for any iea me&quot;&apos; period during whiqh it may be certified that such treatment is necessary in his interests.The Committee were in favour of legislation to enable the full pension and allowances awarded under the Warrant, to be subject to the condition that the disabled man shall undergo the medical treatment certified to be necessary in his interests.5. (1) When a permanent pension has been granted it shall not be altered on Permanent account of any change in the man&apos;s earning capacity, whether resulting from training *&quot;&apos;^dto or other cause; neither shall it be subject to review except  soldiers;(a) When a man whose pension is assessed under Article 1 of this Our Warrant &apos; mWmclaims that there has been a substantial increase in the extent of the disablement due to the original cause.,(b) When a man whose pension is assessed under Article 1 of this Our Warrantshows that it would be more advantageous to him to be assessed under Article 3.(c) Under the following subsection.(2) The Minister of Pensions may at any time order the review of any pension in -Error, &amp;e. any case where (a) A pension has, by error in law or fact, been granted to a disabled man inexcess of the amount appropriate to the degree of his disablement; or(b) The Minister of Pensions has reason to believe that a pension has beenobtained by any improper means.
In view of the changes.in the rates of children&apos;s allowances it was agreed that in any case in which these allowances were paid there should be no right to claim an alternative pension under sub-head (1) (b) by reason of these allowances ceasing.Under sub-section (2) (a) the word &quot;interpretation&quot;&apos; is substituted for the word &quot; law.&quot;  Otherwise the Article as revised was approved.Xe-eniisi- 5a. A  man who, being in receipt of a pension under any of the precedingment,Sfc.,of Articles, re-enlists, or joins Our Royal Navy, or is granted a commission, or is &apos;recalled to Our Naval or Military service, shall, whilst he remains in Our Naval or Military service, be entitled (a) if in receipt of a permanent pension, whether disablement or alternative,to receive his appropriate disablement pension, but shall not be entitled to receive any children&apos;s allowances; and(b) if in receipt of a temporary pension, whether disablement or alternative, toreceive his appropriate disablement pension, without allowances to chil-dren for the period of the award, at the expiration of which the grant of pension will be reviewed. &quot; During the continuance of the present war &quot; was added at the request of the Treasury at the commencement of Article 5a, which was otherwise agreed to.Grants to and       6. (1) In any case where it is certified that a disabled man should, in 2X!e0nf consequence of his disablement, undergo any course of medical treatment, in an imder&quot;treat-   institution or otherivise, or where it is decided that he should receive training in a tohfing.      technical institution or otherwise, and he is deemed unable in consequence to provide for his own support and that of his family, there may be granted to or in respect of him, in lieu of any pension and children&apos;s allowances or gratuity or temporary allowance awarded to him, under the preceding Articles of this Our Warrant, for the purpose of undergoing treatment or training, for such period, and subject to such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine, either (a) an allowance of an amount not less than that corresponding to the highestdegree of disablement as shown in the First Schedule to this Our Warrant. together with allowances at the full rate shown in Article 2 (1), in respect of each child without regard to the definition of child contained in this Our Warrant, - and in the case of a man whose treatment or training necessitates the man living away from home, a further allowance which will secure to his wife an amount not less than the pension authorized for a widow under Article 11 of this Our Warrant, or to a dependant sup-ported by him up to the time when his treatment or training commences, an amount not less than such dependant would have received under A rticles 20 to 28 of this Our Warrant had the disabled man died in the circumstances set forth in Article 11 of this Our Warrant; or(b) an allowance equal to the maximum pension which would be payable to himunder Article 3 of this Our Warrant if he were -without earning capacity,whichever is the greater. Provided that any allowance under this subsection to a lunatic soldiermay be reduced by the amount which may be granted to a dependant whois not a relative of such soldier or by such less amount as the Minister ofPensions may determine. It was agreed that the words in the first line of 6 (1) (a) &quot; not less than &quot; should be altered in accordance with the original intention. It was also agreed that the words &quot; without regard to the definition of child contained in this Our Warrant &quot; should remain, it being explained that it was necessary to support the actual family of the man while he was under treatment or in training. The other alterations in (1) were also agreed to.(2) A deduction of such an amount and under such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine, may be made from any allowance granted under sub-section 1 of this Article, on account of the cost of the disabled man&apos;s maintenance in an institution.(3) Any charges, fees, or expenses in respect of the treatment or training of a disabled man that are not otherwise provided for may be paid under such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine.(4) At the termination of, or if the Minister of Pensions so determines, during any period of training as is provided for in this Article, there may be granted
In view of the changes in the rates of children&apos;s allowances it was agreed that in any case in which.these allowances were paid there should be no right to claim r   an alternative, pension sunder: sub^head (.1) (b) by reason of these allowances ceasing. Under sub-section (2)&quot;(a) the word &quot; interpretation &quot; is substituted for the word &quot; law.&quot;  Otherwise the Article as revised was approved.Ze-eniisi- 5a. A man who, being in receipt of a pension under any of the precedinginent,$c,of Articles, re-enlists, or joins Our Royal Navy, or is granted a commission, or is y recalled to Our Naval or Military service, shall, whilst he remains in Our Naval orMilitary service, be entitled (a) if in receipt of a permanent pension, whether disablement or alternative,to receive his appropriate disablement pension, but shall not be entitled to receive any children&apos;s allowances; and(b) if in receipt of a temporary pension, whether disablement or alternative, toreceive his appropriate disablement pension, -without allowances to chil-dren for the period of the award, at the expiration of which the grant of pension will be reviewed. &quot; During the continuance of the present war &quot; was added at the request of the Treasury at the commencement of Article 5a. which was otherwise agreed to.Grants to and       6. (1) In any case where it is certified that a disabled man should, in LSen consequence of his disablement, undergo any course of medical treatment, in. an under treat-   institution or otherwise, or where it is decided that he should receive training in a Sing.      technical institution or otherwise, and he is deemed unable in consequence to provide for his own support and that of his family, there may be granted to or in respect of him, in lieu of any pension and children&apos;s allowances or gratuity or temporary allowance awarded to him, under the preceding Articles of this Our Warrant, for the purpose of undergoing treatment or training, for such period, and subject to such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine, either (a) an ahWance of an amount not less than that corresponding to the highestdegree of disablement as shown in the First Schedule to this Our Warrant, together with allowances at the full rate shown in Article 2 (l), in respect of each child without regard to the definition of child contained in this Our Warrant-; &apos;ahd&quot;-in;-the&quot;-&quot;ease of a man whose treatment or training necessitates the man living away from home, a further allowance which will secure to his wife an amount not less than the pension authorized for a widow under Article 11 of this Our Warrant, or to a dependant sup-ported by him up to the time wdien his treatment or training commences, an amount not less than such dependant would have received under A Hides 20 to 23 of this Our Warrant had the disabled man died in the circumstances set forth in Article 11 of this Our Warrant; or(b) an allowance equal to the maximum pension which would be payable to himunder Article 3 of this Our Warrant if he were without earning capacity, whichever is the greater. : -Provided that any allowance under this subsection to a lunatic soldier may be reduced by the amount which may be granted to a dependant who is not a relative of such soldier or by such less amount as the Minister of Pensions may determine. .It was agreed that the words in the first line of 6 (1) (a) &quot; not less than &quot; should be altered in accordance with the original intention. It was also agreed that the words &quot; without regard to the definition of child contained in this Our Warrant &apos;-should remain, it being explained that it was necessary to support the actual family of the man while he was under treatment or in training. The other alterations in (1) were also agreed to.(2) A deduction of such an amount and under such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine, may be made from any allowance granted under sub-section 1 of this Article, on account of the cost of the disabled man&apos;s maintenance in an institution.(3) Any charges, fees, or expenses in respect of the treatment or training of a disabled man that are not otherwise j)rovided for may be paid under such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine.(4) At the termination of, or if the Minister of Pensions so determines, during any period of training as is provided for in this Article, there may be granted
75to the disabled man an amount equal to the sum of 5s. for each week of the period during which he has been undergoing training, and at the termination of the train-ing there may be a further grant not exceeding 10Z. for the purchase of tools ifrequired to be provided by the man in the trade in which he has. been trained. -It was agreed to omit the woms in the first line of (4) enabling training bonus to be paid during training. The grant for the purchase of tools at the termination of training was agreed to.(5) In any case where it is certified that a disabled man should, in consequence of his disablement, undergo medical treatment in circumstances which do not render him unable to provide for his own support and that of his family, but require him to absent himself from his work on one or more occasions in a week, there may be granted to him in addition to any pension, gratuity or temporary allowance awarded to him under the preceding Articles of this Our Warrant an allowance not exceeding 105. a week for the time he is required so to absent himself, the allowance to be subject to such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine.6a. In addition to any pension awarded under the foregoing Articles there may ^llo^ancIe be granted, under such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine, to or on o^disabiecf06 behalf of a man disabled in the highest degree, an allowance not exceeding 20s. a man-week in any case where the constant attendance of a second person is necessaiy.7. A soldier discharged as medically unfit for further service, such unfitness Gratuities to being neither attributable to nor aggravated by military service, and not being due ^nbicment to the serious negligence or misconduct of the discharged man, may be granted a not attribute gratuity or temporary allowance.   The grant will be subject to such conditions as aggravated by the Minister of Pensions may determine.  In exceptional circumsances it may amount military to a sum not exceeding 150Z., and generally it will depend on the extent to which senice-a man is incapacitated, on the length and character of his service, and on the other circumstances of the case.(2) Subject to such conditions as he may determine, the Minister of Pensions Medical may pay any charges, fees, or expenses in respect of the treatment of any disabled man tr^ment. who comes within the provisions of the preceding subsection and who is certified during or within a year after the conclusion of the present war to need medical treat-raent in an institution: provided that such treatment shall be limited to the disability for which the man was discharged.The new section (2) was agreed to.It was further agreed that a man receiving treatment on account of an injury or disease not attributable to or aggravatedby his military service might have his family supported by the usual allowances while such treatment lasted, this concession (in the same way as the original concession as to treatment in non-attributable cases) to be for the period of the war and twelve months afterwards.8. (1) A soldier discharged as medically unfit for further service may be Temporary granted a temporary allowance of 27s. 6d. a week together with children&apos;s allowances ^y^063 to as for the full rate of disablement for any period that may elapse between the date of soldiers, bis discharge and the announcement of a decision as to the award of pension or gratuity in his case.  Arrears of this allowance will not be granted for more than a fortnight before an intimation of the discharge is received by the Ministry or, if there has been no such intimation, before the date of any application that may be made to the Ministry for an allowance or for a pension.(2) This temporary allowance will be deducted from any pension for the cor-responding period in so far as the-pension for that period may be sufficient to meet it, but no deduction on account of the temporary allowance exceeding the rate of pension will be made from any subsequent issues of pension and no deduction will be made from any gratuity.(3) Subject to such conditions as he may determine, the Minister of Pensions Medical uay pa,y any charges, fees, or expenses that are not otherwise provided for in respect fi,eatme&quot;t-of the treatment in an institution of any disabled man to whom a temporary allow-once has been granted under subsection (1) of this Article, and who is certified to need medical treatment in consequence of the disability for ivhich he was discharged.The new subsection (3) was agreed to.The proposal that the Director of Finance should concur in the allowances granted under Article 6 (2), 6&quot;(3), 7 (2), and 8 (3) was agreed to.[366] :
Pensions when disable-ment takes effect after discharge.9. If a man after discharge from the Army suffers from a disablement which is certified as either attributable to or aggravated by military service in consequence of the present war, such disablement not being due to the soldiers serious negligence or misconduct, he may be granted a;disablement pension or a gratuity or temporary allowance under Article 1 of this Warrant as if he had been discharged as medically unfit for further service upon the date from wdiich his claim is established.The change of the wording to bring this Article into line with Article 1 wa agreed to, it being explained that this involved no additional charge.Part II. WIDOWS AND DEPENDANTS.General conditions.Pensions to widows.Children&apos;s allowances widows.10. (1) Pensions to the widows, children, and dependants of deceased soldiers, for which provision is made in the following Articles, shall not be claimed as a right, but shall be given as a reward of service, and no pension shall be granted or continued to a widow or dependant who, in the opinion of Our Minister of Pensions, is un-worthy of Our Royal favour, and it shall be in the power of Our Minister of Pensions to terminate or suspend any pension that may have been granted to such persons or to provide for its administration under such conditions as he mav determine, and his decision in any case shall be final.(2) It shall be within the power of Our Minister of Pensions to deduct from any sum paid by way of pension or allowance under this Part of this Our Warrant the cost of any benefit which it may hereafter be decided to substitute for part of the pension or allowance, provided that no deduction made under this subsection shall be at a greater rate than one penny for each full half-crown of the pension or allowance.11. The widow of a soldier who in consequence of the present war either (a) is killed while in the performance of military duty, or (b) dies as a result of wounds or injuries received in the performance of such duty within seven years of receiving such wounds or injuries, or (c) dies of disease, certified as contracted or commencing while on active service, or as having been aggravated by active service, within seven years of his removal from duty on account of such disease, may, provided the soldier&apos;s death has not been caused by his serious negligence or misconduct, be granted a widoiv\s pension at the following rates: Widow of Warrant Officer, Class I.    -Widow of Warrant Officer, Class II., or Non-Commis-sioned Officer, Class I. - .- -Widow of Non-Commissioned Officer, Class 11. -Widow of Non-Commissioned Officer, Class III. Widow of Non-Commissioned Officer, Class IV.-Widow of Private, &amp;c. (Class V.)Weekly. s.   d.22   620 18 17 16 150 9 63 0The pension granted to the widow&apos; of a soldier who held paid acting rank at the time he was killed or was removed from duty owing to wounds, injuries, or disease, from which he subsequently died may be at the rate appropriate to that rank.It was agreed that no change should be made in the rates of widow&apos;s pensions, which are as follows: Weekly.II.,   or   Non-Commissioneds. 21d.3Warrant Officer, Class I. Warrant Officer,  ClassOfficer, Class I. 18   9Non-Commissioned Officer, Class II.     - - 17   6Non-Commissioned Officer, Class III. - - - 16 3 Non-Commissioned Officer, Class IV.     - - 15   0Private, &amp;c. (Class V.).....13   912. A widow pensioned under Article 11 of this Our Warrant may be granted a to further allowance at the following weekly rates for each child under the age of 16 maintained by her: For a first child   - -        - ----- -      6For a second child 5For each child after the second8 0 2
The provisions for the grant or continuation of this allowance beyond the age of 16, for its administration to secure the proper maintenance of the child, and for its reduction to the extent to which the parent is relieved of the charge of the child shall be as set forth in subsections (2), (3), and (4) of Article 2 of this Our Warrant.The proposed new rat?s for children !s allowances were agreed to.13; Any widow pensioned under the conditions set forth in Article 11 of Alternative this Our Warrant, who makes application and shows that she was married to the widows.3 0 soldier before the commencement of the war or before the date of his enlistment, whichever was the later, and that the widoiv&apos;s pension, with children&apos;s allowances (if any), which she had been granted under the two preceding articles, is less than two-thuds of any alternative pension that mightliave been awarded to the deceased soldier under Article 3 of this Our Warrant had he survived and been incapable of supplementing that pension by earnings, may be granted, in lieu of a tuidow&apos;s pension and children&apos;s allowances, an alternative pension which shall not exceedtwo-thirds of such deceased soldier&apos;s alternative pension.After discussion and on a vote (3 to 1) it was agreed that two-thirds a soldier&apos;salternative pension should be substituted for one-half as the basis of a \vidow&apos;s alter-iiative pension.14. In addition to any pension and children&apos;s allowances awarded under the Allowances foregoing three articles there may be granted, under such conditions as the Minister widows-of Pensions may determine: (1) To any widow a gratuity not exceeding 51. for herself and ll. on account of each child for whom she may be receiving separation allowance to meet expenses consequent on or caused by the soldier&apos;s death.(2) To any widow an allowance not exceeding 12s. Qd. per week for a period not ordinarily exceeding 13 weeks whilst she is undergoing any course of instruction which, in the opinion of the Minister of Pensions, will be advantageous to her. Where an allowance is granted under this sub-section any fees for training, for which provision is not otherwise made, may be paid, subject to such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine.The additional gratuity to a widow on account of each child on the occasion of a soldier&apos;s death was agreed to.15. The widow of a soldier who ivhile serving during the present war has died, Gratuities, from wounds, injuries,  or disease, neither attributable to military service nor certified as aggravated by such service, but not due to the serious negligence or 0f soldier on misconduct of the deceased man, may be granted - at^buHbie(1) A gratuity not exceeding 5l. for herself and ll. on account of each child for whom she may be receiving separation allowance to meet expenses con-seguent on or caused by the soldier&apos;s death; and(2) A pension as follows: (a) If and for so long as she has children in her charge 15s. a week andallowances for the children as in Article 12 of this Our Warrant.(b) If she has no children or has ceased to have them in her charge, 15s.a week for the period of the war and 12 months afterwards, or for 12 months after ceasing to have any child in her charge, whichever be the later date, and for any subsequent period during which, from infirmity or age, she is wholly or partially incapable of supporting herself.The provisions of this Article as to pensions and allowances shall apply to the where soldier widow of a soldier who after discharge and during the present war dies in the circum- ffjsI&quot;f^ stances set forth above from the wounds, injuries, or disease which caused his clciarffe-discharge.A gratuity to a widow for herself and on account of each child was agreed to be given m cases where the soldiers death was neither attributable to nor aggravated by his military service.It was decided to make no other alteration in the grants to widows where the death was in these circumstances.16. Any pension granted to the widow of a soldier under Articles 11 or 13 of ^^^to this Our Warrant shall cease on her re-marriage, and she may then bp given a re-mamage
gratuity equal to one year of her widow&apos;s pension under Article 11, subject to such conditions as to payment as the Minister of Pensions may determine. Allowances for children under Article 12 may be paid after re-marriage.17. The widow of a man who was at the time of his death in receipt of a disable-ment or of an alternative pension of not less than 10s. a week, but whose death does not entitle her to a pension under Article 11 of this Our Warrant, may, provided she was living with the man at the time of his death, receive a pension of not more than one half of the deceased soldier&apos;s pension, and in no case at a higher rate than pro-vided for under that Article, this grant to be subject to such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine.      (Omitted.)It was decided to make no change in the provision for the widow of a pensioner. i.e., Article 17 above will stand good with the substitution of the words &quot; has been &quot; for the words italicised and the addition of the words &quot; and to cease on re-marriage &apos;&apos; at the end of the Article.18. The child of a soldier who has died in the circumstances set forth in Article 11 of this Our Warrant may be awarded a pension of (1) 11s. 8d. a week where the child is or becomes motherless, or has been removed from the control of its mother. In the event of two or more children being maintained by one person in the same household or institution, the amount will be reduced to 10s. for the second and 9s. 2d. for each of the children after the second,.(2) 6s. 8d. a week where an affiliation order was in force on account of a child at the time of the soldier&apos;s death, or in the case of a child of a woman who wras not married to or supported by the soldier, where there is satisfactory proof that he was its father.This pension may continue in either case while the child is under the age of 16, and beyond that age in the circumstances set forth in subsection (2) of Article 2 of this Our Warrant, and shall be administered subject to such conditions as the Minister of Tensions may determine.Clause (1) of this Article shall apply to the case of the child of a soldier who has died in the circumstances set forth in A rticle 15 of this Our Warrant.It was decided that a pension, not exceeding 10s. a week, might be granted to the child of a soldier which was or became motherless or had been removed from the con-trol of its mother, and that in the event of two or more children being maintained in the same household or institution the amount should not exceed 9s. 2d. for each child after the second^.The proposal to raise the amount where affiliation order was in force from 5s. to 6s. 8d. was agreed to.The proposed new sentence applying the motherless rate in the case of a soldier who had died from disease not attributable to his service was to be omitted.19. The separated wife of any soldier who has died in the circumstances set forth in Article 11 of this Our Warrant may, provided the marriage took place at a time entitling a widowr to a pension and the man contributed to her support be granted a pension equal to the amount due to her under a separation order or otherwise paid by her husband, or both, but not less than 3s. 6d. a week and not exceeding 15s. a week, and allowances for her children, if maintained by her, as- in Article 12 of this Our Warrant. Allowances for children as in Article 12 may also be granted to the separated wife of a soldier where he did not contribute to her support.The proposed alteration in the pension granted to. separated wives was agreed to, but the amount of such pension was not to exceed 13s. 9d. a week.20. Any woman who has lived as his wife with a soldier, who has died in the circumstances set forth in Article 11 of this Our Warrant, may, if she had been wholly or substantially dependent on that soldier, and has been drawing separation allowance as for a wife or was eligible for such allowance, be granted a pension as follows: - (1) If and for so long as she has children of the soldier in her charge, 15s. a week and allowances for the children as in Article 12 of this Our Warrant. (2) If she has no children of the soldier, or has ceased to have them in her charge (otherwise than from their being removed from her control on account of
77tier misconduct), 15s. a week for the period of the war and 12 months afterwards, or for 12 months after ceasing to have any child of the deceased soldier in her charge, whichever be the later date, and for any subsequent period during which, from infirmity or age, she is wholly or partly incapable of supporting herself.It was agreed that there should be no change in the existing provisions for temporary pensions to unmarried wives, i.e., the amount of 10s. a week in sub-sections (1) and (2) above should not be varied.21. (1) The parent (or parents) of a soldier who has died in the circumstances Peusionito set forth in Article 11 of this Our Warrant may be granted a pension under the parents-following conditions: (a) If dependent on the soldier, a pension equal to the amount of pre-wardependence or 3s. 6d. a week, whichever is the greater, but not exceeding 15s. a week; or(b) If at any time either or both of the parents is or are wholly or partlyincapable of self-support from age or infirmity, and they are in pecuniary need, a pension of not less than 3s. 6d. and not exceeding 15s. a week; or(c) Whilst no pension or allowance is being paid to or for a ividow, child, ordependant in respect of the soldier, a pension of 7s. 6d. a week, whether or not the conditions under (a) or (b) are fulfilled.(2) (i) A pension under subsection 1 (a) of this Article may be granted on account of each son who has died in the circumstances set forth in Article 11, but the total of the pensions shall not exceed 15s. a week for each surviving parent.(ii) If the amount of pre-war dependence on two or more sons was greater than 15s. a week (or than 30s. a week in the case of two surviving parents), a gratuity not exceeding that under Article 22 (2) may be given, under such conditions as the Minister may determine, in respect of the balance of pre-war dependence not repre-sented in the pension.(Hi) If either parent is in receipt of a pension in respect of a son who has died as an officer, the pension or pensions which may be granted under this Article in respect of other son or sons shall not, together with that pension exceed the pension which has been or could have been awarded to the widow of the officer son under Article 11 (1) or (2) and the second schedule of Our WTarrant of the 1st day of August 1917, or, where there are two parents, 30s. a week if greater.(3) Subject to subsection (2) of this Article, the pension shall be the same whether both parents are concerned or there is only one parent, and on the death of one parent payment may be transferred to the surviving parent, but so that no parent  . receives a pension of more than 15s. a week.(4) A pension shall not be granted or continued to the mother of a soldier under subsection 1 (a) or (c) of this Article if she marries or remarries after his death.(5) The parent (or parents) of a soldier may be awarded a grant as in Article 22 (2) of this Our Warrant in lieu of a pension under subsection 1 (a) if in the opinion of Our Minister of Pensions such grant would be more beneficial to them.(6) The parent (or parents) of a soldier who has died in the circumstances set forth in Article 15 may, if they would have been eligible for a pension had his death taken place in the circumstances set forth in Article 11, be awarded a grant as in Article 22 (2) at the discretion of Our Minister of Pensions.It was agreed that subsection (1) (c), granting a flat rate pension to mothers, should be dropped, but that a proposal to grant an enlistment pension based on the period which elapsed between the date on which a deceased soldier enlisted and that on which he would have been called up under the Military Service Acts should be further considered by Sir Robert Chalmers and Sir Matthew Nathan. (After consideration the proposal was dropped.)The proposals under (2) were agreed to, it being pointed out that (2) (Hi) was a limitation considered necessary by the War Office.(3)  and (4) as proposed were agreed to.(5) was to be omitted.(6) was agreed to.22. (1) Any dependant of a soldier who has died in the circumstances set Tee^f00nr&quot;^d forth in Article 11, not coming under Articles 18, 19, 20, or 21 of this Our Warrant, gratuities to[366] &quot; D daS:.depea&quot;
but in respect of whom separation allowance has been paid, or who was eligible for such allowance, may, provided he or she is wholly or partially incapable of self-support and in pecuniary need, be granted a pension equal to the amount of pre-war dependence but not exceeding 15s. a week, so long as the incapacity continues. If it ceases, a terminal gratuity may be given not exceeding the amount of 26 weeks&quot; pension, or the balance of such gratuity as might have been issued under the follow -ing subsection, if there has been no incapacity, whichever is the greater.On the death of a dependant pensioned under this subsection payment may be transferred to a surviving dependant at such rate and under such conditions as Our Minister of Pensions may determine.(2) Any dependant of a soldier who has died in the circumstances set forth in Article 11, but not including a woman who has lived with a soldier as his wife, ma v. if not entitled to a pension under the preceding Articles, receive a grant by way of gratuity or weekly payment, not exceeding in all a year&apos;s pay of the deceased soldier, or a year&apos;s allowance at the rate at v\7hich separation allowance and allotment were last paid or payable, ivhichever is greater, to be awarded at the discretion of Our Minister of Pensions.[3) Any dependant of a soldier who has died in the circumstances set forth in Article 11 may be granted,, under such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine, an allowance not exceeding 12s. 6cl. a week for a period not ordinarily exceeding 13 weeks whilst undergoing any course of instruction which in the opinion of the Minister of Pensions will be advantageous to such dependant. Where an allowance is granted under this subsection any fees for training, for which pension is not otherwise made, may be paid subject to such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine.It was agreed that the dependant&apos;s pension might be equal to the amount of pre-war dependence, but not exceeding 13s. 9d. a week. The proposal that on the death of a dependant pensioned under this subsection payment might be transferred to a surviving dependant was abandoned.. Section (3) providing for the training of dependants wras abandoned.23.. Any pension granted to a widow or to the separated wife or to a female dependant of a soldier under Articles 15, 17, 19, 20, 21, and 22 of this Our Warrant shall cease on her marriage or re-marriage, and she may then be given a gratuity not exceeding 26 weeks of that pension subject to such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determine. Allowances for children under Articles 15, 19, and 20 may be paid after marriage or re-marriage.No change is now necessary in this Article, i.e., the italicised words and figures should be omitted.Part III.-GENERAL PROVISIONS.24. In this Our Warrant, unless the context otherwise requires (1) &quot;Soldier &quot; means a soldier as defined in the Army Act, who has been enlisted or entered into service in any portion of the Regular Army, the Special Reserve, or the Territorial Force ordinarily maintained by enlistment in the United Kingdom.It also covers all troops raised within or without the United King-dom, whose terms of service included, or have, under due authority, been made to include, the pension provisions for the time being for British troops, if such provisions are a charge on British revenues. But it does not include soldiers who have been merely attested and passed to the Reserve, or members of the Volunteer Force, or any other persons, unless and until they actually served as soldiers in circum-stances to which the pension rights of the Regular Army normally, or under their conditions of service, attach.(2) &quot; Widow &quot; means the widow of any soldier as defined above, but shall not include a widow whose marriage took place after the end of the war, or after the discharge of the soldier, or if during the service of the soldier after the receipt of the wound or injury which caused his death, or after removal from duty on account of the contraction (if contracted during the war) or aggravation of the disease which caused his death, or a widow who was separated from her husband at the time of his death.
78(3) &quot; Child &quot; means the child of any soldier as defined above, born before or ChM-within nine months after the soldier&apos;s discharge, and may include any child regularly maintained by such soldier at the commencement of the war or at the date of his enlistment, whichever was the later, but shall not include the child of a wife or widow who was married to the soldier after the end of the war, or after his discharge, or after the receipt of the wound or injury which caused his death, or after removal from duty on account of the contraction (if contracted during the war) or the aggravation of the disease which caused his death.(4) &quot;Parent &quot; includes a grandparent or other person who has been in the Parent, place of a parent to a soldier, and has wholly supported him for not less than one year at some time before the commencement of the war.(5) &quot; Dependant &quot; means any person (other than a widow or child as defined DePendant-above) who is found as a fact to have been wholly or mainly or in part dependent upon a soldier for a reasonable period immediately before the commencement of the war, or before enlistment if subsequent to the commencement of the war, and up to the death of the soldier, unless he shall have been prevented prom contributing by circum-stances beyond his control. &quot;Dependent&quot; means so dependent as aforesaid.The alteration of the definition of &quot; Dependant &quot; was to be further discussed by Sir Robert Chalmers and Sir Matthew Nathan, and was subsequently agreed. (6) &quot; Pre-War Earnings &quot; means the average weekly earnings of a soldier Pre-war during the 12 months preceding the commencement of the war, and, so eimii&quot;gs-far as regards a man who was in employment before the war, shall be computed generally in the same manner as for the purposes of the Workmen&apos;s Compensation Act, 1906.   In the case of a man in a trade, business or profession, the average profits of the last three years preceding the commencement of the war shall be taken, or of such lesser period as he engaged therein.In the calculation of the pension payable to or on account of a soldier, who at the commencement of the war was serving and had served not less than one year as an apprentice in any recognised trade, the standard rate of wages of that trade in the district at the time of the commencement of the war may be substituted for pre-war earn-ings, provided enlistment took place before the age of 26, and that the man is by reason of his disablement incapable of completing his apprenticeship.In the calculation of the pension payable to or on account of a soldier who for the purpose of qualifying for any profession or employ -ment had, after the age of 16, attended regularly any school, college, university or hospital, or had been articled in accordance with the recognised practice of any profession, an amount equivalent to what would have been the soldier&apos;s disablement pension for the highest degree of disablement, with an addition of os. for each completed year of such attendance or &quot; articles &quot; before the age of 23, may be substi-tuted for pre-war earnings, up to a maximum of 50s. a week, provided enlistment took place before the age of 26 and the man is by reason of his disablement incapable of qualifying for such profession or employ-ment.(7) &quot;Pre-war Dependence &quot; means the amount, expressed as a weekly or Pre-warannual sum, representing the value of the support afforded to, or of dePendence-benefits conferred upon, a dependant by a soldier for a reasonable period immediately preceding the commencement of the war (or entry into service or enlistment, if subsequent to the commencement of the war), exclusive, however, of any increase thereof due to circumstances arising out of the war, in the case of entry into service or enlistment subsequent to the commencement of the war, and shall include the following: (a) Amount regularly contributed by the man if he received no material benefits in return therefor.(b) Amount regularly contributed by the man in excess of expenditure incurred on his account.(c) Money value of any benefit conferred upon, the dependant by the man.[366]v.
Certified.Discharge.(8) &quot; Certified&quot; means, in respect of any medical certification, certified by a medical officer or Board of Medical Officers appointed for the purpose by the Army Council or by the Minister of Pensions.(9) &quot;Discharge&quot; includes transfer to Class P. or P. (T) of the Army Reserve.retold hi  ^e Provisions enumerated in the  Second Schedule to this Ouroperation. Warrant, of Our Warrant for the Pay, &amp;c, of the Army, 1914, and of the subse-quent Warrants specified, shall remain in force as regards pensions and grants on account of disablement or decease, except as modified herein, or therein, and by the substitution, so far as these pensions and grants are concerned, of Our Minister of Pensions for Our Army Council and for Our Commissioners of Chelsea Hospital.(2) The provisions of Our Warrants for the Pay, &amp;c, of the Army, 1914, and of any of Our subsequent Warrants dealing with the disability pensions and with ^ wifch the pensions to the families and dependants of other soldiers than those dealt with in this Our Warrant shall remain in force pending the issue by us of any new Warrant in the matter, and nothing in this Our Warrant shall be held to affect the existing Warrants or Regulations in regard to service pensions or other grants the administration of which continues to be vested in our Army Council or in our Commissioners of Chelsea Hospital.Prevision for soldiers and their familiesm this Warrant.
7*fFIRST SCHEDULE.Pensions that may be Granted for Specific Injuries.Specific Injury.Propor-tion eorre-spondingto Degreeof Disable-ment.Disablement Pensions.If not entitled to a Service Pension.Warrant Officer, Class i.jPer cent1 i Loss of two or more limbs j    100 Loss of an arm and an eye. ; Loss of a leg* and an eye. Loss of both hands or ofall fingers and thumbs. Loss of botli feet. Loss of a hand a- d a foot Total loss of sight Total paralysis, j Lunacy. Wounds,     injuries,     or disease resulting in dis-abled  man being per-manentiy bedridden. Wounds of, or injuries to, internal, thoracic, or ab-dominal organs, involv-ing total permanent dis-abling effects. Wounds of, or injuries to, head or brain involving total permanent disabling effects,  or   Jacksonian epilepsy. Very  severe  facial  dis-figurement. Advarcad   cases  of  in-curable disease. Amputation of right arm atshoulder joint. Amputation of leg at hip or left arm at shoulder joint.Severe   facial   disfigure-ment. Total loss of speech. Short thigh amputation of leg with pelvic band, or of right arm above or through elbow. Total deafness. Amputation of leg above knee (other than 3), and through knee or of left arm above or through eibow, or of right arm below elbow. Amputation of leg below knee (including Symes&apos; and Ohopart&apos;s amputa-tion), or of  left arm below elbow. Loss of vision of one eye. Loss of thumb or of fourhngers of right hand Loss of thumb or of four fingers of left hand, or of three fingers of. right hand.Loss of two fingers of either hand.5. d. 42   690SO70GO5040302034   029   921   317   012   98   6Warrant Officer.Class II, or N.O Officer, Class I.N.O. Officer, Class IIs. d. 37   Cs.   d.35   033  930   02625   6   I 22   G18   915   01131   628   024   621   017   614 0 10   67   6   17   0NO        N.C. &apos; Officer,  i Officer, Class III. ! Class IV.s. d. 32   62926   022   919   G16   313   09   9G   6s.   d.30   027  024   021   018   015   012 0 9   0G   0	Private,Warrant	&amp;c.or N.C.	(Class V),Officers	irrespec-entitled	tive ofto	ServiceService	PensionPensions.	to which	entitled.s.   d.	s.   d27   6	27   622   019   316   613   911   024  9   j 24  922   019   316   613   911   08   3* The proposed alterations were agreed to. Note. In the case of left-handed men, certified to be such, the compensation in respect of the left arm, hand, &amp;c, will be the same as for a right arm, hand, &amp;c.
\SECOND SCHEDULE.Provisions of previous Warrants remaining in Force.Description of Warrant.	Article.	Subject.Royal Warrant for the Pay, Ap-pointment, Promotions, and non-Effective Pay of the Army, 1914.	2 4 7 8 22 777 779a	Reserved rights to pensions. Soldiers&apos; pensions. Claims not preferred within 12 months. Stoppages. Public claims. Special pensions for Warrant Officers when not provided for in Regulations. Pensions of Warrant Officers ordinarily payable quarterlylloyal Warrant of the 28th January, 1915.Eoyal Warrant of the 4th November, 1915.780781 1,134 1,195 1,198 1,201 1,202 1,206\1,207/ 1,2081,209 1,210 1,211 1,212 1,218 1,214 1,215 1,245(6)1,246 1,297in advance.Pensions of Warrant Officers governed by rules for N.C.0&apos;s. and men.Commutation of Warrant Officers&apos; pensions. Classification for pension.Gratuities to men of First Class Army Reserve. Medical report necessary for disablement pension. Special grants not provided for in Regulations. Selection for most beneficial pension.Pensions payable weekly.Grounds for forfeiture.Neglect to draw pension.Pensioner quitting British dominions.Pensioner or family obtaining parish relief.Pensioner becoming insane,In-pensioner to Chelsea or Kilmainham Hospital.Restoration of forfeited pension.Commutation of pension.Widow or family obtaining&apos; parish relief, provided that where a widow is undergoing treatment in a poor law institv-tion any pension or allowance which may have been granted to her shall not be paid to her, but shall be administered on behalf of herself and her children wider such conditions as the Minister of Pensions may determinedDate of commencement of widow&apos;? pension, &amp;c.Man unfit on mobilisation.Warrant Officer, Class II, Classification.Proviso as to soldiers who have completed 18 years&apos; servicedThe proposed alterations were agreed to.O

</content>
</cab>
