<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/5/0 images: 153-154</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.j...&quot; &apos;/&quot; Printed for the War Cabinet.   May 1918.SECRET.G.-206. ...WAR  CABINET.THE POSITION OF THE NORTHERN NEUTRAL COUNTRIES.Holland.(Previous papers, G.-.153, 184, and 186.)IN accordance with the instructions in War Cabinet 400, Minute 12, I assembled this afternoon the Northern Neutrals Committee to enquire into the action that should be taken in view of the German demands on Holland.2. With reference to the Report of the Committee as set out in paper G.-1S6, it appears that no action was taken with regard to paragraphs 3 and 4 of the recommendations then made by the Committee, i.e. (a) to further the negotiations with the Dutch authorities ; (b) to supply them with certain munitions ; and (c) to acquaint them that we would send a mixed force to support them in defending Walcheren against the Germans.3. Since that Report was rendered to the War Cabinet in December last, it appears that the troops that were to form the mixed force have mostly been sent to France, and consequently no assistance is now available in that respect.4. It appears that the opinion of the General Staff is that, in the event of the Germans putting inadmissible demands upon the Dutch, we should encourage them to resist the demands even to the extent of going to war with Germany, the reason being that this would tend to divert from the Western front some portion of the German army. As, however, the trained Dutch army consists of only four divisions, this diversion would be comparatively small to begin with.5. The Admiralty view is that the Scheldt would offer a much better base for submarines than Zeebrugge and Ostend, and would, moreover, enable the Germans to station at the former light cruisers and big destroyers, and that for this, as well as other reasons, we should do everything within reasonable limits to prevent war between Holland and Germany, especially as the sudden occupation of the Scheldt by the Germans would be a comparatively easy affair. The great importance of Walcheren in regard to the German use of the Scheldt was emphasised, and it was pointed out that even if the Germans seized the Scheldt, but we held Walcheren, it would be possible for us to maintain a minefield at the mouth of the Scheldt, and thus deny the enemy ingress and egress. It was also agreed that the wiser policy for us was not to appear to agree to the illegal demands of the Germans, but rather in the last resort to let them coerce the Dutch. If the Dutch were thus forced to make unneutral concessions to the Germans, we would be in a position to claim concessions, and inter alia, use Dutch territorial waters or air bases when occasion might arise.6. With regard to the existing demands of the Germans, the Committee were of opinion that the British Government should not adopt too uncompromising an attitude towards the Dutch as regards the sand and gravel question, but endeavour to keep them to their proposal to appoint a Commission to visit Belgium in this connection. With regard to the use of the Limburg railway for the conveyance of goods of a purely non-military character, the Committee were of opinion that no objection should be raised to this concession on the part of the Dutch, though it was realised.-that the Germans would probably also endeavour to send militant goods over this railway. As to the new condition, namely the free passage of German and Austrian ships at Antwerp down the Scheldt, the Committee were of opinion that the British Government should press the Dutch Cabinet in the strongest terms not to accede to this German demand,, which was probably only the first step in still larger demands in connection with the Scheldt.   Mr. Balfour and Lord Robert Cecil undertook to draft a telegram
to the British Minister at The Hague in the above sense and show it to the Prime Minister before transmission.   (Copy attached).7. The Committee were of opinion that we should point out to the Dutch the action that the Germans were likely to take in regard to the Scheldt, and the necessity of adequately defending Walcheren and other points. It was highly desirable, if a force could be re-collected at a future date, that we should re-open the question of the occupation of Walcheren by us in certain eventualities as, quite apart from giving us control of the Scheldt, it would be of great advantage to us to obtain air bases there or in Holland with a view to bombing German munitions establishments, &amp;c, on the other side of the Rhine.8. With a view to encouraging the Dutch, who have no aircraft or air defences for their large towns against German attacks, the Committee recommend that we should be prepared to supply the Dutch with aeroplanes, pilots, and anti-aircraft guns, and also, as far as possible, with the munitions, &amp;c, enumerated in (B) on page 1 of paper G.-186, and that our readiness to assist them with these supplies in case of trouble with the Germans should be confidentially communicated to them through the same channel as before.(Signed;      J. C. SMUTS.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W., April 26, 1918.Paraphrase of a telegram, No. 933, sent by the Foreign Office to the British Ministerat The Hague on April 26, 1918.WITH reference to your telegram No. 1022, His Majesty&apos;s Government do not desire to make any formal objection. to the railway transit of non-military goods, and are glad that you have called the attention of the Minister for Foreign Affairs to the fact that the difficulty of distinguishing between goods of a military and n on-military character in transit over the Limburg railways will be very great.As regards the sand and gravel question, His Majesty&apos;s Government cannot in any way admit that it is legitimate for the Netherlands Government to permit the conveyance over Dutch water-ways of any sand and gravel intended for military purposes. His Majesty&apos;s Government understand that the Netherlands Government do not admit transit claims of this nature, and if the Netherlands Government were to weaken in their previous attitude on this question and were to permit the transit of further quantities of sand and gravel without taking those precautions as to their use, which the Netherlands Government had itself thought necessary, namely, the further inspection by Dutch officers which His Majesty&apos;s Government understand is a condition precedent to the permission of any such transit, the latter will deeply regret it, and you should communicate with M. London in this sense.I may say for your information, provided that the amount of sand and gravel to be transmitted does not exceed the quantity mentioned in your telegram under reply, His Majesty&apos;s Government do not desire to put pressure on the Netherlands Government to take action on this question which would lead to a rupture of relations between Holland and Germany.The position is, however, different with regard to the passage of German and Austrian vessels down the Scheldt. His Majesty&apos;s Government, quite apart from the fact, that the Netherlands Government appear to have given a perfectly definite undertaking on the loth September, 1914, that no such vessel should be allowed, would regard with the greatest concern any utilisation of the mouth of the Scheldt by the Germans, as such a use, however limited it might be at first, would undoubtedly be extended until Antwerp was for all purposes converted into a belligerent port.His Majesty&apos;s Government are advised that it would almost certainly lead to the occupation of Cadsand and Walcheren by Germany, which eventuality they could not regard with indifference, consequently any concession by Holland to German demands for the vise of the Scheldt would not be looked upon by us as consistent with Dutch neutrality.These poiuts should be put before the Netherlands Government very clearly, and their urgent attention should be drawn to the necessity for protecting Walcheren from a coup de main by the German forces, \vhich, unless precautions are taken in good time, might take place with great rapidity. You should, if possible, act with your French, and American colleagues in this matter.(Repeated to Washington and Paris.)o

</content>
</cab>
