<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/5/0 images: 155-161</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
EPiis Document is the Property--of His Britannic Majestyss Government]Printed for the War Cabinet.   May 1918.SECRET. G.-2G7.SOLDIERS&apos; AND SAILORS&apos; PAY COMMITTEE.Fifth and Supplementary Report.(Previous Papers G.-154, G.-L72, G.-18S, G.-193, and War Cabinet 23*5 (13), 2S0 (11),ol520(8), 349 (10), and 364 (13)).Equalisation of Navy and Army Separation Allowances.1. IN this Fifth and Supplementary Report the Committee deals with the question of the equalisation of Navy and Army Separation Allowances, which was raised by Mr. Butcher, M.P., and Colonel Leslie Wilson, M.P., in the House of Commons of the 5th March, 1918, in the course of the debate upon the Navy Estimates, and in accord-ance with a suggestion then put forward by the Financial Secretary of the Admiralty the Soldiers&apos; and Sailors&apos; Pay Committee was reassembled to consider the subject, approval of this course being given in a Minute of the War Cabinet, dated the 12th idem, No. 13.2. The Committee have held three meetings and now submit the following report. 3. In order that the position which has arisen may be made clear it is desirable to recite the following facts : -(a.) Army Separation Allowance at rates much lower than those now in force was in existence for many years prior to the war, while Navy Separation Allow-ance is a new grant instituted since the outbreak of the war with effect from the 1st October, 1914.(6.) Navy Separation Allowance was deliberately granted at rates lower than Army Separation Allowance because of the greater opportunities for advancement and for earning additional emoluments open to sailors than the soldiers.(c.) Both Navy and Army Separation Allowances have been increased since October 1914, but the differentiation between the two scales has always been maintained for the reasons indicated.4. The possibility of hardship arising in a limited number of cases from the lower rates of Navy Separation Allowance has long been recognised. Under a regulation issued by the late War Pensions Statutory Committee, Local Committees have power to grant supplementary Separation Allowances to the families and dependants of Naval ratings in receipt of the lowest rates of pay, where they are satisfied that such grants are necessary to maintain the pre-war or pre-entry standard of comfort. There is reason to believe, however, that relatively fewT grants have been made under this regulation.5. The Admiralty do not advocate the levelling up of Navy Separation Allowances to the standard of Army Separation Allowances for the reasons already given. The War Office representative on the Committee has, moreover, urged that any increase in the rates of Navy Separation Allowance, which had the effect of placing all Naval ratings with dependants, regardless of their pay, in a still more favourable position as compared with soldiers, would inevitably result in a strong demand for an increase either in pay or in Separation Allowance by soldiers with dependants. The Committee concur in the view of the Admiralty that a general raising of Navy Separation Allowance rates is unnecessary and in the view of the War Office that any such general rise would involve a serious reaction in the Army.6. It appears to the Committee, however, that, while the original reasons for nxmg Navy Separation Allowance were sound, inasmuch as sailors of any given rating were always better paid than the soldiers who could be considered to be &quot;of more or less !439j B
corresponding rank or rating, the position has since been modified by the concessions in the matter of pay and allotment sanctioned with effect from the beginning of October last.7. Before that date the lowest paid soldier was the Private of Infantry in receipt of 7s. a week, while the lowest paid sailor was the Ordinary Seaman in receipt of 8s. (Jd. a week. The former had to allot 3-s. 6Y/. to his wife and the latter 5s. in order to obtain Separation Allowance. The effect of the concessions then granted was to increase the pay of the soldier to 10s. Qd. a week, and to relieve him entirely of his allotment, while the pay of the Ordinary Seaman was left unchanged and his allotment reduced from 5s. to Is. Qd. It will be seen, therefore, that the Ordinary Seaman is now not only at a disadvantage in the matter of pay as compared with the Private in the Army, but that he has to allot from his pay in order to obtain Separation Allowance, while the soldier need not do so. Other instances of ordinary ratings in Branches of the Navy, other than the Seaman Branch, could be adduced in which the pay of the rating and the Separation Allowance of his dependants are now both lower than the corresponding pay and Separation Allowance of the Private in the Army and his dependants. Prior to October 1917, the difference in Separation Allowance in favour of the soldier was always, in a measure at any rate, offset by a difference of pay in favour of the sailor.8. It is for the benefit of these ratings, and also of those whose pay only slightly exceeds that of a Private in the Army, and who consequently cannot declare, or are only able at considerable personal sacrifice to declare an allotment to their dependants, which when added to Navy Separation Allowance and Allotment concession will make a weekly payment equal to that provided by the State for dependants of the soldier, that some remedy is necessary.0. Except, however, as regards sailors holding the rating of Ordinary Seaman or A.B. or any equivalent rating in Branches of the Navy, other than the Seaman Branch, and as regards Marines holding the rank of Private or any equivalent rank, the Committee are satisfied that no adjustment of existing Navy Separation Allowance rates is required.10. Apart from non-substantive pay and other additional earnings, the range of pay of ratings in the Navy equivalent to Ordinary Seaman or A.B. is from 8s. Qd. to 27s. od. a week. Bearing in mind that the pay of the Private of Infantry is only 10s. Qd., it is clear that a great many of the Naval ratings included in the classes specified will not require additional assistance for their families, to put them on an equality with the Army. It is impossible, therefore, to include all Ordinary Seamen, A.B.&apos;s, and equivalent ratings within the scope of any scheme providing for supplementary allowances.11. On grounds of administrative simplicity the Committee would have preferred, if practicable, to divide these ratings into two classes, namely, those who by reason of their low pay required a further grant from the State for their families or dependants, and those who by reason of their higher emoluments did not require such a grant. The evidence adduced by the Admiralty, however, satisfied them that this was impracticable, because(a) of the impossibility of dividing them into two classes, in one of which the ratings would in all cases and in all stages of their career in the particular rating be more poorly paid than the ratings included in the other class ; and(6) of the difficulty arising on promotion of individual ratings when the gain in pay might be insufficient to compensate for the withdrawal of the supplementary allowance.The force of these arguments will be evident when it is stated that the maximum pay (including non-substantive pay, allowances, &amp;c.) of a particular rating may exceed the minimum pay of the same rating by something approaching cent, per cent.12. Failure to obviate these two difficulties would inevitably result in a strong demand for an extension of the system of supplementary allowances to the more highly paid ratings of the Navy, and this in turn would give rise to a similar demand by the soldier with dependants for higher pay or for higher allowances for his family..13. These considerations have led the Committee to the conclusion that, in spite of the greater administrative difficulties eutailed, the only satisfactory solution is to be found in requiring the sailor who desires a supplementary allowance for his family or dependants to contribute to their support in proportion to his pay. In other words, the actual pay, including non-substantive pay, &amp;c, of the sailor, rather than his rating,
should he the factor determining both the necessity for, and the amount of, any supplementary allowance to be granted.14. Bearing in mind that the Private of Infantry is now paid at the rate of 10s. M. a week, out of which he need not make any provision for his family^ or dependants unless of his own free will, the Committee consider that the Naval rating or Marine rank who desires a supplementary allowance to be granted to his family or dependants should be required to allot the surplus, if any, of his actual emoluments over 10s. M. as a condition of the grant, and that the supplementary allowance granted should be reduced or withdrawn whenever his emoluments increase, and thus enable him to increase his allotment without reducing the balance available for his personal use below 10s. Qd. a week. No such stipulation would be made in the case of any rating not requiring a supplementary allowance.15. The amount of the supplementary allowance should in all those cases which it is now proposed to endeavour to meet be such weekly sum as, when added to the allotment to be required of the sailor or marine under the conditions just stated, and to the actual sum in course of payment to his family or dependants as Navy Separation Allowance and Allotment concession, will make a weekly provision for his family or dependants equal to that made by the State for the family or dependants of a Private in the Army. In other words, the provision for the families and dependants of the lower paid ranks and ratings of the Navy, Marines, and Naval Reserve Forces now under consideration should be brought up to the level of the Army Separation Allowance and State Allotment issued to the family or dependants of a Private in the Army, but the sailor or marine should be required to contribute towards this provision from his pay a sum approximately equal to the surplus of his earnings over 10*. tid. a week, the recognised minimum pay in the Army. As in the case of the soldier, so in the case of the sailor and marine, any excess allotment declared should be paid to his famity or dependants, and not in any way affect the total grants payable by the State by way of Separation Allowance and State Allotment in the case of the Army, and by way of Separation Allowance and Allotment concession and supplementary allowance in the case of the Navy and Marines.16. The Committee further considered.the question whether the proposed supple-mentary allowances should be granted as hitherto by the Local Committees constituted under the Naval and Military War Pensions Act,&quot; 1915, or by the Admiralty. Payment by Local Committees has certain advantages. It would obviate ail possibility of confusion between these supplementary allowances and the ordinary scale of Navy-Separation Allowance, and would relieve the Admiralty, the duties of which in relation to Separation Allowance are already extremely onerous, of a material amount of additional and somewhat complicated work. It is, however, in the opinion of the Committee open to one vital objection, namely, that, rightly or wrongly, the wives and dependants of men in the forces regard supplementary allowances issued by Local Committees as partaking of the character of charity. They accordingly consider it essential to the success of their proposals that the work should be entrusted to the Admiralty, and the grants made on application by the men.17. Adoption of this course wall necessitate cancellation of the regulation issued by the late War Pensions Statutory Committee and referred to in paragraph 4 above. All allowances granted thereunder should be withdrawn as from a date to be settled by the Admiralty and Ministry of Pensions, and the&apos; opportunity should be taken to prevent the possibility of overlapping between the supplementary Separation Allowances recommended in this report, and any other supplementary Separation Allowances payable under the regulations of the Special Grants Committee acting under the Ministry of Pensions.18. Three tables are annexed to illustrate the operation of existing Navy and Army Separation Allowances, and the amount of the supplementary allowances which will be payable to wives and other dependants of Seamen and Marines if the foregoing recommendations be approved.19. It is estimated that the cost of the proposals will not exceed 350,000L a year, inclusive of about 6,000L for additional staff at the Admiralty, and that the supple-mentary allowances may be distributed among the families of approximately 50,000 ranks and ratings.20. The Committee summarise their recommendations as follows : (a.) That supplementary Separation Allowances should be granted to the wives and dependants of certain sailors and marines holding the rating or rank of Ordinary Seaman, A.B., Private, or any relative rating or rank in other branches of the Navy, Marines, and Reserve Forcees (paragraphs 8 and 9).
(6.) That the sailors or marines whose families are to receive supplementary allowances should declare allotments reasonably proportionate to their pay, i.e., they should allot approximately the surplus, if any, of their actual pay. including non-substantive pay over 10s. Gd. a week, and that such supplementary allowances should be reduced or withdrawn when the emoluments of the sailors and marines concerned admit of their increasing their allotments without reducing the balance available for their personal expenditure below 10s. Gd. a week (paragraph 14).(c.) That the amount of the supplementary allowance should be in each case such weekly sum as when added to the allotment to be required of the sailor or marine under (6), and the actual sum granted to his family or dependants as Navy Separation Allowance and Allotment concession will equal the sum payable as Army Separation Allowance and State Allotment to the family or dependants of a Private in the Army (paragraph 15).(d.) That such supplementary allowances should be granted by the Admiralty on application by the men concerned subject to the fulfilment of the foregoing conditions (paragraph 16).(e.) That the existing regulation 7 (1) (g) of the Regulations, Part II, issued by the late War Pensions Statutory Committee, under which similar grants are made by Local Committees, subject, however, to more serious restrictions and conditions, should be cancelled, and all grants payable thereunder withdrawn as from a date to be settled by the Admiralty acting in conjunction with the Ministry of Pensions (paragraph 17).(/.) That the Admiralty and Ministry of Pensions should take such steps, if any, as may be necessary to prevent overlapping between the supplementary separation allowances hereby granted and other supplementary separation allowances issuable under regulations sanctioned by the Special Grants Committee of the Ministry of Pensions (paragraph 1.7).EDWARD CARSON.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W., May 7, 1918.
COi__iComparison of the Combined Emoluments of (]),a Soldier and Wife, (2) a Sailor and Wife.		Army.			:Navy.			Allowance	Navy.			Allowance	Navy.			Allowance													Able Seaman over 3 years 			sNumber in&apos; Family.		Standard Rate for Private Soldier.			Ordina^ Seaman. (Pay, 8s. dd. a week.)			upplementary	Able Seaman without &quot; B.&quot; ?&apos; G,&quot; or &quot; T &quot; Pay. (Pay, 12s. lOd. a week.)			u a CD a CD &quot;5. Oh 0	Pay S. G. G. li.3 Badge R. P.		tf.     u.. 14   7 1   9 1   2 0   7 1   2	ipplementary								CO				co			19   3	w CO		Drawn by Man.	Drawn by Wife.	Total per Week.	Drawn by Man.	Drawn by Wife.	Total per -Week.	Amount o to Wife	Drawn. by -Man.	Drawn &apos;    by Wife.	Total per Week.	Amount, o: to Wife.	Draw n by Man.	Drawn by Wife.	Total per Week.	Amount, of to Wife.Wife            ....		5.   d. 10   6	s.  d. 12   6*	a   d. 28   0	*.   d. r 3	s.   d. 11   Of	s.   d. 18   3	s.   d. 1   6	s.   d. 10 10	s.   d. 11   6J	s.   d. 22   4	.s.   d. 1   0	s.   d. 15   3.	s.   d. 12   6S	s.   d. 28   9	Wife and one child		10   6	19   6*	30   0	7   3	17   Of	24   3	2   6	.10 10	17   6J	28   4	2   0	15   3	19   6H	34   9	Wife and two children..		10   6	24   6*	35   0	7   3	21   6f	28  -9	3   0	10 10	22   0J	32 10	.2   6	14   9	24   61	39   3,	Nil* All paid by the State.t Includes Is. 6d. allotment; balance paid by the State.4,. 64     ,,      ,, -     ;; -
Comparison of the Combined Emoluments of (1) a Soldier and Dependants, (2) a Sailor and Dependants where the Sailor is a ContinuousService Rating.Note. For the purpose of this Table it has been assumed that the dependence is 12s.. Qd. where there is one dependant, 17s. Qd. where there are two,and 21s. where there are three.Number of Dependants.One dependant Two dependants Three dependantsArmy.Standard Kate for Private Soldier.Drawn    Drawn by    I by De-Man.   I pendant.Total.s. d.10 610 610 6s.   d.17   6*Navy.Ordinary Seaman. (Pay, 8s. lJd. a week.)DrawnbyMan.Drawn by De-pendant.s.	d.	s.	d.	s.	d.	s.	d.23	0	7	3	7	6f	14	928	0	7	n O	7	6f	14	931	6	7	CO	7	6t	14	9Total.o a a&amp; maCD &amp;&amp;   .3  rtM so sgo2 0 aNavy.Able Seaman without &quot; B,&quot; &quot; G-,&quot; or &quot; T &quot; Pay. (Pay, 12s. lOd. a week.)DrawnbyMan.Drawn by De-pendant.Total.s. d.5 010 013 GCOo PIo3oap COTilO CO ST 3 I-&apos;2 oaN avy.Able Seaman over 3 yrs.  s.Pay .. .. 14 7 S. G. .19 G. L. 3 , . . . 1 2 Badge .. .. 0 7 II. P.....12Drawnby Man.Drawn by De-pendant.19   3Total.COop.Oce aCOco  ,&quot;&amp;I &amp;     -c Sgo a ^s.		s.	d.	s.				s.	d.	s.	d.	- s.	d.&apos;	s.10	10	8	n	19	4	4	0	14	n O	13	OS	27	8	Nil10	10	8	6J	19	4	9	0	11	Q o	17	611	28	9	Nit10	10	8	61	19	4	12	6	to	9	18	Oil	28	9	3   0* All paid by the State.t Includes Is. M. allotment; balance paid by the State. t      ,,     2s. S      &quot;      5s.n5) IJs. fid.it )J
Comparison of Combined Emoluments of (1) a Soldier and Dependants, (2) a Sailor and Dependants where the Sailor is a Reservist or entry forHostilities only.Note. For the purpose of this Table it has been assumed that the dependence is 12s. Qd. where there is one dependant, 17s. Qd. where thereare two, and 21s. where there are three.&apos;	Army.			Navy.			Amount of Supplementary Allowance to Dependant.	Navy.			03 O s	Navy.			Amount of Supplementary Allowance to Dependant.Number of Dependants.	Standard Kate for Private Soldier.			Ordinary Seaman. (Pay, 85. 9d. a week.)				Able Seaman without &quot; B,&quot; &quot; Gf,&quot; or &quot; T &quot; Pay. (Pay, 12s. lOd. a week.)			Amount of Supplementary Allov, to Dependant.	Able Seaman over 3 years  s.   d. Pay     ..       ..  14   7 S. Gr.....19 Gr. L. 3 ..       ..    12 Badge ..       ..    0   7 R. P.....12 19   3				Drawn by Man.	Drawn by Dp-pendant.	Total.	Drawn by Man.	Drawn by De-pendant.	Total.		Drawn by Man.	Drawn by De-pendant.	Total.		Drawn by Man.	Drawn by De-pendant.	Total.	One dependant	s.  d. 10   G	s. d. 12   6*	s. d. 23   0	s.  d. 7   3	s.   d. 10   Of	s.  d. 17   3	,s.  d. 2   6	s. d. 10 10	s.  d. 11 ot	s. d. 21 10	s.  d. 1   6	s.  d. 16   3	s,  d. 12   65	s.  d. 28   9	s.  d. NilTwo dependants	10   6	17   6*	28   0	7   3	10 ot	17   3	7   6	10 10	11 01	21 10	6   6	13   9	18   OH	31   9	NilThree dependants	10   6	21   0*	31   6	7   3	10   Of	17   3	11   0	10 10	11 ot	21 10	10   0	12   3	21   01	33   3	Nil* All paid by the State.f Includes Is. 6d. allotment; balance paid by the State.I &quot;      2s. ,f 3             3a.II .) 5s. 6d. ,, T     &quot;      7** ,,

</content>
</cab>
