<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/5/0 images: 213-215</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is&quot;&apos;the7Property:of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government]Printed for the War Cabinet.   June 1918.SECRET. G.-213.GOVERNMENT ESTABLISHMENTS AND THE WHITLEY REPORT.I CIRCULATE to the War Cabinet a memorandum prepared in the Treasury for submission to the War Cabinet.(Signed) A. BONAR LAW.June 21, 1918.There have been a number of questions in the House of Commons asking whether it is the intention of His Majesty&apos;s Government to put the recommendations of the &quot;Whitley Report&quot; into force in Government Departments. There have also been many references to the subject in the Labour papers and in the press generally.The recommendations of the WThitley Committee (Interim Report on Joint Standing Industrial Councils, Cd. 8606) were directed towards attaining the two objects defined in the terms.of reference to the Committee, which were as follows: &quot; (1.) To make and consider suggestions for securing a permanent improve-ment in the relations between employers and workmen.&quot; (2.) To recommend means for securing that industrial conditions affect-ing the relations between employers and workmen shall be systematically reviewed by those concerned with a view to improving conditions in the future.&quot;The Committee decided first to address themselves to the problem of establishing permanently improved relations between employers and employed in the main industries of the country, in which there exist representative organisations on both sides; and the Interim Report in question accordingly deals more especially with these trades.The Committee recommended (1.) That His Majesty&apos;s Government should propose to the various associations of employers and employed the formation of Joint (National) Industrial Councils in the several industries, where they do not already exist, com-posed of representatives of employers and employed, regard being paid to the various sections of the industry and the various classes of labour engaged.(2.) That the following proposals should be laid before the National Industrial Councils: (a.) That District Councils, representative of the trade unions and of the Employers&apos; Association in the industry, should be created, or developed out of the existing machinery for negotiation in the various trades.(b.) That Works Committees, representative of the management and of the workers employed, should be instituted in particular works to act in close co-operation with the district and national machinery.The Committee contemplated that the functions of Works Committees, District Councils, and National Councils would require to be determined separately in accordance with the varying conditions of different industries, and so would the methods by which the functions of the proposed councils should be correlated to those of joint bodies in the different districts and in the various works within the districts.The sort of subjects which might be dealt with by the National Councils or allocated by them to District Councils or Works Committees are stated in some detail in paragraph 16 of the Interim Report.The possibility of applying the recommendations of this Report with any necessary modifications to Government establishments has, for some time past, been under the consideration of some of the great Departments, who have establishments under them to which, if to any, the application of the recommendations would be
appropriate, and the Departments have been in communication with the Ministry of Labour.It has been recognised that, whatever line be adopted by His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment as to the application of the Report, and whatever forms its application may take in the different Departments in order to meet their varying conditions and requirements, the Government and the Departments should endeavour to secure the greatest possible measure of uniformity as to the main principles by which the Departments should guide themselves in preparing schemes for their respective establishments.After the question had been separately considered by Departments in com-munication with the Ministry of Labour, it was thought desirable to hold a conference at the Treasury, with a view to seeing how far there was general agree-ment between them as to the main principles to be observed.The Financial Secretary to the Treasury presided, and the following, being the principal Departments appearing to be primarily concerned, were represented: Ministry of Labour.Admiralty.War Office..Ministry of Munitions.Post Office.After a useful discussion, it was agreed that the question had reached a stage when the main issues involved might properly be submitted to the War Cabinet for decision.The first question is, naturally, whether the recommendations can be applied at all, even with modifications, to Government establishments, or whether the conditions of Government employment are so different from those of outside industries as to preclude their application to the former.The position of a Government Department is essentially different from that of an organised industry.(a.) The latter comprises a number of employers, who are free to make such bargains as they like with their employees, and pay the cost of them; in a Government Department there is only one employer, i.e., the State, represented by the Minister in charge for the time being, who is subject to the financial control of the Treasury, and is responsible to Parliament.(&amp;.) In private industry, the question of profit and loss is one of the determining factors in the bargains between employers and employed, whereas in State employ-ment it plays little of no part. The great mass of Government work is administra-tive, and not industrial, and there is no question of a profit indeed, it is nearly all conducted at a loss.But, leaving out of account the administrative and clerical staffs, it seems clear that there are many Government establishments, such as (say) the Admiralty Dockyards, the Reyal Arsenals and factories, and certain establishments under the Post Office, e.g., the Engineering Department, where the work is of an industrial character, and performed: under industrial conditions fairly analogous to those obtaining in outside industries.In this latter class of cases, at all events, it is obviously difficult for the Govern-ment to decline to put into operation, as between themselves and their employees, a scheme which they are urging outside employers to adopt, alnd the Chancellor of the Exchequer stated on  he 18th December last, in answer to a question in the House, that the Government fully realised the importance of setting an example in this respect.The first question then is, does the Government accept the principle of applying the recommendations of the Report, with any necessary adaptations, to Government establishments wbere the conditions are sufficiently analogous to th6se subsisting in outside industries to make this course practicable?Assuming the answer to be in the affirmative, the following further questions of principle arise: (1.) As it will be recognised that Public Departments should be administered for the benefit of the public, and the Minister in charge of the particular Dep&quot; artifteht is responsible to Parliament for its being so administered, it id cleacrly of the&apos; first importance that the control of the Minister should riemafo unimpaired.
With, a view to securing this end, it is submitted that the following conditions should be insisted on: (2.) Any Joint Committees to be set up should be purely consultative, and should not be invested with any executive powers. The Minister would be placed in an impossible position if he were bound by a decision in which his subordinates had acquiesced, even though he felt unable to defend it. If his responsibility to Parliament is to be maintained, he must be free to accept or reject the conclusions of any committees, even if they are unanimous. If this position be accepted, no occasion for voting could arise, and there would be no necessity for numerical equality on the two sides. In any case, as the official representatives must vote alike according to their instructions, a vote would be a mere formality; and the Committee would either produce a unanimous report or a pair of divergent recommendations. As a matter of practice a unanimous recommendation would usually be accepted.(3.) Both the Department and the staff should have the right of nominating their own representatives, subject to a reasonable limit of numbers on the part of the staff. In practice, the departmental representatives would not consist of more than two or three, and the Minister should reserve the right to vary them according to the subject under discussion.(4.) The Committees should not be free to discuss questions of management or policy, e.g., in the case of the Post Office, such a subject as the revision of postage rates, &amp;c. It is submitted that their scope should be strictly limited to matters which directly affect the conditions of service of the staff.(5.) It would probably be necessary to allow the Committee to discuss questions of wages, although in more important cases such discussion would be merely a preliminary to a hearing before the Conciliation and Arbitration Board. The discussion of wages questions may undoubtedly make the position of the Treasury more difficult, and will disclose to the staff any differences of opinion between the Treasury and the employing Depart-ments. On the other hand, the exclusion of such questions would practically destroy the value of the committees from the point of view of the staff, and it is doubtful whether they would be accepted.(6.) Questions of discipline and promotion should be definitely excluded. The tendency of a representative body would always be in the direction of promotion by seniority as distinct from promotion by merit, and dis-cussion of discipline cases would usually involve the review of the action of supervising officers by their own subordinates, which would be intolerable.The representatives of the Departments who attended the conference at the Treasury unanimously agreed in the opinion that the application of the recommenda-tions in the Report should be subject to the above conditions, and the directions of the War Cabinet are requested (1) as to whether the principle of the recommenda-tions should be applied to such Government establishments as those referred to above where the work and conditions are similar to those in outside industries; (2) whether the above principles and conditions, numbered (1) to (6), as those to which the preparation of schemes should be subject, are approved.The Ministry of Labour concur in the submission in this memorandum.

</content>
</cab>
