<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/5/0 images: 597-601</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government 1----: 311Printed for the War Cabinet.   May 1919.SECRET. G.-242.WAR CABINET.89COMMITTEE  OF HOME AFFAIRS.Continuance of Emergency Legislation after the Termination of the War.(Previous Paper G.-233.)Second Report to the Committee of Home Affairs of the War Cabinet by the Continuance of Emergency Legislation Committee, consisting of: The Right Hon. Viscount Cave [Chairman). Sir William Ryland Adkins, M.P. Mr. A. Andrewes. Uthwatt. Sir Reginald H. Brade, K.C.B. Sir William Graham Greene, K.C.B. Mr. Francis Jones, C.B. Sir F. F. Liddell, K.C.B. Mr. Ronald McNeill, M.P. Sir Claud Schuster, K.C., C.V.O. Sir Hubert Llewellyn Smith, K.C.B. Sir Edward Troup, K.C.B., K.C.V.O. &apos; Mr. J. Kemp (Secretary).This Committee, which was appointed by the Committee of Home Affairs of the War Cabinet on the 18th December, 1918, made a RepOrt to that Committee on the 5th February, 1919, and submitted a Draft Bill for the Continuance of War Emergency Laws.At a meeting of the Committee of Home Affairs, held at 2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1, on Monday, March 24th, 1919, it was decided :-(a.) To approve the report of Lord Cave&apos;s Committee.(6.) To ask Lord Cave&apos;s Committee to re-assemble and to bring the Schedule ofthe Draft Bill up to date, with a view to the early introduction of the Bill, (c.) To ask the Board of Trade to submit a Memorandum on the subject ofextending the provisions of the Courts (Emergency Powers) Act, 1917, : -.,   for a period of three years after the conclusion of peace. (d.) That Sir Claud Schuster should submit a Memorandum on the question ofextending protection under the 1916  Act to  officers and men afterdemobilisation.Lord Caves Committee accordingly met at the offices of the War Cabinet on Thursday, the 1st May for the purpose of revising the Draft Bill and Schedules, and I agreed to the following Report and to the revised Draft Bill which accompanies it: 1. The memoranda of Sir Claud Schuster and the Board of Trade referred to above, which relate to the Courts (Emergency Powers) Acts, were before the Committee under the following circumstances.   The decision of the  questions of principle[1004]-605 B
involved in the &quot;proposed amendment of the Courts (Emergency Powers) Acts, is, of course, reserved for the Committee of Home Affairs, but as the temporary provisions of those Acts are continued by the Draft Bill it was necessary for this Committee to consider how the schedules to the Draft Bill would be affected by any decisions of principle at which the Committee of Home Affairs might arrive.2. The point raised by Sir Claud Schuster&apos;s memorandum is that, according to the commonly accepted construction of the Acts, the protection which officers and men of His Majesty&apos;s forces enjoy during their military service is lost when they cease to belong to the service, and that it is a matter for consideration whether that protection should not be continued at any rate, for a time equivalent to that for which it may be decided to extend the Acts generally.3. If the Home Affairs Committee decide that this exteusion of the protection given to officers and men of His Majesty&apos;s Forces should be granted, this Committee are of opinion that effect can properly be given to that decision by the Praft Bill.They have therefore provisionally made the necessary amendment of the First Schedule of the draft Bill by providing that the Act of 1916, as amended by section 8 of the Act of 1917, shall extend and be deemed always to have extended so as to have effect in favour of persons who, having served as officers or men in any of His Majesty&apos;s forces during the present war, have ceased to be members of those forces for a period of six months after the date when they so ceased, but in no case beyond the expiration of twelve months after the termination of the present war.4. The question raised by the memorandum of the Board of Trade is a wider one, and involves the amendment of sections of the Courts (Emergency Powers) Act, 1917, which are not of a temporary nature.Speaking generally, Avhat the Board of Trade ask is that the Courts shall be able during three years after the termination of the war to alter contracts made before the 1st January, 1916, or even a later date, when it appears that the general conditions with regard to prices, scarcity of materials, &amp;c, arising out of the war make it inequit-able that parties should be bound by contracts entered into before these conditions prevailed.5. If the Home Affairs Committee approve of the principles advocated by the Board of Trade it will be necessary to amend the Courts (Emergency Powers) Act, 1917, in a manner which could not properly be done by the Draft Bill, but will require special legislation. The necessity for such legislation and the scope of it must be left for the decision of the Home Affairs Committee.Amendment of the Draft Bill.6. The only amendment of the draft Bill itself which appears to the Committee to be necessary is in clause 3, sub-clause (2) line 3, where it was decided to omit the words &quot; the Defence of the Realm Begulations continued by this Act&quot; and insert the words &quot; any Regulations made under the Defence of the Realm Consolidation Act, 1914 for the time being in force.&quot; The object of this amendment is to remove any doubt as to whether the Liquor Control Regulations, which do not lapse on the termination of the war, will be enforceable after that date, as contraventions&quot; of the Liquor Control Regulations are punishable as summary offences against the Defence of the Realm Regulations.. Amendments of the First Schedule.. 7. Injuries in War (Compensation) Acts. The Injuries in War (Compensation) Act, 1914 (4 and 5 Geo. V, sec. 3, cap. 30), as amended by section 2 of the Injuries in -War (Compensation) Act, 1914 (Session 2) (5 Geo. V, cap. 18), is at present continued j by this schedule so as to apply to injuries and disablements suffered by persons employed afloat by or under the Admiralty, or Army Council, during one year after the termination of the present war in conditions rendered hazardous by acts done during the war. The Army Council now ask that cases arising out of the operations of the armies of occupation should be covered, and the Committee agree. This involes the continuation, with modifications, of section 1 of the second Act of 1914, referred to above (5 Geo. V, cap. 18). .    . ;8. The Courts (Emergency Powers) Acts.-These Acts have already been dealt with in connection with the memoranda of Sir Claud Schuster and the Board of Trade.9. The National Registration Acts.-The continuation of these Acts by the draft Bill was not recommended by the Committee in their first Report, because they were
informed that the general question of establishing a permanent National Register was under consideration by a Committee of the Local Government Board. The War Office, however, now represent to the Committee that it is improbable that the Local Government Board will be able to make recommendations with regard to this matter in time to enable new legislation to be introduced before the expiration of the present Acts, and they ask that the existing Acts should be continued, in order that the War Office may be in a position to call to the Colours the younger classes, if a sudden emergency should arise. Unless, they say, the continuity of the National Register is ensured, there will be no machinery ready at hand to identify and call up these classes, and it will be necessary to re-establish the Register before this can be done. The Committee, however, are informed by the Local Government Board that the existing National Service Register has not been kept up to date and that the National Register from which it was derived is becoming less and less reliable. Some other points of law and policy were raised and ultimately the Committee decided that the Acts should not be included in the Schedule to the&apos; Bill, but that the War Office proposals should, if so desired, be brought before the Home Affairs Committee with a view to separate legislation.10. Army (Courts of Inquiry) Act, 1916. The Committee decided to omit this Act from the First Schedule, as the War Office informs them that in view of the fact that demobilisation has progressed to a very considerable extent without the necessity for using the powers of this Act, they do not consider its continuance essential.Amendments of the Second Schedule. Part I.11. Army Act (48 &amp; 49 Viet. cap. 8, sec. 115).-The Committee have omitted this section of the Army Act from the Second Schedule of the Draft Bill as the War Office do not consider that it need now be continued, otherwise than is provided by the Army Act itself.Amendments of the Third Schedule.12. Regulation 2 b. The Committee amended the third column of the Schedule in the case of this Regulation on account of representations of the Ministry of Munitions and the Board of Trade.   &apos;13. Regulation 2 c. The Committee have added this Regulation to the Schedule so far as relates to timber already purchased, as it was pressed upon them that the Timber Supply Department requires the powers of entry upon land, &amp;c, given by the Regulation until they have finally disposed of the standing timber they have already bought.14. Regulation 2 JJ. -The Committee amended the words in the third column by substituting the same words as are used in the case of Regulation 2 b, as respects articles other than food.15. Regulation 2 l. The Committee decided to omit this Regulation from the Schedule. It was only continued so far as relates to Ireland, and the main reason given for its continuation was that there is no permanent allotment legislation applying to that country. It is not, however, the object of the Bill to supply defects in the general law, and although in some cases where permanent legislation is contemplated as soon as possible, they have agreed to continue a Regulation as a temporary substitute, the Committee did not see their way to do so in the absence of evidence of any such intention, and in the face of opposition..16. Regulation 2o. The Committee amended the third column so as to continue sub-section (5) of this Regulation, which empowers local authorities themselves to provide and maintain piggeries.17. Regulations 7, 8 a, 8cc, and 8d. These Regulations have all been omitted as the Departments principally concerned agreed that they would not be required after the war.18. Regulation 9 g. On the representation of the Board of Trade the Committee amended the third column by omitting the words limiting the Regulation as continued.19. Regulation 9 gg. This Regulation is omitted, as the Ministry of Munitions say it is no longer required.[1004]-605 B 2
20. Regulation 21 a, paragraphs (a) and (o). The Committee added para-graphs (a) and (b) of Regulation 21 a to the Schedule on the representation of the War Office that it is very important to maintain their powers for the protection of carrier and homing pigeons until permanent legislation on the subject can be obtained. They point out that, prior to the issue of the Regulation against the killing of carrier pigeons, they lost on an average 100 pigeons a week, whereas as soon as the Regulation was issued, this loss dropped to an average of three or four a week. Moreover, it is most important that information should be given of any carrier pigeon found dead or wounded or in an exhausted condition, as it might be carrying a message giving important information, such as the whereabouts of an airman who has had to descend in the sea.21. Regulation 27, paragraph (d). The Committee tranbferred this paragraph of Regulation 27 from the Second Part of the Third Schedule to the First Part at the request of the Treasury, who represented that this paragraph which prohibits the spreading of reports intended to undermine public confidence in banking or currency notes which are legal tender in the United Kingdom, or to prejudice the success of any financial measures taken or arrangements made by His Majesty&apos;s Government  was necessary for a longer period than six months after the war.22. Regulation 30 bb. This Regulation imposes restrictions on dealings in interests in mines and oilfields and, as the Board of Trade stated that the restriction was no longer required except as regards oilfields the Committee omitted the paragraph which refers to certain kinds of mines.23. Regulation 30 r. The Committee added this Regulation to the Schedule. It has been made since the date of their Report, and contains the Treasury Regulations as to new capital issues and dealings in securities issued for the purpose of raising capital.24. Regulation 37 d. The Committee added this Regulation, which is also a new one made since they reported. It restricts the employment of aliens and persons of alien parentage as masters of British ships, and the Board of Trade say it should be continued after the war.25. Regulation 39 c and 39 cc. The Committee transferred these Regulations to Part II of the Third Schedule, as the Shipping Controller said that it would be sufficient to continue them for six months after the termination of the war.20. Regulation 39 gg. The Committee decided to omit this Regulation from the Schedule, as the Shipping Controller said it was unnecessary to continue it after the termination of the Avar.27. Regulation 40 bb. This Regulation deals with the. purchase and distribution of drugs designed for the treatment of venereal disease. The Committee decided to amend the Schedule by continuing this Regulation in its entirety instead of in the restricted form they recommended in their first report. The Local Government Board have explained that it is required to enable Galyl, as a substitute for Salvarsan, to be used without the danger of legal obstacles being raised, which would be very inconvenient pending the settlement of the general question of the control of these classes of drugs, which is now under the consideration of a Committee appointed by the Medical Research Committee.28. Regulation 42 a. The Committee have added this Regulation to the Schedule. It was not included before because it was the iniention of the War Office to include it in the Army Annual Bill. They did so, but it had to be dropped as it was included in the same section with another provision which dealt with the making and spreading statements and reports likely to prejudice recruiting, to the enactment of which as part of the permanent statute law serious objection was taken in the House of Commons. This Regulation makes it an offence for any person to attempt to induce a member of His Majesty&apos;s forces to act in a manner which such person knows to be in contravention of duly authorised Regulations and Orders under the Army Act. It is an offence punishable with a maximum sentence of two years&apos; imprisonment with hard labour for a soldier to commit a breach of Regulations or Orders, and there appears to be no reason why a civilian who knowingly attempts to induce a soldier to commit such an offence should not also be subject to a penalty, especially during the period of demobilisation, when any concerted effort on the part of civilian workers to induce the military forces to commit such breaches might have serious consequences.29. Regulation 45, paragraph (h). The Ministry of Munitions say they require this paragraph of Regulation 45 to be continued to protect the Government against attempts to pass off bad and dangerous material. In the circumstances the Committee decided that the whole Regulation should be continued.
Part II.30. Regulations 10, 10 a., and 10 c. The Committee have omitted these Regu-lations, as the War Office and other Departments agree that their continuance after the war will not be necessary.31. Regulation 27. The Committee have amended the words in the third column bv adding &quot;and paragraph (d),&quot; because at the request of the Treasury they have transferred this paragraph to the first part of the Third Schedule.32. Regulations 39 c and 39 cc. The Committee transferred these Regulations from Part I to Part II of the Schedule, as the Shipping Controller said it would be sufficient to continue them for six months after the termination of the war.CAVE, Chairman.May 12, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
