<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/5/0 images: 720-722</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
:&quot;   --56 &quot; .     -.374This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.WAR CABINET.INTERIM REPORT ON ARMY OFFICERS&apos; PAY.Circulated by the Secretary of State for War.I: The rates of pay which we recommend as appropriate for the officers of the future RegularArmy are based upon the principles set forth in paragraphs 2 to 6 below. &quot;(%. The present multiplicity of rates of regimental and corps pay for different arms of theService should be replaced by uniform inclusive rates, except where the duties of a particulararm are essentially those of a special profession such as Medicine or Civil or MechanicalEngineering..3./As far as possible, there should be a clear distinction between the expenditure to becovered by pay and that to be covered by allowances.   It follows that allowances, when given,should be adequate to meet the expenses to which they relate, and should be adjusted from time-to time in accordance with the movements of prices./ The scheme of consolidated payintroduced after the South African War has not realized the expectations of its authors!/ 4 The pay of an officer when first commissioned should be sufficient to enable him to takea share in the normal life of his regiment without private income,/ A sub-coromittee, presidedover by-Sir William Robertson, has advised us that, on the assumption that rations will be givenin kind, thaYt initial outfit grants should be given to all officers and that soldier servants shouldbe paid by the State and should not wear civilian clothes (which the officer now provides), thenecessary income of a 2nd Lieutenant on these lines, including a reasonable allowance foramusements and expenses on.leave, &amp;c, is just under 2507. year.5. An officer may expect to reach the rank of Captain at art average age of 30\years. At thatage we consider that the State should recognize him as entitled to marry without private means,giving him a rate of pay adequate to maintain a wife and providing quarters (or allowance in -lieu), travelling expenses on change of station. &amp;c.,,on a married basis for such officers as are infact married. At. present the Lieutenant-Colonel and the Quartermaster are the only regimentalofficers whose marriage.is so recognized by regulations.6. We have not adhered to the principle hitherto obtaining, that the pay of a 2nd Lieutenantmust necessarily be higher than that of a senior Warrant Officer. But it has not been possiblefor us to overlook the fact that by decision of the Government a Corporal of Marines will infuture receive over 100/. a year clear pocket money and a Company Serjeant-Major of Marinesover 180/. clear, in addition to being &quot;all found,&quot; while the officer will still have necessaryexpenses to meet out of his pay. \y7. On these principles we recommend the normal scale of pay set out in Table &quot; A.&quot; Wehave added to that table the value of allowances proposed for the several ranks at present rates,in order to show approximately the total public income provided; but the rates of allowancerequire revision in detail.8. A further proposal&apos;of Sir William Robertson&apos;s Committee, to which we attach greatimportance, is that an officer, who. has graduated at the Staff College should receive a specialaddition to his regimental pay whife employed with his regiment. This is desirable on severalgrounds,&apos; and we propose to submit definite recommendations on these lines in a further report.9. In drawing up the normal scale we have (as far as is possible) excluded from considerationthe proposals for officers of the Royal Navy, Marines ana? Air Force. But it would be manifestlyimpossible, as well as unfair, to canyon the Army as a Service definitely inferior to the otherfighting Services, and it is therefore necessary to consider the effect which would be producedon Army rates should the Government approve the proposals made for the other Servicesunaltered.10. If the scale of payment proposed for the Royal Air Force is approved, we are preparedto adhere to our proposals up to and including the rank of Lieutenant-Colonel. For the rank ofColonel and above we see no justification for giving lower ratesthan those of corresponding ranksin the Royal Air Force. The difference in the&quot;lower ranks could, we consider, be justified by theextra risk involved in the Royal Air Force; but in the higher ranks, the greater, responsibilities ofArmy officers fully balance what special element of risk may remain with those, of the Air Force.11. If the Admiralty proposals for the Royal Marines are approved, or any scale of pay forthe Royal Marines in excess of our proposed scale, it must in our judgment inevitably follow thatthat scale should also apply to the Army. No Marine officer above the rank of Major normallygoes afloat in peace; and the dutieR of the senior ranks are less, not more, responsible andarduous than those of the same ranks in the Army.12. As regards the Admiralty proposals for the Navy, before the war the rates of pay in thetwo Services were generally speaking much on the same level. The extra responsibily ofcommand by junior ranks in the. Navy, and the greater risk in peace are compensated for by thevery general grant of command pay, specialists, pay, &amp;o., for junior officers. Any very specialdegree of discomfort in the Navy is similarly compensated for by hard-lying money; while inwar the discomforts and risks of Army officers on field service have under modern conditions ,(B19/286)   100  6/19  II&amp;S  7235wo
increased out of all recognition. We therefore coneider that there can be no justification for now introducing any marked difference between the substantive pay of corresponding ranks in the Navy and Army.13. We append a Table (B) comparing the proposals made for the several services, and showing the average ages at which the respective corresponding ranks are expected to be readied. It will be seen that in almost every case the Army officer is older, rank for rank, than those of oilier services ; and we note that proposals are made by the Admiralty for lowering the ages for retirement of certain senior officers. The effect of this disparity is to increase the relative disadvantage of the scale of Army pay.14. The net result of our conclusions is thai we recommend a scale for the Army which is considerably more moderate than those proposed for the Navy, Marines and Air Force, but this scale cannot hold good if the proposals for those forces are accepted as they staud.15. The increased cost of the scale of pay we propose over the scale existing before the war, for the pre-war establishment of 10,000 officers (corresponding to a total of 184,000 all ranks) would be about 2,750,000/. The increase over the rates in force to-day (exclusive of Army of Occupa-Occupation Bonus) would be 1,750,000/. During the retention of the Armies of Occupation the figures would be proportionately increased.1(3. We are not yet in a position to make proposals as to pension and half pay, but we are very strongly of opinion that an announcement should immediately be made that any officer who.desires to leave the Army or lias left since the date of the Armistice, will be given the benefit of any new rates of retired pay that may be brought out alter his retirement. There are a large-number of officers Avho have decided to leave the Army Avhatever the rates of retired pay mav be. They are hanging back now through the fear that if they go at once they will forfeit the benfits of the future scale, some increase in which is clearly foreseen. These officers would be happy to retire at once with the assurance we proposed at a cousiderable saving to the public.H. W. FORSTER. G. M. W. MACDONOGII. C. II. HARLNGTON. C. HARRIS.R. PATERSON, Secretary. 17th June, 1919.TABLE A.PROPOSED NORMAL SCALE OF PAY FOR ARMY OFFICERSPay and Allowances under Peace conditions at Home.Rank.	Pay.			Rations, lodging and fuel and light.			Total per annum			 	s.	d.	 	s.	d.	 	s.	d.2nd Lieutenant      .........      ...      ......	0	12	6	0	4	7	311	15	0Lieutenant (promoted after two years as 2nd Lieutenant)    ......	0	15	6	0	4	7	357	7	6Lieutenant (after seven years commissioned service).........	0	18	6	0	4	7	421	0	0Captain       ........................	1	2	6	0	7	5&apos;*&apos;	545	6	8				if n	arried.				,,    (after 15 years commissioned service)............	1	5	0	0	7 m	5*	591	9	0				if nc	arri	ed.			Brevet Major...........................	0	2	0		...			..		in addition to								Major ...	Captain&apos;s		pay.							1	10	0	0	7	5*	G82	11	9				if married.					,,   (after 5 years as such)       ..................	1	15	0	0	7	5*	773	16	8				if married.					Lieutenant-Colonel........................	2	0	01	0					,,           command pay for Cavalry and Infantry   ......	0	10	o)		7	5	1,047	11	8Colonel        ......	2	10	0	0	8	1	1,059	15	0Brigadier-General (Brigade Commander only)............	3	0	0	0	12	3	1,318	0	0Major-General       .....................	4	10	0	0	15	3	1,920	5	0Major-General (when not in command)...............	4	0	0	0	15	3	1,737	15	0Lieutenant-Generalt...............      .........	5	10	0	0	18	5	2,353	0	0General!	6	10	0	1	1	7	2,766	0	0* Allowances are being revised. The present Lieutenant-ColoneFs allowances are taken for married Captains and Majors.Cartain General Oftcers receiva tible money and furniture allowance in addition. The rate3 are under revision, t These ofticars will g^ra ly be paid by thiir post, and not by their rank.
o375TABLE B.Comparative rates of pay. excluding allowances, proposed for the Royal Navy, Royal Marines, Army, Royal Air Force and table of average ages Rank.Itoftp Sc9a so   oRoyaL^Marine rates of Pay.Army.Royal Air Force.Midshipman........Sub-LieutenantLieutenant (junior).....Lieutenant (senior) ... Lieut.-Commander (junior).. Lieut.-Commander (senior)..Commander (junior).....Commander (senior).....Captain (junior)......Captain (senior)Rear-Admiral       ......Vice-Admiral        ......Admiral...........Admiral of the Fleet  s. d. 0 5 0 0 10 0 0 17 0 4 0 10 0 14 0 0 0Is. d. 2 0 2 3 3 5 5 72 12 Oj 7 6&apos;o oi8 o;15 0J8 0l 0 0&quot;*o o;*0 0*0 0*2nd Lt.-7*. 6d. Lt.-10s. to U. 4s. Capt.-11. 10s. to 11. Us. Major-21. to 21. Us. Lt.-Col-31. to 3l. 5s. Col.-3Z. 5s. to 21. 10s. Maj.-Gen. 51. Lt.-Gen.-61. Gen.-11.Cadet-Nil. 2nd-Lt-12s. 6d. Lt.-15s. to 18s. 6d. Capt.-11, 2s. 6d. to K.5s. Maj.-\l, 10*. to 11. 15s. Lt.-Col.-21., 10s.  com-mand pay. Col.-21. Ws. Brig.-Gen.-3Z. Maj.-Gen.-4Z.  10s., 41.when not in command. Lt.-Gen.- 51. 10s. Gen.-61. 10s.Cadet 5s. to 10s. 2nd Lt.-18s. Lt-11. 3s. to 11. 5s. Capt.-11. 9s. Maj.-11. 14s. to 11. 16s. Lt.-Col.-21. to 21. 15s. Col.-21. 15s. to 31. 10s. Brig.-Gen. U. Maj.-Gen. 51.* Table money.Ages. -	Midshipman and Cadets.	2nd Lieut.	Lieut, and Sub-Lieut.	Captain and Lieut., R.N.	Major and Lieut.-Commander.	Lieut.-Col.-Commander and Junior Captain.Royal Navy   ...			20	22	30-37	35-41Royal Marines......		18-22	22	30	37	46Army.........	17-19	19-21	21-23	30	38	47Royal Air Force	17*-19^		21	25	30	35TABLE C.TABLE SHOWING PR0P3ED TOTAL EMOLUMENTS FOR NAVAL OFFICERS.The rates of pay proposed for Royal Marines are practically the same as those for the Navy and their allowances are Naval orAjmy allowances according as they are home, afloat or ashore.Rank,Pay.O cS o3o-a 3a s a-So o OcoM&apos;3oT3Ocr.si - -p-so Q9 ,c 60o t3-on&quot;&quot;,0 0) s2 f*to a) ei toMaximum yearly Emoluments.Afloat.Ashore.In London.Age.Army rank.Marine rates of pay.Midshipman........Sub-Lieutenant      .....Lieutenant (Junior).....Lieutenant (Senior) ... Lieut.-Commander (Junior) Lieut.-Commander (Senior) Commander (Junior) Commander (Senior)Captain (Junior)    .....Captain (Senior)    .....Rear-AdmiralVice-Admiral        .....Admiral      ........Admiral of the Fleet  s. d.0   5 00 10 00 17 0 1   4d.0 0 0 01 10 0 I 5 0 1 14 0:5 0 2 0 0 2 12 0 3 0 0il8 0 3 15 0 18 0 0   0*   ...e o o*; ...7 0 0*j ... 8   0   0*   ...2 2 30 I 3  84 84J-102V132 ^80 .20-40 	 	 				127	255	296		...		2nd Lt. 7s. 6d.219	317	388	20	Lieutenant		10s. to 11. 4s.365 494	513 542	558 587	21	j-Captain ...		11.10s. to 11.14s.629 713	750 821	795 866	30 37		-Major   ...	21. to 21. 12s.866	952	977	35			1,086	1,172	1,217		-	- Lt.-Col..	21. to 31. 5s.1,423	1.566	1,489	41	J		1,697	1,840	1,768	* a *	Col.		31. 5s. to 31.10s.1,825*	2,037	2,088		Maj.-Gen.		51.2,190*	2,402	2,453	***	Lt.-Gen.		61.2,555*	2,767	2,811		General		11.2,920*	3,132	3,183	...	F.-M.		Table money.   An allowance in lieu of provisions is given in ad iition.

</content>
</cab>
