<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/5/0 images: 907-914</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
NOTE BY THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER.I CIRCULATE to Ministers a Memorandum on the Financial PositionIarepared in the Treasury by direction of the Prime Minister (compare IT. 7729).The position grows daily more grave.   No estimates hold good, andIihe Cabinet sanctions increase after increase with, as it seems to me, an insufficient appreciation of the aggregate result.Our capital commitments are already enormous. Borrowing is difficult and rates will be exorbitant. If we cannot balance revenue&apos; and expenditure next year, our credit national, and international will be jeriously shaken and the results may be disastrous. Any estimate framed now must be largely hypothetical, but we are heading straight for a deficit of 200 millions.Will my colleagues consider what this means and how it is to be provided by new taxation in addition to filling the gap left by the repeal )f the Excess Profits Duty (50 millions), and to making good the reliefs which are certain to be recommended for large classes of income-tax payers by the Royal Commission on Income-Tax and Super-Tax ?A.C.Treasury, July 26, 1919.i.287 Aj
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s GovernmeniJPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1919.SECRET. -G.-257. ^ 58WAR CABINET.MEMORANDUM BY THE TREASURY ON THE FINANCIAL POSITION AND FUTURE PROSPECTS OF THIS COUNTRY.I.Pre-War Position.1. THE total expenditure (Exchequer Issues) for 1913-14 was 197,493,0001, and the total revenue 198,243,000?., of which 163,029,3001, or 3?. 10s. per head of population, was tax revenue. The pre-war Budget estimate for 1914-15 showed an increase of approximately 10,000,000?. on these figures. Pre-war expenditure and revenue may therefore be said to have balanced at about 200,000,000?, per annum.2. For 1913-14 Income Tax was Ls. 2d. in the   with additional super-tax of 6d. in the  ; Tea duty, bd. lb; Sugar duty, lOd. to Is. \0d. a cwt.; Raw tobacco, 3s. 8d. to 4s. Ihd. lb; Spirits, 14s. 9d. to 25s. a gallon ; Beer, 7s. 9d. a standard barrel.3. At the outbreak of war the National Debt was 645,000,0001., or about 14?. per head of population.4. Nearly all this debt was of permanent character with no fixed date of redemption ; and (with insignificant exceptions) it was all held in this country.5. In the year 1913 United Kingdom Imports (merchandise) were  valued at ... ... ... ... ... ...     768,735,000Exports were valued at        ... ... ... ...     634,820,000(of which coal accounted for 53,663,000?,.)Balance of Imports for twelve months ... ...     133,915,000(covei-ed by payments due from abroad for freights and interest).6. The holding of the United Kingdom in foreign securities was estimated at about 4,000,000,000?.  7. The total national wealth was commonly estimated at about   ...  16,000,000,000 (of which  private  individuals  are  estimated to haveheld 11,500,000,0001) and the annual National Income of about        ... ...    2,000,000,000II.Position in the Financial Year 1919-20.8. On the basis of Budget Estimates 1919-20 the Expenditure for  the present year is ... ... ... ... ... 1,434,910,000Revenue .. ... ... 1,201,100,000of which tax revenue amounts to 940,000,000?., or 20?. per head of population, but of this 300.000,000Z. is due to the old rate of Excess Profits duty.Deficit ... ... ...        233,810,000or rounded as in the Budget speech     ... ... ...        250,000,0009. Income tax is 6s. in the   with super-tax rising to 4s. 6d. in the   ; Tea duty, ls. a lb.; Sugar duty, 11s. 2d. to 25s. Sd. a cwt., Raw tobacco, 8s. 2d. to 9s. a lb.; Spirits, 30s. to 51s. 9d. a gallon; Beer, 70s. a standard barrel.Excess Profits duty, 40 per cent.; Estate duties on estates over 15,000?. increased up to a maximum rate of 40 per cent, (or double previous rates) on estates exceeding 2,000,000?.10. The National Debt on the 31st March, 1920 (exclusive of the premium payable on National War Bonds amounting to some 50,000,000?., and of the liability to repay 1?. for each 15s. Gd. War Savings Certificate representing a further liability of about [287] 1 B
65,000,0002.) was estimated in the Budget at 7,6 8 5,0 00,0002., or 1632. 10s. per head of population.Of this total of 7,685,000,000Z., about 1,300,000,0001. would be External Debt, and the balance of 6,385,000,0002. Internal Debt. Of the same total of 7,685,000,0001. some 2,850,000,0002. (External 200,000,0002. : Internal 2,650,000,0002.) would be redeemable in the next five years.   Details of debt are given in Appendix I.These figures are subject to some adjustment when the results of the recent loan are available.11. Against these liabilities there are certain assets, viz. : (a.) Obligations of Dominions and India   Face value as at the 1st April, 1919  ... ...         ...      201,000,000,,   31st March, 1920, say ...          ...       226,000,000(5.) Obligations of Allies as at the 1st April, 1919 ...          ...    1,568,000,000 Of which Eussia owed ...         ... 568,000,000France   ,,     ...         ... 434,500,000Italy     ,,     ...          ... 412,500,000Belgium,,     ...          ... 86,750,000Serbia          ...... 18,650,000Other Allies         ...... 48,000,000(Taken at half this might represent 784,000,0002.)As at the 31st March, 1920     ... ... ... ...    1,668,000,000(of which half would be 834,000,0002.)(c.) Vote of credit assets (balances, ships, commodities, surplus stores, &amp;c.) roughly estimated at 800,000,0002., of which 450,000,0002. has been applied to 1919-20, leaving 350,000,0002. to come in subsequently. (The allocation of these amounts between various financial years will now be altered to some extent.)(d.) Payments on account of German War Indemnity.12. These assets are no doubt appreciable, but the figures with regard to them must be used with every caution. The estimate of Vote of Credit assets is necessarily largely conjectuial. The decision to continue food control will in any case postpone the payment to the Exchequer of part of these receipts from 1919-20 to 1920-21, and it may, if prices fall, actually diminish ultimate cash proceeds of sales. It has also been found necessary to agree to reinvest in France for ten years a part of the realisa-tions in respect of property now in France.With regard to loans, it is impossible to foresee when repayments of principal may be expected from the Allies, who at present are not even paying interest. The Dominions pay interest, but they have as yet made no arrangements for repayment of capital. Consequently it cannot be expected that we can realise the obligations of Allies and Dominions for a considerable time.13. On the other hand, our liabilities are very immediate. Whatever we may receive from our debtors in five, ten, or fifty years we have to pay our creditors either at once or in the near future.The internal debt redeemable in the next five years amounts to no less than 2,650,000,0002. In addition, even assuming that the loans from the American and Canadian Governments (amounting to about 840,000,0002. and 90,000,000/. respectively) can be placed on a long term basis, we have to repay abroad within the next five years, in round figures, 200,000,0002. Any further depreciation of the exchanges (and particularly the American exchange) will intensify the burden of this repayment.14. In the six months from December, 1918, to May, 1919, the United Kingdom imported in merchandise 710,605,0002., and exported only 355,059,0002.,* leaving an adverse balance, for six months and at present values, of 355,546,0002. .     15. During the   war,  we  have had  to  export to   America,  approximately 1,000,000,0002. of our foreign securities.16. The national wealth in private hands in 1918 is estimated by Dr. Stamp at 16,0 00,0.0.0,0002., as against 11,500,000,0007. pre-war. This figure, howiver, is an estimate of money value only, and makes no allowance for decreased purchasing power.17. To complete 19L9-20, it is now probable that.there will be a further deficit over .and .ahove the Budget deficit of some 200,000,0002.   This is mainly due to Army* Including coal, 34,i87,W).(M,
*20. In addition to the expenditure dealt with above, it is necessary to face very considerable capital expenditure outside the Budget figures proper. Under legislation now being passed there will be extremely heavy demands for such capital expenditure ; and, although much of this will fall on local authorities or on special funds, it will naturally increase the difficulty of raising permanent loans for the State, or of financing industry.At so low an estimate as 500L a house, the provision of 600,000f houses means a capital expenditure of 300,000,0001. If the-cost of a house amounts to 1,000L (as it shows signs of doing) this total would be doubled.Under the Ministry of Ways and Communications Bill large sums may have to be raised for railways, and in particular the Treasury may have to raise 70,000,000/!. for purchasing privately-owned railwav waggons.Under the Electricity Supply Bill the district boards are authorised to raise 25,000,000L with a Treasury guarantee of interest, and the Treasury itself is to raise 20,000,000Z. for emergency power stations.Provision has been made or will be made in the Budget figures for 20,000,000Z. for Land Settlement, but any amount required above that sum will have to be raised for the Local Loans Fund ; and in addition there will be very heavy demands on the Local Loans Fund for general capital expenditure by Local Authorities under Public Health Acts, &amp;c21. The raising of these large sums, either directly by the State or indirectly by the Local Authorities, will naturally compete with the demands of industry and commerce for trade expansion, and to that extent will tend to force up money rates.2&apos;1. At the same time the continued inflation of credit is fraught with the greatest dangers to the stability of the country.   At the outbreak of war the legal tender money in circulation is estimated to have been about 214,000,000L   In April, 19-1-9, it was. estimated at more than 540,000,000/., including about 350,000,0001. in Currency Notes.On the 24th July the amount of Currency Notes outstanding was still 340,000,OOOL These notes are issued to the banks against payments by them of money which they derive from increased deposits resulting from Government payments out of bank credits. In so far as these credits are not represented by savings or earnings due to.the increased, production of actual goods they result in inflation..The supply of purchasing power is increased without relation to the supply of* Estimates for 1919-20 (net), 502,000,000/. (which will be exceeded by some 80,000,000/, at least); 1913-14 (net), 77,000,000/. &apos; /&apos;*t England, 500,0001 Scotland, 65,000; Ireland, say, 50,000,.and Navy expenditure, to loans to Allies, and to decreased revenue in 1919-20 from the Vote of Credit Assets owing to continued food purchases.III.Future Prospects.18. The Chancellor of the Exchequer in his Budget speech put forward a forecast of expenditure and revenue in &quot; a future normal year&quot; at a total of 766,000, OOOi. This estimate referred &quot; not to next year, nor perhaps to the year after,&quot; but to a normal year when all special war expenditure arising out of or consequent on the war and also the initial capital cost of reconstruction had ceased. It was further based on certain stated assumptions. For instance, that the total votes for Army, Navy, and Air would be reduced to 110,000,000L*; that strict economy would be observed in public expenditure; that all fresh loans to Allies will have ceased; and that the deficit on railways, coal mines, and bread subsidy would be made good from sources other than the Exchequer.19. For the immediate future, i.e., for the next two or three years, it is highly improbable that expenditure can be reduced to this total. It is impossible to frame any reliable estimates in the present state of our knowledge. Appendix II contains an attempt to form such an estimate for 1920-21, but the result cau only be regarded as an indication of probabilities. It is difficult to see how expenditure can drop much below 1,150,000,000L for 1920-21, if it can reach that figure, and the Budget, on present tendencies, will again hardly balance without further borrowing, a course most detrimental to industrial recovery.
goods. It inevitably follows that the amount of money required to purchase any given article increases. In other words, the price of that article goes up. If the capital expenditure which we have to face is met not from savings or increased production, but by the creation of bankers&apos; credit, the certain result will be increased prices with correspondingly increased money wages, resulting in further increased prices.Higher prices will accentuate the difficulty of increasing output, and in particular will make it more than ever difficult for this country&apos;s export trade to compete with foreign countries in the markets of the world. This in its turn will accentuate the already difficult problem of exchange, which the necessity of paying our foreign debts (particularly to America) and of purchasing abroad raw materials and food makes it essential to solve.23. Public opinion has not yet realised that four and a-balf years of exceeding costly war impoverish and do not enrich a country, even when allowance is made fur-improved industrial plant and industrial methods. It is very commonly held that the enormous financial effort of the war proves that we can continue to spend on a very large scale without serious damage, or even with advantage. In the reaction from the strain and restrictions of war the reasons for economy are much less obvious to the man in the street than they were in the dominant presence of actual hostilities. Only persistent explanation, particularly outside Parliament (and possibly with groundwork prepared by the War Savings Committees), can bring the financial facts home to the minds of ordinary citizens.24. If the financial future is to be faced with success the urgent need is fur increased production, and particularly increased production for export.In order that industry may be able to supply this increased production the first need is hard work to the utmost of their powers by everybody. The next need is to remove as far as possible all war restrictions on export trade. There is particular need of definite and specific pronouncement of what restrictions on import and export are still in force. Piecemeal withdrawal leaves traders in great doubt as to what is still left.   No doubt an early pronouncement on future fiscal policy is also most desirable.The final and most pressing need is to reduce prices, so that British trade may compete successfully in the world markets. According to the President of Board of TraaVs statement, after allowing for the increased price of coal : Rails will cost in 	 	s.	d.Great Britain	...     17	10	0United States of America	10	0	0Ship-plates cost in 			Great Britain            ...         ... *	...                     ...           1 *J	5	0United States of America	.......     14	0	0Crown bars cost in 			Great Britain	...                   2j 2j	10	0United States of America	ii	15	0Pig iron cost in 			Great Britain	9	0	0United States of America	6	0	0Reduction in prices requires, in addition to increased work and removal of restrictions : (1.) Early cessation of Government borrowing and reduction of public debt, in order that capital may be set free for industry.(2.) Immediate reduction of expenditure, both personal and public, in order that savings may be available for investment. Experience in the recent loan shows that it is impossible to appeal effectively for private thrift unless the Government give a notable (even, perhaps, an exaggerated) example. A substantial reduction of the estimates would produce effects reaching considerably beyond the actual money involved. It is difficult to see where such substantial reduction can be made except on the expenditure of the Army, Navy, and Air Force.Treasury-, July 18, 1919.
APPENDIX I.National Debt.Note. These figures are subject to modification when the adjustments resulting from the recent loan are known. Possibly 500,000,0002. of the shorter maturities (particularly Ways and Means Advances and Treasury Bills) may be converted into longer maturities.Pre-war issues (Consols, &amp;c.) .. ,,       ,,   Terminable Annuities3^ per cent. War Loan, 1925-28       .. ..A\ per cent. War Loan, 1925-45 4   per cent. War Loan, 1929-42 5   per cent. War Loan, 1929-47 3  per cent. Exchequer Bonds, 1930   .. National War Bonds, 1925-27-28 National War Bonds, 1922-23-24 Exchequer Bonds, 1919-20-21-22 Anglo-French American Loan, 1920 War Savings Certificates Treasury BillsWays and Means Advances  .. n,,    n    f Short Termutner uecii Tjnited States Government, Canada, and certain 1927-1937 (abroad)]      debt &apos;..Debt as on March 31, 1919Add Deficit 1919-20 (Budget Estimate).Debt as on March 31, 1920 (as estimated in Budget) Add further deficit .. 317,661,000 20,635,000338,296,000 62,745,000 15,990,000 56,306,000 2,013,000,000 15,640,000 938,000,000 697,000,000 369,000,000 51,000,000 227,000,000 957,000,000 455,000.000 165,000,0001,074,000,0007,435,000.000 250,000,0007,685,000,000 200,000,000 7,885,000,000
APPENDIX II.Estimates,of Revenue and Expenditure 1919-20 and 1920-21. Note. The Estimates for 1920-21 are necessarily largely conjectural.(Details below.)	Budget Estimate 1919-20.	Tentative Estimate 1920-21.Expenditure Revenue	  1,434,910,000 1,216,100,000*	  1,166,300,000 1,041,000,000Deficit  ....	218,810,000	125,300,000	(Say)  250,000,000	125,000,000* Adding&apos; 15,000,000/. to the Budget figures for increased Beer Revenue.		* (A.) Revenue.		-	Budget Estimate, 1919-20.	Tentative Estimate, 1920-21 (on basis of existing taxation in a full year).Customs.. Excise Death Duties Income Tax Excess Profits Duty-Other Inland Revenue	  119,000,000 118,500,000 33.500.000 354,000,000 300,000,000 15,000,000	  128,000,000 154.000,000 41,000,000 350,000,000 100,000,000 15,000,000Total Tax Revenue Post Office Sundry Loans, &amp;c. Miscellaneous Revenue	940,000.000 41,000,000 10,400,000 209,700,000	788.000,000 41,000,000 12,000,000 200.000,000*Add Further Beer Revenue	1,201,100,000 15,000,000 1,216,100,000	1,041,000,000* A very speculative item for which no reliable estimate can yet be made. Postponements of anticipated receipts in 1919-20 might increase the above figure./Jk
(B.): Expenditure.-                  1   Budget 1919-20. &quot;1		1920-21.	Remarks.	 	 	National Debt	360,000,0001	410,000,000	Allowing 5  per cent, for inter-			est and sinking fund all over			on, say, 7,900,000,000/.Issues for Death Duty Bonds	m v	25,000,000	Quite speculative.Local Tax Account	9,763.000	10,000,000	Land Settlement	5,000,000	15,000,000&apos;	(Capital)			Other Consolidated Fund Charges	1,832,000	1,800,000	Eoad Fund		1,500,000	Total Consolidated Fund	376,595,000	463,300,000	Army (net)	287.000.0005		Navy	119,200,000	y   350,000,000	Pure guess.Air	66,500.000	J	Civil Services 			Education	38,841,000	45,000,000	Old Age Pensions	17,892,000	18,000,000	This   might   easily   increase			100 pei cent, as the result of			the Committee now sitting-			and certain to recommend			largely increased   expendi-			ture.Pensions Ministry	72,855,000	75,000.000	Select Committee sitting.Insurance	13,435,000	15,000,000	General Civil Service	78.407,000	&quot; 70,000,000	Civil Demobilisation..	38,874,000		Loans to Allies	115,500,000		Bread Subsidy	50,000 000	25,000,000	Railway Agreement..         ..	.   60,000,000	25,000,000	Remanet Railway Subsidy and			New Department.Coal	20,000,000	25.000,000	Customs and Inland Revenue ..	8,537,000	10,000 000	Post Office..	41.274,000	45,000,000	Total Supply	1,058,315,000	703,000,000	Grand Total ..	1,434,910,000	1,166,300,000	I Includes no Sinking Fund charge.g In addition to Appropriations in Aid, 153,000,000/.Note 1. Excesses over the Budget estimate, 1919-20, which may reach 200,000,000/. are treated as non recurrent in 1920-21 (except in so far as they are allowed for in Army and Navy figures, in Labour Ministry, and generally as war bonus).Note 2. Army estimates, 1919-20, are 440,000,000/. gross. In 1920-21 appropriations are not likely to reach anything like 150,000,000/. Therefore, even 200,000,000/. net for Army wculd mean a reduction of over 50 per cent.Note 3.-The 78,407,000/. for general civil service, 1919-20, included about 20.000,000./. (c.g.. Road Board and housing materials) for items which should not recur. This brings the figure down to 58,407.000/. (including 4,000,000 for W.B.). Add for land and housing subsidies in 1919-20 3,000,000/., and for training (other than on education vote) 4,000,000/.   Total 65.407,000, say, to allow margin, 70.000,000/.o

</content>
</cab>
