<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/5/0 images: 1067-1084</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JjThis Document is the. Property of Hi&amp;Bntaimxe Majestys Government,]Printed for the War Cabinet.   August 1919.SECRET.   AyTKALLSPITSBERGEN.On the 9th instant I circulated to my colleagues a note on the subject of the island of Spitsbergen. A copy of this note was sent to the Peace Delegation in Paris. On the 16th August I received a telegram from Mr. Balfour asking me to suspend further action pending the receipt of a despatch from him on the subject. (Enclosure A.) I now circulate this despatch together with a copy of my previous note, for convenience of reference.   (Enclosure B).It will be seen that matters have progressed so fast in Paris that we are placed in a somewhat delicate position. All the other Allied and Associated Powers, with a vicarious generosity, as they themselves have no interests in Spitsbergen, are prepared to give Norway full sovereignty over the island instead of, as I had proposed and should have preferred, a mandate under the League of Nations. The fact that Sweden, the only other Power besides Norway and ourselves which has interests in Spitsbergen, also favours a mandate as against annexation to Norway, does not materially alter the situation. If, therefore, we alone at the Peace Conference withstand Norvvay&apos;s claims, we are faced with the prospect of incurring the resentment of the Norwegians, a people with whom we desire to maintain the most cordial relations and to whom we are under a serious debt of gratitude for services rendered during the war. Nor is it at all certain that our opposition to Norwegian sovereignty would prevail against the unanimous opinion of the other Allied and Associated Powers in Paris.In the circumstances, and subject to anything which my colleagues at the Admiralty, War Office, and Board of Trade may have to say, I advise that we should agree to the course proposed by Mr. Balfour on the clear understanding that British rights, interests, and claims, both actual and prospective, are completely safeguarded. The draft Convention seems, on the face of it, to be well devised for their due protection. But certain articles, notably Article 7, may require further explanation, and the mining regulations foreshadowed under Article 8 must be subjected to very careful scrutiny.I think we should be prepared, if we agree in this course, for a considerable amount of criticism in the press, no doubt mainly inspired from interested quarters but nevertheless not altogether neglible, for what will be represented as an abandon-ment of British interests. This criticism will in the future be enhanced should the deposits of iron ore in the island prove to be as rich as is claimed by the British prospectors, although the outlook on this head is at present uncertain. It was with a view to forestalling and deflecting such criticism that I had suggested to the Peace Delegation that representatives of the British companies interested in the Spitsbergen should proceed to Paris to lay their case before our representative on the Spitsbergen Commission and explain to him what precautions and safeguards they considered to be necessary. This proposal has not met with approval in Paris, and I, therefore, propose to consult here in London the British interests concerned.I should add that from what the Norwegian Minister here has said, it seems not impossible that the Norwegian Government may decline to accept the sovereignty over Spitsbergen if the regulations and conditions which the Peace Conference lay down appear to them to restrict unduly the sovereign rights of Norway over the island.CURZON OF KEDLESTON.August 25, 1919.Enclosure (A). Mr. Balfour to Earl Curzon.(No. 1646).My Lord, Paris, August 19,1919.I HAVE received your Lordship&apos;s despatch No. 5368 of 12th August, forwarding the draft of a despatch which you propose to address to me on the subject of the future of Spitsbergen, and for which the approval of the Cabinet is sought.[713] . B
2. The passage in the fourth paragraph of the draft in which it is stated that &quot;a violent outburst of public opinion&quot; would arise in the event of His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment consenting to recognise the sovereignty of Norway over these islands, is causing me some anxiety and embarrassment. I regret that a solution on these lines should appear to your Lordship impracticable, and I would fain nope that this view may on further consideration appear unduly pessimistic. I find it in fact difficult to believe that a settlement which fully recognised and guaranteed all British rights, both those already existing and those that may be required in future, could possibly create so unreasonable an impression on the British public; of which only a small portion is likely to have any knowledge of the Spitsbergen problem, or any practical interest in its solution.3. I am under the impression, based on the recollections of members of my present staff now here who were at the time actual dealing with the question at the Foreign Office, that before the assembly of the Spitsbergen Conference of 1914 the chief if not the only ^ reason which prevented His Majesty&apos;s Government from favouring the annexation of the island to Norway was the known opposition of the other interested Powers which rendered it impossible at that time to get such a solution accepted.4. When the question was re-examined at the Foreign Office during the autumn of last year for the purpose of determining the attitude to be taken up by His Majesty&apos;s Government at the Peace Conference, it was believed that the opposing tendencies of the several Powers still subsisted, and it was in view of the situation so understood that the solution of a Norwegian mandate under the League of Nations was advocated as the line of least resistance.5. The situation has, however, now altogether changed. Norway has succeeded in persuading all the other Powers that the simplest, cleanest, and most satisfactory settlement consists in placing the island under her sovereignty. Both Russia so far as the various Russian groups and political associations represented in Paris may be allowed to speak for Russia Denmark and the United States of America have expressed themselves in favour of the Norwegian claim, which is also warmly supported by France, Italy, and Japan. Even Sweden has not nor is expected to make any really serious opposition, although she has intimated that the course she prefers is a Norwegian mandate.6. It was in these circumstances that I decided not to allow our country alone to stand forth as the opponent of a settlement which met with practically unanimous assent, and which has much to recommend it on its merits. I accordingly instructed our representative on the committee of the conference dealing with this question to concentrate his efforts on securing all necessary guarantees for the maintenance and legitimate development of all British rights. Our efforts in this direction have met, and are meeting, with the readiest response, and I have no doubt that the draft convention now being prepared by the Committee will be found to give every satisfaction in this respect.7. I hope you will agree, and the Cabinet approve, that provided all our legitimate requirements are amply and firmly secured by the Convention, it would be not only unnecessary as well as ungracious, but would be bad policy for us to incur the odium of thwarting the not unreasonable and on the whole modest ambitions of a State which during the war has done much to deserve our gratitude, and of upsetting a reasonable arrangement with a friendly Government for the sake of an apprehended movement of public opinion in England which, I fear, may prove on closer analysis to be rather the result of an artificial agitation by interested parties than the genuine expression of national feeling. It is, unfortunately, notorious that some of the British companies having interests in Spitsbergen were promoted, and have conducted their operations, in circumstances not deserving to be measured by the highest standards; and I under-stand that considerable doubt has been expressed from time to time by the Board of Trade as to the amount of support which it would be desirable, or even proper, for His Majesty&apos;s Government to give to some of the promoters in these concerns. Nevertheless, I need hardly assure your Lordship that the recognition of any definite regime in Spitsbergen by His Majesty&apos;s Government will be made unequivocally dependent on the complete safeguarding of all British rights and well-established claims.8. I transmit herewith the preliminary draft of the treaty as tentatively drawn up in the committee of. the Conference, the general lines of which I have provisionally approved, although minor amendments will, no doubt, have to be made in some respects. An^ explanatory memorandum by Mr. Tufton accompanies the draft. Although His Majesty&apos;s Goverment, are, of course, not finally committed to anything not actually passed by the Supreme Council, the matter has reached a stage when a reversal of the
British attitude in the face of the unanimous recommendation of the other Powers will not merely cause great inconvenience and delay at a time when the Conference is working at high pressure to get through its programme, but will in all probability lead to a complete deadlock, with the result that no settlement at all will be arrived at, a result which I feel sure is to be deprecated in every way.9. I would add that I have no means of compelling the committee of the Conference or the Council of Five, contrary to the established practice, to listen to the verbal explanations of private individuals interested in the commercial development of Spitsbergen, and I cannot undertake that if representatives of the British companies are sent out to Paris, as your Lordship proposes should be done, that they will obtain a hearing. The proper course to adopt is, in my opinion, for the British interests concerned to make their representations to your Lordship, and for such conditions to be inserted in the proposed treaty as will protect their legitimate interests. I have no hesitation in stating that, in my opinion, the establishment of Norwegian sovereignty over Spitsbergen constitutes no hindrance to British interests receiving all the consideration which can rightly be claimed, for them.I am, &amp;c.(For Mr. Balfour), (Signed)        EYRE A. CROWE.Memorandum by Mr. Tufton.I SUBMIT herewith the text of a draft convention on the subject of the future of Spitsbergen. This text is the outcome of the labours of the Spitsbergen Committee up to date, but it should be noted that none of the interested neutral Powers except Norway have yet been heard by the Committee; both the Russians and the Swedes have put in memoranda, many of the points in which are already covered by the present text of the Treaty.The Treaty is drawn up to recognise the complete sovereignty of Norway over the islands, and all the Signatory Powers are treated as being on an absolute equality.Article 1 defines the territories in question without any mention of territorial waters, as the Admiralty representatives desired all mention of territorial waters to be omitted.Article 2 is designed to protect the fauna and flora of Spitsbergen, which has suffered abnormally from the depredations of hunters of all nationalities.Article 3 is designed to provide for complete equality for all signatory Powers and their nationals in all that relates to commerce, industry, and shipping. It is, perhaps, too much compressed, and will possibly have to be expanded into two or three separate articles. This is, I think, a matter for the Board of Trade to consider in London, and, if you agree, I propose to send a copy privately to Mr. Fountain for his observations.Article 4 deals with wireless telegraphy, and whilst recognising the right of Norway, if she obtains sovereignty over Spitsbergen, to reserve one or more particular stations for international correspondence, provides that persons or companies shall have the right to use their own wireless installations for their own purposes. Our companies have already one or two stations, and the Swedish companies also.Article 5 provides for the establishment of an international meteorological station, to which the Admiralty and the Air Ministry attach importance.Article 6 is, perhaps, the most important for British interests. It recognises the validity of all acquired rights, and as regards claims to land, it lays down in an Annex the procedure to be followed.All claims must be submitted with full details within a short specified period to an arbitrator, who, it is proposed, shall be selected by the Government of Denmark from the ranks of eminent Danish lawyers. The idea of requesting the Danish Government to nominate the arbitrator, whoso preliminary duties will be merely to sort out the contested from the uncontested claims, emanated from the Italian delegate on the Committee, who pointed out that the selection of such a person would go far to inspire confidence in Norway and Sweden, and he thought in England also. The original British proposal was that the preliminary arbitrator to verify the claims should be selected by the President of the United States, but both Mr. Malkin, who was preseut at this meeting, and I myself saw no objection to the Italian proposal, and we agreed to embody it in our scheme.   This Danish arbitrator (who will be described during his
preliminary function as &quot; Commissioner&quot;) will prepare a statement showing precisely those claims which in his opinion should be recognised at once, and the Norwegian Goverment will be obliged to take necessary steps to confer on those claimants a valid title to their property.Claims which the Commissioner does not recommend will then come before a Court of Arbitration, consisting of the Danish Commissioner, who will be President of the Court, and arbitrators nominated by Governments whose nationals possess claims in Spitsbergen.Certain rules for the guidance of the Tribunal in arriving at their decisions have been laid down. The expenses of the Tribunal will be provided by all claimants depositing sums in proportion to the area of land claimed, an arrangement which will, it is hoped, have the advantage of excluding exorbitant and unreasonable claims which cannot be substantiated.Article 7 is designed to provide that in future all nationals of the High Con-tracting Parties will be on a footing of absolute equality in all that relates to the acquisition, enjoyment, and exercise of the rights of ownership of property in Spitsbergen. A special provision has been inserted whereby expropriation may only be resorted to on grounds of public utility and after full compensation, because the Norwegians have intimated to the Committee that they would like the right to expropriate for other purposes as well, but the Committee does not think this just or equitable.Article 8 obliges Norway to draw up and submit for the approval of the signatory Powers mining regulations for Spitsbergen, and the Treaty will not come into force until these regulations have been approved.Article 9 is designed for the demilitarisation of the islands, although a loophole is left to Norway to use them for military purposes if the League of Nations decides that it is necessary for any particular purpose.Article 10 provides for the accession of other Powers than signatories and for the ratification, and provides that both the English and French texts will be authentic.I would propose, with your concurrence, to send this draft Convention to the Foreign Office, asking them to submit their observations upon it to Mr. Balfour with the least possible delay. I would also propose to circulate it to the Naval, Military, and Air Sections of the Delegation here for their observations also.No provision has yet been made in the Treaty stipulating that taxation raised in Spitsbergen shall only be applied for the needs of the Islands, and it is possible that stipulations should be made providing for the right of sending Consular Officers there.Paris, August 14, 1919.
Draft Convention relating to Spitsbergen, including Bear Island.THE President of the United States of America ; His Majesty the King of Great Britain and Ireland and of the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India; His Majesty the King of Denmark; the President of the French Republic; His Majesty the King of Italy ; His Majesty the Emperor of Japan; His Majesty the King of Norway ; Her Majesty the Queen of the Netherlands; His Majesty the King of Sweden;Desirous of recognising definitively the sovereignty of Norway over the Spitsbergen Archipelago, including Bear Island, and of seeing this territory provided with an equitable regime assuring its development and peaceful utilisation;Have deputed as their respective Pleni-potentiaries with a view of concluding a convention to this effect:The President.of the United States of America :His Majesty the King of Great Britain and Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India :His Majesty the King of Denmark : The President of the French Republic : His Majesty of King of Italy : His Majesty the Emperor of Japan : His Majesty the King of Norway : Her Majesty the Queen of the Nether-His Majesty the King of Sweden:Who, having exchanged their full powers, found in due and proper form, have agreed to the following provisions : Article 1.The high contracting parties have agreed to recognise the full and absolute sovereignty of Norway over the archipelago of Spits-[713]Projet de Convention relative au Spitsberg, y compris Vile aux Ours.LE President des Etats-Unis d&apos;Amerique; Sa Majeste le Roi de Grande-Bretagne et dTrlande et des Territoires britanniques au dela des Mers, Empereur des Indes; Sa Majeste le Roi de Danemark ; le President de la Republique frangaise; Sa Majeste le Roi dTtalie; Sa Majeste 1&apos;Empereur du Japon ; Sa Majeste le Roi de Norvege ; Sa Majeste la Reine des Pays-Pas; Sa Majeste le Roi de Suede ;Desireux, en reconnaissant definitivement la souverainete de la Norvege sur 1&apos;archipel du Spitsberg, y compris 1&apos;ile aux Ours, de voir ces regions pourvues d&apos;un regime equitable propre a en assurer la mise en valeur et 1&apos;utilisation pacifique ;Ont designe pour leurs Plenipotentiaires respectifs en vue de conclure une conven-tion a cet effet, savoir :Le President des Etats-Unis d&apos;Amenque:Sa Majeste le Roi de Grande-Bretagne et dTrlande et des Territoires britanniques au dela des Mers, Empereur des Iudes :Sa Majeste le Roi de Danemark :Le President de la Republique francaise :Sa Majeste le Roi dTtalie :Sa Majeste 1&apos;Empereur du Japon :Sa Majeste le Roi de Norvege :Sa Majeste la Reine des Pays-Bas :Sa Majeste le Roi de Suede :Lesquels, apres avoir echange leurs pleins pouvoirs, reconnus en bonne et due forme, sont convenus des stipulations ci-apres :Article ler.Les hautes parties contractantes:sont d&apos;accord pour reconnaitre, dans les condi-tions stipulees par la presente Convention,c
bergen, comprising, with Bear Island, or Beeren-Eiland, all the islands situated between 10&quot; and 35Q longitude east of Greenwich and between 74c and 8I0 latitude north, especially West Spitsbergen, North-East Land, Barents Island, Edge Island, King Charles Land, Hope Island, or Hopen-Eiland, and Prince Charles Island, together with all islands, great or small, and rocks appertaining thereto.la pleine et entiere souverainete&quot; de la Norvege sur 1&apos;archipel du Spitsberg com-prenant, avec Pile aux Ours, ou Beeren-Eiland, toutes les lies situees entre les TO0 et 3o0 de longitude est de Greenwich et entre les 74D et 8I0 de latitude nord, notamment : le Spitsberg occidental, la terre du nord-est, 1&apos;ile de Barents, Pile d&apos;Edge, la terre du Eoi Charles, 1&apos;ile d&apos;Esperance ou Hopen-Eiland, et Pile du Prince Charles, ensemble les lies, ilots et rochers qui en dependent.Article 2.Ships and nationals of all the high con-tracting parties shall enjoy equally the rights of fishing and hunting in the terri-tories specified in article 1 and in their territorial waters.Norway shall be free to maintain, take, or decree suitable measures to ensure the preservation and, if necessary, the reconsti-tution of the fauna and flora of the said regions and their territorial waters, it being clearly understood that these measures shall always be applicable equally to the nationals of all the high contracting parties without any exception, privilege, or favour whatso-ever, direct or indirect, to the advantage of any one of them.Owners whose rights have been recog-nised in accordance with the terms of articles 6 and 7 will enjoy the exclusive right of hunting on their own land, subject to the regulations made by the Norwegian Government with the conditions laid down in the present article.Article 2.Les navires et ressortissants de toutes les hautes parties contractantes seront egalement admis a 1&apos;exercice du droit de peche et de chasse dans les regions visees a Particle lcr et leurs eaux territoriales.11 appartiendra a la Norvege de main-tenir, prendre ou ddicter les mesures prop res a assurer la conservation et, s&apos;il y a lieu, la reconstitution de la faune et de la flore dans lesdites regions et leurs eaux territoriales, etant entendu que ces mesures devront toujours etre egalement applicables aux ressortissants de toutes les hautes parties contractantes, sans exceptions, privileges et faveurs quelconques, directs ou indirects, au profit de Pune quelconque dentre el les.Les occupants dont les droits seront reconnus selon les termes des articles G et 7 jouiront du droit exclusif de chasse sur leurs fonds de terre, sous reserve de Pdbservation des reglements ddict&amp;s par le Gouvernement norvegien dans les conditions enoncees au present article.Article 3.The nationals of all the high contracting parties shall have equal liberty of access and entry for any reason or object what-ever to the waters, fjords, and ports of the territories specified in article 1; subject to the observance of local laws and regulations they may carry on there without impedi-ment all maritime, industrial, and com-mercial operations on a footing of absolute equality.They shall be admitted under the same conditions of equality to the exercise and practice of all maritime, industrial, or commercial enterprises m both on land and in the territorial waters, and no monopoly shall be established on any account or for any enterprise whatever.Ships of the high contracting parties going to Spitsbergen shall have the right to put into Norwegian ports on tneir outward or homeward voyage, withoutArticle 3.Les ressortissants de toutes les hautes parties contractantes auront une egale liberte d&apos;acces et de relache, pour quelque cause et objet que ce soit, dans les eaux, fjords et ports des regions visees a Particle lcr; ils pourront s&apos;y livrer sans aucune entrave, sous reserve de 1&apos;obser-vation des lois et reglements locaux, a toutes operations maritimes, industrielles et commerciales sur un pied de parfaite egalite.Ils seront admis, dans les memes conditions d^galite, a Pexercice et a Pexploitation de toutes entreprises mari-times, industrielles ou commerciales, tant a terre que dans les eaux territoi iales, sans qu&apos;aucun monopole, a aucun egard et pour quelque entreprise que ce soit, puisse etre etabli.Les navires des hautes parties contrac-tantes se rendant au Spitsberg auront le droit de relacher tant a Pailer qu&apos;au retour dans les ports norvegiens, sans que cela
Article 4.All wireless telegraphy stations estab-lished or to be established within the territories referred to in article 1 shall always be open on a footing of absolute equality to communications from ships of all nations and from nationals of the high contracting parties, under the conditions laid down in the Wireless Telegraphy Convention of the 5th July, 1912, or in the subsequent international convention which replaces it.Subject to international obligations arisino- out of a state of war, owners of landed property in Spitsbergen shall always be at liberty to establish and make use for their own purposes of wireless tele-graph installations, which shall be free to communicate on the private business of the owners with fixed or moving wireless stations, including ships and aircraft.Article 4.Toute station de telegraphie sans fil etablie ou a etablir dans les regions visdes a 1&apos;article ler pourra toujours etre ouverte sur un pied de parfaite egalite&quot; aux com-munications des navires de tous pavilions et des ressortissants des hautes parties contractantes, dans les conditions prevues par la Convention radio-telegraphique du 5 juillet 1912, ou de la Convention inter-nationale qui serait conclue pour etre substitute a celle-ci.Sous reserve des obligations inter-nationales resultant d&apos;un etat de guerre, toute exploitation ou entreprise pourra etablir et utiliser pour ses propres affaires des installations de telegraphie sans fil, qui pourront entrer en communication, dans le but indique, avec des postes fixes ou mobiles de telegraphie sans fil, y compris les navires et les aeronefs.Article 5.The high contracting parties recognise the utility of establishing an international meteorological station in Spitsbergen, the organisation of which shall form the subject of a subsequent convention.Article 6.Subject to the provisions of the present article, acquired rights of nationals of the high contracting parties shall be recog-nised.Claims arising from the possession or occupation of land before the signature of the present treaty shall be dealt with in accordance with Annex &quot; A.&quot;Article 5.Les hautes parties contractantes recon-naissent 1&apos;utilite fdune station mdteoro-logique international au Spitsberg dont l&apos;organisation fera 1&apos;objet dune convention ulterieure.Article 6.Sous reserve des dispositions du present article, les droits acquis appartenant -aux ressortissants de hautes parties contrac-tantes seront reconnus valables.Les reclamations relativement aux droits resultant de prises de possession ou d&apos;occu-pation anterieures a la signature du present traite seront reglees d&apos;apres les dispositions de 1&apos;Annexe &quot;A&quot; ci-joint.Article 7. Article 7.Norway undertakes to grant to all La Norvege sengage a accorder a tous nationals of the high contracting parties   les ressortissants des hautes parties con-that being considered an infraction of any soit considere cornme une infraction aux rules about coasting trade which may be regies du cabotage qui pourraient 6tre en in force in Norway. vigueur en Norvege.It is agreed that in every respect and II est entendu qua tout egard et notam-especially with regard to exports, imports, ment en tout ce qui concerne 1&apos;exportation, and goods in transit, the Norwegian 1&apos;importation et le transit, il ne pourra Government will not take any step nor  tre pris par le Gouvernment norvegien seek to impose any duty or restriction aucune mesure ni edicte aucun droit ou whatever in the area defined in article I restriction quelconque qui puissent etre above, either as regards the high contract- appliques aux regions visees a 1&apos;article lcr ing parties, or their nationals, ships, or taut aux hautes parties contractantes qu&apos; a goods, unless similar treatment is applied leurs ressortissants et aux navires ou in the same areas to Norway, and her marchandises de ceux-ci, a moins quun nationals, ships, and goods. pareil traitement ne soit applicable en cequi concerne les memes regions a la Norvege, a ses ressortissants et aux navires ou marchandises de ceux-ci.
treatment based on complete equality and in conformity with the stipulations of the present treaty, with regard to methods of acquisition, enjoyment, and exercise of the right of ownership of property in Spits-bergen.Expropriation may be resorted to solely on grounds of public utility, and then only on payment of proper compensation.tractantes, en ce qui concerne les modes d&apos;acquisition, lajouissance et 1&apos;exercice du droit de propriete au Spitsberg, un traite-ment base sur une parfaite egalite et conforme aux stipulations du present traitc.II ne pourra etre effectue d&apos;expropriation que pour cause d&apos;utilite publique et contre le versement d&apos;une juste indemnity.Article 8.Norway undertakes to provide for the territories specified in article 1 mining regulations which, especially from the point of view of imposts, taxes, or charges of any kind, and of general or particular labour conditions shall exclude all privileges, monopolies, or favours for the benefit of the nationals of any one of the high contracting parties, including Norway, and assure to the paid staff of all categories security of wages and the necessary protection of their physical, moral, and intellectual welfare.The Norwegian Government shall not levy in Spitsbergen any tax, due or duty in general, which differs from or exceeds in amount taxes, &amp;c, paid by Norwegian subjects in Norway.So far as the exportation of minerals is concerned, the Norwegian Government shall have the right to levy an export duty which shall not exceed 1 per cent, of the maximum value of the minerals exported up to 100,000 tons, and after that quantity a diminishing proportion. The value shall bo fixed at the end of the navigation season by calculating the average f.o.b. price obtained.Three months before the date of their coming into force, the regulations outlined in the first paragraph shall be communi-cated by the Norwegian Government to the other high contracting parties. If during this period one or more of the said Powers propose to modify these regulations before they are applied, such proposals shall be communicated by the Norwegian Government to the other signatory Powers of the present Treaty, in order that they may be submitted to examination by and the decision of a Commission composed of one representative of each of those of the said signatory Powers to the present con-vention who shall express a desire to that effect.Article 9.Subject to the rights and duties resulting from the admission of Norway to the League of Nations, Norway undertakesArticle 8.La Norvege s&apos;engage a pourvoir las regions visdes a 1&apos;article V d&apos;un regime minier qui, notamment au point de vue des impots, taxes ou redevances de toute nature, des conditions generales ou particu-lieres du travail, devra exclure tous privileges, monopoles, vu favours au profit des ressortissants dune des hautes parties contractantes, y compris la Norvege, et assurer au personnel salarie de toutes categories les garanties de salaire et ,de protection necessaires a leur bien-etre physique, moral, et intellectuel.Le Gouvernement norvegien ne pourra percevoir dans 1&apos;archipel du Spitsberg aucun impot,taxe ou droit en gendralquidiffererait ou qui serait d&apos;un montant superieur a ceux auxquels sont soumis les sujets norvegiens en Norvege.En ce qui concerne 1&apos;exportation des minerals, le Gouvernement norvegien aura la faculte d&apos;etablir une taxe k 1&apos;exportation qui ne pourra pas etre superieure a 1 pour cent sur le maximum de la valeur des minerais exportes jusqua concurrence de 100,000 tonnes, et puis selon une proportion deeroissante. La valeur serait ddterminee a la fin de la periode de navigation en cal-culant le prix f.o.b. obtenu en moyenne.Trois mois avaut la date de sa xnise en vigueur, la reglementation preVue au premier alinea devra etre cornmuniquee par le Gouvernement norvegien aux hautes parties contractantes. Si dans ce delai une ou plusieurs desdites Puissances pro-posaient dapporter des modifications a cette reglementation avant qu&apos;ellesoit appliquee, ces propositions seraient communiquees par le Gouvernement norvegien aux autres Puissances signataires du present traite&quot;, pour etre soumises a 1&apos;examen et a la decision d&apos;une Commission composed d&apos;un representant de chacune de celles desdites Puissances signataires de la presente con-vention qui en exprimerait le desir.Article 9.Sous reserve des droits et devoirs pouvant resulter pour la Norvege de son adhesion  a  la  SocieTe des  Nations, la
not to create nor to allow the establish-ment of any naval base in the territories specified in article 1, and not to construct any fortification in the said territories which may never be used for warlike purposes.Article 10.Until the recognition by the high contracting parties of a Russian Govern -ment permits Russia to adhere to the present treaty, Russian subjects shall enjoy the same rights as nationals of the high contracting parties.Claims in Spitsbergen which they may have to put forward shall be presented under the conditions laid down in this treaty (article 6 and annex) through the inter-mediary of the Danish Government, who declare their willingness to lend their good offices for this purpose.Article 11.Third Powers will be invited by the Government of the French Republic to the present convention. This adhesion shall be effected by a communication addressed to the French Government, who will undertake to notify the other contracting parties.The present convention, of which the French and English texts are both authentic, shall be ratified.Ratifications shall be deposited in Paris as soon as possible.Extra-European Powers may confine their action to informing the Government of the French Republic, through their diplomatic representative in Paris, that their ratification has been given, and, in this case they shall transmit the instrument as soon as possible.The present convention, duly ratified by each of the high contracting parties, shall come into force at the same time as the mining regulations referred to in article 8.In witness whereof the above-named plenipotentiaries have signed.Done at Paris, the 1919, induplicate, one copy to be transmitted to the Government of His Majesty the King of Norway, and one deposited in the archives of the French Republic, and of which authenticated copies will be trans-mitted to the other signatory Powers.Norvege s&apos;engage a, ne crder et a ne laisser s^tablir aucune base navale dans les rep-ions vis^es a 1&apos;article ler, a ne construire aucune fortification dans lesdites regions, qui ne devront jamais etre utilisees dans un but de guerre.Article 10.En attendant que la reconnaissance par les hautes parties contractantes d&apos;un Gouvernement russe permette a, la Russie d&apos;adherer au present traite, les sujets russes jouiront des memes droits que les ressortissants des hautes .parties contrac-tantes.Les reclamations quils auraient a faire valoir au Spitsberg seront presentees, dans les conditions stipulees par le present traite (article 6 et annexe), par les soins du Gouvernement danois, qui declare prefer volontiers ses bons offices a cet effet.Article 11.Les tierces Puissances seront invitees par le Gouvernernent de la Republique francaise a adherer au present traite. Cette adhesion sera effectude par voie de notification adressee au Gouvernement frangais, a qui il appartiendra d&apos;en aviser les autres parties contractantes.La presente convention, dont les textes frangais et anglais font fbi, sera ratified.Le depot des ratifications sera effectue a Paris, le plus tot qu&apos;il sera possible.Les Puissances dont le Gouvernement a son siege hors d&apos;Europe auront la faculte&quot; de se burner a faire connattre au Gcuverne-ment de la Republique francaise, par leur representant diplomatique a Paris, que leur ratification a ete donnee et, dans ce cas, elles devront en transmettre 1&apos;instrument aussitdt que faire se pourra.Le present traite&quot;, diiment ratine&quot; par chacune des hautes parties contractantes, entrera en vigueur en meme temps que le regime minier prevu a 1&apos;article 8.En foi de quoi les plenipotentiaires susnommes out signe&quot;.Fait a Paris, le 1919, endeux exemplaires, dont un sera remis au Gouvernement de Sa Majeste&apos; le Roi de Norvege et un restera depose&quot; dans les archives du Gouvernement de la Repu-blique francaise, et dont les expeditions authentiques seront remises aux autres Puissances signataires.
ANNEX (A).Article 1.1. Within three months from the coming into force of the present Treaty, notifica-tion of all claims to land which had been made before the signature of the present Treaty must be sent by the Government of the claimant to a Commissioner charged to examine such claims. The Commissioner will be a judge or jurisconsult of Danish nationality possessing the necessary qualifications for the task, and shall be nominated by the Danisii Government.2. The notification must include a precise delimitation of the land claimed, and be accompanied by a map on a scale of not less than f ooouoo on which the laud claimed is clearly marked.3. The notification must be accompanied by the deposit of a sum of Id. Cor each acre of land claimed, to defray the expenses of the examination of the claims.4. The Commissioner will be entitled to require from the claimants any further documents or information which he may consider necessary.5. The Commissioner will examine the claims so notified. For this purpose he will be entitled to avail himself of such expert assistance as he may consider necessary, and in case of need to cause investigations to be carried out on the spot.6. The remuneration of the Commissioner will be fixed by agreement between the Danish Government and the other Govermnents concerned. The Commissioner will fix the remuneration of such assistants as he may consider it necessary to employ.7. The Commissioner, after examining the claims, will prepare a statement showing precisely the claims which he is of opinion should be recognised at once, and those which, either because they are disputed or for any other reason, he is of opinion should be submitted to arbitration as hereafter provided. Copies of this statement will be forwarded by the Commissions to the Governments concerned.8. If the amount of the sums deposited in accordance with paragraph 3 is insufficient to cover the expenses of the examination of the claims, the Commissioner will, in every case where he is of opinion that a claim should be recognised, at once state what further sum the claimant should be required to pay towards the expenses of the examination. This sum will be based on the amount of the laud to which the claimants title is recognised.If the sums deposited in accordance with paragraph 3 exceed the expenses of the examination, the balance will be devoted to the cost of the arbitration hereafter provided for.9. Within three months from the date of the statement referred to in paragraph 7 of this Article, the Norwegian Government shall take the necessary steps to confer upon claimants whose claims have been recognised by the Commissioner a valid title securing to them the exclusive property in the land in question, in accordance with the laws and regulations in force or to be enforced in Spitsbergen, and subject to the Mining Regulations referred to in Article      of the present Treaty.In the event, however, of a further payment being required in accordance with paragraph 8 of this Article, a provisional title only will be delivered, which title will become definitive on payment by the claimant of the further sum required of him.Article 2.Claims which for any reason the Commissioner referred to in paragraph I of the preceding Article has not recognised as valid will be settled in accordance with the following provisions: 1. Within three months from the date of the statement referred to in paragraph 7 of the preceding Article, each of the Governments whose nationals have been found to possess claims which have not been recognised will appoint an arbitrator. The Commissioner will be the President of the Tribunal so constituted. The President will nominate a secretary to receive the documents referred to in paragraph 2 of this Article, and to make the necessary arrangements for the meeting of&apos; the Tribunal.2. Within one month from the appointment of the secretary referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article, the claimants concerned will send to him through the intermediary of their respective Governments statements indicating precisely their claims, and accompanied by such documents and arguments as they may wish to submit in support thereof.
3. Within two months from the appointment of the secretary referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article, the Tribunal shall meet at Copenhagen for the purpose of dealing with the claims which have been submitted to it.4. The language of the Tribunal shall be English. Documents or arguments may be submitted to it in any of the Scandinavian languages, but in that case must be accompanied by an English translation.5 .The claimants shall be entitled, if they so desire, to be heard by the Tribunal either in person or by agents, and the Tribunal shall be entitled to call upon the claimants to present such further explanations, documents, or arguments as it may think necessary.6. Beforo the hearing of any case the Tribunal shall require from the parties a deposit or security for such sum as it may think recessary to cover the share of each party in the expenses of the Tribunal. In fixing the amount of such sum the Tribunal shall base itself principally on the extent of the land claimed. The Tribunal shall also have power to demand a further deposit from the parties in such cases.7. The salaries of the arbitrators shall be per month, unless theGovernments concerned agree otherwise. The salary of the secretary and any other persons employed by the Tribunal shall be fixed by the President.8. Subject to the provisions of this Annex the Tribunal shall have full power to regulate its own procedure.9. In dealing with the claims the Tribunal shall take into consideration: (a.) Such established rules of international law as it may consider to be applicable; (6.) The general principles of justice and equity; (c.) The following circumstances :(i.) The date on which the land claimed was first occupied by the claimant;(ii.) The date on which the claim was notified to the Government of the claimant;(iii.) The extent to which the claimant has developed and exploited his claim. In this connection the Tribunal shall take into account the extent to which the claimants who are nationals of States who took part in the war of 1914-19 may have been prevented from developing their claims by conditions or restrictions which did not apply to nationals of neutral States.10. All the expenses cf the Tribunal shall be divided among the claimants in such proportion as the Tribunal shall decide. If the amount of the sums paid in accordance with paragraph (6) is larger than the expenses of the Tribunal, the balance shall be returned to the parties whose claims have been recognised in such proportion as the Tribunal shall think fit.11. The decisions of the Tribunal will be communicated by it to the Governments concerned, including in every case the Norwegian Government.The Norwegian Government shall within three months from the receipt of each decision take the necessary steps to confer upon the claimants whose claims have been recognised by the Tribunal a valid title to the land in question, in accordance with the laws and regulations in force or to be enacted in Spitsbergen, and subject to the Mining Regulations referred to in Article of the present treaty. Nevertheless, the titles so conferred can only become definitive on the payment by the claimant concerned of his share of the expenses of the Tribunal.Article 3.Any claims which are not notified to the Commissioner in accordance with paragraph (1) of Article 1, or which not having been recognised by him are not submitted to the Tribunal in accordance with Article 2 will be finally extinguished.
Enclosure (B).INASMUCH as the policy proposed in the accompanying draft despatch to Mr. Balfour is likely (as indeed would be any policy on the suhject) to be made the subject of some controversy, I would like to be assured that it has the approval of the Cabinet.CURZON OF KEDLESTON.August 9, 1919.Sir, Foreign Office, August     , 1919.In my despatch No. 48G6 of the 21st ultimo I had the honour to forward to you a memorandum drawn up in this Department in regard to Spitsbergen. Since that date I have devoted some consideration to the various possible forms of settlement of this question, especially from the point of view of His Majesty&apos;s Government.It appears that there are three possible methods of settlement which could be applied to the problem. (1) Annexation by some&apos;Power. (2) Internationalisation or condominium.   (3) A mandate under the League of Nations.With regard to the first solution, there exists, as you are already aware, a certain party in this country which favours annexation by Great Britain. For various reasons, however, this solution cannot be entertained, and I do not propose to deal further with the arguments bearing upon it.The only other Power which could lay any apparently reasonable claim to annexation would appear to be Norway. There is, however, no doubt that such a solution would give rise to a violent outburst of British public opinion, which has become deeply interested in these islands, where British commercial interests already occupy a very predominant position, and which would regard this manner of dealing with the question as a betrayal of these interests. Such a solution of the question is therefore, in my opinion, impracticable.2. As regards a settlement by internationalisation or condominium, I would remind you that the Powers represented at the Spitsbergen Conference in 1914 bad under consideration the administration of the island by a Commissioner under the control of a Commission composed of representatives of Prussia, Sweden, and Norway, to sit in the capital of the President of the Commission. At the moment when the labours of the Commission were interrupted by the war, this scheme was on the point of breaking down owing to the insistence of Germany upon representation. The memory of this attitude on the part of Germany led the Allied Powers more recently (1918) to agree that in any future arrangements for the island, if Germany claimed representation, Great Britain and France should also be represented, in order to counterbalance any possible combination between Germany and liussia to out-vote Norway.It is claimed in favour of a condominium that it would carry out more closely than any other scheme the settlement proposed in 1914; that Germany could now be ruled out altogether and representation only granted to the Powers actually interested; that the island would be neutralised and the members of the condominium would give a joint guarantee against its use as a naval base ; and that it would possibly prove more agreeable to Sweden than the other alternative, while British mining interests would more easily be protected against objectionable foreign laws.On the other hand, consideration was given to this form of Government in connection with the problem of the future administration of the German colonies. As a result, this method of Government has been universally discarded in favour of the mandatory system. Previous attempts at internationalisation or condominurn have, with scarcely an exception, proved unsuccessful, and have been abandoned. In Crete and in Egypt the system has been superseded by historical development, while in the New Hebrides and Samoa it has been a complete and admitted failure. In a country like Spitsbergen, where the conflicting claims of various commercial companies already form
the subject of somewhat acrimonious controversy, government by condominium on which several countries would be represented with equal powers and where none could claim a predominant voice might easily tend to aggravate the situation. Moreover, this solution would not fulfil the conditions set forth by the Admiralty (of which you have already been informed in the memorandum referred to), because there would exist no force at the immediate disposal of the guaranteeing Powers to prevent one powerful nation from seizing the island in order to use it as a naval base. On the other hand, the argument may be used that it would be easier for Great Britain than for any other Power to forestall an attempt to make a naval base on these islands, since Great Britain, being one of the guaranteeing Powers, could take quicker action than if prior cousulta-tion with the League of Nations under the next ensuing alternative were necessary.3. The third solution by which the islands would be placed under a mandate would be more in accordance with the principles of the League of Nations than either of the other alternatives. It would not be desirable for His Majesty&apos;s Government to put forward a claim of their own to such a mandate, nor would it be advisable from the point of view of British interests for a mandate to be granted to any other Great Power. If, therefore, a mandate is given, Norway seems to be the only suitable country which could receive it. It is also apparent that, as a point of practical politics, it might be advantageous for His Majesty&apos;s Government to support this solution. In the first place, they would thus secure a useful lever and a strong claim for obtaining a satisfactory solution of British claims and protection for British interests. Secondly, the claims of Norway to some consideration in view of her attitude during the war, in particular as regards the services of the Norwegian Mercantile Marine in the Allied cause, have already been brought to my notice. To support Norway&apos;s claim to a mandate in Spitsbergen would be an excellent method of making some return from this point of view. Thirdly, for general political i&apos;easons it would appear desirable for His Majesty&apos;s Government to support this solution, partly from the point of view of friendly Anglo-Norwegian relations, the importance of which has been amply illustrated during the war, and partly in order in some measure to correct the impression, which undoubtedly prevails abroad, that His Majesty&apos;s Government have already secured immense advantages and privileges themselves by being given mandates in other parts of the world.For the above reasons I am disposed to think that the attitude of the British members on the Spitsbergen Commission might well be to support the grant to Norway of a mandate over the islands.With regard to the interests of British companies, it appears to me be essential that those companies mainly concerned should be given every opportunity of laying their views before the British members of the Commission. I therefore propose to invite such companies to send representatives to Paris forthwith to explain the position in regard to their claims.Memorandum.Tlie political aspects of the Spitsbergen question have been dealt with so fully in the past in a series of memoranda that it only seems necessary to provide connecting links betAveen them and to bring the subject up to date.The liiston of the islands down to the break-up of the Spitsbergen Conference in 1914 is dealt with in Mr. Malkin&apos;s memorandum of the 18th November, 1916 (Annex (A)).The further history during the first three years of the war is dealt with by Mr. Howard Smith&apos;s memorandum of the 17th July, 1917 (Annex (B)), which was printed as a War Cabinet Memorandum (G.T.-1494).In March 1918 the &quot; Times &quot; published an article on the alleged existence of a clause in the Treaty of Brest-Litovsk, from which it appeared that the German and Russian Governments had come to an agreement by which Germany would obtain a seat on the next International Spitsbergen Commission.In order to counteract the predominating influence of Germany, it was proposed to obtain the concurrence of the other States interested to representation by Great Britain and France. The position on this point is clearly set out in Foreign Office memorandum of the 29th June, 1918 (Annex (C)), which was submitted to the War Cabinet.
In May of the present year (1919) it was considered that as the question of Spitsbergen was liable to come up at the Peace Conference, it would be advisable to find out if the Admiralty had for any reason changed their last expression of views on the strategical importance of the island.On the 14th June, 1919, a letter was accordingly addressed to their Lordships enquiring whether they were still of the opinion that the island would be of no value as a naval base, and that His Majesty&apos;s Government should therefore confine themselves to taking diplomatic measures to secure that the control of the island should be either in the hands of a friendly nation or a powerful neutral.On the 4th July the Admiralty replied that they did not wish to develop Spits-bergen in British naval interests, but that they considered that some of the harbours on the west coast could be developed by any of the Great Powers in such a way as to prove a threat to British naval interest, and that they therefore considered that the island should be neutralised and administered by an international commission.Politically, therefore, the position seems to be as follows : Throughout the seventeenth, eighteenth, and nineteenth centuries there appear to be no historical grounds upon which any one country can base a claim to sovereignty. It is clear that the British claims the seventeenth century claims which were intermittently acknowledged by the Dutch were afterwards allowed to lapse. The claims of the Dutch, Russians, Danes, and Scandinavians arc equally unconvincing; nor should it be maintained, as Sir Douglas Mawson urges, that His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment are committed by their policy with regard to unclaimed lands north of Canada to acknowledge out of hand the claims of tlie Norwegians solely on the grounds of propinquity.In any case we can fairly urge that all the Powers which took part in the 1914 Conference admitted that Spitsbergen was a terra nullius, and by so doing tacitly waived all prior claims.   Nothing has occurred since 1914 to alter the position.Politically, therefore, we have no claim to annexation.Strategically, we are only interested to see that Spitsbergen is not made use of by one of the Great Powers for our future detriment.Commercially, we desire to see British claims safeguarded. There are three courses open .to us :(1) Annexation; (2) International administration; (3) Norwegian mandate under the League of Nations.(1.) Annexation is clearly out of the question. We have no historical claim. Such an action would not only endanger our relations with the Scandinavian countries, but would lay us open to the charge of land grabbing.(2.) Under international control we might have greater difficulties in securing claims and privileges than if we were dealing with one country, but, in a minute dated July 1917, Mr. Balfour expressed himself in favour of mternationalisation.(3.) By allowing Norway to receive a mandate under the League of Nations, provided we madefa prior stipulation that British rights especially as to mining laws  were duly safeguarded, we should undoubtedly make a very favourable impression in that country, to which we are under some debt of gratitude for her attitude during the war, and at the same time we should, to a certain extent, undermine the criticism which other countries may direct against us on account of the number of mandates which the British Empire has already received.In case of necessity or of any serious attempt on the part of Norway to prejudice British rights we could bring pressure to bear on Norway by (eg.) threatening the cancellation of the leases of the fishing stations in the South Shetland and other islands.As regards the specific claims of British companies, apart from the general duty to see these safeguarded, it is felt that His Majesty&apos;s Government should not themselves undertake the responsibility of drawing up statements of the claims. This is a matter for the companies themselves, and, should it be thought necessary, they could be requested to forward properly attested statements to the Peace Delegation^ The Foreign Office would of course check the claims and verify the dates of notification, &amp;c.
Annex (A).Spitsbergen is at present and always has been a no-man&apos;s land, and no system of Government exists there. It is believed to possess considerable mineral riches, and mining operations have been commenced or claims staked out by a considerable number of persons of several nationalities. Before the war the nations which were interested by reason of claims of this nature by their nationals were, in a very rough order of importance, Norway, Great Britain, the United States, Sweden, and Russia. There were also a few German claims.In consequence of the operations conducted by prospectors and the commencement of actual mining, the necessity has of recent years become apparent of establishing some form of law and order in Spitsbergen, and also of setting up some organisation which could decide the conflicting claims&quot;of the various parties interested and give a valid title to those whose claims were established.The attitude which Great Britain has always taken up is that she has no political interests in Spitsbergen, and is-only concerned to see that such rights as British claimants may have established there are properly protected.- The three countries which were generally admitted to have most interest in Spitsbergen were Russia, Norway, and Sweden, and for several years attempts were made to induce these three countries to agree upon some scheme satisfactory to them which could be accepted by the other countries concerned. This was not an easy task, because both Norway and Sweden were very much afraid of Russia&apos;s designs on the islands, it being feared that she was anxious to annex them with the possible view of obtaining a good advanced base for a sudden attack on the sea-coast of Norway..Finally, however, the three countries were brought together, and a scheme drawn up by their representatives was submitted to a Conference held at Christiania in June and July 1914, when, in addition to these three countries, there were also represented Great Britain, France, Germany, the United States, Denmark, and Holland. The scheme provided for the administration of Spitsbergen by a commission to be appointed by the three Powers, the other countries represented at the Conference having certain powers of control. The Conference failed to agree, principally because Germany, whose representatives took a much more prominent part in the proceedings than the magnitude of German interests appeared to warrant, insisted on a greater share in the administration of the islands than the three Powers concerned, but more particularly Russia, were prepared to allow her. There were, however, signs that Norway and Sweden were not averse to both Germany and Great Britain being associated on equal terms with the three Powers in the administration of the islands, the idea being that this would&quot; prevent Russia from becoming dominant upon the commission. The Conference finally broke up on the eve of the outbreak of war.During the last two years information has been received showing considerable activity on the part of the Norwegian, Swedish, and Russian interests. Companies with considerable capital have been formed, and it is believed that the American interests have been bought out. On the other, hand, the British interests have been unable to send the usual summer expeditions to develop their holdings and prevent their being &quot;jumped,&quot; and the Foreign Office was given to understand that some of them at any rate might be compelled to sell their claims to one or other of their Scandinavian competitors. On several occasions recently repi-esentations have been made to the Foreign Office as to the desirability of Great Britain annexing the islands.Annex (B).It does not seem necessary to go into the history of Spitsbergen. The present international status of the islands can be put briefly as follows : They are terra nullius in which Great Britain, Denmark, France, Germany, Holland, Norway, Russia, Sweden, and the United States are interested in varying degrees. An International Conference was held in June and July 1914 respecting the administration of the group, but adjourned without reaching a decision. Various claims have been pegged out by British and other companies, hut the titles of any of these companies. or syndicates to the land they claim are in any case shadowy, owing to the fact that there is no sovereign state or central authority from which they could hold such titles. The [713] F
attitude adopted by His Majesty&apos;s Government bas always been tbat tbey have no political interests in Spitsbergen, and they are only concerned to see that such rights as British claimants may have established there are properly protected.At the beginning of the war there were two chief British companies concerned with concessions in Spitsbergen, the Scottish Spitsbergen Syndicate and the Northern Exploration Company. In February and again in November 1915 the latter company wrote to Sir E. Grey urging the annexation of Spitsbergen to the British. Crown. Their arguments in favour of this course were : (1.) Strategical. The importance of. the islands as a coaling station and. naval base on the newr ice-free route to Russia.1 ! 2.) Political. To defeat alleged German designs on the islands after the war. In support of this it should be mentioned that the German Government had established a small wireless station on the islands prior to the war, and that throughout the whole of the International Conference of 1914 the German representatives adopted an attitude arrogating to Germany a much larger share in the administration of the islands than her interests there seemed to warrant.(3.) Commercial. The existence of rich coal, iron ore deposits, as well as marble, magnetite iron, molybdenum, iron and copper pyrites, asbestos, and other minerals.As regards the points made by the company, (1) was clearly for the Admiralty to decide. As to (2), the German wireless station is a low-power station which can only correspond through the stronger Norwegian station, and early in the war the German station was closed and cannot now transmit or receive messages. It is in charge of Norwegian caretakers, and. its German- operators left for Germany early in the war. As matters now stand, the Norwegian Government are scarcely likely to reopen the German, station in the interests of Germany. Apart-from this, the political advantages of annexing Spitsbergen appeared at the time to be very small, and the difficulties connected with any such idea very great. Owing to the peculiar status of Spitsbergen any arbitrary act on our part would almost inevitably embroil Great Britain with one at least of her Allies, namely, Russia, and would create the worst possible effect in Norway and Sweden, the former of which two countries may perhaps be said to have a stronger claim to the island than Great Britain.The commercial aspect of the question, point (3), was not considered fully in November 1915. No operations of any kind would be possible until the summer of 1916, and the only apparent advantage of Great Britain securing a predominant interest in the coalfields at that time was in order to prevent them falling into the hands of Sweden or Norway, and thus making those countries independent of British coal and of the consequent pressure which&apos;Great Britain could in this way exercise on them in contraband questions.Sir E. Grey consequently referred the matter to the Admiralty, proposing to inform the.company that the question could not be considered at the present moment in view of the claims of Allied and neutral countries, which could not be disregarded in settling the question of Spitsbergen. Sir E. Grey also considered that the status of Spitsbergen should be noted for discussion at the end of the war. On the 15th January, 1916, the Admiralty concurred in tho reply proposed by Sir E. Grey.Meanwhile the Northern Exploratiou Company informed Sir E. Grey that in virtue of a prior agreement they were contemplating transferring a large number of their shares to Aktiebolaget Isfjorden-Belsand, a Swedish company, and they at the same time suggested that His Majesty&apos;s Government might think it advantageous to purchase the company!s concessions on the islands. It appeared inequitable to prevent the company from carrying out their obligation to the Swedish company, but it was also feared that if Sweden acquired those rights before the close of the summer she might he in a position to work the mines to her own advantage and thus become, at any rate in part, independent of British coal supplies. It was further reported, though with inconclusive evidence, that the transaction proposed by the company might result in a considerable part of these interests falling into German hands. As to the proposal that His Majesty&apos;s Government should purchase the properties of the company, it did not appear that this was advantageous from a political point of view, even if the company could give a good title, which was doubtful.The Admiralty were again consulted and replied that there were no strategical reasons for acquiring the company&apos;s concessions in the islands. It was, however, thought that the Ministry of Munitions might be interested in the coal and iron and might wish to make; some arrangement with the company for the purchase of the
output. The Ministry of Munitions, however, considered that the property could not be developed in time for the output to be of any importance during the war, and therefore they did not propose to take any action of the nature suggested. The company were accordingly informed on the 24th May, 1916, that His Majesty&apos;s Government did not wish to purchase their properties ; they had previously been requested not to hand over the shares to the Swedish company until the end of the summer, and had been warned that this transaction might possibly lead to a charge of trading with the enemy.In November 191(5 the Northern Exploration Company, the Scottish Syndicate, and Colonel Yate again urged annexation, chiefly for commercial reasons, it being alleged that valuable magnetite, &amp;c, was to be found in the islands. The Ministry of Munitions, however, advised that this had little commercial value and they were not prepared to send an expedition to the islands in 1917 to investigate their mineral resources. The Admiralty again repeated that there were no naval reasons for annexing Spitsbergen, and that a formal annexation without naval force to support it would not prevent the islands being used by the enemy if it should be of any advantage for him to do so, which the -Admiralty clearly doubted.Colonel Yate, who was informed of these views, then urged that in case the Germans should think of using Spitsbergen as a submarine base, one of His Majesty&apos;s ships should be sent to the islands at the opening of the season to remove or destroy the German wireless station. This question was left entirely to the Admiralty, but their views were invited on the whole subject once more in view of the fact that a regular campaign had been opened not only by the companies referred to above, but by the Royal Geographical Society and various Chambers of Commerce as well as by Colonel Yate. The Admiralty replied that they did not desire to modify their previous views regarding the strategic advantage in annexing the islands. As regards the German wireless station, they were satisfied that it had been dismantled, and that this appeared to be all that was required.Annex (C).In the War Cabinet Minute 365 of the 13th March, Item 11, the Foreign Oflice was directed to confer with the Admiralty on the subject of the Spitsbergen position, and report to the War Cabinet. A letter had already been sent to the Admiralty, in which it was pointed out that one of the reported provisions of the Russo-German Peace Treaty appeared to show that Germany intended to secure Russia&apos;s support for an endeavour by her to obtain a seat on the Commission for the administration, of Spitsbergen when the question came up for decision at the end of the war. The German representative, if supported by the Russian, would be in a position to dominate the Commission if the only other countries represented were Norway and Sweden. Mr. Balfour therefore proposed, if the Admiralty concurred, to suggest to the French Government that France and Great Britain should also claim representation on the Commission, that it should be ascertained whether Norway and Sweden would look favourably on such a proposal, and that the United States Government should, be asked whether they were still interested in Spitsbergen and whether they had any views as to the German action. Before doing so, however, Mr. Balfour requested that the position should be once more examined from the naval point of view, since the events which had occurred in Russia since the Admiralty had last expressed their opinion that Spitsbergen possessed no strategic importance, and the possibility of the Arctic Sea becoming the only available route between this country and Siberia, might perhaps have affected the naval view as to the strategic importance of Spitsbergen.The Admiralty replied that they had re-examined the question of the value of Spitsbergen as a naval base and found no reason to alter the views given in Sir John Jellicoes letter to the Secretary of the War Cabinet of 22nd July, 1917. They con-sidered that the only practical measures to prevent Germany obtaining eventual control of Spitsbergen were diplomatic, and concurred in the action which Mr. Balfour proposed to take.Replies have now been received from the countries addressed. The French Government agreed that a position in which Germany was able to dominate the Commission was unacceptable; they were ready to consider any solution proposed by Great Britain or other interested States, and to claim to be also represented on the
Commission. With this object they instructed the French Ministers at Stockholm, and Christiania to join their British colleagues in any action which they might take in the matter, especially with a view to ascertaining whether a proposal to admit to the Commission British and French, and eventually United States representatives would be favourably regarded by the Swedish and Norwegian Governments.The Norwegian Government replied that they would welcome French, and British representatives on the eventual Spitsbergen Administrative Commission.The Swedish Government replied that they had no objection to all the contracting Powrers being represented on the Commission.The United States Government replied that they were not at present in a position to state whether they might in the future have an interest in the settlement of affairs relating to Spitsbergen.The position, therefore, is that the Admiralty remain of opinion that Spitsbergen possesses no strategic importance for this country;. that in&apos; the event of Germany seeking to obtain a dominating position on the Commission by the admission, of a representative, a claim by the French and British Governments for representation will be favourably regarded by Norway and Sweden ; that the United States attitude is doubtful, though it seems very unlikely that they would oppose such a claim. No other countries except Russia have any particular interests in Spitsbergen.Foreign Office, June 29, 1918.o

</content>
</cab>
