<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/53/37 images: 380-415</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSECRET . Copy No.  36vV.P. (44) 437(Also CCS. (44) 145)10th August, 1944WAR cabinet H, Hi J\l, i   i\n^ u Mil/(No. 258)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 3rd August, to0700 10th August,1944[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War Room.
NAVAL SITUATION.General Review.&apos; 1.   H.M. ships have successfully attacked enemy convoys off Saint Nazaire.Allied coastal craft have fought a number of engagements in the Channel.A Japanese convoy in the Bonins has been successfully attacked by a U.S.carrier force.Two U-boats have been sunk.Home Waters.2. The totals unloaded up to p.m. on the 8th are: 1,754,204 men,373,411 vehicles and 2,036,670 tons of stores.3. The port of Cherbourg is now handling shipping on a considerable scale.Twelve liberty ships are being berthed in the harbour simultaneously, besidesL.S.Ts and a large number of small craft.4. On the night of the 5th/6th H.M. ships Thornborough and Retalick(frigates) were unsuccessfully attacked by torpedo bombers off Cap d&apos;Antifer.Later Thornborouqh and coastal forces heavily engaged E-boats, which retiredunder cover of smoke. Retalick was ineffectively shelled by shore batteries. Onthe same night M.T.Bs operating close inshore off Havre seriously damaged oneR-boat and repeatedly hit three others. On the night of the. 7th/8th U.S. coastalcraft attacked and damaged four R-boats off Cap d&apos;Antifer. Early on the 9thM.T.Bs. in the same area attacked four R-boats and four small craft, two ofwhich were probably sunk. S.G.Bs torpedoed an escorted ship off Fecamp. an unsuccessful attack on shipping in the assault area was made by explosive motor-boats, over 40 of which were destroyed.5. Early on the 6th M.T.Bs sank an armed trawler, and probably sank a landing-craft, off Saint Malo; four M.T.Bs were slightly damaged. On the 9thU.S. coastal craft damaged a minesweeper off Jersey; one P.T. boat is missing.6. On the 7th the hospital ship Amsterdam was sunk, probably by mine, offArromanches. Three hundred and twenty survivors were rescued; seventy-fourare missing. On the 8th H.M.C.S. Regina (corvette), escorting a convoy, was sunk, probably by a U-boat, off the north coast of Cornwall; six officers and about70 ratings were rescued. On the 9th H.M.S. Frobisher (cruiser) was damaged bytorpedo at anchor off Courseulles. There were no casualties and she is able tosteam.Bay of Biscay.7. On the night of the 5th/6th HALS. Bellona (cruiser) with H.M. shipsTartar and Ashanti (destroyers) and H.M.C. ships Haida and Iroquois(destroyers) attacked a heavily escorted convoy south-west of Saint Nazaire.Six enemy ships were probably sunk and only one ship possibly escaped. Laterit was reported that about 800 German troops had been drowned. Another-convoy proceeding to Saint Nazaire was also engaged for a short time, but dueto the possibility of E-boat attack the action was broken off, but not before some ofthe enemy ships had been damaged. Haida was slightly damaged and had twofatal casualties. On the 8th Bellona bombarded the radar station on Belle He.H.M.C.S. St. Laurent (destroyer) was slightly damaged by a glider-bomb whileoperating west of Lorient.Mediterranean.8. During the week ending the 31st July, 16,034 tons were discharged atAncona. At Leghorn ships up to 200 feet in length can enter the harbour.Demolition of blockships continues.On the 20th July H.M. S/M Upstart torpedoed and sank an escorted 4,000-ton ship off Toulon.9. On the 4th August H.M. S/M Vox sank an R-boat north of Crete. Onthe 5th the German-controlled Italian destroyer Calatafimi reached Syros fromPiraeus. The Greek S/M Pipinos was instructed to intercept her, and on the9th she torpedoed and sank her outside Karlovassi, Samos. Pipinos also damaged a cargo ship and two barges inside the harbour.
East Indies.10. ELM. S/M Sirdar on patrol north of the Malacca Strait sank a 100-tonjunk and took two prisoners on the 18th July. On the 21st she sank a 350-toncoaster by gunfire and probably sank another of 400 tons which was left burningfiercely.Pacific.11. Apra harbour, the principal port of Guam, was captured in good condition, and was already in use on the 1st.On the 4th and 5th a U.S. carrier force attacked a convoy in the BoninIslands. One destroyer, four escort vessels, six cargo ships and some barges were sunk, and 21 other ships were damaged. Thirteen enemy aircraft were destroyed and five were damaged.  Sixteen U.S. aircraft were shot down by A.A. fire.Anti-Submarine Operations.12. Twenty-three attacks were reported during August to noon on the 9th;of these, 11 were by shore-based aircraft, two by carrier-borne aircraft and tenby warships. On the 5th H.M.S. Stayner (frigate) sank a U-boat off beachy head and took six prisoners. On the next day H.M.S. Loch Killin (frigate) sank one south-west of Lorient; some survivors were rescued.Enemy Intelligence.13. Photographic reconnaissances on the 3rd and 7th showed the Emden,Nilrnberg, Prinz Eiogen and the two old battleships at Gdynia. Hipper was offthe port on the 3rd/ At Elbing five destroyers were fitting out, and at Danzigone destroyer and one torpedo-boat were located.There are three Narvik and one Elbing destroyers in the Channel and biscay ports. Of these, two Narviks are docked, at La Pallice and Bordeaux, and thethird is at Bordeaux. The Elbing was last seen off Lorient on the 6th. Thelast torpedo-boat in the Channel was bombed and sunk in dock on the 6th atHavre. Two escort ships are at St. Nazaire and a third at Nantes : there are twocorvettes at Havre. There are about 40 minesweepers and 22 sperrbrechersbetween Havre and Bordeaux. Between Den Helder and Havre there are36 E-boats, and between Calais and Havre 35-40 R-boats. Very few, if any,E or R-boats are west of the assault area. Between Calais and Havre there areup to. 20 landing craft.14. It is estimated that in the attack on the assault area on the 3rd,60 human torpedoes, operating in six groups, were launched from two beaches inthe Trouville-Villers-sur-Mer area. Forty-eight explosive motor-boats, operating in 16 groups, were launched between Deauville and Houlgate. Twelve dummyhuman torpedo cupolas were sown by explosive motor-boats.15. Between the 20th July and the 3rd August more than a third of theE/R-boat shelters at Dunkirk collapsed. The damage entirely blocks the entrance to the pens, which could accommodate 14 boats. Damage has also been seen byreconnaissance at Dieppe, Etaples, Gravelines, Nieuport and Blankenberghe.Reconnaissance of Marseilles shows that steps have already been taken to close the port by scuttling ships in the entrances.U-boats.16. About four U-boats are operating in the English Channel and one hasbeen reported off the north coast of Cornwall. There is considerable activity inthe Bay of Biscay.There has been no activity in the Atlantic. Four German U-boats are on passage to and from the Indian Ocean.Reconnaissance shows 40 U-boats at Gdynia, 28 at Danzig and eight at Hela.Enemy Attack on Shipping.Chan ^ 1 During t^le week one S*&quot;P was sunk ^ U-boat north of the MozambiqueOne ship in a U.S. eastbound convoy was torpedoed by aircraft off Benghazi.One ship in convoy was mined or torpedoed off Trevose Head.  A U.S. ship was torpedoed and a British ship mined in the assault area.[27976] &apos;     B
18. Shipping losses by enemy action during July amounted to 18 ships of80,905 tons. Marine casualties raised the total of losses from all causes to101,631 tons. U-boats sank 11 ships of 61,424 tons, five of them in the indian ocean, four in the Atlantic and two in the English Channel. Three ships(9,269 tons) were sunk by mines in Home Waters and two in the Adriatic.E-boats sank one ship in convoy in the Channel and damaged six others.There was some increase in the figures for shipping losses in June due tolater notification, and the total from all causes was 88,754 tons.Protection of Seaborne Trade.19. During the week ending the 6th, 872 ships in convoy arrived at their destinations. Of these, 408 were in ocean convoys and 464 in British coastal convoys. Two escort carriers, 39 destroyers (including 17 U.S. destroyers) and75 sloops, cutters, frigates and corvettes, were employed on escort duties. Fourhomebound convoys consisting of 235 ships and four outward-bound convoysconsisting of 173 ships reached their destinations without loss. A convoy fromthe U.S. consisting of 167 ships carrying 1,056,413 tons of cargo, and constitutingthe largest convoy yet to cross the Atlantic, has recently arrived in Home Waters.During July, 6,711 ships in 353 convoys reached their destinationswithout loss.Allied Minelaying.20. Mines have been laid by surface craft off the north coast of France.Aircraft have laid mines off the Biscay ports, in the -^aegean off Paros and Rhodes,and in the Danube.On the 19th June H.M.S. Ariadne (fast minelayer) laid mines off Wewak.This is the first lay to be made by H.M. ships in the U.S. combat area in the pacific.Enemy Minelaying, Allied Minesweeping.21. There has been no enemy minelaying in Home Waters. Minelayingby enemy aircraft in the assault area was on a considerably reduced scale. the approaches to St. Vaast have been cleared. During the week 18 ground mines have been destroyed and nine self-detonated. Up to date 534 ground mines(420 swept by H.M. minesweepers), 271 moored mines and 201 others have been destroyed, making a total of 1,006.Sweeping in the Cherbourg Rades and harbour approaches has been mainlynegative, but on the 4th a dredging hopper was sunk in the Petite Rade anda mine was destroyed in the Grande Rade. Three more mines have been destroyed in the Darse Transatlantique. On the 7th three magnetic mines were destroyed in Querqueville Bay.During the week 71 moored mines have been destroyed off Leghorn.The mine totals are 5,296 ground and 5,552 moored.Enemy Merchant Shipping.22. The German s.s. Johanna (1,899 tons), which has been loading copperand other cargo at Istanbul, has been detained by the Turks. This will depriveGermany of 400 tons of copper.Swedish Shipbuilding.23. It has been reported that at the end of June 1944 there were 133 ships,totalling 554,395 tons, under construction in Swedish building yards : of these,96 ships of 377,795 tons were Swedish, 19 of 144,600 tons were Norwegian, 15 of26,000 tons were German and three others of 6,000 tons probably German.Russian Intelligence.24. On the 1st H.M. ships Roxborough and Georgetoivn (destroyers) were transferred to the Russian Navy and renamed Glorious and Hardy, One battle-ship, four submarines and eight destroyers have now been transferred.
MILITARY SITUATION.North-West France.   (An outline map is included as an inset.)General.25. The last week has seen bold exploitation of the break-through into theBrittany Peninsula by U.S. forces. Their main effort has been directed toclearing the Peninsula, and exploiting their success to the east. Considerableheadway has been made by the British Army N.E. of Vire and the Mont Pinconfeature has been captured.The Canadian Army&apos;s offensive south of Caen is progressing satisfactorily.United States Sector.26. A strong corps of the Third U.S. Army, which took over the rightof the TJ.S. sector, was given the task of securing the Brittany Peninsula, whilethe remainder of the army was ordered to exploit to the east. In the BrittanyPeninsula an armoured formation proceeded via Dinan and is facing Brest,and another struck through Rennes and is now approaching Lorient. Infantryformations followed up the armour and consolidated the ground gained. Rennes,Yannes, Redon have been captured, and after heavy fighting St. Malo was taken on the 9th.To the S.E. a column has reached the River Loire at a point about 15 miles east of Nantes, and Angers was captured on the 8th. U.S. armour and infantryformations, exploiting to the east, proceeded via Laval, reached Le Mans on the8th, and the next day struck north in the direction of Alencon.On the left of the ELS. sector the First U.S. Army have met very considerableenemy opposition. The right flank of this army directed on Alencon met strong-resistance on the general line Mortain-Vire and in the Domfront area.On the 7th, the enemy launched a powerful armoured counter-attack in thearea between Barenton and Vire, apparently directed on Avranches. With theassistance of squadrons of rocket-firing aircraft, which exacted a heavy toll ofthe enemy tanks, this attack was contained and the general position remainedintact. Fighting round Vire was particularly fierce, but the town was capturedon the 6th and remained in our hands.British Sector.27. In this sector an attack south of Caumont resulted in the capture ofBeny Bocage, and troops reached the Vire-Conde-sur-Noireau road. Further tothe east the important feature of Mont Pincon, which dominates the country tothe south, was finally captured on the 8th after heavy fighting by armoured and infantry formations. A general advance to the south resulted in the capture ofthe much disputed towns of Evrecy and Esquay.An attack on the 7th towards the River Orne resulted in the establishment ofa bridgehead across the river some 2^ miles north of Thury Harcourt, Thisbridgehead was held against strong enemy counter-attacks.On the night of the 7th/8th, preceded by a heavy air bombardment, an attack was launched by the Canadian Army astride the Caen-Falaise road. In very heavy fighting, an advance of about 10 miles on a three-mile front has so far beenreported.The Russo-German Campaign.    (An outline map is included as an inset.)Northern Sector.28. The Russians are now within 70 miles of Riga to the east. german counter-attacks S.E. of the town have been repulsed after a few days&apos; fighting andthe Russians have now resumed their advance. -Central Sector.29. The Russians are now close to, the frontier of East Prussia, but duringthe past week German opposition has stiffened, and it is clear that the enemy aremaking determined efforts to keep the Russians from German soil.At Warsaw, too, the Russians are meeting stubborn resistance from thereinforced German forces.   The Russians are firmly established over the eastern[27976] b 2
bank of the River Vistula from just south of Warsaw to its confluence with theRiver San. Above the confluence they have formed a bridgehead over the Vistula,which they are slowly but steadily expanding. They have now reached a point40 miles from Cracow.The Russians also advanced between Przemysl and Stanislavov, probably asa result of a German withdrawal.General.30. Russian progress in the past week, although on a wide front, has beenslower than in previous weeks. Probably the Russians have paused to regroupand to reorganise their system of supply, but there can be no doubt that they are meeting stiffer opposition, particularly near East Prussia and Warsaw. german propaganda has continually stressed the fact that the fighting in the east was taking place far from the German frontier, and that there was plenty of room forthe &quot;elastic defence &quot; on which their strategy was based. By now the fightinghas approached so close to German territory that no such plea is possible.Therefore, a firm stand must be made if German soil is to be kept inviolate.Italy.31. Activity along the Fifth Army front was confined to patrol work withnumerous exchanges of mortar and artillery fire. Eighth Army troops have,however, maintained close contact with the enemy, and made slight advancesthroughout their front.On the Adriatic Sector the River Misa has been crossed along its wholelength. Polish forces are now approaching the River Cesano, and further inlandItalian troops found the enemy holding the north bank of the River Fenella.In the central sector Indian troops established themselves on numerous highfeatures which lie to the N.W. of Sansepolero. The town of Subbiano fell onthe 7th.On the left flank of the Eighth Army, strong enemy resistance which was holding our troops to the S.W. of Florence was overcome on the 4th; this enabledDominion forces to enter the southern outskirts of the city on the same day. they found that the enemy had blown five out of the six bridges over the River Arno,and were holding, as they continue to do, the north bank of the river. The enemy&apos;transaction therefore disposes of any claim they may have made to regard Florence asan open city.Yugoslavia.32. Important fighting is taking place in the area north of Split, wherethe Germans succeeded in recapturing the town of Brlika on the Knin-Sinj road.Strong Partisan attacks were subsequently launched nearer Knin and bitterengagements resulted.To the N.E. the town of Prnjavor (20 miles N.E. of Banjaluka) changedhands twice and is now held hy the Partisans. The Germans suffered many casualties in this area.A British field battery supported by Partisan forces landed on the island of Korcula on the night of 1st/2nd August, and after successfully shelling enemyinstallations on the island and on the Peljesac peninsula was withdrawn without loss.Albania.33.   An Allied Commando raid was carried out on the 29th July upon thecoast north of Corfu.   The Allied troops were assisted by Partisan attacks from (the mainland and by bombardment from sea and air.   A spirited action ensuedin which the enemy lost some 40 killed, 30 wounded and 30 captured against british casualties of 7 killed and 47 wounded.Greece.34. E.L.A.S. forces have carried out a small attack upon the enemy garrison at Naoussa in Western Macedonia. The neighbouring town of Edessa is reportedto have been captured by Yugoslav and E.L.A.S. forces acting in concert. Onthe west coast Zervas forces have attacked south of Egoumenitsa.
Burma.Chin Hills and Chindtvin.35. On the Imphal-Tiddim road our troops reached a point 14 miles southof Churachandput. Advancing down the road from Imphal, British troopsoccupied the villages of Moreh and Tamu.North Burma.36. After a ten weeks&apos; siege, Myitkyina fell to Chinese and British troops on the 4th. Resistance did not cease until the 6th, and enemy stragglers are still being rounded up.Pacific Theatre.Guam Island.37. U.S. troops have reached the east coast of the island, thus cutting theJapanese forces in half. Only remnants of the enemy are left in the southern part, and the main Japanese force is being gradually pressed into the northern-most tip of the island.New Guinea.38. U.S. forces have advanced to a distance of about five miles up theDriniumor River. The Japanese force which was trapped in the Wewak area and which has been making suicidal attacks against the U.S. perimeter in this area, has now been split into three by this latest U.S. counter-drive.AIR SITUATION.General Review.39. Allied aircraft of all types provided powerful support to the militaryoperations in Normandy and Brittany, particularly in the destruction of enemyarmour and M..T. and fuel dumps in forward areas. A number of damagingattacks was made on oil plants and aircraft factories in Germany.M.A.A.F. heavy bombers attacked oil and other targets in Southern France,Eastern Germany, Hungary and the Balkans.There was a slight decrease in the number of flying-bombs launched against,this country.United Kingdom.40. Flying-bomb attacks are reported under &quot; Enemy Activity and home security.&quot;   No other important enemy air activity has been reported.Home Waters.41. Aircraft of Coastal Command flew 687 sorties involving 6,384 flying-hours.   Aircraft of Bomber Command laid 338 sea-mines.On the 3rd, Spitfires attacked enemy human torpedoes, west of Havre,destroying four, probably destroying two others and possibly destroying aseventh.A formation of escorted Beaufighters, operating off south-west Norway, setfire to four 2,500-ton ships and six escort vessels. Other Beaufighters attacked a destroyer or torpedo-boat in harbour at Les Sables d&apos;01onne and left her burning,and, off Belle He, set four minesweepers on fire. Off Flushing, R.P. Typhoonsdestroyed two coasters and damaged a 2,000-ton ship, a barge, a tug and two -boats. A Wellington sank two E-boats off Terschelling. Halifaxes severely damaged a minesweeper in midstream at Concarneau and three others in theRiver Odet and left a Sperrbrecher burning off He de croix.Western Front.42.   There was an appreciable improvement in the weather.A total of 33,605 sorties was flown and 41,900 tons of bombs were dropped.Though the total sorties only exceeded those of last week by 3,665, the weight of bombs increased by 16,193 tons; over half the total of 41,900 tons was dropped by aircraft of Bomber Command.
It is estimated that G.A.F. fighter activity over Western France was lessthan 240 sorties per day. There were no daylight operations by bombers. at night, an average of some 75 sorties was flown by bombers. On the 7th, when amaximum effort was required to support his counter-attack at Avranches, theenemy had, to all intents and purposes, no air cover. During the Allied exploita-tion of our break-through to Brittany, close air-support received by german troops was on a scale quite inadequate to meet the situation.Allied losses were 294 aircraft, of which 129 were heavy bombers, 39 medium and light bombers and 126 fighter and fighter-bombers. Enemy casualties in combat were 221 destroyed. 14 probably destroyed and 76 damaged.&apos; France.(a) Close Support to Allied Armies and Armed Reconnaissances.43. On the 7th, fighter-bombers were detailed to counter an enemy armouredthrust on a large scale in the Moftain area; rocket-firing Typhoons carried outalmost continuous attacks and, conjointly with Spitfires, Thunderbolts andMustangs, flew 1,100 sorties; 81 tanks and 140 M.T. were destroyed and many others damaged.Just before midnight on the 7th/8th, heavy bombers dropped 3,460 tons inconcentrated attacks on five aiming-points north of Bretteville-sur-Laize to allowCanadian divisions to advance along the Caen-Falaise road: as the operationsproceeded, markers became obliterated by smoke and dust from the bomb-bursts,resulting in a further 370 bombers not attacking: on the Master Bombers&apos; instruc-d otions. At noon the next day, another strong force dropped 1,140 tons of bombs on troop concentrations and tank harbours at Gauvicourt and around Brettevilleand St. Sylvain.Offensive operations by medium bombers, fighter-bombers and fighters overXormandy and northern France, and in support of our own forward armouredcolumns in Brittanv. involved a further 6.500 effective sorties, durins: which about 1,600 tons of bombs were dropped and 7,000 R.P. were discharged. Inaddition to those mentioned above, 203 tanks and 915 M.T. are claimed to havebeen destroyed, together with 37 mortars and A.A. guns, 129 locomotives and496 freight cars (including 54 oil tankers); an ammunition train was destroyednear Bordeaux and a fuel train left blazing near Paris. Barges on the riverSeine were the targets for fighter-bombers on several occasions; 27 craft were destroyed. Night and day defensive patrols, involving approximately 1,250sorties, were maintained over the assault area.(b) Oil and Fuel targets.   (Approximate total 7,000 tons of bombs.)Accurate attacks were made on oil storage depots (1,290 tons of bombs) anda refinery (1,215 tons) at Bordeaux. A further 1,110 tons were dropped on oil plants at Merkwiller (near Strasbourg) and on depots in the Lille area. On one day, a total of 610 tons was dropped on 11 depots in the battle area and, on other occasions, similar objectives were attacked by heavy bombers at Aire-sur-Lys(285 tons) and in the following forests Forets de Chatellerault (850 tons),Chantilly (725 tons), Marmal (705 tons) and Lucheux (460 tons). VideAppendix VII, paragraphs 1, 2, 3 and 7.(c) Railway centres, bridges and embankments.Over 4,000 tons of bombs were released on road, rail and water communica-tions around Paris and in the centre and west, as well as at Strasbourg, Saar-brucken and Mulhouse on the German frontier. In addition to hits on importantrail and river bridges and on specific road and rail junctions, tracks were cut at anumber of vital points.   Vide Appendix VII, paragraphs 6, 8, 10, 11 and 13.(d) Flying-bomb installations. (Approximate total 13,100 tons of bombs)Escorted heavy bombers, on three days, dropped 5,095, 3,200 and 1,195 tons respectively and, in other attacks, a total of 3,410 tons was dropped on supplyand storage depots and launching sites. (Vide Appendix VII, paragraph 12.)A Mosquito dropped LB. in the mouth of a railway tunnel reported to house atrain carrying fuel for flying-bombs.(e) Ports.U-boat pens at Lorient, Brest and La Pallice were bombed (145, 75 and 64tons of bombs, respectively). Eleven 12,000 lb. bombs were among those droppedat Lorient, while in the attacks on Brest and La Pallice, this calibre of bomb was
used exclusively. At St. Malo, 40 tons were dropped on hulks in the harbour,believed to be potential block-ships. Enemy shipping in Brest Harbour was the target for medium bombers, which dropped 95 tons.Belgium.44. Among the objectives attacked were coke ovens and chemical works at brussels (130 tons) and a rail-centre and fuel dump at Ghent (95 tons).Germany, Luxembourg and Poland (Approximate total, 8,000 tons of bombs).45. A total of 1,215 tons of bombs was dropped, during two attacks, on oil refineries at and near Hamburg. An underground oil-storage depot atNienburg and a refinery at Dollbergen were effectively bombed (585 and 245 tons,respectively). Vide Appendix VII, Paragraphs 18, 20, 23, 25, 29 and 36.Satisfactory results were also achieved in a raid on the experimental station atPeenemunde (465 tons). Vide Appendix VII, Paragraph 30. Twelve plantsengaged in aircraft production and five airfields were attacked, a total of3,535 tons being released; Berlin/Genshagen, Hanover, Brunswick and Magde-burg received the heaviest tonnage of bombs and good results were reported onnearly every one of these 17 targets. Vide Appendix VII, Paragraphs 15, 16,19, 21, 22, 24, 27, 28, 32, 33 and 34.About 385 tons of bombs were dropped on two works manufacturing M.T.vehicles, 185 tons on an armaments factory and a total of 380 tons in two attacks on Kiel port area. Saarbrucken railway centre was bombed (385 tons) with fairresults and 600 tons were dropped on targets of opportunity in southern Germany.Mosquitoes bombed Cologne (52 tons) and synthetic oil plants at Castrop-Rauxel and Wanne-Eickel (total 80 tons). Sixty-one tons of bombs were dropped on marshalling yards at Luxembourg. Seventy-three Fortresses, with an escortof nine squadrons of Mustangs, after bombing an aircraft factory at Rahmel,near Gydnia, landed, without loss, at bases in Russia.In the course of these operations, escorting fighters destroyed 54 locomotives,several units of rolling-stock and nine A.A. positions and Flak towers.Mediterranean Front.46. During the week ended dawn on the 8th, Allied aircraft of the M.A.A.F.flew a total of 9,878 sorties, of which 2,219 were by heavy bombers and dropped4,499 tons of bombs; 83 Allied aircraft, including 40 heavy bombers, are missing and 56 enemy aircraft were destroyed.Although once again adverse weather restricted operations to some extent,the strategic Air Force attacked railway communications and oil storage depotsin the south of France. U-boat pens were successfully bombed at Toulon. Air-fields, an oil refinery and other targets were attacked in Hungary.The Tactical Air Force continued attacks on enemy railway centres, road and rail communications and transport. Support was provided for the Alliedland forces.Italy.47. In Northern Italy, attacks were made on railway centres, road and rail communications and bridges. Roads were cut in many places, as were thePrato/Bologna and Ferrara/Bologna railway lines.In the battle areas fighter-bombers operated successfully against railway centres, enemy positions and other military targets. In operations over Italy,medium, light and fighter-bombers made a total of 2,492 sorties. Two bombers and nine fighter-bombers are missing, enemy casualties being five destroyed.Off the coast, five schooners were destroyed, several other vessels and a Siebelferry were damaged, and a number of barges were sunk.  A convoy was success-&apos;fully attacked off Porto Fino, and at the same place an ammunition dump was hit by bombs and violent explosions were observed.Southern France.48. U.S. heavies of the M.A.A.F. bombed railway centres at Miramas(218 tons) and Port les Valence (321 tons). Railway bridges at Avignon.Tarascon, Givors-sur-Rhone and Lavoult were attacked and received direct hits.Two spans of the Lavoult bridge were destroyed.Oil storage depots in the Lyons area were also bombed.
Yugoslavia.49 Although bad weather hampered flying, the Balkan Air Force flew253 sorties and made attacks on roads, railways and M.T. Thirty-six locomotives,some 30 wagons and 25 M.T. were destroyed or damaged.TJ.S. heavies dropped 103 tons of bombs on an airfield at Ahbunar (35 miles .E. of Belgrade) and 52 tons on oil installations at Novi Sad (45 miles N.W.of Belgrade).   Fortresses successfully attacked Brod railway centre, dropping67 tons- * ,      .  i        ,       , ,Off the Dalmatian coast, one schooner was sunk and three others damaged.East Germany and Hungary.50. On the 7th, the synthetic oil plants at Blechhammer (55 miles.E. of Breslau) were attachedly 353 heavies of the M.A.A.F. (14 missing) which dropped 730 tons of bombs.  Severe damage was inflicted.- On the night the 7th/8th August, the airfield of Szombathely (65 miles S. of vienna) was attacked (136 tons) with good results. On the 9th, escorted TJ.S.heavies attacked two -airfields near Budapest (398 tons) and an oil refinery atAlmasfuzito (50 miles N.W. of Budapest), dropping 169 tons. Fortresses also attacked a wagon works (144 tons) and Fabric Assembly shops (135 tons) atGyor (60 miles W.N.W. of Budapest).Rumania and Greece.51. On the 4th, a sweep by 90 Lightnings and Mustangs was made overairfields in Rumania, the aircraft subsequently landing in Russia. On anotheroffensive sweep by fighters, strikes were scored on hangars, buildings and sixA.A. batteries near Focsani (100 miles N.N.E-. of Bucharest).Seventy-three Fortresses of the 8th U.S. Air Force, escorted by 55 Mustangs,taking off in Russia and all of which subsequently landed in Italy, attacked Buzauairfield (62 miles N.E. of Bucharest) dropping 58 tons, and Zilistea airfield(70 miles S.E. of Bucharest), dropping 62 tons.Wellingtons attacked Leros (Portolago Bay) where hits were observed on naval workshops and stores, and on Lepida seaplane base.Russia.52. The Russian long-range bomber force was inactive during the weekended the 8th August. This is probably to allow for rest and refit before the resumption of a large-scale offensive. Some bombing attacks have, however, been delivered against East Prussian railway communications.Burma.53. Allied aircraft, for the week ended the 8th August, flew a total of2,276 sorties of which 1,303 were by bombers and fighter-bombers. transport aircraft flew 972 sorties, carrying 2,233 tons, 2,147 men, and evacuating 1,327 menand 1,539 casualties.The principal Allied activity was in the Chindwin/Thaungdut/Myitkyina.areas, where attacks were made on railway rolling-stock, river-craft and M.T.The railway station at Mandalay was bombed with good results.   In Central and lower Burma Beaufighters effectively attacked river craft, M.T. and bridges.China Zone.54. Allied aircraft, for the week ended the 8th August, flew a total of820 sorties. Four Allied aircraft are missing and 19 enemy aircraft were destroyed in combat.   Transport aircraft flew 212 sorties, carrying 384 tons.During the week the railway centre at Yochow (100 miles S.W. of Hankow)was bombed with excellent results, much damage being caused to installations, and warehouses being destroyed. On the Yangtze, river-craft were attacked, while in the Loyang area locomotives were destroyed on the line &quot;to Chenghsien.The airfield at Pailuchi (N.E. of Changsha) was raided by fighter-bombers,and at Changsha 25 M.T. and two river-craft were destroyed, 65 M.T. and afurther number of river-craft being damaged.Pacific Zone.New Guinea.55. In Dutch New Guinea, a total of 220 Liberators, Bostons, Mitchells andKittyhawks attacked the airfields at Ransiki, Moemi and Nabire, oilfields at
Vogelkop, military targets at Sarmi and, co-operating with our troops, huts atthe mouth of the Kor river (20 miles N.E. of Cape Sansapor). In N.E. new guinea, activity was reduced by unfavourable weather. Bridges, stores andA.A. positions at Wewak, Dagua and Boiken, and enemy troops east of theDriniumor river, between Yakamul and But and near Afua were bombed and machine-gunned; about 360 sorties were flown.New Britain and New Ireland.56. A total of 260 sorties was flown between the 1st and 5th, mainly againstsupply centres in the wharf area at Rabaul and A.A. gun-sites in the vicinity.In New Ireland, during the same period, Kavieng and villages to the south of itAvere attacked by a total of 72 aircraft; numerous buildings were set alight.Other bombers raided Mane Island (West Balgai Bay).Carolines, Marshalls, marinas and Moluccas.57. Liberators carried out seven attacks on Yap and bombed supply a reason Utagal Island (Woleai) on two occasions and Malakal (Palau) twice. islands in the Marshalls group were attacked on three occasions by 93, 57 and 50 bombersrespectively. On each of two days, 100 carrier-borne aircraft attacked Guamwith bombs and R.P. Liberators dropped 25 tons on Galela airfield (Halmahera)and small raids were made on landing-grounds at mitigated and Lolobata.Solomons.58. Dauntless and Avengers flew 240 sorties against villages, hutments and japanese troops in the Choiseul Bay area, Buka Passage and at EmpressAugusta Bay.Timor.59. Thirty tons were dropped on a camp 30 miles east of Koepang.Liberators bombed airfields at Lautem and Cape Chater. Mitchells probably destroyed a 1,500-ton ship off Goenoeng Api Island.ENEMY ACTIVITY AND HOME SECURITY.General.60. During the week 768 F.Bs. were launched as compared with 833 lastweek and 759 the week before.   462 were destroyed.The style of attack, generally speaking, has been short periods of a compara-tively high concentration; the longest lull has been of approximately 21 hours&apos;duration.The use of explosive LB. in conjunction with F.Bs. has been confined to fourincidents, representing 1-3 per cent, only of the total number of incidentsreported.London remains the principal target, and, except for the night of the 3rd/4th,when all four boroughs reporting F.Bs. were north of the river, the emphasis of attack has remained south of the river.During the week, boroughs mainly affected were Woolwich (14 incidents),Croydon (14), Orpington (12), Lewisham (11), Coulsdon (10), Camberwell (9), andWandsworth (8).Outside London, Kent had 190 incidents, Sussex 103, Essex 23 andSurrey 22.Damage.61. The number of key-point incidents during the week ending 0600 on the9th is provisionally estimated at 55. The proportion of incidents involving-damage of national importance has been greater than of recent weeks, and in20 cases out of the 55 reported the effects were material, nine being factories.Eighteen railway incidents have been reported, eight causing some temporaryinterruption of services.On the morning of the 3rd, a 40-pump fire, which was caused at the ordnance Tar Works at Greenwich, involved the South Metropolitan Gas Works.On the night of the 4th/5th, there was a 30-pump fire at a grain warehouse onChambers Wharf, Bermondsey.[27976] c
Casualties.62. Estimated civilian casualties for the week ending 0600 hours on the9th August arc : SeriouslyKilled.      Injured.London        ...............      395 943Elsewhere     ...............        57 129Total        ............      452 1,07263.   Provisional Statistical Tables. Flying-Bombs.Table I.Date.		Launched.	Crossed Coast.	Over London.	Destroyed.								Fighters.	A.A.	Bal-loons.	Total.24 hours ended :   0600 4th August       ...... 5th     ,,......... 6th     ........... &quot;,, 7th         ... ,, 8th     ,,   .         ...... ,, 9th      ,,-          ...... ,, 10th                 ...... Totals      ......		193 149 126 89 122 37 52	119 102 73 56 67 27 29	40 35 23 19 19 12 10	57 44 41 32 25 6 12	58 53 30 17 25 4 15	9 7 8 8 2 4 5	124 104 79 57 52 14 32		768	473	158	217            202 i		43	462Table II.								For 7-day periods ending 0600 hours on 	Average number launched per 24 hours.	Average number crossing coast per 24 hours.	Per cent. of Flying-Bombs crossing coast to Flying-Bombs launched.	Average number over London per 24 hours.	Per cent. of Flying-Bombs over London to Flying-Bombs launched.	Per cent, of Flying-Bombs over London to Flying-Bombs crossing coast.	Average number destroyed per 24 hours.	- Per cent. of Flying-Bombs destroyed to Flying-Bombs launched.23rd June ... 29th June...... 6th July 13th July   ... 20th July...... 27th July  ...... 3rd August... 10th August	131 117 142 100 73 108 119 110	97 91 107 73 54 77 85 68	74 77 77 73 74 71 71 62	44 48 60 29 26 34 44 oq	34 41 42 29 35 32 37 21	45 53 55 .41 47 45 52 33	46 56. 60 53 32 50 47 66	35 48 42 53 43 1 47 39 60
13 &apos;    107APPENDIX I.Merchant Vessels (excluding Commissioned Merchant Vessels) of all tonnages lost by enemy action during the month of July 1944.Table I.The following table shows the division of losses into cause and nationality : 1--- Flag.	U-Boat.		Mine.		Surface Craft.		Aircraft.		Other Causes and  Cause Unknown.		Total.		No.	Gross 1      I  Gross Tons. 1     &quot;1  Tons.			No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.British    .........j   5		23,207	5	12,190	1	7,219	1	72			12	42,688Ulied-Dutch......... Norwegian United States ...	. 1 1 4	5,593 1,499 31,125							...	...	1 1 4	5,593 1,499 31,125Total of Allied Losses	6	38,217							...	...	6	38,217Neutral Countries			...									Total          ......	11	61,424	5	12,190	1	7,219	1	72		...	18	80,905Table II.The following table shows the division of losses into cause and area: Area.	1 I U-Boat.           Mine. 1 1				Surface Craft.		Aircraft.		Other Causes and Cause Unknown.		Total. ,		No.	Gross ; -,,-r m            i NO. Tons.  !		Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.Atlantic  North   ... South  ...       ...   &quot; Indian Ocean picific Areas Mediterranean   ...... United Kingdom Coastal Waters       (including Channel) Elsewhere      (including Worth Sea and Barents bea^ Total    ......	2 2 5 2	15,480 14,062 30,176 1,706	2 3	2,921 9,269.	1. ...	. 7,219	... ... -1	72			2 2 5 2 .   7	15,480 14,062 30,176 2,921 18,266	11	61,424	5	12,190	1	7,219	1	72		r	18	80,905---.__I !_I I_I I_I I_i I _I_l[27976] - c 2
Table III. The following table shows the ships convoyed and the losses inflicted by enemy action on Atlantic, Indian Ocean and United Kingdom Coastal Convoys during July 1944 (excluding Operational Convoys).				Convoys.	Number Convoyed.(a)		Losses by enemy action.		Convoys.	Ships.	In Convoy.	Ex Convoy.To and from United Kingdom West African Coastal United States to Gibraltar and West Africa and return... Gulf to Gibraltar and West Africa and return Caribbean and West Atlantic Cape area Sub-Total Atlantic Ocean ... Indian Ocean ...    - ... United Kingdom Coastal Grand Total(^	33 20 7 1 92 8	1,33S 84 353 10 904 50			161 48 86	2,739 352 2,099	...		295	5,190		(a) The convoys included in the table are those arriving at their destinations in the month.(b) There remains the matter of Mediterranean convoys, which deal with a large volumeof shipping, much of it for short voyages, and which, if shown in the form set out above,would be somewhat misleading. During the month 58 of the principal Mediterraneanconvoys of 1,521 ships completed their voyages without loss by enemy action.
IO appendix II.I Total Losses by Enemy Action and Marine Causes of Merchant Ships outside EnemyIControl, including Tankers but excluding Fleet Auxiliaries, Merchant Ships commissionedI for Naval Service, American Merchant Ships owned by or on bare-boat charter to the armed Services, and other United Nations Merchant Ships similarly employed.I (Including vessels of all tonnages for losses by enemy action and vessels of 100 gross tonsand over for losses by marine causes.)A. Losses from all Causes.(Tonnage in Thousand Gross Tons.)Period.	British.		Allied.                   Neutral. i				Total.		No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage, i    No. i		Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.September-December   1939 (4 months) 1940   ......       ...... 1941............ Totals: September  1939-December 1941 ...	158 729 893	498 2,726 3,051	i 17             90 i 201   !        822 340         1,286 1		148 416 183	347 1,002 347	323 1,346 1,416	935 4,550 4,684	1,780	6,275	558	2,198   i     747 1           ,		-1,696	3,085	10,169(In Thousand Gross Tons.)								Period.	British Control.		United States Control.		Others.		Total.		No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.      Tonnage.		No.	Tonnage.1942   ............ 1943: lBt quarter 2nd quarter   ... 3rd quarter 4th quarter p44: 1st quarter    ...... April   ... May    ......... June 2nd quarter   ... July    ......... 3c totals:    January    1942-June 1944	1,097 191 120 88 76 64 17 5 25	5,229 961 554 436 287 265 66 27 56	532 95 49 40 44 41 10 3 7 -	2,572 490 277 229 197 236 61 8 26	228 46 20 21 21 33 3 3 6	533 78 36 47 56 26 8 5 7	1,857 332 189 149 141 138 30 11 38	8,334 1,529&apos; 867 712 541 527 135 40 89	47	149	20	95	12	20	79	264	17	51	7	51	1		25	102	j 1,700         7,932 i		828	4,147	382	i 796   J 2,910 i		12,876r
B. Losses analysed by Cause.(Tonnage in Thousand Gross Tons.)Period.	Enemy Action.						Marine Kisk.				U-boat.	Mine.	Sur-face craft.	j Other . .          or ,,   !   Un-craft.   , iknown 1 Cause.		Total.	Over-due, pre-sumed lost.*	Other Non-Enemy Cause, t	Total	Total.September-December 1939 (4 months) 1940         ......... 1941         ......... 1942         ......... 1943 1st quarter 2nd quarter   ... 3rd quarter 4th quarter 1944 1st quarter    &quot;... April   ... May    ... June   ... 2nd quarter   ... July .:. Totals, September 1939-July 1944        ......	421 2,103 2,133 6,257 1,190 706 443 245 328 55 24 36	258 510 230 103 31 18 12 32 14 18	61 518 493 401 5 19 15 9 17 2	3 557 958 686 88 30 143 154 39 20 3 9	4 189 319 269 2 10	747 3,877 4,133 7,716 1,314 773 615 440 398 75 27 75	99 92 8 9 10 1	177 574 459 610 206 94 87 101 128 60 13 14	188 673 551 618 215 94 97 101 129 60 13 14	935 4,550 4,684 8,334 1,529 867 712 541 527 135 40 89	115	18	2	32	10	177		87	87	264	62	12	7			81		21	21	102	14,003	1,238	1,547	2,690	793	20,271	230	2,544	2,774	23,045* Some of these losses may eventually be held to be due to enemy action.* Including losses due to vessels running on British or Allied mines.
rAPPENDIX III (A)Non-Tankers under British Control.Analysis by availability.1,600 g.t. and over.(Thousand gross tons).End of mi	jnth.	Vessels not engaged in or available for carrying cargoes to or from overseas countries (including all troopships).							Vessels carrying or available for carrying overseas civil or military cargoes.	Total.		Troopships^).	Other vessels wholly on Fighting Service(l).	Immobilised by damage or repair.	Engaged in coasting or inter-coastal fcrade(S).	New vessels not yet allocated, &amp;c.	Employment information incomplete.	Total.		1943-June     ...    &quot;... July      ............. August ...      ...      ...... September October......      ....     ... November December 1944-January...      ...      ...... February        ....... March............ , April     ...       ... May     ...      ......... June		2,127 2,120 2,153 2,180 2,209 2,208 2,217 2,331 2,313 2,313 2,285 2,293 2,292	1,366 1,338 1,287   . 1,251 1,259 1,263 1,271    &apos; 1,188 1,326 1,305 1,383 1,345  . 1,406	1,177 1,006 935 1,041 1,176 1,222 1,445 1,276 1,270 1,043 1,086 1,166 1,251	1,618 1,265 1,604 1,673 1,597 1,708 1,680 1,700 1,608 2,089 2,496 2,894 3,073(3)	58 36 70 85 31 58 105 73 45 141 106 101 136	10 13 14 6 3 3 3 2 7 2 5 2 12	6,357 5,777 6,060 6,235 6,275 6,462 6,721 6,570 6,569 6,893 7,361 7,801 8,170	7,889 8,450 8,392 8,449 8,566 8,617 8,607 8,898 9,013 8,896 8,567 8,341 8,185	14,246 14,227 14,453 14,685 14,841 15,079 15,328 15,468 15,582 15,789 15,928 16,142 16,355(l) Including those under repair.(2) Including vessels temporarily allocated for or specially engaged in local operations.(3) Including 1,844 thousand gross tons engaged on local operations in N.W. Europe, Mediterranean, India, &amp;c.
APPENDIX III (B)Tankers under British Control.Analysis by availability.1,600 g.t. and over.(Thousand gross tons.)i End of Month.	Tankers not engaged in or available for carrying cargoes to or from overseas countries.						Tankers carrying or available for carrying overseas civil or Service cargoes.	Total.	Engaged in Fleet attendance.(&apos;)	Immobilised by damage or repair.	Engaged in coasting or inter-coastal trade.	Employed as depot ships.	Employment information incomplete.	Total.		1943-June July      ...             ...... August    ...      ...... September October   ... November        ......... December... 1944-January   ... February ... March     ......... April May       ...      .......... June	395 409	734 769	246 285 261 283 338 294 279 295 271 295 323 483 511	33 39 39 47 47 54 54 42 51 51 51 51 57	3 3	1,408 1,502 1,427 1,439 1,620 1,553 1,540 1,522 1,455 1,515 1,504 1,610 1,549	2,212 2,133 2,206 2,206 2,019 2,108 2,172 2,240 2,322 2,284 2,296 2,191 2,299	3,620 3,635 3,633 3,645 3,639 3,661 3,712 3,762 3,777 3,799 3,800 3,801 3,848	447 424 456 425 442 455 452 432 479 442 444	680 685 779 .     780 765 730 678 734 651 634 537						(x) For August 1943, and succeeding months, includes those under repair.
(C) Merchant Ships (100 gross tons and over) under construction in the UnitedKingdom as at 31st July, 1944.(Tonnage in thousand tons.) *	Tankers.		Others.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.Coasting ships and colliers Other Bhips Total in the United Kingdom	10 29	5 213	36 143	37 780	39	218	179	817In addition, the following merchant ships have been ordered in tJhe UnitedKingdom: No.       Gross Tons..    Tankers       .................. 21 169Coasting Tankers   ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 8 other Vessels        ...............        163* 422192 597* Including 2 vessels (2,000 gross tons) of merchant type to be built for the Navy.APPENDIX IY will be published periodically.APPENDIX Y.Casualties to H.M. and Allied Auxiliary vessels and to Naval Personnel.31st July. M.T.B. 675 damaged by shore batteries off Cap d&apos;Antifer.3rd A ugust. M/ S Trawler Gairsay sunk by human torpedo in assault area.3rd August. M.T.B. 608 damaged in action off Cap d&apos;Antifer.3rd August. M.M/S. 279 damaged by mine in assault area.6th august.-^M.T.Bs. 717, 720, 716 and 677 damaged in action off St. Malo.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : rOfficers : 27 killed; 1 missing; 12 wounded.Eatings :&apos; 68 killed; 115 missing; 31 wounded.These figures include casualties in H.M.S. I sis.APPENDIX YI will be published periodically.[27976]
APPENDIX YII.Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.France.1. Bee cVAmbes Oil Refinery.-Photographs, taken after the bomber command attack on the 4th August, show that damage throughout the refineryis severe. At least one of the six large tanks is on fire and 13 tanks of varyingsizes have been destroyed or damaged, and the main installations at the southend of the plant have been partly wrecked or are still burning.2. Bordeaux: Bassens Oil Storage. Photographs, taken the day following the attack by Bomber Command on the 5th August, show volumes of smoke stillrising from the target area. On such parts as can be seen, damage to tanks and buildings is severe.Blave Oil Storage. Photographs show that, after the Bomber command attack on the 5th August, the largest storage tank and the oil bunkering pier were completely destroyed. Many other smaller tanks and several buildings have been destroyed or damaged.3. Courchelettes. Photographs show that, as a result of the US.A.A.F.attack on the 3rd August, almost every building in the oil refinery has been hit and the power plant is severely damaged. Fires are still burning as a result ofthe attack and there is considerable damage to storage tanks. The railwayadjoining has been cut.4. Joigny I La Roche Marshalling Yard. Photographs show that, duringthe Bomber Command attack on the 31st July, damage was concentrated on thecentre&quot; section of the marshalling yard. Two of the three locomotive roundhouseshave been seriously damaged, all tracks and platforms at the passenger stationare heavily damaged and the through sidings north of the locomotive round-houses and the dead-end spurs south of the Quarter roundhouse have also been seriously affected. A considerable number of locomotives, passenger coaches and goods wagons in the yard has been destroyed or damaged and the main line toAuxerne has been cut by a number of hits.5. Melun Airfield. Photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the1st August, show at least 650 fresh craters on the landing-groUnd, nearly all ofthem in the centre. There are also approximately 60 fresh craters on the tworunways. There is some slight damage to buildings in the workshops area and, tothe north of this, five barrack-type buildings (one of them damaged in a previousattack) have been destroyed.6. Mulhonse Marshalling Yard. Photographs show that, as a result of theU.S.A.A.F. attack on the 3rd August, fresh damage has been caused in the wagonrepair sidings, where the large wagon repair shop has been more than half destroyed and the tracks cut in about 20 places; three railway wagons were severely damaged. The town passenger station has been slightly affected andthe through lines Mulhouse/Basle have been cut in at least six places. Bothapproaches to the rail bridge over the Canal du Rhone have been cut in severalplaces.7. Pauillac Oil Refinery. Although the first photographs, taken after the bomber Command attack on the 4th August, are smoke-obscured in the southern half of the target, major damage is seen to all visible installations. 27 smallstorage tanks have been destroyed, and an area containing another 28 is seen tobe on fire; two tanks in the western area are damaged. The cracking plant and thedistillation units have also been affected and 11 small buildings have been destroyed or gutted.In the port area, pier installations have been damaged by fire.The southern part of the target area was clear at the time of the secondcover and shows that the Bomber Command attack on the 4th August severely damaged four large, 14 medium and eight small buildings and destroyed one large, six medium and two small tanks in this area. On photographs, taken after the second Bomber Command attack on the 5th August, all five main build-ings and six small buildings are seen to have been destroyed.   One large tank
has been slightly damaged and one medium tank has been destroyed and twodamaged; two small tanks are destroyed. The oil bunkering pier has been destroyed and the railway running north of the target has been cut by six direct hits. .8. saarbrucken Railway Centre. Photographs show that the U.S.A.A.F.attack on the 3rd August caused damage to tracks at the junction of the lines to Neunkirchen and Metz. A span of the road over rail bridge has been destroyed and the main railway bridge damaged. There is severe damage to the coaltranshipment depot, the locomotive depot has been further damaged and manyof the through lines near the main passenger station have been cut. In theVereinigte Huttenwerke (Steel and Armaments) 11 buildings have been affected.9. Sens. Photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the2nd August, show that the fuel depot has been severely damaged. In the southern half of the plant, the high protecting wall has been destroyed and the smallbuilding wrecked. In the northern half, one storage tank has been damaged anda second was still on fire at the time of photography. Roads throughout the areahave been blocked by craters and a number of very small buildings have been destroyed. East of the fuel depot an unidentified industrial plant has suffered heavily, many buildings being completely or partially destroyed.10. Strasbourg Marshalling Yard. Photographs, taken after theU.S.A.A.F. attack on the 3rd August, show approximately 230 craters in theforwarding and train formation sidings, where a large amount of rolling-stockhas been derailed. The through lines Paris/Karlsruhe on the east side of thesidings have been cut in several &quot;places.11. Troyes. Photographs show that the main weight of the attack by theTJ.S.A.A.F. on the 3rd August has fallen on the railway junction, where there hasbeen considerable damage to tracks. The road bridge crossing the railway atthis point has been destroyed.12.   Flying-bomb supply depots.Foret de Nieppe. Photographs show that, in the Bomber Command day-light attacks on the 2nd and 3rd August, in that part of the target which is covered, at least 46 buildings have been destroyed or damaged.Ulsle Adam. Photographs show that in the daylight attack by bomber command on the 3rd August, 45 of the storage bunkers have been destroyed or damaged.Railway Bridges.13.   Photographs show that &apos;(a) Bouchemaine. The section of the bridge from the large centre pier tothe east bank of the river Maine is reduced to rubble and partiallycollapsed.   Traffic is impossible.(b) Etaples. Photographs show that the single-line bridge over the riverCanche carrying the line from Calais and Boulogne to Paris has been broken in three places.(c) Goulard Port Martineau. The bridge over the Loire is almost completely destroyed.   Through traffic is impossible.(d) Tessy-sur-Vire. Photographs show that two spans of the bridge havecollapsed into the river.Belgium.14. Ghent. Photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the27th July, show that the Purfina Oil Storage and Refinery on the Terneuzen Canalhas been hit on the north and west sides. One building has been destroyed, threehave been gutted and two more have been damaged. An unidentified installationhas suffered severely and one storage tank has been damaged.Germany.&quot; 15y   Anklam Airfield. Photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attackon the 4th August, show heavy damage in the north sector o  the airfield.   Fiveout of six hangars have been severely damaged and eight barrack buildings havebeen practically destroyed : two workshops have also been affected.   There are[27976] E
20 craters in the centre of the landing-ground and approximately 150 in and around the hangar area.   Eight aircraft on the ground have been damaged.At the storage depot three miles W.S.W. of the airfield, there is a largeconcentration of craters in the target area and three large, two medium andthree small buildings have been destroyed.16. Berlin. Photographs taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attacks on factories in the Berlin area on the 6th August show  Genshagen. The aero-engine works of Daimler-Benz have been severely damaged and, although the buildings are widely spaced, the majority have suffered in varying degree. The buildings most heavily affected consist mainly of workshops and at least three test beds have been damaged. Two huttedcamps have also received damage, eight huts being destroyed and seven damaged.Marienfelde.(a) The Daimler-Benz plant (diesel and aero-engines) has been severely damaged. Four machine and assembly shops, the forge, five work-shops, two stores buildings and three office buildings have all been affected, most of them heavily.(b) The machine-tool factory of Fritz Werner has received severe damage and the power plant was still on fire at the time of photography. Thecoking bunkers, heat treatment shops and main workshops have all been affected.(c) The plant of Siemens and Halske (inter-communications equipment) has suffered severely. Three machine shops, two stores buildings and theworkshops have all suffered.Niederschbneweide. Heavy damage has been caused to the factory ofNordcleutsche Motorenbau (tank engines). The two large buildings have bothreceived many hits, one of them being largely gutted. Of the three mediumbuildings, two have been destroyed and the third partially destroyed. other buildings in the plant have been affected in like degree.17. Bottrop. Photographs obtained of the synthetic oil plant 14 days afterthe Bomber Command attack on the night of the 20th/21st July show the works to be out of action. Damage, which is mainlv in the northern half of the works,includes several parts essential to the production of oil, together with the boiler house, generating and transformer stations.18. Bremen j Oslebshausen. Photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F.attacks on the 4th August, show damage is spread over the entire oil refinery ofDeutsche Vacuum. Three crude oil storage tanks have been severely damaged andthree small buildings concerned in lubricating oil treatment have been destrovedand several more damaged. In addition several tank cars on the tracks have beenburnt. In the marshalling yard N.E. of the plant several tracks have been cut and there is further damage to the aircraft works of Weser Flugzeugbau.19. Brunswick. Photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attacks ohaircraft assembly components and aero-engine factories on the 5th August,show : Querum. Damage is mainly concentrated in the Western and Southernportions of the aero-engine works of Niedersachsische Motorenwerke(Daimler-Benz engines), where six large workshops or stores buildings havebeen damaged in varying degree. Six out of 30 engine test beds have beenwrecked or severely damaged and several more have been affected to a lesser extent. In addition, many medium and small buildings have been destroyed or damaged.Waggum. Severe damage has been caused to the M.I.A.G. factory(Me. 110 assembly) involving mainly the sub-assembly and workshopfacilities.On the factory airfield damage has been inflicted on the N.E. hangararea, where two large hangars have been damaged; an aircraft shelterdestroyed and five small buildings and two barracks also damaged.Wilhelmitor. The M.I.A.G. components factory (Me. 110 components)has been considerably damaged, principally as a result of fire. Two of thelargest workshops have been partially destroyed and severely damaged andthe power station partly burnt out.
The adjacent premises of Wilke-Werke (boiler-makers, &amp;c.) have alsobeen heavily damaged, the large steel shop and the annealing shop beingparticularly affected. A machine shop and canteens and stores buildings have also been damaged in varying degree.20. Dollbergen. Photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the5th August, show severe damage has been caused throughout the Deutsche Gasolinoil refinery and none of the installations has escaped. The main boiler house hasbeen almost entirely demolished and a large number of storage tanks has been damaged or destroyed. Some 25 hits have cut railway tracks south of the targetand the main lines have been blocked.21. Fallersleben. Photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the5th August, show that the Volkswagenwerke plant (Ju. 88 components) has againsuffered severely. Nearly all the large buildings (with the exception of the powerhouse), including the machine shop, the assembly and machine shop and the pressshop, have been hit inany times. Rail tracks and roads serving the site have been cut and the main line tracks cut in at least five places. Two huttecl camps havereceived many hits which have seriously damaged some 14 huts.22. Halberstadt. Photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the5th August, shown that the main weight has fallen in the south-west hangar andbarracks area (connected with the assembly of F.W. 190). Five hangars, twomedium workshops and five barrack buildings have been severely damaged; inthe north-east dispersal area, one open aircraft shelter has been damaged.23. Hamburg. Photographs, taken about four hours after the U.S.A.A.F.attack on the 6th August, are largely obscured by the smoke of fires still burning,but it can be seen that considerable further damage has been inflicted on theRhenania Ossag Mineralolwerke oil refinery. The storage tanks in the northand west of one part of the works are well alight, and fires are burning fiercelyin the oil storage in the north of another part of the works and also in two groups of tanks on the western side. There are many direct hits among buildings inthe rest of the plant, some of which were damaged in the previous attack.24. Hannover I Lang enhag en Airfield. Photographs show that, as a resultof the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the 5th August, heavy damage has been caused inthe northern sector of the airfield which houses the F.W. Experimental Station.Of the eight large hangars, one has been destroyed and six have been severely damaged, while the control tower has been similarly affected. In addition, one large, two medium, nine small barracks and several other small buildings havebeen destroyed or damaged. The railway tracks in the hangar area have been cut by at least 13 craters.25. Hemmingstedt Oil Refinery. Photographs show that, as a result of theU.S.A.A.F. attack on the 4th August, a number of major units of the plant havebeen severely damaged or partly destroyed. The whole roof covering of the oilextraction plant has been destroyed as well as a building at the oil-mine entrance.At least two unidentified buildings, a large storage shed, the drum-filling plant and a cooling tower have all been severely damaged, a smaller storage shed hasbeen destroyed and a number of miscellaneous buildings have received varying degrees of damage.26. Ludwigshafen. Photographs show that the U.S.A.A.F. attacks on the21st and 31st July caused further damage to the south end of the I.G.Farben-industrie. Buildings affected include the main offices and laboratories, theengineering laboratory, two buildings connected with clyestuffs manufacture, fourworkshops or stores, and two unidentified buildings. In the north end of the plant two buildings in the gas generator plant have been damaged.27. Magdeburg I Buckau. Photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attackon the 5th August, show that practically all the buildings in the works ofFr. Krupp Grusonwerke (tanks, heavy machinery, engine crank shafts, &amp;c.) havebeen damaged, many of them severely. The north-west section of the works has suffered particularly heavily and buildings destroyed or damaged include the steel and copper foundries, repair shops, two pattern shops and the boiler-making shop.The three very large machine and assembly shops have all received direct hits.To the north-east of the works, the locomotive depot in the Buckaumarshalling yard has been hit many times and both round houses and the waggonrepair shop &quot;have been damaged, while tracks and rolling stock in the marshalling yard have also suffered. In addition, the machine and assembly shop in theBuckau railway repair shops have been affected.
28. Magdeburg (Neustadt). Photographs taken show that, as a result of theU.S.A.A.F. attack on the 5th August, damage has been caused to the Junkersaero engine works making Jumo 211 and 213 engines. The main stores havebeen gutted and the main workshops severely damaged, while the two engineassembly shops and the propellor and injection pump workshops have been damaged to a lesser degree.Extensive business and residential damage and destruction in the area west of the works has been caused.29. Merwiller Oil Refinery. Buildings in the southern half of the targetare seen on photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the 3rd August, tobe obscured bv smoke from fires still burning fiercely 20 hours after the attack.Nearly every visible building, however, is seen to be heavily damasred. these include the distillery, refineries, shaft apparatus, topping and cracking plant,boilers, head offices, petrol filling stations, laboratories and crude oil tanks.30. Peenemunde. Photographs show that in the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the4th August, further damage has been caused to the hydrogen peroxide and powerplants.31. RegensburgIObertraubling. Photographs, taken after the U.S.A.A.F.attack on the 21st July, show that severe damage has been caused in all parts ofthe plant (Me. 109 assembly). Every important building in the factory, with theexception of the repair hangar and the flying control and three barrack blocks,lias now been destroyed or severely damaged. Eleven Me. 109 on the ground havebeen damaged.32. Rostock j Marienehe. Although smoke obscures the western half of the target, it can be seen that the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the Heinkel Flugzeugwerkehas caused extensive damage throughout the factory area. The final and sub-assembly buildings, the component fabrication shops and the stores have all been affected * and the W.T. station has been destroyed. Other buildings hit include a wind tunnel, a gun-testing range, a paint store and several canteens.33. Schiuerin Airfield. Smoke rising from many buildings hampers theinterpretation of photographs taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the4th August, but it can be seen that the Station Headquarters, storage hangars and workshops and two warehouse buildings are all on fire. There are some 200craters across the centre of the airfield.34. Stendal. Photographs show that, as a result of the U.S.A.A.F. attackon the 6th August, one of the five large hangars in the north-west dispersal area has been completely destroyed and another partly destroyed, while other buildings in the barracks area have been been similarly affected. The railway track at the rear of the north-west dispersal area has been cut in at least five places.35. Stuttgart. Further photographic cover, taken after the three heavy attacks by Bomber Command on the 24th/25th, 25th/26th and 28th/29th july and the smaller U.S.A.A.F. attacks on the 19th and 21st July, shows that damage is concentrated in the old part of the city, especially in the central area S.W. ofthe main station. Many parts of this district have been completely devastated,mainly by fire, and there is most heavy damage to the south and west. In one area of about 50 acres, many public buildings have been damaged or destroyedby fire, including the Alles Schloss, the Main Post Office, Wilhelm&apos;s Palace and several banks and Government offices.36. General. A responsible German official concerned with fuel production has stated that air attack has resulted in a 50 per cent, decline in synthetic fuelproduction. In the opinion of his chief there would be a complete breakdown ofGerman fuel supplies within three months at the latest if attacks on plants andrefineries were to be continued on the present scale.He gave as an example the Rheinpreussen plant at Homburg (last attacked by Bomber Command on&apos; the 21st July), which would not resume production before september or October.













</content>
</cab>
