<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/2/1 images: 22-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Dojiument is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s&apos;&quot; GovernHentT&quot;WAR_____CABINET.MEAT      AND      SUGAR.Note by The First Lord of the Admiralty.RET.(59) 51,Copy No. /3M EAT.According to the Ministry of Food, after taking accountof losses from delays and sinkings and without assuming any increase in our average imports, we shall have 2,100,000 tons of meat available in the first war-year.    This is exactly the normalfigure.The only new facts are:-(l)    that,  averaged over the first year of war, say, 1,000,000more men than usual will have joined the Forces and thus be entitled to 5 or 6 lbs.  of meat a week instead of theiraverage consumption of 2 lbs.    Thus, say 3i lhs.  a weekextra must be found for 1,000,000 men, i. e. -in one yearbarely 80,000 tons.The answer- to (l) is that there should be no difficultyin increasing our imports by 80,000 tons, i.e.  less than,000 tons a month; or trenching to that small extent upon our reserves.(2) that,  the French are desirous of building up a reserve of220,000 tons and that we have agreed to help them in this.It appears that we were under the irrraression that we were only committed to supply h0,000 tons, but that the Frenchthink we should supply 20,000 tons a month for the first year ......

- 2 -year of the war, i.e.  240,000 tons.This promise was wholly unauthorised and made by a subordinate officer of the Food Ministry under a completemisapprehension of the facts or of what he was doing,    Surelythere is no need to build up a large reserve of refrigeratedmeat either here or in France, since both countries have an enormous natural reserve on the hoof.     In England this amountsto well over a year1s supply and in France it is probably larger.Obviously if 12/6 of our imports are put to reserve andanother 2k% handed to France to build up a French reserve, therewill be a deficit in Great Britain.    To introduce rationing,with all the live stock available, in order that both countries can build up a few weeks refrigerated reserves is surelyunreasonable.S U G A R.The sugar at present in our ownership at home (includingprivate hoards) afloat and abroad would feed us for over 10months, or for nearly 9 months if we continue our pre-warexports.    In addition we are told we have already contracted to buy Empire sugar after January at the rate of 10% of our normal consumption plus export.    Provided this Empire supplycontinues, we should be left a year from to-day with 2-g-months of sugar reserve in hand quite apart from the extra2-g- months reserve which next year&apos;s home beet crop will bring.There will be plenty of time as the war goes on toconsider rationing sugar, or buying further supplies to sustain our reserve.(Intd). W.S.C.1st October, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
