<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/6/15 images: 148-157</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1940.SECRET.Copy No.w.p. 0* (40) 4* 5WAR CABINET.THE CENSORSHIP OE UNITED STATES MAILS AND THEQUESTION OF A POSSIBLE CONTRABAND CONTROL base at   ST.  JOHN.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and theSecretary of State for the Dominions.IN accordance with the conclusion of the War Cabinet of the 27th February,53 (40), we circulate herewith two memoranda, the first on the censorship ofUnited States mails and the second.on the question of a possible contraband control base at St. John, New Brunswick. We also attach a draft telegram tothe United Kingdom High Commissioner at Ottawa, embodying the outline ofthe present scheme for the proposed base.AT the beginning of the war His Majesty&apos;s Government put into operationa scheme of censorship which had previously been elaborated. This dealt withterminal mails, that is, mails originating in the United Kingdom or arrivinghere. It was not until the 4th October that steps were taken to extend thiscensorship to transit mails on neutral ships,, that is, mails on ships brought intocontrol bases in this country and elsewhere for contraband examination.Under The Hague Convention No. 11 the postal correspondence of neutralsor belligerents is stated to be inviolable on the high seas. Nevertheless, the examination of these transit mails is essential to the conduct of economic warfare,since it provides the information upon which seizure and condemnation may bedecided. His Majesty&apos;s Government have therefore, as in the last war, feltconstrained to take this action, which is justified on the grounds that the examina-tion made is not for censorship, but for contraband purposes. This point of viewhas been successfully upheld on the whole by reference to the large number ofundeniable contraband items which have been found in the letter and parcel mail;these include food, clothing, industrial diamonds, currency cheques, bonds, &amp;c.It has, however, naturally been the object of protests by various Governments,who have appealed to The Hague Convention quoted above, and His Majesty&apos;sGovernment have been obliged to maintain the ostensible grounds for their examination in the face of considerable neutral criticism.2. The attitude of the United States towards British measures in exercisingbelligerent rights has undergone a considerable evolution since the beginningof the war.   At the outset, there were few complaints, but these have increasedH.A. E.Foreign Office, March 7, 1940.(1)The Censorship of United States Mails.10921   [20952]b
in number and the censorship has been an especial target for public resent-ment. On the 27th December, 1939, the United States Embassy in Londbnaddressed a note to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs protesting againstthe searching of American transit mails on board neutral ships, and invokedThe Hague Convention. A long and reasoned reply was returned to Mr. HerschelJohnson on the 16th January, in which some effective use was made of the total loss of mails occasioned by German sinkings of neutral ships. Nevertheless,the feeling aroused in the United States has only slightly abated in the interval,and there is abundant private evidence to show that the average American takes the strongest exception on personal grounds to any interference with his corras-pondence. The United States Secretary of State has on several occasions drawnLord Lothian&apos;s attention to the strong public feeling on this matter, and various measures have been taken in this country to improve the position. Among other things. United States correspondents in London have been shown an exhibitionof contraband! taken from mail bags, including a very large variety of parcelscontaining food of all kinds, clothing, soap, &amp;c.3.   His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Washington reported on the 14th February    Ithat while he was well on the way to having useful discussions with the State     department on most of the matters which produced the recent flare-up, the     1mails question was still the one about which the Department and american public opinion was most sensitive.   He referred particularly to the examinationof United States transatlantic air mail at Bermuda, which had served to whipup agitation considerably in recent weeks.   (It should be explained here thatthe examination at Bermuda is undertaken on the strength of the undoubtedBritish sovereignty in the island, and there are no legal grounds for any Americanprotests.   This has not, however, lessened the public irritation against thisparticular branch of the censorship, which is naturally of a spectacular kind.)Lord Lothian went on to recommend that His Majesty&apos;s Government should eithermake up their mind to make a strong case for the necessity of the censorship of transit mails, with such minor improvements in speed and administration as maybe possible, and try to persuade the Administration that to abandon the inspection of the mails would be a grave hindrance to the prosecution of the war,     or they must make some concession which would be recognised as a real attemptto meet American susceptibilities.   In reply, Lord Lothian was furnished with astatement at some length of the grounds which would render the abandonment of the examination of mails far more than a grave hindrance to the prosecution    of the war, and he was authorised at his discretion to explain to the State Depart-ment the real reasons for His Majesty&apos;s Governments persistence, namely, as    8described above, the necessity for obtaining evidence for the seizure and con-    fldemnation of contraband and enemy exports.   He was also authorised to assure     tthe United States Government that the &quot;information obtained from the mails is used solely to damage German interests, and that there is no question of the    fljimproper use of information to further British trade interests at the expense of    m. American or other neutral traders, either now or after the war.   This assurance    mwas given because the suggestion that our examination of mails is used to assistBritish competition with American exporters has been widely disseminated in   mthe United States, both in this war and in the last.4.   Lord Lothian has now replied that he does not think that he can speakeffectively to the Secretary of State about mails until he can state that analternative to Kirkwall has been found.   This depends, as indicated in theaccompanying memorandum, on the establishment of the proposed control base at   jS:St. John, New Brunswick.   The Canadian Government have now replied to the   9Jsuggestions made to them by His Majesty&apos;s Government on this subject, and itis hoped to secure their agreement to the details of the scheme worked out by the   HDepartments concerned in this country.   When this is forthcoming it will be   Hjpossible to approach the United States and to attempt to obtain their acquiescence   Bin the examination of mails as part of the general arrangements in connexion   with the new base, but it is clear that it will be necessary to proceed with thegreatest caution. fmflpHForeign Office, March 6, 1940.
Possible Contraband Control Base at St. John, New Brunswick.The idea of establishing a control base in Canadian waters was first mootedin December last in order to meet the United States Government&apos;s objections tothe diversion of their vessels to Kirkwall, which is inside the &quot;combat area &quot;forbidden them by the United States Neutrality Act. Lord Lothian was authorised on the 6th January to sound the State Department as to whether theUnited States Government would welcome the establishment of a base inCanadian waters for the examination of passengers and mail, it being understoodthat the navicert system provided an adequate method of avoiding the examina-tion of cargoes at Kirkwall. The State Department^ reaction to this suggestion was not very enthusiastic, and Lord Lothian represented strongly that theproposed base should deal with cargoes as well as mails and passengers. he further reported that owing to some leakage in Washington (and also, perhaps,to the fact that he had felt obliged to consult the Canadian Under-Secretary ofState for External Affairs, who was on a visit to Washington) it had becomeurgently necessary to enlist the co-operation of the Canadian Government withoutfurther delay. ,2. As the result of the Washington disclosures, the base became the objectof attention by the Press on both sides of the Atlantic and the matter was urgentlyconsidered by the Departments concerned. The Ministry of Economic Warfaremaintained as the result of close examination that the practical difficulties of organising a contraband control base in Canada would be almost insurmountable.The difficulty of communication with the Ministry of Economic Warfare inLondon, to which it.would be necessary to transmit lengthy manifests, would beenormous and would probably be beyond the capacity of the existing cables.Worse still, ships would have to be delayed in Canada until all the guaranteesfrom the consignees of their cargo had been received, whereas now, if manifestsare sent in advance by air-mail, the process is half completed by the time they reach the control base. There are already complaints of delays at European bases,and it was felt that considerably greater ones in Canada would be the cause of very serious objection in the United States. The proposal, therefore, as put to theCanadian Government on the 1st February, envisaged only a base for the controlof passengers and mails, cargoes being left to the navicert system. A proviso wasalso inserted, in view of the delicate position of the mails dispute with the UnitedStates Government at the time, that the Canadian Government should not beasked to agree to the examination of mail at St. John until &apos;&apos; the difference ofopinion with the United States as to the examination of mail had ceased to be an issue of real difficulty.&quot; This was the widest formula to which it was felt that theCanadian Government would agree.   . -3 At this point, however, on the initiative of the First Lord of theAdmiralty, it was decided that it would be bad tactics to rule out altogether thepossibility of dealing with cargoes at the proposed base in making our proposal tothe United States, and His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Washington was authorisedto explain to the State Department privately that cargo examination in canada would result in very greatly increased delays to United States ships. While,therefore, we did not wish to exclude the possibility altogether, we hoped that theUnited States Government would appreciate the far better facilities offered by thenavicert system. Lord Lothian has not hitherto specifically made this communi-cation, and it will be necessary to include a convincing explanation of the pointsinvolved in the final proposal to be made to the United States Government.4. The position at the beginning of February was, therefore, that theCanadian Government were considering, it was understood favourably, our proposal for the control of passengers and mails at the Canadian base, and ithad practically been decided already that this base would have to be at St. John,New Brunswick, since all other suitable British harbours on the western side ofthe Atlantic are barred to United States shipping under the Neutrality Act.Meanwhile, the United States Government were already generally aware of thearrangement which it was proposed to put forward, and Lord Lothian reported[20952] b 2
that the President almost certainly expected the substitution of St. John forKirkwall, but no official approach could be made until the Canadian Governmenthad expressed their readiness to co-operate.5. The Canadian Governments reply was not received until the 29th-February, but is at least as satisfactory as could have been hoped, if not more so.All His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s proposals are accepted with the repetition,however, of the proviso that the examination of mails should have &quot;ceased tobe an issue of real difficulty,&quot; and the Canadian Government further assume thatHis Majesty&apos;s Government in this country would establish and control theoperations of the proposed base.6. During February, however, while the Canadian Government was making up its mind, the situation did not remain static and various factors were introduced which affect the question of the base from the point of view of thiscountry. In the first place, the public agitation in the United States against thevarious aspects of His Majesty&apos;s Governments exercise of belligerent rights,which, probably with the connivance of the State Department, had been gathering-force since the beginning of the year, assumed somewhat serious proportions.Lord Lothian reported with some alarm on the extent of this feeling, withparticular reference to the question of diversion of United States ships intothe &quot;combat area&quot; which attracted greatly increased attention following the published German threats against neutral vessels entering the waters roundGi*eat Britain. As the result of this increased attention, the First Lord of theAdmiralty issued on the 29th January an order to the Fleet prohibiting the diversion of United States vessels into the &quot;combat area&quot; under any circum-stances. On this, the Ministry of Economic Warfare immediately took steps to conclude with the Moore McCormack Line, the only United States line trading to scandinavia, a temporary agreement whereby the Line undertook to give&quot; hold-back &quot; guarantees in respect of all items of cargo not covered by navicerts.This arrangement is still in force. It means that the items of cargo in respect ofwhich these guarantees have been given will be held at Bergen until the consentof the Ministry to their release has been received. This agreement is defectivebecause (a) there is no means of checking the accuracy of the statements made bythe shippers, (&amp;) there is no provision for dealing with mails, and (c) it clearlycannot be confined to United States vessels indefinitely. In consequence of (b),there is reason to suspect that mail for Germany in large quantities is beingintentionally routed by these steamers.7. The seriousness of the position in this respect rendered it necessary to consult Lord Lothian as to the prospects of inducing the Moore McCormack line to forgo the carriage of mails during the currency of the temporary agreementdescribed above. The Ambassador replied saying that he would be very loth tomake an approach in this sense, and again urging the immediate establishmentof a base at St. John to deal with the situation on regular lines. In view, however,of the absence at that time of any reply from the Canadian Government, it wasnot anticipated that a solution on these lines could be contemplated for some little time, and the First Lord of the Admiralty agreed to approach President Rooseveltdirect, explaining that his order to the Fleet of the 29th January had resultedin. creating this unforeseen gap in the machinery of. contraband control, and asking whether the President could do anything to ease the position. No replyhas as yet been received from the President, but it is now possible, in view of the intervening receipt of the Canadian Governments answer, to proceed with the steps towards the establishment of a base at St. John.8. In the light of the discussions which have been taking place between the interested departments since the proposal was first made, the general scheme now contemplated has undergone certain modifications.(a) Passengers could be dealt with at St. John without any serious difficulty.Their number is likely to be small.(b) Cargoes, for the reasons set out earlier in this memorandum would, itis hoped., be navicerted as far as possible. It is proposed, however, that complete&quot; hold-back &quot; guarantees should be given. Arrangements would have to be madewith the Scandinavian Governments for supervising unloading by some british or Anglo-Scandinavian organisation in the country concerned. The Ministry ofEconomic Warfare are about to take this matter up, and it is thought that in
return for the exemption of their own ships from calling at Kirkwall the scandinavian authorities may be willing to co-operate. Their co-operation is,however, an essential part of the plan and if, as is possible in the presentcircumstances, it is refused, some alternative will have to be found for dealingwith non-navicerted cargoes. For this reason the possibility in the last resortof a cargo control base in Canada cannot altogether be excluded. The canadian government have agreed that this possibility need not be entirely ruled out.(c) Mails constitute, as will be readily appreciated, the most difficult problem in connexion with the proposed base. In the first place, the Canadian Govern-ment, in accepting His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s proposals, have explicity repeated the reserve put to them that examination is intended to be introduced only after this question &quot; has ceased to be an issue of real difficulty &quot; with the United StatesGovernment. It can hardly be contended that this is as yet the case, but the urgency of the need for seme permanent arrangement is such that it is submitted that an attempt should be made in conjunction with the Canadian Governmentto procure the requisite measure of United States acquiescence by representingthe matter as part of the general proposal which is expressly designed with united States approval&apos;to meet their difficulties on other points. In the second place, consideration by those chiefly interested has now shown that actualexamination in Canada would present very considerable difficulties. TheCanadian willingness to allow the base to be organised from this country hasremoved one obstacle, since it was clear that, if they insisted on their consti-tutional right to organise the machinery for the examination of mails, it couldnot, in the light of their existing resources, be adequate for some time to come.Nevertheless, the difficulty of assembling a large censorship staff, transportingthem to St. John, and accommodating them there would be very great, and the usefulness of their efforts would be considerably affected by their distance fromthe principal intelligence centre in this country. It is accordingly agreed betweenthe Departments that it would be best to remove the mails at St. John andforward them by British mail boat to the United Kingdom for examination.This arrangement is likely to cause less delay than examination in Canada, andis much preferable from the point of view of the censorship organisation. It isnot suggested, however, that examination in Canada should be excluded in thelast resort.9. The action now suggested is to propound to the Canadian Governmentthe scheme contemplated and to seek their assent to a joint approach to theUnited States Government on these lines. A draft telegram to the UnitedKingdom High Commissioner at Ottawa has been prepared and is annexed hereto.Foreign Office, March 6, 1940.(3)Draft Telegram to the United Kingdom High Commissioner in Canada.(No. .  Secret.)MY telegram of 29th February, No. 345 : Control base. I shall be glad ifyou will now communicate with the Canadian Government in the followingsense.  Begins: 1. His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom have already expressed their gratification at learning that His majesty&apos;s Government inCanada are willing to co-operate with them in this very important question andthat they are prepared to authorise the establishment of a base at St. John,New Brunswick, for the examination of mails and passengers, while not ruling-out the possibility of cargo examination there also. They note also the canadian government&apos;s assumption that the base would be established, and its operationscontrolled, by the Government of the United Kingdom.2. The various problems as they present themselves to us are discussedbelow, under the three heads already indicated, viz., mails, passengers and cargoes,and, subject to the Canadian Government^ concurrence, we are anxious to makea joint approach with them to the United States Government with the least possible delays and to submit to them proposals on the following lines :  
3.   As regards mail, our view is (a) That the best arrangement in the interests of all concerned would bethat it should be taken off United States or other neutral vessels at st.. John for immediate transhipment to the next fast British shipleaving Canada for onward despatch to the United Kingdom whereit would be fully examined with all the facilities available forexpeditious handling there, and forwarded to its destination.(6) For reasons of administrative efficiency and despatch the above arrange-ment is infinitely to be preferred to actual examination in Canada,but in the last resort if United States acceptance of the whole scheme were to depend on it, it might be suggested to them that the mailsshould be taken off at St. John and examined there prior to onwarddespatch by the next United States ship to call at that port.(c) As regards mail carried by other neutral vessels, the alternative (a) alone would be suggested in the first place to the Government concerned;if, however, (b) above had been conceded to the United States and ifwe were pressed, we should find it difficult to refuse similar facilities to other neutrals, i.e., examination at St. John.4. The examination of passengers and their personal luggage (and cabins)and the quarters of the crew would, it is thought, present little difficulty at st.. John, and being carried out concurrently with other operations, would involve no additional delay. It is hoped that the Canadian Government would make such arrangements as might be necessary for- their own agents to exerciseauthority under Canadian law for detention of any persons who have to beremoved. (A separate telegram is being sent to you giving information as tothe procedure followed here in this respect.)5. As regards cargoes, we have always felt, as the Canadian Governmentwill be aware, that no satisfactory alternative to the navicert system exists. Thisis particularly applicable to that period of the year when the St. Lawrenceroute is open and cargoes leave United States territory from the Lake ports aswell as from ports on the Atlantic. As has already been explained (my telegram to you of 1st February, No. 159), the difficulties of dealing with cargoes at abase in Canadian waters are very great, unless formidable delays are to beexpected, and we should therefore hope that the United States Government andother neutral Governments concerned in shipping from the United States to northern Europe will themselves come to the realisation of the advantages ofthe navicert system. This system would be rendered entirely satisfactory from our point of view if the neutral Governments of Northern Europe would agreeto proposals, such as are about to be made to the Norwegian Government, thatthey should allow the unloading of cargoes at specified ports to be supervised.If this could be done, the call at Kirkwall would be rendered superfluous, andthere would also be no necessity for anything but nominal cargo control at theCanadian base. The latter would, however, serve some very useful purposes,e.g., it would enable the manifests of ships calling there to be examined forevidence of cargoes likely to present special difficulty.b\ We should be glad of the views of the Canadian Government on theinstitution of a similar system at Montreal or Quebec for cargoes of United Statesorigin on the Great Lakes route.7. We note that the Canadian Government are agreeable that examinationof west-bound cargoes for enemy exports (vide my telegram to Canadian Goveru-ment of the 25th November, No. 110) should take place at St. John, and we should propose that this should be suggested to United States and other neutral Govern-ments to eliminate the necessity for calls by their ships on the northern route at a united Kingdom base. Here again we should be glad of the Canadian Govern-ment&apos;s views on examination at Quebec or Montreal of incoming cargoes on thatroute for destinations in the United States.8. The question of the examination of mail for enemy exports is still under examination, but it is hoped that it will not be necessary to suggest the inclusionof this operation at St. John.
9. The operations which it is suggested should be carried out at St. Johnand which it is proposed should form the subject of a joint approach by theGovernments of Canada and the United Kingdom to the United. States are thus : (a) The trans-shipment of mail from east-bound vessels, preferably to thenext fast British ship leaving Canada for the United Kingdom. Inthe last resort, the possibility of its examination at the Canadian base for despatch by the next ship of the same Line is not excluded.(b) The examination of passengers and their luggage and cabins, and the crew&apos;s quarters.(c) In the case of east-bound cargoes, the examination of the manifest.(d) In the case of United States and other neutral west-bound ships on theNorthern route, the examination of their cargoes for enemy exports.10. Accepting the Canadian Governments view as to the control and operation of the base, we should propose to place its operations under the general supervision and administrative control of the Commander-in-Chief, America and west Indies Station. The staff could be provided, in the first place, from UnitedKingdom sources, but we should hope that the Canadian Government would not exclude the possibility of making Canadian personnel available at a later stage.It may prove difficult, for instance, to find all the Post Office staff required for there constitution of mail if it became necessary to resort to the alternative mentionedunder 3 (b) above. The examination of mails, if this alternative had to be adopted,would be progressive, i.e., in the initial stages we should not aim at a 100 percent, examination, though it would be necessary to work up to this. It is thoughtthat the despatch of a special vessel, with the necessary trained personnel, wouldbe desirable as soon as the United States Government had indicated their generalwillingness to encourage the use of a Canadian base on the above lines.A suitable vessel is available, and the necessary staff could be assembled herewithout delay. The first advance staff could be accommodated on board, but itwould be necessary later tc obtain premises on shore and to free the ship for other duties elsewhere.11. There remains the need for certain small craft, which it would bedifficult to provide from this country, viz., four vessels of large drifter or tug type,able to stow several hundred bags of mail, land small numbers of passengers, and carry search parties of 12-18 men, and four motor-boats for harbour work, com-bining speed and seaworthiness. It would be very helpful if the canadian government would inform us whether these craft could be provided locally.12. As regards the last paragraph of the Canadian communication, weentirely agree that Ashton-Gwatkin should visit Ottawa for full discussion ofthis matter with the appropriate authorities as soon as he finds it possible todo so.   Ends.It is suggested that )rou should allow Rayner, the United Kingdom Censor-ship Liaison Officer, to see this telegram for his own confidential information.Repeated by Foreign Office to Washington, No.




</content>
</cab>
