<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/114/0 images: 110-112</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1963C. (63) 1179th July, 1963Copy No.   ^ fjCABINETLONDON CONFERENCE ON SATELLITE COMMUNICATIONSAt the first meeting of the European Conference at Paris in May, there was almost unanimous support for the United Kingdom view that our objective should bea single world-wide system organised on as comprehensive a basis as possible. Inview of the attitude taken by the other countries, the French did not pursue theiridea of an agreement of limited scope and duration with the United States until such time as Europe was able to establish a system of its own. Consequently theconference was able to adopt a resolution, which stated that satellite communicationsshould be organised in such a way as to permit European countries to take a full part in the provision of launchers, satellites and other equipment for inclusion inthe system as it was developed.2. It was agreed that the views of the United States authorities should besought on this resolution, and a written statement of the United States attitude hasnow been received. This is satisfactory; the United States Government expect thevoice of participants in questions of management, finance, technology, operations and supply to be related to capital invested and use of the system. It is clear thatan international consortium or corporation of some kind will be needed to establish and operate the system and that an inter-Governmental convention will be requiredto establish this. It would seem desirable for the United Kingdom and as many other countries as possible to contribute their full share of the capital in order toprevent the managing board of the consortium being dominated by United Statesinterests.3. It will be necessary to ensure that the convention which establishes the consortium safeguards the right of member-countries to make a materialcontribution to the system in proportion to their capital investment. The implications of this principle are certain to be discussed at the London Conference. It should beborne in mind that the United States Communications Satellite Corporation, whichwill own the United States share of the system, consider that the sole criteria in the placing of contracts for the provision of material should be cost and efficiency.These criteria will tell heavily, at least in the first instance, in favour of United Statesequipment. The consortium cannot be expected to purchase equipment regardless of price, and will need to satisfy itself that the equipment which it purchases isreliable. It follows that, if we wished to provide satellites, we should have to demonstrate our ability to produce a reliable satellite. The research anddevelopment cost for a medium-orbit system might amount to some  20 to 30 million. Most, if not all, of this money would have to be found by Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment; and it would not be possible to recover any large proportion of itin the foreseeable future in the cost of the equipment we sell to the consortium.On the other hand, unless and until we were prepared to undertake such research and development, we should, through the medium of the consortium, be assisting the development of the technology of other countries. Whether this should be anoverriding consideration cannot be decided now.4. If a satellite communications system were to cost about  200 million toestablish and if, as would seem right, the capital contribution of individual countries was related to their use of international communications, the United States shareMemorandum by the lord Privy Seal2788
might be between  100 and  150 million, and the United Kingdom sharemight be between  20 and  30 million depending on the number of countriestaking part. These figures are necessarily very broad estimates. Though we would hope that some of this  20 to  30 million would be spent in the United Kingdom,it should be recognised that in the initial stages the consortium would be obliged to do almost all its purchasing in the United States. As long as this continued,our financial contribution would be simply an investment in a telecommunicationssystem, but an investment which we would expect to be profitable.5. There are thus two distinct problems, our expenditure on research anddevelopment and our investment in a global system. Neither of these problemscan be resolved at present. We shall be in a better position to reach decisions ina few months when our design study of a communications satellite has beencompleted. We should not allow this to delay the progress of our discussions with Europe and the United States, since these discussions should assist inclarifying the issues.6. As far as the discussions with the United States are concerned we should accept their view that they should be on a comprehensive, and not a purelyEuropean-United States basis. We should therefore advocate the holding of a preliminary international meeting of all the countries concerned before the endof this year, the primary purpose being to establish some kind of international machinery with an appropriate structure to carry the project forward, withparticular reference to the design of the system and the nature of the formalorganisation or consortium required to establish and manage it.7. As regards further discussions with Europe, we argued at the Parismeeting that no formal organisation was needed at the present time, either for the mobilisation of European potential or for the co-ordination of European generalpolicy. These questions were not discussed in detail, but it was clear that most other countries did not share our views and we are likely to come under heavy pressure on this score. Indeed, some countries are thinking in terms of a jointlyfinanced European contribution. As far as the mobilisation of Europeanpotential is concerned, we should be prepared to go along with the Europeansto the extent of proposing a detailed study of the practical issues. On the wider questions of the machinery for the formulation of a common European policy,there is likely to be general support for further meetings of the conference, andwe should propose this, suggesting however that a small secretariat will berequired. We should at this stage avoid taking up a rigid position which wouldisolate us from our principal European partners.8.   The above suggests that:(a) We should continue to regard a single global system as our primaryobjective.(b) If we wish to provide equipment for such a system we shall need to spend a substantial sum on research, and communication satellitesystems development. We cannot expect to recover much of this expenditure from the sales of our equipment.(c) We cannot consider what we ought to spend on research and developmentuntil we have completed our design study and know more about the characteristics of the eventual world system.9. At the London Conference the United Kingdom Delegation should,therefore, take the following lines:(a) Welcome the United States reply to the resolution on the organisation ofsatellite communications adopted at the Paris Conference.(b) Propose that the establishment of a single global system should beentrusted to an international consortium or corporation.(c) Propose that European and other countries should contribute capital tosuch a consortium or corporation, approximately in proportion to their share of inter-continental telecommunications traffic.(d) Propose that countries or groups of countries contributing to the capital cost of the system should have the option, in the future, to provideequipment in proportion to their capital contribution. But it should berecognised that equipment supplied under that arrangement would
need to be competitive in quality and price and that the countrieswishing to exercise their option might have to pay for research anddevelopment in order to make this possible. The delegation should makeit clear, if necessary, that Her Majesty&apos;s Government have not themselves finally decided whether to incur such expenditure.(e) No formal European organisation, in addition to the European launcher development Organisation (ELDO), need be established immediately.In particular, any further work on communication satellites should, forthe time being, be undertaken by individual countries working inco-operation with each other. The United Kingdom should proposethat there should be a joint study of the arrangements for the effectivemobilisation of European potential and that further meetings of theconference, serviced by a small secretariat (probably in London),should formulate overall European policy.(/) Propose that the London Conference should suggest to the United StatesGovernment that an inter-Governmental meeting should be convenedbefore the end of the year, to be attended by the United States and interested European, Commonwealth and other countries. Such aconference could establish machinery whereby the various aspects ofthe problem, including settlement of design and management of thesystem, could be considered further.10. I invite my colleagues to endorse the line proposed in paragraphs and 9 above.E. H.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,8th July, 1963.

</content>
</cab>
