<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/114/0 images: 158-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1963C. (63) 132 . Copy No.     6 419th July, 1963CABINETFUTURE DEFENCE policy memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer the decision we are asked to make by the Minister of Defence about the replacement of existing aircraft carriers is of very great significance. What is involved is not merely the cost of the carriers and their aircraft, important as thisis, but the whole strategic plan to which we intend to work in the 1970s.2. Every time we look at defence in the round, we decide that our commitments in total are too great. Every time we look at one or other commitment in isolationwe decide that it is inescapable. The net result is that we go on planning to do more than we can or should afford in the field of defence. Moreover, when we seethe true cost of these plans, the figures are so alarming that we are continuallyforced to chop the programme about and look for economies (often deferments).As a result, we do not, I suggest, really get proper value even for the large sumswe spend.3. I consider that the current decision about the carrier programme is theopportunity for taking an effective grip on our future defence programme and its main elements: the independent deterrent, the European commitment and theworld-wide role.4. I must stress to my colleagues my very real concern at the rate of growth of defence expenditure. The 1964-65 defence costings at  2,012 million are84 per cent in real terms above this year&apos;s Budget without any allowance for aid for India and Malaysia or any contribution to a North Atlantic Treaty Organisation(NATO) mixed-manned force. When this figure is taken in conjunction with the forecast estimates for expenditure generally it seems that total Government spendingnext year will rise by even more than this year&apos;s figure of  527 million or about  per cent. These figures clearly involve a serious and significant increase in theproportion of the national income taken by Government expenditure.5. I am equally concerned about the position for the more distant future. Itis true that defence costings show little further increase after 1965-66 but I am afraid I have no confidence in these costings whatever. All experience points theother way. Not only have we had increases in recent years in defence expenditureon a much higher level what is more significant is that the figure now estimated for 1965-66 is nearly 10 per cent, in real terms above what was last summerestimated for Defence in 1965-66. In other words, the closer the year we are considering and therefore, presumably, the more settled the programme and themore reliable the figures, the greater and more rapid the rate of increase in theestimates.6. I believe the only realistic conclusion we can reach from these figures isthat if we intend to pursue a defence policy based on all our existing commitments and on meeting them to the extent that our professional advisers consider necessary,we shall be deliberately planning to increase the proportion of the national incomespent on defence. I am not at this moment seeking to argue that such a decision isunacceptable. What I do wish to point out very clearly to my colleagues is that sucha decision once taken cannot be kept secret and that the inevitable corollary is either a reduction in public expenditure on other things, e.g., education, housing, roads,2842
or a strict control over the growth of private consumption through the use of the tax system. Already it is difficult to see how next year&apos;s budget can contain any netreductions in taxation whatever. This is not just a piece of annual Treasurypropaganda this is a commonsense estimate of the position presented to us bynext year&apos;s level of public expenditure on the assumption that our present policiesare successful in achieving a steady expansion of the economy.7. I accept the argument that the needs of national defence must have priority. This 1 think is inescapable in logic and in politics. But what we have todetermine is what are the needs of national defence. However much money wespend we cannot alone, in modern times, guarantee the defence of these islandsagainst Communist aggression. We have already deliberately decided not to providefor certain eventualities, e.g., a broken-back war, a prolonged nuclear exchange in western Europe or an unaided landing against opposition east of Suez. Clearlywe must make some choices. The extent of the defence commitments we accept isa matter for our political decision and such a decision, I would argue, must betaken in the light of our economic capacity. For it is unrealistic in modern times to separate out strictly defence expenditure in the military sense. We are fighting apolitical as well as a military campaign. All expenditure in support of externalpolicy defence, aid, propaganda, diplomacy is therefore part of the same pictureand should be looked at as one; and in the long run the strength of our owneconomy must be regarded as fundamental to our defence against the social andpolitical, as much as the military, threat of Communism.8. I would therefore ask my colleagues to consider the problems of defence expenditure against this background. What is it that we shall be seeking to do inthe 1970s? What is the most economical way of meeting our commitments?Which commitments, if any, are so expensive that we can no longer afford to carrythem?9. I will take as one example expenditure east of Suez (in which of course the carriers play a very large role). We are working on the assumption that what will be involved is not a nuclear exchange but a limited war. Our expenditure inthe Far East is in the order of  300 million to  400 million a year and we arespending an additional  150 million to  200 million in the Middle East. The sumspent on the Far East is equivalent in resources to about twice our overseas aid programme, two-thirds of the electrical power programme, total public housing,or half the total cost of the schools or of the hospital services. It may be that weshould be right to continue to commit our resources on this scale to this objective.But I must point out that none of our competitors, apart from the United States,is accepting commensurate responsibility and at the same time maintaining aswe are substantial forces in Western Europe and an independent deterrent. Itmay be that we have to handicap ourselves permanently with a level of defence commitments greater than that of our competitors. But if so let us take a consciousand deliberate decision, and not fall into the situation by sheer inertia.10. I am very well aware that the present time is not propitious for takingmajor decisions in the field of our overseas commitments; equally I think I canargue that it is not wise now to take decisions which commit us for the future and which may prevent us at a more convenient time taking the decisions onpriorities that will, at some time, have to be taken. I do hope very much therefore that my colleagues will not wish at this stage to accept a commitment for expenditure on any carrier replacement.R. M.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,19th July, 1963.

</content>
</cab>
