<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/114/0 images: 174-175</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HER. BRITANNIC MAJESTY!S GOVERNMENT)C.(63) 138COPY NO.p ftCABINETEXPORT of  BUCCANEER AIRCRAFT TO SOUTH africa the Strategic Exports Committee at its meeting on 19th July-considered a Note by the Chairman of the Official Committee on strategic Exports (S.E.(63) 17) about the position which has arisenon the contract between the Hawker Siddeley Aircraft Company andthe South African Government for the delivery of sixteen buccaneer aircraft at a price of  24 million.2.     The South African Government is concerned that if theOpposition were to be returned to power and fulfilled their threat toplace an embargo on the delivery of the sixteen Buccaneer aircraft which the South Africans have ordered, they would be unable under theterms of their present contract with the manufacturers to recover anyof the payments which they had made.    The total value of the contractis  24 million and a second payment of  6 million is due in October.The South African Embassy have now informed the Foreign Office that unless they can obtain assurances either that the aircraft will be delivered, or that they will obtain compensation for the deposits theyhave already made, they may decide to cancel the order rather thanrisk making a second payment.   Failure on the part of the South african government to make a second payment would almost certainly amountto a breach of contract and the manufacturers would then be entitledto be indemnified by the Export Credit Guarantee Department.    the manufacturers, on the other hand, have no liability under their presentcontract with the South African Government to repay the deposit,provided that they complete the aircraft and deliver them ex-works.3.     It was suggested that a method of inducing the manufacturers toamend the contract so as to allow for a refund to the South Africans ifthe delivery of the aircraft was prevented, would be for Her Majesty*sGovernment to enter into a formal contract with the suppliers underwhich they would undertake either to take over the aircraft if exportwere refused or to pay the firm full compensation for work done up tothat stage.    It is understood, however, that the manufacturers wouldbe unwilling to modify the contract even to this extent unless the SouthAfrican Government undertook to place a further order for Buccaneers,which it is believed that they are contemplating.
4.      The Ministerial Committee on Strategic Exports were agreedthat this contract was of the first importance to the United Kingdomaircraft industry, not only on its own account but because of othereven more valuable orders which were in prospect.    Some membersof the Committee feared that if we Sid not take the action suggestedin the preceding paragraph there was a serious risk that the order would be cancelled.    The majority of the Committee however took the view that there was considerable political disadvantage in adoptingin substance the course of a.ction which the Opposition have announced that they propose to follow, if they are returned to power.They thought that there was a large element of bluff in the SouthAfrican approach since it was extremely doubtful whether the south africans would be able to obtain aircraft with similar characteristicsfrom any other source, for example from France..   Moreover, buccaneer aircraft from a cancelled South African order would be surplus tothe requirements of the Royal Navy and were of a type that wouldrequire substantial modifications before they could be taken into service on aircraft carriers.5,     In any case it seems intolerable that threats by the opposition should place Her Majesty&apos;s Government in the position of having to indemnify foreign governments against the possibility that theOpposition may be returned to power.6.     In the circumstances therefore the majority of the committee held that v/e should take no further action with the South AfricanEmbassy other than to make it clear that we had no intention of stopping the delivery of the aircraft.7.      The Committee saw no objection to the manufacturersnegotiating with the South African Government a variation in thecondition in respect of deposits in return for the placing of a furtherorder,    In the absence of action on the lines desired by the minority9 ^    of the Committee, it would seem sensible to suggest this to theX^virt chapter.v&amp;rnm-etrt.8.      The Buccaneer is an aircraft designed for maritime work,and would be an unsuitable instrument for internal repression.    Itis arguable that a refusal to supply it would be a breach of the spirit,if not the letter, of the Simonstown Agreement.9.     I invite my colleagues to agree with the view expressed bythe majority of the Ministerial Committee on Strategic Exports.J. A.E. -C.Treasury Chambers, S, 17. 1.23rd July, 1963-2j-

</content>
</cab>
