<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/114/0 images: 251-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   September 1963C. (63) 15216th September, 1963CABINETRURAL BUS services memorandum by the Minister of transport i seek a decision on the long-outstanding problem of rural bus services. my predecessor set up a committee under Professor D. T. Jack in 1959. They reportedin March 1961. Their main conclusion was that the lack of some bus services wascausing hardship to a small number of people and inconvenience to more, andthat the only real remedy was financial assistance. The majority recommendeddirect financial aid, administered by county councils and paid for partly from local and partly from central funds. (The minority preferred a remission of the fuel tax.)Special studies confirmed the Jack committee&apos;s assessment2. Following discussion in the Home Aifairs Committee in January and june 1962, I instituted further factual studies in six selected rural localities.I circulated an analysis of them under E.A. (63) 122. They confirmed the JackCommittee&apos;s assessment of hardship and inconvenience. It would seem that, for those without private transport, the shortage of public facilities imposes a significant limit on the pattern of life. The trend in private transport is steadilyupwards, both as to ownership and ability to drive. Only 10 per cent of the journeysin the survey were by public transport. But those without private transport travelledsignificantly less than those with it. Half the people from households withoutprivate transport made no journey during the survey week, compared with lessthan a quarter of those with private transport.Further discussion of my proposals3. In July I renewed my earlier proposals in a memorandum to the economic policy Committee (E.A. (63) 122). The Committee agreed (E.A. (63) 31st Meeting,Item 5) that a statement should be made towards the end of the summer recess.They also invited a meeting of Ministers to consider my proposals further. Thismeeting, on 1st August, invited me to bring my proposals before the Cabinet.These proposals were that:(i) the County Councils be given power to assist financially in providing ruralbus services, allowing any money they spend in this way to rank forrate deficiency grant;(ii) we should explore ways of allowing the small man greater freedom inobtaining licences for minor bus services;(iii) we should consider stimulating the provision of a car lift pooling schemeto be run on a voluntary basis by welfare organisations.The first of these is the crucial one.Considerations to be taken into account4. (i) In our 1959 manifesto we said &quot; We have set up a committee to help us solve the problem of public transport in the countryside &quot;. This was the JackCommittee. Under the Transport Act, 1962, we have ensured that, where railwaypassenger services are closed down, adequate bus services exist or are introduced,if necessary as a charge on the railways and thus (in present circumstances) on theExchequer. But no similar steps have been taken in areas where it is bus, ratherthan railway, services which risk being discontinued.Copy No.3153
(ii) We cannot use the bus licensing system to force bus operators to continueuneconomic services against their will.(iii) The problem appears to be transitory in most affected areas (as privatetransport takes over). But it is likely to shift from one area to another as individualrural bus services become uneconomic.i* ^(iv) The problem is therefore essentially a local one and it is right that therrrain responsibility for any subsidy should rest with the County Council ratherthan the central Government.Objections to my proposals. The Chancellor of the Exchequer has objected to my principal proposal on the ground that it would mean financing a new social service. But the exchequer is already subsidising rural transport in the form of either trains or bus servicesreplacing railway passenger services (see paragraph 4 (i)). Moreover, if the british railways Board&apos;s bus subsidies can be transferred in due course to the CountyCouncils as I think they should there would be an appreciable saving to theExchequer. When the Railways Board were paying  60,000 (the figure is now 86,000 and likely to increase materially as passenger closures proceed) only some 8,000 would have fallen on the Exchequer as rate deficiency grants.6. My proposal in paragraph 3 (i) will add to the County Councils&apos; rate burden. They cannot be expected to welcome it. One way of meeting their difficulties would be for the Exchequer to pay a proportion of the subsidy. But I have not proposed this: (a) it is essentially a local matter, and (b) if the full financial responsibility is on the County Councils they have more incentive to avoid unnecessary subsidies.The present legal restrictions on sharing arrangements which might otherwisehelp in meeting the difficulties7. My colleagues have asked me to explain the licensing and other legalrestrictions on private or ad hoc transport sharing arrangements. Briefly, a roadservice licence is required for every vehicle, including a private car, carryingpassengers at separate fares. A taxi or hire car operator breaks the law if on anyjourney he carries two persons from both of whom he takes fares direct or all hispassengers are not one party under a collective contract. The object of road servicelicensing is to protect established bus operators from unfair competition. the licences specify the service to be run and control, as necessary, the route, timetableand fares. Applications for licences are published and existing operators can object.A small operator is not likely to be refused a licence if his service does not conflict with another. But the procedure is undeniably cumbersome for him.8. If the controls are relaxed the danger is that these vehicles will poach onthe routes where bus services are still running and undermine them. I propose to explore whether the licensing procedure can be simplified to encourage the useof smaller vehicles for fare-paying passengers where they can do no harm to thebus operators&apos; services, and also how we can encourage car pooling schemes. ButI am positive that relaxations of this kind alone are not the answer to the problem.Will new legislation be required to empower local authorities to subsidise ruralbus services?9. I understand that the powers conferred on local authorities by Section 136of the Local Government Act, 1948 (and in Scotland, Section 339 of the LocalGovernment (Scotland) Act 1947), could be regarded as capable of use for thispurpose. But it may be objected that this was not one of the purposes in mindwhen the two Local Government Acts became law. I should be grateful for theviews of my colleagues.Conclusion10. I have, from the outset, taken the position that a solution of the ruralbus problem is required on social and political, rather than economic, grounds.The pressure from Members of Parliament and other representatives of rural areas continues. And I think we must accept that the special surveys have shown the existence of a social problem, though a shifting one.
annex draft STATEMENT ON RURAL transport the Government have now completed the studies of rural transport put inhand last year to help in the consideration of this difficult problem. The mainelement of these factual surveys was a house to house canvass of all the inhabitants of six carefully selected small areas in Devon, Lincolnshire and Westmorland inEngland, Montgomeryshire in Wales, and Kirkcudbrightshire and Banffshire inScotland.2. The analysis of the results of this canvass shows that only 10 per cent ofthe journeys made by the people concerned were by public transport of one formor another, mainly by bus. Even those in households without their own transportmade many journeys in other people&apos;s cars, but they made fewer journeys thanthose who had private transport. The proportion of private vehicles to population in the survey areas was above the national average; the trend of both vehicleownership (and of ability to drive) is steadily upward.3. The surveys, the results of which I am now publishing, confirm the earlierfindings of the Jack Committee on rural bus services. In rural areas, people havesubstantially deserted public transport. Private transport has filled much of the breach; but there are people who lack their own transport, and who cannot relyentirely on others to meet their needs. For these people, lack of public transportlimits what they can do, sometimes to the point of real inconvenience, sometimeseven of hardship.[4. The proposals for the reshaping of the railways are a further factor ofwhich we must take account. I have powers under the Transport Act. 1962, torequire the Railways Board to ensure the provision of substitute bus serviceswhen rail passenger services are withdrawn; and as long as the Exchequer meetsthe railway deficit, any expenditure incurred by the railways in providing these services falls on the taxpayer. But in the longer term we cannot expect the board to carry indefinite commitments to see that these services go on, and any arrangements made to deal with rural buses generally ought to be wide enoughto meet the situation which may arise when the method of payment for particularbus services by the Railways Board ceases to be appropriate.l5. The problem in each case is essentially a local one, and the government consider therefore that where a rural bus service, if it is to continue, will requirefinancial assistance, the provision of that assistance must he the responsibility ofthe County Council. The expenditure involved would of course be eligible where appropriate for help from the Exchequer through the Rate Deficiency Grant(in Scotland, the Exchequer Equalisation Grant).[6. County Councils do not at present have the necessary powers to make payments for general bus services, and an enabling Bill would be necessary. I shall therefore be inviting the County Councils&apos; Associations and the Association of bus operators to discussions with my Department.111. In these circumstances I feel it right to put to my colleagues the threeproposals in paragraph 3.12. If there is agreement in principle that proposal 3 (i) should be accepted,then we should consider its application after an interval in each case (I would suggest two years) to those bus services which are subsidised by the railways board under the provisions of the Transport Act, 1962.Procedure13. The view has been expressed that it would be necessary to consult theCounty Councils before the Government can finally settle its policy. I attach at annex a draft statement which might be made before such consultations began.E. M.Ministry of Transport, S.E. 1,12th September, 1963.

</content>
</cab>
