<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/114/0 images: 294-295</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL &quot;        272C.(63) 164 COPY NO.20th September, 1963CABINETDIFFICUET EXPORT CREDIT MARKETSMemorandumJbx.^ieJPrgsidexit of the Board of Tradehi connection, with the discussion on Cuba, my colleagues may find it convenient to have before them by way of background a shortnote briefly listing the markets which from the Export Credits pointof view could be troublesome.2.      They are:-JndonesiaTotal Export Credits Guarantee Department (E.C.G.D,)liabilities are  lljf million.    This does not include a FinancialGuarantee in respect of a dredger which is being constructed in theUnited Kingdom and on which our maximum liability could rise to afurther   3 million.IranE.C.G. D, liabilities amount to come  17 million.    Owing to internal financial stringency there have been defaults and delays, and claims payments since 1st April, 1961, have come to some  2 million.During the same pexnod we have had recoveries of  400, 000.    Inview of the fact that Iran is an oil producer we would hope in due course to get a substantial part of the money back.ArgentinaE.C.G. D. liabilities amount to some  56 million.    TheArgentine would have been forced into default if special internationalassistance had not been organised.BrazilE.C.G. D. liaibilities are of the order of  10 million.Inflation in Brazil is proceeding at an alarming rate.    Here againwe have been spared claims becuase of the special assistance whichhas been organised.TurkeyThis is where S.C.G.D. has made big payments in the past.We have paid out some  22j million in claims of which some 16 million have not yet been recovered (although an inter-Governmental agreement i3 in operation for phased repayments over-1-(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNlvISNT)
ct hL i 0a long period) and we shall have to pay another   ijt million.This relates to past debts;  recently the position has been more satisfactory because of international assistance being given to turkey.3.      The position on Cjjba is that the Cubans have continuedpayments on large contracts to the Department and have repaida substantial part of the claims which we had to meet since therevolution.     The relevant figures are:-E.C.G. D. total liabilities Jan, 1961    -    9a million&quot; &quot;        &quot; Sept. 1963   -    2^ million total claims paid  960, 000;   of whichrecovered  565, 000;  leaving    395, 000 outstandingThe Cubans seem to have been conscientious in their efforts to repay, and they have done this without the injection of any newmoney.    It will be noted that they have reduced their outstandingdebt by some  7 million, and have repaid the larger part of theclaims.4.     As regards other countries, India and Pakistan do not present Export Credit problems, but this is only because of thevery substantial scale of international assistance which has been accorded to them.    Yugoslavia and Egypt are also countries wheredifficulties in the future cannot be exluded.5.      It should be noted that the figures of liabilities above relateonly to S.C.G.33. experience:  i. e. debts not covered by theDepartment are not included.E . ji/.Eoard of Trade, S. W. 1,21st September, 1963-2

</content>
</cab>
