<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/114/0 images: 316-317</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  October 1963C. (63) 172 ^ &apos; .    . Copy No.    631st October, 1963    - &apos;:&apos;      \:&apos;:-&apos; %... - - .   CABINET -RATESMemorandum by the Secretary of State for scotland as the Minister of Housing says in his paper C. (63) 167 about the burden ofrates, he and I have not been able to discuss the proposals he makes on this subject.I feel, however, that my colleagues should know the Scottish repercussions thatwould undoubtedly result from the adoption of his proposals.2. First, however, I should like to make a general point. The Scottishrevaluation which took effect in 1961-62 also produced major difficulties, includingbitter complaints from some local authorities whose share of equalisation grant(equivalent to the English rate deficiency grant) suffered, and individual caseswhere householders suffered increases in rate burdens that would qualify for reliefunder the Ministers 25 per cent- 5 test. But with the support of the local authoritiesgenerally we stuck firmly to our guns, and the complaints died down. In spiteof the inevitable continuing rise in rate burdens, they have not been renewed.Might not a firm stand have the same result in England and Wales, especially as in the Minister^ own words there has undoubtedly been a drop in the temperature?3. For my part I believe that the appointment of the Allen Committee (whichis concerned with Scotland as well as with England and Wales) has demonstratedour immediate concern for those suffering hardship. I agree with the Minister of housing that we should accept the need for a comprehensive review of the wholefinancial relationship between central and local government, to follow on afterthe Allen Committee&apos;s report. This I find throughout Scotland is what our supporters are hoping for. A decision to look at and solve the long-term problem is most important to them.4. On the Minister^ detailed proposals, Scotland could not possibly standout. If extra money is put into the English general grant on the basis proposed inparagraphs 6 and 7 of the paper, it will be quite inescapable that similar additionsshould be made to the Scottish general grant. I can see an arguable case on meritsfor adjusting the formula which is designed to reflect an area&apos;s basic needs, soas to put more money into areas where the proportion of old people is high, asproposed in paragraph 7.1 could accept this, but it would have to apply in Scotlandtoo. I confess, however, I can see no logical basis for putting a floor under a localauthority&apos;s share of general grant, as proposed in paragraph 6. And if a floor,why not a ceiling? An adjustment of this kind seems to me entirely at variance with the principles on which general grant is distributed, while the relatively smallcost suggests that the political capital to be got out of it may be minimal, and the debate that would follow far from easy.5. The major Scottish difficulty however arises on the proposal for dealingwith individual ratepayers, in paragraphs 9 to 11 of the Minister^ paper. Theadoption of any scheme on these lines exposes us to the question why somethingsimilar was not done in Scotland before now. Something would certainly have tobe done in Scotland now. It could not use the same base year, but would have to go back to 1960-61, the last year before the Scottish revaluation. And as the comparison would therefore be between 1960-61 and 1964-65, the qualifyingincreases in burden would (because of the greater natural growth in expenditure over the longer period) have to be higher than in England.3225
Scottish Office, S.W.1,30th September, 1963.6. Local authorities in Scotland already have power to remit rates on grounds of poverty or inability to pay; and the very least we could do in Scotland, if theMinister^ proposals on this point are adopted, would be to institute a grant to scottish local authorities in respect of relief given under their existing powers,equivalent to the grant proposed in paragraph 10 for English authorities. Butanything that involves widespread new inquiries into means and I gather from^paragraph 11 of the Minister^ paper that he envisages detailed inquiries as wellas application of the qualifying increases in burden will be, I think, mostunpopular both with authorities and with ratepayers.7. To sum up, hardship cases in general are being considered by Allen. Thelong-term problem of a different division of burdens between local authorities andthe taxpayer is the main political issue at present. If we can make a suitableannouncement on this, I believe we should stand firm and offer no interim measureswhich will have undesirable repercussions apart from those in Scotland in debate on the Floor of the House.M. N.

</content>
</cab>
