<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/114/0 images: 326-327</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
confidential this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1963C. (63) 1761st October, 1963CABINETFUTURE POLICY FOR HORTICULTUREMemorandum by the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food at their meeting on 18th July, 1963, the Cabinet authorised me to continue discussions with representatives of the horticultural industry on the future policysuggested in my memorandum C. (63) 127 (CC. (63) 47th Conclusions, Minute 3).Annexed to that memorandum was a draft statement showing how this packagedeal might be publicly presented and incorporating the best terms on the tariffaspect to which I thought it possible that the Farmers&apos; Unions might be broughtto agree.2. Further discussions have now satisfied me that the leaders of the industry will welcome a new policy on these lines. They have confirmed their unqualifiedsupport for the positive measures in our proposals; these are the expansion ofthe Horticulture Improvement Scheme, credit guarantees, grant-aid for somewholesale markets, and the discipline of compulsory grading for selected fruitsand vegetables. In return, they are prepared to concede the room for manoeuvreon the horticultural tariff that we have been seeking. Duties on the less vulnerableproducts would become negotiable immediately. Those on vulnerable productscould be bound immediately at their present levels; and it would be open to theGovernment to consider reductions, if this were in the national interest, after a standstill period of no more than four years. We should have to recognise the need to protect growers against imports at unrealistically low prices arising fromsurpluses in other countries, but we should not be committed to any particular form of safeguard.3. I attach a revised draft statement in terms to which I would now expect the Unions to subscribe. The only significant changes from the earlier draft arereferences at the beginning to the general aim of our policy for horticulture, andat the end to periodic examination of developments within the industry. To both these the Unions attach much importance and I would regard both as entirelyacceptable.4. My feeling is that these proposals, taken as a whole, would be seen as a realistic and progressive measure designed to meet the needs of both the industryand the country. They will improve the competitive efficiency of the industry, andthey will enable the Government to get out of our present excessively rigid pledgeon the horticultural tariff and thus considerably improve our negotiating positionin international trade negotiations. I therefore invite my colleagues to authoriseme now to inform the leaders of the industry that we are ready to proceed, on theunderstanding that we have the firm support of the Unions. They will then haveto consult the full horticultural committees of their Unions, but I hope and expect that these will endorse the conclusions of their representatives with whom our discussions have been held. Following the previous conclusions of the Cabinet towhich I have referred, the drafting of the necessary legislation is already in hand.C. S.Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, S.W. 1,30th September, 1963.Copy No.633228
DRAFT STATEMENT ON HORTICULTURE       ;   - .      *1. It is the continuing policy of Her Majesty&apos;s Government, as it has been for many years, to promote the well-being of the horticultural industry, as it is for agriculture, lo this end the Government consider that all practical steps shouldfbe. taken to bring our horticultural production and marketing to a higher statejoljbompetitive efficiency; and they propose to offer substantial aid to the industryto reduce costs of production and improve marketing. The effect of this shouldbe to strengthen the competitive position of the industry and thereby to reduceits dependence on the tariff, which has been the principal means of support. Itshould thus create conditions in which reconsideration of the tariff would bepossible.2. The Governments proposals will include grants towards the cost of a wide range of production equipment (including replacement of glasshouses) for existing viable holdings, towards the reorganisation of such holdings, and towardsthe establishment of marketing co-operatives. Arrangements will also be madeto provide guaranteed credit facilities for horticultural producers.3. In addition to the grant-aid already available to growers and co-operativestowards equipment for the better marketing of horticultural produce, theGovernment will offer grants towards the cost of redevelopment of a numberof wholesale horticultural markets throughout the country. They will also seekpowers to require the grading to prescribed standards of certain horticulturalproduce passing through wholesale channels of trade.4. Details of all these measures will be worked out in consultation with theinterests concerned in order that legislation may be introduced as soon as possible.5. Introduction of these substantial forms of assistance will enable theGovernment to consider making changes in the tariff on horticultural items, where these would be in the national interest. The timing of any such changes would,however, be of great importance.6. Some products are in a favourable position to withstand competition fromimports because, for example, their perishability, or their bulk in relation to their value, afford a high degree of natural protection. For these, early reductions in import duties could be made without damage to the industry.7. Other products, however, are at present more sensitive to overseascompetition and enjoy a significant level of tariff protection during the homeseason. For these, the Government will feel free to bind the duties at their currentlevels if they consider this to be in the national interest. There will, however, haveto be a period of some four years before any reduction in the tariff on these sensitiveitems could be considered. This should give the industry time to benefit from theassistance offered, and thereby enable it the better to withstand any normalcompetition from imports. After this standstill period the Government will be free to make reductions in the duties on sensitive items if they consider this to be inthe national interest.8. The Government recognise that the specific duties on a number ofhorticultural products have not only offered protection against normal competition from imports, but have also been a safeguard against abnormal competition fromimports at unrealistically low prices arising from surpluses of varying degrees. Itis likely that such surpluses will reappear from time to time, so means to prevent them from undermining our market will continue to be necessary. The government consider that such means would best be devised in consultation with othercountries.9. In considering possible tariff reductions and safeguards against abnormalcompetition, the Government will, of course, take the views of the industry fully into account. It is also the Governments intention to have periodic examinations,in consultation with the Farmers&apos; Unions, of developments within the industry,including the evidence available on such matters as costs of production and thetrends in prices and imports, and the progress made towards achieving a higherdegree of competitive efficiency.

</content>
</cab>
