<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/114/0 images: 330-333</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1963C. (63) 1784th October, 1963Copy No.   62CABINETFRENCH NUCLEAR policy memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs as a result of our discussion on 24th September (C.C. (63) 57th Conclusions,Minute 2) I am circulating the attached memorandum on French Nuclear policy for the information of my colleagues.M. Habib Deloncle&apos;s speech on 24th September M. Habib Deloncle, French Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (i.e., second Minister at the Quai d&apos;Orsay), said in a speech to the consultative Assembly of the Council of Europe:&quot;Tomorrow, when Europe strengthens its political structure, it will be appropriate to define how the French [nuclear] effort can be used by theEuropean nations as a group for the common defence. The mere fact that france has committed herself to this course opens the possibility of revising,for the benefit of Europe, the balance of burdens and responsibilities withinthe Atlantic Alliance. I venture to add that if Great Britain conceives her future as being within the community of Europe, she can find in this fieldan opportunity for a real contribution, taking account of the necessary choiceswhich such a decision would entail.&quot;2. It is reasonable to suppose that if the French Government had intendedto put new and serious proposals to us, they would have done so privately throughthe diplomatic channel and not publicly in a speech by a junior Minister. that being so, we can only interpret what M. Habib Deloncle said in the light of what we already know about French nuclear policy. In this context M. Habib Deloncleseems to have suggested that(a) the   defence. of  Europe   should   be   organised   round   the   french force de frappe;(b) it would be open to the United Kingdom to associate herself with suchan arrangement;(c) The United Kingdom would have to choose between relations with Europe(i.e., in effect with France) and relations with the United States in the nuclear field.H.Foreign Office, S.W.1,3rd October, 1963.FRENCH NUCLEAR POLICY3249
French Motives &apos;.- &apos;   &apos;-    &apos;&apos;.&apos; 3, There was &quot;nothing new in M. Habib Deloncle&apos;s remarks. He said as muchto the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs immediatelyafter his speech. The French Prime Minister, Minister of Foreign Affairs and minister of Defence have made similar statements publicly and in private in thepast. French Ministers and officials during the last nine months have generallytaken the line that General de Gaulle was anxious for Franco-British co-operation in the nuclear field and United Kingdom participation in Europe provided thatthe force thus produced was equal in rights with United States forces and equallyindependent. When the French Ambassador called on me on 24th September,he made no reference to M. Habib Deloncle&apos;s speech; but he said that the UnitedKingdom and French nuclear forces could be in the Western alliance without being subject to a United States veto, and there might later be a single Europeandeterrent when Europe was organised politically.4. It is evident, however, that the French wanted M. Habib Deloncle&apos;remarks to attract attention. He laid considerable emphasis on them in his speech and the Press agencies at Strasbourg were well briefed beforehand. Her Majesty&apos;ambassador at Paris has heard from a reliable source that the original text of the speech was redrafted by M. Couve de Murville and that extensive amendments were made at the Elysee. He also understands that every effort will be made to exploit this theme in the coming weeks.5. This raises the question whether or not the speech was intended as aserious proposal. I feel sure that a serious proposal would have been put to usprivately at a high level rather than in a public speech by a junior Minister atStrasbourg. Moreover, a serious proposal would not only have to correspond to french interests but also to represent a real move towards an accommodation.It is hard to believe that General de Gaulle would welcome an arrangement wherebyFrance would admit the United Kingdom to a share in the control of the force defrappe, thus sharing the leadership of Europe with the United Kingdom. Therehas been no indication that he contemplated any form of integration of the Frenchand United Kingdom nuclear forces, nor the transformation of the force de frappeinto a collective &quot; European &quot; force in any real sense of the term. General de Gaullehas not given any hint that he would accept a United Kingdom or a European vetoon his use of the force de frappe. He has also avoided any implication that anarrangement such as M. Habib Deloncle mentions would be the key to UnitedKingdom entry into the European Communities. (M. Deloncle clearly refers to the&quot; community of Europe &quot; in a generalised sense rather than in the sense of theEuropean Economic Community). Any such implication would be a major reversal of French policy in Europe. If General de Gaulle had wanted to imply this, hewould certainly have put forward the idea himself. He must also realise that thearrangement mentioned by M. Habib Deloncle would involve a major reversal of United Kingdom policy, cutting the nuclear links between this country and theUnited States and breaking the indivisibility of the nuclear defence of the West,on which our policy has been based and to which we subscribed again at Nassau.Nor can he have expected that an arrangement involving Franco-British nuclearhegemony in Europe would appeal to his other European allies, particularly if itmeant abandoning the protection of the United States deterrent.6. It might just be possible to interpret M. Halib Deloncle&apos;s statement as meaning that France would contribute with us to a multinational European force.But his third sentence makes it clear that a condition of United Kingdom entry into such a force would be the severance of our nuclear ties with the United States.I do not think this is the right interpretation and, even if it was, that it would be acceptable to us or attractive to our allies.7. Thus: M. Halib Deloncle&apos;s statement was neither new nor a seriousproposal. It was probably designed to help justify the force de frappe as a future&quot; European &quot; force at a time when it is coming under serious attack both at homeand abroad. As regards the United Kingdom, it held up the possibility of a Europeanalternative to the NATO multilateral force at a crucial moment in the debate on whether Her MajestyV Government should or should not participate in thepreliminary discussions. General de -Gaulle may have reasoned that if the UnitedKingdom could be kept out of these discussions it might help to kill a project he particularly dislikes, upset United Kingdom relations with the United States andGermany in particular, and bring the United: Kingdom into the same sort ofisolation as France. On the other hand, a straight United Kingdom rejection of
. Habib Deloncle&apos;s proposal could be represented as justification for General de gaulle&apos;s\iv^e^,)tJiai-;!^vLT^it?!4 Kingdom would always choose the United Statesinstead, of Europe and was not therefore &quot;European enough &quot; to qualify for membership of the European Communities.reactions in&quot;Eurppe.,;: IV;;&quot;&apos;,,Germany.    -  .,,, ,    :   /;     ....... . i &quot; i      &apos; . , , &apos;8.. :Professor Carstens,(State Secretary at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs)told Her MajestyV. Embassy at Bonn that so far as he knew the French had made no approach to the Germans on this question. His interpretation of dr. Adenauer&apos;s statement that the proposal was &quot; very important and noteworthy &quot;was that he was trying to let the General down lightly. The creation of a multilateral force remained the Germans&apos; first objective, whatever the French ideas might turn out to be, although it was true that the Germans had never excluded thepossibility of a European defence system once the necessary political conditionshad been achieved (i.e., a European political organisation had been set up andthe appropriate relationship with the United States established). The German Pressgave M. Habib Deloncle&apos;s statement wide coverage but the tone both of reports and comment was sceptical. Only one paper suggested that General de gaulle had given the Chancellor prior notice of the proposal. He may have done so however,and the Chancellor^ remarks indicate a certain tentative interest on his part inthe idea of creating in the long run a nuclear force free from the United Statesveto. The Federal Government spokesman publicly stated on behalf of the federal government on 27th September: &quot; From the very beginning the federal government has supported this plan [i.e., the United States proposals for a multilateral force] and co-operated in its promotion. As early as 14th Januaryon the occasion of the visit of the United States Under-Secretary of State, Mr. Bali,the Federal Chancellor pledged to him his full support. There has been no changesince. The Federal Government is determined to continue to back these plans inco-operation with its allies. The fact that the Federal Chancellor called thepossibility of a European nuclear force, which was hinted at by the FrenchGovernment, &apos; worth studying and significant&apos;, is no contradiction to thiswhatsoever.&quot;Italy9. There has been no official reaction so far but the Italian Press has tended to assume United Kingdom rejection of the ideas in M. Habib Deloncle&apos;s statement.Netherlands10. The Ministry of Foreign Affairs were not inclined to take this as a seriousnegotiating proposal: they thought the timing was related to Her Majesty&apos;s government&apos;s decision on the multilateral force and to the increasing isolation inwhich the French were finding themselves on nuclear questions. There has been noPress reaction.Belgium11. The Belgian Press have given the matter iittle prominence and there hasbeen no comment.The United Kingdom Position12. Her Majesty&apos;s Governmenfs attitude must take account of purarrangements with the United States. These are governed by Article VII of theAgreement for Co-operation on the Use of Atomic Energy for Mutual defence purposes at July 1958 as amended in May 1959. This Agreement was made pursuant to the McMahon Act, as amended in our favour in 1958 and 1959. This provides thatwe may not communicate classified United States information, or transfer, or permitaccess to, or use of, materials or equipment made available under the agreement to any other Government unless either .. :\.v&apos;..-&apos;:. Y&apos;(i) we are notified by the United States that &quot; all appropriate provisions and requirements of their laws have been complied with &quot; and that theUnited States duly authorise us to transfer the information; or   .(ii) the United States inform us that they themselves have communicated:, this&apos;      - &apos; information, or permitted-access to such materials or equipment to thatGovernment. &apos;-&apos;       -&apos; :\* &quot;i       -
13. . Anglo-American nuclear know-how is so closely enmeshed that these provisions would in practice prevent us passing any information about sophisticatedweapon designs of a kind in which the French would be interested without UnitedStates consent. In present circumstances there is no prospect that either theUnited States Administration or Congress would be willing to give such consent,particularly if the information would assist the development of the French nationaldeterrent. The United States Administration have indicated that they might beprepared to consider helping a European deterrent within the Atlantic Alliance ifpolitical conditions changed so as to make unified political control possible. Butthis, with its implication of constraint on the use of national nuclear forces, is farfrom what General de Gaulle wants and is not necessarily compatible with thecontinuance of an independent United Kingdom nuclear arm.&apos;14. As a result of the arrangements made at the NATO Ministerial Meetingat Ottawa in May 1963 the United Kingdom V-bombers will be jointly targetedwith other strategic nuclear weapons assigned to NATO and co-ordinated throughliaison arrangements at Omaha with the United States Strategic Air Command.General de Gaulle has indicated in the past that he would be prepared toco-ordinate the French force de frappe within the Atlantic Alliance. Theoreticallyit would be possible for the French nuclear force when it comes into existence andour own deterrent to be targeted on a separate joint plan. This would however be something that we should have to look at again when the French force de frappeexists, in the light of the circumstances at the time. It would be important to avoiddoing anything from which mistaken conclusions as to our European policy mightbe drawn by our allies.15. There is no evidence that the other European countries, and Germany inparticular, would wish to see a European nuclear defence organisation in whichthe United States were not closely involved. The German desire for the UnitedStates eventually to suspend its veto over the use of the proposed multilateral force is not the same thing as wanting an entirely separate European deterrent. Indeedtheir main objectives are to bring greater influence to bear on United States nuclearpolicy, and to bind the United States into the European defence system. TheGermans are anyway fully committed to the multilateral force.16. Any development of a purely European deterrent on an Anglo-Frenchbasis would bring into question the United States commitment to the defence ofEurope. Mr. Rusk told me on 28th June, and has repeated more than once, that,if Europe was to be independent, the United States would be independent too. he does not intend to allow 5 per cent of the deterrent to trigger the other 95 per cent.In this context, it is significant that the State Department do not regardM. Habib Deloncle&apos;s remarks as a serious proposal.17. Our own position was stated by the Lord Privy Seal in his speech to theCouncil of Western European Union on 10th April, 1962, when he said &quot; Wequite accept that a European point of view on defence will emerge. What isessential, however, is that any European point of view or policy on defence shouldbe directly related to the Atlantic Alliance.&quot;Conclusions18. My conclusions are that we should take M. Habib Deloncle&apos;s speechas a propaganda move designed partly to improve the image of the force de frappeat home and abroad, partly to take advantage of the differences of opinion aboutthe multilateral force and partly to enable the French to accuse us of being &quot; notEuropean enough &quot; in General de Gaulle&apos;s sense of the term. If General de Gaullehas a serious proposition to put to us, he will no doubt do so through the rightchannels. In the meantime I suggest that for the time being we should avoid any public indication of interest in M. Habib Deloncle&apos;s speech. Nor should we publiclyreject it. Either course would play into French hands. We should merely leave it to the French to make any further moves.19. The French Foreign Minister has expressed a wish for a private talk with the Lord Privy Seal at the time of the W.E.U. Ministerial meeting atThe Hague on 25th and 26th October. This would offer an opportunity forM. Couve de Murville to raise this question and obtain our reactions if he wants to do so.

</content>
</cab>
