<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/159/11 images: 189-195</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(71) 11113 October, 1971CABINETTHE queen&apos;S SPEECH ON THE prorogation of parliament note by the Lord President of the council I circulate, for the consideration of the Cabinet, a draft ofThe queen s Speech on the Prorogation of Parliament.W. W.Privy Council Office12 October 1971COPY NO 0 $
THE queen S SPEECH ON THE PROROGATION OF parliament my LORDS AND MEMBERS OP THE HOUSE OP commons.    My husband and I, and The Princess Anne, recall with pleasure ourvisit to British Columbia on the occasion of the centenary of thatProvince1s joining the Federation of Canada.    V/e also had the pleasureof visiting Turkey this month and of welcoming to this countryTheir Imperial Majesties the Ersperor and Empress of Japan.2.    My Government have virtually completed negotiations for british membership of the European Communities and are confident that the outstanding issues can be satisfactorily settled in the near future.3.    My Government welcome as Commonwealth partners, Tonga, WesternSamoa and Fiji.4.    My Ministers have contributed fully to the work of the North atlantic alliance, and have sought to improve relations between East and West.     Theywelcome the progress which has been made towards more normal relationswith the Peoplers Republic of China.5.     The decision has been taken to retain certain British forces in SouthEast Asia as part of Five Power Defence arrangements relating to malaysia and Singapore.6.    My Government welcome the establishment of a new relationship with theStates of Bahrain and Qatar and the progress made towards establishing theUnited Arab Emirates.7.    My Government played an active part in cyclone relief work in EastPakistan.     They have since contributed generously to international reliefmeasures for refugees in India and to the United Nations1 relief efforts in East Pakistan.8.    My Government have played an active role in the internationaldisarmament negotiations.     They have signed the Seabed Arms Control treaty and welcome the agreement reached in the Conference of the Committee on disarmament on a draft convention banning biological weapons.1
9.     My Ministers have been actively seeking to find an acceptable basis for the negotiation of a just settlement of the rhodesian problem inaccordance with the Five Principles.10.   Measures have been announced to encourage British private investment in developing countries and the necessary steps taken to enableMy Government to continue to play their full part in the work of theInternational Development Association.11.   My Ministers have begun discussions with representative groups inNorthern Ireland to seek agreed ways and means within the constitutional and democratic framework of giving the minority as well as the majoritycommunity an active, permanent and guaranteed role in the life and public affairs of the Province.     I take a special pride in the skill,perseverance and restraint with which my Armed Forces are carrying out their onerous tasks.MEMBERS OP THE HOUSE OP COMMONS12.   I thank you for the provision which you have made for the public services.Iff LOKDS AND MEMBERS OP THE HOUSE OP COMMONS13.   A substantial surplus has been maintained on the current account ofthe balance of payments;   confidence in sterling has remained high;   therehave been substantial increases in the official reserves since June 1970 and 1,04-6 million of short and medium term official overseas debt has beenrepaid,14-.   My Government have taken an active part in discussions to resolveproblems of the international monetary system.2
15.   The burden of taxation has been significantly reduced, and provision has been made for a major reform of the structure of personal direct taxation.     A simplified and improved system of tax allowances has been introduced for capital expenditure on plant and machinery with special treatment for the development areas.     These are the first stages of afar-reaching programme to reform the tax system.16.   A major reorganisation of the structure of Central Government has beencarried through.     Special attention has been paid to improving the effectiveness of Departments and other public bodies.    A defence procurement Executive has been e 3tablished to unify defence research,development and procurement activities.     Acts have been passed to establish a Civil Aviation Authority and a British Airways Board and to transfer theUnited Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority&apos;s nuclear fuel and radio-chemicalproduction business to companies set up under the Companies Acts,17.   Provision has been made for further assistance to the coal industryand for a fresh look at the National Coal Board&apos;s non-colliery activities.18.   Steps have been taken to encourage effective competition in theinterests of the consumer and of industrial efficiency.    A far-reachingreform of credit control techniques has been introduced.19.   My Government have established Rolls-Royce (1971) Limited to continueessential activities of Rolls-Royce Limited and, in parallel with theUnited States Governments support for the Lockheed TriStar Aircraft, areassisting the new company to produce the RB211 engine for that aircraft.20.   Legislation has been passed to raise the limit on guarantees under the shipbuilding Credit Scheme.     Special attention has been given to helping the development and intermediate areas.     Further expenditure has been authorised to improve economic and social opportunities in these areas and provision has been made for higher grants to be paid to assist theimprovement during the next 2 years of older houses and their surroundings.3Si K (TIBET
21.   Action has been taken to encourage the expansion of agriculture and changes have been made in support arrangements to strengthen the market for agricultural products and to limit the commitment of public funds.22.   An Act has been passed to reform and modernise the system of industrial relations.     Urgent steps have been taken to improve facilities for industrial retraining and to increase the number under training.23,   My G-overnment have taken active steps to improve the quality of the environment in our towns and countryside and on the coast.2k.,   Acts have been passed to protect our shores from oil pollution and tomake it easier for victims of pollution to claim compensation.25.   Plans have been announced for a primary trunk road network built to high standards and achieving substantial environmental improvements.26.   The decision has been taken to build a third London Airport at Foulness.27.   An Act has been passed to strengthen the law relating to fireprecautions in residential establishments and places of amusement andpublic resort.28.   Legislation has been passed to abolish State management for the sale and supply of intoxicating liquor in Carlisle and certain districts ofScotland.29.   The law on the misuse of drugs has been strengthened.30.   My Ministers have made important improvements in the system of social security, giving priority to those most in need.     They have provided pensions for those over 80 and for younger widows, a new attendance allowance for thevery severely disabled and better benefits for the chronically sick and their families.     Legislation has been passed to introduce family income supplementsfor poor families with children and to remove obsolete provisions from thesocial security system and prevent its exploitation.4
31.   Substantial increases in national insurance retirement pensions and related benefits took effect in September 1971.    At the same time the occupational pensions of retired members of the public services and armed forces and their dependants were increased under new arrangements designedto maintain purchasing power.32.   Acts were passed concerning the supply of free school milk and theeducation of mentally handicapped children previously considered unsuitable for education in school.     A very substantial primary school improvementprogramme has been launched.33.   The recommendations for redistribution of seats made by the boundary commissions for England, Scotland, Y/ales and Northern Ireland in their reports in ^S&amp;S have been implemented without modification.34-.   An Act has been passed to extend the field from which candidates for election to local authorities may be chosen.35.   Legislation has been passed providing for a unified system of immigration control.36.   Acts have been passed to implement the recommendations of the RoyalCommission on Assizes and Quarter Sessions and to improve the organisationof the sheriff court system in Scotland.37. Further progress has been made in the systematic reform of the lawand in the consolidation of enactments and repeal of obsolete statutes.MI LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS38.   I pray that the Blessing of Almighty God may attend you.5SECRET


</content>
</cab>
