<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/57/47 images: 384-391</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   November 1944.The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It Is issued for the personal use Bf r^4^r^.^^&apos;iA^7f..................tTOP SECRET V Copy No. *W.P. (44) 647.14th November, 1944.WAR CABINET.ETHIOPIA.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.1. Lord De La Warr&apos;s negotiations with the Ethiopian Government arenearly at a deadlock over the Reserved Areas and the Ogaden. His instructions are to insist on the retention of these areas under our administration, possibly by leases, pending the peace settlement when we hope to obtain permanent posses-sion of the Reserved Areas at least. Meanwhile we are ready to recognise thetechnical sovereignty of the Emperor.2. Before the week-end the Ethiopian attitude had been that it was only with difficulty that the Emperor in 1942 had justified to his Rases and Notablesthe fact that we were to continue to administer the territories in question on military grounds for the two years of the Agreement, and that it was impossiblefor him to agree to an extension. The Ethiopian Government appeared even to have adopted a suggestion put forward by their American Adviser that thefuture of the Ogaden should be referred to the arbitration of the United StatesGovernment.3. At the week-end, however, the Emperor, faced with the prospect of theDe La Warr&apos;s Miss-ion returning home, made the following proposals- see addis ababa telegrams Nos. 649 and 651 annexed to this paper : (a) Great Britain to retain administration over the Ogaden. (It is not clear whether this is to be for the duration of the new Agreement or pendingthe peace settlement.)(6) Ethiopia to recover all the Reserved Areas. But, in order to meet ouranxieties as regards treatment of the British Somali tribes who enjoygrazing rights there, the Emperor offers (1) to. appoint as Governorone of his best younger men who will be responsible directly to theMinistry of the Interior in Addis Ababa; (2) to accredit to him aBritish adviser (it is not clear whether this adviser would enjoyonly advisory or executive powers); and (3) to move in military and police detachments which would be under the command of british officers.4. Meanwhile Lord De La Warr has suggested moving to meet the Emperorby offering that while we retain administration of the territories, we would agreeto the British Administrator being the joint appointment of the Emperor and ourselves, and that his proclamations and similar announcements should beworded so as to make clear that his powers were delegated to him by the Emperor see paragraph 7 (a) and (b) of Addis telegram No. 649.5.   The gap between ourselves and the Ethiopian Government would in suchcase be narrower.   Each party is perhaps moved by the belief that at the peace settlement administration will prove to be nine points of the law.    But the12569   [28604] b
Ethiopians are in fact offering us a further temporary control over the Ogaden(where they have reason to believe that the Americans will eventually support their claim) in return for recovering- the Reserved Areas where there is less certainty of american support. Also the Emperor says frankly that only the recovery now ofthe Reserved Areas would enable him to justify to his Rases his leaving to us fora further period the Ogaden which legally reverts to Ethiopia on the expiry of the1942 Agreement, i.e., this Christmas. It would have suited us better if theEmperor had made his- offer the other way round : viz., if he had insisted onrecovering control of the Ogaden (apart from the Haud) and agreed to ouradministering the Reserved Areas until the peace settlement.6. It is for the Cabinet to decide whether we should be justified in breakingwith the Ethiopians over the difference that now divides us. Whether or notthis resulted in a successful appeal by the Ethiopian Government to tJheAmericans for help, a breakdown would presumably mean the recall of our military Mission and the cutting off of further financial help; and we shouldhave to decide between remaining in the territories in question on no legal basis,or clearing out of them. I feel that a breakdown in such conditions would bebad for us, and my own advice to the Cabinet is that we should recognise thatthe Emperor&apos;s offer, more particularly on account of the measure of British influence that it would admit into the Reserved Areas, goes a considerable way tomeet our principal apprehension, that of the security of our tribes; that he hasshown good sense in shelving the idea of American arbitration for the Ogaden,and that we should accept his offer subject to certain conditions : First, weshould press that the British official attached to the Ethiopian Governor should enjoy executive powers as apparently suggested by the Emperor in his conver-satioii with Lord De La Warr, but not in his subsequent memorandum. Secondly,Lord De La Warr should make sure that the military detachments in the areas aretroops of the regular Ethiopian army commanded by British officers and includingother British officers and N.C.O.S. (The police are in any case under a BritishCommissioner.) Thirdly, we should have to make it clear that the arrangement for the Reserved Areas was without prejudice to reconsideration of the question at the peace settlement, and that His Majesty&apos;s Government could not endorseany assurance concerning the future of the Ogaden that the Emperor might give his people. Apart from the above, Lord De La Warr would have to make clearour position on certain other points connected with the Military Mission, and railway and finance.7. I recognise that the administrative arrangement contemplated, by which an Ethiopian Governor and British Adviser would share control of the ReservedAreas is not ideal and might prove difficult in practice. But it seems reasonable to suppose that the Ethiopian authorities, knowing the question of final owner-ship would be raised at the peace settlement, would be on their best behaviour.On the other hand, if they behaved badly, this would strengthen the case forseparating those Areas from Ethiopia, and possibly including them in the GreaterSomalia, which is one solution proposed for the territories in this corner of africa.8. It is, however, necessary to draw attention to Lord De La Warr&apos;s ownadvice, based of course on his existing instructions to which he has adhered veryfaithfully, that we should continue to insist on administrative control over bothOgaden and Reserved Areas, but coating the pill, as proposed in paragraph above. I believe myself that the Emperor might very easily elect to break ratherthan give way to us over the Reserved Areas as well as over the Ogaden. It maywell be that adherence to the law will prove even more advantageous to us at thepeace settlement than the nine points of it derived from administration; and Ibelieve that relations with Ethiopia will be less difficult in the coming years ifwe now accept in a good spirit the Emperor&apos;s week-end offer subject to theconditions already enumerated. I hope, therefore, that my colleagues willauthorise me to telegraph to Lord De La Warr in this sense.A. E.Foreign Office,14:th November, 1944.
&apos;&quot; ANNEX.Mr. Howe to Mr. Eden. (Received 10th November.)(No. 649.   Secret.)(Telegraphic.) Addis Ababa, 10th November, 1944.RW. 73. &apos;DURING the last two days I have had a long private and extremely franktalk with the Minister of the Pen followed by an almost equally long talk withthe Emperor. The atmosphere- is changed from that existing at the time of receipt of Ethiopian memorandum described in my telegram D.W. 65 but I am afraid you must get used to these changes as progress in this country is neversteady and is usually achieved by an explosion after a period of interminabledelay. It is not necessary to bother you with an account of the discussions as no new arguments were produced on either side.2. I informed them of your views and of the fact that your finalinstructions represented your minimum demands. In order that they shouldhave our possible concessions in their minds in a comprehensive form I put them down on a sheet of paper as follows : *&quot; In the event of Your Imperial Majesty agreeing to the principle of continued British occupation of reserved areas and Ogaden, I should beprepared to agree to the following proposals from Your Majesty &quot; (1) That we should include in the agreement the words alreadysubmitted by me to Your Imperial Majesty at out last meeting, viz. : &apos;&apos; &apos; During any negotiations which may take place at the peace settlement with regard to this part of Africa, such negotiations shall be conducted on basis that Ethiopian sovereignty over reserved areas and Ogaden are fully recognised by His Majesty&apos;s Government.&apos;&quot; (2) That the Ethiopian flag should continue to be flown in. reservedareas on Ethiopian buildings, e.g., Post Office, Customs, &amp;c, in Jigjigaand elsewhere to be mutually agreed.&apos;&apos; (3) In addition, I have further examined the question of assuringYour Imperial Majesty&apos;s sovereignty over areas concerned and suggest thatthe following draft might be considered preferable by Your imperial majesty to our original proposal for a lease.&quot; (4) Without prejudice to his underlying sovereignty His imperial majesty hereby delegates to the Government of the United Kingdom forthe period of the duration of this agreement all legislative, judicial, fiscaland other powers and functions of the Government in respect of territorydescribed in the schedule to the agreement and of all persons therein.&apos;&apos; (4) That in addition to British evacuation of railway and Dire Dawa,subject to certain conditions already mentioned, the British should evacuatethat portion of reserved areas lying north-west of the railway.&quot;I also gave them two additional minor points as follows : &quot; (5) Ethiopia to have full right of passage over the road passing  -through Jigjiga from Harrar to Gojjiar and also over the road east of therailway leading from Dire Dawa to Aisha.&quot; I think that it may be possible that  Your Majesty might feel that itwould be useful at some later stage after the conclusion of this agreement to discuss further matters with my Government and for this purpose you may desire to visit the United Kingdom. If this should be Your Majesty&apos;desire I would undertake to convey &quot;your wishes to my Government on myreturn and I feel sure that Your Majesty will be most cordially welcomed.&quot;I did this because I was satisfied that these were of much greater importanceto them than they might seem&apos;to us and felt that in view of crucial point of -negotiations at which we had arrived I must take that responsibility.3. Paragraph (5) about rights of way is really a very trivial matter butI trust that I have not embarrassed you by what I have said about the Emperor&apos;visit. The previous refusal, however, is rankling hard with him and you will see that my words do not commit you.4.   The Emperor replied by putting forward a proposal that had beenhinted at by Wolde Giorgis at my interview with him.   It was as follows : That[28604? &quot; b 2
he should pick out one of his best young men and appoint him as Governor of reserved areas. He should have British advisers with full executive powers.The Emperor should guarantee security by stationing units of his regular armyand police both under British officers. This arrangement to apply only toreserved areas, the Ogaden not really presenting any great difficulties.5. - With your last instructions in mind I said I was very sure that you would not be prepared to agree and endeavoured to dissuade him from pressingme to communicate it back to you. I said that, in my own view, if this had beena long-term agreement his proposal might have been worth considering but that. agreement such as we envisaged might very well be nearly over before the arrange-ments he suggested could be put into effect. In the meantime, in view of hispressing me no less than three times to telegraph this back to you I do not feelthat I could refuse to do so.6. My own view after a very full discussion with the Minister and Emperoris that whilst totally contrary to our intentions and instructions, this offer isone that is difficult to turn down without revealing our intentions concerning thefuture to a greater extent than I imagine you wish to do, but it is, in fact, a bidto prejudge the future by immediate re-establishment of an Ethiopian administra-tion. It definitely, however, professes to meet all arguments, i.e., grazing,security, our desire not to have to send more troops for maintenance of peacealong the frontier, &amp;c. The only easy argument against it of which I can thinkis the one that I put to the Emperor (see paragraph 5 above).7. If, however, as I assume, you turn it down, there are points of possibleextended interpretation of your words used in your telegram No. 382, &quot; by agree-ment with the Emperor &quot; on which I would appreciate your views. These are that: (a) Ail proclamations, decrees, &amp;c, in reserved areas, not (repeat not) Ogaden,should make a direct reference to His Imperial Majesty as on theiollowing lines : &quot; In exercise of administrative powers delegatedby His Imperial Majesty the Emperor of Ethiopia to british authorities in reserved areas and administered territory herebyannounces (decrees), &amp;c.&quot;(b) British administrator of reserved areas not (repeat not) Ogaden shouldbe appointed jointly by His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Emperor.This would follow last sentence of proposed draft in (3) of my proposals to the Emperor, on drafting of which I should alsoappreciate your views.8. It is desirable that I should know your views with regard to these pointswhen I see the Emperor on Monday,- or at the latest Tuesday, and inform him of the same.Mr. Howe to Mr. Eden. [Received 11th November.)&apos;   (No. 651.   Secret.)(Telegraphic.) Addis Ababa, November 11, 1944.DW. 74.MY immediately preceding telegram.I send you verbatim copy, just received, of Emperor&apos;s note of our interview,which I agree is a correct record of what he said, with the exception that heomits any reference to executive powers of British adviser : i-&quot; In the course of audience granted on 9th November, 1944, by His imperial majesty to His Lordship Earl De La Warr, His Imperial Majesty stated that itwas the firm desire of the Imperial Ethiopian Government to strengthen friendly relations which have always existed between the two Governments, andparticularly at this time to conclude an agreement which might achieve the objectives. Unfortunately, however, although the two delegations have reached agreement on all other matters, the problem of reserved areas and Ogadenthreatens to upset the course of negotiations towards that goal so ardently desired.&quot;2. It is clear, that in order to be able to persuade others of the necessityof a certain course of action, it is essential to have gained for oneself a personalconviction of that necessity. As sovereign head of the Empire of Ethiopia, itis difficult for His Imperial Majesty, in the absence of a personal conviction
of such necessity, to convince the Ethiopian people of the need for transferringreserved areas.&quot; 3. His Imperial Majesty has accepted the principle of transfer of Ogadento British military administration, but with the lifting of the blockade of Jibutiall reasons advanced in 1942 for retention of reserved areas have now disappeared.&quot;4. His Imperial Majesty does not feel that any necessity now exists for retaining reserved areas under British military administration. If, however,His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom still entertain doubts inregard to administration of those areas, His Imperial Majesty is fully preparedto afford all necessary safeguards in order to remove any possible misgivings inthat respect. Specifically, His Imperial Majesty would propose in that case(1) to appoint a capable and outstanding governor for these areas, to be assisted by a British adviser; (2) that a detachment of the Ethiopian Army be sentthere for the purpose of assuring security; (3) as in the case of Borana, thata detachment of regular police be stationed there; and finally (4) that adminis-tration of those territories depend directly on Ministry of Interior instead ofindirectly through provinces. His Imperial Majesty is convinced that such measures would afford all necessary assurances to His Majesty&apos;s Government inthe United Kingdom.. &quot;5. At the time of negotiation of agreement 1942, His Imperial Majestycarefully explained to ruling dignitaries, both civil and ecclesiastical governors and similar officials and leaders, and to the entire nation that territories com-prising Ogaden and reserved areas had been transferred to British military administration for necessities of the war and only for duration of military agreement of 1942 and that with termination of that agreement those territories would thereupon return to Ethiopian administration.&quot; 6. When these same questions were again brought forward during courseof present negotiations, and especially since the last audience granted to HisLordship, His Imperial Majesty has again consulted all the highest officials of the Empire as well as the local International Labour Office and leaders inregard to propositions formulated with reference to areas under consideration.His Imperial Majesty assures His Lordship that all without exception demandreturn of these territories as promised in 1942.&quot;7. In course of the last audience, His Lordship manifested a desire to guarantee, by written declaration, recognition of His Imperial Majesty&apos;ssovereignty over these territories and on his part His Imperial Majestyhas stated frankly his determined desire that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin United Kingdom might find it possible by concrete proposals and actions to foster the confidence of the Ethiopian people in His Majesty&apos;s Government inUnited Kingdom.&quot; 8. Although His Imperial Majesty has taken the difficult decision of agreeing to the transfer of Ogaden to British military administration, it would nevertheless be possible to explain and justify this [gp. undee. : ? sacrifice&quot;if it could be shown to the nation that the transfer was temporary. only anc.was necessitated by exigencies of the present war. Return of reserved areas to Ethiopian administration would afford him the possibility of making suchan explanation and demonstration.&quot; 9. The importance of returning reserved areas to Ethiopian administra-tion is therefore that such a gesture would confirm that which His imperial majesty had promised to his people in 1942, i.e., prove to the Ethiopian nationthe temporary character of the transfer now called for -in regard to Ogaden.&quot; 10. Return of reserved areas thus becomes a vital and essential condition for obtaining support of the nation to transfer of Ogaden.&quot; 11. His Imperial Majesty therefore requests His Lordship and HisMajesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom to seek to comprehend the situation as explained and to consider in that light the return of reserved areas. AllEthiopia anxiously awaits the outcome of these negotiations.&quot;




</content>
</cab>
