<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/22/17 images: 134-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.W.P. (42) 87. 1February 18, 1942. ^TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.THE INDIAN POLITICAL SITUATION.Note by the Secretary.THE attached telegrams are circulated by direction of the Prime Minister.(Signed) E. E. BRIDGES.Great George Street, S.W. 1.February 18, 1942.Copy of Telegram from Secretary of State for India to Viceroy, dated february 13, 1942.3--U.The Prime Minister feels strongly that draft reply to Sapru manifesto,in which you concurred, will be regarded not only in India but elsewhereas merely argumentative and negative in substance and as pushing back onIndians responsibility for making next move in order to cover our own incapacityto give any clear lead. He therefore has now decided upon entirely novel methodof in effect answering Sapru&apos;s letter by broadcast appeal to India in near future,of which following paragraphs give preliminary outline. The detailed applica1-tion of his proposal will require a good deal of working out, and on this youradvice and help will be invaluable, as well as your personal impression of thescheme as a whole.2. The general line of his broadcast (I am not, of course, attempting to givethe wording) will be to this effect: -(1) India is in grave danger. All must unite and co-operate wholeheartedlyto save her. For this purpose we must all leave aside our controversies and makeeach our contribution to the present and to the future.(2) This is no time to make profound changes in the Executive government or hamper the authorities who are carrying on the war.(3) My appeal to you is that India&apos;s best and most representative men from every community, party and province, as well as the Princes to whom we arejoined by Treaties, should now come forward to serve India in her hour of needand to lay the foundations for a new future. The basis of that future must beIndia&apos;s complete freedom to control her own destiny, continuing, as I both hopeand believe she will, within the fellowship of the British Commonwealth.[23476] copy No.Printed for the War Cabinet.  February 1942.
(4) As our own contribution I make the following proposals to the Peopleof India and I ask them as their contribution to come forward and make a successof them by their co-operation with us and with each other.(5) For this purpose I invite you to come together in a representative IndianCouncil of Defence to be elected, so far as British India is concerned, by theexisting members of the Lower Houses of the Provincial Legislatures in such manner as to enable every community to secure the same proportion in the Councilof Defence as in the electing body. I suggest that the total number for british india might be about 100, to whom would be joined, as in the existing nominatedNational Defence Council, the due proportion of representatives of the States.(6) The main duty of this Council, during the war, would be to serve india by consultation with the Government on the progress of the war and to help thewar effort throughout India in the raising of men, the production of munitions,the organising of Air Raid Precautions and the steadying of the population incase of raids or invasion.(7) Its further duty will be to nominate for inclusion in the Viceroy&apos; executive Council the representative of the People of India, who is to attend the meetings of the British War Cabinet and of the Pacific War Council.(8) At the end of the war it will similarly be its duty to nominate the repre-sentative or representatives of India at the Peace Conference.(9) After the war its duty will be to set to work without delay to hammerout India&apos;s future constitution.(10) As in the case of every other constitution-framing body, the mainoperative decisions on this matter will naturally have to be, in their nature andin the processes by which they are formulated, an expression of the desire of thepeople of India as a whole to adopt the proposals so framed. The procedure bywhich effect is to be given to this principle will be discussed with the Council assoon as practicable. I, on behalf of the British Government, now declare that we&apos; undertake to accept in advance a constitution so arrived at.(11) The Council will also be empowered to negotiate with the BritishGovernment with regard to the conditions, and the method by which the existing and continuing obligations of the British Government can best be fulfilled.3. For some further explanatory notes on points of detail, see my immediately succeeding telegram.Copy of telegram from Secretary of State to Viceroy,dated February 13, 1942.4-U.My immediately preceding telegram. For composition of British Indianportion of Defence of India Council the scheme sketched in this para-graph seems to us the simplest and most likely to appeal as based ultimately onpopular election. It will clearly require a great deal of detailed examination,and we should be most grateful for your observations and suggestions.Provincial Lower Houses should constitute a single constituency for electing,say, 100 representatives of British India to the Defence of India Council (which,of&quot; course, will take place of existing National Defence Council), in such afashion as to secure representation in it of the different communities and other elements in the various Provincial Legislatures in the same proportions as theyare found in this electing body. Method of election would no doubt be propor-tional representation. Candidates would be drawn either from members of the legislatures or persons qualified to become members, and would have each to be nominated by a member of a Provincial Legislature.2. An alternative method of composing the British Indian element whichhas been suggested would be by elections as follows : each Provincial lower house, acting separately, would elect a quota of persons in accordance withparagraphs 19, 21 and 22 of Schedule I of Act of 1935, the size of the quota beingapproximately 2/5ths of the component elements of the Federal Assembly, as laiddown in Schedule I of the Government of India Act, 1935, giving a total ofapproximately 100-110, allowing some latitude for the elimination of fractions.
To make good omissions either of eminent individuals or communities that wouldbe excluded from representation by election, Council when constituted might havepower to co-opt another 10, subject to the original communal balance not beingdisturbed.3. Indian States should be represented in the same proportion to theBritish Indian total as on the present National Defence Council (and as now bynomination by the Crown representative).4. As regards persons nominated to represent India in War Cabinet and peace Conference, they must, since they are charged with duty of helping informulation of policy, be responsible to, and therefore formally appointed by, theexisting Executive authority in India. The Princes would presumably resist any suggestion that British Indians should have a voice in nominating their repre-sentative, and British Indian element correspondingly would object to Princelymembers of Council having a say in nomination of British Indian representatives.In any case, neither element in the projected Council, which has no statutory basis, will have any executive authority, and it seems to us that the correctprocedure would be for the British Indian element to recommend to the Governor-General in Council a person for appointment to his Council for the purpose ofbeing the Government of India&apos;s representative, it being understood that theGovernor-General in Council would accept Defence CounciVs recommendation.It is suggested similarly that the Princely element would recommend a nomineeto the Crown Representative who would accept the recommendation and appointhim. The Governor-General in Council could, we think, hardly appoint ;aPrincely representative responsible to him in Council as proposed in paragraph 2of your 285S in the light of Sections 3 and 313 (5) of the Act, but might adopt aResolution that the Princely representative nominated by the Crown Repre-sentative should be associated with the British Indian representative.5. As regards constitution-making function at the end of the war, guiding principle is as stated in paragraph 10 of my preceding telegram. Of course, ifJinnah and the Princes are not to denounce this scheme from the outset, it willbe essential to make it clear that His Majesty&apos;s Government stands by the 1940pledge to minorities. On the other hand, it is desired to avoid antagonisingCongress unnecessarily by creating impression that Jinnah and the Princes areto be given an unlimited veto. Language of paragraph 10 of preceding telegramhas been worded with special regard to this danger.6. It is recognised that this considerable enlargement of the presentNational Defence Council, particularly if it has to meet more frequently or forlonger sessions than the present one, would entail a very considerably increasedburden for yourself, so much so as perhaps to involve question of a deputyPresident of it.  But this is only one of many details to be examined later.7. The Prime Minister is most anxious to have your reactions to the plan as soon as possible. While I had myself previously advised the Cabinet that therewas nothing that could be done for the moment beyond strengthening the authority and prestige of your existing Executive and National Defence Councils, I amgreatly attracted by proposal, which makes no immediate change in theconstitutional position but gives you a popularly-elected Defence Council and simultaneously affords an instrument for the eventual solution of the constitutional problem on lines which Congress cannot denounce as undemocratic and whichcan be commended to Muslims and Princes as maintaining our 1940 pledges.The imaginative boldness of the scheme and the Prime Minister &apos;s personalitymight together succeed in putting the plan across, even with Congress and the muslim League, at a time when danger to India herself is so obvious. If it does,you will be able to carry on with your Executive Council expanded as you have proposed and with a larger, and we hope better, consultative body, which, whileperhaps more openly critical than the existing National Defence Council, might also be more effective in promoting the Indian war effort throughout the Provinces.If, on the other hand, the appeal fails, and if the offer is rejected, the publichere, in America, in China and in a large measure even in India, will realiseat last that the real difficulty lies in the unreasonableness of Indian politicians andthe incompatibility of their respective domestic policies.[23476]
Copy of Telegram from Viceroy to Secretary of State for India, dated february 13, 1942.302 S.My immediately preceding telegram.* Following are some interim comments on the merits of the Prime Ministers scheme. I have not yet receivedthe promised statement of the details, but I cannot imagine that these couldrender much more acceptable a plan to which I see so many powerful objectionsof principle. As I understand it, the plan involves the creation of an enlargedDefence Council, in which different parties, communities and areas would berepresented in proportions determined by ourselves and by persons who would inform be nominated by me, even though many would be in practice selected by their political parties. This body would not only be entrusted with continuouslyadvising me, the Commander-in-Chief and my Executive Council as a whole on defence matters, but would supersede my Council as authority for selection ofIndia&apos;s representatives at the War Council and at the Peace Conference (and presumably other Imperial or International meetings), and would, moreover, bethe body which is to frame a new Constitution after the war.2. I would anticipate (? that) such proposal would be rejected out of handby the principal Indian parties on various and sometimes conflicting grounds, asa flagrant breach of pledges, and as an attempt to hand over both the present andfuture power to a nominated body with neither constitutional nor popular sanctionbehind it.Although my own case against the proposed body is largely based on assump-tion that it would achieve real power, the Congress could and would abuse it as a mere facade. Even taking it for what it was worth, they would insist upon itsreflecting their own numerical superiority whereas I would expect the Moslemsto refuse to serve on any body in which they would be an ineffective minority.; 3. If, however, the proposed Council were ever to come into being therewould ensue the following grave results : (a) Strong resentment would naturally be felt by many members of the presentNational Defence Council. They deserve a better reward than to be thrown overin favour of a Council which must be constituted with an eye as much upon theconstitutional views of its members as upon their capacity to contribute to theconduct of defence. Apart from this warping of its composition, such a body would never be content to sit occasionally and to conduct business by way ofcommenting upon official [ ? material] laid before it, but would certainly insist upon more or less continuous sessions and upon rules of business which wouldvirtually stamp it as a parallel Executive cum Legislature. No Viceroy could possibly undertake the Chairmanship of such a body, compatibly with all his original duties, whereas his Chairmanship of N.D.C. sitting for three days every two months has been the key to its utility as a link between Government andpublic opinion, and to our ability to bring representatives of British India andPrinces round a table. I very much doubt the willingness of the latter to join a body representative of the British Indian Political parties as such, more especially when they would be implicitly accepting its authority to draft a Constitution forAll India after the war.(b) The bitter communal rivalries which are inseparable from the constitu-tional problem would be imported entire into the conduct of the war, since it is topmuch to hope that such a Council would think with one mind about present andwith another about future.(c) Since Indian public opinion, speaking generally, is more concerned aboutcommunal aspects of the future Constitution than about anything else, the new body would be bound to gain popular prestige at expense of my Council. I would expect the latter either to come into dangerous conflict with (? new) body or tobecome subservient to it and to be distracted by political and communal factionfrom proper conduct of its current war work. Nor do I like the idea of handing over to an extra-constitutional body very important executive functions like the choice of representatives in London or at Peace Conference, which fall withinconstitutional responsibility of Governor-General in Council.* Not printed.
(d) The Legislature, which, despite its staleness and its somewhat, shallowpopular support, is a valuable part of constitutional machine, would be side-tracked, and, as far as anything to do with conduct of the war or planning for post-war world is concerned (and this covers almost everything of importance),would have to be content to ratify the conclusions of an extra-constitutional body.It is the Legislature, or rather Legislatures, to which Indian opinion properlylooks for continuity of Parliamentary Government as India advances to nation-hood. Moreover, I would view with alarm the prospect of having to press areluctant Legislature to pass supply for measures prompted by an extra-constitu-tional body, and perhaps having to use my powers of certification to obtain it.(e) The minorities certainly, and even any sections of Hindus who felt them-selves under-represented! in the new body, would complain with every reason that we had torn up our pledges, firstly, not to effect fundamental constitutional changes during war (for this would in effect be a request of power which must inevitably I ? become] a live transfer); secondly, to seek friendly agreement amongIndians themselves upon the form of post-war body, which will devise framework of a new constitution; and thirdly, not to transfer responsibility for the peace and welfare of India to any system of government whose authority is directlydenied by large and powerful element in India&apos;s national life, as authority ofcontemplated council would probably be denied.(/) The movement would be regarded as a direct challenge to Pakistan and.whatever may be said for throwing down such a challenge, now is scarcely the,moment for it.4. To sum up, it is to my mind a fatal defect in the Prime Minister&apos;s pro-,posal that it precipitates whole constitutional controversy, which is so largelycommunal and on a present view irreconcilable, into the conduct of the war andday-to-day government of this country. This marriage of two elements which both our pledges and interests of India command [ ? us to] keep apart rendersthe proposal not more but less likely to obtain the co-operation of political parties,especially those of minorities.5. At the same time I sympathise with and share the spirit that animatesthe Prime Ministers proposal; what I press for is further consideration by us all of ways of giving it practical form which will not make the task of Governmenthere more difficult, nor throw India into a communal turmoil at this criticalmoment.Copy of telegram from Viceroy to Secretary of State for India,dated February 14, 1942.5-U.   Secret.   Following for Prime Minister : I do hope you may not allow yourself to become wedded to any particular,part of your plan until you have given your most serious attention to my comments.I am sure public interest requires that you should hear with an open mind theviews which I and my immediate advisers will put before you. I am well aware ofthe gravity of the military position in Burma and the Malay Archipelago, but thatis no reason for doing anything hasty or unsound. Above all, we must have anxious,regard for continuing soundness of Indian Army, which alone stands between[ ? Japanese] and their ultimate [ ? goal] which must be a union, military andeconomic, with German army on Persian Gulf. For if Germans get licked theJapanese will forfeit all theymay have acquired. If we go about things the rightway I think we can keep them apart, despite the weakness of the sea positionas it is now developing. In India, if they invade, we shall have elbow room and ground and climate [corrupt group ? to] suit us. But we must regard morale and fighting value of army as more important than United States of Americaopinion or that of any minorities in the United Kingdom. For reasons whichI will develop at length to Amery, I am quite clear that an important element [ ? inthe scheme] would damage gravely our power of resistance to Japanese invasion.That   element is your proposal to give Defence Council the function of
constitution-making as well as the duty of advising about the war. I shall showreasons which in my judgment render it imperative that you should jettison,utterly any notion of these separate functions residing in a [ ? single] body.2.   I shall be prepared, if you will kindly agree to consider them, to do mybest to offer through Amery constructive alternatives to those parts of your scheme &quot;which  I find myself bound to criticise.3. It is a great comfort to me to feel that I shall find you, like another greatChurchill, magnanimous and unruffled in the hour of crisis, and that whatever may befall us our relations will continue to be [group omitted] -ed by mutualsympathy for each other&apos;s public difficulties and warmed by private affection.Copy of telegram from Viceroy to Secretary of State for India, dated february 18, 1942.324-S.   My telegram 302-S.I have now received your telegrams Nos. 3-U and 4-U and can adjust andexpand my comments in light of further details which you have sent me.Please note that I have not repeated below all points of criticism in my tele-,gram 302-S, which should be read with this telegram. I recognise that some ofmy particular objections must be modified. Thus, proposed Council would not be exposed to charge of being merely nominated, though method of compositionsuggested is open to criticism of the different order which I shall advance later..Again, the method proposed would be based on Parliamentary institutions, andcomment in sub-paragraph 3 (d) of my telegram correspondingly qualified, thoughreference to Central Legislature is unaffected. Still more important is proposal that main operative decisions of constitution-framing body must express desire of people of India as a whole, and that this condition should reinforce rather thanreplace His Majesty&apos;s Government^ 1940 pledges to minorities. This in itself would plainly help to allay hostility of minorities, particularly the Moslems, ofwhich I otherwise have such grave fears.2. Nevertheless, the objection of principle which I summed up in para-graph No. 4 of my telegram thus remains unshaken, and is indeed in some respects reinforced by details now disclosed. The constitutional function whichis to be added to proposed Council of Defence may seem to us secondary, because it cannot begin to be discharged until victory is won, which is prime consideration,but in Indian eyes it would altogether overshadow the Council&apos;s present influenceupon defence policy as justification for its existence and criterion of politicalattitudes toward it. Hence, whatever formulae may be used on the one hand topledge acceptance of the body&apos;s constitutional decisions, and on the other hand to reassure the minorities that these will not be taken by counting heads, from the start such a body would be bound to take on violently communal character of constitutional controversy itself. This would not only gravely handicap thehigher conduct of the war in India but would also be liable to produce a communalupheaval which might make a heavy and prolonged call upon troops for internal security and upon the resources of civil administration while dislocating com-munications and war production generally. Worse still, it might precipitate a dangerous communal reaction in the forces themselves. I cannot express too strongly my fear that the plan in its present form would before long infect thearmy with communal fever of most catastrophic kind.3. As one special example of these dangers I would mention the certainty that such body would be keenly interested in communal proportions in recruitingforces and in the question of Indianisation. The interference and intrigue towhich this would give rise could only have lamentable effects upon the discipline and morale of the Forces themselves. This danger cannot perhaps be altogetheraverted in ^any scheme of political advance in India during war, but there is no need to heighten it by using the same body as must fight out the constitutionalissue to guide our present administration of defence.
4. I profoundly hope, therefore, that I can persuade you and Prime Ministerto separate the incongruous purposes of solving the post-war constitutional problem and securing wider political co-operation in the conduct of the War.In this hope I propose to examine the detailed plan for establishing a Council ofDefence, on the assumption that the same ad hoc body would not also be loaded with constitutional functions.5. If compelled to choose between the two methods of election outlined in para-graphs 1 and 2 of your telegram No. 4-U, I would prefer the second, (a) becausethe first would require an impossibly complex electoral system with several hundred candidates facing a single electorate of about 1,600 voters, (o) becausethe second would give a fairer representation both to Moslems and to otherminorities and special interests (approximately 33 and 25 respectively out of 100.against 30 and 20). If resultant body were to have constitutional functions, thesecond method would enjoy the further advantage that expected Federation orConfederation of Provinces would be negotiated by accredited representatives ofProvinces themselves. If, on the other hand, as I trust, those functions are to bedealt with by distinct machinery, it becomes unnecessary now to go beyond hintingat kind of Constitution-framing Conference which might in due course prove acceptable to Indian opinion.6. Even on this assumption, however, both your alternative methods of election for war-time body are open to the following grave criticism if they areapplied to existing Provincial Assemblies. These were elected more than fiveyears ago on issues very different from those which now present themselves. TheCongress might well be content with overwhelming position which they wouldacquire in resultant Council, and which they would be unlikely to repeat if freshelections were held now. The Moslems, on the other hand, would be enraged;for it is part of their case that only as a result of Congress rule in seven Provinces, from 1937 to 1939 were their eyes subsequently opened to danger to Islam., Jinnah, in particular, could claim, with reason, that since 1937 Moslem League,which was then very weak in some Provinces, has been strengthened enormouslyin organisation and public support. This is one of main grounds of my belief that any such proposal would, from birth, fail hopelessly to secure its expressobject of communal solidarity during the war, but would only make matters much worse. On the other hand, to hold fresh election now, expressly on constitu-tional and therefore communal issue, might well plunge large areas of India intobloody civil war. Even without general election the necessary by-election wouldbe apt to produce same result on a somewhat smaller scale. The omission from the electoral college of Central Legislature, which contains a number of leadingpoliticians, who would have little chance of election by Provincial Legislatures,is a secondary defect.* t&apos;7. Assuming, however, that these initial difficulties were overcome, I can see no escape from dilemma that a Council of Defence of this kind must either havereal power, in which case it must destroy responsibility of proper executive, ornot have real power, in which case it would be of little use, a fact that would not need to be pointed out to Indian public opinion. It is an attempt to escape fromdilemma by adding to an advisory body tempting but incongruous functions thatin my view lies at root of error in plan as I see it.8. My own expectation would be that new Council would soon acquire realpower, which would prove more than embarrassing to Government. This, indeed,is implicit in proposal to entrust it with selection of representatives at WarCabinet and Peace Conference. Whoever nominally appoints and instructs them,such representatives must in practice be answerable to the body that selects them,gives them its confidence and can, if it wishes, insist on their recall. This break-down of my Council&apos;s responsibility would spell weakness just where strength is most needed. As a further example, I shudder at the prospect of allowing such a body to take on, as you propose, the organising of air raid precautions, sincethe efforts of political bodies to do so are already a potential source and gravedifficulty to Provincial authorities. I set my face firmly against anythingsmacking of parallel government. , ,  u
9. I do not imagine that it would have been thought necessary to re-constitute an Advisory Defence Council as such on a representative political basis had the later constitutional function not been in view; but while reserving final comments on merits of such a proposal if it is to be considered alone, I have many objections.Even if we isolate the plan to re-constitute the Advisory Defence Council on arepresentative political basis, while reserving final comments, I see manyobjections, apart from dangers of proposed electoral method to which I havealready alluded. There is a world of difference between a nominated councilwhose main purpose is to keep Provinces and Provincial representatives informed and give them a sense of importance and a body which without responsibility would want to run war. We could not, for instance, impart military secrets toits elected personnel. Then there is the obvious difficulty of getting the Princesto co-operate in such a body. Nor do I think that my point about the difficultiesassociated with Viceroy&apos;s Chairmanship is fully covered by your suggestion that. I might be assisted by a Deputy President. Apart from problem of finding such aperson who would be acceptable without usurping my own functions, I see almostequal difficulties about attendance at new Council of staff of the executive headsof my Supply Department, and others concerned with execution of defence policy. The best elements in the Provinces would likewise be distracted fromproper duty of helping to carry on provincial administration.10. Turning to constitutional problems which I am now assuming will attract an attempt at solution separate from that of current war effort, I appreciate the momentous importance both in itself and in its likely effect uponopinion in India and elsewhere, of proposed pledge or rather scheme of pledgesoutlined in last sentence, paragraph No. 3, and in paragraphs 10 and 11 of yourtelegram 3-U. I would prefer not to comment upon it in the present context,but to link my comments, which I may say are entirely favourable in principle,to any positive plan that I may find myself able to offer, if this is desired of me,as an alternative to proposals which I have been obliged so strongly to criticise.11. Finally, I would beg Prime Minister not to overdo the references toIndia&apos;s danger with Which he would propose to introduce any revised offer. Itis not only that public opinion here is not tough like that which the PrimeMinister is accustomed to addressing, but is liable to waves of dangerousdepression and needs tonics rather than purgatives; but I also want to save him from exposing himself to criticism that only when the enemy was at the gate andthe British power to hold India already flagging did he hear her cry for freedom.Let him rather stress the rising need for India to take her place in the world&apos;sCouncils of War and reconstruction, and to consolidate the status which hersoldiers, sailors and airmen have already been winning by their valorous partin the defence of her integrity and her ideals.12. I note from paragraph 4 of your telegram 4-U that, although you had previously endorsed my view that there was nothing to be done for the momentbeyond strengthening my existing Executive and National Defence Councils, you had been swayed from this judgment by what you describe as a bold imaginativeplan. While I am anxious to accept any sound constructive plan, I would askyou to read again my telegram No. 1Q4-S,*&apos; dated 21st January, in which Igave you my considered view of the political situation here. Nothing that has happened since either in India or elsewhere has done anything to alter the broad outline of that view or of the conclusions to which it gave rise. Indeed theyhave rather been fortified by recent unfortunate course of the war, which hasrendered it all the more dangerous for us to risk a crumbling of the Governmentin India and an outbreak of communal strife.* W.P. (42) 43.



</content>
</cab>
