<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/38/0 images: 8-11</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ABSENCE OF MINISTERS EEOM THE UNITED kingdom note by the Prime minister from indications which have reached me recently it seems possible that theremay be some misunderstanding about the extent to which one Minister may actfor an absent colleague. The primary purpose of such an arrangement is toensure that political guidance is readily available for the officials who will be acting on behalf of the absent Minister and to enable the Departments interests to be adequately represented in Ministerial discussions of policy. The currentinstructions on this subject (paragraphs 54-56 of the Notes annexed to CP. (49) 95)do not make it sufficiently clear that a Minister should not purport to exercisepowers expressed by statute as exercisable by another Minister. Nor do they makeit clear that such arrangements require my prior approval. I have thereforearranged for the current instructions to be recast so as to bring out these points.2. I have also taken this opportunity to insert in the instructions a newparagraph reminding Ministers of the need to consult the Foreign Secretary or,as the case may be, the Secretary of State for the Colonies or the Secretary ofState for Commonwealth Relations, before visiting countries overseas. a ministerial visit to a country overseas may present an opportunity for pressingsome point of policy; alternatively, the presence of a United Kingdom minister in a particular country at a given time may be inopportune or even embarrassing to the Government. It is important therefore that the need for such consultationshould not be overlooked.3. The attached Notes should be substituted for the existing Section VIIof the Notes annexed to CP. (49) 95. They Avill be incorporated in the nextconsolidated edition of those Notes on Procedure.C. R. A.10, Downing Street, S.W. 1,2nd January, 1950.38069aPrinted for the Cabinet.  January 1950CONFIDENTIAL Copy No.    31CP. (50) 12nd January, 1950CABINET

VII. ABSENCE OF MINISTERS FROM THE UNITED KINGDOM54. It is the established practice that any Minister who is a member of theCabinet or is in charge of a Department should obtain The King&apos;s permission tobe absent from the United Kingdom, whether on duty or on leave, and should inform His Majesty what arrangements are to be made for the administration ofhis office during his absence. Such arrangements should have the prior approvalof the Prime Minister.Other Ministers who propose to leave the United Kingdom, whether on duty or on leave, need not obtain The King&apos;s permission to do so. They should,however, obtain the consent of the Prime Minister as well as their own Minister.Any Minister who proposes to visit a foreign country should consult theForeign Secretary, before seeking the Prime Ministers consent, and a minister who proposes to visit another part of the Commonwealth should consult theSecretary of State for Commonwealth Relations (if the visit is to a self-governingCommonwealth country or to the High Commission territories in South Africa)or the Secretary of State for the Colonies. Projected visits to the Irish Republic,even on holiday, should be the subject of prior consultation with the Secretaryof State for Commonwealth Relations.55. When a Minister is to be away from London, his Parliamentary Secre-tary will normally take Ministerial charge of the Department. On some occasions,however, it may be desirable that arrangements should be made for another minister of Cabinet rank to hold himself available to give political guidance to officials of the Department and to represent the Departments interests in discussions in Cabinet or Cabinet Committees. Any such arrangements, if notinitiated by the Prime Minister, should have his prior approval.When: one Minister of Cabinet rank is acting in this way on behalf of another,,special care must be taken over the exercise of statutory powers. With someexceptions the powers of a Secretary of State can be exercised by another Secretaryof State; and the powers of a Board or Council may be exercisable in the absenceof its principal member. But for the most part the powers of a Minister cannotbe exercised by a Minister in charge of another Department; and a Minister whois acting for an absent colleague should be careful to avoid appearing formally to exercise powers which are expressed by statute as exercisable by his colleague.There is no similar difficulty about submissions to His Majesty. Submissionsmade in the absence of &quot;a Minister should normally be made by his parliamentary secretary if he is a Privy Councillor, but if he is not they may be made by another Minister of Cabinet rank. Submissions on behalf of an absent Secretaryof State must be made by another Secretary of State. Submissions on behalf ofthe First Lord of the Admiralty may be made in his absence by the Senior lord commissioner.38069


</content>
</cab>
