<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/38/0 images: 52-57</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   January 1950SECRETCP. (50) 10iQth January, 1950CABINETABSENCE   ATTRIBUTED   TO   SICKNESS   IN   GOVERNMENTINDUSTRIAL ESTABLISHMENTSMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer at the meeting of the Cabinet on 27th July, 1949 (CM. (49) 49th Conclusions,Minute 3 (3)) the Prime Minister was invited to arrange for the appointmentof a working party of officials to consider what further action might, be takento prevent abuse of the scheme of paid sick leave for Government industrialemployees. It later came to notice that the Joint Co-ordinating Committeefor Government Industrial Establishments had appointed a Sub-Committee,with representatives from both sides of the Committee, for a similar purpose.The- Prime Minister therefore decided that no separate working party shouldbe appointed but that I should report the findings of this Sub-Committee to theCabinet in due course.    &apos; &apos;&apos;2. A copy of the Sub-Committee.&apos;s Report, which was signed on 2nd January,1950, is annexed. It has been formally presented to the Chairman of the JointCo-ordinating Committee and will be discussed at the next meeting of the.Committee on 26th January.3. The Report is unanimous with the exception of the first two recommendations. .4. The first recommendation was intended to reduce or remove the financialinducement which is otherwise present in almost every case. The Sub-Coiumitteeagreed (paragraph 11 (iii)) that this rarely amounts to less than 5s. a week andmay be, as much as  1; this accords with the information already given to theCabinet by the Minister of Supply in a memorandum dated 20th July. 1949(CP. (49) 156, paragraph 9).The Trade Union side members objected to this recommendation on the groundthat no similar restriction of benefit was required by the Government in the case oftheir non-industrial employees, and that discrimination against their industrialemployees was unfair and unjustified.5. The second recommendation was intended to serve two purposes. Thefirst was to meet the very common, criticism of the scheme that it encourages the employee to stay away for at least five days in order to get his pay for the first three. The Sub-Committee found little evidence that employees stay away for the exact period of five days, but there were indications that the number of longerabsences had increased at the expense of those of less than five days. The: secondwas to put a sanction against absence for a trivial cause, by requiring the employeeto bear a small part of the expense of any absence. In both these respects therecommendation is directed to the same, purpose as the provision for a. &quot;waiting-period &apos;&apos; (found in this and most other schemes), but carries the. principle further.The Trade Union Side objected on the grounds that the recommendation was.directed not to the prevention, of any abuse of which there was evidence&apos; but was intended only to make the scheme cheaper, and that no similar sanction was imposed on the non-industrial employees.M  illCopy No.38155b
26. To both these recommendations the Trade Union Side also raised thegeneral objection that the current rates of absence did not disclose a state ofaffairs so serious as to.warrant the drastic step of reducing the amount of sickpay.7.   The other recommendations are likely to provoke little opposition.The third proposes that there should be rules of the kind commonly made by voluntary sick clubs, requiring, for instance, that the sick employee should be. inhis home at certain hours, and that he should not do any work.The fourth explains itself.The fifth is complementary to the third, and is directed towards Departments,enjoining them both for the welfare of the employee and for the protection of theDepartment, to visit the sick employee in his home or hospital.The sixth is intended both as a precaution against lax certification and to resolve genuine cases of doubt whether the particular illness is such as to preventthe patient returning to his work.8.   The Sub-Committee were concerned only with the prevention of abuse of the scheme : they therefore did not consider proposals for limiting its scopenor for controlling certification.   The scheme itself is subject to review in twoyears, i.e., in the autumn of this year, when the question must be considered whether the scheme is to continue, and if so, in what form.9. I propose that we should instruct the Official Side of the JointCo-ordinating Committee to accept all the recommendations in the Report, andto seek the agreement of the Trade Union Side to as much of what is recommendedas is possible. It will not be practicable to carry into immediate effect either of thefirst two recommendations without the agreement of the Trade Union Side (whichis virtually certain to be withheld) because they involve amendment of an existing agreement. Assuming that Trade Union consent is withheld it will not be reasonable to take steps to denounce the agreement or to put these recommendationsinto effect by unilateral action, since the scheme as a whole is by agreement to be reviewed in a few months&apos; time. That review will cover the whole question of possible discontinuance of the scheme or of its possible modification either inaccordance with the recommendations or in any other respects. But even adeclaration of policy by the Official Side in favour of the contested recommenda-tions at this stage may have a salutary &apos; effect and emphasise the warningalready posted in all industrial establishments, that the scheme is to be reviewed in the autumn, that the extent of absence must then be taken into account, andthat abuse may endanger its continuance.10. I suggest also that instructions should be given for this report to be sentto all industrial establishments and to be discussed at joint meetings of workers and management, emphasis being placed upon the review and the need to abolishany sort of malingering before the review takes place, lest the advantages of thescheme may be lost.R. S. C.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,16th January, 1950.ANNEXJoint Co-ordinating Committee for Government IndustrialEstablishmentsReport of the Sub-Committee on Absence from Work attributed toSickness1. We were appointed at the 43rd meeting of the Joint Co-co-ordinating committee held on 28th July, 1949, to examine the working of the Scheme ofPaid Sick leave. We have had six meetings and have considered statistical andother information supplied by Government Departments to the Treasury, by whom the information has been put before us.
&apos; We have also approached British Railways, the British Employers&apos;Confederation, the National Joint Industrial. Council for Local Authorities(Non-trading Services), the Rural District Councils Association and the SouthEastern Regional Hospitals Board; none of these bodies was able to supply nisiwith detailed figures.&apos;-      .     i , , ^The Treasury Medical Adviser (Dr. W:. E. Chiesman) has been;present atfour of our meetings. ,We record with great regret that Mr. T. W. Nevard of the Ministry pf Supplydied on 16th October, 1949. Mr. F. A. H. Smith has since sat as a member of theCommittee in his place. . -      - .2. At our first meeting, we thought it desirable to define our terms ofreference more closely, as follows :- ,(1) To establish the extent of the increase in sick absence since the intro-duction of the Sick Pay Scheme ; :    -(2) To examine the reasons for the increase;(3) To consider what steps should be taken to lessen it. ,3. The Scheme of Paid Sick Leave was introduced for the beginning of the pay week containing 1st September, 1.948, and covers virtually all GovernmentIndustrial employees. It is subject to review after two years.4. All Departments keep detailed records of absence from work, but not all departments have central records from which full information of; absencethroughout the Department is available. So to avoid causing unnecessary workwe have not attempted to review the Scheme as its affects all employees, but have examined only information about large blocks of staff which could be readilyobtained. This information came mainly from the five Departments whichbetween them employ about three-quarters of all Government industrial employees,and included statistics for all the Admiralty Home Dockyards and all the; royal ordnance Factories. We are satisfied that the information before us properlyrepresents the general working of the Scheme,5. In most cases the information showed the percentage of working time lostfor a given period among a particular group of employees by absence attributed to sickness. It rarely distinguished between the incidence among men and among&apos;women, nor did it draw comparisons between groups of employees of differentages. We recognise that in a particular investigation of absence among aparticular group these factors are important, but we believe that for the purposeof our examination general averages are significant enough.6. In a very few cases the information before us has covered periods before1947, but in the main it has related only to 1947, 1948 and 1949. Sickness rates were generally higher during the war, but we have otherwise no reason to; suppose that conclusions based on comparisons drawn between rates for the twelve oreighteen months before 1st September, 1948, and those for the months since thenare unsound. &apos;7. Our first conclusion is that there has been a recognisable increase in thesickness rates since the Scheme was introduced. The general pattern of the figuresdown to September 1948 show that the time lost was between two per cent, andthree per cent, of possible working time. For the later period it has been about four per cent, and six per cent, and higher in some establishments. Becausesickness varies with the seasons, the figures for one or two months alone;.cannotbe regarded as significant, it is not yet possible to say whether absence has lessenedsince attention was first drawn to it.&apos; 8. &quot;Information supplied to us aboiuV non-industrial civil servants1-who - areentitled to paid sick leave shows that in the lower grades the proportion of timelost in 1947 and 1948 was between about four per cent, and five per cent, and inthe higher grades about three per cent: - Such-information as we have been&apos; ableto get from sources outside Government Departments suggests that similar ratescan be found in correspondingi grades of employees, outside the Civil Service.From this we have assumed that absence should not-be regarded as abnormallyhigh unless it exceeds four per cent.&quot;as ah average!annual rate,   :    - ;i --&apos;-!,.! u-.irS-\38155 b 2
. If, therefore, four per cent can be faken as the &quot; normal: annual rate,&quot; it follows from our first conclusion that the rates among&quot; industrial employeeswere formery subTnormal but now exceed the normal, with greater excesses insome estabislunehts, ,9. We find also that the increase in rates since September 1948 is generalthough there are many establishments in which it is not excessive. It appears from information supplied to us that there is a widespread impression amonglocal representatives both of the Official Side and of the Trade Union Side thatthe scheme is being abused, but little Concrete evidence of this has been produced.There are-undoubtedly conspicuous examples of excessive increases in the ratesof absence; these are not widespread and an exact assessment of the extent ofthem cannot be made without a full review of all establishments. We have alsolearned of isolated cases in which disciplinary action has been taken againstemployees who took casual work while absent on paid sick leave.10. We find that there has been a considerable reduction in absences of upto five days and a very substantial increase in absences of more than five days.11. We have considered some cases in which the rates of absence have appeared excessive. Examination of the reasons for&apos; the increase involvesspeculation as well as inference from facts.  i-Among reasons which have been suggested to us are the following:  (i) That before the introduction of the Scheme some employees were pre-vented by loss of wages from going sick and from convalescing for aslong as they should have done, and that the patient is no longer con-strained to resist the doctor&apos;s recommendation that he should not return to work until he is properly fit. This would explain an increase to the normal annual rate but would not in itself explain rates in excessof-it.(ii) That the Scheme is new, and its introduction has put employees in mind of the general advantages to be derived from it and so has encouraged:.....a minority to abuse it.&quot;(iii) That many who get paid sick leave receive more money during some ofthe weeks of sick absence due to savings on income-tax and Ministry ofNational Insurance contributions currently payable and savings onfares. This advantage varies with individual cases and with the duration of the sick leave, but is rarely less than 5s. and may amount to.15s, or 20s. a week. On the other hand, there may be financial draw-backs; the illness may cause more expense in the home, and an employee&apos; may lose &quot;part of his piece-work earnings or shiftwork or overtime rates(there is no substantial evidence, that absence is greater among time-workers than among piece-workers).(iv) That in some establishments the average age is very high so that the employees are more prone to sickness. In some cases we found this tobe true, and we note cases in which the average! age of all men in theestablishment is 55 or 56 years,(v) That the provision in the Scheme which gives pay for the first three daysonly if the absence lasts five days or more encourages an employee to stay away for at least five days. This is perhaps, the commonestsuggestion that has been made to us for the reduction in absence, butwe!find little evidence in support of it. There is no doubt that shorterabsences are fewer in number since the Scheme was introduced; as wehave noted, there is little evidence that absences of five days haveincreased but those for longer periods have increased appreciably.12. The point has repeatedly been made that all absence is justified becausesick leave is not granted except upon production of a doctor&apos;s certificate. Wecannot completely accept this because it seems to us that the diagnosis of thephysician in the first place must usually be based upon the. patients own accountof his symptoms, so that the neurotic and the dishonest stand to gain an advantage over the others.13. In considering the information before us we have paid most regard tothe material and measurable facts which it has disclosed. Nevertheless, we havealso been aware of the intangible causes of sick absence which arise from the state
zr,0f mind of the individual employee. Precise evidence of these causes is necessarilydifficult to get and to assess; but two points appear to us to be worth comment,first, it seems to us that the rates of absence are significantly lower in old-estab-lished and compact establishments than in those which have had little time todevelop a tradition and spirit of their own. This suggests that a sound publicopinion is a valuable safeguard against the abuse of a sick pay scheme.Secondly, as we have noted, the Scheme encourages a patient to accept medical advice that he should not return to work until he feels completely well, instead of taking the initiative in obtaining medical permission to resume work as soon asresumption will not endanger his complete recovery.14. We have regarded the question whether the Scheme be abolished orsuspended as outside our terms of reference.15. (a) The Trade Union Side members have been unable to agree to the.following recommendation made by the Official Side : (1) That the amount of the sick pay should be reduced by 10s. a week in every case in order to remove any financial advantage from absence.(2) That no pay shall be issued for the first three days of any period of sickabsence.(&amp;) All members of the Committee are agreed upon the following recom-mendations : (3) That strict and regular personal conduct should be required of everyemployee who is absent sick, according to rules to be agreed.(4) That opportunity should be taken as ofteta as possible and by all con-venient methods both by Departments and by Trade Unions to cam-paign against the Scheme being abused by the irresponsible minority.(5) That provision should be made for any employee absent sick to be visitedat his home at the discretion of the local management.(6) That a Department should be entitled to require an employee to undergoexamination by a departmental medical officer or other doctorappointed by them, to determine, after consultation with the employee&apos;sdoctor, whether he should continue to be eligible for sick pay.STANLEY LEES.A. H. ELWELL.F. A. H. SMITH.F. N. SMITH.W. D. GOSS.G. F. COOK.H. J. HANCOCK.HARRY W CRANE.R. G. SHEPPARD(Acting Secretary).2nd January, 1950.


</content>
</cab>
