<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/38/0 images: 178-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ijjIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)3J C R E TC.P- (50)  211ST MARCH,   1950IRON AND STEEL act memorandum by the Minister of SupplyDuring the course of the Debates on the Address, thecuestion of the Iron and Steel Act,  1949, will undoubtedly beraised,  and my colleagues may therefore like to have this statement of the present position so that the form of the reply to be given by the Government spokesmen can be con-side red.2. Under the Iron and Steel Act, the Iron and steel corporation may be appointed on or after 1st October,  1950,and the securities of the companies to be transferred will vestin the Corporation on 1st January,  1951,  or such later date(but not more than twelve months later) as the Minister may byorder determine;    such an order is not subject to annulmentby either House.The general position is that the Government have allthe necessary powers, without further reference to Parliament,to set up the Corporation and arrange the transfer - subjectto the time limitations indicated above.Having regard to the statement which I made in theHouse of Commons on 16th November,  19^9 (see Annex), no action has so far been taken about approaching persons as possiblemembers of the Corporation.      That statement must be kept inmind in the present circumstances.      There have been certainPress references to it since the Election,  and it may beexpected that &quot;the Opposition will claim that the &quot;atmosphere of political tension and uncertainty&quot; still prevails.3. I had contemplated,  as many of my colleagues know,that shortly after the General Election we might appoint anOrganising Committee to carry on with the preparatory workwhich is necessary in order to ensure a smooth take-over, andthat the Chairman and some,  if not all,  of the members of that committee would be potential members of the Corporation, tobe formally appointed as such on 1st October, 1950.      It is,of course,  of paramount importance that we should secure thebest men available to serve on such an Organising Committeeand on the Corporation, but under present conditions we are unlikely to get the people we want from the industry or from outside, as they would still be loath   to commit themselves.Moreover,  as the Act does not permit me to appoint the membersof the Corporation before 1st October, we have a valid replyto questions about the delay in selecting the Corporation.I4. Departmental preparations for operating the Act are well advanced.      Among other things,  arrangements had beencompleted with a view to -(a)    communicating with the companies soon after theElection on compensation and other matters;-1-2 ICOPY NO. D  *CABINET

(b) opening discussions on administrative arrangements with the British Iron and Steel Federation(B. I. S. F. ) at an early date;    and. (c) providing the Organising Committee with material toenable them to make a prompt start.But since we cannot yet expect co-operation from the leadersof the industry, the companies, or the staff of 3. I. S. P. , thepreparatory work cannot, for the time being, make much further progress.5. The consequent delay might mean that the transfer ofthe companies would have to be delayed beyond 1st January, 195&quot;!(which,  in any event,  is not a convenient date).      The extentof the delay would depend on how soon we could start the actionindicated in the preceding paragraph.      I estimate that betweensuch a start and the date to be fixed for the transfer theremust be at least six months in which the members of theCorporation can be selected and appointed and the Corporationcan familiarise itself with its main problems before vesting date.      The number of compensation settlements which could beeffected in such a period would not be as many as I had previously hoped, but this is not a fundamental consideration.6. Meanwhile, certain provisions of the Act designed toprevent the companies from transferring or dissipating assetsor making imprudent commitments will continue to be inoperation.      But there seems to be little danger that theywill hamper the companies in carrying on their proper business.The Act ensures that, pending transfer, any company can seekcover for any transaction about which, it is in doubt, but sofar such applications have been few.      Similarly, any companycan submit &quot;hiving off&quot; proposals if it wishes, and those can,as hitherto, be dealt with by my Department promptly andwithout great difficulty;    in practice, however,  I am notexpecting many more such proposals.7. There is no good reason to suppose that the periodof some months&apos; uncertainty now and consequent delay in the vesting date in 1951 would adversely affect the productiondrive or the solution of the connected problems of raw materialssupply for the industry.      Nor is there any reason to suppoaethat the solution of the problems of iron and steel prices which may well arise in the next year will be adversely affected.      For the present period of uncertainty at any rate,the industry is unlikely to press for price increases unless Itis compelled to do so because of substantial future increases in the cost of its raw materials or labour (e.g.   allowance ofthe railways claim for increased carriage charges).8. As to the Development Plans, with the exception ofthe major project for complete modernisation of the Colvilleplants in Scotland (which is unlikely to reach a concrete formfor at least twelve months) and a -few minor items elsewhere,the whole of the first Development Plan is well advanced and fully financed and can be expected to be completed to schedule.The next development phase, concerned primarily with the modernisation of the finishing end and regrouping of plants tosecure greater efficiency,  is anyhow not likely to takedefinitive shape for at least another year, when it will bepossible better to assess the effects of the first Plan.G. R. S.in is try of Supply, W. C. 2,1ST MARCH,  1950.

annex extract FROM A STATEMENT MADE BY THE MINISTER OFSUPPLY IN THE HOUSE OF COMMONS ON 16TliHTOVBMBER8   1949There is one further matter I should, like to add.We are bound to have an Election by the middle of next year,and in an atmosphere of political tension and uncertainty itwould plainly he unwise to proceed now with the selection of individuals to serve on the Corporation.      Men who may wellbe best suited for this responsible task might understandablybe reluctant to commit themselves to accepting such aposition, and throw up their present jobs,, as long as theythink there is a possibility, however remote, that theCorporation may not, after all, be established.The Government have therefore decided not to makeany approaches, formal or informal,  inviting individuals tobecome members of the Corporation, until we have emergedinto the calmer atmosphere that will follow the election Ofthe new Parliament.      I think that right hon.   and hon.-Members on both sides of the House will agree that thesuccess of the nationalised industry will depend to a con-siderable extent  on the calibre of the men serving on theCorporation, and that it would be folly to rush our selection of these people unnecessarily.(Official Report, 16. 11.49, Cols.  201+6-7)-3-


</content>
</cab>
