<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/38/0 images: 404-429</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret . P. (50) 561UTH MARCH,  1950BECIiUANALAND PROTECTORATE:    SERETSE KHAMAMemorandum &quot;by the Secretary of State force omm on wealth R e1atIon sIn view of the misunderstandings of our policy inregard to the withholding of the recognition of Seretse Khamaas Chief of the Bamangwato, and of the very widespreadcriticism which the decision has met, I should be glad tohave the approval of my colleagues to the publication of a white Paper which would set out the facts of the case and thereasons for our decision.I circulate herewith the draft of a White paper which has been prepared on the basis that we maintain our refusal to publish the Report of the Judicial Enquiry, as Iam confident we must do;    but I would propose to give ingeneral terms the reasons for our refusal, and also toindicate briefly the advice given by the Enquiry.      I feel itis essential to remove the very common - and excusable -supposition that the Enquiry advised in favour of the recog-nition of Seretse,  and that this is the explanation of our refusal to publish.      The reasons for our withholding recog-nition are given in paragraph 18 of the draft Paper.I would propose,   if the Cabinet agree, to find anopportunity in the House on Thursday afternoon, 16th March,  tostate that a White Paper will be published very shortly.      Iwould hope to lay it early next week.      I therefore ask approval for the presentation of a Paper on the general lines of theaccompanying draft, with the reservation that I should be at liberty to make anj/ revisions of detail that may subsequently be thought necessary.P. C. G. -W.Commonwealth Relations office,8.V7. 1,IhTH MARCH, 1950.COPY NO.CABINET

DRAFT   WHITE   paper in the following paragraphs an account is given ofthe circumstances relating to the succession to the chieftainship of the Bamangwato tribe and of the considerations which have been present to HisMajesty&apos;s Government in reaching their decision uponthe question of the recognition of Seretse Khama.2.      The Bamangwato-Reserve forms part of the bechuanaland Protectorate.    The Protectorate coversan area of 275,000 sq. miles and has a population of300,000 persons, almost entirely African.    It is ,administered by a Resident Commissioner under thedirection of the High Commissioner for Basutoland, the bechuanaland Protectorate and Swaziland, who is himselfresponsible to the Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.    The Bamangwato Reserve, on the eastern sideof the Protectorate, has an area of 40,000 sq. miles anda population of 100,000.    The Bamangwato themselvesnumber only 18,000;    the remainder of the population in the Reserve consists of Africans who originallybelonged to various tribes, but who have adhered to the bamangwato and owe allegiance to the same Chief.    Thehistory of the Bechuanaland Protectorate has been marked by a series of tribal disputes about succession to the Chieftainship, which in one case ledeventually to the formation of four separate tribes whoseruling families derive from a common ancestor.3.      In 1923 occurred the death of Khama III, thegrandfather of Seretse.    He had ruled over the bamangwato for some fifty years and is regarded as oneof the great African rulers.    He was succeeded by his

son, Sekgoma II, who died two years later,leaving as his heir his only surviving son,Seretse, who was born on the 1st July, 1921.A Council of Regency was at first formed, but in1926 it was found more suitable to instal asRegent Tshekedi, son of Khama III -and half-brotherof Sekgoma II.4.      Seretse was educated in South Africa and obtained his Bachelor of Arts degree at Fort Hare. &apos;He expressed a desire to continue his education atOxford where he went to Balliol College in 1945.Subsequently he left Oxford to pursue his legalstudies in London, where he completed the first part of the Bar examination.5.     In September 1948 Seretse notified Tshekedithat he proposed to marry Miss Ruth Williams, anEnglishwoman, on the 2nd October, and said that he feared his uncle and the tribe would not approve ofhis proposed action.    Appeals were made to him bythe Native Authority of the Bamangwato Reserve and hyothers to postpone the marriage.    Seretse thereuponadvanced his wedding day, and despite this opposition was married on the 29th September.6.      Seretse was summoned to Serowe by the triballeaders to explain his action.    A series of tribalmeetings (&quot;kgotlas&quot;) followed, in which the marriagewas discussed.    At the first, in November, 1948, the tribe with very few exceptions condemned the marriage and resolved that all steps should be taken to preventSeretse&apos;s Tvblte wife from entering the bamangwato reserve.    At the second meeting in Decembersupport for Seretse was stronger but was not

decisively in his favour, and he agreed to asuggestion that he should return to England and pursuehis legal studies.    In June, 1949, he returned to theReserve, and at the third meeting of the tribe heldin that month there was a very considerablenumerical majority in his favour.7.      It is important when considering the opinions expressed at these various meetings to bear in mind the position of the Regent Tshekedi.    In acceptingSeretse and his European wife the tribe were stronglyinfluenced by the prospect of ridding themselves of tshekedi.  -He had ruled the Bamangwato during thepast twenty-three years.   His rule was firm andenlightened, but in recent years had become increasingly unpopular.    At the first tribal meeting in November 1948, when the tribe were not yet aware that Seretse would not in any circumstances give up his white wife, there was almost unanimouscondemnation of the marriage. . The subsequentmeetings showed the increasing fear felt by the tribethat Tshekedi would displace Seretse and become their permanent Chief and a determination to avoid this atany cost.    Consequently when the tribe at their third meeting in June 1949 were called on by Seretseto decide whether they would have him as Chief withhis European wife, they declared decisively in hisfavour.8.      The immediate sequel to the June meeting was an announcement by Tshekedi of his intention toleave the Reserve, which he proceeded to do,

accompanied &quot;by a number of his supportersincluding five out of eight of the &quot;ChiefsRepresentatives&quot;, i.e.  the leading nativesappointed to preside over the administrativedistricts of the Reserve.   He has taken upresidence in the Bakwena Reserve.    He issued adeclaration asserting that the recognised lawand customs of the tribe had been violated, andchallenging the validity of the kgotla&apos;decision.    He asked that a judicial enquiry shouldbe held to advise on whether Seretse should berecognised and if so what would be the positionof his wife and children.    It should be notedthat Tshekedi and his supporters have nevercalled in question Seretse&apos;s claims to the succession as the heir of Sekgoma; what they haveobjected to is Seretse&apos;s marriage to a white womanand his suitability while so married to hold the chieftainship.9.      In view of the difficulties which had arisenthe High Commissioner found it necessary inJuly 1949 to recommend the appointment of a judicial enquiry into the question of the recognition of Seretse.    The enquiry was dulyset up under the Bechuanaland ProtectorateNative Administration Proclamation of 1943-This Proclamation provides that on the occurrence of a vacancy in a Chieftainship the successor shall be designated by the tribeassembled in &quot;kgotla&quot; according to native custom.This designation is, however, subject to

recognition by the High Commissioner and to confirmation by the Secretary of State, at their discretion.    In case of doubt a Judicial Enquiry may beheld to report to the High Commissioner.    The functionsof such an enquiry are advisory, the decision being reserved to the High Commissioner, who is&apos; responsible to the Secretary of State.    Thus in this case HisMajesty&apos;s Government had to take a decision one way orthe other.10.    The report of the Enquiry was received towards theend of last year, and, together with the evidencetendered before the Enquiry, has been given most careful study by His Majesty&apos;s Government in personalconsultation with the High Commissioner, and in the lightof all the information available to them of african opinion in the High Commission Territories and in southern Africa generally.    They have considered whetherthe Report should be published.    The Report and theaccompanying evidence form part, but only a part, of the considerations before them and would therefore of themselves present only an incomplete and thereforeunbalanced picture.    Moreover there are certain arguments advanced and views expressed in the Report which they find unacceptable and with which they could not associate themselves.    Those parts of the Report would, they are convinced, tend to be quoted in such a way as to make them&apos; appear to be expressions of the views of his majesty&apos;s Government, and they would never be able toovertake and counteract the resultant misapprehensions.The document is, in the first instance, a confidentialreport to the High Commissioner and it is entirelywithin the discretion of His Majesty1 s government whether to publish it or not.    For the foregoing reasonsthey do not propose to publish it,    But they wish to

record their appreciation of the evidence and materialassembled by the Enquiry which have assisted them in their consideration of a very difficult and delicate problem.11.    His Majesty&apos;s Government feel however that it shouldbe stated that the Judicial Enquiry advised against the recognition of Seretse, and also advised that because ofhis position as Chief designate it was essential to thepeace and.good order of the Bamangwato Reserve that, ifnot recognised as Chief, he should be required to liveoutside the Bechuanaland Protectorate.    For similar reasonsthey considered that Tshekedi should not be permitted toreturn to the Reserve.12,    After careful study of all the relevant factors HisMajesty&apos;s Government considered that it would be ofadvantage to invite Seretse to London and discuss thematter with him before arriving at a decision.    Knowledgewhether he would be prepared to renounce his claimvoluntarily was one factor on which they required evidence from personal interview before deciding what their finalruling should be.13.    No assurance was given to Seretse or to hisrepresentatives that if he came to London no restrictionwould thereafter be placed on his movements.    statements which have been made to the contrary can be categoricallydenied.    In   view of her concern in the issue the invitationwas also extended to Mrs. Seretse Khama but was not acceptedby her.    In a series of meetings with Seretse in London itwas explained to him, as Parliament was informed on the 8thMarch, that His Majesty&apos;s Government viewed with grave concern the danger which recognition would cause to the unity and well-being of the tribe and the administrationof the Protectorate; that in this matter they had to take into account not only their paramount responsibility for good government in the Protectorate, but also all thecircumstances known to them; and that in all the

circumstances - the best solution in their view would be for him voluntarily to relinquish his claim to the succession.14,       As Seretse was unable to accept this viewHis Majesty&apos;s Government thereupon took their decision and announced it in Parliament on the 8thMarch.     It was to this effect:    in present pircum-stances the High Commissioner must he instructed to withhold recognition, of Seretse as Chief, andrecognition must he withheld for a period of years.This period must he of auoh length as experience shows to he necessary for the disappearance of thepresent tendencies to disruption which threaten the unity and well-being of the tribe.      In their view the period required, will certainly not be less than five years, and at the end of it the situation willhe reviewed.     During this time Seretse will he required to reside outside the Protectorate and willhe unable to revisit it unless special permissionshould be given.     A suitable allowance will he offered to him to enable him to provide for himself and his wife while living outside the Protectorate.While the Chieftainship is in suspense Tshekedi, whowill no longer be Regent3 will he required to resideoutside the Bamangwato Reserve and will not he allowed to enter the Reserve unless special permissiondiould be given.15.       His Majesty&apos;s Government are well aware of thevery strong feelings that can he aroused on thesubject of mixed marriages, and they wish it to be clearly understood that they do net regard the issue in any way as or.e of the merits or demerits of suchmarriages.     The marriage assumed importance in this case only because Serstse was in a special positionas a prospective Chief of an African tribe.     What

What His Majesty&apos;s Government were required to decidewas not whether such a marriage was desirable hutwhether the interests of the tribe itself and of theother tribes in the High Commission Territories would best he served by the recognition of Seretse afterthe marriage had taken place.16&quot;,       Nor 1ms the decision of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment been in any way influenced by the existenceof a strong body of   European opinion in southern africa which would favour non-recognition.     In their view the existence of any such body of opinionaffords no ground why they should not decide againstrecognition for quite different reasons which appearto them good and conclusive.17.       The question has been asked why His Majesty&apos;sGovernment did not treat the opinion expressed by thetribal assembly as the governing factor and abide by it.     His Majesty&apos;s Government exercise a widerresponsibility for the well-being and good governmentof the Protectorate as a whole, and of the other high commission Territories.     In particular they have inthis respect a duty in matters of disputedsuccessions that.they must..discharge.     The opinionof the tribal assembly can only he one of the factorscontributing to their decision.18.       The following are the principal reasons whichhave led His Majesty&apos;s Government to their.decision:-(a) They regard as of first importance thedanger of serious disruption in the bamangwato Reserve and in the Protectorate.Signs of this have already appeared in theReserve in the departure of a number of leading tribal functionaries who have joinedTshekedi in voluntary exile.     Among the

seven tribes of the Protectorate outside the bamangwato Reserve opinion is divided;  the two mostnumerous and important tribes are against the marriage,and, if Seretse were now recognised as Chief, theywould he expected to draw away from the Bamangwato.    Inthe past the Bamangwato have suffered much from feudsamong members of their leading families.    The recognitionof Seretse in present circumstances would have givenoccasion for many disputes and would have created many points of uncertainty.   Peaceful administration would accordingly have become increasingly difficult and a process of disintegration would have set in.(b) At the time when Seretse contracted his marriage he expected that it would be unpleasing to his people andwould have grave consequences.    He was entitled tofollow his own wishes as a private individual, butonly if he faced the consequences to him in his publiccapacity.    By contracting the marriage in irresponsiblehaste, without prior consultation and against all theadvice tendered to him by the tribal authorities, Seretseshowed himself to he utterly unmindful of the interestsof his tribe and to be setting his private feelingsabove public duty.    It was necessary therefore forHis Majesty&apos;s Government to consider whether Seretse,who might in different circumstances have made asuitable chief, could be expected to discharge with success the grave responsibilities of the chieftainship.    His conduct raises serious doubtswhether he would retain the support of a tribe whichhas been given to faction feuds and which ismore than likely to question his authority when itis satisfied that Tshekedi will not return.    This isespecially so since, in the circumstances of the bamangwato, with the need for consolidating and

-developing the tribal arrangements, an effectiveChief would be bound to take many unpopulardecisions.    The tendency in this tribe to disputesabout the succession would be aggravated by uncertaintywhether the tribe would accept the rule of the childrenor grandchildren of a mixed marriage.   There isconsiderable danger that, if Seretse were tobecome unpopular, claims would be made that his wifehad never been properly accepted,(c)&apos;   . Among prominent Africans brtth in the High commission territories and in other parts of Southern Africaopinion about recognition or non-recognition is notunanimous.    His Majesty&apos;s Government examined withthe greatest care the evidence given before the judicial enquiry and other expressions of African opinion andwere satisfied that among responsible le Africans therewas a weight of opinion against recognition that could not be ignored.19.     The decision to require Seretse to live outside the protectorate follows from the special circumstances of thecase.    His residence, particularly in the Reserve, or toa possibly less degree, elsewhere in the Protectoratewould be detrimental to the peace and good order of theReserve.    However carefully he refrained from any interference with the administration his presence would undoubtedly be an embarrassment to the authoritiesand would militate against the subsidence of factionfeeling which is essential for the recovery and further development of the Bamangwato tribe.    The development-of the tribe along the lines indicated in paragraph 20below depends on suitable men coming forward to takethe responsibility of office.    This will be moredifficult as Long as Seretse is in the Protectorate,Similar reasons require that Tshekedi, who has now settled

in the Bakwena Reserve, should not reside in the bamangwato Reserve.    Special pemission must be soughtif either of them wishes for special reasons to returnfor a temporary visit.20.     For the immediate future, as han already been announced in Parliament, the District Commissioner willcontinue closely to supervise the administration of the bamangwato Reserve, and will exercise the functions ofthe Native Authority.    This is, however, a purely temporary expedient to meet quite exceptional circum-stances.    Steps will be taken to ensure that theinhabitants of the Reserve are again associated with theconduct of their affairs as soon as practicable, withthe aim of giving fuller scope for popular opinion tomake itself legitimately felt.    Steps will also be takento associate with the administration the allied tribes,who form four-fifths of the population of the Reserve,and to give them a voice in the management of their own affairs.   Responsibility for some of the duties normallyperformed by the Native Authority will for the timebeing be transferred to a small council of leading and suitable persons as soon as they are prepared to come forward and serve in such capacity.    Other duties willbe transferred to the council as soon as it displayscompetence and the interest of peace and good governmentpermit.    Specific instructions have been given thatsuch a council should be formed as soon as possible.21.   . Looking beyond the transitional period, HisMajesty&apos;s Government will also explore every opportunitythat offers to give the Na-cive Administration a more representative character.    This development is fully in accordance with His Majesty &apos;s Government&apos;s

policy ttday of affording the people of the african territories for which they are responsible, a fullervoice and more direct participation in the conductof their own affairs.


</content>
</cab>
