<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/38/0 images: 478-481</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 2ND MARCH,   1950CABINETRETAIL FOOD PRICE increases memorandum by the Minister of Food.The Chancellor of the Exchequer has informed me thathe proposes to recommend a ceiling of  hi C millions on food subsidies for the coming financial year.      This memorandumsets out the  increases in retail food prices which I recommend,on the basis of my Department&apos;s present estimate of ourtrading during the coming financial year, to enable us tokeep within that ceiling.2. The subsidy ceiling for the current financial year was fixed at  h65 millions.      Thanks mainly to a fall inprocurement costs the actual subsidy total, will be of theorder of  hh1 millions.3&apos; In his statement in the House of Commons on 2hthOctober, the Prime Minister said that there would be no increase in the subsidies on ordinary food to cover the elimination of the&apos; subsidy on feedingstuffs.      I am assumingthis means that the recoupment to farmers, which will,  inaccordance with the latest decision of Ministers, amount toi&apos;A 2^ millions, must be passed on to consumers.h. The consumption of subsidised foodstuffs will be greater in 1950/51  than it was in 1949/50,  and the naturaleffect  of this, will be an increase in the subsidy total.      but although we are still pressed to increase some prices to over-seas suppliers because of devaluation, my Department hope tobe able to resist this pressure without loss of supplies.      Wehave therefore eliminated from our estimates some of the pro-vision included under certain heads to defray additionalprocurement costs which, we now hope, will not arise.      Themost noticeable example is in relation to meat supplies fromthe Argentine.5. Given trading operations of the sise we undertake,it is obviously difficult to make precise estimates.      But myDepartment calculate that they should succeed in keepingwithin a subsidy ceiling of  i+IO millions if retail prices areraised now to produce  18-20 millions in a full year (including,of course,  12^ millions recoupment to farmers).6, Thus,  I recommend price increases which,  owing tothe time factor, will -produce rather less than  18 millions in the financial year 1950/51.7. There are, of course,  numerous alternative selectionsof price increases which could be made to yield  18 millions,which I will not attempt to examine in this paper.8. I recommend that we should secure the  18 millionsby making increases in the retail price of two commodities -butter and bacon.      I propose that the price of butter shouldbe increased by L\.a a lb.   and that of bacon by an average of2d a lb.      The earliest dates by which these increases could-1-(THIS DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT)SECRET7 c)0. P. (50) k6 COPY HO. Qnfs

be made effective would be 23rd April for butter and probably18th May for bacon.      An increase of Ad in the price of butterwould produce about  12.7 millions in a full year and theproposed increase in the average price of bacon about  bmillions:    these amounts would not,- of course, be fully realised in 1950/51  owing to the fact that the price increases would not coincide with the beginning of the financial year.9. The butter increase would involve a movement of . AS inthe Gost of Living Index (all items)  and that of bacon .18,making a total of .66.      The cost per ration book of the butterincrease would be approximately 1d per week and that of the bacon increase approximately -g-d per week.10. I recommend that the price, increase should be concen-t rated on butter and bacon for the following reasons: -(a) BUTTERButter has a big effect on the Index, and has alwaysbeen more heavily subsidised than any other commodity.      the retail price is now 1/6d per lb.   and the subsidy is 1/hd.Butter is thus under-priced compared with margarine, which hasa present selling price of 1Od per lb. with a relatively low- subsidy of only Ad.      With an increase of Ad a lb.   the retail price of butter will become 1/1Od - i.e.  a differential of 1/-over the subsidised price of margarine compared with thepresent differential of 8a.      This change raises the questionwhether we ought to alter the present arrangements for the interchange of butter and margarine within the total fatsration, but I shall go into that in the light of the decision reached on my present proposals.It is expected that with a differential of 1/- a lb.there would be no substantial swing of demand from butter tomargarine.      In any event margarine supplies are not being fully taken up by the public at present, so that some increased demand for margarine would not cause any embarrassment,(b) BACONBacon sells at a range of prices from 1/8d to 2/7d per lb..   and averaging 2/3&amp; a lb.,  and there is a relatively highunit subsid.y of just over 1/-.      I am arranging for my Depart-ment to examine how far it would be possible to load theincrease on the dearer cuts:    if this proves&apos;possible I shall,of coarse, make the position clear in any public announcement.Although we have always known that the present ration of 5 02s.would have to be reduced in the near future, bacon supplies arelikely to be greater this year than lost and an increased price would in effect represent the cost of increased consumption.Bacon is largely an imported commodity,  some of which comes from dollar sources.      An increase in the price of home supplies could be justified by the increased price which v/illbe paid to producers as a result of the current price  review.11. My scientific advisers see no objection to the pro-posed price increases from the standpoint of nutrition.12. I therefore ask my colleagues to agree to increases of hd a lb.  in the retail price of butter and 2d a lb.   in theaverage retail price of bacon, to take effect from the datesmentioned in paragraph. 8 above.13- There is a case for announcing these changes singly,but I feel that it would be better to announce them togetherbefore the House rises for the Easter Recess.Ministry of Food,  S.W.1, M*w&quot;22ND MARCH,  1950.


</content>
</cab>
