<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/24/12 images: 156-161</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.)- MOST SECRET -TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested thai special care may betaken toensure the secrecy of this document.COPY No.W.M. (41) 126th CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 2.Confidential Annex.(10th December, 1941, 6.0 p.m.)THE    PAR EAST.(previous reference:W.M,(41) 125 th conclusions,minute e 1.)China.The Position ofthe U.S.S.R.(preventive^religious reference:W.M.(41) 124 th conclusions ,Minute 3.)Supply of aircraft to singapore.MINISTER saidAtlanticnot haveTHE PRIMEwas now moving herEven so, she wouldocean as Japan.    For the moment we could not sendmore ships to the Pacific, and we should develop a different kind of warfarewere available;that the United StatesFleet to the Pacific,as strong a Fleet in thatenchave tountil more shipsSIR EARLE PAGE said, that Australia was anxious that the best possible use should be made of theforces available to us .   He suggested that it mightbe possible, by the use.of aircraft and submarines,to keep the Japanese out of the Indian Ocean.He   added   that if we   could   give   help to China to continue in the war^ this might well be one of the determining fa.ctors.   He suggested that russia, might be able to give material aid. to Chinaand. thus tide over the immediate position.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had little doubt-that Russia would continue to give aid to China.SIR EARLE PAGE then suggested, that a specialappeal should be ma.de to M. &quot;Stalin that Russia should come into the war against Japan.   He referred to theuse which might be made of shore-based aircraft inthe neighbourhood of Vladivostok against the Japanesemainland, and to the valuable help which could beobtained, from the large number of submarines which russia. possessed in Par Eastern waters.THE PRIME MINISTER said that, in view of the enormous service which Russia was giving to us byhammering the German Army on her Western front, he did not wish to ask Russia, to declare war on Japan.To do so would make it    impossible for Russia tobring Divisions from Siberia which might be ofincalculable value on her Western front.    It wasoerhaos relevant that, in view of the changed situation, he haa had to telegraph to the foreign secretary that ho could not now offer the russians to make 10 squadrons available for service on theirSouthern front.    It was, of course, open to theUnited States, if they wished^ to urge Russia todeclar war on Japan.SIR K.RLE PAGE referred to the difficulty of getting aircraft from this country to Singapore,Provided sufficient machine tools were made available,Australia could increase her production, to 40Beaufort bombers a month,

THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR AIR said that theAir Ministry were in full agreement with this,suggestion, which was now being explored by. theAir Ministry and the Ministry of Aircraft ProductionIt was not merely a question of machine tools, but of the materials required to break down certainbottlenecks.SIR EARTJ3 PAGE then referred to the two alternative air routes across the Pacific.   Theformer route could now no longer be used.    It was important, therefore, to maintain the southernroute via Canton Island and Fiji.THE PRIME MINISTER said that this matter was already under consideration, and that due regardwould be paid to it.




</content>
</cab>
