<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/8/42 images: 468-489</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY^S GOVERNMENTSECRET.W.P. (40) 212(Also Paper No. C.O.S. (40) 483)June 21, 1940CopyNo. 26TO BS KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 42)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 12 noon June 13th to12 noon June 20th,1940[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War Room.
NAVAL SITUATION.General Review.THE outstanding event of the week has been the collapse of french resistance and the extension of the German occupation to the entire northerncoast of France, necessitating the withdrawal of the remainder of the B.E.F.U-boat activity in the Western Approaches has been intensified, and therehas been some activity by German M.T.Bs. in the English Channel.Our merchant shipping losses in convoy have been exceptionally heavy.An important convoy of Australian and New Zealand troops has arrived inthe United Kingdom.We have achieved some successes against Italian U-boats in the Mediter-ranean and Red Sea areas.Northern Waters.2. Thirty-seven survivors from H.M.S. Glorious and H.M.S. Acasta were landed at the Faroes by the Norwegian S.S. Borgund on the 14th June. they state that H.M.S. Glorious encountered two German cruisers one 8 inchand one 6 inch (not two battle cruisers as stated by the Germans) about200 miles to the westward of Vest Fjord at 1600, 8th June. The Germansopened fire at 20,000 yards range. H.M.S. Glorious was hit by the third salvo,which prevented her aircraft flying off; she was outranged throughout the action and sank at 1730. H.M.S. Ardent attacked and was sunk. H.M.S. Acasta laid asmoke screen, and when H.M.S. Glorious sank she attacked the cruisers for thesecond time with torpedoes, which it is believed obtained one hit. H.M.S. A castawas sunk during this attack.3. On the 14th June R.A.F. reconnaissance of Trondheim showed that1 battle cruiser and 3 destroyers were present, and further reconnaissance on the15th showed the battle cruiser, 1 cruiser beached and 2 destroyers. raids on these ships were attempted by the R.A.F. on the 15th and 17th, but owing tobad weather aircraft had to return.Air reconnaissance of Stavanger on the 13th showed 16 merchant ships in neighbouring fjords, and 2 destroyers and 2 merchant ships at Stadlandet. the weather has been unsuitable for further reconnaissances.4. ELM. Armed Merchant Cruiser Andania was torpedoed at 2330/15thS.E. of Iceland and sank at 0700/16th.The A/S. trawler Juniper, which left Narvik on the 6th June with theS.S. Oil Pioneer, is presumed to have been sunk at the same time.ELM. Submarine Tetrach reports sinking an escorted south-bound enemytransport off the Lister Light on the 16th.The last convoy of store ships from the Narvik area has safely arrived inthe Clyde.1,000 Canadian troops have arrived at Rejkjavik, Iceland, from Halifaxin the S.S. Empress of Australia.Home Waters.French Coast.5. Plans to evacuate the whole of the B.E.F., amounting to 140,000 troops,were made on the 15th, and the operation was commenced on the 17th fromCherbourg, St. Malo, Brest, St. Nazaire and La Pallice. By noon the same day a total of 33,790 troops had been landed in England. The total numbersevacuated are given in the military section of this resume.Evacuation was not seriously interfered with by enemy action, but St. Nazairewas continually bombed on the 17th and the troopship Lancastria was sunk.The troops on board were transferred to the S.S. Oronsay, which was also bombed and hit but was able to proceed. The French S.S. Champlain (28,124 tons)which was outside the harbour and not taking part in the evacuation wasalso sunk.The evacuation of St. Malo, Cherbourg and St. Nazaire and demolitions atthe two former places were completed on the 18th.
Brest was evacuated by 1230 on the 19th, some Polish troops being takenoff. The French demolitions were effective, and all French warships left withthe exception of 2 submarines, which were scuttled.In the Gironde area H.M.S. A rethusa left Le Verdon on the 19th with british personnel, and H.M.S. Galatea is to relieve her.H.M.S. Beagle is at Bordeaux with a demolition party, and H.M.S. Berkeleyis at Arcachon for the British Ambassador and Staff.French Fleet.6. All French naval ships which could steam have left Brest, St. Nazaire andCherbourg for either British ports or Dakar and Casablanca.The new battleship Richelieu sailed for Dakar on the 18th.The French Admiral of the Quest Command in the destroyer Le Hardi, withthe new battleship Jean Bart and 2 destroyers, sailed for Casablanca on the 19th.The battleship Paris, 1 destroyer and 1 submarine and some small craftarrived at Plymouth on the 19th.The battleship Courbet and 2 destroyers are patrolling in the Channel offPortsmouth, and various small craft arrived there and at Falmouth.The remainder of the French fleet are operating normally from their bases.Other Operations in Home Waters.7. Enemy M.T.Bs. were attacked by Coastal Command aircraft off the Hookof Holland on the 16th without result, and on the 17th 6 enemy destroyers were also attacked off Norderney, one hit being claimed.H.M. Ships Vesper and Vivacious were in action with 2 or 3 enemy M.T.Bs. at0230/18th off Dungeness. H.M.S. Vesper was missed by a torpedo, and the enemyescaped after being chased to the southward.The S.S. Roseburn wa.s shelled and torpedoed by enemy M.T.Bs. offDungeness, and beached.The Fleet Air Arm attacked the docks and M.T.Bs. at Ymuiden on the 19th.The Australian troop convoy of 16,500 troops arrived in the Clyde on the16th, and the 5th Canadian troop convoy at Liverpool on the 20th.Mediterranean.8. During a sweep by the Mediterranean Fleet H.M.S. Gloucester and H.M.S.Liverpool engaged some enemy small craft, probably minesweepers, off Tobruk,and the shore batteries were in action for about 10 minutes. The Italian com-rrmnique admitted the loss of 1 minesweeper.On the 12th/ 13th a French naval force from Toulon bombarded objectivesat Genoa.On the 14th Fleet Air Ann aircraft from Hyeres bombed objectives at Genoa,and hits on seaplane base, power station and Ansaldo&apos;s Works were observed.Malta was raided during the week, and H.M.S. Diamond on patrol was bombed on the 13th and the 18th without success.Four enemy light craft were reported at sea N.E. of Cyprus at 1200/17th, and naval forces were sent to intercept, but to date no report has been received.H.M. Submarine Grampus is reported overdue.Enemy Attack on Seaborne Trade.9. Eight British ships, totalling 73,395 tons, 1 French ship (theS.S. Champlain) of 28,124 tons, and 13 ships of other nations totalling59,053 tons, making a grand total of 160,572 tons, have been sunk. Details aregiven in Appendix I.Protection of Seaborne Trade.10. A total of 776 ships, including 110 allied and 42 neutral ships, were convoyed during the week, of which 6 ships in 3 convoys were lost by U-boataction. All 3 convoys had only one&apos; vessel escorting, there being an acute shortageof A/S vessels, due to the evacuation of the B.E.F. in progress and the necessityfor concentrating light forces in the North Sea.Eleven Armed Merchant Cruisers, 13 Destroyers, 18 sloops and corvetteswere employed on escort duties.[21429] b      .&apos;&quot;
Anti-Submarine Operations.11. U-Boats have been very active during the week, as many as 11 beingbelieved to be operating in waters other than the Mediterranean, mainly theWestern Approaches. . .Six attacks on U-boats have been carried out in Home Waters, 4 by aircraft which are considered promising.In the Mediterranean 3 attacks on Italian U-Boats were^ carried out byH.M. Australian destroyers Stuart and Voyager and HM.S. Diamond, and areali considered successful. There was also a promising attack by an aircraft60&apos; west of Alexandria.On the 19th the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies, reported that an ItalianU-Boat had been captured off Aden.A U-Boat was reported by R.A.F. aircraft 7 miles West of Reykjavik,Iceland, at 1830/16th, and was subsequently searched for by destroyers without success.Enemy Minelaying and Allied Minesweeping.12. Enemy aircraft have continued their activities during the week12th June to 19th June, mainly between the North Foreland and Portland. mines have been seen to drop off Portland, Weymouth Bay, Poole, Portsmouth, Doverand in the Downs. The ports and channels, however, have not been closed for more than a few hours at a time. Owing to the advance of the German forcesin France it has been necessary to send ll trawlers to western Channel portsat the expense of ports on the East Coast. The Downs channel was sweptsuccessfully by a pair of trawlers on passage. When the evacuation of all our troops and material from France has been completed, it should be possible toredistribute the LL trawlers again.Casualties include 2 minesweeping vessels. The skid-towing drifter OceanSunlight, degaussed, was mined off Newhaven in thick weather on the 13th June;the Oropesa trawler Myrtle, degaussed, was mined in the Princes Channel onthe 14th June.   Both these vessels were mined in comparatively shallow water.LL Sweeps have exploded 5 mines during the week under review, skids haveexploded 4, and the magnet sweep 1. A mine having been located oh5 Poole,divers went down and removed a detonator, but the mine exploded while itwas being towed ashore. The total number of magnetic mines dealt with nownumbers 275.13. Cherbourg, Brest, La Rochelle and the Rivers Loire and Gironde, have all been visited by enemy mine-laying aircraft this week. These ports have allusually been re-opened within a few hours, and in some cases have not been closed at all to degaussed ships. British LL trawlers have been employed atthe French ports, though the French have assisted with various kinds of magneticsweeps. In view of the probable cessation of hostilities in France, instructions have been given that every effort should be made to obtain or destroy everythingrelating to the French LL sweeps, including the specifications.The dangerous area which had been declared south-east of FlamboroughHead has now been cancelled. Twenty-four mines were swept in this area. Onthe 13th June 5 contact mines and 1 explosive sweep cutter were swept about14 miles north-east of the North Goodwin Light Vessel. The total of contactmines dealt with is now 419.Mediterranean.14. Enemy mines are reported to have been laid in the Mediterranean about20 miles north of Alexandria, and in the approaches to Tobruk and Derna in libya.   Two cruisers cut mines with their paravanes while bombarding Tobruk.There is evidence that German magnetic mines are being supplied to Italyand instructions in their use being given at Taranto.New Zealand.15. The loss of the British liner S.S. Niagara on the 18th June 60 miles north of Auckland, New Zealand, has disclosed a new minefield, probably laid
by the ship responsible for the mines on the Agulhas Bank and those suspectedoil Durban. Since the loss of the S.S. Niagara a mine has been swept three miles north of her position.British Minelaying.16. Considerable additions have been made off the East Coast Barrier in theperiod under review. On the 13th June H.M.S. Teviot Bank, H.M.S. Intrepid,H.M.S. Plover laid 400 mines, and on the 16th the same ships, with theaddition of H.M.S. Express, laid a further 450. On the 19th H.M.S. Teviot Bankadded 340 more. H.M.S/M. Narwhal laid 50 off Haugesund on the 12th, and h.M.S/M. Porpoise 50 off Ramsoe Fjord on the 14th. Minelaying by aircraftoff German ports proceeded intermittently during the week. In theMediterranean H.M.S/M. Grampus laid 50 mines off Augusta on the 13th June,and H.M.S/M. Rorqual laid 50 off Brindisi on the 16th June.Enemy Merchant Shipping.German.17. The S.S. Barenfels (7,569 tons) was reported on the 11th June to havebeen raised at Bergen. This ship had not previously been identified as havingbeen sunk, but she may have been the ammunition ship which was sunk in theraids on the 9th and 10th April.A report has come from Cadiz that a German ship loaded gas oil fuel and stores on the 10th June. There are four German merchant ships at Cadiz, ofwhich only one, the Thalia (1,122 tons), has shown any activity since the warbegan.Reports have been received that five German ships, which had been taking-refuge at Trieste, were requisitioned by the Italian Government, immediatelyprevious to Italy&apos;s entry into the war. These ships are the S.S. Frienfels(7,563 tons), S.S. Reiehenfels (7,744 tons), S.S. Wachtfels (8,467 tons), S.S. Ankara(4,768 tons) and S.S. Maritza (2,910 tons). The two last have been previouslyemployed carrying bauxite from Yugoslavia to Trieste, and on the 18th June theS.S. Maritza is reported to have arrived at Sibenik for more bauxite for Germany.The S.S. Arauca (4,400 tons), which is at Port Everglades in Florida, was reported on the 10th June to have received 500 tons of oil fuel.Italian.18. The S.S. Conte Biancamano (23,255 tons) is at Balboa, and proceedingshave been instituted for her arrest by the Asiatic Petroleum Company. TheS.S. Caterina Madre (4,020 tons) at Braila and the S.S. Abbrazzia (3,706 tons)at Galatz are also subject to proceedings by the Asiatic Petroleum Company fordebt. The S.S. Santarosa (3,027 tons), which is at Norfolk, Virginia, is said tohave been sequestered for an American debt.Enemy Naval Intelligence.German.19. On the 17th June a cruiser of the nurnberg class and four small craft were reported by aircraft west of Narvik.On the night of the 17th/18th June a large enemy ship was reported betweenCuxhaven and Heligoland. It is possible that it may have been the admiral Seheer undergoing trials.Italian.20. It is believed that no major changes have been made in the Italian FleetDispositions since the outbreak of war, except that it is reported that a ThirdSquadron known as the &quot; Special Squadron &quot; has been formed, and this is ableto be based on Augusta and Messina. It is thought that this Third Squadronconsists of the cruisers Trento,Bande Nere,Luigi Cadona,with probably some destroyers or torpedo boats.[21429] b 2
Italian Submarines.21. The Italian submarine attacked by H.M.S. Watchman on the 12th june was damaged and has taken refuge in Ceuta, where she still remains. Anotheris known to have passed the Straits of Gibraltar westwards, but her subsequentactivities are unknown. The chief evidences of submarine activity have comefrom the area south of Crete and eastwards towards Alexandria.U.S.S.R.22. There has been considerable activity of the Soviet Baltic Fleet inconnection with the full occupation of Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia. Fromthe 6th June onwards there were indications of a concentration of Soviet naval forces and Air Forces from Sventjoe, on the East Prussian-Lithuanian frontier,to the Gulf of Finland, and minelayers proceeded to sea fully loaded.Destroyers visited &quot;Windau (Ventspils) about the 10th June, and by the15th June a Soviet Naval patrol was established in the Gulf of Riga. A despatchvessel arrived at the mouth of the Dwina on the 18th, and the flotilla leaderMinsk arrived at Riga on the 19th June.The battleship Octyabrskya Revolutsiya arrived at Tallinn on the 17th Juneaccompanied by destroyers.It is reported that the Russians are now occupying the remaining islands offTallinn, i.e., Aegna and Karl Islands. Maissaar is already occupied. A largenumber of additional aerodromes are being established, and Russia undoubtedlyhas air and naval superiority in the Baltic.MILITARY SITUATION.Western Front.qt mL ^he evacuation of the B.E.F. from the ports of Brest, Cherbourg,St Malo, St. Nazaire and La Pallice has been completed.   The total numbers ofJLKT and sto^esnevacuated to the United Kingdom up to midnightthe 19th /20th June are as follows :  8Personnel Fit          .................. 109,596Casualties         ............... 1,909Guns   .........      .....,....... 310Vehicles         ...      ...      ...       -..      .-- 2,278Tons.Ammunition   ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 150Stores...................... 193Allied Armies ...       ...      ...      ...       ... 78724. The period covered by this commentary has witnessed the decisivesuccess of the German attacks across the Somme and Aisne. The main Germanthrust east of Rheims, after reaching the Marne at Chalons, swung eastward andsouth-eastwards and reached Verdun and Dijon. The whole rear of the maginot line was thus exposed to further enemy advances into Lorraine and Alsace, andthese continue.Other German forces struck south-west from the Marne at Chateau-Thierryto cut off Paris from the rear. This move, combined with strong enemy pressurenorth of Paris, led to the decision not to defend the French capital. On theSeine the German advance was at first slower, but armoured and motorisedcolumns were used to overrun Normandy and Brittany. The next phase of theGerman offensive carried them forward from the Seine to the line of the Loire.On the 17th June Marshal Petain requested the Germans to inform him ofthe terms for an armistice.Mediterranean and Middle East.25. There has been practically no information from Italy concerningoperations, military activity or internal affairs.
No confirmation has been received of the presence of Italian troops inGermany or on the Western Front. One source has, however, suggested thepossibility of German formations being moved through Italy to Africa. Whenthe situation in France has been settled German domination is likely to comepiore and more into the open and Italy, inspired and aided by Germany, mayundertake more active offensive operations.26. The situation in Egypt may be regarded as satisfactory. Over 85 percent. Italian suspects have been secured. In the Western Desert our forcescaptured the forts of Capuzzo and Madalena and took as prisoners eight officersand two hundred other ranks. In the same area 12 tanks, 6 guns and 7 lorrieswere captured from the Italians, who are reported as demoralised by our attack.There were no British casualties, but about 50 Italians were killed and wounded,and over 200 taken prisoner. Middle East air operations are reported in laterparagraphs.The Balkan States.27. In Roumania, Gestapo cells are reported to have been set up nearBucharest, in the oil district at Ploesti, and at four ports on the Danube. Sincethe beginning of May more than one report has been received from Hungary ofthe presence of Hungarian Staff Officers, troops and police in South Poland, the protectorate, and Slovakia.U.S.S.R.28. All reports received during the w&quot;eek tend to confirm the movement of soviet troops towards their Western frontiers. The fact that the Soviet union is becoming increasingly nervous as a result of German successes in the West wasstrikingly evidenced by the sudden ultimatum presented to Lithuania, and the subsequent occupation by large forces of additional bases in that country, Latviaand Estonia. There are definite indications that the Soviet move into the baltic states was undertaken by Moscow without prior consultation with the GermanGovernment.Far East.29. After the successful conclusion of the Ichang operation, the next step in the Japanese campaign in China is directed against China&apos;s munition supplyroutes. An operation to cut the channel of communication between the HongKong Leased Territory and Chinese guerilla forces in the East River district (east of Canton) is probable in the near future. While the present Japanese Govern-ment continues to exercise a moderating influence, the events of the last few days in France have given considerable encouragement to extremist military circles.AIR SITUATION.General Review.30. During the early part of the week both air forces were concentrating on operations on the Western Front, but with the collapse of French resistancestrategical attacks were resumed. Bomber Command carried out extensive attacks on communications and industrial targets in Germany, and the German air forcemade two raids in considerable force, which marked the beginning of attacks on industry in this country. Attacks on Italy were continued, but our aircraft and servicing units have now been withdrawn from Southern France. coastal command flew a large number of armed reconnaissances off the Norwegian and dutch coasts, and a number of attacks were made an enemy shipping. Fivepromising attacks were made on submarines. Our air operations in the middle east continue to be considerably more successful than those of the enemy.Air Defence of Great Britain.31. This week has been marked by the initiation of German air attacks against industry in this country, though so far damage and casualties have not
been heavy considering the number of aircraft employed. During the week 380fighter sorties were flown over England : 4 fighters were lost and 15 enemy bombersprobably destroyed.32. In the early part of the week there was little enemy activity apartfrom meteorological and reconnaissance fights, down Channel and toward the orkneys and Shetlands. Considerable minelaying was reported on the night ofthe 16th-7th June, and a ship was reported&quot; to have been bombed off the isle of Wight.33. On the 18th-19th June about 120 enemy bombers were engaged onwidespread night raids over England. Objectives included the oil wharves atCanvey Islands, Scunthorpe iron works and various aerodromes in the eastern counties. Substantial damage was done to the oil wharves, and electrical cablesand railway lines were damaged in some areas. One bomb fell on houses nearCambridge and killed several civilians. T+ in bT^rrrl that nine rf th&quot; i emy_      wA-re hTrwrvh.fi drvlTTri HT       fimk^g four of/wfeidh -were lost.34. On tihe 19th-20th Julie there was a second raid by about 150 aircraft over a considerably wider area, evidently concentrated on industrial targets.Bombs were dropped in districts as far north as Durham and as far west asCardiff and Taunton. The LCI. Works at Billingham were considerably damaged by blast, but it is stated that production is not affected. Attacks were also made on the South Durham Steel Works at Stockton, where the gasometer and power mains were damaged, and on the armament works at Marchwood, Southamp-ton, where a magazine was set on fire, and on the docks at Cardiff, where a ship was sunk. Casualties do not appear to have been heavy, and from reportsso far received, eight persons were killed and sixty injured. Tour raiders were shot down by fighters and there are unconfirmed reports that a further two were destroyed, one of which was by anti-aircraft fire.Western Front.35. Thirty-eight offensive patrols and bomber escorts were flown by our fighters, involving 496 sorties. These patrols have swept the northern coast ofFrance in search of enemy bombers, and have escorted our own day-bombing raids.Fighting has not on the whole been intensive. Enemy casualties amount to threeconfirmed and three unconfirmed.  Three of our own fighters have-been lost.36. In the early part of the week practically the entire effort of bomber command was directed against the German army and its communications inNorthern France. In spite of unfavourable weather the medium bombersoperating by day on the 13th and 14th June attacked the Seine crossings belowParis, troops on the move near the Seine and near Evereux, and the aerodrome at Merville, where many enemy aircraft were seen on the ground; a number ofthese are believed to have been damaged. On the night of the 13th-14th Juneour heavy bombers were intensely active in the areas behind the German linesfrom Rouen to Rheims; 163 aircraft were engaged, and a very large number of high explosives and incendiary bombs were dropped on road and rail communica-tions. These raids were repeated by twenty-one aircraft on the night of the14th-15th June. Weather conditions still further deteriorated on the 15th june and both day and night bombing operations were impossible until the night ofthe 17th June. On the afternoon of the 18th June six Blenheims attackedcolumns of motorised troops and motor-cyclists advancing on Cherbourg. Thehead of one column was bombed and machine-gunned, and four or five motor vehicles were overturned; many hits were seen on the roads. On the 19th Junethirty Blenheims attacked aerodromes at Rouen and Amiens, at which enemy aircraft were believed to be concentrating for night raids on England; extensive damage was done to runways, hangars and parked aircraft. The attack onRouen was successfully repeated by twelve Blenheims on the 20th June.37. During the week Bomber Command carried out 156 day and 163 nightsorties against enemy troops and communications on the Western Front; tenaircraft were lost.38. The bomber squadrons of the Advanced Air Striking Force were with--drawn from France on the 15th June, leaving five squadrons of fighters, two toprotect Cherbourg and three the Nantes area.  By the evening of the 19th June.
all fighter squadrons had been withdrawn, three to this country and two to theChannel Islands. Reports of activities during the latter part of the week are notyet complete, but information it was not possible to include last week is now available. On the 11th June there were four Blenheim reconnaissances andtwenty-four day-bombing sorties by Battles against the bridges of the lowerSeine: a bridge at Pontpoint and a pontoon bridge at Courcelles were destroyed.All our aircraft returned safely, and claim the destruction of one enemy fighter.On the same day forty-nine fighter sorties were flown, and five enemy bombers and one Heinkel 113 fighter were shot down without loss. During the following night fifteen Battles raided Les Andelys; little anti-aircraft fire was encountered,but the enemy made observation difficult by firing what appeared to be parachuteflares from the ground. On the 13th June there were seventy-eight Battle sorties and one reconnaissance. Enemy columns were attacked near Evreux and a largetransport park in the Foret de Gault was bombed against intense fighter and anti-aircraft opposition.Attacks on Germany.39. Night operations against objectives in Germany have continued, subjectto some interruption by unfavourable weather; 416 sorties were flown and nineaircraft lost. Raid Assessment Reports continue to indicate satisfactory results,particularly at Hamburg where aircraft works, factories and shipyards have beenvery extensively damaged. The aircraft erecting works of Blohm and Voss are reported to have been destroyed, and a chemical factory (believed to be that ofGesellschaft fuer Lund&apos;s Eisi/machinen A.G.) was hit, and fires and explosionscontinued all day. The morale of the Rhineland population is said to bedeteriorating.40.   The week&apos;s operations are summarised as follows : June 14th-15th-Marshalling yards in Rhineland at Soest, Hamm, Essen, Koln, Rheydt,Duren and Euskirchen, and 24 Wellingtons bombed military objectives in the region of the Black Forest; fires and explosions were caused over a wide area.June 16th-7th-Weather prevented operations.June 17th-18th-Railway junctions at Wedau, Gelsenkirchen, Fallersleben, Hamm,Coblenz, Koln and Rheydt.Aerodromes at Schiphol, Heide, Wesel, and Barmen.Oil plants and storage at Homburg, Wanne-Eickel, Hamburg and Essen.June 18th-19th-Aerodrome at Barge.Power Station at Hamburg.Munitions factory at Koln.Oil installations at Hamburg, Vastrop, Rauxel, Hanover, Sterkrade and elsewhere.June 19th-20th Aluminium plant at Grevenbriick.Marshalling yards at Duren and Euskirchen.Oil objectives at Hamburg, Wanne-Eickel and elsewhere.41. Eighteen sorties were also flown for minelaying in the Rhine andDanube; the latter were somewhat hampered by bad visibility.Attacks on Italy.42. On the 15th/16th June eight Wellingtons were despatched fromaerodromes in Southern France to bomb Genoa. Heavy local thunderstorms were encountered and only one aircraft bombed the target; several hits were registered.On the following night six aircraft operated with greater success; fires were started at a factory near Milan, and the Ansaldo and Caproni works at Genoawere also hit. The aircraft and servicing units in Southern France have now returned to this country. Reports indicate that our attacks on Italy have beenvery successful and have created a deep impression.
North Sea and Coastal Operations.43. Routine patrols have been own^iy. Coastal Command involving 279sorties; there have been 404 sorties on grpootal patrol^and 122 on convoy escort.There were nine submarine sightings at widely separated points and at leastfour promising attacks, excluding one in the Mediterranean.44. As reported in the Naval Situation, numerous reconnaissances of theNorwegian and Dutch Coasts were carried out by Coastal Command : movements of enemy shipping were extensively reported, and a large number of attacks on ships were made.45. Eight Beauforts and four Hudsons raided Bergen Harbour on the15th June, blew up an ammunition dump on the quay, and did serious damage to wharves and warehouses. Six other Hudsons which attacked Bergen and shipping in convoy off the coast found unfavourable conditions of cloud andwere not able to observe results. Three Hudsons sent to raid shipping nearObrestad failed to return.46. On the 15th and 19th June, a Skua, escorted by two Rocs, didsuccessful photographic reconnaissance of enemy batteries at Boulogne, Calaisand Dunkirk. On the 18th June, Norderney aerodrome was attacked by six Hudsons; the seaplane base at Den Helder was attacked and set on fire bya single Hudson on the 19th June. During the night 19th/20th June, twoHudsons carried out separate attacks on Ijmuiden; hits were observed on the dock in the inner harbour.47. There were 24 minelaying sorties by Bomber Command during the week,and on the 18th/19th June six Albacores laid mines under the control of coastal command, three of thow-huicesHlully&apos;.Middle East and Mediterranean.48. There has been considerable activity in all areas and our air operations have been signally more successful than those of the enemy.49. Egypt. On the 14th June squadrons of Blenheims co-operated in aland attack on three Italian frontier forts, which were bombed and machine-gunned in low attacks. Two enemy aircraft, and possibly a third, were shot down; one of our own is missing. Two squadrons raided El Adem and Gubbion the 16th June and damaged enemy aircraft on the ground; the attack was continued by another squadron during the night the 16th-7th June.Reconnaissances for concentrations of troops and aircraft have been regularlymaintained, and anti-submarine patrols&apos; and escorts have been provided bySunderlands. It is reported that the Italian cruiser San Giorgio, believed tohave been hit during a previous raid, is still aground at Tobruk. The Italianshave on several occasions raided Sollum and Sidi Barrani; casualties have been mainly to Egyptian personnel. On the 18th aircraft dropped pamphlets on mersa matruh, and twelve Italian aircraft attacked Buq Buq; three of these were shot down and one captured intact, together with the pilot, a colonel, who waswounded.50. Sudan and Somaliland. There have been sporadic and not very successful Italian raids on Suakim, the Boma Plateau and Port Sudan; oneWellesley was damaged on the ground at Suakim. Massawa was heavily bombedon the night of the 15th-16th June by five Wellesleys, one of which is missing,and it is believed that petrol supplies there were seriously damaged in a raid on&apos;the 17th June. On the 18th two Gladiators attacked two S. 81&apos;s without result.On the 19th enemy aircraft bombed Zeilah, Berbera and Tugaran in british somali land, but the damage is unknown. On the following day two attacks, byfive and six Blenheims, were made on hangars and the railway station atDiredawa.  Hits were secured on the railway and workshops were set on fire.51. Aden. Assab aerodrome was raided by five of our bombers on the13th June, and a hangar was hit. A reconnaissance of the Red Sea and Eritreaon that day showed a new satellite aerodrome with some 25 aircraft; these were bombed on the following day (the 14th June), and it is believed that sevenwere destroyed. This aerodrome and Macaaca were bombed again on the15th June, and it is believed that one more aircraft was destroyed on the ground
and that a fighter was shot down. Massawa, Assab and Gura were bombed onthe 17th June, and a very successful attack was made on the wireless station atRaheita on the night of the 17th/18th June. A submarine was seen by our fighters 30 miles off Aden, which called for bomber assistance before attacking-the submarine was bombed by a Blenheim as it crash-dived, and was machine-gunned by the fighters; the result is uncertain.52. Kenya. The South African and Southern Rhodesian squadronscontinue to be very active. Raids have been carried out on aerodromes atKismayu, Yavello, Neghelli, on a camp at Mega and on armoured cars and troopsnear Moyale. It is believed that about a dozen enemy aircraft have been destroyed on the ground, two armoured cars have been wrecked and substantial damage done to hangars and to a wireless station. There have been a few enemy raids, inone of which (on the 13th June) bombs dropped by a single aircraft hit and destroyed a store of aviation petrol at Wajir.  Two of our aircraft are missing.53.   Malta.-Enemy raids continue, generally in small numbers, and havea considerable harassing effect, though little material damage has been doneThree Hemkel Ills were identified as taking part in one raid.    Two enemy aircraft are believed to have been brought down by anti-aircraft fire, andGladiators have been useful in harrying the raiders.French Air Force Operations.54. No details of French Air Force operations during the period of thissummary are available.German Air Operations.55. There has been a slight reduction in the general scale of operations during the week, as compared with the level of the past five weeks. On theaverage, about eight of the long-range bomber units were active each day, with about 20 per cent, of their strength; this would mean that there were normallysomething over two hundred long-range bombers engaged. Operations have been mainly directed to support of the offensive in the West, although some bombing of naval units near Tromso is reported on the 13th June. Some units have nowbeen withdrawn from Norway. Toward the end of the week activity was transferred to the ports in the North and West of France, and widespread raids were made on England during the night of the 18th/19th and the 19th/20th June.A considerable part of the Air Force has now been moved to forward aerodromes in Belgium and Northern France.German Air Intelligence.56. There has been a decrease in advanced training during the past week,and aircraft previously employed in schools are now in use for transport purposes.This may, in itself, serve as a kind of advanced training. During the week fromthe 11th to 18th June there were ninety-nine confirmed losses of German aircraft and the total may be put at about 120. This brings the corresponding totalssince the 10th May to 2,137 and 3,205. There continue to be indications thatGermany is not, at present, willing to release any aircraft for export abroad.Difficulty in securing delivery of aircraft promised has been experienced byJugoslavia, Roumania, Bulgaria and Esthonia.57. An analysis of German Air Operations against France since the10th May and further notes on Air Landing tactics are included as Appendix IV.Italian Air Operations.58. Details of Italian air operations have been included in the appropriatesections. Operations by the Italian Air Force have not so far been very persistentor well concerted, though a considerable number of raids have been carried outthroughout the Middle Eastern area. The raids on Malta in particular appearto have been surprisingly ineffective, even theugh eome German bombers have[21429] c
been present as-&quot; stiffen lug.&apos;&apos; There still appears to be a shortage of anti-aircraft guns, possibly because the promised supplies of German guns have notyet materialised. Aerodromes are being defended by machine guns placed onthe top of buildings.Italian Air Intelligence.59. East Africa.-- The strength of the Italian forces at the 16th June isreported to be :  Modern bombers ... ...      ...      ...      ... 57Obsolete bombers ... ...      ...      ...       ... 99Fighters    ...... ............. 43Reconnaissance   ... ...      ...      ...       ... 10If these figures are accurate, they suggest that units are about one-third belowestablishment.There are sesae- indications that the condition of landing grounds has deteriorated as a result of heavy rains. Movable obstacles are being placed on aerodromes, and there seems to be some fear of a British landing from the air.Spain.60. The signs now indicate that Spain may soon pass from a policy ofnon-belligerency to that of actual participation in the war. All civil flying,except on regular air services, has been suspended; the &apos;&apos; Swiss Air &apos;&apos; service between Locarno and Barcelona has been abandoned. Service aircraft are not allowed to take off except with express permission. The Germans are maintainingclandestine wireless stations, obviously with Spanish connivance, in more than one part of Spain.The Spanish Military Mission to Germany, which consisted of sometwenty-seven senior officers, under General Canovas, returned to Spain via Italyon the 13th June.Bulgaria.61. Sixty German bomber pilots and observers are reported to have reachedSofia by civil aircraft on the 1st and 2nd June. A further forty-seven reachedRustchuk on the 9th June, and were taken to Bulgarian aerodromes.
APPENDIX I.Ships attacked by Submarines.Date.	Name and Tonnage.	Nationality.	Cargo.	From 	To-	Nature of Attack.	If in Convoy.	Position.	Fate of Crew and Remarks.June 9 ... June 10 ... June 11 ... June 12 ... June 12 ... June 12 ... June 14 ... June 14 ... June 14 ... June 14 ... June 16 ... June 16 ... June 19 ... June 19 ...	Margareta (1,860 tons) Violando      M. Goulandris (3,598 tons) Mount  Hymet-tus (5,820 tons) Willoivbank (5,014 tons) Barbara Marie ... (4,223 tons) Orkanger (8,029 tons) Mount Myrto ... (5,403 tons) Balmoral Wood (5,834 tons) Italia (9,973 tons) Erik Boye (2,238 tons) Wellington Star (11,400 tons) James Stove   ... (8,215 tons) Baron Loudoun (3,164 tons)&apos; Tudor   ...... (6,607 tons)	Finnish Greek Greek British British Norwegian... Greek British Norwegian... Danish British Norwegian British Norwegian	Iron ore .. Tanker ... Grain and 4 aero-planes Gasolene Grain Eefriger-ated Meat Tanker ... Iron Ore	Rosario	Waterf ord... Manchester Sharpness...	Torpedo ... Torpedo   ... Torpedo   ... Torpedo ... Torpedo ... Torpedo ... Torpedo ... Torpedo -Torpedo ... Torpedo ... Torpedo ... Torpedo ... Torpedo	Not...... Yes... (inSL.34) Yes...... (inSL. 84)&quot; Not...... Not...... Yes...... In Convoy HX 47 Not...... In Convoy HGF 34 In Convoy HGF 34	400 miles N.W. of Spain 250 miles N.W.  of Cape Finisterre 200 miles W.N.W. of Oporto 200   miles   W.   of Cape Finisterre 222 miles W.N.W. of Cape Finisterre 50   miles   N.W.  of Alexandria 85  miles  South of Fastnet 70 miles S.S.W. of Cape Clear 50   miles   S.E.   of C. Clear 245 miles West of Cape Finisterre 21 miles South of Aden 180 miles N.N.W. of Cape Finisterre 180 miles N.N.W. of Cape Finisterre	Sunk.   20 survivors, 5 missing. Sunk.   Survivors landed at Santiago (Spain). Sunk. Master and 12 survivors in 1 lifeboat picked up. 1 lifeboat with 11 men missing. Sunk. Sunk. Sunk. Sunk.   3 survivors only. Abandoned.   This ship was a strag-gler from Convoy HX 47. [ Sunk.   16 survivors picked up by 1    H.M.S. Fowey.   19 missing. * Sunk.    22 survivors picked up by (   H.M.S. Fowey. Sunk. Sunk.   Crew saved. Sunk. Sunk.
Ships mined.Date.June 10June 13June 13June 17June 18Name and tonnage.Nationality.Sonja(1,820 tons)British Inventor(7,101 tons)Abel Tasman(314 tons)Ghamplain(28,124 tons)Niagara...(13,415 tons)SwedishBritishDutchFrenchBritishCargo.From Tanker ..2,000 tonsfuel oil600  tonsbunkeroilSydneyTo-Nature of attack.If in convoy.Auckland ...Not.Mine ortorpedoNot.Ships sunk by Air Attack,June 1June 9June 17Ariadne(2,029 tons)Prins Olav(2,147 tons)Royalty...(101 tons)Dulwich(4,102 tons)Lancastria(16,243 tons)Norwegian...Norwegian...BritishbargeBritishBritish(under Govt.charter)NorwayThorshavnFaroesBombPosition.Fate of Crew and Remarks.Off Bergen, Nor-way5 miles S.W. of st. AlbansHeadIn Poole Har-bourEntrance to LaPallice60 miles north of Auckland,New ZealandSunk.12 lost, 9 survivors.Beached at Portland.Sunk.Sunk.Sunk.Off DunkirkMouth of SeineSt. NazaireReported attacked  and  sunk  with  largenumber of passengers on board.Abandoned.Beached and abandoned on fire.   All crewsaved.Sunk.
2i J 8Number and Tonnage of Mercantile Vessels sunk up to Noon,Wednesday, June 19, 1940.British.By SubmarineMine    ......Surface eraft  ...Aircraft...Other causes and cause unknown allied.By SubmarineMine    .........Aircraft...Other causes and cause unknown ...No.9685134118191721259Tonnage.430,440275,32381,33382,03857,840253      926,974118,47961,024113,1664,418297,087Neutral.By SubmarineMine    ......Surface craft ...Aircraft...Mine or torpedo other causes and cause unknown summarised, the Totals are :-By Submarine  ...Mine......Surface craft aircraft mine or torpedo other    causes    and cause unknown ...No.1017721112002161791573128Tonnage.319,701218,9572,06928,1862,43421,780593,127868,620555,30483,402223,3902,43484,038512    1,817,188APPENDIX III.Additions and Deductions of British Mercantile Sea-going Vessels of500 gross tons and over.From September 3, 1939-June 16, 1940,Additions.Tankers. Other Vessels.Tonnage. No.           Tonnage.57,000 85            519,00019,000 49            249,00083,000 123            370,00011,000 70            132,000New vessels enemy vessels captured transfers from other flags*Other additions ...       ...&quot;(Great Lake vessels converted ocean use)No.7312to273301,289,000* IncludingDanish flag.Total Additions :tanker of 6,000 tons151,000357 vessels of 1,440,000 tons.and 79 other vessels, 165,000 tons, transferred fromLosses by enemy action (i) Sunkf    &quot;......(ii) seized other total lossesDeductions.Tankers.No. Tonnage.22 160,0001 6,0007 21,000Other Vessels.No. Tonnage.182 744,0004 11,00070 227,000256982,00030 187,000Total Deductions : 286 vessels of 1,169,000 tons,f Excluding the following commissioned vessels which, being King&apos;s ships, are not regardedas losses of Mercantile tonnage : 1 tanker of 7,000 tons;9 other vessels of 63,000 tons.Vessels under Construction in United Kingdom on June 15, 1940.tankers other vessels23 vessels of 188,000 gross tons145 vessels of 723,000 gross tons total   ...      ... 168 vessels of 911,000 gross tonsThe average weekly increment of British sea-going ships and tonnage over the 41 weeks wasabout 8-7 ships and 35,100 gross tons, compared with an average weekly loss due to enemy action alone, for the same period, of 5-1 ships and 22,500 gross tons, and an average weekly loss from all causes (including Marine casualties) of 7-0 ships and 28,500 gross tons.[21429]D
German Air Operations in France.It is now possible to distinguish five phases in the German air offensive against France since the 10th May : (1) During the first three days the main attack was on aerodromes and landing grounds. Eighty-one separate landing grounds were attacked,and raids on railway communications and factories were on a com-paratively small scale.(2) During the period of the advance through Belgium and France to theChannel Ports, activities were concentrated primarily on targetsdirectly connected with the operations of the ground forces. Fifty-nineattacks were, however, made on aerodromes, and thirty-seven onfactories.(3) During the evacuation of Dunkirk from the 27th to the 31st May theGerman Air Force concentrated on impeding the escape of the Britishand French Northern armies, and raids elsewhere in France were pratically abandoned.(4) From the 1st to the 4th June, there were heavy raids on communications and factories near Paris, in the Lyons district, and at Marseilles andother points in Southern France.(5) Since the opening of the final offensive, operations have again been concentrated on the support of the ground forces; there have, however,been raids on the remaining Channel ports, the Atlantic ports, and on road and rail communications behind the French armies.It is not yet possible to form any picture of the effects of these raids on theindustrial life of France. There is, however, no doubt that substantial damage was done to communications, in particular to railways and ports. After the initial surprise, the damage to aerodromes and aircraft on the ground was neververy great.German Air Landing Tactics.- Recent experience indicates that German methods of landing from the air in hostile territory are likely to follow somewhat the following pattern. Attackswill probably be preceded by diversion attacks elsewhere, in order to draw offfighter defences; they will take place at dawn and will concentrate on two orthree large aerodromes or landing grounds near some suitable port. enemy fighters will appear first to draw off or beat down fighter opposition. They willbe followed by low-flying bombers and fighters attacking the aerodrome defences and the perimeter of the aerodromes. Three or four companies of parachutetroops may be dropped at points some distance from the aerodrome. It wouldbe for these troops to complete the initial attack on the aerodrome defences; andif this were successful, it would at once be followed by the arrival of large numbersof troop transports landing on the aerodrome at very short intervals, possibly atthe rate of six a minute. From these could be landed troops armed with heavy and light machine-guns, two-inch and three-inch mortars, and possibly three-inch mountain guns and light anti-aircraft guns capable of use as anti-tankweapons. Motor cycles and side-cars might also be landed. At the same time,patrols of fighters in considerable strength would be maintained over each of theaerodomes attacked. The essential point in combating these tactics is to preventthe landing of the troop transport aircraft. The parachutists can act only asshock troops and are not in a position to maintain themselves unless reinforcementsand supplies are forthcoming at once, according to plan.There has been considerable discussion of the possibility of using glidersfor air landings, and gliders with a considerable carrying capacity have been evolved. They are, however, very vulnerable to weather conditions and to attackwhile in the air, and have few advantages over ordinary aircraft, except thatthey can land in a comparatively small area.   It-Js-net^mbabfe-iita^tfeey-wrHbe USed rm a large-Beafe whmWn/rO nrlnqnntn rnpply        frnop.^rryipg marinasis available.
BRITISH   SHIPPING losses due TO ENEMY ACTION.By Aircraft:.N.I.D.. June ?94o.By Mine.By surface raider.By S/m.By cause unknown.

SHIPPING LOSSES BY ENEMY ACTION.BRITISH, ALLIED &amp; NEUTRAL.N,l. P.. June \^4-0.By Aircraft.By Mine.By Surface raider.By S/m.By cause unknown.




</content>
</cab>
