<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/30/4 images: 32-39</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
T0 BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.it i8 requested that special care may betaken to&apos;ensure the secrecy of this documentilMOST SECRET,COPY NO,Wf,MP(42)  48th CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 4oConfidential Annexe(14th April, 1942, 12 Noon)0SUPPLIES TORUSSIA.(previous reference:W.M.(41)124thConclusions,Minute 3)*THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that the Pr:^ne Minister had authorised himto  sound Mre Hopkins   and &apos;Mr.- Harrimanin regard to the procedure proposed for dealing with supplies to Russia after June, 1942, (D,0,(42) 33).In this paper it had been suggested that a Three power conference should be held in Moscow in the near future.The United States representatives had not been attracted by the prospect of another   conference, and thoughtthat, if one was held, we should be strongly pressed toincrease supplies,     They suggested that the right plan-would be that the United States and British authoritiesshould make a quick survey, on the   basis of which theyshould determine what supplies wo could afford to send toRussia;    and that wo shov.ld then toll tho UPS,SPRo what we (the U3S9A, and ourselves) proposed to do*,The Foreign Secretary thought that such a discussion should take place as soon as possible with the UnitedStates representatives in this country.     He gathered thatthey had in mind some increase in supplies of tanks toRussia from the United States.     It had been agreedthat in the meantime neither the United States norourselves should make any approach to the Russianauthorities on this matter.THE MINISTER OF PRODUCTION said that he also had had some discussion on the matter with Mr. Hopkins andMr. Harriman.     He suggested that the best line of approachmight be to consider how many ships wo could send toRussia each month     It might well be that this numberdepended on the   convoy escorts which could bemade available.     If this proved to be the bottle-neck,we should then take the available shipping capacity and see how many tanks and aircraft per month could be sentin the available ships, and what free space would beavailable for other commodities,,     He had already arranged for an inquiry to bo sot on foot, setting out the maximumwhich the British Empire could afford to send to Russiafrom the point of view of shipping (including convoy escorts)and of production the MINISTER OF WAR TRANSPORT said that thoAmerican authorities were now making arrangements to sendlarge numbers of ships to Russia, without prior consulation with us.     Ho understood that they proposedto send 40 a month, which, with 12 of our own, made a totalof 52o.    I.t looked as though the necessary convoy escortswould prove to be the bottle-necko     He explained thatof the 40 ships going from the United States, four-fifthsdid not carry Protocol materials, but foodstuffs and other

commodities which, though no doubt acceptable to theRussians, were not essential imports,,     The quantity of heavy tanks loaded was determined by the very limitedlifting facilities in these ships0THE FIRST SlIiA. LORD said that, on present experience,he thought that 25 ships was the top limit for a convoy onthe North Russian route.     In a few days&apos;  time, however, wewould have much more experience as to the size of convoyswhich we could hope to get- into North Russiac.     he explained that it had been necessary to employ a muchheavier scale of convoy protection on the North Russianroute than had previously been adopted,     and that this had meant a reduction in     strength    of the escorts toconvoys on the North American routeoTwo convoys of 25 ships a month representedprobably the absolute maximum which we could send toRussia,     He would much prefer it if a convoy of 25ships sailed once a month with a stronger- escort .     Thiswould also involve fewer risks to the vessels of the home fleet which were employed in covering the convoys,THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY emphasised theserious losses which were likely to be incurred if we continued the effort to sail convoys to Russia on thepresent scale throughout the summer months,,     There was alsothe risk involved to important units of the Home FleetsIt was pointed out that it was unsatisfactory that weshould be making great efforts to send materials in thesestrongly escorted convoys to North Russia, at considerablerisk, without any real knowledge of the Russian rate ofproduction or of the extent of their needSoWhile it was agreed that this position was verydifficult to defend, it was felt that an approach tothe Russians with a view to obtaining f..figures would lead to a demand for reciprocal disclosure on our part,to which some objection might be raised.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DOMINION AFFAIRS,thought that it might be explained to the Russians that,if we were to tie ourselves down to a definite commit-rnent to send them supplies on a large scale, this would inevitably affect our power to c carry cut. operations inother theatres.   ; Surely wo ought to know whether the supplyof munitions from this country to Russia was of such vitalimportance that its continuance ought to take precedenceover other needs.*THE FOREIGN SECRETARY said that it had been suggested to him that the question of supplies to Russia ought tobe linked with our general Treaty negotiations with RussiaoHe thought that this would make the Russians suspicious *and that this linkage was undesirable*General agreement was expressed with this view0

it after further discussion, the War Cabinet agreed  .as follows: - ..(l) The Minister of Production was invited toarrange for the-completion, and circulation to the War Cabinet, of   a   report ^setting outthe maximum which this country could afford to send to Russia, from the point of view ofavailability of shipping   (including convoy escorts) and of production,.     This report should cover (a) July to December, 1942 and (b)January to June^ 1943*(2) The Minister of Production should arrangefor the views of the Chiefs of Staff, onthe strategical aspect, to be incorporated in the reporte(3) This report should be completedas quicfely as possible, in order that, after consideration by the War Cabinet, the matter could be discussed with the representatives ofthe United States now in this countryeGreat George Street, S.?/.la9




</content>
</cab>
