<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/38/13 images: 132-141</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
to be ke^jjj^rIock&apos;a&quot;nd key it is requwt^ thai 5f,,,ia. care may betaken toonsupa the secrecy of this document.65- MOST SECRETFUTURE OPERA-TIONS .OperationLIFEBELT .(previous reference:W.M.(43)   76 th conclusions .)COPY UpW..M... (43)   R4th COM PLUS TONS.  MINUTE 1 .0on f i d ent ial Ann ex .(10th June, 1943, 5-3 0 p.m.)The War Cabinet met to consider Telegrams Nos .931,932    and 933 from our Ambassador at Lisbon, reportinga recent conversation  with Dr Salazar.    In this conversation, Dr Salag-ar had expressed the vie? that theconclusions reached try London conversations, which hadbean based on   tho promises that Germany could, and mightinvade the Peninsula and.   that Groat Britain was not then strong enough to meet the throat, no longer heldgood.    Sir Ronald Campbell thought that Dr Salazar&apos;sconversation might indicate that he hoped that we wouldmake an appeal to- the Alliance.THE FOREIGN SECRETARY said,    that he thought, thatthe right course was that we should now make a&quot; diplomaticapproach    to Dr Salazar.    Ho thought that,  in order tomake    a sac.cose of the diplomatic approach, we should,have to be prepared to meet Portuguese demands, on&apos;-&quot;certain points on which they would, feel anxiety, namely:-(a)(b)(c)&quot;.7o should have to agree that their ships should join our convoys .We should, have to offer some fightersupport for the defence of the mainlandWo should have to give some kind of under taking in regard, to the future ofthc Portugucse Empire.The Foreign Secretary then read, to the War Cabinettwo telegrams to our Ambassador at Lisbon which had beenprepared on the above lines.THE PRIME MINISTER said   that he was still rathersceptical of   obtaining our requirements by moans of a diplomatic approach unsupported by a threat of force.He agreed, however, that   Sir Ronald. Campbell&apos;s interview with Dr Balazar introduced a now factor, and.he agreed, that a diplomatic approach should be made onthe broad linos suggested by the Foreign Secretary.-The programme   which   he  envisaged was as follows :*(i)   Instructions  should, be sent to Six&quot; Ronald.Campbell as to the lines on which he shouldmake    a diplomatic approach to the portuguese government asking for the facilities which were quired in the Islands .

(ii) Before Sir Ronald Campbell could, act on those instructions, it   would be necessaryto obtain the concurrence of the UnitedStates Government in the course of action -proposed.The Prime   Minister    said that he wouldbo ready to send, a Personal telegram to president Roosevelt on this natter atonce.    In particular,  the President should,he   asked, not to. bring the brazilian government into this matter for the timebeing.(iii)  The main    points which Sir Ronald Campbellshould   make in his approach would, be asfollows(a) We should, make it clear that wo   would return the Islands at the end of the war.,together with the improved facilities which we   should have introduced.:&apos;    We night evenoffer to lease the Islands for the duration of the war, on very beneficial terms .(b) We should offer facilities for    theprotection of Portuguese shipping!e      ,  in convoy .( c) We should    give assurances regarding thefuture of the Portugucsc Co 1 onia 1 Empire .(d) On    the other hand, we    could not offerany help on the Portuguese mainland, saveperhaps a few Spitfi.ro Squadrons to assist in the defence of Lisbon7(iv) Generally, the Prime Minister thought that itwas important to make rather more of   theadvantages wo, could offer, than had. been donein   the Foreign Office draft, and,    further,that la    would he   a mistake, at this stage toinclude anything by way of a veiled threat of possible consequences to the PortugueseColonial Empire.   At this stage our policy should he all inducevaents and no threats.(v)  It; would be necessary to obtain Field Marshal- Smuts&apos;   concurrence in the terms of the assurance covering the future of the PortugueseColonial Empire.(vi)The Prime Minister thought, however, that itwas. unnecessary at this stage to consult &quot;theComuonvealth of Australia about Timor,

(vii)  If the diplomatic approach should provesuccessful, it was important that no time should be lost in establishing ourselves inthe Islands.   A Brigade of troops withan oil 1 aries   should immediately be /prepared,and shipping should be collected so that theforce could embark any time after the 18thJuno.    The advantages&apos;of being ready to take up   the lease at once outweighed anydisadvantage in collecting and holding thenecessary shipping and escorts ,    This force would, of    course, be prepared for an occupation and&apos; not for an assault, and if   the diplomaticapproach fall or1 it would, have to return tothes o shores .(viii)  Should the diplomatic approach fail, our ambassador should, give the impression that wehad reluctantly deferred to the Portugueserefusal.    Preparations   would, however,  -osteadily on for a full-scale operation LIPKBELT,to sail about the 20th August.    On this hypothe-8id, he would propose to   warn Dr Salazar afew hours in advance   of    the assault that wewore about to seize the Islands, but that it laywithin his power, by the despatch of the neecssaitelegram, to avert bloodshed and the terminationof our 600 years old Alliance *    In return forthis action on the part of Dr So.lo.zar, we shouldbe prepared to give the assurances which we werehow about to offer.General agreement was expressed by the War cabinet with the    course of action proposed by the Prime Minister.THE CHIEF 0? THE AIR STAFF asked that- the Chiefs of-Staff might be   given an opportunity of considering themilitary&apos; implications&apos; of the Foreign Office instructionsto Sir Ronald    Campbell.   With regard to any offer of airprotection, we could not hope to do more than provide afew s qua-irons for the defence of Lisbon.    The protectionof other ports  in Portugal would be beyond our resources.THE VICE-CHIEF    OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF saidthat there would probably be no    difficulty in providing a garrison Brigade at.this short notice.    The limiting factor would probably   be the time required to provideand load a M-T/Store-Ship,  out every effort would be madeto have the expedition ready to embark within the timesuggested. :&quot;loo War Cobi.net&apos;s Conclusions were as follows:-(1)   It was agreed that    a diplomatic approach should be made on. the lines indicated by thePrime Minister;    and. that if this  failedwe   should take military action to obtainour requirements later in the year.(S) The Prime Minister undertook to send animmediate telegram&quot; to President RooseveltsCchine, his concurrence in our making a diplomatic approach on   the lines indicated;.-3-4- Despatched as T 777/3.

(3) The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs was invited to re-^raft his telegram with:.M .Ambasso..dor at Lisbon in the light ofthe discussion, arid to send it to theChiefs of Staff for their comments .(4) The telegrams-.referred -to in ( ) would thenbe submitted to the  P rime Minister for his approval an1 despatch, without further reference to the War Cabinet.(5)  The Chiefs of Staff were ashed to issue instructions for    the immediate preparationof an expedition of the approximate strengthof a Brigade, which should, be ready to embarkby the 18th or 19th June.    This Brigade wouldbo an occupying, and not an assault, force.(6) The Foreign Secretary and. Dominions secretary would, arrange for   the preparation of o drafttele grain for the Prime Minister to send toField M:riJh..l Smuts.// Despatched as No. 791 fromDominions Office to SouthAfrica (H.C.))ffices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1..,10th June, 1943,




</content>
</cab>
