<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/6/49 images: 556-565</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)404th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT  UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 104 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Friday, April 26, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The   Right    Hon.    Lord    Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Air Marshal R. E. C. Peirse, Vice-Chief of the Air Staff&apos;.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. F. Hemming.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Lieutenant-Colonel E. I. C. Jacob, R.E.[21212]b
WAR CABINET 104 (40).Contents.minute no.                                       Subject. page 1      The Air Situation     ..................     425Enemy activity.R.A.F. mine-laying operations.Operations in Scandinavia.Gladiator aircraft in Norway.2      The Naval Situation..................     426Shipping losses.Results of mining operations.3      Operations in Norway ...      ....      ...      ...      ...      ...     427Narvik.Namsos.Trondhjem.Andalsnes and the Southern Front.4      Italy     ............      .............    427Proposed approach to Signor Mussolini.Naval situation in the Mediterranean.5      Aircraft Production Questions       ...      ...      ...      ...     428Raw materials.Homing device.6      R.D.F. Development..................     429Priority arrangements.7      United States of America    ...      ...      ...      ...      ...    429Proposed Anglo-American exchange of information regarding navaland military devices.Co-operation in R.D.F. research. -8      War Cabinet Arrangements ...      ...      ...      .......    429
The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 103rdConclusions,Minute 1.)Enemy activity.R.A.F.mine-laying operations.Operations in scandinavia.Gladiatoraircraft in norway.1. The Secretary of State for Air informed the War Cabinetthat during the previous day, four enemy aircraft tracks had beenplotted one at 6 a.m. through the Straits - of Dover and lateranother over France, south-east of Cape Gris Nez. There had alsobeen an enemy aircraft over the Humber estuary during the morning, and in the Wick area during the afternoon. During the night eight unidentified tracks had been plotted between Fair Isleand Kinnairds Plead. It was thought that these might have beenGerman aircraft foiled by weather in an attempt to attack Scapa.About 200 miles north-west of Lossiemouth. one Blenheim had seen two Dornier 18 flying boats, one on the water and the other in the air. The aircraft in the air had been engaged and when lastseen had been sinking. The aircraft on the water had also been attacked with machine guns.Mine-laying had been carried out in the Belts and Lower Soundduring the previous night by 27 FLampdens. The weather had been extremely bad, and consequently only two mines had been dropped.Three Hampdens were definitely missing, the losses being probably due to anti-aircraft fire. The Air Ministry had decided to makeanother attempt that night with the object of completing the mine-laying programme, as it would be the last occasion during thepresent month on which there would be sufficient moonlight.An aircraft on reconnaissance off the Norwegian coast had met two Dornier 18 flying boats, and had damaged one of them.Six Blenheims had been despatched at noon on the previous day to attack enemy ships reported in Hardanger and GranvinFjords. One aircraft had returned without locating the target andanother was missing. A wireless report from the latter gave reasonto believe that direct hits had been registered on a German transport at the head of Hardanger Fjord. Some bombs had also fallen onthe quay at Granvin.Six Whitleys had left the previous night to carry out attacks on shipping, oil. tanks and aerodromes near Oslo. A report fromonly one aircraft was so far available. This stated that the oiltank and refinery at Vallo had been successfully attacked, and agood fire had been started. A ship of about 5,000 tons had alsobeen attacked off Moss and was believed to have been hit. A fireat Stavanger had been observed on the return journey. One air-craft had returned early without completing its task.Twelve Wellingtons had left to attack Stavanger aerodrome onthe previous night. Six aircraft had returned, having failed tofind the target on account of bad weather. From the remainingsix, only one report was as yet available. The aircraft had been unable to locate the oil tanks, but had attacked four large shipsNorth-west of Stavanger with, incendiary bombs, and also the sea-plane base, on both of which hits were believed to have been registered. Eight or nine large ships, some transports and warshipshad been observed stationary one mile South-east of Gru Island.Two Whitleys had carried out a reconnaissance of Aalborg onthe previous night. One of these had reported intense searchlightglare, which had made it impossible to see anything. This was anew development.A Blenheim fighter patrol over Andalsnes had encountered aHeinkel 111 about 4-15 p.m., 45 miles West of the entrance toSonge Fjord. The enemy aircraft had attacked and had been seen to crash in the sea.Two Sunderlands had left for Namsos on the previous nightcarrying a Staff Officer and stores,A very corrupt telegram had been received during the previous night giving information about the Gladiator aircraft which hadbeen sent to Lesgeskogen. This stated that the position was verycritical, owing to the melting of ice. Continuous bombing and low-flying attacks had been carried out by the enemy, as a resultof which 16 out of 18 Gladiators were reported to have been[21212] b 2
destroyed or put out of action. A later telegram stated that during these enemy attacks 6 Heinkels had been shot down, three by anti-aircraft fire, two by Skuas and one by the Gladiators. A telegram had stressed the importance of sending more fighters to Norway.A suggestion had been put forward by our Minister in Stockholmthat aircraft could operate from a frozen lake at Vangmosen.Without this fighter support, it was stated that the Army couldnot hold out.The Vice-Chief of the Air Staff said that two sections, eachof three Blenheim fighters, were flying that day to Lesgeskogen,where they would refuel and carry out operations if landing con-ditions permitted.The Secretary of State for Air drew attention to the very heavy demands which the Norwegian campaign was making on theRoyal Air Force, but presumed that the War Cabinet would agreethat the situation at the moment allowed us no alternative. Forthe time being the risks involved must be accepted.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.The naval situation.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 103rdConclusions,Minute 2.)Shipping losses.Eesults ofminingoperations.2. The First Lord of the Admiralty reported thatS.S. Franconia, returning to the Clyde from Namsos, had been attacked 75 miles from Cape Wrath by a U-boat, but had escaped.H.M. Submarine Truant had reported that two explosions,probably due to magnetic torpedoes, had taken place in herimmediate vicinity. She had been very slightly damaged, and was now at Rosyth.Shipping losses during the previous twenty-four hours had been as follows :  The British tanker Cree, 4,791 tons, had been mined nearSmith&apos;s Knoll buoy. The crew had been rescued and the ship was still afloat.The S.S. Margam Abbey, 2,470 tons, had been mined in the thames Approaches, and had had her bows blown off. her crew had been saved.The British tanker Seminole, 10,389 tons, had been minedoff Swansea, but had been beached in Mumbles Bay. At thetime of the explosion she had been in a dangerous area.H.M.S. Curacao had arrived at Scapa. Details of the damageshe had sustained had not yet been received, but she had reportedthat thirty had been killed and thirty-six wounded.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs enquired whether there was any news to indicate whether the mines we had beensowing had caused casualties.The First L,ord of the Admiralty said that the only definite evidence was that two of the Denmark ferries had been damaged.The Secretary of State for Air said that one could only judge the effect of mining of this kind from the effect it had on us whenit had been started by the Germans. After the Belts had first been mined, news had been received that the Germans had diverted their ships to the Aalborg Channel.  This had also now been mined.
Operations in norway.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 103rdConclusions,Minute 3.)Narvik.Namsos,3. The War Cabinet were given the following information asto the position : Trondhjem.Andalsnes andthe southern front.(i) There was no change in the position at Narvik,(ii) A telegram had been received from General Carton deWiart, timed 7-20 p.m. on the 25th April, reporting thatthere was no change in the situation on the Namsosfront. A British battalion was holding a position in front of French supports; and the air superiority whichhad apparently been achieved by the aircraft from thecarriers was of great value.(iii) Thirty-five aircraft from H.M.S. Ark Royal had carriedout attacks on Trondhjem. It was not yet known whatobjectives had been attacked (though the attack hadbeen reported as successful^, but ten aircraft had failedto l^return. Of these, two had made forced landings andthe crews had been picked up.Operations from aircraft carriers were continuing.(iv) During bombing attacks on Andalsnes on the previous day the trawlers Hammond and Bradman, and theNorwegian destroyer Trygg, had been sunk. Theremainder of General Paget&apos;s Staff, and certain troops from H.M.S. Manchester, had been disembarked duringthe night at Molde.A message had been received from General Pagetat Andalsnes to the following effect : The situation was reported to be that german forces, with medium artillery and armoured fighting vehicles, were advancing up the valley towards Dombaas.The two British battalions of Morgan&apos;s brigade wereretreating in front of the Germans, and now formed acomposite battalion of a strength of about 400. Theenemy&apos;s complete superiority in the air, and the lack of artillery on our side, made it appear doubtful whetherthe German advance could be stopped. The 15thInfantry Brigade were taking up positions South ofDombaas. General Paget asked urgently for moresupport from the air.A record of the discussion on the latest reports of operations in Norway and on future possibilities is contained in the Secretary&apos;standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.Italy- 4.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs recalled that proposed at the meeting of the War Cabinet noted in the margin, doubt hadapproach to been expressed as to the wisdom of a proposal which had been madeSignor that His Majesty The King should send a letter to the King of mussolini. Italy.   Later the same day he had discussed the matter in Paris(Previous with the Prime Minister who had agreed that it would be wiserReference: that the letter should not be delivered. The Foreign Secretary had.M. (40) 100th explained the matter to His Majesty who had agreed that the letterConclusions, should not be delivered.Minute 5.)
Naval situationin theMediterranean.(previous erence:W.M. (40) 103rdConclusions,Minute 4.)We had no obligation, under the Anglo-Italian Agreement, to notify the Italian Government of fleet movements in the Mediter-ranean, but he felt that it would be well to inform the ItalianGovernment of these movements after orders had been given forthem to be carried out.The First Lord of the Admiralty hoped that we should makeit clear that, owing to the heavy German naval losses, the balanceof naval strength between Germany and ourselves had been greatlyaltered and that we were now able to revert to our normal fleetdispositions.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs agreed that thiswas the line which we should take; a message on these lines wouldbe concerted between the Foreign Office and the Admiralty andwould also be sent to certain of His Majesty&apos;s Representativesabroad.The Foreign Secretary also drew attention to telegram No. 321DIPP, dated 25th April, 1940, from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador,Ankara, reporting that the German Ambassador had been making enquiries regarding a rumour that we were moving half the home fleet to the Mediterranean.The War Cabinet (i) Took note of the above statements.(ii) Invited the Foreign Secretary, after consultation with theFirst Lord of the Admiralty, to send a notification onthe lines proposed to the Italian Government and tocertain of His Majesty&apos;s Representatives abroad.AircraftProductionQuestions.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 14thConclusions,Minute 1.)Raw materials.Homing device.(previous.M. (40) 102ndConclusions,Minute 3.)5. In the course of discussion on Minute 3, the Prime ministers aid that the operations now proceeding in Norway emphasised theimportance of air strengths.The Secretary of State for Air said that the maintenance of aircraft production on the planned scale depended very largely uponsatisfactory solutions being obtained to two serious problems,namely (i) The  provision   of   adequate  supplies  of  certain   rawmaterials, notably high grade steels.(ii) Satisfactory arrangements being made for the manufac-ture of light alloys. The difficulty here was that we werebehindhand in the provision of the necessary presses.He hoped shortly to be in a position&apos; to make definite proposals fordealing with these difficulties, which would have to be overcomeunless production was to fall in the autumn. He feared that furtherdollar expenditure would be unavoidable. &apos;The Secretary of State for Air also referred to the discussion at the meeting noted in the margin regarding the difficulties which our aircraft were experiencing in making a rendezvous with ships at sea. He had now given orders that the highest priority was tobe given to the equipping of Hudson aircraft with a homing device.He hoped that forty such aircraft would be so equipped resifein amonth. Ic      Week&quot;s,
R.D.P. 6.   In connection with the discussion recorded in Minute 5,Development. the Minister without Portfolio said that a large number of Govern-Priority ment Departments, and in addition the B.B.C., were concerned inarrangements. the development of R.D.F. in various forms. He had formed theopinion that, both as regards material and personnel, some ministers should be invited to examine the system of priorities established inthis field.The War Cabinet agreed That the Minister without Portfolio, in consultation withthe Ministers concerned, should take such steps as might benecessarv to review the system of priorities in respect ofR.D.F.United States ofAmerica.Proposed Anglo-Americanexchange ofinformationregarding navaland militarydevices.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 109thConclusions,Minute 9.)Co-operation inR.D.F. research.7. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that in thecourse of a conversation the previous day the United states ambassador had told him that the United States Government had given us all their secrets in regard to naval and military deviceswith the exception of two, one of which was the Nordern bombsight. The Foreign Secretary thought that it might be worth whileconsidering making an appeal to President Roosevelt to give usparticulars of this sight.The Prime Minister referred to a letter in which Lord Lothian,when discussing the United States proposal that we should exchangeinformation in regard to R.D.F. devices, had expressed the view thatas we had more to give in this matter than the United States, itmight be possible to persuade the latter to give us particulars of thisbomb sight.The Secretary of State for Air said that he welcomed theproposal for the exchange of information on R.D.F. devices. Hewould like also to see closer co-operation in R.D.F. research between british and American scientists. We were very short of expertresearch workers in this field, and we should try to get as manyAmerican scientists as possible to work on these problems for us.The War Cabinet took note of the above discussion.War cabinet arrangements.8.   The War Cabinet agreed : (a) That the Meeting on Saturday, 27th April, 1940, shouldbe held at 10-30 a.m.(b) That a Meeting of the War Cabinet should be held on sunday, 28th April, 1940, at 10-30 a.m.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,April 26, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
