<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/17/0 images: 21-26</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TT&quot;-------------- -..........- - cz    . :U. :..:.....I &apos;   ?!&quot;  20(Shis Document if&quot; the Property of His BritannicMajesty&quot;s Government).3 E G R E T.X-0.  ,4 V/AR CABINET.NOTES OE A CONVERSATION held at 10 Downing Street, S.WY,on FRIDAY, MAY 17, 1918, at 11.15 a.m.P r e s e n t:-THE PRIME MINISTER (in the Chair):The Rt.  Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G.,  Secretary of Statefor War:General Sir H.H.Wilson, E.C.B., D.S.O.,Chief of,the Imperial General Staff:lieutenant-Colonel Sir M.P.A.Hankey, K.C.B.,Secretary, War Cabinet:lieutenant-Colonel l.S.Amery, M.P.,Parliamentary and Personal Military Secretaryto the&apos;Secretary of State for War:&apos;GENERAL MAURI CE.LORD MILNER read out a reply from General Maurice to theletter which he had sent him on the previous day,  (See X-2),which was of a satisfactory character.    In it General Mauricesaid he would not indulge in any recriminations or attempt to reopen his case, unless officially requested to do so, andthat he would regard the Censor as a help and not as an enemy.AMERICAN COOPERATION.THE PRIME MINISTER read out a telegram from Lord Reading(No. ), in which he stated that the numbers that wouldbe sent during May would exceed the totals hitherto given.He estimated&apos;approximately that a total of 250,000 &quot;troops of all hinds would be sent during the month, of whom 180,000
would be infantry, machine-gunners, and engineers, includingreplacements.THE prime MINISTER said that he wished to be sure that sir Douglas Haig was disposed to make the best and prompt-est use of these American reinforcements.    He had been told that only 3 battalions would be fit to serve with the Brit-ish Army by the first week in June.      It seemed to him that so long a period of training,  in addition to their previoustraining of six months or so in America, was hardly necessary.He would very much like General foch  to have a look at these troops himself.    General Wilson might also, if he was overin Erance, take an opportunity of looking at them.    If the resistance to their early use came not from Sir Douglas Haig,but fi-om General Pershing&apos;, it would be necessary to applypressure to overcome it.LORD MIDEER stated that there had been 20,000 of theseInfantry reinforcements in France by the end of April, includ-ing some 12 or IS battalions.    Some of this first lot, ho?/ever,had been pretty rough, and hardly knew how to handle a rifle.This may have partly accounted for Sir Douglas Haig&apos;s reluct-ance to use them without a good deal of further training.GENERAL WILSON mentioned that General Dawnay, who was responsible for the training in France, had just come over. Hethought he could extract from him a pretty good opinion as tothe real value of these troops and the time required for train-Ing them.THE WESTERN FRONT.GENERAL WILSON mentioned that the Germans had moved one division away from opposite the Belgians to some point further south in the line.    There had been other small movements af-fecting 2 divisions.    Altogether the Germans now had 48 freshor recuperated divisions.in.hand for the attack.    They werehard at work on intensive training in the same areas as beforethe attack of March 21.    They would have a good moon for mass-J....... a.
ing their troops at night from now till May 23.    We, however,now had very good aeroplane flares for showing up the roadsat night.LABOUR IN THE TRENCHES.LORD MILNER reported that he had discussed the matter with Sir Ernest Moir (see X-2), who was disposed to do any-ihing that the Government wished, but had first to see his part-ner,With regard to General Stewart, LORD MILNER was not quite clear yet whether he should accompany Sir Ernest Moir.    Hewas inclined to think that it would really be best to put him at the Head of the whole of the railway transportation.RAILWAY. TRANSPORTATION IN FRANCE.LORD MILNER pointed out that General Stewart,  though prim-arily a contractor, would be able to effect great economies,not only in the labour required for railway work, but in thewhole railway organisation.    When Sir Eric Gedd.es had inaugurateed his Railway Service in France, it was under conditions of ur-gency, which involved the creation of an enormous establish-ment which was not justified by present conditions.    There weresomething like 13 Brigadier Generals at present on the Railway&quot;Staff in France.    General Nash was now in Paris on the Inter-Allied Committee, which was laying out the general plans ofthe railway work required on the whole Western front.    He was doing very good work there,  and he did not feel disposed tobring him back, more particularly as he also, like Sir eric geddes, had rather large ideas of the Staff required.    He con-sidered General Stewart the best man for the purpose.    He hadan enormous capacity for getting work done.    The  only criti-oism against him was that he lacked aggressiveness in dealingwith the Military Authorities.    To meet this deflect it would benecessary for him to have a strong military backing at G.H0Q03o
GENERAL WILSON suggested that General Stewart should be put under the Quartermaster General at G.H.Q. This was the best solution in the opinion of the War Office.

THE PRIME MINISTER and LORD MILNER both agreed that General Travers Clark, the Quartermaster-General at G.H.Q., would amply supply the element of aggressiveness which General Stewart lacked. It was a further advantage that General Travers Clarke wanted General Stewart for that purpose.

GENERAL WILSON pointed out that Sir Eric Geddes and Sir Sam Fay would probably both raise a considerable protest against the ideas of railways being put back under the Quartermaster-General.

THE PRIME MINISTER pointed out that the essential thing was to make the system fit in with the characteristics of the men available and the needs of the present situation, and that there was no question of principle involved.



CONCLUSION.

Lord Milner undertook to push the matter forward.



GENERAL WILSON AND GENERAL FOCH.



THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that General Wilson should have another talk before long with General Foch, in order to ascertain General Foch&apos;s plans for dealing with the German attack, more particularly in the contingency of the attack succeeding.

GENERAL WILSON mentioned that General Foch had at least been induced to face the possibility of that contingency and to make plans for it. He understood that a letter from General Foch, suggesting his coming over, was on its way to him. General 






Boon was seeing Sir Douglas Haig yesterday and today, and wouldprobably want to see him after that. If the letter did not ar-rive , he would telegraph to find out.DOHD MILKER said that he had already suggested general wilson going over early next week.    He had been anxious, how-ever,  to get certain other matters settled here before goingover.RUSSIA.THE PRIME MINISTER reported that he had had a conversa-tion on the previous day with Mr.  Leslie Urquhart, whom SirA. Steel Maitland had brought to see him.    Mr. Urquhart waspositive that any force could go straight through Russia like a hot knife through butter.    His view was that the germans were aiming at getting across to the Caspian and so utilising the Volga Fleet for getting down the produce of Siberia, aswell as copper,  zinc, &amp;c., from the Urals.    THE PRIME minister suggested that,  as the United States did not seem disposed todo anything,  it might be possible to get the Canadian Govern-ment to send a force of engineers, &amp;c, to vladivostock, andthat these, combined with the Czeoho-Slgv^c infantry, a fewbattalions of Japanese, and such French Officers as were theresmight make a sufficient international force to take action.COLONEL AMERY mentioned that he had recently had a con-versation with Dr. Benes, Secretary of the Czecho-Slavoc Na-tional Council, who had stated that the Czecho-Slavoc troops at vladivostock might be induced to take part in internation-al operations in Russia, but only if they were assured thatthis would bring them directly against the Atistrians or Ger-raans, and did not mean their taking part in civil war in Russiaitself.    He suggested that possibly the Australian Government,might also send a detachment of engineers.GENERAL WILSON mentioned that General Poole was juststarting for Russia, and was determined to do what he could to
bring about active military operations there.    He was quitesanguine as to raising a large army.THE PRIME MINISTER referred to the fact that Mr. Lindleywas also going, and apparently had no belief that anythingcould be done at all in Russia.0 0 IT 0 L U S I 0 N.It was agreed that:-The question whether Mr. Lindley ought togo at all to Russia should be raised at the&quot;Tar Cabinet immediately afterwards.UKRAINE.GENERAL WILSON read a telegram to General Macdonogh froman Agent who, in the past, had given trustworthy and usefulinformation, stating that the Central Powers were now get-ting very substantial assistance from the Ukraine.    600 car-loads a day were going through to Austria, which was at pres-ent getting four-sevenths of the total food from the Ukraine,the remainder going to Germany.    The cost of living in Aus-tria had gone down considerably, food was plentiful,  and foodcards were now hardly being used.    The Austro-Hungarian cropprospects were also good.    Eats and soap were still veryscarce.    Germany was busy organising the Ukraine and sendinglarge quarj titles of agricultural machinery to Odessa,withthe idea of finally displacing American machinery.    His in-forrnant mentioned that he saw 5,000 Austrian prisoners a daycoming back from Russia..    On the other hand., the bulk of thereleased. Russian prisoners were staying on in Germany and austria for wages.    Some 50 per cent,  of the Roumanian oil-wells were now in working order.&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;itehall Gardens, S.W.,May 17, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
