<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/17/0 images: 94-95</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government).



WAR CABINET.



NOTES OF A CONVERSATION at 10 Downing Street, S.W., on THURSDAY, JULY 18, 1918, at 11 a.m.



Present:



The Prime Minister (in the Chair):

The Rt. Hon.

The Viscount Milner, G.C.B., G.C.M.G., 

 Secretary of State for War:



General Sir H.H. Wilson, K.C.B., D.S.O.,

 Chief of the Imperial General Staff:

 

Lt.-Col. Sir M.P.A. Henkey, K.C.B.,

 Secretary, War Cabinet:



Lt.-Col. L.S. Amery, M.P.,



THE WESTERN FRONT.



GENERAL WILSON mentioned that General Foch had begun a counter-attack that morning on a front of 40-45 kilometres between Torcy and Nouvron, i.e., on the Western front of the Chateau Thierry salient. The number of enemy divisions identified was now reduced to 27, of which only 7 belonged to Prince Rupprecht&apos;s Army, while 7 were divisions originally in line West of Rheims, and 13 belonged to the Crown Prince&apos;s Reserve. It was quite possible that an exchange between divisions of the Crown Prince&apos;s Reserve and Prince Rupprecht&apos;s Reserve had taken place, so that the identification of divisions of the latter did not necessarily mean that his total strength was reduced. As regards the British divisions, 2 had been detrained at Arcy-sur-Aube, and were marching up to the line Chalons-Epernay, the other two were detraining on the line Claremont-Senlis. While there was no evidence that this was the big attack, there was some possibility that the French were right in claiming that they had caught a serious attack East of Rheims before it started.

   


There was also no definite evidence of the attach in the Kemmelsector referred to by Sir Douglas Haig.    General piumer had 12British and 3 American divisions to meet this attack, and oughtto he perfectly safe, more particularly if GoH*Q., were right intheir view that the German divisions now in the line were not worth very much.THE PRIME MINISTER was inclined to think that General foch  hadbeen too hasty in bringing the British divisions round behind hisown front. If it should turn out that he had let us down in thismatter, it would wreck the unity of command.LORD MILNER and GENERAL WILSON both suggested that there wasno proof that General Poch had let the British Army down, and thatthe failure of the German attack might have been due to the veryfact that General Poch had moved all his divisions down so quickly.THE PRIME MINISTER thought that it would be a good thing inany case for him to get an answer from M. Clemenceau to his letterwithout waiting for General Pooh&quot;s letter to General Wilson, whichwas understood to be on its way.    A telegram might begin with oon-gratulations to M. Clemenceau on the success of the Prench troops,or with a reference to the fact that a separate telegram of con-ixfflfefcESH congratulations was being sent on behalf of the imperial warCabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,July 18, 1918o2o

</content>
</cab>
