<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/52/0 images: 58-59</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)CONFIDENTIAL CABIN E 1   OFnGuRECORD copy . (52) 165 COPY NO..16th MAY, 1952.CABINETCONSTITUTIONAL REFORM IN HONG Kong memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.\\Constitutional reform in Hong Kong was promised after the war and hasbeen under discussion since 1946.   When I visited Hong Kong in December theGovernor represented to me that in view of all the prospects which had beenheld out since that date the fact that there had been no progress towards reformwas beginning to lead to agitation;  that he would find it increasingly difficultto hold the position for much longer;  and that the consequent restiveness in hong Kong itself would be more embarrassing than any Chinese communist propaganda which might be provoked by the publication of proposals which the communists might attempt to deride.   While in Hong Kong I was asked toreceive a deputation on this matter and I stated that proposals for someconstitutional advance were receiving my sympathetic consideration.2^        The present constitutional position is as follows.   The LegislativeCouncil consists of not more than nine officials and eight unofficials.   Six ofthe unofficials are appointed by the Governor, three of these being Chinese;  one is nominated by the Justices of the Peace and one by the Chamber of Commerce.3.        The main features of the proposals now under consideration are theintroduction of an indirect elective system, with the grant of an unofficialmajority in the Legislature.   (An indirect rather than a direct elective system is because of the difficulty of arranging for a franchise limited to Britishsubjects in the peculiar conditions of Hong Kong.   No one who is not a british subject will of course be eligible for appointment to membership of the Council).The Council would then consist of four officials, five unofficials nominated bythe Governor and six members elected by the Justice of the Peace, the GeneralChamber of Commerce, the Chinese Chamber of Commerce and the UrbanCouncil.   The Governor would have the usual reserve powers.   He is howeversatisfied that, on any conceivable voting combination of the unofficial members,Government could count on a majority of the Council to carry any measure of real importance.4.        These proposals were agreed on as long ago as the end of 1950, but were postponed early in 1951, at the request of the Foreign Office, on the grounds that, since they did not provide for a wide Chinese franchise, they might provoke a propaganda campaign at a time when the situation in the Far east was particularly serious, and when it was especially desirable to avoid givingthe Central Peoples Government an excuse to raise the question of theretrocession of Hong Kong to China.
In view of the recent representations to me by the Governor thematter was taken up again with the Foreign Office, Commonwealth relations office, Ministry of Defence and Treasury, who are all interested in come degree, and all agreed that, for the reasons given in paragraph 1, the time had come to go ahead, in spite of the present unsettled situation in the far east.   The introduction of these reforms, involving as they do considerabledrafting and consultation with the Hong Kong Government, will take several months and if, in the meantime, the situation in the Far East shoulddeteriorate, they could again be deferred.5.        I recommend that we should proceed with constitutional reform in hong Kong on these lines.O.L.iij&apos; ,V.;.:. .: v;;..-,/Colonial Office, S.W.1.,16th MAY, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
