<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/52/0 images: 68-69</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABiNET OFHCfcRECORD COPYcopyno._ gCABINETFOOD SUPPLIES AND BALANCE OF PAYMENTS.Memorandum by the Minister of food think I ought to let my colleagues know how currency and balance ofpayments difficulties affect our efforts to procure more food,2.        Here are a few examples:-(a) There are ample dollar sugar supplies available to restore the jammaking bonuses which we have had to cut - possibly to abolishsugar rationing at an early date.(b) We could probably buy some 50,000 tons of additional pork meatthis year in Europe and Canada,(c) We could buy, at reasonable prices, in Europe, indonesia and the Belgian Congo, adequate  supplies at reasonable pricesof ingredients to make more margarine to compensate for areduction from 3 ozs. to 2 ozs. in the butter ration which willbe inevitable for a period in the autumn of this year owing toa world shortage of butter.(d) We could buy substantial quantities of cheese in North America -we bought 47,200 tons last year, which is equal to 1 oz. on the ration for 32 weeks.   Present prospects of supplies  from sterlingsources are such that we shall have difficulty after the end ofthis year in maintaining even the present 1 oz, ration.3.        I have fully accepted the necessity of a policy of import restrictions tomeet our balance of payments difficulties and cuts in food imports have madea bigger contribution to the carrying out of this policy than those in any othersingle sector of the economy.   The full effects of these cuts have not yet been felt.Moreover some fairly substantial cuts in expenditure e. g. in the case of sugar and oils and fats have been made by eating into stocks.   This is an operation which cannot be repeated and if we want to continue to make cuts at this rate they will have to be directly at the expense of consumption.   If we are tocontinue the policy of import cuts for any length of time, I would ask mycolleagues to recognise that we must accept the unpopularity attendant on it,while defending it as a positive step to avert the worse fate of national bankruptcy.4.        There is a risk that such a policy^ if continued for long, may damagehome morale and ultimately restrict our own export markets.   I assume therefore that we cannot contemplate the indefinite continuance of this policy in relationto food supplies.secret.(52) 16820th MAY, 1952.
5.        The purpose of this note is to remind my colleagues that ifwe could earn more currency of the right kind - and so could afford to allocate more to food - we could soon begin to restore the buying of food to the trade.   I am satisfied that this is the right way to increasesupplies of many of our important foods.   But any attempt to move inthis direction is for the time being largely frustrated by currencydifficulties whenever we have to look beyond the sterling area for largersupplies.   The limitation of supplies involves the maintenance of rationing and price control which are in themselves deterrents toeffective private trading:  and so the vicious circle is complete.   Atpresent therefore we are exposed to the full blast of the criticism whichcan be directed against rising food prices, without the compensatioaof being able to offer people more to eat.6.       I invite my colleagues to review our food policy in the lightof this note.G. JLLi&quot;G.Ministry of Food, S.W.1.20th MAY, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
