<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/52/0 images: 73-74</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  May 1952.C. (52) 17123rd May, 1952SECRETCABINET OFFICtRECORD copy copy No. 6 6CABINETECONOMIC policy note by the Secretary of the CabinetBy the Prime Ministers direction I circulate, for the information of the Cabinet,a personal Minute addressed to him by the Paymaster-General on the memorandumby the Chancellor of the Exchequer on Economic Policy (C. (52) 166).I agree with almost everything in this very important paper. It shows withfrightening clarity how much poorer we are than before the war and how much wehave increased our commitments. Unless we use the present short breathing spaceto cut our coat according to our cloth, economic and political disaster will be inevitable. . .It is vital to decide quickly on a balanced programme, however painful, on defence, food, housing, &amp;c, and to stick to it. It is no use for the Cabinet to agreebroadly that we must balance our overseas accounts and then for each departmentto come forward with individual cases demanding special piecemeal treatment. :Separate papers or reviews are promised on the main aspects which will haveto be considered. These include:  (a) Defence Programme ,   &apos; !&apos;Reductions seem inevitable. I believe they may best be made by cuttingout whole wedges: e.g., anti-aircraft guns may be of little use against modernstrategic bombers;  100 million for moving the Middle East base merely toappease Egyptian amour propre is intolerable. If we had a financial disasterand could not import food and materials, the defence programme would ipsofacto go by the board. Purely from the defence point of view, therefore, itdoes not pay to attempt more than we can afford.(b) Import programme a review of 1952-53 is urgent before the pattern is prejudged by theestablishment of prior claims. Moreover, the cuts imposed by the chancellor on imports, especially from E.P.U. countries, are, it seems, being circumventedin some way; our imports are not falling as they should. This should be examined at once. //&quot;/&apos;/(c) Investment Programme 1953 hA difficult balance will have to be struck between defence, housing, schools,hospitals, electrical generating capacity, &amp;c.NORMAN BROOK.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,23rd May, 1952.Minute from the Paymaster-General to the Prime MinisterECONOMIC POLICY: C. (52) 16642301
We must examine ruthlessly our expenditure:  on direct defence middle east, Malaya, Hong Kong, &amp;c.; indirect defence supporting Yugoslavia, &amp;c.;oil development which should only be undertaken if we can guarantee to...   hold the refineries; inflated war-time sterling balances still being released to Egypt, &amp;c; the Colombo Plan.(e) Incentives to ExportersWe should try to discover at once ways of giving special financial incentives to exporters, especially to the dollar area. I am sure, too, that profits mustbe progressively freed from taxation if we in this crowded island, with littlebut skill and enterprise to sell, are ever to pay our way in an increasinglycompetitive world. The Socialists ruled in a world sellers&apos; market; they received vast American aid. I believe that the soaking of profits was a luxuryBritain could afford only in those exceptional circumstances.(/) AgricultureI hope that the review promised by the Chancellor and the Minister ofAgriculture will show ways of securing a large expansion.I also agree with the Chancellor on the importance of a stern internal financial policy even if it involves higher rents and food prices. This is bound to be unpopular, but it is far better than national bankruptcy.I agree that exporters and others must be able to rely on adequate suppliesof steel. The Socialists failed to provide for our needs; as a result, in the lastyear supplies have fallen far short of demand and our whole economy has beenhamstrung. We must make quite sure that our future needs are covered. Asimmediate measures we should examine urgently the possibilities of: -(i) replacing cast-iron by steel products which often use only half as muchmetal;(ii) importing more steel;(Hi) reducing exports of steel of low value.I agree, too, that we must export more coal. We have 34- million tons more in stock than last year and could sell it on the Continent to great advantage (I hopeat a higher price). We should also, I think, set a high target for expansion of coal exports over the next few years. This will no doubt call for an even greater increasein output than seems to be contemplated at present. The task is difficult but wortha great effort.I should also like to see additional measure to enforce exchange control,attempts to fund sterling balances on a voluntary basis, and more high level and continuous co-operation with the Americans to foresee and forestall those ups anddowns in trade which have such disastrous effects on our exiguous gold reserves.If the Chancellors paper is followed up resolutely we shall really have themakings of an economic policy to put the country on its feet again before the nextelection.(Signed) CHERWELL.

</content>
</cab>
