<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/52/0 images: 121-121</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  June 1952CABINET&apos;OFFICE Copy No.42RECORD COPYCABINETROYAL VISIT TO AUSTRALIA AND NEW ZEALANDNote by the Secretary of the CabinetBy direction of the Prime Minister I circulate a note by the Prime Ministerof Australia on the Royal Visit to Australia and New Zealand.NORMAN BROOK.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,3rd June, 1952.NOTE BY THE PRIME MINISTER OF australia the last date on which an Australian Election can be held is fairly early inJuly 1954. It would be safe to treat this date as the end of June 1954. An election campaign in Australia lasts six weeks, and, allowing for two weeks before thatto prepare policy speeches and the like, the campaign period can be treated asbeginning at the beginning of May. It would be undesirable to have a Royal Visitimmediately followed by an Election campaign. Therefore there ought to be aperiod of a month intervening during which a short Session of Parliament, say fora fortnight or three weeks, could be held. This means that the Royal Visit toAustralia should finish by the end of March. This means February-March forthe Visit to Australia, and January for the Visit to New Zealand, there being noAustralian objection to the Visit to New Zealand coming first. This means thatif the journey can be organised so that the Royal Visitors are in New Zealand bythe beginning of January it would be all to the good. The Queen and the Duke of edinburgh have both indicated to me that they would rather like to be in london for Christmas Day, for obvious reasons. This would be not inconsistent withtheir being in New Zealand by 1st January if they flew. I have gathered that,if the new Royal yacht is to be constructed, it will not be built by this date.Therefore the probabilities are that the Gothic should be in New Zealand watersby the end of December. Having regard to the large expenditures incurred onthe Gothic, which would be thrown away to some extent if it were not used forthe Royal Visit, and having regard to the further fact that to keep the Royal suitein the Gothic out of action for the next eighteen months would involve a loss to theCompany of something of the order of  125,000, I indicated to the PrimeMinister that so far as the Australian Government is concerned, we wouldwillingly accept a rateable proportion of this outlay to enable the Gothic to beavailable for the Visit, there being great advantages in the Royal Visitors having a ship at their service in the Australian ports.ROBERT MENZIES.2nd June, 1952. iCONFIDENTIALC. (52) 1833rd June, 195242349

</content>
</cab>
