<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/6/41 images: 424-431</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1940.SECRET. Copy No.     ^W.P. (40) 111.(Also C.O.S. (40) 270.) . /March 26, 1940. &apos;.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.CERTAIN ASPECTS OF THE PRESENT SITUATION.Memorandum by the Chiefs of Staff Committee.Policy agreed before the war.THE military policy to be adopted by the Allies for a war againstGermany and Italy was agreed in May 1939. Briefly, it was to remain on the defensive, except at sea and in the economic sphere, during the first phase ofthe war, &quot;while building up our resources to a point at which we should be in aposition to pass to the offensive!It was realised that our military resources were so undeveloped by comparisonwith those of Germany that this phase would necessarily be a long one, but it was felt that time was on our side.The War Cabinet decided at the outset that our programme should be basedon the assumption that the war might last three years.Developments since this policy was agreed.2.   The situation we had envisaged in May 1939 has been changed by : (a) a virtual German-Russian alliance;(b) an uncertain, instead of a hostile, attitude on the part of Italy;(c) the tripartite convention between the Allies and Turkey;(d) the recent Russo-Finnish war and treaty.(e) Contrary  to  expectations,  the  Germans  have  not embarked  uponunrestricted air warfare.3. We have in course of preparation a full appreciation in which we hope to weigh the effect on our policy of these changes, and, in particular, to estimateto. what extent it is still true to say that time is on our side. In the following paragraphs we summarise our views on certain aspects of the present situation.Certain Factors in the present Situation.General. :4. The fact that the enemy has not yet launched a major land or air offensive has given the Allies a valuable, if unexpected, breathing space in which to make good some of our many deficiencies. We are, however, still far short ofour essential requirements for defence, let alone the forces required for a major[21028] b
offensive. On the other hand, the Germans also are likely to be making good useof the present jJeriod of military inactivity, and, if this is allowed to continue too long, they may be able to exploit Russian resources.5. The German Higher Direction of war has not, except in the case ofthe invasion of Poland, been impressive, nor has it given evidence of a determina-rion to force a quick decision. Their attacks both by sea and air convey theimpression of a desire for cheap and spectacular successes. They threw awaythe surprise of the magnetic mine by using it in &quot;penny packets,&quot; insteadof waiting until they could do so on a magnificent scale. Their failure toattack our destroyer force on its return journey from the Altmark affair suggestsa weakness in countering a surprise situation and lack of co-ordination. Inthese circumstances any enterprises which are calculated to mystify and misleadthe German High Command, to play on their nerves, and to prevent themorganising at leisure might have far-reaching results.A t Sea.6. At the present time we have the measure of the U-boat campaign, andhaving regard to the various counter-measures we are developing, we do notconsider that, even with the increased Construction of U-boats which must beexpected, our sea communications will be seriously endangered. Our lossesthrough mines have been heavy, but again we feel that our counter-measures will soon get the better of this form of attack. At the same time, thereappearance of German raiders, whether surface or U-boat, on the trade routesmight compel a wider dispersion of naval forces.7. An intensification of air attack on our shipping in home waters, perhapsextending to our ports, is a very grave danger and may cause increased losses,possibly forcing diversion to West Coast ports. It is essential that the develop-ment of our counter-measures, and the completion of preparations at the WestCoast ports should be pressed on unremittingly and regardless of cost.- 8. The total losses of Allied and neutral shipping in the first six monthsof the war amount to over a million tons, of which the British have lost some776,000 tons. Against this loss, however, must be set a gain of 580,000 tons,due to new construction, captured vessels, transfers from other flags, &amp;o, thusgiving a net loss of only 196,000 tons. Our present production of merchantshipping is about three-quarters of a million tons per annum, and our futureprogramme aims at reaching a rate of 1,500,000 tons in about a year from now.In view, however, of what has been said in the preceding paragraph, the attain-ment of this programme is most important.Economic Pressure.9. Allied plans for exerting economic pressure on Germany were put intoeffect from the beginning, and have already aggravated her economic difficulties.Italian imports and exports are still not satisfactorily under control; there isno control of the trade across the Black Sea and in the Far East it has not yetbeen possible to go beyond detaining occasional ships bound for Vladivostok.In regard to Russia, there are some grounds, for the belief that German exploita-tion of Russian resources, particularly of oil, may during 1941 largely nullifythe effects of our blockade. This is now under examination; but it is apparent that Allied diplomacy should aim at dissolving the Russo-German coalition, whilecreating a situation in Turkey in which, if it suited us to go to war with Russia,we could do so effectively. Meanwhile, we should do our utmost to close the gapsin our contraband control. Any project to intensify our economic pressure, suchas cutting off supplies from adjacent countries, dislocating Germany&apos;s inland waterways or interrupting her Scandinavian trade should be adopted, providedreally effective resources are available and the political and military disadvantagesinvolved are not disproportionate to the results to be obtained.The Air Situation.10. The outbreak of war found us: with our pre-war plans for air forceexpansion incomplete. It was, however, decided to adopt a greatly increasedprogramme of expansion, on the basis of the Government&apos;s policy that we shouldorganise our resources for a long war. Preparations were therefore put inhand to develop on progressive lines a very powerful air force by the third year
of war. These involved a programme of production aiming at an outputby., that, time of 2,500 aircraft a month, including trainers, which hasto be matched by a training programme on an appropriate and exten-sive scale. This latter can only be achieved by striking a prudentbalance between future requirements and immediate requirements for increasein first-line strength: &apos; In effect, a very high proportion of our resources in personnel and aircraft must necessarily be devoted to building up a great airforce for a long war-inevitably at the expense of our ability to wage a short one on an intensive scale.11. The first-line bomber force was particularly affected by the requirementsof training. The position will show a progressive improvement during 1940, butit must be a considerable time before the real results of the war expansion programme begin to be felt. Meanwhile, the expansion of our first line can onlybe gradual, and, unless it proves possible by some means to increase the rate ofproduction, could not be accelerated save at the expense of our long-term programme, and with most serious dislocation of existing approved developmentmeasures.12. The same factors apply, though not to the same extent, to the development-ment of our fighter force. We are still gravely deficient in certain essentialcomponents of active defence, particularly fighters, both front line and reserve,and light A.A. guns.13. The French air situation is less satisfactory than our own, and we couldnot rely on any appreciable assistance from them if we were seriously attacked.14. Taking both offensive and defensive factors into account, it is clear thatwe are considerably short of the position when it would be wise for the Allies toadopt the initiative in undertaking an air offensive on an intensive scale. Weshould bend all our energies, regardless of cost, to accelerating our production andtraining programme so as to give us greater offensive resources and improve our defensive capacity.15. Our air forces overseas have deliberately been kept short of their full requirements in equipment and personnel in order to assist in building up our strength in the metropolitan sphere, and are not at present in a condition toundertake operations on a serious scale.Land Forces.16. On the Western Front the Germans hold a position of strategicadvantage. Apart from numerical superiority, they know that, providing theyare not the first to infringe the neutrality of the Low Countries or Switzerlandthey have only to consider for defence their common frontier with France, whichis strongly defended in depth. The Allies, on the other hand, cannot exclude thepossibility of attack at any point from the Channel to the Mediterranean. Theincrease in Allied strength likely to be achieved in 1940, even if all new british divisions were to be allocated to France, would not be sufficient to warrant an offensive this year. On the other hand, taking into account the French frontierfortifications, the Allied forces now in the field should be capable of stopping aGerman offensive against France. It is clearly desirable, however, to determine what will be, from time to time, the minimum Allied requirements to ensure thesecurity of this front.Mediterranean and Middle East.17. Although the security of the United Kingdom and France must still begiven first priority, the maintenance of the Allied position in the Middle Eastis of great importance.  A defeat in this area would be a disaster.18.   The Germans have sufficient forces for a two-front war, but it isdoubtful whether the present condition of their railway system would admit oftheir transferring considerable forces from the West to the South-East of Europe.It would, however, be most unsafe to disregard the possibility of their doing so.[21028]  ;      , . . .b. 2
19. Turkey is the northern bastion of the Allied position in the middle east, and:our agreement with her was an important diplomatic success, whichwe should be prepared to take the most energetic action and some risks to consolidate. A point of particular importance is that, without her activecollaboration, it would be difficult, should it be necessary to undertake activehostilities against Russia, to attack the vitally important sources of oil supply in the Caucasus: We should therefore place ourselves in a position to afford the necessary degree of support to Turkey so as to ensure that she stands firmlyin the Allied camp. Any appropriate measures we can take in this direction,without involving undue risks in the west, should be put in hand immediately.Meanwhile, we should adhere to our policy of creating a benevolently neutral blocin the Balkans. We should try to secure the adherence of Bulgaria to that bloc and thus afford some support to Roumania, to whom we have given a guarantee.To meet a sudden development of the situation we must recognise the fact that wemay at any time have to reconcentrate a fleet in the Eastern Mediterranean, withthe consequent strain upon our naval resources.The attitude of Italy.20. It is not yet known whether the recent meeting of the two Dictatorson the Brenner will have any influence upon Italy&apos;s attitude to the war. On theother hand, we think it right to mention that the intervention of Italy on the sideof Germany would greatly complicate our difficulties. It is probably true that herarmy is in no shape to fight against a first-class Power, owing to poor morale, lackof training, and shortage of material resources. Nevertheless, Italy&apos;s entry intothe war against us would involve the detachment of considerable naval forces from the North Sea to the Mediterranean; and she could, by naval and air actionalone close that sea to our shipping, and force us for tbe time being to use the cape route.   This would be a heavy strain on our mercantile marine.21. If, as we think may be the case, Italy is at the cross roads, all possible steps should be taken to ensure that she moves in the right direction. It might,for example, be thought that our best course was to arrange a show of force inthe Middle East with the object of impressing her with the dangers of rangingherself against us. On the other hand, it might be thought that this would beprovocative, and that the better policy was to maintain our present conciliatory attitude. This question is, of course, essentially a political one, but we think it important from the military point of view that it should be discussed with theFrench at the forthcoming meeting of the Supreme War Council.Propaganda.22. There are some grounds for the belief that our propaganda in germany is having useful results, and this should be continued and intensified, particularly by wireless and secret channels, since leaflet dropping by air will be restrictedduring the short nights of summer. We should, however, direct particular attention to the importance of vigorous propaganda in neutral countries,particularly in the Balkans and the Middle East. Vigorous and immediate measures must also be taken to counter enemy propaganda and subversive activities, especially in Middle Eastern countries, where there is some reason tothink they are making headway.Conclusions.23. The Allies embarked upon this war incompletely prepared and in aposition of dangerous weakness relative to the enemy on land and in the air. Wehave so far conducted it in accordance with a carefully considered and agreed policy. We have not yet reached the stage, and are unlikely to reach it this year,when we can adopt a general offensive strategy except at sea and in the economic sphere.24. Time, however, is on our side only if we take the fullest possibleadvantage of it. It is essential particularly in view of the closer Russo-Germsncollaboration that we should be in a position to pass to the offensive at theearliest possible moment.   We should therefore shrink from no sacrifices and
from no measures, however drastic, to intensify and accelerate the building upof our resources with a view to shortening the period that must elapse before wecan pass to a general offensive strategy.25. The lack of spectacular military events tends to create pressure toundertake projects that offer little prospect of decisive success and are calculated to impair our resources and to postpone ultimate victory. This tendency shouldbe resisted. At the same time our object should be to harass the enemy materiallyand morally wherever the opportunity offers or can he created, provided that suchenterprises are commensurate with our resources, and that they do not involvepolitical and military disadvantages disproportionate to the effects likely to beachieved.(Signed)      C. L. N. NEWALL.DUDLEY POUND.EDMUND IRONSIDE.Cabinet War Room.




</content>
</cab>
