<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/5/10 images: 120-131</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  January 1940.SECRET. ^.......Copy No.W.P. (40) SO.(Also P.O.G. 17.)TO BE KEPT UNDER LOOK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.EQUIPMENT AND RAW MATERIALS FOR ROUMANIA.Memorandum by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence and theMinister without Portfolio.ON the 19th January Lord Hankey&apos;s Committee on Preventing Oil from reaching Germany, completed a review of the present position of Germanoil supplies, in which they dealt, among other matters, with Roumania asa source of supply (W.P. (40) 26). The last paragraph of that Report contained the following suggestion : &quot; That the Roumanian Government should be warned that if they take action calculated to interfere with the exportation of supplies of oil byproducing companies in which British or French capital exercises acontrolling interest, they must expect to meet with corresponding difficulties and delays in the supply of commodities to be furnished to them by theBritish or French Governments.&quot;2. The latest information as to the continued obstructive attitude of theRoumanian Government towards the execution of our policy rendered it necessarythat we should follow the above suggestion up with the least possible delay,particularly in connection with the recent request of the Roumanian Ministerfor further war equipment and credits. The Minister for Co-ordination ofDefence accordingly summoned a special meeting of Ministers on the19th January to consider what commodities Roumania requires from this countryand France, and how far it is practicable or desirable to use them as a bargaining counter to prevent interference by the Roumanian Government with the exportation of British and French controlled supplies of oil.3. At this meeting there were present, besides the Minister for Co-ordina-tion of Defence and the Minister without Portfolio The Secretaries of State for War and Air.The Minister for Economic Warfare.The Secretary for Mines.The Secretary of the Department of Overseas Trade;and official representatives of the Treasury;Foreign Office;Admiralty;Air Ministry;War Office;Board of Trade;Ministry of Supply;Mines Department; and export Credits Guarantee Department.[20675] jj
* Appendix I.4. The Committee had before them a memorandum by the Chairman of theAllied Demands Committee (Sir Arthur Robinson) reviewing the position on supplies to Roumania, a letter from the Treasury containing certain suggestions as to policy, and a draft telegram drawn up as a result of an interdepartmental conference.5. In addition, most of the Ministers present had received a copy of a letterfrom the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to the Minister without Portfolio,a copy of which, together with Lord Hankey&apos;s letter to which it is a reply, isattached herewith *6. The policy towards Roumania, which Lord Halifax proposes to pursue,may be summarised as follows : (1) We must make the utmost use of all the cards in our hand in order to compel the Roumanians to allow us to take oil up to the maximum possible quantities, and particularly in order to induce them to allowfriendly companies to place contracts freely.(2) The first thing to be done is to make it clear that any actual deliveries ofwar materials to Roumania would be withheld unless the Roumaniansadopt a reasonable attitude over oil. The same pressure could beexercised over any other supplies to Roumania,, including the rawmaterials for which the Roumanian Minister has asked, and any other commodities which the Roumanians have bought or are trying to buyunder credit or by other means.(3) They would be more likely to come to terms if we could give a definite and detailed account of how we could help them in the event of theirreaching agreement with us. The first essential is to make up ourown minds without delay as to what supplies under these heads wewould, given complete satisfaction over oil, be able to spare forRoumania.(4) It is the policy of the Government to strengthen Roumania as much aspossible, but this policy has not yet been translated into any decisionto give special treatment to her in the matter of war material orother supplies, and in view of our other commitments it is unlikelythat this will be done in present circumstances on political orstrategical grounds alone. On the other hand, if we continue to be unable to give the Roumanians any serious assistance, they will turnmore and more to Germany and will inevitably want to pay theGermans in oil for the material with which the latter are ready tosupply them out of their Polish loot.(5) Other forms of pressure lie in the Clearing and Payments agreement and the possibility of granting further credits, for which theRoumanian Minister is angling. As regards credits, the Minister isbeing told that we cannot reach a definite decision now, but will beprepared to consider his request again in April or June.(6) Generally speaking, the only method seems to be to get clearly into our minds what concessions of every kind we are in a position to make and what total conditions we insist upon.(7) When this has been done and we have a clear idea of how we stand inregard to our own offers the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs will send for the Roumanian Minister and present him with a completeset of proposals.(8) In the meanwhile no further promises or offers of any kind should bemade to the Roumanian Minister by any Department. This, however,should not prevent the British Minister in Roumania from continuing to press in the strongest possible manner for the approval of the long-term contracts already submitted by the friendly companies or for thegrant of export licences for the quantities of oil which we havepurchased.(9) Meanwhile, our correct policy is to continue to do everything possiblewhile the Danube is frozen to consolidate our position.
7. In order to carry out these proposals the first step is to arm the foreign secretary with particulars as to what supplies the British and French Govern-ments would-be able to spare for Roumania in return for a more accommodatingattitude by the Government of that country on the question of oil supplies.8. The original credit in the spring of 1939 was for  5-^ million, of whichgoods to the value of  2,110,000 have already been despatched to Roumania.These include such important items as 40 short-nose Blenheims and 12 Hurricanes,with ancillary equipment, as well as boots, clothing, saddlery, tents, medicaJappliances and motor vehicles.9. The above items, having already been despatched, are of no value as a bargaining factor for the future.10..   The following, however, can be used for this purpose :   Remarks.Goods ready for immediate delivery 300,000 These include 3 motorGoods on order        ...       .......    1,666,000 torpedo boats cost-Balance of original credit      ...    1,500,000 ing  200,000, which,although handedover, might be sub-jected to hindranceor delay in de-par ture.Owing to the rise in costs, however, if the Roumanian requirements as previouslyagreed are to be supplied,  2 million will have to be added to the last item of 1,500,000 to pay for them. These potential requirements comprise further boots,clothing and cloth, medical apparatus and also cotton yarns.- 11. Up to this point we have mentioned only the materials that were agreedor were still being discussed with the Roumanians arising out of the originalcredit. Quite recently the Roumanian Government has presented a further listof so extravagant a character as almost to raise doubts as to its bona fides. this list has not yet been examined by the Allied Demands Committee. So far as HisMajesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom are concerned, the armamentsportion of these new demands, to which we referred in paragraph 19 of our second report, is for the most part impossible to meet. The list also contains extravagantdemands for raw materials. But some of these can be obtained from the BritishEmpire countries whose currencies are based on sterling (and also Egypt, Sudanand Iraq) and it may be possible to go some way to meet the Roumanian demands in this respect. In this connection we note from a despatch by Sir ReginaldHoare dated the 5th January, 1940, that the Roumanian President of the Councilspoke of Roumania&apos;s urgent need for raw materials, so that they may possesssome value  IS Si bargaining factor.12. Before any approach is made to the Roumanian Government, however,we think it advisable that we should ascertain precisely from the French Govern-ment how far they are supplying or can supply Roumanian requirements so asto fortify the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs with a complete list ofarticles which are available to the Allies as a bargaining factor in the oilnegotiation. Sir Arthur Robinson, as Chairman of the Anglo-french -ordinating Committee for Supplies (British Section) has undertaken this task and will forward the results, in the first instance, to the Minister without portfolio, who will at once get in touch with the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs. &apos;; 13. So far as supplies are concerned, therefore, we are not in a positionto give the Foreign Secretary the information he requires until Sir ArthurRobinson has been able to furnish the complete list.14.   Although our meeting had been arranged primarily to consider thequestion of supplies, we took the opportunity to give some attention to the other-forms of pressure available to us.   We suggest that, to make up in some degree[20675] b 2
for our inability to furnish armaments to. Roumania owing to the paramountneeds of our own Forces, and as a very special concession which has not beengranted to other countries, His Majesty&apos;s Government1 should offer that 25 percent, of the proceeds of oil exported from Roumania and paid into the ClearingAccount should be made available not only for the purchase of raw material and supplies from the United Kingdom and other British Empire sterling countries, but also, in exceptional cases, from third&apos; countries. This should besubject to the limitation that not more than 10 per cent, of the sterling proceedswould have to be converted into dollars for the purpose of these purchases.We suggest that Flis Majesty&apos;s Government should themselves make these purchases in third countries and resell the goods so purchased to the roumanian government. This would give to the Roumanian Government the benefit of theorganisation which Flis Majesty&apos;s Government have set up for purchasing arma-ments and materials in third countries. This provision would be in substitution for the proposal that 25 per cent, of the proceeds of oil exports paid into3theClearing should be convertible into United States dollars, but it would equallyhave the effect of assisting the Roumanian Government to cover their require-ments in third countries where these cannot be provided from the sterling area.Conclusions:Our conclusions on which action is already being taken are as follows : (1) That firm and active steps on the lines proposed by the Secretary of Statefor foreign Affairs in Appendix I (2) (summarised in paragraph 6)should be taken to ensure, whether by inducement or by threat, thatthe Roumanian Government adopt a more accommodating attitudetowards the requirements of His Majesty&apos;s Government in respectof oil.(2) That a complete list of the means of pressure available to us must be presented to the Foreign Secretary as soon as possible.(8) That so far as the Roumanian demands for supplies are concerned, thematerial required should be completed as soon as possible by theChairman of the Anglo-French Co-ordinating Committee for Supplies(Sir Arthur Robinson), who will forward it to the Minister without portfolio for transmission to the Foreign Secretary. (See alsoconclusions (7) to (10) below.)(4) That as regards financial arrangements the following proposals of theTreasury should be approved : (i) The offer to pay up to 25 per cent, in dollars for oil should be withdrawn.(ii) Sterling at Roumania&apos;s free disposal in the Clearing should beavailable to buy (a) raw materials from the sterling area, of which suppliescan be made available. A list of these should be givenindicating what is, on present indications, likely to beavailable (see (3) above);(b) such munitions as may be available in the United Kingdomnow or later (at present little will be available for earlydelivery);(c) war material from third countries, e.g., Italy, and, in exceptional cases and within prescribed limits, theUnited States of America. Such material to be boughtby His Majesty&apos;s Government and resold to Roumania,(United States dollar commitments to be limited to10 per cent, of the total amount paid for oil.)(iii) A further credit of  2 million to be granted to enable contracts to be placed to cover Roumania&apos;s remaining requirements underthe existing programme.
(iv) His Majesty&quot;s Government will facilitate the export of 3 motor torpedo boats.Boots already ordered (when available).Boots, clothing amd cloth, yarns and medical apparatus tocomplete existing programme for future delivery.Raw material and munitions to be paid for through the clearing.on condition that and as long as export licences are given without restrictions and without imposing unreasonable con-ditions to Roumanian oil companies to export to the destina-tions which they desire; and provided that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment receive a definite assurance that no commitmenthas been or will be given to Germany which ensures her a fixedquota and would thus prevent export licences being given asstipulated.(5) That the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should be invited tocommunicate to the Roumanian Government the decisions recorded in(4) above and to request their acceptance.(6) That unless and until the condition referred to at the end ofparagraph (4) above is fulfilled, no further promises of any kind .should be made to the Roumanian Minister by any GovernmentDepartment, and Government Departments should hold up all exportof goods to Roumania and export licences in connection therewith.Further instructions will be issued to Departments when this ban islifted. In this connection the Admiralty are asked to take suitablesteps to hold up the departure from England of the 3 motor torpedo boats recently handed over to the Roumanian authorities.(7) That the Allied Demands Committee, in working out details, should assume (a) That an additional credit of  2 million will be granted to cover the cost of requirements, the supply of which was originallyagreed with the Roumanians, but their export will at all timesbe dependent on the fulfilment of the conditions stated at theend of Conclusion (4) above.(b) That as regards shipments of goods, they should act in accordancewith Conclusion (6) above.(c) That in principle it is desirable to meet the new Roumaniandemands provided that the furnishing of supplies at all timesdepends on the fulfilment of the condition at the end of conclusion (4) ahove.id) That they are desired to examine the possibility of supplying rawmaterials from the sterling area, whether or not such materials are included in the list of the Roumanian requirements detailedin Annex B of Paper No: A.D. (40) 7, and report as early aspossible to the Minister without Portfolio.(e) That no further credit (other than that referred to in (a) above),would be offered to the Roumanian Government at present.(8) That the Minister without Portfolio should be asked to co-ordinate thenecessary action in connection with this matter, and to keep thesituation under constant review with a view to the removal at theappropriate moment of the present temporary ban on exports to roumania and its reimposition at any time should the roumanian government in the future fail to hold to their assurances.(9) That Departments should keep the Minister without Portfolio informed in detail as to the position of supplies promised to the Roumaniansunder the following headings : (I) Items for which contracts have already been placed and whichare under supply.(II) Items agreed to with the Roumanians but for which contracts have not yet been placed.[20675] b 3
Departments should also notify the Minister without Portfolio of anyother inducements which might usefully be employed in these negotiations.(10) That the Chairman of the Anglo-French Co-ordinating Committee for supplies (British Section) should be invited to keep the minister without Portfolio informed as to the position of French supplies to roumania.(11) That the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should be invited tocommunicate to the French Government the action taken and proposedby His Majesty&apos;s Government with a view to corresponding action being taken by the French.Note. Following this meeting the attached Telegram (Appendix II) was sent by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to the British Ministerat Bucharest.(Initialled) H.-
(1)Minister without Portfolio to Secretary of State for Foreign. Affairs.(Secret.) January 10, 1940.AS I mentioned to you the other day, the Roumanian Government have notbeen behaving very well to the Allies over supplies of oil. Apart from their recent agreement with Germany, for which they have a plausible case, they havethreatened a system of quotas, which would gravely hamper our plans for preventing Roumanian oil from reaching Germany. Although the President ofthe Council and the Minister of National Economy have denied that any Govern-ment decision has been taken on the subject, Sir Reginald Hoare reports that heis convinced that such a proposal is under very serious consideration. worse than that, the Roumanian Government have refused their approval to long-term contracts for the supply of oil, which companies friendly with us were on thepoint of concluding in pursuance of a suggestion made earlier on by theRoumanian Government that we should buy as much of their produce aspossible; and, in addition, they have refused licences for the export of oil in execution of contracts which they had previously approved.This is only the barest summary of a position which will be dealt withfully in a report which Lord Chatfield and I are now preparing for the Cabinet.I understand that at this moment the Roumanians are pressing us to supply them with certain armaments (which, of course, we can only supply in comparatively limited amounts), and for Empire raw materials. Although Ipresume that the policy of the Government is to strengthen Roumania as muchas possible, and that an agreement to supply whatever we can is eminentlydesirable, I suggest that a hint should be given to the Roumanian Governmentthat actual deliveries will depend upon their adopting a reasonable attitude in facilitating the export of oil which the companies in which we are interestedsucceed in selling.I should hope also that if, in practice, the Roumanians withhold instalmentsof our supplies of oil, we should withhold instalments of anything we are dueto give to them. As M. Tilea is, I understand, rather active just now in trying to secure supplies, I thought it as well to utter a caveat about any promises wemay be giving in anticipation of our Report to the War Cabinet.I am sending a copy of this to Lord Chatfield, the Minister for economic warfare, the Secretary for Mines and the Minister of Supply.(Signed) &apos;       HANKEY.(2)Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to Minister without Portfolio.(Confidential.)My dear Maurice, Foreign Office, January 18, 1940.THANK you for vour letter of the 10th January about the Roumanianattitude in regard to oil supplies, and the possibility of exercising pressure on them by refusal to provide war material and other supplies.2. I entirely agree with you that we must make the utmost use of ailthe cards in our hand in order&apos; to compel the Roumanians to allow us to takeoil up to the maximum possible quantities, and particularly in order to induce them to allow friendly companies to place contracts freely. The cards whichwe hold are not all of equal strength, but if used together and at a suitablemoment might prove quite effective. As the general question is somewhatcomplicated, perhaps you will forgive me if I set out the various points, as i see them, fairly fully.&quot;3. The first thing we could do, as you say, is to make it clear that anyactual deliveries of war materials to Roumania would be withheld unless the roumanians adopt a reasonable attitude over oil.   The same pressure could be
exercised in regard to any other supplies to Roumania, including the rawmaterials for which Tilea has asked, and any other commodities which the roumanians have bought, or are trying to buy, under credit or by other means.4. I think a first essential is that we should without delay make up our minds as to what supplies under these heads we would, given complete satisfac-tion over oil, be able to spare for Roumania. To what extent, for instance, could we in any circumstances meet the Roumanian demand for arms 1 Tilea recentlytold Chatfield that his country might be satisfied with static anti-aircraft gunsand anti-tank rifles, knowing that there is a shortage of mobile anti-aircraft and anti-tank guns. But I do not know how far even this request could be met, andI imagine that, unless a general directive is given to the supply departments on grounds of high policy, nothing very definite will come of this request or ofTilea&apos;s other demands for military, naval and air equipment. The same applies to the various lists of raw materials which Tilea has presented. The presentsituation is that Tilea&apos;s efforts (which are many-sided and not always consistent)are having a generally unsympathetic reception, which is explained, and probablyquite justified, by the known obstructiveness of the Roumanians about oil. Theresult, however, is that the Roumanians as yet have no definite knowledge of whatthey are losing by their obstructiveness. I feel sure that they would be far more likely to come to heel if we could give a definite and detailed account of how wecould help them in the event- of their reaching agreement with us. A mere hintthat we shall be obstructive is much less valuable, particularly as Tilea&apos;experience gives him nothing to make him expect that our capacity for meetingRoumanian needs is very high. In this connexion may I draw your attention to paragraphs 7 and 8 of Hoare&apos;s telegram No. 32, of which I enclose a copy?5. I therefore feel that it might be desirable to set out, in connexion perhapswith your paper to the Cabinet on the oil situation, the importance which we attach to what I may call the &quot; carrot &quot; policy in dealing with Roumania. It iscertainly the policy of the Government to strengthen Roumania as much aspossible, but this policy has not yet been translated into any decision to give special treatment to her in the matter of war material or other supplies, and, inview of our other commitments, it is, I think, unlikely that this will be done inpresent circumstances on political or strategical grounds alone. Incidentally, Ishould mention that I have just seen a letter from Hoare, in which he warns us that, if we continue to be unable to give the Roumanians any serious assistance,they will turn more and more to Germany, and will inevitably want to pay theGermans in oil for the war material which they are ready to supply them without of their Polish loot.6. I understand that meetings of the appropriate committees are at present being held to assess the value of the commodities which we are now proposing to deliver to Roumania, but, if we want to ascertain the utmost that we coulddeliver, a higher initiative will be required.7. Other forms of pressure which we possess lie in the Clearing and Pay-ments questions, and also in the possibility of granting further credits Tileahas already been angling for an increase. As you know, Tilea has alreadybeen handed a draft revised agreement under which we have agreed to make certain concessions in regard to sterling allocations, provided that the Roumanianson their part will sign two Agreed Minutes, one of which relates to oil. I gather that there is little likelihood that they will accept this, and Hoare hasnow suggested that, even if they do, the oil Minute would have little value inpractice unless we can find out exactly what commitments the Roumanians have accepted towards the Germans. Only then could we know what sort of under-takings the Roumanians could give to us in good faith. It seems to me thatthis object will be very difficult to achieve, as it is clearly the policy of the roumanians at present to keep each party in the dark about their commitments to the other. But, nevertheless, I still feel that it would be useful to haveRoumanian signature of the two Minutes, though it is true that nothing signed by the Roumanians can in present circumstances be regarded as binding.Fortunately the Germans are in this respect up against the same difficulty as ourselves. As regards credits, Tilea is being told that we cannot reach a definite decision now, but will be prepared to consider his request again in April or inJune. Here again we might be able to turn the offer into a positive one, dependenton sgtisfaction over oil.
8. Generally speakings the only method seems to me to be to get clearly in our minds what concessions of every kind we are in a position to make and what total conditions we insist upon. We could then go to Tilea with the handcomplete, and I think our position could be a fairly strong one.9. If you agree with the above suggestions, I would like to suggest thatno further promises or offers of any kind should be made to M. Tilea by any department, but that when we have got a clear idea of how we stand in regardto our own offers, I should send for him myself and present a complete set of proposals. This would not, of course, prevent Hoare from continuing to press in the strongest possible manner for the approval of the long-term contractsalready submitted by the friendly companies and for the grant of export licences for the quantities of oil which we have purchased.10. If you consider-that any additional paper for the Cabinet is requiredin support of your own memorandum I will, of course, be glad to prepare sucha paper. I much say that generally speaking I feel that our correct policy isto continue to do everything possible, while the Danube is frozen, to consolidateour position.11. While on this question, I would like to refer to one point which was raised in Hoare&apos;s telegram No. 32 (not reproduced). You will have seen thathe there expresses the view that we should temporarily cease buying Roumanianoil and thus force down the at present artificially inflated prices. This view iselaborated in Hoare&apos;s telegram No. 38 (not reproduced), of which I also enclosea copy for convenience of reference. I understand that this idea was discussed at :&apos; recent meeting of your Committee, and that it was felt that the attendantrisks in such a policy are greater than the possible advantages.12. I am sending copies of this letter to Chatfield, Cross, Geoffrey Lloydand Burgin, and if you agree, I would like to send copies of the correspondenceto the First Lord, the Secretary of State for War, the Secretary of State for air and the Chancellor of the Exchequer; and also to the Department of OverseasTrade.Yours sincerely,HALIFAX.P.S. Since the above was drafted, I have received a letter from Chatfieldsuggesting a meeting of Ministers, in regard to the question of supplies forRoumania, for Friday, the 19th January. I shall, of course, be glad to sendsomebody to attend this meeting, and in the meantime I think you may like toknow my views, as set out in the present letter.APPENDIX II.Telegram, No. 82 to Roumania, dated January 21, 1940.OIL.Refusal of Roumanian Government to approve long-term contracts, refusal of export licences for purchases already made, and reported establishment of aState Commission whose object must be to force friendly companies to sell toGermany, have led His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom to reviewthoir whole attitude towards question of purchase of oil from Roumania. It hasbeen decided that we must make use of any means of inducement and pressurewe possess in order to secure a more reasonable attitude on the part of theRoumanian Government.2. It is clear that in view of constant German pressure mere promises fromthe Roumanian Government have no value, and our policy will, therefore, be tomake no concessions or promises to Roumania except pari passu with actualdeliveries of oil. We propose to invite the French Government to adopt a similarattitude. The following four paragraphs summarise the methods of inducementand pressure of which it is proposed we should make use.3. Owing to increase of prices the goods which Roumania had intended topurchase under the  5-1- million credit will not be covered without an additionalcredit of about  2 million. We are prepared to grant this, but the actual exportof goods (which include boots, clothing and cloth, yarns and medical apparatus,
and are, consequently, very urgently required by Roumania), would at all timesbe dependent on the fulfilment of the conditions in paragraph 7 below.4 Supplies already ordered by Roumania and ready for immediate ship-ment amount to a value of about  300,000, and include 3 motor torpedo boatsalready handed over to Roumanian Government but still in England, and armyboots. These will probably be held up (though the question of the boats is not as yet finally settled) until conditions in paragraph 7 below are fulfilled. Onthe same conditions all export licences for goods to Roumania will now be refuseduntil further notice, including licences for the war material ordered under theexisting credit but not yet delivered, which amounts to some  1,600,000.5. Offer which has been made by the Treasury to pay up to 25 per cent, in dollars for oil purchased in Roumania will be withdrawn. Following alternativeconditions will be put before Roumanian Government: All sterling atRoumanian free disposal in the Clearing will be available to buy : (a) Rawmaterials from the sterling area of which supplies can be made available. Alist of these will be prepared, (b) Such munitions as may be available in theUnited Kingdom now or later (at present little would be available for earlydelivery), (c) War material from third countries, e.g., Italy and, in exceptional cases and within prescribed limits, the United States. Such material to be boughtby His Majesty&apos;s Government and resold to Roumania. Dollar commitments inthis connexion would be limited to 10 per cent, of the total amount paid for oil.The advantage to Roumania of this offer is that it places at her disposal for purchases in the United States the whole purchasing organisation of HisMajesty&apos;s Government.  No such concession has been made for any other country.&quot;!- 6. The list of requirements handed in by M. Tilea on his return mentionsenormous quantities of armaments, raw materials and mixed manufactured articles to a value of some  10 million. Supply of most of these would, in anycase, be quite impossible and we cannot believe that the request was made withany expectation of acceptance. It looks more like a move in the game designedto justify Roumanian attitude over oil. We propose to take the line that we will do our best to meet Roumania&apos;s requirements in raw materials and manufactured articles and also in munitions if and when we are able to do so. All deliverieswould, however, be dependent on conditions in paragraph 7 below. We are examining urgently the position of supply from the sterling area of all goods which might be useful for Roumania, whether or not included in the Roumanianlists. The greater the offers we can make here the more the Roumanians will appreciate the disadvantages of obstruction over oil, and we hope to make the proposition as attractive as possible. In any case, however, we are not prepared at present to consider an additional credit for these purposes, though the prospectof such a credit will be kept alive in the background as an added inducement.7. The following are the conditions which we shall require to see fulfilledbefore agreeing to any of the above concessions or permitting any exports Avhat-eyer to Roumania : (a) The issue without restriction and without unreasonableconditions of export licences enabling Roumanian oil companies to export to anydestination they desire, (b) A definite assurance from the Roumanian Govern-ment that no commitment has been or will be given to Germany ensuring her a fixed quota, which would prevent export licences being given as stipulated in (a)and would lead to an impossible position in which friendly companies would be compelled to sell to Germany.8. I propose to inform M. Tilea of the above decisions as soon as possible,and will telegraph to you immediately it is done in order that you may be in aposition to take parallel action with the Ministry for Foreign Affairs. In themeantime, if you have any comments to make, please telegraph as urgently aspossible.9. I await also your comments on reported establishment of a commissionof control over the oil industry. As regards rejection of contracts, explanationsgiven to you, as recorded in your telegram No. 47 [of the 18th January], are, ofcourse, quite inadequate. We cannot regard as valid an objection to the exportof oil owned by companies under British capital control on ground of the quantityinvolved.   You will doubtless press for further explanations.



</content>
</cab>
