<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/71/15 images: 151-154</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET!HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTcC(81) 35th COPY NO 79ConclusionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinetheld at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 5 NOVEMBER 1981at 9. 30 amPRESENTThe Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MPPrime Ministerhe Rt Hon William Whitelaw MP The Rt Hon Lord Hailshamecretary of State for the Home Department Lord Chancellorhe Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC MPhancellor of the Exchequerhe Rt Hon Francis Pym MPord President of the Councilhe Rt Hon John Nott MPecretary of State for Defencehe Rt Hon Michael Heseltine MPecretary of State for the Environmenthe Rt Hon Nicholas Edwards MPecretary of State for Waleshe Rt Hon Patrick Jenkin MPecretary of State for Industryhe Rt Hon David Howell MPecretary of State for Transporthe Rt Hon Leon Brittan QC MPhief Secretary, TreasuryThe Rt Hon Sir Keith Joseph MPSecretary of State for Education andScienceThe Rt Hon James Prior MPSecretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon Peter Walker MPMinister of Agriculture, Fisheries andFoodThe Rt Hon George Younger MPSecretary of State for ScotlandThe Rt Hon Humphrey Atkins MPLord Privy SealThe Rt Hon John Biffen MPSecretary of State for TradeThe Rt Hon Norman Fowler MPSecretary of State for Social ServicesThe Rt Hon Baroness YoungChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterSECRET
SECRETThe Rt Hon Nigel Law son MPSecretary of State for EnergyThe Rt Hon Norman Tebbit MPSecretary of State for EmploymentThe Rt Hon Cecil Parkinson MPPaymaster GeneralALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Michael Jopling MPParliamentary Secretary, TreasurySECRETARIATSir Robert ArmstrongMr R L Wade-Gery (Items 2 and 3)Mr D M Elliott (Items 2 and 3)Mr D H J Hilary (Item 1)Mr L J Harris (Item 1)CONTENTSItemSubjectPagePARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRS12FOREIGN AFFAIRSArab/Israel1Canadian Constitution23COMMUNITY AFFAIRS30/31 October Informal Meeting of Finance Ministers2iiSECRET
CONFIDENTIALtUAMENTARY   1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theJpAlRS House of Commons during the following week.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatMinisters should be careful in any public statements not to appear toenter into any commitments involving public expenditure which wentbeyond undertakings already given by the Cove rnmeint.   In particular, theSecretary of State for Social Services, if pressed during the Debate onthe Address, should go no further than confirming the existing pledgeto maintain the real value of state retirement pensions during thelifetime of the present Parliament.The Cabinet -Took note.REIGNFAIRSib/Israeliviouserence;(81) 34thlclusions,lute 22. THE LORD PRIVY SEAL said that there had been a last-minutehitch in the arrangements for four members of the European Community-Britain, France, Italy and the Netherlands - to participate in the pro-posed multinational force and observers in Sinai.    The ten members ofthe Community had reached agreement on a public statement by the fourGovernments designed to make clear that participation was consistentwith the Venice Declaration of June 1980 and that support for thearrangements associated with Israel&apos;s withdrawal from Sinai wasdistinct from the rest of the Camp David process; and on an anodynestatement by all ten Governments along the same lines.    These state-ments had been due to be published on 6 November.     But the UnitedStates Secretary of State, Mr Haig, to v/hom they had been shown inconfidence on 4 November, had reacted very unfavourably.    He waspressing in particular for the omission of any reference to the VeniceDeclaration.     This was a request which the European Governmentswere not in a position to accept.    Publication had therefore been sus-pended and representatives of the four Governments would be meetingin London on 6 November to consider how to proceed.    Meanwhile theIsraeli Government had publicly suggested that they would veto anypotential participant in the Sinai multinational force who enteredreservations inconsistent with the Camp David Agreement.    The presentsituation was particularly unsatisfactory for the British Government,who had from the beginning had good reasons for being reluctant toparticipate at all.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALnadian stitutionevious(crence:;(81) 33rdtclusions,Inttte 3THE LORD PRIVY SEAL said that the current conference between theFederal and Provincial Governments in Canada seemed to have got offto a reasonable start.    It was not likely to reach unanimous agreementon the problems associated with patriating the constitution, but it mightjust be able to produce a satisfactory compromise between the FederalGovernment and a reasonable number of the Provinces.    It wasimpossible to say how long the conference would last.The Cabinet -Took note.Immunity[fairs(31 Octoberormal MeetingFinancelusterseviousference:1(81) 34thinclusions,nute 33. THE CHANCELLOR QF THE EXCHEQUER said that discuseion of the30 May 1980 mandate at the 30-31 October informal meeting of FinanceMinisters had made no significant headway.  The Germans had presentedtheir case for some limit on their net contribution to the Communitybudget to be agreed alongside any solution proposed for the UnitedKingdom, and the Dutch had restated their earlier arguments for a newbudgetary framework in terms that to some extent echoed the approachhe had put forward in his speech in The Hague in June,    He had had aprivate talk in the margins of the meeting with Monsieur Delors, theFrench Finance Minister.    It was apparent that he at least recognisedthe need for the Community to find a solution to the budget problemsoon, though Monsieur Delors had made clear that this represented hispersonal approach and that there was as yet no agreed FrenchGovernment view on this subject.    Finance Ministers had also voicedtheir continuing concern at the refusal of the United States Governmentto intervene in the exchange markets ard their hope that this attitudemight give way to a greater willingness to co-operate with othermonetary authorities if the dollar weakened next year.    In a review ofthe economic situation within the Community, it was noteworthy that acommon pattern of financial stringency and public expenditurereductions was emerging throughout Europe; the Germans had nowembarked on their third round of expenditure cuts.The Cabinet -Took note.Cabinet Office5 November 1981CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
