<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/65/34 images: 322-401</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   May 1945.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (45) 284.3rd May, 1945.WAR CABINET.SUMMARY OF OPERATIONS OF BOMBER COMMAND FOR four weeks ENDING 22nd. APRIL, 1945.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.A. A detailed summary of operations is appended.B. Results of Operations.- v Despite adverse weather during the last week of March, in which operations were severely restricted, more sorties Avere despatched and more bombs droppedduring March than in any previous month. 21,341 sorties were despatchedand 67,637 tons of bombs dropped, as compared with the previous highest figuresof 20,659 sorties and 65,854 tons of bombs achieved in August, 1944.Oil Targets.The Harburg Rihenania oil refinery (4/5 April), and the oil plants ofLutzkendorf (4/5 and 7/8 April), Leuna (4/5 April) and Molbis (8/9 April)were, attacked with good results. Thereafter, with the rapid advance of theAllied armies, operations were directed in the main to ground support and navaltargets.Naval Targets.Highly successful attacks were made on the Deutsche, Germania andHowaldts Werke at Kiel (9/10 and 13/4 April) in the course of which the pocket battleship Admiral Scheer was capsized. (Print No. 1.) The Emden andHipper, which were also present, have probably been damaged by near misses and blast. Dockyard buildings destroyed or damaged include the covered-in sub-marine slips, engineering workshops, plate sheds and iron store. All three ship-yards received a heavy concentration of bombs. In an attack on the Blohm andVoss shipyards at Hamburg (8/9 April), severe damage was caused to manybuildings, including the construction shop, power house, gasworks and the dieseltesting shop, while many of the remaining buildings in the Stulcken yard werepartly or wholly destroyed. Very severe damage was also caused to the entranceof the Elbe tunnel, which was half destroyed, and to the two floating dry docks,one of which is wholly, and the other two-thirds submerged.In a daylight attack on the Finkenwarder U-boat pens at Hamburg(19th April) 7 direct hits were scored including five penetrations of the roof.(Print No. 2.)On the 16th April, 18 aircraft were despatched to attack the Lutzow atSwinemunde : 15 attacked dropping 11 x 12,000 and 48 x 1,000-lb. bombs. Threedirect hits were scored in addition to many near misses, and the stern of the shiois now resting on the bottom. (Print No. 3.) The island fortress of Heligolandwas attacked on the 18tih and again on the 19th April. Very heavy damage was caused, and nearly all the buildings destroyed. Of the 26 guns on the island,8 were definitely destroyed, a further 5 probably destroyed, and near misses onothers have undoubtedly caused some damage.   (Print No. 4.)Print No. 5 is a striking illustration of the capsized Tirpitz.[29830]
Communications Targets.Numerous successful attacks were carried out on marshalling- yards. PrintsNos. 6 and 7 show damage to the marshalling yards at Schwandorf(J6/17th April) and Pilsen (16/7th April), and Print No. 8 shows the damage to the railway traffic centre resulting from the attack on Potsdam (14/15th April).Other attacks were carried out on marshalling yards at Plauen, Nuremberg,BayreutJh and Leipzig, where three separate yards were attacked.German Towns.Nordhausen was attacked on the 3rd and 4th April. The town was almost completely devastated, and the GAP. Signals School in the south-east has hardlya building that is not wholly or nearly destroyed. Included in the devastationare the airfield control building, barrack blocks and hangars of the NordhausenAirfield, various railway tracks and sidings, and amongst other public utilities,the town gasworks. Only a small suburban area in the south-west escaped.(Print No. 9.) In addition to damage to the railway centre in the attack onPotsdam referred to above, the aircraft components factory of AradoFlugzeugwerke was severely damaged and several unidentified industries gutted.There was also considerable damage to the barrack buildings in the town.Results of Previous A attacks.The industrial area surrounding the Linden marshalling yards was severely damaged during the attack on Hanover (25th March). Severe fresh damage was caused in the western end of the Hannoverschen Maschinenbau A.G. where the pattern shop, foundries, press shop and other buildings were all heavily hit.Considerable damage was inflicted on the Vereinigte Leichtenstallwerke G.rn.b.H.,and further to the west part of the Gebriider Kortig A.G. destroyed. In the attack on Farge U-boat shelters (27th March), Laneasters dropped 13 x 22,000and 4 x 12,000-lb. DP. bombs, securing two definite penetrations of the roofalmost in the centre, and another probable hit on the western end. Print No. 10was taken during the attack. Prints Nos. 11-16 show some of the results achieved at Hildesheim (22nd March), Bocholt (22nd March), Nienburg Bridge(22nd March), Bad Oeynhausen Bridge (23rd March), Paderborn (27th March),and Dresden (13/14th February). Print No. 17 gives an interesting trio of photographs illustrating the progressive destruction by air raids of the citycentre and dock area of Bremen.A. H. M. S.Air Ministry,3rd May, 1945.APPENDIX.Summary of Operations.Date.Mar. 25TargetA ir craftDespatched.31Apr.   2/327/282929/3030/3126/27273/43tlanoverOsnabriickMinisterBerlin ...Farge, U-boat shelterFarge, oil storageAltonbogge Kdnigsborn, benzol plantHamm-Sachsen, benzol plantPaderbornBerlin ...llallendorf-Salzgitter, benzol plant berlin ...Berlin ...ErfurtHamburg, U-boat yardsBerlin ...       ...       ...MagdeburgNordhausen BarracksBerlin ...275156175862095767427682130484345468545025594
Date.April 44/577/88/999/101010/111111/1212/1313/1414/1515/161616/1717/181818/191919/202020/2121/22Target.Nordhausen TownNordhausen BarracksLutzkendorf, synthetic oil plantHamburg (Harburg), oil refinery......Merseburg (Leuna), synthetic oil plant berlin ...       ...MagdeburgSperrbrecher at IjmuidenMolbis, oil plant      ............Hamburg, Blohm and Voss U-boat yardsLutzkendorf. synthetic oil plant   ...Berlin ...DessauHamburg (Finkenwarder), U-boat shelter ...Hamburg, oil refineryKiel, Deutsche Werke and Germania shipyardsKiel, Howaldts Werke shipyardBerlin ...PlauenLeipzig/Engeldorf marshalling yardLeipzig/Mockau marshalling yardPlauen, marshalling yard   ...Leipzig/Wahren marshalling yard.Berlin ...Nuremberg, marshalling yardsBayreuth, marshalling yardBerlin ...Berlin ...Kiel, Deutsche Werke shipyard   ...BoizenburgHamburgStralsundRiesa, oil storagePotsdamBerlin ...      ...      ...      ...CuxhavenBerlin ...Swinemunde-LutzowPilsen, marshalling yardSchwandorf, marshalling yardBerlin ...      ...      ...      ...Cham, marshalling yardBerlin ...- Ingolstadt, airfieldHeligoland, (a) Main Island(b) Naval base ...(c) Dune, airfieldKomothau, marshalling yardBerlin ...Schleissheim, airfieldMunich-Pasing, railway transformer stationHeligoland, gun batteries   ...BerlinWittstock, airfieldRegensburg.Berlin ...Schleissheim, airfieldKiel    ...............Eggebek, airfieldAircraftDespatched...     15993.. 272.. 327..     341353115.. 186.. 440..     24228.... . 711740... 379... 220...      443713496... 3159577...     143...     122...    10797...    482  &apos;28872012... 51262...    -28...    10618...     233...    175641016143...     684...     160125123573649367935...    1007636...    10716In addition, 375 aircraft were despatched on small raids on German townsand other targets, 1,229 aircraft were employed in bomber support operations,and 1,314 mines were laid during the period.














































































</content>
</cab>
