<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/59/0 images: 38-51</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1953SECRETCopy No.C. (53) 5912th February, 1953CABINETFINANCES OF THE NATIONAL INSURANCE scheme memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Minister ofNational InsuranceAt the meeting on 12th June, 1952, we were asked to undertake a limitedenquiry into the financial prospects of the National Insurance Funds (C.C. (52)59th Conclusions, Minute 4).2.   A memorandum has now been prepared and is attached.3. Expenditure at present benefit rates, and on present conditions, from theNational Insurance Funds is expected to exceed income from contributions(including the Exchequer Supplement) by over  400 millions a year in 1977-78.In 1957-58 the excess will be over  100 millions. This excess, which will have tobe met by the Exchequer, is largely due to the growing cost of retirement pensions.There are three main factors:  (a) the pensionable population is expected to rise by more than 40 per cent.over the next 25 years;(b) only persons who pay the present rate of contribution from age 16 will pay sufficient to cover the cost of their pensions; in fact even personswho have contributed for comparatively short periods get the full rateof pension;(c) contributions will not be put to earn interest as in normal superannuationpractice, but used to meet current expenditure.4. On certain optimistic assumptions with regard to the maintenance of ahigh level of employment, the hours of work, the terms of trade and the percentageof the occupied in the total population, national income might be expected to riseby 1-^ per cent, to 2 per cent, a year. In that event the increase in the averagestandard of living would reduce the real weight of the burden of pensions at present rates. But a rising standard of living will in all probability create demands fora corresponding increase in the real value of pensions, and if any of the assumptionsfail, the future burden might be as intolerable as. it appears in the light of thenational income to-day.5. The proportion of occupied in the highest age groups has tended to fall partly as a result of the extension of superannuation schemes. Bearing in mind the other public burdens that will increase with an ageing population includingthe related problems of National Assistance it is essential that every effort shouldbe made to keep down the rising numbers of pensioners by extending the normal working life. Future demands for higher pensions to meet increases in prices andthe rising cost of living must therefore be considered in terms, not only of their immediate cost, but of their effect on the ultimate burden of retirement pensions.The growth of this burden could be checked if any future increase of benefit rates were to be linked with an adjustment of the National Insurance Scheme to raisethe effective minimum age at which able-bodied people may retire oh pension.The Report indicates alternative ways in which this could be done if and whenincreases of benefit and pension rates have to be considered.43728b
6. We endorse the recommendation that drastic action is not required atpresent. But this may become necessary, and meanwhile, we consider that it isessential that (a) account should be taken of the future, as well as the immediate, cost whenproposals for increased expenditure are under consideration;(b) future proposals for increases in the rates of benefit should be framed soas to keep the burden on the Exchequer as nearly as possible withinpresent expectations;(c) every support should be given to the campaign to change the traditionalviews about the age of retirement.R. A. B.O. P.12th February, 1953.FINANCE OF THE NATIONAL INSURANCE scheme memorandum by the Treasury, Ministry of National Insurance, government actuary and Economic Section of the Cabinet OfficeSummary of the MemorandumAn annual excess of expenditure over income begins in 1954-55, reaches over 100 millions in 1957-58,  275 millions in 1967-68, and over  400 millions a year in1977-78. The Exchequer will have to meet the excess in addition to the paymentof the fixed Exchequer supplement to contributions amounting to about  70 millions a year. Thus, by 1977-78 the total annual Exchequer charge rises to nearly  500millions paragraphs 1 and 2. &apos;:2. The excess of expenditure and the increasing Exchequer charge are mainly:due to retirement pensions. Not only will the population of pension age greatly increase, but new classes (self-employed and non-employed) have been brought intothe pension scheme, and pensions are paid at the full rate to persons who would only have earned them fully had they paid at the latest rate of contributions fromage 16; in fact they have paid at lower rates for comparatively short periods (at most since 1926). At present only 5 per cent, of the expenditure on retirement pensions is covered by past contributions. Apart from this, there will always bea gap between income and expenditure because current contributions are taken topay current pensions and are not therefore put to earn interest; this gap theExchequer will have to fill paragraphs 3 to 10.3. The expenditure could be still heavier if there were further inflation leading to higher pensions. There are also other public burdens that will increase with anageing population. National Assistance, paid for by the Exchequer, alreadysupplements pension in many cases, and changes in the rate of pension react on national Assistance expenditure paragraphs 11 to 13.4. The proportion of occupied in the highest age groups has tended to fallover a period and the extension of superannuation schemes will encourage thattendency. A radical change of attitude will be necessary if the trend is to be reversed. Given that change, there is scope in the next few years for bringing intooccupation a maximum of nearly 300,000 men fit but unoccupied between the ages of 65 and 70, and some above that age paragraphs 14 to 16.5. On past experience the national income might be expected to rise on average by \\ to 2\ per cent, a year. In that event, although the ratio of benefits to national income and the ratio of the Exchequer charge to personal incomes would still rise, the increase in the average standard of living would greatly reduce their ,real weight; but this all depends on certain optimistic assumptions that may not berealised, namely  ,(a) no fall in the percentage of the occupied in the total population;(b) a level of employment as high as recently; 0.(c) no significant reduction in the hours of work; and(d) no significant change for the worse in the terms of trade.
Any or all of these assumptions might fail and the future burden might then be asintolerable in fact as it appears in the light of the national income to-day, orconceivably even worse paragraphs 17 to 20.6. The present balances in the National Insurance and National Insurance(Reserve) Funds offer no remedy (paragraph 21); nor is it practicable, at any rate atpresent, to transfer the burden of the Exchequer supplement to the contributions of insured persons and their employers paragraphs 22 to 23.1. There may be demands for further increases in the pension rate if wagesincrease, and the pressure would be the greater and more difficult to resist if prices and the cost of living were also to increase. Should there have to be an increase inthe pension rate at any time the opportunity should be taken to increase the effectiveminimum pension age paragraphs 24 to 28.8. The main question is whether the future burden of pensions and theExchequer charge will become so unmanageable as to force a cut in pensionsbearing in mind that this would probably have to be accompanied by a radical change in the needs test for National Assistance if the drop in pensions were notto be followed by nearly as great an increase in expenditure on Assistance. Sucha drastic course is not recommended at the present juncture, when expenditure ishot yet outrunning income, so long before the burden begins seriously to rise to itspeak, and in view of the complete uncertainty of the future trend in the national income. But meanwhile, and until the future becomes clearer, it is at leastnecessary to avoid further increases in the future burden of expenditure and inparticular in pensions expenditure which adds directly to the Exchequer charge.Every support should be given to the campaign of the Ministry of Labour and national Service to change the traditional views about the age of retirement--paragraph 29.FINANCE OF THE NATIONAL INSURANCE scheme the Future Charges on the exchequer. Tables I and II show the annual expenditure and income of the national insurance Fund, in total and for the constituent items, for the next few years andat subsequent intervals up to .1977-78, on the assumption that the rates of benefit and contribution will remain unchanged. The figures are shown graphically inthe Appendix. Figures for the. years beyond 1978 are necessarily extremelyspeculative but, on certain assumptions as to the progress of the population, therewould be a further slight rise in retirement pensions followed by a very slow and relatively small fall in both benefits and contributions. The figures for 1955-56and subsequent years are based on the assumption of 4 per cent, unemployment lower rates being assumed before then. The contributions towards the health service are excluded from both income and expenditure.Table I-Expenditure  millions	Retirement			Widows&apos;		Financial.	Pensions	Unemploy-	Sickness	(under 60)	Other Benefits	Year	(including	ment	Benefit	and	and	Total	Widows	Benefit		Guardians&apos;	Administration		over 60)			Benefits			(1)	(2)	(3)	(4)	(5)	(6)i953-54	344	30	93	30	37	,5341954-55	355	45	- 98	32	38	5681955-56	364	61	104	34	39	6021956-57	374	62	110	36	40	6221957-58	384	62	113	37	40	6361967-68	556	64	121	38	44	8231977-78	688	64	118	34	49	953
Table II Income&quot;5:   : ;   i&apos;.&apos; i       millions	Contributions from	Exchequer		/    Financial	Insured Persons	Supplements to	Interest	Total IncomeYear	and Employers	Contributions	on Funds	1953-54	(1)	(2)	(3)	(4)	444	71	41	5561954-55	r   ;  439	70	41	5501955-56	431	69	41	5411956-57	427	68	41	536-,. 1957-58	424	68	41	5331967-68	438	70	41	5491977-78	427	68	41	5362. In Table III below the total expenditure and income of the national insurance Funds in the years to 1977-78 are- combined to give the net excess of. expenditure over income. When the original Act of 1946 was passed it was expected;, on the basis adopted for the estimates, that the expenditure would fromthe start exceed the income from contributions (including Exchequer supplements)and interest on the initial Funds. Provision was accordingly made in Section 2 (3) (b)for annual Exchequer payments to meet the residual difference and thus to maintainintact the balance of the Funds. But, mainly because the rate of unemployment was much lower than anticipated, income exceeded expenditure throughout theperiod to October 1951, when the financial provisions were modified. As incomewas still expected slightly to exceed expenditure for a few years without the aid of payments under Section 2 (3) (b), that Section of the original Act was (temporarily)repealed by the Act of 1951. It will be seen, however, from column (3) of Table III,that expenditure on the basis of the 1952 Act will very shortly exceed income,including the Exchequer supplements, and the excess will grow rapidly. It will,therefore, be necessary in the legislation following the quinquennial review to make provision on the lines of Section 2 (3) (b) for annual payments from the exchequer to meet the residual difference between expenditure and income. The alternative would be to allow the excess of expenditure to be met for a time from the investedbalance in the insurance fund and reserve fund, but, as indicated in paragraph 21below, such a course would be undesirable for many reasons. Columns (3) and (5)of Table III accordingly show for each year the excess of expenditure over income to be met by the Exchequer, and the total charge on the Exchequer includingsupplements to contributions, assuming that Section 2 (3) (b) is reinstated and the balances in the Funds are kept intact.Table III Excess of Expenditure over Income and Charge on Exchequer  millions			Excess of		Total charge			Expenditure	Exchequer	on ExchequerFinancial	Expenditure	Income	over Income	Supplements	includingYear			to be met from	to	Supplements to			Exchequer	Contributions	Contributions	(1)	,    (2)	(3)	-       (4)	.   (5).1953-54    ...	534	556	[-22*]	71	&apos;   ,711954-55    ...	568	550	18	70	881955-56    ...	602	541	61	69	130.1956-57    ...	622	536	86	68	1541957-58	636 &apos;	533  .	103	68	1711967,-68    ...	823	549	274&apos;	70	344   -1977-78    ....	953 :	536	417.....	68	. 485* Excess of income over expenditure and consequent1 increase in Fund. ;., .     ..
3. The outstanding features of the tables are the steadiness of the annual income, the preponderance in the expenditure of the payments for retirement pen-sions and their increase over the years and hence the growing annual charge onthe Exchequer as guarantor of the scheme. The cost of retirement pensions willdouble in the next quarter of a century; these pensions already account for nearly two-thirds and will increase to nearly three-quarters of the total benefit payments.Growth of Expenditure on Retirement Pensions4. The growth of the expenditure on retirement pensions is due to three main factors (1) The expected increase in the number of persons of pensionable age whichrises from 6f- millions in 1952 to 9f millions in 1977 i.e., by more than40 per cent.;(2) the inclusion from 1958 onwards of pensions for the new classes first broughtinto insurance in 1948 which adds to the bill  30 millions a year, rising to  150 millions a year by 1977-78; and(3) the growing expenditure on increments earned where claims for retirement pension are postponed beyond the minimum pension age estimated torise from less than  5 millions in 1953-54 to about  80 millions by1977-78. These figures represent the amounts paid in the year in theform of increments (additional to the basic pension), on the assumptionthat in the future retirement will be postponed beyond age 65 (60 forwomen) to a slightly greater degree than at present.5. The future cost of retirement pensions in money terms is much greaterthan originally contemplated. The Beveridge Report advocated 245. a week for asingle person and 40s. a week for a married couple as an ultimate arrangement after20 years, but starting with much lower figures; the Coalition White Paper advocatedrates of 20,s. and 35j. respectively to come into force at the beginning of the scheme without any transitional period of lower rates; the 1946 Act put the rates at 26s.and 42s. from the start, and they are now 32^. 6d. and 54.?. Increments were originally to be Is. instead of the present 3s. for every yearY delayed retirement.Why Income will fall short of Expenditure6. The combined rates of contribution to be paid by the insured person, his employer (if any) and the Exchequer by way of supplement are calculated on theprinciple that the contributions for entrants at the minimum age, if accumulatedat interest, should, on average, just suffice to pay their benefits as they becomedue. The 1946 Act, however, conceded full benefits, not only to the existing insuredpersons of all ages (though the pensions contributions paid by them in the past werenecessarily at inadequate rates and for a relatively short period at the most from1926), but also to the large number of persons brought into the scheme at agesover 16 who had never previously been insured. In addition it conceded fullbenefits to existing pensioners, and this resulted in a very heavy annual expenditureon pensions from the start. It is estimated that at present no less than 95 per cent,of the expenditure on retirement pensions is in respect of benefits which are not adequately covered by contributions. Gradually this proportion will fall until after some 70 or 80 years on the assumption of no further increases in the rates of benefit all expenditure will be in respect of benefit for which adequate contributions willhave been paid.7. There would always, however, have to be a balancing payment from theExchequer (in addition to the fixed supplement to contributions) and this requiresexplanation. It is to be found mainly in the method of financing retirement pensions; the contributions would only suffice to meet the benefits of those con-cerned if the portions not currently required for this purpose were set aside tobuild up reserves and earn interest as commonly happens in superannuation funds;but this has not been done. It has never been Government policy to build upreserves to meet contingent liabilities on a national scale; the practice is toiiseincome currently to meet appropriate national expenditure and in return to guarantee future benefits. Current income from contributions has in the present instance been largely used to meet the cost of current pensions which, as already explained, are far from adequately covered by contributions.
8. There has so far been an unexpected excess of income over expenditure,due principally to light unemployment since the new scheme started, and this has gone to swell the balances of the funds of the scheme. These balances, however,are not in any sense actuarial reserves; they are the fortuitous balances taken over from earlier schemes, augmented by the temporary margins of income just mentioned. Though large they represent only about one-tenth of the actuarialreserves required under a fully funded scheme, and they are invested in Govern-ment securities the interest on which reduces the residual charge on the Exchequer.9. In elaboration of the foregoing it may be useful to consider the trans-actions between the Exchequer and the National Insurance scheme as falling into two parts. First, there is an &quot; insurance scheme &quot; under which the statutory contri-butions are accepted from insured persons and employers with an exchequer supplement and, in return, actuarially equivalent benefits are paid in due course.The Exchequer, in its capacity as insurer, prefers to avoid the piling up of hugereserves from these contributions; instead it uses any excess of income to meetother expenditure in the knowledge that as a result it will have to pay for the useof the money by making up the difference between expenditure and income forever after. This is a perfectly proper proceeding, to which there are parallelsmore or less in the arrangements for the sale of Government Annuities and inthe National Savings Scheme. Secondly, there is the liability which the exchequer has accepted for benefits in so far as they are not covered by contributions, a liability which, as already indicated, is at present being met from the excess income from contributions under the &quot;insurance scheme.&quot; This liability is in quite adifferent category from the first. It is not the result of a &quot; savings &quot; or &quot; insurance &quot;transaction, properly so called, but represents a real addition to the State&apos;sliabilities. Moreover, every time benefits are increased even though the rates of contribution are increased so that no liability is incurred for future entrants at theminimum age a further burden is thrown on taxation in respect of every personthen over the minimum age, including all existing pensioners. Indeed, the enormousliability imposed by the Act of 1946 has already been substantially added to twice,by the Acts of 1951 and 1952.10. The following figures will give some idea of the magnitude of the sums involved in respect of retirement pensions smaller liabilities arise in addition for sickness and widow&apos; benefits. The value of the pension of 265. (42s. for a couple)given to a man aged 65 in 1948 was about  650 if he was single and over  1,300 ifhe was married to a wife four years younger (the average disparity). Even if hehad been contributing fully ever since 1926 the contributions he and his employerhad paid, with interest added, would not amount to more than about  55 to set against this liability of the Exchequer and in most cases at this age the wife wouldherself have paid few, if any contributions. On average, the liability for the retire-ment pensions of persons over pension age at July 1948 (without allowing for thesmall offset of any accumulated contributions) was about  550 a head for each ofthe 4 million pensioners. Turning to persons under pension age at July 1948 theExchequer, in addition to promising to supplement the contributions of the insured person and his employer, accepted liability for the difference between the value ofpensions and the future contributions of the three parties. For a single man aged25 this liability was about  40; at age 40 it was over  150 and at 55 it was over 350. gainst these sums the maximum that could have been accumulated frompast contributions for his own pension was  15 for a man aged 25 at July 1948 and 35 for one aged 40 or over. For technical reasons it is not possible to give similarfigures for married men or for women. But, in total, the capital liability for retire-ment pensions at 5th July, 1948, after deducting future contributions of existingcontributors but including some  500 millions for Exchequer supplements to thecontributions, was of the order of  8,000 to  9,000 millions, of which over  6,000millions was in respect of persons under pension age. This latter represents, anaverage of no less than  270 for each of the 23 million contributors to the scheme.The Acts of 1951 and 1952 together increased the benefits by one-quarter for the single men and rather more than this fraction for a couple.. The additional liabilitythus undertaken by the State was of the order of  2,500 millions bringing the totalliability to a figure of the order of  11,000 millions. After inclusion of the similarliability for other benefits (mainly widows, and sickness) and of Exchequer Supple-ment to the contributions of future contributors, the total comes, to about  15,000millions.  These sums must, in due course, be met by additional taxation.
Table IV. Changes in Population of Great Britain(thousands)Age	Males		Females		1951	1977	1951	1977	5,599	4,761	5,387	4,580,15-19...    .......	1,575	1,542	1,565	1,48920-59 ...	13,363	13,242	14,019	13,09460-64 ...	1,046	1,439	1,328	1,60665-69 ......	867	1,318	1,153	1,56870 and over          ...	1,308	2,035	1,972	3,i82; ;.; . ,.    Total ...	23,758	24,337 .	25,424	25,519The Seriousness of the Future BurdenAmount of the Charges on the Exchequer11. Table III in paragraph 2 shows that the annual Exchequer charge risesfrom  71 millions in 1953-54 to  171 millions in 1957-58,  344 millions in 1967-68and  485 millions in 1977-78. These figures would, when the time comes, turn out to be higher, and perhaps much higher, if recent experience were perpetuated, he.,rising prices leading to increases in the rate of pension to existing and futurepensioners. Any substantial increase in the wage level without an increase in theprice level would also no doubt increase the public demand for higher rates ofpension.12. How serious these future burdens would be depends upon the future trend in the ratio of productive to unproductive members of the population and more generally in the ratio between benefit expenditure and national income and in the proportionate burden of taxation due to the Exchequer payments. These factorsare considered in paragraphs 14-19 below. 1 &apos;13. This memorandum deals only with the finance of National Insurance. Itmust always be borne in mind, however, that public funds also have heavy liabilitiesin connection with National Assistance (paid for by the Exchequer) and other expenditure for the old, particularly through the Health Service and in the provisionof old people&apos;s homes. The ageing of the population will increase these burdens,and in any case the percentage of retirement pensioners in receipt of supplementaryAssistance (about 24 per cent.) may easily increase in the future if family ties arefurther loosened, if savings fall, or if retirement pensioners make fuller use ofthe National Assistance Scheme. If owing to an increase in prices the national assistance scale had to be raised again and the National Insurance benefits remained unchanged, there would be more supplementation of Insurance by Assistance, andthe same result would follow any attempt to meet the future National Insurancedeficits by cuts in the Insurance rates. On the other hand, if the National Insurancerates were increased while the National Assistance scales were left stationary therewould be some saving on National Assistance. This does not, of course, mean that changes up or down in the National Insurance rates have exactly correspondingeffects upon National Assistance expenditure because National Assistance is paidsubject to a needs test; the inter-action between the two schemes would dependat any time upon the amount of savings and other resources including superahnua-tion payments available to individuals and the character of the Assistance needs test.The other point to bear in mind is that so long as the Insurance rate is as at presentbelow the Assistance scale there is criticism from those who think that the Insurancerate should be at a subsistence level, and a gap of this kind can tend to bring theInsurance scheme into disrepute so that it looks more like a tax which brings little or no advantage to those of the insured who are without substantial means.Future Ratio of the Productive to the Unproductive14. The estimated population changes between 1951 and 1977 and thepercentage occupied in each age group in 1951 are shown in the following tables:  
Table V. Percentages Occupied in 1951Age	Males	Females0-14   ...      ......		15-19   ......	84-8	78-420-59   ......	97-7	38-060-64   .........	87-8	14-465-69   .........	48-7	9-070 and over   ...	20-9	3-1	67-4	27-2Table IV shows an ageing of the population, but this does not necessarily mean that the occupied percentage of the total population will fall; for the increase inthe unoccupied old may no more than balance the decline in children. In fact, ifthe proportions occupied in the different age groups as shown in Table V for 1951are applied to the prospective numbers of persons in 1977, the overall proportionoccupied remains practically unchanged. Allowance must, however, be made forthe possibility of a further rise in the school-leaving age and consequent loss of older children from work, the pressure for which will be increased by the drop in the school population. It is also open to doubt whether the proportions occupied in the highest age groups will be maintained; in the last 20 years the proportionoccupied in the groups aged 65 and over has dropped from 47 - 9 per cent, for menand 8-2 per cent, for women to 32-0 per cent, and 5 - 3 per cent, respectively. Canthis decline be expected to stop in spite of the effect of the new pensions schemeitself and of recent extensions of private superannuation schemes to which reference is made later? Is there a prospect of reversing this trend, and if so how manyadditional people could join the occupied?15. The proportion of women in paid work in the highest age groups will always be small, and it is hardly possible to estimate the possibility of increasing it.As regards men, there are over 400,000 at work between the ages of 65 and 70.The unoccupied in this age group are nearly 450,000, but this includes 120,000 whoare chronically sick and incapable of work and 40,000 who had stopped workingbefore age 65. Excluding the 40,000, those unoccupied but fit for work in this age group number less than 300,000, and that figure includes those who, though not actually ill, are not really physically fit for regular work under ordinary conditions.By 1977, when the 65 to 70 age group will have increased by one half, the progressof medical science may have further reduced the number of the unfit. Assuming,however, that as at present nearly 50 per cent, of this age group continue in employ-ment, the maximum number of the unoccupied but fit for work would be about420,000 about 2 - 6 per cent, of the working population of men at that time. that therefore indicates the possible effect on men under 70 of a successful campaign to persuade men to stay at work. To achieve anything approaching it there wouldhave to be an abandonment of the traditional view on the part both of employersand workers that 65 or less is the right age for retirement, a willingness on bothsides to continue employment until the age of 70 at least, and a state of full employ-ment calling for the services of all the fit and willing members of the community.16. An increasingly serious obstacle is the effect of public and private super-annuation schemes. At present, superannuation schemes generally operate at aretirement age of 60 or 65 at most; moreover the provision made is such that many people especially those in the lower income groups may with their super-annuation payments and National Insurance pensions be almost as well offfinancially in retirement as in work, if not sometimes even better-off. Owing tothe post-war extension of superannuation schemes some 3f million people in private industry are now covered for superannuation payments in addition to over2 million in the employment of government, public bodies and nationalised industries. Thus without any further increases in the number of schemes almost30 per cent, of the insured population will have a pension from a superannuationfund as well as from National Insurance. This must have an important effect uponreadiness to continue at work above 60 or 65.Benefit Expenditure and National Income.......17. The burden of the National Insurance Scheme upon the community canbe represented by the command over national output given by benefits. The future
expansion in national output and what it will reach in 197,7 is almost wholly aquestion of individual judgment (not to say guesswork), and it depends mainly onthe view that is taken about future increases in productivity. Such information asis available from past experience suggests that it would be optimistic to assume anaverage annual increase in productivity over a long period of 2\ per cent., whilelJj per cent, would appear to be on the low side. If National Insurance benefits in 1951 are recalculated at the rates introduced by the 1952 Act (so that they may properly be compared with the future), then they represented 4-3 per cent, ofnational income in 1951. Table VI illustrates what would happen to this ratio of benefits to national income by 1977 on various assumptions with regard to increases in productivity and the rates of benefits. In making these calculationsit has been further assumed that:  id) there is no fall in the percentage of the occupied in the total population;(b) the level of employment remains as high as recently;(c) there is no significant reduction in hours of work; - :id) there is no significant change in the terms of trade.Table VI. Ratio of Benefits to National Income		When National Income increases at annual rate of:				Per cent.	Per cent. 2	Per cent. 2Ratio  of Benefits t,o National Income in 1977* when:	Benefit rates same as to-day ...	4-5	5-1	- 5-8   &apos;	Benefit rates raised pari passu with average standard of living	8-4	8-4	8-4Increase in average standard of living of 1977 over 1951		87	65	45The comparative figure for 1951 is 4-3 per cent.In interpreting these figures two points might be noted. First, the greater relativeburden of benefits in 1977 may be borne by a community with a higher standard ofliving as illustrated in the bottom row of Table VI. Second, the incidence oftaxation upon beneficiaries will slightly reduce their command over national outputbelow the ratios given.18. The figures in Table VI depend upon the preceding assumptions (a) to id)as well as the assumptions about increases in productivity. All these assumptionsare open to question. It is difficult to forecast even a range of figures for probableincreases in productivity; paragraphs 14-16 show that the percentage of the occupied in the population may easily fall; neither the Beveridge Report nor anyearlier authority envisaged a continuing rate of unemployment nearly as low asthe 4 per cent, now assumed for future financial estimates which is itself higherthan the current rate; there may easily be a resumed demand for shorter hours ofwork (much longer here than, in the United States) especially if there is anysubstantial rise in the standard of living; the increases in national income pre-suppose an adequate rate of saving for depreciation and new investment and that neither the required increase in imports nor other economic factors lead to any significant deterioration in the terms of trade.Burden of Taxation . ,      ,19. The increase in expenditure on benefits in the future will mean that largerpayments will&apos;have to be made from the Exchequer to the National InsuranceScheme. These larger payments will entail a greater burden upon the general tax-payer. The magnitude of this burden can be represented by the ratio of theExchequer Charge to personal incomes from work and property. In 1951, ifbenefits and contributions had been on the basis of the 1952 Act, this ratio wouldhave been just under 1-0 per cent. What may happen by 1977 is illustrated inTable VII on the basis of the same assumptions as those used in paragraph 17 for increases in national income.
Table VII. Ratio of Exchequer Charge to Personal Incomes		When National Income increases at annual rate of:				Per cent.	Per cent. 2	Per cent. iiRatio  of Exchequer Charge to personal incomes   in    1977 when:	Benefit and contribution rates same as to-day	2-4 -	2-7	3-1	Benefit and contribution rates raised pari passu with average standard of living   ...	4-4	4-4	4-4In interpreting these figures it might once again be noted that average income per head may be higher by 1977 as illustrated by the bottom row of Table VI. Onthe other hand, these computations do not allow for the higher expenditure on otherwelfare services of the State that may result on balance from the ageing of thepopulation.What Policy should be Adopted20. The preceding paragraphs show how the proportionate burden of general taxation resulting from the National Insurance Scheme and mainly from the pay-ment of retirement pensions will grow. If a number of optimistic assumptions arerealised, particularly about increase in the national income, this growth need not present a serious problem when the time comes. On the other hand, any or all of theoptimistic assumptions might fall and in that case the future burden might be asintolerable in fact as it appears in the light of the size of the national income to-day,or conceivably even worse. The remainder of the Memorandum examines sug-suggestions that have been or might be made for reducing the Exchequer charge oravoiding further possible increases in it.The Balances in the Insurance Funds21. There are balances in the National Insurance Fund and the national insurance (Reserve) Fund amounting to about  1,350 millions, but this sum hasto be considered beside the  15,000 millions mentioned earlier as the capital liabilityinvolved in paying retirement pensions to existing pensioners and contributors.It would not go far to meet an annual excess of expenditure over income risingultimately to over  400 millions. There are in any case several objections to relying on the use of the present invested balances to finance continuing future deficits.(1) Apart from a cash balance of  20 millions invested with the Exchequerand repayable on demand or short notice, the Funds are invested in securities,mainly medium and long term, including  1,100 millions in redeemable stocks.Therefore, any set policy of financing deficits from these Funds means large-scaleselling of securities. But the amount of securities that could be realised in practice,either in the open market or by interdepartmental transactions, is severely limited and would not begin to cover the volume of deficits to be financed. If there werebig sales in the market, security prices would rapidly fall, and the point would soon be reached when the Funds&apos; holdings would be unsaleable. The Funds could onlyrealise securities outside the market to the very limited extent that other Depart-ments had liquid resources available, and these Departments would draw theircash from the Exchequer, and so oblige the Exchequer to replace the outgoingmoney by reborrowing or taxation.(2) Any form of large-scale realisation of the Funds&apos; securities would dislocatethe monetary system and disturb the economy. To some extent it would be in thepower of the Exchequer to offset this; but the process would be full of hazards anduncertainties. The fact is that the Exchequer, not the National Insurance Funds,should be the public fund for adjusting the money supply so as to maintain theeconomic balance of the nation. It is therefore right that any continuing deficitsshould be financed by the Exchequer, for that would make it possible to providefor the deficit payments to be financed out of taxation to the extent appropriate to the economic circumstances of the time.The present invested balances should therefore be looked on, not as a fund to be realised for meeting continuing future deficits, but in the main as a source
of interest income for the National Insurance scheme, which lessens the burdenof the Exchequers ultimate guarantee. The estimates given in Table III aboveof the excess of expenditure over income in future years, to be met from theExchequer, include as part of the income about  40 millions a year on account ofthis interest (see Table II).The Exchequer Supplement22. One possibility is to reduce or abolish the Exchequer supplement(column (2) of Table II) and to increase the contributions from insured persons and employers by the amount required to retain the combined amount at the &quot; actuarialcontribution &quot; appropriate to age 16; the Exchequer supplement at present equals.Is. 6d. a week for adult male workers, and costs for all insured persons  70 millions,a year. Such a change would substitute a poll tax on workers and other insuredpersons for general taxation and thus raises questions of taxation policy. There,would be stiff objections to the change; the Exchequer supplement is an oldestablished element of the National Insurance scheme and has already beenreduced; the opposition, as a matter of taxation and social policy, appear to thinkthat it should if anything be enlarged in order to reduce the burden of the contri-butions. The maintenance of the Exchequer supplement has been defended as theState&apos;s justification for its intervention as manager of the insurance scheme. Moreimportant, it helps to justify the compulsion put upon those who would notcontribute to the scheme if left to themselves and whose circumstances prevent them from deriving full benefit from the scheme; for instance single men andwomen who have no dependants but contribute at the same rate as those who have.The existence of the employer^ contribution may be some answer in the case ofemployed persons though not in the case of the self-employed or non-employedwho have no employer to share the burden with them. There would undoubtedly be great resistance to an increase of contributions not accompanied by an increaseof benefits but solely in order to relieve the Exchequer.23. These arguments are not conclusive and the Exchequer supplement shouldbe considered again as part of the review of the National Insurance scheme due in 1954 or if there are other reasons before then to reconsider benefits or contri-butions. In any case it would be difficult in the next year or so to propose anyrearrangement involving an increase in contributions since the income of theNational Insurance Fund will still until 1954-55 exceed its expenditure. Areduction in the Exchequer supplement involving an increase in contributions could:not be dealt with in a Finance Bill and would involve contentious legislation.Pension Rates24. The only other ways of reducing the future Exchequer charges would,be through reductions in the pension rate or in the number of pensioners by anincrease of the minimum retirement age. The difficulties in the way of reducing:the pension rate are obvious and the financial outcome doubtful in view of thefall-back provision of National Assistance referred to in paragraph 13. There is.however, more room for manoeuvre in dealing with pressure for increases in the-pension rate and such pressure is very likely to come sooner or later, if not as aresult of further inflation of prices, then as a result of an increase in the wagelevel accompanying an increase in the national income.25. If prices rise and the rate of pensions remains steady their real value,drops and the pressure for increased pensions will be very great; the national assistance rates are likely to be increased at such a time to conform with theincrease in the cost of living and that will add to the pressure for arise in pension rates and increase the supplementation of pensions by national assistance if the pension rates are not increased. If prices and pensions,remain steady but wages rise, the standard of living of the pensioners doesnot drop but their position is relatively worsened in comparison with the restof the population. In this case, too, there will be pressure for increase in pension rates; but a refusal would not, as in the other case, be automatically followed byany general increase in National Assistance. - It would be difficult to justify anincrease in pension rates in these circumstances in view of the certainty of the tremendous future Exchequer charge and the present uncertainty of the country&apos;future economic prospects.43728 P
26. One expedient can,probably be dismissed as impracticable, and that isto respond to pressure for an increase in pensions by granting some increase butlimiting it to those who will have paid at least some contributions at new rates,leaving the others, including all existing pensioners, to the old rates of pensionwith such help as they need and can get from National Assistance. There is a contractual fairness about such an expedient but the precedents in this country are so sharply in favour of giving all pensioners the same rate that it would be hard to contemplate a discrimination.Increase of Minimum Pension Age27. If an increase in the minimum pension age is not to worsen peopledpension expectation, it would have to be accompanied by a higher pension rate at the higher minimum age, for the following reason. Under the present systemthose who do not retire but go on working after 65 years of age earn half-yearlyincrements to swell their subsequent pension. Therefore to say that in future aman at 67 can only have a pension which a man of 65 used to get means reducingthe pension expectations of men working beyond 65.28. An opportunity for increasing the effective minimum pension age would however rise at once if at any time the pension rate had to be raised. Such anopportunity occurred this year and was not taken, but it is put forward here as away of limiting the additional cost of any further unavoidable increase in the pension rate and in the consequential charge on the Exchequer. Suppose therewere irresistible pressure to raise the standard benefits (retirement pension, sick-ness and unemployment benefits) from the present figure of 32s. 6d. to, say 38s. 6d.The effective minimum pensionable age could then be raised to 67, at which agea man under the present system of increments can already gain a retirement pension of 38s. 6d. It could be provided either that after a transitional period no one could get a retirement pension below 67, or that existing members of the scheme couldchoose, instead of a higher pension from 67, the old rate of pension for life from 65;the growing inadequacy of the old rate of pension and its lack of relation to thesickness and unemployment benefit rates would encourage men to stay in theemployment field and delay their retirement pension until the age of 67. either of these alternatives would be less expensive than paying a higher rate of pensionfrom the age of 65. The country would also be made richer by keeping moreat work.Conclusion29. The preceding paragraphs show that certain plausible expedients for reducing the future burden or avoiding its increase must be dismissed on closerexamination and that others would meet with very strong opposition or would lead to additional Exchequer expenditure on National Assistance. The only clearconclusion so far is that the effective minimum pension age ought to be raisedif at any time the pension rate has to be increased still further. The questionremains whether the future burden of pensions and the size of the Exchequer chargewill become so unmanageable as to force a cut in pensions willy-nilly, howeverdrastic and disagreeable such a remedy might be felt to be! Drastic it wouldcertainly be and would probably have to bring with it a revolutionary change inthe needs test for National Assistance if a cut in pensions were not to be followed bya nearly corresponding addition to Assistance expenditure. Heroic measures ofthis kind may turn out to be necessary, but are hardly called for at the present justice when they would for a year or two only serve to increase the balances inthe National Insurance Funds, so long a time before the burden begins seriouslyto rise to its peak, and while there is a real possibility of an increasing margin inthe national income sufficient to make the future burden tolerable. There is sucha possibility though the future outlook is so uncertain that there can be no con-fidence about it. Meanwhile, however, and until the future begins to declare itself,it.will be at least necessary to avoid any additions to the future burdens and inparticular any further increase in pension expenditure. Moreover by propaganda,example, persuasion and discussion, everything possible should be done to accustompeople to the idea that man&apos;s working life can be and should be longer and that 70 isa more reasonable age for retirement than 65. The Ministry of Labour and NationalService has this problem under review and it is suggested that they should begiven every possible support and encouragement; it is likely to take many years to make the big changes which will be necessary in the traditional attitudes and practices of employers and workers.
NATIONAL INSURANCE FINANCEEstimated Subdivision of Annual Income and Expenditure on Basis of the Provisions of the family Allowances and National Insurance Act, 1952Note I. For purposes of comparison the Chart shows for 1952-53 the annual rate of income and expenditure as though the changes introduced by the 1952 Act had operated throughout 1952-53.Note 2. The sudden rise in expenditure and fall in income at 5th July, 1958 are due to the fact that pensions will start, and contributions cease, at that date for late age entrants who had to contribute for 10 years from the start of thescheme to qualify for pension.(18432)   .150  D.l.
Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1953CONFIDENTIALC. (53) 6013th February, 1953CABINETREVISION OF THE ARMY AND AIR FORCE ACTS:MUTINY &apos;&apos;&quot;Z\ \lMemorandum by the Minister of Defence uhThe Select Committee on the Army and Air Force Acts have been discussing the death penalty for mutiny, and the Service Ministers and I think the cabinet should be aware of the views which the Select Committee have expressed on this important question, and of the reply which, if the Cabinet approves, it is proposedto make to them. &apos; ;    02. A copy of the relevant section of the existing Army and Air F^orGe/Acteis annexed. It will be seen that death is at present the maximum punishment forall offences of this nature, from violent mutiny in arms to the collective refusal of two or three men to obey orders in a relatively minor matter or the failureof someone present to use his best endeavours to suppress or prevent a mutiny.In practice the death sentence is rarely passed or carried out.   .    ,     ,-i--ir-tV-3. The Naval Discipline Act differs in various respects, e.g., it draws a dis-tinction between mutiny with violence, which carries the maximum penalty of death, and mutiny without violence, which does not, except for the ringleaders.4. The Select Committee have expressed the view that the death penalty formutiny should be confined in peace and war to the most serious offences, such asmutiny accompanied by violence or threat of violence or refusal to embark for service against an enemy; that failure of an officer or man to use his utmostendeavours to suppress a mutiny or to inform his commanding officer withoutdelay of a mutiny, actual or intended, does not in any case warrant the death penalty; and that the maximum penalty for endeavours to seduce a person fromallegiance to Her Majesty should be imprisonment, as under the civil law.5. The Service Departments agree in principle that the death penalty (as amaximum) can be confined to:  (1) Taking part in or inciting to take part in a mutiny accompanied by violenceor threat of violence or, in combination refusing or avoiding serviceagainst or in connection with operations against an enemy.(2) Knowing that a mutiny is taking place or is intended, with intent to assistthe enemy failing to use utmost endeavours to suppress or prevent it orto report it.For any other mutinous offences under the Army and Air Force Acts the maximumpenalty would be imprisonment for life.6. As regards endeavouring to seduce a person serving in Her Majesty&apos;s forces from his duty or allegiance, if this amounted to a mutiny or incitement to a mutinycovered by (1) above it Would carry a liability to the death penalty, and if to anyother form or incitement to any other form of mutiny to imprisonment for life.In any other cases it is considered that it would be sufficient to charge the offenderwith the civil offence of &quot;,maliciously and advisedly endeavouring to seduce anymember of Her Majesty&apos;s forces from his duty or allegiance,&quot; which carries a penalty of 2 years&apos; imprisonment under the Incitement to Disaffection Act, 1934, of,Copy No.      a&apos; in

</content>
</cab>
