<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/59/0 images: 125-126</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)confidential. (53) 7827th FEBRUARY, 1953.FARM PRICE REVIEW;  PRODUCERS&apos; PRICE FOR MILKMemorandum by the Minister of Food.My agricultural colleagues and I have, with the Chancellor of the Exchequer,reached decisions about the line to be taken at the forthcoming Annual Reviewof Agricultural Prices with one exception.   That is the amount of extra moneyto be awarded to dairy farmers.2.       The increase in costs of production of milk (so far as it is not coveredby increases in production grants already agreed) amounts to just over ^d. per gallon and, in total, this is equal to about S.b\ millions in a year.   The national farmers&apos; Union (N.F.U.) will no doubt press for the whole of this to be made good by an increase in prices.   The issue is the extent to which this claim should be met.3.       What the nation most needs at this time from the farmers is more meat,and after that cereals and eggs.   We are not in urgent need of more milk,and indeed we cannot afford more if it is to be the high-cost product of theleast efficient producer - for whose sake we would unnecessarily increase theprofits of the rest.   It would be wrong to make milk production more attractivein comparison with these other products.4.       Milk production is profitable and would remain so if no increase in price whatever were conceded.   The average profit is not less than 9-f-cL, per gallon on an average cost of 2/4-ld.   This is a high rate of profit, and higherthan is earned in the rest of the agricultural field.5.       In spite of persistent propaganda by the N.F.U. designed to show that under-recoupment of dairy farmers&apos; costs in 1951 led to a fall in milkoutput, production during the farming year 1951/52 was fully maintained.   Thelast year has seen a considerable increase.   Recorded sales in the 1952/53farm year are estimated at 1,846 million gallons - 32 million gallons morethan in the previous year.6.       Our commitments on milk are indeed onerous.   We cannot afford toencourage high-cost producers who would be better employed on other commodities which we need more urgently.   Consumption of liquid milk afterincreasing persistently over a period of years declined in 1952.   We haveto buy at a fixed price every gallon the farmer offers us.   The subsidy bill isalready about  90 millions, and my colleagues have already decided that, in the face of declining consumption, it would be unwise to attempt at present to reducethe subsidy by an increase in retail prices with its sharp reaction on the costof living index.   If we cannot reduce the subsidy to give the taxpayer the reliefhe needs, at least We must not lightly increase it.COPY NO.CABINET
7.       Finally, there is the question of feedingstuffs.   It has been generally agreed that it is essential to apply some check to the total demand afterdecontrol by under - re coupment of the increased cost of livestock products.We cannot check the use of grain for egg production because the price ofeggs is to be decontrolled.   We have agreed on a measure of under-recoupmentfor pigs.   Dairy cows are the other main users, and account for about a quarterof the feedingstuffs within the scope of the Review.   Whereas pigs andhens have to be fed on a high proportion of cereal feedingstuffs - so that theuse of feedingstuffs can only be checked at the expense of checking expansionof output - there are alternative feeds for the cow; and it is an important element in our policy to encourage wider and more efficient use of grass andgrass products.   To leave the dairy farmer to carry part of the extra costarising from removal of the subsidy on feedingstuffs does not merely protect the balance of payments, but has the merit of positively contributing to greater efficiency in the industry.8.       The present level of profit on milk compared with other products;our need for some check on demand for imported feedingstuffs;  our need to check further expansion of the milk industry on a high-cost basis and instead to foster the production of beef - all these make a powerful case for retaining the price of milk at its present level.   But I appreciate the tactical advantages of making some concession, and I would agree to an award of an additional 2 millions, equivalent to ^d. per gallon.   I do not think we should go further on a commodity on which we are already so deeply committed.G. L.-G.Ministry of Food, S.W.1.27th February, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
