<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/59/0 images: 184-186</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC -MAJESTY&apos;S-GOVERNMENT)SECRET /C. (53) 98 COPY NOv13th MARCH, 1953.CABINETSANDERS - LEE ment EXCHANGEMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.The case for entertaining the Hungarian proposal is stated in thememorandum by the Minister of State (C.(53) 96).   Unfortunately the affair hasbecome a cause celebre, every move in which is closely watched in Malaya.This has created circumstances which must affect my attitude towards theproposed exchange and I now consider it almost impossible to justify.2. The High Commissioner for the Federation of Malaya is stillstrongly opposed to the exchange for the reasons given in the annexed telegram.His main reasons may be summarised as follows:-(a) The Hungarian offer has already given warm encouragement Xto the Communists and their sympathisers in Malaya.Lee ment&apos;s release in exchange for Sanders  would make a most fortunate impression on public opinion in Malaya and could behailed by the terrorists as a convincing demonstration of the powerand prestige of the Soviet bloc,(b) To make an exchange possible, Lee ment&apos;s sentence of lifeimprisonment would have to be commuted.   This would againinvolve the Sultan&apos;s prerogative, and it is almost certain that hewould not be prepared to exercise it without the formalintervention of the Eiigh Commissioner.   It would subsequently be necessary to place before the Federal Executive Council(which includes 10 Asians in its total membership of 20) theproposal that she should be banished.   A direction to the HighCommissioner to take these steps might well lead to a constitutional crisis.3. A further point, not mentioned by the High Commissioner, is that his right to tender formal advise is intended to be exercised in the interests of&quot;good government&quot; in Malaya, and would therefore be open to challenge in thecircumstances of this case.   This right has so far never been exercised even inthose interests.   I think that it would be politically indefensible to court a constitutional crisis in Malaya by instructing the High Commissioner to intervene in this matter formally unless by doing so we obtained advantages in our struggle with Communism which would outweigh this consideration.No one has claimed that we should secure such advantages from this exchange.4. Even if, by the use of the High Commissioner^ influence, short of formal intervention, it were possible to persuade the Malayan authorities toaccept the exchange, I should still regard the objections mentioned inparagraph 2(a) as almost insurmountable.
5. I have considered whether an attempt might be made to keep theoffer open for some months in order to let public excitement in Malaya subside.But I cannot see how this could be done without the intention behind it becomingobvious to the Malayan public.   In my view the only effective way ofreassuring public opinion in Malaya lies in the explicit rejection of the hungarian offer and I suggest that it is important that this should be done atonce, in case the Hungarian Government themselves decide to withdraw theoffer.O.L.Colonial Office, S.W.1.13th March, 1953.TELEGRAM OF 10th MARCH, 1953 FPx.OM THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FORTHE FEDERATION OF MALAYA TO THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOPv. THECOLONIES.No. 238 .Lee ment.Now that, as reported in my telegram No. 235, the Lee Mengsentence has been commuted, I wish to place before you very cogent reasons why I consider exchange proposal should not be pursued.2. In the first place, although in fact Sultan&apos;s decision was reachedwithout any official advice having been tendered to him and probably representshis own personal opinion, the effect on public opinion if exchange proposal were now to be pursued would inevitably be an assumption that commutation hadmerely been first step towards achieving exchange, and that undue pressure had probably been brought to bear on the Sultan and State Executive Council in orderto achieve this end.3. In the second place, there is no doubt that there is strong feeling in this country at present that the very suggestion of an exchange and the factthat offer originated from the Hungarian Government, presumably on orders from moscow, has already been given Warm encouragement to the Communists andtheir fellow travellers here, and that the effect of this encouragement would bevery serious if this exchange were successfully (from the  Joint of view of the communists) carried out.   As an indication of the strength of this feeling, Ishould tell you that Mr. Yap Mau Tatt, O.B.E., the Secretary General of the malayan (corrupt group ?Chinese) Association, wrote to me the other day,stressing that he was doing so in his personal capacity, to say that he has nodoubt that, if the exchange is completed, there will be a grave upasurge of terrorism in Malaya and that he considers news of the exchange has already served to give terrorists a fillip to morale and would indicate to them that they have all power, influence and the prestige of the active Communist bloc behind their own local efforts in Malaya.   He also states that the exchange proposal,if carried out, would undo a great deal of the success which has been gainedso far in the Emergency, and that the problem of bringing the Emergency to anearly end of which &quot;there have recently been heartening signs&quot; is of far greater importance than the question of exchange, however desirable that may seern
on the surface.   He continues &quot;the life of one Malayan terrorist on the one handand the life of a Briton gaoled in Hungary on the other hand (with all mysympathy and apologies to Mirs. Sanders) are, in my humble view, unimportantto the vital strength of the world of freedom now fighting against Communism&quot;,He may have overdrawn the picture somewhat, but generally I agree withthis assessment.4. Thirdly, I would remind you that, as pointed out in my telegramNo. 208, if exchange proposal is to be carried out the question of remission of Eee ment&apos;s sentence and her banishment will have to be considered afresh,both in Perak Executive Council and in Federal Executive Council,   There isno doubt that feeling against the exchange would be strong if the matter is again taken to Perak Executive Council and, if majority opinion of the council were against remission of her sentence, as I feel sure would be the case, itwould be necessary for official advice to be tendered to His Highness of a nature contrary to that of majority opinion in order to secure necessaryremission.   Furthermore, position might easily arise in Federal ExecutiveCouncil in which a majority was not in favour of her being banished in order tofacilitate exchange.   If, in these circumstances, you felt it necessary to pressme to secure remission of sentence by use of power of official advice (which has never hitherto been used) and to make a Banishment Order against advice of federal Executive Council, and in the face of public opinion, this might lead toa serious constitutional crisis resulting in situation of some gravity.   I realise our view here is necessarily more parochial than yours, but I neverthelessfeel strongly that this exchange might well cause a serious setback in progress which is being made here in suppression of Communist terrorism and risk onvfuture good relations with the Rulers and the people.

</content>
</cab>
