<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/71/0 images: 133-133</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
\  JS B C R E T.Copy No:MALI Q^^plenipoteniary  COMMITMENTS  HEMAIHINQ AFTER PEACE HAS BBBH SIGHED..  ill  A REGULAR ARMY on a  voluntary basis  to provide; (i)  Overseas  garrisons  now  found by soldiers  serving under the     &quot; Military Service Acts;(ii)  Garrisons for Great Britain 6c  Ireland  and the machinery for      providing drafts for  (i);iii)  British personnel for  the Indian  formations  in  the  permanent     &quot;Trmies 6T&quot;0ccupaUon  in Etol,PALBSftKlSS,MESOPOTAMIA  &amp; NORTH      PERSIA.  Arrangements for providing for  the above  are in progress. The following remain to be considered:W Army of Occupation in Germany.  Marshal foch  has  asked for:       (a) 7 to 10 Divisions in the front area;                         and       (b) 7 to 10 Divisions as reserve  in rear.    It is proposed that troops in GREAT  BRITAIN under paragraph 1, sub-paragraph (ii)-estimated at 5  Divisions - should be  considered as available to complete (b) if peace is broken,  thus leaving  to be provided in FRANCE       .....,   ...  9 to 15 Divisions.(ii)  Italian Front, In ITALY &amp;  the ADRIATIC PORTS we may have to                     keep  from  ..    ...    1 Brigade to 1 Division.iil)  Salonika.  Entire  evacuation  of British  troops from  the BALKANS                    is  advocated.(lv)  Turkey.    The  B0SPR0R0US  &amp; DARDANELLES  must be policed to                enforce  the  execution of  Peace Terms,  and  to keep                open the Lines of Communication to BATOUM  &amp; the                CAUCASUS. In  addition  to any Allied Detachments                we  shall require.   .,,         1 Division.(v)  Caucasus.  One Division is under orders  for BATOUM and another               will probably be required.   We  may not be  able  to               withdraw these for a considerable time ...  2 Divisions.j(vi) Egypt, Pales tine. Mesopotamia, Persia &amp; Trans-Caspla.1                for in paragraph 1,  sub-paragrapn liilj..ProvidedP-3-) Russia.   No reduction from the present strength can bo  counted                upon;  some increase may even be necessary. The                equivalent of .............         1  Division,Summary.    Additional to the Volunteer and Indian Armies  referred &quot;to in paragraph 1,  wo shall require as Armies of Occupation the  equivalent of 14 -  20 Divisions (making with Bases and Lines of  Communication troops 350,000 - 500,000 white personnel)  for an  unknown period after Peace has been signed.   No machinery as yet  exists for their provision, since it would be unsafe to  assume  that they will be obtainable on a voluntary  basis.moral staff, War Office, S.W.1.    5th December, 1918.(Signed)   HENRY WILSON,   General,C.I.G.S.,

</content>
</cab>
