<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/71/0 images: 159-160</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
T)COtr..?&apos;?T IS THE PROPERTY 0? HIS  EKITAHNIC LAJTSSTY\S  GDyER^EHT.jI J&amp;        V A R  0 A  B HE T.                         UKSSffiCft SET SHt,.             iremcrondum  &quot;by  the Pi rot Commissioner of Works.      To  the iVar Cabinet,           I find very grave  dieoatiof action in Labour Circles      in  ray constituency (Swansea, \7est) regarding the sum fixed      for unemployment benefit under the Demobilisation Scheme.  The      ourn of 24/- is represented to me by responsible Trade Union      Leaders as being entirely insufficient in presence of the prices      ef  to-day,  to  enable  an unemployed workman and his family t*      pay for the cost of food and rent.  In one or two instances,      in  which a number  of  workmen have been threatened with dis-      charge,  owing  to a cessation of work, they simply decline te      go  to the Labour Exchange for such benefit, and threaten if      the Local pood Controller will not supply them and their      family with food that they will have  to requisition it for      themselves. Up to the  present, I have been able to prevent      any such action, which  would be moot  regrettable, from being      actually taken.  But  the danger of disturbance of this kind      cannot be disregarded.           A proposal has been submitted to me by the Branch Secre-      tary of-one of the largest Unions that the State should under-f      take to pay the rent  and provide food for these men until      they find new  employment.   This would not necessarily be of      long duration,  The Local Itood Controller should be authorised      to  issue the ration tickets for such  purposes.           Another alternative proposal is  that the unemployment      benefit should be  raised to-47/* per  week, which, it is claimed,      is  the minimum necessary to allow a workman and his family to      continue to live under  reasonable conditions.           A great point is made by the men of the fact that owing      to  the restriction under the munitions Act, many of them have      not been able  during the war  to  secure better positions, to      change their occupation,  or to look  for alternative occupations      in  peace industries.    This point seems to me to be one which      has considerable  justification.   It  is not  that the men  are      anxious to live  at the  expense of the State, and do no work,      but that the sudden dislocation  of industry leaves them  and      their families in  a very unsatisfactory position.  They  con-      sequent ly feel they have a  grievance  in as much as thoy have      all been helping  to win the war.           I would suggest that if  it  is not found possible to work      any kind of ration scheme through the Pood  Controller, the      unemployment Benefit Should be raised for a limited period,      say two months,  to a figure of say  35/-,  apart from  the  allow-      anccs for children.  I  further wish  to  emphasise the necessity      of  taking all  possible  steps  to prevent Munitions rectories      having to discharge men owing to  the  difficulty  of  obtainr .      orders.  Several  cases  have been  brought  to my knowledge      recently in which firms could have  obtained orders  abroad      but had difficulties placed in their  way  owing to  export      restrictions.    in one  oaee,  difficulties were raised about ordnrsOR   T.-6440.boinfe
H.M. Office of Works,    5th December,  1918.being taken from France on account of Treasury *bvj-e*tioue;on the score cf exchange.    The firm was informed that it  vwould be considered preferable to see such orders filledfrom America,   This is neither the woy to re-establishBritish industry,  nor to assist the working classes-.     Inthe two caaes which I have been dealing with, both relate tothe manufacture of Spelter,  an industry which the Govern-merit have promised to help to maintain as a key industry.                                (fid.) ALFRED MOOT).

</content>
</cab>
