<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/71/0 images: 244-254</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
     I am forwarding herewith a Paper  on the  MilitarySituation in Siberia, (Appendix &quot;A&quot;) and correspondence whichhas taken place with the Foreign Office on this  subject(Appendix v B&quot; ).     Since this Paper was written the  situation  has  somewhatdeveloped.  Admiral Kolchak appears to be establishing hisposition in Western Siberia, and the difficulties with the czech troops have tc a certain extent  been overcome.  TheBolshevik attacks on Ufa and Orenburg continue t* progress,though but slowly, wing tfl tho stubborn resistance  cf the siberian and Czech forces.     In Eastern Siberia the Japanese have undertaken to  keepSemenov quiet, but there are no signs of their ceasing the subsidies to the Cossacks which are at tho root  of all the trouble.     The Railway situation is becoming steadily  worse indefault ^f any definite Allied policy as to its  management.I  therefore request  that tho War Cabinet will come to adecision  on the following proposals      (1)  That British and Canadian forces should be used            for a defensive campaign co as to help to maintain            the present front held by the Siberian - Czech tro      (2)  That strong action be taken to force the Japanese            to cease their direct subsidies to any Siberian or            Russian  troops, and that all the assistance  they            give to  the formation of the Siberian Armies, and            wo shall gladly welcome such assistance, must come            through  the Government at  Omsk.      (3)   That the Americans and Japanese be pressed to            accept)  without any further delay, the  solution of            the Railway question put forward by Colonel Jack,            and embodied in War Office  letter to the Foreign             Office  (Attached at Appendix &quot;o&quot; .)General  Staff,  War Office, 11th December,(Sd.)  Henry Wilson.1918.O.I.G.S.
APPENDIX &quot;A                                                  SECRET.               THE MILITARY SITUATION IN SIBERIA.1.   With reference to the War Cabinet  policy  for  Siberia aslaid down at their meeting of 14th November, furtherconsideration is necessary on the  steps whioh  ought to betaken to put this into effect.  While  it  was  decided thatno offensive action was to be carried out  against  theBolsheviks, the despatch and maintenance of British and canadian troops to Siberia was to  be continued.    TheCanadian Government  report that there  is  strong feeling,not only against any form of compulsion in raising the units necessary for the Canadian Lxpeditlonary Force, but even against the general policy of employment  of these troops in Siberia.   In order to deal with this  question  itmust be made perfectly plain what  role British and canadian troops are to carry out.   Need for a decision on thissubject has become all the more pressing owing to therecent political developments at Omsk and the  generaluncertainty prevailing in the country, which can be  partiallyallayed by a definite statement of our intentions.2,   At present the Siberian  Government has under arms  some95,000 troops, composed of Russians, Siberians and Cossacks,of which about 60,000 are holding a line which rune  Northand West of Ekaterinburg,  (passing about 60 miles South-east of Perm), and thence genorally southwards covering Birsk,Ufa and Uralsk  from the West, and.also covering Orenburgfrom the direction of Turkestan.   Mixed with this forcethoro are about  5,000 Czech  troops, while in rear ofEkaterinburg and Ufa   there  are a further 30,000 Czechswho have lately  been withdrawn from the front,  owing totiredness,  and  a certain  lack of  moral, after many months                                                       . Of/
of vory hard fighting.   We are  told  that  tho  best  of  the siberian troops have been kept  in rear  principally for political purposes, and there are also  about  11,000 czech troops scattered throughout Siberia  on  garrison  duty.In additioni the Siberian Government has  called  to thecolours about 110,000 men of all arms who are in depotsnear various large towns along  tho Trans-Siberian Railway,but at present are almost entirely deficient  of  trainedofficers, arms and equipment.    General Knox  has pointedout that the material of this force  is  good throughout,that discipline is fairly well  maintained, and that  steps havealready been taken by him for the establishment  of schools for Officers and N.C.0,s., whilst British Officers fortraining purposes, and equipment, are being despatched  fromthis country.3.   The small Allied forces at present in the countryconsist of       (i)   A British Garrison Battalion, the bulk of which             is at Omsk, while  doT. a oilmen 1,3 are being used  as -             guards for the train-loads of stores which             General Knox is pushing forward  from Vladivostock       (11)  An armoured train with Naval guns and detachments             from H*M.St &quot;Suffolk&quot; which has  now beon upon the             Ufa front for some time, whore its arrival was             most cordially welcomed by the Russian troops.     A second British Battalion  (the l/Oth Hants) has now arrived at Vladivostock,  Of the Canadian force of allarms, which, with the two British Battalions  will make  upa Brigade group, General Elmsley, with his headquarters staff and advance body of about 1,000 ia already at vladivostock, while the despatch  of  the remainder is beingpostponed by the Canadian Government pending decision asto policy.     A French Battalion with a battery of 76*a and 12Russian 3&quot; guns has proceeded West of Omsk, and it is                                             understood
understood Is to be utilized on the  front.    Two ItalianBattalions, composed principally of  irredentist  prisoners,with a certain number of guns,  are also en  route to theWest.4.   General Knox has already given  permission to thedespatch of Colonel Ward and a few picked men of theMiddlesex battalion to the front tc  take part in the approaching advance on Perm, but we  have made it quite clear that until further orders no other British troops are to go West of the Urals, and that British policy is opposed to definite offensive action against the Bolsheviks.     The despatch of further troops  to Western Siberia,where they are to be used for training purposes, and asan example in discipline and general moral  to russian and Siberian forces in training, has been proposed as a&quot;via media&quot;.  This, as General Knox very rightly pointsout, will prove a most unsatisfactory expedient, and weshall find levelled at us the accusation already justlybrought against the Americans and Japanese, that we havethere well-armed and equipped troops for show purposes,if not for some ulterior reason, while we allow thefighting to be done by the  poorly equipped and half-trainedSiberian and Russian troops.   Such an accusation would  -damage our prestige, and the consequent attitude of theinhabitants towards our troops would tend to lower theirmoral.5.   The General Staff are  of the opinion that adequatelyto carry out the War Cabinet policy of supporting theOmsk Government, it is essential to hold securely a linoas least as far West as that at present occupied in european Russia, and to prevent any further advance on                                                    the
 the  part  of the  Bolshevlcks,   For  choice  Perm should  be occupied  in order to make  the  situation satisfactory, If the  present line be  abandoned,,  not  only is the  ultimate junction  of the  Siberian forces  with those of Denikin and Krasnov in the Don region  rendered infinitely more difficult, but  Uralsk and Orenburg will also  have  to bo  abandoned, with the  result  that Turkestan will be  laidcPP^ to a Bolshevik invasion in force via  the Tashkend  railway. We should thus expose our  small  force now supporting  the Trans-Caspian  Government at Merv with resulting danger to our  Indian Empire  and our  interests In Persia, 6*  The  most  satisfactory method  of ensuring  the  maintenance of the  present line would  be to  utilise the British trtcps and  such  units as  the Canadian Government  are  prepared to provide,  for operations  of a defensive nature, wofit of the Urals *  Such policy would, however,  Increase  our commitmenta in Siberia  and would necessarily involve  demands for personnel,  which,  In view  of the uninstructed  state of public  opinion as  to Russia and  the  approaching demobiliz- tlon of the bulk  of our  forces may  meet 7?ith much  opposition in this country, 7,   The  situation Is further  complicated by  the action of the  Japanese in subsidising bands of Cossacks in eastern Siberia under Somenoff,  Kalmtaaff  and  other irree- ponalble  and utterly untrustworthy  Cossack  leaders, who,up to the present,  have  refused  to  support  tho Omsk Govern-ment, and are  no??  openly defying Kolehak,   These bonds areastride the Siberian Railway and until they have beensuitably dealt with they are in  a position  at any  timeto cut  the  communications  between our base  at Vladivostockand anyhtroopa which we  may send V/eat of  Lake Baikal,
  8.   Irrespective  cf the  general  policy  that may toe ultimately  adopted by the  Allies with regard to  the Bolsheviks,  it  is  imperative that a  decision should toe  taken  as to the  immediate  policy to toe followed in  regard to the British troops now In  Siberia or under orders to proceed there.       The alternatives are          (1)  To utilize British troops for  purposes of training                  and organization  only.          (11) To authorise their taking pert in such military                  operations e&amp;  may be  recersary to maintain the                  approximate line  held at present.  9.   Further, it is considered essential that the shipment of  all material, whether originally  intended for the Car.adj.an  Forces, or for  the Siberians or Czechs,  should be continued.  10.  With regard to paragraph  7,  whatever policy may be  adopted it is essential that the  Japanese Government  should toe                                                               4  persuaded to cease their  support  of these Cossack bards, and  to ensure the security of railway communications between  Vladivostock and Irkutsk0  11.  To sum  up, I am of  opinion  that the British and Canadian  troops now in,  or  under orders, for Siberia, should he author-  ized to take part  in military  operations for the dcionce of the  existing front, on condition that they are  under Brltiph  command, and that  a satisfactory  agreement  is come to with the  Allies in general, and Japan in particular, for the efficient  control and operation of  the vCrans-Siberian Failway,  which is  vital to the existence of the  British forces.                                      (Sd.)   Henry Wilson.General Staff,  far 0ff5.ee, S.W,1.                         0.1,G*S.   30th November, 1918.
                                             APPENDIX &quot;B&quot; .&apos;(198572/ W/57).                    Lard Hardlnge of Penshurst presents his               compliments the Director of Military Operations and bega               leave to state that he has submitted to the  Secretary               of State the memorandum by the Chief of the  Imperial               General Staff on the military situation in Siberia,               enclosed in the War Office letter No. 6149/5739, of the               30th ultimo.                    In reply Lord Hardingo is to draw the attention               of Ma-joop-General Radcliffe to the Note on British               policy in Russia which was circulated by Mr.  Balfour to               the War Cabinet on the 29th ultimo.                                                                     4                    Lord Hardinge is to add that, from a political               point of view, Mr Balfour concurs generally  in the               conclusions stated by the Chief of the Imperial General               Staff and would himself bo in favour of the  second               alternative put forward in paragraph 8 of General               Sir H* Wilson!s memorandum.               Foreign Office,                   December 9th, 1918.
$49/5739.SECRET.30th November 1918.             The Director  of Military  Operations presents his         compliments  to  the Under Secretary of State for Foreign         Affairs  and  bogs to enclose, for the consideration of Mr.         Balfour, a Memorandum by the Chief of the Imperial General         Staff,  on the military situation in Siberia.             Major-General Radcliffe would be grateful if a very         early  reply  could  be furnished as to the views of the         Foreign Office  on  the question of policy involved, in view         of the  fact  that an immediate  decision is required as to the future         employment of the  British troops now in Siberia.Intld.)  P.de B.R. The Under  Secretary  of  State         for Foreign  Affairs.                                                                           I                                                                           1                                                                           I
                                                 APPENDIX &quot;C&quot;      204      0149/5700  (M.R.2,a0)*                    &apos;                        23rd November, 1918.      Sir,            I am commanded by the Army Council to enclose for your      information copy  of telegram No, 29 dated 17th November from      Col.  Jack  on  the  subject  cf railway control on the Trans-Siberian      line i      2,     I am further to refor to tolegram No, 246 from Sir C, Eliot      dated 18th November agreeing with Col. JackTs proposals.  In view      of  the last paragraph of  Sir C, Eliot!s telegram it is not nec-      essary for the  Council to enlarge on the serious situation which      is  resulting  from the inefficiency  of the railway  service.  While                                                                      4      preferring the  solution proposed by Mr Alston in his telegram of      Oct.  13th  (No,  151) which is substantially in accord with the      views of the  Army Council as expressed in their letter 0149/5700      of  Octo  11th, the Council are  of the  opinion that  it  is more      important  for a definite  decision on  the question  of railway con-      trol to be arrived at promptly than for delay to be incurred in      obtaining  the agreement  of  the Allies to the best  solution..  The      Council, therefore,  request that Mr Balfour will press for the      early adoption  of the arrangements  now recommended by Col, Jack      and approved  by Sir  C, Eliot,      3,     I am to onquire whether  in the  opinion  of Mr Balfour  it is      possible that in the present circumstances  the question  could more      expeditiously be dealt with by an Allied  conference  pt Paris than      by the procedure which has  hitherto been  adopted,                                  I am,                                     Sir,                *                                    Your  obedient Servant,                                       (Sd6)   B.B.  Cubitt,The Under Secretary of State,      Foreign Office *
                                                   SEO  RE  1*From^^-General Knox^ Vladivo3tock.To      War Of floe *  l^peated Tokio.                           DespatoheoV15o30 10.11,1^.                           Reoeived   11,00- 10.11.08.No. 229.     Following,.from Col* Jaok for D.R.R.Nq. 29 Nov. 17th,  Reference -telegram from Tokio to ForeignOffice No. 1149.  I am quite certain that Ru.s3.ian railway autiworities will never accept a joint Japanese-ajki-American controlthough they might have admitted a direct control by the StevensMission if backed by the united support of all the allies.     The seri^sness of the transport situation nqw demands achange in our polioy as we have now waitod for more than twomonths for the Americans to establish Stevens - and have given their proposals every support both here and at Tokio I think the pjreo^nt-dJxorganjLzai-lo^        cn the railway should not be permitted to continue longer.     I recommend that we should ask for immediate control byan Allied commission consisting of net more than four technical experts limited to British, French, American  and Japanese ro-presentatives to be presided over by Oustrugoff who has now been definitely appointed at Omsk as Minister of Ways and Comrminicationsof new All-Russian Government.  The whole cf  Trans-Siberianline would be controlled by this commission which would work through the present Russian administration of the four diff-orent railway systems involved.  Along the whole line technical officers pf (?)administration3 would be distributed assistingand advising Russian railway offioials and they would protestdirect to the central Allied commission in case of non*complianoewith their demands.  If we are to give adequate transport facilities for any considerable number of Allies and Russiansoperating in the Ural region and for the early re-victuallingOf the population 9f internal Siberia I am of the opinion, after hearing Major Johnston&apos;s report on the conditions obtaining onthe Western Siberian railways, that it is urgently neoessary forImmediate action to be taken on the lines indicated. ENDS,
                                            SECRET.                RUSSIA.         MILITARY.Deeypher. Sir C, Elliot  (vladivostock)  18th November, 1918.              D,  4.50 p,m,  19th                                November,  1918.              R.  8.0 a.m.  20th.No. 246.       Colonel Jacks telegram No,  29 to Troopers,       I agree with Colonel  Jacko  proposals and understand from Mr, Alston that they contain  nothing  incompatible with any assurances given here to  representatives  ofUnited States,       I do not think direct American or Japanese  controlof Russian Railway Employes  will be successful.  TheRussians require much supervision and advioe but shouldnot be supplantede       Prom recent experience I can testify to deplorablecondition of railway which threatens to impede not onlymilitary movements but economic relief of Siberia,

</content>
</cab>
