<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/71/0 images: 258-263</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is th* Property of  //November, 1918.     I circulate for the information of the War C cabinet he following brief account of the&quot;work Of the Board ofTrade during the month of November,  1918,  which deale only with a few of the more important questions, likely to in-terest my colleagues and does not profess  to be an ac-eountof the ordinary departmental work of the Board, or to iit-*--dude all the important Questions considered by the Be-  ipartment.COTTON IMPORTS.   In consequence of the Armistice the Ministry   of Snipping have found it possible to increase shipments .-&apos;   for December and January from United States of America to   65,000 tons which is about the maximum the trade can take   at present.   During&apos; the last few months shipments have   been at the rate of 45,000 tons a month.        In view of this increase in supply the industry has   begun to work full time again,COTTON MISSION TO UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.   The mission of   cotton experts sent to United States of America by the Boawt   of Trade and War Offioe to consult with committees set up   by the American  overnsoent for the purpose of deciding cer-   tain&apos;questions connected with the disposal of the cotton   crop, returned to this country on November  3rd,   They had   agreed with the United States authorities as to the x^ercent-   age of lower grades to be taken by this country.   Since the   return of the Mission, the United states Government have   cancelled the system of individual licences for the expoft   of cotton to the Allied countries, and the agreement regar d-   ing the percentage of lower r^ades to be taken.EGfYPTIAH COTTON CONTROL.   A number of types of Egyptian cotton-   which had been specially reserved for military purposes Have,   with the approval of the Director of Raw Materials, now been   thrown- open for the ordinary civil trade of my of the Allies^        In view of the recovery of the lille district and the   prospective requirements of Alsace the amount of the Egyptian   cotton allocated for export to Prance is being increased,   A substantial quantity of cotton purchased in Egypt for expert   to Prance still remains unshipped and talcing this into account   it appears that French requirements will be met by an increase   in the ration from the new crop which had provisionally &quot;been   alloted to her of not more than 15,000 bales.        Spinners in this, country h^ve up to recently been entit-   led to. place orders with a guarantee of price for Egyptian   cotton up to. .50$ of their annual requirements as ceitified   by the Cotton Control Board.   The amount which they areA.H, STARU2Y.11th December,  1918,COMMERCE AND IEDU8TRY,entitled
             entitled to order has now been increased by a further             20;&apos; of their retirements to 70$.IMPORT AND        In viev; of the armistice the Board of Trade haveEXPORT ttiS-   found it possible to re las a lar^e number of the existing?MCTroS^.  restrictions on imports and exports.   A number of oca-             mo&amp;ities vdiich were on list A aid whose export without             licence was thus- prohibited to all destinations.hnve been             transferred to list C and can now &quot;be exported without             licence to all countries other than those bordering on             the enemy.   For the present, exportation to the latter             countries of all goods (ercept printed matter and personal             effects)  remains subject to licence, but the complete free-             ing from restrictions of a large  number of goods has been             considered by the Intor-Allied Blockade Committee and will             probably shortly be brought into  effect.   No goods will             be placed on the free list without prior consideration             by the Committee in question, as  common action on the part             of the Allies in this matter has  been decided on by the             Economic Defence and Development  Committee.                  As regards import restrictions general licences valid             until March 1st, have been Given  to Import certain pro-             hibited gocis.    At the request of representatives of the             United States War Tra$e Board further proposals in this             direction will  be  communicated to them confidentially in             future a few days before publication in this country in             order to enable the United States Government to consider             the expediency of taking common action in the matter.             Reciprocally the United States Government will communicate             to us their proposals for removing restrictions on im-             portation into  the United States  of .merica.                  Steps have been taken to appoint a Commit-bee under             the Chairmanship of lord Emmott raid containing representa-             tives of KEnu&amp;cturing and trading interests to advise the             Board of Trade  on licensing policy,   A prelirl:i:.;:ry raeet-             ing of thv-. Committee will be held in the early part of             December.                  In accordance with a decision of the Raw Memorials             Board, the Board of Trade have conferred with the India &apos;             Office and the  director of Rav? Materials (War Office) re-             garding the e;cp or table surplus of jute from India,    It             is proposed that the exportable surplus shall be  rationed             by the Board of Trade in consultation with the India *             Office a ber considering the recommendations of the Jute             Pro gramme C omraittee,ECOIjgOC          In connection with the Memorandum on Economic con-teORT CP    side rations affecting- the Ter ms of Peace which has beenf![T:&apos;&quot;^R!fI:3H  prepared by the Board of &apos;!rade it was considered desirableroiT5T*       that a farther  Memorandum relating to the Economic Effort             of the British  Empire during the  war should be prepared,             to cover  aspects of the aubjeot outside the soope of those             covered by other departments *  This Memorandum has now             been prepared with the * assistan*e of the Supply Departments             and the Foreign Offloe, Colonial  Office, and&quot;India Office             (vftio have contribute?&quot;  sections  relating to those  parts             of the Empire with which they ore respectively concerned).JUTS
KELEA3B OFK)RCM7BUSINESSmrwm                 The Board of Trade hare advised the Ministry oiJWfrxwr             on  questions connected with the release of &quot;pivotal&quot;  tMtt fronu             the forces for Commercial occupations, and have  also  been in             communication&apos;with the Ministry of labour with regard to  tjae             most suitable Central Authorities for selecting  pivotal men             for Railways, Canals, Goal Mines and the Timber  Industry.                 Arrangements have been made under which special  faoi-             facilities will be granted to business men from Allied and             neutral countries who wish to place orders in this country             and are anxious to be allowed entry into the United Kingdom             for that purpose.                 5?he Department of Overseas Trade (Development and In-             telligenoe) have been entrusted with the compilation  of a             register of men, at present serving in His Majesty&apos;e  Forces,             having special knowledge of overseas markets, with a  view             to securing their early release in order that thoy may jaro-             oeed abroad to  represent British interests in foreign countries-             trios and in the Dominions.   On the day following the             signature of the,Armistice a circular letter was issued to             a number of selected firms and to Cliambers of Commerce a&amp;d             Trade Associations inviting employers to make application             tc the Department for the release of any such men, formerly             In their employment, whose services they urgently required.             fm lists of selected names have already &quot;been transmitted to             the Ministry of labour,  who are making the necessary  arrange^            sumtt with the Admiralty and the War Offioe, and it is hoped             t&amp;at these men will be released at- an early date.                 2fhe Board of UJrade, in conjunction with the  Board ot            B&amp;uoatl on and various &quot;per sons and organisations  connected            with art,  mssmfacture, and commerce, have framed a  wMm            for the establishment of a British Institute.of  Industrial            Art with the object of raising the standard of design and            wortaanehip of British works of industrial art and  of etlmu-            lafclng the demand for such works as reaofc a high standard             of excellence.   It is not proposed that the Institute ftUali            be aotually opened until after the War.    It will be  in-             corporate d under the joint auspices of the Board of $a?%4t            and the Board of Education and its objects will  include            a permanent exhibition in London;  a selling agency;  a put-            chase, fund;  the establishment of machinery for bringing  de- -            signers and art workers  into touch with manufacturers,die-&quot;            distributors  and others;   and the organisation of provincial            and travelling exhibition.   It is also proposed to  con-            stitute an independent Committee to select  works  for  ex-            hiMfclon.iftnSB ffi8?J?I      ^he details of a scheme for affording State  assistanceSM^OilJ^ the  Dye Industry have now been published in the form of            a White Paper, Cd.9194 and arrangements  are being made to            set up the two conmittees required for the administration            of the  scheme.BRITISH IK*fflfITmmmcHZOL.     In view of the proposal to  release  Benzol  for use as a motor spirit tho iDepartjment has  made  arrangements, with treasury approval,  to purchase 30,000 tons  of crude Benzolat the present fixed&apos;price, for  delivery over the next yewto dye manufacturers,  it  being recognised that  the provis-ion of Benzol at a  reasonable price is absolutely essentialto the aye industry.MM&apos;
      Under T irporary War  legislation five  applications  for the grant of Licences to  work  enemy owned  patents  toe  been heard by the Board and four  applications for  licences to reproduce copyright works.   One  of the applications in respect  of copyright referred  to  Herr ErzbergerS  book entitled,&quot;Der Volkerbund&quot;.   Herr Ersberger,  it  will be re- membered, was one of the  German plenipotentiaries  to oon- olude the armistice, and  it  is  interesting to note that in this  book,  he outlines  a  draft  constitution for  a  League of Nations.    A -licence has  &quot;been  recommended  in  this oase, and the  book will shortly be published.      The  question of tricing  immediate fcteps for  the de- veloprnent *of the  electrical supply  industry is receiving my earnest attention.      The  Economic Defence end Development Committee re- cently authorised me to appoint three temporary Electricity Commissioners in  advened  of legislation.   I  hr,ve, however, on further  consideration, decided not to e;:ercise  this authority at  the  moment, but to appoint ct once an adviser to  the b of.rd  of IPrade on all matters arising  out of the Electric  Power Supply Committee&apos;^ Report.      I em in communication with Sir John Snell, an eminent consulting engineer, on the question whether  he will accept this  appointmant.                                                          4     A Sub-Committee of the Water Power Resources Committee has been  appointed to deal specially with Ireland.                  PAB6R COffgROIu     A number  of  questions arising out of the signing of the Armistice  have occupied the attention of  the Department.    &apos;  The  tonnage  situation lias eased with une^peoted rapid- ity,  and  there is new reason to anticipate that sufficient tonnage will  be available to bring in licenced imports with  reasonable regularity, although&apos;the exceptional  Ameri*&apos; can demand which  was the principal cause of the trouble has not been  finally withdrawn.      The  arrangement  wade for the supply of paper to Can- di&amp;ates has worked smoothly end well, e:;cept in casos where applications  have been left until an unduly late date.     Tm  amounts  paid in to the Controller^ account  dur- ing Ilovemher  hsve amounted to  127,000.      In view  of the urgent demand for an additional supply of newsprint  in connection with the General Election; aid in  order to increase the supply to the general trade, an allocation oqullto a further two months&apos;  proportion of im- ported materials, paper and cardboard, has  been made  to  all Importers, lrimufacturers or Dealers.   This special allo- demobilisation was practicable for tw reasons (1)  the claims from Newspapers under the specie!  allocation announced in July proved smaller in amount than had been estimated;  (2) under the Central Ihxrcheoe scheme o certain quantity ai pulp hadbeen contracted for but had not yet been el located.   It is orrpected that the bulk of the demand will be satisfied from these two sources     With the release  f large supplies of  metal, eto.,previously required fox essential  war production it is becoming easier to obtain machinery for  the maintenance and equipment of jfaper mills.                                                   COAL                        M
GOAL CONTROL.LAXATIONMill        The decision  of the War Cabinet as to therelease of miners  from the Army will result in the return.of practically the whole of the men in question by themiddle of January, and it is anticipated that thesituation will be  considerably easier after the New Yearholidays.    Until that time, howeY6r? the effect of theloss of output through Armistice rejoicings and influenzawill continue to be felt, the home position at the presenttime beinpr so serious that in order to secure fullsupplies of house  coal and avoid unemployment it has been necessary to impose drastic restrictions for the timebeing on the export of coal both to Allied and Neutraldestinations (Italy and Norway excepted).        The amount ft authorised for payments to ownersas compensation up to the end of November was slightlyover  1,500,000 and the amount received in the way ofCoal Mines Excess  Payments about  200,000.        It is proposed to dispense with permits inrespect of Home Grown Timber, also to  increase from 20 to  100 the value of imported softwood Timberwhich may be purchased in a month without a permit.        The Treasury  have granted credits for 25 MillionKr. snread over the first four months  of next year, forthe purpose of obtaining supplies for  Scandinavia.   Itis hoped that further credits may be granted so that full advantage may be taken of snipping facilitieslikely to be available.                Patrol Control.        By a new Order of the Board of Trade which comes into effect on the 1st  December,  the restrictions imposed upon the use  of  motor spirit-by  the motor spirit  (Consolidation)  and Gas Restriction Order, 1918,have been relaxed, and  motor  spirit obtained under a licence  issued by the Petrol Control Department may nowbe used for driving a motor vehicle of any type for all purposes within a radius of 30 miles  of  the place wherethe vehicle  is kept.         was mmrni m amiss.        The difficulties that have  been  experienced duringthe past two years particularly  in  keeping&quot;the  horsetransport  of the Country f?oing,  through  tne  lack  bothof heavy horses and  of feeding  materials,  are  beginning to disappear,  and it is expected that  it  will  be&apos;possiblevery  shortly to amend the Horses Rationing Order  in  sucha way  as  to  admit of a limited  cereal  ration  to horsesthat  are not strictly engaged  in trade or business.        The  Boards  of Agriculture for England and scotland having withdrawn  their restrictions as to thesale of Horses from Farms,  the Board of Trade hasrescinded it3 Order r*oulatinj* the ourohase of horsesfrom Farms for tan c*erv.ee., s                  The -
        The demobilisation of the  Array  horses which willvery shortly take place will have  the efleet of  reducingthe price of heavy ho^afor town service which has risen to an unreasonable fi*mre  during  recent months.        Arrangements are beino- made to  assist thoseActing Returning Officers who are  unable  to securetransport for the conveyance of  voting  compartments andballot boxes for use at&apos;the forthcoming general  election.(6)

</content>
</cab>
