<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/71/0 images: 398-401</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
G.T. 6479

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)

???

WAR CABINET

INDUSTRIAL UNREST - UTILISATION OF NATIONAL FACTORIES

?RANDUM BY THE CONTROLLER GENERAL OF CIVIL DEMOBILISATION AND RESETTLEMENT.

I desire to draw attention to the growing unrest amongst the workers. The cause of the unrest appears to be primarily due to the workers&apos; fear as to the future and their dread of a long period of unemployment which will be used in order to reduce wages as soon as the present Act guaranteeing present rates of wages is allowed to  lapse. The points, which the workers press with the greatest insistence are :-

1. That for these workers for whom employment cannot be found, the out-of-work donation - even though increased - is altogether inadequate.

2. That no National Factory should be closed, but that the State should keep them all fully employed on the manufacture of peace products.

3. That is where is not enough work at the moment to keep everybody employed, the output per worker and the number of hours worked should be reduced, and that wholesale discharges are unnecessary.

4. That wages are at present at or below the decent subsistence level, and no reduction can be tolerated unless and until the cost of living is reduced.

In addition to those points, the skilled men&apos;s unions are very ?tent that the Government pledges on the subject of dilution shall ?pt, and constant difficulties are arising, both in connection with ?ismiscal of employees and the re-absorption of women and dilutees, ? to uncertainty on this point.

Further to the above points, which are common to all classes and sexes of workpoople, representatives of the National Federation of ?arged Soldiers and Sailors also claim that:-

(a) No ex-soldier or ex-sailor now employed is to be discharged from his civil employment except for  misconduct;

(b) A guarantee of employment is to be given to all soldiers and sailors ? and when they are discharged from the Army or demobilised;

(c) Discharged soldiers and sailors are to be given civil employment in preference to other workers, even though their individual skill or capacity may be less than that of other applicants.


     I agree that questions of great difficulty arise inconnoction with all the above matters,  &quot;but I am confident that organised 1ahour will not be satisfied until someauthoritative pronouncement is made.     To examine the above points in detail:-     1.   The question of an increase of out-of-work donationmay bo considered to be settled by the recent increase of5/-,   I do not consider that any further increase can booontomplatod, although it may be that the 13 weeks&apos;  poriodmay havo to be oxtonded if unemployment is very bad in thoearly Spring,     2,   The question of the utilisation of National Fac-tories bristles with difficulties but is one to which boththo working classes and the manufacturers attach greatimportance from diametrically opposite points of view.  the workpeople feel\ that tho Stato is a better employer than thoprivate manufacturer, and protest with vigour against beingturned out of Government employment when a demand exists forarticles which tho. National Factories are, or could well be,adapted to make,     As against this argument the confidence of the manu-facturing community will be seriously shaken, and privateonterpriso will be chocked if there is any prospect ofGovernment competition on a, largo scale.     In my opinion there is, however, a middle course, andthat is the temporary use of certain of the National Factoriesfor such special purposes as for overtaking the arrears of rolling stock repairs (there are 38,000 wagons awaitingrepair), repairs to cars, lorries, etc, the replenishmentof  stocks of certain Government stores and any other non-recurring emergency work of a similar nature such as convcrt-ing shells, fuzes, etc., into parts of articles required for commercial purposes.   This question has already been raised inparagraph 7 of the Memorandum on Demobilisation and Employ-men t circulated to the V/ar Cabinet by the Minister of reconstruction in October 1918 (G.T.6047).     3.,,  Where; big discharges have been anticipated owingto  cessation of war contracts, every effort has been made to persuade employers to reduce hours and also to change over from payment by results to time work, but many employersrefuse to do so on the ground that such a change is not onlycostly for them but also very bad for their workpeople, andthat if the system of payment by results is abandoned, eventemporarily, the difficulty of extending it in the future will bo greatly increased,     4.   In my opinion it is not possible to givo the workersany assurance as to the continuance of the present Act afterthe end of the current six months, and that tho rates ofwages after that time must be settled by Industrial Councils,by  discussion between the employers and tho workpeople, orby  arbitration if the parties agree to; -this course.   Greatgoad could, however, be done by taking immediate steps to
reduce the cost of certain staple -articles of food.    I hwealready urged the importance of this course in ray memorandaof 26th November ^nd 5th December.   The present high cost ofliving is contributing more than anything else to industrial unrest.     5.   A very esrly settlement of the War Pledges Billis necessary.   Any further delay will only increase theirritation and suspicion of the skilled unions and render mor*difficult the rc-gbsorptron or&quot; women and dilutees into indus-try.              &apos;&apos;. ?:  ; :V;     6,   The &quot;settlement with! regard to the dilution pledgesshould also include 9 declaration as to the position of ex-soldiers and ox-sailors/  The provisions of the Munitions cf -War Act, besidos applying only to controlled establishments,are very vague and can easily be nullified by employers whoare desirous of avoiding their obligations.   With regard to ex-soldiers and ex-sailors now in employment, a memorandum isattached.     I urge that a decision as to the policy of the Govern-ment on these various points should be taken with the least possible delay.Stephenson Kent14.12.18.
WAR PLEDGES AND &amp;X-MEIBERS OP H.M. FORCES.       (1) Questions are reaching the Department from an increasing number of sources with respect to  the treatment through civilian Demobilisation of discharged sailors and soldiers who have sinoe their discharge been in civilian employment.   Claims are being made both through Shop Committees and through the Federation of Discharged and Demobilised Sailors and Soldiers that these men shall be the last to be discharged and the first to be given vacant posts.   . The numerous Deputations which are visiting the Department nearly always contain representatives of the discharged sailors and soldiers, and are generally the most difficult element in the  deputation,    he question has assumed a very real importance and a decision is immediately required.       (2)  In the first place a clear distinction must be drawn between tho disabled man and the rest of the discharged! men.  In respect of disabled men the State has undertaken a special obligation to provide him with a pension in every case where his disablement is due to war service.   Moreover the State is ready to give a disabled man industrial training in any case where he cannot resume his own occupation, or bi likely to suffer if he did go.  It is further proposed that an appeal shall be issued to employers inviting them to reserve a peroentage of posts for disabled men.  So far as a disabled man is concerned. therefore, while he is not completely covered it is fair to say that a good deal has been done, or is being done to meet his case.      (3)  She position of the ordinary ex-service man is different.- These men divide themselves immediately into two categories. In the first class come the men who return to their old occupation, either skilled or unskilled.   These men have, where they were employed in Controlled Establishments at the beginning of the war a statutory right to priority of employment, and in many cases have be promised reinstatement.   So far as this class is concerned, they are I think entitled, if they are discharged, to be discharged last, though even as regards these men the general consideration set out below will have to be taken into account.   The second category contains the ex-service men who have entered employments different from those which they followed before the war.   Where such men have entered Industrial Establishments, and particularly munitions works, they will in practically all cases be in the position of dilutees.   It is clear that their claim to special treatment is difficult to uphold.   The Trade Unions would claim that they were admitted during the war on sufferenoe, and that it is not fair either to their members at home or to those still in the Eoross to give them preference.   It is certainly ntt possible to say that they shall be retained in the face of pledges, to the contrary.   It is diffioult to go so far as to say that if they must be discharged, they should be discharged last, and it is clearly difficult to say that they should be reinstated first,      (4)   The real solution is to proceed with the pledges Bill. that Bill contains the original clauses proposed by the Conference under ray Chairmanship to the effect that there shall be general prio of employment in their old jobs to -members of H.H.Porces, the positi will be largely met.   The discharged members of the Forces who have a definite olaira on specific grounds will have their claim met. This will cover a large part of the ground, leaving only the general claim to priority to sailors and soldiers not in their own jobs on the score of fighting services.   This claim if conceded would lead tc sharp division between the men who worked on munitions andthose who fought.  The only way to avoid this difficulty is in my view to announce the proposal to proceed with the pledges Bill.  It will then be for persons dissatisfied with the proposals to en- deavour to amend it in Parliament.                                             14.IS.18.

</content>
</cab>
