<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/71/0 images: 481-489</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                            :   379iis  ncciTXiiT  is  Tine pro.p5P.ty    HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government).&apos;   .              WAR cabinet R E T. 65QQ,              &apos; HEPORT OF THE  HIP ARTMENT AI, COMMITTEE                      ON AWAR30S TO ITOUTTORS ..         I circulate the attached report cf the Departmental   Committee rn Awards to Inventors.  I agree with the recom-   mendations cf the Committee that a Commission should be   established as recommended in paragraph 11 of the report,   and I  think that the sanction of the Cabinet should be given   to the proposal as soon as possible.                                (Intld.)  A.3.L.Treasury, S,W. 1.   17th December, 1918.*
             REPORT OF T?!E DEPARTMENTAL COMMITTEE                    ON AWARDS TO INVENTORS,,,      To the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty&apos;s Treasury.      May it please four Lordships.         In accordance -with TheLr lordships  Minute of  27thJune 1918 appointing us a Committee.      &quot;To enquire whether any changes in the  existing pro-cedure for determining awards to inventors during the war are desirable and if so of what nature ?*&apos;   we have the honour to submit a Report embodying the conclusions at  whichwe have arrived.      We have construed the word &quot;inventor&quot;  to includepersons who have provided the Government with valuableprocesses,  designs or drawings though no element  thereinenables the inventor to claim a monopoly.      The existing procedure is governed by  Section 29  cfthe Patents and Designs Act 1907 which re-enacted sectionsof earlier Acts as fellows      &quot;29.   A patent shall have to all intents the likeeffect as against His Majesty the Kins as it  has  against a subject.      provided that any Government department may, by themselvetheir agents, contractors, or others, at any  time after theapplication,  use the invention for the services of theCrown on such terms as may,, either before or  after the  usethereof, be agreed, on, with the approval of  the Treasury,between the department and the - patentee, or,  in default ofagreement,  as may be settled by the Treasury  after hearing  all parties interested.&quot;      prior to the war, claims for awards in respect of  Inven-tions of military value were dealt with as follows.      The Admiralty and Army Council had standing authority  -to award lump sum rewards up to  100 in each case to non-service inventors.  Larger amounts and awards to serviceinventors required the approval of the Treasury as wellas that of ths Admiralty or Army Council,  which was generally given on the recommendation of the  Ordnance Council,an Interdepartmental Committee composed of 12 members of   *whom 8 were civilians, 3 were military and 1  was a naval officer.      Payments to non-service inventors taking the formof Royalty could be given by the Admiralty and Army Councilup to an amount not exceeding 15 per cent of  the value  ofthe supplies without special reference to the Treasury.  with treasury approval a higher percentage, of royalty could  be awarded.      A non-service inventor dissatisfied with the terms offered him had a right under the section above quotedto appeal tc the Treasury,  A few such appeals have infact been heard by the Board of Treasury,  sitting as a tribunal, the appellants and the. Army Council appearing by counsel,
- 2 -381         raring the first years of the War the situation -asregards the Admiralty remained substantially unchanged,save that the Ordnance Council no longer net as a  jointI r.t e r- T)c pa v cm f n I a 3. Committee to consider awards to inventors.-The representatives of the Admiralty on that Council,  whohad since I&amp;94 sat as a Committee to deal with the l*ssimportant cas*r,  have continued to sit and mak* recommenda-tions to the Admiralty, and these have wherw necessary beensubmitted for approval to the Treasury through the NavalExpenditure Committee,   In July 1917 a larger Committeewas formed with Lord Lytton in the Chair, Colonel  Sir  H.Goold-AcCtfs (representing the Ministry of Munitions) andthe Assistant Secretary for Finance among the members.Expert assessors aie added when considered advisable,  ThisCommittee is still sitting to deal with the more importantAdmiralty cases and those in which the attendance  of arepresentative of the Ministry of Hunitiono is considered desirable,         The situation as regards the War Office has been changed during the war by the formation of the Ministryof Munitions and the transfer to it of a great part ofthe Amy supply work including all munitions of war,motor transport and aeronautical supply.   Eor uuch partof the supply work as still remains with the War Office,the standing authority for payment of rewards and royaltiesas above stated remains in force, but, as mentioned abovecases are no longer considered by the Ordnance Committee. Inits place, the Munitions Inventions Department has acted asa technical advisory body for inventions falling within  theWar Office province.         On the formation of the Ministry of Munitions,the same powers of making awards, viz,  100 in lump sumawards and Royalties up to 15% t were authorised by theTreasury.   The amount of the awards has been considereddepartmentally in the Munitions Inventions Department  ofthe Ministry of Munitions and submitted for Treasurerapproval.         For the greater part of the inventions relatingto Aviation the Ministry of Munitions, as the Departmentdealing with aeronautical supply, is responsible;   but certain air inventions, in particular those relating too operations, are dealt with by the Air Ministry departmentallysubject to Treasury sanction.         In our view, tho above procedure is no longersatisfactory for several reasons.  In the first place wethink the limits of the Departments&apos; independent authority,whioh may have .been suitable in peace, are no longer in  semerespects suitable under war conditions.   We think that  onthe one hand the  100 limit is too low, and that without undue danger of mutual inconsistency the departments could safely be allowed to award larger lump sums to outsideinventors and that the same discretion should be given in thecase of service inventors.         On the other hand the power to go up to 1% Royaltyof the value of supplies, gives, regard being had to thevast quantities of munitions and warlike stores required during the war, too great an opportunity of divergence.  sums of colossal magnitude might in certain instances be payable for inventions, for which a much more moderate sum wouldreally be an adequate reward.
3382         Tho Comptroller and Auditor General  in his  report  onthe Appropriation Account of tho Ministry of  Mumtions  1916/1 /corned on the situation vrhich arises from tho. general authorityto Departments described above ana drarws attention to certaindifferences in Departmental procedure thereunder.         Acain the Treasury occupies a double position underSection 29%f the Patent? Act 1907.  It is mallei upon todetermine what suns dowtmnts shall be authorised to awardto inventors who aro oithcr no-Abers of their  own  staff oroutsiders;  at the same time it has judicial  functions undorthe Section which it in bound to exercise when called uponto do so by an outside  inventor,  It might therefore at anytime happen that after  the Treasury in its departmentalcapacity&quot;had decided that a  certain sun iii a proper onofor a department to pay to an inventor, it would be constrained,sitting as  a Board under Section 29, to decide judicially tnata  different sum  should  be paid  to him.   it  is in theendeavour  to avoid the  difficulties created  by this anomalousposition that  the general authority recited  above has beengiven to departments.         The large increase&apos;in  the  number  of casesowing to the War,&apos;&apos; and the fact  that awards have to  besettled after  instead of before the user of  the invenhas  emphasised  the need for efficient machinery &quot;/hieshould  maintain  a uniform  standard of  awards between different  Departments.         The whole question is  one  of  great  complexity and both  the persons to whom awards may be  given and  the matters in reppect of  which awards  may be  given fall into  several classes.     The  person  to  bo rewarded may  be either a servant of the Crown  whether naval, military  or civil  and holding either a permanent  or temporary post, or  a  person  not in the  service of&quot; the  Cro&quot;?n.          The masters  in respect of which awards may be given may be  either useful  only for naval,  military or  air service, or useful commercially as  well as for naval  military or air service 0          Further the  difficulty of determining the  proper amount  to be awarded is increased by the following considerations.          In some oases, it  is doubtful &quot;whether an invention is patentable;  and during the war it is in  many  cases impossible to have this question decided by the Law Courts.          In other cases designs or drawings  whioh may not be registrablc are  adopted by the Department and  the compensation r-uyable  in reppect of them has  subsequently to be determined...                                         J          The above  examples do not of course exhaust  the various points of  difficulty which arise;  they are cited in order to illustrate  the difficulty of the problem,. involved a?eii??r^S^0ii?  ?oint     that.th* ^  which may  be in wiT  2     extiemexy large and that  a mistake in  the basio on which an award  is  made  may have most  serious consequences either  by involving public  funds in unnecessary expenditure &apos; er by giving a quite  inadequate rewardto  nS iJrSrtS?nn ,       ^e have ascertained that  there  are  at least 40 oases  nowunder  consideration by  the  Admiralty and 40  cases now  under L* sideration by  the Ministry  of Munitions  (excluding  ?hos&quot;SdS^M??    ***  SERVI*C) *HICH      *T  E  be&quot; ferredindividually to  tho Treasury..   There  are also certain  awiMlnpending under  section 29 of  the Patents Act  1907.        P
 9.       A possible course would be  on the  one  hand  to    extend the limit for lump sum awards which Departments    might make on their own authority and on the other to    reduce the percentage for Royalty awards to  some  lower    -figure, and to extend that authority to  cover service    as well as outside inventors.          We do not consider this would entirely meet the    case.  We think that cases involving very large  sums    and important questions of principle should  be referred    to some expert body, on which the several Departments    should be represented.10.       We therefore recommend that a special  body  should    be set up by Royal Commission to  deal with these    questions, and that in its constitution  it should be    analogous to the Defence of the Realm Losses Commission.    We recognise that it would not be possible,  without    legislation, tc take away from an inventor the right of    appeal to the Treasury which he has under section 29 of    the patents Act 1907,  or any rights which, he may  have to    appeal to the Lav; Courts.  But we consider that  if a    strong Commission constituted as  proposed by us  in this    report were set up, it would command public  confidence    and in time the practice of appeals to the Treasury and    to the Lav/ Courts would become rare especially if the    inventor&apos;s reference to the Commission were  made  con-    tirgent upon his agreeing to be bound by  their decision.11.       We consider that the proposed Commission should    consist of the following members          (a) A Judge of the High Court as ohairman          (b) one representative from each of the four    departments concerned, namely the Admiralty,  the  War    Office, the Ministry of Munitions and the Air Ministry.          (c) one civil servant, with  special financial    experience and          (d) two members of the House of Commons.  It would    be desirable that if possible a member of the staff of    the Patent Office should act as Secretary.12.       We have annexed to this Report a set of suggested    instructions to the Commission.  It will be  observed    that it is proposed that the Commission should have    power to award a sum of  50,000 to any one inventor    payable either in a lump sum or as a maximum limit of    accumulating royalties and that to this  sum  may  be added,    if the Commission sees fit an allowance  in aid of the    expenditure actually and reasonably incurred by  the    inventor in developing his invention.  Within this limit,    we think that the Treasury should act in accordance with    the recommendations of the Commission,  cases in  which    the Commission may consider for special  reasons  that the    above limit is insufficient should be referred by the    Commission to the Treasury with its recommendation and a    statement of the reasons for special treatment.13.       We consider that the limits within which depart-    ments should be authorised to make awards without,    reference to the Treasury or to  the Commission should be
£1,000 either payable in a lump sum or as a maximum limit of accumulating royalties in the case of both civilian and service inventors.

14. ? consider that any inventor who is dissatisfied with the ? offered to him should be entitled to ? to the Commission and to appear before it in person on condition that he agrees to be bound by its decision in all matters arising out of the Crown&apos;s user of the invention. The Commission might however have a disertion in special cases to ? this condition or to limit it to rights arising under Section 29 of the Acts as distinct from other rights which might have arisen from the Crown&apos;s action. e.g. under 7 (a) (b)(c)and (d) of the Craft instructions to the Commission. The ? whether Counsel should appear before the Commission should in our  opinion be ? for determination by the Commission itself, which should lay down its own rules of procedure.

15. It has been strongly argued that awards should be made free of Excess Profits Duty. While recognising that the incidence of this duty causes hardship in some cases, we do not consider that it ? desirable to authorise the Commission to make a recommendation which would amount to an alteration of a taxing statute in ? of a particular person. In many cases, however the form of the award would govern its liability to Excess Profits Duty and to Income Tax and the Commission should not be precluded from selecting a form of reward free from that liability.
APPENDIX.PROPOSED INSTRUCTIONS TO COI-.&amp;ISSION.      The principle on which Section 29 of the  PatentAct of 1907, is framed,  embodying the provisions  of  earlierStatutes is that the State in giving protection,  by  the  granof a patent, to an Inventor not only against  the  general public as individuals but also against the State  in  itsoorporate capacity reserves to itself the right in thepublic interest of determining the amount of  the  award inthe event of state user.  If it had been the  intention ofParliament that awards to inventors should be calculated on a purely commercial basis the Treasury would not  havebeen named as the ultimate arbiter.  But there  is anacknowledged difficulty in determining what is  a  reasonableamount of reward for the State to pay and that  difficulty has been very greatly enhanced by the circumstances  of theWar.      2.  On the one hand, it is more than ever to thepublic interest to encourage invention by giving  inventorssecurity for an adequate award.      3.  On the other hand, the immense scale  on whichMunitions of War are employed during the present  War wouldnot appear necessarily to involve a correspondingly  greatreward to the Inventor.      4.  Further, it must be borne, in mind that the Waris a national calamity and that the Inventors opportunityhas in many cases arisen solely by reason.&quot;, of the existenceof a state of. War; although on the other hand someinventions are the result of years of work and expenditure which would not have been incurred in peaoe time  unless there had boen the hope of a handsome reward in the  eventof a great war.      5,  special consideration is also required  by  theoases of Inventors who are employed by Government whether in the fighting services or in a civil capacity.  SuchInventors have,.in many cases, derived not merely their training but their opportunities of devising and  perfectingtheir Inventions from the Government, and in many oasesinventions arise directly from the performance of their duties,   It has been the practice to take these  circum-stances into consideration in assessing.awards; and  if  theinvention is definitely within the scope of the inventorsduties, no award would normally be paid,  It is not  howeverintended to exclude from consideration persons with  expertknowledge and technical experience gained in civil  lifewho are serving during the war in His Majesty&apos;s Forces  atrates of pay appropriate  to their ranks.&apos;      6,  The Commission should, bear the foregoingconsiderations in mind in assessing awards.
     7.    In dealing with cases which oojnu &quot;before then theCommission should furthoi&apos; consider    (a)    Whether the Department is to Tamo the right tovend the invented article as well as to make and use it.    (b)    Whether the department is to have the right toauthorise Foreign Governments or Pirns to use it with or without the right of vending.    (c)   Whether any or all of the above rights are to beavailable for commercial as well as for defence purposes.     (d)  Whether the circumstances of the transaction are such as to  aoprxve  the Inventor of valuable Foreign Rights.    (e)   Whether tho Inventor  is  to  retain the right ofmaking&apos;and  vending  the articles himself and if  so in whatcountries.    (f)   Whether the transaction  covers  the whole  life  ofa  patent  or only  some shorter  period.          It  is  underttood that any,claims which  theInventors may have  in respect  of  (a)  (b)  I cj  id)  and \ejwould not nroperly  fall  under  Section 29  of the Patents  and designs Act,  1907,    If  it is1  intended that the department should  acquire  ail  or any of the  rights  under  (aj (b)  and (c)the rights  or right to- be acquired should be  expressly made over  by the Inventor to  the Government and the. payment  of theaward should  be  contingent on  this if it  has  not  alreadybeen  done,    As  regards  (d) (e)  and (fy,  these are  matterswli...ch it  is suggested should be taken into accoUnt  in fixing the amount  of his award.   If  tho Inventor is  to be prohibited from making&apos;and/or  vending the invented  articlesproper measures must be  taken  to  secure this.    When theInventor  is to place his services at the disposal of theDepartment  for making,applying and developing the inventionthis  would constitute a  further matter for consideration in assessing the amount of  the award.           In p-jcmo cases  processes or designs  or drawingswhich may not be legistrablc are  adopted by a Department.The compensation reasonably payable in respect of this user should also bo decided  by the  Commission,      8.   Following on  the general position outlined above, it appears advisable that there should be a maximum limit ofthe amount  which the Commission should be empowered to award, in fenpoot  of any particular invention,  a limit which, while largo enough to form a  very substantial inducement  to Inventory tc devote their talents of invention to the service of the Crate, will yet  Becure  the.State against excessivepayment s.     -9&quot;   It  has been decided to  fix this sum at  ^0,000whether payable in a lump sum or as the maximum limit ofaccumulating royal ties.   To this  sum may be added,  if the Commission  see fro. an  allowance in aid of expenditure actuallyand reasonably incurred by the Inventor in developing his in-vention.   Oases an which the Commission may consider that for special reasons even this limit.is insufficient, should be ret erred with the Commissions recommendation, and  a statement or the reasons for special treatment to the Treasury.A-      .         on desirable to consult tho Ooumissionersoi li-and Kavenrn in oases where  there j.3 anv GPMC. r-m    to
   11.   The Commission should bring to notice  any points which in the course oft heir experience of claims  submitted  tothem may show the need for special instruction  or  legislation.   12.   Before hearing an appeal the Commission should(unless they see reason to the contrary) Satisfy themselves that the claimant has agreed to abide by iheir  decision in all matters arising out of the Crown&apos;s user of the  invention.(Sgd.$   R.H.  Bacon.                 (Sgd.)  Stanley Baldwin.(3gd).   Philip G.  Henriques.        (Sgd.)  O.L.  Barstow.(Sgd.)   P.  Tindal  Robertson.        (Sgd).  G.C Upcott.1st November 1918.       In view of the urgency of presenting this&apos; Report,  werecord our general agreement with the proposals-contained inIt.   But some amendments, on point of fact, have been introduced in it since it was before us in draft with which  weare not in agreement.   The awards given by the Army Councilwithout Treasury sanction, in a lump sum up to a limit of 100 or in royalties up to 15$ of the value of the articles.have not been confined to the cases of non-service inventors,and the Report should, In our view, be read as amended.on thisquestion of fact with such consequential modifications asnaturally follow from it.Secretary.(Sgd),&apos;0.E.  Cobb.21.10.18.(Sgd).CW. Biggs.Lieut. Col.(Sgd) .P.C. Borenschen.      The grant&apos; of lump sum.awards  up to  100 withoutTreasury sanction has not been limited to non-serviceinventors by the Ministry of Munitions.(Sgd).   R.H.  Bacon.1.11.18.

</content>
</cab>
