<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/171/0 images: 215-215</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Lt^ DOCUMENT IS thb property op HIS BRIMKIO majesty f3 government. 165 IgjjSJ/ C A B I HE T.l.p.36  (25).further programs of road   jqrks.Memorandum by the Minister of Transport .I hAve discussed ?/Ith the Chancellor of the Exchequer the programme of further road works to be financed from the Road Fund submitted to the Cabinet in CP.55lC.Uf.).It has been suggested by tho Chancellor that, as the estimated net surplus revenues of the Road Fund for the period ending 51st March, 1930, are approximately  6.000,000 It i3 not desirable at this moment bo allocate so large a proportion of them as was proposed in C.p.551. It may be desirable, should the situation not improve, to be able to make an announcement of some further works in the Autumn,   I therefore suggest that the following changes should be made in the proposals previously submitted:-Recommendatlqn by the Cabinet 5omai11e e 1 of Unomployment in CP.551.Proposals now submitted.(1)To authorise the Minister of Transport to allocate the  6,000,000 estimated net surplus revenues of tho Road Fund up to 51st March, 1950 &amp;3 follows:-(i)        632,450Newcastle-Gateshead Bridge.(1)     No change        632,450(II)      650,000 towards the con- (ii)   Reduced to      500,000structIon and re-constmction of bridges estimated to coat  1,000,000 in all.(ill)    700,000 toward3 the en-    (lii)   No change      700,000largement -and improvement of .1st and 2nd Class **Roads and the construction of new roads of classification value estimated to cost  1,200,000 in all.(iv)  2,000,000 for reconstruct-  (iv)   Reduced to  1,000,000ion of trunk road a for ifhich  5,000,000 was previously provided.(v)  1,000,000 for similar pur-    (v)   Reduced to     500,000poses In the Highlands of Scotland.(vi)  1,000,000 in reserve. 3,352,450I have discussed this proposal with the Secretary of State for \Tsr, who concurs. , ,.Ito of Tr-Pn^rt. (Initialled)   W.A.of Transport,., ,. &amp;ehpli Gardens, S.v9.1. r&apos;cn January, 192 .

</content>
</cab>
