<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/171/0 images: 230-244</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
In submitting the Naval Estimates which the Admiralty have prepared for the year 1935-26, it is necessary ihat I should furnish the Cabinet with some explanation of the large increase over last year&apos;s figures.They have been drawn up to meet the requirements of the policy adopted by the last Conservative Government and based (1) on the deoision of the G.I.D. of 14th November, 1921, over which the present Chancellor of the Exchequer presided, and (2) of the Cabinet Oommittee of the 4th February 1922, consisting of Mr. Churchill (Chairman), Mr. Stanley Baldwin, Lord Birkenhead, and Mr.E*S.Montagu. There decisions were -(1) &quot;The Committee considered that the number of British &quot;Cruisers mast be based not upon the number of Cruisers &quot;maintained by other Powers., but upon the length and &quot;variety of sea cammanieations over which food and &quot;other vital supplies for the United Kingdom, must be &quot;transported.&quot;(2) &quot;we think it indispensable that the One Power Standard &quot;should be genuinely maintained.&quot;Enough ships of the battleship, battle-cruiser, light.cruiser, destroyer and submarine classes must be kept In commissionpo enable the tactical training and seagoing efficiency of thettoyal Navy to be maintained.        As against 49 battleships andlp battle-cruisers manned with active service ratings before the war,e ape now reduced to 15 battleships and 3 battle-cruisers In fullommission.     Less than this we cannot oontemplate. . (Substantiallyhis is also true of cruisers and Destroyers) *   Any furtheriminution of numbers on Vote A can only be achieved by the payingff of seagoing ships out of this scanty minimum fleet.secret^O R B T.DOCUpNT^IS   THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT.CP   tfT*S$) C   A   B, I   WET......RAVY ESTIMATES 1935*86.^&quot;&quot;^Tfcemortodum by the, First Lord of the Admiralty.
-   2   --It will bo remembered that In the debate of 12th March,1923, the then First Lord said in regard to his Estimate of 58,000,000 - ,,&quot;I should be failing in my duty to this House and to the &quot;Country if I suggested the possibility of further reductions &quot;In our strength in succeeding years.   On tho contrary, I Kmu3t ask the House -to, keep clearly in mind that these are &quot;exceptional Estimates framed to meet an exceptional &quot;financial situation, and that the economies which we have &quot;achieved are In part, at any rate- due to the postponement &quot;of necessary expenditure, which will have to be made up with &quot;the return of more normal conditions*&quot;In the following year Mr. Amery prepared Estimates, which I understand were agreed to by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, amounting to  57,250,000, together with a special building programme of  5,000,000 - making an increase of  4,750,000 on his previous year*s figure.But the Labour Government reduced these figures, and presented to Parliament a total Estimate of  55,800,000* Thus you have -1.   Mr. AmeryTe &quot;Exceptional&quot; Estimate for 1923-24..  58,000,0002.   Mro Amery1 s proposed Estimate for-1924-5.......  62,250,000(including for new programme  5,000,000).3.   Labour Government aet&amp;al Estimate for 1924-5..  55,800,000(including for now programme  1,800,000)*If you compare 2 and 5, it appears that tho Labour Government (besides Initiating a smaller programme of construction costing  3,2oq,000 less than that accepted by the previous Government) reduced tho Estimates, already *?ut to the bone, prepared by Mr. Amery, by   3,250,000.This reduction, however, was obtained, as to  600,000 by deferring important services, and aa to  400,000, by depleting reserves, - expedients that in themselves inevitably swell the total for which I have to ask this year..      The remaining  2,250 , 000 was reduced &quot;by discounting in advance&quot; ( to quoto
the First Lord * a statement) &quot;various causes of possible delay in the advancement&apos;1 of ship cCnstructlon and other contract workprovided, for in the Estimates of the year ( 1,900,000) and bybudgetting for a larger receipt from Approprlatic-ns-in-Aid.Tha net Navy Estimate a for 1925-26 amount in all to 65,500,000 so that an increase of  9,700,000 over the publishedEstimates for 1924-5 has to be accounted for.      -2,250,000 of thisdifference,, howeverIs accounted for by the special expedient ofthe overhead &quot;out&quot; to which I have referred, so that the realdifference between the figures of the two -years- is  7,450,000*Besides this difference there are three factors which have animportant bearing on the Estimates In the coming year(1)   The fall in the amount of the Annuity In repayment of Naval Works Loan by  580,000*It was understood for the last two or three years that wa should hold back the beginning of Important new Nava&quot;i Works until this anticipated fall in the Annuity became due, so that the extra cost of these New Works might be found out of it.     A number of important New Works were consequently begun in 1924-5 with the result that there is a net extra charge on Vote 10 in the coming year of  279,000 for continuance of Works already begun.     There is also expense for Singapore, beyond the  250,000 covered by the contribution from Hong Kong, amounting to  53*000: so that the amount of the fall In the Annuity which-is not balanced by these Items is  248,000*(2)   The amount of War Charges Included in 1924-5 Estimates was  200,000*   We anticipate that the&apos;War Charge a in the coming year will be  120,000, or  80,000 less.(8.)   In the coming year a charge for the Fleet Air Arm amounting to  1,323,000 will be included for the first time in Navy Estimates.   The charge for this Arm has In previous years been borne on the Air Estimates,&apos;whloh will henceforward recover tha cost from Navy Estimates by an AppropriatIon-ln-Aid*   Similarly a sum of  50,000 will be Included as an Naval contribution to the overhead charges of Shoeburyness .a.rp Experimental Station, hitherto borne entirely on Army Estimates..If these factors are allowed for -  248,000 and  80,000 on one side of the-aocount and  1,323,000 and  50,000 on the other side   -   the increase Whioh I have to explain amounts to  6,405,000*Increase * * * * *
4 -183 Increase to be  explained 7,450,000Add?.For reduction of&quot;Works Loan Annuity , ,o.*. o0,  248,000For reduction of War Charges&quot;3*0000009          80,000Deduct328.0007,778,000Charge for Fleet Air- )Arm . 0 ,        oo, . 1,323,000        )iCharge for. Shoeburyness ) 1,373,000ExperimentalStation .,,.,.,..    50,000Still to be explained   6,405,000Of this Increase a substantial sum is due to expenditure which must be regarded as automatic and uncontrollable, and which must be provided for in any event0   The chief items of this kind are - (a) Increase due to Wages Awards co 620,000(b) Reduced quantity of Naval and VictuallingStores available to be withdrawn without replacement e*e,,o.s,fto....s.*...s*.&apos;,. 620,000(c) Falling off In Approprlations-In-Aid(compared with Estimate before theoverhead &quot;cut&quot;)   ......50,000(d) Increase in.prices  (Oil)   , ,,, 9,.,,, .,,. 195,000(e) Increase inj/Effective Votes (Pensions). 150,000.( )   Automatic Increases in Navy Pay and MenrsMarriage Allowance s . , *,:, ,... 0 o,,...., 234,000-These uncontrollable items amount in all to         1,869,000&apos;The chief increases other than those which are automaticare the following :-    .1.   New&apos;1&apos;programme . of shipbuilding e o    1,950,0002o   Provision for an increase of 4,350 men on Vote A,- mainly consisting of 3,100 men required for training in order to manships  ,,...
-   Q ** -   - ships already laid down and to be completed within the next 3 years.   The proper practicealways followed before the war is to enter the numbers required for training In theyear in which the ships are laid down, butthe policy of postponing Naval reqo. irementshas led to these additions which ought to havebeen provided in 1924/25 at latest beingthrown upon the 1925/26 Estimate^ ,.........,.     42V,0003.     Replacement of Reserves depleted when mr, Amery1s Estimate was cut last year .......     600,0004.     Marriage Allowance for Naval Officers(question now before the Cabinet)............     350,0005. Additional expenditure due to speoial pro-gramme of work on retublng of the cruisers and destroyers&apos; built during the war (with -which the ordinary Dockyard numbers cannot cope)j though they will all require retubing almost simultaneously, It is proposed to spread the work over 6 years .,...............     190,0006, Larger provision Jbr Oil necessary to make up arrears in the accumulation of the approved reserve    ............................     402,0007. Larger provision necessary for renovation and improvement of Dockyard machinery and plant ..........,,     120,0008.     Increased expenditure on improvements inequipment for&apos;the Fleet (Vote 8, Section II -chiefly radio-telegraphic and Fire-controlequipment)...................................     150,0009,     25^ of provision necessary to complete the Reserve Outfit   of Ammunition for the Fleet (provision being spread over 4 years)   ........       53,00010, Special provision for examination and alteration of Fuses and Powder Cases, necessary in order to ensure safety ofammunition ...,.v................. i.&apos;   &apos; &apos;60;000&apos; -4,302,000There are a number of small but.important services, amounting to  234,000 which account for the remainder of the Increase,I have shown above the Increases in the present Estimates over the figures put forward by the Labour Government,      But I should like to call the Cabinet&apos;s attention to the fact that- in January 1924 the Conservative Government were apparently prepared
to spend  62,250,000.     Since that date automatic increases of about  1,870,000 have matured, and the cost of the Fleet Air Arm and part of the cost of Shoeburyness, about  1,370,000 have been charged to the Navy Vote,If these items are added to the figures of January 1924, their total would amount to  65,490,000 which coincides very closely with the expenditure proposed by me9Moreover if the 8 Cruisers and other vessels of the 5 million programme had, actually been laid down, the building figures for 1925/26, even without any     other new construction programme, would have been  12 ,000,000, making, the total of Navy Estimates at least 2 millions more than I have to ask fee 0It Is proposed to lay down the following ships,  and to provide  1,950,480 for work upon them during 1925/26:-5 Cruisers (3 Dockyard-built, 2 contract-built).8 Submarines (1 Dockyard-huilt, 7 contract-built)2 Submarine Depot Ships.2 Destroyer Depot Ships.2 Minesweepers e4 Gunboats (for Chinese rivers)e1 Coastal Motor Boat &amp; 4 Motor boats for the Upper Yangtse.1 Repair Ship.1 Victualling Supply Ship, (NOTEs   Further work on the  ex-German Floating Dock sections is also included in the figures for new construction)eAs regards cruisers, the policy of replacement  adopted by the last Conservative Government has again been followed. A programme of cruiser construction extending over 10 years had   ! been prepared by the Admiralty involving 5 cruisers for 1924-25 and 6 for 1925-26.   But the 8 cruisers which the Prime Minister agreed should be laid down at the close of 1923-24, had he remained in office, were reduced to 5 by the Labour Government, and we are proposing the same number, 5, for this year in
ADMIRALTY, &apos; S.W.I. .27th January, : 1925 *addition to the cruiser which the Australia!  Government are understood to be going to lay down this year.A brief note as to the necessity for including the other vessels is attached,I also append an abstract of the Estimates, and some notes on the various Votes.   But I am convinced that, apart from some minor adjustments, we cannot substantially reduce the sum required without abandoning the One Power Standard, or postponing work which will lead to very serious increases in future years,(Intd.)      W.G . B,
APPENDIX    I.   &apos;NEW:,CONSTRUCTION PROGRAMME,. Reasons for inclusion of pertain types of yesse1s.SUBMARINES *    The reason for beginning to build Submarines no v.- is that, failing replacement, we shall only have 36 efficient submarines on 1st April 1929, \/hereas Japan will have 70, France 53$ and the UaSoA. 74 at the same date.Investigation into our requirements of submarines in the evbnt of War has shown that 80 is the minimum number required for either an Eastern or a European War.   AS the effective life of a Submarine is only ten years, it is essential to build at the rate of 8 Submarines per year. SUBMARINE &amp; DESTROYER DEPOT SHIPS.   In making provision for a north sea war, it was possible to rely to a great-extent on shore bases for Submarines and Destroyers,,    This is not possible When we have to oonsider the probability of the Fleet operating far from the shores of this country, and Depot Ships.must be provided in order to give the necessary mobility to our IPlotillas,Of the two Submarine Depot Ships&apos; to be built, one is necessary to replace the &quot;Vulcan&quot;, whioh is utterly worn out and fit only for harbour service, and the other is to provide an efficient Depot Ship for the China Station, to which it is proposed to assign a larger number of. Submarines. 11WThe two Destroyer Depot Ships ere to replace the &quot;Dido&quot; and; &quot;Blenheim11, whioh have had to be removed from sea service and are only fit for use as Hulks. MINESWEEPERS.    The two Minesweepers included in the 1925-26 programme are experimental.Assuming a life of 20 y/;.,-?xs for existing Minesweepers, it will be necessary to commence replacementat....
at the rate of 4 a year from 1929.-30.Neither of the two types of Minesweeper at present evolved Is entirely satisfactory, and experience is essential in order to evolve the best single type with which to replace existing vessels.   By laying down 2 experimental vessels in 1925-26 we shall have 4 years in which to complete these vessels and try.them out,   This is considered the -minimum time necessary for this purpose.,, ; GUNBOATS.    The four vessels included in the, programme are to replace tho four existing vessels employed in the pro-teotion of British interests in the Yahgtse.    The present vessels are all from 2J. to 28 years of age; two of them are no lon er serviceable for duty in the -waters of the Upper Yangtse, and the. other two are.rapidly approaching a similar state of inefficiency.   During: the last year the Foreign Office have constantly drawn attention to the necessity of making adequate provision for protecting British shipping&apos; and -trade in this quarter.:COASTAL MOTOR BOAT.   The performances Of these little boats  -in the.war are too well known to-need description.   It is considered that in order to maintain a nucleus of a G.M.B. Servioe for training and development work, it is necessary to build one of them each year.REPAIR SHI?.   This is required in connection with the Float-ing Dock to be placed at Singapore, for use prior.to the completion of the Base,    bubsequently she will replace the &quot;Assistance&quot;, our only existing Repair Ship, now 21 years old,YICTTJALLING SUPPLY-.SHIP..   A ship of this type is essential to the mobility of the Fleet, vvhen     orating out of reaoh of the Home Bases or Malta.    The United States Navy, -organised,,,.
organised as it is for operating at distances from its Home Bases - has had such Supply&apos; Ships for many years, end the Japanese have recently built one for service with their Fleeto
appehdiz ruf.ABSTEAOO? OF 8EKEGH NAVY ESTIMATES FOR THE YEAR 1925-26.Vote9xoss Estimatei Appropriations ; ini Aid,Net EstimateTJ^bersT Officers    ;I Seamen &amp;c,; 104,850 (Marine ; 350 (Police.      iMaximum 104,850350,Seo,I.Wages,&amp;c, ,Sec,II.CiviliansVictualling,Medicalfleet Air Arm. EducationalScientificReservesSec ,1,Dockyards &apos;Sec,II,Stores Seen,fuel Sec.Ill, ContractI Armaments WorksMiscellaneous Admiralty&apos;otaI Effective ^ScrvioesHon-Effective ;(Officers)Hon-3ffactive (Men)Pivil Superannuation \15,146,700	87,900	!    15,058,000107,130	i         1,130	186,0005,535,080	920,280	4,606,000496,800	1       40,000	1          456,000 11,323,000	i	j      1,323,000406,025	65,525	:       .  340,500510,431	1       70,631	439,000513,406	\          1,056	!          512,3508,163,670 4,357,700 5,043,000 8,272,080	j      165,070 860,200 500,000 100,000 j	7,990,600 3,497,500 4,543,000 0,172,0005,699,020	350 j000	5,349,0203.278,000	430,000	-&apos;.       2,048,000892,780	80,030	812,7501,234,606	6,106	:      1,228,50061 .,059,428	j 3,685,928	57,373,5002,912,925	j        21,325 i	j       2,891,6004,431,300	33,800 i	I       4,397,500837,824	j I              424	j           83 7,400otal Non-Bffeotive^Services &apos; ,SHAND TOTALo !8,182,049:69. 241,477______55^549,3,741,477^0X126,500. 65,500,000
ISlappendix iii. notes om trs votes .Tote A.     I am asking for an increase of 4,350 men:if,800 are seamen for the 5 &quot;Kent&quot; Glass Cruisers now under construction, and 350 are Marines for three of the &quot;Kent&quot; Glass.     These Seamen and Marines aro required after placing an equal number of &quot;C&quot; Class Cruisers in Reserve.     We are tafcing the risk of two of the &quot;Kents&quot; being sufficiently behind the others in completion for us to defer the provision of the extra Marines and other ratings required for these vessels until 1926-27.1,550 are for completing the extra personnel wanted for the Battleships &quot;Rodney&quot; and &quot;Kelson&quot; now under construction, for the &quot;Courageous&quot; and &quot;Glorious&quot; now being converted into Aircraft Carriers, for &quot;Adventure&quot; and &quot;Emerald&quot;., Cruisers now completing, and for the Fleet Air Arm.     This provision allows for four existing Battleships being scrapped as provided for under the Washington Conference.Of the remaining 1,250, the bulk; are required (a) for crews for the 2 new Destroyers, and (b) for the staff of the new Forton Boys&apos; Training Establishment and for additions to the staff of other Training Establishments on account of extra numbers under training.     200 are additional Apprentices entered in the &quot;Flsgard&quot; Mechanical Training Establishment to meet increased wastage;   and the balance of 300 are for miscellaneous small requirements, all of which have been very carefully scrutinised,I have kept the increase In Vote A down to the figure I propose with some misgiving, because no provision has been made for the crews of any of the vessels that may be approved to be laid down in the coming financial year,nor.....
- 2 -nor for the extra &quot;burden of crossing reliefs due to the greater concentration of our ships in foreign waters.     in making these arrangements the Admiralty are falling considerably short of the recognised rules for calculating and providing manning requirements.There is a small increase in the numbers of the Boyal Marine Police, in case we may bo able to extend the substitution of the Metropolitan Police by this Force:    an economical policy with whiohf I believe, the Treasury is in complete sympathy.Vote lti Section I.    contains the normal provision for the Pay, etc. of the numbers to be borne on Vote A.     This time it also contains a provision of  350,000 for the proposed Marriage Allowance for Officers.Vote JL, Section 11*   provides for the Pay of Civilians employed on Fleet Services, which, since 1914-15 has been voted as&apos;Vote 4.Vote S - Victualling and Clothing, makes the normal provision for the numbers in Vote&apos;A.-     Its only unusual feature is the provision of  46,200 for beginning the construction of a Victualling Store Carrier, estimated to cost  404,000. Votes 3, 5, 6 and 7 prosent no unusual features. Vote 4, formerly used for Civilians on Fleet Services, is now taken for the provision for the Fleet Air Arm, to whioh I have already referred in my Memorandum.In the three&apos;Sections of Vote 8 and in Vote 9 provision is made for beginning the construction of the New Programme of Ship Construction (except the Victualling Store Ship already mentioned under Vote 2).The total expenditure I propose for this New Programme in 1925-26 is  1,950,480, divided over the Vote as follows :-
Vote 2..................... 46,200Vote 8, Section I.......... 157,000Vote 8, Section II......... 174,600Vote 8, Section III........     1,425,580Vote 9..................... 167,100 1,950,480In Vote 8, Section I, money is also taken for the wages of 600 additional men required to cope with a six years&apos; programme of retubing work on the Destroyers and Cruisers that were &quot;built during the war.     As I point out in my Memorandum, these vessels having been built at practically the same date, will require retubing almost simultaneously, and even though it is proposed to spread the work over six years, the ordinary Dockyard numbers cannot cope with it.The extra estimated cost over all Votes of increased Wages Awards to Workpeople in our employment is  620,000. We have been endeavouring successfully in the last two or three years to inorease the system of Payment by Results in the Dockyards, and we ar*e budgetting for an increase of  325,000 expenditure under Vote 8, Section I, on aooount of money earned beyond the cost of ordinary time wages.Under the Fuel Subheads of Vote 8, Section II, we have reluctantly decided, in view of the difficulties of the financial situation, not to ask for the full 500,000 tons of Oil Fuel which previous Boards have aimed at as the standard annual contribution needed to build up the Reserve in order to complete it by the date agreed by the Defence Committee and Cabinet, and we are proposing an increase of 450,000 tons only.121 Vote 10, we ere allowing  250,000 on works (apart from a small sum for staff and equipment) for beginning the resumption of the Singapore Naval Base Scheme. We are fortunately able to balance this by a contribution of.....
- 4 -of  250,000 appropriation in aid from Hong Kong.We are only taking  140,000 for &quot;beginning New Works in 1925-26o    -Most of them are for bringing oar Yards, especially Malta, more up to date in order to cope with the requirements of the modern Fleet,Nothing special requires to be said about the remainder of the Votes, with which Policy is not concerned.

</content>
</cab>
