<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/171/0 images: 430-431</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[&quot;This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]g   printed for the Cabinet.   February 1925.SECRET. Copy No. 9CP. 58 A (25).CABINET.INTER-ALLIED DEBTS.Proposed reply to M. Clementel. Note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.I CIRCULATE to my colleagues a final draft of the note to M. ClementeL &quot;To improve is to change; to be perfect is to have changed often!&quot;Unless I receive further suggestions by to-morrow night (Thursday) the note will be dispatched in this form.W. S. C.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1, February 4, 1925.His Majesty&apos;s Government adheres to the principle of the Balfour note. Much of the substance of this note was repeated in Lord Curzon&apos;s note of the 11th August, 1923, more particularly in paragraphs 2 and 8 to 11 of the enclosure. But paragraphs 6 and 7 of the enclosure, which refer to. Mr. Bonar Law&apos;s proposals of January 1923, are clearly no longer applicable to the existing facts of the situation. These paragraphs were written before the framing of the Dawes plan and on the assumptions that the total German liability would be fixed at a figure less than that adopted in the Dawes plan, particularly in the earlier years, and that bonds of the kind contemplated in Mr. Bonar Law&apos;s plan, with the rights of redemption given in that plan, would be issued. These assumptions are not now tenable. It follows that Lord Curzon&apos;s statement cannot, therefore, in this respect serve as a basis for the policy of His Majesty^s Government.The principle of the Balfour note is that Great Britain should receive from Europe payments equivalent to those she is under obligation to make to the United States of America. His Majesty&apos;s Government cannot accept a position in which this principle could only be achieved upon the basis of the full normal yield of the Dawes annuities or by taking at their face value debts which oannot be at present treated as good assets.His Majesty&apos;s Government have already consented not merely to reduce their claims against the Allies to an amount necessary to cover their own payments in respect of the British war debt to the United States Government, but actually to apply the whole of the United Kingdom share of German reparations to that purpose. This means that Great Britain not only takes to her own charge the whole of her own war damages; but also the  800,000,000 of foreign securities devoted to the general effort before the United States entered the war.In the application of the Balfour note to the existing situation, His Majesty&apos;s Government, remembering that war debts between Allies have been incurred in a common ca/use, have been prepared to consider proposals under which the existing French debt to Great Britain would be reduced provided that the principle of a definite payment by France from her own national resources, fixed with due regard to her relative wealth and taxpaying capacity, is assured without reference to reparations.[12651]
In the view of His Majesty&apos;s Government, therefore, it might be found convenient that the^ienchrpayments should be divided ink) . ^(a.) Fixed annual amounts to be paid by France irrespective of the actual receipt^from the Dawes annuities in a particular year; and (b.) A further annual charge on the French share in the Dawes annuities..It would, of course, be understood, first, that all counter-claims by France against Great&apos; Britain would be superseded, and, secondly, that if and when the payments derived by Great Britain from European War Debts and Reparations were sufficient to provide for the full discharge of the British obligations towards the United States over the full period of such obligations, including the payments already made, any surplus would be used to diminish the burden resting upon Britain&apos;s Allies.His Majesty&apos;s Government entertain the hope that if the French Government were prepared to make proposals for a settlement on the lines here suggested, a solution satisfactory to both countries might be reached.

</content>
</cab>
