<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/171/0 images: 710-716</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ffilS DOCUMENT IS TBS. PROPERTY OF HIS BRITMHIG MaJ3STYTS GOVERN M5NT.SECRET cabinet.F. 32  (25) ROADS IMPROVEMENT BILL.Memorandum by the Minister of transport the above Bill was placed by the Home Affairs Committeein Category C. and in view of the Cabinet approval 4 (25) of therecommendations of the Home Affairs Committee 1 (25), I now askleave to introduce the Bill at an early date.A draft of the Bill^Is attached, from which it will beseen that It contains three proposals(1)   Power to plant trees along roads.(2)   The extension of the Development and Road Improvement Funds Act, 1909, to Include the erection of milestones and sign posts and the freeing of roads from tolls *(3)   Power to conduct experiments.None of these matters can be regarded as controversial and it is considered that the Bill should pass through Parliament without any opposition and Its passage into law at an early date would be of considerable value.(Initialled) W.A.&quot;ministry of Transport, 6, Whitehall Gardens, S,   71.  1.14th February, 1925.
Roads Improvement Bill;ARRANGEMENT OF CLAUSES.Clause.1.   Planting of trees and laying out of grass margins in highways.2.   Amendment of s. 8 of 9 Edw. 7. c. 47. 3.   Power to conduct experiments. 4.   Expenses.5.   Interpretation and short title.67-1
[15 Geo. 5.]        Roads Improvement.drafts  aBILLTOMake further provision for the improvement of   ad. 1925. roads and for purposes connected therewith.      . &quot; T)E it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, J3 by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows :-1. (1) The Minister of Transport (hereinafter re- Planting of ferred to as the Minister) and any county council or trees and other highway authority shall have power to  cause laying out trees or shrubs to be planted and grass margins to be of gr^ss . 10 laid out in any highway maintained by him or them i^gnwaysH respectively; and to erect and maintain guards or fences and otherwise to do anything expedient for the main-tenance or protection of such trees, shrubs and grass margins.15        (2) No such tree, shrub, grass margin, guard or fence shall be placed, laid out or allowed to remain in such a situation as to hinder the reasonable use of the -highway by any person entitled to the use thereof, or so as to be a nuisance or injurious to the owner or occupier20 of any land or premises adjacent to the highway.(3) Where an urban authority incurs expenses under this section in connection with a main road which is maintained and repaired by the authority pursuant to subsection (2) of section eleven of the Local Government25 Act, 1888, the expenses shall not be treated as part of the costs towards which the county council are required67-1 A 2
2Roads Improvement.[15 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1925. to   make an annual payment under  that subsection        except where and so far as the county council consent to their being so treated.Amend- 2. For the purposes of Part II. of the Developmentment of s. 8 and Road Improvement Funds Act, 1909, the expression 5 of 9 Edw. 7. &quot; improvement of roads &quot; shall, in addition to the matters specified in subsection (5) of section eight of that Act, include the planting, laying out, maintenance and protection of trees, shrubs and grass margins in and beside roads, the erection on or near roads of notice fo boards, milestones and sign posts, and the freeing of roads from tolls.47.Power to conduct experi-   , ments.Expenses.Interpreta-tion and short title.3. (1) The Minister may, either by himself or through any authority or other organisation approved by him, con-duct experiments or trials for the improvement of the 15 construction of roads, or for testing tho effect of various classes of vehicles on various types of roads, and may construct such roads and works, erect such plant, provide such accommodation, and, subject to the approval of the Treasury, incur such expenditure as may be necessary 20 for the purpose.(2) An experiment ortrial under this section shall not be conducted on.. any highway maintained by a highway authority except &quot;with the consent of that authority, and, where the highway is a main road 25 maintained by an urban authority pursuant to sub-section (2) of section eleven of the Local Government Act, 1888, the consent of the county council also.&apos;4. All expenses under this Act incurred by the Minister shall be paid out of the Road Fund, and all 30 such expenses incurred by a county council or other highway authority, so far as not defrayed out of any advance made by. the Minister, shall be defrayed as expenses incurred by the county council or authority in exercise of their powers as a highway authority, and 35 the enactments relating to such expenses, including the provisions thereof as to borrowing, shall apply accordingly.5. (1) In this Act the expression &quot; roads &quot; includes bridges, viaducts, subways, road-ferries and footways.     40(2) This Act may be cited as the Roads Improve -ment Act, 1925.

Roads Improvement.DRAFTOF AB  I  L  LTo make further provision for the improvement of roads and for pur-poses connected therewith.LX.  (1.)24$ January 1925.67-1
(This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government).Memorandum by the Home Secretary.This Bill has its origin in the Reports of four Committees dealing with various questions that have arisento the more important provisions in the printed memorandum prefixed to the Bill.      The main objects of the Bill are:-(l)    The development of the probation system by the appointment of probation officers in every district.     It will be assisted by an Exohequer Grant.(2)    A reduction of the more prolonged periods of detention in prison of prisoners awaiting trial.(3)    A simplification in certain respects of criminal procedure.(4)    Various amendments of the law relating to certain offences and the creation of a few fresh offences:    etc.As regards  (l) there is a strong demand for early legislation and the matter was mentioned in the King1s speech.As regards  (2), it may be mentioned that it is proposed that examining Justices shall in certain circum-stances be empowered to commit to any convenient Court for trial;    that if a trial is abortive, tho fresh trial may take place in a convenient Court elsewhere;    that the jurisdiction of Quarter Sessions should be enlarged,  that the number of offences triable summarily by Magistrates with the defendant&apos;s consent should be increased, etc.As regards  (5), grand juries will be abolished at Quarter Sessions;    the unnecessary attendance at the trialpRET. .P.83(25) .HOME    AFFAIRS    COMMITTEE.G A ,B I If E T.ORIMIHAL JUSTICE BILL,  1925.in connection with the criminal law.Attention is drawn

</content>
</cab>
