<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/171/0 images: 791-792</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;a Government.Printed for the Cabinet, February, 1925.SECRET....:       ih-. --. i. ,.. -       Com No.C.P.&apos; 89 5(^5). -,   . ..   . THE CABINET. ,,ARMY PENSIONER EX-RANKER OFFICERS&apos; CLAIM.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.I wish to draw the attention of the Cabinet to the position in regard to the claim made by army pensioner ex-ranker officers.These ex-ranker officers, who are army pensioners given temporary commissions in the war, are in effect asking to be given the same pension and retiring gratuities as were given to ranker officers who were granted permanent commissions. All that they are entitled to and have received is the same treatment as all other temporary officers, in addition to drawing their soldiers&apos; pensions throughout the period of their commissioned service. . All retired officers and pensioners who served in the war drew their pensions throughout, and were not entitled to have their pensions modified by reason of their further service. - .The immediate effect of admitting this claim would be  175,000 a year, the capitalised value of which is  1,750,000, and the aggregate annual payments  3,000,000.The consequential effect of admitting their claim would be that every pensioner private who acted as serjeant, or serjeant who acted as a company serjeant-major or regimental serjeant-major in the war, and every retired captain who was a temporary lieutenant-colonel or brigade commander, would have an equal claim to have his pension reassessed on his temporary rank. The cost of this extension would be  500,000 a year, representing, a capitalised sum of  5,000,000. The aggregate annual payments would be nearly  10,000,000. It is agreed that in equity and law there is not the slightest claim for this reassessment, but it could not be withheld in equity if the ex-ranker temporary officers claim were admitted.The late Government agreed to refer the claim to an impartial committee under the chairmanship of the Right Bon. G. N. Barnes. This Committee reported (Command Paper 2121) unequivocably and absolutely against the claim. The Committee, however, made one slight concession (paragraphs 29 and 32 of the Co.committee&apos;s report), which the late Government approved ; but this concession was not made to the claimants, i.e., the pensioner ex-ranker officers, and only some 20 men were affected. The concession was that a soldier serving on a regular engagement for pension who took his discharge on obtaining a temporary commission before he had had enough service to earn a pension, should add together his soldier&apos;s service and his officers service, refunding his officers gratuity, and get a pension calculated on the combined service, although such service might be short of the 21 years normally necessary for pension.If, for the reasons to wffiich I call attention below, it is considered necessary to re-open the question, the utmost concession which I should recommend would be to extend the principle contained in paragraphs 29 and 32 of the Barnes Committee Report by giving an undertaking to the following effect : &quot; No serving soldier who went to pension on receiving a temporary commission instead of continuing to serve in the ranks shall be worse off as regards his pension than he would have been had he continued to serve until the date he was demobilized in the rank he held before being commissioned. In making a financial comparison, allowance must, of course, be made for pension drawn, rate of gratuity, &amp;c.&quot;The effect of such undertaking would be to allow any ex-ranker officer who could demonstrate that he came within the terms thereof to count his officers service as man&apos;s service towards increased pension, and draw a man!s pension based on his combined service, subject to the refund of man&apos;s pension drawn while serving as an officer, and.
refund of the difference between an officer&apos;s and a man&apos;s gratuity. In other words,.the man&apos;s whole service up to the date of his demobilization would be regarded as having been in the ranks in the same rank as he held when he took a commission. It would be quite impossible to allow a pension to be based on any hypothetical rank which the man might have attained had he continued serving in the ranks. I am advised that there is no likelihood-hood of any claim being substantiated within the terms of such conditions, which in any event would only affect some 500 out of 2,500.I have detailed above the main facts of the claim. The immediate point for consider-ation is the question of whether any further discussion on or re-opening of the claim should be allowed.   On this point the position is briefly as follows : The recommendations of the Barnes Committee were endorsed by the late Govern-ment without consideration by the House of Commons. The question was, however, raised again during the debate on the Appropriation Bill on 4th August last, on the ground that the then Prime Minister had undertaken, when proposing the reference of the question to a Committee, that the House should have an opportunity of acting on the report, and that this opportunity had, up to then, been denied to the House. On the ensuing day Mr. Clynes, the then Lord Privy Seal, promised a future dafe for discussion after the recess.During the last election a memorandum was received setting forth the claims of the ex-ranker officers, the demand being for a &quot; free debate and unfettered decision of the House &quot; in the event of the Unionists being returned to power. As the result of a full discussion on the subject the following reply was sent out from the Central Office to all enquiries, and was given by most of the members to whom the question was referred : &quot; The Unionist Party, when returned to power, will certainly give an opportunity for discussion of the claims of ex-ranker officers.&quot; I have personally been pressed to grant a day for the discussion of the matter and a &quot; free &quot; debate during the present session. In these circumstances it is for consideration (a) Whether a day should be allowed for such a discussion, and, if so,(b) What form the discussion should take, e.g., whether a free debate or otherwise.My own personal view is that having regard to the Barnes Report, the careful and comprehensive nature of its enquiries and the authoritative and definite declaration of its recommendations, it would be most inadvisable to re-open the question, but we may be considered pledged by the answer given on the advice of the Central Office, to give a day, though not necessarily pledged to a debate without Whips. If we can have the Whips on, the debate might take place on the War Office estimates. But unless the Whips are on the risk is too great of a vital vote being given against the Government. If, therefore, it is not possible to put the Whips on and the debate cannot be avoided, a day had better be given and a motion put down which, in the not -improbable event of its being carried, would, while costing a considerable sum of money, not endanger the Government. &apos;   jL. W.-E.The War Office,14th February, 1925.

</content>
</cab>
