<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/171/0 images: 804-805</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*J* O &apos;1[This Document is the Property of His Britannic kajesty1s Government.jCABINET. Copy Wo.I.p. Wo.94  (25)TITHE;   HEW T C EAR GE .Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.Until 1918, the amount payable in respect of each  ,100 (commuted value) of tithe rentcharge varied yearly according to the average prices of British corn for the preceding seven years.In 1918, the yearly amount was fixed at  109,3.11.  (con-siderably less than would otherwise have been payable) until 1st January, 1926.     As from that date, the basis was changed to a fifteen year average, and the result, in the absence of legislation, will be that the yearly amount will rise in 1926 to  130 (approxi-mately).     In the next fev/ years, it may be expected to rise slightly and after 1930, it may be expected to fall gradually.Under the Tithe Rentcharge (Rates) Act, 1899, and the Ecclesiastical Tithe Rentcharge  (Rates) Act, 1920, which expires at the end of 1925, temporary relief from rates is afforded to ecclesiastical tithe owners.There is a strong feeling among the official representatives of the Church, though it is not universally accepted by incumbents, that it would be undesirable that in 1926, when the prices of agricul-tural produce are unlikely to be very high, that there should be any substantial increase in payments for tithe rentcharge, and that though the Church ought not to be asked to surrender any longer their legitimate claims, the stabilisation of ecclesiastical tithe rentcharge at a fixed figure would be more satisfactory, provided it were accompanied by some scheme of general redemption.      Landowners, generally, appear to adopt the same view as regards stabilisation, although they are not so unanimous in regard to the desirability of redemption, particularly in relation to lay tithe rentcharge.     The Church representatives attach to their assent to any scheme on the
lines indicated a condition that any future . payments in respect of ecclesiastical tithe rentcharge should be free from rates.Though for some months representatives of the clerical tithe owners and tithe payers have been in negotiation to arrive at a scheme to meet the situation arising in 1926, no agreement has been reached, and the negotiations are suspended.A Church scheme (Canon Bell&apos;s), a Landowners scheme (Lord Clinton1s) and other schemes have been submitted to me and my present view is that 1 could not recommend the adoption of any of them by the Government.By my direction, other schemes have been explored in my Department, and I desire the appointment of a Sub-Committee to consider the various schemes and advise as to the legislation that should be introduced in fulfilment of the announcement in the King&apos;s Speech.The main points for consideration are:-(1)   The mode of  stabilising the present fluctuating charge; (2)   The extent to which redemption should be required or facilitated;(3)   The relief from rates to be given to clerical tithe rentcharge;(4)   The protection of the general body of ratepayers from the effect of redemption of clerical tithe rentcharge or its relief from rates.(5)   The contributions by the Exchequer involved in the adoption of any scheme.E . Jr&apos; . L . ulT.

</content>
</cab>
