<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/171/0 images: 811-832</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic MajestyV Government]   printed for the Cabinet.   February 1925.SECRET.CP. 98 (25).89CABINET.SPECIAL  REPORT  ON   UNEMPLOYMENT.No. 113.     January 1925.THE number of persons on the Registers at the end of January was 1,240,922, a decrease of 32,963 since the end of December. A sharp increase in unemployment during the first week of the month was followed by an almost equal decline during the second week, with successive reductions in the Registers during the remaining two weeks.The net decrease among men and women may be ascribed mainly to the return of workers after extended holidays in certain industries following the seasonal break in employment at Christmas, rather than to any important improvement in any particular industry. The net increase among juveniles was due to the number of school leavers at the end of the Christmas term who have not yet been absorbed into industry.It will be seen from the detailed reports on the chief industries in Part II of this Report that cotton and motor engineering still maintained their steady progress. On the other hand, the woollen trade suffered a set-back, and the position in this industry is very uncertain.   In the other industries very little change took place.Compared with a year ago, the unemployment figures are slightly lower, but it should be mentioned that at the end of January last year the figures were inflated by a Railway dispute. The industries which have undergone the most marked change during the year appear to be the coal mining and cotton trades; in the former the position is considerably worse than at this time last year, but the cotton industry has begun what may be hoped to be something more than a temporary revival.A. STEEL-MAITLAND.Ministry of Labour.February 24, 1925.(A.) Numbers of Persons on the Registers of Employment Exchanges inGreat Britain.	1923.	1924.		1925.					Jan. 29.	Jan. 28.	Dec. 29.	Jan. 5.	Jan. 12.	Jan. 19.	Jan. 26.	Increase (-t-)or Decrease ( - ) since Dec. 29, 1924.Men Boys Women Girls	1,121,408 52,383 217,640 44,211	982,083 43,550 254,026 40,859	969,815 35,308 ! 238,626 i 30,136 j	998,174 37,788 238,475 32,703	969,737 39,536 235,162 35,419	959,684 39,517 234,561 35,971	935,495 37,778 231,678 35,971	- 34,320 +   2,470 - 6,948 -t   5,835Total    ..	1,435,642	1,320,518	1,273,885 il,307,140 i -		1,279,854.	1,269,733	1,240,922	- 32.963ine above ngures represent tne number 01 persona recurueu aw nuu wmi uue uara gucu, wuowioi they were totally unemployed, suspended or stood off, &amp;c, or working systematic short time and claiming-unemployment benefit.Percentage of unemployment (Great Britain) in the insured industries at the end of January 1923 ,, 1924 ,,      1925[12714]12-8 11-8 11 3B
due to the cessation of temporary seasonal employment and to slackness of work at the docks. In the case of Canning Town the decrease of women was due to the re-engagement of golf ball workers.(B.) Important Changes in the Live Registers of Employment Exchangesduring the Period.London and South-Eastern Division.Bermondsey.- Increase 1,067 (915 men, 152 women)Borough. Increase 1,343 (1,122 men, 221 women)Canning Town. Increase 771(Increase 976 men, decrease 205 women)Deptford. Increase 700 (614 men, 86 women)Poplar. Increase 833(667 men, 166 women)Camberwell. Increase 1,017 (679 men, 338 women)Clapham Junction. Increase 1,013 (938 men, 75 women)Croydon. Increase 605 (428 men, 177 women)Lewisham. Increase 501 (331 men, 170 women)Tottenham. Increase 566 (501 men. 65 women)Ed ware Road.-Increase 1,604 (1,223 men, 381 women)Hollo way. Increase 982 (832 men, 150 women)King&apos;s Cross. Increase 1,299 (1,018 men, 281 women)Leyton. Increase 803(719 men, 84 women)Hackney. Increase 1,089 (820 men, 269 women) dressing, tailoring and printing trades.Shoreditch. Increase 1,098 (702 men, 396 women) due to slackness in the cabinet, furniture and upholstery trade, and to the discharge of temporary workers on railway and seasonal work.due to the cessation of temporary seasonal  employment and  to extended holidavs.-due to slackness in the farSouth-Western Division.Bristol. Increase 546 (200 men, 346 women) due to the cessation of Christmas seasonal work.Kingswood. Decrease 560  (336 men, 224  women) due  to  improvement in employment in the boot and shoe industry.Southampton. Increase 871 (775 men. 96 women) due to slackness of trade and to discharges of merchant seamen.Midlands Division.Birmingham. Increase 827 (363 men, 464 women) due mainly to the cessation of temporary work for the Christmas trade.Leicester. Increase 696 (343 men, 353 women) due to slackness in the textile and hosiery industries.
Longton.-Decrease 963 (409 men, 554 women) due to the resumption of work in the pottery industry after extended holidays.Walsall. Increase 929 (825 men, 104 women) due mainly to depression in the iron and steel industry.Wednesbury. Decrease 588 (decrease 669 men, increase 81 women) due in the case of men to resumption of work in the iron and steel trades after extended holidays.Heanor. Decrease 525 (decrease 627 men, increase 102 women) due in the case of men to an improvement in the coal-mining industry, and in the case of women to slackness in the hosiery trade.North-Eastern Division.due to under-employment in the woollen and worsted industry. In the case of Huddersfield, the increase among men was also due to slackness in the engineering industry.Bradford.-Increase 2,500(1,377 men, 1,123 women)Halifax. Increase 915(236 men, 679 women)Huddersfield.-Increase 1,482 (722 men, 760 women)Hull. Increase 1,091 (831 men, 260 women) due in the case of men to slackness of work on the docks and in the case of women to slackness in the needlework trades.North Shields. Decrease 396 (decrease 504 men, increase 108 women) due in the case of men to better employment in the ship-repairing industry.Sheffield. Increase 654 (102 men, 552 women) due to slackness in the iron and steel trades (men) and among silver and cutlery workers and tailoresses; (women).South Bank. Decrease 967 (decrease 990 men, increase 23 women) due in the case of men to the resumption of work in the iron and steel trades after extended holidays and to the restarting of an additional blast furnace in this area.North-Western Division.Barrow. Decrease 562 -(Decrease 692 men, increase 130 women)    due m the case of men to increasedl employment m the iron and Workington.-Decrease 704 steel smelting industry.(decrease 721 men, increase 17 women)        /Birkenhead. Decrease 643 (decrease 754 men, increase 111 women) due in the case of men to better employment on ship-repair work.Burnley. Decrease 898 (45 men, 853 women)Chadderton. Decrease 892(762 men, 130 women) I due to improvement in the cottonGlossop.-Decrease 611 I    industry.(208 men, 403 women)Rochdale. Decrease 642(Increase 126 men, decrease 768 women)Famworth. Increase 786 (137 men, 649 women) due to under-employment in coal-mining and cotton industries.Liverpool__Increase 1,091 (465 men, 626 women) due to cessation of temporaryemployment in seasonal work.Wigan. Decrease 686 (595 men, 91 women) due to better employment in the coal-mining industry.Liverpool Docks. Increase 667 (men) due to fluctuations in casual employment at the docks.[12714]. B 2
Scotland Division.Dunfermline. Increase 2,066 (1,945 men, 121 women) due mainly to reduced employment in the coal-mining industry.Edinburgh. Increase 1,367 (996 men, 371 women) due in the case of men to less employment in miscellaneous trades and in the case of women to cessation of seasonal work.Leith.-Increase 694(441 men, 253 women)Dundee. Increase 598(Increase 652 men, decrease 54 women)Partick. Increase 618 (534 men, 84 women)Bridgeton. Increase 709 (435 men, 274 women)due in the case of men to reduced emplo^ment among shipyard and metal workers, dockers and seamen, and in the case of women to the cessation of seasonal work.Wales Division.due   to   stoppage collieries iof   work   at   localdue to resumption of work at local collieries.Abertillery. Increase 688 (men)Mountain Ash. Increase 1,395 (men)Crumlin. Decrease 654 (men)Dowlais. Decrease 799 (men)Cymmer. Decrease 621 (men)Blaenavon. Increase 608 (men) due to depression in the iron and steel trades.Neath. Increase 1,142 (men) due to stoppages and intermittent work in the tin-plate trade.Llanelly. Increase 766 (men)due to depression in the tin-plate and iron and steel trades.Morriston. Increase 907 (men)Swansea. Increase 1,793 (men)Port Talbot. Decrease 748 (men)- due to a general improvement in all the chief local industries.
CM33 1II. POSITION  IN  CHIEF  INDUSTRIES. COAL MINING.There is little change to report in this industry, and under-employment was still fairly general. Further depression was reported in the Northumberland and Durham coal-fields, and shipments of coal and coke from the Tyne were considerably below those for the corresponding period in 1923. In the South Yorkshire coal-field the collieries continued to work full time. In the North-Western Counties there was a slight improvement in employment, but short-time working was still the general rule. The position fluctuated in different districts, e.g., employment was good at Tyldesley, but bad at Farnworth. Employment was slack in the South Staffordshire area, and at Cradley Heath 600 miners were still suspended, while the position at Walsall and West Bromwich was only fair. In the North Staffordshire area the position was rather better, employment being good at Stoke and Newcastle-under-Lyme, while a number of men resumed work at Longton. In the Nottinghamshire area 1,000 miners were placed on short time at Basford, but improvement was shown at Ilkeston, Chesterfield and Derby, and employment was good at Mansfield and Nottingham. In the Kent coal-field steady progress was made towards recovery after trade disputes, breakdowns and floods. Employment was not good in the Forest of Dean, and the closing of a colliery near Lydney is in contemplation. In Scotland there was improvement in Ayrshire and Lanarkshire, but increased unemployment is anticipated in the Fifeshire coal-fields owing to further decline in the export trade. In South Wales the general position was unchanged. Intermittent unemployment and stoppages continued, but there was a slight tendency towards improvement and employment appeared to be becoming steadier.IRON AND STEEL.Employment was still bad in this industry, but there are signs that the industry is slowly recovering from the severe depression which has continued for the past few months. In the North-Eastern Counties a very slight improvement was shown. Employment remained good on the production and manufacture of steel for railway equipment. The demand for; Cleveland pig-iron showed a slight increase, and two blast furnaces at Middlesbrough and one at South Bank were restarted. There was no change in conditions in the Sheffield area, enquiries for steel billets being very quiet. The severe depression in the Scunthorpe area still continued. The dispute at the Sheffield Forge and Rolling Mills was settled during the period under review, and 600 employees resumed work. In the Midlands further improvement was shown at Newcastle-under-Lyme, but the position was only fair at Stoke and Burslem. Employment was fairly good at Ilkeston and Basford, all furnaces being in blast. In the South Staffordshire area the position was still depressed at Bilston, Dudley, Oldbury and Walsall. There was an improvement at Brierley Hill and West Bromwich, but the position was only fair at Cradley Heath. In Scotland, employ-ment was generally slack. Several blast furnaces were blown out at Wishaw, 200 men being affected. At Coatbridge only eight of thirty-five furnaces were still in blast. At Motherwell unemplojonent decreased with the reopening of works. Trade in light castings showed a steady improvement at Falkirk, and at Uddingston steel works were busy. The position of the industry in South Wales is adversely affected by the depression in the tin-plate trade, and employment was bad on the whole. There was, however, an improvement in the position at Neath and Ebbw Vale, and there were signs of improvement at Port Talbot. In North Wales employment continued good at Wrexham, and the position improved at Flint.TIN-PLATE TRADE.No marked change took place in this industry. At Llanelly all works were slack or idle, and much short-time working continued at Swansea, Morriston and Neath. In the Rhondda Valley an improvement was shown, while at Risca a distinct improvement took place.SHIPBUILDING AND SHIP-REPAIRING.Employment in this industry remained bad, and little general change was shown. On the North-East coast a slight improvement in repair work was shown at North and South Shields, but the position in the constructional branch of the industry remained bad, except at Selby, where contracts will keep 350 employees at work until
aAugust. On the Tyne, completion of contracts and lack of fresh orders were responsible for berths remaining unoccupied, and only eighteen of fifty-three berths on the Wear were occupied by ships in course of construction. At Hull, repair work gave continued employment, but unemployment was on the increase on the Tees. On the Mersey, employment in repair work was slightly better than last month, and in the Barrow area prospects are more satisfactory, although there was still&apos;con-siderable unemployment. A 6,00D-ton vessel has just been launched, and one is nearly ready for launching; the work of completion on these two vessels should give considerable employment to ships&apos; joiners, for whom there was already a strong demand. In the South-Eastern Counties repair work was generally quiet, but at Bermondsey and North Woolwich employment was fairly good. A small ship-repairing yard at Wivehhoe which has been closed for some considerable time is being reopened, and will give employment to a number of unemployed men in this area&quot; In Scotland launches took place at White-inch, Port Glasgow, Clydebank, Govan and Dundee. The volume of fresh orders has, however, diminished, and replacement work generally is of less weight. At Aberdeen an order for two hopper barges and a steam tug will give employment to a number of unemployed shipyard workers, calculated to last from nine to ten months, while at Troon an order for two vessels will afford much relief. In Wales a decided improvement was shown in repair work, except at Newport, and in North Wales the improvement at Holyhead was maintained.ENGINEERING.Motor, Cycle and Aircraft Engineering.- Continued activity was shown in this industry and the improvement was maintained. Full time was still worked in most districts in the Midlands. Work at Birmingham continued at full pressure in all sections, and trade was good at Coventry. In the South-Western Counties engagements of more workpeople took place at Basingstoke and Oxford, while firms in the North-Eastern Counties manufacturing motor-car parts were fully employed. In the South-Eastern Counties activity continued, and improvement was reported from Luton.General Engineering. There was on the whole a slight improvement in this industry during the month. In the North-Eastern Counties manufacturers of engineers&apos; small tools and parts required in the building industry remained busy, but the textile section of the industry at Huddersfield and Todmorden resorted to short-time working. Employment in Marine Engineering remained slack. Some improvement in employment took place at Elswick and Scotswood-on-Tyne. Manufacturers of railway wagons remained busy. In the North-Western Counties very little improvement was shown except in the textile engineering section, and even in this section there was some short-time working, in some cases only three days per week being worked. In the Midlands unemployment was still heavy. The demand for highly skilled workers at Birmingham still continued, and trade was good at Coventry, while a slight improvement was shown at Cradley Heath and Dudley. A falling off in employment occurred at Wolverhampton, West Bromwich, Kettering and Rugby, but the position at Leicester, Coalville, Chesterfield, Sutton-in-Ashfield, and Oakengates was reported as good. There was plenty of work in railway-wagon building, and employment was good in this section. In the South-Eastern Counties, steady progress was maintained in London, particularly in the Borough and Deptford areas. In the provinces, the position was fairly good at Bedford and satisfactory at Erith, Chelmsford and Luton. At Enfield discharges were reported due to slackness in the electrical branch. In the South-Western Counties no change took place in the Bristol area, but there was a further improve-ment in the Reading district. Railway work at Swindon still remained busy, and many men were engaged. In Scotland employment in this industry was more or less quiet, small work being fairly good, but heavy work less in demand. At Bridgeton two important contracts for bridge work have been secured. Railway orders have been placed at Motherwell and Glasgow. In Wales the position still fluctuated owing to the uncertain position in the coal, tin-plate and iron and steel trades. Employment was fair at Cardiff, Port Talbot and Swansea, but the position at Pembroke Dock and Newport remained bad. Iron foundries at Ebbvs Vale were working full time. In mid-Wales trade was generally quiet and there was much short-time working. In North Wales some slight improvement took place at Holyhead, but the position was bad in Flintshire, where there are now practically no works open.
TEXTILES.Cotton. Conditions in this industry remained steady, and the improvement was maintained. An appreciable reduction in the unemployment registers occurred after the Christmas holiday season, but, on account of a falling off in the number of cloth orders booked and in the demand for yarn, the Master Cotton Spinners Federation decided to reduce the number of working hours from 39^ to 35 per week in the American cotton section from the 16th February, with a view to stabilising the position. There was still an extensive demand for weavers. In Scotland an improvement was reported from Paisley and the mills at Bridgeton were busy.Woollens and Worsteds. A further depression is reported in this industry, which is stated to be largely due to high price of wool. At Bradford the unemployment registers increased by 2,500. In the South-Western Counties, at Witney two blanket mills were working short time, but at Wellington (Somerset) improvement was reported. Short-time working was prevalent in most districts in Scotland, except at Ayr, where trade was good. The position in Wales was very bad and in South Cardiganshire and Montgomeryshire there was much unemploy-ment.   The largest flannel factory at Llanidloes was working short time.Hosiery. Trade in this industry was very quiet, and short time was prevalent in many districts. The heavy goods branch has been particularly affected by the mild weather. At Nottingham trade was good, but at Leicester was rather quiet. In Scotland, better conditions are reported from Alexandria and Kilmarnock. but employment was slack at Galashiels, Hamilton and Wishaw.Lace. No improvement was shown in this industry, and heavy unemployment still existed. At Basford trade was bad in the Levers Section and at Beeston there was a falling off. The position at Long Eaton became worse and no improvement was shown at Nottingham.   Short-time working was still in operation at Derby.Silk. There is little change to report, and trade generally was rather quiet. Short-time working prevailed at Nottingham and Coventry and trade was still bad at Leek, but a further improvement was shown at Cheadle. The artificial silk trade was better at Derby, while at Flint employment was goodJute. Considerable activity was shown in this industry, and orders were being booked ahead for two or three months. There was a demand for experienced weavers.  Trade was very active at Dundee and good in other places.Carpets. Employment continued satisfactory at Kidderminster. Unsystematic short time was confined to the manufacture of the cheaper class of fabric.BUILDING, BRICK AND TILE MANUFACTURE.Employment in this industry remained steady, but the bad weather somewhat hampered building operations in certain districts. The demand for bricklayers continued, but less difficulty was being experienced in meeting the demand for carpenters, joiners and masons. The usual seasonal unemployment amongst painters continued, but in Scotland an attempt was made by certain employers and Local Authorities to undertake decorating and painting work in order to give employment during the winter to men in this branch of the industry. Employment in the brick and tile industry was good at most centres. A shortage of orders in the fire-brick industry was&apos; experienced at Brierley Hill, but otherwise trade in this branch remained good.CLOTHING.Seasonal slackness still continued, but there were indications of slight improve-ment in the needlework trades, due to the approach of Spring. In the West End of London wholesale dressmaking and ladies&apos; tailoring showed signs of commencing activity. In the East End of London there was a slight improvement in ladies&apos; tailoring and trade in men&apos;s tailoring was still busy. In the North-Eastern Counties there was still much unemployment and under-employment among dressmakers, tailoresses and milliners, and at Huddersfield an increase of 100 tailoresses on the Register was reported. Trade was still slack in corset and glove manufacture, but the shirt trade was still busy, although collar work was quiet.
BOOT AND SHOE.Little change was shown in this industry. At Leicester the improvement was maintained, but at Kettering unemployment increased among men, although there were no skilled women out of employment. Short-time working took place at Wellingborough, Stafford and Mansfield. In the South-Eastern Counties employment was fairly good and there was a slight improvement, although trade was quiet at Hackney, and there was a falling off at Norwich. The heavy boot trade at Chesham was slack. There was no change in the Bristol area apart from a slight improvement at Kingswood.POTTERY.The position in this industry became slightly better, though unemployment is still heavy. Short-time working was still prevalent at Hanley, although some fimis resumed full-time working. At Longton the position steadily improved, but at Burslem there was a further decline, nearly 3,000 women being unemployed, which is the highest figure since 1921. At Stoke, trade was fairly good, and there was a brisk demand for high-class enamelled china. Little unemployment prevailed at Worcester and the position was fairly satisfactory. At Derby there was an increase in short-time working. In the Bristol area short-time working was re-introduced, and the immediate prospects are not favourable.DOCKS.Employment among dock workers continued slack on the whole. At ports on the&apos;North-East Coast there was a falling off in timber imports and a slump of grain imports at Hull, both of which caused further increase of unemployment. At Salford Docks employment was good, while docks at Gloucester and Sharpness were fairly busy. In the South-Eastern Counties work was not so good. In Scotland employment was slack owing to the slump in coal exports, while in Wales, the position still continued unsatisfactory, and slackness was experienced owing to the conclusion of the pit-wood season. At Swa,nsea docks there was a slight improve-ment, but the position at other South Wales docks showed a decline.
	Number&apos;of Men employed at 		Works assisted by 				Jan.31,1925. -	Dec. 27,1924.	Jaii. 25,1924.1. Ministry of Transport 			Road and Bridge Schemes	17,007*	17,389*	12,027*2. Unemployment Gnmts Committee	40,843*	38,605*	34,836*3. Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries 			(a.) Land Drainage Schemes	3,347^	2,288	3,727(b.) Water Supply Schemes	.  117	17	1474. Board of Agriculture for Scotland 			Land   Drainage   and   Improvement			Schemes	343	112	256   .5. Forestry Commission -			Grants   to   Corporate  Bodies and			private individuals	806f	691	1,1416. Office of Woods, fee-			Wash Reclamation Works, Wingland	35	26	7. Ministry of Transport 			Iialwill-Torrington Light Railway ..	357	364	4808. Office of Works-			Unemployment Relief Programme ..	3,973	3,189	1,8849. Guarantees under Trade Facilities Acts	42,571J	40,5801	34,549tTotal    ..	109,399	103,261	89,047* These figures represent the number of men actually employed on the site on the date given, and exclude any additional men not at work on that date for whom employment is also provided by means of alternate week working or other short time system. The figures take no account of the employment provided indirectly. e.g., in the preparation and transport of materials, &amp;c.t In addition to the figures quoted, the average number of men employed during January 1925 on the Commission^ operations (including Crown woods) was 2,257 as compared with 1912 during January 1924-J These figures indicate men employed on the work itself. They include part only of the men employed on the manufacture of the materials used. They take no account of the labour involved in winning,, transporting. &amp;c, raw materials.[12714] cIII. WORK INSTITUTED FOR RELIEF OF UNEMPLOYMENT.Numbers Employed.[See note on page 1 of November 1924 Report (CP. 541 (24))]The table which follows has been prepared to show, so far as information is available, the number of men employed on works instituted, with financial assistance from the Exchequer or the Road Fund, for the relief of unemployment.Scope of Table. The schemes included are those undertaken by Local and other Authorities and Public Companies with a financial contribution from the State with the object of relieving Unemployment; certain schemes-put in hand by Government Departments for the same purpose; and works in respect of which guarantees have been given under the Trade F facilities Acts as capital undertakings calculated to promote employment in this country. Schemes to which State financial assistance is given, but which are not undertaken primarily for the relief of unemployment (e.g., Housing Schemes), and works put in hand by Local Authorities without State assistance are not included. Certain other schemes involving Government assistance are also-excluded in view of the impracticability of ascertaining the exact number of men who are directly provided with employment thereby; these include the Export Credits Scheme and contracts for equipment, clothing, &amp;c, accelerated by Government Contracting Departments.Method of Compilation. The figures for the Road and Bridge Schemes assisted by the Ministry of Transport and for schemes assisted by the Unemployment Grants Committee are (with the exception of certain road schemes t in respect of which returns are received direct by the Ministry of Transport) obtained from returns received at Employment Exchanges from Local and other Authorities and Public Companies. Those relating to schemes assisted under the Trade Facilities Acts are compiled by the Trade Facilities Act Advisory Committee from returns received from Companies to whom guarantees under the Acts have been given. In the case of the remaining works the figures are compiled or estimated by the Departments mentioned.It should be noted that in view of recent modifications in the scope of the table the figures given cannot properly be compared with those previously announced in Parliament in similar connections. The figures given for January 1924, which have been prepared (so far as information is available) on the same basis as that now in use, provide an approximately accurate comparison.
IY. OVERSEAS SETTLEMENT. , (Colonial Office.)Under the Empire Settlement Act, 1922, assisted passage schemes for Australia, New Zealand, Canada and Ontario have been agreed with the Dominion Authorities eoncerned. In addition, schemes for the settlement of immigrants on the land have &quot;been agreed with .the Governments of New South Wales, Victoria and Western Australia. A number of organisations; having as their object the provision of facilities for the settlement of immigrants in certain of the Dominions, have also been assisted. An extension of this assistance to other organisations is under consideration.The number of persons approved for assistance and the number of departures during the month of December (with the corresponding figures for December of last year) and for the nine months ended the 31st December, 1924 and 1923 respectively, are set out in the following Table :  Monthly Progress Return relating to Schemes approved under &quot; The empire settlement Act, 1922.&quot;Approval and Departure Figures.	Number of Approvals.				Number of Departures.			Dominion.	Month of December.		Nine months ended December 31.		Month of December.		Nine months ended December 31.		1924.	1923.	1924.	1923.	1924.	1923.	1924.	1923.(1.) Australia  (a.) Assisted passage scheme (b.) Land Settlement Schemes  (i.) New South Wales   ] Included f (ii.) Victoria    ..            ^ under (a) J. (iii.) Western Australia   J    above    [	1,768 53 28 5	1,535 22 261	17,105 291 351 129	20,689 421 2,977	1,804 69 38	2,068 66 437	16,845 268 350 592	19,327 463 2,129Total Australia under Government schemes	1,768	1,535	17,105	20,689	1,804	2,068	16,845	19,327&quot;(2.) Canada  (a.) Dominion assisted passage schemes-(i.) Nominated passages . . (ii.) Female household workers (iii.) Children    .. (iv.) 3,000 Families scheme (6.) Ontario assisted passage scheme (c.) Alberta training scheme	3 28 8 547 62	33 42 29	3,685 *1,487 1,317 547 &apos; 62	480 1,988 . 928 993	3 22 8 62	39 53 &apos;23	8,607 1,479 1,329 62	479 1,911 1,114 1,149Total Canada under Government schemes ..	648	104	7,098	4,389	95	115	6,477	4,653^3.) New Zealand assisted passage scheme	840	534	*7,055	5,482	196	819	6,289	5,072-(4.) Minor schemes -(a.) Society for the Oversea Settlement of British Women (b.) British Dominions Emigration Society (Canada)          .. (c.) Salvation Army (excluding those coming under agreements with Canada)  (i.) Women (Canada) (ii.) Hoys (Australia and Canada). . (iii.) Widows with families (Canada) (iv.) Families (Canada) .. (d.) Craigielinn Farm (Australia and Canada) (e.) Dr. Barnado&apos;s Homes (A australia) (f.) British Red Cross Society (Ca.nada) .. (g.) Fellowship of the Maple Leaf (Canada)	25 122 49	1	. *418 414 151 136 162 &apos; 35 13	137 441 278 251 161	7 122 &apos; 31	8	366 414 151 136 119 35 13	140 438 &apos;278 251 87Total minor schemes   ..          ..          .,	196	1	1,329	1,268	160	8	1,234	1,394Totals	3,452	2,174	32,587	31,828	2,255	3,010	30,845	30,246* These figures have been reduced on account of cancellations during December.In addition, since the Armistice, free passages have been granted to over 88,000 persons under the Government Free Passage - Scheme for the settlement overseas of ex-Service Men and their Dependents. The Scheme, however, closed to new applications in December 1922.
These Statistical Tables have been compiled with a view to showing the extent of the effort from public sources since the Armistice to meet the problems of Post-War Resettlement and Unemployment, and to indicate the measure of assistance provided by the Exchequer. With regard to the latter, the methods of financial co-operation are so diverse that it is impracticable to give an aggregated figure of Exchequer Assistance. For this reason, the accompanying Summary is only indicative of the extent to which the Exchequer is involved, and must be regarded as supplementary to, and not in substitution of, the detailed. information given in the Tables themselves.Summary.(A.)Schemes.	Table.	Total Approximate Value of Schemes Assisted.	Approximate Exchequer Contribution from Armistice to March 81, 1925 (excluding Loans).Training, &amp;c.            ..           . .          .&quot;. Unemployment Insurance        . . Unemployment Grants Committee Ministry of Transport Programmes Resettlement         ..          . .      ... Acceleration of Road Schemes Miscellaneous Land Settlement Women&apos;s Training, &amp;c.	1 2 3 3 &quot;s 4 5	  million. 103 198 82 20 50 H 20J-!1	  million. 103 of &quot;n 12^ (including Road Puud) H 4 * ,Total    ..		476*	189*[12714]			DY. STATISTICS RELATING TO FINANCIAL PROVISION FOR RELIEF OF UNEMPLOYMENT (including Post-War Resettlement of ex-Members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces), from the Armistice.Schemes of which the Whole Cost is Borne by the Exchequer  Table 1. Out-of-Work Donation, Training Schemes, &amp;c.Schemes of which Part of the Cost is Borne by the Exchequer  Table 2. Unemployment Insurance.Table 3. Unemployment   Grants  Committee,  Ministry  of transport schemes, &amp;c. Table 4.-Land Settlement.Table 5.  Schemes for Training Women and Juveniles.Schemes involving Exchequer Guarantees Table 6. Trade Facilities Guaranteed Schemes.Other Schemes Table 7. Expenditure by Poor Law Authorities, A (England and Wales), B (Scotland).
Scheme.	Table.	Grants.	&apos; Guarantees.		  million.	  million.Training, &amp;c, Schemes       ....	1	1	Unemployment Grants Committee Loan			Schemes	3	18 	Ministry of Transport Schemes	3	20	Land Settlempnt	4	10	Trade Facilities Guaranteed Schemes	6		59Total   ..		49J-	59		108 	(C.) Further Exchequer Liabilities in respect of Schemes which the Government have offered to assist if undertaken, or if the necessity arises.Scheme.	Table.	Grants.	Guarantees.Unemployment Insurance Unemployment Grants Committee Loan Schemes Trade Facilities Guaranteed Schemes Total	2 3 6	  million. 3	  million. 24 32		3	56		59	(B.) Additional Future Exchequer Liabilities under Schemes already Approved
Schemes of Post-War Resettlement, mainly of ex-Service Men.Scheme. (The Appropriate Vote of the Estimates is given in Brackets.)	Approximate Net Expendi-ture from Armistice to March 31, 1924.	Provision in 1924/25 Estimates.!;	Estimated Total Expenditure to March 81, 1925 (Approximate Set &apos;  Expenditure to end of Month stated is given in Brackets).(1)   - *   ,	(2)	(3)	(4).1. Out-of-work donation..          .. (His Majesty&apos;s Forces and Merchant Seamen (see No. 4 below as to civilians).)	  40,722,846	 	  40,722,846 (40,722,846 Jan.)2. Grants for resettlement in civil life (Class VII, Vote 3.)	3,794,132	165,000	3,959,132 (3,901,000 Jan.)-3. Training of demobilised officers and men of His Majesty&apos;s Forces, also ex-Service nurses and war widows  (a.) Ministry of Labour    ..      ,   ..           .. (Class VII, Vote 3.)     ,   ,	23,219,650	1,369,911	24,589,561 (24,526,000 Jan.)(i.) Ministry of Pensions (Class VI, Vote 4.)	1,192,000	68,000	1,260,000 (l,266,500\Jan.)(c.) Board of Education (England and Wales).. (Class IV, Vote 1.)	7,675,512	64,500	7.740,012 (7,732,999 Jan.)(d.) Scottish Education Deoartment (Glass IV, Vote 11.)	1,303,310	20,640	1,323,950 (L,320,727 Jan.)(e.) Ministry  of   Agriculture  and   Fisheries (England and Wales) (Class 11, Vote 14.)	1,498,868	4,850	1,503,718 (1,501,847 Jan.)(/.) Board of Agriculture (Scotland) (Class II, Vote 36.)	53,899	150	54,049 (53,996 Jan.)Total for training	34,943,239	1,528,051	36,471,290 (36,402,069 Jan.)Totals (1 to 3 inclusive)	79,460,217	1,693,051	81,153.268 (81,025,915 Jan.)4. Out-of-work donation : civilian men and women ..	21,725,395		21,725,395 (21,725,395 Jan.)Totals (1 to 4 inclusive)	101,185,612	1,693,051	102,878,663 (102,751,SlOJan.)Note, (i.) The costs of administration and &quot;allied Services&quot; are not included in this table.(ii ) The cost of the Overseas settlement free passage scheme for ex-Service men and women and their dependants (now rapidly approaching termination), which up to 31st March, 1924, had amounted to approximately  2,400,000, is not included in this table.
Statement of Income and Expenditure from Armistice to January 30, 1925.Expenditure                    Benefit paid        .....        ....         .... 191,051,000Appropriation for Administration   .... 17,639,000Section 9 Unemployment InsuranceAct (No. 2), 1924         ....          .... 676,000Miscellaneous Refunds, &amp;c.....          ....          .... 2,362,000-   211,728,000Income Contributions Employers .... .... ....     72,112,000Employed .... .... ....     65,483,000Exchequer   ;       .... .... .....47,481,000Exchequer (for ex-Service Men)      ....      3,038,000--   188,114,000Interest (Net).... .... .... .... 819,000Balance of Old Fund at Armistice (excluding Interest accrued) * Employers .... .... ....      5,825,000Employed-.............. ....      5,825,000Exchequer .... .... ....      3,884,000---    15,534,000Loans from Treasury (Net).... .... .... 6,080,000Miscellaneous Deposits in respect of future  Contribu-tions, &amp;c................. 1,181,000211,728,000* Note.--The old Fund at November 8th, 1920, had reached a total of  22,210,000. Estimate of Benefit payable from Armistice to March 31, 1925,  198,000,000.Unemployment Insurance. (Estimates, Class VII, Vote 3.)The National Insurance Act of 1911 provided Insurance against unemployment in certain selected industries. It was followed by the Act of 1916, which increased the numbers of persons insured, and, in 1920, by an Act of general scope which applied compulsory Insurance against unemployment to 12,000,000 persons. Subsequent amending Acts modified the conditions of receipt of benefit, increased contributions, provided benefit in respect of dependants, and authorised the Treasury to make advances out of the Consolidated Fund up to a limit of  30,000,000.By the -Unemployment Insurance (No. 2) Act, 1924 the rates of benefit were raised (from 155.) to 18s. a week for men, and (from 12s.) to 15s. a week for women, with 2s. (instead of Is.) a week for each young dependent child. Until the 30th June, 1926, benefit in respect of contributions may be paid for 26 weeks in a benefit year, while benefit, irrespective of contributions, may be paid&quot; during unemployment subject to the satisfaction of special conditions. The Act also amends the disqualification for benefit in the case of persons affected by trade disputes, and it abolishes the right to a, refund of contributions at the age of 60, subject to the payment of compensation for the loss-of refund rights in certain cases.
Totals to January 31, 1925.	No. of Schemes.		No. of Local	Estimated	i II Grant&apos; allocated. (6) .	Grants paid. (7)Financial Years. (1)	Submitted. (2)	Approved. (3)	Authorities whose Schemes were approved. (4)	cost of Schemes approved. (5)		1920/21 1921/22 1922/23 1923/24 1924/25	. 964 2,045 992 1,086 916	640 1,168 688 795 655	219 235 244 301 266	  4,666,484 5,567,837 1,646,835 2,259,487 1,595,882	  1,206,925 1,601,307 459,800 688,187 642,613	  26,636 1,816,715 486,593 544,671 444,168 (to Dec. 31, 1924)* For various reasons it is found that the total amount of grant allocated exceeds the total amount which the Committee will be called upon to pay; the latter will not in the four years, 1921/22, 1922/23, 1923/24 and 1924/25, exceed  3,650,000.(B.) Unemployment Grants Committee : Grants in respect of Interest or Interest and Sinking Fund Charges. (Estimates, Class VII, Vote 1, and Class II,. Vote 35.)Totals to January 31, 1925.Financial Years. (1)	No. of Schemes.		No. of Local Authorities whose Schemes were approved. (4)	Estimated cost of Schemes.		Amount of loan approved for Grant.* (7)	Submitted. (&apos;2)	Approved. (3)		Submitted. (5)	Approved. (6)	1920/21 1921/22 1922/23 1923/24 1924/25	Nil 2,540 2,601 2,277 -   1,910	Nil 1,650 1,773 1,648 1,256	Nil 520 489 462 461	*    Nil 24,651,083 17,839,410 24,61)8,480 23.289,592	  Nil 17,609,747 11,868,414 19,404,680 14,859,462	  Nil 16,579,107 11,059,080-18,416,151* 13,246,781*Notes. (1.) Provisional approval has also been given to nine schemes estimated to cost  1,090,287.* (2.) In addition, schemes promoted by Public Utility Companies have been approved to the extent of  1,705,774 for 19.23/24 and  855,412 for 1924/25.Estimated Exchequer Liability in respect of Loans Approved.Payments by Exchequer towards interest, &amp;c, charges on Loans.		Estimated Exchequer liability 1924/25 onwards (Capital-ised) (3)	* Approximate annual charges ou Exchequer in respect, of 								1924/25 (4)	1925/26 to 1932/33 -   (5)	1933/34 to 1937/38 (6)	1938/39    1939/40 i (7)          (8)		1940/41 (9) .From Jan. lj 1925, to Jan. 31, 1925. &apos;    (1)	Armistice to Jan. 31, 1925.							  168,150	  i,28i,ayo	  19,800,000	  1,500,000	  2,260,000	&amp; 1,300,000	  830,000	  530,000	  165,000* JJdtb. Tlie years given are financial years.[12714] . E&quot;&apos;;-&quot;&apos;&apos;!!MMM- mm.......MMMMIIIIIIIIlMIHIMIIimm.............UOJVJJU.....JI&apos;W1U U ...&apos;ti^.^...Ji,t^!T^V^^^CT--n^-^^JT!^7P^.,... ..  ....... M),.......^   ...................... ,1 gTable 3.(A.) Unemployment Grants Committee : Grants made in respect of the Wages Costs.    (Estimates, Unclassified Services, Vote 1.)
(U.) Ministry of Transport Schemes.Road and Bridge Programme, 1919-20.To assist in the provision of employment for demobilised members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces until such time as they could be re-absorbed into industry, the Government after the Armistice inaugurated a special fund for the purpose of making grants on certain conditions to Highway Authorities for road work. The total of such grants has amounted to approximately  9,328,000 for Great Britain and it is estimated that the works carried out by Local Authorities in order to earn a grant aggregated in cost to approximately  20,000,000.Unemployment Works assisted out of the Road Fund.1920-23 Programmes.The first &quot; Unemployment Programme &quot; proper was initiated by the Ministry of Transport in the Winter of 1920/21, and the following statement shows the total estimated expenditure by the contributing parties to date and a forecast of expend! -ture during subsequent years, against the three programmes instituted prior to October 1923.Payments during Year.	Road Fund.	Exchequer.	Unemployment Grants Committee.	Local Authorities. (Estimated.)	Total.(1)	(2)		(4)	(5)	(6)1920/21 1921/22 1922/23 1928/24 1924/25* 1925/26 1926/27 1927/28	  395,200 1,305,800 2,042,268 2,887,630 2,87.1,000 2,370,951 680,000 138,069	  118,600 887,890 539,015 89,500	-  11,400 141,600 22,000 19,868 65,132	  502,400 1,492,600 1,871.700 2,222,349 1,841,968 1,859,841 680,000 138,069	  1,027,600 3,327,890 4,474,983 5,219,347 4,778,100 4,230,792 1.360,000 276,138Totals	12,690,918	1,135,005	260,000	10,608,927.	24,694,850		1,395,005				14,085,923				, * Notes. (1.) The estimated payments for the first nine  months of 1924/25 are :   Road Fund,  2,070,000; Unemployment Grants Committee,  36,000; Local Authorities,  1,288.000. (2.) Up to the end of December, of the total Government contribution provided, amounting to  14,085,923-&apos;(a.) Net grants formally made, less balances of grants cancelled, amount to 13,442,974 and (b.) Grants promised but not formally made to  505,289. (c.) Leaving a balance which has been partly hypothecated of  137,660.
October 1923 Programme.An additional programme was authorised by the Government in October 1923. The following statement shows the estimated expenditure by the contributing parties during 1923 /24, and a forecast of expenditure during subsequent years.Payments during Years.	Road Fund.	Exchequer.	Local Authorities.	Total.			(Estimated.)	(1)	(2)	(3)	(4)	(5)	 	 	 	&apos;  1923/24        .. 1924/25*	21,499		10,044	31,543	1,350,000		665,000	1  2,015,0001925/26        .....	2,200,000		1,030,000	3,230,0001926/27	1,950,000		880,000	2,830,0001927/28	1,350,000	50,000	600,000	2,000,0001928/29	929,868		419,956	1,349.8241929/30	170,557		67,635	238,192Totals	7,971,924 i	50,000	3,672,635	11,694,559	8,021,924			Motes. (1.) The estimated payments for the first  nine months of 1924/25 are:   Road Fund,  863,000 ; Local Authorities,  440,000. (2.) Up to the end of December,- of  the total Government  contribution amounting to  8,021,924-(a.) Net  grants formally made, less balances of grants cancelled, amount to  5,579,634.(J.) Grants promised but not formally made to  2,106,413.(c.) Leaving a balance which, has been partly hypothecated of  335,877.February 1924 Programme.A further additional programme estimated to cost  13,500,000 was authorised by the late Government, towards which the Road Fund will contribute a maximum of  10,400,000. This programme includes the construction of the Liverpool-Oldham (formerly Manchester) road.The following Statement shows the Total Estimated Expenditure by the Contributing Parties during 1924/25 and a Forecast of Expenditure during Subsequent Years.Payments during Year.	Road Fund.	Local Authorities. (Estimated.)	Total.1924/25..          ..       ... 1925/26.. 1926/27,, 1927/28.. 1928/29..	  169,000 3,906,000 3,550,000 1,850,000 925,000	  85,000 1,065,000 1,000,000 600,000 350,000	  254,000 4,971,000 4,550,000 2,450,000 1,275,000Totals ..       -   . .	10,400,000	3,100,000	13,500,000Note. Of the total Government contribution provided amounting&apos; to  10,400,000 (a.) Net grants formally made amount to  289,697 ; and(b.) Grants promised but not formally made to  8,727,715;(c.) Leaving a balance which has been partly hypothecated of  1,382,588.&apos;1271411     &quot; ^^^^^ ---......^-.............: .-V,,-,-    ^
j:(D.) Miscellaneous.   (Estimates, Unclassified Services; Vote 2.)	Past Expenditure.				Total Expenditure 1921/22 to 1923/24.		Provision for 1924/25.	Schemes.	Exchequer.		Other Sources.			Other Sources.	Exchequer.	Other Sources.:               yy:.y&apos;:;.&apos;y\	1921/22 and 1922/23.	1923/24.	1921/22 and 1922/23.	1923/24.	Exchequer.			(1)	(2)	(3)	(4)	(5)	(6)	(V)	(8)	(9)(a.) Land Drainage (ft.) Water Supply (c.) Forestry&quot; .. (d.) Light Railways (e.) Scottish Schemes	  402,597 11,617 300,000 70,000 53,242	  156,484 11,311 100.000 65,774 44,513	  97,292 28,596 67,474&apos; 31,208	&apos;   104,579 19,000 72,335 47,076	  559,081 22,928 400,000 135,774 97,755	     -201,871 47,596 139,809 78,284	  j. 300,000 30,000* 25,000 75,000	100,000 20,965 81,500Totals					1,215,538	467,560	430,000	202,465					1,683,098		632,465	Notes. (1.) The figures given in this Table relate to &quot; Financial Years.&quot;* (2.) In addition a Supplementary Grant in Aid to the Forestry Fund of  275,000 has been made for an expansion of Afforestation and for the establishment of Forest Workers&apos; Holdings.
Table 4. Land Settlement.In England and Wales the provision under the Land Settlement (Facilities) Act, 1919, of small holdings and other Land , Settlement Schemes for the benefit primarily of ex-Service men, are carried out (a) through the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries, and (b) through the agency of County Councils and Councils of County Boroughs.Settlement through Local Authorities. These schemes are financed by the Exchequer in three ways : (1) by providing through the Public Works Loan Board the necessary capital; (2) by paying each year up^to the 31st March, 1926, the loss on Councils&apos; small holdings account (e.g., due to charging a fair, as opposed to ah economic, rent) so far as such loss has been reasonably and necessarily incurred; (3) by writing-off the difference between outstanding liabilities and the then value of the undertakings at the 31st March, 1926.In Scotland land settlement is not conducted through the agency of County Councils.Ministry&apos;s Settlements. Since the Armistice a number of properties have been acquired, the capital expenditure thereon and the difference, if any, between the annual cost of maintaining and administering them and the rents received from small holders being borne by the Exchequer. No further properties are being acquired, and it is anticipated that for the future cash receipts will suffice to meet cash outgoings.Land Settlement. .(A.) England and Wales.   (Estimates, Class II, Vote 14.)	Amounts from Armistice to March 31, 1924.	Amounts from April 1, 1924, to end of January 1925.	Totals.(1)		(8)	(4)Advances by Public Works Loan Board Commis-sioners to County Councils, &amp;c. Borrowed locally by Councils (estimated) Payments to Councils for losses . Expenditure on farm settlements by Ministry direct	  13,664,278 900,000 2.250,877 780,215	  446,562 100,000 806,241 (- 9,018)	  14,110,840 1,000,000 3,057,118 771,197Total gross expenditure    ..          ... Less advances repaid by Councils	17,595,370 708,751	1,343,785 191,506	18,939,155 900,257Net expenditure	16,386,619	1,152,279	18,038,898(B.) Scotland,   (Estimates, Class II, Vote 36.)			-	Amount from Armistice to March 31, 1924.	Approximate Amounts from April ], 1924, to end of January 1925.	Total.(i)	(2)	(3)	(4)Net expenditure by Board of  Agriculture  for Scotland   ..	  1,559,751	  158,822	  1,718,573** These figures include : 			 Expenditure on (a) Public Works in Congested Districts .. .. ..   59,621aud (6) Rural Housing     .. .. .. .. .. 104,809
Approximate Net Expenditure from Armistice to March 31, 1924.			Proposed Provision for 1924/25.	Estimated Total Expenditure from Armistice to March 31, 1925. (Approximate Net Expenditure to end of Month stated is given in brackets.) (5)Exchequer. (1)	Other Sources. (2)   -	Total. (8)	Exchequer. (4)		 	 	/     ji	 255,219	206,432	461,651	180,000	661,651				(587,723 Jan.)(b.) Juveniles.After the Armistice, Juvenile Unemployment Centres were opened in certain localities to deal with the problem of unemployed juveniles. After a period of closure centres were again established, and the cost, which was originally shared by the Board of Education and, Local Authorities, was, from the 1st April, 1923, to the 31st March, 1924, partly met out of Relief of Unemployment Vote by grants up to 75 per cent, in respect of approved schemes, the Local Authority providing the remaining 25 per cent. From the 1st April, 1924, the Exchequer Grant will, as an emergency measure, so long as unemployment amongst juveniles remains at its present scale, be raised to 100 per cent, of the approved out-of-pocket expenses of Local Education Authorities.Net Expenditure from Armistice to March 31, 1924.			Provision for 1924/25.	Estimated Total Expenditure from Armistice to March 31, 1925. (51Exchequer. a)	Other Sources.* (2)	Total. (3)	Exchequer. (4)	  123,100	  19,500	  142,600	  110,000	252,600* In addition, a scheme of Juvenile War Scholarships met from sources other fchan Government Grants was administered through the Board of Education, and cost approximately  18,380.Schemes for Training Women and Juveniles. (Estimates, Unclassified Services, Vote 2.)(a.) Women.The following table aggregates: (i) the expenditure incurred, wholly by the Ministry of Labour in connection with the Registered Unemployed Women&apos;s Scheme which operated from 1919 to 1921; (ii) the expenditure, met partly from Exchequer Grants and partly from other sources on schemes for training women in Domestic Service,.&amp;o, under the auspices of the Central Committee for Women&apos;&apos;s Training.
Table 6.Trade Facilities Guaranteed Schemes. (Estimates, Unclassified. Services, Vote 3.)(a.) Export Credits.Under the Export Credits Scheme, which is intended to facilitate the resumption of the ordinary means whereby traders can obtain facilities&apos;!from their bankers to enable them to finance their export trade, the Government guarantee drafts drawp against shipments of goods exported from Great Britain to approved countries abroad.Originally a system of Cash Advances against Bills of Exchange was adopted, but has been discontinued and superseded by a system of &quot; Guarantees.&quot;Period ending February 2, 1925.Advances Scheme (Operative from 1918 to 1922).Advances Sanctioned.	Balance of Advances not Required.	Advances Made.	Repayment of Advances.	Amounts Outstanding.3,164,257	- &quot;   1,412,107	  1,752,150	&apos;     487,273	  1,264,877Guarantee Scheme (became Operative July 1921).Total Sanctions.	Sanctions Lapsed or Cancelled.	Guarantees taken up.		Bills Paid and Guarantees Cancelled.	Amounts not yet taken up, i.e., Amounts Earmarked.	Amounts Outstanding, i.e., Amounts in Use.		New Bills.	Renewals.			  26,087,190	  19,911,941	  5,630,836	  6,885.580	  9,550,105	  544,413	  2,966,311 Amount authorised by Acts of Parliament     .. .. ..       26,000,000Amounts in use or earmarked under both schemes      .. .. 4,775,601Balance available       .. .. .. ..       21,224,399Notes.-(1.) The renewals under the guarantee scheme include a very large proportion which were contemplated at the time the credit was sanctioned. (2.) The bills paid and guarantees cancelled column is again affected by renewals.   Where a renewal is granted the old bill is cancelled and the renewal bill (usually for a reduced amount) is included under the heading of Guarantees taken (renewals).(b.) Guarantees under Trade Facilities Acts, 1921 to 1924. .Under these Acts the Treasury is empowered, on the advice of an Advisory Committee, to guarantee the payment of interest and principal, or either interest or principal, of loans raised in connection with capital undertakings, provided the loans are expended in such a way as to relieve unemployment in Great Britain.Position at January 31, 1925.Exchequer contingent liability authorised by Trade     ,. Facilities Acts, 1921 to 1924, in respect ofcapital    ....         ....         ....          ....         ..... 65,000,000Total amount in respect of which Treasury have stated their willingness to give guarantees upto 9th November, 1923       ....      &apos;   ....         .... 38,205.645Additional guarantees in period 10th November, 1923,  to   31st   January,   1925,   which   theTreasury have stated their willingness to give 15,911,666
2.2Period.(1)Total ApproximateExpenditure in respect of all classes of Poor (includingthe Sick, Aged, Widows, &amp;c.) otherthan Capital. Expenditure out of Loans.(2) _Domiciliary Relief in Money or Kind to persons ordin-arily engaged in some Regular Occupation and their Dependants (included in column 2).Persons Insured under the Unem-ployment Insurance Acts and their Dependants.(3)Persons not so Insured and their Dependants.(4)Approximate Total.(5)	 	 	 	 	Armistice to March 31, 1920	30,567,241	Not	separately ascertained.		1920/21  ..           ..           ,	31,924,954		Do.       do.	500,000	1921/22  ..	42,272,555		Do.       do.	(estimated) 8,000,000	1922/23 (estimated)    ...				(estimated)		41.934,437	9,414.708	949,126	10,363,834	1923/24	38,000,000 &apos;	6,409,265	793,705	7,202,970	1924/25, April (4 weeks)   ..	(estimated)					Not yet ascertained	384,455	57,629	442,084&quot;	May  (5 weeks)   ..		453.832	67,532	521,364	June (4 weeks)   ..		341,937	50,292	392,229	oJuly   (4 weeks)   .-.	&apos;           ::         &quot;. f	331,179	46,645	377,824	CDAug. (5 weeks)   ..		414,000	58,659 45,080	472,659	Sept. (4 weeks)   ..	&apos;                            J) i ;	273,643		318,723	CDOct.   (4 weeks)   ..	%f-   &apos;         &apos;   . )J .:&apos;	275,950.	46,266	322,216	CONov. (5 weeks)   ..		359,758	59,261	419.019	Dec.  (4 weeks)   ..	5,                      5,	309,903	;49,939	359.842^	Total: Armistice to December 27, 1924				29,692,764	(B.) Scotland.The Poor Law Emergency Provisions (Scotland) Act, 1921, conferred on Parish Councils in Scotland, for the first time, power to grant poor relief to the able-bodied poor. Particulars are not available regarding the number of unemployed persons in receipt of poor relief who were insured under the Unemployment Insurance^ Acts.	Period.	Total Approximate Expenditure other than Capital Expenditure out of Loans.	* Approximate Expendi-ture on OutdoorRelief to the Destitute Able-bodied Unemployed (included in column 2).		(1)	(2)	(3)	Armistice to May 15, 1 920 1920/21 1921/22 1922/23 1923/24        . . 1924/25t May      (3 weeks)   . . June     (4 weeks)   .. July      (4 weeks)   .. August (5 weeks)   . . Sept.     (4 weeks)   .. Oct.     . (4 weeks) Nov.      (5 weeks) Dec.       (4 weeks)   ..		  2,945,591 2,797,695 3.775,462 4,538,127 &apos; Not yet ascertained. .,               ,, . S:Z&apos;&apos;V :&quot;&apos;        V v &apos;	  500 (estimated) 659,925 1,352,170 1,113,400 43,100 56,700 58,800 69,000 38,900 37,800 4:.&apos;,200 39,500		Total: Armistice to December 27, 1924		3,518,995	* The&apos; figures exclude expenditure on interest and wages of extra staff  43,240 in 1921/22 and  102,000* in 1922/23.t From May 11, 1924.   The cost for four weeks in April was  60,000, and for the first two weeks May  29,200.Expenditure by Poor Law Authorities on the Relief of the Poor and Purposes ^      &quot; , , connected therewith.(A.) England and Wales. As from the 1st April, 1922, special returns have been obtained of the expenditure on Poor Law Relief given in their own homes to persons ordinarily engaged in some regular occupation, but these figures must necessarily be accepted with caution. Prior to this date no comparable figure is obtainable, but it is estimated that similar expenditure amounted to approximately  500,000 in 1920/21 and to  8,000.000 in 1921/22.

</content>
</cab>
