<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/3/51 images: 737-25 December 1939</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS T H E P R O P E R T Y OF HIS B R I T A N N I C M A J E S T Y ' ^
GOVERNMENT.
Secret.
(Printed for the War Cabinet, December, 1939.)
W.P. (G.) (39) 163.
Copy No. 0
TO BE K E P T UNDER LOCK AND KEY.
It is requested that special care may be taken to
ensure the secrecy of this document.
WAR CABINET.
The A merican Zionist Organisation and His Majesty's Government's Policy in
Palestine.
Memorandum by the First Lord, of the Admiralty.
I . I much regret that owing to the pressure of business I did not see the
paper W.P. (G.) (39) 161 which was printed on December 20, and it is only to-day
that I read in the Foreign Office telegrams what has been sent to Lord Lothian.
I would venture to hope that even so it is not too late to give some reconsideration
to the terms of the reply which is to be given to Dr. Brandeis.
2. The trend of American opinion since the war has been disappointing,
and the movement to interpret neutrality in the strictest manner has gathered
unexpected strength. United States warships are shadowing ours inside the
wide zone that has been proclaimed by the P a n a m a Congress, and in one case at
least the position of a British cruiser has been disclosed by broadcast. The
reactions in the case of the ARUCA have been distinctly unfavourable, and
the interview between Mr. Welles and Lord Lothian reveals a critical and even a
captious attitude towards us. At any time fresh incidents, which we are of course
endeavouring to avoid, may occur. All American attention is becoming increasingly
concentrated upon the impending Presidential election; and I fear
there can be no doubt that a harder line towards Great Britain and the affectation
of a stiff impartiality would be a help to President Roosevelt and the Democratic
Party. Do we really wish at this juncture to throw what Lord Lothian calls
" the powerful factor" of the influence of American Jewry into the scales
against us ? Can we afford to do so ?
3. It is very easy to take the lofty line of the draft telegram No. 33,
in reply to Lord Lothian's, and declare ourselves entirely above allowing
our policy in Palestine to be influenced by any desire to procure Jewish
or Arab support. But it was not for light or sentimental reasons that
Lord Balfour and the Government of 1917 made the promises to the Zionists
which have been the cause of so much subsequent discussion. The influence of
American Jewry was rated then as a factor of the highest importance, and we did
not feel ourselves in such a strong position as to be able to treat it with indifference.
Now in the advent of a Presidential election, and when the future is
full of measureless uncertainties, I should hnve thought it was more necessary,
even than in November 1917, to conciliate American Jewry and enlist their aid
in combating isolationist and indeed anti-British tendencies in the United States.
4. One hopes that if we were at the last gasp, American opinion would
rally effectively to our side, and we know this is what Mr. Roosevelt would wish.
But the war may continue in an indeterminate fashion during the long period
of electioneering"; there may be no sense of an imminent catastrophe to the
Western democracies, and yet no prospect of their early victory; and in these
circumstances Americans, though well disposed to us, and even American Jews,
may feel themselves free to use their influence in party or racial controversies
without particular regard to our immediate interests. If we had need of financial
assistance in dollars, this might be particularly inconvenient.
We ought not to do anything which will add to the weight we have to bear,
or which President Roosevelt, our best friend, may have to bear.
5- I am most reluctant to stir pre-war disputes; but I cannot help beino
struck with the uncompromising tone of the draft telegram just sent
to Lord Lothian. It must be remembered that the White Paper gave
rise to the sharpest differences of opinion in the House of Commons. The Labour
and Liberal Oppositions denounced it as a breach of faith. Mr. Lloyd George
and I who both were concerned in the giving or interpretation of the original
promise were forced to testify in this sense. Both the Liberal and Labour Parties
voted against the White Paper; and a number of Conservatives, of whom I was
one, voted with them. The Labour Party spokesman announced that
should they obtain power, they could not be bound by the White Paper
as an instrument. There were m a n y Conservative abstentions from the Division.
Since then the Mandates Commission of the League of Nations has pronounced
against the validity of the White Paper, having regard to the conditions of the
Mandate. In fact it is h a r d l y possible to find a topic more calculated to divide
British opinion and to enable those elements who support the war, but do not
like the Government, to come together, and to make a powerful case that
our war effort is being hampered by undue insistence upon the views of the
pre-War Cabinet.
6. It is perhaps futile to forecast the course of British politics at such a time
as this. Nevertheless it would seem that if the war darkens and deepens, we may
have increasingly to rely upon the support of the Liberal and Labour Parties
to marshal the whole force of the nation. They would certainly regard the
White Paper as a grievous obstacle. Moreover it seems to me most unlikely
that a n y future British Government which may take office in the next five years
will espouse the theme of the White Paper that all Jewish immigration into
Palestine will be closed down at the end of that period, unless the Arab majority
is found willing to re-open it. Are we therefore entitled to speak with the
confidence of the draft telegram to Lord Lothian about the White Paper as a
just, fixed unalterable settlement.
7. Dr. Weizrnann came to see me before he left for New York, and I am
sure t h a t it is his whole desire to bring United States opinion as far as he possibly
can on to our side, but the line indicated in the draft telegram may well make
his task impossible; and he will find himself confronted with the active
resentment of American Jewry. Their anger may become public and be readily
exploited by all unfavourable elements in the United States. This may do us
great h a rm there; and when the repercussions of this outcry reach this country
the Government will have to face a debate in the House of Commons which will
be not only embarrassing, but dangerous and damaging to our common interests.
8. I plead therefore for reconsideration of the draft telegram, and that our
Ambassador should be instructed to use softer and smoother processes. He might
say for instance that the White P a p e r represented the sincere effort of the pre-war
Cabinet to hold the scales evenly between J ew and Arab, and to fulfil all the
pledges which h a d been given; but that there were admittedly great differences of
opinion about this in the House of Commons; and t h a t it was our desire during
the war to reduce all domestic controversies to the smallest limits. He could
continue that His Majesty's Government were not now prepared to take a new
view of the policy announced b y the former Cabinet, b u t that having regard to the
attitude adopted by the Mandates Commission of the League of Nations, they
felt t h a t the future of Palestine was one of the questions which must find its place
in the general peace settlement at the end of the war; and that meanwhile
nothing would be done to prejudice the final form which that settlement would
take.
The one thing he ought not to say is that with the world in flux and the life
of every European nation and the British Empire hanging in the balance, the sole
fixed, immutable inexorable fact was that Jewish immigration into Palestine
would come to an end after five years in accordance with the White Paper.
9. Many people are called upon in these days to make sacrifices, and sacrifices
not only of opinion, in order to save the country, and I venture to urge for
the sake of our sailors and soldiers, and of all our hopes of victory t h a t we also
should allow no minor obstacles to complicate our task.
W. S. C.
December 25, 1939.


</content>
</cab>
