<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/217/0 images: 9-9</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS  BRTTANNIC  MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT.Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1930.SECRET.                                                    Copy No.   ^3CP. 402  (30).CABINET.PALESTINE GARRISON.         MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE  COLONIES.    AT a meeting of the Cabinet held on Wednesday, the 30th July, it was agreedthat  the  Departments concerned  should  consider  the recommendation  of  theCommittee of Imperial Defence (Minutes of 249th Meeting held on  the 14th July see  CP. 255 (30)) for stationing a Royal Army Service Corps Unit, with suitabletransport, in Palestine to avoid the  present expensive system of hiring, and should report to the Cabinet whether, on financial grounds, the suggestion is desirable. Thequestion has now been examined by the Colonial  Office, in consultation with theAir Ministry, the War Office and the Treasury, and it has been ascertained that the approximate cost of a Royal Army Service  Corps  Unit would be as follows :     Capital                                                              Expenses of sea transport (initial and terminal  charges)    3,400        Provision of permanent accommodation (hutted camps)...   10,900                                                               14,300    Annually recurrent         The additional annual cost to Army funds is estimated bv the War Office to            be between  4,000 and  5,000&quot;a year    2.  The High  Commissioner estimates the  cost of  hiring  at  approximately 16,000 per annum.    3.  Information has been received from the War Office that the Army council are prepared to despatch to Palestine a Mechanical Transport Company, Royal ArmyService Corps, consisting of  3 Officers, 88 other ranks, 20 light six-wheeled lorries,]   six-wheeled  car,  2  light four-wheeled cars,  1  six-wheeled  workshop  lorry,1 six-wheeled stores lorry and 6 motor cycles, and that  this Company will be ready to embark six weeks after the Unit is told definitely that it has to go to Palestine.    4.  As regards the  question of the  apportionment of the cost of defence asbetween His Majesty&apos;s Government and Palestine, it has been decided that thePalestine Government shall, in principle, be liable for  the whole of the excess cost ofthe Army Troops stationed in Palestine and a moiety of the excess cost of the R.A.E.stationed in Palestine and Trans-Jordan,  and  also the capital cost of works services in Palestine for both Forces.  The  other moiety of the excess cost of the R.A.F.,together with the capital cost of works services in Trans-Jordan, will be borne byHis Majesty&apos;s Government.    5. . Actual repayments by the Palestine Government are to be determined withregard to the Palestine Governments  ability to pay.    6.  It is clear that the employment  in  Palestine of a R.A.S.C.  Unit is aneconomical arrangement, which is desirable on financial grounds.                                                                         P.    Colonial Office, November 28, 1930.[22128]

</content>
</cab>
