<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/217/0 images: 10-34</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOOUiOTT  IS  THE PROPERTY  OF HIS BRITANNIC iIAJ &apos; !STY&apos; S GOVERN! gLNO)                                                          COPY nos. E C RET.CP, 403 (50) .C A B I NET.STATEMENT OF TH2J PRINCIPAL MEASURES TAMEN BYHIS MAJESTYTS GOVERN!DjITT IN CONNECTION WITH               UNEllPLOYI [ENT.           Note by tho  Secretary.           In pursuance  of  Cabinet  70  (30), Conclusion 3 (a)  and (h),  the draft White Paper nn the Principal Measures  taken by the Government in connection with Unemployment (Paper CP.  391 (30) has been revised, and a revised draft i-s attached for consideration by the Cabinet at their Meeting on Wednesday, December 10th, 1930.(Signed)  M.P.A.  HANMEY    Secretary,  Cabinet02, Whitehall Gardens, S.W,lc   9th December,  1930.
STATEMENTof  the  principal  measures  taken  byH.M.  Government in  connection  with unemployment.Presented to Parliament by the             by Command of   His Majesty, December, 1930.                   LONDON:   PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICE. To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses:   Adastral House, Kingsway. London, W.C.2; 120, George Street, Edinburgh;       York Street, Manchester; 1, St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardifl;.             15, Donegall Square West, Belfast;               or through any Bookseller.                    1930.                  Price   Net,Cmd.
INTRODUCTION.  Part I of this statement is in continuation of previous statementspresented to Parliament in December, 1929 (Cmd. 3449) and March,1930  (Cmd.  3519), and brings up to date figures,  given in  thosestatements, of  approvals  for  Government  assistance  under  theDevelopment   (Loan  Guarantees  and  Grants)  Act,  1929,  theColonial Development Act, 1929, from the Road Fund, and  under other arrangements for works of important employment value.  The promotion of  emergency works is, however, only  one partof the Governments programme for dealing with unemployment;and  the present statement has been expanded so  as to include a brief review of other relevant branches of the Government&apos;s policy.  Since the summer of 1929, the chai-acter of  the  unemployment problem has been transformed by  the onset of  a world trade  de-pression of quite  exceptional severity.  Apart from the slump of1920-21, there is no  recorded case in modern economic history of so violent and  rapid a collapse  in the prices of  primary  com-modities,  as has  occurred  during  the past 12  months;  and  the significance of the present collapse is altogether more serious thanthat  of 1920-21,  which represented a  reaction from abnormallyprofitable prices to which costs of production had not been adjusted.  The fall in the prices of primary commodities has inevitably been associated  with a depression of  business  activity of  almost  every kind throughout the world as a whole.    The  familiar  &quot; viciouscircles &quot; of a general trade depression  have been  set in motion.The  primary producers,  unable to sell their  goods at remunerativeprices, have been forced to reduce their purchases of manufacturedgoods;  and the activity of  manufacturing  industries  has accord-ingly been reduced.   Shipping has  suffered from  the decline inforeign  trade;  the depression of  shipping  reacts, after a period of delay due to the working off of old  orders, upon shipbuilding;  thedecline of  shipbuilding injures iron and steel and coal; ultimately,as industry in general becomes  depressed,  retail trade begins to suffer from the consequential reduction of purchasing-power. Thus,through one channel or another, the initial depression in the primarycommodity markets has been communicated throughout the entireeconomic  field ; and  the  process has  been aggravated by variouscomplicating factors arising  from the depression, the depreciationin the exchange values of the currencies of certain countries, finan-cial failure and  stock-exchange  losses, a  general  atmosphere of uncertainty and apprehension which is inimical to business enter-prise.  The developments, thus briefly outlined, have  been internationalin scope.    Their origins lie,  for  the  most part,  outside  Great
Britain  and indeed outside Europe.   As a country which engagesvery largely in foreign trade, Great  Britain has  suffered from the disturbance of world  markets more quickly and more acutely thanmany European countries with a relatively self-contained economic life.   But  all countries are now feeling  its effects in  greater orless degree, and many are much more seriously affected than GreatBritain.  The occurrencce of the world depression was,  however, fraughtwith  special  dangers for Great Britain.  Her economic conditionhad been far from satisfactory for several  years previously. several of her  principal exporting  industries had  been  confronted withspecial difficulties in world markets in the post-war decade.  Somehad been  prejudiced  by political troubles  in countries which havenormally been particularly important markets for British  goods.Others  had suffered  from technological changes, e.g.,  coal fromthe growing use  of oil as a source  of power.   The growth of tariff barriers throughout  the world  had  added to  the difficulties ofBritish  export trade as a whole, and these difficulties were further increased by the fact that Great Britain  was the only  one  of the belligerent  countries in the late war which had restored its currencyfrom  a  depreciated level to  its pre-war parity with gold.  As theresult of such difficulties,  important  industries   had  lost  ground in export  markets, and the loss had never been  fully  made goodby compensating developments  in other  trades.   Unemploymenthad ruled high for about nine years.  Great  Britain thus entered the world  depression with  her economic vitality already  some-what  impaired ;  and  the position was made more serious for herby the consideration that the world depression must tend inevitablyto intensify competition in  world  markets, as well as  increasingthe real burden  of fixed money charges upon  industry,  to accentu-ate, in  other  words, :some  of the  difficulties  from which she has suffered in the past decade.  Before the international  depression  had made itself felt, theGovernment  had already set on foot a twofold  economic policy,comprising -       (1) a  short-range policy,  designed to provide   immediate    employment by pressing forward development work of  public    utility with  the utmost vigour;      (2)  a long-range  policy,  designed to increase the efficiency    of British industry, and to promote the prosperous develop-    ment of British  economic life.  The slump  in world trade increases  the  urgency of  both  the objectives.   But  it also increases some of the difficulties in their way.  When the economic  outlook  is unsatisfactory,  local  autho-rities  and  public utility companies  become more reluctant to incur the financial  commitments entailed by new works of public utility.Similarly,  in  a  period of bad  trade, the business  atmosphere  is
not favourable to  bold  schemes of industrial reconstruction.   Itis  in  the  face of such  difficulties that the work  which is  brieflysummarized in the present statement has been accomplished.                            PART I.Emergency Works approved for Government Financial Assistance.  In June  and July  last the Government  held a series of con-ferences with representatives of local authorities  with the object ofsecuring a considerable extension of the programme of useful publicworks which could be put in hand in order to mitigate the effects ofthe prolonged unemployment from which  the country is suffering.As  a result of these conferences,  at  which special stress was laid on  providing as  much work as possible  for the  coming winter,substantial concessions were  made to local authorities in regard tothe conditions under which Government assistance would be madeavailable for local  schemes.   Arrangements for expediting  thepreparation,  approval  and  execution of schemes  were  discussed and  agreed.  The  Government  decided also to  increase  very  largely  the trunk  Road programme and to  facilitate  the  execution  of  theFive-Year programme  for the improvement of classified roads and bridges  (and the construction of new roads and bridges likely tobe classified).  In  addition Votes  amounting  to  500,000 were taken to pro-vide for grants to Local  Authorities in selected necessitous  areasin respect of approved employment schemes to  be undertaken inthe winter of 1930-31.  At the close of last Session the  principle of expediting the grantof powders needed in  connection  with works designed to  relieve unemployment was greatly extended by the passing of  the PublicWorks  Facilities  Act.   That  Act provides  an  alternative  to ordinary Private Bill legislation which will very  materially shorten the process of obtaining  statutory powers in such cases by localauthorities and public utility undertakings.   The  Act  also  makesavailable a  greatly simplified and  more expeditious procedure  forthe compulsory acquisition of land and easements.     Development (Loan Guarantees and Grants)  Act,  1929.  The following Table shows the  schemes approved for grant onthe recommendation of the  Advisory Committee appointed  underPart  I  of the  Act up to 30th  September,  1930 (including  those contained in Cmd. 3449 and Cmd. 3519) : 
TABLE I.	Total Estimated Cost of Schemes.	Total Estimated Exchequer Grants.	Present Valuo of Grants.	Nature of Undor-ta kings receiving Assistance.			Amount.	Percentage of Total Estimated Cost.1.	2. -	3.	4.	5.Railways (excluding docks). Docks (including rail-	  22,181,663 *3,681,482	  7,316,188 1,638,140	5,184,201 1,079,191	Per cent. 23 29way-owned docks). Water Gas ... ...... Electricity-	838,739 1,425,624 83,722	304,658 281,036 10,175	245,435 247,085 8,816	29   17 11Total ......	28,211,230	9,550,203	6,764,728	24  * This figure includes a sum of  1,350,000 for certain dock schemes whichare now understood to be subject to reconsideration.  In  addition  to  the grant schemes set out  above it  has beenagreed to guarantee under Part I of the Act a loan of  206,000 for expenditure  on an electricity  supply scheme estimated  to cost 236,000.  The total estimated  cost  of the  electricity schemes approved under Part I of the Act is therefore  319,722,  and thetotal for schemes of all classes  28,447,230.  The following Table shows  the  schemes approved for grant onthe recommendation of  the Committee  appointed  under Part ii of the Act (the Unemployment Grants Committee)  from 1st June,1929,  to  30th September,  1930  (including  those  contained in cmd. 3449 and Cmd. 3519).   The figures in this Table represent2,397  schemes submitted  by 865  local  authorities and  other statutory bodies :                             TABLE II.Nature of Scheme. 1.	Total Estimated Cost of Works. 2.	Total Estimated Exchequer Grants. 3.	Present Valuo of Grants.				Amount. 4.	Percentage of Total Estimated Cost. 5.1. Loan schemes Re-venue - producing 2. Loan schemes   Non-revenue pro-ducing. 3. Schemes financed otherwise than by loan. Total ......	  24,608,187 21,000,490 1,158,018	  9,619,000 17,941,000 587,000	  7,103,000 11,677,000 587,000	Per cent. 29 56 51	46,766,695 1 28,147,000		19,367,000	418188A 2
TABLE I.	Total Estimated Cost of Schemes.	Total Estimated Exchequer Grants.	Present Valuo of Grants.	Nature of Under-takings receiving Assistance.			Amount.	Percentage of Total Estimated Cost.		CO	4.	5.1.	o			Railways (excluding docks). Docks (including rail-way-owned docks). Water ...... Gas ......... Electricity ...	  22,181,663 *3,6S1,482 838,739 1,425,624 83,722	  7,316,188 1,638,146 304,658 281,036 10,175	  5,184,201 1,079,191 245,435 247,085 8,816	Per cent. 23 29 29 ------ 17 11Total......	28,211,230	9,550,203	6.764,728	24  &quot; X1US Ilgure Iliuiuuea tt ouiii m *j *.,w*,JVw .are now understood to bo subject to reconsideration.   In addition  to the grant  schemes set out  above it  has been agreed to guarantee under Part I of the Act a loan of  206,000 for expenditure  on  an electricity  supply  scheme  estimated  to cost  236,000.  The  total estimated  cost  of the  electricity schemes approved under  Part I  of the Act is therefore  42319,722,  and the total for schemes of all  classes  28,447,230.   The following Table  shows the schemes  approved for grant  on the  recommendation of the  Committee appointed  under  Part  II of the Act (the Unemployment Grants  Committee)  from 1st June, 1929,  to 30th  September,  1930  (including  those contained  in Cmd. 3449  and  Cmd. 3519).  The figures in  this Table represent 2,397  schemes  submitted  by  865 local  authorities  and  other statutory bodies :                              TABLE II.	Total Estimated Cost of Works.	Total Estimated Exchequer Grants.	Present Value of Grants.	Nature of Scheme.			Amount.	Percentage of Total Estimated Cost.1.	2.	3.	4. -	5.1. Loan schemes Pe-	  24,608,187	  9,619,000	  7,103,000	Per cent. 29venue- producing 2. Loan schemes -	21,000,490	17,941,000	11,677,000	&apos;. 56Non-revenue pro-ducing. 3. Schemes financed otherwise than by loan.	1,158,018	587,000	587,000	51Total ......	46,766,695	28,147,000	19,367,000	418I8SA 2
                    Summary of Schemes.  The following Table Contains a summary of the various  types of scheme approved under the Act, together with the estimated costof each type of scheme :  TABLE  III.	Total Estimated Cost of Approved Schemes.					Nature or Schemes.			i	Under Part I.	Under Part II.	Total.	 	 	 Railways (excluding docks) ...	22,181,603	- &apos;	22,181,063Docks and harbours (including	3,081,482	4,049,707	8,031,189railway-owned docks and			&quot; harbours).			Water supply ...	838,730	5,610,600	6,449,429Electricity ... ... &apos; ...	310,722	12,526,303	12,846,025Gas .........	1,425,624	901,872	2,327,406Sewage... ... ....	 	8,779,357	8,779,357Land reclamation and drainage	 	1,695,242	1,695,242Sea defence works	 	1,288,472	1,288,472Unclassified roads		5,973,667	5,073,667Parks, recreation grounds, etc.	-	1,904,S80	1,904,886Civic Buildings and Public		1,563,218	1,503,218Institutions.			River improvement ...	 	654,629	654,029Baths and washhouses	 	479,812	479,812Sanitation .;.	 	316,491	316,491Cemeteries	-  	55,237	55,237Miscellaneous ...	 	67,112	07,112Total ......	28,447,230	46,766,695	75,213,925               Colonial  Development  Act,  1929.  Section II of Cmd. 3519 outlined progress under the colonial development  Act  until 28th  February,  1930,  by  which  dateschemes involving a total estimated expenditure of  5,650,000 from home and Colonial funds had been approved under the Act.  Up to 30th September, 1930, further assistance had been  recom-mended  byi the  Colonial  Development  Advisory  Committee  inrespect of  development works  in Kenya,  Tanganyika  Territory,Northern Rhodesia, Nyasaland,  Somaliland,  Gold  Coast, Nigeria,the West Indies, Cyprus,  Mauritius,  Seychelles,  North Borneo,Fiji, British Honduras, Western Pacific,  Palestine and  Trans-Jordania, Falkland Islands, St. Helena, Bechuanaland and  Swazi-land.   The ;total  estimated cost  of the schemes  recommended forassistance by  the Committee  from its inception until  30th  Sep-tember, 1930, and approved by the Treasury, was  8,374,697.   Of
this  total  4,122,440  represented the  cost  of  schemes  in  EastAfrica, which will be  met by the Governments of the territories concerned from  loans raised  under the  Palestine and East AfricaLoans Act,  192G, as  amended  by the  Colonial  development act,  1929.   Of the  total  of   8,375,000  it  is  estimated  thatsome  3,300,000 will be  spent in Great Britain.   In addition tothe schemes covered by this figure of  8,375,000, further schemes under the Palestine and East Africa  Loans Act have been inaugu-rated, the estimated cost being  some  4,820,000.                          Road Fund.  Under the  Trunk Road  Programme (the total  of which was raised in July last to  21,000,000)  the schemes approved  amountedat 30th September, 1930, to over  15,000,000, of which schemesrepresenting  expenditure  of  over   5,000,000 had been  definitelyapproved for grant and  the  balance approved  in  principle.   Themajority of  the schemes approved will  cost  individually  over 100,000 each, including  33  schemes of widening and reconstruc-tion  and 12 important  by-pass schemes.  Under the Fivc-Year Programme  of   27,500,000,  the schemes approved amounted at 30th September, 1930, to nearly  25 000 000,of which  schemes representing  expenditure of nearly  9,000 000had  been definitely approved for grant  and the balance approved in principle.   Nearly half the schemes approved will cost individu-ally  over   100,000 each, including  20  schemes of widening and reconstruction  and 30 new sections of  road  of  which  7 are important by-pass roads.  It is  estimated  that the Road Fund liability in respect of thewhole  of the  schemes already approved  will  be approximately 30,000,000.  In addition to the above, the  Annual Programme deals withschemes of  improvement  of  classified roads and bridges of  lessermagnitude.  &apos;The Annual Programme schemes  approved for  grantunder  the present Government  (i.e.,  since 30th  August,  1929)amounted at 30th September to  9,000,000. It is estimated thatthe  Eoad  Fund liability  in respect  of  these schemes will be approximately  6,000,000.  The Five-Year  and Annual  programmes absorb  the  previousprogramme  for 1929-30.  In addition to the above, grants have been made by the Unem-ployment Grants Committee (as shown in Table  III on page 4)in respect  of  expenditure estimated at about  6,000,000 in con-nexion with unclassified roads and bridges.                      Other Programmes.  The Ministry of Agriculture and  Fisheries had up to the 30thSeptember agreed to  assist  175  land drainage schemes,  submitted   81S8                                                   A3
by land drainage authorities, which are estimated to cost  236,000in addition to the  schemes referred to in Table III above.*   Thesame department had agreed to assist 459 schemes of field drainageestimated to cost  48,000, and 133 schemes for the supply of waterto agricultural holdings at an estimated cost of  93,000.  The Development Commission have power to  assist  agricultureand  rural industries, the construction  and improvement of fisheryharbours, and  land drainage and  reclamation, and  between thedate when the present Government assumed office and  the  30thSeptember,  1930,  the total  estimated  cost of  the schemes  inrespect  of which  the  Development  Commission  had  agreed  torender financial assistance was  807,000.  These schemes are quiteseparate from those dealt with by other Governmental authorities.  Reference  was made in Cmd. 3519 to the programme of work at a cost of some  60,000 being carried out over the winter 1929-30by the Office of Works.  This programme has now been completed,but  during the present winter works suitable for the employmentof unskilled labour on Ancient Monuments and Historic buildings and  in  the Royal  Parks will be carried out by  the  same depart-ment at a cost  of  129,000.  The accelerated programme of  trunk  telephone  construction  bythe  General  Post  Office, at an estimated  cost of   1,500,000,  towhich reference was made in Cmd. 3519,  is being  actively carriedout  in  addition to the main  construction  programme of a capitalannual  cost of  about  10,500,000.  As is explained in  the  prefatory  note,  grants  amounting  to 500,000 have  been made available for grants to Local  Authoritiesin selected  necessitous areas in respect of  approved employmentschemes,  440,000 being  allocated   to  works  in England andWales  and   60,000 to works in  Scotland.  Schemes in Englandand Wales to a total value of  410,000 have already been approvedby the Ministry of Health.   For  the purposes of land  settlement  in Scotland the grant  in aid  to the Agriculture  (Scotland)  Fund  was increased in the vote for  the  financial year  1930-31  from   115,000 (the amount voted in 1929-30) to  175,000.  Farm and field drainage  schemes costingsome  100,000 and involving assistance from the Exchequer to  theextent  of  30,000 have been approved by  the Department of Agri-culture for Scotland, and the Land Drainage (Scotland) Act, 1930,under which main drainage works costing some  100,000 will be proceeded with over a period of 5 years, is now in  operation. Im- provement schemes to Scottish fishery harbours  at a cost of about  * The land drainage schemes where tho work is to be financed by the localauthority  out  of  a  loan  are dealt  with  by the Unemployment GrantsCommittee.
 10,000, have&apos;been  approved for assistance from the funds of the fishery Board for Scotland.  The Government decided to increase ithe financial provision forafforestation for the 10  years from 1st April,  1929,  by approxi-mately  3  millions  to  9 millions.  This will enable the ForestryCommissioners to increase  their total  planting  programme from237,000 acres to 353,000 acres for the period the annual planting programme rising  from 25,000 to 44,000 acres.   The  scheme willalso provide 3,000 forest workers holdings  instead of 1,500  duringthe 10 years.  With the  smaller  programme the  number  of  forest workers employed would have varied  from a minimum of 2,700 in summerto a maximum of 3,500 in  winter.   With the new programme thenumber employed will increase each year up to  5,200  (summer)and 6,700  (winter)  in the tenth year.  These figures  are apartfrom  additional  workers employed  in  ancillary occupations thenumber of which is  difficult  to estimate.  The number now directly employed is 410 more than a year ago.                          Summary.  The  value of schemes  under various programmes  which havebeen approved up  to September 30th, may  be summarised  asfollows :                                                               Development (Loan Guarantees and Grants) Act,      1929, Part I     ...............   28,447,230    Development (Loan Guarantees and Grants) Act,      1929, Part II    ...............   46,766,695    Colonial Development Act, 1929  .........    8,375,000    Boad Fund..................   49,000,000    Miscellaneous       ...............    3,340,323Total ...  135,929,248  On the  basis commonly accepted that  1,000,000 provides workfor one year for 4,000 men, these schemes will provide work to theextent of  more than 500,000 man years or over 150 million  days of work.
                          PART II.                   Economic Reorganisation.  Although as will be seen from the foregoing tables, the policy of promoting public works in relief of unemployment has been vigor-ously pursued, it must be  recognised that sucli  a policy is subjectto certain general limitations.  The  acceleration of programmes ofwork by local  authorities and  many public utility undertakingshas  been in progress for the  last  ten  years,  and  during  thatperiod the  economic equipment  of the country its  roads, bridges,docks, railways  and the like has been greatly improved. But ina country already very highly developed, the process of anticipatingfuture needs cannot in the nature of things continue indefinitely.The arrears of work which had accumulated during the war  years  &apos;have been  overtaken, and there are signs that the visible pro-grammes of public works which can conform to any  reasonabletest of economic justification, now embrace, to a large extent what can usefully be  done in the near future.   The promotion of public  works  is avowedly only a temporaryemergency measure.   Side by side  with this, the Government are pursuing a long range policy of development.                    Indusirial Reorganisation.   As was  stated in Cmd. 3519, referred to above,  it is  to the in- creased  provision of ordinary industrial employment through the revival  of  our  trade  and industry that  the Government  attach primary importance.  Their work  in the  industrial field may be grouped under  two heads : the encouragement  of reorganisation of industry at home and of trade  abroad.   Legislation  has been  passed putting the coal industry  of the&apos; country for the first time in its history in  a position to  promote a national sales policy and  organisation and to deal with international problems on a  footing more nearly equal to that of its competitors abroad.   The Government is also  in negotiation  with the Railway Com- panies,  the Coal  Owners and the  Iron and Steel trades  with a view to the introduction  of an aided scheme under the provisions of  the Development Act, 1929, for the adaptation of colliery and works sidings  and equipment to facilitate  the wider use of  20-ton wagons.    Immediately upon taking office the Government  appointed Com- mittees to consider and report upon the condition and prospects of the Cotton and Iron and  Steel Industries,  and to make  recom- mendations as to  any action that might be taken to improve their  position.   The Reports  of  these Committees have  now been  received.
  The Report on the Cotton Industry (Cmd.  3615), recommendedthat the Government should take every  step in  their power to urge upon employers and operatives in Lancashire the; importanceof considering  certain means of reducing the costs of productionwith a view to  the recovery of lost trade.   This recommendation isbeing acted upon,  and the Government  is in close  and constantconsultation with all the interests concerned upon the basis of theReport.  The Report on the Iron and Steel  Industry  is similarly the subject of  discussion with representatives of the industry  andof finance.  One of the measures  recommended in the Report on the CottonIndustry is the formation  of large units.   Careful  consideration isbeing given to  the  question how far similar measures are requiredin other industries, and in  certain cases measures of reorganisationare under discussion. These matters are of course highly confidential -tial, affecting as they do the position of individual firms, and cannotbe referred to  in detail.  Further, the negotiations leading up toreorganisation cover a large number of interests  and  must of their nature be delicate and prolonged.  With a view to ensuring that finance will be available for soundschemes of reorganisation discussions have taken place with leadingfinancial interests and  a new  organisation has  come  into being,known as the Bankers&apos; Industrial Development Company, with thesupport  of the leading  banks  and  financial  houses,  to considerschemes submitted  by the  basic industries of this  country for thepurpose of  their rationalisation,  either by industries or by regions.  The Cunard  Company proposed  to  build one  and perhaps  two large  express steamers, but were doubtful whether such a  vesselcould be fully insured in the open market and were not preparedto build without assurance on that point.   The  Government haveagreed,  for reasonable  premiums,  to cover  any insurance  notabsorbed by the  market.   The  cost of each vessel is expected tobe something between  4,000,000 and  4,500,000, and the  build-ing of  one of  these ships will provide  employment,  direct  and indirect, for some 5,000 men for three years.                     Monetary Conditions.  As  a  stimulus to trade recovery and industrial development  lowrates  for short term borrowing have an especial importance.  Cheapmoney  depends on  a variety  of influences, many of them  worldfactors  outside  the  control  or guidance of  any single  country;  andmany causes  have contributed to the attainment  of the easy creditconditions which now widely prevail. But towards their attainmentin this country the Government were able to make a  material con-tribution by their handling of the floating debt.   In the autumn of1929, and the early months of 1930, when it  became evident thatthere was a surplus of  long term money available for  investment
the public were invited to subscribe to issues of 5  per  cent, and4J per cent. Conversion Stock.  These new issues provided, overand above the amounts required to  meet maturing debt, a free sumof about  160,000,000.   This new money, as it became available in stages, was used to reduce the need for public  borrowings in the short  term market on Treasury Bills.   The repayment of these bills had the effect of increasing the market resources  available for tradeand commerce, while diminishing the demand upon  them for non-trade  purposes.  The process was so devised and  timed  as to hasten the rapid  transition  from high rates to easy conditions, which wasthe outstanding monetary feature  during the past year; and theGovernment thus contributed materially to the fall in TreasuryBill rates from 6 per cent, to little more than 2 per cent, and there-establishment of  the  monetary conditions most likely to favour a world recovery of  trade.                          Export Trade.  As  regards export trade, the Government in  April of this yearbrought into being  the Overseas Trade Development  Council atthe instance of, and for the purpose of assisting, the  Departmentof Overseas Trade in their study of present  and  potential markets,in their investigation  of reasons for the decline in  Exports, andin their search for fields of  profitable expansion of British  Trade.In co-operation  with the industries concerned,  steps have  alreadybeen  taken  which should  lead to an expansion  of trade overseas.The more important of these steps include the despatch abroad ofTrade Missions.  A Mission has just returned from  South  Africa,and the  Overseas Trade Development Council is discussing withthe leader and  members of the Mission the best means of  makingthe work of the Mission  as effective  as possible.   Another very important Mission which includes a specially constituted  CottonSub-Mission is at present visiting Japan  and China.  A further activity which is  being developed by the  Departmentof Overseas Trade is that  of arranging for  trade investigations in selected overseas markets on behalf of particular industries.   Thereis  at present in South America  a  trade  delegation from Sheffieldunder the leadership of the Master  Cutler, the reports of whose work  are  distinctly encouraging : an investigation on behalf of theBoot  and Shoe industry is proceeding in Northern Europe.  The Government  have  decided  to  participate; in  the  BritishEmpire Trade Exhibition  to  be held in  Buenos Aires in 1931,and  their decision has led to co-ordinated efforts by  the Britishmotor, electrical and aircraft industries on a very large  scale.  In order the better to assist exporters in  finding or  maintainingmarkets  abroad,  the  Government have created or  restored  14overseas posts  under the Department  of Overseas Trade; four inthe Trade Commissioner  Service  within the Empire, and 10 inthe Commercial Diplomatic Service  in  foreign countries.
                                                               15 17,805,000                          Electricity.  The Electricity Supply Industry  stands  in a special  position under the  Electricity  Commissioners who  are charged with thestatutory duties of promoting, regulating and supervising the supplyof electricity throughout  the country.  The executive bodies  by whom actual  developments  are  undertaken  are  (a)  the central electricity Board  who are charged  with the duty of  carrying outthe new Regional (Grid)  Schemes prepared by the Commissionersfor the co-ordination of generation  and trunk transmission; and(b) upwards of 600 public authority  and company undertakers whoare charged with the duty of supplying  and  distributing electricityin their respective areas.  In  spite of general trade depression, the output of electricity(units generated)  by the  authorised  undertakers in Great britain during  each  of  the  first  ten months of the present  year  was inexcess of the corresponding output in each  of the first ten monthsof the year 1929.   The  total  output for the ten months ending31st October, 1930, showed an  increase of 5.4 per cent,  on theoutput during the corresponding  ten  months of 1929.  Reference was made in Cmd. 3519, p. 6, to the important scheme,( 9,000,000) for  the standardisation  of  frequency in  North east england, towards which a grant had  been made under the Develop-ment Act.  Other assisted schemes relating to electricity supplyare included in Table III on page 4  of this Paper.   Apart,  however,  from  direct  financial assistance,  the  Govern-ment  has taken  all possible  steps to  encourage  the continueddevelopment of electricity supply  in Great  Britain,  not only inthe centres of population but also  in the  rural districts;  and no opportunity has  been lost of  urging the undertakers to expeditedevelopment and  put in hand well-considered schemes in advanceof normal requirements.  Complementary to  the  work of the Government  in helping in-dustry to retain  old  and open  new  foreign  markets,  stands thework  of  the Export  Credits Guarantee Department.   provision was made  in the Overseas  Trade Act, 1930, for the continuanceof the scheme to March 31st, 1935,  and the increasing extent towhich recourse  has been had  to the facilities afforded since thepresent scheme began in 1926 may be gathered from the following figures of exports assisted :                                                               9 months to 31.3.1927     .........      365,000    12 months to 31.3.1928     .........    2,455,000    12 months to 31.3.1929     .........    4,283,000    12 months to 31.3.1930     .........    5,661,000      6 months to 30.9.1930     .........    5,041,000
  With regard to the Central Electricity Board, the eight schemes already prepared by  the Commissioners and adopted by the Boardcover the whole  of  England  and Wales and the industrial beltof Central  Scotland.  These  Schemes  extend over  an  area  of63,324  square.miles  or nearly 72 per  cent,  of the total area ofGreat  Britain,  and  include a  population of  41.6 million or over97 per cent, of the  total population.   The  Scheme  for central scotland has already  been formally inaugurated and rapid  progress is being made in the carrying out of the other Schemes.  At theend  of  March last, the Central Board  had constructed  about 280circuit  miles of trunk and secondary grid lines  and had placedcontracts to the total value of  approximately  12,250,000.  With regard   to  public  authority  and  company  undertakersgenerally, the expenditure incurred by these bodies on transmissionand  distribution alone during each of the years 192S-29 and 1929-30amounted to upwards of  17,000,000.  In addition t6 the developments which are taking  place  in the urban centres, many schemes for the development of supplies inthe  rural  portions  of the  country have been approved  by theCommissioners and  put  in  hand during the  past 12  months.   Aspecial Demonstration Scheme for  a large  tract of typical ruralcountry in  the neighbourhood of  Bedford is  being  carried out bythe  Corporation of Bedford, while a similar Scheme in respect of a rural  area  in the  neighbourhood of Norwich has recently beenadopted by the  Corporation of Norwich and  is being put in hand.   The Government, through the Commissioners, have  been in close touch  with  the  industry generally in  regard to the expediting,wherever practicable, of  programmes of new constructional work, and have  also urged on  undertakers the desirability of initiating schemes of assisted wiring and of facilities for the hire and hire- purchase of electrical apparatus with the object of encouraging the development of domestic supplies.                            Housing.   The  removal  of  bad  housing  conditions which  sap national efficiency by their prejudicial effect on the health  of the inhabitants is  a permanent gain which justifies a higher place  for housing policy in a general  programme of national development  than if its value were to be measured solely in terms of its immediate effect in giving employment.   Since the War a large programme  of house building has been undertaken towards which substantial aid has been afforded by the Exchequer.  Experience has  shown, however, that if the maximum progress and efficiency in this work is to be reached and maintained  with consequent  benefit  not only to  those in  need  of  better accommodation  but also to  all engaged  in  the  building industry and,  indeed, to  the whole  community the  plans of  each local
1515authority  should  be carefully  laid on the  basis of a  steady  and continuous programme.  And while it will be necessary to revisefrom  time to time the extent of  Government  assistance,  suchrevisions should  take place at reasonable intervals  so that the dis-location and uncertainty and check  to development consequent ontoo frequent changes may be avoided.  Accordingly one of the first acts of the present Government wasto pass the Housing (Revision  of Contributions) Act, 1929, which,with the object of preserving continuity  of house building by localauthorities,  provided that the reduction  in the rate of Exchequerassistance due  to be made on the  1st  October, 1929, under anOrder  of  the  Governments predecessors, should  not  take place.Under the Housing Act,  1930, the  rate of assistance was furtherstabilised  until 1933.  For  some years past it has  been  apparent that  the removal ofslums and the improvement of bad housing conditions was laggingbehind the general  progress of housing  since the War, althoughthe deplorable effect of existing conditions remained evident anduncontested.   The  Housing Act,  1930,  provides machinery for a systematic and sustained attack  on bad  housing conditions  andfor all necessary  rehousing.   Former difficulties and  complexities of procedure have been swept away,  and  a new basis of Exchequerassistance has been introduced, with  a view to providing generouslytowards the expenses of local authorities,  particularly in the diffi-cult task  of adjusting the rents of houses provided in connectionwith slum clearance and improvement to a level which the tenantscan afford to pay.  The new  Act  also meets the need for a long term  programme already referred  to,  and accordingly, with a view to securing  con-discontinuity of action  and an adequate  volume  of new construction,requires  local authorities to  submit to the Minister  of Healthduring the present  year a  programme of the steps they  proposeto take during the ensuing five  years  for  dealing with housing conditions in  their  areas and  for providing new accommodation,and a  similar  programme is to  be furnished each  fifth year.  Another direction in which a speedier advance than in the pastis desirable is in that of  remedying the shortage of houses in rural areas.   The Act of 1930 contains  special provision  designedto  secure the execution  of comprehensive  schemes  for  meeting this need.  Housing progress in Scotland  has also been hamper-ed in thepast by many factors and  accordingly  a corresponding  Act waspassed for Scotland with the  object of  encouraging a  systematicand rapid improvement in  the  slum conditions  in  the  country.  The Acts  were welcomed by local authorities and vigorous steps are being taken  in both countries  to urge them  to  make activeuse of the new  powers conferred upon  them.
15iGauthority should be carefully  laid on  the basis  of  a steady and continuous programme.   And  while it  will be necessary to revisefrom  time to  time the  extent  of Government  assistance, suchrevisions should take place  at  reasonable intervals so that the dis-location and  uncertainty and check to  development consequent ontoo frequent  changes may  be  avoided.  Accordingly one of the first  acts of the present  Government wasto pass the Housing (Revision  of  Contributions) Act, 1929, which,with the object  of preserving continuity of house  building by localauthorities, provided that the  reduction in the rate  of  Exchequerassistance due to be made on the 1st October, 1929,  under anOrder  of the Governments predecessors,  should not take place.Under the Housing Act, 1930, the rate of assistance was furtherstabilised until 1933.  For  some  years past it has  been apparent that the removal ofslums and the improvement of bad housing conditions was laggingbehind  the general  progress of housing since the War, althoughthe deplorable effect of  existing conditions remained evident anduneontcsted.   The  Housing Act,  1930, provides  machinery  for a systematic and  sustained attack  on bad  housing conditions andfor ail necessary rehousing. Former difficulties  and complexities of procedure  have been swept away, and a new basis of  Exchequerassistance has been introduced, with a view to providing generouslytowards  the  expenses of local  authorities,  particularly in the diffi-cult task of  adjusting the rents of houses provided  in  connectionwith slum clearance and improvement to a level which the tenantscan afford to pay.  The new  Act also meets the need for  a long  term programme already referred to,  and  accordingly, with a view to securing con-discontinuity  of action  and an adequate volume of new  construction,requires local  authorities to   submit  to the Minister  of Healthduring  the present  year  a  programme of  the steps  they  proposeto take  during  the ensuing five  years for dealing  with housing conditions in their  areas and  for providing new  accommodation,and a  similar programme is to be furnished each fifth  year.  Another direction in which  a speedier advance  than in the pastis desirable  is  in  that  of  remedying  the shortage  of houses in rural areas.  The Act of 1930 contains special provision  designedto  secure the  execution of comprehensive schemes for meeting this need.   Housing progress in  Scotland  has also been  hampered  in  thepast by many  factors and accordingly a  corresponding  Act waspassed  for Scotland with the  object of encouraging a systematicand rapid improvement  in  the slum conditions  in the  country.   The Acts were welcomed by local authorities and  vigorous steps are  being taken in both countries to  urge them to make activeuse  of the new powers  conferred upon them.
                          Agriculture.  Assistance towards the revival of industry proper must,  unlessthe existing social disequilibrium  is  to  become even  more  pro-nouhced,  be accompanied by  measures  to  restore agriculture inthis  country to a more prosperous &quot;condition.   Embodied  in theAgricultural Land Utilisation Bill  now before Parliament are cer-tain proposals of the Government designed to increase the. numberof persons  deriving their  livelihood  from the cultivation  of theland, and also  to increase  the  provision of instruction and  demon-stration so as to give all occupiers of agricultural holdings improvedfacilities  for  carrying  on  their  business  with the  maximum efficiency,  and  at  the same time provide  fuller opportunity for existing farm workers and others.  In addition to the employment which would be  directly  provided in the  re-equipment and re-conditioning of land, the Bill contains provision for directly assist-ing unemployed men and women in two  ways.   In the first place,it will  enable the Government to provide smallholdings  for un-employed  persons  in  other industries  who satisfy the  Ministerof Agriculture that  they are able  to cultivate  a holding properly.The Bill empowers the Minister to make a loan to an  unemployedperson  of  sufficient amount to enable him to purchase the live and dead  stock necessary for the holding.  It also  enables theMinister to make a grant to  the  man,  after he has entered intooccupation  of the holding, of  a weekly  allowance until such time as the holding becomes productive.  This allowance will, of course,only  be available  in  substitution for any  unemployment  benefitto which  the smallholder might be entitled.   The Bill also  enables the Government to provide agricultural training for suitable selectedunemployed persons so as to fit them to become successful small-holders.   The  Government  recognizes,  however,  that, no -matter  what progress is made with the provision of smallholdings, there willremain large numbers of persons unemployed,  who will be  anxiousto be given access to a small area of land so that they may growfor- their  own  families adequate supplies of fresh vegetables.   TheBill, therefore, enables  the Minister ;of Agriculture  to maintain and extend the valuable work which has been  done during  the last two  sessions in certain limited areas in regard to the cultivation of allotment gardens by the unemployed.  The &quot;Government realises that part  time work  of this nature is no cure for unemployment, but experience has shown that, to a man wholly or very largely unemployed, an  allotment garden can  be  of  immense benefit  in two  ways : (1) it can provide a  substantial increase  in  the food supply of himself and his family, and  (2)  it can give him a new interest as well as a healthy occupation.  Under this part of  the Bill, it will, generally speaking, be the  duty of  the local&apos;authority to provide land  for  cultivation by unemployed persons in their area  as  allotment gardens.   The Minister  has,  however,  asked
Parliament to give him direct power to acquire land for allotmentsin  cases where it  proved necessary  for the  Government itself toprovide land.  The Minister will also be empowered to  carry onthe excellent work done  by the Mansion House Fund in the pro-vision of seeds,  fertilizers,  and other requirements necessary toenable the allotment holder to  plant and cultivate his plot.  Thearrangements for the distribution of these requisites, as well asthe general  responsibility for  promoting the cultivation  of allot-ment gardens by the unemployed, has been  undertaken  on behalfof the Minister by a  strong and experienced Committee preside over  by Sir William Waterlow, Bart., K.B.B.,  the late lord mayor  of  London.  Local  authorities  have  also  been   asked  to mobilise to the utmost voluntary effort in each of  their areas soas to  ensure the  success of the  scheme.   The principal features ofthe Governments  proposals under  this  head were placed before a representative  meeting  of local authorities which was held atCaxton Hall, Westminster,  on  the  18th November, at which thePrime Minister,  as well  as the Minister of  Agriculture, outlined the Governments  proposals in regard to the cultivation of allot-ment  gardens by the  unemployed.   It is particularly satisfactory to observe  that, at this meeting, as also in Parliament and in thePress, these proposals have met with  hearty support   from all political  parties.  It is the intention of the  Government  to  develop  organizedmarketing  for home agriculture.  For this  purpose,  legislation hasbeen introduced to  facilitate the comprehensive organization of pro-ducers for the systematic  marketing of their supplies.  Apart fromfresh   legislation,   the    Government  has   actively   developedstandardization schemes for the sale of home products under theNational Mark and, as a  new departure in this field, has providedfunds to enable these standardized products  to be widely advertised.Special provision has  also been made to  enable  the subject  oforganized commodity marketing to be objectively studied at homeand abroad for  the  information and guidance of the home producer.  Closely associated with agriculture is the work of  land drainage.Large areas of  the  agricultural  land of the  country  are urgently in need of drainage, if the full production from the  soiL  is  to  beobtained.   The Act of this year provides for the establishment ofnew and comprehensive Drainage Authorities and gives them wide powers, inter alia, to execute land drainage schemes, many of whichshould be of very substantial proportions.  The Ministry of Agri-culture is proceeding with the constitution  of these Authorities as rapidly as possible, and when the necessary  transfer of powers tothem  from the  smaller existing  Authorities  has been made,  it maybe anticipated  that, with  the aid of Government grants  in manycases,  the  most important of the land drainage problems will be tackled in  such a manner that  not only will great  benefit be con-ferred on agriculturists, but a substantial contribution will be made
to the relief of unemployment.   Useful  work has been  done both for agriculture and for unemployment under the smaller  schemes which alone are practicable with the present Authorities and withthe present powers, but the effect of the Land Drainage Act shouldbe, in course of time, to confer a much wider benefit.  The Land  (Utilisation)  Bill  is  applicable to Scotland.   Thepowers and duties set forth in the Bill apply jointly  to the Depart-ment of Agriculture for Scotland and the Minister and the various branches of the work  proposed under the Bill will proceed  in Scot-land as in England with some modifications to meet varying con-ditions such as the different procedure in land settlement, etc.  The legislation which has been introduced for the  developmentof organized marketing of  home agricultural produce will  apply to scotland.  Active development  of  standardization  schemes  underthe National Mark  has been pursued in Scotland and the provisionof funds for advertising the standardized products applies  to Scot-land as well as toEngland.  A separate Land Drainage Act for Scotland was passed this year under which drainage works are now being scheduled and for which 100,000 has been provided to be spent over a period of  five years.farm  and field drainage works in Scotland, costing some  100,000and involving assistance from the State of   30,000 have   beena2iproved by the Department of Agriculture during the current year.  The provision for the purposes of Land Settlement in Scotland,which is  earned out  by   the  Department  of  Agriculture, was increased in the current financial year from  115,000 to  175,000.                          PART III.                 The Quality of the Population.  In the long run, nothing is more vital to the economic welfare ofany community than the quality of the human beings who composeit.  It would be  of  no avail to improve the technical equipment and business organization of British industry, if the capacity andphysique of the working population were to deteriorate meanwhile.A  regenerated industrial and economic  life can only be built onthe  foundation   of  a  strong,  healthy  and  intelligent  people.Measures taken to sustain or improve the quality of the populationmust,  therefore,  be  included in any survey of the Governmentslong-range economic policy.                          Education.  Some  of  the measures described  above, notably, for  example,Housing and Slum  Clearance,  are  directed primarily to  this
objective.   In the same connection may be mentioned the Educa-tion (School Attendance)  Bill which will  give completion  to  the educational reorganization now proceeding throughout the country,thus securing for all children between the ages of 11 and 15 a more adequate national system of education  and  providing  a  betterfoundation than has  existed heretofore  for technical  and furthertraining.  This  should make a real contribution to the economicefficiency of this country since there ai-e few generalizations betterattested by  experience than that the industrial pre-eminence of apeople is dependent, in the long run, on its educational standai&apos;ds.  There is,  moreover, another direct effect of the Bill to raise theschool age, which is the removal from the Labour market of 500,000children who most of them now compete for employment.  It isquite impossible to ascertain accurately  the economic  effect but itis obvious that many older children and adults must be employed inorder to replace the children so kept  in school.  It would  probablybe no exaggeration to say that 300,000 children between 14  and 15now obtain  work  and that  some 150,000 older people would take their place in employment as soon as they are kept in  school.                 Training for the  Unemployed.  More directly connected with unemployment are the various steps which  have  been taken by -the Ministry of Labour to prevent the deterioration of persons who become unemployed.   The centres for  training the  unemployed, both  men and women, have been extended and their scope lias been widened.  The training centres for  men now have an annual output of 8,500 and those for women of 4,400.   In addition, there are  centres where  men who have suffered from  prolonged  unemployment  can be put into  a better position both as. regards physique and general morale for getting a footing in industry; these can deal with 7,500 a year.  admission to centres of the latter type has so far been confined to men fromthe depressed mining  areas in recognition of the particular urgency of their needs.  Notwithstanding the contraction of industry duringthe present  slump, a  very high proportion of the men and women who have   passed  through these  centres  have  obtained  usefulemplo3&apos;ment.  Special attention has been given to the needs of unemployed boysand  girls.   The Unemployment  Insurance Act,  1930,  for the first time made it the duty of  the  Ministry  of Labour  to arrange with local Education Authorities for the provision of courses of instruc-tion for such of these  boys and girls  as are claimants to unemploy-ment benefit.   The Government has accepted and put into force the   recommendations on  this  point of the  National  advisory councils for Juvenile  Employment  and in  conjunction with LocalEducation Authorities has improved  the  machinery with a view to ensuring as far as possible that every boy and girl  who is out of
work and claiming benefit shall be able to receive suitable part-timeinstruction.   In the thickly populated areas separate courses of instruction,  known as  Junior Instruction Centres or  Classes,  are provided for  these unemployed boys and girls.  There are 107 ofthese  courses now open, and  about  65,000 boys and girls have attended them in  the last eight months.  In other areas arrange-ments have been made for the unemployed boys and girls (o attendexisting evening  classes; there are over 110 towns  and  villageswhere  this system is  now  in  operation,  and it is  being rapidlyextended.  It is one of the features of juvenile as of adult unemployment thatthere are large surpluses  in some areas and what  almost amounts toa deficiency in others. Steps have been taken to extend  and  improve the Ministry of Labour&apos;s machinery  for placing boys  and girls incarefully  selected  openings  under supervision  away  from their homes.                  The Employment Exchanges.  In other directions,  also, the machinery  of the Exchanges  hasbeen stimulated and improved.   In  spite of the depression in trade,there  has been  a  large increase in  the number of  placings  byExchanges.   For the year 1929 the  figure amounted to no less thana million and a half,  and the figure for 1930 will be larger still.The premises of Employment Exchanges had been allowed to fall into a condition  which  seriously hampered their usefulness.   Alarge  programme of reconstruction  and rehabilitation  has  been set in hand.  New efforts have been made to adapt Exchanges more closely to the requirements  of industry for example by the estab-lishment of  a specialist Exchange for hotel and catering employeesrun in co-operation with the trade.                     Unemployment  Relief.  The relief  provided by the Unemployment Insurance Scheme has gone  a long  way  to  avert the  widespread distress   and  physicaldeterioration which used to  be a feature of severe.trade depressions.The Acts have been amended so as to improve the scale of benefit for married claimants  and certain others.  Conditions for  the pay-ment of benefit,  which have been  found in practice to be inequit-able,  have been modified, and the administration improved so as tomake  the payment  of benefit  simpler  and  more prompt.    these changes have entailed a sensible relief to Poor Law  expenditure,particularly in the depressed areas.  The cost of the scheme, greatlyaccentuated  by the increase of unemployment arising from  thedepression of trade, has  inevitably  entailed  a heavy addition to theexpenditure both of the Unemployment Fund and of the Exchequer.General conditions such as now obtain were not even thought ofwhen the scheme of Unemployment Insurance was first formulated,and it  has now been  found necessary to have  a general  overhaul
 of  the  whole system.   The  Government  are  appointing  a Eoyal Commission with this purpose in view.  Heavy as is the  present load of expenditure,  it must be borne in mind  on  the other side of the account that  Great Britain  has been singularly free from rhe grosser forms of  destitution, as  compared with the experience of previous depressions  in this country or of the present depression in other countries  which are not equipped with similar arrangements for relieving unemployment.                         CONCLUSION.  The  broad results of the  various  measures  described  in  the previous sections  may be  summarized as follows :        1. A programme of  emergency works of public utility  has    been set on foot which will  provide employment  to  the extent    of more than  500,000 man years.  This is  a programme which    compares favourably with that which the  Government of  any    other  country has been able to frame to  mitigate the unem-    ployment resulting  from the world depression of trade.       2. Despite  the severity of the  trade  depression, the well-    being  of the population  has  been  maintained  in  a degree    which compares  favourably with the experience of any previous    depression.       3. A variety of steps have been  taken to improve technical    equipment,  to   increase  the efficiency  of   British  business    organization and to put British industry  in a  stronger position    for competing  in  world  markets; and  this  policy is being    actively continued.       4. The need for readjusting the balance  of  British economic    life to altered post-war conditions has been recognized by the    introduction of measures  designed  to restore  agriculture to a    more prosperous condition!  Conditions of  world  depression  provide a  discouraging  atmo-sphere for constructive  work,  and are  apt to  obscure recognitionof  the results  that  have been accomplished.  The ultimate  test of the value of the  work that has been done will be  the positionin  which  Great  Britain emerges from the world  depression ascompared  with  the  position  in  which  she entered into it.   Forthe reasons stated in the introductory  section,  it might have beenfeared that the  depression  would exert particularly  injurious con-sequences  on British economic life.  So  far, however,  the avail-able indications  suggest that Great  Britain has been less seriously affected than some  of her principal  competitors.  The Board ofTrade index of manufacturing  production for  the United  Kingdom,as estimated for  the third  quarter of 1930, shows a decrease of9.9  per cent., compared with the  third  quarter of  1929.  Theindex  prepared  by  the Institut  fur Konjunkturforschung  for
Germany (including  coal  mining) shows a decrease  of  20.4 percent,  on a  comparison of the  same  two periods;  and  the index of manufacturing production  compiled  by the  Federal  ReserveBoard  for the United States for ithe period June to August, 1930(September not  available), shows a  decrease of 23.5 per cent.,compared with the period June  to August, 1929.  As regards  the future, it is  already possible to  detect, both athome and  abroad,  a marked change  in the prevailing view withregard to the economic future of Great Britain.  A few years ago,although conditions seemed  on the surface more prosperous thanthey are to-day,  the view  was widespread abroad that Britain had entered on  a phase of industrial decline, and  was destined to loseground steadily  to other  countries.    To-day this view  is  beingreplaced by a growing sense  that Great Britain, despite her special difficulties,  is  weathering the  world  depression better  upon thewhole  than many of her principal rivals, and is likely  to emerge from  it in  a stronger relative position  than before.(8(88-82) Wt. 17774-12-16 la, la, 60,70 12/30  P. St. G. 304

</content>
</cab>
