<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/154/0 images: 102-112</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet. 1. \) *)SECRET.FOREIGN  COUNTRIES  REPORT.No. 10.   11 fch February 1920.contents.Afghanistan.- Afghan Officials for Persia.   The Amir and Bolshevik Activities in Turkestan.Arabia. ldrisi&apos;s Activities.   Dal a.Austria. The Western Counties of Hungary.The Baltic-Pettish Military Operations.    Great Britain, Latvia, and Soviet Russia. Belgium. Discontent in the Army.The Caucasus. The Turkish Pashas.   Azerbaijan and Armenia,   Northern Caucasia. The Kuban Government.China. The Position at Macao.   General Horvat and the Chinese Eastern Railway Area.   The Tibetan Question.Cuba. Measures against Strikers.Finland. Finland and the Diocese of Mohileff.   The Amnesty Bill.   The Aland Islands.Germany. The German Unitary State. Guatemala. The New Party.Hungary. Position of the Coalition Cabinet.   The Food Question.   The General Situation.   Preparations for Evacuation by Rumania.Italy. The Adriatic Question.Panama. President Porras.Persia.-Bolshevik Intentions.Poland. Soviet Peace Proposals.Russia. Siberia: Instructions to the Japanese   Expeditionary  Force.    American Troops and Railway Experts.Sweden. The Proposed Neutral Conference.Syria. The District North of Aleppo.Turkestan. -The Bolsheviks.   Afghan Activities.Turkey. General Franchet cVEsperey.   Smyrna.United States of America^ The Peace Treaty.   The Proposed Grant for Central Europe.
FOREIGN   COUNTRIES   REPORT.AFGHANISTAN.Afghan Officials for Persia. The Viceroy reported on 26th January [No. Ill S.J that he had received information from Meshed to the effect that the Governor-General of that place had received an application for facilities for the crossing of the frontier by Abdul Aziz, the Afghan Minister-Designate at Teheran, and Abdul Baki, the newly appointed Consul-General for Meshed [F.C.R. ix., p. 2J, both of whom had reached Herat.   The Governor-General of Meshed had asked his Government for instructions.The Amir and Bolshevik Activities in Turkestan. The Viceroy telegraphed on 28th January that it had been reported from Kabul that the Amir was becoming alarmed at the Bolshevik activities in Turkestan.   [See page 10.]ARABIA.IdrisVs Activities. -On 25th Januaiy the Resident at Aden transmitted [No. 291 A.P.] a telegram sent from iiodeidah by Major Meek to report that on 11th Januaiy, amid popular rejoicings, Bajil had been entered by Iclrisi&apos;s force. His orders had too been promulgated in Marawa, and his men posted in Quhra and the Aboos territory on the lmam&apos;s border. The Resident added that, though provocative, this action did not appear to be contrary to Idrisi&apos;s undertakings.Doha. On 24th January the Resident at Aden telegraphed [No. 289 A.P.] that it was reported that Dala had been occupied by its Emir, who, however, had been again driven out by the Zaidis.AUSTRIA.The Western Counties of Hungary. Mr. Hohler telegraphed from Budapest on 26th January [No. 45] as follows : This morning Admiral Horthy expressed to me the earnest hope that no steps would be taken by German Austria to take possession of the western counties which are to be ceded under the Peace Treaty until the Treaty is in force and due notice has been given. He also stated that both [? the Hungarian] Government and the population concerned were much disturbed hy rumours which were current, and which were confirmed by [? the late] representative at Vienna, that negotiations were on foot for the cession of this territory to Gzecho-Slovakia.This was repeated to Vienna, and on 30th January Mr. Lindley reported [No. 47] that the State Chancellor had that day informed him that he took his stand on the Treaty of Versailles and had full confidence that the Powers would see that Austria secured Western Hungary. He had no intention of trying to take the district by force, but thought that the Hungarian troops should be withdrawn and replaced by Austrians as soon as Hungary had signed peace. There were signs that the Hungarians intended to strip the place before evacuating it, and he thought the Powers should prevent this.The State Chancellor again denied that there was any idea of ceding Western-Hungary to the Czecho-Slovak Government or of invoking their aid to acquire it by force.THE BALTIC.Lettish Military Operations. On 6th February Mr. Dewhurst reported [No. 28] from Riga that he had been informed bv the Lettish Minister for Foreign Affairs that their army would advance no further and, unless attacked, would cease operations as Latgallen had been cleared of Bolshevik troops. Telegraphing again on 9th February [No. 36], he reported that an armistice had been concluded, the Letts agreeing not to advance beyond the boundary line of Latgallen and the Soviet that that line shall not be attacked.Great Britain, Latvia, and Soviet Russia. On 9th February Lord Curzon tele-graphed [No. 34] to Mr. Dewhurst telling him that the representative of Latvia in
London had been informed that full liberty would be left to his Government in regard to concluding an armistice with Soviet Russia, the attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Gevern-ment having undergone no change in that respect.BELGIUM.Discontent in the Army. Sir Francis Villiers reported on 2nd February [No. 17] the existence of discontent in the Belgian Army, and said that it had been brought about chiefly by the recent legislation enabling married men with one child or more to do military service for four months only, instead of the twelve exacted from others. The inferior qualify of the rations was a further cause of discontent,THE CAUCASUS.The Turkish Pashas [F.C.R. ix., p. 11].-On 29th January&apos; [No. 53] Lord Curzon instructed Mr. Wardrop to inform the Prime Minister of Azerbaijan that the presence of Khalil Pasha, Nuri Pasha, and Talaat Kutchuk was viewed with misgiving by His Majesty&apos;s Government, as tending to corroborate reports that continued to reach them to the effect that an influential party in Azerbaijan was intriguing with the Turkish Nationalists. It appeared that a report was even current in Constantinople that an understanding on pan-Islamic lines had been reached.These persistent reports must, as he would readily appreciate, have a most unfortunate effect after the recent de facto recognition of the Republic by His Majesty&apos;s Government, and could only prejudice future confidence in the Republic.Mr. Wardrop should therefore urge upon him the arrest or expulsion of Khalil, Nuri, and Talaat, and a denial both at Baku, and, through Veziroff, at Constantinople, of the rumours of a secret agreement between Azerbaijan and either the Turkish Government or the Nationalists, unless he should consider that there were serious objections to this course, in which case he f-drould communicate them by telegraph before taking any action.In regard to this telegram, on 5th February Mr. Warclrop transmitted [No. 78] a message from Colonel Stokes. The latter said that he was of opinion that the moment was inopportune to demand the removal of the three Pashas as the Govern-ment was already threatened with a serious Cabinet crisis and its position would be imperilled. When we had given a visible proof of our assistance in the shape of uniforms and equipment we mi-glit demand the removal not only of the Pashas, but of all Turkish officers and officials who, in his opinion, constituted a more serious dano;er.Azerbaijan and Armenia. Telegraphing from Tiflis on 25th January [No. 50], Mr. Grundy transmitted a message sent by Mr. Wardrop on the previous day from Baku. The latter reported that he had been informed by the Azerbaijan Govern-ment that the Armenians had been guilty of great massacres and of the destruction of 21 Aullages, in consequence of which there was considerable agitation in Azerbaijan, the Government being accused of inaction at the bidding of the Allies. Mr. Wardrop added that he had demanded that the attacks should cease and the troops be with-drawn, and had informed the Armenian Prime Minister, to whom he had telegraphed, that if his demand were not complied with he should recommend His Majesty&apos;s Government not to grant any aid to Armenia.In reply to this, on 29th January [No. 54] Lord Curzon informed Mr. \\ ardrop that his action was apjn-ovecl, and went on to say: You should carefully investigate the accusations of the Azerbaijan Government, and. if you find the facts to be as stated, you should address a strong reprimand to the Armenian Government and demand the immediate cessation of the attacks. You should emphasize the deplorable effect of these reports both on His Majesty&apos;s Government and on British public opinion, whose sympathies will be alienated by their continuance. Such attacks are peculiarly ill-timed, following, as they do, immediately upon the recognition of Armenian independence and pending the delimitation of the boundaries of Armenia,xou  should  also   inform  the Azerbaijan Government  that  you   have   been-instructed by His Majesty&apos;s Government to address a strong protest to the Armenian Government.
Northern Caucasia. On 28th January Mr. Grundy, telegraphing from Tiflis, reported [No. 54] that information had been received from Baku that the Mountaineer-National Council of Defence would expel the Turks and Bolsheviks if they received a promise of independence together with help in medical stores, guns, and rifle ammunition, and a further one that the Volunteer Army should be withdrawn. The local Shaykh-ul-Islam was the President of the Council, whilst Mr. Chermoev, an oilfield owner, represented it in Paris, and could give the necessary information and assurance. Mr.- Grandy added: that Mr. Kantemir, the Vice-President of the Council, did not inspire confidence : he was working with Nuri Pasha.On 5th February Mr. Wardrop transmitted [No. 80] a message from Colonel Stokes in regard to the decision, not to assist the North Caucasian Republic at the present moment. This decision, Colonel Stokes said, was tantamount to a declaration that the spread of Bolshevism to that region was regarded with indifference by His Majesty&apos;s Government. Daghestan was the key to the Caucasus, and the control of Daghestan meant the control of the Caucasus ; and, should we not support them, the mountaineers would be obliged to accept Bolshevism. This was no side issue, but an integral part of the Caucasus problem ; and at this moment the control of Daghestan could be got more cheapby and more easily than probably ever again.The Kuban - Government. Telegraphing from Novorossisk on 28th January [No. 10], General Keyes reported that the constitution which had been abolished by the coup (Tel a I, in November had been restored by the provincial Rada, and. that a legislative Rada was being elected.The South-Eastern Confederacy had practically been revived as. the Kuban, Don, and Terek administrations had, for the purpose of co-ordinating the policy and administration of those three territories, formed a supreme Krug with power to admit other territories into the group ; negotiations had already been begun by agents from Georgia and Azerbaijan, but it was not yet sure that they held a mandate.A stirring appeal had been made to the Cossacks by the Kuban Government, and the members of that Government have now to see things through, for should the Bolsheviks take their territory they would certainly be the first victims. They were inviting General Denikin to become Commander-in-Chief of an independent Cossack army which was in course of - formation, with, however, the proviso that he should dispense with the services of certain of his staff officers. If General Denikin accepted, the Kuban Cossacks, who were much more stable ^than those of the Don, would probably respond to the call; but the General might refuse to dismiss officers who had been through so much with him, for he was loyal to a fault.CHINA.The Position at Macao [F.C.R, ix, p. 1]. On 25th January Sir Lancelot Carnegie reported from Lisbon [No. 9] that he had been informed by the Minister for Foreign Affairs that instructions had been sent to the Governor of Macao to undertake no works outside the interior port, The Portuguese Government, the Minister had added, would respect what had been prescribed by the Treaty of 1887, but they could not admit that China was &apos; in a position to forbid works in the zone under their jurisdiction.On 28th January Mr. Jamieson reported [No. 1] that on his suggestion work had been suspended four days earlier. On the previous clay delegates from Macao had had a long conference with the Foreign Secretary of the Southern Government, and had put forward certain proposals, which had been met by counter-proposals. There was but little common ground : both sides, however, were referring the proposals to their respective Governments. The situation, Mr. Jamieson added, was gravely complicated by the fact that the Southern Government could &quot;exercise but little, if any, control over the Military Governor, who was ignorant in the extreme, and obstinate ; he, moreover, professed a contempt for international law and its obligations, and might therefore, at any moment, create a serious situation.On 27th January Sir John Jordan reported from Peking [No. 44] that he had had an interview with the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs, who had contended that the work being clone at Macao was a violation of the arrangement reached at Hong Kong in 1909. He disclaimed all responsibility for the action of the Southern Government, and affirmed that the Central Government was helpless ; he consented, however, to telegraph advice to the Canton authorities to assume a non-aggressive
o-attitude. He also said that in view of the relations between North and South, settlement hy arbitration and delimitation of boundaries were alike impossible.General Horvat and the Chinese Eastern Railway Area. On 28th January Sir. -John Jordan reported [No. 47] that on 17th January General Horvat had announced his assumption of full administrative powers over. Russians in the Chinese Eastern Railway area, and that Wai-chai-pu had addressed to him (Sir J. Jordan) what appeared to be an identic note officially refusing to recognize this action on the following grounds : (I) The Chinese Eastern Railway area was on Chinese territory, and China alonehad powers of government therein. (2) General Horvat&apos;s duties being connected with the management of the railway,he was not empowered to assume administrative functions. (3) According to the railway agreement, &quot;China was responsible for the protection of both Chinese and foreigners m the railway area.The Tibetan Question. Sir J. Jordan telegraphed [No. 60] on 5th February that he had received a report that 1,200 Chinese troops were moving from Sining [in the province of Kansu] to assist the Mohammedan authorities there in carrying out an expedition into Tibetan territory. Our representative who made the report thought the move would probably be in the nature of an irresponsible raid on the part of the Kansu Mohammedans, but that the discovery of their intentions might end the project. Sir J. Jordan pointed out to the Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs the gravity of the situation which would arise if the report were true, in view of the. assurance given by the Chinese Government regarding abstention from all hostile action by the Kansu authorities pending negotiations respecting Tibet, The Acting Minister assured Sir J. Jordan that he had no knowledge of the matter, and that the Chinese Government had issued no orders for such a move. He thought it improbable that the Kansu frontier authorities contemplated anything more than measures of defence if they had made any dispositions of troops on the border.   -The Acting Minister promised a reply in a few days&apos; time to Sir John Jordaifs-memorandum inviting China to negotiate at Lhassa.CUBA.Measures against Strikers. On 3rd February, Mr, Erskine reported [No. 16] that energetic measures were at last being taken against the strikers : many labour-leaders had been arrested, and the constitutional guarantees had been suspended.FINLAND.Finland and the Diocese of Mohileff. On 26th January, Sir Horace Rumbold. telegraphed from Warsaw as follows : The papal Nuncio infcrms a member of my staff that, while it has undoubtedly been decided to detach Finland from the diocese of Mohileff, he does not imagine that in view of the small number of Finnish Roman Catholics, it will be considered desirable to give episcopal rank to the head of what will in all probability be a vicariate-apostolic. Asked whether there was any likelihood that the Poles might object to the detachment of Finland from the diocese of Mohileff, Monsignor Ral.tr said that the Poles had no locus stanch in the matter, and that the Vatican would not, he imagined, pay much heed to any protests which they might make. He did not admit that he knew of any agitation in this sense by official Polish circles, either lay or clerical ; but he said that certain Poles, particularly a Countess Plater, had, as private individuals, clone much for the Roman Catholic Church in Finland, and he implied that these.persons might be trying to exercise a predominant influence over the Church which they had done so much to foster. As regards the future vicar, the-Nuncio professed eutire ignorance whether any choice had as yet been made. He said that it would be more in accordance with the usual procedure in the case of. countries with a very small Roman Catholic population if the vicar were chosen not from the few native secular priests, but from one of the religious orders. The religious orders were largely occupied with missionary work, and it was not. so difficult to find, among their members persons with the requisite knowledge of obscure languages. In such an event the vicar would presumably establish in Finland a house of the order to which he belonged.
The Amnesty Bill. On 27th January Lord Acton reported [No. 117] from Helsingfors that the Presidents decision in regard to the signature of the Amnesty Bill was viewed with profound&apos; apprehension hy both parties, and that the General Staff were convinced that the passage of the Bill would result in civil war. The pro-Mannerheim party, who opposed the Bill, laid the blame on the British Government owing to their creation of the Murman Legion, the repatriation of that Legion to Finland, and their intervention with a view to the lenient treatment of offenders. Consequently it was expected that demonstrations would take place against the British officials at Helsingfors, either in the form of a general Press attack or of something graver.The Aland Islands. Telegraphing on 31st January [No.134], Lord Acton reported that the measure for the autonomy of the Aland Islands had been approved by the President in the Council of State in its draft form, and would now come before Parliament, which met on 2nd February.The Finnish Government had, at their request, been furnished with particulars of the constitution of the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man for their guidance in this matter.GERMANY.The German Unitary State [F.C.R., viii., p. 5]. A wireless message from Norddeich, dated 1th February, states that the agitation by the leader of the Catholic Bavarian peasants, Heim, against the unitary programme of the Berlin Government is still going on. Heim delivered yesterday at Munich a speech, giving the strongest expression to his dislike of Berlin, and giving the movement an outspoken anti-Semitic character. The union, proposed by the Catholic Peasants&apos; Association and the Peasant?&apos; Alliance, was unanimously voted in a joint meeting, which strongly opposed Socialism, demanding opportunities for the establishment of new farms, if necessary by dividing large estates.GUATEMALA.The New Party [F.C.R., ix., p. 6].---On 30th January Mr. Armstrong reported [No. 10] that it was not expected that the President would yield without a fight to the new party, which was gaining ground peacefully and rapidly. Should an outbreak take place, British lives and property would be endangered as the military leaders would be unable to restrain the soldiery. The 10,000 troops in the city were regarded as a menace by everyone ; they were mostly Indians and were well armed.HUNGARY.Position of the Coalition Cabinet. On 31st January Mr. Hohler reported from Budapest that Friedrich was claiming that, the elections having taken place, the mandate of the Coalition Cabinet formed by Sir G. Clerk had terminated and that the Christian National Union should at once form a Government. Huszar, on the other hand, held that the present Government should remain in power until the House met and appointed a head of the State, who would send for a leader of the majority party to form a Cabinet. Admiral Horthy had published a declaration supporting the latter -view, which, in his (Mr. HohleFs) opinion, was undoubtedly the correct one.The Food Question. On 27th January Mr. Hohler telegraphed [No. 16] saying: The Minister of Finance and Admiral Horthy told me to-day that while they considered their people inoculated in some respects against Bolshevism by what they Irad suffered from it, they could not answer for what might happen owing to the continued and increasing lack of food.Admiral Troubridge informs me that the normal reserve of food at this time of year should be about 700,000 tons, but that at present it is nil.It would appear advisable to apply some of the means which are being adopted to remedy the situation in Aienna to prevent a similar one arising here.Telegraphing again on 30th January [No. 54-j, he said :  It is impossible to contemplate without indignation the sufferings of the population, and especially of the children here, due simply to the illegal and inhumane
refusal of our Allies, on the most frivolous pretexts, to allow food and fuel to be imported. Even in Constantinople the first care of His Majesty&apos;s Government was to provide for the re-victualling of the town, and there would not seem to be any good reason for treating Hungarians with greater severity than Turks.I am assured by the inter-allied Military Mission that the idea of an attack by this country on its neighbours is at the present time, and under the present circumstances, quite out of the question.At the present moment, the amount of flour in official hands amounts to 50 tons. There is no movement from Serbia, and nothing is coming in from the Hungarian territory in Rumanian occupation.I regret to be so insistent, but my- idea merely is to anticipate a catastrophe.The General Situation. -On 6th February Mr. Bolder reported [No. 76] : -I have been in constant contact with members of the inter-allied Military Mission, who are the persons best fitted to judge impartially of the situation here, and I have lost no opportunity for coming into contact with every shade of opinion, but especially with foreigners.The Generals are uuitecl in complaining most bitterly that their protests, recom-niendations and requests for instructions are alike ignored by the Supreme Council, whose representatives they are, and they feel their position very keenly. The French member, who is a full General, feels it so acutely that he is unwilling to send any further written communications to our Allies the Serbians, Rumanians and Czechs.All these, their Allies, obstinately refuse to obey any of the orders of the Supreme Council whether as regards evacuation, sending of food, proper treatment of occupied territory or any other matter.In the short time I have been here I have much regretted to be obliged to give very complete instances of this statement, One result is that by defiance, with impunity, of the 1 gss6t A Hies to the commands of the Supreme Council, the full weakness of the Allies is brought into prominent notice. It is even currently stated that the pressure on Rumania to withdraw to the treaty frontiers is not serious, with the intention that their troops may push on to Budapest, should Hungary refuse to sign the peace conditions. I have good reason to think that the Hungarians are ready to sign any terms as regards frontiers, as they are convinced that the very forces of nature will, within a measurable time, restore them to their natural and historic limits ; but presumably the question is that of food which, contrary to justice, to contractual engagements and payments made, is being withheld. \I wish to state as/proofs at the present moment that I myself am unable to obtain Hour, and that somejsggs, &amp;c, sent to the French General for his personal consumption are held up by Serbia. The absolute lack of food already reported to you is again affirmed to me to-day by the local representative of the Supreme Economic Council.These, after all, are minor matters. I have not the least anxiety that the French General and myself will not obtain some food, but the question over which [ find all the representatives of the great Allies united is the future tendency of Hungary. The papers to be signed at the Conference, as at present drafted, may whittle their kingdom down as much as they like, but 1 find the opinion universal that the old limits wil! reassert themselves. As to Czecho-Slovakia, it has been observed to me that, whilst the Hunsarians had been unable to make themselves beloved in a thousand years, the Czechs had made them so in one. Account does not seem to have been taken of the satisfaction of Hungarians on being at last entirely free and independent of Austria .... My colleagues are united in thinking that the Hungarian nation is by far the most solid and reliable that exists in South Eastern Europe ; at the outset they welcomed the Allies as delivering them from German-Austrians; they were sadly disappointed at the course of events which led to-Bolshevik and Rumanian ascendency ; and now they are at the parting of the ways.The conduct of their neighbours in face of the sternest orders of the Supreme Council shows abundantly that engagements are not to be regarded too seriously. But what policy are they really to follow? With anything like reasonable treatment they will be glacl to follow our guidance, and to help in forming a chain round Germany of! Baltic States, Poland, and Jugo-Slavia, Otherwise the strongest link may be lacking. I can see no greater interest for His Majesty&apos;s Government at present on South Eastern Europe than the preservation of order and the limitation of German influence. It appears hard to see where these all are more immediately involved than in Hungary.
These views are shared by local American, French, and Italian representatives whether military or civil, who think the matter one of extreme urgency, if indeed&apos; /things have not already gone too far to be remedied.Preparations for  Evacuation by   Rumania..  On   9th February   Mr. Hohler reported [No. 86] that about 3,000 Hungarian troops had been despatched towards the Theiss in order to maintain order when the Rumanian troops evacuated.    Of course they would not attempt to cross the river without the authorization of the inter-allied Military Mission which was supervising their movements.ITALY.The Adriatic Question. On Sth February Sir George Buchanan reported [No. 56] that the President of the Council in winding up the debate in the Chamber on foreign affairs had made an important statement with regard to the policy of the Italian Government.In contrasting the terms of the Treaty of London and the proposed compromise, he said that the latter provided that the corpus separatum of Fiume should constitute a sovereign State in direct communication with Italy, without mentioning that it should be under the League of Nations.He fully emphasized the necessity for evacuating Fiume if the Treaty of London had to be applied, and condemned the want of discipline in the Army and the Press attacks on the Allies and J ugo-Slays. He denied that the latter had mobilized three classes, and declared that he wholeheartedly desired closer relations with them.The President of the Council then drew attention to the general situation in Europe, urged generous treatment of the enemy, and hoped that relations with Russia would be soon re-established.   The speech was well received.PANAMA.President Porras. On 27th January Mr. Bennett reported [No. 4] that in accordance with the provisions of the Panama Constitution, which required that a President who had been called to office through a chance vacancy and who intended to stand for election should retire from such office six months before the elections were held, President Porras had tendered his resignation to the National Assembly to take effect from the end of January and would be the presidential candidate at the election to be held in August next when serious opposition was not to be anticipated.During the interregnum the chief executive power would be vested in Ernesto Lefevre, the only surviving Yice-President, Minister for Foreign Affairs in the present Cabinet.PERSIA.Bolshevik Intentions. The Viceroy of India telegraphed [No. 1182] on 28th January that all the reports that he received agreed as to the intentions of the Bolsheviks to attempt an invasion of Persia and eject the British. Personally the Viceroy was of opinion that the Bolsheviks would make no serious move so long as they thought there were possibilities of coming to terms with us. He attributed the above reports to the entourage of the Turkestan Commission who had just visited Merv and Askabacl, who spread them with the idea of making us nervous, and he--thought that for the present they should be treated with reserve.POLAND.Soviet Peace Proposals. Telegraphing [No. 70] from WarsaAV on 30th January, &apos;.Sir H. Rumbold reported that the Director of the Political Department, who is in charge of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs there, had just read to him another radio telegram received the day before from the Soviet Government proposing peace. The telegram was signed by Lenin, Trotsky and Chicherin, and was much more definite. Some of the passages were missing, but it was hoped to reconstruct the telegram.The telegram began with a preamble stating that Poland was confronted by a decision which might have far-reaching effects on the fortunes of the two countries. She should not listen to Imperialists of the school of Clemenceau or Churchill, but should follow the dictates of humanity. The Soviet Government stated that they were fully prepared to recognize the independence of the Republic of Poland, which
independence they had acknowledged almost from the first, on the basis of self-determination of peoples. The telegram went on to enumerate two points on the White Ruthenian front, i.e., Drysa and Risua, beyond which troops of the Red Arniy would not advance. At this point there was a passage missing from the telegram, and the Political Director supposed that the Soviet Government proceeded to define the remainder of the line beyond which their troops would not advance. He inferred from elsewhere that the Bolsheviks would be prepared to take the present line occupied by the Polish troops as a basis for negotiation in settling the eastern frontier of Poland. He said that this offer was a serious oue, but that the Polish Government wished to await the return of M. Patek, who was expected on 1st February, before dealing with it.Tlie Political Director, who had evidently not heard, the result of the conversa-tion between the Prime Minister and M. Patek, went on to say that the Polish Government would wish to consider the Bolshevik offer in consultation with the Allies. Sir Horace then spoke to him in the sense of the language used by the Prime Minister to M. Patek. :Sir H. Rumbold inferred that this latest Bolshevik peace offer, coming at a moment when the Bolsheviks had triumphed over the anti-Bolshevik forces, and when the raising of the blockade was apparently claimed as a moral success for them, i.e., at a moment when their prospects were outwardly bright, indicated that they were apprehensive of the internal situation in Russia itself, and that if they succeeded in making peace with a State like Poland, Soviet Russia would have accomplished the first step towards admittance into the family of Nations.Sir H. Rnmbold followed this with a telegram [No. 87] on 2nd February, stating that the Director of the Political Department had informed him that the Polish Government had resolved to send to the Soviet Government an interim reply acknowledging the receipt of the Soviet peace proposals which were under consideration.A wireless message from Moscow, just received at Warsaw, indicated that the Soviet Government proposed that their troops should not advance beyond the line on which they stood at that time.RUSSIA.Siberia.Instructions to the Japanese Expeditionary Force. On 23rd January Mr. Alston transmitted [No. ? 83] the following message from the Military Attache : The following telegraphic instructions have been sent to the Commander-in-Chief of the Japanese Expeditionary Force in Siberia and have been communicated to the Allied Military Attaches : When our troops were originally despatched to Siberia we declared that our main object in doing so was to render assistance to the Czech forces. That object remains unchanged. Consequently our troops must make every endeavour to facilitate the repatriation of the Czechs. In the event of any attempt being-made to hinder their movements, even if such opposition comes from Russian or Seminoff forces, it must be suppressed by the Japanese Army with all its power.The Japanese Minister of War is anxious that the above instructions should be generally known in order to avoid the possibility of misunderstandings such as have occurred between the Japanese, the Czechs and General Seminoff.American Troops and Railway Experts. Telegraphing from Washington on 5th. February [No. 104] Mr. Lindsay reported that the State Department had sent him a copy of a memorandum they had addressed to the Japanese Embassy in reply to a memorandum on the subject of the withdrawal of the United States troops and railway experts from Siberia.The memorandum stated that the United States Government, would place no obstacle in the way of any decision which might be reached by Japan to Continue single-handed the stationing of her troops in Siberia and the despatch of reinforcements.The United States Government desired to record an assurance of their confidence that the Japanese Government would pursue the same policy that was mutually agreed on when the Governments determined to co-operate in Siberia, particularly in connexion with the Siberian railway system (including the Chinese Eastern Railway), the existing rights to which the United States Government confidently assumed would 10-2 B
in no way be impaired in consequence of the efforts of the. Japanese Government to cany out the purposes which induced the two Governments to send their military forces to Siberia.SWEDEN.The Proposed Neutral Conference. Mr. Barclay telegraphed [No. 39] from Stockholm on 8th February that he bad been told that day by. the Minister for Foreign Affairs that the Swedish Government had accepted the invitation of the Netherlands Government to attend the Conference of Neutrals at The Hague, to discuss the question of protecting neutral interests in the organization of an International Court of Justice to be established under the League of Nations. The Minister said that Scandinavian countries had much hesitated before doing so, as they had already submitted their observations to the Secretary of the League of Nations, but they finally gave way before the insistence of the Netherlands Government.Baron Marx von Wurtenberg would be one of the Swedish representatives, the other had not yet been selected.SYRIA.The District North of Aleppo. Telegraphing from Constantinople on 4th February [No. 102], Admiral de Robeck reported that he had been informed by his French colleague of the receipt of a telegram from General Gouraud in regard to the situation in the area north of Aleppo, the General saying there was, in fact, a state of hostilities between the Turkish forces and his own, andjthat he viewed the situation with grave concern. His French colleague was making representations to the Turkish Government on the subject of the Turkish hostile movements, and he contemplated making representations in his support.TURKESTAN.The Bolsheviks. On 31st January the Viceroy of India transmitted [1306/M./ 20/1/T.] a report from our Agent in Merv that branches of the Bolshevik Committee were being established in Askabad, Merv and elsewhere. The Committee claimed to have a branch already working in Kuchan, and that others were being formed in Persia. Persians, by means of inflammatory notices, were being called upon to rise in arms, not only against their own corrupt Government, but against the British troops who supported them. The Agent reported great resentment, in Bolshevik and Afghan circles against the propaganda which had considerably reduced- the value of rouble notes.Afghan Activities- A telegram from General Malleson was transmitted [No. 14.42] by the Viceroy on 3rd February, in which the former states that he had invited the views of the Amir of Bokhara on Afghan activities in Turkestan, and asked whether they were approved by him. The Amir had replied by letter that the view of his Government was that the Afghans had come to Bokhara and Turkestan for the1 sole purpose of establishing relations with Bokhara, and of bringing Turkestan Mohammedans together, with the object of taking action against the Bolsheviks when the time came.General Malleson interpreted this as some sort of insurance agreement between Afghanistan and Bokhara in case the Bolsheviks should play either of them false. In his opinion, the Amir would not encourage Afghanistan in any distinctly anti-British design, but was chiefly occupied in the preservation of the integrity of his own dominions, with an eye to the restitution of territory annexed by Russia, and the possibility of complete independence to follow.TURKEY.General Franchet d&apos;Espercy. On 29th Januaiy, General Milne sent a long telegram [G.C. 42] in regard to the attitude of General Franchet d&apos;Esperey, and the dangerous situation created by him To relieve the situation General Milne saw three possible alternatives, and three only : to withdraw all British troops from General Franchet d&apos;Esperey&apos;s command ; to recall General Wilson and himself; to insist on the recall of&apos;the French General who had now nothing to do but to interfere.Smyrna,. Telegraphing from Constantinople on 8th February [Nos. 113 and 111], Admiral de Robeck reported that his representative at Smyrna had forwarded the-
-correspondence about port control, including the letter of ISth January, in which the-Greek High Commissioner definitely claimed that the Allied High Commissioners should await the decision of the Supreme Council regarding the port control.The position, he continued, was unsatisfactory as the control was not functioning. This in appearance meant that the Greek High Commissioner^ point 0f view had prevailed, though the actual reason for the delay in starting was the non-arrival of the British and French officers.Meanwhile the French High Commissioner had received a telegram from his Government, based on the complaints made by M. Venezelos. Instructed to suspend the execution of the decision to establish control, they hesitated to bring the matter to a head by sending their officers, pending the rejoinder to the reply which he bad sent to ParisThe matter was discussed by the Allied High Commissioners at their last meeting, and it was decided to address to their Governments the following identic telegram :  The attitude adopted by the Greek High Commissioner at Smyrna in the matter of inter-allied port control raises a Question demanding immediate solution. This solution is more necessaiy since the control, although approved by the High Commissioners and elaborated by the Allied Admirals, has not yet come into force. This situation lends itself to the interpretation that the Greek High Commissioner is able to postpone execution of decisions taken by the Allied High Commissioners pending instructions from his own superior authorities.The Allied High Commissioners have up till now followed the principle that they exercise the same authority at Smyrna as elsewhere in Turkey. In admitting the attitude adopted by the Greek High Commissioner in the question of port control they would be admitting that the zone of occupation constituted an exception to this principle.The logical consequence for the Allied High Commissioners would be to abandon responsibility for the zone of occupation. We request our Governments to give us precise instructions as to the course to be followed, with the minimum possible delay.UNITED STATES  OF AMERICA.The Peace Treaty. On 8th February Mr. Lindsay telegraphed [No. 110] saying that, it was clear that the only person who could now prevent the treaty being ratified was Mr. Wilson, and that a letter from him, which had been published that morning, seemed to have been written with that object in view. Even irreconcilable opponents of tire treaty had been weakening and inclining to accept Mr. Loclge&apos;s reservations if slightly toned down, whilst Mr. Lodge himself was prepared to tone clown any of them with the exception of the one relating to Article 10. In regard to this, however, the President was equally uncompromising, and there was now unfortunately a likelihood of the Democratic leader throwing him over and preventing ratification by a disruption of the party.The proposed Grant for Central Europe. On 3rd February Mr. Lindsay reported from AVashingtoii [No. 95] that the prospects with regard to a grant of relief for Central Europe had become a good deal worse. The Committee had heard the evidence of General Bliss who presented the question mainly as a means of assisting Poland to maintain her armies and combat the Bolsheviks ; and as the only chance was to have the proposals regarded as pure relief of distress, and as Poland is considered in Congress to have imperialistic tendencies, the GeneraPs evidence was disastrous. The Committee had [? approved] the proposal to grant $50,000,000, but there was no disguising the fact that even this would not be obtained without a severe light in the House. Against the proposal were the views indicated above and all tendencies towards retrenchment and towards withdrawing from European compli-cations. In favour of it was the fact that some very influential republicans were committed to helping, so that the fight would not be entirely on party lines.Mr. Lindsay thought that the chances were in favour of a S50,000,000 grant being made, but against any increase now or in the future ; and added that the best chance of improving matters would be for His Majesty&apos;s Government and other Governments to give a lead by stating what they would contribute, attaching as few conditions as possible to their participation. If these contributions appeared generous they might affect the situation here, but he would not guarantee that they would absolutely ensure anything.

</content>
</cab>
