<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/154/0 images: 322-333</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.SECRET.foreign  countries  report.No. 29.   3rd November 1920.-Contents.Afghanistan.--Internal Affairs.Arabia. King Hussein and Idrisi.   The Hejaz Delegation.    The Ikhwan.    Emir Abdulla. -Austria. The Plebiscite. .Baltic. States.-Lithuania and Vilna.   New Esthonian Government.The Caucasus. Complaint against General Wrangel.Dantzig. Signature of the Act establishing the Free City.Germany. The Geneva Conference.Greece. Message of Sympathy.Hungary. Extension of Time for the Ratification of the Treaty. Mexico. Recognition of Mexico by the United States Government. Persia.-Government Budget.Poland. Vilna.   Ratification of the Russian Peace Preliminaries.   Relations with Latvia.Rumania.: Persecution of Hungarians.   Bessarabia. Russia. Exchange of Prisoners.   Soviet Submarines. Serbia. The Russian Refugees. Sweden. New Cabinet.Turkey. New Cabinet.   Tewfik Pasha and the Financial Situation.   Ratification of the Treaty demanded.SO   22-1      120   11.20A
FOREIGN  COUNTRIES   REPORT.:   AFGHANISTAN.Internal Affairs. On 20tli October the Viceroy of India reported (a) increased recruiting activity, and the collection of transport animals in Kabul; (6) the departure of Jemal Pasha and his . party from Herat for Kabul on 4th October, the party including Bedrie Bey, one-time Turkish Minister of Commerce ; (c) that Abdus Hadi, Assistant Foreign Minister, was said to have left Kabul on an unknown mission and. to have been replaced by Mirza Ghulam Ply der, formerly Afghan postmaster at Peshawar.ARABIA.King Hussein and Idrisi [F.C.R., xxviii, p. 2]. Telegraphing on 22rudOctober, the Resident at Aden reported [No. 300 A.l\j the receipt of a letter from Captain Fazluddin relating the events which had preceded King Hussehfs letter to Idrisi. Saved Senoussi, the bearer thereof, had spent, he said, 40 days in Mecca, during the course of which he had had five interviews with King Hussein and the Emir Abdulla. They repeatedly asked him to act as intermediary between them and Idrisi, and at length he agreed to do so. King Hussein stated that he was willing to surrender to Idrisi the whole coast line of Asir, and hoped that he would come to an agreement with the Imam in regard to their boundary. The King also suggested a triple alliance between himself, Idrisi, and the Imam, and said: &quot; What a blessing it would be for all of us Arabs if we, the Arab chiefs, came to a mutual settlement acceptable to all. Our union will prevent strangers entering our land.&quot;The Hejaz Delegation.   On 31st October Mr. Scott transmitted [No. 1045] the following message from Jeddah : -Feisal and Lotfallah have asked King Hussein as to the headship of the delegation.. King Hussein explained that as it was appointed before the Syrian crisis and the decision of Feisal to proceed to Europe, Lotfallah had been appointed.Later Feisal decided to visit London, so he notified the Foreign Office that Feisal would be head ; Lotfallah. however, retains the position until the actual arrival of the formerKing Hussein referred to (? the importance of the) second duty of the delegation, which is to obtain the views of His j\!ajesty&apos;s Government as regards the mutual agreements.As to the second part of the message, he says that it seems that Great Britain has done with him, as it would be simpler to receive the delegation than to cause doubt as to the intentions of His Majesty&apos;s Government, and the Foreign Office notification is only a convenient excuse. If it were not for his fidelity he would have recalled the delegation.Although King Hussein mentioned the incidental nature of the second duty, it is plain the reception is to be made the occasion for political discussion, hence his anxiety.The Ikhwan.-MT. Scott telegraphed from Alexandria on 31st October [No. 1043] that complaints had been received of late from King Hussein in regard to several minor raids on the part of the Ikhwan to the east of Taif, to which place he had sent the Emir Ali on account of the threatened danger.The Emir Alduila. On 31st October Mr. Scott also telegraphed [No. 1043] that, according to a report received from the British agent in Jeddah, the .. Emir Abdulla had left Medina en route for Ma&apos;an [an important depot on the Hejaz railway, 526 miles to the north-west of Medina.]
AUSTRIA.The Plebiscite [F.C.R., xxviii, p. 3].-Lord Derby reported, on 20th October [No. 1225], that the following communication from the Conference of Ambassadors had been sent to Sir Alban Young at Belgrade that day : * After having taken note of the reply made to yon by the Jugo-Slav Government; the Conference of Ambassadors request you to co-operate immediately with your French and Italian colleagues with a-view to your addressing a further joint demand to the Minister for Foreign Affairs on the subject of the invasion of the Klagenfurt plebiscite zone by Jugo-Slav troops.    You should, in doing so, read to him the following   communication   and  leave   with  him  a   copy :-The  Conference  oF Ambassadors  consider as unsatisfactory the reply which the Jugo-Slav Govern-&apos; ment have  returned to the communication made to them in the name   of  the Allied Powers.     The Inter-Allied Plebiscite   Commission is perfectly capable of administrating the nationals with the means at its disposal, and of ensuring  the: maintenance of order there, provided the troops which have invaded zone &quot;A&quot; are: withdrawn.    The Conference therefore formally request the .J ugo-Slav Government-to withdraw their troops from the zone, without further discussion, within a period of 48 hours, to count from the presentation of this communication.In regard to this, telegraphing on 23rd October from Klagenfurt, Colonel Peck transmitted to Lord Derby a message from the Klagenfurt Plebiscite Commission for the Conference of Ambassadors informing them that the Serb-Croat-Slovene troops had evacuated zone A. &apos;. :BALTIC STATES.Lithuania and Vilna.-Oa 22ncl October Colonel Ward reported from Kovno. [No. 160] that he had been informed officially that if the League of Nations would formally propose that an armistice should be concluded with General Zeligowski without prejudice to any measures which should be taken against him by the League of Nations, the Entente, or Poland, and would further communicate its suggestion to the General, they woidd accept it. Colonel Ward added that this might be the means of averting much bloodshed and suffering.Telegraphing again on the following clay [No. 163], Colonel Ward said that any direct negotiations could only be pursued with Poland on the grounds that that country was responsible and that General Zeligowski was carrying out its policy. The Lithuanian Government therefore wished it to be clearly understood that negotiations between themselves and the General could only fake place at the direct invitation, of the League of Nations or the Entente, and then only for the purpose of avoiding bloodshed pending the measures to be taken by the League by making temporary arrangements.New Esthonian Government. Mr. Lohergan telegraphed from Reval on 27th October [No. 274] that a new Government had been formed as foRows : Professor Piip, Prime Minister and War Minister.O. Strandmann, Minister for Foreign Affairs and Minister of Justice.Lui Olest, Minister of the Interior and Social Minister.J. Kukk. Minister of Trade,.Commerce and Communications.A. Pool, Minister of Agriculture.Carl Baars, Minister of Finance.C. Annuson, Minister of Education.J. Johannson, Minister of Food.THE CAUCASUS.Complaint against General Wrangel. Colonel Stokes telegraphed as follows from Tiflis [No. 451] on 24th October : The Georgian Government informs me that on 12th October 5,000 Cossacks, including women and children^ were driven into Georgia by the Bolsheviks and interned by the Georgians at Igoumnovo, near Gagri.; On 17th October several vessels, including the cruiser Almaz, sent by General Wrangel appeared off this place and demanded the delivery of the Cossacks under threat of opening fire.-   The demand-was refused and fighting ensued in which the
Georgians bad several killed and wonnded. The skips succeeded in embarking all the Cossacks.The Georgian Government desire to protest to His Majesty&apos;s Government against this violation of their neutrality by General Wrangel and request that steps should he taken to prevent a recurrence of such, in view of the Black Sea being, defactoT under Allied control. &quot;      -     -:DANTZ1G.- Signature of the Act establishing the Free City. -Lord Derby reported on 27th October [No. 1246] that the following message had that day been sent to Warsaw and Dantzig :- The Act establishing the free city of Dantzig was signed to-day by the principal Allied Powers and comes into force on 15th November. The signature of this document and the date are being kept secret until the present negotiations for an agreement between the two parties on certain proposed modifications of detail in the Polish-Dantzig treaty are concluded.The free city, Lord Derby added, thus comes into existence on 15th November whether or not Poland signs the treaty.GERMANY.The Geneva Conference. On 22nd October Lord d&apos;Abernon telegraphed [No. 570] as follows :  I saw the Minister for Foreign Affairs to-day and gave him a general outline of the present position of the Anglo-French discussions respecting Geneva, He agrees with the view that an immediate conference between German and French plenipoten-- tiaries would be dangerous, unless opinion in both countries could previously be brought more into harmony with each other and with the facts. On his expressing some fear lest very soon the conference at Brussels should become a substitute for Geneva, instead of a preliminary, I assured him that this would not be the case. I added that if the German Government made a point of an immediate conference at Geneva, His Maj esty &apos;s Government would not draw back from any engagement taken by them at Spa. His Excellency seemed gratified and completely satisfied with my assurances, but said he was quite content to allow matters to proceed as they were now being negotiated between London and Paris, provided, as stated above, that Brussels shall be only preparatory and shall not take the place of Geneva, He agrees that an impartial and (? just) examination of financial facts is the main tbing required.GREECE.Message of Sympathy. On 27th October Lord Curzon sent the following message to M. Venizelos: On the occasion of the national mourning in which your country is plunged, His Majesty s Government desire to express to you their deep sympathy with the Hellenic people.The Hellenic nation may rest assured of the continued and traditional interest of the British nation in their welfare and prosperity.HUNGARY.Extension of Time for the Ratification of the Treaty. On 23rd October Lord Derby reported [No. 1239] that the following message had that day been sent&apos; to Budapest: The Conference of Ambassadors decided this morning to postpone from 1st November to 15th. November the time limit within which the Hungarian Government is to be asked to ratify the treaty. The Hungarian delegation here will be informed of this concession, You are authorized, therefore, in making your joint representation to the Hungarian Government to fix 15th November as the time limit, but in doing so you should notify the Hungarian Government that this date is to be considered as the furthest time limit which the Allied Governments can agree to, and If the Hungarian ratification has not taken place by then the Hungarian
representatives at present sitting on various commissions will no longer be admitted to sit. - . .       &apos;:Similar instructions are being sent to your French, Italian and United States -Colleagues. - .        .The Italian Ambassador assured the Conference this morning that further instructions had been sent to the Italian representative so as to brino-: them into conformity with those of his French and British colleagues.MEXICO.Recognition of Mexico hy the United States Government. Sir Auckland Geddes telegraphed on 29th October [No. 738] that discussions between the State Department and the Mexican agent had been proceeding and that the following position had been reached : A letter has been written by S1&apos; Pesquira to Mr. Colby explaining how Mexico proposes to deal with foreign-owned . properties and concessions, and Mr. Colby intends now to reply that these proposals provide a basis for discussion upon which he feels he can confidently proceed with the preliminaries of recognition.PERSIA.Government Budget. Mr. Norman telegraphed [No. 698] on 23rd October that the Prime Minister had supplied him.-with-a copy of the Persian Government budget, showing estimated receipts and expenditure up to 22nd November. This was the first budget ever presented in the history of the country. The estimated receipts did not include sums already ^ or expected to be, received from the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. In the estimated expenditure provision was made for extraordinary military requirements, apart from special sums for national defence from other sources, and the Treasury woidd have an accumulated deficit of 41,683,143 tomans. The present Cabinet was making an earnest-endeavour to reduce expenditure and to increase receipts. Surplus personnel was being gradually diminished, and a tempo-rary reduction in the salaries of officials was being made, although the wisdom of this&quot; step was doubtful, as the pay of many of them was already too little to ensure honesty. The prospects of&apos; increased receipts were more hopeful. The Opium concession had been cancelled and had been made a Government administration, which, combined with the smoking and tobacco administration, had been entrusted to a very able and honest official, who had informed Mr. Norman that during the next twelve months he hoped to show an increase of receipts of about 1,000,000 tomans, and later on, with the better organization of his administration, to increase this amount six times or more.POLAND.Vilna [F.C.R., xxviii, p. 6]. On 20th October Sir Percy Loraine reported from Warsaw [No. 952] that the Minister for Foreign Affairs had handed to him a reply of a joint declaration made by the French Minister and himself on 17th October, which was as follows : While renewing and confirming its previous declarations the Polish Government categorically deny that either the armistice concluded between the Polish and Lithuanian armies under the auspices of the League of Nations or the declaration of the Polish Government with regard to the occupation of Vilna has been violated.The   Polish   Government regret that  the   insubordination of  certain troops -commanded by General Zeligowski should have intervened to disturb its general desire to put at end to the Polish-Lithuanian dispute in a friendly way.The population of Vilna and the Polish soldiers, natives-of the region of Vilna, who have revolted against their authorities, are a third factor which has made its appearance in the dispute and for which the Polish Government is unable to accept any responsibility. As regards the League of Nations, the Polish Government, so far from damaging its prestige, is on the contrary firmly resolved to respect the League&apos;s decisions, and is maintaining in force the armistice concluded by the two armies under the .auspices of the Commission of Control.Thanks to the beneficial influence of that Commission, not only have hostilities between the Polish and Lithuanian troops been stopped, but also the exchange of prisoners.of war contemplated in the arrangement of, 17th October is in process of execution.22-1 B
Poland will be ready to contribute towards any effort which aims at settling the question of Vilna in accordance with the principles of justice and complete impartiality.Two days later Colonel Ward telegraphed from Kovno [No. 160] that the number of troops round Vilna was daily increasing and that Lida was being used as a common junction for Poles and rebels. It was, he said, known that trains were running from Lida to Vilna, although the rebel troops had had no rolling stock and none had been captured from Lithuania.Telegraj)liing from Brussels on 28th October [Nos. 128 and 129], Sir George Grahame reported that the Council of the League of Nations, after hearing the Polish and Lithuanian delegates, had passed the following resolution : -The Council of the League of Nations desiring above all to establish peace between the Lithuanian and Polish peoples, and having duly noted the solemn declarations by which the Polish Government has disclaimed responsibility for the action of General Zeligowski and has declared him a rebel, having also noted that both parties claim for the populations concerned the right of self-determination and base their respective claims on this right, draws the attention of both parties to the agreements entered into by them with the League, and formally invites them to accept the following recommendations : (1) A public expression of opinion shall be taken under the auspices and super-vision of the League whereby the inhabitants of the disputed territory east of the line fixed by the Supreme Council on 8th December 1919 may freely express their wishes on the subject of their attachment either to the State of Lithuania, the seat of whose Government is at present at Kovno, or to Poland. The Council of the League shall determine the extent and boundaries of this territory and shall fix the method of taking public expression of opinion and its date so as to ensure freedom and the genuine character of the vote.(2) The Council of the League shall decide what measures shall be taken before and during this public expression of opinion, whether for the withdrawal or for the disarmament of any troops of whatever nationality in occupation of territories in which the public expression of opinion is taken. With this object, and to ensure the carrying out of the Councibs recommendations, the latter shall have the right to exercise forthwith control over tbe roads and railways leading to the disputed territory or passing through it. The Council requests the delegates of both parties to inform it within ten days of the 28th October whether their Governments accept these recommendations. The Council requests the delegates of both parties to give it forthwith, in the name of their respective Governments, a formal assurance that they will abstain from any act of hostility against each other and Avill do all in their power to maintain peace, Members of the Military Commission continue to be entrusted with the fair settlement of any difficulties which may arise.Sir George Grahame further reported that the Polish and Lithuanian delegates had given the assurance asked for.Next day Sir percent.y Loraine telegraphed [No. 981] that the Polish Cabinet had accepted the proposal to hold a plebiscite under the control of the League of Nations in the Vilna district; this accceptance being conditional on the holding of the plebiscite without delay in the territories occupied by General Zeligowski s army.Ratification of the Russian Peace Preliminaries. Sir Percy Loraine reported on 23rd October [No. 961] that the Diet had ratified unanimously the peace preliminaries and armistice concluded at Riga with the Soviet Government,Relations ivith Latvia. On 28th and 30th October Sir Percy Loraine telegraphed [Nos. 977 and 987] to the following effect :.-The Minister of Foreign Affairs had intimated that an additional outlet to the sea was a vital necessity for Poland in case she should be blockaded by the free city of Dantzig, and this could easily be secured at the price of a cle jure recognition of Latvia towards which the Polish Government was very favourably disposed.His calculations, however, had been rather upset by the fact that His Majesty&apos;s-Government did not wish for such a recognition, at all events for the present. He had expected the disapproval of the French Government, but had believed that the British was on the point of recognizing Latvia cle jure.He pointed out the solid advantages which would accrue to Poland from the mere act of recognition, which, moreover, fitted in with his general policy. Poland was about to sign a peace with Russia, and the best means of securing herself in the
future was to strengthen the ties between herself and such of her neighbours as might be threatened by Russia.Sir Percy urged reasons against hasty action, and finally Prince Sapieha said that he proposed to grant a de jure recognition to Latvia on 18th^November unless he were meantime informed that His Majesty&apos;s Government definitely wished him to abstain.RUMANIA.Persecution of Hungarians. On 30th October Lord Derby informed the Foreign Office [No. 1272] that the following telegram had been sent to the British Minister at Bucharest :&apos; I request that you will, in accordance with the decision of the Conference of Ambassadors, co-operate with your French and Italian colleagues in drawing the attention of the Rumaniau Government to the persecutions suffered by Hungarians at Cluj, and invite them to put a stop to such violations of the Minorities Treaty of which they are signatories. As the principal Allied Powers are likewise signatories, they consider it undesirable that such violations should be allowed to pass unnoticed.Bessarabia. The foUowing telegram was received from M. Chicherin on 2nd November : Ayant appris qu&apos;un traite vient d&apos;etre signe entre les Grandes Puissances Alliees et la Roumanie au sujet de 1&apos;annexion de la Bessarabie par cette derniere, les gouvernements des Republic] ues Sovietistes de Russie et d&apos;Ukraine declarent qulls ne peuvent reconnaitre aucune transaction survenue quant a la Bessarabie sans leur participation comme ayant force et valeur, et qulls ne se considerent point lies par tin traite conclu entre autres gouvernements a ce sujet.(Signe)      Chicherin, Commissaire du Peuple aux Affaires Etrangeres de la Republique Russe. (Signe)      Rakowsky, President du Conseil des Commissaires du Peuple, et Commissaire du Peuple aux Affaires Etrangeres de la Republique Ukrainienne.RUSSIA.Exchange of Prisoners [F.C.R., xxviii, p. 8]. On 26th October the following-telegram was sent to Mr. Leslie at Reval [No. 290] for transmission to M. Chicherin :  Babushkin and his party will leave England on 27th October: further details and the full names of the party will be telegraphed to you as soon as possible.A ship conveying Russians from Egypt, Chanak, and Constantinople will probably leave Constantinople on 3rd November accompanied by a light cruiser and a destroyer Owing to mine fields off Odessa the convoy will await the Soviet vessels sent to meet it from Odessa at a point about 20 miles south of Odessa where the transfer of Russians, numbering about 300, will take place. The precise date and hour will be communi-cated to you as soon as possible, daylight of 5th November being probably- the earliest on which this can be done.His Majesty&apos;s Government request that you will communicate the above to your representatives at Baku and Tiflis and to your authorities at Odessa in order that there may be no hitch in the arrangements.His Majesty&apos;s Government expect the arrival at Tiflis of the British prisoners and civilians detained at Baku to synchronize with the arrival off Odessa of the Russians mentioned above, and will be glad to learn that the Soviet Government has sent instructions to that effect. This is the more important as regards Tiflis as telegraphic communication between that town and this country has recently been slow and uncertain.On 29th October the following message [No. 249] was sent to Mr. Kidston at Helsingfors : We still have no indication that the release of-&quot; the Baku prisoners is imminent, and consequently it wiR probably be necessary to hold up Babushkin and his party, who left on the Ariadne on the evening of the 27th.His Majesty&apos;s Government are anxious to avoid causing any embarrassment to the Finnish Government by taking off the party just outside Helsingfors, and they have therefore decided to intercept the Ariadne in the neighbourhood of Dantzig,
convoy her into that port, and there transfer the Russians in question-to a British cruiser. They will he detained until the Baku release is effected and then taken to Helsingfors.   Please explain matters to the Minister for Foreign Affairs.It appears that the Captain of the Ariadne consented to take the Russians on hoard only on condition that they would be met at Helsingfors by the British Consul and their passage through Finland effected without ;delay. You should accordingly see that this is done when they eventually arrive.On the same day Lord Curzon telegraphed again to M. Chicherin, through Mr. Leslie [No. 293], saying that His Majesty&apos;s Government would be glad to learn that the Soviet Government had agreed to the provisional arrangements communicated in his message of 26th October for the transhipment of the Russian prisoners off Odessa. His Majesty&apos;s Government proposed in this event that any final details should be arranged by direct wireless correspondence between the Soviet authorities and the British naval conimander-in-chief at Constantinople, and they were instructing the latter accordingly.The following note from M. Chicherin, dated 30th October, was presented by M. Krassin on 1st November&quot;:: In the course of negotiations with the British Government regarding the release of prisoners at Baku, the Soviet Government has always called the attention of the British Government to the fact that Azerbaijan.is an independent State whose actions cannot be determined by the Russian Soviet Government. Your note of 28th October stills fails to recognize this fact. However, the Soviet Government has earnestly urged the Government, of Azerbaijan to meet the wishes of the British Government in regard to the Baku prisoners, and now again in view of your complaint of delay is renewing its representations&quot; at Baku, trusting to reach a favourable result. Your allegation of our non-compliance with the agreement is rather misplaced in view of the fact that, regardless of altogether unnecessary delay on. the part of the British Government in the matter of the repatriation of Babushkin and his party, the British Siberian Mission, Britishers sentenced to prison for grave offences and many British civilians are being delivered to-day to the representatives of the British Mission in Finland at the Finnish border. Other Britishers are being rapidly brought to the same border. Steps have been taken to meet the transport announced by you as bringing Russian prisoners from Egypt and Constantinople to Odessa, and the Azerbaijan Government has been informed of our urgent wish to have the release of the British prisoners in Baku and their delivery to the British representative to synchronize with the arrival outside Odessa of the British transport.On 30th October Mr. Kidston reported [No. 653] that the Minister for Foreign Affairs had sent him a copy of a very urgent wireless telegram dated 28th October from M. Chicherin, &quot;stating that the Soviet Government had learnt that His Majesty&apos;s Government were repatriating, besides Babushkin and his party, 30 individuals unknown to the Soviet delegation in London and without their approval. He promised further details with regard to these persons and warned the Finnish Government that only those approved by the Soviet delegation in London would be allowed to pass the Russian frontier.He, Mr. Kidston, was telling the Minister for Foreign Affairs that the only repatriated Russians of whom he had any knowledge were eight persons whose names he had alread3^ communicated to him and to M. Chicherin, and that he could not fathom the object of this allegation of the Soviet Government.On 1st November [No. 663] Mr. Kidston telegraphed as follows : The director of the Finnish Steamship Company called on me this morning and showed me wirelesslnessages received from the captain of the Ariadne in which the captain states : &quot; English men-of-war advise me that the Finnish Government in conjunction with the English Government have ordered the Ariadne into Dantzig.&quot; Did British naval officers allege that the Finnish Government were a consenting party ? Unless some arrangement of which I am ignorant was reached with the Finnish Minister in London, our case will be stud further embarrassed by such a statement.1The director, is a staunch friend of Great Britain, and promises to do everything that.he can to curb sensational announcements in the Press, but points out that when the passengers, who number about 150, arrive, aR efforts in this direction will be futile. The passengers probably include Germans from Copenhagen, and he antici-pates a violent Press campaign from both the pro-German and the Socialist sides-. I- am doing what I can with the Press Bureau of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs, but
such, an opportunity is too good to he missed hy our enemies, and the full force of the Bolshevik. propaganda organization all over the world will doubtless be set in motion.The director mentioned claims for bunkers, passengers, food, &amp;c, and I told him these must be presented in London. lie is particularly anxious about bunkers as the extra expenditure, of coal has (? group omitted) in view of the coal strike. He wishes for coal to be delivered to him at once at Hull in spite of strike regulations, and I cannot sufficiently urge that this and all other practical questions raised bv the incident should be.met in the most liberal spirit.Telegraphing again on the same day [No. 664], Mr. Kidston further reported as follows :  : Major Fitzhugh telegraphs from Terijoki that he informed the Soviet Commissaries at the frontier that Babushkin and his part)&apos; would arrive at the frontier to-morrow, 2nd November. .Meanwhile, 62 British subjects have been handed over and more are expected. I have told Major Fitzhugh not to venture across the frontier again pending further instructions, as I fear he maybe kidnapped. I request.instructions by telegraph as to whether I should ask him to risk this in the event of another British party arriving. The Bolsheviks are scarcely likely to hand them over [until Babushkin arrives., Fitzhugh holds a letter of appointment as my personal representative, so that in view of his statement with regard to Babushkin, I am doubtless regarded by the Bolshevik authorities as guilty of a breach of faith.: In reply to this Lord Curzon informed Mr. Kidston on 3rd November [No. 252] that his instructions to Major Fitzhugh were approved: he should run no risk of being seized by Bolsheviks.Lord Curzon went on to say that the failure of the Soviet Government to redeem its engagement about the Baku prisoners, though three weeks have now elapsed, was the sole and sufficient reason for the action of His Maj esty&apos;s Government in detaining Babushkin and his party, and if, as was still hoped, the Baku exchange took place on 5th November, the party would be conveyed hy the cruiser to Helsingfors on the same day.   The breach of faith was entirely on the side of the Soviet Government.On 2nd November the following note was presented by M. Krassin, acting under instructions from his Government: . In reply to the British Governments communication, received on 26th October, dealing with the trans-shipment of Russian citizens to Odessa on British transport ships, in which communication the British Government asks the Russian Government to meet this transport 20 miles from the shore, the Russian and Ukrainan Soviet Governments express their willingness to do so&quot;Since then the Russian Government has received a communication suggesting that the final details in this matter be arranged by wireless with the British naval command in Constantinople. Unfortunately, wireless communication between Odessa and Constantinople is not to be depended upon, and may make such arrangement? impracticable.The Russian Government is also taking energetic steps with the Azerbaijan Government with, reference to the repatriation of the prisoners in Baku, audit expects during the next few days a favourable result with regard to these negotiations.The Russian Government takes this opportunity of again informing the British Government that British prisoners from Siberia, grave offenders and other British subjects, crossed the Finnish frontier on Saturday, 30th October. The remainder will be delivered without delay.The Russian Government is quite sure that the British Government realizes the fact that this arrangement with the Azerbaijan Government is not an easy matter, especially as it is a matter dealing with the internal administration of another country. The Russian Government would also point out that communications between Moscow and Baku are difficult owing to the country having been devastated by DenikhTs forces, and hence communications having been destroyed.Finally to-day, 3rd November, the following telegram was sent to Mr. Kidston [No. 253] for transmission to M. Chicherin : It is how three weeks since the -Soviet Government agreed to my proposals for the release of all British nationals either directly or indirectly under its control, and so far only half its undertaking is in process of being carried out. 22-1 C
I permitted M. Babushkin and his party to. leave the United ^Kingdom on 27th October in the S.S. Ariadne in the confident hope that by the end of last week I should have heard that definite arrangements had been made for the release of the Baku prisoners. As the only news that reached me from Tiflis indicated further obstruction, there was no alternative but to hold up M. Babushkin as a pledge that the whole agreement with the Soviet Government will be scrupulously carried out. He and his party were consequently removed to one of His Majesty&apos;s ships at Dantzig, and they will be held on board until information has been received that the British prisoners at Baku have been released.I am still hopeful, in view of the concluding words of your message of 30th October communicated to me by M. Krassin, that the exchange will duly take place on 5th November, in that case M. Babushkin and his party will at once be conveyed to Hango and set at liberty. But if the Soviet Government fails to make its influence effective at Baku, His Majesty&apos;s Government will be reluctantly driven to the conclusion that it is unwilling to carry out its undertaking in this respect.Soviet Submarines [F.C.R., xxvii, p. 10].-On 2nd November the following-message [No. 296] was sent to Mr. Leslie for transmission to M. Chicherin: In reply to M. Krassin&apos;s note of 19th October, I have to state that the belief of His Majesty&apos;s Government as to the aggressive intentions of the Soviet submarines was based on the open avowal of a Soviet Minister when launching a submarine, in the Black Sea that he hoped it would sink an Entente vessel.His Majesty&apos;s Government did not feel justified in running this risk, and they now find themselves confirmed in their fears by such a vague statement as that contained in para. 4 of the note under reference, which would provide a Soviet submarine commander, who desired to torpedo any of his Majesty&apos;s ships, with the excuse of mistaken identity. Further, the Soviet forces in the Black Sea are still engaged in acts of open hostility against British interests, in which submarines may at any time be engaged.If the Soviet Government desires to bring this situation to an end, it can do so at once by giving the assurances called for.SERBIA.The Russian Refugees [F.C.R., xxvii, p. 11].-Telegraphing on 26th October [No. 332], Sir Alban Young said that as he- had learnt from the senior naval officer at Lemnos that a large number of Russian refugees had been sent from that place to the Crimea, he presumed that His Majesty&apos;s Government had no objection in principle to refugees being sent from Serbia to join General Wrangeks army, provided that the British authorities&apos; took no part in their despatch. He understood that refugees of military age and standing would be picked out at the Serbian frontier with a view to sending them to the Crimea.On 2nd November Sir Alban Young was informed [No. 244] that on the under-standing that the journey of the refugees would not be facilitated by any British official there was no objection to the proposed action.SWEDEN.New Cabinet. On 27th October Mr. Barclay telegraphed [No. 286] the following; list of the new Cabinet: ;Prime Minister : H. de Geer. Finance : H. Tarmn.Foreign Affairs : H. Wrangel. Church and Education: H. Bergqvist.Justice : H. Ekeberg. Agriculture : Professor Hansson.Defence : General Hammarskjold. Commerce : H. Malm..    Social: H. Elmqnist. Without  Portfolio :   HH.   DahlbergCommunications: H. Murray. and Ericsson.TURKEY.New Cabinet. On 21st October Admiral de Robeck telegraphed [Nos. 1138,1-139] the list of the new Cabinet with comments :  Grand Vizier, Tewfik Pasha.Sheik-ul-Islam and Acting Minister of Pious Foundations, Nouri Effendi. Minister of Foreign Affairs, Sefa Bey. Minister of the Interior, Izzet Pasha.
Minister of War, General Zia Pasha.Minister of Marine, Salih Pasha. :&apos;Minister of Finance and Acting- Minister of Public Works, Rashid Bey. Minister of Public Works, Abdullah Bey.Minister of Agriculture and Commerce and Acting Minister of Justice, Hussein.Kiazim Bey. Public Instruction, Reshid Pasha. Council of State, Mustafa Arif Bey.The Cabinet is evidently intended to be one of &quot;safe,&quot; even of moderate Nationalist leanings a Ministry of conciliation in fact.The most significant selection is that of the ex-Grand Vizier Izzet Pasha for Minister, of the. Interior. He is generally credited with strong Nationalist sympathies, but he has kept very quiet for a long time past.The imperial decree appointing the new Grand Vizier is very short and entirely colourless.Tewfik Pasha and the Financial Situation.  Telegraphing- on 19th October [Nos. 1120, 1121], Admiral de Robeck reported that Tewfik Pasha had called on him on 18th October, the day after receiving the offer of the grand vizierate. Anatolia, the ratification of the treaty, financial and economic matters formed the chief topics of conversation.   In regard to the last, Admiral de Robeck telegraphed as follows :-Tewfik Pasha urged the importance of assisting, Turkey to meet her immediate liabilities not by direct Allied assistance, which he (? agreed) was out of the question, but by facilitating financial establishments.I said that my view was that the Financial Commission alone could render effective assistance, and that the policy should be to expedite the functioning of that Commission which would follow on the ratification of the treaty.Tewfik said that this was all very well, but that the Commission could not relieve the situation for some time, whereas the Government would need ready money. He said that the French High Commissioner, speaking unofficially and for the French only, had led him to hope for assistance in this direction without indicating its nature.1 said that nothing in my instructions would justify&apos;me in holding out any hope of direct help. He asked me to submit his views to you aud to obtain a very early answer. I promised to report what he said, but explained that answers regarding financial questions came very slowly from London, and I pressed the point of view which I had expressed regarding the Financial Commission.Sir A. Block tells me that in his view the only thing to do is to expedite the constitution of the Financial Commission, and to arrange for the application of the financial clauses in anticipation of the coming into force of the treaty as a whole. Once this is done, relief can be afforded at once for the Financial Commission can create the credit which the Turkish Government does not possess owing to the restrictions imposed by the treaty. As for the short interval requiring to be bridged, essential payments for September have been assured, and similar payments for October, which will fall due at, the beginning of November, can also be assured under the auspices of the public debt control by incoming revenue, such as it is, plus disposal of stocks other than war material in a strict sense.The course now indicated would appear to be to press strongly for ratification, and to arrange for the completion of the Financial Commission by the appointment of a French member, and for the application of the financial clauses of the treaty in anticipation of the Allied ratifications.My colleagues and I propose to apply the first part of this programme as soon as the new Government is approved. The only thing likely to (? delay) action is the desire of the Italian Actiug High Commissioner, based on instructions from Rome, to obtain simultaneously some sort of recognition by the Turks of the tripartite agreement.   If this difficulty assumes serious proportions 1 will telegraph further.Meanwhile I venture again to urge very strongly that the French Government be pressed to appoint their member of the Financial Commission.The constitution of the military and. other commissions should also follow the Turkish ratification as soon as possible, but the Financial Commission is of such primary importance that if the new Government and the Sultan should prove recalcitrant about ratification I should revert to my previous idea of instituting the Commission (? and) bringing- (the financial) clauses into operation without awaiting any ratification at all.
With reference to the above the following message was telegraphed to our representatives at Paris and Rome,on 3rd November:-In the opinion of His Majesty s Government the only course open to the Allies is to make further representations to theTukish Government insisting on immediate ratification, and asking the Porte to realize what are the logical consequences of the refusal to make peace. Some compromise must be devised on the constitutional question. In order not to provide an excuse for endless delay, the proposed mission to the Nationalists should be postponed until the Porte agrees to the ratification.Please represent the above to the Government to which you are accredited, and ask them to instruct their representatives in Constantinople to join their British colleague in taking this line,&quot;&quot;  Ratification of the Treaty demanded. Admiral de Robeck sent the foUowing telegram&apos;[No. 1157] on 28th October :-A collective note demanding the immediate ratification of the treaty by Turkey was handed to the Grand Vizier on the afternoon of 25th September.Later on the same day the Government published a statement of policy, the most significant passage of which was as follows : &quot;The Cabinet being convinced of the absolute necessity that the Government and tlie nation should work hand in band, will summon Parliament as soon as the effort to secure union has produced its result, in order to render possible the ratification, in a legal form, of the peace treaty, in accordance with the requirements of the constitution.&quot;This statement was doubtless drafted before the receipt of the collective note of the High Commissioners, but Tewfik was already aware of our views regarding ratification. I therefore hoped that the passage quoted above was mainly for public consumption, and that the intention was to devise some formula which would combine immediate ratification with the reservation of the right of Parliament, if and when assembled, to have the treaty formally submitted to it.The attitude of Ministers does not, unfortunately, confirm this view. Tewfik himself manifested hesitation and embarrassment when the note was presented, and the Minister for Foreign Affairs, who paid me his first official visit on 27th October, expressed the very definite view that the order of proceedings should be to effect a composition with the Nationalists, then to convene the Chamber representing non-occupied areas, then to ratify. The Minister for Foreign Affairs urged, that this was the only course at all compatible with the.constitution, and that it was also the only practical course, as immediate ratification by the Sultan and the Government would be so resented by the Nationalists as to destroy all chance of bringing them into line by peaceful means.I said that your telegrams showed increasing anxiety on the part of His Majesty&apos;s Government for immediate ratification by Turkey ; that this was a preliminary condition of the assistance which they were willing and eager to render, e.g., by instituting a Financial Commission and bringing that and its clauses into operation as soon as possible ; and that delaj7 would entail financial chaos besides being fraught with dangerous possibilities for Turkey.I exhausted every argument in favour of immediate ratification, but I made little or no impression. The Minister for Foreign Affairs promised to speak to Tewfik, whose views, however, he stated to be identical with his own. I promised to report what the Minister said, but intimated that I could hold out no hope of a favourable reception by His Maj esty&apos;s Government of the programme which he outlined.Three other important Ministers have taken a similar line in private conversations with a member of my staff.The constitutional difficulty is a very real one, and can only be got over by some formula on the lines indicated above, but I fear it looks as if tbe High Commissioners may have the greatest difficulty in obtaining from the new Government ratification in anv shape at all until they have first tried to bring the Nationalists round.The attitude of the Government is hardly consistent with what Tewfik led us to expect in conversations preceding his advent to power, but this merely illustrates the fact that in any tight place he is more likely to be influenced by others than to exercise any real control. The Ministers are also encouraged in their view by the knowledge that the Sultan, however much he may differ from them otherwise, also shrinks from immediate ratification.

</content>
</cab>
