<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/6/0 images: 118-125</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property-of His Britannic Ma,iesty&apos;s Government, jPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1918.SECRET.79WAR  CABINET,  398.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onWednesday, April 24, 19.18, at 1P30 a.m.Present :The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon.  the Earl  Curzon of j The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.Kedleston, K.Gr., G.C.S.I., G-.G.I.E.       . Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.1    Smuts, ICC.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P.The following were also present :-The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner.G.C.B., G.C.M.G., Secretary of State forWar (for Minutes 1 to 4).General Sm H. H. Wilson, K.C.B., D.S.O.,Chief of the Imperial General Staff (for minutes 1 to 4).Lieutenant-General Sir C. F.N.Macready,G.C.M.G., K.C.B., Adjutant-General tothe Forces (for Minutes 13 to 15).The Right Hon. Sir G. Cave, K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs (for minute 16).The Right Hon. W. H. Long, M.P., Secre-tary of State for the Colonies (for minutes 1 to 11).The Right Plon. W. S. Churchill,M.P.,Minister of Munitions (for Minutes 13and 14).Sir Stephenson Kent, K.C.B., Ministryof Munitions (for Minutes 13 and 14).Rear-Admiral G. P. W. Hope, C.B., deputy first Sea Lord (for Minutes 1 to 7).The right Hon. T. j. Macnamara, LED.,M.P., Financial Secretary, Admiralty(for Minute 17).The Right Hon. Sir J. Haclay, Bart.,Shipping Controller (for Minute 11).The Right Hon. G. H. Roberts, M.P.,Minister of Labour (for Minutes l3to 18).Sir D. J. Shackleton, K.C.B., permanent secretary, Ministry of Labour (for minutes 13 to 18).The Right Hon. Sir A. C. Geddes,K.O.B., M.P., Minister of National Ser-vice (for Minutes 13 to 15).Major P. Lloyd Greame, M.C., Secretary,Ministry of National Service (for Minutes13 to 15).The Right Hon. H. E. Duke, K.C., M.P.,Chief Secretary for Ireland (for Minute15).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. Wilson, C.M.G., D.S.O., M.P., Assistant Secretary.Paymaster-in-Chief P. H. Row, R.N., Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Captain L. F. Burgis, Assistant Secretary.[1365-398]B
Co-operation of the 2. With reference to War Cabinet 397, Minute 4, the SecretaryUnited States of 0f State for War reported that the result of the conversations at theAmerica. War Office avith General Pershing avas that an agreement had beenreached as to the programme for the next six weeks.The Prime Minister said that it had transpired from a conversa-tion with Captain Guest, Avho had seen and spoken to american troops embarking from this country for France, that men had beensent forward from the United States without any method, avith theresult that men with six months&apos; training Avere to be found side by side with raw recruits. General Pershing had confirmed this information, and had expressed surprise at the occurrence, avhich hesupposed was due to the haste with avhich the orders to piishforward troops had been carried out. He had said that it wasnecessary to sift and re-organise these troops before they could beemployed.The western front.The Belgian Front. 3. The   Chief of  the Imperial General Staff said that theGermans had three diausions, two of which avere in the line and one was in the reserve, opposite the Belgian front.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff informed the WarCabinet that General Foch had sent one French division to supportthe Belgians, and that the move would be completed by to-morrownight. Instructions had also been given to General Plumer and tothe Belgians that, in case of attack, the reserves of the two countriesavere to be co-ordinated. General Wilson added that this meant that by to-morroav night the French avould. have six infantryandthree cavalry cliausions in the north of Flanders.The Chief of the 4. The Chief of the Imperial General Stall stated that he hadAir Staff. been in communication with the Field-Marshal Commanding-in-Chief in Prance in regard to General Trenchard ; that Sir douglas haig had offered to give General Trenchard immediately the com-mand of a brigade ; and that, if such a command was carried outsatisfactorily, he hoped to give him the command of a division at alater date.This gave rise to a short discussion on the subject of theforthcoming debate in Parliament relative to the recent change inthe post, of Chief of the Staff at the Air Ministry, and the suggestionAvas made that it would be more suitable if, in vieav of GeneralTrenchard&apos;s unrivalled experience in the air, he were given a command in the Air Service.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that he understood from General Trenchard that, in his view, in the highest interests ofthe Air Service, he ought not to take up an air command.1. THE Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that theGermans had brought to their front one fresh division, in the vicinity of Robecq.A question was asked as to when the next offensive on the partof the Germans was likely to take place, and reference was made toa speech which had recently been made by General von Stein, in theReichstag, which indicated that no large offensive was probable inthe immediate future.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff inclined to the same view.Genera] Wilson stated that at the present moment there were only seventeen fresh German divisions, two of which were composedof Landwebr troops, and avere consequently of small fighting value.This represented on the Western front the smallest number of fresh divisions since the offensive began.
WC 398It was also stated that General Trenchard had declined toaccept a post as Chief of the Air Staff on Sir Douglas Haig&apos;s Staff.It was suggested, however, that it was desirable that an Inspector-General of the Air Service might be appointed, with a view toco-ordinating the work of the outlying and home air stations, andfor the inspection of equipment and aerodromes, and that it wouldbe more desirable to utilise General Trenchard&apos;s experience in thisway than in the field.General regret was expressed that Lord Rothermere wasindisposed, and that the question could not be discussed with him,but, in view of the trrgency of the matter, the War Cabinet decidedthat (a.) The Prime Minister, Mr. Bonar Law, and General Smutsshould, on behalf of the Avar Cabinet, discuss the question at once with the Under-Secretary for Air.(b.) The Secretary should send to each member of the WarCabinet a copy of the correspondence between LordRothermere and General Trencharcl on the subject of thelatter&apos;s resignation.Wheat for Italy. 5. Mr. Chamberlain said that Signor Orlando had sent theItalian Ambassador direct to Sir John Beale, asking for more wdieatfor Italy. The situation was that the arrivals of wheat in each ofthe Allied countries were short of the programme in approximately the same proportion, but that the difference between the Frenchand ourselves on the one hand, and Italy on the other, was that wehad begun the year -with several weeks&apos; supply in reserve, and thatthe French had now been obliged to admit that they also had had several, though not quite as many, weeks&apos; stock in reserve. TheItalians, on the other hand, had no reserve and had actuallyimpinged on the new harvest before the new cereal year hadcommenced. Sir John Beale was of opinion that they had justenough if no exceptional losses of wheat in transit, such as hadsometimes taken place, occurred, but that if such exceptional lossesdid take place they might be very short. Looking at the questionpurely on the merits, lie would be inclined to take this risk.Having regard to the policy which the Cabinet had hitherto pursuedof being rather more generous to Italy, and to the fact that ourposition was so satisfactory that we could afford to spare the wheat,he would be prepared to release 50,1)00 tons of wheat to Italy, as areserve in order to relieve the Italian Government from anxiety andto cover any possible sinking of wheat ships. He considered thatthis would be in harmony with the policy previously pursuedtowards Italy by His Majesty&apos;s Government. Mr. Chamberlain alsodrew attention to Joint Note No. 22, by the Military Representativesof the Supreme War Council, which indicated that the transport oftroops, in the case of an offensive in Italy, would have to be carriedout between France and Italy with the greatest possible rapidity,and, consequently, there would be a temporary suspension of alltrains carrying coal and supplies for the armies and war factories in. Italy. This went to prove that Italy ought not to be left in any danger of being found short of breadstuffs at a critical moment.On the other hand, shipping losses in the Mediterranean were very heavy, and the Minister of Shipping objected to the diversion of-more shipping in that direction than was absolutely essential.Mr. Chamberlain stated that he would be prepared to recommend a compromise, namely, that 25,000 tons of wheat should be diverted to Italy.The War Cabinet authorised -Mr. Chamberlain to arrange the matter, after consultation asrequisite with -the Minister of Shipping and the wheat commission.
Submarines. 6. The Deputy First Sea Lord informed, the War Cabinet thatseven attacks on enemy submarines had been carried out during thepast twenty-four hours, some . of which promised to render good results.ZeXniSfand 7&apos; With reference to War Cabinet 397, Minute 2, the DeputyOstena. First Sea Lord gave the following summary of the reports that hadbeen received up to date regarding the operations carried out onthe night of April 22/23 at Ostend and Zeebrugge. It was intended that an aerial bombardment should have taken place prior to themain operations, but such was impossible, owing to the state of the weather. The &quot; Vindictive&quot; was received with heavy fire, and suffered many casualties before getting alongside the mole. The&quot;Thetis&quot; was also received with heavy fire, and sank just outsidethe harbour. The &quot; Intrepid &quot; and &quot; Iphigenia &quot; passed round the, latter and were sunk in such positions that it is believed that theBruges Canal is blocked. The majority of the crews were mostgallantly taken off by motor-launch No. 282. Our storming anddemolition parties which landed on the mole suffered heavy losses from the fire of the German destroyers alongside the mole, but theynevertheless inflicted considerable damage, and their work enabled the block-ships to attain their position. The destroyer &quot; NorthStar &quot; and the coastal motor-boats came inside the harbour and firedfive torpedoes at the German destnwers alongside the wall. The&quot; North Star &quot; was afterwards sunk. The smoke screen, which wasmade to assist the operations, acted effectively until the windchanged, after the engagement had lasted an hour, which enabled the land batteries to pick up the ships, and consequently casualtiesresulted. The submarine &quot; C. 3&quot; was blown up in the correctposition in the pile-work at the neck of the mole, and a large gaphas been observed in the viaduct. The other submarine failed to attain her correct position, and returned into harbour.As regards Ostend, the wind had changed after the flares hadbeen placed, and the flares were extinguished by enemy gunfire ;consequently, the &quot; Sirius &quot; and &quot; Brilliant &quot; were unable to find their correct position. Later observation, however, indicates thatthere is a sunken object lying between the pier, blocking about two-thirds of the fairway of the harbour, and that another vessel isashore f mile to the east of Ostend. , About 500 men were landedon the mole at Zeebrugge, and our total casualties are about 400,from the whole force engaged. In addition to the &quot; North Star,&quot;two motor-launches and one coastal motor-boat are missing.The Adriatic. 3,  The Deputy First Sea Lord reported that on Monday night,the 22nd April, five Austrian destroyers were engaged by two ofour destroyers in the vicinity of the Otranto barrage, and that theenemy destroyers retreated to Durazzo, our destroyers being-supported in the chase by five British and one French destroyer onthe Otranto patrol line. As regards damage, the fore magazine ofone of our destroyers (the &quot; Hornet &quot;) blew up, 5 ranks and ratingsbeing killed and .15 wounded. The other destroyer was fit for service, and had 2 killed and 4 wounded. As the attack took placein the dark it was not possible to say what damage the Austriandestroyers sustained.Ireland. 9.  The question Avas asked as to Avhether there was any truth in the rumour that de Valera had been discovered to be in commu-communication with the enemy. No information to this-effect had reachedany member of the War Cabinet, and there avas no reference to it ina private letter from Lord French on the situation which the PrimeMinister read to the War Cabinet. From this letter it was seen thatpreparations in Ireland are for passive rather than active resistance
Propaganda inIreland.Diversion ofShipping fromCanadian to UnitedStates Ports.Proposed NewPensions Warrant,to the Military Service Act. Lord French drew attention, inter alia,to the necessity of stopping speeches and actions inciting activeopposition.The question was postponed for a more formal discussion..10. Attention was called to the entire absence of any organisedsystem of propaganda in Ireland. It was pointed out that theUnited Kingdom had been excluded from the sphere of activities ofthe Minister of Propaganda, and that Ireland was not a suitablefield of action for the War Aims Committee. , A suggestion wasmade, however, that suitable cinema performances might be useful,and it was stated that an xAmerican Mission had gone there, andthat they might be able to create in the minds of Irishmen an interest in the war.[1365-398]11. The War Cabinet had under consideration a Report by theSecretary of State for the Colonies (Paper G.T.-4287), in which itwas stated that the Canadian Government complain of the diversion of shipping from Canadian to United States ports without prior consulation with them.Mr. Long drew particular attention to the following extractfrom a telegram from the Governor-General of Canada, dated the17th April, 1918 : &quot;The Canadian Government hope that they mayhave an explicit assurance that, in respect of matters so vitallyconcerning this country, His Majesty&apos;s Government will not proceedupon the principle of deciding first and consulting the canadian government afterwards.&quot; Mr. Long stated that he must press forthe acceptance, of the principle of consultation, as urged by theCanadian GoA^ernment, and said that feeling on the subject avas very strong in Canada, where they Avere making special efforts to obtainrecruits and generally to assist in the prosecution of the avar, andconsequently keenly felt any omission to consult them in matters ofshipping, which affected the vital interests of the Dominion.The Minister of Shipping stated that he considered it would bea mistake to giare a definite assurance that in all cases the canadian government would! be consulted as to the transfer of shipping, as itavas impossible to do under avar conditions what it avas usual and necessary to do under conditions of peace, and that the move which caused the present trouble avas necessitated by the urgency ofcarrying American troops to France at the earliest possible moment.Mr. Bonar Law recalled that when he had been Secretary ofState for the Colonies a difficulty had arisen with the canadian government about the requisitioning of shipping, and that he hadgia^en a definite undertaking that, such would not be carried out infuture without the Dominion GoArernment being consulted.The War Cabinet decided that It was impossible to lay down a condition that the BritishGovernment must obtain the prior consent of the DominionGovernments with regard to the diversion of shipping, butrequested the Minister of Shippiug, if any similar cases&quot; arose in the future, to inform the Secretary of State for theColonies, in order that he could communicate,our intentions.12. With reference to War Cabinet 367, Minute 21, the WarCabinet had under consideration a Report of the War PensionsWarrant Committee (Paper G.-205).Mr. Barnes pointed out that the two main changes were anincrease in the amount payable to children, which would incur anadditional expenditure of about 30,000,000Z., and the addition toalternative pension of the widows of those who have been avell-to-do^which meant an extra 8,000,000/, or 9,00O,000Z.   All the otherC
Man-Power :Mobility ofMunitions Labouralterations, as set out in the Report, were of a trifling nature, andwere necessary as the result of experience gained in the working ofthe old Pensions Warrant. He added that the Treasury had agreedto the proposals contained in the new Warrant.The War Cabinet approved the Warrant as set out in paper g -205.13. The War Cabinet bad before them a memorandum byMr. Churchill, covering a minute by Sir Stephenson Kent (paper g.T.-4306), dealing with the question of a wide extension ofenrolment under the War Munitions Volunteer scheme.Mr. Churchill stated that, in order to secure the release of thelargest possible number of men for the army and to maintain thegreatest possible output of munitions, it was indispensable thatthere should be a greater control of the residuum of labour left behind in the workshops. It was necessary to bring great pressure to bear on everyone to enrol as a War Munitions Volunteer. Thosewho refused, and were not available to be moved about as required,should be made to understand that they stood a greater chance ofbeing recruited for the army. This proposal had been put to theTrade Union Advisory Committee, and they were whole-heartedly infavour of steps being taken to increase the mobility of the menremaining available for the munitions industry. He did not ask theTrade Union officials to commit themselves to an approval of what might be called &quot;industrial conscription&quot;; he contented himself with the general resolution set forth in the memorandum before theCabinet. The Advisory Committee were in favour of promiit action being taken. Mr. Churchill added that the removal of absolute pro-tection from trades and groups of workmen had resulted in verystriking improvement in output and in methods of production. Theproposals which he now was putting forward included the power toregulate and restrict employers in the use of labour of importanttypes of which there was a shortage, and of controlling the engage-in ent of labour by firms who are using labour unecononiically.Mr. Roberts said that he was in favour of the proposals, providedonly moral pressure was used to secure enrolment. If there were any open threat of compulsion there was sure to be trouble. Hethought the present moment propitious, and, if action were takenpromptly, the proposals might be accepted without much opposition.Mr. Chamberlain suggested that the public announcement, as drafted in the memorandum, was rather in the nature of a threat tothe men who did not enrol. It would be better so to word it as toprovide a special encouragement to the man who does enrol, and hasshown himself willing to place himself at the disposal of the State.The War Cabinet decided To approve the proposals of the Minister of Munitions, subjectto the modification in phrasing suggested by Mr. ChamberJain.Shipyard Labour.14. In the course of the discussion on the previous question,attention was called to the lack of co-ordination in the use of labourengaged in munitions and shipyards, and more particularly to thelow rate of progress with dilution in Admiralty yards.The Secretary was requested to place the subject on the agenda of the War Cabinet of Friday next, the 26th April.Man-Power: &apos; 15. The War Cabinet had before them a draft Order in CouncilRecruiting in prepared by the Minister of National Service, postponing indefinitelyIreland. the transfer by the Army Council to the Minister of National Serviceof the power to recruit in Ireland (Paper G.T.-4318).Sir Auckland Geddes explained that, under an Order in Council,
dated the 23rd October, 1917, the powers of recruiting, then vested in the Army Council, were transferred to the Ministry of NationalService. The Order contained a provision that the Minister mightpostpone its operation as regards any particular area in the United-Kingdom up to the 1st May, 1918. Under this provision, thetransfer of recruiting in Ireland had remained under the controlof the Army Council. In view of the present circumstances inIreland, he proposed that no change should be made. If theOrder in Council were not issued, recruiting would passautomatically to the Minister of National Service.Mr. Duke concurred in the proposal of Sir Auckland Oecldes.The War Cabinet decided To submit the draft Order in Council to His Majesty.Order of theBritish EmpireMedal.Naval Prize Bill.Port of london authority andTransport Workers&apos;Federation.16. With reference to War Cabinet 273, Minute 20, the WarCabinet had before them the Ueport of the Sub-Committee dealingwith the distribution of the British Empire Medal, with a coveringnote from Sir George Cave (Paper G.T.-1-268).Sir George Cave explained that the CabineCs proposal to distribute the medal in the proportion of one to every hundredworkers, the recipient to be nominated by the workpeople, had notbeen found to be acceptable, the reason being given that, where all had worked well, such a distinction would be invidious. The list of awards made at the New Year was limited to persons who hadperformed acts of great courage and self-sacrifice in different kinds of war service. That list had been very well received, and theSub-Committee now suggested that the difficulties of distributingthe medal on the basis originally proposed should be met by  (a.) Limiting the British Empire Medal to acts of courage orself-sacrifice, or specially distinguished service.(6.) Issuing at the end of the war a general medal to allpersons who had rendered war service for a certainlength of time and are not otherwise disqualified.Sir George Cave pointed out that it was not necessary to come to adecision on the second of the proposals at present.The War Cabinet decided To approve the first proposal.17. The War Cabinet had before them the draft of a Bill toamend the law relating to naval prize of war (Paper G.T.-4312).Dr. Macnamara explained that before the present war prize-money was given to the actual captors. The unfairness of this procedure had led to a discussion by the Admiralty in 1911, and, asa result, it had been agreed to recommend that prize-money shouldbe pooled for the whole, of the fleet and distributed under suitableregulations, so that all could share in it, whether captors or other-wise. The present Bill had been drafted to give effect to thisproposal. In repty to a question, Dr. Macnamara said that asummary of the proposals had been circulated to the dominions,and that, after discussion had taken place and certain amendmentshad been made, no objection had been raised to them by theSecretary of State for the Colonies.The War Cabinet authorised The Board of Admiralty to proceed&apos;with the Bill.-18. The attention of the War Cabinet was called to a dispute,arising from an application for an increase of wages, between theNational Transport Workers&apos; Federation and the Port of london authority. The workmen were willing to proceed to arbitration,but Lord Devonport, acting on behalf of the Port and Harbour
authorities of the Kingdom, was not only opposed to arbitration, hutunwilling to comply with the Arbitration Award if it went againstthe Port Authorities. The Ministry of Labour wished to proclaim astrike, so that the issue should be decided under the Munitions ofWar Acts. The men were in the right legally, as they were free to demand an increase in wages so long as they were prepared to acceptarbitration upon it.The War Cabinet decided To authorise the Ministry of Labour to advise His Majesty toissue the proposed proclamation.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,April 24, 1918.o

</content>
</cab>
