<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/6/0 images: 160-167</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property ..of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   May 1918.SECRET.anWAR CABINET, 404.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Friday, May 3, 1918, at 12 noon.Present :The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (in the Chair).The Right Hon.^ the Earl  Curzon of j Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. 0.Smuts, ICO.IgKEDLESTON, KG., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.EThe Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.1The Right Hon. austen chamberlain, M.P.The following were also present :-The Right Hon. A. .T. Balfour, O.M., \ Rear-Admiral   G.  P.   W.  Hope,   C.B.,M.P.:, Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Major-General Sir G. M. W. Macdonogh,K.C.M.G., O.B., Director of military intelligence (for Minutes 1 to 10).The Right Hon. Sir R. Chalmers, G.C.B.,Permanent Secretary, Treasury (for minutes 14- and 15).Deputy First Sea Lord (for Minutes 10to 12).Sir T. W. Holderness, G.C.B., K.C.S.I..Permanent Under-Secretary, India Office(for Minute 14).Sir L. Worthington Evans, Bart., M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry ofMunitions (for Minute 15).Lieutenant-Colonel W. Dally Jones, C.M.G., Acting Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel Leslie Wilson, C.M.G., D.S.O., M.P., Assistant Secretary.Captain L. F. Burgis, Assistant Secretary.The western front.1. THE Director of Military Intelligence reported that localfighting had taken place, to the advantage of the British forces, last night, in the neighbourhood of Villers-Bretonneux. Successful raids had been carried out south of Arras and east of St.-Venant, in thecourse of wdiich 10 prisoners and 5 machine guns were captured by our troops. Artillery had been active on both sides during the night, between Givenchy and the Foret de Nieppe, in the neighbour-hood of Lucre, and south of Ypres.G-erman Reserves.2. With reference to War Cabinet 402, Minute 1, the Directorof Military Intelligence stated that two fresh German divisions hadbeen identified in the line at Montdidier, which made a total of 106[1305-104]German divisions now engaged in the soxithern area of operationsNorth of the La Bassee Canal, the 3rd German Guard Division, which1 B
had previously been in the Somme area, was now in the Ypres-Comines battlefield. This made a total of 14-1 divisions engaged,and there were 15 fresh divisions in reserve, and 23 good divisionsavailable for roulement. The rest of the front was reported to belightly held, and information had been received that German artilleryhad been withdrawn from the Vosges area.Questioned as to the remainder of the front on which fightinghad. not taken place for a considerable period, General Macdonoghexplained the position on a map, and said that in Alsace, on the21st March, there were five German divisions in reserve, four ofwhich had been withdrawn, and there was now only one the 21stLandwehr Division there. In Lorraine there were three german divisions in reserve before the present battle started, which had all been moved. He pointed oiitthat the French reserves in these areashad also been moved, and, when asked as to whether there was nota possi bility of some active operations being undertaken in this area by the French troops, General Macdonogh expressed the opinionthat this was not possible.Austrians on the 3. With reference to the eight Austrian divisions mentioned in western Front. War Cabinet 400, Minute 9, the Director of Military Intelligence saidthat there was no definite information as to the exact position ofthese divisions, but that, as far as had been ascertained, they were still in Western Austria.Co-operation of the 4. With reference to War Cabinet 403, Minute 9, in reply to united States of a cpiestion as to the number of American troops now in the line, orAmerica. which would shortly be ready to take part in active operations,General Macdonogh said that the first division of Americans wasoperating with the French in the Montdidier area, and four other divisions were in the line on the eastern part of the French front.It was expected that Americans would be operating with theBritish troops by the end of May.It was pointed out that exaggerated reports were appearing inthe Press as to the number of men and aeroplanes which werebeing sent from America, and the opinion was expressed that itwould be advisable to stop the publication of these reports.. General. &quot;Macdonogh said that, as these reports all originated inAmerica, it would be very difficult, to stop them appearing in thePress of this country.Italian Offensive. 5. With reference to War Cabinet 403, Minute 3, the Directorof Military Intelligence reported that he had received a telegramfrom General Delme-Eadclifle to the effect that General Badogliothinks that a decision will be taken, probably within the next five or six days, as to an offensive on the Italian front. The telegramfurther stated that orders had meanwhile been given for the 11thItalian Division to be placed at once under Lord Cavards orders,for  tactical and instructional purposes. It was generally agreedthat the co-operation of British troops in the proposed operations would increase the moral of the Italian forces, and that these operations would be of valuable assistance, in anticipating any action which the Austrians might have in contemplation.Palestine. (3. With reference to War Cabinet 403, Minute 4, the Directorof Military Intelligence reported that the operations east of the jordan were continued on the 1st May. The 60th Division hadresumed the attack on El Hand, making some progress. An Australianmounted division had entered Es Salt at 4 a.M., capturing 350prisoners, including 33 Germans.   Two brigades had been left to
hold Es Salt, while two brigades moved south-west to attack theShumret Nimrin position from the east and north-east. A force ofthe enemy, estimated at 4,000 infantry, succeeded during the night of the 30th April and the 1st May, in crossing the Jordan from west to east, at Jisr Damie,and attacked the brigade which was protecting the British left flank. This brigade was forced back. During the retirement, three batteries of horse artillery supporting the brigadebecame entangled in the broken foothills of the mountains, and only three guns were able to retire, the remaining nine being abandoned,the detachments and most of the horses being, however, brought back.Reinforcements had been sent up, and the new line is now held by six regiments, supported by two additional batteries of artillery.General Macdonogh further reported that the enemy had carried outlocal attacks at Abu Felah, Mezrah, Berukin, and Haram Ridge,during the night of 30th April-lst May. These attacks wererepulsed. General Macdonogh said that operations were still beingcarried out by the Arabs in the Iiejaz, who had torn up more of therailway and had destroyed the telegraph lines.Attention was drawn to the good work of Major Lawrence inthis connection.Mesopotamia. 7. The Director of Military Intelligence reported that since27th April, the total captures by the IHrd Corps in Mesopotamiaincluded 1,950 prisoners, 3 mountain guns, 12 field guns, 25 machine-guns, and a quantity of transport, munitions, rifles, and otherbooty. General Macdonogh said that General Marshall had reportedthat he was making arrangements to capture Kerkuk, but that the underlying difficulty was one of maintenance, and that to maintainthe line of communications entailed, placing the whole of thelilrd Corps on reduced rations whilst operations lasted. general marshall had further said that he could only maintain troopspermanently at Kerkuk by supplying them from Tekrit, and had pointed out that, as the summer was now commencing, the climate conditions, due both to rain and heat, were a constant difficulty, inview of the lack of shelter and water. General Marshall recom-mended that the limit of his forward posts in the Illrd Corps area should be Tuz Khurmatli, as Kerkuk was so difficult of access, and said that he could maintain a mobile column at Khurmatli, which he felt sure would be able to deny to the Turks the use of theKerkuk-Suleimanieh road for wdieeled traffic. He proposed,as he was at present unable to send troops to Suleimanieh, tosend a lightly equipped mobile force, accompanied by Kurdlevies, to the rich agricultural district of Halabja, wdth a view toblockading that route into Persia, and to occupy Suleimanieh whenopportunity offered. General Macclonogh said that, from informa-tion that he had received, he did not consider that General Marshalhsreports as regards Kerkuk were quite correct; he had been informedthat the summer climate of Kerkuk was much better than that ofBaghdad.Persia. S. The Director of Military Intelligence stated that there was an unconfirmed report from Tabriz, dated 25th April, to the effectthat the Jelus had had a fight at Usbnu with Turkish troops, andhad captured 500 of them. The report stated that the turkish troops consisted of the Shivekan frontier company, the 1st battalion of the 22nd Regiment, the 2nd Battalion of the 2nd Regiment, witheight machine-guns and four guns. The Turks had sunk their guns in the Gadyr River. The Jelus were reported to be short ofcartridges and money.
Macedonia. Q. With reference to War Cabinet 384, Minute 5, and WarCabinet 387, Minute 2, attention was called to a telegram, dated the30th April, from General Guillaumat, in which he had reported tothe Supreme War Council in Paris that the assistance which had upto now been received from the Greeks was insignificant, and that ifthings did not go well on the Western front all Greece, and probablySerbia, would turn against the Allies.It was pointed out that this was an entirely new situation, andif it were true that there was any likelihood of the Serbians turning-round and opposing the Allied forces, the situation at Salonica wouldbecome very dangerous. General Macdonogh said that the reports which had been received lately from General Guillaumat as to the moral and the loyalty of the Serbians had been very bad.The War Cabinet requested  The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to telegraph to LordGranville, calling his attention to this telegram fromGeneral Guillaumat.10. The Deputy First Sea Lord reported that the with FishHydrophone Division on the previous afternoon had chased anenemy submarine from 7 miles south-west of Portland Bill to aposition 2 miles west of Blocknor Point. Almost immediately afterstopping, the armed cruiser &quot; Westphall&quot; struck a submergedobject with sufficient force to throw the fires out of the furnace.The division dropped twenty-five depth charges over and round thisspot, and buoyed the position, which was being watched hy trawlers and motor-launches. No oil or wreckage had yet been seen, but aperiscope was sighted from shore shortly before an explosion tookplace ahead of the trawlers.Bombing raids . 11. The Deputy First Sea Lord stated that fifteen machines had made a special mission low-bombing patrol from Dover, and that12 112-lb. and 8 20-lb. bombs had been dropped on or near themole at Zeebrugge. One machine had failed to return. two further bombing patrols had been made, and 12-230-lb. bombs hadbeen dropped on Zeebrugge lock-gates. One hit was observed inthe middle of the lock, and. there-were several very close to it. Twotorpedo-boats were observed at Zeebrugge on a northern course, andthere were also four or live ships seen alongside the mole.Despatch of 12. The War Cabinet had under consideration a memorandumAmerican Troops. by Lorci Milner, covering an agreement (Paper G.T.-4388), atelegram from Lord Reading dated 30th April, 1918 (Paper G.T.-4411), and a memorandum by the Ministry of Shipping (paper g.T.-4408) with reference to the despatch of American troops.It was pointed out that the original proposal was to tranship toFrance during the next three months some 480,000 Americaninfantry and machine-guns, but that now the Secretary of State forWar had come to an agreement with General Pershing to bring-over, in. the first place, the infantry, machine-guns, and signallersof six divisions, which would amount to about 72,000 troops, and&apos; then that no further infantry should be sent until the rest of the personnel of these six divisions had been shipped to France. Theresult of this would be that these six divisions would then becompleted and would form part of the American Army in France.This alteration of the original arrangements had interfered very considerably with the arrangements which had been made not only by Sir Joseph Maclay in regard to the utilisation of British shipping,but also with the preparatory work which had been done byLord Reading-, at the urgent request of the Prime Minister.
In view of the fact that full information would not be availableuntil the return of the Prime Minister and the Secretary of State forWar from France, the War Cabinet decided To defer further discussion on this question.Proposed British 13. With reference to War Cabinet 360, Minute 10, and WarMission to Japan. Cabinet 377, Minute 12, the War Cabinet had under considerationcorrespondence which had passed between the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs and Lord Beaverbrook, with notes by membersof the War Cabinet, on the subject of the proposed Mission to Japan(Paper G.T.-4412).It was pointed out that, at the discussion on this question onthe 1.8th March, Lord Derby had desired that a Military Missiononly should be sent to Japan, in order to present a baton to theMikado, but that the War Cabinet had generally agreed that it\ would be advisable for a Civil Commission to be sent, in order toremove from the minds of the Japanese the impression that we were doing badly in the war and to raise our prestige in Japan. no definite understanding had been arrived at that any distinguishedstatesman should be approached to head the Civil Mission, although in. the course of conversation some names had been suggested.Attention was called to War Cabinet 377, Minute 12, when itwas decided that the composition of the Mission should be left inthe hands of the Secretary of State for War, the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs, and Lord Beaverbrook, but it was agreed thatthis decision did not authorise Lord Beaverbrook to offer theposition of Head, of the Mission to anyone.The War Cabinet decided that-On reconsideration, it was inadvisable that a Civil mission should be sent to Japan.Shipment of 14. With reference to War Cabinet 399, Minute 15, the WarSovereigns to Cabinet had under consideration memoranda  by Lord IslingtonIndia- (Papers G.T.-4327 and 4383) with reference to the shipment ofsovereigns to India.Sir T. W. liolderness said that the Government of India was anxious to increase its metallic resources. At the juesent timethe Government of India had 2,500,000 in sovereigns, and anticipateto have between now and the end of July 5,000,000 more insovereigns from Australia and 15-rupee pieces ; but only some5,000,000 sterling in rupees. Silver was being obtained from america, but there were considerable delays. It was hoped that a first consignment of about 2,000,000 sterling would reach India bythe end of May, and that by the end of June a further large con-signment would arrive. He pointed out, however, that this silvermust be coined, and that the Government of India was anxious about their position during May, June, and July, as to meetingpajunents for necessary War purchases, for which it was anticipatedthat they would require from 10,000,000 to 15,000,000 sterling.If 5,000,000 sovereigns could be sent to India between now and theend of June, the ability of the Government of India to finance these purchases for the British Government would be much more assured.Sir T. W. Holderness said that the Colonial Office had been askedto arrange with the Australian Government for the shipment of1,500,000 sovereigns at a time, against bullion which would be shipped from India to Australia. Between now and the end ofJuly about 2,500,000 sovereigns might, in this way, be obtained.Questioned as to the method in which the 5,000,000 sovereignsrequired could be transported. Sir T. W. Holderness said thatthe only practical way was across the Continent to Taranto, and thence by despatch-boat across the Mediterranean to Egypt.
Sir R. Chalmers pointed out that the difficulties were : (a.) That the immediate convertibility could not be assuredto-day by the despatch now of 5,000,000 sovereigns.(b.) That it would be very difficult to ship the gold to India.(c.) That the gold was not available unless it were taken fromthe gold reserve at the Bank of England, or the reserveheld against Treasury notes.He was of opinion that the immediate requirement of India wassilver, and that the silver would arrive in India as quickly assovereigns could possibly arrive from England. He added thatthere was no gold in England that was free.The Chancellor of the Exchequer was of opinion that it wouldbe most inadvisable to send any more sovereigns from Englandunless there was real danger in India, as there was no gold available the transmission of which would not show depletion of our balance.The War Cabinet recognised the difficulties of India, and thatthe failure to send sovereigns might affect the power of India toprovide supplies for this country and the Allies. But it appearedso unlikely that the despatch of 5,000,000 sterling could be effected in time, and, if effected, would be sufficient in amount to preventinconvertibility, that it was not justifiable to incur the certain risks of transport, and the certain disadvantages of withdrawing the goldfrom London for such a problematical advantage, to India.The War Cabinet decided that (or..) It would not be right to ship gold from the United kingdom to India at present;(6.) In view of the possibility that currency difficulties mightrender impossible in due course purchases in India upto the full requirements of the various Imperial Depart-ments, the Chairman of the Royal Commission on wheat supplies, the Secretary of State for War, the Minister ofMunitions, and the Food Controller should investigateas to the reduction which each of their departments could make in its requirements if reduction became necessary.Norwegian Pyrites. 15. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinistry of Munitions (Paper G.T.-4424) with reference to thepurchase of pyrites from Norway. The memorandum asked for authority to purchase 250,000 tons of pyrites at terms which hadbeen reached with the Norwegian Government, and which, in theopinion of the negotiators sent to Norway by the Ministry ofMunitions, and of Sir M. Findlay, were the best that could besecured. The memorandum stated that, at the present moment,nine-tenths of our pyrites supply came from Spain, and it was most desirable to have a second source of supply.The Chancellor of the Exchequer stated that, whilst realisingthe importance of coming to an agreement with Norway, the priceasked by them was higher than that which we paid for pyrites in spain, and. the result of paying a higher price in Norway would beto force up the Spanish price. He appreciated the fact that theNorwegian Government had intimated that the offer was only openuntil the 4th May, and that, if it was refused, Germany might be willing to pay a higher price and store the pyrites until deliverycould be made. It was possible, however, that this was only bluff.Also, according to Lord Reading&apos;s telegram No. 1950, dated the1st May, an American-Norwegian agreement had been signed which,it was understood, contained a clause to the effect that the export ofpyrites to enemy countries would entail a cessation of the import ofwheat from America.
2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,May 3, 1918.Sir Worthington Evans said that, if this was an ordinary business transaction, he would certainly advise holding out to see whether the Norwegian Government would reduce their terms ; buthe felt that, as the pyrites was so urgently needed for war purposes,we should close with the offer, and not run the risk of losing this source of supply. He suggested that Sir M. Findlay should beauthorised to conclude the best agreement possible with theNorwegian Government.The War Cabinet decided that The price asked by the Norwegian Government for the250,000 tons of pyrites was not a fair one, and the Ministryof Munitions should make further endeavours to concludean agreement at a lower figure.


</content>
</cab>
