<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/40/0 images: 7-11</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel Jones J*&apos; (This Document is the Property of 1SECRET. His Britannic Majesty&apos;? CovernroerfcW w0? 17        &apos; *01/143/41019.1.18.^-^-^^^V     MEMORANDUM ON A PROPOSAL TO RAISE A FORCE OF&apos; 1 &quot;\ \ 200,000 MEN IN ABYSSINIA.gTJALLj^^ In accordance with the request of the War Cabinet I ;,324/2. forward the following observations regarding the question of raising a force of 200,000 Abyssinians as suggested by M. Clemenceau.   I may say at once that arguments as to the fitness of African forces for employment in the major theatres, based on the proved capacity of&quot;Africans for warfare in their own country and under native conditions, are to a great extent illusory.   This is particularly so in the case X)f Abyssinia, where,, apart from the mere fighting qualities of the men in their own-country, practically all conditions are opposed to the possibility of raising a military force for service with the Entente Armies.2.     The military qualities of Abyssinians are fully apprec-iated by the British officers who have come into contact with them, either as enemies on the borderlands of British East-Central African possessions, or as elements in British native formations.   An experienced British officer speaks of them thus i-&quot;The Abyssinian is extremely independent and is generally unaccustomed to discipline,,   The men recruited for the Kings African Rifles (in East Africa) required very careful handling, but have proved excellent fighters (in Africa).   They are faithful, smart, and intelligent&quot;.The Italian authorities in Somaliland and Eritrea alwaysspeak in the highest possible terms of their Abyssinian askaris,in whom they place much confidence (again, for African warfare).Though venereal and other diseases have played havoc with greatmasses of the Abyssinian population, there are many who arehardy, enduring, capable of living on simple food, and needing,in their native warfare, little in the way of transport orimpedimenta.   The proposition to raise large forces from thissource is therefore prlma facie attractive.   The practicaldifficulties, however, are very great, and probably insurmountable.(&apos;.&apos; .     ;;   - 3.        &apos; j;
The principal difficulties to the formation of a large , .. , Abyssinian force are :-(a) The racial, religious, and political situation ?f the country,.v.   ,   There are four main racial divisions, and many sub-div-isions, in the total population of 7-g - 8 millions. Abyssinians proper - Include Tigreans (of the north &amp; north-east); Lasta (of the north); and Amharas. Gallas inhabit the central and south-western provinces; Somalis the eastern and south-eastern provinces; and Negroid tribes the western provinces. Of these, the Gallas are numerically (3 millions) and militarily perhaps the most important, and are also the most accessible.The Shoans are also important, and,are an admixture of Abyssinian and Galla blood.All these races and provinces, ill-defined, and ruled by semi-independent princes, are mutually antag-onistic, and internecine warfare is chronic, having reached its climax in the serious internal var provoked by the reversion of Lij Yasu to Islam, and the Shoan revolt, resulting in a state of chaos which still per-sistSe; The multiplicity of religions accentuates theseconditions, a debased (Coptic) Christianity, Roman Catholicism, Mahomedanism, Paganism, and the Jewish faith, all being represented, and all being mutually intolerant.   One-fifth of the Abyssinian population is included in an ignorant and dissolute priesthood, exempt from military service.    The important Mahomedan element is anti-Entente,There exists no central established Government and consequently no authority capable of enforcing a general native law of compulsion to military service, . .      &apos;&quot; -&apos;- :----- &apos; or
or of assisting an outside party to apply measures of its own, or even of organising any extensive recruiting on a voluntary basis.Any extensive recruiting amongst one race, or in one province, would provoke the attack of neighbours who would profit by the weakening of the race or province affected. Any attempt to conduct such recruiting would fail before the opposition of the ruler thus exposed to attack. ^)   Linguistic diffioo-lties^-A common language for command and administration would be necessary.    (This difficulty, in the case of British recruits, is surmounted by making them sufficiently acquainted with English, the language of command, or with Kiswahili, the lingua franca of East Africa,   This is possible only with small numbers).Each of the important races of Abyssinia speaks a distinct language, and the official language (Amharic) is understood by very few Europeans.   There are many dialects mutually incomprehensible.British (and it may be added, German) experience proves that for warfare against an enemy possessing modern equipments, even in Africa, it is necessary to provide European personnel in the proportion of 30 Officers and about 30 non-commissioned officers per 1,000natives, and these must either be specialljr-selected men with previous experience of the natives they are to train and lead, or else be specially chosen for their likelihood to acquire the special qualities necessarjr,For a native force of 200,000 at least 6,000 Europ-eans Officers, and the same number of non-commissioned officers would be needed in the first instance, together with drafts for maintenance at (say) 10 per cent per month.4.
Taking all the Allisd States together, the number of their subjects who have practical experience of the handling of any natives is very small, and these are virtually all now employed in occupations from which they cannot be withdrawn without detriment to important interests.    Of these, the number who are acquainted with Abyssinia or its inhabitants is infinitesimally s:&apos;iallf   Of these again the proportion who are of military age, or who possess any military qualifications whatsoever will be still smaller.It will, therefore, be realised that it would be virtually impossible to form the necessary cadres, even by pooling the qualified resources of all the Allies, and if it were possible, the linguistic problem in the cadres themselves would be impossible of solution, apart from the difficulty of establishing a common tongue for communication with the natives.(c).   Recruiting,-As explained above, the application of compulsion is out of the question.   A policy of inducements is the only alternative, and, since Abyssinians have no direct interest in the present conflict, this would resolve Itself into an attempt to raise a mercenary army by the offer of rates of pay in excess, in some cases, of those given to combatant European troops.   Such a procedure would obviously be undesirable, and there is no guarantee whatever that it would effect its purpose, or produce any results commensurate with the expenditure of money and energy Involved.
General Staff,War Office, S.W.1,19th January,&apos; 1918.4.      The conclusion is that native forces can only be used to advantage, in the major theatres, in diluting European elements, preferably in the auxiliary services.   This is the policy adopted, and non being carried out, by us.

</content>
</cab>
