<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/40/0 images: 128-129</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
From: C.M.A, To:    D.M.I.D, 2,30 p,nv 20.1.18. R, 11.30 a,m. 21.1.18,240 Jan. 20th.Weekly summary of week ending Jan.19th.\Xpolitical.   Bolshevik element of head military control committee had a split with the other members and have now left Committee. Proposals made by G.0.C, 3rd  Turkish Army to &quot;Independent Trans-Caucasus Government&quot; to make a separate peace with Turkey.   In spite-&quot; of desire of Georgians and other elements trans-Caucasus Government eventually decided to pass proposals to Constituent Assembly of all Russia.    Reply will be sent to this effect and also that in the &quot;capital of trans-Caucasus&quot; peace delegates cannot be received,, further that trans-Caucasus forms part of great Russian Republic and that it cannot entertain separate negotiations.Pressure has been brought on General Prjevalski by Georgian trans-Caucasus Government to resign;    -G.O.C. is now temporarily General Le Bedinoki former Chief of the Staff,   New War Minister   -Gubachia, a Georgian; Donski has left Constituent Assembly.   New Committee has been formed of Representatives of all nationalities for formation of national units Prosident Ramishvili a Georgian.   It is likely that Committee will have great influence.   Representatives are proportional to strength of national units,- Woot of Baku and near Alexandrople small Tartar disturbances have occurred against Armenian villages.Bolshevik element considerably weaker;   strength practically concentrated in Baku area.In the past fortnight the political strength of the trans-Cauoasus Government has improved, 500 new Militia arrived reoently fromKutais;   punishment has been inflicted for shooting strays; this has sensibly decreased.Military.Presidents of all national Committees interviewed during the week results satisfactory Tartar sincerity questionable however though professionally ? professedly in accord, &quot;in Baku Patrovsk and Elizabetoya Turkish Officers are still agitating.   Information from reliable sources points to desire of Tartars to act with Turks to remove all Russian influence in the Caucasus dealing later with the Armenians.   On the other hand President of Tartars Committee assured me that they were willing to take their share defence of the front. The Georgian military strength is insignificant they do not wish to go-to the front.Shortly decrees are to be issued for the mobilisation of all nationalities for 6 months of all males of 19 years from Jan, lot 1918 (OS) and for those under military obligation to serve of 32 and under for 6 months to return to national units.   Non-inhabitants of trans-Caucasus to serve outside Trans-Cauoasus if they leave at once.The question of the new rate of pay of men has not yet been settled. * - JIntelligence..
Intelligence.Peace overtures made &quot;by G.0.C, 3rd Array see your (?my) telegram 528.Reconnaissance in Erzinjan sector dis&amp;ever (?ed) (?) no (?) Turks for a distance of 15 miles (Armenian information)Finanoe.Issue of bonds of 5 roubles and 10^ roubles denomination is proposed by Trans-Caucasus Government.   Baku local Government proposes issue of bonds up to 20,000,000,   Don republic proposes same up to 2,000,000,   Kuban provinces requests payment of 20,000,000 for food supplied;   it threatens otherwise to stop the supply of food.   Money is scarcer than ever here,   Pood stuff supply-question may force trans-Caucasus Government into ooalition with South Eastern Union. Especially if a loan is arranged more difficulties may force them to deal more in accordance with use,Prasaganda,Reuter telegrams are now in all local papers.C2, Copies te M,I,l.a.

</content>
</cab>
