<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/40/0 images: 132-134</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
EG^OlTHEijT IS ths property of HIS BRmflJEIC majesty1 S/0     V\   XJ    i. 93429.ehployi^ht 0? J-iPANESS troops OB theMemorandum by Mr, P.aEPiggott. formerly Constitutional Adviser &quot;go the Japanese  rTme Minister.; (1)Copy of letter from Mr. Pir-gott to Private Secretary to Prime Minister..Tower House,, Tite Street,, Chelsea, S.E.3. 18 Jan. 1918,Dear Mr. Davies,I have cast what I am anxious to say to the Prime Minister into the form of a Memorandum, which I enclose herein. If you should think it of sufficient importance to lay before Mr. Lloyd George will you be good enough to do so. But if you think it covers no new ground pray do not trouble him with it.The memorandum is based on confidential talks I have recBntly had with two leading newspaper editors.   Their information, given independently, tallied in all respects.   I view the position with some disquiet, as it seems to me to contain the seeds of future disturbance of our relations with Japan,   I do not wish to be unduly alarmist; but having been in the Japanese service I know the defects as veil as the virtues of their character.I do however believe that the Mission, dexterously handled, may be the means of eradicating those seeds before they germinate; and it is in that belief that I have written the memorandum.   The nature of it is such tfcat I have thought it advisable to mark it &quot;secret&quot;.If I can in any way throw any additional light on the question I am entirely at the Prime Ministers service.Believe me, Very truly yours,(Sd)   F.*T.Piggott.P.S.   My position in Japan was that of Constitutional Adviser to the Prime Minister, and I remained, a oersonal friend of &quot;Prince Ito till his death.
chit-The baton is the means; the end to be achieved the despatch o of Japanese troops to the Western front,I assume that the Japanese, if they send troops, will send an effective force: say, 400,000 men; and that the Shipping Controller believes that the question of bringing these troops to 3urope is not an unsurmountable difficulty.   It may involve considerable trouble to organise; but the result of having so large a body of efficient troops thrown on to the ?/estern front in the early summer -70uld be so far-reaching, that no difficulty of transport can be e-onsidered insuperable.I assume also that the baton will be taken to Japan by a Mission, end that it \7ill propose to the Smperor the sending of the troops.But between the despatch of the Mission and the accomplish-ment of its ultimate object lies a -?hole field of policy which requires most serious consideration.The fact must be recognised that at the present moment public feeling is running strongly against Japan.   The appointment of the 3mperor as Field Marshal excited no enthusiasm, very little interest.   The impression is very widely spread that Japan Is not pulling her full strength in the War; that she thinks that with the operations at Tsingtao, and the assistance she has given and is giving at sea, her share in the War is accomplished: that having secured Tsingtao, the rest is represented by the very large commercial profits which she is making.Further, an Idea is abroad either that she has been asked to send troops and has refused: or that she has offered troops and they have been declined.Only those who understand the subtle irorking of the Sastern mind can appreciate exactly what is passing in that mind at present. It may be taken for granted that the Japanese know the state of public feeling in England, and that they are annoyed that ifc should be what it is.   It is generally known that mistakes have been made in the proposals -vhich have been made to her.   Thus the reouest that she should supply labourers behind the line has galled her pride as a military nation.Again, Japan is practically the only friendly nation to which a Mission has not been sent: and to her the pomp and circumstance of a Mission means much.Her present mood is one of irritation.   But the custom of the East requires a sufficiently plausible explanation of the absence of her troops in the line, and &quot;vant of shipping&quot; has served the purpose.So far I have only referred to matters ^hich lie on the surface. But there are far more serious opinions abroad, though I do not think that at present they are very wide-spread; and it ie doubtfiil whether the Japanese are at present conscious of them.   These opinions are, first, that Japan is ready to attack Russia: secondly, that she has an ulterior design of making an alliance with Germany after the War.Ho one who knows Japan conld entertain either of these opinions for a moment.   But the fact that they do exist shows the position to be far from satisfactory politically.   The seeds of distrust may, if they are not choked, develop  prejudicially to the future relations of the two countries.
It is c. fact that tho 3omans in Japan have not been interned.     It is also a fact that there is an extensive German propaganda in the country, which has not at present been counteracted on our side.      But it must be romembered that the Alliance with England is &amp; thing which affects every individual Japanese.   It causes them personal pride.     -he German propaganda may not affect the Govern-ment, but it will reach.the individual;   and if. this personal feeling of friendship for.England were to disappear one of the^&apos;mainstays of the alliance would break down.I believe that if the instructions to the Mission are conceived in s spirit sympathetic with Japanese feeling and idiosyncrasies, it may he msde the instrument not merely for removing present ill-feeling on both sides, but also for strengthening the relations of the two countries in. the future.Japan has adhered to the declaration of the allies not to conclude a separate peace;   but -she has not, I think,- as yet joined the &apos;.;:-r Alliance formally,   tfhrrfc she h?s done so far hDS been in virtue of the Treaty of Alliance with -England.I venture to suggest, therefore, that the special function of the mission should be to invite Japan to join the war alliance, and to induce the Emperor to make a. declaration of Vv&amp;r : irns in terms similar to thoee of the Prime Minister, with v, special reference to her future relations   ith Germany,decent utterances of the Cmperor and his Ministers indi cats that the accomplishment of this should not be difficultThis done the despatch of troops should follow as a matter of course, :;.-nd the shipping difficulties, I have no doubt, will be overcome.(Signed)     FfT.?IGGOTT,18th January 1918.

</content>
</cab>
