<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/40/0 images: 278-284</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Intelligence Bureau,Department of Information. BPW/024.Weekly^Report on Poland.   XXIV. (25th January. 1918.)1.    The peace negotiations at Brest-Litovsk have found polish public opinion and Polish politicians as unprepared as had the outbreak of the war.    For a whole century they had boen talking about the European War from which Poland was to emerge free and reunited; they have schemed, prepared, conspired.    But when the war came it found them incapable of any effective con-certed action.    For the last three years Polish political parties and the press have been discussing Poland&apos;s position at the coming Peace Congress.    But now when the fate of Poland is discussed at Brest one would search in vain for any trace of a conscious will or of independent thinking.     In a kind of paralytic torpor they watch the unfolding of events, trying pathetically to look wiee and diplomatic.    But below that surface one can see the unspeakable mleere of Polish political life and of Polish intellectual brilliancy.    The daily news from Brest appears in the press without even an attempt being made at comment or dis* cuesion; the public reads it with a bewildered and yet placid vacuity.2.     &quot;Warsaw watches with much interest the peace negotiations at Brest-Litovek as one watches sensational events,&quot; wrote the Warsaw correspondent of a Piotrkoff daily, about lew Yearfs Day. &quot;Yet a deeper foundation is lacking to that interest.    It came to be more real when the question was raised of the -evacuation of Poland by the occupying armies.     Serious anxiety came to be felt for the future, and in the absence of a Polish army the fear&apos;
- 2 -nas arisen of^olaneviem^reading to Poland.&quot;    1ft the Ukraine the agrarian movement 1b in full swing, the oonfisoation of the big landed estates, mostly owned by Poles, has been authorised by the Ukrainian Rada.     In the parts of Lithuania which have remained under Russia the peasant revolt iB aflame.    And in the districts of Lithuania and he Ukraine which remain under Austrian and German occupation Ukrainian, white Russian and Lithuanian peasants, another correspondent informs us, &quot;look with a covetous eye at the land of the Polish nobility&quot;.      &quot;Hence the fear of contact with Russia and the instinct of self-preservation are apt to subdue other political eJ-ms,&quot; writes the Warsaw correspondent of the Kur^er Lwowski, a Galician paper friendly to the national Democrats.     &quot;In Poland there is less reason for such fears (than In Lithuania etc.), but still they exist.    The desire is steadily growing among the Conservatives for a State in which law and order prevail, protecting the &apos;upper classes&apos; ....... voices are raisedmore and more frequently among the land-owning ciroles arguing in favour of a Polieh army for internal purposes.&quot;      &quot;Disquieting news is reaching us from the oountry,&quot; writes the Lublin -correspondent of the Nowa Reforma  under date of January 1, &quot;that the movement and watchwords now current in Russia are beginning to filter through to us across the front.    Upper class circles demand energetic coUnter-aotion.&quot;     And Archbishop Kakowski in an unctuous New Year address, when he came to catechise whatever there survives of the Polish Legions, addressed them as follows: &quot;Let the Polish soldier take courage and be ready to shed his blood in defence of law and order at home, and in defence of the frontiers of a wide, whole, independent Polish fatherland.&quot;    It will be remarked that &quot;law and order&quot; come first.3.    The Poles have been caught unprepared.     Their mindU . eye beheld a detailed picture of a Peace Congress at which the Polish Question was to be the centre of all discussion and they
fthemselves-the ^ourt ed arbiters in a difficult   diplomatic situation full of intricate intrigue and of far-reaching possibilities - in a field worthy of Talleyrand as he appeare to the free and fertile imagination of Polish politicians.    But events have taken a very different turn.    Without having made any serious independent effort in the war, the Poles had dreamt of wide acquisitions, of a new Polish dominion over Lithuania, White Russia and the Ukraine, acquisitions larger than those contemplated in Europe by any of the Great Powere.    And what is their position now?    Their plans, nay even the foundations of their plans, are breaking down with a rapidity which hardly leaves time for a cry of protest.     &quot;The ground is cut away from under our feet over there (in Lithuania and theUkraine)    whines the correspondent of the Kurjer Lwowski.    &quot;They are taking the land (of the Polish nobility).    then the land is once divided among the peasant a, what government, however reactionary, will be able to take it back from them?&quot;    While the only baBis of Polish dominion is thus disappearing,, these peasant nations are also organising themselves into States, and their States are receiving the recognition of the great Powers.    Polish claims to ethnographic Lithuania, which embraces the Government of Kovna  and parts of the Governments of Vilna, Grodna and Suwalki, have gone to &quot;the land where the dead dreams goH* &apos;   Their claims to Ukrainian land have become a joke.    The Ukrainians at Brest now hold the key to the European position.    They can give to Austria the peace and the food which alone can stave off revolution in Austria. Can any one suppose that Count Czernin would at such a moment hand over Ukrainians to heir hereditary enemies, the Poles? That, the Polee will not even retain the dominion over Bast Galicia whioh under Austrian auspices they have exercised for the last fifty years, and which was assigned to them once more in a more complete form in the first days of November last, is now
certain.     It only remains to be seen whether Austria will hare to make a clean cession of Bast Galicia to the tfkraine or whether she will be able to retain it as a completely self-governing Ukrainian province in which the big landed estates, all at preeent in the hands of Poles or of Polonised Jewe, will be transferred to theUkrainian peasants.     As was indicated in our Report No.XVII of October 4, 1917, the occupied districts of White Russia - most of the Government of Grodna and the southern part of the Government of Vilna - are likely to remain the only territory into which the Poles may yet hope to extend their frontiers by the grace of the Central Powers, if the Russians prove unable to carry their demand for free national self-determination for the occupied districts.4.    Three different proposals have been put forward with regard to self-determination in the occupied districts.    Russian representatives demand a complete evacuation and a free plebiscite; the Germans speak of ^elected and supplemented representative bodies&quot;, i.e., they want to maintain the governments or councils which have been set up in Poland, Lithuania and Courland merely &quot;supplementing&quot; them; no doubt in a manner to suit their own convenience.    The Austrians begin to speak of a Polish Con-stituent Assembly.     A referendum is a crude method and certainly does not lend itself to a discussion of complicated proposals and of politioal bargains.     How could, e.g., Austria develop her own Polish scheme through a popular vote?    On the other hand she is afraid of the German proposal and sees for herself the best chances in a Constituent Assembly elected in a manner sufficiently free to keep out German official influences, but sufficiently restricted to exclude the extreme Left.     It is perhaps with the Austrian proposal of a Constituent Assembly that the Poles will fall in.     Y/hat the feelings of the Polish upper classes must be with regard to the Russian demand which implies an immediate evacuation of Poland by the enemy and the return of the evacuated
can be judged by reading any of the innumerable accounts of what is now happening beyond the Russian front.5.     he following is a description of the pogrom at Hlevin as it appeared in the Dziennik Kijowski of November 25,    MM. Raczkowski and Jaronski mentioned therein were both Polish National Democrat members of the Duma, and the former came to London with the Duma Delegation in 1916.&quot;Dziennik M in ski reports that the manor house at Hlevin was surrounded by crowds of peasants, women and children.    By torch-light the mob began to plunder and within a few hours carried off more than a hundred cows and horses, all the agricultural imple* ments, oars, grain, etc..    Not content with this the peasantsV tried to storm the manor house itself.    The brother of Mrs. Swida, M. Raczkowski, member of the Duma, M. Jaronski, another member of the Buma who was staying at the house, and tf. Swida defended all night with firearms the entrance to the house.    Having thus passed the night the besieged inmates of the house asked the peasants to allow them to drive off to the railway station but were answered that if they liked, they might walk to Borisoff, which is eight miles distant.     Even the request for permission to take away in a carriage the mother of Mrs. Swida, Mrs. Raczkowski, a woman eighty years old, and her sister, was refused. Finally a Jew came up round the bskfik of the house and agreed to take the two old women to Borisoff.    The others, sinking in mud up to the knees, aocompanied the miserable vehicle.     It was found impossible to remove a cousin of M. Swida who was ill.    The relations with the peasants at Hlevin had previously been of the test.    Mrs. Swida was able to recognise among the robbers patients whom she had looked after during illness.    Hlevin has been completely burnt down.    Thus perish our most Cultural* big landed estates which we have held for centuries.    No one was allowed to carry away anything from the house.&quot;
6.     Instead of appearing as diplomats at an old-world peace congress, the Poles have to answer the straight question whether they prefer as the lesser of two evils /the German and Austrian military occupation or an immediate evacuation which would put them at the mercy of their good and loving peasantry.There can hardly be any doubt that the Polish Regency Counoil and the Prime Minister during their recent visite to Berlin have come to some practical understanding with the Central Powers.    We may assume it as certain that some kind of secret alliance has been concluded, though its terms are likely to be vague as yet because the basis for defined, detailed terms is lacking. Probably a certain number of concessions have been made by the Central Powers concerning the transfer of the administration in Poland to the Poles themselves and concerning the formation of a Polish army-   - On the other hand the Poles are likely to have undertaken some general obligations with regard to the future political, military and economic relations of Poland with the Central Powers.    The common fear of revolution is thus likely to have produced an agreement.     As was pointed out in our last report, the Germans fear social revolution in Poland and Lithuania almost as much as do the polish upper classes themselves.    Herr von Kflhlmann said so on January 24 in words of which it is not difficult to read the full meaning: &quot;The fundamental difference between our conception and that of the Russian Delegation is that, contrary to it, we wish to see arise in those regions, without abrupt or violent transition, an orderly State, and that we decline to adopt, out of sheer altruism, the theory of creating a vacuum ......n7.    The position of the Poles in Russia is becoming ex-oeedingly difficult.     The front runs just through those regions inwhich the Polish noble landowners are now being forcibly ousted by their White Russian Or Little Russian peasants.     In the
m   f   mdecaying Russian army the Polish soldiers are naturally gathering into national groups of their own.    What attitude are these groups to assume towards the internal Russian struggle where Poles are personally concerned in them?    The Polish Socialists -and their numbers seem to be growing rapidly - declare their proletarian solidarity with the peasants in revolt.    The non-Socialists are naturally tempted to defend their compatriots in a foreign land against what after all in detail is anarchical lawlessness.    But should they attempt it on any considerable scale, national war is likely to break outf between them on the one hand, and the Ukrainians and Russians on the other, of which the consequences cannot be foreseen as yet.    And also civil war among the Poles themselves.H. Lednioki, in view of his connection with the Cadets and  -Jt. Kerensky, has been removed from the Chairmanship of the Liquidation Committee, and a Polish Bolshevik, U* Leszcisynski, has been appointed Commissioner for&quot; Polish Affaire.    The Polish National Biamacrat^rees aasert*--that he is a Jew, which is not true.25.1.18.

</content>
</cab>
