<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/87/0 images: 130-131</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
5 (THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)iSECRETC.(57) 122 COPY NO. U**S16th May, 1957CABINETNIGERIANote by the Lord chancellor the Colonial Policy Committee have further discussedparagraph 19 of the memorandum circulated with C. (57) 120.2. The Committee now submit for consideration a revised version of the declaration set out in that paragraph, designed toavoid any commitment on the part of Her Majesty&apos;s Government toa precise date for the grant of Federal independence to Nigeria.While the Colonial Secretary sees merit in the revised version,he wishes to reflect further on it, and will report his final vieworally to the Cabinet.K.Lord Chancellor!s Department, S.W.1.16th May, 1957.NIGERIA:  PROPOSED TEXT OF DECLARATION&quot;The United Kingdom Government have noted the resolution passed in the House of Representatives on 26th March in favour of independence for Nigeria within the Commonwealth in 1959.    Inparticular they welcome the increased sense of unity among the political parties which enabled the resolution to be adopted without a dissentientvote.    For their part the United Kingdom Government have alwaysfirmly believed.that it is in the best interests of the peoples of Nigeriathat the unity of the country should be preserved.2. The United Kingdom Government have agreed to amend the Constitution so as to permit the appointment of a Prime Ministerat the Centre and the withdrawal of the ex officio Members from theCouncil of Ministers during the period until the life of the presentHouse of Representatives comes to an end in 1959.3. Thereafter, if it is still the wish of the Nigerian people to attain independence within the Commonwealth, and assuming that in the interim the Governments in the Federation have demonstrated their
capacity for good and stable government, the United Kingdom Governmentwill confer with all the Nigerian Governments to determine the processes whereby the Federation of Nigeria would advance towardsindependence within the Commonwealth.    In the view of Her Majesty1 sGovernment, an integral element in such processes would be theappointment of a Constitutional Commission to make recommendations for the framing of a Constitution for a fully independent Nigeria.It would in particular be the duty of the Commission to review thepresent Constitution of the Federation in the light of the experience gained since its inception and to consider the constitutional and other changes which would be necessary to enable the Federation to become eligible for full membership of the Commonwealth.    Included within these matters would be the making of special constitutional provisions to safeguard tribal and religious minorities and full regard would bepaid to the wishes of both the northern and southern sections of the trust Territories of the Cameroons under the United Kingdomadministration and to the United kingdom s responsibilities under theUnited Nations Charter and tne Trusteeship Agreement.i. Meanwhile, certain preliminary administrative steps arebeing taken.    It has been agreed that the Government of the Federationwill assume responsibility for the Nigerian military forces on1st April, 1958.    An expert study of the problems connected with theestablishment of a Central Bank and of a Nigerian currency hasalready begun with the assistance of an adviser from the Bank of England;and further measures will be taken towards training Nigerians for a future foreign service&quot;.

</content>
</cab>
