<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/87/0 images: 146-149</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  May 1957CONFIDENTIAL Copy No. g QC. (57) 12728th May, 1957CABINETTHE LAW OF THE SEAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe last statement of Government policy on the law of the sea was that of14th December, 1953, concerning the delimitation of the territorial sea (Annex A).This statement reaffirmed our adherence to the three-mile limit and pronouncedagainst the application to our coasts of the baseline system of measurement whichhad been approved in defined circumstances in the Anglo-Norwegian FisheriesJudgment of the International Court of Justice.2. Since 1949 the whole complex of the law of the sea (both the high seas *and the territorial sea) has been under study by the International Law Commission(I.L.C.), the advisory body of jurists to the United Nations. The I.L.C. weregiven the task of codifying the law of the sea and advising what progressivedevelopments of international law might be required. Their final report was prepared last year and the principal conclusions and proposals are summarised in annex B.3. The I.L.C. proposed to the General Assembly that their report shouldbe considered at an international conference where all aspects of the problem technical, biological, economic and political, as well as legal could be considered and whatever measure of agreement might be reached could be embodied in aninternational convention.4. The general tenor of the report is broadly consonant with the attitudes of&quot; free seas &quot; countries such as the United Kingdom, while offering sufficient to the&quot; coastal State &quot; school to make agreement possible, given a reasonable approach on both sides to the problems. We therefore joined with the Americans and others in co-sponsoring in the General Assembly at the session recently concluded aresolution supporting the I.L.C.&apos;s proposal in paragraph 3 above, which wasadopted without opposition and with only three States (Iceland, Iraq, Libya)abstaining. The International Conference on the Law of the Sea will be held in geneva or in Rome in March and April 1958.5. The issues to be negotiated there are of great importance to the strategic,mercantile and fishery interests both of the United Kingdom and of the Coloniesespecially in view of the serious threat to the traditional three-mile limit of \territorial sea arising from the claims of many countries to wider and differinglimits. The Conference will offer an opportunity of seeking lasting agreement tosafeguard our essential needs in a world situation which has been moving againstthe &quot; free seas &quot; countries. It is most desirable therefore that a strong UnitedKingdom delegation should attend it and, still more, that the intervening time should be devoted to creating, in association with like-minded, well-disposed anduncommitted States, a negotiating position which will be firm on essentials and atthe same time sympathetic towards the reasonable claims of the &quot; coastal States.&quot;The General Assembly Resolution convening the International Conference itselfcalls upon Governments &quot; to utilise the time remaining .... for exchanges of viewson the controversial questions relative to the law of the sea.&quot; Special attention willhave to be paid to Commonwealth countries, particularly new entrants, such as51689
India and Ghana, and prospective entrants, such as Malaya, and to such keycountries as Norway and Japan. It is proposed to concert lobbying of othercountries and general tactics with the United States Government and to hold ameeting of representatives of Western European countries in London in order todiscuss the fisheries aspects.6. As the recent United Nations debate on the I.L.C. report served to makeclearer, the trend of recent years towards the extension of the territorial sea inso many parts of the world has been motivated largely, if not exclusively, by thedesire to control fishery resources. It is evident that the deep-sea fishery interestsof the &quot; free seas &quot; countries will be threatened at the Conference by demandseither for a simple extension of the territorial sea or for a contiguous zone, beyond limited territorial sea, in which control of the fisheries would be vested in the coastal State. The latter is now Canada&apos;s position. Against this we can urge thevalue to the coastal State of a code of fishery conservation law. What the coastalState wants, however, is not simply the maximising of the fish stocks, but themaximum exclusive slice of those stocks. At bottom the argument is economicand not biological.7. At the Conference it may therefore be easier to secure our strategic and mercantile needs than to safeguard the livelihood of our deep-sea fishing fleetswhich predominantly depend upon the grounds close to the shores of Iceland,Norway, the Soviet Union and the Atlantic Dependencies of Denmark. The issue is also complicated for the United Kingdom by our responsibility for colonial territories overseas and their fishery requirements. We shall have to seek to balance these several interests where they may be found to conflict.8. I have thought my colleagues should know of these developments and problems. The several Departments concerned are now at work upon them underForeign Office co-ordination, and consultations with other Governments will takeplace in the course of this year. I shall later be making proposals as to the line that the United Kingdom should take at the International Conference in the spring of 1958 and as to the composition of our delegation.S. L.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,27 th May, 1957.
ANNEX AExtract from Hansard, 14th December, 1953TERRITORIAL WATERS(Definition)Mr. Selwyn Lloyd: I ask your permission, Mr. Speaker, and that of the House,to make the following statement.For some time past Her Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom havehad under consideration the question whether the territorial waters round the coasts of the United Kingdom and overseas territories for which Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment are responsible should be redefined in the light of the judgmentdelivered by the International Court of Justice on 18th December, 1951, in theAnglo-Norwegian fisheries case.After full consideration of the matter they have come to the conclusion thatthere should be no change; these territorial waters will, therefore, continue to bedelimited by a line drawn 3 miles from low-water mark, or, in the case of bays andestuaries, from a closing line drawn at the first point where they narrow to 10 miles in width.The judgment in the Norwegian case depended on the facts of that case. Inthe view of Her Majesty&apos;s Government it ought not to be inferred from thatjudgment that, as a matter of international law, a baseline drawn in the mannerauthorised by that judgment in that particular case would necessarily be applied toall or any other coasts.Her Majesty&apos;s Government recognise that, legal considerations apart, anextension of United Kingdom territorial waters by means of the drawing ofbaselines, such as have been adopted along the indented coast of Northern Norway,would be of some advantage to British inshore fisheries. Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment sympathise with the point of view of the inshore fishermen and areconscious of the effect on them of their decision.Her Majesty&apos;s Government are also informed that an extension of territorial waters would be of some advantage in certain Colonies and other overseas territories for which Her Majesty&apos;s Government are responsible and they have taken this fully into account. Her Majesty&apos;s Government have, however, come to theconclusion that wider considerations, arising out of the naval, mercantile anddeep-sea fishery position of this country and like interests in the other territories concerned, must take precedence.Her Majesty&apos;s Government consider that the true interests of all seafaringnations are best served by the greatest possible freedom to use the seas for alllegitimate maritime activities and they view with concern the increasingencroachments on the high seas which have taken place in recent years in many parts of the world.At the same time, Her Majesty&apos;s Government will continue to co-operate in securing the fullest possible measure of conservation of fisheries by means ofinternational agreement through the commissions set up under the InternationalFisheries Conventions.ANNEX BSUMMARY OF PRINCIPAL CONCLUSIONS AND PROPOSALS of report OF INTERNATIONAL LAW commission the Delimitation of the Territorial SeaThe Commission feel that international practice regarding the breadth ofthe territorial sea is not uniform enough to enable them to fix any specific breadthand consider that the figure should be determined by an international conference.A greater breadth than 12 miles is not permissible under international law: forthe rest, the Commission note that many States have fixed a greater breadth than3 miles, while many others have not recognised such claims.
The territorial sea may be measured from straight baselines joining headlandsor other appropriate points instead of from low-water mark where geographygives grounds or important economic interests fortified by long usage may justify;but baselines must not appreciably depart from the general direction of the coast,and the sea areas lying within must be sufficiently closely linked to the land domainto be capable of being regarded as internal waters.The Right of Innocent PassageThe right of warships, merchant ships and fishing vessels to navigate throughthe territorial sea on innocent passage, which is so important to us, is well established in international law and the Commission^ Report has defined this right in considerable detail. It recommends that the coastal State may make passageof warships subject to previous authorisation or notification.The Freedom of the High SeasThe Commission specifically list the freedom of (i) navigation, (ii) fishing,(iii) laying of submarine cables and pipelines and (iv) flying.On navigation, the Commission has indicated that all ships are free, withcertain very limited exceptions, to navigate on the high seas without interferenceexcept from ships of the flag State. The exceptions concern the rights of warshipsto verify the flag of a ship and to take action against pirates and slave traders.Exceptionally also, pursuit and arrest of an offender begun in territorial watersmay be continued on the high seas.On fishing, the Commission have formulated in the light of the conclusionsof the International Technical Conference on the Conservation of the LivingResources of the Sea held in 1955 a code which constitutes a new development in international law. This code would make the universal freedom to fish subject toan obligation to pursue fishing activities consistently with the indefinite maintenanceof the maximum productivity of the stocks in accordance with scientific knowledge and guidance. The special interest of the coastal State in this objective as regardsadjacent resources is specifically recognised, and procedures are suggested wherebyin default of agreement the coastal State may take unilateral measures ofconservation provided they are scientifically justified and do not discriminate against foreign fishermen. All disagreements between States would be referableto binding arbitration.The Contiguous ZoneThe Commission recognise such a zone, of no more than (including theterritorial sea) 12 miles breadth, solely for the enforcement of customs, fiscal andsanitary regulations. The area of the contiguous zone outside the territorial searemains high seas.The Continental ShelfThis is defined as the seabed and subsoil of submarine areas adjacent to thecoast to a depth of 200 metres or, beyond that limit, to where the depth admits ofthe exploitation of the natural resources therein. Sovereign rights for exploringand exploiting these natural resources are accorded to the coastal State, whichmay not unjustifiably interfere with the exercise of the freedoms of the high seasin the superjacent waters. These rights are expressly declared not to affect thelegal status of the superjacent waters as high seas, or that of the airspace above.

</content>
</cab>
