<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/87/0 images: 189-192</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1957CONFIDENTIAL Copy No.C. (57) 13030th May, 1957CABINETCOLONIAL DEVELOPMENT: LOAN finance memorandum by the Secretary of State for the colonies am increasingly concerned with the growing danger that shortage of loanfunds may slow down or even stop essential development in certain major Colonies.The possibility that the London Market might be unable to provide sufficientloan finance for Colonial development was foreseen in 1954, when the currentColonial Development and Welfare (C.D.W.) provision was being worked out,and in November of that year the then Chancellor of the Exchequer gave me an assurance that, if the difficulty actually arose, efforts would be made to find some suitable way to help Colonial Governments to raise externally the money they required. That situation has now arisen, and I consider that we cannot any longerdelay taking special measures to assist Colonial Governments to obtain the loanfunds they need. In this memorandum I describe the present situation and themeasures which I recommend we should take.The Immediate problem. When the plans for the current development period (1955-56) were being drawn up, it was estimated that Colonial Governments would be able, if necessary,to raise an average of  25 millions a year on the London Market. In fact in 1955the Colonies raised only  9 millions and in 1956 only  11-25 millions they were able to make do with these sums by drawing on local resources. I am howeversatisfied that Colonial Governments will need to raise up to  14 millions in Londonbetween now and the end of 1957. There is no reasonable prospect of raisingas much as this from the Market.The Continuing problem. The best estimate I can make of future loan requirements by colonial governments is that they will need  25-30 millions of loan money from Londoneach year after 1957 to carry out agreed development programmes. Thisassessment takes into account the fullest possible use of Colonial sterling assets.Colonial Governments are being actively and continually encouraged to use theirown resources to the full. The only substantial element in the Colonial sterlingassets which might possibly be run down even more than is at present plannedis the currency funds. In 1954 Colonial Governments were authorised to invest20 per cent, of their currency backing (previously held in sterling securities) inlocally issued stock; this 20 per cent, fiduciary issue thus became available for investment in local development loans. It will shortly have all been taken up.A fiduciary issue of up to 50 per cent, might release a further  40 millions or so of colonial sterling assets, but only some  15-18 millions of both long and short-termmoney would thereby become available over a period of two to three years. Thisdevice could not therefore meet the immediate needs of 1957 and it would notgd far to meet total requirements after that date. I am having this suggestionexamined, although there is a distinct danger that an increase of the fiduciaryissue from 20 per cent, to 50 per cent, at this stage might weaken public confidence in Colonial currency.   Another possible source ; of funds is of course the51703
International Bank. Though we hope to obtain further loans from this sourcefor certain projects in the Colonies, I have no reason to believe that the assistance we might get from the Bank will be more than marginal in the next five to six years. This, I am sure, will be true also of other external sources, e.g., the north american or Western European markets. In short, despite the intensive efforts which we and Colonial Governments are now making to use local resources to thefull it will still be necessary to raise Colonial loans in London of between 25-30 millions a year, after 1957. For reasons which I shall explain I am satisfiedthat sums of this order cannot all be obtained from the Market.:,London Market Operations4. The basic difficulty we have to face is that investors fear for the securityof their long-term loans (usually 20-25 years) made to Colonial Governments,on the ground that those Governments may become independent before the loanmatures. Investors do not discriminate between various Governments in this regard: they are influenced by the general trend towards independence and bytheir assessment of how the situation will develop generally over the next20-25 years. I have considered whether Colonial Governments could overcomethis difficulty by offering more attractive terms. The terms for Colonial loansare however already more attractive than those for any other section of the gilt-edged market and I am, advised that- it would be unwise materially to improve,the general level of terms now in force: to do so would add to the impression thatinvestment in. Colonial Government stock entails a risk.5. There is also another factor which will affect Colonial government borrowing on the London Market in future. It is perhaps not generally realisedhow much Colonial loans in London have in the past been taken up by other(Colonial Governments. Out of the total of  116 millions raised in London inthe years 1951-56, no less than  83^- millions was contributed locally or taken up by Colonial Government funds under the management of the Crown Agents,and only  32f millions was contributed by United Kingdom investors. By far the greatest part of the Colonial contribution was made via the Crown Agents.The latter cannot however keep up this rate of contribution to Colonial loans,partly because the increased use of local resources by Colonial Governments fortheir own development is leaving less money in the hands of the Crown agents for investment, and partly because the funds hitherto held by the Crown Agentson account of Ghana and Malaya will no longer be available for this purpose.The Crown Agents have already this year subscribed  2^ millions to Market loans and  8 millions has been raised from United Kingdom investors. During therest of this year the Crown Agents expect to be able to find another  2 millions to  3 millions to subscribe to Market loans, but they have no way of telling whetherUnited Kingdom investors will still be willing to subscribe or in what amounts.It seems highly unlikely that we could raise another  1.1 millions to  12 millions from United Kingdom investors and any reasonable calculation of the amount which could be raised will not meet the needs foreseen in 1957, nor the continuingneeds thereafter. ..6. This situation is not one that could be remedied by the colonial development Corporation. In the first place, the Corporation has very nearlyreached the limit of its borrowing powers under the Overseas resources development Act. Secondly, to regard the Corporation as a source of further&apos;loan finance for Colonial Governments would provoke severe criticism from bothmajor Parties in Parliament. The Corporation was set up primarily to bridge the gap between basic development of the type normally financed by colonial governments and private enterprise development of the type that requires no special stimulus. In recent years the Corporation has concentrated far more onloans to Colonial Governments or Government guaranteed loans to statutory/bodies than on the work it was primarily set up to do. This type of &quot; financehouse&quot; activity has on several occasionsi attracted severecriticisminParliamentand the Public Accounts, Committee, and last August I was obliged to give anundertaking to Parliament that, in conjunction with the Corporation, I would ensure that an appropriate balance was; maintained between the Corporation^&quot; finance house &quot; activities and its other types of investment At present something over 40 per cent, of the: Corporation^ total investments fall within the definition of &quot; finance house&quot; transactions and I have reached the- conclusion that the
amount which the Corporation has at present invested in this type of activityrepresents the maximum that can be permitted. The Corporation has asked thatits borrowing powers should be increased from  100 millions to  200 millions.This demand is clearly unrealistic; but some increase, though much more modestthan the Corporation has proposed, will be required if the Corporation is toundertake further development of the type for which it was primarily established.I hope to circulate soon a memorandum to my colleagues setting out my proposals on the further capital requirements of the Corporation. But whatever decisionsmay be reached on that point, it is clear that the Corporation should have nofurther significant part to play in the provision of loan finance for colonial governments, provided that we can devise other and more satisfactory measuresof doing so.  My proposals to this end are explained in the following paragraphs.Possible Solutions7. In these circumstances, I am satisfied that, if we are to avoid a seriousreduction in the present scale of Colonial development, with all the consequences which that would entail, special measures must now be taken to increase the flow of loan finance from London. I have considered various methods of improving the status of Colonial stock in the Market by providing some formof official United Kingdom support, e.g., the investment of funds managed bythe National Debt Office. Unfortunately there appear to be; insuperable objectionsto all the measures which have been considered, and on the advice of the treasury have accepted that a solution cannot be found on these lines. We are, in-fact;left with the provision of loans from the Exchequer as the only: feasible methodof meeting the shortfall in loan finance that Colonial Governments can expect to raise on the London Market; and this is the system I recommend we must now adopt.Proposed System of Exchequer Loans8. There are certain principles which should be followeddn any arrangementsfor providing loans to Colonial Governments from the Exchequer. In the firstplace it must be made absolutely clear to Colonial Governments that such arrangements are intended to supplement what the London Market can provide,and that in the first instance they must continue to look to the Market to meet their needs to the maximum possible extent. This means that we should continueto subject their demands for permission to raise loans externally to rigorousscrutiny; and in order to encourage Colonial Governments to make the fullest possible use of the Market, and to regard the Exchequer as a lender of last resort, I would propose that loans from the Exchequer should be made at the equivalent of the current market rate for comparable Colonial Government loans,plus provision for full sinking fund. (Market&apos; issues carry only a 1 per cent,sinking fund: a full sinking fund on a twenty-year loan would be about3i per cent, per annum.  There would thus be an appreciable difference.)9. The creation of a system of direct loans from Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentto Colonial Governments might well give rise to pressures from individual Coloniesclaiming that on political grounds they should be given loans. This risk already exists but we must be careful not to increase it. Thus, while it Would continueto be the responsibility of the Colonial Office and the Treasury to decide whichColonies need loan funds and the amounts involved, I suggest that it would bedesirable for Exchequer loans to be made solely on the recommendation of anindependent body appointed by the Colonial Secretary with the concurrence ofthe Treasury. The independent body I have in mind would only accede to requests for those amounts when it was satisfied that the. Colony in question could not obtain them, or all of them, from ordinary Market sources..Thjs^independent body would also be charged with [ the responsibility for deciding what theappropriate rate should be in respect of any loan. :vi;.;i ,10. As I have said in paragraph 3 of this paper, the best estimate we can make of the loan requirements of Colonial i Governments in London is that they -will need  25- 30 millions of loan money from London each year after 1957.I think it would be necessary in instituting arrangements of the kind I propose t6continue them for a period of several years in order to give Colonial government sufficiently long assurance about the supply of loan funds to enable them to
go ahead with their economic planning. If the period selected were five years,that would end in 1962, which will be about half way through the five-year period from 1960-65 when many Colonial Governments will be carrying out a five-year plan of development based on what I hope will be a new C.D.W. Act in 1959 tocover that five-year period. I am sure therefore that it would be better for usto have arrangements which run in the first instance for seven years, that isuntil March 1965, so that both our loans arrangements and our arrangements force.D.W. grants can cover an identical period. In this connection I would hopethat, if the system of Exchequer loans which I propose is adopted, the need force.D.W. grant assistance in the period after 1960 might be substantially reduced below its present level. Loans rather than grants would be both more advantageous to the United Kingdom in the long run, and would also be in keeping with the increasing prosperity of several of our larger Colonial territories.11. Past experience has shown that the London Market can produce as little as  250,000 of new money from United Kingdom investors in a year, while its bestrecent performance has been  12 millions. In these circumstances I think thebest arrangement would be to provide for an average annual rate of loan assistanceto Colonial Governments of  20 millions a year, i.e.,  140 millions in all over the seven years, with authority in any one year to make loans up to a total of 30 millions. It would be understood that this amount would be drawn upon onlyto the extent that it was actually needed by Colonial Governments.12. The system of Exchequer loans proposed above would apply only toColonial territories: on attaining independence, territories would cease to be eligible for such assistance. The figure of  140 millions proposed in the preceding paragraph covers all the territories at present in the Colonial sphere except theFederation of Malaya. If other territories attained independence in the period upto 1965, there could be a reduction in the amount that in practice it would benecessary to provide.13. If these suggestions are acceptable to my colleagues legislation will berequired. It is improbable that this could be enacted before the end of 1957, sothat some means of meeting the 1957 need by way of temporary advances will berequired. I would propose to solve this technical problem in consultation withthe Chancellor.Conclusion14.   I invite my colleagues to agree:  (a) that special measures should be taken to avert a serious reduction in colonial development as a result of the failure of the London market to provide the loan finance needed by Colonial Governments;(b) that those special measures should take the form described in paragraphs7-13 above.A. L.-B.Colonial Office, S.W.1,29th May, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
