<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/87/0 images: 197-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet. May 1957The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of...............................................................TOP SECRET Copy No.C. (57) 13230th May, 1957CABINETFUTURE legislation memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home Department andLord Privy seal the Future Legislation Committee have recently completed, with the help ofall Ministers whose departmental interests are affected, a comprehensive review ofthe legislative programme for next session. The candidates for inclusion numberover 100, and the Committee began by dividing those which appeared to have the strongest claims into three lists of varying degrees of priority, as shown in the annex to this memorandum.2. Assuming a normal session and making allowance for other categories ofbusiness, the time likely to be available for legislation should be about 55 days.The Bills in Lists A, A.1 and B, which form the material from which next session&apos;programme might be constructed, would require about double this time. It ispossible that some of the Bills in List A.1 will not be necessary, but, even so, it isclear that time cannot be found for many of the Bills in List B.3. The Committee were therefore obliged to consider which of these bills would have to be deferred to a future session. The choice is a difficult one; manyof the Bills in List B are not only desirable in themselves, but have been awaitinga place in the programme for some time. We must, however, try to reduce the strain on Members next session, particularly in committees, and we must devise a programme which will arouse the interest of our own supporters. There is agood deal of feeling in the Party that there is altogether too much legislation andthat too little of it is genuinely Conservative in character.4. We must also have an eye to the session after next. We shall probablywish to avoid overloading it with measures which would arouse political controversy, but we must see that it includes some important measures, particularlyin the field of social legislation, which will be part of a forward-looking and constructive policy.5. We must also bear in mind our undertaking to dispense with all theremaining emergency powers in the lifetime of this Parliament. The two bigproblems which have still to be dealt with are the powers relating to the acquisitionof land and the economic controls; we must seek to deal next session with theformer, on which a good deal of work has already been done.6. With these considerations in mind the Committee decided to recommend to the Cabinet that the following Bills (in addition to the others included in List Aand those in List A.1 which may prove to be required) should form the basis for next session&apos;s programme:  (i) Major BillsLocal Government.Local Government Finance (Scotland).Pensions and National Insurance.House of Lords Reform.Emergency Powers Repeal (Land) (possibly 2 or 3 Bills).51706
(ii) Medium Committee BillsAgricultural Holdings or Slaughter-houses.Betting and Gaming.Land Drainage (Scotland).Tariffs.Credit Trading (Part I),(iii) Minor BillsColonial Loans.Charitable Trusts (Baddeley Judgement).Royal Naval Hospital, Great Yarmouth.Isle of Man Constitutional Reform.New Towns.Disabled Persons Employment.Public Record Office.Inventions and Designs.1. The Bills indicated in paragraph 6 would themselves take more time than is likely to be available. Of the Bills in (i) and (ii), all, with the exception of theHouse of Lords Reform Bill, may have to be referred to standing committees. Itis therefore doubtful whether it would be possible to include any other major orcontentious Bills. There is, however, some uncertainty about the proposed scopeof some of the Bills in the list, and this may affect the time which they will require.In view of this the Committee considered that it would be desirable to proceedwith the preparation of a Bill or Bills on Adoption and Child Life Protection anda Bill on Deer (Scotland), on the understanding that it will probably be necessaryto defer them to a later session.It is unlikely that it will prove possible to include all the minor Bills in (iii)and it may be necessary at a later stage to decide on an order of priority.8. The Committee have assumed that the Shops Bill will not be introducednext session, and that if the Credit Trading Bill is introduced it will be restricted to replacing the emergency powers relating to the control of hire purchase.9. Among the important Bills which on this plan would be deferred to a latersession would be:  Agricultural Holdings or Slaughter-houses.Mental Laws Reform.Registration of Opticians.Industrial Arbitration.Catering Wages Council.Administrative Tribunals.Charitable Trusts (Nathan Report).Economic Controls.The Mental Laws Reform Bill and the Administrative Tribunals Bill depend onReports, of which one has only just been published and the other will not bepublished until July. Time must be allowed to assess the reactions to these reports and legislation on these topics will be better left to the 1958-59 session. Togetherwith the other Bills referred to above, they will form the nucleus of a usefulprogramme in that session.10. The Bills referred to in paragraph 6 will make up a reasonably well-balanced programme for the 1957-58 session. The Pensions Bill and the betting and Gaming Bill provide the main element of social reform; the reform of ourinstitutions is strongly represented by the House of Lords Reform Bill, the LocalGovernment Bills and the Bills relating to the Colonies and the Isle of Man; andthe Bills on Emergency Powers Repeal (Land), Tariffs, Credit Trading andInventions and Designs will make a very substantial contribution towards the replacement of emergency powers. I invite my colleagues to agree that the Billsreferred to in paragraph 6 should be regarded as the basis for next session&apos;programme and that the Ministers concerned should be authorised to obtain thenecessary policy clearance and to give instructions for drafting.Trustee Savings Banks.R. A. B.Home Office, S.W. 1,29th May, 1957.
ANNEXList A : Bills known to be essentialImperial Institute.British Nationality (Amendment).Local Government (England and Wales).Local Government Finance (Scotland).Post Office and Telegraphy Money.Finance.Expiring Laws Continuance.Exchequer Loans to Nationalised Boards.List A. 1: Bills which may become essential in particular circumstancesCrown Aircraft (actions for nuisance).Malta.Singapore.Ceylon (Consequential Provisions).Representation of the People (Redistribution).Insurance (Nuclear Reactors).Public Works Loans.Suez Canal Company.Egyptian Sterling Balances.Jamaica Dependencies.West India Regiment.List B: Bills with strong claims to inclusion in the programmeAgricultural Holdings.Slaughter-houses.Colonial Loans.Overseas Civil Service.Jamaica Dependencies.Charitable Trusts (Baddeley Judgement).Mental Laws Reform.Royal Naval Hospital, Great Yarmouth.Registration of Opticians.Adoption.Child Life Protection.Isle of Man Constitutional Reform.Betting and Gaming.Water (England and Wales).New Towns.Disabled Persons (Employment).Industrial Arbitration.Catering Wages Council.Public Record Office.Pensions and National Insurance.Wireless Telegraphy Act (1949) Amendment.Land Drainage (Scotland).Deer (Scotland).Tariffs.Inventions and Designs.Credit Trading (Part I).Milford Haven.New Park Lane Scheme.Trustee Savings Banks.Emergency Powers Repeal (Land).House of Lords Reform.Administrative Tribunals.

</content>
</cab>
