<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/87/0 images: 280-282</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-    276THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1957SECRET Copy No. 5 8C. (57) 14418th June, 1957CABINETTHE FUTURE ORGANISATION OF THE army memorandum by the Secretary of State for WarReducing the Army to 165,000 means cutting it almost in half. In order tokeep a high proportion of fighting arms, a higher proportion of civilians will haveto be employed in the administrative services, especially in the static installations in the United Kingdom. This will mean a better proportion of teeth to tail armsthan we have had in the past.2. Even so, we shall have to come down from 176 major teeth arm units to 125. The reductions in the teeth arms will be carried out in two phases. Allbut nine reductions will be completed in phase I, which I plan to complete by theend of 1959, leaving phase II to be completed by the end of 1962.3. The reductions in the administrative corps are not very difficult, as eachcorps has one cap-badge and loyalty is to the corps (R.A.S.C., R.A.O.C.,R.E.M.E., &amp;c).4. Similarly, in the Royal Artillery, the Royal Engineers and the RoyalSignals, where all units wear the corps cap-badge, buttons and facings, the processis simpler and less painful than in the Infantry and the Cavalry wing of the RoyalArmoured Corps, whose strength lies in their regimental traditions and esprit decorps.5. The Royal Armoured Corps will be reduced by 6 regiments in Phase I(3 Cavalry regiments and 3 battalions of the Royal Tank Regiment) and by two more regiments in phase II. This will reduce the corps from 30 regiments to 22.Of these, 2 regiments will be employed in the training role, leaving only20 operational armoured and armoured car regiments.6. The Cavalry reductions will be effected by amalgamating regiments inpairs: thus 6 regiments will amalgamate to form 3 in phase I. This follows the pattern of the amalgamations of the early 1920s. Similarly, 6 of the existing8 battalions of the Royal Tank Regiment will amalgamate in pairs, leaving themwith 5 battalions.7. In the Infantry the traditions and regimental system of Infantry of the line and the special position of the Brigade of Guards and the Parachute Regiment makethe problem harder still. I consider that, because of the operational need for theParachute Brigade, all 3 battalions of the Parachute Regiment should remain.8. The existing 10 battalions of the Brigade of Guards will be reduced by, one in each phase. This will leave them with 8 battalions, of which 5 are normally required for London duties, leaving 3 for service overseas. If, however,by easing London duties 4 battalions can meet the requirement, then 4 Guardsbattalions will be available to form 2 Guards brigades, each of 2 Guards battalions and one Line battalion.  This is the best organisation for a Guards Brigade.9. The Infantry of the Line will ultimately have to be reduced from 64 to 49battalions. In phase I the reduction will be to 52 battalions. This will be doneby amalgamating 24 existing regiments in pairs to form 12 new regiments. Inphase II a further 6 regiments will be amalgamated into 3 new regiments.51766
The War Office, S.W. 1,13th June, 1957.10. All new and remaining old regiments will be grouped into 14 brigadesof 3 or 4 battalions each, but in the Highland Brigade there will be 5 battalions (seeAppendix A).11.   The brigades will remain on a territorial basis except in the case of the 3 g Fusilier, Light Infantry and Green Jacket Brigades.12. It should be remembered that the Infantry of the Line have already lostall their second battalions since 1947.13. In the case of Infantry battalions of the Territorial Army I do notconsider that there is any need to change their existing titles. There is a precedent for this in that there are already T.A. infantry battalions that have no regularregiment (e.g., the Herefordshire Light Infantry which is a T.A. battalion of theKing&apos;s Shropshire Light Infantry).14. These measures are steps in the direction of &quot; new regiments &quot; as in theCardweil reform when, for instance, the 43rd Foot and 52nd Foot were joinedtogether to make the Oxfordshire and Buckinghamshire Light Infantry. Flexibilityis essential in any new plan and all that I am now proposing will help to that endwithout, I hope, breaking too much with the old regimental traditions. It will set the stage for a natural evolution into the new regiments. Meanwhile, all regimentsin a brigade will wear the same cap-badge. The brigades will have one bandserving ail battalions, though battalions will retain their drum, pipe or bugle bands.Officer cadets will be gazetted initially from Sandhurst into the regiment, but theywill come on to a common brigade list at a later date. Other ranks recruits willbe enlisted into the brigade and posted to a regiment, wherever possible to the regiment of their choice. They will be trained centrally at one depot for eachbrigade.&apos; 15. The Royal Artillery will be reduced from 53 regiments to 32 regiments.The number of both light and heavy anti-aircraft regiments will be reduced; andwe can do with fewer field and medium artillery regiments, partly because thearmy will be smaller, and partly because of the introduction of guided weaponregiments, each of which will have far greater fire-power than the old traditionaltype medium and heavy regiments. The details of the scheme will be worked outby the Master Gunner, who will give full weight to the regimental and batterytraditions of the old regiments. It should be remembered that the Royal Artilleryhave already been reduced by 19 regular regiments since 1950, mainly due to theabolition of Anti-Aircraft Command and Coast Artillery.16. The Royal Engineers will be reduced from 16 to 11 regiments, to fit theneeds of the smaller army. Details are being worked out on the advice of theEngineer-in-Chief.17. In the Royal Corps of Signals the reduction in divisional signal regimentsand squadrons will stem automatically from the reduced number of divisions andbrigades. There will still be a requirement for communications at the higher level,but overall the Royal Corps of Signals is likely to be reduced from some 27,000to about 14,000.18. A summary is attached at Appendix B of what should be the shape ofthe army of the future.  All the figures are still subject to minor adjustments.19. If the Cabinet approves these proposals, some three weeks will berequired in order to allow a full explanation of the changes to be given to her majesty, other Royal Colonels-in-Chief and Colonels of Regiments. When these consultations are complete, I propose to issue a White Paper setting out the detailsof the amalgamations which will take place.20.   May I have approval to proceed as I have proposed?J. H.
Appendix a proposed GROUPING OF INFANTRYBrigadeGuardsLowlandHome CountiesLancastrianFusilierMidlandEast AnglianWessexLight InfantryYorkshire   ...MercianWelshNorth IrishHighlandGreen JacketsParachute  ...Number ofRegiments8 (Battalions)344333444333533Total60Appendix BSUMMARY OF THE REDUCTIONS1. Numbers of Units			End of	End ofArm	Now      Phase I	Phase IIRoyal Armoured Corps Regiments	30            24	22Royal Artillery Regiments.........	53            34	32Royal Engineer Regiments ...      ......	16            12	11Infantry Battalions 		Brigade of Guards      .........	10             9	8Parachute Regiment    .........	3             3	3Infantry of the Line    .........	64            52	49Total Infantry        ......	77            64	60Total number of units	176          134	1252. Reductions in Manpower of Other Large Arms/Services				End ofArm	Now	Phase IIRoyal Signals     ......      ......	27,000	13,700Royal Army Service Corps     ......	30,000	12,500Royal Army Medical Corps     ...	11,000	5,600Royal Army Ordnance Corps  ...	22,000	10,500Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers	36,000	12,500

</content>
</cab>
