<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/31/18 images: 212-223</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.)

TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY

It is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.

SECRET COPY NO. 11

W.M. (42) 115TH CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 1.

Confidential Annex.

(20th August, 1942 - 6.0 p.m.)

?

 THE CHIEF OF COMBINED OPERATIONS gave the War Cabinet a short account of the combined operations the Dieppe area on the previous day.

 The following were the main points in his account:-

 Our Naval losses had been extremely lights.

 Two thirds of the total Military Forces (numbering some 6,100) were accounted for, and had returned to this country.

 Although Tanks had been got ashore, they had been unable to leave the immediate vicinity of the beaches, owing to the exits being blocked. As a result, the objectives of the forces which had landed on the central beaches had not been reached.

 The personnel of one enemy coastal battery had been wiped out, while another battery had been neutralised by a small party of determined men who had sniped the gun crows.

 Planning, organisation and co-operation between all the Services had been excellent. The air support had been faultless. The enemy had been obliged to send air support from a considerable distance. The air fighting had been very heavy and the general results achieved could be regarded as very satisfactory.

 [Fuller details are contained in the account sent to the Prime Minister as TULIP 222.]

 Lord Louis Mountbatton said that the lessons learnt in this large-scale raid would be invaluable in planning for operation "ROUND-UP". The raid would be carefully examined in order that we might profit by the experience gained, and evolve new methods and technique to deal with the very strong German coastal defences. It might well be that we should decide that we ought to attack soft spots rather than strategic or militarily important points, which were bound to be strongly defended.



 THE FOREIGN SECRETARY said that the notable achievement of the Royal Air Force was a most encouraging aspect of the operation. The German Air Force had been roughly handled and would probably not have been able to maintain the same scale of effort had there been other more widely separated large-scale landings, or had the operations continued for some days, as they would, were we making a re-entry on the Continent. He asked that if it were found that the Allied contingents taking part had acquitted themselves well, appropriate mention should be made of the part they had played.

 THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF was most anxious that there should be no suggestion that this raid had been undertaken merely to cause an air battle.

 THE VICE-CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF thought that it was too early to say what might be the lessons of this operation. Past experience had shown, however, that a landing regardless of cost could always be achieved but that the second stage - exploitation - had always proved more difficult than the landing itself.

 THE DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER said that the planning and execution of this raid reflected the greatest credit on all concerned.

 This observation was warmly endorsed by the War Cabinet, who asked that the Chiefs of Staff, when examining the lessons to be learned from the operation, would also consider whether a further operation could be carried out, in time to act as a diversion in connection with Operation TORCH.



? George Street, S.W.1.



Unparaphrased Version of a secret

Cypher Telegram not One Time Table.

Tulip 222

Too 2200Z/20

TOD 2340A/20

MOST SECRET CYPHER TELEGRAM

MOST IMMEDIATE

From :- Air Ministry.

To :- C.-in-C., Middle East.

TULIP NO 222. 20.8.42.

For Prime Minister fro C.C.o.

 Have now interviewed principal commanding officers concerned in Dieppe raid. It is clear that although strategical surprise was impossible tactical surprise was achieved.

 The synchronisation of each part of the assault was perfect.

 No. 3 Commando and 40 Americans who were embarked in 20 landing craft, made a chance encounter with enemy flak ships and E-boats, probably escorting a tanker, within 7 miles of the coast. In the battle which ensued, the flotilla was dispersed but one flak stop was sunk and the other damaged by one of your beach protection craft which was accompanying the flotilla. The surviving craft re-formed and carried on with the landing at yellow beaches.

 At yellow 1, troops got ashore but failed to reach their objective. At yellow 2, the 20 men who landed scaled the cliff and engaged a six-gun coastal battery manned by 200 Germans, with rifle fire for four hours during which time its fire on our ships was entirely ineffective.

 260 men of No. 4 Commando with 5 Americans went into Orange 1 and 2 beaches. They overcame beach resistance, fought their way up to the battery, took it by assault and killed 160 Germans taking 4 prisoners.

 These two successful actions enabled our ships to operate off Dieppe for the whole of the 9 hours.

 The landing on green beach was successful and the canadians fought their way inland. The landing on blue beach, which had erroneously been reported a failure



, e,? was&apos; a success but the Canadians got held op -).i&apos;y ,.C.&apos;lQ.C(jQ:&apos; opposition-.)&apos; - , The landir-vd on red and white beaches met very ;f; j-iion &apos; -    18 tanks were got ashore0    Greatdimculty was experienced in the necessary demolition of the sea-wall to enable tanks to get through and9although some of &quot;them were able to operate most of the.   day rouiixl the Casino grounds^ strong&quot;tank; obstructions   -prevented their breaking out into the town end it wasimpossible to .get demolitions up to destroy theobstacleSo    The Royal Marine Commando put up a good&apos;-show at red beachQThe Germans had been reinforcing their garrisonssteadily, presumably in response to the rumours of a  &apos;second front    Our troops were unable to capture thetown before the time for withdrawal, which started6 minutes late, at 1106, and proved a very difficultproposition.    By now the Germans were bringing everyform; of weapon to bear on the beaches, mainly fromcaves in the cliffs9, which could; not be silenced.Captain Hughes^Hallett collected the 6 destroyers and gun-boat together and under: the concentrated gunfireof the destroyers j the armoured landing craft were, pushed in at one beach after the other to take off suchsoldiers as had been able to fight their way back to the beaches.,   The force withdrew at 1350, 9 hours after landing.Of the 6,100 soldiers taking part, about one-thirdare missing and of these the Germans claim 1,500 areprisonerSg presumably cut off from the beaches.     &apos;Naval casualties were 100 killed,, one destroyersunks 42 landing craft sunk or missing of a total of167 employedc -The air support was faultless0    2,890 sorties- were fiowna the, final figures of the battle are      ;-enemy, losses;- 95-certain9&apos;38:probably destroyed; 140&apos;-damaged.    Our losses are: 98&quot;, but 30 pilots are safe.-,.      The Germans must have been rattled as they havepeen,p.^ two entirely cootradietory lines:,U this was an invasion which it has taken us 10/o^K- JO-P^Pare and which ended in our being driven out.Wf ! -   &quot; having     i- - 1..... - - -.- or 5 days as a, rests?vv of instruct-

ices.1:111




</content>
</cab>
