<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/46/37 images: 524-535</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.P.(44) 877TH FEBRUARY. 1944WAR cabinet copy NO,THE PROTECTION OF MONUMENTS,,ND WORKS OF ARTNote by the SecrotaryBy direction of the Prime Minister I circulate for the information of the War Cabinet,, a copy ofthe correspondence between the   Prime Minister andArchbishop Lord. Lang of Lambetha      (This matter was discussed, by the War Cabinet on 20th   January,  1944.See   W.M.(44)9th Conelusi ons, Minute 2*)EaE.  BRIDGES,Offices of the War Cabinet,S.W,1.;7th February, 1944,I.Copy of a letter dated 51st January, 1944 from thePrime Minis&quot;!;or to iirchbishop Lord Lang of Lambeth,55The authoritatively signed Memorial about therisk of war damage to architectural  ;.nd culturaltreasures in the course of -allied operations in .Europej which you addressed to me last month, has nowbeen most carefully considered by the Cabinet.I need hardly assure you that my colleagues and I most fully understand the importance of thematter with   which the Memorial deals, and I nowenclose a - memorandum prepared under the War Cabinet&apos;sdirection, setting out, for your information andthat of the other signatories of the Memorial, theresult of our enquiries and deliberations.WINSTON S. CHURCHILLa   W.P.(44)  14(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)

&apos; While the fierceness of the struggle and the cause forwhich it is being waged put the absolute necessities of warfar in front of any other consideration, Allied commandersand those acting under their orders have the responsibilityof avoiding needless  destruction, and especially of doing all they can, consistently with military necessity, to avoidor limit damage to monuments and artistic collections whichare part of the inheritance of civilization.      To announce that a particular target should be spared at all costs would merely be to provide the enemy with a sanctuary from which tocarry on his operations in safety, but the importance of doing all that is possible to  conserve the arts and monumentsof Italy was recognised by the War.Office before the invasion of Sicily began in April last.      The invasion of Sicily, likeall sea-borne operations, was conditioned by the availability of shipping and by the priority of its use for strictly military purposes with the inevitable result that the servicedevoted to art preservation suffered in the opening stages ofthat campaign.      Similarly,, the exacting circumstances inwhich the advance from SI Alaraein and the clearance of thenorth coast of Africa were effected did not permit of much attention being at first given to the preservation ofmonuments.On the American side, the&apos;initiative was taken by various learned bodies, and in August 1943 a special commission was appointed by the President of the United States.Its objects were to correlate the work of  the independentcommittees formed to supply the U. S. Army with advice andmaterial, but, more particularly,  &quot;to aid. in salvaging andrestoring to their lawful owners such objects of art as havebeen appropriated by the Axis powers or by individuals acting under their authority or consent&quot;.      In this  country the dutyof conserving art monuments in the war areas was assumed bythe War Office and was naturally assigned to  the civil affairs branch of the Service.    &apos;By an agreement coveringlarger issues, the United States were to play a predominantpart - actually, of the officer experts sent into the field12 were American as against 3 British, and the organisation was framed on lines devised by the&apos; U. S.  Commission.      the directive, frauied in common,  to the organisation providedfor the protection of monuments in areas occupied by theAllied Forces against wanton or avoidable damage,   for theapplication to damaged monuments of such &quot;first aid&quot;measures as might prevent their further deterioration, andfor the collection of evidence of appropriation or wantondestruction of works of art by the Germans.      This directivein fact anticipated the recommendations made to the deputy prime Minister by a Parliamentary deputation on 12th November.Nevertheless, despite the powerful constitution of theAmerican Commission and the orders published on the initiative of the War Office by Commanders, reports showed that the steps taken were not fully effective, and the Secretary ofState for War on 1st November appointed Lieutenant-colonel sir Leonard V/oollejr to be&apos; archaeological adviser to theDirector of Civil Affairs and ordered him&apos; at the earliestpossible moment to visit Italy and Sicily and carry out a personal investigation.

Sir Leonard Woolley found that the organisation,admirable in theory, was  not adapted to conditions in thefield.      The staff of officer experts was admirably equipped for its purpose, but they were not distributed to the areas where they were most needed?    in so far as they were distri-buted,  they had lost touch with the centre of their ownorganisation,- and they lacked the authority necessary forthe effective performance of their duties,,The organisation was accordingly remodelled, and underthe. new arrangement some officer experts are attached to thefighting commands, wail e others,   in rear of the battle area,are available for posting wherever required. ..    Moreover,the officers now enjoy an authority which formerly they did   -not possess. /On the  conclusion of his tour Sir Leonard Woolleyreported to Allied Force Headquarters,  and, as a result ofhis recommendations, General Eisenhower, before leaving totake up his new comma nd,  is sued general orders to allcommanders as to their duty and responsibility in thismatter, together with some detailed directions which it isthought could not be improved upon,,      Whatever - failuresunder this head may have occurred in the past,   the new arrangements which have thus been worked out in the light of experience are well calculated to promote,  so far as militaryexigencies allow, a more effective effort to protecthistorical -monuments of first importance in the future.-As  regards the practical problems that confront theArmy in&apos; the field, both while pr e pa ring for an advance andwhen military occupation, of a new area has been secured,the right,  and indeed the only, machinery to use must bethe executive authority of the Commander-in-Chief and ofthe officers under his command.      The weakness of theMonuments and Fine Arts organisation in the past was in large measure due to the fact that it had been elaboratedby and depended on an external  civilian body not in touchwith the Army, whereas  it is only as part of the appropriatebranch of the Service that it can function at all.It is hoped that the above will furnish sufficientassurance that this important matter has   received theserious attention it deserves, both from the Cabinet andfrom the Allied Commanders,  and that the steps which havenow been taken will go far to effect the purpose which allalike wish to promote. - &apos;-.The third and last point mentioned in the Memorialraises a different issue.      There it is suggested that aCommission, pa.rallel to that appointed by. the President ofthe United States,   should be formed at once to deal withthe post-war problem of the restitution of stolen works of art.      There is complete agreement on this point.      The army officers of the Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives sectionsoperating in the different countries now occupied by theenemy will have the duty of collecting evidence of theftor destruction, but there their  duty ends;    they are not and will not be responsible for restitution.      That problemlies outside the scope of the fighting services and, as thePresident of the United States has foreseen,  will have tobe referred to an inter-Allied board of experts.It. would be helpful if the Memorialists,  in consultationwith such bodies as the Eoyal Fine Arts Commission and theBritish Academy, would submit for consideration the names of the art experts who might form a Commission appointedby the Government to represent the British Commonwealth ofNations on any post-war inter-Allied Board of Restitution,,

Copy of a 1ottor datc1st Fobruary, 1944 from i.rch-bishop Lord&quot; Lang of&quot;TVj.m5o&quot;tti &quot;to the Prime iViinTsTorIH 5s 5tI hasten to thank you for your letter of 31stJanuary and for the very valuable and reassuringMemorandum prepared under the direction of the WarCabinet on the subject of the protection and preser-vation of objects of historical or cultural importancein tho War areasaOn my own behalf and on behalf of tho other signatories of the Memorial, addressed to you, I ammost grateful for the full thought and care which theCabinet have given to it, and I will see that theMemorandum you have sent to me will be communicatedto these signatories0Let me also express my gratitude for the willingness of the Cabinet to appoint some commissions to represent the British Commonwealth of Nations onany post-war Allied Board of Rostitution0    I will seethat steps are at once -taken to consult with those whosigned the Memorial addressed to you and such other bodies as -your Memorandum suggests as to persons who might be submitted to the Government as suitable forthis purposeoLANG OF LAMBETH.Archbishop *






</content>
</cab>
