<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/44/6 images: 40-45</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  October 1944.SECRET.W.M. (44)135th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 135 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers.Room, House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Thursday, 12th October, 1944, at12-15 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).Copy No. glThe Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService. ^The Right Hon. Lord Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present:The   Right  Hon.   Viscount   Simon,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P.Production.Minister  of aircraft the Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Sir Donald Somer-vell, K.C., M.P., Attorney-General.The Right Hon. W. Whiteley, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury. .The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air. .The Right Hon. H. U. Willink, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Health.The Right Hon. W. S. Morrison, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Town and country planning.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury.The Right Hon. Thomas Williams,M.P., Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Ministry of . Agriculture andFisheries.Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Contents.[28438-1]Subject,Town and Country Planning Bill.
Town and At their meeting on the 9th October the War Cabinet hadCountry appointed a Committee to give further consideration to the questionsPlanning Bill, raised by Clauses 45 and 46 of the Town and Country-. Planning(Previous Bill. The War Cabinet now had before them a Memorandum by the reference: Minister of Town and Country Planning (WP. (44) 566), to which.M. (44) 134th was annexed an appendix setting out the principles on which theConclusions, Committee suggested that a solution of the compensation clausesMinute 12.) &apos;   should be based. 1The following were the main points raised in discussion : Expenditure since 31st March, 1939, on Capital Improvements.(a) The Committee had suggested that an endeavour should bemade to deal with the cases of owners (and not merely owner-occupiers) who had spent money since the&apos;31st March, 1939, inmaking capital improvements at costs in excess of March 1939 prices.This applied particularly to improvements to agricultural propertymade at the direction or with the consent of the Wap AgriculturalExecutive Committee. The same principle, however, also appliedto owners who had spent money on factories or additions to factoriesrequired for war purposes at higher prices.It was recognised that this type of case could only be met by aprovision conferring very wide powers of discretion on the arbitratorto examine all the relevant facts in each case, in order to determine the unexhausted value of the capital improvements.After discussion, the War Cabinet agreed -(1) That, while the general principle must be maintained that compensation should&apos; be assessed by reference to- pricescurrent on the 31st March, 1939, special provision shouldbe made to deal with the type of case referred to, on thefollowing lines :  Authority should be given to the arbitrator to awardadditional compensation by reference to the value ofcapital improvements carried out at prices in excess of1939 prices, subject to deductions in respect of con-tributions by the State, depreciation allowances, orcontractual arrangements ^whereby special amortisationof capital expenditure entered into the cost of productssold. . K   *All awards of additional special compensation underthis head would be subject to a ceiling (see (b) below).(b) The next question discussed was what ceiling would be appropriate to the additional compensation proposed in (a) above.It was pointed out that the circumstances to be taken into account in this type of case were wholly different to those which would normally be taken into account in dealing with claims on behalf of owner-occupiers of buildings or agricultural land for additional compensastion. It was urged that in many cases restriction to a ceiling of 30 per cent, would be very unfair.On the other hand, it was felt that there would be greatdifficulty in defending the use of different percentages as ceilingsin different clauses of the Bill. Moreover, in the great majority ofcases capital improvements would only have been made to a part ofthe property affected, and a 30 per cent, ceiling would thereforepermit the arbitrator to take into account expenditure on capitalimprovements made at prices considerably in excess of 30 per cent,over the 1939 level of prices. Furthermore, the scheme wasnecessarily something of a compromise, and some hard cases couldnot be avoided. aThe War Cabinet agreed-(2) That the provisions proposed under (1) above should include a ceiling of 30 per cent.(c) The War Cabinet next discussed the relation of additional compensastion under, the provision outlined at (a) and (b) to theadditional compensation proposed for owner-occupiers of buildings
129 W.M. 185 (44).and agricultural land. It was clear that in certain cases there wouldbe an overlap between the two types of additional compensation.The War Cabinet-(3) Directed that the officers of the Departments concerned should examine this matter and report on the relationship between the provision for these two types of compen-sation.Compensation for Sites bought by Speculators.(d) In paragraph 5 of his Memorandum the Minister of Townand Country Planning reported that at the meeting which he had held with Members of all Parties a keen desire had been shown togive effect to a proposal to give the speculator who had boughtbombed land at knock-out prices not more than he paid, for it.The general view of the War Cabinet was that this would befound to be impracticable. Moreover, any provision on the lines proposed would weaken the general basis on which the compensationclauses were based, namely, prices current at the 31st March, 1939.The War Cabinet decided (4) That the Minister of Town and Country Planning shouldnot put forward any scheme to give effect to this pro-posal, but should leave the matter to be dealt with whenthe amendments to give effect to it were- debated inParliament.Compensation to Owner-Occupiers of War-Damaged Buildings.(e) In paragraph 5 of the Appendix to W.P. (44) 566 it was proposed that where a building entitled to a cost-of-works payment was acquired compulsorily, with the result that the cost-of-workspayment was turned-into a value payment, the owner-occupiershould receive supplementary compensation and that such supple-mentary compensation should be given by the local authority.The Minister of Town and. Country Planning said that therewould be strong opposition from the local authorities to the proposal that they should pay the supplementary compensation.It was pointed out that, if the obligation to pay the additional compensastion were placed on the War Damage Commission, theywould be obliged to discriminate between owners and owner-occupiers, which they could not do under present statutes, and thatit would be difficult to resist the argument that the Governmentshould pay full compensation for all.forms of loss of property dueto the war. The Government had never accepted this responsibility,which might involve them in additional expenditure to the order of 100,000,000. In fact, no hardship was imposed on the localauthorities, since, if they acquired a war-damaged building andrestored it, they would get a cost-of-works payment, while, if theychose to pull it down, they would get the benefit of the value payment.The local authority would also benefit from any additions to thevalue payment which might be given later under Section 11 of theWar Damage Act, 1943.The War Cabinet-(5) Agreed to maintain the principle that the local authority should be responsible for any supplementary compensa-tion given under paragraph 5 of the Appendix toW.P. (44) 566.Proposal to increase the Amount of Value Payments to all Owner-Occupiers of War-Damaged Property.(/) The Minister of Health asked whether the War DamageAct should not be amended in order to enable the owner-occupiers ofhouses entitled to value payments to receive up to 30 per cent, inaddition to the normal payment.
Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,13th October, 1944.The War Cabinet-(6) Agreed that this point was outside the scope of the Townand Country Planning Bill.Provision for varying the 30 per cent. Ceiling/(g) The Minister of Town and Country Planning suggestedthat the provision to be inserted in the Bill with regard to the30 per cent, limit on the additional payment which might be madeto owner-occupiers and to owners who had carried out improvementssince the 31st March, 1939, should allow the 30 per cent, to be variedby an order subject to an affirmative resolution.The War Cabinet (7) Approved the proposal of the Minister&apos; of Town and country Planning.(h) The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that he wished to record his personal disagreement with the distinctionbetween owner-occupiers and owners embodied in the principles setout in the Appendix to W.P. (44) 566. The effect of these principleswas to penalise the owner who had chosen investment in propertyform of thrift.The Chancellor of the Exchequer pointed out that during thewar and the period of disturbance which would follow it wasimpossible to rely on market value and that it seemed reasonablethat all property owners, at whatever time during this period theylost their property, should be compensated on the same basis.Different considerations arose in the case of the owner-occupiers of buildings and agricultural land who had to reinstate themselves.(j) The Minister of Town and Country, Planning said that itmight not be possible for Parliamentary Counsel to have the newclauses ready in time to put them on the Paper before Tuesday, the17th October, at the earliest. In these circumstances he suggestedthat the Government should state to Parliament the principles onwhich they had agreed and promise to embody the principles in aseparate Bill.The general feeling of the War Cabinet was that it was essential that the principles agreed on should be embodied in the bill now before the House.The War Cabinet-(8) Gave general approval to the-statement of principles set outin the Appendix to W.P. (44) 566; subject to con-clusions (1), (2), (3) and (7) above, and agreed that thestatement should form the basis of a reply to be givento a private notice Question, addressed. to the deputy prime Minister on the following day.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs asked whether itwould be possible for the Bill to reach the House of Lords by the19th October.The Minister of Town and Country Planning said that, if, as seemed necessary, the Bill had to be recommitted, this would not bepossible. Moreover, unless the present Session were extended fora further period, it might be found that there was not time to pass the Bill.&apos; The War Cabinet-(9) Agreed that, if necessary, there should be a further extension of the Session in order to ensure that the bill was passed. :



</content>
</cab>
