<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/23/0 images: 82-82</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TRIBUNALS AND MEDICAL BOARDS.

1. I understand that a suggestion has been made that the control of the work of the Tribunals set up to deal with exemptions from military service should be transferred from the Local Government Board to the National Service Department, or whatever new Department is to deal with recruiting.

2. I should like to press very strongly that this step would be retrograde and dangerous. The work has been exceedingly well done at the Local Government Board. That Department has the confidence of the local bodies who naturally look to the Board for guidance, and the transfer would be keenly resented by them and in the present state of public opinion would, I am sure, be generally unpopular. I believe the change would be strongly objected to by Local Government representatives in Parliament.

3. There is another point. The work of the tribunals is of a judicial nature and it would be unwise to bring it under a Department whose main business, whatever name may be given to it or whatever in theory may be its functions, must be the finding of men for the Army. The change would in effect be making the Recruiting Department judge in their own cause.

4. In my opinion it is essential to go further. The work of the Medical Boards stands very much in the same position. This also is work of a judicial nature, and should be controlled by a Department which is recognised as impartial. I therefore think that the control of the Medical Boards should be transferred to the Local Government Board, as was originally suggested by the Shortt Committee. There is great danger that, if the Medical Boards are placed under the Department which is responsible for finding men for the Army, public suspicion in connection with medical examinations will continue and a lever will be given for fresh agitation later. In view of what has happened before the Shortt Committee, it is most desirable to avoid any possibility of this.

W.H.L.

Colonial Office,

14th August, 1917.



</content>
</cab>
