<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/23/0 images: 138-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
WAR CABINETThe Supply and Distribution of WoolMemorandum by the Seoretary of State for War,With reference to War Cabinet 200, minute 5? I regret that owing to the illness of &amp;r. Forster I am unable to submit his report on the supply and distribution of wool.The subjoined minute from the Director of Raw Materials to the Surveyor General of Supply shows, I think, the present position of the Wool Trade in regard to the War Office.In view of lir, Forster&apos;s absence through illness, you have asked me to report what I know regarding his visit to Bradford on July 19th in connection with the dissatisfaction on the part of the Wool Trade.I did not accompany&apos;Mr. Forster, but I have heard        \ several accounts of the two Heetings which he addressed at Bradford.The firBt was attended by Wool : erchants, Spinners and Manufacturers, and the second by the Operatives.     In both cases Mr. Forster explained that the threatened shortage of wool shipments through the Submarine trouble had necessitated cutting down the hours of labour to conserve&apos; the supply, and he gave an estimate of the statistical position.I understand that at the Meeting of Employers, many angry speeches were made and the Department&apos;s figures were disputed.    Mr. Poreter accepted the appointment of a Committee of Enquiry, eonsiting f  Sir William Rayner, Ilr,.Norman Rae and three other members to go into the statistical position.The Labour Meeting was also I believe, rather unfriendly,^ and a general strike was threatened unless some means wero Revised of giving the operatives the wages corresponding lie a week of 55 hours., &quot;   &apos;After returning from Bradford, Mr. Forster reoeived Deputations in London from the Yorkshire Operatives in which, I understand, the demand was made that the Government should, in some way, make up to the labourers whatever wages were lost through short time enforced by Army Council Orders.     I have aince heard from some of the Labour representatives that Ilr. Forster held out very little hope of a solution on those lines, but at the Meeting of the Central Wool Advisory Committee   &apos; yesterday, it was stated that the Deputation was still awaiting the Government&apos;a reply with some impatience.Meantime, the census of wool stocks as at June 30th, which was not ready at the time of Mr. Forster!s-visit, has shown stocks of raw wool nearly 30$ greater than was anticipated. There is no doubt in the minds of our trade Advisors that this is due in a large part to returns in previous censuses having been under-stated.     In consequence of the larger stocks now reviewed 3 ^.7 tlle Department was able to agree at yesterday^ s*Iieeting of the 1 Central Wool Advisory Committee to an allocation for civilian trade of 12;,000,000 lbs,, per month for September, October andNovember,
November, as against 8/9,000,000 lbs which had before been contemplated as the extreme figure compatible with conserving military supplies.     In view of this arrangement, and in order to meet, if possible, the labour difficulty, the Advisory Committee recommended, and the Department agreed, that working hours in the Wool Textile industry should be raised to $0 hours per week, from September 1st.     Some of the Labour R representatives held out hopes that this would settle the labour question, but others were decidedly of the contrary opinion, and I should not like to lead you to suppose that the operatives will be content unless, in one way or another, they receive wages at the rate of     hours per week, calculating on Sir George Askwith&apos;8 reoent decision.As to the grievances of the employers, the report of the Committee of Enquiry has been received since&apos; Mr. Forster!s illness, and he has not been able to consider it.     The view of the Department is that no further light Is derived from that report, which merely twists round the Departments own figures in various ways.Mr. Porster, at the Meeting of the Central Wool Advisory Committee of August 2nd announced that a Board of Control would be set up in Bradford, consisting of one-third officials, one-third employers and one-third operatives, and that this Board will take charge of such Wool questions as the War Department is able to hand over without interfering with the execution of Army Contracts and other essentials which the Government must control.     This scheme has met with a mixed reception, and it as early yet to say whether it will remove any substantial part of the dissatisfaction in the Trade. &quot;While the position is difficult, I think &quot;that we shall be able to come to a satisfactory arrangement.(Sd.)   Derby,

</content>
</cab>
