<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/23/0 images: 140-142</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
mk SUPPLY OF LABOUR .Copy of letter fieri theJ^abour. -Aavigory &quot;CommitteaJo&quot;*th&apos;e Pr: me MiBi^er.National Service Department,St. Ermine, .tiestminstor. S,w.l : 10tb August, ,1917. ..Sir,In accordance with your request when we saw you on the 8th instant, we have pleasure in submitting tho following Report which has beon endorsed by tho Labour Advisory Committec.The National Service Department realising the necessity for the cordial co-operation of both employers and employed, set up Trade Committees to secure Substitution Volunteers.   Great hostility existed in regard to tho 25/- minimum in the original scheme, and to remove this hostility the Director-General, on the advice of his Central Advisory Committee (Messrs. Allan Smith, Muir Rjtohie, David Gilmour and Torn Shaw) and tho Labour Advisory Committee, adopted terms and conditions similar to those of the War Munition Volunteer.The securing of Substitutes through Trade Committeesmeans(1)   Me obtain experts to find us the workmen best fitted for the jobs. .(2)   V*&apos;e get cordial co-operation to find the workmen wlth-out inflicting undue hardship on any firm, or individual. Further, this co-operation ensures equality of sacrifice in each trade, thus maintaining a &quot;skeleton&quot; of every firm, so that work may bo rcsumod after the V/ari(3) The constitution of the Trudo Committees puts at tho disposal of the Department practical advice and guidance, with the result that the possibility of foolishly putting high salaried men into badly paid jobs is altogether remote.It is we know contended that the Labour Exchanges have beon successful in regard to the placing of men as V?ar Muni-tlon Volunteers, but it should be borne in mind that in thou-sands of eases the men wore invited to leave badly paid jobs to take up munition work at double or treble their old wages, , while even where financial sacrifices were actually made., it was often done to avoid what was regarded as the greater sacrifice of having to join the Army..,With National Service, the vast majority of the men with whom we shall havo to deal are men in middle life holding regu-lar jobs.   However patriotic they may be it can hardly be expected that men will leave their own regular work;   suffer the discomfort attendant on learning new work;   loso all home life, and, in addition, make a pecuniary sacrifice.
Through the Building Trades Committees we can oecure thousands, of men, released by the goodwill and co-cperation of the masters and men1s organisations working together for the purpose.   This is an admirable source from which to draw shipyard labour, but we understand that it is proposed to ignore it and to try to obtain the men required through the Labour Exchanges although it is admitted that the Exchanges are not able to meet even the current demands of the Admiralty for labour in the existing Shipyards.   We gather that the Labour Exchanges propose to obtain the men by means of adver-tlsements, but it must be apparent that when the very men to whom National Service terms and conditions have already been promised (without&apos;their having to pass through the Labour Exchanges) see that they are being asiced to pass through the Labour Exchanges and to work at lower rates and under worse conditions both they and their representatives will feel that they are being played with and badly treated, and the result will be.that - they will refuse to come forward to undertake the work under any conditions.The duplication,  the overlapping and confusion due to want of co-ordination is deplorable.Weeks have been wasted, and valuable time lost because this,  that, and the other Department were busy trying to claim certain work an theirs alone.In our view the whole question of man-power should be vested in ONE DEPARTMENT, with absolute authority to deal with all the Complex problems that arise.As illustrating the chaotic condition that exists through want of co-ordination, we give the following instances:IRON ORE. One Department (Munitions) build3 a large number of huts for men who are to be imported into the Di3-trict.   Another Department (National Service) is asked to supply men.   When a lot of trouble and expense has been- in-curred to find the men the Department is told not-be bother further because the other Department (munitions) has learned that certain local working conditions prevent the importation, while another Department (Treasury) believes that the men when obtained will cost too much.   Then we learn that other Departments (Labour and Munitions) are making arrangements &apos; ,. to bring over cheap Irish labour, but on ascertaining that the importation would precipitate a strike the matter i3 dropped.   The net result is, no fresh labour found; no in-crease in production; and 3,000 nutmeg standing empty.&apos; tsSHAf+E.   Shale Oil is urgently wanted,   The transfer of labour was practically arranged for by the National Service Department &quot;through Messrs. Adamson and Gilmour, when a hitch occurred.   Another Department (Munitions) stepped in and all
the ground previously covered had to be traversed again te arrive at a position already secured.   Not only is there delay, tut the men who have taken considerable trouble become disgusted when they find that their efforts have been wasted.PLYING BOATS. The Air Board asked the National Service Department to find them some practical boatbuilders.   The Director-General, in the light of previous experience asked if ,any other Department was being asked to do the same thing.   The answer was &quot;No&quot;-. - Messrs. Gilmour, Shaw and&apos;Williams were deputed to find the men required, but no sooner had they commenced the work than another Department (Admiralty) protested that in finding the men,  so urgently required, the National Service Department was interfering with /their work,    Some delay was caused while the matter was being adjusted, but subsequently the work was proceeded with, on lines similar to thoseAwhich -cur Trade Committees are based,  and the most satisfactory results have ensued.We   are firmly convinced that the obtaining and placing if all labour required for Government Departments should&apos;be Under the control of one Department only and we venture to submit that, as the National Service Department possesses the greatest degree of confidence of the organised workers, it is the proper Department to undertake the work, leaving the Labour Exchanges to continue to supply unemployed labour for other purposes than Government work.   The National Service should, however, have the right to obtain for Government purposes through the Labour Exchanges any suitable labour which they may have available.Such method would prevent overlapping in the supplying of men.   The Exchanges would carry on their work, while the ivational Service Department would fulfil the special function for which it was set up.We estimate that the extra cost to the Nation will not be large, because through our Trade Committees we get practical substitutes who are cheaper in the long run.   Any increase in cost in: the vast majority of cases would be due to the difference in &quot;rates of wages&quot;.   That some extra cost will be incurred is obvious.   Even the Admiralty and Ministry of liunitions have found it necessary to increase the subsistence allowance, and that, too, to men earning the best wages.We regret that we have to advise anything that may appear hostile to Labour Exchanges but we must face facts, and we should be lacking in cur duty both to. our Country and those we represent if we did not clearly state^tne foregoing is the only practical advice we can give^in view of the feeling exhibited, both by employers and enrployed, against the Exchanges at all the meetings we have attended.We are, on behalf of the Labour Advisory Committee,Yours respectfully,(sgd)    T. SHAW. ( &quot;   )   DAVID GILL OUR. ( &quot;   )   JOS. B. WILLIAMS. Secretary,Labour Advisory Commits?he Right Hon. D. Lloyd George, L.P., 10, Downing Street,Whitehall, S.W.I.

</content>
</cab>
