<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/23/0 images: 144-145</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I /123ItWAR CABipT, .RECOGNITION OF CLAIMS FROM ORGANX2ATION8 OUTSIDE THE CIVIL SERVICE.. Memorandum by the Obnciliation and Arbitration Board. (For Memorandum by the Ministry of Labour, s^e Paper G.T.1732).The Conciliation and Arbitration Board for Government Employees are desirous&apos; of obtaining instructions from His M?5.jesty*&apos;s Government 6n a point of interpretation in their Terms of Reference and Method of Procedure, viz.;&quot;Any claim which may fall within the Terms of Reference shall be heard before the Board acting as1 a triplicate Chairman, together with not more than three official representatives, and not more than three representatives of the class of employees con-cerned or their Associations, where such Association exists.&quot;Question - ARE THE WORDS UNDERLINED TO BE INTERPRETED AS COVERING AN ORGANIZATION OUTSIDE THE CIVIL SERVICE TO WHOM THE CLASS CONCERNED MAY HAVJB ENTRUSTED ITS INTERESTS .   OR AFFILIATED ITS ASSOCIATION?To illustrate the point it may be mentioned that claims have been received by the Board on behalf of certain classes of Government employees,.from the Amalgamated Society of Engineers, the Workers&apos; Union, and the National Union of Clerks.The general question was touched upon in the Majority Report^of the Royal Commission on the Civil Service (Chapter XI). but the Commissioners deliberately refrained from expressing any opinion on it.   At the end of that chapter (paragraph 25, p.99) they 3et out six questions relating to the civic rights of civil servants, one of which in, &quot;Should Associations of civil servants be at liberty to join with outside Trade Unions?&quot; They add &quot;The whole subject,&quot; (i.e. the subject covered by their six questions) &quot;it seems to us, is far too large, diffi-cult,- and complicated to be dealt v/ith as a minor issue in our enquiry.   We recommend therefore that a special enquiry should be held without undue delay to consider these matters, and we think that the body conducting the enquiry should include persons who have experience of conciliation and arbitration in the industrial world ............ It is in our opinion onlyafter full consideration of these and cognate matters by a body constituted for the purpose that a satisfactory conclusion can be reached on this difficult and complex subject.&quot;The Minority Report (sir Henry Primrose, Sir Guy Granet and Sir Alfred Booth) v/as less guarded.   In paragraph 69 (p.148) the subject is dealt with as follows&quot;A development has, we understand, taken place within recent time3 which raises the Question whether associations of the kind&quot;(i.e-, &quot;associations of civil servants formed for the purpose of formulating and advocating their professional claims&quot;)% may legitimately affiliate themselves to similar bodies outside the public service.   To this we should unhesitatingly reply in the negative.   Without examining closely what the
precise meaning and purport of nffiliation may be, it seems to us obvious that it must at least mean this, that theaffHating body sacrifices something of its indepen-denoe, and may under certain circumstances, be under an obligation to take action dictated, not by its 6wn needs or interests, but by those of the body or bodies to which it has affiliated itself,.   That at once condemns 1affilia-tion&apos; for associations of public servants in the nature of &apos;Trade Unions&apos;.   For associations of other kinds, mutual insurance societies, musical societies, and such like, affiliation would not be open to the same objections.   We therefore recommend that affiliation with bodies outside the Service should be forbidden, under pain of non-recog-nition, to associations having for their object the promo-tibn of Service interests.&quot;The Board understand that no steps have as yet been taken to set up such a Committee of enquiry as was proposed by the Majority Report.From the information before them,  the Board gather that the three War Departments, at any rate, have already gone a considerable way towards recognition or quasi recognition, of outside Trades Unions.   But the Treasury &quot;have represented to the Boaru that it would be unfortunate if the mature considera-tion of so important an issue were prejudiced by the Board1s treating outside organisations on the same footing as associa-tions of civil servants,  and have indeed suggested that such action would be contrary to the intention of Ills Maje3ty&apos;s Government as signified in the methods of Procedure prescribed for the Board.   The Board fully realise the importance of the question and are equally anxious to avoid prejudicing by any action of theirs an issue which is not specifically included in their reference.So long hovrever as the question remains undetermined the Board is liable to find itself confronted with the question of recognition of outside associations. : Claims from such organisations are being made to them, and it will be necessary for them either to hear the claims or to refuse to hear them. They therefore desire to obtain the views of His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos; on the question whether or.tside organisations should or should not be treated for the purposes of the Board&apos;s Terms of Reference on the same footing as associations of Government employees either absolutely, or provisionally pending further consideration of the subject by His Majesty&apos;s Government.

</content>
</cab>
