<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/23/0 images: 240-240</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
From Secretary of State to Viceroy, 14th August 1917. [Addressed to Viceroy, repeated to Sir P. Cox, Bagdad.)[? 3073] Foreign Secret. Mesopotamian Administration. Maude&apos;s telegram X. 2782, Cox&apos;s 2768, and yours of 30th July. His Majesty&apos;s Government are anxious to do justice to both points of view. They fully realise pre-occupations of General Officer Commanding, especially during next few months, and desire to avoid anything that can hinder his freedom of military action. On the other hand, civil administration must be carried on, under such military supervision as the General Officer Commanding considers essential, and carried on writh due regard to local conditions and prejudices, if only to prevent disorder which might necessitate detachment of troops urgently required elsewhere. His Majesty&apos;s Government cannot believe that General Officer Commanding should have any difficulty in working on these lines with an officer of the experience and tact possessed by Sir P. Cox ; but they repeat for latter&apos;s guidance what they have already said in my telegrams - of 10th May and 4th July, viz., that in view of present military situation ultimate responsibility of the General Officer Commanding must remain unimpaired, and that for the present&apos;only such minimum of administrative efficiency should be aimed at as is necessary to preserve order and meet needs of occupying force, while amendment of laws and introduction of reforms should be kept within,narrowest possible limits. Accordingly, until &apos;. danger of serious Turkish attack is past, His Majesty&apos;s Government do not desire that large or controversial administrative cpiiestions should be raised and referred to them. But they nuw receive very scanty information regarding course of events, number of Arab Bureau reports having latterly been greatly reduced. They desire to receive such information by mail or telegram from Civil Commissioner through General Officer Commanding, or if General Officer Commanding prefers, Civil Commissioner can submit reports to His Majesty&apos;s Government direct, sending him copy of everything. - It would perhaps conduce to more rapid and smooth despatch of business if an experienced officer of the General Staff were attached to Cox in order to ensure closer co-operation between the Army and Civil Staff.

</content>
</cab>
