<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/23/0 images: 241-246</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Department of Information. DGW/009.WSKKLY REPORT OH GREECE.  IX. (1G August, 1317).The Meeting, of the Chamber.The Chamber had   been convoked for July 12/25.     On that day, however, as 1b usual at the first meeting of the session, not enough deputies were present to make a quorum;   consequently Mr Venizelos merely read the Decree of Convocation and requested that the Chamber should adjourn and that it should be left to the President to summon it as soon as the requisite number of deputies could be present.     Mr Alavanos acted as President, as the former President of the Chamber, Zavitsianos, in 1915 had left the Venizelist Party and is now a member of the Opposition.Hardly any members of the Opposition had been present on July 25.   There seems to have been considerable doubt amongst them as to whether they would recognise the legality of the Chamber by attending, and such deputies as the ex-Venizelist L. Rouphos and the ex-Premier, Mr S. Dhraghoumis, championed abstention.     The anti-Venlzelist organ Skrip, however, wrote strongly advising attendance.   It declared that by being present deputies would by no means give their endorsement to the legality of the summoning of the Chamber, but merely would prevent more harm being done than might otherwise be done.     On August 1 the Chamber again assembled to elect a President.     The Venizelist candidate, Hr Sophoulis, was elected by 180 votes to 12. It will be remembered that the Venizelist deputies in June 1915 numbered 180 out of 316.    In the last few weeks it appears that a certain number of anti-Venizelist deputies have now decided to
throw in their lot with the Liberal Party, but anti-Venizellsts as a whole abstained from taking part in the election of the president.On taking the chair Kr Sophoulis emphasised the fact that the resummoning of the Chamber was a triumph for the principle $f democracy against monarchical tyranny.     The only attempt to controvert this triumphant assertion of the Venizelist victory was made by Mr Sokolis, deputy for Corfu, who has always been noted for the violence of his language.On August 4 the King attended a meeting of the Chamber and took the oath to the Constitution.     In his Speech from the Throne it was made perfectly clear that it wa3 &quot;in order to inaugurate the nev constitutional era which we are entering&quot; that &quot;we have repealed the decree which, by a violation of the1Constitution, dissolved the Chamber, and have convoked this Chamber for its regular second session&quot;.     The King went on to declare   definitely that Greece v/as now at war and had put herself at the side of the Entente Powers.   The need for a thorough purging of the Church, the Civil Service and the Judiciary was referred to and emphasis was laid on the fact that Greece1s new policy had led to the very satisfactory decision taken by the Conference at Paris to re-establish Greek Sovereignty by the abolition of the Controls and evacuation of the armies of occupation.The first important question arose on August 6.     The sixteen deputies of Northern Epirus sent in a petition demanding admission to the Chamber.   Though they had been temporarily denied this right by the Venizelist Government in 1915, the Skouloudhis Government in January 1916 had admitted deputies from Northern Epirus to the Chamber, and it was therefore
1188hoped that Mr Venizelos would now take the same course. In reply the Prime Minister went over his policy on the Epirote question and showed ho?/ the occupation of Northern Epirus, carried out in October 1914 with the consent of the Entente Powers, would have permanently secured this province to Greece but for the fatal policy of succeeding Cabinets who alienated from Greece the support of the Entente. At the present moment to admit the deputies would be to create international complications, but he declared that he had by no means given up the hope that the Peace Congress vould recognise the &quot;indisputable rights of Greece in Northern Epirus&quot; and the right of the inhabitants to decide their own fate.At this meeting the Opposition for the   first time turned up in full force.    It wag only to be expected that spasmodic attacks should be made on Mr Venizelos.   These were opened by Mr Kavallioratos, deputy for Kephallinia, who complained of the application of martial law (this had been applied by decree to Attica on August 2).   This roused the anger of the Venizelist majority who were by no means inclined to be tolerant of objections on the part of their opponents.    Mr Venizelos appealed for fair play, but informed the Opposition that they must realise the present situation and acquiesce in necessary precautionary measures.   If necessary, the Prime Minister declared himself ready even to have recourse to a dictatorship.Investigations and Reprisals.Already many of the worst offenders under the old regime have &quot;been removed from their posts, including all the chiefs of the Court of the Areopagus (the Greek Court of Cassation).Similar measures are to be applied to the ecclesiastical members of the Holy Synod who took a leading part in anti-Venizelist
politics.   Exhumations of bodies have shown that many Venizelist civilians were brutally killed and mutilated during the events of December last.   A more sensational revelation was that of the Minister of Finance on August 9.     He announced that the Skouloudhis Government had in January and April last year concluded two loans vrith the German Government each for  2,000,000, a/nd that these had been paid to Greece immediately after the surrender of Port Rupel.   Apparently the money had been used to subsidise the Reservists&apos; Leagues and anti-Venizelist press.     It is now announced that the Venizelist Government has the intention of bringing Mr Ghounari6, who is at present in Italy, to trial before a special tribunal. Some of the Venizelist papers are clamouring for vengeance against their opponents, but the Venizelist Government is determined to punish only those whose guilt is beyond doubt. The former anti-Venizelist press, which Is now pro-Ally in tone, naturally asks for mercy and appeals to the Venizelists not to disturb the newly-won harmony of the nation.Greece?s International Position.Greece is now officially recognised as being at war with the four enemy Powers.    (This fact is&quot;frankly recognised even by the anti-Venizelist press).     Mr Venizelosfs intention is to train the 1916 and   1917 classes at once.   These, together with the 1915 class, now under arms, and the army of the former Saloniki Government which is now in the field, would make a total force of between 150,000 and 200,000 men. Possibly some classes of Reservists may be called up, but for the moment it would be unwise to brirg up the bulk of the troops, especially those from the Peloponnese.
i190On the whole Greek public opinion was favourably impressed by the result of the Paris Conference.     In so far as it decided to withdraw the troops of occupation from Greece and definitely to recognise Greek Sovereignty in Corfu, the result was received &quot;with relief1&apos;.     Nor is the Italian occupation of the triangle of land round Poghoniani on the frontier of Northern Epirus, though it includes some indisputably Greek territory, very much objected to, provided the Greek civil authorities are reinstated and the occupation is considered a purely strategic one.     But considerable misgiving is expressed as to the future status of Northern Epirus as a whole aid the Greek press makes the point that now Greece is the Ally of the Entente, &quot;and therefore of Italy&quot;, it is hard to see why Italy should continue to suspect Greek intentions.On other points the relations between Greece and the Entente as a whole are naturally much smoother.   The Allied Control over posts, telegraphs, police, roads and railways was finally abolished on August 2.   A reservation was made as to the Control of the British Navy over ports and passports, but every consideration to the wishes of the Greek authorities is being given, and arrangements have been made to supply Greece with wheat mainly from Australia, the Greek Government being responsible for the bringing of the cargoes from Port Said.      The loan of some 200,000,000 francs from the British and French Governments is hoped for;   final arrangements between the British and French Treasuries as to this loan, its amount, character and use, have not yet been made.The French Government do not consider   that M. Jonnart&apos;s mission has yet terminated and desire him to return to Greece.
The Greek Government have shown signs of uneasiness lest Greek intervention in the war and the sending of Greek armies to the Macedonian front should be regarded by the Entente Powers as a substitute for their own efforts in that area.     In order that Greece should derive any benefit from the Saloniki campaign it is necessary that any troops supplied by her should be not a substitute, but a supplement, to the Allied forces on that front.   On this matter the Greek and Serbian Governments are in fu3J agreement.    It can easily be seen that Mr VenizeJLos^ prestige would be seriously affected by a with-drawal on a large scale from the Saloniki expedition.16.8.17. A.W.A.L.

</content>
</cab>
