<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/23/0 images: 311-315</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
D/HS/540.SUMMARY OF BLOCKADE INFORMATIONAugust 10-16, 1917*MI TED STATES.     H.M. Government desire that the United States and Great Britain should set up a joint Blockade Council, either in London or in Washington, to secure rapidity and unity of action in applying pressure to Germany&apos;s neutral neighbours.   It is also suggested that the United States should give us financial assistance in a policy of &quot;buying systematically from these neutrals whatever commodities they would otherwise export to Germany.   H.M. Government are pre-pared to embargo the exportation, from the United Kingdom to these neutrals, of all commodities which appear on the United States Prohibited List, except coal and such raw materials as we supply to firms manufacturing war supplies for us.   But the pressure which we can exercise through such an embargo is trifling in comparison with that which could be applied by the United States.   It is now from the States that the northern neutrals derive the greater part of their essential imports.SWEDEN.     There is some danger that the Russian Government may fall into a practice of exchanging important Russian products for Swedish munitions and food-supplies.   The Russian Government are proposing,for example, to supply Sweden with 20,000 tons of oil cake in compensation for shell cases, and to give further compensation for 40,000 tons of salt meat.   Sir E. Howard suggests that, if these exchanges cannot be prevented altogether, Russia should at least be induced to consult with her Allies in the matter.NETHERLANDS.     Our difficulties with the Dutch Government respecting the potato agreement are nearly settled.   Only a small balance - about 3,25q tons - is still owing to us from the
C       old crop; and the Landbouw Export Bureau are prepared to supply more than half of this deficit immediately.   But H.M. Government do not propose to grant letters of aesur-ance and other facilities for Butch cargoes until the transit of metals from Belgium to Germany is prohibited by the Butch Government.The Netherlands Overseas Trust have notified their willingness to resume official correspondence with H.M. Government.The Coal Distribution Bureau do not expect to receive more than 100,000 tons of German coal in August.   Though about 220,000 tons of Dutch coal will be available, the whole supply will be absorbed this month by the gas and water works, the railways, a few indispensable industries and private consumers.   Under these circumstances the Dutch are likely to pay the increased prices whioh the Germans demand as a condition of a new coal agreement.   The Germans have also asked for assurances that, if the agreement is signed, they will receive certain quantities of Dutch agri-cultural produce.   Sir W. Townley is anxious that more British coal should be exported to Holland.   It will be urgently needed by the Dutch industries which work for the Allies;   and only by providing the Dutch with British coal can we prevent them from purchasing German coal on terms injuriops to our interests.SWITZERLAND, Swiss delegates in Paris have signed ad referendum C      an agreement binding Switzerland to prohibit, as fromAugust 15, the export of all silks except those which the Allies admit to be of no military importance.
g,   baXONS.     An intelligence report states that, under arrangements made hy the Germans, the surplus of the Roumanian wheat-crop will go exclusively to Germany and Austria Hungary while the Bulgarian surplus will be sent to Turkey.   All reports agree that the Bulgarian harvest is excellent.86.   SOUTH AMERICA.   Subject to the approval of the United States we propose to inform the Brazilian Government that Brazilian coffee may enter the United Kingdom up to 50fo of the quantity imported in 1916, provided that at least 50$ of the enemy tonnage lying in Brazilian ports is chartered to the Inter-Allied Chartering Bureau for distribution among the Allies.The Peruvian Government have demanded from the German Government an indemnity for the sinking of the s.s. &quot;Lorton&quot;, and it is believed that, unless this demand is granted, Peru will break off diplomatic relations with Germany.S7, OCCUPIED TERRITORIES.     Mr. Hoover has offered to buy, for the use of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, large quantities of cereals which have been purchased for the Swedish, Nor-wegian and Dutch Governments and which are now detained in American ports.   If these offers are accepted, he will grant to each of the three Governments certain licences for the export of smaller quantities of grain.   To the Norwegian Government he promises that, after October 15, they may export the full equivalent of the cereals which they surren-der to the Relief Commission.   We do not oppose the scheme; but we assume that we shall be consulted before any suspectq commodities are licenced for export to these three countriesin consequenoe of Mr. Hoover1s bargains.   To expedite the delivery of relief cargoes H.M. Government have instructed Senior Naval Officers that vessels carrying such cargoes are
sot to be detained for reasons of general policy arising out of disputes between ourselves and neutral countries. We are also willing to let these cargoes be examined at the United States port of departure, to avoid the delays of a call at Halifax.Mr. Hoover has asked the French Government to relinquis to the Relief Commission in Northern France a part of the wheat which is held for French account by the United States.8. GERMANY.      For the present the food-crisis has abated. But thereare reasons to expect a coal famine during the winter, owing; to the shortage of labour, the congestion of the railways and the faulty system of distribution which has been in force during the past few months.   Only munitions works and a few privileged firms have been able to build up eatisfac-tory reserves.   There are also indications that the output of steel will be unavoidably curtailed during the winter. Some of the Luxemburg foundries are expecting to close down at the New ^ear for want of raw material.   Hardening materials are very scarce; for Norwegian molybdenite the Germans are paying prices 350$ higher than those which we have fixed in our contracts; the use of nickel is severely restricted, even in the manufacture of mot or-vehicles, and axles for such vehicles are now usually made from ordinary steel.GERMAN SUBMARINE CAMPAIGN. The following is a summary of the ^ losses of merchant tonnage, due to enemy activity, whichwere officially reported in the period Aug. 10 - 16 inclusive.     Smacks and trawlers are omitted.
Steamships (500 tons gross &amp; over)British ..........     48,199 tons gross.Allied &amp; Neutral..     43,784     &quot;      &quot;Sailing    (100 tons gross &amp; over) ?es&apos;selsBritish..........Allied &amp; Neutral..      6,015    n      &quot;Grand Total......     97,998     &quot;       &quot;Total British.....     48,199     * ..--------oOo---------H. W. C. D.WAR TRADE INTELLIGENCE BEPAgTMENT 17 August 1917.

</content>
</cab>
