<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/23/0 images: 604-607</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.

G.T.1776

WAR CABINET.

THE CONDITION OF IRELAND.

MEMORANDUM BY THE CHIEF SECRETARY FOR IRELAND.



During the past ten days violent activity in the Sinn Fein movement hae not been so marked as in the previous few weeks. A large number of Orators and organisers from Dublin as well as the resident local agents have pursued their activities as before, but action has been taken by the police and the competent military authority upon the decision of the Covernment to deal sharply with open offences against the Defence of the Realm Acts and Regulations, and a considerable, number of arrests, followed by prosecutions before resident magistrates and courts martial, have removed several mischiefmakers. The steps taken and to be taken will have the effect, I hope, of keeping the movement within the bounds of safety. There is still serious disquiet in the country. The county inspectors of the Constabulary in their reports for July stated almost unanimously that Sinn Fein is the only political agency in the country which shows any signs of activity, and in Galway, Glare, Kerry, Cork and N. Tipperary they speak of it as producing a change for the worse in the bearing and demeanour of large classes of the population.

Following upon the negotiations between Colonel Maurice Moore, C.B. Inspector-General of the National Volunteers, and the leaders of the Irish Volunteers, which lately came to light, and which created a risk that the arms and ammunition of the former organisation would be transferred to the ? ?, the General Officer commanding in Ireland made arrangements with the chiefs of police whereby during the


jght of Tuesday last all the known repositories of these arms were entered under the powers of the Defence of the Realm Regulations, and the arms and ammunition - 8,668 rifles and 11,226 rounds - were taken under   military control.     The danger to which   referred in a recent memorandum that theSe ?/eapons would pass into the hands of a disloyal organisation, end which was thought hy the General Officer Commanding to be serious from s military point of view, is thus removed.     The custody of the arms was secured without resistance.The seizure has caused some angry comment in the nationalist newspapers and in a speech of Mr.John Dillon, M.P. tut the measure is one which I have often represented as a necess-&amp;ry precaution,, and I regret only that there yet remain large numbers of rifles in the hands of private persons in Ireland, which ought, in the public interest 7  to be under safe custody.A strike of labourers in the flax-growing districts of Donegal and some areas of Tyrone gave rise to serious apprehension of loss of a crop peculiarly valuable at present as the means of providing canvas for aeroplanes.     For some days the situation was critical, and it appearsed possible that measures would have to be taken to transfer the control of this crop to the Ministry of Munitions.     Thanks in part to the good offices of representatives of the Ministry andjthe Department of Agriculture in Ireland, and the very tactful behaviour of the county inspector- of the Constabulary, the dispute was settled soon enough to. admit of the saving of the crop.
iSscelleut harvest prospects aro stated from all partsof the country in the lr-tost reports I have seen, and cn*result h;s boon to rc-liove some of the difficulty which had-risen from unemployment by reason of the restrictions oftrade imposed under the Defence of the xtealm Modulations.Trie .ifficultieo caused by the restrictions becomes nevor-theless an increasingly serious factor in the Irish situation.A prohibition of dealings in farm produce which came first tomy knowledge when questions were asiced about it of theMinistry of Food and an angry Speech made in the House of theCommons, and/publication of maximum prices for cattle and for cereals havo caused very general excitement during the week.   These necessary stagos in tho regulation of dealings in food provoke inevitsblo dissatisfaotion among agricul-turists.    It would probably be advantageous if food control were to a greater degree localised in Ireland.   I am oom-pleting: arrangements for an Irish Advisory Committee, but I doubt whether something more may not prove to be necessary. Two questions involving much risk cf conflict snd loss aro now about to arise.   The oat csop which will be unprece-dentedly large was produced under a governmental guarantee of s price of 36/6d, but this is not for new oats.   The oats are ordinarily threshed and marketed immediately after harvest when they are too green for carriage in bulk.-  Means of storage do not exist, and the Irish farmer?has never learned to st$ok his corn crops,   iso it may well happen unless the reprsentatives of the Government - preferably tho Army buyers -are able to make arrangements about the handling of this crop that a great deal of food i*ill be sacrificed and a large claim set up wider the guarantee of pricesv-   I am told these arrange-, raents have been discussed but not decided u -on and that they could very easily be made...   .  Again, a. Committee set up in Ireland by the Government, lor the buying of cat tie for Army
rations, lately issued through tho newspapers an announcement that the Government would buy100,UuO cattle there for the Army at the maximum prices fixed in lord RhonddaJe recent Order and.various arrangements wore mado in &quot;the cattle trade on this footing.   Tho.issue ef the Order has had tho effect of bringing cattle into the market in such numbers that prices are below the maximum.   Thereupon as I ata told it is sought on behalf of the Army buyers to reduce tho prices announced in the newspapers.   Such a proceeding would certainly have unfortunate consequanooc, whethor it wero resorted to in England or in Ireland.   In Ireland one of the offeots of every blunder of a Government Department: is to aggiar&amp;to the prevailing discontent, and a blunder   : whioh affects the prices of cattle., corosls or potatoes, &apos;&apos;&quot; has its effect in every pafiish.   I mention thece topics becauso the constant recurrence of difficulties in the administration of Food Control confirms my belief that the uniform extension to Ireland ef the regulations whioh are made for Groat Britain may presently be a cause of increased trouble in Irish administration.(Initialled)    H.E.D.Irish Office.19th. August,. 1917.

</content>
</cab>
