<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/42/41 images: 310-317</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT   151Printed for the War Cabinet.  June 1944.SECRET. Copy No. 52W.M. (44)83rd Conclusions.WAR CABINET 83 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Cabinet War Roomon Wednesday, 28th June, 1944, at 6 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the ChairItems 4-6).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee,. M.P:,Lord President of the Council (in theChair, Items 1-3).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson.M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The. Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minster of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present:The   Right  Hon.   Viscount   Simon,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.Sir James Grigg,of State for WarThe Right Hon.M.P., Secretary(Items 2-6).The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C.,  M.P.,  Minister of AircraftProduction.The Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster(Item 6).The   Right Hon.   Lord   Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Joint     Parliamentary     Secretary,Treasury (Item 6).The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Colonel the Right Hon. OliverStanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies (Items 2-5).The Right Hon. Sir ArchibaldSinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Richard Law, M.P.,Minister of State (Items 1-5).The Right Hon. Sir Donald Somer-vell, K.C., M.P., Attorney-General.The Right Hon. W. Whiteley, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Item 6).Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite.
WAR CABINET 83 (44).Contents.MinuteNo.                                     Subject. Page1      United Nations Reconstruction and Development Bank 1392      Ethiopia........      ....      ....      ................ 1393      Arrangements for Repatriation of certain Germans      .... 1404      War Criminals............................      140Treatment of Major Enemy War Criminals.5      War Criminals ....       ............       ........       ....       141United Nations War Crimes Commission.6      By-E lections   ........................      ....      142Suggested Temporary  Release  of  Party   Agents   from theServices.
UnitedNationsReconstructtion andDevelopmentBank.1. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (W.P. (44) 338) on the proposedUnited Nations Bank of Reconstruction and Development, whichwas to be discussed at Bretton Woods. There were strong argumentsfor the organisation of the Reconstruction Bank at a very earlydate, but the American scheme needed elucidation and amendmentin certain essentials.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the Treasury feltthat if such a Bank could be established on the terms for whichwe proposed to press, it might serve a very useful purpose. Themain point on which amendment was necessary was to ensure thatloans should be completely &quot; untied,&quot; and so available for purchasenot only in the country in which they were issued, but in any membercountry. The position of existing bondholders would also need verycareful consideration. Subject to these points, and to the remainingpoints which he had made in paragraph 3 of his Memorandum, hethought the plan a good one.Points made in discussion :  (a) The Minister of Labour and National Service asked whetherthe Bank would be required to pay any regard to labour conditionsand the importance of raising the general standard of living inmaking loans. Would the Committee of the Bank consult the I.L.O. ?Certain observations had been made on this point in the recentI.L.O. Conference in Philadelphia.The Chancellor of the Exchequer sympathised with the Ministerof Labour&apos;s point. The Bank was not compelled to agree to aparticular proposition if it did not think it merited approval. Herather doubted the suitability of inserting a stipulation on thispoint in the charter of the Bank, but he would be.very ready toinstruct our representatives to see that this point was taken intoconsideration.(b) The Lord President of the Council suggested that ourdelegates might keep in mind the desirability of constituting theBank in such a way that it could be used to maintain a steady aswell as a large flow of international investments.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that this would accordwith the intentions of the scheme.The War Cabinet-Agreed that, subject to amendment of the American schemein the respects described in paragraph 3 of W.P. (44) 338and to consideration of the point raised by the Ministerof Labour and National Service, our delegation to theforthcoming Monetary Conference should be authorised tosupport the drawing up of a definite scheme for submissionto Governments.Ethiopia.(PreviousReference:W.M, (43) 167thConclusions,Minute 1.)2.   The War Cabinet had before them two Memoranda by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs : (a) W.P. (44) 333.-Policy in Ethiopia.(b) W.P. (44) 334.-British interests in Ethiopia.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that in the firstof these Memoranda he had examined the general question of thepolicy to be adopted by His Majesty&apos;s Government in Ethiopia, andhad urged the advisability of collaboration with the United Statesto provide Ethiopia on a joint basis with financial and otherassistance. There were many detailed points which called forconsideration. He suggested that the issue as a whole might beconsidered by a Ministerial Committee. He felt that there was a. basis for a very reasonable deal at the peace table between Ethiopiaand ourselves. The difficulty was to bridge the interim period untilthe peace, and for that purpose to keep the old Agreement in beingpending the negotiation of a new one.
The Secretary of State for the Colonies supported the proposalsof the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Secretary of State for War suggested that our case mightbe stronger than appeared on the surface, and thought that theCommittee should not be tied down to recommending a policy ofstrict collaboration with the United States.After further discussion, the War Cabinet Appointed a Committee comprising the Chancellor of the Exchequer (in the Chair);the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs;the Secretary of State for the Colonies;the Secretary of State for War; andthe Minister of State;to consider and report to the War Cabinet on the questionsof policy in Ethiopia set out in W.P. (44) 333 andW.P. (44) 334.ArrangementsforRepatriationof CertainGermans.3. The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security saidthat arrangements had now been reached with considerable difficultyfor the exchange of 500 Germans now interned in this country forthe same number of British subjects interned in Germany. Nearlyall were interned in the Isle of Man, but ten were at present at large.He proposed to arrest and intern the ten until they were exchanged.In the interests of preventing up-to-date information from gettingback to Germany, he had considered whether all visits to interneesin the Isle of Man should not be stopped until the exchange hadtaken place. Such a decision would be open to the charge that wewere behaving in an inhumane fashion, and there was the risk ofretaliation.In reply to questions, the Home Secretary and Minister ofHome Security undertook to enquire further as to the position ofthese ten individuals. He emphasised his anxiety that therepatriation of the 500 British internees to be exchanged for the500 German internees should not be held up if this could be avoided.The War Cabinet-Agreed that the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs andthe Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security shoulddiscuss-the matter with authority to settle any outstandingpoints.WarCriminals.Treatment ofMajor Enemy-WarCriminals.(PreviousReference:W.M. (44) 34thConclusions,Minute 4.)4. On the 13th March the War Cabinet had considered thequestion of the treatment of the major enemy war criminals, namely,those &apos;&apos; whose offences have no particular geographical location, andwho will be punished by a joint decision of the Governments andtheir Allies.&quot;The War Cabinet now had before them (i) A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (W.P. (44) 330) to which were attached tentativelists of the major German and Italian criminals;(ii) A Memorandum by the Lord President of the Councilcommenting on this list (W.P. (44) 345); and(iii) A Memorandum by the Lord Chancellor (W.P. (44) 294) towhich was annexed a revised draft formula to expressthe proposal which His Majesty&apos;s Government shouldmake to the United States and Soviet Russia in definingthe procedure to be adopted in dealing with these majorcriminals (Annex 7).
WarCriminals.UnitedNationsWar CrimesCommission.&apos;(PreviousEef erenee:W.M. (42) 131stConclusions,Minute 7.)5. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theLord Chancellor (W.P. (44) 294) reviewing the work of the UnitedNations War Crimes Commission.The Lord Chancellor thought that the Commission had put anunduly narrow construction on their terms of reference, and thattheir work had suffered accordingly. He made a number ofsuggestions which may be summarised as follows :-(a) The Commission should be pressed to take a broader viewof their functions.(&amp;) They should be told that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentattached importance to their collecting evidence of the commissionof war crimes generally by our enemies.The following were the main points made in discussion: . (a) It was urged that the compilation and publication of thelist of the 50 or 100 most prominent Avar criminals would tend toisolate them from the ordinary people in the Axis countries. Itcould not be denied that the Nazi Leaders had committed terriblecrimes which called for the extreme penalty.(&amp;) It was pointed out that the list compiled by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs included a considerable number of personswho occupied prominent posts in the Nazi party, but who were quiteunknown to the general public. On the one hand it could be arguedthat the fact that they had held these posts was, prima facie, evidenceof guilt. On the other hand, it was argued that what was reallycalled for was a short list of a dozen or so of persons who hadexercised supreme power in Germany in the last few years, and whowere responsible for the crimes which had been committed.(c) Some Ministers feared that publication of a list at thepresent time might result in a threat to put to death, by way of *retaliation, a number of men of Allied nationality now in the handsof the enemy. Moreover, such a threat might well be acted upon.It was, therefore, suggested that it would be better to postponepublication of the list until the defeat of the enemy could be seento be more imminent.(d) It was important to stress in a public announcement thecontrast between war crimes committed in particular localities, andfor which specific evidence could be adduced, and the major warcriminals whose offences had no geographical location.(i?) Some of the difficulties referred to in (c) might perhaps beavoided by an announcement on the lines of Annex 7 toW.P. (44) 294, which stressed the distinction in (d) and proceededon the following lines : &quot; The inner ring of enemy leaders whose crimes have nogeographical location and who have been generally responsible. -. . . if they fall into the hands of the Armed Forces of theUnited Nations will be dealt with according to the decision ofthe United Nations as to their fate. This inner ring wouldconsist, among others, of . . . ., &amp;c.&quot;The War Cabinets decision was as follows : (1) The Lord Chancellor, the Minister of Aircraft Productionand the Attorney-General were invited to submit to theWar Cabinet revised proposals, prepared in the lightof the discussion, for dealing with the major warcriminals. This report should include a revised draftformula to express the proposal that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment would make to the United States and SovietRussia for defining the procedure to be adopted indealing with these major criminals.(2) A decision as to publicity was deferred; bearing in mindthat this point would not arise until a later stage.
By-Elections. 6.   The War Cabinet considered whether authority should beSuggested given for the temporary release from one of the Services of the PartyTemporary Agent in a Constituency in which a by-election would shortly takeRelease of        place.Party Agents In favour of this course, it was urged that it was greatly in thefrom the public interest to take steps to facilitate the proper working of ourServices. democratic institutions.   Moreover, as the proposal was limited toby-elections, the number of cases would be&quot;, small. All the politicalparties must, of course, be treated alike in this matter.From the point of view of the man-power situation, the Ministerof Labour and National Service said that it would be difficult to domore than- apply to such cases the machinery which already existedfor dealing with persons with special qualifications whose releasewas asked for. For example, thei Party- Leaders might makeapplication to his Department through the usual channels, it beingunderstood that no men could be released unless this was compatiblewith military requirements. Most of the men concerned were ofmature age.On the other hand, it was urged that the needs of the Partiesat by-elections could usually be adequately met by officers detachedfrom.the central party political organisation; and that temporaryrelease from the Services for political purposes might well be subjectto severe criticism.The War Cabinet-.Agreed that the matter should.be the subject of examina-tion and early report by a Committee.  The Parliamentary.Secretary to the.Ministry of Labour would be Chairmanof this Committee. The, Joint Parliamentary Secretariesto the Treasury would arrange for a representative of each-of the main political parties to be associated with theParliamentary Secretary in this enquiry.Offices of the War Cabinet, S. W. 1,28th June, 1944.(c) Sir Cecil Hurst should be informed that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment agreed that further consideration should be given tothe suggestion that members of the German organisation that hasbeen administering the various occupied territories might properlybe detained pending the further evidence that would be availableafter the countries were reoccupied.(d) We should be ready to agree to an extension of theCommission^ terms of reference to include crimes committed againstItalians and Danes.(e) We hoped that the Commission would collect evidence ofatrocities perpetrated in occupied countries by Germans againstJews.The War Cabinet-Approved these proposals, subject to the discussion by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs and the LordChancellor of certain minor points.



</content>
</cab>
