<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/51/24 images: 176-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S (SOVEB1MBNTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of..;......S&amp;iks^a^............TOP secret copy No..../..&quot;?..,W..M. (45)  24TK conclusions MS , MINUTE confidential Annex(22nd February, 1945 - 6.30 p.,;.)IanpowerJianpower injhe first HalfIf 1945[Previous[of erence:(45) 17th[Conclusions,Minute 2)The War Cabinet considered a Memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (W.F.(45) 87),  setting out the results of an examination by the ministerial committee on Manpower of the effect upon other manpowerprogrammes of the revised requirements of theMinistry of Aircraft Production and the admiralty for the first half of 1945, arising from the decisions taken by the War Cabinet at their meeting on the25th January (W,M.(45) 9th Conclusions, Minute 1).  &apos;The Manpower Committee estimated that the effect ofthese revised requirements&apos; would be. that the netincreases during the first half of 1945 in manpowerallocations to all industries and services other thanmunitions would have to be reduced from 315,000 to210,000, as against requirements amounting to over532,000.       In the case of the Board of Trade thereduction would be from 170,000 to 85,000, as againsta requirement of 375,000.      It would also be impossibleto meet in full the approved intakes to the armed forces for the first six months of 1945 (the deficiencymight be about 5,000).Points in discussion -(a) Board of Trade.      A reduction to 85,000 ofthe allocation to the Board of Trade would have veryserious effects on the supply of goods, for civilian consumption and on - preparations for the expansionof our export^ trade.      In particular, it would mean that the clothing ration would have to be reduced and that the programme for the production of utilityfurniture would be set back.(b) Ministry of Works.      Although it was not proposed to cut the allocation of 30,000 originally intended by the Ministerial Committee, which had as its object to build up the labour force of the building and civil engineering industries to 517,000 at the end ofJune,-  there was a danger that, unless buildingoperatives were specially earmarked.for release from munitions production,  this figure would not infact be achieved,     Moreover, even if it were achieved,it might not suffice to ensure the fulfilment of theprogramme of temporary houses and would not enableany progress to be made on the programme of permanent houses during 1945.-1-

(c) Air Ministry. . The new assumptions adopted at&apos; the Crimea Conference regarding the terminationof hostilities with Germany meant that it would be ,necessary to train 5?000 additional men as air crews,in order to insure against the possibility of a continuance until the end of December of casualtiesat the rate estimated to be probable so long as theEuropean war lasted.    The improvement in the war situation in Burma might, however, make it possiblefor a modification, as from the beginning of June,of . the arrangement whereby men were being transferred -from   the R.A.P.  to the Army,.(d)&apos;Ministry of Aircraft Production.    The effectof the decisions taken &quot;by the War Cabinet on the 25thJanuary had been to increase the labour force required at the 30th June, 1945j by 100,000 workers, from1,1^0,000 to 1,22+0,000.    Some 6o per cent of this increase was, however, in respect of bombs and otherancillary equipment whose production it would bepossible to stop at short notice as soon as. hostilities in Europe actually came to an.end.    Meanwhile, no cut in the allocation to the Ministry of Aircraft production could be accepted unless the aircraft programme wasmodified.(e) Ministry of Supply.   Very substantial cutshad been imposed on the&apos; Ministry of Supply labour force during 19kk and the prolongation of the war inEurope had made it necessary to re-start the productionof some items which had then been eliminated from theprogramme.    In the case of the Ministry of Supplyalso, there would be no reduction in the presentallocation unless existing programmes were modified.In further discussion the view was expressed that it was essential that there should be someexpansion before next winter in civilian production,both for the home market and for exportj    and itwas suggested that this could be achieved if some reduction were, accepted in both the quantity and quality of munitions for, use in the Japanese war only.THE PRIME MINISTER said that first priority mustbe given to the maintenance of the front line strengthof the Army in Europe, and to the production of the munitions required for the European war.    Subject tothis, however, every effort must be made to meet themost essential requirements for a reasonable expansionof civilian production, even at the expense of somediminution or delay in our contribution to the japanese war.    In particular, it must not be assumed that new equipment of tho very, latest design mus-t beproduced for use against the Japanese if stocks were available of similar equipment which,  though   &apos;slightly less up-to-date, was yet serviceable -for the far Eastern war.    There should be no change in programmes, and no announcement of the change of emphasis now contemplated;    but programmes should be reviewed in the light of this general principle andshould be allowed to fall behind schedule to an extent representing n diminution of, say, 15per cent in our contribution to the Japanese war.

The War Cabinet -Agreed to the. Prime Minister&apos;suggestion&apos; that he should issue a Directive on the steps which &apos;should be taken to carry put the-policy indicated in his summing up* &apos; y ; ; -       ^ :Offices of the War Cabinet, 3.W.1.




</content>
</cab>
