<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/35/19 images: 134-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet. August 1943.SECRET.Copy No.109th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 109 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W.lion Monday, 2nd August, 1943, at p.m.. Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime, Minister\ (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.,The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Horn Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.    .The following were also present:The Right Hon. S. M. Bruce, Repre-sentative of the Government of theCommonwealth of Australia.The Right Hon. Sir KingsleY Wood,M;P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production!The Right Hon. Sir Donald Somer-vell, K.C., M.P., Attorney-General(Item 6).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal; Chief of the Air Staff.The Right Hon. Viscount Simon,Lord Chancellor (Items 6-8).The Right Hon. L. S. Amery^ M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Item 2).Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.General Sir Alan Brooke, Chief of theImperial General &quot;Staff.Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Lieutenant-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. L. F; Burgis.[25877]b
WAR CABINET 109 (43).Contents.minute no. Subject.1      Naval, Military and Air Situation ....Air Operations -Home Theatre.Comparison with Battle of Britain.Mediterranean.Ploesti.Naval Operations.Military Operations Sicily.Russia.2      France ....       ....   ,   .............. General de Gaulle.Press Directive.3     Prisoners of War......       ....      ....Shackling.4     Italy     ....      .....     ....      ....      .....-5      Italy     ....      .............Propaganda Policy.6      The Regency Act       ....      ....      ....      ....7     Aircraft Production   ........      ....Labour Disputes.8     Government Departments...........Inquiry into staffing of Public Relations Branches.
Masai, Military / 1. The Chiefs of Staff reported the principal events of theand Air previous week. -Operations. bomber command;had made two heavy attacks on Hamburg(Previous        (on which - 7^&apos;^;toli8^ha4^^been/ &quot;dropped; -*j(uriiig.ibhe previous nine.Reference:       days) and had also devastated Remscheid. HDhited States AirW.M. (4$) lb4th Forces had attacked Hamburg; Cassel, Kiel and Magdeburg.Conclusions,      During July the R.A.F. had dropped 16,700 tons and United StatesMinute 1)&apos;     Air Forces 3,200 tons on Germany.Air Operations.        During the previous week the Air-Sea Rescue Service hadHome Theatre,  rescued some 156 bomber personnel (121 belonging to the UnitedStates Army Air fore,  ). &apos;-The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for Air to convey to theOfficer Commanding this Service the congratulations of theWar Cabinet on this achievement.Coastal Command had made 7 promising attacks againstU-boats, 3 of which had almost certainly been sunk.Enemy losses (including those claimed by the United States AirForce) had been 287 destroyed and 80 probably destroyed. Britishlosses had been 87 aircraft (including 60 bombers). The UnitedStates had lost 77 aircraft.Comparison The Chief of the Air Staff said that a comparison of R.A.F.with Battle of .and United States Army Air Force activities in the home theatreBritain. for the week ending the 1st August this year with the heaviestweek of the Battle of Britain (i.e., week ending the 31st August,1940) was as follows : Offensive Sorties by R.A.F. and U.S.A.A.F. weekending the 1st August, 1943        ......     8,128Offensive Sorties by G.A.F. in 1940, week ending the 31st August      ...      ...    &apos; ...      ...     5,120Bombs   dropped   by   us   week   ending   the1st August, 1943     ...      ...      ...      ...     6,830 tonsBombs dropped on Britain week ending the31st August, 1940   ... ......     5,060 tonsR.A.F. and United States losses week ending the1st August, 1943      ............       157G.A.F. losses in week ending the 1st August,1943-Destroyed ...      ...      ......       287Probably destroyed     ...      ......       107Damaged .........      ...       122G.A.F. fighters lost in the week ending the31st August, 1940 ...      ... ... ...       318R.A.F. fighters lost in the week ending the31st August, 1940 ...      ... ... ...        138In short (approximately) last week the R.A.F. and UnitedStates Air Forces had-carried out: 60 per cent, more sorties;dropped : 35 per cent, more bombs;lost: half as many aircraft;destroyed: 90 per cent, of the number of aircraft that theGermans had lost in the week ending the 31st August, 1940.Enemy losses in the Mediterranean had been 88 destroyed,14 probably destroyed and 22 damaged. We had lost 16 aircraft.Nine large and 10 small vessels had been hit, including an Italiancruiser and destroyer. -A powerful force of United States Liberators had made a successful attack on the oil refineries at Ploesti. The operation wasconsidered one of the finest that had been carried out during the war.The Prime Minister said that, when further details hadbeen received, he proposed; to send a message of congratulationto the American Air Command responsible for planning the[25877j;:.. - b 2Mediterranean.Ploesti.
naval operations;Military:Operations.Sicily.Bussia.operation. He asked the Chief of the Air Staff to furnish him with the necessaiy particulars.        &apos;Shipping losses by enemy action for the previous weeki amounted; to 89,000 tons. Losses by enemy action for the month of&quot;July lamountcdto 313;000 tons, of which 54,000 had been lost in theSicilian operations. /Marine losses for the month had been 21,000.The number of U-boats sunk during July equalled the recordsinkings for the month of May.The battle for Catania had begun the previous night. no reports of its progress had yet been received. In the &quot;fighting beforethe battle the Germans had suffered heavy casualties. Prisonersnow amounted to 100,000, mostly Italians.The Russians had been attacking on all sides of the Orelsalient. They had also been carrying out attacks in the North in front of Leningrad and in the South in the regions of Isyum,Kuibyshevo and Krinskaya.The War Cabinet-Took note of these statements.France.general de Gaulle.Press Directive.(previous reference:-W.M. (43) 99thConclusions,Minute 1.)2. The Prime Minister said that Mr. Aneurhv Bevan, M.P.,and others proposed to raise in the House of Commons on thefollowing day the question of the directive which he (the PrimeMinister) had given to the press some eight weeks ago regardingBritish policy towards General de Gaulle. Some portions of thisdirective (which had been confidential) had been published in theUnited States Press. In reply to a Question in Parliament on the21st July, he had stated that, while he took full responsibility forthe directive, he was not prepared to discuss it in the Houseotherwise than in Secret Session. If the matter was raised on thefollowing day, the House should at once be moved into secret session. Any public discussion of the incident would havedeplorable results.The War Cabinet-Agreed that if the matter was raised in the House ofCommons on the following day it should be handled in theway proposed by the Prime Minister.The Minister of Information mentioned that there was some reason to believe that Mr. Aneurin Bevan might publish the directive in the Tribune. It was difficult to see what could be done to prevent this, although action Could be taken after the event.Prisoners ofShackling... \(previous reference: ,W.;M. (43) 101stConclusions, :Minute 2.)3. The War Cabinet had before them a Note by the PrimeMinister (W.P. (43) 348) suggesting that a statement should bemade that a record would be kept of the total number of man-dayson which British and Canadian prisoners were chained, and thatthe Officer Corps of the German Army would be required to servedouble this number of man-days in chains after the defeat ofGermany. &apos; ,&apos;The following points were made in discussion :- .(a) The. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs suggested thatwe should await the upshot of an enquiry which hadbeen made through-our Minister in Berne as to whether&apos; the shackling had not now become symbolical, before. consultation took place with the\Dominion and UnitedStates Governments on this proposal.
201w, . The Secretary of State for War said that his information ledhim to believe that this was now the case.it should also be for consideration whether the proposed/ x it st^te^ents?ouldbemadeprivatety(c) il/r5mce said that he thought that both the Canadian and australian Governments would be strongly opposed tothe adoption of this suggestion.The Prime Minister said that, in view of the doubts which hadbeen expressed, he would not press his suggestion at the presenttime. -. .Italy.(Previous .Ref erence:W.M. (43) 108thConclusions.)4. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by thePrime Minister (W-P. (43) 353) covering a redraft of his Noteentitled &quot;Thoughts on the Fall of Mussolini &quot; (previously circu-latedas W.P. (43) 339) incorporating certain amendments suggestedby President Roosevelt.In discussion, it was pointed out that paragraph 11, as nowdrafted, might seem to imply that we had not kept in touch withthe Russian Government on our policy in regard to Italy. TheSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he had informed the Russian Government of our general intentions in regard to draftArmistice Terms, and that they had expressed themselves assatisfied.It was suggested that, if the words &quot; affecting the Balkans&quot;in paragraph 11 were omitted, this point would be met. This wasagreed to.The Prime Minister said that he had sent a further telegram tothe President suggesting the following altered wording in para-graph 2/ &quot;. ... . namely, the destruction of Hitler and the totaldefeat of Germany.&quot;The War Cabinet- .(1) Took note, with approval, of the revised Memorandum(subject to these two further amendments) as nowconstituting a Joint Directive to the United Kingdomand United States Governments on the broad policy tobe pursued.(2) Agreed that the Dominion Prime Ministers should beacquainted with the final text of the Memorandum and informed when this final text had been accepted by theUnited States Government.Italy. 5.   The Prime Minister read to the War Cabinet a messagePropaganda which he proposed to send to President Roosevelt about the needPolicy. for co-ordinating;high propaganda policy between the United Statesand ourselves in regard to our attitude towards Italy.; In particular,,he proposed that no propaganda announcements should be issued in the name of the Supreme Cbmmander-in-Chief unless they hadthe prior agreement of the President and himself.The War Cabinet-. Took note, with approval, of this message.the regency 6.   At their Meeting on the 27th July the War Cabinet hadAct, asked;the Lord Chancellor,;in consultation with the Home &quot;Secretary(Previous ami Parliamentary Counsel; to prepare a draft Bill amending the reference; Regency Act, 1937, so as to provide that the^Heir-presumptive toW;TW. (^)-i06th theThr^Conclusions, the.age of 18.Minute 8 j .;--, ^::?:r;&apos;&apos;v&apos;&apos;-:?::^
Aircraft 7.   The Minister of Aircraft -Production reported that a strikeProduction. had occurred at Avro&apos;s Wdodford works over the determination ofLabour fixed piece prices. The Shop Stewards&apos; Chairman, on the 24th July,Disputes. had informed the Works Manager that, unless the price which hadbeen paid when the firm had been making aircraft of a different typewas restored, the men would cease work on the 26th July. This was an illegal procedure, contrary to the agreement for avoidingdisputes.The strike was still continuing. On the 30th July a meeting ofthe shop stewards representing the engineering trade generally inthe Stockport area had decided that, unless Avro&apos;s posted a notice on the 3rd August withdrawing from their position, the whole ofthe workers in the Stockport engineering trade would come out on strike. The position would perhaps be a little clearer when theresults were known of a meeting of the shop stewards in theStockport district which was being held that evening.&quot;. The Minister of Aircraft Production felt bound to warn theWar Cabinet that he took a grave view of the position, and feared that these labour difficulties, unless firmly handled, might spread.He thought that this strike arose from the struggle between the shop stewards Movement and the Trade Union organisation.The Prime Minister suggested that the measures for dealingwith this situation should include full Press publicity, laying stress on the fact that this strike was an illegal procedure and contrary tothe existing arrangements for the avoidance of disputes; and,moreover, that it had already resulted in serious losses of produc-tion. Thereafter it would be for the War Cabinet to consider whatremedial action should be taken.The War Cabinet-Took note of these statements.GovernmentDepartments.Enquiry intoStaffing ofPublic RelationsBranches.8. The Prime Minister said that he had come to the conclusionthat an effort must be made to reduce the staffs of the public relations Branches of Government Departments. He thought thatthis task should be entrusted to a Cabinet Committee under theChairmanship of the Chancellor of the Exchequer, comprising three or four other Ministers. The Terms of Reference should be asfollows : &quot;To report what reduction can be effected in the staffingof Public Relations Branches of Government Departments; andwhether the scope of the functions performed in these Branchesis appropriate.&quot;After a short discussion, the War Cabinet Approved this proposal and invited the Prime Minister to nominate the Committee to carry out this Enquiry:Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,2nd August, 1943.The War Cabinet now had before them a Memorandum by th^lHome Secretary and the Lord Chancellor (W.P. (43) 347) covering fa draft Bill dealing with this point, and also providing that theslCounsellors of State need not include any who are absent from the fUnited Kingdom.After a short discussion, the War Cabinet-Expressed their approval of the draft Bill, which should Ibe submitted to The King for an expression of His jMajesty&apos;s pleasure; and agreed that, subject to HisMajesty&apos;s approval, the Bill should be introduced in theHouse of Lords at the first convenient opportunity afterthe Recess.
ll^piPlS -sptpJE M ^he ; War Cabinet * in cbnf i-dance, the informatipn which had b een gathered about theGerman development of the long-range rpcket.   While it seemed clear that some rocket development was in hand,the balance of opinion among experts doubted whether theGermans had in fact achieved so remarkable a technicaladvance as would be implied in the firing ofja heavyrocket of a range sufficient to attack London from northern Prance.   At the same time,   it   seemed clearthat some form of rocket development was being carriedout, and appropriate precautionary measures were beingtaken.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1,6th August-,.-. 1943 .:




</content>
</cab>
