<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/33/34 images: 224-229</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO BE kept under; LOCK AND key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET 34 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime Minister&apos;room, House of Commons, S.W.1, on Tuesday, February 23, 1943, at12 15 p.m.        .       ;_,. Present: ,     *The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary   of   State  for  Foreign- Affairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,.    M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security,The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,MP.,, Chancellor of the Exchequer.The&quot; Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Thomas Johnston,M.P., Secretary of State for Scotland(Item 2).The Right Hon. Ernest Brown,) M.P.,Minister of Health (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. Lord Portal, M.P.,Minister of Works (Item 2).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The   Right   Hon.   Sir   ArchibaldSiNCLAKi Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,President of the Board of Education(Item 2).The  Right  Hon.  Lord  Leathers,Minister of War Transport.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Item 3).GeheralSir Alan Brooke, Chief of theImperial General Staff.. Secretariat:; -Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. Norman Brook.minute no.1Contents:Subject.H6rne*Defence....      ....      ....      ....Admission of Visitors, &amp;c.,.to Coastal. Areas.Post-War Buildtng Programme    ....North American Convoys   ...      ....Page181
Home J?efeiHje. &apos;%.- The War Cabinet considered a Joint Memorandum by the admission of Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security and the MinisterVisitors, &amp;c.,to of Health (W.P. (43) 74) regarding the suspension of the restrictionsCoastal Areas, on entry into the Isle of Wight and into the coastal area from King&apos;s(Previous       Lynn to Littlehampton.Reference; The Memorandum explained that, as in previous years, these&amp;M&apos;.) (41) 45tb restrictions had been suspended during the winter months on theConclusions, understanding (which had been made public) that they would be minute 5.) reimposed on the 1st March. The civil Ministers concerned were ofopinion that, in view of the recent appreciation by the Chiefs ofStaff of the invasion risk, there was a strong prima facie case against reimposing, these restrictions, on the 1st March throughoutthe &quot;area as a whole, but they suggested that the question ofreimposing these restrictions in respect of the Isle of Wight (wherespecial considerations applied) should be examined on its merits bythe Civil Defence Executive Sub-Conimifjtee.The military view was that the restrictions should bereimposed, for the following reasons; (i) The development of our offensive preparations would makeit necessary that the population of these areas should bekept as low as possible,(ii) The risk of seaborne raids was a further reason for limiting the non-resident population in these areas,(iii) The continued suspension of: the restrictions would convey. the impression that there was no longer any risk of invasion, and this might have a serious effect, not onlyon public morale, but on the morale of the Home Guard.The Secretary of State for War stressed the need for concealingour preparations for an offensive against the Continent of Europe,The enemy would, of course, know that such preparations were beingmade, but should be denied knowledge of the details of thesepreparations. From this security point of view, there would be advantages in restricting access to the coast over&apos;a wide area-stretching further to the . west than the restrictions previouslyimposed. The existing restrictions had been imposed for differentreasons, and he was prepared to consider whether for the purposewhich he :now had in view the restrictions should be differentlyframed and Imposed under different powers.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff suggested that the suspension of the previous restrictions should be extended until the1st April, and that in the interval proposals should be formulatedfor new restrictions designed to serve this different purpose.In discussion, it was pointed out that, from the security pointof view, it might be more effective to have a more strict control over, entry (on the lines of that enforced in the Jsle of Wight), but appliedover a smaller area than that covered by the previous restrictions.[ &apos;       The War Cabinet-     -:&apos;&quot;./    / . (1) Decided that the present suspension of these restrictions should be continued until the 1st April; and asked theV Home Secretary and Minister qjf Home Security to\ arrange for an early announcement of this decision.\Y2) Invited the War Office to formulate, and to discuss with the\      civil Departments concerned, new proposals for restric-\. tions designed to safeguard our preparations for\ offensive operations.(3) Agreed that the question of restricting access to the Isle of wight should be separately considered by the. CivilDe^nce/ Executive Sub-Committee, in consultation with&apos;N v the Minister of War Transport.     ^
W.M. 34 (43).

Post-War Building Programme.

2. The War Cabinet had before them a Joint Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National Service and the Minister of Works (W.P. (43)75) covering a draft White Paper on Training for the Building Industry.

This Memorandum had been considered by the Committee on Reconstruction Priorities on the 28th January, when doubts had been expressed as to the statement included in the earlier draft that the post-war building programme would employ a labour force of 1,400,000 men within three years after the end of the war. The draft had now been amended, in consultation with the Departments concerned the most important alteration being the statement in paragraph ? that, on the basis of the facts at present available, it was considered that a post-war construction programme designed for 10 to 12 years would require the labour force in the building industry to be built up over the period to about 1,250, 000 men.

It was explained that this reduction had been made as, on present information, there seemed to be a risk that a building programme employing 1,400,000 men would absorb too great a proportion of our estimated yearly savings after the war.

In discussion, it was explained that this reduction did not mean that it was proposed to scale down the housing programmes contemplated by the Secretary of State for Scotland and the Minister of Health.

The War Cabinet-

Approved the draft White Paper, and authorised the Minister of Labour and National Service and the Minister of Works to arrange for its immediate presentation to Parliament, and thereafter to proceed with the steps necessary to give effect to the policy outline therein.

North American Convoys.

3. The Minister of War Transport said that he was confronted by an urgent problem, in as much as there were more ships waiting to sail from North America to this country than could be included in each convoy. This was due, in part, to the convoy cycle having been opened out from 8 to 10 days; but also to the fact that the Americans were now beginning to make additional merchant ships available for the service of the United Kingdom Import Programme. In two recent convoys 15 and 19 ships had been left behind. Some time ago the Admiralty had said that the number of ships in each convoy should not exceed 60. On this basis, 29 ships would have been excluded from a convoy due to leave the United States that evening. The Admiralty had agreed to his urgent request that the number of ships in each convoy might be put up to 80. But the United States authorities had raised new difficulties about, allowing their ships to sail in convoys of the size.

The Ministry of War Transport added that, if the additional ships which the Americans were making available to us were to be excluded in this way from sailing in our convoys, there was grave risk that the American authorities would refuse to make extra additional ships available to us. This would be extremely serious.

The First Lord of the Admiralty and the First Sea Lord said that, on weighing the dangers and disadvantages of the various alternatives, they had come to the conclusion that the right course would be to accept an increase in the number of ships in convoy to 80. They had come to tis conclusion largely because they did not see how they could make sufficient escort vessels available at the present time to run more frequent convoys. If, however, the American authorities maintained their objection to their ships sailing in convoys in excess of 60 ships, then it might be necessary for the Admiralty to consider again whether more escort vessels would not have to be made available for the North Atlantic convoys, although this would have to be at the expense of other routes.

  
Agireoa that ihe , following action sho^d.: tak^.iiSnediately to meet the situation as-regards the convoydue to leave North America that evening;  ^(I) The Minister of War Transport undertook to&apos;get into,touch with Mr.Harriman and arrange for an urgent,: communication to be sent from the, CombinedSMppi% Adjustment Board, London, to the Qom-bineu Shipping Adjustment Board,&apos; Washington,strongly urghig that the number of vsMps in thisconvoy should Be increased to 80. The Minister ofWar Transport would also ask/Mr. BEarriman toarrange for; a personal message to be sent toMr: Hopkins;       : ,&apos;\(2) The,First Lord of the Admiralty and the First Sea-Lord would consider what action. should be takento provide additional, escorts for this convoy, andwould arrange for a message to be sent on a high level to the Naval authorities in Washington,strongly urging them to reconsider their attitude and to agree to American ships being included inthe convoy up to a total of 80 ships.(3) The First Lord of the Admiralty and the Minister ofWar Transport were authorised to make it clearthat their request in this matter had the authorityof the War Cabinet.Offices of the War Cabinet,&quot;S.W.1,February 23, 1943.



</content>
</cab>
