<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/66/0 images: 128-129</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
AmXOAtlOar OS THE MILITARY SBRTOGB. ACTS TO IBELAMD,Hamoi^dum. by- the. Chief Secretary for Ireland..2 wish to put before tho War Cabinet what in my opinion will toe the results of any endeavour to enforce conscription in Ireland^.Although I agree that the results to-day will hot he eo bad as they would have been had the. attempt been made three or four months ago* 1 am none the less satisfied thtyt they will ha very serious^The opposition to ooneoription arises from two motives. In the first place there is a certain numbs r of men who &quot;fear the Bullets&quot;.    They would,not give muoh trouble in the taking., hut they would probable refuse to ohey orders, preferring prison to the trenches.    In the second place there is a large body of Irishmen and Irish women who hate English rule and English people and bitterly resent the enforcement of &quot;oonsoription by the English&quot;,    $hey beliave that resistance to &quot;conscription by the English&quot; is a solemn duty.    They are sincere, fanatical and reckless.    The young men are hot-headed and will be dangerous., but but by far the greater danger will come from the women.    Very many of them are of the type of the militant suffragette.During the. Recess 1 have been over a great part of Ireland and have asked the opinion of everyone who X thought knew the feeling of his or her own neighbourhood.    I find almost every-where a feeling of apprehension, sometimes of deep apprehension. Although they are not armed in the way the Ulster Volunteers were armed, the opponents of conscription have sufficient explosives for a large amount of sabotage and sufficient arms to start a conflagration by shooting some of those who come to take the conscripts.    The women will be in the forefront and some of     - &apos; them are cert aim to be shot when firing and bloodshed begin as in my opinion they inevitably will begin.&apos; f.Visitors to Ireland from America and the Coloniaa have expressed to me very strongly what in their view would be the result among the American and Colonial people of the shooting of even one woman.How far the threatened policy of universal &quot;down tools&quot; will be oarried out it is difficult to say.    I think it will be attempted, although I do not think it will last very long. Partial strikes, however, which would hamper the military and police are almost certain.    The whole Irish labour movement is opposed to the poliov of oonsoription and is pledged to resist it.I cannot, of course, state my opinion as to the help which might be expected from the police against that of the Inspector General anu Chief Commissioner, but I feel bound to state that the information given to me by members of the Force in various parts of the country did not reveal so sanguine a view as that which the ins;? sot or General and Chief Commissioner have expressed to me, a-id   hav9 been forced to the conclusion that the least help may ^e ducted in those parts of the country where it will be most needed.
Ireland is at present outwardly Quiet and is certainly prosperous, but I fear that many people misled by that;guiet and prosperity, fail to appreciate the dangerous elements that are underneath consisting as they do of deep and sincere con-viotions and reckless and fanatical men and women,I am not now.expressing any opinion as to the policy to be pursued, but I wish to put on record the views I&apos; have forced from the best information I can obtain as to the results to be expected,(Signed) .  EDWARD SHORTT.Dublin Castle.7th October 1918,

</content>
</cab>
