<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/66/0 images: 165-172</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
The German Government have now communicated through the Netherlands Govern-ment their deoision not to ratify the Anglo-German Agreement for the exchange of prisoners, except on the terms of securing a settlement satisfactory to Germany of the position of Germans in China.   (Mr. Robertson^ telegram of 4th October, No. 3446 - copy annexed).At the same time reliable information has been received to the effect that there are 5,000 British prisoners in the Charleville district in a most deplor-able condition, so much so that in one camp of 350 n* less than 190 have died since June.   Immediate steps are being taken through the Netherlands Minister at Brussels to render assistance to these prisoners.   (Mr. Robertson^ telegram of 4th October, No, 3450 - copy annexed).The Oharleville incident is only the latest of a series of inoidents which show that Germany&apos;s inhuman treatment ef British prisoners still continues. Instances of such treatment are given in the Report of Mr. Justice Younger&apos;s Committee on the Treatment by the Enemy of British Prisoners of War behind the firing lines in France and Belgium (6th March, 1918, Miscellaneous No.7 (1918), Cd. 8988), iti Lord Milner&apos;s memorandum on Reprisals in the case of Prisoners of War (7th May, 1918, G.T. 4464) and in Miss Vulliamy&apos;s Note on the Conditions amongst Prisoners of War and Civilians in Germany and Holland (llth July, 1918, G.T. 5083).At the recent Hague Conference the British Delegates lodged formal and strongly worded complaints on the subject of -(A) the breaches by the Germans of existing agreements, including the retention of British prisoners within 30 kilometres from the firing line and the improper treatment of such prisoners in occupied territory;(B) the improper treatment of British prisoners in mines, factories and internment camps.The German Delegates promised inquiry and amendment, but recent information tends to show that no effective amendment has occurred.Recent instances of gross mal-treatment by the Germans of British prisoners of war are given in the annexed note.The above considerations make it necessary to take immediate steps with a view to securing the repatriation or better treatment of the British prisoners of war in Germany.    Of course, coercion cannet be exeraised to compel the ratification of the agreement so far as it relates te &quot;the exchange of prisoners, and it appears probable that ratification could only be obtained (if at all) by accepting the agreement as it stands and adding that, while the British
Government oannot interfere with the internment of Germans in China, they are willing that those Germans&apos; (whether interned or not) should.oome within the arrangements for repatriation contained in the Hague agreement.   It is for the Cabinet to say whether this offer should be made.Notice has been reoeived from the Dutch Shipping Companies that the sailings of the vessels (&quot;Sindoro&quot; and &quot;Zeeland&quot;) now used for the transport of exchanged prisoners to Boston v/lll be suspended from the end of October until &quot;the middle of February,    Efforts are being made to procure the, with-drawal of this&apos; notice; but should these efforts not be; &quot;successful, it will be necessary to provide other&apos;vessels for the purpose, as otherwise the whole process of repatriation Would for the time&quot;being come ;to an end.The question of the mal-treatment of British prisoners cannot await the conclusion of negotiations for ohe ratification.of the agreement, and appears to the Committee to require immediate and drastic action.   They therefore recommend thafthe attention of the German Government be called to the inhuman treatment of British prisoners of war in the occupied distriots (as for example, in the Charleville district), and that the message proceed somewhat as follows!-   The information which has been received&apos;shows that notwithstanding the undertakings of the German Government.and the promts of amendment made by the German delegates at the Hague the German Government continue to employ British prisoners in the 30 kilometre zone and to subject them to cruel and inhuman treatment.    The British Government therefore call upon the German Government forthwith to bring these methods to an end and to give security against their repetition, and with this view they require the German Government (l) to adopt and carry out Articles 28 to 59 of the Hague agreement which deal with the treatment of prisoners of war;   (2) to give immediate effect to the first and second paragraphs of Annexe A which relate to certain camps where,mal-treatment of prisoners has occurred; (3) to undertake&apos;that no British prisdner of war shall henceforth be employed under ground in a salt-mine; (4) to permit representatives &apos;of the Netherlands Government forthwith to visit and inspect the Occupied territory^behind the German lines, the camps in the district of the Tenth Army Corps and the salt-minefc with a view to ascertaining whether the grievances &quot;complained of have been redressed.&apos;    Unless within 14 days the German Government make a satis-factory response to these requirements and the British Government is satis-fied by the reports of the neutral representatives that the necessary action has been taken, the British Government will without further notice resume the measures of reprisal interrupted by the Hague Conference and..will take in concert with our Allies such further measures of reprisal as may appear^ neoessary for compelling the German Government to treat their prisoners in accordance with the rules of international law and the praotice of civilized nations.    In any case the Brifish Government give formal notice to the German Government that they will hold Germany-responsible for the injuries caused by the unlawful &quot;and inhuman treatment of the British prisoners in their hands and will insist that the persons responsible for these outrages shall be punished for their misdeeds.While the ab*ve notice is running we should concert with our Allies
illsuitable measures of reprisal.8. The Committee think that the Hague agreement should now be published;and that a statement as to the recent mal-treatment by the Germans of prisoners of war and as to the measures taken by the Government should be sent to the Press.9. As regards Turkey, a telegram from Sir H. Rumbold, dated the 3rdOctober (No.1759), shows that the Turkish Government are interposing further delay in the way of the carrying out of the Anglo-Turkish agreement for the exchange of invalid prisoners.    The Turkish Government have been informed that a vessel will be at Soalanova on the 16th November to land-Turkish     fi-prisoners and take off British prisoners in accordance with the. agreement; &apos; . and they should be told that unless the agreement is carried out strictly full compensation will,be required for this breach of agreement, and that in any event, any Turkish agents guilty of mal-treatmenf or neglect.of British prisoners of war will be held personally responsible for their misdeeds and&apos;,, severe punishment will be exacted.10. The Committee also recommend that the immediate and unconditionalrelease of British prisoners should be a condition of any armistice whether with Turkey or with the Central Powers;   and that instructions to that effect should be given to the Commanders in the field.   ,The British prisoners in Bulgarian hands are, it is understood, in course of being released.j .,r-&apos;v-^/.:   ii&amp; -I-.;&apos;:       ;.&apos; V&apos;-. . &amp; G. C. &apos;10th October, 1918. :.% ,
NETHERLANDS.MILITARYDecypher. Mr. Robertson (The Hague) October 4th, 1918.D*   8 p.m, October 4th, 1918,R.   8 a,ra, October 5th,.1918, Ho. 3446 (a).Your telegram Ho. 1888,Netherlands Government have now communicated to me reply of German Government who states they are willing to accept His Majesty&apos;s Governments limitation to paragraph 3 annex A but that they cannot agree to alteration in agreement preposed by His Majesty&apos;s Government regarding submarine crews.    They (? only) agreed to Article 8 which affords less favourable treatment to submarine crews than to other prisoners of war after serious (? consideration) and under express reservation that it would not lead to special treatment of submarine crews either in law or in practice.Therefore German Government cannot agree to alteration in agreement which places submarine crews in an even more unfavourable position.They state His Majesty&apos;s Government are completely mistaken if they consider proposal to exclude submarine crews from repatriation was already accepted by German Delegates during negotiations at Hague and they deny present wording is not absolutely clear.    On the contrary it is definitely laid down that internment in Holland is to be substituted for repatriation only in case of submarine crews who have beeh in captivity over 18 months on or after date on which agreement comes into force while members of submarine crews who are already interned in Holland together with those who are entitled to repatriation on account of illness or injury should not be excluded from  repatriation.    German Government are prepared to ratiiy^A^naVterations in text prt posed by them (see my telegram No. 2716).They make however in accordance with reservation (? conceded) at time of signing, ratification dependent on His Majesty&apos;s Government using their good offices to secure satisfactory settlement of position of Germans in China. After Chinese Government have declared they have given up the idea of deporting Germans and that they have no intention of interning them German Government would be contented with declaration by His Majesty&apos;s Government that they, as was agreed by British Delegates at the Hague Conference, will allow Germans in China to return home should they so desire under the same conditions as Germans in British overseas territory and that further they will not bring about deportation or internment of Germans remaining in Chinese power nor take part in any measures to this end.
. Following the. Prisoners Department. \    &apos;Netherlands Minister at&apos; Brussels telegraphs that he has received reliable Information to the effect that there are 5,000 British prisoners in Oharleville district in most deplorable conditions    Immediate assistance in nourishment and complete clothing necessary&apos;.    In one camp of 350. 190 died since June.    They beg to be saved *    Committee has been organised to render assistance and has requested clothing and nourishment from Comite National.I have instructed Red Cross depot at Rotterdam to send supplies for 5,000 men direct to Doctor Janssens.Further report follows *I presume you will desire me to enter strong protest but before doing&quot;so I should like to know if you.have &quot;further recent information regarding deplorable conditions cf our prisoners in occupied territory in,which case it might be advisable to embody Charleyille in (? a) general protest. -NETHERLANDS &apos;.   military   .Decyphcr, Mr, Robertson, (The Hague)e October 4th, 1918,5,^0 p,,m. , .-,&apos;   Q ,, October 4th, 1918.R,, 9k30 p,m.No. .3460. (r).
The treatment to whioh British prlSTrners of war fn German hands are subjeotod is illustrated by a number of instances which were brought to the notioe tf the late Hague Conference (particulars can be given when required) and by the following instanoes which were not then known J- ;(l) A Corporal in the Seaforth Highlanders states that about the end of Deoember, 1917, some two hundred British arrived at Langensalza from behind the German lines.    He and other British prisoners met them at the station.    He says that their oondition was such that ^hardly wne of them could walk and they had to orawX on hands and knees.    They had had no food for three days since they left the Verdun front and Somme front;    They were almost all frostbitten in hands and feet and were nothing but skeletons&quot;.    Some had been at work behind the German lines as ltng as 15 months - on an average 8 to 10 months, They were *f all ranks including sergeants.    They were made to work at the point of the bayonet until they dropped.    More than 100 of the men belonging to. this party died frtm starvation and illtreatment.    Many were shot in oold blood for refusing to work,(2) Another Private in the South African Infantry was at Brie (about 9 miles N.E. tf Chaulnes) from May 7th to August 8th last,    **e states that the prisoners were shockingly overcrowded in a cage.    The ftod was entirely insufficient although they had to perform very severe work on a railway.    The prisoners were reduced, to gathering herbs to put in the soup,    Most of them  . were sick and some were covered with sores.    As soon as the siok were able tt walk they were sent back to work.    The prisoners were kntcked about by the guards, generally for failing to work owing to weakness,.(3) A Corporal in the Royal Field Artillery was at Ramecourt from May 27th to June 1st last and from June 24th to August 7th last.    He states that there were some 2,000 prisoners at this place for whom there were no washing faoili-ties ar shelter.    Conditions were very bad.    Many of the prisoners fainted at work.    There were nt medical stores although tiysenterjwas rife.    The prisoners were empltyed at shifting munitions and 30 died as a result tf an explosion.(4) Two sergeants, one in the Lincolnshire Regiment and the tther in the Leicestershire Regiment were at Bazancourt from June 2nd to August 27th last. They state that there were 400 British prisoners at this place, which ,was with-in range tf the British artillery.    Their treatment was bad.    No parcels tr letters were received.    They had to work on the railways 10 htura daily, although nearly every jnan in the oamp was suffering from dysentery.    The guards   kncoked the prisoners about.    No clothing was issued.    Both these men lost at least three stone during captivity.A Sergeant in the East Yorkshire Regiment wht was at Bazanoourt during the same peritd statos that a prisoner had tt be on the point of death before he was taken into hospital.      He himself ltst twt stone during his captivity.NOTE CP THE PRISONERS OF WAR DEPARTMENT AS TO TREATMENT OF BRITISH PRISONERS OF WAR.
It appears from the evidence of a Company Sergeant Major in the Lincolnshires Regiment that the treatment of prisoners of war at Bazanoourt has beoonie worse since the German retreat.(5) Reliable information has recently been received to the effeot that there are five thousand British prisoners in the district 4f Charleville (Meziores) in a most deplorable condition.In one &quot;tamp of threo hundred and fifty, one hundred and ninety died since June,(6) Apart from the shooting and bayonetting of wounded; *f which much evidence has accummulated, German officers and men were guilty of particularly atrooious barbarity in turning liquid fire on British prisobers who were oolleoted in a trench at lionchy on waroh 28th.(7) Stendal.About 2800 British prisoners of war arrived at this camp between March and July last, all very weak from hard work, and lack of food and olothing. Many were in rags and had no boots and their clothing was filthy.    Most of them arrived in a verminous condition and many had sores and neglected wounds. An epidemic **f dysentery intervened and 77 men died between June 6th and July 20th.    It has been reported that the conditions under which the dysentery patients lived were so filthy that when a man died and was placed in a coffin the seams of the coffin were in a short time covered with lide so that it presented the appearance of a line of snow along the seams.    Also when men died their faces in a few minutes became alive with lioe.(8) Honingen Chemical Works (Parent Camp Limburg). A repatriated prisoner states that he was sent to these works *n 1st March 1918,    The plaoe was filthy and swarming with lioe.    Two thin blankets only were supplied.     The prisoners were compelled to work 10 hours a day including Sundays,    Punishment consisted of forcing men to walk up and down with sacks filled with sand and very heavy stones and making them drop down every two or three yards and then raise themselves with these heavy weights.. The prisoners were knocked about and were made to stand up against a wall for long stretches,    The chemioal used is very dangerous.    If the prisoners sweat or get wet and the ohemioal touches their hands these swell up and fester and the flesh becomes rotten.    A number of prisoners who are at Honingen Works have had half their feet burnt away but are still made to work.    They are given no medical treatment except that they are told to keep wetting their , wounds with lukewarm water and are given paper bandages about once a week,, &apos;:&apos;hen a wound does heal it is as though the flesh had all gone, the skin being simply stretched aortss the bone*(9) Langensalza.About the end of April last about 5000 British prisoners of all ranks including officers arrived at this oamp in a terrible condition, having travelled there in cattle trucks for three days with nothing but water during the whole journey/    Quite half of the men were wounded, some very badly, but they had had no dressings whatever.    On arrival they were crowded into a very dirty barrack and for 6 days were given no medical attention at all.    After
that, tho wounded wore picked out and put into hospital where about 30 died, partly frcm starvation and partly from neglect, as there were no medical stores and the medical attention was quite inadequate.    20 British N,0,0*&apos;s volunteered to act as orderlies but were not allowed to do so.The arrangements for the burial of the dead were revolting.    Old boxes carelessly nailed down wore used as coffins and bodies were often left unburied for days 30 that the stench was terrible4Many of the British,1 with open wounds, were compelled to work in the pig styes among diseased pigs *    The sanitary arrangements were perfectly appalling. Ho attempt was made to clean the latrines*    The smell was terrible and the walls wore smeared with filth,(10) Sprottau.A British prisoner who was at this damp from 5th September 1916 to the 9th April, 1918, states as follows:-&quot;At least 15 men died daily in this camp.    The mortuary, whloh I have passed frequently on my way to the parcels room, is the most horrible thing I have ever seen.    Tho lead were thrown in there anyhow, one on top of the other, absolutely nude, and I have seen them piled up four or five deep, A certain number of the corpses have post mortem examinations made of them before burial, and I oan swear)having seen on several occasions corpses after the severest form of post mortem examination,    I estimate the number of deaths which have taken place in this camp since November 1916 at more than two thousand, and this is based on the fact that a man in the East Yorks Regiment who died very early in Januasy 1918 was registered as No,1762&quot;,

</content>
</cab>
