<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/66/0 images: 206-218</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUHJWT IS. Tli^g OP HIS ERITAlTiTIC .MAJESTY *S&apos; GOTOHtUXBITT.6 jj C R g T.WAR CABIEST,G.T.5941..WEEKLY IMPORT 03? TIES HIITISTRY OP LABOUR MPIiOYllJilT II3PARTC3HT, (Sept&apos;B 30th*1918)Hote by Mr,,&apos; 0. EN Barnes.I circulate a copy of a weekly report which has been issued by the ISmployment Department of the Ministry of Labour for the. last year,   Tliei info mat ion siren on pages 7 and 8, as regards the difficulties of placing dis-charged men is somewhat disquieting, and it is to be hoped that the experience of the Department will be very different when general demobilisation takes place,   It is satisfactory to note that there is still a very large demand for labour (pagejl), and that the unemployment rate and claims for un-employment benefit remain very low Jpage 10)0   The unemploy-ment fund is nearing ^15,000,000, (page 10), and this will form a valuable reserve when unemployment once more becomes a difficult social problem,(initialled) G*H,B,2, Whitehall Gardens, 8.17.1, 11th. October, 1918.
MINISTRY OF LABOUR.Employment Department.WEEKLY REPORTNo. 53.30th September, 1918.TABLE OF CONTENTS.(1) Priority Demands :-(a) General   ......     ......(b) Mercantile Shipbuilding......(2) Enrolment Schemes, Men :-(a) War Munitions Volunteers   ... (6) War Work Volunteers ...(c) Army Reserve Munitions Workers(d) War Agricultural Volunteers ... (3) Substitution Scheme.........I.-labour supply. Page.(4) Labour from the Continent ... (5) Women&apos;s Enrolment Schomes :-(a) Q.M.A.A.C.......(6) W.R.N.S..........(c) W.R.A.F.........(6) Notes on Womens Work(7) Temporary Women Clerks   ...(8) Women&apos;s Service Exhibitions...(9) Placing of Discharged Men(11) Local Advisory Committees (12) Women&apos;s Sub-Committees(14) General Statistics (15) Unemployment Fund (16) Courts of Referees(19) National Clearing House (20) Liverpool Docks Scheme (21) Restrictions on Advertisements(24) Staff Statementii.-discharged sailors and soldiers..........    7    i (10) Action by Local Advisory Committeesiii.-advisory committees.(13) Juvenile Employment Committees ...iv.-unemployment insurance.10 10 10(17) Non-Compliance(18) Repayments to AssociationsV.-miscellaneous and general.11 11 11(22) Aliens&apos; Restriction Order (23) Trade Disputes......VI.-staff and premises. ..     ...   12    i (25) Premises...Page. 445 5 5 6 710 1112 1212PART I-LABOUR SUPPLY.(1) PRIORITY DEMANDS FOR LABOUR.O) General.The following table shows the demands, submissions, and number who started work during the week ended 20th September, 1918, in respect of all vacancies on the Priority List:-    -  &apos;Week ended 20th September, 1918.	Skilled Men.	Semi-skilled and Unskilled Men.	Women.	Total.Demand at beginning of week       ......	12,373	9,365	1,070	22,808Demand at end of week       ............	12,209	9,025	2.U02	23,236Submitted during week        ............	1,064	1,202	628	2,894Started work during week    ............	683	746	567	1,996A comparison with the returno for the previous week shows an increase of 428 in the total demand, decreases of 208 and 6 respectively in the number of skilled men submitted and placed, a decrease of 137 in the number of unskilled and semi-skilled men submitted, and an increase of 52 in the number of such men placed.(19852r-14a.)  Wt.       -G 38. 20.  10/18.  D &amp; 8.  Q. 4.
0) Mercantile Shipbuilding-.During the week ended 20th September, 19.18, 1,651 persons were submitted and 1)97 placed in mercantile shipbuilding and marine engineering compared with 1,678 submissions and 1,068 placings in the previous week. In the following table the figures for the week and. for ihe period ended 20th September arft analysed by Divisions : 	&apos;           Submissions.		Plaoings.		Current Demand at 20th September.	Week ended 20th September.	Total.	Week ended 20th September.	Total.	London and South Eastern South Midlands and Eastern  ... Yorkshire and Bast Midlands ... South Western   ......... West Midlands   ......... North Western    ........ Northern............ Scotland  ......... Wales      ............ Ireland    ...     ..........	53 1 127 \ 157 j 126 32 260 338 293 228 28	9,670 4,076 678 9,052   . 19,244 17,624 8,803 2,507	24 i 25 i 92 ) 56 16 137 193 219 210 25	4,964 3,095 208 4,909 12,747 10,859 8,124 1,706	750 704 371 358 59 &apos;      1,477 4,365 3,423 88 698Total	1,651	71,654	997	46,612	12,293(2) ENROLMENT SCHEMES-MALE LABOUR.(a) War Munitions Volunteer Scheme.The following is a summary of the work done by the Department during the week ended 20th September, 1918, the figures for the previous week being also given : 	Week ended.........	20th September.	13th September.		Enrolled     ............... Submitted to employers   ......... Transferred............... On Live Register at end of week......	386 1,755 696 2,709	365 1,903 690 2,750	Compared with the previous week there were increases of 21 in the number of enrolments and 6 in the number transferred, and decreases of 148 in the number submitted and of 41 in the Live Register.(b) &quot;War Work Volunteers.General. The total number of War Work Volunteers enrolled under the General Scheme in the week ended 19th September was 437, compared witb 523 in the previous week. Of these enrolments,&quot;381 were yearly men and 50 men for special jobs.The following Table shows the enrolments under the three schemes since 6th November, 1917, together with the number in employment at 19th September : 	Enrolments.		In employment at 19th September.		Yearly Men.	Men for Special Jobs or Areas.	Yearly Men.	Men for Special Jobs or Areas.Shipyard Labour       ............... Assigned to present employment    ......... General Scheme......     .........	5,766 4.801 8,344	1,183 1,267 5,087*	3,609 4,376 7,301	815 1.140 3,812Total	18,911	7,537	15,286	&quot; 5,767* Includes 549 for the Cumberland Iron Ore Industry.-     1 * -The Z scheme, which was extended from 1st September to 1st October, has now been extended indefinitely. On the 9th September arrangements were concluded for training suitable men at the Ministry of Munitions Training Centres with a view to placing them as War Work Volunteers on work of a semi-skilled nature witb. Munitions firms.During the period of training they are exempted from being called for Military service, and on completion of their training they are enrolled as War Work Volunteers and receive protection certificates in the ordinary manner.The first year of the scheme is drawing to a close, and the position of the men who enrolled for one year is now receiving attention.
(c) army reserve munitions workers and men registered for substitution.The following statement shows the action taken during the four weeks ended 10th September1918Enrolments and Eegistrationa&apos;... Placings as substitutes ... Plaoings as reinforcements Under submission at end of period (a) as substitutes   ......(h) as reinforcementsArmy Reserve Munitions Workers.870 92 1,335209 1,676Registered Men.242 996262 356There was little change in the number of&apos; enrolments of Army Reserve Munitions Workers compared with the previous month, but there was an increase of 142 in the number of men placed. The total number of placings since the commencement of the scheme in October, 191.(5 (including second and subsequent placing), is 53,923. Of the 2,171 cases on the Live Register at 10th September 286 were not under submission.-As regards Registered Substitutes there was some decline on the previous month both in registra-tions and placings. The number of placings of registered men (including second and subsequent placings) up to September 10th was 11,511.id) war agricultural volunteers.The returns for the fortnight ended 12th September, 1918, show a considerable decrease as compared with the previous fortnight both in the number of fresh applications for enrolment and in the number of placings. Fresh applications were 153 as compared to 364, and placings 212 as compared to 463. This falling off is general throughout the Divisions. A possible explanation is the very unseasonable weather, which is undoubtedly hindering agricultural operations and renders an outdoor occupation unlikely to attract fresh applicants if they can find other employment. Details for the fortnight and for the whole period since the inauguration of the scheme are given in the following Table : No. on Register at beginning of period     ......No. registered during period............No. placed on Live Register on becoming unemployedTotalApplications withdrawn, cancelled, etc. Volunteers enrolled and placed No. still to be dealt with : (a) Under Submission......(V) Not under SubmissionFortnight ended 12th September.1,331 153 251,509,281 212Total to 12th September.5,589 625,6511,817 2.321646 367(3) SUBSTITUTION.(a) army index at the claims and record office.The following Table sets out the number of men submitted from the Army Index at the Clainis and Record Office during the week ended 25th September, 1918, and also the whole period, which is in the case of Coal Mining since May 4th, 1918, Internal Substitution within the Army since March 7th, and External Substitution since April 19th :  	Coal Mining.	Internal Substitution and other Special War Office Demand?.	External Substitution.	Total.Weekended 25.9.18   ......... Period ended 25,9.18......     ......	2,515 39,228	4,201 28,391	300 13,628	7,016 81,247The men submitted for Internal Substitution and other special War Office demands were chartered accountants, experienced mechanics (capable of working plant for the supply of oxygen in liquid form), camera men, developers, drummers, perforators, hypo-hands, and stainers (Cinema work), and locomotive engine drivers, firemen, cleaners, guards, and brakesmen (railway work).As regards External Substitution, the number of men offered for the week is in respect of 147 cases, of which 69 were cases of re-submission ; the total number of cases dealt with to 25th September, 1918, is 7,53&apos;j, of which 1,784 were cases of re-submission.19852 &apos;&quot;   : A 2
The following cases occurring in the course special interest: Required.Bath attendant, able to swim, used to steam boiler,and laundry engine. Manager of explosive storage. Manager of silk factory.Butcher&apos;s machine man and cook (hams, meats). Stonemason, able to take full charge, give esti-mates, book-keeping, &amp;c.    Able to work inmarble and cut letters. Manager and foreman of boot factory, superviseproduction of boot uppers.   Must be mechanic,attend gas engine, pay wages, keep books. Varnish works foreman and chemist.of submissions for External Substitution are of Offered.Bath attendant and swimming instructor.   As-sistant engineer. Assistant manager of explosives works. Silk mill manager. Cook and purveyor.Monumental sculptor on own account 5 years, subsequently 5 years as a manager.Boot and shoe salesman.maker&apos;s manager, mechanic and(1) Works chemist (lacquer and varnish manu-facturer).(2) Foreman (oil, paint and varnish manufac-turer).Substitutes were also offered for the following :-Gas Fittings Inspector, lb&apos; Asylum Attendants, Quantity Surveyor, Assistant Clerk to Board of Guardians.It was not possible to offer substitutes for the following vacancies :  Chief Works Engineer.   Must have had Steam and Electrical engineering training, and hadposition as chief with five years&apos; experience.   Used to Lancashire Boilers, high-speedengines, etc. iForeman  and Mechanic in patent frame, seaming and linking departments.   Able tosupervise manufacture of underwear.   Must have held similar position before.  -Fitter and Joiner.   Repairs to Coal Washing Plant and Railway Wagons. Experienced Coal and Timber Carter and Horsekeeper.   Knowledge of Crossley gas engine forChaff Cutter, etc.   Must be experienced in ailments of horses. Scribbling Engineer.  Work from three tape condensers. Accustomed to high-speed machinery,and thoroughly experienced. Tool Setter and Night Shift Superintendent. Tool Turner.Machine Shop Foreman and Tool Setter.    Must be highly skilled and able to control female labour.Electrical Engineer.   Manage staff and be responsible for continuity of supply.   Qualified to take charge of gas plant, electrical generators, switchboards, engines, etc.(4) LABOUR FROM THE CONTINENT.Danes.On Satuaday, the 21st September, a party of 70 Danish workmen who had been recruited by the Departments Agent in Denmark arrived at Aberdeen. The party included 54 timber fellers, 14 agriculturists and 2 blacksmiths.The men were met on their arrival at Aberdeen by an interpreter from the Timber Supply Department and officers of the Aberdeen Exchange, and they were maintained at Aberdeen until Monday, the 23rd instant. Twelve agriculturists and the 2 blacksmiths were then despatched to . London and allocated from there an arrival. The 54 timber fellers and 2 agriculturists were sent direct from Aberdeen to their respective employers.All arrangements for feeding the men before and en route were carried out by this Department.Portuguese.During the week arrangements were made to repatriate, at the request of the Timber Supply Department, 18 Portuguese woodcutters.(5) ENROLMENT SCHEMES-WOMEN.(a] Queen Mary&apos;s Army Auxiliary Corps.During the week ended 20th September there was a decrease of 2 in the number of applications for and an increase of 9U in the number of enrolments in the Queen Mary&apos;s Army Auxiliary Corps compared with the previous week. Details of applications, enrolments, etc., are given in the following Table: 	Week ended 20th September.	Total.Applications received at Exchanges.........     ......... Incomplete cases rejected by D.O.&apos;s............     ......	1.012 35	108,932 3,565Completed Applications. Awaiting interview at beginning of week............... Received during period..........     ............	1,210 1,024	88,882Total	2,234	88,882Withdrawals before interview        .................. Rejected without interview..................... Rejected at interview........................ ENROLLED (a) Home Service      .................. (J) Home or Foreign.................. Awaiting interview on 20th September    ...     ............	386 142 224 380 83 1,019	26,108 -7,250 18,187 27,279 9,039 1,019
The enrolments during the wook were distributed as follows :-Divisions.	Home.	Home or Foreign,	Divisions.	Home.	Home or Foreign.London and South Eastern	91	17	Northern      ........	25	5South Western     .........	30	3	Scotland      ..........	20	11West Midlands    .........	38	4    &apos;	Wales............	27	1Yorks and East Midlands......	41	6	Ireland............	20	7North Western    .........	85	29			(6) Women&apos;s Royal Naval Service.The figures relating to recruitment for the Women&apos;s Royal Naval Service during the week ended 20th September and since the commencement of recruiting are as follows :-	Week ended 20th September.	Total.Applications received at Exchauges.................. Incomplete cases rejected by D.0.&apos;b..................	266 10	11,131 154Completed Applications. Awaiting interview at beginning of week............... Received during period       ...    ....	581 180	7,123Total	761	7,123Withdrawals before interview       .................. Rejected without interview ...      ...      ............... Rejected at interview..................     ...... ENROLLED    ........................... Awaiting interview on 20th September    ...............	65 22 65 108 501	2,251 512 1,872 1,987 501(c) Women&apos;s Royal Air Force.		The position as regards recruitment for the week and for the whole period since the scheme was started is given in the following Table :-		&apos;   &apos;&apos; &apos; - 	Week ended 20th September.	Total.Applications received at Exchanges.........    ........ Incomplete cases rejected by Divisional Officers............t	557 5	10,354 63Completed Applications. Awaiting interview at beginning of week ... Received during period.....................	1,446 311	6,261Total	1,757	6,261Withdrawals before interview    -.................. Rejected without interview..................... Rejected at interview..................... ENROLLED    ........................... Awaiting interview at 20th September     ...............	100 42 92 129 1,394	1,641 366 1,239 1,621 1,394The enrolments during the week were distributed as follows :-Divisions.	Enrolments.	Divisions.		Enrolments.London and South Eastern.........	54	Northern		12South Western...............	 	Scotland	...     ...     ...     ...     ...	13West Midlands........	19	Wales	...     ...     ...     ...     ...	;   7 v;Yorks and East Midlands    .........	24&apos;	Ireland	...     ...     ...     ...     ...	 North Western...............				- - it :(6) NOTES ON WOMEFS WORK.(a) Substitution of Women for Men.Several fresh instances of the substitution of women for men in industry are reported from the Yorkshire Division, including the placing of women on axle turning, on micrometer work, as stone dresBers and as labourers on a benzol plant.Most Exchanges in this Division also report an increase in the substitution of women in engineering works, in brickyards, and on the railways, and also as shop assistants and plumbers.The placing of women as substitutes for men in the South Western Division include placings of 13 turners, 2 welders, aiid 2 filers (all through the Bournemouth Exchange), and of 6 labourers for the gas house and a tally clerk for the Army Ordnance (through the Southampton Exchange). In the London and South Eastern Division the placings include an electric crane driver and two women turners in artificial limb-making factory.19852A3
	Week ended	Previous	21st Sept., 1918.	week.Candidates summoned for interview      .........	375	359,,       recommended for employment       ......	258	258,,       considered unsuitable............	115	97,,       who withdrew application    .........	2	4Outstanding vacancies at end of week   .........	280	140The total number of women clerks supplied to Government Offices in this way since 31st March, 1915, is now 22,060. &apos;(0) Labour Supply.There has been a particularly brisk demand for female labour at Gainsborough, both from the local engineering firms and the Aircraft Factory. The local supply of labour has been sufficient to meet the demands of the engineering firms ; for the Aircraft Factory it has been necessary to import six trained workers from the Loughborough Instructional Factory.The National Filling Factory has also notified a demand and 80 women have been brought into the town from within a 25-mile radius in respect of this. An order has also been received from a local firm for 50 women to work in a malt kiln, and it is hopt d it may be possible to fill this order from women who are too old or are physically unfit for munitions work.(c) Reduction of Staff at the Minstry of Food and Transfers effected by the Civil Service Commissioners.By special arrangement with the Ministry of Food a recruiting campaign was organised by this Department in December, 1917, and January, 1918; and a lar?e number of girls were obtained for the Food Controllers Department, Imperial Institute Branch, under a twelve months&apos; agreement.In July of this year the Department was notified that owing to a re-arrangement of work the Food Controllers Department would be obliged to reduce considerably their staff of girls.Negotiations were immediately set on foot by the Department for the re-allocation of these girls by the Civil Service Commissioners to other Government Departments. Arrangements were made with the Food Controller^ Department for the possibilities of re-allocation to be put before the girls and if necessary before their parents.It was further agreed that the girls should remain in the employ of the Ministry of Food until arrangements for their re-allocation were completed.The Ministry of Food also consented to hand over to the Civil Service Commissioners the appli-cants&apos; original application forms and references and the handing over of these forms was understood to imply a satisfactory reference from the Ministry of Food.The Civil Service Commissioners, on the other hand, made special arrangements for the interview-ing of the girls at certain specified hours.The numbers dealt with and the results are as follows : 89 girls were submitted by the Ministry of Food to the Civil Service Commissioners ; 77 passed the examination and were re-allocated by the Commissioners ; 9 failed to pass the examination and three failed to appear. The papers of these 12 girls were referred back to the Ministry of Food.The Civil Service Commissioners state that the 77 girls who were re-allocated appear to be ren-dering satisfactory service and they consider that the negotiations were both useful and successful.id) Max Pulling in Yorkshire.An interesting sequel has occurred in connection with the arrangements for Flax Pulling in Yorkshire which was described in a previous issue of the Weekly Report.It appean d that eerious discontent arose amongst the workpeople employed in this work in connection with the payment for the work done. It was ascertained that in some cases the minimum wage of 30s. a week had not been paid, and that in other cases the foreman had refused to measure up the ground each night and the women, being unable to measure it themselves, had no check whatever against the statement of the foreman.The facts were reported to the Women&apos;s Sub-Committee of the Hull and District Local Advisory Committee at their meeting held on September 5th, when it was decided to send a representative to interview the employer at once, and that pending a statement by him the amount due to the work-people should be advanced by the members of the Committee, on the distinct understanding that the Department would take the requisite legal steps against the offending employers.An immediate communication was therefore sent to the employer, with the result that he attended at the Exchange on the following Tuesday for the purpose of paying the money due to the workpeople concerned. . -Several applicants to whom money was due were unable to meet him at that time, but the necessary money was deposited by him, and payment will be made as soon as the workpeople can arrange to call at the Exchange.Whilst the regularity of this action of the Sub-Committee may perhaps be questioned, its effectiveness cannot be, and the episode affords a wholesome proof of the value of a sound public opinion.(7) TEMPORARY WOMEN CLERKS FOR GOVERNMENT OFFICES.During the week ended 21st September, 1918, the results of interviews by the Civil Service Commission of candidates for temporary women clerkships in Government Offices-were as follows, the figures for the previous week being given for comparison : 
PART II-DISCHARGED SAILORS AND SOLDIERS.(9) PLACING OP DISCHARGED MEN. In his report for the period ended 6th September the Divisional Officer for the Yorkshire and East Midlands Division notes that a considerable dearth of suitable vacancies for discharged men is hampering the work at various Exchanges. At Attercliffe, for instance, light jobs are few, and most ex-Service mon prefer work on munitions because of the high wages, and for this reason veryfew will consider training courses. The question of the provision of light employment is also a difficulty at Leeds, Morley, Scarborough, aud Wakefield. . The Wakefield Manager has, however, placed 55 men ; and the Morley Manager reports that since the new procedure came into force there has been a great improvement in the responses to the Exchange letters of invitation. At Todmorden the Manager finds great difficulty in placing men who are suffering from internal ailments. The Derby Manager corroborates the statement emanating from Morley as to the improvement in response to Exchange letters, but he finds that the discharged men whom he endeavours to place usuallv demand wages in excess of the normal rates. The Leicester Manager, who has also been fortunate in the replies to his letters, has succeeded in effecting 40 placings; and other good results in placings are as follows :-Ilkeston, 17 ; Mansfield, 19 ; Lincoln, 38 (three better than their pre-War occupations); and Hull, 50. Amongst the men placed by the last-mtmed Exchange was an ex-soldier suffering from neurasthenia. This man had applied for outside work, and had accordingly been sent for labouring work at a local aerodrome. His ability was very quickly recognised, and he has now been appointed Traffic Manager.  This man is one of the few who have expressed any(8) WOMEN&apos;S SERVICE EXHIBITIONS, &amp;0.(d) Liverpool.A Women&apos;s State Services Exhibition was held at Liverpool from September 18th to 25th on premises kindly lent by Messrs. Lee &amp; Co., Limited.The Exhibition was opened by Mr. Bridgeman, Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Labour, and representatives of the various&apos;Corps spoke at meetings during the week.September 20th was set aside as a special recruiting day for the Women&apos;s Royal Air Force, and a large meeting was held at rit. George&apos;s Hall, Liverpool.A full report as to the results has not yet been received, but it is anticipated that a large number of recruits will have been obtained from the publicity given to the needs of the Corps.Scotland.The Scottish Women&apos;s Recruiting Week is now in full swing. Its inauguration was announced from all the pulpits on 22nd September, and the Clergy are giving great assistance.The Campaign opened on Monday with demonstrations, parades, meetings, etc., in the principal towns in the Division, and over 100 of these are being held during the course of the week.In Glasgow, decorated Tram Cars went from place to place in the city, accompanied by bands, detachments of Q.M.A.A.C.&apos;s, W.R.N.S., and W.R.A.F,&apos;s. The cars were stopped at convenient points, platforms quickly erected and open-air meetings held, at which representatives of all the Services spoke. These representatives were attended by members of the Divisional Office Staff, the Secretary of the Women&apos;s War Employment Committee, Sir Andrew Pettigrew, Chairman of the Women&apos;s War Employment Committee, and the Manager of the Glasgow Tramway Company. All the meetings were most successful and large numbers of names have been handed to the Orderlies and clerks assisting. The recruiting enthusiasm of the Orderlies is proving one of the most effective approaches to new recruits. Ten special Recruiting Offices have been opened for the week, and in addition the Exchanges are opened until 9 p.m. At the special Recruiting Office for War Services at 224 Sauchiehall Street, 600 enquiries were made on Monday alone.In Edinburgh the Campaign also consists of a large number of outdoor meetings. A Recruiting Hut has also been opened at the Mound, a central part of the city, and excellent results are being obtained.In Dundee a Parade of Q.M.A.A.C.&apos;s, W.R.N.S., W.R.A.F.&apos;s, Land Army Workers, Boy Scouts, Ac, took place on Monday, 23rd. This Parade was accompanied by two bands, and after going through the principal streets of the city, where it attracted a great deal of attention, and much literature was distributed, it drew up in Albert Square, where an open-air meeting was held. Officers of all Services were represented, and there was some excellent speaking. Many&apos; enquiries were made at the close of the meeting, and until 9 p.m. applicants were calling at the Employment Exchange.In Aberdeen some 200 applications were taken on the first day of the week. The meetings are being held throughout the area all week, and the officers at that Exchange are aiming at the issue of 1,000 Application Forms before the close of the week.In Paisley the proceedings opened with a Women&apos;s War Services Exhibition in the Y.W.C.A. Hut. This was opened by Lady MacCallum, wife of a local M.P., and was well attended. It was followed on Tuesday, the 24th inst., by a large public meeting, at which it is estimated from 1,500 to 2,000 persons were present. The meeting was a most enthusiastic one. Speakers were present from each Corps, the most up-to-date War Service Films were shown and several patriotic songs were sung.Programmes somewhat similar to the above are being carried out all over the Division, and smaller burghs as Hawick, Irvine, Beith, &amp;c, are having most successful meetings.One or two shop windows have been tastefully decorated and show Q.M.A.A.C. uniforms, the typewriter and desk, and cooking utensils, together with posters appHaling for workers, for the various categories in the Services. These windows have; attracted a great deal of attention. Similar arrangements have been made in all towns of any size and a particularly effective display has been made in Messrs. Jenner&apos;s, Edinburgh.It is quite evident that the campaign is creating a very strong impression upon the minds of the people and that it is being given wide publicity in both the populous and the more scattered areas.During the first two days of the week practically 950 applications had been received at the Divisional Office through Coupon advertisements, and it has been necessary to put special staff on to handle these applications in order to avoid delay in dealing with them. In addition 5,i 00 and 6,000 forms had been given out in the Division.
gratitude. He has called in person to thank the Exchange for their efforts on his behalf. The Boston Manager has succeeded in getting a discharged man selected out of 2,000 applicants for employment as a store-keeper. Some interesting placings are reported from Castleford, where one man (ordinarily unplaceable because of neurasthenia) has been set up as a greengrocer by the Sir John Leigh Fund, and where another man suffering from congenital imbecility has been placed as a colliery labourer. This Manager is, however, finding much difficulty with discharged men who were originally colliers, and have been discharged because of nystagmus contracted in the mines. It is naturally impossible for such men to resume their pre-War work.Commenting on the same period the Divisional Officer for Ireland states that Belfast has placed 37 discharged men, Limerick 24, and Tralee 23.&apos; Considerable difficulty is, however, being found in this Division. In some districts local vacancies are hard to find and the results of submissions for cross-channel vacancies are disappointing. The Tralee Manager finds discharged soldiers generally unsatisfactory as employees, and the Divisional Officer roports that these men are generally apathetic in their attitude to the Exchange.The Rotherham Joint Sub-Committee has dealt with 48 cases in the month of August Of these cases 13 have returned to their previous employment, eight reported unfit, four were referred to the Local War Pensions Committee, two found work for themselves, and 21 were placed.It was reported to the Boston Local Advisory Committee of 5th September that a discharged man had been placed as Dilution Officer under the Ministry of Munitions at a salary of  350 per annum.(10) ACTION BY LOCAL ADVISORY COMMITTEES AND JOINT SUB-COMMITTEES.The CheEterfield Local Advisory Committee recently investigated a complaint from the &quot; Comrades of the Great War &quot; as to the treatment experienced by one of their members at a local Exchange. The complainant was summoned to attend before the Committee and was given an opportunity to substantiate his statement. As a result of their investigation of the circumstances the Committee passed the following resolution : That this meeting regret the hasty and ill-considered action of the &quot;Comrades of the Great War&quot; in reporting our Secretary to the Minister of Labour charging him with misdemeanour to one of their members ; that we find the charges and statements made quite uncorroborated and entirely false ; that as they have representation on our Disablements Committee we suggest that they should first enquire into any complaint through their own representative; and that we express our unwavering confidence in our Secretary.As a result of certain complaints made by the National Association of Discharged Sailors and Soldiers against a local engineering firm the Discharged Sailors and Soldiers Sub-Committee of the Colchester Local Advisory Committee decided to ask the members of the above Association who had made the complaint to attend before them in order that all the facts might be investigated. To ensure a full and fair investigation, it was decided also to ask for the attendance of the employers concerned. The Committee also resolved to augment the General Purposes Sub-Committee and to call it together at an early date to formulate a scheme of co-operation with the War Pensions Committee in connection with the interviewing of ex-Service men who had registered unsuccessfully at the Exchange.Having accepted representatives of the National Federation, the National Association, and the &quot;Comrades of the Great War,&quot; the Leeds Joint Sub-Committee have requested these three bodies and the Local War Pensions Committee to enquire into the disinclination shown by many discharged men to apply to the Exchange, to endeavour to find out how many have failed to attend the Exchange during the month of August, and if possible to ascertain the reason for their non-attendance.The Cowes Local Advisory Committee have circularised all employers in the Isle of Wight asking them to nofify all vacancies suitable for discharged men to the Exchange.. They have also instructed their Secretary to arrange that the circular letter referred to should be sent to all municipal bodies in the island. This Committee have expressed approval of a suggestion that slides should be exhibited in local cinemas advising discharged men to register at the Exchange and inviting employers to notify to the Exchange all vacancies suitable for such men.PART III.-ADVISORY COMMITTEES.(11) LOCAL ADVISORY COMMITTEES.No further new committees have met since the last weekly Report, the number remaining at 256. Most of the committees (some 195) have held between 5 and 9 meetings. Fourteen meetings remain the record for one committee.The following items of interest may be mentioned : Chelmsford. Afforestation Scheme. For some considerable time this Committee have been interesting themselves in the question of afforestation in regard to the employment of discharged men ; at the la^t meeting an interesting discussion arose on the subject. A letter was read from the Ministry of Agriculture stating that they had the matter under discussion and were making arrange-ments with the Ministry of Pensions for training disibled men at the Forest of Dean, as there is likely to be great forestal activity after the War. The Committee agreed that in regard to their own district, there was no reason why at the present time planting should not be carried out to replace the timber now being cut down. Continuing the discussion in regard to the employment&apos;of discharged men, the Committee considered whether there was any suitable land in the district for reclauiaiion.Folkestone. Apprenticeships. A long and animated discussion occurred at the last meeting of the Folkestone Local Advisory Committee regarding the general employment of workpeople by tho South Eastern and Chatham Railway at their works at Ashford. The question of apprentices came up and some interesting figures were given as to their terms of agreement. A number of apprentice-ships were arranged at premiums of  60 per annum and these came first on the list. Men who were employed at the works had the right of entry for, their sons, provided sufficient vacancies were available, but the waiting list was always very heavy. One member thought it would be a good thing if special technical classes&apos;were established at Technical Institutes in connection with apprentices; he
suggested that boys should attend these classes as part of their apprenticeship and in their employer^ time. Further, in fact when a lad entered on his apprenticeship, he should cease to be an expense to his parents, but instead be supported by the State.The Committee finally recommended that tho South Eastern an 1 Chatham Railway should offer two or three free apprenticeships for lads in the district.Leeds. War Munitions Volunteers Working on short time. This Committee has passed a resolution asking that the attention of the Minister of Munitions should be drawn to the fact that certain War Munitions Volunteeers in the district have been working, on an average, 30 hours per week only, owing to shortage of material, in spite of the fact that the services of men in the Engineering Trades are urgently required elsewhere.Sanctioned Vacancies for War Work Volunteers. This Committee has previously raised the question of being allowed to submit War Work Volunteers to vacancies other than sanctioned vacancies, but were informed that the Ministry of National Service were unable to agree to the Committee&apos;s proposal. The Committee, however, still recommend that the list of sanctioned vacancies should be extended aud suggest that, the placing of War Work Volunteers on work of National importance should be left to the &quot;discretion of the Local Advisory Committee.By the time this report is printed the first of the conferences of chairman and vice-chairman of Local Advisory Committees will have been held, viz.: that in the Yorkshire and East Midlands Division, the date of which has been fixed for the 30th September.(12) W0MEN&apos;S SUB-COMMITTEES OF LOCAL ADVISORY COMMITTEES.Certain of the Local Advisory Committees have now accorded special terms of reference to their Women&apos;s Sub-Committees.The terms of reference of the Women&apos;s Sub-Committee of the London Central Advisory Committee are as follows : (1) To deal with all questions relating to Women&apos;s work affecting Employment Exchanges inthe London County area. (2) To receive and consider reports on Women&apos;s work from London County Exchanges. (3) To advise the Minister of Labour, through the Central Committee, on questions affecting theGreat Marlborough Street Women&apos;s Exchange. (4) To report direct to the Minister of Labour on matters affecting Women&apos;s work not involvingquestions of principle.(5) The Women&apos;s Sub-Committee to present reports of their proceedings to the Central Committee quarterly.The Edinburgh Women&apos;s Sub-Committee is empowered to take action on questions set out in L.A.C. 15, but any recommendations adopted at the Sub-Committee outside these functions are to be referred to the Main Committee before action is taken. Somewhat similar terms of reference have been accorded to the Women&apos;s Sub-Committee of the St. Albans Local Advisory Committee.(13) JUVENILE EMPLOYMENT COMMITTEES.Propaganda-The experiment referred to in Weekly Report No. 50, arranged by the Finsbury Juvenile Advisory Committee in connection with the fete organised by the local Juvenile Organisa-tions Committee, proved an undoubted success. The Juvenile Advisory Committee arranged a small model Exchange equipped with the ordinary paraphernalia for registration, Officers of the Department being present to explain the work of the Committee and to answer any enquiries. A large number of parents and children came for information, and the Juvenile Organisation Committee have expressed to the Juvenile Advisory Committee their appreciation of the effort made in helping to carry out the purpose for which the fete was designed.Meetings for Foremen. Several Committees have done useful work lately in holding meetings for Foremen in order to interest them in the work of the Committees. A very successful meeting was held at Birmingham for Sparkbrook foremen, at which the Chair was taken by Sir Halliwell Rogers, Chairman of theB.S.A.. A large number of Foremen attended the meeting. Among other Committees which have held successful meetings are Dundee and Motherwell.Rota Committees.-The Dundee Juvenile Advisory Committee, who have been referred to lately in the Weekly Report, are pursuing their work with great enthusiasm. A striking feature has been the marled success of their Rota meetiugs. In 28 meetings, 942 children were invited, and 760 attended, of whom 472 were accompanied by parents. The Committee have been successful in per-suading children to remain at school, and have even induced some children, who have left school before they were 14, to return and finish their course.Employment out of school hours. A report brought out by the Dundee Committee in connection with the inquiry on behalf of the Ministry of Reconstruction showed to what extent children in full-time attendance at school were working out of school hours. The number thus employed did not appear excessive, considering the needs of the times and the size of the town. On the other hand, the hours worked were abnormally long in many cases and the wages surprisingly low. A number of very young children were shown to be working early and late. A result of the enquiry has been that the School Board is taking steps to enforce the byedaws and in investigating the worst cases expressed with a view to prosecution.Neiv Committees-Draft Choice of Employment Schemes for Burnley, Dudley and Newbury have recently been received in the Department. The Scheme for West Sussex has now, with the agreement of this Department, been formally approved by the Board of Education.The new Juvenile Advisory Committee at Accrington is now ready to begin work, and will hold its first meeting shortly.Glasgow. The reorganisation of Juvenile work in Glasgow and the surrounding district is now complete. The nine District Committees appointed by the Central Juvenile Advisory Committee have each held their first meeting, which was in every case most successful. Each Committee is anxious to proceed as quickly as possible with the organisation of the work in their own area, and everything promises well for the success of the extended scheme.
The Chairman of the Central Juvenile Advisory Committee attended seven out of the nine meetings ; the remaining two were attended by the Vice-Chairman. Several meetings were also attended by His Majesty&apos;s Inspector of Schools, who, in some instances, addressed the meetings.PART IV-UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE.(14) GENERAL STATISTICS.(a) Unemployment.The following statement shows by Trades the percentage number.of workpeople unemployed in tho Insured Trades on 20th September and 13th September (a week ago) and 23rd August, 1918 (a month ago), respectively : 	Males.				Females.			Trades Insured under Insurance Act of 1911.	Books Current,	Percentage Unemployed at			Books Current.	Percentage Unemployed at				20th Sept.	A week ago.	A month iiga.		20th Sept.	A week ugo.	A month ago.A. Building............ B. Construction of Works...... C. Shipbuilding    ......... D. -Engineering and Ironfounding E. Construction of Vehicles F. Sawmilling X. Other Industries       ......	469,333 106,765 254,769 974,524 150,680 8,979 36,811	0&apos;52 0-44 0-18 0-27 0-18 0-31 0-03	0-53 0-48 &apos;0-17 0-28 0-18 0-36 0-05	0-53 0-51 0-18 0&apos;29 0-21 0-33 0-06	5,405 2,226 9.293 466,230 19,047 700 131)	1-83 2-96 1-87 1-70 0-85 1-00	1-70 2-74 1-93 1-48 0-96 0-43	1-44 2-92 2-01 1-19 0-97 0-29Total	2,001,811	0-32	0-32	0-34	503,040	1-67	1-47	1-48Trades Insured under Act of 1910.								G. Ammunition    ......... H. Chemicals       ......... K. Metals   ............ N. Leather............ P. Brick. Tile, etc.......... R, Sawmilling and Machine Wood-work, T. Rubber   ............ M. Other Insured Workpeople   ...	58,118 71,221 332,719 26,311 21,660 49,849 18,897 48,426	0-69 0-41 0-12 0-28 0-20 . 0-57 0-50 0-73	0-87 0-41 0-13 0-26 0-18 0-62 0-41 0-64	0-88 0-49 0-15 0-24 0-20 0-54 0-52 0-71	245,642 39,751 172,682 29,001 10.264 36.120 39,113 217,247	1-21 1-09 0-94 0-96 0-69 2-79 0-95 1-28	1-18 1*64 0-91 0-84 0-63 3-05 0-96 1-22	1-23 1-60 0-92 0-31 0-59 3-43 0-95 1-19Total	627,201	0-81	0-32	0-34	789,826	1-24	1-20	1-23All Trades     ...     ......	2,629,012	0-32	0-32	0-34	1,292,866	1-40	1-31	1-33(b) Claims to Benefit.1911 Act.1916 Act.Males.Females.Males.Females.Total.Week ended :-6th September. 1918 13th September^ 1918 20th September, 1918730 092 686629 67&apos; 1,287156 156 155661759 7792,176 2,284 2,907(c) Books Exchanged, etc.Books exchanged during week ended 21st September, 1918 ............ 32,732Total to date, 14th July to 21st September, 1918     ... 3,335,174(1911 Act 11 ^25 )New Books issued during week ended 21st September, 1918 j              y&apos;^g f 19,764 1Books reported lost during week ended 21st September, 19 J 8       ......... 1,485(15) ST ATM OF THE UNEMPLOYMENT FUND.The balance of the Unemployment Fund at the beginning of the week ended the 21st September, 1918, was  14,728,279.The receipts brought to account during the week were  54,792, and the payments were&quot; 11,382. The result is a net addition of  43,4.10 to the Fund, which stood at  14,771,689 at the end of the week.During the week  53,000 was transferred to the National Debt Commissioners for investment, making the total amount transferred  14,760,000.(16) COURTS-OF REFEREES,The Courts of Referees held 11 sittings during the week ended 21st September and gave 28 decisions, of which 10 were in favour of, and 18 against, payment of benefit.; &apos; (17) NON-COMPLIANCE. *The Solicitor has reported the conviction of three employers for non-payment of contributions due under the National Insurance (Unemployment) Acts, 1911 to 1918.Two of the prosecutions arising out of the survey of London, which is now in progress, took place at Bow Street and Old Street Police Courts respectively. At Bow Street the defendant, a metal button manufacturer, was fined  3 in respect of each of four workpeople and ordered by the Court to pay  7 7s. Od. costs and arrears of contributions, amounting&apos;to  2 8s. id., while at Old Street a leather
The amounts of repayments to Associations during the week ended 21st September, 1918, were under Section 105  340 10s. 7rf., and under Section 106 as follows : 	No. of claims received.	Total payments by Associations.	No. of claims examined.	Amount repaid.		&amp;   X.    (I.		&amp; s.  d.Associations    having   arrangements   under	2	5 11  h	Nil	2 17   1Section 105.				Other Associations       ......   i......	1!!	113  3   6	Nil	NilPART V-MISCELLANEOUS AND GENERAL.(19) NATIONAL CLEARING HOUSE.&apos; During the week ended 19th September 790 demands were received for circulation, covering 5,474 vacancies. During the same week 1,088 cancellation notices were received in respect of 7,068 vacancies: of these 7,068 vacancies 3,998 (or 56 per cent.) have been filled by Exchanges, 1;)0 are known to have been filled otherwise than through Exchanges and 2,920 were reported as cancelled.The corresponding figures for the period from 11th January, 1918, to 19th September, 1918, were 41,006 demands received, covering 238,674 workpeople of all classes, and 35,229 demands withdrawn, covering 261,188 vacancies : of these 261,188 vacancies, 129,101 (or 49- 42 per cent.) have been filled by Exchanges, 5,227 were stated to have been filled otherwise than through Exchanges and 126,860 were cancelled.The demands in circulation on 19th September in the weekly edition of the circulated newspaper were as follows : (1) labour priority gazette (No. 36) (a) Priority................      ........... 3,492(6) Ordinary        ......             ..........     ...... 3,163(c) Women (1) Priority...............     ........... 16(2) Ordinary...     ...............     ...... 925(d) Juveniles       ........................ 25(e) Discharged Soldiers only     .................. 8--7,629(2) national clearing house newspaper (No. 31) (a) Ordinary.....................      ... 11,411ib) Discharged Soldiers only     .................. 80-    11,49119,120(20) LIVERPOOL DOCKS SCHEME.The following figures set out the work done under the Liverpool Docks Scheme during the week ended 23rd September, 1918, figures also being given, for the sake of comparison, for the weeks ended 16th September, 1918 (a week ago), and 24th September, 1917 (a year ago).Week ended.	Number of Dockers paid.	Amount of wages paid.	Average wage per head.		&amp;    s. d.	  s. d.23rd September, 1918      ..............	13,918	38,074   5  4	2 14  916th September, 1918      ............	13,573	35,276   6  5	2 12  024th September, 1917       ......    -.........	14,641	39,955  2 10	2 14  7(21) RESTRICTIONS ON ADVERTISEMENTS FOR LABOUR.The number of advertisements dealt with by the Department under the Defence of the Realm *       Regulation 8B during the past week was :-Forwarded for approval prior to publication       ............     ...    48Inserted by newspapers and notified to Department      ..........&apos;..    34goods manufacturer was fined 10s. in respect of each of two workpeople and ordered to pay  5 5s. od. costs and  2 8s. id. arrears.At Donadea, Co. Kildare, a building contractor and cart maker against whom a previous conviction had been recorded was fined  2, with one month&apos;s imprisonment in default, and ordered to pay  1 costs and ltis. 8rf. arrears. In this case the defendant was told by the Court that if he were again brought before them for a similar offence he would be most severely dealt with.The Solicitor has also reported the conviction of a workwoman at Leeds for signing the unemployed register while in employment. The woman had not succeeded in obtaining any benefit as a result of her fraudulent act, and the Stipendiary Magistrate doubtless took this into account in fixing the penalty, which was a fine of 40s. with 11. days&apos; imprisonment in default;(18) REPAYMENTS TO ASSOCIATIONS (Sections 105 and 106).
PART VI.-STAFF AND PREMISES.(24) WEEKLY STAFF STATEMENT. The following Table sels out the figures for (a) the Staff working, excluding officers serving with H.M. Forces or lent to other Departments, and (&amp;) resignations, terminations of appointments and deaths during the weeks ended 14th September, 1918, and 21st September, 1918 :-	(a) Ptaff working Weeks ended		(V) Resignations, etc., Weeks ended		14th Sept.	21st Sept.	&quot; 14th Sept.	21st Sept,Central Office. Permanent   -! ??,en j Women      ......... n,              fMen............ temporary   (^omm     .........	134 31 56 384	133 31 56 383	2 4	-Claims and Record Office. Permanent   \^en     Z     Z w              l Men............ Temporary   \ ... 1     J    ] Women     .........	91 112 29 914	91 112 HO 913	15	2 16Divisional Offices. Permanent   j ^ -      &quot;      &quot;     -Temporary                     ...      ...      ...	200 114 82 426	199 115 83 426	8	1 1 5 17Employment Exchanges. Permanent                            ;;;     ;;; Temporary                  &quot; ;;;             ;;;	1,293 390 683 1,171	1,288 389 695 1,161	4 13 10	1 2 7 7Totals. Permanent   j ^men&quot;             Z     Z Temporary   ($Tnen     ;;;             ;;;	1.718 647 850 2,895	1,711 647 864 2,883	4 15 37	2 5 12 40Grand Total...............	6,110	6,105	56	59The number of Local Agents now working i* 1,080 (184 have Employment Exchange powers). During the week ended 21st September, 1918, there were 7 permanent and 13 temporary transfers of permanent staff.Mr. E. Russell (Clerk-Gateshead E.E.) and Mr. H. E. Davis (Clerk-Bristol Divl. Office; have been killed on active service.(25) PREMISES.The following Table shows the progress under the Premises Programme since 30th August, 1918 :     .	30th September.	13th September.	30th August.Exchanges where work is completed      ...............	112	101	100Plans approved and Treasury authority received...     ........,	54	60	63Plans approved and returned to Office of Works awaiting Treasury			approval     .:.........................	89	92	93Schemes being considered with the Office of Works    ......     ...	71	72	71Exchanges fur which the Office of Works have not yet submitted			plans......     ........................	62	62	65The following new premises have been occupied by the Department :-Swindon     ............... 11th September, 1918.York   ................... 19thLoughborough      .........     ... 21stCradley Heath      ............ 23rdThe Seasonal Offices opened for the fruit picking season at Auchterarder and Blairgowrie were closed on the 14th September.(22) ALIENS&apos; RESTRICTION ORDER-Artide 22B. Under Article 22B of tho Aliens&apos; Restriction Order permits to bring Aliens into this country were issued in 64 cases and refused in 19 cases during the week ended September 25th, while 51 fresh applications for permits were received during the week.(23) TRADE DISPUTES.During the Aveek ended 27th September, 1918, there were notified to the Exchanges the commencement of 29 trade disputes and the termination of 24. The most important dispute during this period was that of the Railwaymen. The Shipwrights&apos; dispute upon the Clyde has spread : all of these men were engaged upon very urgent work. A number of men at Leith engaged upon Shipbuilding and Engineering work struck against the employment of four Danish fitters.

</content>
</cab>
