<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/66/0 images: 232-245</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the Property of  ^ i 6 3-Is Britannic Majesty^ Government.m**u*. ws ****** MMHPi,i. OFFICE - JF wJIii-[s, &amp;o.Li^JRT for fortnight ended llth October, me, for the information of the Prime Minister.^&quot;aGOO^ODAiION.   1,    In May last, the ministry of Food asked for the first &quot;ant second floors of Carlton House, Regent otreet, as additional accommodation for the wheat Commission, who occupied the third to the fifth floor-; of this building.    At that time the War Cabinet Committee on Accommodation&apos; authorised the requisitioning of the first flJor for immediate use, and the second ,floor when it-should be- required. , The Committeers Inspector is satisfied th-t the second floor is now necessary, and it is proposed to proceed with the requisitioning,S, - . The. Frenoh Ambassador has&quot; applied for accommodation for the staff of the Military Attache -whom it is proposed to outhouse from the French Embassy,. The owner of No.  16, Rutland Gate... has consented to lerd her house rent free for this purpose,-5, &apos;  Additional accommodation being required by the Ministry of Food for the National Kitchen Staff at 4, st, i^aulChurch yard,&quot; it&quot;&apos;is proposed to requisition the second floor of those premises for the purpose.-4,     In order to provide addition 1 accommodation for the lest&apos; and Recreation Rooms of the Newfoundland Contingent In -58, Victoria Street, arrangements&apos;have b--en made to &apos; transfer the   Audit branch of the ,Colonial Office from the first floor to the sixth floor.
5,     Assistance h-is been rendered to the Australian Government in their negotiations for the acquisition&quot;of Nos, 84 and 80, Cromwell Road.6,     During the past fortnight 43 removals of Departments and 45 internal removals have been carried .  &apos; out. -    *  -7,     Further wGrk 1b being, carried out in connection with the purchase of chairs for the Navy and Array-Canteen board, for issue.to Canteens throughout . the United kingdom;--. ,8. , - Hostels for te War Office .        A. A, C. )-.-.&apos; are being equipped ..t the following, addresses J *Stirling.   -  ,&apos;,. ( .          Tidworth.,Pembroke Dock, j*,           Oramllngton.Dover, - &apos;        -   Woolwich....liittlethorpe. Hounslow.,Ballingcolllg, Bromley.Chatham^   .    : , ., Kidbrook,..; .9c ;;f Equipment is being provided, for Government--/: Factory.. Of flees for.; Assembling American Aircraft forthe:Ministry, of i/iuni,tid.ns, .GROSyEKOiv GAliDpS. A temporary building for the Canadian jitaple Leas&apos;.&apos; Glub- has been; commenced.1,011 DOS COUNTY COUNCIL BALL* The completion of the 2nd floor for the Ministry of Food has been commenced. .FaLHBO ROUGH HOUSING SOHJSaE.    (250 houses). Completed with the exception of ground levelling and fencing, . sOIKKOL HUbTO. Completion of Western portion for War emergency Mae,    Temporary Adaptation. Progress fair. . .    Roofing in hand.r, **4
Oxford.  .Report -submitted.Bromley (Park Hotel). Appointment arranged with owner.Portsmouth (Coaham). Report submitted.   Awaiting &quot; decision as toHiiTe.     Revised plan and. estimate being prepared.^IiL^L L^SIJI;tS&apos; HOSPITALS, Ac.Awaiting Ministry of Pensions:-II ew ca e tie -on-Tyne, Lynwood, Jeemend Dene. Southampton, Surgical Accommodation.     -Cardiff, Extension of Hospital. Reading Hilitary Hospital. Shepherds Bush Military Hospital. &quot;Pounds&quot; Plymouth, Convalescent Home. Brighton, M a ib, Sussex Square. Farnham (vJhitffiead). Hull (V.A.E.) Hospital. West London Hospital.&apos; Aberystwith ^Belle, Vue Hotel). .:   . Hewoastie-on-Tyne (Woods Pottery). *f . ,.Hoye.-Orthopaedic Cliniccompleted-  &apos;, , Bray Court, maidenhead.Lonsdale House, Clapham Park.Survey made s-  &apos;   &quot;&quot;.Hanwell&apos; (&quot;The Spring&quot;, Elthorne). Bangor,* Training Centre. T.&apos;rexham (a) Pavilion, (Workshops ). ,   -   - ?- &quot;(b)&apos;Plas Darland (Kostei).Droitwich (Alexandra Hotel). l. ,.   , Tottenham. (Jewish. Hospital), -Allerton Towers, Liverpool.   Sanitary goods arriving and . . .&quot;      fair progress generally.By ton Towers, - Newoas-tle-on-Tyhe.;&apos;Fair progress.7)2, Queen&apos;s Square- Progress oatisfactory.&apos; West Hartlepool, Bradgate House. Plans approved by . :       local -Committee and matter reported to Board.Donoaeter Convalescent Home (Alverley Hall).   Awaiting &apos;plan from County Council.Aghf ord &amp; --OhiBlehurst (Kent). Ashford. Nearly completed.Chislehurst,   Waiting . &apos;        landlord&apos;s consent to commence building.t&apos;rexham-Hostels, Little Acton. &quot;Contract documents , ...    ,:---        , . . prepared.Bridlington &quot;(spa Hotel).   Awaiting offer from owners.Durham.   Work in hand.
Alderhey Military, Hospital (Annexe).   Owner agrees to &apos; *      &quot; lease.     Flan &quot;&quot;&quot;being prepared.Bristol (Southmead). Sketch plans in hand.BOARD OF AGRICULTURE. FLAX PRODUOTION BRANCH. 0*The following &quot;factories are ready for runnings-Bridport&apos; (Ailington Barn-). West &quot;Chinnock.Factory at Pinohbgqk.   Machinery being tested.DO.      Crowle.     Breaker room in hand.Do.      Selby.      De-seeding room roofing in hand.Scutch and breaker room walls proceeding.Do.      Glemsfordt Drawings in hand for scutchingand breaking sections.Do.       Yecvil (Lopen iaills). Tenders being invited.Do.      Yeovll (Bunford). De-seeding section up to - &apos; &quot;    &quot; roof.Do.&quot;     Yeovil (Preston).&apos; Foundations for de-seeding &apos; &apos; - -&apos; section in.Do.       Dorchester (Louds Mill).   De-seeding blockcompleted.Do.&apos; &apos; &apos; South Petherton.   De-seeding machinery fixed.-&quot; i)6v , - ^&quot;,,B&apos;ridport: ,CGrove.:.!lron Works) * Scheme not ..... ;   &apos;  settled.. Building in use as 0,W.Do.&apos;&quot;&apos;/.   Peterborough..   De-seeding building walls15Tt. high.   1st Floor timbers fixedDo.&apos; -    Taunton (Staplegrove Mill)..:Roofing in hand,Lack of labour delaying progress.,Db. &apos; % B&apos;eamir.Bter.   .iAaohinery. being tested.Do*   &apos;   Holbeach.   Engine house in hand.   Framing upelevator supports.Do*-     Wellingborough.   engine being fixed.Installing machinery.Do.       Thorney*.   Engine House completed.   .
1 p rFactory at Pcfikirk. Framing for dust ehute and &quot;...... &apos;    elevator in hand.Co*       Bourne.   Engine bed and framing forelevator in hand.Bury St * Edmunds. Walls to de-seeding building, star fed.    Work delayed through shortage of Bricklayers.Do.        Ha verh.il 1*   Dutch barns in hand.   Machineryall in.Do.        Bures. Machinery inotalled.   Barn in hard. SOUTH AFRICAN HOSPITAL, RIOHMOKD. HARK, New Motor EngineeringWorkshop,    Completed. AMEHIOAN RED&apos;CROSS HOSPITAL, RICHMOND PARK. Builders&apos; workcommenced.EMERGENCY HOSPITALS, RICHMOND PARK. Awaiting decision from O.R.E. Hospitals.     Schemes in abeyance but drawings ready.EMPLOYMENT EXCHANGES&apos;/ SFff&quot;PROGRAMME.A. Schemes completed - New Premises,Alterations, &amp;c. 59B. Building work in progress -  Do.    ;,, 21C. Schemes approved ,by the Ministry ofLabour, but which have not reached the - J       - stage-that building Work is&apos; in hand. 39D&apos;.   Schemes under...consideration of/Ministryof Labour&apos;, 16E.   Premises in view. 7P.   Schemes for which no premises are in.&apos; view at. present..   . 43G. Awaiting information. 5H. Schemes abandoned.&apos; 1I. Treasury refused to sanction. _2^
I,10R&apos;TqAMBq, m! 3HED. All building work completed, andthe premises handed over for occupation. BAKBUKY ADDIT1ON AL BUILDIHGS. Pilling Houses and Drum      ^Sheds-ancLCalorif ier House completed.The Box Stores A and B, two Transit Sheds,Stores, Unheading, House and four Pump Houses:- workIs,proceeding satisfactorily.BIRIUNGHA^&apos;&apos; (3KALL HEATH) PACKING SHgD.   The building is inio ccupation.BRAMLEY&apos; STORES * &apos; Extensions to&apos; the Locomo&apos;tive&apos; Shed and allstructural work to the Power House have been finished, No. 8 -Utet Pour additional&apos;stores arepractically ready for occupation.     Eight furtherbuildings are in course of erection. BRIGHTON (THE DYKE) BOMB TESTING STATION. Progresssatisfactory.BRISTOL, COALPIT HEATH, GUN LIMBER REPAIR WORKS. Work generally is approaching completion.OOL^FORD WOOD DISTILLATION FACTORY. Satisfactory progress, DUMFRIES TlLtiER DRYING KILN.; Building work completed.Engineering services are being ,installed as required,and the work is proceeding satisfactorily. GAIUSBOROUGH (BLYTON) FILLING&apos; STATION. Petrol Stores.A commencement has been made with the erect-ion of thisbuilding.   -Unit 2*   Unheading House.. This building is ffinisl kelt House. Melting Tanks completed. Trolley Tracks and Boundary Fencing.   Progress satisfactory.
i p psco&apos;..LAND (URANGEHOUTH) TIMBER DRYING kiln     sa&apos;7 mills. sketch desipns have been forwarded and approval to proceed ,.j s awaited ,london (gre^v:i0h) coal fuel.research station..   the wholeof foundations for the (power building have been &apos;   completed and satisfactorily tested with loads varying from 1-- to ?A; tons per foot super,,building operations are.proceeding to the main building, laboratory and office and lavatory blocks.london (holloway) respirator faotori.    batavia &amp; hollowaymillsobatavia mill.   alterations have been practically finished, &apos;:kolloway kill.   only a few items of finishing remain to complete the whole work. london (hendon) sidings a bil/&apos;. i&apos;qm railway,.    the whole of permanent way and sidings is now completed including the-additional siding south of no. 5 siding.a block of offices at the edgwaro road side of site is being erected , london (hendon) housik. scheme,the chauffeur&apos;s house has been built to the 1st &quot;floor level,two blocks are built damp course high, two flocks are scaffold high,seven blocks - are first floor high; with the floorsentirely completed. -seven blocks are at first floor level, ready for theconstruction of floors. ten blocks are at.roof plate level. eleven blocks have been slated. eight blocks are being slated * three blocks are being plaster-, d. one block is being floored. three blocks are finished.
The erection of four blocks of shops has not yet been commenced and the site of six blocks of houses in Stag Lane/has not yet been cleared.site in a satisfactory way. LONDON UiOkOK STREET) NEW OFFICES, AUSTRALIAN FOKOLStTho two floors to this building are now both completedand in full occupation. LONDON (PURPLEET) STORAGE SHI;PS. Shed &quot;E&quot; is practioally&apos;completed.LONDON (PUTNEY VALE) ROBIN^OOD ENGINEERING COMPANY.An extra shop and lavatory accommodation has beenapproved at a cost of about  3,450 inclusive of heatinand lighting services..   Good progress can be reported,LONDON (R&apos;[:GEHT&apos; S PARK) AIRCRAFT STORAGE SHEDS, EXTENSION.The works which are now proceeding are additional tothe Contract and are as follows.-Military Gviard House. All structural work finish ..............&apos;&apos;-...............LONDON (WAR OFFICE) LAVATORY ACCOMMODATION. Main buildingentirely completed. MANCHESTER (TRAFFORD PARR) CENTRAL INSPECTION DEPOT. Schemfis in abeyance. -MOR &apos;CAiv.!BE NATIONAL FILLING FACTORY.Dismantling.   The dismantling of Goal ConveyorGenerally. Work is proceeding to six roads onRoads.   All no^w ready for use.Fence around site.   Erection is proceeding.Canteen.   Erection proceeding satisfactorily.plant has been completed.
New Canister Fnotory, / 1st Unit,   Good progress -has been made with the erection of the.Permite Building which is approaching, completion.2nd Unit.   Permitey Charcoal and Finishing Buildings are being proceeded with.5rd Unit,   All concrete foundations have.been completed to the Stores, Permite Buildings, and Charcoal Buildings. RUDHEATH, RU1TC0RN, RE-ERECTION OF HUTS. Progress, satisf actcry, SOUTHAMPTON (EYTHE) SEAPLANE SHED,.. Main BuiJlding.   Half of-the. Shed area is now in use.   The second.half of roof is almost complete.: The,constructions of marshalling platformand slipway is proceeding&apos;.1 SHEPHERDS BUSH, RESPIRATOR ASSEMBLING FACTORY. A.2. Certificate has now been granted and building operations have been .commenced.ayilliPOE STRATTON FACTORY. The constructional work to theTank House has now been completed.&apos;  Work is&apos; proceeding to the Boiler House, North Vertical Kestners, Filter House.   The Vacuum House is structurally completed.TEDDINGTON NATIONAL PHYSICAL LABORATORY.:  All available-labour has been concentrated on the Aerodynamics Section where work is&apos; satisfactorily proceeding.   The -Magnetic Hut is in occupation.NATIONAL FILLING- FACTORIES; -AINTREE.   Extensions of mains for&apos;additional Hydraulic Press Plant completed.
Fireproofing all buildings.;. )Installation of a ventilating scheme     )to the Incorporating and Press Houses.j Proceeding Provision of ,.Five new Storage Dumps..     ) satisfactorily. Extensions to Existing&apos;Boiler House.&apos;     )(IGEORGETOWN.   Building for installation of T.N.T.Recovery Plant and Now steam mains completed,,alsoalterations and additions to the Sectioning Buildings.Fireproofing covered ways.&quot;    4 )Various alteration works .to Melt Houses proceeding1 and 2. )Extensions to Shell Cleaning Houses       )satisfactorily. . and Melt Houses 1 &amp; 3.&apos; ) iGLOUCESTER.   Proceeding- satisfactorily.HEREFORD.   Building work in connection with mechanical stokers to boiler, houses completed.The undermentioned works are procoedingsatisfactorily.]-Building in connection with Hot Mix Plant No.1.Unit. Additional Staff Lavatory accommodation to AmatolFactory. Extension of Workshops,Building for installation of.N:Ltrate Drying Plant. Building for Empty Shell Stores and Boiler House . Erection of &quot;additional Laundry.. Installation of Fire Alarm System. Construction of Loop line and.sidings and passenger (staff) platform at West Amatol Building.&apos; &apos; Re-arrangement of Boundary fence to Factory Managements requirements.PEMBREY.   Generating House in connection with the Laboratory &quot;completed. &apos;Alterations and additions to B and 0 sheds, Amatol Recovery Section: Laying hew &quot;sidings-from.-existing lines to the Lando Stores: Extension to the existing Boiler House all proceeding satisfactorily.10
CANTEENS GENERALLY.   On.behalf of the Ministry of Munitions -(Pood. Section) plane ha^ve been examined., the sites visited &apos;and the schemes&apos;recommended for &quot;approval in the oases of 360 Canteens.The erection qf 148 Canteens is being supervised. 954 standards of timber have been released.The total of completed canteens is now 338 and the checking^of accounts for these is proceeding. The approximate cost of the above 841 buildings is  1,825,328.GRAIN STORES, CARDIFF.   Railway Sidings to Shed No. 3. completed.With regard to the area of 6,300 superficialfeet, which is being, handed over for use by the U.S.A.Naval Authorities, the alterations involving theerection of Offices and fittings&apos;have been commencedLONDON ANTI-AIRCRAFT -DEFENCES.tAmmunition. Dumps,     Work has been started at:-Ingatestone. Englefield.Earlswqod, , Wanstead,Beckenham. Ridgeway.The sitd at Redbourn has been abandoned and a new site selected at Harpenden: &apos;* .      *Accommodation-for Q.R.A. A.C, Chelmsford, completed. :&apos;    Accommodation for &apos;i:.^.A.&apos;A.0., Putney,, a revised plan has now been submitted for &apos;approval.&quot;A.
Transformer Chambers.   Instructions have beenreceived to&apos;build brick-transformer-chambers at the    1following Light Stations:-4Ear Is wood. . Belvedere.,&apos; ,   Shooters,Blaokwall. Reigate.-Bunkers Hill Light., The erection of Hew EngineHut is in hand, .Stations Demolished.Sidcup Gun. Fawkham Gun.Tunnel, Gun.   1 ; Bromlwy Gun,&quot; &quot;!&quot; Demolition of Stations in hand.: Lincoln Light. Southfleet Gun.HETLEY ORTHOPAEDIO HOSPITAL,,,    Proceeding satisfactorily.ORDNANCE SURVEY PRINTING ESTABLISHMENT/ FRANCE.Main Buildings , Map Production Department.The installation of printing plant and machinery iscompleted/The work of extending&apos; the Men and Women?ssleeping&apos;huts by an increase of 900 superficial feetto each building is&apos; proceeding.-&quot;LONDON -(STRAND). &apos; PROPOSED HOSTEL., for Australian Governmentfor N.C.0&apos;s on leave&apos;in abeyance.  &apos;PREMISES ACQUIRED IN- THE PROVINCES.a- : War Services.. -NATIONAL SERVICE DEPARTMENT.    Increasedaccommodation for Medical Boards and Area Offices atBarnsley, Halifax, York and Newcastle is being- considered.   &quot;INLAND&apos;REVENUE&apos;DEPARTMENT &amp; CUSTOMS. Accommodationis being acquired * in London,&apos; Stockton, Rugby, Swindon,Welshpool, Bradford and Lincoln.
MINISTRY OF FOOD.   Additional accommodation io &quot;being taken in Chelsea, Exeter, Bristol, Leeds, Porivale, Derby, Cardiff and Newcastle.MINISTRY CF MUNITIONS,   Premises have been secured in Manchester, Cardiff, Bristol, and Bolton.GENERAL.   Accommodation has also been provided in Cardiff, Loeds, Newcastle, Sheffield and Manchester and many other towns *STATIONERY OFFICE.   Tho work of putting into repair and fitting up the warehouse in Oldham   for storage purposes is proceeding satisfactorily, and a further portion beyond that already reported as complete has. been handed over for ubo.SOMERSET HOUSE.    The work of roofing over one of the large, light wells in order to provide storage accommodation for the Controller of Stamps is proceeding The work of extending the Refreshment Room to provide accommodation for the increasing staff is proceeding satisfactorily, together with the work of rendering tho storage Vaults waterproof.ORDNANCE SURVEY.   The work of providing extensions and alterations at the Office- at Southampton is proceeding.BOARD OF TRADE.   The repairs to the Wharf ml Mills occupied by tho Timber Controller at Erith are still in hand. .MINISTRY OF SHIPPING (GRAVESEND).   The Seamen&apos;s House has been requisitioned and the necessary work of adaptation is proceeding satisfactorily.
ORDNANCE SJJHVEYj   Drawings havo boen proparod and Bills of Quantitios aro now &quot;being mado in conn^ with tho lextonaion of tho Map Stores in order to provide storage for the large number of maps of HomoI Defence Aroas, &amp;o. CULTIVATION IN RIQHM0ND &amp; DUSHY PARKS.Tho wholo of tho Oat and Wheat crops have now boen stacked and thatched, The continuous rain caused much delay in carrying out the latter operati.ITinoty Two tons of Potatoes have b&apos;een soldi to the Navy and Army Canteen Committee, bringing in j over  50C*The Root crops promise well and some remarkably fine Swedes have boen grown in Bushy Park! These will also be disposed of to the Navy and Army Canteen Committee.Over 25 acros have boon ploughed for tho wintdr Wheat and Oats, Lime and seeds are on order. The Pigs aro doing well.The amounts recovered for the Quartor end September 30th, for the salo of Vegetables in the London Parks and Hampton Court Gardens, amounts to ovor  1,000.(Sd.) LIONEL EARLE.

</content>
</cab>
