<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/66/0 images: 267-276</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]        32183Printed for the War Cabinet.  October 1918.SECRET.,Vy NAVAL WEEKLY APPRECIATION--^.Week ended 5th October, 1918.0. 72.NAVAL OPERATIONS.Minelaying in the North Sea and Heligoland Bight has been continued. North SeOn 4th October, at 11 p.m.,two enemy trawlers were sighted and sunk by our LightForces [61 miles north of Terschelling Bank Light.   Four prisoners were taken, theremainder of the crews being lost.R.A.F. machines from Dunkirk have assisted the Belgian Army by bombing and also Flanders by machine gun fire from low altitudes, many thousands of rounds having been fired at Area, bodies of enemy troops and transport convoys.   Many raids, too, have been made with good effect on road and railway communications in rear of the battle front, trains having been hit and fires caused.   The total weight of bombs dropped during the week was over 70 tons.During aerial fighting 25 enemy machines were destroyed and seven driven down out of control.  Eleven of our machines are missing.A recomiaissance over Ostend on 4th October showed that a boom had been laid from the &quot; Vindictive &quot; to the western side of the harbour.On 2nd October Durazzo was bombarded at a range of 12,000 yards by Allied Adriatic, naval forces, consisting of three Italian armoured cruisers of the &quot; San Giorgio &quot; class and the British light cruisers &quot; Dartmouth,&quot; &quot; Lowestoft&quot; and &quot; Weymouth,&quot; with a covering&apos;force comprising the Italian battleship &quot;Dante Alighieri,&quot; the light cruiser &quot; Marsala,&quot; and eight flotilla leaders, together with the.British light cruisers &quot; Glasgow &quot; and &quot; Gloucester.&quot; Sixteen British destroyers, two Italian destroyers, 12 United States submarine-chasers, and a number of Italian submarines and motor boats also took part. During the operations Durazzo was also attacked by British and Italian aircraft, the British machines alone dropping about 15 tons of bombs.Considerable damage was done to the port and shipping, two out of three large ships in the harbour were sunk and one set on fire.   Enemy batteries replied with heavy fire, but did no damage.  Austrian torpedo craft attempted to escape but were attacked and forced to return, while an enemy hospital ship escaping from the port was detained for., examination, but was released in the vicinity of Brindisi. *The only casualty to the Allied forces was ,to H.M.S.^ &quot; Weymouth,&quot; which was torpedoed by a submarine, her stern being blown off and four men killed. The ship, how-ever, reached Brindisi in safety. It is believed that the submarine which torpedoed the &quot; Weymouth &quot; was destroyed, and another enemy submarine was damaged and probably destroyed.During a reconnaissance at dawn our machines were attacked by four enemy aircraft, three of which were destroyed.(C ] 438)  Wt.  -  50   10/18   E&amp;S A:
Casualties,       On 29th, September Motor Launch 247, whilst making Mounts Bay to shelter from heavy seas, was driven ashore.  Eight out of nine of the crew were drowned.On 30th September the torpedo gunboat &quot; Seagull&quot; was sunk in collision with a merchant ship off the entrance to the Clyde, one officer and 52 men being lost.On 30th September H.M. trawler &quot; Sealark II&quot; was sunk in collision with another trawler off St. John&apos;s Point, Dundrum Bay, seven of the crew being lost.On 3rd October H.M. drifter &quot; Lusting &quot; was sunk in collision with another drifter close to the shore off Hellier Holm (Orkney Islands).  There were no casualties.ATTACK UPON ENEMY SUBMARINES.Submarinea       During the week under review about 21 large enemy submarines, of a type which operating,   operates further afield than the North Sea, were located.  Amongst these were four of the &quot; cruiser &quot; type, of which one was working off the North American coast, and one proceeding to it; one operating in the vicinity of the Azores, and one returning home after operating in the Bay of Biscay.The chief areas of activity during the week were the Bay of Biscay and the western entrance to the English Channel.Aotions The following Table shows the number of actions between Allied craft and enemywith enemy submarines which are reported to have taken place in all waters during recent Weeks submarines. an(j the nature of the craft which have been engaged ; and also the number of submarines which have been destroyed or lost to the enemy as the result of such actions : 	Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Sept. 14th.		Sept. 21st.   .		Sept.	 8th.	Oct. 5th.	Nature of Craft, &amp;c.									Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Eesults.	Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.Armed Merchant Cruiser							1	T.B.D. andT.B.......t     ...	0 o	 	3	 	5	- &quot;:	2	 A.P. Vessels     .........	2	 	2	 	4	-	2	Aircraft.........	o O	 -	co	 	 	 	3	 Sloops and Patrol Graft......	5	 	 	-	1		5	1Merchant Vessels......	3	 	1	 	1	--	1	Submarines      .....:	 	 	 	 	 	-	-	 Unknown .........	1	 	-		1		1	&apos; -Total	17	 	9 1 &quot;		12	-	15.	1&quot;Results&quot; indicates submarines definitely known to have been sunk according to the reports of the actions received.   Submarines possibly sunk are not included.The submarine known to have been destroyed during the week was sunk by H.M. Sloop &quot; Snapdragon &quot; 85 miles east of Malta, 33 survivors being picked up.On 1st October a determined attack on a convoy was made during daylight by one of the latest submarine cruisers, about 180 miles N.N.W. of Finisterre. The engage-ment began at noon with long-range torpedo action, the enemy having been previously sighted from the masthead. The torpedoes missed, and on the submarine emerging at a distance of 9,000 yards, H.M.S. &quot; Perth,&quot; the ocean escort, proceeded at full speed to the attack and immediately engaged the enemy, who returned the fire by salvoes, straddling the &quot; Perth&quot; and scoring one hit; on the range closing to 4,800 yards the submarine dived. The convoy proceeded, and later the enemy was again sighted astern and out of range, but slowly overtaking. lfPerth&quot; fired a few rounds, and the sub-marine opened fire with both guns (5&apos;9-inch) on two ships which were straggling, scoring hits on both in turn. &quot;Perth&quot; immediately proceeded to attack by gunfire, and on reducing the range forced the enemy to turn round and submerge. One of the two damaged ships was by now in a sinking condition, and the second also eventually sank after being hit by a torpedo from the same submarine.
MERCANTILE LOSSES BY ENEMY ACTION.The following is a Comparative Statement of the Number and Tonnage of all Merchant NumberVessels sunk in recent weeks by enemy action : 	British Vessels.				Allied and Neutral Vessels.				Total.	Week Ended	1,600 tons gross		Under 1,600 tons		1,600 tons gross		Under 1,600 tons		All sizes.		and over.		gross.		and over.			gross.			No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.1918.										August 24th	8	37,029	5	4,823	5	17,468	5	1,691	23	61,011August 31st	3	14,095	2	1,683	5	15,185	. 8	3,486	18	34,449September 7th	9	36,415	1	975	5	16,922	2	221	1.7-	54,533September 14th	4	29,466	4	2,580	2	7,849	4	2,044	14	41,939September 21st	11	37,853	8	5,977	5	14,277	9*	2,201*	33*	60,308*September 28th	6	17,864	 	 	 	 	1	659	7	18,523October 5th	8	30,844	3	3,076	6	22,835	- 7	4,549	24	61,304and ton-nage of all vessels sunk.* Adjusted.The losses during the week under review are again considerable, but the proportion of British vessels lost is less than usual.The Table in the Appendix is a comparative statement of all merchant vessels, Foreign as well as British, sunk, damaged and unsuccessfully attacked in the last two weeks by enemy craft and by mine, classified according to areas.During the week under review there was a concentration of enemy activity in the western approaches to the United Kingdom, nine attacks having been reported in the Atlantic (Southern) area and eight in the entrance to the English Channel, resulting in the loss of 14 vessels.The number of British and Foreign merchant vessels sailing in organised Convoy Vessels which completed their voyages during last week, and the losses sustained whilst in such convoyed, Convoys, compared with corresponding figures for previous periods, are as follows : 	Weekly average		Weekly average		Weekly average		Week ended		July, 1918.		Aug., 1918.		Sept., 1918.		5th Oct., 1918.	Convoy.									No. of		No. of		No. of		No. of		ships	No.	ships&apos;	No.	ships	No.	ships	No.	convoyed.	lost.	convoyed.	lost.	convoyed.	lost.	convoyed.	lost.Atlantic trades 								Homeward       ......	166	1.2	161	1.0	159	.25	192	3Outward.........	125	1.4	130	.5	125	1.25	115	1 ,Scandinavia-Methil	95	.4	100	.25	89	 	106	- ..-French coal trade......	398	.4	408	 	390 .	.25	357	1Local Bast Coast Convoys	.345	1.3	365   &apos;	.:5	398	.25	424	 (N. of Humber)								Mediterranean local	266	3.2	269	1.75	244	1.5	203	2Total   ...     ......	1,395   -	&quot;7.9	1,433	4.0	1,404	3.5	1,397	7The two ships lost in the Mediterranean Local Convoys were in the Bizerta-Gibraltar Convoy.(C 1438) A 2
Compara-tive state-ment of monthly losses.The following Statement shows the Number and Tonnage of British and Foreign Merchant Vessels sunk by Enemy Action in each-month since the commencement of Unrestricted Submarine Warfare: Daily arerage of tonnage attacked.	British Merchant		British Fishing		Merchant Vessels		Merchant Vessels		Total		Vessels.		Vessels.		of Other Allies.		of Neutrals.		of all Vessels.	Month.											No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.1917.										February ..,	105	313,486	30	3,478	60	84,280	69	135,090	264	536,334March &apos;    ...	127	353,478	43	3,586	62	81,151	92	165.225	324	603,440April	169	545,282	41	5,920	82	134,448	122	189,373	414	875,023May......	121	349,419	19	1,448	70	102,960	95	137,957	305	591,784June	122	417,925	21	1,342	79	126,171	89	139,229	311	684,667July......	98	364,430	18	2,736	-72	111,683	56	70,370	244	549,219August	91	329,810	5	242	63	128,489	34	53,018	193	511,559September...	78	196,212	7	245	64	119,086	18	29,941	167	345,484October	86	276,132	5	227	53	127,932	30	54,432	174	458,723November ...	64	173,560	3	87	42	87,646	22	31,476	131	292,769 -December ...	85	253,087	5	413	46	86,981	37	54,047	173	394,5281918.										January	57 &apos;	179,973	&apos; 10	375	45	87,078	21	35,037	133	302,463February ...	69	226,896	12	686	27	54,904	19	36,374	127	318,860March	82	199,458	10	293	61	94,321	26	51,035	179	345,107April	70	215,376	3	241	30	50,779	13	11,361	116	277,757May......	60	192,436	16	504	33	80,826	19	20,757	128	294,523June	50	162,891	6	639	26	50,981	24	38,474	106	252,985July	37	165,449	12	555	34	70,836	24	23,552	107	260,392August	40	145,581	12	1,364	31	91,079	31	41,946	114	279,970September ...	-4-5	136,402	1	142	17	33,606	9	10,393	72	180,543The losses of world tonnage in September due to enemy action are very much lower than in any month since the commencement of unrestricted submarine warfare. The reduction on the August figure is almost entirely accounted for by the reduced losses sustained by &quot; Other Allies &quot; and &quot; Neutrals.&quot;The following Table shows the Daily Average of World Tonnage Sunk by Enemy Action and of British Merchant Tonnage Sunk or Damaged by Enemy Action, or Escaped from Attack, for each month since Unrestricted Submarine Warfare commenced, standardized by taking 100 as the Daily Average for February, 1917, in each case:    -Month.	World Tonnage.	British Tonnage.				Sunk.	Sunk.	Damaged.	Escaped.	Total Attacks.1917.		I			February      ......	/&apos; 100	100	100	100	100March.........	101.7	101.8	64.8	95.7	93.1April   ...     ......	152.2	162.3	70.7	147.3	140.8May    ...     ......	100.1	100.7	44.8	122.3	&apos; 98.7J une    .........	119.7	124,4	99.4	174.0	138.0July..........	92.6	105.0	45.7	124.0	101.5August ...     ......	86.7	95.0	27.7	84.8-	79.5September     ......	60.5	58.4	70.7	53.3	58.7October        ......	77.7	79.6	40.5	39.9&quot;	58.3November     ......	-   51.3	51.7	62.3	45.9	&quot;  51.5December .    ......	66.8   &apos;	72.9	56.5	63.6	66.61918. .					January       ......	51.2	51.9	45.4	50.4	50.2February      ...	59.7	72.4	72.4	43.1	61.7March.........	58.4	57.5	125.0	64.8	72.0April   .........	48.6	64.1	61.4	73.0	66.9May    ......&apos;  ...	49.8	55.4	68.3	53.5	57.0June	44.2	48.5	.     37,0	57.1	49.6July&apos;   ...     ...	45.5	47.7	51.1	48.2	48.5August.........	47.2	41.9	31.9	50.5	43.3September     ......	31.6	40.6	25.5	29.2	33.8
ENEMY MINES.During the week under review there has been no enemy minelaying in Home Waters, Minelaying. but after a long interval enemy moored mines, which, were no doubt laid by a submarine, have been found in the approaches to Mudros.The situation on the East Coast of Scotland has for the moment been cleared up, but a recurrence of minelaying in that area may be expected at any time.The following Table shows the number of enemy mines destroyed in British mine- Casualties sweeping areas and of British vessels sunk by mine in recent Weeks : 	Number of Enemy			;,&quot;.&quot;&quot;v,&apos;	Moored Mines			Week Ended.	Destroyed.		Number of British Mine-sweepers and Patrols	Number of British Merchant Steamships Sunk by Mines.			Sunk by Mines.		Home Waters.	Abroad.		Aug. 24th	30	11	Nil	Nil,, 31st	18	Nil	Nil	NilSept. 7th      ......	2	Nil	Nil	Nil14th       .....	10	Nil	Nil	Nil,, 21st       ......	7	Nil	Nil	Nil28th      ......	4	7	Nil	NilOct.  5th      ......	Nil !	2.	Nil	NilDEFENCE AGAINST SUBMARINE AND MINE.The following Table shows the number of British merchant ships fitted to take Defensive defensive firmament and the number of guns mounted in such ships : : armament	Primary Armament.		Supplementary Armament.		Number of vessels fitted to take.	Number of guns actually mounted.	Number of vessels fitted to take.	Number of guns actually mounted.During 4 weeks ended 28th September, 1918	91	144	45	19Position at  28th September, 1918......     ...	4,171	4,139	970	664The total number of howitzers and bomb throwers delivered to the end of September is 1,322.The number of British merchant vessels fitted with Otter equipment during the month Mine-of September was 133, and the total number so fitted since the commencement of the protection installation is 2,579. geftr-The number of warships now fitted with Paravanes is 408,. of which 16 are United States ships.(C 1438) A 3The daily average of World Tonnage sunk in September shows a large reduction on previous months, but as regards British tonnage, while the daily average number of attacks is considerably reduced, the percentage of enemy success to attacks made is relatively high.
UNITED KINGDOM SHIPBUILDING.Warship The following is a Statement of British Warships and Auxiliary Vessels completedconstrue- during the six months ended 30th June last, and during the months of July, August and *ioD*        September, 1918:-Description of Vessel.	Jan.-June, 1918.		July, 1918.		August, 1918.		Sept., 1918.											Dis-		Dis-		Dis-		Dis-	No.	placement	No.	placement	No.	placement	No.	placement		Tonnage.		Tonnage.		Tonnage.		Tonnage.Light Cruisers   .........	2	8,380	1	4,650	1	4,650	1	9,750Flotilla Leaders         ......	2	3,500		 	1	1,750	1	1,750Destroyers       .........	34	42,840	5	5,510	4	4,800	7	7,470Patrol Boats	0	4,002	 	 	 	 	 -	 Submarines      ......	18	19,815	5	3,680	: 	 	2	1,600Sloops    ............	15	19,350	 	 	 	 	 	 Seaplane Carriers       ......	 	 	 	 	 	I- 	1	14,500Coastal Motor Boats    ......	30	255	7	55	7	60	8	60Oilers     ............	8	20,156	 	- 	 	 	 	Petrol Carriers.........	3	3,030	  .	 &apos;	- 	 	 	-   -Trawlers         .........	86	45,744	11	5,898	15	7,379	11	7,540 &quot;Tugs      ............	3	1,079	1	1,035	4	4,180	&apos; 	 Patrol Gunboats......	12	10,716	5	4,465	3	2,679	4	3,572Drifters............	28	5,180	15	2,775	12	2,220	11	2,035Boom Defence Vessels and    \	12	3,480		1,160	6	1,740		870Barrage Vessels              j			4				3	Minesweepers (Tunnel)	4	1.160	1	290	 	 	 	Minesweepers (Twin Screw)   ...	8	6,400	5	4,000	7	5,600	4	3,200Minesweepers (Paddle)	8	6,560	 	-  	 	. -.	 	 Sloops, &quot;24 Class&quot;     ......	3	3,960	1	1,320	3	3,960	3	3,960Seaplane Towing Lighters	8	240	4	120	6	180	6	180Coast Defence Vessels ...     ...	1	4,825	 	_	 	 	1	4,825Depot Ship      .........	1	3,460		&apos;      -	 	- 	 	 Barges............	7	140	 	-		 	....	 Total	299	214,272	65	34,958	69	39,198	66	61,312Merchant The number and gross tonnage of merchant steamships of 100 tons and upwardsVessel       reported completed during the first nine months of 1918 are as follows :  construe-Month.	No. of Vessels.	Gross TonnageJanuary............	cm	58,568February   ...	...     ...       .33	100,038March       .........&apos;	......        45	161,674April        ............	.......        37 :&apos;:	111,533May......	,.....        49	197,27,4June...............	......        35	134,159July ...     ...     ...     ...	..............39 - -	141,948August     ......     ......	;   :   33	124,675September.........	...     &apos;:  37	144,772Total for 9 months ...	......       329	1,174,641
The number and gross tonnage of Merchant Vessels which completed repairing Repairs to to the end of September of this year are as follows :  MerchantVessels.Completed Repairing during Month.Month.	Total.		Up to 3 days.		OverS	and up to	Over 10 days and		Over 1 month.						10 days.		up to 1 month.				No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons1918.									i	January	594	1,727,526	167	463,715	224	610,697	148	514,859	55	138,255February   ...	650	2,043,180	156	416,965	254	829,919	149	475,554	91	320,742March	655	2,051,148	181	531,886	250	817,223	140	431,492	84	270,547April	719	2,422,489	220	578,101	296	1,025,771	147	515,729	86	302,888May......	875	2,757,846	275	659,447	323	1,134,453	180	623,448	97	340,498June......	,677	2,143,057	202	529,805	263	910,001	142	481,724	70	222,127July......	723	2,293,405	228	649,736	291	969,875	131.	440,471	73	233,323August	677	2,1.74,343	192	562,764	296	982,912	133	429,437	56	199,230September ...	721	2,294,698	217	600,954	318	1,074,287	125	390,027	61	i 29,430UNITED KINGDOM TONNAGE GAINS AND LOSSES.The following statement shows the position of British merchant tonnage of Gains and500 tons gross and upwards at 30th September, 1918, compared with 31st August, 1918 :  Losses inSeptember.At 31 si August, 1918. Gross Tons. Tonnage of British Mercantile Marine (over 500 tons gross) ... 15,012,935 Tonnage of Vessels under and awaiting heavy repairs ... 741,948 Tonnage available for service at 31st August, 1918     ...     .r. ----   1.4,270,987Gains during Month of September,New vessels (British built) entered for service   ......... 142,105New vessels purchased Overseas............... 26,424Vessels transferred from Foreign Flag     ............ 23,419Enemy vessels captured and entered for service under BritishMag      ......     .................. -Vessels coming under British Flag for causes other than thosementioned above        ..................Vessels discharged and entered for service after repairs (10 days and over).........     ...............Losses during Month of September.Vessels sunk by Enemy action     ...............Vessels sunk by -Enemy action on Auxiliary Service    ......Vessels sunk by Marine risk (September 10,985.   Previousmonths, 6,111).....................Vessels transferred to Foreign Flag...............Vesselslost to British Flag for causes other than those mentionedabove    ... \   ......     ...     ...     ...     ....Vessels laid up for repairs (10 days and over)636,119135,244 1,49817,096 12,4595,140 583,110828,067754,547At 30th September, 1918. -Tonnage available for service.............   .........Add vessels under or awaiting heavy repairs...      ............Total tonnage of British Mercantile Marine (over 500 tons gross)      ......Net Gain during Month of September, 191873,52014,344,507 688,93915,033,44620,511It will be seen that in the month of September the new British built tonnage entered for service exceeded the British tonnage sunk by enemy action, but that the total British tonnage lost by enemy action and marine risk slightly exceeds the new British construction. Owing, however,, to increased tonnage purchased overseas and transferred from Foreign Flags there is a net gain to British shipping during the month of September of over 20,000*
tons, while the tonnage available for service has increased during the month by over 70,000 tons in consequence of a further large reduction in the British tonnage under and awaiting heavy repairs.Compara-        The net gain or loss in the total tonnage of the British Mercantile Marine in recent tive Gains  months is shown below and Losses1917.November December1918.January... February March April May June July August SeptemberNet Gain. Tons.10,50040,236 34,296 8,40020,511Net Loss. Tons.172,057137,023 155,74334,274 37,000 55,134German.ENEMY WARSHIP CONSTRUCTION.The following Table shows approximately the position of new German Warship Construction and the numbers of each type available at the present date :  -Type.Building.Laid down since 1st Sept.Launchedsince 1st Sept.Total Number on the Slips.Total Number launched.Total number building.Available.Number added since 1st Sept.Number lost ordestroyedas ascer-tained duringmonth of Sept.Total number avail-able.Battleships (Dread-nought type only)Battle Cruisers   ...Light Cruisers, in-cluding Minelay-ing CruisersTorpedo Boat DestroyersSubmarines210231711021 11331338 16819 633197 183Austro- Austro-Hungarian Warship Construction remains as indicated in the Appreciation foiHungarian, the week ended August 3rd.MOVEMENTS OF-ENEMY SHIPS.Merchant-        During the week under review five enemy merchant ships arrived at and four sail men.        from Norwegian ports outside the Cattegat.   No enemy ships have entered or le Rotterdam.FOREIGN NAVAL INTELLIGENCE. Russia.General Poole reports that all minor operations of the Dvina force have now ter minated for the season.   The recent operations have resulted in two large enemy shi and two barges being sunk, 200 men killed and many wounded, and in the capture
about 100 prisoners, three field guns, many rifles, ammunition, warm clothing, horses, carts, &amp;c. The enemy has retired hurriedly up the river towards Krasnoborsk, where his armed ships are reported to be now lying, the Dvina River having been mined by him before retirement.  Our losses have not been heavy.A small United States force is operating southwards, east of the Archangel-Vologda railway.Mr. Lindley is of opinion that as soon as mobilisation in North Russia is proclaimed, the villagers will respond in considerable numbers.General Maynard does not expect any immediate attack on Pechenga, the bad weather having made communication inland very bad. The victory of the Karelian troops at Ukhtinskaya has resulted in a portion of the enemy being surrounded on an island in one of the neighbouring lakes..A Eerlin telegram states that the Russian battleship &quot;Volya&quot; and other units of the Black Sea Fleet have now been manned by German crews.There are now eight German infantry battalions in the Caucasus, but it is reported from a trustworthy source that the Germans have decided to abandon all further efforts in the direction of Turkestan. It is stated that at the beginning of September two submarines from the Baltic Fleet had been stripped down preparatory to their transport to Astrakhan for use by the Bolsheviks.Information has been received that the Turks propose to place some long-range Russian guns at Baku to protect the town from the sea.Spain.On 1st October the Spanish s.s. &quot; Francoli&quot; was sunk by gunfire by a submarine in the Mediterranean, and on 4th October the Spanish s.s. &quot; Mercedes &quot; was torpedoed by a submarine in territorial waters near San Sebastian, only three being saved out of a crew of 39. . In addition the &quot; Vivalero &quot;was fired on off Tenerifie but escaped, and there is evidence that German mines have been laid off Corunna.Even in face of these acts of aggression the Spanish Government still hesitates to take any decisive step.Naval Staff.10th October, 1918.[Appendix.
APPENDIX.Statement of the number of British and Foreign Merchant Vessels sunk, damaged, or molested during weeks ended _ 28th September and 5th October, 1918, according to Areas.___		Sunk.						Damaged, but not Sunk.						Unsuccessfully attacked.						Attacks.	Area.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Total.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Total.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Total.		Total.			Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week endjd		Week	ended		28th Sept.	5th Oct.	2Sth Sept.	5th Oct.	28th Sept.	5th Oct.	28th Sept.	5th Oct.	28th Sept.	5th Oct.	1 28th j Sept.	j   5th 1 Oct.	28th Sept.	5th Oct.	28th Sept.	5th Oct.	28th Sept.	5th Oct.	28th Sept.	5th Oct.Arctic and White Sea	/British... \ Foreign																				Atlantic (Northern) ...	/British... \ Foreign	 	 	 	&quot; -,&apos;.	 	 	 	 	 	&quot; - 	 	 	1	1	 	 	1	1	1	1 .Atlantic (Southern) ...	/British... \ Foreign	1 ,	3 3	 	1	1	3 4	 	 			 	-  	 	1 1	 	 	 	1 1	1	4 5Bay of Biscay-	/British... \ Foreign	 	1	 	-	 -	1	 	 	.  -	 	-	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	1Gibraltar Azores	/British... \ Foreign	 	 	 		 	 	 			 	- 	 	 	1	 	 	 	1	 	1South of Mogador	/British... \ Foreign	 	-																		North Sea	/British... \ Foreign	 	 	1	.  	1	 	1	-		 	1	-	1	 	 	 	1	 	3	 English Channel	/British... \ Foreign	1	1	 	3 3	1	4 3	 	 	 	 	 	 	 	1	 	 	 	1	1	5 3Irish Sea and Bristol Channe	/British... \ Foreign	1	1		 	1	1	 		 	: -	 	-	 	 	1	  :	1	-	2	1Mediterranean         ...	/British... \ Foreign	3	3 1		3	3	3 4	 -&apos;	&apos;.  	 	 	 	 	1	 	 	 	1	 		3 4American Coast	/British... \ Foreign	-	1				1								1				1	 	1 1Total    ...      ...	/British... \ Foreign	6	8 6	1	3 7	6 1	11 13	1		-	 	1	-  	2 1	5 1	1	 	3 1	5 1	9 3	16 14

</content>
</cab>
