<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/66/0 images: 337-340</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fhiiQ       &amp; * JNOTE   BY   LORD   WEIR   ON   THE   RESTORATION   OF PRE-WAR   PRACTICES   BILL.I have- carefully considered the draft of the Restoration of Pro-War Practices Bill, and although its connection with the Royal Air Force ts- very remote, I e&amp;nnot refrain from entering the strongest possible protest against the measure, which appears to me to have been drafted without any regard.to the future wellbeing of British labour and industry, or to the industrial experience gained during the war.At ft critical period like the present, when the solution of practical reconstruction problems is of pre-eminent importance, tho attempt to perpetuate by Act of &quot;Parliament the causes of countless disputes and to give form and being to that which is Us intengifcle, ill-defined and infinitely varying as &quot;trade practices&quot;; can only end in the multiplication of disputes, waste of energy, and increasingly embittered relations between employers and employees.In connection with the Pre-War Practices Bill, it is1 proper to consider the recommendations of the Adult Education Committee which have been.discussed by Dr. Addison in Memorandum G.T. 5838.   With many of the recommendations therein made, I am in full agreement; particularly in regard to those conditions of industry which he refers to as &quot;a menace to social well-being&quot;. ..-His apt reference *to the vicious circle of inefficient conditions and inefficient production, is of great importance, and I am convinced that the circle can only be broken by immediate freedom from restriction of production, as that is the one and only method of obtaining the important social and economic standards of living which are requisite for the worker..I am equally convinced.that only limited success will be achieved if the matters are discussed in a spirit of bargaining,    During the war the impelling influence of the national needs has been unable- to evoke a genuine relaxation of restrictions, and it is *obvious that a remedy will only be provided by the fullest appreciation of the circumstanees which confront us and of the certainty of unemployment if the present methods are pursued.One of our most pressing needs, therefore, is to devise methods of publicity&apos;and education which may . bring homo to employers, employed and to the public as a whole, on the one hand the conditions -of employment which impede the sound development of industry, and on the other, the evil of the weapon which the Trade Unions have devised as a protection against these conditions.The policy of the Government should surely be to point out the way to the Trade Unions and the employers,) whereby they may come together and tackle the post-war problems with feelings and desires which I believe they no possess that the olfi policy of higgling and bargaining should give place to a spirit of joint co-operation in establishing a fairer and more human relationship.
** 2 t*I fully realise the difficulty of the Government as the plain facts show that a bargain was made between the Unions and the Government, under.which the Government undertook certain obligations in exchange for certain     ^ obligations undertaken by the Trade Unions, and common justice would now appear to demand fulfilment of these.      The Government having reeognided certain sections of the community as possessing oertaln privileges, bargained for the relaxation of the privileges, and the present Bill calls&quot;for fulfilment   of the bargain.   On careful consideration, it would appear that the bargain  j should have been unnecessary in war time, inasmuch as the] Government failed to treat everyone as a citizen of the tountry and as holding citizon&apos;s responsibilities.Two important factors appear to stand out(a) The privileges, customs ana practices in question, either directly or indirectly, involve limitations on the rate of production .and on the develop-ment of processes and methods of production.(h) It is Impossible to agree&apos;that the bargain has been fulfilled on the part of the Unions or those whom they represent.    Without reference to the past, counties eases can be counted even now of active hostility to dilution, refusals to work on any system of payment by results, refusals to withdraw-demarcation restrictions,?)Pinally, It eannot seriously be alleged that the! right to strike has been given $p. Accordingly, as it I oannot be contended that the Trade Unions &quot;and the men till represent have fulfilled their part, does not the obligJI of the Government fall in the game degree? IIf there is any one thing elear and definite in If regard to post-war conditions,&quot; it is sure: the necessity!! leaving industry untrammelled by precedents or practices! which detrimentally affect efficiency of production,, anil this respect, the present Bill, if passed, would represlj the industrial suicide of Great Britain.     There is eve)I evidence that British industry will be faced with the   1 keenest foreign and allied competition, that the supply I capital will be lacking, and that industrial risks will N so great as to restrain development, unless a stable awl efficient set of -conditions is created.,I am firmly convinced that from the technical, B administrative, imaginative-and craftsmanship points otm view, Great Britain and the workers of Great Britain cA do most things better than any Other country, provided! arc allowed to exercise their ability under^ improved if social conditions and standards of living, &quot; I:In -the future, the greatest regret we will su41 from as a Nation, is that during the war we bargained W trifled with, and thus complicated, the conditions     J; surrounding efficiency of production.     We utterly faifi;, to demonstrate the necessity of the skilled male workJlC putting himself -in a position to earn high wages by   W relaxation-of old-fashioned practices and customs, anojj thereby proving that high wages&apos; aro generally associate with lo^ production costs and good conditions of liviiiiThe Bill as drafted, and if passed, will have! effect of strangling British effort&apos; in the most import! year in industrial history, and is calculated to do rm harm to the working classes of this country than evenB -war has done. t
It is this type of labour legislation whioh has prevented in this country the creation of that spirit of true national servico which is exemplified at present In America in the shipbuilding yards, where record breaking performances are constantly being achieved.     It does not appear too much to say that America has learned to build ships during the&apos;war, due in the first place to the proper guidance   of the impelling Influence of war necessity, and secondly, to the whole-hearted spirit of endeavour which has, not been handicapped, as in this country, by the baneful and restrictive influences, termed &quot;trade practices&quot;.The real gravity of the situation is that the maintenance of these practices here during tho war has now permitted American shipbuilding to develop Into a gigantic industry, which will represent very formidable competition, with probable loss of employment to the British shipyard-worker In the future.Amerioa has had to build up her shipbuilding industry in less than 2 years, from a very small and weak nucleus, whereas British shipbuilding, one of tho largest industries in this country, has failed to develop to any substantial extent.It would be of interest and value to know how many &apos; men have been trained and put to work as rivettors in the last 12 months in British shipyards. and the corresponding figures for America in the same period,I am unaware if the Cabinet fully appreciate the extent of tyranny which exists at present in British industry, and to what extent personal liberty and freedom has degenerated.For example, within the last 6 weeks, 2 skilled iron moulders, having each produced 9 cores for a certain mould instead of the normal output of 8 permitted in the period, were each fined  5 by. their Society.     There is reason to believe that those men, without any undue physical exertion, could havo produced 12 in the same period.I definitely suggest that instead of considering /the Bill as it stands, consideration should be deferred for 3 months.     An immediate detailed Investigation should be made into the labour costs of half-a-dozen products, in say, the engineering industry, such investigation to define the exact influence of present day restrictions on production and on possible earnings.     The results of such investigation should be made as public as possible, so that the community at largo may understand-exactly what is happening and thereby enable them to support the Government.Further, such an investigation would amply demonstrate by the evidence of facts, the enormous possibilities of British industry and the bright future for the workers in this country under an enlightened under-standing of the economics of production.On both sides, I feol it is now appreciated that many cherished traditions and views must bo sacrificed, on-botteasldes and that a new and liberal charter with labour must be jointly agreed if our country is to maintain its position as an industrial and manufacturing nation. Otherwise, the younger and more progressive employers will undoubtedly come to tho conclusion that Great Britain is not a place to ma o anything in and.that some other part of tho British Empire or North America will offer a bettor
- 4 -set of working and social conditions, with proper environment and freedom for the worker.These somewhat discursive notes comprise the following suggestions:-(a) To defer consideration of the Bill for 3 months.(b) To organise an investigation into the detailed influence of restrictive customs on the cost of production and on earnings.&apos;    The results of this Investigation to be published.(c) Steps to be taken by the Government to bring Employers and Unions together so that they may settle suet a new basis of post-war relationship as will enable Briti industry to develop on efficient lines untrammelled by precedents and practices.(d) Consideration should be given to the method of educating public opinion with regard to tho industrial situation after the war and to the necessity of achieving efficiency of production as the only means of making good the losses, due to the war and of securing any permanent improvement in working conditions for the people.11.10.18.

</content>
</cab>
