<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/66/0 images: 342-355</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
mi&quot;\tfais DocumentCONFIDENTIALroperty ^of His Britannic Majesty\ Government.][October 10, 1918.][Revised,\Qctober 28, 1918.]Political  Intelligence  Department. Foreign Office.General/001. [Revised and Supplemented.]5DOCUMENTSbearing onTHE DIPLOMATIC SITUATION CHEATED BY THE GERMAN REQUEST FOR AN ARMISTICE AND NEGOTIATIONS OF THE 4th OCTOBER, 1918.9/10h    01. The German Note to President Wilson of the 4th October, 1918. 2. The Austro-Hungarian Note to President Wilson of the 4th October, 1918. 3. Extract from the speech made by Prince Max von Baden in the Reichstag on the 5th October, 1918. The documents referred to in the speech, viz.:  4. Extract from the answer of the German Government to the Pope&apos;s Note of the 1st August, 1917. The Resolution passed in the German Reichstag on the 19th July, 1917. The Fourteen Points or President Wilson&apos;s speech of the 8th January, 1918. The essential statements contained in subsequent pronouncements by President Wilson on the 11th February, 1918, 4th July, 1918, and 27th September, 1918.Statements by Mr. Lansing regarding the recognition of the Czechoslovakson the 28th June, 1918, and 3rd September, 1918. Extract from letter from President Wilson on Zionism, September 1918. President Wilson&apos;s answer to the German Chancellor of the 8th October, 1918.The German Note to President Wilson of the l^th October, 1918. The Turkish Note to President Wilson delivered the 14th October, 1918. 13. President Wilson&apos;s Note to Germany of the 14th October, 1918. 14. President Wilson&apos;s Note to Austria of the 18th October, 1918. 15- The German Note to President Wilson of the 20th October, 1918. 16. President Wilson&apos;s Note to Germany of the 23rd October, 1918. 17. Mr. Lansing&apos;s Note to Lord Reading of the 23rd October, 1918, communi-cating the Presidents correspondence with Germany. 18. The German Note to President Wilson of the 27th October, 1918. 19. The Austro-Hungarian Reply to President Wilson of the 27th October, 1918.5. 6. 7.8.9. 10.11. 12.1. The German,Note to President Wilson of October 4.The German Government requests the President of the United States of America to take in hand the restoration of peace, acquaint all belligerent States with this request, ana1 invite them to send plenipotentiaries for the purpose of opening negotiations. The German Government accepts the programme set forth by the President of the United States in his message to Congress of the 8th January, 1918, and in his later pronouncements, especially his speech of the 27th September, as a basis for peace negotiations.With a view to avoiding further bloodshed, the German Government requests the immediate conclusion of an armistice on land and water and in the air.Max, Prince of Baden,Imperial Chancellor,Die deutsche Regierung ersucht den Prasidenten der Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika, die Herstelhrag des Friedens in die Hand zu nehmen, alle kriegfiihrenden Staaten von diesem Ersuchen in Kenntnis zu setzen und sie zur Entsendung von Bevollmachtigten zwecks Aufnahme der &quot;Verhandlungen einzuladen. Sie nimmt das von dem Prasidenten der Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika in der Kongressbotschaft vom 8. Januar 1918 und in semen spateren Kundgebungen, namentlich cler Rede vom[367-47 a] B
27. September aufgestellte Programm, als Grundlage fur die Friedensverhandlungen an. Urn weiteres Blutvergiessen zu vermeiden, ersucht die deutsche Eegierung den sofortigen Abschluss eines allgemeinen Waffenstillstandes zu Lande, zu Wasser und in der Luft herbeizufuhren.Max Peinz von Baden, Reichshander,2. The Austro-Hungarian Note to President Wilson of October 4.The Austro-Hungarian Monarchy, which has always waged the war solely as a defensive war, and has repeatedly announced its readiness to put an end to the bloodshed and to attain a just and honourable peace, approaches herewith the President of the United States of America with a proposal to conclude with him and his Allies an immediate armistice on land and sea and in the air, and immediately, therefore, to enter into negotiations for the conclusion of peace, for which the Fourteen Points of President Wilson&apos;s message to Congress of the 8th January, 1918, and the Four Points in his speech of the 12th February, 1918, should serve as a basis, while attention will likewise be paid to the declarations by President Wilson on the 27th September, 1918.Die osterreichisch-ungarische Monarchie, welche den Krieg stets nur als Verteidigungskampf gefuhrt und wiederholt ihre Bei&apos;eitwilligkeit bekundet hat, dem Blutvergiessen ein Ende zu machen und zu einem gerechten und ehrenvollen Frieden zu gelangen, tritt hiermit an den Prasidenten der Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika mit dem Antrage heran, mit ihm und seinen Verbundeten einen sofortigen Waffen-stillstand zu Lande, zur See und in den Luften abzuschliessen und im unmittelbaren Anschluss hieran in Verhandlungen liber einen Friedensschluss einzutreten, fur welche die vierzehn Punkte der Botschaft des Herrn Prasidenten Wilson an den Kongress vom 8. Januar 1918 und die vier in der Rede des Herrn Prasidenten Wilson vom 12. Februar 1918 enthaltenen Punkte als Grundlage zu dienen hatten, wobei auch auf die Ausfuhrungen des Prasidenten Wilson vom 27. September 1918 Bedacht genommen wird.3. Extract from the speech made by Prince Max von Baden in the Reichstag onOctober 5, 1918.The programme of the Majority parties, upon which I take my stand, contains first an acceptance of the answer of the former Imperial Government to the Pope&apos;s Note of the 1st August, 1917, and an unconditional acceptance of the Reichstag resolution of the 19 th July of the same year.It further declares willingness to join in a general League of Nations on the basis of equal rights for all, both the strong and the weak.It considers the solution of the Belgian question to lie in the complete resfcora-tion (&quot; Wiederherstellung &quot;) of Belgium, particularly of her independence and her territorial integrity An effort shall also be made to reach an understanding in regard to the question of an indemnity.The programme will not permit the peace treaties hitherto concluded to be a hindrance in the way of the conclusion of a general peace.. Its particular aim is that popular representative bodies shall be formed immediately on a broad basis in the Baltic Provinces, in Lithuania, and in Poland.We will further the bringing about of the necessary preliminary conditions, therefore, without delay by the introduction of civilian rule. All these lands shall regulate their Constitution and their relations. with neighbouring peoples1 without outside interference.4. Extract from the answer of the German Government to the Pope&apos;s Note ofAugust 1, 1917.The Imperial Government welcomes with special sympathy the leading idea of the peace appeal, in which his Holiness clearly expresses his conviction that in the future the material power of arms must be superseded by the moral power of right. We also are convinced that the sick body of human society can only be healed by the fortifying moral strength of right. From this would follow, according to the view of hrs Holiness, the simultaneous diminution of the armed forces of all States and the institution of obligatory [binding] arbitration in international disputes.
We share the view of his Holiness that definite rules and certain safeguards for the simultaneous and reciprocal limitation of armaments on land and sea and in the air, as well as for the true freedom and community of the high seas [constitute the subjects for discussion between the States] are the things in treating which the new spirit that in future should prevail in international relations, should find its first hopeful expression. The task would then of itself arise of deciding inter-national differences of opinion, not by the use of armed forces but by peaceful -methods, especially by arbitration, the great peace-producing effect of which we, together with his Holiness, fully recognise. The Imperial Government will, in this respect, support every proposal which is compatible with the vital interests of the German Empire and people.Germany, owing to her geographical situation and her economic requirements, has to rely on peaceful intercourse with her neighbours and distant countries. No people, therefore, has more reason than the German people to wish that, instead of universal hatred and battle, a conciliatory and fraternal spirit should prevail between the nations. If the nations are guided by this spirit it will be recognised to their advantage that the important thing is to lay more stress upon what unites them than upon what separates them in their relations. They will also succeed in settling individual points of conflict which are still undecided, in such a way that conditions of existence will be created which will be satisfactory to every nation, and thereby a repetition of the great world catastrophe would appear to be impossible.Only on this condition can a lasting peace be founded which will promote an intellectual rapprochement and a return to the economic prosperity of human society. This serious and sincere conviction encourages our confidence that our -enemies also may see a suitable basis in the ideas submitted by, his Holiness for approaching nearer to the preparation, of the future peace under conditions corre-sponding to the spirit of reasonableness and to the situation in Europe.5. The Reichstag Resolution of July 19, 1917.As on the 4th August, 1914, so on the threshold of the fourth year of the war, che words of the speech from the throne, &quot; We are not actuated by desire for conquests,&quot; still holds good for the German people. Germany took up arms for the defence of her liberty and independence, and of her territorial possessions. The Reichstag is striving for a peace of agreement and for a permanent reconciliation of the nations.The forcible acquisition of territory, and political, economic, or financial con-quests, are incompatible with such a peace. The Reichstag also rejects all plans aiming at economic isolation and the fomenting of animosity between nations after the war. The freedom of the seas must be ensured. Economic peace will alone make it possible for the nations to live side by side in amity. The Reichstag will energetically promote the creation of organs of international law.As long, however, as the enemy Governments will not accept such a peace, as long as Germany and her allies are threatened with conquest and violation, so long will the German nation stand together as one man, and hold out and fight till its right and the right of its allies to life and development are assured. The Reichstag knows that in this declaration it is at one with the men who in heroic conflict are defending the Fatherland.   Imperishable gratitude is assured them.6. Extract from President Wilson&apos;s Address to Congress, January 8, 1918.The programme of the world&apos;s peace, therefore, is our programme; and that programme, the only possible programme as we see it, is this : I. Open covenants of peace, openly arrived at, after which there shall be noprivate international understandings of any kind, but diplomacy shall proceed always frankly and in the public view.II. Absolute freedom of navigation upon the seas, outside territorial waters,alike in peace and in war, except as the seas may be closed in whole or in part by international action for the enforcement of international covenants.
* According to a press telegram, President Wilson, in a letter to Mr. Simmons, the chairman of the Finance Committee of the Senate, has replied to the Republican contentions that the third of his fourteen peace principles, pronouncing in favour of the removal of economic barriers, meant free trade. He explains that he did not mean to suggest any restriction upon internal economic policies, but only that whatever tariff, high or low, any nation might deem necessary should be applied equally to all foreign nations. The President says : &quot; The weapons of economic discipline and punishment should be left to the joint action of all nations for the purpose of punishing those who will not submit to the general programme of justice and equality.&quot; The dragging in of the free trade issue was a partisan attempt to detract from his general programme.His policy, the President declares, is no discriminations against some nations that did not apply to others. &quot;It leaves every nation,&quot; he says, &quot;free to determine for itself its own internal policies, and limits only its right to compound these policies of hostile discriminations between one nation and another. Experiences of the past among nations has taught us that attempts by one nation to punish another by exclusive discriminatory trade agreements has been a prolific breeder of that kind of antagonism which oftentimes results in war, and if permanent peace is to be estab-lished among nations every obstacle that stood in the way of international friendship should be cast aside. It was with that fundamental purpose in mind that I announced this principle in my address of the 8th January.&quot;t This is the correct version, not first as appeared in the telegraphic reports.aIII. The removal, so far as possible, oi ail economic barriers, and the establish-ment of an equality of trade conditions among all the nations consenting to the peace and associating themselves for its maintenance.*IV. Adequate guarantees given and taken that national armaments will bereduced to the lowest point consistent with domestic safety.V. A free, open-minded, and absolutely impartial adjustment of all colonialclaims, based upon a strict observance of the principle that in deter-mining all such questions of sovereignty the interests of the populations concerned must have equal, weight with the equitable claims of the Government whose title is to be determined.VI. The  evacuation of all Russian  territory, and such a settlement of allquestions affecting Russia as will secure the best and freest co-operation of the other nations of the world in obtaining for her an unhampered and unembarrassed opportunity for the independent determination of her own political development and national policy, and assure her of a sincere welcome into the society of free nations under institutions of her own choosing; and, more than a welcome, assistance also of every kind that she may need and may herself desire. The treatment accorded Russia by her sister nations in the months to come will be the acid test of their goodwill, of their comprehension of her needs as distinguished from their own interests, and of their intelligent and unselfish sympathy.VII. Belgium, the whole world will agree, must be evacuated and restored,without any attempt to limit the sovereignty which she enjoys in common with all other free nations. No other single act will serve as this will serve to restore confidence among the nations in the laws which they have themselves set and determined for the government of their relations with one another. Without this healing act, the whole structure and validity of international law is for ever impaired.VIII. All French territory should be freed, and the invaded portions restored, and the wrong done to France by Prussia in 1871 in the matter of Alsace-Lorraine, which has unsettled the peace of the world for nearly fifty years, should be righted, in order that peace may once more be made secure in the interests of all.IX. A readjustment of the frontiers of Italy should be effected along clearlyrecognisable lines of nationality.X. The peoples of Austria-Hungary, whose place among the nations we wishto see safeguarded and assured, should be accorded the freestf oppor-tunity of autonomous development.XI. Roumania, Serbia, and Montenegro should be evacuated; occupied! terri-tories restored; Serbia accorded free and secure access to the sea; and
the relations of the several Balkan States to one another determined by friendly counsel along historically established lines of allegiance and nationality; and international guarantees of the political and economic independence and territorial integrity of the several Balkan States should be entered into.XII. The Turkish portions of the present Ottoman Empire should be assureda secure sovereignty, but the other nationalities which are now under Turkish rule should be assured an undoubted security of life and an absolutely unmolested opportunity of autonomous development, and the Dardanelles should be permanently opened as a free passage to the ships and commerce of all nations under international guarantees.XIII. An independent Polish State should be erected, which should include the territories inhabited by indisputably Polish populations, which should be assured a free and secure access to the sea, and whose political and economic independence and territorial integrity should be guaranteed by international covenant.XIV. A general association of nations must be formed under specific covenants for the purpose of affording mutual guarantees of political independence and territorial integrity to great and small States alike.In regard to these essential rectifications of wrong and assertions of right, we feel ourselves to be intimate partners of all the Governments and peoples associated together against the Imperialists. We cannot be separated in interest or divided in purpose.   We stand together until the end.For such arrangements and covenants we are willing to fight and to continue to fight until they are achieved; but only because we wish the right to prevail, and desire a just and stable peace such as can be secured only by removing the chief pro-vocations to war, which this programme does remove. We have no jealousy of German greatness, and there is nothing in this programme that impairs it. We grudge her no achievement or distinction of learning or of pacific enterprise such as have made her record very bright and very enviable. We do not wish to injure her or to block in any way her legitimate influence or power. We do not wish to fight her either with arms or with hostile arrangements of trade if she is willing to associate herself with us and the other peace-loving nations of the world in covenants of justice and law and fair dealing. We wish her only to accept a place of equality among the peoples of the world the new world in which we now live  instead of a place of mastery.in either do we presume to suggest to her any alteration or modifications of her institutions. But it is necessary, we must frankly say, and necessary as a pre-liminary to any intelligent dealings with her on our paTt; that we should know whom her spokesmen speak for wfien they speak to us, whether for the Reichstag majority or for the military party and the men whose creed is imperial domination.7. Later Pronouncements Made by President Wilson. (a.) EMmct from President Wilson&apos;s Address to Congress, February 11, 1918.After all, the test of whether it is possible for either Government to go any further in this comparison of views is simple and obvious.   The principles to be 1 applied are these: First, that each part of the final settlement must be based upon the essential justice of that particular case and upon such adjustments as are most likely to bring a peace that will be permanent;- Second, that peoples and provinces are not to be bartered about from sovereignty to sovereignty as if they were mere chattels and pawns in a game, Oven the great game, now for ever discredited, cf the balance of power; but that&apos;Third, every territorial settlement involved in this war must be made in the interest and for the benefit of the&apos; populations concerned, and hot as a part of any mere adjustment or compromise of Claims amongst rival States; and &quot;&apos;-&apos; FOitrth; thkt all well-defined national aspirations shall be accorded the utmost satisfaction that can- be accorded them without introducing new or perpetuating&apos; Old
elements of discord and antagonism that would be likely in time to break the peace of Europe, and consequently of the world.(b.) Extract from President Wilson&apos;s Mount Vernon Address, July 4, 1918.These are the ends for which the associated peoples of the world are fighting, and which must be conceded them before there can be peace:-I. The destruction of every arbitrary power anywhere that can separately,secretly, and of its single choice disturb the peace of the world; or, if it cannot be presently destroyed, at the least its reduction to virtual impotence.II. The settlement of every question, whether of territory, of sovereignty, ofeconomic arrangement, or of political relationship, upon the basis of the free acceptance of that settlement by the people immediately concerned, and not upon the basis of the material interest or advantage of any other nation or people which may desire a different settlement for the sake of its own exterior influence or mastery.III. The consent of all nations to be governed in their conduct towards eachother by the same principles of honour and of respect for the common law of civilised society that govern the&apos;individual citizens of all modern States m their relations with one another; to the end that all promises and covenants may be sacredly observed, no private plots or conspiracies hatched, no selfish injuries wrought with impunity, and a mutual trust established upon the handsome foundation of a mutual respect for right.IV. The establishment of an organisation of peace which shall make it certainthat the combined power of free nations will check every invasion) of right, and serve to make peace and justice the more secure by affording a definite tribunal of opinion to which all must submit, and by which every international readjustment that cannot be amicably agreed upon by the peoples directly concerned shall be sanctioned.These great objects can be put into a single sentence. What we seek is the reign of law, based upon the consent of the governed, and sustained by the organised opinion of mankind.(c.) Extract from-President Wilson&apos;s address in New York, September 27, 1918.We are all agreed that there can be no peace obtained by any kind of bargain or compromise with the Governments of the Central Empires, because we have dealt with them already, and have seen them deal with other Governments that were parties to this struggle, at Brest-Litovsk and Bukharest. They have convinced us that they are without honour and do not intend justice. They observe no covenants, accept no principle but force and their own interest. We cannot &quot; come to terms &quot; with them. They have made it impossible. The German people must by this time be fully aware that we cannot accept the word of those who forced this war upon us.  We do not think the same thoughts or speak the same language of agreement.It is of capital importance that we should also be explicitly agreed that no peace shall be obtained by any kind of compromise or abatement of the principles we have avowed as the principles for which we are fighting. There should exist no doubt about that. I am, therefore, going to take the liberty of speaking with the utmost frankness about the practical implications that are involved in it.If it be, in deed and in truth, the common object of the Governments associated against Germany and of the nations whom they govern, as I believe&quot; it to be, to achieve by the coming settlements a secure and lasting peace, it will be necessary that all who sit down at the peace table shall come ready and willing to pay the price, the only price, that will procure it; and ready and willing also to create in some virile fashion the only instrumentality by which it can be made certain that the agreements of the peace will be honoured and fulfilled. That price is impartial justice in every item of the settlement, no matter whose interest is crossed; and not only impartial justice, but also the satisfaction of the several peoples whose fortunes are dealt with. That indispensable instrumentality is a League of Nations, formed under covenants that will be efficacious. Without such an instru-mentality, by which the peace of the world can be guaranteed, peace will rest in part upon the word of outlaws, and only upon that word.  For Germany will have
to redeem her character, not by what happens at the peace table but by what follows.And as I see it, the constitution of that League of Nations and the clear defini-tion of its objects must be a part, is in a sense the most essential part, of the peace settlement itself. It cannot be formed now. If formed now it would be merely a new alliance confined to the nations associated against a common enemy. It is not likely that it could be formed alter the settlement. It is necessary to guarantee the peace; and the peace cannot be guaranteed as an afterthought. The reason, to speak in plain terms again, why it must be guaranteed is that there will be parties to the peace whose promises have proved untrustworthy, and means must be found in connection with the peace settlement itself to remove that source of insecurity. It would be folly to leave the guarantee to the subsequent voluntary action of the Governments we have seen destroy Russia and deceive Rumania.But these general terms do not disclose the whole matter. Some details are needed to make them sound less like a thesis and more like a practical programme. These, then, are some of the particulars, and I state them with the greater confidence because I can state them authoritatively as representing this Governments inter-pretation of its own duty with regard to peace:-First, the impartial justice meted out must involve no discrimination between those to whom we wish to be just and those to whom we do not wish to be just. It must be a justice which plays no favourites and knows no standard but the equal rights of the several peoples concerned.Second, no special or separate interest of any single nation or any group of nations can be made the basis of any part of the settlement which is not consistent with the common interest of all.Third, there can be no leagues or alliances or special covenants and under-standings within the general and common family of the League of Nations.Fourth, and more specifically, there can be no special, selfish economic combina-tions within the League, and no employment of any form of economic boycott or exclusion, except as the power of economic penalty, by exclusion from the markets of the world, may be vested in the League of Nations itself as a means of discipline and control.Fifth, all international agreements and treaties of every kind must be made known in their entirety to the rest of the world.Special alliances and economic rivalries and hostilities have been the prolific source in the modern world of the plans and passions that produce war. It would be an insincere as well as an insecure peace that did not exclude them in definite and binding terms.8. Statements by Mr. Lfmsing.(a.) June 28, 1918.Since the issuance by this Government, on the 29th May, of the statement regarding the nationalistic aspirations for freedom of the Czeebo-Slovaks and Jugo-Slavs, German and Austrian officials and sympathisers have sought to misinterpret and distort its manifest interpretation. In order that there may be no misunder-standing concerning the meaning of the statement, the Secretary of State has to-day further announced the position of the United States Government to be that all branches of the Slav race should be completely freed from German and Austrian rule.(&amp;.) September % 1918.The Czecho-Slovak peoples, having taken up arms against the German and Austro-Hungarian Empires, and having placed organised armies in the field, which are waging war against those Empires, under officers of their own nationality and in accordance with the rules and practices of civilised nations; and Czecho-Slovaks having, in the prosecution of their independent purposes in the present war, confided supreme political authority to the Czecho-Slovak National Council, the Government of the United States recognises that a state of belligerency exists between the Czecho-Slovaks thus organised and the German and Austro-Hungarian EmpiresIt also recognises the Czecho-Slovak National Council as a de facto belligerent Government, clothed with proper authority to direct the military and political affairs of the Czecho-Slovaks.
The Government of the United States further declares that it is prepared to enter formally into relations with the de facto Government thus recognised for the purpose of prosecuting the war against the common enemy, the Empires of Germany and Austria-Hungary.9. Extract from Letter from President Wilson to Rabbi Wise, September 1918.I welcome an opportunity to express the satisfaction I have felt in the progress of the Zionist movement in the United States and in the Allied countries since the declaration by Mr. Balfour, on behalf of the British Government, of Great Britain&apos;s approval of the establishment in Palestine of a national home for the Jewish people, and his promise that the British Government would use its best endeavours to facilitate the achievement of that object, with the understanding that nothing would be done to prejudice the civil and religious rights of non-Jewish people in Palestine or the rights and political status enjoyed by the Jews in other Countries.10. President Wilson&apos;s answer to the German Chancellor of October 8.*Before making a reply to the request of the Imperial German Government, and in order that the reply shall be as candid and straightforward as the momentous interests involved require, the President of the United States deems it necessary to assure himself of the exact meaning of the Note of the Imperial Chancellor.Does the Imperial Chancellor mean that the Imperial German Government accepts the terms laid down by the President in his address.to the Congress of the United States on January 8 last, and in subsequent addresses, and that its object in entering into discussions would be only to agree upon the practical details of their application?The President feels bound to say in regard to the suggestion of an armistice that he would not feel at liberty to propose a cessation of arms tc the Governments with which the Government of the United States is associated against the Central Powers so long as the armies of those Powers are upon their soil. The good faith Of any discussion would manifestly depend upon the consent of the Central Powers immediately to withdraw their forces everywhere from invaded territory.The President also feels that he is justified in asking whether the Imperial Chancellor is speaking merely for the constituted authorities of the Empire who have so far conducted the war. He deems the answer to the questions vital from every point of view.11. German Note to President Wilson, October 12, 1918.The German Government has accepted the terms t laid down by President. Wilson in his Address of the 8th January and in his subsequent addresses as the foundation for a permanent peace of justice- Consequently, the object of the proposed, discussions would be only to come to an understanding upon practical details of the application of these terms.The German Government assumes that the Governments of the Powers associated with the Government of the United States also adopt the position taken by President Wilson in his public declarations.The German Government declares itself ready, in agreement with the Austro-Hungarian Government, with a view to bringing about an armistice to comply with the proposals of the President in. regard to evacuation. The German Government suggests that the President should bring about the meeting of a mixed Commission, whose duty it would be to concert the necessary arrangements concerning the evacuation.The present German Government, which takes the responsibility for this step towards peace, has been formed by negotiations and in agreement with the great majority of the Reichstag. The Chancellor^ supported in all his actions by trie will of this majority, speaks in the name of the German Government and of the German people.(Signed)   SOLF,State Secretary of Foreign Office.Berlin. October 1.2. 1918.* The written text, has not yet been received from Washington;f &quot; SatBe.&quot;  Perhaps nearer to &quot; stipulations,&quot; or even ci propositions.&quot;
Die Deutsche Regierung hat die Satze angenommen, die President Wilson in seiner Ansprache vom 8. Januar und in seinen spateren Ansprachen als Grundlage eines dauernden Rechtsfriedens niedergelegt hat. Der Zweck der einzuleitenden Besprechungen ware also lediglich der, sich liber praktische Einzelheiten ihrer Anwendung zu verstandigen.Die Deutsche Regierung nimmt an, dass anch die Regierungen der mit den Vereinigten Staaten verbundenen Machte sich auf den Boden der Kundgebungen des Prasidenten Wilson stellen.Die Deutsche Regierung erklart sich im Einvernehmen mit der Osterreichiseh-Ungarischen Regierung bereit, zur Herbeifuhrung eines Waffen still standee den Raumungsvorschlagen des Prasidenten zu entsprechen. Sie stellt dem Prasidenten anheim, den Zusammentritt einer gemischten Kommission zu veranlassen, der es obliegen wurde, die zur Raumung erforderlichen Vereinbarungen zu treffen.Die jetzige Deutsche Regierung, die die Verantwortung fur den Friedensschritt tragt, ist gebildet durch Verhandlungen und in Ubereinstimmung mit der grossen Mehrheit des Reichstags. In jeder seiner Handkmgen gestutzt auf den Willen dieser Mehrheit, spricht der Reichskanzler im Namen der Dexitschen Regierung und des deutschen Volkes.(gez.)        SOLE, Staatssekretdr des Auswartigen Amtes.Berlin, den 12. Oktober 1918.12. The Turkish Note to President Wilson delivered at Washington on the 14th October, 1918.*The undersigned Charge d&apos;Affaires of Turkey has the honour, acting upon instructions from his Government, to inform the Secretary of State of the United States by telegraph that the Imperial Government requests the President of the United States to take upon himself the task of re-establishing peace, and to notify all belligerent States of this demand, and invite them to delegate plenipotentiaries to initiate negotiations.The Imperial Government accepts, as the basis of negotiations, the programme laid down by the President in his message to Congress on the 8th January, and subsequent declarations, especially the speech of the 29th September.!In order to end the bloodshed, the Imperial Government requests that steps be taken for the immediate conclusion of a general armistice.13. President Wilson&apos;s Note to Germany of the 14th October, 1918.The unqualified acceptance by the present German Government and by a large majority of the German Reichstag of the terms laid down by the President of the United States of America in his address to the Congress of the United States on January 8th, 1918, and in his subsequent addresses justifies the President in making a frank and direct statement of his decision with regard to the communications of the German Government of the 8thI and 12th October, 1918.It must be clearly understood that the process of evacuation and the conditions of an armistice are matters which must be left to the judgment and advice of the military advisers of the Government of the United States and the Allied Governments, and the President feels it his duty to say that no arrangement can be accepted by the Government of the United States which does not provide absolutely satisfactory safeguards and guarantees of the maintenance of the present military supremacy of the armies of the United States and of the Allies in the Field. He feels confident that he can safely assume that this will also be the judgment and decision of the Allied Governments.The President feels that it is also his duty to add that neither the Government of the United States nor, he is quite sure, the Governments with which the Government of the United States is associated as a belligerent will consent to consider an armistice so long as the armed forces of Germany continue the illegal and inhuman practices which they still persist in. At the very time that the German Government approaches the Government of the United States with proposals of peace its submarines are engaged in sinking passenger ships at sea, and not the ships alone, but the very boats in which their passengers and crews seek to make their way to safety ; and in their present enforced withdrawal from Flanders and France the German armies are pursuing a course of wanton* The official text is not at present available, f Query : 27th September. 1 Query: 4th October.[367-47 a] D
destruction which has always been regarded as in direct violation of the rules and practices of civilised warfare. Cities and villages, if not destroyed, are being stripped not only of all they contain, but often of their very inhabitants. The Nations associated against Germany cannot be expected to agree to a cessation of arms while acts of inhumanity, spoliation and desolation are being continued which they justly look upon, with horror and with burning hearts.It is necessary also in order that there may be no possibility of misunderstanding, that the President should very solemnly call the attention of [the Government of *] Germany to the language and plain intent of one of the terms of peace which the German Government has now accepted. It is contained in the address of the President delivered at Mount Vernon on July 4th last.  It is as follows:&quot; The destruction of every arbitrary power anywhere that can separately, secretly and of its single choice disturb the peace of the world; or, if it cannot be presently destroyed, at the least its reduction to virtual impotence.&quot;The power which has hitherto controlled the German nation is of the sort here described. It is within the choice of the German nation to alter it. The Presidents words just quoted naturally constitute a condition precedent to peace if peace is to come by the action of the German people themselves. The President feels bound to say that the whole process of peace will, in his judgment, depend upon the definiteness and satis-factory character of the guarantees which can he given in this fundamental matter. It is indispensable that the Governments associated against Germany should know beyond a peradventure with whom they are dealing.The President will make a separate reply to the Royal and Imperial Government of Austria-Hungary.14. President Wilson&apos;s Note to Austria of the 18th October, 1918.fThe President deems it his duty to say to the Austro-Hungarian Government that he cannot entertain the present suggestions of that Government because of certain events of the utmost importance which, occurring since the delivery of his address of the 8th January last, have necessarily altered the attitude and responsibility of the Government of the United States.Among the fourteen terms of peace which the President formulated at that time occurred the following: X. &quot; The peoples of Austria-Hungary, whose place among the nations we wish to see safeguarded and assured, should be accorded the freest, opportunity of autonomous development.&quot;Since that sentence was written and uttered to the Congress of the United States, the Government of the United States has recognised that a state of belligerency exists between the Czecho-Slovaks and the German and Austro-Hungarian Empires, and that the Czecho-Slovak National Council is a de facto belligerent Government, clothed with proper authority to direct the military and political affairs of the Czecho-Slovaks. It has also recognised in the fullest manner the justice of the nationalistic aspirations of the Jugo-Slavs for freedom.The President is therefore no longer at liberty to accept a mere &quot; autonomy &quot; of these peoples as a basis of peace, but is obliged to insist that they, and not he, shall be the judges of what action on the part of the Austio-Hungarian Government will satisfy their aspirations and their conception of their rights and destiny as members of the family of nations.15. The German Note to President Wilson of the 20th October, 1918.In complying with the proposal to evacuate occupied territories the German Government adopted the position that the procedure in this evacuation and the con-ditions of armistice are to be left to the judgment of military advisers, and that the present relative strength on the fronts must be made the basis of arrangements that will safeguard and guarantee it. The German Government leaves it to the President to create an opportunity to settle the details.   It trusts that the President of the United* These three words do not occur in all the telegraphic versions.  The written text has not yet beenreceived from Washington. I The written text has not yet been received from Washington. , :i
States will approve no demand that would be irreconcilable with the honour of the German people and with paving the way to a peace of justice.The German Government protests against the charge of illegal and inhuman practices that is made against the German land and sea forces, and thereby against the German people.Destructions will always be necessary to cover a retreat, and are in so far per-mitted under international law. The German troops have the strictest instructions to respect private property and to make provision for the population according to their ability.  Where, notwithstanding this, excesses occur&apos;, the guilty are punished.The German Government also denies that in sinking ships the German Navy has purposely destroyed lifeboats together with their occupants. The German Government suggests that in all these points the facts shall be cleared up by neutral commissions.In order to avoid everything that might impede the efforts to secure peace, orders have, at the direction of the German Government, been sent out to all U-boat commanders that will exclude the torpedoing of passenger ships. At the same time, however, for technical reasons, no guarantee can be undertaken that this order will reach every submarine at sea before its return.President Wilson describes as a fundamental condition for peace the removal of every arbitrary power that can separately, uncontrolled, and of its own single choice disturb the peace of the world. To this the German Government replies: In the German Empire the representatives of the people have hitherto had no right to influence the formation of the Government. The Constitution did not provide for the co-operation of Parliament in decisions on war and peace. A fundamental change has come about in this regard. The new Government has been formed in complete accord with the desires of a Parliament which issued from equal, general, secret, and direct suffrage. The leaders of the great parties of the Reichstag are amongst its members.In the future, too, no Government can enter upon or carry on its office without possessing the. confidence of the majority of the Reichstag. The responsibility of the Imperial Chancellor towards Parliament is being legally extended and safeguarded. The first act of the new Government was to submit a Bill to the Reichstag so amending the Constitution of the Empire that the approval of Parliament is requisite for a decision on war and peace. The pledge for the duration of the new system, however, does not He only in legal guarantees, but also in the unshakable will of the German people, the great majority of which is behind these reforms, and demands their energetic prosecution.The Presidents question as to with whom he and the Governments associated against Germany are dealing is therefore clearly and unequivocally answered, to the effect that the peace and armistice offer comes from a Government which, free from all arbitrary and irresponsible influence, is supported by the approval of the overwhelming majority of the German people.(Signed)   SOLF,Secretary of State of the Foreign Ministry.Berlin, October, 20.Die deutsche Regierung ist bei der Annahme des Vorschlags zur Raumung der besetzten Gebiete davon ausgegangen, dass das Verfahren bei dieser Raumung, und die Bedingungen des Waffenstillstandes der Beurteilung militarischer Ratgeber zu iiberlassen sind und dass das gegenwartige Krafteverhaltnis an den Fronten den Abmachungen zu Grund zu legen ist, die es sichern und verburgen. Die deutsche Regierung gibt dem Prasidenten anheim zur Regelung der Einzelheiten eine Gelegenheit zu schaffen; sie vertraut darauf, dass der President der Vereinigten Staaten keine Forderung gutheissen wird, die mit der Ehre des deutschen Volkes und mit der &quot; Anbahnung eines Friedens der Gerechtigkeit unvereinbar sein wiirde.Die deutsche Regierung legt Verwahrung ein gegen den Vorwurf ungesetzlicher und unmenschlicher Handlungen, die gegen die deutsche Land- und Seestreitkrafte und damit gegen das deutsche Volk erhoben wircl. .Zerstorungen werden zur Deckung eines Ruckzuges immer notwendig sein und sind insoweit volkerrochtlich gestattet. Die deutschen Truppenhaben die strengste-Weisung Privateigentum zu schonen und ftir die Bevolkerung nach Kraften zu sorgen.. Wo trotzdem Ausschreitungen vorkornmen, werden die Schuldigen bestraft.Die deutsche Regierung bestreitet auch dass die deutsche Marine bei Versenkung von Schiffen Rettungshoote nebst ihren Insassen absichtlich vernichtet hat.Die deutsche Regierung schlagt vor in alien diesen Punkten den Sachverhalt durch neutrale Kommissionen aufklaren zu lassen.[367-47a] E
Urn Alles zu verhiiten was das Friedenswerk erschweren kdnnte, sind auf Veranlassung der deutsche Regierung an saintliche U-Bootkommandanten Befelile ergangen die eine Torpedierung von Passagierschiffen. ausschliessen, wobei jedoch aus technisohea Gruhden eine Gewahr dafur nicht iibernoinmen werden kann, dass dieser Befehl jedes in See befindliclie U-Boot vor dessen Ruckkehr erreipht.Als grundlegende Bedingung fur den Frieden bezeichnet der President die Beseitigung jeder auf Willkur beruhenden Macht, die fur sich, unkontrolliert und aus eigenem Belieben den Frieden der Welt storen kann. Darauf antwortet die deutsche Regierung: Im deutschen Reiche stand der Volksvertretung ein Einfluss auf die Bildung der Regierung bisher, nicht zu. Die Verfassung sah bei der Entscheidung liber Krieg und Frieden eiue Mitwirkung der Volksvertretung nicht vor. In diesen Verhaltnissen ist ein grundlegender Wandel eingetreten. Die neue Regierung ist in volliger TJbereinstimmung mit den Wunschen, der aus dem gleichen, allgemeinen, gelieimen und direkten Wahlrecht hervorgegangenen Volksvertretung gebildet. Die Fiihrer der grosseu Parteien des Reichstages gehoren zu ihren Mitgliedern. Auch kiinftig kann keine Regierung ihr Amt antreten oder weiterftihren olme das Yertrauen der Mehrheit des Reichstages zu besitzen. Die Verantwortung des Kanzlers gegeniiber der Volksvertretung wird gesetzlich ausgebaut und sicher-gestellt. Die erste Tat der neuen Regierung ist gewesen dem Reichstag ein Gesetz vorzulegeii durch das die Verfassung des Reiches dahin geahdert vvird, dass zur Entscheidung liber Krieg und Frieden die Zustirnmung der Volksvertretung erforderlich ist.Die Gewahr fur die Dauer des neuen Systems ruht aber nicht nur auf gesetzlichen Blirgschaften, sqndern auch in dem unerschutterlichen Willen des deutschen Volkes, das in seiner grossen Mehrheit hinter diesen Reform en steht und deren energische Fortfuhrung fordert.Die Frage (Jes Prasidenten mit wem er und die gegen Deutschland verblindeten Regierungen es zu tun haben, wird somit klar und unzweideutig dahin beantwortet, dass das Fried ens- und Waffenstillstandsangebot ausgeht von einer Regierung, die frei von jeder willkurlichen und uuverantwortlichen Eiufluss getragen wird von der -Zustimmung der liberwaltigendeu Mehrheit des deutschen Volkes.SOLF.16. President Wilson&apos;s Note to Germany of the 23rd October, 1918.*Having received the solemn and explicit assurance of the German Government that it unreservedly accepts the terms of peace laid down in his address to the Congress of the United States on the 8th of January, 1918, and the principles of settlement enunciated in his subsequent addresses, particularly the address of the 27th September, and that it desires to discuss the details of their application;And that this wish and purpose emanate, not from those who have hitherto dictated German policy and conducted the present war on Germany&apos;s behalf, but from Ministers who speak for the majority of the Reichstag and for an overwhelming majority of German people;And having received also the explicit promise of the present German Government that the humane rules of civilised warfare will be observed both on land and sea by the German armed forces,The President of the United States feels that he cannot decline to take up with the Governments with which the Government of the United States is associated the question of an armistice.He d3ems it his duty to say again, however, that the only armistice he would feel justified in submitting tor consideration would be one which should leave the United States and the Powers associated with her in a position to enforce any arrangements that may be entered into, and to make a renewal of hostilities on the part of Germany impossible. The President has, therefore, transmitted his correspondence with the prssent Germin Authorities to the Governments with which the Govern-ment of the United States is assosiated as a belligerent, with the suggestion that, if those Governments are disposed to effect peace upon the terms and principles indicated, their military advisers and the military advisers of the United States be asked to submit to the Governments associated against Germany the necessary terms of such an armistice as will fully protect the interests of the peoples involved and ensure to the Associated Governments the unrestricted power to safeguard and enforce the details of the* The written text has not yet been received from Washington.
peace to which the German Government has agreed, provided they deem such an armistice possible from the military point of view. Should such terms of armistice he suggested, their acceptance by Germany will afford the best concrete evidence of her unequivocal acceptance of the terms and principles of peace from which the whole action proceeds.The President would deem himself lacking in candour did he not point out in the frankest possible terms the reason why extraordinary safeguards must be demanded. Significant and important as the constitutional changes seem to be which are spoken of by the German Foreign Secretary in his Note of the-20th October, it does not appear that the principle of a Government responsible to the German people has yet been fully worked out, or that any guarantees either exist or are in contemplation that the alteration of principle and of practice now partially agreed upon will be permanent.Moreover, it does not appear that the heart of the present difficulty has been reached. It may be that future wars have been brought under the control of the German people : but the present war has not; and it is with the present war that we are dealing. It is evident that the German people have no means of commanding the acquiescence of the military authorities of the Empire in the popular will: that the power of the King of Prussia to control the policy of the Empire is unimpaired : that the determining initiative still remains with those who have hitherto been the masters of Germany.Feeling that the whole peace of the world depends now on plain speaking and straightforward action, the President deems it his duty to say, without any attempt to soften what may seem harsh words, that the nations of the world do not, and cannot trust the word of those who have hitherto been the masters of German policy, and to point out once more that in concluding peace and attempting to undo the infinite injuries and injustices of this war, the Government of the United States cannot deal with any but veritable representatives of the German people, who have been assured of a genuine constitutional standing as the real rulers of Germany. If it must deal with the military masters and the monarchical autocrats of Germany now, or if it is likely to have to deal with them later in regard to the international obligations of the German Empire, it must demand, not peace negotiations but surrender. Nothing can be gained by leaving this essential thing unsaid.17. Mr. Lansing&apos;s Note to Lord Reading of 23rd October, 1918.&apos;*I have the honour to enclose herewith certain communications which have passed between the United States Government and the German Government relative to an armistice and the terms of a Treaty of Peace between the belligerents in the present war, with the request that you should transmit the same to your Government.The President instructs me to make the request that your Government should take this correspondence under its careful consideration and should communicate at its convenience its views and conclusions concerning it.The President desires especially an expression of your Government as to its willingness and readiness to acquiesce in, and to take part in, the course of action with regard to an armistice which is suggested in my Note of October 23rd, 1918, to the Charge d&apos;Affaires of Switzerland, in which is set forth the decision of the President with regard to the submission of the question of an armistice to the Governments with which the Government of the United States is associated in the prosecution of the war against Germany, and with regard to the manner in which the terms of an aimistice are to be determined, provided that an armistice at the time is deemed possible from the military point of view.I wish to point out to your Lordship&apos;s Government that the President has endeavoured to safeguard with the utmost care the interests of the peoples at war with Germany in every statement made in the enclosed correspondence, and that it is his sincere hope that your Government will think that he has succeeded, and will be willing to co-operate in the steps which he has suggested..[The communications enclosed in the Note are the three German Notes dated October --6th,I October 14thf and October 22nd,&quot;)&quot; and the Eeplies of the Government of the United -States dated October 8th, October 14th and October 23rd.]* Printed from a telegraphic version.f i.e., delivered at Washington on these respective dates.
18. The German Note to President Wilson of October 27, 1918.The German Government has taken cognisance of the answer of the President of the United States. The President is aware of the far-reaching changes which have been carried out and are being carried out in the German Constitutional structure.The peace negotiations will be conducted by a peopled Government, in whose hands rests both actually and constitutionally the power to make deciding conclusions.  The military powers are also subject to it.The German Government now awaits proposals for an armistice which shall be a first step towards a just peace, as the President has described it in his proclamations.SOLF,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs *19. The Austro-Hungarian Reply to President Wilson of the 21th October, 1918.In answer to President Wilson&apos;s note of the 18th instant, addressed to the Austro-Hungarian Government, and in accordance with the Presidents decision to treat the question of armistice and peace separately with Austria-Hungary, the Austro-Hungarian Government has the honour to declare that it agrees, as with the Presidents former declarations, so also with the views expressed in his last note concerning the rights of the peoples of Austria-Hungary, especially of Czecho-Slovaks and Jugo-Slavs. As, therefore, Austria-Hungary has accepted all the conditions on which the President has made the opening of negotiations for armistice and peace depend, the Austro-Hungarian Government considers that nothing stands in the way of such negotiations being opened, the Austro-Hungarian Government therefore declares itself ready, without awaiting the result of other negotiations, to commence negotiations for peace between Austria-Hungary and the opposing States, and for universal armistice on all Austro-Hungarian fronts, and requests the President to take introductory steps accordingly. (Signed) Andeassy.*o* Printed from a telegraphic version.

</content>
</cab>
