<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/66/0 images: 358-362</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
telegrams-&quot;shipminder, vic, london.&quot;any furthor communication on this bubjoot should be addroascd to-the secretary,ministry of shipping, &apos;st. jamos&apos;8 park,london, s,w. 1,* rjmd^hg^]^^u  number quoted:-MINISTRY  OF  SHIPPING14th October, 1918.In continuation of my letter of the 7th instant, Iam directed by the Shipping Controller to report, for theinformation of the Vvar Cabinet, as follows1. LOSSES AND GAINS OF BRITISH TONKAflE.During the week ended the 5th instant, the total number of British vessels of 500 tons gross and upwards reported lost was 13 vessels of 43,055 gross tons, of which 11 were lost by enemy action, including the ex-Norwegian &quot;BAMSE&quot; and the prize steamer &quot;POLJAMES&quot;.     Three of these vessels together with two foreign ships were lost whilst in convoy.    The total number of new vessels, British built, brought into service during the same period was 5 vessels of 28,939 gross tons, Including three standard steamers, making a net loss of 14,096 tons.flag one vessel of 687 gross tons.     This, however, is not additional tonnage available for service as the vesselwas already employed in the service of the Allies. 923,447&apos;was paid in compensation for loss of requisitioned ships, making a total of  32,053,270 paid on this account since the 1st April 1918. 3.      . AMERICAN TROOFlNG.In addition there was transferred from the NorwegianFINANCE.During the week ended the 5th instant the sum ofIt is regretted that recently there have been severalcollisions between vessels carrying American troops and HisWAR CABINET.
Majesty&apos;s ships.     In one case the vessel was the escort ship (H.M.S, &quot;OTRANTO&quot;) also carrying American troops, and considerable loss of life resulted; the facts are being fully investigated.Owing to winter conditions and an outbreak of influenza amongst American troops, the number being embarked on the vessels is at present being reduced by 20 per cent, of the vessels&apos; carrying capacity.STORES rOR THE BRITISH ARiVIY IN FRANCS.The quantity of military stores discharged in France in the week ending 5th October was 156,181 tons, compared with 191,212 tons during the previous week. EXCHANGE Or BRITISH AND GERMAN PRISONERS OF MR.The twenty-fourth exchange of Prisoners of War has taken place, the Dutch ships disembarking 105 British prisoners and 3 women and children at Boston and embarking 148 German prisoners of war and civilians and 82 German women and children.The total number conveyed in the twenty-four trips has been as follows :-British        ... 3,585German ... 11,460TURKISH PRISONERS.In addition to the arrangements already reported for moving 5,000 Turkish Prisoners from Egypt to Cyprus, arrangements have also been made to move 5,000 to Salonika. SUPPLIES FOR SALONIKA.The question of the provision of additional supplies for Salonika necessitated by the activity in that region is under consideration, GRAIN FROM INDIA.Information has been received from the Government of India that that country will no longer be able to export grain. The question of conveying grain from other sources to Egypt, Salonika, etc, is receiving consideration,
9* SPANISH INFLUENZA.The serious outbreak of Spanish influenza at Southampton is, to a certain extent, Interfering with the Transport work. 10.        HOME TRADE SERVICES&apos;.A memorandum on the organisation and work of the Home Trade Branch of this Ministry is attached.I am,:  Sir, Your obedient Servant,(Sgdw) John Anderson.
The Home Trade Branch of this Ministry has a general executive responsibility for watching the Coastwise trade round the United Kingdom for arranging diversions in that trade, and for making the best use of any tonnage that may be available, The Branch also shares general executive responsibility for the French General Cargo trade and for securing the proper administration of the new Conference Scheme.To further the objects for which the Branch wpp formed, anorganization has been set up in Dublin under Mp. H.6. Burgess,with the title of Director of Cross Channel Transportation,whose function it is to co-operate with Home Trade Branchin all matters   relating to the Trade between Great Britain andIreland,During the year, the Branch has framed and published Scales of Maximum rates of freight for the principal avenues of trade round the coast, and for time-chartered steamers.The Branch has also arranged employment for requisitioned tonnage controlled by other Branches of the Ministry which has through the exigencies of Government requirements been temporarily available.Generally, the work of the Branch has proceeded very smoothly, and the necessary control and direction has been carried out with the minimum of friction,eThe maximum rates appear (with very few exceptions ) to be mutually acceptable to merchants and shipowners,There is a shortage of tonnage all over, but every opportunity is taken to ration the available vessels to the best advantages In this connexion special attention is being paid to the movements of ships in ballast, which movement is now reduced to a minimum, and machinery is in existence whereby all vessels about to shif% ports in ballast are first offered to this Branch, when every effort is made to utilize them.Advisory Committees hase boon set up at the principal outports, with a Central Committee,In London, In conjunction with the Port &amp; Transit Executive&apos;Committee, for the purpose of assisting in the more effective use of available tonnage, and with the object of directing all possible traffic, more particularly of , a rougher description, from Rail transit to sea.The work of the Sections is as followsj-GENERAL CARGO 3c PASSENGER LINERS.   This Section exercises a general oversight upon the established regular services, coastwise and cross-channel, including Messrs MacBrayne&apos;s Highland &amp; Island Service, and apportions tonnage whenever the returns shew that this may be necessary, so that steamers on the services may as far as possible be always fully loaded.It makes arrangements in co-operation with the Shipping Dept. of Royal Commission on Wheat Supplies, for the transhipment of Foodstuffs arriving from Overseas, utilizing  Coastwise Liner tonnage in the first instance, but   taking up cargo coasters only when Liner and Railway facilities are not procurable,MINISTRY OP SHIPPING.
EAST COAST SECTION Is concerned with the trading of cargo vessels within the limits given.It manages in conjunction with the Ministry of Shipping Coasting Trade Office, a fleet of 25 Interned and other steamers, and has In particular special interest In the London Coal Trade, the East &amp; South of England Coal,Trade, the trade to and from Orkney &amp; Shetland and the Channel Islands, and the conveyance by sea coastwise of Manganese Ore brought into the Thames from abroad, and other comm-odities such as Chalk, Cement, Roadstone, Pyrites, Jute etc.It has arranged tonnage for the conveyance of the New Potato Crop from Jersey, and Tomato traffic from the Channel Islands.WEST COAST SECTION looks after traffic on that side, andIn particular deals (In conduction with the Directorof Cross Channel Transportation) with vessels engaged Incarrying coal to Ireland and returning to the United Kingdomwith Irish Produce (Pitwood, Potatoes, Oats, Kelp, Burnt Oreetc.)It also deals with tonnage engaged in the Welsh Limestone trade, the Raasay Ore trade, the Bristol Channel Area, and to and from-Devon &amp; Cornwall.Together with Requisitioning Branch, it has made arrangements for the allocation of requisitioned tonnage for the Ministry of Pood&apos;s requirements   in the Stornoway Herring trade, the coal supply to Scottish and Irish Lights, the conveyance of Fabricated Steel for standard ships etc., and for the carriage on a freight basis of the Important supplies of coal for Railway purposes in Iceland,

</content>
</cab>
