<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/66/0 images: 405-415</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ej U (0( THI.&quot;&apos; DOCUMENT IS T!TE 1 Rl/iTiRTy. OF K13 BRITANNIC Iv.AJ.l&quot;STY1 S GOVERimiNT ,),SECRET.g.T.-5995..WAR   CABINET.DIRECTION OF ALLIED ACTION IN RUSSIA.Minutes of the 47th Meeting of the Military Repre-Bentatives, Supreme War Council, held in the Council Chamber, Versailles, on Monday, 7th October, 1918,at 11 hrs.. 3,0.PRESENT.PRANCE.GREAT BRITAIN.ITALY.AMERICA.General Maj-Gen.Ho.n. C.J..Belin, K.C.B..    Sackville-West,  C.i, .G.General General Lochridge,di Robilant,    representing C.M.G.     General Tasker H. Bliss, G.C.M.G.IN ATTENDANCE.Ma j or Lac ombe.Captain PortiorBrig-Gen, H.W. Studd, C.B..,  C.k.G.,  D.S.D.SECRETARIAT,Mpjor A.M.. Caccia, V- .V.O.Colonel. BusinelliCaptain A. Jones.Colonel Wallace. Lieut. Bedard,CHAIRl;&quot; ANGeneral Belin.DIRECTION 0? ALLIED ACTION IN RUSSIA. - .GENERAL BELIN said that, before beginning the discussion on the draft Joint Note, he wished to remind.the meeting of its relation to Joint Note No.37, concerning the general policy recommended for the Allies in the Autumn of 1918 and for the year 1919.   In that Joint Note certain portions of the text had been deliberately left vague.This- specially applied to Russia, concerning which the Military Representatives had only expressed the view that an Eastern front should be re-constituted both from the Northern ports and from Siberia and from  j the Caspian.   .The liaison between these various fronts had not yet been achieved.   He had,  therefore, thought it requisite to lay down the conditions in which each of the Allied Governments should participate towards effecting it.   , Hence the draft Note proposed.   .In it wore points of a diplomatic nature and others of a military. order.. -.As regards the diplomatic side, all French officials had roceived instructions from tho Ministry of Foreign Affairs.   But the president of the Council had written to say that &quot;by reason of the general interest of the question of Inter-Allied action in Russia and Siberia, and, of the necessity of a speedy understanding among the Entente powers on this question, it was, in his opinion, desirable that it should be considered as a whole by the Supremo tfar Council.at its next Meeting.&quot; The opinion of the Military Representatives was,therefore
therefore, asked, for; and he had sup- oned his colleagues in order - to obtain their views and with that purpose had submitted the draft Note in question.GI:.ERAL di ROBTLANT said that the Note contained no new matter but only d-. fined what had previously been said in justification of a despatch of troops which, by now, had already arrived.   His opinion had not changed and the draft iiotc was such that he was prepared to aecept . it without modification.QreS^AL SAOyVILLE-VEST said that he was in agreement withthe&quot;&quot;princieelc of -oo-ordination,       In the note, however, * it was suggested that 5 Battalions should be sent to Archangel,1 and, though he was ready to recognise that an error of judgement had been mode in previously opposing tli-.. despatch of these 5 Battalions, he wished to observe that he, personally, had only opposed it at the last meeting because the harshal Commanding the Allied Armies in prance had stated at that time that he was not able to furnish these 5 Battalions from his front.        This   &apos; had occurred on the 14th September.In the Note which had been withdrawn from the Agenda he noticed a statement that the I arshal on the 12th September had written to say that he was ready to give these 5 Battalions, and, further, that he considered  -the operation advantageous,    It followed that,  at the last faceting when agreeing that these troops could not be sent, he had not been in possession of correct information..   As nothing else was changed, he was, therefore, now disposed in favour of the despatch of these 5 Battalions since the j arshal v-ns no longer opposed to it.   The only other new point in the present draft was that France, in the character of the oldest Ally of Russia,  desired to take charge of the organisation of Russian forces in Siberia. &apos; To this he- raised no objection at all.Before proceeding further with the discussion, however, he thought it would be well to ask the American Representative to express his view,  as it might affect the acceptance of the I-Iote,   He had only been able to glance rapidly&apos;at General Bliss * memorandum, which appeared to study the case in great detail, and which, he thought,, should be read to the Meeting&apos;.GmlTRAh BEL IK said that,&apos; at the time the question was being discussed at the last meeting,, it was also being studied elsewhere.- French Officers who had returned from Russia had. . . . brought fuller and. more detailed information than had boonfurnished by General poole.     These Officers had had an inter view with the Larshal,. and., after this interview,, on the 12th September, the harshal had written that, in view&quot; of the important result which it seemed possible to bring about in northern Russia with small forces, he thought it would be advantageous to send straight from America to Archangel 5 Battalions &quot;of African troops.    In view of this opinion, it was suggested that the original advice should be modified.Gll^SriAL SAChVILLB-hEST said that he wished to point out that tho letter in question was dated, the 12th September and.that the previous Erecting of the &apos;; ilitary Representatives had been on the 14th.GLJgRAL ELLIN said this was so, but the letter had only been delivered after the Meeting of the 14th.   Had it arrived sooner, ho would have communicated it to his colleagues..   It was for this reason that, at. thy -opening- of this hceting, he had said that the previous i\ote had &quot;been based on incomplete information.   He. would ask General Lochridge to inform the Looting of the American point of view.GLNBRAL LOCKRIDGE
GEhrER;.L LOO&apos;:CRI DOE read the folio v. ing memorandum prepared &quot;by General Bli so ;-The American. 1-Hilary Representative is directed &quot;by his Government to present to his colleagues the following statement in regard to the drafts of the two Joint Notes und&apos;..r consideration at this Meeting of the i ilitary Representatives on the Supreme War Council.The Till&apos;, s of the Joint Notes and the objects which they propose to attain.1.   The drafts of the Joint Notes above referred to, are entitled, respectively;l0 L1 Orient ation de 1&apos;Action des Allies,en Russie; ?2Q Ronfore orient dts Contingents Allies d&apos;Arkhang-a) Thv first of thsse Notes relates1.   To a general policy to be pursued by tho Allies in Russia; and2.   To a contribution of additional forces for the Expedition operating from Archangel; end, in Siberia, to a participation by the united States in the occupation of the Trans-Siberian Railway and to assistance by the United States in a general policy of pacification of the country.b) The second of these Notes relates to:Thv reinforcement, as a matter of urgency, of the forces at Archangel by five additional American battalions.B*     The policy to be pursued in Russia by the United States.The Government of the United States has already cl&amp;arly outlined the only policy which it will pursue in Russia.a)   Under datt of .i,oy 28, 1918, the American Military * Representative was officially informed that his Government deolined to participate in military intervention via Vladivostock for the purpose of attempting to re-establish a Russian Western Front.   Repeated communications from Washington show the extreme reluctance with which that Government considered the proposition to send an *Expedition to Murmansk and Archangel; and when it agreed to take part in this Expedition it contributed its quota of troops for a very limited and very clearly defined purpose., -Under
- 4 - 3051)   Under date of July 22, 1918, tho American Military Representative received the full text of tho note delivered that day by his Government to the Ambassadors of Great Britain, Prance and Italy, -which hote contained a clear statement of the- military- policy that would be pursued, by the United States.   At various times sine, that date efforts hove been made by some of the European Allies to obtain from the Government of the United States a modification of that polioy that would bring it in lin, with the policy d:sired by the European Allies.     ileverth, less, all the official information received Up te this date by tho American Military Representative, from Washington, reiterates the deter-mination of thr-t Government to pursue its declared policy without rectification.     Of that fact the Amerioan Military Representative must take note and be guided accordingly.What is the Military polioy of the United States in respect to Russia, as declared in its Note tc thet hr u e Amb as s ad o r s ?a) With respect to the military intervention which had been proposed to it by the European Allies, the United States declines to either approve or to take part in such intervention.b) The United States agreed to send a small force to -Vladivostock for the purpose of helping the Czechs to get out of Russia and to steady any effort at Self-government or self-defence in which the Russians themselves may be vailing to accept assistance, but not to help any partyof Russians against any other party or against any form of Russian government or to help that government against thorn.-The United States agreed to send a small force to * the Northern Ports for the sole purpose of guarding mili-tary stores that might h. there and to make it safe for Russians to organise tIkmscircs there of their own free will, but not to help them fight against any form of Russian government cr against any other body of Russian people.And to. make more clear its polioy of non-inter ferone-., in Russian affairs the- United States has refused to permit any Russians,, either officers or soldi era -to take- service with its own troops. .Tho United States plainly states that it will &quot;go no further than these modest and experimental plans&quot;.The United States plainly declines &quot;to take part in organised intervention in adequate force- from either Vladivostock or &apos;] urmansk and Archangel&quot;.The United States plainly declares that it will &apos;3   be &quot;obliged to withdraw those forces in ord^r to add them to the. forces at the Western front if &quot;the plans in whose execution it is no-,  intended that they should co-operate should develop into others inconsistent with the policy to which the government of the United States feels con-- strained to restrict itself&quot;.But,   and I beg my oolleague-s to take careful not., of this,       tho government of the United States, in its declared policy says &quot;.* ith the utmtfst cordiality and good will that none of the conclusions hurt, stated ismeant
meant to wear tho least colour of criticism of what tho other governments associated against Germany may think it wis   to und.rtakc.    It wishes in nc e?y to embarrass their choice of policy.   All that is intended is a perfectly frank and definite statement of the policy which the United States feds obliged to adopt for itself and in tin uso of its own military forces.     Tho government of the United States de..- not wish it to be. understood that in sc restricting its.own activities it is seeking, even by implication, to set limits to the action of to define the policies of its associates.,:c)   Thus, it. appears that the United States, having reserved to itself the right to limit, as may seem to it wisw, the use pf its military forces,  and having plainly declared the limitations which it has imposed upon their use in Russia, nevertheless ham. s the Luropcan Powers with which it is associated in the ear against Germany absolutely free to form and carry out their policy, and Without further r- fer,.noe to tho government of the United States,c*     The proposition in the second of the. Joint Notesabove r-.. f erred t o^ to s e nd a re inf ore em e nt of five   , additional&quot; AmcrI&apos;cah batta 1 ions:-a)   &apos;hen the United States announced on July 22 its   v military policy with respect      Russia, it had already agreed to send three battalions to hurmrmsk and Archangel. It declared that this was the limit beyond which it would not go,  .Nevertheless, in the month of September one of the Allied Governments requested the United States to send tho same five battalions which are. again asked for in the draft of the Joint hote before the military Representatives. And this request ;* - s supported by the recommendation of the Marshal Cbmmandihg-in-Chief the Allied Armies in Fr.wa.oo, After full consideration of this request the President of the. United States, -on September 27, informed all tho European Allied Governments that the United States Govern-ment would send no more troops to North Russia,Conclusion.Prom the foregoing it. will bo evident to his colleagues why the, American Representative cannot join with them in a recommendation to his Government to asso-ciate itself with.their Governments in the execution of a policy in Russia which is opposed to the policy which it has solemnly declared to those Governments that it will pursue; and also why he. cannot .Join them in a recommendation for the sending of American reinforcements which his Government has repeatedly and recently declined to do.GENERAL. SACKVILLE-VEST
GENERAL SACKVILLE-WEST said that the conclusion of the document indicated that General Bliss as unwilling to sign the Joint Note for the reasons explained.

GENERAL di ? remarked that in the French draft Note the ? several important points which might be accepted without ? on the question which concerned the United States Government. According to General Bliss&apos; memorandum, President ? did not oppose our policy and left us free to pursue it, even without keeping him informed. He would, therefore, suggest, if his colleagues agreed, to sign the Joint Note after suppressing paragraph (b) which concerned the United States.

GENERAL BELIN suggested that the previous decision could be modified by stating that, in view of new circumstances, it was desirable to send the reinforcement of 5 battalions asked for. A reason opinion would this be given in modification of the previous resolution. He asked whether General Elise would sign the Note after the suppression of the paragraph concerning America.

GENERAL LOCHRIDGE said that he would have to submit this proposal to General Bliss.

GENERAL BELIN then proposed that General Lochridge be requested to submit the question to General Bliss. The Minutes would explain why mention of America was omitted from the Joint Note.

The Military Representatives accepted this proposal and requested General Lochridge to submit this question to General Bliss and to inform them of his reply.

(The Meeting was adjourned to allow General Lochridge to carry out his mission.)

The American Military Representative having stated that he was unable to sign the Joint Note for the reasons given in the memorandum quoted above, the French, British and Italian Military Representatives decided to sign the Note and to annex to it the memorandum of their American colleague.

(For text of Joint Note 38, see Appendix "A".)

 
9 ft 0o y oAPPENDIX &quot;AyDRAPT JOIN? 17QT5 No, 38.Joint Note to the Supreme War Council, by its Military Re-pr.. a* nta.tiv--s.pi ACTION OP ALLIED ACTION IN RUSSIA&quot; .To ; *tit&amp; supra &apos;: war council-.In Jeint Note Ho-. 37 the military Representatives - st.&apos; blished that one of th   principal aims of the Allies in Rub sir. was to form a new Eastern front, by ira ana of co-ordination&apos; and liaison between the actions undertaken in Northern Russia, Siberia and the Caucasus.According to the latest information available, on the Russian situation, it would appear that this liaison is still far from being achieved.     In fact,  the situation in the whole , of the Russian theatre has grown worse and demands all the attention of the Allies.In the North, of Russia, General poole is held up in hisadvance on Vologda and Viatka owing to insuffioiont r,source s.In central Russia the Czechs,  exhausted by the efforts they have maintained for so may months, arc -  beginning to weaken, and are in a critical situation..In the South Alexieffs forces aiw paralysed by hostile elements surrounding them on every side,Under such conditions as these., the Allied effort may prove- fruitless.   It is therefore desirable, in order to guard o;gainst this dangere1, That the Entente should, without delay take thenecessary measures to ensure by the three available routes (Northern Russia, Siberia and Southern Russia) liaison between the various intervening forces and the Czech Army, -the sole centre- of resistance around which the loyal Russian elements can be. rallied.. -2, That tin  contribution of each of th. Allies to thecommon purpose, in Ruoai;  should be. clearly d-. termmed.The situation being thus defined, the British, Prench and Italian hilitary Representatives /   are. of opinionA.   As/The- American Hilitary Representative did not feel able to approve of thi opinion expressed for the reasons given in Annexurc to this Note,.
4&apos;Vi   Ab r- gards the first point, th* t it would he advisablo :-(a) That the Archangel force he increased by the I                 few thousand men (5 battalions) asked for by GeneralPoole.(b) That Allied forces on th. Trans-Siberian Railway be pushed forward ao quickly as possible to relievo the Czechs and allow them, on the one hand, to advance very rapidly on Samara to gain contact with   * Alcxicff*s forces,  and, on the other hand, to advance to Ekaterinburg so as to join hands with tho Archangel force.(c) To move en the Caspian Sea and South Russia so as tc r. ccue th.se regions from Germano-Turkish sway;IV As regards the contribution of each Ally to the common acTi o rfi n&quot; Ru fl s i a.     &apos;     &apos;that it would be the duty of the(a) Engli shTo continue to- direct operations in Northern Russia until the establishment of an effective liaison via Vologda and Viatka with the Catcch elements which aro   . operating near these regions.To undertake- by moans of contributions from the Mesopotamia an Force the ncacssary action towards the Caspian Se v. and Southern Russia.,(b) FrenchTc assume effective control of the Czech Army, in accordance with the agreement reached with the Czech National Council.In their capacity as the oldest Ally of Russia, to organise,and, with the help of the other Powers, to take charge of the Russian forces in course of \formation,(c) &apos; Japanese,To push rapidly along the Trans-Ofcberian Railway their * own and the Allied troops under their command.To plac in echelon behind the Czech Army, which ie to&quot; be r.-formed and - nabled to intervene epc- illy, ouch forces as ar   r-. quir- d to support it in cos-, of need. &apos;Military Military MilitaryReprtse ntativV Re pros-, ntativc., Re pr esentative,French Section, British Section, Italian Section,jj., Supreme Jar Supreme War Supreme WarCouncil. x        Council. Council.
SUPREME WAR COUNCIL.   , AMERICAN SECTION, VERSAILLES. October 6th, 1918.., The American Military Representative is directed by his Government to present to his colleagues the following . statement in regard to the drafts of the two Joint Notes under consideration at this meeting of the Military Representatives on the Supreme Y/ar Council.A.       The Titles of the Joint Notes and the objects which they propose to attain.1. The drafts of the Joint Notes above referred to, are entitled, respectively:l0   L&apos;Orientation de l&apos;Action des Allies&apos;en Russie;20   Renforcement ees Contingents Allies d&apos;Arkhangelsk.a) The first of these notes relates1.   To a general policy to be pursued by the Allies in Russia; and- 2&apos;.   To a-contribution of additional forces for*be Expedition operating from Archangel; and, in .Siberia, to a participation by the United States in the occupation cf the Trans-Siberian Railway and to assistance by the United States in a general policy of paci-fication cf the country.b) The second of these Notes relates to:The reinforcement, as a matter cf urgency, of the forces at Archangel by five additional American battalions&apos;.3.    &apos;The-policy to be pursued in Russia by the United StatesLThe. Government cf the United States has already olearly outlined, the only policy which it. will pursue in Russia.a) .. Under date cf May 28.&apos;, 1918, the American Military Representative was officially informed that his Government declined, to participate in military intervention&quot;viaVIadivostock for the purpose of attempting to re-establish a Russian Western Front.   Repeated communications from Washington show the extreme reluctance with which that Government considered&apos; the proposition, to send an Expedition.&apos;&quot; to Murmansk and Archangel; and&apos; when it agreed to take part in this Expedition it contributed its quota of troops for a very limited and. very clearly defined purpose.b) Under date of July 22, i&apos;918, the American Military Representative received the.full text of the note delivered that day by his Government to the Ambassadors of Great Britain,Prance
9 1 1 tullfrance and italy, which note contained a clear statement of the military policy that would &quot;be pursued by the united states. at various times since that date efforts have been made by some of the european allies to obtain from tho government cf the united states a modification of that polioy that would bring it in line with the policy desired by the european allies. nevertheless, all the official information received up to this date by the american military representative, from washington reiterates the determination of that government to pursue its declared policy without modification.   of that fact the american military representative must take note and be guided accordingly.what is the military policy of the united states in respect to russia, as declared in its mote to the three ambassadors ?a) with respect to the military intervention which had been proposed to it by the european allies, the united states&apos; declines to either approve cr to take part in such intervention.b) the united states agreed to send a small force tc vladivostock for the purpose of helping the czechs to get out tf russia and to steady any effort at self-government or self-defence in which the russians themselves may be willing tc accept assistance, but not to help any party of russians against any other party cr against any for:&quot;; of russian govern-ment or to help that government against them.the united states agreed to send a small force to the northern ports for the sole purpose of guarding military stores that might be there and to make it safe for russians to organise themselves there of their o&apos; n free will, but not to help them fi$it against any form cf russian government or against any other body of russian people.and to make more clear its policy of non-interference in russian affairs the united states has refused to permit-any russians, either officers or soldiers, to take service with its own troops.the united states plainly states that it v.ill &quot;go no further than these modest and experimental plans.&quot;the united states plainly declines &quot;to take part in organised intervention in adequate force from either vladivostock or murmansk and archangel.&quot;the united states plainly declares that it rill-be &quot;obliged to withdraw those forces in order to add them tc the forces at the western front if the plans in &quot;whose execution it is no-- intended that they should co-operate should develop into others inconsistent with the policy to which the government of the united states feels constrained to restrict itself.&quot;but, - - and i bey my colleagues to take careful note of&apos; this, --&quot;the government cf the united states, in its declared policy says &quot;with the utmost cordiality and good will that none of the conclusions here stated is meant to wear the least colour of criticism of what the other governments associated against germany may think it wise to undertake.   it wishes in no way to embarrass their choice Of policy.   all that is intended is a perfectly frank anddefinite
definite statement of the policy which tho United States feels obliged to adopt for itself and in the use cf its om military forces.   The Government cf the United States does not wish it to be understood that in so restricting its own activities it is seeking, even by implication, to set limits to the action Or to define the policies cf its associates.&quot;&quot;t)   Thus, it appears that the United St ate 3, having reserved to itself the right to limit, as may seem to it wise, the use cf its military forces, and having plainly declared the limitations&apos;which it has imposed upon their use in Russia, nevertheless leaves the European pavers with which it is associated in the --*ar against Germany absolutely free to form and carry out their policy, and without further reference to the Government of the United States.C*        The proposition in tho second of the Joint Notes above referred to7*&quot;&quot;t 0 send a re inf ore omen t of five additional Ame rican ba11ali cns.a) when the United States announced on July 22 its military policy with respect to Russia, it had already agreed to send three ba/ttalions to Murmansk and Archangel.   It declared that this was the limit beyond which it would not go.Nevertheless, in the month of September cne of the Allied Governments requested the United States to send the same five battalions which are again asked for in the draft cf the Joint Note before the Military Representatives.   And this request was supported by the recommendation cf the Marshal Command!ng-in-Chief the Allied Armies in Prance. After full consideration of this request the president of the United States, on September 27, informed all the European Allied Governments that the United States Government would send no more troops to North Russia.,   Conclusion.Prom the foregoing it will be evident to his colleagues why the American Military Representative cannot join with them in a recommendation to his Government to associate itself with, their Governments in the execution of a policy in Russia which is opposed tc the policy which it has solemnly declared to those Governments that it will pursue; and. also why he cannot join with them in a recommendation for the sending of American reinforcements which his Government has repeatedly and recently declined to do.

</content>
</cab>
