<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/1/49 images: 678-683</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYrS GOVERNMENT.o /jRBTi. Copy No.     &apos;X &apos;...(G) (39) h9.WAR CABINET.DIVERSION OF SHIPPING.Memorandum &quot;by the Minister of Supply.At their meeting on 1k.th October,  (War Cabinet47(39) Cone.6) the War Cabinet discussed a memorandum by theMinister of Transport on the diversion of shipping from theEast Coast to the West Coast (W.P.(G)  (39) 35).Whilst I am unable to assess the importance of the strategical reasons for the diversion,, I feel bound to pointout that any diversion on a large scale will have serious effects on the production of essential materials in thecountry, and more particularly on their cost and the rate of output.Among the cargoes to be diverted in the near futureare two shiploads of iron ore consigned to Middlesborough, andtwo shiploads of newsprint paper consigned to London.      It isproposed to unload the iron ore at Barrow and to transportit by rail to Middlesborough.      This will add considerably to the cost of the ore and eventually therefore to the costof steel made from it.      Moreover I fear that if diversion of this kind is continued for long the rail transport system will be quite unable to cope with the additional traffic.In normal times some 2,000,000 tons of iron ore are importedannually to the Middlesborough district by sea direct andthere is now need, fhv still greater imports.     All our steelplants must work to their full capacity and continuously if our needs are to be met.Representations have also reached me in regard tonewsprint paper.      It has been possible for the importers of -one of the cargoes to take the paper at plants printing-associated papers in the West;    but the other cargo is to/be

be unloaded at Liverpool and railed to London at a costof  2 a ton for the journey.These are, of course, only examples.     among other heavy raw materials which are normally brought to theEast Coast in large quantities are wood pulp, phosphaterock (for fertiliser), pyrites (for sulphuric acid),timber and bauxite.(Initld.)       E.L.B.The Adelphi,20th October, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
