<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/40/12 images: 124-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   August 1943.The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.   It is issued for the personal use of cj^e^^^r^r^. ^^^^rr^ri^&apos;&apos;MOST SECRET. Copy NoW.P. (43) 362.9th August, 1943.WAR CABINET.TRADE DISPUTES AND TRADE UNION ACT, 1927.BY direction of the Prime Minister, I circulate the following verbatimReport of the Deputation which he received from three Civil Service Unions.*(Signed) E. E. BRIDGES,Secretary of the War Cabinet.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,9th August, 1943.TRADE DISPUTES AND TRADE UNION ACT, 1927.Verbatim Report of Deputation received by the Prime Minister at no. 10, Downing Street, at 12-30 p.m. on 3rd August, 1943: The Prime Minister.Postmaster-General.Mr. Harvie Watt.Mr. Rowan.Present:Civil Service Clerical Association.Mr. McMillan, President.Mr. White, Secretary.Post Office Engineering Union.Mr. Power, President.Mr. Edwards, General Secretary.-  Inland Revenue Staff Federation.Mr. Jagger, President.Mr. Houghton, Secretary.PRIME MINISTER : I have with me the Postmaster-General and myParliamentary Private Secretary and my own Private Secretary.I am very glad to receive the Deputation because I felt, in all the circum-stances which Mr. Bevin put to me, that you would like to be personally received as the contact between the Head of the Government and the Civil Service is.especially close.I thought the best arrangement would be for us to have a talk, and after-wards we will have an agreed report as to what should be put out. We shall not put out a verbatim report; the papers would not take it, and it is better that the* See W.M. (43), 107th Conclusions, Minute 4.[258&apos;99] b
more important parts of anything that is said should gain prominence in viewof the limited space that is available to the papers.Woud you like to make any remarks to me ?Mr. HOUGHTON : Yes, Sir. First of all,&quot; may I say that we are verygrateful indeed to you for receiving us. We are very sensitive to the calls on your time, and we know how many grave responsibilities you have to shoulder justnew, but we did feel that probably we had something to contribute something that might be helpful.First of all, may I say that we are not sure that.we are anxious for any statement to be made at all. Perhaps we could think about that before we part,because we are rather anxious for this to be an informal talk in which we couldbe perfectly frank with you from our side; and we are not at all sure that weare anxious for any statement to be made to the Press.The three organisations that come here this morning were all affiliated tothe Trades Union Congress before the Trade Union and Trade Disputes Act1927. We could have come with representatives from other influential bodies in the Civil Service, and they would have been very glad to be with us, but we felt that the suggestion we have to make to you might possibly involve our intervention with the Union of Post Office Workers or with the Trades UnionCongress, of both of them, and having regard to the fact that we were affiliatedto the Congress we thought perhaps it would be better if our delegation were confined to those who had that particular and intimate interest in this problem.The next thing to say is where we stand on this matter. Ever since theTrade Union and Trades Disputes Act 1927 we have been very anxious indeed,for what we feel to be almost punitive legislation to be altered. We felt veryhard done by after 1926 to be quite frank, because we did not feel that what had happened then merited the legislation which was ultimately passed asregards the affiliation of Civil Service bodies to the Trades Union Congress;but be that as it may, time has gone by since then, and the whole of the CivilService Staff Associations are undoubtedly united in their wish that some modification should be made in the present position. It is not entirely basedon spiritual grounds if I may put it that way, it is not only an interest infreedom for freedom&apos;s sake, although the spiritual side of this problemundoubtedly affects a number of people who are in favour of some modificationof the law even though they would not wish to take any advantage of any facilitiesit offered. There is, however, essentially a practical side to this. The CivilService is one of the largest war industries; there are more people, permanent and temporary, in the direct employ of the Crown at the present time than there are in the mines or on the railways, and we feel we are an essential partof the war effort, Government administration being as important a war industry as any. The Trades Union Congress, very rightly and properly no doubt, inpresent circumstances is consulted at every touch and turn by His Majesty&apos;sGovernment or by Ministers; all questions such as call up, workmen&apos;s compensa-tion, Essential Work Orders, welfare arrangements, changes in the ContrioutoryPensions Acts everything that has any semblance of a bearing, direct or indirectupon the general welfare and interest of the workers is a matter of consultationwith the Trades Union Congress. We have no part in that consultation. Weonce went to see Mr. Bevin on a particular Civil Service aspect of some general arrangements which had been fixed up with the Trades Union Congress, and we feel very keenly indeed that we ought to have a share in the consultation which takes place between the Government and the representative body of workers. Atthe present moment we are excluded. Nobody consults us on the broad questionsof policy affecting projected legislation or the Statutory Rules and Orders, orwhatever it may be. We only come into the picture when the general principleshave been settled between the T.U.C. and the Government and we are then onlyconsulted on the purely Civil Service aspects of them and that, we do not think,is good enough, especially as we have half a million temporary Civil Servantswho have a very close relationship indeed to the general standards of wages andconditions of service of people outside. When we meet to discuss with theGovernment, with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, it may be, questions affectingGivil Service remuneration, all the time there is this cross-reference to outsideconditions in which we have no part, in which we have no consultation and thereis no doubt that the whole Civil Service does stand behind this, believing that something should be done.PRIME MINISTER : You have other, much more direct, contacts with theGovernment. ,
Mr. HOUGHTON : Yes, Sir, but not on matters and at the time when theTrade Union Congress are helping to form policy. That is where we feel adeprivation, not being able to share with the T.U.C. this broad basis of con-suitation on matters which undoubtedly affect our own interests and determineour own conditions.That is where we stand, and the question is, what is to be done? We believethat we may be able to offer some contribution towards a solution. The Unionof Post Office Workers have taken a certain step, and the Trades Union Congresshave indicated their own attitude towards that step. - We on this side of the table have not taken the same step. Throughout the years, strongly as we have felt about it, we have been anxious to follow the strict constitutional line, andwe make no virtue of the fact that we have not done as the U.P.W. have done;it did not occur to us that would be a possible remedy. At the same time, thatstep having been taken by one Union, you can understand that we are all putin an embarrassing position. Pressure is very strong behind us; we are beingdriven very hard by people who feel the time has come for this ban on affiliationto the T.U.C. to be lifted, and there is very strong pressure upon us to follow the line which the U.P.W. have taken. So far we. have been able to avert com-plicating the whole situation by doing the same as the U.P.W.The question is this. Can we be of any service in this situation ? If therewere solid enough hope that if the decks were cleared of any alleged provocation,which has so far been taken up by one of the Civil Service Unions -if it would help to resolve this problem we are prepared to intercede with the other parties concerned. We do not under-estimate the difficulty and delicacy of the task which we should be prepared to attempt, but it does occur to us that the presentdeadlock may be an obstacle rather than anything else to a common course ofaction which the Government might feel disposed to propose to Parliament. Ifthe hope was solid enough we do not ask for any undertaking, clearly that wouldbe improper for us to ask but if there is anything that you can give us whichwould encourage us to intervene with the T.U.C. and the U.P.W. in the hopethat we might prevail upon them to either withdraw the application for affiliationin the case of the U.P.W. or modify the attitude of the General Council of theT.U.C., we are prepared to have a shot at it. If, as I say, you could give us any encouragement to do that it would mean we should have to be taken on trustby these bodies and they might feel that we really had not anything to offer them,but we are prepared to do our level best if you can give us enough hope on which to make, the attempt.That is the practical proposition that we make in the hope that it maycontribute something. If, on the other hand, there appears to be no hope in thepresent circumstances of any step being taken by the Government to let-up &quot;on affiliation with the T.U.C. by Civil Service bodies, clearly our position asintercede!s would be quite impossible, we should be bound to fail. We are not certain that we should succeed even with the strongest grounds for hope, but we felt that to take this step is our clear duty if we can take it in the present circum-stances. It would also help towards averting what may be the extraordinarilydifficult position in which we ourselves may be put because of the pressure ofthe people behind us, and on this side of the table we sit with varying degrees ofintensity of the pressure behind us to follow the line of the U.P.W. or to amend the rules to permit of affiliation and that sort of thing.That is the best we can offer you in this situation. It is, we hope, somethingtangible. It is a step which none of us could take without feeling very strongly that we must attempt it in the interests of the removal of difficulties which may otherwise prove to be very troublesome. None of us wants to get involved indisputes on this sort of thing at this crucial stage of the war, and the Govern-ment do not want to be troubled unnecessarily with difficulties of this kind, andfor anything that you can say to us that will enable us to make the move that wehave come here prepared to make, we shall be very grateful indeed.PRIME MINISTER : This is of course a very serious matter, Mr. Houghton,because anything which caused a rift between the Civil Service and the Govern-ment would be deplorable; and also, anything which caused a rift in the greatdemocratic, national forces which are marching steadily on towards the finalvictory over Fascism and Nazism, and not only that but over the wicked powers that have laid the world in this violent confusion and suffering.I know a good deal about this story, as you know, and the position is very different from what it was on the morrow of the General Strike, I quite agree.I have always approached this request for an alteration in the law with the sense of comradeship which I have with the Trades Unions and our colleagues in the[25899] . b 2
Trades Unions who are fighting side by side with us; and I can assure you thatit is not out of any lack of goodwill or out of any slavish regard for consistencythat I have found myself hitherto unable to do anything. We have had longtalks with the Trades Union Leaders and with Sir Walter Citrine and others,and, as you know, I wrote to Sir Walter a letter on the 2nd September, 1942,after various negotiations and informal testing of opinion. You have that letter in your minds.Mr. HOUGHTON : Yes.PRIME MINISTER : I do not need to read that out again, but it says, &quot; Iam especially anxious that nothing should be done to impair the national unityas also the good relationship between the Government and the Trades UnionCongress. I will gladly avail myself, if unity can be maintained, of any opportunity that arises of considering the matter further, but, in the absence ofagreement, I feel that the national interest would best be served by your refraining from pressing the matter at the present time.&quot; That was the position which we took up, and now of course, as you realise, nothing can be done without legislation ....Mr. HOUGHTON : No.PRIME MINISTER : . . . . and legislation depends upon Parliament, bothHouses of Parliament. You have to pass the legislation though, and I naturally,being head of the largest Party in Parliament, which has a very great majority,have to make enquiries to find out in every way what would be the chances of such legislation. I am absolutely sure that, even if the matter were discussed only on its merits, there would be very great differences. People would say, &quot; It is a greatpity to introduce Party affiliations into the Civil Service,&quot; they would say &quot; Itis a great pity that they should be, as it were, considering themselves otherthan as servants -of the State &apos;&apos;; they would say &apos;&apos; It would be a great pity if it came to something like what happened in other countries, that promotions andadvantages go with changes of Government,&quot; and so on. All these argumentswould be put forward, and, of course, this only applies to permanent establishedpensionable Civil Servants, who are a class who render most responsible andinvaluable services to the State, but who are certainly a privileged class, in thematter of security which is thought so much of, compared with those who work inthe ordinary labour market, in the ordinary rough and tumble of life; and it hasalways been held that special conditions require special obligations in this matter.It has been held since this Act was passed. But all this would be brought up, Ido not say that in order to argue the merits, but merely to show that there wouldbe very serious arguments deployed, and I cannot help thinking that, even if a bill were introduced by the Government, it would cause very great disturbance andconfusion in people&apos;s minds, and weaken the solidarity of our array at a timewhen, as everyone can see, our affairs are somewhat better off than they were alittle while ago.That being so, I found it impossible to promise Sir Walter Citrine any positive legislation in my letter of the 2nd September, and there the matter stood.But now it has all been very much complicated by the declaration of intention onthe part of the Union of Post Office Workers to break the law as it stands, and ofthe T.U-C. to assist them in it. That really has brought the question into a very unsatisfactory atmosphere, and I am unable to advance at all beyond my letterof the 2nd September in any way at the present time, because it would undoubtedly be said that we had yielded to this threat of breaking the law; and there is not much time. I thought it was a mistake, if I may say so, to make that threat.There have been three General Elections since this Bill was passed, there has beena Labour Government in power, or at least in Office, and there pro^bably will beLabour Governments in power in the future, and it is a very proper matter onwhich everyone should use his rights as a citizen in every way to get the lawchanged. It is quite true that sometimes people think that sectional interests arenot able to get their full consideration at Elections, but the Trades Unions form amost important and influential body in our life, and really I should have thoughtthat, if there was any serious grievance behind it, or a great sense of injury, theywould have used their influence more in the various Elections which have takenplace in the past than they did. At any rate, it would be quite open to them to use it to the full in the future when we have an Election.Now this particular threat, to break the law, I think is unnecessary becausethe laws are made by the people and can be changed by the people when they choose,and there is not any need for that threat; but, as I said, the time is now very short,
and there is no possibility of any legislation before the Trades Union Congressmeet in September; Parliament is.soon separating and even if it was not soonseparating there is not the slightest prospect of it being prepared to take any newposition on this subject while this threat hangs over them.. As I say, my feeling-has been less that of logic than of being very anxious that we should all go onworking together until these great tyrannies are overthrown; but there is not the slightest possibility at the present time of any change in the situation being effected by legislation, and therefore I really ought I am really bound to put before you some of the consequences which would follow.You three Unions have strictly adhered to the constitutional position, but,supposing that the U.P.W. persist in their course and the T.U.C. endorse it, theposition under the law is inescapable. The Government have no choice in thematter, the application of the law is automatic and absolutely clear. If a Unionof which established Civil Servants are members becomes affiliated to the T.U.C.the result follows that the warning contemplated by the Act must be given to everyestablished Civil Servant who is a member of the Union. If at the end of one month thereafter that established Civil Servant has not resigned his membership ofthe Union, he automatically becomes disqualified from being a member of the CivilService, and thereupon all his accumulated pension rights are forfeited. I should think that everybody ought to have that clearly in their minds, because somethingmay be done in the matter which would bring that into operation, and there wouldbe no means of altering it, because I do not think that Parliament would interveneat all at the present time. The Government are bound to make this position clear to Civil Servants, and I think it is also the duty of the Civil Service organisationsat least to let their members knowr how they stand. It is not only a matter of this very serious issue, but of course litigation may be set on foot by members of a union in regard to what they would consider the effect upon their rights and interests, and then you would be involved in all the endless business of the courts and tangles of the law and worries of that kind, which would be most unfortunate.Therefore I do not feel that you should leave your members in any doubt about it;the most clear warning would have to be given, and ought to be given, so that people know exactly what it is they are doing. I cannot conceive that a large mass of the Civil Servants, who are a most responsible, provident, stable, patrioticclass in the General Strike only 40 out of 200,000 were found to have infringedat all the rules of the Service I cannot possibly think that they would wish to belet in for this kind of thing which will affect their position so much and do no endof harm to them individually, and to their whole position as a class; I cannot think they would wish to be let in for that if they knew, and they ought to know andthey will have to be told, and you should tell them that very clearly. I was verymuch surprised to read in the papers Sir Walter Citrine&apos;s statement, but I knew the moment it was made it put us in a most difficult situation, and made any chance of ameliorating the position far more difficult.Now I have to be very careful not to say anything from which afterwards itcould be suggested that I had, in the face of this threat of breaking the law, heldout hopes or made promises different from what would have been held out or madein the ordinary discussions which always take place between us under our broadly-based system of government. I have to be extremely careful. If I were to do that I should get very.much censured by public opinion and by Parliament, and,therefore, while I was very anxious that you should not feel cut off at all from me,and anxious to receive and see you, I asked Mr. Bevm to tell you that it did not follow that I should be able to say anything which would be satisfactory to you,and I am afraid I am not in a position to do so. There cannot be any legislation at the present time, and therefore you really must take account of the situationwhich might arise so rapidly and endeavour to bring those facts before yourmembers.I am very distressed about the whole situation. I wish it had not beenbrought forward in this way at this time. Undoubtedly Ave shall come to a period when there will be a General Election, but not now; we could not do it, everybodyis so scattered; but afterwards, when the war is over and we get to a breathing space, the very earliest reasonable breathing space where we can conduct an election, there will have to be a newr Parliament. The nation has endorsed theaction that there should not be an Election under the present circumstances but,as I say, one will come, undoubtedly, and there, is the time for you to press forwhatever changes you think fit. .&apos; I must say I should be very glad if it were in my power to do something which removed from your breasts anything in the nature of, as you say, a stigma,but I did not myself consider that this was in any way particularly a stigma.  It125899] &apos;. b 3
seems that established Civil Servants ought to keep free from political movements,and it is pretty well understood how it works. I certainly had not thought it wasa stigma. Still, it was legislation which was passed on the morrow of a veryfierce industrial and constitutional dispute, and apparently it has rankled all these years. I feel very much indeed the comradeship of pur Trades Union colleagues,and I hate to think that those who are marching with us should feel a prick intheir hearts if it can be removed without detriment to the public. But I am notin a position to take any step at the present moment beyond what I have put inthe letter which I wrote to Sir Walter Citrine on the 2nd September, 1942. IfI did it would, I think, entail all kinds of very serious evils, bickerings andquarrels, and it would not be in the public interest. Therefore I do hope thatyou will try your very best to find a way out of this deadlock. I do not like to seegood people get into deadlock with each other. We are all good people and wedo not want to get into deadlocks when we are working together. Undoubtedlythis is a matter which should be dealt with wdien an Election comes. I am not//saying that if an agreement could be reached on any point before the Election it\\ could not be dealt with, but I must not allow myself to hold out any hopes orI expectations at the present time. All I can say is that I do trust you will see&apos; our difficulties as well as your own, and that you will make sure that your peopleunderstand that what will happen might happen quite quickly, and the mostvexatious difficulties arise out of which it might not be possible it would not bepossible, I think for the Government, the executive Government, or Parliamentto help you. I am sorry if what I have said is not very satisfying, but at anyrate I have to put the case frankly I hope I have done it courteously t,o you,and beg you to think of your interests and our interest the common interest inevery step you take. You have great influence on the other Civil Service Unions,and I would be very glad indeed if we could reach some agreement, but I couldnot undertake at the present time to make any sort of promise, or hold out anyhopes, which you could use in regard to the other Unions.If anyone would like to say anything, I am entirely ready to listen.Mr. WHITE : Would what you have said apply to a modification as distinct from a repeal ? The Section deals with two things political and industrialaffiliation. We are primarily concerned now with industrial affiliation and notwith political affiliation.PRIME MINISTER : All those things I should be very glad to talk over,but I cannot talk over them under the shadow of this threat, I assure you itwould prejudice all chance of getting anything through Parliament if it were thought it were done in that way. - You mean that the Unions would be affiliatedin respect of their industrial aspects and not affiliated in respect of their political aspects mr. WHITE : Yes.PRIME MINISTER : All that might be very helpful. You should openthat with Mr. Beyin, who has been in close touch with you. I am far fromwishing to bang, bar and bolt doors at all in this matter, as I said many years ago.Mr. EDWARDS : Mr. Power and I represent the telephone men. It is notmy business to talk of how the U.P.W. took decisions, but you asked that weshould tell our members quite frankly everything about this. We did that; wepresented to our Conference a complete report which showed every legal penalty,quite plainly, and we circulated that to all our members in general. In spite ofthat, our Annual Conference, with some difficulty, with.the Platform unitedlyopposing was prevented from instructing the Executive to apply for affiliationat once, and then only on the understanding that we would take what to us isthe correct procedure for determining these things, to endeavour to amend ourRules. The representatives of 50,000 telephone men, having all the facts put-in front of them as plainly as they could be put, nevertheless took this contraryview. In other words, you must be aware that those behind us; many of them,at least the active ones who come to Conferences, are saying, &quot; Whatever the penalties, we will take them rather than be debarred from close affiliation withthe T.U.C.&quot;The second thing I want to say is that, quite frankly, my work as general secretary of my Union would be quite impossible if I did not every day in spiritbreak this 1927 Act, as I could not do my work without having the closest possiblecontact with the T.U.C. Government Departments send me to. the T.U.C. todiscuss matters where the T.U.C. is advising the Government, and so on. I justcould not go on.   It is only a matter of chance that the telephone men happen
to be State employees; they might, not be. In some matters they are not; and whatever may be the merits of this case for higher Civil Servants, when it comes to the linesman who earns  3 a week.....PRIME MINISTER: Does not that tend to show that as a matter of practice it is working fairly smoothly at the present time? The question for meis legislation. That is my difficulty. Changing the law is a regular process,and we have to see the forces which would be ranged on each side. There is noobjection at all to your having the most intimate relations with the T.U.C. in a friendly way. I have very friendly relations with them myself, and we are allvery good friends, but where the letter of the law is infringed there would bedanger, and that can only be put right by passing a Bill through the First and second Readings, Committee, Report and Third Reading and through bothHouses, and that is an occasion which would give opportunity for an immenseamount of bickering and division which would be very harmful. I do not think could force it through Parliament even if I tried. &apos; ,Mr. POWER : If the application by the U.P.W. to the Trades UnionCongress for affiliation were withdrawn, and the T.U.C. would agree that onlyindustrial affiliation were requested, could you give any encouragement then atall that there would be likely to be ... .PRIME MINISTER : Once you were away from the threat I should be.very glad to talk all these matters over, but I cannot go beyond my limitationsat the present moment.Mr. POWER : If the application to the T.U.C. by the U.P.W. was to be withdrawn and we confined our application or suggested that in any legislation which the Government were prepared to introduce it should be strictly on theunderstanding that it was industrial affiliation, would that in any way give youan opportunity of, say, encouraging us to hope that something might be done?PRIME MINISTER: I should like to think about that in a clearatmosphere. If that had been brought up before the threat was used, I wouldcertainly have set to work to see what could be done. I have not looked into it,but in principle one can see that one can draw a line between the objectionablepart, which is the political association with one particular Party that is fightingelections, and the industrial aspect.Mr. POWER : I am Chairman of the Council of the Post Office Engineering-Union. I am a workman in the Post Office, and a member of that Union and Iwork in the Post Office, and consequently, on each and every occasion when we goto the Post Office to discuss wages and conditions of service, we must of necessity,in order to comply with the Post Office requirements, go to the very Union withwhich we are not allowed to affiliate, because we are compared with. outsideindustry; and therefore we find the greatest difficulty in working side by side with,say, a man working from Callender&apos;s Cable Company, both working together, one from the Post Office and the other from the Union.PRIME MINISTER : People whose affairs are all mixed in with yours ?Mr. POWER : Yes.PRIME MINISTER: We are all on the legal point, really. In substance,intimate association prevails, but I agree with what you said, that there is avery marked distinction between the political association and the industrialaffiliation. What one does not like about the political affiliation is that peoplethink it brings Party politics into the day-to-day life of the Civil Service, theywould say &quot; These are our men, and those are their men,&quot; and it would poisonthe impartial relationship now prevailing. Our Civil Service is the glory of thecountry, and one of the sources of our great, strength; its cleanliness as comparedwith other countries is tremendously marked and I would not like to see theService infected by Party. Here I am getting into merits. On the industrialaspect I am bound to say it seems to me there is a valuable distinction, but I mustnot use this as a means of inducing you to take any particular action.What do you.say on this, Postmaster-General&apos;?POSTMASTER-GENERAL : I agree with you that we cannot discuss meritson the present situation..PRIME MINISTER : Is this suggestion of separating the industrial fromthe political aspects a new point ?
POSTMASTER-GENERAL : I think it has been in mind before; I do notthink this is the first time it has been raised. I think you have ventilated it inyour newspaper, have not you ?Mr. POWER : We ourselves have pressed the point for industrial affiliation.Mr. WHITE : It has never before been put forward formally at all.Hitherto the plea has been made for the repeal of Section 5 of the Trades union and Trade Disputes Act, which is an all-embracing Section, and I think, there-fore, the distinction between the political and the industrial affiliation is fairlyrecent so far as the staffs own wishes are concerned.Mr. McMILLAN : Before we came here, and for some weeks, we have tried to assess your personal difficulty in this situation, and it is pretty clear from yourstatement this morning that a good part of your difficulty lies in the reactions, as you assess them, of the different political line-ups in relation to this question.PRIME MINISTER : Yes.Mr McMILLAN : You quite plainly foresee bickerings and the rest of it inan attempt to put forward legislation. It is also clear that yon had in mind the repeal, or such amendment of the legislation as would embrace both political andindustrial affiliation.PRIME MINISTER : Yes.Mr. McMILLAN : In view of what we have said and we put the emphasisall on the industrial affiliation does your estimate of this difficulty still remainwhere it is. or would you say it could be modified ?PRIME MINISTER : I should like to put it to my colleagues. We have very good colleagues leaders of Trades Unions, and others and I should like toput the matter to them. But you should not go to the others and say &quot; Take acertain course,&quot; or &quot; Abstain from a certain course because the Prime minister is going to do this, that or the other.&quot; It is for you, you see. You can putforward proposals. We are bound to consider them. We are not looking forquarrels God forbid; we are looking only to smooth things over. It is a very different atmosphere from the morrow of 1926 or 1927. The Trade Unions are agreat pillar of the country. I have been in favour of all who have advocated the repeal of the Osborne Judgment, in my Radical days. And I must say that you have this always to say, that the Civil Service Unions did not take a partimproperly in that General Strike; they sympathised, they did what they were entitled to, but they did not take part. They kept to their service to the Stateand carried on. As I said, there were only 40 out of 200,000. Now the atmosphere is extremely good; there never was a time when it was so good in thiscountry; we are the most united country in the world; and that is why I thoughtit such a pity that this thing should have come up. I would like to bring beforethe Cabinet this point which you have raised as to the possibility of distinguishing between the political and the industrial aspects. Now you have mentioned it Ithink I am bound to state it to my colleagues. I would not like you to go away and come back and say, &quot; You have &apos; sold us a pup.&apos; You encouraged falsehopes.&quot; I do not want to do that. I would rather you said, &quot; There you are;you gave us nothing.&quot; It is much better to be frank in Britain; people like that,and the other is not any good. I do not like double-edged formulas which meandifferent things to other people. I will bring this, to me, new point to the noticeof my colleagues, and see whether it introduces any new factor; but anyhownothing can happen before September.Mr. McMILLAN : No; but there is a point, if I may put it; and it might help. Quite frankly, it was our hope that arising out of this visit we might be putin a position to go to the T.U.C. and the U.PW. and, from what you told us thismorning, be in a position to persuade them to withdraw for the time being at anyrate in order to allow you to assess the position without any words to either side,and to reach some conclusions. You are going to discuss the question ofindustrial affiliation, apart from political association, with your cabinet colleagues. Would it be asking too much, knowing how busy you are, to ask you to let us know what fresh views you form, if you form any, arising out of that discussion, so that we can at that stage, possibly being in a much differentposition, exercise the influence which we might be a,ble to exercise after thismorning&apos;s talk ?
PRIME MINISTER : I should like to consider that when I put it to theCabinet.Mr. WHITE : Could you also, Sir, put to the Cabinet the fact that we are compelled by the facts to enter into affiliations which are technically illegal inorder to work the Whitley system in the Civil Service ? For example, in the bigDepartments like the Ministry of Supply and the War Office we are compelled, inorder to negotiate with the authorities there, to affiliate to Whitley Councils onwhich are such bodies as the Transport and General Workers Union.PRIME MINISTER : Nobody has ever taken any objection to that?Mr. WHITE :  No.PRIME MINISTER :  It all works quite smoothly.Mr. WHITE : Except that it seems to us not to make for respect of theConstitution that infringements of it have to be winked at in order that businesscan be done.Mr. HOUGHTON : It is of course the difference between minor infringe-ments and the major challenge. That is how it strikes me. The harmlesscircumventions and modifications in practice really still leave us without the mainneeds of this situation. When Mr. Edwards mentioned a moment ago that he issent along to see the T.U.C. by Government Departments, it is a very different matter to go to the T.U.C. in consultation and to go there with some votingstrength. After all, our wish is to mould opinion in the Trades Union Congresswhich is very influential in affairs in which we are ourselves concerned; so thatthe circumventions we are permitted, and which nobody would take any noticeof, are comparatively trivial matters. Although there is nothing to prevent a civil Service Association exclusively composed of temporary Civil Servants fromaffiliating to the Trades Union Congress, it is only an Association containingpermanent Civil Servants ....PRIME MINISTER : I know,Mr. HOUGHTON : We are barred because although in many cases now more than one-half of our membership consists of temporary Civil -Servants, wecannot affiliate to the Trades Union Congress for those temporary Civil Servantsbecause if we do our established personnel are immediately put under the Act.That is another aggravation, and it is really leading up to this position, that iftemporary Civil Servants who have got such a direct interest in outsideconditions cannot get this affiliation through the orthodox and existing staff associations, it may lead to confusion by creating new ones for the expresspurpose of linking up with the Trades Union Congress which would be a greatbother to us and to everybody; it would multiply the number of Associations,divide representation, and make the work of negotiation extremely cumbersome;so we are up against those difficulties.Another thing, too. You tell us what the penalties are. We understandthem. We put them to our members, and will have to continue to do so, but you see Sir Walter Citrine has said that the blanket of protection of the wholeTrades Union movement will be thrown over those who defy the Act and who may be victimised for doing so.   Where are we getting to?PRIME MINISTER : I think it very serious, because I am sure it wouldbe a great disaster if, in this period of the war, we had a sort of &quot; show-down &quot;between Parliament and the Trades Unions, which is what it would come to.It would be most unfortunate.   I do not think it would happen for a moment.Mr. HOUGHTON : We wonder who is going to do the climbing down,and when?PRIME MINISTER: No; those who have climbed up have got toclimb down.POSTMASTER-GENERAL :  We are on the ground.PRIME MINISTER : If there had been no war, undoubtedly there wouldhave been a General Election three years ago, and this question would have played a very large part, I have no doubt. Some would have said one thing,and others another.Mr. HOUGHTON : Frankly, I doubt whether it would be such a keenlydiscussed issue but for the war. It is this tremendously powerful position into which the Trades Union Congress have been pr % because of the extraordinary
patience which the Government have shown to understand and to accommodate the workers&apos; point of view. Really the T.U.C. matters a great deal more to usto-day than ever it did before the war, because practically everything is discussed with the T.U.C. to start with.PRIME MINISTER : We work with them. Well, I cannot say more than Ihave said, but I will put this new point you make to my colleagues, and I must also say that nothing can be done in the presence of the threat; and it must never be said that the threat was withdrawn because of any suggestion. I would like tosee this settled like friends. That is my wish, not to get into legal attitudesand constitutional grimaces and all that sort of thing, challenges and counter-challenges; it is silly when we have the biggest show in the world to finish up, andwhen we have done the biggest thing in the world.Mr. JAGGER : In the midst of your preoccupations it makes us a littlehesitant to come in circumstances like this.PRIME MINISTER : I am very glad to meet you. I have learned somethingthis morning.Mr. JAGGER : There is one observation I would like to make in referenceto the threat. Your letter to Sir Walter Citrine wras September 1942, many months before any question of threat obtruded itself. Admitting the preoccupa-tions in the meantime, of which we are conscious, we are getting concerned, shallwe say, in the absence of any progress whatever, either in the House or elsewhere.PRIME MINISTER: Exactly.   I know; only this rather plays into thehands of those who took the opposite view, as you can see for yourself.Now what about the statement ?Mr. HOUGHTON : I think in the circumstances we would much prefer thatno public announcement of any sort should be made, because even if there is an agreed statement you are almost bound to put in things from your side, things thatyou have said, which I think it would be much better were not on record publiclyat this stage.PRIME MINISTER : Albright. I had thought it would be made public, butI should like to consider that, and, naturally, without your agreement, I would not do anything.  What I suggest is that we first of all agree upon a record ....Mr. HOUGHTON : Yes.PRIME MINISTER : . . . . and then we agree what we do with the record.Mr. HOUGHTON : All right.PRIME MINISTER: We can agree on the record and, and if anyone says that this, that, or the other was said, there it is, and we can perhaps put it awayin a box and lock it up. It may never be wanted, but if it were wanted, there is an agreed record. If one of you will meet Colonel Harvie Watt, my Private Secre-tary, and just draw it up and shorten it, making it a representative account ofwhat has actually taken place, I shall be very glad.Mr. HOUGHTON : Yes; thank you very much for your courtesy and consideration.PRIME MINISTER : Thank you; I hope we will find some way out of thedifficulty.







</content>
</cab>
