<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/195/9 images: 132-140</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government 2CP(77) 34 COPY NO      023 March 1977CABINETREPLV TO THE SECOND REPORT FROM THE SELECTCOMMITTEE ON THE PARLIAMENTARY COMMISSIONERFOR ADMINISTRATION, SESSION 1975-76Note by the Lord Privy SealMy colleagues will wish to see the attached reply to the Second Report fromthe Select Committee on the Parliamentary Commissioner for Administration,Session 1975-76 which has been agreed by the members of the legislation committee,    It is to be published as a White Paper on Monday 28 March 1977.PCivil Service Department23 March 1977
CONFIDENTIAL-FINAL REVISE[to be published as Command 6764 by her Majesty&apos;s Stationery office price 25p net]Second Report from the Select Committeeon theParliamentary Commissionerfor AdministrationSession 1975-76Observations by the government not FOR PUBLICATION BROADCAST or use ON CLUB TAPES BEFORE 7 8 MAR 1977This document is issued in advance on the st&quot;&apos;.ct understandino that no apo-o-.&apos; h is made. i      &apos;  o&quot;pan::at&apos;on or  person about its........-s befc-?. the time of publication.
Second Report from the Select Committee on theParliamentary Commissioner for AdministrationSession 1975-76Observations by the GovernmentINTRODUCTORY1. In their Second Report for the 1975-76 Session, the Select Committeemake a number of comments and recommendations, to which this White Papercontains the Governments response.PERSONNEL MATTERS2. In paragraphs 9 and 10 of their Report, the Select Committee refer again tothe exclusion from the Parliamentary Commissioners jurisdiction of personnelmatters covered by paragraph 10 of Schedule 3 of the Act. The Governmenthave considered carefully the views expressed by the Select Committee, but it remains the view of the Government that it would not be appropriate to amendSchedule 3, paragraph 10.3. The Select Committee have drawn a distinction between matters relatingto persons already employed by the Crown and those who are, for instance,candidates for employment in the Civil Service. The Parliamentary Commissionerwas not established to deal with relations between the State as employer and itsemployees. This applies as much to those seeking Crown employment as to those already in Crown employment. If either category were able to complain to theParliamentary Commissioner about personnel matters they would be in a parti-cularly privileged position, since they would have an additional grievancemachinery not open to the outside employee or potential employee.4. A further consideration supporting the conclusion that it would be inappropriate to extend the powers of the Parliamentary Commissioner into thearea of selection by the Civil Service Commissioners is the fact that the CivilService Commissioners are like the Parliamentary Commissioner himself appointed by the Queen; their terms of appointment ensure that they areindependent of the Government, in the same way as the Parliamentary Com-missioner.METHOD OF APPOINTMENT OF THE PARLIAMENTARYCOMMISSIONER5. In paragraphs 29 to 32 of their Report, the Select Committee commentcritically on the method used to appoint successive Parliamentary commissioners and raise 3 main questions. The Select Committee consider firstly that theHouse of Commons, or the Select Committee on the Parliamentary Commissionerfor Administration, on behalf of the House, should be entitled to consider andapprove the name or names of proposed candidates; and they refer to a proposal
in a Private Member&apos;s Bill, introduced during the last Parliamentary session,that the appointment of the Parliamentary Commissioner should follow con-sultation with the Chairman of the Select Committee and be subject to con-firmation by a resolution of each House of Parliament. The Select committee consider such an arrangement to constitute the minimum requirement for consultation on this appointment. They suggest secondly that the House ofCommons should have an opportunity of discussing whether or not the personappointed should invariably be a former civil servant, and thirdly that when such a person is appointed there should be a period of &quot;quarantine&quot; between hisretiring from the Civil Service and becoming Parliamentary Commissioner.6. Under Section 1(2) of the Parliamentary Commissioner Act 1967,appointment of the Parliamentary Commissioner is made by Her Majesty byLetters Patent; the Prime Minister advises Her Majesty on such appointments.In the view of the Government, a procedure similar to that envisaged in thePrivate Member&apos;s Bill is open to the objections that it would limit the presentdiscretion of the Sovereign, that it could prejudice the independent nature of theappointment, and that any debate on the floor of the House about the merits of individual candidates would be invidious. Moreover, any description of theParliamentary Commissioner as &quot;in a sense a servant of the House&quot; is strictlycolloquial since the Parliamentary Commissioner is unable to carry out any instructions of the House if these are not within the scope of the Act; in this situation it would be misleading if the function of making the appointment weregiven to the House rather than to the Sovereign.7. Although for these reasons it rejects the Select Committee&apos;s proposals, theGovernment is nevertheless prepared to make changes in the method which hasbeen followed in each of the 3 appointments made to date. It intends that whennext the post comes to be filled the Prime Minister will arrange for the Chairmanof the Select Committee to be consulted about the experience and qualitiesdesirable in candidates; any names the Chairman wishes to recommend at that stage will be taken into consideration. At a later stage the Chairman will be shown the short list of 2 or 3 names from which the Prime Minister intends tomake his recommendation to the Queen, and later the Chairman will be givenin confidence the name of the person selected, before the announcement ismade. Such an arrangement must, however, be subject to the wishes of thePrime Minister of the day and in giving his final advice to the Queen he would,in any event, retain a real element of choice.8. The Select Committee ask whether or not the person appointed shouldinvariably be a former civil servant. This question was raised in the House ofCommons on 29 June 1976 when the Prime Minister said that there never hasbeen a requirement for this post to be held by a former civil servant (HansardVol. 914 col. 195). It is the Government^ view that it is desirable for successiveholders of the post to bring to it diverse experience of relevant fields of public administration; and that, since the 3 appointees to date have been from theCivil Service, the next appointee should be someone with substantially differentexperience, perhaps from local government or the nationalised industries.9. The third suggestion of the Select Committee is that if a former civil servant is appointed there should be a period of &quot;quarantine&quot; between hisretiring from the Civil Service and becoming Parliamentary Commissioner.
However, there is no evidence to suggest that the lack of any such quarantinehas impaired the impartiality of any civil servant who has moved directly from a civil Service post to become Parliamentary Commissioner. Moreover, aperiod of quarantine would not necessarily avoid a situation where a Parlia-mentary Commissioner might have to deal with cases relating to the work of hisformer department several years earlier; and a quarantine requirement couldrestrict undesirably the field of choice. Nevertheless, the Government acceptsthat in certain individual instances a period of quarantine might be appropriate and that this is a factor to be borne in mind in considering candidates for the post.INVALID TRICYCLES10. In paragraph 16 of their Report the Committee express the hope that theGovernment will continue to strive to find further ways of meeting reasonablecriticisms of invalid tricycles. When the Report was made, it was alreadyGovernment policy that the main mobility benefit should be the new cashMobility Allowance, payable to drivers and non-drivers alike, with the tricycleas an alternative choice. Subsequently, on 23 July 1976 the Secretary of State for social Services announced that production of invalid vehicles would be phasedout and that their issue to new applicants would cease (Hansard Vol. 915col 2229-2231). People holding tricycles issued under the pre-1976 scheme wouldbe able to keep them and to get worn-out vehicles replaced, as long as supplieslasted, which was expected to be at least until 1981. They would, under legislationnow before Parliament, become automatically eligible to switch to the MobilityAllowance, to be held free of the normal age limit. Those who held their tricyclessubject to a condition of continuing to be in employment would be free fromthis condition. For disabled drivers who still needed a specialised vehicle when their tricycles could no longer be replaced, the Government would look at whatwas available on home and world markets. Tricycles would become subject to theMOT test, from which they have hitherto been exempt.11. Production of tricycles is expected to cease some time in 1978. Develop-ment will continue of design changes for greater safety which it would be practicable to introduce within the limited remaining production life of thetricycle. Steps are being taken to improve the standards of maintenance,with particular attention to matters which affect safety. Driving instructionarrangements are also being improved.e.c. SOCIAL SECURITY REGULATIONS12. In paragraph 19 of their Report the Committee say they hope thedepartments concerned will monitor and streamline where necessary the newprocedures under the e.c. social security regulations for determining title to unemployment and sickness benefit on return to the UK after employmentelsewhere in the e.c.. Instructions to all levels of staff in the local offices of theDepartment of Employment and the Department of Health and Social Securityhave been and are being kept under review. Management and staff dealing with
claims for unemployment and sickness benefit involving foreign insurance are aware of the need to check that the requirements of the e.c. regulations aresatisfied before taking liaison action with another e.c. state. The quality of thework done on these cases, as for the whole of the operations in local offices,will be subject to examination and report by inspection teams.-13. The new leaflets, produced by the e.c. Commission, which give an explanation of the e.c. Regulations and a resume of each country&apos;s social security scheme are not yet all available because the Commission have experiencedprinting difficulties. Persons making enquiries before going to work elsewhere inthe Community are sent either the appropriate e.c. leaflet or a general leaflettogether with a covering letter which includes specific advice on safeguardingentitlement to unemployment benefit on return to the UK.TELEVISION LICENCES14. In paragraph 20 of their Report the Select Committee refer to thedecision by the Court of Appeal and the consequent arrangements made by theHome Secretary to refund certain licence fee payments made by some people.All these refunds have now been made.15. The Committee express the hope in paragraph 21 of their Report thatthe procedures applied at the time of the next television licence fee increase willbe as free as possible from the possibility of misuse and that adequate steps willbe taken to provide clear and unequivocal information to the public. The HomeOffice intends to achieve this. On 7 February 1977 the Home Secretary announced in a written answer to a Parliamentary Question the procedure which would befollowed to implement the next increases in television licence fees (HansardVol. 925 col 526-528). He said that the increases would come into effect atmidnight on the day on which they were announced and explained in detail theperiod for which a licence would run depending upon when the applicationfor it was made. Full publicity was sought for this statement. The Home Officealso proposes to bring this announcement to the notice of licence holders by including information leaflets in television licence reminders, starting with those to be sent out to those members of the public whose licences expire at the end ofMarch.DELAYS IN DEALING WITH PLANNING ISSUES16. In paragraph 28 of their Report the Select Committee say they con-sider appeals should be capable of completion in less than the present 22 weeks and hope that the Department of the Environments constant experiments withmethods of saving time will achieve this. The Committee appeared to accept that,of the period of 9-10 weeks actually within the Departments control, there was little scope for reducing the 3-4 weeks normally taken from the time that thelocal authority&apos;s representations are sent to the appellant to the date of the inspectors site visit and, for the reasons given in evidence to the Committee,the Department were doubtful whether it would be possible to achieve muchreduction in the remaining 6 weeks between the site visit and the issue of the
decision While the Department will continue to do their best to save time, it isfeared that the cuts in public expenditure and consequential reductions in startwhich have since been announced and the fact that the number of appeals shows signs of increasing make it unrealistic to expect that these 6 weeks can be brought down in the near future. It should be mentioned that the total average time whichbeing taken by appeals when evidence was taken by the Committee and whichwaswastherefore given to the Committee was 25 and not 22 weeks.Printed in England for Her Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office byMcCorquodale Printers Ltd., LondonHM 7826  Dd 294298  K20  3/77   McC 3336/2
HER MAJESTVS STATIONERY office government Bookshops49 High Holborn, London WC1V 6HB13a Castle Street, Edinburgh eh3 3AR41 The Hayes, Cardiff CF1 1JWBrazennose Street, Manchester M60 8ASSouthey House, Wine Street, Bristol BS1 2BQ258 Broad Street, Birmingham Bl 2HE80 Chichester Street, Belfast BT1 4jy government publications are also available through booksellers ISBN 0 10 167640 9


</content>
</cab>
