<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/5/29 images: 290-299</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
s  uzTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT .Printed for the War Cabinet.   February 1940.SECRET. Copy No. 4 8W.M. (40)29th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 29 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 downing  Street,S.W. 1, on Thursday, February 1, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present :The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Lord Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. F. Hemming.Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, R.E.[20762]b
WAR CABINET 29 (40).Contents.     - -minute no. Subject. page 1      The Air Situation      .................. 2272      The Naval Situation.................. 2273      The Military Situation        ............... 228Western Front and Finland.4      Assistance to Finland. ...       ...       ...       ...       ...      ...     228Supply of aircraft.5      Anglo-Soviet Negotiations, Summer 1939 ...       ...       ...     229Proposed publication of Blue Book.6      United States of America    ...       ...       ...       ...       ...     229Discussion of outstanding problems.7      The Balkans    ..................       ...     229Attitude of Italy.8      The Far East : Relations with Japan        ...      ...       ...     230The case of the S.S. Asama Maru.The case of the S.S. Heyio Maru.9      War Cabinet Business ...............     232
The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 28thConclusions,Minute 1.)1. The Secretary of State for Air said that bad weather hadseriously interfered with air operations the previous day. Therehad been no enemy activity close to our coasts till the late afternoon,when 5 enemy aircraft were reported off our coasts fromNorthumberland to Skegness. Heavy fog prevented fighters takingoff except in the north, where a Spitfire tried to intercept the enemy aircraft off Northumberland.Fighters took off from a number of aerodromes during the day for patrol duties, but were compelled to land almost immediately by fog. One Blenheim, which took off from Duxford, collided with high ground close to the aerodrome, the crew of the aircraft beingkilled.Two bodies had been washed up on the Scottish coast, whichwere believed to have been those of the crew of a Heinkel bomberwhich had been attacked by Spitfires on the 19th January. It was known that the bomber had been damaged on this occasion.The Heinkel destroyed on the 30th January off St. Abb&apos;s Headhad been attacked by two Hurricanes approaching from the beam.This was the first occasion on which this method of attack had been used; it necessitated aiming ahead of the enemy in order to allow for his movement at right angles to the line of attack.There had been no operations by Bomber. Command or theBritish air forces in France, and the patrols of Coastal command had been seriously interfered with by weather.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.The naval situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 28thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the process ofgrouping the Ea,st Coast shipping in order to counter German air attacks had been started. One convoy would run each way everyday. As a result of the two days of intensive enemy air attack onEast Coast shipping on the 29th and 30th January, a total of some34,000 tons of British and 9,000 tons of neutral shipping had been sunk. A long continuance of such attacks would be a very serious matter. Every effort was being made to provide ships with some form of anti-aircraft weapon, including rockets and&apos; guns fromwarships undergoing refit. Steel plating was being fitted to giveprotection against machine-gun fire. The main counter to this formof attack, however, must be the institution of convoys under airprotection. Conditions during the two days in question had been particularly favourable to the enemy owing to the low cloud.Representations had. been made to Trinity House as to theprovision of anti-aircraft protection to lightships. Steps to this endwere being taken, notwithstanding that the Elder Brethren hadbeen somewhat disturbed at the prospect of thereby compromising-the international character of light vessels.The Minister without Portfolio, while not underrating the seriousness of these attacks on East Coast shipping, pointed outthat, according to the latest report by the Ministry of Shipping,there had been a net gain during the preceding week of 10,000 tonsof shipping, the total net loss since the beginning of the waramounting only to 23 ships, totalling 100,000 tons in all. Thesefigures excluded tanker tonnage, which showed a net gain(W.P. (R.) (40) 40).[20762]
The MilitarySituation.Western front and Finland.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 28thConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The Secretary of State for War said there was nothing toreport on the Western Front.In Finland there was renewed activity at Kuhmoniemi andsouth of Petsamo.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Assistance to finland.Supply of aircraft.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 23rdConclusions,Minute 5.)4. The Secretary of State for A ir gave details of the progress made in despatching the aircraft which were being provided for Finland, as follows : 30 Gladiators. 9 already in Finland, 17 in process oferection in Sweden, 4 in transit to Sweden.28 Gauntlets. 4 in transit to Sweden. The modifications to fit these aircraft for operation in Finland were being carriedout, and all would be ready for packing within about a week.12 Hurricanes. All would be ready for use by Finnishpilots very shortly, and arrangements had been made for thetraining of the Finnish pilots. These would not be arriving,however, for three or four weeks. The Secretary of State forAir proposed to take up with M. Gripenberg this delay in the arrival of the Finnish pilots.12 long-nosed, Blenheims. 11 were now in Finland, the twelfth having been lost in transit flying over the North Sea.12 short-nosed Blenheims. Now being prepared for despatch.17 Lysanders. 9 ready for despatch, and shipmentexpected to begin at the end of the week. The remainder wouldthen be ready for packing.33 dive bombers. Arrangements for despatch were beingmade between the Admiralty and the Air Ministry.Appropriate quantities of ammunition and bombs were being released with each consignment of aircraft.Fifteen volunteers, to be temporarily demobilised from theRoyal Air Force, had been selected for the ground staff of theHurricanes, Gladiators and Gauntlets. The contract between theFinnish Government and the manufacturers of the Lysandersincluded provision for sending two mechanics.It would be difficult temporarily to provide civilian pilots toferry over the short-nosed Blenheims, as the recent bad weather hadhindered the transport of aircraft from manufacturers to AirMinistry stores. If these aircraft were to be sent to Finland with-out delay, it would be necessary temporarily to demobilise RoyalAir Force personnel.The War Cabinet :-(i) Took note of the above statement.(ii) Authorised the temporary demobilisation of Royal AirForce personnel to ferry over the Blenheim aircraftpromised to Finland, if sufficient civilian personnelcould not be made available.
Anglo-soviet negotiations,Summer, 1939.proposed publication of blue Book.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 21stConclusions,Minute 13.)U.S.A.Discussion ofoutstandingproblems.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 22ndConclusions,Minute 8.)5. In reply to a question, the Prime Minister said that he had seen Mr. Attlee and Sir Archibald Sinclair on the previous day on another matter, but that they had not referred to the proposed publication of the Blue Book.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.6. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs referred to asuggestion made by President Roosevelt early in the war that, when matters of dispute arose between the United States Government and ourselves, we should avoid Notes and seek a settlement by less formalmethods. He had considered drawing Lord Lothian&apos;s attention tothis suggestion and he was glad to note, therefore, that lord lothian had himself put it forward at his meeting on the30th January with Mr. Cordell Hull (telegram No. 119 from washington). In a long conversation all major problems out-standing between the United States and ourselves had been touchedupon, and Lord Lothian had taken full advantage of the oppor-tunity offered. On the specific question of contraband control he(the Secretary of State) was still in discussion with Lord Lothianon the terms of the long and reasoned reply which he proposed togive the United States Government. In general, the position asbetween the United States and ourselves was now somewhat easier.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was glad to note that Lord Lothian, when discussing the question of tobacco, had pointed out to Mr. Cordell Hull that on balance we were buyingmuch more in the United States than before the war.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that this fact,while of importance, was no consolation to the tobacco growers inthe States.The Secretary of State for War said that he was not altogetherhappy in regard to the amount of the United States tobacco stocksheld in this country, and suggested that further inquiry wasadvisable before a reply was returned to the specific question put byMr. Cordell Hull.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he would makeinquiries in regard to this matter.The War Cabinet took note of the above discussion.The Balkans.Attitude ofItaly.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 28thConclusions,Minute 10.)7. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attentionto telegram No. 16, Empax, Saving, from His Majesty&apos;s Minister,the Vatican, dated the 26th January, 1940, giving a summary of theleading article in that day&apos;s issue of the Osservatore Romanodealing with the problems confronting the Balkan Entente, andstrongly advocating the achievement of Balkan unity. This articlewas of interest, since he believed that in this matter the Vaticanwas working in close touch with the Italian Government, and thatit probably indicated the general nature of Italian policy in the balkans.
The Far East:Relations with japan.The case ofthe S.S.Asama Maru.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 28thConclusions,Minute 11.)8. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that atelegram (No. 80) had been sent the previous afternoon to HisMajestjr&apos;s Ambassador, embodying the conclusions reached by theWar Cabinet as to the terms on which he (the Ambassador) couldsettle the Asama Maru incident, including the return of (say) up toone-half of the Germans in question. He had since receivedtelegram No. 186 from Sir Robert Craigie reporting a conversation which he had had on the 31st January with the Japanese Ministerfor Foreign Affairs :  Mr. Arita had stated that the Japanese Government were&apos;prepared to consider a settlement of the incident on the linesreported (telegram No. 175 from Tokyo), subject to corrsidera-tion as to the number of Germans who would be handed backto Japan. After a little fencing, Mr. Arita had indicated thathe hoped it might be possible for us to return about thirteen ofthem. Sir Robert Craigie replied that this had not at all beenhis idea of the arrangement, and it seemed improbable thatinvestigation would,show that so many of the men in questionfell outside our categories. The impression derived bySir Robert Craigie from this part of the conversation was thathis previous estimate (7 or 8 men) was the lowest which theJapanese would contemplate, and might be optimistic.Sir Robert Craigie and Mr. Arita had agreed that, subjectto his (the Secretary of State&apos;s) concurrence, the return ofthese men should appear to take place as the result of a/spontaneous action of His Majesty&apos;s Government after clueinquiry, and not as part of a prior agreement. The JapaneseGovernment would have to maintain their theoretical claim toreceive back all the twenty-one men, but in practice would not press it. Similarly, we should reserve our right to haveretained all the men intercepted.As regards the future, it was provisionally understoodbetween Sir Robert Craigie and Mr. Arita that the arrange-ment might take the form of a &quot; gentlemen&apos;s agreement,&quot;which would neither be signed nor initialled. For the efficientexecution of this arrangement, the best plan seemed to be thatthe British and Japanese Consular Officers on the Pacific coast of North and South America should be instructed confidentiallyto get in close touch with one another.Mr. Arita. stated that it would be embarrassing for him to announce in the Diet that the Japanese Government had agreed to accept our list of categories. He wished, therefore,to confine his public announcement on this point to a statement that Japanese shipping companies had been instructed that infuture they should refuse passages to the national of anybelligerent country who was embodied in the armed force ofthat country or was suspected of being so embodied. Inpractice the Japanese authorities would interpret the words&apos;&apos; suspected of being so embodied&apos;&apos; as applying to all Germansfalling within our categories, but he hoped that, for publicitypurposes, we should be satisfied with some general phraseologysuch as he had suggested. Sir Robert Craigie had replied thathe was sure that the Secretary of State would meet theJapanese Government as far as possible in this matter, but thathe (the Secretary of State) also had the public to consider, andthat it might in such circumstances be difficult to make any public announcement that Japanese ships would not in future be interfered with.Sir Robert Craigie had asked for instructions on the followingpoints : (a) the maximum number of men whom His Majesty&apos;s Govern -ment would be prepared to release (stating whetherofficers or ratings);
(previous reference:W.M. (40) 26thConclusions,Minute 8.)The case ofthe s.s.Heyio Maru.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 28thConclusions,Minute 11.)A&quot;(b) the question of publicity, bearing in mind the great difficulties with which the Japanese Government wouldbe confronted if, as the result of the proposed agreement,they were to be exposed to serious attack from Japaneseextremists.In telegram No. 187 Sir Robert Craigie had suggested the draft frr the memorandum embodying the proposed &quot; gentlemen&apos;s agreement.&quot; This text the Foreign Secretary proposed to discuss with the First Lord of the Admiralty. Had the Admiralty anypreference as between officers and ratings in the selection of those to be returned ?The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the men removed from the s.s. Asama Maru comprised thirteen officers and eightratings. Fie thought that those handed back should include someofficers and some ratings. He would discuss the details with theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he did not entirely understand the nature of Sir Robert Craigie&apos;s proposals as to the method by which the agreement with the Japanese Govern-ment and ourselves should be made public. What he had in mind was that simultaneous statements should be issued by the twoGovernments; that is to say, that we should announce in a suitablemanner our decision to return certain of the Germans to Japan,while the Japanese would announce the arrangements which theyhad reached with us for the avoidance of incidents in future.The First L,ord of the Admiralty said that a statement on theabove lines would be highly satisfactory. As regards the WingSang case, he had had a very satisfactory report from the NavalLiaison Officer, who, on presenting a strong protest to the JapaneseNaval Authorities, had been promised that the matter would beinquired into, and had been informed that the Japanese Com-mander-in-Chief had on two occasions issued orders that Inter-national Law should be strictly respected. The relations betweenthe Japanese and British Naval Officers concerned had been of amost friendly character.The Prime Minister said that, as regards the making public ofthe proposed arrangement with the Japanese Government, he would favour whatever might be the method best calculated to protect our prestige.The Chancellor of the Exchequer inquired whether it would bepossible for Sir Robert Craigie, at the present stage, to raise in some suitable form with the Japanese Government the case of thes.s. Heyio Maru.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he had theprevious day sent a preliminary telegram (No. 81) warningSir Robert Craigie that this case might arise in the near future.He agreed that it would be an advantage to give Sir Robert Craigiediscretion to inform the Japanese Government that we had received an unconfirmed report that German officers of the Graf Spee were proposing to embark in this vessel, that we were making inquiriesto ascertain whether this report was well founded, and that in the meanwhile we informed them of this report in order that, if it waswell founded, they (the Japanese Government) might have anopportunity/ of arranging for the removal of these men from thes.s. Heyio Maru before she sailed from Callao. As the officers inquestion were supposed to have been interned by the argentine government, he had sent a telegram the previous day asking HisMajesty&apos;s Ambassador, Buenos Aires, to make inquiries.
The War Cabinet agreed : (a) As regards the s.s. Asama Maru: (i) to take note of the progress towards a settlementreported in Sir Robert Craigie&apos;s telegramNo. 186;(ii) to take note that the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs would confer with the First Lord of theAdmiralty as regards the text of the Memo-ran dum embodying the proposed &quot; gentlemen&apos;s agreement &quot; with the Japanese Government andas regards the number of officers and ratingsrespectively to be handed back to Japan;(iii) that the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs should authorise Sir Robert Craigie to agree toa procedure whereby we should announce that,for reasons to be given, we had decided to returnto the Japanese Government a certain number ofthe Germans in question, and the JapaneseGovernment would announce the agreement theyhad made with us for avoiding further incidents in future.(b) As regards the s.s. Heyio Maru that the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should send a telegram authorising His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador, Tokyo,at his discretion, to make a statement to the JapaneseGovernment on the lines of &quot;A.&quot;War Cabinet 9.   The Prime Minister stated that the Chiefs of Staff wouldBusiness. return from Paris, where they had been discussing Scandinavianproblems with the French flight Command, late that evening. Itwould be necessary to circulate a paper recording the results ofthese conversations, and it was therefore most unlikely that the WarCabinet would be able to have a full discussion on this matter attheir Meeting on Friday morning. It was therefore proposed thatthe Secretary of State for lndia&apos;s Paper on &quot; India and the War &quot;should be considered at the meeting on Friday morning, thediscussion on Scandinavian problems being deferred until Fridayafternoon at 5 p.m, or until Saturday morning.The War Cabinet took note of this arrangement.Richmond Terrace, S. W. 1,February 1, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
