<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/41/46 images: 338-341</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1943.EXAMINATION OF THE PRESENT SYSTEM OF CONTROL IN the coalmining INDUSTRY AND FUTURE POLICY.Memorandum by the Minister of Fuel and Power.ON the 6th October, 1943, I submitted a memorandum to the Lord presidents committee (L.P. (43) 219) in which I recommended that consideration should begiven to certain changes in the organisation laid down in the White Paper on coal. It was agreed that I should submit to the War Cabinet a memorandumdescribing the nature of the steps which I wish to see taken immediately toimprove the machinery of control.2. The scheme has been in operation for just over a year and I have been examining it very carefully for some time to see whether it has in fact given theGovernment the control that it was intended should be exercised. I am definitelyof the opinion that it has not given that measure of control. I am supported inthis view by my Regional Controllers who are in direct contact with the problemsof the industry.3. I will first give my reason for reaching this conclusion. Though theGovernment is theoretically in full operational control of the industry, inpractice that control has proved difficult of achievement. The Government hasthe power to remove managers who are inefficient and to assume control of pitsthat for one reason or another are not giving satisfactory results. In severalcases this has been done. There are, however, 1,600 pits working under myjurisdiction, the managements of which are responsible for day to day operationswhile remaining the employees of the colliery owners.4. The effective operational control of so many pits is precluded by theinsufficiency of staff to maintain the close oversight which would be necessaryboth before and after the full exercise of my powers. I could not provide sucha staff as would be necessary because the required personnel is available only within the industry itself.5. Certain factors common to other industries are in part responsible forthe present unsatisfactory output of coal. Nevertheless, I am convinced that more coal can be got with the present man-power provided that the limitations of the present organisation and in the practical use of my powers are removed.In my view it will be necessary to bring under my direct control the manage-ments and technical staffs in order to make possible their most efficient distribu-tion and use regardless of their existing ties to individual colliery owners. this may require the renting of the mines or the taking of other stops which wouldrelieve the coal owners for the duration of the war from their present functions in regard to the pits.6. The taking over of managements would ensure a continuous and expertsupervision of production by the rearrangement and. grouping of pits undertechnicians whose sole responsibility would be to the Regional Controller and[26215]The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.   It is issued for the personal use of c::^2l^^^MOST SECRET. Copy No     2 3W.P. (43) 446.7th October, 1943.WAR CABINET.
through him to me. Nevertheless, this step alone would not provide the outputwhich I am seeking unless explicit pledges were received from the leaders of the mine workers (and carried out to the limits of their powers) to remove all obstacleson the men&apos;s side to increased production.7. If these changes are made the opportunity will present itself for developing a technique of labour management in the coalmining industry such aspresent circumstances require.8. The means of carrying out what is required should be urgently considered.If the principle is agreed I would undertake co submit a draft scheme with theleast possible delay. In the meantime it would be necessary to announce in theforthcoming Debate on coal that the Government was giving its immediateattention to the improvement of the machinery of operational control.9. It is my own strongly held view as well as that of all my advisers, whoare in the best position to judge the temper and spirit of the industry, that anydevice for improving the existing control will fail in its effect if it is merely ofa temporary character. I therefore recommend, as invited by the Lord presidents committee, that the War Cabinet should appoint a Committee of Ministers toconsider long-term proposals, which I will lay before them, regarding theorganisation of the industry.G. Ll. G.Ministry of Fuel and Pozver,Dean Stanley Street,Millbank, S.W. 1.



</content>
</cab>
