<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/37/0 images: 14-39</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP. (49) 20325TIL OCTOBER a 1949COPY NO. v. 1CABINETPROPOSALS POR THE ECONOMIC UNIFICATION OF europe memorandum by. the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs and the Chancellor of the exchequer of EuropeCouncil of almost cerGroup of Mat Ministeend. of tillMajesty&apos;s27th OctobProposals envisaging further 1 economic unification&apos;are now caning forward in connection both with theEurope and D.E.E.C In particular they aretain to arise at the meetings of the Consultativeinisters of 0*E.E.C and of the Council of O.E.E.C.rial level which will take place in Paris at thes week.   It will therefore be necessary for HisGovernment to have their views settled byer at the latest.Reconimendations of the Consultative Assembly2. The recommendations of the Assembly of the Councilof Europe adopted at Strasbourg in September, the text ofwhich is reproduced at Annex A, are based on the broadassumption that &apos;European Economic Union&apos; of the participating countries is an agreed aim.   This emerges clearly in the preamble (paragraphs 4 and 5) and in Section I (paragraphs 1 and4(b)).    This document will come before the Committee ofMinisters in Strasbourg at the beginning of November, and theywill be expected to draw up and submit to the Assembly, thoughprobably not until its next ordinary session in the summer of1950, proposals for the implementation of these recommendations.In setting this work in hand it will be necessary for UnitedKingdom Ministers to have reached decisions not only on the UnitedKingdom&apos;s attitude to the broad issue of policy, but also on thenature of the relationship of 0.E.E..C. to the Council ofEurope .Developments in the sphere of O.E^E.C.3* From its inception a basic objective of the european recovery Programme in the minds of important sections &quot;of american opinion has been to promote the &apos;unification&apos;  ofEurope.   So far as the participating countries are concerned,they undertook, in Part I of the Convention under which O.E.E.C.was  established, general obligations directed towards co-operation and mutual help.   There was also an undertaking to 1 study&apos; CustomsUnions or analogous arrangements such as free trade areas$ and toco-operate in reducing tariffs and other barriers to theexpansion of trade.   So far as the United States is concerned the Economic Co-operation Act was amended in 1949 to include thewords &apos;It is further declared to be the policy of the people ofthe United States to encourage the unification of Europe...&apos;;and Mr. Horriman and Mr. Finletter have both- stressed that this amendment was the expression of a deep-seated feeling among theAmerican people.   Again, Mr. Truman stated in a speech of29th August that closer ties of economic union in Europe were essential for a better v/orld.

ho- A recent development has &quot;been the promotion of a schemefor closer economic union &quot;between France, Italy and Benelux.We discuss this scheme in paragraph 11 below.5* Mr. Hoffman and his principal advisers are convinced ..:that Congress will &quot;be unwilling to vote a furtherappropriation for Marshall Aid unless effective progress towards &quot;unification&apos; can he demonstrated to Congress beforeconsideration of the 1950-51 appropriation begins next March.6.   &apos; There is no item on the formal agenda of theforthcoming Paris meetings which brings up the issue of*unification1 *   But Mr. Hoffman is himself attending themeeting;    and we must have our answer ready if, as isprobable, we are asked to declare our attitude on this issue and on the nature of any further contribution which theUnited Kingdom is prepared to make.Policy on ^economic unification&apos;7* His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s policy towards european economic co-operation was set out in E.P.C.(ii-9) 6 of25th January, 1949, which was approved by the economic policy Committee on 26th January (E.P.C.(2+9) 5th Meeting,Minute 2).   In brief the policy there set out was one underwhich His Majesty&apos;s Government were not to involve themselvesin the economic affairs of Europe beyond the point from whichthey could, if they wished, withdraw.   This policy has never been publicly set but, or conveyed in any form either to the americans or to the participating countries.8. The risks which we ought not to run in co-operating with Europe were not explicitly set out in E.P.C. (2+9) 6, but inpresent circumstances we consider that we should not accept measures or proposals which would have any of thefollowing effects, directly or by implication;-(i)   Loss of His Majesty1s Government&apos;s responsibilityfor &quot;budgetary and credit policy, and for themanagement of the reserves;(ii)    hindrance to our own efforts to reach and maintainequilibrium between the dollar area and the sterling area;    we cannot sacrifice opportunities for dollar-earning (or dollar-saving) in order tomake it easier for other European countries to earn or save dollars;(iii)    opening to European decision the size of strategicdollar-earning and dollar-saving United Kingdomindustries;(iv)    materially affecting the system of imperial preference.Vifithin these limits, we have since last January goneas far as we could in the direction of European co-operation.The most important step is our proposals for the liberalisation of trade.   We have also made a substantial contribution tothe Intra-europe on Payments Scheme.9* But the changes which have taicen place in the economic position of Europe and of this country since January make economic union with Europe less rather than more attractive than it wasthen.   At that time, our policy was based on the assumption

that our dollar position would progressively improve andthat we had a reasonable chance of achieving viability by .1952&apos;on the basis of existing policies.   Tho quite minorrecession in the United States during tho summer revealedthe real weakness of our position and the complete inadequacy of our reserves.   While the European countries have controlled -their inflationary tendencies more effectively than we thenthought likely, they have shown little or no intention of taking the steps necessary to remedy their other basicweaknesses.   As the resources which we could contribute to continue union are now less than they were thought to be inJanuary, the prospects of such a union being successful arecorrespondingly diminished, especially as we should have toassume leadership in it.   We have also had experience duringthe summer of the difficulty of real co-operation in O..E.E.C,and, as a result of the&apos; Washington talks and of the Common-wealth Finance ministers meeting, we have established, or areestablishing, a new relationship with the United States andwith the rest of &quot;the Commonwealth.    Our relations with these areas take priority over our relations with Europe and forthat reason alone there is a limit to the part we can play in european union.10. We have no doubt therefore that the policy set outin E.P.C (2+9) 6 must be maintained.   But if we maintain our existing policy we must still decide hoy/ within those limitswe can further develop economic co-operation with other european countries.11. The only new proposal at present current is thatrelating-, to closer economic union between Prance, Italy andBenelux.   The main object of this scheme is to abolishquantitative restrictions on the movement of goods and exchange control restrictions between the five countries.   There would .not be a Customs Union.   The full details of this scheme (ifthey have been fully worked out) have not been disclosed to us.The five countries did not intend to bring the United Kingdom(and the sterling area) within the scheme or to extend its bone-fit s&apos;to us.    They would probably have preferred to include theUnited Kingdom in a scheme of this kind;   but&apos; their suspicion that we will not come into an economic union may be one reasonfor their going ahead without us.   The Economic Co-operation administration, who support the scheme, also rep;ard us as beingoutside its orbit, and Mr. Hoffman has discussed it with II.M.Ambassador in Washington on this basis with a view to reaching a common line towards it.   On general grounds our policy hasalways been to encourage such co-operation, between members of1,E.E.C*, and we could not oppose this example of it unless it materially conflicted with our interests (e.g. by prejudicingsterling exchange rates or by establishing trade restrictionsagainst us other than on balance of payments grounds).   while taking this line we should insist as an essential preliminarythat a firm proposal should be brought to 0.E.E.C fordiscussion.12. If pressure develops for the United Kingdom tosupport further measures leading to 1 unification1, we should undertake to study any proposals that may be put forward.13. We thought it necessary to give the Americans some indication of our attitude to European economic union, as outlined in this paper, before Mr. Hoffman leaves for Parisin the middle of this week, and we have telegraphed accordingly to Sir Oliver Franks.   A copy of the telegram is at Annex B.It will be seen that the Ambassador has been asked to explainour views to the United States Secretary of State, but toinform him that it has not yet been possible to show the

mossago to the full Cabinet.   If our colleagues endorse thispolicy, it will form the basis for our general attitude toany proposals which may be put forward at the forthcomingmeetings, though we shall not of course make any formal statement of it.    Other Commonwealth Governments should beinformed immediately.Relationship of O.E*E.C* to, &apos;the Council of Europe1U* It is clear that in the working out of the policy involved in the recommendations of the Assembly of theCouncil of Europe adopted at Strasbourg, problems will ariseof the relationship between the. Council of Europe and O.E.E.C.These have been studied by officials, and we annex (Annex G)the results of their consideration of them and theirr e c recommend t i ons *15* We agree that the general policy should be one ofthe closest collaboration between  the two bodies, but thatthis collaboration must be on the basis of equality betweenthe two and with full recognition of the fact that the UnitedStates Government are at present directly concerned with thework of O.E*E.C. and are not directly concerned with the workof the Council of Europe.   We agree also with the detailed recommendations made.Conclusions16. We therefore recommend that the Cabinet shouldendorse: -(a) the policy set out in the telegram at Annex Bi    and(b) the recommendations contained in Annex C regardingthe relationship between the Council of europe and O.E.E.C.E .B aR.S.G.25th October, 19k9*

1.     The Consultative Assembly of the Council of Europepledging itself to promote a policy of full employment anda rising standard of life, warns the peoples of Europe thatmillions among us will soon go hungry and unemployed unless we act at once to re-establish the economic equilbrium betweenEurope and North America.2.     The most urgent task is to pay for the food and rawmaterials which at present have to be bought in North America.The necessary dollars can only be found if a fresh effort ismade on both sides of the Atlantic.    The countries of Europemust increase their productivity and reduce their costs andselling prices, so as to adapt themselves to the hard facts of the post war world.   On their side the U.S.A., whichrecognises the need for Europe to sell more to them, should encourage these imports by every possible means and inparticular by lowering its customs tariffs.3. ,The free nations of Europe can do much to save themselves by mutual help.Together with their overseas associates and territoriesthey represent a population which as regards numbers andskills is the equal of any other population in the world.If the peoples of Europe are weak to-day it is., because theyare divided, but if they have the vision and courage to unite their markets, they can lower their costs and sellingprices, sell more to each other and more than recover theirlost prosperity.1+.     The economic union of free Europe should not create an exclusive trading area.   On the contrary, the door wouldbe open to the exchange of goods and services of fair terraswith all the world.5*     The realisation of economic union would include theabolition by stages of restrictions on the movement of men,money and goods;    the co-ordination of investments, of basic Industries, of agriculture, and the gradualharmonising of national legislation in the field of social policy and taxation.6,     This union would include the free circulation ofmen, goods and capital.   It implies the rapid establishmentof a multilateral system of payments, leading to therestoration of convertibility of European currenciesf with one another * subject to the safeguards necessary to enablemovements of capital to be controlled during the transitional period.7.     The building up of such a union of free peoplesimplies central planning, combined with a maximum degree of individual liberty.    The central planning must be by consent,and the liberty must be used for the good of all.ANNEXOOUNOIL OF EUROPE:    CONSULTATIVE ASSEMBLY1SRECOMMENDATIONS TO THE COMMITTEE OF .MINISTERS ON ECONOMIC AFFAIRSPREAMBLE

1.     To invite the Governments to intensify the spread ofeconomic information through existing channels and at thesame time to provide for the Council of Europe itself totake direct action by every available means to make the peoplof Europe aware of the gravity of the peril in which they are living, and of the advantages to themselves of uniting their resources in a common effort to. regain solvency and reach anew level of prosperity.2.     To take all practical steps to establish as quickly as possible a multilateral system of payments, including therestoration of the inter-convertibility of Europeancurrencies, subject to the safeguards necessary to enablethe movement of capital to be controlled during the transitional period.3.     To create permanent machinery for consultation on credit policy between central banks of issue, and for theco-ordination of credit policy.U.     (a)    To follow up and. extend the work of O.E.E.C.in liberalising inter-European trade, and allstudies now being made in regard to the economic relations of Europe and its overseas associatesand territories.(b) To take all preliminary action for the  -establishment of a European economic union, whichshall retain the preferential systems and economicties now in existence between certain european nations and the overseas countries and territoriesassociated with them,&apos;    and to consider theirprogressive extension to the other Member Statesof this union.(c) To study the development of production withinthe territories of the members of the conferenceso that their individual import requirements maybe   met as efficiently as possible from theircombined resources.(d) To study appropriate action for the progressiveabolition of the obstacles to the free movementof men and for promoting the widest possibleemployment of labour in the metropolitan and overseas territories of Member States and oftheir associates.(e) To study the conditions under which the investment in their territories of American, and other non-European capital could be encouraged.Proposals for action to be taken by the member States of the Council of Europebetween themselves and also between thelatter and other nations&apos; The Consultative Assembly requests the Committee ofMinisters:

(f) To extend and develop a system of guaranteedmarkets.(g) To oall an economic conference, representingthemselves and their overseas associates and territories, in order to study the above proposals.&apos;5.     To call as soon as possible, industrial conferencesrepresenting both employers&apos;, workers&apos;  and consumers&apos;organisations, as well as government services interested inthe main manufacturing and agricultural industries, in order &apos;to make concrete proposals to the Assembly on the organisationof these industries and the increase in their productivity in the common interests of Europe.6,     To draw up a draft European convention for thecontrol of international Cartels, which it will present tothe Assembly.11The Consultative Assembly also requests the Committeeof Ministers:-(a) To submit to it proposals to meet the recommendationmade above together with a report on the progress made on these subjects since the ordinary sessionof the Consultative Assembly.(b) After the Consultative Assembly has consideredthese proposals, to nominate a delegation fromthe Council of Europe which shall enter into negotiations with the Government of the UnitedStates of America and with any other government concerned, in order to express the common policyof the Member States and to seek through jointagreement the modifications which should be madeto existing treaties, and in particular the actionto be taken in the matter of lowering customstariffs in the United States so as to allow of thedevelopment of European exports to that country.IllProposals for the future work of the  -Economic Committee1.     The Consultative Assembly shall decide:(a) that the Economic Committee may sit in the interval between sessions;(b) that it may split into specialised sub-committees$(c) that these sub-committees may hear evidence fromexperts on their own subjects.2.     The Consultative. Assembly shall request itsPresident to make contact with the Secretariat of U.N.O.,of O.E.E.C. and B.I.S. in order to have access to all documents of O.E.E.C. the European Economic Commission,- and B.I.S.  andto arrange for the international and national officers ofthese two organisations to be heard by the Economic Committee,should the committee so desire,  .

3.     The Appendix to.this report act out thosequestionsreferred to the Economic Committee by the Committee ofMinisters and by members of the Consultative Assembly whichthe Committee has decided should be studied by itsSub-C ommi 11 e e s.APPENDIX&quot;[,     The Economic Committee has set up four Sub-Committees:A. Finance and CurrencyB, Commercial policy , Industry, Agriculture and PoodD. Public Works.2.     In addition the Commission has appointed a rapporteurfor the study of a European Office of Patents.3.* The following subjects raised by Members of the consultative Assembly in resolution submitted to theCommittee have been sent for study to Sub-Committees,A. Finance and Currency 3ub-Committee(a) A common currency for the Member States of theCouncil of Europe,(b) A European Reserve Bank(c) A European Bank for Investments(d) Co-ordination of Investments(e) A European clearing system,B. Commercial Policy Sub-Committee(a) Liberalisation of inter-European trade(b) Development of exchanges with the countries of eastern Europe by means of special agreementbetween Member States(c) Issuing of a European postage stamp(d) Development of the Tourist Industry in Europe.C. Industry. Agriculture and Food Sub-Committee(a) The coal industry of the Ruhr(b) Go-ordination of transport, steel and power(c) Development and co-ordination of production andinrprovement in distribution of agricultural products.

ANNEX copy OF TELEGRAM SENT TO H.M.. AMBASSADOR. WASHINGTON. on &apos;5&apos;TH OCTOBERA series of meetings begins&apos;in Paris this week ofthe Consultative Group of O.E.E.C., the Ministerial Council ofO.E.E.C, the Council of Ministers (European Assembly) and the consultative Council of the Brussels Treaty.   At all of these meetings the question of European economic collaboration will come up in one form or another, the Belgian Government havingput Article 1 of the Treaty of Brussels on the agenda of the consultative Council of the Brussels Treaty.2. At these meetings, pressures are likely to develop forfurther steps towards &apos;unification&apos; of Western Europe.   There is reason to believe that the proposals for a greater Benelux andother ideas for closer economic union in Europe, which have beencanvassed without consultation with the United Kingdom, havenot been making progress.   There may be a realisation that progress cannot be made without United Kingdom support.3* EtCA. appear ready,  in order to meet theirCongressional difficulties, to sponsor any scheme which can berepresented as progress towards unification without muchregard to merits.   There is strong pressure within theEuropean Assembly for integration, and though it may be doubtedhow far the Continental governments would go towards union whonit came to the point, they are likely to favour schemes for this in principle and to be ready to throw the blame for any lack ofsuccess on the United Kingdom.   There remain some rather strong feelings on the Continent, excited by our devaluation, and wecannot exclude the possibility that certain members of E.C.A.and the Office of the United States special representative(O.S.R.) will, in their anxiety to get something done,  join inthe pressure upon us, even though this&apos;may not represent either the policy of E.C.A* itself or of the United states administration.   On this I accept the view set out in yourtelegram No. I4.890 which I found very helpful.Li.. In these circumstances I think it is necessary to ensurethat the United States Secretary of State should be informed ofthe attitude which the Chancellor of the Exchequer and I havedecided to recommend to the Cabinet for adoption at the forth-coming meetings in Paris and the reasons for it.   The following paragraphs set out this attitude and I should be grateful if you would convey them in the form of a personal message toMr. Acheson.   You should tell him that we have not yet been ablet o. show this message to the full Cabinet.   I expect thesematters to come before the Cabinet on Thursday and,, if there is any change of substance, I will let you know.   You have discretion to vary the language of this communication in anyway which seems to you desirable.3. - Begins:    In preparation for the forthcoming meeting inParis&apos;of O.E.E.C. Council of Ministers,  the European assembly and the Consultative Council of the Brussels Treaty, HisMajesty&apos;s Government have reviewed their general attitudetowards proposals for closer European union or unificationwhich may be put forward.

6* In the first place, we re-affirm the obligations which they have assumed under the Convention for european economic Co-operation, the Statute of the&apos;Council of Europe,the Brussels Treaty and the bilateral agreement between theUnited States and United Kingdom.1* In accordance with these obligations, His Majosty&apos;,sGovernment have participated fully in O.E.E.C. and other european bodies and have taken the lead in the elaboration ofthe practical steps which have been taken, notably the Intra-European Payments Agreements and measures for liberalisation oftrade.   They have been prepared to go a long way and indeed totake considerable risks in order to promote these and similar measures of co-operation.   Proposals may now be put forwardwhich, if they were to be accepted by His Majesty&apos;s Government,might involve some degree of merging or integration of theUnited Kingdom economy with the economies of Western european countries.   Although no actual proposals have been formulated,or at least communicated to the United Kingdom, we have considered the general principles involved.   We must have regardto the position of the United Kingdom as a power with world wideresponsibilities for administration and defence and as theleading member of the British Commonwealth and sterling area aswell as to the general responsibilities which we have assumedunder the Atlantic Pact,  and the similar obligations under the brussels Treaty.   Finally, we wish to do nothing which is incompatible with the objectives of the communique issued afterthe Anglo-American-Canadian economic talks in &quot;Washington inSeptembe r*8* In summary, the principle^aj objective of our policy isto reconcile our position as a world power, as a member of theBritish Commonwealth, and as a member of the European community.We -believe that v/e can effect this reconciliation but that, ifwe are to do so, we cannot accept obligations in relation to western Europe which would prevent or restrict the implementation of our responsibilities elsewhere.9* In these circumstances if proposals are put forward for closer economic groupings in Europe or otherwise for thelowering of tariffs and the freeing of exchange and other financial controls and restrictions in Europe we will examinethem sympathetically.   We are in principle in favour of suchgroupings if their establishment can be proved to be in thegeneral interest of European recovery.   But we naturally expect that these proposals should be clearly formulated and discussed with us so that we can judge how they will affect our interests and can define our attitude towards them.   Thedecision whether we could support them generally must depend ontheir nature and their possible effect on us and on our widerresponsibilities,   v/e have neither the desire nor theintention to impede any sound scheme of closer European union.10* We believe that this general attitude coincides withthat of the United States Government and we hope that we maylook to them for their general support.   Ends.11* We are taking steps to inform commonwealth governments of the contents of this message.12* We do not, of course, propose to make any formal statement of this kind during the meetings in Paris, though our general attitude will be based on this policy in considering any proposals which may be put forward.

-ANNEX 0RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN THE COUNCIL OF.. EUROPE AND O.B.E.C* INTHE ECONOMIC. FIELD &apos; &apos;Report by officials* We assume that it is accepted, policy that theCouncil of Europe should not have any executive authority and,secondly, that it is the intention to make the maximum possible use of existing organisations for the discussion and carrying-out of economic policies.   Unless this policy is maintainedthere is not only danger of overlap, but the certainty ofconfusion and of an impossible strain on, man-power resources.2. The Economic Committee of the Assembly has alreadyset up four sub-committees to study specific matters and nodoubt their purpose will be to advise the Assembly so that itcan take an informed view of economic matters.   It seems clear tous also that the Assembly will discuss all economic mattars and-that it will- ha wrong to try to restrict this liberty. On tlx- otherhand governmental work on economic or any other kind ofco-operation is quite outside the province of the consultative assembly.   Any such work, assuming it were to be done in theCouncil of Europe- at all, would properly fall to the Committeeof Ministers, which is a body of governmental representatives.This body could in certain fields assume some powers of an     .executive character, although strictly speaking it is limited bythe Statute to making recommendations to governments and asking for a report on the action taken on them.   We suggest, however,that all economic work on the governmental level should.bekept in O.E.E.C., though this is not to say that we should be against the Committee of Ministers, should it wish to do so,setting up some kind of sub-committee of officials fop thepurpose of studying the economic proposals submitted to it bythe Assembly.   &quot;We hope, however, that it would still be thepolicy of the United Kingdom representatives on such a sub-committee to try as far as possible to steer executive work inthe economic field hack to O.E.E.C.    This is in accordancewith the views provisionally expressed both by the Chancellorof the Exchequer and the French Finance Minister in washington.3. There should at the present stage be no questionof O.E.E.C. becoming, or being regarded as, a body inferior instatus to the Council of Europe.   Some elements of the consultative Assembly undoubtedly hope that the Council as awhole may eventually acquire a central position of asupervisory   character over all European organisations, whetherthey deal with economic or other. affairs;   but it is in ourview much too early to accept any idea of this kind, moreparticularly as lit is impossible to tell yet what kind of balance will be struck within the Council of Europe betweenthe governmental and the non-governmental elementsrepresented by the Committee of Ministers and the Assembly.k*- In considering the relationship between the two .bodies we must bear in mind the very close association of theUnited States administration with O.E.E.C.   We must thereforebe careful not to cross wires with the United States in any arrangements we may make for the relationship betweenO.E.E.C. and the Council of Europe.

5* Bearing these considerations in mind our view isthat some latitude should be allowed about the sending of papers by O.E.E.C. to the Council of Europe.   Any question ofsubmission of papers must be considered ad hoc in the lightof the fact that we give to O.E.E.C. as the institution representingonly the executive arms of the European Governments some papersof a greater degree of security than any which we- would normallygive to the legislators of those countries.   On the other hand it is our view that it should be quite firmly laid down that -(a) any reporting of the work of O.E.E.C. to theCouncil of Europe should be carried out by the secretariat on quite firm instructions from theExecutive Committee of the Council of O.E.E.C.:(b) none of the officers of O.E.E.C.s e*g. .the Chairmanof the Council or of the Executive Committee or ofany of the other Coinmittees, and in particular norepresentatives of individual delegations, should beexpected to make reports to the Council of Europe.6* &apos; The general policy should be, of course, one of the closest collaboration between the two bodies, but thiscollaboration must be on the basis of equality between thetwo and with full recognition of the fact that the UnitedStates Government is at present directly concerned with thework of O.E.E.C. and is not directly, concerned with the work ofthe Council of Europe.




</content>
</cab>
