<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/37/0 images: 76-85</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENT - n---  - -  48Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1949SECRET Copy. No.CP. (49) 208ISth October, 1949CABINET31EUROPEAN policy memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs this paper, which is circulated for the information of my colleagues,discusses the question whether the aim of European policy should be the creationof a third world power or the consolidation of the Western world.I. IntroductionUntil about the end of 1947, when the Great Power system known as theCouncil of Foreign Ministers broke down, it was assumed, with decreasingconfidence, that the general structure of peace would be based essentially onjco-operation between the United States, the Soviet Union and the UnitedjKingdoni, which to some extent might be taken as representing the BritishCommonwealth and Empire. The breakdown on the question of Germany, how-jever, destroyed this conception, perhaps temporarily, perhaps for ever. Although(the United Nations was maintained as a kind of symbol of a real world system,and no doubt in the expectation that it would ultimately prove possible to revert to it, it was then clearly necessary to cast around for some alternative systemof security which would be capable of maintaining peace for a long period tocome.2. This process of consolidating the non-Communist world really began inJune 1947 with the announcement of the Marshall Plan and my acceptance of it.It passed from the economic to the political and military sphere early in 1948.At that time I envisaged action in three stages. The first stage was the conclusionof the Brussels Treaty, described as the hard core of the European system. Thesecond stage was its reinforcement by the power and wealth of North America.The third stage was the extension of the European system. The first stage was completed by the signature of the Brussels Treaty on 17th March, 1948. Thesecond stage was completed by the signature of the Atlantic Pact, which, for thefirst time, committed the United States and Canada to the defence of western europe. The third stage has now been initiated with the signature of the statute of the Council&apos; of Europe. It therefore seems desirable to consider carefully whatis to be the ultimate aim of this policy.3. For the moment the Brussels Treaty and the Atlantic Pact provide amilitary alliance of those free democracies of the West which are threatened bythe Soviet Government. But&apos;it has been suggested that this should be a temporaryphase, and that the real object should be to organise Western Europe into a&quot; Middle Power,&quot; co-equal with and independent of the United States and theSoviet Union alike. The supporters of this proposal admit that for a considerable period of time, and notably for such period as Western Europe is dependent forits very existence on American economic support, the European political organisation, whatever it may be, will have to lean heavily towards America andaway from the Soviet Union. At the same time it is suggested that the underlyingaim of an organisation of Europe should be the eventual creation of a system which would enable Western Europe, plus the bulk of the African continent, and37723 B
in some form of loose association with other members of the Commonwealth, to run an independent policy in world affairs which would not necessarily coincide with either Soviet or American wishes.4. This concept of a Third World Power has had many advocates. In thisl ?j country it has appealed particularly to those who find American capitalism littlemore attractive than Soviet Communism, and to those who feel a natural; dislikeof seeing this country in a dependent position. But the policy is not without itsadvocates in the United States itself. These have included, at one time at anyrate, the Planning Section of the State Department, who thought that the best way to consolidate the &quot;Western world was to build up another power-unit with a strength equivalent to that of America and Russia. It has also found favouramong the isolationists, who feel that if this unit came into existence it wouldprovide America with an excuse for retiring into her shell and leaving the task of containing Russia to the Third World Power.5. Another school of thought, more common perhaps on the Continent ofEurope than in the United States or the United Kingdom, has suggested that a third World Power of this kind, even if its physical power were less than thatof either of the other two great Powers, would by remaining neutral developan influence out of proportion to its strength, since it could hope to be courtedby both sides. The ability of a weak State to exploit its neutrality in this manneris illustrated by the conduct of Bulgaria in 1914-15 and Italy in 1939-4:0, thoughthe subsequent experiences of these two countries are not encouraging.6. All these schools of thought, different as they are, have in common theassumption that it is possible to create a workable Third World Power, indepen-dent equally of Russia and America. The object of this paper is to considerwhether this assumption is justified; whether, if the creation of a Third WorldPower is possible, it is also desirable; and, if not, what the alternatives are.II. Possible Composition of a Third World Power7. The first question that requires consideration is what the composition ofa Third World Power might be. The only serious suggestions that have been madeare that it should consist of the Commonwealth, or of Western Europe (includingthe United Kingdom) with its overseas territories, or of these groups combined.These suggested groupings may be examined under three headings, politicaleconomic and military.Commonwealth &apos;(a) Political8. There are no political tendencies in the Commonwealth to-day whichsuggest that it could successfully be consolidated as a single unit. The Common-wealth is not a unit in the same sense as the United States or the Soviet Union.It has no central authority and is unlikely to create one, and its members areincreasingly framing their policies on grounds of regional or local interests. Theonly member of the Commonwealth which might assume a position of leadershipwithin it is the United Kingdom, and it seems unlikely that any proposalsoriginating in London for a closer co-ordination of Commonwealth policy wouldbe welcomed at present. It should not be assumed that centrifugal forces arecertain to increase, and it remains true that concerted action may well be achieved in a crisis. The substantial identity of view among Commonwealth countries is undoubtedly an important influence for world peace. Nevertheless, there is no guarantee that a common policy will be followed.(b) Economic9. Since the creation of the O.E.E.C. machinery, the economic planning ofthe United Kingdom is tending to become more closely tied in with WestersEurope than with the Commonwealth. The general trend of O.E.E.C. planninghas so far been satisfactory to the sterling members of the Commonwealth. TheUnited Kingdom, however, needs to be able to speak with greater authority inParis as the representative of the whole sterling area. Moreover, a greater mutualexchange of economic information within the Commonwealth is needed if thecentral gold and dollar reserves of the sterling area are to be fully safeguardedThere is little sign that the other members of the Commonwealth would accept
;olIective planning, arrangements for the Commonwealth similar to O.E.E.C:,. butive may well hope to persuade them increasingly to discuss their long-term)roblems individually with the United Kingdom. Even so, Commonwealthjountries are likely to take the view that their needs for investment capital fornrlustrial development cannot be met by co-operation with the United Kingdommd Western Europe alone but that dollar assistance will be needed. the americans have shown reluctance in the past to use the United Kingdom as ahannel for extending dollar aid to the rest of the Commonwealth.c) Military10. The military picture is similar. As a result of the Brussels Treaty theUnited Kingdom has gone much further in military planning with western europe than it has with the Commonwealth. Moreover, the Commonwealth is noti strategic unit, and here again it must be clear to other Commonwealth members &apos;hat their defence cannot be assured without United States support. For example,he Commonwealth, even with the help of Western Europe, will not in the foresee-ible future be strong enough to hold the Middle East, which is vital to its security.d) conclusion .1. Despite the possibility of improved economic consultation, there seemsittle prospect of the United Kingdom being able to unite the Commonwealth asi single world power. The attraction exerted by the pound sterling and the RoyalSfavy is now less strong than that of the dollar and the atom bomb. An attemptto turn the Commonwealth into a Third World Power would only confront itsnembers with a direct choice between London and Washington, and thoughsentiment might point one way interest would certainly lead the other.Western Europe (including the United Kingdom) with its Overseas Territoriesa) Political12. The progress so far made in such directions as Benelux and the. Italo-?rench Customs Union is primarily economic in character, although there are)political implications. These experiments have, however, not yet reached a suffi-:i ently advanced stage to permit of optimistic conclusions regarding prospects ofnore far-reaching political unity. The new Council of Europe may graduallycreate in this old Continent a consciousness of European unity and a will to playm independent part in world affairs. But it must be recognised that centrifugaltendencies are still strong and there is a danger that the Council of Europe may;eem to give Europe a greater cohesion and strength than it in fact possesses andio encourage the Americans to retire into an isolation dangerous both for them-elves and for Europe. Whatever the tendencies may be, the fact remains thathe military and economic situation of the Western European nations is now suchhat there can be no immediate prospect of welding them into a prosperous andecure entity without American help; and even with American help it is uncertainvhether this can be achieved for some time to come..13. The above has been written without special regard to the problem ofGermany. The problem of including Germany, in whole or in part, in western europe and the effect which this would have on the possible constitution of aMrird World Power, cannot be dealt with fully within the limits of this paper.?here are many schools of thought on this topic. Some claim that western europe could only hope to achieve security and independence if, it included thevhole of Germany. Others feel that the inclusion of all Germany in any western european group would involve a serious risk of its eventual domination by aevived Reich, and moreover that Western Europe would thereby become involvedn quarrels about Germany&apos;s eastern frontiers which it would be highly desirableo avoid. Others again say that the inclusion of Western Germany in the western european group is now a foregone conclusion, that the addition of the Soviet Zone,f that ever became practicable, would not be of such weight as to alter the wholealance, and that ways can and must be found of integrating a united Germanytito the European family of nations. In any event if Western Germany, or even, unified Germany, is, after a period of years, fully integrated in the economy ofVestern Europe, that would probably not in itself result in Western europe       37723 : &apos; &apos;&apos; b 2     -
becoming an independent Power of the same order of magnitude as the soviet union or the United States, unless indeed the military as well as the economicpotential of Germany was fully developed and it is difficult to see this being accepted by the Soviet Union or even by the Western democracies themselves.(6) Economic14. Western Europe, including its dependent overseas territories, is nowpatently dependent on American aid, although in the longer run it should be ableto pay its way. It is, however, always likely to be dependent for the maintenanceof a reasonable standard of living on a large exchange of goods and services withthe Eastern bloc, with the Commonwealth and with the United States. Althoughthe O.E.E.C. countries and their dependent overseas territories now enjoy a pre-ponderance of economic potential over the Soviet orbit, this preponderance maywell disappear within ten years if Soviet plans are fulfilled. Soviet plans may be particularly limited by commitments to the satellites and by high military expendi-ture, or even by technical shortcomings in Russia itself. But it is safest to assume that, even if the economy of Western Europe is closely linked with that of theUnited States, their present joint margin of superiority over the Soviet economic system will tend to shrink.15. It is true that O.E.E.C. has shown the beginning of satisfactory economuco-operation, but the impetus has been given by the United States in the conditionswhich they imposed as a price for dollar aid. There are already signs that as theindividual countries become economically stronger and more self-sufficient the cen-trifugal tendencies are likely to increase, and it may well be that when Americanaid ceases altogether the present limited degree of European economic co-operation will not survive. We should in any case be wise not to place undue reliance on itat the expense of our relations with the Commonwealth and the United States.16. Moreover, from the United Kingdom point of view, economic integratioiwith Western Europe involves great risks which would only be worth taking ifwe could be confident that economic integration would create a unit economicalljand militarily strong enough to be capable of resisting aggression. For thtmoment there seems little prospect of such a development and we might, if we wenttoo far along this road, find Europe over-run and our own segment of the economjunable to function on its own.(c) Military17. From the military point of view, the situation is that even with Americanhelp there is nothing at present to stop the Russians occupying the entire Atlantiicoast of Europe. In ten years&apos; time Western Europe might possibly be able to holtout until full American assistance could be brought into play. Even this limiteidefensive role involves an expenditure which may well be too heavy for Europeainational incomes. Unless therefore we are prepared to effect a drastic lowering ofour present standards of living or to accept the remilitarisation of the Reich, anjthought of a Third World Power in Europe being militarily capable of resistinjRussia by itself can be dismissed.18 In actual military strength Russia is now, apart from weapons of massdestruction, vastly superior to the United States and Western Europe combinedand although, as has been said, our economic potential may for the time being to greater than that of the Russians, the difference will lessen with time. Moreoverowing to the Soviet Union&apos;s present ability rapidly to overrun Western Europtthere is a danger that American potential will be left with no area in which tideploy itself.(d) Conclusion19. Whereas in the case of the Commonwealth the principal difficulties ithe way of consolidation as a Third World Power are political, in the case oWestern Europe the difficulties lie mainly in the economic and military weaknesof its members, though the political will to union must always be doubtful.The Commonwealth and Western Europe Combined20. Unfortunately the objections to either group in isolation are not remove&apos;by their combination, and this alternative is therefore not examined in detail
Political cohesion of the Commonwealth countries with Western Europe is even less likely than with the United Kingdom, and the dangerous choice between london and Washington is hot eliminated. Moreover, the economic and militaryweaknesses of Western Europe are not significantly diminished by the additionof the Commonwealth countries other than the United Kingdom, and the needfor American support remains. Incidentally, this need for American supportunderlines the danger of even trying to create a group which could give theUnited States an excuse for believing that a buffer State had been created andthat accordingly America need not exert herself strenuously on behalf of Westerncivilisation.General Reflections on a Third World Power21. The preceding paragraphs suggest that none of the possible combinationsof Powers is likely in the near future to amount to a unit capable of pursuing apolicy independent both of the Soviet Union and of the United States. There is,moreover, a further argument which is valid in regard to any possible combination of Powers. The belief in the ability of a Third Power to exploit its independenceby a policy of neutrality and by playing off the other two Powers against eachDther is based on a total misconception of Marx-Leninist ideology. It is surelyessential to take at their face value the frequent assertions by Soviet leaders thatMarx-Leninism is the basis of their policy. This being so, they would not beprepared to establish any lasting agreement with a neutral, non-Communist ThirdWorld Power; at the most they might be prepared to make a show of reachingiuch an accommodation for tactical reasons. A policy of neutrality would inact only encourage the Soviet Union to swallow its opponents one by one and,from the point of view of the United Kingdom especially, would afford noirotection for our vital interests in the rest of the world, notably in the Middleind Far East.III. Consolidation of the, West22. The conclusion seems inescapable that for the present at any rate theilosest association with the United States is essential, not only for the purposeif standing up to Soviet aggression but also in the interests of Commonwealtholidarity and of European unity. The form which such an association shouldake is a matter for another paper, but it is perhaps worth recording the negative:conclusion that the mobilisation of general collective security on the basis ofarticle 51 of the United Nations Charter does not seem a promising method. Thetrobable result of such a process would be the establishment of a new UnitedUtions organisation without the Soviet Union or its satellites, resulting in anmwieldy bloc of countries with no organised leadership, in which the specialnterests of single countries or groups of countries would be liable to paralysection by the organisation as a whole.23. The positive arguments in favour of the consolidation of the West, inrhich at first, at any rate, the United States would be the largest single unit, maye summarised as follows : (a) As long as Russian policy continues to be based on the Marx-Leninistphilosophy which regards all non-Communist Governments as enemies,these Governments will be forced to combine, and in this sense the consolidation of the West will come about as a natural process.(6) The combination produced by this natural process, of which the AtlanticPact is the first example, represents such a vast effort that onceachieved it may in practice be very difficult to dissolve.(c) The association of the United States, Western Europe and the Common-wealth, different though their cultural backgrounds and politicalphilosophies may be, has at least in its favour a sufficient number ofcommon traditions to make the group workable. :24. There are of course some arguments on the other side. It must beecognised that in a Western system the United States will be the most powerfullember, will inevitably take the lead in a number of fields, and will no doubtxpect her views to prevail to a considerable extent. This, however, was already
the case before the signature of the Atlantic Pact: In all fields in which theUnited States makes the major contribution, whether financial, military or other-wise, it is inevitable that proportionate (although hot always determining) weightmust be given to her views. -25. At the same time experience has shown that it is usually possible to reconcile British and American views. As United Stated policy evolves fromisolation to the assumption of increasing responsibility in world affairs, heroutlook (e.g.; over colonial dependencies) is evolving also, and it has so far provedless arduous for us to find a common approach towards world problems with the americans than with most other Powers. While, therefore, extremely difficultadjustments of policy, which are inevitable in any partnership, will have to bemade under a Western system, there are not so far sufficient grounds for the fear that partnership with the United States in a Western system would involve theUnited ! Kingdom in dangerous dependence oh the United States. There is sufficient kinship of ideas to make this unlikely. We are in fact more likely tofind it difficult to reach.a common approach with Western European countries,and most of all with Germany.26. The fear is sometimes expressed that the United States might be tempted to indulge in adventurous policies, and that too close a partnership with them would add to the risk that the United Kingdom and its other partners might be involved against their will in the consequences of such policies. Although thepossibility of their adopting ill-considered and therefore dangerous policies is always with us, the likelihood Of the United States embarking on an aggressivepolicy is extremely remote. In spite of occasional violence of talk, american public opinion and the American Congress are both peace-loving and cautious,and more likely to err on the side of prudence than of rashness. Moreover ifthe United States were nonetheless to embark on adventurous policies the UnitedKingdom would almost inevitably be involved in the consequences in any case, andit may reasonably be expected that partnership with the United States in a West-em system would increase rather than diminish the opportunities for the UnitedKingdom to apply a brake to American policy if necessary.27. The possibility must also be considered that a slump might occur inthe United States which would have serious repercussions on the economies of theI United Kingdom and of Western European countries. This is true. But the effect would be much the same whether a Western system comes into being or not. More-over, here again the existence of a Western system improves the outlook for fruitfuldiscussion on economic policies between the members.28. There is no necessary contradiction between the consolidation of a western system and a much greater unification and strengthening of Europe. Itis only the concept of Western Europe as a Third World Power acting independentlyboth of the United Spates and of the Commonwealth, in other words as a ThirdWorld Power in the strict sense of the term, which is inconsistent with the consolidation of Western system.29. During the next ten to twenty years the economic dependence of western european countries on the United States ought to disappear, and their ability tomake a valid military contribution to a Western system ought to increase. even to-day it is a mistake to regard the relationship of the Western European countries,and particularly of the United Kingdom with the United States as one of completedependence. In fact the United States has no desire to find herself confronted with a Western Europe under Communist domination, or a Western Europe whichis completely neutral. On the contrary, the United States recognises that theUnited Kingdom and the Commonwealth, and to a lesser extent the WesternContinental Europe, are essential to her defence and safety. Already it is, apartfrom the economic field, a case of partial interdependence rather than of completedependence. As time goes by the elements of dependence ought to diminish andthose of inter-dependence to increase. The United Kingdom in particular, by virtue of her leading, position both in Western Europe and in the Commonwealth,ought to play a larger and larger part in a Western system.30. It must, however, be appreciated that the Western system is coming into being under the pressure of Soviet policy. It is probiably fair to say that it isa system desirable in itself, since had it been in existence at the time the wars of1914 and 1939 might well have been avoided.   But whether this is so or not, it
night well prove that, if Soviet pressure were relaxed as a result of some majoractical deviation, the development of the system might be arrested in proportionis the compelling cause of the danger from the Soviet Union diminished. Thisispect of the question will form the subject of another study.31. There are two further points which require to be borne in mind in:onnexion with the consolidation of the West, though they cannot be fully developedIvithin the limits of this paper. The first is that consolidation of the West cannot[ie solely a matter of agreement between governments. It must also involve annternal consolidation of the peoples of the Western countries and a rejectionjif Communist influence.32. Secondly, it may prove to be the case that the consolidation of the Westia a passive sense will not prove to be enough, and that the only final hope for aiettled world will be that the ideas it represents and the system which incorporates;hese ideas should spread eastwards.IV. Conclusions33.   The general conclusion of this paper may be summarised as follows : (a) The Commonwealth alone cannot form a Third World Power equivalentto the United States or the Soviet Union.(b) Commonwealth solidarity is more likely to be promoted by the consolidation of the West than by the formation of a Third WorldPow r independent of America.(c) A weak, neutral Western Europe is undesirable and a strong independentWestern Europe is impracticable at present and could only come about, if at all, at the cost of the remilitarisation of Germany.(d) The best hope of security for Western Europe lies in a consolidation ofthe West on the lines indicated by the Atlantic Pact.(e) During the next 10-20 years, Western Europe, provided it continues onits policy of co-operation, should emerge from economic and even from military dependence on the United States but the two areas willremain interdependent.(/) The United Kingdom will have an increasingly important part to play-in the consolidated West, and must also seek to maintain its specialrelations with the United States of America.E. B.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,ISth October, 1949.




</content>
</cab>
