<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/37/0 images: 454-457</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY of HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1949SECEETCP. (49) 21626th October, 1949CABINETGOVERNMENT expenditure memorandum by the Prime minister in my memorandum of 4th August (CP. (49) 170), I asked all Ministers incharge of Civil Departments to undertake forthwith a-searching scrutiny of theexpenditure for which they are iresponsible. The reports made by Ministers in response to that memorandum provided the material for .the proposals subse-quently considered by the Economic Policy Committee for the reduction in the rateof Government supply expenditure, as part of the programme of measures to combat inflation. Decisions were taken by the Cabinet on 21st October (CM. (49)61st Conclusions, Minute 2) and I announced them to the House of Commons on24th October.2. I now ask Ministers in charge of Civil Departments to press forward with the action required to give detailed effect to the Governments decisions.8. The reports rendered by the Civil Departments in response to my memo-randum of 4th August contained proposals for measures of economy under thetwo heads mentioned in paragraph 3 of that memorandum (a) curtailment of services which are not essential to major Government policy, and (b) more econo-mical administration of policies which must be retained. Now that decisions havebeen taken on the economy programme as a whole, action can be taken on theproposals made by Departments under these heads, and I ask the Ministers con-cerned to give effect to them at oncej subject to the following provisos : . (i) I recognise that in a number of cases conditions are attached to themeasures proposed, and that in those cases the economies cannot besecured till the conditions have been cleared. For example, somemeasures depend upon negotiation with local authorities or public corporations. Others are proposed by one Department but requirethe agreement or participation of another.  I ask all the Departments37760CopyNo. 31
concerned in such cases to enter into the negotiations at once and topress them as matters of urgency, in order to give effect to the Governmenfs intention that all practicable economies should be put intoeffect as early as possible,(ii) It should not be assumed that the proposals made by Departmentsnecessarily represent, in every instance, the limit to which they cango in curtailment of services and in administrative economies. Allare subject to further scrutiny by the Treasury, under the directionof the Chancellor of the Exchequer. &quot;While Departments should actnow on the proposals already made, they should be ready to discuss with the Treasury any steps that can be taken to modify or add tothese proposals in order to increase the savings, present and prospective-tive, that may be achieved.4. The possibilities will naturally vary between Departments, according tothe nature of the proposals made by each. Detailed action will be taken by theTreasury with each Department, on the basis of the facts and figures furnished by Departments in response to my memorandum of 4th August.5. Separate arrangements are being made with the Ministers concerned forcarrying out the measures in the economy programme which were not proposed under paragraph 3 of my memorandum of 4th August, but which follow from the major decisions of Government policy taken by the Cabinet.C, R. A.10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,26th October, 1949.



</content>
</cab>
