<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/37/0 images: 504-529</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S&apos; GOVERNMENT)SECRETINDIA - CONSEQUENTIAL LEGISLATION TO DEAL WITHTHE POSITION WHICH WILL ARISE WHEN INDIA BECOMES A REPUBLICOn 29th August (C.M. (49) 54th Conclusions, Minute 4)the Cabinet agreed(1)    that legislation on the lines indicated inparagraph 3 of CP. (49) 181 should be passed before the new Indian constitution came intooperation on 26th January, 1950;(2)    that the Commonwealth Relations Office should beauthorised to inform the Government of India ofthe general lines of this proposed legislation,,should seek to elucidate their attitude on the nationality question and should try to secure their agreement that persons of United Kingdomdescent and. connection who were qualified anddesired to become Indian citizens should beable to do so and at the same time to retain their status as British subjects or as UnitedKingdom citiaensj(3)    that a final decision on the nationality provisions to be included in the proposed legislation shouldbe taken in the light of the outcome of these discussions with, the Indian Government;(4)    that the Secretary of state for commonwealth relations, in consultation with the Lav/ Officers,should submit a memorandum on the liability to military service of Indian citisens resident inthe United Kingdom.2. The memorandum on the liability to military serviceof Indian citizens in the United Kingdom has been circulatedseparately as CP. (49)  218.3* An opportunity was taken to discuss with Sir GirjaBajpai,  the Secretary for External Affciirs in the Government ofIndia, when he accompanied Pandit Nehru on his visit to london in October, the procedure which should be followed to obtain theviews of the Government of India,   sir Girja asked that hepersonally might be given an indication of the main points ofprinciple on which the views of the Government of India weredesired in order that he might discuss them with Pandit Nehruin the United States.   lie offered, to interrupt his stay in theUnited states to return to London early in November for furthertalks.   A copy of an aide memo ire sent to sir Girja isattached (Annex &apos;A&apos;):    a copy of this was also communicatedCP. (49) 2243RD NOVEMBER,  1949COPY NO.^ &apos;cabinet memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal

to Sir Girja&apos;s deputy in India, in order that Sir Girja might also he provided with the comments of the Indian GovernmentDepartments concerned before his return to London*   A draftBill has meanwhile been prepared by Parliamentary Counsel,in consultation with the Commonwealth Relations Office and theother United Kingdom Departments concerned, indicating thelegislative provision which will be required if the UnitedKingdom proposals are accepted by the Government of India.A copy of this Bill is also attached.k* It will be seen that the draft Bill provides(a) That after the establishment of the Republic ofIndia citizens of India shall not be Britishsubjects, t hou gh t he e xp r e s s i on ;! C ommonwe a11 hcitizen1&apos; shall nevertheless continue to includecitizens of India.   It will be necessary toobtain a definite indication of the desire ofthe Government of India in this respect, and itis hoped that they will agree that the term&quot;Commonwealth citizen&apos;-&apos; may continue to be soapplied.    It is not considered that there would bethe least prospect of their agreeing to the continuation of the status or description^British subject&apos;1.    The descriptions ^british subject&apos;1 and :Commonwealth citizen&quot; have infact the same meaning under the british nationality Act, 19ho.(b) That the existing l-aw of the United Kingdom and colonies should continue to have effect ;1in relationto India and persons and tilings appertaining&apos; toor connected with India as it would, have had hadIndia not become a Republic11.    This would restorede facto, the position altered by the decision that&apos; Indians should cease to be British subjects;would cover Indian ships,  goods and aircraft;    andwould give to the Government of India in thiscountry all the exemptions which the Crown enjoys(for example, freedom from taxation on property).(c) That persons resident in India who can prove bothclose association with the United Kingdom anddescent in the male line from   a United kingdom or Colonial ancestor,, but who may be unableto conform with the other requirements of the relevant provision of the British Rationality Act,192+8, may nevertheless be registered as UnitedKingdom citizens,  since otherwise such persons would lose their British nationality.5. It is hoped to persuade the Government of India toagree that   a  United Kingdom citizen may also,  if qualified,possess,  or continue to possess, Indian citizenship, evenif he acquires United Kingdom citizenship voluntarily.    It isproposed,  in the course of discussion with Sir Girja Bajpai,to make clear that the normal doctrine of master nationalitywill apply,  i*e. when in India a person having dual citizenshipwill be primarily an Indian citizen and when in the UnitedKingdom and Colonies he will be primarily   a United Kingdomcitizen.    It is important -that this principle should be estab-lished because many Indians in the- colonies will have dualcitizenship.    It will be necessary also to confirm that theGovernment of India&apos; will not raise objection to the continuanceof the practice by which Indians resident in the United Kingdomover two years become, with certain exceptions, liable to con-oeription in the United Kingdom forces:    this ernes ti on is dealtwith in detail in CP. (2+9) 218,

v* v&quot;: 9&amp; V w6. If, however, Indians resident in the United Kingdom-re to continue to be given all the rights and privileges..hich they at present enjoy it is important to ensure thatthe Government of India will reciprocate to the greatest degreepossible so far as citizens of the United Kingdom and Coloniesresident in or visiting India are concerned.    There isunfortunately no prospect of obtaining national treatment for United Kingdom companies operating in India and it is not considered that it will be possible to obtain completereciprocity even in the treatment of persons.   The. indian constitution, for example, provides that only Indian citizensmay sit in the legislatures, both of the Union of India and ofthe States, and that only Indian citizens may hold importantoffices of state,  and elections are to be on the basis of adultsuffrage i;that is,  that every citizen who is not less than11 years of age shall be entitled to voteu.    It is possible,however, that the Indian Parliament could, under theConstitution, provide for other persons to vote also, and it ishoped that it may be possible to arrange at the talks with sir Girja Bajpai for a. statement of the intention of theGovernment of India to introduce legislation whereby UnitedKingdom citizens resident in India shall be eligible for the franchise on the same terms as Indian citizens.   From apractical point of view the individual right which it isimportant to obtain in India is non-foreign treatment,  including,in particular, freedom of entry and from deportation (exceptof genuine undesirables) and freedom from requirements imposed on aliens such as registering and-reporting to the police.7. Sir Girja Bajpai will arrive in London on 8th November.It is desirable that a copy of the draft Bill should becoaaunicated to him in the course of discussions which havebeen arranged for 9th and 10th November, and. I invite mycolleagues to agree that this should be done.1A *

6, If, however, Indians resident in the United kingdom are to continue to he given all the rights and privileges&apos;which they at present enjoy it is important to ensure thatthe Government of India will reciprocate to the greatest degreepossible so far as citizens of the United Kingdom and Coloniesresident in or visiting India are concerned.   There isunfortunately no prospect of obtaining national treatment for United Kingdom companies operating in India and it is not considered that it will be possible to obtain completereciprocity even in the treatment of persons.    The IndianConstitiition, for example, provides that only Indian citizensmay sit in the legislatures, both of the Union of India and ofthe States, and that only Indian citizens may hold importantoffices of state,  and elections are to be on the basis of adultsuffrage i;that is, that every citizen who is not less than21 years of age shall be entitled to vote&quot;.    It is possible,however, that the Indian Parliament could, under theConstitution, provide for other persons to vote also, and it ishoped that it may be possible to arrange at the talks with sir Girja Bajpai for a. statement of the intention of theGovernment of India to introduce legislation whereby UnitedKingdom citizens resident in India shall be eligible for the franchise on the same terms as Indian citizens.   Prom apractical point of view the individual right which it isimportant to obtain in India is non-foreign treatment, including,in particular, freedom of entry and from deportation (exceptof genuine undesirables) and freedom from requirements imposed on aliens such as registering and reporting to the police.,7. Sir Girja Bajpai will arrive in London on 8th November.It is desirable that a copy of the draft Bill should beconrmmicated to him in the course of discussions which havebeen arranged for 9th and 10th November, and. I invite mycolleagues to agree that this should be done.A-

AIDE MEMOIRS ON THE LEGISLATION PROPOSEDTO BE ENACTED BY THE UNITED KINGDOMGOVERNMENT, TO DEAL WITH THE CONSEQUENTIALMATTERS ARISING WEEN INDIA BECOMES are public.1. The minute on preferential treatment agreed by theMeeting of the Commonwealth Prime Ministers in April 1949(P.M.1.1.  (49) 5 Item &apos;iv) recorded,(l)    That all countries cf the Commonwealth shouldcontinue to regard themselves as not foreignin relation to ore another;(2)    That each Government within the commonwealth should take such steps as may be necessary,whether by legislation or otherwise, to enable it to maintain the right to accord preferential treatment, as has been customary, to the citizensand trade of other Commonwealth countries, buteach Government would remain free to determine the extent of that preferential treatment and the precise method of according it.Consideration has been given to the legislation requiredin the United Kingdom to continue to accord to India after she^ecomes a Republic the same preferential treatment under Unitedkingdom law and the law of Colonial territories as is received byother Commonwealthi countries.    (Broadly speaking this treatment is at present national treatment in the law of the United Kingdomand Colonies for citizens and interests of Commonwealth countriesend preferential treatment for their goods, though in certainColonial territories the principle of national treatment is some-vmat modified in respect of all British subjects not permanentlyresident there.)Hitherto Indians in the United Kingdom and Coloniesnave received this treatment by virtue of be in; British subjects,At present India is part of His Majesty&apos;s dominions and Indians^re British subjects.     When India becomes a Republic it willpease to be part of His Majesty&apos;s dominions, and, though it mightpossible to maintain that Indians nevertheless continue to be british subjects by virtue of Section 1 of the British Nationalityjvet, 1948, it is assumed that this interpretation of the law&apos;0Uld not be acceptable to the Government of India.    Moreover,such an interpretation is open to dispute, since it could be argued that when the British Nationality Act was passed India was^eluded in Section 1 because she was a self-governing part of^-s Majesty&apos;s dominions and that, once she ceases to be this,JMians will lose the status they enjoy in the United Kingdom andpolonies as British subjects.      It therefore seems necessary toeSlslate on the lines indicated in paragraph 4.In view of India&apos;s continuing membership of the^imonwoalth the United Kingdom Government would, subject to whatajUows, be disposed to give to Indian citizens the same position  the ^ law of this country and. of the Colonies as heretofore.&apos;;6 United Kingdom Government therefore contemplate passingdelation which will have the effect that a person shall not be a

British subject by reason only that he is a citizen of India butthe expression &quot;Commonwealth citizen&quot; shall continue to includecitizens of India whether they arc- or arc not British subjects&quot;;and also that notwithstanding that Indian citizens arc no longerBritish subjects, existing laws in force in the United Kingdom and colonies shall (with adaptation where necessary)  continue to apply in relation to India and persons and things connected with india as it would have if India had not become a Republic.     Theintention would be to maintain that position in future legislation by including the necessary provisions in it on each occasion.5. Before, however,  it is finally decided to legislate in thi;way, the United Kingdom Government desire to ascertain from theGovernment of India whether action on these lines would be acceptable to them and how they would propose to treat citizens of the United Kingdom and Colonies in India, having regard inparticular to the minute of the Commonwealth Prime MinistersMeeting referred to in paragraph 1 above.      In this connection it is noted that the Indian Constitution,  in its original draft,prepared before the recent Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos; Meeting,drew a distinction only between Indian citizens and foreigners,but the United Kingdom Government assume that it is not theintention of the Government of India to treat citizens of theUnited Kingdom and Colonies as aliens.    If the United KingdomGovernment promote legislation of the kind proposed, they are bound to be faced with enquiry in Parliament as to the policy ofthe Government of India in this respect towards the UnitedKingdom and Colonies in India and they would be glad to know theGovernment of India&apos;s attitude on this subject before they reachfinal decisions on the form of their own legislation.      TheUnited Kingdom Government hope that the Government of India willbe able to give them an assurance which could be made public thaton the basis of reciprocity they would be ready to provide intheir law for the treatment of citizens of the United Kingdom and colonies as if they were,citizens in all matters affecting therights and duties of citizenship.6. In addition to these general issues certain more detailedquestions arise in the sphere of nationality and citizenship onwhich the United Kingdom Government would be glad to know theviews and intentions of the Government of India, before finallydeciding what provision to make in United Kingdom law.7. The Government of India are aware of the general scheme of nationality and citizenship within the Commonwealth which was .agree a upon in principle at the Commonwealth Prime Ministers&apos;meeting in 1946 and was further elaborated&apos;at the Britishcommonwealth Conference on Nationality and Citizenship in 1947.+ i Principle of this scheme,, which is embodied, in the   .%n,onality Act, 1948,. was that each Commonwealth countryferine its own citizens and that all citizens so definedwouio. nave the status of British subjects.3Hitherto all persons born in India have been Britishsubjects by virtue of the fact that India has been part of Kisthe    -l- S d?minions*-     This will cease to be the position whennrn^neV&apos;VIrdian Constitution comes into operation and the provisionWhilr-S ln. Paragraph 4 above is made in United Kingdom law.ivroioo-,0--  Un3-,tGa Kingdom Government readily assent to theper&quot;oni01&quot;nn   lt it is for the Government of India to decide whathave nn becorae Indian citizens, they consider (and they- ^ no.,,doubt -that the Government of India will agree)  that

persons resident in Indie, who arc descended in the mole line froma person born or naturalised in the United Kingdom or theColonies and have a close connection with the United Kingdom ora Colony should not be deprived of their status as Britishsubjects without their own consent.      Article 5 of the new indian constitution recently approved provides that domicile in India isthe basic requirement for qualification for Indian citizenshipand it is understood that for this purpose the Government ofIndia will use the normal conception of domicile which, broadly speaking,is that a person&apos;s domicile is in the country whore hehas taken up his fixed habitation.    On this basis many membersof what may be called the United Kingdom community in India willnot become Indian citizens since they are resident in India merely for the purpose of carrying on a business, profession or callingand have not taken up their fixed habitation in India.    Butthere will be some members of this community who,  so far as canbe judged from the text of Article 5, will become Indian citizensand it is desired to reach an understanding with the Government ofIndia on the position of such persons.9. The persons referred to in the last sentence ofparagraph 8 fall into two main groups.10, First, there are persons who are or may hereafterbecome, citizens of the United Kingdom and Colonies under existing United Kingdom law.     These include (without any actionon their part) persons born in India whose fathers were born ornaturalised in the United Kingdom and Colonies: and persons born in India whose fathers were born outside the United Kingdom and colonies but who under Section 12 (6) of the British nationality act, 1948, have become citizens of the United Kingdom and colonies by registration; and sundry others.      Some of these persons may qualify for Indian citizenship under the Constitution,and it is assumed that tho provision in the Indian Constitution inregard to the voluntary acquisition of the citizenship of aforeign state is not intended to apply to citizenship of theUnited Kingdom and Colonies.       The United Kingdom Governmentwould be glad to know whether this assumption is correct.      this position would merely be the reverse of the position provided forin Article 5C of the Indian Constitution which will allow aperson who is a citizen of tho United Kingdom and Colonies toacquire Indian citizenship by registration.    Such a person wouldnot, under existing United Kingdom law, lose his citizenshipI of the United Kingdom and Colonies.s[ii- Secondly, there is the class of person who is for the;time being a British subject and is descended in the male line&apos; from a person born or naturalised in the United Kingdom or the^olonies and has a close connection with the United Kingdom or aloJr?3&apos;&apos;&apos; but wh0 by reason Qf the residential condition in section^bj^of the British Nationality Act, 1948, is not eligible forregistracion as a citizen of the United Kingdom and Colonies.borne of these will not of course qualify for Indiana citizenship,in which case they will become citizens of United Kingdom anduoioriies under Section 13 (s) of the British Nationality Act.Jl+C. *f.*0 d0 qualify to become Indian citizens, some may,aout intending to return to the United Kingdom or a Colony for

persons resident in Indie, who are descended in the male line froma person born or naturalised in the United Kingdom or theColonies and have a close connection with the United Kingdom ora Colony should not bo deprived of their status as Britishsubjects without their own consent.     Article 5 of the now indian constitution recently approved provides that domicile in India isthe basic requirement for qualification for Indian citizenshipand it is understood that for this purpose the Government ofIndia v/ill use the normal conception of domicile which, broadly speaking, is that a person&apos;s domicile is in the- country where hehas taken up his fixed habitation.    On this basis many membersof what may be called the United Kingdom community in India willnot become Indian citizens since they are resident in India merely for the purpose of carrying on a business, profession or callingand have not taken up their fixed habitation in India.   Butthere- will be some members of this community who, so far as canbe judged from the text of Article 5, will become Indian citizensand it is desired to reach an understanding with the Government ofIndia, on the position of such persons.9. The persons referred to in the last sentence ofparagraph 8 fall into two main groups.10. First, there are persons who are or may hereafterbecome, citizens of the United Kingdom and Colonies under existing United Kingdom law.     These include (without any actionon their part) persons born in India whose fathers worci born ornaturalised in the-United Kingdom and Colonies: and persons .born in India whose fathers were born outside the United Kingdom and colonies but who under Section 12 (6) of the British nationality act, 1948, have become citizens of the United Kingdom and colonies by registration; and sundry others.     Some of those persons may qualify for Indian citizenship under the Constitution,and it is assumed that the provision in the Indian Constitution inregard to the voluntary acquisition of the citizenship of aforeign state is not intended to apply to citizenship of theUnited Kingdom and Colonies.       The United Kingdom Governmentwould be glad to know whether this assumption is correct.     this position would merely be the reverse of the position provided forin Article 50 of the Indian Constitution which will allow aperson who is a citizen of the- United Kingdom and Colonies toacquire Indian citizenship by registration.    Such a person wouldnot, under existing United Kingdom law, lose his citizenship of the United Kingdom and Colonies.11. Secondly, there is the class of person who is for the   ,time being a British subject and is descended in the male line from a person born or naturalised in the United Kingdom or theColonies and has a close connection with the United Kingdom or a colony, but who by reason of the residential condition in Section12(6) of the British Nationality Act, 1948, is not eligible for registration as a citizen of the United Kingdom and Colonies.Some of these will not of course qualify for Indiana citizenship,in which case they v/ill become citizens of United Kingdom and colonies under Section 13 (2) of the British Nationality Act.Of those who do qualify to become Indian citizens, sotfie may,without intending to return to the United Kingdom or a Colony for

e\ jr* *-iresidencey nevertheless&apos; attach great importance to hereditary andother ties with the United Kingdom or its Colonies;    and be anxious on that account to retain British nationality, which they/ould be able to do only by becoming citizens of the United Kingdommid Colonies.      The United Kingdom Government are disposedaccordingly to ease the conditions in Section 12(6) of the UnitedKingdom Act,  in&apos; its application to India by extending its operation until 1st January, 1951 or 1952, and by withdrawing the requirement as to intention to return to the United Kingdom and colonies for ordinary residence.      As regards children born inIndia of such families, they propose- to take such steps as willenable them also to possess citizenship of the United Kingdomand Colonies.IS. There is a separate matter of importance to the Governmentof the United Kingdom.    As the Government of India is aware,under the new system of Commonwealth citizenship british nationality is to depend on the possession of the citizenship of a commonwealth country.      When the British Nationality Act 1948, waspassed most Commonwealth countries had not yet passed citizenshiplaws, and it was therefore necessary to preserve the british nationality of persons who wore- born in or otherwise belonged tothose countries.      This was done by transitional provisions in theAct.   Briefly speaking, a person belonging to a particularCommonwealth country which had not yet passed a citizenship lav/remained a British subject without citizenship until that countrypassed a citizenship law.      The intention was that, thereupon, ifthe law in question made him a citizen of that country he wouldbecome a British subject through that citizenship under Section 1;f the United Kingdom law;    if not,  Section 13 (2) preserved his-British nationality by making him thereafter a citizen of theUnited Kingdom and Colonies.      The passing of the citizenship lawis thus an essential part of the process;  and under Section 32(8)it is also essential that the law should be declared to be acitizenship law for the purpose of an order made in the UnitedKingdom which can, however, only be made at the request of thegovernment of the country which passed the law.      It seems clearthat notwithstanding the forthcoming change in India&apos;s status,the nationality provisions of the Indian Constitution are to beregarded as a citizenship law for this purpose, and it is hopedthat the Government of India will be prepared to make thenecessary request.      In view of the provision which it is proposed,in paragraph 4 above,  to make in United Kingdom law in regard tome position of Indian citizens, such a declaration would not have -the effect of making Indian citizens British subjects.     without it the citizenship of many persons who were born in India and will-not become citizens of India under the Constitution would remainindefinitely in suspense, a condition which iti would be difficult -&apos;j3 ask them to accept.13. The Government of the United Kingdom v/ould bo gratefulif the views of the Government of India on the above matters couldoe communicated to them as soon as possible.    It is essential that legislation in this country should be introduced in November andthey would therefore be grateful to have the Government of India s-hservations by the middle of November at latest.

jSECRETIndia (Consequential Provisions)ARRANGEMENT OF GLAUSESClause1.  Provisions as to nationality.2.  Provisions as to existing law generally.3.  Short title.205-2A

12 &amp; 13 Geo. 6 India(Consequential Provisions)DRAFTOF AB  I  L  LTOMake provision for certain matters arising in view of a.d. 1949India*s becoming a Republic while remaining a memberof the Commonwealth.E it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by andwith the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and temporal, and  Commons, in1 this present parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5   1. (1) On and after the date of India&apos;s becoming a Republic Provisions as(that is to say, the twenty-sixth day of January, nineteen hundred t0 nationality,and fifty, being the day fixed by the Constitution of India enacted by the Constituent Assembly for the coming into force of theConstitution) [On and after the date declared for the purposeso of this Act by Order of His Majesty in Council as being the dateof India&apos;s becoming a Republic], a person shall not be a british subject by reason only that he is a citizen of India, but theexpression &quot; Commonwealth citizen &quot; shall continue to includecitizens of India whether they are or are not British subjects.5 (2) Subsections (1) and (2) of section one of the british nationality Act, 1948, shall have effect subject to the provisionsof the preceding subsection.(3) Notwithstanding anything in subsection (8) of section thirty-two of the said Act, the expression &quot; citizenship law &quot; in!0that Act means, in relation to India, Part II of the said Con- ostitution [of the Constitution of India enacted by the Constituent205 A 2
2 India 12 &amp; 13 Geo. 6(Consequential Provisions)A.D. 1949 Assembly], and the said Part II shall be deemed for the purposesof that Act to have taken effect in India on the said twenty-sixthday of January [on the date declared as aforesaid].(4) Subsection (6) of section twelve of the said Act (which enables certain persons who would have become citizens of theUnited Kingdom and Colonies on the date of the commencementof that Act but for their citizenship or potential citizenship ofa country mentioned in subsection (3) of section one of that Act,and who make application before the first day of January nineteenhundred and fifty for the purpose, to be registered as citizens of i\the United Kingdom and Colonies) shall, in relation to personswho were on the date of the commencement of that Act potentiallycitizens of India, have effect as if (a) for the reference to the first day of January, nineteenhundred and fifty there were substituted a reference to the first day of January, nineteen hundred and fifty-two;&amp; (b) at the end of paragraph (a) (which requires the Secretaryof State to be satisfied that an applicant is descended inthe male line from a person having the qualifications ao)therein mentioned) there had been inserted the words&quot; or is descended in the male fine from a person born in the part of Ireland known at the passing of this Actas Eire &quot; ; and(c) paragraph (b) (which requires the Secretary of State to 2jlbe satisfied that an applicant intends to make hisordinary place of residence within the United Kingdomand Colonies) were omitted.(5) References respectively to a citizen of India and to citizens of India shall be inserted, after the references to a British subject and to British subjects, in the following enactments in the said act, that is to say, (a) in subsection (1) of section three (which limits criminalliability in the case of a British subject who is not a citizen of the United Kingdom and Colonies); 35 j(b) in the definitions in subsection (1) of section thirty-twoof the expression &quot; alien &quot; (which excludes a person whois a British subject), and of the expression &quot; naturalisedperson &quot; (which includes a person who became a british subject by virtue of a certificate of naturalisation); and 401(c) in so much of Part I of the Fourth Schedule as relates to the Act of Settlement (which specifies a provision inthat Act as repealed so far as it relates to Britishsubjects).Provisions as      2. (1) All existing law to which this section extends, other 45 jto existing law than the provisions of the British Nationality Act, 1948, shall,generally.       unless and until provision to the contrary is made by the authorityhaving power to alter that law and subject to the provisions of
12 &amp; 13 Geo. 6 India(Consequential Provisions)subsection (4) of this section, have the same effect in relation   A.D. 1949to India, and persons and things in any way belonging to orconnected With India, as it would have had if India had not become a Republic and subsection (1) of section one of this Act5 had not been enacted.(2) In this section the expression &quot; existing law &quot; means law which, whether being a rule of law, or a provision of an Act ofParliament or of any other enactment or instrument whatsoever,is in force on the said twenty-sixth day of January [on the dateio declared as aforesaid], or comes into force after that date by virtue of provision for its so coming into force in an Act ofParliament or other enactment or instrument passed or made before that date.(3) This section extends to existing law which has effect as15 law of, or of any part of, the United Kingdom, a colony, aprotectorate or a United Kingdom trust territory, and also, sofar as concerns law which cannot be amended by a law of thelegislature thereof, to existing law which has effect as law ofSouthern Rhodesia or of any part thereof.20 The references in this subsection to a colony, to a protectorate and to a United Kingdom trust territory, shall be construed asif they were references contained in the British Nationality Act,1948.(4) His Majesty may by Order in Council make such modifica-25 tions of any existing law to which this section extends (other thanthe provisions of the British Nationality Act, 1948) as may appear to him to be necessary or expedient in View of India&apos;sbecoming a Republic while remaining a member of the Common-wealth, and subsection (1) of this section shall apply to any such.50 law as modified by such an Order, save in so far as the contraryintention appears in the Order, unless and until provision to thecontrary is made by the authority having power to alter that law.1(5) An Order in Council under this section (a) may be made either before or after the said twenty-sixth35 day of January [the date declared as aforesaid];(b) may be revoked or varied by a subsequent Order inCouncil; and(c) shall be subject to annulment in pursuance of a resolution of either House of Parliament.40 (6) Any increase attributable to an Order in Council underthis section in sums payable out of moneys provided by parliament or out of the Consolidated Fund of the United Kingdom or the growing produce thereof shall be defrayed out of moneys soprovided, or out of that Fund or the growing produce thereof,45 as the case may be.3. This Act may be cited as the India (Consequential Pro- Short title,visions) Act, 1949.
secretIndia (Consequential Provisions)DRAFTOF ABILLTo make provision for certain matters arising in view of India&apos;s becoming are public while remaining a member ofthe Commonwealth.XCI-H (4)29th October, 1949205-2(73953)



</content>
</cab>
