<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/37/0 images: 630-633</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT)S: E C RET C.P. (49)   232 COPY NO. 1111TH NOVEMBER,  1949CABINETTHE EAST AFRICAN GROUNDNUTS scheme memorandum &quot;by the Secretary; of state for the ColoniesAfter studying the paper circulated by the Ministerof Pood (CP. (49) 231), I think that he is right in recommending that the groundnuts scheme should go on.    I agreefully with his reasons for taking this view.    In particular,I strongly endorse what he says in paragraph 19 of his memorandum.    It would in my view be a most grave decision toabandon the scheme before it has had a long enough trial.The operations in Africa have been going on for less than three years and the Corporation itself has been responsiblefor only just over eighteen months.    In the early stages thescheme was hampered by lack of experience of large-scale bushclearing in Africa, by the necessity to use secondhand clearingequipment, by severe climatic conditions and the setting ofunattainable targets, and by the emphasis on the need to producelarge amounts of groundnuts quickly to help meet the general shortage of oilseed.   As a result of the experience gained sofar clearing costs have already been greatly reduced and will,we hope, be reduced further.    Agricultural operations are not even yet on a large enough scale to make any precise estimateof the economics of the scheme possible.   In my view it mustbe carried on for a further period and on a large enoughscale to make a useful judgment possible at the end of thatperiod:    the mere carrying on of pilot schemes in the threeareas would not be sufficient.2. For this reason, 1 think that the scheme should proceed during the next four years on the general lines proposed by the Corporation and the Minister of Pood.    this plan involves a very heavy cut both in the acreage to be cleared and in the capital investment in the scheme up to1954.   Without expressing an opinion on the actual figuresit is clear that any further cut in the acreage below thefigure suggested by the Minister of Pood would increase theburden of overheads and thus reduce the chances of ultimatesuccess u3. I warmly welcome the Minister of Pood&apos;s suggestion inparagraph 27 of the memorandum that there should be regularconsultation between the Corporation and my agricultural adviserson the technical aspects of the scheme.    I hope that this cancover not only crop rotation and selection,  so that the possi-bliity of a greater degree of diversification of crops can beconsidered, but also the general organisation of production sothat the experience which my agricultural advisers have gained of methods of mechanical cultivation can be drawn upon.    In Tanganyika itself the liaison between the Corporation and the Tanganyika Government is satisfactory both in technicalagricultural matters and in other fields.A * C J .Colonial Office, S.W.I.




</content>
</cab>
