<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/216/12 images: 396-398</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT0 9C(83) 12 COPY NO6 May 1983CABINETFUTURE OF THE INNER LONDON EDUCATION AUTHORITYMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Education and ScienceThe Inner London Education Authority (ILEA) - details at Annex A - islegally a special committee of the Greater London Council (GLC). Theabolition of the GLC would open the way for improving the arrangements foreducation in inner London.    I recommend a scheme which retains the advan-tages of what exists and removes its worst defects.2. A single education authority for the whole of inner London has provedadvantageous in two important respects:1. It has secured further and higher education, much of it servingstudents from far beyond inner London, which is - despite somenotorious blemishes - in general good and economically run.2. It serves, much more than the GLC, as an instrument for redistri-buting for local government purposes the exceptionally high rateableresources of Westminster and the City of London: some  400 million ayear, which could otherwise be obtainable only from a Government-imposed levy on these two authorities, or from the Exchequer or other,poorer, local authorities outside London, is made automaticallyavailable through the education precept for inner London.A BETTER SINGLE AUTHORITY3. But as now constituted the single authority has shown glaring weaknesses. iIn particular its schools, notably the secondary schools, are not performingwell despite very high expenditure and much waste.    To tackle this problem Ipropose that the ILEA should be replaced by a Joint Board, consisting entirely Iof nominees of the 12 inner London boroughs and the City of London. Theauthorities whose ratepayers pay the education precept would then in effect be Iresponsible also for the education element in their rate levy.    This bringingtogether of managerial and financial responsibility is bound to encourage agreater degree of financial prudence.4. Although the representatives of each borough would collectively determine Ian education precept which would be the same for all ratepayers, the rate-payers of Westminster and the City would provide about half of the JointBoard&apos;s rate-borne income.    It is a well-established electoral principle thateach elector&apos;s vote should be given as nearly as possible equal weight; butthe wholly exceptional incidence of the Joint Board&apos;s power to tax mightCONFIDENTIAL^____ ..........._____^Li_jj_B
tCONFIDENTIALjustify an arrangement which allowed the City and Westminster a moregenerous representation on the Board than would follow from the strictapplication of this principle.5. If the principle underlying this approach were acceptable, further workwould be necessary to devise a satisfactory scheme.6. If it turned out that the Joint Board did not budget more prudently thanthe ILEA now does,  it would be open to us to consider making its preceptsubject to control by the holder of my office, whether or not we decide tointroduce controls on local authority rates or expenditure.   This exceptionalmeasure could be justified on the ground that the Joint Board would be auniquely large single-purpose precepting authority which was not directlyelected and ought therefore to be subject to an appropriate wholly exceptional jexternal control.CONCLUSION7. I invite my colleagues to agree that, if the GLC is abolished, thelegislation should establish a single local education authority, constitutedas a Joint Board on the lines set out in paragraphs 3 and 4, to run educationin inner London.K JDepartment of Education and Science6 May 19832CONFIDENTIAL
(confidential) IANNEX ACONSTITUTION AND FUNCTIONS OF ILEA1.      ILEA is the local education authority for the area covered bythe City of London and the 12 inner London Boroughs.    It is aspecial committee of the GLC,  its membership consisting of:i.      all of the (35)  councillors elected to the GLC from theinner London area;ii.      one member appointed by each of the 12 Boroughs and theCity from amongst their own members.2.      in January 1981 ILEA was providing primary and secondaryeducation for 314,000 pupils  (Essex,  the next largest LEA, had257,000 pupils)  and further and higher education for 140,000 fulland part-time students. Like other LEAs it makes provision forspecial education,  adult education (300,000 students),  the youthservice and the careers service.ILEA maintains 45 nursery schools, 812 primary schools, 179secondary schools, 112 special schools, 27 colleges of further andhigher education, 30 adult education institutes, 116 youth centresand clubs, residential sports and outdoor centres, 2 museums, 54teachers&apos; centres and 24 careers offices. It also grant-aids the 5London polytechnics and gives financial assistance to 8 specialistestablishments of further education.4.      in 1980/81 full-time equivalent staffing levels in ILEA(including staff in the polytechnics) were:teaching staff 33,500others 32,2005       ILEA determines its own budget and fixes its own precept (whichthe GLC has to levy on its behalf).  Its net budgeted expenditure in1982/83 is around  775m,   financed largely on the basis of a precept f 7lp. This compared with a GRE of  514m.  Block grant is not paiddirect to ILEA.  In 1982/83 the inner London Boroughs received, afterhold-back,  no block grant in respect of education.6 May 1983?1(confidential) I

</content>
</cab>
