<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/199/0 images: 74-75</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Brft&amp;nnie Majesty&apos;s Government.]                   Printed for the Cabinet.  November 1928.SECRET.                                                     Copy  No.    ^ C.P.  359 (28).                                 CABINET.THE  CHINA  BOXER INDEMNITY.         MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE  FOR THE COLONIES.    IN the memorandum circulated by the Acting  Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs with his note of the 13th November, it is suggested that the question of theBoxer Indemnity might be finally disposed of by releasing  all future instalmentsunconditionally to the Chinese Government.  It is urged that this striking act ofgenerosity would have a very good effect in China. It is further suggested that that part of the Indemnity which has already been paid  to the Bank on account of the china Indemnity Fund, and amounting to  2,500,000, might also be remitted uncon-ditionally to  the Chinese.  I wish  to urge  very strongly  on  my colleagues thedesirability of utilising this portion at least of the Indemnity for a purpose of mutualbenefit to British and Chinese, as intended by the 1925 Act.  I consider that the best way to do that  is to devote  this sum, or a large part of it, to  the Hong KongUniversity.    The  claims  of the  Hong Kong University have already  been  urged  in my memorandum of the 15th December, 1926, and Mr. Ormsby-Gore&apos;s memorandum ofthe 1st February, 1928.  The University was founded in 1910 in  the belief that itwould provide both a centre of British influence in the Far East and a means bywhich Chinese students  might obtain all the advantages of a  Western educationwithout having to travel long distances to Europe or America.  Land and buildings were provided by a prominent citizen in Hong Kong, and the original endowment &quot;fund was built up of subscriptions from the general public in Hong Kong, bothBritish and Chinese, from Chinese communities in  Canton  (the Viceroy of which showed great enthusiasm for the scheme), and other places in  China proper, FartherIndia and Australia, and from the Chinese Government itself.    To  supplement its original  endowment,  the University has  been assisted  bybenefactions by private individuals  and by grants from the Government of HongKong (in 1928 the grant amounted to 63,800  dollars).  It has received also a littleassistance from the Imperial Government, which provides an.annual sum of  300for scholarships.   Three  chairs in the Medical School have been endowed by theRockefeller Foundation.  Certain sums (now  largely in arrear) have been payable by the Central and Provincial Governments  in China  in respect of scholarshipstenable at the University.    The University has, however, never been  adequately endowed, while very soon after its opening in 1912 it had to struggle against difficulties arising out of the warand the growing chaos in China after the 1912  Revolution.  Nevertheless, it has now a teaching staff of about 50 and some  300 students, including 250 Chinese, drawn from practically all over China (but mainly from Hong Kong and Kwangtung) andalso from India and Farther India.    The University commenced with Faculties of Medicine, Engineering and Arts.The Faculties of Medicine and Engineering were most successful  as  difficulty wasexperienced in conveying instruction in English in the subjects dealt with under the faculty of Arts.   There is, therefore, a growing feeling that the original purpose ofthe University would best be served by greater development of Chinese studies.    As a result of the activity of Sir Cecil Clementi, at present Governor of HongKong,  sufficient money  has  been subscribed  in the last few months by the local      &apos;[18482]
Chinese Community to make possible, with the help of an increased grant from the hong Kong Government, the establishment of a School of Chinese Studies on a small scale.    Considerable further expenditure is necessary if the University is  really toplay the part intended for it.  Besides the expansion  of existing activities, theestablishment of a Faculty of Science, the further extension of Chinese studies anda development of the scholarship system are  all necessary items.  It is impossible toraise any further considerable sums by local subscription, as the public in Hong Kong(at least,  the  British  community)  feel that the benefits to  British influence  and prestige generally are  such that they should not be called upon to bear the whole burden.  They feel that the Imperial Government should do its share in a matter ofImperial importance.   In principle I agree with them,  but direct Imperial assistance is impossible.   These  Indemnity  funds,  which  would  be  sufficient  to make theUniversity a great centre of both  Chinese  studies and progressive education forChinese, put it within the power of the Imperial Government to  establish it on a secure footing at no cost to Imperial funds.    It is universally admitted that  the education and technical training of so manyyoung Chinese in the United States or in institutions under  American influence inChina is the main buttress of American trade, in China.  Our chief hope of counter-acting this influence is in the Hong  Kong University.    I, therefore, feel most strongly that the sum necessary for the further develop-ment  of  the Hong Kong University should be provided out  of  the accumulatedinstalments of the Boxer  Indemnity now in our hands.  There can be no questionbut that this  will be  an object  of mutual benefit to  Great Britain and  China,especially when  the  part played by  the  Chinese in  the original foundation  and subsequent maintenance of the University is borne in  mind.   If the unpaid balanceof the Indemnity is to  be handed over unconditionally to the  National Government,this affords our only means of ensuring that  some part of it at least shall be devotedto the cause of education in China, and not to the maintenance of the troops andharems of the  war lords, which seems its most probable destination if it is handedover unconditionally.   It will at the same time enhance our  prestige  and influenceboth now and permanently, far more effectually than  a gesture of  generosity whichwill only too soon be forgotten.    It seems to  me that the only bit of solid ground in the Chinese chaos is ourposition in Hong Kong. Anything we can do to strengthen that, both materially andmorally, will be to oUr  credit and advantage, however many changes and fluctuationstake place in Chinese politics.  If the announcement that His Majesty&apos;s government intended to devote the balance in their hands to this object were made at the  sametime as the proposed  announcement of the waiving of future instalments,  there seemsto be no reason whatever to expect that the Chinese would do anything but welcome it.    I beg that if my colleagues agree to the immediate proposal of the Foreign office memorandum,  they will also agree that  the balance of the Indemnity now in our hands should be  devoted to the assistance of  Hong Kong University, and the Act of1925 amended accordingly.                                                                    L. S.  A.  .    Colonial Office,  Downing Street,           November 20, 1928.

</content>
</cab>
