<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/199/0 images: 78-81</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   [This Document is  the  Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.&quot;)                   Printed -for the Cabinet. ,   November 1928.        -SECRET...  CP. 361 (28).  ..                                            .        - .   The Indian  Contribution to the Home Effective Charges  of the                               British Army.The political atmosphere in India, as shown by  the  controversy  over the question           of establishing; a Secretariat  for the Legislative Assembly.        MEMORANDUM BY THE  SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA.    Last week I circulated  a  Memorandum (OP. 341 (28)) explaining the political inadvisability of any attempt to  impose on  the Government of  India  a decision on the question of the Capitation Rate.                                       .  &apos;    I think my colleagues ought to  know that the question of the Capitation Rate is not the only  question now at issue between the Government  of  India and myself which is likely to  give  rise to controversy.  I may  give, as another instance, the discussion now proceeding between us on the proposal to  set up a separate office establishment for the Legislative Assembly.  As shortly as I can state them for the present purpose the main facts here are as follows :     When the new bicameral Indian Legislature was set up in 1921  as  the result,  of the Reforms Act  of 1919, the arrangements previously in force for  carrying out- the administrative  work of its  predecessor the Indian  Legislative  Council were continued..   These  arrangements  were  that  the   Secretaries - whose  functions correspond roughly to those of the  Clerks at the Table of the House of Commons  were provided from the staff of one of the Departments of the Government of India, while the clerical staff subordinate to  these officers were similarly part and parcel  of this same Department.   The only analogy I can suggest by way of describing  this arrangement is to suppose the work of Sir Lonsclale Webster and his subordinates  in the offices of  the House  of Commons as being performed by the officials and clerical staff of, let us say,  the Home Office or the Treasury,  in addition  to  their  ordinary duties at the Treasury  or Home  Office while Parliament is  not  in session.   This arrangement has been cheap and convenient with Council sessions covering only some three  months of the year, and was as a result, of long  experience  under the old regime in good  working order ; obviously therefore the most  convenient  procedure at  the start of the new order was to make no essential change in this respect.    Very soon after its inauguration, however, a demand was made  by the Assembly for an  executive and administrative  staff of its  own,  to be  controlled by its own President.  For  some time,  mainly on the score of. economy, and to a  large  extent through the influence of the first President, Sir Frederick Whyte, these demands were staved off, but the succession in  due  statutory course  of an elected President  to the office originally held by Sir  Frederick Whyte naturally strengthened the demand  of the Assembly for a greater independence  in  this respect, with the result  that the President, Mr. Patel,  some  months  ago,  submitted  an  elaborate scheme to  the. Government  of India.   This scheme  the Government of  India endorsed,  so  far as abandoning  the use  of  the  staff of  their Legislative Department for the conduct of   the  Assembly&apos;s business  was  concerned,&quot; and the  substitution  for  it   of an  entirely  separate  establishment.  They found themselves  unable,  however,  to accede to the Presidents demand  that  he should be entirely independent in  the matter of appointing and controlling the proposed new establishment, and  free from supervision by the  Finance Department in the matter of expenditure.  They therefore addressed to my predecessor, in July last a long despatch in which they set out the whole case,  including  the Presidents original  proposals and their  own  proposed modifications of thenij the most important of which was that  the AssembJy&apos;s  estab- lishment, though now to be a separate office, should  he directly controlled, through the member of the  Governor-GcneraFs Executive Councilin charge of the Department, by one of the existing Departments of  their own  Secretariat.  Before my predecessor could answer this  despatch  the matter was raised yet once more in  the Assembly,3257    75  11.28
the fact having become known  that the definite  proposals were  under consideration ;and, with my predecessors consent, the Government of India laid before the assembly the despatch which they  had sent him.  The  modifications proposed by  the Govern-ment of India were naturally not to the Presidents liking, and  it was soon apparent that the majority of the  Assembly would be behind him in objecting strongly to anyattempt  to  curtail the  independence  of  the President (and  through  him  of  theAssembly itself)  in controlling the new establishment.  The matter was  debated atsome length in the Assembly on the 22nd September, when,  as  the  result of a gooddeal  of lobbying and dismission, a  more  or less  agreed compromise  between  thePresident,  the Government  of India  and the representatives  of all parties  in  theAssembhr was tabled in the form of a Resolution, which was carried without a division.The essential features  of this revised scheme were :     (i) the  creation  of   a  separate  Assembly  Department, to  function from  1st         December next;    (2) this  Department  to  be included in  the portfolio  of the Governor-General         himself ;    (3) the chief officers of the  Department (corresponding to the  Clerks at the Table         at  the House  of Commons) to be appointed  and to be liable to  dismissal by         the Governor-General in consultation with the President, who should be free         to  exercise any other lesser forms  of  control over  these officials subject to         their right of appeal to the Governor-General ;    (4) the President and the Secretary to  have  entire control over the rest  of  the         establishment,  subject to a right of appeal against  disciplinary action  to         the Governor-General; and    (5) &quot; Treasury control&quot;  over the new Department to be exercised in the ordinary  .. ...    way by  the Finance Department,  but subject to the important  reservation         that in any case of  a  difference of opinion between the President and  the         Finance Member on any question of expenditure, there should be a reference         to  the Governor-General,  whose decision should be final.         -    These proposals were accepted without any very material modification by  theGovernment of India,  the  chief  modification&apos; being  that  the recently  establishedPublic Service Commission should  be  brought in so far as possible as a buffer betweenthe Governor-General and the President in personal matters relating to appointmentsand discipline.   On  receipt of the  revised  proposals  my Council raised  strong objections, of the nature and existence  of which I thought  it  necessary to warn theViceroy and to invite his estimate of the position if  I were to subscribe  to the pointof view of the objectors.  I here append  the private telegram in which this information was conveyed, and the Viceroy&apos;s private telegram in reply.               From Secretary  of State to Viceroy, 1st November 1928.    3120.  Private  and personal.  Assembly  Office.  I think I  should tell you that,after examination of your proposals  by a strong  Committee of  my  Council, there islikely to be determined  opposition to them in the Council, who  will probably urgepostponement of  consideration  of whole  matter until after Commission has reported.General  line  of  opposition  is  likely  to be that one  of  crucial  questions  whichCommission is bound to examine,  is relations  between executive and. legislativeauthorities in Central Government, with possible conclusion that position of executivevis-d-vis Assembly must be  strengthened, whereas your proposals  tend  to prejudgethat  issue by conceding, during progress of Commission^  enquiry, an  appreciableincrease of  power and independence  to Assembly.  There is also strong objection to&quot;Assembly  Department&quot; being placed in your personal charge as certain to bringyou constantly into personal  conflict with President and Assembly.  These views  are held in spite of  impression  that yon are committed  to revised  scheme and that  myveto&apos;would  evoke much hostile criticism, but opponents draw attention to concludingsentences of my predecessors  official telegram  of  I1 th: September.  It might,  ofcourse, be urged  that even if scheme is unsound and Commission recommend changes which involve  scrapping or  alcering  it, its introduction now, in  pursuance of yourcommitments, cannot  do much harm, as it would necessarily be shortlived.  But Ishould  like to  have privately as soon  as -possible your, comments  on the situationwhich would arise if I were  to adopt, the line I have indicated  as, likely to be urgedupon me, and  any observations you  may have to make on  the line of opposition have foreshadowed^     ..    . ,  &apos;-.        .  -         ,  :, :.        -
   . -  - i       &apos;     *     From Viceroy, 5th Nooember 1928.            &apos;    728  S.  Private and  personal.  Your ^private and personal telegram  dated 2ndNovember, No.  3120.  Assembly Office.  I am unable to -see how  the  position ofGovernment  vis-d-vis the Assembly is affected  by our latest  proposal.  Members ofthe Assembly establishment will continue to be  persons in the service of the Grownin India, and will not be the servants of  the Assembly.   Constitutionally, there  is no difference in principle  between the  scheme  accepted  by the Assembly and, our original - scheme.   It  is  true  that the Assembly  scheme  confers  powers  on thePresident, but there are ample safeguards against the abuse of these powers, and theAssembly is not invested with any powers over the establishment.                .    I  have already assessed at  their highest  value the objections to the AssemblyDepartment being placed directly in my charge ; but I am satisfied that, by utilising the Public Service Commission to  the extent  indicated in my last telegram, I shallplace on  that body, which  is well able to bear it, the odium, if  any, arising fromreversal of the orders of the President.  Further, I am  sure  that the  President willvery quickly realise the danger of placing himself in conflict with that body.   Apartfrom  that, I am sure that in present circumstances grave friction would be inevitablebetween the President and any Department  of  the Government of India to which theAssembly Office might be attached.  Speaking generally, I am quite convinced thatthe present system has become unworkable, and also, as result of further developments and our experience of last  session, that the scheme set out  in our  despatch  would now  prove  equally unworkable.  The&apos;proposals now supported by us represent a compromise agreed to by all sections of the  House, and  are very far from being a personal  triumph  for Patel.  He  wanted  much more extensive powers  in his own hands, but was compelled to realise that on this matter general sense of party leaderswas.against him.  Your  veto at this stage, or  suspension  pending the Commission^Report, could not fail to produce an acute situation which  would certainly have very wide reactions, all unfavourable.  In fact, such action on your part would  be - sharplyresented even in the quarters usually friendly to the Government, and would be seizedupon  by the recalcitrant and obstructive  elements as justification for redoubling their efforts to render impossible  transaction of Government business in the Assembly.  i feel that the opposition  in  your Council, no doubt  under influence of recent events,is unwittingly exaggerating importance of the  proposal.  I regard  scheme  as  acomparatively minor administrative adjustment for which our proposals afford  an amicable,  moderate and practical solution, and  I most strongly deprecate any prospectof its being  allowed to  develop  into  a  serious constitutional issue between theGovernment and the Assembly, for which  no  time could  be  more inopportune thanthe present.  Our difficulties here are great enough  already, without  adding to, themunnecessarily.  :    I  do  earnestly trust,  therefore,  that  you will  approve our  proposals  andcommunicate your sanction as soon as possible.    After further long discussion and consideration of these documents by my council the following telegram is about to be sent to the Government of India :-    &quot; Secret.   Legislative   Department.    Correspondence  ending  your  telegram16th  October, D. 1999.  Assembly Establishment.  I  have examined your proposals in Council, and  must ask you to  consider them further in view of following serious objections.    &quot;The  scheme,  though  in  appearance a   comparatively  minor  administrativeadjustment, iuvolves an  appreciable constitutional change, modifying the relationsbetween  Exerative  and Legislature and  consequently affecting  capacity  of  your government  to  discharge  its responsibility  to  Parliament  which  should  remainunimpaired pending any decision taken by Parliament as result of Simon Commission.It is particularly inopportune to introduce organic changes  of  this character at a timewhen the  Commission is  sitting.    &quot; Apart from  details  which may require further examination, I will confine this telegram to fundamental objections.    &quot; (1) Ths position of  your Government charged with administration of India but without an assured majority in Assembly, and  therefore dependent,  in the  last resorton the intermittent use  qf  emergency powers to. secure legislation r. and supply,, wasirorn&apos; the  first admittedly One  of&apos; exceptional difficulty,  and I desire to  express my,acknowledgments to yoti and your  Government,&apos;as to your predecessors also,,for. theirskill  and  courage in maintaining it.  Pcplacement of  appointed by elected President
lias necessarily increased the power  of  the  Assembly, and  experience  suggests  the-doubt whether this is  the occasion, when no administrative necessity for the changehas  been demonstrated, to increase  that power still further at the expense  of  theExecutive.                              .                          -   &quot;Whatever representative of your Government  is in nominal charge of proposedAssembly Secretariat there is no real  doubt in my mind that its composition  will bedetermined in practice by President.  The  tradition  of judicial  impartiality and of official secrecy is a slow growth, and  I need  not point out the opportunities which inthe  meantime the staff  if so disposed  would possess of embarrassing Governmentin the Assembly.  There is no guarantee that the goodwill and co-operation which is-essential to the effective conduct of Government business will be maintained betweenthe  new Assembly Secretariat  and the various  Departments of  Government.  Theproposal is in fact that  a Government without an assured majority should abandon suchincomplete safeguards as are now afforded by existence of a non-politic*al Secretariat.    &quot;If my apprehensions are well founded the result must be to weaken the Executivefurther, to  increase unduly  the power  of the Assembly, and pro tanto to affect  therelations of your Government with Secretary of State.   On this main ground, therefore,I should much prefer not to decide this particular issue until  the Statutory commission appointed by Government has made its report.    &quot; (2) I gravely question  wisdom of including Assembly business in portfolio of governor-General.   This arrangement seems likely to lead to differences between theGovernor-General and the President, and thus to  subject  the Governor-General to criticism in the Assembly from which it is  most desirable  he should be immune.  i cannot regard interposition of Public  Service Commission as effective bulwark.    &quot; The  appropriate member of your -Government to  take immediate charge of assembly.business is  surely the Law Member.  Failing him  I  should  prefer to seethe matter placed in the hands  of a Council  Committee consisting of  the Law, Homeand Finance Members.  But in  any case the ultimate  authority in  India  in  matters-pertaining to  the staff who will be servants  of the  Crown in India should normallyremain the GovernqrrGeneral in Council, and I strongly deprecate the isolation of theGovernor-General from his  Council   and  the abdication of  authority by the latter..Even if such an arrangement were  free from  constitutional objection,  it might  prove-a source of embarrassment to your successors.  Moreover, it will be, difficult  to resistdemands for its extension to provincial Legislative Councils, in which case the positionof the Governors will also be affected.    &quot; I realise that present proposals are supported by representatives of various parties in Assembly and that  strong disappointment, and  indeed resentment, may be caused in. certain quarters by  rejection or postponement.  But I am  not  without hope that among those who supported  scheme out of natural  desire  to increase the prestige of assembly, some will,  on fuller consideration, realise  the strength  of the objections which I have indicated above.    &quot; However that may be, my responsibility to Parliament does not allow me to regardsuch considerations as  necessarily conclusive,  and  the closing  sentences of LordBirkenhead&apos;s telegram of 11th September,  of which  the Assembly does not seem to-have been informed, were meant to  safeguard entire, liberty of action of Secretary of State.&quot;.    &apos;  .     My colleagues must often have heard  of the depth of feeling to which. &quot; interference from Whitehall &quot; is apt to give rise nowadays in India.     The mere fact that Lord Birkenhead delayed, at  the Government of India&apos;s  own request, to reply to their despatch provoked an outcry, even in the European Press ; and Avlien it becomes known and  in India everything becomes known that the Secretary of  State in  Council is objecting to the  scheme,  and objecting to it on the very grounds which  commend it to the &quot;politically-minded,&quot;  the  outcry will be redoubled.  I am not asking my colleagues  to pronounce upon  this question, but I want them to realise the atmosphere at  the other end.                                                                         PEEL.      20th November 1928.

</content>
</cab>
