<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/199/0 images: 108-110</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENT)*S E C R E T.CP. 565 (26).                          g A B j N E rjt                      HOUSE OF LORDS REFORM. -               Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal.,                We have In the House of Lords in the course of the next           fortnight two motions upon the reform of that Chamber, one           next Thursday from the Liberal benches by Lord Buckmaster,           and the other on December 11th from our own side by Lord           Clarendon,   The liberal motion  contains an element of censure           The precise terms of the Conservative motion are not yet           settled but of course it will be entirely loyal.   Beyond           this It is noticeable that both  the motions will be directed           to the question only of  personnel, and both will have as           their object to secure something like adequate representation           of the Labour Party in the House,  and no doubt alse           incidentally to reduce the total membership as well.   It Is           possible  that the two debates raw  be amalgamated,                Ministers in the Lords  would  be very glad of  the           Instructions of the Cabinet  as to  the line they should take.           We must  of  course resist the unfriendly motion from the           Liberals.   We should also be well advised to decline           responsibility for  any particular  scheme put forward  from           any  quarter.   Nothing would be  more inopportune than that           we  should be committed to details  at a moment when we have           no  time  to  weigh them, and when, whatever  they may be, thoy           would  be  torn to pieces  on the hustings.                VIe  can therefore have nothing to do with a detailed            scheme.   But this  does  not  conclude  the matter.   The            leaders  in  the House  cannot  be mute on such  a subject, with                                  -1-0*\copy no. ry
opinion growing,- not on one side only but on every side,.that trie present situation is no longer possible.    Theycannot refrain from giving guidance to the House.     There is another point.   The Conservatives who aremoving are I know anxious to testify to their ewn bona fides.They are convinced&apos; that a false impression remained after theCave resolutions.   They never conceived at that time, anymore than the Government did, that the whole abject of reform was to dig the Conservative majority securely in sothat other parties would be powerless.   Yet this was whatwas represented, and they are determined to pat themselvesright with public opinion.   The same considerationsperhaps apply to the Cabinet.   But in any case we could not show ourselves unsympathetic to such an attitude.     Lastly we must consider the future.   Just as It wouldbe a mistake to mix ourselves up with details it would be equally a mistake to push aside House of Lords Reformaltogether.   On the contrary we ought, I presume, to make up our minds that Lords Reform is to be kept open  for usin the next Parliament.   Obviously if we are turned outthere will be no  question of a mandate on this or  any otherissue.   But supposing  our  Party is returned by a  smallmajority.   In  that case the paralysis of the Sesnd Chamberwill have a very  different  appearance to  our friends.Confronted with the rising  tide of Labour opinion  those whofear subversive legislation will be very uneasy.   They willbe  demanding an effective Second Chamber, and will hold a conservative Government to  a strict account  if it  should beinactive  in  the emergency.   But with what face  could itapproach  the  subject if vshen we had been  challenged inParliament  on  it  we had had nothing to  say,  if we  had evadedeven the  most  general  commitment on the  subject before theelection?   So  that  these  motions probably offer  to us a mos-t.                              -2-
convenient opportunity:.-   We have clearly n^-t provokedthem.   The occasion&apos; is the spontaneous act of independent politicians.   And it will be plain to all our friends, however hesitating they may be on thisquestion, that we cannot without futility avoid an expression of opinion;  w-hich will have the additionaladvantage of leaving the issue open for treatment inthe&quot; next Parliament, if such a course should seemexpedient when the time comes.                              S.November 26th, 1928.

</content>
</cab>
