<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/199/0 images: 182-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1928.SECRET.                                                    Copy No.   28CP. 385 (28).                                 CABINET.COMPENSATION  FOR IRISH  LOYALISTS.    NOTE CIRCULATED  BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DOMINION AFFAIRS.    IN view of the statements in paragraph 3 of the Memorandum circulated bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer [C.P. 379 (28)], I  think  it right  to circulate tothe Cabinet a memorandum prepared in the Dominions Office.                                                                  L.  s. a.;- ,&apos;.    Dominions Office, Downing Street,          December 7, 1928. &apos; .           .                    MEMORANDUM.    With  reference  to  paragraph  3 of  the Chancellor  of the  Exchequersmemorandum, the facts as to successive estimates,  according to the dominions office records, are as follows :     1.  On the 29th October, 1927, the Chairman of the Irish Grants Committeesent to Lord Lovat, in the  Secretary of  State&apos;s absence,  a letter covering amemorandum in which the total recommendations for awards  likely to be made bythe Committee (on the basis of the applications then before  them, i.e., excluding the additional claims brought in by  the extension of time granted, in February,1928,  and  referred to below) were-estimated at   1,167,000 by calculation, or 1,250,000 as a probable round figure.    This was the estimate submitted to the Cabinet Committee, recorded in theirreport [OP. 319 (27)] and brought before the Cabinet in December .1927, when thedecision to pay on the Sumner Scale was reached [Cabinet 63 (27), Conclusion 12].The report of the Cabinet Committee, however, contains also a statement that theDominions Office, &quot; taking a more optimistic view,&quot; calculated the total cost at about 900,000.   This statement appears to have been based on the following remarksby Lord Lovat recorded in I.C. (27), 1st Conclusions (9th December, 1927):            .&quot;v-. .J;&apos;.:;V-&apos;         &quot; He was disposed to think that a settlement could be effected for a total    of about  900,000.  The figure of  1,167,550 was an estimate only, and after    examining it he thought that it was a liberal estimate.  All the  claims were    now in and the list was closed.   Of the first 1,600 odd claims  54 per cent, had    been  rejected, but the estimate was based  on only 40  per  cent,  of  the    remaining  1,500  cases  being rejected.   His  reduced figure was based on    taking the rejects as 54 per cent, throughout, and also  on  the  exclusion of    certain large claims.&quot;    In  a minute to  the  Prime  Minister previously  laid  before  the  CabinetCommittee [LC. (27) 3], Lord Lovat had stated the  opinion that &quot; a fair  and final settlement could be reached by the grant of a total sum of  1,000,000.&quot;  This didnot, of course, imply that  1,000,000  would have covered all the recommendations.
    2.  There is a reference to an  estimate of  1,000,000 in a semi-official letterto the Treasury from  the  Secretary to the Irish Grants Committee, dated 10thFebruary.  This, however, on the face of it, is not a new estimate, and does notpretend to be more than a guess for the purposes of actual expenditure.    It would appear that at the Cabinet meeting at which the later decision wasreached ] Cabinet  7 (28), Conclusion 5] this estimate  of  1,000,000  was beforethem.  It would, however, also appear from Cabinet 8 (28), Conclusion 7, that itwas realised that this figure might be insufficient to meet the recommendations ofthe Committee in full.    In this connexion it may be observed that on the morning of the 20th February(i.e., the day on which  the terms of the Chancellor of the Exchequers statement in Parliament were finally settled, and the statement  itself made) special repre-sentations were made to the Treasury  from the  Dominions  Office  which  were directed  to  making it clear  that  the  Irish  Grants  Committee must  not  bemade  responsible  for  estimating their total recommendations at  1,000,000; onthe contrary, the Committee could not guarantee  that this total  would  not  be exceeded possibly by a considerable amount.    3.  As regards the extension of time, this  proposal  was submitted to. theTreasury in January 1928 and approved by them on  3rd  February.   The  IrishGrants Committee certainly did not anticipate then that any substantial additionwould be made to their recommendations as a result of this extension, since it was hardly to be supposed that any  persons with valid claims had not previously beenaware of the existence of  the  Irish Grants Committee. Subsequently, and quitecontrary to  anticipation, after  the  date  of the announcement in  Parliament, itappeared that there was a number of such persons, with claims on which the totalrecommendations are expected to reach  250,000 ; it will be noted that this figure,with  the original estimate of  1,167,000 (or  1,250,000), corresponds nearly to the tentative figure of   1.400,000  mentioned  in Mr. Amery&apos;s  Memorandum  of the30th November, 1928 [C.P. 372  (28)].    4.  As regards the statement at the top of page 2 of the Chancellor of the exchequers Memorandum that &quot; the Cabinet have had before them  successiveestimates of  400,000,  1,000,000 and  1,400,000,&quot; it would not appear that therewas ever an  &quot;estimate &quot; of  400,000; see  Mr. churchill&apos;s statement at the meetingof the Cabinet Committee on the 9th December, 1927 : -        &quot; The Committee would remember that the figure of  400,000 adopted in &quot;N  1926 was not based on any relevant consideration.   That figure represented a    sum of  250,000 which had already been earmarked  for this particular service,    and a further sum of  150,000 which had been received from the  Irish  Free    State as a result of the financial agreement made at the end of 1925 with that    Dominion.&quot;  [I.C. (27), 1st Conclusions ; see also Mr. Amery&apos;s  Memorandum    CP. 286 (26) of the 21st July, 1926.]As to the  &quot;estimate&quot; of   1,000,000, see  above.   The only estimates  based oncalculation which  have been  put  forward from the  Dominions Office are theestimates of   1,167,000 (or  1,250,000) put forward  at  the  end of 1927 and the tentative figure of  1,400,000 referred to above.

</content>
</cab>
