<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/199/0 images: 196-201</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  December 1928.SECRET.CP. 387  (28).                                 CABINET.POSITION OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR THE UNION  OF                   SOUTH AFRICA IN LONDON.      MEMORANDUM BY THE  SECRETARY OF  STATE FOR  DOMINION  AFFAIRS.    COPIES of recent telegraphic correspondence with the Imperial Secretary inSouth Africa, on the subject of the status of the High Commissioner for the Unionof South Africa in London, have been circulated to the Cabinet with the dominions office telegrams.  Copies of the relevant portions of these telegrams are annexedfor convenience of reference (Appendix A).    It appears  from this correspondence that  a point  to which General Hertzogattaches special importance is that the title of  the High Commissioner should be such as to indicate  that &quot; he enjoys the confidence of his  Government to the same extent as an Ambassador,&quot; and. to emphasise his status  as  the representative inLondon of the Union Government charged with functions of the nature contemplated in the Resolution adopted by the Imperial Conference of 1926 on the subject of thedevelopment of  the  system of intercommunication between His  Majesty&apos;s Govern -ments (see page 27 of Cmd. 2768).   The phrase originally suggested by the  UnionGovernment for this purpose, as additional to the title &quot; High Commissioner,&quot;  viz.,&quot;Diplomatic Representative,&quot; seems clearly unsuitable,  as it would be open to the implication that the relations between Great Britain and the Union are those offoreign countries, and it will be seen from Captain Cliffords telegram No. 98  thatGeneral Hertzog does not attach importance to the use of the word &quot; diplomatic &quot; inthis connection, and would welcome any alternative suggestions.    There is really,  I think, no.reason why the title of &quot; High Commissioner &quot;  shouldnot suffice by itself.  The fact  that we have  ourselves adopted  the title &quot; HighCommissioner &quot;  for the post in Canada corresponding to that of the  Union repre-sentative in London, shows that we, at any rate, are quite satisfied,  and indeed avery cursory study of the list of posts in all parts of the world to which the title isattached shows  their dignity and importance.   I should  accordingly much  preferit if General Hertzog could be induced to retain the title &quot; High Commissioner &apos;&apos;and  add nothing to it, and I would recommend that, in the first instance, every endeavour should be made to secure his  agreement to this course.   In case, however,it proves impossible to dissuade General Hertzog from the proposal for some additionto the  title, it  seems desirable  that we  should be  prepared with alternative suggestions.    It is not easy to suggest any completely satisfactory addition to the title &quot; HighCommissioner.&quot;   The phrases suggested in Captain Cliffords  telegram No.  101,&quot;Deputy of State &quot; and  &quot;  State Deputy,&quot; though they  might be acceptable to theUnion Government, are hardly likely to be understood in this country. It appearsprobable that the phrase  &quot;Accredited Representative&quot;  would be acceptable  toGeneral Hertzog, but, as  the term &quot;accredited&quot;  has now acquired  a specialsignificance, it  is  open  to the same objection  as &quot;diplomatic.&quot;    The ImperialSecretary mentions  the expression  &quot;Political Representative,&quot;  and this does  not seem to be open to any obvious objection.  Other possible  suggestions which mightbe made are :         &quot; Plenary Representative.&quot;        &quot;Chief Representative.&quot;        &quot; General  Representative.&quot;        &quot;Representative  for the  purpose  of   consultation  with His  Majesty&apos;s            Government in Great  Britain.&quot;       [18583]                                                         copy No.    28
My own preference, on the whole, would be for the term &quot; Political Representative&quot;(Which, incidentally, is a title which we might, I think, well give to Captain Cliffordhimself in addition  to his existing title of &quot;Imperial  Secretary &quot;).  Failing that,my inclination is for the term &quot; Plenary Representative.&quot;  Subject to the approvalof the Cabinet/ I should  propose  to  authorise  Captain  Clifford  to put the firstsuggestion (i.e., Political Representative) to General Hertzog, if he persists in his desire  for  some  additional  descriptive  designation,  and, should   this  proveunacceptable, to mention the second (i.e., Plenary Representative).    As already indicated,  it  seems  clear  from  the  draft  Executive  council resolution quoted in Captain Cliffords telegram No.  94,  that the existing title&apos;&apos; High Commissioner &quot; is intended in  any  case to be part of the  new title,  and  itwould  seem probable that, whatever may be the  full title of the officer, he will, inpractice, generally be referred to as  &quot;the  High Commissioner.&quot;   From this pointof view, it would appear of * less  importance what are the precise terms  of theremaining part of the title so long&apos;as it does not include any phrase possessingimplications such as  those of &quot; Diplomatic Representative.&quot;    As to the  procedure  for conveying to General Hertzog any suggestions whichwe may have on this point, it will be  observed from the Dominions  Office telegram to the  Imperial Secretary,  No.  47,  that  I  had  an  interview  with .the HighCommissioner&apos; for the Union on the 12th November, when Mr.  Smit handed to mea  copy of  General  Hertzog&apos;&apos;s  telegram  to  him  on  the subject of  the high commissioners status, and that  I contemplated that  an official  reply would bereturned to General Hertzog through the  Hisrh Commissioner.   I feel, however,that it would be best, before any formal reply is made to Mr. Smit, first to try toteach agreement with General Ffertzog, through the Imperial Secretary,  as  to thequestion of title.    If the Cabinet  approve of  this method of procedure, I would propose, whentelegraphing to Captain Clifford, to instruct him to point out to  General Hertzogthe dignity and importance which, in our view,  attach  to the  existing title, asindicated  in  thevthird paragraph of this Memorandum, and to make every effort to dissuade him from pressing  his proposal for an addition to  the present title.Onlv if it becomes  clear  that it  is impossible so to  dissuade him, should CaptainClifford throw  out suggestions as to a  possible alternative  title.    In any official reply which may eventually be sent to General Hertzosr, I  should propose to emphasise the  point  alreadv indicated in the telegram to CaptainClifford, No. 47. that, in practice, the High  Commissioner already enjoys a very high status and that, in particular     (1) as regards direct access to Ministers and authority to discuss and deal, with           any subject, we are only too glad  to  accord to the High Commissioner           whatever position his own  Government may wish him to occupy;    (2) as regards exemption from taxation and similar  matters, Dominion High           Commissioners have already been placed on the same footing as foreign           Ambassadors and Ministers; and    (3) as regards  precedence, it is hot possible, for reasons which are known to           General  Hertzog,  to  place High  Commissioners on exactly the same           footing as foreign Ambassadors or Ministers, but they are already given,           on ceremonial occasions, the highest precedence possible without, involving           their ranking, by virtue of  their  office, before Ministers  of Great Britain           or of a Dominion who may  be present  on the same occasion.    I emphasized these  points generally in my conversation with  General Hertzogin South  Africa on  the  7th September,  1927, to which reference is made  in thetelegraphic correspondence.   An  extract  from  the record of  our discussion  isattached  (Appendix  B).  It would seern indeed  from  Captain Cliffords telegramNo. 98that on all these points General Hertzog is satisfied with the present position,but I think it would be desirable to lay stress on them again.              ;    In the meantime, I have sent an interim reply to Mr. Smit explaining thatI  am consulting my colleagues with regard to the proposals submitted in general hertzog&apos;s telegram to him. and that I hope to be  in&apos; a position to send him a furtherreply shortly.                                                                   .&quot;  L. S. A.    Dominions Office, Downing Street,            December 7,  1928.
APPENDIX  A.                                     (1)    Paraphrase Telegram from the Imperial Secretary, South Africa, to the                Under-Secretory of State for Dominion Affairs.    IMPORTANT,  No.  93, 9th November.    In view of its importance, I considered that the text of telegram sent to theHigh Commissioner for the Union  of South Africa by the Prime Minister shouldbe transmitted to you  in  case the High  Commissioner does not hand you a copy.For text, see telegram &quot;A&quot; in my telegram No.  94 of tp-day.    I have  arranged an  interview on Tuesday, 13th November,  with the PrimeMinister, and I will endeavour to ascertain what  his views are.  I do not think thathe will ask  you to give  the High  Commissioner the same precedence as  foreign ministers in London,  but it is quite possible that he may do so if we raise that aspect of the question ourselves.    Proposal may have  been  made by Smit in letter  to Hertzog  from  Geneva,written on the 18th September, which I have not seen, and may be the outcome of feeling that  when  he is  at the League of Nations Headquarters the High Com-missioner appears to occupy inferior position vis-a-vis foreign delegates there whoenjoy ambassadorial or ministerial rank.   Question of precedence in  London wouldnot appear to arise if above conjecture is correct.    Question may have been discussed between  Smit and the High Commissionerfor the Irish Free State if both were at Geneva on the 18th September, as following telegram  has also been sent to Smit.   (Insert telegram  &quot; B,&quot; my  telegram No.  94of to-day.)   Both  questions may be interwoven, as Free State and Union high commissioners might have discussed at Geneva  Tyrrell&apos;s despatch of 28th Augustas tending further to  lessen in the eyes of foreign  countries to which  they are accredited status of Dominion diplomatic  representatives.   I  advise delay  in replying to any representations Smit may make  until I am able to obtain furtherinformation  on Tuesday.   I should, however, welcome any observations from youwhich you consider likely to be of  assistance to me at interview on that date.   Ihave not  overlooked information  supplied in enclosures to  Harding&apos;s letter  of2nd August  about my representation  work  here  nor matters raised  in  notes  of conversation  which  took  place on 7th September,  1927,  between  Mr.  Amery andGeneral Hertzog.                                     (2.)Telegram from the Imperial Secretary, South  Africa, to the Under-Secretary  of                          State for Dominion A ffairs.    No. 94, 9th November, Confidential.   Following is text  of telegram &quot;A.&quot;Begins: Confidential, No.  79, 6th November.   Union Government has consideredposition of High Commissioner and proposes following resolution of the ExecutiveCouncil in connection therewith :  &quot; That it is desirable, without prejudice to existing system of direct communication between the two Governments concerned, to facilitatediplomatic  and political intercourse  between the Union and Great Britain andNorthern Ireland by the appointment of an official stationed at London and chargedwith the care of the interests of the Union in the United Kingdom of Great Britainand Northern  Ireland on the  same footing as Envoy Extraordinary and minister; that the High Commissioner  in  addition to his ordinary  duties under  Act No. 3  of 1911 be charged with the performance  of these functions and in future  be known as High Commissioner  for the Union of South Africa and diplomatic Representative of the Union of South  Africa with His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in Great Britain and Northern Ireland.&quot;    I shall be glad if you would submit these proposals to His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin Great Britain  for their comments and also  favour me with  your observations.Ends.18583]
    Following  is  text of  telegram &quot; B.&apos;&apos;   Begins:  Confidential,  No.  80,  6thNovember.   In connection with your private letter of 18th September, re objectionof the Irish Free State Government (to) terms of despatch of  British Ambassadorof 24th June, 1924, to Secretary of State re  Irish Minister  in Washington  anddespatch of Tyrrell to M. Briand of 28th August last re Canadian Minister at Paris,I am  sending you  my observations on the latter despatch by  mail and also writing to Amery as I share view that terms thereof not satisfactory.   Please inform BritishGovernment and Irish High  Commissioner.  Ends.                                      (3.) Paraphrase Telegram from the Under-Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs to                      the Imperial Secretary, South Africa.    IMPORTANT, Secret, No. 47, 12th November.    Smit has handed to Secretary  of State copy of Hertzog&apos;s message No. 79, andreply is being prepared for communication through Smit to Hertzog.   Meanwhile,for the purpose of your discussion to-morrow  with Hertzog, following  may  helpyou:-            &quot;       Position of High Commissioner for Union of South Africa in London.    In so far as question  is one  of High Commissioner having  direct access  to ministers here and authority to discuss and deal with any subject whatever, principlehas already  been agreed upon see letter of  28th April, 1927, from  Sir  austen chamberlain, of which a copy was enclosed with Harding&apos;s letter of 2nd August.It is simply for his Governments decision how responsible is the work they wish  togive him.  As the Secretary of State said in conversation with Smit: &quot;The house is wired and the lights are in.  All  General Hertzog need do is to turn the switch.&quot;In so far as question is one of grant of privileges equivalent to those granted  toforeign diplomatic representatives, it will be remembered that  Dominion High Com-missioners in this country have already been placed on the same footing as foreignAmbassadors and Ministers as regards exemption from taxation and similar matters as a result of discussion at Imperial Conference  of 1923.  Grant of any title to theHigh  Commissioner which might  suggest  that position of  one of His  Majesty&apos;governments,  representatives in relation to another of His Majesty&apos;s Governmentswas precisely the same as that of a representative of any of those  Governments  inrelation to the Government of a foreign country is, however, unsuitable and strongly to be deprecated.  Indeed,  it is felt  that title in proposed Executive Council Minute&apos;&apos; Diplomatic  Representative of the  Union of  South  Africa&apos;&apos;  would  be  whollyinacceptable to Cabinet here on the ground that latter title is only suitable for anenvoy from  a foreign country and accredited to the King by the Sovereign of  that foreign country.  Similar considerations applied in settling question of precedenceof High Commissioners here (as to which, see P. LXXV of &quot; Dominions Office List,&quot;1928,  and recent telegraphic correspondence regarding precedence in the Union).                                      (*/)  Telegram from the Imperial Secretary, South Africa, to the  Under-Secretary of                          State for Dominion Affairs.     IMMEDIATE, No.  98, 15th  November.   Your telegram  No. 47  of  12thNovember.  Have had most satisfactory interview with the Prime Minister.     I told General Hertzog  quite frankly that we saw objection to the use of theword &quot; diplomatic &quot; in the title of the Union representative.  I said that a Dominionrepresentative was given the run of the Foreign Office and the Dominions Office, andin addition access to the Ministers and  officials he was permitted to see most secretdocuments and treated more like a member of the British Government than a foreignAmbassador.   Word  &quot; diplomatic &quot; conveyed entirely  wrong impression of hisposition.  I showed him Sir A.  Chamberlain&apos;s letter of 28th April and  notes ofMr.  Amery&apos;s conversation with him of 7th September, 1927, on this subject.
    Prime Minister stated that he was quite satisfied with precedence given to theHigh Commissioner for the: Union of South Africa; and said that the privilegeswhich  the British Government  accorded the High Commissioner for&apos; the Unionofv South Africa&quot; in  regard  to  his  &quot; representation&quot;&quot;&apos;&apos; functions as  set  but  in&quot;Sir A. Chamberlain&apos;s letter left  nothing to be desired.   Proposal in  Union&apos; tele-gram No. 79  of  6th  November was  merely intended as  formal intimation thatSmit was in fact entrusted with&quot;the&apos;duty of representing the Union Government inGreat Britain, and the  object of the  Executive Council mih&apos;ut&quot;er is to indicate thathe enjoys the  confidence of his Government to the same extent as ah Ambassadordoes.   Prime  Minister has ho desire  to  insist oh exact wording of the&apos;minute orprecise title, nor does he especially wish the word &quot; diplomatic&quot; to be portion of the title.   He does, however,  desire that  the title should emphasize&apos;&apos; the  hew functionentrusted to the High Commissioner for  the Union of South Africa as the outcome of resolution of the 1926  Conference in connection with representation  and themethods  of communication between Great Britain and the Dominions.   He would welcome any alternative suggestion for title.   Prime Minister said that the proposedCouncil minute was intended to &quot; Gazette &quot; the new post.                                     (5.)Telegram from the Imperial Secretary, South Africa, to the Under-Secretary of State                             for Dominion Affairs.    IMPORTANT, No. 101, 17th November.    Prime Minister, reverting to  the need  for some new style to denote politicalfunctions of the High Commissioner for the Union of South Africa, suggested sometitle bringing in the word &quot; Commonwealth &quot; inspired no doubt by the term&apos;&quot; Commonwealth of Nations.&quot;   I  replied that, in spite of its other merits, use ofthis word would create  confusion  owing to  its special association with Australia.Prime Minister agreed,  and asked  if I had any suggestion to offer.   I replied thatI was unable to think of anything suitable at the moment, but proposed that he shouldawait receipt of promised  reply from you to Union Government telegram No. 79,which Smit intimated would be forthcoming  in a few days and which might containuseful suggestions for new title.    Advise you to endeavour  to devise some appropriate designation which, to be acceptable, should,  I think,&apos; imply exercise of political functions on  behalf ofautonomous nation.  The word  &quot;State &quot; occurs to me, since it has political complexionand denotes national entity. Moreover, it is peculiarly associated with former DutchRepublic,  and is  in  use in some titles  in the  Netherlands to-day.  &quot;High Com-missioner, Deputy of State for  Union&quot;  or &quot;State  Deputy&quot; is  best  I  can think of; &quot; Political Representative,&quot; though most appropriate, may not sound sufficientlyimposing.APPENDIX  B.  Extract from Notes of Discussion between Mr. Amery and General Hertzog on                              September 7, 1927.    WE agreed that there  were two aspects of the matter,  viz. : the ceremonialprecedence, &amp;c, attached to the office, and the real power and position enjoyed bythe High Commissioner de facto.  As regards the former, we were entirely in agree-ment that there must always be a difference between a foreign Minister who  is  therepresentative of  a separate Sovereign, and therefore gets courtesy recognitionafforded to his Sovereign, however insignificant in fact the State which he represents,and a High Commissioner who cannot represent the King to himself but representsIns Government.  As such, he obviously should not rank in front of his own Govern-ment or of members of the British Cabinet, and the present  arrangement by which
the High Commissioners rank immediately after British Cabinet Ministers (and theirown Ministers when in London), but before other Privy Councillors, seemed,veryfairly to meet the case.  General Hertzog  remarked  that his idea was that high commissioners should be treated substantially as if they were Ministers of their own government over in London.  I entirely concurred in this view, and pointed out thatwhen it came to de facto recognition and status  everything depended on the extentto which the High Commissioners own Government recognised him.  We certainlywere only too willing to afford to the High Commissioners whatever position theirown Governments wished them to occupy.  For instance, if General Hertzog wishedto use his High Commissioner for the purpose of discussing  foreign policy with theBritish  Government, he would find both myself and the Foreign Secretary only toowilling to meet him in the matter.-yr           -ft-                       -JF           -Jr0

</content>
</cab>
