<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/199/0 images: 336-339</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government,]Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1928.SECRET.Copy No.  &amp;CP. 399  (28).CABINET,UNCLAIMED BALANCES  OF  PAY  EARNED  BY  NATIVE    MEMBERS  OF THE  MILITARY  LABOUR  CORPS        DURING  THE  EAST  AFRICA  CAMPAIGN.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE  COLONIES.     IN June 1925 I circulated a paper regarding the unclaimed balances of pay- earned by native East African personnel of the Military Labour Corps during the Campaign in East Africa.  I append a copy for reference.     2.   The Cabinet considered this paper on the 29th July, 1925, but came to no decision.  Since then I have been negotiating  with the  Treasury  officially and semi-officially,  in the hope of securing an agreed solution  to the question without further  reference to the Cabinet, but  this has not proved  possible, and  I have  no alternative to bringing the matter before my colleagues again.     3.   Paragraph 11  of  the 1925 paper refers to  the fact that His  Majesty&apos;s Government  had recently  accepted a  proposal  by the German Government  that facilities should be given to the German Government to pay admitted claims by their ex-soldiers and carriers in the  Tanganyika  Territory.  Since then, the  German Government  have sent out a  special  mission to  the  Territory,  which, under the supervision of  the Tanganyika Government, has  paid out approximately  284,000 to the ex-German Askaris.  The German payments, it is true, did not extend to the issue of unclaimed balances,  but it is  impossible not  to contrast the  fact that the German Government have paid  claims by their native ex-soldiers  in  East Africa, which they could have avoided paying,  with the fact  that the British Government have not paid the British carriers all that they duly earned.  I have received ample evidence from East Africa showing how disastrous failure to pay is, both to our prestige and  our boasted defence of native rights and interests.     4.    The  objections which have been urged against the payment of the unclaimed balances to the tribes ignore the fact that it is in accordance with the practice of all native East African tribal organisations that the tribes should receive what is due to an untraceable individual in cases of this kind.  A  tribe  as a whole makes itself responsible for  the support of the dependents of its members who die or disappear. There could thus be no fairer method of disposing of these unclaimed balances than by paying them over to the tribes, as this would ensure the money being devoted to the  objects for which it is really necessary and beneficial.    5.   My view has been throughout that there is no equitable justification for the Government retaining the sums due to these men or their dependents, and  that it is a debt of honour which it is incumbent on His Majesty&apos;s  Government  to liquidate. In view of the  apparent  hopelessness of any agreement being reached between theDepartments, I  strongly urge that a small Cabinet Committee should be set up, such Committee to consider the arguments of the Departments concerned and suggest  aline of policy to the Cabinet.L. S. A.Colonial Office, December 17,  1928.[X8624AJ
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]      230Printed for the Cabine-t.  June 1925.SECRET.CP.  302 (25).CABINET.UNCLAIMED  BALANCES  OF  PAY  EARNED  BY  NATIVE    MEMBERS  OF  THE  MILITARY  LABOUR  CORPS        DURING  THE  EAST  AFRICA  CAMPAIGN.         MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF  STATE FOR THE  COLONIES.    THIS  question, which has been the subject of discussion between the  ColonialOffice,  the  War  Office  and  the  Treasury for  several years,  concerns  a sum ofabout  165,000.   It will be observed from  what  follows that  it  has  alreadyattracted public attention, and it is likely to be a source of serious embarrassmentif a solution  cannot be found.  I do not feel it possible to accept the views of theChancellor  of the Exchequer and  the Army Council without first  referring thequestion for the consideration of  the Cabinet generally.    1.   At the end of the war it was found that  there were large balances due tonative carriers who had disappeared and whose relatives it would be difficult orimpossible to trace.   This position had arisen from the fact that, as in  so many other respects,  the  organisation for the East African Force was  improvised  from local resources. It was not until 1916 that the arrangements for recruiting carrierswere taken seriously in hand, but  a satisfactory  system of identification  had notbeen evolved until a later stage of the operations.  The difficulty which has arisen is,therefore, primarily due to a cause which might have been avoided if the importanceof the operations had been foreseen from the start.    2.   When  the  matter attracted attention locally, it was proposed by theDirector of Military Labour  (Colonel Watkins, a Colonial  Official,   now deputy chief Native Commissioner,  Kenya) that unclaimed balances should be paid overto the tribal organisations to which the men belonged, and the Civil  and Militaryauthorities  concurred.  Ordinances were passed locally providing that  such monies,remaining undisposed of  for three years without any claim  having been made,should  be applied and made  over for the benefit of the tribe to which the nativebelonged, and these Ordinances were approved in the Colonial Office as representingthe most adequate arrangements which could be made.    3.   It must be admitted that  there was an oversight on the  part of the  ColonialOffice in  this  matter, as the expenditure involved would, to the extent  of  aboutnine-tenths,  fall upon Imperial Funds,  and the consent of the War  Office shouldhave been sought.    When  the oversight  was brought  to notice  it  was considered   necessary to direct the repeal  of the provision.   The Governors  protested strongly against the repeal,  and it then appeared that the provision had been made after  very carefulconsideration.  It had been evident  that the task of tracing the  individuals entitledto the balances would require a large special organisation  out of all proportion tothe amount involved, and Colonel Watkins had agreed to the alternative of payment to the tribes on that ground.   If the alternative had not been accepted by the  localrepresentative of the War Office and provided by law, he would have felt compelledto press for the more elaborate investigation.      [18624]
    4.  It is to  be regretted that full information  of  the circumstances had notbeen  furnished at the outset,  as  the  question would certainly  in  that  case  havebeen  referred to  the  War Office, and would have been considered on  its  meritswithout the further loss of time which necessarily tended to accentuate the difficultyof tracing individuals.    5.  On the receipt of the Governors&apos; protests, an effort was made to obtain theconcurrence of the War  Office and the Treasury  in the  arrangements  originally contemplated.  The arguments used by the  Acting Governor  of Kenya  were thatthe arrangement  was reasonable  in view  of the special  tribal communal  systemexisting in East Africa,  by which any native having no  resources is maintained bythe tribe; the fact that in the Imperial Army such unclaimed  balances are devotedto military  charities, and do not revert to.the Exchequer;  and the  fact, already  1mentioned,  that  the  trouble was due to  the&apos; failure  of the  Imperial military  Iauthorities to provide a special organisation  for the administration of the Military  ILabour Corps.                                                                  f    6.  The representations of the Colonial Office failed, and the matter  rested  1until  Colonel  Watkins came  on leave  in 1922 and raised  it with some force.  He  considered  that  the  failure  to recognise the arrangement agreed  to locally was  Idefinitely a breach of faith with him, in view of the fact that he had only accepted  1the proposal as an alternative to an exhaustive search for the individuals entitled to  1the payments.  He desired to be allowed to enlist the influence of  General  Smuts  I(who had commanded in chief in East Africa), and was deterred  from resigning, in  Iorder to draw public attention to  the matter, only by the fact  that Mr. Wood, the  1Under-Secretary of State  for the  Colonies at the time, decided  that a further effort  Ishould be made.   Attention had already by that time been drawn to the  subject in  Ithe House of Commons.  -    -                                 - -     -            I    7.  In  the further representations made  to  the War Office the question of  Ipayment to the tribes was reserved, and the Army Council were asked to agree to  ja determined  effort being made to trace the individuals entitled to the balances.  IThe War Office/ however, refused to  agree to any systematic effort being made to  Itrace  individual claims, and, while consenting to the payment  of individual&quot;  claims  ias presented, asked that the  amount of the unpaid balances should  be surrenderedat once.  Since then a few individual claims have come to light and have been paid,but the position has not materially altered since the returns made in 1922,  of which an abstract accompanies  this memorandum.                        ......    8.  Early in  1924, the late Governors of Tanganyika and Kenya again pressed for payment to the tribes to  be approved.  In the case of  Kenya this would meanpayment to  the Native  Trust Funds,  which have now been set  up.   In  the otherDependencies  the respective Governors would be  responsible for  administering themoney for the welfare of the  tribes.    9.  The War Office and the Treasury were again approached, and Mr. Thomasalso wrote semi-officially to Mr. Walsh and Mr. Snowden asking for their support.The matter  was still outstanding when the present Government took office,  and I took an early opportunity of impressing on my  colleagues at  the War Office andthe Treasury  that  I was in  complete accordance with  my  predecessor on thisquestion.  It had been hoped that, subject to the consent of the Chancellor  of theExchequer, a compromise might be effected by devoting  100,000 to this object outof the Army surplus which was anticipated,  but the surplus was not realisedj  and,in addition, Mr.  Churchill said that he could, in any case, only  have consented onthe condition of the Army Council agreeing  to the payment in principle.  This, itis understood, they felt themselves unable  to do.    10.  The matter was brought to  Mr. Ormsby-Gore&apos;s attention when  in  Kenyalast autumn, and this case was quoted as an example of the Imperial Government&quot;letting down &quot; native interests.   Protest against the retention of these balances bythe Government has already been made in the local press in East Africa,  and it isone of the  allegations  against the administration of Kenya made by Dr. NormanLeys  in his book &quot;Kenya,&quot;  which has attracted, and is certain again to attract,attention in  the Houses of Parliament, where questions have already been  askedon this subject, and outside.   In view of the  attitude embodied in the White Paper(Cmd. 1922) of 1923, His Majesty&apos;s Government stand to be attacked for a breach of.their  trusteeship  for the  natives.  The operations could not have been carried onwithout the assistance of these large  bodies  of native carriers, who rendered loyaland invaluable service in circumstances always arduous and often dangerous, andthere is no equitable justification for the Government retaining the sums due to these
*                                                                                 9 91                                                                                 to o JLANNEXTJRE .                  Unclaimed Balances: Military Labour Corps.  RETURN made by Officer in Charge, Clearance Section, King&apos;s African Rifles,                              October 11, 1922.    (a.) Number  of  claims   which  have  been  admitted  and  paid  to  the31st March, 1922:-KenyaTanganyika territoryZanzibar and MafiaUgandaTotalNumber of  Men. 6,240    25 1,250   880 8,395     Amount.       s.   d.28,095 16  0   112 10  0 5,510  8  0 3,575 18  037,294 12  0    (6.) Number of claims refused owing to inability to trace claimants in M.L.C.Credit Lists approximately 20.    (c.) Number of claims still otxtstanding : Number ofAmount.KenyaTanganyika territoryMafia      :  ...ZanzibarUgandaMen.	&amp; s.	d.13,748	66,788 18	027,535	94,093 6	424	187 6	8325	1,273 16	7780	2,780 7	3Total42,407165,123 14 10men or their dependents.   It is unfortunate that the balances could not have been paid over to the individuals to whom they were due, but it is impossible now for theGovernment to take up the attitude that their liability ended with the failure to trace the individuals, seeing that it has  definitely refused to  agree to a systematicsearch for them.    11.   In this connection it may be mentioned that His Majesty&apos;s Governmenthave recently accepted  a proposal from the German  Government that facilities should be given to them to pay admitted claims by their ex-soldiers, carriers, &amp;c, In Tanganyika territory.  It would be unfortunate if the readiness of their old mastersto pay should cause the natives to  make comparisons in the  matter of good faithunfavourable to the British Administration.    12.   I sincerely hope that the  Cabinet will agree  to the full amount  of  the balances  still unclaimed being  re-voted,  in  order that they may be applied  to  thebenefit of the tribes, and if my appealis unsuccessful I do not  see how I can answerany attacks which may be made, except by saying that the matter has been repeatedlypressed by my predecessors and myself, but that  it has not been found possible tosecure the concurrence of the  other Departments of  State which are  more closely concerned from the financial point of view.                                                             L.  S.  AMEBT.    Colonial Office, June 1925.

</content>
</cab>
