<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/167/17 images: 415-418</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CP(73) 17 COPY NO    g 116 February 1973CABINETDEFAULT UNDER THE HOUSING FINANCE ACT IN ENGLANDMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the environment. Since I last reported to my colleagues (CP(72) 154) the number of authorities in England in default under the Housing Finance Act has reduced to one.    That is Clay Cross Urban District Council (UDC).2. The London Borough of Camden resolved on 10 January to make the required increase in rents towards fair rents and to assess fair rents fortheir dwellings.    The payment of their outstanding subsidy entitlement for1972-73, which I had informed them that I intended to suspend, was made immediately on their taking this decision.3. Conisbrough UDC resolved last v/eek to implement the Act.    I hadalready-given a direction for an extraordinary audit, but since the DistrictAuditor had not completed the audit at the time when the Council made its decision, I have withdrawn my direction, since the loss caused by defaultis no longer a continuing one.    It will therefore fall to be considered byhim at the ordinary audit afcer the end of the present financial year.CLAY CROSS4. The District Auditor on 17 January surcharged the sum of 6, 985 jointly and severally upon the 11 members of the Clay Cross UDC.Because of the size of the sum involved, they are automaticallydisqualified from membership of a local authority for a period of five years.But they have a right of appeal to the High Court.    They have until the endof February to decide whether to appeal.    They have not yet decided whether to do so, although my latest information is that they seem likely to,5. Since the Auditor has served his certificate of surcharge upon them,the Council have taken a number of serious and irresponsible steps.    Theyhave resolved not to pay to the Public Works Loan Board interest amountingto some  20, 000 due to be paid at the end of March.    They are activelysupporting a local rent and rate strike, for example by barring their officers from sending out rent collectors.    They have voted a specialallowance to the Chairman as a means of financing the provision of freeschool milk for children of seven upwards.
6. If the II councillors are disqualified, either as a result of notappealing or if the District Auditor&apos;s findings are confirmed by the Court,the Council will be without members and unable to act.    And under theLocal Government Act 1972 the normal rule is that no election car. takeplace to bill casual vacancies arising on an existing district councilbetween 31 December 1972 and the reorganisation of locai government on1 April 1974.7.        On the latter date, Clay Cross UDC will disappear as such and its functions (including housing) will be exercised by a new district councilcomprising the areas of Clay Cross and two other district councils inDerbyshire.    However, it is my intention to make orders in the summer of 1973, on the recommendation of the Local Government boundary commission, designating certain district councils as &quot;successor parishes&quot;.If such an order were made for Clay Cross - and it is within the guidelinesfor that purpose - the statutory cancellation of by-elections would cease to take effect.    As soon as the order came into force a by-election wouldbe held for Clay Cross and the persons elected would become urban district councillors until 1 April 1974.    They might or might not implement the Housing Finance Act;  if they did not, then the question of default would arise again, with the likelihood of further surcharge and disqualification.8.        Where a district council loses so many members as to becomeunable to act - as may well occur in the case of Clay Cross - the countycouncil for that area have power under Section 72(3) of the LocalGovernment Act 1933 to appoint persons to form the district council.They are noc, however, obliged to do so.    It is likely that DerbyshireCounty Council would be unwilling to appoint persons who would have totake controversial political decisions.9.        It is still open to me to appoint a Housing Commissioner under theHousing Finance Act.    But a Housing Commissioner could only undertakehousing functions.    I have no other power to intervene directly in anyother way.    There are, however, other possible measures.    TheAtiorney General could seek a writ of mandamus, or the Public WorksLoan Board, if the Council were in default, could move to have a receiverappointed.POSSIBLE FUTURE ACTION10.       Much now depends on timing.    If the Clay Cross councillors do notappeal, the Council will be without members at the end of this month and,among other things, no rate for 1973-74 will have been fixed.    In such a situation there would seem to be a strong case for Derbyshire CountyCouncil to intervene, whether or not their appointees took decisions affecting housing functions.    If the councillors do appeal they will remainmembers of the Council until the appeal is heard, which could be somemonths ahead.    They will then be in a position to make a rate, if they donot deliberately abstain from doing so.2
11.        The Minister for Housing and Construction is to discuss theposition in the next few days with the Chairman of Derbyshire CountyCouncil to ascertain the Council&apos;s willingness to appoint persons to forma caretaker council.    I will keep my colleagues informed of developments in the light of whatever decision the Clay Cross councillors take about anappeal against their surcharge.G r department of the Environment16 February 19733


</content>
</cab>
