<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/30/12 images: 132-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1942.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (42) 482.October 23, 1942.WAR CABINET.THE EFFECTS OF AIR RAIDS ON GERMAN CIVILIAN MORALE.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.I circulate to my colleagues herewith a paper on the effects of air raids on german civilian morale, which represents the agreed views of the various departments concerned with this question, including the Service Departments.A. E.Foreign Office, October 23, 1942.ANNEX.The Effects of Air Raids on German Civilian Morale.IN attempting to assess the effects of air raids on German civilian morale wehave considered : (a) What is their effect on the relationship between the German people andthe Nazi regime, and(b) What is their effect on the ability and willingness of the German people to maintain the war effort.2. The German civilian population might be expected to be psychologicallymore susceptible to air raid attack than the British people. The British people were from the start prepared for the worst, whereas the German people had been assured by their leaders, and believed, that they would be safe from enemybombs. The British people had confidence that conditions must soon improve,whereas the German people fear that conditions can only deteriorate. TheBritish people had no thought of any end to the war save victory; the Germanpeople, on the other hand, when the heavy raids hit them, were war weary andsuffering from great nervous strain.3. Heavy raids concentrated in time and space have a disproportionatelygreater effect on morale than less heavy raids. Such concentrated attacks have so far been delivered on comparatively few German towns; but there is evidence to show that in at least some of the areas affected they have caused in varying degrees temporary panic, breakdown in administration and even anti-Nazireactions, including one authenticated case of anti-Nazi rioting in Duisburg. Incertain towns where the A.R.P. organisation has been overwhelmed, a feeling of complete helplessness has been induced and the tendency in such circumstances had been for the victims to throw much of the blame for the disaster on the regime.There have also been isolated cases of subversive activity and this development isknown to be causing increasing concern to the authorities.11881   [24532]
4. In addition to these psychological effects, concentrated raids produce twomaterial effects which severely depress morale   These are: (a) Dislocation of essential services, food supplies and transport; and(6) Accentuation of housing difficulties. The latter has become for theGerman authorities a first-class problem owing to the already existingacute shortage of accommodation, clothes, furniture and labourThere is no doubt that, after a very heavy raid, industrial efficiency is seriously affected in consequence of the preoccupation of those whohave been bombed out with their own personal affairs.5. A by-product of all raids has been loss of sleep. If carried out oftenenough, nuisance raids, as well as medium and heavy raids, have this effect in areas which are liable to heavy attack.6. Thus, concentrated raids have at least temporarily a very damagingeffect on morale in the bombed areas, though it is not yet clear that the effect is of long duration unless the areas in question are subject to the threat of renewedbombing. The incursion of a large number of refugees from a heavily raidedcity into the neighbouring countryside has inevitably produced friction in the reception areas, where stories of their experiences have, in addition, tended to spread alarm and despondency.7. The areas immediately affected, though important, are, however, atpresent limited to a comparatively small part of the Reich. It is too early as yet to be able to determine with any precision the effect of heavy air raids on Germanmorale as a whole. All that can be said with any certainty is that the heavy raidshave contributed as a result of the intensification of food, transport and housingdifficulties to the general nervous strain throughout the Reich. In addition,they are undoubtedly causing anxiety as to the future, and the German authoritiesare doing all they can to forestall a drop in morale by propaganda stressing theimportance of civil defence, the greater sufferings of front-line troops and the certainty of reprisals in due course on Great Britain.8. The conclusion is that, with the exception of the important areasimmediately affected, the heavy raids have not so far seriously weakened the loyalty of the German people to the Nazi regime nor had such an effect on german morale generally as seriously to affect the willingness and ability of theGerman people as a whole to maintain the war effort. None the less, heavy&apos; air raids have already had a sufficiently marked effect on civilian morale for theauthorities to attribute primary importance to the problem. There is anxietyin the highest Nazi quarters that the continued destruction of German citiesby mass air raids, if these are maintained through the winter with increasedregularity and frequency, may lead to grave unrest in the areas affected seriouslythreatening the general war effort.



</content>
</cab>
