<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/52/17 images: 215-232</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cm(73) 39thConclusionsCOPY NO KCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 26 JULY 1973at 11. 00 am present the Rt Hon Edward Heath mp prime minister the Rt Hon Sir Alec Douglas-Home mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Hon Anthony Barber mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Lord Hails ham of St marylebone lord Chancellor(Items 5-8)The Rt Hon William Whitelaw mp secretary&quot; of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon Lord carrington secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon James Prior mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Geoffrey Rippon QC mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Gordon Campbell mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon John Davies mp chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Rt Hon Maurice Macmillan mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Robert Carr mp secretary of State for the home department the Rt Hon Sir Keith Joseph mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher mp secretary of State for Education and science the Rt Hon Peter Walker mp secretary of State for Trade and industry the Rt Hon Peter Thomas QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Joseph Godb&amp;r mp minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC mp minister for Trade and Consumer affairs
THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon John Peyton MP The Rt Hon Patrick Jenkin mp minister for Transport Industries (Item 7)        Chief Secretary, Treasury (Items 5-8)The Rt Hon Francis Pym mp parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat the Rt Hon Sir Burke trend sir John hunt mr P D nairne mr. H F T smith mr P benner mr J An sonMr H F Ellis-rees mr R L BaxterCONTENTSItem                                                             Subject page 1.                   PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRS 12. OVERSEA affairs middle East 1Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting 13.                  EUROPEAN COMMUNITY AFFAIRS 24.                  NORTHERN IRELAND 45. INDUSTRIAL AFFAIRSOperation of the Counter-Inflation (Temporary Provisions)Act 1972 5The Newspaper Industry 5Rent Allowances for Metropolitan Police 56.                  PUBLIC EXPENDITURE 97.                  THE CHANNEL TUNNEL PROJECT 138.                  REORGANISATION OF THE TRAINING OF JUNIOR SOLDIERS 15* *n
PARLIAMENTARY       1. THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL said thatAFFAIRS there had recently been several indications, includingobservations by some of the Select Committees of theHouse of Commons, of a revival of concern about the procedures of Parliament and the possibility of promoting their reform on more practical and realistic lines.    He would in due coursecirculate some reflections on the issues involved, forconsideration by his colleagues.OVERSEAAFFAIRSMiddle east previous reference:CM(73) 26thConclusions,Minute 32. THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH secretary said that the Security Council of the United Nations was considering a resolution on the Middle East.    The text wasnot acceptable to the Israeli Government.    But there seemedto be no possibility of amending it in a way which would makeit less objectionable  to them; and we should have no alternative but to vote for it.Commonwe althHeads ofGovernmentMeetingTHE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat President Amin of Uganda had decided to attend theMeeting of Commonwealth Heads of Government which was to open in Ottawa on 2 August.    This should not inhibit us fromcriticising his Government for their treatment of the UgandanAsians and for their failure to pay compensation to Britishresidents whose property had been confiscated.THE PRIME MINISTER said that we must also be prepared forthe Meeting to seek to criticise both the French Governmentfor the nuclear tests which they were in course of carrying out and the Portuguese Government for their allegedly repressivepolicies in Africa. In addition, there would probably be somecritical reference to our attitude towards Rhodesia. On allthese issues we might find ourselves standing virtually alone.The Cabinet -Took note of the statements by the PrimeMinister and the Foreign and commonwealth secretary.
3, THE CHANCELLOR OF THE DUCHY OF LANCASTER saidthat the meeting of Ministers of the European Economic Community(e.c.) in Copenhagen on 23 July had made some progress in defininga European identity for the purposes of further consideration of the relationship between the Community and the United States,The meeting of the Council of Ministers in Brussels on 23 and 24 Julyhad reached agreement on a satisfactory text for the Community^opening statement at the forthcoming Conference with the associatedStates and the Commonwealth countries eligible for association.In discussion of the forthcoming negotiations under the GeneralAgreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), the French representatives had attempted to insert a provision precluding progress in the multilateral trade negotiations unless there were parallel progressin the monetary discussions.    But after a difficult discussion a specific link of this kind had been avoided.    No agreement hadbeen reached on an offer to be made to countries claiming compensa-tion under Article XXIV(6) of the GATT; but the prospects  or the gatt meeting in Tokyo in September seemed fair.    There had beena difficult discussion about the supplementary budget proposed by theCommission.    The greater part of it related to expenditure entailed by the Common Agricultural Policy (CAP), which the Council had little option but to approve, since it was consequential upon poHcydecisions which had been taken at an earlier stage.    So far we hadnot secured a corresponding increase in the provision for the SocialFund;  and this would be considered further in September.In discussion it was suggested that the supplementary budget raisedserious issues for the United Kingdom.    It was unsatisfactory thatwe had not been able to secure increased provision for the SocialFund while the additional agricultural expenditure, which represented a net loss to the United Kingdom, had been approved.    If we were to anticipate a recurrence of this situation in relation to the SocialFund, we must press our objections at the point when the poHcydecisions which could increase expenditure were being considered.This was the more important in that the supplementary budget wouldbe liable to have an adverse effect on Parliamentary and publicopinion towards the e.c. at a critical juncture in the developmentof the Governments counter-inflationary policies.    It was alreadydifficult to point to benefits which had resulted from our accession,as an offset to the disadvantages which were more evident.    the supplementary budget cancelled out the improvement in our net contribution which had been noted in the 1972 White Paper on public expenditure;  and the financial burden of membership appeared likelyto become heavier rather than lighter, since increases in expenditure under the CAP might counterbalance any net gains which we might make in other areas.   Although our industry was beginning to benefit from access to the larger market and we had been successful in someCommunity negotiations such as the CAP price determinations, thetotal outcome to date was less than satisfactory.
THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that thebalance of advantage to the United Kingdom of membership of theCommunity should be kept under careful review;  and an attempt should now be made to assess it in quantitative terms.    In viewof the financial implications it would be necessary to adopt a determined attitude towards the negotiations with the community on the CAP and the Regional Development Fund.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister fssumming up of their discussion.
northern ireland previous reference:CM(73) 38thConclusions,Minute 54. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN ireland said that the recent major successes of the Security Forces inarresting members of the Provisional Wing of the Irish republican army, including some of its leading figures, were the result of a sustained intelligence effort.    It was perhaps significant that theage of those engaged in violence continued to fall; he had recentlyfelt obliged to issue a detention order against a youth of 15.Agreement had not yet been reached on the choice of a PresidingOfficer for the Northern Ireland Assembly, which was to hold its first meeting on 31 July.    It was important to avoid, if possible,a conflict on this issue between the Social Democratic andLabour Party (SDLP) and the Unionist Party; and, since mr Faulkner, the leader of the Unionists, now appeared to thinkthat he would not have the support of his colleagues in agreeing toan SDLP candidate, it s&amp;emed likely that the choice would fall upon a Unionist member.    Progress towards agreement on the composition of an Executive was proving difficult;  and there was considerable opposition to the choice of Mr Faulkner as chief executive.    The critical point for securing a decision on thismatter was likely to be in September.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Irish Government had cometo the conclusion that the choice of Mr Faulkner as Chief Executivewas the only realistic course, and had tried to persuade the SDLPthat this was so.The Cabinet -Took note of the statements by the Prime Ministerand the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland.ft
INDUSTRIALAFFAIRSOperationof the counter -Inflation(Temporary-Provisions)Act 1972PreviousReference:CM(73) 36thConclusions,Minute 550 THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said thatit had now been decided that the deferred pay increases, totalling 500,000, which the Co-operative Societies had paid to 63,000workers and were likely to pay to 6,000 more did not require the prior approval of the Pay Board.    It would be necessary to reconsider the repercussions of this ruling and the means of deterring othersfrom making use of the same loophole in the Pay Code.    The NationalUnion cf Bank Employees and the National Union of Journalists were known to be seeking legal advice; but there was ixo indication yet ofthe action which they were likely to take.    There might be^few otherinstances in which the Pay Board were inhibited from takingcorrective action in Stage 2 under paragraph 113 of the Code.It would be necessary, however, to keep the position under review.TheNewspaperIndustryPreviousReference:CM(73) 38thConclusions,Minute 6THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said that the newspaper Publishers Association were consulting both the pay board and the Charity Commission about their agreement to payinto a benevolent fund the sums which would otherwise have been due under their threshold agreement with the printing unions.    it seemed likely, therefore, that the resulting arrangements would prove to be in accordance with the Code.    Although Mr. Briginshawwas still agitating for the implementation of the threshold agreement,he was not likely to gain much sympathy when the public becameaware of the high level of pay already received by those concerned.The chapels were now preparing separate &quot;house&quot; claims.The Cabinet -1, Took note of the statements by the Secretaryof State for Employment.RentAllowancesforMetropolitanPoliceTHE HOME SECRETARY said that at a meeting of the ministerial committee on Counter-Inflation Measures on the previous day themembers of the Committee other than himself had taken the viewthat the Pay Board should be asked to rule whether the rent allowance for the Metropolitan Police must be treated as pay for the purpose of the Price and Pay Code.    He had been unableto accept this conclusion and was accordingly referring the matter to the Cabinet.
In recognition of the fact that the police were denied the right to livewhere they chose they had enjoyed for the last 50 years a statutoryentitlement either to free housing or to a rent allowance in lieu.The entitlement to free housing was regularly taken into account in determining pay.    It was a basic element in police conditionsof service; and the rent allowance was essential both for themaintenance of parity between police forces and for the avoidance of unfairness between those who enjoyed free housing and those who did not.    The allowances had never been regarded as part of apoliceman!s pay.    The pay was settled on a national basis, whilethe allowances were reviewed separately for each police force at regular two-yearly intervals.    The latest review of the rent allowance for the Metropolitan Police had recommended thatthe maximum should be increased from  10 to  15. 32,    Thiswould bring the Metropolitan allowance into, line with those inother parts of the country: at present it was less than that inTeesside and equal to that in Gloucestershire,    Agreement hadlater been reached on a national pay increase for the police withinthe Pay Code, to take effect from 1 September.    If the rent allowances were to be brought within the Stage 2 pay limit, the agreement wouldhave to be renegotiated.    This would be keenly resented by the wholepolice force; and in the case of the Metropolitan Police it would be liable to aggravate the recent sharp decline in recruitment,,THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN IRELAND said thathe faced a similar problem in relation to the Royal ulster constabulary (RUC).    There had been a sustained campaign in favour of their being paid, special allowances, which he had successfully resisted on the basis of a settlement within the pay code,    But the discussions had been based on the assumption thatthe rent allowances would be treated as outside the Code,    If thiswas not to be so, the question of special allowances would be revived;  and the position would become very difficult.    TheRUC!s recruitment problem resembled that of the MetropolitanPolice;  and it would be similarly aggravated by an adverse rulingon rent allowances.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said that the increases in rent allowances which had been implemented duringthe standstill had been approved at a time when discretion had lainin the hands of Ministers.    When the Government had established the Pay Board, however, they had taken the decision that all public bodies should be subject to it and that even cases where pay was determined under statutory arrangements should be referred toit.    The Board, as an independent body, must be expected to acton its own interpretation of the Pay Code.    It had the right to demand the prior notification of an increase; and it could rule, on its own initiative, whether the rent allowances were within or outside the pay limit.    If they were within the limit, it could exercise its powers
to reduce the pay settlement for the police accordingly.    When the code was drawn up it had been intended that paragraph 142, whichexempted the reimbursement of expenses incurred in the course ofemployment, would apply to police rent allowances;  but it was forthe Board itself to decide whether to adopt this interpretation.    Inother instances the Board had ruled that rent allowances shouldcount as pay.    The recruitment implications were not necessarilya conclusive argument, for London weighting, which was intendedto deal with an analogous problem, was not exempt -under the Code.If the issue was not submitted to the Board, the Government would put at risk their policy for Civil Service pay and for the remuneration of doctors and dentists;  and it would be unwise to appear to favour the police at the expense of other workers at a time when there wasa possibility of further industrial unrest.    It was reasonable to suppose that the considerations advanced by the Home secretary should influence the Pay Board in reaching its conclusions; butthey should not be used to justify evading the Board&apos;s scrutiny.For these reasons it would be preferable that no decision shouldbe taken until the Board had been consulted.In discussion it was suggested that great weight must be attachedto the recruitment difficulties of the Metropolitan Police and theRUC and that to diminish the statutory right of the policeman to free accommodation would be more serious in its implicationsthan to set aside a collective agreement.    Moreover, the arrangement whereby the rent allowance^ was taxable (even though the tax wasrefunded) while no tax was paid on the free accommodation to whichthe rent allowances&apos; was an alternative was an anomaly which couldnot reasonably be used to justify including the rent allowance, but notthe free accommodation within the pay limit.    It was relevant thatthe increased rent allowance for the Metropolitan Police could havebeen paid in January; that the increases in the correspondingallowances of other police forces which had been approved duringthe standstill had attracted no publicity; that there would be no need to publicise a current increase in the allowance for the MetropolitanPolice outside the police force itself; and that, if the Pay Boardfound that the allowance was not exempt under the Code, theMinister would remain entitled to overrule the Board underSection 6 of Schedule 2 of the Counter-Inflation Act, 1973, eventhough it might be undesirable for the Government to implementthis power.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet felt that some means should be found of enabling theMetropolitan Police to receive their increased rent allowancewithout reducing their Stage 2 pay settlement.    As a first stepthe Secretary of State for Employment should consult the Pay Boardinformally and should ascertain, in particular, whether they would
CONFIDSNTSALagree with the Government in regarding the allowances as exemptunder paragraph 142 of the Price and Pay Code.    In the light of theirresponse he would consider, in consultation with the Secretary ofState and other Ministers concerned, how to give effect to the intentions of the Cabinet.The Cabinet -2. Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister.3. Invited the Secretary of State for employment to consult the Pay Board informally and to report the outcome to the Prime Minister by Monday 30 July.
PUBLICEXPENDITUREPreviousReference:CM(73) 38thConclusions,Minute 76, The Cabinet resumed their discussion of public expenditure to 1977-78,, They had before them a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (CP(73) 87) about public expenditure priorities,THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that at their meetingon 19 July he had explained to the Cabinet the background to the 1973report of the Public Expenditure Survey Committee (PESC),    It hadbeen agreed on that occasion that he should initiate bilateral discussions with Departmental Ministers on the basis proposedin CP(73) 81, with a view to keeping the rate of growth of public expenditure within the totals published in the 1972 White Paper on public Expenditure (Cmnd 5178),    The recent movements in theexchange rate for sterling, which was critically important for the restraint of prices, had re-emphasised the need to maintain this objective.    The Cabinet were not required to take decisions on specific programmes until the bilateral discussions had taken place;and it was at that stage also that final decisions on strategicpriorities would need to be taken.    The Cabinet had expressedthe wish, however, to have an early general discussion of public expenditure priorities;  and for this purpose they had asked forfurther information about the proportion of national resourcesdevoted to the main expenditure programmes.    This information was provided in CP(73) 87, which showed the proportion of total public expenditure represented by the main programmes in 1970-71,1973-74 and 1977-78, together with the rates of increase in theindividual programmes between these years.    Total public expenditure was equivalent to about 50 per cent of the gross domestic product.    The figures were in cost terms, includingthe relative price effect; but further work was being done on the analysis of the relative size of the different programmes in demand terms, with a view to including the relevant information in the 1973White Paper.In discussion it was suggested that, although the proportion of public expenditure devoted to the health and personal social services wasrising during the period, this would still not meet the urgent need toimprove the services for the elderly and disabled.    Provision hadbeen made for some increase in current expenditure; but the annual rate of capital expenditure on these services had now levelled off,even though by the end of the period the numbers of the elderly wouldhave increased by 10 per cent since 1971,    Fewer places for theaged were being built in the United Kingdom than in the Netherlands,which had only a quarter of our population.    Moreover, the numberof new places for the elderly was less than the number of additionalpla&quot;ces provided by the prison building programme; and, howeverdesirable the reduction of overcrowding in prisons might be as an ultimate social objective, it would appear of lower priority than animprovement in the distressing conditions in which many aged people
had to live0    Housing also represented a serious social problem,A reduction in the existing planned figures for the social services would therefore be liable to appear indefensible when increases in real terms were proposed for programmes such as roads and overseas aid, both of which were at present planned to grow more rapidly thanmost other programmes, or the renewal of buses for the NationalBus Company,    If sufficient reductions could not be found by other means, it might be preferable to increase the charges for health and school meals as soon as the counter-inflationary programme would permit rather than to reduce the level of the main social serviceprogramme s0On the other hand, while there might be political difficulties in reducing the social service programme, there were also compellingobjections to reducing those categories of expenditure which werefundamental to economic expansion.    The services which could beprovided for the elderly were basically dependent on the efforts ofthe working population.    The recent strategy presentation to theCabinet by the Central Policy Review Staff had demonstrated theextent to which, as a result of insufficient investment, our economicachievement was falling behind that of other European countries.Decisions to reduce nationalised industry investment, while possiblymore immediately popular with the public, could be very damaging inthe longer term.    The proportion of modern steel-making capacity inthe United Kingdom, for example, was now markedly lower than thatin other countries of the European Economic Community or in theUnited States or Japan,    It would simply be short-sighted to curbprofitable investment, such as that on buses for the National bus company or aircraft for the British Airways Board, which would undoubtedly have qualified for finance on its commercial merits ifthe organisations concerned had been in the private sector.    Whilethe road programme should be critically examined, some roadprojects also could show a high economic rate of return as wellas helping to reduce the burden of casualties on the hospitals.More generally, further analysis was needed to identify those parts of the various programmes which made a particularly effective contribution to economic expansion.In further discussion the following main points were made -a. The estimates for the last two years of the PESCsurvey period were in any case more tentative than those for the earlier years.    Since the present difficulties in increasing health and school meal charges derived fromthe immediate needs of the counter-inflationary policy, itwas for consideration whether, if the responsible ministers were to undertake to increase these charges at some pointbefore 1977, this might justify some reduction in the
contingency allowance incorporated in the PESC totals.There were serious dangers, however, in any further reduction in the contingency allowance, which had alreadybeen reduced by comparison with that provided in the 1972expenditure survey.    If sufficient reductions in expenditure could not be found without prejudice to economic expansion,the possibility of higher levels of taxation should not be altogether ruled out.    A very stringent attitude might also need to be adopted towards the determination of the level of rate support grant; and the possibility of charging for theuse of roads might also be examined^b. The inclusion in a single total of both capital and current expenditure could lead to an unsatisfactory distortionof investment decisions; and it would be helpful if theinformation placed before the Cabinet could distinguishclearly between them.    Moreover, the nationalised industries and the social services did not appear to be dealt with equallyin this respect, in that the cost of the counter-inflationaryaction on health and school meal charges v/as fully countedin the PESC totals, while the cost of subsidising the nationalised industries was only included in those caseswhere a subsidy would evidently be needed, any subsidies to other nationalised industries being left to be borne by the contingency allowance.    It was also arguable that to theextent to which public expenditure programmes were ableto attract capital finance from the private sector^ this shouldbe excluded from PESC, although the diversion of private sector funds to such projects might in practice increase thedifficulties of financing the Governments borrowing requirement.c. In any further discussion of priorities it wouldbe instructive to be furnished with a comparison of therelative amounts devoted by other industrialised countries to the broad categories of defence, social services and support of economic expansion.    Such comparisons,however, would need to be made with care, in view ofthe different ways in which social service expenditure was financed in different countries.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said thatthe Cabinet had now conducted an initial examination of strategicpriorities; but the information provided in CP(73) 87 clearly needed to be supplemented by a more sophisticated analysis.    In particular,more information was required about the extent of the need for certain categories of expenditure, such as roads;  about the distinctionbetween those parts of the expenditure programmes which contributed
to economic expansion and those which financed social objectives;and about the proportions of public expenditure devoted to thedifferent main categories in the United Kingdom and in othercomparable countries.    The Chancellor of the Exchequer should therefore consider the means by which information on these mattersmight best be provided for the Cabinet in the form of a presentationas soon as the holiday period was over.The Cabinet -1. Took note, with approval, of the summing upof their discussion by the Prime Minister.2, Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer -i. To pursue bilateral discussions withother Ministers on the lines agreed at their previous meeting, and to circulate a reporton the outcome as soon as possible.ii. To consider whether, in the meantime,a presentation could be arranged for theCabinet on the lines indicated in the PrimeMinisterls summing up of their discussion.
7, The Cabinet gave further consideration to the Channel tunnel project.    They had before them a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for the Environment (CP(73) 85), together with a draft white paper, which had been circulated by the Minister for transport industries,THE MINISTER FOR TRANSPORT INDUSTRIES said that agreement on the financial terms had not yet been reached with the private companies;  and further negotiations were due to be held duringthe following week.    Once agreement had been reached, however,it would be impossible to prevent the details from becoming widely known; and there would therefore be advantage in publishing theWhite Paper as soon as possible thereafter.    Meanwhile, theexisting contract with the companies would expire on 31 July;and arrangements would have to be made to finance the projectuntil its future was settled.In discussion some concern was expressed that the government might be committed, by the issue of a White Paper during the recess, to a project which would make a heavy demand on resources at a period when public expenditure as a whole would be underpressure; and the Government1? political opponents would notbe slow to suggest that the resources involved might be devotedto programmes of greater social merit.    There were stillconsiderable misgivings about the project in Scotland; andpublic comment in general was tending to associate the ChannelTunnel and the projected Maplin airport as extravagant venturesof doubtful benefit to the country as a whole.On the other hand, the Cabinet had already agreed that, providedthat acceptable financial terms could be secured, the Tunnel shouldbe allowed to proceed to the next stage.    Once agreement aboutthose terms had been reached delay in publishing the government&apos;s decision might be misconstrued by French opinion, while theinternational status of the project itself, together with the natureof the engineering work involved, would make it difficult and costlyto defer the work after it had been launched.    It would be necessary,however, to take vigorous steps to reassure public opinion; and theGovernments exposition of the case for the Tunnel must carryconviction,    A small group of Ministers should therefore examinethe text of the proposed White Paper and consider means of securingits most effective presentation.    In this connection, it was notedthat Annex 5 to the draft text continued to assume a rate of growth of gross national product for the United Kingdom, in the period to1990,   of 3. 5 per cent; and that the arrangements proposed for thepayment of interest to shareholders from capital during theconstruction period depended on powers which had survived in company law since the beginning of the century but had never been invoked hitherto.13CONFIDENTIAL
THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theMinister for Transport Industries, in close consultation with theChief Secretary, Treasury, should continue his negotiations withthe French Government and the private interests about the financial terms.    He himself would make whatever arrangements were required for the necessary consideration of the outcome duringthe Recess; and, subject to its proving satisfactory, the balanceof advantage would probably lie in publishing as soon as possible thereafter the White Paper announcing the decision of principle which the Cabinet had taken at their last discussion about the project.The Lord President should therefore arrange forthwith for theMinisters most closely concerned to examine the draft text in thelight of comments from members of the Cabinet and to considerthe provisional arrangements for its publication.    The necessaryexpenditure should be maintained until the future of the project was settled.    It would be important to ensure, shortly before the white paper was published, that all members of the Government were informed of the announcement of this major policy decision.The Cabinet -1. Took note, with approval, of the summing upof their discussion by the Prime Minister.2, Invited -i. The Lord President of the Council toarrange for the Ministers concerned toconsider forthwith the text of the draft white Paper and the provisional arrangementsfor its publication.ii. The Minister for Transport Industries -a. In consultation with the chief secretary, Treasury, to continue thenegotiations with the FrenchGovernment and the private interestsabout the financial terms and to reportthe outcome to the Prime Minister andother Ministers concerned,b. In consultation with the chief secretary, Treasury, to provide, withthe French Government and the private interests, for the continuation of thenecessary expenditure on the projectfrom 31 July until its future was settled,
REORGANISATION 8. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the SecretaryOF THE of State for the Home Department about the training of junior soldiersTRAINING (CP(73) 84).PF JUNIORSOLDIERS THE HOME SECRETARY informed the Cabinet that as a result of therecent increase in the school-leaving age and a reduction in the periodof training there was now a substantially reduced need for juniortraining facilities in the Army; and the Ministerial Committee on regional Policy and the Environment had accordingly considered aproposal that the Junior Tradesmen^ Regiments at Rhyl (north wales) and Troon (Ayrshire) should be closed and that the training should be carried out elsewhere.    In terms of military organisationthere would be substantial benefits in such an arrangement, including a saving of more than  1 million a year in running costs.    But the closure of Rhyl and Troon would have serious implications for regional policy, since both were areas of high unemployment andthe training centre at Rhyl v/as adjacent to Shotton, where majorsteel closures were also in prospects    The Committee had accordingly recommended that urgent consideration shouldbe given to the continued use of Rhyl and Troon for other military purposes;  and they had also expressed doubt about the wisdom of announcing the cessation of junior training at these two establishmentsuntil some indication could be given that the premises concerned might be put to alternative use,In discussion there was general acceptance of the view that it wouldbe uneconomic to retain Rhyl and Troon for junior training facilitiesor to consider the transfer of infantry junior leaders or tradesmenfrom Shorncliffe to either place.    But the impact on the localeconomy would be serious at troops which also represented theonly remaining military establishment in West Central Scotlandand was therefore of considerable recruitment importance as well;and it would be liable to be even more severe at Rhyl in the light ofits proximity to Shotton,    Since one-third of the Army in the UnitedKingdom still occupied hutted accommodation, it should be possibleto put the premises at Rhyl and Troon to good military use and thereby to maintain a more even distribution of military facilitiesthroughout the country.    Alternatively, it might be possible to use the buildings at Rhyl for a new Borstal which was under consideration.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DEFENCE said that it was atfirst sight anomalous that, at a time when he was being pressed to secure the utmost economy in defence expenditure, he shouldalso be asked to keep in being for military purposes premises and facilities for which the Army had no economic use.    Nevertheless,he would consider further in the broader interests of the Governments- regional policy whether some other use could be found for theB establishments in question, which would mitigate the impact oftheir closure on local employment.
CON Fa3The Cabinet -Approved in principle the closure of the Army juniortraining establishments at Rhyl and Troon, on theunderstanding that the Secretary of State for Defencetin consultation with other Ministers concerned, would endeavour, before announcing this decision, to devisealternative uses for the two establishments, whether for military purposes or otherwise.Cabinet Office26 July 197316

</content>
</cab>
