<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/284/0 images: 3-5</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT.SECRET.                                                         COPY NO.CP. 54 (59) .                            CABINET.  .                       Local Government  (Scotland)*                      Proposed Amending  Legislations             Ilemcrajidun/oy the . Secretary c of -State  for ^Scotland-,,        1*   Representations have been made to me  as  to the  need for immediate   legislation to deal with two points of difficulty  arising out of the present   statutory provisions governing the disqualification of Councillors in   Scotland.   The questions vi/hich have  arisen relate to the right of Councillors   who occupy Council houses to vote on. housing., matters;  and to the placing of   contracts by local authorities with Co-operative Societies in which members   of the local authority have an interest.        2.   So far as the housing difficulty is  concerned,  the present position   is regulated by Section 107 of the Housing (Scotland) Act, 1925, which   provides that &quot;a person shall not vote as a member of a local authority or any   committee thereof upon any resolution or question which is proposed or arises   in pursuance of this Act if it relates to any house, building or land  in   which he is beneficially interested&quot;.   Difficulties in the administration of   housing business, especially in relation to the fixing of rents, have  in   consequence arisen in a number of burghs, owing to  the high proportion of   Councillors occupying council houses.   In each of two areas, for example,   seven out of nine Councillors are understood to occupy council houses, while   in a number of other areas a majority of the Council is similarly situated.   The result is that the conduct of housing business has become in these areas   extremely difficult if not, in relation to such matters as the fixing of   renie,altogether impossible.        5.   As regards the position of Councillors who are  members of   Co-operative Societies, the difficuliy arises  under the Sections of the   Town Councils (Scotland) Act, and the Local Government (Scotland) Acts                                                          relating/
 relating to the  disqualification for &quot;being members of Town, County and District Councils  in Scotland^   Generally those provisions lay down that a person &quot;shall  he disqualified for &quot;being nominated or elected or for being or continuing a councillor if and while he ... 4 has directly or indirectly by himself or his partner any  share or interest in any contract *. ... with,  by or  on behalf  of the Council.&quot;&apos;   An exception is made in favour of Councillors who have  a  share or interest in any company incorporated by Act of Parliament  or Roj^al Charter or under the Companies Acts.   This exception does not cover the case of members of Co-operative Societies, who are  consequently disqualified for membership of the Council in the event of that Council entering  into a contract with the Co-operative Society  of which they are  members.   Public attention has recently been directed to the  position of such Councillors, whose statutory disqualification had not  hitherto been appreciated, and  as in many areas in Scotland contracts with  Co-operative  Societies are in existence there is a danger that a large number of  Councillors will have to vacate their office.   There is also a likelihood that  in such  an event Co-operative Societies whose members are affected may decline  to  enter into further contracts with local authorities. Such  a situation would not only be difficult to defend but might, in certain areas, result in the  disorganisation of such local authority services as the supply of milk to school children, in cases where the only source of supply is  the local Co-operative Society,      4-.  These difficulties do not arise in England, as the lav/ in that country was  altered in the Local Government Act of 1933.   The position inEngland  is, briefly,  that  there is no provision corresponding to Section 107 of the Housing (Scotland)  Act, 1925, under which the first of the difficulties to which I have referred arises, and. no disqualification of a Councillor whohas an interest in a  contract with the local authority from membership ofthe authority.   In the cases both of a Councillor occupying a Council house and of a Councillor who is interested in a Council contract,  the position is                                                             regulated/
       regulated by Section 76 of the Local Government Aetj 1933.   Briefly, this       Section provides that &quot;if a member of a local authority has any pecuniary       interest, direct or indirect, in any contract or proposed contract or other       matter, and is i^resent at a meeting of the local authority at which the       contract or other matter is the subject of consideration, he shall, at the       moeting, as soon as practicable after the commencement thereof, disclose the       fact, and shall not take part in the consideration or discussion of, or vote       on any question with, respect to, the contract or other matter.&quot;   It is       further provided that the Minister of Health &quot;may i . . . remove any       disability Imposed by this section in any case in which the number of members       of the local authoritjr so disabled at any one time would be so great a       proportion of the whole as to impede the transaction of business, or in any       other case in which it appears to ... . the Minister that it is in the       interests of the inhabitants of the area that the disability should be       removed&quot;,            5, I am satisfied tho.t the difficulties to which I have referred are       now acute, and I think that the most satisfactory way of dealing with then is       to introduce legislation on the lines of that which is already in operation in       England,   I am consulting the Departmental Corxiittee which is at present       considering the consolidation of Scottish local government law and I       anticipate that they will endorse this view.   On that assumption, I shall       be glad to have the authority of my colleagues to announce the Government&apos;s       intention to legislate;  and to prepare and submit to the Committee of Home       Affairs a draft of the necessary Bill with a view to its early introduction.       I an assured that it is unlikely to -prove in any way controversial I       As I have indicated, its effect would be to bring; the Scottish lav/ into       line with the lav/ as it has existed in England since 1933.                                                      J.C.Scottish Office,     Whitehall, S.W.1.24th February, 1939.

</content>
</cab>
