<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/5/43 images: 462-467</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
$^jvUvmv] .    22/THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT &quot;TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.S E C R. E T . /W.P.(40) 65. \/fAlso C.0.S.(40) S49(S)).. war GAB IN- JT.FORCE &quot;ST^ATFORIj&quot;^___THE......TI Ti FACTOR.REPORT BY THE CHIEFS OF STAFF CO. I; IITTliE.ACOPY NO.1. At their meeting on the 18th February&quot; the &quot;JarCabinet:-&quot;Invited the Chiefs of Staff to report to theWar Cabinet, as a matter of urgency, theearliest date by which the force &quot;Stratford&quot;( i. e.  the force fcr Bergen, Trondheim andStavanger)  could be made ready to sail.&quot;2. The answer to this question is as follows:-(a) The general position is that once the force is ready, the time lag between thedecision by the &apos; &apos;ar Cabinet for itsdespatch and its arrival in Norwegianports is 3-g- - 4 days;    the precise perioddepending on the time of day when theCabinet decision.is taken.(b) The earliest time at which the troopsearmarked for this operation can be readyto leave their home stations is the earlyhours of the 26th February.(c) Provided the War Cabinet decision to despatchthe force has been given by that time&apos; ( i. e.early hours 26th February),  the troops forBergen and Stavanger could sail on the 28thFebruary and would arrive on the morning of the 29th February.NoteP    The force for Trondheim will notarrive until two days after theforces for Bergen and Stavanger,  asit is to move in a. liner by a -    ^longer sea route,.      The . delay,however,  is of no consequence,  since it would not be practicable for theGermans&apos;to forestall US&apos; at this port.s 7. M. (AO)  4,5th Conclusions, Minute 1.-1-n

3.   IIciintc.inin.rj tho &quot;Stratfor-d&quot; force. at tho abovenotice will entail the withdrawal of 1$. cruisersfrom the Northern patrol &amp;0 tijese ships must beavailable at 36 hours&apos; notice.(Signed) G.L.N. NEWALL.&quot; DUDLEY POUND.&quot; EDMUND IRONSIDE.Richmond Terrace, S.W-1.20th February, 19L0.




</content>
</cab>
