<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/75/0 images: 107-128</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1^CABINETCOLONIAL immigrants memorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations,and the Secretary of State for the ColoniesWe were invited by the Cabinet on 17th February to verify by reference tothe other Commonwealth Governments concerned, whether the draft White paper containing a Summary of the Restrictions on the entry of British Subjects into british Territories overseas and the Irish Republic (annexed to C. (55) 34) wasaccurate (C.C. (55) 15th Conclusions, Minute 4). As a result of this verificationthe draft White Paper has undergone some amendment of detail, and we attach a revision which is accepted by the other Governments as an accurate summary ofthe position in their countries at the present time.A. L.-B.10th June, 1955.46068aPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1955SECRET Copy No.CP. (55) 3111th June, 1955

\ SoSummary of Restrictions on the entry ofBritish Subjects into commonwealth countries and the Irish Republic
PART IRESTRICTIONS ON THE ENTRY OF BRITISH SUBJECTS INTOSELF-GOVERNING COMMONWEALTH countries the following is a summary of the principal relevant regulations in each country at the present time:  canada the Immigration Act, 1952, empowers the Government of Canada toregulate the admission into that country of all persons other than (a) Canadiancitizens and (b) persons who have had a place of domicile in Canada for fiveyears, after having been granted admission therein as an immigrant, and whohave not relinquished the status of &quot; Canadian domicile&quot; thereby gainedthrough departure from Canada for other than a mere special or temporarypurpose.The following classes of persons are (among others) deemed to be prohibited, and persons found to be in those classes may not enter Canada:  &apos; Mentally defective and diseased persons and physically defectivepersons who are likely to become a public charge; criminals, prostitutes,homosexuals and procurers; professional beggars or vagrants; chronicalcoholics, drug addicts or traffickers; persons who are members of or aresuspected of being members of subversive organisations; and thedependents of persons in these classes.Certain classes of persons are allowed to enter and remain in Canadafor limited periods as non-immigrants. These include:  Tourists, visitors, clergymen or priests, students, dramatic, artisticand athletic groups, and persons wishing to enter Canada for thetemporary exercise of their trade or calling.(Persons who enter Canada as non-immigrants and who subsequently donot wish to belong to that class, are bound under Statute to report the fact tothe nearest Immigration Officer and present themselves for examination asmay be directed and such persons are treated as persons seeking admission to Canada as immigrants.)The Governor-General-in-Council is empowered to make such regulations as are necessary to carry out the provisions of the Act, including the prohibitionor limitation of admission of any persons by reason of nationality, citizenship,ethnic group, occupation, class or geographical area of origin, and the criteriacontained in sub-paragraph id) of paragraph 6 below.The Immigration Regulations, 1954, provide, inter alia, the following&quot; norms of admissibility &quot;:  (a) British subjects by birth, or naturalisation, in the United Kingdom,Australia, New Zealand or South Africa, and citizens of the irish republic, may be admitted if they have sufficient means to maintainthemselves until they have secured employment.ib) The admission of any Asian is limited to the wife, husband orunmarried children, under 21 years of age, of any Canadian citizenresident in Canada who is in a position to receive and care for them as dependents.
\(c) The landing in Canada of any immigrant is limited to the nationals of a country with which the Canadian Government has entered into anagreement or convention respecting immigration or in regard to whichthere is in operation an agreement or convention.00 The admission into Canada of. any person is prohibited when, in theopinion of a Special Inquiry Officer, that person should not be admitted by reason of:  (i) the peculiar customs, habits, modes of life or methods of holdingproperty in his country of birth, citizenship or prior residence;(ii) his unsuitability, having regard to the economic, social, industrial,educational, labour, health, or other conditions or requirementsexisting temporarily or otherwise in Canada, or the area or country from or through which he comes;(iii) his probable inability to become readily: assimilated to or assume the duties and responsibilities of Canadian citizenship wthin areasonable time.No immigrant is to be admitted to, Canada without a medical certificateshowing that he has undergone medical examination sufficient to establishthat he does not fall within the relevant clauses of persons prohibited by the immigration Act. This provision does not, however, apply in the case ofpersons who are British subjects by birth, or by naturalisation, in the UnitedKingdom, Australia, New Zealand, or the Union of South Africa, or citizens of the Republic of Ireland, though such persons may, as a measure offacilitation, equip themselves with a medical certificate. It also does notapply to persons coming directly from the United States of America or Alaska.However, all immigrants are subject to medical examination before beingadmitted.British subjects seeking to enter Canada must be in possession of anunexpired passport issued by the country of which such person is a subject orcitizen, except those born or naturalised in the United Kingdom, Australia,New Zealand or the Union of South Africa.australia the entry into Australia of all persons other than those whose permanenthome is in Australia is regulated by the provisions of the Immigration Act.1901-1949.The Immigration Act applies only to the mainland of Australia andTasmania.The Act specifies that the following persons are prohibited immigrantsand that their entry is forbidden unless they are possessed of a certificate -of exemption issued by or with the authority of the Minister for Immigration :persons who if required to pass a dictation test in any European languagefail to pass that test; persons suffering from mental or prescribed physicaldiseases; prostitutes, procurers or persons living on the;prostitution of others; persons who are considered likely by reason of infirmity or otherdisability to become a charge on the public; persons who advocaterevolutionary or subversive practices; persons who have been convicted of a crime and sentenced to imprisonment for a year or more; personswho have been deported from Australia and are not authorised to return;persons declared by the Minister as a result of information received from another Government to be undesirable inhabitants or visitors; and personsover 16 years of age who are unable on demand to produce a passportor similar document and authority for entry into Australia.348068 n*
In practice British subjects, of European race who do not come withinthe above-mentioned: classes are admitted freely as visitors or permanentresidents and do hot require any special authority to enter Australia. It isthe practice, however, to demand the production of a valid passport in orderto establish that they are. British subjects.The dictation test arid the power to demand production of a passport and authority for entry into Australia are two means by which the Minister mayprohibit the entry of persons who are regarded as undesirable residents orvisitors but whose entry is not specifically prohibited by Statute; while thepower given to the Minister to admit persons Under certificate of exemptionenables him to allow prohibited immigrants to enter lawfully where thereare special reasons Why they should be exempted.&apos;Non-European British subjects who are not prohibited immigrants by statute are generally admitted quite freely as visitors or for specified purposesof temporary duration such as education, medical treatment and the conductof overseas trade between Australia and their own countries. They are not generally admitted for permanent residence and are required to be inpossession of valid travel documents and authority to enter Australia. Ifthey are unable to produce such documents they may be prohibited fromlanding.New ZealandImmigration into New Zealand is controlled by the ImmigrationRestrictionActs, 1908-1951.The following classes of persons are deemed 10 be prohibitedimmigrants: :.Idiots or imbeciles, persons suffering from a loathsome or contagiousdisease, persons who have within two years of arrival been released from imprisonment imposed for serious criminal offences.All persons subject to infirmity of any kind require special permission toenter. The Attorney-General may.prohibit the entry of any person notpermanently resident in New Zealand whose presence might be injurious tothe peace, order and good government of the country.Persons not of British birth and parentage are required to be inpossession of a valid permit. To be of &quot; British birth and parentage&quot; aperson must be a natural-born British subject born of parents of Europeanstock who were themselves British by birth. The term &quot; British birth andparentage &quot; expressly excludes persons who, or either of whose parents, arenaturalised or persons who are, or are descended from, aboriginal natives ofany Dominion other than the Dominion of New Zealand, or of any british colonial territory. Any British subject arriving without a permit but provingto the satisfaction of the Minister of Immigration that he desires to enterNew Zealand as a visitor for not more than six months for business, pleasureor health, may be granted a temporary permit.&apos;-- &apos;  *&apos; Union of South africa the entry of all persons other than South African citizens is controlled by the Immigrants Regulation Act, 1913, as.amended, which specifies certainclasses of prohibited immigrants, viz:-.Persons who on economic grounds or on account of standards orhabits of life are deemed unsuited to the requirements of the union or any particular province thereof (including South-West Africa);persons unable by reason of deficient education to read or write any european language; persons likely to become a public charge by reason
\. of infirmity or lack of means; persons who from information receivedfrom any Government are deemed to be undesirable inhabitants of orvisitors to the Union; criminals, idiots, seriously diseased persons,consumptives, prostitutes,. procurers and persons convicted of seriouscrimes.Persons not of pure European descent must obtain prior permission toenter the Union.:British subjects who fall within the Aliens Act, 1937, i.e., those, whoare not natural-born British subjects, citizens of South Africa, or lawfullydomiciled in the Union, are required to obtain permits to enter the union for the purpose of permanent residence. ...All natural-born British subjects who do not fall within the prohibitedcategories are free to enter the Union.In terms of section 8 (1) of the South Africa, Citizenship Act, 1949, aBritish Subject may only apply for registration as a South African citizenafter five years&apos; continuous and unrestricted residence in the Union withinthe period of six years immediately preceding the date of application.india the Indian Passport Act, 1920, empowers the Government of India tomake rules to require persons entering India to be in possession of passportsand for matters ancillary to that purpose. The Indian Passport Rules, 1950,provide that British subjects (with minor exceptions) proceeding from anyplace outside India and seeking to enter India must be in possession ofa valid passport endorsed as valid for entry into India.An amendment to the Indian Passport Rules, 1950, made in 1952 providesthat Pakistanis must be in possession of a visa for entry into India. Ceylonesealso require visas.The Reciprocity Act, 1943, provided that persons not being of Indianorigin domiciled in a British Possession should be entitled only to such rightsand privileges as regards, inter alia, travel and residence as were accordedby such Possession to persons of Indian origin. In 1944 the Governmentof India applied these powers to persons not of Indian origin domiciled inthe Union of South Africa, who accordingly require permits for entry into and residence in India.PakistanThe Indian Passport Act, 1920, empowers the Government of Pakistanto make rules to require persons entering Pakistan to be in possession ofpassports and for matters ancillary to that purpose. Rules made by theGovernment of Pakistan under that Act provide that no person proceedingfrom any place outside Pakistan shall enter Pakistan unless he is in possessionof a valid passport. Members of Her MajestyVNaval, Military or AirForces entering Pakistan on duty and members of the family of such personswhen accompanying such persons to Pakistan on a Government transport are exempt from this requirement. According to these rules British subjectscan enter Pakistan only on passports issued and specifically endorsed asvalid for entry into Pakistan.The Pakistan (Control of Entry) Act, 1952, requires Indian citizensentering Pakistan to be in possession of valid passports duly visaed for entry into Pakistan. 5The Indian Reciprocity Act, 1943, provided that persons not being ofIndian origin domiciled in a British Possession should be entitled only tosuch rights and privileges, as. regards, inter alia, travel, and, residence as wereaccorded by such Possession to persons of, Indian origin.   In 1944 the548068 c* 2
Government of India applied these powers to persons not of Indian origindomiciled in the Union of South Africa, who accordingly require permitsfor entry into and residence in India. These provisions remain in force inrespect of entry into and residence in Pakistan.Ceylon .   , ,The, Immigrants and Emigrants Act of 1948 and the regulations made there under give powers to the Government&apos; of Ceylon to control the entryand stay of all persons, other than citizens of Ceylon, and the departure of all persons. All persons other than citizens of Ceylon, unless they havebeen specifically exempted, require a visa or residence permit for purposesof entry into and stay in Ceylon. jNormally permission to enter Ceylon will be refused to: persons whoare unlikely to be able to support themselves and their dependants; mentallydefective persons or persons with communicable diseases; prostitutes andprocurers; stowaways; persons who have been sentenced for extraditableoffences; and persons deemed to be undesirable or dangerous to the peace and good. order of Ceylon.In practice, citizens of Commonwealth countries, other than India,Australia, New Zealand and South Africa, who wish to enter Ceylonas bond fide tourists for short periods can obtain the necessaryentry facilities at port of entry, Citizens of India, Australia,New Zealand and South Africa are, however, required to be inpossession of a visa before seeking to enter Ceylon. The maximum periodof a stay permitted by a visa is six months. Statutory provision also existswhereby the Controller of Immigration can, if he considers necessary, takea security deposit not exceeding 500 rupees before granting a visa.Permanent residence permits may be issued to (a) the spouse or dependent child of a citizen of Ceylon;(b) any other dependant of a citizen of Ceylon if his maintenance isassured;(c) any person of good character who has or is likely to acquire apermanent and abiding interest in Ceylon;(d) the spouse or minor child of the holder of a permanent residencepermit, if the Controller is satisfied that adequate means will beavailable for the maintenance of such spouse or child.Note. The issue of permanent residence permits has now been sus-pended indefinitely.Temporary residence permits may be issued to id) any person to whom a permanent residence permit would have beengranted if he had applied for one;y(b) British subjects who were ordinarily resident in Ceylon for,a period. of at least five years, immediately preceding 1st November, 1949;;-i (c) a. person of good character having, adequate means for his main-tenance, if. the Controller is satisfied that such person is.  .,.(i) a person for whom a place has been reserved in an approved&apos;. educational institution, or &apos;,., (ii) an apprentice or trainee in an approved firm or business under-&apos;   taking, or a person serving a period of apprenticeship with a viewto qualifying himself for admission to a profession, or(in) a person who wishes to spend a holiday in Ceylon, or
(iv) a person desirous of conducting an approved trade or business,provided the Controller is satisfied that the person has the necessaryaptitude and means to conduct such trade or business with reasonable prospects of success and his conduct of such trade or business will not bei prejudicial to the interests of the permanentinhabitants of Ceylon, or(v) a person having definite prospects of securing remunerativeemployment in an approved trade or business, provided theController is satisfied that such person has the necessary aptitudeso to be employed and his employment in such trade or businesswill not be prejudicial to the interests of the permanent inhabitants of Ceylon.Note. Legislation is about to be introduced to substitute visas of shortor long duration for all residence permits.-     Federation of Rhodesia and NyasAlandThe entry of all persons into the Federation is controlled by the provisionsof the Immigration Act, 1954, and the Regulations made thereunder.The following classes of persons are prohibited immigrants: -id) any person or class of persons deemed on economic grounds or onaccount of standard or habits of life to be undesirable inhabitants or tobe unsuited to the requirements of the Federation;(b) persons, other than Africans, who are unable, by reason of deficienteducation, to read and write a European language;             .(c) persons likely to become a public charge by reason of infirmity or lackof means;(d) persons (with certain exceptions) physically afflicted, or suffering frommental or prescribed physical diseases;(e) persons convicted of serious criminal offences, or deported from theFederation; , -(/) prostitutes, homosexuals or procurers;(g) any person who, from information received from any Government, is deemed to be an undesirable inhabitant or visitor;(h) persons not in possession of a valid passport.The Governor-General is also empowered to make regulations for furthercontrolling, restricting or prohibiting the entry of persons into the Federation,and such regulations may, inter alia, provide for requirements as to (1) education, training and experience;(2) capital or income;(3) the obtaining of employment in the Federation before arrival and forsuch period as may be prescribed;(4) the setting up of Boards or other authorities for the (selection of immigrants.Such regulations may prescribe different requirements for. different classes ofpersons or for persons of different occupations, and limit the number ofpersons from any specified country or group; of countries which may be permitted to enter the Federation during any specified period.The Immigration (Selection) Regulations, 1954, made under these powersprescribed that no European visitor to the Federation shall take up employmentin the Federation or remain longer than 12 months, unless he has beengranted a residence permit. Residence permits are to be granted.by the BritishImmigrant Selection Boards set up in London and Salisbury, in accordancewith quotas prescribed for countries or groups of countries; to persons ofg7
l     ^O:......Jgood character likely to be efficient in the occupation to be undertaken in theFederation, in possession of sufficient capital or income, or likely to earnsufficient means for the maintenance of themselves and their families.A temporary permit may be issued to any immigrant prohibited otherthan on the grounds specified in (a) and (g) in paragraph 2 above.PART IIRESTRICTIONS ON , THE ENTRY OF BRITISH SUBJECTS INTOTHE DEPENDENT OVERSEAS TERRITORIESGeneralEvery oversea territory has its own immigration legislation to govern the entry of persons other than those defined in the law as &quot; natives of &quot; or&quot; belonging to &quot; the territory. Few territories have separate legislation forBritish subjects and the conditions governing entry are, as a rule, applicablefor both British subjects and aliens.The legislation varies from territory to territory, but it generally definesthose who are exempted from its operation and those whose entry is prohibited. In many territories the Governor has absolute discretion to prohibit the entry of any person not regarded as belonging to the territory.The particular categories of exempted and prohibited immigrants again vary from territory to territory, but they usually include some or all of the following catergories.Prohibited classes:-(a) any person Who is unable to show that he has the means of supportinghimself and his dependants, or that he has definite employmentawaiting him, or he is likely to become a pauper, or a charge on public funds;(b) anyone who is suffering from mental disorder or is a mental defective;(c) any person suffering from an infectious, contagious or communicabledisease;(d) prostitutes;(e) vagrants and habitual beggars;(f) any person whose presence is considered to be harmful to good order and government;(g) any person who in consequence of information received from any source deemed to be reliable is deemed to be undesirable;(Ji) any person previously repatriated or deported from the territory;(/)&apos; any person who has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment,and has not received a free pardon;(k) any person who may be deemed by the Governor to be an undesirableimmigrant.The exempted classes normally include (a) those deemed to be &quot; natives of &quot; or &quot; belonging to &quot; the territory as defined in the law,(6) those in the service of the Government of the territory or inapproved employment,(c) Members of Her Majesty&apos;s regular armed forces.For those not in either the &quot;prohibited&quot; or &quot; exempted &quot; classes theconditions of entry vary as to whether the person is a visitor or intends tobecome a resident.
\Aden Colony &apos;The Governor may, in his absolute discretion, prohibit the entry of anyperson, not being a British subjects born in Aden, provided that no subjectof Her Majesty shall on grounds of religion, place of birth, colour, descent,or any of them, be prohibited on such grounds from entering the Colony.Intending residents must obtain a permit from the Principal immigration officer, and permission will be granted&apos;only to persons taking up employment: in an approved occupation.,....   .....  .......Visitors are granted permits On arrival, valid for three months; provided they are properly documented,&apos;-&apos;have sufficient funds to reach their destination or an onward passage ticket.A. deposit, in cash or by bond, of -up to  100 may be required by the immigration Officer, of anyone entering the Colony.Aden ProtectorateEntry into the Protectorate is prohibited without prior permission.Intending visitors or immigrants must apply to the Chief Secretary, AdenGovernment, setting out their reasons for wishing to enter the Protectorate.If entering via the Aden Colony, the colony immigration regulations apply.BahamasImmigrants i.e., any person not a native of the Colony and a british subject, or his wife or child under 16, must produce medical and charactercertificates, and a deposit of  20 or sureties. Bona fide visitors, persons in transit or with return tickets, persons in an official position in the Colony,and persons who have resided for 5 years or more and who have not beenabsent more than 2 years are not treated as immigrants., Immigrants maybe required to leave or be deported if they receive a prison sentence, orbecome an inmate in a lunatic asylum, or pauper, or if they are consideredundesirable. No separate provision exists for the treatment of Britishsubjects not natives of the Colony. Intending residents must obtain permission from the Immigration Officer which will be granted only to thosetaking up employment in an. approved occupation or who are in a financialposition to maintain themselves without taking up employment in the Colony.Visitors are granted permits on arrival valid for 8 months, provided theyare properly documented, have passage tickets out. of the Colony, and sufficient funds for their destination. The holder of a visitors permit maynot take employment without the permission of the Immigration Officer.The Immigration Officer may, at his discretion,, require anyone entering the Colony, to make a deposit in cash, or. by. bond, to cover repatriationexpenses. &apos; &apos; . . -     ;    ., , .Barbados -Sec under West Indies.Basutoland, Bechuanaland Protectorate and SwazilandThese territories form the High Commission; Territories and their requirements are as follows:   &apos;       .    : .British subjects who are not prohibited immigrants may; enter, the territories for a temporary purpose without prior permission;   ,
For this purpose the term prohibited immigrant includes any person orclass of persons deemed on economic grounds, or on account of standards orhabits of life to be potentially undesirable inhabitants: it also includes idiots,epileptics, persons suffering from certain diseases and persons with seriouscriminal records.For more than purely temporary residence, official permission is required under the legislation in force in each territory.Bechuanaland ProtectorateSee under Basutoland.BermudaBritish subjects not Bermudians by birth must have 7 (temporarily 8) years&apos;residence in the Colony before acquiring domicile, which confers the rightto carry on any trade, profession or business, to enter into employment, andbe exempt from liability of deportation. Permission for undomiciled persons to enter employment is conferred in respect of a few approved forms ofoccupation or by special permission only. Domicile is lost if the person concerned has resided in another part of^ Her Majesty&apos;s dominions for7 years or more. No difficulties are placed in the way of bona fide visitorsand persons of independent means wishing to take up residence. the implementation of legislation is in the hands of a statutory Board of immigration which works more or less autonomously and interprets the lawstrictly.New legislation, now passing through the Bermuda Legislature, providesfor the acquisition of &quot; Bermudian Status &quot; for which the qualifying periodof residence will be 7 years, as previously in the case of domicile. Theacquisition of Bermudian Status after the qualifying period is, however, notto be automatic but at the discretion of the Governor-in-Council. For those not of Bennudian birth, Bermudian status will be lost after 5 years unless theperiod is extended up to 7 years by the Governor-in-Council.British GuianaProhibited and exempted classes are as in the &quot; General&quot; section above,but dependants of exempted persons also qualify for exemption.Generally, permission to enter the Colony for permanent residence is granted to British subjects on condition that they furnish satisfactory evidencethat they are in a position to support themselves for an indefinite period,i.e., they must either hold a guarantee of employment from a reputable firmor organisation established locally, or be in possession of adequate financialmeans. British subjects wishing to enter the Colony for permanent residenceare advised also to apply in advance to Chief Immigration Officer of british guiana for an entry permit. In addition they are required to make a depositvarying from (B.W.I.) $96 ( 20) to (B.W.I.) $2,000 ( 417) according to country of origin. For temporary residents the only requirement is a deposit or,alternatively, possession of a ticket for a return passage or, if in transit, for a passage to next destination.British HondurasThe Immigration Ordinance does not discriminate between British subjects and those of other territories.Visitors who are properly documented must be in possession of - sufficientfunds to defray the cost of their stay.  They must have onward or return
passage tickets or adequate funds for securing the same. They may be askedto furnish security in the form of a cash deposit or a bond to cover the costof a return fare to their country of origin.Intending residents should obtain a permit from the Chief immigration officer. Such permits are issued only to certain classes of persons, the mostoutstanding being:  (a) persons possessing professional or specialist qualifications which wouldenable them to earn their living without prejudicing the interests of thepeople already resident who hold the same qualifications;(b) persons who are skilled artisans whose entry will be in the economic interest of the country and whose trade or occupation is undermanned;(c) farmers and planters who have sufficient funds (minimum  500) toestablish themselves as such in the country;id) persons who are employees of established firms;ie) persons who satisfy the immigration authorities that they have an assured income, will not become a charge on public funds and thattheir entry is not contrary to the public interest;if) any other person whose admission would in the opinion of the immigration authorities be in the interest of the country.Such persons are required to make an immigration deposit depending on theircountry of origin and varying from $10 (U.S.) to $1,000 (U.S.). At the discretion of the Chief Immigration Officer a bond in lieu may be accepted.They may also be required to produce a character certificate.British Solomon Islands ProtectorateIntending residents must obtain a permit from the Principal immigration officer, and permission will be granted only to those taking up employmentin an approved occupation. Visitors may enter and remain for a periodof 4 months, subject to their being properly documented, having onwardpassage tickets or sufficient funds to reach their onward destination.The Principal Immigration Officer may, at his discretion, require anyoneentering the Protectorate to make a deposit in cash, or by bond, of a sumcovering the cost of either air or steamship passage from the Protectorateto the person&apos;s country of domicile.Brunei, North Borneo and SarawakIn all three territories any person, including a British subject, can be refused entry for permanent residence if he is not sponsored or has no definiteemployment waiting for him, unless he is a person born in the territory whohas not subsequently become an alien. Entry can also be refused to anyperson declared undesirable.The Governor of Sarawak also has power to prohibit or limit entry into the Colony of any person or class of persons in the interest of public security, or by reason of any economic, industrial, social, educational orother conditions in the Colony.The Governor of North Borneo has power to prohibit the entry of anyperson or class of person whose entry is considered to be to the prejudice ofthe inhabitants of the Colony, and may prescribe any class of persons asprohibited immigrants.Intending residents for Brunei State must obtain a permit from the SeniorImmigration Officer, and permission will be granted only to those taking upemployment in an approved occupation.y
For Sarawak permission is issued only for a limited category ofemployment.For North Borneo permission is only granted for limited categories ofemployment. British subjects who have not obtained permission to enterbefore sailing for the Colony are liable only to be granted visitors permitfor not more than three months&apos; stay. Entry from Hong Kong or China is prohibited except under special permit.,-. Anyone entering Sarawak or North Borneo may be required to makea deposit in cash or by bond, while for Brunei there is a stipulated amountof money which an immigrant must have in his possession on arrival.CyprusBritish subjects who are not prohibited immigrants may enter the Colonywithout formality. The Chief Immigration Officer may, however, impose suchconditions, limitations or restrictions, as he may think fit, on their residence.East AfricaImmigration legislation common to the three mainland territories (Kenya,Uganda and Tanganyika), applying both to British subjects and aliens, wasenacted in 1948 and broadly maintains the same form at present. Similarlegislation was enacted in Zanzibar, but in 1954 it was amended to control the entry of East Africans from the mainland.Under the provisions of the legislation no one may enter any of the east african territories who is not in possession of a valid entry permit or pass,except serving members of Her Majesty&apos;s Forces and their families and theaccredited Diplomatic and Consular representatives of other countries andcertain categories of exempted persons.An intending immigrant who wishes to remain in a territory for longer than 4 years (i.e., to become a &quot; permanent resident&quot;) must apply to theauthorities for one of eight classes of Entry Permits. The application isconsidered either by the Principal Immigration Officer or by an immigration control Board appointed by the appropriate Governor-in-Council (or by theBritish Resident in Zanzibar), but the Principal Immigration Officer mustin all cases be satisfied that the applicant belongs to the class in respect ofwhich application is made. Once having satisfied the Principal immigration officer, and the Board where necessary, a person (other than a prohibitedimmigrant) is entitled to the issue of an Entry Permit. Appeals against decisions of the Control Boards are heard by Immigration Appeal Tribunals,also appointed by the territorial Governors-in-Council (or by the british resident in Zanzibar).The eight classes of Entry Permits cover : (a) permanent residents and government servants, (6) farmers, (c) prospectors, (d) traders and merchants,(e) manufacturers, (/) members of certain prescribed professions (e.g., medical,dental, legal, and veterinary), (g) persons who have been offered and have accepted employment (other than temporary employment) in a territory,and (fi) persons of independent means. Where an immigrant is to be self-employed, he is required to have sufficient capital to set up in business.Provision is made in the regulations for the issue of Temporary Employ -ment Passes.to cover employment in a territory for a period not exceeding4 years. These Passes are issued at the discretion of the Principal immigration officer in each territory.: Certain categories of. persons may be declared prohibited immigrants, inone category the Governor of the territory must be satisfied that the person is an undesirable immigrant; in the remaining categories, the Principal
Immigration Officer is the authority to be satisfied, save that in one instancehis decision is subject to confirmation by the Governor-in-Coiincil of theterritory concerned (or by the British Resident in Zanzibar). These categoriesinclude destitute persons; mental defectives; those who fail to submit to&apos;a medical examination, or who are certified to be suffering from any infectiousof contagious disease which would make their presence in a territorydangerous to the community; convicted murderers and others who have served prison sentences; prostitutes or any person who may have received orlived on immoral earnings; anyone&apos;&apos;who enters a territory illegally. &apos;the governors may make orders for the deportation of any persons who havebeen declared prohibited immigrants.Any person, other than a permanent, resident, entering the East african territories may be required to make a deposit to cover the cost of possiblerepatriation. -  ;  - * - &apos;.Visitors&apos; passes for tourists or business men, valid in the first instancefor 3 months and extendable to 12 months, are issued in Uganda at the discretion of the Principal Imigration Officer in Uganda.Falkland IslandsThe Governor may prohibit any person landing in the Colony and may require any person entering the Colony, who appears to be a prohibitedimmigrant, to make a deposit in cash, or by bond, of  100 pending productionof a certificate that he is a fit and proper person to be received as animmigrant.Federation of Malaya and SingaporeBoth territories have in general terms the same regulations and movement between them is unrestricted except under the Emergency Regulations.In the Federation of Malaya, apart from the Emergency Regulations,restrictions on the entry of British subjects are imposed by the Immigration(Prohibition of Entry) Order, 1953. Its object is to ensure that nobodyis admitted whose entry is not of benefit to Malaya. With certain exceptions,of which the most important provides for the entry of wives and children of residents in Malaya, the Order allows a British subject to enter Malayaonly if he falls within one of the following categories:  (a) he possesses professional or specialist qualifications which would enable him to earn his living in Malaya without prejudicing the interests.of people already resident who hold the same qualifications;, or(b) he is an employee of an established firm and holds a Contract ofService providing for his employment on such terms and conditionsas to minimum period of engagement and minimum remuneration asmay from time to time be laid down. (At present the minimum period is 2 years and the minimum, remuneration is, $500 per month); or -    .-.. ... - *     &apos; ;(c) he is a skilled artisan whose entry will be in the economic interests of malaya and whose.trade or occupation isundermanned; pr, , j&apos;(d) he is any other person whose admission would,.in, the opinion ,of.,thecompetent authorities be in the economic interests of Malaya. /These restrictions do not,&apos; however, apply to a British subject who is alsoa citizen of the Federation, or who was born in Malaya or has lived there for7 of the last 10 years, or becomes a British subject by local naturalisation.These have a right of entry at any time. ; Nor do they apply to a temporaryvisit pass issued on condition that its holder does not take up any employment without consent of the Government.
Other restrictions imposed under the Emergency Regulations provide that any British subject who wishes to enter the Federation must hold anentry permit,; unless he is either a citizen of the Federation, or a british subject born in Malaya and ordinarily resident there who has not travelledon a foreign passport, or a serving member, of Her Majesty&apos;s armed forces,or the wife and child of such a member.Similar restrictions, with very much the same exceptions, are imposed in singapore. .. .Entry permits both to the Federation and Singapore may be refused atthe discretion of the Departments of Immigration, and security deposits maybe required against the issue of Visit Passes. .ixi mi) -\ni-iu-.- rn&quot;.;:,:&apos; ii\pr, ,,-JPvi i   :    ,    ------   :        :&quot;No person (other than persons who belong to Fiji, members of Britishand Allied armed forces, and persons employed by commonwealth governments) may enter the colony for a stay of more than 4 months withouta permit.Permits to reside for a period less than 4 years may be issued to persons under short-term contracts of employment with local undertakings, and such persons as skilled tradesmen, apprentices and miners.Permits to reside permanently in the Colony will, save in very exceptional circumstances, be issued only to certain classes of persons, the most importantbeing:  (a) Professional men and women with recognised qualifications who intend to practice their profession in the Colony.(b) Persons who satisfy the immigration authorities that they have an assured income, will not become a charge on public funds, and thattheir entry is not contrary to the public interest.(c) Farmers and planters who have already acquired a property in theColony of not less than 100 acres, three-quarters of which is productiveland.Visitors must be in possession of adequate funds and have onward orreturn passage tickets. They may be asked to furnish security in the formof a cash deposit or a. bond to cover the cost of a return fare to theircountry of origin.GambiaPersons wishing to enter for permanent residence or employment must make prior application. Such persons are subject to conditions as to durationand place.of residence, occupation or business, security to be furnished, andany other conditions as the Immigration Officer may impose. permission to enter to take up employment in any occupation which is adequatelycatered for, or which can be undertaken by Africans will not  as a rule,be granted.Visitors who are properly documented and have sufficient funds for their return journey may be granted permits on arrival valid for any period up toone month.The Immigration Office may require any person entering the Gambiato make a deposit in cash, or by bond, of a sum sufficient to cover cost of repatriation.
nGibraltarEntry of all persons who are not natives of Gibraltar, other than her majesty&apos;s Forces, is prohibited except on a temporary permit for which priorapplication has to be made if the visit to to last more than one month andwhich can be revoked at any time by the Governor. Persons are allowedto take up employment in Gibraltar only in exceptional circumstances, andthen only when an application made in advance by the prospective employerhas been approved.The Commissioner of Police has the right to refuse entry into Gibraltarto any person without assigning any reason.Gilbert and Ellice Islands ColonyIntending residents must obtain a permit from the Principal immigration officer, and permission will be granted only to those taking up employmentin an approved occupation. Visitors may enter and remain for a periodof four months, subject to their being properly documented, having onwardpassage tickets or sufficient funds to reach their onward destination.The Principal Immigration Officer may, at his discretion, require anyoneentering the Colony to make a deposit in cash, or by bond, of a sum covering the cost of either air or steamship passage from the Colony to the person&apos;scountry of domicile.Gold CoastBritish subjects seeking to enter the Gold Coast either as residents orvisitors are not required by law to be in possession of entry permits, butthey are advised to obtain them prior to entry in order to ensure that they willbe permitted entry under the provisions of the Immigration Ordinance.No person other than a native of West Africa (as defined) is permitted,without the permission of the Principal Immigration Officer, to accept anypaid or unpaid employment in the Gold Coast, change employment orestablish or enter into partnership in any firm established in the Gold Coastor form or take part in forming a company under the Companies Ordinanceor accept any directorship paid or unpaid in any such company. Applicationsfor permission to establish businesses must be submitted to the commissioner of Commerce. A person wishing to establish a business in the Gold Coastis required to have a minimum capital of  5,000 except in the case of a professional practice where a capital of  1,500 is required.The Immigration Officer may, at his discretion, require any one entering the Gold Coast to make a deposit in cash or by bond of the cost of thereturn fare to thecountry of domicile of the traveller plus 25 per cent.Visitors who have not obtained prior approval to enter are grantedpermits on arrival for a period of 14 days subject to extension at the discretion of the Principal Immigration Officer. They are required to be fullydocumented and have a return passage ticket of produce evidence of sufficientfunds to reach their destination.The Governor, notwithwithstahding anything in the ImmigrationOrdinance, has power to prohibit the entry of any person or class of persons.Hong.Kong, i-^u--::All British subjects not born in the Colony require an entry permit granted by the Immigration Officer, who has power to refuse entry to undesirableimmigrants, including persons without-the means of subsistence or areasonable prospect of employment.
nJamaicaSee under West Indies.KenyaSee under East Africa.Leeward IslandsSee under West Indies.MaltaBritish subjects (excluding members of Her Majesty&apos;s Forces) are not allowed to enter the Island except on a temporary permit from the immigration Officer unless (a) they &quot; belong &quot; to Malta (i.e., born in Malta, or born of Maltese-bornparents, or resident for more than 7 years in Malta); and(b) they are provided with suitable accommodation (this latter provision istemporary, due to housing shortage, and is renewable annually).Any immigrant may be required to make a deposit of  50 if from Europe,and  100 if he belongs elsewhere.MauritiusThe Governor in Executive Council may, by proclamation, prohibit the landing of any class or category of persons.Persons who wish to immigrate into the Colony must obtain a provisionalentry permit from the Immigration Officer prior to leaving the country wherethey reside. Permission will not be granted to a person likely to prejudice theinhabitants, generally, of the Colony, by engaging in certain businesses, trades,arts or callings.Visitors are allowed to land for a stay not exceeding 6 months, provided they are properly documented and have a return passage ticket.The Immigration Office may refuse a landing permit to any visitor whoprior to leaving the country where he last resided failed to obtain a provisionalpermit to enter the Colony.A cash deposit of Rs. 1,000 ( 75) is required from any person entering the Colony except Government officials, persons deemed to belong to theColony, visitors and persons in transit.NigeriaImmigration into Nigeria is a subject within the exclusive legislativecompetence of the Federal Government.Holders of British Passports who wish to enter Nigeria and remain lora period in excess of a short visit are required to make prior application tothePrincipal Immigration Officer, Lagos.A deposit or bond equivalent to the Cost of repatriation to the country of origin and a further sum of 25 per cent, may be required, and entry is subject also to Conditions as to duration and place of residence and occupa-tion or&quot;business. No change of the occupation or employment thusauthorised may subsequently take place without the consent of the PrincipalImmigration Officer. Persons whose parents were members of a tribe ortribes indigenous to Africa are not subject to the imposition of theseconditions of entry.The Governor-General has absolute discretion to prohibit the entry ofany person who is not a native of Nigeria.
I &quot;north BorneoSee under Brunei.Pitcairn IslandPrior permission to enter must be obtained from the Governor of Fiji.St. Helena, Ascension and Tristan da CunhaNo one may enter St. Helena for residence or employment without a permit from the Immigration Officer, but visitors may obtain one on arrival.No person is allowed to land on Ascension Island and remain on the island beyond the period of the vesseFs stay unless he has received a specialpermit signed by the Governor of St. Helena, or in case of emergencyby the Resident Magistrate on Ascension. (Members of Her Majesty&apos;s Naval,Military and Civil Services and members of the staff and employees of cable and Wireless Company Limited, their families and servants&quot; are exempt fromthis requirement.)The same restrictions on leave to land apply to Tristan da Cunha as forAscension Island.SarawakSee under Brunei.SeychellesIntending permanent residents must obtain permission and produce proof of an annual income of Rs. 3,000 ( 225).Employment Passes may be issued by the Principal Immigration officer on application. The person must show that he is suitably qualified toundertake employment of a particular class and permits will only be issuedif no suitably qualified residents in the Colony are for the time being available for employment of such class.  Permits will not exceed 4 years.The Immigration Officer may, at his discretion, require anyone entering the Colony to make a deposit, or by bond, of up to Rs. 2,000 ( 150).Visitors must also have sufficient funds to maintain themselves whilst inthe Colony.Sierra LeonePersons who wish to reside in Sierra Leone must obtain prior permissionfrom the Principal Immigration Officer, and permission will be granted onlyto persons taking up employment in an approved occupation and with an approved firm or organisation. Permits for permanent residence are issued,at the discretion of the Principal Immigration Officer, for a maximum period of 2 years in the first instance and a deposit or bond should be madeby the immigrant or his employer. The intending immigrant is issued withan employment and occupational permit and cannot change his employment without permission of the Principal Immigration Officer.Residential permits do not apply to natives of Sierra Leone or any personemployed in the service of the Sierra Leone Government, which includes thewives and children of such officials.Visitors on arrival are granted permits valid for a period of 3 months,provided they are properly documented, have onward passage tickets and sufficient funds to maintain themselves while in the Colony., These permitsmay be extended monthly up to a maximum period of 6 months.The Governor notwithstanding anything in the Immigration Ordinance has power to prohibit the entry of any person or class of person.
The Principal Immigration. Officer may, at his discretion, require anyperson entering the Colony to make a deposit in cash or by bond in thesum of up to  200.SingaporeSee Federation of Malaya.Somali land ProtectoratePersons wishing to enter the Protectorate must obtain a permitin writing from the Principal Immigration Officer. SomalilandImmigration laws prohibit British subjects who are idiots, lunaticsor prostitutes from entering the Protectorate. The authorities may also exclude others who are or are likely to become paupers; who areundesirable on the grounds that they have been convicted and imprisoned inany country; who are deemed undesirable on the grounds of informationofficially received by the Governor; or who are shown to the Governorssatisfaction to be likely to endanger peace and security. Further, any personwjio has entered into an agreement to labour for hire in the Protectorate or whose passage has been paid on his behalf with a view to his entering into such an agreement must obtain a permit from the Governor before being allowed to enter into the Protectorate. And any person intending toundertake missionary or educational work in the territory must obtain permission from Her Majesty&apos;s Government in writing before being allowedto enter. Excluded from the provisions of the Immigration Ordinance are members of the Somaliland Government Service and of Her Majesty&apos;s Forces,members of the Diplomatic Corps and natives of the Protectorate who havenot become British subjects.SwazilandSee under Basutoland.TanganyikaSee East Africa.Trinidad and Tobago see West Indies.\ UgandaSee East Africa.West IndiesThe territories in the West Indies group are Barbados, Jamaica, LeewardIslands, Trinidad and Tobago and Windward Islands.Restrictions on British subjects wishing to enter any of these territories are normally imposed under general immigration laws, but Jamaica has a specific law dealing with British subjects only. A person is held to belong to a territory if he was born there or if his parents at the time of his birthwere domiciled or ordinarily resident there; if he has been domiciled therefor 2 years; or if he has been resident for at least 7 years.British subjects not belonging to the territory concerned are onlyprohibited immigrants, or can be classed as such, if they come within certain categories or classes of persons. .
In addition in all territories the Governor-in-Council has power to declarea British subject a prohibited immigrant if he is deemed undesirable eitherindividually or as one of a class on economic grounds. There is no appeal for persons made the subject of a particular order. In some territories theGovernor has absolute discretion to prohibit the entry of any British subjectwho does not belong there. In Trinidad the occupations which personswho enter may be allowed to pursue are restricted. In Barbados, as ageneral rule, British subjects desirous of residing and working in the Islandare permitted to do so provided that they satisfy the Chief immigration officer that they will be unlikely to become a public charge.Visitors&apos; temporary permits may be granted for short periods, but some form of security may be required. In Jamaica visitors are normally onlyrequired to be in possession of a return or onward journey ticket, but aperson entering Jamaica for an indefinite stay may be required to furnish a security deposit of an amount varying from  30 to  100, depending uponcircumstances, and to satisfy the Immigration Authorities that he has access to sufficient funds to maintain himself while in the country. In Barbadosvisitors&apos; temporary permits may be granted for periods up to 3 years.Security ranging from $96 to $1,500, depending on the country to which the immigrant belongs, may be required.British subjects held to be prohibited immigrants may have to have theirfingerprints taken. All British subjects not belonging to the island concernedmay have to be examined by a health officer and may have to produce theirpassports or certificates of entry on demand.Windward IslandsSee West Indies.ZanzibarSee East Africa.PART iii the Republic of IrelandControl over persons entering the Irish Republic is exercised underthe provisions of the Aliens Act, 1935. Broadly speaking, however, Britishsubjects are exempted from the application of the Act by virtue of an order made in 1935 under Section 10 (1) of the Act.


</content>
</cab>
