<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/247/0 images: 237-242</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   January1934.SECRET Copy No:CP. 19 (34).CABINET.AUSTRIA.ON the 30th August last, I circulated to my colleagues a memorandum by the Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs on the German threat to Austrian independence, which dealt very fully with some of the disagreeable consequences which we might have to face if Austria were incorporated, in whatever form, in the German Reich. In bringing the matter-once more to the notice of my colleagues I should perhaps begin by recapitulating very briefly some of the principal consequences foreseen in Sir R. vansittart&apos;s memorandum.2. An &quot; Anschluss &quot; between Germany and Austria or even an assimilation between the two administrations on Nazi lines would at once involve reference to the League under Article 80 of the Treaty of Versailles guaranteeing the independence of Austria and would bring about another serious League crisis. Such action by Germany, moreover, would be her first move in a general policy of the reassertion by force, if necessary, of her international position a policy of which German rearmament, German domination of Central Europe, and the eventual recovery of the Polish Corridor are the other principal objectives. A more immediate result would be the reaction not only on France (which would regard such a move as definitely upsetting the balance between herself and Germany), but on Italo-German relations. Once the German frontier is advanced to the Tyrol, Germany will march with Italy and the latter&apos;s position will be one of great danger and embarrassment, particularly as the contiguous portions of Italy are those which are inhabited by Germans and were acquired from Austria by the Treaty of Saint-Germain. Not only is it probable that the Germans would, for sentimental reasons, institute in the Italian Tyrol the same sort of agitation which they have been carrying on in Austria, but it is likely also that they would for strategic and economic reasons start agitating for the recovery of Trieste- a very much more serious matter. Hungary would be easily brought within the German orbit and Hungarian revisionist claims espoused against Czechoslovakia and Roumania; and German claims to the German parts of Czechoslovakia would be brought to the forefront and pressed to a decision. The attitude of Yugoslavia would be doubtful, but her hostility to Italy is more deep-rooted and fundamental than her hostility to Germany. In any case Germany would become the dominant force in the Danube Basin, preparatory to trying out her strength elsewhere.3. Notwithstanding Italy&apos;s vital interests in the maintenance of Austrian independence, the Italian Government have from the outset preferred to deal with the problem by solitary action in Vienna and Berlin rather than in co-operation with France and Great Britain. This policy, adopted against our wish, has proved, as we always expected, to be entirely unsuccessful. But not only that, it has been actually harmful, inasmuch as it was this policy which rendered abortive our own attempt of last July to organise joint representations to the German Government, and since then it has prevented our appealing to the League, since it was felt that such an appeal would be altogether too hazardous unless we could count upon the loyal co-operation of not only France, but Italy.7221   [9564] b
&apos; &apos; 4. Failing direct diplomatic pressure on Germany, it was pointed out in Sir Rli vansittart&apos;s memorandum that the!interested;Powers might help Austria to maintain her independence by economic assistance, and it was reported at that time that we had already approached the French and Italian Governments with a view to discussing what assistance could be rendered. Although in previous years the three Governments had contributed generously to the financial assistance of Austria, I regret to say that the results of more recent efforts to give economic  as distinct from financial assistance have been altogether insignificant. Italy has made certain concessions to Austria, of the full extent of which we are not aware, regarding the transit of Austrian goods on Italian territory and through the port of Trieste; but it may be suspected that these concessions have been made as much in Italian as in Austrian interests. By France and Great Britain virtually nothing has been done, and I feel it my duty to explain the reasons for this failure in so far as it depends on His Majesty&apos;s Government.5. It had been hoped that it would be possible to assist the Austrian economic situation by increasing Austrian export trade to the United Kingdom, which between the years 1930-32 had declined to little more than one-fourth of its previous value. The most obvious way to do this was to accord preferential treatment to Austrian goods. This possibility was carefully explored. But unfortunately it was found that none of the principal Austrian exports to this country-yelour hats, electric lamps and timber -were received exclusively or even mainly from Austria, and that any tariff rebates on these goods, which would have to be extended to all countries with whom we had most-favoured-nation agreements, would benefit other countries, in particular Italy, France and Czechoslovakia, more than Austria. In regard to timber, our commitments to Canada under the Ottawa Agreements prevented any tariff concessions. Proposals were further made for an exchange of Austrian timber and British opal. The Board of Trade referred these proposals to the traces concerned, but the latter displayed no interest in them. There does not appear to be any inclination among timber importers in this country to increase their purchases of Austrian timber.6. A more indirect method of economic assistance was also explored. Under the agreements reached at the Stresa Conference of September 1932, we agreed to waive our most-favoured-nation rights, subject to certain conditions, in respect of any agreements which might be concluded betweien Austria and the other Danubian States for the granting of preferential duties on imports of all kinds from Austria, or of any agreement between Austria and any other State for the granting of preferential rates on Austrian agricultural products. In March 1933 Austria and Poland concluded an agreement under which Poland undertook to accord preferential rates to Austrian imports of certain goods in return for Austrian purchases of Polish coal and pigs. The Austrian imports into Poland (covered by this agreement were industrial and not agricultural and were therefore not covered by the recommendation of the Stresa Conference. In these circumstances His Majesty&apos;s Government are entitled to claim most-favoured-nation treatment from Poland, and have informed the Polish Government that they reserve their right to do so, if and when the agreement comes into force. The Foreign Office are, however, of the opinion that His Majesfy&apos;s Government would be well advised not to exercise this right, as such a course would bring no material benefits to British trade and might have the effect of wrecking the Austro-Polish agreement. The matter is now being considered by the Treasury and the Board of Trade.7.   Such is the position which we have now reached..8. In the meanwhile the German Government have pursued their attacks on the independence and integrity of Austria, in particular, by two of the methods mentioned in Sir R. vansittart&apos;s memorandum, i,e., by economic pressure and by. fomenting disorder and sabotage in Austria; and His MajestyY Minister at Vienna now once more reports that, the position of Dr. Dollfuss and his Government is critical. In the summer Dr. Dbllfuss calculated that if he could survive the winter he would benefit by the fact that that season would also discredit the Nazis in Germany, where trade would fall and unemployment rise. &apos;This calculation has pxwed false, and Dr. Dollfuss&quot;, who had a few weeks ago
b;ec&apos;^ hasevidently failed to come to terms- fotMur has now been obliged by a.recrudescence of Nazi activities to takje;strong repressi^with the curtailment of Italian subsidies; appear to have had the effect of shaking the loyalty; of the Heimwehr. the - only effective armed force on. which he can rely.- 9. I would point out again to my colleagues that the fall of Dr. Dollfuss, which is: now measurably nearer than in the autunm, would be followed inevitably by the consequences pointed out in Sir,R. VansittarVs memorandum, since there is clearly no one in Austria who would be prepared to take his place and continue the struggle with a victorious Germany. ... ,..   j.&quot;,10. The gravity of the Austrian crisis has been brought to a head within the last few days by two specific moves on the. part of Dr. Dollfuss : (1.) He has addressed a formal appeal to His Majesty&apos;s Government for economic assistance1; and (2) he has informed, the German Government that he has proof that that Government is encouraging subversive Nazi activities in Austria, and that, unless the support of such activities, by the German Government ceases, he willbe compelled to appeal to the League of Nations...  - ..i IL As . regards. the. appeal to His Majesty&apos;s Government for economic assistance (a copy of which is annexed hereto), I have arranged for an inter-departmental. committee. on. which the Treasury, the Board of Trade, the Department.of Overseas Trade and the Mines Department, as. well as the Foreign Office are represented, to consider the new Austrian proposals. I do not profess to give any assurance that, however generously we may be able to respond to the Austrian appeal, we shall avert the fall of Dr. Dollfuss and the establish merit of a Nazi, or quasi-Nazi, regime in Austria. But it seems to me that the attempt should be made, if only in order that we may be in a position, if or when the catastrophe occurs, to show that we had been alive to the clanger and had.done our best to meet it. It is for this reason that I urge that on the highest political grounds the most sympathetic consideration should be given to Dr. Doll fuss&apos;s present appeal., : 12. As regards Dr. Dollfuss&apos;s threat to appeal to the League of Nations, the. Austrian representative at Geneva told me last week that Austria would appeal to the League, and the German Ambassador saw me on Monday with a message that his Government did hot intend violence or breach of treaty obligations against Austria which is not, however, the point. .; &apos;13. It is to be observed that up till now Dr. Dollfuss has always declared that he could not appeal to the League against his &quot;brother German.&quot; The fact that he is now threatening to do so shows how desperate his position has suddenly become.14. The question of bringing the German-Austrian problem before the League was considered in Sir R. Vansittart&apos;s memorandum of last September, and it was there suggested that, short of an open &quot; Putsch,&quot; it would: be inadvisable for His Majesty&apos;s Government or any third party to take so drastic a step. If, however, now Austria takes the matter herself to the League we cannot avoid the issue, however severe a strain it may. put upon the League in its present debilitated condition. (For instance, if coercive measures were suggested against Germany it is almost certain that Italy would not co-operate in them, and it is possible that she might leave the League.) \ . -15. The French Ambassador has within the last few days enquired the views and intentions of His Majesty&apos;s Government on the situation which is. obviously developing in Austria. The French Government, recognised that Austria would probably bring the matter before the League, and would probably prefer this to raising the question at Geneva themselves. The question is whether this French enquiry should be made the occasion of a further exchange of views between the two Governments, with a view to common action either at Geneva or elsewhere. , \16.   If Dr. Dollfuss&apos;s threat to appeal to the League does materialise, I am of opinion that His Majesty&apos;s Government should in that case at once approach [9564] b 2
not only the French Government, but also the Italian Government, with a view to concerted action. It is possible that the Italian Government may be sufficiently conscious of the failure of their independent policy to make them now more inclined to common action. At any rate, they ought to be given another chance, and if they refuse to co-operate the situation will have to be considered further on the basis of Anglo-French co-operation.J. S.. Foreign Office, January 22, 1934.JR 339/339/3] Annex,v&apos;       M. Franckenstein to Sir John Simon. (Received January 18.)Austrian Legation,Sir, ;   1 London, January 17, 1934.THE Austrian Cabinet has again examined the question of trade relations between Austria and Great Britain and, in accordance with certain suggestions made in British quarters, drawn up concrete proposals for a development of trade, which I have been instructed to transmit herewith to His Majesty&apos;s Government.In view of the efforts which are being made to undermine the independence of Austria, it is of the utmost importance that the economic position of the country should be improved and unemployment lessened. Every sign of economic distress&apos; is exploited by the enemies of the Government to strengthen their agitation arid to weaken the confidence of the population in the Government&apos;s policy and their faith in the independent future of Austria.Everything the Austrian Government can do by themselves they have already done- with success. They have brought about budgetary equilibrium and the stability of the currency has been maintained; foreign obligations have been faithfully met and internal resources developed. In their endeavours to expand foreign trade, however, the Austrian Government have to count upon the syriipathetic goodwill of other countries. It is a matter of life and death for Austria that her trade should increase, for she has.to pay for essential raw materials and food-stuffs with her exports. Owing to the most-favoured-nation clause, however^ she has been unable to obtain adequate concessions by means of normal commercial treaties.All attempts to solve the Austrian problem on lines appropriate to her special position have so far been frustrated by international difficulties, with the result that much valuable time has been lost. With a view to avoiding such difficulties, the Austrian Government have therefore adopted the plan of negotiating agreements on new lines with any countries willing to do so.His Majesty&apos;s Government have repeatedly declared that they attach the greatest importance to the maintenance of Austrian independence. Active British support of the Austrian Government&apos;s proposals would not only have the practical result of stimulating production and lessening unemployment in Austria, thus consolidating the economic position of the country and ^strengthening public confidence; there can be no doubt that great political and moral: significance would also attach to the conclusion of an agreement with Great Britain.The Austrian Government hope, therefore, that their proposals will be examined sympathetically and in the light of the desirability of promoting trade between.the two countries even should they involve, owing to the extraordinary circumstances of the case, special concessions and some innovations.i  The Austrian Government, for their part, will be glad to consider with warm interest any wishes His Majesty&apos;s Government may desire to make known in regard to the importation of British goods into Austria. &apos;i&quot; I have, &amp;c..    &quot;. ... G. FRANCKENSTEIN,
Enclosure.fV-...7- /&apos;        M?M^X^--a.a&apos;&apos;^ftt&apos;&quot;       &apos;  ;&quot;&apos;AUSTRIA steadily continues to havea highly adverse balance of trade: In the last few years the adverse balance has become smaller in consequence of the fall in the total volume of Austria&apos;s foreign trade; but even in 1932 imports amounted to 1,400 million Schillinge, exports to 780 millions, and the&apos;adverse balance to 620 millions.Austria is a debtor country, and from her tourist traffic and from various services rendered to foreign countries she. is only able to derive the amount required to meet her financial obligations abroad. She has therefore to pay for her imports of commodities by exports of commodities. She needs to increase her exports, not only in order to be able to obtain the raw materials arid food-stuffs she requires, but also in order to reduce the disproportionately large volume of unemployment. It is therefore a matter of life or death for Austria that her export trade should be developed. Austria cannot secure adequate concessions by means of the ordinary commercial treaties, for, as a rule, Austrian exports constitute only an insignificant part of the total imports of the commodities in -question into foreign countries, and any concession granted to Austria would, as a result of the most-favoured-nation clause, mean that far greater concessions were being made at the same time to other countries. :-The existence of Austria&apos;s economic problem has long been recognised on all sides, but np positive solution has yet been found for it. All attempts to reach a solution have been frustrated by political difficulties. The Austrian Government have therefore conceived the plan (a plan which has the advantage of eliminating political bias of any kind) of entering into negotiations for a commercial treaty on new lines with any country willing to do so. The aim of these negotiations will be to secure that all foreign countries taken together shall purchase as much from Austria as Austria purchases from them.The Conference of Stresa took note of the fact that the Austrian Govern-ment was negotiating with a view to obtaining unilateral preferences, . The resolution of the conference on this subject runs as follows : &quot; La continuation des negociations commerciales entamees particulierement par rAutriche, doht 1&apos;exportation n&apos;est pas de caractere surtout agricole, et la communication des resultats qui seront obtenus dans ces negotiations a la Commission d&apos;Etude pour 1&apos;Union europ6enne.&quot; -Since that time the Austrian Government has been in negotiation with France, Germany and Poland for preferential treatment. A preferential -duty for timber has been arranged in France. The negotiations with Germany had reached an advanced stage, but could not be concluded owing to the. political difficulties. Agreements in regard to preferences were reached with Poland, and were brought to the knowledge of all most-favoured-nation countries.In September the Italian Government put forward proposals for, the -settlement of the economic problems of the Danubian States, and suggested that Austria might obtain unilateral preferences for manufactured articles also,; The French Government accorded a friendly reception to this proposal.       ;.;v.-;;It would be mistaken to assume that&apos;Austria&apos;s&apos; trade with Great Britain-,.is--of minor importance. In 1930 Austria&apos;s exports to England amounted to 102 million Schillinge; in 1932 Austria&apos;s total exports were 780 millions.- The mere juxtaposition of these figures rhakes it clear that an increase or a decrease in her exports to England must be a matter ! of considerable importance&apos;to Austria. The Austrian Governments plan for increasing Austrian exports can only be carried out if negotiations are entered into with each country concerned, no important country, being omitted. Apart from this, however, it is obvious that great political and moral significance would attach to the conclusion of i an appropriate agreement with Great Britain. - vThe Austrian Government is well aware of the difficulties which exceptions from the most-favoured-riation clause involve for His Majesty&apos;s Government. Should they succeed, therefore, in obtaining exceptional treatment from other countries, they will count upon not explicit consent, but merely silent acquiescence on the part of the British Government, There should be no great difficulties in this respect, since the very modest quotas for which Austria may be able to secure preferences cannot be of harm to British or other interests.
The question arises whether His Majesty&apos;s Government themselves would be willing to grant preferences to Austria on condition that the most-favoured-nation countries, although not explicitly signifying their consent, do not raise serious objections to such a step. It is improbable that objection would be raised even by Germany, for Germany agreed to the Stresa resolutions and has not. protested against the preferences granted by France and Poland.The Austrian Government, for their part, would give careful consideration to any suggestions made by Great Britain in regard to the import of British goods into Austria.Should the.method of preferences encounter difficulties .of a fundamental nature, a system of customs duty reimbursement might be considered instead. This might be worked as follows : Part of the receipts from customs duties levied on Austrian imports would be handed over to the Austrian Government, who would refund to the Austrian exporters a proportion of the duty paid by them. Details as to the scope and figures of such a system would have to be settled by arrangement.Another possibility would be to use half the customs revenue from duties upon Austrian goods imported into Great Britain to develop the export of British coal and other goods to Austria, and half to further the export of Austrian goods to England. Here again it would be a matter for arrangement between the two Governments to decide in respect of which goods and to what extent such facilities should be accorded. The question may quite reasonably be asked why the revenue obtained in Austria from imports of British goods should not be devoted to the same purpose. There is no reason why this possibility should not also be considered. The main objection to it lies in the fact that other countries will-acquiesce in preferences or indirect customs facilities being granted to Austria, .but would object to Austria herself according such facilities, apart from facilities for the agricultural products of the Danubian States.Finally, the following plan might also be considered : The import restrictions or foreign exchange restrictions which are in force in many countries adversely affect British export trade. Austria happens to have a strongly adverse balance of trade and balance of payments with several of those countries, for instance, with Poland, Germany, Czechoslovakia, Hungary and Yugoslavia. It would be possible for Austria to ask these countries to set aside, for the payment of British imports, part of the credit balances arising out of their favourable trade balance with Austria. This would make possible an increase in British exports to the countries in question. It would be to the interest of the countries concerned to accept the proposal, for otherwise they would have to reckon with restrictions, upon their exports to Austria. Great Britain, for its part, would utilise the credit balances thus made available for the purchase of Austrian goods. An argument in favour of this plan is that it represents an attempt to restore the triangular. basis of trade relations which existed before the system, of import prohibitions and foreign exchange restrictions came into being. All that the Governments need do is to permit such transactions to be made; it would then be up to private firms to arrange the actual business. The feasibility of according direct or indirect customs facilities on the lines discussed earlier on to special export transactions of this kind should also be examined.At a later date the Austrian Government will perhaps put forward some proposals in regard to the processing trades. In the meantime they will be most grateful if His Majesty&apos;s Government will give their consideration to the foregoing suggestions. The Austrian Government would like to have the matter discussed in verbal negotiations after an appropriate period. of time, say February or March.

</content>
</cab>
