<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/247/0 images: 337-339</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAMMIC MA JE5TY ^ S^OQ , )Copy Mo,^HOUSING joGOTLAMD) , Memo rand unt, by., the Secretary; of u St at e for Sco 11 and .1 lay before ray colleagues a brief Mate on Scottish Housing policy.My purpose is to let them know that    1 shall,,  at an early date,,  submit proposals for dealing with the Housing problem in Scotland and that in many particulars they will be baaed upon the same considerations as are set forth in the Memorandum of the   Minister of Health.       For instance, with regard to slum clearance,-  the policy I am pursuing it? similar to that indicated in the Memorandum. Thereremain (l) overcrowding;.     (2) the provision of houses to meet the ordinary needs of increased population,,   (3) recon-ditioningsI. The situation in Scotland as regards overcrowdingis very much worse than in England .   14 a 9$ of the Scottish population is living more than 3 to a room as compared with 1c49% of the English .   This situation was recognised last year when the cabinet  and subsequently Parliament  (in the Housing (Scotland) Acts 1933)p  approved the proposal to give a special subsidy of  3 a house for dealing with low-paid, wage earners living in overcrowded conditions, while no similar subsidy was provided in England.So far local authorities have not availed them-selves to any appreciable extent of the  3 subsidy and they have very generally represented that they find themselves unable to provide housese even with its assistance,, without making/
making rat? contributions which impose an undue burden &amp;n the locality.I am satisfied,, therefore,  that only really generous assistance on the part of the State will secure early and effective dealing with overcrowding in ScotiancL The object    of the proposals I shall submit will be to ensure that the asnistance to be given by the State for overcrowding will provide a stimulus sufficient to ensure that the or obi em of overcrowding will he dealt v/ith as effectively as that of slum clearance.In Scotland,, as in England,  the Local Authority is under the statutory obligation,  if necessary,  to provide houses.      The Minister of Health and the Secretary of State far Scotland are el^so given statutory powers to compel the local authorities to fulfil that obligation^        I am satisfied, however,  that it is impracticable to use any such powers against local authorities as a whole.      They art&apos; only serviceable if the assistance given by the State is such as to secure the willing co-operation of the great body of Local Authorities j,  in which case they can effectively be used, to deal with a small recalcitrant minority. 2, With regard to the provision by unassisted privateenterprise of the ordinary houses required for the working classes.,  I desire at present only to say that unfortunately in Scotland there seems little prospect of private enter-prise functioning effectively.      In my viwt however,  the importance of&apos; this consideration in connection with the matters dealt with in the Memorandum is that it makes it ail the more essential that the provisions we make to deal with overcrowding should be fully effective,. 3, There remains the question of reconditioning-,    Mycolleagues will remember that a Committee similar to theMoyne/
Moyne Committee was appointed &quot;by me to deal with that question in Scotland,      The recommendations of the two Committees vary in certain important respects.    But   do not think it is necessary at this stage to enter into this question further than to say that in this matter we may find it necessary in Scotland to proceed along i:;omcv*h&amp;i different Unas than those suggested in the Memorandum of the Minister of Health,,(ltd,- )    G, P0C,Scottish Office,,Whitehall,, &apos;s.;W,i,2nd February,   19341.

</content>
</cab>
