<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/247/0 images: 477-483</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
9i) k 0S DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT) OR E T.\ 54 (.34).COPY NoJVCAB I N E T.AFGHANISTAN:    BRITISH POLICY. Defence of India Plan.The accompanying Report, which has been submitted by the Chiefs cf Staff Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence, in accordance with Cabinet 5 (34), Conclusion 3 (a),  is circulated to the Cabinet by direction of the Prime Minister.(Signed)    M.P.A.  HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet., Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1. , 20th February, 1934.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   February 1934.SECRET. Copy No.CCS. 326.(Also C.I.D. Paper No. 185-D.)-COMMITTEE  OF   IMPERIAL  DEFENCE.Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee.AFGHANISTAN: BRITISH POLICY. Defence of India Plan. REPORT.Term of Reference.1.   WE have been instructed to submit a Report on the following question : &quot; On the assumption that the policy of the Defence of India Committee&apos;s Report of 1928 holds good (C.I.D. Paper No. 158-D approved by the . Committee of Imperial Defence at its 232nd Meeting, Conclusion 2), to consider and report whether any new military factors have arisen since that date, which would make it impossible to implement that policy and would invalidate the plan approved in principle by the Committee of Imperial Defence in 1929 (C.I.D. Paper No. 172-D-C.I.D. Minutes, 242nd Meeting, Conclusion 3).&quot;This subject was examined by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee at a meeting held on Wednesday, 21st February, 1934, and the following report is accordingly submitted : Changes since 1928.2. Since the Defence of India Plan was approved in 1929* certain changes in the political and military spheres, and developments of communications, have taken place. These are reviewed in the following paragraphs. In regard to the changes of a political nature, only those that have a direct military implication have been considered.Political Changes of Military Significance.Russian-Afghan Relations.3. Since 1928 Russian influence in Afghanistan has weakened. Efforts on the part of Russia to secure a trade agreement have failed. The Afghan Govern-ment have refused to renew the Termez-Kabul air line agreement with Russia. Russian telegraph operators have been removed. Russian control of the Afghan air force has ceased.Generally, since the departure of Amanullah, the Afghan Government has taken a strong stand against Russian infiltration.Since 1928 the influx into Afghanistan of many thousand refugees from north of the Oxus should have removed any illusions which may have existed in Afghan minds regarding conditions of life under the Soviets. It may be hoped that tribal opposition to a Russian invasion would, therefore, be more ardent than would previously have been the case.[9696]* C.I.D. Paper No. 172-D.B
We understand that definite anti-Soviet measures and propaganda have been initiated by the recently appointed Governor of the Northern Provinces of Afghanistan.British-A fghan Relations.4. The relations between His Majesty&apos;s Government and the Afghan Government have, on the other hand, improved since 1928. The latter have on several occasions shown a desire for closer relations. They have, for example, confided in His Majesty&apos;s Minister their fears of Russia. They have asked for his advice as to how they should deal with the pressure which the Soviet Govern-ment has brought to bear; they have asked for military advice. They have, further, shown themselves to be more willing to co-operate with us in connection with the problems of our North-West Frontier tribes. More than once the Afghan Government have asked us to define our attitude in the event of Russian aggression. It is significant to note that the Afghan Prime Minister on one occasion informed His Majesty&apos;s Minister at Kabul that failing some assurance of our support the Afghans would have to make such terms as they could with Russia. .Afghan Internal Situation.5. The tendency, then, appears to incline towards a deterioration of Russian-Afghan relations and an improvement in British-Afghan relations. The latter is a tendency which it can only be to our interest to encourage. But, in the event, the existence of a stable Afghan Government, enjoying the confidence of its army and people, must be a factor of the first importance. In this respect the position is certainly no worse. In our opinion it is more favourable than it was in 1927-28. In 1928 the Government of Afghanistan depended upon one man, Amanullah himself, who, in spite of his undoubted capacity, was rapidly undermining the popularity which the third Afghan war of 1919 had gained for him, by his ill-judged reforms. To-day the Government is on a broader basis; instead of depending upon one man it includes a number of Ministers who are believed to be incomparably better than were Amanullah&apos;s team. The Government is having its troubles, but appears to be gradually strengthening its hold on the various factions throughout the country. Subversive movements and a pro-Amanullah party undoubtedly exist, but no Afghan Government is ever a stable one if measured by civilised standards, and we see no reason to think that the existing Government is less stable than was that of Amanullah in 1928.Conclusion on Political Factors.6. So far as we are in a position to appraise the military effects of such political changes as have taken place in Afghanistan and in the relations between the Government of that country and those of Russia and Great Britain, we should judge the present position as being more favourable to us than it was in 1927-28. If, however, we fail or continue to delay to accept the hand which the Afghans offer us, we fear than the situation may deteriorate to a dangerous degree.Changes in Commtmications.Roads in A afghanistan.7. A new unmetalled road, fit for occasional light motor traffic in good weather, has been made from Kabul via Dare Shikari to the Oxus. In its present condition this road would be of little practical value for the maintenance of any large Russian force moving on Kabul. The distance from the Oxus to Kabul by this route is about 400 miles, most of which traverses the great mountain range of the Hindu Kush. The forces which could be supplied by this one road are strictly limited, and air action, combined with that of Afghan regular and irregular forces, suitably encouraged and stiffened, should enforce prolonged delay. The duration of such delay cannot be accurately estimated, but it is clear that we, with our railhead at Landi Khana, only 176 miles from Kabul, should have no difficulty in winning the race to that place.; Anything which can be done, in peace time, to improve the Landi Khana-Kabul road will, obviously, increase our favourable position, and we would
aemphasise that, the greater the indications of a Russian advance by the Dare Shikari road become, the greater will be the necessity to improve communications between India and Kabul.The existence of this new Kabul-Oxus road should enable the Afghan Government to strength their hold on the Northern Provinces and thus enable them to offer earlier and stronger resistance to a Russian advance.The Afghan Government have already asked for our advice in regard to the defence of this Northern road, advice which it is clearly in our interests to give.Work has, naturally, been going on and is constantly going on on other roads in Afghanistan, some of which are fit for light motor traffic in good weather. But in all Afghanistan there is nothing which could be called a road in a civilised country, and certainly no road which would lend itself to the advance of large military forces without a great deal of heavy work involving great delay.We must expect to see further road developments in Afghanistan, giving better facilities for a military invasion than exist at present.Railways on the Northern Frontier of Afghanistan.8. Certain railway developments have taken place in Russian territory to the North, of Afghanistan, but the railway position in the essential matter of maintenance capacity at railheads on the Oxus and at Kushk Post remains substantially unaltered since 1927-28.The new construction referred to is : (a) A single-line railway (the Turk-Sib railway) connecting Siberia with theOld Central Asian system at Aris, about 700 miles from Russian railheads On the Oxus. This railway constitutes a possible new line of supply to forces in Central Asia and might be of use as an alternative to the Central Asian (Orenburg-Tashkent) line in case of failure of the latter. But, as it feeds into the existing single line railway from Arris southwards, it does not increase the possible delivery at railheads.(b) A short railway extension from Namangan to Andijan opens up a fertilearea, but has no important bearing on the problem under consideration.(c) A railway extension from Termez to Kulab, some 30 miles from theOxus, will offer the Russians the advantage of being able to deploy on a wider front and to avoid some congestion at Termez, but it does not increase the total numbers which can be employed: The limiting factor is the single-line feeding railway. No matter how man)&apos; branch lines are constructed at the end of this, the total capacity remains unaltered.(d) A further minor railway extension is planned from Dyushambe toKurghan Tapa. Even if completed, the effect of this extension would be the same as that of the Termez-Kulab extension dealt with in the preceding sub-paragraph.Conclusion on Communications.9. The conclusion which we draw is that none of the new railway works, either completed or projected, affect the military problem in any important degree.Further railway development must be expected as the years pass which may compel us to consider improving our own facilities. But, when full allowance is made for such improvements, if Russia&apos;s intention is to advance into Afghanistan, it is the communications inside Afghanistan which are the key to this problem. For a serious advance she will have to build railways and roads southwards from the Oxus and from Kushk Post, a process which will take much time. So long, however, as we maintain friendly relations with Afghanistan and ensure that the roads we shall need to come to her assistance do not lag too far behind the roads which Russia must use for invasion we have nothing to fear from this cause.if 7 r. Military Changes.A fghan Military Resources. &quot; 310. No important changes have occurred in the strength of the Afghan army, but we would judge that it has improved in efficiency since the days of Amanullah. To-day, it is paid regularly; then, it was months in arrears. To-day, greater attention is being paid to its organisation, equipment and[9696] b 2
training, and, above all, our assistance and our advice have alike been asked for. If we give both, we may well bring about such an increase in Afghan strength as would be of great value to us. . The moral of the Afghan forces, vis-a-vis Russia, may be expected to have improved as a result of the political changes to which we&apos; have referred in paragraph 3. It is obviously a difficult matter on which to obtain reliable information, and it is not one on which we can express a definite opinion. We mention it only as a not unreasonable expectation.Russian Military Resources.11. Since 1927-28 Russia has devoted much attention to the development of her military and air power, including the necessary industries to maintain it.12. As regards her war industries, in 1928 the munitions industry of Russia could not have supported a large-scale war. To-day, thanks to the predominant military aspect of the Five-Year Plan, the munitioning of a war in Afghanistan should present no trouble in the industrial field.13. In regard to her military transport, Russia has made great advances in the substitution of mechanical for animal transport. In this connection, however, it must be remembered that Afghanistan is not a country at present suited to a large-scale use of mechanical transport without much time and labour being devoted to road-making.The vital area of the Hindu Kush is, and for many years must be, in the main unsuitable for mechanical transport in the mass. Further, the large-scale use of mechanical transport will greatly strain the long single-line railways upon which supply and maintenance must depend. The animal of the 1927-28 transport could to a large extent live upon local supplies; not so the mechanical vehicle of to-day. There are advantages and disadvantages in the change from animal to mechanical transport. On balance we see no reason here to suspect any change of serious importance in the problem.14. Coincident with the change from animal to machine referred to in the previous paragraph, Russia has developed important forces of armoured fighting vehicles, far more formidable than they were in 1927-28. Two possible results follow from this development. The first of these can be deduced from the geography of Afghanistan. In the great mountain mass of the Hindu Kush the armoured fighting vehicle can have but a very limited role. It is, we consider, most unlikely that, in the event of such a war as that under consideration, Russia would be content to make little use of the arm upon which she has devoted so much industry. From this, then, we deduce the probability of her developing operations, subsidiary to her main advance on Kabul, southwards from Herat in the open country where armoured vehicles can operate. In considering this we cannot but be struck with the foresight of the framers of the 1927-28 plan, who decided to place our main armoured forces in this region at as early a date as possible.That is the first result we foresee of Russia&apos;s tank development. The second, a more distant one, is the possibility that, one day in the future, if and when the Kabul-Oxus road has improved to a degree not at present within sight, Russia may try to seize Kabul by a coup-de-main carried out by a specially organised mechanised force. This is a matter to be kept in mind in any military advice that may be given to the Afghans. If suitable steps are taken when and if the danger becomes more definite, we see no reason why we should not be able to counter it.15. The strength of the Air Force both in India and elsewhere has been augmented and its efficiency has been increased considerably since the Plan drawn up by the Chiefs of Staff was approved by the Committee of Imperial Defence, and therefore we are in a better position to implement that Plan than we were in 1929. The increase in the size of the Russian Air Force has, however, been much greater. In consequence, we are relatively not so favourably placed in the matter of air power as we were in that year. There is no doubt that this is the case as regards the numbers of aircraft the Russians can dispose of and it is probably so as regards their performance, nor that under the Five-Year Plan their resources to maintain their air forces have been largely increased; but it is difficult to assess this new Russian Air Force as an instrument of war until it has been proved under the stress of hostilities.
While the characteristics and numbers of their aircraft should enable them to launch a formidable attack across the 16,000-ft. barrier of the Hindu Kush on Kabul and on objectives beyond, it is difficult to believe that the Russians, who, both before and during the war, proved themselves the least capable of European nations to exploit scientific inventions, should have been transformed in 17 years of revolution to a people who will lead the world in aviation for the purpose of aggression. It is, however, clear they are convinced that aviation provides a weapon which can be used to strike at the vitals of a country on the outbreak of war without the delay necessary to develop communications, which the occupation of a country by land forces entails, and that we must be prepared for heavy air attacks, when conditions are favourable, against Kabul and other objectives in Afghanistan, with the object of demoralising the inhabitants and bringing about a collapse of the central Government.It is probable, therefore, that when the Plan is reviewed by us it will be found necessary to place the units of the Royal Air Force in the field earlier than has hitherto been envisaged, and for this purpose to make a small increase in the strength of the Royal Air Force, which is located in India prior to the outbreak of war. It is essential also that when the re-equipment of the India squadrons is next carried out the types should be selected more with a view to their employment against long-range targets in the Central Asian Military District than to meet the immediate requirements of frontier operations. Nevertheless, we do not think that these changes are likely to prove such as to invalidate the general Plan approved by the Committee of Imperial Defence.16. In chemical warfare also Russia has made notable advances. She main-tains offensive chemical warfare units, and it would be foolish to think that she will not make use of this weapon both from the ground and from the air if she considers such action to be to her advantage. This possibility is one we must prepare, and are preparing, to face in any war in which we may engage. It is in no way peculiar to possible operations in Afghanistan.17. In the training of her forces Russia has brought about a steady improve-ment in the last seven years. Even to-day, however, we may take it as true that the Red Army is below that of any first-class European Power, and definitely inferior to the combined British and Indian forces which we could put into the field.18. We have thought it our duty to draw attention to the important headings under which Russia has increased her military strength. We do not wish either to minimise or exaggerate them. We do, however, invite attention to the fact that it has yet to be shown that Russia&apos;s inherent defects in the matter of organisation and administration do not still persist. These defects have brought her military power to ruin in the past. Improvements have no doubt been made, but it would be a very sweeping assumption to think that the defects have been eliminated.Changes in our Military Position.19. Since 1928 there have been certain reductions in the strength of the land forces in India. On the other hand, certain improvements in their organisation and equipment have enabled our initial moves under the Plan to be accelerated. The actual details are, for the moment, immaterial, but they do, definitely, improve our position in the opening stages of the campaign as compared with the original time table.In addition the Royal Air Force in India has been increased by two squadrons, and two squadrons are located at Singapore, which, in favourable circumstances, might be made available early for use in India. The squadrons in the United Kingdom, from which the bulk of the reinforcements have to come, have been increased by nine, and four further squadrons are to be included in the estimates for 1934.We understand from a recent Government of India telegram that &quot; the Army in India is completely ready to undertake the role assigned to it in the first phase &quot;* of the Plan. In taking note of this expression of opinion we desire to emphasise that it is on the Army and Air Force in India that the first brunt of the operations will fall, and that our conclusions are based on the assumption that there will be no further diminution in the military power (using the word &apos;&apos; military &apos;&apos; in its widest sense) of India.* Government of India telegram No. 308 of the 8th February, 1934.
20. Except for the increases of the Royal Air Force mentioned in the preceding paragraph, no great changes have occurred in the military strength of Great Britain which can be compared in detail to those changes in Russian military strength with which we have dealt at some length in this Report. It must be remembered, however, that Russian changes have been those from a very low level to a more reasonable standard. In efficiency, especially in air and mechanised forces, we believe our standard is second to none.Conclusion regarding Military Changes.21. Military strength is variable, changes constantly take place. The changes we have outlined above are normal; we see nothing in them to lead to any reconsideration either of policy or of plan beyond those alterations in detail which must constantly be made in any war plan.General Considerations.22. We consider it our duty to draw attention to the following general considerations : The military importance of Afghanistan to us lies in its existence as an independent buffer State between the north-west frontier of India and Russia, Were Russia to occupy Afghanistan we should then have a common frontier, some 500 miles in length, between India and a great Continental military power. In this event we would be faced with a military commitment on a scale which we have never yet had to contemplate in peace-time, and we would be burdened with a financial load which we could not support.The isolated problem looks, and is, formidable, but a war between two great Empires will hardly be confined to the barren uplands of Afghanistan. There must be repercussions, grouping of nations and campaigns in many places. The details of these it is not possible, even were it desirable, to forecast. Russia&apos;s problem, looked at through her eyes, will be no less formidable than our own, apart from the purely military problem of operations in Afghanistan. She might have serious preoccupations in Europe. A war of pure aggression, such as an invasion of Afghanistan would be, might well have internal repercussions of the most serious character. The relations of Japan with Russia have deteriorated, and may deteriorate further, and, were Russia embarked on a war with us in Central Asia, Japan might well seize the opportunity to attain her aims in the Far East. When regarded from this angle, our problem seems to diminish in difficulty; that of Russia&apos;s to grow.   In any case, we have no option.Conclusion.23. From the broad standpoint in which we suggest we should view problems of this nature, our potential war capacity is as great to-day as it was in the years 1914-18. Were it otherwise, it would be our duty to make strong-representations to His Majesty&apos;s Government where such a vital issue is involved.In the light of the foregoing examination of the developments and changes which have occurred since 1928, we are of the opinion that no military factors have arisen since that date which would make it impossible to implement the policy laid down, or which would invalidate the Plan approved in principle by the Committee of Imperial Defence in 1929 (C.I.D. Paper No. 172-D; also C.I.D. Minutes, 242nd Meeting, Conclusion 3).(Signed) ERNLE CHATFIELD.A. A. MONTGOMERY-MASSINGBERD. E. L. ELLINGTON.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1, February 23, 1934.

</content>
</cab>
