<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/247/0 images: 512-514</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.This documerrIt is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.s Government.S E CM. E T.C A B I M E T.Copy No.CP. 62  (34).INCITEMENT    TO    SEDITION    BILL.Memorandum   by    the   Home    Secretary.1.    In pursuance of Cabinet 7  (34), Conclusion 5, I circulate, for the information of my colleagues, the following details as to the nature of the additions to the existing law which would be involved in my proposal that the Incitement to Sedition Bill should be extended so as to apply to the Police.2.    The only existing statutory provision relating to the Police which, bears on this subject is section 3 of the Police Act, 1919, which provides that &quot;if any person causes, or attempts to cause, or does any act calculated to cause disaffection amongst the members of any police force, or induces, or attempts to induce, or does any act calculated to induce any member of a police force to withhold his services or to commit breaches of discipline, he shall be guilty of a misdemeanour, and shall be liable on conviction on indictment to imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a term not exceeding two years, or on summary conviction, to imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a term not exceeding^ three months, or to a fine not exceeding fifty pounds, or to both such imprisonment and fine,   .........&quot;3.    This provision is comparable with sub-clause   (1) of clause 1 of the draft Bill as approved by the Cabinet and accordingly no amendment is recu. required  in this sub-clause if it is to be extended to the Police.4.    Sub-clause   (3) of clause 1 of the draft Bill, however, provides that &quot;if any person attempts to do, or causes to be done, or does, any act preparatory to the commission of an offence under the foregoing provisions of this section, he shall be guilty of
352    -1- 2  &quot; Ian offence under this Act.&quot; I contemplate that if the Police are I &quot;brought within the scope of the Bill, this sub-clause would be amended so as to apply to acts preparatory to the commission of an offence under section 3 of the Police Act, 1919.5.    The remaining provisions of the draft Bill deal   with  (a) the possession of documents of such a nature that the dissemination of copies thereof amongst members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces would be an offence under the Bill (clause 1 (2) of the draft Bill);    and(b) the issue of warrants authorising the search of premises and the seizing of any documents or things which are evidence of an offence under the Bill (clause 2 of the draft Bill).6.   These provisions, as pointed out in the memorandum of 10th October, 1933 (G.P. 230  (33)), are, in relation to the Defence Services, new provisions.     They are also new provisions in relation to the Police and the grounds for seeking these powers are the same in the case of the Police as in the case of the Defence Services, namely, that  (a) whereas under the existing lav; the publication and distribution of documents calculated to seduce members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces from their duty or allegience would be an offence, the mere possession of such material is not an offence, and there is, therefore, no power to take any action until the material is actually distributed. Moreover, the existing law punishes the subordinate who distributes subversive literature and leaves untouched the persons responsible for its production;(b) a number of statutes provide for the issue of searchwarrants with a view to the detection of offences, but the offences covered by these statutes are in many cases less serious than offences dealt with by statutes which donot contain corresponding provisions for preliminary
3rd March, 1954.search.     Experience has shown that without the power of search the authorities are very seriously handicapped in dealing with the offence of incitement to mutiny and the same considerations apply to the offence of incitement to disaffection amongst the Police.7.   Briefly&apos;, therefore, the effect of my proposal is that there would be a minor extension of the powers which exist undersection 3 of the Police Act, 1919, and two new provisions which are not comparable with any of the existing provisions of section 3 of the Police Act, but logical developments of these provisions.J.G.

</content>
</cab>
