<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/199/18 images: 498-504</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DoCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJEST Y&apos;S GOVERNMENT80CP(78)18 COPY NO14 February 1978CABINETNORTH SEA OIL DEVELOPMENT FUNDNote by the Secretary of State for Energy, the Secretary of Statefor the Environment and the Secretary of State for scotland. We were invited to prepare in association with the Chief Secretary,Treasury and the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster a paper showing how a practicable North Sea Oil Development Fund could be devised.(CM(78) 4th Conclusions, Minute 4 refers.)2. A paper is attached, agreed by us, which we have discussed with theChief Secretary and the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster, although theywere not convinced by the case it makes for a separate Fund.3. The paper includes, as an Annex, draft paragraphs setting out ourview to fit the framework of the existing text of the White Paper. Howeverseveral of us felt that whatever the ultimate decision on the Fund, whether for or against, a fuller treatment would have to be given than was containedin the earlier draft.A W BP SB MDepartment of Energy14 February 1978
^proposal FOR A NORTH SEA OIL DEVELOPMENT FUNDNote by the Secretaries of State for Knergy, the EnvironmentScotland.White Paper on the benefits of North Sea Oil sets out prioritiesfo^ the use of the additional resources which the oil provides,and itipj likely that there will be widespread support for the view that^vestment to strengthen the economy should take precedence overconsumption.    But unless the means by which this is to be achievedis made plain, it will not be surprising if there is much scepticismabout the Governments ability to achieve its aims.   Already Northoil output is equal to about half of the UK&apos;s requirements and (*th Sea gas meets virtually all of the country&apos;s gas requirements.Yet there is as yet little to show for these advantages in the levelof industrial investment.   Whatever the Government&apos;s hopes andMentions may be, if the needs of increased investment are leftto compete with other pressing claims at times when there may be&quot;^h political pressure to reduce taxes or to increase publice*Penditure, it is unlikely that they will be realised.    Thus if&apos;th* Government is determined that its objectives should beSieved, it is essential to have an appropriate institutionalRework which will set aside a portion of the oil revenues forVestment purposes.    Such an arrangement will also carry much moreEviction with the public as well as giving those responsible forVestment decisions confidence that resources would be ava^lable0n &amp; continuing basis.paper aims to demonstrate that a practicable scheme can be*evised, provided that the Cabinet is prepared to commit itselfto expenditure on new investment projects beyond those envisagedln existing plans, recognising that there would have to be con-*^ential changes in expected levels of taxation, in other forms0f Public expenditure or in the PSBR in order to finance it. This0f course is not simply a consequence of the Fund proposal, but ofrealisation of the Government&apos;s aim to give a higher priority^vestment..
Given this broad policy commitment, a non-statutory development fund could be established without the need for legislation andwithout administrative complications.    The establishment of a development Fund would also strengthen the content of an annual report to Parliament, which might otherwise pose serious proW-erD 1and would demonstrate the seriousness of the Government^ inteto invest a part of the benefits in industrial and regional development.An illustrative oroposal for a Fund is outlined below to demonits feasibility.   Details as to the scale of the Fund and wc rhp lefrange of projects which would be eligible can if necessary ucover for fuller discussion and decision later.    Provided tha*csuch scheme is regarded as desirable, colleagues are invited toa^ree to the inclusion of a paragraph in the White Paper on lines of the draft at Annex A.Ldva*ce3 *       An Illustrative Proposal ^ ofA non-statutory Fund should be established to secure reinvesta substantial propostion of revenue from the North Sea in ne*industrial and social infrastructure projects with emphasis on regional development including Scotland, Wales, Northern Irel^and the Development Areas in England.   A Ministerial Commit&apos;would authorise projects and programmes according to thiswj thin a total sum fixed and set aside for some years in from North Sea oil revenues.   Expenditure authorised through ^Development Fund would be covered by normal PESC arrangement5&apos;would be brought together in a special section of the PubHcj. to expenditure White Paper.    The expenditures would be subject ^.rfljige&apos;the usual PAC and Accounting Officer arrangements.    Such an^ment under Ministerial control appears much preferable   *0 afiO0&apos;ferring the revenues to some new independent Board or or^anlS,e^the latter would need legislation, could not be so easily r6\cftteon to meet the Governments priorities and would tend to dupltho role of the not and the Development Agencies.
confidential the Committee should propose an initial budget and guidelines fora Fund with a view to it being established later this year (and tobe included in the next PES).    This would enable greater priority to be given to investment, making it possible for some much-neededprojects to be brought forward in time and a longer view to betaken of the returns to investment^inisterr would of course retain the responsibility for decidingbetween competing claims on the Fund according to the criteriathat they themselves decide on.    The appropriate size of the Fund&quot;o-would of course depend on the range of investment projects Ministers*ished it to cover.    The TUC asked that all the oil revenues should0e spent on investment and public expenditure.    If the Fund were^tended to cover a range of types of additional investment,including social infrastructure, it would certainly need a sub-stantial allocation.    For example an initial allocation of  5 billionto last a number of years might well be appropriate. Expenditure*ould take time to build up but would absorb about one half of thetotal oil revenue accruing in the 1980s;    the remainder of theAvenues, and the additional balance-of-payments benefits, wouldrtill be available for general measures to stimulate the economy.Fund would be used to provide additional resources for investmenttrough the Scottish, Welsh and Northern Irish Development Agenciesthrough the not.    It would assist genuinely additional projects^ the nationalised industries and i^, would assist private companies^er planning agreements.    It would also be used to assist social1?tfrastructure investment in inner city and assisted areas. the location of revenues to the Fund, and its implications forfyure taxation, public expenditure and the PSBR, would have to^ taken into account henceforth in treasury forecasting and^dgetary planning.^ Government, in announcing the establishment of the Fund, could^dertake to provide annual reports to Parliament on the use of*0**tn Sea benefits.    These benefits will of course go far widerVi the use which is made of the Fund.   But many of these widerbefits, though real, will be hard to quantify or even possibly^separate from other influences.   In accounting for the operationC* the Fund, the Government will therefore be able to give real
substance to these annual reports which might otherwise prove a difficult commitment to fulfil convincingly.2.       The Wain Point at issue the main objection to a Fund of the kind proposed above centres onthe problem of additionality.    To set aside a portion of theGovernment&apos;s revenue in a special fund is no guarantee that expenditure financed by such a fund will be truly additional towhat would otherwise be undertaken.    If the projects were worthdoing, the argument runs, the means to finance them would be foundeven in the absence of a fund;    and the existence of a separatefund may simply result in some reduction in the finance madeavailable from other sources for the type of projects which areeligible for the Fund.However, existing arrangements do not in any case provide forselection of investment expenditure according to purely technicalcriteria.    Whether implicitly or explicitly, they involve an assessment of the relative claims of productive investment, socialinfrastructure and consumption which is political in its nature.Tho Fund as conceived here would constitute a political commitmentnot to spend all the oil revenues on consumption, but to earmarka substantial part for investment.    Without a Fund, a generalisedcommitment in the White Paper would lack credibility and may indeecfail to achieve the shift in favour of investment that we alldesire.    In short without a supporting institutional framework,out intent would be eroded.   Moreover once a Fund has been establsMany pledge to wind it up and disperse the oil revenues would beseen to be irresponsible.Pure additionality would be very hard to achieve in practice, andif the Fund is set up there may be some projects undertaken whichwould have been financed by other means in its absence.    But manyprojects will be enlarged or brought forward in time, while otherswill be adopted which would not have been undertaken at all. Thatthere may not be pure additionality does not really matter so longas the emphasis is on increasing investment beyond what it would otherwise have been.    What is at issue therefore is whether the setting up of the Fund will in practice make it more likely thata portion of North Sea resources will be safeguarded for investmen
purposes against other competing claims.    Ultimately this must depend on how it is operated;    but it undoubtedly could be used&quot;to considerable advantage for this purpose and investment would&quot;then be higher than it otherwise would be.^e main question to be resolved therefore is whether or not Cabinetbelieves it is right to make a commitment to allocate funds to new investment projects on a scale something like that illustrated here.such a commitment is accepted, it will be necessary to release^he finance by means of compensating adjustments to expected levels of taxation, or to the PSBR or to existing public expenditure plans,^he recent Public Expenditure Y/hite Paper did not entirely pre-empt&quot;the choice since it projected a sharp cut in the forecast governmentdeficit between 1977/8 and 1979/30, implying either that there isscope for large tax reductions or that the PSBR will be reduced to* ^?HL level.   Moreover even if the eventual allocation to the Fundwene at the upper level of the range indicated, this wouldTstill^present only 2 per cent of total public expenditure, so thatfinance can hardly be impossible to find.3.CONCLUSIONT*e proposal for a non-statutory Fund avoids the need for initialAgination and would be compatible with existing administrative arrangements.    It would fall within standard government accountingProcedures.    The only administrative innovation would be to bring!*e process of Ministerial decision making on new investment projects of a certain type together within a pior overall budgetu*der a Ministerial Committee.    There is no doubt about theadministrative feasibility of such a procedure.Colleagues are therefore invited to agree that a Fund of the typeoutlined would be feasible, to decide whether or not the relatedcommitment to additional investment projects is desirable, whether^ the light of this there would be advantages in establishing sucha Fund, and whether to include the draft paragraph in the Annex tobounce such an intention in the White Paper on the Benefits of north Sea Oil.
ANNEXSgAFT PARAGRAPHS FOR WHITE PAPER51 The Government has considered whether it would be betteranle to achieve the long run objectives set out in this paperbY establishing a special Fund financed by North Sea oilAvenues.   As this paper has made clear, North Sea oil benefitsh*ve widespread implications for the whole fiscal and financialmanagement of the UK economy which go beyond expenditure through a special Fund.52 However the Government believes that a non-statutory Fund^ould he established to secure reinvestment of a subtantlalProportion of revenue from the North Sea in new industrial andSQcial infrastructure projects with emphasis on regional developmentincluding Scotland, Wales, Northern Ireland and the development areas in England and the renewal of our inner cities.    Such a fund would safeguard the oil revenues coming into the budget from the competing claims of other needs which may be desirable and pressing,blJt of less long term value to the country&apos;s future.    It will also We the nation confidence that the priorities set out in thisP*Per will be met and those concerned will he able to plan in con-fidence that substantial resources will he available over a periodof years.53 ( as in CP(78) 16, but add at end:)Xt is intended that the activities of the Fund together with anacoount of the wider benefits of North Sea oil should be set outdually in a report to Parliament.

</content>
</cab>
