<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/227/0 images: 156-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.81Printed for the Cabinet, January, 1932.SECRET. Copy No. ^CP. 2 (32).THE  CABINET.CONVENTION  TO  IMPROVE   THE   MEANS   OF PREVENTING  WAR.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE  FOR WAR.I circulate  or the information of my colleagues a Memorandum by the Chief of 0160 the Imperial General Staff. 1741The War Oitice, H.2nd January, 1932.MEMORANDUM BY THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF.1. The principal reasons in favour of signing the Model Treaty given in the Foreign Office Memorandum attached to Sir John Simon&apos;s note of 15th December, 1931 (OP. 319 (31)), are that it was His Majesty&apos;s Government who, in 1929, took the lead in turning the original German proposal for a Model Treaty into a General Convention ; that His Majesty&apos;s Government were chiefly responsible for obtaining an agreed text of the Convention in May last ; and that the French and German Govern-ments are about to sign the Convention before 2nd February, 1932. There is no suggestion that it is a particularly desirable Treaty, although Sir William Malkin, whose comments were attached to the Foreign Office Memorandum, suggests that some of the objections of the Chiefs of Staff Committee appear to him to be rather less serious than they appear at first sight. Other objections, and particularly those which apply to the possible effect of the Treaty on actual and existing problems of the British Empire, are confirmed, and indeed emphasized, though Sir William Malkin belittles them on his assumption that the Members of the Council will be guided in their action solely by motives of common sense and justice, a rash assumption considering the political history of Europe. The Cabinet are therefore asked to authorize the signature of a Treaty, not because it is a good one, but because a previous Government took an active part in its preparation, and because it is necessary to keep the French and German Governments in a good humour for the Disarmament Conference, even if it entails a sacrifice of important safeguards to the British Empire.A further point is made in the Foreign Office Memorandum that we might sign the Treaty but withhold ratification. Signature at any rate commits His Majesty&apos;s Government to agreement in principle, and to sign a Treaty without intending to ratify seems hardly consistent with either the past traditions or the dignity of this country.2. The objections to signing it are even more apparent when the sequence of events and procedure which led to the present situation are examined. Mr. Baldwin&apos;s Cabinet of 1928 criticized the Treaty adversely and instructed its delegate at Geneva (Lord Cushendun) &quot; not to commit himself in his criticism so far as to involve any risk of his being pressed to sign it,&quot; and it must be noted that at that time the Treaty was intended only as a model which any two or more States might adopt if they so desired and put into force as between themselves.3. The British representative (the Honourable A. Cadogan) made the following-declaration on 17th September, 1928, in the 3rd Committee of the Assembly : &quot; It would be remembered that, when the question first came before the Committee on Arbitration and Security, Lord Cushendun had expressed various misgivings in regard to the provisions of the draft Treaty, and as he saw that the resolution submitted by the Committee on Arbitration and Security &apos; requests the Secretary-General to forward the said model ... to the Governments in order that they may give the necessary instructions to their delegations at the Assembly,&apos; he felt bound to say one word to explain that, if they now let this draft pass in silence, it must not be taken as indicating any real change of mind on the part of the British Government. On the contrary, after careful consideratiou, they still had certain misgivings about certain provisions in the draft.   They were, in point of fact, not yet convinced of the necessity or the utility(b32/8)   60   1/32   w.o.p.   5951
of such a model Treaty and he could not hold out any prospect of their being able to sign a document of the kind. On the other hand, they were assured in the Committee on Arbitration and Security an assurance which had been repeated and referred to in that Committee that the document was in the nature simply of a model for, as it were, the assistance of those Governments who wished to enter into such a Treaty. Tberefore it was unnecessary for them, perhaps, to criticise the terms of a Treaty which other Governments or groups of Governments might find useful. If in the past they had joined in criticising the terms of the draft, he wished to emphasise that they only joined to that extent in the framing of the Treaty, and it must not be taken to mean that they were convinced of its necessity or utility  at all events, as regards his own country.&quot;4. After the change ot Government in June, 1929, the British delegates at the Assembly of the League abandoned the critical attitude of their predecessors and proposed that the Model Treaty should be redrafted and turned into a Genera! Treaty. This decision was taken without any consultation whatsoever in the Committee of Imperial Defence, notwithstanding that it was obviously one of great importance from the point of view of that Committee, and, so far as the Army Council are aware, without the knowledge of the Secretary of State for War and a fresh decision of the Cabinet. Subsequently there were several discussions at the Committee of Imperial Defence on the details of the Treaty. The Chiefs of Staff Committee made their point of view on the question perfectly clear in their Memorandum of 2nd May, 1930 (C.I.D. 986-B.), but the discussions at the Committee of Imperial Defence were always confined to details. From June, 1929, the Committee of Imperial Defence have never discussed the principle, except in so far as it has arisen in connection with detail.5. Hitherto the criticisms of the Model Treaty have been based solely on the ground that it is injurious to British interests. Recent events, however, have tended to show that it is also unlikely to be of much value for the purposes for which it was designed.   The former aspect will be dealt with first.6. It is clear from paragraph 4 of Sir William Maikhvs note that he entirely misconceives one of the main objections to the Treaty made by the Chiefs of Staff. The suitability of the Treaty for particular countries depends not upon their size and quarrelsome disposition, as he suggests, but upon their geographical position and political conditions. The Treaty may be suitable for neighbouring and centralized States with well-defined land frontiers&apos;such as France and Germany, or, to take lesser powers, Bulgaria and Serbia. The situation of the Empire is entirely different. It has frontiers all over the world, both geographically and politically ill-defined, where there is often on the other side no stable Government able to exert control. Equally the British Empire is in contact with States which are quite ready to undertake any obligation although they may not have the intention, and will almost certainly not have the power, to carry it out ; States which are, moreover, situated in parts of the world where it is quite impossible for the League of Nations to enforce its decisions. Again, we have to deal with such countries as China or Egypt where we have certain rights and our material interests are very great, though our juridical position is vague and ill-defined. It is in such areas as these that prompt movements of troops or ships may be necessary to save British lives and protect British interests. France is an admirable example of a State which could accept this Treaty without great difficulty. It is true that she has overseas commitments, but they are not in general likely to involve her in frontier incidents with neighbouring Powers of any great consequence. Her great interest lies in her eastern frontier, and she has caused a clause to be inserted to the effect that the lines behind which the armed forces must withdraw shall not uncover the exterior lines of the defence organizations existing on the frontier, thus adequately safeguarding herself. The French eastern frontier is being protected by fortifications along the whole length and the army will in consequence be under no obligation to withdraw. Similarly, Germany need have little anxiety about signing the Treaty as she has no colonies or overseas commitments of any kind and her armed forces cannot conceivably be ordered to withdraw behind any lines of demarcation as they are already located 50 kilometres east of the Rhine in accordance with the provisions of the Treaty of Versailles.Having in view the characteristics of the States beyond her borders, the Government of India is impressed with the same anxieties as those of the General Staff. Great Britain is just as interested in the security of the North-West Frontier and may be in the future as actively committed to its defence as the Government of
....................-.........................-..........* ..............     . - . .........    ........     ........* &apos;India itself. The same reasons which dictated to the Government of India the need of freedom of action should apply with no less force to the Government of the United Kingdom which is ultimately responsible for the defence of that Frontier.7. Paragraph 7 of Sir William Malkin&apos;s note deals with four different parts of the world to which the Chiefs of Staff consider we might be forbidden to send reinforce-ments by the Council if we sign the Treaty. It is significant that in each case Sir William Malkin agrees that the Council would have the power to do so. He qualifies his observations, however, by suggesting that the Council would be &quot; unlikely&quot; to take such a course or that their decision would &quot; depend upon the view they took as to the reasonableness of our action.&quot; No Government responsible for Imperial Defence can dare to base its actions upon a vague opinion that the Council will probably not act in an extreme manner. The Council clearly has the power to do so and for that reason, if for no other, His Majesty&apos;s Government caunot afford toxrun a risk of this kind. It has many grave risks to shoulder in many parts of the world, but it surely is under no obligation to add to them by signing a Treaty from which it can gain no possible advantage and which was never designed to apply to an Empire of this kind. It is hardly to be supposed that any British Government would take provocative or aga-res-sive action in excess of the needs of the situation, and we ought to retain the freedom to act in defence of our interests in the many disturbed areas of the world.8. One of the most important points raised by the Chiefs of Staff was whether the Council can fix lines behind which the armed forces must withdraw without the consent of the party concerned. Sir William Malkin disagrees with the views of the Chiefs of Staff (paragraph N of his note), and it is not proposed to continue the controversy. The significance of the phrase &quot; It shall, in every case, rest with the Council to determine the period within which the said lines shall be fixed&quot; must, however, remain a matter of speculation unless it is accepted that it means that the will of tbe Council will, in the last resort, prevail. How can the period be determined, if the party concerned is free to persist in its objection ? This article is characteristic of the loose and unsatisfactory drafting of the Treaty, which is one of its clangers. It is understood that certain other delegations do not accept Sir William Malkin&apos;s view -on this article. His Majesty&apos;s Government cannot afford to permit our vital interests to depend upon phrases in this Treaty, in the interpretation of which the Permanent Court of International Justice might differ from Sir William Malkin.9. Coming now to the second line of criticism, Sir William Malkin states that:  &quot; The object of the draft Convention is to strengthen the hands of the Council of the League in their efforts to prevent a possible outbreak of war, by conferring on the Council (acting unanimously except for the parties to the dispute) certain powers in relation to the forces of the disputants. Under Article 2 the Council can prescribe the evacuation of the territory of one disputant by the forces of the other which may have entered it, and under Article 3 the Council may fix lines which must not be passed by the forces of these disputants. The object is to enable the Council to stop fighting which may have begun, and to ensure that no further fighting takes place while it is endeavouring to settle the question.&quot;10. Recent events suggest that any attempt to apply the Convention is not likely to have a very happy result. For two and a half months the League of Nations was engaged in an attempt to apply the principles of the Convention to the Manchurian dispute. Its efforts were largely directed to inducing the Japanese to withdraw their forces from outside the railway zone, and latterly to arrange a neutral zone between the Chinese and Japanese forces. It entirely failed to achieve its object. The Japanese decided for reasons of their own (it is immaterial to the argument whether they were good or bad) to occupy large areas of Manchuria and give the Chinese a salutary lesson. When withdrawal was proposed, they felt that they could not afford to leave their fellow subjects at the mercy of more or less irregular Chinese forces and bandits. When a Great Power has made up its mind on a certain course of action, which will involve it in accusations of a breach of the Covenant and of the Kellogg Pact, it is certain that it will not be deterred from its course of action by such a minor matter -as a theoretical breach of the Convention. Can it seriously be suggested that if the Convention had been in force, it would have influenced Japanese action in the smallest degree ? The main result of the League&apos;s efforts was to exacerbate Japanese opinion, and at times fears were entertained lest either China or Japan should leave the League. The final result that was achieved would probably have been obtained much earlier but for the attempt to apply the principles of the Convention, and the League has come out of the affair, so far, without very much credit.
11. This is exactly what might be expected to happen in applying the Convention to many disputes. On 30th July, 1914, the French Government, desiring to avoid a frontier incident, ordered its forces to withdraw 10 kilometres behind the frontier. .This was reinforced by instructions from the President of the Republic the following day. On 30th July, a German cavalry patrol had crossed the frontier and on 2nd August German cavalry and cyclists had committed acts of aggression at several points. German troops also entered Luxembourg. Nevertheless on this day French troops were ordered to keep at a distance of at least 2 kilometres from the Belgian frontier and the line was also drawn back from Luxembourg territory. On the morning of 3rd August General JofFre represented that the above - instructions were gravely embarrassing his concentration, and about 2.10 p.m. they were cancelled by the Minister of War. This is precisely what may usually be expected to happen. It is asking too much to expect that Generals, who are faced with tremendous responsibilities for the safety of their country and for the lives of the soldiers under their command,, should take the risk of incuz-ring a strategical or tactical disadvantage. If a Govern -ment, acting on its own initiative and with a sincere desire to avoid a war, was unable to draw a line which its military commanders could take the i*isk of enforcing, how much less likely is it that the Council of the League will be able to secure observance of its instructions, even though the line is drawn in consultation with the Government of the country concerned ? Yet, if the instructions are not obeyed it will become known to the enemy and there will be accusations of bad faith.12. In this connection, attention is called to a Historical Note circulated by the Secretary to the Committee of Imperial Defence in May, 1930 (OLD. Paper No. 987-B), in which he gives two instances in which proposals were made by neutral Governments for military dispositions to avert the outbreak of war. These were not identical with the measures contemplated by the Convention, as in each case it was not withdrawal of the forces but demobilization that was suggested, i.e., in the case of the War^pf 1866-and the Russo-Turkish War of 187*. In both these cases the good intentions of the mediators failed to produce the desired result. &quot; On the contrary,&quot; as the Secretary to-the Committee of Imperial Defence states, &quot; in the state of suspicion which then prevailed and which always prevails just before the outbreak of war, they merely exacerbated the situation.&quot;13. The Foreign Office have adduced certain political reasons why the Treaty should be signed. They are less concerned with advocacy of the Treaty, as such, than with the fact that, since 1929, we have been prominently concerned in its drafting. There does not appear to be any valid reason why, because one false step was taken in not consulting those Departments.upon whom the main responsibility for carrying out the Treaty rests, a second false step must necessarily follow.14. Sir William Malkin is in agreement with the Chiefs of Staff Committee that the Council would have it in their power to prevent us from despatching reinforcements to Egypt, Iraq, China and South Persia, if the Treaty wrere signed. This by no means exhausts the lists of parts of the world, such as the North-West Frontier, where our responsibilities are grave and where the Model Treaty might hamper us and assist our enemies. There is no other nation in the world which could be placed in such an equivocal jDOsition as ourselves or to which it could be less advantageous to accept the Treaty. What are we to receive in exchange for these admittedly serious risks to our national security ? So far as can be deduced from the Foreign Office Memorandum, the rewards are to be the possibility of an improved atmosphere for the Disarmament Conference and a recognition of our consistency in a somewhat belated advocacy of the Treaty.15. The weighty reasons affecting our national security have been stated above-and to these may be added the loose and obscure drafting of the Treaty, which makes it difficult to be sure of or foresee the lull extent of our obligations. It is submitted that the reasons adduced by the Foreign Office ought not to outweigh the grave reasons against the signature of the Treaty put forward by the Service Departments which are responsible to His Majesty&apos;s Government tor Imperial Defence and consider that the Treaty may not only embarass the Empire in the. future but may well prove to be a source of great danger to its security.

</content>
</cab>
