<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/227/0 images: 220-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
* X 4i JL(This document, is the property of His Britannic -v:C5 hajes-ty-&apos; s.-Government)RET Copy No,, W/,7(31) CABINET government BUILDING programme memorandum by the First Commissioner of Works.In accordance with a Cabinet Conclusion of 14th December I submit, for the information of my colleagues, a Memorandum on the Government Building programme so far as I am responsible for itB    (I am not, of course, responsible for the building work of the Service Departments but, on occasions, my Department acts as agent)0The volume of the work involved is small in comparison both with the total volume of the nation&apos;s building work and with the volume of work carried out on a grant supported basis by local authorities and otherss    It consists in the main (a)  of the new works and maintenance voted by Parliament in Civil Estimates Class VII. and (b)  of the building works in connection with the erection,  etc.,  of new Postal buildings the cost of which is met from Loans raised by the Postmaster General under the Post Office and Telegraph (Money) Act,   1928.The policy adopted in framing the programme for1932 is based upon the Cabinet instructions contained inTreasury Circular of 4th September last which lays down the following guiding principle:-&quot;The Budget position today is, however,  such as to render a more stringent pruning of expenditure imperative and Departments must be prepared to consider the suspension or abolition of many services which, however desirable, cannot be regarded as essential in present circumstances.&quot;
1 09i- W MThe amounts provided - for 1931 and those proposed for 1932 are:-1931 1932   -:c- New Works  (Vote) 921,675       706,670    (as submitted to treasury).Maintenance (Vote)  1,432,614    1,291,904    ( do. )Postal Telegraph      1,380,000    1,100,800    ( do. )and Telephone Loan.* excluding public Buildings Overseas.4 Note.    The 1931 &amp; 1932 figures include about  150,000 in respect of Works under  2,000 in value.New Works (Vote). As regards the volume of New Works to be provided for in the Vote, my Department is mainly dependent upon the demands of other departments.      As works now in progress are completed and drop out others will, no doubt, be commenced.      The provisions proposed for 1932 are in respect of the completion of works already in hand and of the commencement of new works of urgent necessity.      I am not in a position to forecast a definite programme of works over a period of years as the Departmental demands are to some extent an unknown quantity.      I can only indicate, under the principal headings the prospects as they are at present known to me.Art and science Buildings.Estimates have been prepared of a large number of building works which have been recommended by the Royal Commission on National kuseums and Galleries and of other works requested by the authorities of the various Institutions and by the Department of Scientific and Industrial Research.      The total estimated cost of these works is about  750,000 and their execution would neoessarily be spread over a number of years.
x   uEmployment Exchanges.There is a large programme for the provision of new Employment Exchanges and the programme for 1931 would normally have been  450,000.      This was restricted to  290,750 owing to the necessity for economy.     For 1932 the expenditure has been restricted to  200,000 at which level it will probably remain for the next few years.      If the restrictions on expenditure were removed at once a maximum expenditure of  250,000 could be achieved in 1932 and the full programme of  450,000 in 1933 and subsequent years.Various Public Buildings.Proposals, for which no provision has yet been made, have been considered for the extensions of the Patent Office, Home Office Industrial Luseum, Stationery Office Press and the Ordnance Survey Office,  Southampton.      The estimated cost of these works is  174,000.The scheme for the development of the Montagu House - Whitehall Gardens site for the purposes of Government Offices at an estimated cost of  2,215,000 has been held in abeyance since the proposal to alter the Statutory &quot;building line&quot; was rejected by Parliament last year.      The original scheme must.inevitably be considerably modified and reduced and the estimated cost will probably not exceed  1,800,000.Consultation with Departments in regard to their revised requirements and with the Local Authorities in regard to the disposition of the buildings,  the selection of an Architect,  the preparation of plans and bills of quantities and the invitation of tenders will inevitably occupy a period of at least two years from the date of approval to go ahead before work on the site can be commenced.
Extensive bull- ing schemes in Edinburgh have also.been projected involving the erection of a new Sheriff Court House, extension of the National Library on the site of the existing Sheriff Court House and new Public Offices at the estimated cost of upwards of  750,000.      In the event of the Order Confirmation Bill promoted by the Edinburgh Corporation receiving Parliamentary approval this session, building operations on the Sheriff Court House can be begun oarly in 1953 but the scheme for new Government Offices has been in abeyance since the Fine Art Commission for Scotland rejected the proposal for the dovelopmont of the Calton Jail site.      The site problem in this case is beset with difficulties and may render any scheme unattractive from the financial aspect.A new building at Cardiff for the Welsh Board of Health estimated to cost  130,000 has also been proposed.Demands for now County Courts estimated to cost  55,000 have been received and others are understood to be in contemplation.Various building works (Refreshment Pavilions, etc.) in the Royal Parks, estimated to cost  40,000, have boon under consideration.Summary.These works comprise a future building programme of upwards of four million pounds in respect of Works costing more than  2,000 each.      The smaller works would be commenced about six months after their approval and the larger works would require from eighteen months to two yoars for the nocossary preparations.      In certain cacos such as the Montagu Houso Scheme and the Edinburgh Scheme there are difficulties connected with design and amenity which would probably prolong the preparation poriod.     The time of execution of the various work will range from six months to six years.
Maintenance.HaintonanoG includes the upkeep and repair of the various buildings in charge of my Department and expenditure in 1932 will be limited to tho bare essentials. Many works such as repainting,  and repairs to roofs, floors, brick and stone work will be deferred,,Ma.inteha.rioe also includes certain special types of work, viz;Ancient Monuments and Historic Buildings.The work proposed for 193? (estimated to cost  50,630) has been limited to that necessary to retain,  so far as possible,  the  skilled men who have acquired a certain technique through yoars of employment on it;    tho normal provision would have been about  70,000.      There are also various non-essential works such as caretakers&apos; houses museums,  etc., estimated to cost  11,000 and work suitable for unskilled labour, ostimated to cost  45,000, for which provision has not been made.Houses of Parliament.      Ropair of Stonework.This work is being continued at a rato involving oxpondituro of about  40,000 a yoar and the rate of progress could bo accelerated if more monoy were available. River Defences.Flood prevention works at the Houses of Parliament&apos;, Victoria. Tower Gardens and the Tower of London, ostimatod to cost  26,500, will shortly be necessary but no provision has boen made for 1932.Postal, Telegraph and Telephone Loan. This programmo is settled between the Post Office and the Treasury on tho basis,  inter alia, of the estimates for tho various works prepared by my Department.      I understand that the building programme is likely to remain
at the present level for the next few years unless circumstances should arise to necessitate an acceleration of postal or telephone development.General.Subject to no substantial change in financial policy occurring, the building programme for which I am responsible can continue for several yoars at or about tho level for 1932 as a minimum.      It may be said that prevision is made for all Departmental requirements of an absolutely essential character but that many schemes of improvement which would facilitate better organisation and future economies in running costs ha,vo been suspended. It would, of course, be practicable to accelerate tho preparation of a number of the schemes, referred to above, if the necessary financial provision could be made for their execution, but unless there is a reasonable prospect of money being made available, I should deprocato expenditure of the time and labour entailed in carrying through the preliminaries in a large number of schemes of varying degrees of importance.(Intld.)      .::     W.O.G.8th January,  1932.

</content>
</cab>
