<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/227/0 images: 486-489</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i This document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   January 1932., secret.-CP. 28 (32).bpy Nocabinet.reports by liocal governments on the political situation in india.I circulate for the information of my colleagues copy of telegraphic reports from -the Local Governments in India.india office, 19th January 1932.United Provinces.Orders prohibiting processions and meetings have been generally obeyed, and -much less enthusiasm for the no-rent campaign is being shown. Congress leaders in many places are anxious to avoid arrest. A number of Congress Committees have been dissolved and dictators have been appointed. So far there has been very little picketing. Illicit salt has been manufactured at Benares only. Government is still following the policy of arresting leaders and organisers only, as far as possible. Ordinances II, III and V were extended to the whole Province on 9th January. &quot;The Criminal Law Amendment Act was similarly extended on ]2th January and Ordinance IV on 15th January. A number of Congress offices and buildings have been taken over, notably Swaraj Bhawan, the Allahabad headquarters of the Provincial Committee. All District Tahsil and Town Congress Committees, War Councils and similar Associations have been declared unlawful, and their offices notified under section 3 of Ordinance IV. Situation at Benares has improved and is now normal. Cawnpore has given trouble, but is now under control. Allahabad is still the worst -centre of activity in the Province, though no further serious clash between the police and processions have occurred. In Lucknow there is very little Congress activity. The number of convictions under the Ordinances is 299 and under the ordinary law (mostly for defiance of orders forbidding processions) 4-30. Releases under section 562, Cr.P.O, number 90. Casualties : 5 deaths, 39 detained in hospital, S2 slightly injured. Government have not empowered any magistrate under section 3 of the Emergency Powers Ordinance, which is consequently unused. Rent revenue collections are proceeding slowly but satisfactorily, except in some parts of the Allahabad Division. There are very few reports of recusant tenants, though many are delaying payment in the hope of better prices, which are still rising. His Excellency&apos;s meeting at Cawnpore on the 9th was well attended by business men. Similar meetings have since been held by Commissioners in all the divisional head-quarters. District Magistrates have been directed to do the same at all the important trading centres with a view to assuring traders of Government help in meeting the threat of boycott and picketing.North-West Frontier Province.There has been a steady and general improvement in the situation in all districts -except in Dera Ismail Khan, where there has been an outburst of agitation in the northern part of Tank Tahsii.   This has led to picketing in Tank bazaars by villagers from outside on a fairly large scale at a time when Mahsud jirgas were being interviewed in Tank by the Political Agent.   As a precautionary measure one Indian battalion has been sent to Tank from Waziristan.   Peshawar city and district have been quieter and there have been no serious demonstrations during the week. Attempted picketing has been half-hearted and on a smaller scale.   Iu certain areas, notably Katlang in the North-East portion of Mardan sub-division, agitation continues and Congress offices which have been closed by order are reopened and substitute leaders sent up.    Such villages are visited by columns, and the Congress emblems -are confiscated or destroyed and the leaders arrested.   There have been no signs 598      60   1.32MEMORANDUM BY  THE  SECRETARY  OF STATE FOR INDIA.S. H.
of the recovery of Congress from the disorganisation caused by the original arrests,, and satisfactory features are the increasing number of villages which have taken action&apos;- themselves against Congress agents, and the revulsion of feeling against Abdul&apos;Ghaffar, which is growing but not yet widespread. It has been possible to reduce the strength of all columns in the Peshawar district and to dispense with two columns which have returned to cantonments. Kohat district is very satisfactory; all troops have been withdrawn to cantonments and agitation has ceased. There has-been an improvement in the Bannu district, where there have been, comparatively few attempts to picket. No political agitation in Hazara district, where the situation is normal. Arrests under section o of the Emergency Powers Ordinance during the-week ending 12th January were 568. The total arrests under the Ordinance at that date were 2,569.Bombay.Th&apos;e arrest of the leading agitators and the seizure of notified places has continued generally. The number of further arrests under section 3 of Ordinance II was 229 during the week in 27 districts, including Bombay city. A considerable number of those arrested have since been dealt with under section 4, and realeased.. In several cases action was met by disclaimers or apologies, which have been accepted by District Magistrates. The position generally is quiet. Occasional hartals were not well supported. Meetings and other demonstrations lack support with, the arrest of successive dictators or speakers and are Usually dispersed without difficulty where necessary. Some rowdyism after meetings in Ahmedabad and Bombay was due mainly to the hooligan element, and in Pandharpur to schoolboys. The situation in Bombay city is not at present causing serious difficulty. Attempts at organised picketing are almost confined to Bombay city. Land revenue collections are coming-in steadily where due, and generally, in the rural areas, there is little enthusiasm for Congress or for its programme and the public generally support the action taken. The removal of - the&quot; principal agitators has had a salutary effect everywhere. A warning was issued to all newspapers on llth instant to avoid publication of objectionable matter.Madras.The situation in all districts is satisfactory. Swift and vigorous action at the outset has taken the civil disobedience party by surprise and has disorganised their plans. The Congress Committee is dissolving and is appointing a dictator to carry on the campaign. The resultant action is negligible except for sporadic picketing in Madras and a few other places, which has proved to be generally ineffective. The Congress Association is short of funds and is finding difficulty in securing further financial support. The tendency on the part of those formerly in sympathy is to dis-sociate themselves from the movement now that Government has shown determination to govern and ability to afford protection from molestation. Collection of land revenue is proceeding promptly in the three districts to which the, Unlawful Instigation Ordinance has been extended. The Mahommedan attitude is satisfactory, noticeably in Malabar. The warning issued to the Press has been generally effective in discouraging outward support of civil disobedience. Action is j^proposed against two newspapers only. Seventy-four associations have been declared unlawful under the Criminal Law Amendment Act. The number of arrests up to date is comparatively small. Figures will be telegraphed separately. The police were compelled to open fire on the mob in Berhampore, with the result that one person was killed and two wounded. &quot;One man was killed in Coimbatore district during a lathi charge. Attempted meetings elsewhere have been dispersed without serious incident.Bengal.The situation is still generally quiet and the movement has not gained momentum. The number of arrests under section 3. of the Emergency Powers Ordinance is approximately 87.Bihar and Orissa.Continued   action  against leaders and Congress centres  has  caused  further -disorganisation of the movement.   Sporadic attempts to revive it have been countered without difficulty, and there is no general revival of picketing.   Champparan district reports a revival of the no-rent campaign, and the Unlawful Instigation Ordinance-
has been extended, but elsewhere no such attempts are reported. The general public continues to show little sympathy with the movement and several districts report promises of assistance from leading zemindars and others. Schools and colleges are not affected.Ajmer Merwara.Little Congress activity of importance has taken place in Ajmer Merwara during the past week. The rural area is unaffected and civil disobedience advocates have gained no support in the towns. Eleven more persons, most of whom belong to places outside the district, were arrested for attempting to organise demonstrations. A few Mahajans Kekri who tried to persuade the town inhabitants to join in the movement formed Congress Committees, which have been declared unlawful. The situation in the Indian States is normal.Punjab.The general situation is quiet. Various plans of Congress in Lahore and&apos; Amritsar to provoke a clash with the police and to arouse public enthusiasm, have-been successfully countered under ordinal law. In Lahore public interest is small, and attendance at largest meeting was 1,500 only. Picketing has been threatened but not materialised. Independence Day throughout Province was a complete-failure. Sardul Singh Kavishar returned to Lahore on the 14th, and is exhorting all Congress followers to seek arrest. Congress Volunteers in Lahore number 216 and in Amritsar 80. No powers under any Ordinance have been actually exercised. The total number of arrests throughout the Province under the ordinary law, including the Criminal Law Amendment Act, is 51.Central Provinces.So far as present indications go, the renewal of civil disobedience has not been a success in Nagpur. Following on the declaration of the Marathi War Council as an unlawful association, five members were arrested and subsequently convicted. Arrests were effected without trouble and there has been no violence. Three women were also arrested. The Molestation and Boycotting Ordinance was applied to Nagpur district, and when picketing started 145 arrests were made. Picketing has-since been of a sporadic and half-hearted nature in Jubbulpore. Four principal Congress leaders were arrested while holding a seditious meeting, and the meeting was dispersed with polo canes. Since then there has been practically no Congress activity in the Central Provinces. The Mahakoshal Congress Committee and War Council and the Naujavan Bharat Sabha have been declared unlawful, and Unlawful Association and Molestation Ordinances have been applied to the Jubbulpore district. In Saugor, a meeting held after Gandhi&apos;s arrest wras banned and dispersed by force,, slight injuries being caused to 28 persons. The Molestation Ordinance was applied to the district in Chhattiagarh Division. The Kisan Sabha which was to have been held at Raipur dwindled into an ordinary public meeting, and the movement has not started. The Molestation Ordinance was applied to Raipur and Bilaspur districts. In Berar, the leaders have been cautions up to date, but four lesser lights have been prosecuted for making objectionable speeches inciting to civil disobedience or violence. Aney has, however, just issued a call to the Beraris to join the movement. The Berar Congress Committee has been declared unlawful and the Unlawful x\association Ordinance has been applied to the whole of Berar. The Molestation Ordinance has also been applied &apos;to the Buldina district. So far no public enthusiasm has been shown for the renewal of civil disobedience, and movement has made little headway.Assam.Hitherto Assam has remained quiet. Meetings held in Sylhet district to secure volunteers have meet with little apparent success. A report received from Goalpara district indicates that picketing may be resumed there. The Governor is going there on tour to-day. The Prevention of Molestation and Boycott Ordinance has been extended to the whole Province.Telegram from Government of India, Home Depatrment, to Secretary of State for India, dated 17th January 1932.Delhi reports slight Congress activity, mainly in picketing, but an absence of popular enthusiasm or excitement. Further efforts by Congress are, however,, anticipated.
2. The DomiriioDS apijreciation, which was sent yesterday, gives a general survey.0 3. Provincial reports are very satisfactory as showing the great initial success of the action taken.   The following features are particularly reassuring : (a) The small activity in most Provinces, e.g. Madras, Punjab, Bihar and Orissa, Bengal, Central Provinces, and Assam.(b) General absence of trouble in the rural areas except in the North-West Frontier Province.(r,) Control of the situation in Bombay city and the lukewarm support of Congress in the rest of the Presidency.(d) Failure of no-rent campaign in the United Provinces. Definite tendency for the situation to settle down in the large towns of Provinces.(e) Improvement in the North-West Frontier Province, where, however, it is still necessary to make many arrests, and disaffection tends to revive in some centres.   This was to be expected as Red Shirt movement was strong.4. Situation generally is much better than might have been expected, but the cautions contained in Dominions appreciation&apos;5&apos; hold good.Burma.Surrenders continue satisfactorily, particularly in Prome district. In Henzada, Anti, the most important leader, has been shot dead. Reports from Zigon sub-division show that there was an attempt by one or two absconding leaders to organise rising in a number of villages. Immediate steps were taken by local officers and a number of arrests effected which have prevented an outbreak. Important crime shows slight decrease from previous fortnight. No Government casualties reported. Twenty-two under-trials were released and number remaining in custody is 567. Latest reports show exportable surplus of rice likely to be considerably less than wTas expected, owing to failure of late rains. Price of paddy has risen very slightly ; price of cotton, sesamum and groundnut in Upper Burma has risen considerably. Paddy is being brought to mills with unusual rapidity after harvest, probably owing to shortage of cash in villages. K-[* This will be circulated as a separate paper.]

</content>
</cab>
