<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/19/32 images: 354-371</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNMENTSECRET Copy No.W.P. (41) 259(Also G.O.S. (41) 661)November 6, 1941TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may*be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 114)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 October 30th, to0700 November 6th,1941[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War Boom
naval SITUATION.General Review.t.   A French convoy has been intercepted south of Durban. ;jShipping losses have been moderate.A German supply ship has been intercepted by United States warships inthe South Atlantic.There has been a marked increase in the number of U-boats at sea.North Atlantic.2. The United States destroyer Reuben James, escorting a homeward boundCanadian convoy, was torpedoed and sunk 600 miles west of Ireland on the31st October with considerable loss of life.The United States Fleet Oiler Salinas, in an outward convoy from the UnitedKingdom, was hit by two torpedoes 600 miles east Of Newfoundland on the 30th,but succeeded in reaching St. Jdhn&apos;s.Home Waters.3. A large enemy merchant ship, steering to the westward with an escortof patrol craft and R-boats, was intercepted off Cape Gris Nez during the night of the 3rd/4th by a force of motor torpedo-boats and motor gunboats. The ship was hit by two torpedoes and either sank or was beached. Two motor gunboatssuffered damage and casualties in an engagement with the escorting craft.It is estimated that 14,000 tons of enemy shipping have been sunk and86,000 tons damaged by our aircraft.   Details are given under Air Situation.Mediterranean.4. H.M. Submarine Thunderbolt sank a caique on the 10th October 30 miles .W. of Casso Island (east of Crete). On the 25th HM. Submarine Trusty sank one of two escorted merdhant ships, of 5,000 tons, west of Cephalonia.H.M. Submarine Tetrach is overdue and is presumed lost.The Admiralty have made special acknowledgment of the valuable services rendered by the four destroyers of the Royal Australian Navy in theMediterranean.During the week nine French merchant vessels (23,432 tons) westbound and four (12,456 tons) eastbound, have passed the Straits of Gibraltar under escort.South Atlantic.5. A French convoy from Madagascar, escorted by the sloop D&apos; Irberville,was intercepted, 450 miles south of Durban, on the 2nd November by a cruiserforce working with the South African Seaward Defence Force and the SouthAfrican Air Force. The convoy consisted of the Commandant Dorise (5,529 tons),Tourane (8,009 tons), Compiegne (9,986 tons), Bangkok (8,056 tons) and CapPadaran (8,009 tons).The D&apos;Irberville refused to order her convoy to proceed into Port Elizabethfor examination and, on boarding parties being sent, attempts at scuttlingwere made in three of the ships. Some damage was done, but all thevessels were able to proceed under escort with the exception of one ship, whichwas taken in tow. The D&quot;Irberville, after shadowing for some time, was last seensteering to the southward.A German supply ship was intercepted on the 6th by the United StatesCruiser Omaha and the United States destroyer Somers 660 miles north-east ofPernambuco.   The ship was damaged in an attempt at scuttling.Anti-Submarine Operations.6. There have been thirteen attacks on U-boats during the week; eight ofthese took place in the Western and three in the Eastern Atlantic, one south-west of Dakar and one north of Tobruk.
H.M. Sloop Gorleston and ELM. Corvette Verbena reported the probabledestruction of a U-boat west of Ushant, and H.M. Canadian Corvette Buctonchealso made a promising attack east of the Belle Isle Straits. United states destroyers attacked a contact south-east of Newfoundland.Hits were claimed in three of the seven attacks carried out by aircraft;one attack by a Hudson to the south-west of Ushant was very promising.Enemy Intelligence.U-Boats.7. More than forty U-boats have been operating during the week. Themajority have been reported well out in the Atlantic; there has been practi-cally no activity in home waters. Several U-boats were working to the east ofBelle Isle, and another group was reported to the south-eastward of Newfound-land.There have been few reports of U-boats in the area west of Gibraltar or between the Azores and Freetown.Enemy Attack on Seaborne Trade.8. U-boats, in a two-day attack on a homeward-bound convoy, sank fiveships to the eastward of the Belle Isle Strait.One ship sailing independently was sunk, possibly by a U-boat, to the west-ward of Walfish Bay, South-West Africa, and a ship in an outward convoy was torpedoed and sunk west of Ireland.Aircraft attacks resulted in five ships being sunk and three damaged off theEast Coast, a trawler sunk near Cork, and one ship damaged in the bristol channel. Shipping in the entrance to the Suez Canal was ineffectively bombedon the night of the 3rd/4th.Three small craft were sunk by mine in home waters, two of which were inthe Bristol Channel and one in the Thames Estuary.Protection of Seaborne Trade.9. During the week ending the 5th November 947 ships, including 167 allied and 35 neutral, were convoyed. British warships employed on escort dutiesincluded two cruisers, five anti-aircraft ships, six armed merchant cruisers and&apos; ocean boarding vessels, 75 destroyers and 107 sloops, corvettes and minesweepers.United States warships on escort duties included one battleship, one aircraft-carrier, two cruisers and 39 destroyers.Imports into Great Britain by ships in convoy during the week ending the1st November totalled 785,295 tons compared with an average of 953,082 tons during the past ten weeks. Oil imports were 312,151 tons. Mineral imports were 185,495 tons, of which 126,634 tons were steel, scrap iron, pig iron andiron ore. Wood and pulp imports were 19,194 tons, copra 6,741 tons and cereals72,675 tons. Other food imports were 108,439 tons, of which the principalcommodities, in tons, were sugar 37,762, refrigerated and tinned meats, bacon and ham 17,754, tea 6,792, evaporated milk 5,763, fruit 3,121, butter 3,005, lardand cooking fats 2,685, cheese 1,835. There were also 4,482 tons of unspecifiedtinned goods.   Tobacco imports were 5,741 tons.British Minelaying.10.   Mines have been laid during the week in the Faroe Islands area.Minelaying by aircraft was on a somewhat larger scale than of late, but was confined to the Baltic and off the German North Sea coast.Enemy Minelaying, British Minesweeping.11. Minelaying by enemy aircraft took place on three nights of the week,mainly over the Bristol Channel and Liverpool Bay. Minelaying was reportedoff the Tees area on one night.Six magnetic and! five acoustic mines have been destroyed during the week.The mine totals are : Magnetic 1,495; acoustic 1,148; moored 1,063.[23117] ^ b
Enemy Merchant Shipping.12. The Italian Tanker Tampico (4,958 tons) passed Istanbul on the 1stbound for Trieste and the Italian Tanker Torcello (3,336 tons), bound for the black Sea from the ^aegean, called at Istanbul on the 2nd.The Norwegian Rogaland (902 tons) was mined in Oslo harbour about20th September and was beached.According to a Danish broadcast, the Danish motor ship Stockholm (28,000tons), which has been building in Italy, has been sold to the Italians.Russian Intelligence.13. It is reported that the new heavy cruiser VorosMlov (12,000 tons,nine 7 - 1-inch) was damaged by bombs at Novorossisk during the past week.On 3rd November a Russian submarine sank a Turkish caique off Media.There appears to be considerable traffic in small coastal craft from Turkey bythe west coast of the Black Sea to Bulgaria.The damage done by Russian air attacks in August to the Cernavoda Bridgeis still not fully repaired and in consequence the port of Constanza is cut off from the main railway system.Vichy French Intelligence.   .14. A Vichy French submarine arrived at Jibuti from Saigon on the28th October.   It is reported that more are expected.MILITARY SITUATION.(An outline map showing Axis operations against Russia is included in this resume as an inset.)Russo-German Campaign.Finland.15. There has been little change in the situation. No advance is believed to have been made by German or Finnish forces on the Murmansk front, in spiteof Finnish claims to the contrary. Further south, the Finns now hold the railway from Petrozavodsk to the northern corner of Lake Onega. This gain will onlyassume strategical importance if it is extended northwards to the railway junctionat Byelomorsk on the White Sea, whence a railway now runs to Archangel.Leningrad Sector.16. German forces have made progress north-eastwards from the bridgeheadover the River Volkhov in the direction of the railway Leningrad-Vologda.Kalinin Area.17. The situation remains unchanged. Russian counter-attacks are stillpreventing any further advance by the Germans.Central Sector.18. Apart from very slight progress near Wolokolamsk and Narofominsk,the Germans have not improved their position immediately west and south-west of Moscow.A German armoured thrust has made considerable progress in the directionof Tula, but, though now seriously threatened for several days, this importantmanufacturing town and railway junction remains in Russian hands.The position in the Mtsensk area is unchanged, but further south theGermans have advanced towards Kursk, and their recent official claim to have captured the town may well be true.Ukraine.19. The Germans have advanced eastwards from Byelgorod and Kharkovto the line of the River Donetz. Between Kharkov and the region north of Stalino
the position is obscure, but Axis forces are believed to have made progress towardsthe. River Ponetz, Thus the industrial basin of the Donetz. is virtually inGerman hands.Rostov Sector.20. Strong Russian resistance has prevented any advance by the Germans,who are still some 10 miles west of the town.Crimea.21. After the break-through at the Yushun Isthmus, German progressacross the Crimea has been rapid. The Germans claim to have captured the port of Feodosia, some 65.miles west of the Kerch Strait. Further west, the town of Bakhchisarai, half way between Simferopol and Sewastopool, is in german hands.Conclusions.22. Russian resistance and bad weather, with its attendant maintenancedifficulties, have prevented any serious deterioration of the situation, with theexception of the threat to Tula and the German break-through into the Crimea.The Crimean situation has two serious aspects. First, a successful crossing-of the Kerch Strait, especially if it coincided with the capture of Rostov,would appreciably increase the menace to the Caucasus; secondly, the advance onSevastopool threatens to deprive the Russians of their only effective naval base in the Black Sea. Little is known of the position at Sevastopool, but the success-ful defence of the port, for a time at least, by the Russian forces withdrawn inthat direction is regarded as possible.Operations.Libya and Egypt.23. There has been the usual considerable activity by our patrols in theTobruk and Frontier areas in which it may generally be said that we had theadvantage of the enemy.East A frica.Northern A byssinta.24. Our patrols have been active in the Volaich area (N.E.. of Gondar),where recent bombing is reliably reported to have caused casualties to the enemy.Patriot forces continue to harass the enemy all round Gondar, and they have beenjoined by three more Kamant chiefs from the Ambazzo area (8 miles North ofGondar). It has been reported that in accordance with our demands the Emperorhas ordered Ras Seyyum, Governor of the Tigre province, who has been detained in Addis Ababa, to return.Southern Abyssinia..25. The situation in the Galla Sidamo province remains; unsettled. TheEmperor&apos;s representative, whose conduct gave- rise to the unrest, has not yet been removed and murders and raiding have continued. .Persia and Iraq.26.   Further reinforcements have arrived from the United Kingdom.Intelligence.Germany.27. There has been a revival during the week of rumours of peace-feelers.These rumours are doubtless being spread with the usual purpose of testing ourreactions.[23117] b 2
Indo-China&apos;.28. Reliable reports indicate that approximately 20,000 Japanese troops have recently arrived in Tongking and that a small number of troops are being dispatched from South to North Indo-China. This brings the total number of japanese forces in Tongking to approximately one and a half divisions (30,000)whilst the number in the South is approximately one division plus ancillary troops(26,000).29. The Japanese force immediately available for an operation againstKunming is approximately one and a half divisions from Tongking. In addition,it is estimated the Japanese have available in the south for future operations two divisions from Formosa, one division from Hainan and one division from Canton.These probably include one division (20,000) which is reported to be arriving in indo-China shortly. In Yunnan the Chinese have at present approximately 15divisions (2 Chinese divisions are equivalent numerically to 1 Japanese division).Some of the best Chinese troops are in this area, and it is probable that they couldbe reinforced shortly by further troops from Kwangsi and Kweichow. TheChinese weakness would be in artillery and in the air, though it is probablethat they will soon have available a small number of pilots and machines of theinternational air force at present arriving in Burma. Such a force would atpresent have little effect on Japanese air superiority.AIR SITUATION.General Review.30. Operations by Bomber Command were again hampered by bad weather.Fighter Command made successful sweeps against military objectives in northern france. Extensive and effective anti-shipping operations were carried out by coastal Command.Enemy activity against this country remained at a low level.Germany and Occupied Territory.Day.31. Bomber Command despatched 32 sorties, compared with 48 last week.Fighter Command flew 449 sorties in the course of offensive operations overoccupied territory and against coastal shipping. Attacks on shipping areincluded in the &apos;&apos; Coastal Operations &apos;&apos; Section.32. Hurricane bombers claim to have destroyed a transformer station atTingry, near Boulogne, and to have scored hits on another at Holaue, nearGravelines.33. Our fighters carried out a number of low-level cannon and machine-gun attacks on objectives in Northern France. A large building was wreckedat Joburg wireless station, near Cherbourg, and an extensive fire was caused atan oil refinery at Bricquebec, in the same area. During other sorties over theCherbourg peninsula and elsewhere, 14 locomotives were destroyed or severely damaged and a number of railway waggons were left burning or otherwisecrippled. Determined attacks were also made on a variety of other targets,including factories, warehouses, motor lorries, troops, army huts, aerodromehangars, ammunition dumps and gun-posts.34. German defensive activity was on a restricted scale and few combatstook place during the week.Night.35. Bomber Command despatched 580 sorties, compared with 473 last week.Totals of 456 tons of H.E. bombs and 35,750 incendiaries were dropped. attacks were concentrated against dockyards in North-Western Germany and onChannel ports.
On two nights, operations were cancelled owing to the weather, and, onthe remaining nights, few results were reported owing to bad visibility whichpersisted throughout the period under review.36. The heaviest effort of the week was directed against Hamburg and Kiel :83 tons of H.E. bombs (including four 4,000 pounders) and 9,500 incendiaries were dropped in the first-named area, and 67 tons of H.E. bombs and 7,000incendiaries in the latter.37. Raids on a lighter scale were carried out on Bremen and Essen, and onthe Channel ports of Dunkirk, Havre, Ostend, Boulogne and the naval bases ofBrest and St. Nazaire.United Kingdom.38.   Fighter Command flew 2,076 sorties by day and 597 sorties by night.39. The scale of effort of the German Air Force remained on a low level.During daylight few aircraft crossed the coasts and no bombs were dropped.40. Enemy offensive operations by night were mainly directed against shipping. On the lst/2nd November, however, dispersed raids were made over-land, with the Merseyside area as the main objective. Between 50 and 60 Long-Range Bombers were employed, and six aircraft were shot down, five by nightfighters.Coastal Operations.41. Coastal Command flew 231 patrols (452 sorties) and provided 47 convoy escorts (86 additional sorties). Shipping protection patrols by Fighter Commandtotalled 593 (1,340 sorties).42. Aircraft of the three Commands harassed enemy shipping both by day and at night. Particularly outstanding results were obtained on the night of the31st October/1st November, when aircraft of Coastal Command reported hits on12 ships totalling approximately 40,000 tons. These consisted of a tanker and six merchant vessels (including the Reichenfels-^-1,800 tons claimed as sunk)off the Frisian Islands and four merchant vessels and a Flax-ship off theNorwegian coast.   In these operations we lost only one aircraft.43. On other occasions attacks with bombs, cannon or machine-gun fire weremade on 19 ships of an estimated total tonnage of 60,000, details of which are setout below : 	Estimated. Tonnage.	Locality.	Details.Merchant Vessel ... Merchant Vessel in convoy Reporting Vessel... Three barges Merchant Vessel ... Merchant Vessel ... Merchant Vessel ... Merchant Vessel ... Merchant Vessel ... Merchant Vessel ...       ...... Tanker Motor ship          ...       ...... E-Boat     ............ B-Boat    ............ Merchant Vessel in convoy A Vessel  ... Merchant Vessel......       ... Merchant Vessel in convoy Escort Vessel (? Destroyer)	200 4,000 360 6,000 6,000 5,000 3,000 1,200 1,500 7,000 400 8,500 800 5,500 6,500	Off Norway Off Frisian Islands Off Frisian Islands In canal near Gravelines Off Frisian Islands Off Frisian Islands Off Frisian Islands Off Frisian Islands In Sogne Fjord   ... Off Frisian Islands        ... Off Frisian Islands Off Cherbourg Off Cherbourg Near Sark... Off Frisian Islands Boulogne Harbour Off Frisian Islands Off Frisian Islands Off Frisian Islands	Bombs straddled. Hit near mast. Hit on stern. Destroyed. 2 hits ; believed sunk. 1 hit. Damaged. 1 hit. Fire on stern. Hit amidships. 1 or more hits. Hits on waterline list-ing. Hit and left listing. Hits and left listing. 1 hit. Hit. 1 or more hits. Near misses: fire seen. Explosion seen: all Flak from ship ceased.
44. In these operations three, Fighters and three Bombers were lost. Inaddition, a number of other promising attacks on shipping were made, butresults were less positive.45. Aircraft of Coastal Command attacked Norwegian Fish Oil Refinerieson Floro and Bergso Islands, where considerable damage was caused to oilcontainers and buildings. A W/T station on Frolen Island was bombed and seton fire.46. Eighty-five aircraft were despatched to lay sea mines off the frisian islands and Kiel Harbour, in the Baltic Sound, and the Jade and Weser rivers.47. Our shipping was attacked by day in the Faroes and off Aberdeen,Spurn Point and Harwich. At night three shipping attacks occurred-off east anglia, in Yarmouth Roads and off Aberdeen. Minelaying was suspected in the bristol Channel, St. David&apos;s Head, Cardigan Bay and St. Alban&apos;s Head areas.48. Operations of a routine character over the North Sea and Atlantic by enemy aircraft of the Condor unit took place on six days and on two occasionsthis activity was continued into the night.Central Mediterranean.49. Offensive operations against objectives in Italy, Sicily and Libya have continued.50. On the night of the 31st October/1st November eight Wellingtonsattacked Naples, and were over the town for more than six hours; one 4,000-lb.bomb was seen to hit the torpedo factory, while other bombs fell on or near therailway station and on an airframe factory. At the same time six Wellingtonsbombed Palermo and hit the main power station, as well as other targets. Thefollowing night two Wellingtons repeated the attack,51. Nine Blenheims carried out a successful daylight raid on a factory atLicata (Sicily). Fighters carried out a number of sweeps over Sicily and attacked trains, M.T. and other fleeting targets; three Hurricanes bombed a campnear Cape Passero, and a bridge.52. Two very successful night attacks were made on Castel Benitoaerodrome (south of Tripoli (L)) by a total of 40 Wellingtons from Malta. Atleast 12 aircraft on the ground were set on fire, and workshops, administrativebuildings and ammunition dumps were hit. In addition, two petrol tanks were destroyed and fires were started in hangars and buildings. One C.R. 42 was shot down and one Wellington is missing.53. Reconnaissance aircraft reported a number of enemy shipping convoys,some of which were later attacked. A convoy west of Apollonia was intercepted by four Wellingtons, and six hits were made on a merchant vessels of 6,000 tons.Blenheims made one hit on the stern of a vessel of 3,000 tons in convoy N.E. ofMelita, and attacked and damaged the aircraft escorting the convoy. West ofBenghazi, two merchant vessels of 3,000 tons, escorted by a destroyer, were attacked both by day and by night, and one vessel was hit six times and leftsinking.   Two Blenheims were shot down by A.A. fire.54. There were no offensive operations against Malta, by day. Four enenrybombers attacked the island by night, causing a number of Service and civilian casualties; one of these bombers was shot down by Hurricanes. Two nightslater five out of thirteen enemy aircraft made landfalls, but all their bombs dropped into the sea.There were no offensive operations against Malta by day.Eastern Mediterranean.55, A marked feature of the week&apos;s operations has been a series of bombing attacks by day and night on enemy landing grounds and supply dumps.56. Berca was heavily attacked on three occasions by Wellingtons andMarylands, hits being scored on hangars, barracks, workshops and dumps.El Gazala was bombed twice, and repair-shops and dumps were hit.   Derna
harbour and aerodrome was bombed in daylight by nine mary lands. A fire was started in the dock area, and many bombs burst on the Mole and among dispersedaircraft, four of which were destroyed. Other targets attacked included a barrackblock near Benghazi which was destroyed, and supply dumps at Benghazi, Bininaand Gambut.57. Twelve Wellingtons were detailed to attack shipping off Crete; a freightship in Suda Bay was hit, another was straddled, and a ship at Heraklion was bombed, but clouds obscured results. From this operation two Wellingtons are missing.58. Four Blenheim fighters made a cannon attack on M.T. on the mainJedabaya road, during which two petrol tankers and eighteen lorries were hit and about fifty personnel were machine-gunned.59. Reconnaissances were made of the shipping routes to Libya, south ofCrete, and Southern Greece and of Eastern Cyrenaica. Tactical reconnaissancesof the enemy dispositions in the frontier area were carried out by Hurricanes. on one occasion eight Me. 109&apos;s were encountered over Sollum, and one was destroyed and another damaged.60. Enemy activity has been on a very small scale and even Tobruk has hadless than its usual share of bombs. Two small attacks were made in theAlexandria area but no damage of any importance was caused. On the night of 3rd/4th November ten enemy aircraft bombed landing-grounds in the Fukaarea, and four Blenheims and five Hurricanes were damaged.61. The absence of any determined attempt to interfere with shipping inthe Red Sea and Suez Canal areas for some considerable time is thought to be largely clue to the fact that long-range bombers and coastal units based in greece and Crete are pre-occupied with attempts to protect Axis shipping in theMediterranean by means of anti-submarine patrols.Russia.German Air Force Operations against Russia.62. The City of Moscow and the lines of communication leading to it havebeen the main objectives of long-range bombers which have operated extensivelyat night, although there is no indication that the raids have at any timeapproached an intensive scale. Leningrad has also been raided at night, butthe air situation there generally remains quiet. Operations by close-support unitscontinue to be restricted by boggy aerodromes, but conditions are likely to improveas soon as the frost has set in.63. In the south, air operations have been directed mainly against the crimea, where important progress has been made, and against shipping and ports on the Sea of Azov. If the Germans succeed in occupying the Crimea, long-range bombers from there would be within range of Batum and all ports on the easternshore of the Black Sea; they could also cover the whole of the Caucasus. Hitherto,however, it has been a noticeable feature of German Air Force operations inRussia that long-range bombers have been mainly employed against communica-tions and Russian ground force in direct support of military operations, ratherthan against targets more remote from the immediate battle zone.Withdrawal of Russian Air Units from Far East.64. Three Air Divisions which have been operating on the Western RussiaFront were amongst those which were believed to be stationed in Trans-Baikaland the Far East before the 22nd June. This represents the move of some450 aircraft.65. It is thought that the number remaining in the East, including thoseof the Naval Air Service, is probably not less than 1,250 aircraft, but precise information is not available.
HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.66. During daylight no bombs fell on land, but on the afternoon of the1st November Dover was shelled from the French coast. Some houses were damaged and 1 civilian was killed.On the night of the lst/2nd November considerably more bombs were droppedthan of late; while these were widely scattered the majority fell on Merseysideand on Deeside (Cheshire).Apart from this, night bombing was confined to a few incidents chiefly in coastal Areas.Damage.67. At Birkenhead on the night of lst/2nd November Johnson&apos;s Flour Millwas demolished and substantial damage at the works of the New VittoriaEngineering Company will entail some loss of production.On the same night, the Shell Mex and B.P. Company&apos;s premises at Stanlow,Ellesmore Port, were considerably damaged. There was also some damage to therailway line, rail tank cars and a tanker in the dock area.Elsewhere except for slight interference with railway and utility services,damage has been confined to private property, the most extensive being atBebington and Worthing.Casualties.68. Casualties for the week ending 0600 p&apos;.m., 5th November, are estimatedat 14 killed and 16 seriously injured.
APPENDICES I, II and iii will be published monthly.APPENDIX IY.Merchant Ships (all sizes) lost by the enemy up to 3rd November, 1941.--	German.		Italian.		Finnish.		Together.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.Captured or seized Scuttled or sunk  ... Unidentified ships reported by S/M, A/C, &amp;c, as sunk or destroyed (tonnage estimated) Total      ......	67 138 414	307,000 734,000 1,656,000	47 146 179	223,000 &apos; 607,000 985,000	13 3	36,000 9,000	127 287 593	566,000 1,350,000 2,641,000	619	2,697,000	372	1,815,000	16	45,000	1,007	4,557,000In addition, 94 ships of 191,000 gross tons under enemy control or useful to the enemy havebeen sunk.Also some 85 ships, totalling 483,000 gross tons, have been placed under protective custody in United States and South American ports to prevent sabotage by their crews. Some of this tonnage has been taken over and put into service by the United States and some by south american Republics.The losses of unidentified German ships include a number claimed by the Russians.APPENDIX Y.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.The following casualties have occurred to H.M. auxiliary vessels during theperiod under review : &apos;November 3. -A/P Vessel Ouzel blown up and sunk, presumably by mine, off Mablethorpe, Lincoln.   All hands lost.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : Officers : 7 killed; 10 missing; 1 prisoner of war.Ratings: 39 killed; 82 missing; 10 wounded.These figures include 5 officers and 60 ratings missing in H.M. CorvetteGladiolus.[23117]c
APPENDIX VI.Operational Aircraft Battle Casualties.0700 hours, Thursday,, 30th October, 1941, to 0700 hours, Thursday,6th November, 19M.Metropolitan Area.British. In the Air. On the Ground.Bombers...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 14Fighters.................. 10Coastal ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 8Total............ 32German.bombers fighters miscellaneous destroyed.7ProbablyDestroyed.4Total      ...... 7 4No account is taken of aircraft destroyed on ground.Damaged.122216British.Bombers...Fighters...Coastal ...TotalMiddle East.In the Air.7613On the Ground.German.Bombers ...Fighters ...miscellaneous destroyed.2ProbablyDestroyed.Damaged.11TotalnilProbablyItalian. Destroyed. Destroyed. Damaged.Bombers ...       ... &apos;    ...       ... fighters............ 2 1 1MiscellaneousTotal    ...... 3 1 1
Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports of damage have been received during the past week from Air Reconnaissance and Intelligence sources : Germany.Berlin. In the raid of the 2nd/3rd September bombs fell in the districts ofSchmargendorf and Neukolln and at the Vehrbelliner Platz near the GorlitzerStation, in the cattle yards, in the Alexander Platz and the Sophien Strasse. TheLessing theatre and adjacent buildings had windows and the greater part oftheir roofs destroyed. Heavy explosions (believed to be bombs) were observed inthe vicinity of Spandau Moabit and Siemenstadt, where a large fire was alsoseen. The afternoon press of the 3rd September announced the casualties as 52killed and 70 injured.Hamburg. On the 15th/16th September a machine-testing shed in theHowaldfs shipbuilding yard received a direct hit from a heavy bomb. about twenty engines for submarines that were in the shed awaiting test were rendereduseless.Frankfurt. In the raid of the 20th/21st September an army welfare depotwas severely damaged. The Air Force Works and Buildings Department was hit and a military equipment depot damaged.   Casualties were heavy.Hamborn. An informant who passed through in July states that it was apparent there had been a recent raid. The station was badly damaged and he saw fifty to sixty wagons, probably an ammunition train, and a locomotivecompletely destroyed. Rails were sticking up in the air and a considerablenumber of the tracks had been damaged.General. The Hamburger Fremdenblatt reports that 47 civilianswere killed in Hamburg in the raid on the night of the 26th/27th October.The Ostsee Zeittong of the 24th October contains a report of a correspondentsvisit to the NSV (comparable to our W.V.S.) kitchen in Stettin. One of the voluntary women assistants said to him : &quot; But you should have looked in here when we fed people who had beenwounded in air raids, then we had a really busy time! We had to cut up and serve as sandwiches 75 to 100 loaves daily. Ten women were continuallybusy in our kitchen. Altogther we served 3,700 dinners, 2,965 breakfasts and2,580 suppers.&quot;Italy.Naples. The petrol and oil depot which was hit on the night of the21st/22nd October was still burning 24 hours later. As a result of damage to the gas works there was no gas for two days, and a warehouse in the port containingmachinery was destroyed. On other nights a ship of 500 tons was damaged and houses near the royal palace destroyed or damaged. A sheet-iron works receiveda direct hit from a heavy bombb.Belgium.Ostend. Photographs taken on the 25th October disclosed the completedestruction of two buildings to the north of the Bassin Sas. A block of buildingsnear the barracks has also been demolished over a length of 75 ft.Sea-Mining.It is learnt that two further ships were mined off Oslo on the 7th September;one, a 2,000-ton vessel, was beached near Gronlien to the south-east of Oslo, theother, a small coastal passenger steamship, the Ragaland, sank.APPENDIX YII. 1 f 0
SECRETAXIS OPERATIONS AGAINST  U.S.S.R.showing approximate advances.legend approximate lines reached by Axis Forces:-29TH Sept27r.&quot; Oct.3 *&apos; Nov...Main thrusts of Axis Forces....Note--    It is emphasized that in the mobile warfare which has taken place up to date there can beno continuous front line.   The   lines   on   the map   therefore indicate only the approximate limits of advance of the foremost  troops.
AXIS OPERATIONS AGAINST  U.S.S.R.showing approximate advances.legend approximate lines reached by Axis Forces:-29TH Sent27r&quot; Oct3    Nov..Main thrusts of Axis Forces....Note:-    It is emphasized that in the mobile warfare which has taken place up to date there can beno continuous front line.   The   lines   on   the map   therefore indicate only the approximate limits of advance of the foremost  troops.SECRET




</content>
</cab>
