<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/80/0 images: 288-295</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(fljlS PnTiiMgNT IS THE PROPERTy Qg H*s BRITANNIC MAJESTY * S GOVERNMENT).COPY NO.CABINET    44 (54).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held in the Prime Minister&apos;room, House of Commons, on FRIDAY, 30th NOVEMBER, 1934,at 10.30 a.m.AGENDUM.UNEMPLOYMENT ASSISTANCE BOARD:    DRAFT REGULATIONS.(Reference Cabinet 40 (34) Conclusion 12).Report of Cabinet Committee.CP. 271 (34)    -    to be circulated.(Signed)    R. B. HOWORTH,Acting Secretary to the Cabinet,2-r-Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1. ,29th November, 1934.
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)T. COPY NO.CEi.CABINET    44 (54).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held inthe Prime Minister&apos;s Room, House of Commons,on FRIDAY, 50th NOVEMBER, 1954, at 10.30 a.m.PRESENT:The Right Hon. J. Ramsay MacDonald, :Prime Minister.      (in the Chair).L. 1Jlei Right Hon.&quot;-Stanley Baldwin, M.P. ,Lord President of the Council.he; Right Hon.\ Sir John Gilmour, Bt. , D.S.O. ,M.P. , Secretary of State for home Affairs.[he Right Hon.IThe Viscount Hailsham,Secretary of State for &quot;War.p; Right Hon.-J.H. Thomas, M.P. ,(Secretary of State for DominionfAf fairs.rtie Most Hon.IThe Marquess of Londonderry,[K.G., M.V.O. , Secretary of[State for Air.Right Hon.:Sir Edward Hilton-Young,G.B.E. , D.S.O., D.S.C. , M.P. ,Minister of Health.cunliffe- Right Hon.Sir Bolton Eyres Monsell,G.B.E., M.P. , First Lord ofthe Admiralty.Je Right Hon.&quot;waiter Elliot, M.C., M.P. ,Minister of Agriculture andI Fisheries.m Right Hon.fk W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P.,H First Commissioner of Works.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.The Viscount Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.C.S.I.,G.B.S., C.M.G., M.P., Secretaryof State for India.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.M.C., MVP.,, Secretary ofState for the Colonies.The Right Hon.Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.S.,C.M.G., M.P., Secretary ofState for Scotland.The Right Hon.&quot;Walter Runciman, M.P. ,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K.G. ,G.C.S..I., G.C.I.E., Presidentof. the Board of Education.The Right Hon.Oliver Stanley, M.C , M.P. ,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley &quot;Wood, M.P. ,Postmaster-General.R*B. Howorth, K.C.M.G., C.B.,  ..............    Acting Secretary,
1* uWRMPLOYMFNTllpISTANCF BO^RD.fjjfeft Regula-&quot; tions.[Previous&apos;$eferenee:Cabinet 40(54), Con-clusion 12.)In pursuance of the Conclusion mentioned inthe margin the Cabinet had before them the Report ofthe Committee on the Draft Regulations of the Unem-ployment Assistance Board (C.P.-271 (34)).   The Draft-Regulations, a copy of which was appended to theReport, had been prepared by the Board and submittedto the Minister of Labour in accordance with the relevant provisions of the Unemployment Assistance Act,1934,   They are designed to govern the assessment of need of applicants for allowances under the Unemploy-ment Assistance scheme which is to be brought initiallyinto operation on January 7, 1935, subject to theapproval by Parliament of the Regulations,to be expressed, by affirmative Resolutions of both Bouses.The Report of the Committee explained the nature,scope and. purpose of the scale of allowances set outin Regulation TV, and drew attention, inter alia, tothe adjustment for rent, which was an important feature of the scheme, and to the increased children&apos;s allow-ances payable under the Regulations,In.paragraph 10 of the Report the Committeeexamined the probable effect of the rent rule havingregard to the wide variation in rents in different parts of the country, and. indicated that the board would have to exercise their discretion widely indealing with (l)  exceptional!;; high rented areas, suchas London:    (2) the low rented rural areas:    and (5)transitional payment cases in low rented industrial areas .    In conclusion, the Committee submitted thefollowing recommendation to the Cabinet:-&quot;That, subject to the reservation setout below, the Regulations submittedby the Unemployment Assistance Boardand. annexed hereto, should be approved for presentation to Parliament underSection 52 of the Unemployment Assist-ance Act, 1934.&quot;
?3ie reservation above referred to was as follows&quot;The Chancellor of the Exchequer hasreserved for further consideration the question of the extra cost tothe Exchequer resulting from theoperation of the Regulations andwill report thereon to the Cabinet.&quot;As regards this reservation the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer reported to the Cabinet that he had originally estimated that the Exchequer would have tofind about  4,500,000 per annum for the relief of thecases taken over from the Public Assistance Committees.He had. also assumed in his estimate that the Unemploy-ment Assistance Hoard would have to pay out more inthe aggregate in respect of the &quot;transitional payment *cases than the recipients of transitional payments were now receiving.   This extra cost might amount to 8,500,000 per annum and, if added to the above-mentioned  4,500,000, made a total of  7,000,000 perannum.   He had regarded this large commitment with much anxiety, but had agreed to it in order to ease the passage of the Bill and to give the scheme a successful start.    Subsequently the Board had determined that further concessions were necessary.   The first ofthese was concerned with adjustment for rent, and was described in paragraphs 4 and 10 of the Committee1sReport.   This concession was estimated to cost  650,000in the first year, and if it should have to be extendedto public assistance cases a further  150,000 must beadded, making  800,000.   The second concession was set out in (e) of Part I of the scale under RegulationM,,   The reduction of 1/- there mentioned was to take effect in respect of each member of the household inexcess of five, instead of in excess of four as originally suggested.   This concession was estimated,to cost  700,000 in a full year.   After careful
consideration he, the Chancellor of the Exchequer,had reached the conclusion that, notwithstanding the gravity of the 19 35-36 financial position, he wouldnot be justified in inviting the Cabinet to rejectthese two concessions on financial grounds.   mheCabinet would, however, observe that the estimated total annual increased cost to the Exchequer of thescheme now amounted to  8,500,000.The Minister of Labour explained to the Cabinetin considerable detail the arrangements embodied inthe Board&apos;s draft Regulations.   In the course ofthis explanation he drew special attention to thefol1owing, amons other considerationsUnder the scale set out in Regulation IVa single person and a man and wife would suffer reductions as compared with thepresent position.   A majority of thenumber of persons who would sufferreductions under the scheme was inthis category.The large increase in the provision made for children.The manner in which the rent rxile would -operate in various cases was illustrated by examples, and the Importance of the concession in Regulation IV 2 (1)(b)emphasised.    The rent rule would necessitate an adjustment in the amountof the scale allowance, and in some lowrented industrial areas where it was thepractice of Local Authorities- to make noadjustment for rent there would bereductions in the amount of actualpayments. . &quot;The concession in RegulationTV 3 (l)(b) would ease the position,but if uniformity was to be securedthroughout the country a rent ruleseemed Inevitable,   mhe proposed rule would operate most severely in areas such as low rented industrial towns.^he proviso requiring a deduction in thecase of lat*ge households was, in the Board&apos;view, justifiable because the initial allow-ance provides for overheads ( fuel, lighting,etc.), the cost of which *oes not increaseproportionately with the si?,e of the family.The position in regard to the computation of available resources (Regulation V) and thefinal assessment of needs (Regulation VI)was explained, and particular attentiondrawn to the discretionary powers given to theBoard under the proviso to Regulation VI,
The general effect of the regulations would he to benefit a large number ofpersons now in receipt of transitional payments and out-relief.    On the otherhand, a large number of transitionalpayment cases will suffer reductions.The Board had done their best to minimizehardship, but had found it impracticable to devise a more favourable scale whichwould not be destructive of the principles on which the Act was based and. open to objection that under it assistance couldbe given in ordinary cases in excess ofwages .The Cabinet were warned by the Secretary of Statefor Dominion Affairs of the grave political implications-tions involved in the scheme, and of the kind of criticism which the Opposition would be certain toraise.   Cities like Glasgow% practically the wholeof the mining areas, and some industrial towns in theMidlands, would suffer reductions under the scheme.On the other hand, Lancashire, Newcastle and london would, on the whole, benefit by the scheme, which hadthe great merit, from the political point of view,that it abolished the Poor Law.   Moreover, much couldbe made of the fact that the Exchequer was findingan additional  8,500,000 per annum in aid of theable-bodied destitute.   It was imperative that verygreat care should be taken in the way the scheme was presented to Parliament and to the country.In the course of discussion general agreement was expressed with the view that much would depend on how the scheme was presented, and that features such asthe increased allowances for children should have an excellent effect on public opinion.   Moreover, therewould be very considerable public support for theprinciple of uniformity in administration on whichthe scheme was based.The Prime Minister suggested that public opinion would not be so much concerned with the actual way inwhich the money was to be distributed as with the
question whether the distribution in all the clrcum-stances was equitable and reasonable.    If the schemewas presented to the country in the right way it would,he thought, be regarded as a careful and valiantattempt to secure, so far as it was possible to do so,equal and equitable treatment for those concerned.He wished, however, that it had been possible to find some other basis of adjustment than the rent basis,as he felt that, speaking generally, rents were alreadytoo high and that this scheme would help to perpetuatehigh rents.    He agreed that the provision in RegulationTV 8 (1)(b) gave some elasticity to the system, and he hoped that this feature of the scheme would be emphasised-s ised.It was pointed out that, expressions such as &quot;child&quot;were not defined in the Regulations, and the question was asked whether an illegitimate child would, underthe Regulations, receive a, larger allowance than a legitimate child.   The Cabinet were informed thatit had been thought best to leave matters of this kind to the Hoard&apos;s instruotions.In the course of the discussion, stress was laid on the vital importance of keeping the Regulationssecret until the time for their publication arrived.Steps must be taken to ensure that there was nopremature leakage of the Regulations.There was general agreement that it would be very desirable that, in addition to issuing a White Paper,a broadcast address should be given, either by theMinister of labour or by the Chairman of the Unemploy-me nt As sis tance B oar d.A suggestion which met with general approval wasthat the Minister of Labour should be in a positionto inform the House of Commons of the intention ofthe Board in the treatment of various kinds of-resources which are not specifically referred to in
the Regulations, and also the manner in which theBoard will exercise their discretion in the treatmentof the balance of those sources of income which arealready specifically safeguarded to some extent in theRegulations.    mhe Minister undertook to write to theBoard on this matter.&quot;&quot;he Cabinet agreed  (a) ^o approve for presentation to Par 1 lament-under Section 52 of the Unemployment Assist-ance Act, 19 34, the Regulations of theUnemp1oyment Assistance Board in the formset out in the Appendix to 0.P.-271 (3-4),subject to the deletion of the square bracketson page 3 thereof:(b) To take note that the Prime Minister proposedto confer with the Parliamentary Secretaryto the Treasury with a view to the debate on the Affirmative Resolution in the Houseof Commons taking place as early as practi-cable, and in any event before the christmas recess:(c) That as soon as the date for the Debate hadbeen determined, the Minister of labour should arrange for the presentation of theWhite Paper, which should be published notmore than a week in advance of the Debate:(d) That the Minister of Labour should be at liberty to consult with such of his colleagues as he may think fit in regard to matters relating to the presentation of the Regula-tions to Par1iament:(e) That the Minister of Labour should confer with the Chairman of the Unemployment Assist-ance Board in regard to a broadcast addressbeing given at the time that the White paper was published:(f) That, pending their presentation to Parliament,every possible step must be taken to safeguard the secret character of the Regulations andto prevent any premature publication oftheir terms ,(WgTF:     On the conclusion of the Meeting the membersof the Cabinet handed to the Acting secretary the copies of CP.-271 (34) which had been circulated, to them on the previous evening.)Whitehall Gardens, S.&quot;&apos;.l,November 30^ 19 34.

</content>
</cab>
