<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/65/73 images: 724-729</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   May 1945.The circulation of this paper ha^ been strictly linjiteri.   It is issued\r the personal use of top SECRET. : X/ Copy No.W.P.&quot;(45) 323.23rd May, 1945.WAR CABINET.ADMIRALTY REQUIREMENTS FOR SHIPPING FOR THE FLEETTRAIN.Memorandum by First Lord of the Admiralty.1. At their meeting on the 26th January (War Cabinet (45) 11th Con-clusions) the War Cabinet deferred for two months consideration of my paper W.P. (45) 56 on the outstanding Admiralty requirements for shipping forthe Fleet Train.2. The allocation for which I then asked was eighteen large ships(7,000 g.r.t. each) and thirteen smaller ships (3,000 g.r.t. each). As I then stated,this calculation assumed that the voyage between the rear and the advanced basewould average 2,000 miles and it made no allowance for losses. I pointed outthat as operations progressed we should undoubtedly need further ships.3. The situation has in fact developed a great deal since my earlier paper was prepared, and indeed it has been necessary to wait some little time to achievesufficient, though doubtless temporary, stability to justify the formulation ofrevised requirements. The principal changes in the interim which requirerevision of the requirements are as follows : (a) It is now clear that the voyage between the rear and the advanced basesmust be set at 4,000 miles. This automatically increases the numberof auxiliaries to keep the Fleet replenished without the necessity of bringing ships back too often for victualling, fuelling and arming.(b) As regards Armament Store Carriers and Armament Store Issuing Ships,we must budget Tor a considerably larger monthly expenditure ofammunition after July. The Commander-imChief, British PacificFleet, has put the monthly figure as high as 10,000 tons as opposed to2,500 tons assumed in the earlier calculation.(c) It is now clear that, unless the efficiency of His Majesty&apos;s Ships is to be jeopardised and the risk of having to restrict operations accepted,some margin must be allowed for losses and casualties among theauxiliaries. Even if they come off scathless from enemy action, whichis unlikely, casualties from other causes, and the necessity for regularrefits, are inevitable. A provident margin to allow would be 25 percent., but, in view of the general shipping situation, the Admiralty areprepared to try to make do with only 10 per cent., pending furtherexperience.4. The result of these inescapable factors is to increase the requirement to twenty large ships (7,000 g.r.t.) and twenty-five smaller ships (3,000 g.r.t.). the resulting total bid of cargo ships is analysed in Appendix &quot; A,&quot; and the dates bywhich the vessels are required on station are shown in Appendix &quot; B.&quot; This isbased on the build-up of the British Pacific Fleet expected to be achieved by december 1945, and&apos; the arrival of the Second and Third Assault Forces inS.E.A.C. by December 1945 and June 1946, respectively. I suggest that, in viewof the long time needed to provide distilling machinery, the requirement for fourDistilling Ships might be met by providing Clean Tankers, wdiich may become more readily available after the end of hostilities in Europe.[29944]
5. In addition to the above cargo vessels, the complete lack of accommodation in the forward area, and of labour to construct it at least for a long time,makes it essential to have one ship capable of accommodating 500 officers andmen at &quot; Manus &quot; or an alternative site, and one ship capable of accommodating1,000 at the intermediate base proper. These numbers are exclusive of SpecialDockyard Repair Ratings and Submarine personnel.6. I must now press the War Cabinet to approve, as a matter of urgency,the allocation of additional vessels in accordance with these revised requirements.Given the time lag between the approval of allocations and the arrival of theships on station, some of them are already bound to be late in relation to theschedule of operations. Further delay would affect our ability to conduct sus-tained operations and would make our operational programme much less intensethan it otherwise would be. The loss of fighting time entailed by having toincrease the frequency of voyages from the forward area to the rear base isobvious when it is remembered that in the Pacific a round trip of 8,000 miles isnow involved. Moreover, the Commanderdn-Chief, British Pacific Fleet, has reported within the last two weeks that his &apos; fleet must return to Sydney,4,000 miles in rear of his intermediate base, for lack of logistic facilities inadvance of Sydney. Unless the Fleet Train requirements are met, thiswithdrawal will have to be repeated every two months. The Admiralty have con-sidered the possibility of reducing the need for additional Fleet Auxiliaries by holding large stocks in the forward area. This alternative is impracticablebecause, unfortunately, there is no labour with which to build a forward basecapable of providing before the end of the year at the earliest more than aminimum of amenities for the Fleet and very limited storage. Even if this alternative were practicable, the smaller number of auxiliaries would be offset byan increase in ordinary freighting tonnage to take stores to the forward base.7. I need hardly call attention to the obvious risk that Americancriticism will be aroused if British Forces, and particularly the British PacificFleet, are not enabled to operate as intensively as the American Navy has shown itself capable of doing. The bid I am now making is the minimum requiredto guard against this risk. It is a good deal less than Admiral Fraser considersprovident: for purposes of comparison his calculations are also shown inAppendix &quot; A.&quot;8. I must also bring to the attention of the War Cabinet the lack of heavylifting facilities in the forward areas in S.E.A.C. and the Pacific wdiich willconsiderably handicap the Fleets when guns have to be changed or gun turretsplumbed. Discussions are taking place between the Admiralty and the Ministryof War Transport in order to decide whether floating cranes can be provided tomeet this very important requirement. I ask the War Cabinet to approve that,iii the event of it being impossible to find floating cranes, two crane ships shouldalso be allocated to the Fleet Train.9. As before, I am bound to add the warning that it is impossible to saythat this demand represents finality. The development of operations is unprecedented-dictable. The outlook is also obscured by the continuing uncertainty as to thescale and timing of reinforcements of constructional labour to build shorefacilities in the advanced areas, any ultimate deficit being remediable, if at all,only by the allocation of additional ships to meet the same purpose. Furthermoreit is possible that changes in the broad strategical layout of the Pacific theatresmay lead to inescapable increases in Fleet Train requirements. I can, however,assure the War Cabinet that the Admiralty will not put forward any furtherdemands which are not, in their view, essential for the fulfilment of the policies of His Majesty&apos;s Government and the maintenance of Imperial prestige.10. We are doing our utmost to speed up the release of ships wholly on admiralty service. Since January, the Admiralty has released the ocean-goingcargo vessel Latimer (10,200 d.w.t.) and Manchester City (8,591 d.w.t.) and theocean-going passenger vessel Hilary (6,200 d.w.t.). The future employment ofLatimer on Government service is under consideration. I anticipate that theocean-going cargo vessel Bancroft (10,200 d.w.t.) will have been returned by theend of April. The following sea-going coastwise vessels have also &apos; been released: Antwerp (741 d.w.t.), Corinthian (4,260 chw.t.), Royal Scotsman(900 d.w.t.), Stuart Prince (3,200 d.w.t.), and Princess A strict (659 d.w.t). Weshall continue to do all we can in this direction., 7  -   7 A. V. A.Admiralty, S.W. 1,23rd May. 1945.
APPENDIX &quot;A.Table of Fleet Train Requirements.Type of Ship.	Total required in Eastern Theatre as stated in W.P. (45) 56.	Revised Total Requirement in Eastern Theatre.	Number now available or allocated.	Balance required.	C-in-C, B.P.F.&apos;s Stated Total Requirements.naval Store Carriers Naval Store Issuing Ships Armament Store Carriers... Armament Store Issuing Ships  ... Air Store Issuing Ships   ... Victualling Store Issuing Ships ... Distilling Ships Dockyard Eatings Accommodation Ships Base Accommodation Ships	16 (6 S.E.A.C., 10 Pacific) &apos; 12 (5 S.E.A.C., 7 Pacific) 9 (3 S.E.A.C., 6 Pacific) 22 (9 S.E.A.C., 13 Pacific) 3 (1 S.E.A.C., 2 Pacific) 25 (17 S.E.A.C., 8 Pacific) 8 (7 S.E.A.C., 1 Pacific) 4 (1 S.E.A.C., 3 Pacific)	16 (8 S.E.A.C., 8 Pacific) 11 (6 S.E.A.C., 5 Pacific) 17 (3 S.E.A.C., 14 Pacific) 26 (10 S.E.A.C., 16 Pacific) 4 (0 S.E.A.C., 4 Pacific) 28 (18 S.E.A.C., 10 Pacific) 8 (6 S.E.A.C., 2 Pacific) 4 (1 S.E.A.C., 3 Pacific) 2 (0 S.E.A.C., 2 Pacific)	9 (4 S.E.A.C., 5 Pacific) 9 (4 S.E.A.C., 5 Pacific) 6 (3 S.E.A.C., 3 Pacific) 19 (9 S.E.A.C., 10 Pacific*) 2 (0 S.E.A.C., 2 Pacific) 17 (10 S.E.A.C., 7 Pacific) 4 (3 S.E.A.C., 1 Pacific) 3 (1 S.E.A.C., 2 Pacific)	7 (4 S.E.A.C., 3 Pacific) 2 (2 S.E.A.C., 0 Pacific) 11 (0 S.E.A.C., 11 Pacific) 7 (1 S.E.A.C., 6 Pacific) 2 (0 S E.A.C., 2 Pacific) 11 (8 S.E.A.C., 3 Pacific) 4 (3 S.E.A.C., 1 Pacific) 1 (0 S.E.A.C., 1 Pacific) 2 (0 S.E.A.C., 2 Pacific)	16 8 14 co 17 4 15 2 3 2* N.B.- 6 are over-age coal burners requiring replacement by oil burners.COto
APPENDIX &quot;B.&quot;Dates by which additional Fleet Train Vessels are Required on Station.	Victualling-Store Issuing Ships.		Naval Store Issuing Ships.		Naval Store Carriers.		Armament Store Issuing Ships.		Armament Store Carriers.		Air Store Issuing Ships.		Distilling Ships.		S.R.R. (D) Accommoda-tion Ships.		Base Accommoda-tion Ships.		Totals.	SEAC.	Pacific.	SEAC.	Pacific.	SEAC.	Pacific.	SEAC.	Pacific.	SEAC.	Pacific.	SEAC.	Pacific.	SEAC.	Pacific. SEAC.		Pacific.	SEAC.	Pacific.	Required  on   Station by July 1945 Required  on  Station by December 1945... Required   on   Station by June 1946	3 2 3	3	1 1		1 2 1	3	1	4 2		8 3		1 1	1 2	1		1		2	27 15 5 47 i



</content>
</cab>
