<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/44/0 images: 50-59</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1969CC (69) Copy No. 3 32nd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W:1, on Wednesday, 8th January, 1969,at 6.30 p.m., resuming on Thursday, 9th January, 1969,at 9 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, mp, Prime minister the Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,Secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Employment and productivity the Right Hon. Denis Healey, mp,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, mp, Minister of technology the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,mp, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. Lord Shackleton,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Roy Mason, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, mp,Chancellor of the Exchequer(9th January only)The Right Hon. Richard Crossman,mp, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. James Callaghan,m p, Secretary of State for the HomeDepartmentPeart, m p,the   council the Right Hon. FredLord   President   of(9th January only)The Right Hon. George Thomson,mp, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. George Thomas, mp,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Judith Hart, mp,Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. John Diamond, mp,Chief Secretary, treasury the following were also present:The Right Hon. Frederick Lee, mp,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. John Silkin, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury sir Arthur Irvine, q c, m p, Solicitor-General
Secretariat :Sir Burke Trend (9th January only)Miss J. J. nunn mr. R. R. D. mcintosh mr. P. E. ThorntonMiss S. W. FogartySubjectIndustrial AffairsPolicy for Industrial Relations: Draft White Paper
IndustrialAffairsPolicy forIndustrialRelations:Draft white paper(previous reference:CC (69) 1stConclusions,Minute 1)secret the Cabinet gave further consideration to the proposals inthe draft White Paper on Industrial Relations annexed to amemorandum by the First Secretary of State (C (68) 131). they also had before them further memoranda by the First Secretary ofState (C (69) 2 and 4) and the Paymaster General (C (69) 3), onaspects of the proposed policy, and by the Lord President (C (69) 1)on the timing of legislation.The First Secretary of State reported that she had that afternoon met representatives of the General Council of the TradesUnion Congress (TUC) to hear their views on the outline which she had given them of the proposals in the draft White Paper. she had earlier learnt that at the meeting on the previous day of theGeneral Council, a motion to oppose her proposals as a whole hadbeen withdrawn in favour of unanimous agreement on the more moderate written comments of the Council which she had circulated(C (69) 4). At her meeting the delegation had been unwilling to add substantively to the written comments which had evidentlybeen the outcome of a difficult negotiation. They had, however,made it clear that they would welcome early publication of a white paper.The First Secretary of State also reported that the ministerial committee on Industrial Relations had met twice. They had firstconsidered points of substance raised in the previous discussion inthe Cabinet and she had reported the outcome in C (69) 2; broadly,after considering the alternative approaches of the DonovanCommission, of Mr. Shonfield and of the CBI, the Committee had reached unanimous agreement on all the proposals in the white paper, subject to certain changes of emphasis in the drafting, except the conciliation pause in unconstitutional strikes to which asubstantial majority of the Committee agreed. At a later meetingthe Committee had examined the draft White Paper in detail, andredrafting to take account of their comments and those madepreviously was in progress.In discussion it was argued that the conciliation pause wouldbe unworkable and ineffective and that further examination was needed of the proposed procedure and of the difficulties whichwould arise. Even its presentational advantages would be lost whenthe public realised that it could not be invoked in the majority ofcases; there would be constant pressure to use the power, anddisillusionment when it was not employed. Moreover, the proposal would cause major difficulties with the trade unions and the labour movement. The former were holding back only because they regarded it as unworkable; and it must be recognised that their9794a 2
co-operation was essential in the manning of the Industrial Board.The procedure would take weeks to apply and there was a risk thatit would provoke a hardening of attitudes and increase the numberof strikes declared official. The Donovan Commission had recommended against such powers; the practical remedy lay in aspeedy reform of procedure agreements, and the Commission on industrial Relations (CIR) should concentrate at the start on themain trouble spots in industry.On the other hand it was argued that the conciliation pause was an essential part of the package of proposals. Unofficial strikeswere unpopular and many were extremely damaging to the economy. The strike ballot proposal would provide a reservepower in relation to only a very small proportion of strikes; much the more serious problem facing the country was the succession ofunconstitutional strikes especially those where small numbers ofworkers took advantage of the growing interdependence of industryto hold their employers, fellow workers and the community toransom. A considerable period must elapse before satisfactoryprocedure agreements could be negotiated and brought intooperation in the more troublesome sectors of industry, even if theCIR concentrated all its energies on them. Even if satisfactoryprocedure agreements were universally in operation, they would notcompletely put an end to unnecessary and damaging strikes. Theproposal was only to provide a reserve power which could be made effective quickly in appropriate cases, such as the recent Girlingstrike. The psychological effect of its existence and the threat ofits use were, however, expected to be even more important.Moreover, it would often operate to the benefit of the strikersbecause of the requirement that during the pause, the terms ofemployment should be those operating before the strike began. Itwould provide a spur to both management and workers to use tothe full the negotiating machinery which would have been institutedin agreement with the trade union. If the proposal became law,the TUC could be expected to co-operate. The proposal of the donovan Commission that the protection of Section 3 of the TradeDisputes Act, 1906, should be withdrawn from unofficial strikerswould be far more bitterly opposed, and rightly so not allunconstitutional strikes were unjustified. The choice lay betweenproviding only for the long-term improvement of procedure agreements (i.e., doing less than the Donovan Commission proposed and nothing about the immediate problem of unconstitutional strikes) and introducing the conciliation pause as well. The latter,with its imperfections and limitations, would prove effective in somecases. There were a considerable number of proposals in the white paper going beyond the Donovan Commission^ recommendations in strengthening the rights and powers of trade unions.  They, in
turn, might reasonably be asked to accept the conciliation pause,which affected only strikes begun where the agreed constitutional machinery had not been used. Moreover, opposition so far hadbeen muted; and polls of the public, of trade unionists and oftrade union M Ps had suggested that there was a substantial volumeof support for the proposal.In discussion of the timing of the White Paper, it was argued that it was essential to secure the maximum possible agreement withthe TUC and the Labour movement before the Government becamepublicly committed to proposals from which it would be difficultto withdraw at a later stage even if the TUC were able to providesatisfactory alternatives. The tuc&apos;s comments should be examined in detail and discussed further with them to see whether any concession could be made, for instance on the conciliation pause,to reduce the opposition which would otherwise build up over thenext few months. The proposals should also be discussed with theNational Executive Committee of the Labour Party and with theParliamentary Labour Party before final decisions were taken onthe content of the White Paper. On the other hand, it was suggestedthat it was essential to publish the White Paper to provide the basis for further consultations; it would be very unsatisfactory for public discussion to continue on the basis of Press accounts and without an authoritative public statement of the Governments proposals.The White Paper would, where appropriate, indicate that proposals were subject to further discussion. If the TUC put forward, beforethe Industrial Relations Bill was enacted, satisfactory proposals todeal with union registration, inter-union disputes, or unofficial strikes, the Government could certainly reconsider their own proposals in the new situation. But in the absence of firmGovernment proposals there was no prospect that the TUC wouldmake real progress with alternatives. Unless the White Paper were published very shortly, considerable difficulty could be expectedwhen Parliament reassembled.In further discussion the following points were made:(a) The proposal for strike ballots was more strongly opposed by the TUC in their written comments than was the conciliationpause, but ballots were already required by a number of unions.(b) The Ministerial Committee on Industrial Relations had discussed the implications for supplementary benefits of theproposals for enforcement and reached provisional agreement on thematter but the detailed position required further study.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that itappeared that a substantial majority of the Cabinet were in favour
of the proposals in the White Paper as a whole. A significantminority were, however, still opposed to the conciliation pause,partly because they feared that it would arouse strong oppositionamong the trade unions and in the Labour movement, and partly because they were doubtful whether it would be workable oreffective. There was some difference of opinion about whether theWhite Paper should be published immediately, in which case itwould provide the basis for consultation with such bodies asthe Parliamentary Labour Party and the National ExecutiveCommittee, or whether such consultation should take place beforethe Government were committed by the publication of a white paper. The Cabinet would resume their discussion on thefollowing day.The Cabinet-(1) Took note with approval of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister.In the resumed discussion on 9th January it was argued that,while making clear their determination to deal effectively withunofficial strikes, the Government need not at this stage commit themselves irrevocably to a particular method. It should be possibleto draft the White Paper in a form which would leave the way open for the Trades Union Congress (TUC) to come forward with alternative proposals which the Government could undertake toconsider seriously before introducing legislation. The point wasalso made that it was difficult to contemplate having legislation on industrial relations and on prices and incomes going through parliament simultaneously and that the trade unions and others concerned would not be slow to realise this. This could have serious consequences for the operation of prices and incomes policy thisyear and the form and timing of legislation on industrial relations should accordingly be examined further.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were not yet in a position to decide whether or not theWhite Paper should be published in the following week, but that inorder to keep this possibility open the text of the draft White paper should be sent for printing on the following day. The ministerial committee on Industrial Relations should meet this week to.examine further the points raised in the discussion. They should considerthe problems involved in enforcing the conciliation pause inparticular cases; the impact on individual strikers, including the implications for the payment of supplementary benefit and therefund of income tax; and the extent to which the CIR might beexpected to improve the arrangements for collective bargaining inkey industries in the next 18 months.   The Committee should
examine the text of the draft White Paper as revised in the light of earlier discussions. They should consider the possibility of including in it a reasoned statement of the Governmenfs views on the TUCscomments on the proposal for compulsory strike ballots; and whetherthe White Paper should state the Governmenfs willingness toexamine seriously any alternative proposals put forward by the TUCfor dealing with unconstitutional strikes and other disputed mattersor whether this could best be indicated in answer to queries from thePress. Further consideration would need to be given to the formand timing of the legislation on Industrial Relations; and to theposition of the Armed Forces, the Civil Service and other crown servants under the new legislation and to the form of words to beused on these matters in the White Paper or an accompanyingstatement. The Cabinet would meet to consider reports on all thesematters on Tuesday, 14th January, when they would also have beforethem a revised text of the draft White Paper.The Cabinet (2) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of this part of their discussion.(3) Invited the First Secretary of State (i) to arrange for the Committee on Industrial relations to examine further the points raised in thediscussion and to consider the text of the draft white Paper; and to report to the Cabinet at their meeting on 14th January; and(ii) to arrange for a revised text of the draft White paper to be printed and circulated to the Cabinet in timefor their meeting on 14th January.(4) Invited the Lord President, in consultation with theChancellor of the Exchequer and the First Secretary ofState, to give further consideration to the form and timing of the proposed legislation on Industrial Relations.(5) Invited the Lord Privy Seal, in consultation with the first secretary of State and the Secretary of State for defence, to consider further the form of words to be usedin the White Paper and in any accompanying statement on the position of the Armed Forces, the Civil Serviceand other Crown servants under the proposed legislation.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,9th January, 1969.




</content>
</cab>
