<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/44/0 images: 122-133</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1969CC^ Copy No.   QQ8th Conclusions 00CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 11th February, 1969at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,m p, Secretary of State for foreign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Employment and productivity the Right Hon. Denis Healey, m p,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Peter Shore,SecretaryAffairsm p,of   State   for   economic the Right Hon. William Ross, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Edward Short, m p,Secretary of State for Education and science the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. Lord Shackleton,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Roy Mason, m p,Minister of power the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. James Callaghan,m v, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Fred Peaut, m p,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. George Thomson,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, m p,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. George Thomas, m p,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Judith Hart, m p,Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. John Diamond, mp,&apos; Chief Secretary, TreasuryAlso present:The Right Hon. John Silkin, m p, Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury
Secretariat :Sir Burke trend miss J. J. nunn mr. R. R. D. mcintosh sir Robin hooper mr. P. E. ThorntonContentsSubjectParliamentary Affairs      ...............Future BusinessParliament (No. 2) BillPublic Expenditure..................White Paper on Public Expenditure in 1968-69, 1969-70and 1970-71Oversea Affairs   ..............&apos;.&apos;......Ministerial Meeting of the Western European Union inLuxembourgGermanyVietnamIndustrial Affairs..................inter-Union Dispute within the British Steel CorporationTeachers&apos; SalariesUnrest in the London DocksAgricultural Policy        ...............Farm Price Review 1969
confidential. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that at their meetingon 28th January the Ministerial Steering Committee on economic policy had agreed that he should publish a White Paper on20th February giving details of public expenditure in 1968-69,1969-70 and 1970-71. All the necessary policy decisions had beentaken but it would not be possible to complete the drafting of theWhite Paper until the end of this week. He would circulate the text not later than Monday, 17th February, for the information ofthe Cabinet and on the basis that if there were disagreement on a major point in the White Paper it could be considered by the cabinet or by the Ministerial Steering Committee on Economic Policy, as appropriate, before publication.The Cabinet Took note of the statement by the Chancellor of theExchequer.confidential. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.The Lord Chancellor said that the Ministerial Committee onthe House of Lords had considered points arising from the debate on the Second Reading of the Parliament (No. 2) Bill and had invited the Lord President and the Chief Whip to ascertain whetherthe Opposition would be interested in further discussion of thepossibility, mentioned by the Prime Minister and the Home secretary in their speeches, of resolving the differences between the Parties onthe question when the reform of the composition of the House ofLords should be introduced. The Committee had also commissioneda paper on the advantages and disadvantages of alternative ways of implementing changes in the composition of the House.In discussion the Cabinet were informed that the opposition had themselves indicated that they would be interested in informal discussion of possible changes in the proposals on the composition of the House of Lords. The Ministerial Committee would considerlater in the week what changes might be acceptable,The Prime Minister said that if the Ministerial Committee were unable to agree on the line to be taken in discussion with theOpposition, the matter should be brought before the Cabinet; if theywere in agreement, the Cabinet should be informed of the outcome of their discussion.
OverseaAffairsMinisterialMeeting of theWesternEuropeanUnion in luxembourg(previous reference:CC(68) 11thConclusions,Minute 2)secret. The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that our objective in the Western European Union (WEU) had been to seekco-operation, for as long as we were excluded from the european economic Community (e.c.), within the framework of the WEUwith the e.c. countries. The French were naturally opposed tothis. The other five members of WEU were anxious for us to beadmitted to the e.c. but the extent to which they were preparedto press our case in the face of French hostility varied from countryto country. However, when he had visited the German ForeignMinister, Herr Brandt, during the latter&apos;s recent convalescence inthe Black Forest, Herr Brandt had been considerably moreforthcoming than on previous occasions. After the previousMinisterial Meeting of the WEU in Rome, an informal meeting hadbeen held of all WEU members except the French, at which theItalian representative had been invited to prepare a paper on european co-operation. The Italians had come to Luxembourg witha considerable list of constructive proposals. On the first proposal,for regular consultations on foreign policy, all the WEU countriesexcept France had stated their firm intention of adopting this practice. The French had not yet rejected the proposal out of hand,but had said that they would give their views at the next council meeting in three months&apos; time. Meanwhile, the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary intended to do what he could to establish the habit of consultation so that when the French expressed theirnegative views the other WEU Powers would not weaken in theirresolve. With this in mind he intended to propose a consultation onMiddle Eastern affairs in preparation for the proposed meeting ofthe Security Council representatives of the four Powers (the UnitedKingdom, the United States, the Soviet Union and France). All thiswas something of a side issue in comparison with the main problemof British entry into the e.c.; but at least it established that ournot being members of that body did not exclude us from consultationwith those e.c. Powers which wished to consult with us, and thatthe e.c. was not the only forum for consultation. Moreover, itemphasised French isolation, of which the French were becoming increasingly conscious, and might also encourage the other membersof the e.c. to take a more robust attitude to the British applicationfor membership.Germany(previous reference:CC (68) 31stConclusions,Minute 3)The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that therestrictions which the East German authorities had placed on travelby land to Berlin by political personalities from the Federal Republicin connection with the Presidential Elections were similar to thosewhich had been imposed on previous occasions. They were unlikely to have much practical effect, since few of those involved would
Vietnam(previous reference:CC(69)7thConclusions,Minute 2)travel by road or rail anyway. Unless, therefore, there were somesudden and unprecedented change in East German policy, there didnot appear to be any major cause for anxiety.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that talks inParis between representatives of the United States Government andthe Government of South Vietnam on the one hand and representatives of the North Vietnamese and the National LiberationFront (NLF) on the other were still at the propaganda stage, withthe representatives-of North Vietnam and the NLF making speechesintended to make difficulties for the other side. He added that he agreed with the Home Secretary&apos;s decision to allow Madame Binh,Jhe Deputy Leader of the NLF delegation to the Paris talks, to cometo the United Kingdom for the Easter Rally of the Campaign for nuclear Disarmament (and). This would afford an opportunityfor testing the sincerity of the critics of the Governments policy inregard to Vietnam and of establishing publicly whether they were primarily concerned with furthering the interests of the North orwhether they really wanted peace in Vietnam. In this connection he hoped that the and would urge on Madame Binh a progressivede-escalation of the war, which North Vietnam and the NLF had sofar consistently opposed.The Cabinet Took note of the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary&apos;sstatements.IndustrialAffairsInter-UnionDisputewithin theBritishSteelCorporation(previous reference:CC (69) 5thConclusions,Minute 3)confidential. The First Secretary of State said that the Trades UnionCongress (TUC) had recommended that the British Steel corporation should confine recognition, up to and including middle management,to the six craft unions, thus reversing the findings of the court of inquiry under Lord Pearson which reported in August 1968. TUCleaders had made it clear informally that they regarded therecommendation as an important step towards industrial unionismand that they might be forced to discipline the two white-collarunions if they were unwilling to accept it.In discussion, attention was drawn to the growing importanceof technical and supervisory grades in industry generally, resultingfrom the spread of automation. It might be worth instituting an enquiry into the problems arising from this development and inparticular its implications for the relationship between the oldercraft unions and the new unions representing supervisory staff,9935a 3
Teachers&apos;Salaries(previous reference:CC (69) 5thConclusions,Minute 4)The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that one ofthe main weaknesses of British industry was that middle managementwas less effective than in many other countries, including the UnitedStates and Japan. The case for instituting an enquiry, which shouldnot be related to the present dispute in the steel industry, into the role and status of foremen, middle management and othersupervisory staff should be further examined.The Cabinet (1) Invited the First Secretary of State to examine the case forinstituting an enquiry into the role and status of supervisory staff.The Secretary of State for Education and Science said that the burnham Committee had reached agreement on teachers&apos; salaries inEngland and Wales but that the National Association ofSchoolmasters had refused to accept the settlement and had decidedto work to rule. As a result some members of the Association hadbeen suspended, against his own advice, by the local authorities concerned. The Association had now threatened strike actioii.Their intention was presumably to try to influence the discussions at the forthcoming conference of the National Union of teachers and it seemed clear that no action could be taken to end the disputeuntil after that conference.The Cabinet (2) Took note of the statement by the Secretary of State for education and Science.Unrest inthe london docks(PreviousReferenceCC (67) 74thConclusions,Minute 1)The First Secretary of State said that, after sending warningletters to the men concerned, the employers had suspended thosedockers who had taken part in unofficial strike action in the RoyalDocks to support their claim for higher wages. She had warned the employers in advance that suspension would be pointless as themen could appeal to the National Dock Labour Board which was certain to take the line that suspension was not appropriate in casesof collective indiscipline. They had, however, decided to proceedand there had been further unofficial strike action as a result.Fortunately the unions had now advised the men to appeal to theBoard and it should be possible to avoid further stoppages. It wouldbe some time before the men&apos;s appeals were heard and in thetechnologists and junior management. On the other hand it was argued that to do anything which might lead to an extension of thepower of white-collar unions, most of whose members were juniorclerks and draughtsmen, would be a retrograde step and wouldimpede progress towards industrial unionism.
confidential. The Cabinet resumed their consideration of thememorandum by the Minister without Portfolio (C (69) 16) and also considered memoranda by the Chancellor of the Exchequer(C(69) 17) and the Minister of Agriculture (C (69) 18) about the farm Price Review 1969.The Minister of Agriculture said that his memorandum set outthe movements in farm output, income and costs over the five yearsof the present Administration. There would be an estimated 5-pointfall in the index of agricultural production between 1967-68 and1968-69 due to very adverse weather and other difficulties. Inconsequence, farmers would have made no gain from increased productivity in 1968-69 and their net income was expected to be 39 million lower than in the previous year. Thus the improvementwhich last year&apos;s award was intended to produce had not materialised,and farmers&apos; incomes this year had fallen far behind those of therest of the community. It was acknowledged that the record of theagricultural industry since the war had been an exceptionally goodone under the stimulus of agricultural support provided by theGovernment. The very substantial expansion in output had made a major contribution to our balance of payments and, in consequenceof rapidly increasing efficiency, had been combined with releases of manpower at the rate of 20,000 or more a year since 1945.Meanwhile the level of Government financial support had beenreduced in real terms. Farmers had however been left with a smallergrowth in real incomes than the rest of the community since the mid-1950s and the divergence had widened very sharply in thecurrent year. It had been argued that an award of  50 million would increase net farm income by  42 million, but it had to be borne in mind that there would be further cost increases in 1969-70additional to those identified for the purposes of the Review. the tables on page 3 of his memorandum indicated very clearly thatmeantime the employers would press ahead with implementing thesecond stage of the modernisation of the structure of dock workers&apos;pay-In discussion it was suggested that everything possible shouldbe done to ensure that ill-considered action on the part of theemployers did not provoke a stoppage in the docks which could have very damaging effects on the economy.The Cabinet (3) Took note of the statement by the First Secretary of State.
farm incomes were not comparable with wages and salaries. Evenon a large farm, the net income left to a farmer in 1967-68 didnot leave much over for investment. It was not possible to establishany precise statistical relationship between the size of the award and of the subsequent agricultural output, but if the award were insufficient to maintain farmers&apos; confidence there would certainly be stagnation. The award of  50 million for which he was askinghad been based on most careful judgment of all the factors involved and was in his opinion necessary to maintain confidence and obtainthe expansion of output, and consequent import saving, on whichthe Government had determined last November. He fully accepted that, once the farming industry was back on course, the farmers should bear out of their productivity gain a reasonable proportionof their increasing costs. It was relevant to their consideration thatin every year since 1964 the actual cost of agricultural support hadbeen substantially less than the estimate.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the Minister ofAgriculture in his memorandum had chosen 1964-65 as the baseyear; as that year had been an exceptionally favourable one, the picture in C (69) 18 of the development of output and income since1964-65 had been severely distorted. He thought perhaps the bestindication was given by the figures in Annex B of his ownmemorandum (particularly the three year moving average) whichhad also been circulated to the Agricultural Policy Committee andwhich showed a rising trend of both income and output between1964-65 and 1967-68. He believed that there were a number ofmisconceptions about the nature of net farm income. It was truethat it was not comparable with a wage or salary, but nor was thewhole of farm investment provided from it. The comparison ofthe incomes of farmers with those of others in the table inparagraph 11 of C (69) 18 was misleading in that the index of farmers&apos; income was calculated after provision for depreciation,whereas the indices of the incomes of other sole traders, professionalpersons and gross company profits were calculated before provisionfor depreciation. It had also to be borne in mind that the numberof farmers was decreasing by about 5,000 a year, so that theaggregate net farm income was shared out between fewer farmerseach year, the same did not apply to professional persons and othersole traders.It had been strongly emphasised by the Agricultural ministers that increased income was required next year in order to financeadditional investment. But the economic statistics provided for the review by the Agricultural Departments showed, inter alia, thatgross capital formation in agriculture between 1963 and 1968 had risen, at current prices, from  167 million to  205 million and hadnot varied from year to year according to income or climatic
conditions. Investment in plant, machinery and vehicles in 1968was, in fact, virtually equal to the depreciation provision which hadbeen deducted before estimating net farm income in 1968-69. Thus,the whole of this type of investment appeared to be financed out of provision for depreciation. Similarly, investment in buildings and works was allowed for in computation of gross rents which were also deducted in calculating net farm income. Investment which hadto be financed by farmers out of net income or borrowing was thuslimited to the increase in value of their crops and livestock. Thecontinually rising price of agricultural land an increase oftwo-and-a-half times in the last ten years did not suggest that farmers were disssatisfied with their return. As regards the expectedfall in farmers&apos; net income in 1968-69, it appeared from other information recently circulated by the Agricultural Departments thata moderate increase was expected in net income in Northern Irelandfrom all except mixed farms. Substantial increases were forecastfrom all except cropping farms in Scotland in 1968-69. In Englandand Wales, a fall in 1968-69 was forecast for dairy, cropping andmixed farms, but an increase was expected for livestock and specialistpig and poultry farms. The increase in income expected fromlivestock rearing throughout Great Britain was particularly relevant to the claims for special treatment for beef in the current Review.Any excessive generosity in the current Farm Review would reducethe contingency reserve for 1969-70 and greatly increase the risk ofa repetition this summer of the painful pruning of public expenditurerequired last summer. He considered that an award of  26 million would be generous.The Minister without Portfolio said that they should bear inmind that the selective expansion programme to 1972-73 had beenagreed on the basis of extensive groundwork by officials andeconomic advisers on the implications and requirements of such a programme. The official report had indicated that between now and1972-73 the programme would be achieved if the farmers were left with about 50 per cent of their real productivity gain. in considering the size of the award at this Review, he believed thatthis was the rational starting point. An award calculated to leavethe farmers with half of their real productivity gain in 1969-70would amount to  23 million. There were, however, special andconflicting considerations affecting 1969-70. It would not be rightto ignore the bad weather in 1968-69 and the aftermath of the foot-and-mouth epidemic, or the announcement in November of theGovernments selective expansion programme to 1972-73. If theconfidence of the farmers was to be maintained and this was clearly of great importance then an award more generous than
the norm was indicated. On the other hand, he had borne in mind the extremely tight expenditure position in 1969-70 which had ledto the review of the programmes of other spending Departmentslast summer and had resulted in very difficult reductions in expenditure on roads, housing and education. Taking these twoconflicting considerations into account, he had reached the conclusionthat leaving the farmers with 60 per cent instead of 50 per cent oftheir expected productivity gain in 1969-70 would meet the case.An award on the scale proposed by the Minister of Agriculturewhich would leave the farmers with 140 per cent of their productivitygain in 1969-70 seemed completely to depart from the basis on whichthey had agreed the selective expansion programme; or else itwould mean that a minimal award of only 5 per cent of the productivity gain could be made at each of the following two FarmReviews in order to restore the norm of 50 per cent on average.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that opinion was fairly evenly divided between those Ministers who supported the recommendation by the Minister without Portfoliofor an award of  26 million and those who wanted more. On balance the Cabinet agreed that the Minister of Agriculture should beauthorised to negotiate an award of  30 million. The agricultural policy Committee should be consulted about the details of thesettlement. If in the course of the negotiations the Minister decidedthat he must ask his colleagues to increase this limit on hisnegotiating authority, he was of course free to do so. But, in viewof the extremely serious public expenditure and budgetary problems which now faced the Government, the Minister of Agriculture shouldnot expect the agreement of his colleagues to any significant increasebeyond  30 million.The Cabinet-Invited the Minister of Agriculture to negotiate a totalaward in the Farm Price Review for 1969 of  30 million.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,11th February, 1969.



</content>
</cab>
