<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/44/0 images: 350-357</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government cc (69)25th conclusions printed for the Cabinet. January 1970Copy No.   31CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in thePrime Ministers Room, House of Commons, S.W.1,on Thursday, 22nd May, 1969, at 4 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,Secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe   Right   Hon.Lord chancellor lord  Gardiner,The Right Hon. Roy Jenkins,Chancellor of the exchequer p,The Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Employment aridProductivityThe Right Hon. Denis Healey, mp,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Peter Shore,SecretaryAffairsmp,of  State  for  economic the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Lord Shackleton,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Roy Mason, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Fred Peart, m p, lord president of the council the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes, m p,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food (Item 1)The Right Hon. George Thomas, mp,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Judith Hart, mp,Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. John Diamond, mp,Chief Secretary, treasury the following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, qc,m p, Attorney-General
)Secretariat :Sir Burke trend miss J. J. nunn mr. R. R. D. mcintosh mr. J. CrockerContentsItem Subject page 1     Social Services        ..................      3Uprating of Social Security Benefits2     Prices and Incomes Policy...............      6Central Pay Increases for the Non-Industrial CivilService
SocialServicesUprating of social security benefits(previous reference:CC (69) 23rdConclusions,Minute 5)Taking contributions first, the Committee had considered whether it would be possible to limit the increases in employees&apos;contributions, and in particular those of the lower paid, either by putting more of the burden on employers or by increasing theExchequer contribution; but both these courses seemed to be ruled out by what the Chancellor of the Exchequer had said in winding upthe Budget Debate. Accepting that  370 million had to be found from contributions, relief to the lower paid could come only fromraising still further the contributions of the higher paid, includingmany in the middle ranges who were only comparatively well off; theCommittee had examined a number of alternative scales of increases,the most attractive of which would have limited the increase on theman earning  10 to Is. Od. a week at the expense of increasing the contribution of the man earning  30 by 7s. 7d. a week. The view ofthe majority had been that a saving of 6d. a week would make no significant difference to the small group of men earning less than  10,whereas to raise the contribution at the  30 level by more than 7s.a week would attract a great deal. of criticism. On balance theCommittee preferred the scale of increases proposed in his originalmemorandum.10388SECRET1. The Cabinet resumed their consideration of a memorandumby the Secretary of State for Social Services (C (69) 50) on the uprating of social security benefits; they also had before them notes by the Secretary of State for Social Services (C (69) 55) and the lord privy Seal (C (69) 57) on the same subject.The Secretary of State for Social Services recalled that at their discussion on 15th May the Cabinet had accepted in principle that part of the sum needed to finance increases in benefits and meet the deficit on the National Insurance Fund should be found by increasinggraduated contributions, but the general feeling had been that more time was needed to study the detailed proposals in his memorandum(C (69) 50) and he had been invited to arrange an early meeting ofthe Ministerial Committee on Social Services for the purpose. TheCommittee had met on 20th May and had considered two furthermemoranda: one by the Minister of State, Department of Health and social Security, instancing alternative ways of raising the sum to befound from contributions, and another by the Lord Privy Seal onthe implications of the proposals for public service superannuationschemes. These had now been circulated to the Cabinet (C (69) 55and 57).
.1)    4SECRETOn dynamism the Committee were agreed that it was politically impossible for the Government to raise a large part of the sum neededfrom graduated contributions without undertaking to remedy thedefect which they had so often criticised in the Conservative scheme,namely its failure to revalue the pensions earned to take account of movements in prices or earnings; under the White Paper scheme allbenefits would be dynamised. The promise of dynamism was alsoessential to prevent widespread contracting out of the present scheme.But it would undoubtedly lead to charges of breach of faith fromemployees who had been contracted out, and in particular those inthe public sector. The Lord Privy Seal in his memorandum(C (69) 57) had proposed that Civil Service and similar occupational pensions should not be further abated on account of additional benefits earned by the increase in contributions and the introductionof dynamism, and thought that with these concessions theGovernment should be able to obtain the agreement of the CivilService National Staff Side; the Committee had accepted his recommendations. But this would not necessarily provide a solution for the nationalised industries and there would be pressure for improved benefits. The introduction of dynamism would not affectthe text of the Bill, but would need to be announced at lateston Second Reading and preferably when the Bill was published andthe new rates of contribution became known. An early decision was essential to allow time for urgent consultation with the trade unions and staff organisations concerned.Contributions ^In discussion the Cabinet first considered the proposed increases in contributions. It was argued with some force that it was morallywrong to increase employees&apos; contributions as proposed, andparticularly so where lower paid workers were concerned;Contributions of men and women employees had already increasedrather faster than average earnings since 1964 and if the newcontribution rates were adopted they would have increased substantially faster than earnings. The higher contributions were particularly difficult to defend in so far as the need for them arose from a higher level of unemployment; (it was pointed out, however,that this was not a major factor in the deficit in the national insurance Fund). If it had reluctantly to be accepted that the chancellors statement made it impossible to place more of theburden on employers, as had been done in 1964 and 1967, or toincrease the Exchequer contribution, contributions should be required from those earning more than  30 a week.On the other hand it was pointed out that the proposed increaseshad been designed to be in line with the proposals in the White Paper,which provided for parity of contributions and an upper income limit
of one and a half times national average earnings. The economiceffects of higher employers&apos; contributions and higher contributions from the better paid had both to be taken into account. Taking allthe factors together there seemed no alternative to raising  370 million from increased contributions and the question was how the burdenshould be spread. A majority of the Cabinet favoured Alternative Cof those specified in paragraph 6 of C (69) 55.DynamismIn further discussion the Cabinet considered the proposal touprate benefits earned by graduated contributions to reflect changesin the cost of living. There was general agreement that it would be extremely difficult for the Government not to accompany theincreased contributions by the promise of dynamism, but it wassuggested that this would cause considerable difficulties for the nationalised industries. There were 1 million contracted out workersin the power industries alone and there would be pressure on the boards to bring the benefits of those contracted out up to the levelof those payable to employees in the State scheme; the Boards in their turn would expect the Treasury to pay. On the other hand the point was made that employees contracted out had had the better of the. bargain in recent years, and pension funds which had pursued a wiseinvestment policy were in a flourishing state; and that the cost ofdynamising the benefits of those who had left the industries, or did soin future, might prove not to be so great as was feared. The proposalsof the Lord Privy Seal should be approved as the best available basis for consultations with the staff interests concerned, both, in the nationalised industries and in other parts of the public sector; ifserious difficulties arose the matter should be considered further. Itwas planned to take the Second Reading of the Bill on 18th June, withthe Committee Stage being taken on the floor on 24th and 25th June,and the Bill should be published not later than 11th June. the consultations should therefore be undertaken as a matter of urgency.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that themajority of those present favoured the table of increases in contributions shown as Alternative C in paragraph 6 of C (69) 55, andthe National Insurance (Uprating) Bill should be framed accordingly.The Cabinet also approved the principle of dynamising benefitsearned by graduated contributions and the proposals made by theLord Privy Seal that as some recompense to those contracted out under the Civil Service and similar schemes there should be noabatement of occupational pensions on account of the benefitsearned by the increased contributions and the introduction of
dynamism. Ministers responsible for pension schemes in the public sector should urgently initiate discussions with the staff interests concerned on the basis of the Lord Privy Seal&apos;s memorandum, witha view to a statement on the introduction of dynamism being made,if possible, when the Bill was published and at latest during theSecond Reading debate.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the increased contributions should be fixed asproposed in Alternative C in paragraph 6 of C (69) 55.(2) Approved in principle the proposal to dynamise the presentgraduated pensions from 1972 onwards.(3) Approved the proposals in C (69) 57.(4) Invited the Lord Privy Seal and other Ministers responsiblefor pensions schemes in the public sector to initiate urgentdiscussions with the staff interests concerned, on the basisof the proposals in C (69) 57.CONFIDENTIALPrices andIncomesPolicyCentral pay increases forthe Non-industrial civil service. The Cabinet considered a note by the Lord Privy Seal towhich was attached a memorandum on the National Staff Side&apos;s claim for a central pay increase for the non-industrial Civil Service.(C (69) 58).The Lord Privy Seal said that there were two groups of staffinvolved: those who had pay research settlements from 1st January,1968, but whose increases were staged in two instalments with thesecond taking effect without retrospection on 1st January, 1969(Group 1), and those whose last pay adjustment was a central pay increase on 1st July, 1968 (Group 2). At their meeting on the previous day the Ministerial Committee on Prices and Incomes had authorised him to offer central pay increases of 5 per cent for Group 1 and 3J percent for Group 2, both with effect from 1st July, 1969.The Cabinet Took note of the statement by the Lord Privy Seal.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,23rd May, 1969.



</content>
</cab>
