<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/44/0 images: 386-401</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MA.IESTY&apos;S government cc (69)28th conclusions printed for the Cabinet.   January 1970Copy No.  31CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 17th June, 1969,at 10.15 am. and resumed in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W.1, at 430 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime Minister*Thc Right Hon. Michael Stuwart,m p, Secretary of State for foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (Item I)&quot;The Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,First Secretary of Stale and Secretaryof State for Employment and productivity (Item I and morningdiscussion of Item 2)The &quot;Right  Hon.  Fred  Peart,Lord President of the Councilm pThe Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m i&apos;, President of the Board of Trade*The Right Hon. George Thomson,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Minister of technology the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m \\ Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. Lord Shackleton,Lord Privy seal the  Right  Hon.  Roy Mason, m p,Minister of power the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, m i\Chancellor of the Exchequer (In the chair for Item 2)The Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Secretary of Slate  for social services the Right Hon. James Callaghan,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Peter Shore, m p,Secretary of State for economic affairs the Right Hon. William Ross, m p,Secretary of Slate for scotland the Right Hon. Edward Short, m p,Secretary of Stale for Education and science the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, m p,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p. Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. George Thomas, m p,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Judith Hart, m p,Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. John Diamond, m p,Chief Secretary, treasury the following were also present:The Right Hon. Robert Mellisii, m p,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, qc,m p, Attorney-General* Absent from the resumed meeting in the afternoon.SECRET
Secretariat :Sir Burke trend miss J. J. nunn mr. R. R. D. mcintosh mr. P. E. ThorntonContentsItem Subject page 1     Industrial Affairs   ..................      3Industrial Relations bill     Upper Clyde Shipbuilders Limited      .........     10
IndustrialAffairsIndustrialRelations Bill(previous reference:CC (69) 27thConclusions,Minute 5)SECRET*1.  The Cabinet resumed their discussion on industrial relations.The Prime Minister said that records of the discussions whichhe and the First Secretary of State had had with the general council of the Trades Union Congress (TUC) had been circulatedto members of the Cabinet. It was generally agreed that the TUCsproposals on inter-union disputes were satisfactory and that therewas no need for the Government to introduce legislation on thistopic. The position on unofficial strikes involving disputes with employers, however, was much less satisfactory. The TUCsproposals did not distinguish between official and unofficial strikes;and they put too much emphasis on the role of the TUC as aconciliator in such disputes and too little on the need to obtain a return to work. At the last meeting with the General Council hehad told them that the Cabinet had authorised him to say that,if the TUC were prepared to strengthen the provisions in Rule 11relating to unconstitutional strikes in such a way as to bring them into line with the provisions in Rule 12 relating to inter-uniondisputes, the Government would be prepared to abandon legislationincorporating &quot; penal clauses&quot; and that, if the General council would undertake to make a recommendation on these lines to theirautumn Congress, the Government would accept this without waiting until the recommendation had been formally ratified. The general council had made it clear, however, that they would not be preparedto amend Rule 11, even though the amendments which he and theFirst Secretary had suggested followed closely the language of the tuc&apos;s own report &quot; Programme for Action &quot; and the wording whichthey had proposed (C (69) 67) would leave the TUC considerablediscretion in deciding whether the circumstances of any individualunconstitutional strike required them to initiate the disciplinaryprocesses provided by the amended rule. The rnost that the general council had been prepared to contemplate was an interpretativestatement on the lines of Annex B of the record of the meeting withthe TUC on 12th June. This, however, would be a mere declarationof intent, with no binding force; and it could not be regarded asa satisfactory alternative to the Governments proposal. If theGovernment were to accept it, they would be going back on their previous decision to secure an effective solution to the problem ofunconstitutional strikes. They would lose all credibility both athome and abroad; and their authority would disappear. He andthe First Secretary had therefore considered whether any statutoryalternative could be found which would not involve either an amendment of the Trade Disputes Act, 1906, which was unacceptable* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.
for the reasons given in the White Paper &quot; In Place of Strife &quot;, orthe imposition of fines on individual strikers and the attachment ofwages, to which the TUC and members of the Parliamentary LabourParty (PLP) took such strong exception.The First Secretary of State said that the broad approach inthe White Paper &quot; In Place of Strife &quot; (Cmnd. 3888) and the TUCsown proposals in &quot; Programme for Action &quot; were very similar; andin seeking an alternative form of sanction she had tried to build onthis identity of purpose and, in particular, to strengthen the authorityof the TUC themselves. The Government and the TUC bothrecognised that in the long term better industrial relations depended on the improvement of negotiating procedures. But their efforts to improve procedures would fail if employers thought the unions would not discipline those of their members who took part inunconstitutional stoppages in breach of procedures. She had therefore considered whether, instead of imposing fines on individualworkers, the Bill should include provision which would make theunions responsible for the conduct of any of their members who took part in unconstitutional strikes. Her proposals (which were summarised in a memorandum distributed at the meeting andsubsequently circulated as C (69) 70) envisaged that, in the case of astrike which was in breach of agreed procedures (or where no adequate procedure existed) and involved directly or indirectlylarge numbers of workers, the Secretary of State would make anOrder for a conciliation pause in the same circumstances as wereenvisaged in the White Paper. The employer would be requiredto observe specified terms and conditions, which might include a return to the status quo; and the employees would be required toreturn to work. The Bill would lay responsibility on the union orunions concerned to use their best endeavours to ensure that their members did in fact return to work in order to allow for proceduresto be used or, if necessary, an inquiry to be held. If the strikecontinued and the Secretary of State considered that the unions were not seriously trying to get the strikers back to work, she wouldbe empowered to take proceedings before the Industrial Board onthe grounds that they had not used their &quot; best endeavours &quot; forthis purpose. The term &quot; best endeavours&quot; was commonly usedin the field of industrial relations; and the proposed powers were inany case likely to be used only in cases where there was convincing evidence that a union had failed to do its best to obtain a resumptionof work. If the Industrial Board found against the union it wouldbe subject to a substantial financial penalty, which would be a debtrecoverable from the union as a corporation and not from its general Secretary. The Bill would also have to provide that a trade union could not plead in its defence that its rules precludedit from taking action to secure a return to work by its members.
Since some unions did not have appropriate disciplinary rules todeal with unconstitutional strike action by their members, it wouldbe necessary to give unions time to take action to amend their rulesbefore the appointed day, which might therefore be fixed at, say,six months after the Bill received Royal Assent. A measure onthese lines should be more acceptable to the PLP than the original proposal for sanctions involving fines on individual workers; itwould constitute a short, clear Bill; and it would be a reasonableproposal to put to the TUC as the alternative which the Governmentwould be compelled to adopt if, but only if, the TUC themselvescontinued to reject the suggestion for an amendment of Rule 11.In particular, it would be consistent both with the White Paper&quot; In Place of Strife &quot; and with the attitude which the Governmenthad taken in the recent discussions with the TUC. Finally, even ifit proved necessary to introduce a Bill on these lines, it could not reach the Statute Book by the summer recess; and, if the TUCsubsequently changed their mind and secured approval to thenecessary amendment of Rule 11 at their Congress in September,the Government could then abandon the Bill in the autumn spilloverbefore it had been enacted at all.In discussion, there was general agreement that the issues for decision were (a) Should the Government inform the General Council onthe following day that they would introduce legislation immediately,including some form of &quot; penal clauses &quot;, unless the TUC were ableto provide an adequate assurance forthwith in relation tounconstitutional disputes?(b) Must an adequate assurance take the form of a firm commitment by the General Council to recommend to Congress achange in Rule 11 on the lines suggested by the Government? or would an interpretation of the procedure to be adopted underRule 11 on the lines suggested by the TUC, suitably strengthened instatus and wording, be sufficient?(c) If the Government stated their intention to introduce legislation, including &quot; penal clauses&quot;, should these take the formoriginally proposed or the alternative form now suggested by theFirst Secretary of State?In relation to (a) and (b) it was argued that the gap betweenthe respective positions of the Government and the TUC was now very narrow. The difference in status between an amendment to rule 11 and an interpretative document which would be includedin the General Councils report to Congress and would be formallyapproved by it was minimal. The divergence between the texts ofthe proposed amendment to Rule 11 and of the interpretative
document as shown in Annexes A and B to the note of themeeting with TUC representatives on 12th June also seemedsmall. The Government and the TUC were accordingly nearenough to agreement to make it worthwhile pursuing negotationsfurther; and it would be unnecessary and unwise to threaten the tuc at this stage with the immedate introduction of &quot; penal&quot;legislation, particularly since in any event they did not believe thatthe Government would be able to secure the enactment of such legislation, and it was indeed uncertain whether the Governmentcould count on the support of the PLP if the Bill, when introduced,were condemned by the TUC. It was therefore not whollyunreasonable on the part of the TUC to threaten, in return, towithdraw their own proposals, as set out in &quot; Programme for action&quot;, if the Government introduced any form of &quot; penal&quot;legislation; and their attitude in this respect should not necessarily be taken as an indication that they were simply offering their scheme as a tactical manoeuvre in order to avoid legislation. Theywere genuinely convinced that no &quot; legal &quot; sanction, whetherprovided by the Government or by themselves, could be implementedeffectively. But many of them would be prepared to make a realattempt to operate the principles set out in their interpretativedocument; and it was on the various ways of enhancing the status of this document that the Government should now concentrate.It would be unreasonable and would seem so to public opinion to allow the negotiations to break down on the single and not easily comprehensible issue whether the tuc&apos;s own sanction againstunconstitutional strikes should take the form of an amendment to rule 11 or an interpretative document. The Government hadalready procured a very substantial advance by the TUC fromtheir original position; and, if they could now reach agreement onthe sole outstanding issue, they would be seen to have secured, ina few months, a more significant reform of trade union organisationthan had been achieved in many years. It would be foolish to put this potential achievement at risk for the sake of a difference of presentation which would, in any event, be of little practical importance.On the other hand, it was argued that the position adopted bythe Prime Minister and the First Secretary of State in the negotiationswith the TUC had not only been in accordance with the cabinet&apos;s earlier decisions but had also been fully justified by the merits ofthe case. The Government were proposing to require employers to restore the status quo in the case of a strike provoked bymismanagement on their part; and there must clearly be somecorresponding requirement on the workers to return to work incases where they were at fault. Nevertheless, the Government had offered to abandon &quot; penal&quot; legislation for this purpose provided
that the TUC themselves &quot; legislated &quot;. But effective &quot; legislation &quot;by the TUC could only be secured by an amendment to their rules:a circular letter of interpretation would have no binding force andwas therefore no substitute. The leaders of two of the largestunions the Amalgamated Engineering and Foundry Workers&apos;Union and the Transport and General Workers&apos; Union appearedto be determined to avoid an amendment of Rule 11 on the lines proposed by the Government, because such an amendment, unlikea circular letter, would make plain the obligations which the TUCwould have accepted to secure a resumption of work in the caseof unconstitutional strikes. They had also ensured that the termsof the proposed circular letter itself were more imprecise thanthe terms of the amendment to Rule 11 proposed by theGovernment. Thus, the circular was related to constitutional(and official), as well as to unconstitutional, strikes; and it gaveprominence to the role of the TUC in securing a settlement of the issues in dispute as well as in obtaining a resumption of work.It was in fact little more than a prescription for conciliation; andit was clear that the more intransigent elements in the general council hoped, by blurring both the precise nature of the TUCsobligations and the means by which they would be discharged, toreduce those obligations or to evade them altogether. The essence of the problem was their refusal to be made publicly answerablefor the effective implementation of the principles to which they themselves purported to have subscribed in the tuc&apos;s owndocument &quot; Programme for Action&quot;. But, although the TUCrepresentatives had said that they would withdraw their own proposals if the Government introduced &quot; penal&quot; legislation, theywould in practice be increasingly likely to modify this position if legislation were once introduced, particularly if it provided thatthe &quot; penal clauses &quot; would not take effect for a defined period. If,on the other hand, it became apparent that the Government had accepted an arrangement which was obviously less than adequate todeal with the problem of unconstitutional strikes, it would be clearthat the reason for their doing so was their fear that they would be unable to carry legislation which was against the wishes of the tuc and the PLP; and in that event they would forfeit all respect and authority, both at home and abroad. &apos;When the Cabinet resumed their discussion in the afternoonit was urged that they should consider their course of action on thebasis of a clearer definition of their objective. Basically, this objective was to improve industrial relations. But there must be considerable doubt whether this would be achieved by legislation inany form. Even if it proved possible to secure the passage of theproposed Bill through Parliament, which on present evidence
seemed highly doubtful, the effect on the morale of the Government^supporters would be very damaging and would be liable to persistfor many months; and the Governments credibility depended asmuch on their ability to maintain the unity of the PLP on basicissues of policy as on their ability to solve a particular problem. the tuc&apos;s own proposals in &quot; Programme for Action &quot;, on the otherhand, seemed likely to have a reasonable chance of being put intopractical effect, particularly as regards inter-union disputes; and theywould also help to strengthen the central authority of the TUC,which was in itself a desirable reform. The gap between the positions of the Government and the TUC was now so narrowthat it would be politically unwise to confer the privilege ofmartyrdom on the more recalcitrant unions by introducing legislation which public opinion would regard as directed largelyagainst them. The Governments position would be far moredefensible if they took their stand on the solid achievements already secured in the course of negotiations with the TUC and did notjeopardise all the ground they had won for the sake of oneexposed salient which was in fact untenable. The latest proposalfor legislation, which the First Secretary of State had describedat the Cabinets discussion in the morning, would be no more acceptable to the TUC than any of the earlier versions of the&quot; penal clauses &quot;; and it would be unrealistic to resume discussions with the TUC on the basis that the Government could afford to threaten them with the prospect of legislation which the TUCthemselves would know the Government could not enact except at the cost of grave and lasting damage to Party unity. Nor, indeed,had the Cabinet ever taken a formal and final decision on their course of action if it proved impossible to reach agreement withthe TUC. They had suspended judgment on this issue; and theyshould continue to do so, since it was clear that the balance of the argument inclined in favour of making one further attempt tobring the negotiations with the TUC to a conclusion which all parties could accept, probably on the basis of a further strengthening of the proposed interpretative circular.On the other hand it was argued that the progress made inthe discussions with the TUC should not be over-estimated. Whilethe Governments pressure had induced the General Council tomake satisfactory proposals in relation to inter-union disputes,there had been virtually no advance as regards unconstitutional strikes. Moreover, such progress as had been achieved had been due entirely to the tuc&apos;s knowledge that, unless agreement on somesatisfactory alternative proposals were reached, the Governmentwere firmly and publicly committed e.g., by the Budget speech and the White Paper to introduce legislation including disciplinaryprovisions in some form.  The effect of this knowledge, however,
CC28(69)had been increasingly offset by reports in the Press and elsewherethat the Cabinet were divided on this issue and were not preparedto introduce statutory penal sanctions. It was clear that individualunions remained opposed to any surrender of power, whether tothe Government or to the TUC, and that, if the threat oflegislation were now finally removed, the TUC would not be ableto offer any further advance on their proposed interpretativecircular, which was clearly inadequate as an effective sanction inrelation to unconstitutional strikes. If they were prepared to convert this into a rule, by amendment of Rule 11 on the lines proposed by the Government, it would be possible to forgolegislation. But they would not be moved in this direction except by a clear indication that, in default of a change of mind on their part, the Cabinet had unanimously decided to enact statutorydisciplinary provisions. It might, admittedly, be difficult to carrysuch a Bill through Parliament. But no Government could affordin the last resort to accept dictation by its Parliamentary Party,particularly when there were grounds for believing that the Partyat Westminster did not entirely reflect the sentiment of the majorityof the Governments supporters in the country as a whole. nor should it be assumed that the PLP itself would necessarilywithhold support from the Government when Ministers were free to put all the facts before it.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were not yet ready to reach a decision on the form whichstatutory &quot; penal &quot; sanctions might take, or to make a choice, forthis purpose, between the original proposals and the latest suggestion made by the First Secretary of State that morning. Even on the prior issue whether, in default of agreement with the TUC on an amendment of Rule 11, legislation of this kind should be introduced at all, there appeared to be a division of opinion and a preference for continuing discussions with the TUC on the basis of their proposed interpretative circular, preferably in a strengthened form.But in view of the Cabinet&apos;s earlier decisions and the Governmentspublic commitment in the White Paper, it would not be possiblefor the First Secretary of State and himself to resume negotiationswith the General Council on this hypothesis alone; nor could any positive result be expected from further discussions with the TUCif they were allowed to believe that the Government were not agreed upon the need to introduce legislation embodying sanctionsof some kind if 5the TUC themselves were unwilling to make anyfurther improvements in their proposals for dealing withunconstitutional strikes. In these circumstances he and the first secretary of State, at their meeting with the General Council onthe following day, would be guided by the various views which had
seemed highly doubtful, the effect on the morale of the governments supporters would be very damaging and would be liable to persistfor many months; and the Governmenfs credibility depended asmuch on their ability to maintain the unity of the PLP on basicissues of policy as on their ability to solve a particular problem. the tuc&apos;s own. proposals in &quot; Programme for Action &quot;, on the otherhand, seemed likely to have a reasonable chance of being put intopractical effect, particularly as regards inter-union disputes; and theywould also help to strengthen the central authority of the TUC,which was in itself a desirable reform. The gap between the positions of the Government and the TUC was now so narrowthat it would be politically unwise to confer the privilege ofmartyrdom on the more recalcitrant unions by introducing legislation which public opinion would regard as directed largelyagainst them. The Governmenfs position would be far moredefensible if they took their stand on the solid achievements already secured in the course of negotiations with the TUC and did notjeopardise all the ground they had won for the sake of oneexposed salient which was in fact untenable. The latest proposalfor legislation, which the First Secretary of State had describedat the Cabinefs discussion in the morning, would be no more acceptable to the TUC than any of the earlier versions of the&quot;penal clauses &quot;; and it would be unrealistic to resume discussions with the TUC on the basis that the Government could afford to threaten them with the prospect of legislation which the TUCthemselves would know the Government could not enact except at the cost of grave and lasting damage to Party unity. Nor, indeed,had the Cabinet ever taken a formal and final decision on their course of action if it proved impossible to reach agreement withthe TUC. They had suspended judgment on this issue; and theyshould continue to do so, since it was clear that the balance of the argument inclined in favour of making one further attempt tobring the negotiations with the TUC to a conclusion which all parties could accept, probably on the basis of a further strengthening of the proposed interpretative circular.On the other hand it was argued that the progress made inthe discussions with the TUC should not be over-estimated. Whilethe Governmenfs pressure had induced the General Council tomake satisfactory proposals in relation to inter-union disputes,there had been virtually no advance as regards unconstitutional strikes. Moreover, such progress as had been achieved had been due entirely to the tuc&apos;s knowledge that, unless agreement on somesatisfactory alternative proposals were reached, the Governmentwere firmly and publicly committed e.g., by the Budget speech and the White Paper to introduce legislation including disciplinaryprovisions in some form.  The effect of this knowledge, however,
had been increasingly offset by reports in the Press and elsewherethat the Cabinet were divided on this issue and were not preparedto introduce statutory penal sanctions. It was clear that individualunions remained opposed to any surrender of power, whether tothe Government or to the TUC, and that, if the threat oflegislation were now finally removed, the TUC would not be ableto offer any further advance on their proposed interpretativecircular, which was clearly inadequate as an effective sanction inrelation to unconstitutional strikes. If they were prepared to convert this into a rule, by amendment of Rule 11 on the lines proposed by the Government, it would be possible to forgolegislation. But they would not be moved in this direction except by a clear indication that, in default of a change of mind on their part, the Cabinet had unanimously decided to enact statutorydisciplinary provisions. It might, admittedly, be difficult to carrysuch a Bill through Parliament. But no Government could affordin the last resort to accept dictation by its Parliamentary Party,particularly when there were grounds for believing that the Partyat Westminster did not entirely reflect the sentiment of the majorityof the Governmenfs supporters in the country as a whole. nor should it be assumed that the PLP itself would necessarilywithhold support from the Government when Ministers were free to put all the facts before it.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were not yet ready to reach a decision on the form whichstatutory &quot; penal&quot; sanctions might take, or to make a choice, forthis purpose, between the original proposals and the latest suggestion made by the First Secretary of State that morning. Even on the prior issue whether, in default of agreement with the TUC on an amendment of Rule 11, legislation of this kind should be introduced at all, there appeared to be a division of opinion and a preference for continuing discussions with the TUC on the basis of their proposed interpretative circular, preferably in a strengthened form.But in view of the Cabinet&apos;s earlier decisions and the Governmenfspublic commitment in the White Paper, it would not be possiblefor the First Secretary of State and himself to resume negotiationswith the General Council on this hypothesis alone; nor could any positive result be expected from further discussions with the TUCif they were allowed to believe that the Government were not agreed upon the need to introduce legislation embodying sanctionsof some kind if ^he TUC themselves were unwilling to make anyfurther improvements in their proposals for dealing withunconstitutional strikes. In these circumstances he and the first secretary of State, at their meeting with the General Council onthe following day, would be guided by the various views which had
been expressed during the Cabinets discussion. They would seek, to refrain from committing the Government to any precise form of statutory disciplinary provisions, since the Cabinet were not inagreement on this matter; but it would not be possible for them, inexploring whether the TUC were prepared to strengthen their own proposals, to avoid indicating the advice which they themselves would feel compelled to give their Cabinet colleagues if thenegotiations reached a final deadlock. He would report the outcometo the Cabinet; and it would then be necessary for individual ministers to consider their respective positions in reaching the finaldecision.The Cabinet Took note of the Prime Minister^ summing up of their discussion.Upper ClydeShipbuildersLimited(previous reference:CC (69) 24thConclusions,Minute 5)confidential. The Minister of Technology recalled that the board ofUpper Clyde Shipbuilders Limited (UCS) had requested  8 million tocover expected losses in addition to about  4 million for futureinvestment which was not in dispute and that the Governmenthad supported the Shipbuilding Industry Board (SIB) in offering 5 million, which the SIB were satisfied was adequate to meet theCompany&apos;s financial requirements. The offer of  5 million hadbeen made subject to conditions, including acceptance by the unions concerned of redundancies totalling about 3,000 and assurances bythem on pay and productivity. All the unions concerned, with theexception of the Amalgamated Society of Boilermakers, had givensatisfactory assurances. The Amalgamated Society of Boilermakershad agreed to forgo a wage increase amounting to 6s. Od. a weekwhich had been nationally negotiated this year. They had also agreed to forgo a premium of 54d. an hour which their membersenjoyed in the Govan Yard. But they had not given the fullassurances which the SIB had required on mobility of labour andon productivity. The board of UCS had failed to obtain theadditional  3 million which they considered necessary to cover theirexpected losses. It seemed most probable therefore that they would now decide to put the Company into liquidation. The government might, however, still be able to prevent liquidation by persuading the SIB to give a guarantee covering a further  3 million-inaddition to the offer of  5 million in cash which had already beenmade despite the absence of a fully satisfactory assurance from theAmalgamated Society of Boilermakers.
In discussion, it was argued that the trade unions concerned had come a very long way in meeting the requirements of the SIB andthat liquidation would be a catastrophe, not only for the Clyde butfor British shipbuilding as a whole. The report which had been circulated to the Ministerial Steering Committee on economic policy (SEP (69) 70) underestimated the cost to the Exchequer ofliquidation. In addition to the costs of social security payments,redundancy payments, etc., provision must also be made for the substantial costs involved to the Exchequer in providing new jobs in a development area. In any event, the estimate of the effects ofliquidation on employment were over-optimistic. If UCS now went into liquidation after the strenuous efforts made by the trade unions to save these jobs, the Government would be held responsible. Onthe other hand, it was urged that SEP (69) 70 convincingly argued that the possible gain to United Kingdom shipbuilding output wouldprobably not justify a commitment, which might prove open-ended,to further financial support to UCS. The approach hitherto adoptedin an attempt to improve conditions in the Upper Clyde shipbuilding industry had failed, and was always likely to fail, since it involved a forced merger of well managed and badly managed companies.There was no prospect of UCS satisfying the two essential conditions set by the SIB: first, adequate assurances about future labour productivity, and, second, that Yarrow and Company Limitedshould fully integrate with the rest of UCS. In the circumstances,the solution most likely to lead to a satisfactory and viable outcomein the longer term was the appointment of a liquidator who couldbe assisted if necessary financially by the Government.The Chance/lor of the Exchequer, summing up the discussion,said that it was the general view of the Cabinet that the Minister of technology should be authorised to discuss with the SIB thepossibility of avoiding liquidation of UCS by the offer of an SIBguarantee covering  3 million in addition to the cash offer of 5 million which had already been made. The Minister of technology should examine this possibility with the SIB but withoutfinal commitment to it, and should report the outcome to theCabinet at their resumed meeting later that day.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.(2) Invited the Minister of Technology to explore the possibilityof avoiding liquidation of UCS by the provision of anSIB guarantee covering  3 million.
When the Cabinet resumed their discussion the Minister of technology reported that the Board of Upper Clyde ShipbuildersLimited (UCS) had informed him at midday that they had been unable to raise the money which they considered they needed toavoid liquidation. Accordingly, acting on the authority which theCabinet had given him during the morning, he had had a further discussion with the Shipbuilding Industry Board (SIB). The board had informed him that they believed the difficulties of UCS to beattributable to poor management; but that they had been impressed by the willingness of the unions to sacrifice some of the gains whichthey had recently made in order to save the Company. The SIBbelieved that the very substantial sums already offered would besufficient, taken with the plan proposed and as accepted by theunions, subject to the re-negotiation by the Amalgamated society of Boilermakers of their insistence on the present guarantee [i.e., offall-back pay under a previous productivity agreement]; to permit the creation of a viable unit in the Upper Clyde, and they thereforebelieved that liquidation now would not be right. They had authorised him to inform the Board of UCS of their view and oftheir willingness to discuss with the reconstructed Board and management the developing financial situation early next year inthe light of the performance of the Group following the implementation of the present UCS plan. If the Cabinet agreed,he would inform the UCS Board of this development in the SIB&apos;position, which he thought offered a slight chance of avoiding the liquidation of the Company. The money which the SIB wouldprovide if the UCS now accepted their offer would come from the funds to which they already had access.The Cabinet-(3) Agreed that the Minister of Technology should communicate to the Board of UCS the further statement which he hadreceived from the SIB.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,18th June, 1969.



</content>
</cab>
