<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/44/0 images: 498-513</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held inthe Prime Minister&apos;s Room, House of Commons, S.W.1,on Thursday, 24th July, 1969, at 10 a.m.and later at 10 Downing Street, S.W.present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,Secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Employment and productivity the Right Hon. Denis Healey, mp,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Peter Shore,SecretaryAffairsmp,of  State  for  economic the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Secretary of State for Education and science the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins,Chancellor of the exchequer p,The Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,mp, President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. George Thomson, m p.Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Minister of technology the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes, m p,Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. Lord Shackleton,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Roy Mason, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. John DiamondChief Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. George Thomas, mp,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Judith Hart, mp,Paymaster Generalmp,THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  February 1970CC(69) Copy No.  3]36th Conclusions
The following \The Right Hon. Reginald Prentice,mp, Minister of Overseas Develop-ment (Item 4)The Right Hon. John Silkin, mp,Minister of Public Building and works (Item 4)The Right Hon. Robert Mellish, m p,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury(Items 1-3)re also present:The Right Hon. Kenneth Robinson,m p, Minister for Planning and Land,Ministry of Housing and LocalGovernment (Item 4)The Right Hon. John Stonehouse, m p,Postmaster-General (Item 4)The Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, q c,m p, Attorney-General (Items 1-3)Secretariat:Sir Burke trend miss J. J. nunn mr. P. E. ThorntonMiss S. W. FogartyContentsItem                                     Subject page 1     The Governments Record...............      32     Questions of Procedure for Ministers.........      3Policy in response to academic enquiries3     Parliamentary Affairs      ...............      4House of Commons (Redistribution of Seats) (No. 2) bill     Nationalised Industries............     ...      7Investment ReviewAir Corporations and British Airports AuthorityTransport ServicesGasElectricityPost Office
CC 36 (69)confidential the 1.   The Prime Minister said that in view of the approach of the record&quot;16111&apos;8 anniversary of tlie Labour Government assuming office, itwould be appropriate for the Paymaster General to undertake thepreparation of a comprehensive review of the Governmenfsachievements measured against the promises in their electionmanifestos. He hoped that all Ministers would give their personalattention to the contributions to this review which their departments would be asked to supply.The Cabinet Took note of the Prime Ministers statement.Questions ofProcedurefor MinistersPolicy in response toacademicenquiriesCONFIDENTIAL2. The Prime Minister said that Professor Richard Rose ofthe University of Strathclyde, assisted by Mr. Bruce Heady, wasundertaking an academic study of government, in the course ofwhich Mr. Heady had written to all departmental Ministers asking for information about their departmental work and the problemsthey encountered, and asking for an opportunity to discuss some ofthe problems of government with Ministers personally.The Prime Minister recalled that the Government had beenunder strong pressure from Mr. Ernest Marples, m p, who had beenasked by the Leader of the Opposition to undertake a study of themachinery of government and had commissioned a firm ofconsultants to assist him. In response to Mr. Marples&apos; request forinformation about a certain aspect of the machinery of government,the Cabinet had agreed that he should be invited to tableParliamentary Questions, in reply to which Ministers would give such information as they would normally give in ParliamentaryReplies. In view of this it might be thought undesirable that ministers should supply information to Professor Rose or Mr. Headyin response to their enquiries.In discussion it appeared that some Ministers had declined to accord an interview, but others had agreed. They understood thatthe study was intended to be of government as such, and not of thecurrent Government in particular; and that any comments or factualmaterial supplied by Ministers would not be attributed to them inthe finished work. In view of this it was arguable that there would be advantage in Ministers giving an interview to Professor Rose or mr. Heady as a contribution to a greater understanding of the10524A 2
practical problems of government among academic writers on political theory. A distinction could be drawn between giving an interview to an academic writer and giving one to a journalist, sincethe academic writer, unlike the journalist, normally had no interestin attributing views to particular Ministers.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were of the opinion that each Minister should decide for himself whether to assist in this study; but those who agreed to doso should insist that in the published work particular views shouldnot be attributed to individuals.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.ParliamentaryAffairsHouse ofCommons(redistribution of Seals)(No. 2) Bill(previous reference:CC (69) 35thConclusions,Minute 1)SECRET*3. The Prime Minister said that the Group of Ministers whohad been considering how the Government might best handle theHouse of Commons (Redistribution of Seats) (No. 2) Bill had met toconsider the situation on the eve of the House of Lords debate on theCommittee Stage of the Bill and had made certain contingency plans which had been further examined that morning in the light of the heavyvote against the Government in the House of Lords. The principalquestion for consideration was whether the balance of advantage layin disposing of the Bill one way or another before the Recess, or in keeping the issue between the two Houses open until after the recess. If the House of Commons disagreed with the amendmentsby the House of Lords, and the Lords insisted on them, the bill would be dead, though it could be reintroduced in the following session. Alternatively, the Government could accept the House ofLords&apos; rejection of the Bill, lay the Orders necessary to implement the Boundary Commission^ recommendations, and use their majority in the House of Commons to defeat the Orders. It was not necessary,however, for finality to be reached: the dialogue between the two houses could be kept up by tabling a Motion in the House ofCommons to amend the Lords&apos; amendments, and the Governmentcould retain the initiative in their own hands by not discussing the motion until after the Recess. The Group of Ministers consideredthat the balance of advantage lay in the last course. After the recess a calmer atmosphere might prevail; and the fact that theBill was still before Parliament might be expected to afford grounds,at least until the Prorogation, on which a court could reject anapplication for a mandamus against the Home Secretary, shouldone be sought during the Recess.
It was possible that Left-wing supporters of the Governmentwould press for the introduction of a Bill to limit the powers of theHouse of Lords. The Group of Ministers were advised, however,that in view of the doubt which existed as to the point at which,for the purpose of the Parliament Acts, the House of Lords couldbe said to have rejected a Bill, there would be no advantage in layinga Parliament Bill before the Recess rather than after, and they recommended that this matter should be considered again in theautumn.The Home Secretary said that four courses were open to theGovernment on the House of Commons (Redistribution of Seats)(No. 2) Bill: (i) to lay and pass Orders implementing the boundary commission&apos;s recommendations;  (ii) to agree with the lords amendments to the current Bill and lay the Orders next Session;(iii) to disagree with the Lords amendments and adhere to theirdisagreement, laying a Bill to restrict the powers of the House ofLords thereafter; and (iv) to amend the Lords amendments.   he himself preferred the last course, since it offered some prospect, not of meeting the main Conservative point that  the boundary commission^ recommendations should be implemented during the lifetime of the present Parliament, but of going some way to meetan amendment moved by the Opposition in the House of commons to require him to lay the Orders by a fixed date. He now proposedthat the Bill should require the Home Secretary to reactivate the boundary Commission not later than 31st March, 1972, and permithim to do so earlier if at any time he were satisfied that this wouldnot be premature, having regard to the prospects of local government reorganisation.   The Bill would also confer an option on theSecretary of State to implement, before 31st March, 1970, therecommendations of the Boundary Commission for Scotland or for northern Ireland if it appeared reasonable to do so notwithstandingany proposals for local government reorganisation in those areas.This would enable the Secretary of State for Scotland to implement the Scottish Boundary Commission^ proposals if the report of theRoyal Commission on Local Government in Scotland (the WheatleyCommission) did not propose any considerable changes in scottish local government boundaries. Nothing in the proposed amendmentswould prejudice local government reorganisation in Wales whichwas expected to take place before that in England.In discussion some anxiety was expressed lest the link establishedby the Bill between the reorganisation of local government and thedate at which the Government had to choose between reactivatingthe Boundary Commission and laying Orders to implement the 1969reports should prejudice the thorough consideration which ought to
be given to the recommendations of the Royal Commission on LocalGovernment in England (the Redcliffe-Maud Commission) and the detailed work of preparing the legislation required to implementthem. It would be unfortunate if, in order to obtain the tacticaladvantage of securing.the agreement of the House of Lords to anamended Bill on the redistribution of seats, the long-term advantages of allowing sufficient time for the thorough preparation of the majorreform of local government were lost. It was true that if the localgovernment reorganisation were not sufficiently advanced to justifyactivating the Boundary Commission in March 1972 the Bill wouldprovide for laying Orders at that point to implement therecommendations made by the Boundary Commission in 1969. Butto implement the recommendations as late as 1972 would mean thatthe conjunction of the revision of constituency boundaries and ofthe revision of local authority boundaries would be even closer thanit would be now. On the other hand, it was urged that there was good reason to expect that the local government reorganisationwould proceed sufficiently rapidly to enable new constituency boundaries to be fixed before the next General Election but one.Where a Government had a substantial majority, it was likely toremain in office for at least A\ years; and although the timetablemight be somewhat tight, it would be possible within this period for the local government reorganisation to come into effect.Moreover, while it was necessary that the Boundary commission should consult the reorganised local authorities before publishingtheir provisional report, the authorities were likely to be elected bythe spring of 1973; and there was much preliminary work which theCommission could do, in the first place before the Order in Councilreactivating them and secondly before their provisional report hadto be published. The balance of advantage seemed therefore to lie with moving the amendments which the Home Secretary proposed.They would not wholly satisfy the Conservative Opposition, but theymight well satisfy those cross-bench Peers who had voted with the conservatives in the divisions at Committee stage; and they would assist the Government to correct the suggestions made by theOpposition that it was the Governments intention to retain theexisting constituency boundaries into the 1980s.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the balance of advantage lay in tabling the amendments proposed by the Home Secretary to the lords amendments of the House of Commons (Redistribution of Seats)(No. 2) Bill. The necessary Motion should be tabled that evening and made available to Members and to the Press at once, and theHome Secretary should explain its effect to the Parliamentary Lobby.The Motion should not be debated until after the Recess, nor shouldany decision be taken about the introduction in the following Session
NationalisedIndustriesInvestmentReview(previous reference:CC(67) 67thConclusions,Minute 4)secret. The Cabinet considered a note by the Chancellor of theExchequer (C (69) 80) covering an official review of the investment programmes of the nationalised industries from 1969-70 to 1973-74;and a memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer (C (69) 96)about reductions in these programmes in 1970-71.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that at this stage he wasasking for decisions only on the level of investment in 1970-71. the investment programmes of the nationalised industries were broadlysettled in accordance with the criteria set out in the White paper on the Nationalised Industries in 1967 (Cmnd. 3437), but a margin of choice nevertheless remained. As previously indicated, he considered that a reduction of  75 million should be found in 1970-71as a contribution to the required reduction of public sector expenditure in that year. The review by officials had alreadyidentified inter-departmentally agreed savings of  52 million. Hehad considered bilaterally with the Ministers concerned how thefurther savings required could be made with the least harmfulconsequences. He would not propose any reduction in the electricitygeneration programmes for Great Britain. Although the forecast of further demand indicated that it might be feasible to postpone the start of one power station in 1970, such a postponement would lead to a serious underload of work for the plant manufacturers,followed by an equally serious overload later. He recognised thatsome smoothing out of orders was desirable in order to maintainthe efficiency and the contribution to the trade balance of the electrical engineering industry. He would suggest a small reductionof  2 million in the Post Office investment programme ( 472 million)of a Bill on the powers of the House of Lords, though preparatory work could continue.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the Home Secretary should put down a Motionto amend the House of Lords amendments to the Houseof Commons (Redistribution of Seats) (No. 2) Bill, withthe effect which the Home Secretary had indicated, fordiscussion after the Parliamentary Recess.(2) Agreed that consideration of the introduction of a Billlimiting the powers of the House of Lords should be deferred until the autumn.
only if the full  75 million could not be found by his other proposals.But demand for telecommunication services was rising rapidly andit was therefore desirable that officials should examine, without commitment, the possibility of raising the existing financial objectivefor telecommunications. The results of this examination could beconsidered by Ministers in the context of next year&apos;s investmentreview. The future financial objectives for the electricity and gassupply industries must now be decided. He proposed that theyshould be fixed at 7 per cent, a level which would avoid the need for price increases during 1970.For 1970-71 he proposed that the investment programme of the gas supply industry should be reduced by  12 million below the levelrecommended by the Ministry of Power in the official review attachedto C (69) 80; that the programme of the British Railways board should be similarly reduced by  5 million; and that a  7 millionreduction should similarly be found from other transportprogrammes, including aviation.The Cabinet then considered the recommendations in C (69) 96relating to the individual investment programmes.The Cabinet (1) Approved the investment programme of the National coal board for 1970-71 recommended in Appendix 2 toC (69) 80.(2) Approved the investment programme of the british transport Docks Board for 1970 recommended inAppendix 13 to C (69) 80.(3) Approved the investment programme of the BritishWaterways Board for 1970 recommended in Appendix 14to C (69) 80.(4) Approved the investment programme of the TransportHolding Company for 1970 recommended in Appendix 15to C (69) 80.(5) Approved the investment programme of the National freight corporation for 1970 recommended in Appendix 16 toC (69) 80.(6) Approved a limit of  105 million on total investment by theBritish Steel Corporation for 1969-70.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that agreement had beenreached with the President of the Board of Trade that savings of between  2-55 million and  3-3 million would be found from thetotal investment programme of the Air Corporations and the british airports Authority, though certain details still remained to besettled.
CC36(69)In discussion it was suggested that the reintroduction of an airport tax on passengers on international flights might enablesubstantial additional revenue to be raised without adverse effects, ifthe technical difficulties of collection could be overcome.The Cabinet (7) Invited the President of the Board of Trade to agree withthe Chief Secretary, Treasury, on the source of savings of between  2 - 55 million and  3 - 3 million (includingsavings on the deferment of the rail link to London(Heathrow) Airport) in the investment programmes for1970-71 of the Air Corporations and the British airports authority.(8) Subject to Conclusion (7) above, approved the investment programmes for 1970-71:(i) of British Overseas Airways Corporation recom-mended in Appendix 8 to C (69) 80;(ii) of British  European  Airways  recommended inAppendix 9 to C (69) 80;(iii) of the British Airports Authority recommended inAppendix 10 to C (69) 80.(9) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultationwith the President of the Board of Trade, to give furtherconsideration to the reintroduction of an airport tax onpassengers on international flights.Transport The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had proposed cutsServices of  5 million in the 1970-71 investment programme of the british railways Board (BRB), but that the Minister of Transport had sofar felt able to agree only to a cut of  3 million. He had also proposed savings of  2-5 million in the programme of the london transport Board, including  2 million by the deferment of the newFleet line of the London underground system; he.understood theMinister of Transport would accept these cuts. He had also proposed a further cut of  0-8 million in the 1970 investment programme of the National Bus Company which had not so far beenagreed; and a further saving of  0-5 million in the 1970 investment programme of the Scottish Transport Group.In discussion it was argued that the transport services as a whole were being asked to carry an excessive share of the reductions in public sector expenditure. Moreover, the cuts now proposed would reduce facilities for public transport and would increase the pressure for a still larger road programme. In London, deferment of theFleet line would make it more difficult to offer any public transport10524
alternatives to major road works such as the controversial proposalsfor the motorway box and Ringway 2. The investment programmeof British Railways had already been cut by  10 million in the courseof discussion between the Treasury and the Ministry of Transport.A further cut of  3 million, which the Minister of Transport was prepared to accept, would involve considerable risks; the replacement of some of the 400 unsafe bridges would have to be delayed, as wouldother replacements urgently needed for safety reasons. Derailmentshad increased substantially over the past three or four years as aresult of outdated and outworn wagons and track. An additional 2 million cut would delay replacements and substantially increasethe risks of rail accidents. The proposed cut in the programme ofthe National Bus Company would lead to delay in the change-overto one-man-operated buses and to the loss of the consequentialoperating savings, although considerable concessions had recentlybeen given to the busmen in return for agreement to operate them.Moreover, under the 1968 Transport Act, the Government were offering 25 per cent grants to competing bus companies, to encourage them to renew their fleets.The Cabinet (10) Agreed that a further cut of  3 million should be made inthe British Railways Board&apos;s main investment programme for 1970 and approved a total of  77 million for that yearsubject to Conclusion (12) below.(11) Agreed that construction of the Fleet line of the LondonUnderground should be deferred for a year and, subjectto this and to Conclusion (12) below, approved the investment programme of the London Transport board for 1970 as shown in paragraph ID (iv) of Appendix L2to C (69) 80.(12) Invited the Minister of Transport to agree with the chief secretary, Treasury, the source of a further saving of 0-5 million in 1970-71 from transport investment.(13) Approved the investment programme of the National bus company for 1970 as recommended in Appendix 13 toC (69) 80.(14) Approved the investment programme for the Scottish transport Group for 1970, as shown in paragraph 14 of appendix 18 to C (69) 80; and invited the Secretary ofState for Scotland, in consultation with the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer, to consider how savings of 0-5 million should be found.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had reached agreement with the Minister of Power on a reduction of  12 million in the investment programmes of the gas industry. He also invited
the Cabinet to agree with a view to the early fixing of its financial objective at 7 per cent net per annum on average net capital employed for the period 1969-70 to 1973-74 inclusive.The Minister of Power said that he had reluctantly agreed to thereduction proposed. A financial objective of 7 per cent would not involve consequential price increases before 1971, and he would make clear to the Chairman of the Gas Council that this was his consideredview.The Cabinet (15) Agreed that a reduction of  12 million should be made inthe investment programme of the gas industry for1970-71, and approved the programme recommended inparagraph 11 (ii) of Appendix 6 to C (69) 80.(16) Invited the Minister of Power to open discussions with the gas industry, with a view to fixing a financial objective of  per cent net per annum on average net capital employed for the five years from 1st April, 1969.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, for reasons whichhe had already explained, he was not proposing any reduction in the investment programmes for the electricity industry. He also invited the Cabinet to agree to the opening of discussions with the industry with a view to the early fixing of a financial objective for theelectricity industry in England and Wales of 7 per cent net per annumon average net capital employed from 1969-70 to 1973-74, andfinancial objectives for Scottish electricity in the light of the decisionon England and Wales.The Minister of Power said that a 7 per cent objective shouldnot lead to any consequential price increases before 1971, and hewould make known to the Chairman of the Electricity Council thatthis was his considered view.In discussion it was argued, on the one hand, that it would be wrong to agree without further consideration to a start being madein 1970 on a power station in England. It was not needed to meetthe estimated demand, and the argument that the order should beplaced then to smooth the flow of work to the plant manufacturersseemed inadequate justification, in view of the reductions beingmade in public expenditure on other services such as education and health. On the other hand, it was argued that if the station were notordered, there would be a very real risk of undermining the stability and export potential of the heavy electrical industry, and that the plant manufacturers might reduce their capacity. This in turn might lead to serious shortages of equipment and an increase in imports
and loss of exports in future years, when a number of power stationprojects would have to be undertaken concurrently. In any event,it should be possible to find reductions totalling  10 million in theelectricity programmes as a whole, particularly those of the area boards, without deferring the start of new power stations.The Cabinet (17) Invited the Minister of Power and the Secretary of Statefor Scotland to consider, in consultation with the chief secretary, Treasury, and the Minister of Technology,whether savings of  10 million might be made in the programmes of the electricity industry without deferringthe start of a power station in 1970.(18) Subject to Conclusion (17), approved the electricity(England and Wales) investment programme for 1970-71as recommended in Appendix 3 to C (69) 80.(19) Subject to Conclusion (17) above, approved the investment programmes of the South of Scotland Electricity Boardand the North of Scotland Hydro-Electric Board for1970-71, as recommended in Appendix 4 and Appendix 5to C (69) 80.(20) Invited the Minister of Power to open discussions with theelectricity industry in England and Wales with a view tothe early fixing of a financial objective of 7 per cent net perannum on average net capital employed for the five years from 1st April, 1969.(21) Invited the Secretary of State for Scotland, in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer, to consider the setting of financial objectives for Scottish electricity inthe light of the decision on England and Wales.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, in spite of the rapid growth of investment in the Post Office, he had hoped to avoidhaving to ask for reductions in this programme. Demand for expansion of telecommunications facilities was high; investment here was profitable; and it provided substantial employment in thedevelopment areas. In view, however, of the Cabinefs decisions notto make all the savings he had proposed in investment by the nationalised transport industries, he now felt he must ask for amarginal reduction of  2 million here. At the same time he felt thatas demand for Post Office services was rising, officials should examinethe possibility of setting a higher financial objective (possibly % percent) for telecommunications, implying some rise in telephone charges in the longer term.In discussion, there was general agreement that the financial objective for telecommunications should be reviewed, possibly with
a view to fixing it even higher than 9^ per cent. It was, however,suggested that rather than cut investment, it would be preferable inthe short term to increase the maximum connection charge for domestic telephones to  50. This might, however, raise difficultiesof social policy which would have to be carefully considered.The Cabinet (22) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer in consultationwith the Postmaster-General and other ministers concerned, to consider how  2 million might be providedby reductions in the investment programme of the PostOffice or by increases in charges and to report the outcometo the Cabinet if necessary.(23) Subject to Conclusion (22) above, approved the investment programme of the Post Office as recommended inparagraphs 9 (i), 14 and 18 of Appendix 1 to C (69) 80.(24) Invited the Postmaster-General, in consultation with theChancellor of the Exchequer, to arrange for officials to review the financial objective for telecommunications.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,24th July, 1969.




</content>
</cab>
