<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/44/0 images: 540-555</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1970CC (69)39th Conclusions Copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Wednesday, 30th July, 1969,at 10.30 am.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, mp, Prime minister the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,m p, Secretary of State for foreign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner, lord chancellor the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Employment and productivity the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. George Thomson,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, mp, Minister of technology the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. George Thomas, m p,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Judith Hart, mp,Paymaster GeneralThe Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, mp,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. James Callaghan,mp, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Peter Shore, mp,Secretary of State for economic affairs the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Edward Short, mp,Secretary of State for Education and science the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Lord Shackleton,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Roy Mason, mp,Minister of Power
The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Stonehouse,m p, Postmaster-General (Items 3and 4)Mr. John Morris, m p, Minister ofDefence for Equipment (item 4)The Right Hon. Robert Mellish, m p,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury mr. Roy Hattersley, mp, Ministerof Defence for Administration(Item 5)The Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, q c,m p, Attorney-General (Item 4)Secretariat:Sir Burke trend miss J. J. nunn mr. R. R. D. mcintosh sir Robin hooper mr. G. F. KearMr. G. P. PrattContentsItem Subject page 1      Parliamentary Affairs      ...............       3Divorce Reform BillPermanent Abolition of Capital Punishment for MurderLegislative Programme 1969-702       Oversea Affairs     ..................       3AnguillaEuropeNigeriaMr. Gerald BrookeMiddle East3      Industrial Disputes..................      7Post Office Engineering Union Pay ClaimPay Negotiations in the London Docks4      Public Records       .........     ...     ......     10Timing and Method of Release of Records of the1939-45 war      Northern Ireland    ......    &apos;............     11
ParliamentaryAffairsDivorceReform Bill(previous reference:CC (69) 31stConclusions,Minute 1)PermanentAbolition ofCapitalPunishmentfor Murder(previous reference:CC (69) 24thConclusions,Minute 7)LegislativeProgramme1969-70(previous reference:CC (69) 19thConclusions,Minute 5)CC39(69)confidential. The Cabinet were informed that it was proposed that the1969-70 Session of Parliament should be opened on 28th October.The remainder of the present Session&apos;s business might well occupy the House of Commons for the two previous weeks.In discussion attention was drawn to the possibility thatGovernment time might have to be found to deal with the Houseof Lords amendments to the Divorce Bill.The Home Secretary recalled that the Cabinet had invited theSecretary of State for Scotland and himself on 22nd May (o moveduring the remainder of the Session the resolutions required underthe Murder (Abolition of Death Penally) Act 1965 to continuepermanently the abolition of capital punishment. The precise timing of this would require further consideration in September.The Lord Privy Seal drew attention to the importance of introducing Bills suitable for introduction in the House of Lordsduring the early part of the Session so as to avoid the congestion of business in the House of Lords during the summer.OverseaAffairsAnguilla(previous reference:CC(69) 35thConclusions,Minute 2)secret. The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that, before leaving Anguilla on his resignation, HM Commissioner, Mr. Cumber,had submitted a report on the situation. This was being studied inthe Foreign and Commonwealth Office and Ministry of Defence,who were also considering the possibility of withdrawing withoutreplacement the paratroops at present stationed in the island, if thesituation permitted. Consideration would also be given, inconsultation with the Home Secretary, to reducing the MetropolitanPolice contingent or withdrawing it altogether. As it would bedifficult to bring the matter to the Defence and Oversea PolicyCommittee or the Cabinet during the Recess, he suggested that any decisions which might be necessary during the Recess should be taken
by the Prime Minister, himself, the Home Secretary and the defence secretary.The Cabinet (1) Took note of the statement by the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary.(2) Agreed that any questions which might arise during the recess in regard to force levels in Anguilla, or theMetropolitan Police contingent there, should be taken onthe basis proposed by the Foreign and commonwealth secretary.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that at themeeting of the Foreign Ministers of the six countries of the european economic Community (e.c.) held at Brussels on 22nd July, theFrench Foreign Minister, M. Maurice Schumann, had proposed thata summit meeting of the Six should be held to discuss the enlargement of the Community. The other five countries had not objected to thisproposal, but had pointed out that the enlargement of theCommunity and its development should be considered together. Atthe meeting, the Commission of the European Communities hadbeen instructed to bring up to date their 1967 &quot; opinion &quot; regardingthe admission of the United Kingdom to the e.c.. On the whole the meeting had gone well and the Netherlands Foreign Minister,Mr. Luns, had expressed himself as well pleased with its results.The Cabinet (3) Took note of the statement by the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary.(4) Agreed to discuss the problem of Britain&apos;s entry into the eec further after the Recess.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that theInternational Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC) had reached agreement with the Nigerian Federal Military Government (FMG)on a relief flight of three or four aircraft direct from Cotonou to theairstrip at Uli in the territory held by the secessionists. The ICRCwere now seeking the approval of the secessionist leader, colonel ojukwu, and it was difficult to see how Colonel Ojukwu could object.So far as regular daylight relief flights were concerned, the ICRChad enlisted the support of the Vatican and the Roman Catholicrelief organisation &quot; Caritas&quot; in bringing pressure to bear onColonel Ojukwu to authorise these; but the prospects of securing his consent were not good. There had been some night relief flights,but these had not followed the routes agreed by the FMG, and hadtaken place against the latter&apos;s wishes. The FMG had agreed inprinciple to discuss the opening-up of a supply route by ship via the
Cross River with secessionist representatives at a private meeting in geneva; and we had had some part in promoting this. Meanwhile,two river craft were in Lagos harbour loaded and ready to sail withprotein and medical supplies for a month. The Head of the FMG,General Gowon, would not be attending the meeting to be heldshortly in Kampala by President Obote of Uganda; but he wassending two Federal Commissioners, one of whom would beChief Enahoro. The meeting would also be attended by the administrator of the Eastern Region. This would be a usefulpropaganda point, as the Administrator was an Ibo.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary drew attention tothe attack by secessionist forces on the Shell-British Petroleum Howstation at Kokori and the continued activities of Count von Rosen,the Swedish soldier of fortune who was conducting air attacks on targets in Federal territory with light aircraft flown by mercenarypilots and armed in France. The Ministries of Defence and Power,together with the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, were consultingwith Shell regarding the defence of the latter&apos;s installations against air attack. The Swedish Government had banned the export of aircraft to Count von Rosen and to the insurgents, but he had beenable to obtain aircraft and armaments in France. The swedish government had also attempted to curb Count von Rosen&apos;s activities,but had been unable to find any legal basis for doing so.The Prime Minister, summing up a brief discussion, emphasised the importance of Nigerian oil to our balance of payments, it was likely that Shell (though not necessarily the FMG itself) wouldapproach the Government for advice and assistance on the defenceof their installations in Nigeria; and the Foreign and commonwealth secretary and Defence Secretary, in consultation with the Ministerof Power, should discuss with Shell arrangements for air defence withminimum involvement on the part of Her MajestyV Government.Any action which might prove necessary would be taken, with his approval, by the Ministers concerned. Public presentation was important, and we should avoid giving the opponents of our Nigerianpolicy any pretext for drawing unfavourable comparisons between our alleged indifference to starvation in Biafra and our zeal in protecting our oil interests.The Cabinet-(5) Took   note   of   the   statement   by   the   Foreign   and commonwealth Secretary.(6) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.
Mr. GeraldBrooke(previous reference:CC (69) 35thConclusions,Minute 2)*The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that some ofthe statements made by Mr. Brooke since his return to the UnitedKingdom, in particular during his appearance on television, had-beeninterpreted as implying that his activities had been less innocuousthan had previously been generally believed. On the other hand,it had always been known that he had been acting for an anti-Communist organisation in this country, though it had not been generally known until his return that he had taken with him codinginstructions for contacts in the Soviet Union as well as distributingpropaganda leaflets. Mr. Brooke had clearly been indiscreet. Inparticular, by undertaking during his imprisonment to transmitmessages from his fellow prisoners to other Russians, he had laidhimself open to serious further charges under Soviet law. But therewas of course no question of his being a British intelligence agent,or indeed a spy of any kind. He had returned from imprisonmentin a state of some nervous tension, and the possibility that he hadbeen subjected to a form of &quot; brain-washing &quot; could not be excluded.Full reliance could not be placed on all his statements, though itmight be possible as time went on to obtain a more coherent andaccurate account from him. But it was already clear that, even if all his statements about his activities before his arrest were true, the actions which had afforded the pretext for the original charge against him would not have constituted an offence under British law.In a brief discussion, the following points were made (a) It would not have been possible to prevent Mr. Brookeappearing on television, or to control what he said during his interview. Any attempt to do so would have been counter-productive.(b) The exchange of Mr. Brooke for Mr. and Mrs. Kroger hadbeen criticised on the ground that we had been handed a comparativeinnocent in exchange for two important agents. Mr. Brooke&apos;sstatements might do something to suggest that he was of more importance-at any rate in Soviet eyes and that the bargain wasa less unequal one than had previously been supposed.(c) On several occasions, Ministers visiting the Soviet Union hadbeen asked to make representations on behalf of Mr. Brooke. Theyhad always done so on the basis that Mr. Brooke had been guiltyonly of the comparatively minor indiscretion of distributingpropaganda material. Should it be established that there was some basis of fact for the statements he had made since his return, theMinisters concerned might retrospectively be placed in an awkwardposition.The Cabinet-(7) Took   note   of  the   statement   by   the   Foreign   and commonwealth Secretary and of the points made in discussion.* Previously recorded as a Confidential Annex.
confidential. The Cabinet considered memoranda by the Postmaster-General on the pay of grades represented by the Post office engineering Union (POEU) and on the effects of industrial action by the POEU in support of their current pay claim (C (69) 109 and110); and by the Lord Privy Seal on the possible repercussions ofa settlement of the POEU pay claim (C (69) 111).The Postmaster-General said that the Post Office was faced witha claim by the POEU for a 10 per cent increase, to take effect from 1st July, 1969. The claim was based partly on comparability andpartly on productivity. The POEU grades were also due to havea comprehensive pay review in 1970 with an operative date of1st January. The Ministerial Committee on Prices and Incomes had authorised him in June to offer, without prejudice, 5 per cent basedsolely on productivity. The Union rejected this and carried out a one-day strike on 14th July. The Committee had then authorised him to increase his offer to 7 per cent, and later 8J per cent; but hehad not in fact offered the Union anything above 7 per cent,The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that he had been considering whether any initiative could usefully be taken within the framework of the Four-Power talks on the Arab-Israel problembetween the representatives on the Security Council of the UnitedKingdom, the United States, France and the Soviet Union. the talks were temporarily in abeyance pending the outcome of bilateral discussions between the United States and Russia; and it was unlikelythat there would be any movement on this until September, when hewould be taking soundings at the meeting of the United nations general Assembly. Meanwhile, incidents between the two sidescontinued. We had urged restraint on both parties and were inconsultation with France and the United States on how best the temperature might be lowered.The Prime Minister said that the question of a British initiative in the Four-Power talks had been discussed by the Defence and oversea Policy Committee on 28th July. He would also be discussing the matter with the United States President when Mr. Nixon landed in this country on 3rd August on his way home from his tour ofRumania and South-East Asia.The Cabinet-(8) Took note of the statements by the Prime Minister and theForeign and Commonwealth Secretary.
accompanied by a concession on overtime hours which had been authorised by the Committee. The POEU, who had been veryco-operative in the past on productivity and other matters, were nowin a militant mood. A further strike would have very damaging consequences for telecommunications services. He proposed thatwhen meeting the POEU on the following day he should beauthorised either to offer 7 per cent from 1st July, 1969, with aguarantee of at least a further 3 per cent on 1st January, 1970; or tooffer to call in an independent arbitrator on the Union&apos;s claim and tobring forward the start of the projected pay research study, while leaving the operative date at 1st January, 1970. If the Union rejectedboth these offers he would like authority, in agreement with theChancellor of the Exchequer and the First Secretary of State, tooffer 8 per cent from 1st July with a further 2 per cent from 1st January, 1970.The Lord Privy Seal said that to offer the POEU 10 per centor anything approaching that figure would have serious repercussions in the non-industrial Civil Service and elsewhere. It would mean that over a period of about three years POEU members would receive an increase of 28 per cent, compared with 14 per cent fornon-industrial technicians who were their nearest analogues. Togive way to the POEU&apos;s demands would encourage the existing trendstowards militancy among the Civil Service unions. A strike wouldnot necessarily have such damaging consequences especially as thePOEU had no strike funds. In any case, if there had to beconcessions, it would be best for these to be made after a strike hadtaken place, and not simply under the threat of militant action.In discussion, the importance of adhering to traditionalnegotiating procedures was emphasised. The right course was todetermine in advance the maximum figure for which the Governmentwould be prepared to settle and to insist on the matter going to arbitration if the Union rejected this. The principle of comparabilityhad many advantages from the employer^ standpoint and should notbe lightly abandoned.Against this, it was pointed out that the POEU had themselvessuggested arbitration with a view to securing an award on grounds of comparability and then exacting a price for every futureconcession on productivity, on which they had previously been veryco-operative.In further discussion it was suggested that there were good prospects of reaching a settlement on the basis of 8 per cent from 1st July, 1969, to which any increases from the pay review in January1970 would be added. On the other hand, it was urged that therepercussive effect of yielding to militancy should not be under-rated;even if the Government were forced to make concessions in the end,
The CabinetPayNegotiationsin theLondonDocks(1) Invited the Postmaster General, if his proposed 7 per centpay increase was rejected, to offer the POEU in additiona guarantee of a further increase from 1st January, 1970,of at least 3 per cent, as the outcome of the forthcomingcomprehensive pay review, together with the prospect ofan early start on the review.The First Secretary of State said that, although agreement hadbeen reached some time ago on the pay for work at the new containerterminal at Tilbury of Overseas Containers Limited and AssociatedContainer Transportation, representatives of the No. I Docks group of the Transport and General Workers Union (TGWU) had refusedto ratify the agreement lor work at the terminal until negotiations were completed on the second stage of the dock modernisationprogramme. In June, the employers had refused to proceed withthese negotiations unless the Tilbury container terminal agreement was ratified; but at a joint meeting in her Department on 10th July,they had offered to resume the negotiations with a commitment toreach a settlement and put it into effect by 1st October, 1969, togetherwith certain other concessions to the trade unions, provided that theTilbury container agreement was accepted. The No. I Docks Grouprepresentatives had not accepted this offer, and a further meeting ofthe two sides would take place on Thursday, at which the port employers proposed to reaffirm their decision of last June and, ifthis failed to convince the trade union representatives, to make publictheir offer of 10th July. If this were to happen, there might be agood deal of trouble at docks throughout the country, but the presentseemed to be the least harmful time for any such consequences.Despite a natural suspicion of the port employers&apos; real intentionsit was important that they should not appear to have given in tooeasily.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that although some members of the Cabinet considered that the right course was to stand firm on 7 per cent, the general view was thatif the POEU rejected this the Postmaster General should beauthorised to offer in addition a guarantee that they would receive a further increase of at least 3 per cent from 1st January, 1970, asa result of the forthcoming pay review. If it were likely to be helpfulhe could also point out to the unions that it would be open to thenew Post Office Corporation, which would be conducting negotiationsafter 1st October, 1969, to start the pay research review before theend of the year.
and of their hitherto faulty judgment, she proposed to let themproceed as they proposed, in the hope that at the meeting or thereafter the dockers might be brought to see the advantages for them of theTilbury container terminal agreement and of permitting further progress with the second stage of the modernisation programme.She would arrange to be consulted about the terms in which theport employers made their proposed public announcement. Therewas no need to take steps to prepare for a full-scale emergency,since industrial action was not likely to be more than sporadic atleast for some little time.The Cabinet (2) Took note of the statement by the First Secretary of State.PublicRecordsTiming and method of release ofRecordsof the1939-45 WarCONFIDENTIAL4. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Secretary ofthe Cabinet (C (69) 102) covering a memorandum on (he timing and method of the release of the records of the 1939-45 War.The memorandum proposed that, in order to avoid the inconvenience to historians which would result from the normalapplication to the records of the 1939-45 War of the Thirty YearRule, further complicated by the assembly rule under the PublicRecords Act, which would result in the papers becoming availablepiecemeal over some six years, those which were known fromexperience to be most in public demand (the &quot; cream &quot; papers) shouldbe opened together in 1972. Those Departments which could releasepapers, whether among the &quot; cream &quot; or not, on the normal dateunder the Thirty Year Rule where this was earlier than 1972, would do so; and where the concentration of the available resources onthe scrutiny and release of the &quot; cream &quot; papers involved a delay inthe opening of other papers, the delay could be authorised underSection 5(1) of the Public Records Act. The arrangements were designed to achieve the release of the papers en bloc, with theminimum increase in the staff required to carry out the necessaryscrutiny of the papers and the identification of those which must bekept closed for a longer period. Most Departments believed thatthey could carry out the task within their present stall&apos; complement;but the Foreign and Commonwealth Office would require somereinforcement, and the Public Record Office would also need some extra staff, most of them immediately before the opening date. Ifthe Cabinet agreed to the proposed arrangements in principle, itwould be necessary to consult &quot; old&quot; Commonwealth countriesabout the release of shared papers and to inform certain Governmentswho also had an interest in the opening of the papers. The Leaders
NorthernIreland(previous reference:CC(69) 24thConclusions,Minute 2)SECRET*5. The Cabinet considered memoranda by the Secretary ofStale for the Home Department (C (69) 108) and by the Ministerof Defence for Administration (C (69) 107) about developments inNorthern Ireland.The Home Secretary said that, when the Apprentice Boys of londonderry held their annual parade on 12th August, there was a prospect of more severe disorders than since the recent unrest began in Northern Ireland. Four times as many people as usual were expected to participate. The event was so well established and onsuch a scale that any attempt to ban it would provoke more trouble.Although the underlying trend was for moderate opinion torecognise that the Northern Ireland Government were serious intheir pursuit of reforming policies and for leaders of all but theextreme factions to be willing to join together to prevent violence,the events of the weekend of 12th-13th July had shown howsuddenly and graveiy violence could erupt. The situation was placinga severe strain on the Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC), on whoseefficiency we depended if British troops were not to be involved in maintaining law and order. He was concerned therefore that theRUC should have every reasonable means to carry out their dutiesunaided. For this purpose tear gas could be vital; and its use bythe RUC would be preferable to the intervention of British troops.On Sunday, 13th July, the Northern Ireland Government hadrenewed more urgently an earlier request for supplies of the CS typeof tear gas which was less harmful than the CN type which theof the Opposition Parlies would also be consulted, and, subject toThe QueerTs consent being obtained to the disclosure of cabinet papers, an announcement could then be made in the autumn.In discussion there was general agreement with the proposed arrangements for Ihe earlier release of the records of the 1939-45War. It was emphasised that the ability of the Foreign and commonwealth Office and of the Public Record Ollicc to complywith the proposed timetable would depend on (he willingness of theCivil Service Department to agree to the necessary increases of stall&apos;where these could not be found within the present limits.The cabinet approved the proposals in C (69) 102.
RUC already held. He had agreed, in the light of the situation at that time, and with the concurrence of the Prime Minister andthe Defence Secretary, that CS gas should be supplied from Servicestocks, on the condition that its use would be subject on each occasion to the specific and prior approval of the Northern Ireland Ministerof Home Affairs, and that it would be used only if the RUC hadexhausted all other means of controlling a disorderly crowd andwould otherwise have to open fire or call for assistance from Britishtroops. The decision had been ratified by the Group of ministers who had been considering the Northern Ireland situation and he asked the Cabinet to endorse it. We were assured that CN gaswould not now be used.A deputation of Members of Parliament had suggested that either he or representatives of the Home Office should visit NorthernIreland as observers, but he had persuaded them that to go would merely involve him more deeply in the issues which divided theProvince. Likewise, he thought that the suggestion that the PrimeMinister should go there was ill considered.The Minister of Defence for Administration said that NorthernIreland officials had raised informally with the Home Office thepossibility of using Wessex helicopters, at present stationed inNorthern Ireland, for the emergency transport of members of theRUC to a trouble spot where their presence was essential to keepthe peace. It had also been suggested that Army Sioux helicoptersshould be used to observe and report to the police on crowdmovements. His view was that, while it was right to try to ensurethat the RUC were equipped to control the situation, in the hopethat intervention by British troops would be obviated, the overt useof Army helicopters in circumstances where law and order had notbroken down would be dangerously provocative. The informalrequest had been made in the hope that, if the United KingdomGovernment turned it down, this would forestall a public request;he could not however guarantee that the Northern ireland government would not make a public request.The 1st Battalion The Prince of Wales&apos; Own Regiment ofYorkshire (1 /PWO) had been sent to Northern Ireland in April thisyear as an addition to the normal garrison to assist in guardingvulnerable points against sabotage. It was planned that all vulnerable points should be handed back to the RUC by 2nd August, and the battalion understood that they would return to Great Britain not later than 22nd August, in accordance with the assurances given them that their posting to Northern Ireland would be for not morethan four months.&apos; It had to be decided, therefore, whether 1 / PWOshould be replaced by another battalion. It was difficult to foretellwhether an extra battalion would still be needed, but it would berash to deplete the forces in Northern Ireland just after the
Apprentice Boys&apos; parade. He proposed therefore that 1/PWOshould be withdrawn as planned on about 18th-22nd August, and replaced immediately by another battalion who should be warnedto prepare for the move.In discussion it was suggested that circumstances might arise inwhich it would be right to provide Service helicopters to move RUCreinforcements, notwithstanding that the situation did not warrant the participation of British forces generally. It was also pointed outthat the police might be so embroiled in a dangerous riot that theycould not obtain the authority of the Minister of Home Affairsbefore they were obliged to resort to the use of tear gas; neverthelessthis condition would serve a useful restraining purpose.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theGroup of Ministers had considered that the use of troops to assistthe civil power would raise fundamental constitutional issues. TheHome Secretary had therefore sought by every means to avoid their use save for guarding certain vital installations. It was to reduce thepossibility of the use of troops that the Group had ratified thedecision to supply CS gas to the RUC on the conditions described&apos;by the Home Secretary; and the Cabinet now endorsed that decision.They agreed that Service helicopters should not be made availableto the RUC either to transport reinforcements or for spotting crowdmovements. There would be advantage however in the NorthernIreland Government exploring the possibility of hiring civilianhelicopters. 1/PWO should be withdrawn as proposed on about18th-22nd August and replaced immediately by another battalion,who should be given adequate notice. Neither the Home Secretarynor representatives of the Home Office should go to Northern ireland as observers, nor would he go there himself. We had had considerable success in persuading the Northern Ireland Governmentto introduce measures of reform; the present outbreaks of violencewere the work of hooligans and members of the Irish republican army rather than a manifestation of serious political grievances.But the underlying causes of unrest-bad housing and unemployment could not be removed overnight. Furthermore Captain 0&apos;Neill,the former Prime Minister of Northern Ireland, had warned thatsome Unionist members in both the Stormont and WestminsterParliaments might be subjected to increasing pressure from right wingextremists to dissociate themselves from the present reformist policyof the Northern Ireland Government. In the long term, therefore, thesituation could raise grave constitutional issues. He, with the HomeSecretary, the Defence Secretary and the Foreign and commonwealth secretary, if available, should be authorised to take any decisionurgently required while Ministers could not be called together.
The Cabinet-(1) Agreed (a) that supplies of CS gas should continue to be madeavailable to the RUC on the conditions alreadyspecified by the Home Secretary;(b) that Service helicopters should not be made availablefor use by the RUC;(c) that the 1st Battalion the Prince of Wales OwnRegiment should be relieved in mid-August by another battalion on a four month tour of duty;(d) that it would not at present be appropriate for thePrime Minister, the Home Secretary or HomeOffice observers to visit Northern Ireland.(2) Authorised the Prime Minister, the Home Secretary, theDefence Secretary and, if available, the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary to take any decisions urgently required.Cabinet Office, S.WJ,31st July, 1969.



</content>
</cab>
