<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/44/0 images: 572-583</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1973CC (69) Copy No. 0 342nd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10  Downing Street, S.W.1., on Thursday 4 September, 1969,at 3 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,m i&apos;, Secretary of State for foreign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. James Callaghan,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Peter Shore,  m p,Secretary of State for economic affairs the Right Hon. William Ross, m p,Secretary of  State   for  scotland the Right Hon. Edward Short, m p,Secretary of State for Education and science the Right Hon. Richard Marsh,m p, Minister of transport the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Minister of Agriculture, Fish-eries and food the Right Hon. George Thomas, m p,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Barbara Castle,m p, First Secretary of State and secretary of State for employment and productivity the Right Hon. Fred Peart, m p,Lord   President   of   the   council the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m i&apos;, President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. George Thomson,m p, Minister without portfolio the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Minister of technology the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. Lord Shackleton,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Roy Mason, mp.Minister of power the Right Hon. Judith Hart, m p,Paymaster General
The following were also present:The Right Hon. Robert Mellish, m p,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury mr. Roy Hattersley, m p, Ministerof Defence for administration the Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones,q c, mp, Attorney-General (items and 2)secretariat sir Burke trend . R. R. D. mcintosh sir Robin hooper mr. P. E. thornton mr. J. C. W. BushellContentsItem Subject page 1     Oversea Affairs        ...............      3LibyaCzechoslovakiaMulti-Role Combat Aircraft2     Northern Ireland       ............      ...      53     Equal Pay        .............     ......       54     Industrial Affairs      ...............      7National Newspaper Price Increases
&apos; 1. The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that the newRevolutionary Council in Libya (RCC) now seemed to be in controlof the country, including the town of Tobruk where it had at onetime looked as though there might be some pro-royalist resistance.There had been no hostile demonstrations against the UnitedKingdom or British subjects. The RCC had stated that they wouldhonour Libya&apos;s international obligations and had addressed a warmmessage of friendship to the British Government. On the other hand,they had closed ports and airports. This presented a problem for us at El Adem, where it was our intention to maintain routine flights.There had been no interruption in the flow of oil and none was expected.The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that it was important to be on good terms with whatever Government controlledLibya. BP and Shell had an investment in the country of about  100million and our exports to Libya were running at an annual rateof  34 million.   Meanwhile he had received a visit from OmarShelhi, the personal emissary of King Idris, who had urged thatwe should intervene in Libya to save lives and property and to restore the King.  This was not a proposition that we need considerseriously; the visit had however aroused some criticism in Libya.It had been explained to the RCC that the interview had taken place at Shelhi&apos;s request and it was hoped that criticism would now diedown.   It was not to be excluded that the King might still have some part to play.   His presence might be required to hold thedisparate parts of the country together.   Consideration was nowbeing given to the possibility that Sir Duncan Gumming, a formerGovernor of Cyrenaica, might be sent to visit the King in Athens,provided that this could be achieved with complete secrecy.   Asregards recognition, the RCC appeared to be reaching one of the criteria which we considered necessary, namely, effective control ofthe country. All the evidence was that they were likely to remain in control, and our diplomatic mission on the spot was strongly infavour of recognition.   On the other hand, the name of only one member of the RCC was known to us, Colonel Abu Shuwayrib,and he might well prove to be only a figurehead.  It was difficultto extend recognition to a Government without knowing how it wasmade up and whether, for example, it would be a military regime.HM Charge d&apos;Affaires was being instructed to make a friendlyapproach to the regime, telling them about our criteria for recogni-tion and asking them to let us have information about themselves,the nature of their Government and their policies.  If the answerswere satisfactory, we might accord recognition over the weekend.Apart from the political and economic considerations involved the matter was of some urgency for us, since our new Ambassador,whose agreement had been granted by the previous Government, waswaiting to proceed to his post.   His doing so would of course initself constitute recognition.  We were in touch with the americans and the other members of the Western European Union about thequestion of recognition.   It was likely that the Americans, while not disagreeing with us, would be inclined to go more slowly.
The possibility of a coup d&apos;etat in Libya had always been on thecards the King was now 80 and it was difficult to suppose that the regime created by him would continue after his death. But therehad been nothing to indicate that it would occur at this particularmoment.The Minister without Portfolio said that he had just returned from a visit to the President of the United Arab Republic (UAR),Colonel Nasser, who appeared to have been taken by surprise.This was perhaps borne out by his remark that the Egyptians had sought to check on the success of the coup by monitoring Libyanpolice and army communications networks rather than by sendingemissaries to the RCC. As regards the Arab-Israel questiongenerally, he had come away with the impression that the president had a realistic appreciation of the risk that the UAR would suffera second military humiliation if the present situation was allowed toescalate to full-scale fighting.In the course of a brief discussion it was noted that an early decision would be required about certain heavy arms, includingChieftain tanks, which we were due to deliver to Libya shortly. Itwas also noted that if our troops at present in Libya had to be withdrawn, they could be rehoused in Germany.The Cabinet-(1) Took note of the statements by the Foreign and Common-wealth Secretary and the Minister without Portfolio.(2) Agreed that the question of arms deliveries to Libya shouldbe further considered in the Defence and Oversea PolicyCommittee.Czechoslovakia The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary said that the Sovietgrip on Czechoslovakia appeared to be tightening and that theposition of Dubcek was increasingly precarious. A number ofBritish subjects had been in trouble with the Czechoslovak author-ities at the time of the anniversary disturbances but only one hadbeen detained. We were seeking consular access to him.The Cabinet-(3)  Took note of the statement by the Foreign and Common-wealth Secretary.The Minister of Technology said that he had just been informedthat the contract for the engines for the Multi-Role Combat aircraft had been awarded to Rolls-Royce. The news would not be made public until midnight on 4 September in order to give theGermans time to inform the United States Government since an american firm (Pratt and Whitney) had also tendered for this contract.The Cabinet-(4)  Took note of the statement by the Minister of Technology.(previous reference:CC (68) 42ndConclusions,Minute 2)Multi-RoleCombatAircraft(previous reference:CC (69) 22ndConclusions,Minute 7)
NorthernIreland(previous reference :CC (69) 41stConclusions)SECRETEqual pay 3.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the first secretary of State and Secretary of State for Employment and productivity on equal pay to which was attached a report by officials on the economic and social implications of equal pay for women(C (69) 113).The First Secretary of State said that of. the seven items listed in the chapter on workers&apos; rights in the 1964 election manifestoequal pay was the only one on which no move had yet been made.In June 1968 she had told the House of Commons that she wouldbe entering into discussions with the Confederation of British Industry(CBI) and the Trades Union Congress (TUC) with a view to agreeinga timetable for the phased introduction of equal pay over an appro-priate period. As a result of these discussions she had arranged fora survey of the cost of equal pay in a number of industries to becarried out. The results of the survey had now been analysed and formed an important part of the raw material for the report by officials. Pressure for equal pay was mounting steadily and it was clear that trade union leaders could not resist it even if they wanted to. Employers would increasingly be compelled to concede equal payin the course of normal pay negotiations and the Government now had to decide whether to let equal pay come as a result of sporadicaction or as a controlled operation in which the economic disadvan-tages were minimised.The cost of introducing equal pay depended on the timing anddefinition used. She proposed that legislation should be enacted in the next Session under which equal pay would be introduced overa five-year period ending on 31st December, 1975, possibly with provision that the differential between men&apos;s and women&apos;s wages should not exceed a given percentage by the end of 1973. Sheproposed that the definition used should be &quot; equal pay for the samework &quot;; this was the definition adopted by the European economic commission and we should have to use it if we became members ofthe European Economic Community. On that definition officials had estimated, on a very conservative basis, that there would be an addition to the national wage and salary bill of about 5 per cent.This would imply a cost to the balance of payments of some 350 million: but if as was in her view not improbable the additionto the wage bill were only 3 per cent, the cost to the balance ofpayments might be less than  200 million. The TUC would clearly not accept that increases resulting from the introduction of equal pay should be accommodated within any norm set for the purposes of incomes policy and there would accordingly need to be a specific141771-2b*2. The Cabinet discussed the situation in Northern Ireland; theconclusions reached were separately recorded and circulated onlyto The Queen, the Prime Minister and those Ministers who had totake action.The conclusions are recorded separately in the standard file held by the Secretary of the Cabinet.
exception for it in any criteria laid down in the White Paper on prices and Incomes which was to be published later in the year. She wouldbe seeing the TUC in the following week and the CBI shortly afterwards and would have to inform them of the governments intentions on equal pay. In her view it was no longer possible tostall; they must either fulfil the expectations which had been arousedor say publicly and firmly that they could not go ahead in the present economic situation. She recommended that they should proceed onthe lines set out in the paper and that she should be authorised toinform the TUC accordingly next week.In discussion it was generally agreed that there was a strong case in equity for introducing equal pay and that the Governmentwere committed to make an early move in this direction. It was,however, pointed out that while 5 per cent was probably a realisticestimate of the addition to the wage and salary bill, it was by nomeans an absolute maximum much would depend on the rate atwhich the differential between men&apos;s and women&apos;s wages was reduced.Moreover, the balance of payments cost would be substantial unlessmale workers were prepared to moderate their own demands to accommodate substantial increases for women. It was unrealistic to suppose that they would do this and therefore the policy would carry with it a need to increase taxation, reduce the growth of public expenditure and run the economy with a higher level of unemploy-ment than would otherwise be necessary. An early decision to implement equal pay by the end of 1975 would have little effect onthe economy in the next 18 months but it would pre-empt substantialresources in the period 1971-75 and would accordingly limit the government&apos;s freedom of manoeuvre in the next Parliament. Theeffect on the distribution of incomes between families would be considerable and in some cases regressive. The introduction of equal pay would not lead to an increase in national wealth and must therefore be paid for, in one way or another, by a reduction in therate of increase of real male wages. Experience suggested that themore highly paid male workers would be able to protect their realwages and that the introduction of equal pay would in practice be atthe expense of low-paid workers who were already finding it difficultto maintain their standard of living. The introduction of equal pay,however desirable, was not so urgent a social reform as the raising ofthe wages of the lowly paid. These considerations pointed towardsdelaying an announcement of the Governmenfs attitude to equal pay and perhaps extending its full implementation over a longer period than the First Secretary had proposed.As against this it was argued that it would be wrong to assume that in the next two or three years the cost of a phased programme would be much greater than allowing equal pay to be implementedhaphazardly in normal pay negotiations and through industrial action.With a five-year programme employers should be able to arguesuccessfully that increases should be phased over this period.Without such a programme they would be under continuous pressure to make large adjustments in women&apos;s pay to eliminate discrimination and the evidence indicated that the industries and companies best able
to meet the cost would give way and that others would then be forced to follow suit. While an announcement of early legislation on equal pay would not be particularly popular in the country generallyit would be greeted with enthusiasm in the Parliamentary LabourParty and would do much to strengthen the hand of the moderates onthe General Council of the TUC. Moreover, the case in equity for introducing equal pay particularly after the introduction of legisla-tion for a new system of earnings-related pensions later in the year -was overwhelming.In further discussion it was suggested that, because of theregressive effects of equal pay, its introduction might be linked insome way with a move towards a national minimum wage. Thissuggestion was opposed on the grounds that the repercussions of introducing a national minimum wage would be very damagingeconomically: but it was generally recognised that further considera-tion would need to be given to ways of mitigating the adverse effect onlow-paid male workers of introducing equal pay.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that while some reservations had been expressed about timing the cabinet agreed that legislation should be introduced in the next Session onthe broad lines indicated in the First Secretary&apos;s memorandum.There would be great advantage in announcing this at the LabourParty Conference but because of the implications for confidence in sterling a decision on this would have to be taken in the light of theinternational monetary situation at the time. In her talks with the tuc the First Secretary could express the Governments willingness to encourage the phased introduction of equal pay but should notreveal their intention to legislate next Session. She should seek toelicit the tuc&apos;s views on the need for legislation and the form itmight take and should draw their attention to the problem which theintroduction of equal pay would create for low-paid male workers.She should have a similar discussion with the CBI and it would be helpful if she could then see the TUC and the CBI together; and she should report the outcome of her discussions to Cabinet in time forthem to take decisions about the timing and form of legislation beforethe Labour Party Conference.The Cabinet (1) Took note with approval of the Prime Minister^ summing upof their discussion.(2) Invited the First Secretary of State to discuss the introductionof equal pay with the TUC and CBI on the lines indicatedin the Prime Ministers summing up and to report the outcome to the Cabinet before the Labour party conference.confidential industrial 4.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the President ofairs the Board of Trade about proposed increases in the prices of a numberNational of national newspapers (C (69) 115).NewspaperPrice The President of the Board of Trade said that since hisIncreases memorandum had been circulated he had been notified of a proposed
early increase of Id in the price of the News of the World. He hadinitially considered that a general reference of newsr aper prices wouldbe desirable for the reasons set out in paragraph 9 of the Annex to his memorandum. On reflection, however, he had come to the conclusionthat a further reference to the National Board for Prices and Incomes(NBPI) would achieve no useful purpose. The proposed increase inthe price of The Times seemed fully justified, and those for theBeaverbrook papers were reasonable. The proposed increases for the sunday and Daily Mirrors and the People were more dubiouslywithin the criteria of the prices policy, but it would be difficult tosingle out for reference the papers of the International PublishingCorporation, which was the most efficient publisher. In any event,the NBPI could do no more than repeat its previous exhortations and,possibly, proposals v/hich had proved unacceptable to the Govern-ment for subsidies to assist the process of eliminating surplusmanpower. Some embarrassment could also arise from the fact thatthe pay and productivity agreements reached in the industry in 1967had not been referred to the NBPI. There was widespread anxietythat the number of national newspapers might continue to dwindle.The Government had resisted pressures directly to assist newspapersand if they now refused to allow the publishers to assist themselves the Government could justifiably be criticised. For these reasons, he proposed that the Government should inform the publishers that theyhad no objection to the proposed increases and that there should accordingly be no general reference to the NBPI.In discussion, it was argued that the newspapers concerned should be allowed to make the immediate price increases which theyhad proposed while leaving the increases scheduled for 1970 subjectto the outcome of a general reference. This course course (c) inparagraph 11 of the Annex to C (69) 115 would not prevent the publishers, therefore, from making the increases which they now considered necessary. A further general reference to the NBPIwould maintain pressure of public opinion on the newspaper proprietors and the unions to tackle more effectively the notoriousinefficiency and over-manning of the industry. Moreover, if therewere no reference in this case, it would become increasingly difficultto maintain Government pressure on other industries to containprice increases. On the other hand, it was suggested that the NBPIwould not necessarily focus attention on the industry&apos;s generalinefficiency if a further reference were made. They might express theview that the industry&apos;s troubles stemmed in part at least from theGovernments failure to implement the earlier recommendation bythe Board for financial assistance to help with over-manning.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that course (c) as described in paragraph 11 of the annex to the Presidents memorandum should be adopted. The latestproposal for an increase in the price of the News of the World couldbe authorised if the President of the Board of Trade considered this to be necessary and consistent with the treatment of the otherproposed increases.
The Cabinet (1) Invited the First Secretary of State, in consultation with thePresident of the Board of Trade, to refer the costs and revenue of national newspapers to the National Board for prices and Incomes.(2) Invited the President of the Board of Trade (a) to authorise the proposed increases in 1969 in theprices of The Times, the Sunday Express, thePeople and the Sunday Mirror; and, if necessary,similar increases in the News of the World and TheGuardian;(b) to request the newspaper publishers concerned not to implement proposed price increases in 1970 beforethe National Board for Prices and Incomes had reported on the reference at (1) above.Cabinet Office,5 September, 1969.




</content>
</cab>
