<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/27/32 images: 338-351</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TI152nmUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)Note b.v the Secretary of the War Cabinet.By direction, of the prime Minister theattached Report by Lord Justice du Parcq. is circulated for the information of the War Cabinet.(Signed) E.E* BRIDGES.WAR   CABINET.RADIO COMMUNICATION AND EQUIPMENT IN THEFIGHTING SERVICESoGreat George Street, S.W.I.

ilj3THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTTo the Right Honourable Winston S. Churchill, C.H., M.P.,Prime Minister and First Lord of the Treasury.Sir,BY a letter dated the 2nd May, 1942, I was informed of your desire thatI should undertake an Enquiry with the following Terms of Reference : (i) Whether there  is full co-ordination between  the  three FightingServices in respect of radiolocation.(ii) Whether full advantage of technical help has been taken in effectingcommunication in the field between tanks and aeroplanes and between troops and Commands.(iii) Whether the situation with regard to the production and supply of wireless equipment to the three Services is satisfactory.2. In order to prevent misunderstanding, it is necessary to define the term &quot;wireless equipment&quot; which is used in the third of the Terms ofReference. In the Services the word &quot;wireless&quot; is now used as applyingparticularly to wireless telegraphy and telephony excluding R.D.F. and other forms of radio. For the present purposes, however, I have interpreted theexpression &apos;&apos; wireless equipment&apos;&apos; as including all forms of wireless equipment,including R.D.F. Thus the first and third of the Terms of Reference both deal,the first wholly, the latter in part, with R.D.F. (or radiolocation), and are closely linked. It will be convenient to deal with these questions first, and later to deal separately with the question contained in the second of the Terms ofReference which is distinct from the other two.I. Whether there is full co-ordination between the three FightingServices in respect of Radiolocation.3. Under the heading of the first Term of Reference, I will deal first withresearch and development. I have found a large measure of agreement on thefollowing principles : (i) It is necessary, or at least desirable, that each of the FightingServices should continue to maintain its own research establishments,but every establishment should be kept informed of the workundertaken and the results achieved by each of the otherestablishments. Some overlapping of research work is, however,inevitable, and, within limits, may even be advantageous.(ii) It is essential that those engaged in research should be in close touchwith- the Services, and that there should be a constant interchange of ideas between the Services and the scientists,(iii) Research must be planned, and planning must depend upon(a) the results of experience in the field of war;(6) policy, including long-term policy.It follows that (a) the research workers, or the scientists at their head, should beinformed at the earliest possible moment of the results of practical experience;(b) the direction which research and development is to take must be controlled, or at least influenced, by direction from above, thatis to say, from the Chiefs of Staff and ultimately, throughthe Chiefs of Staff, the Defence Committee of the WarCabinet. -[24200] . B
2(iv) While planning and the course to be followed by research must depend upon policy, it is also true that policy may sometimes be affected bythe results of research. (E.g., the development of such devices asH.2.S may, and perhaps must, affect the general strategy of the war).Thus, although policy is not the affair of the scientists, the scientistsshould be permitted and enccyaraged to suggest lines of enquiry which they think may be fruitful, and should often be given anopportunity to pursue them.4. There seems to be little ground for criticism so far as co-operationbetween the research establishments is concerned. There are however sometimesinstances of overlapping in research which goes beyond what is desirable, andthere are sometimes gaps which should be filled. In this connexion it mustbe remembered that the supply of persons competent to conduct research is limited, and that the field of necessary research is very extensive and continuesto grow rapidly. While it would be a mistake to say that two or more teamsof workers should never be engaged independently on the same piece of work,there are occasional cases of unnecessary duplication of work; and the resultsof work which is being done on the same lines at different establishments arenot always &apos;&apos; pooled &quot; at a reasonably early stage as they should be if the best possible product is to be obtained. These are not at present grave faults, andthey are not due to any lack of goodwill. The Superintendents of the variousestablishments, and the research workers themselves, are aware of the risk of unnecessary overlapping, and do their best to avoid it by visiting each others&apos;establishments as often as possible. It is, however, very difficult to keep pace with the rapid march of research, and the Superintendents of the establishmentsconcerned are busy men, forced to spend a large part of their working timein attendance at Committees and in the exercise of other duties which areimposed on them. The Directors of Signals are alive to these difficulties, and,in the circumstances, I do not recommend any further control. It is indeedprobable that any rigid system of control would rather hinder than helpresearch. I have thought it right, however, to draw attention to a danger which will only be prevented from becoming serious by constant vigilance.5. The relations between the Services, as represented by the Directors ofSignals and the scientists whose duty it is to co-operate with them, are, onthe whole, extremely good. Further, in the actual working out of the problems on which research workers are engaged there seems to be full and enthusiasticco-operation between Service representatives and the scientists. The formersuggest in oral discussion what they would like done, and the latter suggestwhat might be done, and there is fruitful exchange of ideas across the table.I was told more than once that &apos;&apos; on the lower levels &apos;&apos; co-operation was very good.6. Communication to the scientists of the results of practical experience in the field is best ensured by the work of the v operational research groups &quot;which are now in being in all three Services. These groups consist of &quot; scientistsin uniform,&quot; who, as the result of their skilled observation, are able to indicateany deficiencies or weakness that may exist, to suggest improvements, and toprovide material on which others are able to work. The reports (for instance)of the Air Ministry&apos;s operational research groups in the Middle East have been most illuminating. It is now generally agreed that the value of the work doneby such groups is very great, and that everything possible should be done toencourage them. They are a necessary link between the Services and the research workers, and a valuable source of information to those directing policy.Their value has not, until recently, been sufficiently recognised in the case ofthe Army.   (See paragraph 18 below.) .7. So far as planning and the necessity for direction are&apos; concerned, it seemsto be clear that until quite recently such direction has been lacking. The RadioPolicy Sub-Committee, in response to appeals for guidance, had its first meeting with the representatives of the Chiefs of Staff within the last few weeks, andsome time after this Enquiry had been begun. It is probably right to attributeto the absence of such conferences at an early date the fact that the Radio PolicySub-Committee has not hitherto been able itself to give any very useful guidance as to priorities.   It has been compelled to allot the highest class of priority to
some 38 different subjects of research, without distinguishing between their claims to priority as between themselves, and such a list of &quot; priorities &quot; couldnot be of great value.It is, in my opinion, most desirable that the Chiefs of Staff should holdfrequent meetings with the Radio Policy Sub-Committee, or with any other body which may succeed to its functions, and that the clearest possible guidance should thus be given. It is obvious that the direction given to research (and subsequently to development and production) must sometimes be subject to variation. In warthe unexpected often happens, and a sudden emergency may at any time compel adeviation from the course laid down. Speaking broadly, however, a clear directioncan, and should, be given from above. It has been suggested to me that theStaff and the Services may sometimes have been reluctant to impart mattersrelated to policy to the scientists, and, whether justly or not, it appears that somescientists have been suspected of a desire to stray outside their province and discuss policy. An unfortunate gap in co-ordination may be explained but cannotbe justified by such considerations.8. A further and distinct question which comes within the first of theTerms of Reference has been raised with regard to the installation andmaintenance of ground R.D.F. stations. This was the subject of a report by major-General Butler to the Radio Policy Sub-Committee in February 1942(R.P.C. (42) 11). Some, but not the whole, of Major-General Butler&apos;s proposals have been accepted. I understand that it has now been agreed that all generalreporting stations (including all coast-warning stations), except those in defended ports (which are closely linked to a gun control), are to be handed over to theR.A.F., which is to be responsible for operation, manning and maintenance.The transfer to the R.A.F. is now in progress. This is the outcome of longdiscussion, and I have not thought it desirable to re-open a question which hasbeen so fully investigated by competent persons, and upon which a decision has been taken. Those who are critical of the decision, and think it does not go far enough, are, I think, all willing that it should be left to the new RadioBoard which it is contemplated should be set up for reconsideration. (See below,paragraph 15.)II.  Whether the Situation with regard to the Production and Supply of wireless Equipment to the Three Services is Satisfactory.9. Whereas almost everyone whom I interviewed gave an affirmative answer(with certain qualifications) to the question contained in the first of my Terms ofReference, nobody has been prepared to answer &apos;&apos; Yes ;&apos; to the question containedin the third, with which it is convenient to deal at this point. It must beremembered, of course, that the production of wireless equipment is only part ofa much larger whole. My attention has been confined to this part. On a wider view, it would be necessary to consider what are the limits of possibleproduction and of available resources, whether those limits have been reached, and where wireless equipment in the wider sense (see paragraph 2 above) must rankin the list of priorities. Further, if the whole field of production were beingsurveyed, many complaints would have to be investigated with which it was not,I think, contemplated that I should deal. His Majesty&apos;s Government are well aware of the criticisms which have been directed in Parliament and elsewhereagainst the alleged defects in the machinery of Government on which productiondepends. I have interpreted my Terms of Reference as excluding any such general survey, and I confine myself to those matters which are clearly relevant to the case of wireless equipment. For this reason I have not investigated ageneral allegation that works have sometimes remained idle because the Ministryof Aircraft Production has objected to their undertaking contracts offered themby the Ministry of Supply during the idle period. I have had the advantage of reading the Report of the Minister of Production, which suggests.a change indepartmental machinery with a view to improving production, and I willpresently refer to that Report in more detail.10.   It is generally agreed that the lack of components has been, andcontinues to be, the great difficulty in the way of speedy production.   This, saidProfessor Cockcroft, is &quot; the real bottle-neck,&quot; and this comment accords with much,of the evidence.   The main trouble has been that orders for components[24200] B 2
have not been placed until the Services have made a demand for the equipment inwhich they were to be used. This is true even of components (e.g., condensers)which might have been expected to be ordered in bulk in advance of requirements,so that a large stock would always exist which might be drawn upon. A minoraggravating circumstance has been that designs tind specifications have sometimescalled for components which have had to be specially manufactured, whenstandard components which were available could have equally well satisfiedrequirements. A delay of about twenty weeks in the delivery of components was stated to be normal, and I was told that the delay has been as long as six months.11. It seems clear that there should be a comprehensive list of &apos;*&apos; preferredcomponents,&quot; i.e., of the components most readily available which designers shouldincorporate in their designs, and that a large stock of these should be established and maintained. Much has been done in this direction at the Admiralty&apos;sresearch establishments, and I understand that such a stock is being created and that a general catalogue of available components will be supplied to all three services. Professor Cockcroft told me that, according to his information, thesituation would clear up by the end of 1942. This will at last satisfy whatseems to be an obvious need, which should. I think, have been foreseen earlier.It seems to have been overlooked because during the first two years of the war .manufacturers in the radio industry were able to provide many components, in large numbers, from their existing stocks.   &apos;Where special components have had to be made, the policy of waiting till the equipment could be finally ordered has led to grave delays. As one example of many, it is said that in. the case of Mark VIII A.I, where the delay was considerable, components (e.g., magnetrons and magnets) might well have been ordered in advance of detailed definition of the equipment, but, although it was obvious for a long time that large-scale production of magnetrons and magnetswould be necessary, nothing was done until the stage of detailed definition wasreached.12. A further source of delay, which is avoidable at least in part, is to befound in the fact that there is great and natural reluctance to proceed fromdevelopment to production until a design has been &quot;finalised.&quot; Everybody isnow familiar with the dilemma caused by rapid improvements in design. at whatever moment production begins, the product may soon be obsolescent. Onthe other hand, if production is not to be begun until something approachingperfection is achieved, nothing will ever be produced in time to win the war.The Navy is in a more favourable position than the other Services (a) because,the number of ships being relatively small as compared with that of aircraft ortanks, their demands are not on a grandiose scale, and there is less hesitation inembarking on production, and (b) because they are not under the necessity of persuading&apos; any Ministry other than the Admiralty that production should be begun without delay. It appears that serious delay in supplying the require-ments of Army Co-operation Command (as to which see paragraph 14 below) isdue, in part at least, to the gap which has to be bridged between the Air ministry and the Ministry of Aircraft Production. The latter Ministry has to deal withcompeting claims, and development and production are slowed clown by the factthat the machinery of a second department has to be set going. I have been much impressed by representations made to me that, where need is urgent (as it is withregard to many R.D.F. devices), facilities for quick small-scale production shouldbe greatly increased. It is argued that one aeroplane fitted with such a deviceas, e.g., A.I. or &quot; Gee &quot; is worth at least three which are not so fitted. In thecase of A.I. success was in fact obtained in the spring of 1941 with a small number of sets. There are many cases in which 200 sets now are of more value than 1,000 in nine months&apos; time. It has been suggested to me (for example) that200 aircraft fitted with A.S.V. sets working on centimetres would have a greateffect on the sea war. The proposal made, which seems to me to be worthy of careful consideration, is that the system under which about six months is spent in tooling for production should be replaced (in many cases) by a system of&quot; progressive tooling.&quot; By this is meant that, during the production of earlymodels, further tools can be produced which will enable the rate of output to be accelerated. T.R.E. realised early in the war that it was desirable to establish aPrototype Production Factory, and such a factory was eventually set- up atBournemouth.   Here it is possible to make equipment in small quantities.
Several other &quot; model shops &quot; like the Bournemouth factory might be established and run under the control of the D.R.P. Here &quot; progressive tooling &quot; should beemployed, preferably in liaison with the firm who have the contract: thus theService would have the advantage of testing equipment supplied in smallerquantities before the main production began, and the manufacturers would gain by being provided with tools capable of assisting in the production.13. A criticism which appears to me to have substance is that aircraft are designed and planned without due regard to the radio equipment with whichthey are to be fitted. I was told that in May 1942, when a number of gliders werein course of production, it was realised late in the day that they needed radionavigational equipment for their effective use; and a radio installationprogramme was hurriedly begun. Another instance referred to was that ofWellington Mark VIII and Whitley Mark VII bombers for use in coastal command; radio equipment for these machines is being prototyped, but no orders have yet been placed for them, the existing order only covering equipments in200 Sunderland flying boats. The suggested remedy is that orders for radioequipment should be placed as soon as the scientists developing the equipmentcan state that they are reasonably certain of its success, and that a provisionalallocation of aircraft should be made at the same time.14. What has been said above as to &quot; priorities &apos;&apos; (paragraph 7) is, of course,of importance in relation to production and need not be repeated. A particular case in which serious delays seem to have been occasioned by failure to grant .priority to pressing needs is that of the Army Co-operation Command. A newwireless set for the single seater reconnaissance type of aircraft is an urgentrequirement. Until these sets are supplied these aircraft are of little use in bad weather because of the lack of navigational facilities. The specification of the required set was complete in January 1941. Army Co-operation Command havebeen told that they may expect deliveries in fifteen months from now. Nocontract has yet been placed. Although a very large number of sets will ultimately be required, this is one of the cases where 100 sets now would be very valuable.Other instances of delay in production were given to me. I do not cite them allin detail because I am assured that all the needs of the Command have been stated (and recently re-stated) to the Air Ministry, but the delay has resulted ingrave deficiencies in vital equipment such as V.H.F. sets for fighter reconnais-sance squadrons, and inter-communication between tug-aeroplane and glider.15. I have found that, in principle, all are agreed that the setting up of aRadio Board on the lines recommended by the Minister of Production would go far towards solving the difficulties surrounding production, so far as R.D.F. isconcerned. What is generally envisaged with approval is a Board divided intosub-committees dealing with R.D.F. policy under two main heads which may be distinguished, a little loosely, as (a) Research, and (b) Production. The sub-committees grouped under (a) would be presided over by a scientist, those under(b) either by a scientist or a man of business experience, or someone (possibly anengineer) combining both qualifications. It is generally regarded as of&apos; theutmost importance that whenever a Supply Ministry is affected by a sub-committee^ activities, that Ministry, as well as the Services, should beauthoritatively represented on it. When all concerned are agreed, it is contem-plated that effect should be given at once to the decision of the sub-committee.In the event of a dispute, the matter would be finally considered by the Chairman,who would be advised by1 selected members of the Board. Almost everybody whom questioned on the point thought that it was vital to the success of the planthat the Chairman should be independent in the sense that he was not associatedwith any of the departments which might be brought into conflict. It is hopedthat the Chairman would not very often be called upon to act, and it was generally felt that, to ensure the success of the organisation, it was much to be desired that the Minister of Production should act as Chairman.I must add that it has become clear to me during my enquiry that &quot;the successor failure of the plan will depend largely on the persons selected for the office ofDeputy Chairman. Some appointments which necessarily suggest themselves asprobable would be generally welcomed; others would be equally generallyregretted. I feel bound to mention this delicate question, but have thouo-ht itclearly outside my province to make any suggestions as to these appointments[24200] .      b 3
III. Whether full Advantage of Technical Help has been taken in effectingCommunication in the Field between Tanks and Aeroplanes and betiveenTroops and Commands.16. The conclusions at which I have&apos; arrived under this head may besummarised as follows : (a) Before the war the Army had not the financial resources which wouldhave enabled full advantage to be taken of technical help in relationto Winter alia) communications.(b) For some time after the war began full advantage was not taken of thetechnical help which might have been obtained.(c) In order that such advantage may be taken it is essential that the require-ments of Army Co-operation Command, which are known, shouldbe more rapidly and completely fulfilled. (This applies, in particular,to communication between tanks and aeroplanes.)(d) In general it is true to say that the Army now realises its deficienciesand that steps are being taken to remedy them.17. As to (a), although the Army had the benefit of skilled scientific-advicebefore the war, not enough was being done in the way of research by, orconsultation with, scientists. Lack of money was also responsible for inadequateequipment. Further, in order that full advantage of technical help may be taken,it is necessary that those who have to use the means provided should be skilled and well trained, and that they should be given proper opportunity of puttingboth their knowledge and their apparatus to the best use. It is, I think, clearthat the importance of signals was formerly under-estimated and that full opportunity of co-operating with other branches of the Service was not given tothem.18. As to (b) and (c), there is evidence pointing clearly to the conclusionthat two years or even eighteen months ago the position was still very unsatis-factory. More recently, much has been done. Operational groups are being sentto the Middle East by the War Office which will study signals. The work of theAir Ministry&apos;s operational groups has already been most helpful (see paragraph above), and these and the Army groups will work in close conjunction. Muchmore scientific assistance has been obtained. The essential work done by army co-operation Command is undoubtedly having good results. See, however,paragraph 14 above as to the handicap under which this young, but vitally important, Command suffers. Inevitably and rightly, the needs of coastal, fighter and bomber commands were long paramount, and these needs absorbed much of the energy of the B.A.F., of the skill available for research, and of the availablefacilities for development and production. There seems to have been a tendency to keep Army Co-operation Command at the bottom of the ladder, where of necessity it began its career.19. The equipment at present provided is unsatisfactory. Modernmechanised warfare, with its extreme mobility, coupled with the increased speed of aircraft and the use of single-seater planes (with little room for apparatus and only one man to deal with it), have created a demand which has not yet been supplied. I have already mentioned (paragraph 14) the inadequacy of the setwith which reconnaissance aircraft are equipped. Ground sets are alsounsatisfactory. Complaints have come from the Middle East. The sets in usehave too short a range. The want of &apos;&apos; suitable wireless sets,&quot; which would have enabled units &quot;to receive orders and instructions rapidly, , . .. . was seriouslyfelt on several occasions, especially during night moves.&quot; (Notes from theatres of War, No. 4 : Cyrenaica, November 1941 /January 1942, p. 7. See also ibidp. 34, and No. 1, November 1941, p. 11.) Better sets are coming into use in small quantities, but production is slow.20. It is still doubtful whether the importance of signals is always fully understood. Critics say that it is usual in the Army to call signal officers intoconference only at the last moment, when all plans are complete, instead ofobtaining their collaboration at an early stage. I was told that although this mayhave been true two years ago, it is true no longer.  Evidence that the old practice
lingers seems to me to be provided by the following extract from Notes fromTheatres of War, No. 4, Cyrenaica, p. 34:  &quot;It is essential that signals be consulted during the administrativeplanning and reconnaissance stages, as it is likely that communications canbe provided more efficiently in one place than in others, and this factor mustbe taken into consideration in formulating administrative plans.&quot;Thus a principle which should long have been regarded as elementary is beinginculcated, at this late stage of the war, as the result of painful experience.21. The training of officers and men has been a good deal criticised. Itseems to be true that formerly signal officers were not encouraged to interestthemselves in technical matters, but I was assured that this is no longer true andthat the present training of officers is good. The men are not always as efficientas they should be. So far as the Middle East is concerned this is due, in part atleast, to the fact that training cannot be continued, owing to exigencies of spaceon board ship, during the long journey from England, so that the men forgetmuch of what they have learned and are out of practice when they arrive.22. Inadequate equipment, and to some extent inadequate training, have led to unsatisfactory results. It seems certain that we are behind the enemy inco-operation between ground and air. Vol. 4 of the Notes cited above (para-graph 19) says of the enemy (page 22) that, when he was on the defensive, &quot; there could have been only a very short lag between the call and the answer for air support.&quot; In November 1941 (Notes, No. 1, p. 8) our time for the arrival of aircraft &quot; was normally about two hours.&quot; Practice by the Army Co-operationCommand in this country-has reduced the time to about forty minutes, assuming the aircraft when summoned to be 50 miles away. Generally, however, the resultsof recent exercises are not regarded by Army Co-operation Command as satis-factory so far as communications are concerned. The deficiencies which I have mentioned are, indeed, such as to preclude satisfactory results of exercises oroperations.23. One of the problems which arouse general interest is that of recognitionof tanks from the air. It is believed that it has not been solved by the enemy.There is a school of thought which holds that no system of identification by theuse of wireless or radiolocation is likely to be efficient or practically useful, butthe matter is being investigated and a device is now being tested. It is possiblethat an earlier call for assistance from scientists would have resulted in speedierresults, but it would be premature to pass such a judgment when it is not quite certain that a satisfactory result will be achieved even now.24. It will be obvious that my Terms of Reference covered a very wide field.I have tried to confine myself within -reasonable limits without unduly narrowingthe scope of the Enquiry, though I am not confident that I have succeeded. TheEnquiry has throughout been conducted on informal lines. The difficulty of mytask has been much lessened by the fact that I have had the advantage of the valuable and ungrudging assistance of Mr. Clement Jones, C.B., of the Treasury.I am also indebted to Wing Commander Jefferson of the War Cabinet Secretariatfor the help he has given to me, and I wish to thank the representatives of thethree Services, and of the Departments concerned, on whose help I have relied,and who.readily afforded it.I have the honour to be, Sir,Your obedient Servant,HERBERT du- Parcq.August 5, 1942.
APPENDIX &quot;A.&quot;Interviews.I. Navy.&apos;Rear-Admiral C. S. Holland, Director of Signals, Admiralty.Commodore R. G. Duke, Southwick.Commander Taylor, R.N., Southwick.Commander Windsor, R.N., Southwick.Captain J. W.* Cuthbert, R.N.Captain M. Hodges, R.N., Combined Operations.Captain R. B. Gossage, R.N., Stanmore.Captain B. R. Willett, R.N., Haslemere (Lythe Hill).Mr. G. Shearing, Haslemere (Lythe Hill).Mr. L. S. Alder, Haslemere (Lythe Hill).Mr. C. Crampton, Admiralty Signals Establishment (A.S.E.).Mr. C. R. Evershed, admiralty Signals Establishment (A.S.EV).Mr. C. F. Horton, Witley (A.S.E.).Mr. John du Parcq, A.S.E.&apos; II. Army.Major-General C. W. Fladgate.Major-General D. D. Butler, Ministry of Supply.Brigadier A. P. Sayer.Colonel R. Gambier-Parry.Colonel Yeo, from Libya.Major Mylne, from Libya.Brigadier J. D. Woodall, Army Co-operation Command, Bracknell.III.-R.A.F.Air Chief Marshal Sir Sholto Douglas, Fighter Command.Air Vice-Marshal C. W. Nutting.Air Vice-Marshal M. Henderson. Fighter Command.Air Commodore P. F. Fullard, Fighter Command.Group Captain V. G. A. Hatcher, Fighter Command.Air Marshal T. L. Leigh-Mallory, No. 11 Group, TJxbridge.Air Commodore G. Harcourt-Smith, No. 11 Group, Uxbridge.Squadron Leader J. H. Rowlatt, Ventnor.Supervisor Simonds, Ventnor.Wing Commander J. Cherry, Tangmere.Squadron Leader J. H. Sprott, Tangmere.Wing Commander L. R. Ridley, Air Ministry, Whitehall.Squadron Leader T. J. Norton,&apos; Air Ministry,&apos; Whitehall.Group Captain P. J. R. King, R.A.F -Station, Defford, Worcs.Air Commodore V. H. Tait, Air Ministry, Whitehall.Group Captain I. J. Fitch, Army Co-operation Command; Bracknell.Wing Commander C. W. Stewart, Army Co-operation Command, Bracknell.IV.-^scientists.Lord Cherwell.Sir Henry Tizard.Sir Robert Watson-Watt.Sir Charles Darwin.Sir Edward Appleton.Professor Cockcroft.Professor Blackett.Sir R. Fowler.Dr. Varley.Mr. A. P. Rowe, T.R.E., Malvern.Mr. W. B. Lewis, T.R.E., Malvern.Mr. P. I. Dee, T.R.E., Malvern. - !Mr. J. Sieger, T.R.E., Malvern.Mr. Holt Smith, T.R.E., Malvern.
V. Members of Parliament.Professor A. V. Hill.Mr. Glenvil Hall.Mr. Garro-Jones.Mr. Alfred Edwards was also invited, but, owing to absence from London,was unable to attend. He felt that the other M.Ps. had presented his case.VI. Other Witnesses.Mr. Geoffrey Crowther, Office of the Minister of Production.Sir Robert Renwick, Air Ministry.Group Captain P. D. de Laszlo, Air Ministry.Sir Frank Smith, Ministry of Aircraft Production.Sir Archibald Rowlands, Ministry of Aircraft Production.Mr. Harmer, Pye Radio Company.APPENDIX &quot;B.&quot;Places Visited.1. T.R.E., Malvern.2. RAP. Station, Defford, Worcs.3. R.A.F. Station, Ventnor, Isle of Wight.4. R.A.F. Station, Bembridge, Isle of Wight.5. Fort Warrington, Southwick.6. R.A.F. Station, Tangmere.7. Fighter Command, Stanmore.8. Headquarters, No. 11 Group, Uxbridge.9. Haslemere, A.S.E.10. Whitley.11. Army Co-operation Command, Bracknell.




</content>
</cab>
