<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/28/17 images: 172-177</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^Jz^l^U+XS      .cT. 00gjS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).SECRET.W.P.(42)  587.28TH AUGUST. 1942. COPY NO.WAR CABINETREORGANISATION OF THE ARMOURED FIGHTINGVEHICLE DIVISION OP THE MINISTRY OP SUPPLY.Note by the Minister of Production.By arrangement with the Minister of Supply (and in histemporary absence) I circulate herewith, for the informationof my colleagues, a Memorandum setting out new arrangements forthe organisation of the Armoured Fighting Vehicle Division ofthe Ministry of Supply.     I am in agreement with these arrange-ments*O.L.Ministry of Production, S.W.1*28th August,  194-2.MINISTRY OF SUPPLYArmoured Fighting Vehicle Division.Chairman of A.F.V. Divisione1.Director Generalof A.F.V. SupplyDirectorof A.F.V.inspectionDirector of A.F.V,Research andDevelopmentCommandant ofA.F.V. ProvingEstablishment.The Chairman of A.F.V. Division will also be Chairman of the tank Board. Commander S.R. Micklem has been released by Messrs.Vickers-Armstrongs for this purpose. He will exercise executive authority over all sections of the Division.2o     In the past, research, development and all phases of designincluding modifications to A.F.V&apos;s in production, have come underthe control of the Controller-General of Research and Development(Mr. Oliver Lucas).     Mr. Lucas will continue his functions asController-General of Research and Development in the Ministry,and as C.G.R.D. he will continue to be a member of the Tank Board.3,     A.F.V. Research and Development will however for. the future be under a Director of Armoured Fighting Vehicles, Research andDevelopment, who will bo directly responsible to the Chairmano     Tothis post, it is proposed to appoint Mr. Robotham, at present ChiefEngineer of Tank Design,

This Department will bo responsible for the initiation andcompletion of the design of a vehicle to fulfil a user specificationup to the point where cither (a) a pilot model is accepted, or (b)the project; can be accepted by the user and the Director-Generalof AoPoVo Supply (Sir George Usher)0The Chairman will review the present Department of TankDesign at JSghair. and other facilities for A0F-,V0 design with a -view to deciding which sections shall remain the responsibilityof the D-&apos;.rec;cr of Research and Development and which shallbe transferred to the Director General of AoF0V. Supplyo4o     ffixpprimontal wing of Tank Design Department?Hitherto the Experimental Wing of the Tanlc Design Department?originally at Farnborough-, no&apos;v at Chobham, has been under thecontrol of the Chief Engineer of Tank Design and the Directorof Tank Design0     It is proposed that this organisation should become an independent unit under the direction of the Commandantof the Proving Establishment who will bo directly responsible tothe Chairman?The establishment will be organised as an independent testingand proving establishment available to:-(1) War Office (including user trials)^2) The Director of AcFoVo Research and development  5) Director General Armoured Fighting Vehicles Supply,,(4) A ,FnVn ivlanufacturers050     InspectionaInspection has hitherto been under the Director General ofSupplyo      It is proposed that it should now be placed under a director of A*FoVo Inspection, who will be directly responsible to the Chairman,!6o      GeneralThe relations between the Director General AoFoV. Supply andthe Controller General of Munitions Production will remain as atpresentoResponsibility for Gun and Gun Mounting Design rests withthe Director of Artillery under the Controller General of research and Developmento     The closest liaison will be maintained betweenthe Director of Artillery and the A0F*Vo Division027th August, 1942*




</content>
</cab>
