<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/49/6 images: 80-92</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1972CM (71) Copy No. 136th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 2 February, 1971,at 10 am.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, mp, Prime minister the Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,m p, Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of St.Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, m p,Secretary of State for Social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,mp, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for the environment the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Secretary of State for Trade andIndustry and President of the Board   -of trade the following were also present:The Right Hon. Frederick Corfield,mp, Minister of Aviation Supply(Item 1)The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury mr. Maurice Macmillan, mp, chief secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Sir Peter Rawlinson,qc, mp, Attorney-General
Secretariat :Sir Burke trend . P. E. thornton mr. N. F. cairncross mr. J. crocker mr. B. G. tucker miss S. W. FogartyContentsItem1Economic AffairsRolls-RoyceSubjectPage32Upper Clyde Shipbuilders10
nomicTSIfiih 1 -nicholls-RoyceviousT,ence:(70) 45thinclusions,Mute 5*1.CM 6 (71)secret the Prime Minister said that there had been extremely serious developments affecting the future of Rolls-Royce which hadbeen considered at a number of meetings since the previous Thursdayby a small group of Ministers under his chairmanship (GEN 16).The Cabinet would recall that in the previous autumn Rolls-Royce had informed the Government that they required an additional 60 million to complete development of the RB 211-22 engine for the lockheed trijet-aircraft which was due to enter service in November1971. In November 1970 the Government had agreed to provide anadditional  42 million by way of launching aid; and the banks had agreed to increase the company&apos;s overdraft facilities by  18 million.This additional provision was subject to verification of the need for it by an independent accountant appointed by the Government,Sir Henry Benson of Cooper Brothers. None of this money had infact been paid over to Rolls-Royce. The Board of Rolls-Royce had met on the previous Wednesday and had decided that the RB211engine could not be produced within the time and price specifiedin the contract; that the cost of developing the engine would be farin excess of the  60 million requested last autumn and that they wouldbe liable to a very heavy indemnity to Lockheeds for failure to produceon time. The Board had accordingly decided to abandon develop-ment of the RB211 and had decided that the company was inconsequence no longer solvent and that a Receiver and Managershould be appointed by the Trustees to the Debenture Holders duringthe course of the present week (almost certainly on Wednesday,3 February). When this decision of the Board became known to theGovernment, the small group of Ministers under his chairmanshiphad considered the following alternative courses of action:(i) To accept cancellation of the RB 211 but to take over thecompany, accepting all its debts and obligations. The total estimatedliabilities of the company consisted of  55 million to the DebentureHolders and secured creditors;  60 million to the clearing and merchant banks;  10 million to the Industrial reorganisation corporation; and about  70 million to trade creditors, making a totalof some  195 million. In addition there would be a liability ofsomewhere between  40 million and perhaps  300 million toLockheeds for breach of contract. This course would involve theGovernment in an open-ended commitment to meet the company&apos;obligations, which could total as much as  500 million.* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.SECRET132950-1 B*
(ii) To allow the appointment of a Receiver and Manager by the trustees to the Debenture Holders and to take no action. They hadbeen advised that no British company would be prepared to buyRolls-Royce; and even if, as seemed unlikely, a United Statescompany were found ready to take it over, the consequentialdependence of United Kingdom air defence on a foreign interestwould be unacceptable. Failure on the part of the Governmentto take any action would probably result in disintegration of Rolls-Royce^ present activities and assets. Apart from the Royal AirForce and the Royal Navy, 81 foreign air forces and 200 airlineswere dependent on continuing supplies and servicing of Rolls-royce engines and would be in the gravest difficulties if the companydisintegrated.(iii) To allow Rolls-Royce to be forced into a receivership andthen immediately to negotiate with the Receiver for purchase by theGovernment of the necessary fixed and floating assets of the companyrequired to protect defence and civil airline interests, i.e. to takeover the assets of the aero engine and marine engine parts of thecompany, leaving the motor car, oil engine and computer parts tobe disposed of by the Receiver or liquidator. A takeover of partof the assets in this way from the Receiver would avoid theassumption by the Government of any obligation for the existingdebts of Rolls-Royce or for the RB 211 contract with Lockheed. Thenecessary assets would be taken over at a valuation and placed in anew company which would carry on the necessary supply andservicing of engines. Sir Henry Benson had advised that such a company should be able to operate profitably; and, if this proved tobe the case, the company could in due course be handed back by theGovernment to private interests or merged with European companies.The cost to the Government of purchasing the assets and providing the necessary working capital might be about  200 million.The Ministerial Group had decided that there was no practical alternative but to adopt the last course; and the Minister of AviationSupply was now arranging for the drafting of the Bill which wouldbe required to empower the Government to acquire these assets.The consequences of these developments would be very seriousboth at home and in the United States. The failure to complete the rb 211 engine could well entail the termination of the Lockheedtrijet project; and this in turn might render the Lockheed Corporationitself insolvent, with severe consequences not only for the UnitedStates economy but for the United States Governments defence procurement. He had accordingly warned President Nixon in strict confidence of the problems which would now face the two Govern-ments as well as the two companies. The industrial implications of
CM 6 (7.1)the cessation of work on the RB 211 were also very serious in thiscountry. It was expected that some 18,000 of the 21,000 employedon the project by Rolls-Royce would become redundant within a fewweeks. There would be a heavy impact on employment in Glasgow,where the male unemployment rate was already approaching 10 percent and the difficulties of Upper Clyde Shipbuilders Limited (UCS)and Yarrow Shipbuilders Limited (YSL) had still to be resolved. IfUCS and YSL also went into liquidation at the same time as work onthe RB 211 engine was brought to an end, the combined effect wouldbe to raise the male unemployment rate in Glasgow to about 15 percent. Moreover, it was estimated that at least 20,000 furtherredundancies would occur amongst companies supplying material for the RB 211 programme.Unfortunately, Rolls-Royce had given no prior warning toLockheeds of these developments; and the Chairman of the lattercompany was arriving that day for a meeting with the Board of Rolls-Royce with no prior knowledge of the situation. In the circumstances it seemed likely that Lockheeds might ask for some time in which to consider the position; but in the end they could only save theposition of Rolls-Royce by agreeing both to- defer the delivery and toincrease the price of the RB 211 engines. It seemed certain that, evenif they were ultimately able to devise some solution on these lines,they would not be able to provide the immediate assurances whichwere required if the Board of Rolls-Royce were not to incur the legalrisk of continuing to trade when they knew that they were insolvent.Similarly, if the Government provided any temporary financialassistance, they would become liable for the total debts of thecompany. Sir Henry Benson had been attending all the Boardmeetings of the company and keeping in close touch with the Ministerof Aviation Supply. When the company was put in the hands ofa Receiver, which would probably be on 3 February, they wouldissue a statement, the contents of which were the subject of discussion between the Board and the Minister of Aviation Supply. The latter would make a statement to the House of Commons, on present plans,on 3 February, explaining the Governments intention to carry out thecourse which he had described. The Minister had also requesteda statement from Rolls-Royce of the action, if any, which the companywished the Government to take on their behalf in present circum-stances. They had not so far made any request for government assistance; and it was very important that their position in thisrespect should be absolutely clear. Finally, the Chairman of Rolls-Royce had agreed to call an Extraordinary General Meeting of thecompany in order to pass a special resolution requesting the Secretary132950-1
of State for Trade and Industry to appoint an inspector to conductan inquiry into the company&apos;s affairs under Section 165 of theCompanies Act, 1948.The Minister of Aviation Supply said that he agreed that therewas no practical alternative to the conclusions reached by the ministerial Group. He was nevertheless concerned about the lackof advance notice to Lockheeds of the developments and about thefact that they would be given no time before the appointment of aReceiver on the following day to consider possible solutions to theirproblem. On the other hand Rolls-Royce clearly could not continuetrading if they were insolvent, as they must be presumed to be in theabsence of some completely unexpected offer from Lockheeds in thecourse of that day, involving not only major revision of the originalcontract for the RB 211 but also provision of their immediate cashneeds. But, if a Receiver were appointed on the following day, itwould still be possible for Lockheeds to negotiate with him suitable arrangements to continue development and production of the RB 211if this was their wish and they could offer him acceptable terms. TheCabinet should be aware that, in addition to redundancies created incompanies supplying Rolls-Royce, very serious financial problems would be created for some of Rolls-Royce&apos;s trade creditors. LucasLimited, for example, were not merely owed some  4 million foisupplies but had made an investment of  16 million especially for production of parts for the RB211. A number of other suppliers,including Short Bros, in Northern Ireland and Scottish Aviation,would be very seriously affected financially and might no longer beconsidered credit-worthy by their bankers.For these companies the fact that the existing credit ceiling wouldnot prevent bank loans to companies satisfying the normal bankingcriteria of credit-worthiness would be no comfort. As for the failureof Rolls-Royce to produce the RB 211 on time, there was a consensusof view among technical experts that the development of this newengine by Rolls-Royce had run into no exceptional difficulties. the root of the matter lay in the fact that Rolls-Royce had signed anagreement with Lockheeds which did not allow adequate margins oftime and costs to solve the problems which were inevitable in any new technological development on this scale. Rolls-Royce believednow that, given additional finance, they might be able to completedevelopment of the RB 211 engine in a further six months. But other experts thought that it might take a year: and in fact no one couldguarantee precisely how long it would take. A year&apos;s delay would be extremely damaging for Lockheeds, who were already finding itdifficult to compete successfully for orders with the DC 10 and who,
if the RB211 engine was not available, would face the problem of substituting American engines in their trijet, a process which wouldinvolve a complete redesign of the tail section of the aircraft.The Rolls-Royce Board had made it clear to him that they hadnot asked for any further Government financial assistance becausethey considered that it would not be sensible for them to do so. Hehad asked the Board to inform him accordingly in writing.In discussion, there was general recognition that, if the Board of rolls-Royce considered the company insolvent, they were in dutybound to cease trading and to ask the Trustees to the DebentureHolders to appoint a Receiver and Manager. New proposals fromLockheed to renegotiate the RB 211 contract and to forgo any claim on Rolls-Royce for penalties for late delivery of the engine would justify the Board in continuing to trade only if they themselves were satisfied that, as a result, the company had a reasonable prospectof again becoming solvent and of meeting their liabilities to theircreditors in full. Although section 332 of the Companies Act, 1948,did not bind the Crown, it had been the consistent advice of the LawOfficers to successive Governments that the Crown should act as ifit were so bound; and neither the Crown nor Lockheeds could afford to advance the moneys which, failing the appointment of a Receiverand Manager, Rolls-Royce needed in order to meet current expenseswithout incurring an unlimited liability for the company&apos;s presentand future debts. In face of the conditional decisions already reached by the Board it would be improper for the Government to seek to persuade them to continue in business or to show any readiness toprovide further funds in order to keep the RB 211 project alive.On the other hand the appointment of a Receiver and Managerwould allow the company&apos;s incoming cash to be used to meet currentexpenses and would place a moratorium on further outgoings to itscreditors. Provided that no creditor meanwhile forced the winding up of the company, the Receiver and Manager would be able to investigate further any proposal by Lockheeds to revise their contractin a manner which would make the RB 211 project viable and, if hethought fit, to conclude an agreement with Lockheeds to complete the engine. But the company&apos;s lack of immediate cash made it difficultto see how any such arrangement could be concluded withoutsubstantial additional launching aid from the Government.It was unsatisfactory that, despite Lockheed&apos;s major interest inthe completion of the RB 211 and the potentially severe consequences
to them of Rolls-Royce&apos;s failure, the latter had given them no priorintimation of the extent of their difficulties. It would be difficult for public opinion in this country and in the United States to understand why Lockheeds could be given no time now by the Board of Rolls-Royce to consider their position and to make proposals. Formally,however, this was justified by the fact that Rolls-Royce could not continue to trade when they were insolvent. The appointment of aReceiver and Manager was the only possible course in the circum-stances; and the position of Rolls-Royce had already been reportedto the Trustees to the Debenture Holders, who were deferring actiononly until the Board&apos;s discussion with Lockheed had taken place that day. In the light of that discussion, however, it might prove desirable in any subsequent Parliamentary statement by the Government toavoid giving the impression that the Board&apos;s decision to stop work onthe RB 211 was irreversible. If there appeared to be any possibility that Lockheed would wish to try to secure continuance of work onthe RB211, the statement by the Government might be revised tomake it clear that, in declaring an intention to acquire the assets ofthe aero engine and marine turbine divisions, the Government didnot preclude the Receiver and Manager from negotiating a solution which might enable the company to be kept intact or, at any rate, toallow the RB 211 to continue. At the same time it would be necessaryto avoid alterations in the draft statement which would have the effectof impairing the confidence of foreign Governments and airlines inthe Governments resolve to ensure the continuity of supplies andservicing of the Rolls-Royce engines on which their aircraft were dependent or in our ability to continue with the internationalcollaborative projects on which Rolls-Royce were currently engaged.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet endorsed the conclusions reached by the Ministerial group which had examined in detail the alternative courses now open tothe Government. They agreed that the possibility of acquiring thewhole of Rolls-Royce as a going concern must be dismissed. they also agreed that, when a Receiver and Manager was appointed, theGovernment could not simply stand back and leave it to chancewhether some rescue operation could be arranged. Accordingly, theonly tenable course, having regard to our defence and internationalinterests, was for the Government, as soon as action to appoint aReceiver and Manager was taken, to state that they were ready toacquire the fixed and floating assets of the aero engine and marineturbine divisions of the company. Legislation to empower theGovernment to give effect to this intention, if necessary, was being prepared for urgent introduction. But the Cabinet would considerit a preferable outcome if it proved possible to reach an acceptable
arrangement with Lockheeds which would permit the RB 211 engineto be completed as a viable project. It was possible that thediscussions with Lockheeds would enable the Board of Rolls-Royceor its successor, or the Receiver and Manager, to contemplate thiscourse. Against that contingency an alternative version of theproposed Government statement should be drafted, making it clearthat the Receiver and Manager would be in a position to negotiate with Lockheeds about the terms on which the RB 211 (and possibly the activities of Rolls-Royce as a whole) might be continued; but that,failing a solution on these lines, the Government would propose toacquire those assets of the company which were needed to ensure thecontinuance of activities important to our national defence, to ourcollaborative programmes with other countries and to the many airforces and civil airlines all over the world which relied on Rolls-royce engines. The Ministerial Group would keep in close touch with further developments; and the Cabinet would be summoned at short notice, if necessary. It would be important that the public announce-ment of Rolls-Royce&apos;s failure should be quickly followed by suchaction as it was possible for the Government to take to mitigate itsadverse effects and to restore confidence. The Secretary of State for employment would be taking steps to help to find alternative workfor those becoming redundant; and the Chancellor of the exchequer was in close touch with the Governor of the Bank of England aboutthe effects on the Stock Exchange and the temporary assistance whichmight be provided by the banks for major creditors of the companywho might need additional facilities. The secondary effects, forexample upon Rolls-Royce&apos;s subcontractors and other suppliers, couldnot yet be assessed in detail but would need sympathetic consideration.A preliminary examination had already been made of the additional measures of regional assistance which it might be possible to announce, particularly in relation to Scotland. If the expectedannouncement of the appointment of a Receiver for Rolls-Royce weremade on or before 3 February, the Secretary of State for Scotlandcould announce in the course of the debate on that day in the Houseof Commons on Scottish economic planning that the Governmentwould designate West Central Scotland as a Special development area.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Minister of Aviation Supply, in consultation withthe Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Secretary of State
for Defence, to prepare a possible revision of the draftGovernment statement on the lines indicated in the PrimeMinister^ summing up.Upper ClydeShipbuildersPreviousReference:CM (70) 48thConclusions,Minute 4CONFIDENTIAL2. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the Cabinet had agreed in December that shipbuilding credit guarantees in respect oforders placed with Upper Clyde Shipbuilders Ltd. (UCS) should be resumed and the reconstruction of their public loans approved only if there was a realistic possibility of the injection of substantial funds in UCS from elsewhere, if arrangements were made for the earlyclosure of the Clydebank Yard, and if Yarrow Shipbuilders Ltd.(YSL) were separated from UCS. The first two conditions had nowbeen met in a way which the Ministerial Committee on economic policy (EPC) accepted as satisfactory. The third condition had,however, presented difficulties. The proposal had been that Yarrowand Co., who already owned a 49 per cent interest in YSL, would buyout the 51 per cent interest of UCS. It had now emerged that YSLexpected to make a loss of iA\ million on six frigates (three for theRoyal Navy and three for export). The preliminary investigation by ministry of Defence accountants had shown that the firm would shortly run into a cash deficiency of the order at the maximum of 5 million and lasting at least to 1974. Unless YSL&apos;s difficulties wereovercome the separation from UCS would be impossible; such aseparation was a condition for agreement by shipowners to renegotiateupwards the prices of the ships being built for them by UCS; failingsuch agreement, UCS itself would be unable to continue trading afterWednesday, 3 February. Thus although in other respects UCS had done what the Cabinet required of them, they now risked being brought down by the financial difficulties of YSL. The closure ofUCS and YSL would lead to some 20,000 direct and indirectredundancies, sufficient to raise the male unemployment rate in glasgow to well above 10 per cent. The additional cost of completingelsewhere the Royal Navy vessels in the yard was estimated at 31 million plus some extra running costs for old frigates which wouldhave to be kept in service longer. The export contracts of YSL worth 40 million, including three frigates, would be similarly affected andmight be lost to the United Kingdom. This might lead to a loss ofconfidence by foreign buyers in the ability of British warship buildersto complete their contracts satisfactorily. While further investigationwould be needed of the position, the preliminary assessment of theMinistry of Defence accountants was that to enable YSL to complete
132950-1their current contracts and to continue trading legally some 4^ million was required of which only some  2 million could be repaid by June 1974. Whether the firm could be profitable thereafterwould require further investigation, but any help should only begiven on condition that the financial management was reorganised.EPC had agreed that YSL must be kept in business, while recognising that this could be an awkward precedent. It was not possible toreach a decision at this stage as to how assistance of  4-1 million could best be given, whether by loan, direct grant, renegotiation ofthe prices attached to the existing contracts, or a combination of these.This would have to be discussed urgently with the companies.However, it would be easier to present the decision publicly withoutembarrassment to the Governmenfs general industrial policy if the contracts were renegotiated. In any event, any assistance must bejustified publicly on the grounds of cost to the Defence Vote of completing the frigates elsewhere. In negotiating with the companiesthe main object would be to ensure that Yarrow and Co. wereprepared to take over UCS&apos;s 51 per cent share of YSL and so fulfil the remaining condition for saving UCS. He hoped the cabinet would endorse the conclusions of EPC that YSL should be maintained in business, and would authorise the Secretary of State for defence and the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry, in consultationwith the Solicitor-General and the Chief Secretary, Treasury, tonegotiate the best possible arrangements with Yarrow and Co. inthe course of the day.The Secretary of State for Trade and Industry said that UCShad been able to meet those of the conditions set by the Governmentfor the resumption of credit guarantees and the capital reconstructionwhich were within their control. They would, however, from thefollowing day be unable to continue trading legally withoutassurances as to their future; moreover, they would have no cash tomeet further wages. Yarrow and Co. Ltd. had contracted in July to buy UCS&apos;s 51 per cent share in YSL but had not ratified thisagreement. The essential first step was to get them to agree to implement it. If that were done, it would be possible for UCS tocarry on for a few days to enable negotiations to be concluded.In discussion the following points were made:(a) EPC had considered the possibility of a Government takeoverof YSL, but had decided that it would be preferable to arrange for anadditional sum of up to  4^ million to be made available.
(b) While it would be more consistent with the governments general industrial policy to allow YSL to go into liquidation and forthe Government then to acquire the assets or arrange with theliquidator for the vessels to be completed, this was not practicable inthe present situation without also forcing UCS and Yarrow andCo. Ltd. into liquidation with the most serious consequences for employment in Glasgow.(c) It was argued that the renegotiation of existing orders mighthave repercussions on naval orders placed with other yards and thata loan might therefore be preferable. On the other hand, the renegotiation of the naval orders could be more clearly represented asa move by the Government to protect its own interests on the same basis as the commercial shipowners were doing in respect of their orders with UCS.(d) Provision of assistance to YSL in any form would make it more difficult for the Government to defend their refusal to providebridging loans for the Mersey Docks and Harbour Board (MDHB)and for that Board to get its new Bill through Parliament. It wouldalso increase the pressure on the Government to assist other harbourauthorities, notably the Clyde, who were unable to raise money onthe market following the default by the MDHB on their Januarybonds.(e) Further enquiries should be made to establish whether anyother naval shipyards were likely to be in serious difficulty. The effectof the Governments various decisions on the ability of public bodiesgenerally to raise money on the market might also be considered further.The Home Secretary, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet endorsed the conclusion of EPC that YSL should be kept in business.  The Secretary of State for Defence and the Secretary ofState for Trade and Industry, in consultation with the Solicitor-General and the Chief Secretary, Treasury, should negotiate withYarrow and Co. the best possible solution, including the transfer tothe latter of the 51 per cent shareholding in YSL currently held byUCS, within a total cost of SA\ million provided to YSL in grant, \loan or renegotiated prices (preferably the last).   If it were not jpracticable for them to consult the Cabinet further before final jdecisions had to be taken to prevent the liquidation of the UCS, theywere authorised to settle on the best basis obtainable. The Secretary Iof State for Defence should give further consideration, in consultation Iwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer, to the possibility of containing jthe additional expenditure required within the existing defence budget, confidential\11
Cabinet Office,2 February, 1971.The EPC might give further consideration to the points recorded at(e) above.The Cabinet-(1) Took note with approval of the summing up of their discussion by the Home Secretary.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for Defence and the Secretaryof State for Trade and Industry, in consultation with theChief Secretary, Treasury, and the Solicitor-General tonegotiate with Yarrow and Co. Ltd. on the basis indicatedin the summing up of the discussion and to report the outcome to the Prime Minister.

</content>
</cab>
