<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/9/31 images: 256-265</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1940.SECRET.W.M. (40)269th Conclusions.Copy No.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 269CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime ministers room, House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Thursday, October 10, 1940, at11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal (Items 2-9).The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Minister of Aircraft Production.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security (Item 1).The Right Hon. Lord Lloyd, Secretaryof State for the Colonies (items-9).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.Marshal of the Royal Air Force SirCyril L. N. Newall, Chief of theAir Staff (Items 5-9).The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,M.P., Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.Captain the Right Hon. H. D.Margesson, M.P., parliamentary secretary to the Treasury (Item 1).Admiral of the Fleet&apos; Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 5-9).General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff (Items 5-9).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[21826]b
WAR CABINET 269 (40).mContents.minute no. Subject. page 1.      Parliament     ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     179Bill to extend the duration of the present Parliament.2.      Parliament     ............................     179Alternative place of Meeting.3.      Italy     ................................     179Proposed declaration of danger zones off  the coast of italian east African Territories.4.      Air Raid Warnings   ........................     180Effect on aircraft production.5.      Palestine................      ............     180Recruitment of Jewish units for general service in the british army.6.      Naval, Military and Air Operations ....      ....      ....     181Air Operations.Naval Operations.Military Operations:Egypt.The Sudan.7.      Blockade Policy        ........................     182Atlantic coast and French Equatorial Africa.8.      The U.S.S.R.............................     182Attitude towards Soviet absorption of the Baltic States.9.      Germany: Possible Intentions      ....      ....      ....      ....     183Reinforcements for the Middle East.
Parliament.Bill to extend the duration ofthe present parliament.The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theHome Secretary (W.P. (G.) (40) 255) covering a draft Bill in two alternative forms: (a) Prolonging the life of Parliament for one year after25th November, 1940, and making provision for furtherprolongations by means of Orders in Council, on the presentation of addresses by both Houses of Parliament.(6) Prolonging the life of Parliament for one year only.The Home Secretary preferred the first course, although thesecond had been followed during the last war.The Prime Minister and the Parliamentary Secretary to theTreasury favoured the second course, which they thought wouldbe that desired by the House of Commons as a whole.It was suggested that during the debates on the present Bill,questions such as redistribution, proportional representation,the single transferable vote, &amp;c, might be raised. It was the viewof the War Cabinet that it would be wholly inappropriate to dealwith such matters during the war.The War Cabinet-(a) Invited the Home Secretary to introduce, as soon aspossible, a Bill to extend the duration of the present parliament for one year only.(6) Agreed that if redistribution and similar matters shouldbe raised during the debates on the Bill, the line to betaken on behalf of the Government should be that suchmatters could not be considered until the end of thewar.Parliament.AlternativePlace of meeting.(previous erence:W.M. (39) 49thConclusions,Minute 15.)2. The War Cabinet instructed the Secretary to inform theappropriate authorities of their views as follows : (1) That alternative quarters for meetings of the Houses ofParliament within the neighbourhood of the Palace of westminster should forthwith be made ready and ascheme submitted for meetings to be held in thealternative quarters by way of rehearsal.(2) That these arrangements should be completed within thenext ten days.Italy.proposed declaration of danger zones offthe coast of italian BastAfricanTerritories.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 200thConclusions,Minute 16.)3. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theFirst Lord of the Admiralty (W.P. (40) 409) proposing that a notice should be issued to mariners declaring that all vesselsnavigating within 30 miles of Eritrea, British Somaliland andItalian Somaliland would do so at their risk and peril. It was proposed to instruct the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies, to use his discretion in authorising attacks on&apos; shipping and to have due regard to the safety of native dhows and of legitimate shippingentering and leaving the Red Sea.The War Cabinet-Approved the action proposed by the First Lord of theAdmiralty in W.P. (40) 109,[21820]b 2
Air raid warnings.Effect onaircraftproduction.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 256thConclusions,Minute 5.)Palestine.Recruitment of jewish units forgeneral service in the british army.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 39thConclusions,Minute 13.)4. The War Cabinet had before them two Memoranda by theMinister of Aircraft Production circulated as W.P. (40) 408.Reference was made to the strike which had been in progressat Coventry for more than a fortnight. Public feeling was said tobe running high against the strikers.The discussion was adjourned until the MinisterLabour and National Service could be present.of5. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for War (W.P. (40) 404) asking for approval fora proposal to raise Jewish units for general service in the british army.In discussion the following points were made : (1) The Secretary of State for War said that the proposal hadoriginated with Dr. Weizmann. The arrangements now recommended for Cabinet approval had beenagreed with the Colonial Secretary and withdraw. Weizmann. 10,000 Jews were to be recruited for incorporation in special Jewish units. Not more than3,000 of these would be drawn from Palestine. Mostof the rest would be drawn from the United States,although some would be refugees from Germany.The view was expressed that it was right and natural that Jews who had been maltreated by theenemy should be given an opportunity to take up armsagainst them.(2) It was suggested that the assent of the United StatesGovernment would be required before organisedrecruiting for our Army could take place in thatcountry.(3) We must not run the risk of a propaganda outcry being raised that the Jews, who were responsible for theoutbreak of the war, were now seeking to dragAmerica into their quarrel.(4) It was generally agreed that there could be no questionof a Jewish recruiting campaign being opened in theUnited States until after the Presidential Election.The Minister of Aircraft Production doubted the wisdom of this country recruiting Jews in Americaeven after the election.(5) There might have been advantages in arranging for theJewish units to be trained in the Middle East.Dr. Weizmann, however, had not advocated this, whichwould have inflamed feeling among the Arabs. Again,when the training of the Jewish units was complete,it would seem natural for them to go to the middle east. But no commitments could be entered into tothis effect at the present stage.(6) The Colonial Secretary said that he had, in deference tothe views held in the Cabinet on White Paper policy,done all he could with Dr. Weizmann, on the one hand,and others concerned, on the other, to arrive at a plan for Jewish armed co-operation in the war, alwaysprovided that Jewish units were recruited not as a jewish army, but for general service in the british army. None the less the situation in the middle east and the Moslem world was becoming daily more, critical, and, unless both the timing of the recruitmentas well as the presentation of this project were put
Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 268thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.6. The Chief of the Air Staff reported that on the previous day there had been three main enemy attacks, of which two had penetrated to London and one had crossed over Kent and the thames Estuary. It was believed that these attacks had beenmade by Messerschmitts 109&apos;s.Casualties had been : Ourown-1 machine (pilot safe).Enemy 4 certain.4 probable.5 damaged.On the&apos; previous night the enemy air activity had been ratherheavier than usual, and amongst places hit was St. Paul&apos; cathedral, where the choir and altar had been badly damaged.Discussion ensued as to whether publicity should be given tothe damage to St. Paul&apos;s. It was important not to give the enemyinformation of operational value by publishing reports of damage caused. It was noticeable that the enemy had ceased to giveparticulars of the damage which we had caused in Germany.forward with the greatest care, he believed that therewas a serious danger that Moslem feeling in theMiddle East and, indeed, beyond it, would be inflamedand grave danger result. He felt it his duty to warn the Cabinet of the importance of doing nothing to upset Moslem feeling. This had been continuallystressed by every important British authority without exception in the areas concerned. He did not ask thatthe proposal under consideration should be abandoned,but that it should be deferred until the highly critical situation now present in the Middle East cleared up ordeveloped.(6) The Foreign Secretary was clear that there could be noquestion now of abandoning the scheme. Nevertheless,he was somewhat anxious lest Dr. Weizmann should use injudicious methods in his recruiting campaign inAmerica. In particular, it was most undesirable thatthat there should be any appeals to &quot; come and defendPalestine.&quot;The War Cabinet-(a) Gave general approval in principle to the proposals in w.P. (40) 404.(&amp;) Decided that the measures necessary to give effect to thescheme set out in this Paper would have to be further considered after the United States presidential election.(c) Invited the Secretary of State for the Colonies (on behalfof the Secretary of State for War) to see Dr. Weizmannand inform him of the above decisions. Dr. Weizmannshould also be informed that no announcement mustbe made, and no action taken, in this matter until afterthe Presidential Election.(d) Agreed that it should be impressed on Dr. Weizmann thatno guarantee could be given as to the theatre in whichthe force, when trained and equipped, would serve.
The Chief of the Air Staff saw no objection to publication inthis case of the fact that St. Paul&apos;s had. been hit, provided thiswas not taken as a ruling of general application.The War Cabinet agreed That full publicity should be given to the attack onSt. Paul&apos;s Cathedral, including photographs of the damage done. The time at which the attack had takenplace should not, however, be stated.On the previous night our bomber aircraft had attacked Calaisand marshalling yards in Germany. A number of propaganda leaflets had also been dropped in occupied France.Naval The First Sea Lord reported that the Oronsay, which had beenOperations.       bombed on the 8th October, had now reached the Clyde.Three merchant ships totalling 18,000 tons had been sunk onthe previous day, and another of 4,000 tons damaged.    It was hoped to bring this last ship into port.Military The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that air operations: reconnaissance had reported an advance by three enemy columns,Egypt. consisting of 200 motor transports and tanks from Bir Enbar.After proceeding some 15 miles eastward the column had turnedround and withdrawn towards the point from which they had started. This would appear to have been a reconnaissance inforce. Elements of our mobile force were keeping the enemyunder observation.The Sudan. There  had  been  some  movement  by enemy forces fromKurmuk. This probably represented an attempt to strengthen their left, possibly as a preliminary to a thrust towards therailway.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.blockade policy.Atlantic coast and FrenchEquatorialAfrica.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 268thConclusions,Minute 2.)7. The First Lord of the Admiralty referred to telegramNo. 2223 from Washington as to the interception of empty cargo ships on their way to West African ports. With the forcesat present available it was difficult to maintain an effectiveblockade of both Dakar and of Libreville. To which port shouldpreference be given ?The Prime Minister thought that this matter had betterconsidered at a meeting to be specially arranged.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.beThe U.S.S.R.Attitudetowards Sovietabsorption ofthe baltic states.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 245thConclusions,Minute 5.)8. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs referred to telegram No. 840 from Sir Stafford Cripps, containing a furthersuggestion for settling the points at issue between this countryand the Soviet Government in regard to the assets of the baltic states. Sir Stafford&apos;s suggestion was ingenious. It was,however, a cardinal principle of our policy that we should endeavour to carry the United States Government with us, andthe first step was to satisfy ourselves that they would not seeserious objection to a settlement on the lines proposed.Subject to this, he was disposed to allow Sir Stafford toattempt to reach a settlement with the U.S.S.R. on the lines ofhis proposal.The War Cabinet-Approved generally the course of action proposed by theForeign Secretary.
Germany:possible intentions.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 268thConclusions,Minute 4.)reinforcements for the middle east.9. Reference was made to a number of reports as to possible german intentions.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs referred to a reportindicating that the German military authorities had beenstudying the possibility of action in Greece and Yugoslavia, andthat an attempt to invade this country had been postponed untilthe Spring of 1.941.The Prime Minister said that evidence was still accumulatingthat preparations for invasion were still going forward and that itwould be premature to dismiss the possibility of an attempt beingmade. Nevertheless, we should have to consider in the nearfuture the extent to which we could afford to reinforce the middle east at the expense of this country.Reference was also made to the report that General Keitelhad gone to Libya.   There was no confirmation of this rumour.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,October 10, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
