<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/25/9 images: 76-95</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  May 1942.MOST SECRET. V CoP* No&apos;W.P. (42) 22S. &apos;May 28, 1942.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.SUMMARY   OF   OPERATIONS   OF   BOMBER   COMMAND   for fortnight ENDING 1200 HOURS SUNDAY, MAY 24, 1942.Memorandum by Secretary of State for Air.Weather.1. Weather has hampered bombing operations very considerably. Lowcloud and fog have predominated both at home bases and over Germany and north-West France. Conditions over the North Sea were very unfavourableexcept on two nights. On only one night, 19th/20th May, did reasonably fineweather prevail both at home and over Germany.Day conditions have also been unfavourable and only one daylight operation was possible, on the 17th May.Operations9Night BoulogneMannheimSt. NazaireSt. NazaireDay-Boulogne Docks17/18 May19/20 ,,19/2022/23 ,,17 May27 aircraft197652812 aircraft in spite of generally unfavourable weather conditions, it has been found possible to carry out a useful mining effort. . .A total of 419 mines was laid during the period under review, which bringsthe number since the beginning of May up to 917 mines laid. This compares witha total of approximately 2,500 mines laid since the beginning of the war toDecember 1941.During the past three months a record effort of minelaying has taken placein the Western Baltic, the Belts, and in the Sound.Minor Raids.Freshmen carried out two raids on St. Nazaire and one on Boulogne.These attacks were on a heavier scale than usual.A large number of leaflets was again dropped over Occupied and Unoccupied1 TclllCG.[23883]
2Operational Achievements.3.   Mannheim.The spell of bad weather showed break in South-West germany on the 19th May and the opportunity was seized of making an attack of consider-able weight. Navigation was, however, hampered by ground haze and, although a large part of the force readied the vicinity of the target, the attack cannot be claimed as a success.4   Boulogne.In a daylight attack by 12 Bostons with fighter cover on 17th May someaccurate bombing was achieved oil the port area and among groups of barges inthe wet basin. The accompanying photograph taken during the attack showsbombs bursting on the target. There are at least five bursts on the Quay whichjoins the Gare Maritime to the town Station.Information regarding Previous Raids.5.   Renault Works.A series of ground photographs has been secured, and is attached, whichamply confirm previous estimates of the damage to the Renault works.It should be emphasised that these photographs are most secret, and any reference to their existence might compromise their source.6.   Kiel.Recent photographs disclose considerable damage on the West side of the harbour, a part of the town which had not been photographed since the last attackon the 29th/29th April. Between the Karl Strasse and the Hegewische Strassebuildings over an area of 11^ acres have been damaged by fire; 18 buildings havebeen completely gutted. There are further points of damage to property on bothsides of the harbour.7.   Nantes.Recent photographs show that on the island between Bras de la Madeleineand Bras de Permil two large sheds, one of them in the shipyard, are gutted;six large buildings are demolished and several others are damaged by fire or H.e.In the Prairie de la Madeleine three sites have been cleared and a factory building or warehouse has been partially demolished. North of the River Loire there isa large area of damage by blast.8.   Hamburg.A reliable source reports that in the attack on 3rd/4th May very severe damage was caused to property in the northern parts of the city. It has notyet been possible to obtain photographic cover of this area.9.   Dieppe.A photograph is attached showing accurate daylight bombing of the marshal-ling yards on the 8th May by six Bostons. Bombs were dropped from 11,500 feet.It will be seen that 8 bombs are bursting on the yards, including at least one direct hit on rolling-stock; three on buildings west of the yards including a direct hit onengine sheds, and three bursts on buildings in the southern part of the yards.10. &apos; Mining Results.A report has been received dated the 18th May that one of the Gjedser-Warnemunde ferries was recently damaged by a mine, and it is believed thatit will be out of service for some time. It is known that at least two other trainferries have previously been sunk or severely damaged.A Norwegian vessel of 1,422 tons was mined and sank at the South entrance to the Sound on the 20th May.It is reported that the Swedish tanker Procyon, of 8,721 tons, suffered slight damage from a mine.A. H. M. S.
2Operational Achievements.3.   Mannheim.The spell of bad weather showed break in South-West germany on the 19th May and the opportunity was seized of making an attack of consider-able weight. Navigation was, however, hampered by ground haze and, although a large part of the force readied the vicinity of the target, the attack cannot be claimed as a success.i.   Boulogne.In a daylight attack by 12 Bostons with fighter cover on 17th May someaccurate bombing was achieved oil the port area and among groups of barges inthe wet basin. The accompanying photograph taken during the attack showsbombs bursting on the target. There are at least five bursts on the Quay whichjoins the Gare Maritime to the town Station.Information regarding Previous Raids.5.   Renault Works.A series of ground photographs has been secured, and is attached, whichamply confirm previous estimates of the damage to the Renault works.It should be emphasised that these photographs are most secret, and any reference to their existence might compromise their source.6.   Kiel.Recent photographs disclose considerable damage on the West side of the harbour, a part of the town which had not been photographed since the last attackon the 29th/29th April. Between the Karl Strasse and the Hegewische Strassebuildings over an area of 11^ acres have been damaged by fire; 18 buildings havebeen completely gutted. There are further points of damage to property on bothsides of the harbour.7.   Nantes.Recent photographs show that on the island between Bras de la Madeleineand Bras de Permil two large sheds, one of them in the shipyard, are gutted;six large buildings are demolished and several others are damaged by fire or H.e.In the Prairie de la Madeleine three sites have been cleared and a factory building or warehouse has been partially demolished. North of the River Loire there isa large area of damage by blast.8.   Hamburg.A reliable source reports that in the attack on 3rd/4th May very severe damage was caused to property in the northern parts of the city. It has notyet been possible to obtain photographic cover of this area.9.   Dieppe.A photograph is attached showing accurate daylight bombing of the marshal-ling yards on the 8th May by six Bostons. Bombs were dropped from 11,500 feet.It will be seen that 8 bombs are bursting on the yards, including at least one direct hit on rolling-stock; three on buildings west of the yards including a direct hit onengine sheds, and three bursts on buildings in the southern part of the yards.3 0.   Mining Results.A report has been received dated the 18th May that one of the Gjedser-Warnemiinde ferries was recently damaged by a mine, and it is believed thatit will be out of service for some time. It is known that at least two other trainferries have previously been sunk or severely damaged.A Norwegian vessel of 1,422 tons was mined and sank at the South entrance to the Sound on the 20th May.It is reported that the Swedish tanker Procyon, of 8,721 tons, suffered slight damage from a mine.A. H. M. S.


















</content>
</cab>
