<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/184/11 images: 260-269</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF KER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(75) 86 COPY NO25 July 1975CABINETTHE MOTORCYCLE industry memorandum by the Secretary of State for industry. The Ministerial Committee on Industrial Development (XDV) agreedlast &quot;Wednesday that I should discuss with management and workers&apos;representatives the report from Consultants on possible strategies for themotorcycle industry in this country; and because of the need for thisconsultation IDV did not reach final conclusions.    My discussions have notin any way thrown doubt on the general lines of the consultants report;  butthey demonstrated again that if we provide no further support the various parties will join together in levelling powerful and damaging criticismsagainst our handling of their industry,2, The Consultants were asked not to make a specific recommendation;but instead to assess possible strategies.    After a full examination of possible lines they settled on three as the best and the figures for these are summarised on page xix (Annex A) of their own summary of their report,which has already been circulated to members of the Cabinet,    Their costin Government funds ranges from a minimum of at least  15 million to over 50 million with employment between about half the present 3, 000 on motor&apos;cycle production in the former &quot;low&quot; case to about the same as at presentbut with greater productivity in the latter &quot;high&quot; case.    The cost in further government funds would thus be high for the jobs provided and there arevery considerable risks that any of these strategies would fail in the face ofoverwhelming (largely Japanese) competition.    The report brings outpowerfully the way in which our industry has withdrawn &quot;up market&quot; to thelargest &quot;super&quot;bikes (750 cc and above capacity) in response to mountingJapanese competition;  the overwhelming advantages of the Japanese inscale - Honda alone making over 2 million bikes a year against NortonVilliers Triumph&apos;s (NVT&apos;s) 30,000; and the technological and commercialstrengths of the Japanese companies which enable them to continue theirexpansion with new models whilst earning profits and paying substantially higher wages than NVT,
3. This year NVT sales in North America have slumped drastically and stocks financed under Government guarantee have absorbed nearly all thespecial Industry Act support agreed in March;  and would in any event makecut-backs in production necessary straight after the works holiday in two weeks&apos; time.    Such a rundown of NVT!s factories in Birmingham andWolverhampton arises directly because of the collapse of the United Statessales and has nothing to do with the setting up of the Meriden Co-operative.The Japanese with recent models - ours are at least seven years old - have more or less kept up their sales.4, The Co-operative has shown it can produce machines moreefficiently than the factory did before but has so far not supplied any bikesfor the North American market.    Their bike, the Triumph Bonneville, is a pre- -war design and a new model would be needed if the Co-operative is tohave any prospect of long-term survival.    They do not at present have the design expertise;  the name is owned by NVT who are responsible for theirmarketing;  and the Co-operative lacks other managerial and marketingexpertise.5. Both workers and management will argue that they have been misledand accuse the Government of bad faith.    Annexes B-D contain the relevant correspondence.    The reference in Annex B to our being &quot;fullycommitted to securing the future of the motorcycle industry;  and of course this involves the success of NVT no less than the Co-operative&quot; createsthe most difficulty.    In pursuance of these undertakings we moved theOrder on 6 March to authorise an  8 million export guarantee for NVTunder the Industry Act.    With this  8 million and the  4.9 million approvedby the last Administration total assistance to NVT amounts to  12,9 million;whilst for the Co-operative together the  4.95 million finance and thepresent offer of  6 million Export Credits Guarantee Department cover meanwe have made available nearly  11 million in total,6, If we tell the industry that no further support will be provided NVTwill proceed to issue redundancy notices to their workforce;  and may wellclose down their factories over the next three months.    The reaction islikely to be explosive, and could spread to sit-ins and possibly to picketingof Meriden;  and apart from the industry itself I have received powerfulrepresentations from the local Members of Parliament and from the localauthorities and organisations.    Formally the Co-operative would not beaffected at once; but even if their operations are not disrupted by hostile reaction from the NVT workforce, the ability of NVT to market Meridenbikes in North America would be in doubt.    Any special help for theCo-operative would produce an even more hostile reaction from the NVTworkforce.7. All the options put forward by the Consultants depend heavily onurgent steps being taken to remedy present weaknesses in the industry;these include the provision of new and able management;  completing
extensive design and development work in a short period;  and the installation of new plant and rationalisation of production between the threeworks (including Meriden) to bring substantial increases of productivity.The returns and benefits would be small even if everything turned outright;  the Consultants point out that with the &quot;high volume&quot; option therewould be a cumulative deficit in cash flow of at least  51 million in 1979 andthe industry would not recover to a zero cumulative cash flow until the late1980s even if the major risks can be overcome.    The medium volumealternative would show smaller deficits in cash flow but would not achieve azero cumulative cash flow till the early 1990s.    And for the low volumealternative this position would not be recovered for more than 25 years0On top of this it was the view of the recently reconstituted IndustrialDevelopment Advisory Board that the estimated cost of the various strategiesdid not fully quantify some of the risks or contain any contingencies to coveruncertainties in the scale of interim finance stocks nor long-terminvestment;  and their advice was that none of the options in the report heldout any prospect of viability.8. So we have a stark choice.    On the one hand there are powerfulfinancial and economic arguments for refusing further Government support.On the other there are very strong social and political arguments and the likelihood that we shall be bitterly accused of misleading and mishandlingour relations with this industry.    At the meeting which the Chief Secretary,Treasury, and I had with representatives of the Confederation shipbuilding and Engineering Unions and the NVT workers on 24 July, they made it abundantly clear that they relied on the assurances that they considered had been given, that these promises should be discharged by government support for the high volume option and that there was a grave danger of industrial disruption if redundancies or short-term working was introduced at NVT.    Indeed with the likely strength of the reaction in theMidlands and from our own supporters I should not be surprised if theOpposition, who are fully aware of the exchanges that have taken place since march 1974 between the Government, NVT and the workers, and who are inpossession of the relevant correspondence, may make this the occasion fora major attack on our industrial policies.    We shall need to stand firmagainst this;  and it is important that if my colleagues have any feelings thatwe should seek to inject further public funds on a considerable scale into themotorcycle industry we should do so now.    Once I have made anannouncement that we are not providing further funds, if this is the decisionof the Cabinet, I consider there can be no turning back.    I shall wish tomake it clear in my statement that this is a collective decision in whichevery member of the Cabinet is involved.    If NVT went into receivershipand Government could assist in establishing viability for a very much smaller remnant of this concern or possibly to help the Co-operative, we need not rule out making available any appropriate sums needed under theprovisions of the Industry Act, although the basic difficulty of establishing a viable enterprise would remain.
9. Accordingly I seek my colleagues agreement that:a. No further Government funds should be made available to theindustry on the basis of present plans.b. I should inform Parliament in a statement as soon as possible.c. In support of this statement I should make available to the vote Office copies of the full report from Consultants (with sensitiveand confidential information deleted).E J V Department of Industry25 July 1975
COMPARATIVE SUMMARY OF THE STRATEGY ALTERNATIVESModels (cc)Sales (Units)Sales ( 000)New Cash Requirements  ( million)Interim- New plant- Additional working capitalLev Volume750, 100016,70017,411114High Volume500, 750, 100067,00054,45014239Medium Volume750, 100040,50035,6331420.53.5-   Total15il38Employment (Factory)Productivity (Motorcycles per man year)Long Tern Operating Results- Pre-Tax Profits ( 000)- Kefura on Sales (%)Return tdu Nat Assets (%)Sensitiv-ity- ROS % after 10% Price Cut- ROS % after 20% Volume CutEstimated Returns After Finance ChargesI -   Pre-Tax Profit ( 000)- Return on Sales (%)- Return on tiet Assets (%)Contribution to U.K. Balance ci: Payments(  million p.a.)1576 2981 209010.6 22.5 19.4SS9 6590 34235.7 12.1 9.67.5 13.4 9.5(4.3) 2.3 (C.4)0.3 5.3 5.0379 4790 21832.7 3.8 6.12.5 9.3 6.113 41 25Note:    This Table should be. read in conjunction with the note f. overleaf.
ANNEX Briccmlfifyo! ftitn for lndi&apos;:.;fy1 Victori ] Mm &apos;:tLondon :.WUI OtT01-222 7877(o November 1974Convenor;;hop Stewards-imnil Heath WorksJiVTI was very grateful for the frank exchange of views that we hadtoday, which I hope will have dispersed the unfortunate misunder-standing that occurred last Friday.You and your delegation presented very clearly and fully the anxieties felt by your fellow workers at Small Heath, and I rec-opninc the strength of your wish for assurances about the future.You will appreciate, however, that I am not today in a positionio Rive you firm undertakings about possible investment on theVv.is of the long-term plan just presented by the management ofNVT.I can, however, give you my firmest assurance that there will be no discrimination by the Government in favour of the Oo-opcrative *bothe detriment of the Small Heath or Wolverhampton works.    TheGovernment; is fully committed to securing the future of the motorcycle industry in this country, and of course this involves the success of NVT no less than the Co-operative.   Moreover, Ican further assure you that I shall make every effort to see thatthe new plans suggested by NVT are examined urgently.I am looking forward to visiting you on Friday, and I hope that youwill accept what I say as the furthest that I can go at present inearnest of the sincere concern that I feel for the future interestsof the workers whom you represent.I am sending a copy of this letter to Mr Everett.*A V BENN
AKNEX CMOTOR CYCLE industry the Confederation urges the Government to investigate fully the desirabilityto take the British Motor Cycle industry into Public ownership.In view of the urgency of this matter and the time which will be involved in considering the above proposal the following interim actions should take place,1) That Government finance should be made available to create a holdingsituation,j2) The present workforce of NVT should be given the assurances of jobsecurity and job prospects, repeatedly asked for by&apos; their representatives.3) The Government should make immediate appointments to the NVT board,^ The workers co operative at Meriden should be encompassed within the holding situation and final proposals on the public ownership   of theMctor Cycle industry.
SECRET    ,Secretary of Stato for industry Victoria StrsetLondon SW1H GETTelephone Direct Line    01-215Switchboard  01-215 78770(. /December 1974Bob WrightCSEU14-0 Walworth RoadLONDON SE17:;0HTOI7 VI-ELIEKS TRIUMPH AND MERIDENI am writing as I -promised to&apos;record the points: made at our meeting -on 20 December and&quot; my comments on the Statement agreed unanimouslyat the reeling which you held between the workers at the Meriden,;.r.dll Heath and V/olverhampton factories on 16 December, which youia-ided to me at our meeting.First may I express my thanks to you and to Jack Service^ and Tom Crispinfor all the efforts you have made to work out a solution to the difficult problems which face us in this industry.    You emphasised theimportance of getting production, at Meriden re-started as soon aspossible so as to resume the supply of urgently needed-spare parts andto begin to produce motor cycles in time for the American market.    entirely agree with you on this.    For the longer term you stressed theneed for a large cash injection for the motor cycle industry to enao-enew models to be developed and introduced within the next two years andthat this should be achieved by the   Government taking an equity stake in the industry and appointing directors commensurate with the cashprovided.   As I explained to you, I am not at present in a position toGive assurances on those points but I am prepared to ask NRDC oo looksympathetically at any proposals coming forward from NVT and&apos;fromfteriden for assistance in developing new designs of motor cyclessubject, of course, to NRDC1s own policies and statutory duties.You also told me of the absolute conviction by shop stewards at ail&quot;^ree oiants that once a satisfactory solution had been agreed fereoust be a determined drive to increase production and thereby meet the -market.   The stewards had accepted that the three plants were notcompetitive with each other but that their activities werecomplementary.    The Meriden stewards had also given &apos;an assurance thatthey would not press the interests of the Co-operative against thoseof Small Heath and Volverhampton and that after two years the Menoer.stewards would be prepared to accept a &quot;veto&quot; if the workers at Small
- 2 -Heath and Volverhampton decided that their interests were being harmedby the continued operation of the Co-operative.    i welcomed these decisions as helpful and constructive.Regarding the four points made in the Statement, i re-affirmed thatthe offers already made to the Co-operative of  4-.95m of assistancesubject to certain conditions, much of which would be used to buy theiieriden factory from NVT, and &apos;to NVT of up to  8m of export creditguarantees subject to the approval of the House of Commons, remainedopen.   These offers represent the limit of the approvals I already have and to seek to go beyond them would introduce serious further delay and could put the present offers .at risk.On the second point i emphasised that.i could not say that all jobs inthe three plants would be maintained and that the Co-operative has not had a guarantee of this kind.    i did, however, give an assurance thatin the matter of job security there would be no discrimination, infavour of any one plant as against the other two..1 -he third point concerned the appointment of Directors to the NVT 3oard.I have the power to nominate a Director to that Board which&apos; I ampi-spared to exorcise as soon as a suitable candidate can be found.    iI invited the CSEU to let me have their views on -possible candidates.-hi fiuxkh point does nor call for immediate action but i said theviews scores3ed were acceptable to me in principle.-i:r.\.lly, in discussion on the recommendation as to the longer termfuture of the industry in the first paragraph of the   statement, Ipii !;r.at I was ready to consider urgently and seriously any proposalsfor a British motor cycle operation embracing the three plants, togetherv.ith any application for support submitted in the normal way within thepv;ors of the Industry Act 1972.   That Act does not empower me to takefo&apos;/T and Meriden into public ownership though if and when Parliament hasenacted the new industrial legislation forecast in the White Paper onthe Regeneration of British Industry such powers would exist to enable^e to do so by agreement.    If such a request were made by NVT,. theCo-operative and the trade, unions concerned, I would be ready toconsider it urgently.I az copying this letter to Jack Service and Tom Crispin, and also toDennis Poore so that he may know my views on the proposals put forward by the CSEU.k W BENN


</content>
</cab>
