<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/7/71 images: 724-731</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY-S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  June 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)176th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 176 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Saturday, June 22, 1940, at 9-30 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., I The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Lord Privy Seal.secretary affairs.of   State   for   foreign the Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Viscount Caldecote,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Lord Lloyd, Secre-tary of State for the Colonies.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Air Marshal R. E. C. Peirse, Vice-Chief of the Air Staff.Lieutenant-General R. H. Haining,Vice-Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, R.E.Group Captain W. Elliot.[21437b]b
WAR CABINET 176 (40).minute no.123Contents.Subject. PageFrance   ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...    561Armistice conditions demanded by Germany.Broadcast by General de Gaulle     ...      ...      ...      ...     561The French Colonial Empire ...      ...      ...       ...      ...     561Broadcast statement.Appeal to French colonies.Statement by the Prime Minister for publication on sunday, June 23 ..................     562The French Fleet       ..................     562
1. The War Cabinet had before them the following telegrams from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Bordeaux relating to theGerman armistice terms, and in particular to the disposal of theFrench Fleet : Nos. 511, 512, 513, 514, 516, 517, 518 DIPP.In the course of the meeting, it was reported that, accordingto the Germans, an armistice had been signed by the French. Thisagreement would not, however, take effect until six hours after an armistice had been concluded between France and Italy.At the very end of the meeting a telegram was received fromSir R. Campbell confirming that an armistice had been signed(telegram No. 550 DIPP). But it was not known whether the terms were those previously reported by him.In the light of this information, the War Cabinet considered a number of matters, the most important of these being the positionof the French Fleet.Broadcast byGeneral de gaulle.(previous reference erence:2. The Minister of Information read to the War Cabinet thedraft of a broadcast which General de Gaulle was proposing tomake to France over the British wireless.conclusions minute 11.)The First Lord of the Admiralty said he was concerned onlyVv-j 1n t to prevent the French Fleet from falling into the hands of ther,rmp.iiiainTin 8 enemy&apos; Du-f ne doubted whether a broadcast in such strong termswas wise, on psychological grounds. We did not yet know that wehad been betrayed by the French, since it appeared from telegrams nos. 517 and 518 DIPP that Marshal Petain had renewed hisassurances regarding the safety of the French Fleet. The broadcastmight alienate the feelings of many Frenchmen.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pointed out thatthe British Government were not in any way compromised by allowing a distinguished French officer like General de Gaulle touse our wireless for broadcasting. His message was a personal oneto his own countrymen, and he was not acting as the mouthpiece ofthe British Government.The Secretary of State for the Colonies supported this view,,and said that he had been informed by many French officers, when in Bordeaux recently, that, if it had not been for general de Gaulle&apos;s previous broadcast, they would never have known of the opportunities we were offering to them to continue the strugglealongside us.The War Cabinet-Invited the Minister  of Information  to  arrange  forGeneral de Gaulle to broadcast at 10 p.m. in the terms which had been read over to them.French colonial empire.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 175thConclusions,Minute 4.)Broadcaststatement.Appeal to french Colonies.3. The Minister of Information proposed that a statement should be broadcast of the splendid and encouraging replies whichwe had received from all the French colonies. The necessary material had been assembled and the statement was ready and couldbe delivered by the B.B.C. in their midnight broadcast.This was agreed to.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs read a draft statement which had been prepared for issue as soon as it was certain that France had agreed to the terms of the armistice,appealing to the French Colonies to continue the war.In a short discussion one or two amendments were made to thedraft.[21437b]b 2Armisticeconditionsdemanded by-Germany.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 175th(Conclusions,Minute 4.)
The War Cabinet-(1) Invited the Minister of Information to arrange for the broadcast at midnight the 22nd-23rd June, summarising the encouraging replies received from the french colonies.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to issue to our Consuls in French territories the statementprepared appealing to the French Colonies to continuethe war.(3) Invited the Secretary of State for the Colonies to arrangefor a statement on same lines as (2) to be issued toColonial Governors.Statement by 4.   In the course of the previous discussion the Prime minister the Prime suggested that another broadcast should be made on behalf of theMinister for Government, as soon as possible, dealing with terms which GermanyPublication on had imposed on France. These could be described as being of the sunday, most murderous character, such as would make the French Govern-23rd June.        ment the tool of the enemy in striking down the late ally of France.It  should be made clear that the  Bordeaux  Government,  in accepting these terms, had negotiated under duress and had been deprived of all liberty.The Prime Minister prepared, a draft which was read to theWar Cabinet, and agreed to the amendment.The War Cabinet Authorised the Minister of Information to arrange forthis statement to be broadcast on Sunday, the 23rd June.The French 5.   The discussion on this matter is recorded in the Secretary&apos;sFleet. Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.(Previous The War Cabinet agreed-Reference:W.M. (40) 175th (i) With a view to the vital need for obtaining control of theConclusions, French Navy the following action should be takenMinute 4.) immediately : (a) A further appeal should be addressed to admiral darlan in the form of personal messages from theFirst Lord and the First Sea Lord.[The terms of these messages were settled in the course of the meeting.](&amp;) Simultaneously an appeal should be made to AdmiralEstava at Oran. It was proposed that this appeal should be made by the Vice-Chief of naval staff who should fly out at once. It was also proposed that Lord Lloyd should accompany the vice--Chief of Naval Staff on his visit to Oran.Besides providing valuable support in connectionwith the discussion in regard to the Fleet,Lord Lloyd might later proceed to Tunis, andpossibly Syria, with a view to stiffening french resistance in these Colonies.Note. Subsequent to the above decision havingbeen reached, confirmation was received thatthe French had signed an armistice.Accordingly after the Meeting, the PrimeMinister, in consultation with the foreign secretary, decided that it would be wiser thatthe visit of Lord Lloyd and the Vice-Chief
of Naval Staff to Or an should be postponed for, say, 24 hours, pending information asto how the situation was developing.(c) The Admiralty should assume responsibility for making sure that the French battleships Richelieuand Jean Bart did not leave the ports of Dakarand Casablanca respectively.French warships inBritish Ports.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 175thConclusions,Minute 4.)6. In continuation of the discussion recorded in the previousminute, the First Lord of the Admiralty enquired what action should be taken in regard to these warships now that the FrenchGovernment had signed the armistice.The War Cabinet Invited the First Lord of the Admiralty to make certainthat these warships remained in British Ports. This could probably be done by continuing to take procrastinatingaction.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1.June 23, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
