<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/56/0 images: 51-63</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MOST     SECRET*     *     *THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR HOME AFFAIRS firstgave details of the crime.On the Sr5th August a bomb had exploded in thecarrier of a tradesman^ s cycle in a street at Coventry.The explosion had been one of great violence.   Fivepersons had been hilled and 50 injured.   Extensive damagehad been caused, and fragments of the bicycle had beenhurled 300 yards.   The criminal charges had been basedon the death of a girl who had been passing at the timeand had been blown to pieces.    It had only been possibleto identify the body by a ring on her finger and someclothing.   The crime was very much in the mind.;? of thepeople of Coventry.Five people had. been put on trial, of whom threehad been acquitted, and two, James Richards and PeterBarnes, had been convicted of murder.   The three acquittedpersons had been the landlord of the house in whichRichards had lodged, the landlord* s wife, and the wif e* smother.   Richards had. not sought to conceal that he hadbeen connected with the I.R.A., or that he had come overspecially for the purpose of preparing the sort of crimewhich had taken place.   He had said, &quot;What I did I did for ireland&quot;.   Barnes, on the other hand, had. denied allconnection with the I.R.A.Richards had taken up residence in Coventry witha vie1&quot; to committing crimes in the district.   The bombhad been prepared in the house in which he lodged.   Hehad bought the cycle, in the carrier of which the bombhad exploded, and had collected it from the shop.-1-
He had had charge of the cycle and. the bomb to within two hours of the time when the explosion had taken place.It seemed, almost certain that the bicycle had been takento the place where the explosion had occurred by some person who had not been identified.At the date of the crime, Barnes had been living in London, having come over from Sire at the beginning ofAugust.   On the day before the explosion, he had taken toCoventry the moot important ingredients of the bomb, andhad been at Richards&apos; lodgings.   He had probably leftCoventry the night before the explosion, and had left inexpectation that some dramatic event would shortly takeplace.It was fair to point out, however, that there was probably no intention that the bomb should explode in theplace where it did.The events on the date when the crime had been committed had been as follows.   On the morning of the25th August, the Police had raided a house in LeinsterGardens, in the Paddington district, where they had foundfour men and three bombs.   One of the bombs had alreadybeen set to explode at 2.30 p.m. that afternoon, and theclockwork mechanism set going.   The other two bombs were fully prepared, but not yet set.   T1he Police had expectedto find four bombs.   It was believed that the three bombsthey had found had been intended for the Bank of England,Scotland Yard and Westminster Abbey.What follows was somewhat by way of being aspeculation.   It was known that Barnes had associated witithe four men who had been taken prisoner in London, andit seemed likely that the Coventry bomb was the fourth ofthe four bombs which the Police had expected to find inthe Leinster Gardens house.    It also seemed likely thatit had been intended that the Coventry explosion should
synchronise with explosions in London.    It might well be,therefore, that the man who had taken the bicycle in coventry to the place where the explosion took place,had tried, to get in touch with the members of the I.R.A,in the Leinster Gardens house in London;    that he had failed to do so owing to the Police raid;    that he had then been uncertain what to do, and had been afraid to go back and obtain the bicycle with the bomb in the carrier.On the Home Office practice, which was very care-fully recorded, it was clear that there was no ground for idistinguishing between Richards and Barnes.   Nor was there any ground on which clemency could, possibly be urged.It was true that it had not been intended that the explosion should take place where it had taken place, andthat it had not been established, that Richards or Barnesdesired or expected to kill.   But the explosion had been an extremely violent one.   Nor was it the first explosion of its kind which had caused loss of life, others having taken place with fatal results at Manchester and at King&apos;sCross Station.   There had. also been other cases where ithad only been by the greatest good fortune that explosionshad not resulted in death:    e.g., the explosion inPiccadilly.   Richards and Barnes had. not concerned them-selves with the question whether, when the bomb exploded,it would or would not destroy human life;    and it was clear that, wherever it exploded, there would be the gravest danger to human life.   Where s. felony was committed in circumstances which involved a serious risk to life,that was murder.   The fact that the hand which had placed the bomb in the place where the explosion took placewas not the hand of Richards or Barnes, was irrelevant.On juridical and compassionate grounds there was no sort of doubt as to the view which should be taken on HomeOffice practice.
synchronise with explosions in London *   It asigat well be,therefore, that the taan who had taken the bicycle in coventry to the place where the explosion took place,had tried to get in touch with the metayers of the I.R,A*in the Leinster Gardens house in London!   that he had failed to do so owing to the police raid?   that he had then been uncertain what to do, and had been afraid to go back and- obtain the bicycle with the bosfe.&apos;&apos;in the carrier *On the Home Office practice, which was very care-fully recorded, it was clear, that there was no ground for.?-distinguishing between Richards and Barnes,   Nor was there any ground on which clemency could, possibly be urged.It was true that it had not been intended that the explosion should take- place where it had taken place, andthat it had not been established that Eichards or Barnesdesired or expected to kill.   But the explosion had been an extremely violent one*   STor was it the first explosion of its kind which had caused loss of life, others having taken plaee with fatal results at Manchester and at King*sCross Station^   there had also been other cases where ithad only been by the greatest good fortune that explosionshad not resulted in death:   e-*g*, the explosion inPiccadilly *   Biehards and Barnes had not concerned them-selves with the Question whether, when the bomb exploded,it would or would not destroy human life?   and it was clear that, wherever it exploded, there would be the gravest danger to human life.  Where a felony was committed in circumstances which involved a serious risk to life,that was murder.   The fact that the hand which had placed the bomb in the place where the explosion took placewas not the hand of Richards or Barnes, was irrelevant *On Juridical and compassionate grounds there w^s no sort of doubt as to the view which should be taken on HomeOffice practice,:-   &apos;*g&quot;*-- . &apos;&apos;&apos;:?;M.
tt was true that It was not the invariable practice to lot the/law take its course in cases of this type, i*e*,a felony eonaittea in circumstances which involved a serious risk to life* . -It-was, however^ the practice that the-law should not take its course only in cases in which it was most unlikely that death would result from the felony Iirhere, indeed, the fact that death resulted could fairlyhe described as a misfortune.  A good illustration of this type of ease: was afforded by an attempt which had been madeto break gaol at Londonderry early in 19S1.       that attemptseveral warders had been chloroformed, and one or two haddied.   This had been a border-line cases in which it hadbeen decided      perhaps partly on political grounds *-that the balance lay in favour of clemency.TH1 MINISTER said that it was clear thatthese men deserved the full penalty of the law, and. thatthere was no Justification for clemency on merits *   Itmight, however, be necessary to take Other considerationsinto account.   What was the Home Secretary*s position ifsuch considerations were taken into account?THI HOMTJ SECRETARY said that there was no clearlyrecorded, definition of the Home Secretary*s responsihiii-ties in this matter.   The best opinion which he could formwas that the Home secretary responsibilities were not limited to juridical or compassionate grounds?   that onthe Home Secretary fell the ultimate responsibility forthe advice tendered to the Eing*   it was the duty of theHome Secretary to take into account all relevant considera-tions . Where political considerations were involved, he must be in a position to weigh up those considerations,and it was right that he should consult those who mightbe in a better position than hiss elf to determine the weight that should properly be attached to them,  $hisclearly involved, consultation with his colleagues *
At the same time, the final onus of responsibility fOT theadvice tendered lay with him*General agreement was expressed with this view,THE mmmum OF THE TOHEQtJER Adding that these other considerations were only relevant where, but for suehconsiderations^ the death penalty would be enforced.Political considerations oould not, of course, be allowedto weigh in favour of inflicting the death penalty where,but for such considerations, clemency would be shown.THE HOME SECRETARY added that his position in thematter was closely analogous to that of the Attorney-general in deciding whether to launch a prosecution or to abandona prosecution when once launched.   The Cabinet might wellindicate certain considerations to the Attorney-General,but the responsibility for the final decision would rest with the Attorney.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DOMINION AFFAIRS saidthat he had already had an opportunity for discussion onthis matter with the Home Secretary.   He agreed that thesemen deserved the death penalty *   He thought, however, thatit was necessary also to take into account considerations of expediency, deriving mainly from the fact that we were at war.   He referred to the letters from Sir John Maffeyand Mr de Valera., which had been circulated to hiscolleagues *   (Copies ,are.., anneste^ to. this Hote.)    the overwhelming view in lire, and of his advisers, was thatthe l.R,A. movement was generally regarded as misjudgedand mischievous.   If, however, these two men were giventhe halo of martyrdom, there would be an increase in I*R.A*activities, both here and in Ireland.He referred to the interview between Mr de valera and Sir John Maf fey.   It was clear that the former fearedan increase of I*R*A. activity.   Reference had also beenmade at this interview to the position In the United States
Mr de valera had intended to go to the TMited states^ witha view to educating Irish opinion there *  Mr de Valerathought that if the executions were carried, out, greattrouble would ensue in America, and that difficulties would follow in-northern Ireland and elsewhere.   The Secretary of$tate said that confirmatory evidence as to opinion in theUnited states came from a Mr Oohl&amp;n, the. editor. of &quot;the^Gaelic Ameriean% who had been a supporter of Mr Gosgraveand now held a Judicial position in the tJnited States.A ratessa-ge had also been received from the PapalNuncio in Dublin, s?he had made unofficial representationsagainst allowing the law to take its course.   His ownadvisers took the&apos; same view.-  The Duke of Devonshire, whohad many contacts in Ireland, thought that it would be a major mistake to allow these men to be executed, and thatthere would be a crop of outrages if the sentences were carried out.   Opinion in Ireland \?as that our failure to distinguish between political and non-political crime wasone of our least explicable qualities*   He (the Secretaryof Stafc e) thought that if these men were put to death, theywould be regarded as martyrs, and that this would.be the   jbest possible advertisement for the I.R.A.   The executionof the sentences would not be a deterrent, but a stimulant.At the present time the Government of Eire were taking a strong line with the T*R*A**   but if the sentenceswere carried out, their position would be weakened, anti-British feeling and Irish sympathies would increase abroad,and trouble might ensue on the boundaries of northernIreland.   Ho doubt commutation of the sentences would besubject to criticism in this country, but he thought thatsuch criticism would be short-lived *THE HOME $ECRETARY -was asked whether, if the sentences were commuted, it was necessary to give reasons *He said that the Home Office view was strongly against
giving reasons In such eases!   but in fact in a number ofimportant cases it bad been found impossible to escapegiving reasons In public, and lie felt sure that it wouldbe impossible to avoid giving reasons in the present case if the sentences were eesrsauted,   Xn a case of this kind,if-clemency was shown, the normal course was a sentence of penal servitude for life.emoluments LORD PRIVY SEAL recalled to the war Cabinetthe position in the previous Summer, when we had been facedwith formidable difficulties in obtaining convictions andin arresting suspects.   Public opinion had been so stronglyworked up that it had been possible to pass unanimouslythrough the House of Commons a very strong Bill giving theGovernment additional powers.It was important to keep in mind the position ofthe Police, who had great difficulties in unravellingthese conspiracies.   He remembered Sir Norman Kendalsaying to him that the Police were afraid that, if theycaught a guilty person, they might fail to get a conviction?or that, if they got a conviction, the sentences might becommuted.    Once the sentence had been commuted, therewould, of course, be a tendency later on to ask that theperiod of imprisonment should be drastically reduced,which would result in the infliction of a wholly inadequatepenalty.   On all these grounds, therefore, there was astrong case for allowing the law to take its course.But we were no longer in August, 19SS.  While he saw all the objections, from the point of view of thePolice, to commutation of the sentences, in time of warit was necessary to accept unpleasant consequences.   We must take what action was best calculated to help us win the war*He was not so much influenced by what would be said In Hire,since we were always being told that if we would make this
oi? that concession to Blre they would adopt a more friendsly attitude to us?   and in the event they did not do so*Opinion in the United states, however, mattered a greatdeal morea   The Clan na Gael had a strong nuisanoe value,\thlle he would not press the Home Secretary on the matter,he thought that this was a consideration which should begiven great weight*TH1 f HIST LORD OF &quot;ME MSMMMJUt thought that thefact that we were at war told the other way.   It was mostimpolitic to fall to execute Justice according to law ina case of this kind.   Such action would not square withan equal standard of justice, especially at a time whenmen were risking their lives daily for their country *Failure to execute these men would not relieve us of ourtroubles in lire.   Long sentences were never enforced,and these men knew that if their sentences were commuted,their caseawould be worried over until they were let outafter, say, five years.   His Majesty&apos;s lieges had a right-to protection,   its for the suggestion that the executionswould be an embarrassment to Mr de Valera, if this argu-ment was to have weight no-one would ever be afforded the due protection of the law.   If we yielded to this clamour,there was no logical basis on which we could rest*   Irishopinion in the United States was of very limited effect,and it was useless to think that any action on our part would placate the small secret societies.   In any casehe strongly deprecated the idea that, in order to placateopinion in the United states, we should fail to give HisMajesty4s lieges their due protection.   He had no doubtthat we must do our duty and allow the law to take itscours e *THB OHAHOBLLOR OF THE BX0H10JJER drew attentionto the fact that three former HomeSecretaries werepresent.   On the whole, his view went with that of theLord Privy Seal.   He thought we had no choice but to
5&apos;.4sexamine this matter from the point of view of wM eh coursewould be most helpful to our war effort ,   If to carry outthe extreme penalty in these cases would have serious consequences for us, then we were not failing in our dutyif we decided to show, cleaency*   fhe real question was whether there was solid ground for believing that theexecutions would prejudice our war efforts   tt was well to remember that there had been cases in the past wherethe view had been taken that it was not wise to commutea death sentence, but where, looking back* it seemed clearthat the infliction of the death penalty had not been justified by the results.   He referred to the case ofLarkin, who had been executed in Manchester and who was regarded as a martyr.   It was not weakness to try and look at what was politically the wiser course.   His own view,although with much hesitation, went with the Lord privy seal.TH1 SECRETARY OP STAI1! FOE AIR asked what would happen if the sentences on these two men were coBEautedand two more murders were committed in the ensuing week?THS OHAirCETJLOE OF THE said that if furtherjeases took place it would be necessary to inflict theextreme penalty.fHE MOMS SIORETAHY said that he felt extremedistaste and difficulty in arguing against the suggestions for mercy, but he thought it was necessary to consider thepolitical aspect of the matter in regard to England,northern Ireland and Eire.As regards England, the protection of the peopleof this country weighed considerably with him.   It was his duty to see that the public received proper protection,The present case was not the first, nor an isolatedoases   nor was there any reason to suppose that the I*H*A*would be influenced to desist from crime by clemency *
The purpose of the I*R*A* was to weaken our war effort.The effect of el amen cy In this case on the majority of people in this country would be deplorable*It had been the policy - of the Some Office: to refrain from giving reasons for the exereise of the prerogative of mercy, but it bad not always been possibleto refrain from giving reasons.   It was impossible toprevent a Bebate In the House of Commons in a ease wherethe circumstances suggested that political considerationshad weighed heavily in the decision,   The Home secretary said that he had referred the whole case to Sir ErnleyBlaekwell, who was of opinion that, in this case, reasonswould have to be given.   Sir Irnley had added, &quot;I cannotframe one which would go near to satisfying the public&quot;*The Home Secretary then referred to the case ofRonald True, who was ordered to be detained during his majesty&apos;s pleasure, after a statutory inquiry into hismental condition.   In that case the Adjournment had been moved by Commander Kenworthy,   When the Motion was called,forty Members had not risen in their places?   but otherwise it would have been impossible to prevent a Debate On that case.The Home Secretary then turned to the effect on northern Ireland and on the Government of northern Ireland,which, he thought, would be considerable.   It was not as though the I*R,A* suspended activities after the Coventrymurders *   The Hioenlx i?ark affair had taken place several-months afterwards.   A reprieve would be a direct invitation to the I*R*A* to continue their outrages*The Home Secretary then dealt with the effect onopinion in Ireland,   It was not true that every Irishmanwho was hanged became a martyr.   One rarely heard the names of the two men who had murdered Sir Henry Wilson.He found it impossible to judge this case without reference
hie own experiences in Ireland when he had been 0nder**Secretary in Dublin at the end of the Great War.   He hadbeen there when the first murderer had been, convictedafter the bad tiises in 1919 ^Kewin Barry * a youth of 18*His- own decision had been in favour of-Barry*s execution.,but strong arguments had been urged in favour- of clemency.Sarry had been executed.   The Home Secretary said that hewas net aware that the effects in that case had been otherthan good.   It was necessary to convince those who wereconducting the t.R*A. campaign that they must stop their activities *   He could not take any other view in thepresent case than that the balance was heavily in favourof allowing, the law to take its course.The Home Secretary also quoted the views of Judge^lie, who had held office under the British Governmentand under the Free State Government, and was a man ofliberal views.   He had expressed the very definite opinionthat the only proper line was to let the law take itseourse* .He also referred to the views expressed by Mr de valera*s supporters in the Bail, when the Bill givingthe Eire Government more drastic powers had been underconsideration.   They had said that their patience had beensorely tried, and that they had attempted conciliationTHE PRIME MINISTER said that he had come to theMeeting disposed to support the plea that these sentencesshould be commuted on the ground of expediency, havingregard to the effect on our war efforts   but, having heardthe Home Secretary&apos;s views, he entirely accepted thoseviews *THS SECRETARY OF STATS FOR A3R and THS MINISTERFOR CO**0RDUIATIOH OF BEFE&amp;CE expressed their agreement *The former said that If these sentences were eeraaiuted
-is-we would soon be faced with another ease in which we shotidhave to carry out the death penalty.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR BOOfXHXOSr AFFAIRS saidthat the one point he wished to stress was $he effect onour war effort *   It was because he thought that* if the sentences were carried out* the I.R.A. would gain sympathy and that our troubles would increases that, he favouredcommutation.THE MIHXSTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO thought that commuta-tion of the sentences in this case would do us great harmand would be regarded as a sign of weakness throughout theworld.   This was not, in-his view, a border-line: case.He would as soon give way to Nazi opinion as to the opinionof Irish sympathisers in the United States,THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS saidthat his mind went with that of the Prime Minister, although he was disposed to rate more highly some of the consequences!of carrying out the sentences.   Before hearing the HomeSecretary, his judgment had been disposed to go the other way?   but, having heard the Home Secretary, he had come tothe conclusion, rather reluctantly, that it was difficultto resist the Home Secretary4s arguments.THE PR BUS MINISTER said that the discussion shouldnot be recorded in- the Minutes of the War Cabinet.* * *

</content>
</cab>
