<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/56/0 images: 123-123</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Confidential Motes ..WMA g,gij7(SLth- CONCLUSIONS..9 oil .39Minute 2.Air Situa-tion.Minute 4.Naval Situa-tion.In reply to a question THE DEPUTY&quot; CHIEF OP THEAIR STAFF said that the German flying training wasstrictly limited owing to the restriction of petrol.THE FIRST LORD- OF THE ADMIRALTY said that theprotective shield of ten submarines (the &quot;Pad&quot; asthe First Lord calls it), which was sent out to theWestern edge of the minefield&apos; in the North Sea whenthe rumoured invasion of this country was under dis-cuss ion ten days ago, had now been withdrawn, as the submarines had been at sea for some time.   They wouldbe kept at present at home ports at short noticesWoM.(S9)  77th CONCLUSIONS..holland and Bel belgium.Air Policy.9 oil .59.9.50 Pern.The account of this Meeting is, perhaps, not quiteas clear as it might be.   It should be recorded that,whereas C.A.S. returned at 6 p.m. and had had time towork up, in conjunction with General Ismay, a detailed statement of what had happened at the Conference, theC.I.G.S. did. hot return until after dinner, havingcomeback by sea.   It had been contemplated that CA.S.should give the main account of the visit, but the.G.I.G.S. gave an account of the contemplated movements of land forces which perhaps failed to bring out onerather important point.   This point is that, whereas the movements for the advance up to the Scheldt are fully worked out, the suggested seizure of variousislands was not put forward by the French as more thana rather ill-defined projet.Another point which should be recorded is that .whereas the C.T.G.S. stated that General Gamelin andGeneral Georges thought that a move on the part of theGermans was bound to take place shortly, and expectedthat this would take the form of an invasion of Holland;the C.A.S*s impression was that the French did not expect any such movements and were viewing the matterextremely calmly, although they were prepared for sucha movement if it took place.My personal impression of the discussion on air policy was that there was a good deal more opinionagainst the proposal to launch a heavy air attack on military objectives in the Ruhr, in the event of aGerman invasion of Holland and Belgium (irrespective of whether the Germans had inflicted heavy casualties &quot;&quot;on civilians outside the battle zone), than was perhapsapparent on the surface.

</content>
</cab>
