<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/56/0 images: 128-129</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M. (59 ) 89th CONCLUSIONS;39 .3.3,.59Minute, 1.The air situation-Minute 2.R.A.P. Recon-naissanee ofGerman Fleet.Minute, 5.The naval situation.Minute 2.The naval situation.Minute 5.Polish Forces,Formation andEquipment.Minute 2.The naval situation.Minute 5.shipping losses.igneticMines.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR reported thatballoon-like objects had been seen off Yarmouth;   alsoa merchant ship with barrels on the poop.   The formermay well have been the first occasion on Which magnetic mines were seen being dropped from aircraft.In connection with this item it was mentioned,       ,after the Meeting, that there was a possibility thatan attempt might be made, in connection with theoperation referred to, to bomb a Battleship undercons truct ion.In connection with the Naval Situation, reference was made by THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY to thepossibility that we might use the magnetic mine on german rivers.W.M. (59) 90th CONCLUSIONS.Reference was made to the dropping of mines by aircraft.   A project for the development of this typeof mine was under investigation by the Royal Air Force,but had been taken over by the Admiralty on the groundthat it was a Naval weapon.   Obviously the Royal AirForce think that the Admiralty have not pressed on with it as quickly as they might.A suggestion by the MINISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OFDEFENCE that the whole of the southern part of theNorth Sea should be declared a mined area did not meet with approval.THE FDUST LORD expressed great determination todrag, scrape and plough a channel out of the City OfLondon.THE MINISTER FOR CO-ORDINATION OF DEFENCE produced a draft Agreement which was circulated at the Meeting.Exception was taken to this Agreement on the twogrounds referred to at the conclusion of the accountof the discussion, and a Minute which had been preparedJI think, in some haste before the Meeting, was with-drawn.W.M. (59) 91st CONCLUSIONS.22.11.59THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY stated that theFleet was in Western Scottish waters .THE CHIEF OF THE NAVAL STAFF said that theAdmiralty, as the result of experiments carried out over a number of years, did not think that magnetic mines would operate in depths greater than 120 fathoms&apos; The view was generally expressed that this mightbe the &quot;s ecret weapon&quot; of which Herr Hitler had spoken JTHE FIRST LORD again expressed the greatest eonfi-denee that the Admiralty woi^d Mster this new weapon.
THE LORD PRIVY SEAL reported that the Minister   vof shipping had informed him--that the Norwegianshipping deal had been settled, and that he had alsoSucceeded in obtaining 20 Greek, and a number of Yugo-Slav ships.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY was distressedto hear that all the Norwegian ships to be obtainedunder this deal would hot be in our hands at an earlydate, as he was anxious to take early steps toprevent the export of ore from Narvik.   He would shortly be putting before the War Cabinet a paper explaining how he propos ed to do this.. 0 .......  ^W.M.-.(-89) 92nd CONCLUSIONS.S5 a^.^L Ofl59..oMinute 1.The air situation,In connection with the visit of German pilotsto the Shetlands, reference was made to a foreignreport that the Germans contemplated seizing a base in the Shetlands.Minute 2.The naval situation,THE CHIEF OF NAVAL STAFF gave the War Cabinetinformation as to the anti-submarine defences in theForth.   These were complete, except in respect ofthe Loop minefield, which would be ready before thenext visit of the Fleet.   Work was going on as rapidly as possible on the anti-submarine defencesof scapa.Request forSecret Session.After the conclusion of the matters recorded inthe Minutes, a discussion took place &quot;off the record&quot;on two matters.   The first concerned a request byMr Attlee for a Secret Session on Supply.THE PRIME MINISTER&apos;s view was that, provided aSecret Session were asked for on a specific subject and was confined to that subject, he had not muchobjection to it.On the other hand the view was expressed that ifthere was a Secret Session in the Commons there wouldhave to be one in the Lords, where the Rules ofDebate were very wide.   Further, that if a Se cretSession was agreed to on Supply, one would be askedfor next week on Air, and so on and so forth.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY thought that aSecret Session would amount to no more than a general discussion on the War, which would be rather afterthe fashion of itatements made by Ministers to the1922 Committee.   He thought that the Secret Sessionsin the Great War had done good, but a very powerfulcase could be made out on Supply matters.The question of secrecy was referred to.   It was generally agreed that it would be impossible to rely on the information given being kept secret, and thatreally secret information cOuld not, therefore, beimparted.   On the other hand, if the informationimparted became known, there would be a good argument against having another Secret Session.In conclusion, THE PRIME MINISTER said that hehad still to discuss the matter with the Chief Whipand he could not yet come to any decision.

</content>
</cab>
