<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/56/0 images: 141-141</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
9KoM.(59) 119th. CONCLUSIONS.E.E.B. absent *19.12.29Minute 1-.P.M*s visit to Prance.Minute g.ShippingDelays.Minute 5.BritishCasualties.W.M.C59) 120th CONCLUSIONS.20.12.S9Minute 8.Supply of aircraft to finland.The P.M. pressed the War Office to investigatewhether the 25 mm. anti-tank gun could not be adopted inthe British Army .As an illustration of the ways in which shippinggets delayed, it was noticeable that the First Lordstated that the sailing of the Norwegian Convoy had been delayed for 48 hours for fear the Germans might try toattack it as some recompense for the destruction of the admiral GRAF SPEE.The figures of casualties given by the Secretary ofState for War were 10, including 3 Offleers.   He subse-quently altered this, presumably to exclude certainaccidental casualties which resulted from one of our patrols walking into one of our own mines and had been blown up on it.   This was mentioned in the discussion.Telegram No. 256 from The Hague was mentioned bythe Foreign Secretary towards the end of the War Cabinetproceedings.   As it seemed to be contradictory to theprevious information given under this item^ it seemedas well to relate the items one to the other.There was some dispute afterwards as to whether thefree gift was to include only the 28 Gauntlets or theadditional 10 Gladiators.   In the Office we were quite certain that the gift related only tothe 28 Gauntlets.The Air Ministry asked for a copy,of the Minute and, on receiving it drafted in this sense, told us that theSecretary of State for Air had said that the gift also included the 10 Gladiators.   We said that we differedand would consult the Treasury, whereupon we were told that a decision in the wider sense had already been communicated to the Finns s   whereupon I communicated withthe Chancellor of the Exchequer and got him to agree tothe gift covering both the 10 Gladiators and the 28Gauntlets.W.M.(59) 12Jst CONCLUSIONS.Nothing to record.21.12.39WoMo(39) 122nd CONCLUSIONS.22.12.59As the War Cabinet dealt first with two very longitems, the Prime Minister suggested that the usualreports on the Military and Political Situations mightbe omitted unless there was something of special interest the SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR said that two of Our&quot;Hampdehs&quot;, which had been out oh reconnaissance overthe German flying-boat stations , had been brought down that morning by our own fi^ttters.   These aircraft hadbeen opposed by a north-west gale and had made theirlandfall in the-Firth of Forth instead Of hear the

</content>
</cab>
