<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/56/0 images: 158-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
At the end, after all but the War Cabinet hadretired, information was given as to President Roose-velfs peace feelers, which wales recorded elsewhere.THE FOREIGN SECRETARY reminded his colleagues that before he went to Paris he had said that he expected to see Mr Prytz.   Re had failed to do so as mr Prytz had been delayed.   He asked for the PrimeMinister&apos;s mind as to whether he should ask to see Mr Prytz at once, or whether this would give too muchprominence.THE PRIME MINISTER thought that the foreign secretary should give Mr Prytz 24 hours to ask for an interview, and, if he did not do so, that Lord Halifaxshould then take the initiative.W.M. (40) 56th CONCLUSIONS.8 .2 .40,Minute 2.The naval situation.Minute 8.Vote &quot;A&quot;.Red BalloonS care.Minute 5.-^jlllAssistaneefcrwv/to Finland.There was really nothing which necessitated aMeeting of the War Cabinet, but the Prime Minister didnot like the suggestion either of postponing the WarCabinet to a later hour or of not having a Meeting.Some of the subjects discussed were rather discussed by way of filling in time.The First Lord mentioned that H.M.S. REPULSEwould soon reach Devonport, and that he was going to let the newly-arrived Italian Naval Attache see her.He seemed to be well-disposed towards us, spoke Englishvery well, and had an attractive wife.The Secretary of State for War was very anxious that maximum numbers should not be used.   His predecessorlhad stated that we should have three million men underarms by August.    In reaching this figure he had included the total number of men in various Classes which wereto be called up, and had thereby included 50 per cent,of those Classes who were in reserved occupations andwould not be called to the Colours.   It would, therefore,]be extremely embarrassing for the War Office to quoteany figure.At the end of the Meeting there was a referenceto a scare which had started through a red balloonfloating about in the Eastern Counties.   This balloonhad been sent up for meteorological purposes, but ithad apparently given rise to a scare that gas balloonswere being let loose by the Germans.   The london passenger Transport Board had told their employees tobe ready to put on their gas-masks!W*M. (40), 57th CONCLUSIONS.9 sg .40 oxe M.P. who was the recipient of unasked        ^and unjustified confidences from M. Reynaud and M. Leger,was Mr Victor Oazalet.   Lord Halifax also said thatM? Robert Boothby, M.P., had given some information which seemed to imply that he had heard of the develop-ments in regard to assistance to Finland.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL said that he understood thatGeneral Georges was against the proposals *
After everyone except members of the War cabinet had retired, THE PRIME MINISTER referred to the agreementwith the railways which had been announced in the newspapersthe previous evening, and said that he thought the WarCabinet ought to have been informed of the position,although he did not think any harm had been done.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER agreed that heshould have reported the matter, although, broadly speaking,we were getting what we wanted.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL suggested that it would bedesirable that the Home Policy Committee should be informed of matters of this kind, having regard to reactions on other Departments.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER undertook to givethe War Cabinet information on thekubject, probably onMonday next.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS saidthat Mr Dal ton had come to see him oh the previous -day aridhad talked to him for three-quarters of an hour.   He hadbeen rather puzzled as to why Mr Dalton had come to see him.Mr Dalton had had a certain amount of information as to peace feelers put forward by German Generals.   He saidthat there was a good, deal of rumour current in his Party,which he did his best to check, to the effect that certain members of the War Cabinet (in particular, the Prime Ministerand Lord Halifax) were frequently in receipt of peacefeelers and were somewhat suspect on this account.The Foreign Secretary said that he had. not acquaintedMr Dalton with information on this subject which had reachedthe Government, but that he had exposed his point of viewto Mr Dalton freely.   Mr Dalton had been in agreement withthe point of view expressed.      The Foreign Secretary had said that he could give a definite assurance that if any occasion arose which seemed, to offer the prospect ofsecuring a genuine peace, we should consult the Frenchand also inform the leaders of the Opposition.Mr Dalton had said that Herr Hitler was putting itabout that we were making peace feelers to Germany.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR said that Mr Daltonhad rs-spoken to him on the same lines, and had said thatearlier on the Prime Minister had spoken as though therewas a distinction betfeeh Hitler and the German people,but that it now appeared that the Prime Minister no longerdrew this distinction.   Mr Dalton seemed to think thatthe German people could be divided.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS addedthat in conversation with Mr Dalton he had said that he did not distinguish between Field Marshal Goering andother Nazi leaders.

</content>
</cab>
