<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/56/0 images: 183-184</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
r    176FirstCivilianCasualtyresultingfrom german air-raid.Minute 1.western front.The Nether-lands .Minutes 2and 5...worked out. It was clear, however, that the admiralty and the Air Ministry were both working at the positionvery hard.Nothing else of particular importance in a veryquiet Meeting.P.S.   It should be noted that the raid on Scapacaused the first civilian casualty in thiscountry resulting from a German air raid.W.M. (40)  72nd CONCLUSIONS19 oo .40.A quiet Meeting.The decision to take a much more forthcomingline in regard to assistance to the Netherlands wasreached without any difficulty, notwithstanding thefact that the extent to which we could lend assistanceto Holland has not been fully worked out.   It seems tobe generally agreed, however, that the Dutch are in amuch better position to resist than they were last autumn, and that, provided they put up a decent res is t-ance, we ought to be able to come to their help.This was a very rambling discussion - what thediplomats call a tour d&apos; horizon, covering the iron oretraffic, the position in the Balkans, the Royal marine operation, the likelihood of an early Meeting of theSupreme War Council, and. one or two other matters in passing.    It seemed to be generally agreed that we arepassing through one of our periodical bad patches, fromthe point of view of prestige abroad. The French, inparticular, are jumpy and anxious to do something, andare liable to try and push us into something ratherfoolish.Minute 5.The naval situation.The First Lord gave more details of the Luleaproject.   As, &quot;however, we had had all this the day before,it was not worth while&apos;repeating it.The Prime Minister suggested that we might make some play with the fact that vjust at the time whenHitler and Mussolini were embracing on the Brenner,an Italian ship in ballast from Rotterdam to italy was being mined off the North Foreland.Nothing of particular interest.W.M. (40) 73 rd CONCLUSIONS. 20.3 .40.A nice, quiet, short Cabinet.Minute 1 * Everyone was delighted at the success of the attackon Sylt.   This was the first occasion on which our air Attack        bombers had really had things their own way.on Sylt.I When the discussion was proceeding as to thet likelihood of reprisals, the P.M. said that the weather was clouding over, and we must not assume that theGermans would have a clear night for an attack this evening.Wing-Commander Elliot afterwards said to me thatthisshowed the amateur&apos;s outlook, since any flying man-57- &quot;Sv-1&quot;-
knows that the weather changes every fifty miles on along flight.Minute 2.The naval situation,Minute 6.Prance.Health ofMr Savage,P.M. of MewZealand.once!Very little.   The admiralty in the shade forThe Poreign Secretary said that Sir RonaldCampbell had told Sir Alexander Cadogan that M. Legerhad been extremely depressed.   It seems clear that oneof the reasons why certain people in Prance have a down on M. Daladier is that he kept so many offices in hisown hand.   People have been saying lately that Prancehas been governed by a triumvirate - Daladier, Legerand Gamelin.   Perhaps it is cynical to say that ifthere is a new Government and a Poreign Secretary,M. Leger will not have quite so much power in thefuture as he has had in the past.    It is also clearthat a lot of M. Daladier&apos;s fellow politicians havebeen extremely irritated with him because they thoughtthat he stood aloof from them and did not take enoughpains to see them and talk to them.   This is said tobe the case particularly with M. Blum, whom M.Daladieris said not to have spoken to for ever so long.After the conclusion of Minute 7, the PrimeMinister asked the -Dominions Secretary if he had anynews of Mr Savage, the Prime Minister of New Zealand.Mr Eden said No, but he was afraid that Mr Savagewas dying.The Prime Minister then said that he well reraem-bered an occasion some years ago in the Cabinet Rooni,when he was presiding at some Imperia.1 Conference and aForeign Office Paper had been under discussion.   ThePrime Minister had asked various Dominion representa-tives for their views and they had all replied thatthey had nothing to sayt until he came to Mr Savage,who had said &quot;I have only one thing to say. that it sbunk from beginning to end&quot;, whereupon he (the PrimeMinister) had said &quot;Oh, that is all you have got tosay, is it?&quot;   Apparently, when Mr Savage had realised that he completely misunderstood one paragraph in the document, he changed his views.   We all had a goodlaugh about this.Minute, 9.Supply ofLabour forthe B.E.F..C.C.Meeting,W.M. (40)  74th CONCLUSIONS. 21.5.40.An uneventful and unexpectedly short Cabinet.We expected some fireworks about this item.   TheFirst Lord of the Admiralty had taken a very fierceline on this matter when it had been previouslydiscussed at the War Cabinet, and even a stronger linewhen the same matter had been discussed in the M.C.C.This meeting was, indeed, reported as having been thehottest meeting yet recorded of this Committee, whichis saying a good deal.   I was only present at the tailend of it, which struck me as pretty warm, but I was told the earlier proceedings had been at an even highertemperature.The Prime Minister, however, saw Lord Ghatfieldand also the Secretary of State for War before theMeeting, and suggestions were made which resulted in

</content>
</cab>
