<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/42/0 images: 76-87</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)secret.P.(50) Z09 COPY NO.    J 116TH SEPTEMBER, 1950CABINETEXPORT OF TWO MACHINE TOOLS TO POLANDMemorandum by the President of the Board of TradeTreaty obligations in considering the fate of the two vertical borers ordered byPoland, it is necessary to review the general question of our commitments to Eastern Europe.     Disregarding pre-war agreements the question of specific treaty obligations arises only in the case of the 1947 Agreementwith Russia (Cmd.  7297) and of the 1949 Five-Year Agreement with poland (Cmd.  7628).     It does not arise under the Five-Year Agreement of1949 with Czechoslovakia.     We have no trade agreements with theremaining satellites.2. A summary of the undertakings which we have given is containedin Annex A.3. There is still in the course of manufacture equipment orderedunder the Russian Agreement in respect of which we had given undertakingsabout ensuring delivery.     As to machine tools, some (particularly wood-working) may be included under the general descriptions in the Schedulesto the Agreement.     The Minister of Supply will doubtless be able to say how much equipment is in question, though there is a certain amount ofobscurity as to what was ordered under the Agreement and what was not.4. The position under the Polish Agreement is certainly clearer.The Minister of Supply will be able to indicate the extent to which there areorders outstanding.     We undertook not to prohibit the export of capital equipment ordered before 14th January, 1949-     Further, the polish authorities have received from us under the procedure outlined in the confidential -Letter, referred to in Annex A, lists of equipment agreed tohave been ordered before 14th January, 1949, as well as lists of equipmentordered thereafter, with an assurance that export would be permitted.Details of the two machine tools5. Both the Craven vertical borers were ordered after the signing of the Polish Agreement, but before the Export Control Order of February1949 came into force.     One of them which for the sake of clarity I will callMachineMA&quot; is specified in one of the lists sent to the Polish authorities.We were asked for and gave an assurance about this only.     There is nocorrespondence about the other.     Export licences have been issued toCraven Brothers in respect of both, in pursuance of the policy in force atthe time (and announced in February, 1949) that the controls would notapply to orders previously placed.

6. The Attorney-General&apos;s opinion is attached at Annex B.     He wishes to look at the minutes of the negotiations and is at present doing so.     TheUnited Kingdom negotiator   of the Agreement in my Department, however,feels confident that, where we have given these assurances about the grantof an export licence, we are pledged, so far as the Agreement is concerned,not to revoke any licence issued.     Such an assurance applies in the caseof Machine &quot;A&quot;.     In the case, however, of the other of the two Cravenmachines, (hereinafter celled Machine &quot;B&quot;) where no such assurance wassought or given, it would appear that we have no clear commitment, thoughthe Poles would almost certainly argue that revocation of the export licence was a breach of the Agreement.7. The Ministry of Supply wish to requisition for a Royal Ordnance-Factory Machine &quot;B&quot;, which, as stated, is not   the subject of any corres-pondence with the Poles.     This machine will not be completed until december, 1951.     Indeed, constructional work has not yet been startedthough the Poles have paid a 20% deposit.     It is known that the Poles arewatching with special interest the fate of these machines, and although itcould be argued that the requisition of one machine would not by itselfmean the frustration of the Trade Agreement with Poland, it is certainthat the line taken will be regarded as symbolic of our intention towardstrade with Eastern Europe.     It will be regarded as significant not only byPoland but by Russia and Czechoslovakia.General Considerations8. My colleagues are aware of the importance to our economic strength of the supplies of coarse grains from Russia and of timber fromRussia and Poland.     Although further supplies from Russia are not thesubject of any trade agreement a representative of the Ministry of Foodis at the moment in Moscow seeking to negotiate a further contract.     ought also to mention, although it is obviously of less importance, that theagreements with Poland and Czechoslovakia make provision for thesettlement of financial obligations including compensation for Britishinterests which have been nationalised.9. I do not suggest that we shall, or should, let the Poles haveMachine &quot;B&quot;.     Assuming that the Attorney-GeneraPs further study of the documents confirms that we are not committed to supply it, the requisition-ing of this machine would clearly fall within the scope of the Governmentdeclaration on the requisitioning of equipment required for our arms pro-gramme.     But it is a question whether we need say so now, when neither of the two machines in question can be ready for over twelve months.    Sofar Ministerial statements have included a reservation of the treaty position.Possibly an announcement that we intend to retain Machine &quot;B&quot; would notprovoke any retaliatory action since the Soviet bloc needs to acquiresterling, but it is arguable that we should not expose ourselves to therisk until we know that we can count on, and can pay for, supplies of coarse grains and timber from other sources.     Knowing as we do, thatthe Poles are watching with particular interest the fate of these twomachines, we might, long before we need take a decision, be embarking onthe first - and an irretrievable   - step towards an economic blockade of soviet Eastern Europe at a time when we have no assurance that theNorth Atlantic Treaty Powers are prepared to follow us in that policy.

Possible courses of action10. On the other hand (again assuming that the Attorney-Generalconfirms that Machine &quot;B&quot; is not covered by our Governmental commit-ments to Poland), if we feel that it is desirable to reassure publicopinion about its ultimate shipment - as I feel we should - I considerthat the best line in the debate would be to avoid all discussion of thesecomplicated and legal issues, and simply to state that, in fact, theGovernment understand that the machine in question will not be ready for over twelve months, but that when it is ready, &quot;it will not be going to poland&quot;.11. The question of Machine &quot;A&quot;, which will not be completed until1952, also arises.     This is the subject of a special assurance, unlikeMachine &quot;B&quot;, but on the other hand it is not wanted by the Minister ofSupply.     I feel that we might take one of two courses of action.     In thefirst place, even though the Minister may not at present require it, he might take steps to reserve it, on completion, for some other north atlantic Treaty Power.    Alternatively, he might administratively askCraven Brothers to begin work on another machine (of a type he will want) and put Machine &quot;A&quot; into cold storage, thus ensuring that it is not completed until, say, 1954, by which time the international position may beclearer.     He would, of course, have to indemnify Craven Brothers inrespect of any penalty clause for failing to deliver on time.RE C OMME ND A T IONS12. I would summarise my conclusions on this extremely complicatedproblem as follows:-If Machine &quot;B&quot;, which is wanted for our arms programme, is notthe subject of a firm commitment, it should not be allowed togo to Poland and we should requisition it.The next question is whether we need announce this now.   Thearguments on this are finely balanced, but I feel that, allthings considered, the House and the country should have an assurance now.     I would propose doing so on the lines of the concluding words of paragraph 19.If the Attorney-General advises that we are committed onMachine &quot;B&quot;, an order should be placed for a similar machine tool for Royal Ordnance factory use, and Craven Brothers,should be asked to put this ahead of Machine &quot;B&quot; in their production schedule.     Since work has not begun on Machine &quot;B&quot;this should not be difficult.Machine &quot;A&quot;, which is not at present wanted for our arms pro-gramme, is the subject of a commitment.     Nevertheless, i feel that it is better that the machine should not go to Poland.This   could be achieved either by requisitioning it for possible use by another North Atlantic Treaty Power, or by taking action, with the goodwill of Craven Brothers, to crowd it outof their production plan and hold up its completion.H.W.hard of Trade, S.W.1, -   .16TH SEPTEMBER, 1950.(a)(b)(c)(d)

0e3ANNEX ADETAILS OP UNITED KINGDOM treaty obligations WITH RUSSIA AND POLAND1947 Agreement with russia the United. Kingdom scheduled items of equipment suchas locomotives, trucks, winches, excavators, tugs and. dredgers,diesel electric generators, plywood and timber mill equipment,ore grinding mills, electrical gear, steam cranes and the like.      The United Kingdom undertook -&quot;to afford all possible aid for ensuring that the contracts......for the delivery of the equipment in question shall be signed in good time and carriedout by the prospective dates of delivery specified inthe schedules&quot; and &quot;to use any of the powers exerrcised in such matters in particular with regard to the giving of permission to the supplying firms to acquire the materials necessary for the orders&quot;.There is also a general provision under which theUnited Kingdom declared, their &quot;readiness to facilitate thesupply through the appropriate trade channels&quot; of wool,rubber, aluminium, cocoa beans, coffee and other good.s tobe agreed.The United. Kingdom also undertook to enter intoadditional negotiations concerning supplies of tin to theTT   o   q   pU. kj. t-J. xv..The compensatory Russian undertakings have been implemented by the supply during 1948 of 750,000 tons of coarse grains.      There is no terminal date to the undertakingsreferred to above and. the Foreign Office took the view whenlast consulted that strictly speaking these undertakings mustbe regarded as still binding.1949 Agreement with PolandThe Unit eel Kingdom undertook not to prohibit theexport to Poland, of capital equipment ordered on or before thedate of signature of the Agreement, i. e.  14th January, 1949.The United Kingdom also undertook to take whateversteps were open to them in the light of their general exportpolicy to facilitate the placing of Polish orders for capital equipment.The statement  of the President of the Board of Tradein February, 1949, about the new Export Control Order was astatement of United Kingdom general export policy and included the exception in favour- of prior commitments.In a Confidential Letter the United Kingdom under-took that, when the Poles were ready to place an order,  a firm statement would, be given in writing that an export licence for that product, if required, would be granted orrefused.The United Kingdom intended by the terms of this letter and the Polish Delegation so understood it that thiswould be a firm assurance that the item in question would beallowed to go to Poland.

ANNEX BDATED 1UTH SEPTEMBER FROMTHE ATTORNEY-GENERAL TO THE MINISTER OF SUPPLYX x x xI must point out, however, that questions of breach of contract as between the English manufacturers and their foreign purchasers might conceivably arise (although I thinkthese are improbable) and also that there may well be questionsof Treaty obligations.      I was consulted in regard to the latter question for the first time last night by the representativesof a number of Departments including your own,, and I am sorry to say that the Treaty position is at present extremely obscure.The facts in regard to this particular transactionbetween the Poles and Craven Brothers seem to be as follows.In January, 1949, a Trade Agreement was entered into betweenthe United Kingdom and Poland by Clause 9 of which the UnitedKingdom undertook to continue to take all steps it could tofacilitate the placing of orders consistent with the Govern-ment&apos;s general export policy.      At the same time, what v/ereknown as confidential letters v/ere exchanged, the effect ofwhich, so far as is now material, was that the government undertook,  if asked to do so before the placing of an order for particular and identified equipment, to enter into a firm commitment whether or not its export would be licensed.      Ihave little doubt that the intention of the Trade agreement was to enable the Poles before placing an order to have some kind of guarantee that the execution of the order and delivery of the equipment would not be frustrated by subsequent changes.in Government policy.      The confidential letter provided, asa step to facilitate the placing of the order within the termsof Clause 9 of the Agreement, machinery whereby the Governmentwould firmly undertake to licence the export if it thought fit.whether, however, Clause 9 has been so framed as to achieve in law what, I feel sure was its real intention, I cannot finallysay until I have seen the minutes of the negotiations leading up to the language used in the Agreement.At the time of the Trade Agreement, boring machineryof the type concerned was not in the list of prohibitedstrategic exports and it would, therefore, at least have beenthe Government^ duty to facilitate the placing of the order for the machinery.      whether this means that havingfacilitated the placing of the order the Government wasprecluded from subsequently refusing an export licencedepends, as I have said,  on whether the language of Clause 9really secures the intended object^ [o. matter on which i cannot yet express a final opinion/ and on the use made ofthe confidential letter machinery.On the 15th February the President of the Board ofTrade announced that the list of prohibited exports would beextended.      He did. not specify at that time what the additionswould be but he stated that  orders placed before the announce-ment of the specific additions was made would be allowed to go through.      On the 31st March the list of additional prohibiteditems was published but the Order prohibiting their export was expressed not to come into operation until the 8th April.There was, therefore, a week during which,  in the terms ofthe President&apos;s announcement, orders could still be placed in

the expectation that despite the prohibition coming intooperation thereafter they would he allowed to go through and export licences would be issued.      On the 6th April, thePoles placed with Graven Brothers the order for the machinerynow in question.As far as the records show, there was no application by the Poles for a firm commitment under the confidentialletter that the export of the machinery would eventually be licensed.      The Poles may well have thought that the matter was covered by the declaration made by the President of theBoard of Trade.      It is, however, very curious that no suchapplication is recorded especially as an order for anothermachine of identical type was placed by the Poles and wasdealt with under the terms of the confidential letter with theresult that in June, 1949, a firm commitment was entered intoby His Majesty&apos;s Government that its eventual export would be licensed.      It is difficult to think that the Poles wouldhave placed an order for the machine now in question (andpossibly have made payments on account of its purchase price)unless they had obtained a firm assurance that its ultimatedelivery would be permitted by the Government.      Indeed, it isdifficult to think that Craven Brothers would undertake theorder unless they had been assured that an export licence,would be granted.      In January, 1950, an export licence wasin fact granted for this particular machine.      It is unfor-unfortunate that no information appears to be available at presentshowing the circumstances in which the licence was granted.I am told it was a mistake but I confess I should like to knowmore about it.      Ho doubt an export licence once granted can,apart from other considerations, be subsequently cancelled ifthe export has not yet taken place but I cannot help thinking that the actual grant of the export licence does bring thismatter within the spirit of the confidential letter although not within its literal terms and it may be that the Polespaid money to Craven Brothers on the faith of it.As you will see, therefore, it is quite impossiblefor me to reach any confident conclusion about the Treatyposition without more information in regard to the making ofthe Trade Agreement and. as to the circumstances in which the contract was placed, with Craven Brothers and an export licence was eventually issued.      My present inclination is tothink that prohibition of the export might not constitute an actual breach of the terras of the Trade Agreement but that itwould most certainly be regarded by the Poles as a breach ofits intention and spirit and that the Poles having secured an export licence in January would be entitled to feel unjustlytreated.      It is, therefore, a question of policy havingregard to all the circumstances whether the machinery shouldbe requisitioned.      This you may think is one for the Cabinetto decide.


</content>
</cab>
