<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/42/0 images: 190-205</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY &apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP. (50) 221 COPY NO.    Cv g6TH OCTOBER, 1950CABINETNEW YORK MEETINGSDEVELOPMENTS IN FAR EASTERN policy memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs in CP. (50) 200 of 30th August, 1950, I outlined to mycolleagues the policy which I sought to pursue in regard to the Far Eastwhile I was in New York.   The proposals which I made were approvedby the Cabinet on 4th September (CM. (50) 55th Conclusions, Minute 4),and I now give some account of the way in which effect was given tothese proposals.United States Attitude2. Though the attitude of the United States Administrationtowards the problems of Chinese representation in the United Nations,Korea and Formosa was much as I had expected, it soon became clearthat the series of representations which had been naade in the precedingmonths had not been without their effect.    The landings at Inchon inAorea, which took place three days after my arrival in New York, and thebrilliant successes which followed, no doubt had their mellowingeffect upon American opinion, and thus rendered easier the developmentof a more moderate attitude on the part of the Administration towardsthe problems which were exercising our minds in the United Kingdom.Be that as it may, I am able to record that, as a result of our discussions in New York, definite progress has been made.Chinese representation in the United Nations3. As indicated in C P. (50) 195 of 1st September, 1950,this was the most difficult of the problems confronting me, and, as Iexpected, Mr. Ache son found himself unable to modify the attitudeof the United States Government because of the forthcoming elections.Nevertheless, he intimated in the course of the Tripartite Ministerialtalks that, in the view of the United States, others should feel free to vote as they thought fit.   He also indicated that the United StatesGovernment would! not oppose the setting up of a Committee to go intothe question of Chinese representation.4. In the event, the result at the opening session of theUnited Nations General Assembly was not unsatisfactory from our ownpoint of view.   India put forward a resolution to admit the representativesof Peking, which, when put to the vote, was defeated by 33 votes to 16with 10 abstentions.   The 16 favourable votes were those of the Powers

who have recognised the Peking Government, including the UnitedKingdom.   It is interesting that of the remaining forty-three Powers,ten should have abstained.    Two resolutions put forward by the soviet union on the same subject were defeated by larger majorities, but a canadian resolution for the setting up of a Committee by the Presidentof the General Assembly for the further examination of the question of chinese representation was carried by a large majority, including theUnited States.    This resolution was the direct outcome of a meeting of commonwealth representatives which I had held the same day, at whichI had explained the United States attitude arid our own intention to vote for the admission of representatives of the Peking Government.5. The result of the Assembly vote on China appears tohave caused acute disappointment and anger in Peking, where it appearsthat the Central People&apos;s Government had expected a more favourable response.   In India, however, reactions were on the whole favourable.6. There was no hostile reaction in the United States to theattitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government, and since the developments Ihave recorded, there has been a noticeable tendency, both in theAmerican press and amongst informed opinion, to take a more reasonable attitude towards China.7. Before leaving New York I gave an off-the-record talk to american columnists in which I explained our attitude towards theChinese question.    This explanation met with quite a favourable response.I think we can claim that our efforts over a period of months have been responsible for the change which has taken place, and I am not withouthope that after the Congressional elections in November, it may be possibleto secure a change-over in Chinese representation in the United Nations.i,orea8. There was no divergence of view between us and the UnitedStates Government on Korea.   The substance of the memorandum containedin CP. (50) 193 of 31st August, 1950, had been communicated to.theState Department who found themselves in general agreement with it.But the spectacular change in the military situation in Korea shortly after our arrival in New York made it clear that the need to find an acceptable solution of the Korean problem had become urgent, and I was concerned to discover that the United States Government had no clearidea as to what the next step should be.    It was in these circumstances that I instructed my advisers to prepare a draft resolution on Korea and todiscuss it with State Department officials who were in New York.   In viewof the fact that the United States are responsible for military operations in Korea and are bearing the principal burden, I considered itnecessary to take into account their views before consulting commonwealth and other friendly Governments.   After ascertaining that the UnitedStates Government were in general agreement with the purpose of ourresolution, and after a number of drafting amendments had been made,meetings were held with Commonwealth and other representatives with aview to obtaining a fairly wide sponsorship of our resolution.    India,in particular, was consulted at an early stage, but though the Indian dele-gation in New York were favourably disposed, Pandit Nehru, who had becomesomewhat unduly alarmed as a result of reports which he was receivingfrom his Ambassador in Peking, was unwilling that India should be oneof the sponsors of the resolution.   He had, on the other hand, no

constructive alternative to offer.   At a Commonwealth meeting the day before my departure, Pakistan agreed to become a sponsor, and in theevent the Korean resolution was introduced into the Political Committeeof the General Assembly under the sponsorship of the followingPowers, in addition to the United Kingdom:-  Australia, Brazil,Cuba, Netherlands, Norway, Pakistan, and the Philippines.   The text of the  .,orean resolution is at Annex.9. I should add in explanation that the main purpose of theresolution is to fulfil the primary objective of the Assembly resolution of 1948, namely the unification of Korea.    It was drafted so as to ignore the 38th Parallel which has become such an obsession in people&apos;s minds andwhich in fact has never had any international recognition as a boundary.It had become increasingly apparent that by constant mention of the38th Parallel, particularly in the United States but also throughout theworld, we were creating a barrier for ourselves which it might bedifficult to break down at a subsequent stage.    To Pandit Nehru the38th Parallel seemed to have assumed nightmare proportions, and it isby no means certain that this imaginary line Will not in the end defeat ouraims if we are not careful;    I accordingly made every effort while I was in new York to discourage reference to the 38th Parallel, and in myspeech to the plenary session of the General Assembly on 25th SeptemberI stressed the necessity to think not in terms of South Koreans and NorthKoreans, but only of Koreans who should unite to rebuild their country.10. Our Korean resolution is now under discussion in thePolitical Committee of the Assembly.    I am not without hope that itwill pave the way for a settlement of the Korean problem.   Mr. Achesonhas expressed his gratitude for the initiative taken by the United Kingdom,and there is no doubt that this initiative has been widely welcomed byfriendly Powers.    It is regrettable that India should not have supportedus; but on the other hand there can be no grounds for criticism by india of the action we have taken.Formosa--11. It was not possible to make the same progress over Formosaas in the case of Korea, for the reason that a Formosan item was under active consideration in the Security Council.   On the day of mydeparture from New York, however, the Security Council voted for the hearing of representatives of the Peking Government after 15th November,and it is hoped that before that date discussion will take place in theGeneral Assembly on the Formosan item which is on the agenda of that body.12. Though the United States Government are not unwilling that formosa should be discussed in the General Assembly, their concern overthe forthcoming Congressional elections has resulted in their beingopposed to any concessions in the Security Council, and to the hearing of Peking representatives there.   It has been intimated to me, however,that they would not be opposed to the presence of representatives of the peking Government when Formosa comes up for discussion in theAssembly.13. As in the case of Korea, I had instructed my advisers to prepare a draft resolution.   This resolution, which was in line withthe memorandum on Formosa contained in CP. (50) 194 of 31st August,1950, envisages the despatch of a United Nations Commission which would

visit Formosa and report to the Assembly after consulting withinterested parties and Governments.   The resolution has beenconsidered both by the United States and by Commonwealth Governmentswho have proposed certain amendments which are generally acceptable.Discussions are proceeding in New York, and it is hoped that before long the resolution can go forward to the Assembly under the names ofa number of sponsoring Powers, as in the case of Korea.    The UnitedStates Administration have so far not been impressed with the urgency of the problem, but now that the Korean conflict appears to be drawingto a close, they may expect to be called upon to explain their futureattitude, since their action to neutralise Formosa was taken as aresult of the aggression in Korea.   I am not without hope that theinitiative which we have taken over Formosa will, in due course, relaxinternational tension on this question, and enable a solution to beconsidered in a more dispassionate atmosphere.Japanese Peace Treaty14. Almost exactly a year after I previously discussed thesubject with Mr. Acheson in Washington, the United States announced their readiness to begin informal discussions with friendly Powersabout a Japanese Peace Treaty.   The initial approach was made byMr. John Foster Dulles, and in the case of the United Kingdom discussionstook place on the 21st September.   Mr. Dulles outlined United Statesideas about a treaty and stressed that they were only tentative andin the nature of suggestions.   Briefly, while confirming the cession of territories of which Japan has already been deprived, the maintenanceof United States and perhaps other forces in Japan by agreement is contemplated together with limited rearmament which would enableJapan to assume at any rate partial responsibility for her ownprotection.    Complete sovereignty would be restored to Japan and she would be permitted entry into the United Nations.15. Mr. Dulles indicated that the United States expected thepreliminary informal exchanges with friendly Powers to last twoor three months, and that the negotiating stage would not be reacheduntil early in 1951.   As to the conclusion of a treaty, Mr. Dulles did not contemplate ratification by the United States until the Congress of 1952.16. The United States proposals are at present under examination by Departments and reference to Ministers is not contemplated at thisstage.Conclusions17. The most significant development in the conversations in new York was the increasing tendency on the part of the United States to turn to the United Kingdom on Far Eastern questions.   On Korea andFormosa they seem inclined to follow the course outlined in our memoranda on these subjects.    Though they are not yet ready to align their policy with that of the United Kingdom as regards China, they have been anxious thatthat there should be no breach with us on this issue, and are ready to listen to our views.   It is not to be expected that United States policy will undergo any dramatic change in the near future, but if one looksback over the past three months, it becomes clear that the UnitedKingdom has in fact exercised a steadying influence upon the United States,

and that, as a result, there is a fairer prospect that United states policy in the Far East will develop on lines more in harmony withour common aims than has hitherto been the case.   I am satisfied thatour own influence, if it is to be maintained, must continue to beunobtrusive.    The fact that we have a.voided criticism of the UnitedStates in public has enabled us the more readily to express our views in private.   It was evident in New York that these views had prevailedto a very considerable extent, and it is clear therefore that the tactics which we have been pursuing with the United States in regardto Far Eastern questions since the Korean conflict began have been theright tactics.E. B.Foreign Office, S. W. 1. ,6TH OCTOBER, 1950.

ANNEXUNITED NATIONS RESOLUTION ON KOREAThe General Assembly having regard to its resolutions .of 14th November 1947 of 12th December 1948 and of 21st October 1949;Having received and considered the report of the united nations Commission on Korea;Mindful of the fact that the objectives set forth in theresolutions referred to have not been fully accomplished and inparticular that the unification of Korea has not yet been achieved andthat an attempt has been made by an armed attack from North Korea toextinguish by force the Government of the Republic of Korea;Recalling its declaration of 12th December 1948 that therehas been established a lawful Government (the Government of theRepublic of Korea) having effective control and jurisdiction over that part of Korea where the United Nations temporary commission of korea was able to observe and consult and in which the great majorityof the people of Korea reside;That this Government is based on elections which were a valid expression of free will of the electorate of that part of Korea andwhich were observed by the temporary Commission;And that this is the only such Government in Korea;Having in mind that United Nations armed forces are atpresent operating in Korea in accordance with the recommendations ofthe Security Council of 27th June 1950, subsequent to its resolution of25th June 1950, that members of the United Nations furnish such assistanceto the Republic of Korea as may be necessary to repel the armed attack and to restore international peace and security in the area;Recalling that the essential objective of the resolutions of the General Assembly referred to was the establishment of a unifiedindependent and democratic Government of Korea;Recommends(a) That all appropriate steps be taken to ensure conditionsof stability throughout Korea.(b) That all constituent acts be taken including the holding of elections under the auspices of the United Nations forthe establishment of a unified independent and democratic government in the sovereign state of Korea.(c) That all sections and representative bodies of the populationof Korea South and North be invited to co-operate withthe organs of the United Nations in the restoration ofpeace, in the holding of elections and in the establishmentof a unified Government.

(d) That United Nations forces should not remain in anypart of Korea otherwise than so far as necessary for achieving the objectives specified at (a) and (b) above.(e) That all necessary measures be taken to accomplish theeconomic rehabilitation of Korea;Resolves that(a) A commission consisting of..............known as theUnited Nations Commission for the unification and rehabilitation of acres be established to(i)  Assume the functions hitherto exercised bythe present United Nations Commission in Korea.(ii)   Represent the United Nations in bringing aboutthe establishment of a unified independent anddemocratic Government of all Korea.(iii)   Exercise such responsibilities in connexion withrelief and rehabilitation in Korea as may bedetermined by the General A.ssembly after receiving the recommendations of the Economicand Social Council.    The United nations commission for the unification and rehabilitation of Korea should proceed to Korea and begin tocarry out its functions as soon as possible.(iv)   Report to the next regular session of theGeneral Assembly and to any prior special session which might be called to consider thesubject matter of the present resolution, andshall render such interim reports as it may deem appropriate to the Secretary-General for transmission to Members.(b) Pending the arrival in Korea of the United Nations commission for the unification and rehabilitation of Korea governments represented on the Commission should form an interimcommittee composed of their permanent representatives at the seat of the United Nations to consult with and advise the United Nations unified command in the light of theabove recommendations;The interim committee should begin to function immediately upon the approval of this resolution by the General Assembly;The General Assembly furthermore mindful of the fact thatat the end of the present hostilities the task of rehabilitating the Koreaneconomy will be of great magnitudeRequests the Economic and Social Council in consultation withthe specialised agencies to develop plans for relief and rehabilitation onthe termination of hostilities and to report to the General Assembly within three weeks of adoption of this Resolution by the General Assembly;

Also recommends the Economic and Social Council to expedite the study of long-term measures to promote the economic development and social progress of Korea and meanwhile to draw attention of the authorities which decide requests for technical assistance to the urgent and special necessity of affording such assistance to Korea;Expresses appreciation to the members of the United nations commission on Korea for the services that they have rendered inthe accomplishment of their important and difficult tasks;Requests that the Secretary General shall provide theCommission with adequate staff and facilities including technical advisers as required;   and authorises the Secretary General to pay theexpenses and per diem of a representative and alternate from eachof the states members of the Commission.


</content>
</cab>
