<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/42/0 images: 232-235</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS   DOCUMENT IS THE   PROPERTY OF HIS   BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS  GOVERNMENT-Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1950SECRET Copy No. 3 cp. (50) 225\2th October, 1950CABINETREPORT OF THE PRIVY COUNCIL ON THE CASE OFMr. J. G. MacMANAWAYMemorandum by the Lord President of the Council and the Attorney-GeneralThe Judicial Committee have now reported their answers to the questionssubmitted to them in regard to the eligibility of Mr. J. G. MacManaway, electedMember for West Belfast, to sit as a Member of the House of Commons, he beingordained a clergyman of the Irish Church. An Order in Council has been madedirecting that the Secretary of State for the Home Department should communicate this report to the Commons, and we assume that he will do this orally when parliament resumes and at the same time lay a copy of the opinion.2. The report, which will not be made public until so communicated to the commons, is to the effect that Mr. MacManaway, like all clergy ordained by theform of laying on of hands into whatever Episcopal Church, is disqualified. Inthese circumstances our colleagues will wish to consider what further action shouldbe taken.3. The report of the Judicial Committee is not binding upon the House ofCommons: it is an advisory opinion only and the House remains the sole master of its own Constitution. Moreover, amongst lawyers in the House who expressed their opinions only Mr. Geoffrey Bing reached the conclusion now found to becorrect by the Judicial Committee. Sir David Maxwell Fyfe considered that theHouse of Commons (Clergy Disqualification) Act, 1801, only applied to clergyordained in and according to the forms of the established Church of England.Mr. Conolly Gage took the same view, and it appears from the report of the SelectCommittee that it was shared by two of the King&apos;s Counsel on that Committee.Moreover, whilst the present Law Officers expressly dissented from the reasoningadvanced by Sir David Fyfe, the Attorney-General advised (largely on historicalgrounds, some of which could not be advanced before the Privy Council) that whilst&quot; the arguments were nicely balanced&quot; his own &quot;very tentative opinion &quot; wasin favour of eligibility.4. We do not, however, think that anyone (even Mr. Churchill, who statedthat he thought the law clearly entitled Mr. MacManaway to sit!) will wish to challenge the conclusions of the Judicial Committee. In these circumstances the courses open are:  (i) to alter the law in regard to clerical disqualification and, in so doing, retro-respecively to validate Mr. MacManaway&apos;s election;(ii) to declare Mr. MacManaway&apos;s seat vacant, whether or not indemnifyingMr. MacManaway in respect of the penalties incurred by him whilstsitting and voting, although disqualified.Of these alternatives we recommend the latter.5. It is true that the Select Committee did recommend that the matter shouldbe dealt with by legislation declaring that ordained clergy outside the establishedChurch were qualified to sit and that some newspapers, notably The Times, sup-ported this view.   But an alteration of the law in regard to clerical disabilities39468&apos;
presents many problems on which controversy would not follow normal Party lines.Should the disqualification be removed from all clergymen in Episcopal but non-established Churches-e.g., the Greek Orthodox and the Roman Catholic Churches?Or should it be removed only in the case of those who divested themselves of their orders?. In the latter case, although the United Kingdom Parliament has properlyprovided machinery by which clergy of the English Church as by law established candivest themselves of their orders, would it be-,proper.lor.our Parliament to provideby law similar machinery for other and perhaps foreign Churches whose ownecclesiastical law does not recognise the possibility of orders once given beingrelinquished? Is it desirable that those in holy orders of whatever Church shouldengage in politics? These are controversial questions, and there are others. It istrue that under the existing law clergy of the non-conformist Churches, because notordained, are eligible. And there are other anomalies. But the issues seem socomplicated and controversial that no legislation altering the present law shouldbe attempted without prior enquiry by a Royal Commission. Until that has beendone we should leave the law as it is.6. In our opinion, therefore, we should advise the House to declare the seatvacant and issue a writ for a new election. It has indeed been suggested that the candidate next on the Poll at the general election (Mr. Beatty, over whomMr. MacManaway had a majority of about 3,000 in a large Poll) should be held tohave been elected. This on the basis that the electors who voted for mr. MacManaway must have known that he was an ordained clergyman and thusthrew their votes away. This was so held in the case of Beresford-Hope v. LadySandhurst (1889 23 Q.B.D. 79) where a woman, then ineligible, was at the top ofthe Poll in an election for the L.C.C. But so to hold in the present case would be quite contrary to the modern practice of Parliament and we can find no justification for it.7. It remains to consider whether the Government should introduce legislationindemnifying Mr. MacManaway from the penalties he has incurred (which includethe disability to act as a cleric) and if so to what extent. We think that thisshould certainly be done in respect of any occasion on which he sat and voted priorto 21st July, 1950, when the matter was submitted to the Judicial Committee. Upto that time Mr. MacManaway had acted in good faith. He had been for manyyears and still is a member of the Northern Ireland Parliament to which the samedisqualification applies, without challenge; before standing for the imperial parliament he obtained a firm opinion from Sir David Maxwell Fyfe that he wasqualified and he was no doubt entitled to think that this was so.8. Whether he should be indemnified in respect of the period subsequent tothe matter becoming sub judice by its submission to the Privy Council is another matter. He did sit and vote in the debate on the nationalisation of steel inSeptember. By this time a common informer&apos;s action had been started against him and discreet steps were taken to ensure that he was made aware that theJudicial Committee might well decide against him. His action in seeking to influence the decision of Parliament by voting in a critical division reflects no credit upon him and we feel that something should be said in the House by way of deprecationof it. There was certainly no pledge, express or implied, that he would be indemnity-nified during this period. Indeed, the implication of the Attorney-GeneraFs speech on the motion to refer to the Privy Council is rather the contrary. (See Cols.2469-2470 Official Report 29.6.1950).*   Moreover, before the Select Committee* In the debate on 29th June, 1950,1 used the following words when asked if the Governmentwould introduce indemnifying legislation were the Judicial Committee&apos;s report to the effect thatMr. MacManaway was disqualified: &quot; I cannot go further than to say that we, having urged that the matter should go to the privy Council, if the Council expressed an opinion to the effect which, I gather, is beingspeculatively put forward at the moment that he was disqualified, then I think there would bean obligation on the Government to indemnify the hon. Member for the past disqualificationand bring in legislation to that effect, but I would not be in a position to say what legislation, ifany, we could bring in to rectify the law in that case.&quot;I intended to convey that the indemnifying legislation would only cover the period up to the submission of Mr. MacManaway&apos;s case to the Judicial Committee, but I realise that it might be argued that my words meant that this legislation would cover the period up to the Judicial Committee&apos;sreport.H. M.
the Attorney-General had expressly warned Mr. MacManaway that the law was so uncertain that he should on no account act on the Attorney-General&apos;s tentativeopinion that it was in his favour. None the less we feel that the magnanimouscourse would be to introduce a Bill giving him a complete indemnity for allpenalties he has incurred both in the Imperial and in the Northern ireland parliament.9.   Accordingly we recommend that:(i) The Commons should be advised to declare West Belfast vacant and thata writ be issued for a new election;(ii) a Bill of Indemnity be introduced;(iii) the Lord President should make a statement to the Commons of theGovernments intentions.H. M.H. W. S.12th October, 1950


</content>
</cab>
