<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/42/0 images: 350-351</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT IS THE   PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1950CONFIDENTIAL Copy No.^2CP. (50) 24226th October, 1950CABINETHOUSE OF COMMONS: PRIVATE MEMBERS&apos; TIMEMemorandum by the Lord President of the CouncilWe have to take a decision on Private Members&apos; time in regard to the next session because, as my colleagues are aware, the Prime Minister must refer to itin his speech on the first day of the new Session.2. Under the^present Standing Order and on the basis of our plans for the session, Private Members would have the following facilities:  (i) Nine Wednesdays for Motions seven before Christmas and two after (twoMotions to be taken on each Wednesday one until 7 p.m. and theother until 10 p.m.) ;(ii) Fifteen Fridays for Bills seven before Christmas and eight after (the last four Fridays being allocated to the most advanced Bills).3. This question was considered in 1945-46 by the Select Committee on procedure appointed by the House, and they recommended that the first twentyFridays after the Debate on the Address should be Private Members&apos; days, Motionsand Bills being taken on alternate Fridays. The first six Bill Fridays would be for second Readings and the last four for Report stages and Third Readings, and, ofcourse, ten Fridays were for Private Members&apos; Motions.4. In the present political situation I do not see how we can avoid making an allocation for Private Members&apos; time in the next Session, though I regret it.The Opposition and some of our own supporters made it clear when we took partof Private Members&apos; time at the beginning of this Session that for the future any similar infringement of their rights would be resisted. In these circumstances theonly question to my mind is what form the arrangements should take. When thismatter was discussed at a recent meeting of the Parliamentary Labour Party therewas some talk of dividing Private Members&apos; days between Wednesdays and Fridays.This was no doubt suggested for the convenience of Members, but the Chief Whipand I did not favbur it because of the distinct advantage to the Government of having four consecutive days in the week available for Government business.In all the circumstances I would recommend my colleagues to agree that weshould persuade the House to accept the recommendation of the Select Committeefor the Session of 1950-51.5. There is also the question whether Private Members should be allowed topresent Bills in the ordinary way and also under the &quot; ten minutes rule &quot; procedure.The latter is certainly open to abuse, and I would propose simultaneously with theannouncement about Private Members&apos; time to seek (if I can) not to revive the&quot; ten minutes rule &quot; procedure. If this is agreed, it rather looks to me that weshall have to allow Private Members to present Bills in the ordinary way after the ballot has been held.H. M.Privy Council Office, S.WA,26th October, 1950.39538


</content>
</cab>
