<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/42/0 images: 382-393</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1950The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of ..................................TOP SECRET copy No.[D.O. (50) 9123rd October, 1950]cabinet defence CommitteeTHE FINANCE OF defence memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and theChancellor of the ExchequerOur discussions with the Americans on the finance of rearmament have now reached the point where we can take stock of the position and consider what our future course should be. The decisions which we, in co-operation with the americans and our other allies of the North Atlantic Treaty, must take in the nextfew months will be of far-reaching significance for the future not only in respectof our defence and economic policy but also for our foreign policy. This memo-randum, after summarising the course of the recent discussions, sets out the considerations which we must take into account in making up our minds.I. Historical background. By the middle of this year the British economy was doing better than could have been hoped at the beginning of the European Recovery Programmethree years earlier. The internal position was healthy; we had full employmentbut suffered from neither inflation nor deflation. There was a steady and rapid increase in production and productivity. The external position was developingsatisfactorily. The sterling area as a whole was earning a dollar surplus and thegold reserves were increasing rapidly.&quot; The United Kingdom was also in surplus onits current balance of payments, so much so that in May, June and July taken together there was no increase in the sterling balances and at the same time alarge increase in our reserves of gold and dollars. In short, we were, provided the current trends continued, within sight of the objective which we had setourselves at the beginning of the European Recovery Programme independence of external assistance and a level of reserves at least equal to that which obtainedwhen the European Recovery Programme started.3. The aggression in Korea and the reaction to it of the United StatesGovernment was, in the short run, favourable to the continuance of this improve-ment for the sterling area as a whole, since it assured the maintenance for a further period of a high level of United States business activity. At the same time, however,from the longer-term point of view, the need for a substantial measure ofrearmament on the part of all N.A.T.O. countries, accentuated as it has been bythe worsening of the terms of trade for the United Kingdom, were new andunfavourable factors which radically altered the picture and threatened to impose a set-back to our recovery as well as that of the other free nations of the western world.
4. This was the situation when towards the end of July the United StatesGovernment approached us and other N.A.T.O. countries with a request for&apos; information concerning the nature and extent of the increased effort both asregards increases in forces and increases in military production which His Majesty&apos;sGovernment and other North Atlantic Treaty Powers were willing and able toundertake as well&quot; as information concerning additional military production programmes which could be initiated with United States assistance.&quot; The UnitedStates memorandum added: &quot; The conviction of the United States Government that the achievement of security, economic well-being and cohesiveness in the Western World shouldbe our continuing objective, remains unchanged. It is recognised thatcontinuance of economic recovery in the near future, although possibly at aless rapid rate than heretofore, will be essential not only to the attainment ofthat broad objective but to the attainment of the immediate objective of greatermilitary strength. While the United States recognises that rearmament will necessitate economic sacrifices, including a reduced level of consumption, andretard the pace of recovery, it does not believe that the means which will berequired to achieve increased military strength are inconsistent with the broader objective mentioned, but will, on the contrary, be essential to the eventual achievement of that objective.&quot;5. The United States Government requested an immediate reply in a form which could be published, and our reply, which was delivered within ten days ofthe receipt of the United States request, stated that we were prepared to undertakeover the next three years a programme, which it is now estimated would amountto  3,600 million, i.e., an average of  1,200 million a year, subject to the followingqualification:  &quot; His Majesty&apos;s Government does not, therefore, feel able to undertakeconsistently with the objectives indicated by the United States Government sofull a diversion of productive resources to defence purposes unless the UnitedStates can offer financial assistance.&quot;Shortly afterwards a top secret memorandum was sent to the United StatesGovernment intimating that the assistance required was calculated at  550 million over the period.6. This exchange of memoranda was followed by discussions at the official level with the object of seeing whether the Americans would in fact be prepared togive assistance on the scale proposed. These discussions made no progress and theForeign Secretary was authorised to take the matter up with the United states secretary of State in the discussions between the British, American and french foreign Ministers in September at New York. As a result of this and in view of the urgent need to get the increased production programmes started, it was agreed to divide the problem into two parts:(a) American and British officials should discuss what immediate assistance theUnited States Government could give us on an interim basis towards the.gh-priority programme, totalling  200 million, which we had agreedto put in hand at once.(b) American, British and French officials should discuss the longer-rangeproblems of the implementation of the Medium-Term Defence Plan.7. It is important to distinguish between the United Kingdom programme of 3,600 million and the United Kingdom share of the Medium-Term Defence plan the former represents our total defence effort over the next three years which wehave offered to undertake with American assistance. It is based on the cost of forces and their equipment, and the figures are based on estimates of the most thatour productive and other resources are capable of providing without mobilisationmeasures, such as restoring the direction of labour and the requisitioning of factories.The Medium-Term Defence Plan is a statement of the military requirements in menand material for the defence of the North Atlantic area, i.e., it is prepared from the standpoint of what the military authorities consider to be needed, not from the standpoint of what can be provided. The cost of the Medium-Term Defence plan is now being studied by the N.A.T.O. organisation and definite results are not yet available. But the stage has been reached in this study at which the countries arc
reporting the expenditure required to raise and equip their respective shares of theforces making up the Medium-Term Plan. The report for the United Kingdomshows that our total defence budget over the next three years, if it included theUnited Kingdom share of the Medium-Term Plan, would be of the order of  6,000million. Any figures given at the present stage are, of course, provisional, and thereare many uncertainties in the calculation. But it is clear at the outset that theUnited Kingdom defence budget over the next three years, on the basis of the medium-Term Defence Plan, would far exceed  3,600 million.8. The discussions on interim aid have now reached the stage at which theUnited States Government, in an aide-memoire dated 3rd October, 1950 (of whicha copy is reproduced as Annex I to this memorandum), made a definite offer toprovide the dollar components of the  200 million programme (valued at $84million) together with $28 million made available by the purchase by the UnitedStates Government of equipment produced in the United Kingdom. It was made clear that this offer, which was considerably less than we had hoped, was the best that the Americans could do in the light of our position and their existing legislative authority. It was also made clear that the United Kingdom equipment to be purchased by the United States Government would pass into their complete controland would not necessarily be transferred back to us.9. Meanwhile, the tripartite talks on the long-term problem had resulted inthe production of what has come to be known as the Nitze Memorandum, a copy ofwhich is reproduced as Annex II to this memorandum. (It is named after the authorof the first draft, who is the Director of Policy and Planning in the State Depart-ment; but the revised form appended to this paper represents a proposal madeofficially by the United States Administration.) This document sets out a procedure for a multilateral approach to the fair division between the North Atlantic countries of the burden of implementing the Medium-Term Defence Plan, and represents thepresent view of the United States Government under which the long-term problemof the finance of defence is to be solved by allocating the measures required to carryout the Medium-Term Plan between the countries and distributing the cost.II. Political asid Economic Cosisideratiojas10. Before the implications of the Nitze Memorandum are examined, it willbe convenient to set out the main political and economic considerations which mustbe taken into account in determining our attitude towards it. The first point isthat the objective of our whole endeavour is not to prepare for war but to seek toensure peace. If we regarded war as inevitable, we should now be putting thecountry on a war footing and subordinating everything else to war preparation.The stage of recovery now reached would be overwhelmed in the general catastropheand since we should, from the moment war broke out, be utterly dependent on an immense volume of direct American aid, considerable dependence in the preliminarystages would not make much difference. This, however, is not the position. Webelieve that, if we and our Allies prepare sufficiently quickly and thoroughly and are.well organised and strong, war can be averted. It is this that leads the Americansas well as ourselves to insist that the continuance of our economic recovery isessential; it is this that makes them ready to offer us assistance so that recoveryshould not be dislocated and halted by the heavy impact of rearmament.11. But the very state of affairs which makes the Americans ready to offer usassistance makes it desirable that the assistance should not take the form of directaid on the lines of that given under the European Recovery Programme. Theexperience of the middle months of this year already referred to in paragraph above showed what a difference to our position in the world was made by our rapid progress towards the attainment of economic independence. As the strength of sterling steadily increased so did the power and influence of Britain. We no longerhad to rest content with the knowledge that we were a Great Power, but we were becoming able, for the first time since the war, to sustain our world-wide commit-ments. The visible growth of economic independence gave us weight in the Counselsof the nations. If by accepting direct aid for military purposes we were to forfeitour economic independence we should lose the position we were just regaining asthe principal partner in world affairs of the United States. We shall be back again in the European queue and our loss of power and influence will reflect itself inmany ways/ It will be more difficult to hold the Commonwealth together.  Our
position in Europe will be weakened. In the many negotiations and arrangements to be made in the months ahead we shall find that we are treated not as partners,though of unequal power, but as just another necessitous European nation. Ingeneral, the preservation of good relations between ourselves and the United states would become increasingly difficult.12. An up-to-date assessment of the relevant economic considerations points in the same direction as the political arguments outlined above. Since the war wehave lived under conditions of dollar shortage, with the reserves of the sterling area at or below danger point and with the ever-present need for dollar grants and loans to enable us to secure our essential dollar imports and to keep the sterling areatogether as a going concern. There has been no particular difficulty in proving our need, and since it was for dollars, it was natural that aid should be given by theUnited States itself in This form. That is not the position to-day or for the imme-diate future. The sterling area is balancing and is likely to continue to balance itsdollar accounts. The reserves, though still much too low for any striking changein our fundamental financial and economic policy, are certainly well above dangerpoint and are still rising. We have indeed been told by United States representatives that it is their intention that we shall receive no more E.R.P. assistance after theallotment of $175 million for the current six month?. We cannot ignore this when we are considering the likelihood of our succeeding in any bilateral negotiations forfurther dollar assistance to us as the result of rearmament.13. As has been said in paragraph 2, the British economy has shown a greatdeal of strength in the early part of this year, and the continued increase in produc-tion gave reasonable grounds for hoping for some easing of the burdens we hadbeen carrying. As a result of the continued rise in the cost of our imports sinceKorea, however, the cost of living will certainly increase over the next six months.This increase is taking place as a consequence of general rearmament rather than of our own, but it is against this background that our new commitments must beconsidered. The addition of very substantial amounts to our defence expenditure will mean a direct burden on the Budget, and will involve either additional taxationor the reappearance of some inflation with all the adverse economic consequencesthat this entails. In the context of an inevitable rise in the cost of living, the politicaland social difficulties of increased taxation or renewed inflation are obvious.14. Rearmament will compete with exports for our production, and at thesame time the rapidly rising price of imported raw materials is causing a further deterioration in the terms of trade. It will therefore become increasingly difficultto avoid a deficit on the United Kingdom overall balance of payments, which will show itself in a rise in our overseas sterling liabilities. It will be still more difficultto attain that surplus which our external commitments require if we are not to runinto debt.15. These are serious issues. But they are issues which are facing all theNorth Atlantic Treaty countries, including in some respects the United States itself.They make inappropriate in the future the presentation of a special United Kingdomcase calculated to convince the United States in bilateral discussion of our need fordollars. The arguments which we would now wish to put forward turn on a compari-son between the worsening of our whole economic position as a result of rearmamentboth here and elsewhere, with the changes which will be taking place in the othercountries concerned and particularly in the United States. Our arguments are entirely appropriate to a multilateral examination of what constitutes an equitable distribution of the new burdens. But they are not suitable to an examination ofthe position of the United Kingdom in isolation, and we would be unable in suchan examination to provide adequate statistical justification for a direct plea fordollar assistance. Nor could we easily reconcile such a presentation with our basicdetermination to stand on our own feet at the earliest possible moment.III.  The Division of the Burden16.   The procedure envisaged in the Nitze Memorandum is (a) On the basis of the Medium-Term Defence Programme, there will be drawnup a statement of the military requirements in men and material.(b) The requirements of material will be translated into broad production pro-grammes for each of the N.A.T.O. countries, each being allotted thework it can best carry out from the technical point of view.
(c) The Governments will work out the cost to them of the tasks allotted tothem.(d) An assessment will hen be made of the economic burden on each country-the assessment to take account of the total proposed defence expen-diture of each country, including the expenditure required to carry out its share of the Medium-Term Defence Plan.(e) On the basis of th:s economic analysis, decisions will be taken on the equitable distribution of the economic burden.The method for reaching such decisions has still to be negotiated. But, in ourview, there is one point, of first importance, for which the scheme must provide. Itmust not be confined to the fair distribution of a given total burden: it must alsoensure that the total is not of such an order of magnitude that the division, howevermade, results in allocations which are intolerable for any of the countries concerned.In other words, the plan must be so framed that the assessment of the economicburden leads, not only to proposals for distributing the burden, but also to a reviewof the scale of the defence plan itself in the light of its economic consequences.17. Given a tolerable total, the fair share for each country may be establishedby comparing the cost of each country&apos;s allotted task with a figure which is agreedto be the equitable share of the common burden for that country, having regard toits economic position in relation to that of the others. The principles by whichhis equitable share is to be determined and the precise factors to be taken intoconsideration are not yet settled, but, roughly speaking, it may be assumed that thericher countries will be required to bear a proportionately greater share of theburden than the poorer and that the result will be to show that if the tasks allottedunder paragraph (b) above were carried out, some countries would be bearing morethan their share and others less.18. The next stage would be a series of adjustments to secure that the objectof the plan as a whole is achieved while, at the same time, each participating countrybears its fair share of the burden and no more. These adjustments may take theform of some re-allotment of the tasks under the plan, or some revision of the scale of the plan itself, if required to ensure that the allotted tasks are tolerable. Inaddition, however, there will inevitably have to be arrangements whereby thosecountries whose effort in physical terms proves to be less than their fair share make up the balance financially, the money being made available to those countries whoseeffort in physical terms is greater than their fair share.19. It is clearly of the utmost importance that the implications of this procedure should be clearly accepted by all concerned. From our point of view,they may be expressed as follows:  (a) Under the North Atlantic Treaty twelve countries are freely allied together to pursue a common end, each contributing to that end according to itsability.(b) Under the procedure proposed in the Nitze memorandum the twelvecountries sitting together will reach decisions on the magnitude of the tasks which each can reasonably undertake and on the fair and equitablecontribution which each shall make to ensure that means are availablefor attaining the common end.On the basis of these two concepts, any contribution made by any country, whetherexpressed in physical terms or financial, is a contribution to the attainment of thecommon end &quot;and this applies whether the contribution takes the form of supplyingman-power, equipment or finance. The plan itself, with its allotment of productiontasks to the countries technically best fitted to carry them out, envisages that someof the equipment produced in one country will be used in another; under the Nitzeproposals, when the economic position of the various countries is brought intothe account some countries will make financial transfers to others. In neither ofthese cases should the transfers be regarded as &quot; assistance &quot; or &quot; aid &quot;; they are merely the practical expression of the common agreement that will have beenreached as to the best and most equitable way of achieving the common end.20. One consequence of this is that each country will have the fullest rights to assure itself, through N.A.T.O., that any other country is carrying out its obli-gations.   Indeed, without this, there could be no sound basis for continuing the
alliance. Moreover, it must be recognised that the United States, as in all probability the largest contributor, will have a particularly large interest in the procedures designed to ensure the due carrying out of obligations, but the relation-ship would be essentially different from that prevailing for Marshall Aid, when theUnited States alone, as the giver of aid, had rights of that character recognisedunder its bilateral agreements with the individual O.E.E.C. countries.IV. Conclusions21. The conclusions which we draw from the considerations set out above-may be stated first with reference to the long-term problem and secondly in relationto the immediate situation.22. The long-term problem. If it is accepted that it is neither desirable norpracticable that we should receive direct assistance from the United States, then we are irresistibly drawn to the proposals of the Nitze memorandum.23. It is important that we should not decide to embark on the Nitze planwithout realising that it carries financial and economic risks as well as advantages.On the one hand, it is clear that the Nitze proposals offer virtually the only hopethat the economic burden we shall have to bear will be tolerable in itself and equitable-able in relation to that borne by the others. On the other hand, the starting-pointof the Nitze memorandum is the adoption of the Medium-Term Defence Plan asthe basis for calculating the total burden to be distributed. We know that our shareof the Medium-Term Plan involves a military effort for the United Kingdom far inexcess of our  3,600 million programme and one which would not be practicablewithout departing from the basis on which our  3,600 million programme was based,that is (as stated in paragraph 5 of the published memorandum of 3rd August, 1950:&quot; It is the largest programme practicable within the period envisaged and withoutrestoring the direction of labour, the requisitioning of factories or embarking on theslow process of building and equipping new industrial capacity which could nothave rapid results.&quot;) It is therefore essential for us to establish that any plan formultilateral distribution provides that the shares allotted to each country are notonly equitable but also tolerable, and that this may involve a revision of total defence requirements as well as their distribution.24. We therefore conclude that it is right to proceed with the Nitze plan, pro-vided always that the concepts which we see as the basis of the Nitze memorandum are understood and accepted by all concerned and, in particular, by the UnitedStates Government itself. The tasks of securing the acceptance of these conceptsand of carrying out the procedures will be of great technical complexity. We shallhave to face United States insistence that they should have some close supervisionboth for Congressional reasons and to ensure that any transfers of dollars andequipment that they make are used for the purposes contemplated by N.A.T.O. Weshall probably find other European countries more ready to accept this in returnfor the assistance which they feel they so desperately need. Nevertheless we feelthat these difficulties must be faced and overcome if we are to secure not only thedefence of the West but also the maintenance of our economic independence andpolitical influence.25. At this point it may be convenient to refer briefly to the outcome of therecent bilateral negotiations conducted between the Americans and the French.The French problem was particularly urgent because they must prepare theirbudget for their new financial year which starts on 1st January next. The assistancethey have obtained, as published by the French on 18th October, may be summarisedas follows:  $ million   million(1) Military equipment............     1,600-2,200 786(2) Equipment for Indo-China        ......       275 98(3) Dollar aid, described by the French as a first instalment of United States credits to go against French Budget deficit to30th June, 1951.........        200 71(Another $200 million expected from congress in second half of 1951.)2,675955
26. This treatment may appear generous, but these points should beremembered:  (a) It is greatly in our interest that there should be American troops stationed in Europe, and, as the condition precedent to this, a large and fully-equipped French force.(b) The equipment and finance which the French are to receive must beregarded as an instalment, on account, of the arrangements which willbe finally made under the proposals of the Nitze memorandum.(c) The Americans have told us that, apart from finished equipment, the interimaid for the French will consist of dollar materials or off-shore purchases in France, and that the United States regard the interim settlement with france as on all fours with the interim offer they have made to us.27. The immediate situation. We are here concerned with two main points:first, the reply to be made to the United States aide-memoire referred to in para-graph 8 above, and, secondly, the status of the  3,600 million three-year production programme.28. As regards the aide-memoire it seems clear enough that we should acceptthe $84 million worth of dollar components in the  200 million high priority pro-gramme. This fits in with long-term concept under which end-items orcomponents are produced by the countries technically best fitted to do so and trans-ferred to those who require them for the carrying out of their share in the commonplan. On the other hand, the proposal that the United States Government shouldpurchase $28 million worth of our equipment does not appear to fit in with basicconcepts and a decision on it should therefore be deferred until the arrangements under the Nitze memorandum have been worked out in greater detail.29. As regards the  3,600 million programme which we have announced wewould undertake with United States assistance, it is clear that the basis upon whichthe United States request and our reply were made will be rendered obsolete ifthe proposals of the Nitze memorandum are accepted since we shall be consideringour effort from an entirely different starting-point the medium-term defence plan-and relying on multilateral agreement to secure that as a result the economicburden we undertake is equitable. This may well mean that our actual military effort over the three years may be greater than  3,600 million; but it also means that, to the extent that we secure a just multilateral settlement, the economic burdenactually imposed on us will be no greater than we can fairly bear. Meanwhile, there remains the urgent need to get ahead with the placing of orders so that the produc-tion urgently required can be obtained in time. The authorities given under the 200 million programme will be used up by the end of this month and we must therefore give further authority so that production will not be delayed. This is a necessary interim measure and does not mean that we are committed either inpractice, or in international discussion, to carrying out the whole of the  3,600 millionprogramme; the worst that could happen, if in the event it proves that we are toundertake a smaller or different programme, is that we shaii have involved ourselves in a certain amount of nugatory expenditure.V. Recommendations30.   We therefore make the following recommendations:  (1) We should accept the United States offer of interim aid of $84 million forthe dollar content of the  200 million instalment of the production programme to which we are already committed.(2) We should reserve our position on the United States offer of interim cashaid of $28 million to be given by purchase of $28 million worth of ourequipment, so as not to prejudice our position under the final arrange-ments for equitable distribution of the economic burden.(3) We should proceed with the Nitze plan, that is, collaborate with the otherN.A.T.O. countries in working out the procedure for determining ona multilateral basis the equitable division of the burden of North Atlanticdefence between the partner countries. Our participation must be onthe footing that the aim is to produce not only a fair distribution, but also
gresults which are tolerable for our economy. The scheme must there-fore provide, if necessary, for the review of the scale of the Medium-Term Defence Plan in the light of its economic consequences.(4) Meantime a decision must be taken on the extent to which further commit-ments are undertaken on the  3,600 million programme before a final settlement is reached on the distribution of the defence burden betweenthe N.A.T.O. countries. On the one hand, the stage has been reached at which further orders must be placed for many items over a consider-able range of the complete programme if we are to avoid loss of timeand the dissipation of capacity. On the other hand, the more we engage in commitments on our domestic programme, the more likely we are to suffer disadvantage in two ways. In the first place we prejudice our prospects of not being asked to carry more than a fair share of theburden under the Nitze procedure. Secondly, the programme itself maychange as a result of the review of collective N.A.T.O. defence require-commitments  and the capabilities of the partner countries, and we may find that time and money has been wasted by our embarking on theproduction of the wrong things.In the light of these conflicting considerations, if our colleagues are satisfiedthat, notwithstanding the economic and financial consequences, we must proceed on the basis of the full  3,600 million programme, we recommend that authority should be given to place further orders, so far as these are needed to create ormaintain productive capacity and avoid loss of time, within the  3,600 million pro-gramme and beyond the instalments of  200 million to which we are already committed. On the other hand, we should not be financially committed to thefull programme of  3,600 million till progress has been made, with the determination of our share of the collective defence plan and the distribution of the economicburden between the North Atlantic countries.E. B.H. G.23rd October, 1950.ANNEX united States Aide-Memoire on Interim Aid, dated 3rd October, 1950(Note. The text below was reported in Washington telegram No. 2670 of 4th October.)Following is text of Aide-Memoire handed to us by the Americans in originalform (we have not yet received revise of paragraph 4 (3)):  During the past several weeks representatives of our two Governments haveengaged in a series of conversations concerning the programme of additional high priority military production being developed by the United Kingdom. It was recognised that, pending consideration and appraisal of the long-range defenceefforts of all North Atlantic Treaty countries and the determination within N.A.T.O.of the apportionment of responsibilities, it was impracticable to reach any firm decisions concerning the  3 - 6 billion programme under development in the UnitedKingdom; conversations, therefore, centred particularly on the first two instalments(aggregating  200 million) of that programme which the United Kingdom, becauseof the urgency of the situation and of the importance of initiating production action,has gotten under way prior to arrangements for United States assistance.2. These conversations have not only provided the Government of theUnited States with information concerning the composition and phasing of this programme, but have brought out that the Government of the United kingdom was prepared to make available to the United States, either for the use of the UnitedStates or for use in meeting general North Atlantic Treaty requirements, someportion of the materials to be produced under the programme. In addition, these conversations have permitted a useful exchange of views on the economic andfinancial problems which this programme, and the larger defence effort of whichit represents an initial segment, will raise for the Government of the UnitedKingdom.  As a result, the Government of the United States has a much better
appreciation of the kinds of difficulties which may be encountered in implementingthis defence effort and a fuller understanding of the initiative and speed with whichthe Government of the United Kingdom has undertaken the development of a programme and its translation into concrete forward steps.3. During the course of these conversations we believe that it was mutually agreed that any assistance which the United States might be prepared to furnish tothe United Kingdom in connexion with the  200 million production programme should logically be worked out as part of any long-range programme of assistance which might be developed to assist the United Kingdom in the implementation ofits total defence effort under the medium-term plan. It was also recognised, how-ever, that the urgency of the situation required that some understanding with respectto the maniier and scope of assistance to be furnished for this initial segment of the overall United Kingdom defence effort must be reached before it would be possibleto work out any long-range arrangements for United States aid. The determination of total assistance to be furnished will have to take in account a variety of factors,some of which cannot now be projected with any degree of accuracy. these include (1) A thorough examination of all the relevant economic and financial factors involved;(2) A determination of the exact nature of the responsibilities of the UnitedKingdom under the medium-term plan;(3) The final assignment of production tasks to the United Kingdom viewedin the light of the total requirements of the North Atlantic Treaty area;(4) Multilateral arrangements under the North Atlantic Treaty designed toequalise the economic and financial burdens of the total defence effortrequired by the medium-term plan, including transfer arrangements; and(5) A determination of the contribution which other portions of the sterling area might make to the maintenance of the defence effort of the UnitedKingdom.Accordingly, it has been agreed that any arrangements made as to the manner and scope of United States assistance to the  200 million production programme must be considered without prejudice to any subsequent determinations with respectto the total assistance which might be furnished to the United Kingdom or as to theprinciples which will ultimately determine the amount of such aid.4. The Government of the United States, within the context of the foregoing,has given careful consideration to the request of the Government of the UnitedKingdom for assistance in carrying out the  200 million programme. Based onsuch consideration and upon the understanding that these proposals will in no senseconstitute a precedent and shall be without prejudice to any subsequent longer-termagreement, the Government of the United States is prepared to agree as follows:  (1) To accept, as appropriate for United States assistance, subject only toprobably minor modifications therein or deletions therefrom which(a) may be mutually agreed upon, (b) may be required by north atlantic Treaty considerations, or (c) may be necessitated by UnitedStates legal requirements, the  200 million production programme whichhas been submitted by the Government of the United Kingdom and acopy of which is attached as Annex A hereto. It is recognised that a portion of this programme is still in the stage of refinement and willrequire certain additional joint examination, particularly as it relates to (3) below. Similarly, the end-items requested, and which are referredto in (2) below, will be screened in accordance with the proceduresnormally employed in connexion with the United States end-itemprogramme.(2) Furnish all dollar components which are required for this programme to theextent that they consist of production equipment (including machine tools), materials, components, licences, technical assistance and certainrelated end-items which may legally be provided by the United States as a assistance under Public Law 329, 81st Congress, as amended by PublicLaw 621, 81st Congress, and any other applicable legislation, and to thefurther extent that such items may be available for procurement.Criteria for determining the dollar components of the programme and procedures for justifying assistance therefore will be of the same general
type as those which have heretofore obtained in connexion with UnitedStates assistance for increasing military production abroad. Thisproposal is based on the estimate that the value of the dollar componentsof this programme will approximate 84 million dollars, and that of this total about 14 million dollars represent items which are normally includedin United States assistance programmes for end-items of equipment. Inthe event that the value of the dollar components of this programme should exceed this. amount, it will be necessary for the United States,because of limitations in its appropriated funds, to consider whethercomponents represented by such excess can be provided. Similarly, tothe extent that steps have not been taken by the United Kingdom which make possible the obligation by the United States prior to 30th June,1951, of funds now available to provide the dollar components of this programme, to such extent the furnishing of such components will be dependant on action by the United States Congress to make thenecessary funds available subsequent to that date. In this latter respect,however, we recognise a moral commitment in the same manner as has been the case for the European Recovery Programme in similar circumstances.(3) In consideration of the fact that the undertaking of a greatly increaseddefence effort, of which the  200 million production programmerepresents an initial instalment, will make it necessary for the UnitedKingdom to draw increasingly on resources of areas of the world whichcannot be obtained through sterling expenditure, and in further con-sideration of the capabilities of the United Kingdom to satisfy certainN.A.T.O. requirements in military materials over and above its own needs, the United States agrees to procure from the United Kingdom,for use of the United States or for use in meeting the general require-ments of the North Atlantic Treaty area, military materials which arescheduled to be produced under the  200 million production programmeof a value equivalent to 28 million dollars over and above the value ofany dollar components therein which may be provided pursuant to (2)above. The specific materials to be procured and the precise termsof payment and delivery will be the subject of further negotiation and agreement.5. In making these proposals, the Government of the United States believes that the following additional observations are necessary and appropriate in termsof the proposals themselves, in terms of the longer-range problem of any UnitedStates assistance to the United Kingdom in connexion with the total defence effort,and in order to avoid any possible future misunderstanding.6. First, the United States recognises the importance of North atlantic treaty countries maintaining political and economic stability adequate to support their respective responsibilities in the co-operative defence effort and, within thelimits of military necessity, to prevent serious internal deterioration.7. Second, the United States wishes to note, however, that, in view of the magnitude of the defence effort which it is itself undertaking and the probablesize of the effort required of all North Atlantic Treaty countries over the nextseveral years, the whole character of the economic problem may change and thelevel and form of assistance which the United States may be able to provide tothe United Kingdom and to other countries requesting assistance may be severely affected not only by financial consideration but also by limitations of physicalresources, and more particularly by shortages in many essential commodities.8. Third, the United States recognises that, as the size of the defence effort of the United Kingdom increases, it will impose progressively great burdens on the economy of the United Kingdom, and that this fact, among others, must be takeninto account in working out arrangements for United States assistance for suchdefence effort in the future.9. Fourth, the United States, in negotiating the amount of any assistance tobe provided in connexion with the total defence effort of the United Kingdom,must necessarily take into account, and weigh, the relative degree of effort and need represented by the requests of the United Kingdom and of other members of
the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation in the light of the findings of the N.A.T.O.concerning the requirements of an effective medium-term plan and an equitable distribution of the total burden. Such factors have similarly had to be taken intoaccount in formulating the proposals contained herein.10. Fifth, the United States is of the view that until the medium-term planhas been approved, the tasks thereunder allocated, and the cost of carrying it outdetermined, it will not be possible for the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation toreach any firm conclusion as to whether the fundamental economic and politicalassumptions underlying the proposed defence effort of the United Kingdom andits request for assistance, as expressed in the recent conversations, will, in fact,constitute proper assumptions if the North Atlantic Treaty Nations are to carryout such plan successfully and with an equitable distribution of burdens among them. Based on North Atlantic Treaty Organisation recommendations, the amount,form and timing of United States aid will be directly conditioned by the degree of effort made by the recipient country and by its adequacy measured in terms of therequirements of the medium-term plan.11. Sixth, the assistance herein proposed is without prejudice to the level of aid to be provided to the United Kingdom under the Economic Co-operation act of 1948, as amended, and to any future adjustment thereof which the United states may determine is necessary or desirable.ANNEX IISuggested Method for arriving at an Equitable Distribution of EconomicBurdens in carrying out the Medium-Term Defence Plan (The NitzeMemorandum)(Note.-The text is that of the United States Deputy as submitted to theN.A.T.O. Working Group on Production and Finance)The responsibility for action in raising and supplying forces must be placed upon national governments. Co-ordination through the N.A.T.O. machinery isnecessary, however, if the actions of the individual governments are to conform with an integrated overall defence plan, if the forces for defence of freedom inEurope are to be sufficient to carry out their task, and if there is to be an equitable distribution of the economic burdens involved.2. The decisions involved in arriving at an equitable distribution of economicburdens cut deeply into the internal affairs of individual countries and affect their most vital immediate and long-range interests. They are,- therefore, basic political decisions and will probably need to be taken by governments acting through theNorth Atlantic Council itself.3. The preparation of recommendations to the Council and arrangements forthe necessary staff work on which those recommendations are to be based shouldbe the responsibility of the Deputies. The Deputies should have such staff assist-ance in carrying out this responsibility as they may consider necessary. the composition and organisation of this staff should be determined by the Deputies.4. The Deputies can look to the Standing Group for guidance on effectives,equipment and other military requirements by countries. They can look to theMilitary Production and Supply Board for guidance on the distribution of produc-tion tasks by countries. There is an ad hoc costing group from which the Deputieswill be able to secure costing formulas.5. From these data it should be possible to compute gross cost of the militaryprogramme in the aggregate and by countries computed before aid. It is suggestedthat the Deputies arrange for this work to be completed by the appropriateN.A.T.O. agencies.6. When the cost of the medium-term defence plan is computed, the nextstep should be an analysis of the economic impact of the programme of this magnitude-tude on the member countries. This analysis should, of course, take account ofthe total proposed defence expenditures including the additional expenditures
required specifically to carry out.the medium-term defence plan. It should alsodraw on, and be appropriately related to, the broad analysis of European and north american economic prospects being developed concurrently in the O.E.E.C. in con-nection with that organisation^ third annual report. To this end it is suggestedthat (a) The form of O.E.E.C. questionnaires covering general national accounts,balance of payments and budgetary projections be reviewed to insuremaximum usefulness for this specific N.A.T.O. purpose as well as thegeneral purposes of the O.E.E.C.;(b) The national submissions by the member countries to the O.E.E.C. bebased on assumption by each country of the cost of military programme as indicated in paragraph 5 above;(c) The Deputies create a N.A.T.O. Working Group based on the N.A.T.O.countries&apos; delegations to the O.E.E.C. (including the United States and.   - Canada) utilising if possible the services of experienced members of theO.E.E.C. Secretariat;(d) This working group, under guidance from the Deputies, arrange for sup-supplementary submissions by the N.A.T.O. member countries coveringmore specific information bearing on the impact of the proposed mili- .tary programmes on their economies and their relative abilities to carry the burden of expanded defence requirements, and(e) The working group develop for the Deputies a report, drawing both on(1) the O.E.E.C. submissions on their analysis in the O.E.E.C. and (2) onthe special submissions to the N.A.T.O. group and their analysis, thisreport indicating the effect of the proposed military programme on thenational accounts and balance of payments of each country and inclu-ding a critical evaluation of the data bearing on equitable distribution ofthe economic budget. An important purpose of the report should be to isolate out the major questions of policy requiring decisions by theN.A.T.O. Governments, individually and collectively.7. The recommendations referred to in paragraph 3 would be worked out bythe Deputies and the decision referred to in paragraph 2 would then have to bereached by Governments acting through the Atlantic Council. Assistance wouldbe bilaterally arranged in conformity with N.A.T.O. programmes and administeredpari passu with performance-i of the N.A.T.O. programme by the variousparticipants.8. While the above programme is being worked out, interim arrangements should go forward bilaterally on an urgent basis so that actions which are necessarynow will not be delayed. The impact of these interim arrangements would betaken account of in the final decisions.

</content>
</cab>
