<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/42/0 images: 396-415</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Sis document is the property of  HIS  britannic  m^jestvs  government/. 0 dIt is issued for the personal use of ..^*-v.......^ST!^r^..../^*S*-fOP SECRET Copy No...C. P. (50) 24630TH OCTOBER, 1950CABINETSIZE AND SHAPE OF THE ARMED forces.951/1954Note by the Secretary of the CabinetIn his memorandum on t he Finance of Defence(CP. (50) 246) the Prime Minister refers to a memorandumby the Minister of Defence on the Size and Shape of the armed forces for the years 1951/54, which was considered by theDefence Committee on 25th October, 1950 (D. O. (50) 20thMeeting, Minute 5).   A copy of this memorandum isattached.(Signed)   NORMAN brook cabinet Office, S. W. 1. ,30TH OCTOBER, 1950.

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1950-.----,--m-The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited,   it is issued for the personal use cf...............................................................TOP SECRET[D.O. (50) 8112th October, 1950.]cabinet defence CommitteeSIZE AND SHAPE OF THE ARMED FORCES 1951-54Memorandum by the Minister of defence the Chiefs of Staff have given careful consideration to the Size and Shape ofthe Armed Forces over the three years 1951-54 and I attach a report which theyhave submitted to me.It will be seen from Annex IV to this report that the first estimate of the costof the programme is  3,880 million. I should, however, explain that in this figureno allowance has been made for a variety of factors, such as normal final estimatingreductions in &quot; hard core &quot;* expenditure and such items as shortfall allowances onthe works and production programmes. When this is done the total cost of theprogramme should be about  3,700 million.The Chiefs of Staff agree that the programme may require revision in detail and there are some matters to which I should wish to give further thought. It is,however, important that we should accept it in broad outline so that detailed planning can proceed, particularly in the supply field, and long-term contracts canbe placed wherever the need exists. An additional reason for a decision on the broad aspect of this problem is that at the meeting of the North Atlantic defence ministers commencing on Saturday, 28th October, we are under an obligation togive a forecast of our contribution to the Medium Term Plan.Meanwhile I am by no means satisfied that the proposals which the Chiefs ofStaff have necessarily limited themselves on financial grounds will in fact meet our essential defence requirements. They fall far short of what would be needed ifwe were to contribute our quota towards the North Atlantic Treaty OrganisationMedium Term Defence Plan. In my view, a front-line strength of 2,450 aeroplanesby 31st March, 1954, will not meet our needs and I should like to see a more rapidbuild-up particularly of Fighter Command. I am also very apprehensive about thepresent and prospective production of tanks and it may be necessary to open up an additional production line for the purpose of increasing the supply of these weapons. Further, I propose to take energetic steps to accelerate deliveries of cer-tain items of equipment included in the programme.My immediate proposal is that the Committee should approve the broad out-line of the proposals put forward by the Chiefs of Staff so that where necessarydetailed plans can be made, and orders placed. The present estimate is that thecost of the programme may be about  3,700 million over the three years, but theremust be some uncertainty as regards the later part of the period. If experience showed that expenditure was running at a higher level than was acceptable to theGovernment, it would be possible to make some adjustments in the plans for1953-54 and defer certain expenditure until the following year.E. S.Ministry of Defence, S.WA,\2th October, 1950.* Pay, Pensions, Movements, Supplies, Civilians, &amp;c.39542 copy No.*S
[C.O.S. (50) 409]    *CHIEFS OF STAFF COMMITTEETHE SIZE AND SHAPE OF THE ARMED FORCES OVER THETHREE YEARS BEGINNING  1951-52Report by the Chiefs of StaffIn this report we submit our new proposals for the Size and Shape of the armed Forces over the three years4951-52, 1952-53 and 1953-54.2. Our proposals are, in the main, determined, as to scope and timing, bysupply possibilities on the assumptions laid down by the Government, (though therate at which personnel can be recruited and trained is also a relevant factor). the resulting programme is, in our view, reasonably well balanced, and the distributionof resources is in harmony with the conclusion reached in our recent review ofGlobal Strategy.3.   We must make it clear, however, that the programme^ (a) does not, in point of magnitude, provide our estimated share of the require-ments of the Medium Term N.A.T.O. Defence Plan. In certain impor-tant respects it falls short of the contributions that the United KingdomGovernment may be called upon, and may indeed feel obliged, to make;(b) may not, in point of timing, meet the needs of the international situation.Its real effect will not be felt until 1953 and 1954.4. It is essential that the programme now proposed should be authorised atonce, so that planning and production can go ahead without delay and potentialconflicts between defence claims and those of exports can be identified and resolved.The Government has already announced that, in the matter of priorities, defence and exports to dollar markets must now rank together at the top of the list.5.   Our proposals may be summarised as follows:  (a) Navy(i) The size of the Fleet for 1954 remains generally the same as thatplanned in 1949 but a larger part of the re-equipping and pre-paring the fleet for war, which it was originally planned should becarried out between 1950 and 1957, has been concentrated intothe next three years; also a number of ships, particularly frigates,which it was planned to dispose of, have been retained in a lowcategory of reserve.(ii) By making good the deficiencies in mobilisation stores and equipment as quickly as possible, the Navy will be able to fight with the fleetthat it has got should an emergency arise. At the same time the modernisation of the fleet will be accelerated, within the limitsenforced by the production of new ships, weapons and equipment.Details of the planned fleet will be found at Annex I.(b) army the Army proposals are essentially a compromise, as hitherto,between the conflicting claims of the Cold War and the need to provideas soon as possible the best equipment for our forces to use in the eventof Hot War.The revised proposals involve (i) The creation of a proper strategic reserve to consist by mid-1951 of one new armoured division, one new infantry division and the parachute brigade, with the addition of anotherdivision (partly armoured) by the end of the three year period.
(ii) The strengthening of B.A.O.R. early in 1951 by one armoured division and certain anti-aircraft and engineer units.(iii) Such steps as are possible to improve the state of readiness andequipment of the Active Army and first contingents of theReserve Army so that they can plan an immediate and effec-tive part in the opening stages of a war. These steps will bepropressive but, even by the end of the third year, equipment will only be available to the extent of 70 per cent, of require-ments with maintenance scales at only half normal activeoperational scales.(iv) Reducing the time that would be required to deploy availableAnti-Aircraft guns and equipment for the Air Defence ofthe United Kingdom.A table* giving the deployment of the Active and Reserve Armies in mid-1951is attached to this report.(c) Air force the plan for the R.A.F. provides for an expansion of the front lineby over 80 per cent. (i.e., from 1,344 to 2,450 aircraft) by March 1954. this expansion begins slowly and accelerates rapidly after the first two years.By the same date we should have some 2,700 modern operational aircraft in reserve behind the front line, and the training organisation should haveexpanded to a total of approximately 3,200 aircraft (i.e., 470 operational and 2,730 training types). Secondly, the plan provides for extensivere-equipment of the force with modern aircraft. Thirdly, it provides for building up a war reserve of air crews, aircraft and other equipment. this plan brings the force closer to the &apos;minimum strength required to meet itscommitments, but there are the following important deficiencies:  (i) The expansion of Bomber Command and B.A.F.O. is onlyenough for our contribution to the interim Western UnionTactical Air Force; the Tactical Air Force required under the medium-Term plan is twice as large.(ii) The report of the Maritime Air Defence Committee will showthat a much larger maritime force will be required.(iii) The rate of introduction of the F.3/48 and the Swift is unsatis-factory, and the front line of Fighter Command is some 20 percent, short of that recommended by the Air DefenceCommittee.(iv) There will be no reserves of Canberras; an inadequate reserve of ground attack aircraft; and a day fighter reserve consistingalmost wholly of Meteors till 1954.The notet attached to this report sets out the salient points in the plan, andthe tablet attached to the note gives details of the build-up year by year.The programme will be kept flexible. For example, the run-down of theTransport Force and the rate of expansion of Fighter Command and the T.A.F.will be kept under review, and the proposals in the Table will be improved if at allpossible.Provision is made for extensive improvements to our infrastructure, including a comprehensive reconstruction of the United Kingdom radar chain by the earliestpossible date.Man-Power6. The active man-power strength of the three Services, including women and boys, had previously been planned to run down from 682,000 in April .1951to 677,750 by April 1953. Under the present proposals, requirements are estimated to average about 810,000 in 1951-52, rising to about 840,000 in 1953-54. these estimates are based on the assumption that whole-time National Service v/ill remain at 2 years and that the present pay increases will continue to stimulate regularrecruiting. ** Annex II. t Annex III. t Enclosure to Annex III.
7.   Individual Service requirements are as follows:  (a) Royal Navy. Instead of a strength of running down from 128,900 on1st April, 1951, to a stabilised level of 124,000 by 1st April, 1952, theRoyal Navy would now require 130,000 regulars and an annual nationalservice intake of 2,000 to maintain the fleet at the proposed increasedstate of preparedness, making a total strength of 134,000.(b) Army. Previous plans provided for an active Army of 380,000 (including some 16,000 women and boys) in 1950 running down to about 355,000by 1953. The revised Order of Battle would require some 420,000 menand 12,000 to 15,000 women and boys.Allowing for improved regular recruiting, this requirement couldbe met by 1st April, 1951, with no immediate increase in the rate ofcall-up of national servicemen, but between 1st October, 1951, and1st April, 1952, there would be a drop in strength of 35,000 men if,as is likely, regular reservists are not detained beyond October 195.1!and at the same time regulars cease to be held back from release.(c) Royal Air Force. Present proposals for the Royal Air Force wouldrequire a considerable increase in uniformed man-power. Strengthswere to have been 198,000 on 1st April, 1951, and 206,000 on 1st April,1953. Average requirements are now estimated to be 245,000 in1951-52, 260,000 in 1952-53 and 275,000 in 1953-54. Although thesefigures may be reduced somewhat by civilianisation and despite the considerable increase which is hoped for in regular recruitment, theman-power requirement could only be met by a distinctly high degreeof dilution with National Servicemen. Resources of skilled man-power would be strained to the utmost and the main limiting factor on theexpansion of the force would be the provision of trained air crews.8. The plan has throughout been related to supply possibilities, and repre-sents in fact the best that can be done with the maximum deliveries which theAdmiralty and Ministry of Supply consider possible on the assumptions currentlylaid down by the Government, e.g., no direction of labour, no requisitioning, &amp;c.(CP. (50) 181). Bottle-necks will undoubtedly develop, particularly in the vitalfield of electronics. Special steps will have to be taken to prevent a general slowing down of the whole programme, including the planned diversion of effort from thehome market and, where necessary, from export. No allowance has been madefor export of tanks or aircraft to N.A.T.O. countries or elsewhere, except againstorders already outstanding.Tank Production9. The War Office will absorb the total output of the tank factories at presentin operation. That output is as follows:  This will provide 1,400 additional tanks, which, together with existing stocks,will barely cover the war equipment needs of the Active Army and the1st Contingent of the Reserve Army plus 25 per cent, peace maintenance reserve.It will, however, leave the 2nd Contingent of the Reserve Army at training scalesand make no provision at all for tanks for New Zealand, Australia, South Africaor any North Atlantic countries. Requirements to meet the needs of the Common-wealth countries and prospective demands from the North Atlantic Treaty countries are being taken up separately, as these would not be a charge on the Army budget.Aircraft Production10. Orders have already been placed with the Ministry of Supply for aircraftcovered by the two &quot; shopping lists &quot; of  100 million each, and Treasury authority has been given for a limited number of further orders which are required irame-diately. Other substantial orders will have to be authorised in a few weeks if theaircraft and equipment are to be available by the dates the programme requires.ProductionTanks1951-521952-531953-54500500
11. The general aim is to provide a three months&apos; reserve of equipment. Theposition can be summarised as follows:  (a) Fighters. There will be a three months&apos; reserve of Meteors throughout theperiod,, increasing rapidly after 1953 as the F.3/48 is introduced andMeteors are thrown up.The reserve of Vampires remains at about half a month untilaircraft begin to be thrown up by rearming in 1954. Venom reservesrise to H months in 1954.Only very few, if any, F.3&apos;s and Swifts will be available in reserveuntil 1954-55, unless production is accelerated.The reserve of jet night fighters will gradually increase to 3 monthsby 1953.(b) Bombers. There will be an ample reserve of Lincolns from 1951 onwards.Reserves of Washingtons should be available from the U.S.A.Virtually no reserve of Canberras can be accumulated until,1954-55.(c) Naval Aircraft. Except in the case of the Naval anti-submarine aircraft the G.R. 17, it is intended to build up reserves progressively until thereshould be 3 to 4 months&apos; war replacements in 1955. In the case ofthe anti-submarine aircraft, it is unlikely that more than 1 month&apos;s warreplacements will have been built up by 1955.Research and Development12. These proposals will necessarily entail an increased effort and expenditureon Research and Development.13.   The added cost has been included in the table at Annex IV:Cost14. The cost of the proposals outlined above has been roughly worked outby the three Service Departments and Ministry of Supply and figures under the threebroad headings Production, Works Services*and &quot; Hard Core &quot; (Pay, pensions, &amp;c.) are given in Annex IV.15. It will be seen that, according to this estimate, the cost of the three-year programme works out at about  3,880 million. For various reasons, however, itseems probable that this estimate is at least  150 million too high. For example,experience shows that money spent on Works Services invariably falls short of programme figures, sometimes by a substantial amount.Again it is doubtful whether the whole of the total sum of  1,600 millionallotted to production will actually be spent in the 3-year period. All past experience indicates the likelihood of some lag in parts of the programme, with theresult that some deliveries scheduled for the third year will not have to be paid foruntil the year following the conclusion of this programme. This is the usual shortfallallowance. Finally, in the case of the RAF. there is a reasonable hope that someof the items of equipment for which provision has been made on the programme will be obtained as &quot; end items &quot; under American aid.16. It can be said, therefore, that after allowance has been made for these factors and for the effect of the more detailed estimating that will now be made, theactual cost of the programme may work out at about  3,700 million. although this is some 2\ per cent, in excess of the  3,600 million figure, we think it wouldbe a serious mistake to try to reduce Production estimates (which is the only wayof making the reduction required) at this stage. The programme as now presentedwill have to be reviewed in detail, but this must take time. On the other hand,there are a number of essential orders which must be placed within a few weeksif the programme is to have any hope of materialising. In our view, the programme which we submit should be accepted in broad outline and authority should be givento place orders covered by it. If towards the end of the period it becomes clearthat the programme as a whole is going to cost too much, steps can always be takento retard deliveries and new Works Services so that the cost over the 3-year periodcan be kept broadly within a limit of  3,600 million.
Recommendations17.   We recommend that the Defence Committee:  (1) Give general approval to the proposals outlined above.(2) Authorise the immediate placing of production orders necessary to give full effect to this programme, subject to the proviso in paragraph 16above.(Signed)       FRASERW. J. SLIM.R. A. COCHRANE (V.C.A.S.).Ministry of Defence, S.W.1,12th October, 1950.ANNEX 1Strength of the Royal Navy on Increased Navy Estimates for 1951-52to 1953-54Peacetime FleetIt is the intention to maintain approximately the same fleet in commission asat present, for the next three years; it may be possible to make some increase inthe small ships in commission if the re-engagement rate improves amongst skilledratings, particularly higher ratings, as a result of the recent pay increases.2. The peacetime disposition of the Fleet at the present time is given in Table I.Wartime Fleet3. In the following table is set out the fleet that will be available six monthsafter mobilisation, in 1950, and 1954; in the third and fourth columns is shown thenumber of ships that will be in low categories of reserve in 1950 and 1954, and whichwould require at least six months after mobilisation for bringing forward for service. These include a number of ships that it was planned to dispose of, but which are being retained in view of the international situation and could be madeavailable for unforeseen commitments or to renlace war losses.Fleet A vailable      Ships in lowatD + 6 months  category Reserve	1950	1954	1950	1954Battleships	1	1	4	4Fleet Carriers      .........	3*	3*	3	5Light Fleet Carriers	5t	5t	1	5Cruisers	18	18	6	6Fast Minelayers   .........	3	3		Destroyers          ...      ......	54	62		89Frigates     ...      ...      ......	145	145	74	Submarines         ...      ...      ...	53	53	8	8Ocean Minesweepers      ......	61	61		Coastal and Inshore Minsesweepers	90	151		Front Line A/C   ...      ......	150	213		New Construction4. Below is set out the new construction which the Admiralty proposes toput in hand during this and the next three financial years; two Fleet Carriers, fourLight Fleet Carriers and eight Destroyers, at present under construction, are not shown in the table:  1950-51   1951-52   1952-53   1953-54     TotalFrigates......... 3 5 15 4 27Submarines      ...... ... 8 ... ...             8Coastal Minesweepers ... 20 12 12 12 56.Inshore Minesweepers ... 21 8 8 8 - 45Coastal Forces(MTB/MGB) 5 8 8 12 33Seaward Defence Craft 2 ... 8 8 18* Includes one ship for trials.                    t Includes one ship for training.
Modernisation and Conversion of Ships5. As many of our ships are rapidly becoming obsolescent, particularly inregard to the weapons used against modern forms of attack, it is necessary to re-equip and modernise them if they are to carry out their tasks; the conversion ofa number of our older Fleet Destroyers to fast A/S Frigate is required to combatthe fast submarine.6. The Admiralty proposed to put in hand the following modernisation andconversion during this and the next three years:  Modernisation of Fleet Carriers   ......      .	1Modernisation of Cruisers ...	......5Modernisation of Destroyers	......    10Modernisation of Frigates..........- .	.....      22Convert old Fleet Destroyers to 	A/S Frigates   ...      ......      ...      .	.....      35A/D Frigates   ......      .......	..      ...       6Convert &quot; T &quot; Class Submarines to 	Fast Battery Drive     .........	..      ...     &apos; 6Naval Aviation7. A front-line strength of 250 aircraft is considered to be the minimum whichwill enable Naval Aviation to carry out its prescribed roles in wartime. It was planned to reach this strength through gradual expansion by 1957.8. The increase in Naval Votes now proposed will have the effect of accelerat-ing this programme by two years. This will mean that by April 1954 our FrontLine Strength will have reached a figure of approximately 210 aircraft from itspresent strength of 150.Mobilisation Stores and Equipment9. A portion of the increased Naval Votes, particularly of the Navy&apos;s shareof the two  100 million recently allocated to the Services, will go towards making good deficiencies in mobilisation stores and equipment that would have existedunder the stabilised naval estimates of  201 million for the years 1950-51 1952-53.Man-Power10. The man-power strength of the Navy is at present running down: on1st April, 1950, it was 141,800 and on 1st April, 1951, and 1952 it is planned to be128,900 and 124,000 respectively. In the new programme man-power would be stabilised at 130,000 regulars and an annual National Service, intake of 2,000. Theadditional man-power over the figure of 124,000 regulars, which it was planned toreduce to, will enable the Fleet to be maintained at an increased state of pre-paredness.Summary11. To summarise, the foregoing shows how the planned increase in NavyVotes over the next three years will be used in re-equipping and preparing theFleet for war. This is achieved without unduly interfering with the economy ofthe country. By making good deficiencies in mobilisation stores and equipment as quickly as possible, the Navy will be able to fight with the Fleet it has got shouldan emergency arise. The revised plan above is based primarily on re-equippingthe existing Navy for its traditional role, the defence of the United Kingdom and sea communications. Althoiugh it goes some way to meeting the United KingdomNaval requirements of the Medium Term N.A.T.O. Plan, it does not include any provision for the additional contribution the United Kingdom may be called uponto make under that plan.
1137103No.1 (Harbour Training Squadron)2 (1 Harbour Training Squadron)2 (Trooping to the Far East)1432211813611532653130Table I.-The Present Dispositions of the Peace-time FleetStation and Class of ShipHome  NumberFleet Carriers      ............... 1Light Fleet Carriers       ............ 2Cruisers     ............      ...... 3Destroyers ...      .........      ...... 12Frigates     ...      :.............. 2Mediterranean Light Fleet Carriers      ............ 1Cruisers     ...      ...      .........      ... 4Destroyers ...      ...      .........      ... 9Frigates     .................. 11Submarines.................. 7Minesweepers      ............... 12East Indies Cruisers     ......      ............       2Frigates     ..................       5American and West Indies Cruisers     ...      ...      .........      - - -       1Frigates     ..................       3South Atlantic Cruisers     ...      ...      ...      ...... 1Frigates     ..................       2Far East Light Fleet CarriersAircraft Repair ShipCruisersDestroyers ...Frigates     ......SubmarinesTrials and Training Battleships......Fleet CarriersLight Fleet CarriersCruisersDestroyers......Frigates     ......SubmarinesMinesweepersSummary Battleships......Fleet CarriersLight Fleet CarriersAircraft Repair ShipCruisersDestroyersFrigatesSubmarinesMinesweepers
ANNEX IIDeployment of the Active ArmyShortly after 1st April, 1951, the Active Army to carry out its tasks, set out above, is planned to be ten equivalent divisions deployed as follows:  3^ divisionsy 2idivisionsH divisions2\ division:;f divisionB.A.O.R.one infantry division ...      ......two armoured divisions     .........one infantry brigade ...      ...      ...United Kingdom one armoured division      .........one infantry division16 Independent parachute Brigade(to be formed later in 1951 one armoured brigade).........      .........Middle East one infantry division        ...      .........one infantry brigade ......      ......two infantry battalions      ...      ...      ......Far East one infantry division        ... ...      ...      ...&quot;one infantry brigade group .........Anglo-Gurkha Division      ... ...      ...      ...Austria and Trieste one infantry brigade each......      ......CaribbeanGibraltar small garrison forces        ...      ...      ......Total ...   10 equivalent divisionsThe Reserve A rmyThe Reserve Army is planned to contain 12 equivalent divisions in two categories:  (a) Divisions in the first contingent of the Reserve Army available as part ofan Expeditionary Force: --50 Division ... .....51 (Highland) Division.....-53 Division56 Armoured Division .....161 Independent Infantry Brigade23 Armoured Brigade ......9 Armoured Brigade(b) Divisions in 2nd Contingent of the Reserve Army42 Infantry Division43 Infantry Division44 Infantry Division49 Armoured Division52 (Lowland) Division16 Airborne Divisioncertain independent infantry and armouredbrigades        ...      ...      ...      ....5 equivalentdivisionsI 7 equivalentdivisionsTotal ...   12 equivalent divisionsc
Anti-aircraft Command arid other Anti-aircraft Units(a) Defence of the United KingdomRegiments ...A ctive A rmy   TA.14 1561(b) Overseas in PeaceRegiments ...13(c) Overseas after Mobilisation(some of them initially deployed in UnitedKingdom)Regiments ...      ...      ...      ...        51412 equivalentdivisions(d) TA. divisionsL.A.A. regiments(some on mobilisation deployed in non-div. role)Regiments ...      ...      ...      ...       -9(e) Total A.A. regiments32179211regimentsIt is intended in the immediate future to raise two additional L.A.A. regiments forthe Regular divisions now being raised.Attention is drawn to the following points:  Bomber Command1. The plan provides for an increase of one squadron (8 aircraft) in 1951-52,of eight squadrons in 1952-53 and nine squadrons in 1953-54, giving a total frontline of 36 squadrons (288 aircraft) by the end of 1953-54, together with three targetmarking and four photographic reconnaissance squadrons. This provides for animportant part of our obligations to Western Union.1 2. Most of this force of 36 squadrons will be equipped with the Canberra(see below), which can only carry 7,500 lb. over a radius of 500 miles; and itshitting power will be small in relation to its commitments in support of the defenceof the United Kingdom and the land battle in Europe.3. At present nearly the whole of the medium bomber force is equipped withLincolns. Four squadrons will remain on Lincolns throughout the period, in orderto provide for heavy mine-laying and lor the carriage of heavy bombs. By June1952 eight squadrons should be re-equipped with Washingtons and the rest withCanberras. The new squadrons to be formed between 1952 and 1954 will all be equipped with Canberras.4. If it should prove possible to accelerate the introduction of the B.9/48, thefirst deliveries will probably be used to re-equip the four Lincoln Squadrons.Fighter Command5. The plan provides for the following increases in the front line at a fairlyuniform rate up to March 1954:  Short-range day fighter (regular) ...      ...      from 208 to 440Night fighter/all-weather  ...      ...      ...      from   56 to 286Intruder      ...      ......      ...      ...      from   32 to   48a total front line increase of 478 aircraft. However, even allowing for the RoyalAuxiliary Air Force squadrons, which would not be ready on the outbreak of war,Fighter Command would still be 218 aircraft short of the number recommended bythe Air Defence Committee.ANNEX IIIExpansion of the R.A.F. 1951-54
6. Apart from four squadrons which will be re-equipped with Venoms in 1952as the Vampire disappears, the whole regular day fighter force will remain on theMeteor until the F.3/48 and the Swift begin to be introduced in 1953; that is, unless,by special measures, the F.3 and the Swift can be produced more quickly. TheRoyal Auxiliary Air Force will complete re-equipment with Meteors and Vampiresby the end of 1951. The night fighter /all weather force will be equipped with nightfighter versions of the Meteor and latter of the Venom.Coastal Command7. The front line is increased by 32 aircraft, and in addition 8 G.R. aircraft are transferred to Coastal Command from M.E.A.F. and 10 flying boats fromF.E.A.F.8. When the Maritime Air Defence Committee has reported, the programme for Maritime Reconnaissance Squadrons will have to be reviewed. It seems certainthat it will be necessary to provide for a substantially large increase.Transport Command9. Transport Command is reduced to three long-range squadrons (24 aircraft)and one medium-range squadron (8 aircraft).If C.119&apos;s can be obtained from America, they will increase the carrying capacity of the overseas transport force.Western European Tactical Air Force (B.A.F.O.)10. The programme provides for an expansion of the fighter/ground attackforce from 80 to 256 aircraft, the whole force being ultimately equipped with theVenom. It also provides for the formation of 10 squadrons (160 aircraft) of light bombers (Canberras) in 1953-54.11. If two-thirds of Bomber Command is reckoned to be available for supportof the land campaign in Western Europe, the above expansion meets the recom-mendation of the Western European Regional Planning Group for the UnitedKingdom contribution to the interim Western European Tactical Air Force of2,196 aircraft. On the other hand the full Western European T.A.F. required for the medium Term Plan is over 4,500 aircraft, and there is no doubt we shall be pressed for a substantial further increase.Middle East and Far East Air Forces12. The front line of the Middle East Air Force is increased in 1954 by 48light bombers and 1.12 day fighter/ground attack aircraft.This expansion of Tactical Air Forces in the Middle East is the minimum required for support of the land campaign and for the air defence of the middle east.The front line in the Far East remains the same as at present, except for areduction of two flying boat squadrons which are transferred to Coastal Command.By the end of 1953-54 combat squadrons in M.E.A.F. and F.E.A.F. will be largely re-equipped with the Venom and Canberra, but the rate of re-equipment isslower than at home.13. Thus the front line is increased in total from 1,344 to 2,450 aircraft andextensively re-equipped. The points which should especially be noted are:  (a) The rate of introduction of the newest fighter types should if possible be improved on.(b) The expansion of the Tactical Air Force in Western iiurope achieves theUnited Kingdom contribution to the interim force of 2,196 aircraft, but4,500 aircraft are required under the Medium Term Plan.(c) The programme for Coastal Command will need review when the MaritimeAir Defence Committee has reported.

		Bomber Command					Coastal Command					Fighter Command					Transport Command			Home Com-mand		Serial No.	Date	Medium Bomber	Light Bomber (Strat.)	Long-range Photo. Recce.	Short-range Photo. Recce.	Total Bomber Command	Flying Boat	G.R. Landplane	Met.	Total Coastal Command	N.F./A11 Weather 1	L.R. Intruder	S.R. Day (Regular)	S.R. Day (R. Aux. A.F.)	A.O.P.	Total Fighter Command	L.R. Transport	M.R. Transport	Total Transport Command -	A.O.P. Home Command	Light Bomber	1	September    1950, current order of battle   ......	144	16	24	16	200	10	24	16	50	56	32	208	160	10	466	56	24	80	100	16	2	March 1951	144	16	24	16	200	20	24	16	60	64	40	248	160	10	522	40	16	56	100	16	3	March 1952	152	16	24	16	208	20	32	16	68	84	48	312	160	10	614	24	8	32	100	16	4	March 1953	216	16	24	16	272	20	64	16	100	160	48	428	160	10	806	24	8	32	100	16	5	March 1954	288	24	24 -	16	352	20	64	16	100	286	48	440	160	10	944	24	8	32	- 100	160	Note. * One of these Light Bomber Squadrons (8 U.E.) ist The A.O.P. is temporarily established at 21 U.E.
Fighter Command						Transport Command			Home Corn-mand	B.A.F.C						M.E.A.F.								F.E.A.F.									L.R. Intruder	S.R. Day (Regular)	S.R. Day (R. Aux. A.F.)	A.O.P.	Total Fighter Command	L.R. Transport	M.R. Transport	Total Transport Command	A.O.P. Home Command	Light Bomber	Fighter/Photo. Recce.	Day Fighter/G.A.	A.O.P.	Total B.A.F.O.	Light Bomber	Fighter Recce.	Day Fighter/G.A.	N.F./A11 Weather	L.R. Photo. Recce.	G.R. Landplane	M.R. Transport	A.O.P.	Total M.E.A.F.	Light Bomber	Day Fighter/F.R./G.A.	L.R. Photo. Recce.	Flying Boat	MR. Transport	Met.	A.O.P.	Total F.E.A.F.	Grand Total R.A.F.	32	208	160	10	466	56	24	80	100	16	16	80	10	122	16*	16	80	8	12	16	40	10	198	8	64	8	15	24	4	St	128	1,344	40	248	160	10	522	40	16	56	100	16	16	144	10	186	16	16	80	16	16	16	40	10	210	8	64	8	5	24	4	5	118	1,452	48	312	160	10	614	24	8	32	100	16	16	208	10	250	16	16	80	16	16	16	40	10	210	8	64	8	5	24	4	5	118	1,600	48	428	160	10	806	24	8	32	100	16	16	224	10 -	266	24	16	80	16	16	8	40	10	210	8	64	8	5	24	4	5	118	1,904	48	440	160	10	944	24	8	32	100	160	16	256	10	442	64	16	192	16	16	8	40 j	10	362	8	64	8	5	24	4	5	118	2,450Note. * One of these Light Bomber Squadrons (8 U.E.) is temporarily detached to F.A.E.F.t The A.O.P. is temporarily established at 21 U.E. for the duration of the present emergency.
Fighter Command						Transport Command			Home Coffi-mand	B.A.F.C			. 1       .			M.E.A.F.								F.E.A.F.									L.R. Intruder	S.R. Day (Regular)	S.R. Day (R. Aux. A.F.)	A.O.P.	Total Fighter Command	L.R. Transport	M.R. Transport	Total Transport Command	A.O.P. Home Command	Light Bomber	Fighter/Photo. Recce.	Day Fighter/G.A.	A.O.P.	Total B.A.F.O.	Light Bomber	Fighter Recce.	Day Fighter/G.A.	N.F./A11 Weather	L.R. Photo. Recce.	G.R. Landplane	M.R. Transport	A.O.P.	Total M.E.A.F.	Light Bomber	Day Fighter/F.R./G.A.	L.R. Photo. Recce.	Flying Boat	M.R. Transport	Met.	A.O.P.	Total F.E.A.F.	Grand Total R.A.F.	32	208	160	10	466	56	24	80	100	16	16	80	10	122	16*	16	80	8	12	16	40	10	198	8	64	8	15	24	4	5t	128	1,344	40	248	160	10	522	40	16	56	100	16	16	144	10	186	16	16	80	16	16	16	40	10	210	8	64	8	5	24	4	5	118	1,452	48	312	160	10	614	24	8	32	100	16	16	208	10	250	16	16	80	16	16	16	40	10	210	8	64	8	5	24	4	5	118	1,600	48	428	160	10	806	24	8	32	100	16	16	224	10 -	266	24	16	80	16	16	8	40	10	210	8	64	8	5	24	4	5	118	1,904	48	440	160	10	944	24	8	32	100	160	16	256	10	442	64	16	192	16	16	8	40	10	362	8	64	8	5	24	4	5	118	2,450Note. * One of these Light Bomber Squadrons (8 U.E.) is temporarily detached to F.A.E.F.t The A.O.P. is temporarily established at 21 U.E. for the duration of the present emergency.

Admiralty Hard CoreWorks    ......ProductionR. and D.TotalWar Office-Hard CoreWorks    ......ProductionTotalAir Ministry Hard CoreWorks    ......ProductionTotalService Departments Hard CoreWorks    ......ProductionR. and D. (Adm.)TotalMinistry of Defence ...Ministry of Supply ...Civil DefenceTotalANNEX IVAnalysis of Cost of Three-year Programme				Total	3 year1950-51	1951-52	3952-53	1953-54	1951-54	increase m.	 m.	 m.	 m.	 m.	110-55	128-5	125-5	126-0	380-0	48-359-52	13-7	14-0	420	420	13-4462-36	133-7	143-4	160-3	437-2	250-3210-57	13-8	12-9	33-8	38-5	6-79193-00	289-7	295-8	312-2	897-7	318-70212-02	256-5	256-5	256-5	769-5	133-4429 16	31-5	31-5	33 0	960	8-5257-82	148-1	394-9	201-5	544-5	371-0429900 436-3 482-9 493-0 3,430 0 51300318-43 355-826-57 42-278-00 354 0223-00 352 0368-7 383-840-3 36-23790 2490388-0 4670506-3 35303338-7 38-99582-0 348-003,207-0 538 00443-00	540-8	550-7	564-3	1.655-8	332-8065-25	87-4	85-8	83-5	256-7	60-95398-38	435-8	537-3	630-6	3,563-7   .	969-3630-57	13-8	32-9	31-8	38-5	6-79715-00	3,077-8	3,366-7	3,270-2	3,514-7	1,369-700-82	4-5	30	20	9-5	7 0465 00	850	89-0	91 0	265-0	70-00	20-0	300	40 0	900	90 00780-82	3,187-3	3,288-7	1,403-2	3,879-2	1,536-74


</content>
</cab>
