<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/54/10 images: 121-133</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HE DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cc(74) 10thConclusionsCOPY no cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onWEDNESDAY  10 APRIL  1974at 10. 45 am present the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon James Callaghan mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth Affairs (Items 4, 5 &amp; 6)The Rt Hon Roy Jenkins mp secretary of State for the home department (Items 1-3)The Rt Hon Anthony Crosland mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Shirley Williams mp secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection the Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon William Ross mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-jones lord chancellor the Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Barbara Castle mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp secretary of State for Education and science the Rt Hon John Morris QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Harold Lever mp chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the.Rt Hon Lord shepherd lord Privy Seal
uTHE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Samuel Silkin QC mp attorney General (Items 1 and 2)The Rt Hon Judith Hart mp minister of Overseas Development(Item 3)The Rt Hon Robert Mellish mp parliamentary Secretary, treasury mr Joel Barriett mp chief Secretary, Treasury(Item 3)The Rt Hon Ronald King Murray QC mp lord Advocate  (Items 1 and 2)The Rt Hon Edmund Dell mp paymaster General(Items 4 and 5)Mr Roy Hattersley mp minister of State for Foreign and commonwealth Affairs  (Item 3)Mr Gavin Strang mp parliamentary Under-Secretary of State,Department of Energy (Items 3-6)secretariat sir John hunt mr H F 1 smith mr P benner mr J A hamilton mr K R StoweMr H F Ellis -Rees   (Item 3)Mr R L Baxter (Item 2)contents item subject. BUILDING SOCIETIES2. REPEAL OF THE INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS ACT3. PUBLIC EXPENDITURE 1975-76 to 1978-79.4. NATIONAL INSURANCE BILL5, SOCIAL SECURITY ACT 1973: INTERIM ACTION6. CHILE(Item 6)(Items 1, 4 and 5)(Items 2 and 3)(Items 4 and 5)Page125789
1. The Cabinet resumed their discussion of building societies and mortgage finance.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE ENVIRONMENT said that,despite the somewhat misleading reports which had appeared in that morning^ Press, the Council of the Building Societies Association(BSA) had given a sympathetic reception to the proposals for aGovernment loan which he had described to the Cabinet at their meeting the previous day.    There were, however, a few points on which the Council wished for clarification ;and he would bemeeting their representatives for this purpose later in the day.Before that meeting he proposed to make a short holding statement in the House of Commons.    He had little; doubt that, followingclarification of the outstanding points, the BSA Council would accept the Governments proposals at their next meeting on19th April.The Cabinet -Took note of the statement by the Secretary of Statefor the Environment.1
3PEAL OF THEINDUSTRIALRELATIONS ACT2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Employment (C(74) 25) on the legislation to repeal theIndustrial Relations Act.previous reference:CC(74) 6thConclusions,Minute 2THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said that had discussions with the Trades Union Congress (TUC) and the confederation of british Industry (CBI) about his legislative proposals had now taken place, and difficulties arose on 3 points.First, as regards picketing, the proposal to allow the stopping of vehicles had aroused much controversy.    The TUC weresuspicious of his proposal to give the Government the power tomake regulations or a code of practice.    The difficulty could notbe resolved in the time available.    He proposed, therefore, to confine his Bill to a restoration of the right to peaceful picketingas laid down in the 1906 Act, but without the picketing of homes,and to leave the whole question of stopping vehicles to be dealtwith under a subsequent Bill.    In his speech on the Second Readinghe would express the dissatisfaction of the Government with thepresent legal position and promise to consider further whatamendments should be introduced.    As regards the closed shop,the TUC were opposed to any provision for safeguards for theindividual against arbitrary expulsion or exclusion from unionmembership.    Nevertheless ha was sure that there would be pressure in Parliament for some such safeguards, and he proposedto include a clause in the Bill providing for a right of complaint,on the lines proposed by the Donovan Commission.    Complaintswould be heard by a special tribunal consisting of a legalchairman and 2 members nominated by the TUC.    The tribunal would be able to award compensation but not to order reinstate-ment.    In order to meet part of the TUC objections he would propose to limit the exercise of the right to cases where an employee had been dismissed or given notice of dismissal as aresult of his loss of union membership.    He had told the TUCthat unless some such clause were included in the Bill theOpposition could be expected to move an amendment which theywould find less acceptable.    Thirdly, as regards the transitional provisions for cases before the National Industrial RelationsCourt (NIRC), he had accepted the Lord Chancellors advice thatit would not be defensible to extinguish or modify existing rightsof action under the 1971 Act when the Repeal Bill came intoforce; the most that could be done was to provide that in casesstarted in the NIRC after the publication of the Repeal Bill and still unfinished when the Bill took effect the plaintiffs rights would be automatically extinguished, but cases started before thatdate would be transferred to the High Court or the Court of Session,It was unfortunate that this would provide no remedy against the 47, 000 compensation award against the Amalgamated Union of engineering Workers (AUEW), but he did not think that any betterarrangement could be devised.    He invited the Cabinet to agreethat the Bill should be introduced with the modifications he had proposed. 0
The following points were made in discussion:-a. Picketing.   Any provision to change the law onpicketing, particularly as regards the obstruction ofthe highway, would have to be discussed in detail withthe Police Federation; for this and other reasons itwould be better if the statement to be made on the SecondReading by the Secretary of State for Employment were to omit any specific reference to the stopping of vehicles.b. Safeguards for Individuals.    It was argued that although an individual might suffer in other ways from hisexpulsion or exclusion from a trade union, a right of complaint against the denial of the right to work would remove  the worst possibilities of injustice.    Althoughideally it would be desirable for ithe tribunal to be able to order a union to reinstate a member, this would bedifficult to enforce in practice;  the tribunal might however be authorised to reduce the compensation where the memberwas re-admitted.    For the sake of natural justice the rightof complaint should cover the denial to the individual of areasonable opportunity to argue his case to the union.    Itwould be worth considering also whether the provisions should cover professional associations such as the british medical Association and the Law Society.c. Transitional provisions for NIRC cases.    It waspointed out that the award against the AUEW could lead to astrike and that the case of General Aviation Services versusthe Transport and General Workers Union could result incompensation of more than  1 million being awarded againstthe union,    It was suggested that the Repeal Bill shouldhave retrospective effect from the date of the announcement ofthe Governments intentions in The Queen&apos;s Speech; but itwas pointed out that this would not affect the troublesomecases which had been mentioned, all of which were alreadybefore the NIRC.    A provision to qualify the right to continuean existing action had been considered but if the effect wouldbe to eliminate the cause of the action such a provision would be a sham.    It was argued that there should be ageneral amnesty for NIRC cases or, failing this, a provisionsetting a limit to the damages that could be awarded; this could be introduced by a backbench amendment and if itwere defeated the Government could at least claim credit for having supported it.    On the other hand it was argued that such a provision in civil cases was opsa to serious objections of principle that did not apply to a criminalamnesty, since it extinguished the rights of private
individuals or bodies.    Such a measure would encounterstrong opposition in Parliament.    There might be less objection to a measure by which liabilities under the 1971Act would be taken over by the Government, but since this amendment would i,nvolve public expenditure it could not beintroduced except by the Government.    Any of theseproposals could have repercussions on the surcharging ofCouncillors under the previous Governments housing finance Act.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the Secretary of State for Employment should introduce amending legislation on the lines proposed in his memorandum (C(74) 25).    As regards picketing, he should indicate in his speech on the Second Reading that the Governmentwas considering further legislation, and should clear the wording of his statement with the Home Secretary.    On safeguards for individuals the Cabinet agreed that the right of complaint shouldbe confined to cases involving loss of employment.    As regardsthe transitional provision for cases before the NIRC, the cabinet agreed that the legislation should take the form proposed by theSecretary of State for Employment, but the Lord Chancellor, theSecretary of State for Employment and the Law Officers should look further into the suggestions that had been raised in discussion and report back to the Cabinet.    Their report might take the formof a series of alternative courses of action, showing theadvantages and objections to each, and the possible repercussions on the Housing Finance Act.    It might also help to clear the airif they would examine the rights and wrongs of a recent case inwhich the NIRC had sequestered money that was in the possessionof a local authority.The Cabinet -1.      Took note with approval of the summing upof their discussion by the Prime Minister.2.      Invited the Secretary of State for employment to proceed with the preparation of a Bill on the lines which he had proposed.3.      Invited the Lord Chancellor, the Secretary ofState for Employment and the Law Officers to lookfurther into the possible transitional provisions forNIRC cases and to report back to the Cabinet.4
3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (C(74) 23) on the procedure for determiningpublic expenditure programmes for the years 1975-76 to 1978-79.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that it was now necessary to decide how to settle the public expenditure programmes for 1975-76 to 1978-79.    The issue for immediate decision wasprocedure.    It was usual to start from the basis of existing policies costed in the annual Public Expenditure Survey; but theGovernment would not wish to rely on the policies of their predecessors, who had in any case admitted that the forwardprogrammes of their White Paper on Public Expenditure (Cmnd. 5519)*published in December 1973, had been overtaken by events.    A freshsurvey was therefore required, based on instructions which tookrealistic account of the economic prospect assessed in Annex 1 tohis memorandum.    If the Government were to fail to make animpact on the main problems of inflation and the balance of payments,virtually all their hope s would be frustrated; demand must be managed with the primary view of solving these problems, but without sacrificing a high level of employment.    In his judgment,it would be unwise to base plans for resource allocation on a largerannual increment to national resources than 3 per cent on average;something like half of this increase would need to be devoted to exports and productive investment, leaving only about 1 \ per cent for public expenditure and private consumption together.    the critical question was how far private consumption could be held downwithout leading to demands for greater wage increases.    He concluded that the level of expenditure on goods and services for 1975-76 shouldbe held close to that in 1974-75 in real terms, growing in aggregatethereafter (though not uniformly for all programmes) at about per cent a year, and that comparable stringency should be appliedto transfer payments.    Certain areas had been identified forspecial treatment: from Defence he hoped to obtain additional savings; expenditure on Northern Ireland, nationalised industryinvestment, housing and infrastructure for offshore oil mightdemand increases above the norm.    But he wished to emphasise that the procedure he proposed implied no final judgment on thelevel of programmes.    At this stage he sought agreement only tothe method of approach and the working assumptions on whichofficials should report, as a basis on which the Cabinet could take decisions on the priorities, policies and programmes.    Theeconomic prognosis might well need to be changed in the light of the studies which were now in hand; but even a higher rate of increasein gross domestic product (GDP) would leave public expenditure programmes under pressure.    If the Cabinet were now to endorse the method of proceeding outlined in Annexes 2 and 3 to his memorandum, he would arrange to present the report by officialstogether with a further assessment of the medium term economicprospect.
In discussion, the need was urged for a broader and deeperconsideration of the Governments economic strategy before decisions were taken on the size and content of public expenditure programmes.    It would be cause for concern if under a LabourAdministration the needs of public expenditure were to be subordinated to the demands of private consumption, and endorse-ment of the procedural framework proposed in C(74) 23 should notbe allowed to lead on to the formulation of programmes and priorities which were at variance with the government s economicphilosophy.    Even within present economic constraints there wasroom for alternative strategies to improve the balance of payments and encourage productive investment, and these should bethoroughly explored before the Cabinet was asked to reach decisions on particular programmes.    Nor should methodology inhibit thediscussion of spending priorities: Ministers in charge of majorprogrammes should have discretion to reallocate expenditure between the main sectors.    It was also open to question whethercertain types of transfer payment, for example on food subsidies,represented a true addition to public expenditure; and different methods of providing incentives to industry could have a widelyvarying effect on public expenditure programmes.    This suggestedthat the definition of public expenditure needed further analysis.The Government should also bear in mind the expectations whichhad been aroused by the published programmes of their predecessors; in particular, if public expenditure in 1975-76 wasto be held in real terms to the level of 1974-75, it could have amost prejudicial effect on social programmes of critical importance.On the other hand, it was argued that some working basis must be proposed, and it was preferable to err on the side of prudence;even an annual rate of growth of 3 per cent was higher than theaverage over the last twenty years.    Moreover, public expenditure programmes were generally unsuited to be the vehicle for economicfine-tuning; and even if some degree of reflation were to become necessary later in the year, action on indirect taxes or family allowances would probably be more appropriate than an upwardrevision of public expenditure.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet endorsed the Chancellor of the Exchequer^ proposals about the procedure for carrying forward the review of public expenditure, but on the clear understanding that this implied no commitment to a particular balance between public and privateexpenditure, nor to decisions about particular programmes.Officials should now put work in hand as indicated in the Annexesto C(74) 23.    At the same time the Chancellor of the exchequer would proceed with his examination of the economic outlook in the medium term.    The Cabinet would wish to have a further discussion on the general direction and balance of the Governments economic strategy before considering specific decisions on public expenditure
programmes.    Meanwhile, care should be taken that ministers in their public statements did not commit the Government to anyparticular timing for the second Budget or the public expenditure white Paper.The Cabinet -1.      Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister.2.      Approved C(74) 23, on the understandingindicated by the Prime Minister in his summing up.NATIONAL 4. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SOCIAL SERVICESINSURANCE said that Opposition amendments had been tabled to the NationalBILL Insurance Bill which did not entail six-monthly upratings, as hadbeen expected, but instead required the Secretary of State to layPrevious before Parliament after each annual review of social securityReference: benefits a report setting out her conclusions about the rate ofCC(74) 9th change in the general level of prices and earnings and, in the lightConclusions, of this, the desirability of having more frequent reviews of minute 4 benefits.    Another amendment would require the Secretary ofState to consider the relationship of income tax allowances to social security benefits.    Both these amendments were relativelyharmless, although they would provide opportunity for debate about six-monthly upratings and the tax credit scheme.    She proposed to resist them; but if they were pressed to a division and carried,the Government would not be embarrassed.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthe Cabinet agreed that the amendments should be resisted but that,if carried, they could be accepted with good gracejThe Cabinet -Took note.7
5. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the Secretary ofState for Social Services (C(74) 24 and C(74) 29) about the interimaction which the Government might take on the Social Security Act1973, and about the level of National Insurance contributions afterApril 1975 to finance the basic National Insurance scheme.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SOCIAL SERVICES said that theGovernment had to decide urgently what to do about the social security Act 1973, embodying the previous Administration^ long-term schemes for occupational pensions and a State Reserve Schemefor those workers not covered by-occupational schemes.    The Actcame into operation in April 1975,    The Labour Party had opposed the State Reserve Scheme and were pledged to replace it with abetter scheme which would in particular make improved provisionfor the lower-paid and for women.    She proposed to retain thechangeover to a fully earnings-related contribution to the basicscheme of National Insurance, and the arrangements for preservation of pension rights on change of employment, both of which were in line with the Governments own proposals.    The problem was toknow what to do about the Reserve Scheme.    She had set out threeOptions in her paper (C(74) 24): to continue with it pro tem, tocontinue but change it to a pay-as-you-go scheme and use the income for basic scheme pension provision, or to stop it.    On balance shepreferred to stop it: this could be done by a Revocation order whichwould not require Parliamentary approval.    On this basis she would propose to deal with the problem of the shortfall in basic national insurance contribution income from April 1975 by leaving the employees&apos; contribution at 5j per cent of earnings (in place of thetotal of 6f per cent that would have been payable under the 1973 Act)and increasing the employers&apos; contribution to about 8f per cent,an increase of about 1% per cent on what they would have paid underthe 1973 Act.    These proposals would be acceptable to the TUC andhad the agreement of the Treasury; and she would like to announcethem, together with the decision to stop the Reserve Scheme, assoon as possible - preferably during the debate in the House ofCommons later that day - so that industry could suspend itspreparations for the coming into operation of the 1973 Act.    she would then publish a White Paper in the Summer about theGovernments own proposals.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthere had not been time for the Cabinet to consider fully the verydifficult and controversial issues raised by the Secretary of State&apos;sproposals which were fundamental to the Governments policy on social security.    The operational difficulties of those preparing for 1973 were recognised but the Government could not reasonably be criticised for not rushing into hasty decisions on very complexissues when they had been in office for less than six weeks.   more time was needed for study and consideration and the Cabinet would
Oresume their discussion at a later date.    Meanwhile the Secretaryof State for Social Services could say in the House, if need be, thatthe Government were aware of the need to tell industry and the pension interests what was to happen in April 1975; and undertakethat she would make a statement as soon as possible after the easter recess.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^summing up of their discussion and invited theSecretary of State for Social Services to be guided accordingly.CHILE 6.        The Cabinet resumed their discussion aa policy towardsChile.    Their discussion and the conclusions reached arePrevious recorded separately.Reference:CC(74) 9thConclusions,Minute cabinet Office10 April 19749
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy NO        f u cabinet&quot;MILE. previous reference:C(74) 9thConclusions,/minute confidential annex cc(74) 10th Conclusions, Minute 6Wednesday 10 April 1974 at 10.45 am the FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that he wadue to answer a Parliamentary Question that day on the subject ofarms supplies to Chile and that this provided the occasion forannouncing the decision about the warships which the cabinet had reached at their previous meeting.    The proposed answermade it clear that no new contracts would be entered into butreferred to fulfilling existing ones.    This might be deemed to prejudice the discussion which the Cabinet were due shortly tohave about the arrangements for overhauling Chilean aircraftengines at East Kilbride, and he wondered therefore whether he should defer a definitive reply.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, saidthat the Cabinet agreed that the Foreign and commonwealth secretary should give the answer proposed subject to referring to the completion of the review of &quot;sales11 rather than to &quot;contracts&quot;,thus leaving open for later consideration the question of engineservicing on which the Secretary of State for Industry would becirculating a memorandum.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime minister&apos;s summing up of their discussion.


</content>
</cab>
