<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/25/22 images: 204-211</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet. February 1942.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (42)22nd Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER liOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR GABIMET 22 (42).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Thursday, February 19, 1942, at 6 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary- of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security (Items 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., Minister of Supply (Items 1and 2).The Right Hon. R. S. Hudson, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries (Items 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Lord Woolton,Minister of Food (Items 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Thomas Johnston,M.P., Secretary of State for Scotland(Items 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Ernest Brown, M.P.,Minister of Health (Items 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport (Items 1and 2).The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lan-caster.Sir Edward Bridges, Secretary.[23492]b
WAR CABINET 22 (32).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      The Milling Ratio    ....      ............      ........    1172      Agricultural Prices   ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    1173      Income Tax    ..............................     117Incidence on Weekly Wage Earners.4      Prisoners of War     ....      ....      ....      ....      ....       .... 118The Duke of Aosta.5      Consideration under Lease-Lend ....      ....      ....      ..... 1196      The Par East........      ................... 119
The Mining 1.   The War Cabinet had before them-Ratio\ (i) a Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council(W.P. (42)88) stating that a majority of the lord presidents Committee recommended that the rate ofextraction of flour from wheat should be raised from76 to 85 per cent, at the earliest possible moment;&apos; 7 :   (ii) a Joint Memorandum (W.P. (42) 90) by the Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries, the Secretary of State for1 V Scotland and the Secretary of State for the Home&apos; ,&quot;  &apos; Department pointing out the adverse repercussions such1 &apos; a proposal would have upon the output of one or morer of the following commodities : milk, bacon and eggs.The War Cabinet-&apos; - (1) Decided to postpone a decision on this matter for, say, a&apos; fortnight, during which period the Prime minister would enquire from the United States Government asto the extent to which the shipping capacity available a  , .... to us for the United Kingdom Import Programme wouldbe increased, in the second six months of 1942, out of theUnited States programme of merchant shipbuilding.(2) Invited the Agricultural Ministers to consider, and reportto the Lord Presidents Committee, on the steps whichcould be taken to mitigate the effects on food production-..-.,,;/ in this country of the loss of wheat offals by the raising of the rate of extraction, on the understanding that no part of this loss should fall on the dairy herd.agricultural prices.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 20thConclusions,&quot;Minute 5.)2. The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries said that,thanks to the financial concessions which had been made by theChancellor of the Exchequer, a settlement had now been reached with the National Farmers&apos; Unions of England and Scotland on thebasis of increases in the Price Schedule, which they accepted as complete fulfilment of the Governments pledge. As, however, theSchedule of Price Increases did not include a revised figure, for milk, in regard to which no settlement had yet been reached, it wasnot possible to give a global figure of the total increased prices whichhad been authorised.The Minister of Food emphasised that the fact that agreement had not been reached on milk prices meant that there might be a contingent claim for an additional  1^ millions over and above the milk figure set out in the Schedule submitted to the War Cabinet bythe Lord President of the Council (W.P. (42) 75).The War Cabinet took note of these statements.Income Tax.-Incidence on&apos;Weekly .wage earners.[23492]3.   The War Cabinet had before them (i) a Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and NationalService (W.P. (42)78) as to the effect of the presentsystem of Income Tax collection from the weekly wage-earners, and asking that a Committee be appointed toreport urgently on improvements which could beincluded in the forthcoming budget;(ii) a Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer(W.P. (42) 89) stating that a departmental committeewas already considering the two main points against which criticism had been levelled (i.e., (1) the delay in bringing deductions into force, and (2) that, wheresummer earnings are at a higher level than winterearnings, the high tax corresponding to the summer paywas, in fact, recoverable from the low pay of winter months); and that he hoped to be able to announce some changes in his budget speech.b 2
The Minister of Labour and National Service emphasised the disadvantages which ensued from Income Tax not being paid bydeduction from weekly earnings as they accrued, but six months in arrear. He thought that the sense of injustice which resulted fromthe present- system was exercising a retarding influence on production.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that 4^ million wage-earners were now paying Tax, and that no difficulty had arisen inregard to 4 million workers. The only troubles which had arisenwere in connection with (a) Income Tax payable by married women who had gone into employment and whose earnings were reckonedwith their husbands&apos; earnings for Tax purposes; (6) half a millionwage-earners whose earnings were of a seasonal nature and werehigher in summer than in winter, with the result that higherdeductions were made in winter from wages which were at a lower level. He hoped to meet this by an equalisation of deductionsthroughout the year. He would be happy to go into the matter withthe Minister.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that hewould be glad to go into the matter, although he rather doubted whether the difficulties could be. resolved by a mere adjustmentwithin the existing system.The War Cabinet , (1) Took note that the Chancellor of the Exchequer would discuss this matter further with the Minister of Labourand National Service.(2) Asked that any outstanding points should be referred for settlement to the Lord President of the Council.Prisoners of 4.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that a^Tar. telegram had been received from the Minister of State saying thatThe Duke of the Duke of Aosta was suffering from acute tuberculosis. UnderAosta. the Prisoners of War Convention, prisoners who were seriously illcould be repatriated without regard to rank or the relative numbersexchanged. At the present time negotiations were proceeding withthe Italian Government for an exchange of severely woundedprisoners. So far, however, no such prisoners had been exchanged.If we were to repatriate the Duke of Aosta at once, it might therefore be argued that we were showing undue discrimination inhis favour on account of his position. On the other hand, if the duke of Aosta died while a prisoner in our hands, advantage mightbe taken of the fact by enemy propaganda. The Minister of Statethought that an offer of repatriation should at once be made.The War Cabinet- (1) Decided that it was inexpedient to arrange for the repatria-tion to Italy of the Duke of Aosta, except as part of some general arrangement.(2) Asked that arrangements should be made for a suitableannouncement with a view to discounting the effects which might follow if the Duke died, while a prisoner of war, without any previous indication of his illness.
ConsiderationunderLease-Lend.(previous reference:.W.M. (42) 20thConclusions,Minute 4.)119W.M. 22 (12).5. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that approval had now been obtained to the signature of the Lease-Lend Agreementfrom all the Dominions except Canada, whose assent was expectedshortly. A simultaneous announcement should be arranged with theUnited States Government, and it seemed appropriate that thePrime Minister should make a statement on the matter in the house on Tuesday, the 24th February.The War Cabinet agreed as follows : -fSubject to the approval of the Canadian Government being obtained, the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the foreign secretary and the Dominions Secretary were authorised tosettle, in consultation, the form of the announcement, andto arrange with the United States Government for a simultaneous announcement to be made, if possible on tuesday, the 24th February.The Far East.(previous reference:W.M. (42) 21stConclusions,Minute 2.)6. The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster made a short statement about his tenure of office as Resident Minister. he explained that he was circulating a written report to the WarCabinet (W.P. (42) 92).A short discussion ensued.The Prime Minister gave instructions that the Chancellor ofthe Duchy should be furnished with full information as to the courseof events in Malaya since his departure.Great George Street, S.W. 1,February 19, 1942.




</content>
</cab>
