<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/79/0 images: 6-11</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
AiJffi   \J11&apos;-:) i p .This Document is the Pro  rtL2L &apos; chSq^Ic MafotVs Government &quot;Weights &amp; Measures jLeather Measurement)^Mllj, ^ ^jCAB/^v Ho t e  from the Bp ay d o g gr age/la Circulate to my colleagues a draft Bill to amend ^^il^HMiW^^^^1&apos;^ 81ld Measures Acts in relation to instruments for measuring leather &quot;by superficial area.The following &quot;brief note explains the position, and 1 should foe glad to receive sanction for the introduction of the Bui into Parliament.A.G. GKDDE3.5th Ma?, 1919.Erplana tory Ifo te.During recent, years, light leather hae &quot;been sold by superficial area instead of as formerly by weight or skin and the increasing employment of various types of leather measuring instruments&quot;led to a demand from the trade that   . their use should be legalised by the Board of Trade and that approved types should be governed by regulations slmil-ar to those in force with regard to weighing instruments.Millions of pounds worth of leather are sold annually (estimated at 400 million feet at an average price? of ls/Sd. per square foot).Buyers and&apos;seHers of leather are united in the request for legislation,A renewed demand for legalisation of such instruments was made by the federation of the Light Leather Trades of the United Kingdom and in January 1915 the Board received a joint Deputation from the federation of Light Leather Trades, the United Tanners&apos; federation and the Boot and Shoe Trades1 federation,    At this meeting it was explained that it might not be possible to legislate at that time, but the Department agreed to have a draft Bill prepared.    This was done and approved by the Trade federations interested.   In December 1915 also trie London Count;/ Council requested the Board to give favourable consideration to the question of bringing leather measuring instruments within the purview of the Weights and Measures Acts.At present there is no public control orer   these machine/ No authority has the power to prevent the use of undesirable types of machine or to test the accuracy of machines in use. -
Numerous disputes and difficulties are said to arise between buyers and sellers of leather in regard to the accuracy of the measurement of the skins sold, and the leather trade hopes that if leather measurements and measuring instruments were recognised &quot;by law and controlled in somewhat the seme way as ordinary weights, measures and weighing instruments are bohtroiled xinder tile Weights and Measures Acts, these diffi-difficulties might be lessened.2!he object of the draft Bill therefore is:-(a) by moral effect to induce the majority of those traders who use instruments for the me asur em en t of leather by superficial, area to adopt instruments of &amp; pattern certified by the&apos;Board of ^rade; and(b) to enact that such instruments of such pattern shall do subject in the same way as weighing machines to the provisions of the Weights end Assures Acts, 1878 to1904.   as.and&apos;it Is hoped that in the result buyers would obtain subs* tantially correct measure when buying by superficial area as they secure correct weight whew, buying by weight.k These Acts subject weighing machines used for trade to compulsory verification and stamping, and to inspection from time to time, by an inspector of weights and measures.(Z)
[9 Geo. 5.]  Weights and Measures [Leather Measurement).D RIf TOF AB I L LTOAmend the Weights and Measures Acts, 1878 to 1904, a.d. i9i9. in relation to instruments for measuring leather  by superficial areaf^BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5       1. (1) The powers and duties of the Board of Trade under Instrumentssection six of the Weights and Measures Act, 1904, in relation [^&quot;2^.to certificates of suitability for use of certain appliances, shall bysuperficiaextend to instruments for measuring the superficial area of area&quot; leather %w faade^ and patterns thereof, and that section shall 10 have effect accordingly.(2) The powers of the Board under section five of the aforementioned Act to make regulations with respect to measuring instruments shall include power (a) to make the like regulations with respect to any instru-15 ments of a pattern certified by the Board of Tradein pursuance of the powers conferred by this Act; and(b) to make regulations for applying to any instrument ofa pattern so certified any of the provisions of the 20 Weights and Measures Acts, 1878 to 1904, withrespect to weighing machines, weighing instruments, or measuring instruments ; and(c) to make general regulations for carrying into effect theprovisions of those Acts and this Act in relation to 25 instruments of a pattern so certified.102-1
2      Weights and Measures [Leather Measurement),   [9 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1919. 2. (1) This Act may be cited as the Weights and Measures Citation, (Leather Measurement) Act, 1919, and shall be construed as construction, one with the Weights and Measures Acts, 1878 to 1904; and moncemcnt those ^c^s an(* this Act may be cited together as the Weights and Measures Acts, 1878 to 1919. 5(2) This Act shall come into operation on the [first day of * January nineteen hundred and twenty].&apos;

Weights and Measures (leather Measurement).DEAF TOF AB   I   L   LTo amend the Weights and Measures Acts, 1878 to 1901, in relation to instruments for measuring1 leather [by superficial area].LXXXIX.  (1.)im April 11)11).102-1

</content>
</cab>
