<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/79/0 images: 127-128</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-^- Lvvl/fM OUlUVA k&quot;0-*-^uw, rilLs...P^c&apos;i!!I^lt is the Property of $Jjj^Brnar)? 1 *jVtaj8Sty&apos;s Government.)  .With reference to Paper G,T, 6642 I circulate     1 herewith a memorandum relative to tho memorandum hy Mr. -ten Chamberlain&apos;on the.subject of the Oilfields of:   W.H.L,     ; &apos; 6.V.19.PSTROLSUil EXECUTIVE,1 consider that it would be undesirable and unwise to refuse at this stage to participate with the Australian-Government.    The matter has been under discussion with -Mr, Eugh.es and Sir Joseph Cook for many months and a meeting was held on 12th December at which they were present and at which after full consideration of the question and of Lord Harccurt*s Committee1s views there on it was agreed to recommend to the Cabinet that His MajestyJs Government: should co-operateo    It is quite true that the Treasury representatives emphasised that the Chancell$r!3 sanction must be obtained but the general sense of the meeting was favourable, to the proposal.    An outline scheme has been drafted and a copy has been furnished unofficially to the Treasury but it is clear that more detailed arrangements cannot be worked out with the Australian Government until approval in principle has been givenvI fully appreciate the Chancellor Is difficulties in providing for the heavy liabilities with which he is faced for all services, but I would urge that It would bo in the highest degree regrettable if we were to decline to co-operate in this undertaking because we were not prepared to put up the comparatively modest sum of  50,000*      Such a step would have an unfortunate, effect, not merely on
the OcanmoiiweaHhi Government, but on the Australian public: (who already know of the proposals through their premature publication in tho Australian press).I am c(anfident that the scheme, which has now beon. approved by the Admiralty and the Colonial Office, will be of Imperial benefit far outweighing the &apos;actual expenditure to which we would be committed,,

</content>
</cab>
