<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/79/0 images: 180-184</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
WAB CABINET.DOGS1 PROTECTION BILL.1 j * , &apos;&quot; .. ....As Chairman of tue national Health Insurance Joint Committee I am responsible for the Medical Research Committee: the body which is financed from the Exchequer for the carrying on of Medical Reoearoh throughout the United Kingdom, and whoae  . adnirable work, now well-known throughout Efurope, has been of immeasurable value throughout the war.    It speaks with unrivalled scientific authority and weight.This important body has sent to me the attached Memorandum as to the irreparable mischief to Medical Research that must result unless the Government will take effective steps to prevent the passing of the Dogs&apos; Protection Bill which will prohibit experiments of various kinds that nre essential to investigation. They request that the Government may be moved to take the requisite stops accordingly.I agree fully with the Committee and would urge that the War Cabinet should cause an announcement to be made of their objections to the Bill and of their determination to ask Parliament to reject it.    If this were done I would pubjieh the medical Research Committee Memorandum as a White Paper.* WALDORF ASTOR. . fI cordially support the above.0. ADDISON. *12th Kay, 1919.
National Health Insurance.MEMORANDUM UPON THE DOGS  PROTECTION BILL BY THEMEDICAL RESEARCH COMMITTEE.To the Chairman of the National Health Insurance Joint Committee.2nd May, 1919.Sir,(1) The Medical Eesearch Committee conceive it to be their duty to submit to you the following observations upon the Dogs Protection Bill which is now before Parlia-ment. The Committee are charged with the responsibility of applying the Medical Research Fund constituted under the National Insurance Act for the promotion of medical research throughout the United Kingdom. It is their duty to use the Fund so as most effectively to assist the increase of that knowledge by which alone can be secured the sure maintenance of health and the diminution of disease and suffering in human beings and, no less, in animals.It is the considered and unanimous judgment of the Committee that the proposals of the Dogs Protection Bill now under discussion would place an insuperable and perma-nent barrier across some of the chief paths of progress in this work.(2) It is not relevant here to discuss the general moral question of using animals or taking animal life for experiment or for other human uses or pleasures. The Com-mittee are now only concerned to show the special reasons which make it necessary that dogs should not be excluded from that special service to mankind in which animals have so greatly aided the advancement of medical science.(3) It is beyond dispute that the present-day science and art of the physician and surgeon have been founded in large part upon the experimental use of dogs in the past. It has been by the use of dogs that the chief foundations of our knowledge of the processes of digestion, the circulation of lymph, the work of the heart, and the circulation of the blood have been laid. Large and essential parts of our knowledge of the science of feeding are based upon the results of trials made in the feeding of dogs. The work of the surgeon, whether upon the brain and spinal cord, or upon the intestine, or upon the chest, has been made possible by experiments upon dogs. Methods of life-saving, as by the transfusion of blood or in the resuscitation of the drowned, have been worked out chiefly by trials with dogs. Important parts of our knowledge of anaesthetics and their safe adminis-tration, and of the actions of many kinds of drugs, have been gained by the experimental use of dogs.(4) Many reasons have made it necessary, and will always make it necessary, to use dogs instead of other animals for some of this experimental work. Considerations of size are important, and in this respect the only animals giving a practicable alternative are the sheep, the pig, the goat, or the ape. The dog, unlike these animals; can be kept completely healthy and comfortable in the laboratory, and in near association with man. He is not afraid of close and friendly observation. His long domestication has assimilated his natural diet to that of man. Many of his bodily structures provide the nearest approximation among other available animals to those of man. The study of diet, and the chemical study of the excreta can be carried out readily in the dog, and the results of these are in the main directly applicable to the case of the man or of the child. The actions of drugs and of anaesthetics are in the main identical for the dog and the man.It might indeed be urged that owing to these reasons in favour of the use of dogs, and on the general humane grounds of avoiding discomfort to animals when in captivity, or when receiving an anaesthetic for painless experiment, or when under observation, the dog&apos;s special habituation to man makes it more, rather than less, desirable to prefer the use of the dog to that of wild or less domesticated animals when the nature of the experiment requires or allows it. Experimental work with animals can, however, in most instances attain its aims in the acquisition of new knowledge by the use of smaller animals, and actually the dog is used in a very small minority among other animals.(B 14746) Wt. 5121-g 6985  100  5/19  H&amp;s
For the better and more rapid diminution of suffering and disease, it is plain that the selection of the animal most fitted for the special purpose in view should be left to the discretion and skilled knowledge of the worker in medical science.(5) The Committee think it their duty to explain the nature of the experiments upon dogs which, as it happens, are now being or have recently been supported on their recommendation by grants from the Medical Research Fund. The work now to be men-tioned would necessarily be abandoned if the proposals of the Dogs Protection Bill should be adopted by Parliament, and it would pass to workers in other countries.(a) Rickets is a disorder of growth in infants leading to deformation of the bones(seen, for instance, in &quot; bandy-legs &quot;), and to other grave secondary results. It is very common in our large cities, and it is known indeed on the Continent as the &quot; English disease.&quot; It is also found among confined animals at the Zoological Gardens, for instance, and sometimes among foxhound puppies. Its causation has never been satisfactorily determined, but has been hitherto attributed uncertainly to errors of diet or to improper environment.During the past three years a large number of experiments upon young dogs have been made with the support of the Committee. The dogs, though receiving abundant food, have been deprived of one or other particular con-stituent of diet. It has been discovered by this work for the first time that, in the absence of a certain type of constituent hardly appreciable in amount, and with food otherwise abundant, typical &quot; rickets &quot; may be produced in a puppy, corresponding exactly with that found in thousands of our infants. The disorder when pronounced can, moreover, be cured completely by the restoration of the missing constituent of the diet, and a discovery of this kind must be of the utmost value in preventing rickets among human infants.The disorder itself in the puppy, as in the child, is quite painless. Each feeding experiment has been done in a place licensed and inspected by the Home Office, under Home Office licence, and with the additional Certificate A -f E, allowing anaesthetics to be dispensed with. Each has appeared in the annual Home Office returns under that heading, and these experiments have sometimes been quoted accordingly with technical but misleading accuracy as experiments, or, even as &quot; vivisections,&quot; done without anaesthetics.The supporters of the Dogs Protection Bill would forbid any further progress in this work.(b) Disorders of the teeth. A wholly unexpected outcome of the experiments justdescribed has been to show that the absence of a particular and minute factor from the diet may prevent the formation of the hard enamel covering of the teeth as these are being developed, and that deficiency of this factor at the time of tooth formation (as during weaning) causes the enamel to be thin and imperfect. There can be no doubt that this is a piece of knowledge fundamental in its importance for the prevention of that undue subsequent decay of the teeth which is one of the gravest and commonest physical defects among people of the United Kingdom and one of the most fertile causes of secondary illness. These studies are quite new and are being actively followed up, but they must be abandoned if the Dogs Protection Bill becomes enacted ; it is uncertain whether by the use of other animals further progress can be made even though by the help of the dog the key to the problem seems to have been obtained.(c) The effects of alcohol. For the assistance of the Liquor Control Board the Com-mittee have supported some experiments upon dogs in which the intoxicating actions of alcohol have been studied, as well as the rate of disappearance from the blood of alcohol taken into the system under different conditions, as when different dilutions are used, or different forms of beverage, or various :. foods taken, and so on.   These experiments have not been painful to thedogs used. In most cases small samples of blood have been taken for examination at different times by a tiny cut made at the edge oi the ear. All have been returned as experiments upon dogs done without anaesthetics. The results obtained have been regarded by the Liquor Control Board as useful to them in their work, and they have incidentally given much new and valuable knowledge to guide the medicinal uses of alcohol in man.(d) The study of diseases of the heart and circulation, Dr. Thomas Lewis, in thewhole-time service of the Committee, has given in a letter published in The Times of the 7th April, 1919, the reasons for saying that our knowledge
of the heart and -blood circulation in man has been grounded in the results of experiments upon the dog. These results have been and are now being applied on behalf of the Committee by Dr. Lewis for the assistance of the Army Medical Service and of the Ministry of Pensions, and no fresh experi-ments upon dogs have recently been made. The chief progress in this part of medicine has by universal admission been made in this country, and probably the greater part of the necessary experimental work with dogs has been finally done. But new experiments must be expected to be necessary from time to time for the solution of accessory problems and the Committee would view with dismay any legislation blocking further advances in this subject, in which such lasting benefits to mankind have been brought already &quot;. by experiments upon dogs.It should be added here that much of the work which was done to aid the saving of life among the seriously wounded during the war, by the intro-duction of improved methods of blood transfusion and of other modes of treatment in the dangerous states of wound shock, was made easy or possible only by experiments upon dogs.(e) Tetany in children. The experiments so far named have all been painless or have at the most only involved a painless death. The Committee would draw attention, however, to another class of experiment of which some examples have been recently performed, with their support, upon dogs. Of all rickety children in our great cities many (in Glasgow about one-third) suffer from a condition of localised muscular cramps known as tetany. These fixations of the muscles are generally painless, and tetany is not to be confused with the painful cramps of tetanus (lockjaw); but the state of tetany is disfiguring and to a human subject distressing. By a surgical operation made painless by anaesthetics, a certain small gland (the parathyroid) can be removed from the neck of a dog. The healing of the small skin wound after the operation is obviously painless enough to make no change in the comfort or usual spirits of the dog. It has been discovered that the absence of this gland may produce later a condition of the muscles apparently identical with that in tetany. Further experiments in dogs and other animals gave the information that this gland controls the health of the muscles not by nervous influences directly but through control, by way of the blood, of their chemical changes. Know-ledge of this land plainly could not be gained except by such experiments, and without new knowledge of this disorder our treatment of innumerable afflicted children must remain as imperfect and ineffective as it has hitherto been. Closely similar experiments upon another gland in the neck (the thyroid) of dogs and other animals long ago gave us for the first time the means which are now successfully used for curing the idiocy and deformities of &quot; cretin &quot; children in whom the thyroid gland is congenitally absent or deficient.Further progress along this path would be greatly hampered, and might be barred, by the provisions of the Dogs Protection Bill.(6) The Committee are able to speak with knowledge, and in the case of most of their members, with intimate knowledge, of the actual conditions in which experiments upon dogs are performed in this country. They are able to assert confidently that, in the vast majority of experiments upon dogs, out of the few score altogether used annually for the purpose, no pain at all is inflicted; the experiment or the observation is either made wholly under an anaesthetic and death produced without awakening, or the experiment is a feeding experiment as in studies of the kind described above. In the small minority of cases, when for special reasons and under a special certificate recovery after operation is allowed, there is rarely any condition of pain as distinguished from discomfort. The worker in medical science knows too well that pain as such of itself would vitiate the results of an animal experiment by its disturbing influence, even if he had no other reason to use his skill for avoiding it. By the present law he is under bond moreover to destroy the animal painlessly and at once if severe pain that is likely to endure is present, and whether the experiment is complete or not.(7) The Committee are able also to speak with first-hand and intimate knowledge of the great mass of suffering among men, women and children, and among animals, from present disease, which it is the aim of medical science by research to relieve. They cannot do otherwise than raise their protest against what they must deem the inhumanity of placing any hindrances in the way of those working for the diminution of this total volume of human and animal pain.
In their opinion the Dogs Protection Bill now before Parliament would bring serious and, in many directions, fatal hindrance to this work. In an appendix to this Memo-randum they have set out the resolutions of some principal bodies of medical men who have been led to express the same conviction.We are, Sir,Your faithful Servants,GOSCHEN.C. J. BOND. WILLIAM BULLOCH. HENEY HEAD.F. G. HOPKINS. W. B. LEISHMAN.D. NOEL PATON.WALTER M. FLETCHER, Secretary.APPENDIX.The Royal College of Physicians, on the 14th April, 1919, passed the following unanimous resolution : &quot; The Royal College of Physicians of London, in full meeting, hereby records its opinion that the passing into law of the Dogs Protection Bill, now before the House of Commons, will greatly retard the progress of our knowledge with regard to the prevention and treatment of disease.&quot;The Royal College of Surgeons, on the 7th May, 1919, have also passed the following unanimous resolution: &quot; The Council of the Royal College of Surgeons are of opinion that the Dogs Protection Bill, if passed &apos;  into law, will seriously impede the progress of medical science in this country, and they view with grave concern this proposal to prohibit a form of research through which knowledge of great value as regards the causes and treatment of disease has been acquired in the past.&quot;The Royal Society of Medicine,, on the 28th April, 1919, unanimously resolved as follows : &quot; That the Royal Society of Medicine, representing as it does every branch of the medical profession throughout the Empire, and with full knowledge of the grave issues involved, feels bound to place on record its earnest hope that the Dogs Protection Bill will not pass into law, as if enacted it will place this country at a great disadvantage as compared with all other civilised countries, and will practically compel our ablest workers to seek opportunities for preventive and curative research abroad.&quot;At the Special Clinical Meeting of the British Medical Association, held on the 10th April, 1919, the following resolution was passed unanimously at a meeting of several hundred members : &quot; This meeting of the combined sections of Medicine, Pathology and Preventive Medicine of the British Medical Association learns with dismay of the possibility of the passage through the House of Commons of a Bill to prohibit experiments upon dogs.&quot; The anatomical structure and omnivorous habit of the dog, together with the fact that it can be kept in health and comfort under the conditions imposed by laboratory work, render the larger sort the only available subject for experiment in important fields of physiological and pathological investi-gation.&quot; The prohibition of experiments upon dogs would, in the opinion of this meeting, have the deplorable result of hampering the progress of medicine and of rendering Britain alone, among the civilised nations of the world, unable to contribute to progress in a department of medical research in which it has hitherto played a distinguished part.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
