<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/79/0 images: 197-204</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this Document is the Property or H-s Britannic Majestyfs Government BTOMr DIRECTORATE OP HTfflliiaBNCE(Home Off!oo)Roport No, 3, Scotland Houeo, 8.W.I.14th May, 1919.REPORT ON BHVOIitnflONABY ORGANISATIONS IN THE UNITED KINGDOM,(Circulated toy the Home Secretary)TKffl PBACB TSRM3............................Page XTHE) CO-OPKRATIVK MOVEMENT.................. ?   XTHS AWALOAjaTElD 80CISTY OP WOBJ61BR0....... *  2tOTMPLOYMT............................... *   2MAY DAY DEMONSTRATIONS .................... &quot;   3THS FEDERATION OP d!is CHARGED ANDdemobilised sailors AND soldiers....... &quot;   3THS iraPBlIDBKT. LABOUR PARTY.............,. *   4COVENTRY-.................................. *   4MR, RAMSAY mcdonald AND THE 8OOIM1I8Tooiwrwob at AMSTERDAM................ *   5ROBEIRT E1HILIE............................. &quot;mm and cedar paul........................ nC0NSCXOT1OUS OBJECTORS.,.................. *THB CONVICTIONS OP RAMSAY AMD WATSON....... w   6PROSECUTIONS............................... &quot;   7SUMMARYThe principal incident of the week has been the attempt of the &quot;Daily Herald&quot;r working through the Bailors&apos;, Soldiers4 and Airmen^ union, to bring out serving soldiers on the lXth May on the ground that the period of their enlistment had expired. Bvidenoe la in the hands of the Police, showing that the pXot was widespread, that Mr. George LANS BURY had subscribed  80 to the Uhlon funds, and that H.T. MoDONALD, a &quot;Herald11 reportes, intended to go with Eden PAUL, the notorious revolutionary speaker, to Grove Park and other centres, and bring a disorderly demonstration down to Whitehall,    Owing to the effective steps taken by the Military Authorities and to publicity given to the movement in the Press, as well as the action of the Polioe in searching premises and in putting the two ringleaders under observation, the movement collapsed,    What the *DaiXy Herald&quot; of yesterday is pleased to oaXX a &quot;carefully pXanned and oXeverXy exeouted manoeuvre&apos;&apos; has disorganised the Bailors&apos;, SoXdiers&apos; and Airmen&apos;s Union, and Bums, the Secretary, complains that he and his wife and ohiXdren are being boycotted at Romford by the XooaX tradespeople and neighbours.    The &quot;Daily Herald&quot; has been singularXy mild in its comments, probably from fear that their connection with the movement wilX damage its circulation.About 800 Army Servioe Corps men at Battersea, and 150 at OsterXey threatened to &quot;demobilise themselves&quot; on the 12th, but after some persuasion they resumed duty before any disoipXinary action became neoessary.The present warm weather is very favourable to revolutionary propaganda, for fine evenings are the harvest time for the revolutionary agitator.The reports from Coventry are rather disquieting.
PMACE? M.The Socialists complain that the Peace Terms provide only for the disarmament of the enemy, and that unless there is general disarmament on the part if the Allies, the League of Nations will become a faroe.    The general public appears to think the Terms severe but just.    In Birmingham several meetings have been held by the L&amp;fcour Party to   s protest against the Terms as being too severe.    On May 10th there was a demonstration at which Professor Lees-Smith described the Terms as &quot;militaristic, imperialistic, and revengeful&quot;, and urged that Labour should abstain from Government Peace celebrations as a protest;  when Labour came into power they would substitute a clean and just -, Peace.    The meeting was widely advertised, but the &quot;attendance was small,entente which has been formed between. Labour, and..-Co-operators should be carefully watched.-  If rightly handled this movement should have a steadying effect, for the Co-operator is a cautious person and an advocate of&apos; praotical socialism without disorderly revolution. .  It is noteworthy that in Russia Lenin and Trot -sky aro now inclined to fall baok upon the Co-operative movement as the one bright spot, and our own extremists-are inolined-towards, the same opinion.    Co-opetatora have hitherto been distributors rather than prcdaocr^ /&quot;but lately they are said to have bought land and to &apos;be much cenoemed about the question of taxation on excess profits..At the Co-operative demonstration at the Albert Hall on Hay 3rd a few of the audienoe tried to sing &quot;The Bed Flag&quot;, but they had no support from the huge audienoe ofCo-operators/
*Co-operators who had oome from all parts of the Country.m^Mmmm society of wsmub  &apos;.f J.T. who has been little hoard of lately,lectured to 200 men at the A.S.B. Institute at Sheffield on Sunday, May 4th, on MHhe Histdry of Industrial Development&quot;.    Questioned as to now help was Vo he given tt revolutionaries lh Russia and Hungary, he replied that ; nothing oould, he done until a revolution broke out here and was maintained.    How that was to he done he did not know, Wt the first operation would he a general strike.    There %ere people who feared that strikes might leave their families without food, hut he would tell them that onoe a general strike was in operation they would take over oontrc and the millers and bakers would turn out the food for thei It was useless expecting a revolution where no one would get hurt, for there oould he no idea of a *walk-overw.Between 40,000 and 50,000 men and women are reported to be uneagployed(in the Birmingham district, though it is stated that raw material is obtainable, and that there are orders enough to keep the faotories busy on full-time for over twelve months. The oause of the check ia that firms are re-organising, replacing machinery, altering buildings shafting, eto., and in six months&apos; time it is thought that most of the workmen will be employed, Bevoltttlenary propagandists are more aotive than ever, but-their numbers are still small. Heads of firms appear to be optimist^ regarding the future.-......      - MAS/1
(JBngliah)Ity Leeds correspondent reports that in Yorkshire the Ma^ toy demonstratione have left an aftermath&apos;&quot; of reorimination between the various Branches of the Labour Party.   At Bradford the extremists thought the resolutions too slid.     At Huddersfield the demonstration was a small affair.There is unrest in this Sooiety throughout the country.    The chief oeajplaint is that the pensions are too snail and are made an aot of Grace rather than a statutory right.    It Is claimed that widows1 pensions should be increased from 13s. 9&amp;. to 17s. 6d. a week, and that allowances to children should not he reflutted on the death of the father, and that pensions should be increased by 50 per cent with 27s. 6d. minimum for total disablement. The men are determined to continue the agitation until their points are conceded by the Government.Mr. J.R. , H.P. t speaking at Bargoed on May 3rdsaid, &quot;Men are returning from the Artsy angry and dissatisfied&quot;. They were appealing for the ritfot to work, and Parliament had not shown the comaon sense to meet their demands.My Birmingham correspondent reports that the organisation Is int close touoh with the ?&quot;,.abour Party, and that a meeting is to be held in Manchester on June 9th to oonsider the question of admitting Officers as members. In Birmingham the federation is assuming a Soolallst complexion, but in Leeds, at a meeting on May 11th, the Branoh aeoretary vehemently denounced Bolshevism, and an
I.L.P. agitator who tried to start a rival meeting could not obtain an audience ef more than a dtzen.EafrpSergeant Major BIOTiS has again oome inte vpreaia as the organiser of a National Union of ox-Serviee Men em Women in Birmingham.m iEaBB mmAgitators of this Party are carrying on a orusade against the Peaoe Terms as oonduoive tc further wars.   I Australian deportee, Wilson, who has been appointed organiser for the Liverpool district, has a method of ore which appears to appeal to nis audienoes.    He worics him up like a berserker into a paroxysm of raving and soreaiti nevertheless, the extremists in that area oomplain bittei of the lack of enthusiasm shown by the workers, and gaze London and Glasgow with longing eyes.    The fact is that workers are following their recognised official leaders i more than they did a few months ago.The extremists In Manchester have not lost heart. Beoently they held a secret meeting to bring about a general strike in support of the men looked out at Meseri Berwioks, Park Royal, but they are unlikely to succeed.&quot;The Northern Xiight&quot;, the organ of the Barrow extremists, may shortly have to cease publication, as th workers are not buying it.SSMW.        where are disquieting symptoms at Coventry, wheretidea of forming one big Union appears to be more advanotthan in other places.    The Workers&apos; Union, the AmalgamSociety of Engineers, and other Unions have amalgamatedthere, and it has now become a stprm oentre.    The que^
(English) .* 5 *.most aotlvely cliBoueeed ore tho Military Service Aot and the Intervention in Russia % ttie motive in Coventry appears not to be so ouch the dislike of fighting as admiration for thet .    .i ......Soviet Government.    Coventry Is a place where anti-Bolshevik propaganda should be concentrated.In the issue of the &quot;Forward&quot; of May 10th, Mr. Ramsay MACDONAIJ) said that he had formed the impression that Bhgl&amp;nd was becoming unpopular, for after literary outbursts about Uberty and Treaty obligations, we acted inconsistently, and now no nation will trust us.    &apos;Bae blockade has done us moral damage.    As to Bolshevism, Hungary would be a standing example of its failure.   Xt may be a phase in revolution, but not the revolution itself,    Both extremes -Bolsheviks and the old Trade Union leaders - had failed squally.   He said that the Shop Stewards movement has aroused universal interest, and this is borne out by Lenin&apos;s remark to Mr. Arthur HANSOMS, quoted in an earlier report.Besides his activities on the ooal oampaign, where he has made a considerable reputation, Bobert StiXLLVb has been speaking in the oountry as well as in Iiondon on the A &quot;Hands off Russia&quot;, the Co-operative movement, and the Peace Settlement.    In acknowledging the testimonial from the Lanarkshire miners on May 10th, he said that the older he grew the more of a rebel he became, but he denied that he was out for bloody revolution if that could be avoided.mbb mb fflaiB task-Sden Paul and his wife have resigned their membership of the Independent labour Party and the British SocialistParty/
Party beoause they think that tho politioal type of Socialist organisation has outlived. itsa,usefulness, and t the future rests with the Workers1 Committee and the Shop &apos;   Stewards movement.    Their objection to the Independent labour Party is that it is affiliated to the labour Party advocate Parliamentary methods.    !Ihey believe not in demeo but in&quot;communist ergatooracy&quot;.    These two persons are Indefatigable revolutionary propagandists coupled with son ability and untiring energy.    The man, however, appearsM lacking in the courage of his convictions, for when he was put under observation last week, so far from oourting the advertisement of prosecution,&quot; he went ignominiously into hiding.   v&apos;* :&apos;     &apos; hThe recently liberated Conscientious Objectors have not &quot; &apos;fceen successful in their public meetings-.    Their recent meeting in Pins bury Park was &quot;olosed abruptly11 by ex-Army men.    The ooalminers employed at the Vfoltborn Colliery;&apos;V * Durham, refused to work with two C.O.*s, and the mine was stopped for the day, the colliers only resuming work when the.-(Manager promised to get rid of the C.0&apos;s.   The same situationis threatened .at -the-Silkworth Colliery.&quot;... &apos;&apos; -   &quot;   &apos;u &apos; &apos;*&apos;    -ass m&amp;ssms q* i^say miimM-3he London Workers&apos; Committee called a Conference on *J&amp;y 10th to urge industrial action for obtaining the release of Ramsey and the withdrawal of the oharge -against Watsonv !Bie result is not yet known.    On Sunday last a thousand &apos; &quot;people were present at a meeting in Trafalgar Squarecalled with the same object.    Tom MAM and Neil MoLEAN, M.P., were amongst the speakers.    Hie latter advised the Derby men present, that under theirs Army contract they were no longerliable/
B.H.T.liable Tor service with the Colours, and that if he were erne of them he would walk off that night.On May 11th Tom MMl addressed a meeting at Beaumont Hall and made a violent speech again at the Government, the master class, and some Trade Union leaders,    &quot;What we want is the Shop Stewards movement or a Rank and File movement.    The revolution will oome and the young men must do it&apos;1.    It is generally known that Tom MAKtf is paid for his oratory, and his influence has deolined in consequence.Arnold Yates was fined  50 or two months&apos; Imprisonment at Liverpool on tiay 9th for distributing the leaflet &quot;*Eo British Sailors&quot;.    The fine was paid.The Director of Public Proseoutions is applying for prooess for the publication of a poster% &quot;What does Britain stand for?&quot;, and a leaflet, &quot;A Starving Baby&quot;.    He has decided not to prosecute in respeot of the following publications&quot;Starvation and Blockade&quot; &quot;Spectre of Famine&quot;, &quot;Cruoifixion of Europe&quot;, &quot;Famine in Europe&quot;.

</content>
</cab>
