<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/134/0 images: 122-136</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
OCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYT3 GOVERNMENT)C(67) 176 COPY NO.14tli November, 1967CABINETBRITISH EUROPEAN AIRWAYS RE-EQUIPMENTMemorandum by the First Secretary of StateWe have now to decide whether to accede to the request byBritish European Airways (BEA) that they should be allowed to buy theBritish Aircraft Corporation (BAG) 2-11 aircraft in place of the Boeingswhich last year v/e refused thern permission to buy.    The President ofthe Board of Trade in his memorandum C(67) 177 argues that we shouldlet BEA have the BAG 2-11;  in C(67) 178, the Minister of Technologyputs the contrary view.    These memoranda, together with the joint memorandum by officials of the Board of Trade and the Ministry of technology appended to this note, were considered on 13th Novemberby a meeting of the Ministers mainly concerned under my chairmanship.I summarise below the views of that meeting.2.      Some of the considerations are clear-cut -(i) It could have a damaging effect on the morale, and hence the productivity, of BEA if v/e overrule their commercial judgment for asecond time.(ii)  On the other hand, to go ahead with the 2-11 would involve muchheavier cost to the Exchequer than the development of the Trident 3Bwhich would probably by the alternative aircraft for BEA.    The figures are summarised in Table III and paragraph 13 of the Appendix,    Theyshow that, while BEA&apos;s operating losses with the 2-11 would be likely tobe less than with the Trident, this would be more than offset by the heavier launching costs of the 2-11, which the Government would haveto bear.    The net result would be that the 2-11 would involve anadditional cost, as compared with the Trident, of some  50 million in discounted terms.(iii) The effec ts on employment in the aircraft industry of adoptingone course rather than the other are not sufficiently significant to influence our choice..3,      There are a number of further considerations which are lessclear-cut and which do not decisively favour one alternative rather thanthe other --1-
(i) A decision in favour of the 2-11 would upset the French becausethey would regard it as prejudicing the success of the Airbus.    But wehave avoided giving them any commitment about the 2-11 and haveretained our freedom of action.    Moreover, the French themselves have allowed Air France to buy Boeings, deBpite their concern for the airbus.(ii) The 2-11 would have some export prospects, while the Tridentwould have none.    On the other hand, the fact that BAC are notprepared to contribute to the launching costs perhaps suggests that theyhave no great confidence in the export potential of the 2-11.(iii) The 2-11 would be preferable to the Trident on noise grounds,but this would not significantly affect the overall noise problem at ourairports.4.      There was general agreement that, apart from costs, the crucialconsiderations revolved around two major uncertainties.    The first isthe effect on the export potential of Rolls Royce aero-engines of adecision in favour of the 2-11.    Rolls Royce have two &quot;new technology&quot;engines with great export potential - the RB.207 and the smallerRB.211,    The RB.207 will go into the European Airbus.    The 1AB, 211has perhaps a fifty-fifty chance of being adopted for the American Airbuswhich Lockheed and McDonnell Douglas propose to develop.    Since wecannot be sure that the European Airbus will go ahead beyond the projectdefinition stage, there is at present no assured market for the R3.207engine.    It is therefore all the more important that Rolls R.oyce shouldbe able to market the RB.211 engine, lest we should be left with nooutlet at all for our advanced technology engines.    If the 2-11 aircraftgoes ahead, this would in itself be an outlet for the RB. 211 engine]moreover Rolls Royce feel strongly that this would improve theirchances of getting the RB.211 into the American Airbus.    But to buy aforeign engine for their Airbus v/ould be a major decision for the americans and it is doubtful how far they would in fact be influenced by the knowledge that the RB. 211 would be flying in the 2-11 aircraft.5,      The second uncertainty is the future of the European Airbus.Recent reports make it clear that the German Government will have difficulty in persuading Lufthansa to place a firm order for the Airbuson completion of the project definition stage, and there must therefore remain some doubt whether they will in the event insist on this.    Onthe other hand, all the three Governments concerned agreed to proceedto the project definition stage on clear assurances that, if the specification could be complied with, they would between them provide an assured market with their national airlines for 75 airbuses.6.      If we assume that the European /tirbus will go ahead, this wouldargue in favour of the Trident and against the 2-11:  the Airbus wouldprovide an outlet for one of the Rolls Royce engines;  development ofthe 2-11 would be partly (though not wholly) in competition with the airbus and would run counter to our general policy of Europeancollaboration as the basis for all future airframe ventures.    If on theother hand the Airbus were not to get beyond project definition, the effectmight well be that in the long term Europe, including the United Kingdom,-2-
would be obliged to buy the American Airbus.    In these circumstances,there would be an argument for developing the 2-11 as an interim measure, but it is not a conclusive argument.     The 2-11 would enablethe British airframe industry to stay in business for a short period;but in. the long run it could not hope to survive American competition.70      My colleagues and I found this a difficult issue with the considerations evenly balanced.    The general view, however, v/as that further study or inquiries would not help matters;  moreover a decision is required urgently by BEA and the industry.     The majority view was against development of the 2-11, and I invite the Cabinet to endorse that view.    I should add that this is the only decision we are called, on tomake at present;  if we do not go ahead with the 2-11, there should befurther urgent discussion with BSA before deciding the type and numberof alternative British aircraft they would then need.M.S.70, Whitehall, S.W.1.14th November, 1967-3-
Joint memorandum Toy Board of Trade and ministry of Technology officials    Ministers will recall that in the summer of 1966 BEA were[refused permission to purchase a fleet of Boeing aircraft.    ItJv/as announced that BEA would &quot;buy British aircraft and that aircraftBunder consideration were developed versions of the VC-10, the Tridentland the BAG 1-11; the Government were prepared to give launching aidBfor the types selected and would &quot;take steps to ensure that BSA isable to operate as a fully commercial undertaking with the fleet itacquires&quot; .2,   The BEA requirement fell into two parts.   The first was met bythe purchase of an improved and larger version of the BAC 1-11 - the bac 1-11/500.   The second and larger requirement was for an aircraft to match the Boeing 727 which is being acquired by continentalcompetitors and to provide the larger capacity aircraft which will be needed as traffic grows on many routes at home and abroad.   Withoutfurther aircraft BEA will be badly short of capacity to meet thegrowth in traffic from about 1969 until the airbus is available in1973, but the aircraft they acquire will continue to be needed for years after the airbus is available.3,   To meet this requirement for a larger aircraft intermediatebetween the iet aircraft now operated by BEA (e.g., Trident with about 100 seats) and the airbus (about 270 seats) there were inAugust 1966 only the VC-10 which might be modified for short-haul use(175 seats) and an enlarged Trident which has now emerged as theTrident 5-B (1R6 seats).    Meanwhile the British Aircraft corporation have proposed a substantially new aircraft the BAC 2-11 (203 seats).BEA asked in February 1967 for permission to buy the BAC 2-11 on theground that it was the right intermediate size (about 200 seats) onthe way to the airbus, and had the attraction of being first in thefield of a new generation of quieter aircraft with good operatingeconomics.Id   Of the five possibilities theoretically before us, two appear tobe ruled out in practice.   First, we assume that Ministers willadhere to their previous decision not to permit the purchase ofBoeings, even though Air France and Lufthansa have been allowed toacquire them.   Secondly, there seems no case for a modified VC-10,to which consideration was given earlier,  since this aircraft is rejected by BEA on operational grounds, and has no advantage on financial grounds.5.   Accordingly, in more detail, the paper discusses(a)   various possible fleets;Since any aircraft purchased are integrated with the whole of BEA&apos;s operations it is notpossible to isolate their particular costs and earnings; one has to work on the totalfleet.(b) the consequences for BEA&apos;s operational efficiency in financial terms;(c) aid to BEA;i)   launching costs;(e)incidence of Exchequer expenditure;(f)   consequences for the balance of payments;1BEA RE-EQUIPMENT
(g) efTec-t on the aerospace industry;(h) noise o;aivne fleets for BEABEA have no doubt that they want the BAC 2-11 .    They have0y;ever evaluated other possible courses.    The various &quot;mixes&quot; ofircraft for which a detailed analysis has been made are shewn inatie I.   The main assumptions which BEA have made and discussed withartments are set out for reference at Annex A.   The :&apos;Boeinp-,!eet is that originally proposed by BEA in 1966*.    It is included fororposes of comparison only.   As far as Tridents are concerned it wille seen that a fleet with a reduced number of Tridents and a greaterumber of airbuses has been included as well as the &quot;mix&quot; that BEAhemselves would prefer; the exact numbers and mix of aircraft inhis reduced Trident fleet are not finally determined.    The newof whatever sort would be absorbed gradually throughout theircraft970sTABLE IALTERNATIVE BEA FLEETSTypes ofAircrafto    tQ   BAC 2-11    TridentSeats   -tzttti      -    . .TridentFleetFleetFleet1-11(18 on order)rident 2(15 on order)11C 2-11Trident 3-BAirbusBoeing 727-200(Boeing 73797	23	21	21	25	, -106	21	17	17	25	17203	3k	-	-	-	-1k6	-	k7	29	-	-267	15	18	26	k3	17155					kh111	-	-	-	-	2k(Previously fleets containing respectively 18 short-haulVC-10s and 20 Boeing 727s were considered, but theresults are worse than for the Trident fleet and theyare omitted.)^sequences for BEA(a)   Effect on BEA&apos;s investment andprofit and loss accountpi The expected results with each of these fleets are shewn inJ&amp;ble ii.   This is done in two ways.    First is shewn how long BEA&apos;ould expect to make losses; what their accumulated deficit would be107ft/6 end ^ tha-t period j and how far that would be reduced, by^8/79, by subsequent annual surpluses.    Second the nett presentvdf of these results is shewn in terms of discounted cash flowttn the internal rate of return this represents.    It is to be served that the figures represent nett results of very large sumsrevenue and expenditure over the years.2
TABLE IIBEA FINANCIAL FORECAST  MillionAccountancy TermsD.C.F. Terms(10 year period)!.   .    - Accumulated Deficit Nett Internal RateI  period of - ... Present        of Return[losses from at end of       ,ft     1fl Value asi   1068/69 Period in ^    &apos; &apos; 1 a-i Col.1yearsat 19682-11 7 yearsridenteducedrident-Bxistingeseing27/7377 years8 years9 years-47-60-70-67-13-34-55-59-44-54-63-645o24.53.73.75 years-104-587.6These are the with the financialBOAC.   The problemdeficit; the 8&apos;* millstone round(Id)   Exchequer Aid to BEAWhen BEA were refused permission to buy Boeings the Governmentdertook to ensure &quot;that BEA is able to operate as a fullyaercial undertaking with the fleet it acquires2 words as were used when the Government dealtconsequences of the equipment decisions taken for is different because BOAC had a heavy accumulatedbjective here Is to avoid such an accumulation ashe neck of BEA and the Government.    It is important to give BEA aidairing the next few years when otherwise they would be accumulating aeficit, and to avoid the implication that the aid is directly relatedthe economics of the British aircraft.The method proposed, after discussion with BEA,  is^that theirxisting borrowings should be reduced by a given sum and that aspecial &quot;fund&quot; of the same amount should be created for the purpose ofsustaining their revenue account during the pe period of anticipatedosses.   This transaction would not require the provision of-Mitional Exchequer money, but as it would involve writing off part the Corporation^ debt to the Exchequer it would require legislation.   Additional Exchequer money is not required because,although the creation of the special &quot;fund&quot; reduces the interestPayable by BEA and receivable by the Exchequer, BEA1 s need to borrowfcring the same period is reduced to the same extent.   A predeterminedwould be transferred from the &quot;fund&quot; to the revenue account eachl^r so as to afford BEA, on the basis of present forecasts ofgrating conditions and out-turn, the opportunity to achieve a&quot;asonable margin of profit.   Prom these profits a reserve would beadually built up.   At the end of the period for which aid isWired BEA could be expected to be able to operate in a fullylercial fashion without support.    It would then be open to thevernment either to reclaim the reserve (which could be done underasting powers) or to convert it into interest-bearing borrowings orcapital.These matters will have to be settled before BEA finally commit^e^es to the purchase of aircraft.   Negotiations are continuing^selves to the purchase of aircraft.hef i    :xact size of the fxAllowing amounts for the various fleets discussed:exact size of the fund involved but they should not exceed3
&amp; 2! 7CONFIDENTIALBAC 2-11 Fleet  ^0 m.Trident 3-B Fleet  50 m.Reduced Trident 3-B Fleet  57 m.Existing types Fleet  58 m.These sums do not,  of course, modify the financial figures given inparagraph 7, since they represent no more than the method to headopted for dealing with the short falls shewn there.If^Tir-hing Costs11,  The figures in Table II are the results for BEA on the assumptbnthat launching costs are borne by the Government.    Table III shewsthese costs, combines them with the value of BEA1 s investment as inTable II, and shews therefore the total nett present value of the(investment,TABLE III	PRESENT VALUES	OF TOTAL INVESTMENT		1968-9 to 1977	-8 at 8% DISCOUNT			 	MillionFleet	Launching Cost	Value of          -i-    ^ . Tvp* t Q              Import Investment               y (From Table II)	Value of total InvestmentBAC 2-11	-78 (-56)		-122 (-100)Trident 3-B	-17	-5k	- 71Reduced Trident 3-B	-17	-63	- 80Msting Types	0	-Gk                 -	- 6hBoeing 737/727	0	- 6                   20	i- 1kNotes   (a)   Figures in round brackets are those applicable tothe B/C 2-11 Fleet if the basic engine launchingcosts&apos;can be attributed to the American airbus.(b)   According to normal practice the launching costs of the BAC 2-11 would be offset to a modest exoentby a Government levy on sales.   Allowance has beenmade for this in the above figures.Exchequer Expenditure12. An analysis has been made of the incidence of the funding by theTreasury of BEA and of the aircraft industry (in its civil role j overthe next five years in respect of the different BEA fleets considered in this paper. In this context it is the gross launching cost (notdiscounted as above) that is relevant in  130 M. for the BAC 2-11 and 17 M. for the Trident 3-B. The results are shewn m Annex B ana forcompleteness cover Concord developire nt and production which is oi norelevance to BEA.&amp;IJMMARY13.  These tables shew that the BAC 2-11 is rightly preferred by BEA^financial grounds - in nett present value terms it is  10 M. betterthan the full Trident fleet or  20 M. better than the reduced Tridentfleet - as well as because of its advantages in size and quietness.k
5dually they make it clear that the BAC 2-11  is the least attractive^vestment with launching cost taken into account, involving an^itional cost in discounted terms of some  50 M. or, in Exchequerterms? an outlay of some  20 M. per year greater from 1968/9 -971/2.of Payments111, The Trident 3-B has negligible export potential.    There iscertainly a world market for an aircraft of around 200 seats in sizeDud with economics as good as, or preferably better than, those of the bac 2-11.   How great it is and how successful the BAC 2-11 would be incapturing it must be speculative.   The Americans could well produce a competitor of more advanced design by, say, 197h and export salesroiled probably be achieved only in the early years of availability ofthe BAC 2-11.    In the view of the Ministry of Technology, it isinmrobable that export sales would amount to more than 60 represent-iag a foreign earning of  130 M.    This would, involve an implied pref-erence rate for foreign exchange of some 50%, (relating Government loss to export earnings), or some 35% allowing for the fact that we shouldsave the cost of developing the Trident 3-B for BEA, and that BLA*s foreign currency earnings would be improved with the BAC 2-11.    If,less probably, 100 export sales were secured earnings might be 220 M. and the implied subsidy 23^o and 17% on the two bases.15, There are two other factors here that are more speculative - thefurther export earnings that might be achieved if on the one hand thedevelopment of the BAC 2-11 enabled Rolls-Royce to market the RB.211engine; and if, on the other, a decision not to develop the BAC 2-11led to the later project for a European minibus discussed below.Effect on the Aerospace Industry16,  (a)   EnginesOn past experience the export potential is greater forengines than for airframes.    It is therefore of the utmost importance to give Rolls-Royce a secure basis for develop-ing at least one of their new technology engines, RBo207or S3.211.    The RB.207 will go into the airbus, but weshall not be sure until the middle of next year that the airbus will go ahead.    The RB.211 is on offer for an american Lockheed or Douglas airbus, but it faces strongcompetition from American engines.    In these circumstances,the BAC 2-11 provides the one present application for anew technology engine entirely within our control.ft-  (b)   Aircraft Industry PolicyAircraft industry policy is now firmly based onpartnership with Europe, since we do not rate veryhighly the chances in future of selling large civil aircraft in world markets, in the face of increasingAmerican and Russian competition, unless they have asa starting point an assured market in Europe.    Thiswas the basis of the decision to start the airbus.j8* The BAC 2-11 would run counter to this policy.    On BEA&apos; s plans,Ruining they buy the BAC 2-11, they would not require more than 15Rouses by 1980, which would make it difficult to achieve the assuredll^et of 75 aircraft which we regard as a minimum for continuing therous project, particularly as Air France have already been allowedsolfl   BoeinSs as an intermediate aircraft.   To the extent that itd abroad it would constitute a threat to airbus exports.The Trident 3-B would also, to a less extent, run counter to theto i^0an Policy.    If BSA have no new type of aircraft they will havetake something like R0 airbuses; their optimum Trident fleet would
leave a demand for only 18 airbuses and even the reduce Tridentfleet which haa &quot;been considered calls for no more than 26 airbuses.But no exports of the Trident 3-B that would further prejudice theoirbus market are expected.20. As a continuation of a European policy we should, in the view of3 Ministry of Technology, plan towards a 200-seat aircraft ofau/anced design (a &quot;minibus&quot;) as a collaborative project enteringservice in 1975 or later and aimed at a wider market than the purelynational BAC 2-11.    Conceived as a Boeing 727/200 successor,  andsufficiently up to date in concept to go on selling into the 1980s inthe face of competition, such an aircraft might hope to achieve sales of 200/250 in all, earning for the United Kingdom foreign currency toa nett present value of  150/200 M.   At this 13 vel of sales, theUnited Kingdom might be expected to recover its share of the launch-ing costs, so that there would be no implied subsidy.   We should layclaim to design leadership (since the French are leading on the airbus).   The minibus, following the airbus, might possibly be the start of a European family of aircraft and therefore lead to continuing export sales.21. This policy will, of course, not be without difficulties.    Therecan be no ascurance that the technical improvements necessary for a successful minibus will prove feasible, or that other countries canbe persuaded to join in or accept our leadership.    The French haveagreed that officials should discuss this project, and are thought tohave accepted the philosophy of a European family of aircraft, but we know that French finances are already strained by the currentaircraft programme.Manufacturing considerartions the BAC 2-11 would be designed and built by BAC at weybridgevfhere a sharp rundown of work is threatened on completion of the bac 1-11.   All things being equal, we should aim to maintain thisteam, since it is the only one which has achieved ^al success in the major civil aircraft field.   However, in the absence of the        ^-i ise night employ the nucleus of the team in preliminary studies toestablish the feasibility and economics of a minibus concept \at a cost in the order of  1-2 M. a year).    The Trident 3-B would dodesigned and built by HSA at Hatfield.   Yiithout it there woula oe ashortage of work at this factory until the airbus gets underway.Aircraft noise23.  The noise characteristics of the aircraft under considerationare set out in Annex C.   The BAC 2-11 and the airbus are the only two types which would incorporate advanced technology engines, ^intrinsically much quieter than those in use now.   The Trident 3-B,like the Boeing 727-200, is not significantly different from currentaircraft,2tu  If BEA buy the BAC 2-11 in the numbers they propose, by 1973something like h0% of BEA&apos; s movements to the London airports or about 16% of the total of all airlines, would be with these quieterengines.   Similarly, maximum deployment of the airbus would have^traction from this point of view.   Existing types of aircraft, orstretched&apos; versions of them, would precede the new noise certifica-ion scheme and,at least initially, not be affected by it.    It has to?e recognised, however, that noise suppression will have growingimportance during the lifetime of the aircraft now to be ordered andli is possible that the Trident 3-B which, like the Boeing 727,  isabove the criteria to be applied, will have to be re-engmed orretired well before the end of its service life.25- BEA are well aware of the advantages to them of quieter engines,aridhave assumed that they would obtain a higher utilisation of theluieter BAC 2-11, especially at night, than of the Trident 3-B.   BEn6
re also aware of the danger of restrictions on the Trident 3-B andir Anthony Milward nas made it clear that, if he is compelled to take it) he will want a guarantee that it will he exempt from the noisecertification scheme     Clearly no such guarantee can he given and ity be necessary instead to promise here also to make good any Jossesincurred as a result of noise policy. .     uosses2gt  In addition to the advantage to BEA, an attempt has heen made tn5Valuate the amenity benefit of the BAC 2-11 to thSpuolic     &apos;   t2irports, like, Heathrow which is BEA&apos;s main base an! wSre there is al highhigh rate of air transport landings and take-offs with a genertnoise level and intermittent bursts of high intensity, the oresence0f some quiet aircraft will only marginally affect amenity nearby,,;t less busy airports the relative importance of some quieter air-craft will be greater but the loss of amenity due to noise at thoseplaces is, in total, very much less.    Furthermore,  the number of movements that BEA will make with their new aircraft at these placesis small in relation to their activity at Heathrow.    Overall,  thevalue of the improvement in amenity near airports where BEA operatesis considered to be marginal in relation to the other sums involvedin choosing an aircraft for BEA but so far as there is an advantageit lies with the BAC 2-11 .BEA&apos;s position27, Finally, it is necessary to have some regard to BEA&apos;s positionin all this.   By refusing their first choice, the Boeing 727 and 737,have already once overruled their judgment.    If now we refuse tosake the BAC 2-11 available against their considered preference, andfurthermore insist on reducing the number of Trident 3-Bs below whatthey regard as the optimum, we are undermining the BEA Board andsubstituting our own judgment.    BE/, is a national asset and we are bound to attach importance to their success in carrying out their statutory responsibility to provide an efficient and economicairline.28.  On the other hand the BAC 2-11 had not been conceived at thetime BEA were refused permission to buy Boeing aircraft.    the alternatives under consideration then were much less expensive inlaunching aid than the BAC 2-11 and it was these smaller sums theGovernment was prepared to pay when it made its decision.   While the bac 2-11 fleet gives the best internal rate of return on BEA&apos;sinvestment none of the fleets of British aircraft examined by BEAensures an Q% a year return on capital invested in BEA, the criterion laid clown in the recent white Paper on financial objectives for the nationalised industries as the minimum return on new investment.29. While the figures in the tables in this paper are reasonablyreliable as a guide to the relative values of the fleets consiaercdthey are not entirely solid in absolute terms.    In particular, tnetotal capacity in aircraft the airline needs to meet forecasttraffic demand is not certain and, indeed, could be influenced bythe conclusions of the Edwards Committee.    It is not necessary todecide the precise numbers of aircraft to be purchased now.    *henthe type to be bought has been chosen BEA would, in accordance withusual practice, place an initial order for fewer aircraft than they expect to need and take options, which may be turned into firm orderslater, on additional aircraft.30. There is no dispute that for BEA the BAC 2-11  is the bestPurchase; that it presents the only prospect of earnings from^Port; that it is attractive from the point of view of noise    andth&amp;t it is the only project wholly within our control that willProvide a basis for Polls- Royce new technology engines.   On theother hand this is the most expensive solution altnough these7rnMCincwTiAi
advantages might perhaps justify a heavy expenditure on launchingcoSts if this were also desirable on industrial grounds0   against this has to he set the judgment of the Ministry of Technology thatto develop the BAC 2-11 would seriously prejudice, if not even put anend to, the airbus project and the prospects of an integratedEuropean aircraft manufacture on which we are predicating ourresent policy for the aircraft industry and our future hopes of selling large civil aircraft in world markets.31, If we do not proceed with the BAC 2-11  it would be possible togoto the other extreme, refuse to develop the Trident 3-B and leaveBCA with no alternative to making do with the existing types,  i.e.,Irident 2 and BAC 1-11/500.    This, because we shall have no launchingcosts to meet, is the course with the best present value for thejftole investment, and would have the effect of maximising BEA&apos; s needfor the airbus.    But .lt is not only financially less attractive toBEA than other courses but would leave them with obsolescent and too small aircraft to meet the competition of airlines which are acquiringlarger American aircraft and a very difficult transition to the airbus.32, Accordingly, if we do not proceed with the BAC 2-11 the bestalternative in the view of the two Departments is  the Trident 3-B.If that course is chosen it is necessary also no decide whether BEAshould be allowed to acquire v/hat they regard as the optimum &quot;mix&quot;of Tridents and airbuses, or whether, as the Ministry of Technologywould wish, the number of Tridents should be kept to a reasonableminimum so as to maximise BEA&apos;s support for the airbus.    The reducedIrident fleet which has been considered is shewn in Table II to leaveBEA with a deficit after 10 years some  20 M. greater than would thefull Trident fleet, and to have present value,  as shewn in Table III,some  9 M. worse than that fleet.    It would on the other hand forceBEA to order twenty-six airbuses instead of eighteen.33.  If it were decided not to proceed with the BAC 2-11 the Ministryof Technology would propose a small study contract to coverpreliminary design investigations into a minibus and to conserve the nucleus of a team at BAC, A&apos;eybridge, which could lead on such a project.8
Annex AB.E.A.&apos;s ASSUMPTIONSB.E.A. have based their calculations of the fleet they require on the main assumptions set out below.1 .   Fleets are based on matching expected traffic growth,international and domestic.    This is taken as IO-g-%falling to 8% annually for international passenger traffic and at varying amounts, according to the fleetchosen, falling to 7% for domestic traffic.    Freight is assumed to increase at 20% annually.2.   All jet operations as soon as possible are assumed on international routes and parity of equipment and opportunity with independent airlines is assumed for the1970s on domestic routes.3.   The results assume actual anticipated cost and revenue for the first three-four years at expected fares andwage rates.    In subsequent years fares and wage rates are assumed to move in parallel.k.   The results are much affected by the extent to which BEAconsider they will be short of capacity, or unable to operate matching services with their competitors, in theearly years.    All fleets, including the Boeing fleetoriginally asked for, would be expected to become profit-able, though to differing extents.5.   The notional Boeing fleet assumes payment of Import Duty.B.E.Ao&apos;s growth figures have been checked and are consideredreasonable.    Their cost and revenue figures are more open to doubt in detail, but it is considered that in the earlier years theyindicate fairly the likely trends with each fleet and therelativities between them.
x *tAnnex B1967/8 1968/9 1969/70 1970/1 1971/2   5-yeartotalrent aircrafteluding Concord and Airbus)2-11 developmentcord production,A, financingTotalrent aircrafteluding Concord and Airbus)dent 3-B developmentcord production0)J.A. financingTotalluced Trident 5-Brent aircrafticluding Concord and Airbus)dent 3-B development;Cord production(D\,k, financingTotalsting; typesrent aircrafteluding Concord and Airbus)cord production-A. financingTotal48	63	60	52	46	2	17	31	31	28	3	9	20	30	30	15	33	14	0	2	68	122	125	113	106	53448	63	60	52	46	1	k	6	4	2	3	9	20	30	30	19	29	11	1,2	-4	71	105	97	98	74	44548	63	60	52	46	0	k	6	4	3	3	9	20	30	30	17	28	15	9	-7	68	104	101	95	72	44048	63	60	52	46	3	9	20	30	30	11	29	7	-9	-9	62	101	87	73	67	390:   (1) New borrowing by B.E.A. less payment of interest.,If B.E.A. is relieved of some part of the interest payable,then new borrowing is reduced by the same amount.    The above figures would, therefore, remain unchanged.(2) If the BAC 2-11 is rejected, a study contract for a&quot;Minibus&quot; should be placed, at a cost of, say,  1 Moin 1968/69 and rising to  2 M. per year thereafter.
	CONFIDENTIAL			Annex C		Estimated Noise Levels of Aircraft			ConsideredHirrraft with existing engines			Effective PNdB				Approach 1 mile from threshold	Lateral 1000 ft.	Flyover k statute miles from take off, throttle hack to 500 ft./min. climb, 1000 st.miles rangerident 3-B 1	115	116	103oeing 727/200 1	116	11k	103mm        .....                  ..... tort Haul VC.1 0	116	117 - 120	97A01-11/500	106	112	99rident 2-E	11.0	115	106Aircraft with nev/ technology engines (RB207 or .211 )				Approach 1 mile from threshold	Lateral 1000 ft.	Flyover k statute miles from take off, throttle back to 500 ft./min.climb, 1000 st.miles rangeiAC 2-11	103	109	90irbus	109	110	92CONFIDENTIAL.			


</content>
</cab>
