<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/44/0 images: 82-82</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property qf Eis Britannic Majestyrs Government).       iIB C RE f,              !AB   C A B II 3 f.g.T. 3826.           POLICY WITH REGARD TO RUSSIAN 3UBJ3CT3                        SERYIIG IH vjg BRITISH ARkT.             (Reference War Cabinet 329, Minute 12, &amp; 345, Minute 3).      Copy of Minutes in gar Office Registered File go. 19/lnfantry/699Q.C.2.          I am informed that a rule for a writ of habeas corpus wasobtained this morning (5c3.18) at the suit of a Russian namedKutchinsky against the Officer Commanding 39th Battalion RoyalFusiliers, Crownhill Barracks, Plymouth; and I understand that itwill be served on the Secretary o,f State for v/ar and the 0,0. andthat the Court intimated that the hearing should be as soon aspossible.  The ground of the application is that the applicant whois serving in the Army is no longer bound to serve as the Conventionwith Russia is no longer-binding.  I presume that I shall be desiredto act for the Secretary of State and the CO. and I shall be gladof instructions and information as to the facts of the case as soonas possible.  The matter is presumably one in which the ForeignOffice and the home Office will desire to be informed of the Proceed-ings, but that is, I think, for your consideration.Treasury Solicitor,                       (Intd.) A.H.Dc5.3.18. Mobilization 5 A *G 4 3.L *           Can you please furnish instructions and information for Treasury  Solicitor^  guidance to enable  him to act,  as I presume  he should.  The 0.C  should be  asked to  authorize Treasury Solicitor acting on his behalf.   &apos;./e understand  there is an Inter-Departmental Committee sitting which is dealing with  the whole question of Russians  under the Convention,  and. on which the Foreign Office and Home  Office  are represented,  rerhaos  you would kindly bring this action to the notice  of the  Committee, as it raises  the whole policy :and equally  affeots the Foreign Office,  ^ome Office  and Ministry  of Uati^nal  Service as much as  the ://ar Office.                                            (Sd)  L.D.Eolland.                                              0.2. 5.3.10. A.G.13,           Will you deal with this?                                       (3d)  Gerald A&amp;J&amp;ead.                                                   6.3.18.  j P.S.  to S.of 3.           This is a matter on which the  War Cabinet  will have to decide the nolicy we  are to  adopt.                                        (Sd) R.F.  Riley.  . A. G .13.                                           4.  . G.. 6^3* 16 * Secretary, War Cabinet.           Lord Derby  thinks  this ought to be mentioned at  to-morrow morning1 s Meeting. VJould you please  note -*nd let S.of 3.  have  the papers to-morrow?                                         (3d) E.J. Greedy.                                                   6,3,18,

</content>
</cab>
