<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/44/0 images: 149-152</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(0  -Intelligence Bureau,Department of Information.GSW/011.Weekly Report on Sweden. XI.     (7th March, 19145.)    Mr. Trygger,  leader of the Conservative Party in the firstChamber, on  February 26 asked the Swedish Government the followingquestions: -    1. Do not  the Government now consider that the^ can give thelawful  Government  of Finland the right in principle to send intransit through Sweden and then  export thence arms and ammunitionI  procurable from private firms in Sweden or abroad?       2.   Do the Government still consider themselves prevented  from allowing the lawful Government of Finland to receive from  Swedish State stores arms and ammunition which, without risk to  Swedenfs preparedness for defence, could be placed at the Finnish  Government1s disposal for the re-establishment of order in Finland?       The Prime Minister stated in reply that he had already dealtI  with this matter last week and that during the interval he had  seen no reason to alter the general principles of the Government  rep;arding Sweden&apos;s position towards the crisis in Finland or their  attitude in the questions again raised by Mr. Trygger.   The  Conservative leader considered the Prime Minister&apos;s reply un-i  satisfactory.   He maintained that if the lawful Government inI Finland issued victorious from the present civil war, Finnishj  sympathies for Sweden could not be expected to br. strong.    This1 would  effectually prevent Sweden realising the idea of an aseocia-1 tion of small states in the north.   If sufficient help was given11 to Finland by a Great Power she would seek support from that power
and it  was clear what  this would mean for the future of Sweden.The late premier Mr.  Swartz ani other Conservative members supportedMr. Trygger&apos;s point of view.     There is little  doubt that the action of the Swedish Govern-meat has greatly displeased the Finnish Government.   The latterare specially dissatisfied with the fact that while preventing thetransit or supply of war material to Finland the Swedish Govern-                       omerit have occupied the Aland Islands.                               o     The Swedish troops in the Alands amount to about 500 men ofthe Gttta Guards.   The German Government has now decided to inter-vene in Finland,anthe Swedish Government have been informed that                                                     (x)the Aland Islands will be used as a base of operations.   In ordernot to  interfere with the humanitarian mission now being performed   the  Swedish forces, the German expedition will limit its actionin the  Islands to using them as a base for its communications.In making this communication to the Swedish Government the GermanMinister at Stockholm added that Germany having no territorialinterest in the  land Islands and recognising their vital importanceto Sweden readily admitted that the whole question must be settledby direct agreement with Sweden.   The Swedish Government has pro-tested  against the use of the Islands in a manner which may drawthem into war-like operations and prevent Sweden carrying out thehumanitarian mission  which she has undertaken for the protectionof the  inhabitants.  They take note of Germany&apos;s explanations atthe same time pointing out that even the limited use of the Islandscontemplated will raise great difficulties in the prosecution of thehumanitarian mission  in question.   The  action of the  Germans in the Baltic during 1917 had alreadydone something to cause a revulsion of feeling among the pro-GLerma. -:)  On the 4th March the German force had got no further than   Gothland.
                            -  3  -  in Sweden.    It will  be  interesting to  Gee what such staunch  henchmen of the Germans  such as  the editor of &quot;Aftonbladet&quot; will  have to say about  the German occupation of a group of Islands  situated at the mouth of the fjord leading to the Swedish capital.  ITeunwMle  there is little doubt  that the new move on the p.&apos;.rt oi  Germany will e^use dismay and  indignation ^mong those Swedes who   are sufficiently  sane to understand what German hegemony in the  Baltic will mean in the  future.    Whether the events in the Is-lstnd  o  Mando will lead to the  long&apos; deferred Scandinavian Defensive Union  remains to be seen.    It may  be  said  that as regards  intervention in Finland - the  initiative for which  has now passed from their hands - Sweden is  divided into  two camps.    The  powerful  Socialist party has all along  been opposed  to intervention.    The view of t&apos;&quot;is party is briefly  as follows.   They consider  the  resort  to force of the Finnish  Bol3heviks as a denial of the  fundamental basis of Democracy and  regard the attempt to establish  a  new social order by revolutionary  violence organised by a  minority as indefensible in a country 3u&amp;h  as Finland, already enjoying universal  suffrage.  They reject  3ol?hevist opinions as likely  to lead through social anarchy to  reaction.   While  in  no  way  countenancing the Bolshevists, they pro-  test against  the action  of the Swedish  Conservatives,  *?ho wish to  use  disorder  in Finland  as an  excuse to take part in what is a cliss-  war  end who deolihe to see that  intervention would lead Sweden into  open hostility to  the present  de facto  Government at ^etrograd.  Swwdi3h action, the Socialists think,  should be confined to media-  tion between  the  contending  factions.    There is also the usual  tendtnoy on the side  of  the  Swedish Socialists to ignore or pro-(  claim  as exaggerated  the terrible  atrocities committed An Finland  by the proletariat and the criminals who have assisted them in
                          -  4 -inaugurating a reign of terror at Helsingfors,  Viborg and generallythroughout the South.  - It is very difficult to say at oresent what  effect the lastGerman move in the Baltic will have on the elements of disorderin Sweden.    As long as the  Swedish army is loyal,  although theremay be local disturbances, nothing dangerous is likely to occur.But the food question is increasingly serious and it is impossibleto say to what extent Bolshevik  ideas have infected the Swedisharmy.   In any case the co-mtry,  usually so peaceful, is face tof,?ce with a situation such as it has not been through since thefall of the House of Tasa.   It  is fortunate that the Swede habin general a strong sense of discipline and gtest patriotism.

</content>
</cab>
