<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/44/0 images: 205-206</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
( i his Document Is  the Property ofHis  Britannic Maiesty^s Government.)Oolonel JonesConfidential.166 /UR  POSITION  IN  MUNITION  INDUSTRIES.               (6th  March  1918.)    I circulate the following notes which have been  prepared iu the Intelligenceand Statistics  Section  of the Ministry  of  Munitions on  the  labour  position inmunitions industries.                                              WINSTON S.  CHURCHILL.                                I-STRIKES.    The  time lost through strikes on munition work  was again very, low in the weekending the 27tli February, the total days lost being under 9,000, or less than &quot; 06 percent, of the possible working time.  The largest amount of  time was lost by the glass-workers at Gateshead,  who have  been  on strike since the 12th January; iu &quot;threeother strikes the time lost approached or  exceeded 1,000  days.  At the end of theweek 2,033 workers were still on strike.    Since the 27 th February two of the four important continuing strikes have beensettled; only two  new strikes of considerable  magnitude have  been reported,  andboth of these have been settled.   The Gateshead glassworkers, to the number of637, and 525 employees of the British Aluminium Co., Ltd., in Staffordshire, are stillon strike.Statistics for February, 1918.    The  following table  shows for  February the number of persons involved instrikes, and the total number of working days lost: Disi rict.	Number of Workpeople involved. _____	Number of Days lost in February.London and South Eastern ------South Western West. Midlands - - &apos; . -Yorkshire and East Midlands ------North Western Northern .......... Wales - - - - - - - -Scotland - - - - - -	9,576 739 1.761 536 631 1,180 5,860 9,513	16,783 1,846 5,325 657 689 13,506 15.250 50,105	29,796	104,161    This represents a loss  through strikes of &quot;17 per cent.    of 1 per cent.) ofpossible working days, as compared with &apos;76 per cent, (f of 1 per cent.) in November,* 38 per cent, in December,  and &apos; 37 per cent,  in January-in  each of the last  twocases a little over \ of 1 per cent.    The figures of the Scottish district are obviously much the worst.  35,000 dayswere lost through a strike or lock-out at the Parkhead Works of Messrs. W. Beardmore&amp; Co.,  Ltd., the seventh strike at the establishments of this firm in nine weeks.                   II.-THE A.S.E. AND  MAN POWER.    The  A.S.E. Delegates, after  an  interview with  the  Prime Minister, have senthim two letters.  The first restated their position at some length; the second con-tained  the suggestions  of  the  Delegates as  to  the policy to be adopted by  theGovernment.  They demanded that the Agreement of May, 1917, should  be carriedout,  and in effect extended, i.e., that before  any skilled men or apprentices  arerecruited, all dilutees liable and fit for general military service shall first be recruited.    x (88)5321 Pk 20  125  3/18  E&amp;S
They defined  &quot; dilutee&quot; as  a man who has entered his present occupation sinceAugust 4th, 1914, with an exception in favour of apprentices and boys  undergoingtraining in technical schools.  They also asked that any skilled men who may be calledup or may enlist voluntarily, shall be posted to technical units.     The present  determining date for  dilutees is  August  loth, 1915.  The A.S.E.hitherto have been reluctant to  go back to 1914, because the change would affectmany men who have  joined their Society  since  the  war.  The other craft Unionshave&apos; pressed for  1914, and to this extent, therefore, the  A.S.E. are falling  into linewith them.  On the other hand, their definition would treat as dilutees members ofthe general Unions who have been upgraded to  do skilled  men.&apos;s work during thewar.   Any promise that dilutees (however  defined)  shall  be recruited before  youngskilled men would seriously delay recruiting, and Sir Auckland Geddes will probablyadhere to his present policy that dilutees  and skilled men shall be  recruited  con-currently, but that, other things being equal in any given Avorks, the dilutee shallbe taken first, because, as  a rule, he can  best be spared.   On the 1914 point, thedifficulty of meeting the Unions is a practical one, that there are no  records  of theindustrial occupation of workmen before  August  15th,  1915, the date  of  NationalRegistration.     As to the claim that skilled men shall be posted to technical units, the positionis that the needs of the Army for young  fit men for hue regiments,  cannot he metwithout drawing upon skilled men.

</content>
</cab>
