<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/44/0 images: 214-223</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
pSocubent is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government..114                                                              /IfPrinted for the War Cabinet.  March 1918.SECRET.NAVAL  WEEKLY  APPRECIATION-No. 41.Week ended 2nd March, 1918.                             NAVAL  OPERATIONS.    On February  22nd  H.M.S. &quot; Tay and  Tyne &quot; captured off  Grudene  Rocks the North Sea.unarmed German s.s. &quot; Dusseldorf &quot; with a cargo of iron ore.   A prize crew was put onboard, and she arrived in the  Firth of Forth on March 1st.    Mine-laying operations in  the North Sea and in the Heligoland Bight have beencontinued.                                                                i    R.N.A.S. machines from Dunkirk have carried out the following raids :-        Flanders                                                                                 area.Date..	Target.	Weight of Bombs dropped.	Results.25th-26th February 26tb February ......	Bruges Dock Oostacker Aerodrome ... Engel Dump ......	2  tons ... ...... 2f tons ......... 1,150 lbs.......	Well straddled. A fire was observed to break out.    Dunkirk machines have also carried  out many reconnaissances and patrols, in thecourse of which three enemy destroyers were attacked, six bombs being dropped from lowaltitudes, but without result.   On another occasion 800 rounds were  fired  at  ZeebruggeMole.    One of our machines was lost in combat with six enemy seaplanes.    On March  1st  the armed merchant  cruiser &quot; Calgarian&quot; was  torpedoed about North11 miles  north-west of Rathlin Head, 554  officers and men (including the commanding ChanneLofficer) being saved, and 49 officers and men not accounted for.    The  trawler &quot; Thomas Collard &quot; was  also torpedoed when alongside  &quot; Calgarian,&quot;but another trawler &quot; Opoieroy &quot; fired one  round point blank at the submarine and alsodropped three depth charges on it, and the officer in command believes that the submarinewas destroyed.    On February 26th the hospital ship &quot;  Glenart Castle,&quot; bound from Newport (Mon.) Bristolto Brest, was torpedoed without  warning  6 miles north of Hartland  Point.  The  ship Chi mel.was showing all lights at the time, and sank in seven minutes.  There were no patientson board, but out of  182  crew and medical personnel only 29 were saved.    On February 27th, owing to failure of  petrol supply, the airship S.S.Z.  26  had to be Casualties.abandoned in Dover Straits, after several efforts had been made by the destroyer &quot; Phoebe ;;to take her in tow.  The crew were saved, but the airship was last seen at a great heightto the eastward of the Goodwins,  drifting east.    On February 28th the special service trawler &quot; Brown Mouse &quot; accidentally caughtfire and finally  blew up, 10 miles  south-east of Brixham.  The crew were  saved.   (C1014)  Wt.   55 3/18 H&amp;S
ATTACK-. UPON ENEMY  SUBMARINES.SUBMARINESOPERATING.    During the week 21 to 24 large enemy submarines have been located, six being vesselsof the converted &quot; Deutschland &quot; type.  Of these latter, two were operating to the north-westward  of  Ireland homeward bound, two  in the  Bay  of Biscay, one westward  ofGibraltar,  and one was last reported off Dakar on March  1st.   Of the remaining largeboats, 13 to 16 were operating in Home Waters, the North of Ireland and the Irish Sea,where as many as seven boats were operating at one time, again being the areas of greatestactivity.AOTIONS        The following8 Table shows the number of actions with enemy submarines in HomeWITH ENEMY Waters during recent weeks, and the nature of the craft which have been engaged, andsubmarines.             -                                                          o o  &apos;also the number of submarines destroyedNature of Craft.	Week ended February 9th.		Week ended February 16th.		Week ended February 23rd.		Week ended March 2nd.		Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.	Actions.	Results.Cruiser ............ T.B.D. and T.B....... A.P. Vessels ......... Aircraft............ Sloops and Patrol Boats Gunboat............ Merchant Vessels... Destroyed by Mine ... -Destroyed by Mine Nets Submarines Special Service Ship ...... Total	5 1 2 1 1 2	1 1	1 3 5 2 5 1	1 1	5 2 3	1	5 4 1 1 1 3 1	1	12	2	17	2	10	1	16	1   &quot; Results &quot; indicates submarines definitely or probably sunk according to the reports of the actionsreceived.   Submarines possibly sunk are not included.NUMBERAND TON-NAGE OF ALLVESSELS LOST.                 MERCANTILE  LOSSES  BY  ENEMY  ACTION.    The following is a Comparative Statement of the Number and Tonnage of all MerchantVessels sunk in recent weeks by enemy action : -Week Ended	British Vessels.				Allied and Neutral Vessels.				Total.		1,600 tons gross and over.		Under 1,600 tons gross.		1,600 tons gross and over.		Under 1,600 tons gross.		All sizes.		No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.	No. I Tonnage. J		No.	Tonnage.	No.	Tonnage.1918. January 19th January 26th February 2nd February 9th February 16th February 23rd March 2nd	5 9 12 13 10 14 12	15,878 37,248 61,652 70,219 38,033 50,267 50,319	2 6 5 7 3 3 6	1.227 3.510 2.097 2,554 2,070 2,794 5,529	2 10 5 9* 4* 3* 3 .	7,031 26,792 19,715 38,114* 13,624* 5,848* 9,796	! 4 &apos; 10 20* 9 2 -1 8	3,274 7,137 6,101* 6,034 1,473 5,917	13 35 42* 3S* 17* 22* 29	27,410 74,687 89.565* 116,921* 53,727* 60,382* 71,561* Adjusted.
                                 ENEMY MINES.    Enemy minelaying has this Aveek been confined to the Peterhead and Harwich areas, Minelaying.in the latter of which regular and sustained minelaying is now directed against the Dutchconvoys.  Having regard  to the number of U.C. boats known to have  been operatingand the number of enemy mines destroyed an  unusually  large number of mines wouldappear  to  be unaccounted  for,  but extended searches have failed to locate them andno vessel has been mined in unexpected localities.   Similar experience  has been reportedby the  French minesweeping authorities as regards  their areas.   The matter  is beinginvestigated,  but it  seems not improbable that,  finding that the torpedo yields betterresults than  the  mine, the  enemy have adapted some of the mine tubes in certain  oftheir submarines  to carry spare  torpedoes.    The following table shows the  number of enemy mines destroyed and British vessels Casualties.sunk by mine in Home Waters in recent weeks : Week Ended. L	Number of Enemy Mines Destroyed.	Number of British Mine-sweepers and Patrols Sunk by Mines.	Number of British Merchant Steamships Sunk by Mines.February 2nd....... 9th ...... 16th...... ,, 23rd...... March 2nd ......	26 30 19 54 46	2 Nil Nil Nil Nil	Nil Nil Nil Nil 1    The  merchant ship sunk this week was  mined  in the Harwich area,  where alsoanother merchant vessel was damaged.(C 1014)    The table in Appendix I shows in detail the numbers and tonnage of sailings and LOSSES OFof losses by enemy action, and the percentage  of losses to sailings of British merchant Blitis^steamships of over ,500 tons gross, register ; and the table in Appendix II shows by trades fbeaxa^Saas regards such ships the percentage of tonnage sunk by enemy action to tonnage sailing ^ tradea&quot;to and from United Kingdom ports during the last four weeks.    .     .                     &quot;:&apos; J    The British tonnage engaged  this week in overseas trades lias been normal andshows a considerable  increase on the  figures for last week, while the losses in  thesetrades.  are appreciably  less than  in the  previous  week, with  the result  that thepercentage of  losses to sailings as regards British tonnage employed in overseas tradesis-only  1.86 as against 3.60 last week.   In  coasting and cross-channel trades, however,the total tomiage  employed was less and the tonnage lost greater than in the previousweek, the percentage  of losses to sailings in these trades being 1.29 as against .88, whilethe percentage as  regards. all United Kingdom trades combined is 1.47 as against 1.62the previous week.    The table in Appendix III has this week been considerably extended, and now comprisesa comparative statement  of all merchant vessels, foreign as well as British, sunk, damagedand unsuccessfully attacked in the last two weeks by enemy craft and by mine, classifiedaccording to areas.  It will be seen  that submarine activity has been greater in the IrishSea and the Mediterranean and somewhat less in the English Channel than in the previousweek.    It may be of assistance in considering Appendix III to describe generally the limits ofthe different areas referred  to Avhere any doubt  can exist.  The &quot; Arctic and White Sea &quot;includes the area north of a line drawn due east and west through the south of Iceland :the &quot; Atlantic (Northern) &quot;  extends between that line and a line  drawn due  west fromGalway Bay and is bounded on the east by the coasts of Ireland and Scotland, and a linedrawn due north from the Shetland  Islands ;  the &quot;&quot; Atlantic (Southern) &quot; extends betweenlines drawn due west from Galway Bay and from a point about 100 miles north of Lisbon..and is bounded on the east by a line drawn from the south-eastern point of Ireland to theScilly Islands, and thence to Ushant and Finisterre ;  and the &quot; Gibraltar-Azores &quot; areaextends between lines drawn due west from a point about 100 miles north of Lisbon andfrom  Mogador.
                         DEFENCE  AGAINST  SUBMARINE AND MINE.COBTOY.        The number of Merchant Vessels under organised Convoy and the  losses sustained          whilst in Convoy during the last two weeks are as follows : CONVOYS.	WEEK ENDED FEBRUARY 23RD.		WEEK ENDED MARCH 2ND.		NO. OF SHIPS CONVOYED.	NO. LOST.	NO. OF SHIPS CONVOYED.	NO. LOST.ATLANTIC TRADES:  HOMEWARD.................. OUTWARD .................. SCANDINAVIA LERWICK HUMBER ......... FRENCH COAL TRADES ............... MEDITERRANEAN LOCAL ............... TOTAL......	61 106 145 289 209	3 1	184 128 63 295 256	1 1 1 2	810	4	926	5    The five ships lost during the week ended March 2nd were sunk by submarine, andof the two shown in  the Mediterranean Local Convoys  one was on the  Malta-Bizertaroute  and  the other on the Gibraltar-Genoa route.DEFENSIVE       During the week 35 merchant vessels were fitted to take primary armament, andARMAMENT  39 ^0 take supplementary armament.              The number of howitzers and bomb throwers  delivered to date is 768.                                                                 1MINE PRO-       1,401  merchant vessels have been fitted with  Otter installations, and  356 warshipsTECTIONGEAR. are now fitted with Paravane equipment.MOVEMENTS  OF  ENEMY  SHIPS.MERCHANT-      Five enemy merchant ships have this week arrived at, and eight have sailed from,MEN.      Norwegian ports outside the Cattegat.  None  have entered or left Rotterdam.              Thirteen vessels  are reported as  having left Delfzyl with enemy coal for Sweden,          and eight are reported to have passed Elsinore  during the week.HAIDERS.        The steamship &quot; Wolf &quot; is stated to have arrived at Kiel on February 24th, and the          steamship &quot;  Igotz Mendi,&quot; which ran ashore to the westward of the  Skaw on the same          day, is reported to be badly aground.  All hands have been landed from this ship, and          the British passengers are returning to England.              The schooner &quot; Lutece,&quot; which was captured and equipped as a raider by the crew          of the &quot; Seeadler,&quot; after the latter had run aground at  Mopeha, appears to have been          abandoned owing to  her leaky condition, and  the crew are reported  to have  landed in          October last on Easter Island,  a Chilean possession, in the South  Pacific.   They are          now said to have arrived at Talcahuano, Chile,  on March 2nd in the Chilean schooner          &quot; Falcon,&apos;&apos; and to have been placed on board the interned German steamer &quot; Memphis &quot;          pending instructions  from the Chilean Government, the local naval  authorities  having          taken charge of their rifles and arms.              If the foregoing report is true there would  appear to be no enemy raiders,  other than          submarines,  now at large.
                 ss:v. UNITED KINGDOM SHIPBUILDING.    7 v-  The  number  and gross  tonnage  of  merchant steamships of 100 tons and upwards  Merchantreported  completed in January  and February are as follows :                           Vessel Con-                                                                                            struction.                                               Number of Vessels. Gross Tonnage.                Month-                    January ............       21             58,568                    February      .........       33             100,038     The output for February is considerably below the monthly average of the last quarterof 1917,  but  slightly  exceeds  the  monthly average for  the whole of that year.   Thereduced output in the first two months of this year is  due to a variety of causes but ismainly attributable to the time lost in the yards at the commencement of the year onaccount of holidays, bad weather and industrial unrest.     The  following  statement  shows the  position of  British  Merchant  tonnage  of  Gains and500  tons  gross  and upwards at 28th February, 1918, compared with 31st January. 1918 :   lQSses m                                                                                            February.                                                                      - Tons (Gross).Tonnage of  British   Mercantile Marine available  for service at      31st January, 1918..................              14,290,830        Add Vessels under or awaiting heavy repairs    ......                921,324Total tonnage of  British Mercantile Marine at 31st January, 1918                         15,212,154                           Gains.    New vessels (British built) entered for service   ...    ......      96,908    New vessels purchased Overseas   ...     ...    ...    ...    ...       6,978    Vessels transferred from Foreign Flag    ...    ...    ...    ...       7,099    Enemy vessels captured and entered for service under British        Flag     ...   :...    .....:   &quot;&apos;.*..    :..    ...       -    Vessels coming under British  Flag for causes other than those        mentioned above     ...    ...     ...    ...    ...    ...       4,447    Vessels discharged and read)1-  for service after repairs (10  days        and over)...............    .........     796,296                                                             --911,728                     Losses.Vessels sunk by Enemy action    ...     ...          ...    ...     224,834Vessels sunk by Enemy action on Auxiliary service    ......        Vessels sunk by Marine risk      ...     ...    ...    ...    ...      27,580Vessels transferred to Foreign Flag...     ...    ...    ...    ...        868Vessels lost to British Flag for causes other than those mentioned    above   ......    ...    ...     ...    ....    ...    ...      17,893Vessels laid up during month  for repairs (10 days and over)    or damaged and not yet ready for permanent repair     ...    1,679,0291,950,2041.038,476Tonnage of British Mercantile Marine available for service at 28th    February, 1918     .................................   14,173,678        Add vessels under or waiting heavy repairs ...     ...    ...    ............     882,733Total  tonnase of British Mercantile Marine at 28th February, 1918...............   15,056,411Net Loss during month      .........     155,743     The corresponding figures for January and December last were net losses of 137,023and 172,057 tons respectively, and for November a net gain of 10,500  tons.   The increaseover the January figure of new British vessels entered for service in February is morethan counterbalanced by the increased losses  in  February due  to enemy action, whichare 27 per cent,  greater than in January.    (0 1014)                                                                        A 3
WARSHIPCONSTRUC-TION.GERMAN.Austro-HUNGARIAN.     The  following is a statement  of British warship  and  auxiliary vessels  completedduring  the months  of  January and February, 1918.         _Description of Vessel.January.No.Displacement  Tonnage.February.NO.Displacement  Tonnage.Light Cruisers   ...Flotilla Leaders  ...DestroyersPatrol BoatsSubmarines     ...Depot ShipsSloopsCoastal Motor BoatsOilersPetrol Carriers  ...Trawlers....     ...Tugs     ......Drifters  ...Minesweepers  (Tunnel)Minesweepers  (T.S.)Minesweepers  (Paddle)Admiralty BargesTotal 1 2 1 2 1 3 212 1 11,7502,620 8931,5803,4603,8702,2906,682 290 8202624.255 4 2 1 2 3 2 110 1 2 1 2 4.378,3805,2401,7861,0702,580  306.9911,0005.588 500 370 8001,640  SO36.055                        ENEMY  WARSHIP  CONSTRUCTION.     The following table shows the position of new  German  Warship Construction  andthe numbers available at the present date :-Type.	Building.					Available.			Laid down since 1st Feb.	Launched since 1st Feb.	Total Number on the Slips.	Total Number launched.	Total number building.	Hf Number added since 1st Feb.	Number lost or destroyed J as ascer-tained since 1st Feb.	Total number avail-able.Battleships (Dread-nought type only) Battle Cruisers Light Cruisers, in-eluding Minelay-ing Cruisers Torpedo Boat Destroyers Submarines	10	10	4 2 10f 24 70	2 2 4 12 117	6 4 36 187	10	7	19 5 32 193 184                              f Number approximate.The following table  indicates the  present  position of Austro-Hungarian WarshipConstruction:                     Type.Battleships:    Dreadnoughts    Other types.....    2nd Class   .....  &apos;  3rd Class   .....Battle Cruisers  .....Cruisers  ........Light Cruisers:    Helgoland Class    Other Light CruisersT.B.D.&apos;s:    Tatra Class (1916) ..    Improved Tatra Class (1917)    Other T.B.D.&apos;sT.B.&apos;s    ......SubmarinesBuilding.Projected.Built.   12(REPORTED)    9(REPORTED)4632 2 6 4 61290   18*(APPROX.)* 2 OTHERS REPORTED COMPLETED.
                     FOREIGN  NAVAL  INTELLIGENCE.                                     RUSSIA.    A British, cruiser and French and American men-of-war are being sent to Murmanskto reinforce H.M.S. &quot; Glory.&quot;  Negotiations with the authorities at Archangel as regardsthe exchange of stores for provisions,  &amp;c., are believed to be proceeding satisfactorily.    Clause VI  of the Russo-German peace terms states that &quot; Warships in the  Black,Baltic, and Arctic Seas are to return immediately to Russian ports and remain there untilthe conclusion of  a general peace, or be disarmed.   Warships of the Entente within thesphere of Russian authority are to  be regarded as Russian ships.&quot;    The British Naval Attache is remaining at Petrograd in order to attempt to organisethe destruction of the more valuable ships.   The coast batteries on Nargen Island, offRevel, have already  been destroyed.  Revel is now in the hands  of the Germans,  hutno news has  yet been received  of the capture of Russian ships.                                     SWEDEN.    The Germans are occupying the Aaland Islands as a base for operations  in Finland.Swedish troops are at-present in these islands, and the Swedish Government had informedthe German Government at the same time as the  other Powers, that her troops wouldonly be retained there as a police force until a general peace was signed.   The relationsbetween Germany and Sweden are believed to be strained in consequence of. this episode.    Sweden has refused to assist the Finnish Government, whom the Germans are nowon their way to help.  It is reported that General Mannerheim, commanding the FinnishGovernment forces, is not short of provisions.                                      CHINA.    The situation on the Yangtze gives cause for apprehension.  Desultory fighting hasoccurred above Hankow between Northern and  Southern troops, the latter of whomappear to be little  better  than an undisciplined mob.  A British Vice  Consul  (fromHankow), while proceeding by river to negotiate, was fired on and was unable to land.Several  Japanese vessels, including the river gunboat &quot;Fushimi,&quot;  have also been firedon, and the gunboat retaliated.   The Japanese Admiral is at Hankow and should be ableto control the situation, but he does not appear to be acceptable to the American S.N.O.                                   ARGENTINA.                         . -    The Argentine  Government announce  their  intention of acquiring cruisers andsubmarines immediately after the war.   The placing of contracts is not yet  decided, butthe Minister of Marine denies the German press report that the orders will be placed inGermany.NAVAL STAFF,      March 1th, 1918.[APPENDICES.
                                                                    APPENDIX  1.STATEMENT off  NUMBERS AND TONNAGE OF SAILINGS AND LOSSES OF BRITISH MERCHANT STEAMSHIPS OF  OVER 500 TONS GROSS REGISTER FOR                                                         THE  WEEK ENDED 2ND MARCH, 1918.          TRADEUnited Kingdom, to and from-North America Coast ...    .........Gulf and West Indies ...    ...    ......Gibraltar...    ...Dakar, St. Vincent, W. Africa and S. AmericaBay,  Portugal and Spain, West of GibraltarScandinaviaHolland  ...Russia   ......    . ...    .........Total Overseas Traffic to and from United  KingdomCoasting............Cross-Channel  ......Total of  Coasting and Cross-ChannelGrand Total of traffic  to and from United  KingdomSailings.Losses.Percentage of Losses to Sailings.In.		Out.		Total.		In.		Out.		Total.		In.		Out.		Total.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No. 1 1 1 2 1	Tons..	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.	No.	Tons.36 14 18 15 19 14 5	204,719 77,586 101,646 77,877 48,058 21,390 6,076	45 17 44 14 15 10 5 2	323,904 95,898 173,052 72,140 24,454 17,753 6,839 3,096	81 31 62 29 34 24 10 2	528,623 173,484 274,698 150,017 72,512 39,143 12,915 3,096	1 1 2	4,502 6,696 6,413	1 1	4,880 806		4,880 4,502 6,696 6,413 806	7.14 5.56 10.53	5.80 6.59 13.34	2.22 20.0	1.51 11.79	1.23 3.23 1.61 5.88 10.0	.92 2.59 2.44 8.84 6.24121 99*	537,352 317,130*	152 115*	717,136 462,647*	273 214* 569 504	1,254,488 779,777*	4 5*	17,611 21,158*	2 2*	5,686 6,913*	6 7* 4 5 9 7*	23,297 28,071*	3.31 5.05*	3.28 6.67*	1.32 1.74*	.79 1.49*	,2.20 3.27*	1:86 3.60*246	406,784	258	395,184		998,584 801,968	2	2,287	3	10,265		9,224 12,552	.81	.56	1.16	2.60	.70-.99	.92 1;57 	 	 	 	1,073 1,201*	1,800,552 2,079,861*	 	 	 	 		21,776 18,309*	  -	--	 	-	.84 .58&apos;*	1.29 . .88* 	 	 	 	1,346 1,415*	3,055,040 2,859,638*	 	 		 	15 14* 2 2*	45,073 46,380* 10,715 6,493*	 	 	 	 	1.11 .99*	1.47 1.62*Losses on other Trades Total Losses for Week............																							 	 	 	 	17 16*	55,788 52,873*						* PREVIOUS WEEK&apos;S FIGURES,
&quot;STATEMENT showing by Trades as regards British Merchant  Steamships of  over 500 tons    gross the percentage of tonnage  sunk by Enemy Action to tonnage sailing to and    from United Kingdom Ports in recent weeks.TBADB United Kingdom, to and from 	Week ended 9th Feb.	Week ended 16th Feb.	Week ended 23rd Feb.	Week ended 2nd Mar.fin ... North America Coast ............K Out ... t Total FIN ... Gulf and West Indies ............-i Out ... L Total FIN ... Gibraltar..................-1 Out... 1 Total fIn -Dakar, West Africa and South America ... -K Out ... L Total FIN ... Bay, Portugal and Spain, West of Gibraltar ... 4 Out ... t Total FIN ... Scandinavia..................-1 Out ... L Total FIN ... Holland ...... ...... ... ... \ Out ... [ Total FIN ... Russia ... ...............-i Out ... t Total 1 FIN ... Total of above Trades .........^ Out ... L Total Coasting ...... ... ... ... ... Total FIN ... Cross-Channel ...............-i Out ... 1 Total * Total of all United Kingdom Trades	4.57 6.36 5.31 3.71 6.64 5.22 S.20 5.67 6.82	1.14 .57 6.18 2.91 12.85 6.86	13.27 4.42 9.32 3.17 5.46 8.34 6.84 7.62 6.67 1.49 3.60	1.51 .92 5.80 2.59 6.59 2.44 13.34 8.84 11.79 6.24	3.45 4.35 3.88	.93 1.34 1.14		3.28 .79 1.86	.86 .40	.58 .22 .12	.96 1.08 .51 .79	.92 .56 2.60 1.57	1.58	.69	-1.62	1-.47[APPENDIX III.
APPENDIX III.STATEMENT of the number of British and foreign merchant vessels sunk, damaged, or molested  during weeks ended  February  23rd  and_. _                March 2nd, 1918,  according to areas.Area. *	Sunk.						Damaged, but not Sunk.						Unsuccessfully attacked.						Attacks.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Totals.		1,600 te*s and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Totals.		1,600 tons and over.		Under 1,600 tons.		Totals.		Totals,		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		Week ended		23Feb.	2 Mar.	23Feb.	2 Mar.	23Feb.	2 Mar.	23Feb.	2 Mar.	23Feb.	2 Mar.	23Feb.	2 Mar.	23Feb.	2 Mar.	23Feb.	2 Mar.	23Feb.	2 Mar.	23Feb.	2 Mar.Arctic and White Sea ... / GRITI?H- - -^ it oreign Atlantic (Northern)......1J^1.811&apos;&apos;&apos; (^Foreign Atlantic (Southern)......^Foreign&apos; of Biscay ; ......(^h... Gibraltar-Azores ....../British... \, foreign South oLMogador ....../ 5RITISH-&apos; -\li oreign North Sea - ....../British... -.. V; - V. Foreign English Channel &quot;....../British... -6 \ Foreign Irish Sea and Bristol Channel/GRITISH-\, Foreign Mediterranean ....../British... \^ it oreign Totals ....../British... \. h oreign	1 2 1 1 5 3 2 2	1 1 1 1 7 1 2 1	1 1 1 2	1 1 1 3 3 2 1 2	1 - 1 2 1 5 1 5 2 2	1 1 2 1 4 3 9 2 2 3	1 1 1	1 1 1 2	1	 	1 1 1 1	1 1 1 2	1 3 1 1 1 1	2 1 1	1 2	. 1 1	1 3 2 2 1 1 1	2 1 1 0	1 2 1 1 3 2 &apos; 8 3 8 3 3 2	1 1 2 1 1 4 1 5 3 12 2 4 3	14 3	12 3	3 2	6 8	17 5	18 11	2 1	5	1	 -	2 2	5	4 4	1 3	2 1	2	6 5	3 3	25 12	26 14

</content>
</cab>
