<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/44/0 images: 253-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETHis Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.)( i his Document Is the Property ofdepartment of Information,    F.S.W./019Intelligence BureauColonel UOBag200Id        WEEKLY  REPORT  ON  SPAIN.   XIX.       ************** ***mamm*mwmm- - m axifcwttwwMwiM^MMMiwn^^^               (March 7th 1918)   The much-anticipated Elections are over and there is no  sign thatthey vd.ll produce any new era in  Spanish political history.The results are more or less in accordance with the propheciesquoted in the Report of a fortnight ago.   The principal differenceis that the ^loc1 of the Left which with the Regionalists  wasput down as likely to secure some 90 seats among its varioussections, has in fact only secured 65.   It was thought that therewould be some 50 or 60 Reformists and Republicans and  some  50 or40 Regionalists.   There are, in fact, only 15 Republicans,9 Reformists (more moderate Republicans who were Monarchical alittle while ago and might easily become so again) and 6 Socialists.Lerroux, the Republican leader was defeated in two constituenciesand has no seat in the Cortes.   Melchiadcs Alvarez, the leader of theReformists, was defeated in one place, but elected in  another.The imprisoned Strike Committee won seats at Madrid, Barcelonaand Valencia and with them the Socialists will have six Deputiesas against one in the last Parliament.   But as a whole the anti-Monarchical groups suffered a great disappointment, and lostground instead of gaining it.   The Regionalists (provincialHome Rulers) gained 20 seats in Catalonia, the home of theircreed and party:  and this was less than was expected.   But onthe other hand they gained another 15 &amp;n other provinces who werereturned as Andalusians, Asturians, and so en, and represent thesame order of political ideas.   There were 9 Carlists elected anda dozen or 13 deputies are split.-ainong,^ytJaer&quot;-^tiny^groups, including
a solitary Agrarian Deputy.   So ranch for the Deputies who are outside the old Liberal andConservative Parties.   these two parties, as explained in the lastReport,  are each now divided into three groups, under six leaders.These have come bade in very much the anticipated numbers, some ofthem like Dato and Maura and Alba a little stronger, dividing amongthem the seats lost by the Left.   The final figures are: Followers of the Prime Minister (Marquis of Alhncemas)   95.   &quot;       &quot;  Count Romanones                             40.   &quot;       &quot;  Senor Alba                                  30.   These are t,he three nominally Liberal groups.   The threeConservative groups are divided as follows in the new Cortes:Followers of Senor Dato (the official Conservatives)   94    w     !&apos;  Senor Maura (a former Prime Minister)     27    &quot;     :!  Senor la Oierva (Minister of War)         25   As none of these groups act at all consistently together, it isobvious that no leader has a Majority of the Cortes, which contain408 Deputies.   Evan if the three Liberal groups reunited, which isnot very likely, they only come to 165 Deputies.   Such a situation is plainly a very difficult one.   In the old ays any Ministry which dissolved came back with an overwhelmingniajority.   How, partly ov/ing to the fact that the Cabinet wascomposed of men of several groupa and therefore had to divide itsfavours, and partly because it did really to a large extent allowand encourage freedom of election, the new Parliament.    a, djyJLdjsd.&quot;body and provides no sure support for any Statesman.   Nor have theDeputies any greatly increased authority: . for though not nominatedfey the Government, they owe their^-6eats-^ry&quot;&quot;iargely to the oldforces of influence and intrigue:  and to bribery which jrasriieverso freely employed.
I   In the last Report it was mentioned that the Prime Minister  had announced Mtat he would not retain office after the  election.   This intention has not so far been acted uoon.  On the  contrary Senor La Cierva seems to have raised the question of the continuance in  office of the present Ministry which has no majority of its own.    This and other things behind the scenes produced the resignation  of the  whole Cabinet.  But the King requested the Marquis of /.lhucemas  to remain Prime Minister:  and he has done so with the same  colleagues except that Ventosa and Rodes, the two Catalan Regionalists, have resigned and been re-placed by Silvela, the late Pood Controller,  an intimate friend of iihe Prime- Minister&apos;s and formerly Editor of his  parper the Manans,  and a certain-Senor Cara^ who &quot;becomes Finance Minister in place of Senor Ventosa,  who has been negotiating the Commercial and financial agreements  (recently under diaeuesion -and partly signed)- with France and  America.   The reason given for these resignations is that the two Ministers (who, it is to be remembered, were members-of the-  --i^wiaJJ^ ^Parliament called at Barcelona 6 months ago) demanded that constitutional  re-                        under forms should be at once/^ta&amp;en  and ^announced by the  Government: and&quot; for this the rest of the Cabinet, consisting -of  members of  the old parties, were not-prepared.   This is orobably true.   But it is not -the whole truth.   It is known that Senor La Cierva,. whose.ability, ambition and reliance on the  rmy were discussed in  the  last Report,, has not only proposed to -the Cabinet.considerable  army  Reforms&apos;, (consisting, it is said, mainly in a further swelling of the budget for officers&apos; pay already believed to be the mostrexor^rfcgant in Kurotte:  the Spanish Army in 1913 had more Colonels  than the German.)l*ut desired to carry them out by Royal Decree without submitting them for the approval of the Cortes.   This is legally  possible under a law passed  last year authorising ezT)onditure without Parliamentary
authority during the war.    But the sum involved is large:  thematter cannot he regarded as urgent:  and Count Romanones has in-formed the Prime Minister that, if he peremits this course to hefollowed,  Senor Cimeno4,  his representative in the Cabinet, willresign.   As these words are written the news comes that La Cierva hashad his way and that the military reforms will he authorised byRoyal decree^.   There apnears to he some kind of concession as tothese being laid before the Cortes for ratification and as to theexpenditure being postponed till june, but Count Romanones evident-ly regards them as insufficient, as Senor Cimeno has resigned.   Hiresignation following on those of Ventosa and Rodes deprive theAllies of two if not three (Rodes is rather an uncertain quantity)of their best friends in the Cabinet.   The responsibility therefor-which seats upon the Prime Minister, and ultimately still more uponthe King,  is very heavy.   Is the King prepared to see the Governmeof Spain become pro-German and to risk the oossible consequences ofthat course, both domestic and foreign?   The further news &quot;grhich has  lust come in should surely give himpause.   A pro-Ally paper has published a facsimile-of a letterfrom the First Secretary of the German Embassy to an Anarchistnamed Pascual, well&quot;knarcm, to the police.   Such gentry are: alwaystwo-edged tools to play with and Pascual appears to have given thegame awap1 and told the whole story to the &quot;Sol&quot;, as soon as thatpaper published the document which is believed tto ha&quot;ve been ob-tained by Prench agents-   The letter ^shown him receiving moneyfrom the Germans for the printing of &quot;your flyleaf&quot;, which was ananarchist sheet directed against shipowners-and is also re-produce.&quot;by the Sol.   Pascual describes himself as having paid severalvisits to the Embassy, where he was received.by the Secretaries anugiven instructions to create disturbances, organise revolutionary
 strikes,  and in particular to foment attacks of every kind upon                       E; Count Romanones.    Some of the proposals wer  of such a nature that pascual shrank fr&amp;m them though the Germans promised that they vrould protect him from the police.   He says that, as might he ex- per ed, he was particularly desired to produce strikes that would interfere with the export trade to the Allies and  that in some fac- tories the Germans have workmen in their pay for these purposes.   &quot;That effect will these revelations have?  The Sol has been suo-Ipres3ed so far as possible at the request of the German Embassy: but&apos;the mischief is done. *  Is it oo3Sible that the German Ambassador can be allowed to remain at his post?.  Unluckily it is:  for there appear to be no limits &quot;tot Spanish complaisance or  Spanish fears.   The revelations of German complicity with revolutionary action are probably no revelations to the King or the other authorities and as th*ey have looked the other way before they will probably Incline to . do so again.   But their hands may &apos;   possibly be  forced by public? indignation.   Anyhow the public revelation must be of use to the-Ulies. -  It will warn strikers in the eroort trade as to whose &apos;agents those who call for strikes may be:  and It  must alarm all that Is genuinely Conservative in Spain and make it decidedly less in- olined to follow in the wake of an Embassy which troves such a very strange patron of the cause of law and order.   Manjr even of the officers of m the Army, one wuld suppose, *will be disgusted and indignant.               &apos; &apos;            &apos;            &apos;&apos;      -. .  .   All this.may make, the, supposed olans of La Cierva jnpre difficult of realisation.   His eneniies-say that he is-a eomnle-te reactionaryand disbelieves in all liberal&quot;ideas and forced and is inclined there fore to intrigue with ths&apos;sArmy and use military support in further- ance&apos;nf. the objects which may  or may net be confined within ConSti- tutional  limits.   It is obvious that whatever his&apos;private sympathies may be (and he is  said toot to jbe^otheTwl5e--thari--^Auglophil).t such a
                                                                  205                             - 6 -programme would necessarily make him tend to lean on German supoort.He cannot rely upon any popular support,  for he has never been for-given for his share in the execution of Perrer, as event which wasthe chief cause of Maura&apos;3 resignation of the Conservative leadership^He is plainly trying to unite the Army and the King and to make hime-     theself/indispensable man of both. .  He lately organised a greaC militaryceremony and banquet at which the King presided and scenes of en-thusiastic loyalty ocoureed.   The officers had had free railwaytickets given them and official pressure was used to induce them toattend.   But it is likely enough that the loyalty was genuine andgood fudges regard the affair as a sign that the power of the Juntasat any rate as a centre ,of&apos; disloyalty is rapidly passing away.  &apos;   If the movement is successful the present w&amp;ak Prime &quot;Minister will           &apos;                 i *either disappear or be used as a mere tool and La Cierva will rule underthe King with Army mpport.&apos;.  But Is the King orepared to run the risksof this, especially if, as -seem3 likely, it involves a definitelypro-German policy?   The country is already indignant at the submarine-outrages:  it will not be made  less so by the  anarchist revelations.Besides whatever international  sympathies Spaniards -may have they areno less sensitive  to their interests than other people.  And there isno doubt - the Spanish papers  themselves are pointing it out now -that all the commercial interests of S ain bind her to- the-Allies:and that Germany,  on the contrary,  is obviously interested in destroy-ing a  trade  from whioh it  can  terive no benefit. *  A Barcelona  cottonman or -a Valencia  orange merchant may be pro-German till his ppcketis-touched:  but  if a  pro-German Ministry causes America to send nocotton and England to  take no  $ranges their Eiews-^are-.sooS -modified.Moreover  though a  Government  resting on military support and franklyopposing  the constitutional  and parliamentary -development ,of Spain,might  safely rely  on  its material strength  for a time,  the King canhardly be  blind to the fact  that  he would be risking the whole  future
of his dynasty by identifying himself with the policy believed to bedesired by La Cierva.    Political life in Spain is weak and back-ward and its growth ought not to be forced;  but  there is a soirttworking in Spain as elsewhere which can hardly fail to spread ul-timately to the Army,  and which would make a merely reactionarypolicy not only short  lived but fatal to the King aad to the insti-tution of I-fonSTfichy.   At present the King is said to be supportingLa Cierva, probably because he feels he must have the Army support.But it is to be hoped  that he will take a little  longer view and corsuit wiser and more liberal statesmen.   His.best course would seemto Englishmen to be that suggested in the last Reoort, viz. a com-bination of Dato and ^omanones, on a frankly oro-Ally basis:  forwhich the Submarine and Anarchist incidents would seem to  ive anadmirable reason.   But what he will do it  is impossible to say:                         un-and for the moment Dato,/like  Romanones, is said to be satisfiedwith the compromise or concessions in the Army Reform question made,as mentioned above, by La Cierva and the Government.   We must waitto see when the *0ortes will meet and what action  it will take.

</content>
</cab>
