<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/44/0 images: 273-279</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Telegrams-&quot;SHIPMINDER, VIC, LONDON.&quot;                       OnWl W**  Any further communication on thissubject should be addressed to-The Secretary,           J^FChR OABt/U^S,   Ministry of Shipping,      &apos;^   ----St. James&apos;s Park, SI &apos;h-          Bl             London, S.W. lo 1and the following number quoted: ^\ /fi T is?MINISTRY  OF  SHIPPING,9th March, 1918.(This Document is the Property cf                           RI&amp;yBritanrijc Majesty^ GovernmeniSir,                      &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;             &quot;*&quot;  ----          In continuation of my letter  of the 2nd instant,I am directed by the Shipping Controller to  report forthe information of the War Cabinet as follows    (1)  Convoys.            (a)  Homeward Bound Convoys.                 Since the last report twelve  convoysconsisting  of 183 ships (1,256,700 tons  deadweight) havearrived.    There were two casualties by enemy action.The s.s. &quot;EUMAIUS&quot; was torpedoed and sunk off South Bastof Falmouth on the 25th ultimo, and the  Armed Merchant                   *Cruiser &quot;CALGABIAN&quot; was torpedoed and sunk on the 2ndinstant, 8  miles from Rathlin Island, while  steaming 19knots and escorted by two destroyers after having leftthe Convoy.          There were no casualties by marine  peril.          There are now on passage home  17 convoysconsisting  of 264 ships.            (b)  Cutward Bound Convoys.                 Since the last report 7  convoys consistingof 125 ships (804.800 tons deadweight)  have  been  escortedthrough the  danger zone.          There were 2 casualties by enemy action.   Thes.s. &quot;IMCHA0I\T&quot; was torpedoed and sunk off Sardinia on the27th ultimo, and the s.s. &quot;TIBERIA&quot; was  torpedoed in theIrish Sea and sunk off Black Head on the 26th ultimo.
          There were no casualties by marine peril.          There are now in the danger zone 4 convoysconsisting of 72 ships.          Statements are enclosed shewing respectively(a) the number of convoys and tonnage convoyed, and(b) the percentage of Steamers, gross registered tonnageand deadweight capacity sunk on the different routes uptill the 2nd instant.    (2)  Direct Convoys between Norway &amp; United Kingdom.            Homeward.            Two homeward bound convoys consisting of39 ships have arrived from Bergen,   There were nocasualties of any kind.            Outward.            One outward bound convoy of nine ships arrivedoff the Norwegian Coast on the 27th ultimo, withoutcasualties.            Another outward convoy of 15 vessels leftMethil on the 1st instant, and arrived off the NorwegianGoast on the 3rd instanti    (3)  Finance.            During the week ended the 2nd instant the sumof  1,064,405 was paid in compensation for loss ofrequisitioned ships, making a total of  48,822,209 paidon this account since the  1st April 1917.    (4)  New Tonnage delivered.            The s.s. &quot;WAS EAMBLER&quot; built at Sunderland wasdelivered on the 5th instant.  This ship has been fitted(as an experiment) with the Yarrow Anti-Submarine smokefitting for use within the danger zone.  The effect of thisfitting is to divert the smoke from the ship5s funnel to                                                     outlets
outlets on the ship1s sides, and to cause the smoke to falltowards the water instead of rising above the ship in theusual manner (see photograph attached).          The s.s. &quot;WAR AMAZON&quot; built at Kobe, Japan, wasdelivered on the 5th instant.    (5)  Requisitioned Neutral Vessels.          -  The following casualties to requisitionedNorwegian ships have been reported.          The s.s. &quot;1STB1LLA&quot; (Norwegian) was mined andsunk on the 5th instant, and the s.s. &quot;BOBGA&quot; is believedto have been mined on the 3rd instant.  The s.s. &quot;MUNTBR&quot;was lost by marine peril.    (6)  In view of the imperative necessity  for increasingthe imports of cereals during the next few weeks,instructions have been given that during the month oflarch grain shall be loaded in preference to Admiraltyfuel oil in the double bottoms and deep tanks of vesselsproceeding across the Atlantic to the United  Kingdom.Where grain is not available, however, oil is to beloaded as hitherto.    (7)  Hospital Ships (Naval),            An offer has been received by the Admiraltyfrom the United States Government of the services of oneor possibly two American Hospital Ships in European Waters.After consultation with the Departments concerned, thisoffer has been gratefully accepted, and Admiral Sims hastelegraphed to the United States Navy Department recommendingthat both ships be sent for service with the Grand Fleetfor both British and American forces.  If this proposal                                                  is
220is agreed to by ths United States Navy Department, it willresult in the release of one or more British Hospital shipsof equivalent capacity for other services.         In addition, arrangements are in progress torelieve the Hospital Ship &quot;KaRABAKaV at present employed in theMediterranean.          This will result in the release of another largeship for trooping or commercial service.    (8)  RUSSIAN situation.          The American s.s. &quot;DORA&quot; referred to my letter of26th January was intercepted &quot;by British Naval Forces and sentinto Lerwick, where she is being held pending the receipt of theAmerican Governments concurrence in a proposal to dischargeher at Liverpool, and to tranship that part of her cargo con-sisting of foodstuffs to a steamer which will shortly  be loadingat Liverpool for Murmansk.           AS a result of discussionsbetween the variousDepartments concerned, it has been decided to send two or threesteamers to Archangel with such articles as rice, salt, coffee,herrings, and cement, which would be delivered to the localauthorities at Archangel in exchange for the most valuable warstores now lying there.  The British steamers &quot;SGBA&quot; and&quot;NASCOPIE&quot; - the latter is specially built for ice-work - areexpected to commence loading at Liverpool during the next fewdays.  It is intended that these ships shall be escorted intoArchangel by a ship of war, an Icebreaker which has recently beencompleted in the Tyne and which has been requisitioned by theAdmiralty.   The exact composition of the cargoes to be despatchedto Archangel is not yet decided; particulars as to what is mostrequired are expected hourly from the British Consul.          The large Russian cargo steamers &quot;NOVGOROD&quot;, &quot;YAROSLAVL&quot;and &quot;ALTAI&quot; - bound for this country - and &quot;IRTYSH&quot; - bound forAmerica - have now been permitted by the local authorities to                                                         le are
                                                     -    221leave Archangel with part cargoes of flax, hemp, wood, etc.on board.   There are consequently no large steamers fit forservice now left in Archangel.          The Russian steamers &quot;MINSK&quot; and &quot;KURSK&quot; havebeen requisitioned by the British Government,  transferredto the British Flag, and handed over to the Gunard Line tomanage.   The Russian crews have been repatriated.  Similaraction will shortly be taken with the Russian s.s. &quot;CZAR&quot;,and probably with other Russian and Finnish steamers.    (9)  Coal Position in South Africa.            The position reported in paragraph 5 of yourletter of the 2nd instant has improved and it has now beenfound possible to arrange for two or three coal cargoesto be loaded for South iunerica.   (10)  Stores for the British Army in Prance.           The quantity of military stores discharged inPrance during the week ending 2nd March, was 179,024.   (11)  ghinese Coolies.           In accordance with the War Cabinet decision ithas now been arranged with the War Office that no moreChinese Coolies shall be shipped.                  I am,                       Sir,                   Your obedient Servant,                (Signed)  JOHN ANDBRSON.
222STATEMENT SHOWING NUMBER OF CONVOYS AND TONNAGE        CONVOYED TO 2nd MARCH 1918.222345442323546DirectionHalifaxSydneyNew YorkNorfolkS.LeoneDakarGibraltarMedn.th.ro&apos;  TOTALShips  171  537  633  777  164  282-  793   80HOMEWARDS      Gross   Registered   Tonnage ,071 ,532 .792  762-,1911,215&quot; 462  50531,661,515,226,547,353,619,239 026 Dead- weightCapacity1,814,7003,665,2005,425,6005,662,1001,370,6001,838,1003,946,700  714,400Sinkings        Dead-        weight No.   Capacity 2 6 712 3 414 421,80047,30048,50086,50021,10023,90000,60034,1003,457    17,553,186  24,637,400    52    363,800            Percentage of losses  1.49    1.46ivoys25594329464j)20Direction    ShipsFalmouthDevonportMilfordQueenstownLamiashLiverpool sp.Medn.thro&apos;  TOTAL3367121,083209500 11 80OUTWARDS   Gross  Registered   Tonnage   1,181,051   4,211,757   3,659,265  954,5032,804,611  125,703  518,007 Dead- weightCapacity1,677,9505,603,4006,13 8,8001,435,1503,921,100    87,700_742,700Sinkings      Dead-No. 3 1 5 8 MM 3 weightCapacity 20,300  7,100 34,900 62,900 32,7002,931    13 ,,654,897  19,986.800    20    158,400Percentage of losses  .68.79HOMEWARDS AND OUTWARDS14620fieDirectionHomewardsOutwards  TOTALShips3,4372,9316,568  GrossRegistered Tonnage Dead-* weightCapacity17,533,186  24,637,40015,054,897  li^iM^SOO31,186.085  44,624,200   Percentage of losses  Sinkings       &quot;Dead-        weight No.    Capacity. 52    363,800 20    158,400 72    522,2001.12      1.16.
223z1                        B.           CONVOY REPORT 2nd MARCH 1918.PERCENTAGE OB&apos; STEAMERS, GROSS REGISTERED  TONNAGE AND      DEAD WEIGHT CAPACITY SUNK  ON THE DIFFERENT                     ROUTES.                   HOMEWARDS.Ire ct ionBlifaxydneyew Yorkorfolk, Leoneakaribraltar6dn.thro&apos;TOTALShipscon-voyed  171  537  633  777  164  282  793   803,437   SINKINGSShips   G.R.T.    D.W.C. 2 6 712 3 414 45223,86029,14030,77753,74319,73915,43049,57123,230245,49021,80047,30048,50086,50021,10023,90080,60034,100Ships1.161.11.091.521.  81.41.734.76G.R.T.1.141.14 .811.411,631.251.974.4D.W.C.1.191.21 .891.51.521.282.4.56563,800  1.491.381.46OUTWARDS[irection   Ships    Ships     G.R.T.     D.W.C.  Ships    G.R.T.   D.W.C.galmouth       336 svonport      712flford     1,083Jieenstown     209 Mlash        500[iverpool ap.   11 Bdn.thro&apos;      30TOTAL2,931 3 1 5 8 mm 32012,919 4,46020,91445,75823,44820,800 7,10034,900.88.14.4662,900  1.5732,700  3.61107,499   158,400   .681.08 .11 .541.614.33 .781.1 .12 .571.584.35 .796.368    72HOMEWARDS AND OUTWARDS  552,989   522,200  1,121.121.16MEDITERRANEAN HOMEWARDS AND OUTWARDS16046,678    66,800  4.194.364.38

</content>
</cab>
