<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/44/0 images: 303-304</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Tins Document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.INDIAN BULLETIN No. 26.                                NOTES.   The additional  squadrons of cavalry now  being raised  in India arechiefly  for  internal defence  in  place of  cavalry  units  sent on  serviceoverseas.   Reports  have  been received  from  India that  the  Maris, a tribe inBaluchistan,  have been  giving trouble, and it  has  been  found necessaryto concentrate troops at certain points in case operations become necessaiy.   Telegram from Viceroy to Secretary of State for India for half-month                         ending Ath March 1918.   2759.  In continuation  of our  telegram  of the  16th ultimo, 2139.Following is submitted for information :    1. New Formations. Infantry  Battalions. Of  2-1  new battalions, twoare overseas, thirteen complete, three within 50, two within  100, three within150* and one within 250 of completion.   Of  21 additional battalions, one complete, one within  50,  three within200,  three within 300, one  within 350,  two  within 400,  two within 450,and eight within 500 of completion.   Of  the 12 battalions sanctioned in telegram dated 1st February, nuclei ofeight now en route.  Orders for formation of  remaining four battalions  willshortly be issued.   Cavalry  Squadrons. Of  10 Indian  Cavalry  squadrons  reported  in ourtelegram of  the  20th ultimo,  2255, three are  complete, two within 50, threewithin  60, one  within  70, and  one within 90 of  completion.  The  twosquadrons reported in our telegram of the 26th  ultimo, 2542, are within 70of completion.   Medical. 38 dressers engaged Indian Subordinate Medical  Department.   2. Munitions Board. Following  information   reported  up  to  27thFebruary : Railway material. For  Egypt,  16  miles  of  75-pound  rails,5,285  broad-gauge  sleepers,  1,256  crossing sleepers, and 40,407 narrow-gauge   sleepers.   For Mesopotamia,  10 miles of  , 75-pound  track   and16 miles of 50-pound track, all shipped since last reported.   Shipbuilding. Barges handed over  at Karachi, 53 Indian, 16 English,45 Canadian, and  63  port  barges  50  feet.   Handed over at Bombay. Three Indian and two port barges 50 feet.  Under re-erection  at Karachi. Five Canadian and four  English.  Under construction at Bombay. Fourcomposite and 18 port barges 50 feet.   Stern-wheel  tugs for re-erection.  Bombay. S.  45,  half  finished,  andS. 46,  work commenced.   Karachi. S. 41,  half  finished,  S. 42, workcommenced, and. S. 55, arrived.   Hospital stern-wheelers for re-erection.  Bombay. H.S.W.  16 arrived.   Craft  for East  Africa. 35-feet hospital  motor. launch,  despatched;72-feet  steam launch,  three-quarters  finished.   Two  45-feet steel  lightershanded over for  despatch. Four 30-feet steel canoes, completed.   Pontoons  for  Director of Railways, Baghdad. Two  35-feet  deckedpontoons, one  completed and one  three-quarters  finished.   Two  5Q-feetpontoons, completed.   Steam pinnaces. Two 46-feet  6 inches, both three-quarters finished.   36-feet diving boat and  28-feet mooring boat, despatched.  11.0 lightsteel pontoons, 75 despatched, 10 three-quarters finished,  17  half finished,and 8 a quarter finished.   Two anchor pick-up boats. Tenders for humans being considered.   Trawlers.  Trawlers  1 and  2. Scriening  complete, and  moulds  welladvanced, bulkhead plates  shaped  and punched.   Stem,  keel  and dead-woods, &amp;c,  completed.   Awaiting supply of angles.  Trawlers 3 and 4. Majority of  frames  bent.  Work of  flanging and punching keel and framesprogressing.     OT 593 60 3/IS
2   86-feet  steam  drifters. -Telegram lias been received  from Admiraltystating that offer could not be entertained (? on account of) prohibitive cost.   Proposed 1,600 ton composite-built cargo steamers. Now superseded  byproposed 1.900 ton steel cargo steamers.   Communicating with Admiralty.   3. Supplies. Timber. Shipped  since last report:  Basra, 1,592 tons ;Egypt, 2,704 tons ; Salonica, 161 tons;  Aden, 20 tons; and Bunder  Abbas&apos;18 tons.   Ordnance. Further 18 tons M.D. cordite were shipped to War  Office  on13th February.   Barrack Blankets. Quartermaster-General estimates 2,037,000 barrackblankets required  for year  1918-19.    Estimate  being  considered, andendeavour  will be made to meet demand from India, but it is feared  supplywill fall short of demand,  and substitutes will be necessary.   Pig-iron. Orders have issued prohibiting export and regulating manu-facturers&apos; output by Munitions Board.   Hides  and  Wool, Following  covers   period  since  report   dated1st February : -   Tanned Hides. 1,000  bales shipped from Bombay, 4,158 bales shippedfrom Madras, during January 1918.   Raiv Hides. 250 bales  shipped, from Karachi; no  shipment  reportedfrom Calcutta.  45,279 pieces purchased by Karachi Committee during fourweeks  ended  29th January,  and 179,476  pieces  purchased by  CalcuttaCommittee  during  four weeks ended  26tli January.  Balance of requisitionedhides at Rangoon, unsuitable for War  Office, was disposed of by  sale  toItalian Tanners&apos; Syndicate at requisition prices, plus interest at 6 per cent.,thus clearing Governments hide stocks at,  Rangoon.   Rides. Skins and Wool from Mesopotamia.-10L),il)0 sheep-skins, 19,575goat-skins,  7,350 cattle hides and 605 buffalo hides, shipped from Basrah toBombay.   Thibetan Wool. Purchases  by Government Agent  at Kalimpong up  to28th January amounted  to  12,576  maunds,  excluding purchases   undercontract of  9,000 maunds to end of December.   Medical Stores Department. Following articles which, prior to war wereimported, are now  being manufactured in  Medical Stores Depots in India tomeet our total requirements.  These are in addition to manufactures reportedin our telegram No. 8083. dated 1st June 1917 : Amylum, B.P., Butitalis(? Digitalis) preparations, Lysol  and Ferri  Sulphas, Thymol  Nux Aromicapreparations,  vermi-jelly,  anti-fly   spray, an  insecticide   substitute  forKeatingjs  powder, Barnber  oil;  Sinclair&apos;^  glue substitute  for  adhesiveplaster.  We have lately  succeeded in making following  preparations,  ofwhich  we  hope shortly to manufacture  our  total requirements : iEtlier,tannic acid, B.P., chaulmoogra oil (corrupt groups), (? oleum gynocardia),boric acid  and collodium.  flexile.   Arrangements have also been made forsupply  in  India of  practically  all  our  ordinary requirements of  varioussurgical  dressings  (excepting  first  field  dressings) for 1918-19.   Largeorders have been also placed to meet war demands.   4. Marine. Following are details of marine transport work for  fortnightended  26th  February: Transports sailed,  70 ;  tons  of stores  shipped,128,741.   Troops all classes &quot;embarked,  15,297.  Animals, 283.  Rivereraft,despatched,, 6.  Transports  fitted, 1.  Transports re-fitted, 6.   Transportsdismantling,  7.   5. Internal  Condition.-Operations   against Kukis in Manipur  pro-ceeding.   Outpost was raided in Lushai Hills and  four men wounded.Superintendent has proceeded to locality with reinforcements.   Political situation continues quiet.   High prices continue,  and rain is urgently needed  for  crops in Punjaband elsewhere.       India. Office,           March 1918.

</content>
</cab>
