<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/44/0 images: 352-354</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
285/ This Document is the Property of     I circulate for the informationof the Vlar Cabinet a memorandum pre-pared oy the Coal Controller  whichprovider for an extension of thepresent system of rationing coal fordomestic purposes outside  the Londonarea.                     A.  H.  STANLEY.Board of Trade,  12th March, 1913.
                                     j      Memorandum-on Rationing of Coal for Domestic purposes.     The output of coal from the mines will be reduced by thewithdrawal of miners for  -Jar services and the most seriouseffect will be noticeable in the coalfields not now fullycoping with the demands made upon them and it is estimated thatthe reduction in output in these coalfields will be between sixand sevsn million tons.     For various purposes it is estimated that the Ministry ofiviunitions will roquire during- 1918 something like seven milliontons more than tliev required in 1917,    Information is beine:elicited from the Ministry of Munitions as to the extent towhich their demands will bo modified by the reduction in theMinistryf s programma.     Public Utility Services have advanced claims for additionalquantities of coal amounting approximately to four million tons.     There is a general reduction in the supolv of raw materialfor textile, oil and metal industries (other than such parts ofthese industries as are engaged on war supplies) which may resultin a general dacline in tho demand for coal by these industries.Figures are not available and having regard to the uncertaintyof the measures to bo taken to deal with the situation which willariso in these industries, it is not possible to count upon anysubstantial economy.     The only safo course to adopt under the circumstances is toration coal supplies.  This has already been done with respecttc household coal in the Metropolitan area without experiencingany serious difficult? or causing any disturbance.     It is now proposed to extend tho scheme which has been ineffect in the Metropolitan area to the whole of England and vteles(excl&apos;--aive of contain coalfields) subject to such improvementsas have been suggested to those engaged in the work sinco Augustlast when it was first instituted.  The rationing of industrialcoal (except for minor or domestic industries) is deferred fortho moment.
287     It will be necessary to reduce the  scale of allowancesestablished for tho Metropolitan area during this winter byabout 20%.     It is proposed to establish a  compulsory usor of Coke asa portion of the supply of fuel to  domestic consumers of over12 tons.    It midit be necessary to bring to account gas andelectricity used for heating and cooking purposes.     The saving to be made on domestic coal is estimated atabout five million tons per annum.     The scheme will be applied under the auspices of the localauthorities these boine- srouced together into twelve  divisions.Negotiations are beine- commenced with a  view to determining  theboundaries of these divisions and to establish a local organisation.     A central co-ordinating control will be esthalished in  London.     It is hoped to have tho scheme issued and effective by  May1st.12th March,. 1918.

</content>
</cab>
