<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/17/0 images: 1-1</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.82(57). 28th November, 1957.
1. Joint Intelligence Committee. [Enter E.H.
P.M. Change in constitution. Circulation of reports.
2. Parliament.
R.A.B. Business for next week.
Motion for reference of privilege point to Judicial Cttee. Whips to be on.
F.A. debate may be needed before Xmas recess.
P.M. NATO mtg. will last until 19/12. Parlt. rises on 20/12.
R.A.B. They will ask for it before that mtg. Then to a gap on 11/12. Opposition and
Hinch will both press for it. We may have to concede it.
E.H. Wait &amp; see how gt. the pressure is.
3. Hebrides Rocket Range.
D.S. Deplorable delay in bringing facts to light. This new plan justified. But as much
disappointment among crofters at w’drawal as there was dismay at original
proposal. This gives us, much more cheaply, nearly all the facilities needed by
Services and M/Supply. Wd. draw up statement in consultn. with J.M.
G.W. Avoid impression tht. we shall never expand facilities in Hebrides. We may
x| need it. Leave door open.
J.H. Satisfied.
A.J. Endorse what G.W. says – may need it in 3 – 4 yrs’ time.
P.M. We shall be criticised for vacillation. Hope there won’t be another change, save
for possibility at x/.
What propn. of saving is on land-purchase &amp; what on bldgs thereon?
D.S. Not yet clear – mainly on bldgs etc., We are committed to buying the land if
owners hold us to it – tho’ we cd. do with less. Crofting rights : we must avoid
treating them badly : some have sold up stock etc., on assumptn. they are to be
cleared out.
J.M. This will be matter for music-hall jokes for 50 yrs.
Nervous of x/ because it means continuing uncertainty for crofters.
D.S. Can’t be sure tht. we shall never need it. But doubt if we can leave a legal
loophole to creep back.
P.M. Are you quite sure it’s practicable to extend Welsh ranges? What of shipping
routes?
 
 
H.W. 100 ships in each 24 hrs. pass thro’ extended area. May need a lot of rearrangement.
D.S. Risks are infinitesimal. Can’t be too restricted on firing.
P.T. Welcome redn. of cost from £18 M. to £4 M.
But only purpose of Hebrides range is now to fire Corporal &amp; its descendants.
We have spent only about £460.000 so far. Can’t we give it up altogether?
D.S. We have spent about £½ M. Propose to spend another £1½ M. Latter wd. soon
be consumed in cost of hiring alternative trial ground. Also Hebrides range cd. be
used by N.A.T.O. Also pol, row wd. be even greater if we abandoned it
altogether.
S.Ll. How can we explain our change of plan?
D.S. Economies followg. Defence W. Paper.
S.Ll. Any chance of having to revert to earlier plan?
D.S. No chance for 5 years.
P.M. Better to say we are going to restrict this range pro. tem. to ground to ground.
Take all land, but refrain from bldg.
R.A.B. Para 4. Not good govt.
P.M. Answer to para. 4 affects it. But saving is not on land, and much to be said for
not changing that part of the plan. * This should be considered. *
D.S. Subject only to not buying any land we don’t want if owners wish to retain it.
P.M. Also want report on wtr diffies. in para. 4 can be overcome.
1. Buy the freehold of whole area.
2. Compensate crofters dispossessed for the part of the range we intend to
use.
3. Compensate any crofters who have acted &amp; suffered loss as result of
earlier announcement.
4. Clear up doubts on para. 4.
D.S. On 4, I accept now the limitations on firing – to extent unavoidable.
Agreed : accept 1-3 on basis that P.T. will review cost and on
understanding tht. compulsory purchase shd. not be used for
1.
M/H &amp; L.G. to consult Welsh planning authies.
P.T., G.W. &amp; J.M. to discuss also handling of Land Court.
[Exit G.W., A.J., J.H.
4. National Health Service. [Enter D.W-S.
P.M. Decision needed to-day is only – what we say to deputn. on arbitration if they ask
for it.
D.W.S. Don’t court it. But can’t refuse it, if requested.
 
 
Ready to try to steer them off it. But, if they ask for consent under Ind. Disputes
Act, we can hardly refuse. We cdn’t stop them from going to arbitn. on an
individual hospital : para 3(c). And what do we say if they ask us to advise how
they shd. go to arbitn.
I.M. These are small people : we must therefore appear to be fair to them.
This means arbitn. or review.
At arbitn. you might get award of 3½% or 4% V. embarrassing. Also wrong. tht.
Ministerial decision shd. be reviewed at arbitn.
Therefore I prefer review. And if it is linked with N. Hall report, we cd. get over
to grading vice straight pay increase.
P.T. Agree on dangers of arbitn. To accept it willingly wd. appear weak.
But nervous of linking this with N. Hall – which means more &amp; more adminn.
And has to be considered by same W. Council as got out of control on the wage
claim.
Ch.H. Action so far has strengthened Govt’s position. Staff side seem to be set diffy
over arbitn. Must be fair &amp; slow. Considn. of N. Hall report is inevitable. Can’t
determine a line finally until we know what depn. says.
D.W.S. We can’t stop arbitration : only ques is wtr we guide it in one direction or another.
Hail. L.O.’s may have advised that arbitn. on Ministerial decision is constitutionally
possible. But it remains constitutionally undesirable.
We may be forced into some arbitn. e.g. under 3(c). But we shd. play the hand to
avoid it.
We can say a new situation has bn. created by N. Hall report.
K. How far are we committed to arbitn.?
I.M. That if an arbitrable issue arises we won’t refuse arbitn.
H.W. V. awkward qua buses etc., if we appear to be seeking arbitration. If there is to be
arbitn., better that we shd. be forced into it.
P.M. Must see this v. background of wider issue.
See P.T.’s reluctance re N. Hall report. But it is there – can’t be escaped – will
have to be considered. On balance, wiser to use this as a means of widening
issue. We can appear to be reasonable, on basis of a new factor. Better to agree
to a new plan, tho’ costly, than give way on existg. wage claim.
J.M. Staff side were told N. Hall enquiry wd. not be used as excuse for p’poning wage
claims.
P.M. Cd. offer different machinery for discussing N. Hall rept.
D.W.S. Remember tht. we are committed to view that arbitn. is not excluded “on an
arbitral issue.”
P.M. But we can still argue tht. Ministerial decision is not “above”.
After further discussion on good faith –
 
 
P.M. Surely, if they ask for arbitn. Ministers shd. avoid direct answer &amp; promise to
consider.
Agreed : at deputn., try N. Hall report line. If they raise ques of arbitn.
adjourn mtg so that each side can consider suggn. made by
other.
[Exit D.W-S.
5. Suez Canal.
S.Ll. Do we vote for Sec. Genl’s plan? Had hoped to be able to abstain. But now
appears it mayn’t got thro’ w’out our vote. And both U.S. &amp; France press us to
vote for it. Alternative : a resoln. requirig U.K. &amp; France to pay whole cost.
H.W. Have consulted again with ship-owners – have warned them we may have to vote
for it. They will prob. claim re-imbursement from Ty. If we refuse, they may
decline to pay.
Despite this, I don’t ask F.O. to take a difft. view on tacties.
S.Ll. We cdn’t re-imburse w’out appearing to admit that it was all our fault.
H.W. No : comparable with wrecks in late war.
P.M. Consider that ques when it comes.
</content>
</cab>