<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/17/0 images: 4-4</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.85(57). 20th December, 1957.
1. Wages Policy. [Enter E.H.
P.T. Para. 2. New emphasis.
Avoid glosses on our earlier statements.
Watch for price decreases – &amp; see they get publicity.
Keep open mind on arbitn. etc.,
Some awkward cases – v. small in economic significance.
I.M. Agree.
Bus claim. Men are going back to B.T.C. – may be trouble when rebuffed.
D.E. Not much prospect of price redn. on a/c of falling cost of raw materials.
Food prices may reflect this. Elsewhere material cost represent only about 25% :
and a 10% drop in that wd. mean only a drop of 2% in cost of article.
R.A.B. Police. Don’t want trouble with them if likelihood of strike.
2. Industrial Disputes.
R.A.B. Official plans have bn. carried as far as practicable.
Propose that Ministers (below Cab. rank) shd. be earmarked to go to regions.
Will submit list to P.M.
El. power stations : wd. have to be operated by troops. Plans being made.
Drivers of road tankers : ear-marking Service-men for this.
x/ Memorandum available – for consultn. by Ministers who wish.
H.W. Roads : for 3 wks. we cd. manage to deliver essential food supplies by road in a
rlway strike.
I.M. Can Unions afford it? Not a long strike. But 3 wks. is nearly covered by
P.A.Y.E. refund + strike money.
H.W. And NUR has about £5 M. in hand.
Note x/.
3. Electrical Trade Union.
I.M. Best that reform shd. be undertaken by Union or T.U.C. – if it is.
x| Party feeling is tht., if they don’t take action, Govt. may have to.
Action is “within the rules” – on advice from Pritt. If necessary, the rules are
amended to cover what Executive wants to do.
Propose to see Chairman of T.U.C. and tell him informally Govt.’s attitude as
y/ at x/. Might strengthen his hands.
Action at y/ authorised.
[Exit P.T.
4. Rent Restriction in Scotland.
 
 
J.M. As in memo.
Timing – a long drawn-out process will take from Jan-July.
May not be unpopular with moderate opinion.
H.B. Will bring inclusive rents for l.a. houses into line with those in E. &amp; W. New
town rates will still be lower.
I.M. On timing wd. prefer to start process before 15/1.
Memo. approved.
5. N. Atlantic Council.
P.M. Mtg. was satisf. on the whole.
Envisaged originally at W’ton mtg. Fear of Anglo-U.S. hegemony were
dispelled. French were relaxed. Private talks were helpful.
Principle of interdependence – in all fields – considerable advance made.
Eis. statements : indicatg. realisation of new dollar gap. Promise to propose to
Congress new measures for aid. Sale of weapons two ways will also be helpful in
this.
Looking outwards to flanks – was put across. Indonesian situation helped us to
get this across. Leaven left to work.
Secret agreemt. to seek link with other Alliances – not in communiqué
Great issue – however we strengthen mil. power of NATO – fear is creaping over
Europe, esp. in U.K. &amp; Scandinavia, that there shd. be some further gesture twds.
negotiation with R. Fr. pol. opinion is also restive on this point. We therefore got
the suggn. of For. Min. Mtg. U.S. wanted to tie this closely to disarmament &amp;
U.N. Others wanted NATO to handle it – this wd. have provoked reply tht.
Warsaw Pact shd. answer for other side. These 2 considn. made it necessary to be
vague.
I.R.B.M.’s. Odd situation. No unease here after B’muda : indeed they criticised
on basis we shd. control. Decn. : accept by Alliances as a whole : siting on basis
of strategic plan : &amp; agreemts. bilateral
“Arm to parly” – this line will appeal to large body of opinion here. This is
policy we shd. stand on.
Development of Kennan-ism &amp; defeatism (tiredness) thro’ Europe. Key is
Germany. G. has bn. crucial to peace of Europe since 1870. A neutral G. wd. be
a v. dangerous pawn for others. NATO w’out G. wd. make no sense. G. has
always bn. in it, as occupied or free. But there are possibilities to be considered.
“Thinning-out” shd. be by mileage not by natl. territory. But, even then, awkward
to measure fr. line dividing G.
Labour Party will exploit mood of tiredness. V. dangerous. Therefore “arm to
parly” policy is wise.
Hail. Party concerned at lack of strong propaganda line on f. policy. Kennan has called
in ques fundamental basis of our policy. In ’58 we shall have to put out more &amp;
give clearer lead.
Labour propagating theory tht. Commn. has lost its dynamism &amp; no longer aims at
world domination. This must be countered.
H. Can we have mil. apprecn. of value of medium-range missile.
So as to get measure of advantage in w’drawng. troops fr. Poland &amp; Germany.
 
 
D.S. Militarily don’t need them so far forward. And inspn. wd. be most valuable quid
pro quo.
Gt. difference between that plan and neutralisation.
H.W. R. visitors ready to talk, &amp; interchange, on technical achievement. For they are
confident of their own. Need therefore to counter that type of impression.
G.Ll. Recent visitor to R. Alarmed by i) evce. of impending trade drive by R. ii) evce.
of many visits by foreigners &amp; teaching of f. languages.
D.S. Cuts both ways – reduces risk of world war.
K. “Peace at any price” puts you at mercy of ruthless. Must take other line (P.M.’s)
of makg. clear tht. there is a point at wh. you will resist even if it involves major
war.
R.A.B. Use of surpluses of U.S. &amp; G. overseas to compete with R. – e.g. in underdeveloped
countries.
Have you made any impact on G.
P.M. Opened it up with G. T.L.R. followed it up with Etzel. Must continue to press
them.
D.E. i) Kennan must be answered.
ii) We can’t do, in overseas trade, all that all our friend want. cf. the amount
of development Canada wants us to do there. If we attacked this in a
concentrated, vice dispersed,view great results wd. be achieved.
</content>
</cab>