<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/17/0 images: 6-6</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.1(58) 3rd January, 1958
 
 
1. Government Expenditure. [Enter 3 Serv. Ministers, DWS.,
B.C.
P.M. Principle : no substantial increase over this year’s expenditure. Gt. efforts made
to find economies to bridge much of gap £153 M.
Miscellaneous savings of £40 M. secured.
Defence : further saving of £18 + 5½ M. civil on atomic test.
P.T. Actually atomic saving is £8½ M. not £11 M.
Hence saving so far, civil &amp; military = £40 M. + £21 M.
P.T. Thanks for co-operation. Savings essential – central to main position : no more
money to be provided to finance inflation.
Not arithmetic, but principle. But must be able to say no substantial increase over
this year’s expenditure.
With 3 N.H.S. economies &amp; what is agreed offer, we get cut of £92 M.
Defence : this leaves on “inducements” a betterment of £7 M. If that were
deferred, we shd. reach £99 M. Gap of £53 M.
[Real burden worse because shan’t get £50 M. from Germany.]
Can’t wear a gap of £53 M. Three alternatives –
i) If Def. Ministers wd. p’pone direct pay increases (£19 M), and do only
marriage &amp; out of quarters allowance – there wd be saving on Estimate
of £20 M. Much to be said for deferring this while wage claims
generally are so crucial.
ii) One big change vice a parcel. Take child allowance instead of others –
net additional saving of £20 M.
iii) Larger increase on N.H.S. stamp (8d.) and 8d. vice 6d. on milk would
give another £20 M.
H.A. By rosier estimating of course of world prices I cd. cut £10 M. off total of my
subsidies – all in next year.
D.S. Ty. swithering over pay etc., They offer allowances, tho’ they think them wrong,
because amount is smaller. They said P.T. shd. not deal with pay : they now say
defer pay increases until P.J. reports.
Public attitude to pay and recruiting. Build-up of assumptn. we shall fail to get
regulars. Increases wh seem stingy may be worse than none.
My latest effort to cut out another £18 M. was made in order to save pay
proposals.
Sel. Have absorbed £100 M. costs this year &amp; are £45 M. below. Our total reduction
is therefore £140 M. We surely (defence) have made our contribution.
J.H. Recruiting mainly Army ques. We agreed in Oct. to defer pay increases, to help
P.T. That was gt. sacrifice. Unless we go fwd. now, with both pay &amp; allowances,
we haven’t a chance of getting the all-regular Army. With that there is just a
chance. Nothing has happened yet to falsify assumptn. on wh. W. Paper rested.
N.H.S. and Social Service
D.W-S. Of alternatives in para.5. I prefer children allowances –
i) a single large cut is politically easier; &amp; more impressive.
ii) N.HS. proposals all open to grave objn.
iii) that action wd. strengthen feeling tht. Tories always go for N.H.S.
 
 
Eyes : wd. need legn. Wd. be 1st. service to be wholly abandoned. Saving in 1st
year wd. not be more than £4½ m. because notice, contracts etc., Pledges that this
is permanent part of N.H.S.
Stamp : Health element doubled only last Sept. Stamp going up in Feb. because
of o.a.p. element. But this is less objectionable than others &amp; might yield more
because Scotland doesn’t seem to have bn. taken into a/c.
Milk : recent cut was defended (Apl.) on ground that it put it back to 50% of real
cost. The “half price” principle. Saving in first year wd. be £1 or £2 M less than
stated because of notice &amp; because of paymt made in arrear. Attack on mothers
&amp; children under 5 – wd. be harder to defend than cut on school milk.
General : expenditure on N.H.S. as propn. of G.N.P. has already fallen under Tory
Govt. from 1/7
th. to ⅛th.
Wd. prefer larger increase in stamp and no other change in N.H.S.
M. Supported P.T. on cap exp’re. We cd. have gone further on that.
But Estimates = weekly house-keeping. Of course our bills go up – as others do.
Increased N.H.S. charges wd. be taken by Unions as reason for wage increases.
Will imperil our genl. posn. on wages front.
World won’t end if we don’t save £157 M. off Estimates.
Family Allowances.
B.C. This wd. involve dismantling 50% of this service. Bitterly controversial legn.
Consequential changes in N.I. legn. – altering again a Bill which hasn’t yet come
into operation. This also wd. be bitterly controversial.
Contrary to general policy of discontinuing general subsidies and giving where
need is.
Wd. remove payment fr. 5 m. and reduce it for another 1¼ m.
M/Ag. Food survey shows tht. larger families are only section of community
which is in danger nutritionally.
N.H.S. Increase in stamp. Wd. be 3rd. increase in total stamps w’in a year. And
at 17/6 it is thght we have got it as high as can be borne.
R.M. We are commd. to curbing infln. If we fail, we are ruined. If we succeed credit
for that will out-weigh all these pol. difficulties.
£92 M. + £10 M. for agric. Increase N.H.S. stamp to 8d. Defer Service pay
increase. And you then get about £140 M.
H.A. Best to concentrate on N.H.S. stamp – even to 1/=.
I.M. Cdn’t hope to hold wages front if children allowances were cut. Nor wd. Party
support it.
Not worth dropping a service (Eyes) for saving secured = 1d. on stamp.
Attack on family (milk) wd. also be objectionable qua wages.
S.Ll. Cuts in defence have damaged f. policy seriously. Supported them because of
need for solvency as backing for f. policy.
Problem now : how far can we narrow gap? Children’s allowances and milk wd.
be regarded as decln. of war on T.U.’s.
I wd. therefore take 92 (?) and see how much farther we can go on N.H.S. stamp.
What about increased revenue – wh. also reduces consumption &amp; helps to check
inflation.
Cannot remaining gap be presented as consistent with policy of no more money –
e.g. more children or old people.
 
 
K. Prefer method of compromises &amp; scraps vice large policy decisions.
Take £40 misc. increase N.H.S. by 8d. = £26. Hosp. boarding £11. At. tests 8½
M. Services £12½ M. Agric. £10 M. Service pay £18 M. (i.e. 50% of the £35).
Total saving £126 M. Gap wd. then be ½ of 1% of total Budget.
B.C. Repeated objns. to increasing cost of stamp still further.
D.W.S. Hospital boarding charge. Wd. be most unpopular. Rejected by Gillebaud.
V. diff. to do this and the stamp.
I.M. Cdn’t do both.
R.A.B. Can’t make this occasion for major change in social policy. All we can do is to
secure economies – but support them with pledges for future action. One is a firm
determination to bring exp’re on the old under control by a scheme of contm. &amp;
benefits related to wages. This will help to win psychological battle.
Don’t under-rate success P.T. had already.
Don’t on this round endanger wages battle.
Thus, look for £30 M or so here. I wd. do 6d. on milk.
I believe we cd. get £110 M. by these means. (i.e. £40 M. + £30 M defence + £30
M civil + £10 M on agriculture.)
P.T. Appeal to Def. Ministers on Service pay. e.g. p’pone until autumn : doing
allowances now. cf. action on N.H.S. clerks.
P.M. Good progress made.
Ministers must realise this may be turning point for us.
Remember posn. when we took office. We had to overcome greatest shock to our
prestige since Majuba. We had survived. We have re-established relns. with U.S.
We have promise on Macmahon. Gt. prizes lie ahead – potentially v. large
savings. Also v. grave problems – Cyprus, defeatism on f. policy, disengagement.
We shd. not allow disintegration on marginal difficulties. Even in fin &amp; econ.
affairs think what we have escaped. Recovery of £.
Three main ques : i) what is acceptable gap. Somewhere betwn. 0.5% and
1.0% cd. be defended.
Timing. Service Estimates must be settled to-day. On civil there are some days
during which we can select least damaging economies.
Defence. Small additional contribn. must be found. a) Do allowances and p’pone
pay indefinitely or preferably to specified date. b) Announce whole plan
incorporating a delay for certain aspects.
Civil : we must get not less than £30 M.
</content>
</cab>