<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/17/0 images: 16-16</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.24(58) 18th March, 1958
1. Farm Price Review. [Enter E.H.
H.A. Views of N.F.U.’s as submitted by letter. “No purpose in continuing
discussions”.
Proposed that Minister shd. announce “imposed” settlement at reduction of £19
M. on Thursday. Wh. Paper for Cab. to-morrow.
J.H. Propose to add (no cost to Exchequer) small concession for quality bacon – will
give a little help to N. Ireland.
H.A. £1.297M. = total value of guarantees : this is background for £19M.
R.A.B. Still worried about some points in draft Wh. Paper.
P.M. Ch. Hill to watch publicity.
2. Territorial Waters. [Enter S., O.G.
P.M. U.S/Canada are now going to put fwd. their 3/12 mile compromise. Att.G.
suggests we remain silent at this stage. But a) U.S. will be upset if we later
oppose it. b) U.K. will seem to be abandoning their fishing interests.
S.Ll. If it secures simple majority, we shall enrage U.S. by opposing it later, to avoid
⅔rds. majority in plenary.
We cd. move amendment.
J.H. We can’t support U.S. plan : we shd. therefore tell them. And in discn. we shd.
state our view w’out lobbying for it : i.e. we favour 3 m. with no extension for
fishing.
P.M. {Instruct Att.G. to make it plain in Cttee. tht. we favour 3 and don’t favour
Agreed. {extension for fishing. For answer to para. 5 is that it isn’t politically tolerable.
Don’t authorise him to act on para. 8., if confused situation arises, without
referring to me – tho’ to save time he cd. start an argument on 6 with military
rights for 3.
H. Why not let it founder?
P.M. For fear tht., if majority settled on 12, states might act on it unilaterally.
Hail. No juridical right : we cd. take them to Int. Court.
[Exit O.G., S.
 
 
3. Foreign Affairs.
a) S.E.A.T.O.
S.Ll. SEATO. went well. Concentn. on counter-subv. and economics, vice mil. organn.,
was welcome.
b) Iraq.
S.Ll. Serious crise de nerfs. Remedy – spaced dollops of short-term aid – as tangible
evidence of support.
c) Tunisia.
Improved. Elements of a deal are now emerging. Looks encouraging.
d) German Support Costs.
S.Ll. Let this simmer until Adenauer comes to Ldn. in April.
e) Summit Talks.
S.Ll. F.D. gave me v. legalistic memo. I gave him P.M.’s in return. We have evolved a
compromise document summarising Western posn. F.O. Tel. to W’ton 1484.
P.M. If U.S. wd. agree to that we have something we can stand on.
I.M. Cd. we somewhere include a specific date – e.g. in para 6. for start of diplomatic
exchanges in W’ton.
Agreed : Send this suggn. to W’ton, e.g. 2 wks after agreement in
N.A.T.O.
f) P.M.’s Visit to Washington.
P.M. Announcemt. of my visit had to be made in a hurry because of a leak.
4. Wages Policy.
I.M. Memo. originated fr. discns. 12 mos. ago. These led to Cohen Cttee. New thought
wh. emerges here is “guiding light”. Not v. keen : but prs. worth ventilating.
No prospects for 2 mos. or so in any approach to employers on T.U.’s – round of
applns. are going on. Must consider other means of floating the idea – even a lr. in
Times.
Cttee. of Ministers wd. waste their time until we are more clear about new claims.
H.W. 2% or 2½% wd. not be tolerable for rlways - £9 M.
H.A. Hoped to get a lead – guiding light fr.Cohen Cttee. Not keen on having it fr. Govt.
Cttee. of Ministers mght consider it – but not now. Danger of its being a floor, not
an average.
Debate in H/L. later (as H. suggested) might be useful.
 
 
D.E. Guiding light wd. build inflation into Govt. policy. As it is, we can at least treat it
as somethg. which has happened. Can’t give all results of increased productivity
to increased wages.
Hail. I’m against it too.
M. This is no time for any new initiative on wages.
H.W. Not so much against it – can’t accept effect of arbitration. Shd. study problem.
R.M. Can’t leave wages problem alone. No other remedy. Cttee. of Ministers shd.
consider – hope somethg. else may be found.
For real reason is full employmt.
I.M. Agree : must go on thinking.
K. We can’t abdicate. Must think further.
R.A.B. Consider paras. 16 et seq of officials’ report. If somethg. cd. be found there,
might be a basis for joint approach. Cohen’s Rpt. won’t provide such a basis.
(1) First therefore see if there’s any way of getting T.U.’s into review of classic
U.K. methods of wage negotiation.
(2) If that fails, review conciliation machinery. Whitley must be reviewed. (3)
Then prs. we cd. tackle arbitration.
I.M. Opportunity for serious talk with T.U.’s this summer : on ques wtr we put in
perm. legn. on compulsory arbitn., when D.R. disappear, or wtr we abandon it.
P.M. Thus – at this particular moment of wages struggle, it wd. be mistake to take any
new initiative. Keep guiding light, pro. tem., under bushel.
But we can’t rest there. We want expansionist policy &amp; full emplt.
[Tho’ recession threatens.] How do we achieve it w’out excessive wage awards?
How do we face next round, in autumn, w’out continuing or resuming restrictive
policies.
Arbitration is no guarantee. We cdn’t expect to do again, or in a bigger case,
what we did to N.H.S. clerks. (1) We must at least consider that problem i.e.
Whitley machinery. On RAB’s (1), time isn’t ripe for it, but we can’t let it be
overlooked. Let H.A. follow this up, under aegis of E.P.C.
H. Can we have study of pros &amp; cons of a link with c/living. – with experience of
other countries.
5. Malta.
A.L.B. M.’s view now on integration is that Malta wd. remain free to go out into
independence at any time after U.K. legn. passed – on ground tht. full equivalence
hadn’t bn. achieved.
I am mtg. him once more on prospects of emplt. in dockyard.
He is going back to full econ. equivalence as condition of integration. He says we
have “deserted” this. And now wishes to discuss independence. I shall make it
clear we don’t tolerate this.
 
 
P.M. Oppn. have asked to see me. I’ve said I can’t see them, at any rate until after
dinner. Will have to see them to-morrow, or Thursday. With K. and A.L.B.
</content>
</cab>