<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/17/0 images: 19-19</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.28(58) 1st April, 1958
1. Summit Meeting : Nuclear Tests. [Enter E.H.
P.M. Statement of W. position delivered. Has off-set to some extent effect of R.
unilateral suspension of tests.
Read lr. from Pres. Eis. of 29.3. Since then US. have suggested discussions of bilateral
agreemt. on assumptn. of passing of legn. amending MacMahon Act.
Importance of the 30 days = diffce. betwn. opn. July or Feb ’59.
Next B. test v. soon. Wd. solve fission/fusion problem : and pave way twds.
knowledge of know-how for weapon small enough for war-head of rockets. Not
by any means sure U.S. will give us all informn. we need, if we are to have no
tests. Must therefore carry thro’ this next test.
Reaching point now at wh. it will be easier for us to forego knowledge than
material. Can contemplate suspension of tests : not so much cut-off of
production.
Public line?
I.M. Cd. we advocate suspension at end of f’coming U.S. series?
S.Ll. Doubt if U.S. wd. agree w’out adequate inspn.
P.M. Diffy about this line : not known that we are about to have a test.
H.W. Say : ready to consider posn. at end of current series of tests. That is what R. did.
Terms of reply to P.N. Ques discussed and agreed.
2. European Free Trade Area.
[Not heard.]
3. Cyprus.
P.M. Damp this down. Avoid appearance of proposing brand new &amp; difft. plan. Put it
as part of continuous search for solutions – and in Ldn, which wd. be less marked
than in Ankara.
R.A.B. Prefer tri-dominium : provided it’s clear that U.K. retain [Enter H.B.
responsibility (jointly) for order in Island : i.e. to check civil war.
S.Ll. Gks. will never accept it.
Attraction of alternative is tht., if T. wd. accept it, Gks. wd. take it too.
R.A.B. Wd. we intervene then, if disorder broke out.
S.Ll. No : once Island in Gk. hands.
R.A.B. Then unpalatable to Party.
K. Yes : if tri-dominium rejected, enforce tel. plan.
 
 
S.Ll. Prospects for tel. plan are more promising. U.S. wd. back it.
P.M. Don’t put it as a plan. Must keep it going until May, after Gk. elections.
M’while, officials to work out tri-dominium plan. So that we can, in end, produce
it publicly.
4. Parliament.
R.A.B. Business for week after Recess. [Exit S.Ll.
5. Rent Act.
H.B. Discussed outstanding points under K.’s chairmanship.
i) Level of rent. From 1/10 onwds. level of twice until Co. Ct. decn. : if stay of
execution then granted, it shd. be rent asked by l’lord subject to power of Ct. to
reduce it on proof tht. tenant can’t afford it tho’ not below twice. Effective protn.
v. hardship : and satisf. to those who have already made agreements.
Hail: Suppose l’lord’s object is to sell, he will have named unreasonable rent. Co. Ct.
will then be obliged to order that rent unless proved tenant can’t pay.
K. Good point in theory : but unlikely to arise in practice.
Object of main Bill was to secure a free market. Don’t abandon that now, for a
theoretical point.
J.M. V. dangerous to set maximum : for l’lords will take it as reasonable level for
agreements made betwn. now and Oct.
R.A.B. Merits – in favour of action. Politics – against it, save Ldn., Glasgow. But
conclude we must do it.
I.M. Provide that it shd. apply only to areas to wh. extended by Order?
H.B. Hard to define areas. Facts (alternative accommn.) will in practice localise it.
Agreed : Introduce Bill after Easter
Announce Wed. 2/4.
6. Land : Compulsory Acquisition.
RAB. x| Authorise prepn. of Bill.
| Negotiate with Corfield, who wants early announcement.
J.M. My reservations. i) Mght involve some l.l.a.’s in heavy costs over slum
clearance.
H.B. Studying problem when industry, shops etc., planned as well as houses.
[J.M.] ii) Is this wise politically? Must be righted sometime. But how many votes will
it earn now? Our supporters want it, but will not more people be alienated by it.
 
 
J.H. Agree – will alienate middle vote.
Hail. Is it not equitable? cf. cases where l.a.’s find they don’t need it, and are
compelled by Ty to sell at a profit.
P.M. Drew attention to dangers.
H.B. Don’t seek decision now. Only x/.
Agreed : as at x/.
7. Malta.
A.L.B. Debate to-day. Hope to avoid division. But Govr. has assented to Appropn. Bill :
and warrants for £7M have bn. submitted – and must be signed because Govr.
acts on advice. I must make it clear there will be no more from U.K. this year
than £5M. This may upset Opposn.
8. Territorial Waters.
K. On behalf of S.Ll. – Att.G. must to-day put in amendment on 6 miles. Canadian
hostile &amp; trying to persuade us to support their 12+13.
Att. G. will carry on - pursuant to existing instns. Oppose Canadian plan but not
lobbying against it.
Agreed : m’tain existg. instructions.
</content>
</cab>