<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/17/0 images: 37-37</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.53(58) 10th July 1958
1. Defence Organisation. [Enter 4 Def. Ministers.
4 C.O.S., E.H.
P.M. Protracted discussions. Need for prompt concln.
Current need : plans for total war, wh. we seek to prevent for world wd. be
destroyed : plans for lesser operations. Not easy to cater for both.
Basis followed. In 2nd. war : P.M. as M/D. w’out a Ministry &amp; gave most of his
time to it. If that situation arose again, our present organn. wd. not continue : but I
doubt if it cd. happen again (total war lasting for some years). Some believe this
organn. is still apt – P.M. with 3 C.O.S. with an Ismay. In peace it cd. hardly
operate unless P.M. cd. devote much time to defence.
From 1946 we have had a statutory M/Defence : with powers.
A.E. appointed a Chairman of C.O.S. Cttee.
On assuming office I issued a new directive (hurriedly) strengthening authority of
M/D. Need now to make this more formal &amp; permanent. Hence present draft.
Main change : Ch. of Defence Staff. Nothing revolutionary or drastic. That cd.
not be done (integration) w’out legn.
Some want to go further twds. integration. Wd. need legn.
Some wd. prefer to go back to 3 C.O.S. Believe that wd. need repeal of 1946 Act.
This solution steers a middle course betwn. these extremes.
H.B. Short notice : can’t express a useful opinion.
A.L.B. Nor can I.
Hail. No supporting argument – can’t form a judgement on that basis.
K. Constitutionally – no gt. change. Narrowing of Ministerial responsibility of
Service Ministers. Paras. 4 and 6. together mean tht. Serv. Minister remain
responsible to Parlt. for efficient adminn. &amp; particular appln. to each Service of
general policy determined by M/Defence. Doesn’t narrow their posn. much as
cpd. with posn. under 1946 Act to-day.
Appointments : para. 10. This needs some thought – where wd. respons. to Parlt.
lie. Suggests it wd. be with M/Defence. Some narrowing of their responsibility.
P.M. “Efficiency and adminn.”. But eg. air defence, efficiency depends on decisions
taken under para 5. It is not “efficient administration”
P.M. Para. 7 indicates tht. all Ministers concerned will be consulted in formuln. of
major policy under para. 5. It is a joint responsibility.
D.S. No change (para 5) as cpd. with my current directive : except to leave out certain
powers related to pay etc.,
A.J. This is a middle course. Our view was that policy shd. be for a group. D.S. View
tht. ultimately we shd. have single Minister with deputies. Believe this is a
weakness. Will compare unfavourable with Labour’s W. Paper of ’46.
Moreover, each side will interpret it in light of their differing view. My view is
therefore tht. it wd. be preferable not to publish it.
 
 
I.M. If in fact little change, why publish something which will dismay Services and
Party.
Para. 2 is an obvious compromise. Paras 9 &amp; 17 are v. dangerous.
P.M. Some statement ought to be made next week.
This is no more than a restatement of existg. posn. plus Ch. D. Staff.
A.J. Directive of ’57 was an experiment.
P.M. Can be represented as carrying on status quo.
G.W. In last 18 months great re-organisation of Services – neither easy nor popular.
We have, however, put policy across to Services. Existg. directive works. In
seeking agreemt. on new formuln., we have come across diffies. paras 2 &amp; 17,
where we are still troubled by intention to lower status of S. Ministers &amp; C.O.S. &amp;
to concentrate power in hands of one Minister and one serving officer. D.S. has
not concealed his intention to do this. Tho’ status of Ministers is to be depressed,
responsibility remains. And lowering status of C.O.S. will shake morale down to
roots of Services.
Not a matter of words. It is intention behind them.
S. Aim : (1) closer co-opn. w’out O.K.W. We all agree on need to avoid O.K.W.
(2) retain real sense of responsibility in Service Dpts. Effect on Services’
morale. M/D. is not popular with them.
Heavy responsibility of Serv. Ministers because their work is not
much known to Cab.
Need for informed decns. Advice shd. not be impeded. Will it still
come fwd. under this organn.
C.S. “Turn 1957 directive into more formal document &amp; create C.D.S.” I believe
paper goes much deeper than that – in changing relns. of S. Ministers &amp; C.O.S.
Object of paras 2 &amp; 9 = restrict attendances of Serv. Ministers at Def. Cttee.
Earlier drafts excluded us specifically. And D.S. has said it is unnecessary for us
to attend – as he is responsible under para 5. If we disagreed, wrong tht.
arguments be repeated in Def. Cttee.
Para. 17 Joins 3 Genl. Staffs and gives C.D.S. access to any of them over the
heads of 3 C.O.S. How can they expect to control their own Staffs.
W.D. Spkg. as individual, not as Chairman. Have bn. in touch with central def. organn.
since 1923. Growing complications in recent years – esp. in internatl. &amp; technical
fields. Principles in W. Paper are suited to present condns. Believe a C.D.S. is
required. All other Gt. Powers have somethg. of this kind. P.M. must have a
M/D. and latter needs a senior mil. adviser, closely linked with C.O.S. Terms
here meet requirements of M/D. w’out undermining posn. of C.O.S. Cttee. – many
safeguards for their position, which must not be weakened. Also avoids O.K.W.
– para 17 : no C.D.S,. wd. go behind C.O.S. : contemplates their co-operation.
P.M. Object of para. 17 was to make it plain there is not to be O.K.W.
W.D. Strategic work, as now, will be done thro’ C.O.S. machine.
But M/D. wants mass of informn. on all sorts of mil. matters &amp; shd. be able to get
it thro’ me. At present he can’t.
 
 
Hail. But Naval Staff was previously under control of 1st. Lord. Para 17 puts them at
disposal of C.D.S. or M/Defence.
R.A.B. But M/D. must be able to get informn. he needs.
C.N.S. Naval Staff will work normally to C.O.S. Cttee. thro’ C.N.S.
Hail. But responsible to-day to Bd. of Admy. Will that be changed?
C.N.S. No. Always bn. problem of dual responsibility of a C.O.S. – to M/D. and to his
own Minister.
C.A.S. If CDS is to be head of this “Joint Def. Staff” he has right to go to any member of
it, by-passing the C.O.S. That is unacceptable so long as we have our present
titles &amp; responsibilities. If this is not intended, why are our amendmts rejected?
P.M. If confidence m’tained betwn. senior officers, no problem will arise. But willing
to find form of words, to meet C.A.S. point.
C.A.S. I believe it was wrong to have a Chairman. That won’t increase power of
M/Defence.
C.I.G.S. Why are these proposals necessary at all? Existg. machinery cd. work perfectly
well, if disposn. to make it work.
Real issue : shd. there be a mil. Supremo, or shd. we rely on C.O.S. That has bn.
obscured by drafting.
We have 3 Services &amp; Govt. say they are to remain separate. Must have single
defence policy. C.O.S. must be prof. heads of Services &amp; must remain respons.
for efficiency of Services. That can’t be passed to a single Supremo – with no
knowledge of any Service but his own. Single policy – must be secured thro’
collective responsibility of C.O.S. Cttee. : our duty to see that our advice is known
to &amp; understood by Govt.
H. Is this not preserved in draft?
C.I.G.S. Para. 17.
Our duties are covered if it is intended to work it that way.
P.M. Para.2. Two ways of running Def. Cttee. Driven to ad hoc mtgs. [Exit M.
because Cttee. is cumbrous &amp; heterogeneous. cf. Macmahon or disarmament.
What I wd. like to do is to be able to convene ad hoc but have continuous
recording in D.C. series. cf. Maldives : ridiculous to summon all Def. Cttee. cf. at
other end, nuclear p’mme : is it wise to pitch that undigested to Def. Cttee.
If you insist on rigid composn. of Cttee., I shall have to by-pass it. More flexibility
is essential.
Hail. cf. history of Suez. Def. Cttee. never met. Suez Cttee., with floating membership.
I.M. But why publish these details? P.M. Because it was in 1946 W. Paper. And
because of publicity, wh. has aroused speculation.
J.H. What is the reason for all this? We have achieved gt. changes in def. policy under
existg. organisation. It is working well.
 
 
Believe this increases powers of M/D. – &amp; will create ill-will. Too much turns on
interpretns.
This system, in diff. hands, wd. be v. dangerous. It cd. put too much power into
hands of Ministers &amp; C.D.S.
It will be so interpreted.
P.M. Much talk &amp; speculation. Ought to re-state posn., more formally.
We cd., alternatively, announce that we intend no gt. change except C.D.S.
D.S. Duty to formulate general policy. Natural therefore tht. I shd. be unpopular in
Serv. Dpts. : because strong mil. arguments v. most of decisions I have had to
make to keep expenditure w’in bounds.
“Why do we have to make a statement”? My diffy. is to find what material
changes we are making. This didn’t originate with me. Two of C.O.S. are not
happy with directive &amp; Chairman. They wd. prefer to go back. But that is, why
issue arose.
Two aspects of problem – advice and decision. On advice there is no real diffce.
of view. I’m against large M/D. or O.K.W. Duplicn. &amp; divorce of policy fr.
execution. But alternative must be to ensure tht. advice is available fr. Service
Dpts,. to M/D. and C.D.S. We can’t rigidly define boundaries betwn. M/D. &amp;
Dpts, or channels for advice. Ministers don’t rely always &amp; solely on Perm Secy.
Must be possible for M/D. &amp; CDS similarly to have access to advice throughout
the Staffs. But, of course, formal advice will be sought thro’ C.O.S. concerned.
Decision. Def. Ministers were appointed on basis of ’57 directive, wh. gave
wider powers of decision to M/D. These are essential to his job. Previously he
was no more than Inskip. Decns. of past year cd. not have bn. reached w’out that
authority.
Relations with Service Ministers. This memo. does no more than reflect existg.
practice. Does M/D. continue as Minister with power of decn. or a Minister who,
if he can’t get agreement, must refer to higher authy. No M/D. will put his neck
out if at the end it has to go to a Def. Cttee. which hasn’t studied problem.
Inefficient way of doing business. Tho’ if S. Minister feels gt. mistake is being
made he has right of appeal.
Def. Cttee. Two functions. Occasionally a forum for S. Ministers to dispute decn.
of M/D. But mainly to handle mixed ques going beyond defence – embracg.
foreign or Col. policy.
H. x| If our purpose was to increase authy. of M/D. &amp; C.D.S., we shd. proceed by legn.
This memo. has so many checks &amp; balances that it cd. not be so described.
Must have system of ’57 directive. This paper has no new philosophy. It is
attempt to explain to Parlt. tht. we are trying to run organn. in acc. with current
needs.
Def. Cttee. wd. be better run in panels – acc. to subjects discussed.
Two points in draft lend colour to suspicions of x/. Para. 17 cd. be adapted in
wording : to make it clear tht. CDS wdn’t go behind back of C.O.S. Must not
reduce status of S. Ministers who are i/c great Services &amp; remain respons. to Parlt.
This set-up won’t work save by team work. ?Add to para. 2 indicn. tht. Def. Cttee.
will comprise Ministers concerned.
G.W. Suspicions based on earlier drafts – e.g. housing all Staffs in M/D.
P.M. Then he must be free to draw his advice from the Staffs.
D.S. I have not put forward any draft.
 
 
S.Ll. My original view, when I came to M/D, was to assume powers of all Service
Ministers. Recognised this impracticable. But certain there shd. be 4th. C.O.S. as
Chairman.
Essential that M/D. shd. have right to seek informn. throughout the Service Staffs.
Matter of practical convenience.
Accept para. 2.
What is to happen to Dpl. contacts with C.O.S.? Is any change intended? Is para.
7 to replace those contacts.
P.M. Purpose of para. 7 is to enable all Def. Ministers to consult on major defence ques
– shape &amp; size etc., Many ques centring even on single Service are of interest to
all.
Para. 21. There are some ques which shd go to M/D. vice C.O.S.
D.S. To ensure that Minister &amp; civil side of M/D. are brought in on matters wh. go
beyond C.O.S. Cttee.
S.Ll. Last sentence of para. 20.
P.M. Cd. be omitted.
D.S. Whole of para. 20 cd. be left out of published statement.
A.J. Accept broad distinction betwn. policy (M/D) and execution (S. Dpts) The
crucial ques is wtr executive Dpts. shd. attend Def. Cttee. on final decision. I
believe this to be essential. Doubt arises from combination of paras 2 &amp; 9. I take
more objn. to 9. No access to Def. Cttee. save by way of top-hat appeal.
P.M. Surely, para. 7 helps over this. Must be some flexibility.
D.S. If you follow principle tht., whenever any diffce. between M/D &amp; S. Minister, it
must go to Def. Cttee. – you have removed the M/D. power of decision.
H.A. I wd. be against going back to old system.
Accept para. 2. – flexibility.
Somethg. wrong with para. 17.
Haven’t bn. able to consider how financial control wd. work.
R.A.B. We cd. adjust drafting in some places.
y/ Parly. posn. We must announce something.
D.E. P. opinion expects some statement.
C.S. Whatever directives are issued, we are responsible to Parlt. and for our Services.
They expect us to represent them in final forum where defence ques are settled.
We shd. therefore be present when matters affectg. their Dpts are to be discussed.
I.M. Is y/ right? Most of arguments today go against publication.
P.M. Alternatives a) statement : no change in directive of ’57.
b) W. Paper., wh. shows we have bn. thro’ all these difficulties
and come to these conclusions.
 
 
We are agreed in substance to stand pretty well as we are, with slight emphasis on
a forward move.
R.A.B. My advice is that we shd. publish.
H. Can we see re-drafts of 2, 9 and 17.
Adjourned to Friday 10 a.m.
2. Aden.
A.L.B. Sultan of Lahij must be deposed. Found him at Como.
Must announce this to-day, so tht. mil. action can be taken at once in Aden.
3. Yemen.
P.M. Need for politico-military machinery – to retain initiative. How to handle U.N.
etc.,
Mtg. of Ministers will be needed.
[Exit Serv. Min. &amp; C.O.S.
Exit A.L.B.
4. Parliament.
R.A.B. Business for next week.
5. Egypt.
H.A. As in memo.
P.M. Two gt. points are size of lump sum &amp; waiver of war damage claim. The rest is
detail.
Approved.
6. Cotton Imports.
P.M. After consultn. with colleagues, I have drafted proposals which I have discussed
with A.L.B. These are to be sent to Rochdale. I will circulate it for informn.
Read out para. 3.
7. Industrial Dispute : Docks. [Enter Strathclyde
I.M. Risk of national dock strike. No provision for arbitration. Traditional remedy :
Ct of enquiry. Mght not be accepted. Moreover, in face of threat, wd. prob. be
regarded as weakness. Have asked M/P. for a view on this. If it is so regarded,
we shd. lose more than we cd. gain.
P.M. Confer with me in course of Friday.
[Exit H.A.
 
 
8. U.S. Naval Forces in U.K.
P.M. Def. Cttee. have endorsed this proposal. But there is political aspect.
D.S. U.S. haven’t yet decided where they wd. be based – Sc. or N.I. No serious objn.
so long as we can say tht. we have made agreemt. providing tht. they won’t
engage in hostile opns. w’out our consent.
Agreed : subject to P.M.’s approval of agreement as under para. 4.
Str. Scotland rather than N.I.
RAB. N.I. rather than Scotland.

</content>
</cab>