<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/17/0 images: 47-47</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.66(58) 31st July, 1958
1. Middle East. [Enter E.H.
Iraq.
S.Ll. Propose to recognise new regime in Iraq to-morrow. Other members of B. Pact
are doing it to-day. No announcement in Parlt.
Mtg of Heads of Govt.
S.Ll. Diffies. in N.A.T.O. – draft amended to meet their points. Read revised draft.
Approved.
R.A.B. What will happen?
P.M. Will try to circulate “briefs”.
Local situation.
S.Ll. Nil to report re Kuwait : no immediate danger. Need of education re dangers to
any feudal system in M/E. Discussions on this are procdg. on spot.
Jordan : diff. to assess : cd. be blown off at discretion by N. Alert to danger to the
King. Recognition of Iraq will be a shock to the King. Br. troops have 41 days’
supplies. 2 ships arrived Aqaba.
H.A. What if J. Army (armour) turned v. us and the King.
P.M. Unlikely : more prob. that they wd. ask us to go.
H.A. Heavier anti-tank guns from U.S.?
D.S. No.
J.H. Cd. not a-tank weapons go in now via Aqaba.
S.Ll. U.N. shd. be urged to show themselves in Jordan – H.Q. etc., To discourage
developmt. of trouble, esp. on W. Bank. That = greatest risk because Israel wd.
then move &amp; risk of major war.
Agreed : D.S. to consider wtr a-tank armament of these forces cd. be
increased.
[Exit S.Ll.
2. Parliament.
R.A.B. Parlt. will rise 1/8 : H/C. at 5. p.m. Usual promise to recall in emergency.
Cttee. on Procedure. Shall have to give evce. in Oct/Nov. Wd. welcome suggns.
from Ministers for changes etc., Can they be sent to me in Recess?
3. Parliament : Television of Opening.
 
 
P.M. Suggested tht. H/L. is a Court w’in meaning of s.41. of Cr. Justice Act.
K. Judicial functions subsidiary to main function : and it is not functioning as court
on occasion of opening.
E.H. Feeling has warmed up – on both sides of this ques.
P.M.
CLOSED UNDER THE
FREEDOM OF INFORMATION
ACT 2000
[Enter J.B.C., D.W.S.
4. Pensions.
P.M. Reported as in para 2. of brief : Agreed.
.. .. .. .. 3 .. .. Diffies. of this compromise – as in para 4
J.B.C. a. will be the case in either event : because of individual injuries.
H.A. Hadn’t understood that.
J.B.C. Amount of contns. goes up in steady progress : it is appln. of that by State which
varies.
P.M. Is Ty. satisfied with compromise in para. 4?
H.A. I don’t like it, but all other Ministers favoured it. £8 is proper level for lowest
earnings (tho’ not prs. in ’61) – reduces room for manoeuvre (i.e. to adjust flat
rate benefit) to put it at £9 now. Leaves married at £4 – 50% of full (?) But this
is not financial point – and I will accept views of colleagues on a.
J.B.C. Objn. b. Wd. arise on any cross-bar. You cd. have difft. bar for women. Figures
do at one or two points bring women’s pension above men’s but at top it wd. be
lower. This is, however, a separate ques and can be adjusted.
R.A.B. Para. 67 of W. Paper suggests tht. it always happens – women over £11. Shd.
there not be more examples in W. Paper?
J.B.C. Cd. be ironed out – difft. percentages. Add figure for £9, and then leave it for
public opinion to develop in discussion.
H.A. N.H.S. contn. 2/4. flat. Why shd. it not be treated as absolute – and graduated
contn. adjusted accordingly? Wd. leave us free to vary 2/4 later, as required.
J.B.C. As now in W.P., at £9 &amp; below : flat-rate 8/4 (employee) embodying N.H.S.
contn. split as at present. Above that 4¼% on each side in graduation. If Govt.
wished later to increase it, they could.
 
 
We agreed Ind. Inj. contn. shd. remain flat-r Adopn. of H.A.’s plan wd. not make
even progressive increase.
RAB. But it means tht., if you raised NHS by 1/=, you wd. get anomalous results.
J.B.C. Inherent in having fixed element for I.I. and N.H.S.
Hail. Why isn’t it easier to present as having N.H.S. flat r unchanged and graduated is
only for remainder.
J.B.C. Why not wait for public re-action?
Ch.H. Enough to make it plain tht. N.H.S. and I.I. conribn. are still unevenly divided
betwn 2 sides.
P.M. Can we not get on with Bill on this basis. Then have Cttee. in being to clear up
minor points – presentn. in W Paper. Publn in end/Sept. or 1st. week of October.,
before Party Conference.
P.M. Lay-out of W. Paper. Cd. we not put whole of 1st. 4 parts as Pt I. Then our
proposals, after blank page, as Pt. II.
R.A.B. Paras 35 and 53. Not enough justificn. for graduation, as big new developmt. Cd.
claim more for it.
H.W. Emphasis emerging deficit – e.g. by graph. Scheme is bust.
Agreed – subject to points noted above.
[Exit J.B.C.
5. Employment.
H.A. Next month expect seasonal factors to decrease level of umemplt. But thereafter
it may rise fr. 400.000 to 600,000.
Work is going faster. Some p’mmes wd. out-run allocation unless we stopped
them.
Even so, reflation p’mme of £30 M wd. be justified -
7.500 houses in E. &amp; W. – with corr. reductions in later years.
hospitals £9 M. } arrears of maintenance.
Govt. bldgs. £1 M. }
L.A. misc. £5 M. in areas of high unemplt.
About ⅓rd. of this cd. go into areas of higher unemplt.
Other rapid items cd. be put in, if sitn. deteriorated in Sept.
Also : cd. relax h.p. control : wd. have same effect : esp for machinery &amp; plant.
Propose to apply that in 3-4 wks’ time.
RAB. What of prisons, educn. etc.,
H.A. This is for money to be spent in remainder of this year. Not related to cap.
investment p’mme.
H.B. Need to sort out details.
 
 
I.M. Latest unemplt. figures have not moved down, save for seasonal. Jan. peak may
be 600,000 only vice 750.000 prev. assumed.
Therefore we have sought projects wh. bring quick jobs, esp. in areas of high
local unemplt.
This doesn’t affect at all the long-term investment p’mmes.
G.Ll. I cd. do £5 M. quickly on minor works – restoring cut in p’mme.
D.E. Moves quite slowly.
H.A. Ready to look again at proportions between the £9 M. and £5 M.
x | But problem is to get more of £5 M in areas of high unemplt. Also :
longer arrears in hospitals than anywhere else.
P.M. No announcement of this as a plan. Let it happen administratively.
Agreed : about £30 M. H.A. to review distribn. as at x/.
H.P. changes to be announced 26/8.
D.E. Steel now at 80% capacity &amp; likely to drop to 70% by autumn. Demand is falling
esp. for heavy construction &amp; machinery.
Car prodn. also expected to decline. Machine-tools : replacement orders falling
off.
Will h. p. proposal affect this? Means about £50 M more will be borrowed at
maximum : tho’ personal savings are dropping. Wd. it be better to reduce interest
rate?
H.A. Don’t rule out latter.
H.A. Emplt. implication. At £30 M prs. 30,000.
D.E. Agree : but will make quite a stir.
H.A. Better to act, as proposed, bit by bit – esp. Aug. – to avoid alarm.
Agreed : H.P. relaxations as proposed.
6. Social Investment.
R.A.B. Pensions W. Paper early Oct. Followed by Papers on Educn. Hospitals, Prisons in
that order. Housing : method wd be facilities for house-purchase.
P.M. How do we work on this?
H.A. Further mtgs. in September. After Ty. estimate of capital cost.
G.Ll. But Hail. has to select resolns. in Aug.
Hail. I can do that.
7. Agricultural Policy.
 
 
H.A. Will involve £3½ M. not covered in price review. Hope to recover £6 M of
remainder in that review.
P.M. Carries out promise made in W. Paper.
J.H. Only one issue in negotns. – grant v. loan point. May get over that by encouraging
their plan for medium-term Bank credit. Wd. promote idea of self-help.
H.B. Paras 5-6. Small Welsh farms?
J.H. Will benefit Wales.
H.A. Hope good many Welsh farms will be cut out : not viable.
Agreed : Prepn. of Bill authorised.
8. Civil Aviation.
a) Action re Kuwait Airline : approved.
b) London Airport.
H.W. Means R. service comes in around Oct. But our lines can’t get to Moscow
otherwise.
Shall be tough on noise.
9. Cabinet Business in Recess.
P.M. As in brief.
10. Financial Situation.
H.A. Lost nil. on reserves this month. Seasonal or rather more debit on E.P.U. Expect
to lose more in Sept./Oct. No sign of alarm.
</content>
</cab>