<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/58/21 images: 176-181</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   November 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (44) 671.20th November, 1944.WAR CABINET.MORALE AND WELFARE IN THE FAR EAST.Directive by the Prime Minister and Minister of Defence, to the viceroy of India, the Commander-in-Chief, India, and the Supreme Commander,South-East Asia Command.1. The end of the war in Europe will be a time of particular importancein the Far Eastern theatres. The general relaxation of tension, and the thought of substantial releases to civil life, will disturb the minds of those who must continue the fight against Japan far from their homes, and under bad climate conditions. In matters concerning the welfare of the forces it is necessarythat a new view should be taken, so that as far as is humanly possible all reasonable cause for complaint shall be removed. A whole-hearted drive is now required to ameliorate conditions of service, and to prepare to make the fullest use of the air transport and other resources which will become available when germany is defeated.2. The welfare of the men of all three Services, and of the Merchant Navy,must be given a higher place relative to operational requirements than it occupiesat present. The aim should be to provide British sailors, soldiers, and airmenwith a standard of amenities as close to that enjoyed by American troops asthe resources at your disposal will allow. Financial considerations must notbe allowed to stand in the way of improvements which are otherwise possible.Indian and Colonial troops must receive full consideration, but improvements inthe amenities for British troops must not be held back because they cannot be fully extended to troops more accustomed to the climate and to local conditions.3. The most important direction in which action is required is in theimprovement of accommodation and amenities in leave centres and static camps.Present scales should be drastically revised to bring them into line with thosewhich have been approved for British troops in the West.   Modern design and[28574]
construction should be adopted, buildings should be made properly flyproof, andshould be fitted with modern appurtenances, including refrigerators, ampleshower baths, and good furniture. There should be no hesitation in requisitioningsuitable houses, irrespective of ownership, to serve as canteens and clubs in thelarger cities. Up-to-date and hygienic systems of preparing and cooking food should be brought into operation, and special attention should be paid to providing as varied a diet as possible.4. All this will require the provision of personnel, materials and equipment from the United Kingdom or the United States. Your demands should be -formu-lated without delay, and I will take steps to ensure that they are met as fully and as rapidly as possible.5. The presence of British women at leave centres, hostels, &amp;c, is ofimportance to the maintenance of morale. We at home are examining means foraugmenting the numbers available to proceed to India. You should furnish thestatement of your requirements for which you have been asked, and in the mean-while you should do all that you can to encourage the British women now inIndia to play their full part.6. Nothing will contribute more greatly to the wellbeing of the troops at the front than the rapid delivery of mails and fresh food, and the liberaluse of air transport for the evacuation of casualties, for the movement of menon urgent compassionate leave, and on ordinary leave from the forward areasso far as may be possible. %  very effort is being made to improve the services to the Far East, and to increase your resources in transport aircraft. A muchgreater quantity will be available when Germany is defeated, but in the mean-while in assessing the priorities for the use of transport aircraft you shouldaccord a greater degree of importance than at present to welfare purposes.7. The assurance of full support and a sense of contentment in the minds of the men and women in the Forces, including the merchant seamen, will yieldfruits on the battlefield. I count on you to drive these matters forward, and you can be sure that the efforts of those at home will be fully engaged to supportyou.w. s. c.10 Downing Street, S.W.1,20th November, 1944.Note. The above directive has been issued to the Viceroy under cover of thefollowing,letter from the Prime Minister : &quot; I feel it essential at the present time that I should keep in closepersonal touch with all those matters which are of such importance to the welfare and morale of the British forces in the Far Eastern theatres of war.I am anxious to ensure that all concerned work together to get the best
possible conditions for the men and women serving in the war against Japan,whose numbers will shortly be swelled by large transfers from the Europeantheatres. I know that much has already been done with limited resources,but we must do more. I hope the steps which I am taking, and which are set out below, will strengthen the hands of those concerned :  1. I am sending you the enclosed Directive, a copy of which goesseparately to Admiral Mountbatten, and a copy of which you should transmitto General Auchinleck.2. I have issued a separate Directive to Departments at home, to applyall possible pressure to meet those demands which are beyond the capacity ofIndia to furnish.3. I am appointing Major-General King, now Engineer-in-Chief atthe War Office, to be my personal representative in India and South-east asia with the acting rank of Lieutenant-General. General King will reportto me personally on the matters referred to in my Directive, and will thusenable me to ensure that obstacles are surmounted, and that unremittingefforts are made at home and abroad to secure the wellbeing of the services in the arduous Ear Eastern campaigns.&quot;A similar letter has been sent with the directive to the Supreme Commander,South-East Asia Command.




</content>
</cab>
