<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/53/10 images: 72-75</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1944.SECRET. ; Copy No.W.P. (44) 410.25th July, 1944.WAR CABINET.AGRICULTURAL MAN-POWER IN THE FIRST YEAR AFTERTHE  GERMAN  ARMISTICE.Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries and theSecretary of State for Scotland.1. In paragraph 2 of his memorandum (W.P. (44) 381) the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer sets out the four main objectives to which allocation of man-power should be directed in Stage II; and in paragraph 13 he suggests a line of approach to the problem of adjusting man-power demand to man-power supply.While we are in fundamental agreement with this summary of the position, and do not dissent from the line of approach suggested, we are anxious to remind our colleagues that agriculture has been set a definite task in the immediate future,a task which it cannot hope to accomplish if its man-power requirements are-scaled down.2. Agriculture&apos;s special position as a primary producer of food should be given special consideration. Agriculture should rank at least equally with the exporttrades, in as much as larger home production, while not providing the means to pay for imports, will reduce the volume of imports for which payment hasto be made. Moreover, world shortage of food after the end of the european war will make it difficult to maintain the flow of imports both of vegetable andanimal foods. Maintenance of the largest possible output of home producedfood will therefore contribute towards both (b) and. (d) in paragraph 2 of theChancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s Memorandum (W.P. (44) 381); they will reducethe size of the bill for imports and will help towards ensuring some increase inthe standard of living.3. These points have been recognised. We have been asked to maintain ahigh level of production and in particular to increase supplies of milk, meat and eggs. This, increase in the output of animal products will in turn necessitatenot only an expanded, acreage of fodder crops, and encouragement of the practiceof ley farming but also increased man-power to look after the livestock.4. For five years agriculture has been labouring under man-powerdifficulties, and the increase in production that has been accomplished has only been possible by calling upon all in the industry to work abnormally long hours,by retaining in active employment many whose retirement, for reasons of age, islong overdue, and by enlisting the help, continuous or periodical, of largenumbers of supplementary workers members of the forces, prisoners of war,schoolchildren and civilian volunteers at harvest camps, in land clubs and the like. Much of this labour will no longer be available after the German armistice.Farmers and farm workers will expect to have some relief from present excessivehours; older men and women will wish to retire; voluntary part-time help will inevitably fall off; within the first year many Italian prisoners will presumablybe repatriated.5. Agriculture will have, however, to perform an increased task. It will accordingly need more, not less, labour. We estimate that the intake into theindustry, other than the normal inflow of boys and girls, in the first post-Armisticeyear will be 150,000 to make good abnormal wastage, to afford some relief to farmers and workers, and to provide for additional output. If the proposal in[27886]&apos;
paragraph 13 of the Chancellor&apos;.? memorandum leads to an allocation to agriculture of only a proportion of its requirements, the food output will inevitably fall short of the programme.6. Approximate figures of agricultural man-power in June 1939, June 1943and estimated requirements in Stage II are shown below. These figures differ from those in W.P. (44) 362 because the latter exclude men over 64, women over59 and uninsured workers, of whom the most important constituent are the prisoners of war.Man-power in A griculture in Great Britain.(Thousands.)1939. &apos;  1943.              1945.(minimum required)Farmers&quot;      ......         327 331               335Farm workers Men       ......         618 620               917tWomen   ......           93 2221,038 1,173 1,252* Taken at 75 per cent, of number of agricultural holdings.f Increases over 1943: 40,000 to relieve long hours of work of farmers and farm workers;10,000 for ancillary industries (estate workers, farm drainage, &amp;c); 25,000 for care of increasedlive-stock-total 75,000.7. As indicated above, prospective losses among the older farmers and workers, and among the uninsured classes, will have to be filled by workers ofinsurable age. To some extent the loss of volunteer seasonal labour may be made good by the greater use of men in the services or by the use of men released fromthe forces before they take up other employment.8. We cannot accept the figure of 1,071,000, given in W.P. (44) 362 as agriculture^ man-power figure in Stage II, since it makes insufficient allowance for the factors enumerated in paragraph 4. Moreover; since it was computed,we have had to step up our programme for live-stock production. In our view thefigure in W.P. (44) 362 is underestimated by fully 80,000; if it were increased to1,151,000, the gap between the Ministry of Labour&apos;s figures and those of the agriculture Departments would become 101,000 in 1945 against 79,000 in 1939.R. S. H.T. J.25th July, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
