<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/8/37 images: 370-377</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
BEJ  FT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 225  (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Tuesday, August 13, 1940, at 12 noon.Present :The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair]The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer(Items 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air (Item 1).The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister of Economic Warfare(Items 1-5).Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff(Item 1).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. R. H. Cross, M.P.,Minister of Shipping (Items 1-5).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 1-3).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[21640]THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  August 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)225th Conclusions.
WAR CABINET 225  (40).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Naval and Air Operations    ...      ...      ...      ...       ...     227Air.Naval operations.2      U.S.S.R. ...      ......      ............     227Attitude to be adopted towards Soviet absorption of the baltic states.Gold of the Baltic States Banks.Proposed trade agreement with Soviet.Shipping.3      Dangerous Areas       ...       ...      ...      ...       ...       ...     229Proposed declarations in respect of the English Channel and the atlantic coast of France.4      Australia        .........      ...      ......      ...    229Air liner disaster.5      Contraband Control   ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       ...     229Admission of food-stuffs to enemy-occupied   territory   and   un-occupied France.6      The Military Situation        ...      ............     230.   7      The Middle East       ..................    230The military situation.
227W.M. 225 (4.0).1. The Chief of the Air Staff said that there had been considerable enemy air activity that morning. One raid had come over the Thames Estuary, and another, estimated at 250 aircraft,had come in over Selsey Bill as far as Horsiham. According toreports so far available, the casualties were as follows : Our Own 3 aircraft crashed.2 unaccounted for.Enemy 6 confirmed.11 unconfirmed.19 damaged.The final figures of air casualties during the previous day&apos;sfighting had been : Our Own 13 machines (4 pilots safe).Enemy 62 destroyed (certain).36 probable.39 damaged.The total civilian and service casualties during the twenty-four hours ending at 6 - 0 that morning had been 63 killed and 155 injured.Naval The First Sea Lord reported that an engagement had takenOperations.        place the previous night between three of our M.T.B.S and a numberof E-Boats, with the result that one E-Boat had been rammed butnot sunk.The First Sea Lord gave the War Cabinet information aboutthe dispositions of the Home Fleet.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Naval and air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 224thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air.U.S.S.R.Attitude to beadopted towardsSovietabsorption ofthe baltic states.(previous references:W.M. (40) 223rdConclusions,Minutes 2and 3.)Gold of theBaltic StatesBanks.2. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (40) 312) containing adraft telegram to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Moscow definingour attitude to the Soviet annexation of the Baltic States.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that Sir stafford cripps, while agreeing that there was no immediate prospect ofEussia changing her policy, thought that she might do so later on.He therefore urged that it would be unwise to make difficulties overour attitude towards the Soviet annexation of the Baltic States.The Foreign Secretary said that his belief was that soviet policy would be realistic and that she would not risk trouble withGermany at the present time. He saw great difficulty in grantingde jure recognition, which would be distressing to the Poles, andpuzzling to the United States, and in his view would not be ofgreat value to the Soviet. He suggested, however, that we mightrecognise that the Soviet Government were de facto in administrative control of the Baltic States and be .prepared todeal with them on that basis in matters affecting those States. Asregards the retention of Baltic gold and ships, he thought we were bound to do our best to ensure compensation for the loss of british property, but, subject to this, he thought that we should giveSir Stafford Cripps a measure of discretion as to the best meansof arriving at this result.The following points were made in discussion : (1) The  Chancellor of  the  Exchequer  reminded  the  WarCabinet that the State Banks of the three Baltic States,[21640] b 2
acting under duress, had instructed the Bank ofEngland to hand over their gold to the Russian StateBank. The Treasury had instructed the Bank ofEngland not to hand over the gold, and a defence regulation had subsequently been made giving legalcover to this instruction. The United States Govern-ment had also frozen the Baltic States&apos; assets.(2) If the Soviet Governments claim to this gold were nowrecognised and the ban on transfer removed, we shouldbe unable to prevent the gold from being paid over tothe Russian State Bank and should lose all control overit. What chance should we then have of recoupingourselves for the loss of British property in the BalticStater ?(3) Further, :he United States Government had frozen the balances of all the countries overrun by Germany.   Ifwe were to unfreeze the Baltic gold, we might therebyencourage the United States to unfreeze the frozen.balances of the invaded countries.The Minister for Economic Warfare agreed withthis view, and thought that the United States Govern-ment should be consulted before action was taken on thismatter.(4) The Minister for Economic Warfare added that cautionmust be exercised in regard to the money value put on certain claims submitted by British firms in the baltic states, and in regard to the extent of diplomatic support which should be accorded to them.Proposed Trade (5) The Minister for Economic Warfare thought that the lastAgreement with sentence of the draft telegram should be omitted, sinceSoviet. the instructions given to Sir Stafford Cripps, before leaving for Moscow, by his Department had been that abarter arrangement should be made in the first instance,preliminary to a War Trade Agreement.Shipping. (6) The Minister of Shipping was anxious not to detain Balticshipping indefinitely. It was felt, however, that to requisition Baltic ships at the present moment wouldmake Sir Stafford Cripps&apos;s task harder, and that theships should therefore continue to be detained for, say,another week, subject to review thereafter.(7) The general view of the War Cabinet was that the line taken in the draft telegram was right. De factoagreement must be conceded, but it would be reasonable to withhold de jure recognition pending a general peace settlement.(8) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pointed out that sir Stafford Cripps had arranged to see M. Lozovski onthe following day (telegram No. 606 from Moscow).There would not, therefore, be time for the United Statesreaction to the proposal for dealing with the Baltic gold to be received before this interview; but it seemed unlikely that rapid progress would be made in thenegotiations at Moscow.The War Cabinet-. (1) Approved the despatch to Sir Stafford Cripps of the draft telegram prepared by the Foreign Secretary, subject tothe following :-(a) The last sentence of paragraph 9 of the draft shouldbe omitted.(b) It should be made clear that we should not in any circumstances hand over the gold of the Baltic
State Banks until we had received satisfactorycompensation for British interests.(c) It should be explained to Sir Stafford Cripps thatwe did not wish to be committed to return theBaltic gold until we had had an opportunity of consulting the United States Government.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, afterconsultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, to instruct Lord Lothian to ascertain how the UnitedStates Government would be likely to view the suggestionthat the gold of the Baltic State Banks should be released in exchange for adequate compensation for the interestsof our nationals.(3) Agreed that, for the time being, Baltic shipping in british ports should continue to be detained and should not berequisitioned.DangerousAreas.Proposeddeclarations inrespect of theEnglish channel and the Atlanticcoast of France.(previous references:W.M. (40) 195thConclusions,Minute 2, andW.M. (40) 211thConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theFirst Lord of the Admiralty (W.P. (40) 311) proposing to declareas dangerous to shipping areas bordering the English Channel andthe Atlantic coast of France.The Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs said that, whilsthe recognised the necessity of the First Lord&apos;s proposals, he was alittle apprehensive about their effect on Spain. It would helpmatters if Spanish coasting vessels could be treated with a certainamount of leniency.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that he would bear theForeign Secretary&apos;s point in mind, but it must be remembered thatsuch vessels might be used by Germany for hostile purposes. Therewould be no interference with shipping in Spanish territorial waters.The War Cabinet approved the proposals of the First Lordof the Admiralty.Australia.Air Linerdisaster.an4. The Prime Minister said that news had been received ofair accident in Australia, in which three commonwealth ministers (Brigadier Street, Mr. Fairbairn and Sir II. Gullet) andSir C. Brudenell White, the Chief of the Australian General Staff,had lost their lives. The Prime Minister was invited to send asuitable message to Australia expressing the profound regret withwhich the War Cabinet had received this news.contraband control.Admission of foodstuffs to enemy-occupied territory andunoccupiedFrance.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 223rdConclusions,Minute 4.)5. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that atelegram had been received from Lord Lothian suggesting that thetime was ripe for a public statement to be made as to the admissionof foodstuffs to enemy-occupied territory and unoccupied France.This statement should be on the lines of the discussion in the WarCabinet on the 9th August.The Prime Minister suggested the inclusion of a passage onthe subject in the statement he was to make in Parliament on tuesday, the 20th August. This procedure would avoid undueemphasis.The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, inconsultation with the Minister of Economic Warfare, to
draft a passage dealing with this question, for inclusion in the Prime Minister&apos;s statement to be made on the20th August.The Military 6.   A record of the discussion on this subject, and of theSituation. conclusions reached, is contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard file of War Cabinet Conclusions.The middle east.The militarysituation.(previous reference:W.M. (40.) 222ndConclusions,Minute 10.)7. A record of the discussion on this subject, and of theconclusions reached, is contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard file of War Cabinet Conclusions.Richmond Terrace, S. W. 1,August 13, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
