<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/19/0 images: 12-14</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
The weiaiatieH of this paper has been strictly limited. 6t is issued for the persona! use of .......:./4^W^^V;^)f\*^......TOP SECRET. Copy No.CP. (47) 1539th May, 1947CABINETESTABLISHMENT OF DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH THEGOVERNMENT OF THE UKRAINIAN SOVIET SOCIALISTREPUBLICMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs ^I should welcome the approval of the Cabinet for an approach to the Govern-ment of the Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic through the Ministry for ForeignAffairs of the U.S.S.R. suggesting that diplomatic relations be established betweenthe Ukraine and the United Kingdom. I have discussed this proposal with HisMajesty&apos;s Ambassador in Moscow and have reached the conclusion that we have little to lose and a good deal to gain by such a move.Recommendation2. I recommend that the Governments of the Dominions be first consulted onthis proposal and, if they agree, the United States Government.ConsiderationsPresent Position3. Neither the United Kingdom nor the Dominions have at present anyrepresentative in the U.S.S.R. outside Moscow. The Soviet Government, on theother hand, has diplomatic representatives in London, Ottawa, Canberra andWellington, and in addition has consular representatives in Halifax (NovaScotia) and Pretoria, with an acting consular agent at Capetown. Taking theCommonwealth as a whole, the balance is thus heavily in favour of the soviet union.4. For purposes of comparison it may be mentioned that the United StatesGovernment have a diplomatic representative in Moscow, a consular represen-tative in Vladivostok and a Naval Control Officer at Odessa. The Soviet Govern-ment have a diplomatic representative in Washington and consular representatives in New York, San Francisco and Los Angeles. Again the balance is in favourof the U.S.S.R. There are also some Chinese and a Persian consul in the soviet union; but in spite of this the Soviet Government steadfastly refused during thewar to agree to the opening of British consulates on a basis of reciprocity andthere is thought to be no likelihood of their changing their attitude. If, therefore,our representation in the Soviet Union is to be extended outside Moscow, it willbe necessary to enter into direct relations with one or more of the constituentRepublics.Diplomatic Representation in the Constituent Republics of the U.S.S.R.5.   Under a law of 1st February, 1944, an article (18a) was added to theSoviet Constitution under which each Constituent Republic has&quot;the right to enter1405D-33601Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1947
into direct relations with foreign States, to conclude agreements with them and exchange diplomatic and consular representatives with them. So far as is known,no Union Republic has yet availed itself of the right thus conferred upon it to exchange representatives with other States.6. The War Cabinet decided on the 5th June, 1944 (W.C. 72 (44) ) that thequestion of the recognition of the constituent Republics of the U.S.S.R. forpurposes of international representation should be postponed until the peace settlement and that the Governments of the Dominions and the United states should be informed of this decision. It was agreed at the time that His Majes,ty&apos;sGovernment would keep in touch with the Governments of the Dominions in theevent of the Russians making any move bearing on this matter. In August 1944the State Department agreed informally with His Majesty&apos;s Embassy atWashington that there should be a full exchange of views and information on&quot;this subject. We are thus committed to consulting the Dominions and the UnitedStates Government before we alter our attitude. Subsequently the Soviet Govern-ment pressed for the admission to the United Nations of all sixteen constituentSoviet Republics. His Majesty&apos;s Government, the Dominions and the UnitedStates Governments all declined to agree to this, but after prolonged discussion the Ukraine and Byelo-Russia were admitted to membership of the united nations Organisation (the War Cabinet&apos;s concurrence was given on 8th February,1945 [W.MI (45) 16th Conclusions]). It may be added that on two recent occasionsofficials of the State Department have said that; the United States Governmentwould be reluctant to take official cognizance of the Ukrainian Government forpurposes other than membership of the United Nations..7. The admission of the Ukraine and Byelo-Russia to the United&apos;nations organisation constituted recognition of these two constituent republics as separateentities for; international purposes and a proposal to exchange diplomatic repre-sentatives: with the Ukraine would not therefore be a departure from principle.Itriswith the Ukraine that it: would be most worthwhile to have direct diplomatic relations.   The advantages would be  -(i) we should have a regular source of reports on an area of the U.S.S;R:which is of great economic and military, if not political^importance.The Ukraine is the second largest Republic in the U.S.S..K,.;(ii) we should have another centre in the Soviet Union for contacts and the spread of cultural, if not political, influence;(iii) we should learn about the working in practice of the Soviet machineryof government outside Moscow.8. In return we should merely have to accept the addition of: a fewUkrainians to the Diplomatic Corps in London. They would really be littlemore than additions to the staff of the Sovist Embassy. If we are refusedpermission, as is probable in view of the difficult conditions at present prevailing in the Ukraine, we shall have done something to expose the unreality of theUkraine&apos;s pretensions to independence and we shall have an additional argument&apos;for refusing to recognise or to admit the separate representation of other consti-tuent republics, especially the three Baltic republics, on international bodies.Incidentally the fact that we are asking for diplomatic relations to be established with the Ukraine might, in itself, deter the Soviet Government from asking for recognition; of other parts of the Soviet Union.9; The possible disadvantage of the proposal is that, whereas it is generally known that we agreed to the admission of the Ukraine and Byelo-Russia to theUnited Nations Organisation because there was no other way in which Sovietconcurrence and participation could be obtained, and . whereas it is generally recognised at present that both republics are, in foreign affairs at any rate,mere puppets of the Soviet Government, we might by ourselves proposing an exchange of diplomatic representatives with the Ukraine confer a certain airof respectability on it. It may, however, be argued that the principle of separaterepresentation was really given away when we admitted these states to the united nations Organisation and that having given the principle away we might aswell derive what advantage we can from it.E. B.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,9th May, 1947.


</content>
</cab>
