<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/19/0 images: 71-74</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
qaciiLflnp..J^,lJl...At. /.g^--llS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRIT ANN IC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP. (47)162. COPY NO.   ^)lSTft MAY.  19U7.cabinet coal imports memorandum by the Minister of state .     At its 16th Meeting^on 16th April the Fuel committee agreed that an application should be made to the european coal Organisation for an allocation of coal to be imported into the United Kingdom during the third quarter of 1947and proposed that steps should be taken to secure the supportof the United States Government for such an application.2-     The steps which have been&apos; taken to implement theCommittee&apos;s decision are described in a paper by the Ministerof Fuel and Power which is now before the Cabinet (C.P.(1+7)159)3*      It will be seen that the attitude of the United Statestowards our allocation is likely to be determined by thatof other members of the European Coal organisation; andthat while the general response to our proposal has beenforthcoming,   the French have taken the discussions to thepolitical level and have suggested that they will not supportour application unless we are prepared to give them a priorassurance that&quot;we will support a tripartite declaration toE.CO. concerning the incorporation of the Saar in france for purposes of coal allocation.     This under the existingE.C.6. formula would result in additional coal being madeavailable to the French at the expense of other european countries, in receipt of German coal.      To overcome this objection the French have proposed s sliding scalearrangement which they think will make the proposal accept-able to other E.CO. countries.1+.      I do&apos; not propose&apos; to burden my colleagues with precisedetails of the French proposal,  the statistical basis ofwhich is not yet fully agreed.      But in- itself it is not an unreasonable one.    But it will be necessary, before we agree to it, to ascertain the views of the American Government,since they would also have to be associated with anytripartite decision concerning .eoal production in the Saar.I am taking steps to seek their views urgently, but it seems doubtful whether it will be possible to give the Frenchsatisfactory assurances in advance of the meeting of theEuropean Coal Organisation, which takes place on 21st May,to consider third, quarter coal allocations.F. C.  (1+7) 16th Meeting, Minute 3.-1-
5,      I do not at this stage propose to say more to the Frenchthan that we see no    objection to it in principle but thatwe cannot pursue it further until the two questions whichare   at present under negotiation with the French,namely the Saar frontiers and. the reparations value of the saar, had been settled.6.      In the circumstances we cannot be sure of the attitude which the French will adopt towards our own application.While they may not wish to oppose it openly, it is not improbable that they will seek to influence the views ofother E.C.O. members unfavourably towards it, and theymay welj. stimulate a press campaign to the effect that theUnited Kingdom is endeavouring to deprive Fr nee of much-needed supplies of coal.7*     We must therefore, in my view, be prepared for thepossibility of considerable opposition to our applicationwhen E,C*0, meets on 21st June; and we cannot be sure^thatour application will receive American, support.     In;&quot;thesecircumstances, I would urge my colleagues to&apos; give our negotiators on the Organisation full discretion to withdraw the application, rather than force it to an issue on thisinternational committee against French opposition andwithout American support.     In particular, I would hope thatthey would follow this course if the, quantity of coaldeclared available for the third quarter by the UnitedStates and from the Western,Zones of Germany is substantially less than the maximum forecasts which have been made.This would mean both that the quantity of coal which weshould hope to obtain through such an application would be small, and that, we should only obtain it at the expenseof other countries, whose coal needs in their own view are quite as great as our own,8.      Another important factor is the entry into force ofthe agreement reached at Moscow with the French and the americans for a percentage increase in the allocation tothe E,CO* pool from Ruhr production after Ruhr productionreached a certain level.    This increase was expected totake effect on 1st July,  and the French Government have represented this agreement as a political and economic gain.Moreover - the recent drop in Ruhr production makes it very unlikely.that this agreement will now take effect on1st July, and the French will be correspondingly dejected,and resentful.9*      The repercussions on our foreign policy if we insist on a coal allocation without regard to the interests of othercoal-importing countries are liable to be very far-reachingand, if the quantity of coal concerned is small, out of,proportion to the benefits which we should receive.      Fromthe point of view of our European neighbours,  and particularly of France, with whom we must continue to work in closestrelationship in our own interest, the current coal shortage,which is the core of their economic problem as well, as ours,is inevitably regarded as due in-the main to our own inability to supply them with coal as before the war.     They are already,inclined to lay this, their major economic trouble,  at ourdoor.      If in addition we proceed, by seeking an allocation
so for imported coal, ourselves to deprive them of substantial quantities of this much-needed commodityfrom other sources, the effect on Anglo-French relationsmay be very serious.      Coal is capable of becoming the  .determining factor in French polities at the moment.10.    But if these availabilities are less than anticipatedand if our application encounters serious opposition,I hope it will be withdrawn, on the ground thatdesperately as&apos;&quot;we need this additional quantity of coal,we would not wish to press for it at the expense ofour European neighbours,  and particularly France.,(Intld.)    H. McN.Foreign Office, S.W.I.18TH MAY, 194-7**


</content>
</cab>
