<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/19/0 images: 116-134</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secretCP. (47) 16828th May, 1947&apos; Printed for the Cabiiiet. - May 1947Copy No.CABINETAERODROMES IN THE UNITED kingdom memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion AffairsTHE Minister of Civil Aviation has submitted to the Civil Aviation Com-mittee a programme for the establishment of aerodromes in the United Kingdomoutside the London area, based on the probable requirements of the network ofinternal civil air services which will eventually be established in this country.2. The plan is described in detail in the annexed memorandum by theMinister of Civil Aviation. Its main features may be summarised as follows : (a) So far as possible the aim has been to select pre-war or war-time aero-dromes and to secure joint user with the Service and Supply Depart-ments. In the result only six entirely new sites are required, and ofthese four are in remote parts of Scotland where new aerodromes are proposed to provide air services considered by the Scottish Office tobe essential in view of the inadequacy of surface communication. Theremaining two hew sites are intended to serve Newcastle and Crewerespectively, where there are no suitable existing aerodromes.(b) Apart from developing six new sites the Minister proposes to acquireand convert for civil use some 59 existing aerodromes. Of these 17are already owned in whole or in part by the State, 31 are on requisi-tioned land and the remaining 11 are under private or municipalcontrol.(c) The estimated total cost of the programme is  37 million, but this esti-mate is necessarily tentative and may be subject to modification asfurther experience is gained of present day costs of labour and.   materials.&apos; &apos; &apos;.....&quot;id) The cost of land acquisition and compensation for disturbance was estimated to amount to about  5,750,000 before the recent decision fora departure from the 1939 standard for the acquisition of land for public purposes. The total expenditure involved in the first phase ofthe plan, including works services, the cost of land acquisition and compensation is now estimated at rather more than  18 million. Mostof the constructional work represented by this sum will be needed assoon as it can be undertaken. - ;Internal Air Services _3. The network of internal air services which is shown in Appendix II to-the memorandum by the Minister of Civil Aviation is necessarily tentative insome of its details. Plans for air services must be capable of variation in thelight of experience. The policy should be to give priority to services which aresocially necessary because of the lack of other means of communication or arecommercially justified by existing or prospective demand. On internal routes theservices in the Scottish Highland and Islands, for example, and those to belfast and the Channel Islands clearly have high priority. Services between townswhich are well served by rail, particularly where the distance is short, can wait.At this: stage it would waste national resources and perhaps cause prematuredisplacement of labour from surface to air transport, to run air services between,for instance, London and Brighton and London and Birmingham. On longerdistances where air transport makes the difference between getting there and back[33684] b
in a day, with time for business during the visit, there is a much stronger case.No general conclusions can be reached on which services qualify for high priorityon these considerations; the decision is one to be taken in the light of theparticular circumstances of the time, as the programme is worked out. Providedthat the ground organisation is available, variations in routes and services canreadily take place. . CContinental Services4. On the considerations mentioned in the preceding paragraph, a high priority must be given to direct connections by air between provincial centres and the Continent. The Minister of Civil Aviation proposes that out of thefourteen aerodromes for Continental Services mentioned in paragraph 9 of his memorandum, priority should be given to the immediate development of seven,viz., Belfast, Birmingham, Cardiff, Glasgow, Manchester, Newcastle and theWest Riding.At present all British operated Continental services operate from London,and the initiation of Continental services from the provinces should provide anurgently needed relief to congestion of air traffic in the London area.Subject to the views of the Chancellor of the Exchequer who has not hadan opportunity of examining in detail the acquisition programme involved,, we agree that priority should be given to the acquisition and development of theseievenv aerodromes. &apos; If they are brought tb &quot;standards&quot;appropriate for CohtihentfallServices and1 relatively modest improvements are made at other existing;&quot;aero?dronies, a: workable ittterini network of both Continental and internal services&quot;ean be provided-without baiting., for -the whole aerodrome, development programme .to be completed.        ^ - -   - .&apos;       -      1 j -      - v.Acquisition -      &apos; f;;&quot;&apos; &quot; - &quot;*  v&quot;&apos;5. The Minister of C iyij Aviation asks, for authority to treat the aerodromes and sites listed in Appendix I of his Memorandum as a working programme and,subject to Treasury approval,&apos; to proceed as necessary with acquisition.. We understand that, as the Chancellor of the Exchequer has not so far hadail opportunity of examining the. proposals in detail, he would, before giving his approval to the &quot;programme, desire to satisfy himself on its financial aspectsincluding&quot; the questionof the revenue which the Ministry of Civil Aviation (asthe owhersbf the aerodromes) and the nationalised operators using the aerodromesare likely to obtain. Subject to his views, however,, we agree that the Ministerof&apos; Civil Aviation should be authorised to proceed with acquisition (seeparagraph 6 below). .Ii. support of this recommendation we would point put that; until decisions have been taken oh the aerodrome programme, long-term planning of our internalair services must lack reality. Moreover, it is only fair to the owners ofrequisitioned property that adequate notice should be given of the governments intention to acquire their land. It should also be borne in mind that some 14 million of war works expenditure has. already been incurred on runways,hangars, factories and other buildings on many of the sites to be requisitioned.The recent decision to extend the Requisitioned Land and War Works Act fora further four years will relieve the pressure for immediate acquisition to securethe value of this expenditure to the State; nevertheless, acquisition with thisobject will be necessary within the extended period now available.6. In paragraph 3 above we have touched on the question as to how far it is justifiable to go in present economic circumstances in the development ofinternal air services, particularly in cases where existing surface communications are reasonably adequate. The issues involved are for the most part outside our termsof reference, but we may perhaps say that we feel doubtful whether any general conclusion is possible. As he has pointed out in his memorandum, the Ministersscheme is elastic and can be varied in the light of experience. We suggest, there-fore, that the point should be dealt with as each part comes up for consideration.The approval of an aerodrome programme as such does not commit theGovernment as regards the rate of completion of that programme or to any specificplan of air services; and as indicated below the works part of the programme(and to some extent the land acquisition part as well) can be phased to take account of financial and economic conditions and of changes in those conditions.7.   The actual carrying out of constructional work on the aerodromes will depend on the amount of money, labour and materials that can be spared for civil
aviation from the national resources, and it will be for the Minister of CivilAviation to consult with the Treasury, and the Investment Working Party, whendeciding as to the timing of each project and the scale of the work to becarried out.The Bristol Airport8. It will be recalled that in pur report on the facilities required at Filtonin connection with the development of the Brabazon I (C.P. (46) 99), we said that,prima facie, if it were decided to spend large sums of public money on theconstruction of a runway at Filton there were good grounds for establishing themain Bristol civil airport in that location.The Minister of Civil Aviation has given further consideration to thequestion of tihe site of the civil airport for Bristol, and after detailed investigartion and inter-departmental discussions has decided that Lulsgate Bottom is the better choice on the score not only of operational suitability but also of cost.We have examined in some detail the evidence in favour of Lulsga,te Bottomas set but in Appendix V to the Minister of Civil Aviation&apos;s memorandum andwe conclude that, on tihe whole, Lulsgate Bottom should be developed as the maincivil airport for Bristol in preference to Filton.In support of this we should add that, apart from the provision of the extended runway needed for the Brabazon machine being completed there, ribother expenditure has been incurred. :Public Announcement ,,,: 9. The Minister of Civil Aviation asks for authority to make a public announcement of his plans in tihe terms of Appendix IV of his memorandum.The list of places to be served included in this statement covers only those where there is an existing requirement for the provision of air services and whereit is clear that some provision of ground facilities will have to be made in thenext three to four years. A few places are also included, e.g., Hull and Swansea,in respect of which the Minister feels he is committed to an early announcement-of his plans.Subject to the views of the. Chancellor of the Exchequer on the desirabilityof including this list, we agree that the Minister should be authorised to make astatement on tihe lines he proposes.Summary of Conclusions10. -(i) Subject to the views of the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Ministerof Civil Aviation should be authorised to treat the aerodromes andsites listed in Appendix I of his memorandum as a workingprogramme.   (Paragraph 5.)(ii) Priority should be given to the development of seven aerodromesrequired for direct services to the Continent.  (Paragraph 4.)(iii) The phasing of the prograhime of air services, of constructional workon the aerodromes, and, to the extent to which it is practicable, the phasing of the process of acquisition, should be determined inconsultation with the Treasury and the Investment Working Party.(Paragraphs 3, 6 and 7.)(iv) Lulsgate Bottom should be developed as the main civil aerodrome for- Bristol, notwithstanding tihe work on a runway which is being carriedout at Filton at Government expense.   (Paragraph 8.)(v) Subject to the views of the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Ministerof Civil Aviation should be authorised to make a public announcementof his plans in the terms of Appendix IV of his memorandum.(Paragraph 9.)Dominions Office, S.W.1,28th May, 1947. ,       -[33684]
&apos; -ANNEX 1 -;. -    . , . .1. ....   -AERODROMES IN THE UNITED KINGDOM (OUTSIDE-THE, LONDON AREA)Memorandum by the Minister of Civil Aviation1. The White Paper on British Air Services (Cmd. 6712) presented by my predecessor, in December 1945 outlined the Governments policy for the acquisition and management by the State of all aerodromes used by scheduled air services.2. The purpose of this memorandum is to set out for the information ofmy colleagues the present position regarding acquisition and management by theState of aerodromes required for scheduled air transport services in the UnitedKingdom, outside the London area. The provision of aerodromes to serve theLondon area presents a special problem by reason of the size of the population to be served and the inevitable concentration of overseas services on the capital. I shallsubmit a further memorandum on the London aerodrome situation in the nearfuture as well as on marine airports and any special provision required for the brabazon I.Basis of Selection3. The planning of future air services and the sequence in which they willbe introduced is proceeding by reference to such fundamental criteria as popula-tion, commercial activity (existing and prospective) and alternative forms oftransport. But plans made now must remain fluid and be varied in the lightof experience. Provided, however, that the ground organisation is available,variations in routes and services can readily take place. The aerodromes listed in Appendix I of this memorandum, are those which I expect to be broughtinto use for scheduled services within, say, the next four or five years, althoughfurther study and operating experience may show that other aerodromes besidesthese may be needed within the same period. The map at Appendix II depictsthe connections at present contemplated for these aerodromes, although, as I have mentioned above, experience as the air services plan develops may show thatcertain variations are desirable. A number of the services is, of course, already in operation.4. It has been the aim in planning the aerodrome programme to make themaximum use of pre-war or war-time aerodromes. Only six entirely new sitesare included and, of these, four are in remote parts of Scotland where newaerodromes are needed to provide air services desired by the Scottish Office.The suitability of these sites is subject to confirmation when further technicaldetails are available. The remaining two new sites are in England, to serveNewcastle and Crewe; these are referred to in more detail in paragraph 7 below.In addition a number of very small grass aerodromes in the Orkney Islands which fell into disuse during the war will have to be reconstructed and improved. Inall other cases, the aerodromes listed in Appendix I are existing aerodromes.5. In selecting aerodromes for acquisition, I have also been guided by theneed for economy in the use of land. To the greatest possible extent, therefore,joint user with Service or Supply Departments has been secured, and, where thishas not been possible, I have endeavoured to select aerodromes already provided with hard runways and not, therefore, restorable to other uses without consider-able difficulty and expense. Of the fifty-nine aerodromes mentioned in Appendix I,at least three and possibly five will be used short-term only. Thirty-eight of the aerodromes mentioned will be used jointly with other &quot; Flying &quot; Departments, andtwenty-one only will be required for civil aviation alone. These twenty-one includesix very small aerodromes in remote districts where there is a civil air transportneed, but no Service or Supply interest. There is also no Service or Supplyinterest at present in any of the six proposed hew sites. All the war-time aero-dromes selected for retention for civil aviation are aerodromes already provided with hard runways.War Works Expenditure &quot;:6. It will not be necessary for my Department to acquire all the fifty-nineaerodromes named in Appendix I Seventeen are already wholly or partly State-owned, and thirty-one are on requisitioned land. Some of the latter are beingor will be purchased by Service Departments. On many of those which I proposeto purchase, war works expenditure amounting to over  14 million has been
(incurred on runways, hangars, factories-and other, buildings as compared with a cost of: acquisition (estimated on 1939 values plus supplements where appropriate),for this particular group of aerodromes, of  3,500,000. The cost of acquisition;may be increased, in accordance with recently announced Government policy,applying current restricted market valuations to land acquired for public^purposes, but it will still be considerably less than the cost of Government expen-diture already incurred on these aerodromes. The alternative to acquisition bymyself in these cases would be: (a) acquisition by other Departments under the Requisitioned Land and WarWorks Act (particularly where the land is in multiple ownership or- where the value of war works must be preserved); or(b) derequisitioning, involving, no doubt, heavy claims for reinstatement upto the value of the land itself.I am advised that under the Civil Aviation Act notices to treat must, ifadjustments for compensation in respect of war works expenditure are to beobtained, be issued before the expiry of the Requisitioned Land and War WorksApt, 1945. The recent decision to introduce legislation to extend the Requi-sitiohed Land and War Works Act for another four years does in some respectsreduce the urgency for acquisition of the aerodromes named. It is, nevertheless,only equitable that landowners of requisitioned property should be given theearliest possible indication of the Governments intention to acquire their property, even though actual acquisition does not take place for some little time.Special Cases7.   There are a few cases that present special features :-(a) The choice of a civil airport for Bristol lay between Filton, on whicha new long runway is being laid by the Ministry of Supply for thetesting of the Brabazon I and other aircraft, and the ex-Royal AirForce airfield at Lulsgate Bottom. After detailed investigations andinterdepartmental discussions, it has been concluded that LulsgateBottom is the better choice on the score not only of operational suita-bility but also of cost. The case is developed in detail in Appendix V.The pre-war municipal aerodrome, Whitchurch, is too small formodern aircraft but it may be necessary to retain it, at any rate fora time, both on account of the Government expenditure incurred on it during the war and its usefulness as a maintenance base.(b) At Crewe an aerodrome is required solely for the operation of air mailservices; the only existing aerodrome within acceptable distance isoperationally unsatisfactory and will not afford the safety andregularity required for these services. Pending the development ofa new site, the night air mail service will have to operate (at consider-able inconvenience to the G.P.O.) to-Manchester (Ringway). The best of the only two possible alternative sites for Crewe is at MinshullVerhon, but consists of valuable agricultural land. An effort is, there-fore, being made to devise a suitable layout on the other possible site at Weston Lane, part of which has, however, already been earmarked for a large factory.(c) There is some doubt whether Yeadon can be developed into a suitableaerodrome for the Leeds/Bradford area, where there is.a heavy trafficdemand. Technical investigations are proceeding, but no steps willbe taken to acquire it until it is demonstrated that it is capable ofsatisfactory improvement.Doncaster has been selected as the airport for Doncaster, Sheffield and, the surrounding area, and for development up to the standard necessaryfor services direct to the Continent,  While it is being extended, Yorkmay have to be used temporarily to serve a wide area.   York aero-drome will in any case probably be required later for services to meet, purely local traffic demands, and the heavy war works expenditure andthe fact that the land is in eighteen different ownerships are addi-tional arguments for acquisition.(e) For Newcastle, there is no existing aerodrome suitable for: modern types of transport aircraft nearer than Croft, 38 miles away. ^ The best site:        for an aerodrome for Newcastle and the north-east of England is atBoldon, just south of the proposed Tyne Tunnel.   It lies on coal-bearing strata, but further technical investigations are proceedingj order to minimise the amount of- coal sterilised. ,       ,
(/) At Cardiff, the pre-war civil aerodrome at Pengam Moors is too smallfor any but small aircraft and can only be extended at enormous cost.Llandow will be developed for internal trunk routes and possibly; continental services.  But Pengam Moors, which is half a mile fromthe City Centre, is essential to the success of the intensive air ferryservice across the Bristol Channel and will be retained for that purposewith joint use by the Air Ministry and Ministry of Supply.Cabinet Airfields committee. As the aerodrome programme in Appendix I has been in process ofevolution, the proposals have been made known to, and agreed by, the OfficialSub-Committees of the Cabinet Airfields Committee. Further inter-departmentaldiscussions will take place before new sites are developed or extensions to existing aerodromes undertaken.Services to the Continent9. I attach importance to the introduction of services from provincial centresdirect to the Continent. This will not only give relief to congestion of air traffic in the London area, but should provide a stimulus to provincal business and help to counteract the drift towards London. The places which have been provisionallyearmarked for continental services are Aberdeen, Belfast, Birmingham, Bristol,Cardiff, Edinburgh, Glasgow, Hull, Leeds, Liverpool, Manchester, Newcastle,Sheffield (Doncaster) and Swansea. Some of the aerodromes require extension,and the development programme must be spread over a number of years. In theearly years not more than seven aerodromes would be developed for continentalservices. No developments required solely for continental services will be under-taken except after most careful consideration.10. I dp hot at present contemplate the use of any airports other than theLondon Airport and Prestwick for regular trans-Atlantic and other long-distanceservices. Prestwick will need to be further developed to remain suitable for this class of traffic and, owing to the nature of the site, its development will be difficult and costly. Technical investigations are proceeding. To undertake improve-ments is politically essential, and, indeed, my predecessor gave an undertaking in the House that improvements would be made.Other aerodromes besides those mentioned in Appendix I will be used on occasions for diversionary purposes. I have, for political reasons, includedValley airfield in Anglesey in Appendix I although it will be used as a bad weather alternative only.Phasing of Expenditure;11. The principal financial expenditure over the next year or two will bein connection with the acquisition of aerodromes included in the programme andthe provision of certain minimum improvements, mainly lighting and temporarybuildings. There will also be a few urgent runway extensions and similar works.Later will come the main programme of development of other aerodromes whichare not at present operationally satisfactory for the aircraft that will be cominginto use in the future and the provision of passenger-handling-and; terminalfacilities generally on a more permanent basis. The assessment of costs, except asthe plan matures, isia matter of extreme difficulty. For example, the bearingstrengths of the runways and taxi tracks can normally be determined only afterexhaustive tests by specialised staff and special equipment. The demands on thisstaff and equipment by the Air Ministry and by my Department are so great thatit will be years, rather than months, before the programme can be completed. Ifit is found that in many cases runways, &amp;c, are below strength, the cost of relayingthem may well throw out the present estimates by a considerable figure. a financial estimate, under broad headings, based on the best information at present available is, however, given at Appendix III to this paper.   It will be seen that-the initial (Phase I) expenditure on the programme contained in Appendix I isestimated at rather more than  18 million, with further expenditure at a later stage (Phase II) on this same group of aerodromes of  19 million. There can,as far as can be seen at present, be reasonable latitude in the phasing of the; expenditure of the  19 million, but most of the work represented by the initial 18 million will be needed as soon as it is physically practicable to undertake it.Firmer estimates of costs will, of course, emerge piecemeal as the individualaerodrome cases are examined and surveyed in detail.
&quot;Aerodromes for Future Exteiisijoiis -of Air Services ,;.. 12. While the aerodromes listed in Appendix I represent a workable scheme&apos;oi aerodromes for the United- Kingdom, I cannot yet be certain that otheraerodromes will not, at a later date, be required for long-term ; expansion ofinternal air routes. T anticipate/however, that any requirements for addi-, tic-rial aerodromes could for the most part be met by the acquisition-at a later date of aerodromes in private or municipal ownership, or by joint use of serviceaerodromes, or by restoration of surplus war-time aerodromes.Public Announcement13. I ask my colleagues for approval of the programme in Appendix I asa working plan, so that I can press on with acquisition, where appropriate, andwith the necessary constructional work and installations to enable air services to expand as aircraft and personnel become available. Apart from this, I amcontinually being pressed by local authorities and other interests for decisions on particular cases, and it has been a cause of embarrassment, both in parliament and outside, to have to decline to give information on individual cases pendingan announcement of a general programme. It would, I consider, be prudent to withhold any public announcement except in general terms at this stage of thefour new sites needed in Scotland (see remarks in Appendix I against FortWilliam, Mull, Skye and Ullapool) and of a few other difficult cases. I propose,however, subject to the agreement of my colleagues, to make an announcement in the terms of Appendix IV. I would propose to release information later at my discretion about the places omitted from the announcement.   -Effect of IIelicopier Development : Ii 14. The aerodrome programme to which this memorandum relates is basedon the continuing use of conventional fixed-wing aircraft. It is, however,visualised that if and when a successful helicopter is developed capable of operating in all weather-with an economic payload it may be practicable torearrange the internal afr services of this-country on the basisjof a certainnutfiber of main trunk routes operated by fixed-wing aircraft, to and &quot;from whichhelicopter feeder-services can work. Various technical problems connected witJhthe helicopter have to be overcome, and it will probably be about tea years beforecommercial; services are operated on a substantial scale. When that stage isreached a Considerable economy in the use of land for aerodromes will beachievable. Helicopter aerodromes will not necessarily be very, small becauseadequate parking space is necessary for the aircraft, and in the interests of safety an adequate area around the actual alighting area must be safeguardedfrom obstruction. Nevertheless, the need for long runways at places of minortraffic importance will have disappeared and substantial economies in land use should thus ensue. The helicopter has not, however, at present reached a stage of development at which I should be justified in planning my aerodrome prdrgramme on this basis. The bulk of the expenditure in this programme relates tomain line aerodromes into which helicopter feeder-services would run from the surrounding areas.Conclusions .&apos;. &apos;r\ &apos; &apos; ,15.   Subject to the agreement of my colleagues I propose (i) To treat the aerodromes and sites listed in Appendix I of the attachedt Memorandum as a working programme, and, subject to treasury approval, to proceed as necessary with acquisition,(ii) Tb make a public announcement in the terms of Appendix IV and touse my discretion regarding public references to places and aerodromescontained in Appendix I but not mentioned in the announcement.(iii) To proceed, after detailed consideration and in consultation with otherDepartments, to put into effect schemes of development at individual.    aerodromes,(iv) To submit a further paper in-due course dealing with tlhe LondonAerodrome situation.N. of C.
&apos;:Aerodromes for Future Extensions of Air Services ;       i[i    , 12.   While the aerodromes listed in Appendix I represent a workable scheme-of aerodromes for the United Kingdom, I cannot yet be certain that otheraerodromes will not, at a later date, be required for long-term-expansion ofasternal air routes. I anticipate, however, that any requirements for addi-tional aerodromes could for the most part be met by the acquisition at a later date of aerodromes in private or municipal ownership, or by joint use of service-aerodromes, or by restoration of surplus war-time aerodromes.Public Announcement- 13. I ask my colleagues for approval of the programme in Appendix I asa working plan, so that I can press on with acquisition, where appropriate, andwith the necessary constructional work and installations to enable air services to expand as aircraft and personnel become available. Apart from this, I amcontinually being pressed by local authorities and other interests for decisions on particular cases, and it has been a cause of embarrassment, both in parliament and: outside, to have to decline to give information on individual cases pendingan announcement of a general programme. It would, I consider, be prudent to withhold any public announcement except in general terms at this stage of thefour new sites needed in Scotland (see remarks in Appendix I against FortWilliam, Mull, Skyer and Ullapool) and of a few other difficult cases.&quot; I propose,however, subject to ;the agreement of my colleagues, to make an announcement in the terms of Appendix IV. I would propose to release information later at my discretion about the places omitted from the announcement.   ;Effect of Helicopter]: Development y. ; ^&apos;; 14. The aerodrome programme to which this memorandum relates is basedon the continuing use of conventional fixed-wing aircraft. It! is, however,visualised that if and when a successful helicopter is developed-&quot;capable of operating in all Weal&amp;er :;with an economic payload it may be- practicable torearrange the internal air services pf this country on the basis of a certainnunlber of main trunk routes operated by fixed-wing aircraft, to and: from whichhelicopter feeder-services can work. Various technical problems connected with,the helicopter have to be overcome, and it will probably be about ten years beforecommercial&apos; services are operated on a substantial scale. When that stage fsreached a considerable economy in the use of land for aerodromes will beachievable. Helicopter aerodromes will not necessarily be very, small becauseadequate parking space is necessary for the aircraft, and in the interests of safety an adequate area around the actual alighting area must be safeguardedfrom obstruction. Nevertheless, the need for long runways at places of minortraffic importance will have disappeared and substantial economies in land use should thus ensue. The helicopter has not, however, at present reached a stage of development at which I should be justified in planning my aerodrome prdrgramme on this basis. The bulk of the expenditure in this programme relates tomain line aerodromes into which helicopter feeder-services would run from the surrounding areas. ;Conclusions15.   Subject to the agreement of my colleagues I propose (i) To treat the aerodromes and sites listed in Appendix I of the attached memorandum as a working programme, and, subject to treasury approval, to proceed as necessary with acquisition,(ii) To make a public announcement in the terms of Appendix IV and touse my discretion regarding public references to places and aerodromescontained in Appendix I but not mentioned in the announcement,(iii) To proceed, after detailed consideration and in consultation With otherDepartments, to put into effect schemes of development at individualaerodromes;.; (iv) To submit a further paper in due course dealing with tihe LondonAerodrome situation.N. of C.
APPENDIX I list of Aerodromes in the United Kingdom to be Incorporated in the Initial PlanStopping PlaceAerodromeAberdeen	Dyce       ...Anglesey Barnstaple	Valley      ...... Chivenor   ...Barra......	BarraBarrow Belfast Benbecula Birmingham ... Blackpool Bournemouth... Brighton, Hove and Worthing Bristol	Barrow Nutts Corner Benbecula ...      ... Elmdon Squires Gate.; Hum Shoreham ...     ... (a) Whitchurch   ... (b) Lulsgate BottomCampbeltown...	MachrihanishCardiff	(a) Pengam Moors... (b) LlandowCarlisle... &apos;	Great Orton       ...Crewe ...	(i) Minshull Vemon site or (ii) Weston Lane siteEdinburgh	turn house......Pre-war Civil StatusLicensed civil aerodromeNone    .........Licensed civil aerodromeLicensed civil aerodrome-&apos;:   .        .Municipal aerodromeNone     ......Licensed civil aerodromeMunicipal aerodromeMunicipal aerodromeNone     ......Municipal aerodromeMunicipal aerodromeNone     ......None    ......Municipal aerodromeNone     ......None     ...(i) None(ii) Municipally    ownedsiteNonePresent TenureRequisitioned      andleasedRequisitionedRequisitionedGreater   part   State-ownedRequisitionedState-owned ...State-owned ...RequisitionedRequisitionedRequisitionedRequisitionedRequisitionedRequisitionedGreater  part   State^ownedRequisitionedGreater  part   State-ownedRequisitioned(i) Privately    ownedland(ii) Municipally ownedsiteState-owned ...      ...Type ofConstructionRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedForeshoreRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedGrassRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedProposed Joint Userby other FlyingDepartmentsAir MinistryAdmiraltyAir ministry air MinistryAdmiraltyAir ministry ministry of SupplyAir ministry ministry of SupplyAir ministry air Ministry ...Admiralty ...Acimiralty ...Air ministry ministry of SupplyAir ministry air MinistryControlling andOwning Department(provisional)M.C.A.Air ministry air MinistryM.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A..   M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.AdmiraltyM.C.A.Air MinistryM.C.A.M.C.A.(See remarks)RemarksWhitchurch to be used forscheduled services pendingadaptation of Lulsgate Bot-tom. Whitchurch may be acquired as MaintenanceBase only.To be used for Bristol Channelferry service only.To be main airport for Cardiff.Crosby is being used pendingtransfer to Great Orton.Air Ministry will retain the ownership of turn house, but .C.A. will be controlling-Department.
Exeter	Exeter     ......	Municipal-, aerodrome ...	RequisitionedFort William ...	Site only  ... : : ...	None            ...	Glasgow     and Glydeside Grimsby Hull   ...      ...	Renfrew   ...... Grimsby Catfoss     ...	Municipal aerodrome ... Municipal aerodrome ... None    ......	Requisitioned Requisitioned State-owned ... -Inverness	(a) Inverness (b) Dalcross	! Municipal aerodrome ... None	Requisitioned Part State-owned (a.m.) Part RequisitionedIslay  ...... Isle of Wight ... Kirkwali      ... Leeds and Bradford	Port Ellen... Ryde HatSton    ...... Yeadon    ...      ..:	Licensed civil aerodrome Licensed civil aerodrome None     ...      ...   - ... Municipal aerodrome ...	Requisitioned Privately owned State-owned ... &apos;    ... RequisitionedLiverpool Lossiemouth and Elgin Manchester   ...	Speke      ...... Lossiemouth Ringway......	Municipal aerodrome ... None     ......... Municipal aerodrome ...	Requisitioned State-owned...... Municipally owned VS4Mull   ...      ... Newcastle   and North-East ,... . England; Newquay ______...	Site, only   ...... (a) Croft   ...... (b) Boldon Site   ... St. Mawgan	None......... None    ...:    ...     ... None    ...     ...... Licensed civil aerodrome	State-owned   ;..... Privately owned land Requisitioned......North Uist   ... Norwich     and Gt. Yarmouth Nottingham ... Oban ....   ...	Sollas          ...   ... Rackheath...... Tollerton   ... Connel	Licensed civil aerodrome None    ...     ... Municipal aerodrome ... None	Privately owned land Requisitioned Requisitioned Requisitioned        ...RunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedGrassRunwayedRunwayedGrassRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayed.RunwayedRunwayedGrassRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedAir MinistryAdmiraltyMinistry of SupplyAdmiraltyAir MinistryAdmiraltyAir ministry air ministry air MinistryAdmiralty    ......Air MinistryI Ministry of SupplyAir MinistryAdmiraltyAir ministry air MinistryM.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.(See remarks)M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.. M.C.A..M.C.A.(See remarks)M.C.A.AdmiraltyM.C.A.M.G.A.; -M.C.A.Air MinistryM.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.Development of Fort Williamwill depend on findings of engineering survey report and the potentialities of anamphibian service which1would obviate.the need forthe aerodrome.Services to be; transferred toDalcross in the near future;No proposal to acquireInverness.Acquisition of Yeadon wttldepend on whether it can be developed to necessary stan-dards.As for Fort William. ;Services to be transferred fromCroft to Boldon when thatsite has been developed.
Stopping Place	Aerodrome	Pre-war Civil Status	* Present TenureOrkneys	Sanday     ......	Licensed civil aerodrome	Private land......	Stronsay   ...	Licensed civil aerodrome	Private:land ...	Westray   ...	Licensed civil aerodrome	Private land .... : ...	N. Ronaidsay	Licensed civil aerodrome	Private land......	Long Hope	Licensed civil aerodrome	Private;land ...Penzance	(a) St. Just	Licensed civil aerodrome	Privately owned land	(b) Culdrose	None	State-owned ...Perth/Dundee...	Enrol&quot;	None	RequisitionedPlymouth	Harrowbeer	None    .........	RequisitionedPortsmouth   ...	Portsmouth	Municipal aerodrome ...	Requisitioned        ...Prestwick	Prestwick......	Licensed civil aerodrome	RequisitionedScilly Isles	St. Mary&apos;s......	Licensed civil aerodrome	Part requisitioned and			; part privately owned			landSheffield     and	Doncaster......	Municipal aerodrome ...	RequisitionedDoncaster			Shetlands	Sumburgh ...	Licensed civil aerodrome	RequisitionedSkye  ...	Site only   ......	None            ...     ...	Private land ...Southampton ...	Eastleigh.......	Municipal aerodrome  ...	Part municipally ownec			and part requisi-			tioned&apos; South-West	Haverfordwest	None     ...	State-owned......Wales			Stornoway	Stornoway......	Licensed civil aerodrome	Greater   part   State-			ownedSwansea	Fairwood Common	Municipal aerodiome site	Requisitioned.!&apos;JTiree  ......	Tiree       ......	Licensed civil aerdorome	Greater   part   State-			ownedTJllapool       ...	Site only   ......	None    ...     ...	Westoh-super-	Weston-super-Mare	Municipal aerodrome ...	Part State-owned, partMare			requisitionedWick......	Wick       ......	Licensed civil aerodrome	Greater  part   State-			; ownedYork  ...	York       ...      ...	Municipal aerodrome ...	RequisitionedType ofConstructionProposed Joint Userby other FlyingDepartmentsGrassGrassGrassGrassGrassGrassRunwayedRunwayed;Runwayed.GrassRunwayedGrassGrassRunwayedGrassRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedRunwayedAdmiralty ...Admiralty ...Air ministry air ministry ministry of supply ministry of SupplyAir MinistryAdmiralty......Ministry of SupplyAir ministry air ministry air ministry ministry of SupplyAir ministry ministry of SupplyControlling andOwning Department(provisional)M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.(See remarks)AdmiraltyM.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.M.C.A.Air Ministry-  M.C.A.M.C.A:Air MinistryM.C.A.RemarksFor&apos; inter-island service. Ac-quisition of grass aero-dromes will depend on whether it proves prac-ticable to restore and ex-tend them to the requiredstandard.       &apos; rService to be transferred toCuldrose at early date. Noproposal to acquire St. Just.Aerodrome constructed oncommon land. Acquisitioninvolves special Parliamen-tary procedure.As for Fort William.As for, Fort William.



APPENDIX IIIAnalysis of Expenditure on Aerodromes in Appendix Ihase I. Mainly acquisition and conversion for civil use of Aerodromes in Appendix I i8,ooo,ooaI. Land  acquisition  arid  compensation   fordisturbance          ...     ....      ...      ... 5,750,0002. Works services, including temporary build-ings, taxiways, adaptation of buildings and   urgently   required   extensions   torunways     ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 3,000,0003. Aerodrome lighting (Stage I)       ...      ... 1,000,0004. Rehousing and miscellaneous demolitions... 250,0005. Roads closing and reprovision,   ... 4,000,0006. Easements and restrictions on adjacent land 2,000,0007. Contingencies          ...      ...      ...      ... 2,000,000&quot;hase II.-Further development of Aerodromes inAppendix I8. Terminal buildings   ...      ...      ...      ... 3,000,0009. New aerodrome near Newcastle     ...      ... 1,500,00010; New aerodrome near Crewe ...      ...      ... 1,000,000                ^II. Prestwick development      ...      ...      ... 2,000,00012. Other long-term development expenditure 11,500,000- -      19,000,00037,000,000Notes on Sub-HeadsI. Land acquisition costs have been estimated on the basis that Part viii of the Requisitioned Land and War Works Act, 1945, will apply. The alteration in the basis of compensation payable on compulsory acquisition, which hasrecently emerged from Town and Country Planning legislation now before Parlia-:went, may increase land acquisition costs, but no estimate of the increase has yet been made.   Surveys are still very incomplete. &apos;5. Data concerning the reprovision of roads are very incomplete as yet. Onlyin a few cases of exceptional urgency have the estimates been based on figuressupplied by the Ministry of Transport.6.   Surveys are incomplete and in many instances negotiations with land-owners have riot yet begun.   The estimate attempts to measure the total capitallability likely to arise, although in practice it is expected that many personsEffected will agree to accept an annual payment in the nature of rent or wayleavejih complete or partial satisfaction of their claim.8. The estimate for terminal buildings takes into account the number andhe varied nature of the aerodromes at which new buildings will be necessary:Experience in the operation and management of temporary-and adapted buildingsis expected to provide a guide to the range and standard of the facilities andmenities which will ultimately be required. Meantime the figure of capitaLcostan be provisional only.II. Several schemes for the development of Prestwick are under considera-\\on and the figure adopted isvery tentative.12. It is thought that this estimate makes reasonable provision for all major projects involving the extension of existing runways and the provision of newunways, including the cost of any resultant road diversions. The cost ofinstalling the final system of aerodrome lighting is also included. At the presenttime, however, it is not possible to forecast even approximately the outlay whichnay be required to strengthen, widen or replace existing runways to meet the&apos;equirefnents of civil aircraft not yet in operation. This contingent liability may)e substantial and is not covered by the estimate..   [33684] c 2
Draft statement in the White Paper on British Air Services published in December 1945 itwas announced that the State would own and operate the aerodromes used byregular air transport services. The selection of suitable sites for these aero-dromes has been a long and difficult task. It has been undertaken in close consul-tation with British European Airways with the object of providing for the country a planned network of air services designed to serve the nation&apos;s needs.A preliminary list of aerodromes outside the London area, which area needs to be considered separately and to which this Note does not therefore refer, hasnow been prepared as set out below, together with the names of the main townswhich each aerodrome is intended to serve. Many of the aerodromes will be usedon a joint basis with the Service departments and aircraft manufacturers.Much work has to be done to many of these aerodromes before they can beready for the operation Of regular air services and, in addition, it will, of course,he necessary, where this has not already been done, to extend to them the network of radio and air traffic control services.The object is to provide safe and regular services and not to rush aerodromes and aircraft into ill-prepared use. Services, when they are introduced, must bedependable and generally speaking those which fill a social or commercial needthat other forms of transport do not satisfy, must be introduced first. Bearingthese facts in mind, together with the shortages of man-power and materials,particularly for building purposes, it would be unwise to attempt to indicate a date by which the whole of these aerodromes will have been brought into use, butthe work will be pressed ahead on a properly integrated plan.Locality	Aerodrome	RemarksAberdeen	...   Dyce        ...	Already in use by regular services.Anglesey        ...      ......	...   Valley........	Diversionary airport.Barra......-     ...      ...      ... -	...   Barra       ...      ...	Barrow... ,    ...      ...      ...	...   Barrow     ... &apos;    ...	Belfast ...      ...      ...	...   Nutts Corner	Already in use by regular services.Benbecula      ...      ...      ...    -	...   Benbeeula ...      ...	Already in use by regular services.Blackpool      ...      ...      ...	...   Squires Gate       ...	Already in use by regular services.Birmingham   ...	...   Elmdon    ...      ...	Bournemouth ...      ...	...   Hum	Brighton, Hove and Worthing	...   Shoreham ... .    ...	Bristol ...	...   Lulsgate Bottom .	Whit church will continue to be avail-		able at any rate for a time.Cardiff.........	...   (1) Pengam Moors...	Pengam Moors will  continue to be		used for the ferry services across		the Bristol Channel.	&apos; (2) Llandbw       ...	Campbeltown ...      ...      ...	...   Machrihanish	Already in use by regular services.Carlisle ...	...   Great Orton	Crosby is being used tempprarily&apos; by		regular services.Edinburgh     ...      ...	...   turn house ...	Already in use by regular services.Exeter ...      ...      ...      ...	...   Exeter      ...	Glasgow and Clydeside      ...	..;   Renfrew    ...	Already in use by regular services.Grimsby        ...    _____	...   Grimsby         ...	Hull    ......      ...	...   Catfoss     ... .   ...	Inverness       ...      ...	...   Dalcross........	Longman aerodrome is being used at		present by regular services but trans-		fer to Dalcross will be made as soon	...   Ryde       ...      .&apos;.	as. practicable.Isle of Wight ...      ...      ...		Already in use by regular services.Islay	...   Port Ellen ...	Kirkwall:       ...      ....	...   Hatston,   ... .    ..	Already in use by regular services.Leeds and Bradford ...      ...	...   Yeadon	Subject to further technical investiga-		tion showing that the aerodrome can		be improved to the necessary stan-	i i .:./:! 1 - v &apos;.&apos; ! ;     i       ! &apos;	dard.Liverpool	...   Speke       ...	. Already in use by regular services.Lossiemouth and Elgin      ...	...   Lossiemouth       ..	Already in use by regular services.Manchester    ...      .......	...   Ringway   ...	
i LocalityNewcastle and North-East England:AerodromeNew SiteNorth Uist    ...Norwich and Great YarmouthNottingham   ...      ...Orkneys ...&quot; ...&quot; ...Penzance       ...      ...Perth/DundeePlymouthPortsmouth    ...      ...Prestwick ...Scilly Isles ...Sheffield and DoncasterShetlands      ......Southampton ...StornowaySwanseaTiree    ...      ...Weston-super-Mare   ...Wick   ...      .....-York    ...SollasRackheathTollertonCuldroseEnrolHarrowbeerPortsmouthPrestwick ...       St. Mary&apos;s ...Doncaster ...Sumburgh......Eastleigh   ......Stornoway...Fairwood   CommonTireeWestonWick        ...York        ....Remarks.Croft; is intended for temporary usepending the development of a newsite.&apos; The site provisionally selectedis at Boldon, south of the projected, Tyne Tunnel. It lies, however, on coal-bearing land and further tech-nical investigation is necessary beforethe : selection of the site-&apos; can be confirmed. ^ 1 .See below.St. Just aerodrome is now in use byregular services and will continue tobe so used Until a transfer toCuldrose is possible.The permanent: use of the aerodrome is subject to Parliamentary approval,in view of Commoner&apos;s rights.Already in. use for regular services.Already in use for regular services. &apos;Already in use. for regular services. .Already in use for regular services.Already in use for regular services.Already in use for regular services.Already in use for regular services.Already in use for regular services.The provision of air services to additional places, as, for example, the highlands and Islands of Scotland, including the Orkneys inter-island service, is contemplated, but detailed surveys of the sites provisionally selected are necessary before their suitability can&apos;be determined. Some of the landing grounds usedbefore the war are much too small for medium-type aircraft, which will provide afaster and more efficient service, and the best means of serving these placesrequires further examination.The introduction of air services direct from certain aerodromes in England,Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland to the Continent is intended as aircraftbecome available and the aerodromes can be suitably improved and equipped.Additional sites will be announced from time to time as their acquisitionbecomes necessary for further expansion of air services.APPENDIX VSelection of a Civil Airport for Bristol1. On 14th March, 1946, the Chairman of the Civil Aviation committee recommended to the Cabinet (CP. ,(46) 99) that the construction of the Brabazon Iprototype should proceed and that the Ministry of Supply should be authorisedto construct a long runway at Filton, together with the necessary buildings. TheCivil Aviation Committee agreed at that time that, prima. facie, there was acase for establishing the main civil airport for Bristol at Filton in view of theheavy expenditure of public money there, but the! matter Was one for furtherconsideration by the Minister of Civil Aviation in consultation with theChancellor of the Exchequer and other Ministers. The Cabinet at a meeting of18th March, 1946, agreed to the construction of the prototype and of the run-way and buildings, but decided that this could not be regarded as authorising the development of Filton into the main Bristol airport. This question required further consideration.2. Since that date various schemes for the civil use of Filton have been examined and the comparative merits of two sites, Filton and Lulsgate Bottom,have been investigated in detail from the operational, engineering and financial
Squadron activities. The combination of test flying with theoperation of scheduled air services is not recommended either on thegrounds of safety or expediency.(ii) Lulsgate Bottom is operationally superior to Filton, having obstruction, free approaches, which would permit safe landings, in weather conditions when Filton would, through the presence of high ground and building obstructions, be unusable.(iii) The development of Lulsgate Bottom causes less interference with housing development than would the development of Filton.(iv) Some use could be made of Lulsgate Bottom, provided small aircraft are used, even before development is undertaken. Also the aerodromecould remain in operational use while development work was inprogress. Operations at Filton would, on the other hand, have to be suspended for some part of the time that the new runway was being laid.8. On the strength of the foregoing factors, the Committee will, I think,agree with me that there is an overriding case for the selection of LulsgateBottom as the civil airport for Bristol.9. Some civil aviation use will, however, be made of Filton, which will beinvaluable when the weather is good at Filton as a diversionary airport for the brabazon I and other big aircraft, as it will be one of the few aerodromes inthe country with a runway of sufficient strength to bear these large aircraft.10. I am informed by my colleague, the Minister of Supply, that thedevelopment of Filton is now continuing on the assumption that it will not be developed as a civil airport, and that the long runway should be completed in theAutumn of this year. I have not, for the reasons given above; pursued theCommittee&apos;s suggestion that I should acquire additional land for the develop-ment of Filton. I understand that the only additional land acquired at Filtonis that required by the Minister of Supply for the long runway.N. of C.


</content>
</cab>
