<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/19/0 images: 194-196</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETCP. (47) 1789th June, 1947CABINETCopy No.31REPLIES TO LETTERS AMD STATEMENTS IN THE PRESSNote by the Prime MinisterAT my request, the Ministerial Committees on Home and Overseas Informa-tion Services have considered the practice which should be followed as regardsreplies to letters and statements in the Press which are inaccurate or otherwiseobjectionable (I.H. (47) and O.I. (47) 1st Joint Meeting, Item 3), and I thinkthat it may be useful to Ministers to have the following statement of the view taken by the Committees, with which I agree.2. As far as letters to the newspapers from Heads of Information divisions and Press Officers are concerned, it is undesirable that officers should involvethemselves in public controversy. Not only are there objections in principle, butin the case of Information Officers it cannot fail to react adversely upon thestatus of the Information Services and give to officers the impression that theyare being used as political or personal instruments.3. The general line to be taken was stated in my reply to a Question on 8th October, 1946 :-&quot; It should be, I think, a general rule that, where the personal conductof Ministers is concerned, the matter should be dealt with by the minister himself.&quot;   (Hansard, Vol. 427, No. 191, Col. 25),and the reply given by Mr. Churchill in the House on 22nd February, 1945:. &apos;&apos; The best practice is that Ministers of the Crown should themselvesexpound all matters of Government Policy, and that Press interviews by officials should only be given on Ministerial responsibility and after dueauthorisation by the political Chief. Such expressions of opinion by officialswould usually have regard to technical aspects only. Of course, in anemergency, exceptions may be made. The principle of Ministerial respon-sibility to Parliament is paramount.&quot; (Hansard, Vol. 408, Col. 954.)[33734]Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1947
4. Letters to the Press from Information Officers (and for that matter fromother officials) should accordingly be purely informative; and the fewer the better.This does not mean that they should not write to correct misstatements of factor even of already announced policy, but they should be careful not to enter intoarguments on the merits of Government policy, and should take pains to keep their letters as inoffensive in tone as possible.5. Where under this ruling a reply from an official will be inappropriate,a choice should be made between the following courses which, between them,would seem to cover most of the cases which are likely to arise: (a) For the Minister or his Parliamentary Secretary to write a letter tothe Press. This will be appropriate only where the point at issue is substantial, or in a special sense personal to the Minister (e.g.,arising out of a purely political speech). Discretion should beexercised to avoid any risk of offending Parliament by making state-ments to the Press which would more properly be made in Parliament.(6) For the Minister to reply in a public speech. This is only occasionallypossible and not always appropriate.(c) For the matter to be taken up direct by telephone by the InformationOfficer or Press Officer in a friendly way with a view to correction.(d) To get a supporter of the Government or other well disposed person of authority to send a reply, the material for which has been providedby the Department.   This is only occasionally suitable.(e) To issue an official statement to the Press generally.  This again is onlysuitable occasionally.(/), To inspire a Parliamentary Question in answer to which the matter canbe disposed of.(g) To do nothing. There will be many cases where this is the light course.The significance of inaccurate statements in the Press often looksdisproportionately great at the time when they actually appear.Frequently members of the public will themselves write to correct the misstatement, and sometimes there is more to be gained fromlying low than from stimulating public controversy.6. I should be glad if my colleagues would make the contents of thismemorandum known not only to their Chief Information Officers but&quot; also to the senior administrative staff of their Departments?C. E. A.10. Downing[Street, S.W. 1,9th J&apos;une,, 1947. &apos; &apos;    .   -


</content>
</cab>
