<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/19/0 images: 348-360</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.&apos; July 1947SECRET Copy&apos;No.   31CP. (47) 1903rd July, 1947CABINETDEVELOPMENT  OF  NATIONAL  ARBITRATION  MACHINERYMemorandum by the Minister of Labour and National service in accordance with the desire of the Lord Presidents Committee on 2nd May,1947 (L.P. (47) 13th Meeting, Minute 1), I have given careful consideration tothe question whether the existing machinery for arbitration might be consolidatedin a Central Arbitral Body, which would be under a duty to make itself acquainted with the facts of the economic position and which would be empowered to obtain from the Government any further economic facts about a particular industry should they be relevant to the case with which it is concerned. The followingmemorandum is submitted at the request of the Lord -Presidents Committeegiving the results of my examination of this matter:   .Existing Machinery &apos;,2. The existing arbitration machinery may be said to fall into three classes : (i) Voluntary machinery set up by agreement between the two sides of an industry;(ii) Voluntary machinery under the Conciliation Act, 1896, and industrial courts Act, 1919, which includes (a) the Industrial Court set up underthe Industrial Courts Act, (&amp;) Boards of Arbitration consisting ofthree or more persons, and (c) Single Arbitrators; and(iii) Compulsory machinery set up by the Conditions of Employment and national Arbitration Orders, 1940-45.3. In the case of voluntary arbitration machinery set up by agreement withthe two sides of an industry, the Minister may or may not be consulted as tothe form of machinery or the person or persons to be appointed with the powersof arbitrator. Notes on the arrangements in various industries are containedin Appendix I. It will be seen that they include provisions in the constitutionof Joint Industrial Councils for the reference of disputes to the Industrial Court,or the National Arbitration Tribunal, for arbitration by an independent chairsman, or by a Committee of the Council with the powers of an umpire, for&quot;arbitration&quot; without specifying the form, or for conciliation either withinthe Council or by the appointment of outside conciliators..-! There are many otherJoint Industrial Councils which make no direct provision, but which in practicerefer disputes to arbitration: under the Industrial Courts Act, either to theIndustrial Court itself, or to a Board of Arbitration ..or Single Arbitrator.Examples of large and important industries with comprehensive agreed arrange-ments for arbitration of disputes are also given in Appendix I, together witha note on the systems evolved for the Civil Service, both industrial and non-industrial, for the railways, and for Civil Air Transport (as an example of a nationalised industry).Any attempt to impose a central arbitral body on industry tvould involvea far-reaching revision of, voluntary arrangements which many industries would refuse to undertake.4.   The Industrial Court.is a central standing body which is always availableto industry.  In the case of ad hoc appointments, the Minister makes the appoiut-ments and is entitled to defray the expenses of the arbitrator.   If one side or[33856] B    - &apos;
the other is not agreeable to arbitration there is -no authority in the minister under these Acts to compel arbitration. The two parties are thrown back ontheir own resources and are free to reach such agreement as is mutually acceptable.A description of the relevant provisions is contained in Appendix II.The experience of the last 30 years has shown that the flexibility of thepresent arrangements has great advantages and that there is much merit in theexistence of these alternative forms of voluntary arbitration. It has frequentlyhappened that the parties to a dispute have refused to have recourse to oneof them, but have agreed to make use of one of the others, with the result thatdisputes and stoppages of work have been avoided.5. In the case of compulsory arbitration, it must be appreciated that thisis a purely temporary provision introduced during the war on the recommenda-tion of the two sides of industry with a view to avoiding strikes and lock-outs.It has been continued since the war on the recommendation of the Joint Con-consultative Committee, but on the clear understanding that the Conditions ofEmployment and National Arbitration Orders will be revoked whenever either side so desire. There is no intention under present circumstances of retainingthis form of machinery as a permanent feature of our industrial legislation.Under this Order either side is entitled to report a dispute to the Ministerand the Minister in certain circumstances is bound to refer&apos; it to the national arbitration Tribunal for decision, but the Minister has no power to compel any party to report a dispute to him, and without a report he cannot refer the matter to arbitration. When a case is referred, any award is binding and becomes animplied term of contract between the employer and the worker. Strikes andlock-outs are made illegal under the Order unless the Minister has failed to refer the matter to the National Arbitration Tribunal within a specified period, or tothe appropriate machinery where such machinery has not yet been exhausted.Penalties are provided for breach of the Order, but experience during the war has shown that they are quite ineffective if required to deal with any largenumbers of men.6. In addition to the above classes of arbitration machinery there is theform of compulsory arbitration-cum-conciliation, which is obtained by means of adding independent members to Wages Councils and other statutory wageregulating Boards, but it is necessary to bear in mind that these independent members only begin to function either as conciliators or as arbitrators if thereis a difference on which the two sides cannot agree a settlement.7. Any proposal to impose a central arbitral body on industry would, be .valueless without the full co-operation of both sides. A tribunal must be seen and known to be completely independent, and if the parties were to suspect thatoutside influence was being exerted on the Arbitration Tribunal there would be a refusal to go to arbitration which would simply put the Tribunal out of business.The lack of acceptable arbitration machinery might then throw the workers backon to strike action to redress their grievances. The high regard in which theexisting machinery is held is due, firstly, to its independent status and freedom from Government control, and, secondly, to its flexibility which enables everyindustry to obtain that form of arbitration best suited to its needs and circumstances.8. My inquiries lead me definitely to the conclusion that the co-operationof industry-would not be forthcoming for the proposal that has been made. Theprinciple of compulsory arbitration as embodied in the Conditions of Employ-ment and National Arbitration Order is accepted only for a limited purpose.It is most useful under present circumstances, but if anything were done whichmight prejudice its independence in the eyes of industry this would cause one side or the other to ask for the revocation of the Order.9. I am satisfied that, although the employers to-day might welcome a leadfrom the Government which would, assist them in resisting wage application,they would not be prepared to accept such aid if it involved Government inter-vention in arbitration machinery, even if only to present the economic positionto the country. As one employer put it, economic facts are really economic views which may be expressed one way on one occasion but might be expressed in another way on another occasion. The danger is that confidence in arbitrationmachinery might be destroyed and with it the most effective means of disposing of disputes when the differences cannot be resolved by negotiation.
10. The policy I am pursuing is directed to ensure that arbitrators shallbe drawn from a select body of men who will have a knowledge of a number ofindustries, and can be depended upon to have a broad and statesmanlike outlook.Moreover, by employing the same individuals as Chairmen of a number of wages councils or Wages Boards or as independent members of such Councils andBoards, we are going a long way to ensure that the awards to different classes ofworkers are kept reasonably well in step. This is the policy I have been pursuingin my appointments and I have every hope that it can be built up on the basis ofconfidence of both sides. The President of the Industrial Court is also theChairman of the Railway Staff National Tribunal, of the Retail Pharmacy joint industrial Council, of the South Wales Conciliation Board for the coal mining industry, and of one of the Iron and Steel Industry Wages Board; he is on the panel of independent Chairmen for the Co-operative National Conciliation Board,and has held a number of ad hoc appointments as Chairman of Courts of Inquiry.The Chairman of the National Arbitration Tribunal, in addition to filling anumber of ad hoc appointments on Courts of Inquiry, &amp;c, is also Chairman ofthe Licensed Non-Residential Establishments Wages Board, of the LicensedResidential Establishment and Licensed Restaurant Wages Board, of the VarietyEntertainments Council (which deals with conditions of employment) and of theLondon Passenger Transport Board Negotiating Committee. During the past three months I have made or approved twenty-five appointments of independent members of Wages Boards and Councils, but the number of individuals who havebeen appointed is only eleven. So far as the appointment of single arbitratorsis concerned, I have made use of five individuals during the last five months forsixteen arbitrations.11. There, are plenty of public-spirited men of established position and prestige who are willing to serve in the above capacities, but they would not beprepared to serve in any capacity which restricted their independence. It isknown that in fact they pay great attention to the Economic Survey for 1947 and government statements about the economic position. They are conversant withthe economic position of the various industries and their relationship to eachother and are fully alive to the repercussions of any awards they may make.12. By following the policy described in the preceding paragraphs, I am satisfied that, in so far as arbitration machinery is Concerned, we are doing allthat can be done to achieve in most cases the two important objectives : (1) Of ensuring that in wages awards due regard is paid not only to theposition in the particular industry concerned but to the general economic position of the country.(2) Of ensuring that a proper relativity is maintained between the awardsmade to different classes of workers.13. It is doubtful how far the above considerations apply in the case of-certain forms of machinery Whose recommendations regarding remuneration,being unrelated to the awards of other bodies, are already causing a certainconcern and may, unless carefully steered, give rise to considerable embarrass-ment. Examples of such bodies are the Burnham Committee on teachers&apos;remuneration and the Rushcliffe Committee on nurses&apos; remuneration. In eachcase the Chairman, although an experienced public personality, has no otherappointment in connection with, the settlement of the remuneration of largebodies, of employees. In each case the Committee contains no independent members. It might be possible in due course, when vacancies occur, to appointas Chairman of each of these bodies a person who already is Chairman of oneor more other Wages Tribunals or is accustomed to acting as an&apos;arbitrator inmatters of remuneration. / suggest, that consideration should be given to themaking of appointments to these Committees which would apply to them theprinciples I am following in my appointments.14. In the case of Local Authorities, there are no arrangements for arbitra-tion in the constitution of the various Joint Industrial Councils. These councils are empowered only to make recommendation to their constituents. The individual authorities being democratically elected are unwilling to concede to anybodythe right to determine, the wages and conditions of their employees.15.   Apart from the damage that might be done to the machinery of arbitra-tion by injudicious action on the part of government, there is the furtherconsideration that the antecedent provisions for negotiation and conciliation may[33856] &apos; b 2
be likewise affected detrimentally, and this, at a time when the principle of voluntary machinery has received a new impulse by the inclusion in the variousSocialisation Bills of clauses requiring the new socialised Boards to consult withthe trade unions for the establishment of adequate machinery on a voluntary basis. The principle of voluntary negotiation and arbitration has been completelyaccepted for socialised industries (as indeed it has been in the Post Office formany years). The process of nationalising some of our most important industriestherefore has brought with it no departure from the general principles of collective bargaining, as applied in privately-owned industry.16. There is another problem which in my view is most important, namely,to create conditions which will avoid the formulation of wage applications by pressure from the rank and file. This can only be done by educating the workersthemselves and it was with this in mind that the recent White Papers were issued.The National Joint Advisory Council is pledged to support the Government inthe endeavour to make known generally the full economic facts and I shall bein the very near future putting forward to the Lord Presidents Committee a comprehensive scheme for the active encouragement of the formation of joint production Committees which I feel might provide the necessary medium forconveying the information which it is desired to transmit. As my colleagues willbe aware, the National Joint Advisory Council has recently come to an agreement on the establishment of Joint Production Committees.17. When considering the problem of wages it is necessary continually tokeep it in its proper perspective; We are only two years away from the endof the war. Times are still difficult but we have every reason to congratulateourselves on the remarkable success that has so far attended the handling ofindustrial relations in this country. Although my colleagues will be fully aware of the great difference in the two years since VJ-day as compared with the years1919-20 it might be as well if I restated the facts. In 1919-20 the working hoursof 7 million workers were reduced by an average of six hours a week. Thecorresponding figure since VJ-day is 4-j million workers, with an average reduc-tion of three hours per week. At the end of 1920, wage rates had risen 175 percent, as compared with the pre-war figure. To-day, wage rates are 66 per cent,above the pre-war figure. In this connexion I would like to point out that itwas always seen that wage rates would continue to rise until the end of post-warsettlements which occurred in July 1946. Since July 1946 wage rates have remained virtually stable. I realise of course that the satisfactory measure ofwages stability which we have been able to achieve so far has been made possible by means of extensive subsidies. It may also be that the percentage increase in real wages following VJ-day is higher than the increase in wage rates suggests.The existing Cost of Living Index is however completely discredited and the newInterim Index of Retail Prices gives no basis for comparison for the purposeof estimating the increase in real wages.18. This position has been reached with the minimum of disturbance. In1919-20 the number of working days lost owing to trade disputes amounted to61^ million. Since VJ-day the corresponding figure is about 5 million, and itis significant to note that in the three calendar years 1944, 1945 and 1946 thecorresponding figures were respectively as follows:. -The trend shown by these figures is, I suggest, most encouraging, and I feelthat we are fully justified in avoiding any drastic change that involves a riskof disturbing or disrupting the established machinery.19. In considering the future, however, it would be a mistake to ignore the growing feeling that rising prices are affecting the cost of living to the detriment of the worker, but I have every hope that the new interim index of retail prices which was introduced on 17th June will supply the necessarystabilising influence. This new index is on a much broader base. It will notbe subject to the same pressure in respect of food prices, and should commandgreater confidence as being a considerable improvement on the existing index.It may very well be that the movement of prices will be such that some upward movement of the new index will be inevitable. If this results in a small controlledincrease of wages, that might, in fact, be a most useful safety-valve.1944194519463,710,0002,840,0002,160,000
20.   To sum up : (1) I have very carefully considered the proposal to focus arbitrationauthority in a central body, but I have come to the conclusion thatthe risk to the established machinery involved in anything that mightimpair general confidence in its independence is too great to be taken.We cannot afford it.) (2) As an alternative to the proposal in (1) we should continue the policyof:-(a) Drawing arbitrators from a select body of men who will have aknowledge of a number of industries and can be depended uponto have a broad and statesmanlike outlook.(6) Employing the same individual as Chairman of a number ofWages Councils or Wages Boards, and adopting the same policyin regard to the independent members of such Councils andBoards. This, I am satisfied, is the best way of achieving thetwo important objectives of (i) ensuring that in making awards proper regard is paid tothe general economic position of the country;(ii) a reasonable relativity is maintained between the awardsmade to different classes of workers.(3) Consideration should be given to the possibility of making appointments to bodies like the Burnham Committee on teachers&apos; remuneration and the Rushcliffe Committee on nurses&apos; remuneration, which wouldhave the effect of applying the same principles to those Committees.(4) With a view to bringing home to the workers and the public as a whole the dangers of unrestrained claims for improved remuneration weshould take steps to make the facts of our economic position more widely known, and for this purpose we should   ;&quot;&quot;(a) press on, in association with the two sides of industry, with theestablishment of Joint Production Committees or their equivalent;(b) take full advantage of the co-operation of the National joint advisory Council in disseminating information relating to our economic position.(5) The results to date of the working of the existing system have been most satisfactory. There seems to be danger of an upward trend in pricesthat may affect wages, but the change-over to the new interim index of retail prices should prove a stabilising influence.G. A. I.Ministry of Labour and National Service, S.TV. 1,3rd July, 1947.APPENDIX IProvisions in Constitutions or Agreements of Joint Industrial Councilsfor the Final Settlement of DisputesI.^By Arbitration (a) The following Councils have made provision for reference to theNational Arbitration Tribunal, or to the Industrial Court if the terms ofreference are not appropriate for consideration by the National arbitration tribunal  National Joint Council for County Council Roadmen.National Joint Council for Staff of Hospitals and Allied Institutions(England and Wales).(&amp;) The following Councils have made provision for reference to theIndustrial Courts-Building, Brick and Allied Industries National Joint Council.National Joint Council for Civil Air Transport,British Furniture Trade Joint Industrial Council.
National Joint Industrial Council for Land Drainage Authorities.National Joint Council for the Monumental Masonry Industry.National Joint Industrial Council for the Road Haulage Industry.National Joint Committee for the Salt Glazed Ware Industry.National Joint Industrial Council for the Sand and Ballast Industry.Joint Industrial Council for the Stock Brick Manufacturing Industry.(c) The following Council has made provision for reference &quot; under theIndustrial Courts Act &quot; : National Joint Board of Employers and Members of Staff-Electricity(Supply) Industry.(d) The following Councils have made provision for arbitration by Indepen-dent Chairman of the Council or of a Committee of the Council with the powersof an umpire (or by a majority decision) if agreed settlement not reached :-National Joint Council for the British Ball Clay Industry.National Joint Industrial Council for the Cast Stone and Cast ConcreteProducts Industry.National Industrial Council for the Freestone Quarrying Industry.National Council for the Omnibus Industry (excluding Municipal Under-takings and the L.P.T.B.),National Joint Industrial Council for the Paint, Colour, Varnish andLacquer Industry.National Joint Industrial Council for the,Quarrying Industry.National Joint Industrial  Council  for  the  Roadstone  QuarryingIndustry.       -   :.National Joint Industrial Council for the Rubber manufacturing industry. .    ^National Joint Industrial Council for the Seed Crushing Compoundand Provender Manufacturing Industries.National Joint Council for the Silica Moulding Sands Industry.Joint Industrial Council for the Silk Industry.(e) The following Councils make provision for arbitration withoutspecifying the form : National Joint Industrial Council for Local Authorities Non-trading services (Manual Workers) England and Wales.Joint Industrial Council representative of Employers and Workpeopleconnected with the Animal Gut Industry, in England and Wales.Bacon Curing Industry National Joint Industrial Council.Joint  Industrial  Council  for   Cane,  Willow,   and  Woven  FibreFurniture Trade in Great Britain and Northern Ireland.Joint Industrial Council for the Boot and Shoe Manufacturing Trade.Joint Industrial Council covering all employees of the management committees of the Canteens and Dining Clubs of the Four MainLine Railways in the London Areas;National Joint Industrial Council for the. Industrial Catering Trade.Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committee for the Cocoa, Chocolate,Sugar Confectionery and Jam Industries.Educational and Allied Woodworking Industries Joint Industrial. Council.;&apos;Joint Industrial Council for the Glass Container Industry.Joint Industrial Council for the Glue and Gelatine Group.Joint Industrial Council representative of Employers and Workpeopleconnected with the Hide and Skin Market Trade in England and&apos; Wales.National Joint Council for the Mastic Asphalt Industry.National Joint Industrial Council for the Motor Vehicle Retail and.Repairing Trade.British Pianoforte Trade Joint Industrial Council.Printing Ink and Roller Making Joint Industrial Council (see note *).Joint Industrial Council for Process Engraving Trade.Joint Industrial Council for the Retail Meat Trade.Joint Industrial Council representative of Employers and Workpeopleconnected with Slaughterhouses in the Meat Trade.Joint Industrial Council for the Welsh Plate and Sheet Trades.* In this case the agreements were made between the Employers&apos; and Workers&apos; Organisationsnot meeting as a Joint Industrial Council.
The Wallpaper Makers&apos; Industrial Council (see note *).Joint Industrial Council of the Wood Box, Packing Case and WoodenContainer Industry in England and Wales.II. By Conciliation, other than Conciliation by the Council or Committees ofthe council the following Councils have made provision for conciliation by means of outside conciliators :: &apos; National Joint Industrial Council of the Hosiery Trade.National Joint Council for the Port Transport Industry.Joint Industrial Council For the Printing and Allied Trades of GreatBritain and Ireland.National Joint Industrial Council for the Surgical Dressings Industry.National Joint Industrial Council for the British Veneer Producingand Plywood Manufacturing Industry.III.1--There are, in addition to the foregoing, 64 Councils who make no direct provision for arbitration or conciliation by persons outside the Council.In a number of cases, however, provision is made for the reference of disputesto the Council or to a Committee of the Council. In some oases, includingGovernment Industrial Councils, disputes are, in practice, referred to theIndustrial Court, though specific provision for this has not been made in theConstitutions or Agreements.JOINT NEGOTIATING MACHINERYRailwaysTraffic Staff (including Supervisory and Clerical Staffs)&quot; Machinery of negotiation for railway staff &quot; established by an agreementbetween the Railway Companies, and the Unions, provides as follows : Local Departmental Committees consider such questions as arrangements of transfers of personnel, working hours, meal intervals, holiday arrangements, staffaccommodation, &amp;c.Sectional Councils consider the local application of national agreementsrelating to standard salaries, wages and other standard conditions.Railway Staff National ComucU, representing the Companies and the Unions,decides questions, other than minor issues, as to standard salaries, wages, hoursof duty and other standard conditions of service.Railway Staff National Tribtinal is composed of only three members, onerepresenting the Companies, one representing the Unions and one, the Chairman,appointed by agreement between the Companies and the Unions or, failing such agreement, by the Minister of Labour and National Service after consultationwith the Companies and the Unions. The Tribunal decides issues of major importance not settled by the Railway Staff National Council.Railway Workshop Supervisory Staff-Railway Workshop Supervisory Staff National Council, consisting of theEmployers&apos;. Side of the Railways Staff Conference and. (on the Workers&apos; Side)of the N.U.R., R.C.A., Association of Supervisory Staffs and EngineeringTechnicians, the Confederation of Shipbuilding and Engineering Unions andthe Amalgamated Engineering Union, deals with rates of pay and conditions ofservice. There is no special provision for arbitration, but in the event of disagreement recourse would no doubt be had to voluntary arbitration.Railway ShopmenRailway Shopmen&apos;s National Council, .consisting, on the Employers&apos; Side,of the Railways Staff Conference, and, on the Workers&apos; Side, of the N.U.R.,A.E.U., N.U.F.W., Confederation of Shipbuilding and Engineering Unions, andAmalgamated Machine Engine and Iron Grinders&apos; and Glaziers&apos; Society, settlesall national questions relating to rates of pay, hours of duty and general conditions of employment. In the event of disagreement recourse has, for manyyears, been had to the Industrial Court for arbitration.* In this ease the agreements were made between the Employers&apos; and Workers&apos; Organisationsnot meeting as a Joint Industrial Council.
The agreement governing the procedure for railway shopmen also providesfor the consideration of any question (not settled locally with an employee or group of employees) at the various levels by : (1) A Shop Committee;(2) Works Committee;(3) Departmental Line Committee.Electricity Generating Station StaffArrangements for negotiating machinery in this section are similar to those for railway shopmen.Railway police the Railways Act, 1921, required special arrangements to be made for settling pay and conditions of service of railway police. The scheme agreed between the Companies and Police representatives provides for the following arrangements :-Railway Police Central Conference, comprising representatives of theCompanies and Railway Police Federation, deals with wages and conditionsof service.Line. Conferences, separately composed to deal with matters affecting,respectively Inspectors,; Sergeants, and Detectives and Constables, thoughany two of the separate Conferences may, by agreement between the partiessit together as one Conference.   ,Central Conference deals with general matters affecting Police Forcesof all railways and with disputes, referred to it by Line Conferences.London Passenger Transport -Underground RailwaysPart VI of the London Passenger Transport Act provides that rates of pay and other conditions of service should be dealt with by a Negotiating Com-mittee and, on appeal, by arbitration by a Wages Board, the latter consistingof six representatives of the London Passenger Transport Board, six representa-tives of the Unions, four representatives of certain&quot; organisations representingusers of the railways, and an Independent Chairman. So far it has not beenfound necessary to set up such a Wages Board.The Act also provides for the establishment of one or more Councilsconsisting of officers of the London Passenger Transport Board and representa-tives of their employees. There are separate Joint Councils for the various classes of employees of the Board, e.g. (1) traffic grades, (2) certain specialiststaff and (3) workshop supervisory engineering staff.The Civil Service(a) Non-Industrial Grades ,&apos;(1) Shortly after the publication of the Whitley Report, a National whitley council was set up to deal with conditions of employment of a general natureaffecting the whole service, and Departmental Councils were appointed to dealwith matters of departmental concern only. Briefly, the objects of the Councilswere : -&quot;To secure the greatest measure of co-operation between theAdministration in its capacity as an employer and the general body ofthe Staff in matters affecting the Department with a view to increased efficiency in the Department combined with the well-being of those employed;to provide machinery for dealing with grievances, and generally to bringtogether the experience and different points of view respecting conditionsof service within the Department.&quot;(2) The National Council membership is made up in equal numbers of anOfficial Side-in the main Civil Servants of high rank-and a Staff Side ofthe representatives of the Staff Associations. Joint agreements between the two sides nave first to be reported to the Cabinet, whereupon they become operative.The membership of the Departmental Councils is modelled on that of the NationalCouncils, agreements becoming operative on report to the head of the; Department.(3) The Civil Service Arbitration Tribunal was set up in 1936 as a resultof an agreement reached between the Treasury and the Staff Side of the national whitley Council.   This Tribunal deals with questions on which there has been
failure between Government Departments and recognised Associations of CivilServants within the scope of the National Whitley Council for the administrative and Legal Departments of the Civil Service to reach agreement by negotiationaffecting the emoluments, weekly hours of work and leave of classes of CivilServants. This Tribunal consists of an independent Chairman, one memberdrawn from a Panel appointed by the Minister of Labour as representing theChancellor of the Exchequer for the time being, and one member drawn from aPanel similarly appointed representing the Staff Side of the National whitley council.(b) Industrial Grades1. During the years 1919 and 1920 the principles of the Whitley reports were applied to Government industrial establishments by a scheme which providedfor the setting up of two types of. Council, viz., Departmental Joint councils and Trade Joint Councils, and also for local machinery such as Works or YardCommittees. All but one of the existing Councils date from the years 1919 and1920. There are two types of constitution common to the Councils, one for theDepartmental Joint Councils and one for the Trade Joint Councils. A Depart-mental Joint Council may be sai d, in brief, to deal with matters other than wagesand trade questions, i.e., mainly domestic matters, such as*the interpretation of departmental regulations, welfare and other questions on which the Trade union side may wish to make representations or which have been referred to theCouncil from a Yard or Works Committee. Wages and trade questions, whichare often common to various Departments, are dealt with on Government TradeJoint Councils.Departmental Joint Councils2.   The constitution of a Departmental Joint Council provides : (1) that the members of the Official Side shall be appointed by the Department concerned, except as to one representative appointed by theMinister of Labour and National Service, and that the members ofthe Trade Union Side shall be appointed by the Trade Unions havingmembers employed in the various establishments of the Department;(2) that the representatives shall serve for one year and be eligible forre-appointment by the Department (or the Minister of Labour and-     National Service) or Trade Unions as the case may be;(3) that the Council may delegate special powers to any committee itappoints;(4) that the Chairman shall be a member of the Council appointed by theDepartment concerned and the Vice-Chairman a member appointedby the Trade Union Side of the Council and that a Secretary shallbe appointed from each side of the Council. (In the case of someCouncils it has been the practice for the Chairman to be a Ministerand in the case of others a senior officer of the Department);(5) that decisions of the Council shall normally be by agreement but a votemay be taken by show of hands or Otherwise as may be determined, noresolution being regarded as carried unless it has been approved by amajority of the members on each side of the Council. (Eor manyyears there has been no instance of voting);(6) that the Trade Unions or Groups of Trade Unions shall be responsiblefor the travelling and other personal expenses of their representativesattending meetings of the Council or its Committees.3. Each of the larger employing Departments has a Departmental joint council. Councils have not been set up in the case of Certain Departmentsemploying only a small number of industrial workpeople. In such cases negotia-tions take place with the Trade Unions direct.Trade Joint Councils4. The constitution of a Government Trade Joint Council provides thatthe members of the Official Side shall be appointed by the Ministers of theDepartments concerned (including the Treasury and the Ministry of Labourand. National Service), and that the members of the Trade Union Side shall beappointed by the Trade Unions having members in the various establishments.The other provisions in the constitution are similar to those contained inthe constitution of a Departmental Joint Council.[33856] &apos; c
5. The Shipbuilding Trade Joint Council deals with the wages of thevarious classes of industrial employees of the Admiralty. Failing settlement onthe Council, wages questions are referred by joint agreement to the industrial court for settlement.6. The Engineering Trades Joint Council and the Miscellaneous TradesJoint Council deal with matters affecting a number of Departments, e.g., Ministryof Supply, War Office, Air Ministry and Ministry of Works. Matters affectinga single Department are frequently dealt with by direct discussion with theUnion or Unions concerned, while the Councils deal with matters of common concern to several Departments or matters which cannot be settled by Depart-mental negotiation.Failing settlement on the Engineering Trades Joint Council and the Miscel-laneous Trades Joint Council matters .are referred by joint agreement to theIndustrial Court for settlement.Joint Co-ordinating Committee7. Shortly after the establishment of the Departmental Joint Councils andthe Trade Joint Councils it was decided to set up a Joint Co-ordinating Com-mittee for Government Industrial Establishments for the consideration of general service questions affecting Government industrial employees generally. TheOfficial Side of this Committee consists of representatives of the various employingDepartments and of the Treasury and the Ministry of Labour and NationalService. The Trade Union Side is composed of representatives of the variousTrade Unions having members in Government industrial employment.8.   Below is a list of the various Councils in active operation.Departmental Joint Councils Admiralty Industrial Council.Air Ministry Industrial Whitley Council.Ministry of Supply Industrial Council.Ministry of Works Departmental Joint Industrial Council.His Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office Departmental Industrial Whitley&apos;   Council.War Department Industrial Council.Trade Joint Councils Engineering   Trades   Joint   Council   for   Government   industrial establishments.^Miscellaneous   Trades   Joint   Council   for   Government   industrial establishments.Shipbuilding Trade Joint Council.Co-ordinating Committee        &apos;Joint Co-ordinating Committee for Government Industrial Establish-ments.Civil Air Transport IndustryExtract from the Constitution of the National Joint Council for civil air TransportProcedure for the Settlement of Differences14. Each of. the employers shall, in consultation with such of the TradeUnions represented on the Council as may be concerned, save where the Councilagree special circumstances obtain requiring special arrangements, review forth-with, and from time to time, the arrangements at its establishments for thesettlement of differences with a view to establishing and maintaining procedure to secure that as far as possible purely local questions arising at an establish-ment shall be settled at that establishment, and any such question arising shall,in the first place, be dealt with through that procedure. Failing settlement inthis manner the difference shall be reported jointly by the parties as follows : (a) When the difference relates to a matter within the jurisdiction of aSectional Panel the report shall be made to the Secretary or joint secretaries of that Sectional Panel.(&amp;) When the difference relates to a matter outside the purview of a SectionalPanel the report shall be made to the Secretary or Joint secretaries of the Council.
15. (i) Upon a difference being reported. as provided for in the precedingsub-paragraph the Sectional Panel or Council as the case may be shall: (a) act as a conciliation board; &apos;(&amp;) investigate the full facts relating to the difference;(c) make recommendations thereon and communicate them to the parties;(d) use all available means for settling the difference and for preventing a cessation of work arising from the difference.(ii) For these purposes set out in the preceding sub-paragraph the SectionalPanels and the Council may appoint conciliation committees in such manner asthe Sectional Panels and the Council may decide, with full powers to act.Provided that at any stage the parties shall not have authority to- adopt termsof settlement at variance with the terms of employment decided by the appropriateSectional Panel or the Council and any question of national principle shall bereferred in the first place to the Sectional Panel concerned or to the national council as the case may be. Failing settlement through the procedure outlined in this paragraph the difference shall be determined by the appropriate SectionalPanel or the Council as the case may be under the procedure applicable to otherdifferences arising between the two sides of a Sectional Panel or the Council as outlined in the succeeding paragraphs and the parties to the difference shallaccept this procedure as binding upon each of them.16. Where any difference arises between the two sides of a Sectional Panelsteps shall be taken in the first place to exhaust all possible avenues of reaching a settlement by negotiation, and for this purpose tihe Sectional Panel may set upa conciliation committee in such manner as it may determine, or may refer thematter to the Council, to assist in arriving at a settlement, or may refer thedifference to the Ministry of Labour and National Service with a view to inter-vention by a conciliator. Failing settlement through this procedure or failing agreement to such a reference, the difference shall stand referred at the requestof either side to the Industrial Court appointed under the Industrial court act, 1919, and the decision of the Court shall be final and binding on the partiesto the difference.17. Where any difference, arises between the two sides of the Council stepsshall be taken in the first place to exhaust all possible avenues of reaching asettlement by negotiation, and for this purpose the Council may set up aconciliation committee in such manner as the Council may determine to assist in arriving at a settlement or may refer, the difference to the Ministry of Labour and national Service with a view to intervention, by a conciliator. Failing settlementthrough this procedure&apos; the difference shall stand referred at the request of either side to the Industrial Court appointed under the Industrial Courts Act, 1919, andthe decision of the Court shall be final and binding on the parties to the difference.Prevention of Stoppages of Work arising from Trade Disputes18. In consideration of the procedure provided in clauses 14 to 16 hereofrepresentatives of both sides of the Council and of the Sectional Panels shalluse their best endeavours to secure that no strike, lockout or unauthorised action&apos; shall take place at any stage of the procedure and in the event of any stoppage of work or other unauthorised action,taking place shall use their best endeavours to terminate the same.APPENDIX IIProvisions of the Conciliation Act and of the Industrial Courts Act1. The Conciliation Act, 1896This Act empowers the Minister of Labour to keep a register of all Con-ciliation Boards which exist in individual industries, in which term is appre-apprehended any machinery established by agreement between employers and workers for the purpose of dealing with and settling disputes between them by conciliationor arbitration.
The Act further empowers the Minister of Labour where a dispute existsor is apprehended to do all or any of the following things : 1(a) to enquire into the circumstances and causes of the difference.   (Underthis Clause the Minister has appointed Committees of Investigationon numerous occasions);(b) to arrange a meeting under an independent Chairman, either mutually agreed or appointed by the Minister, with a view- to the amicable settlement of the difference;(c) after considering the adequacy of existing machinery for conciliation,to appoint on the invitation of either party a Conciliator or Boardof Conciliation;(d) on the application of both parties to appoint an Arbitrator.2. The Industrial Courts Act, 1919This Act set up the Industrial Court, whose members are appointed by theMinister of Labour. Of these, some are independent persons, some representativesof each side of industry, and at least one must be a woman.The Act provides that trade disputes, whether existing or apprehended, maybe reported to the Minister by either of the parties and that tine Minister shall take such steps as seem to him expedient for promoting a settlement. To thisend he.may, if both parties consent, and provided that, if there exists in that trade or industry any agreed arrangements for settling disputes by conciliationor arbitration, there has been a failure to obtain a settlement by means of those arrangements: &apos; ^ -(i) refer the matter to the Industrial Court for settlement;(ii) refer the matter to the Arbitration of one or more persons appointed&apos;by him for settlement;(iii) refer the matter for settlement to a Board of Arbitration, consistingof equal numbers of representatives nominated by each side and an: . independent Chairman appointed by the Minister.The Act further provides that the Minister may also, where a trade disputeexists or is apprehended, whether it is reported to him or not, refer any matters connected with the dispute to a Court of Inquiry consisting of a person or persons appointed by him. The Minister may authorise the Court to require by orderany person to give evidence before it on oath. The report of such a Court hasto be laid before both Houses of Parliament, and the Minister may -further publish(with certain exceptions) any information obtained or conclusions arrived at bythe Court.


</content>
</cab>
