<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/19/0 images: 403-407</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Period	13   -	22nd	June	- 19th	July	2ii	1   -	20th&quot;	Ju ly	- 16th	August	3ii	2    -	17th	August	- 13th	Sept.	2it	3   -	14th	Sept.	-11th	Oct.	it	4   -	12th	Oct.	-   8th	Nov.	2ii	5   -	9th	Nov.	-   6th	Dec.	tea ration memorandum by the Minister of food. Since I last reported to the Cabinet (CP.(47) 130) andthe matter was discussed on 2L,th April (CM. (i+7; 39th Conclusions,Minute 5) the tea supply position has deteriorated seriously inthe short term.2. The present tea ration for ordinary consumers averages2,-g- ozs. weekly but for convenience of distribution it is distributed in alternate four weekly periods as follows:-ozs. weeklyii nii iiII &apos;        !lII IIII II(For persons of 70 years of age and over the ration is 3 ozs.weekly and for seamen 4 ozs. weekly).Total consumption of tea at 2? ozs. weekly amounts to 8.9 millionlbs.  per week.      This is approximately the same per capitaconsumption as before the war.3. Bulk stocks which at 31st May amounted to 67.5 millionlbs.  (7-g- weeks&apos;  supply) as compared with 138.3 million lbs.(15 weeks) at the end of January, will amount, at the end ofJune to 55*4 million^ lbs. . (6^- weeks) and at the end of July to30.1 million lbs.  (3^ weeks).      This falling away of stock is largely due to; a very substantial reduction in arrivals for june and in the estimated arrivals for July,  as compared with thefigures I put before the Cabinet on 24th April, this being &apos;accounted for by -(a)    A strike in Colombo between 22nd May and 20th June(four weeks) during which time no. shipments from Ceylonto the United Kingdom were possible, and(to)    A dock strike in Calcutta which lasted twelve weeks and. which, when it ended on 3rd May, was followed by continuing unrest which has resulted in a slow tempoin the passage of tea through the port.     Whilst theTea.Controller for India and the Tea Commissioner in ceylon are taking all possible steps to facilitate themovement&apos;of tea, &apos; labour, and other conditions are extremely unsatisfactory.h SECRET COPY NO.0^.(47)  1997th July, 1947..CABINET
m4* The following table shows the arrivals and. bulk stockpositions (million&apos; lbs.) month by month from June to October onthe basis of continuing an average 2-g- oz.  ration:-	June	July	August	September	October	(4 weeks)	(5 weeks)	(4 weeks)	(4 weeks)	(5 weeks)Opening Stocks:	67.5	55*4	30.1	24.5	22.9Add estimated					arrivals	21.6	19.2	30.0	34.0	64.9    &quot;	89.1	74.6	60.1	58.5	87.8Less estimated					utilisation	33.7	44.5  .	35.6	35-6	44.5Closing Stocks:	&apos;55*&apos;4-	30.1	24*5	22.9	43.35* Tea is a highly valuable commodity and its handling on arrival before it can be passed over to the blenders and packersis a lengthy and complex process.      There are many differentvarieties and qualities and a wide range of values per :lb.  of tea..Moreover, the chests vary in weight and the contents of each chestmust be separately Weighed and valued and the weights and valuesrecorded against the mark on the chest which denotes the gardenfrom which the tea has come.      The Ministry, by arranging for overtime and by other exceptional means has lessened by 25 per cent,the time required to move the tea from the ship to and through thewarehouse, but the process still takes 6 weeks.6. Of ,the total bulk stocks at 1st June of 67.5 million lbs.,39*7 million.lbs. were already allocated to the trade but notremoved from Government warehouses.      Of the balance of 27.8 millionlbs.  the Ministry was able to get ready and allocate to the tradeup to the 18th June 9*0 million .1bs. only as against an amount required for consumption of 35*6 million lbs.      To the extent ofthis difference of 24 million lbs.,  the wholesalers have beendistributing to, retailers from their reserves.      On the 18th June,the wholesale trade still held reserves of 27 million lbs., mostlyin packets ready for distribution,  and the Ministry held 27*million lbs.  unallocated to the trade and 29*5 million lbs. ^allocated but not cleared by the trade.      Some part of the 27million lbs.  held by the trade on 18th June (estimated at 5 millionlbs. ) will ,;have been distributed to retailers and consumed in the rationing period 22nd June to 19th July.      The 3 oz. ration for. theperiod 20th July to 16th August would require 42.7 million lbs.,arid this could be met from the remainder of 22 million lbs.  of thestock held by the trade on 18th June and from the 29*5 million lbs.already allocated on 18th June, but it would leave the trade a balance of about 8.8 million lbs. with which to begin its deliveriesfor the ration period beginning 17th August.7. The utmost efforts in speeding up the handling of tea atthe warehouse will make available for allocation between.18th june and 31st July only an additional 31 million lbs.      This, with thebalance of 8.8 million&quot;lbs.  referred to above would theoreticallycover the 2 oz.  ration for the period 17th August to 13th Septemberrequiring 29.2 million lbs..     But the newly allocated tea will need to be blended,  packed and distributed to retailers and this cannotbe done at the rate of more than about 9 million lbs.  a week.Consumers are permitted to draw their rations for a whole period atany time during the period and the weights of the packets are such that they must draw at.least four three-oz. rations together.
There is no doubt that if the trade is left with a balance of only 8.8 millions at the beginning of the period failures toprovide people with their ration during the early weeks of theperiod will be numerous and widespread.      Moreover,  the stockin the hands of &quot;the trade at the end of the period will be no more than 10.6 million lbs.   (39.8 minus 29.2) and this with an    -allocation of 9 million lbs. which, owing to the low arrivals inJuly,  is all that the Ministry can do in the first half of Augustwill make only 19*6 million lbs.  available to the trade to meetthe requirement of 42.7 million lbs. if a 3 oz.  ration is to be covered in the period 14th September to 11th October.8.. Everything possible is being done to accelerate the rate at which tea becomes available for shipment and is shipped atCalcutta and Colombo.      The greater part; of the tea we have boughtboth in India and Ceylon is still on the bush and has yet to be manufactured.      Tea is coming forward as soon as manufactured and freight is available at Calcutta to lift all the tea as it becomes available for shipment.     At Colombo, according to cabled information,there were 12 million lbs.  awaiting shipment at 27th June.      Of this quantity,  freight has so far been made available for 6 millions.The balance of 6 million lbs., together with, such teas as willmeanwhile arrive in Colombo from tea estates, is scheduled forlifting towards the end of July.      The latter appears to be theearliest possible time in view.of the congested state of the Port,but representations are being made to the Ministry of Transport totake all possible steps to accelerate shipment of all teas becoming available.      Even if earlier shipment were secured for say,  12million lbs. the tea could not arrive until the latter, half ofAugust and could not be available to the trade before the end ofSeptember and would not reach the shops in the period 14th september to 11th October.9. I am therefore afraid that if we are to avoid a real break-down in the tea ration it is quite unavoidable that the normal weekly3 oz.  ration due for the period 20th July to 16th August should bereduced to 2 oz.  (except for persons of 70 years of age and over,and seamen).      This will save approximately 13 million lbs.      Asimilar saving of 13. millions in the period 14th September to11th October (another 3 os.  ration period).should enable us tomaintain a 2 oz.  ration from 20th July to 8th November without serious shortage in retail shops.10. As regards the long term position,  the prospects are better.      I have continued negotiations for further supplies oftea both from the Government of.India and the Government of Ceylon.As the result of discussions which I had in London withMr. Chundrigar, the Commerce Member for the Government of India,the Government of India has now agreed to our raising our bulkpurchases from the 1947 crop to 260 million lbs. on the understandingthat we purchase in the Calcutta auctions a further 40 million lbs.from the 1947 crop if suitable teas are available at no more than4d.  per lb. above our 1947 bulk purchase price.      This means that weshould obtain 300 million lbs.  of tea from India for 1947-48.The Ministry wished to buy 150 million lbs. of tea fromCeylon but tenders so far received amount to 95 million lbs.  only. :I have seen Sir Oliver Goo.netilleke and have sought to enlist the aid of the Government of Ceylon in persuading producers to providethe balance of 55 million lbs.     . Sir Oliver was prepared to recommendhis Government to do this if we would undertake a bulk purchase of150 million lbs.  in 1948 at the same price as in 1947*-7-3-
In view of the grave risks of further strikes in Calcutta and in Colombo,  of communal disturbances affectingshipments from Calcutta,  and of the general unsettled positionin India,  I attach the greatest importance to securing duringthis crop year this balance of 55 million lbs. from Ceylon toenable us to weather any interruption of shipments of moderateduration.      I do not see any reason to expect the price of teato fall before the end of 19148, so. that I believe it&apos; would be most unwise to refuse Sir Oliver Goonetilleke&apos;s proposal for a bulkcontract of 150 million lbs. for 19I48.      I seek the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer&apos;s approval for this deal.I expect to receive 300 million lbs. from India,  atleast 95 million lbs.  from Ceylon,  15 million lbs.  from EastAfrica,  and I have still 55 million lbs. of Indian tea to come forward from the 1 9I+6 purchase, giving total supplies of Z4.65million lbs.  against total requirements of 1+55 million lbs.      Thiswill cover&apos; a 2J oz.  ration-.      But it is extremely urgent tore build our stocks so that we are not at the mercy of everyCalcutta or Colombo strike.      The saving of 26 million lbs.referred to in paragraph 9 above,  together with a possible 10million lbs. of tea from China will go some little way torestoring our tea stocks from their present very precarious positionand the balance of 55 million lbs.  from Ceylon if obtained would raise our stocks to about 120 million lbs.  in the hands of thetrade, which we are now in process of exhausting.      We therefore;hope, to be able to maintain the 2^- oz.  ration from November 191+7onwards,  provided there ore no more serious strikes in Calcuttaor.Colombo or serious communal troubles affecting Calcuttashipments.-11. *   I ask authority, therefore :-(a)    To announce that the usual increase in alternate months in the tea ration from 2 ozs.  to 3 ozs.  cannot take placein the periods 20th July to 16th August or 11+thSeptember to 11th October, but that it,is hoped to restore the normal ration in the period beginning9th November,  although this will obviously depend uponthe rate of arrival of tea from India and Ceylon.(b.)    To make a contract with Ceylon to purchase in I9I48150 million lbs.  of tea at not more than the 19U7 .price. /J.S.Ministry of Pood,  S.W.17th July,  191+7..


</content>
</cab>
