<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/28/18 images: 178-185</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVE^Rl*government /rPrinted for the War Cabinet.   September 1942.MOST SECRET. Copy No.   20W.P. (42) 388.September 2, 1942.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET.PROVISION OF AIRCRAFT FOR THE WAR AT SEA.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.AT their 111th Meeting held on the 12th August, 1942, the. War Cabinet&apos;asked that a statement should be prepared regarding the provision of aircraft for certain functions, the terms of reference given taking the form of four specificquestions : Question I. The target figures and present strength of our Air Forces(together with those of our Allies) in the theatres covered by the annex to W.P. (42) 302, both on functional and geographical basis.2. These figures are shown in the Tables at Annex &quot; A &quot; to this report.It should be clearly understood that those in Table &quot; B &quot;&apos; represent only a TargetProgramme for the purpose of planning and provisioning. They are theestimated strategic requirement and the strength which the Air Ministry hope to attain by the date shown. There can, however, be no definite guarantee either that they will be met in full or that the distribution of the squadrons when thetime comes will be as shown in the Table. The former depends on productionforecasts, which, as experience has proved, are not always fully realised by thetime anticipated; the latter must remain flexible and liable to alterationaccording to strategic needs.Question II.-The present policy covering the allocation, of resources as they become available.3. The allocation of resources as they become available is made inaccordance with the strategic policy of the United Nations, which is decided bythe Governments with the advice of the Combined Chiefs of Staff. That basicpolicy was defined in the course of the Washington War Conference in December1941 and January 1942 as follows : &quot; . . . . Notwithstanding the entry of Japaninto the war . . . . Germany is still the main enemy and her defeat is the key tovictory. Once Germany is defeated, the collapse of Italy and the defeat of Japanmust follow. In our considered opinion, therefore, it should be a cardinalprinciple of A-B strategy that only the minimum of force necessary for the safe-guarding of vital interests in other theatres should be diverted from operations against Germany &quot; (W.W. 1).The application of that policy to the effort of the British Armed Forces can hardly be better summarised than in the terms of reference quoted in paragraph 1of W.P. (42) 302. It will be noted that those terms of reference-postulate theminimum necessary allocations for securing our vital communications, coupled with the maximum possible provision for the offensive.Barely a month ago the Combined Chiefs of Staff, in a report dealing withoperations in 1942/43, placed in the forefront of their recommendations : &quot; ThatAllied Air strength continue to be built up in United Kingdom to provide for aconstantly increasing intensity of air attack on Germany &quot; (C.C.S. 94).T24293] . &apos; B
Question III. To what extent the aircraft at present devoted to the &quot; offensive,both direct and in support of land operations,&quot; are- capable of being diverted, to &quot; the Fighter defence of the United Kingdom &quot; or to&quot; securing our vital communications and interrupting those of theenemy.&quot;4.   This question can best be answered by the following- examples : (a) The Light Bomber squadrons of Bomber Command are used  for&quot; intruder &quot; operations against enemy aerodromes and could be soused on an extensive scale in the event of really serious air attack onthis country.As an alternative role, these squadrons can be-and in the pasthave been used to take a heavy toll of enemy shipping in home waters and in the Mediterranean.(b) Since the beginning of this year eight squadrons of Bomber Commandhave been transferred or loaned to Coastal Command. In addition, afurther two squadrons have been formed in Coastal Command at theexpense of Bomber Command.(c) A system has recently been instituted, in accordance with paragraphs 6to 12 of W.P. (42) 302, whereby Heavy and Medium bombers fromfirst-line squadrons and O.T.Us. of Bomber Command operate underthe direction of Coastal Command on anti-submarine patrol, convoy escourt and attack on enemy surface vessels.(d) During the past 3 months over 3,000 mines have been laid by aircraft of bomber Command.   Ever since the inception of air mine-laying in- 1940 this form of activity has been a speciality of Bomber Command,who have laid many thousand mines in these two years.(e) In the Mediterranean the air striking forces are used either against objectives directly connected with the land battle or against theenemy&apos;s sea line of communication, according to the situation andthe degree of importance attaching to the different objectives fromtime to time.The foregoing takes no account of the indirect contribution of bomber command to the war at sea by attack on objectives such as the naval bases and building yards.on the German Baltic and North Sea coasts, and the factorieselsewhere in Germany engaged in the manufacture of submarine components.Question IV.  What steps have been taken to ensure that aircraft now in production are being equipped with the necessary fittings to enable themto operate as effectively as possible over the sea or in tropical climates?5. (a) The following types of landplane have been fully converted with thenecessary equipment for work over the sea.: Wellington VIII, Hampden, Hudson,Whitley VII, Liberator, Beaufort.Fortress,(b) All types required for G.R. work over the sea are fitted with A.S.V.  Inaddition if the developments now in progress are successful, as theyhave every indication of being, our policy is to fit in all heavy bombersa device of a similar nature which will be equally effective.(c) The provision of tropicalisation parts has been made for the following : Wellingtons IC, II and VII,      Hudson,Halifax II, Beaufighter IF, IV, V and VI,Blenheim IF, IV &amp; V, Spitfire V,Beaufort I &amp; II, Hurricane I &amp; II.Sunderland I &amp; II,In addition Lancaster I and Wellington III are being preparedfor tropicalisation and should be cleared in the very near future.A. H. M. S.September 2, 1942.
ANNEX &quot;A.&quot;Table &quot;A.&quot; British and U.S.A. Present Establishments.Home(includingIceland and gibraltar).South Atlantic-WestAfrica.SouthAfrica.indian ocean.mediterranean-nean.Bomber-Heavy-British ..U.S.A.   ..Medium-british u.S.A.Light T.E.-S.E.-British ..U.S.A. ..British ..U.S.A. ..G.R. Landplane-Heavy british u.S.A.Medium british u.S.A.Light-T.E.-british u.S.A.S.E.-british u.S.A.T.B.-T.E.british u.S.A.E/Boat-4-Eng. british u.S.A.T.E.-british u.S.A.ElGHTER-S.S.-BritishTJ.S.A.M.S.-.    Day-british u.S.A.Night-BritishUSA.P.R.U.-S.S.-british u.S.A.M.S.-british u.S.A.468963341541636661721641006051.1,8383201204866013181618278412321248241602844363254232556Note. Present strengths in Middle East are in excess of establishments owing to diversionsfrom India to meet requirements of present situation.[24293] B 2
Table &quot;A.&quot; British and U.S.A. Present Establishments (continued).	Home (including Iceland and Gibraltar).	South A West Africa.	atlantic  South Africa.	Indian Ocean.	mediterranean-nean.Army Co-operation  S.S.F.-British ...    &apos; ... U.S.A....... Bomber-T.E.-British ... U.S.A....... S.E.-British ... U.S.A.......	298 20	...	...	44	60      .Note. Present strengths in Middle East are in excess of establishments owing to diversionsfrom India to meet requirements of present situation.
Table &quot; B.&quot; Target Figures for British and U.S. Aircraft.Home(includingIceland and gibraltar).South Atlantic-WestAfrica.SouthAfrica.indian ocean.mediterranean-nean.Bomber Heavy 1942-british u.S.A.1943/44BritishU.S.A:Medium 1942-british u.S.A.1943/44-british u.S.A.Light 1942-british u.S.A.1943/44-british u.S.A.Transport L.R.-1942-British-   U.S.A.1943/44-british u.S.A.M.R.-1942-british u.S.A.1943/44-british u.S.A.Fighter -Dav-1942-british u.S.A.1943/44-british u.S.A.Night-1942-british u.S.A.1943/44-british u.S.A.Turbinlite-1942-british u.S.A.1943/44-british u.S.A.6482250490April306456April226290223April602083201,4341,462800April45045060603264363660481441635October803257October6417617620144-   232160October4163235October8096114December803123044880320368320368480February3264Notk,   Coastal types are as agreed with the Naval Staff.
Table &quot; B.&quot; Target Figures for British and U.S. Aircraft (continued).Home(includingIceland and gibraltar).South Atlantic-WestAfrica.South.Africa.indian ocean.mediterranean-nean.Fighter (continucd)-L.R.-1942-British ...U.S.A.   ...1943/44-British ...U.S.A.   ...Coastal F.B.-1942-British ...USA.   ...1943/44-British ...U.S.A.  ...land planes-L.R. (T.B.)-1942-British ...U.S.A.  ...1943/44-British ...U.S.A.  ...S.R.-1942-British ...-   U.S.A.   ...1943/44-British ...U.S.A.   ...T.B./T.F.-.1942-British ...U.S.A.   ...1943/44-British ...U.S.A.   ...Reconnaissance F.R.-1942-British ...U.S.A. ...1943/44-British ...U.S.A.B.R.-1942--British ...U.S.A. ...1943/44-British ...U.S.A. ...P.R.U.-S.E.-1942-British ...U.S.A. ...1943/44-British ...U.S.A. ...M.E.-1942-British ...U.S.A. ...1943/44-British ...U.S.A. :..36909012615219216016020020023823842(observation.) 399April308027361616162410366496484872144441404848481122448244810620Note. Coastal types are as agreed with the Naval Staff.



</content>
</cab>
