<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/16/29 images: 398-401</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY; R OOV^nmtjmt. )TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.li is requested t.iai special care may betaken to J. &amp;ensure the secrecy of this document.SB ORE T.W.P.(41) COPY NO.      Vf9,0 th May,  1941.WAR    CABINET.RATIONING OF CLOTHING.^^ M^^J!a^^h&amp;^o^^e^^&amp;r^qf the Council.The proposals made by the President of the Boardof Trade in his Paper W*P. (41) have been fully dis-cussed by the Lord President&apos;s Committee and have theirunanimous supporto2.      This scheme is put forward, not for the purposeof curtailing supplies of civilian clothing, &quot;but in orderto secure the equitable distribution of the supplies available.      Production of cotton and woollen goods forthe civilian market has already had to be reduced toabout 25 per centc  of normal by reason of the exigencies of our import programme,3.      Traders&apos;  stocks have up to now protectedconsumers from the full effects of these reductions inthe supply of raw materials;    but these stocks have nowfallen substantially below the pre-war levelo      Unlesspurchases are regulated by a rationing scheme, the impact of an unregulated demand on reduced supplies will inevitably produce, within the next few months, acuteshopw-shortages, panic buying and an upward movement ofprices which could not be controlled by the machinery of price regulation.    The social consequences of such a development would be very serious.4.      This scheme is complementary to the extendedpowers of price control proposed in the Goods and Services(Price Control) Bill, which parliament will be asked topass into law immediately after the Whitsuntide recess,Experience has shown that the great difficulties of controlling prices are materially eased if the distributionof the goods is also subject to regulation;    and the rationing scheme is an integral part of the plan for keeping in check the prices of clothings5.      Finally, the scheme is in line with the declared policy of the Governmrr^o to resist inflationary dangersby securing that the impact of surplus purchasing powershall not fall on a reduced supply of consumer goods.The Lord President&apos;s Committee commend thescheme to the War Cabinet as forming an integral part ofthe general economic policy of the GovernmentsJoAoPRIVY COUNCIL OFFICE.




</content>
</cab>
