<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/185/0 images: 250-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Off HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERMIENT) .CABINET.THE FRANCHISE QUESTION. Memorandum by Lord Cecil.As I shall probably be out of England when the Cabinet considers this question, perhaps my colleagues will forgive me if I venture to say a word or two about it.The Chancellor of the Exchequer is alarmed at the great increase of the electorate which would result from lowering the age for women voters to Sic      I myself would have greatly preferred to have seen the age fixed both for men and women at 25, but I am assured by my colleagues in the House of Commons that that is an impracticable solution.      I regret it, but at the same time the extent of the probable increase if the age is lowered to 21 must not be exaggerated.      It would, not be nearly so large an increase proportionately as that which was made in 1867,  in 1884 or in 1918, and no very fearftil results followed any of these Increases.      I do not think it can be fairly said that the electorate shewed itself more inexperienced or unstable in the Elections which followed each of these extensions of the franchise than it did at Elections which preceded them.Mr.  Churchill seems to me on stronger ground when he says that to lower tho voting age to 21 for women might operate harmfully to the Conservative cause.      Other things being equal,  it is probably true that the younger a man or woman Is the less prudent he or she is and
therefore women between 21 and 30 will probably be loss! 6 conservative than those who are over 30.      But even if it be the case that younger women are less conservative than thoso who are older, is it true that the majority of women between 21 and 30 would vote labour?     I doubt it and that is the real point.     Most of them would,  I suppose, be married, and most married people, particular! married women, are conservative.     Moreover, generally speaking a woman is more conservative than a man because she is less adventurous and more religious, both of which characteristics ma.ke against revolution and Bolshevism.,      The women are said to have voted against us in 1923.     But that was because they were afraid of the fiscal changes proposed.      In 1924 the-same fear of change made them vote against the policy of friendship with Ilussia, and 1 believe that similar influences would govern the votes of the younger women, though perhaps not to the same extent.But I must frankly admit that I regard all these conclusions as exceedingly uncertain.      One thing does seem fairly clear from history, and that is that the newly enfranchised voter has a tendency to vote for the Party which has bestowed the vote.      That certainly happened in &apos;S2 and in  735, and, as a matter of fact, though that may well have been due to other causes, in 1918.      In 1868 the rule did not hold but, then, the Reform policy was taken over from the Opposition and was passed largely with their help.      Another thing is also quite certain - that if we refuse to extend the franchise now and the Labour Government corns in next time and extend It, the majority of the new voters will vote Labour.      It is doubtful whether labour disputes, with or without women of 21, will win the next Election.      It is certain
tht;t if they do win it on tho present electorate they will &quot;be able to consolidate thoir position at the following Election by giving the younger women the vote, which we should have refused.Apart from theso considerations and in spite of tho very ingenious reasoning of the Chancellor, I feel sure that we should suffer greatly in public estimation if we were to go back.from tho pledge given on the 13th February, 1925.      It was given as an inducement to some of our supporters to vote against the Second Reading of the Bill   then under consideration, and. it was taken widely In the country by those who were interested in the matter as a definite pledge by the Government as to their policy on this question.      I think the women might urge with some truth that in consequence of that pledge they abstained from agitation, and that it is partly due to that abstention that there is now no serious movement of opinion on the question.      nor can it be justly said that it was a pledge by one of our colleagues only.      It was a pledge made in the presence of the head of the Government and assented to by him, nor has it ever been repudiated by any member of the Cabinet.      It Is suggested that wo might ask the House of Commons to release us from that pledge.      But has it authority to do so? Formally, no doubt,  the pledge was given to the Eou.se. Really it was given to the country and it is only the country that can release us.      There is a well-recognised way of seeking such a release, namely by resignation.     But no one would suggest that in the present case.     Moreover, even if we did ask the House to release us what reason should we give?     Should we say that further consideration had made us doubtful
whether women of 21 would vote Conservative, which is the real truth?     Clearly not.      We should have to invent some specious argument which nobody would take seriously and which would add to our discredit.For these reasons I an convinced that If we were to take the course recommended by the Chancellor our reputation as a Govermierit would suffer severely and we should lose part,  at any rats, of that which is our chief asset, the belief of our fellow-countrymen that we can be trusted to carry out our promises even if it turns otic to be inconvenient to do so.      If then the Cabinet is of opinion that it is Impracticable to fix the age for both sexes at 25, which seems to me intrinsically the right solution, then I very much hope they will decide to fix the age for both at 21.      Otherwise,  I foresee very difficult and damaging discussions in Parliament followed not impossibly by undignified surrender at the end.(Intd.)      H* 0.Treasury Chambers, S.W.,11th Llarch ,  1927 .

</content>
</cab>
