<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/57/36 images: 292-327</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
140  *this   DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet..   November 1944.SECRET,*/ Copy No.    ijW.P. (44) 836.17th November, 1944.WAR CABINET.SUMMARY OF OPERATIONS OF BOMBER COMMAND FOR four weeks ENDING 5th NOVEMBER.  1944.A.-A detailed summary of operations is appended.B. Results of Operations.1. Oil Targets.THE following oil targets were attacked during the period : Wanne Eickel,Homberg (on three occasions) Wesseling and Bottrop Welheim. Several of these attacks were blind, using the G.H. Navigational aid. Columns of oil-smoke were observed in some of the attacks, but photographs have not yet been obtainedshowing the results of any of them. Air cover has, however, been obtained of theLeverkusen Chemical Plant since the attack on the 26th October, which was also made through 10/ 10th cloud by means of the G.H. Navigational aid. This attack was seen to have been extremely successful, and the plant was severely damaged(see Print No. 1). There is, therefore, good reason to hop^e that some of the blindattacks on oil targets will also be found, when photographs have been obtained, tohave been successful. This is a matter of great importance, as the success of the offensive on oil targets during the winter months must depend, in part, on the useof navigational aids.2. German Towns.A very large number of attacks was made on German Towns during theperiod. During the day and night of the 14th October a total of 9,200 tons of bombs was dropped on Duisburg and the large industrial districts near it for theloss of only 22 aircraft. Damage inflicted was widespread and was particularlysevere in the built-up areas including and to the east of the Thyssen steel works,north and west of Ruhrort, and at Beeck, Lar and Stockum and also in the largeindustrial steel plants both north and south of the main docks (see Prints Nos. 2and 3). The old town between the docks and the main railway station was almostentirely destroyed.Print No. 4 shows the results of a devastating attack made on Brunswickduring the same 24-hour period, when 60 per cent, of the fully built-up area ofthe town was destroyed. Stuttgart was successfully attacked on the19th/20th October and a number of important factories, among them steel,ball-bearing and chemical works, were hit, the Robert Bosch A.G. factory sufferingthe most severe damage.Two heavy attacks were made on Cologne, in the first of which a large areaof Mulheim am Rhein, north-east of the city, was destroyed by fire (see print. 5). Severe damage was also done to many industrial premises, including the chemical works at Kalk and the marshalling yard at Eifeltor. In an attack onWilhelmshafen on the 15th October, widespread damage was caused to residential property and public buildings and at least 12 buildings of the Marine Werftshipbuilding yards were severely damaged. Prints Nos. 6 and 7 show the resultsof two very heavy attacks on Essen in which hardly a building in the Kruppsworks escaped destruction or severe damage.  Bonn, attacked on the 18th OctoberMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.[28634]
(see Print No. 8) suffered heavy damage in the centre of the built-up area, and forty-seven buildings in the I.G. Farben chemical works at Leverkusen were destroyed or badly damaged on the 26th October (see Print No. 1).Attacks were also made on Bochum, where the Weitman plant of the UnitedSteelworks was damaged, Neuss, where further damage was inflicted in the dock area, Nuremberg, Oberhausen and dusseldorf.3. Enemy Positions and other Military Targets in Holland.The sea wall at Veere was successfully breached on the 11th October andsubstantially completed the flooding of all the low-lying areas on the island ofWalcheren (see Print No. 9). Good concentrations were achieved on gun positions at Flushing, and at Breskens two of the five gun positions were destroyed andt     others damaged by near misses.4. Other targets.The submarine pens at Bergen were bombed. Lancasters from a base inScotland made an attack on the battleship Tirpitz in Tromso Fiord and severalnear misses were scored but on that occasion no direct hit was made.In an attack with 12,000-lb. bombs on the Sorpe Dam, 6 hits were obtained on the dam itself, as Print No. 10 shows.5. Results of Precious Attacks.Prints Nos. 11 and 12 show the destruction caused in the town centres ofKleve and Emmerich by the attacks made on the 7th October. The breach in theKembs Dam mentioned in the previous summary is seen in Print No. 13, whichwas taken eight days after the attack. Print No. 14 shows the bombing of the ports of Boulogne and Galais on the 19th and 20th September before their captureby the Canadians and Print No. 15 a crater made by a 12,000-lb. bomb in the concrete roof of one of the U-boat pens at Brest.A H. M. S.Air Ministry,17th November, 1944.APPENDIX.Summary of Operations.aircraft date. Target. Despatched.Oct.   9/10          Bochum         ...................... 435Wilhelmshafen         ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 4710/11           Cologne         ...............      ... 4911                Veere, sea wall        ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 63Flushing, gun positions      ...       ...       ...       ... 115Breskens, gun positions      ...       ...       ...       ... 18011/12           Berlin           .........       ......... -   4612                Breskens, gun positions      ...       ...       ... 96Wanne-Eickel, oil plant     ...      ...      ...      ... 14712/13          Hamburg       ...      ............... 5213/14          Cologne         ......      ...      ...                ... 5614                Duisburg       ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 1,06314/15          Duisburg       ...                .........      ... 1,005Brunswick     ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 24015               Sorpe Dam    ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 1815/16          Wilhelmshafen        ................ 506Hamburg       ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 4416/17           Cologne...............      ... 3917               Walcheren     .................. 4918                Bonn............       ...       ...       ... 12819/20           Stuttgart.......      ...      ...      ....... 583Nuremberg     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 270Wiesbaden     ...      ...      ......      ...      ... 4821        -      Flushing, gun positions      ...      ...      ...      ... 7521/22          Hanover        ...      ..........      ...... 263
aircraft date, Target. Despatched.Oct. 22 Neuss........-----      ---22/23           Hamburg       ....      ........, **j23               Flushing, gun positions.......                - - -j-l^. 23/24          Essen   ...      ....      .......&apos;     ....               ---- WooBerlin  .......       ...       ......       ....       .-- 3824/25          Hanover        ....      ...      ...      ...      ....  &apos;   .... 5725               Essen   ...      .........      ...      .......   .... 771Homberg (Meerbeck), oil plant      ...       ....      ... 24326               Leverkusen    ...      ...      ...      ...      -. *.      ... 10527/28           Berlin .........      ...&quot;      ....      ...      ... 6028               Flushing, gun positions      ...      .......... 50Dishoek         ...      ...      ...      ...                ... 37Westkapelle   ....      ...      ...      ....      ..... 76Domberg        ...       ....       ...       ....      ....      ... 75Oostkapelle    ...      ....      ...      ...      .... 39Cologne         ...      ...      ...      ...      ....      ... 73328/29           Bergen          ................      ... 244Cologne &quot;       ...      ....      ...      ...      ....      ... 3029               Walcheren Island    ...      ....      ....      ....      ... 358Tirpitz in Tromso Fiord    ...       ....      ....      ... 3929/30           Cologne         ...      ...      ...      ....               ... 5930               Wesseling, oil plant ...........      ....      ... 102Walcheren     ...       ...                ....      ...       ... 11030/31           Cologne   .     ............      ...... 905Berlin......       ......       ...       ...... 6231               Bottrop Welheim     ......,      ...      ...      ... 101Oct. 31/Nov. 1    Cologne         ....      ......      ...      ...      ... 508     ,,Hamburg       ......       ...      ....      ...      ... 49Nov.   1               Homberg (Meerbeck), oil plant.......... 2421/2            Oberhausen    ...............      ... 288Berlin ...&quot;    ..............,      ... 492               Homberg (Meerbeck), oil plant     ......... 1842/3            dusseldorf     ......      ...      ....      ...      ... 992Osnabruck      ...   *  ...       ......      ...       ... 423/4            Berlin ...      ...      ............      ... 554               Solingen        ...      ...      ...      ...                ... 1764/5            Bochum         .........      ......... 749Ladbergen      ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 176Hanover        ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 43In addition 294 aircraft were despatched on small raids on German townsand other targets.

LOlFarben Chemical &quot;Tories was attacked in 10/10 cloud on ^th 0ctobcr ,T%4&quot;.      This shVn/s &quot;some of the damage.   -  In alii V7buildings vore destroyed or heavily damaged in this v/orks duringthe attack.

^IK-iBUIift.    &apos;Ms photograph we t taken after the attacks of 14th and nightVi/15&apos;th October,192+4, and :5hc.s some of the damage done to the many steel works duringthcoo attacks.

SJISBURG.      After the heavy attacks of 14 th and night 14/15th October, 1944.      Thisphotograph shows the present state of accumulated devastation in the town.    Note the many sunken and destroyed barges in the docks.

BRUNSWICK^   Before and after the devastating attack on the night 14/15th  October,1944.&quot;aSs&quot;&apos;town vas virtually destroyed &quot;by just, over 200 aircraft dropping 350 tors of bombs.
OOLCXME.    The town cf Mulheim shown before and after the attack of the 28th October, 19^4,A vast area of Mulheim along the E* bank of the Rhine was destroyed by fire,    &quot;Scio fires were ntill burning when the photograph on the right was taken 19 hours after the attacks
0OIXXS3E.    The town cf Mulheim shown before and after the attack of the 28th October ,1944.A vast area of Mulheim along the E* bank of the fihine was destroyed by fire,    rJhe firewwere ntill burning when the photograph on the right was taken 19 hours after the attack.

EoSEtT-(1); Extremely heavy damage was done to the Krupps Works after the two heavy   -raids of the night 23/24th. October and day 25th October,1944.      Biis photograph shows the devastation0^ a part of the Krupps Works (sec also 2).    Nearly every workshophas been either destroyed or severely damaged by blast.

A further part of the Krupps ,works showing severe damage to all shopsfroin the raids 23/24th October and 25th Octcber-,1944. (sue also l)

BOM. 18th October,1%4*-11 -1 mn in mmmmm mi mm1&apos; wmmmm m in 11 i --1m -rr--firm i. man -ii mm- -nr m.....ifniim -TP^r^^T^iff^This photograph, taken during the daylight attack, shows a concentration of H* S* and incendiary bombs on thecentre of the Town.

V^gS. A flooded area of approximately 300 x 250 yds. at the first high tide afterthe dyke was Breached or. 11th Octobers1944.

THE SOKPE DAM which was attacked with 12,0001b, bombs on15th October,1944*    This photograph taken directly after the attack shows the huge craters on the dam and the apronleading down to the compensating basin which is empty.

KLEVE..  &quot;The tovna was virtually destroyed by the attack of 7th October,1944*      The photograph shows the town centredevastated vdth one building still burning.

miERICHi^ Thia photograph shows a portion of the town, th* v^ricle oxwas&quot;r&quot;ci&apos;evastated in the attack of 7th October,1944.

The KScsBS Dow which was attacked v/ith 12001b. bombs.     This photograph, taken onthe 15th.October51944 shows that one section of the dain has been completely&apos; &quot;destroyed and the river now flows freely through the breach.     The river level is nearly the same on both sides.     Note the fall of water on the up - streamside as shown by the shelving banks.

GERMAN DEFENCES  BEING OBLITERATED BEFORE THE  CANADIANS  TAKE   BOTH THESE  CHANNEL   PORTSHEAVY BOMBERS SUPPORT THE ARMY

BREST - U-BOAT PENS.U-boat shelter roof.A 12,000lb. bcrib crater through 19&apos;6&quot; reinforced concrete




</content>
</cab>
