<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/67/4 images: 80-94</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secretsecretIs DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTP80^&apos; COPY NO clulionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinetheld at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 31 JANUARY 1980at 10. 00 amPRESENTThe Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MPPrime Minister e Rt Hon William WMtelaw MP The Rt Hon Lord Hail sham cretary of State for the Home Department     Lord ChancellorL RtJHon Lord Carrington The Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC MP cretary of State for Foreign and Chancellor of the ExchequerImmqnwealth Affairsle RtHon Sir Keith Joseph MP The Rt Hon Francis Pym MP cretary of State for Industry Secretary of State for Defencelie RtHon James Prior MP The Rt Hon Sir Ian Gilmour MP cretary of State for Employment Lord Privy Seal|e RtHon Peter Walker MP The Rt Hon Michael Heseltin* MP nister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food   Secretary of State for the Environmentlie Rt Hon George Younger MP The Rt Hon Nicholas Edwards MPJcretary of State for Scotland Secretary of State for WalesFilon Humphrey Atkins MP The Rt Hon Patrick Jenkin MPry of State for Northern Ireland Secretary of State for Social ServicesHon Norman St John-Stevas MP The Rt Hon David Howell MPlor of the Duchy of Lancaster Secretary of State for EnergyHon Mark Carlisle QC MP The Rt Hon John Biff en MPry of State for Education and Science Chief Secretary, TreasuryThe Rt Hon Angus Maude MPPaymaster General
secretTHE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENToa Norman Fowler MP\ of TransportChdnnon MPi of State, Civil Service Department6 and 7)The Rt Hon Michael Jopling MPParliamentary Secretary, TreasuryEarl FerrersMinister of State, Ministry ofAgriculture, Fisheries and FoodSECRETARIATSir	Robert Armstrong	Mr	M D M Franklin	(Items 2-4)Mr	P Le Cheminant	(Items 5 and 7)Mr	P J Harrop	(Item 1)Mr	R L Wade-Gery	(Items 2-4 and 6)Mr	P Mountfield	(Item 7)Mr	R M Has tie-Smith	(Item 6)Mr	W N Hyde	(Item 1)Mr	G D Miles	(Item 5)CONTENTSSubjectPARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRSFOREIGN AFFAIRSRhodesiaAfghanistanCOMMUNITY AFFAIRSCommunity BudgetCommon Fisheries PolicySteelNORTHERN IRELANDINDUSTRIAL AFFAIRSSteel StrikeWater IndustryPort of LondonAmbulancemenSTATEMENT ON THE DEFENCE ESTIMATES 1980PUBLIC EXPENDITUREPage1112233445568iisecret
confidentialIMENTARY       1.        The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons during the following week. iaouslice:[3rdI2.        THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY saidthat in spite of the South African withdrawal from Beith ridge,which had now been announced, a debate was being held in theUnited Nations Security Council at African insistence. Theupshot was likely to be a resolution unacceptable to Britain, whichwould have to be vetoed if (as seemed possible) it secured therequisite nine votes*    The matter would probably then be raisedunder the Uniting for Peace procedure in the General Assembly,where over 100 votes might be cast against Britain. PresidentNyerere of Tanzania, who had never wanted the settlement atLancaster House,  appeared to be the prime mover on the Africanside; and the Russians were of course active in supports Oneunfortunate effect of these developments might be to decrease theprospects for general acceptance of the results of the forthcomingRhodesian elections.    It was ironical that this disruptive,dishonest and dishonourable course was being followed at a timewhen the situation was developing reasonably satisfactorily insideRhodesia, where the war had been ended and the election campaignbegun.    The only serious irregularities were being committed bythe partisans of Mr Mugabe, who would certainly escape censureat the United Nations.    The Governor&apos;s estimate was thatMr Nkomo might win 25-30 of the 80 non-white seats, and thatMr Mugabe might secure rather more of the remainder thanBishop Muzorewa.    Mr Ian Smith&apos;s recent speech in support ofMr Nkomo seemed to have been designed to damage the Muzorewafaction and was unlikely to benefit the Nkomo faction.rdIns.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thatPresident Giscard d&apos;Estaing&apos;s visit to India had produced acommunique which was ambivalent on the subject of Afghanistan,But the Islamic Conference in Islamabad had passed resolutionssatisfactorily condemning the Russians over Afghanistan and alsocalling on them to withdraw from the Horn of Africa. Internationalsupport for the American attitude to the Olympic Games appearedto be growing.    The Germans disliked President Carter&apos;s approachbut would probably come into line; and even the French wereshowing signs of movement.    The position of the InternationalOlympic Committee was likely to be clearer after their meeting on10-12 February.The Cabinet -Took note.confidential
confidential3.        THE PRIME MINISTER said that most of the time during theAnglo-Italian Ministerial talks on 29-30 January had been taken upwith the United Kingdom&apos;s budget problem.    Signor Cossiga hadshown a strong* desire to reach a solution tc the problem and, whileit would not be helpful to him in his forthcoming discussions withother Heads of Government for us to say so publicly, he was anxiousto be as helpful to us as possible.   Part of the Italian desire to behelpful stemmed from their dislike of the Franco-German axis withinthe Community.    Although progress towards a solution was not asfar or as fast as she would have liked, the efforts of the Foreign andCommonwealth Secretary and die Lord Privy Seal appeared to haveproduced some movement.    Nevertheless a substantial gap stillremained, and it was essential to stick firmly to our position thatthe prospective United Kingdom net contribution was intolerably high.There would be no point in having an early meeting of the EuropeanCouncil unless there were good prospects of a settlement, and it nowseemed likely that the matter would come up at the meeting scheduledfor the end of March,    What action should then follow if a satisfactoryagreement could not be reached was still under consideration. Therewould be attempts to link with the Budget other matters, such asagreement on a sheepmeat regime: but it would not be possible forthe United Kingdom to accept a sheepmeat regime on the basis nowbeing proposed by the French Government,THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD said thatthe Council of Ministers (Fisheries) had been able to reach agreementon the levels of Total Allowable Catches (TACs) for 1980 and a systemof catch reporting.    The success of the meeting owed much to thefact that he had reached a prior understanding with the FrenchMinister of Fisheries.    This good Anglo-French collaboration wouldhe more severely tested when the Council moved on in March to thodifficult questions of quotas and access.    It was planned to hold afisheries debate in the Houae of Commons shortly, and it would benecessary to explain why we had allowed a decision on TACs to betaken in the Council before the matter had been debated in the House.The fishing industry had been content with what had happened in theCouncil,    Their present anxieties were not with the Common FisheriesPolicy but with their current financial difficulties.    Increased imports,in themselves perfectly legitimate, had depressed market prices. Atthe same time, fishermen were facing higher costs and higherinterest charges on their borrowing.    THE SECRETARY OF STATEFOR SCOTLAND added that the leaders of the Scottish fishing industrywould come under strong pressure from the rank and file at a massmeeting to be held on the following Saturday in Peterhead,    The poorstate of the fishing industry was stirring up Nationalist feeling inScotland,2confidential
confidentialTHE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said thatCommissioner Vredeling had made misleading statements about thefailure of the Government and the British Steel Corporation to claimmoney from the European Community to help finance redundanciesin the steel industry.    As the Prime Minister had pointed out in theHouse, the Commission&apos;s agreement to provide  7.7 million towardsthe cost of redundancies at Shotton had been approved by CommissionerVredeling himself.In a brief discussion, it was pointed out that Commissioner Vredelingseemed to be trying to score points because of his disappointment thatnot only the United Kingdom but most other members of the Councilhad not supported his proposal for a worksharing scheme in steelplants threatened with closure.    There had  been previous cases whereCommissioner Vredeling had made accusations against us which hadbeen proved to be unfounded.   Although the situa-tior. over Communityfinance for steel closures was a complicated one, it would beimportant to rebut firmly the Commission&apos;s unwarranted criticisms.The Cabinet -Took note.ern 4.        THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN IRELAND saidD that the Conference on the future government of Noithern Ireland hadnow started to consider the central question of how a devolved systems for the Province would actually function.    The Social Democraticce: Labour Party were at this stage participating actively.    The positions3?d of the parties represented at the Conference were of course far apart,lons, and no rapid progress could be expected.    Contrary to Press reports,however, the Conference did not appear to be on the verge of breakdown;and the mere fact of its existence was having a beneficial effect on theparties, who were now on the whole treating each other with lessrancour than might have been expected.The Cabinet -Took note.3confidential
confidentialTRIALStrikepuspnce:i 3rdasions,55.        THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDUSTRY said that therewere now signs that the Iron and Steel Trades Confederation (ISTC)might be willing to resume negotiations.    Even if the will to reach asettlement existed, it would take time to convene the ISTC delegatesto approve any settlement which might be reached with the leadership.Although the dma*ler unions would have been willing to settle lastweek, they had held off, in the hope of achieving a united front withthe ISTC.    The effect of the strike on industry was still relativelysmall.    A few companies would run short of stocks within 2 to 3 weeks,but the majority could last for a further 3 to 4 weeks.In discussion it was noted that the House of Lords was consideringthat morning whether to allow an appeal against the ruling in theCourt of Appeal against an extension of the steel strike into theprivate sector.    If the House of Lords did allow the appeal to proceed,they would consider the case on Friday 1 February.    It was suggestedthat the ruling from the Court of Appeal had provided a rallying pointaround which both moderates and militants within the trades unionmovement could combine in opposition to the Government* Whateverthe outcome of the House of Lords judgment, it would be desirable tohandle all relations with the trade unions with especial delicacy in thecoming weeks.The Cabinet -1.    Took note.Industryiousrence:I) 3fd Ilusions,Ite 5.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE ENVIRONMENT said that,although no agreement had been reached at Monday&apos;s meeting betweenmanagement and unions on the pay of water industry manual workers,it had been agreed that negotiations should resume on Friday,1 February.    The management had made a firm offer involving acomparability element, aj well as an-annual uprating of pay, and inthese circumstances it was unlikely that the unions would contemplateany precipitate industrial action.The Cabinet -2,    Took note.confidential
confidential[of London        THE MINISTER OF TRANSPORT said that the Port ei LondonIAuthority (PLA) had this week warned the unions concerned mat,unless agreements on improved working practices could beimplemented in full by June, the financial position of the PLA wouldrequire the closure of one of the Upper Docks.    There had so farbeen no adverse anion reaction, but it seemed likely that, if such aclosure was eventually necessary, there would be some strike actionwithin the Port of London,    It was unlikely, however, that this wouldspread to other ports.The Cabinet -3.   Took note.rancemenTHE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SOCIAL SERVICES reported thatthere was a risk of industrial action by ambulancemen in some areasof England and Walec   in opposition co attempts by the HealthAuthorities to reduce restrictive practices in the Ambulance Service,The Cabinet -4.    Took note.confidential
confidentialT ON     6.        The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofNCE       State for Defence (C(80) 8) to which was attached a draft of the 19806 1980    Statement on the Defence Estimates.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DEFENCE said that this year&apos;sDefence White Paner sought to offer a more coherent basicexplanation of policy and roles than the statements of the previousAdministration.    The Defence and Oversea Policy Committee hadalready considered a draft of the White Paper, and the version beforethe Cabinet incorporated certain changes they had suggested.Following discussion with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, he nowproposed to publish the White Paper shortly after the publication ofthe Public Expenditure White Paper.In discussion some concern was expressed about the contents ofparagraphs 628 - 643 which dealt with civilian personnel. Theirrole in the defence field was an important one; and it was right tobe concerned for their morale, which was not as high as that of theuniformed services.   But their position was comparable to that oftheir colleagues in other Departments of central government, suchas the Department of the Environment, and in local government; andthere was a danger that statements about recruitment levels or payin these paragraphs might be used to cause difficulties in othercontexts.The following additional points were made:-a. Paragraph 634, which dealt with improvements inefficiency and the curtailment or elimination of functions,should be amended to make it clear that this was a continuingreview rather than one which had now been completed withinthe Ministry of Defence.b. Consideration should be given to some expansion ofthe section of the White Paper dealing with the TerritorialArmy and other reserve forces, not least in order to encouragerecruitment to them.c. The figures for the Defence Budget in Chapter 8 of theWhite Paper and elsewhere would be filled in when decisionshad been taken on public expenditure, in consultation withthe Chancellor of the Exchequer, who might also wish tosuggest further amendment to the reference to economicstrategy and public expenditure in paragraph 803.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said thatsubject to the points made in discussion the Cabinet approved thedraft Statement on the Defence Estimates 1980.   As the Ministry ofDefence employed one-third of the Civil Service it was obviouslyimportant that no hostages to fortune should be given by the WhitePaper&apos;8 references to civilian personnel; the paragraphs on thisconfidential 6
confidentialsubject should therefore be revised and shortened.    The Secretaryof State for Defence should then arrange for the White Paper to bepublished after the publication of the Public Expenditure White PapeThe Cabinet -Invited the Secretary of State for Defence to amend thedraft Statement in accordance with the points made indiscussion, in consultation as appropriate with theChancellor of the Exchequer, the Secretary of State forthe Environment, the Secretary of State for Employmentand the Minister of State, Civil Service Department;and to arrange for its publication after the PublicExpenditure White Paper.confidential
secretsecret7  The Cabinet considered a joint memorandum by theChancellor bf the Exchequer and the Chief Secretary, Treasury,(C(80) 9) reporting oh hi a further discussions with Ministers aboutreductions in the planned level of public expenditure in the years1980-81 to 1983-84, and making further proposals for changes.The Cabinet18 discussion is recorded separately.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet had now completed its examination of public expenditure in1980-81 and subsequent years, subject to some minor points raisedin discussion which should be resolved before the end of the dayand subject to an outstanding decision on the cash limits to beapplied to Civil Service manpower.    The Cabinet would considerthis and any related issues at a meeting in- the following month.The Cabinet -1. Agreed to the reductions in public expenditureset out in C(80) 9, subject to the alterations, additionsand exclusions agreed in discussion.2. Invited the Secretary of State for Employment,the Secretary of State for Industry, the Chancellor of theDuchy of Lancaster, the Secretary of State for theEnvironment and the Secretary of State for Education andScience, to consider again certain of the points made indiscussion and to inform the Chancellor of the Exchequerbefore the end of the day of any further reductions in theirprogrammes which might be possible.3. Took note that the totals of public expenditure for1980-81 and later years would be announced by theChancellor of the Exchequer in the course of thepresentation of the Budget and the White Paper on PublicExpenditure,4. Invited the Ministers concerned, in consultation withthe Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Prime Minister,to consider further the timing of any announcements ofspecific decisions.5. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer tocirculate the text of a draft White Paper on publicexpenditure in due course.Cabinet Office31 January 19808
secretCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCOPY NOJoCABINETLIMITED CIRCULATION ANNEXCC(80) 4th Conclusions, Minute 7Thursday 31 January 1980 at 10.00 amITUREce:3rdsions,7The Cabinet considered a joint memorandum by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer and the Chief Secretary, Treasury, (C(80) 9),reporting on ti-eir further discus sions with Ministers -abeutreductions in the planned level of public expenditure in the years1980-81 to 1983-84, and making further proposals for changes.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that, as a result ofhis discussions, he had now identified potential savings of about 800 million in 1980-81, and of between  1, 750 million and 2,200 million in the subsequent years, compared with theCabinet&apos;s approved target of reductions of  1, 000 million in1980-81 and of  2, 000 million in each of the later years. Allthese figures - both the potential savings and the targets - wereexclusive of any reduction in the United Kingdom contribution tothe Budget of the European Community.    Some of the proposedchanges had been agreed by the Ministers concerned subject toapproval by the Cabinet,    Others were in dispute.    Some, bothof those agreed and of those not agreed, were politically sensitive.He therefore sought the Cabinet&apos;s decisions on all of the proposalsmade.The Cabinet then considered in turn&apos;the possible savings listed inAnnex A to C(80) 9.    The following main points were made indiscussion, and the following conclusions reached.Security The Cabinet was reminded that the original proposal had been thatshort-term benefits should be increased by ten percentage pointsless than the movement in prices at the next annual up-rating.This had been felt to be too drastic a curtailment, and the proposalnow was that the abatement should be five percentage points.    It wassuggested in discussion that an abatement of l\ percentage pointswould produce a larger contribution to the Chancellor&apos;s target, andwould be consistent with the objective of improving the incentive towork; but the Cabinet agreed that the abatement should be limited tosecret
SECRETfive percentage points less than the movement in prices. Thatshould be regarded as a temporary adjustment pending the taxationof these benefits.    The Cabinet also agreed all the other proposalslisted on page 1 of Table 1 of Annex C to C(80) 9.    As for ChildBenefit, it was argued that, now that child tax allowances had beenabolished, this was the only fiscal provision for families; it wentto families at all income levels; and a substantial increase wasneeded to maintain fiscal equity between families with childrenand those without.    Child Benefit was also important in helping tomaintain the income differential between those in work and thoseout of work, because other benefits to those out of work weresubject to abatement in respect of Child Benefit*    Against this, itwas argued that this was the only major benefit not yet formallyindexed to prices or earnings, and that it would be inconsistentwith the Government&apos;s new policy on benefits to compensate fullyfor price movements.    The Cabinet agreed to increase ChildBenefit by 75p from November 1980,    The Cabinet also agreed thatthere should be no premium paid for fourth and subsequentchildren; that there should be no restriction on the lines proposedin the increases in supplementary benefit child rates; and that aspecial supplement should be introduced for one-parent families atan annual cost of about  5 million.    The Cabinet further agreedthat the  10 pensioners&apos; Christmas bonus should be continued, butthat the pensioner a&apos; earning rule should be frozen at the presentlevel of  52 instead of increasing in line with earnings.The Cabinet endorsed the savings already agreed by the Secretaryof State, and approved the additional savings on public hectorhousebuilding, council house improvements and assistance to privatesector housing proposed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, as setout in paragraph 5 of C(80) 9.    They noted that it would not bepossible to make further savings by transferring part of thefinancing of the Housing Corporation to the private sector in view ofpast criticism from the Public Accounts Committee,of *e The Cabinet approved the further savings agreed by the Secretary*&apos;.| of State for the Environment as set out in paragraph 6 of C(80) 3.The Cabinet also agreed to seek further savings of approximately10 per cent a year in the expenditure of the Property ServicesAgency.2
SECRETThe Cabinet approved the savings already agreed with the Secretaryof State for. Education and Science, set out in paragraph 7 ofC(80) 9.    It was noted that further savings might be possible inthe provision for teaching and non-teaching staff in the years inquestion, and the Secretary of State for Education and Science wasasked to re-examine these provisions.An increase of prescription charges to  1 would be politicallytroublesome, coming on top of the recent and prospective increasesalready agreed; but less troublesome than removing all theexemptions (particularly for the elderly) or further cutting healthservice expenditure.    The Cabinet agreed therefore to increaseprescription charges to  1 from December 1980, and to imposecharges for prescriptions provided to outpatients at hospitals, fordental treatment for young people between 16 and 21 no longer atschool and for ophthalmic sight testing, but otherwise to maintainthe present exemptions from charges.It was noted that the Manpower Services Commission had recentlyincrea&amp;ed its staff by 300, and that there might be scope forsavings on this account.    In addition, the Cabinet noted withapproval an undertaking by the Secretary of State for Employmentto secure savings of about  40 million a year from 1981-1982onwards, from the transfer of financial responsibility for theIndustrial Training Boards to industry, subject to the passage ofthe necessary legislation.The Cabinet approved the remaining changes set out in C(80) 9.The following further points were made in discussion:-a.      After all the savings now agreed, the total reductionswere still some way short of the targets which the Cabinethad set themselves.    Ministers in charge of Departmentsshould as a matter of great urgency consider and report tothe Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Chief Secretary,Treasury, what further savings they could offer. Theremight be some small further savings to come from theDepartment of Industry; and the programme of the Office ofArts and Libraries should be further reviewed for possiblesavings.3SECRET
secretb. The cash limits already approved or shortly to beapproved by Cabinet for 1980-81 might impose a furthervolume squeeze on expenditure in mat year, the extent ofwhich could not yet be accurately measured.    Because ofthese and other uncertainties, no decision could be takenat this stage about the size of the Contingency Reserve forthat year*    The timing of any announcement of theGovernment&apos;s decisions would require further consideration.Where it was necessary for an individual Minister to announceor act upon a decision hearing on his responsibilities, heshould clear beforehand both the text and timing of any suchannouncement with the Prime Minister and the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer.c. That apart, the Cabinet&apos;s decisions must remain secretIn due course steps would be needed to secure the completesupport and understanding of Ministers not in the Cabinetand of die Parliamentary Party for the decisions reached.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet had now completed its examination of public expenditure in1980-81 and subsequent years, subject to some minor points raisedin discussion which should be resolved before the end of the day andsubject to an outstanding decision on the cash limits to be appliedto Civil Service manpower.   The Cabinet would consider this andany related issues at a meeting in the following month.The Cabinet -1. Agreed to the reductions in public expenditureset out in C(80) 9, subject to the alterations, additionsand exclusions agreed in discussion.2. Invited the Secretary of State for Employment,the Secretary of State for Industry, the Chancellor ofthe Duchy of Lancaster, the Secretary of State for dieEnvironment and the Secretary of State for Educationand Science, to consider again certain of the pointsmade in discussion and to inform the Chancellor of theExchequer before the end of the day of any furtherreductions in their programmes which might be possible.3. Took note that the totals of public expenditure for1980-81 and later years would be announced by theChancellor of the Exchequer in the course of thepresentation of die Budget and the White Paper on PublicExpenditure.4secret
SECRET4, Invited the Ministers concerned, in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the PrimeMinister, to consider further the timing of any annouce-ments of specific decisions.5. Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer tocirculate the text of a draft White Paper on puhlicexpenditure in due course.Cabinet Office1 February 19805SECRET

</content>
</cab>
