<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/4/39 images: 534-551</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
WAR      cabinet air OPERATIONS AND INTELLIGENCE.EIGHTEENTH WEEKL? REPORT BY THE Secretary Of STATE FOR AIR(Previous Report Paper W.P.  (40) 3)The accompanying report on Air Operations and Intelligencefor the week ending midnight, 7th January, 1940, is submittedto the War Cahinet.(Signed)      KINGSLEY WOOD.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1,8th January    1940.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY. - . . h * *It is requested that special care may be taken to ^    ^ ,ensure the secrecy of this document. oo-e&amp;U e*-v-j/SECRET \lWrF&apos;  (4Q) 9- COPY NO

MOST SECRET.COPY NO.     -2 Lf-WEEKLY REPORT NO,18 ON AIR operations and INTELLIGENCE FOR THE WEEK ENDINGMIDNIGHT,  7TH JANUARY,  1940,Bomber Command,1.     The week was on the whole a quiet one.      There were,however, a number of valuable reconnaissance flights, some of thorncarried out in force, and offensive patrols over German seaplanebases were continued by night when the weather permitted.2,     Two of the reconnaissances in force took place unevent-fully, no enemy activity being observed.      In the course of thethird reconnaissance, which was carried out by a force of Wellingtonaircraft, a combat took place between a section of three of our aircraft and a force of between twelve and fifteen Messerschmitt 110long range fighter aircraft about 100 miles off the German coast.One Wellington was seen to be shot down, and one other failed toreturn.      One Messerschmitt was shot down in flames and two othersv/ere seen to go down and did not return to engage the formation.The remaining Wellington returned to its base on one engine.3.     Two valuable reconnaissances Here carried out by singleBlenheim aircraft on the 2nd january     The first aircraft flew thelength of the Island of Sylt to search for possible balloon barragesand reported that no balloons or ships carrying balloons were to beseen.     A number of photographs were taken.      The second aircraft operating over Wilhelmshaven in favourable weather conditionssucceeded in photographing a number of units of the German fleet in the harbour.4. Offensive patrols over German seaplane bases were hamperedduring the week by unsuitable weather conditions. Two such patrolstook place, however^ on the nights of the 4th and 5th Januaryrespectively./5o

5W     Leaflet dropping was also resumed on the nights of 4thand 5th January *     Two Whitlejr aircraft were engaged each night,and successfully raided Bremen and Hamburg,,      The broadcasting stations at these towns closed down for a period on each occasion.Advanced Air Striking JForceo6.     On 2nd January one Blenheim aircraft carried out aphotographic reconnaissance to a depth of 20 miles beyond the franco-German frontier.      Intense and accurate anti-aircraft firewas reported at 22,000 feet0Fighter Command07P     Enemy air activity in the vicinity of the British Isleswas again on an exceedingly small scale during the week,      Apartfrom the attack on H0Mc3o   Coventry&apos;   (see paragraph 10) no raidstook place which were definitely identified as hostile.      Therewere a few unidentified raids reported, but no contacts were effected by the fighter patrols despatched to investigatec8.     Routine patrols over certain estuaries and over the fishing fleet were maintained during the week, and fighter escortswere provided for leave boats crossing the Channel.      In additionto the usual patrols, high altitude patrols were flown on 4th and 5th January to intercept any enemy aircraft attempting reconnaissance flights at great heights0Coastal Command^9.     The usual patrols, searches and convoy escorts continued,though fog caused some interference on the last two days of the;week.10*    Shortly before 11 osclock on 1st January an attack waswade by enemy aircraft on H^M^Sc  Coventry&apos;, the anti-aircraftI -icruiser which has been stationed in the Shetlands to protect thefflying-boat depot ship &apos;Manela&apos;*      Two bombs v/ere dropped from500 feet and fell about 20 feet from the ship before the enemy/aircraft

aircraft were driven off &quot;by fighters and anti-aircraft fireeIn the course of this engagement one of our fighters pursued anenemy aircraft some   &apos;0 miles out to sea and fired 400 roundsbefore it was forced to return owing to shortage of petrol.      Onlyminor superficial damage was caused to KoM0S..  ?Coventry&apos;,lla    On the same day,  three.Hudson aircraft sighted twoHeinkel lll&apos;s ISO miles east of Far-n Island, and after a longchase brought the enemy to action.-      One Heinkel, after beingrepeatedly hit, caught fire^. fell into the sea. and sank immediately.The other, although severely hit-,  escaped into the clouds, and,as appears from later reports-, macle its way hack to its &quot;base.One Hudson failed to returnc12o    On the 2nd January,,  a Hudson sighted and attacked aHeinkel 115 float-plane 30 miles from the Danish coast0      TheHudson succeeded in getting in one burst from a range of 50 yardsbefore the enemy made an escape into the clouds013o    Submarines were sighted on 1st and 3rd January, one bya London5  flying-boat 90 miles north-east of Muckle Flugga, andone 14 miles north-east of Cape Wrath.-.      Both submarines &quot;crash-dived&quot; on the approach of the aircraft,-, and although bombs were dropped on one of these submarines as it disappeared, no damage is believed to have been donecAir Component of the .Britij^hJSxpeditionary ForeecI        14o    Unfavourable weather has again interfered with flying,fand apart from fighter patrols, the only operation has been one^strategical reconnaissance0     On 3rd January, a Blenheim aircraftlanded in England after a successful photographic reconnaissancealong the Siegfried Lino in the region Wegburg-Kaldenkirchen-yeldern-Cleve0      The pilot reported one long goods train movingjjfest at Emmerich and a circle of what appeared to he &quot;barbed wireStretching south east from Cleve through Moyland and Keppeln, withhuts or pill boxes at regular intervals along the east side.     Allecond Blenheim engaged on the same task was attacked &quot;by German/fighters

fighters at Raeren and forced to land just inside the Belgianfrontier,,Overseas Commands,150    Anti-submarine patrols and convoy escorts were provided in the Mediterranean area and reconnaissances were also carriedout by the Air Forces in India,     There are no operations to reportfrom Palestine or Aden-AIR INTELLIGENCE.[German Ajr Activity0160    There has been little activity apart from normal1I training during the week      On 1st January, eight aircraft of a; bomber formation were operating in the North Sea, probably workingI in pairso      One pair was intercepted by Hudson aircraft and the resulting combat is described in paragraph 110      On the sameImorning, two enemy aircraft; probably from the same formation,attacked H0M0SC -Coventry5 (paragraph 10), Meteorological flightslover the North Sea continued during the week, and reconnaissanceactivity was noted over the Central North Sea area on 6th January.IOn 3rd January, several flights were made over Eastern Prance,sand two aircraft penetrated as far as Paris, dropping leaflets onthe wayc      Training activity, which was much reduced during the christmas period, is now normal, and a considerable number of-training flights are being made to and from East Prussia.17,    The total confirmed enemy losses up to 31st December,I ;are set out in the following table:-

-5-282	He. in	Do. 17	Do. 215	Ju. 88	Ju. 87	Me. 109	Me. 110	Hs, 126	Do. 18	He. 115	Not known		Total.Great Britain Prance North Sea Germany Neutral Countries	9 4 s s	1 11 1	-	1 1	-	24 8 1	9	3 t x	7 4	1 5	1 mm		12 42 \. 16 I 17 9TOTALe	17	13	-	2	-	33	9	4	11	6	1		96Accepted in Polandj	30	28	4	-	10	16	2	10	-	-	-		100j GRAND TOTAL        j	47	41	4	2	10	49	11	14	11	6	1		196Of the aircraft brought down ih Franoe, the Frenchaccounted for 31, and the British 10,    In addition, British andFrench together shot down one Heinkel 111.French Air Activity.18.     The week was one of increased aut-l-v t$7/on the part of theFrench Air Force,   Regular photographic reconnaissances were carried out, and during the night of 2nd January high altitudereconnaissance and leaflet-dropping flights were made over the black Forest region and the Nuremburg, Ulm, Freudenstadt and--Sigmaringen areas. In addition, there were numerous fighter patrols.The Russo-Finnish War.19..    Operationso        During the pa:;t week Russian air attacksIon the principal towns of Finland continued, but little damaged is-reported.   The attacks appeared to be directed chiefly againstPorts, and the raid on Abo was no doubt intended to interfere with, &quot;shipments from Sweden.

20.     Finnish aircraft nave been employed during the r/eekin &quot;bombing retreating Russian troops and attacking largeencampments in the vicinity of Lakes Kauk, Perk and Riesk.Assistance from other countries.21.     The Swedish Government have organised one squadron of twelve Gladiators and one squadron of twelve Harts equipped withskis to proceed with the Swedish Volunteer force which is to operate from the neighbourhood of Uleaborg.   The air bases willbe at Kemi and Oulu, with advanced bases on the neighbouringfrozen lakes.22,     Forty-four -Brewster fighters are to be released fromthe United States of America for sale to the Finnish Government;they will be delivered as soon as possible.gussian Air Tactics*23.     Russian air tactics in Finland may be summarised asfollowsi-(i)   Bombersa        Bombing raids are being carried outlargely by formations of twelve, nine or seven aircraft, while attacks on troops and reconnaissancesare undertaken by aircraft singly or in threes.The bombers are not accompanied by fighters.    Thenumber of pilots fit for cloud or night flyingseems to be very small; pilots seldom enter cloudeven when attacked, and rarely fly by night.    Theyhave standing instructions to return to their basesone hour before nightfall.Fighter8.        Attacks are usually made by sections ofthree aircraft in such tight formation that only the leader can make use of his guns./North

-7-284North Sea Civil Airlines.24.    The German Legation has warned the Norwegian ministry for Foreign Affairs of the dangers of flying across the north sea.     The German Government has disclaimed &quot;beforehand allresponsibility for possible losses through warlike measures.   Asimilar warning has been addressed to the Swedish Government.Moscow-Berlin Air Service.25.    A daily air service is expected to begin on 21stJanuary between Moscow and Berlin via Minsk, Belostock,Koenigsberg and Danzig.




</content>
</cab>
