<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/2/29 images: 318-325</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.TO BUY.KEPT:i:IJuCJ&apos;CK:^AN-D;-KBy.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 93 (89).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W.1, on Sunday, November26, 1939, at 12 noon.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. Lord Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.Air Marshal R. E. C. Peirse, deputy chief of the Air Staff.Maior-General H. R. S. Massy, deputy chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Colonel L. C. Hollis, R.M.Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, R.E.Wing Commander W. Elliot.
Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1     The Air Situation     ...      ............     ... 2212     The Naval Situation ...      ...      ... ...     ... 2213     Magnetic Mines        ....      ......      ...      ...... 222Suggested retaliatory measures.4     The Military Situation       ...     ......    .......    2225     Balkans and the Middle East       ...      ...      ...      ...    222Anglo-French discussions on strategy.General Weygand&apos;s activities.6     Roumania       ... .    ...      ...      ...      ......     ...    223Conversion of Danube grain barges for transport of oil toGermany.-Italy -   ...     ....     ...... .   ..... ...... 223
CjO^UpiOnB)),;,;;Minute.!.)&apos;..The Qeputyt,Chietof the A^ WarJ^^t&quot;ibiit six WpUingl^ns: sweep on, ^previous day to a point West of Sylt, thence North-East andhphxe. .They had foTihd nothingFour Blenheims had carried out a reconnaissance of : us no jrj^ the base of heavy cloudyd; w. r ; alt 6,000 feet, they had seen six warships in two lines of..* three at anchor, probably cruisers., (ii) Heligoland-The aircraft had circled the islands three times between 7,000 and 3,000 feet, but had seen nothing of importance.(iii) Cuxhaven. Six small warships, possibly destroyers, had; been seen moored to the quayside.&apos; Coastal Command had carried out their, usual patrols. On oneof these a Hudson aircraft had engaged a Dornier 18 flying-boatBO ihiles- West of the Lister Light, with what were believed to be good results. After the third attack the Hudson had in turn been engaged by a Heinkel, and had taken avoiding action by climbinginto the clouds.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.situation.(previous reference:: :W.M. (39) 94thConclusions,Minute 2.)(Previous..Reference: :Conclusions,Minute 12.); % The First Lord of the Admiralty gave the War cabinet particulars of the dispositions of the Fleet for the interception ofthe Deutschland. These would continue to be maintained until further information necessitated a change.A further message from H.M.S. Newcastle revealed that the attack on the Rawalpindi had been carried out by two enemy ships one of the Deutschland Class and one of a smaller type, verypossibly the Leipzig, which was not fitted with Diesel engines andwould, therefore, not have the same endurance.Despite very unfavourable weather, extensive air recon-reconnaissances had been carried out by German aircraft during thewhole of the previous day, during which the Aurora had been bombed but not hit. These and other indications pointed to theGermans being anxious to bring their ships home and to find out what dispositions we had made to prevent this. If the Deutschlandhad sufficient fuel left, she might go out again into the Atlantic.    ,It was feared that, with the exception of ten survivors picked up by the S.S. Chitral and the faint hope, that a few more mighthavebeen picked up by our trawlers-the entire crew of theRawalpindi had been lost. Publication of the loss had been delayedso as to keep the Germans in doubt about our knowledge of the engagement. It was also in accord with general practice to delayan announcement until we had more definite information aboutcasualties. The Admiralty would, however, be issuing a statement in,the course of the day. This would not describe the circumstances in ;which the loss had occurred, which could be given later in astatement to Parliament.V Tjie S.S. Royston Grange had been torpedoed and sunk15pmiies W^S.W. from Land&apos;s End.ASwedish tanker had been mined West of Fair Island, but was reported to be still afloat. ..\;Vr^^ip^^ol^-^p&apos;:%ilsp(fyl$h^ been either torpedoed or mined;off^rthe/East..C^st,-and. 100 ^survivors had been picked up. It was.sti]il hoped tlm&apos;l^fb^:&apos;&apos;&apos;^Xa^ a^.&apos;h)^r^i^^.ixit&apos;on U-boats, including one150 miies. ^ contact had beenobtained, and&apos; it was thought that the submarine had been destroyed.--/As^atisffactory clearance had been made from the Downs, 102&apos; l-j    -    - -    - *   * b 2       ,
A conference had been held at the Admiralty onevening, at which the Chief of the Air staff /a^dfJCdmmanding-in-Chief,  Fighter&quot; Cohito presAgreement had been reached regarding^ intensive1 measures^defence of the Thames Estuary by balloons, which would be tetMre^tto barges. These.measures were being carried out at once, -&quot;Later!new methods of defence, which were in their final stages of deveidp-ment, would ensure a much higher degree of protection.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Magnetic&apos;mines,Suggestedretaliatory-measures.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 93rd-Conclusions,Minute 3.)The Military(previous reference:W.M. (39) 94thConclusions,Minute 4.)3. The First Lord of the Admiralty gave the War Cabinetfurther particulars regarding the project which he had describedat the meeting referred to in the margin, and suggested that heshould take an opportunity of going to France to discuss thepolitical and juridical aspects involved with the French authorities.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.4. The Deputy Chief of the Imperial General Staff informed the War Cabinet that reports had been received from a reliable source of considerable troop movements recently westward fromHanover.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.IBaltams amdl ttaAnglo-Frenchdiscussions onstrategy.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 39thConclusions,Minute 7.)General&quot;Weygand&apos;activities.5. The Chief of Naval Staff reminded the War Cabinet that,at their last meeting on the 17th November, 1939, the Supreme WarCouncil had agreed that the Military experts in France and GreatBritain should study plans for operations in South East Europe.The French Ambassador had recently proposed to the permanent under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs that there should be ameeting in Paris the following week of the Comity d&apos;Etudes, i.e.,the Permanent Military Representatives. The/French had, more-over, suggested that this body should not necessarily include theFrench Permanent Military Representatives now in London. it seemed possible that General Gamelin himself would wish to take part in any discussions in Paris. General Weygand was shortlyreturning to Paris, and would probably be associated with any such conversations. He was believed to have rather far-reaching ideasfor Staff Conversations with the various Balkan countries, and theChiefs of Staff were therefore somewhat apprehensive of the&apos;proposal for a meeting in Paris.The Joint Planning Committee had drafted anew Appreciationcovering oUr strategy in the Balkans and the Middle East, whichwould be considered by the Chiefs of Staff oh/Thursday, the 30thNovember. The Chiefs of Staff would prefer not to initiate anyAnglo-French discussions until they-had had time to examine this new Appreciation. They therefore favoured a reply to the Frenchsuggesting, first, that the French Military Representatives inLondon/should be furnished forthwitht with; the views, in general terms, held by the French High Command oh; this subject; and,secondly, that the discussions should be /stajrtod at an early date,-v^^fi the mac in the form ofthe Permanent Military&apos; Representatives;-  i&apos;&apos; /,Tihe Secretary of-State, for Wotei:g&amp;,A$idrs agreed that itwould be preferable to defer any discussions ^rothithe French un&apos;**the Chiefs of Staff had approved the
in draft, He also agreed that our reply might indicate a preference for dealing with the matter by the existing machinery. At the same time it was important not to adopt too rigid an attitude on a question of procedure. Our reply might include, therefore, a statement to the effect that, if General Gamelin himself wished to take part in the discussions, we should be ready to meet his convenience and send officers of appropriate status to Paris. We could not very well press General Gamelin himself to come to London again so soon after his last visit.

The War Cabinet agreed:-

That the terms of the reply to the suggestion of the French Ambassador should be framed in accordance with the discussion recorded above; and should include the following points:-

(i) An invitation to the French to communicate forthwith the views held by the French High Command on this subject.

(ii) A preference for dealing with this matter through the machinery of the Permanent Military Representatives in London.

(iii) A willingness to meet General Gamelin&apos;s convenience by holding a meeting in Paris of Officers of suitable rank, if he desired to take part in the discussions.

Roumania. Conversion of Danube grain barges for transport of oil to Germany (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 98rd Conclusions, Minute 12.)

6. The Minister without Portfolio reported that it had now been definitely ascertained that the Germans were installing tanks in Danube grain barges for carrying oil.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.

7. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew the attention of the War Cabinet to Vatican telegram No. 97, which contained interesting information regarding Signor Mussolini&apos;s increasing anti-German feeling. This was the first report which had been received recently regarding Signor Mussilini&apos;s personal feelings.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.

Richmond Terrace S.W. 1

November 26, 1939






</content>
</cab>
