<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/54/21 images: 132-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   august 1944. \fThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. It is issued for- the personal use of .^^rfrf^^rrr^l^.&apos;.-......................................TOP SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (44) 471.26th August, 1944.WAR CABINET.MAN-POWER FOR THE NAVY.1944 Allocations Final Estimate.Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty.IN accordance with the decision of the War Cabinet on the 14th August(W.M. (44) 106), I submit an estimate of the man-power requirements for theNavy and the Admiralty during the second half of 1944 based on the assumptionthat war with Germany will not continue beyond the 30th June, 1945.Navy.The provisional allocation for this period, on which we have been planning,was approved by the War Cabinet on the 1st December, 1943 (W.M. (43) 164)as 30,000 men, or 5,000 men per month. As pointed out in the memorandumby the Chancellor of the Exchequer (W.P. (44) 375) this was 25,000 short ofthe estimated number of trained men required to meet the Navy&apos;s commitmentsby the 31st March, 1945.1 have carefully reviewed our liabilities in the light of the revised dates of completion of new construction, and, on a most strict estimate, after allowing for resources accruing from the output of training establishments, men returning from Combined Operation Organisation, and so on, they will be 49,700 men andwomen. In view of the stringency of the man-power situation, I have imposedsevere cuts to reduce this figure. These include paying oil, or reducing ships now in commission, including one aircraft-carrier, six battleships, seven cruisers and nine destroyers. Even after these drastic steps, there remains a deficiency of 40,900 men and women.If allocations of men at the rate provisionally agreed (5,000 a month) aremade during the period September-December, and, if I receive the balance of3,500 women out of the total of 5,000 for which I asked at the time of the Junereview, I shall receive only 23,500 men arid women towards this deficit of40,900.The man-power review carried out &quot;by the Cabinet in July resulted in the sacrifice by the Navy through loss of intake, and transfers to the Army,of 11,000 men. In view of the fact that the monthly allocations for september to December will not meet the full deficit of 40,900, I must ask for the restorationof the 11,000 men which we lost in July and August. This will still leave a deficit of 6,400, but I hope that I shall be able to provide this number by furthercuts.A dmiralty Labour.At the meeting on the 12th July (W.M. (44) 90th Conclusions) a provisionalreduction to 868,000 men for the Admiralty Industries was approved.   I havenow considered whether any further reduction is acceptable on the assumptionreferred to in paragraph 1.[28093]
we have reached the limit of economies in labour employed in the manu-facture of consumable stocks and equipment and any reduction below 868,000would directly affect both naval ship-building and the achievement of themerchant ship-building target. In the light of our known commitments incurrent merchant ship-building and repairs, in addition to the preparation forthe Japanese war and the heavy repairs arising from the maintenance of&quot; Overlord,&quot; it is not possible to agree to any further reductions.A. V. A.Admiralty, S.W.1, 26th August, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
