<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/182/14 images: 172-178</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY &apos;S government(75) 39 COPY NO 8219 March 1975CABINETPUBLIC EXPENDITURE MEASURES 1976-77Memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer. The January White Paper &quot;Public Expenditure to 1978-79&quot; gavewarning (in paragraphs 30-32) that world conditions and uncertainties aboutthe underlying rate of growth in productivity might require us to reappraisethe programmes so as to achieve the appropriate balance between privatelyfinanced consumption and public expenditure. In my minute to the PrimeMinister of 19 February 1975, I undertook to circulate a paper summarising the latest economic prospects and proposing how officials should approach the preparation of the 1975 survey. u2. I now believe it is necessary that I should be able to announce in myBudget Speech cuts in the public expenditure programmes to take effect in1976-77.    Such cuts have become inevitable;  public knowledge that theyhave already been decided will enable me to adopt a less rigorous approach to the problems of 1975-76 than would otherwise be required.3. Our balance of payments deficit last year was equivalent to about per cent of gross domestic product (GDP),    In other words we werespending at home about 5 per cent more than we were earning,4, Last year our rate of inflation was among the highest in theOrganisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) countries;but we had companions in distress.    This year we look like being out on ourown with a rate of inflation nearly twice that of our main competitors.Meanwhile our balance of payments deficit, both absolutely and as a percentage of GDP, will be by far the highest among the OECD countries.5, So far we have been able to finance our external deficits by borrowing abroad from sources which did not impose restrictions on our economic policy as the price of this lending.    I believe that, unless wechange eur policy, we shall not be able to go on relying for funds on sources of this kind.1
6. One essential element in the change of policies must be a substantial and progressive reduction in the public sector borrowing requirement,    i cannot achieve all that is necessary by increases in taxation alone, for bothshort and long-term reasons.    There are Hmitc to the extent to which I canraise taxes without putting an excessive strain on the retail price index.(RPI).Under the Trades Union Congress guidelines, increases in indirect taxationfeed through into higher wage increases at the next pay settlement.    Thereis in practical negotiating terms little hope of preventing this so long asincreases in the cost of living play a major part in pay negotiations.li In the longer term the resources picture, as we now see it, is such that the maintenance of the present public expenditure programmes would leave only a negligible increase available for privately financed consumption.On the assumption that income tax allowances are raised in line with inflation and indirect taxes similarly adjusted, the standard rate of incometax will have to be increased by 1979 by 6p-8p assuming a 3 per cent annualrise in GDP from 1973 to 1979.    If the rate of growth in 1973-79 were \ per cent - and we cannot count on 3 per cent - the rise in the standardr?.te might be as much as 10p-12p.    A standard rate of income tax of something like 45p in the pound is in my judgment inconsistent with any-acceptable medium-term development of the economy.    It would also endany chance of the trade unions continuing to base settlements on comparisons with the RPI before tax and contributions.    Moreover the political consequences of income tax at this level are self-evident,,THE CUT REQUIRED IN PUBLIC expenditure, So far as 1975-76 is concerned, I accept that it is now too late toreduce expenditure programmes significantly without arbitrary anddisruptive effects, which we must avoid if we possibly can.    Without, ofcourse, anticipating my Budget, I can say that I have other measures inmind for that period.    But these will need to be reinforced in 1976, whenthe expected improvement in world trade will give us the chance of asubstantial improvement in the balance of the economy at much lower levels of unemployment.    If we are to get through the next 12 months without a major crisis, and at the same time avoid excessive deflation whenunemployment is already rising, we must be able to show that we havealready taken the necessary decisions on cutting the public expenditure programme for 1976-77;  some of the cuts may of course feed back into1975-76.ii fj9. My judgment is that we must secure a reduction in the expenditure programmes in 1976-77 of about  1,000 million at 1974 survey prices.    Tosecure this it is essential that the savings should be spread as broadly aspossible, with exclusions limited only to those programmes, or parts of programmes, of the very highest priority.
10,        We have been making large improvements in social security benefits,last year and this year, and are planning further ones for future years.There is constant pressure for more: for example, to introduce six-monthly upratings (with Christmas bonuses as well) which would cost about 300 million in 1976-77 and similar amounts in each subsequent year.    Wecannot face such additions.11,        It will also be essential to ensure that expenditure on industrialsupport of all kinds satisfies the strictest criteria of the public interest,and that the rate at which we pursue policies of public acquisition pays full regard to our capacity to finance it.12.        I will return to the question of the programmes beyond 1976-77 inthe context of the 1975 Public Expenditure Survey,    But I should make itclear, for the reasons given in paragraphs 3 and 4 above, that the constraints are likely to continue to be severe, at least until the end of the survey period.13.        I well appreciate that the reductions required must mean somedisappointment of commitments or objectives already publicly announced,but the alternative, of being forced to bigger and less well plannedretrenchment, following a collapse of external confidence, would be farworse.14,        It is not essential that all the details of the savings should be agreedimmediately, but it is essential that we should agree on the total and on the allocations to the programmes concerned, so that the references to myBudget Speech can carry the necessary conviction, and the necessary actionto secure the savings is straight away set in hand.    I attach an illustrativetable showing how the total might be allocated.CONCLUSION15.        I therefore ask cabinet a. To approve savings in the expenditure programmes for1976-77 of about  1,000 million at 1974 survey prices.b. To agree that I should enter immediately into consultations with my colleagues on the basis of the attached table to determine the distribution of these savings.D treasury Chambers19 March 1975
annex proposed PUBLIC  EXPENDITURE REDUCTIONS 19/6-77  million.     D defence Bu dge t- (a )2.    Nat a enaliscd industry investment   (b)3,     Gpiiom]   reduction  of&quot;  1-J per cent  onCmnd 5w9  figures  (excluding defence and services.in note c),  on(i) wages and salaries(ii) other current  expenditureon goods and services,   and current grants to p1ivatebodiesh.    General reduction of 10 per cent onCmnd 5879  figures for gross domesticfixed capital  fornintion,  and capital grants to persons and private non-profit-making bodies  (Exceptions asin note d)5.    Reduction in municipalisation and/ornet lending for house purchase  (a)G.     Subsidies,   etc.   (e)(i)  Reduction in food subsidies(ii) Reduction in local transportsubsidies and new bus grants  (f)(iii) Increase local authority rentsbeyond 1eve1s imp1icit in cmnd 53?9  (g)7-    Overseas aid  (a) -a. . Rostpone,, introduction, of community .ownership of development land  (h)-    (i)  Administrative costs(ii)  Purchase of land197&apos;&apos;i  Surveyprices20010010530260501503520Total  (j)1015
NOTES TO TABLE OF PROPOSED REDUCTIONS 1970-77(a) Reduction on Cmnd 5079 figures.(b) Reduction to be obtained by more rigorous scrutiny ofinv estin ent pro grammes.(c) The figures quoted are the result  of applying a  ij percent reduction to the Cmnd 5379 figures fox* wages and salaries;    other current  expenditure on goods and services;    and current grants to private bodies.They exclude defence;    overseas aid;    other c.e.g.s.on certain &quot;demand dependent&quot; and other services(viz:   family practitioner services,   drugs,   food and medical  stores in hospitals and personal  social  servicehomes,   grants  for residential homes,  welfare milk andconcessionary  fares,   agricultural  support,   support tofishing industry,   regional  support  and regeneration,industrial innovation,  general support to industry,functioning of the labour market,  crown and police p  11prosecutions,   legal aid,   food in prisons,  rates on government property and other rates and rent);     andthe Northern Ireland&quot; equivalents of these.    They alsoexclude the administrative costs of social security benefits and revenue collection;     and civil  servicesuperannuation payments.(d) The figures quoted are the result of applying a  1.0per cent reduction to the Cmnd 5379 figures  Tor gross domestic  fixed capital  formation,   and capital grants to persons and private non-profit-making bodies.  Theyexclude&apos; defence;     overseas aid;    nationalised industries;housing  (and new dwellings  in other programmes);   &quot;basicneeds&quot; school building;    regional  stq^port andregeneration;    industrial innovation,   general support to industry;     functioning of the labour market;agricultural  support,  arid support to the fishing industry;    arid Northern Ireland equivalents.(e) No reduction  is included for price subsidies to nationalised industries since (apart from 1he transport industries)  Cinnd 5^79 assumes that these would anyway
have been phased out by 1976-77* The reductionsindicated in other subsidies are reductions fromplanned Cinnd 5^*79 levels.Made up of local transport subsidies  (32)  and new-bus grants  (3)*The forecasts in Citmd 5&amp;79 imply rent increasesaveraging about 4-5p &amp; week in 1975-76  and 48p in1976-77*    The expenditui-e reduction suggested wouldrequire average rents to be about  3^P a week higher in 1976-77 than the levels implied in Cmnd 5279-The figures given are DOE estimates provided last,year.     They -would not represent a  saving on Cinnd5079i   since this item was not programmed in theWhite Paper.     There would however be some saving in the borrowing requirement.Excluding the saving on development land (see note  (h)  above).


</content>
</cab>
