<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/11/8 images: 56-63</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.secret.P.(40) 528a9,2ND AUGUST,  1940.WAR CABINETROYAL AIR FORCE TRAINING.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air0I have the following comments on the memorandum .P.(40) 327 by the Minister of Aircraft Production:-Para,3(a)eThere is no possibility of providing from overseasresources the personnel or aircraft for new schools in theDominions,     All the resources of instructors and technical personnel in Canada are already devoted to the Empire air training Scheme^ and the extensive arrangements for trainingadditional men for these purposes are fully mortgaged for the accelerated expansion of schools*     This applies to an even greater extent to South Africa where resources of semi-skilledtrainees are far more restricted,.      There are, of course, nosurplus trainer aircraft in the Dominions!    in fact, supplies are in arrears for the Empire Air Training Scheme due to the suspension of shipments for two months,-      Every effort has beenmade by the Minister aimself to obtain additional aircraft ofsuitable types from the UaSPA*, and all those obtainable willbe absorbed.COPY NObPara.3(b).Of the 19 aerodromes in use for elementary flying training schools, 15 are not suitable for Service flying training schools either because they are not large enough foruse by advanced trainer types or because the approaches of the aerodromes make them unsuitable for night flyingo      Of theremaining 4? 2 are already being transferred to smaller sitesunsuitable for Service flying training schools0     The remaining2 are in themselves suitable for Service flying training schoolsbut the relief landing grounds attached to them are not large enough;    I hope however that it may be possible by enlargingthe relief landing grounds to make the parent aerodromesavailable either for Service Plying Training Schools or for operational Training Units0     The Air Ministry is constantlysearching for open spaces since these would make naturalaerodromes without any further work being done;   but there has long been a shortage of natural sites, and this has beenaccentuated by the intensive drive for the cultivation of land.Every effort has been and is being made to seek out Usenatural open spaces.Para,. 5(c).The risk we deprecate is not so much that of trainingstations and aircraft being attacked by day, but that at nightthe display of landing lights will attract enemy bombers owingto the conspicuousness of the lights in a blacked-out country,,/To

9 Qhi WTo avoid attack the present policy is to stop night flying training on parent training aerodromes on receTpT^or^a^-yoilow&quot;warning b      Even if we took the risk of continuing night flying training until receipt of a red warning? training would heseriously interrupted,,      Moreover many of our schools ^haveAircraft Storage Units located on the same aerodrome.The standard of night flying training is not heingmaintained.      The more flying training schools we have outsidethe United Kingdom the greater will he our chance of attaining the desirable standard of night flying for our pilots.      Wehave reason to suppose that the enemy has realised his mistakein neglecting this training, especially for his fighters, andfor us also as technical equipment improves the importance of night fighting will increase,.The risk of damage to training stations and pupilsis only one of the operational reasons for transferring part ofour training organisation from this country       As was statedat the meeting of the Defence Committee (Operations) on the13th August -(i)    there is now no water round the United Kingdom exceptoff North-West Scotland whore training flights can be  made without interfering with RoDoFo(ii) if training aircraft, flying at night go ahove 3,000feet * they interfere with the work of the observer corps plotting tracks of enemy raids0These are factors imposed &quot;by the vital requirements of our defence organisation;    if we relax those requirements we endangernot only the training organisation, hut the whole country.Para, 3(d)0The Air Ministry has powers of requisition in common with other Departments0     A numher of racecourses have heeninspected and three have already heen taken over as emergencylanding grounds,,      Experience shows that racecourses as a ruleafford only landing strips, while the land in the centrerequires grading and resowingc      Nevertheless no efforts areheing spared to make increasing use of racecourses for ourpurposes0Parae 4CThe Minister of Aircraft Production refers to the shipment of 2,500 aircraft during the last half of this year.The majority of these are for the Empire Air Training Scheme,the African Training Scheme, and operational units overseas.For the transfer of schools overseas the requirement is 650aircraft,I am arranging to send a proportion of aircraftahead of the schools, so that they will find, on arrival, mostof their initial equipment ready erected;    and allowing 2 weeks to pack up the remaining equipment,, 2 weeks for the voyage, and4 weeks to settle in to the new station and complete theerection of aircraftj-T do not consider that the estimate given of 2 to 2-1- months is over-optimisticr,     The task of packing isformidahle, hut additional capacity is heing developed and Ihave every hope that the full&quot; programme will he achieved.      TheMinistry of Shipping anticipate no difficulties in shipment./The

The prohlem would he eased if it were possible for theMinister of Aircraft Production to produce additional advancedtrainer aircraft in America^Parase .5 to 8.The considerations here put forward hy the Ministerof Aircraft Production must he set against the grave restrictions imposed hy enemy action and operational requirements.       TheUnited Kingdom is small in area and upon it the weight of enemy air attack is directed.     This will increase.     To counterthis attack;., which is launched from the wide areas of enemyoccupied territory, we have to &quot;build up an air force of muchgreater size than at present0      This force will leave little airspace available for training purposes, and it may well he thathy 1942 operational flying and operational training will occupy the whole air space available in this country.      That is a longerview that I have taken hitherto? andy I hope, may not he provedcorrect in the event;    hut the trend is there and is unescapahleif we are to deploy our full resources against the enemy022nd August, 1940,,(Int0 )   Ao.H*M*S.




</content>
</cab>
