<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/18/36 images: 346-353</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.)COPY NO.O &apos;   .. , WAR    CABINET.&apos;&quot;,      &quot;.&apos;    Detention of a Member of Parliament under Defence -&apos;Regulation 18B.Should a-&apos;Member of Parliament.-be given a&apos; rlp;ht to have his caseexamined by-a &quot;Committee &apos;of - the&apos; House? &quot;&apos;Memorandum by . the Home Secretary.Some-,Members of parliament have, represented to me&apos; that whilethe several discussions and- Parliamentary statements on the \ subjectof&apos; Defence Regulation l8B have disposed of most.of the -doubts and difficulties.-felt by the House with regard to this Regulation, thereis&apos;still a strong feeling that if a Member is detained under this regulation he should be given a right to have his case investigated by a Committee of the House rather than by the existing AdvisoryCommittee.    Much importance of course-attaches to the principle,--that Members of Parliament should be protected against any risk: ofarbitra-r-y action by the Executive Government,, but in my&apos; view&apos; thisproposal must be rejected for the following reasons;-1.     By,&apos;.accepting&apos;. the &apos; report of the Committee of Privileges on thecase of Captain Ramsay, the Hou.se of -Commons has recognised that the privileges of a Member/of Parliament&apos;.do not entitle him to immunity from arrest and detention under Defence Regulation 18B-.&apos; - They&apos;have therefore: no cognised that it-is the duty of. the Home ; Secretary &quot;to.use the regulation against .:a Member of -parliament -in-the same ,njay:as he &quot;would use it against a-nyone else, if &quot;detention is- necessaryfor purposes,-of public security.,    It follows-that the Home Secretaryexorcising., of course,  great care and.-, judgment,&apos; must take-the,responsibility for deciding.whether a Member of Parliament who hasbeen&apos;&apos;detained shall remain- in&apos;detention after his case&apos;has been investigated by a Committee of enquiry in the manner provided for ...in the Regulation. &quot;The .suggestion - of the- Members of Parliament who have-made.  , ..- -representations to me/is that the case of any Member who is detaineeshould be . investigated by a Committee-of the&apos;- Ho^e which would present a report giving advice-to the -Home.-Sec- . cary,. but that theresponsibility for coming, to a decision on that report&apos; should stillrest on &quot;the.Homo Secretary. -&quot;To place, the Homo Secretary in. the position in which it may be his duty to reject the advice of a Committee-of the House ofCommons would- create most serious difficulties.    Ministers are-answerable to.-the House for their actions, and if the Home     ere tar 2were to reject the advice of a Committee of the House of Commons,he could not resist 2 demand that he should explain his reason tothe House and accept the right of the House to debate the case.Such a debate might take place in secret session, but it would
necessitate a full disclosure to the House of the Home Secretaryiginformation, however confidential that information might be.Under the present system the Home Secretary is not under any obligation to tell the House what is the effect of the report ofthe Advisory Committee in any particular case.    He is required by paragraph 6 of Regulation 18B to make a monthly report toParliament as to the action taken under the Regulation and &quot;as tothe number of cases, if any, in which he has declined to follow the advice of&quot; the Advisory Committee;    but he is not required to specify by name the individuals with regard to whom he has rejected the advice of the Advisory Committee, and it is not the practice to give such information.If however the case of a Member of Parliament wereinvestigated by a Committee of the House of Commons, it would beimpossible for the Home Secretary to decline to tell the Housewhether his decision on the case was or was not in accordancewith the advice tendered to him by the Committee, and if he wereto inform the House that he had rejected the advice of theCommittee of the House it would be incumbent upon him to explain to the House why he had come to a conclusion different from thatof a Committee representing the House.   For the Home Secretary to reject the advice of such a Committee without giving the House anopportunity of debate and without setting before the House full information as to the reasons for his decision would be inconsistent with the constitutional relation of a Minister toParliament.2.     It was represented to   me   th&quot;t   a   Committee ofthe House would take a judicial view of such cases, and that thecompetence and suitability of such a Committee was illustrated bythe recent Committee on the case of Mr. Boothby.    Comparison withthe Boothby Committee however, seems to me entirely mistaken.   Thequestion which the Boothby Committee had to decide was.whether theconduct of the Member transgressed the standards expected ofMembers of. Parliament.    This is a question for Parliament itselfto decide.   The question whether the detention of an individual isnecessary for the security of the State is an entirely differentproblem.    The decision in such a case ought to be taken by theMinister who is charged with the responsibility for internal security.   For the purpose of exercising that responsibility theMinister must obtain information from the police and the security services which is often highly confidential and the action taken as a result of such information cannot properly be made the subjectof Parliamentary discussion.3.     There is a further consideration that the appointment of aspecial tribunal to investigate the case of any Member ofParliament who is detained under Regulation 18B must give rise tothe suggestion that the existing Advisory Committee is not a completely satisfactory body.    The necessary inference from theappointment of such a special tribunal would be that Parliamentregards the existing Advisory Committee as a sufficient protectionwhen the liberty of an ordinary member of the public is at stakebut as not sufficient when the liberty of a Member of parliament is at stake.    If it is admitted that the existing AdvisoryCommittee is not a satisfactory body to deal with every type of case, it would be extremely hard to resist the argument that it is
not a satisfactory body to deal with any typo of case involving the liberty of the subject.    In this connection attention nay bocalled to a reply by the Prime Minister to a parliamentary question on the 21st January, 1941.    A copy of the Question and answer is attached.4.      It is no doubt arguable that in time of war, if in someacute emergency political controversy became extremely tense, a minister might abuse the power conferred upon him by Regulationl8B, and that if the Government wore in danger from some powerfulpolitical opponent, he might come to the conclusion that the detention of such political opponent was neces^ry under Regulationl8B on grounds of national security, when in ,uct the motive waspreservation of the Government&apos;s position rather than the safety of the State.    If, however,  such a situation should ever arise,it is doubtful whether investigation of the case by a Committee ofthe House of Commons would in fact act as a corrective to anysuch misuse of power.    In such a situation it is to be expectedthat political passions would be strong on the Committee, andthere is no reason to suppose that such a Committee would belikely to take a more judicial   view than the Minister.5.     Jt must be remembered that this question affects the positionnot only of Members- of the House of Commons, but also of Membersof the House of Lords, and that if the proposition were admitted that the case of a detained Member of Parliament should go before a Committee of the House of Commons it would follow that the caseof a detained Peer should go before a Committee of the House ofLords.6.      The position of Members of the Parliament of NorthernIreland must also be considered.    The Government of Ireland Act,1920, conferred on Members of the. Parliament of Northern Irelandthe same privileges as are possessed by Members of the british parliament.    At the present time Mr.  Cahir Healy, a Member of theHouse of Commons of Northern Ireland, Is detained under Regulation.18B.    If it were agreed that a Member of the United kingdom parliament should be entitled to have his case investigated by aCommittee of that Parliament, the question would arise whether aMember of the Northern Ireland Parliament should not be entitledto have his case investigated by a Committee of that Parliamentjbut no one, I imagine, would hold that a Comrai&apos;-&apos; eo of the House&apos;of Commons in Northern Ireland is a suitable ...to investigatesuch a case as that of Mr. Cahir Healy or to give advice on sucha case to the Home Secretary.H.M.HOME OFFICE.4th September, 1941.

Extract f,?om Parliamentary DebatesTuesday.  21st January.  1941.Defence Regulation 18B(Members of Parliament)Mr. MANDER asked the Prime Minister whether hewill consider making immediate arrangements to securethat, in the event of any further hon. Mer..jer &quot;beingdetained under Regulation 1833, the Advisory Committeeto consider his case shall he composed of hiscolleagues of this House, with a view to safeguardinghim against any possible misuse of the powers conferred?THE PRIME MINISTER:    I am most anxious that thereshall be full safeguards against any possible abuse of these powers, not only in the exceptional case ofa Member of Parliament, but in every case where a citizen is detained under this Regulation,  and i cannot accept the suggestion that the existing proceduredoes not provide adequate safeguards.




</content>
</cab>
