<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/175/1 images: 6-12</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT71C(74) 1 COPY no cabinet the QUEEN&apos;S SPEECH ON THE OPENING OF parliament note by the Lord President&quot; of the council I attach for the consideration of my colleagues a draft of The Queen&apos;sSpeech on the Opening of Parliament, as approved by The Queen&apos;s speech and Future Legislation Committee,E privy Council Office6 March 1974\
DRAFT QUEEFS SPEECH Oil THE OPEMIHG OF PARLIAMENTM LORDS AM) MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF commons.     The continuing grave situation created &quot;by the interruption of fuel supplies has required that I proclaimed a state of emergency under theEmergency Powers Act 1920 to enable My Ministers to take the steps necessary to maintain supplies and services which are essential to the life of the community.2.    My Husband and I look forward with pleasure to our visits to indonesia and Japan and to the State Visit which Her Majesty Queen Margrethe of denmark will pay to this country.3.     My Government will work for the strengthening of international institutions and of co-operation between all countries concerned to promotepeace and prosperity through the world.   They will attach particular importance to the work of the United Mations and its agencies and to co-operation within the Commonwealth.4.     My Government will seek major changes in the policies of theEuropean Community, in particular in the Common Agricultural Policy andin the method of financing the Community budget.   After these negotiations have been completed, the results will be put to the British people so that,if their consent is forthcoming, this country can play a full part in anew and wider Europe.5.    Recognising the economic problems concerning the developing countriesMy Government will seek to increase the provision of aid and to establish a more liberal pattern of world trade.6.     My Government will give their support to the search for a just and lasting peace in the Middle East, based on the implementation of security Council Resolution 242 of 19&amp;7.7,     Recognising that the availability and the price of oil is a problem for the whole world, My Government will co-operate with consumer andproducer countries in seeking to establish arrangements which will be inthe interests of all.
8.     My Government will oppose all forms of racial discrimination.    in rhodesia they will agree to no settlement which is not supported by the african majority.9.     My Government will give full support to the maintenance of the WorthAtlantic Alliance,   They will regard the North Atlantic Treaty organisation as an instrument of detente no less than of defence.   In consultation withtheir allies they will pursue a policy directed to maintaining a modernand effective defence system while reducing its cost as a proportion ofour national resources.10.     My Ministers will contribute fully to the negotiations for forcereductions in Central Europe and to the Conference on Security andCo-operation in Europe.11,    My Ministers will give their support to the constitutional arrangements which offer to Northern Ireland the prospect of healing its political and social divisions and of achieving prosperity and security for all its people.   They will play their part, together with the NorthernIreland Executive and the Government of the Republic of Ireland, in developing co-operation in matters of mutual interest and in bringingviolence to an end.MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS12.    Estimates for the public service will be laid before you,MY LORDS AND MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS13.     In home affairs, My Government will first seek to ensure a returnto full-time working in industry.   They will give the highest priority toovercoming the economic difficulties created by rising prices, the balanceof payments deficit and the recent dislocation of production.14.     Steps will be taken to establish fair prices for certain key foods,with the use of subsidies where appropriate; and to restrain priceinflation.2
15.     My Government is taking immediate steps to halt the increases inrents due in 1974*   They will bring forward comprehensive proposals, whichwill require the repeal of the Housing Finance Act, to reform the law relating to rents and housing subsidies.   Urgent measures will he taken to reverse the fall in housebuilding, to protect furnished tenants fromeviction and to encourage municipal ownership.   Proposals will be preparedfor bringing land required for development into public ownership.&quot;i&amp;i-lly Government will bring furward comprehensive proposals to roform Lhe law relating to housing and rents. They will seek to reverse thedecline in housebuilding, to stabilise the cost of housing and to increasethe availability of land for dovolopmont.lj&amp;     My Ministers will work for a greater measure of social justice as aprerequisite of national unity at this difficult time.   Legislation willbe brought forward to increase social security benefits for the retired,widows, the long-term sick and the unemployed.   Proposals will be put before you for the redistribution of wealth and the protection of thelower paid and the disadvantaged.   A review will be instituted of improvedmethods of meeting the needs of the disabled.l^f.     In the light of these measures, My Ministers will discuss urgently,with the Trades Union Congress, the Confederation of British Industry andthe others concerned, methods of securing the orderly growth of incomeswhich will command the willing acceptance of all concerned.1$.     My Ministers will hold urgent consultations on measures to encourage the development and re-equipment of industry.   A Bill will be laid before you to consolidate and develop existing legislation to promote national industrial expansion.   High priority will be given to the stimulation of regional development, and new machinery will be established for thispurpose.   They will develop an active manpower policy, with a powerfulNational Labour Board.3
My Ministers will set in hand urgent action to improve energy supplies,to secure their efficient use and to ensure that oil and gas from theContinental Shelf are exploited in ways and on terms which will confermaximum benefit on the community, and particularly on those areas whosetraditional industries have declined,   A commission will be established atonce to examine and report urgently on the future of the coal industry,2D.     Measures will be introduced to repeal the Industrial Relations Actand to replace it by new legislation which will include the establishmentof a new conciliation and arbitration service.2^.     Legislation will be introduced to reform and extend the law relatingto consumer credit; and a measure will be laid before you requiring goods to be labelled with the price at which they are to be sold, and where appropriate with the unit price.2$/    Proposals will be laid before you to reform the law relating toguardianship and adoption.2.%%     Within available resources My Government will aim for progressiveimprovement in the social services.   The National Health Service will be expanded and its organisation improved; and there will be an immediatereview of the reorganisation due to take effect in April 1974*2j5p    Plans will be prepared for the introduction of a national scheme ofnursery schools and for the ending of selection for secondary education.High priority will be given to improving educational facilities for children in need of special help; and a major review will be made of theparticular needs of handicapped children.2^T    Museum charges will be abolished.2^?.     My Ministers will work for the protection and improvement of the environment including the improvement of public transport, and will re-appraise accordingly the value of certain major development projects.4
2jp.     My Ministers will initiate discussions with all concerned in Scotlandand Wales on the Report of the Royal Commission on the Constitution, andwill Taring forward proposals for consideration and discussion.   [They will undertake a review of the organisation and public accountability of regional Authorities in England.-]2$.     My Ministers will make proposals for conferring equal status on my LORDS AMD MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE Off COMMOMB3$.     I pray that the blessing of Almighty God may rest upon your counsels.women.Other measures will be laid before you.5


</content>
</cab>
