<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/117/0 images: 198-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 This document is  the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.----   13()SECRET.t 4THE  CABINET.REFUGEES  FROM  THE  CRIMEA.9861      MEMORANDUM  BY THE SECRETARY  OF STATE  FOR ,WAR.    I  circulate  herewith  a letter from the General  Officer  Commanding-in-Chief,___jjjf9the Army  of  the  Black  Sea on  the  situation  as regards the Russian  refugees atConstantinople.                                                                     w. s. c.    THE WAK OFFICE,       13th December, 1920.To the Secretary, the War Office,    I beg to forward this report on the Russian  refugee situation at Constantinople,for the information of the Secretary of State for War.  Soon after my arrival here on 7th November the situation in the Crimea became  steadily worse, and the  information received from our Intelligence Group there showed that the end was approaching.    The first request was for accommodation for 80,000 refugees and 2,000 wounded,which was notified home by Admiral de Robeck, who was then High Commissioner.    The policy of the British Government was conveyed to me by him.    Circumstances which I will relate have occurred since then which  have  made itincumbent on me to take certain action in the cause of humanity, and for the protectionof the force under my command, and of the British inhabitants.  I accept full responsi-bility for my action.    While recognizing fully that  the  responsibility  rested with the French, it soonbecame evident to me that the problem was beyond any organization which they couldpossess  here.   Ship after ship absolutely crammed kept passing my house.  They were all sent to Moda  Bay, and anchored off 28th  Divisional Headquarters.   About 65 to70 ships soon collected, some carrying up to  8  or 10,000, without food or water, the refugees and troops standing day and night without any sanitary arrangements.  Therewere no deck awnings.   The 28th Divisional  Headquarters reported  to  me that the scene was  indescribable, and  that their  forced  inaction was mor^ than British soldierscould bear.   I immediately approved their desire to give hot soup to the nearest ships.I went  myself amongst the ships to see the conditions, a sight I pan never forget.   AsI described it in one of my  reports&apos; a &quot; starving mass of humanity.&quot;   I decided atonce, with Admiral cle Robeck,  that we must  act as England would expect us to act,but that in order  not to depart from the policy of the Government, we should devoteour efforts to helping our French Allies to compete with their almost impossible task.We  set our  bakeries, &amp;c, going, and I am glad to say that we have been able to meetevery demand  the  French  have  made  on  us  so  far all  transfers  of  food,, tents,.blankets, &amp;c, being recorded.  We have also transferred to the French vacant hospitals,barracks and  camps.     With regard  to private effort, a British Russian Relief Fund was started at once,.and  as its President  I  should  like to record  my deep appreciation of the  response.Some  2,500/. has so far been collected, and as an instance of  how intensely the men ofthe Services  feel for  those  in distress  before  their  eyes I , should like to record thegenerous donation of 300/. from the ships&apos; companies of H.M.S. &quot; Benbow &quot; and H.M.S.&quot; Centurion &quot; alone.   &apos; The  28th Division  have done  yeoman service in succouring three large shipsanchored  alongside their  headquarters with hot  food,  &amp;c, and  the  ready helpers British men and women who are hourly getting off the children to  bathe and clothethem, deserve every credit.  I have no  hesitation  in saying they are  averting disease and saving life. .     When I  wired home to the  Chief of the  Imperial General Staff  for help I  canhonestly say  that I was very seriously concerned.  The picture before me  was beyond     (B20/.U1) 100  m/20 H&amp;S, Ltd. 8811WO
description, and literally thousands were being landed.  The majority are covered withlice and vermin, and it seemed to me that nothing but a  miracle could save us from aserious- epidemic.    With the  small  force  at  my  disposal, and the situation distinctlydelicate, I was very much concerned for the protection of my force.     If disease should break out amongst my troops, I should in a short time be in avery serious position.     I  am more grateful  than I can  say for  the  generous help-of  20,000^. from theBritish Government.   It has not only disarmed the  rather  unpleasant  propaganda which  has been spread as regards our refusal of help and brutality, but it has enabled us to co-ordinate our efforts into a practical scheme.        *     The French are struggling manfully with an almost  impossible task.   They asked us to take 10,000 into a camp at Tuzla.  I agreed to take 2,000, which I  have done,and I have established a camp in some vacant huts and tents under Colonel Walshe and officers of his Intelligence Group who  were  in the  Crimea.   Baths  and  disinfectingplant exist and I am pleased to say that the whole arrangement is working  well.     In the 2,000 landed I  found  a majority  of soldiers.  By arrangement with theFrench I have had these moved in order to conform exactly to the policy of the BritishGovernment and the camp now consists  of women and  children  and the husbands  ofthese women.   The British effort is  thus  concentrated  on this camp.   If I have  toextend the camp, which I  do not want to do,  it can  be arranged.   All the clothesmade and the  money collected go  to maintain this camp.  The only other organizationwe assist is the hospital established at the  Russian  Embassy.   This was in extremis.As was to be  expected the Russians  who landed  flocked to the Embassy.    I havehelped to equip this hospital which is  under  Baroness  Wrangel.    It  was a horriblesight to see these wretched people concentrating at the Embassy literally starving.     I  have cancelled all other British effort to ships, &amp;c.,  and  have concentrated uponTuzla Camp and the Russian Embassy hospital, and  I am glad to report that the wholeof our  arrangements are now on a satisfactory  basis.     I  preside, myself, over the Relief Fund meetings and I allow no  money to be spentexcept with my approval on the recommendation  of  my  Finance  Committee.  There isno danger whatever of any money being deflected for any purpose except real relief.     The French are  extremely  grateful for  the help  we have  given them and theRussian authorities  have expressed to me their deep appreciation.     I  do not know  what the future will be.   The Russian Admiral tells me  that it  ishoped  to clear the ships from Moda Bay in  about  a  week and the programme I havebeen given shows that it is proposed to send elsewhere all except 10,000 refugees and7,000 wounded.  I  hope this may be done but I doubt it.  The  streets of Constanti-nople are crowded with Russians all without money.     So far we  have been extraordinarily lucky as regards disease.  I  hear  there are many cases of typhus from one ship which went to Mudros.   In so far as  I  know thecases of plague, typhus,  and smallpox  landed here have been small, but we are by nomeans  out of the wood yet.     The situation has been a difficult one but I must place it on record that the Britishhere, both men and women, have done their utmost,  and I  speak for all when I saythat we are deeply grateful to the British  Government for the gift which  has enabled us to act as Britons always have  acted in the  cause of humanity,     Nothing we have done or  will do can be interpreted  in any way as counter to thepolicy  of  His Majesty&apos;s  Government and, I think I  can now say  that,  thanks  tothe help I have received on all sides,  the British flag has in no way been lowrered in thecause of humanity.                                            C. H. HARINGTON, Lieut-General,                     General  Officer Commanding-in-Chief, Army of the Black Sea.

</content>
</cab>
