<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/117/0 images: 231-232</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOvSmSBT 13 ?1S PROPERTY OP HIS BHIXaHBIC MAJESTY1 S OOTOHiSHf)BSC RJ3 -                               Copy No,Oo P. r  338.USS 0? CAL^D H^RIgGS FOR AUSTRIAN RELIEF.   So to by the Chancellor of tho Exchequer.     (Reference - Cabinet Minutes 72(20)               section 4 (d)).         I circulate Sir *.Y0 Goods1 s reply to my instructions that   our stock of salted. (Scotch and English) Herrings was to be   used for Austrian Relief.         It is disappointing to find that even Chinese bacon is   better appreciated than these herrings.                             (Initialled)    A.O. -TREASURY, 3.W.  .   18th December, 1920.     With regard to lord Lee&apos;s letter of the 10th DecemberI have endeavoured for some time past to find a market for united Kingdom herrings but without success.   The people ofAustria are not accustomed to salted herrings and if they werebought by the Austrian Government out of British credits theywould probably become a total loss on the hands of the austrian government, with no resulting benefit to anyone.   The norwegian government are in exactly the same position.  They have largequantities of herrings which they are willing to dispose of atalmost any price through the International Committee for ReliefCredits.  Mr. Gorvin, Secretary of this Committee, tells me that so far as he lias been unable to dispose on&apos; credit either ofBritish or Norwegian herrings on any terms&apos; to Austria&quot;, Poland orany other country.  The Danish Government have opened a credit for 800,000 Danish Kronen in favour of Austria for the purchase                                                        of
 i                      1      &apos;                                - ^ 152                                   *    of dried fish, and fish products,  and the representative of the    Austrian Government on the International Committee for Reliefd  Credits has written to the Danish representative stating that the    dried fish could not find any market in Austria and requesting    that the Banish credit should be applied for the purchase of    cattle for slaughter.   The only markets in which we should be at    all likely to dispose of herrings to the benefit of the borrowing    country would be Russia, Germany and possihly the Baltic States.    As you know, none of these countries are at present entitled to    British Relief Credits.                                  WILLIAM GOODS*                                        17.12.SO.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.    20th December, 19 20.

</content>
</cab>
