<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/117/0 images: 335-350</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
P-K&apos;1 Mlit)3     Ho Weekly Report will be  issued  on  Thursday,30th Deoember, but any natter  of importance  occurringbefore January 6th will be specially  reported.
)ort No. 86         DIRECTORATE OP INTELLIGENCE                (Home Office)                             Scotland House,  S.W.I.                               83rd Deoember,  1920REPORT ON REVOLUTIONARY ORGANISATIONS         IN THE UNITED KINGDOM-----------------0O0----------------- (Circulated by the Home Seoretary)UNEMPLOYMENT .......................................  Page  1THE COMMUNISTS .....................................   M    4RUSSIAN DICTATORSHIP IN EJ&amp;LAND....................   &quot;    6THE CO-OPERATIVE &amp; LABOUR MOVEMENTS................   &quot;    7&quot;HANDS OPF INDIA&quot;..................................   &quot;    8THE INTERNATIONAL UNION OF EX-SSRVICE MEN..........   &quot;   10THE POSTAL WORKERS.................................   &quot;   10THE &quot;DAILY HERALD&quot;.................................   f   10A BATTERSEA OUTRAGE................................   &quot;   11SINN FEIN IN GREAT BRITAIN........................   &quot;   11IRELAND...........................................   &quot;   13SUMMARY       Unemployment is still growing and discontent is becoming very  serious.  The doctrine of olass hatred, which in normal times has  few adherents in this country,  is now taking root under the  persistent teaching of agitators and the Socialist Press.   The  London Council of Unemployed Organisations has whipped up  the  moribund Council of Action into some appearance of life.  TheyI  pretend to regard the re-opening of trade with Russia as the  only  panacea for unemployment.       Interesting figures are given of the unemployment register  in Lancashire.       The &quot;Unity&quot; Communist Conference,  which is to take place in  January, will probably be held  at Leeds.  The City of London  Branch  of the Communist Party is arranging a farewell dinner to Malone.       Walton Newbold thought it  necessary to obtain permission from  Moscow to stand as a Labour Party candidate.       Francis Meynell has been offered the editorship of the  &quot;Communist&quot;.  This paper can only be financed from Russia.       A &quot;Bands off India&quot; movement has been started on lines similar  to those of the &quot;Hands off Russia&quot; Committee.       There are negotiations for the fusion of the General  Woikers1  Unions.   If they come to anything, the  Union will be the largest in  the world,  with a membership of over 1,300,000.       45,000 miners in the Rhondda Valley have struck to enforce the  reinstatement of twelve men who were dismissed by the Ocean Coal  Company.
     Unemployment  continues to  increase  steadily; according to the  &quot;Daily Herald&quot;  over one  million are now  out of work and  their  dependents total over three millions; distress is acute and feoling is becoming very bitter, especially as the  Christmas season accentuates the  difference between rich and poor.  This fact has been cleverly exploited by the  &quot;Daily Herald&quot; which, has done its, host to foster class hatred  by  publishing in alternate paragraphs notices relating to the actions and extravagant  purchases of the rich and details of cases of hardship among the unemployed.     On December 81st  a deputation representing the London  District Council of Unemployed Organisations met Messrs. F. Bramley and J.]?. Middleton, joint secretaries of tho  Council of Action, and  brought before them the necessity  of trading relations  being resumed -with Russia as the  chief  means of alleviating  the prevailing and increasing unemployment in the country. &quot;According  to an official report great stress was laid  on the large Russian contracts for all kinds of agricultural, engineering, leather, and other products,  falsely  alleged to have been secured by Mr.-Vanderlip, on behalf of an American syndicate, and the growing; unrest exhibited by the unemployed in London and  . elsewhere was urged as an imperative reason for the Council to consider what direct or other action  organised Labour might take to bring to a successful issue the prolonged : negotiations between: representatives of  the Government and Krassin.  The deputation was-informed that the full Council of Action would meet to-day to review the situation in the light of the debate: in/the House of Commons on the trade agreement.  In the meantime arrangements have been made for the representatives of -the London Unemployed Council&apos; tomeet the officials of the Parliamentary Labour Party before
 before the  debate takes place.     The labour Party has put forward a scheme under which each unemployed person would receive a maintenance grant of  2 per week.  The &quot;Daily Herald&quot; supports this policy and supplements it with the advice  &quot;Go to the Guardians&quot;, adding that &quot;what  Parliament end the Government wm&apos;t do, Poor Law Guardians must do, and will do, if organised Labour and the unemployed  will but stand together and compel them to carry out the law.&quot;  This mischievous advice, which it is claimed explains to the unemployed &quot;their legal rights&quot; has been printed in  leaflet form and is being distributed free.     There  is further evidence to show that the seizures of buildings in London have been the work of an organised gang of revolutionaries and that, if opportunity occur, they will use violence,  A former member of the Committee of the Unemployed  who seized Acton Baths, has given information to this effect and states that the chairman told him that they had deoided &quot;not to take any distress relief, but to commit damage.&quot;  Petrol has been purchased and  9 spent for implement for protection.     On December 17th about 200 of the genuine unemployed at Ponder-s End took possession of St. James1  Parish Hall, but subsequently acoepted an offer of two rooms at the Carnegie Library, Enfield Highway, in order to conduct their business.     On the same day 32 men (who termed themselves ex-Servioflmen) two women and eight children took possession of anunoocupied house of four rooms in Southward; the seizure was organised from &quot;Poverty Hall&quot;,  Walworth.     Some 300 unemployed men,  under the leadership ofStraohan, the seoretary of the looal branch of the NationalUnion of Ex-Service  Men, seized the Town Hall at Stratfordon December 20th;  the Mayor now appears to have granted the                                                     men/
                            M 3 **                           Applicants             VacanciesJoiners                        92                    330Bricklayers                    13                    897plasterers                      8                     60Painters                     1541                     22Plumbers                      190                     21Shipwrights                    14                     33Patternmakers                  16                     21Moulders                      145                    547Turners                       918                      4Engineers&apos; fitters           2543                     20Metal mechanics               982                     13Coaohmakers                    18                    119Cabinet-makers                 69                      1                       Semi- and Unskilled                           Applicants             VacanciesLabourers in shipyards        2236                     general engineers&apos;      labourers               2261                     4Clerks, General                974                    47Carmen &amp; Carters              2227                     6Steam lorry drivers            109                     0Motor van drivers              828                     general labourers,         heavy                7373                    19   w    labourers, light      2693                     1                                                  The/                                         i           men the use of the Hall from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. eaoh day.     From the provinces come reports of increasing unemployment and unrest and my correspondents state thatthe communists are particularly aotive;  they urge that theemployers are responsible for unemployment and that the onlyoure is the overthrow of capitalism.  &quot;Ca&apos;canny&quot; has been urged by Robert Williams in South Wales, on the familiarand false premise that the less each worker does, the moreworkers will be required.  In Birmingham the extremists have again proved that they are averse to the creation of work byrelief schemes, preferring to foment disoontent whioh they hope will lead to revolution.  In Lancashire short time is causing much distress, as the weavers are in some cases earningonly one-eighth of their customary wage;  the following tableconveys a good idea of the present supply and demand for labour in Lancashire and Cheshire; the figures relating tojoiners and brioklayers are particularly instructive, inview of the position taken up by the Building Trade Union:                            Skilled
          The imempl^ymorrt grant is considered inadequate in     this area and a demand has been made for 30/-;  it is urged     that it would be much better for the money to be disbursed     at the mills.  In a queue at Silverwell Street  Exchange,     Bolton, last week, eighteen,people fainted from exposure.     The majority of the Lancashire unemployed infinitely prefer     work to maintenance.          Speaking to an audience of about- 150 at Glasgow Green  l     on December 19th, &quot;Sandy&quot; Ross dealt with the unemployment  !     question.  Re said that he and MacLean advised those out ofI     work to go in for housebreaking, and take forcible         j     possession of the necessaries of life.  They were not going     to stand by and see women and children die of starvation     whilst there was food and clothing to be had.  They were     going to have it by any means in their power.  Lloyd George     said he was going to have dilution of labour in the     housebuilding trade, well, he was ^oing to have dilution     in the &quot;housebreaking&quot; trade.THE COIJOTISTS          As a result of the Manchester Conference, which as     stated in my last report was attended by only about twelve     people, a manifesto has been issued over the signatures of     A. MacManus and A.  Inkpin (Communist Party of Great Britain)     J.V. Leokie and John McLean (Communist Labour Party),     R. Beech and T. Watkins (Communist Party, British Section     of the Third International).  The manifesto states that the     above named parties, together with the,National Shop     Stewards&apos; and Workers1 Committee  &quot;in a consultative     capacity&quot; and the Left Wing ,of the  Independent Labour     Party &quot;in an, informative capacity&quot;, have assented to the     proposal for the formation of a united communist party.     They will participate in a &quot;National Convention&quot;, which                                                         will/
will probably &quot;be-hold in Leeds on January 29th and 30th.  Itis possible that if anything tangible results from this meeting,the Socialist Labour Party will join forces.     A circular letter has been sent out from the headquarters of the Communist Party of Great Britain directing all members,and particularly shop stewards, to spread communist doctrinesceaselessly among the unemployed, into whom it was to be&quot;drummed&quot;- that, communism- and the control of industry by theworkers were their only salvation.  It is of interest to note that Dingley and Emery, who are living in the same house in coventry, were in London last week to consult with the shop stewards&apos; and Workers&apos; Committee as to the best means ofobtaining control of workshops and factories.     Francis Meynell has been asked by the Editorial Committeeof the Communist Party of Great Britain to take over the editor-ship of &quot;The Communist&quot;; there is no doubt that if any part ofthe  75,000 had been rescued from the clutches of the &quot;daily herald&quot;, the party would welcome him and it with open arms; in coventry the rumour is current that he holds a large sum ofRussian money which is to be devoted to oommunist propaganda.     Dinners are apparently to become a feature of Londoncommunist life; on January 3rd the City branch of the CommunistParty of Great Britain will hold &quot;a dinner and social&quot; at theShaftesbury Hotel, to bid farewell to Comrade Malone, &quot;prior tothe hearing of his case.&apos;1  There is little doubt, in view of thedesire to send the Prime Minister to prison, that had this beenthe expression of any but a communist, it would have been&quot;contempt of court&quot;.  Malone&apos;s speeoh on unemployment in the Houseof Commons is being hawked at extremist meetings and the proceedsare to be devoted to defraying the&apos; cost of his appeal.&apos;&apos;.&quot;:     Aocording to the &quot;Daily Herald&quot; upwards of  21 has been                                                  collected/
oolleoted for the support of  Harvey&apos;s  and Steel&apos;s dependentstthe Communist Party of Great Britain has granted a further sum of  10.     It is doubtful if there has ever been a smaller meeting in Trafalgar Square than when thirty people assembled inpouring rain to hear Colonna, of the International CommunistFederation on December 19th.  When the first speaker mountedthe plinth, the audience consisted of three of his friends;Colonna expressed dissatisfaction with the proceeds which amounted to 3s. Id.RUSSIAN DICTATORSHIP IN ENGLAND     The astonishing influence of Russia on Britishrevolutionaries is revealed in a letter from Walton Newboldto &quot;Forward&quot;; he writes &quot;I myself took opinion on thefitness of my accepting an invitation to stand as a LabourParty candidate and was informed by the representativeof the Third International that there was no objection.Otherwise I should not have accepted.&quot;  Other passages ofthis letter indicate the extent  to which Newbold has absorbedthe teaching of his Russian masters:          &quot;We are no longer operating in the days of archers,     pikemen or even musketeers.  War - civil war - is     possible for the infinitesimal minority disciplined and     equipped with, and aocustomed to use, hand-grenades,     machine-guns, armoured-cars, tanks, gas-outfits, fire-   *  jets and aeroplanes.          &quot;I say  it is political cowardice, to dodge the       question  of preparing to use force because your now       applauding publio would then dissent.  To knw that       you will  one day need to fight, and meanwhile to seek       popularity by postponing the advocacy of a disagree- &quot;       able  necessity,  is  the  opportunism  of the mob-orator       of a  moment, not the enduring vision of a  statesman.       It is not illegal to prepare your people by  an       equivalent  organisation  of physical  training,       elucidation in  mass action/ and  intelligent  initiative       such  as  was put into effect by the  Boy  Scout and       similar  movements long before the war to facilitate       the transformation  of  civilian recruits  into a future       Kitchener&apos;s Army.   The  basis  of  the&quot;, Bed  Army training       is  in the athletic  clubs  of  Soviet  Russia.   Physical       training and workshop  discipline  are amongst thepreliminaries/
     preliminaries for the eventual  organising  of  an  army     to defend the workers1  Parliamentary (or any  other)     majority.&quot;     In a pertinent reply to this  letter,  Shinwell, who can scarcely be classed among the moderates,  writes:          &quot;It is well-known that the majority of the     communist bodies are opposed to Parliamentary action.     Those who are not so opposed are,  as Newbold     pathetically admits, ol&amp;y in the hands of  the Third     International potters.          &quot;May I ask if, now that the Third has endorsed     his oandidature, if this implies financial responsibility?          &quot;Obviously, if an infinitesimal minority can     inspire counter-revolution and  use modern  weapons of     warfare against a Labour Government, an unscrupulous     Capitalist minority supported by an  overwhelming anti-     Socialist majority would make short  work of Field-Marshal     Walton Hewbold and his provisional comrades.   Even a     know lodge of military tactics derived in  the  course of     comradoly conversation in the comfortable  cafe*s  of     Manchester or Glasgow would be  of  no avail.&quot;TBS CO-OPERATIVE &amp;  LABOUR  MOVEMENTS     On December 18th a joint oonferenoe of representativesof the London Trades Council, trade unions and co-operative societies diisoussod the erection of a &quot;Labour Temple&quot; whiohwould house trade unions with headquarters in London andserve as a central trading dep6t for the metropolitan co-operativs societies^  The proposed building, in addition tothe office and etcre accommodation, would contain a centrallibrary, statistical and information bureau, central office accommodation for smaller bodies, club-rooms, board-rooms,meeting rooms and largo and small halls.  Alfred Btj:nes, chairmanof the London Co--operative Society, pointed out that it was proposed to oroct the Temple on the basis of loans from tradeunions at five per cent interest.  The loan would be guaranteed by the London Co-operative Society, which was in a very strongfinancia?. position.  Duncan Carmichael,  on behalf of the LondonTrades Council, promised that that&apos;body would invest  100 in                                                     the/
     the  scheme.   Delegates  of  the London  Society  of  Compositors,     announced  that a  subscription of  1,000 would  be  forthcoming,     The  meeting pledged  itself  to assist the  Co-operative     Movement in everyway possible, by trading at  Co-operative     Stores, by divesting their  savings from capitalist banks to     savings banks of  the Society., and by investing trade union fa     either in  local society  loan stock or  in  the Co-operative    &apos; Wholesale  Bank.          The Co-ppeiative Wholesale Society directors have been  I     obliged to modify their  attitude towards  the political seotic-     of the movement and they have decided  to  recommend a grant oi      1,000 to  the Co-operative.  Party for the  year  1920.   Facilitji     will be given for the holding of meetings in support of     Co-operative Parliamentary&apos;  candidates  at  Co-operative Wholes!     Society works during the dinner-hour,  and the  directors have     agreed to tho loan of vehicles for the use of  Co-operative     Parliamentary candiciates at elcotion times.          The recent quarterly meeting of the  Scottish Co-operatiJ     Wholesale Society decided after &quot;some  confusion&quot; by 285 to SI     votes to invost  1,000 in the &quot;Daily ReraldrT Limited; one     delegate stated that he had been instructed by his society top     ask if the investment  wore sound.                         /   I&quot;RANDS OFff INDIA&quot;  ..                                              I          On December 18th a meeting was held under the auspices  I     of the British Committee of the Indian National Congress at  I     Manchester; it was one of a series  which the Committee intend!     to hold throughout the country &quot;so  that the rank and file of  1     the  Labour movement may become informed of the  situation in  I     India&quot;.    Tho. underlying idea is apparently the initiation oil     a  &quot;Hands off India&quot;. movement on lines similar to that in sup?     of Russia.          The speakers  included Dr.  Robert Dunstan,  to. Bruce     Glasier,  Fenner Brockway, J.M,  Parikhand  B.G. Horniman;  the                                                      resolution/
resolution protested against &quot;the scandalous conditions ofpoverty under which millions of Indians are forced to live asthe result of exploitation &quot;by capitalist imperialism&quot; anddenounced the &quot;tyranny:&apos;  said to be exemplified in such legislation as theRowlatt Act, the Seditious Meetings Act,the Press Act, and by the horrors perpetrated under martial law.   It also declared the terms of the Turkish treaty to bea breach of faith with the Mussulmans of India: opposed therecommendations of the Army in India Committee, which, it was said,, had as their object &quot;the establishment for Imperialistpurposes of a large Indian Army, maintained and manned by theIndian people, but controlled by the British War Office&quot;,and. called for the withdrawal of Indian troops from mesopotamia.     Saklatvala put the Indian question in a form more likelyto arouse the interest of the British workers, to a Batterseameeting on December 16th.   Re said:          &quot;Supposing you take over workshops and factories,     the capitalists will still get their fat dividends,     because, they have their interests in the East from     which they can draw their 125$ and you will have to     go to them for your raw material, which they will     refuse and so bring you on your knees again, the only     way to fight these people, is by internationalising     the Trade Unions, so that when you refuse to work for     the Boards of Directors and all other legislative     powers, your brothers in the Sast will also refuse to     work for them, you could then ask your brethren of the     East to send the raw materials necessary end return  *     to them, those things which are necessary to thorn.     &quot;Xou have made many promises with regard to sending     representatives of your Unions to India, but like the     cotton workers of Lancashire you have always sent     them in the shape of the Lancashire Fusiliers and     obtained your cotton through their bullets, and at     the same time, the brothers and sisters of those     soldiers have had to go down on their hands and     knees to the bosses of the cotton mills for a job, so     that they may exist.   India, like Ireland, is  sick     end tired of Trade Union promises and is commencing     to act for themselves as the Irish have done.   The     English democrats and not the aristocrats are to     blame, it was the democrats who made the bullets used     by the soldiers, who are also democrats, at iunritsar.     The Black and Tans are not aristocrats.&quot;THE/
          In consequence of the ballot on strike policy, which     resulted in a majority of over 12,000 on a vote of .83,000,     the exeoutive has decided to collect weekly contributions to j                                                        *     the strike fund as from January 1st, 1921.   It is obvious,     from the tone of this week&apos;s &quot;Post&quot; that a strong minority lag     in violent opposition.and may decline to pay the weekly 6d.     The Editor also, finds it necessary to defend his support of tf     &quot;Daily Ferald&quot; and his conception of the functions of a trade     union journal. &apos;THE &quot;DAILY HERALD&quot;          The current issue of &quot;Freedom&quot;, the monthly gharchist     journal, contains the following comment in reference to     meetings held on November 29th and 30th: . &quot;we regret to say     that the 1 Daily Herald1  failed to publish our advertisements.     On November. 16th we paid for three advertisements, but only a     of them appeared on the  date promised,  end the third one nevei     appeared at .all.   They complain that advertisers are shy in     using the columns of the Herald.   Perhaps our experience     explains matters.&quot;                                                            A/THE INTJ5RNAT10MAL UNION OF    SERVICE jffig          This union is in a parlous condition; according to the     official report for the quarter ending October 31st, 1920,     the membership of the Glasgow branches has deoieased, the     literary secretaries in Edinburgh have appropriated funds     and left a deficit of  10.13.4d. in &quot;The Worker&quot; account,     Dundee has not paid any affiliation fees for six months,     Bristol is in debt and not all the London branches have paid I     their dues.   The total amount of affiliation fees received i     headquarters during the three months was  7. 7. 4d. and!     collections amounted to  27, 2. lid.   Although branch report     indicate a membership of 6,000&apos;, the total deficit was      27. 4. 9^d.THE POSTAL WORKERS
A 3ATTSRS5A 0133?RAGS          On December 18th a curious case of intimidation.     thought at first to be due to Sinn Fein, occurred at the     house of Mr. Thomas Brogan, residential engineer to Price&apos;s     Soap and Candle works, Battersea, President of the looal     seotion of the incient Order of Hibernians and Labour Mayor     of &quot;iattersea for 1912-1913.   Six masked and armed men, who     stated that they were -Sinn Feiners, oalled at his house     and demanded the keys of Priced factory T,so as to set fire     to itn.   They herded Mir.  Brogan&apos;s wife and three daughters     into the kitchen and searched the house for the keys and for     a private entrance to the factory.   Finding nothing, they   (     left without making any further demande and shook hands with     all the women at oarting.    They were evidently in possession     of information, which was at one time accurate, as the     entrance to the works from the house had been clocked in     1912 and in the same year, Mr.  Brogan -ceased to keep the     key.   As I:r. Brogan made himself conspicuous in raising     recruits during the war and is unpopular with extremists in    , the neighbourhood,  the outrage may have been an elaborate     hoax designed to frighten  him.SINN FEIN IN GR5AT BRITAIN          London Sinn Fein circles have been somewhat quieter, as     a result of the recent raids;  Irish Self-Determination     League meetings have,  however,  been held in Canning Town,     Silvertown and Clapham;  the Cork outrages were the chief     topic of disoussion and were openly attributed to the  Crown     Forces.          On December 29th  a special Labour Party Conference on     the Irish  situation will be held at the Central Hall,     Westminster,  under  the chairmanship of ./...G. Cameron.    The     private announcement of  this  conference is as follows:                                                          &quot;A/
     &quot;A report of the Party Deputation upon itsrecent visit to Ireland will be circulated, andresolutions, based on the following policy put forward by the Labour Party, in the House of Commons and approved by a special all-Ireland Trades Union andLabour Party Congress on November 16th, will besubmitted for discussion:-1.  Withdraw all the armed forces.2.  Place the responsibility for maintaining    order in each locality in Ireland (as in Gt.    Britain outside the Hetropolitan area) on the    Looal Authorities themselves: and3.  Provide for the immediate election, by    proportional representation of an entirely    open Constituent Assembly, charged to work out,    at the earliest possible moment, without    limitations or fetters, whatever Constitution    for Ireland the Irish people desire, subject    only to two conditions, that it affords    protection to minorities, and that the    Constitution should prevent Ireland from    becoming a military or naval menace to Gt.    Britain.&quot;     On December 19th fJU Jowett detailed his experiencesas a Labour delegate in  Ireland to an appreciative Leicesteraudience of about 500.   He stated that the allegationsagainst the Government had been anroly proved and describedcases which he said had  come to his personal knowledge.He added that the Labour Party intended to hold great meeting in the Albert Hall, to awaken the public to &quot;the fact ofIreland&apos;s crucifixion.&quot;   My correspondent reports that although the activities  of the Irish in the Midlands havehitherto been negligible, a few more meetings such as :&quot;   :u&quot;that addressed by Jowett and another at which 7&quot;.rs. ^nnanBryoe spoke, might bring about greater support for Sinn Fein     On December 19th J. Bromley was the chief speaker ata large Sheffield meeting; describing his recent visit toIreland he said that &quot;men placed in the position, of authorityof Ministers of the Crown are far and away lower than thebrute.&quot;     It is reported from Glasgow that the recent arrests                                            &apos;  prevented/
***&quot; 1 3 &quot;*  prevented the execution of a plan for reprisals  and  have  sobered the Sinn Fein element.   A branch  of the  Irish  Labour Party has been formed in Govan.LAMP       There v/as no material change in  the  state of the  Provinces during the week.  Outrages  still  continue  and  while there was a slight  decrease on  the  previous  week&apos;s  total, there was an increase in the number  of police killed.  212 outrages were committed as  compared with  239 for the  previous period; of these 107 were attributable  to Sinn  Fein, 6 were attributable to agrarian motives, while 99  wero serious crimes.       There has been much  discussion of Bishop CohalanTs  denunciation&apos;of murder and ambushes and his decree of  excommunication of any persons  taking part  therein within  his Diocese of Cork.  The Cork  Municipal  Corporation in turn  denounced the Bishop and  repudiated his right to interfere.  On December 19th,  however,  the  Bishop of  Cork again  in the  strongest possible language re-iterated his denunciation and  repeated his decree of excommunication.   Those who object  to the Bishop&apos;s action take up  the attitude that the  Bishop does not recognise that  Ireland is a nation and under  a  government of her own which government  has  the moral  and political right to kill the enemies of  the nation.  Bishop Cohalan,  however,  asks that has the  country gained by  the murder of policemen and says  he would be  a bold  Republican who would talk now in  the  city or  county  of  districts delivered from  British  rule by reason  of the  murders of police  and the burning of  barracks, and he  adds,  that the  killing of policemen was morally  murder and                                           politically/
politically of no consequence.     Father O1 Flanagan has been repudiated by all the ^leading Sinn Fein extremists as the representative of SinnFein opinion and the Peace overtures have been scathinglycommented upon.  It is apparent, however, that added togethe pronouncements of Father O1Flanagan and Bishop Cohalamay be said to express the wishes and opinions of the majof the people, brought into being by the firm action of tgovernment.  The extremist section is not yet conquered amay be expected to fight to the end until overwhelmed byopinion of the majority.     The Sinn Fein papers appeared as usual.  Neither vJoIreland&quot; nor &quot;Old Ireland&quot; contained muoh of importance.The tone of both is that of opposition to the rumoured trunegotiations.

</content>
</cab>
