<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/117/0 images: 692-698</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^1      She  following  Memorandum on tho  subjeot  of  the  continuation oi  tho leaso  of the Las talmas Meat  Tories  is  submitted :- lc   j?prior to  1907 the  jtdver  Plate refrigerated moat  trade  was shared between British and Argentine  companies,  but  after  the advent of the American meat  companies in that year  periods of fierce competition.followed,  alternated  by periods  in ;vhioh fr&amp;e respective interests agreed as to their shares  of the  tra e. After the last and  bitterest  of those price-wars (1913-14) two of  tho Baritian companies amalgamatod  to  form  the British and Argentine Sfcat Company,  Limited,  concentrated tlioir  ^edaoed shares in their Gamp ana works and shut $pm thylx Las&apos; Ealmas works. 2.   In August, 1915, the Board of Trade  on behalf of His Majesty1s Government entered  into an  agreement with  tho British and Argentine Meat  Company to lease the  Las PalmaS wezfcs for the period of the war  and for six menths after the.signing of a definitive  treaty of peace  with Germany.  The  works were operated  by the Company on profit-sharing  terms, the produce was applied to the  needs of  ilie allied Forces., and 8i saving cf  650,000  accrued.to His  Majesties Government,  as the&apos; oe-mpany in  addition to a nominal rent received only one-third of the net profits and their  works were  valued  at. t600,000  whereas the capital put in  by  the Government  was only about   250,000 the transaction was an extremely advantageous one for the  State.- 3.   The Agreement expired at  the  end  of  1919, but before it terminated the question  of its continuance  wee considered  by two Coimiittees appointed by  the Board of Trade.   The first frf these was. the Committee  on Imperial Meat Resources consisting of  representatives  nominated, by the Board  cf  Trado,  the Colonial  Offiae, and the High Commissioners of Canada,Australia, J:Iew Zoaland,  and South Africa,  with Sir  (/then  Mr. ) a,Shirley Benn,  M.P.  as ohairman.memorandum by the President  of the Board  of  Trade.0 A B I JSI Jfi. TThis Document is     Piroertv of
                                              .......        544.    That  Commilrtee- waa^ppolnte-d as  a result of the imperial war  Conference  of  1917,  to const dor the means-oof giving  s-ffocM^ca resolution passed by  that  Conference urging tho &quot;desirability offreeing British Markets  from excessive dependence $n foreignorganisations which control  important sources of supply&quot; andthe  mating of the  Empire&quot; as far as possible self-sufficing inthe.  matter of meat supplies&quot;.  The Committee in its heport dated26th March, 1918,  came to the conclusion that for a long time theUnited  Kingdom  must be dependent on South America for the main partof its  supply of imported beef, and for.the maintenance  of thatsupply  advocated the direct  support of the British meat  companies operating  in South America.  In paragraph 49 of its Heport, itpointed out that,  by. the lease of the las Palmas Works,  &quot;the government has  obtained  an insight into the costs of operation which could not have been got otherwise,  and has been of great value in controlling contract prices&quot;.5.   In the Spring of 1919,  the Board ;of Trade appointed anotherCommittee  of representatives of the Board of Trade,  Colonial Office,Board of Agriculture and Fisheries, and Ministry of Food, withMr.Y?.C.Bridgeman,  M.P., as Chairman, to consider &quot;the means ofsecuring suff ic ient meat supplies for the United Kingdom at reasonable prices&quot;.  It reported on 16th September,  1919, against  -the  direct measures of support to British meat companies proposedby the  earlier  Committee, but recommended (par.60 (b) ) thecontinued  operation of the Las Palmas Works and the acquisitionof an interest  in  one or more freezing works in overseas countries i&quot;for the purpose of ensuring, by first-hand acquaintance with thefacts,,that the position of British firms engaged in exportationof meat from these countries is not unduly prejudiced&quot;,6,   On October 27th,  1919,  the President of the Board of Tradeput forward a Memorandum to the Cabinet (Cabinet Paper 4) express-ing  &quot;general agreement&quot; with the unanimous recommendations of the meat Supplies Committee (of which the indefinite continuance ofthe Las palmas Agreement was one)  but not meiitioning specifioallythe Las Palma3 agreement,  Wo action appears to have been taken,and no Minute made by  the Cabinet  on this Memorandum^ 4o jpiA
       7.  The Board of Trade then proceeded wi th- negotiations for t renewal of the Agreement dud with Treasury sanction (jWen 6th December,  1919)  continued the operation of the works for another y during Which the .policy&apos; of the Goveirnment was to he settled and the terras  agreed.       Renewed discussions wore held with the Ministry Cf Food and the  British and Argentine Meat Company.   The chief difficulty was to protect the Government against the risk that the Company should part with their interest in the works to some  out- side r,  and ultimately,  on 16th September,  1920,  the Company offered a  lease of ten years,  terminable  by  either party at the end of five&apos; years  on six mohths1 notice.     This  offer  was accepted,  subject to covering sanction,  and a new Agreement  has been  drawn  up on substantially the same terms as; the former one,,.   Tao period  of this  Agreement runs frocr 1st January, 1920,  so  that one  year  out of the nominal  five is now  expired,.     The  works  are  to be  run-.on profit-sharing termsby the  British and  Argentine Meat Company  on  behalf of  theGovernment,  and, although a higher basis rent  has  been  conceded, it has  been  stipulated, that the Company is not  to  receive more for rent and remuneration together under the  new  Agreement  thanit would have  received  under  the  old for equivalent quantitiesof meat.    The Company  cannot dispose  of their interest  In  theworks without  the consent  of  the Government,   - This agreement is now  awaiting  signature.    The Ministry  of   ood,&apos; had  already-&quot;written  to-the&quot;&apos;Bdard of  Trade on  9th  August,.  1920,  that &quot;thev&quot;-ow of  the Food Controller is  that the  Government  shouldcontinue the agreement with the Las Palmas meat, works&quot;.,     8,  Meanwhile  the  Standing Committee  on  Trusts set up under the  Profiteering Acts, 1919 and 1920, appointed a Sub-Committee  to investigate  the effects  of  trusts and  combinations^on the price of meat.    This Sr.b-Comrai.ttee, enquired,  inter  alia,into the operations  of tho  American meat companies  in SouthAmerica, and reported on  9th November,  1920.   Regarding the&apos;LIT. Palmas works paragraph .17 of  their  report  is  as follows,-  .                                        \
           &quot;We alee agree  with the  reooMDendation of  tho lloat      Supplies-Commi^t^-^para.60 (b)  of thoir Report)  that  the      operation of the Las Palmae Works  of tho British  and      Argentine Meat Co.  Ltd.,  (which  since the  summer  of 1915      have  heen operated  on behalf of  His Majesty1 s Government)      should continue to  be run on the same lines as  during  that      period.  Convinced  as we are that  tho movement  of the      prices of refrigerated meat must be -carefully watched, we      hold  that it is necessary that the costs of producing  such      moat  should be accurately and systematically ascertained,      so  that it oan at any moment&apos;be  determined whether any      particular :.;rioe movement is  natural or artificial,  Tho      possession of the Las Palmas works gives the Government an      &quot;observation post&quot;  of great value  in the very centre of      the operations of the American meat companies,  and we  are      confident that its utility will  be no less  in peaoe time  .      than  it was during  the war&quot;. 9.    The output which it  jls intended  to obtain  from  the Las Palmas Works is from three to  five thousand tons a month; ordinarily about 3,500, tons are produced.   Out  of this tho requirements of the War Offioo (from  1,500 to 3,000  tons monthly) are mot, so that effectively thoy  get their supplies of frozen. meat  at cost.   The  surplus has hithorte been sold by the British and Argentine Meat  Co.,  on the open markot in tho usual oourse of trade on behalf  of  the  Government, but it is  contemplated that  in future  an endeavour will be made  to dispose  of  such surplus to public institutions. 10,   At the  outbreak of  the War practioally all the insulated steamers, in the! hiver  Plate trade  were  affected  by long-torm contracts  at very low rates of freight,  but sinoe the  Spring cf 1915 all such  shipping has boen controlled by the-Board of  Trade unaer requisition powors  obtained  by  Orders in -Council of 1915 and by the;  Shipping Controller undor  the  Defence of  the healmAct.  In, this way the  Government war? able  to ensure that in- sulatejl shipping should be  used in the  way  most  advantageous for
national purposes- dnri ng tho uar, and,  incident ally.,  to provideshipping space for las Salinas produooo   At the present  moment-all the insulated space ensa^od in.tho  hiver Plata trado,  oneeptwhat is required for Las Salinas, is assigned; monthly to the moatcompanies for their private trade at rates (paid to tho shipping companies) based on costs of operation and from two to  threotimes greater than the pre-war rates.  The powers of the ShippingController will, howovorj coase on March 31st, 1921,  and thoso4&apos;f the Board of Trade will laps a on the issue of a Proclamationunder the Termination of the Present War..acts; (1918.-) declaringthe&apos;official end of tho War.- The River Plate ihsulatod ships will then revert to their pre-war contracts at rates which unlessthe Meat Companies agree to their revision will invnlvq loss tothe shipowners, and it will bo difficult if not impossible toprovide sufficient, if any, shipping tonnage for La&apos;s  almas, .11.  The situation thus created has been under discussion between.the Board &amp;f Trade, tho Ministry of Shipping, the Ministry of food, and the Shipowners.  &amp; Bill has been drafted proposing togive to the Board of Trade during a period of five years powersto requisition British, shipping for the carriage of foodstuffs,provided that a resolution had been.previously passed by Parlia-mont on the initiative of the Board and the Ministry-of Fooddeclaring that an emergency existed in which, it was necessaryto utilize these powers for the securing&quot; or regulating, thesupplies of food&apos; for tho/United Kingdom.  Sir     lewis ofPurness Withy and Company undertook to open up negotiations withthe American moat companies for,the purpose .of-seeing whether .an amioable arrangement could he madeV enabling.the Bill to be dispensed with, but those negotiations broke down, He thenrecommended the Board ta proeeed with the-Bill,-.after reducingits  term  to  two  years  and  Obtained  from  the
   f^ip-wnsra5 Parltejnant-ory-Oonml&apos;Vtee--e. premiss, that-, on  -   the undertaking that the powers iii the Bill wouldjnot be   abused ^. they would not. oppose it.,  There will s;U.ll,, notwith   standing, be seme opposition on,general grounds from   individual shipowners of high..standing..12.     This Bill was,Rafted, in general, terms covering all   foodstuffs in order that it might not appear to be directed   against a particular American interest.-    Its immediate -   objects are to secure,the shipping necessary for tho   operation cf the Las P&amp;lmas works and to prevent the   interruption of the meat supplies of the United Kingdom   Tyy a dispute1 between the  shipping companies&apos; and the  meat   companies.   It d^es net involve  new powers but merely   the continuance fcr a short period and under very   stringent  conditions of some of the powers utilised   during the war...   It is, indoed.&apos;.  not Improbable that  the   possession of  these powers by the Government will   facilitate an  amicable  settlement and make their enforce-   ment nnneoessaryv .  It  is true  that  the  Bill only  confers   powers for two. years whereas the  Las Palmas Agreement   is  for five years/ but&apos; Sir F..W. Lewis  is  of  opinion that   he  will  have new  ships  not covered by  contracts  and   available.for  L&amp;s  Palmao, or,  alternatively,  that   the Bill,could be  extended when the  time came. 15.     Lord:Robert  CecilTs departmental  Committee en   Combinations  in the meat  trade  reported en 29th April-,   1909,  as follows         &quot;It seems to be within  the limits ef possibility^             put  it no higher,  that the  United States  firms          will acquire very considerable interests In          Argentina and perhaps  elsewhere.    If this shoult&apos;          be the  case, it Is net&apos; Improbable that the methods.
      of combination, which have been adopted so effectively      in the United States, might be extended, at any      rate to Argentina... It does not seem likely that this      condition of affairs will arise in the near future, but      in the event of its doing so we are of opinion that the      situation in regard to the beef supply of the United      Kingdom might well become serious&quot;.That danger has now been realized, for in 1914 the american companies possessed about 60$ of the beef output of theRiver Plate,  They have throughout the past thirteen yearssuccessfully pursued the policy of reducing the Btfctish shareof the Argentine Meat trade by periods of violent competition,and the Meat Sub-Committee of the Committee on  rusts are ofopinion that this policy is &quot;still in full activity&quot;.  TheAmerican ueat Companies have always regarded the operation ofthe Las ?almas works by the British Government as a sign thatthat Government would, if the occasion demanded it, take steps.,to prevent the extinction of uritish interests in the Argentinekeat Trade, and during this autumn they have steadily put pressure on the Lritish and Argentine Meat Company to induce them to consent to the shutting-up of the i*as talmas works.If&apos;the policy that has been hitherto followed by the governmentis now revised, there is little doubt that the Americans will consider that they have a free hand and will start anotherperiod of destructive competition in which their immense wealthwill give them a tremendous advantage.  ,  (Intd.) R.S.H.31.  12. 20.

</content>
</cab>
