<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/13/30 images: 468-477</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government most SECRET.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.COPY NO.ILW.M. (40) 152ND CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 2.Confidential Annex.(2nd June, 1940).IE STERN FRONT.future Assistanceo France.previousbf erence:M.(40) 151bnclusions,minute &amp;. )THE PRIME MINISTER said that the effect ofM. Reynaud&apos;s telegram was that a &quot;battle of capitalimportance was impending on the Somme and Oise Front.The French Government expected that the three british divisions which it had &quot;been intended to send to france in the next few weeks should he sent to France at once,and that these Divisions should he followed as soon aspossible hy units reconstituted from the personnel ofthe B. E. F. which had &quot;been evacuated from Dunkirk tothis country.    In addition, it would be essential thatfighter aircraft based on French soil should be availahlefor the support of the French army.General Weygand and General Vuillemin also asked that the maximum British air strength should immediately be based in France     General   Vuillemin asking that 320 British fighter aircraft should he based inFrance.A preliminary   discussion ensued as to the forces which could immediately be sent to reinforce theFrench Front.On the.one hand it was argued that with the considerable accession to the strength of our home forces,  represented by the 200,000 troops withdrawnfrom Dunkirk, even without their heavy equipment, therisk of a successful invasion of this country was greatlylessened.    The difficulties of re-equipping the B.E. F.were, however, very great.    Time would be taken in re-equipping the units, and sending them overseas again.It would almost certainly be impossible in the time available to send to the  assistance of the French a force.of sufficient strength to play a decisive part inthe battle which the French were now awaiting on the somme,,At the same time it was pointed out that ifwe were to decline to respond to M.  Reynaud&apos;s appealthere was a considerable danger that a point might hereached at which French resistance might collapse;    andif Paris fell,  they might be tempted to conclude aseparate peace.    This would mean the establishment inFrance of a Government friendly to the Nazis.    Then weshould have to bomb aerodromes in France, occupied by german air forces, and to exercise economic pressureagainst France.      We might eventually be faced with a french Government, not merely out of the war, butactually hostile to us.

As regards air support,  if we were to confine our assistance to the operations of long-range bombers we should lay ourselves open to thecharge of exposing the French Forces to overwhelmingGerman air superiority.    It would be a very seriousstep indeed to denude this country of its essentialdefences of fighter aircraft;   but the despatchof further fighter squadrons to operate on french territory might provide the element of supportnecessary to encourage the French to resist.      Inthis connection, it must be remembered that we had withdrawn the Air Component of the B. E. F.  to thiscountry;    and if any further divisions were sent to reinforce our troops in the Lower Somme   area, theywould have to be accompanied by an appropriate air component.Since the opening of the battle our losses in trained fighter pilots had been extremely heavy.Our main difficulty in regard to fighter squadronswas not machines but a shortage of fully trainedfighter pilots.       Hitherto it had been the practice for these pilots to undergo their final trainingwith the fighter squadrons.    It had now been necessary to create a special organisation forthe intensive training of fighter pilots.    Some little time must elapse bexore these measures brought usup to strength again in fully trained fighter pilots.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL said it would beimpossible to meet the French demands as they stood.We must not impair the essential fighter defences ofthis country.    Invasion of this country could not be disregarded and it would be unjustifiable to weighthe scales against the chances of repelling such an invasion in order to secure hypothetical advantages in France, more especially as it was most doubtfulwhether the French hadevolvedarrynavnijtods of meeting freshonslaughts by German armoured divisions.    We should,however,  do something to hearten the French,  and theoffer of even one or two Divisions would be a tokenof our sincerity, as the French must know how fewfully equipped troops we now had available.THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO said thatwe already had two divisions in France and anotherDivision or two was unlikely to make much difference to the French morale.    We had, however, a consider-able amount of equipment still in France and theChiefs of Staff might think it desirable to sendextra troops to safeguard this equipment and,incidentally, get some benefit from it,&apos; THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that, while he did not exclude the possibility ofgiving further assistance to the French, he thoughtthat the Cabinet would wish to have an opportunity of seeing the considered viow of the Chiefs of Staffbefore reaching a decision on this vital matter.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he would wait for the appreciation of the situation from theChiefs of Staff before asking the Cabinet to come toa decision but would now give, for the benefit ofthe Chiefs of Staff, an outline of a course ofaction that he asked them to consider.

He would like to tell the French that wewould send three divisions as quickly as we could; wewould send the Canadians first and would hope to havethe three divisions in France within 5/6 v/eeks.    Wewould use the full strength of our long-range bombers to bombard by night, and when possible by day, targetsas indicated by the French Commander-in-Chief.This task should have preference whenever necessaryover the bombardment of the Ruhr area.    The AdvancedAir Striking Force would remain in action in France.Lord Gort would be sent back to re-form the headquarters of a reconstituted 3ritish Expeditionary Force.    Ifwe sent over fresh British divisions, we should likewisereconstitute an expropriate Air Component.But, unless we found that Fighter Squadrons could operate from thiscountry on the lower Somme, fighter support shouldbe limited to the Fighter Squadrons in the AdvancedAir Striking Force and the Air Component.    Additionalfighter squadrons would not be sent across theChannel unless it was found possible to operate them from west of Abbeville.The French would thus, by the middle ofJuly, receive reinforcements corresponding to IDDivisions made up as follows:-   Three British Divisions,the equivalent of 2 Divisions from Narvik (which should reach France by the middle of June), and 60,000 -80,000 French troops which were being evacuated from dunkirk - the equivalent of, say, 5 Divisions.The Chiefs of Staff should consider asolution to the problem on these lines giving thegreatest possible support to France without leaving the defence   forces of the United Kingdom dangerouslyreduced in face of the risk of invasion.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR said that french demands for bomber assistance could probablybe met, with the aid of assistance from Polishpilots.    The difficulty would be to provide thenecessary fighter squadrons.    It had been decided earlyin the war that we could only spare 10 Squadrons for france.    Now that the Germans were in occupation ofSouthern Norway, Holland, Belgium, and part of theFranch coast, we would run a grave risk by sendingextra squadrons overseas, a risk which would bevery difficult to justify.THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL suggestedthat, on this point as on several others, the viewsof the Chiefs of Staff, should be available, before theWar Cabinet came to a decision.The War Cabinet -Instructed the Chiefs of Staff tomake recommendations as to the reply which should be given to the Frenchdemands for assistance.\

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY. 232It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.MOST SECRET.COPY NO.JORWAY.(previous reference z/sioW,M. (40) Me-thConclusionsHiHttiW.M.(40) 152nd CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 8.Confidential Annex.(2nd June,  1940. )THE PRIME MINISTER said that he had been giving further consideration to the question of thewithdrawal of the Allied forces from Narvik.    He hadbeen hoping that now that we had succeeded inwithdrawing so large a proportion of the B.E.P.from Prance it might be possible to re-considerthe decision to withdraw all our forces from narvik and to maintain a garrison there for some weeks on a self-contained basis.    He had now reachedthe conclusion that the decision to withdraw must stand.THE CHIEF OF NAVAL STAFF said that themeasures for the v/withdrawal from Narvik had been postponed for 24 hours,  in order to allow theNorwegian Government time to negotiate on theMowihkel   plan for the neutralisation of northern norway.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.




</content>
</cab>
