<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/34/0 images: 264-267</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. (60) Copy No. 4 732nd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Friday, 20th May, 1960^ at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for foreign affairs the Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord Privy Seal and Ministerfor science the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of aviation the Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Minister of transport also present:The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,treasury secretariat:Mr. F. A. bishop mr. M. ReedPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1960
ContentsSubjectInterception of CommunicationsProfessions Supplementary to Medicine BillMeeting of Heads of Government, 1960
Interception ofCommunica-tions.ProfessionsSupplementaryto MedicineBill.(previous references:CC. (60) 28thConclusions,Minute 1 and cc. (59) 63rdConclusions,Minute 2.)1. The Home Secretary said that the report of the committee under Lord Simonds on the powers of subpoena of disciplinarytribunals had been published on the previous day. The reportrecommended that disciplinary tribunals established by statute forthe various professions should be empowered to secure the issue ofwrits of subpoena for the production, subject to all proper exceptions,of evidence obtained by police officers in the course of their duty.These recommendations were to be considered later that day by theHome Affairs Committee. If they were accepted, this would involve further amendment in the House of Lords of the ProfessionsSupplementary to Medicine Bill, which had previously been amended to deprive the tribunals established under it of the statutory powerof subpoena.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Home Secretary.Meeting of heads ofGovernment,1960.(previous reference:CC. (60) 31stConclusions,Minute 1.)2. The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet of the statement which he proposed to make to Parliament that day about the summit meeting. This described briefly the discussions and events whichhad taken place in Paris, which were fully set out in a White Paper tobe laid before Parliament, and it explained that it was too early todecide whether the Soviet Government had deliberately decided to pursue a more aggressive policy. In this situation it was necessaryfor the West to continue to work for satisfactory settlements ofinternational problems by negotiation, but at the same time to beready to meet new threats with firmness. The purpose of thestatement was to try to keep a balance between unjustified optimismand extreme cynicism as regards the prospects for any futurenegotiations with the Soviet Government.It had to be admitted that the reconnaissance flights by UnitedStates aircraft over Soviet territory, and the United states government public endorsement of this policy, had createddifficulties for the Soviet Government. It was at present impossibleto say to what extent Mr. Khrushchev&apos;s attitude in Paris had been due to internal criticism, particularly on account of the implications of the American flights for Soviet defence policy. It seemed likely that Mr. Khrushchev had not taken a final decision until the eve ofthe meeting, but it then became clear that he was determined to avoidgenuine negotiations. He must have known that the conditions whichhe had put forward could not be accepted by President Eisenhower.In a sense this had been fortunate, since President Eisenhower wouldhave been put in a difficult position if Mr. Khrushchev had askedonly for a vague expression of regret.It could be argued that, in the difficult atmosphere which had developed in Paris, it would not in any case have been possible tomake satisfactory progress in any negotiations, and that the Westmight have been led in consequence into taking up an unnecessarilyrigid position about the Berlin question. In fact, if the SovietGovernment still entertained the possibility of negotiations at some future date, they might not bring the Berlin issue to a head; in that event we should in practice have secured some period of delay over this issue, which was what we wanted. On the other hand, we hadto face the possibility that the Soviet Government might sign anearly peace treaty with East Germany, and that there might beinterference with the Allies&apos; rights in West Berlin.One good result of the meetings in Paris was that there had beena further improvement in relations between the Governments of theUnited Kingdom and France. Also, the three Western governments were becoming considerably more realistic in their attitude towardsthe Berlin problem, and this had been achieved without the United
Kingdom&apos;s coming under suspicion of weakness on this issue.Furthermore, the need to consolidate the Western Alliance might provide a better opportunity for a satisfactory settlement of theproblem of our economic relations with Europe. Arrangements wereto be made for closer consultation between the Governments of theUnited Kingdom, the United States and France; and this might lead the French Government to be more favourable towards an accommodation between the European Economic Community andthe European Free Trade Association. In certain respects, therefore,the outcome might be helpful. Nevertheless, the failure of the summit meeting was a serious setback to the Governmenfs policyand was bound to be a shock to public opinion.The Foreign Secretary said that it was due to the Prime Ministerspersonal efforts that the meetings in Paris had ended without damage to the Western Alliance. It had been necessary, from the point ofview of public opinion, for President Eisenhower to give an assurance that there would be no further reconnaissance nights by United states aircraft over Soviet territory, and this had been achieved by thePrime Ministers persuasion. It had also been necessary to resist theintention of the United States and French Governments to bring the meetings to an end prematurely.The plan which Mr. Khrushchev had pursued in Paris had enabled him to leave it open either to revert to the settlement ofinternational problems by negotiation, or to pursue a more aggressivepolicy in the future, as he thought fit. In these circumstances weshould not take any action to intensify the cold war atmosphere andwe should be ready to take any opportunity of resuming or continuinggenuine negotiations. Although, from his discussions withMr. Gromyko, it looked as though the Soviet Government no longerhoped for any progress in the disarmament meetings, there were stillreasonably good prospects for the conference at Geneva on nuclear tests. The meeting on the previous day of the Permanent Councilof the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation had taken place in a spiritof consolidation. In this connexion it was satisfactory that it had now been established that any decisions which the three western governments might take in response to a threat against their rights in West Berlin would be the subject of full consultation with theother members of the North Atlantic Alliance.Discussion showed that it was the unanimous view of the Cabinetthat the immediate aim should be to seek to keep a balance betweenpessimism at the failure of the Summit meeting and optimism aboutthe possibility of resuming negotiations.In further discussion it was pointed out that we had not yet beenable to work out a satisfactory plan for an economic accommodationbetween the European Economic Community and the European free trade Association. The present circumstances, however, might makeit possible to consider solutions which would not otherwise have beenacceptable to the United States. It was also suggested that it mightbe preferable to establish closer economic relations with Europe onthe basis of specific projects, such as co-operation in civil aviation orin atomic energy. The Foreign Secretary said that the French ForeignMinister had expressed the view that both the Community and theAssociation might agree to make mutual tariff concessions affectingsensitive items, and in this way might move towards some kind ofindustrial common market covering both groups.The Cabinet-Took note with approval of these statements by the PrimeMinister and the Foreign Secretary.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,20th May, I960.

</content>
</cab>
