<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/34/0 images: 531-539</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1960C.C. (60)65&amp;h ComduisibfflsCopy Mo.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, SW. 1, oh Wednesday, 21st December, 1960* at.10-30a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P; Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler^ M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Horn:Viscount Hailsham,Q.G., Lord President of the Counciland Minister for Science.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations (Items 1-4)The Right Horn Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of defence the Right Horn Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of education the Right Hon. Lord Mills,Paymaster-GeneralThe Right Hon. John Hare, M.P.,Minister of Labour (Items 1-4)Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P.,&apos; Chancellor;; of $ the /Duchy - of lancaster the Right / Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary; of State &apos;for scotland the Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment; and ;minister for welsh affairs the Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Minister of aviation the Right Hon/ Reginald Maudling,M.P., President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Christopher Soames,M.P., Minister, of Agriculture,Fisheries and food the following were also present:The Right Hon. J. Enoch Powell, M.P.,^Minister of Health (Items 4-5)The Right Hon. Reginald Bevins, M.P.,Postmaster-General (Items 5-6)The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M:P.,: Minister /-of Pensions landNational Insurance (Item :4ft&apos;.The Right Hon;. Richard Wood, m p.*\Minister of Power (Item 5)The Right Hon. Martin Redmayne,M.P., /-Parliamentary //Secretary,treasury secretariat the Right Hon. Sir Norman brook mr. F. A. bishop mr. M. Reed
.SECRET:.&apos;CONTBNTSMinuteNo!subject      Congo RepublicM^^^^j^k^f^^^W Organisation:;3(?ynAgriculWf^l]:Pplicy;Farm Jtnproveinerit&apos;4-^&quot;&quot;(National HeaJth^Seryice&apos;5V;6^b?fe5rpadeastingiDeVelopnientSubscription ?Televisiqii ;j1,CPmmerciaLPolicy.
Congo(previous reference:C.C. (60) 64thConclusions,Minute 1) i. 1. The Foreign Secretary said that the resolution put forward by the United Kingdom and United States Governments to strengthen the influence of the United Nations Organisation in dealing with the. situation in the Congo had failed by one vote to secure the necessary two-thirds majority in the General Assembly. Meanwhile the effortspf the supporters of Mr. Lumumba to set up a separate Governmentin Stanleyville, which were being encouraged by certain african countries including the United Arab Republic, had increased the dangers of civil war. It was important, that the United Nationsauthorities should continue to control the airports, in order to lessen the chances of direct intervention, and that they should be encouraged to help the! administration in Leopoldville to deal with widespreaddistress and shortage of food in the country.&apos; The Cabinet-&apos; . ,;.Took note of this statement by the Foreign Secretary,South-Easf &apos; 2.   The Foreign Secretary said that General Phoumi had nowAsia Treaty secured control of Vientiane, but that there were strong forces of theOrganisation Left-wing Pathet Lao in other parts of the country who were receivingLaos assistance from the Communist Woe.   As a result of his recent(Previous        discussions with the United States Secretary of State and the FrenchReference:   h- Foreign Minister: in, Paris, the United States authorities nowC.C. (60) 64th   appreciated the dangers of an appeal for intervention by South-EastConclusions,?: Asia Treaty Organisation forces, and were trying to ensure that minute 3)       neither General Phoumi nor the Government of Thailand made suchan appeal.  It seemed that the best chance of securing a genuinelyneutral Government in Laos might lie in reviving the International. ;  Control Commission, but the authorities in Laos had not so far beenV prepared to agree;to this.    . ,,      /; &quot;&apos;,  .     ;He had- also :.sent: a: message ^to theqSoviet: Foreign Minister,^warning him of the dangers that would arise from outside intervention in the situation in Laos;.there had not yet been any response to this.&quot;v -&apos; The Cabinet-Took note of this statement.by the Foreign Secretary.^Agricultural :.&apos;.;IPoIicy-..Farm;Improvement(previous reference:&quot;?;:.-C.C. (60) 45th;Conclusions^!;Minute 4)Vv-3.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Minister:jof,Agriculture (C. (60) 192) about jtheiarmimprovements scheme,^&apos;-s?Thk Minister of Agriculture recalled that this scheme, introducedunderthe Agriculture Act, 1957, provided; for grants at the rate ofI 331--per^cent.- on longrterm capital improvements. Under the Actithe scheme; would ;run for 10 years^and.was subject to ,a limit of; 50 millions.(which might be extended by Order?to.  55 millions) onthe ^total; arnqunt of. thej grants.- The ; rate?; of expenditure hadjbutstrippedithe original estimate and,  27 \ millions &quot;had already been^committed in: tjue;first three years, If this rate were not checked, the^tdtaj-of grantsVpyeik be at least^  70&apos;, millipris.&quot;; Whenthe Cabinet had last considered the development of the\ scheme^ the balance of; Opinion had favoured maintaining the present rate of grant, since any reduction might be unfair to farmers who hadplanned toapply-for assistance in one of the later years of the scheme.The then Minister of Agriculture had/however-been invited to give; further consideration to the possibility of limiting expenditure underthe i scheme b$Uadministrative   means,and&quot;&quot;&apos;of  finding  some
National,Health .Service(previous reference:C.C.(60)56th4.  The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary (C. (60) 193) about the cost of the National Health Service.The Minister oft Health said that next year would be the fifth in-succession in which there had been an increase&apos;in the cost of the/National Health Service of between 8-10 per cent. Apart from thep burden on&apos; the taxpayer, this large and continuing increase made it-more difficult to effect the redeployment&apos;of expenditure within theservice which modern trends in medicine demanded.  In agreementwith the Secretary of State for Scotland, he had put forward a numberof proposals which would provide about half of the  54 millions bywhich the Health Estimates for the following year exceeded the/original Estimates for,the^current year.; These were to reduce by 2d./the subsidy on liquid welf are; milk, and j to make, an economic charge-for the other welfare foods; to increase the charges: for dental and/optical appliances and for amenity beds in hospitals; and to double the present prescription. charge of Is./per item.. These measures could be presented not as cuts in the service but as a move to alter the priorities for expenditure within the service.  For example, thecompensating reduction in other forms of Exchequer assistance to agriculture. Examination had now shown that no major economies in the scheme could be effected by administrative means and that,,,; u : since the grants were statutorily excluded from the annual farm price Review, there was no possibility of recovering any excess overthe limit imposed by the Act by compensating reductions in the... value of the price guarantees. \JiThe Government had made it clear when the Agriculture Bill of1957 had been before Parliament that, if expenditure under thescheme seemed likely to exceed the figure contained in the Bill, thequestion would be examined afresh. Since/the scheme was one ofthe most successful means of increasing farm efficiency and reducingthe long-term dependence of agriculture on Exchequer support, and since to restrict it at this stage might reasonably; be;regarded as a breach of faith with the industry, the Minister proposed that thescheme should be maintained for its full 10 years^atjthe present rateof grant.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he: would welcomefurther time in which to consider this proposal in?the light of the examination which had been made of the alternative courses.In a short general discussion it was ;pointed out that, while theexistence of the farm improvements scheme/ had. enabled theGovernment to take a firmer line in recent Farm Price Reviews, thehigh level of Exchequer assistance to agriculture. had: led to excessiveprices for farm land. It might be desirable to adopt a much morecritical attitude to proposals for increasing the amount of assistance.It was also suggested that it would be helpfuFif the cabinet could be given more detailed information about the type of farmswhich were benefiting from the scheme.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer tq give furtherconsideration in the light of their discussion to the-; ;:      proposal in C. (60) 192; that - the farm i, improvementsscheme &quot;should be maintained for its fuU&apos;period; at thepresent rate of grant(2) Invited the Minister of Agriculture to circulate amemorandum containing information about the types of farms benefiting from the scheme/(3) Agreed to resume their discussion at a later meeting.
/----r.&apos;--.-.:: &apos; i C.C. 65 (60)total amount of the welfare milk subsidy was at present not far short of the total capital expenditure in the hospital service; a reduction inthe subsidy would make more money available for capitaldevelopments. Again, an increase in the charges for dental andi; optical appliances would make it possible to introduce concessions,desirable on medical grounds, on appliances for children andexpectant and nursing mothers. The proposals had been approvedby the Home Affairs Committee, although the Home Secretary hadreserved his position about the introduction of legislation.Discussion showed that there was considerable support in theCabinet for these proposals as the most acceptable method of bringingunder control the increasing cost of the health service. There was evidence that the present level of direct taxation was a disincentiveto expansion of the economy. If, therefore, any progress was to bemade in reducing taxation, some means must be found to relieve theExchequer of some part of the mounting cost not only of the national health Service but of other services also. The Government were likely to be under increasing pressure from their own supporters totake action for this purpose.On the other hand, the proposals could not properly be regardedas genuine economies, since they were not primarily designed &quot;toreduce the total amount spent on the Service. They would, without question, provoke the strongest political reactions especially inconjunction with the increase to be made in the Health Serviceweekly contribution. They were also open to the particular objection that, like the increase in the contribution, they would bear mostheavily on those sections of the community who were in the leastfavourable position to meet them.In discussion of the particular proposals the following main points were made: 1(a) When the last reduction in the welfare milk subsidy had beenmade in 1957, it had resulted in a reduction of average consumptionof less than 1 per cent. It might be inferred from this that the present proposal would not result in a further reduction in consumptionsufficient to have any significant effect on health. But on the earlieroccasion consumption in families with four or more children hadbeen reduced by as much as 7 per cent. It would be necessary tomake certain that any further reduction in the subsidy would notendanger the nutritional standards of such families. It might benecessary either to allow the larger families to continue to obtainmilk at the present subsidised price or to find some other method of helping them.An arguable case could be made for abolishing the welfare milksubsidy altogether and at the same, time abandoning some or all ofthe other proposals before the cabinet The financial effect on theExchequer would be approximately the same but the consequent reduction in milk consumptionlwhich must then be expected wouldhave a very serious effect on the1&apos;milk industry and, since milk production would not be proportionately reduced, on the guaranteed; price scheme:An alternative, which should be examined, would be to abolish the welfare milk subsidy altogether for certain; classes of recipientbut,at the same time to make the subsidy more generous for others.1 (b) The proposal to double the present prescription charge would provoke strong political criticism&apos;and might inflict some degree of genuine hardship on elderly people on an income level slightly above that which would entitle them to help from the National assistance board. But it could be justified in part by the 50 per cent, increasein the cost of drugs which had occurred since the present charge was fixed at the end of 1956, and it could be presented in the context of

action which was being taken to control the price of drugs and to influence the prescribing habits of doctors. v   ;&quot; ,(c) There would be political difficulty in the legislation required if the charges for dental and optical appliances were to be increased,especially if the guillotine had to be applied and&apos; if, as seemed probable, the Bill could not appropriately be combined with thatwhich would effect the increase in the health service contribution.On the other hand, the increased charges could be fully justified by increased costSj and the proposed legislation would enable theGovernment to make the concessions on dental and optical appliancesto which the Minister of Health had referred; It would also make itpossible1 to provide that, for the future, the/charges for theseappliances could be adjusted ^without legislation. i; ; M: ;j        r  -^Summing .&apos;.up the Prime Minister said that it Was the generalsfeelingi-of (the Cabinet that some action must be taken to secure[sayings to the Exchequer of the order of those which would accrue from the -Health Ministers&apos; proposals. .&apos;The: needs of the economyfandUhe Governments philosophy alike demanded that some checki,should;be put&apos;on the increasing burden&quot;on\the taxpayer.   It was,\ however, difficult to do this without at the same time putting tooheavy a burden on the least affluent members of the community and-the proposals before the Cabinet gave rise to some apprehension onthis score; The balance of opinion appearedtto be in favour of theproposed legislation&apos; on dental and optical appliances and there seemed to be no objection to increasing the charges for amenity beds in hospitals;  But the proposals on the welfare milk subsidy shouldbe reconsidered, with a view to adjusting them by one or other ofthe methods put forward in the discussion^ and revised proposals should be brought before the Cabinet in due courser&apos;; &apos;\, V - The Cabinet ,,(1) Took note that the Home Secretary reserved his position on;$M0?3-L legislation to increase, the charges,forvdental^and optical^li&apos;^-&apos;&apos;^^&apos;;^&apos;^:&apos; appliances. ;:&apos;:;&apos;      &apos;*fHHg,%HA*     !^fl?;(2^ubject to Conclusion ^(1),1:V approved vthe proposals in,1 *C. (60) i ?3: to increase the charges jfor^dental and optical- appliances and amenity^bedsj -   ,       (, *ff^ (3) Invited the Secretary of State for Scotland-and the Minister;:of Health to give further consideration to the proposalsh &apos;i; &apos;        on welfare milk and the prescription charge on the lines,&quot;?    :     indicated by the Prime Minister; - and ^ to.; bring! revised:&apos;:ProPos3ls before them.&quot;-/&apos;; i^r^nfX^:
SECRET(Broadcasting (( &quot; &apos;H (6/rtThe Cabinet had5 before them;a( memorandum! by theDevelopmental pr^gid^ht&apos;! of the1.1; Board of&quot; (Tirade:andfiHe HfP^stnmSter-GeneralSubscripiion &apos; 1 (cV (60)iil9l)(about(a. proposed experimentiinisubs^(p   *   ^&apos;SM%^fTh^:liresident of ihe Board o/^m^-said-Ttha^thg^overiinieiit-;^yv^^,   ( i had been asked by a number of groups(interested^iifsu^criptionCC^OHPthhte&apos;ev&apos;s&apos;on to agree to a field trial m^^parlin^toii?l^lt?&apos;!seemed? Conclusions,! improbable&apos; that- at; some time in the&apos; future,; Shbsqrjipti6n( televisionMinute 5):&apos;^ (would become an important servic^ valuable^opportunity&apos; fbr^developing our ?exr^ftnecessary ! for&apos;&apos;&apos;the? service. 1 It might^aliblxielp!!-tbf f einvigorate theilBfiuMi^h^jopportunitiefcf&apos;%^television bh!^i&apos;c6mhierciaIbrittheTeebmrrieridatjbns bf^fhe^CbiHM3 the&apos;1 Ghairniariship! of j 5iFHarry&apos;:;Prlkihg^$ before:&apos;kny^^The PostmasterrGeneral^ saidl^atiifIthe?,proposed experimentiproved successful it would* in,his .yjew,itbejvirtuallyvrnrpossible forllhe,&apos;, Government (npt&apos; to allow the* introduction of a%npfe general^ervjce pfj.subscription television.,! He could, not  therefore^agree that^^lii^ti^ex^rim^iit woujld not prejudge^the findings; of ithe PilkingtoniCpttimittee if? arid the&apos;&apos; Government decisions, on -(them. Herecoiriniended&apos; that&apos; the proposal $^rejected &apos;Sndfhoped; that at least the &apos;-experjnrient&apos; would &apos;hot^gi^6rnefltf pf (the [PJlkmgton^Cbr^ittee^Discussion (showed, that there fwas considerable &quot;support in theCabinet&apos; fbi^thejview that it would be! difficult fto refuse: to allow the experiment^ for which the promoters themselves would provide all theI necessary?equipment ?and &quot;would assume fulFfinancial responsibility;(The promoters(were!Cpnvinced.that/if an early start Were made, theyshould :? secureVi affiead ?l oVerr Umtfed^ States ^manufacturers in thei&apos;deVelopmenti*of)&apos;equipmen^^^ easy to(defendnarf decision i*which%wp^^ with the1 Government^ declared I policy of ^dPirtg eVerything^bssible to expandjouriexport) trade.WOm the/othef !&apos;tand,&apos;Hhe^VieW*of the PilkingtonhGommittee;that theirtwprk w^even on an experimental basis?of&apos;ah^dditiohaI^ommercial television^sefyicer:iaboutiwhich(there.:were&apos;already^ thej
Commercial 7.   The President of the Board of Trade said that it was anPolicy essential feature of our proposals for a commercial treaty with JapanJapan that we should maintain import restrictions on certain sensitive(Previous        products. The Japanese had accepted this in principle but, since the reference:      present list covered items which made up more than half of Japan&apos;sC.C. (60) 62nd   export trade, it would be necessary to make some further concessions.Conclusions,    The Economic Policy Committee had approved the PresidentsMinute 10)     proposals, made in response to representations from the Japanese,that we should delete from the sensitive list cigarette lighters made ofprecious metals, certain types of non-precision cameras, surveyinginstruments and non-transistorised radio and television apparatus;that We should delete clocks and mechanical timing devices, and ships and boats, on the understanding that for their part the japanese would liberalise these items by the time the treaty came into force;that we should accept a five-year limit on the maintenance of restrictions on certain other photographic equipment  and ontransistors and transistorised radio and television apparatus; but thatwe should refuse to delete from the list textiles and textilemanufactures, toys and games, pottery, domestic sewing machines and cutlery. The President had also proposed that we should deletecanned pilchards,  but on this proposal the Economic PolicyCommittee had been unable to reach agreement.Discussion showed that the Cabinet were in general agreementwith; the Presidents proposals. The deletion of canned pilchardsfrom the list wouldL have little effect on! trade, since present importsof pilchards from Japan were negligible and they could; under theterms of the proposed treaty, be reinserted in the list if the situationchanged materially. Although there might be some politicalreactions in Cornwall, where unemployment was higher than average,on balance it would be preferable ^ in the interests of the trade negotiations to accept the deletion of&quot; canned pilchards from the list.In further discussion it was suggested that further consideration should be given to the precise significance of deleting ships and boatsfromAthe sensitive list, especially in^relation to ocean-going ships.The Cabinet--      .(1) Invited the President of the Board ofTrade to inform thePrime: Minister of the significance of deleting ships andboats from the sensitive list of products being negotiatedin connexion with the proposed commercial treaty with japan;(2) Subject to Conclusion (1), approved the proposals made bythe President of the Board of Trade for the contents ofthe sensitive list.country) was by no means unreasonable. Further consideration should therefore be given to this aspect of the question before adecision was reached.The Cabinet Agreed to resume at a later meeting their discussion of theproposal in C. (60) 191 for an experiment in subscriptiontelevision.

</content>
</cab>
