<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/9/113 images: 630-631</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SEC R E TaWeP5(G)(4l)  113. COPY NOo,19TH OCTOBER,  1941cWAR CABINET -,RECPUITMENT OF JEWISH UNITS FOR GENERAL service in&quot; THE BRITISH ARMY.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies91&apos;o With reference to W.M0(41) 102nd Conclusions paragraph.6,I  informed      the High Commissioner that, while the project forming a Jewish contingent in Great Britain mainly from united States recruits had been abandoned, it was desired toencourage enrolment of additional Palestinian Jews in themilitary and police forces In Palestine, primarily for- local defence, under such conditions of service as will proveattractive to recruits and acceptable to Jewish public opinion-Complaints as to unsympathetic treatment, especially in handling information as to the Jewish war effort, should besympathetically examined and if practicable a few purelyJewish&quot;units should be formed provided that this could bedone without undue publicity0.2o- v.   - The -High Cornmissioaer has not yet been able to discuss this &apos; with the. Goners&apos;!- Officcp Commanding Palestine,* bat has in; the meantime sent me-the following information about thepresent; powatwors in Palestine as- - regards recruiting. which I&apos; think will br. of -interest to the War Cabinet *(l)     service so- &apos;Apart from 1575 Jews in the RoAoFo and 3199 in theServices (R0Ao,. R.EU , R,A,-S DC OJ&apos; Signals-, R&apos;.A;0 3C 0, and R,A.M .0.)many of.&apos; whom .are technicians, there are 1340. Jews in the Buffs(7 Companies are.:purely Jewish) and 2832 in AJvUPoG 0 (purelyJewish Companies) and 475 in Port Operating &quot;Companies0     Thetotal number of Jews in the Services at present is thus 9351(this total includes 1505 Jews who.-are missing and prisonerswhose places it is desired to replace)*     The MilitaryAuthorities have urgent need, of more recruits and a vigorouscampaign sponsored by the Jewish Agency is at present inprogresso     They are giving it a maximum publicity,     For theBuffs, four additional Companies (720 men) are required forPalestine apart from the ten Companies under discussion for egypt and these are being embodied, as recruitment offers, upto the limit of training facilities and available equipment.
(2) Police.There are 920 Jews in the regular policej  2,620in the Jewish Settlement Police (the strength of whichhas been doubled in accordance with the decision takensome months ago);  2,230 temporary additional police.All these are embodied on full time basis.      In addition there are 16,000 special and supernumerary police whohave had some training.      Total Jewish Police 21,770.Grand total,  Services and Police 31,121.3.     As regards enlisting in purely Jewish units,Sir Harold MacMichael points out that in the Buffs,A.M.P.C., and almost all the Artisan Works CompaniesR.E., the Jews enlisted are in purely Jewish unitsalthough,  of course, they are within the framework ofthe British Army.      They are not grouped in formationslarger than Companies, Battalion formations being, inthe opinion of the Military Authorities, not required^4.      The High Commissioner states that, as he understandsthe position, tho authorities in Palestine, are alreadyacting on the lines contemplated by the War Cabinet1sdecisions.      Commenting on the allegations ofunsympathetic--handling on &quot;the.part of - these authorities of Jewish recruitment matters, he points out that the zionists? for political reasons, want a Jewish army as such, and suggests that this is the. reason for theseaccusations of lack of appreciation.      As regards actualterms of service, he is informed that important causes of dissatisfaction are:(a) payment on Maltese rates (two thirds ofBritish r ates) v/hen serving in Palestine.(b) Scale of family allowances (which Jewscontend do not cater for Jewish social service under which 51 dependant&quot; haswider rights than in British society).Those rates and scales are applied on theinstructions of the War Office.(ltd.)      M.Colonial Office.19th October, 1941a

</content>
</cab>
