<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/2/33 images: 366-377</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed forthe&apos; War Cabinet. November 1939.SECRET.&apos;:W.M. (39)99th Conclusions.Cojpy Eta.TO m KEPT TOPER LOCK AMD KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.MAR *ojyCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Thursday, November 30, 1939, at 11-30 a.m.PresentThe Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. L. Hore-Belisha,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.Viscount Halifax,State   for   foreign the Right hon secretary   ofAffairs.The    Right    Hon.    Winston    S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Sir Horace J. Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.The Right Hon.Secretary ofAffairs.Anthony Eden, M.P.,State for DominionN.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.Major-General H. R. S. Massy, deputy chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.ajor-General H. L. Ismay.n A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Mr. F. Hemming.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Wine Commander W. Elliot.
WAR CAM WET SB (80).minute no.123478101112Contents..   Subject,The Air Situation     .........The Naval Situation.........Defence of Scapa Flow.The Military Situation        ......Poison Gas     ...      .........Protection against A risene gases.Balkans and the Middle East......The strategical situation and General Weygand&apos;s activities.The Northern Barrage...........Iron Ore...............Swedish exports to Germany via Narvik.Suggested British action in Norwegian territorial waters.Finland ...Invasion by Soviet Union.Yugoslavia      ...      ...      ...      ...    .......Alleged agreement with Germany in regard to loans cancelled bythe Treaty of Versailles.Turkey : Discussion with M. Menemencoglu in London ...Supply of armaments to Turkey.Cancellation of the Suspensive Clause in the Anglo-turkish treaty.Commercial questions.JFl^SOlCG ( a a * a a a a a * * 9 a,* a * *&apos;* * * * a a *Attitude towards sharing in financial aid! to Allies.War Cabinet Arrangements ...      ...Page.261261262262262263264265266267268268
oL -TheSeer^^$$featsjjm.   .    j&amp;ty appro^bed^the. ee$st of Northum^(Previous       berland. In spite ofl^d ^ of, these had^ beenleference: intercepted and almost certainly shot down. The track of the second!w3)&amp;.. (8$) 98jh aircraft(t showed that it had conclusions,     to a point 12 miles South of Glasgow. This aircraft had not been minute 1.)       intercepted.During the previous night, two aircraft had been plotted offthe North Foreland, but owing to adverse weather conditions, it hadnot been possible to send fighters up to intercept them.a Air escort had again been provided for the submarine Triadduring daylight hours. One of the escorting aircraft had shot down a Dernier flying-boat. Seven other Dorniers had been engaged andthe rear-gunner in one of them had been seen to be hit. One ofour aircraft had been slightly damaged, but had returned safely.Intensive search for the Deutschland had continued.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.f be MasaiSituation.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 98thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The First Lord of the A dmiralty said that a British trawlerwhich had arrived at the Humber had reported having sighted aGerman pocket battleship and a smaller warship 50 miles North ofthe position in which H.M.S. Rawalpindi was sunk, on the24th November, i.e., 24 hours after the action. The First Lordinformed the War Cabinet of the Fleet dispositions in the continuedsearch for the Deutschland.H.M.S. Triad had been taken in tow by the destroyer Inglefieldon the previous afternoon. It was only possible to tow thesubmarine at 4 knots, and the Triad had been told that she haddiscretion - to seek refuge in Norwegian territorial waters ifnecessary.No attacks had been carried out on trade during the previous24 hours.The attack on a U-boat by H.M.S. Icarus, reported at theprevious meeting, had been successful. The submarine had been sunk and the entire crew taken prisoner. It had at first been hopedthat this was the U-boat commanded by Captain Prien, but this had proved not to be the case.Shipping conditions in the Downs were satisfactory and a large volume of shipping had sailed into and out of the Port of London.The Prime Minister asked whether the large amount ofshipping in the Downs did not provide a most vulnerable target inthe event of the Germans deciding to begin unrestricted air attackon shipping.The First Lord of the Admiralty agreed that the shipping inthe Downs, although mainly neutral, provided a very good target.It was possible that the communication made on the previous day by the German Naval Attache&quot; at The Hague to the Dutch naval staff (telegram No. 232 from the Netherlands) that all neutral shipping found in the approaches to the British Isles or france would be sunk without warning, foreshadowed such attacks. Therewajs similar concentration of shipping at the contraband controlbase at; kijkwaib If unrestricted attacks developed; we might haveto find alternative contraband control bases for both the Downs andkirkyralj,The] Prime Minister enquired&apos; as tip the arrangements forndiJgV shaping in the^defe:of Staff Sud-!ommittee should; hear;this&apos;p&quot;he&apos;   ... -     e an4^^ted
Defence ofSeap&amp;JpIow. .(previous reference: -W.M. (39)?08thConclusions,Minute 2.)In-reply to &amp;,- question Ay-the IMnie AMSnister, &quot;the Chiff ^pfMavah staff said \ that,- M&apos; reiuiMimg - -the: Djge of. -Siapa Flow&quot; asf iianchorage- for ertoimra,: only thaApart&apos; of the-anchorage would&apos; 60used which had been: umderAhe&apos;&apos; cm whichtherefore - it was - not&apos; thought possible that magnetic mines could have been sown.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.fte MilitarySitattoBo(previous reference:W.M. (39) 98thConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The Secretary of State for War said that there was nothing to report from the Western Front;.The War Office had sent a General Officer to the ShetlandIslands to carry out a reconnaissance and to organise the raising ofHome Defence Units. As a temporary measure two companies of infantry, with eight light Anti-Aircraft Automatics, were on their way to the Islands. A number of rifles were also being sent.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Masn Gas.ProtectionagainstArsene Gases.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 93rdConclusions,Minute 6.)ESffiltams ami fflmaBIls BastThe strategical situation andGeneralWeygand&apos;activities.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 95thConclusions,Minute 5.)4. The Secretary of State for War asked whether the WarCabinet still required periodical reports in connection with the deliveries of extension bases for service respirators designed to giveprotection against arsene gases.The Prime Minister suggested, and the War Cabinet agreed That further reports were unnecessary provided that thesituation remained satisfactory.5. The War Cabinet had under consideration a Report by theChiefs of Staff on the Strategical Situation in South-East europe and the activities of General Weygand (Paper W.P. (39) 142).The Chief of the Air Staff recapitulated the main points inthe Report of the Chiefs of Staff, and explained General Weygand&apos;sproposals for secret conversations with the Greeks and his general attitude with regard to the policy to be adopted in the Balkans.The Chiefs of Staff thought that General Weygand had gone beyondthe policy which had been agreed between His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment and the French Government; and that this view should beintimated to the French Government through diplomatic channels.The First Lord of the Admiralty hoped that this divergence ofview would be conveyed in terms consonant with the respect due to do  distinguished a person as General Weygand. He questioned whether (a) and (6) in paragraph 6 of the Chiefs of Staff Reportrepresented the only alternatives which would ensure Balkanneutrality. Personally, he thought that the Balkans were graduallyveering towards the Allies; and that, if Greece, Roumania and yugoslavia were to come in on our side, it might even be possiblethat Italy would eventually declare war in favojli&quot; of the Allies.TM]Seereti^jo^-State for Foreign Affairs feW that it was ^erydifficult to forecast the future attitude of the Balkan Countries.He was, however, in- favour of dissuading General Weygand from taking measures which might disturb the present equilibrium, andhe mow agreed with the Chiefs, of -Staff .t&amp;at -this would be better&quot;dope through our ilihbassador.r;&apos;    ;r:   l&apos;AA?A-,-AA&apos;; TteWaf Cabinet-- - f;: --A&apos;&quot;///&quot;A AA AA :A: :&apos;...&apos; - A-:&apos;p-h- &apos;(!)&apos;-Approved&apos; theLRegw^ on- -General&apos;; &apos;A&apos;!&quot;&apos;Weygffi3*s&apos;-f- :W.P:::(SS))yi4i).;.. . &apos;--;&quot;;:h-&apos;3^-^p^^v^-^^^;
263(SB).(2) Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to instruct His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Paris to suggest to the French Government in the most tactful way thatthey should take steps to ensure that there should be nodeparture from the policy in regard to the Balkanswhich had been agreed between the two Governments.(3) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, during his forth-coming visit to Paris, to convey to our Ambassador ingeneral terms the views of the War Cabinet in thismatter in amplification of the official instructionsconveyed to him in accordance with (2) above.Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty (paper memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(Paper W.P. (39) 143).The First Lord of the A dmiralty drew attention to the protec-tion which would be afforded by a Northern Barrage, drawn fromthe Orkney Islands to Norway, against the enemy&apos;s surface vessels,as well as against U-boats. In operations such as those in whichthe Fleet was engaged at the present time, the Barrage would be ofgreat value. He also emphasised the support which a NorthernBarrage would afford to our Contraband Control in the North Sea.The Barrage would be at such a distance from the German basesthat mine-sweeping operations against it would be impracticableexcept as part of a major operation supported by the German Fleet,which would in its turn give our own Fleet the opportunity for seeking battle, which it desired.The First Lord explained that the Barrage would be of great value even if it stopped at the edge of the Norwegian territorial waters, and thus left a navigable passage between the end of the barrage and the coast of Norway. The value of the Barrage would,of course, be enhanced if later it was found possible to carry it right up to the Norwegian coast.The Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs said that his memorandum (Paper W.P. (39) 143), which was of a historicalcharacter, brought out the reluctance of the Norwegian Governmentin August 1918 to complete the Eastern end of the barrage, thenunder construction, by laying mines in their territorial waters. by september 1918, however, this reluctance had been overcome, butonly as the result of the influence exerted by the Allied militarysuccesses and by Germany&apos;s increasing internal weakness. In thepresent war we had not yet arrived at a similar stage, and it wouldbe imprudent to count on being able to persuade Norway to close the eastern end of our projected Barrage.The First Sea Lord gave a technical explanation of the mannerin which the Barrage would be laid. The preparations, includingthe construction of the mines and the conversion of ships to mine-layers, would take approximately six months. When these steps were complete progress would be rapid. The next step would beto declare the whole area to be covered by the Barrage a dangerousarea. Every ship, in every part of the world, had a right to receivethat notification, and a delay of about one month appeared to be essential for this purpose. If, therefore, mine-laying was to begin on the 1st June next, our notifications ought to be put out about the1st May. The first stage would be to lay the surface mines, whichwould probably take only a week. We should then lay the deepmines down to 400 feet^-a depth below which no submarine could the Northern6.   the documents: The  War  Cabinet  had  before  them   the  followingW.P. (39) 126).[20425]b 3
i&quot;9 - 264dive. The total laying time would be about three months. Therewould be gateways in the mineTfield through which surface vesselscould pass, passages where deep mines would be. laid, but nosurface mines. The Pentland Firth ; also would be uncovered,providing another passage for surface vessels.The First Sea Lord said that the Admiralty now proposed toamend somewhat the plan in Paper W.P. (39) 126. Paragraph 15of that Memorandum spoke of 181,000 mines, all of the contact type.The new proposal was to substitute antennae mines for contactmines (except for the surf ace mines), thus reducing the total numberof mines required to some 60,000.As a consequence of this alteration of the plan, only five mine-carrying ships would now be required (as against the estimate often ships in the Memorandum), and the total cost would be diminished by some  3 million.Some discussion took place as to the date at which our decisionto lay down the Barrage should be announced. It was agreed thatthe present was an unpropitious time to make an announcement onthe matter, and that the right course was to go ahead with our preparations, but to keep the whole matter secret until a monthbefore the time when we were ready to start laying the Barrage.The War Cabinet agreed : (i) That preparations should be put in hand forthwith for the laying of the Northern Barrage, on the general lines proposed in Paper W.P. (39) 126.(ii) That no announcement should be made at the present timein regard to this project,(iii) That a decision should be deferred as to the dates (a) atwhich the area concerned should be notified as a dangerous area, and (&amp;) at which the laying of mines should begin.Iron Qm.Swedish exportsto Germany viaNarvik.SuggestedBritish actionin Norwegianterritorialwaters.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 68thConclusions,Minute 8.)7. In the course of the discussion on the preceding item, theFirst Lord of the Admiralty suggested that there was no need as yet to be exercised over the difficulties which we might experience with the Norwegian Government as regards measures to close the gap at the eastern end of the Northern Barrage. It seemed almost certain that at a much earlier date we should have trouble withthe Norwegian Government over the trade in Swedish, ironnorebetween Narvik and German ports. During the coming winter months, when the Baltic was frozen, this trade would hug theNorwegian coast in order to avoid our Naval Control. Just beforethe end of the last war we had been able to deprive Germany ofthese iron-ore imports by mining Norwegian territorial waters, andthus forcing the ore ships into the open sea. The time was comingwhen we should have to consider taking similar measures. A fewsmall mine-fields, each of perhaps three or four miles square, wouldbe enough for the purpose.In reply to a question, the First Lord said that the germans had already been laying mines off the Swedish coast. broadly speaking, however, they had not violated Swedish neutrality inso doing, but had confined themselves to laying mines in the area between three and four miles from the coast. This was enough tomake all shipping of a deeper draught than, say, 17 feet go outside territorial water. The Swedes were attempting) to counter thisby dredging channels nearer inshore.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs thought there wouldbe serious difficulties in the^way of the measures suggested. Itwas certain that, if we now &quot;asked the Norwegian Government for permission to minetheir terrrtoriMtwaters^
265W;lf.Q0(89).a flat refusal. We were thus faced with some very important&apos;de^8iosi(:;Of^poMd3r.v&apos;&apos;&apos;&apos;&apos; Those ^deeisibinisij&apos; tie -considered, would haveto wait until we had investigated (a) The military, problems involved, including the possibilitiesofretaliation; open to Germany, both by mine layingand otherwise^ :(6) The economic considerations involved, (i) to Germany, asa result of her being deprived of the iron ore, and (li) to ourselves, result of German retaliation in theeconomic, sphere.(c) The imponderable factors whieh ought to be taken intoaccount, including the moral and legal aspects of theviolation of Norwegian neutrality.A preliminary examination on the above lines might show thatwe should be well advised to proceed cautiously. If we deferredaction until we had put down the Northern Barrage, we should then be able to press the Norwegian Government to prevent Germanvessels from making use of the gap left at its eastern end. Ifthe Norwegian Government failed to take the necessary steps, therewould be a stronger case for this country taking action to control the gap.The First Lord of the Admiralty agreed that it was essential togo into all the considerations which the Foreign Secretary had mentioned. For example, the attitude of the United States mightbe a determining factor.-The War Cabinet-(i) Invited the Chiefs of Staff to prepare an appreciation ofthe military factors involved if we took steps to stop theimportation of iron ore to Germany by the sea route from Narvik, either by stationing a Naval force in theVest Fjord, or by laying a minefield on the norwegian coast, so as to force all trade to pass out of territorial waters. This appreciation should deal, in particular,with the counter measures which Germany could takeby way of retaliation.(ii) Invited the Minister of Economic Warfare to consider,in consultation with the other Ministers concerned, (a) the effect on Germany&apos;s economic position of stopping the importation of iron ore by the sea route from Narvik;(6) the counter measures which Germany might take inthe economic field (e.g., the cutting off of all exports to this country from Scandinavian andBaltic countries), and the effect of these measureson our economic position.(iii) Invited the Military Co-ordination Committee, togetherwith the Minister of Economic Warfare, to consider theBeports to be furnished under (i) and (ii), and to report thereon to the War Cabinet.Finland. 8.   The War Cabinet were informed that confirmation hadinvasion by been: receivedFinnishSoviet Union. Frontier north-east of Lake Ladoga, and that firing had taken place(Previous across the                                                            not as yetBeference: confirmed, that^Helsinki had been bombed from the air.w.M. (89) 98th The total Finnish Forces consisted of about 350,000 men,Conclusions, comprising nine weak divisions, supported by a number of unitsMinute 8.) corresponding: to-our Territorials; $$egr Vttd-*.32*&apos;tenlQ3:&apos;ttlid-- 120 first line aircraft. On the Finnish frontier the Soviet had 350,000 men,
,266 :r .750 tanks and 1,500 first line aircraft. The Finns were probablyunduly self-confident of\their ability to defend ith^msblvbs againstthe Russians..The Prime Minister said that he would have to answer aPrivate Notice Question in the House that afternoon as-to theRussian invasion of Finland.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that a draft was being prepared setting out the information so far received.The importance of the Answer, however, would lie in the attitude which we took in regard to Russia&apos;s action. He thought that the reply should show our strong disapproval of Russia&apos;s action, but atthe same time should not lose sight of the fact that there was no effective action which we could take in the matter. It was undesirable, therefore, that we should put ourselves in a position inwhich we might be asked why, if we felt so strongly in the matter,we had not declared war on Russia. He therefore suggested thatthe reply should refer to the Russian case, namely, that they desiredto be able to defend themselves against aggression from whateverquarter; it should contain a statement that we felt sure thatFinland was.prepared to agree to any reasonable demands; andshould conclude by pointing out that in our view the matters in dispute were capable of settlement by negotiation, and that wedeeply regretted that Russia had not taken advantage of the offer of arbitration made by the United States.The Prime Minister thought that it would be very difficult to confine the reply to a strictly impartial statement of the russian and Finnish cases. The situation demanded some expression ofreprobation.The First Lord of the A dmiralty thought that we ought not tobe deterred from expressing disapproval by consideration of thepossible effects on the Russians, who were impervious to words.The Chancellor of the Exchequer suggested that M. Molotov&apos;broadcast on the previous evening, in which he had laid the blameon ourselves and the French as the people who had been determined to attack Germany, almost necessitated some plain speaking on our part.After some further discussion, the War Cabinet: Invited the. Prime Minister and the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs, in drafting a reply to the Private notice question, to bear in mind the War Cabinet&apos;s view thatexpression should be given to our strong sense ofdisapproval of Russia&apos;s action.Yugoslavia.Alleged agree-meht withGermany inregard to loanscancelled by theTreaty ofVersailles.9. The Secretary of State for War drew attention to a stament published m the Daily Mail that morning to the effectThatGermany, as part of a scheme for securing war supplies fromYugoslavia, had compelled Yugoslavia to make payments^ respeSlffn?wWar bT Fuant?d by Gmnany anS iTstria-Hunglrywhich had been cancelled by the Treaty of Versailles.N.N.I.^^SS^^f 8U**i that he hadno information on this matter, but would look ii^t.
toSupply ofarmamentsTurkey.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 47th-Conclusions,Minute 7.)Cancellation ofthe SuspensiveClause in theAnglo-turkish treaty.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 75thConclusions,Minute 10.)Commercialquestions.10. The Secretary&apos; of State for Foreign Affairs said that hexa had a long discussion with M. Numah Menemencoglu, theecreta^ Office.  The substance ofthis discussion might be summarised as follows: M. Menemencoglu had raised at once the question of thesupply of armaments to Turkey. He recognised the effort which we had made in meeting the requests put forward byGeneral Orbay. &quot;The latter was at present conducting discus-sions in Paris, but he (M. Menemencoglu) was not very hopefulof their outcome. The questions outstanding, to which theTurkish Government attached the greatest importance, werethe supply of anti-aircraft and anti-tank guns. As regardsanti-tank guns, they asked for 800 for the frontier in Thrace,and 200 for the front on the Caucasus. M. Menemencogluappeared to anticipate that Turkey would be in the war onour side next Spring, and it was, he urged, of the utmost importance that the Turkish front should be held.The Secretary of State, after saying that no doubtM. Menemencoglu would discuss this question in detail withthe Minister for Co-ordination of Defence, had told him thathe attached great importance to the removal of the SuspensiveClause. Turkey had a direct interest in this also, since, when this was out of the way, they would be able to get their Goldloan, and would also secure the purchase by this country of turkish tobacco.M. Menemencoglu had replied that he was in possession of full powers to sign a Protocol, bringing the Suspensive Clauseto an end, but these full powers were conditional upon asatisfactory solution being obtained in regard to anti-aircraft and anti-tank guns. What he had in mind apparently wasthat these might be purchased from the United States withmoney obtained from us.On commercial questions, M. Menemencoglu had referredboth to British loans to Turkey and to the purchase of Turkishtobacco. Germany had previously taken the greater part of turkish exports which had turned largely upon the supply ofchrome. If these were not to be supplied in future to Germany,some other country must take them. On financial questions,M. Menemericoglu was seeing the Chancellor of the Exchequerand, on commercial questions, the Minister of economic warfare.M. Menemencoglu had said that he was under orders toreturn to Turkey in a fortnight, and that he hoped to concludehis visit to London within a week.The Secretary of State added that it was evident thatM. Menemencoglu intended to take a very stiff line on the subjectof anti-aircraft and anti-tank guns, and he (the Secretary of State)was not hopeful of securing the removal of the Suspensive Clauseunless we could give some satisfaction on this point.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that after the exactingand detailed discussions which had taken place with General Orbay,and the great efforts which had.been made to meet his requests, itwas most embarrassing for the question to be reopened by a Turkishrepresentative of higher standing.The Minister for Corordinaiion of[Defence said that theTurkish intention appeared &quot;to be that, if we could not supply the arms required, they should be purchased from Germany in exchange for supplies of chrome;The Secretary of State for War said that the demands madeby M. Mehemencpglu for guns, were put of all proportion either toour/capacity to supply, or/tp. the&apos; military, needs of the fronts irn
from^^fc^^8- hopes of obtaining,ambe given at his interview that afternoon with M MenenSco^.The War Cabinet took note of the above discussion.Framoe. 11.   In the course of the discussion recorded in Minute 9 above,Attitude the Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the situation as regardstowards sharing the sharing by France in the giving of financial aid to our allies in financial was far from satisfactory. He had received a communication fromaid to Allies. M. Reynaud stating that the view of the French Government wasthat the wealth of France was only one-third of that of this country(it was not clear from M. Reynaud s letter whether in this connexionhe was referring to the United Kingdom or the British Empireas a whole). For this reason, M. Reynaud had stated that theFrench Government considered that when financial aid was givento Allies, the burden of such aid should be divided between thiscountry and France in the proportion of three to one. On the otherhand, M. Reynaud had demanded for France a share of the proceeds of the loan to be made to this country by Canada, though in what proportion was not clear. The attitude of the French Governmentin this matter was one which we could not possibly accept.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.12. The Prime Minister explained that it was intended to devote as much time as possible at the Meeting to be held on Fridaymorning to consideration of the Secretary of State for War&apos;s paper on the State of Equipment and Maintenance Position of the FirstTen Divisions.It was also proposed to have a general discussion on Shippingmatters early in the ensuing week, probably on Tuesday. Thequestion whether this discussion took place at one of the normalMeetings of the War Cabinet, or at a Special Meeting in the afternoon, would depend on the amount of other business to betransacted.The War Cabinet :-(i) Took note of the above arrangements.(ii) Agreed that the Meeting of the War Cabinet on Saturday,the 2nd December, should take place at 10*30 a.m., andthat if this plan was found to be generally convenient,the Meetings on Saturdays would normally be held atthis hour.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,November 30, 1939.



</content>
</cab>
