<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/154/0 images: 115-118</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fcCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(70) 113 COPY NO   w 030 November 1970CABINETTHE SIMONS TOY/N AGREEMENT AND ARMS FOR SOUTH africa memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth affairs,        The Prime Ivlinifter and I have had talks during the last threemonths with a number of Commonwealth, and particularly African,leaders and have explained to them the reasons for the intention whichwe stated last July of resuming certain limited arms sales to South Africa.It has become clear that the objections of African leaders are based on the contention that the sale of any arms at all would confer respectability on aGovernment and country which insults the dignity of Africans by denyingthem political equality.    While they do not reject the security argumentout of hand, they argue that the threat should be met in some other waythan by sales of arms to South Africa which in their eyes have the effectof lining us up with a white minority Government.2.        Certain Commonwealth countries feel so strongly about the issueof apartheid that they threaten reprisals against us if we proceed with thesale.    The threats vary from leaving the Commonwealth, or sssaspellingBritain from the Commonwealth, to economic action against Britain.The last could include the transfer of sterling balances; a co-ordinatedagreement between African countries to exclude British companies fromcontracts or competitive investment (several prospects are being held insuspense by African Governments at present) with the object of ensuring that the net economic outcome of sales to South Africa is a loss; and theimposition of restrictions of various kinds which adversely affect the.operations of e. g, British oil fields in Nigeria.    There is also alikelihood of physical attacks, whether inspired or spontaneous, onour property and citizens in some African countries where we hav*large communities at risk.3,        If we were to announce a decision now to sell arms to SouthAfrica we should have to accept the risk of some leaving theCommonwealth and of some saying they would not attend theCommonwealth Prime Ministers&apos; Meeting.    The consequentiallong-term effects are difficult to estimate.    They would be likely
to include economic reprisals; a probable increase in Soviet and Chineseinfluence on land in Central Africa; and an unquantifiable loss of influencefor the United Kingdom in the world as a whole.    If it were not called off,or postponed, the Commonwealth Prime Minister a1 Meeting in Singaporein January would take place in a truncated form and in a souredatmosphere.4.        If we decide to stand by the policy of fulfilling the spirit of theSimons town Agreement, as I think we should, we should have a better chance of minimising adverse effects if we avoided an announcementbetween now and the Singapore Conference, which because of the closenessof the latter, might give the impression of indifference to Commonwealthopinion.    There is in any case little time left before Parliament rises forthe Christmas Recess and of the time available some will be taken up bycommitments involving the absence from London of the Prime Minister ormyself.    The only practical time that I can see for an early announcement would be in the period 7-&quot;3.0 December,,    The Tanzanian National Day fallson 9 December, Kenya Independence Day on 12 December,    Those public holidays are occasions when crowds gather and Ministers make speeches,and emotion runs high.    An announcement of a decision immediately beforeeither of those days could provoke angry demonstrations and increase the likelihood of damaging reactions.    In mid-December some hundreds ofschoolchildren from this country travel to join their parents in countires overseas for the Christmas holidays,,    The increase in British communitiesat risk would add to our anxieties,,5,        The best solution would seem to be to go to Singapore,    During theConference we would leave the Prime Ministers in no doubt that we shouldhave to sell some arms to South Africa so as to honour obligations already undertaken in the Simons town Agreement,    The main points to be covered in our discussions should beSaa      Wo shall continue to supply South Africa with spares andother items which were being supplied by the previous Administra-tion.b. There is a legal obligation to complete the equipment of thefrigates already sold with naval submarine spotter helicopters(Wasps) for which they have been fitted,c. We shall be prepared to consider orders for equipment andarms necessary to maintain South Africa&apos;s naval contribution to thejoint defence of the sea routes at its present operationaleffectiveness.We hope that before the Singapore Meeting we will obtain from theSouth African Government an undertaking that they will not redeployany arms which we supply for purposes other than the defence of the
sea routes.    We would say that we were ready for the present to limitsales in this way -10       because v/e hoped to see progress towards a dialogue betweenAfrican countries and South Africa and a modification ofapartheid which would eliminate the threat of war, and2.      in order to study, with any other commonwealth countries who might be interested, the security of thewhole of the Indian Ocean to see if a broader basis fordefenoa could be devised.    For that purpose at a convenienttime we would be willing to join in a Ministerial Conference,6,        I think that if we make clear at the Singapore Meeting that our minds are made up and that we are not prepared to be deflected from our intention v/e shall be able to secure some support from other commonwealth Governments to reduce the damage to our interests.At Singapore the forces that work for the preservation of the Commonwealthwill be at their strongest,,    Reason and persuasion will make an impactand with other important work being taken the members will be reluctant to break up the association,7,        Arrangements on these lines would also enable us to consider further the relationships between the problems of arms for South africa and of Rhodesia,    I have arranged for a study of this to be put in handand I shall report further to my colleagues in the Defence and overseas policy Conuailee,8,        It is fair that I should put the case for saying that we intend tosell arms and will accept orders now.    It would please the majorityof the party! it would show decision; it would remove the feeling thatif we go to Singapore v/e will be bumped off our policy.    There is toothe possibility that with a longer interval the doubters will add to their numbers.    It would avoid ganging up at Singapore,9,        I have carefully balanced these arguments,,    I come down infavour of going to Singapore because I believe that we have just a chanceof getting the best of both wovlds and because I would not like to see theCommonwealth break before a meeting of Prime Ministers.A D-HFo^ign azsd Coiamoawealth OffSco SWl30 November 1970


</content>
</cab>
