<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/154/0 images: 145-245</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
OCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYT3 government cp(70) 117 COPY NO     0 010 December 1970CABINETREPORT OF THE PUBLIC EXPENDITURE survey committee 1970Memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer,        In Cmnd 4515 &quot;New Policies for Public Spending&quot; we published the outcome of the review of public expenditure which we undertookimmediately we came into office.    This enabled us to decide on, and to publish, estimates for all the main functional programmes in 1971-72 andfor broader groups of programmes by 1974-75.    But this left a good deal to be done in working out the full implications of those decisions, notably in the progression of expenditure plans in the intervening years up to1974-75; and in working out the effects for individual services of certainbroad policy decisions.2.        This work has now been completed and the results are fully set outin the report of the Public Expenditure Survey Committee 1970 which I now circulate.    This consists of a main report, together with detailedanalyses describing the basis of the estimates for all the individual services, and additional tables giving further analyses by economic content,spending authority, etc.3.        The average annual percentage increase in total public expenditure at constant prices from 1969-70 to 1974-75 is 2.8 per cent (Table 1 of themain report): broadly in line with the current growth of capacity in the economy as a whole, which we have yet to improve.    There are moderatevariations in the rates of increase year by year, but these variations are think within acceptable limits.    This is in line with what we said in cmnd 4515, although inevitably there have been some changes in individual programmes as events external to Departmental planning impinge on themand as our policies are further developed.    These changes are summarised in Table 6 of the report.4.        The rates of growth over the period of the Individual programmes are set out in Table 2 of the main report.    The resulting distribution ofpublic expenditure is shown in Table 3,    Both tables show how ourprogrammes compare with those which our predecessors published in theirWhite Paper last year, Cmnd 4234,    I think that the comparisons fullyvindicate the new approach which v/e are adopting to the control of public spending and priorities within it.1
5, Table 2 also brings out the important point that a simple constant price projection substantially understates the proportion of the national output which certain services will require in real terms in future years.Allowing for this by means of the relative price effect it will be seen thatcertain programmes, particularly those which make heavy demands on public service manpower, grow appreciably faster than the constant pricefigures indicate.    And the growth over the period of the public sectorTsdirect demands on goods and services, as distinct from transfer and other payments, is as much as 4 per cent, after including the relative price effect.6.        We achieved in our public expenditure review prospective net savings in 1974-75 of about  1100 million^ (which is equivalent to rather more than 300 million in demand) after allowing for the tax concessions to industry which were an essential offset to the gross savings on investment grants.However, as I reminded my colleagues in the Cabinet discussion on14th September, I estimated that the plans which we inherited would have involved increasing the current level of taxation by more than  300 million(equivalent to at least  200 million in demand) by 1974,    The cost of theincome tax reduction which I announced on 27 October will by 1974 be well over the initial cost of  350 million (that is, well over  250 million in demand) because of the growth of incomes.    On this basis v/e are unlikely to have more than some  250- 300 million in demand in hand for 1974, sothat our room for further manoeuvre remains strictly limited.7.        Moreover the medium term development of the economy isovershadowed by the current strong inflationary trend deriving mainly from very high wage settlements.    We are determined to halt and reversethis trend, thus restoring the rate of increase of prices and incomes to an acceptable level.    But it is clear that we must leave ourselves as muchfreedom of action as possible in shaping our policies for the allocation of resources,8.        Cmnd 4515 demonstrates that we have made a valuable impact withour new approach to the role of the public sector and the new prioritieswe are establishing.    However, v/e have made it clear that the processis by no means complete, and I hope that we shall secure substantialfurther savings, including those which will spring from the full review of departmental functions in response to the Prime Minister^ request.    Inthe circumstances which I have described we should seek to make every possible further economy consistent with our general policies.9.        &quot;We are committed to publishing the text in the annual series of public expenditure White Papers early in the new year and I think that we should aim to do this as soon as possible after Parliament reassembles on12 January.    The actual date can be settled with the Lord President of theCouncil.*A11 the figures in this paragraph are at 1970 constant prices.2
5. Table 2 also brings out the important point that a simple constant price projection substantially under states the proportion of the national output v/hich certain services will require in real terms in future years.Allowing for this by means of the relative price effect it will be seen thatcertain programmes, particularly those which make heavy demands on public service manpower, grow appreciably faster than the constant pricefigures indicate.    And the growth over the period of the public sector&apos;sdirect demands on goods and services, as distinct from transfer and other payments, is as much as 4 per cent, after including the relative price effect.6.        We achieved in our public expenditure review prospective net savings in 1974-75 of about  1100 million^ (which is equivalent to rather more than 800 million in demand) after allowing for the tax concessions to industry which were an essential offset to the gross savings on investment grants.However, as I reminded my colleagues in the Cabinet discussion on14th September, I estimated that the plans which we inherited would have involved increasing the current level of taxation by more than  300 million(equivalent to at least  200 million in demand) by 1974,    The cost of theincome tax reduction which I announced on 27 October will by 1974 be well over the initial cost of  350 million (that is, well over  250 million in demand) because of the growth of incomes.    On this basis we are unlikely to have more than some  250- 300 million in demand in hand for 1974, sothat our room for further manoeuvre remains strictly limited.7.        Moreover the medium term development of the economy isovershadowed by the current strong inflationary trend deriving mainly from very high wage settlements.    We are determined to halt and reversethis trend, thus restoring the rate of increase of prices and incomes to an acceptable level.    But it is clear that we must leave ourselves as muchfreedom of action as possible in shaping our policies for the allocation of resources.8.        Cmnd 4515 demonstrates that we have made a valuable impact withour new approach to the role of the public sector and the new prioritieswe are establishing.   However, we have made it clear that the processis by no means complete, and I hope that we shall secure substantialfurther savings, including those which will spring from the full review of departmental functions in response to the Prime Ministers request.    Inthe circumstances which I have described we should seek to make every possible further economy consistent with our general policies.9,        We are committed to publishing the text in the annual series of public expenditure White Papers early In the new year and I think that we should aim to do this as soon as possible after Parliament reassembles on12 January.    The actual date can be settled with the Lord President of theCouncil.*A11 the figures in this paragraph are at 1970 constant prices.2
CONCLUSIONS10.       I therefore ask my colleagues -a. to note the pattern of expenditure as costed in this reportfor the period to 1974-75, and to agree that public expenditure asa whole should be so managed that it is kept within the totals foreach year of the periodjb. to approve, subject to c. below, the costings of theindividual expenditure programmes set out in Table 5 of thereport as maxima for the purposes of management of the programmes; subject also to the point about &quot;unprogrammable&quot;services in paragraph 14 of the main report;c. to agree that the search for further savings should bevigorously pursued, including those which may arise from the review of functions commissioned by the Prime Ministerjd. to commission a draft White Paper on Public Expenditureon the above basis, for publication as soon as possible afterParliament reassembles.A treasury Chambers SW19 December 1970
THIS DOCUMENT is the property of her britannic majesty&apos;s government copy no.  g g 0PUBLICEXPENDITURETO 1974-75Main Report1970 Report by the Public expenditure survey CommitteeDecember 1970
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy No.   080PUBLICEXPENDITURETO 1974-75Main Report1970 Report by the Public expenditure survey CommitteeDecember 1970
ECRETcontentsPUBLIC EXPENDITURE TO 1974-751970 REPORT BY THE PUBLIC EXPENDITURE SURVEYCOMMITTEEMAIN REPORTcontentscontent of the report........summary of 1970 survey costings......public expenditure in relation to the development of the economypublic expenditure: balance between programmesrecommendations.........Page22-  23 &apos;.35tablestable 1. public expenditure by groups of programmes, 1969-70 to 1974-75 .      :      .      .       stable 2. public expenditure: rate of increase by programme over survey period at constant prices  .      .      .   ,  .      .      .      .   &quot;&apos;.     &apos;:&apos;      .      . .       4table 3. public expenditure: distribution by groups of programmes as percentage of totalexpenditure, 1969-70, 1973-74 and 1974-75     .......5table4. public expenditure: summary analysis by programme, 1969-70 to 1974-75 withrelative price effect attributed to individual programmes    .....       6table 5. public expenditure: summary analysis by programme, 1969-70 to 1974-75 withrelative price effect as overall adjustment of total expenditure     ....       7table 6. public expenditure: comparison of 1970 survey with cmnd. 4515 ....       8table 7. public expenditure: summary analysis by economic and resource categories    .      .      10secret11296
PUBLIC EXPENDITURE SURVEY, 1970IntroductionThe results of the review of public expenditure which the Government launched immediately ontaking ofBce were published in &quot; New Policies for public Spending&quot;, Cmnd. 4515. Net savingswere achieved of about  330 million in 1971-72and nearly  1,600 million in 1974-75 in straightpublic expenditure terms. The decisions takenin that review enabled firm figures to be publishedfor all the main functional programmes for1971-72, and in broader groups of programmes for 1974-75. But the implications for the fullcosting and control of individual services, and decisions on the allocations for the intervening years, remained to be worked out.2. This report of the Public Expenditure survey committee now displays the full costings andeconomic analysis of present public expenditurepolicies for each of the five years 1970-71 to1974-75. These costings have been agreed^)between the Treasury and Departments, embody-ing the decisions already taken by Ministers on1971-72 and 1974-75 and, subject to Ministers&apos;approval, in respect of the intervening years. Theywould then form the basis for the annual white paper on Public Expenditure which is due tobe presented to Parliament early in the newyear.3. The annual Survey, initiated in 1961following the Plowden Report on the Control ofPublic Expenditure (Cmnd. 1432), is normallyprepared as a comprehensive operation covering the whole public sector each Spring. But the costings reflect the outcome of the continuinganalysis and review of programmes and policiesas it is carried on throughout the year by theDepartments and the Treasury; and the recentspecial review of public expenditure took as itspoint of origin the &quot; previous policies&quot; estab-lished in the Spring exercise.Content of the report. The Report sets out, against a very briefsummary of the wider economic background:0) Points on which further decisions will be needed indue course are noted in the texts in Appendix Part 1.(a) A full progression of expenditure on all the functional programmes defence, housing,health, education, etc. for each of thefive years up to 1974-75, consistent,except where otherwise stated, withCmnd. 4515 (paragraphs 5-7, Table 1,and Tables 4 and 5 at the end of this mainReport).(b) A summary of the rates of increase or decrease in the expenditure programmesover the period and of the distribution ofexpenditure between them; and a com-parison with the corresponding patterns ofthe plans of the previous Administration(paragraphs 10-14 and Tables 2 and 3).(c) A comparison of the 1970 Survey withthe costings published in Cmnd. 4515,showing changes and the reasons forthem (Table 6).(d) Recommendations (paragraph 15).Descriptions and analysis of all the programmes are given in more detail in the Appendix to thisReport, Part 1; and Appendix Parts 2 and 3contain methodology and further detailed analyses.Summary of 1970 Survey costings5. The picture thus disclosed shows that total public expenditure is expected to grow by anannual average rate of 2-8 per cent over theperiod 1969-70 to 1974-75 in real terms,excluding investment grants from the figuresthroughout: and that the year-by-year variations in the rate of growth are not excessive. Withinthe total, however, there is a gradual shift overthe years towards expenditure on employing man-power and on construction, equipment and otherdirect purchases of goods and services. Theseexpenditures, which represent 65 per cent of total public expenditure in 1969-70, will, as Table 7shows, account for 70 per cent by 1974-75; andthey are the forms of expenditure  which make a relatively greater demand on resources.6. The following table shows the levels ofexpenditure of the main groups of programmesover the period.
TABLE public expenditure by groups of programmes: 1969-70 to 1974-75	1969-70 provisional outturn   million	1970-71 estimate   million	1971-72 estimate   million	1972-73 estimate   million	1973-74 estimate   million	1974-75 estimate   million at 1970 Survey prices						Defence and external relations	2,820-6	2,771-3	2,719-7	2,664-8	2,704-2	2,740-2Commerce and industry .	1,648-8	1,696-2	1,670-4	1,359-4	1,115-8	959-5Nationalised industries capital expenditure	1,446-2	1,501-3	1,496-0	1,546-3	1,627-2	1,759-9Transport and miscellaneous local services .	3,413-7	3,683-3	3,799-7	3,958-3	4,077-0	4,184-social serviccs*.....	8,157-6	8,397-4	8,662-6	8,930-2	9,198-9	9,406-other services ......	921-3	1,004-8	1,026-8	1,061-8	1,090-4	1,123-4Debt interestf.....	2,186-0	2,103-0	1,980 0	1,950-0	1,890-0	1,8100Contingency reservef     .      .		 	900	130 0	1800	245-0Shortfall      .      .      .      ...		-200-0	-100-0	-1000	-1000	-100-0Relative price effect and other adjustments .	603-9	856-8	968-4	1,155-1	1,364-5	1,570-9At 1970-71 outturn prices						Total    .     .     .     .      .	.   21,198-1	21,814-1	22,313-6	22,655-9	23,148-0	23,699-8Annual percentage increases in total public expenditure!		% 3-4	% 2 1	% 30	% 2-8	% 2-7Average annual percentage increase 1969-70 to 1974-75?		 	 	 	sl  	2-S* Includes provision for improvements and upratings of social security benefits.t The estimates of debt interest rest on certain conventional assumptions (see Appendix Part 2, Methodology, paragraph 7).t As in Cmnd. 4515 the contingency reserve is shown net of the general reductions in local authority current expenditure whichhave been decided in the context of the Rate Support Grant negotiations. The contingency reserve will be increased when these reductions are allocated.I These annual percentage changes are calculated with expenditure on investment grants excluded.7. Forward estimates of public expenditure are continually changing, certainly in detail, and insome cases in programme totals, as factorsexternal to Departmental planning impinge onthe provision which has to be made, and aspolicies develop. Table 6 at the end of this mainreport shows and explains such changes since cmnd. 4515 was published.Public expenditure in relation to the developmentof the economy8. The various public expenditure programmesinvolve in varying degrees demands on resources,depending on whether they represent final expen-diture by public bodies on goods and services,transfer payments e.g. social security payments-or purchases or sales of existing assets. their claims on the national output thus compete withthe requirements of the other main sectors ofthe economy for which allowance has to be made,namely the balance of payments, private invest-ment, and an acceptable rate of growth of personal consumption.9. The economic assessment against whichpolicies affecting the distribution of output inthis way have to be considered is overshadowedin present circumstances by the strong inflationary pressure in the economy deriving mainly fromvwy high wage settlements. However, for thepurpose of forward expenditure planning it canbe said:(a) that  projections   have   been   made   onthe basis of various alternative policiesSECRETwhich seem possible with the aim of main-taining a reasonable balance of paymentssurplus after taking full account of the savings announced on 27 October. none of these affords a prospect of substantialspare resources becoming available in theyears up to 1974 for allocation to thepublic or private sectors;(b) that in view particularly of the strong inflation-tionary trend which has developed over thelast year, it cannot be excluded that thepublic sector might have to contribute tothe restoration of balance in the economy;(c) that the public expenditure programmes setout in this report should therefore beaccepted as maxima in the knowledge that every further saving which can be achievedconsistent with the Governmenfs general policies for the public sector would add to their room for manoeuvre.Public expenditure : balance between programmes10. We now turn to the rates of growth or decrease in the individual programmes, and somecomparisons with the corresponding provisionsimplied in the previous Administration^ white paper.(&apos;) But first an important point affectingthese rates of growth must be made, namely the significance of the relative price effect.(&apos;) &quot;Public Expenditure 1968-69 to 1973-74&apos;4234).(Cmnd.11296B*
11. in order to show whether the expenditureplans will entail the use of more or less realresources, they need to be expressed atunchanging pay and prices: in this report, at&quot; 1970 survey prices&quot;. but to express the forward programmes simply at constant pay and prices would understate the proportion of the gross domestic product which they will in due course actually take up. this is because pro-productivity in most public sector services cannotrise with productivity in the private sector as awhole; and a corrective allowance known as therelative price effect is introduced accordingly intothe forward estimates. these figures give a truermeasure of the rate of growth of the respectiveprogrammes and the totals (see tables 3 and 4).the  allowance  for  the relative price  effectamounts, as a proportion of total public expendi-ture, to about three-quarters of 1 per cent perannum. a further description of the basis of1970 survey prices as applied to individual pro-grammes and the nature of the relative price effect is given in appendix part 2, methodology,paragraphs 8-11.12. table 2 shows the average annual rates of increase from 1969-70 to 1974-75 in the individual -dual programmes; first, in column (a), with therelative price effect included for each programme;and second, in column (b) with the relative price effect excluded; and also, for comparison withcolumn (b), the corresponding average annualrates of increase implied in the previous administration^ white paper, cmnd. 4234, forthe corresponding years.TABLE public expenditure: Rate of increase by programme over Survey period at constant prices1970 SurveyAverage annual increase per cent1969-70 to 1974-75Cmnd. 4234Average annual increase per cent1968-69 to 1973-74....                             5(1   i	With relative price	With relative price	With relative price	effect * attributed to	effect* as overall	effect* as overall	individual	adjustment of total	adjustment of total	programmes	expenditure	expenditure	(a)	(b)	(c)Defence and external relations			1.  Defence Budget    .      .      .      .	.  0-8	- 0-8	- 2-02.  Other military defence   .	-10-2	-10-3	-29-73.  Overseas aid .      .      .	2-7	&apos; 4-7	3-84.  Other overseas services .	0-9	.0-6	- 0-5Commerce and industry			&quot;:.!..     .. &quot;,5.  Agriculture, fisheries and forestry	-3-8	- 3-5	4-56.   Research Councils, etc. .	5-6	5-0	5-07.  Technology and industry t     .      .      .     \       ^ ^ 8.  Other assistance to employment and industry J		- 5-2	/- 2-2 \&apos;- 5-0Nationalised industries			9.  Nationalised industries capital expenditure .	2-2	4-0	1-7Transport and miscellaneous local services			10.  Roads and public lighting	8-6	7-6	7-411.  Transport     .      ...	- 0-4	01	- 0-512.  Housing      .      .     .	1-5	1-0	3-313.   Miscellaneous local services   .	6-4	4-5	3-314.  Law and order	7-9	6-2	4-415.  Arts     .      .	9-2	7-0	9-3Social services			16.  Education    .      .	4-7	3-2	3-117.  Health and welfare      .      .      .	5-7	,   3-4	3-418.   Social security	2-2f	2-4J	n.a.other services			19.  Financial administration	1-0	- 0-2	- 0-820.  Common services .      .      ....	10-9	101	9-721.   Miscellaneous services   ....	5-7	4-9	7-022.  Northern Ireland   .      .      .      .	4-4	3-4	3-6Debt interestII .      .      ....	- 3-7	- 3-7	- 0-5* Calculated by the Treasury on agreed principles.	Includes adjustments to 1970-71 outturn prices.		t Excludes investment grants.			1t Includes provision of improvements and upratings in social security benefits.			5 The rate of increase would have depended on decisions concerning the extent of uprating of benefits.			I See footnote t to Table 1.
13. Table 3 shows the proportions of total public expenditure represented by the mainoroups of programmes in 1969-70; as they wouldhave been under the previous Administration^plans in Cmnd. 4234 by 1973-74; and as theywould be in accordance with this report by1974-75.TABLE public expenditure: Distribution by groups of programmes as percentage of total expenditure:&apos; 1969-70, 1973-74 and 1974-75With relative price With relative price effectf as overalleffect] attributed adjustment of total expenditure to individual programmes; 1970 Survey 1970 Survey      Cmnd. 4234     1970 Survey1969-70     1974-75 1969-70         1973-74          1973-74(a)           (b) (c)               (d)              (e). Defence and external relations	13-7	12-3	13-7	11-3	11-7. Commerce and industry*  ....	5-5	4-0	5-2	4-7	4-3. Nationalised industries&apos; capital expenditure   .	7-2	7-5	70	7-3	7-1. Transport and miscellaneous local services	17-5	19-7	16-6	180	17-7. Social services.....	40-8	42 -9J	39-5	39 -811	40-01. Other services .      .      .	4-7	5-3	4-5	4-6	4-7. Debt interest !l .      .      .	10-6	.   7-7	10-6	8-9	8-2. Adjustments?   .      .      .      .      .	-	0-6	2-9	5-4	6-3* Excludes investment grants.t Includes adjustments to 1970-71 outturn prices.J Includes provision for improvements and upratings in social security benefits.I Shortfall, contingency reserve, and (for columns (c), (rf) and (c)) relative price effect and adjustments to 1970-71 outturn prices.II See footnote f to Table 1.f In the absence of announced decisions by the previous Administration on future levels of social security benefits, it has been assumed for illustrative purposes in this Table that they would have made additions to the social security programme of thesame size as those decided by the present Administration.14. In considering the allocation for the individual -dual programmes, as set out in Tables 4 and 5,and reflected /elsewhere in percentage rates of change, a necessary reservation must be madefor unprogrammable expenditures, the level ofwhich depends on external factors rather thanon policy for the service in question. The mainservices of this type are agricultural price guarantees while they remain the cost ofwhich depends heavily on the level of productionand on movements in world prices; uncmploy-ment and certain other social security benefits, thecost of which depends on external conditionsdetermining the number of claims; and debt interest, the level of which reflects variouseconomic and financial movements affectingGovernment and other public sector borrowing.recommendations15- Ministers are recommended:(fl) to note the pattern of expenditure ascosted in this report for the period1970-71 to 1974-75, and to agree that public expenditure as a whole should besecretso managed that it is kept within the totals for each year of the period;(b) to note the higher rate of growth of thepublic sector&apos;s claims on final expenditureon goods and services, compared with therate of growth of public expenditure asa whole, with its implications for theallocation of resources between thevarious sectors of the economy;(c) to agree that the search for further savingsshould be vigorously pursued, including those which may arise from the reviewof functions commissioned by the PrimeMinister;(d) to approve, subject to (c) above, the costings of the individual expenditure programmes set out in Table 5 of thisreport as maxima for the purposes of management of the programmes; subject also to the point in paragraph 14 aboveabout &quot;unprogrammable&quot; services;(e) to commission a draft White Paper on public Expenditure on the above basis,for publication as soon as possible afterParliament reassembles.511296B* 2
TABLE public expenditure: Summary analysis by programme, 1969-70 to 1974-75 with relative price effect* attributed to individual programmes   million at 1970-71 outturn prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74    1974.75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate    estimateoutturnDefence and external relations .   Defence budget.   Other military defences.   Overseas aid .4.   Other overseas services ,380-8	2,466-9	2,437-0	2,402-4	2,445-9	2,477-192-3	49-3	51-8	43-5	45-9	54 0210-6	207-0	205-7	213-5	226-7	240-4136-0	135-7	137-0	138-9	140-1	142-4Commerce and industry.   Agriculture, fisheries and forestry    .      . 396-36.   Research Councils, etc..... 105-27.   Trade, industry and employment     .      . 1,217-3468-3        445-5        418-6        366-3       3260115-0        121-0        127-2        132-6       138-31,159-3      1,145-6        844-0        657-4       5341Nationalised industries8.   Nationalised industries capital expenditure.      1,490-8      1,530-3      1,518-7      1,562-3      1,638-8     1,7711Transport and miscellaneous local services9.	Roads .      .     .      .      .	698-1	787-9	828-6	913-0	982-0	1,056-210.	Transport     .      .      .    &quot;...	251-1	244-1	253-3	255-0	254-9	246-111.	Housing      .     .                   .	1,127-2	1.182 0	1,229-8	1,253-5	1,226-6	1,213-9 1,135-612.	Miscellaneous local services	831-4	906-4	924-8	990-9	1,065-8	13.	Law and order     ....	672-8	744-4	803-6	856-2	926-0	984-314.	Arts.......	19-2	22-8	26-6	27-0	28-3	29-social services15.	Education    ....	2,601-5	2,718-9	2,909-2	3,043-8	3,156-6	3,279-616.	Health and welfare .	2,041-9	2,207-7	2,308-4	2,425-5	2,555-4	2,678-917.	Social securityt	3,764-3	3,900-1	3,892-3	4,004-3	4,128-1	4,188-5ther services							18.	Financial administration .	252-4	250-5	249-3	257-1	260-1	264-919.	Common services  .	185-4	218-1	240-4	267-9	291-1	311-920.,	Miscellaneous services	72-4	87-3	92-8	89-2	91-2	95-621.	Northern Ireland   .      .     .	465-1	509-1	522-2	542-1	558-2	576 122.	Debt interest!	2,1860	2,103-0	1,980-0	1,950 0	1,890-0	1,810-023.	Contingency reserves	- &apos; &apos; &quot;   - -	.   &apos; - &apos; -.	900	130-0	180-0	245-024.	Shortfall		-200-0	-100-0	-1000	-100-0	-100-0Total   .      ...      . 21,198-1     21,814-1     22,313-6    22,655-9     23,148-0   23,699-8* Includes adjustments to 1970-71 outturn prices.t Includes provision for approved improvements and upratings in social security benefits, etc,J See footnote t to Table 1,5 See footnote J to Table 1.
TABLE 5Public expenditure: Summary analysis by programme, 1969-70 to 1974-75: with relative price effect* asoverall adjustment of total expenditure   million1969-70provisionaloutturn1970-71estimate1971-72estimate1972-73estimate1973-74estimate1974-75estimateAt 1970 Survey prices defence and external relations . Defence budget. Other military defences. Overseas aid   .4. Other overseas servicesCommerce and industry. Agriculture, fisheries and forestry6. Research Councils, etc.   .7. Trade, industry and employment2,398-9 2,387-0 2,327-091-1 47-9 50-6203-5 207-0 212-8127-1 129-4 129-3373-5        461-6        437-3100-9        109-6        114-71,174-4      1,125-0      1,118-42,270-042-6222-2130-0408-5119-8831-12,290-045 0239-0130-2355-4124-5635-92,300-053 0256-0131-2312-4128-8518-3Nationalised industries8. Nationalised industries&apos; capital expenditure.	1,446-2	1,501-3	1,496 0	1,546-3	1,627-2	1,759-9Transport and miscellaneous local services						9. Roads and public lighting	656-3	745-4	774-0	841-9	892-3	945-110. Transport......	237-1	240-3	248-8	249-3	248-2	238-911. Housing......	1,071-8	1,143-9	1,179-0	1,189 O	1,150-3	1,125-412. Miscellaneous local services	797-1	845-8	845-8	891-4	946-7	994-913. Law and order.....	632-9	686-2	727-2	762-1	814-3	854-614. Arts.......	18-5	21-7	24-9	24-6	25-2	25-9Social services						15. Education    .      .      .   . .      .      .	2,448-6	2,523-0	2,653-1	2,739-7	2,800-5	2,872-416. Health and welfare       ....	1,938-5	2,009-5	2,061-8	2,130-7	2,211-8	2,286-217. Social security)1.....	3,770-5	3,864-9	3,947-7	4,059-8	4,186-6	4,247-other services18.	Financial administration ....	238-7	235-3	230-7	234-4	234-4	236-219.	Common services  .      ......	172-7	203-7	221-3	244-2	263-2	279-720.	Miscellaneous services    .      .      .	67-9	82-5	86-7	82-2	82-9	86-121.	Northern Ireland.....	442-0	483-3	488-1	501-0	509-9	521-422.	Debt interestj.....	2,1860	2,103-0	1,980-0	1,950-0	1,890-0	1,810-023.	Contingency reserve?     .      .      .	-    1;		90-0	130-0	180-0	245-024!	Shortfall      .	 	-200-0	-100-0	-100-0	-100-0	-100-025.	Relative price effect and other adjustments.	603-9	856-8	968-4	1,155-1	1,364-5	1,570-9At 1970-71 outturn prices total   .      .      .      .      .      .     21,198-1     21,814-1     22,313-6    22,655-9     23,148-0     23,699-8* Includes adjustments to 1970-71 outturn prices.t Includes provision for improvements and upratings in social security benefits.see footnote f to Table 1.S See footnote J to Table 1.
1971-72ReferencesCmnd.      1970    Difference       to Cmnd.4515      Survey    between   explanatory    4515(a) and (b)     notes(a) (b) (c) (d) (e)1974-751970    DifferenceSurvey    between(e)and(f)(/)      ,   (g)Referencestoexplanatorynotes(h)At 1970 Survey prices defence and external relations .  Defence Budget .      . .   2,327 2,3272.  Other military defence . .       51 513.  Overseas aid                         213 2134.  Other overseas services .      129 129Commerce and industry.  Agriculture (excluding price guarantees)     ...     286        296 106. Research Councils, etc. . 115 115  -7.  Technology and industry (ex-cluding investment grants) .     575        567       - 8Investment grants      .      .     576        552       -24(i)(ii) j(iii)V   870        879 9 (x)65 65 (xi)Nationalised industries8.  Nationalised industriescapital expenditure   1,5001,4961,770      1,760       -10 (xii)Transport and miscellaneous  local services (excluding housing subsidies)					9.  Roads and transport   .	1,024	1,023	- 1		10.  Housing (excluding subsidies)	838	838	-		11,.  Miscellaneous local services .	859	846	-13	(iv)*	* 3,87012.  Law and order   .	729	727	-2		13.  Arts.....	25	25	- &quot;y.		Social services14.  Education .15. j Health and welfare16.  Social security2,647	2,653	6	(v)2,059	2,062	3	3,974	3,947	-27	(vi)*230	231	i	221	221	. -1&quot;.	91	87	- 4	492	488	- 4	2,020 r	1,980	-40	(vii)565^	572	7	(viii)*1,260      9,406        146        (xiv)*Other services17.  Financial administration18.  Common services19.  Miscellaneous services .20.  Northern Ireland21.  Debt interest22.  Agriculture price guarantees23.  Housing subsidies24.  Contingency reserve25.  Relative price effect and otheradjustments as in Cmnd4515      .850Total, as in Cmnd. 4515 22,396Relative price effect and otheradjustments as at December1970      .      .      .      .      914        8681,140      1,123       -17750*1,490-46(xv)541      -209        (xvi)*23,700(ix)*      1,560      1,471      -89       (xvii)*At 1970-71 outturn prices total, excluding line 25 22,460    22,314-14623,770    23,700      -70* This Survey differs from Cmnd. 4515 by identifying the effect of Government decisions on social security benefits and localauthority current expenditure which were unallocated, and grouped with the contingency reserve for the purpose of publication in Cmnd. 4515.TABLE public expenditure: comparison of 1970 Survey with Cmnd. 4515 f million
Notes on Table 6:(i) Increased payments to curers under the Bacon Curing Industry Stabilisation Scheme, because of substantial recent increases in pigmeat prices not matched by corresponding increases in bacon prices.(ii) A net figure mainly reflecting on the one hand the announced launching aid to Rolls-Royce and on the other hand the elimination of the previous unallocated provision for future industrial and aircraft support projects.(iii) The expected small savings in 1971-72 from the termination of investment grants. No quantified provision for savingwas made in Cmnd. 4515, where it was stated that such savings would start to accrue in 1971-72 but would not become substantialuntil 1972-73.(iv) Mainly savings arising from the recent Rate Support Grant negotiations, provision for which was not allocated in Cmnd. 4515(see Note (viii)).(v) Revised estimates of numbers of pupils in secondary schools.(vi) Social security: Cmnd. 4515 provided under this heading only for the payment of benefit at existing cash rates to the(increasing) forecast numbers of recipients. Provision for the loss of purchasing power of existing cash benefits as a resultof inflation, and the periodic uprating of the main benefits on account of such price movements, was made in the relative price effect, etc. Provision for upratings of benefits in real terms was made in the contingency reserve. This was designed,following the usual practice in this matter, so as not to disclose the Governments intentions on future benefit improvements and upratings. &apos; In the 1970 Survey presentation the social security heading reflects the full provision for benefits after making these adjustments. Compensating adjustments are therefore made to the provision included to Cmnd. 4515 for the contingency reserve (see Note (viii)) and the relative price effect and other adjustments (see Note (ix)).(vii) A small reduction in the forecast of cash payments of debt interest, and a more important reduction in the forecast of thereal value of such cash payments in the face of rising domestic prices.(viii) A net figure reflecting three main changes:(a) Social security: The contingency reserve is reduced by  20 million on account of upratings of social security benefits in real terms, provision for which is now made under the Social Security heading (see Note (vi)).(b) Agriculture: The estimates for price guarantees have been reduced by an arbitrary figure of  25 million on account ofthe assumed introduction of the import levy scheme in 1971.(c) Contingency reserve: The general &quot; squeeze &quot; of  20 million on local authority current expenditure, which was implicit in the provision for this item in Cmnd. 4515, has been reduced to  10 million. Further savings of  40 million havebeen used to increase the contingency reserve from the level of about  60 million implicit in Cmnd. 4515 to  100 million.(rf) A minor rounding adjustment, adopted for this &quot; portmanteau &quot; provision in Cmnd. 4515, has been eliminated in the survey costings.(ix) In the light of new information about price movements in the current year, the adjustment to 1970-71 outturn prices hasbeen increased by  60 million. In accordance with the usual practice, for showing the estimates on a consistent constant pricebasis, the estimate for this item in Cmnd. 4515, and the estimate for total public expenditure in Cmnd. 4515, have also beenrevalued by this amount.The reduction shown in the relative price effect in the Survey estimates largely reflects the different treatment of the priceadjustment for social security benefits (see Note (vi) above).(x) Mainly increased payments to bacon curers (see Note (i)).(xi) The estimated residual payments in 1974-75 of investment grants on contracts entered into before 27 October, 1970. Noquantified provision for these payments was made in Cmnd. 4515, which noted, however, that such payments would arise(footnote t to Table 2).(xii) Mainly results from a change in the application of accounting conventions: in future, payments to BRB&apos;s pension fund will be scored as current, not capital expenditure.(xiii) Mainly expenditure on the Thames barrier.(xiv) This includes an increase of  11 million for Education, mainly the result of revised estimates of numbers of pupils in secondary schools. The main change is the provision in the Survey presentation for the full cost of social security benefits,after making allowance for price changes and upratings in real terms (see Note (vi) above and Notes (xvi) and (xvii) below).(xv) Savings in Northern Ireland expenditure consequent upon the Great Britain savings announced on 27 October; such savingswere foreshadowed in paragraph 33 of Cmnd. 4515.(xvi) The contingency reserve is reduced by  194 million on account of upratings of social security benefits in real terms,provision for which is now made under the social security heading (see Notes (vi) and (xiv) above).  In addition the generalsqueeze&quot; on local authority current expenditure which was implicit in the Cmnd. 4515 provision has been increased from 30 million to  35 million.  The rounding adjustments made in Cmnd. 4515 have been eliminated.(xvii) In the light of new information about price movements in the current year, the adjustment to 1970-71 outturn prices has been increased by  70 million. In accordance with the usual practice, for showing the estimates on a consistent constant price basis, the estimate for this item in Cmnd. 4515, and the estimate for total public expenditure in Cmnd. 4515, have alsobeen revalued by this amount.The reduction shown in the relative price effect in the Survey estimates largely reflect the different treatment of the priceadjustment for social security benefits (see Notes (vi) and (xiv)).
Notes on Table 6:(i) Increased payments to curers under the Bacon Curing Industry Stabilisation Scheme, because of substantial recent increases in pigmeat prices not matched by corresponding increases in bacon prices.(ii) A net figure mainly reflecting on the one hand the announced launching aid to Rolls-Royce and on the other hand the elimination of the previous unallocated provision for future industrial and aircraft support projects.(iii) The expected small savings in 1971-72 from the termination of investment grants. No quantified provision for savingwas made in Cmnd. 4515, where it was stated that such savings would start to accrue in 1971-72 but would not become substantialuntil 1972-73.(iv) Mainly savings arising from the recent Rate Support Grant negotiations, provision for which was not allocated in Cmnd. 4515(see Note (viii)).(v) Revised estimates of numbers of pupils in secondary schools.(vi) Social security: Cmnd. 4515 provided under this heading only for the payment of benefit at existing cash rates to the(increasing) forecast numbers of recipients. Provision for the loss of purchasing power of existing cash benefits as a resultof inflation, and the periodic uprating of the main benefits on account of such price movements, was made in the relative price effect, etc. Provision for upratings of benefits in real terms was made in the contingency reserve. This was designed,following the usual practice in this matter, so as not to disclose the Governments intentions on future benefit improvements and upratings. In the 1970 Survey presentation the social security heading reflects the full provision for benefits after making these adjustments. Compensating adjustments are therefore made to the provision included to Cmnd. 4515 for the contingency reserve (see Note (viii)) and the relative price effect and other adjustments (see Note (ix)).(vii) A small reduction in the forecast of cash payments of debt interest, and a more important reduction in the forecast of thereal value of such cash payments in the face of rising domestic prices.(viii) A net figure reflecting three main changes:(o) Social security: The contingency reserve is reduced by  20 million on account of upratings of social security benefits in real terms, provision for which is now made under the Social Security heading (see Note (vi)).(b) Agriculture: The estimates for price guarantees have been reduced by an arbitrary figure of  25 million on account ofthe assumed introduction of the import levy scheme in 1971.(c) Contingency reserve: The general &quot; squeeze &quot; of  20 million on local authority current expenditure, which was implicit in the provision for this item in Cmnd. 4515, has been reduced to  10 million. Further savings of  40 million havebeen used to increase the contingency reserve from the level of about  60 million implicit in Cmnd. 4515 to  100 million.id) A minor rounding adjustment, adopted for this &quot; portmanteau &quot; provision in Cmnd. 4515, has been eliminated in the survey costings.(ix) In the light of new information about price movements in the current year, the adjustment to 1970-71 outturn prices hasbeen increased by  60 million. In accordance with the usual practice, for showing the estimates on a consistent constant pricebasis, the estimate for this item in Cmnd. 4515, and the estimate for total public expenditure in Cmnd. 4515, have also beenrevalued by this amount.The reduction shown in the relative price effect in the Survey estimates largely reflects the different treatment of the priceadjustment for social security benefits (see Note (vi) above).(x) Mainly increased payments to bacon curers (see Note (i)).I(xi) The estimated residual payments in 1974-75 of investment grants on contracts entered into before 27 October, 1970. Noquantified provision for these payments was made in Cmnd. 4515, which noted, however, that such payments would arise(footnote f to Table 2).(xii) Mainly results from a change in the application of accounting conventions: in future, payments to BRB&apos;s pension fund will be scored as current, not capital expenditure.(xiii) Mainly expenditure on the Thames barrier.(xiv) This includes an increase of  11 million for Education, mainly the result of revised estimates of numbers of pupils in secondary schools. The main change is the provision in the Survey presentation for the full cost of social security benefits,after making allowance for price changes and upratings in real terms (see Note (vi) above and Notes (xvi) and (xvii) below).(xv) Savings in Northern Ireland expenditure consequent upon the Great Britain savings announced on 27 October; such savingswere foreshadowed in paragraph 33 of Cmnd. 4515.(xvi) The contingency reserve is reduced by  194 million on account of upratings of social security benefits in real terms,provision for which is now made under the social security heading (see Notes (vi) and (xiv) above). In addition the general&quot; squeeze &quot; on local authority current expenditure which was implicit in the Cmnd. 4515 provision has been increased from 30 million to  35 million. The rounding adjustments made in Cmnd. 4515 have been eliminated.(xvii) In the light of new information about price movements in the current year, the adjustment to 1970-71 outturn prices has been increased by  70 million. In accordance with the usual practice, for showing the estimates on a consistent constant price basis, the estimate for this item in Cmnd. 4515, and the estimate for total public expenditure in Cmnd. 4515, have alsobeen revalued by this amount.The reduction shown in the relative price effect in the Survey estimates largely reflect the different treatment of the priceadjustment for social security benefits (see Notes (vi) and (xiv)).
TABLE 7Public expenditure: Summary analysis by economic and resource categories, 1969-70 to 1974-75Part A: Analysis by Economic Category  million	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					1/1970 Survey prices						Wages and salaries.....	4,894-8	5,024-4	5,146-7	5,263-7	5,420-2	5,566-5Selective employment tax.....	3180	325-0	333-1	341-0	348-2	355-other current expenditure on goods and services .	3,019-2	3,079-9	3,019-0	3,059-6	3,143-5	3,203-5Subsidies.......	854-7	926-1	905-8	860-2	770-1	649-7Debt interest*.     .     .     .     .	2,186-0	2,103-0	1,980-0	1,950-0	1,890-0	1,810-current grants to persons       ....	3,998-5	4,109-8	4,204-8	4,317-5	4,437-5	4,515-current grants to private bodies	292-4	309-1	330-2	350-1	375-5	407-3Current grants abroad.....	177-9	176-8	168-8	173-5	183-5	195-3Gross domestic fixed capital formation	3,846-3	4,187-1	4,367-3	4,514-4	4,614-7	4,794-increase in value of stocks      ....	11-8	21-0	36-5	44-5	74-4	59-capital grants to private sector ....	826-8	791-4	844-7	558-8	423-6	372-net lending to private sector   ....	46-2	125-3	110-9	58-0	51-3	60-4Loans to overseas governments ....	80-1	80-6	611	56-3	59-4	65-0Drawings from United Kingdom subscriptions to						international lending bodies ....	15-1	15-0	34-0	43-8	48-4	51-other net lending and investment abroad  .	8-0	21-3	21-3	22-2	9-2	22-8Cash expenditure on company securities (net)	18-4	11-5	-34-0	7-2	4-0	4-0Contingency reservef.....		-&apos;-.	900	130-0	1800	245-0Shortfall:						Nationalised industries     ....	!.Vi I	-1500	-175-0	-150-0	-150-0	^150-other     .     . &apos;   .     .     ...	&apos;; -. - A	-200 0	-1000	-1000	-1000	-100-0Relative price effect and other adjustments .	603-9	856-8	968-4	1,155-1	1,364-5	1,570-91 1970-71 outturn prices						Total    .	21,198-1	21,814-1	22,313-6	22,655-9	23,148-0	23,699-8* See footnote t to Table 1.t See footnote i to Table 1.
I JECRETMain reportTABLE 7Public expenditure: Summary analysis by economic and resource categories, 1969-70 to 1974-75Part B: Analysis by Resource Category*  million								Average		1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	annual		provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	percentage		outturn						increaseA.	Net expenditure on resources:								  million    .      .      .      .	13,721-3	14,101-6	14,741 -0	15,318-1	15,944-0	16,616-6	  -	Percentage of total	64-7	64-6	66-1	67-6	68-8	70-2	4-0B.	Transfers, taxation, etc.:								  million    .      .      .      .	7,192-9	7,302-7	7,217-3	6,965-5	6,811-3	6,631-4	-1-6	Percentage of total	34-0	33-5	32-3	30-7	29-4	28-0	-&apos;C.	Net purchase of existing assets:								  million    .      .      .      .	283-9	409-8	355-3	372-3	392-7	451-8	9-7	Percentage of total	1-3	1-9	1-6	1-6	1-7	1-9	-	Total	21,198-1	21,814-1	22,313-6	22,655-9	23,148-0	23,699-8	2-3f* The relative price effect and the adjustments to 1970-71 outturn prices have been attributed to resource categories,t Includes investment grants.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy No. 060UBLICEXPENDITURETO 1974-75Appendix: Parts One and two detailed Analysis of programmes and Methodology1970 Report by the Public expenditure survey CommitteeDecember 1970
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy No. 0 6 0PUBLICEXPENDITURETO 1974-75appendix: parts one and two detailed analysis of programmes and methodology1970 report by the public expenditure survey committeeDecember 1970
CONFIDENTIAL		Part One: Detailed Analysis of Programmes			TABLE 13 (continued)			  million at 1970 Survey prices			1969-70	1970-71	1971-72     1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate     estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn				MAINTENANCEMotorways and trunk roads	1-8	1-9	2-0	2-0	2-0	2-1Principal roads.....	2-1	2-1	2-2	2-4	2-2	2-other roads	8-0	8-3	8-8	9-2	9-4	9-8Car parks       .      .	-0-1	-01	-0-1	-0-1	-0-1	-0-1Lighting and other expenditure .	1-5	1-5	1-5	1-6	1-8	1-9Total.....	13-3	13-7	14-4	15-1	15-3	16-1Central government administration	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-local authority administration  .	2-4	2-9	3-1	3-2	2-7	2-8TotalWales   .      .      .      .      .        34-9 41-1 44-3 47-5 52-8 56-7c. ScotlandNEW CONSTRUCTION AND IMPROVEMENTSMotorways and trunk roads      .      .	23-3	22-8	24-0	23-0	22-0	21-0Principal roads	15-8	19-5	24-1	., 25-1	27-2	28-other roads    .      ...	5-5	50	4-8	5-2	5-7	6-5Car parks       .      .      ...	0-2	0-6	0-7	0-8	0-9	1-0Lighting and other expenditure .	1-1	1-2	1-0	1-2	1-3	1-3Total    .      .      .      .      .	45-9	49-1	54-6	55-3	57-1	58-3MAINTENANCEMotorways and trunk roads      ... 3-3 4-2 3-4 3-5 3-7 3-8Principal roads .      .      .      .      .      . 5-7 6-0 6-2 6-6 6-9 7-2Otherroads    .      .      ...      . 10-4 10-6 10-8 11-4 11-8 12-5Lighting and other expenditure .      .      . 3-0 3-0 3-3- 3-5 3-6 3-7Total    .      .      .      .      . Central government administration Local authority administration  . 1	22-4 0-4 3-2	23-8 0-4 3-2	23-7 0-5 3-3	25-0 0-5 3-5	26-0 0-5 3-6	27-2 0-5 3-8Total Scotland ,   .      .      . :.&apos;	71-9	76-5	82-1	84-3	87-2	89-8Great Britain NEW CONSTRUCTION AND IMPROVEMENTS Major roads..... Otherroads .     .     .     . &quot; &quot;. &apos; Other expenditure (including lighting)	SUMMARY 360-6 46-9 21-9	421-5 43-1 22-2	429-3 44-2 24-9	473-1 46-9 27-1	502-7 56-8 32-5	532-0 60-8 34-5Total    .      .      .	429-4	486-8	498-4	547-1	592-0	627-3MAINTENANCE Major roads .     .     . Other roads .      .      .      .      .&apos; Other expenditure (including lighting)	54-8 104-2 23-4	63-9 116-6 21-9	70-2 122-9 22-6	76-6 131-5 23-5	75-2 138-5 30-7	78-1 148-8 33-3Total    .      .      .      .	182-4	202-4	215-7	231-6	244-4	260-central government administration . Local authority administration	4-4 32-0	4-4 43-5	4-8 46-6	4-8 49-8	4-9 42-2	50 43-6Total Great Britain .	648-2	737-1	765-5	833-3	883-5	; 936-1SET paid by local authorities .	8-1	8-3	8-5	8-6	8-8	90Grand total   ....	656-3	745-4	774-0	841-9	892-3	945-confidential 17
1. Expenditure on roads covers construction,improvements, maintenance and lighting of:(1) major roads, i.e., motorways, trunk and principal roads; and(2) other roads and car parks.Expenditure on new construction and improve-ment of major roads (including lighting) and on maintenance of motorways and trunk roads is either financed wholly by the Government or subject to specific Government grants. Mainten-ance of principal roads (including lighting) andall expenditure on other roads and car parks isa local government responsibility, and is govern-ment-assisted only through the rate support grant.It is therefore not directly subject to central control and accurate forecasting is difficult.2. The main justification for a continuingincrease in road expenditure is the continuinggrowth of traffic. The provision for main roadsremains consistent with previous White Paperssetting out road plans in England, Scotland andWales although the long term implications ofthese are still under consideration.3. The reductions announced in Cmnd. 4515amounted to  4-9 million in 1971-72 rising to 24-7 million in 1974-75. There will be no cut in major roads capital expenditure for 1971-72but progressive reductions (mainly on principalroads) are being made in subsequent years, rising to  20 million in 1974-75. The rest of the reductions will fall on capital expenditure onminor roads. The overall provision will rise from 774-0 million in 1971-72 to  945-1 million in1974-75, an annual average increase of about per cent.4. Additional assistance in the development areas is included in accordance with a decisionof the Ministerial Committee on Regional Policy.The roads block allocation for additional expendi-ture under the Local Employment Acts is 3-5 million. It is expected that additional expenditure will build up to this level by1974-75.    &apos;a.  England5. The figures represent existing policy but some allowance has been made within them for anincreased level of maintenance expenditure to reflect the recommendations of the Committeeon Highway Maintenance (the Marshall Com-mittee). Provision is also included for the costof metrication of speed limit signs.6. The figure of  789-6 million for expenditurein 1974-75 represents an increase of 7-5 per cent a year over 1971-72. This is consistent withcompleting the inter-urban trunk road strategywithin the 15 to 20 year period as envisaged in the White Paper &quot; Roads for the Future&quot;(Cmnd. 4369). This strategy is currently underreview but for the period up to 1974-75 theexpenditure implications of any new strategy are unlikely to be very different from those of theWhite Paper strategy.7. Local authority current expenditure will growby about 1\ per cent a year from 1971-72 to1974-75. This progression is considered to berealistic and takes account of the arguments advanced by the local authorities during therecent Rate Support Grant negotiations, for ahigher level of expenditure in 1971-72 and 1972-73; it makes some provision for the consequences of the Marshall Committee Report. There can,of course, be no guarantee that expenditure willbe at the rate proposed, as the Government hasno direct control over this expenditure.b. Wales8. The provision throughout the period repre-sents a continuation of existing policy as envisaged in &quot; Wales: The Way Ahead&quot;(Cmnd. 3334). No provision has been made foran increased rate of maintenance expenditurefollowing the Marshall Report; this is expectedto be very small.c. Scotland9. The provision is consistent with the policy set out in the White Paper &quot; Scottish Roads inthe 1970s&quot; (Cmnd. 3953), the implications ofwhich are that expenditure on major roads inScotland will grow by an average *of 2 per cent a year at constant prices during the 1970s subjectto review in the light of regional developmentpolicies and the traffic situation. No provision has been made for increased expenditure on road maintenance following the Marshall Report; thisis expected to be very small.
14.  transport table 14				  million at 1970 Survey prices			1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn			lloqfU;.&quot;,l		Department of the Environment, Scottish Development						Department and Welsh Office						a.   Support to nationalised transport industries*						(i) British Railways Board.      .      .	88-2	75-3 &quot;	67-6	57-7	53-8	49-0(ii) National Freight Corporation	17-0	12-4	13-0	8-0	3-0	(iii) London Transport Board	10-7	1-8	&apos;-	&apos; - &apos;	- &apos;	-(iv) British Waterways Board	1-9	3-4	,l 3-5	3-9	4-2	4-3(v) Scottish Transport Group    .      .	0-5	0-6	.   0-8	ri;   0-8	,., 0-8	0-8Total......	118-3	93-5	84-9	70-4	61-8	54-1b.   Other surface transport						(i) Ports .                   -      -	33-8	36-1	37-9	36-2	34-2	331(ii) Bus fuel grants   .      .	20-4	20-8	21-3	21-3	21-3	21-3(iii) Rural bus and ferry grants .	0-2	0-6	2-1	10  -.-!3-3&apos;-:	3-3	3-5(iv) Infrastructure expendituret   .	.10-2	100	14-6	24-0	30-4	33-2(v) Other passenger transport						(a) London     .      ...	30	, 23-5	-.&apos;   23-3	26-6	23-6	22-7(6) Other...      ....	13-0	14-2 .	15-2	15-3	16-5	17-6(vi) Miscellaneous transport services   .	4-2	5-0	. . ...7-6	8-5	10-5	12-6(vii) Departmental administration	11-8   &apos;	11-7	12-2	12-5	12-6	12-6...       ,     .. Total,,                   -,&apos;!.,:.;,,&apos;:;:  Am	96-6	121-9	134-2 1	147-7	:152-4	156-6Department of Trade and Industry						c.   Civil aviation services   .      .      .	25-4	31-4	33-7 :	35-5	36-5	30-5d.   Shipping services .      .      .      .      .		.... T-6.-.5	-4-0	-4-3	-2-5	-2-3Grand total          .      .      .      .	237-1	240-3	248-8	249:3	248-2	238-9* Excluding forms of assistance under b.t Including nationalised industries&apos; capital expenditure.1. The block forms a disparate group includingsupport to nationalised industries in respect mainly of essential loss making activities and :to other branches of surface transport chiefly by loan orgrant for specific services.a.  Support to nationalised transport industries british railways board. Under the Transport Act 1968 grants aremade to BRB for passenger services which arejudged to be socially and economically necessarybut which the Board would otherwise close. Thedecision to withdraw grant to the London networkhas led to a reduction of  10 million in 1971-72and of  15 million a year thereafter in theprovision made. Under the same Act BRB are paid grants to enable them to eliminate surplustrack and signalling capacity which is at presenta burden on their operating account. Thesegrants taper from  11 - 3 million this year to 5 million in 1973 after which they will cease.national freight corporation . Under the Transport Act 1968 grants are paid to the NFC in respect of the deficit on theirsubsidiary, National Carriers Ltd., Which they took over from BRB. To give NFC an incentive to improve on NCL&apos;s performance these grants are tapered and they cease after 1973.london transport board4. Responsibility for London Transport was transferred to the Greater London Council on1 January, 1970. The only grant specific toLondon Transport is a small remanet payment in 1970 71 in: respect of the London transport board&apos;s revenue deficit for 1969.british waterways board. The provision covers the minimum expendi-ture needed for essential maintenance of the waterways, including the strengthening of weakbridges.CONFIDENTIAL1911292
scottish transport group6. The provision relates to subsidies payable tothe Group, mainly in respect of losses on western Highlands and Islands shipping servicespreviously operated at a loss by MacBraynesLimited.b.   Other surface transportports7. The estimates cover investment provision forthe independent harbour trusts and local authority-owned harbours. They are based on returns from individual port authorities.bus fuel grants8. The estimates reflect the continuing policy ofrefunding to operators of bus stage servicesincreases of fuel duty since 1964.b.  Other12. The remaining provision in England coversestimated expenditure on the purchase of newbuses by local authorities and Passenger Trans-port Executives. The latter have not yet beenable to prepare comprehensive investment programmes but the figures are based on thelatest available information about actual and prospective expenditure. Most of this expendi-ture qualifies for a 25 per cent grant.13. Provision for Scotland anticipates thepossibility that the operators of shipping services to Orkney and Shetland may require financialassistance towards the replacement of theirexisting fleet of conventional ships by more economical vehicle ferries, in order to combatrising costs (particularly labour).rural bus and ferry services9. Local authortiies may contribute towards thecost of rural bus and ferry services throughout great Britain under Section 34 of the transport act 1968. The requirement cannot be accuratelyestimated since the level of expenditure is dependent on decisions made by these authorities.Expenditure has been small in 1969-70 and1970-71 but should now increase.infrastructure expenditure10. This provision covers gross expenditure, bylocal authorities and nationalised industries on measures designed to assist public transportprojects in commuter areas. The programme isnot firm and there could be some variation in the timing of expenditure, depending very much onthe starting date of major rail schemes. Adjust-ments have been made to reflect the intentionannounced in Cmnd. 4515 to apply strictercriteria.. These reduce the provision made in1971-72 by  8-5 million rising to  20-0 million in 1974-75.other passenger transporta.   London11. Detailed consideration of the investment programme of London Transport is a matter forthe GLC. The forecasts have nbt been examined by the GLC&apos; but represent the best estimate that can be made;]of likely levels of expenditure.Infrastructure expenditure is excluded. Provisionof  14-1 million over the Survey period is madein this section for the cost of an undergroundlink with Heathrow Airport.miscellaneous transport services14. The main items are road safety and research. Road safety measures as envisaged inthe White Paper &quot;Road Safety A FreshApproach&quot; (Cmnd. 3339) are being encouragedfollowing a circular to local authorities in April1969. Provision is also made for an expandedresearch programme.15. This item also includes provision for theTransport Departments&apos; contributions to estab-lishing a proposed hew Transport andEnvironment Centre, as well as assistance to theBritish Railways Board for a programme being undertaken at the Railway Technical Centre,Derby, which includes the development of the advanced Passenger Train.c.  Civil aviation services16. This covers expenditure at aerodromesoperated by the Department of Trade andIndustry and on air navigation and miscellaneousservices provided by the Department. It also includes capital expenditure by local authorities at municipal aerodromes.d.  Shipping services17.   This  covers  Department  of Trade andIndustry expenditure on shipping services, and net loans to the shipping industry.  The figures include   50,000  from   1970-7.1   onwards for expenditure on the detection, observation andclearance of offshore oil pollution.
CONFIDENTIAL Part One: Detailed Analysis of Programmes15.  housing table 15   million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70 1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn &apos;a.   Subsidies:England      .      .      ...	183-8	222-0	251-4	250-9	222-1	197-wales .      .      .&apos;i   (.-.,/ -      ..	9-4	10-9	11-9	11-9	10-3	100Scotland     .      .      .      .      .      .	71-9	85-4	93-1	97-4	95-5	93-4Total    ...     .      .      .     &apos;&apos;.      .	265-1	318-3	356-4	360-2	327-9	301-1Improvement grants to private sector:			ii  &apos;!			England      .      .      .      .	14-4	16-8	22-4	24-8	27-9	31-wales .          -:&apos;.&apos;   &quot; :&apos; yi      .      .	1-6	1-6	1-8	2-2	2-4	2-scotland     .      .    - .   If.	1-7	2-5	2-8	30	30	30Total    . i   . . .-,          -. .    .	17-7	20-9	27-0	300	33-3	37-1Investment:						(i) New dwellings including land:						England      .      .      .      .      .	618-3	559-4	574-3	567-9	561-1	559-wales .      .      .      .      .      .      .	28-3	25-0	28-8	34-1	35-8	36-3Scotland     .      .      .      ...	142-4	143-0	144-3	145-3	147-6	148-2Total   &apos;.                   :          &apos;	789-0	727-4	747-4	747-3	744-5	744-2(ii) Other:						England      .      .      .      .	9-5	14-8	15-9	17-6	18-2	19-2Wales .      ....	0-3	0-7	0-7	0-9	10	1-1Scotland      .      .      .	60	3-7	1-4	2-6	2-6	2-6Total    .      ...	804-8	746-6	765-4	768-4	766-3	767-1Lending:						(i) By local authorities:						(a) Advances  to  private persons and						housing associations:						England .      .      .      .      .	61-5	145-5	122-3	126-6	128-4	1310Wales     .	4-6	100	8-3	8-4	8-4	8-scotland .      .      ...	50:,	5-5	4-4	4-5	4-4	4-5Total    .      .            .      .      .	71-1	1610	135-0	139-5	141-2	143-9(6) Repayments.....	-loi i	-113-7	-118-3	-123-4	-128-3	-133-5Net lending   .      .      .      .	-30 0	47-3	16-7	16-1	12-9	10-4(ii) By the Housing Corporation and new						towns; and by the Government to housing						associations and building societies (net)	12-7	9-2	11-9	12-6	8-2	80Total net lending   .	-17-3	56-5	28-6	28-7	21-1	18-departmental administration.      .      .	1-5	1-6	1-6	1-7	1-7	1-7Grand total   .            .	1,071-8	1,143-9	1,179-0	1,189-0	1,150-3	1,125-4Of which:England . . ... 808-4 862-0 888-3 885-2 846-7 823-1Wales . . ... 38-2         42-8 46-1 52-3 52-0 52-1Scotland . . .      .      . 225-2 239-1 244-6 251-5 251-6 250-confidential 21
1. The provision made for 1971-72 to 1974-75still largely reflects the policies pursued by theprevious Administration. The new policies nowbeing developed substantially alter the validity of past policy projections, but it is not yetpossible to forecast with any precision their totalor detailed effect on the previously projectedlevels of public expenditure on housing.a.   Subsidies2. The decisions recently taken on the reform of housing finance will bring savings. The totalof these savings, as presently estimated, is for convenience shown as a saving on Governmentsubsidies, although in fact they also include other changes, in particular, of supplementary benefits.3. For England and Wales the total savingswere broadly estimated in the submission of theproposals to the Home Affairs Committee at 25 million in 1972-73,  125 million in 1973-74and  180 million in 1974-75; the corresponding figures for Scotland would be nil in 1972-73, 10 million in 1973-74 and  25 million in1974-75. For the purposes of this Reporthowever the notional savings figure of  150million in 1974-75 which was assumed forCmnd. 4515 (though not published in it) hasbeen used as the basis for the figures in the table. The notional savings have beenapportioned to the three countries on the basisof their share of present Exchequer subsidies,but this apportionment is no more thanillustrative and has been agreed by the housingdepartments only on this basis.4. The savings quoted above depend on anumber of assumptions about long-term subsidies and transitional arrangements. The secretaries of State are about to discuss the financial detailsof the new proposals with the Chancellor of theExchequer and negotiations with local authority associations will follow. The estimates of savingsaxe therefore no more than provisional and maybe modified in due course.b. Improvement grants5. The provision reflects the increased level of spending on improvements since the passing ofthe Housing Act 1969. The shift in emphasisfrom new construction to rehabilitation whichhas already become evident is likely to continue in the future, although the present estimates donot reflect this.c. Investment6. The provision for new house-building isbased on the following estimated approvals:Year England      Wales    Scotland1968 (actual)	148,600	5,800	33,7501969 (actual)	116,700	5,845	33,7501970.    :	119,000	7,350	32,3001971.	119,000	8,700	34,9501972 .	.    119,000	9,000	34,950,   .   1973 .	.    119,000	9,150	34,9501974 .	.    119,000	9,150	34,950It is not yet possible to assess how far the reform of housing finance will affect these estimates. Although there are a number of factors which will sustain investment, such asthe encouragement given by the review of housing finance to local authorities to clear slums andto build in order to deal with obsolescence andovercrowding, there are also factors working theother way. The main one will be the impetusthat fair rents will give to local authority tenantsto become owner-occupiers, thus reducing thedemand for new local authority houses. Theprovision takes no account of these conflictinginfluences, nor of the as yet incalculable effects of local authorities undertaking the former land commission function of acquiring land for private housing where this is the only means ofsecuring development; eventually this would bea self-financing operation.d.   Lending7. The provision made for 1970-71 reflects thedecision of the previous Administration toincrease the allowance for gross advances inthat year to  135 million for Great Britain. for later years, an annual figure of  105 million is used. The view of the Housing Departments isthat a case can be made for a higher level ofmortgage advances than  105 million but specific proposals for increases are unlikely to be made until information about the scale and pattern oflending in the first six months of 1970-71 hasbeen obtained and evaluated.8. The provision for loans by local authoritiesto housing associations recognises the significant increase which is taking place in this activity.This increase follows the passing of the housing acts of 1967 and 1969 which have the combined effect of making associations eligible for loanstowards the cost of purchase of houses for improvement and of giving a higher scale of grant for the work. The new arrangementsreflect a shift in emphasis from new constructionto improvements. This type of lending is not atpresent subject to any overall ceiling or controland in the Treasury&apos;s view some controlmechanism may be needed if further growthcontinues. Allowance has also been made forthe previous Administration^ decision to approveincreased activity by the Housing corporation to the extent of  10 million extra in advancesspread over the next three years.
fjA CONFIDENTIALpayment is made in arrears some provision isnecessary in 1970-71 and, for belated claims, inthe two subsequent years. The regional employment premium, which is only paid inrespect of manufacturing establishments in development areas, will be discontinued from september 1974.Part One: Detailed Analysis of Programmesproductivity services16. This heading includes grants to the BritishProductivity Council for which the Departmentof Employment is responsible and which, as pre-viously announced by the Government, will be phased out from 1971-72.8-12.  Investment by the nationalised ii1. The figures for individual industries in thissection are for expenditure on fixed assets in theUnited Kingdom since this is the operativeconcept for control purposes and the basis onwhich Ministerial approval of nationalised industries capital expenditure programmes is given.However to make these figures compatible withthose in the rest of the Public Expenditure Surveyseparate block adjustments* have been made inorder to produce figures for total capitalexpenditure.2. The programmes are designed to enable theindustries to meet the demand for their products and services in the most efficient way and to conduct their finances so that they meet their financial objectives and/or other statutory obligations. Future policy towards nationalised industries is now being considered by an official working Party under the guidance of a ministerial steering Committee chaired by the chief secretary.3. Experience shows that total capitalexpenditure by the nationalised industries tends to fall short of approved levels.   Reductions8. FuelTABLE 8have been made in some of the programmes onthis account. In addition a central allowance forshortfall for all the industries has been made forpurposes of estimating demands on resources.This allowance has been taken into account inthe summary tables in the main Report but isnot included in any of the tables below. Furtherinformation on shortfall is given in the specialanalysis on the nationalised industries in Part 2of this Appendix.4. As the result of the changes described belowestimated expenditure by the nationalised industries on fixed assets after (and, indeed,before) deducting shortfall is in aggregate belowthe comparable previous programmes in allthe years covered by the Survey.* These adjustments consist of:(i) receipts from the sale of fixed assets (separatelyidentified in the tables) and(ii) increase in the value of stocks, net lending to private sector, net lending and investment abroad,and cash expenditure on company securities(grouped in the tables under the heading &quot; Othercapital expenditure &quot;).  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72provisional   estimate     estimateoutturn1972-73 1973-74 1974-75estimate     estimate     estimateExpenditure on fixed assets in the United kingdom.   National Coal Board    ....	61-2	74-0	75-0	660	600	58-0b.   Electricity Council and Boards	454-0	402-5	357-0	372-0	407-0	505-0c.   North of Scotland Hydro-Electric Board .	10-5	13-6	13-5	17-0	21-7	35-1d.   South of Scotland Electricity Board .	62-5	69-5	58-3	59-8.	47-7	42-1e.   Gas Council and Boards       .      .      .	2100	231-3	2100	181-0	189-0	1720Total......	798-2	790-9	713-8	695-8	725-4	812-2Less: Sales of fixed assets    .	-14-7	-12-1	-130	-10-6	-101	-9-gross domestic fixed capital formation .	783-5	778-8	700-8	685-2	715-3	803-other capital expenditure     .      .	-390	-17-4	0-3	0-8	14-1	110Total capital expenditure .	744-5	761-4	701-1	686-0	729-4	814-confidential 11
1. all the programmes in table 8 are based on demand assumptions for different fuels. theseare affected by rate of growth in gdp, relativeprices and consumer preferences. individual industries&apos; demand forecasts may reflect someoptimism about market shares but they are consistent with the department of trade andindustry&apos;s own forecast of energy requirements in the period up to 1975.a. national coal board. the industry&apos;s programme includes invest-ment in collieries and ancillaries, e.g. brickworksand loans to a north sea gas subsidiary. theother capital expenditure reductions shown intable 8 largely follow the adjustments made forthe large fall in coal stocks in 1969-70 and1970-71.3. colliery investment, at about  50 million ayear, is geared to meeting demand of 128 million tons of coal in 1974-75. although this estimate is realistic the future pattern of supply and demand is necessarily uncertain, but investmentdoes not have to be committed far ahead andthere is sufficient flexibility in the programme for changes to be made from 1972-73 in nextyear&apos;s review. the table does not includeinvestment in coal blending projects which wouldenable the steel industry&apos;s demands to be met with less need for imports. this proposal would add approximately  2 million to public expenditure in 1970-71 and  5 million in eachof the two following years. if it shows asatisfactory return when the project has beenappraised these additional sums would be earlybids against the contingency reserve.4. capital expenditure in table 8 also includes 4 million in 1970-71 and  4 million in1971-72 to meet ncb commitments in diversifiedundertakings;  3 million a year is included for1972-73 onwards. this area of the board&apos;activities is under review, as are the otherancillary activities.b. Electricity Council  and Boards  (Englandand Wales)5. the necessary level of investment in electricity generating capacity is determined bythe forecast level of simultaneous maximumdemand for the sixth and seventh winters ahead(i.e\, when capacity started in year one is cominginto service); the margin of capacity judgednecessary to provide for variations in actualfrom forecast demand, breakdowns, etc.; andthe view taken on whether plant already under construction will be available on the due date.the need to ensure a reasonably steady load ofwork on the electrical plant manufacturers is also important. the electricity councips forecast of demand for the winter of 1975-76 (54,000 mw.) is2,500 mw. lower than last year&apos;s forecast for thesame winter. the department of trade andindustry consider this a realistic central estimate;but it could of course be changed next year in either direction. the cegb have, however, now come to the view that the planning margin of17 per cent of demand to which they have workedsince 1964 is too low and that it should beraised to 23 per cent. on the other hand in theirforecasts the cegb are assuming that the delays in construction which are seriously affecting plantnow being built will have been virtually removed by 1974 and will not reappear thereafter. theproposal to increase the plant margin is thesubject of a detailed study by the electricity council. when they have reached a view on itthe question will have to be considered by thegovernment.6. the extent to which the industry will over-come the present delays in constructing newpower stations is not susceptible to detailedforecasting though the department of trade andindustry regard the assumption set out above asoptimistic. equally the desirable future level of plant margin raises major issues which cannot be immediately resolved.7. the figures in line b of table 8 include provision for the one certain cegb start in 1970indicated in cmnd. 4234, and up to two cegbstations in 1971, on the assumption that the plantmargin will remain at 17 per cent. the autumnexpenditure review took account of the additionalrisk of planning to meet demand with a 17 percent plant margin in the light of plantmalfunctioning. on the other hand, subject to the1971 electricity load forecast, a decision to gofor a more secure plant margin would call forsignificantly higher public expenditure throughoutthe survey period, and is likely to be the subjectof discussion during the 1971 review.8. in arriving at the above expenditure levels,provision for conversion of coal fired power stations to oil and gas has been included only for those conversions included in the cegb&apos;sapproved investment programme. threeadditional conversions have since been approved,and any later proposals, to which there is no commitment, would have to be considered ontheir merits at the appropriate time. any expenditure which could not be met by counter-vailing savings elsewhere in the programme would be an early charge on the contingency reserve. account has also been taken of the factthat in recent years the industry has tended to spend less capital than expected. in the light ofthis experience reductions of  12 million and 20 million a year have been made in the cegband area boards&apos; programmes for realism; if,contrary to expectations, the boards were able
to sustain a case for greater expenditure these reductions would probably have to be restored in whole or in part.c. and d.  Scottish electricity9. Although they are separate statutory bodiesthe North of Scotland Hydro-Electric Board andthe South of Scotland Electricity Board operatea joint generating system. The North Board&apos;sproposals include a new nuclear station in theNorth-East of Scotland, to increase capacity in1977. The timing of the start of this station will depend upon discussions on the type of nuclearreactor involved.10. As with the CEGB, the South Board&apos;expenditure includes provision for the approvedconversion of coal fired stations. The Board haspressed for further conversions (costing  6 millionbut improving performance by  6-5 million over the next 5 years with substantial savingsthereafter). These further conversions depend upon a current special study of Scottish coalprospects and general policy: the cost ofadditional conversions would have to be meteither from savings or the contingency reserve.e. Gas Council and Boards11. The gas programme is aimed at achieving a target absorption rate for natural gas of9. steel table 94,000 million cubic feet a day by 1975by marketing gas as near to maximum availabilityas is prudent and by keeping investment in thenecessary facilities just ahead of marketing.Costs of converting appliances to burn natural gas(up to  88 million a year) which are not includedin the table, but are reflected in the industry&apos;sgross trading surpluses, are also an essential partof the natural gas programme.12. This programme was co-ordinated by the gas Council in anticipation of powers which the gas Bill would have given. This co-ordination,and the adoption of operational researchmethods, etc., resulted in economies in 1969-70and enabled the Gas Council to make somereductions in the Area Boards&apos; programmessubmitted earlier this year. But during theautumn expenditure review the industry was ableto identify further savings, although these put tosome risk the natural gas supply programme to which the industry is committed by contract with the North Sea gas producers. The rapidabsorption of natural gas is an important national fuel policy objective and if it should prove necessary to achieve the programme some part of the reductions in expenditure may haveto be restored.  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74      1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturnBritish Steel Corporation     ....	84 0	130-0	185-0	185:0	185-0	185-0Lew: Sales of fixed assets    .      .      .      .	-3-0	r      	 &apos;	-10		 Gross domestic fixed capital formation .	81-0	1300	185-0	184-0	185-0	185-other capital expenditure     ....	25-0	5-0	40	4-0	21-0	10-0Total capital expenditure .      .      .	106-0	135-0	189-0	188-0	206-0	195-01. The Corporation^ expenditure on fixed assets is to replace, modernise and rationaliseexisting plant, and the programme is designed toenable output to rise from the 1970 level of about25 million tons of crude steel to about 33 million tons by 1975. Expenditure of: around  185million is envisaged in each of the years1971-72 to 1974-75, though the Corporation isexpected to make a case in its next investment programme for a higher level of between 225 million and  275 million geared to a higher level of exports.   Expenditure of  185 millionhas been approved for 1971-72. The Corpora-tion&apos;s case for any further increase for that and later years will be considered by Ministers on its merits and at the appropriate time.2. The amounts for &quot; Other capital expendi-ture&quot; include provision for a net increase in value of steel stocks and work in progress ofabout  40 million in the period to 1974-75, muchof it towards the end of the period, in line withexpectations about the cyclical pattern of steeldemand; but these figures are tentative.CONFIDENTIAL13
10.  Post OfficeTABLE 10  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturnExpenditure on fixed assets in the United KingdomPost Office(i) Telecommunications      .      .	358-2	417	1	452-0	480-4	495-5	493-5(ii) Posts and Giro    .      .      .	29-1*	36	2	41-9	44-7	50-8	51-6(iii) National Data Processing Service   .	3-9	8	0	10-6	13-9	12-6	19-3Total    ...	391-2	461	3	504-5	539-0	558-9	564-4Less: Sales of fixed assets   .	-2-1	-1	8	-0-4	-1-1	-1-1	-1-gross domestic fixed capital formation	389-1	459	5	504-1	537-9	557-8	563-other capital expenditure	16-3	5	5	3-2	3-7	3-2	2-5Total capital expenditure       .      .       405-4        465-0        507-3        541-6        561-0       565-8* Includes  2-2 million investment on behalf of the Director of National Savings.1. The programme as a whole is based oncontinued expansion of the three sides of thePost Office&apos;s business. It assumes average annual increases in telephone exchange connections of8-9 per cent, in local calls of 10 per cent, andin inland trunk calls of 12 per cent reducing to10 per cent. It provides for further modernisa-tion, the expansion of the data transmissionservice, and measures to aid productivity. Theestimates include the costs of conversion of the few remaining manual telephone exchanges and extending subscriber trunk dialling (STD) to allcustomers. Account has been taken of sub-stantial shortfall expected from delays in thesupply of exchange equipment.   Investment inPosts and Giro incorporates expenditure on themechanisation of the postal services andthe essential programme of replacement of uneconomic buildings: a slow rate of growth,not exceeding 2 per cent a year, is assumed formails business.2. The National Data Processing Service, whosefuture is under review, at present providescomputer services.for the other two sides of thePost Office business, and also aims to secure ashare of the commercial market. The totals for future years are estimates based on the continua-tion of present policies, which may be varied,and do not represent commitments.11.  Airways and airportsTABLE 11  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional    estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturnExpenditure on fixed assets in the United kingdom.   British Overseas Airways Corporation   .	46-1	92-8	60-7	76-6	87-1	105-4b.   British European Airways     .	19-2	42-1	59-5	42-9	27-3	47-1c.   British Airports Authority	9-3	11-9	15-1	16-2	19-1	32-4Total   ..     .      .      . .    .     .	74-6	146-8	135-3	135-7	133-5	184-9Less: Sales of fixed assets   .      .      .     .	-4-5	-3-1	-0-4	-2-5	-20	, -1-gross domestic fixed capital formation	70-1	143-7	134-9	133-2	131-5	183-other capital expenditure    .      .     ......	1-3	8-0	5-9	3-0	3-7	2-7Total capital expenditure	71-4	151-7	140-8	136-2	135-2	186-6
a. British Overseas Airways Corporation1. boac&apos;s programme is mainly based onpurchases of new aircraft. These includeBoeing 747s, or their equivalent, and, pro-visionally, five Concordes. The sharp increasein expenditure in 1974-75 is mainly the resultof a build-up of progress payments for fleetreplacement and expansion in subsequent years.b. British European Airways2. BEA&apos;s programme is similarly dominated by its fleet requirements. It is open to revision inthe light of the particular airbus ordered.c. British Airports Authority3. BAA&apos;s programme provides for extension of facilities at Heathrow and Gatwick and also for expenditure on the early stages of the third london Airport. It is liable to considerablechange when a decision is made on the particularsite of the airport and on the date of its opening.12. Surface transport industriesTABLE 12  million at 1970 Survey prices	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					Expenditure on fixed assets in the United Kingdom*						a.   British Railways Board .      .	78-0	83-1	94-0	100-0	1000	100-0b.   London Transport Board	61,		 	 	 	 c.   British Transport Docks Board	16-2	14-8	131	15-5	16-5	13-5d.   British Waterways Board	0-7	0-8	0-8	0-9	0-9	1-0e.   Transport Holding Company .	0-3	0-8	0-9	11	0-4	0-3f.   National Freight Corporation.	30-3	31-5	29-6	29-2	27-8	27-9g.   National Bus Company       .      .	. .      11-8	17-0	17-8	16-5	16-2	16-2h   Scottish Transport Group	3-5	3-4	4-2	4-0	3-5	3-3Total    .      .	146-9	151-4	160-4	167-2	165-3	162-2Less: Sales of fixed assets   .      .	-20-3	-17-6	-28-7	-23-9	-20-9	-15-2Gross domestic fixed capital formation	126-6	133-8	131-7&apos;	143-3	144-4	147-other capital expenditure    ...	-7-7 r	4-4	1-1	1-2	1-2	1-3Total capital expenditure	118-9	138-2	132-8	144-5	145-6	148-3&quot;Excluding infrastructure expenditure which is shown in line b (iv) of Table 14Hiving off1. The Minister for Transport Industries hopesshortly to put forward proposals for the sale tothe private sector of Thomas Cook, and theother subsidiaries of the Transport holding company, of British Railways&apos; hotels, and of theshipping subsidiaries of the National freight corporation. This will benefit the public expenditure programme in terms both ofprospective investment cancelled and also of thereceipts from the sale of the assets. It isimpossible to put firm figures on these.proposals at this stage but in the meantime some credit istaken in the forecast of income from sales offixed assets in Table 12.a. British Railways board. BRB aim to complete by the end of this yeara Corporate Plan which, if approved, will be thebasis of their investment for the following fiveyears.  In the meantime,. the present forecast oftheir expenditure for 1972-73 and the yearsfollowing is inevitably provisional.b. London Transport board. Responsibility for London Transport was transferred to the Greater London Council on1 January, 1970. Expenditure on london transport after that date is shown under &quot; Otherpassenger transport&quot; in Table 14.c. British Transport Docks Board4. The size of this programme is determined bythe forecast level of demand for new port facilities mainly at the Humber, South Wales and southampton.d. British Waterways board. This programme provides mainly for the replacement of craft and for warehousingfacilities. The investment on warehouses isoptional, but the profits it generates reduce theBoard&apos;s overall losses and therefore the grant payable on their operating deficit.CONFIDENTIALis
e. Transport Holding Company6. Investment by the THC is mainly in Thos.Cook &amp; Sons Ltd. There is also relatively smallprovision for investment in two other subsidiaries,Lunn-Poly and Pickfords Travel.f. National Freight Corporation7. NFC expenditure is on their four groups: theroad haulage subsidiaries; National CarriersLimited (formerly BRB&apos;s freight sundriesdivision); freight liners Limited (taken over fromBRB); and their shipping subsidiaries.g.  National Bus Company8. Most of the investment proposed is for theCompany&apos;s bus replacement programme. Therecommendation takes account of possibleslippage in 1970-71 and 1971-72.h.  Scottish Transport Group9. This proposed investment is for modernisa-tion of the Group&apos;s shipping fleet and piers andfor the replacement of buses and the constructionof bus depots.13.  Roads and public lightingTABLE 13   million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional    estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturna. - EnglandNEW CONSTRUCTION AND IMPROVEMENTSMotorways and trunk roads   .	183-4	227-5	2180	236-8	249-2	260-5Principal roads     ....	124-7	132-9	142-3	165-4	177-1	192-other roads.....	37-4	34-1	35-2	37-1	45-6	48-4Car parks    .      .	14-7	14-6	16-6	18-1	21-0	220Lighting.....	4-1	40	4-6	4-6	6-3	6-4Research and other expenditure	0-3	0-4	0-6	0-9	1-2	1-5Total    .      .	364-6	413-5	417-3	462-9	500-4	531-6MAINTENANCEMotorways and trunk roads   .	15-8	17-5	20-2	23-5	23-5	23-6Principal roads     .      .      .	261	32-2	36-2	38-6	36-9	390Other roads.....	85-8	97-7	103-3	110-9	117-3	126-5Carparks    .      .      .            &apos;.	-4-6	-6-6	-7-7	-9-2	-7-5	-8-2Lighting.....	20-9	21 0	21-8	22-6	26-2	27-6Research and other expenditure	- ..     - 2-7   -	3-1	3-8	5-1	6-7	8-4Total146-7164-9177-6191-5203-1216-9-Central government administrationLocal authority administration3-726-43-737-44-040-24-04314-135-94-137-0Total England541-4619-5639-1701-5743-5789-6b.  WalesNEW CONSTRUCTION AND IMPROVEMENTSMotorways and trunk roads	9-8	14-7	15-5	16-5	20-4	22-0Principal roads     ....	3-6	4-1	5-4	6-3	6-8	7-other roads .      .	4-0	40	4-2	4-6	5-5	5-9Car parks    .      .	0-7	0-7	0-7	0-8	0-9	1-3Lighting      .      .      .      .	0-8	0-7	0-7	0-7	0-9	1-0Total    .      .      .      ,	18-9	24.-2	26-5	28-9	34-5	37-4
5. The figures attributed to overseas aid stillinclude the defence component of the special aid to Malaysia and Singapore which is not part ofthe aid programme. The public expendituretotals also differ from the aid programme totalsin the treatment of the Commonwealth Develop-ment Corporation (CDC). Whereas the aid programme includes the amount of advancesfrom the Exchequer to the CDC, the public expenditure figure incorporates the net flow of funds from the CDC to overseas countries. Thereis therefore an adjustment, which may be positiveor negative (see line f. in Table 3) to take accountof the balance of the Corporation^ netinvestment overseas.4. Other overseas services table 4  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70provisionaloutturn1970-71estimate1971-72estimate1972-73estimate1973-74estimate1974-75estimatea. Overseas representation       .      .      .      .        61-3 63-8 65-4 66-1 65-7 65-9b. Overseas information   .      .      .      .      . 30-4 31-5 30-9 31-4 31-1 31-1c. Other external relations       .      .      .     ..        35-4 34-1 33-0 32-5 33-4 34-2Total......       127-1        129-4        129-3 130-0        130-2        131-21. The expenditure on Other Overseas Servicesshows no significant change from 1970-71,although it includes allowance for some reduc-tions in the size of the Diplomatic Service. Theexpenditure is directed to the promotion ofBritish interests overseas. Part of it is governeddirectly by international commitments.M   &quot; ;   &apos;a. Overseas representation2. This expenditure comprises the cost of theForeign and Commonwealth Office (including the overseas Development Administration) and ofthe Diplomatic Service and its accommodation and associated expenses in representing Britishinterests internationally.b. Overseas information.  This covers three main elements:(a) British Council expenditure to promotewider knowledge of the United Kingdomand the English language abroad and to foster cultural relations with other countries(another part of the Councils expenditure is included in Table 3, Overseas Aid).(b) The cost of the BBCs External Servicesand  associated  expenditure involved in1 , v..British broadcasting directed to othercountries; and(c) The cost of information staff at home andabroad and of supporting services of theCentral Office of Information and the stationery Office.The functions described above are under reviewas part of the wider examination of Governmentactivities.c.   Other external relations4. This expenditure mainly comprises the secret service and international commitments andsubscriptions, including the United Kingdom&apos;sassessed contributions to regular budgets ofUnited Nations organisations and of theOrganisation for Economic Co-operation andDevelopment, the Council of Europe and theNorth Atlantic Treaty Organisation (secretariatcosts). While every effort continues to be madeto contain the rate of expansion of such budgets,the forecasts of assessed contributions payableare based on the most realistic assumptionspossible at this stage. Provision has been included for continued voluntary support of theUnited Nations Force in Cyprus.confidential
5.  Agriculture, fisheries and forestryTABLE 5  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturna.   Agricultural support	(i) Price guarantees*	132-2	168-0	141-0	116-0	66-0	160	(ii) Relevant production grants	105-5	1190	1130	112-0	112-0	112-0	(iii) Other grants and subsidies .	37-8	48-0	49-0	400	34-0	36 0	Total    .....	275-5	335-0	303-0	268-0	212-0	164-0b.	Other assistance to agriculture	48-7	70-7	75-0	79-0	78-4	79-2c.		7-3	10-6	10-3	101	9-8	9-9d.		42-0	45-3	49-0	51-4	55-2	59-3Grand total.....       373-5        461-6        437-3        408-5        355-4        312-4* Including arbitrary reductions, see paragraph 4 below,a.  Agricultural support . This expenditure covers the implementation of the price guarantees, the provision of grants and subsidies to farmers and the associatedadministrative costs. This year it is particularly difficult to put a figure on the future cost ofagricultural support. The cost of implementing the guarantees is liable to marked variationsaccording to the levels of supply and of market prices, and no attempt can be made to forecast the effect on expenditure of changes in the levels of the guarantees and subsidies resulting fromthe determinations made at future Farm PriceReviews.2. Account has been taken of the government&apos;s decision to replace investment grants by invest-ment allowances and also of the underspendingnow in prospect for the current year, but no attempt has been made to allow for entry intothe e.c. before the end of the quinquennium.3. The figures for agricultural support do not therefore represent an attempt to predict thefuture course of expenditure but are presented onmuch the same conventional basis as in thepast: namely, a projection of the Estimates forthe current year adjusted so as to take accountof the full-year effects of this year&apos;s Price Review.The conventional figure has been reduced by 10 million in the light of up-to-date information.In practice, the cost of agricultural support may result in higher or lower expenditure than thefigures in the table, depending on the factorsdescribed above.4. A new feature is presented this year by the government&apos;s announced intention of introducing a new system of agricultural support based onlevy arrangements to replace deficiency payments,with the aim of achieving savings of the order of 150 million by 1974-75. It is the intention tomake a start in introducing these new arrange-ments in 1971-72. It is, however, impossible to forecast what the effect of changes in support arrangements will be on expenditure year by year in the intervening period, because the timing and method of implementing the change mustnecessarily be related to the progress of inter-national negotiations. The savings for these years have accordingly been put, on a quite arbitrarybasis, at  25 million in 1971-72,  50 million in1972-73 and  100 million in 1973-74. the expected saving of the order of  150 million by1974-75 has been taken into account in the figuresfor that year.b. Other assistance to agriculture . Most of the other expenditure by MAFF andDAFS on agricultural and horticultural services is included here. As with agricultural support,some expenditure has been projected forward ona conventional basis with no detailed forecast of future variations e.g. animal disease compensa-tion, and payments made under the Anglo-IrishFree Trade Agreement. One of these conven-tional items, provision for stabilisation payments to the bacon curing industry, has been increased in the light of up-to-date information. The othermain increases are due to the development of policies under the Agriculture Acts 1967 and1970, and to the modernisation of wholesalehorticultural markets.c. Fisheries6. The main expenditure under this headingrelates to subsidies for the fishing industry and grants and loans for new vessels and equipment.Future expenditure on these depends on operating
results and on the plans for capital investment which may be made by the industry. Neithercan be forecast with accuracy. The decrease overthe forecast period takes account of reductions in rates of grant following the withdrawal of investment grants.d.  Forestry7. This item includes both state forestry and grants to the private sector. The figures make no provision for a change in policy. They include an estimate of the increasing value of State-owned   forests,   taken   as   equal   to   the. Research Councils, etc.it able 6a. Research Councils.....95-7b. Social Science Research Council .      .      . 2-3c. Agricultural research, Scotland    .      .      . 2*9Total    .      .      ... 100-9  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70    1970-71    1971-72provisional estimate   allocationoutturnAgricultural Research			Council - ..	15-7	16-2	16-8Medical Research			Council	18-5	19-7	20-3Natural Environment			Research Council .	12-2	13-9	14-6Science Research			Council	46-4	49-6	51-9Natural History			Museum*	1-2	1-8	1-7Science: Grants and			Services	ii    1-5	1-6	2-2Documentation			Processing Centre	0-2	0-4	 &quot; Science Budget &quot; j	95-7	103-2	107-5Social Science			Research Council	2-3	3-3	3-8Agricultural research,			Scotland	2-9	3-1	3-4Total    .	100-9	109-6	114-7* Includes provision for major building,a.  &quot;Science Budget&quot;1. This is a block budget which the Secretaryof State for Education and Science allocates eachCONFIDENTIALCommission^ net cost of forestry operations asworked out for accounting purposes. the cash requirement shows little change over thefive years, at about  15 million a year. a review of the method of financing the forestry commission has taken place and, as a result, the presentation of the figures will be altered in future years. A very large part of the cost of interestwill be recorded as a subsidy to the nationalforestry enterprise. Ministers have also directed that there should be a study of the costs and benefits of state forestry and this will be beginningsoon.  million at 1970 Survey prices1971-72 1972-73 1973-74 1974-75estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate103-2        107-5        112-5        117-2        121-43-3      ..   3-8 3-8 3-8 3-83-1 3-4 3-5 3-5 3-6109-6        114-7        119-8        124-5        128-8year to individual Councils after receiving theadvice of the Council for Scientific Policy (CSP).The table shows the allocation for 1971-72 madeon the advice of the CSP.2. As announced in &quot;New Policies for public spending&quot; (Cmnd. 4515), the programme ofexpenditure on the Research Councils is being reviewed but as at present envisaged will rise to 122 million in 1974-75 for the &quot;science budget&quot;. The level of expenditure from 1971-72onwards involves a growth rate well below thatrecommended by the CSP in their review under-taken in Summer 1970.b. Social Science Research Council3. Expenditure on the SSRC, who deal directly with the Department of Education and science and not through the CSP, is at present expectedto remain around its present level between1971-72 and 1974-75. It.is planned in the nearfuture to integrate expenditure on the SSRC intothe &quot;Science Budget&quot; and to adapt presentationin the coming public expenditure White Paperaccordingly.c. Agricultural research, scotland. Within the field of agricultural research anumber of Institutes in Scotland are financedseparately on Scottish Votes although their programmes of research are co-ordinated withthe Agricultural Research Council.71969-70     1970-71provisional   estimate outturn
7.  Trade, industry and employment						TABLE 7				  million at 1970 Survey prices			1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75provisional		estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					Department of Trade and Industry						I.   General services						1.  Administration    .      .	31-3	33-0	34-7	35-9	36-5	37-0: Government research and development 						2.  Industrial research establishments .	12-3	13-7	14-5	14-4	14-2	14-83.  Central computing facility   .		0-3	1-6	2-7	2-0	0-64.  sea civil research and development (other						than capital expenditure on major reactor						projects)......	37-8	39-6	380	34-8	31-6	30-2Direct support for industrial technology 						5.  Sponsored industries and general support .	7-4	9-9	11-6	14-5	19-6	22-06.  NRDC.......	6-2	4-7	2-2	1-7	1-8	2-17.  Industrial research associations	4-0	4-0	4-0	4-0	4-0	4-08.  Unallocated savings arising from						Cmnd. 4515	-	-	-7-5	-110	-15-0	-20-0Total (I).	99-0	105-2	99-1	97-0	94-7	90-7Department of Trade and IndustryII. Promotion of employment and investment9.  Promotion of local employment:	Gross   .     .     .     .	67-5	72-5	88-1	98-9	105-8	109-6	Loan repayments, rents and sales	-21-9	-23-6	-30-8	-33-1	-360	-36.0	Net expenditure     .	45-6	48-9	57-3	65-8	69-8	73-610.	Investment grants       ....	573-4	504 0	552-0	261-0	126-0	65-011.	Assistance to coal industry  .	24-8	26-6	17-5	15-0	130	8-0	Total (II)      .      .      .      .	643-8	579-5	626-8	341-8	208-8	146-6Department of Trade and Industrym. Other12.  Atomic energy:(i) Major  reactor   projects  (capital	expenditure)   .	10-5	10-0	100	5-4	2-7	2-7	(ii) Ore purchases   .      .	11-2	11-4	8-9	4-5	2-6		(iii) sea trading fund-capital							formation	7-6	14-8	 	..  	::&apos;&quot;:J-:		(iv) Prpduction expenditure and receipts							(net)     .      .	-22-9	-50	-7-2	-13-7	-15-5	-11-4	(v) Terminal payments to sea from							Special Materials Vote	-23-4	-20-6	-19-5	 	. &apos;- -j::&apos; &apos;		(vi) Reorganisation expenditure .	0-6	0-2			:&apos;- .	 ; &apos;	(vii) Aluminium  smelters  (plutonium							purchases)     ....	.  .		0-3	0-3	0-3	0-3	(viii) Loans (net) British Nuclear Fuels							Ltd. and Radio Chemical Centre							Ltd.      .      .      .		....   -    .	7-1	3-7 s	12-4	24-8	(ix) Other expenditure	-	-	-	0-8	0-7	0-5	Total atomic energy	-16-4	10-8	-0-4	10	3-2	16-913.	Assistance to shipbuilding industry .	20-3	15-5	8-6	 	-      i 	-0-314.	Industrial investment schemes:							(i) Computers merger .      .      .      .	4-0	3-3	2-3	3-2	  V&apos;		(ii) Aluminium smelters	9-4	12-9	6-9	8-2	1-5	0-115.	Industrial Reorganisation Corporation  .	30-2	25-0	0-5	-2-5	-7-0	-4-016.	Miscellaneous services ....	-7-4	-3-2	0-5	0-4	-15-1	0-517.	Promotion of tourism, exports, etc.	17-9	18-4	21-8	24-4	21-4	17-818.	Unallocated savings arising from							Cmnd. 4515*	-	-	-	-	-	-5-0	Total (HI)     .      .      .	58-0	82-7	40-2	34-7	4-0	26-0* The Category III savings shown are those remaining after the elimination of the provision for unapproved industrial projects.The total unallocated savings shown do not therefore add up to those in Cmnd. 4515.
TABLE 7 (continued)   million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71      1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturnIV. Ministry of Aviation Supply (civil aerospace)19.	Headquarters (civil)     ....	2-3	2-3	2-4	2-5	2-5	2-520.	Aircraft projects and assistance	87-3	85-2	830	87-1	67-8	27-921.	Space: international programme   .	8-3	3-8	2-1	3-2	5-6	6-622.	Central computing facility	 	&apos;-	1-3	0-9	1-0	0-323.	Other civil aerospace   .	19-2	19-5	20-4	20-9	19-7	19-924.	Unallocated savings arising from							Cmnd. 4515	-	.- !    i)	-2-5				Total (IV)     .      .	117-1	110-8	106-7	114-6	96-6	57-2V.  Department of Employment and other expenditure25.	Employment services   .	70-8	76-2	78-1	81-4	83-3	85-1	SET paid by local authorities   .	0-4	0-4	0-4	0-4	0-4	0-426.	Redundancy Fund payments .	38-2	42-7	43-5	39-0	32-2	32-227.	SET additional payments	28-5	70	10	01	&apos; .	28.	Regional employment premiums	109-0	106-2	106-2	106-2	106-2	72-229.	Productivity services    .	6-3	8-6	8-9	8-2	7; 7	7-630.	Covent Garden Market Authority (capital							expenditure)       .      .      .     .      .	3-3	5-7	7-5	7-7	20	0-3	Total (V)      .      .      .     .      . Grand total   .      .      .     .	256-5	246-8	245-6	243-0	231-8	197-8		1,174-4	1,1250	1,118-4	831-1	635-9	518-31. The expenditure in this block (previouslycalled Technology, Industry and Employment)has been rearranged to take account of themachinery of Government changes announced in cmnd. (4506. Categories I to III cover expendi-ture by the Department of Trade and Industry,Category IV covers expenditure by the Ministryof Aviation Supply and Category V expenditure for which other Departments are responsible,mainly the Department of Employment. Of the 60 million reduction in 1974-75 made in theformer Ministry of Technology&apos;s expenditure (on top of the saving through winding up the 1958-59) 35 million has been included under theDepartment of Trade and Industry and 25 million under the Ministry of AviationSupply. Of the  35 million for the Departmentof Trade and Industry,  20 million has been provisionally apportioned to Category I and 15 million to Category III.I. Department of Trade and Industry generalservices2. The expenditure in this section coversactivities which by their nature allow some flexibility in financial management from year to year and can therefore be programmed ahead.The cost of the Department^ administration is contained in this heading. Decreases reflectingdecisions in Cmnd. 4515 are shown as unallocatedCONFIDENTIALpending completion of reviews but will mainlybe found from the Atomic Energy Authority&apos;expenditure on civil research and development,sponsored industries and general support. Thefigures do not, however, allow for possiblefurther longer-term policy decisions affectingthe sea&apos;s expenditure.II.  Department   of   Trade   and   Industry promotion of employment and investmentpromotion of local employment. Expenditure on the promotion of local employment comprises loans and grants by theDepartment of Trade and Industry to jfirmsproviding additional employment in the develop-ment and intermediate areas, the development ofindustrial estates and the provision of factories.The figures allow for the extended measures ofassistance to industry detailed in (a) to (c) ofparagraph 14 of the White Paper on &quot; investment incentives &quot; (Cmnd. 4516).investment grants4. The figures reflect the decision to discon-tinue investment grants. Residual expenditure under contracts entered into before 27 October,1970, will continue for some years but theamount cannot be forecast with precision at thisstage; it has been assumed that in 1974-75 it willbe  65 million.9
assistance to the coal industry. The estimates in line 11 reflect theGovernment^ decision to continue assistance tothe coal industry and to the miners after the expiry of powers under the Coal Industry Act1967. The figures assume the continuation of theincome supplementation scheme in its present form until March 1974; as the Coal Bill makesclear, there is no commitment to this.III. Department of Trade and Industry other6. This covers a number of unprogrammableitems. Previous provision for unapprovedindustrial projects has been deleted. In 1971-72this leads to an additional saving of  4 - 5 million over and above the Cmnd. 4515 savings for thatyear.atomic energy7. This includes capital expenditure on major projects and other nuclear expenditure other thanthat programmed under Category I. the forecasts assume that the Atomic energy authority Trading Fund will be replaced byBritish Nuclear Fuels Ltd. and the RadioChemical Centre Ltd. on 1 April, 1971, and areof necessity tentative.industrial reorganisation corporation8. Following the decision to wind up theIndustrial Reorganisation Corporation theprevious forecast of up to  40 million a year netlending is eliminated from 1971-72 onwards.The saving for that year is  10 million higherthan was assumed in Cmnd. 4515. The negativefigures in later years indicate repayments.promotion of tourism and exports, etc.9. This covers DTI services to promote tourismand exports. It includes expenditure by theBritish Tourist Authority and the English,Scottish and Wales Tourist Boards, andexpenditure administered by the Tourist Boardson the hotel loans and grants scheme (whichis not to be renewed when its existing time limits run out) and on the new limited schemeof assistance to tourism in development areas.It also covers expenditure on trade fairs, on&quot;grants to the British National Export Counciland on assistance to the National ExhibitionCentre and to certain other bodies, principallythe Council of Industrial Design and the national film Finance Corporation.IV. Ministry    of    Aviation    Supply    (civilaerospace)10. This heading covers approved programmes for the development, proving and production ofcivil aircraft and aero-engines, including thiscountry&apos;s share of the Concorde project; theBritish space programme, and Britain&apos;s contribu-tions to international space programmes; andcertain loans and other transactions by way ofspecial assistance to firms in the aircraft industry.It also covers part of the costs of the headquarters and research and development establishments ofthe Ministry of Aviation Supply, and of aerospaceresearch in industry, which are divided betweenthe Defence Budget and this heading becauseof their joint benefit to defence and non-defence purposes. No provision is made in the figuresfor the cost of new civil aircraft or aero-engineprojects. If any such projects arc approved inthe period under review, in accordance with thepolicy of providing launching aid for civil aircraft projects where this is justified, their cost will bea claim on the contingency reserve.V.  Department   of   Employment   and   otherexpenditureemployment services11. Employment services comprise expenditure by the Department of Employment and expendi-ture by local authorities on services (includingthe youth employment service) for which theDepartment makes grants. The larger items ofexpenditure are departmental administration(including the employment exchanges, Govern-ment Training Centres and the factory inspectorate), training and rehabilitation schemes,and services for the seriously disabled.12. The increase over the Survey period is due mainly to further development of the placing,advisory and industrial training services,including the continued expansion of government training Centres to about 14,400 places by theend of 1974-75, and the implementation of theIndustrial Relations Bill.redundancy fund payments ,13. Payments out of the Redundancy Fund whichis financed by employers&apos; contributions collectedthrough the National Insurance stamp, are administered by the Department of Employment.These payments show a reduction for the yearsfollowing 1971-72 - because increased industrial activity is expected to reduce the incidence ofredundancies.set    additional    payments    and     regional employment premium14. Additional payments under the selective employment Tax (SET) arrangements and regional employment premiums are paid in thegreat majority of cases by the Department ofEmployment to qualifying employers. a relatively small amount is paid by otherDepartments to nationalised industries in respectof those parts of their undertakings whichqualify.15. SET additional payments were abolishedwith effect from  1 April,  1970 but because
PUBLIC EXPENDITURE TO 1974-75APPENDIX TO1970 REPORT BY THE PUBLIC EXPENDITURE SURVEYCOMMITTEECONTENTSpart one.  detailed analysis of programmesPagedefence and external relations .  Defence Budget       .      ...      .      .      .	-      -      -      -       32.  Other military defence      .      .      .      .      .	&quot; . 11             -   .       3 &apos; ;3.  Overseas aid           .      .      .      .	.      .       44.  Other overseas services     .      .      .      .      .      -      -	. &quot;   .&apos;&quot;   . -i :   &quot;&quot;5commerce and industry	5.  Agriculture, fisheries and forestry       ...	66.  Research Councils, etc.     .      .      .      .	77.  Trade, industry and employment.      .      .	.    \       8(1 nationalised industries capital expenditure	8.  Fuel...... ,  .      .      .	.    . ; . &apos;   &apos;. &apos; &apos; n9.  Steel      .      .     .     .      .      /     .     .     &quot;.      .	.      .      .      .      1310.  Post Office.........	1411.  Airways and airports .      .      .      .      .	1412.  Surface transport industries       .      .      .      .      .	15transport and miscellaneous local services	13.  Roads and public lighting .      .      .      .	.  \ .      1614.  Transport.........	.      .      .      1915.  Housing  .      .      .      .      .	.      .      .      .     21! 16.  Miscellaneous local services       .      .      .	....     2317.  Law and order .            .      .      .      .      .      .      .	.......2618.  Arts       .      .      .      .      .      .            .      .,	.   . .        .     28CONFIDENTIAL 111292
Pagesocial services19.  Education       .      .      .      .      .      .....      .      ,      .     2920.  Health and welfare............     3221.  Social security .      .      ...      .      . . .      -      .36other services22.  Financial administration...........3823.  Common services............     3924.  Miscellaneous services      .      .      .      .      .      ...      .      -      -      .4025.  Northern Ireland      .      .      .      .      .....      .      .      .      .     4126.  Debt interest...........      .      .      .     42part twomethodology......... notes:1.   Expenditure figures in this Appendix are at 1970 Survey prices unless otherwise stated.2. References in this Appendix to &quot; previous programmes &quot; should be read according to the definition in the White Paper&quot; New Policies for Public Spending &quot; (Cmnd. 4515):&quot; General Notes on Tables 1 and 2(i) The figures in column (a) are the costings made in the latest annual Survey of public expenditure and long-termcostings of defence policy which are prepared in the early summer of each year. They include the estimates then made of the cost of the policies set out in the White Paper &quot; Public Expenditure, 1968-69 to 1973-74 &quot; (Cmnd. 4234),and such changes of policy as were made after the White Paper but before the Survey. They represent the positionas seen at the beginning of this Parliament.&quot;3. The coverage of programmes-is the same as that in Cmnd. 4515. Changes in the organisation of central government,announced in Cmnd. 4505, are not reflected in the table in so far as re-allocation between programmes is concerned. The effects of the changes are, however, explained in the texts.
APPENDIXPART ONEDETAILED ANALYSIS OF programmes. Defence BudgetTABLE 1   million at 1970 Survey prices	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					Defence Budget .      .      .      .	.     2,398-9	2,387-0	2,327-0	2,270-0	2,290-0	2,300-0The figures for the Defence Budget were explained in the Supplementary Statement on defence Policy 1970 (Cmnd. 4521). This settledfirmly the expenditure on the defence programmeover the next four financial years. The figuresallow for the additional  expenditure to be incurred on the United Kingdom military contribution to the Five-Power defence arrange-ments in South-East Asia, the expansion of theTerritorial and Army Volunteer Reserve, and theother measures to improve our defence capabilityset out in Cmnd. 4521.2. Other military defenceTABLE 2   million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturna. Military aid....... 8-3 5-7 3-0           1-9           1-7           1-7b. Allied services    .      .      .      .      .      . 94-5 96 0 94-2         90-2         90-2         90-2c. United States military aircraft:(i) Purchases .      .      .      .      .      . 31-1 10-0 6-4         -           -           -(ii) Repayments..... -43-0 -50-2 -49-6 -49-1 -46-4 -38-4d. Other.      .      .      .      .      ,      .      . 0-2 -13-6 -3-4 -0-4        -0-5 -0-5Total......91-1 47-9 50-6 42-6 45-0 53-0a.  Military aid. This heading covers military technical assistance which provides for courses in theUnited Kingdom for the service personnel ofother countries, the provision of British service training teams on loan or secondment to developing (mainly Commonwealth) countries and a small amount of police training particularlyCONFIDENTIALin South-East Asia. It also covers the cost ofcapital equipment to a few countries although this type of expenditure is being run down. Thefigures for military aid do not include additional expenditure on the defence component of thespecial aid to Singapore and Malaysia, estimates for which are shown separately in Table 3(Overseas Aid).3
b. Allied services . Under this heading the main items areaccommodation for Ministry of Defence head-quarters staff, superannuation for civilian staff and HMSO and COI services (stationery and recruitment publicity).c. United States military aircraft. Final deliveries of aircraft have beencompleted but payments extend through 1970-71and 1971-72 to cover support costs and finalsettlements.4.  The treatment of the payments in respect ofthese aircraft is as follows:(i) Progress payments in respect of thepurchase and associated research anddevelopment    costs   are   included    in line c(i); they constitute the public expenditure cost as defined in thenational accounts. The United StatesCredits from which they are financed are treated as receipts in the national accounts.(ii) Repayments of the Credits are charged tothe Defence Budget when they occur; but since to include both these and theprogress payments in the total of public expenditure would involve double count-ing, the former are offset by equal butnegative entries in line c (ii). Similarlypayments of interest on the Credits whichare charged to the Defence Budget andare also included within the overall totalof debt interest, are offset by a negativeentry in line c (ii).3.  Overseas aidTABLE 3  million at outturn prices*1969-70     1970-71      1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturna.	Aid programme .      .      . .    .	205-0	212-0-&apos;				b.	Other overseas aid     .      .      .      .	13-8	17-1				c.	Total overseas economic aid (a 4- b)	218-8	229-1	245-0	265-0	300-0	340-0d.	Special defence aid for Singapore and Malaysia .	6-6	6 0	6 0	60	40	e.	Total Government expenditure on overseas aid .	225-4	235-1	251-0	271-0	304-0	340-0f.	Other net investment by the Commonwealth							Development Corporation (CDQt	-2-7	-2-2	-2-3	-0-2	-11	-0-7g-	Total public expenditure on overseas aid .	222-7	232-9	248-7	270-8	302-9	339-3* For explanation why outturn prices are used here, see paragraphs 1 and 2 below.t Difference between Government loans to the CDC from the aid programme and net investment by the CDC.1. The table above shows overseas aid expendi-ture in current price terms and the figures aregross, without deduction of amortisation. Thisis because the aid programme continues to bedetermined gross and in cash terms. Most ofthe commitments to overseas countries and international organisations are made in this formand receipts from past aid loans are contractuallydue irrespective of current decisions on new expenditure.2. For consistency and comparison with other public sector programmes however the overseas aid totals are presented in the main Report onthe same basis as these other programmes, i.e.,net of amortisation and at 1970 constant prices.The constant price figures are derived from the cash programmes by applying a deflating factordetermined in the light of historical trends. Theactual allocations for overseas aid will however be the gross cash figures stated above.3. The Government have announced, in theUnited Nations and in Parliament, on 23 and27 October, 1970, that they plan to increase theofficial aid programme for the next few years,and that they will do their best to reach theUNCTAD 1 per cent target by 1975, in the expectation that private flows will be able tomake a substantial, contribution. The overseas development Administration would see objectionif this expectation is interpreted as a conditionof United Kingdom intentions.4. The aid programme for the years up to1973-74 is as stated in Cmnd. 4234, and in1974-75 there will be a further increase of13 per cent in cash terms to  340 million. Until1970-71 certain aid items were separatelyauthorised outside the programme, but from1971-72 all items of economic aid areconsolidated into a single economic aid programme.
a. Records, registrations and surveys. This includes expenditure by several Govern-ment Departments (the Office of population censuses and Surveys, General Register Office(Scotland), Land Registry, Ordnance Survey, andother minor Departments) and a smaller proportion of local authority expenditure.Provision is made under the Office of population censuses and Surveys for the Social Surveys,carried out as an allied service for GovernmentDepartments.2. Expenditure shows a peak in 1971-72 onaccount of the Census.b. i.  British Broadcasting Corporation (HomeServices)3. The figures cover the capital requirements ofthe home broadcasting services of the BBC in theUnited Kingdom, incorporating expenditure onthe colour television service and an increase inthe number of local radio stations from 8 to 20by 1971. The Corporation^ expenditure (capital and current) is financed by Government grantwhich since 1961 has consisted of the whole of net income from licence revenue. Regulationsproviding for increases in the combined sound and television licence fees from 1 August 1971were made on 2 April 1970.b. ii.  Independent Television Authority4, Expenditure covers the capital requirementsof the Authority in providing transmitters andrelay stations to broadcast the programmes of independent television companies. The authority is financed by means of the rentals which itcharges to programme contractors. The capital programme provides for the varying incidence of the requirements for new UHF colour trans-missions.25.  Northern IrelandTABLE 25Northern ireland. The public expenditure estimates for NorthernIreland have been prepared by the NorthernIreland departments. They refer to those services for which the Northern Ireland Govern-ment is responsible and as such are not subjectto detailed control from Westminster. the overall level of expenditure on these services is however   customarily   subject   to   agreementc. Meteorological services. The estimates cover the cost of services provided for both military and civil purposes, thewhole of which is charged to the defence budget; an adjustment has been made in Table 2(other military defence) to enable this item to be shown here. Provision has been made in 1971-72for the purchase of a very large computer, costing 3-7 million.d. Civil defence6. The forecasts are based on the costs ofexisting policy. A review is about to be under-taken. The exceptionally low outturn for1969-70 resulted from extra receipts from sales of certain stocks.e. Royal Parks, historic buildings and ancient monuments, etc.7. This covers expenditure by the Secretary ofState for the Environment and the Secretaries ofState for Scotland and Wales on services which include the upkeep of Royal Parks, maintenanceof ancient monuments and grants to owners of historic buildings.f. Other miscellaneous services. This includes expenditure by the CivilService Department, the Cabinet Office (includingthe National Economic Development Council andthe Public Trustee, the salaries and administrative costs of the Ministry of Posts and telecommunications-cations; the remanet of the land acquisition and management function of the Land Commission;Civil List annuities and pensions; and Royal irish constabulary pensions. An item of  0-2 million in 1971-72 and  0-1 million in 1974-75 is included to take account of grants to the RoyalZoological Society as a contribution to the costof their building programme.  million at 1970 Survey pricesbetween the two Governments and-is determined with regard to the parity of services in NorthernIreland and Great Britain, taking into account the special needs of the Province, as well as the overall constraints on public expenditure in theUnited Kingdom.2. Because the figures in the table representpublic expenditure for which the Northern Ireland1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturn442-0        483-3        488-1        501-0        509-9        521-4
Government is responsible, they do not include expenditure on such items as defence and mostagricultural support, which is contained in the relevant United Kingdom programmes.3. The figures do not include any savings whichmay result from the discussions at present being held between the Northern Ireland and UnitedKingdom Governments.  million at 1970 Survey prices	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75Agriculture, fisheries and forestry*	13-1	13-8	13-8	13-0	12-6Assistance to employment and industry	76-2	69-1	70-6	71-4	72-8Electricity and gas           .      .      .	18-4	18-7	21-3	22-1	22-2Roads      .                   .      .	24-1	23-9	24-6	25-4	26-housing   .      .      .      .      ...	38-9	43-2	47-9	52-1	57-miscellaneous local services...	22-7	27-4	25-9	24-9	23-4Law and order .      .      .      .      .	.      .          21-8	15-5	15-2	15-7	15-9Education........	75-5	82.-0	84-1	86-5	, !   87-8Health and welfare   .	660	68-5	69-7	71-0	72-9Social security   .      .      . \,   -	.      .        108-9	106-9	108-9	1100	111-other programmes    .      .      .      .      .	17-7	19-1	19-0	17-8	18-0Total    .      .      .      .      .	.      .        483-3	488-1	501 0	509-9	521-4* This figure excludes most of the cost of agricultural support in Northern Ireland which appears in the relevant United Kingdomprogramme in Table 5.26.  Debt interestTABLE 26   million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75estimated     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturnDebt interest.......     2,186-0     2,103-0      1,980-0      1,950-0      1,890 0      1,810-01. The basis on which debt interest paymentshave been forecast is set out in paragraph 7 ofPart 2 (Methodology). In particular it shouldbe noted that the projections are on a conven-tional basis assuming the continuation of presentinterest rates. They are therefore subject to a significant margin of error, depending on theinteraction of future changes in public sectorborrowing, in interest rates, and in the price index of the gross domestic product (GDP) at factorcost.2. The debt interest payments now forecast for1971-72 are  40 million smaller than &quot;new programme Figures &quot; in Cmnd. 4515. The main reasons are:(a) The cash figure is some  15 million lower,mainly because of a better calculation ofthe effect on local authorities&apos; interest payments of the replacement of maturingdebt by new borrowing at different interest rates.(b) The cash payments of debt interest aredeflated by the price index of GDP atfactor cost. Prices are now expected,following the recent forecasting round, torise by more in 1971-72 than they were previously, so that the real value of debt interest is smaller.
CONFIDENTIALPart Two: MethodologyPART TWOMETHODOLOGY1. These notes explain the conventions andclassifications used in the 1970 Public expenditure survey.Definitions and coverage2. In order that the figures in the Survey can be consistent as far as possible with the statistics andforecasts of national income and expenditure,they follow the methods, sources and definitionswhich the Central Statistical Office use for record-ing public sector transactions in the national income accounts. The public sector comprises cen-tral government (including the National insurance funds), local authorities and public corporations(including the nationalised industries). Apartfrom transactions on operating account by public corporations and other trading bodies, all current and capital transactions by the public sector are recovered in the Survey. Transfers between thepublic sector and other sectors are included butinternal transfers, such as central government grants and loans to local authorities and public corporations, are generally eliminated. Indirecttaxes, including selective employment tax paidby public authorities, are included as part of thecost of the programmes to which they relate andare credited as receipts by the authority to whichthey accrue. Subsidies to public authorities&apos;trading services and to public corporations arealso included, since they are paid to theiroperating accounts.3. One departure from the national accountingdefinitions is that the figures of current expendi-ture in the Survey exclude imputed rents whichare used in the national income statistics to measure the value of the use made of publicly-owned fixed capital assets in the provision ofpublic services; this is because of difficulties ofestimation and deficiencies of coverage.Price basis4. The estimates of expenditure for individual programmes presented in the main Report aremade at constant prices, so as to enable com-comparisons to be made of changes in demands on resources arising directly or indirectly from public expenditure in successive years; and, when allow-ance is made for the relative price effect (seeparagraph 8 below), the growth of total public expenditure to be related to what is acceptablein the light of the likely growth of the economy as a whole.5. Expenditure on departmental programmes isshown at 1970 Survey prices in all the tables inthe main Report and the Appendix, apart fromTable 4 of the main Report. This price basiscorresponds to that of the 1970-71 SupplyEstimates for current expenditure on goods and services and some transfer payments, except thatthe April 1970 pay awards for the Armed Forcesagreed in February of this year have been included. The estimates for gross domestic fixed capital formation are mostly at March 1970 prices.In some cases, however, such as roads and educa-tion, they relate to the price basis currently in use for planning purposes. The programmeestimates have been converted from 1970 survey prices to estimated outturn prices for 1970-71 bymeans of an overall adjustment based on theprice movements assumed in the short term economic forecasts.6. Certain transfer payments and capital trans-actions are estimated in money terms, that is, atthe amount expected to be disbursed in each year,irrespective of price changes which may by then have occurred. In order to measure the demand on real resources implied by these expenditures,the cash estimates have been deflated to constant1970-71 outturn prices. For social security and overseas aid this adjustment has been applied tothe individual programmes concerned, usingja pricedeflator appropriate to the expenditure involved.For other programmes an overall adjustment hasbeen made related to the estimated movement inthe price level of the output of the economy asa whole. The use of this latter deflator auto-matically corrects for the relative price effect.7. For certain types of subsidies which are intended to reimburse deficits the estimates are entirely notional. Agricultural subsidies are themost important example. The forward figuresof debt interest involve the neutral assumptionthat interest rates continue at their present level.Allowance is made for some change in the total amount of debt, reflecting the balance ofestimated public sector receipts and expenditurein each year, and for the refunding of currentdebt. These projections of debt interest are madeat outturn prices and deflated to constant prices by the price deflator applicable to the gross domestic product.Relative price effect8. The relative price effect arises becausethe prices of goods and services purchased by public sector outlays (either directly in the caseof expenditure on goods and services or indirectlyin the case of transfers to other sectors of the
economy) tend to move differentially from theprices of goods and services in the economy generally. This means that for any future yearpublic expenditure as a percentage of gross domestic product measured at conventionalconstant prices will not reflect precisely public expenditure as a percentage of gross domestic product when measured at the actual prices ofthat future year. And thus the use of realresources by the public sector will not becorrectly stated. In practice for forward yearsthis adjustment for public expenditure as a wholeis a. positive one, although for some programmesit can be negative. This is because the RPEtends to be associated with activities with a highlabour content, and such activities form a largeproportion of public sector operations, particu-larly of current expenditure on goods and services.The RPE as applied to current expenditure on goods and services compensates for two factors:(a) A tendency for the prices of the output of services (including the provision of services by the public sector) to rise more steeplythan those of the economy generally,because of the more limited opportunities to benefit from increased productivity; and(b) The fact that the national income conven-tions, according to which public sectoroutput is measured by the cost of its variousinputs (men, materials, etc.), preclude anymeasurement of the extent to which abetter service is provided for, a givenutilisation of resources.9. For the future years of the forecast therelative price effect applicable to wages and salaries and the labour cost element of services(mainly general practitioners employed in theNational Health Service) has been estimated onthe basis of the forecast relative price movements of gross domestic product at factor cost and of earnings per head used in the medium-term economic assessment. For the remainder of current expenditure on goods and services,expenditure on fixed assets, and on certaintransfer payments which are treated in theSurveys on a similar basis to expenditure on goods and services, the relative price effect hasbeen estimated from an analysis of the pastrelationship between the price movements in thesecomponents of public expenditure at factor costand the movement in the GDP factor cost price index; for this purpose SET and other indirecttaxes have been excluded. Cash programmesincluding net lending have been deflated by theGDP factor cost price index (see paragraph above).10. The relative price effect for 1969-70 hasbeen estimated as the difference between the sumof the individual programmes as returned by departments at 1970 Survey prices and the totalof public expenditure as measured at 1969-70outturn prices revalued by the forecast movementin the GDP factor cost price index between1969-70 and 1970-71.11. The relative price effect together with the adjustment from 1970 Survey prices to 1970-71outturn prices (paragraph 5) and the adjustment of cash programmes to 1970-71 outturn prices(paragraph 6)0) has been allocated to individual programmes in Table 4 of the main report and to resource categories in Table 7, Part B.In all other tables in the main Report and inthe Appendix these adjustments have beengrouped together as an overall correction^) inthe line &quot; Relative price effect and otheradjustments &quot;.Classification by programme12. The programme classification adopted inthe summary tables in this Report follows that used in Table 1 in Cmnd. 4515, except thatroads and transport form two separateprogrammes and that agriculture price guarantees and housing subsidies, which in theWhite Paper were grouped with the contingency reserve, have been allocated to the agriculture,fisheries and forestry and housing programmesrespectively. The technology and industryprogramme has been renamed &quot;Trade, industryand employment&quot;; and investment grants arenot shown separately, although in some tablesthe year-to-year percentage movements in expenditure are shown excluding investment grants.Presentation of social security13. The presentation of social security in thisReport differs from that Used in Cmnd. 4515.In this Report the estimates of expenditure onthis programme represent the cash cost ofbenefit payments in line with the policies decided by Ministers, deflated to 1970-71 outturn prices by the assumed movement in the retail price index. In Cmnd. 4515 the estimates enteredagainst social security in Tables 1 and, 2correspond to the cash outlay calculated at existing rates of benefit. The estimated cost of future improvements and upratings in excess ofthose required to compensate for the rise inprices is included in the contingency reserve,while the cost of biennial upratings in line with prices and the adjustment to 1970-71 outturn prices is grouped with the relative price effect (see note vi to Table 6 of the main Report).(&apos;): This adjustment, when based on the GDP factorcost price index, is the equivalent of applying therelative price effect to these programmes.(2) Except the adjustment to 1970-71 outturn prices forthe overseas aid and social security programmes (seeparagraph 6).
Hospital building programme .  The programme provides for:  million at 1970 Survey prices	1970	1971	1972	1973	1974	-71	-72	-73	-74	-75England	.   107-4	126-1	136-7	137-7	137-wales	80	6-8	6-5	6-3	6-3Scotland	.    14-4	16-7	17-6	17-9	17-9These figures are those for the basic programmeof hospital building; they are lower than those shown in Table 20 as hospital capital expendi-ture because the latter include capital expenditureon the Special Hospitals and artificial limb andappliance centres and centrally purchased capital equipment. The Health Department haveexpressed concern that the figures incorporateonly a small increase from 1972-73 to 1973-74compared with the increases in previous years,and that the total for 1974-75 is the same asthat for 1973-74 although the figures includethe following provisions from the additional 110 million:	 	million	at 1970	Survey	prices	1970	1971	1972	1973	1974	-71	-72	-73	-74	-75England	:&apos;&apos;&quot;&quot;	4-5	60	5-0	5-wales	 	0-3	0-4	0-4	0-scotland	 	0-5	0-8	0-8	0-810. The objectives of the hospital building programme are to continue the replacement and modernisation of hospitals with particular regardto the needs of the mentally ill, the mentally handicapped and the elderly, the improvementof the accident and emergency services and theintroduction of capital items which producesavings on current expenditure. A move will bemade towards eliminating inequalities in standardof provision between regions and care will betaken that hospital building programmes are consistent and complementary with those of thelocal authorities.Hospital current expenditure11. The figures provide for a basic rate of growth of 3\ per cent a year with the additionof the following provisions from the  110million:  million at 1970 Survey prices1970    1971    1972    1973    1974	-71	-72	-73	-74	-75England		50	9-8	10-7	11-wales		0-3	0-6	0-6	0-7Scotland		0-6	1-0	1-0	10The objectives of current expenditure on thehospital services are to continue the normaldevelopment of the services improved treat-ment and diagnostic services, more staff and improved training and to make faster progressin vulnerable sectors such as the care of the mentally handicapped, mentally ill and elderly.Allocations to hospital authorities will be designed to eliminate, over a period, thedisparities between the resources available to different regions. There will be close attentionto a more rapid introduction of productivitypay schemes, more effective building and engineering maintenance and other measures designed to produce savings.Local authority capital expenditure12. The figures in Table 20 represent anestimate of the likely capital expenditure of localauthorities both from loans and from revenue.They include the following measures as part ofthe additional  110 million:  million at 1970 Survey prices1970 1971 1972 1973 1974-71     -72     -73     -74     -75England   (health and Welfare) .     	4	2	6	2	6-2	5	6Wales      (Health							and Welfare) .     -	0	3	0	4	0-4	0	3Scotland (Health)    -	0	1	0	1	0-1	0	1It is expected that more than half of the localauthority building programme will be devotedto homes and other facilities for the elderly.Other main areas of expenditure are the building of health centres and the provision of hostelsand training centres for the mentally handi-capped. An overall objective of the programme will be to increase the proportion of peoplecared for in the community rather than in hospital. (Additional provision rising from 0-3 million in 1971-72 to  0-4 million in thefollowing three years has been made for similarpurposes under local authority capital expendi-ture on social work in Scotland.)Local authority current expenditure13.  The programme provides for:  million at 1970 Survey prices1970 1971 1972 1973 1974-71 -72 -73 -74 -75England   (health and Welfare) . 200-0 216-6 231-5 251-5 266-wales     (health and Welfare .    12-8 13-7 14-7 16-0    17-1Scotland (Health)     8-4 8-8 9-4 10-0    10-6
The figures for 1970-71 are an estimate of whatlocal authorities may spend on health and welfare services. Those for England and Walesfor 1971-72 and 1972-73 are based on the 1970Rate Support Grant settlement. In Englandand Wales the rates of growth assumed for the health services in these two years are of theorder of 4 per cent, and on the welfare services11 per cent (including about 1\ per cent for thenew administrative arrangements to be set up under the Local Authority Social Services Act1970). In Scotland the Rate Support grant negotiations have not been concluded. But thefinal outcome, taking local health and social work together, is unlikely to show any significant change on the figures incorporated in this Report.14. The following additions have been made from the  110 million:	 	million	at 1970	Survey	prices	1970	1971	1972	1973	1974	.  -71	-72	-73	-74	-75England	-	2-8	2-8	2-8	2-8Wales	-	0-1	0-1	0-1	0-1Scotland	-	01	0-2	0-2	0-in addition  0-2 million in each year has been added to the Law and Order programme forincreased family planning provision under theEngland and Wales Urban Aid programme( 0-4 million a year has been added for localauthority expenditure on social work in Scotland).This expenditure is intended to continue thedevelopment of the community services, both intheir own right for the effective care of the sick,the handicapped and the elderly, and as a meansof shifting the emphasis from hospital to community care, and the provision particularly of social workers, home helps, meals on wheels,day centres and old people&apos;s homes.21.  Social securityTABLE 21  million at 1970 Survey prices	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					a.   National insurance and industrial injuries:						(i) Retirement pensions   .      .      .      .	1,739-0	1,781-0	1,821 0	1,919 0	2,005 0	2,064-0(ii) Sickness benefit .	413-0	4180	414-0	437-0	444-0	451-0(iii) Unemployment benefit	136-0	1600	156-0	134-0	137-0	139-0(iv) Other national insurance benefits  .	227-0	231-0	260-0	290-0	291-0	293-0Total national insurance benefits	2,515-0	2,590-0	2,651-0	2,780 0	2,877-0	2,947-0(v) Industrial injuries      ....	112-0	1130	110-0	115-0	1180	120-0Total national insurance and industrial						injuries      .....	2,627-0	2,703 0	2,761-0	2,895 0	2,995 0	3,067-0b.   War pensions     ......	133-8	128-9	123-5	121-9	118-5	113-5c.   Supplementary benefits       ....	503-0	531-2	560-8	530-1	552-8	560-9d.   Old persons&apos; pensions.....	 	7-0	140	130	100	8-0e.   Family income supplement .		&apos;u      -Si	4-0	7-0	7-0	7-0f.   Attendance allowance .      .      .      .   . .	it&apos;.;-	-	&apos;.   . - &apos;.	10 0	100	10-0g.   Family allowances      .      ...	362-0	345-0	330-0	321 0	320-0	310-0h.   Administration......	144-7	149-8	154-4	161-8	173-3	171-1Grand total.....	3,770-5	3,864-9	3,947-7	4,059-8	4,186-6	4,247-5Notes:						1.  Unemployment assumptions ....	559,000	625,000	625,000	550,000	550,000	550,000	(actual)					2.   Price assumptions (percentage movement over						previous year).......	5-2	6-9	6-3	4-6	4-3	4-83.  Real earnings assumptions (percentage movement						over previous year)   .      .      .      .      .     .	3-3	6-2	6-3	3-4	3-7	3-24.   Minor adjustments:As usual the figures for each year include an amount of  2- 5 million which is available for the minor adjustments to the schemes which are needed between upratings.5. The estimate for 1970-71 shows the expected cash outturn, but for later years the estimates reflect the decline in real valueof benefits between upratings.
Policy assumptions underlying the Table1. The figures in Table 21 embody the follow-ing policy changes made by the present administration.upratings2. As part of the review of public expenditureit was decided that instead of social security benefits being uprated in November 1971 and october 1973 in line with the increase of earnings,the 1971 uprating would be in line with pricemovements only, and the 1973 uprating wouldbe in line with the movement of prices plus60 per cent of the difference between that and themovement in earnings. It was also decided thatan amount of  45 million a year ( 20 million in1971-72) should be included for selectiveimprovements to be associated with the upratingsof the main benefit rates. The saving from these decisions is as follows:.  million at 1970 Survey prices1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75131	300	361	4103. These savings were allowed for in the totalfigures for public expenditure in Cmnd. 4515.In accordance with precedent they were notannounced in the White Paper or subsequently.4. It was also decided (but again not announced)that maternity grant and death grant would notbe uprated at all during the current survey period. This produces the following savings,allowed for in Cmnd. 4515.i  million at 1970 Survey prices1971-72    1972-73    1973-74    1974-753 6 7 9waiting days5. As part of the review it was decided, and announced in Cmnd. 4515, that legislation wouldbe introduced to end the arrangement by whichthe three waiting days for sickness benefit,unemployment benefit and injury benefit are paidretrospectively if the claimant is unemployed orsick for a period of 12 days or more. This savesabout  20 million a year, after taking account ofoffsetting expenditure on supplementary benefit.The saving is shown as taking effect from April1971, but the actual date will depend on thelegislative programme.old persons&apos; pensions6. The figures in the table reflect the cost of theprovision made in the National Insurance (Oldpersons&apos; and widows&apos; pensions and attendance allowance) Act 1970 for persons who were too oldto enter the national insurance scheme in 1948and are therefore now over 87 (82 for women).Discussion is taking place about the possibilityof extending this provision to all persons over80 now or in the future, at a cost of some 4 million.attendance allowance7. Attendance allowance, for which a provisional estimate was included in previous programmes, isnow a statutory benefit due to start in April 1972.Because of the uncertain nature of the estimates for this benefit it has been shown as an illustrativefigure of  10 million throughout 1972-73,1973-74 and 1974-75 as before.scaled down widows&apos; pensions8. The figures in Table 21 include the following figures for scaled down pensions for womenwidowed between the ages of 40 and 50, underthe National Insurance (Old persons, etc.) Act,1970:  million at 1970 Survey prices1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-7513	14	15	15Provision for this was included in the previousprogramme on an illustrative basis, but from april 1972 only. Under the above Act they will now be paid from April 1971.family income supplement9. The estimates in Cmnd. 4515 included anamount of  8-5 million for the family income supplement proposals ( 4 million in 1971-72). InTable 21 the full year cost has been split in line with the figures now given in the Explanatory andFinancial Memorandum to the Bill ( 7 million for the supplement itself,  1 million for additionalsupplementary benefit and  0-6 million for administration). In view of the difficulties of estimating the cost of this benefit the same figures have been given for 1972-73, 1973-74 and1974-75.minor changes10. The figures in Table 21 also reflect thefollowing minor policy changes:(i) The introduction of the restrictions onunemployment benefit for occupational pensioners, which will save about 3 million a year, has been deferred from september 1970 to September 1971.(ii) The supplementary benefit estimates make provision for increased expenditure asfollows in consequence of the additionalcharges for dental and ophthalmictreatment.  million at 1970 Survey prices1971-72    1972-73    1973-74    1974-753-5 3-6 3-8 3-9
(iii) Ministers have decided, since the publica-tion of Cmnd. 4515, to improve thesystem of fuel additions in the supple-mentary benefits scheme with effect from january 1971 at a cost of  3-5 million ina full year. This will be found from the uprating allocations, except for thefollowing amounts by which the social security programme has been increased during the transitional period:  million at 1970 Survey prices1970-71	1971-72	1972-730-2	2-3	1-5reconstruction  of   the   national   insurancescheme11. The target date for the introduction of areconstructed national insurance scheme is April1974 but no collective Ministerial decisions on itscontent have yet been taken. The basic benefits of the scheme would be broadly the same as atpresent and nothing extra has been included in1974-75 under this heading.rate of growth of the programme12. The annual rate of growth of the programme in real terms year on year is as follows:per cent1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-752-5	2-1	2-8	3-1	1-5The average annual rate of growth of the pro-gramme in real terms over the whole period is2-4 per cent.omissions from the costing13. No account has been taken in the costingsof a number of minor measures which haverecently been under consideration by ministers for limiting the entitlement to benefit (including that of strikers and their families to supple-mentary benefit). These would produce savings of about  5 million a year.14. No provision has been made in the costingsfor interim upratings of supplementary benefits in1972 and 1974. Nor is there any provision forany uprating of family allowances which aretherefore assumed to decline in real valuethroughout the period. On these two pointsMinisters decided that the proposal for interimupratings of supplementary benefit in 1972 and1974 should be considered later as claims on the contingency reserve, and that it would later bepossible to consider claims on the contingency reserve for up to  15 million a year to provide additional help for poor families.22.  Financial administrationTABLE 22   million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70 1970-71     1971-72     1972-73 1973-74     1974-75provisional estimate     estimate     estimate estimate     estimate outturn	Tax and rate collection	178-7	184-1	186-1	189-1	191-7	192-2	SET paid by local authorities	0-8	,  0-8	0-8	0-8	0-8	0-9b.	Royal Mint (including decimalisation, etc.)	15-8	8-4	2-0	3-4	1-5	1-6c.	Post-war credits .      ...	18-5	18-5	17-5	16-5	15:5	16-0d.	Otherfinancialadministration,etc. .	24-9	23-5	24-3	24-6	24-9	25-5	Total    i       :\.:w -  .- -iififfi	238-7	235-3	230-7	234-4	234-4	236-2a.  Tax and rate collection. The estimates assume a continuation of exist-ing policies and make no provision for additionalfiscal measures. More than half of the total isfor the Inland Revenue, with smaller sums forCustoms and Excise, the Department of the environment, DHSS and local authorities. Thereare small increases in most programmes, mainly on account of the estimated growth of existingwork, and the progress of automation, whichwill eventually yield savings.
2. In particular additional staff are required bythe Inland Revenue to deal with an increasingvolume of work. If these increases were not permitted it would become impossible for the inland Revenue to maintain its standards ofservice and to ensure prompt collection of taxes:delays in handling correspondence could beexpected to increase and accumulate.1b. Royal Mint3. The estimates for the Royal Mint cover thecost of normal requirements for increased coincirculation. That for 1970-71 also includes provision for the completion of the major part of the new coinage requirement for deci-malisation and that for 1972-73 allows forthe plant necessary to complete the move ofthe Royal Mint from Tower Hill to Llantrisant.Pending a decision whether there should be blankmaking facilities at Llantrisant, this estimate inrespect of plant includes  1-7 million for blank-ing capacity of 800 million blanks a year.Estimated building costs for the completion ofthe new Mint on this basis are included in the accommodation (Home) figures in Table 23.c.  Post-war credits4. The figures reflect the best estimate by the inland Revenue of the numbers of those who willbecome entitled on grounds of age and hardship to receive repayments. The figures could bereduced only by amending, by regulation, theconditions of entitlement.23.  Common services table 23   million at 1970 Survey prices		1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75		provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate		outturn					a.	Accommodation (Home)							(i) Capital expenditure   .      .	24-2	33-2	40-3	49-0	54-1	56-2	(ii) Current expenditure							(a) Maintenance and running costs	57-5	63-6	65-6	68-2	70-4;	73-3	(6) Departmental administration	22-3	24-5	24-7	22-1	24-9	27-7	(c) Rates on Government property	42-4	43-5	44-5	45-5	46-5	47-5	1 Total.....	146-4	164-8	175-1	184-8	195-9	204-7b.	II Stationery Office (Home) (excluding c. (ii))							(i) Capital......	9-9	14-7	27-4	25-5	31-6	24-9	(ii) Supply of stationery, printing, etc. .	28-2	32-2	33-6	35-8	37-6	39-4	(iii) Repayments in respect of computer								-3-6	-4-3	-15-0	-13-3	-17-2	-8-3	Total                  .     -	34-5	42-6	460	480	520	560c.	Central Office of Information home publicity							services							(i) COI (Home).....	8 1	9-8	9-5	10-1	100	9-7	(ii) Stationery Office expenditure associated							with COI home services    .	0-5	1-0	0-7	0-9	1-0	0-8	,   Total           .    ..     .	8-6	10-8	10-2	11 0	11.-0	10-5d.	Superannuation of  Civil   Servants   in civil							Departments     .      ...	77-7	81-5	84-2	90-6	94-5	98-7	Grand total	267-2	299-7	315-5	334-4	353-4	369-9	Less:						e.	Allied services (defence) (see Table 2)	-94-5	-96-0	-94-2	-90-2	-90-2	-90-2	Grand total net of e.             .	172-7	203-7	221-3	244-2	263-2	279-7
a.   Accommodation (Home)1. This covers expenditure by the Departmentof the Environment on civil accommodation forGovernment Departments at home and on building research and development work. the accommodation is mainly offices but also includesGovernment training centres, scientific and re-search buildings, museums and galleries and miscellaneous buildings such as those for theRoyal Mint and the Stationery Office. the forecast is substantially the same as that in theprevious programme but will be higher in later years mainly due to the further expansion of theprogramme for building Government trainingcentres announced in Parliament on 4 November,1970 which will increase expenditure under this heading in 1972-73 to 1974-75 in total by some-thing like  3 million.2. About three-quarters of the total expenditurerelates to current expenditure needed to retainand operate the existing accommodation and covering rent, rates, maintenance, running costs and staff costs. The capital expenditure, togetherwith an element of staff costs relates to theprovision and furnishing of new buildings. Thetwo largest programmes are for computer building(principally the Inland Revenue regional computercentres) and for other offices needed for a variety of reasons including replacement of leasedaccommodation or of sub-standard premises andfor dispersal of staff from London. There are alsoprogrammes for increasing the number of placesavailable at training centres and for expandingor improving scientific and research buildings andthe museums and galleries.b. Stationery Office (Home)3. The figures show expenditure by the stationery Office to meet the requirements ofGovernment Departments, together with the stationery Office&apos;s administrative and other costs.The estimate of capital expenditure is based onknown projects, and consists largely of computersand other office machinery for GovernmentDepartments. A deduction is shown for thosecapital items (mainly computers) which arepurchased by the Stationery Office on repaymentby other Departments.4. The rising figures for net capital expenditurereflect the expected incidence of requirements forcomputers: processing of work on computersproduces savings in staff and other costs on other programmes.c. Central Office of Information home publicityservices5. The estimates for COI and related HMSOexpenditure reflect forecasts by GovernmentDepartments of future demands on this CommonService Department, reduced in the light of an appraisal of the reasonable and realistic level oftotal home publicity expenditure likely to be needed. Among other things the figures allow for the completion of the publicity for decima-lisation and for increasing programmes for theMetrication Board.24.  Miscellaneous services table 24   million at 1970 Survey prices		1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75		provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate		outturn					a.	Records, registrations and surveys   .	23-5	24-3	31-8	26-8	26-6	27-4b.	Broadcasting (capital expenditure)							i. BBC.....	;.     .        11-3	15-4	11-6	11-6	9-2	10-8	ii. ITA            Jl     .	3-0	2-9	4-3	3-9	4-3	5-5c.	Meteorological services .	.   7-4:	7-7	11-6	8-4	8-1	7-9d.	Civil Defence.....	1-4	7-2	8-5	9-1	9-7	9-1e.	Royal Parks, historic buildings and	ancient							:y    3-7	4-1	4-6	4-9	5-1	5-3f.	Other miscellaneous services   .	.     .        17-6	20-9	14-3	17-5	19-9	20-1	Total    ....	67-9	82-5	86-7	82-2	82-9	86 1* Provision for grants to owners of historic buildings and for contributions to the Redundant Churches Fund is included in money terms and not at constant prices.
19.  EducationTABLE 19   million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional    estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn(1) EDUCATIONENGLAND AND WALES (EXCLUDING UNIVERSITIES)Capital expenditure:a. Schools	(i) England     ....	178-7	189-8	231-2	224-5	196-4	158-3	(ii) Wales .....	130	13-7	16-7	16-3	14-3	11-5b.	Further education	45-2	46-9	500	47-0	420	44-8c.	Teacher training.      .      .      .	7-0	61	6-3	4-3	3-3	2-9d.	Youth service    ....	6-5	6-8	7-3	7-3	7-6	7-6e.	Other educational expenditure	-0-1	 	  .	. .		 i.O	Total England and Wales .	250-3	263-3	311-5	299-4	263-6	225 current expenditure:a. SchoolsPrimary	(i) England     .      .	383-2	391-7	421-3	439-9	446-5	448-9	(ii) Wales .     .     .     .	27-1	27-8	29-9	31-2	31-6	31-8	Secondary							(i) England	431-1	445-6	480-0	506-1	553-6	592-0	(ii) Wales.....	27-9	28-8	310	32-7	35-8	38-3	Other							(i) England     ....	114-2	118-1	1221	125-9	131-5	135-6	(ii) Wales .....	6-6	6-8	7-1	7-3	7-6 .	7-9	Total schools England and Wales.	990-1	1,018-8	1,091-4	1,143-1	1,206-6	1,254-5b.	Further education (including							awards)	226-1	235-6	244-6	254-7	249-4	253-3c.	Teacher training (including awards)	940	97-8	100-3	102-5	104-9	107-1d.	Youth service    ....	17-6	18-4	18-9	19-8	20-6	21-4e.	School meals							(i) England     .     ;.	77-1	72-0	57-9	57-4	50-3	51 0	(ii) Wales .      .      .	51	4-8	3-9	3-8	3-3	3-3f.	School milk							(i) England                  .	11-5	121	7-4	5-1	50	4-8	(ii) Wales .      .      .	0-7	0-7	0-4	0-3	0-3	0-3g-	Other educational expenditure	4-8	5-1	5-6	60	6-0	61h.	Administration							(i) England     ....	66-3	68-5	72-6	75-5	78-0	80-1	(ii) Wales.....	3-3	3-5	3-5	3-6	3-8	3-9	Total England and Wales .	1,496-6	1,537-3	1,606-5	1,671-8	1,728-2	1,785-scotland (EXCLUDING UNIVERSITIES)Capital expenditure:a.	Schools    ....	31-9	25-5	260	25-2	24-3	23-4b.	Further education	91	9-8	9-6	9-5	8-8   :	8-1c.	Teacher training .	1-4	2-2	2-2	2-2	1-7	1-0d.	Youth service	1-2	1-4	1-9	2-1	2-3	2-5	Total Scotland .	43-6	38-9	39-7	39 0	37-1	350
TABLE 19 (continued)   million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn(1) EDUCATION (continued)Current expenditure:a. SchoolsPrimary.....	51-4	52-8	54-7	56-3	57-5	59-2Secondary      ....	59-1	61-5	64-6	68-0	72-2	74-other.....	13-1	13-1	13-8	14-1	14-6	15-2Total schools Scotland	123-6	127-4	133-1	138-4	144-3	149-3b. Further education (including						awards)	23-6	25-6	28-1	30-5	32-5	34-7c. Teacher training (including awards)	9-7	10-6	11-7	12-5	13-6	14-6d. Youth service    .      .	2-3	2-4	2-6	2-8	3-0	3-2e. School meals	9-4	8-7	80	7-9	7-9	7-6f. School milk      .      .      .      .	1-8	1-7	1-0	0-6	0-6	0-6g. Other educational expenditure	0-3	0-4	0-4	0-5	0-5	0-5h. Administration ....	6-5	6-8	7-0	7-3	7-5	7-9Total Scotland ....	177-2	183-6	191-9	200-5;	209-9.	218-4UNIVERSITIES (GREAT BRITAIN)						Capital expenditure (Great Britain) .	75-4	77-5	74-9	77-8	82-4	92-current expenditure (excluding awards)						-DES.......	190-4	199-9	213-4	228-2	247-8	273-9-SED......      .	0-2	0-2	0-2	0-3	0-3	0-3Student awards						-DES  .      .      .      .      .      .	52-9	55-2	58-1	61-3	65-1	70-3 SED  .      .      .      .      . *   .	7-9	8-3	.8-7	91	9-7	10-administration.....	0-3	0-3	0-4	0-4	0-4	0-4Total universities	327-1	341-4&apos;	355-7	377-1	405-7	447-4TOTAL EDUCATION						DES      .     V     .              .	1,982-2	2,047:4	2,172-3	2,243-7	2,290-8	2,350-6Welsh Office .      .      .	83-7.	86-1	92-5	95-2	96-7	97-0Statistical adjustment						England and Wales*    .		-&apos;	-15-5	-16-1	^ -16-8	-17-4SED     .      .      .      .	228-2	230-2	239-4	247-7 ,	255-7	262-8DAFS   .      .      .      .      .	0-7	0-8	1-1	1-2	1-3	1-3Total Great Britain .	2,294-8	2,364-5	2,489-8	2,571-7	.2,627-7	2,694-3SET paid by local authorities	89-9	91-7	93-5	95-4	97-3	99-2(2) LOCAL LIBRARIES AND MUSEUMS						England and Wales						Capital .      .      .      . i.   .	6-4	6-2	7-2	7-3	7-3	7-current......	49-7	52-1	53-6	55-7	58-2	60-8Total     .      .      .      .	56-1	58-3	60-8	63 0	65-5	68-scotland						Capital......	0-5	10	1-2	1-4	1-5	1-7Current......	4-5	4-7	4-9	5-2	. 5:5	5-9Total     .	5-0	5-7	6-1	6-6	7-0	7-6SET paid by local authorities	2-8	2-8	2-9	3-0	3-0	3-1Grand total                    .      ...	2,448-6	2,523-0	2,653-1	2,739-7	2,800-5	2,872-4* The figures included for local authorities&apos; current	expenditure	in England	and Wales	have been amended to		reflect thegrowth rates agreed in the November 1970 Rate Support Grant settlement, but not the absolute levels of expenditure. this further adjustment is intended to restore comparability with the remainder of the Survey.
general. In the four years to 1974-75 the estimate oftotal expenditure on education in Great Britainincreases by  349 million or 3^ per cent a year.The increase springs from three main sources:the raising of the school-leaving age in 1972-73,the expected growth in the number of school-leavers who qualify for higher education and theprovision for a continuing improvement in the ratio of teachers to pupils in primary schools.2. The basis of the estimates is the continuation of existing policies; the figures take account ofthe changes announced in Cmnd. 4515: the increases in the charge for school meals, thediscontinuing (with certain exceptions) of freemilk for pupils beyond age 7, the raising of feesfor further education (in England and Wales only)and the additions to the building programmes for primary schools in 1972-73. No attempt hasbeen made to anticipate Ministerial decisions onthe future provision for higher education.ENGLAND AND WALES (and universities inGreat Britain)3. Responsibility for primary and secondary education in Wales including special and nurseryschools and ancillary services was transferred from the Department of Education and Scienceto the Welsh Office on 5 November, 1970 andthis is reflected in the separate figures shown inTable 19. But for convenience England andWales are treated together in this section. the forecasts have been adjusted to reflect, as far as local authority expenditure is concerned, thetrends of the rate support grant settlement for1971-72 and 1972-73.4. The growth in expenditure is determinedlargely by the growth in numbers of pupils,students and teachers. The total of primarypupils is expected to increase by only 4 per cent between 1969-70 (the latest year for which actualnumbers are available) and 1974-75, from,936,000 to 5,125,000 with a falling off in numbers by the latter year. By contrast, mainlyas a result of raising the school-leaving age, thetotal of secondary pupils is expected to increase by 28 per cent from 3,040,000 to 3,888,000. the combined increase in primary and secondarynumbers is forecast as 13 per cent comparedwith teacher numbers which rise by 24 per cent from 348,000 to 433,000. If, as has been assumed, current opportunities of entry to higher education continue, university student numbers are forecast to go up by 31 per cent, from219,500 to 288,000. Further education numbers(full-time equivalents) will also, on the samepolicy assumption, rise by nearly 10 per cent(from 649,000 to 713,000) by 1972-73 but they then level off for 2 years when the 15 year-oldsstay on at school, after the leaving age is raised,instead of moving to further education.5. The forecasts of capital expenditure providefor building starts as follows:  million at 1970 Survey prices	1970	1971	1972	1973	1974	-71	-72	-73	-74	-75Schools  .	182-4	1930	193-7	122-2	106-7Further					education	30-2	200	20-9	31 0	35-5Teacher training	5-7	3-1	2-5	2-5	2-5Universities	28-0	24-0	25-0	37-0	47-0Youth service .	5-9	5-9	5-9	6-2	6-2Total    .	252-2	246-0	248-0	198-9	197-9Local libraries .	5-6	7-4	5-7	6-4	6-76. The building programmes for primary and secondary schools will continue to provide forthe expected growth of the school population andfor movement into areas of new housing. Thespecial programme for raising the school-leaving age ends in 1972-73, as is indicated by the lowerfigures for the two following years. Theprovision for the replacement of old schoolsreflects firm decisions on starts up to and including those in 1972-73, when the figure willbe  38-5 million. For the last two years ofthe Survey the figures for these replacementsallow for starts of  11 million only. In theDepartment^ view the figure should be higher in order to maintain a programme of the sizeneeded for the replacement, over a five-year period beginning in 1972-73, of pre-1903 primary schools. But the Department accept that no decision on a revised level can be reacheduntil they have completed their study, aimed atdetermining the extent, if any, to which provisioncan be diverted from other programmes, as in1972-73. The Treasury for their part accept that the programmes for 1973-74 and 1974-75will need further consideration nearer the time,taking into account the prospects for public expenditure as a whole, the need for further progress in replacing old primary schools and theextent to which resources can be diverted fromother educational building programmes.7. The building programmes for further educa-tion, teaching training and the universities, as wellas providing teaching accommodation for thestudent numbers projected in 1974-75, incorporatesmall margins for the replacement of obsoletebuildings, residential and social accommodation and, in the case of universities, for medical education and the transfer of former colleges of advanced technology to new sites: The Depart-ment&apos;s view is that the forecasts for universitybuilding starts for 1973-74 and 1974-75 wouldnot ensure the provision even of the teaching and non-residential accommodation needed for thestudent numbers expected under present policies(see paragraph 4 above). The youth service andlocal libraries programmes now contain an element of flexibility: from 1 April, 1971, they
are within the area of discretion of localauthorities subject to overall expenditure limits.8. The rise in current expenditure in schools is designed in the first place to improve staffingstandards and eliminate over-large classes by theemployment of an increasing number of teachers,thus bringing the number of pupils per teacherdown from about 23 in 1969-70 to about 21 in1974-75. Following the rate support grantsettlement there are improvement factors in non-teaching costs, in current expenditure forecasts for both schools and further education, of 3i percent in 1971-72 and 3 per cent in 1972-73. Thegrowth for 1973-74 and 1974-75 implies animprovement rate of 2\ per cent per annum.SCOTLAND (excluding universities)9.  The   programme   for   capital   expenditureassumes the building starts shown below:	  million		at 1970	Survey	prices	1970	1971	1972	1973	1974	-71	-72	-73	-74	-75Schools .	27-2	22-7	25-0	- 23-3	24-further education .	9-4	9-0	7-3	7-8	6-7Teacher training	3-7	1-4	2-0	10	1-0Youth services, etc..	1-2	1-7	1-9	2-1	2-3Total	41-5	35-8	36-2	34-2	34-0(Unlike the figures for England and Wales, the above figures represent gross starts, i.e., they include costs of fees, furniture and equipment.)10. The programme for schools takes account ofthe increased provision allocated for 1972-73 in cmnd. 4515 for the improvement of primary schools. This is the beginning of a continuingprogramme for improvements in this sector; in later years some of the total provision may be diverted to the schools&apos; sector for this purpose and programmes for other individual sectors maybe correspondingly reduced. The starts other-wise reflect the need to provide for population growth and movement, the effect of the raising of the school-leaving age in 1972-73 and the continuing demand for courses at all levels.11. The reason for the growth in current expenditure is essentially to provide for theincrease in pupil and student numbers over theperiod to 1974-75 and steadily to raise thegeneral standard of education provision particu-larly, though not exclusively, by way of improving staffing standards. To this end,provision is made for increasing the number of students in colleges of education and of teachers in schools and further education colleges. despite this, staffing standards in secondary schools arelikely to worsen slightly when the leaving age is raised in 1972-73; in primary schools, staffingand other standards are expected to improveappreciably as a result of the high priority being given to this sector.20.  Health and welfareTABLE 20  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71      1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional    estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturnCapital expenditure england	105-4	115-7	1340	146-8	150-0	149-7Family practitioner services .		0-5	01	/lii-J^V.:.&apos;:	0-6	0-8Community health and welfare services:						Local health authority services   .	17-4	18-4	21-7	23-1	24-5	26-6Local welfare services      .      .      .	18-4	17-1	.21-7	25-2	25-6	25-other central services and grants   .	3-1	31	2-8	2-6	2-4	1-9Total England    .      .	144-3	154-8	180-3	197-7	203-1	204-2WALESHospitals   .Family practitioner services .Community health and welfare services:Local health authority services   .Local welfare services other central services and grants   .Total Wales       .      .      .      .       10-4 10-6 9-7 9-8 9-7 9-78-57-06-86-56-51-21-11-51-21-51-51-61-6i-/1-5
CONFIDENTIAL		Part Cine : Detailed Analy			sis of Programmes	TABLE 20 (continued)				  million at 1970 Survey prices			1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					Capital expenditure (continued)						SCOTLAND						Hospitals......	15-6	15-6	18-3	19-2	;   190	19-2Family practitioner services .      .      .      .	0-1	01	01	0-1	0-1	0-local health authority services	0-4	0-4	0-5	0-7	0-9	1-other central services and grants   .	0-8	0-9	1-4	1-5	1-4	1-5Total Scotland    .      .	16-9	170	20-3	21-5	21-4	21-9Total Great Britain						(capital expenditure)	171-6	182-4	210-3	229-0	234-2	235-8Current expenditure						ENGLAND						Hospitals.......	858-8	895-8	930-9	966-8	1,001-0	1,035-9Family practitioner services ....	359-1	371-6	359-6	354-1	364-0	374-0Community health and welfare services:						Local health authority services  .	143-4	142-5	148-4	154-5	175-3	185-2Local welfare services      ....	56-9	57-5	68-2	77-0	76-2	81-3Welfare foods......	34-8	351	12-6	8-6	8-7	8-other central services and grants   .	14-6	16-8	18-1	19-3	20-8	22-2Departmental administration ....	10-3	10-7	11-4	120	12-5	13-1Total England    .      .	1,477-9	1,530-0	1,549-2	1,592-3	1,658-5	1,720-6WALES						Hospitals   .      .	51-8	53-9	57-4	59-2	60-2	61-8Family practitioner services .      .	23-8-	24-2	23-6	23-4	24-1	24-8Community health and welfare services:						Local health authority services  .	9-0	9-1	9-3	9-7	111	11-8Local welfare services      ....	3-6	3-7	4-4	5-0	4-9	5-3Welfare foods     ......	2-0	1-9	0-8	0-5	0-5	0-other central services and grants   .	0-7	0-7	0-8	0-8	0-8	0-9Departmental administration ....	0-4	0-4	0-4	0-5	0-5	0-51   Total Wales	91-3	93-9	96-7	99-1	102-1	105-scotland						Hospitals   .      .      .	121-8	126-2	131-4	136-3	141-2	146-5Family practitioner services .	42-7	42-7	41-5	40-5	41-3	42-2Local health authority services	8-1	8-4	8-8	9-4	100	10-6Welfare foods     ......	4-3	4-4	1-9	1-4	1-4	1-other central services and grants   .	3-6	3-8	4 0	4-3	4-4	4-departmental administration ....	1-5	1-7	1-7	1-8	1-8	1-9Total Scotland    .	182-0	187-2	189-3	193-7	200-1	207-0SET paid by local authorities .	15-7	16-0	16-3	16-6	16-9	17-2Total Great Britain						(current expenditure)	1,766-9	1,827-1	1,851-5	1,901-7	1,977-6	2,050-grand Total	1,938-5	2,009-5	2,061-8	2,130-7	2,211-8	2,286-2A. Coverage for expenditure on Social Work in Scotland.1. The figures for Health and Welfare do not With the setting up of local authority social worktake account of the machinery of government departments in Scotland, under the Social Workchanges announced in Cmnd. 4506. Two changes (Scotland) Act 1968, it was necessary to includewill be required in the 1971 Survey. The first is a new heading for &quot; Social Work in Scotland &quot;,
and some expenditure on health, and all expenditure on welfare by local authorities inScotland were placed under this heading, and,as an interim measure for 1970, transferred fromthe Health and Welfare programme to the Lawand Order programme. In the 1971 Survey allthe expenditure on Social Work in Scotland willbe transferred to the Health and Welfareprogramme.2. In England and Wales the new social service departments of local authorities, to be set up under the Local Authorities Social Services Act1970 will bring together child care, some health and all the welfare expenditure of these authorities. In its machinery of governmentchanges the Government decided that responsi-bility for child care in England and Wales should similarly be brought together, with the otherresponsibilities of the two Health departments.All the expenditures by local authorities will therefore be incorporated in the Health and welfare programme as from the 1971 Survey.3. The effect of these two changes will be totransfer the following sums from Law and Orderto Health and Welfare:  million at 1970 Survey prices	1971	1972	1973	1974	-72	-73	-74	-75Child care (England and				Wales)	68-7	72-4	76-7	79-social work (Scotland)   .	23-1	24-7	25-9	27-3B.  Basis of Table 204. For 1970-71 the figures in Table 20 representthe expenditure now expected in the current year.For 1971-72 and subsequent years the costingstake account of the reductions and increasesannounced by the Government in Cmnd. 4515and the conclusion of the Rate Support grant negotiations for England and Wales. the reductions in 1971-72 and 1974-75, from theprevious programmes, are as follows:  million at 1970 Survey prices1971-72    1974-75Abolition of cheap welfare milk . 26-5 31-7Prescription charges and charges forappliances:a. Executive Councils    . . 15-2 30-2b. Hospitals ... . 0-8 1-1Dental charges . . . . 8-9 13-4Ophthalmic charges     .      . . 5-3 6-7Total 56-7        83-15. The above figures represent the latest assess-meht of the net savings for the Health and welfare   programme   from   Ministers&apos;   policy decisions. They do not correspond in all respectswith Cmnd. 4515, mainly because the Cmnd.4515 figures assumed an earlier starting date forthe reductions.6. Cmnd. 4515 also announced decisions to add to expenditure on Health and Welfare and social work (Scotland) as forecast in the previous programmes by  110 million in total (GreatBritain) over the 4 years 1971-72 to 1974-75:this consisted of  20 million in 1971-72 and 30 million in each of the following 3 years. (Thefigures in this Report assume that  0-2 million in each of the years from 1971-72 onwards will infact be added to expenditure on family planningunder the Urban Aid programme Law andOrder.)C.  Implications for the main elements of the health and welfare programmefamily      practitioner      services      currentexpenditure7. The figures in Table 20 from 1971-72onwards show substantial reductions from the1970-71 level because of the effect of theincreased charges (see paragraph 4). Thefigures assume that this will operate from 1 April,1971, including the increase in the flat rateprescription charge to 4s., that charges related toa proportion of cost will supersede the flat ratecharge on 1 November, 1971, and that the age limit for exemption from dental charges will bereduced from 21 to 18 on the same date. Theprovision reflects small increases in the numberof doctors and dentists and the tendency for more effective, and usually dearer, drugs to be developed. The underlying rate of growth onthe general medical, dental and ophthalmic ser-vices is about 2 per cent a year. The forecastgrowth on the pharmaceutical services was expected to be about 4 per cent a year beforethe Governmenfs decision to increase prescription charges, which will reduce expenditure by about15 per cent by 1972-73. The present figuresassume a similar underlying growth of 4 percent, from this lower base. But if the deterrent effect of the proportionate prescription chargeshas been under-estimated the rate of growthwould be lower.welfare foods8. The figures in Table 20 from 1971-72onwards show annual reductions of the order of 32 million from the 1970-71 level because ofthe effect of the abolition of cheap welfare milk,assumed to take effect from 4 April, 1971. Theremaining expenditure represents the estimatedcost of meeting the demand for free welfare milk(liquid and dried) and free vitamin supplements.There is also some provision of dried milk andvitamin supplements at charges which cover thecost.r
16.  Miscellaneous local services table 16   million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71      1971-72     1972-73      1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturnCapital expenditureENGLANDa.	Water supply and conservation *.	50 0	54-5	58-8	65-8	68-5	73-3b.	Sewerage	110-5	125-1	134-7	140-8	148-9	158-4c.	Refuse disposal	12-5	12-3	16-3	18-3 &apos;	20-2	22-2d.	Other public health services	8-2	7-7	8-8	;    8-8	8-8	8-8e.	Land drainage       .	-    -		-   -ri&apos;&quot;&apos;-	-		 f.	Parks, swimming baths, sport, etc.	15-5	12-2	10-7	11-2	12-7	12-4g-	Town and country planning	43-6	43-6	36-9	34-4	37-9	37-9h.	, Unallocated  local  government ad-							ministration       .      .      .	13-3	12-4	12-4	12-4	12-4	12-4i.	Other local expenditure   .	22-7	27-2	24-8	28 1	24-1	25-1	Total      .      .      .	276-3	295-0	303-4	319-8	333-5	350-5WALESa.	Water supply and conservation .	9-4	11-6	11-0	10-4	10-2	10-2b.	Sewerage	7-6	9-4	10-2	11-7	12-5	13-0c.	Refuse disposal	0-2	0-3	0-5	0-6	0-6	0-7d.	Other public health services	0-2	0-3	0-4	0-4	0:4	0-4e.	Land drainage       .	&quot; -	-		Hid ai&apos;-- H		f.	Parks, swimming baths, sport, etc.	0-9	0-6	0-5	0-6	0-7	&quot;   0-7g-	Town and country planning	4-0	3-7	4-0	4-6	5-1	5-6h.	Unallocated  local  government ad-							ministration       .      .      .	0-9	1-2	1-2	( 1.4	1-6	1-6i.	Other local expenditure   .	2-2	2-3	2-4	2-8	3-1	3-3	Total      .....	25-4	29-4	30-2 v,	32-5	34-2	35-53LAND AND WALES				14-2	17-9	24-3	350a.	Lana drainage       ....	10-9	11-8				b.	Parks, swimming baths, sport, etc.	1-2	1-5	1-6	1-6	1-6	1-7ci	Other local expenditure   .	0-9	2-8	1-9	1-8	2-1	0-7	Total     .      .      .	13 0	16-1	17-7	21-3	28-6	37-4TLAND							a.	Water supply and conservation .	15-2	14-5	12-5	11-7	11-2	10-2b.	Sewerage      .      .	9-5	110	11-7	12-9	14-3  .	15-3c.	Refuse disposal      .	3-0	3-1	2-9	hi &apos; 2-8:	2-8	2-8d.	Other public health services	0-9	10	10	&apos;    1:1 &quot;	IT	1-1e.	Land drainage       ....	; - -. :	. ...; 	...  ?ii^v&apos;un*			-f.	Parks, swimming baths, sport, etc.	4-0	4-3	4-6	5-2	5-3	5-7g-	Town and country planning    .	90	9-6	9-9	12-0	12-5	14-5h.	Unallocated  local  government ad-			4 0	4-7		5-8	ministration       .      .      .      .	3-5	3-5			5-5	i.	Other local expenditure   .	10-1	12-3-	12-3	14-1	14-5	15-2	Total     .      .      .	55-2	...59-3	58-9	64-5	67-2	70-6Total Great Britain (capitalexpenditure)     369-9        399-8        410-2        438-1        462-9        494-0Of which public health and avoidance of pollution       . 227-2 250-8        268-8        285-3        299-5        316-4Improvement of the environment and localfacilities  .      .      ..... 117-7 118-8        114-2        121-9        136-6        149-new towns&apos; industrial and commercial development, etc. 25-0 30-2         27-2         30-9         26-8         27.-9
Part One	: Detailed Analysis of Programmes					CONFIDENTIAL	TABLE 16 (continued)					  million at 1970 Survey prices				1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75		provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate		outturn					Current expenditure							ENGLAND							i    . a.	Water supply and conservation .	 	  v .	 	.	-.	b.	Sewerage.....	50-5	54-1	52-5	55-0	66-5	71-2c.	Refuse disposal      .      .      .	77-6	80-4	88-5	94-2	89-8	93-2d-	Other public health services	38-8	40-1	40-7	42-7	43-3	44-8e.	Land drainage       ....	8-9	90	15-5	17-0	9-5	9-6f.	Parks, swimming baths, sport, etc	50-1	51-5	56-6	58-6	54-4	55-9g-	Town and country planning	20-5	21-6	19-7	20-4	23-7	24-9h.	Unallocated local government							administration	77-8	82-9	530	53-8	80-8	82-0i.	Other local expenditure   .	2-1	2-1	2-1	2-2	2-3	Ij i  2-4&apos; -si - *	Departmental administration	10-5	111	12-6	12-5	12-2	12-3	. Total . . ...      .      .      ...    ..	336-8	352-8	341-2	356-4	382-5	396-wales							a.	Water supply and conservation .	 	 		-	:  -	b.	Sewerage.....	2-3	2-5	2-4	2-5	3-0	3-2c.	Refuse disposal      .      .      .	3-8	4-0	4-3	4-7	4-5	4-6d.	Other public health services	2-0	2-1	2-2	2-2	2-3	2-4e.	Land drainage       .      .      .	0-5	0-5	0-9	0-9	0-5	0-6- , f.	Parks, swimming baths, sport, etc.	2-4	2-5	2-9	30	2-8	2-9g-	Town and country planning	1-0	1-0	10	1-1	1-3	1-4h-	Unallocated local administration	5-4	5-5	3-8	3-9	5-8	5-8i.	Other local expenditure   .	0-2	0-4	0-2	01	0-2	;    0-2j-	Departmental administration	0-9	0-9	1-0	1-1	1-1	1-2	....  Total      .      .	18-5	19-4	18-7	19-5	21-5	22-3ENGLAND AND WALES							a.	Parks, swimming baths, sport, etc.	0-9	1-1	1-1	1-1	1-2	1-2	Total     .      .	0-9 i	1-1	1-1	1-1	1-2	1-scotland							a.	Water supply and conservation .		- -   -		- : ,:		b.	Sewerage      .....	3-4	3-6	3-7	3-7	3-7	3-8c.	Refuse disposal      ....	13-2	13-6	140	14-3	14-7.	15-3d.	Other public health services	4-0	4-1	4-2	4-5	4-8	5-0	Land drainage       ....	- 	 	-	. 	...	fi Y- &quot;f.	Parks, swimming baths, sport, etc.	8-4	8-6	90	9-4	10-0	10-6g.	Town and country planning	1-6	1-6	1-6	1-6	1-7	...    1-8h.	Unallocated local government							administration	0-2	0-2	0-2	0-2	0-2	0-2i.	Other local expenditure   .	5-9	6-1	6-3	6-3	6-4	6-6j.	Departmental administration	1-7	1-7	1-7	1-8	1-9	1-9	Total     ..     .	, 38-4	39-5	40-7 .	41-8 ;	43-4	45-2	Tofal Great Britain (current							expenditure)	394-6	412-8	401-7	418-8	448-6	465-0Total Miscellaneous local services:							England      .      .      .      ...		613-1	647-8	644-6	676-2	716-0	746-8Wales .     .		43-9	48-8	48-9	52-0	55-7	57-8England and Wales      ....		13-9	17-2	18-8	22-4	29-2	38-scotland......		93-6	98-8	99-6	106-3	110-6	115-8SET paid by local authorities .      .		32-6	33-2	33-9	34-5	35-2	35-9	Grand total	797-1	845-8	845-8	891-4	946-7	994-9
Capital expenditure england and wales. The totals of expenditure in England andWales set out in the tables for each of the years1969-70 to 1974-75 are in line with those pub-lished in Cmnd. 4515. They incorporate areduction of  8-5 million ( 7-8 million England 0-7 million Wales) out of the  10 million men-tioned in Table 1 of the White Paper for each ofthe years from 1971-72 but, on the other hand,include increases of  1*5 million per annum for england and  0-8 million for Wales in each of theyears from 1972-73 for improvement of infrastruc-ture in development areas. These additions form part of the amount of  25 million referred to inparagraph 13 of Cmnd. 4515 and paragraph 15of Cmnd. 4516 (Investment Incentives). Inaddition  42 million has been included, spreadover the years 1971-72 onwards, for constructionof a Thames Flood Barrier and associated works.This represents approximately half the total costof the works which are expected to take at leasteight years to complete.2. On the policies underlying these figures, well over half the expenditure is accounted for by public health and avoidance of pollution, which includes water, sewerage, refuse disposal,miscellaneous public health expenditure and cleanair policy. Rising domestic standards andchanging customs such as packaging of foodstuffs and technical developments in industry createrapidly increasing demands on these services which have to be met, and the figures allow ingeneral only for the continuation of the present policies under which on sewerage, for example,only those schemes are approved which arerequired for new housing (both public authority and private) and for new industrial developments,or are otherwise essential in the interests ofpublic health. The sewerage figures do, however,allow for the extra expenditure announced by theprevious Administration in Cmnd. 4373 to enable a backlog of small schemes in rural areas to be cleared. Moreover, it should be noted thatschemes carried out in pursuit of the existing policies do, in fact, lead to considerable reduc-tions in pollution. Thus, a major seweragescheme for the Tyne justified within these policieswill lead to its being very largely cleared of pollution.3. In order to allow room for the inescapablegrowth in the first block of services, it has been necessary to restrict the expenditure permittedon other local services wihich are concernedbroadly with the improvement of the environ-ment, provision of local facilities, and industrial,commercial, and miscellaneous development bynew towns. In particular, expenditure on local office building has been severely cut back andthis can be partially justified on the grounds of the impending reorganisation of local govern-ment. On the other hand, no allowance has beenmade within the period of this Survey for the extra expenditure in this field which may become necessary in step with reorganisation.4. The figures for the years 1971-72 onwardswere prepared on the basis of the continuation of the existing system of loan sanction controls over individual projects. However, under the revised arrangements-set out in circular 2/70 ofthe Department of the Environment (116/70Welsh Office) the majority of local expenditure within this block (effectively everything exceptwater, major sewage disposal works, and trunksewers) will cease to be controlled in detail after April, 1971. Instead, expenditure on projectswithin this functional block will fall to be financed from within a total capital expenditure allocationcovering projects falling under other functionalblocks as well, and each individual authority will be free to determine locally which projectsserving which functions it will finance within itsallocation. While the revised system is designedto ensure that total capital spending by localauthorities on these locally-determined schemes will not exceed the aggregrated total&apos;of theamounts allowed in this Survey under the variousfunctional blocks, it is to be expected that the incidence of expenditure under each functionalblock may differ considerably from that forecast in the Survey reflecting the spending choices,in aggregate, made by individual authorities. - Itwill be necessary, therefore, to revise the figures in later years, as between functional blocks, totake account of this.scotland5. The composition of the Scottish expenditure,the background to it, and its general apportion-ment are broadly similar to those for Englandand Wales. The figures take account of thedecisions in Cmnd. 4515, subject only tonecessary corrections of estimates of the cost of policies as these have now been determined; thatis to say, they incorporate a reduction of 1-5 million per annum, the Scottish share of the 10 million referred to in paragraph 16 of cmnd. 4515, and at the same time, they include,- from 1972-73 increases amounting to  1-3 million per annum for improvement of infrastructure in development areas (out of the overall  25 million per annum referred to in paragraph 13 of Cmnd.4515). The position on local office building is thesame as in England: no provision has been madefor the extra expenditure which will become necessary towards the end of the Survey periodfollowing local government reorganisation.
6. In Scotland the control of local authorities&apos;capital expenditure will continue to be by loansanctions granted centrally for individual projects.The revised arrangements for England and wales will not apply. The forecasts are thus not subject to the caveats noted above on theEngland and Wales figures.Current expenditure. For England and Wales, the forecasts for1970-71 are derived from the rate support grantsettlement for that year. While the outturn islikely to be broadly in line with the total of theseforecasts, it is possible that there will be significant   variations   on   individual   services.For 1971-72 and 1972-73 the forecasts are basedon the outcome of the recent rate support grant negotiations. For the last two years previousforecasts are retained unchanged.8. In Scotland the rate support grant negotia-tions will not be concluded until the New Year,but the forecasts anticipate the expected outcome of these negotiations. For 1970-71 the forecastsflow from the 1969-70 out turns of expenditurereported by local authorities. These suggest that expenditure on these services will be about 2 million in each year higher than the forecastsin previous programmes. The forecasts for1971-72 and subsequent years take account ofthis higher level of expenditure.17. Law and orderTABLE 17  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70provisionaloutturn1970-71estimate1971-72estimate1972-73estimate1973-74estimate1974-75estimateCapital expenditure england AND wales.   Home Departments&apos; services:(i) Police .	18-8	26-1	29-8	28-8    .	30-6	31-3(ii) Prisons.....	9-4	10-6	11-6	17-7	22-9	25-7(iii) Probation and after care	0-4	0-4	0-4	0-4	0-6 1	0-7(iv) Child care   .      .      .      .	3-5	4-5	5-4	5-9	6-2	5-7(v) Fire services .	6-7	9-8	10-6	9-8	10-4	10-2(vi) Other services      .      .      .	1-9	4-9	2-4	2-5	2:6	2-6- Total	40-7	56-3	-   60-2	65 1	73-3	76-2b-   Law courts, etc.    .      .	5-6	7-2	9-7	110	12-0 1	13-3Total England and Wales	46-3	63-5	69-9	76; 1	85-3	89- scotland						a.   Home Departments&apos; services:						. (i) Police  .      .      1    , .      .	1-7	2-4	&quot;2-7	2-9	4-1	-   4-2(ii) Prisons .      ;      .      .      .	11	1-0	2-5	3-3	3-1	3-4(iii) Social work .      .	1-7	20	2-9	3-3	3-4	.3-5(iv) Fire services .      ...	1-3	1-4	1-4	1-7	2-0	2-2(v) Other services      .      .	0-1	0-6	Q-5	0-6	0-5	0-4Total    .      .     ...-;        :.....	5-9	7-4	10-0	11-8	13-1	13-7b.   Law courts, etc.    .      .      .,	0-2	0-5   .	.0-4	0-6	1-6	1-3Total Scotland      .             .      .	6-1	- ;   7.9	10-4	12-4	14(7	150Total Great Britain (capital expenditure)	52-4	71-4	80 3	88-5	1000	104-5
TABLE 17 (continued)   million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74      1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimateoutturnCurrent expenditure england AND wales.   Home Departments&apos; services:(i) Police..... 256-7 270-6 282-5 290-5 313 0 327-2(ii) Prisons..... 38-6 42-4 47-1 49-6 51-9 54-1(iii) Probation and after-care       . 10-5 11-6 12-2 13-8 15-0 16-1(iv) Child care    .      .      .      . 58-0 60-0 63-3 66-5 70-5 74-1(v) Fire services . . .  .      .      . 55-9 56-7 58-5 59-9 60-8 62-1(vi) Other services      ... 4-8 6-6 9-2 10-7 12-0 12-8(vii) Departmental administration . 10-6 11-9 12-9 140 150 16-0!    Total    .      .     -.&apos;-     .      .      .     435-1        459-8        485-7        505 0        538-2        562-4b. Law courts, etc.    .      .      .      .       34-5 37-4 39-7 42-0        42-8 49-2c. Legal aid      .      .      .      .      .       13-5 14-8 16-3 18-0 21-2 22-6Total England and Wales      .      . 483-1 512 0 541-7 565-0 602-2 634-2SCOTLANDa.   Home Departments&apos; services:(0 Police..... 25-8 26-6 27-3 281 29 0 30-0(ii) Prisons .      ......      . 4-0 4-2 4-4 4-5 4-7 4.9(iii) Social work ..... 17-7 18-5 20-2 21-4 22-5 23-8(iv) Fire services .      .      .      . 6 0 6-2 6-5 6-6 6-8 6-9(v) Other services             .      . 0-5 0-8 0-9 1-1 1-2 1-4(vi) Departmental administration . 0-8 0-8 0-9 0-9 0-9 0-9Total    .........       54-8 57-1 60-2 62-6 65-1 67-9b. Law courts, etc.    .     .      .      .        2-2 2-3 2-3 2-5 2-6 2-7c. Legal aid     .      ...      .      .        1-3 1-4 1-6 1-7        .1-8 1-9Total Scotland       .      .      .      .       58-3 60-8 64-1 66-8 69-5 72-5Parliament, etc.......        6-9 7-4 7-6 7-8 7-9 8-0Parliamentary election expenses    .      .      .        0-3 2-1 0-3 0-2 0-2 0-2SET paid by local authorities       .      .      .       31-9 32-5 33-2 33-8 34-5 35-2Total (current expenditure)      .      .     580-5        614-8        646-9        673-6       714-3        750-1Grand total.....      632-9        686-2   .     727-2        762-1        814-3        854-61. The law and order programme coversexpenditure by the Government and localauthorities. It includes the cost of the home departments, the Legal Departments, the houses of Parliament and the Privy Council. Most ofthe expenditure is incurred by local authorities on services to which the Government contributethrough specific grants or rate support grant.Police2. Continuing increases are forecast in policestrengths of about 18,000 over the Survey period,and of about 21,000 in civilian strengths(including traffic wardens).Prisons3. At the beginning of 1970-71 the prisonpopulation was about 43,500.   The population is increasing at a faster rate than projectedlast year, and it is expected that this trend willcontinue. The forecasts assume increasingprovision for the prison building programme.Probation and after-care (England and Wales)4. The forecasts provide for the increasedexpansion of this service to help to relieve the pressure on the prison service.Child care (England and Wales)45. The forecasts provide for the implementation of the Children and Young Persons Act 1969 and* As from 1 January 1971 responsibility for child care in England and in Wales is transferred to the Depart-ment of Health and Social Security and the welsh office respectively (Cmnd. 4506). In the 1971 Surveyexpenditure on child care will be incorporated into the health and Welfare programme.
the new system of community homes for childrenneeding care in residential establishments, andthe necessary growth of the child care service.Social work (Scotland)*6. The forecasts have been adjusted to providefor the additions from the additional  110 millionannounced in paragraph 28 of Cmnd. 4515 forthe further development of social work services,particularly for the elderly and mentally handicapped. Some increase in expenditure isalso attributable to the continued implementation of the Social Work (Scotland) Act 1968.Fire services. The forecasts provide for expansion resultingfrom the recommendations of the Departmental* In the 1971 Survey expenditure on Social Work inScotland will be incorporated into the Health and welfare programme.Committee on the Fire Service and fromadditional work on fire prevention.Law courts and legal aid8. The forecasts assume that the work of thecourts and the number of both civil and criminal cases in which legal aid is granted will continueto rise.Other services9. The main services on which a continuingincrease in expenditure is forecast are the urban programme of aid for areas of special socialneed, and the criminal injuries compensation scheme. The forecasts for the urban programmetake account of the addition of  0-2 million ineach year from 1971-72 onwards for family planning. (See paragraph 6 of the text on health and Welfare.)18.  ArtsTABLE 18  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70 provisional outturn			1970-71 estimate	1971-72 estimate	1972-73 estimate	1973-74 estimate	1974-75 estimatea.   National museums, galleries and libraries :*							(i) Staff, administration, etc.	7	3	8-0	8-7	8-4	9-0	9-4(ii) Annual purchase grantsf	1	5	2-2	2-2	2-2	2-2	2-2Total!   .     .     .     .     .	8	8	10-2	10-9	10-6	11-2	11-6b.   The other Arts:							(i) Arts Council, British Film Institute and							National Film School							(a) Current   .....	8	5	9-3	11-2	11-2	12-3	13-5(b) Capitalt   .      .	0	5	0-7	0-9	0-8	0-6	0-6(ii) Other grantsf 5     .      .      .      .	0	1	01	0-1	0-2	0-2	0-2(Hi) National Theatre, South Bankf	0	6	1-4	1-8	1-8	0-9	-....... Total           .      .         .................	9	7	11-5	14-0	140	14-0	14-3Grand total   .      .      .      .								18	5	21-7	24-9	24-6	25-2 ,,	25-9* This includes the National Central Library and excludes the British Museum (Natural History) and Geological Museumwhich are included in Table 6.t These figures are in money terms and not at constant prices.t Expenditure relating to England and Scotland on new buildings, maintenance and running expenses, stationery, superannuationetc., is included under the heading Common Services in Table 23.g This includes grants to the British Institute of Recorded Sound, the Royal Geographical Society, the Scottish Film Council,the Royal Scottish Geographical Society and assistance to local museums in carrying out co-operative schemes.1, Expenditure on the Arts, rising from  21-7 million in 1970-71 to  25-9 million in 1974-75,excludes expenditure by local authorities, exceptfor the Greater London Council&apos;s contribution tothe National Theatre.2. The provision for the national museums,galleries and libraries allows for the maintenanceof and additions to the collections and takes account of the revenue from charges which, as already announced, will take full effect in1972-73.3. The grant to the Arts Council, which includes provision for the Scottish and Welsh ArtsCouncils, is intended to foster the creative artsgenerally and to stimulate artistic activity in the regions.
UBLICEXPENDITURETO 1974-75Appendix: Part ThreeSpecial Analyses1970 Report by the Public expenditure survey CommitteeDecember 1970THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government copy No. 060
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA.TESTY&apos;S government copy No. 060UBLICXPENDITUREO 1974-75Appendix: Part ThreeSpecial Analyses1970 Report by the Public expenditure survey CommitteeDecember 1970
PUBLIC EXPENDITURE TO 1974-75APPENDIX TO1970 REPORT BY THE PUBLIC EXPENDITURE SURVEYCOMMITTEECONTENTS&quot; --i &quot; .......PART THREE.   SPECIAL ANALYSES1.  Local authorities&apos;current expenditure .      .      .      ...      . . .      22.  Nationalised industries     .      .      .      .      ..... . .       3i   ........:-................3.  Regional expenditure on new construction   .   &quot; . &quot; ..      .      .      . . .       54.  Scotland and Wales  .      .      .      .      .      ........ . .       85.  Research and Development.      ........ . .     10SECRET 1
APPENDIXPART THREESPECIAL ANALYSES1.   Local authorities&apos; current expenditureCurrent expenditure of local authorities^  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70provisionaloutturn1970-71estimate1971-72estimate1972-73estimateEngland and WalesRoads     ....Miscellaneous Local ServicesHome Department services education and local librariesHealth and Welfare  .All other ServicesEfficiency reductionTotal current expenditure (PES basis)Adjustments to Rate Support Grant basisfTotal revenue expenditure (RSG basis) .ScotlandRoads     .      .      .      .      .-     .      .      .Miscellaneous Local Services     .      .      .      .Home Department Services!      .      .      .      .Education and local libraries     .      .Healtht   ...     .     ...All other Services......Efficiency reduction      .      .      .      .Total current expenditure (PES basis)Adjustments to Rate Support Grant basistTotal revenue expenditure (RSG basis) .167-8	195-4	208-1	221-0343-7	359-9	346-2	362-3372-3	389-0	406-9	420-61,557-4	1,600-9	1,658-7	1,727-7212-9	212-8	230-3	246-259-6	63-3	67-2	71-0&quot; -	-	-10-0	-25-02,713-7	2,821-3	2,907-4	3,023-8467-1	517-2	550-2	598-73,180-8	3,338-5	3,457-6	3,622-522-3	22-8	23-5	24-936-6	37-6	38-8	39-848-1	49-9	52-6	54-7160-6	164-8	171-1	178-18-1	8-4	8-8	9-45-8	5-9	5-9	6-2-	-	-1-0	-2-5281-5	289-4	299-7	310-6550	62-3	69-0	76-3336-5	351-7	368-7	&apos;     386-9* Excluding Housing, expenditure from Trading and Housing Revenue Accounts and SET paid by local authorities,f Expenditure relevant for Rate Support Grant differs from that included in Public Expenditure Surveys, in particular because it includes loan charges as well as the small proportion of capital expenditure which local authorities meet directly from revenue.$ In Scotland, following the Social Work (Scotland) Act, expenditure on local welfare services is included under home departments&apos; services: in England it is included under Health and Welfare.1. In this section the forecasts of current expenditure on local authority services describedprogramme by programme in Part 1 of theAppendix are brought together. The figures arenot included for the last two years of the Surveywhich fall outside the period covered by presentRSG negotiations.england and wales. For 1969-70 the outturn figures are those shown in previous programmes. They have notat this stage been revised to reflect the actualoutturn figures submitted by local authorities,but it is known that actual outturn was below that forecast previously by about  20 million on---\
an RSG basis, and that significant variationsbetween forecast and outturn materialised on individual services. For 1970-71 it is stillexpected that outturn will, in total, be in line with previous forecasts, but in the light of theactual outturn for 1969-70, substantial variationsare anticipated between services. For this reason,no individual service figures are shown.3. For 1971-72 and 1972-73 the individualservice figures and the totals reflect the recentRSG settlement. For the subsequent years ofthe Survey period, the figures are those in pre-vious programmes adjusted only to reflect the specific policy decisions in Cmnd. 4515, suchunderlying policy changes for certain individual services as were explicitly made in the RSGsettlement, and the general squeeze.scotland. The Scottish figures are generally on a similar basis, except that for both 1969-70 and 1970-71,the figures both in total and for the individual services have been adjusted to reflect the actualoutturn in 1969-70 which was slightly (around 0-5 million in RSG terms) above previous programmes. For 1971-72 and 1972-73 theRSG settlement has yet to be negotiated but the forecasts shown are those that are expected to emerge from the negotiations.2. Nationalised industriesSummary of capital expenditure by nationalised industries  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73 1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate    estimate    estimate estimate     estimateoutturnExpenditure   on   fixed   assets   in   the   United	1,494-9	1,680-4	1,699-0	1,722-7	1,768-1	1,908-7	 	-150-0	-175-0	-150-0	-150-0	-150-0	1,494-9	1,530-4	1,524-0	1,572-7	1,618-1	1,758-7Less: Sales of fixed assets    .      .      .	-44-6	-34-6	-42-5	-39-1	-34-1	-26-3Gross domestic fixed capital formation	1,450-3	1,495-8	1,481-5	1,533-6	1,584-0	1,732-4Increase in value of stocks .     .      .     .      .	-22-8	-25-3	-7-7	-2-8	22-9	10-0Net lending to private sector    ....	3-3	7-5	6-9	4-8	9-2	8-net lending and investment abroad .	6-9	13-3	9-3	6-7	7-1	5-2Cash expenditure on company securities  (net)	8-5	10-0	6-0	4-0	4-0	4-0Total capital expenditure      .     .     .	1,446-2	1,501-3	1,496-0	1,546-3	1,627-2	1,759-91. The purpose of this special analysis is tooutline the objectives of the nationalised industries programme, to bring together certainstatistics for the nationalised industries and to comment on shortfall and the industries&apos; financialperformance.2. The capital expenditure programmes of the nationalised industries account for about 7 percent of all public expenditure and their annualinvestment is roughly equivalent to the whole ofthat for manufacturing industries. The pro-grammes are designed to meet the demand fortheir products and services in the most efficientway arid to conduct their finances so that theymeet their financial objectives and/or other statutory obligations. The programmes of allthe industries have been reviewed before and afterthe election. The results of the latter review haveSECRETbeen to secure reductions of  42 million in1971-72 rising to  73 million in 1974-75.3. Nationalised industries capital expenditure is now expected to continue at much the same level up until 1972-73 but to show a markedupward trend thereafter. This trend is mainlyinfluenced by the rapidly expanding programmes of the Post Office throughout the Survey period and increased spending by the Electricity Counciland Boards from 1972-73 onwards.Shortfall4. For the nationalised industries as a wholeexperience shows that capital expenditure fallsshort of the approved figure. The provision in previous programmes incorporated reductions of 150 milUon in 1970-71,  175 million in 1971-72and  150 million in each of the last three years have been made from the aggregate expenditure3
on fixed assets by the individual industries.These estimates of short-fall have been increasedby  25 million in each of the three years from1970-71 to 1972-73 and by  50 million in thelast two years since experience in recent years has shown that previous estimates have been too low.Comparison with previous programmes5. As noted in Part 1 of the Appendix nation-nationalised industries fixed investment in aggregate isbelow the estimates in previous programmesboth before and after the deduction of shortfall.Total capital expenditure is also within the limits of previous estimates.Fixed assets expenditure by nationalised industries  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate    estimate    estimate    estimate    estimateoutturn1.	National Coal Board   .      .	61-2	74-0	75-0	66-0	60-0	58-02.	Electricity Council and Boards	454-0	402-5	357-0	372-0	407-0	505-03.	North of Scotland Hydro-Electric Board   .	10-5	13-6	13-5	17-0	21-7	35-14.	South of Scotland Electricity Board .	62-5	69-5	58-3	59-8	47-7	42-15.	Gas Council and Boards     .      .      .      .	2100	231-3	210-0	181-0	189-0	172-0	Total (1-5)  .	798-2	790-9	713-8	695-8	725-4	812-2							6.	British Steel Corporation     .      .      .      .	84-0	130-0	185-0	185-0	185-0	185-07.	Post Office.......	391-2	461-3	504-5	539-0	558-9	564-48.	British Overseas Airways Corporation .	46-1	92-8	60-7	76-6	87-1	105-49.	British European Airways    .      .      .      .	19-2	42-1	59-5	42-9	27-3	47-110.	British Airports Authority   .     .     .     .	9-3	11-9	15-1	16-2	19-1	j   32-4	Total (8-10) .      .      .      .      .	74-6	146-8	135-3	135-7	133-5	184-911.	British Railways Board .      .......	78-0	83-1	94-0	1000	1000	100-012.	London Transport Board     .      .      .      .	6-1	-				-13.	British Transport Docks Board .	16-2	14-8	.13-1	15-5	16-5	13-514.	British Waterways Board     ....	0-7	0-8	0-8	0-9	0-9	1-015.	Transport Holding Company	0-3	0-8	0-9	1-1	0-4	0-316.	National Freight Corporation	30-3	31-5	29-6	29-2	27-8	27-917.	National Bus Company .     .......	11-8	17-0	17-8	16-5	16-2	16-218.	Scottish Transport Group    ....	: 1 ,  3-5	3-4	4-2	4-0	3-5	3-3								Total   (11-18)      .      .     .      .	146-9	151-4	160-4	167-2	165-3	162-219.	Shortfall .     .               - .     .     .  &quot; .		-150-0	-175-0	-150-0	-150-0	-150-020.	Total expenditure on fixed assets .	1,494-9	1,530-4	1,524-0	1,572-7	1,618-1	1,758-financial performance7. For the purposes of the Public expenditure survey it has been generally assumed that theindustries are allowed to increase prices in sofar as higher costs cannot be met by higher productivity. If increases were not permitted asthey became necessary it would not be possiblein most cases for the industries to meet their financial objectives and other action either on expenditure or taxation would be required to offset increased demands on the economy.8. The extent to which higher prices will be needed in the period up to 1974-75 cannot be predicted with any precision. This will depend upon the level of demand for the goods and services produced and by individual industries&apos;changes in productivity, in the cost of rawmaterials and in the pattern of future wage move-ments. Allowances have been made for price increases, such as those of the NCB, electricity and Gas Councils, at present under consideration.Over the five-year period as a whole the achieve-ment of current financial objectives is likely torequire increases in many charges, assuming thatthe industries&apos; costs rise approximately in line with prospective increases in costs and pricesgenerally. For estimating purposes it has been assumed that the gross trading surpluses of the nationalised industries will continue to rise as a proportion of total domestic income. This trendreflects the increasing share of domestic expendi-ture devoted to services such as transport and telecommunications.
3.  Regional expenditure on new construction1, The following tables bring together estimates of expenditure on new construction only by regionfor the larger functional programmes (roads,housing, etc.) which are included in the total public expenditure figures. These figures areaimed at giving a regional dimension to majorpublic sector investment programmes, which have important implications for regional policy.2. In recent years the estimates for each regionhave been passed to the appropriate economic planning Council, together with details of major projects under the various programmes. Althoughthe main purpose of circulating this material isto provide Councils with information which maybe relevant to their regional planning activities,it also enables them to comment on the balanceof planned expenditure between individual pro-grammes within their respective regions in thelight of their strategic economic planning forthem. The relevant Departments consider these comments and, wherever possible, take them intoaccount when preparing subsequent programmes,although the scope for this is limited in severalways, including the fact that several of the pro-grammes are under the immediate control oflocal authorities.MAJOR ROADS(Central Government and local authority expenditure)  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70    1970-71    1971-72    1972-73    1973-74    1974-75provisional estimate    estimate    estimate   estimate    estimateoutturnNorthern.......- . 45-5 41-3 34-1 31-6 28-3 25-2Yorkshire and Humberside       .      .,     .    . .      . 14-3 22 6 29-9 36-2 42-1 49-2East Midlands.......      . 8-8 9-5 9-4 12-1 15-8 18.-7East Anglia......... 4-1 5-8 6-7 11-9 15-7 15-1South-East........... 60-6 80-8 101-7 128-0 142-8 156-2South-West......... 27-0 53-8 41-7 &apos;      34-7 34-0 38-0West Midlands........ 45-3 42-5 34-4 33-0 34-5 34-9North-West........ 60-3 58-4 52-0 57-3 50-8 47-1England........   265-9       314-7       309-9       344-8       364-0       384-scotland.........    36-0 38-5 43-7        43-7        44-5        44-6Wales   .      .      .      . .      .      .      .     12-5 17-7 19-6        21-4        25-5        27-4Great Britain     ........   314-4       370-9       373-2       409-9       434-0       456-41. Major roads provide an economic stimulus tothe areas through which they pass and to theareas which they link with the main economiccentres. Improvement of the routes which carrydeveloping major traffic flows are critical forthe regions and for improved accessibility between all parts of the country. In addition to the regional benefits provided by normal roadimprovement, additional funds have from time totime been provided to permit the constructionof special promotional schemes in the regions.Examples are the North-East Special RoadProgrammes, the Workington-Penrith road andthe Humber Bridge.2. There are standing arrangements for consulta-tions between Departments and the economic planning Councils about additions to roadprogrammes and to the preparation pools (inaddition to the recent consultations with themabout the longer term route strategy for England).3. The proposed road programme for 1972-73would permit the start of work on about  350million worth of new schemes in that year. on present plans and subject to normal slippage andunforeseen delays these are likely to be distributed as follows among the regions:  million at 1970 Survey prices	Motorways and		Trunk Roads	Principal	(works only)	RoadsNorthern	12	11Yorkshire and Humberside	34	15East Midlands	12	6East Anglia	10	3South-East	82	53South-West   .	-      27	10West Midlands	24	10North-West   .      .     .&quot;	14	27	215	135SECRET
HOUSING(Local authority and new town corporation expenditure)  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70    1970-71    1971-72    1972-73    1973-74    1974-75provisional estimate   estimate    estimate   estimate    estimateoutturnNorthern......... 46-6 39-1 39-8 41-3 41-2 39-9Yorkshire and Humberside..... 44-3 34-8 34-3 35-6 37-0 37-2East Midlands......:    -     . 27-8 27-5 33-4 35-9 38-6 40-2EastAnglia.......... 14-4 16-2 17-8 19-3 21-8 22-south-East......... 241-9 215-3 222-7 212-7 207-2 209-south-West......... 24-9 27-3 25-8 25-5 25-9 25-9West Midlands........ 71-5 65-3 59-2 55-9 57-5 57-north-West........ 94-6 85-0 86-2 87-2 86-0 85-0England.........   566-0       510-5       519-2       513-4      515-2      517- scotland.......     .   144-8       143-7       142-8       145-5       147-0       148-4Wales.........    28-2        25-0        28-8 34-2 36-0        36-7Great Britain.........   739-0       679-2       690-8       693-1       698-2       702-61. Regional estimates of local authorities&apos; newhouse building assume that the programme willbe divided among the regions in the sameproportions as in the current year. Owing to thelarge number of local housing authorities andtheir freedom to determine the programme levelsappropriate to their areas, forecasts of totalapprovals by regions must inevitably be subject tofairly wide margins of error.2. Within the overall housing programmepriority is given to schemes for slum clearance,overspill and housing for old people in all the regions.MISCELLANEOUS LOCAL SERVICES(Local authority and new town corporation expenditure) i  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70    1970-71    1971-72    1972-73    1973-74    1974-75provisional estimate   estimate    estimate   estimate    estimate outturn ,Northern......	.    161	20	3	25	4	28-3	28	-6	28-9Yorkshire and Humberside	: -&quot;-&apos; .&apos;v 21-3 &quot;	19	8	23	3	23-2	24	8	27-0East Midlands   .      .     .      .      .	.    19-8	22	6	23	2	24-3	26	3	28-1East Anglia......	.     12-4	13	6	14	7	15-3	17	-1	17-south-East......	.    75-8	81	7	86	1	94-4	103	6	117-south-West.......	.    18-1	16	6	18	7	19-0	20	4	21-8West Midlands .     . :   .	.    27-4	27	9	26	3	29-5	30	5	32-0North-West.....	-      -     -    31-3	34	8	32	5 rj	35-9	37	2	40-5England      .     ...	.   222-2	237	3	250	2	269-9	288	5	313-scotland.....	.    46-6	49	2	47	6	50-9	53	6	&apos;57-wales......	.    21-7	25	6	26	0	28-0	29	4	30-5Unallocated	.      .     .      0-1	0	1	0	3	0-5	0	5	0-5Great Britain.......      .   290-6       312-2       324-1       349-3       372-0       401-9
1. The regional estimates are in general basedon recent past performance and known futureproposals by local authorities. In those for watersupply allowance has been made for risingdemand leading to a number of major waterschemes.-2. For sewerage regional apportionment in later years is liable to revision with later information about the preparation and phasing of individualdevelopment   schemes.    For   refuse   disposalINorthernYorkshire and HumbersideEast Midlands   .East Anglia .South-East  .South-West . ,   .West Midlands .North-WestEnglandScotlandWalesGreat Britain     ........   154-31. The basis of the forecasts of capital expendi-ture by region is the assumption that they will follow the most recent actual distribution. Some30 per cent of expenditure is thus attributed to theSouth-East (including London) followed by 15per cent in the North-West. The smallest shareis that of East Anglia (3 per cent). The pattern of distribution is, of course, subject to adjustment to match any changes in the pattern of population growth and movement.2. In the course of circulating the 1969 estimatesto the Regional Economic Planning Councilsthey have been encouraged to consult localeducation authorities in their regions to establishhow changes in local population growth patternsand other detailed factors (such as the differentialeffects of raising the school leaving age and changes in the distribution of new housing) arelikely to affect the future distribution ofexpenditure on schools.account has in particular been taken of the GLCsprogramme for refuse destructors. The estimates for expenditure on town and country planning,which includes town centre redevelopment andexpenditure by local authorities for the encourage-ment of industry, are heavily weighted towardsdevelopment and intermediate areas and expand-ing towns. Indeed the special needs of these latter areas will be fully reflected in the incidence of expenditure throughout the miscellaneouslocal services programme.161-9       198-2       196-8       170-6       138-23. Priority will continue to be given to theprovision of new places required to meet theincrease in and movement of school population.But, taking the country as a whole, numbers inprimary schools will begin to fall after 1973, andthe rate of increase in secondary schools willdecline after the raising of the school-leaving age. Greater resources will therefore be availablefor the improvement and replacement of oldschools.4. These resources (beginning with a starts pro-gramme of about  44 million in 1972-73) willbe concentrated, in England and Wales, on the replacement of primary schools built before 1903(and, in Scotland, on the reduction of overcrowd-ing in primary schools). They will be distributed between regions in proportion to the number of pupils in such schools, with an initial weightingin favour of socially deprived urban areas. Theneed to improve obsolete school buildings hasbeen emphasised by several of the economic planning Councils.SCHOOLS(Local authority expenditure)  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70    1970-71    1971-72    1972-73    1973-74    1974-75provisional estimate   estimate    estimate   estimate    estimateoutturn12-8	14-1	17-6	17-6	15-0	11-914-1	15-5	19-4	19-3	16-5	13-18-9	9-8	12-4	12-3	10-5	8-33-8	4-2	5-3	5-3	4-5	3-538-3	42-2	53-0	52-7	45-2	35-67-7	8-5	10-6	10-5	9-0	7-114-1	15-5	19-4	19-3	16-5	13-119-2	21-1	26-5	26-4	22-6	17-8118-9	130-9	164-2	163-4	139-8	110-426-5	21-2	21-6	21-1	20-3	19-58-9	9-8	12-4	12-3	10-5	8-3
HEALTH AND WELFARE  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70 1970-71 1971-72 1972-73 1973-74 1974-75provisional estimate estimate estimate estimate estimate outturn	H.	LA.	H.		L.A.	H.		L.	A.	H.		L.	A	H		L.A.		H		L.A.Northern	4-6	2-2	5	5	2-2	6	1	2	4	7	0	2	7	7	6	2	7	8	2	2-9Yorkshire and																				Humberside	8-0	2-7	7	1	2-7	11	2	3	0	17	2	3	2	18	9	3	4	15	9	3-5East Midlands	5-1	2-0	6	1	2-0	6	9	2	2	5	3	2	4	4	7	2	4	5	5	2-6East Anglia .	5-9	1-1	6	5	1-2	6	7	1	2	4	1	1	3	4	2	1	4	4	9	1-4South-East   .	38 0	111	44	3	10-8	48	5	12	1	50	5	12	9	51	3	13	5	48	8	14-2South-West .	8-3	2-4	&apos;&quot;&apos;7	2	2-3	8	5	2	5	8	8	2	7	8	3	2	9	9	3	3-0West Midlands	7-4	2-5	9	3	2-4	11	5	2	7	14	0	2	9	13	5	3	1	14	2	3-north-West .	1 A . q	A . 3	1 ^	q		1 *\	7	/I	-7	1 a	-7			1 q				19		5-5	14-y	4 j	ID	O	t*  .	i j	/	-f	/	lu	/	j	u	to	j	j	z	to	y	England .	92-2	28-3	101	8	27-8	115	l	30	8	123	6	33	1	127	0	34	6	125	7	36-scotland	13-3	0-4	13	3	0-4	14	8	0	5	17	3	0	7	17	1	0	9	17	1	11Wales   .	7-1	1-9	7	5	1-8	6	3	2	2	6	1	2	4	,5	8	2	6	5	8	2-6Unallocated &quot; .	-	-			-	4	7	4	2	6	3	6	2	5	4	6	2	5	4	5-6Great Britain     .	112-6	30-6	122	6	30 0	140	9	37	7&apos;	153	3	42	4	155	3	44	3	154	0	45-7H. &apos;^ Hospitals, i.e., central government expenditure.LA. = Local authority health and welfare services in England and Wales; health services only in Scotland.1. The development of health services is seen as a consequence of, and geared to, economic development in each planning region. in considering the distribution of resources betweenthe various Hospital Regions, which are notconterminous with the planning regions, anumber of factors are taken into account.Regard is paid to the present state of services provided for patients in each region, to thecondition of the hospitals and to the rate of population growth forecast. The Secretary ofState is currently reviewing the hospital building programme, and particularly its priorities and balance and the relationship between hospitals and community services. The hospital building programme received a share of the additional resources made available over the four years from 1971-72 for the hospital and local health and welfare services. This will be used mainly to speed progress in developments for the care of the mentally handicapped, the mentally illand the elderlyl12. Fluctuations in investment in some planningregions during this period are partly due to the inception and completion of individual largeprojects. For instance the dip in Yorkshire andHumberside in 1974-75 is due to the completionof the new Hallamshire Hospital main building in Sheffield and the completion of the first phase of the new teaching hospital in Leeds. The dipin East Anglia in 1972-73 is due to the comple-tion of the Bury St. Edmunds developmentproject and the new Cambridge teaching hospital.3. Regions are not uniformly affected bydevelopment and teaching hospital projects. Theformer are few in number and financed from a central reserve. Teaching projects require heavy expenditure over a few years and these are takeninto account in the allocations to regional hospital areas over the decade; the balance due for regional hospital projects being then allocated to give a rising annual programme.4.  Expenditure in Scotland and wales. The following tables show forecasts by sibility of the Secretaries of State in Scotland and departments of expenditure within the respon-      Wales up to 1972-73.
SCOTLANDExpenditure within the Secretary of State&apos;s responsibility			TABLE 5.1	  million at 1970 Survey prices		1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate outturn			5.  Agriculture, fisheries and forestry *.....         55-4	65-4	62-1	57-66.   Research Councils, etc.       .      .      .      .      .      .           2-9	3-1	3-4	3-57.  Trade, industry and employment .      .      .      .      .           3-5	4-2	4-7	4-313.   Roads and public lighting    .      .      .      .      .      .          71-9	76-5	82-1	84-314.  Transport   .      .      .      .      .      .      .      .      .          2-6	3-8	3-7	3-615.   Housing.........        225-2	239-1	244-6	251-516.  Miscellaneous local services......         93-6	98-8	99-6	106-317.  Law and order........         64-4	68-7	74-5	79-218.  Arts   .      .      ...      .      .      .      .      .           0-9	1-0	1-0	1-119.  Education   .      .      .   &apos;- .      .      .      .      .      .        233-9	236-7	246-6	255-520.  Health and welfare.......198-9	204-2	209-6	215-222.   Financial administration      .      .      .      .      .      .           3-2	3-2	3-2	3-324.  Miscellaneous services .      .      .      ---------                         2-5	,,    2-9	4-1	3-3Total........        958-9	1,007-6	1,039-2	1,068-7* Forestry Commission expenditure in Scotland is not included.			Expenditure in Scotland within the responsibilities of other Ministers			TABLE 5.2	  million at 1970 Survey prices		1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-735.  Agriculture, fisheries and forestry4 .      .      .      .      .         22-3,	24-6	25-8	26-96.  Research Councils, etc. .      .      .      .      .      .      .           6-9	&quot;. &quot;    7-1 -	7-5	7-97.  Trade, industry and employment  .      .      .      .      .         183-0	169-8	167-5	121-614. Transport   .      .      .      ...      .      .     &apos;..     .         10-0	10-7	14-1	16-817.   Law and order    .      .      .      .           . .-           .           0-5	0-5	0-6	0-618. Arts   .             .      .      .      .     i:-iniV!:&apos;-         . .    , &apos; &apos;&apos;&apos;0-9&quot;&apos; !	10	1-2	1-319. Education   .      .      .      .      .      .      ,     .      ..         38-0	37-9	42-1	44-721.  Social security     ........        377-0	390-0	395-5	411-722.  Financial administration      .      .      .      .      .      .          16-6	16-5	16-2	16-523.  Common services .........         14-2	15-7	18-2	21-124.  Miscellaneous services .      .      ...      .      .      .           2-0	30	0-8	-1-31         -Total.........        671-4	676-8	689-4	667-8* Forestry Commission expenditure in Scotland is included in line 5 of Table 5.2.WALESExpenditure within the Secretary of State&apos;s responsibilityTABLE 5.3   million at 1970 Survey prices1969-70 1970-71 1971-72 1972-73provisional        estimate estimate estimateoutturn5.	Agriculture, fisheries and forestry4	0-1	0-1	01	0-17.	Trade, industry and employment	0-1	0-8	0-7	0-613.	Roads and public lighting	34-9	41-1	44-3	47-514.	Transport   .      .!	01	0-5	0-7	0-815.	Housing     .      .      .      .      .	&apos; v.      . i      38-2	42-8	46-1	52-316.	Miscellaneous local services   ....	43-9	48-8	48-9	52-018.	Arts........	0-8	0-9	1-0	1-119.	Education   .      .      .	&apos; ..                 83-7	86-1	92-5	95-220.	Health and Welfare     .      .      .	101-7	104-5	106-4	108-922.	Financial administration	.      .           0.9	0-9	0-9	0-924.	Miscellaneous services  .      .      .      .	. -        0-2	0-1	0-2	0-2	Total     ......	304-6	326-6	341-8	359-6* Forestry Commission expenditure in Wales is not included.
TABLE 5.4Expenditure in Wales within the responsibility of other Ministers_  million at 1970 Survey prices1969-701970-711971-721972-735.6.7.14.16.17.18.19.21.22.23.24.Agriculture, fisheries and forestry*Research Councils, etc. .Trade, industry and employmentTransportMiscellaneous local services law and orderArts   ....EducationSocial securityFinancial administrationCommon services .Miscellaneous services  .Total25275602304222010-25-91-1414-928-92-273-44-61-424-0-43-227-12-9-1-429-929-92-374-94-91-025-80-744-8231-812-311-50-9440-30-02-454-75-40-727-40-846-2240-713-612-60-2434-7* Forestry Commission expenditure in Wales is included in line 5 of Table 5.4.5.  Research and development . The following table shows estimates ofexpenditure on research and development by those departments (including the major spendingdepartments in this field) which took part in the review of Government Research and Develop-ment 1970. This Review, completed in August1970, was prepared by the Official Committee on science and Technology (SCTO(70)3 Revise).The present table is based on the SCTO estimates,revised wherever possible by Departments so asto reflect the latest estimates of public expenditurein the 1970 Survey and analysed by programme.2. The figures for the former Ministry of Tech-nology in SCTO (70) 3 Revise have been amended to include agreed additions to the programmes ofthe Ministry of Aviation Supply (on Concorde,Space and Aircraft Launching Aid). Neither theDepartment of Trade and Industry, nor theMinistry of Aviation Supply, is at present ableto allocate to programmes the savings in cmnd. 4515 by the Ministry of Technology. Thefigures for R and D in SCTO (70) 3 Revise, there-fore, cannot yet be amended to take account ofthe savings.3. In the case of some programmes there maybe minor inconsistencies in the treatment of theR and D estimates compared with those for public expenditure generally; these inconsistencies shouldbe removed before the 1971 Survey.  million at 1970 Survey prices1970-71estimate1971-72estimate1972-73estimate1973-74estimate1974-75estimate	Intramural	Total Intramural		Total Intramural		Total	Intramural	Total Intramural		Total		227-6	95-7	254-7	95-4			255-4	93-8	246-defence Budget*.      .      .      .	91-8					249-7	96-6			Overseas aid                  .      .	1-7	3-7	1-9	3-8	2-1	4-1	2-3	4-5	2-6	4-9Agriculture, fisheries and forestry .	7-8	8-7	7-6	8-6	7-3	8-5	7-3	8-6	7-6  ,	9-0Research Councils, etc.	50-2	101-4	511	106-6	55-4	111-8	57-3	1170	59-1	121-6Trade, industry and employment!.	78-4	176-5	79-5	160-1	72-2	134-2	63-7	111-3	60-1	105-2Roads and public lighting   .	2-2	3-0	2-6	3-8	3-6	5-3	4-9	7-3	5-9	9-3Transport.....	1-2	3-0	1-6	5-2	1-4	5-8	1-5	6-9	1-8	7-housing   .	-	^!	0-1	0-1	0-1	0-1	0-1	01	01	01Miscellaneous local services .	1-1	1-3	1-8	2-1	1-6	1-9	1-7	2-0	1-7	2-0Law and order  .      .      .      .	1-0	2-5	1-2	3-1	1-3	3-4	. 1-4	3-2	1-5	3-2Education.....	&apos;   .&quot;	0-9	&apos;&apos; &apos;-	0-9	 	1-2	 	1-5	^  M-	1-4Health and welfare	0-8	9-3	0-8	9-8	0-7	11-7	0-7	10-8	0-6	9-2Social security   .      .      .      .	-   &apos;	0-1	 	0-2		0-2	  -	0-2		0-2Common services	2-2	2-9	2-3	3-1	2-4	3-5	2-5	3-6	2-5	3-8Total   .      .      .      .	238-4	540-9	246-2	562-1	243-5	541-4	240-1	532-4	237-3	523-8* The estimates for these programmes do not take account of the savings in expenditure on civil research and development by the former Ministry of Technology included in the total savings by that Ministry announced in Cmnd. 4515.f The expenditure for 1971-72 to 1974-75 falls to be met within the Defence Budget targets approved by Ministers for eachof those years.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy No. 068- -   . - - .-,-&apos;!!    -vWl-I; -    -: ...PUBLICEXPENDITURETO 1974-75Appendix: Part FourStatistical Supplement1970 Report by the Public expenditure survey CommitteeDecember 1970
PUBLICEXPENDITURETO 1974-75Appendix: Part FourStatistical Supplementii1970 Report by the Public expenditure survey CommitteeDecember 1970I -:-^ THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government copy No. 060
CONFIDENTIAL1dPUBLIC EXPENDITURE TO 1974-75APPENDIX TO1970 REPORT BY THE PUBLIC EXPENDITURE SURVEYCOMMITTEECONTENTSPART FOUR.   STATISTICAL SUPPLEMENTPageTable 1.  Summary analysis by programme......... stable 2.   Summary analysis by economic category........ 4Table 3.  Summary analysis by spending authority   . -....... 4Table 4.  Analysis by programme and PESC category      .      .      .      .      ... 5Table 5.  Analysis by programme and economic category....... 9Table 6. (Analysis by programme and spending authority....... 15Table 7.  Analysis of gross domestic fixed capital formation by programme and category of asset......:.......19
APPENDIXPART FOURSTATISTICAL SUPPLEMENTTABLE summary analysis of public expenditure by programme: 1969-70 to 1974-75   million1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn at 1970 Survey prices defence and external relations .  Defence Budget    .      .      .      .      . 2,398-92.  Other military defence   .      .      .      . 91-13.  Overseas aid...... 203-54.  Other overseas services .      .      .      . 127-1Commerce and industry. Agriculture, fisheries and forestry   .      . 373-56.  Research Councils, etc..... 100-97.  Trade, industry and employment   .      . 1,174-4Nationalised industries capital expenditure.  Fuel     .             ....      . 744-59. Steel    ...      .            .      . -106010.  Post Office...... 405-411.  Airways and airports    .      .      .      . 71-412.  Surface transport..... 118-9Transport and miscellaneous local services13. Roads and public lighting     .      .      . 656-314. Transport     .      .      .      .      .      . 237-115.  Housing...... 1,071-816.  Miscellaneous local services   .      .      . 797-117.  Law and order..... 632-918. Arts....... 18-5iSocial services19.  Education...... 2,448-620. Health and welfare      .... 1,938-521.  Social security      .      .      .      .      . 3,770-other services22.  Financial administration        .      .      . 238-723. Common services .      .      .      .      . 172-724.  Miscellaneous services   .      .      .      . 67-925.  Northern Ireland..... 442-026. Debt interest...... 2,186-027.  Contingency reserve      ....  28.  Shortfall:a. Nationalised industries&apos; capitalexpenditureb. Other   .      .      .29. Relative price effect and other adjustments2,387-0	2,327	0	2,270	0	2,290-0	2,300-047-9	50	6	42	6	45-0 -	53-0207-0	212	8	222	2	239-0	256-0129-4	129	3	130	0	130-2	131-2461-6	437	3	408	5	355-4	312-4109-6	114	7	119	8	124-5	128-81,125-0	1,118	4	831	1	635-9	518-3761-4	701	1	686	0	729-4	814-21350	189	0	188	0	206-0	195-0465 0	507	3	541	6	561-0	565-8151-7	140	8	136	2	135-2	186-6138-2	132	8	144	5	145-6	148-3745-4	774	0	841	9	892-3	945-1240-3	248	8	249	3	248-2	238-91,143-9	1,179	0	1,189	0	1,150-3	1,125-4845-8	845	8	891	4	946-7	994-9686-2	727	2	762	1	814-3	854-621-7	24	9	24	6	25-2	25-92,523-0	2,653	1	2,739	7	2,800-5	2,872-42,009-5	2,061	8	2,130	7	2,211-8	2,286-23,864-9	3,947	7	4,059	8	4,186-6	4,247-5235-3	230	7	234	4	234-4	236-2203-7	221	3	244	2	263-2	279-782-5	86	7	82	2	82-9	86-1483-3	488	1	501	0	509-9	521-42,103-0	1,980	0	1,950	0	1,890-0	1,8100 	90	0	130-0		1800	245-0-1500-200-0856-8-175-0-100-0968-4-1500-100-01,155-1-1500-10001,364-5-150-0-100-01,570-9At 1970-71 outturn prices30.  Total.......    21,198-1     21,814-1     22,313-6    22,655-9    23,148-0    23,699-confidential
TABLE summary analysis of public expenditure by economic category: 1969-70 to 1974-75  million	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					At 1970 Survey prices						Wages and salaries    .      .      .	4,894-8	5,024-4	5,146-7	5,263-7	5,420-2	5,566-5Selective employment tax.....	318-0	325-0	333-1	341-0	348-2	355-other current expenditure on goods and services	3,019-2	3,079-9	3,019-0	3,059-6	3,143-5	3,203-5Subsidies........	854-7	926-1	905-8	860-2	770-1	649-7Debt interest......	2,186-0	2,103-0	1,980 0	1,950 0	1,890 0	1,810-current grants to persons   .....	3,998-5	4,109-8	4,204-8	4,317-5	4,437-5	4,515-current grants to private bodies  ....	292-4	309-1	330-2	350-1	375-5	407-3Current grants abroad       .      .	177-9	176-8	168-8	173-5	183-5	195-3Gross domestic fixed capital formation .	3,846-3	4,187-1	4,367-3	4,514-4	4,614-7	4,794-increase in value of stocks .....	11-8	21-0	36-5	44-5	74-4	59-capital grants to private sector   ....	826-8	791-4	844-7	558-8	423-6	372-net lending to private sector	46-2	125-3	110-9	58-0	51-3	60-4Loans to overseas governments   .      .      .	80-1	80-6	611	56-3	59-4	65-0Drawings from United Kingdom subscriptions to						international lending bodies     .      .      .	15-1	150	34-0	43-8	48-4	51-other net lending and investment abroad	8-0	21-3	21-3	22-2	9-2	22-8Cash expenditure on company securities (net).	18-4	11-5	-34-0	7-2	4-0	4-0Contingency reserve   ......	 	 	900	1300	1800	245-0Shortfall:						Nationalised industries -      .      .      .	 -	-1500	-175-0	-1500	-1500	-150-other.      .      .      .      .      .      .	 	-200-0	-1000	-1000	-1000	-100-0Relative price effect and other adjustments	603-9	856-8	968-4	1,155-1	1,364-5	1,570-9At 1970-71 outturn prices						Total    .      .      .      .	21,198-1	21,814-1	22,313-6	22,655-9	23,148-0	23,699-8TABLE summary analysis of public expenditure by spending authority: 1969-70 to 1974-75  million	1969-70 provisional outturn	1970-71 estimate	1971-72 estimate	1972-73 estimate	1973-74 estimate	1974-75 estimate at 1970 Survey prices						Central government:						Votes (GB) .      .      .      ...	8,646-4	8,877-6	8,967-7	8,712-6	8,659-6	8,607-2National Insurance Funds (GB)	2,726-6	2,806-4	2,867-1	3,007 0	3,118-1	3,186-other .      .      .      .      .      .      i!	305-7	327-5	321-4	310-6	298-4 I	330-0Total central government .	11,678-7	12,011-5	12,156-2	12,030-2	12,076-1	12,1240Local authorities.....	5,070-0	5,313-4	5,506-2	5,703-6	5,880 0	6,051-8New towns	92-0	106-7	112-6	122-7	123-8	123-other public corporations   .      .	113-2	119-2	99-0	104-5	900	97-0Nationalised industries      .      .      .	1,454-3	1,653-5	1,676-2	1,709-8	1,793-6	1,927-6Total    .ii    ...	18,408-2	19,204-3	19,550-2	19,670-8	19,963-5	20,323-9Debt interest     .      .      .	2,186-0	2,103 0	1,980-0	1,950 0	1,890 0	1,810-0Contingency reserve.....		 	90-0	130 0	1800	245-0Shortfall:						a. Nationalised industries&apos; capital expenditure	-	-1500	-175-0	-150-0	-1500	-150-0b. Other       .      .      .      .      .		-200-0	-1000	-1000	-1000	-100-0Relative price effect and other adjustments	603-9	856-8	968-4	1,155-1	1,364-5	1,570-9At 1970-71 outturn prices Total    .      .      .	21,198-1	21,814-1	22,313-6	22,655-9	1 ! 23,148-0	23,699-8
TABLE 4Analysis of public expenditure by programme and PESC category: 1969-70 to 1974-75   million			1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75			provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate			outturn						At 1970 Survey prices							1.	Defence Budget   ....		2,398-9	2,387-0	2,327-0	2,270-0	2,290-0	2,300-02.	Other military defence								United States military aircraft (net)		-11-9	-40-2	-43-2	-49-1	-46-4	-38-4	Allied services .      .      .      .		94-5	960	94-2	90-2	90-2	90-2	Military aid           .		8-3	5-7	3-0	1-9	1-7	1-7	Other military defence		0-2	-13-6	-3-4	-0-4	-0-5	-0-5	Total.....		91-1	47-9	50-6	42-6	45-0	5303.	Overseas aid       ....		203-5	207-0	212-8	222-2	239 0	256-04.	Other overseas services								Overseas representation, etc.		61-3	63-8	65-4	66-1	65-7	65-9	Overseas information		30-4	31-5	30-9	31-4	31-1	31-1	Other external relations		35-4	34-1	33-0	32-5	33-4	34-2	Total    ....		127-1	129-4	129-3	130-0	130-2	131-25.	Agriculture, fisheries and forestry								Agricultural support .		275-5	335-0	303-0	268-0	212-0	164-0	Other assistance to agriculture   .		48-7	70-7	75-6	79-0	78-4	79-2	Fisheries .      .		7-3	10-6	10-3	10-1	9-8	9-9	Forestry.....		42-0	45-3	49-0	51-4	55-2	59-3	Total    ....		373-5 .	461-6	437-3	408-5	355-4	312-46.	Research Councils, etc.		100-9	109-6	114-7	119-8	124-5	128-87.	Trade, industry and employment								Department of Trade and Industry:								General services		990	105-2	99-1	97-0	94-7	90-7	Promotion of local employment		45-6	48-9	57-3	65-8	69-8	73-6	Investment grants .		573-4	504-0	552-0	261-0	126 0	65-0	Assistance to coal industry		24-8	26-6	17-5	15-0	13-0	8-0	Industrial Reorganisation Corporation		30-2	25-0	0-5	-2-5	-7-0	-4-0	Other services		27-8	57-7	&quot;    39-7	37-2	11-0	300	Ministry of Aviation Supply:								Civil expenditure  .		117-1	110-8	106-7	114-6	96-6	57-2	Department   of Employment   and	other							expenditure								Employment services		71-2	76-6	78-5	81-8	83-7	85-5	Redundancy Fund payments  .		38-2	42-7	43-5	39-0	32-2	32-2	SET additional payments		28-5	7-0	10	0-1	 	-	I    Regional employment premiums		109-0	106-2	106-2	106-2	106-2	72-2	Productivity services		6-3	8-6	8-9	8-2	7-7	7-6	Covent Garden Market Authority	capital							expenditure      &apos;.		3-3	5-7	7-5	7-7 &apos;	2-0	0-3	Total    .      .      .      .		1,174-4	1,125-0	1,118-4	831-1	635-9	518-38.	Fuel   .      .      .		744-5	761-4	701-1	686-0	729-4	814-29.	Steel......		106-0	135-0	189-0	188-0	206-0	195-010.	Post Office .      .      .      .      .		405-4	465-0	507-3	541-6	561-0	565-811.	Airways and airports		71-4	151-7	140-8	136-2	135-2	186-612.	Surface transport ....		118-9	138-2	132-8	144-5	145-6	148-confidential 5
Part Four: Statistical Supplement					CONFIDENTIAL	TABLE 4 (continued)						  million	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					At 1970 Survey prices						13. Roads and public lighting						Major roads new works, etc.   .	360-6	421-5	429-3	473-1	502-7	532-major roads maintenance	54-8	63-9	70-2	76-6	75-2	78-other roads new works, etc.	46-9	43-1	44-2	46-9	56-8	60-other roads maintenance ....	104-2	116-6	122-9	131-5	138-5	148-8Lighting, car parks, etc.    .      .	53-4	52-4	56-0	59-2	72-0	76-administration......	36-4	47-9	51-4	54-6	47-1	48-6Total    .     . &apos;   .     .      .	656-3	745-4	774-0	841-9	892-3	945-114. Transport						Department of the Environment/SDD/Welsh						Office:						Support to nationalised transport industries						-British Rail.....	88-2	75-3	67-6	57-7	53-8	49-0Support to nationalised transport industries						 other    .      .      .      .	30-1	18-2	17-3	12-7	8-0	5-other passenger transport	36-6	59-1	61-9	66-5	64-7	65-1Infrastructure expenditure	10-2	100	14-6	24-0	30-4	33-2Ports   .      .    n\      .	33-8	36-1	37-9	36-2	34-2	33-miscellaneous services   .      ...	4-2	50	7-6	8-5	10-5	12-6Departmental administration .	11-8	11-7	12-2	12-5	12-6	12-civil aviation services      .      .	25-4	31-4	33-7	35-5	36-5	30-other surface transport    ....	-3-2	-6-5	-40	-4-3	-2-5	-2-3Total    .:&apos;(&apos;.      .               ^	237-1	240-3	248-8	249-3	248-2	238-915. Housing						Subsidies .      .      .      ...	265-1	318-3	356-4	360-2	327-9	301-1Improvement grants .      .      .      .      .	17-7	20-9	27-0	30-0	33-3	37-1Investment      ......	804-8	746-6	765-4	768-4	766-3	767-net lending     .      .	-17-3	56-5	28-6	28-7	21-1	18-departmental administration	1-5	1-6	1-6	1-7	1-7	1-7Total    .      .      .      .      .	1,071-8	1,143-9	1,179-0	1,189-0	1,150-3	1,125-416. Miscellaneous local services						Water supply and conservation .	74-6	80-6	82-3	87-9	89-9	93-7Sewerage.....a	183-8	205-7	214-9	226-6	.   248-9	264-9Refuse disposal       ......	110-3	113-7	126-5	134-9	132-6	138-other public health services	54-1	55-3	57-3	59-7	60-7	62-land drainage .      .      ...	20-3	21-3	30-6	35-8	34-3	45-2Parks, swimming baths, sport, etc.	83-4	82-3	87-1	90-7	88-7	91-1Town and country planning	79-7	81-1	73-1	74-1	82-2	86-1Unallocated local government administration	101-1	105-7	74-6	76-4	106-3	107-other local expenditure    ....	76-7	86-4	84-1	89-9	87-9	89-departmental administration	13-1	13-7	15-3	15-4	15-2	15-4Total    .      .      .      !i	797-1	845-8	845-8	891-4	946-7	994-9
CONFIDENTIAL			Fart Four : Statistical Supplement			TABLE 4 (continued)						  million	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					At 1970 Survey prices						17. Law and order						Home Departments&apos; services:						Police  .      .      .      .      ...	303-0	325-7	342-3	350-3	376-7	392-7Prisons.......	53-1	58-2	65-6	75-1	82-6	88-1Probation and after care ....	10-9	120	12-6	14-2	15-6	16-8Child care......	61-5	64-5	68-7	72-4	76-7	79-social work, Scotland    ....	19-4	20-5	23-1	24-7 &quot;	25-9	27-3Fire services ......	69-9	74-1	77-0	78-0	800	81-other services.....	39-2	45-4	46-2	48-7	50-8	52-departmental administration .	11-4	12-7	13-8	14-9	15-9	16-9Parliament and law courts ....	64-2	710	77-6	83-6	89-9	99 0Parliamentary election expenses .	0-3	21	0-3	0-2	0-2	0-2Total......	632-9	686-2	727-2	762-1	814-3	854-618. Arts						National libraries and museums .	8-8	10-2	10-9	10-6	11-2	11-other arts       .	,     9-7	11-5	14-0	,14-0	14-0	14-3Total    .     .	18-5	21-7	24-9	24-6	25-2	25-919. Education						Education:						Schools capital.....	223-6	229-0	273-9 &apos;	266-0	235-0	193-2Schools current primary	461-7	472-3	505-9	.527-4	535-6	539-9Schools current secondary .	518-1	535-9	575-6	606-8	661-6	705-2Schools current other	133-9	138-0	143-0	147-3	153-7	158-7Further education.....	304-0	317-9	332-3	341-7&apos;	332-7	340-9Teacher training.....	112-1	116-7	120-5	121-5	123-5	125-6Universities......	326-8	341-1	355-3	376-7	405-3	447-0Youth service, etc. .	27-6	29-0	30-7	32-0	33-5	34-other educational expenditure	94-9	97-2	99-5	101-9	103-8	105-8School meals.....	91-6	85-5	69-8	69-1	61-5	61-9School milk......	14-0	14-5	8-8	60	5-9	5-7Administration     .....	76-4	79-1	83-5	86-8	89-7	92-3Statistical adjustments England and Wales .	 	 	-15-5	-16-1	-16-8	-17-local libraries and museums	63-9	66-8	69-8	72-6	75-5	78-9Total    .    ,.     .     .      .     .	2,448-6	2,523-0	2,653 -1	2,739-7	2,800-5	2,872-420. Health and welfare						National Flealth Service:						Hospitals......	1,161-5	1,215-7	1,279-0	1,335-1 .	1,377-9	1,419-6Executive councils .....	425-7	439-1	424-9	418-1	430-1	441-other central services and grants	22-8	25-3	27-1	.   28-5	29-8	30-9Local health authority services	195-2	195-9	206-5	215-5	240-3	254-2Departmental administration .	12-2	12-8	13-5	14-3	14-8	15-5Welfare foods......	41-1	41-4	15-3	10-5	10-6	10-8Local welfare services      ....	80-0	79-3	95-5	108-7	108-3	113-3-   &apos;        Total    .      .      .	1,938-5	2,009-5	2,061-8	2,130-7	2,211-8	2,286-2						CONFIDENTIAL						711297 b* 2
Part Four: Statistical Supplement	confidential table 4 (continued)	  million1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional    estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn at 1970 Survey prices21. Social securityInsurance funds:Retirement pensions	.     1,739-0	1,781-0	1,821-0	1,919-0	2,005	0	2,064-0Sickness benefits   ....	4130	418-0	414-0	437-0	444	0	451-0Unemployment benefits .	1360	160-0	1560	134-0	137	0	139-other national insurance benefits	227-0	231-0	260 0	290-0	291	0	293-0Industrial injuries benefits	112-0	113-0	1100	115-0	118	0	120 0War pensions   .     &apos;&apos;.      .      .	133-8	.128-9	123-5	121-9	118	5	113-5Supplementary benefits	503-0	538-2	578-8	560-1	579	8	585-9Family allowances    ....	362-0	345-0	330-0	321-0	320	0	310-administration .	144-7	149-8	154-4	161-8	173	3	171-1Total    .      ...	.     3,770-5	3,864-9	3,947-7	4,059-8	4,186	6	4,247-522. Financial administration	Tax and rate collection     ....	179-5	184-9	186-9	189-9	192-5	193-1	Other financial administration	40-7	31-9	26-3	28-0	26-4	27-1	Post-war credits.....	18-5	18-5	17-5	16-5	15-5	16-0	Total......	238-7	235-3	230-7	234-4	234-4	236-223.	Common services		: v					Superannuation.....	77-7	81-5	84-2	90-6	94-5	98-7	Accommodation (home)    .      .      .	146-4	164-8	175-1	184-8	195-9	204-7	Stationery Office (home)   ....	34-5	42-6	460	48-0	52-0	56-0	COI (home)......	8-6	10-8	10-2	110	11 0	10-5	Allied services (defence)    ....	-94-5	-96 0	-94-2	-90-2	-90-2	-90-2	Total                        .      .      .	172-7	203-7	221-3	244-2	263-2	279-724.	Miscellaneous services							Records, registrations, etc. .      .      .      .	23-5	24-3	31-8	26-8	26-6	;   27-4	Meteorological services     ....	7-4	7-7	11-6	8-4	8-1	7-9	Civil defence......	1-4	7-2	8-5	9-1	9-7	9-1	Royal parks, historic buildings, etc.    .      .	3-7	4-1	4-6	4-9	5-1	5-3	Broadcasting authorities&apos; capital expenditure	14-3	18-3	15-9	15-5	13-5	16-3	Other miscellaneous services	17-6	20-9	14-3	17-5	19-9	20-1	Total    .     .            .   , .	67-9	82-5	86-7	82-2	82-9	86-125.	Northern Ireland ......	442 0	483-3	488-1	501-0	509-9	521-426.	Debt interest......	2,186 0	2,103-0	1,980-0	1,950-0	1,890-0	1,810-027.	Contingency reserve     .      .      - //    -	-	-	900	1300	1800	245-028.	Shortfall							a. Nationalised industries&apos; capital expenditure	s        S:	-1500	-175-0	-150-0	-1500	-1500	b. Other .     .      .      .      .      .      .	- \j	-200-0	-100-0	-1000	-1000	-100-029.	Relative price effect and other adjustments	603-9	856-8	968-4	LI 55-1	1,364-5	1,570-9	At 1970-71 outturn prices						30.	Total.......      .	21,198-1	21,814-1	22,313-6	22,655-9	23,148-0	23,699-8
TABLE 5Analysis of public expenditure by programme and economic category: 1969-70 to 1974-75   million1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional    estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn at 1970 Survey prices. Defence BudgetWages and salaries.....	1,194-6	1,185-4	1,146-2	1,106-6	1,108-4	1,099-2Selective Employment Tax	32-0	32-4	32-8	32-6	32-1	31-other current expenditure, goods and services	1,144-0	-.1,133-1	1,105-7	1,089-7	1,108-7	1,128-3Current grants to private bodies	01	0-1	0-1	0-1	0-1	0-current grants abroad     ....	5-8	7-4	8-2	8-4	8-0	8-gross domestic fixed capital formation .	21 0	27-8	31-1	29-7	29-8	29-6Increase in value of stocks	-1-8	-2-3	0-0	0-0	0-0	00Capital grants to private sector	0-8	0-7	0-7	0-7	0-7	0-net lending to private sector   .	2-4	2-4	2-2	2-2	2-2	2-other net lending and investment abroad	00	0-0	0-0	0-0	0-0	00Total    .   &apos; V    .                   ;	2,398-9	2,387-0	2,327-0	2,270-0	2,290-0	2,300 02. Other military defenceWages and salaries......	-4-8	-4-9	-4	9	-4-8	-4-8	-4-8Selective Employment Tax	-0-4	-0-4	-0	4	-0-4	-0-4	-0-other current expenditure, goods and services	90-2	47-6	53	0	46-0	48-6	56-current grants abroad     ....	6-5	4-9	&apos;/    3	3,	2-2	2-0	2-gross domestic fixed capital information	-21	0-0	0	0	0-0	0-0	0-0Loans to overseas governments	1-7	0-7	-0	4	-0-4	-0-4	-0-4Total           .....	91-1	47-9	50	6	42-6	45-0	53-03. Overseas aidWages and salaries.....	1-4	00	0	0	00	0-0	0-0Selective Employment Tax	0-1	0-0	0	0	0-0	0-0	0-other current expenditure, goods and services	-1-5	0-0	0	0	0-0	0-0	0-current grants to persons ....	1-7	1-8	13	5	12-9	12-4	12-current grants to private bodies	0-4	0-0	0	0	00	00	0-current grants abroad     ....	99-3	99-7	92	3	93-7	100-9	110-0Loans to overseas governments .	78-4	79-7	61	7	57-2	60-5	66-2Drawings from United Kingdom subscriptions							to international lending bodies	15-1	15-0	34	0	43-8	48-4	51-other net lending and investment abroad	8-6	10-8	11	3	14-6	16-8	16-5Total    .            .      : ,   .	203-5	207-0	212	8	222-2	239-0	256-04. Other overseas servicesWages and salaries .      .      .      .      .	39-9	40-3	40-2	40-1	40-0	40-0Selective Employment Tax      .     .      .	1-2	1-2	1-2	1-3	1-3	1-other current expenditure, goods and services	64-6	66-5	67-7	68-7	68-9	69-current grants to persons	4-4	4-3	4-1	4-1	4-1	4-current grants to private bodies	0-4	0-4	0-4	0-4	0-4	0-current grants abroad     ....	13-9	13-7	13-3	13-5	14-1	14-gross domestic fixed capital formation .	0-9	1-3	1-7	1-7	1-4	1-2Capital grants to private sector       .      .	1-7	1-1	0-7	0-3	0-3	0-net lending to private sector   .	-0-2	-0-1	0-0	00	0-0	0-0Loans to overseas governments	0-0	-0-4	-0-7	-10	-1-2	-1-other net lending and investment abroad	0-3	1-1	&apos; 0-7	0-9	0-9	1-1Total    .     v&quot;     .  : :..    .	127-1	129-4	129-3	1300	130-2	131-confidential 9
Part Four: Statistical Supplement					CONFIDENTIAL	TABLE 5 (continued)						  million					1973-74		1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73		1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn											At 1970 Survey prices						5. Agriculture, fisheries and forestry						Wages and salaries .      .      .     .	47-3	46-4	47-1	47-5	47-7	47-9Selective Employment Tax	3-6	3-1	3-2	3-3	3-3	3-other current expenditure, goods and services	-5-1	-0-7	-0-6	-0-5	-0-2	0-0Subsidies .      .      . \	240-1	306-6	274-2	248-0	199-1	149-current grants to persons	01	01	0-1	0-1	0-1	0-current grants to private bodies	2-8	3-3	3-9	4-5	4-7	4-9Current grants abroad	1-2	1-1	1-1	1-1	11	1-gross domestic fixed capital formation .	6-4	10-1	11-9	14-7	13-1	13-7Increase in value of stocks	34-7	38-2	41-4	43-8	47-7	51-5Capital grants to private sector	42-9	53-4	54-8	45-7.	38-4	40-net lending to private sector   .      .      .	-0-5	00	0-2	0-3	0-4	0-4Total     .              .   (]         .      .	373-5	461-6	437-3	408-5	355-4	312-46. Research Councils, etc.					... ti-	Wages and salaries .      .      .     .      .	21-0	22-6	23-4	24-4 :	25-3	26-4Selective Employment Tax	1-0	1-1	1-1	1-2	1-3	1-other current expenditure, goods and services	16-5	19-8	21-1	22-0	22-9	23-current grants to persons        .      .      .	9-7	10-9	11-6	11-8	12-2	12-current giants to private bodies	22-1	22-8	24-1	25-4	26-4	27-3Current grants abroad     .	12-5	12-5	13-0	13-5	14-1	14-6Gross domestic fixed capital formation .	12-7	13-5	13-8	14-5	15-0	15-5Capital grants to private sector	5-4	6-4	6-6	7-0	7-3	7-5Total    .      ....     -.	100-9	109-6	114-7	119-8	124-5	128-87. Trade, industry and employment						Wages and salaries .	123-3	125-5	127-6	131-1	135-4	137-9Selective Employment Tax	90	8-2	8-5	8-7	8-9	9-other current expenditure, goods and services	87-0	110-8	93-7	106-6	80-8 &apos;	35-8Subsidies.......	179-5	156-3	138-3	130-6	129-9	92-current grants to persons	50-9	56-8	57-5 &apos;	54-1	47-8	48-current grants to private bodies	5-2	5-5	5-6	5-5	5-5	5-current grants abroad     ....	8-7	6-6	5-4	6-5	7-8	8-9Gross domestic fixed capital formation .	45-9	48-5	61-2	57-3	46-2	40-increase in value of stocks	4-0	7-6	0-0	0-0	0-0	1     -5-capital grants to private sector	599-3	540-1	588-4	306-6	173-7	116-net lending to private sector   .	59-5	60-9	71-7	20-4	15-0	28-2Loans to overseas governments .	00	0-6	0-5	0-5	0-5	0-other net lending and investment abroad	-7-8	-3-9	0-0	0-0	-15-6	0-0Cash expenditure on company securities (net)	9-9	1-5	-40-0	3-2	0-0	0-0Total    .      .      .      .     .	1,174-4	1,125-0	1,118-4	831-1	635-9	518-38. Fuel						Gross domestic fixed capital formation	783-5	778-8	700-8	685-2	715-3	.   803-increase in value of stocks	-44-7	-28-9	-10-6	-7-0	1-9	-0-net lending to private sector   .	3-0	7-5	6-9	4-8	9-2	8-3Cash expenditure on company securities (net)	2-7	4-0	4-0	3-0	3;0	3-0-Total    .&quot; &quot;.&apos;     . 1 &apos;.     .   1 : &apos;	744-5	761-4	701-1	686-0	729-4	814-2
TABLE 5 (continued)  million1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn at 1970 Survey prices9. SteelGross domestic fixed capital formation . 81-0 130-0 185-0 184-0 185-0 185-0Increase in value of stocks      .      . . 23-0 5-0 3-0 4-0 21-0 10-0Net lending to private sector   .      . . 0-0 0-0 0-0 0-0 0-0 0-other net lending and investment abroad . 0-0 0-0 0-0 0-0 0-0 0-0Cash expenditure on company securities (net) 2-0 0-0 1-0 0-0 0-0 0-0Total    .      .      . .      .       106-0        135 0        189-0        188 0        206 0        195-010. Post OfficeGross domestic fixed capital formation . 389-1 459-5 504-1 537-9 557-8 563-increase in value of stocks      .      . . 10-9 0-7 0-0 0-2 0 0 0-other net lending and investment abroad . 5-4 4-8 3-2 3-5 3-2 2-3Total    ......       405-4        465-0        507-3        541-6        561-0        565-811. Airways and airportsGross domestic fixed capital formation. .         70-1 143-7 134-9 133-2 131-5 183-net lending to private sector   . 0-0 0-0 0-0 0-0 0-0 0-other net lending and investment abroad .          1-3 8-0 5-9 3-0 3-7 2-7Total    ...... 71-4        151-7        140-8        136-2        135-2        186-612. Surface transportGross domestic fixed capital formation .      . 126-6 133-8 131-7 ,     143-3 144-4 147-0Increase in value of stocks      .      .      . -12-0 -2-1 -0-1 0 0 0 0 0-net lending to private sector   .      .      . 0-3 0-0 0-0 0-0 0-0 0-other net lending and investment abroad     . 0-2 0-5 0-2 0-2 0-2 0-2Cash expenditure on company securities (net) 3-8 6-0 1-0 1-0 1-0 1-0Total    .      .      .      .      .      ,       118-9        138-2        132-8        144-5        145-6        148-313. Roads and public lightingWages and salaries .      .      .      .      . 94-1 105-6 111-4 118-5 123-3 130-1Selective Employment Tax       . 8-4 8-6 8-9           9-0 9-2           9-other current expenditure, goods and services 124-3 144-2 154-7 166-2 165-9 175-current grants to private bodies      .      . 0-1 0-2 0-6           1-1 1-9           2-9Gross domestic fixed capital formation .      . 429-4 486-8 498-4 547-1 592-0 627-3Total    .      .      .   &quot; i.&apos;.     .      .       656-3        745-4        774-0        841-9        892-3        945-114. Transport,    ,  . 22-4 22-7          23-0          23-4          23-6          23-7Wagesandsalar.es         .... 22 4 ui                                        ^          igSelective Employment Tax             .      - 15 i other current expenditure, goods and services -7-8 -by          ^             &quot; &apos;.Subsidies.             ..... 153 8 131-3        125-7        110-5        102-3          95 3Current grants to private bodies      .      - 0-4 0-4           0-4                           ^           ^Current grants abroad     .      .      -      - 3-0 3-2           3*Gross domestic fixed capital formation.      . 68-3 96 1         105-0        119.-3        125-0        123 1Capital grants to private sector . . 2-0 2-3 ^ ^Net lending to private sector   ...Total    .&apos;    .      .      .      .      .       237-1        240-3        248-8        249-3        248-2        238-confidential 1111297c* 2
Part Four: Statistical Supplement	confidential table 5 (continued)	  million1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn at 1970 Survey prices15. HousingWages and salaries.....	1-6	1-6	1	6	1-6	1-6	1-6Selective Employment Tax      .      .    - .&apos;	0 0	0-1	0	1	0-1	0-1	0-other current expenditure, goods and services	-0-1	00	-0	1	00	0-0	0-0Subsidies.......	255-9	304-7	341	0	342-8	308-4	279-current grants to persons       .      .      :	9-2	13-6	15	4	17-4	19-5	21-gross domestic fixed capital formation .	804-8	746-5	765	4	768-4	766-3	767-1Capital grants to private sector	17-7	20-9	27	0	30-0	33-3	37-net lending to private sector	-17-3	56-5	28	6	28-7	21-1	18-4Total    .      ....!!&apos;.....	1,071-8	1,143-9	1,179	0	1,189-0	1,150-3	1,125-4liscellaneous local services							Wages and salaries         ....	373-1	389-9	405	3	422-8	439-0	456-4Selective Employment Tax	33-1	33-7	34	5	35-1	35-8	36-other current expenditure, goods and services	200	21-1	-5	5	-5-9	7-6	6-5Current grants to private bodies	1-0	1-3	1	3	1-3	1-4	1-gross domestic fixed capital formation	362-2	390-4	400	3	428-2	453-0	483-capital grants to private sector	6-5	6-5	7	8	7-8	7-8	7-net lending to private sector	1-2	2-9	2	1	2-1	2-1	2-2Total    ......	797-1	845-8	845	8	891-4	946-7	994-917. Law and orderWages and salaries .....	401-5	424-5	442-9	458-2	487-3	511-6Selective Employment Tax      .      .      .	35-5	36-4	37-3	38-1	39-0	40-other current expenditure, goods and services	119-9	128-4	139-2	147-4	154-0	162-3Current grants to persons	17-7	19-2	21-0	23-3	27-3	29-current grants to private bodies	5-9	6-3	6-5	6-6	6-7	6-6Gross domestic fixed capital formation	51-4	70-2	79-4	87-7	99-1	103-7Capital grants to private sector	1-0	1-2	0-9	0-8	0-9	0-8Total    .      .      .      .							632-9	686-2	727-2	762-1	814-3,	854-618.   ArtsWages and salaries .      .	6-1	6-4	6-8	7-5	7-9	8-4Selective Employment Tax	0-2	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-other current expenditure, goods and services	21	2-6	2-9	1-9	1-9	1-9Current grants to private bodies    1 .	8-9	10-2	12-1	12-2	13-31	14-capital grants to private sector	1-2	2-2	2-8	2-7	1-8	0-7Total    .      .      .      .	18-5	21-7	24-9	24-6	25-2	25-9Education						Wages and salaries .      .      .      .	1,210-5	1,249-9	1,306-9	1,365-1	1,405-5	1,453-4Selective Employment Tax	93-1	94-9	96-8	98-8	100-7	102-other current expenditure, goods and services	374-5	377-1	377-9	389-2	414-2	431-2Current grants to persons .	160-2	1680	175-8	183-9	189-1	197-2Current grants to private bodies	233-8	246-1	261-2	277-8	299-1	326-current grants abroad	0-3	01	0-0	0-0	0-0 ,	0-gross domestic fixed capital formation .	274-0	281-5	325-0	311-9	277-1	244-capital grants to private sector	100-4	103.1	106-2	109-7	111-9	115-0Net lending to private sector   .	1-8	2-3	3-3	3-3	I2&apos;9 i	1-9Total    .      .      .      .            .	2,448-6	2,523 0	2,653-1	2,739-7	2,800-5	2,872-4
tCONFIDENTIAL			Part Four: Statistical Supplement			TABLE 5 (continued)						  million	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					At 1970 Survey prices						20.   Health and welfare					. il il-	Wages and salaries .      .      .      .      .	896-0	909-4	951-4	993-7	1,040-1	1,081-0Selective Employment Tax	71-7	73-7	76-2	79-3	81-7	84-other current expenditure, goods and services	791-9	836-2	815-1	819-4	845-9	874-current grants to persons	5-3	5-5	5-9	61	6-3	6-5Current grants to private bodies	0-4	0-6	1-0	1-2	1-4	1-current grants abroad     .      .	1-6	1-7	1-9	2-0	2-2	2-gross domestic fixed capital formation .	1690	179-9	208-0	227-6	233-0	234-8Capital grants to private sector	2-9	2-7	2-5	1-6	1-4	1- net lending to private sector   .	-0-3	-0-2	-6-2	-0-2	-0-2	-0-2Total    .            .      .      ....   .	1,938-5	2,009-5	2,061-8	2,130-7	2,211-8	2,286-221. Social security						Wages and salaries .....	71-9	78-1	81-0	83-7	86-2	87-2Selective Employment Tax	5-6	5-8	60	6-3	6-6	6-other current expenditure, goods and services	67-7	66-5	680	72-4	81-1	77-9Current grants to persons       .      .      .	3,600-5	3,688-9	3,766-1	3,868-7	3,983-0	4,045-current grants abroad	24-8	25-6	26-6	28-7	29-7	30-4Total    .      .      .     &apos;..     -    ....	3,770-5&apos;	3,864-9	3,947-7	4,059-8	4,186-6	4,247-5i 22. Financial&apos; administration						Wages and salaries .....	147-4	158-5	161-1	163-5	165-1	166-5Selective Employment Tax	10-2	11-3	11-4	11-6	11-8	12-other current expenditure, goods and services	62-0	46-8	40-3	40-7	41-7	41-5Current grants to persons	18-5	18-5	17-5	16-5	15-5	160Gross domestic fixed capital formation .	0-6	0-2	0-4	2-1	0-3	0-2Total    .      .	238-7	235-3	230-7	234-4	234-4	236-223. Common services						Wages and salaries......	121-0	127-8	129-2	135-5	139-7	147-1Selective Employment Tax	30	3-1	31	3-1	3-2	3-other current expenditure, goods and services	15-6	24-9	21-3	31-1	34-6	48-2Gross domestic fixed capital formation .	33-0	47-9	67-7	74-5	85-7	81 1Capital grants to private sector	0-1	0-0	0 0	00	0-0	0-0! Total-  &apos;.&apos; :&apos;&quot;&apos;v     . r: &apos;. - v . &apos;	172-7	.203-7	221-3	244-2	263-2	279-7
TABLE 5 (continued)1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn at 1970 Survey prices24. Miscellaneous servicesWages and salaries.....	39-5	41-8	50-1	45-6	460	46-8Selective Employment Tax	2-4	2-7	2-8	2-8	2-9	2-other current expenditure, goods and services	11-5	13-0	180	15-3	15-1	15-current grants to persons	0-4	0-4	0-6	0-6	0-6	0-current grants to private bodies	1-0	1-1	1-2	1-3	1-2	1-2Current grants abroad i   .      .	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-4	0-gross domestic fixed capital formation .	17-2	21-4	12-8	14-9	14-9	17-8Increase in value of stocks	-5-2	-0-1	-0-1	0-6	0-9	0-5Capital grants to private sector	0-6	1-7	0-8	0-6	0-7	0-6Net lending to private sector   .      .	0-2	0-2	0-2	0-2	0-2	0-2Total    .      .      .      .      .      .	67-9	82-5	86-7	82-2	82-9	86-125. Northern IrelandWages and salaries.....	87-0	92-9	96-6	100-3	103-3	106-5Selective Employment Tax	6-8	7-3	7-6	81	8-7	9-other current expenditure, goods and services	42-2	48-9	50-9	53-2	56-0	58-8Subsidies .      .      .      .	25-4	27-2	26-6	28-3	30-4	32-8Current grants to persons	119-6	121-8	115-7	117-4	119-0	121-2Current grants to private bodies	9-9	10-8	11-8	12-2	12-9	13-7Gross domestic fixed capital formation .	101-3	119-2	128-7	131-2	128-8	128-increase in value of stocks	2-9	2-9	2-9	2-9	2-9	2-capital grants to private sector	44-3	49-1	43-3	43-4	43-9	44- net lending to private sector   .      .      :	2-6	3-2	4-0	4-0	4-0	4-0Total    .      .      .&quot;&apos;!&apos;&quot;.	442-0	483-3	488-1	501-0	509-9	521-426. Debt interest      .      .      .      .      .      .     2,186-0      2,103 0      1,980 0      1,950 0      1,890 0      1,810-027. Contingency reserve     ..... - - 90-0        130-0        180-0        245 028.   Shortfall:a. Nationalised industries&apos; capital expenditure        -        -150 - 0     -175 - 0     -150 - 0     -150 - 0     -150 - 0b. Other......-        -200-0      -100-0      -100 0     -100-0     -100 029. Relative price effect and other adjustments        .       603-9        856-8        968-4      1,155 1      1,364-5      1,570-9At 1970-71 outturn prices it -30. Total .      .      .      .      .      .      .21,198-1     21,814-1     22,313-6     22,655-9    23,148-0    23,699-8  million
TABLE 6Analysis of public expenditure by programme and spending authority: 1969-70 to 1974-75  million1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn at 1970 Survey prices. Defence BudgetCentral government (Votes) .      .      .     2,398-9 2,387-0 2,327-0      2,270-0 2,290-0 2,300-0Total    .      .      . .      .      .     2,398-9 2,387-0 2,327-0      2,270-0 2,290-0 2,300 02. Other military defenceCentral government (Votes)      .      .      . 95-4 47-9 50-4 42-4 44-8 52-other central government .... -4-3 0-0 0-2 0-2 0-2 0-2Total...... 91-1 47-9 50-6 42-6 45 0 53-03. Overseas aidCentral government (Votes)      .      .      . 216-9 219-9 225-0 234-1 252-3 273-other central government .      .      .      . -22-0 -23-7 -23-5 -26-5 -30-1 -34-other public corporations .... 8-6 10-8 11-3 14-6 16-8 16-5Total...... 203-5 207-0 212-8 222-2 239 0 256 04. Other overseas servicesCentral government (Votes)      . 123-7 125-3 125-8. 126-5 127-1 128-other central government .... 2-5 2-2          2-0 1-7 1-5           1-other public corporations .... 0-9 1-9          1-5 1-8 1-6           1-6Total...... 127-1 129-4 129-3 130 0 130-2 131-2i ;5. Agriculture, fisheries and forestryCentral government (Votes)      .      .      . 372!5 457-8 432-5 401-4 349-5 308-other central government .... -1-9 -1-8 -1-8 -1-7 -1-6 -1-5Local authorities..... 2-9 5-6          6-6 8-8 7-5          5-9Total...... 373-5 461-6 437-3 408-5 355-4 312-46. Research councilsCentral government (Votes)      .      .      .       100-9        109-6        114-7        119-8        124-5        128-8Total    .   ......       100-9        109-6        114-7        119-8        124-5        128-87. Trade, industry and employmentCentral government (Votes)      .             .     1,111 1 1,051-1 1,064-8 797 1 630-5 483-other central government ....        14-2 27-7 32-0 15-3 -2-0 25-6Local authorities     .      .      .      .      .        10-2 10-9 11-4 11-6 11-9 12-other public corporations .      .      .      .        38-9 35-3 10-2 7-1 , -4-5 -2-8Total    .      .      .      .      .      .1,174-4 1,125-0 1,118-4 831-1 635-9 518-3
Part Four: Statistical Supplement					CONFIDENTIAL	TABLE 6 (continued)						  million							1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					At 1970 Survey prices						8. Fuel						Nationalised industries	744-5	761-4	701-1	686-0	729-4	814-2Total    .      .      ...	744-5	-    761-4	701-1	686-0	729-4	814-29. Steel						Nationalised industries	1060	135-0	1890	188-0	206-0	195-0Total    .      .      .      .      .	1060	135-0	189-0	188-0	206-0	195-010. Post Office						Nationalised industries     .	405-4	465 0	507-3	541-6	561 0	565-8Total    .      .      .      .    . .	405-4	465-0	507-3	541-6	561-0	565-811. Airways and airports						Nationalised industries	71 ;4	151-7	140-8	136-2	135-2	186-6Total    ....	71-4	151-7	140-8	136-2	135-2	186-6012. Surface transportNationalised industriesTotal    .13. Roads and public lightingCentral government (Votes)Local authorities&apos; Total    .118-9118-9246-0410-3656-3138-2138-2297-8447-6745-4132-8144-5132-8144-5294-2479-8318-2523-7774-0841-9145-6145-6892-3148-3148-3336-1 350 7556-2        594-4945-114. TransportCentral government (Votes)Other central government .Local authoritiesOther public corporations .Nationalised industriesTotal    .      .181-0	1600	149-2	136-6	131-2	119-8-8-6	-10-3	-7-7	-8-0	-6-2	-6-056-6	88-4	101-7	106-8	106-4	106-900	0-0	0-4	v 0-4	0-4	0-58-1	2-2	5-2	13-5	16-4	17-7237-1	. 240-3	248-8	249-3	248-2	238-9
f---V    TABLE 6 (continued)  million1969-70     1970-71     1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn at 1970 Survey prices15. HousingCentral government (Votes)	172-6	229-3	275	0	282-9	255-1	229-other central government .	-2-5	-3-2	-3	3	-3-6	-4-0	-4-5Local authorities	813-8	823-4	804	0	797-4	783-9	784-5New towns     .     .      .	58-7	65-8	71	4	800	87-1	87-other public corporations .	29-2	28-6	31	9	32-3	28-2	28-0Total    .      .      .  &apos;   .	1,071-8	1,143-9	1,179	0	1,189-0	1,150-3	1,125-416. Miscellaneous local servicesCentral government (Votes)      .      .      . 15-local authorities..... 750-1New towns      .      .      .      .      .      . 31-3Total......       797-117-1 18-7 18-7 18-6 19-0791-8 790-7 833-9 894-4 941-936-9 36-4 38-8 33-7 34-0845-8        845-8        891-4        946-7        994-917. Law and orderCentral government (Votes) . . . 116-other central government . . . . 2-6Local authorities     .      . . . . 513-8Total    .      .     ,.   &apos; .      .      .v     632-9131-3 147-8        162-5        178-3 193-64-6 2-9 3-0 3-1 3-2550-3        576-5        596-6        632-9        657-8686-2        727-2        762-1        814-3        854-618. ArtsCentral government (Votes)Local authorities18-20-321-10-623-91-023-61-024-70-525-900Total18-521-724-924-625-225-919. EducationCentral government (Votes)       .      .      . 364-6 382-0 403-2 425-2 450-3 481-other central government .      .      .      . -0-6 -0-5 -0-6 -0-7 -0-8 -0-8Local authorities..... 2,084-6 2,141-5 2,250-5 2,315-2 2,351-0 2,391-3Total 2,448-6      2,523-0      2,653-1      2,739-7      2,800-5      2,872-4i I__20. Health and welfareCentral government (Votes)      .      .      . 1,662-8      1,733-8     .1,760-4      1,805-9      1,862-6      1,918-other central government .... 0-5          0-5        -0-6       ,  0-6          0-6          0-6Local authorities     .      .      . 275-2        275-2        302-0        324-2        348-6        367-5H -Total...... 1,938-5      2,009-5      2,061-8      2,130-7      2,211-8      2,286-2
Part Four: Statistical Supplement					CONFIDENTIAL	TABLE 6 (continued)						  million	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					. At 1970 Survey prices						21. Social Security						Central government (Votes)      .      .	1,043-9	1,058-5	1,080-6	1,052-8	1,068-5	1,060-other central government ....	2,726-6	2,806-4	2,867-1	3,007-0	3,118-1	3,186-8Total    .      .      .      .      .      .	3,770-5	3,864-9	3,947-7	4,059-8	4,186-6	4,247-521. Financial administration						Central government (Votes)	177-3	181-6	178-0	182-6	183-5	184-other central government ....	40-4	32-7	31-7	30-7	29-7	30-2Local authorities.....	21-0	21-0	21-0	21-1	21-2	21-5Total......	238-7	235-3	230-7	234-4	234-4	236-223. Common services						Central government (Votes)      ...	184-1	216-1	233-1	255-9	275-0	291-other central government .      .      .	-11-4	-12-4	-11-8	-11-7	-11-8	-11-7Total    .      .      .      .   &apos; .     &apos;.	172-7	203-7	221-3	244-2	263-2	279-724. Miscellaneous services						Central government (Votes)	44-3	50-4	63-4	56-4	57-0	57-other central government ....	0-2	4-6	-2-1	0-5	2-6	2-local authorities	9-1	9-2	9-5	9-8	9-8	9-other public corporations .      .      .      .v	14-3	18-3	15-9	15-5	13-5	16-3Total    .      .     .     .     .	67-9	82-5	86-7	82-2	82-9	86-125. Northern Ireland						Other central government ....	296-6	307-1	304-0	310-8	317-2	324-local authorities.....	122-1	147-9	151-5	153-5	155-7	158-0New towns                   .	2-0	4-0	4-8	3-9	3-0	1-other public corporations ....	21-3	24-3	27-8	32-8	340	36-9Total......	442-0	483-3	488-1	501-0	509-9	521-426. Debt interest......	2,1860	2,103-0	1,980 0	1,950-0	1,890-0	1,810-027. Contingency reserve		-	90-0	130-0	1800	245-028. Shortfall						a. Nationalised industries&apos; capital expenditure		-150-0	-175-0	-150-0	-1500	-150-0b. Other .      ...		-200-0	-1000	-100-0	-100 0	-100029. Relative price effect and other adjustments	603-9	856-8	968-4	1,155-1	1,364-5	&apos;1,570-9At 1970-71 outturn prices						30. Total.......	21,198-1	21,814-1	22,313-6	22,655-9	23,148-0	23,699-8
v   TABLE 7Analysis of gross domestic fixed capital formation by programme and category of asset: 1969-70 to 1974-75   million1969-70     1970-71      1971-72     1972-73     1973-74     1974-75provisional   estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate     estimate outturn at 1970 Survey prices. Defence BudgetLand and existing buildings      ...      .      .	3-1	4-3	2-1	00	-0-4	-0-new dwellings......	8-4	11-2	15-4	14-7	14-2	13-new construction (excluding new dwellings).	6 0	5-5	6-0	7-1	7-6	7-7Plant and machinery .....	6-3	8-8	8-8	91	9-5	9-6Sale of land and buildings ....	-2-8	-2-0	-1-2	-1-2	-1-1	-1-0Total    .      .     ...      . i	21-0	27-8	31-1	29-7	29-8	29-62. Other military defenceLand and existing buildings       ... 0 0 0-2 0-3 0-5 0-8 0-8Sale of land and buildings ....       -2-1        -0-2        -0-3        -0-5        -0-8        -0-8Total......-2-1 0-0 0 0 0-0 O-O 0-04. Other overseas servicesNew construction (excluding new dwellings) . 0-0 0-0 0-3 0-4 O-O 0-plant and machinery..... 0-9 1-3 1-4 1-3 1-4 1-2Total...... 0-9 1-3 1-7 1-7 1-4 1-25. Agriculture, fisheries and forestryLand and existing buildings	1-4	4-3	3-4	4-3	3-7	5-8New dwellings......	0-2	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-3New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	5-2	5-4	8-4	10-2	9-3	7-6Vehicles  .......	11	1-5	1-0	0-9	0-8	0-9Plant and machinery .      .      .      .	0-6	0-8	0-9	0-9	0-9	0-9Sale of land and buildings ....	-2-1	-2-1	-2-0	-1-9	-1-9	-1-8Sale of vehicles, plant and machinery .	0-0	-01	-01	00	0-0	0-0, 1   Total    .            .      &apos;.	6-4	10-1	11-9	14-7	13-1	13-76. Research Councils, etc.Land and existing buildings       .      .      .	0-1	01	0-1	0-1	0-1	0-1New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	6-4	7-2	7-4	7-7	8-0	8-plant and machinery .....	6-3	6-2	6-3	6-7	6-9	7-2Sale of land and buildings .	-0-1	0-0	0-0	0-0	O-O	0-0Total......	12-7	13-5	13-8	14-5	15-0	15-5
Part Four : Statistical Supplement						CONFIDENTIAL	TABLE 7 (continued)							  million		1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75		provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate		outturn						At 1970 Survey prices						7.	Trade, industry and employment							Land and existing buildings	4-4	5-9	1-3	1-2	1-2	1-2	New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	18-2	19-9	36-3	36-1	27-4	25-1	Vehicles   .......	0-1	0-1	0-1	01	0-0	0-1	Plant and machinery .....	23-6	23-8	24-5	20-9	18-3	14-4	Sale of land and buildings ....	-0-4	-0-3	-0-3	-0-4	-0-2	-0-2	Sale of vehicles, plant and machinery .	0-0	-0-9	-0-7	-0-6	-0-5	-0-5	Total......	45-9	48-5	61-2	57-3	46-2	40-18.	Fuel							Land and existing buildings	6-0	7-8	5-1	5-2	4-6	5-0	New dwellings .      .      .      .      .      .	11	1-1	1-1	1-1	1-1	1-1	New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	232-4	251-2	224-4	206-2	217-7	227-0	Vehicles  . -......	7-6	8-9	8-6	8-9	9-1	8-8	Plant and machinery .....	550-1	521-9	474-6	474-4	492-9	570-3	Sale of land and buildings ....	-6-8	-6-9	-4-7	-5-0	-5-6	-4-7	Sale of vehicles, plant and machinery .	-6-9	-5-2	-8-3	-5-6	-4-5	-4-3	Total    .   11,,	783-5	778-8	700-8	685-2	715-3	803-29.	Steel							New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	9-5	150	21 0	200	210	20-0	Plant and machinery.....	74-5	115-0	164-0	165 0	164-0	165-0	Sale of land and buildings	0-0	0-0	0-0	. 00	0-0	00	Sale of vehicles, plant and machinery .	-3-0	0-0	0-0	-1-0	0-0	0-0	Total......	810	130-0	185-0	184-0	185-0	185-010.	Post Office					!		Land and existing buildings	9-1	13-4	12-0	9-5	9-4	8-6	New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	43-5	54-2	68-3	81-2	831	89-0	Vehicles .            .      .      ...	4-6	7-5	80	8-0	8-7	9-3	Plant and machinery .....	334-0	386-2	416-2	440-3	457-7	457-5	Sale of land and buildings ....	-1-9	-1-6	-0-2	-0-9	-0-9	-0-9	Sale of vehicles, plant and machinery .	-0-2	-0-2	-0-2	-0-2	-0-2	-0-2	Total    .      .      .      .      .	389-1	459-5	504-1	537-9	557-8	563-311.	Airways and airports							Land and existing buildings      .      .      .	0-2	0-4	0-8	1-1	1-4 &apos;	3-8	New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	20-1	23-2	28-0	29-5	28-6	36-5	Vehicles                .      .      .	43-9	108-3	93-7	93-6	90-2&apos;	132-4	Plant and machinery .....	10-4	14-9	12-8	11-5	13-3	12-2&apos;	Sale of land and buildings ....	-0-4	-1-5	0-0	0-0	0-0	0-0	Sale of vehicles, plant and machinery .	-4-1	-1-6	-0-4	-2-5	-2-0	-1-0	Total    .      .      .      . 4    .	70-1	143-7	134-9	133-2	131-5	183-9
TABLE 7 (continued)  million1969-70provisionaloutturn1970-71estimate1971-72estimate1972-73estimate1973-74estimate1974-75estimate12.At 1970 Survey pricesSurface transport13.Land and existing buildings	3-2	4-5	2-6	1	8	1-6	0-9New dwellings......	0-2	0-1	00	0	0	00	0-0New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	72-9	77-0	82-3	85	7	84-7	81-7Vehicles.......	55-8	55-9	63-3	67	4	67-1	66-6Plant and machinery.....	14-8	13-9	12-2	12	3	11-8	12-9Sale of land and buildings .      .	-16-8	-13-7	-16-7	-14	0	-11-9	-9-1Sale of vehicles, plant and machinery .	-3-5	-3-9	-12-0	-9	9	-8-9	-6-01    Total.....	126-6	133-8	131-7	143	3	144-4	147-roads and public lighting							Land and existing buildings	56-5	60-6	66-7	75	5	82-6	89-5New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	370-6	423-7	428-7	469	2	505-1	532-4Vehicles......	0-4	0-4	0-4	0	4	0-5	0-5Plant and machinery .      .      .      .	4-2	4-4	i     5-0	5	2	7-0	7-4Sale of land and buildings ....	-2-3	-2-3	-2-4	-3	2	-3-2	-2-5Total......	429-4	486-8,	498-4	547	1	592-0	627-314. TransportLand and existing buildings	2:1	3-7	2-4	2 0	1-4	1- new dwellings .	01	. 0-0	0-0	00	00	0-0New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	44-0	47-3	58-4	71-8	73-7	72-9Vehicles	11-8	24-0	25-1	26-6	28-8	30-1Plant and machinery .      .      .      .      .	11-2	22-1	21-2	20-2	21-6	19-2Sale of land and buildings.....	-0-9	-1-0	-2-1	-1-3	-0-5	-0-3i    . &apos;- -  . ; Total......	68-3	96-1	105-0	119-3	125-0	123-1a lousing						Land and existing buildings	93-7	95-6	104-6	1070	99-0	96-0New dwellings .......	739-0	679-0	690-6	692-8	697-8	702-1New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	0-0	0-2	0-2	0-3	0-4	0-vehicles .......	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-3	0-3Plant and machinery .      .      .      .      .	0-5	0-5	0-5	0-5	0-5	0-5Sale of land and buildings ....	-28-7	-29-1	-30-8	-32-5	-31-7	-32-3Total......	804-8	746-5	765-4	768-4	766-3	767-116. Miscellaneous local servicesLand and existing buildings	69-8	77-3	70-8	73-2	73-7	74-8New dwellings .      .      .      .      .	1-6	1-6	1-6	1-7	1-8	1-8New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	289-0	310-6	322-5	347-6	370-2	400-1Vehicles  .      .      .      .      .      .	5-3	5-7	6-5	6-6	6-8	7-1Plant and machinery.	21-0	23-3	24-1.	i 25-2	26-6	27-0Sale of land and buildings	-24-5	-28-1	-25-2	-26-1	-26-1	-26-9Total    .	362-2	390-4	400-3	428-2	453-0	483-9
Part Four: Statistical Supplement					CONFIDENTIAL	TABLE 7 (continued)						  million	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					At 1970 Survey prices						17. Law and order						Land and existing buildings     .      .      ;	!.\  6-7	7-5	9-6	91	9-3	9-5New dwellings ......	6-1	7-3	9 0	11-3	12-7	14-new construction (excluding new dwellings) .	29-5	45-2	47-5	55-3	64-1	65-9Vehicles   .      .      .&quot;	5-8	6-5	7-0	7-4	7-9	8-plant and machinery.....	4-9	5-3	8-1	6-2	6-7	7-1Sale of land and buildings      ...	-1-6	-1-6	-1-8	-1-6	-1-6	-1-6Total......	51-4	70-2	79-4	87-7	99-1	103-719. Education						Land and existing buildings	34-5	33-7	33-7	23-8	21-8	22-0New construction (excluding new dwellings).	202-4	213-0	253-3	244-9	214-9	186-9Plant and machinery.      .      .      .	37-1	34-8	380	43-2	40-4	35-5Total......	274-0	281-5	325-0	311-9	277-1	244-420. Health and welfare						Land and existing buildings	6-2	7-1	7-3	7-1	6-7	6-9New dwellings......	4-9	5-5	61	6-7	7-5	7-5New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	139-4	148-5	174-1	191-4	194-9	194-2Vehicles .      .      .      .	2-8	2-9	3-3	3-5	3-6	3-7Plant and machinery.....	16-7	16-9	19-3	19-8	21-2	23-4Sale of land and buildings	-1-0	-1-0	-2-1	-0-9	-0-9	-0-9Total    .      .      .      .      .      .v	169-0	179-9	208-0	227-6	233-0	234-822. Financial administration						Vehicles .      .      .      .      .      .      .	0-1	00	0-1	01	0-0	0-plant and machinery.      .      .	0-5	0-2	0-3	2-0	0-3	0-21   Total    .      ...      .      .	0-6	0-2	0-4	2-1	0-3	0-223. Common services						Land and existing buildings	1-4	3-8	3-3	1-0	0-5	0-new dwellings .	00	0-1	0-2	0 1	0-1	0-1New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	21-9	26-8	33-3	42-6	47-6	49-vehicles.......	0-1	0-2	0-1	0-1	0-1	0-1Plant and machinery.....	13-9	21 1	34-2	32-2	38-4	31-8Sale of land and buildings	-3-2	-3-0	-3-1	-1-2	-0-7	-0-5Sale of vehicles, plant and machinery   .	-11	-11	-0-3	-0-3	-0-3	-0-3Total...... .7	33-0	47-9	67-7	74-5	85-7	81-1II    . 24. Miscellaneous services						Land and existing buildings	3-6	5-2	1-5	0-1	0-1	0-1New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	4-2	5 0	4-2	4-1	3-4	3-9Vehicles.......	0-1	01	0-1	0-1	01	1     0-1Plant and machinery.	10-9	130	13-2	12-7	11-4	13-8Sale of land and buildings	-1-5	-1-8	-6-1	-2-0	0-0	0-0Sale of vehicles, plant and machinery	-0-1	-0-1	-01	-01	-0-1	-01Total    &quot;...	17-2	21-4	12-8	14-9	14-9	17-8						22					CONFIDENTIAL	
CONFIDENTIAL			Part Four: Statistical Supplement			TABLE 7 (continued)						  million	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72	1972-73	1973-74	1974-75	provisional	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	estimate	outturn					At 1970 Survey prices				j		25. Northern Ireland					j II	Land and existing buildings	6-0	11-5	10-5	8-9	8-8	7-9New dwellings......	23-9	28-8	31-2	33-8	35-5	38-8New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	52-5	57-2	64-0	64-0	58-8	54-vehicles  .......	2-7	2-8	2-9	2-6	2-3	2-6Plant and machinery.	16-2	18-9	20-1	21-9	23-4	24-5Total    .            .	101-3	119-2	128-7	131-2	128-8	128-31 Summary totals						Land and existing buildings	308-0	346-9	338-1	331-4	326-3	334-1New dwellings ......	785-5	735-0	755-5	762-5	771-0	779-8New construction (excluding new dwellings) .	1,567-7	1,736-1	1,868-6	1,975-3	2,020-5,	2,063-6Vehicles.......	142-5	225-1	220-5	226-6	226-3	271-plant and machinery.....	1,158-6	1,253-3	1,305-7	1,331-5	1,374-2	1,441-6Sale of land and buildings	-97-1	-96-2	-99-0	-92-7	-87-1	-83-5Sale of vehicles, plant and machinery	-18-9	-13-1	-22-1	-20-2	-16-5	-12-grand total	3,846-3	4,187-1	4,367-3	4,514-4	4,614-7	4,794-2I!I)


</content>
</cab>
