<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/56/38 images: 494-499</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT 23bPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1944.SECRET. Copy No.      36W.P. (44) 588.25th October, 1944. tWAR CABINET.LOCAL ELECTIONS.i, assimilation of local government franchise with parliamentaryFranchise.II. Revival of Local Elections.Joint Memorandum by the Home Secretary and the Secretary of Statefor Scotland.I. A ssimilation.THE Speakers Conference unanimously recommended that the local govern-ment franchise, confined hitherto in general to the rate-paying classes, should bebased on the same qualifications as the Parliamentary franchise. A sweepingrecommendation of this character would in the past have been very controversial,but it is in line with the general tendency to widen the basis of the franchise andit was a unanimous recommendation of the Conference.The proposal in an unqualified form is, however, likely to be opposed in some quarters, especially in Scotland, not only because it widens the franchise by givingthe vote to local residents who are not direct rate-payers, but because it deprivesabsentee owners in Scotland and plural occupiers in England and Scotland ofthe right to vote which, as rate-payers, they now have. In Scotland the owner,whether or not he is resident, is required to pay a proportion of the rates inrespect of the property which he owns. In England a non-occupying owner isnot liable for any part of the rates, and does not, under the 1918 Act, possessa vote in respect of his property; but assimilation to the new Parliamentary,qualification will adversely affect the person both in England and Scotland whooccupies and pays rates on two or more properties for example, a town and country house. Under the existing law, though a person may not vote more than once for any one local government electoral area he is entitled to be registeredf or any properties he may occupy if such properties are in separate local govern-ment electoral areas, or, except in the case of a Municipal Borough, in separatewards or divisions of the same local government electoral area. Under national registration, however, he can only be registered in respect of one address, andconsequently will only qualify for the Parliamentary vote in respect of the constituency containing that address. If any concession is made to the absenteeowner in Scotland (allowing him to claim a local government vote by the claimsprocedure applicable to business premises) it would be very difficult to resist theapplication of this procedure to the English or Scottish occupier of propertiesin more than one electoral area. The Secretary of State for Scotland feels thatit will in fact be impossible to resist the pressure to retain the owner&apos;s right to vote, especially at a time when the burden of owner&apos;s rates in Glasgow and else-where is a live political issue. We propose, therefore, while accepting theprinciple of assimilation, to provide in the Bill for the inclusion of the occupierin England, Wales and Scotland (and, in addition, the non-resident owner inScotland) in the register for the purpose of a local government election, providedhe makes a claim and satisfies the requirements of the present law for registrationas a local government elector.[28461]
Service Voters. Complete assimilation presents special difficulties in regardto service voters.The normal method of voting by service voters at Parliamentary elections isby proxy, although service voters in the United Kingdom at the time of electionmay vote by post and in the exceptional case of a person being in the constituencyat the time of the poll, he may vote in person. Postal and proxy voting have,however, never been, operative for local elections, and the application of eithersystem to them is open to the following objections :  (a) Postal Voting. Arrangements could not be made to secure that anapplication for a ballot paper by a service voter in the United kingdom would reach the Returning or Acting Returning Officer concerned.In the case of the annual local elections, the G.P.O. would not havethe necessary information about the many different local government areas involved to undertake delivery of applications, as it will do inthe case of a Parliamentary election. In the case of local government by-elections, the Service Departments could not be asked to notify allUnits, as they do in the case of a Parliamentary by-election, of the address -of the Acting Returning Officer.(b) Proxy Voting.1. Proxy voting would only be workable if the proxy is the person who has been appointed for Parliamentary purposes, and a service voter might object to a proxy appointed by him for a parliamentary election voting on his behalf at a local election.2. A service voter would not ordinarily have time to send his proxyinstructions for whom to vote on his behalf.3. If serving abroad, he would be unlikely to know what particularissue may be dominating any local election or to identify the candidates by the labels which they may choose to adopt.4. Proxy voting at local elections would mean the introduction ofplural voting by proxies on a large scale.We accordingly recommend that no provision should be made in the Bill for service voters at local elections. (As a matter of interest, it may be said that no provision for service voters who are overseas to vote at local elections has beenmade in any of the Dominions.) If, however, the matter is raised in Parliament,the Government could point out the difficulties and objections, and a concession could be made providing for proxy facilities, if the House insisted that some provision should be made for service voters.II. Revival of Local Elections.In the present state of the war it is necessary to consider the question ofthe revival of local elections which, since 1939, have been suspended by an Actwhich has been renewed annually to 31st December in each year. This Act hassubstituted a system of co-option by the Councils concerned, which, while beingthe only practicable alternative, has been justifiable only because of war condi-tions. There can be no doubt of the need to restart local elections at the earliestpossible moment, having regard especially to the fact that the main argument in -favour of suspension interference with the war effort has now no longerthe same force. We think that it would be politically difficult to continue theAct of 1939 for another year.It is accordingly desirable before the end of this year to introduce and pass legislation on the subject of local elections : since if the Act of 1939 were merelyallowed to lapse, local elections for County and District Councils in England andWales would have to be held in the spring of 1945 on the 1939 Register. On thebasis that an Act must be passed on the subject before the end of the year, thefollowing points arise for consideration : (1) The date at which elections should be restarted.A. England. We are not in favour of restarting County Council and district Council elections in the spring of next year, because owing to thedepleted condition of the printing industry and shortage of staff in local govern-ment offices, considerable difficulty would be experienced in carrying through theelections so early in the year, and there is the further consideration that therewill still be considerable movements of the population.   We consider that the
earliest time to restart local elections would be in the autumn, and we recom-mend, therefore, that they should begin with the Borough Council elections inNovember. The Association of Municipal Corporations has expressed a wishfor the date for annual Borough elections to be transferred to the spring, butMetropolitan Boroughs are against spring elections, presumably because theywould cause confusion with the London County Council elections in the spring.Similarly in the provinces there would be confusion between the Borough CountyCouncil and District Council elections. In our view there are advantages in thepresent system, because it prevents a clash of County Council and Boroughelections, and we do not therefore recommend any alteration in the date ofBorough elections. *As regards the,County Council and District Council elections, we recommend,that these should be restarted in the spring of 1946.B. Scotland. In Scotland Town Council elections are, under the present law, held in November; County and District Council elections in December.Opinion among local authorities as to the possibility of a change over to springelections is being ascertained, but is known to be divided. We think that in1945, at any rate, the elections should be held at the usual times in November and december.(2) Production of a Register for local elections.Under the 1918 Act an annual register was produced on the 15th Octoberfor both Parliamentary and local government elections. The 1943 and 1944 Acts,which deal with Parliamentary elections, make provision for the production ofa Register only as and when a Parliamentary election is initiated,* and in aBill dealing with local elections it will be necessary to include a provision fixing a date on which such elections shall be deemed to be initiated. We feel it shouldbe sufficient, as before the war, to have one annual register for local electionscoming into force on the 15th October. If the normal procedure under the acts of 1943 and 1944 were followed, this would mean.that the date of initiation wouldhave to be deemed to be in September and the qualifying date the 31st July; butto allow the time required for the compilation of a register, it is proposed to deemthe initiation to be in August and the qualifying date the 30th June.We accordingly recommend that an annual register should be published inOctober and should be used for any local government election held during the year of its currency.It may happen, howTever, that a fresh register might be produced for a parliamentary General Election or by-election after the end&apos; of December 1945(see paragraph (a) below). If such&apos; a Register is produced for a. ParliamentaryGeneral Election, it might conveniently be-used for any subsequent local electionsor local by-election held before the publication on the 15th October of the annualregister for local elections, and, similarly, if a register is produced for a parliamentary by-election, it might be used for a local by-election if the localgovernment unit were contained wholly within the area for which theParliamentary Register had been produced.We recommend that the Bill should also make provision for the following matters: (a) Utilisation of the annual register for parliamentary elections.If a Parliamentary General Election were initiated in any year before themachinery was set in motion for the production of the Annual&quot; register to bepublished in October of each year, it would be necessary for the purposes of thatElection to produce an ad hoc register in accordance with the provisions of theActs of 1943 and 1944; but it must be pointed out that, until conditions in theprmting trade become more stabilised and more staff is available, it would be verydifficult to produce a register in the time prescribed (36 days) and any suchregister w^ould be likely to be grossly inaccurate.If, however, a Parliamentary election were initiated in October, Novemberor December of 1945 or any succeeding year, the qualifying dates, as the lawstands, would be respectively the 31st August, the 30th September and therfJst October.   It would appear wasteful to incur the printing and production* Under the Act of 1943 an election is initiated, in the case of a General Election, on thee of the Proclamation dissolving Parliament, and, in the case of a by-election, on the datee wnt is received by the Returning Officer.
expenses for further registers in any of these months, and we recommend,1therefore, that a provision should be included in the Bill making the annualregister published in October for local elections the register for any parliamentary election initiated between the time of its production and the end of the year.  Theposition then, would be that if a Parliamentary election were initiated in any month from August to December of 1945 or any subsequent year, it would be heldon the register published in October of that year for local elections, but if it-were initiated in any other month in the year, a fresh register would need to beproduced- to the appropriate qualifying date. These arrangements would mean that in the case of an election initiated between the 15th October and the31st December of 1945 or any subsequent year, the interval between the decisionto dissolve Parliament, or the issue of the writ (in the case of a by-election) andthe date of the poll could be the normal pre-war interval instead of the extendedperiod required under the Acts of 1943 and 1944, and we recommend that aprovision for this purpose should be included in the Bill. It is the case that, withthe exception of the year 1929, all recent Parliamentary General Elections havebeen held in the Autumn.(b) Retirement of Councillors.A third of the members of Municipal and certain District Councils, and of town Councils in.Scotland, retire annually under the pre-war procedure. Therepresentative Associations in England have been consulted on this point anddesire that this procedure should be retained on the occasion of&apos; the next election of local Councillors, though they differ as to the method by which retirement byannual thirds should be restarted. The Association of Municipal Corporationsfavour the withdrawal of any co-opted Councillor before any elected Councillor,while the Urban District Councils&apos; Association have proposed that, for thepurpose of withdrawal, a co-opted Councillor should retire on the date that wouldhave been applicable to the elected Councillor in whose shoes he is standing. InScotland, however, the general opinion is in favour of a clean sweep of allCouncillors, and if this procedure should be urged in Parliament it would, wethink, be very difficult for the Government to resist it. In these circumstances we recommend that the Bill should provide for the retirement of all Councillorsat the first local election to be held, and should contain the necessary transitional provisions to enable retirement by annual thirds, in cases where this procedureapplied prior to the war, to be restarted at the next ensuing local elections. this could be effected by requiring that Councillors elected for a ward shouldsubsequently retire according to the number of votes polled, e.g., the Councillorpolling the lowest number of votes retires after one year, the next lowest retiresafter two years. The Councillor with the highest number of votes retires after three years.(c) Qualification for election.We think it right to preserve the qualification for election of an existingAlderman or Councillor notwithstanding that he may be residing outside the areaconcerned on the qualifying date, and would not therefore appear on the register of electors, which is a qualification for election, and we recommend that the:necessary provision for this purpose should be contained in the Bill.H. M.t. J..Whitehall, S. W. 1,25th October, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
