<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/41/35 images: 266-271</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1943.SECRET.W.P. (43) 435.4th October, 1943.WAR CABINET.INDIAN POLICY.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.1. THE Viceroy-Designate desires guidance on the policy he is to follow indealing with the political deadlock in India. He summarised his views in aMemorandum which, supplemented by his oral exposition of various points, hasbeen considered at three meetings by the India Committee of the Cabinet. Brieflyhe holds (i) That while the ultimate aim of our policy in India remains thatindicated in the &quot; Cripps offer,&quot; our immediate intentions are not clear.(ii) That the choice lies between (a) Continued inaction in the political field; and(p) The revival in some form of the &quot; Cripps offer.&quot;(iii) That inaction implies the retention of the present &quot; official;&apos; ExecutiveCouncil with or without changes in its composition a safe enoughcourse with many obvious short-term advantages, but with the serious disadvantage that at the end of the war we should still be at a losshow to advance India towards self-government, and that the situation will have been increasingly embittered.(iv) That the revival of the &quot; Cripps offer &quot; implies a real attempt to carryout the &quot; immediate &quot; portion of that offer and to bring the leadersof the Indian political parties into the Executive Council a courseinvolving many obvious short-term dangers, but almost certainly theonly course which will make any post-war solution of the problempossible.(v) That the second of these two possible courses is to be preferred to thefirst.2, If that general conclusion commended itself to the War Cabinet theViceroy-Designate&apos;s specific suggestion was that he should invite a comparatively small number of the leaders of the different parties to a private discussion among themselves with a view to the inclusion of political leaders in his ExecutiveCouncil. He would come back to the War Cabinet for definite approval of hisissuing such an invitation if, after studying the situation and taking advice, hewas of opinion that there was a reasonable prospect of success and that action could be taken without detriment to the Avar effort. In particular, he felt thathe ought to consult the present Executive Council and, if possible, carry it withhim. In the meantime he asked for authority to make, shortly after his arrival,a cautiously worded statement (Annexure A) indicating that political progressduring the war was not ruled out.3. It would be an essential preliminary condition of the proposed discussion,and of the release of those Conga-ess leaders, such as Gandhi and Nehru, whom he would invite to take part in it, that they should (i) definitely promise their whole-hearted support of the war effort;(ii) disavow any intention of renewing Civil Disobedience;[26167]Copy No- J
(iii) accept the following principles, viz., that the ultimate constitutional settlement must he based on agreement between the main (dements in[ndia&apos;s national life, and that the predominantly Moslem areas andthe Princes must remain free not to accede to a majority constitutionof which they disapprove, and that the interim Government to be formed must remain under the existing constitution and subject to theretention of the 1 rovernor-Generahs powers of overruling the executive and, on occasion, acting independently of it.If the conditions were accepted by the Congress leaders to whom the invitationwas issued they would be released unconditionally and, subject to future good behaviour, remain at liberty even if the discussion proved unfruitful.4. it would be made clear to those invited that tiie task of an interim government, if agreed noon, would be to carry on the war to a successful end insto deal with the immediate economic problems and to consider the needs of post-war social and economic reconstruction. The constitutional problem wouldnot be one of the tasks specifically assigned to them, though it might be hoped thatin the atmosphere of friendly co-operation in the administration they might, infact, make some agreed contribution towards its solution.5. Cord Waved 1&apos;uiiy realises thai such a reconstituted executive might heboth less efficient and more difficult to manage than the present Executive. Asagainst that lie would set the greater measure of public support for the war effort and for dealing with the difficulties of the economic situation, and, still moreimportant, the avoidance of an increasing bitterness which might fatallyprejudice the prospects of India after the war wishing to remain within theBritish Commonwealth, in any case he fee is that the main guarantee for India/s security during the war lies m the British and American forces on the spot andon the fact that the new Executive, if it really proved obstructive, could be dismissed.6. I share Lord WavelEs view that this attempt should be made if. and assoon as, the conditions appear favourable. Our present position is open to the criticism that while we have repeatedly stated that the &quot; Gripps &quot; offer is stillin principle open we in fact make agreement upon it impossible by detaining theleaders of the most important Indian party and allowing them no opportunityfor reconsideration of their attitude towards the internal Indian deadlock. Weare no doubt entitled to say that they must first abandon the attitude whichjustified their detention, but that still leaves us exposed to the charge that weare not, in fact, giving them any effective opportunity to do so, and that we arenot really sincere in our professions of a desire for Indian agreement.7. As for the prospects of success. I do not overrate them. Gandhhs influencemay still be able to wreck any prospect of agreement. At the same time, themilitary situation has entirely changed in our favour since the time when his conviction of the certainty of our defeat, shared by many of the Congress leaders,enabled him to secure the rejection of the &quot; Cripps &quot; proposals. It may be evenmore striking!)&quot; favourable in the course of the next few months. In any casea renewed attempt to break the deadlock, if made with obvious sincerity, should,even if it failed, convince public opinion, here and in America, and in some measure even in India, that we have no alternative but to carry on as we are forthe war. In either event the atmosphere for the future constitutional discussions would be improved.8. I therefore recommend that the. Viceroy-Designate should be given ageneral authority to study the possibility of attempting to break the presentdeadlock in some such way as he has suggested, and that his desire for guidanceshould be met by a War Cabinet directive on the lines of the draft which I attachas Annexure B.L. S. A.India Office, 4-th October, 1943.
ANNEXURE A.Draft Statement to be made by the Viceroy-Designate soon after his arrival in india.The Indian people will expect from a new Viceroy some statement about thepolitical situation. For the time being, I must ask them to be patient. I shallfor some weeks inevitably be much occupied with the arrangements for theestablishment of the South-East Asia Command, and other questions of immediate importance such as the food situation. But I can assure you that theBritish Government and the British people sincerely desire that as soon aspossible after the war India shall become fully self-governing, under an agreedIndian-made constitution and a treaty negotiated between Great Britain5 andIndia, which, while it is hoped that it will preserve India&apos;s position as a memberof the British Commonwealth of Nations in allegiance to the Crown, will notimpose any restriction on India&apos;s power to decide in the future her relation to theother Member States of the Commonwealth. Attempts to make substantial progress towards this end during the war have so far failed, but I intend, withthe approval of His Majesty&apos;s Government, to examine whether a fresh attemptwould appear to have good prospects of success.ANNEXURE B.Revised Draft Directive to the Viceroy-Designate.His Majesty&quot;s Governments aim is directed towards the creation of an atmosphere in India which will rally the Indian people to the maximum war effort and at the same time assist the promotion of the solution of the constitu-tional problem in a manner consistent with India remaining within the BritishCommonwealth of Nations.In pursuing this aim His Majesty&apos;s Government consider that the newViceroy should be authorised to approach the political leaders in India as andwhen he considers it desirable, but should consult the War Cabinet as to the timeand form of any invitation to be issued.Subject to further consideration and advice in India, the most suitablemethod of approach might be by private discussion of possible means of resolvingthe present deadlock.Any invitation should make it clear that the basis of any discussions whichmight lead up to interim changes in the composition of the present ExecutiveCouncil, aimed at making it more representative of Indian political opinion, mustbe a sincere assurance on the part of the Indian political leaders of their intention to (a) carry on with all vigour the war against Japan;(b) work together genuinely and wholeheartedly with the intention of thuscontributing towards the solution of the constitutional problems,and an acceptance on their part of the position that for the period of hostilitiesthe Governor-General&apos;s Executive Council must remain subject to the existing constitution, i.e., to the ultimate control of Flis Majesty&apos;s Government and parliament exercised through the Governor-General&apos;s present statutory powers.




</content>
</cab>
