<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/75/0 images: 21-37</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
AGENDUM.THE REDUCTION AND LIMITATION OF ARMAMENTS.(Reference Cabinet 1 (53), Conclusions 3 and 11).Memorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs, covering a revised draft programme forthe Disarmament Conference.(CP. 9 (33)    -    to be circulated).(Signed) .M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.S Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.20th January, 1933.SECRET. COPY NO.CABINET    2  (55).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at 10 downing street, S.W.1, on MONDAY, 23rd January,1933, at 3.0 p.m.
2 conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on MONDAY,January 23rd, 1933, at 3.0 p.m.PRESENT: -The Right Hon, J. RaPrime Minister.The Right Hon.Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon.Sir John Gilmour, Bt.,D.S.O.,M.P., Secretary of State for home Affairs.The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,.Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Edward Hilton Young,G.B.E.,D.S.O.,D,S.C.,M.P. .Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Sir Bolton Eyres-Monsell,G.B.E.,M.P., First Lord ofthe Admiralty.The Right Hon.Sir Henry Betterton, Bt.,C.B.E.,M.P., Minister of Labour.MacDonald, M.P.,(In the Chair).The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.The Viscount Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I.,K.C.V.0.,O.B.E.,K.G.,M.P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E. ,M.C. ,M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hon.Walter Runciman, M.P.,President of the Board ofTrade.Major The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C.,M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.Major The Right Hon.W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P.,First Commissioner of Works.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT: -The Right Hon.Sir Philip Sassoon, Bt. ,G.B.E ., C .M.G . ,M.P. ,I Under-Seeretary of State for Air.(For Conclusion 1).Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B. .G.C.M.G.,Secretary.SJ3JLRJLT. COPY NO.cabinet    2 (53).
iDUGTlON&apos; ANDCITATION OPSMAMENTS .Is     ie Disarmamentinference,previous reference:cabinet 1[35), Con-Jlusions 3and 11.)lVThe Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (C.P.-9 (33))containing in the Appendix thereto a revise of theprogramme of work for the Disarmament Conferenceattached to his previous Memorandum (C.P.-3 (33)),amended in accordance with the views of the Cabinetexpressed at the Meeting mentioned in the margin.In the present Memorandum the Secretary of State saidthat the new draft was so framed as to make it clearthat its only function was to serve as a list oftopics and suggestions as to how they should be handled by the Disarmament Conference, and was not afresh statement of policy by His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin the United Kingdom..    In view of the Five-Pewer-Agreement signed on December 11th, it was absolutely necessary to include in the programme of work some reference to security as well as to equality of rights,but in order to avoid the possibility of any inferencebeing drawn that in making any proposals for a schemeof work we were committing ourselves in advance tothe French Plan or any part of it, he proposed tostate expressly to the Bureau of the Disarmament Confer-ence that we were not doing so and that we reservedour judgment on any conclusions that might emerge fromany of the proposed inquiries.   In addition, he proposedto point out that in submitting this programme as an agenda Paper to the Conference it had not been thought necessary to mention figures for such matters as maximumweights of tanks, calibre of guns, weights of aircraft,and so forth, for the reason that our view on thesematters had already been announced in earlier state-arrangements.   He proposed, in connection with the Air, to mention the exception as to police bombing. (Appendix r.)
The Prime Minister informed his colleagues thatas the Air Ministry had some observations to offer on the draft programme of work, he had thought it right, in the absence of the Secretary of State forAir, to invite the attendance of the parliamentary under Secretary of State,The Cabinet discussed the draft programme paragraphby para graph.The Cabinet took note that the introduction hadbeen re-drafted so as to make unmistakably clearthat the document was solely a programme of work.PART I (5).    Last Sentence.&quot;The reduction of the armies of thecontinental European States to a uniform general type of organisation  that of a national short-servicearmy with limited effectives&quot;.The Cabinet were reminded that opinion on theContinent was far from unanimous on the question ofnational short-service armies.   Even military opinion was probably divided, but the peace propagandists were very much averse to having conscription thrust upon themagain.    They would criticise this passage in the pro-gramme of work submitted by the British Government asendorsing the principle of conscription.    It would bethe first occasion since the War on which a BritishGovernment had definitely favoured conscription.hither to the furthest they had gone was not to   oppose it if theContinent insisted on this form of military organisation,The Cabinet agreed, that the following words shouldbe omitted:-&quot;  that of a national short-servicearmy with limited effectives&quot;,and that the last sentence of the paragraph in question should read as follows&quot;The reduction of the armies of thecontinental European States to a uniformgeneral type of organisation would have &quot;to be considered in this nn^lZZTTZTZ   -
TAUT I (3) .&quot;The immediate study hy the continentalEuropean States with a view to their mutual security of the possibility of reaching political arrangements defining the conditions in which each of them willbe entitled to the co-operation of theother contracting States&quot;.The Secretary of State for War, while concurringto Part 1(5)in the above alteration^ reminded the Cabinet thatthe Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs had under-taken to state that we were not committing ourselves in advance to these proposals and reserved our judgment on any conclusions which may emerge from any of theproposed enquiries.   He had hoped that the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs might also have gone alittle further and have entered a caveat as to ourobjections to the French Plan in connection withby meansPart I (2), as the principle of mutual security/ofpolitical arrangements for co-operation between thecontinental European States had never been approvedby the Cabinet and was strongly objected to by many people.PART II. (B) (a)  (iii) .&quot;Determine the stages and methods by whichEuropean continental long-service armiesmay be transformed into national short-service armies.   For the discussion ofthis point, the Bureau may require theEffectives Committee to submit recommenda-tlons&quot;,The Secretary of State for War pointed out that theword &quot;long-service&quot; should be omitted, as most of theEuropean continental States had short-service armies.The Cabinet were reminded that this paragraph wouldrequire re-drafting consequentially to the alterationthey had made to Part I (5),The Cabinet agreed that the paragraph should bemade to read as follows:-&quot;Determine the stages and methods by whichEuropean continental armies may be broughtinto harmony with the general type of organisation adopted. (See I (5).)    For the-3-
discussion of this point the Bureaumay require the Effectives Committeeto submit recommendations&quot;.PART IX (B)   (b).&quot;Land War Material,     The Bureau shall -(i) Fix the maximum tonnage of tanks and their numbers for each State.(ii) Decide as to the disposal of tanksexceeding that limit   whetherthey shall be scrapped, and, if so,the dates by which such scrappingmust have been effected,(iii) Pix. for the future the maximumcalibre of mobile land guns and decide as to the treatment ofexisting mobile land guns exceedingthat calibre,(iv) Decide whether there should be a limitation of the numbers of mobileland guns of allowed calibre&quot;,The Secretary of State for War proposed a re-draftof this paragraph (See Conclusion below).   One of hisobjects in submitting a re-draft was to get rid of the definite proposal that the Bureau should fix the numbersof tanks for each State.    It might be possible to fix the numbers of the larger tanks, but he was advised that this would be very difficult for the light tanks.In the first place, it was almost impossible to decide on a definition of a &quot;tank&quot;.   There were all kinds ofvarieties of light tanks, including machines whichordinarily ran on wheels but could be fitted with tracks.He was grateful to the Foreign Secretary for insertingthe words &quot;for the future&quot; in (iii) in order to safe-guard against the scrapping of our 6-inch ordnance,which could only be replaced by 4.5-inch ordnance(the proposed maximum calibre) at a cost . -of  6,000,000.    In the same order of ideas, he desiredto omit the specific instruction to the Bureau to decide as to the treatment of existing mobile land gunsexceeding the maximum calibre.
The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs thoughtthat his draft did carry out the provisional views ofthe Cabinet Committee,   ^e reason for suggesting thatthe Bureau should fix the numbers of tanks allowed to each State arose from the fact that Germany was notat present allowed to have any tanks.    If. however,Germany and the other ex-enemy Powers were to begranted equality of status and no mention was made offixation of numbers, it would be difficult to prevent them from building tanks.   The object of the draft,therefore, had been to try and ride them off by sayingthat the Bureau must consider the numbers for each state .The Cabinet were most anxious not to put theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs at Geneva inthe position where the positive note of his speechwould be whittled away by reservations, and that the document must be so framed as to present as few pointsas possible on which special explanations had to bemade.   They were reminded, however, that the draft ofthe Secretary of State for War was not open to this latter objection and did provide that the Bureau should decide whether there should be a limitation of thenumbers of tanks of allowed tonnage.The Cabinet accordingly agreed to substitute thefollowing:-&quot;Land War Material.     The Bureau shall _(i) Fix the maximum tonnage of tanks *(ii) Fix for the future the maximum calibreof mobile land puns,(iii) Decide whether there should be a limitation of the number of tanksof allowed tonnage and of mobile landguns of allowed calibre,(iv) If a limitation of the number of tanksis accepted, decide as to the disposalof tanks exceeding that limit,&quot;
&quot;Air...........*.* As a preliminary toT2Te decision to be taken by the Committeeof Air Powers, the Bureau shall at once  (i) Fix the maximum unladen weight ofmilitary and naval aircraft,(ii) Decide as to the disposal of machinesexceeding that limit   whether they shall be scrapped, and, if so, the dates by which scrapping must havebeen effected,(iii) Fix the number of machines notexceeding the unladen weight limit which may be allowed to each State.&quot;The Cabinet were informed that the parliamentary under Secretary of State for Air had written a letterto the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, whohad only received it just before the Meeting.    Inregard to (ii) the Parliamentary Under Secretary ofState had in this letter suggested an amendmentdesigned to ensure that we are not unnecessarilyforced into a very heavy expenditure dtie to thescrapping of machines exceeding whatever limit ofunladen weight may be decided on, which would, ofcourse, entail their immediate replacement.    Forexample, if the limit was 3 tons, we should have toscrap between 800 and 250 machines, the replacement of which might cost anything between  1,500,000 and 2,000,000.   The present wording gave the Bureaurather a lead in the direction of fixing a very earlydate, and even left it open to them to recommend thatmachines in excess of the limit should be scrappedforthwith, which seemed to him to serve no useful purpose and to be quite contrary to naval and otherprecedents.   An increase in Air Estimates might thenbe inevitable, which he thought was strongly to bedeprecated, both on financial and political grounds..He suggested some such wording as the followingt-
(four)&quot;(ii) Fix a date not later than (five)(three)years from the ratification ofthe Convention, -whereafter anyaircraft exceeding the limit -under(i) above, the useful life of whichhas not already expired, shall be finally scrapped&quot; ,He also said that the Air Ministry found it difficultto understand why paragraph II (B)  (e)  did not contain the reservation safeguarding the use of aircraft and bombing required for police work in outlying places.This reservation was prominent in the NovemberStatement of Policy, and its omission now, he suggested,would indicate a change of policy, which was unthinkablein view of Sir Francis Humphrysr recent Despatch(C.P.-4 (33)),   The problems connected with entireabolition of all air forces were profoundly alterednecessaryand complicated by the/retention-of tombing machinesin overseas territory.   Although the present document was a programme and not a statement of policy, hesuggested that it would, be most misleading to proposediscussions on total abolition when we intend onlythe abolition of &quot;metropolitan&quot; forces ,     He hoped,therefore, that the Cabinet would agree that it was essential to include the reservation in this new draftprogramme, in terms of the Declaration of November17th (Cmd.4189).The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs explainedthat his intention was, in introducing the portion ofthe programme relating to air armaments-, to make clearthat it had not been thought neoessary to go into detailsas our views on these matters had already been announced in earlier statements.   He proposed also, as stated inhis covering Note to C.P.-9 (33)  in connection with/air,to mention the exception as to police bombing.   He pointedout that if a purely British reservation of this kind
was brought up in connection with a programme it wouldbecome the subject of a vote by the Bureau at that st geof the work.   He thought this was undesirable from severalpoints of view.    For example, it would make it moredifficult to resist all kinds of details being put intothe programme by other Powers.   The right time for thediscussion of the questions referred to by the Parliament-ary Under Secretary of State would be when the subject was discussed at the Committee of Representatives of thePrincipal Air Powers, when a resolution on the subject would, no doubt, be moved,The Cabinet were also reminded that the dominions had views on these points and would raise them at theappropriate stage.The Parliamentary Under Secretary of State for Airsaid that these were points to which the Air Ministryattached great importance.   The proposal in paragraph II(B)(c) was worded identically with the Declaration ofNovember 17th, with the omission of this reservation, andhe knew that the Secretary of State for Air regarded theDeclaration as representing the limit to which we could go consistent with security 0The Cabinet considered that it would be inadvisableat the present stage to insert into the programme purely british reservations, and that the Air Ministry&apos;s pointswould be sufficiently safeguarded by the introductorystatement to be made by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.    They were anxious to keep quite clear the distinction between the character of the document as alist of topics, or an Agenda Paper, and a statement ofBritish policy.Some discussion then took place as to the criticismsthat would have to be faced when this programme was submitted at Geneva.   One criticism would&apos;be that this programme was taking the Conference back to the position at its opening, and that the work of the last twelve
months was being thrown away,   ^he United Kingdomn file pates woulrt be asked whether they visualised theConference continuing for another six or twelvemonths.   Another criticism would be against theproposal to conduct the work in the Bureau, assisted by Sub-Committees, and only submitting agreed matter to the full Conference.The Cabinet were reminded, however, that in thelast year progress had not been satisfactory, andthat this was due to unfortunate methods of procedure.Without animadverting on the past, which would causefriction, it might be pointed out that new methodswere necessary if the work was to be brought to anend.    It was known that the President of the Confer-ence favoured the work being carried out in a bodysmaller than the General Commission, and that hewould prefer to have a programme suggested by a delegation rather than to offer a suggestion of hisown.    It was felt that even if the programme was not accepted, the United Kingdom Delegation would be ina stronger position for having made a practical proposition.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs entereda caveat that he was almost bound to meet with opposition to this programme, and that the cabinet must not expect that he would be able to carry it atthe Bureau in all its details.The Cabinet agreed &apos; (a) To approve the programme of workattached to CP.-9 (33), subject tothe following alterations:-PART 1(5).   The last sentence to be amended to read as follows:-&quot;The reduction of the armies of thecontinental European States to a uniform general type of organisa-tion would have to be considered in this connection&quot;.PART II (B) (a) fill).&quot;Determine the stages and methods by which European continentallesg-M^iee armies r-ay be brought
into harmony with the generaltype of organisation adopted,(See I (5),)    For the discussionof this point the Bureau may require the Effectives Committeeto submit- recommendations.&quot;PART II-(b)  (b) to be re-drafted to read as follows:-&quot;Land War Material.   The Bureau shall -(i) Fix the maximum tonnage of tanks ,(ii) Pix for the future the maximumcalibre of mobile land guns ,(iii) Decide whether there shouldbe a limitation of the numberof tanks of allowed tonnage- and of mobile land guns ofallowed calibre,(iv) If a limitation of the numberof tanks is accepted, decide as to the disposal of tanksexaeeding that limit,&quot;(A copy of the Programme as approvedis attached in Appendix II.)(b) That the amendments suggested on behalfof the Air Ministry by the parliamentary under Secretary of State for Air tendedtowards converting a programme of workinto a statement of British policy:    thatthe position of the Air Ministry would be safeguarded by the statements to be madeby the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs in introducing the programme:and that the appropriate stage forbringir.   up these points would be beforethe proposed Committee of Representativesof the Principal Air Powers .
9 9(previous reference:Cabinet 1(63). Con-elusion 7.)2,   The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet thata whole series of Questions were to be asked in theHouse of Commons on its re-assembly as to whethervarious cuts were to be reduced.    It was proposedthat he himself should answer the whole of theseQuestions together.   The general trend of the Answerwould be to the effect that there was no questionof reducing the cuts that had been made, or of extending them,   He asked the Chancellor of theExchequer to frame the terms of the Answer and tocommunicate it to the Cabinet at their next Meeting.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,January 23, 19 33,
APPENDIX I.(CP. 9.) ----I The Bureau proposes to the General Commission that the following programme of work should be adopted to facilitate progress at the DisarmamentConference:  ,,The General Commission decides that the future work of the conference should be conducted on the following lines, the direction of the work being placedin the hands of the Bureau : I.The aim of the Bureau should be to organise without delay practicaldiscussion of the following topics, with the object of framing a Convention orConventions embodying them so far as they are ultimately approved : mm (1) A solemn affirmation, to be made by all European States, that they willnot in any circumstances attempt to resolve any present or futuredifferences between them by resort to force.(2) The immediate study by the continental European States with a view totheir mutual security of the possibility of reaching political arrange-ments defining the conditions in which each of them will be entitledto the co-operation of the other contracting States.(3) The application of the principle that the limitations on the armamentsof Germany and the other disarmed States shall be contained in thesame Disarmament Convention as that which will define the limita-tions on the armaments of others, so that the articles in Part V of theTreaty of Versailles, which at present limit Germany&apos;s arms and armed forces, and the corresponding provisions of the other peace treaties, would be replaced by the Disarmament Convention as far asthe disarmed States are concerned.(4) The application of the principle that the newly-expressed limitations inthe case of Germany and the other disarmed States shall last for thesame period and be subject to the same methods of revision as thoseof all other countries; and the embodiment in the DisarmamentConference of an undertaking on the part of the signatory States toenter upon negotiations in due course before the expiry of thisConvention with a view to concluding a new Disarmament convention for the purpose of further adjustment of armaments.(5) The embodiment in the Convention, as regards war material, of theprinciple of qualitative equality, and the provision for the realisation of such equality, if not immediately after its entry into force, then by-specified stages. The reduction of the armies of the continentalEuropean States to a uniform general type of organisation that of anational short-service army with limited effectives.II.(A) Security.The Political Commission should be instructed at once to study the methodsof giving effect to point (1) above.^1 A Committee of the European continental States should be immediately-constituted to examine point (2) above.^B) Disarmament.*     (a) Effectives. The Bureau shall at once undertake the following work : (i) In accordance with the plan for the calculation of land forces containedin the proposals of President Hoover, compute the totals of personnel of the &quot; police component &quot; (the irreducible component) of the existingland forces of each country, both metropolitan and overseas. For thispurpose it shall instruct the Effectives Committee to make to it within  days recommendations concerning the ratios to be employedin this calculation. If within that time the Effectives Committeehas been unable to reach a unanimous recommendation, it must report6706   [8129]
fully to the Bureau the state of its discussions, and it will be for-Bureau to take a definite decision,(ii) Agree upon the percentage by which the &quot; defence component&quot; (jiexcess over the &quot; police component&quot;) of each State shall be reducesuch redaction to be effected by a certain date or elates to be specify^iii) Determine the stages and methods by which European continental loaservice armies may be transformed into national short-service armitFor the discussion of this point, the Bureau may require the EffectsCommittee to submit recommendations.(b) Land War Material. The Bureau shall (i) Fix the maximum tonnage of tanks and their numbers for each State,(ii) Decide as to the disposal of tanks exceeding that limit whether theshall be scrapped, and, if so, the dates by which such scrapping muhave been effected.(iii) Fix for the future the maximum calibre of mobile land guns and deciias to the treatment of existing mobile land guns exceeding that calibt(iv) Decide whether there should be a limitation of the numbers of mobiiland guns of allowed calibre.(c) Air. The Bureau shall at once constitute a, committee of representatiwof the principal Air Powers to examine the possibility of the entire abolition jmilitary and naval machines and of bombing from the air, combined wit!an effective international control of civil aviation. As a preliminary to i\decision to be taken by the Committee of Air Powers, the Bureau shall at once-(i) Fix the maximum unladen weight of military and naval aircraft,(ii) Decide as to the disposal of machines exceeding that limit whethethey shall be&quot; scrapped, and. if so, the dates by which scrapping mmhave been effected.(iii) Fix the numbers of machines not exceeding the unladen weight limit which may be allowed to each State.(d) Naval Forces. The Bureau shall fix the maximum tonnage mmaximum calibre of gun for (i) Capital ships.(ii) Aircraft carriers (if these are allowed to be retained or replaced).(iii) Cruisers.(iv) Destroyers.(v) Submarines (if these are allowed to be retained or replaced).The Bureau shall request the five principal Naval Powers to meet togetherat once to discuss the possibility of completing the Treaty of London, thusregulating the naval situation as between them until the end of 1936.On receipt of a report of the results of this meeting of the five Powers, the bureau shall add to their number representatives of the other Naval Powers forthe purpose of agreeing on limitation figures for all signatories of the Convention.
APPENDIX II.(Q.P. 9a.)The Bureau proposes to the General Commission that the following programme oi work should be adopted to facilitate progress at the DisarmamentConference:  hu General Commission decides that the future work of the Confer-eneeshould be conducted on the following lines, the direction of the work being placedin the hands of the Bureau : The aim of the Bureau should be to organise without delay practicaldiscussion of the following topics, with the object of framing a Convention orConventions embodying them so far as they are ultimately approved : (1) A solemn affirmation, to be made by all European States, that they willnot in any circumstances attempt to resolve any present or futuredifl&apos;ei&apos;ences between them by resort to force.(2) The immediate study by the continental European States with a view totheir mutual security of the possibility of reaching political arrange-ments defining the conditions in which each of them will be entitledto the co-operation of the other contracting States.(3) The application of the principle that the limitations on the armamentsof Germany and the other disarmed States shall be contained in thesame Disarmament Convention as that which will define the limita-tions on the armaments of others, so that the articles in Part V of theTreaty of &quot;Versailles, which at present limit Germany&apos;s arms and armed forces, and the corresponding provisions of the other peace treaties, would be replaced by the Disarmament Convention as far asthe disarmed States are concerned.(4) The application of the principle that the newly-expressed limitations inthe case of Germany and the other disarmed States shall last for thesame period and be subject to the same methods of revision as thoseof all other countries; and the embodiment in the DisarmamentConference of an undertaking on the part of the signatory States toenter upon negotiations in due course before the expiry of thisConvention with a view to concluding a new Disarmament convention for the purpose of further adjustment of armaments.Wm (5) The embodiment in the Convention, as regards war material, of theprinciple of qualitative equality, and the provision for the realisation of such equality, if not immediately after its entry into force, then byspecified stages. The reduction of the armies of the continentalEuropean States to a uniform general type of organisation wouldhave to be considered in this connection.(A) Security.The Political Commission should be instructed at once to study the methods,of giving effect to point (1) above.A Committee of the European continental States&quot; should be immediatelyconstituted to examine point (2) above.6706   [8129]
(B) Disarmament.(a) Effectives. The Bureau shall at once undertake the following work:- (i) In accordance with the plan for the calculation of land forces containedin the proposals of President Hoover, compute the totals of personnel of the &quot; police component &quot; (the irreducible component) of the existingland forces of each couritr.y,&apos;bbth!mfetropolitan and overseas.   For thispurpose it shall instruct the Effectives Committee to make to it within    days recommendations concerning the ratios to be employedin this calculation.     If within that time the Effectives Committeehas been unable to reach a unanimous recommendation, it must report,. ., fully to the Bureau the state of its discussions, and it will be for the bureau to take a definite decision,(ii) Agree upon the percentage by which the &quot;defence component&quot; (the excess over the &quot; police component &quot;) of each State shall be reduced,, such reduction to be effected by a certain date or dates to be specified.I ; (iii) Determine the stages and methods by which European continental armiesmay be brought into harmony with the general type of organisationadopted (see I (5)). For the discussion of this point, the Bureau may require the Effectives Committee to submit recommendations.i     (b) Land War Material. The Bureau shall (i) Fix the maximum tonnage of tanks.(ii) Fix for the future the maximum calibre of mobile land guns.(iii) Decide whether there should be a limitation of the number of tanks ofallowed tonnage and of mobile land guns of allowed calibre.(iv) If a limitation of the number of tanks is accepted, decide as to thedisposal of tanks exceeding that limit.(c) Air. The Bureau shall at once constitute a committee of representativesof the principal Air Powers to examine the possibility of the entire abolition ofmilitary and naval machines and of bombing from the air, combined withan effective international control of civil aviation. As a preliminary to thedecision to be taken by the Committee of Air Powers, the Bureau shall at. once (i) Fix the maximum unladen weight of military and naval aircraft,(ii) Decide as to the disposal of machines exceeding that limit whetherthey shall be scrapped, and, if so, the dates by which scrapping must -have been effected.(iii) Fix the numbers of machines not exceeding the unladen weight limit which may be allowed to each State.(d) Naval  Forces. The  Bureau  shall  fix  the  maximum  tonnage  and maximum calibre of gun for (i) Capital ships.(ii) Aircraft carriers (if these are allowed to be retained or replaced).(iii) Cruisers.(iv) Destroyers.(v) Submarines (if these are allowed to be retained or replaced).The Bureau shall request the five principal Naval Powers to ineet togetherat once to discuss the possibility of completing the Treaty of London, thusregulating the naval situation as between them until the end of 1936.On receipt of a report of the results of this meeting of the five Powers, the bureau shall add to their number representatives of the other Naval Powers forthe purpose of agreeing on limitation figures for all signatories of the Convention.

</content>
</cab>
