<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/75/0 images: 94-115</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)S E ORE T. COPY NO.__r** - CABINET   7 (33).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at 10Downing Street,  S.W.1, on WEDNESDAY,8th February, 1933, at 11.0 a.m.AGENDA.1. FOREIGN AFFAIRS.    -    (If required).2&apos;  LICENSING OF MANUFACTURE OF ARMS.Memorandum by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.(CP. 23 (33)    -    circulated herewith) .Report of Inter-departmental Committee.(CP. 24(33).3* POLICY IN PALESTINE.(Reference Cabinet 60(32), Conclusion 11).Memorandum by the Secretary of State forthe Colonies.(CP. 16(33)    -   already circulated).4.  CROWN LANDS:    FUTURE GOVERNMENT RESPONSIBILITYFOR ADM IN ISTRATI ON .(Reference Cabinet 4 (33), Conclusion 3).Second Report of Cabinet Committee.(CP. 20(33)    -    already circulated).
6&apos;  CONCLUSIONS OF THE HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.First Conclusions (33) of Home AffairsCommittee    -   to be circulated.(i) Indian Pay (Temporary Abatements) Bill.(Reference Cabinet 6(33), Conclusion 4).Memorandum by the Secretary of State forIndia, covering draft Bill.(H.A. 4(33)    -    already circulated).(ii) Foreign Judgments (Reciprocal Enforcement) Bill.Memorandum by the Lord Chancellor, covering draft Bill.(H.A. 1(33)    -    already circulated).(iii) Local Government (General ExchequerContributions)  Bill.Memorandum by the Minister of Health andthe Secretary of State for Scotland, covering draft Bill.(H.A. 3(33)    -   already circulated).(iv) Assurance Companies (Winding up) Bill.Memorandum by the President of the Boardof Trade, covering draft Bill.(H.A, 2(33)    -    already circulated).(v) Children and Young Persons (Consolidation)Bill.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.(CP.  21(33)    -    already circulated).7 4 PRIVATE MEMBERS &apos;   BILLS.For Friday, February 24-th.1. Home and Empire Settlement Bill;(Mrs. Ward (Conservative)).2. Local Elections (Proportional Representation)(Mr. Bernays (Liberal)).(Signed) M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.7th February, 1933.
Q9PRESENT: -The Right Hon. J. Ramsay MaoDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister. (In the Chair).The Right Hon.Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon.The Viscount Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I.,K.C.V.O.,O.B.E.,K.C.,M.P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.P., Secretaryof State for Dominion Affairs.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Londonderry,K.G.,M.V.O., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.F.,.Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,G.B.E.,C.M.G.,M.P., Secretary ofState for India.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,G.B.E. ,M.C.,M.P., Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The Right Hon.Sir Godfrey Collins, K.B.E.,C.M.G.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Scotland.The Right Hon.Sir Edward Hilton Young,G.B.E.,D.S.O.,D.S.C.,M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.,Walter Runciman, M.P.,President of the Board ofTrade.The Right Hon.Sir Bolton Eyres-Monsell,G.B.E,,M.P., First Lord ofthe Admiralty.Major The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C.M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Lord Irwin, K.G.,G.C.S.I.,G.C.I.E., President of theBoard of Education.The Right Hon.Sir Henry Betterton, Bt.,C.B.E..M.P., Minister ofLabour.Major The Right Hon.W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P.,First Commissioner of Works,Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.CB. ,G.CM.G., ............. Secretary.6SECRET. COPY MO.cabinet    7 (55).-    . &apos; -     . .   &apos; - &apos;    &apos; . &apos; &quot;  - . &apos;CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held,at 10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on YffiDNESDAY,February 8th, 1953, at 11,0 a.m.
:he economy(previous reference:Cabinet 6(33), Con-clusion 5.)F.R.1. The attention of the Cabinet was drawn tothe fact that in giving the Answer to Questions onthe subject of Economy Cuts in the House of commons on the previous day, the Prime Minister had omittedthe following words from the Answer as approved bythe Cabinet at the Meeting referred to in the margin:-    &quot;I may add that no increase in these cutshas been considered by the Government&quot;,The Cabinet were reminded that by sub-heads(b) and (c) of the Conclusion referred to in the margin, Ministers had been invited to consider thedraft Answer carefully and, if they saw objection,to communicate with the Prime Minister, who, inconsultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer,was to have authority to vary the wording.The Chancellor of the Exchequer informed theCabinet that almost at the last moment he had learned of an objection urged by the Secretary ofState for Scotland, to meet which, in the short time available, he had felt that there was no alternative but to omit the reference to possible future cuts. .In the course of a short discussion theSecretary of State for Scotland indicated that he did not contemplate any cuts beyond the 10 per cent,which had been mentioned in the Prime ministers statement of September 21, 1931.The Prime Minister suggested that in answeringquestions on this subject his colleagues should be careful not to announce that there would be no furthercuts and to keep within the limits of *j.-units of his statementof September 81, 1931, that the simplest way of
removing just grievances is to limit reductionsas regards teachers, police and the three defence services, to not more than 10 per cent.
MANCHURIA. 8,   The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs drew attention to the false rumours that were being.(Re?Irence: spread in China about British policy at Geneva(llfToon-        in the Chin Japanese dispute over Manchuria,elusion 5.) example, a story had been spread that, we had entered into a bargain with Japan whereby, inreturn for a free hand to her in Manchuria, weshould have a free hand in Tibet.   There was, ofcourse,  absolutely no truth in this suggestion.Nevertheless, these false rumours were having a dangerous effect in China, where there was a particularly pernicious Student Movement.   At thesuggestion of the President of the Board of Tradehe himself had seen Mr Swire, the well-known Chinamerchant, that morning, and this gentleman had undertaken to send a telegram to Shanghai with aview to doing what was possible to quiet thingsdown.    Sir Miles Lamps on reported that the Chinesewere getting somewhat hysterical, and there appearedto be a risk of a boycott of British goods, as in1925, for which there was absolutely no justifica-tion.   At his instance, Reuters Agency were doing their best to correct false impressions.   He had also sent messages to the Parliamentary UnderSecretary of State at Geneva, with the same object.Nevertheless, he was somewhat anxious as to thesituation, particularly in its commercial aspects.The present position, the Secretary of Stateexplained, was that the League was now passing outof the conciliation stage and that almost certainlya Report would&quot; have to be produced,   -he parliamentary under Secretary of State was taking part in the drafting of that Report.   The general trend ofopinion at Geneva was, first, that Japan had broken-3-
the Covenant, and, second, that no recognition ofManchukuo could be contemplated.   He did not think we could avoid taking part in conclusions to this effect.   As regards the second of the above pointshe proposed, in supporting the proposition, to makethe suggestion that if, in the future, circumstancesso develop as to require that this matter should befurther considered, His Majesty&apos;s Government do not wish to act in isolation but would seek to apply the spirit of Article VII of the Mine-Power Treatyso that there shall be the opportunity of communica-tion between the members of the League and the signatories to the Nine-Power Treaty in advance ofany decision that any member of the League might be disposed to take.   This statement, of course, wouldhe made on the basis that other Powers, whethermembers of the League or not, agreed to act in thesame way.   He believed that it was essential to agreeat Geneva to the two points to which he had justreferred, if serious trouble in China was to be avoided.    The Japanese, he thought, could hardlyobject to our adopting this line, as he had alwayswarned their Delegation at Geneva that if coneilia-tion did not succeed we should have to act as goodmembers of the League of Nations.   British publicopinion hitherto had perhaps been somewhat pro-Japanese, but if the Japanese took action which involved the occupation of Tientsin and Peking it was likely to change.The President of the Board of Trade emphasised the strong feeling that was growing up, particularlyin Lancashire, against Japan in consequence of her-4-
very severe competition with British industry.The Secretary of State for the Coloniesindicated that he had done his best to prepareopinion in the Colonial Empire for the possiblenecessity of our having to take special measuresto meet Japanese competition, which was veryserious in some Colonies, and particularly in ceylon.In reply to questions, the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs made it quite clear that if circumstances rendered it necessary, we werenot precluded from recognising Manchukuo, butthat we should first have to consult members ofthe League and the signatories of the Nine-PowerTreaty.    China, of course, would like us to gomuch further and to apply Article XVI of theCovenant, but there could be no question of this.He thought, however, that if we participated inthe LeagueTs Report on the lines he had suggested,that should help to alleviate the situation.Enquiry was made as to the reasons why theChinese Delegation at Geneva was so active instirring up opinion against this country, and itwas suggested, that the aim was to play on theBritish commercial community in Shanghai to put pressure on the Government.The Cabinet approved generally the policy ofthe Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs as setforth above, and the Secretary of State for PoreigiAffairs said he had noted especially a suggestion by the Prime Minister that very close touch shouldbe kept both here and in Geneva with the Chineserepres representatives .
S.   The Cabinet had before them the following documents on the subject of the Control of Mann-facture of Armaments :-A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs (0.P.-2S(33))  in which he stated that the ministerial Disarmament Committeehad accepted certain,conclusions onthe subject of the licensing ofmanufacture of arms .    As the resultor ?his conclusion the United Kingdom- Representative at the DisarmamentConference had been instructed thatwhen the question of control ofmanufacture of armaments by licencecame up for discussion, he should oppose any licensing system whichha^ as a&apos;-basis the idea of controllingand licensing? private manufacturingfirms, on the ground that the numberof these firms was so large that itwas impracticable to attempt tocontrol them by this method;    and to propose that the control of manu-facture of arms could more profitablybe approached from the angle of thecontrol of exports .   The Secretaryof State pointed out that this eon-clusion was a reversal of the policywhich had been approved by the cabinet as long ago as July 25, 1928, and whichhad since been consistently followedby successive United Kingdom Delega-tions at Geneva, namely, to advocatea system of national licences asagainst the proposal of the French andsome other Delegations for a system ofinternational licences:A Note by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (C.P.-24 (35))circulating to the Cabinet, at therequest of the Secretary of State forWar, the Report of an Inter-DepartmentalCommittee upon which the decisions ofthe Ministerial Committee referred toabove was based.In the course of the discussion extracts wereread from a speech by the Secretary of State for Warin the House of Lords on December 8, 1932, in whichhe indicated that the most equitable scheme for control of the private manufacture, of arms wasalong the line of control by licences and publicityof manufacture, operated under the authority of thevarious national Governments rather than by someint international ional authority. :
The President of the Board of Trade, on whoseDepartment was likely to fall the responsibilityfor the administration of any legislation thatmight eventually be passed if an international convention were adopted on this subject, indicated that he could give no idea of the magnitude ofthe staff required, and that his Department had little knowledge of what would be needed.The Cabinet were informed that in the draftConvention now under consideration, which was liableto alteration, it was only proposed to apply thesystem to factories producing complete weapons orfinished essential parts easily recognised ascomponents of such weapons,In view of the statements that had been madeon this subject at Geneva and elsewhere during thelast few years, the Cabinet decided to modify theconclusions of the Ministerial Disarmament Committeeof January 23rd, and agreed  (a) That the United Kingdom delegation at Geneva should continue their opposition to any system of inter-national licences, but should beauthorised to agree to a-system ofnational licences, subject to thefollowing Conclusions:(b) That every care should be taken toavoid giving advantage to thosecountries which rely upon publicmanufacture as opposed to thosewhich r^-Iy upon private manufacture,^his equality of treatment to public and private manufacture must include a provision that any publicity whichis stipulated shall apply to bothkinds of manufacture alike:(c)(d)-7- ^See next pgc^,)
(NOTE:    Conclusion (d) was subject to a reservation by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs thathe must consult his expertsbefore final acceptance of thisproposal.)
Government      the Secretary of State for the colonies (CP.-16 (S3))Policy. &quot; , . .on the subject of Land Policy in Palestine, xn which,(Previous        after full particulars of the present situation, reference:Cabinet 60    asked the Cabinet to approve -(32), Con-clusion 11.) (a) that there shall be no new develop-ment scheme at present:(b) that the register of &quot;landless&quot; Arabsshall be limited to ex-tenants:(c) that the High Commissioner shallbe instructed to prepare and submitplans for re-settling &quot;landless&quot;Arabs registered in accordance withthis definition:(d) that the cost of re-settlement of&quot;landless&quot; Arabs and of certainurgent public works shall be met out of a guaranteed loan:(e) that the High Commissioner shall beauthorised to meet Jewish demands for some equivalent treatment bygranting a contribution from palestine government funds to Jewish   research,and by including in the guaranteedloan provision for a contribution of 10,000 or  20,000 to a Jewishagricultural or educational insti-tution and for the cost, estimatedat  60,000, of a Technical School:(f) that the Protection of CultivatorsOrdinance shall be amended on thelines set out in CP.-16 (33):(g) that no restriction shall be placedon owner-occupiers in disposing oftheir land.The Secretary of State for the .Colonies added that ifthis line of action met with approval, he would discuss with the High Commissioner the steps to betaken to give publicity, here and in Palestine, tothe decisions of His Majesty*s Government.After hearing a statement by the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies, the Cabinet agreed  
(a) To approve the recommendationsof the Secretary of State forthe Colonies in CP.-16 (S3)as summarised above:(b) To take note that the Secretaryof State for the Colonies would look further into the followingprovision that he had proposedto include in the revised Ordinance(CP .-16 (33), Para.21 (3):-&apos;&quot;A tenant who has not paid hisrent not to be evicted withoutat least one year&apos;s notice and compensation for improvements,and even then not to be evictedfrom the minimum area requiredfor subsistence provided hecultivates it fairly.&quot;(c) To take note that the Secretary ofState for the Colonies did not propose to make any announcementuntil he had received the HighCommissioner^ recommendations,which it was understood were likelyto be in accord with C.P.-16 (.33).When an announcement was made,  itwould be in the House of Commons,preferably in Debate, and not bymeans of a White Paper:(d) To take note of certain difficulties that have arisen in Transjordaniaresulting from an application byan American Zionist syndicate forthe lease of lands from the EmirAbdullah, regarding which a furtherDespatch from, the High commissioner of Palestine was expected.-10-
THE ADMINIS- 5. The Cabinet had before them the SecondmRATION OPGROWN LANDS. Report of the Cabinet Committee on Future Govern-ment Responsibility for the Administration of(Previous - , , , ,Reference: Crown Lands (CP .-20 (53)), the recommendationsCabinet 4 ^ ,,     ^        .(33), Con- of which are set forth at the end of the Reportelusion 3.)as follows:-(i) That the ex officio MinisterialCommissioner should,be finally- responsible for the administra-tion of Crown Lands, and that heshould not, as at present, sharethis responsibility with thePermanent Commissioner,(ii) That this object should be achievedeither  (a) by Scheme A, which involves thepassage of legislation providing that the First Commissioner ofWorks shall be the sole Commis-sioner for Crown Lands:    or(b) by Scheme E,. by means of a treasury Minute requiring thePermanent Commissioner forCrown Lands to carry out his duties under the direction ofthe Minister of Agriculture.(iii) That in any case a Standing Committeeshould be appointed on the lines ofparagraph 10 of the Report, and thaton questions involving aesthetic and similar considerations in connectionwith the CrownVs urban estates, theCommissioners of Crown Lands shouldbe required by Treasury Minute to consult with that Standing Committee,mhe Cabinet agreed  (a) That,  in view of the desirabilityof avoiding legislation, Scheme&quot;B&quot; should&quot;be adopted:(b) Subject to (a), to approve therecommendations of the CabinetCommittee as set forth above:(c) That the Prime Minister, as FirstLord of the Treasury, should beresponsible for appointing theStanding Committee referred to in(d) That the Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries should be authorisedto announce the gist of the above conclusions in Debate the same evening.
THE INDIAN PAY(TEMPORARYABATEMENTS)BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 6.(33), Con-c Ins ion 4.)6, The Cabinet had before them a Note bythe Secretary of State for India (H.A.-4 (33))covering the draft Indian Pay (Temporary Abate-ments) Bill, the object of which is to grant tothe Secretary of State in Council the powersnecessary to enable him. to continue during theyear to the 31st March, 1934, to make a temporaryreduction in the salaries of those government servants in India whose pay is fixed or protected by Statute:    together with the following recom-mendation of the Committee of Home Affairs thereon(H.A.C. 1st Conclusions (33), Minute 1) :-To authorise the introduction forthwith in the House of commons of the Indian Pay (Temporary Abate-ments) Bill in the form, of thedraft annexed to H.A.-4 (33),subject to any drafting or other minor alterations that/may befound necessary or desirable,  -with a view to the pas sage ofthe Bill into law before the 31stMarch, 19-33.The Cabinet approved the recommenda-tion of the Committee of Home affairs as set forth above.
THE FOREIGN 7. The Cabinet had before them a MemorandumJUDGMENTS(RECIPROCAL by the Lord Chancellor (H.A.-1 (33)) covering the enforcement)BILL. draft Foreign Judgments (Reciprocal Enforcement)Bill, the object of which is to give effect tothe main recommendation in the Report of LordJustice Greerfs Committee (Cmd. Paper 4213) whichcomprised representatives of the Bar, the law society and the Departments concerned:    togetherwith the following recommendation of the Committeeof Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 1st Conclusions( 33), Minute 2) :-To authorise the introduction inthe House of Lords of the ForeignJudgments  (Reciprocal Enforcement)Bill in the form of the draft annexed to H.A.-1 (33), subject toany drafting or other minor alterations which may be foundnecessary or desirable .The Cabinet approved the recommendationof the Committee of Home Affairs asset forth above.
LOCAL GOVERN- 8. The Cabinet had before them a MemorandumMENT  (GENERALEXCHEQUER CON- by the Minister of Health and the Secretary ofTRIBUTIONS) , .&quot;,    ;BILL. State for Scotland (H.A.-3 (33)), covering thedraft Local Government (General Exchequer Contri-but ions) Bill, the object of which was todetermine the amount of certain payments to bemade during the second fixed grant period underthe Local Government Act,  1929, and the LocalGovernment (Scotland) Act, 1929:    together withthe following recommendation of the Committee ofHome Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 1st Conclusions (33),Minute 3):-To authorise the introduction inthe House of Commons of the LocalGovernment (General ExchequerContributions) Bill, in the formof the draft annexed to H.A.-3 (33),subject to any drafting or other minor alterations which may befound necessary or desirable,with a view to the passage of theBill into law before the 31st march next.The Cabinet approved the above recom-mendation-  of the Committee of HomeAffairs, subject to further discussion between the Chancellor of the Exchequer,the Secretary of State for Scotlandand the Minister of Health on the subjectof the amount allocated to Scotland.
ASSURANCE 9.  The Cabinet had before them a MemorandumCOMPANIES(WINDING-UP) by the President of the Board of Trade (&quot;H.A.-2BILL.(33)), covering the draft Assurance Companies(Winding-Up) Bill:    together with the following recommendation of the Committee of Home affairs thereon (.H.A.C. 1st Conclusions, (]33), Minute 4):-To authorise the intrcduct ionforthwith in the House of commons of the Assurance Companies (Winding-Up) Bill, in the form of the draft&quot;annexed to H.A.-2 (33), subject toany drafting or other alterationswhich may be found necessary or desirable.The Cabinet agreed-  That the above Bill should beintroduced in the House of Lordsinstead of in the House of Commons.
THE children and YOUNGPERSONS (CON-SOLID AT ION)BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 40(32), Con-clusion 1.)10. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the Home Secretary (CP.-21 (33)) relative tothe Children and Young Persons (Consolidation)Bill, the object of which was to consolidate theAct of last Session with the unrepealed provisionsof the Children Act, 1908, and other enactmentsdealing with the protection of young people:together with the following recommendation of theCommittee of Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 1stConclusions (33), Minute 5):-To authorise the introduction forthwith in the House of lords of the Children and Young Persons(Consolidation) Bill.The Cabinet approved the above recommend-ation of the Committee of Home Affairs.-16-
THE HOME and empire SETTLE-MENT BILL.11. The Cabinet had tinder consideration theHome and Empire Settlement Bill, to be introduced in the House of Commons by a Private Member onFriday, February 24th.The Cabinet approved the proposal of the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs that he should adopt a favourable attitude towardsthe above Bill, but not to allowit to proceed further.
THE LOCAL 12, The Cabinet had under consideration theELECTIONS(PROPORTIONAL Local Elections (Proportional Representation)REPRESENT A-TION) BILL. Bill, to be introduced in the House of Commons^-p,  - a^is by a Private Member on Friday, February 24th.The Cabinet took note that thiswas a matter for the Home Secretary.18.
NEXT MEETINGOF CABINET .13.The Cabinet agreed -15th, at 4 p.m., in the PrimeMinister&apos;s Room at the House ofCommons, for the purpose of considering the question ofTEE BRITISH WAR DEBT 70 THEUNITED STATES OF AMERICA.8, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,February 8, 1933.

</content>
</cab>
