<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/75/0 images: 404-413</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
c ret.COPY NO.CABINET    24 ( 33).iMeeting of the Cabinet to be held in the PrimeMinister&apos;s Room, House ef Commons, S.W.1,on WEDNESDAY, April 5th,  1933, at  .0 p.m.AGENDA.1. TAXATION OF CO-OPERATIVE RESERVES.(Reference Cabinet 9(53), Conclusion 7).2. THE IRISH FREE STATE SITUATION.3. CONCLUSIONS OF THE HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.ii.A.C.  5th Conclusions (33)    -   already circulated.Road and Rail Traffic Bill.(Reference Cabinet 5(33), Cone: conclusion 4).Memorandum by the Minister of Transport,covering draft Bill.(H.A.  11(33)    -   already circulated)-.4.  PRIVATE MEMBERS&apos;   BILLS.For Friday, April 7th.1. Seditious and Blasphemous Teaching ofChildren Bill.    (Sir R. Craddock (Conservative).)2. Protection of Dogs Bill.(Sir R. Gower (Conservative)).3. Coal Mines (Protection of Animals) Bill.(Sir R. Gower (Conservative)).(Signed)    M..P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet,Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.I  5th April,  1933.
C R .E T.COPY NO,CABINET    84 (33).CONCLUSIONS of a meeting of the Cabinet heldin the Prime Minister&apos;s Room, House-ofCommons,  on Wednesday, 5th April, 1933,at 9.0 p.m.PRESENT:The Right Hon. J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister. (in the Chair),IfRight Hon.panley Baldwin, M.P. ,lord President of the Council.Il Right Hon.Ifr John Gilmour, Bt. , D, S.O. ,II?., Secretary of State forlime Affairs.llRight Hon.ike Viscount Hail sham,Secretary of State for War.ifRight Hon.pr Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.B.E.,iC.:M,G. , M.P. , Secretary oi&apos;gate for India.Right Hon.pr Philip Cunliffe-Lister,S.B.S. , M.C., M.P. , SecretaryB State for the Colonies.(Right Hon.m Godfrey Collins, K.B.E. ,fM.G. , M.P., Secretary ofptate for Scotland.Might Hon.WP Henry Betterton, Bt.,Ip-E. , M.P. 9 Minister of13 our.The Right Hon.Neville Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Right Hon.The Viscount Sankey,G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I.,K.C.V.O.,  O.B.E., K.C., M.P .,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs..The Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.P,, Secretaryof State for Dominion AffairsThe Most Hon.The Marquess of Londonderry,&apos;K.G.L.V.O., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Sir Bolten Eyres-Monsell,G.B.E. , M.P. , First Lori. ofthe Admiralty.Major The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C., M.P. ,Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries.Major the Right Hon.W.  Ormsby-Gore, M.P.,First Commissioner of Works,THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT;The Hon. Oliver 0.Stanley,M.C., M.P., Minister ofTransport.(For Conclusions 2 and 3).Nel Sir M.PiA, Hankey, G.C.B., G.C.M.G.Secretary.
00-OPBRA?IVESOCIETIES.proposedTaxationof.(previous reference:Cabinet 23(33),  Con-clusion 9 .)1. The Cabinet resumed the discussion begun thesame morning on the question of the proposed taxation of Co-operative Societies .   They were reminded thatin his Budget Statement last year the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer had laid some stress on the importanceof reaching an agreement on this long-standing issue,and this had been one of the principal objects forwhich the Committee had been set up.While there was a general recognition that theReport of the Committee could not be set aside withoutgood reason, the Cabinet were informed that theCommittee&apos;s Report would not meet with general aecept-ance and that its adoption would not lead to a perman-ent settlement.    It was recalled that an attempt toreach an agreement with the Co-operative Societieson the basis of the Report failed owing to theopposition of the political elements .    It was recog-nised also that not much money was involved in the taxation proposals of the Committee.In these circumstances the question was mootedas to whether it was worth while to raise thepolitical difficulties involved in implementing theReport .    In this connection the Cabinet were reminded that Parliamentary opinion on this subject was divided, but not exclusively on Party lines.   Thiswas reflected to some extent In the discussions ofthe Cabinet itself, although there was an earnestdesire on all sides to find some just solution thatwould meet the very real difficulties of both points of view.    It was recognised that if the Co-operative societies were not subjected to any further IncomeTax the grievances of the retail traders would notbe met:   while, on the other hand, if the report were adopted in extenso the Co-operative Societies
-would, protest that their principle of mutuality wasinfringed,The Chancellor of the Exchequer (to whose concilia-tory attitude members of the Cabinet paid warmtributes) enquired whether it might not still bepossible to find some reasonable basis of agreementwith the Co-operative Societies .    The Cabinet wereadvised, however, by those members who were best ableto gauge the position, that,  judged by the failure of previous efforts to find, an accommodation, there wasno reasonable prospect of a successful negotiation onthe merits of the case.   More especially after the big effort that had been made by the Co-operative societies on the previous day to exert pressure on individual Members of Parliament by mass propaganda,it was felt that any overtures were likely to betreated merely as a symptom of weakness .   No memberof the Cabinet was disposed to yield to such methods.In these circumstances it was felt that if some reasonable solution could be found which was acceptable to the Cabinet as a whole, it would be better topresent it to Parliament as the decision of theGovernment.In the course of a prolonged discussion, whichranged over the aspects of law, equity, finance and policy, various tentative suggestions were made for asolution:    for example, to tax trading profits of stores on sales to non-members, which was stated to be practicable and not unacceptable to the Co-operative societies, while going some way to meet the grievancesof private traders:    or to find some system whichwould enable the Co-operative Societies to compoundtheir taxation, as had been done in the case ofBuilding Societies ,
The Chancellor of the Exchequer undertook toexamine the question with his Department in thelight of the discussion and to see if he could find some basis for a settlement, and to report to theCabinet, if possible, at their next Meeting,
rppIB BATTERS FAPOWER STATION,(previous reference cabinet 23(33), Con-elusion 10.)2.   The Minister of Transport informed the Cabinetthat the Chelsea Borough Council that afternoon had decided not to raise objection to the applicationof the London Power Company, Ltd.   All the localauthorities concerned were now in agreement.   Heraised the question as to whether the Secretary ofState for Air&apos;s pledge in the House of Lords wotildbe met by an answer to a Question in the House ofCommons.The Secretary of State for War, as Leader of theHouse of Lords, had no objection, as a Question could also be put in the House of Lords, if desired, andthe Secretary of State for Air was satisfied that hispledge would be met by an answer in either House ofParliament.The Cabinet agreed  That the Minister of transport should arrange to answer a question in the House of Commons on thesubject.
transport policy.rp^e Road and[Rail TrafficBill.](previous Reference:1 Cabinet 5j (33), Con-I elusion 4.)3,  The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Minister of Transport (H.A.-11 (33)) covering the draft Road and Rail Traffic Bill, the objectof which was to give effect to a scheme of licensing and regulation of goods motor vehicles based on therecommendations in the final Report of the RoyalCommission on Transport, and also to certain ofthe recommendations of the Salter Report:    togetherwith the following recommendation of the Committeeof Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 5th Conclusions  (33));To authorise the introduction inthe House of Commons forthwith ofthe Road and Rail Traffic Bill Inthe form of the draft annexed with.A.-11 (33), subject to the amendments adopted at the meeting,and subject also to any drafting orother minor alterations that may befound necessary or desirable, onthe understanding that arrangements will be made to secure that theSecond Reading of the Bill willbe taken before the Easter Recess.The Secretary of State for Scotland raised thequestion as to whether, when the Tribunal wasdealing with Scottish cases, the Chairman would besettled in consultation with some Scottish authority.The Minister of Transport explained that appro-priate provisions had been made.    In the appointmentof Deputy Chairmen to the Tribunal the Lord Presidentof the Court of Sessions would be consulted in scottish cases .The Cabinet agreed  ,To approve the recommendationof the Committee of Home affairs as set forth above.
tpPE SEDITIOUS0V BLASPHE-MOUS TEACHINGOP CHILDRENBILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 72(30), Con-clusion 13.)pRD7AmEMEMBERS&apos;BILLS .GovernmentAttitvidetowards .(previous reference:Cabinet 22(33), Con-clusion 14.)4. The Cabinet had under consideration theSeditious and Blasphemous Teaching of ChildrenBill, to be introduced in the House of Commons bya Private Member on Friday, April 7th.The Prime Minister referred once more to thedesirability of leaving Friday&apos;s Bills as much aspossible to Private Members, with a minimum ofGovernment intervention, though he recognised thaton occasions some expression of the attitude of theGovernment was unavoidable.The Cabinet agreed . That the Home Secretary should beresponsible for watching the Billfrom the point of view of theGovernment.-6-
THE PROTECTIONOP DOGS BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 9(33), Con-elusion 9 ,)f.r.j)^7)/7.5. The Cabinet had under consideration theProtection of Dogs Bill, to be introduced in theHouse of Commons by a Private Member on Friday,April 7th,The Cabinet were given to understand that, evenif time was available for discussion of this Bill,it might be dropped.
THE COAL MINES 6.The Cabinet had under consideration the Coal(PROTECTION OPANIMALS) BILL,   Mines (Protection of Animals) Bill, to be introduced in the House of Commons by a Private Member on(previous reference: Friday, April 7th,Cabinet 16(31), Con- The Cabinet agreed  elusion 14.)^hat if this Bill was reached, theHome Secretary should be responsiblefor watching it on behalf of theGovernment,2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,April 5, 19 33.

</content>
</cab>
