<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/1/16 images: 156-164</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT

Printed for the War Cabinet. September 1939.

SECRET.

W.M. (39)

16th Conclusions.

Copy No.

TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.

It is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this dooument.

WAR CABINET 16 (39).

CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held on Friday, September 15, 1939, at 11-45 a.m.

Present

The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain

The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C., M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.

Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon. Lord Chatfield, Minister for Coordination of Defence (Items 1-15).

The Right Hon. L. Hore-Belisha, M.P., Secretary of State for War.

The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.

, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).

The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,

Secretary   of   State   for Foreign

Affairs (Items 1-15). The    Right    Hon.    Winston S.

Churchill, M.P., First Lord of the

Admiralty. The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,

M.P., Secretary of State for Air. The   Right   Hon.   Lord Hankey,

Minister without Portfolio.

The following were also present

The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson, M.P., Secretary of State for the Home Department and Minister of Home Security (Items 1-8).

The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P., President of the Board of Trade (Item 16).

The Right Hon. Sir R. Dorman-Smith, M.P., Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries (Item 16).

Sir Horace J. Wilson, Permanent Secretary to the Treasury.

Admiral of the Fleet Sir Dudley Pound, First Sea Lord and Chief of Naval Staff (Items 1-15).

The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P., Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs (Items 1-15).

The Right Hon. L. Burgin, M.P., Minister of Supply (Item 16).

Mr. R. H. Cross, M.P., Minister of Economic Warfare (Item 16).

Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.

Newall,  Chief of the Air Staff

(Items 1-15). General Sir W. Edmund Ironside,

Chief of the Imperial General Staff

(Items 1-15).

Secretariat. Sir Edward Bridges. Major-General H. L. Ismay. Colonel L. C. Hollis, R.M. Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N. Mr. F. Hemming. Mr. W. D. Wilkinson. Mr. A. Bevir.

[20004]

b


WAR CABINET 16 (39).

Contents.

Minute

\!o. Subject. Page

1 The Air Situation ...... ............ 121

2 Report of RA.F. Raid on German Naval Bases on the

4th September    ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...&quot; 121

3 The Naval Situation.................. 121

Communique on operations against submarines. Munitions for Turkey.

4 Eire ........................ 121

Naval Facilities.

5 Transfer of German Shipping to Neutral Flags....., 122

Transfer to Italian Flag.

Proposed purchase of German ships by Portugal.

6 The Military Situation in Poland............ 122

7 The Military Situation in France............ 122

8 Air Operations and Intelligence ...... ...      ... 122

9 The Balkans   ... .................. 122

10 Roumanian Oil Supplies     ... ...... ...      ... 123

11 Italy ........................ 123

12 The Far Eastern Situation............... 124

13 Belgium ..................... 124

14 Turkey........................ 124

15 Commercial Relations with the Soviet Union ...... 125


121

W.M. 16 (39).

The Air 1.   The Secretary of State for Air said that he had nothing

Situation.        special to report.

(Previous Reference was made to the report in telegram No. 42 from

Reference: Copenhagen of a concentration of aircraft in the Island of Sylt. W.M. (39) 15th Xhe War Cabinet invited the Chief of the Air Staff to

Conclusions, examine the information regarding the air reinforcement

Mmute l.) 0f the Island of Sylt, and to arrange for such recon-

naissance as the results of this examination might indicate to be desirable.

Report of R.A.F. Raid on German Naval Bases on 4th September. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 3rd Conclusions, Minute 8.)

2. The Prime Minister referred to the account issued from the Ministry of Information and appearing in the morning&apos;s newspapers of the R.A.F. attack on German naval bases on the 4th September. The statements in this account as to our losses were, he thought, misleading, and gave the impression that our losses had been less than was the fact.

The Secretary of State for Air said that he could not account for this statement, which had not been authorised by the Air Ministry.

The War Cabinet invited the Lord Privy Seal to investigate this matter, in consultation with the Minister for Information.

The Naval 3.   The First Lord of the Admiralty reported that three

Situation. merchant vessels, all inward bound, had been sunk during the (Previous previous twenty-four hours. Inward convoys would be in operation Reference: in four or five days time. There had been a number of further W.M. (39) 15th attacks on German submarines. One had been sunk, 2 Officers and Conclusions, 43 men being taken prisoners. Item 2.)

Communique At the suggestion of the First Lord of the Admiralty, the

on operations    War Cabinet agreed : 

agamst thsA a communique should be issued to the effect that a

submarines. large number of attacks had been made against German

submarines by our warships and R.A.F. aircraft; that a number of submarines had been sunk; and that some survivors had been rescued and were now prisoners of war.

With reference to the statement made at the previous Meeting of the War Cabinet in regard to the transport of munitions to Turkey, The First Lord of the Admiralty said that it had now been found possible to arrange for the ship carrying these munitions to proceed direct to Istanbul and not, as previously thought necessary, to go first to Port Said.

Munitions for Turkey.

(Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 15th Conclusions, Minute 2.)

Eire.

Naval Facilities. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 6th Conclusions, Minute 5.)

4. The First Lord of the Admiralty stated that the prisoners taken from the German submarine whose sinking is reported in Minute 3 had said that they had been ashore in Eire, and had been found to be in possession of Irish cigarettes. This information, he thought, might provide a useful lever for persuading the Eire Government to allow us the use of Berehaven as a base for Destroyers and Flying-boats. A boom was ready to be placed in position at Berehaven.

The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that a representative of this country, who had been over in Dublin during the last two days, had seen Mr. de Valera and was returning that afternoon. He (the Secretary of State) undertook to pursue this matter as energetically as possible, but he was afraid that Mr. de Valera&apos;s attitude was not likely to be very helpful.

The War Cabinet took note that the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, in consultation with the First Lord of

[20004]

b 2


122

the Admiralty, would continue negotiations with the Government of Eire with a view to ports in Southern Ireland being placed at our disposal for use by Naval

forces.

Transfer of 5.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs referred to the

German telegram which he had sent to Rome (Telegram No. 495) informing

Shipping to      our Ambassador that transfer of merchant ships to a neutral flag Neutral Flags,   after the outbreak of war was illegal, and that the Italian Govern-Trans fer to      ment had themselves subscribed to this rule. Italian Flag.

Proposed Pur- The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that a telegram

chase of German had been received from Portugal to the effect that the Portuguese ships by Government would like to purchase German merchant ships now in

Portugal. their ports.   Our right course was to dissuade them from making

this purchase and thereby giving Germany some exchange which

would be valuable to her.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.

The Military 6.   The Chief of the Imperial General Staff explained that the

Situation in military situation in Poland had greatly deteriorated since the last Poland. meeting of the War Cabinet.  In the south-east Marshal Smygly-

(Previous Rydz was attempting, with a force of five divisions, to establish a Eeference: position with his left flank at the junction of the Slovakian-W.M. (39) 15th Hungarian frontier, in order to safeguard the corridor into Conclusions, Roumania.

Minute 3.) In view of the gravity of the military situation in Poland, a

discussion took place as to what action should be taken in regard to munitions now on their way to Poland. The War Cabinet agreed : 

that the Chiefs of Staff Committee should consider, in consultation with the Foreign Office, what action should be taken with regard to the various consignments of war stores which were already on their way to Poland or were about to be despatched to Poland.

The Military 7.   The Chief of the Imperial General Staff informed the War

Situation In Cabinet of the latest information which he had received from

France. General Gamelin regarding operations on the western front. An

(Previous account of this discussion is recorded on the Secretary&apos;s standard

Eeference: file of Conclusions.

W.M. (39) 15th Conclusions, Minute 3.)

Air Operations 8. The War Cabinet took note of the first weekly report by and Intelligence, the Secretary of State for Air on Air Operations and Intelligence

(Previous        (Paper W.P.(39) 28).

Reference: W.M. (39) 7th Conclusions, Minute 14.)

The Balkans. 9.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs informed the

(Previous War Cabinet that he had discussed the question of Anglo-French

Reference: co-operation in the Balkans with the French Ambassador on the

W.M. (39) 15th previous day, and it was now clear that the French Government

Conclusions, agreed with our general point of view.   In view of the highly fluid

Minute 8.) nature of the present situation, he (the Secretary of State) thought


93

123 W.M. 16 (39).

that it was urgent that the War Cabinet should consider as soon as possible what their course of action should be in the event of a German attack on Roumania, on various possible assumptions as to the attitude of Italy. It was most important that, having reached our own conclusions in this matter, we should be able at once to concert our future action with the French Government.

The Chief of the Air Staff said that this question was already under consideration by the Chiefs of Staff Committee, and he hoped that it would be possible to submit their conclusions to the War Cabinet very shortly. He would take any steps that might be necessary to ensure that the Foreign Office was kept in the closest touch with the preparation of this report.

The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attention to telegram No. 215 from His Majesty&apos;s Minister, Belgrade, stating that Prince Paul did not propose to act precipitately in the matter of calling upon Bulgaria to declare her position, and that he proposed in the first place to consult the Turkish Government. The Secretary of State added that there was no indication as yet what the Turkish view was on this matter, but their reply was expected shortly.

The view was expressed that, in view of the present situation, our policy should be to encourage Yugoslavia to establish contact with Turkey. Bulgaria was, in fact, the key to the Balkans, and every effort should be made to secure that pressure was put upon her by Yugoslavia and Turkey, and if possible, by Roumania.

The War Cabinet agreed : 

To give consideration to the question of the course of action to be followed in the event of a German attack upon Roumania immediately upon receipt of a report on this subject, now in course of preparation by the Chiefs of Staff Committee, with a view to reaching an agreement with the French Government on the action to be taken by the Allies.

Roumanian Oil 10.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attention

Supplies. to telegram 399, dated the 13th September, 1939, received from His

(Previous Majesty&apos;s Minister, Bucharest, stating that if he were to give effect Reference: *  the order conveyed to him in accordance with the decision reached &quot;W.M. (39) 13th Dv the War Cabinet at the meeting noted in the margin to charter Conclusions a^ available barges and rail tank cars in Roumania, without at the Minute 10)&apos; same time being able to purchase future Roumanian oil supplies, the Roumanian Government would be placed in the most difficult position vis-a-vis Germany.

The Chancellor of the Exchequer stated thathehad himself taken immediate action to consult the Departments concerned with a view to purchasing the Roumanian oil in question. The majority of Departments had signified their concurrence in the plan which he had laid before them, and he did not doubt that it would be possible to take immediate action on the lines recommended by the British Minister in Bucharest.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statement, and approved the action proposed to be taken.

Italy. 11.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attention

(Previous to a telegram received late the previous evening from His Majesty&apos;s

Reference: Ambassador, Rome, stating that he had been informed by Count

W.M. (39) 15th Ciano that arrangements had been made for one of the leading

Conclusions, Italian economic experts to meet a representative of the French

Minute 11.) Government to discuss economic matters.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.


124

The Far 12.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs stated that the

Eastern situation in the Far East was now better, than he had anticipated at

Situation. the meeting of the War Cabinet held on the previous day. A tele-(Previous gram which had recently been received from Sir A. Clark Kerr, at Reference.- Shanghai, showed that the meeting of the Japanese Defence Council W.M. (39) 15th had not resulted in any peremptory demands being made to us. His Conclusions, Majesty&apos;s Ambassador, Tokyo, had persuaded the Japanese Govern-Minute 12.) ment to exercise a restraining influence on the local Japanese authorities in Shanghai.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.

Belgium. 13   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs called the

(Previous        attention of the War Cabinet to telegram 78, dated the 14th Septem-Reference:       ber, 1939, from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador, Brussels, reporting that W.M. (39) 14th there was little prospect of the Belgian Government agreeing to Conclusions,      establish contacts between the British and French military author-Minute 5.)       jties on the one hand, and their own military authorities on the other,  but  suggesting means  for  one  further approach to the Belgian Government on this matter.   In view of the latest appreciation of the military situation (see Minute 7 above), this question had now assumed even greater importance.

The Chief of the Imperial General Staff explained the disastrous results which, from the military point of view, would accrue to Belgium if, through refusing to permit the establishment of military contacts at the present time, she were to be invaded by Germany after that country had overrun the Netherlands.

The War Cabinet agreed : 

(a) that the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should con-

sider the despatch to Brussels of some special emissary (who must be a civilian), to impress upon the Belgian Government the gravity of the present situation and the urgency of the need for the establishment of contacts between the British and French military authorities on the one hand, and the Belgian military authorities on the other; and that, if he were to recommend the adoption of this course, he should advise the War Cabinet as to a suitable person to undertake the mission :

(b) that the Chiefs of Staff Committee should prepare, as soon

as possible, a report for the guidance of whoever should be asked to undertake the Mission:

(c) that further consideration should be given to the suggestion

to advise His Majesty The King that he should address a personal letter on this matter to the King of the Belgians.

Turkey. 14.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs stated that a

(Previous telegram dated the 15th September (No. 448) from His Majesty&apos;s Reference: Ambassador, Ankara, showed that the Turkish Government had W.M. (39) 15th decided to maintain in full their original financial demands as a Conclusions, condition of signing the proposed Treaty. This left a gap of Minute 10.)       33 millions between the last British offer and the Turkish demand.

This sum was made up of (a) a credit of  25 millions for the purchase of armaments, not necessarily to be expended in the&apos; United Kingdom, and (b) the sum of  8 millions for unblocking Turkish credits outside the United Kingdom. In the face of these demands, it was necessary to decide whether we should agree to pay the ransom demanded by the Turkish Government, or whether we should refuse to do so, realising the risks which this course involved.


94

t     125 W.M. 16 (39).

In the course of the discussion which ensued, the following points were made : 

(i) It was not clear whether paragraph 7 of the Ambassador&apos;s telegram meant that we should be bound to deliver in Turkey all the armaments promised before the Turkish Government&apos;s obligations became effective, or whether it meant only that we should put Turkey in a position to buy all these armaments. This ambiguity should be cleared up as soon as possible.

(ii) The line now taken by the Turkish Government definitely

suggested that they were playing for time and did not wish to commit themselves until, after the fall of Poland, it was clear whether Germany intended to attack Roumania. (On the other hand, the Roumanian Government were confident that, if they were attacked by Germany, the Turkish Government would honour their obligations and send troops to their aid.)

(iii) In the circumstances which had now arisen there would

be no advantage in increasing our financial offers in the hopes of securing the proposed Treaty with Turkey.

(iv) In view of the German threat to Roumania, and the risk

that Bulgaria might rejoin her former allies, with consequent grave threat to Turkey, it was Turkey rather than the United Kingdom whose vital interests now demanded the conclusion of the proposed Anglo-Turkish Treaty.

(v) It was essential that the attitude of the Turkish Govern-

ment should be clarified at the earliest possible moment.

(vi) Steps should be taken at once to leave the Turkish

Government in no possible doubt in regard either to the gravity of the situation or to the line which we proposed to take.

The War Cabinet agreed : 

That the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should at once address a telegram to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador, Ankara, setting out the views of His Majesty&apos;s Government as disclosed in the discussion summarised above, and directing him to explain the position frankly to the Turkish Government, at the same time pointing out the dangers inherent in the general situation which was now developing.

Commercial 15.   The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the

Relations with President of the Board of Trade (Paper W.P.(G.)(39) 7) on com-the Soviet mercial relations with the Soviet Union, indicating that under the Union.  10,000,000 Credit Agreement with the Soviet Government about

 1 million of goods was due to be shipped during the next few weeks, consisting mainly of machinery. Export licences for these had been held up or refused; and the Soviet Union on their part had done everything to delay shipments to the United Kingdom, the most important commodity affected being softwood, for which EBgf there was an urgent demand in this country.

The President of the Board of Trade pointed out that, since the paper (W.P.(G.)(39) 7) had been circulated, it had transpired that the Admiralty had already requisitioned a large proportion of the machine tools.

The First Lord of the Admiralty said that the machine tools and machinery in question were of great importance, and he urged that none of this machinery should be allowed to go to Russia, and that timber should be obtained from other sources.


126

The Chancellor of the Exchequer admitted the gravity of the timber problem, but suggested that consideration should be given to obtaining timber from Portugal, Roumania and the United Kingdom, and possibly by requisitioning or controlling the use of timber in this country.

The Minister of Supply said that he was in the dual position of wanting timber and also wanting machinery, but on the whole his advice was that the timber was more urgently required than the machinery. The urgency was due to the fact that it would not be possible to clear the timber from the White Sea ports after the middle of October.

Some discussion ensued as to whether it would not be possible to meet the need for hutments by billeting or by some alternative building scheme.

The Prime Minister pointed out that experience in the Ottawa negotiations showed that it would not be at all easy to obtain suitable timber properly prepared from Canada. He understood from the Foreign Secretary that the best channel by which to approach the Soviet Government would be through Sir William Seeds in Moscow, and not through M. Maisky, as proposed in Paper W.P.(G.)(39) 7.

The War Cabinet agreed :  (i) that the timber situation presented acute difficulty, and that it was therefore necessary to consider closely whether some effort should not be made to secure the Russian timber by the completion, or, alternatively, the partial completion, of the transactions with the Soviet Union under the ten million credit Agreement, and that this must be considered forthwith in view of the closure of the White Sea ports after mid-October: (ii) that the Foreign Secretary should ask Sir William Seeds whether he thought that an approach to the Government of the Soviet Union with the object of the completion or partial completion of the Agreement would be likely to meet with success, if it was decided to take that course:

(iii) that in the meantime the Foreign Secretary should, in

consultation with the President of the Board of Trade, prepare draft telegraphic instructions to Sir William Seeds so that these could be despatched at once if it were decided to attempt to negotiate for either the completion, or, alternatively, the partial completion, of the Agreement:

(iv) that the Minister of Supply should prepare a statement

showing the extent to which the machine tools and machinery and other equipment due to be shipped to Russia in the next few weeks were required for, and could be used for, immediate munitions production:

(v) that the Minister of Supply should prepare a statement

indicating what would be the effect on the essential building programmes of failure to acquire the Russian timber and whether and to what extent it would be possible to supply essential soft wood requirements from some other source, either at home or abroad :

(vi) that the matter should be reconsidered at once as soon as

the information asked for was available:

(vii) that, if it were decided to allow the transactions to

continue, it would be essential to take steps to ensure that the Soviet Union fulfilled their side of the bargain.

Richmond Terrace, S. W. 1, September 15, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
