<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/189/23 images: 241-270</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*his DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S government cp(76) 23 COPY NO        8124 May 1976CABINETWHITE PAPER ON THE CHILDREN AND YOUNG PERSONS ACT 1969Note by the Secretary of State for the Home Department, theSecretary of State- fox Wales, the Secretary of State for social services and the Secretary of State for Education and ScienceWe attach for the information of our colleagues copies of the White Paper,Cmnd 6494, on the Children and Young Persons Act 1969 in response to theEleventh Report of the Expenditure Committee for the Session 1974-75.The White Paper is to be published at 2. 30 pm on Wednesday 26 May 1976.RHIJ MD EF W m home Office24 May 1976
HOME OFFICEWELSH office department OF HEALTH AND SOCIAL SECURITYDEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION AND SCIENCECHILDREN AND YOUNG persons act 1969Observations on the Eleventh Reportfrom the Expenditure committee presented to Parliament by the Secretary of Statefor the Home Department, the Secretary of Statefor Wales, the Secretary of State for social services and the Secretary of State for education and ScienceMay 1976LONDONHER MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICE45p net cmnd. 6494
CHILDREN AND YOUNG PERSONS ACT 1969INTRODUCTION1. The Government welcome tie Eleventh Report of the expenditure committee, published la September 1975, on the Children and YoungPersons Act 1969. Since the Expenditure Committee first began to con-sider the subject in December 1973 the Government have themselvesreviewed the working of the Act. Both studies were motivated by thesame serious concern about juvenile crime, and about the operation ofthe law and the treatment system.2. The greater part of the statement of the Governments views which follows is takes tip, inevitably, with detailed comments on the Committee^individual recommendations, in which the Government put forward a number of specific proposals aimed at improving the operation of theAct. This does not mean that the Government see the response to theproblem of juvenile delinquency exclusively or even primarily in termsof statutory arrangements for dealing with children who break the lawand come before the courts. The Expenditure Committee make a similarpoint in the concluding passage (paragraph 167) of their Report, wherethey remark that no legislation can be expected to nave a significant effort on the general level of delinquency and general juvenile mis-behaviour. The underlying personal, social and environmental factors are too complex and too deep rooted to be readily susceptible to influenceby legislative means. Other aspects of social and economic policy must play an important part even though it may not be an easily demon-demonstrated or measured part in making or marring the adjustment of young people to the demands made on them, and the opportunities created forthem or. more importantly, not created for them by society. The quality of parental care; the support that society gives-financially and in otherways to parents; the kind of housing available for families, especiallyin our inner urban areas, and the environment in which it is set; educa-tional provision; recreational and other leisure facilities; the job oppor-tunities available to young people, especially those who leave school early and with few skills: atl these aspects of our national life, and othersbesides, undoubtedly have a bearing on juvenile behaviour. All are mattersof Government concern, difficult though it may be, especially in our presentconstrained circumstances, to bring forward proposals for rapid improve-ment. To do more than Hsi all these factors would be beyond the scopeof the present statement. Nevertheless, they are part of the wider contextthat must not be forgotten in a quest for an improvement of the statutoryarrangements for dealing with juvenile offending.3. As regards these statutory arrangements, the Governmenfs broadconclusion, which is in line with the Expenditure Committee^, is that,though much remains to be done to make the Act fully operative and effective, and although a small number of highly publicised cases havegiven cause for concern, the framework provided by the Act for dealingconstructively and humanely with children in trouble remains a funda-mentally sound one. At the same time, the Government fully recogniseand share the widespread anxiety that is felt, especially by magistrates.
about the continuing problem of how to cope with a small minority,among delinquent children, of serious and persistent offenders. It is inthis area, as the Expenditure Committee observed, that present measuresunder the Act are felt to be falling short.4. There is, and has for a long time been, a bask dilemma here inour policy towards juvenile delinquency (and, indeed, it is reflected inpenal policy generally). On the one hand there is a strongly felt and under-standable demand for the public to be protected from serious andpersistent, albeit youthful, offenders. On the other hand there is a wide-spread revulsion against holding young people in secure custody, especiallycustody of the kind that resembles prison. This reluctance is reinforced by the accumulated evidence over the years that custodial treatment has very disappointing results.5. The 1969 Act did not create this dilemma. The provisions in it which would do most to shift the balance away from custodial sentenceshave not yet been implemented and, for the most part, must for thepresent remain so. The courts still have available to them the sentence ofborstal training for young persons aged IS and 16, and detention centres forboys aged 14 and above. They can still send boys and girls aged 14 and above to prison service establishments on remand. The Government accept these facts with reluctance, especially in view of their serious consequences for the planning and provision of the services which are the responsibilityof the Home Office Prison Department. However, the Government attachparticular importance to the phasing out of remands of juveniles to prisonestablishments at the earliest opportunity, and propose to end such remandsfor girls of 14 almost immediately. Particulars of the Government^proposals are given in paragraphs 13 to 21.6. The Act has been much criticised for what is seen as the loss ofcontrol over juvenile offenders represented by the former approved schoolorder, for which the care order, as administered by local authorities is felt by many magistrates and others to be an inadequate substitute. this criticism tends to overlook the fact that approved schools were not secure;the considerable amount of absconding that took place from them- the poor &quot;success rate&quot; measured by reconvictions;. and the strong criticismexpressed of the isolation of the schools from the mainstream of childcare. Nevertheless, the Government acknowledge that magistrates in par-ticular do not feel full confidence in the care order, particularly for thoseminority of cases where they feel society needs to be protected fromserious and persistent offenders. The Governments proposals in response to the Expenditure Committee recommendations 3 and 4 accept that thecourts have a claim to a greater say in what becomes of such childrenwhom they place in local authority care. Proposals to this effect are inparagraphs 23 to 30; the working of the arrangements proposed would be reviewed after a year. The position should also be eased by the increasein the amount of local authority secure accommodation assisted by directgrants under the new power in the Children Act 1975, and by concertedefforts to make the best use of the accommodation available (Daraeranlnj41 to 43). P ragrapns
7. Additionally, in comments below on particular recommendations theGovernment propose to seek improved measures for the enforcement ofunpaid fines (paragraphs 32 to 34), and to improve the effectiveness of supervision orders (paragraph 59). They stress in paragraphs 61 to 62the importance attached to intermediate treatment and the need to pressahead with its development.8. All these proposals will, the Government hope, serve to reassuremagistrates and others that the Government are determined, even withinpresent financial constraints, to make adequate provision for the enforce-ment of the law and the firm handling of difficult juvenile offenders.The Government are equally determined to provide adequate provisionfor the welfare of the children themselves, which is largely entrusted bythe Act to local authority social services departments. Here the Govern-meot fully acknowledge the difficulties that local authorities face andhave faced ever since the Act came into operation in 1971. Since that timelocal authority social services departments and the local authority systemitself have been reorganised. As the Expenditure Committee point out, itwas only in 1973 that the bulk of the former approved schools becamecommunity homes under the control of local authorities; the buildings were often in the wrong place and in poor condition; and authorities havebad little time to assimilate this major addition to their social servicesresponsibilities. There is no doubt that to enable them to carry out their duties under the Act local authorities needed and still need extra resources,in terms both of buildings (in particular, secure accommodation) and ofstaff (both for field and for residential work). Local authorities have wishedever since 1971 to invest more in capital schemes for the care of childrenthan central governments loan sanction priorities allowed. From April1975 the decision was made to give loan sanctions according to localauthority priorities rather than to re0ect in a rigid formula the prioritiesof central government. This.has resulted in a marked shift in prioritytowards a proportionately greater share for children of a reduced personal social services capital budget9. As regards resources, jt will be appreciated that most of theExpenditure Committees recomniendations relate to the provision anddevelopment of various forms of treatment and care which are the responsi-bility of local authorities. Whatever views the Government may express,the final decision on these matters rests with the authorities themselves,and in any event it must be accepted that, in present circumstances, con-straints on resources will constitute an obstacle to rapid implementation.The Government have agreed that authorities should not be pressed toundertake tasks which require resources to be used at a greater rate thanprovided for in public expenditure planning; and the recent public expenditure White Paper (Cmnd 6393) shows that the total of localauthority expenditure will be falling over the next few years, thoughwithin this there will be a growth of personal social services revenue expenditure of 3.8 per cent, in 1976/77 and in the following three yearsof 2 per cent, per annum. Capital expenditure has, however, had to be considerably reduced from the level originally planned for 1976/77. The
personal social services budget is already under great pressure from an - -increasing elderly population with a 23 per cent, growth over the next 10years in the number of elderly over the age of 75. The children&apos;s services are also under pressure: the number of juveniles under 17 found guilty of indictable offences, or who have admitted such offences without courtproceedings being taken, has grown from 118,883 in 1970 to 184,491 in 1974_an average annual increase of 11.6 per cent.; the number of childrenstaying in care has recently been rising at the rate of about 2.5 per cent, ayear; and we are likely to see an increase in the time spent on cases ofnon-accidental injury.10. Against this sombre background the Government see the task of improving the working of the Act as one which has to be undertakenwithin broadly the present legislative framework, and within human andmaterial resources which, though much increased since the Act came into effect, cannot continue to grow as fast as many would wish. TheGovernment, do not believe that a solution lies in changes in the powersof the courts that would erode the responsibilities of local authoritiesto provide for the treatment and control of young people committed totheir care. Nor, even if there were an unrestricted supply of additional resources for the implementation of the Act, would the Government thinkit right that it should- be devoted to a massive programme of residentialprovision-though there are particular gaps in provision, detailed below,the filling of which deserves a high priority. On the contrary, the Govern-ment share the Committee^ view (paragraph 167) that there should be,within the framework of the Act, a major shift of emphasis towards non-residential care including supervision, intermediate treatment and fostering.11. Above all, in the Governments view, the task is one that calls for greater mutual understanding, consultation and co-operation among all those who share responsibility for helping children in trouble and pro-tecting and reassuring the community. Specific proposals in response torecommendation 36 (paragraphs 80 to 83) outline arrangements for con-consultative machinery at local level, buttressed by a new national advisory body to stimulate and advise on local machinery and to supply a continuingevaluation of the working of the Act. Consultative machinery cannotsolve all problems, especially where there are real differences of perceptionof objective, and dilemmas that cannot be simply resolved: but it cango a long way to relieve anxiety and remove misapprehension, and ensurethat energy and resources are applied to the common task.12. To sum up, the Government see the overriding need as being a renewed and sustained effort to make effective use of existing-and by no means negligible-powers and resources, with a particular emphasis on improved mutual understanding; increased community involvement;and a greater acceptance of parental responsibility, and of the part whichcan be played by teachers, social workers and others. There is no panacea,except a recognition that everyone in the community can help or hinder,individually or collectively, through the part they play in handling theproblems of particular children.
OBSERVATIONS ON INDIVIDUAL recommendations that the practice of remanding young persons to adult prisons shall cease forthwith (paragraph 23).13. The Government accept this recommendation in principle and are determined to implement it in practice. It is already the case that all buta tiny minority of those young persons of 14, 15 or 16 who are remandedto prison service establishments go to remand centres rather than &quot;adult&quot;(ie local) prisons. Indeed, on 31 March 1976 there were only 6 boys and2 girls on remand before trial in local prisons; and this is about an average figure. The majority of young persons are held before trial in remandcentres: on the same date, the remand centres held 118 unconvicted boysand 3 unconvicted girls. They stay in remand centres, on average, for about four or five weeks although because of congestion in the courtsit can sometimes be a good deal longer than that.14. Remand centres are used primarily for young men and womenbetween the ages of 17 and 20, but they have always provided special facilities for those under 17 and still do so. Remand centres are in almost all circumstances more suitable for juveniles than the local prisons, andarrangements are already in hand to ensure that the need for an occasionalremand to a local prison is still further reduced. New remand centres for young men (each providing 60 places) at Rochester and Norwich will beopen within the next 12 months: and the availability of these places will still further reduce the number of boys under the age of 17 who haveoccasionally to be held in local prisons. Work is also proceeding on a newremand centre in the East Midlands, at Glen Parva, and there are plans for further accommodation in the South East. All of these centres will be capable of providing special facilities for the under 17s if necessary. Butthe provision of new places at Rochester and Norwich should, in itself, be enough to ensure that only in West Wales and the Welsh Border, wherethe courts are served by Shrewsbury local prison, will it be necessaryoccasionally to commit a boy to a prison establishment other than a remandcentre. New committal arrangements will be notified to courts to ensurethat this is the case. If, in any circumstances, a boy between the ages of14 and 16 is received on remand at Shrewsbury (or, for exceptionalreasons, at any other local prison), the prison will be required to reportthis fact at once to the Home Office, where consideration will immediately be given to the possibility of arranging a transfer to a remand centre. Asis already the case under existing reporting arrangements, a transfer to aremand centre will be arranged as a matter of course, unless there is good reason to believe that the move would cause serious inconvenience to theboy&apos;s family, friends, social worker or legal adviser.15. In short, therefore, the position about untried boys of 14, 15 and16 is that until such time as their remand to prison service establishmentscan be phased out completely (in accordance with the provisions of the1969 Act) those who are so remanded will be held in remand centresrather than local prisons unless there are exceptional circumstances justify-ing the other alternative.
16. As regards girls, the only local prison which receives girls underthe age of 17 on remand is Hottoway, where the reception of juvenilesis notified in accordance with the arrangements already described. Butthis local prison covers such a large part of the country (almost the wholeof England and Wales south of the Wash and excluding the West Country)that transfer to a remand centre tie Pucklechurch or Risley) is oftenjudged impracticable. Furthermore, it would be uneconomic and prodigalof scarce resources to consider providing more remand centres for girlswho, in accordance with the principles of the 1969 Act and the spirit ofthe Expenditure Committee^ report, ought not to be in the prison systemat all. The Government must, therefore, rely on local authorities to makeit possible to end remands of girls to Holloway. Local authorities in theareas which it serves have, in fact, a number of building projects providingsecure accommodation in observation and assessment centres, eitherexclusively for girls or for both boys and girls, already under constructionor about to start. Nineteen extra secure places in these centres should becoming into service during 1977. Meanwhile, thanks to the co-operationof the London Borough of Htllingdon and subject to the agreement of theLondon Regional Planning Committee, certain works are to be undertaken at an observation and assessment centre in Hfllingdon. When these are completed in two or three months&apos; time it should no longer be necessary,at least as far as the London Region is concerned, to remand girls toHolloway save in exceptional circumstances. They have also agreed for alimited time to take, whenever possible, girls from elsewhere until theother facilities currently planned are built. The Government hope thatthis, together with what is said about boys in paragraphs 14 and 15 above,will make it possible to comply substantially with this recommendation.17. That covers the position on remands to &quot;adult&quot; prisons, but itcannot be too strongly emphasised that it is Government policy to phaseout the remand of juveniles to any prison service establishments,including remand centres, by stages as soon as the local authorities bring into use alternative facilities. As a first step, the remand of 14 year oldgirls to prison service establishments (including remand centres) will ceaseas early as possible this year.18. The future programme for phasing out will inevitably depend uponprogress by local authorities in providing the additional facilities required,and this depends on their giving these facilities a high priority in their loansanction capital programme. The power taken by the Government in theChildren Act 1975 to make direct grants for this very expensive accom-modation should speed this process. However, in view of the severeconstraints on public expenditure, the Government accept that localauthorities cannot be expected to cope with the very large number ofjuveniles (nearly 4,000 in 1974) who are remanded before trial to prisonsor remand centres, and that the phasing out time-table will have to besubject to the fullest consultation with local authorities.19. The Government share the Committee^ concern that certificates ofunruliness, authorising committal to a prison service establishment, should
not be issued unless they are necessary, particularly in view of the factthat only about half the young persons remanded in this way in fact receivecustodial sentences. They have even considered the possibility of requiringlocal authorities to pay for juveniles remanded to prison service establish-ments: but this would be a cumbersome process and would require legislation.They would prefer, therefore, to rely on the powers taken in the ChildrenAct 1975 to prescribe in regulations, criteria which are to be met before anycertificate is given. Consultation on the form and content of these regulations has begun. This includes a survey conducted during Februaryby questionnaire to the courts, seeking information about the circumstancesof offences and the characteristics and previous history of the accused incases leading to the issue of an unruly certificate. The draft regulations will be subject to the usual process of consultation: the Government have itin mind that they shall, inter cilia, require the court before issuing acertificate to be satisfied by a written statement from the local authority that there is no suitable accommodation available within the communityhomes system safely to contain the young person until his date of re-appearance. The Government also intend to invite local authorities toestablish procedures to limit applications for unruly certificates, perhapsby requiring such applications to be approved personally by, for example,the chairman of the authority&apos;s social services committee.20. The Bail Bill now before Parliament, which provides for a statutorypresumption in favour of the grant of bail to unconvicted persons, will apply to juveniles. This measure, when enacted, should result in some reduction in the number of children and young people committed on remandto local authority care and, by releasing places in residential observation andassessment units, should have some effect in easing local authority problemsgenerally in providing for juveniles on remand.21. The Government hope that, by attacking the problem on this widefront, worthwhile progress can be made in implementing the intentions of the 1969 Act with regard to prison service custody during the next 12months. But the immediate ending of all juvenile remands to prison depart-ment establishments (ie remand centres as well as prisons) would not be practicable except by asking the community to tolerate the risk of asubstantial number of serious offences being committed by juveniles awaitingtrial and of their failing to appear for trial. This would not only defeat the ends of justice and be publicly unacceptable but could be more damaging to the welfare of the young people themselves than a remand to a prisondepartment establishment.2. That more educational resources be allotted to remand centres towhich children of compulsory school age are remanded (paragraph 23).22. The Government accept this recommendation. Most young people inremand centres, who are there, in the average case, for no more than 4or 5 weeks, already receive more than the two hours education a daymentioned in the Committee^ report as the provision in some centres; andsome receive as much as six hours a day, five days a week. There are,
however, isolated cases where only two hours education a day is provided and some where only four hours is provided in a whole week. This mustbe a matter for particular concern in the small number of cases whereremands extend for long periods. It is recognised that more educationalresources are needed to provide full-time education for all those of compulsory school age who are remanded to remand centres and theirprovision will.be provided by a redeployment of the prison departmenfseducational service wherever possible. The quality and quantity of educationprovided in remand centres is, of course, directly related to the numberof young people present there and as this number is reduced it will bepossible to provide better educational services for those who continue tobe committed.3. That when a care order is made agreement should be reached incourt between the magistrates and social workers concerned on what should be done with the child. If the agreed course should prove impossible or undesirable the social worker should notify the court(paragraph 24).4. That when a juvenile already the subject of a care order appearsbefore a court charged with an offence the court shall have the powerto make, if it thinks fit, a &quot;secure care order&quot; requiring the localauthority to place the juvenile in secure accommodation for a period not less than that specified in the order (paragraph 25).23. These two recommendations reflect the Committees concern aboutbow decisions are reached on the treatment provided for children who are put into the care of local authorities by magistrates, especially about thetreatment of the small minority of children who commit very seriousoffences, some of them repeatedly. The Magistrates&apos; Association in their evidence to the Committee emphasised their inability to protect the publicfrom what they described as &quot;a minority of tough, sophisticated youngcriminals&quot;.24. The Government see, first and foremost, a need for better co-operation and understanding between the courts and the local authority social workers and have consistently encouraged all authorities concerned with the Act toset up toe necessary machinery. In their view, this is the only way toremove the uncertainty which exists among some magistrates about thebasis on which social workers reach their decisions; the point is dealt withcomprehensively in the reply to recommendation 36. The liaison arrange-ments referred to there should include regular opportunities for magistratesand social workers to meet to discuss the treatment outcome of individual cases or groups of cases.25. As regards proceedings in court, the Government would be unwilling to contemplate a procedure which would blur the lines of resrxmsibflitvbetween the court and the local authority. A juvenile court is not and cannot be, a chfld welfare department, and it is of great importance&apos; that local authorities should accept and shoulder undivided responsibility for
looking after difficult or dangerous young people who have become theircharge by reason of the court&apos;s decision. Moreover, the Government seedrawbacks in the particular form of consultation enjoined in recommenda-tton 3 which goes much further than the need to improve the courts&apos; andthe social workers&apos; understanding of each others roles. By restricting thelocal authorities&apos; discretion it would undermine the concept of the careorder, and limit the authorities&apos; responsibility for determining and providing the proper treatment of young people placed in their care. The court is nota suitable setting for a detailed discussion of what should happen tojuveniles. The social worker appearing in court would rarely be able to commit the local authority to a course of action in respect of a particularchild at the time when the child is before the court, that is in advance ofthe post-trial observation of the child and full assessment of his needs.26. At the same time, the Government recognise that many juvenilecourt magistrates have much experience of the problems and needs ofjuvenile offenders, and also that in the process of the court hearing, which includes the consideration of detailed reports about the offender, the courtcan form its own considered view in the light of all the circumstances ofthe offence and the offender about a suitable disposal.27. With these considerations in mind the Government take the viewthat when a care order has been made the magistrates should be able,in the minority of cases which cause them special concern, to make a recommendation to the local authority concerned about what should bedone with the child, including a recommendation that he or she shouldbe placed in secure accommodation. This should be possible whether ornot the boy or girl was already in care when the case was heard.28. Since such a recommendation would constitute a contribution to the assessment process it would be inappropriate to announce it in open court;it should, instead, be conveyed by the clerk of the court to the localauthority. Such recommendations would carry weight with the localauthority who, following post-trial observation of the child and fullassessment, would notify the court of their decision and the reason for it.The decision regarding placement and treatment under a care order would,however, remain wholly within the discretion of the local authority.29. The Government also suggest that magistrates, in these and other cases of particular children in whom they are interested or about whom they feel special concern, should notify the local authority that they wishto receive within a stated period a report on the arrangements that havebeen decided upon. Because of the pressure on local authority social service departments it will be essential that arrangements of this kind should notbe introduced without consultation between the magistrates and the localauthority concerned and that they (like the power to make a recommenda-tion) should be used selectively. If the magistrates wished to do so theywould raise individual cases on which they had received reports at the nextconsultative meeting in the area. The matter would not be brought backto the court unless the child committed another offence, and in these cases
the court would be free to comment on the full circumstances surroundingthe case and on any disagreement between the court and the local authority.30. If the best use is to be made of these procedures it will be important to ensure that they are used sparingly and operated with the minimumadministrative complexity. With this in. mind the Government would propose to review the operation of these arrangements after a year.5. That consultation between police and social services departments should be intensified in those areas where it is weak (paragraph 35).31. The Government welcome this recommendation (which relates to consultation before a decision is taken whether or not to prosecute ajuvenile). It reinforces advice relating to local liaison and co-operation givenby the Government to the field services operating the Art. The greatmajority of police forces have special arrangements for dealing withjuveniles, and the emphasis of the Act on consultation between the police and the social services departments of local authorities has proved a powerful stimulus to the setting up of juvenile bureaux. The staff of ajuvenile bureau are responsible for gathering information about juvenilessuspected of having committed offences from the relevant agencies, ie thesocial services department, the probation service and the education service,and an officer from the bureau usually visits the cb0d&apos;s home. In the lightof the information gathered, the officer-in-charge of the bureau decideswhether proceedings should be brought, a formal caution administered or no further action taken. It is usual practice for the police to inform thelocal authority of the names of juveniles cautioned so that any necessarysupport or voluntary supervision may be given. The machinery for consulta-tion between police, social services departments and other services concerned, is essentially a matter for local arrangement and will be asuitable matter to be considered within the framework of the consultativemachinery, proposals for which are fully described in the comment onrecommendation 36.6. That there should be a sanction for non-payment of fines in the shape of an attendance centre order, the possibility of which should be made clear at the time the fine is imposed (paragraph J&amp;J.32. The Government share the Committees concern regarding sanctionsin the event of non-payment of a fine imposed on a juvenile. But theCommittee^ recommendation presents a problem. The junior attendancecentre system covers only the main centres of population; and becausetravelling must be kept within reasonable bounds, coverage of all smallertowns and rural areas would not be practicable even if resources for expanding the system were amply available-which is not the presentposition (cf comment on recommendation 10). Moreover, there are nojunior attendance centres for girls; the extension of the system to includegirls is not at present in contemplation since, the question of resourcesapart, the numbers are not such as to make centres even in large cities a viable proposition. The Government doubt whether a fine enforcement
sanction available only in respect of boys, and even for them not in all parts of the country, would be accepted as equitable.33. There is no entirely satisfactory solution to this problem, but with aview to ensuring that some further action is available to the courts in allcases of persistent non-payment of fines by juveniles, the government propose that a court should be given the power by legislation in thesecircumstances, either to order the defaulter to attend an attendance centre(where one is available) or to require the defaulter^ parents to pay thefine or ensure that their child does so. This would mean giving the courta power either to bind over the parent to ensure that his child complieswith the court order (similar to the bind-over power m section 7(7)) or totransfer the fine to the parent or guardian of the child concerned. In thelatter case, the parent would become subject to the ordinary procedures for fine collection and enforcement, and the protection for the person liableto pay which they embody. It would always be open to the court to requirethe parents to pay, if this seemed appropriate, even where an attendancecentre was available.34. Before resorting to any of these measures of enforcement outlined above, the court would have had to bring the juvenile defaulter before it for an inquiry into the reasons for non-payment, and would need to besatisfied that the default resulted from a refusal, and not an inability, topay the fine. Before making the defaulters parents responsible for payment,the court would have to be satisfied that in all the circumstances the require-ment was a reasonable one.7. We recommend that the transfer of responsibilities from the probationservice to the local authority social service departments be halteduntil such time as the latter have adequate trained and experiencedstaff to handle the problem (paragraph 39).8. That courts be enabled to nominate either probation service or social service department as supervisor irrespective of the age of the child. We realise that this may need legislation (paragraph 39).35. The transfer of responsibilittes for supervising children (ie juvenilesunder the age of 14) from the probation service to the local authority social service departments has already been halted for the present because some local authorities are not able to undertake the additional commitment withtheir existing resources. However, any prolonged delay would have serious repercussions for the development of the work of the probation service inrelation to older offenders. A similar consideration arises on recommenda-tion 8. Both recommendations rest on the view formed by the Committeethat, at least at present, the probation service is better experienced and better equipped to deal with delinquency than local authority social workers. In the Govenunenfs view the answer here lies in building up thetraining, skills and experience of the local authority service. To give thecourts a free choice between the two services in every case of a child who
requires supervision could inhibit the local authority service from gamingnecessary and valuable experience in supervising juvenile offenders. It would place on the probation and after-care service an additional burden whichit could not shoulder without detriment to its existing planned commitments(themselves increasing) in respect of older offenders.9. That courts should be enabled to impose sentences of detention in a detention centre for any period between two days and three weeks inaddition to the existing sentences of three and six months (paragraph46).36. The Government are not persuaded that there is a place, in the range of disposals available to the courts when dealing with juveniles, for shorterperiods of detention than the present minimum three-month period,reduced as it is to six-and-a-half weeks through the award of one-halfremission of sentence. As doubtless the Committee recognised, there areStrong arguments against a very short period of custody, especially for young offenders. The Government consider that it is wrong to impose a custodialsentence so short that it is likely to be seen, either by the offender or bythe staff of the establishment concerned or by both, as having only apunitive intent. Moreover, the introduction of offenders with very shortsentences into an establishment catering primarily for offenders servingrather longer sentences could have an adverse effect on, and distractattention from, those in the latter category.37. There would in any event, be substantial practical difficulties in providing a period of custody anything like as short as the two-day lowerlimit proposed by the Committee. The existing junior detention centres havewide catchment areas, leaving some courts several hours journey from a centre. The cost of transport and (more particularly) escort staff would bedisproportionate if the period of stay were very short. Moreover, theexisting stock of places (which in present circumstances and against otherpressing demands for prison department resources cannot be increased) isscarcely adequate for existing demands. It follows that juveniles servingvery short sentences could be accommodated only if these sentencesdisplaced, and were not additional to, the existing three-month sentences-and even then it is likely that extra staff would be required to cope withthe extra work involved in receptions and discharges.38. The Government believe, therefore, that it would be both unrealisticand undesirable to empower the courts to impose sentences of detention onjuveniles which in practice would run for less than six weeks.10. That attendance centres be retained and that, where possible, thesystem be extended (paragraph 49).39. The Govern tnenfs existing policy for junior attendance centres isto see them as a useful sanction and the Expenditure Committees endorse-ment of this policy is welcome. The system would already have beenexpanded in the past two years, had resources been available. Plans for
expansion in a number of areas have been drawn up which can be implemented if resources become available.11. That capital expenditure plans of local authorities for communityhomes should be submitted for approval through the regional planning Committees which should append their observations as to the impact of the proposal on regional plans (paragraph S4).40. The procedure recommended is, in fact, that adopted by the Govern-ment in the preparation of the 1975/76 capital programme. Applications bylocal authorities for inclusion of projects in the programme were submittedsimultaneously to the appropriate Regional Planning Committees (RPCs)and the Department of Health and Social Security. Regional prioritieswere, following consultations within RPCs; notified by them to the Depart-ment. A national programme was then prepared by the Department onthe basis of local authority and regional priorities. A similar practice was followed in Wales by the Welsh Office. The preparation of the programme for 1976/77 has followed a like pattern.12. That priority should be given to ensuring that there is some secure ac-commodation m every area; RPCs should devote consideration to thepossibility of making existing accommodation secure as a temporary measure (paragraph 81).41. Regional planning committees and local authorities are already aware ofthe need for more, and a more even spread of, secure accommodation, as thepresent building programme shows. It is because of the shortage of such ac-commodation, particularly in observation and assessment centres, that thereis often no alternative to a remand to a Prison Department establishment for aboy or girl of 14, IS or 16. It is the Governments declared policy that thisundesirable practice should be ended, and steps already taken and plans forfurther action to achieve this are described in the reply to recommendation 1.But the abolition of this practice could be hastened by a concerted effort on thepart of all the agencies concerned to provide secure remand facilities, reservethem for cases where the need is indisputable and keep such remands as brief aspossible. There is no doubt that the shortage of secure accommodation is alsoreflected in the increasing number of 14 year old boys in detention centres andof 15 year olds in borstaJs, and in the numbers receiving more than one suchsentence.42. The high cost of secure accommodation and the number of trainedexperienced staff it needs have deterred some local authorities from undertaking to provide it, particularly since it is seldom that an authority requires more thana few places for its own use. The Government will make the fullest possible useof the power in the Children Act 1975 to make direct grants for the provisionof secure accommodation in order to remove this difficulty and so encourageauthorities to provide more secure places as quickly as possible. The new power,which will cover revenue commissioning costs where appropriate, will be usedpositively to remedy the current uneven distribution of this type of accom-modation and to encourage co-operation across local authority boundaries.
43, The Government would be glad for local authorities to consider thepossibility of adapting existing buildings, but previous experience of adaptingbuildings for this purpose has been discouraging.13. We recommend the construction of secure wings in ordinary communityhomes which could be used for remand as well as for treatment places(paragraph 81).44. This is a matter for the local authorities, ft is Department of health and Social Security and Welsh Office policy that additional secure places forremand purposes should be provided as part of, or in the grounds of, existing or new observation and assessment centres and that additional secure places forlong-term treatment should be similarly provided in community homes witheducation on the premises. Regional plans generally conform with this policy.However, any attempt to provide remand and treatment facilities within asingle unit would present difficulties in terms of the staff, facilities and types oftreatment required, since the needs of children requiring long-term treatment insecurity are different from those of children on remand. In addition, the stability of homes which seek to provide long-term treatment is likely tobe jeopardised by frequent short-lived visits of highly disruptive children.14. That more strenuous efforts should be made to bring back into the serviceprofessionally qualified or experienced staff on a part-time basis withflexible hours (paragraph 88).45. The Government welcome this suggestion and will certainly continue toencourage local authorities and voluntary organisations responsible for com-munity homes to make it easier to employ professionally qualified or experiencedstaff on a part-time basis. The use of part-time residential staff has, of course, tobe carefully planned in the interests of the children in view of the higher degree ofcontinuity essential in residential care.15. That social workers should be encouraged to move from one field to theother as circumstances allow (paragraph 96).46. The Government share the view of the Committee that the movement of social workers between residential care and field work should be encouraged.Such movement will be stimulated by the policy of the Central Council for education and Training in Social Work (CCETSW) to integrate the training offield and residential social workers which the Government support Movementwill also become easier when more combined field and residential work coursesleading to the Certificate of Qualification in Social Work are set up. progress will, however, depend on the availability of resources.16. That residential staff should not necessarily live on the premises (paragraph96).47. The Government will encourage local authorities and voluntary organi-sations to consider whether an approach on these lines could help to solve then-problems in staffing community homes. It will, however, be for individual
authorities and organisations and the heads of homes to decide upon the implications, in terms of management and the quality of treatment, of a re-duction in the number of staff required to live in, bearing in mind, for anyparticular establishment, the needs of the children and the physical arrangementsfor their accommodation and control. Providing staff accommodation hassometimes been found to be an aid to recruitment, and the lack of it has, it issaid, led some homes to reduce the number of places available for children.However, it cannot in general be necessary for a high proportion of staff to beresident, as distinct from being available during the night for the care and supervision of the children.17. That the present capital programme should stand, but RPCs should under-fake a fundamental examination of their programmes and resources before any more new buildings are proposed (paragraph 96).48. The Government accept that the present regional plans, approved in1973, now need revision. Discussions have already taken place with regional planning Committees on the form revision should take and the policypriorities to be taken into account in it, as a preliminary to the issue of guidance.49. The Committee also refer to the plans in the 1975/76 capital programme,for building over 2,000 new places in community homes. In the event the changed economic conditions necessitated a reduction in this programme.Nevertheless, while some authorities are not going ahead with projects thatcarry expensive overheads, high priority must continue to be given to com-completing those additional places in community homes which provide observationand assessment, education on the premises and secure accommodation whichwere proposed in the 1973 regional plans. It is also essential that better use should be made of the existing accommodation. While the pressure on suchaccommodation continues to be heavy the Regional Planning committees have a crucial co-ordinating role. The appendix sets out the numbers ofadditional places in community homes, broken down by regional planningareas, to be provided in projects already submitted by local authorities.50. As the Committee point out, a critical constraint in residential work,and also in field work with children, is the shortage of staff, especially those with the necessary training and experience. In recent years it has been increasingly difficult to staff residential establishments of all kinds, probably because of improved working conditions in other sectors. The Committee suggest thatthe fundamental difficulty is that young staff are unwilling to live in and workunsocial hours. These are management problems but the solutions are expensive.As the Committee point out, it would be folly to build homes that cannot bestaffed.18. That some social workers should be encouraged to specialise in the field of juvenile delinquency (paragraph 97).51. This is a matter for the local authorities and CCETSW. It is also in line with a recommendation of the Working Parry on Manpower and training for the Social Services, for the development of post-qualification training to
ensure adequate specialist expertise in the personal social services. While theGovernment support the Committee&apos;s recommendation in principle, they feel that the need is less for specially trained social workers working full-time with children in trouble or at risk, than for social workers dealing with suchchildren to have ready access to specialist advice and expertise within the social services department They therefore accept the need for suitable training andother arrangements to be made to enable some social workers to gainexperience in this field.19. That attention be given to ensuring that social workers are trained incourt procedure (paragraph 97),52. This is primarily a matter for the local authorities, but the government agree that social workers who are likely to have to appear before a juvenilecourt should receive training in court procedures. Some training in courtprocedure is already given to social workers on most qualifying courses andalthough their lack of experience in this field was once a serious problem thesituation is gradually improving. Two papers published by the CCETSW in1974 and recommended to local authorities by DHSS have made a significant contribution to this. The CCETSW are at present considering in what waythe training currently provided can be developed further.20. That the community homes for each RPA should recognise a responsibility to find a place within the area for even the most difficult child and theirheads should form a committee to decide to which home such a child shouldbe sent (paragraph 103).53. The Government share the Committee&apos;s concern about children whoare difficult to place, and DHSS Ministers have on a number of occasions,in particular at conferences with Regional Planning Committee (RPQChairman, urged those RPCs which have not already done so to makeregional arrangements for placing such children.54. There are grounds for thinking that, despite calls for more accommoda-tkm, some specialised community homes are not being used to their full capacity and that their use is not confined to children who need to be placed in them. Despite heavy investment and increased demand the numbers actuallyaccommodated in these community homes have not risen. Some authoritiesproviding homes have not clearly defined the roles and functions of thosehomes and have allowed the heads to exercise a discretion on admission thatgoes beyond a necessary professional discretion. There is a problem here, asthe Committee themselves recognised, since they specifically refrained fromrecommending that heads of homes should lose the right to refuse to takea child. The problem is, of course, greatest for those authorities which do nothave sufficient community homes places of the right type to meet their needs.55. Where the problem is purely a local one the solution, in huge measure,lies in social services departments developing stronger controls over the specialised community homes for which they have recently become responsible.Where the problem is one of sharing between two or more authorities the need,is clearly for closer co-operation under the umbrella of the RPC. There is a
growing awareness of this problem within regions, some of which have already taken steps to solve it which are producing positive results. A committee of heads to decide which of them will take a child in need of treatment wouldbe one way of dealing with part of the problem. On the other hand, the headswill not always be aware of the full circumstances surrounding a particularchild&apos;s admission and a better solution could be a panel representing a numberof interests including the heads. Different areas may need different solutionsand it is for local authorities, through RPCs, to choose the best strategy fortheir purpose.21. That more should be done to encourage RPCs and local authorities toproduce more imaginative plans and to stimulate the development of inter*mediate treatment in those areas where it is inadequate.56. This is the accepted policy of the Government, who recognise that thedifficulties in the residential sector already referred to underline the importanceof developing non-residential treatment. The 1969 Act itself enables localauthorities to develop intermediate treatment-intermediate that is betweenhelping a child in his home and removing him from it There is a growingunderstanding of, and enthusiasm for, the new techniques that are beingevolved. Progress has been slow, however, and the numbers provided for inthis way are still totally inadequate,57. The Government are promoting the growth of intermediate treatment and, to this end, a circular will be issued to local authorities later this year in which RPCs and authorities will be urged to bring intermediate treatmentschemes up to date and to widen the range of facilities which they embody.In the meantime, a series of conferences on intermediate treatment is already taking place within regions at which field workers exchange ideas and compareand discuss various schemes of intermediate treatment In addition the social work Service is concentrating on the development of intermediate treatment in areas where the need is greatest and is studying and disseminating information about schemes and projects of special interest22. That the Department should make it clear to the local authorities that money can be spent on intermediate treatment for children in care andchildren at risk, whether or not they are subject to a court order, and thatthe local authority may make facilities available for children under super-vision who express a willingness to take part in intermediate treatment(paragraph 117).58. The Government welcome this suggestion. There appears to be no legalbarrier to doing what the Committee suggest; indeed some authorities alreadydo so. Discussions will be held with the local authority associations to agreewhat needs to be done to assure the other authorities that they may safelyfollow suit, where resources allow.23. That:(a) When making a supervision order the court shall have the power to specifyconditions with which the subject of the order must comply (such con-diiions being similar te those attaching to a probation order).
(b) For a breach of any of these conditions the supervisor shall be able tobring the Juvenile back to court which shall have the power to deal withthe matter, if it thinks fit, by way of a fine or an attendance centre order,whilst continuing the supervision order.(c) When the court proposes to make a supervision order, the conditions ofthe order and the possible consequences arising from a breach of those conditions shall be explained to the juvenile, and his consent and that ofhis parents or guardians obtained before any such order is made (para-graph 119).59, The Government fully share the Committee^ view of the importance of supervision as a means of dealing with juvenile offenders without removingthem from home. Like the Committee, the Government are anxious to increasethe effectiveness of the supervision order and, as a consequence, the courts&apos;confidence in it. The Government recognise that a power to include conditionsin a supervision order, and to impose sanctions for breaches of the terms of theorder, could have a part to play in attaining this object. At the same time it isnecessary to keep in mind the possible effect of such changes (which wouldrequire legislation) on the way in which supervisors carry out their duties underthe Act, and the Government would clearly need the considered views of localauthorities and others. It would also be necessary to consider the likely effective-ness of sanctions for breach of a supervision order. With these considerations inmind, the Government will seek views on the Committee^ proposals, and on thegeneral question of supervision, from local authorities and others concerned.24. That community homes, particularly those with education on the premises,should be used for day, as well as for residential care (paragraph 123).25. That local authorities should make greater provision for day care in theirbudgets (paragraph 123).60. The suitability of a community home as a day care centre would depend upon the circumstances of the home and it must be for local authorities todecide whether a particular home could effectively be used for day care. Subjectto this the Government encourage the use for day care of community honeswhich are observation and assessment centres where children usually stay for only a short period; indeed some recently provided centres include facilities forday assessment. The provision of day care in other kinds of community home isstill in an experimental stage. In general a community home with education onthe premises is intended for those very difficult children whose needs requireconcentrated care away from home in order to equip them for return to their home and perhaps to prepare them to undertake a day care programme. Toprovide for these children and to take in other children on a daily basis wouldmake heavy demands on staff and might detract from the standard of careprovided for the residents. These difficulties need further examination; theGovernment will encourage local authorities to continue to experiment with the mixed use of suitable homes in order to test the practicability of providing daycare in long-term residential settings.26. That urgent attention should be given to non-residential forms of care:intermediate treatment, day care, supervision and fostering.
61. This recommendation is primarily for implementation by local authorities.The Government regard it as a key one. The development of non-residentialforms of care and treatment must be seen as a priority. (&quot;Non-institutionaltreatment&quot; might be a better term, since short periods of residential care com-bined with supervision and other heip in the community is one promisingalternative to long-term care in an institution). Institutional care is now soexpensive that it ought to be reserved for children whose needs cannot be met inany other way. The Government are helping in various ways, including grants under the Urban Aid programme, grants to voluntary organisations andpromotional work. Guidance on financial aspects is being prepared. A firmindication of the Governments commitment to intermediate treatment wasgiven in the joint circular on the Rate Support Grant Settlement 1976/77. Theneed now is for vigorous local action. The Government hope that local authori-ties will interest themselves through corporate management in the coordinationof services for this purpose, as well as consulting other agencies.62. The Government, therefore, take a keen interest in, and are encouraging the development of, intermediate treatment and are keeping in close touch withsuch experimental projects as the Hammersmith Teenage Project organised bythe National Association for the Care and Resettlement of Offenders and withthe experiments in Kent and Reading in professional fostering. Efforts willbe made to encourage authorities generally to follow the example of the mostprogressive in developing these alternative forms of care. A Working Party onFostering Practice was established by DHSS in 1974 and has produced a &quot;Guideto Fostering Practice&quot; which will be published in the near future. In additionDHSS and the Central Office of Information have produced new leaflets andposters which have been issued to local authorities to help them recruit newfoster parents.27. That experiments in fostering disturbed Juveniles should be set up in eachRegional Planning Area. Particular efforts should be made to recruit tothis work those women social workers who have left their jobs to raisefamilies (paragraph 129).63. The Government will commend this recommendation to local authorities.It has been estimated that about 5,000 children in the care of local authorities,who are now living in residential accommodation, could benefit from fostering ifsuitable foster parents could be found. The problem is particularly difficult in relation to very disturbed children because they require from foster parents a profound appreciation of their special needs. Most authorities pay enhancedrates of hoarding out allowance for such children as a means of compensatingfor the additional skill or emotional and physical wear and tear that fosteringthem demands.64. The Working Party on Fostering Practice, in their guide, suggest re-cruiting as foster parents for disturbed children those who already have ap-propriate experience, such as married women who were formerly social workers,teachers or nurses, and who now wish to resume work in their own home.28. That in cases where the main cause of concern is a chiWs failure to attendschool the education welfare service should be able to be designated super-visor. To this end we recommend that education welfare officers shouldreceive more training (paragraph 136).
65. This recommendation is accepted in principle. There is no legal obstacle to education welfare officers undertaking supervision by arrangement with thelocal authority even though the supervision of that work is the responsibility ofthe social services committee of the authority whereas the oversight of thework of such officers is usually the responsibility of the education committeeof the authority or in inner London boroughs the Inner London EducationAuthority.66. The practicalities of involving education welfare officers in the work of supervision are for assessment by authorities in the light of the staff available,of the circumstances of individual cases, and of management implications, butthe Government see no objection in principle to the use of education welfare officers for this purpose; on the contrary, the practice has much to commend itThe Government do not, however, propose to bring forward legislation to empower the court to insist on the use of education welfare officers in specificcases; in their view the choice of supervising officer is best left to the localauthority.67. The promotion and provision of training for education welfare officersis for CCETSW and for local authorities who, through the Local government training Board, have endorsed the training proposals in the Ralphs Report.This report proposes the development of elements designed to meet the needsof the education welfare service within basic quahrying courses in social workand this is being considered by the CCETSW. The report also makes recom-mendations for in-service training on which action has already been taken bythe Local Government Training Board.29. That the attention of beat education authorities should be dram to theHome Office view, expressed in the Guide to the Act that &quot;A child of compulsory school age who, despite the action already taken, is not beingeducated is clearly not receiving the care or control he needs&quot;(paragraph 137).68. As is explained in paragraphs 90 to 91 of the Home Office Guideto Part I of the Act, it was intended that the Act should give legalendorsement to what had already been the administrative practice, in notbringing proceedings in the juvenile court until efforts had been made to resolve the situation without recourse to them.69. It was foreseen in consequence that evidence to establish the care or control test might often consist, as is put in the Guide, of &quot;an account of theunavailing efforts which have been made to secure the child&apos;s attendance at school by other means, and of the reasons why any further efforts are unlikely to be any more successful&quot;.70. It was not envisaged that in every such case a care order would result the Act provides for a number of other possible outcomes--such as an orderbinding over the parents, or a supervision order, with or without intermediatetreatment-one of which might well be more appropriate in an individual casein dealing with the complex problem of truancy. Nor was it envisaged that a
community home with education on the premises was necessarily the right place for a child whose main difficulty is failure to attend school.71. The Government recognise that there is some uncertainty about theinterpretation of the care or control test in relation to truancy and intend todiscuss this with representatives of the interested bodies, and to consider theneed for further guidance in the light of these consultations.30. That school heads should be informed as of right of every child who comes to the attention of the police or local authority (paragraph 238).72. Attention was drawn, in paragraph 98 of the Home Office Guide to Part Iof the Act, to the need for close liaison between social services departments,education departments and schools. The spirit of the present recommendation is, therefore, welcome; some bead teachers are known to feel strongly that existing liaison arrangements are less than adequate. The Government are notpersuaded, however, that a system of compulsory notification would constitute the most appropriate way of bringing about the necessary degree of co-operation;a statutory requirement on the police, for example, to notify bead teachers ofevery child who came to their attention would seem to represent a considerableburden of work, and it is not clear that the benefits would be commensurate.The Committee&apos;s objectives would best be met, in the Governmenfs view,through locally agreed procedures which are fully accepted by all the services concerned as meeting their legitimate requirements, and it is hoped thatauthorities, in consultation with the police, will re-assess the adequacy of present arrangements within their areas in the light of the concern which theCommittee has voiced. The Government win consider whether a re-statement and expansion of the existing guidance would be helpful.31. That a unit be set up to monitor the working of the Act. If staff with thenecessary expertise are not available in the Department of Health and social security they must be seconded from the Home Office Research Unit(paragraph 145).73. The Government accept the need to monitor the working of the Actmore effectively. They propose that, at the national level, standing inter-departmental machinery should be set up to do this and to co-ordinate the research programmes of the Departments concerned. Its functions would include the servicing of the National Advisory Council referred to ia the answer to recommendation 36, in particular by assisting the Council in its tasks relatingto the arrangements for local consultation proposed there.74. The Home Office Research Unit is currently responsible for research into toe operation of juvenile courts and other matters affecting children and young persons for which the Home Office it responublc. When other HomeOffice responsibilities for children and young persons were transferred to theDepartment of Health and Social Security a number of related research projectson the residential treatment of juvenile offenders were in progress and responsi-bility for them was left with the Home Offioe Research Unit The last of thesehas now been completed and the Department of Health and Social Security
are comnussiomiig new projects in this field. A group of Home Office,Department of Health and Social Security and Welsh Office officials meet at intervals to co-ordinate the research programmes of the three departments.Officials also attend from the Department of Education and Science and scottish Office.75. With the agreement of the local authorities the method of collection ofnational statistics and other data on the exercise of their responsibilities for treatment under the Act is being re-organised. A new system of returns ofinformation about children in care was introduced from 1 April 1976. The newreturn will be a considerable improvement because it will show the ages,reasons for being m care and time in care, of children in various types of accommodation. The Home Office, the Department of Health and Social security and the Welsh Office are considering how best to ensure that this and other information needed for improved monitoring is collected and made available.It is hoped that new arrangements for collecting data about the use being madeof community homes which will provide a common data base for the Govern-ment. Regional Planning Committees and local authorities, will also come intooperation this year.32. That the staff of community homes should be enabled to undertake theafter-care of children where appropriate (paragraph 149).76. The Government consider that social work support and after care is of vital importance and that there should be full co-operation between the staffof the community home and the field social workers in the child&apos;s homeauthority. The community home staff need feed back about the child&apos;s progressafter discharge just as the field social worker responsible for the case needsfull reports about the child&apos;s progress in the home. It is for local authoritiesto consider how this necessary co-operation is achieved, and the recommenda-tion will be brought to their attention.33. That police and Directors of Social Services should meet together in eachRegion with a view to evolving procedures to reduce the amount of paperwork involved in each case and to shorten the interval before a child appears in court (paragraph 1ST).77. The Government share the Committee^ concern about present delays in bringing juveniles before the courts, particularly in London, Consultationsbetween the Inner London juvenile courts, the Metropolitan Police and directors of social services have already achieved some improvement, and delays noware due primarily to staff shortages and pressure of work in social servicesdepartments and in police juvenile bureaux. The liaison arrangements referredto in tbe reply to recommendation 36 would be an appropriate means of considering these matters.34. That the issuing of explanatory leaflets in easily comprehensible languageto children appearing before juvenile courts and to their parents should bestandard practice (paragraph 1S8).
78. The Government welcome this recommendation, which -reflects existingcourt practice in a number of areas. Consultations have already begun withmagistrates&apos; courts on extending it.35. That a pilot duty solicitor scheme be established in a juvenile court in oneof the major urban areas in order to obtain a clearer idea of the effectivenessand cost of such a scheme (paragraph 159).79. Duty solicitor schemes are organised by individual local law societies,under the aegis of the Law Society, not by central government. A schemespecifically for juveniles is to be introduced at the Balham juvenile court,serving the London boroughs of Wandsworth and Lambeth, in June this year.If successful, it will be extended to other inner London boroughs. Of the other74 voluntary duty solicitor schemes, half say that they provide services for the juvenile court. There is also power under section 2 of the Legal Aid Act 1974,in cases where a legal aid order has not been made, for a solicitor within&apos;theprecincts of the court to appear for an accused person and to be paid under thelegal aid scheme if the court approves. As a respondent, a juvenile is alreadyentitled to legal aid on his own application, or on that of his parent, while acourt itself may grant legal aid without any application. Section 21 of thePowers of Criminal Courts Act 1973 provides that a juvenile cannot be sent toa detention centre, or sentenced by the Crown Court to borstal training, unless he has been legally represented. In 1973 nearly 16,000 juveniles were grantedlegal aid, and only just over 1,000 applications were refused. Although this&apos;represents only a fraction of the total number of cases, many involve non-indictable offences, and most are dealt with by way of absolute or conditionaldischarge or a fine. The Government consider that the law is adequate to makelegal aid and advice and legal representation available for juveniles where it isrequired, and that it. cannot be claimed that in serious cases any substantial number of juveniles fails to obtain these services. The explanatory leafletsreferred to in the reply to recommendation 34 should help to ensure thatjuveniles and parents are not left in ignorance of their entitlement in respect of legal aid and legal representation, and it is hoped that the development of dutysolicitor schemes for juveniles will improve the situation still further.36. That liaison committees representing magistrates, teachers&apos;, social workers and probation officers should be set up in every local authority in respectof children and young people to discuss not only the progress of individualchildren in care or under supervision, but also more general matters suchas the development of intermediate treatment. These committees should beable to require police officers to attend where appropriate (paragraph 161).80. The Government wholly share the Committee&apos;s view of the importance ofthe closest co-operation at local level among all those who share responsibilityfor the care and control of young people who get into trouble with the. law.As the Committee recognised, there are clear indications that some at least ofthe present shortcomings in the operation of the Act are attributable to failuresof communication and the lack of smoothly working machinery to ensure that each partner in the business of dealing with juvenile delinquency understands even if he cannot always share-the objectives, priorities, constraints and problems of others concerned in the same task.
81. To this end, local consultative machinery is needed and exists already inmany places to bring together, on equal terms, juvenile court magistrates,representatives of the local authority, and practitioners such as the heads of community homes, the police (including juvenile bureaux where they exist),teachers, field social workers (including education welfare officers) and representatives of voluntary organisations. The task of these local bodies willbe to concern themselves generally with the detailed operation of the Act in thearea where their members exercise responsibility, with a particular emphasis onmutual understanding and making the most effective use of the powers and resources available. One example of a particular role that they might play is inrelation to the proposals outlined above (ia relation to recommendation 3) forjuvenile courts to be able, in selected cases, to make treatment recommendations and call for reports from the treatment authority.82. The Government would not wish to prescribe any single pattern ofconsultative machinery: what will suit one area will not suit another, and itwould in any event be wrong to disrupt, in the interests of narrow uniformity,existing arrangements which are judged by all concerned, to meet the need.However, to assist and stimulate the improvement of communication at all levels, the Government intend that the Ministers concerned shall hold informal discussions at national level with the Magistrates&apos; Association, the local authority associations and other national bodies, about the implementation of theCommittee^ recommendations, including their implications for resources.A particular objective in these discussions will be to consider the establishmentof a national advisory council to ensure continued consultation at national level over the whole field. This National Advisory Council, in addition to provid-ing a forum for the provision of advice to Ministers, would have as an importantfunction the encouragement of the local liaison arrangements referred to above,and the formulation of advice regarding the forms that these might best take&apos;drawing upon the existing experience of areas where fruitful discussions havealready taken place between the services concerned.83. The national advisory body might also wish to advise on the desirabilityof consultative machinery at regional level alongside the Regional PlanningCommittees (RPCs). Although some RPCs have made extensive use of thepower of co-option, it seems likely that, elsewhere too, magistrates and repre-sentatives of other agencies and professions could make a useful contributionto regional planning.37. That the Home Office should examine the legislation with a view to definingmore clearly where the responsibility lies for offences committed by a childin local authority care (paragraph 164).84. There has been a number of court decisions in recent years about theextent of a local authority&apos;s responsibility for the payment of a fine or compensa-tion under section 55 of the Children and Young Persons Act 1933 in connectionwith an offence committed by a juvenile while subject to a care order. Thesetouch upon two main points: first, whether the local authority is responsible,as far as the payment of a fine is concerned, for a juvenile who is in care but, bydecision of the local authority, residing in a home not run by the authority
concerned or is with bis parents; secondly, the nature of the responsibility for control of the child or young person when he is in a home maintained by thelocal authority.85. Interpretation of the relevant statutes is a matter for the courts. TheGovernment does not at present consider that an amendment to the statutes is called for, but will continue to keep under review the development of case lawin this area.38. That both individuals and voluntary organisations be encouraged to co-operate in intermediate treatment (paragraph 165).86. This recommendation is accepted. The circular shortly to be issued tolocal authorities on intermediate treatment will emphasise the need to tap re-sources in the community suitable for providing intermediate treatment includ-ing facilities provided by voluntary organisations and the expertise and enthusiasm of individual volunteers. Authorities will be urged to seek theco-operation of such organisations and individuals.39. That attention be given to the possibility of setting up Youth AdvisoryCentres on the Amsterdam pattern in this country (paragraph 166).87. There are a number of voluntary organisations which provide advice,counselling and &quot;drop-in&quot; services in London and other areas, some of which areassisted by grants from public funds. Advice is also provided by Family ServiceUnits and detached youth workers and through voluntary attendance at inter-mediate treatment centres. Voluntary organisations providing such services for young people include GALS (Girls Alone in London Service), Centre Point,Open-door, the London Youth Advisory Centre and the Samaritans. CentralGovernment departmeots follow these initiatives with interest and are keepingtheir development under review.40. That children in community homes be enabled to earn extra pocket moneyby helping with the running of these homes.88. This is a matter within the discretion of the local authority or voluntaryorganisation responsible for the home as part of their general responsibility toensure that the home is properly conducted. Their attention will be drawn to thisrecommendation.
Appendixcommunity homes: building projects financed by loanThe tables below show the numbers of new places in community homes which on 14 May&apos; 1976 the local authorities were in the process of providing, andthe stage reached in that process. The DHSS* is responsible for the allocation of the sums available for loan finance for capital projects for the personal social services including projects for children. The allocation procedure fallsinto three parts. .(a) The issue of the Departments tht of projects provisionally approved the Department selects from lists of projects supplied by local authorities,taking account of local, regional, and national priorities and accordingto the total sum likely to be available, those projects which on the basisof the information then available, would be likely to be approved. The- next stage is for the local authority to formulate the proposal in greater detail and at an acceptable cost.(b) The approval in principle of an individual project with the determination of a cost limitOnce sketch plans and cost limits are agreed the project is approved inprinciple, and the local authority can complete preparations in full detail and obtain, tenders,.  (c) Final approvalWhen a tender is received which they propose to accept, the local author-ity apply for final approval which enables them to raise a loan to the agreed cost of the project and start construction.A project that has been approved in principle but has not reached final approval at the end of the financial year will, if the local authority so wish, havefirst call on the programme for the following year. Otherwise it will lapse.The DHSS* are not directly involved in the planning or construction stages.*The Welsh Office are the responsible department for such matters in Wales.
A.  COMMUNITY HOME PLACES IN BUILDING PROJECTS WHICH HAVE RECEIVED FINAL APPROVAL(as at 14.5.76)Regional Planning Area	*Oft A( Plao	Centres es	tC.H.E. Places		Ordinary CH Places		Total Places		Ordinary	Secure	Ordinary	Secure	Ordinary	Secure	Ordinary	Secure1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 (Wales)	30 147 103 68 74 55 43 215 61 18 24 57	3 11 Z 7 6 9 34 5 2 6	20 16 24 26 48 38 29	36 3 2 9	61 60 50 75 54 106 26 267 12 118	-	91 227 169 167, 128 161 95 530 1(1 18 24 204	39 11 2 7   -6 12 36 5 2 15TOTALS	895	85	201	50	829	-	1,925	135&quot;Observation and assessment centres.fCommunity home with education on the premises.
B.  COMMUNITY HOME PLACES IN BUILDING PROJECTS WHICH HAVE RECEIVED APPROVAL IN PRINCIPLE(as at 14.5.76)	*0 &amp; A Centres				Ordinary CH			Regional Planning A - - -	Places		tCH.E. Places		Places		Total Places	Area									Ordinary	Secure	Ordinary	Secure	Ordinary	Secure	Ordinary	SecureI			25	_	-	-	25	-2	27	3	-	-	8	-	35	33	104	10	-		76	-	180	104	-	-	-	-	-	-	-	-5		-	-	-	42	-	42	-  *6	24	6	-	-	8	-	32	67	59	12	-	-	-	-	59	128	-	4	-	-	24		24	49	-	-	-		-	-	-	-10	-	-	-	-	-	-	-	-11	24		-	-	-	-	24	-12 (Wales)	-	-	-	-	56	-	56	-TOTALS	238	35	25	-	214	-	477	35t Community home with education on the premises.&quot;Observation and assessment centres.

</content>
</cab>
