<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/26/0 images: 22-49</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Bpflpaai^^^ MAJESTY*S&quot;&apos; OOVERNMF/NT).D R E T.. FINAL C npy No.&apos;.-CABINET 49 (21).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W., on Tueeday, June 14th, 1921,at   11   a*ITUPRESENT:-The Right Hon. A.Lord Privy Seal,tight Eton. A.J. BaJLTeur, 0*M*.*HI*P*.President-of the Councilsptght Hon. E. Shortt, K.C.,M.P.,^tary-of Sbadve for Home Affairs.Right Hon. WoS. Churchill, M,P.,etary of State for the Colonies *Right Hon. Sir L. Werthington-a,. Bart.,M.P*, Secretary of StateWar.Right Hon. S. Baldwin. Mo P.,ident of the Board of Trade.Right Bon. H o A.L. Fi sher, M*?.,ident of the Board of Education.Right Hon. C. Addisen, M.P.Chamberlain, M.P.,IN THE CHAIR).The Right Hon. Sir Robert Kor-re,G.B.E.tK*C*,M*P., Chanoellor cfthe Exchequer.The Right Hon. Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G. ,G.C.S.I. ,GaCcI*E* ,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. E.S. Montagu, M* P.,Se-cretary of State for India.The Right Hon. Lord Lee of Fareham,G.B.E. .K.C.B., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir A0 Mond, Bart,M;P., Minister of Health.The Right Hon. T*J* Macnamara,Mi P., Minister of Labour.The Right Hon. ,Sir Hamar Greenwood,Bart.,SoC ?M.P., Chief Secretaryfor Ireland.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT :-L Lovat, K. T..     C.M.G. ,K. C V. 0., Sir H. Llewellyn Smith, G.C*B.,,D.S.0. Board of Trade.&apos; Conclusion 7). (For Conclusion 4).-Col. Sir M.P.A. Rankey, G.C.B........................... Secretary.Thomas. Jones.*..................... Principal Assistant Secretary.
(1) VfltK.,j^-^^i^%o^(^6iy^Jri^t 45 (21), Conclusion 2 (a),tfl*e^6binet-had before them the following documents relatingto the question of Mandates:-A ETote by the Secretary of the Cabinet,covering Departmental Correspondenceand Revised Mandates (Paper CP.-3005),A Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies, including telegraphic correspondence beiween the Secretary ofState and the Righ C ommissioneiS of Meso-potamia and Palestine (Paper C.P.-5040),Notes of a Conference held in LordGurzon&apos;s Room at the Foreign office on Wednesday, June 1, 1921, at 6-30p.m.  (Paper CP.-3028).The immediate issue before the Cabinet was the attitudfto be taken up on this question by Mr H.A.L. Fisher at theforthcoming meeting of the Council of the League of Nations.The Cabinet were informed that some members of theCouncil of the League were anxious, owing to the attitude ofthe United States towards the subject of Mandates, not toproceed with the question of passing the Mandates at theforthcoming meeting of the Council unless an agreement onthis point had first been reached between the United Statesand the Allies.    An alternative French suggestion was thatthe United States of America should be asked if they had any objection to the Council of the League at its forthcoming meeting approving the &quot;B&quot; Mandates but not the &quot;A&quot; Mandates.After considerable discussion the Cabinet agreed  (a) That the whole question of our responsi-inviolability under the &quot;A.&quot; Mandates (including a suggestion that *, if the United States&quot;continued to question our right to theseMandates, we should offer to cede to them the Mandate    for Mesopotamia   or Palestine)should be discussed at the forthcoming imperial meetings, and that this discussion should, if possible, be preceded by a full discussion at the Cabinet:(b) That, in view of the attitude of the UnitedStates of America and the fact that the high commissioners for Mesopotamia and Palestineare no longer pressing for the immediatepassing of the Mandates for th^s^territorses.it would not be in our interests, pendingthe forthcoming discussion proposed in (a) ,for the Council of the League, at the forth-- coming meeting, to pass either the &quot;A&quot; or &quot;E&quot;
Mandates, It would be desirable, however,;that the Council of the League should take steps to let the United States of Americaknow that the settlement of the Mandateswas likely to be strongly pressed at themeeting of the Assembly of the League inSeptember,    The Foreign Office should,however, take no action at Washington forthe present, until moved by the Councilof the League:(c) That, in any conversations on the subjebt,Mr Fisher should bear in mind that^. frokthe point of view of the position in Meso-potamia and Palestine, it is important first, that we should receive no rebuff inregard to the Mandate, and,, second, that itshould be made clear that in accepting theseMandates Great Britain is obtaining no bene-fit but only incurring heavy responsibilities,which had devolved upon her in fulfilment ofengagements entered into daring the War,(2) With reference to Cabinet 8 (21), Conclusion 1, theCabinet, a^ter a short discussion, agreed --(a) To reaffirm the decision to ratify theConvention on the subject of the Inter-national Court of Justice:(b) That the Dominions should be urged to ratify the Convention soon:(c) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should draft, for the Lord privy seal, a reply to a Question on thissubject to be asked that afternoon in the  house of Commons.
THB OPENING (5) Wl-oli..y^fsreiMje^o--^binet -41 (21), Conclusion 2. t&amp;--&quot;)P THE PAR:. *jlAMENT FOR&apos;&quot;&quot;&apos; -^$Jbd^etJhad a abort dis-cussion in regard to the attendancetfSRTHRRNrRffLAWn, of members of the Imperial Covenant,, of Dominions Primeattendance      Ministers,, and of Foreign Ambassadors, at the ceremony ofDf Cabinet &quot; -Ministers        the opening of the ,Parliament of Northern Ireland by theund Dominions ?.p,ndRepresenta- King on June &apos; &quot; &quot; Vith reference to which the Prime Mihistertlvea.of Northern Ireland had,-addressed a telegram to the Secretaryof the Cabinet.The Cabinet were given to understand that, in view of1 his indisposition and the postponement of the forthcoming imperial meetings, it was very doubtful whether the PrimeMinister would be able to carry out his original intentionof being present.Subject to the agreement of the Prime Minister, theCabinet expressed the opinion(a) That, In view of the fact that LordLondonderry Ins been invited by theKing to be the Minister in attendanceon His Majesty, the presence of theHome Secretary would be unnecessary, andthat the Britian C fo.&quot;net should be re-present ad by ths Chief Secretary for ireland:(b) That the Secretary of State for theColonies should only be present in theevent of the attendance of three ormore representatives of the Dominions;(c) That the Secretary of State for Foreign, - Affairs should discourage the attendance of diplomatic representatives, only oneof whom, up. to the present, has expressed his intention of being present.NOTE.A message has since been received that the PrimeMinister concurs in the above arrangements.-3-
Ay      (*)-&quot;ThaJ3atei3^ the&quot;^fcras&amp;fient of the Eoard of Trade on the subject of theBarcelona Oonvervtlons on&apos; Transit and Communications (paper c.P.-55031).The Cabinet were informed that the Admiralty had netyet had time to examine the proposals, and that the ColonialOffice, though prepared to ratify the converted^nticr^themselves on behalf of the Colonies and Protectorates,, would have tooonsult the Colonies and Protectorates in regard to theAdditional Protocol on National Waterways, mentioned on page2, which, the Cabinet-were reminded, had not yet been signed by the British Delegate.After put4.ing^va.rdjous^o:ue-stions       Sir-Hubert.. Llerell;&quot;---Smdth^-theCabinet agreed  (a) That, subject to the agreement of theAdmiralty, the converted-enticns on Transitand Communications should be ratified:(b) That the Admiralty should inform theSecretary of the Cabinet as to their decision as soon as possible, in orderthat Mr H.A%L. FrULex might be in aposition to inform the Council of theLeague of our intenbron to ratify beforethe&quot;termination of its forthcoming meet-ing:(c) That the British Delegate should beauthorised to sign the AdditionalProtocol on National Waterways, inaccordance with the proposals of thePresident of the Board of Trade,  onpage 2 of Paper CP,-3031.    In regardto the Colonies and Protectorates heshould await the instructions of theColonial Office.
I   : 2g.....r .1ESTRI0TIDK (5) With^reference- to Cabinet 38 (21), Conclusion 3. theIP PUBLIC E3WpNDlTURE.       attention of the Cabinet was- directed to the undesirabllityo-f adjudicating on claims for financial assistance for parti-cular schemes without regard to the comparative merits of3uch schemes and the total amount of the claims involved.It was pointed out that, in pursuing the policy of restricting expenditure, it would be a great advantage ifthe Cabinet had before them a general conspectus of thedemands of the various Departments, and that these demandsought to be considered together by the Finance Committee ofthe Cabinet.&apos;  The Chancellor of the Exchequer stated that the returns from, the different Departments, in response to theTreasury Circular, would not be available before the end ofJuly, and it would not be possible, therefore, for decisions *to be reached until early in August,In accordance with the above view, and   as statedbelow (See Conclusions 6 and V), the Cabinet agreed    To refer to the Finance Committee&apos; thefo 11 owirg qu.es tie ns: -(1) Grants in aid of EducationalPurposes abroad:(ii) Forestry- Expenditure.
GRANTS IN AID (6) With ^feren-oe^to&apos; Cabinet 38 (21k Conclusion 8, theOP EDUCATIONAl PURPOSES     Oebdnet had before them a Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs (Paper C.P.-2569) calling atten-tion to the lack of cohesion and common action among Britishsubjects resident in foreign countries, and to a Report onthe subject which had teen made by a Committee appointed bythe Foreign Office.    The Report had bean very favourablyreceived, and, so far as possible, Departmental action hadbeen taken upon it;   but, in order to give full effect toits recommendations, a grant of a sum of about  100,000per annum for a term of^ears was necessary.   This sum wouldbe expended on the advice of a Standing Committee, on which.,the Treasury would be represented.    The sum proposed -sras verysmall and in marked contrast to the very large grants votedby the French and German Governments for the extension of educational and allied interests among their subjects abroad.ABROAD.The CabinetagreedTo refer toothe Finance Costmatter for decision too mini t tee.
OHESTBY EX-     (7)   With reference to War Cabinet 557, Conclusion 5. theENDITURE.Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the Forestry Comr-mission (Paper -0.F.-2939) and a Memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (Paper CP.-2950) dealing with proposals to restrict the annual expenditure of the Forestry Commissionto 50 per cent, in each of the years 1932-23 and 1923-24.Lord Lovat, the Chairman of the Forestry Commission,explained to the Cabinet the interruption to the Forestryprogramme which would be involved if effect were given tothe reduction proposed by the Treasury.    Of the 150,000,000plants in the Forestry Commissions Nurseries, some 50,000,000to 60,000,000 would have to be destroyed in each of the years1922/1923, 1923/1924, as it would not be possible to place them on the market.    Of the present annual grant of  400,000, 292,000 was spent on forestry operations proper.    To reducethe grant by one-half would mean reducing the money spenton planting operations to from  35,000 to  45,000,    He reoog-nised the necessity of making economies, and estimated thatthe lowest figure at which the forestry programme,approvedby the Cabinet in 1919,could be carried out   for the year1922-23 was  365,000,,       and that the lowest figure atwhich an effective forestry policy could be carried out forthe year 1922-23, without substantial waste of material andwithout breach of faith with the staff, was  325,000.    In thelatter case, however, the whole of the authorised planting programme could not be carried out.    Lord Lovat called at-tention to certain administrative difficulties which had been experienced in working the Commission, and the need for more effective consultation on questions of policy,The Cabinet agreed:-(a) To refer the question of Forestry Expendi-ture, f$r decision, to the Finance Committee:(b) That, pending such decision, the forestry commission should restrict their commit-ments for next year to the lowest possiblefigure:
(c) That tha Chairman of the Forestry commissioners-sion should arrange for consultation withthe Chancellor of the Exchequer on general questions of policy once a quarter, andshould present an Annual Report to theCabinet on the working of the Commission,appending to such Report any questions ofprinciple which it had not been found pos-sible to settle with the Treasury.(8) With reference to Cabinet 4 (20), Conclusion 5, theCabinet had before them a Memorandum by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer on the subject of the disposal of surplus warmaterial, involving the question of the sale, under a blockcontract, of the remaining surplus war stores.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the particular proposal which hadbeen put forward should not be accepted:(b) That proposals put forward on the lines suggested in Article 711 of the MemorandumBhould receive consideration, but shouldnot be accepted without farther referenceto the Cabinet.SUBJECTS (9) The consideration of the following questions, whichPOSTPONED.were on the Agenda, each of which raised questions of grant from public funds, was postponed until the Prime minister could be present:-(I) Grants in Aid of Voluntary Hospitals:(II) Compensation for Damage to Property in Ireland:(III) Employment of Severely-Disabled Men:(IV) Unemployment:    Light Railways in NorthDevon and South Wales.DISPOSAL of surplus WARMATERIAL.
&amp; )    T^0 Cabinet took note of the following conclusions-*d*rri3*^-^irfererw^^ Committee of HomeCOMMITTEE OFHOME AFFAIRS. Affairs:-(a) Conference ef Ministers held on May 26,1921, at 4 p,,m.International Labour Organisation.Draft Convention on the Regulationof Honrs of Labour,(Appendix I),(b) Conference of Ministers held on May 27,1921, at 11 8,111.:-The Coal Stoppage.(Appendix II).(c) Conference of Ministers held on i/ay 30^1921, at 3-45 p.nut-Members &apos; Expens es,(Appendix III).(d) Committee of Home Affairs (87), heldon May 25, 1921, at 4-15 p.m.i-Preservation of Public Order Bill.(Appendix TV).(e) Committee of Home Affairs  (88), heldon May 31, 1921, at 4-15 p.m, :-(i) Prohibition o^ the Use of Lead inPainting.(11) Bill for the Preservation of PufelicOrder.(iii) Summer Time.(iv) Markets Committee Report.(v) National Health Insurance.    Adminis-trative Expenses.(Appendix V).2, Whitehall Hardens, S.W.1,June J4, 1921.
&apos;--j&amp;QCTOBW!Fiiii[ISii.iTHBii PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET.Es CONCLUSIONS . of a Conferenceof Ministers held in Mr0 Chamberlain1sRoom, House of Commons, S.W, , onThursday, May 26th, 1921, at 4 pcm0 Q$present:-THE PRIME MINISTER    (IN THE CHAIR).The Right Hono A. Chamberlain.MsP., Lord Privy SealsThe Right Hon* Ec Shortt. K*C,M.P., Secretary of State for home AffairssThe Right Hen, S. Baldwin, M.L?President of the Board of Trade,,The Right hon a take * Macnamara.M.P., Minister of Labour.The Right Hon. Sir Gordon Ilewart,K.C,; M. P. i Attorney-General.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO present sir Co A. Montague Barlow, Kc.B*E..,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Ministry of Labours.Lieut-Col. Sir M*P*A. Hankey, G.C.B................. *       .Secretary,Mr, Pembroke Wicks.....................f......c......... ..Principal.
purposes^R^AW1 With ref,e^ence to Cabinet 76  (SO), Conclusion 1,  andjpIOiM. to Conclusion 1 of a Conference of Ministers held at 11-30n convention- a.m, on May 26, 1921,  the Conference had under considerationm on therulation       a Memorandum by the Minister of Labour (Papor G.P.-2970)  onHours ofpur. the policy to be adopted by the Government in respect cf theDraft Convention, of the Washington International Labour Oon-ference, on the regulation of hours of labourcIt was explained that the following M: :,ion had been putdown by Mr Barnes for consideration in tlie House of commons on the following day:-&quot;International Labour Conference (Gonven-tions), - To call attention to the factthat the Government have not yet submit-ted to Parliament certain conventions adopted by the International Labour Con-ference at Washington;    and to move,That, in the opinion or this Horse, the conventions adopted at the InternationalLabour Conference under the League ofNations should be submitted to Parlia-ment as the competent axithority&apos;!.The Attorney-General stated that since the meeting ofthe Cabinet in December, 1920, above referred to, he had further examined the position of the Government under Article405 of the Treaty of Versailles, and had somewhat modified theopinion he had previously expressed.    Tho Treaty required each member of the International Labour Organisation to bring any recommendation or convention adopted, before the authority within whose competence the natter lien, for the enactment of legislation or other action.    This seemedto contemplate that, although such step might be taken by the member of theInternational labour Organisation,the consent o^ the competent authority would not necessarily be forthcoming.    In his view,the &quot;member&quot; of the International labour Organisation inrespect of Great Britain was the Crown, acting through theExecutive, and the action to be taken differed according asit involved legislation or an International Convention.    if legislation was required, the British Government were boundto bring the recommendation of the International T. ibourConference, in sore form or other, before Parliament,    They
need not press it, but were bound to present it. In tvecase of an International Convention, if legislation were required, that also rust he submitted to Parliament. if legislation were not required, then the Crown, i.e., theExecutive, could decide to ratify or not, independently ofParliament..Attention was drawn to  the fact that,in the present case,if the Government decided to reject the proposed limitation of hours of employment, no legislation would ho necessary.    Ifthoy decided to ratify the recommendation they could only doso by legislation...   In those circumstances, were the Govern-ment bound to bring a Bill before Parliament, assuming thatthey did not intend to accept th mmendation?The Attorney-General said that the matter was open to doubt, but he thought the Article assumed that,wheneverlegislation -would be required to give effect to a recommends-tion, legislative proposals must be presented to the law-making authority.The Prime Minister pointed out that, whatever the technicalposition,  it would be impossible to ratify a proposal of thiskind: without the sanction of Parliament,    It would be a veryserious thing to accept a compulsory 8-hours day which had notbeen agreed to either by workmen or employers ,    It would interfere with the freedom to work overtime,  and would cutathwart the arrangements the Government had made with theRailwayman..   Unlike some foreign nations,  the British G&amp;vern-ment v/ould not be prepared to undertake an obligation of this character in an International Agreement and afterwards neglectto  carry it&apos; out.The Conference then considered in what way parliament should he inform.&quot;d that the Government did not propose to ratify the Eight Hours Convention.The Attorney-General suggested that the Government should state that ratification of a Convention was an act of theCrown, that  it was not proposed to ratify in thin case,
and that it would there f ore_.be nugatory to present a pro-pooal to Parliament which it was not proposed to carry out.*n the other hand,  it was pointed out that the reprssent-ativ.es of the British Government at the Washington conference had made it quite clear that Parliament was to he the body which should determine whether or not the Convention shouldbe ratified.    It was explained, however, that while theoriginal draft of the Convention had used the word &quot;Legisla-ture&quot;   the intention being that a recommendation of theWashington Conference should become operative unless vetoedby the Legislature   owing to the refusal of the american representatives to accept the proposal a compromise had beenagreed on which appeared in the draft finally adopted by the drafting Committee, vizc5  &quot;that the Convention should bebrought before the authority or authorities within whosecompetence the matter lierm  for the enactment of legislation or other action&quot;, and Mr Barnes, as Vice-President of the paris Commission, had been careful to use the words &quot;competent authority&quot; in the discussions before the main Peace Confer-en.Ce.    There was no doubt, however,  that in Mr Barnes1 view the &quot;competent authority&quot; mesnt   the Legislature.The Prime Minister took the view that it was impossibleto disregard the merits of the question.    Mr Barnes had gone to Washington at the invitation of   the President of theUnited States when it was found that the American Senatefailed to accept the Treaty and America accordingly was notbound by it.    At the same time, the German Government wereoutside the Convention, so that two of the three greatestindustrial countries were not parties to the arrangement.The idea had been to have some agreement to give protection against any country taking an unfair advantage of therestriction of hours in otbmr countries, but, as these two great industrial countries were not parties to the arrange-ment,  the circumstances had so altered that it was not right that Great Britain should be bounde
It was further pointed out that France and Belgiumhad not yet- introduced legislation on the point.The Prime minister continued that the Government should refuse to accept Mr. Barnes&apos; Motion on the merits of the case,pointing out at the same time,  tut without pressing it, thatratification should be an act cf the Crown and not of Parliament.The Minister of Labour emphasised that the Government werein a position to say that they were already.  In one form or another,  carrying out the Conventions and recommendations ofthe Washington conference for example. In respect of unen-ployment, the care of women before and after childbirth,  andthe night employment of women and young persons.      The limitationof hours of work was practically the only respect in which thepolicy of this country was not already in full accord with theresolutions of the Washington Conference.It was suggested that unless the Government were able tomeet Mr. Barnes&apos; Motion with a direct negative as to the com-potence of the House of-Commons to ratify a Convention ofthis character, every time a resolution wore passed by theInternational Labour Conference the Government would be boundto find Parliamentary time for its discussion^The Prime Minis tor pointed out, on the other hand,that it would be a somewhat delicate matter to ask the House ofCommons for a direct vote on the question whether the Governmenthad a right to ratify an International Convention without tho  .sanction of Parliament.It was also pointed out that, while the argument againstratifying the Convention was unassailable on its merits, theHouse of Commons was asked in mr Barnes1  Motion to express the opinion that the Conventions of the International LabourConference should be submitted to Parliament as the competent authority, and might very well accept that view apart altogether from the merits of the Convention under discussion^ Mr.Barnes was, no doubt, of opinion that, under Article 405
I tof the Treaty, once a recommendation had been made., theGovernment had to perform a ministerial act &quot;by patting it before Parliament, and world press that point of view,    Itworld be imprudent to ash the House of Commons deliberatelyto admit that it was not the competent authority to ratify.The Conference agreed  (a) That the British Government should decline to ratify the Convention of the Internation-al Labour Conference relating to the llmita-tion of the hours of labour:(b) That the Minister of Labour should move an amendment in the house of Commons  to MrBarnes&apos; Motion, via,.,  to omit the words in brackets:-&quot;To call attention to the fact that theGovernment have not yet submitted toParliament certain Conventions adoptedby the International Lab our Conferenceat Washington;    and to move, Thau  [inthe opinion of this House.   the conventions adopted at the International Labour Confer-ence under the League of Nations should besubmitted-to Parliament as the competent authority n,and insert&quot;in the opinion of this House it is not sx-expedient in existing circumstances to pro-ceed with legislation to give effect to theWashington Convention on Hou:.s of Labour&quot;:(c) That, should it be necessary,  the Attorney-General should intervene,at a later stage inthe Debate,with a legal argument on the tech-nical position under the Treaty,,Whitehall Gardens, S,W.1,May 26,  1921.
IXOUivElHT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRIT-AMMO LA JE3T t&apos;.S GOVERlb.trWfgS&amp;T COITCLuSI0H3 of a Conference -of,.Minis tore hold, at 10, downing Street,&apos;S,W., on Fridayy May 27th,9 1921 at 11-0 a,ffi,P R E S EH T vTHE PRIME MINISTER (in the Chair)Tho Right Hon...A&apos;, Chanberlain, M..p.,lord. -Privy Seal,The Right Eon; Sir Robert Horiie, &quot;G.B.E.,K.C.-,M.P.P Chancellor of the exchequer the following- vjoro also prosent:-The Right : Hon. Y-&apos;.C, Bridge man, T-I.P.,Secrotary, Minos DepartmentMr E.A-. Cowers,  C..3.., MinosDepartment.Thomas Jones... ... . . . Ac tihg Soore tary,.Cabinet
STOPPAGE. With reference to the Conference of ministers held at the House of Commons on May 26 th, 1921,at 6.30 p.in. the Conference further consideredthe lines of the statement uhich the Prime minister was about to make to the Conference of Mine Owreroand Miners at the Board of Trade, at 12 Noon.Whitehall Gardens, S.27th May,  1921.
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&quot;S GOVERNMENT)SEC RE T..CONCJJDSrONS-of a Conference ofMinisters held in Mr. Chamberlain&apos; s Room,House of Commons,. S*wV, on Monday, 50th May,1921, at 3.45 p*m*P R E 3 EN Tr-THE PRIME MINISTER (IN THE CHAIR).The Right Hon.. As--Chamberlains M. P.,Lord Privy SealcThe Right Hon. E. Shortt, RVC.,M.p.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon., E.-S. Montagu, M. P.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. S*. Baldwin, M.P* ,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. H3A.:Jt.. Fisher, M..P. ,President of the Boaro of Education^The Right Hon. T. J. Macnamara, M. P.-,Minister of Labours.The Right .Hon* R* Munro,. K.C.,M. P..,^-Secretary for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Robert Home,Q,B.E* j,.K*-C* jMoP, f Chancellor of theExchequer.The Right Hon. W,S.Churchill, M.P.,Secretary of State for the colonies the Right Hon.. Sir L. Worthing ton-Evans, Bart. ,M..Pi,; Secretary ofState for War.The Right Horn Sir A. Mond, Bart.,M, minister of Health.The Right Bon. Sir Ac Griffith--Boecawen. M. P. - Minister of Agricuitur e and Pi sherle s *The Right Hon. C0 Addison, M.P.The Right Hon. Sir Hamar Greenwood.Bart, ,K.C. ,M.P.Chief Secretaryfor Ireland.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTLieut. Colonel Leslie WilsonjC.M.G.,D.S.O.,M.P., joint parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Lieut.-Colonel Sir VL?*-A..Rankey, i3.C.B..................... .Secretary.Mr, Thwrraa^Jorte-s.................. Principal Assistant Secretary.
With, reference to-Cabinet 39(.21) Conclusion 6,&quot;the-MieTif-erence met to consider tho attitude to be adopted&quot;by Members of the G-government in tho forthcoming debate and in tho subsequent division on the two conc-es^sionsrecently proposed to the House of Commons in regard to payment of Members, namely, free travelling expenses to andhomesfrom Members1 constituencies and   v     during tho sessionof Parliament, and remission of income tax on Members1salaries.It was possible that three issues might be raised and brought to a division:(1) The question of remission of income tax on Members1 salaries, which did not affectMinisters:(2) Tho grant of travelling facilities whichbenefited Ministers:(3) The question of whether first or third classfares should be given.There was general agreement on the latter question that, if free travelling expenses were granted, theyshould be for first class travelling.jLfter considerable discussion tho Conference agreei:-fa) That the Lord privy Seal,, should ask the Chairmanof tne Board of Inland Be venue whether the director&apos; ^of a .public company would not be entitled to       Jcharge to the company and free of income tzrx to themselves,, not only their travelling expensesbut also their out of pocket expenses incurred in the discharge of their public duty and invitothe Income Tax Commissioners to give an inter-protation that MomboT-s-1 salaries could be treatedShould the Board-----!ra&quot;-l3Te^*SWe- ESSESTtof Inlaua Revenue   tg iS*2?ul,t* thG        *n the event of a favourable roply tho Lord Privy- haw officers Seal, after seeing the leader of the labour should bo consulted. Partyj should explain that the proposal forremission of ircome tax had boon made with theobject of providing without administrative difficulties similar privileges to those enjoyed by company directors but in view of the hoped for decision of the Commissioners of Income Tax heshould urge the Labour Party not to press It.toa division..     Should a division take place howeverMembers of the Cabinet would abstain from voting.
(c) That, in any division in regard to railwayexpenses, Members of the Cabinet would vote infavour of the grant of first class travelling expenses to and from any part of Membersconstituencies and their homes during thosessions of Parliament.(d) That Members of the Government who are not members of the Cabinet, and took no part inthis decision, should bo free to vote as they wish.     The Lord Privy Seal should howevernotify to them the decision of tho Government and suggest that, if they could not support theGovernment, they should abstain from voting.Muiiohall Gardens ,May 30th 1921
[This Document is tfie Property of Mis Britannic Majesty&apos;a*\joverhrnent. ](MilPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1921.secret.      &apos; 3 -y(H.A.G. 87th Conclusions.)CABINET.COMMITTEE OF HOME AFFAIRS.   87.Conclusions of a Meeting of the above Committee, held.in Mr. Shortt&apos;s Room, Houseof Covimons, S. IT7., on Wednesday, May 2;&quot;), 1921, at 4-T5 P.M.Present :The Right Hon. H. A. L. Fisher, M.P., President of the Board of Education(in the Chair).The Right Hon. E. Shortt, K.C., M.P., j The   Right   Hon.   S.   Baldwin, M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs. President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Sir A. Moxd, Bart., M.P., J The Right Hon. C. Addison, M.P.Minister of Health. The Right Hon. F. G. Kellaway M.P.,The Right Hon. R. Munro, K.C., M.P., Postmaster-General.Secretary for Scotland. iThe following were also present:Sir M. Barlow,  K.B.E., M.P.,  Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry of Labour.The Hon. Hugh Godley, Third Parlia-mentary Counsel.Sir   F.   Baines,   C.B.E.,   M.V.O.,   HisMajesty&apos;s Office of Works.Mr. A. J. Dyke, C.B.E., Board of customs and Excise.Mr. T. Jones, Principal Assistant Secretary, Cabinet.Mr. Pembroke Wicks, Secretary to the Committee.With reference to Home Affairs Committee, 86th Minutes,Conclusion 2, the Committee had under consideration the revised draft of a Bill for the Preservation of Public Order (C.P.-2767).The Home Secretary explained that the Drafting Committee had further considered the draft Bill in the light of the decisious of theHome Affairs Committee, and had had before them a memorandum from Sir Basil Thompson on the effect of omitting Clauses 1 (b) and1 (c), as decided by the Home Affairs Committee, from which itappeared on the one hand that, unless Clause 1 (b) were retained,there would be no adequate means of dealing with the circulation ofinflammatory leaflets ; while if 1 (c) were omitted it would not bepossible to deal with the people who financed illegal societies. Itwas found that whenever an illegal society had run. through itsmoney it became comparatively harmless, and it was, therefore,essential to be able to stop contributions. Accordingly, it was proposed that Clauses 1 (/;) and 1 (c) should be retained, togetherwith the words &quot;gives or&quot; in Clause 1 (e). Those were the mainrespects in which the Drafting Committee had departed from the[6306]
The Home Secretary explained that it was thought that the factthat no prosecution could be commenced without the leave of the attorney-General or the Director of Public Prosecutions would be asufficient protection of innocent people. He deprecated the sugges-tion that the number of books should be increased above three onthe ground that in many cases the leaders of a seditious movementmight have a small number, of books in their possession, the bulkbeing in the hands of printers or other agents. If it were foundnecessary, a higher number than three could be provided as a concession in debate.The Committee agreed That Clause 3 (5) should be retained at present, and that theHome Secretary should obtain from Sir Archibald Bodkina Memorandum for the consideration of the Committee,showing (1) the reason for inserting in the Bill a provisioncreating presumptive evidence of this characier instead of leaving the matter to the discretion of the Courts in theordinary way ; and (2) why it was necessary to make the possession of so small a number as three books presumptiveevidence of intention to distribute.The Home Secretary explained that the word &quot;edits&quot; had been omitted from Clause 1 (6) in order to avoid all unnecessary words.As there appeared to be some doubt whether the editing ofillegal pamphlets was covered by the words &quot; printed and pub-lished&quot;-The Committee agreed That the word &quot; edits &quot; should be inserted in the last line of clause 1 (b).The Committee also agreed That the words &quot; directly or indirectly &quot; in the last line but oneof Clause 1 (fe) should be omitted.The Home Secretary further explained that Sir Basil Thompsonattached great importance to Clause 1 (c), which makes it an offence to contribute to the funds of a society whose object is to do actsmade an offence by the Bill unless the contributor can prove he did not know the illegal purpose of the society.The Chairman stated, on the general question, that he wasalarmed at the provisions of the Bill. The object of the Bill wasexcellent, and he did not deny that harm was being done by revolu-tionary agitation, but he believed that the efforts of the revolutionarieswere being overcome by the common sense of the country and thedevelopment of the industrial position. If he thought the movementswere really dangerous he would not hesitate, but he doubted thepolicy of introducing such a Bill in the near future. The matter ofpolicy was one, however, for the Cabinet, and if a Bill was necessaryhe had no doubt that this was a good Bill.The Home Secretary pointed out that some sixty speakers had recently been prosecuted, and convictions obtained in most cases.All prosecutions had been taken under the Defence of the Realm Act,and as soon as that came to an end by the legal termination of thewar, the authorities would have no suitable means of bringingoffenders to justice.The Committee adjourned the further consideration of thematter till their next meeting.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,May 26, 1921.
SECRET.(H.A.C. 88th Conclusions.)CABINET.COMMITTEE  Off HOME  AFFAIRS, 88.Conclusions of a Meeting of the above Committee held in the Home Secretary&apos;sBoom, House of Commons, S.W., on Tuesday, May 31, 1921, at 415 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. H. A. L. Fisher, M.P., President of the Board of Education(in the Chair).The -Right Hon. E. Suortt, K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon. Sir A. Mono, Bart., M.P.,Minister of Health.Lieut.-Commander Hilton Young&apos;, D.S.O.,M.P., Financial Secretary, Treasury.The Right Hon. C. Addison, M.P.The Right Hon. R. Munbo, K.C., M.P.,Secretary for Scotland.Sir E. M. Pollock, K.B.E., K.C., M.P.,Solicitor-General.The following were also present :Colonel Sir V G. W. Kell, K.B.E.,C.B., War Office (for Conclusion 2).Sir Frank Baines, C.B.E., M.V.O., HisMajesty&apos;s Office of Works (for Con-clusion 1).Mr. H. Wolfe, C.B.E., Ministry of Labour(for Conclusion 1).Sir Malcolm Delevingne, K.C.B., HomeOffice (for Conclusion 1).The Hon. Hugh Godley, Third Parlia-mentary Counsel (for Conclusion 2).Mr. H. F. Caelill, Board of Trade (for conclusion 1).Mr. Pembroke Wicks, Secretary to the Committee.Mr. T. St. Quintin Hill, Principal.Prohibition of theuse of Lead inPainting.[6345]1. The Committee had before them a Memorandum by theHome Secretary (C.P.-2928) dealing with (inter alia) the prohibitionof the use of lead in painting. It was explained to the Committeethat the International Labour Office had sent a questionnaire to allthe Governments which will be represented at the forthcomingInternational Labour Conference inviting their opinion on thequestion of prohibiting the use of lead in painting. The british governments reply would carry great weight with the Conference,and it was proposed to say that the British Government was infavour of a draft convention for the prohibition of lead in paintsbeing submitted for the consideration of the Conference. At theConference the question could be thoroughly discussed.The Committee were also informed that the policy suggested bythe Home Office was based on the reports of two departamental committees, which had recommended the total prohibition of the useBPrinted for the Cabinet.    June 1921.
of lead in paints. No action had been taken on those recommen-dations because the war had intervened. Moreover, the Office ofWorks had been using leadless paints with very satisfactory results.At this point the Office of Works&apos; representative made a stament on behalf of Lord Crawford. Generally speaking, LordCrawford&apos;s view was that the original opinion of the Office of Worksagainst lead in paint was based on evidence which has subsequently been modified. At the time that opinion was expressed, leadlesspaints had been used only for four years. The Office of Workssince that date and as a result of the drastic demand for economy in painting had made an exhaustive enquiry, and had found thatthe durability of leadless paints was vastly inferior to that of painthaving a lead base.Arrangements had been&apos; made for Sir Kenneth Goad by toexamine workmen of the Department who had been engaged for aconsiderable number of years on painting with zinc base paints.Sir Kenneth Goadby informed the Department that symptomsindistinguishable from lead poisoning had been found in the men engaged upon zinc base paints, while such symptoms were not foundin a group of workers examined by Sir Kenneth Goadby employedin the manufacture of white lead, these latter men being only thosewho were exposed to white lead dust.Sir Kennth Goadby expressed the opinion that this surprisingresult was due to the detrimental action of turpentine upon themen. engaged with zinc base paints, and a point which bears upon this, was brought out, namely, that the percentages of turpentineand turpentine substitutes in zinc base paints are higher than thenormal percentages of turpentine and turpentine substitutes in leadbase paintsIt had also been agreed by Sir Kenneth Goadby and theGovernment Chemist, who has been assisting the Department in itsenquiry, that the gravest dangers in connection with the use of leadbase paints were :-1. In the dry rubbing down, and2. In the burning off of old lead paints.Both these dangers, it was suggested, could adequately be dealtwith by regulM,tion.As regards the cost relative to frequency of painting, there wasno doubt that leadless paints were far less durable than lead paints.During recent restorations in one instance it had been foundnecessary to repaint a building winch had been painted six years before with zinc bnse paint, whereas repainting was not necessary before fourteen years in the case of painting done with lead basepaints, it was true that the operatives were in favour of the useof leadless paints, and this might be explained in part by their knowledge that this use increased the frequency and amount of workto be clone.Lord Crawford was of opinion that it would, be very injudiciousfor the British Government to commit themselves to the prohibitionof the use of lead paints in view of the facts recently disclosed bythe Office of Works. His Department were preparing a comprehensive-sive statement on the whole subject for transmission to the HomeOffice.It was urged that the British Government should not, especiallyin view of the statement made by the Office of Works&apos; representa-tive, commit themselves to a prohibition of the use of lead in paints.Such prohibition would undoubtedly ruin a considerable industry,would cause unemployment, and would favour the continentalmanufacturers of leadless paints. The correct policy would be not to suppress the industry&apos;, but to discover the reasons for lead poisoning.Attention was also drawn to the importance of the white leadindustry in this country, which wras a rival to the zinc industry onthe continent.
General agreement was expressed with the view that the subjectneeded further consideration, and the Committee agreed (1.) That the question of the policy to be adopted by HisMajesty&apos;s Government in regard to the use of lead basepaints should be considered again at their next meeting;(2.) That in the meanwhile the following information should be circulated to the Committee :-(a.) A statement which was being prepared by theOffice of Works ;(6.) The views of the Home Office with regard tothe Office of Works&apos; statement;(c.) The reports by the Departmental Committees ;(d.) A statement by the Board of Trade showingthe size of  the white lead trade   in  thiscountry and the number of persons employedin it ;(e.) Any further scientific information which mightbe available.OrderBill for the Preser- 2. With reference to Home Affairs Committee 87th Minutes,vation of Public ^e Committee had \under further consideration the revised draft ofa Bill for the Preservation of the Public Order (C.P.-2767), togetherwith a note by the Director of Public Prosecutions (C.P.-2767 (a))on clause 3 (5) of the Bill, which provides that possession of morethan three copies of an inflammatory book or document shall beevidence of intention to sell and distribute. The memorandum fromthe Director of Public Prosecutions explained that the clause wasnecessary owing to the fact that it would be most exceptional to findpositive evidence of an intention to distribute, and in the absence ofsuch evidence, apart from this clause, the courts would have no powerto convict.The Solicitor-General pointed out that the clause only providedthat possession of the books should be presumptive evidence of an intention to distribute, which could be rebutted by the personaccused, and the courts might also infer an innocent intention fromthe surrounding circumstances.The Secretary for Scotland agreed that the clause merely shiftedthe onus of proof.The Home Secretary added that, moreover, the courts were notobliged to act on the assumption. There was the further protection given by the fact that prosecutions could only be undertaken atthe instance of the Attorney-General or the Director of public prosecutions.The Committee agreed that Clause 3 (5) should remain in the Bill with the substitution offive copies for three.The Parliamentary^ Counsel drew attention to the point whichhad been raised by the Postmaster-General at the preceding-meeting, i.e., that it was not certain that the last paragraph of clause 2 (1), which prohibits the transfer of credit from abroad forillegal purposes, would operate to penalise the persons who obtainthe benefit of the credit in this country, and he accordingly proposedthat the concluding paragraph of clause 2 (1) should be omitted,and that the following should be inserted after clause 2 (2) : &quot; And for the purposes of this provision any person who availshimself of the benefit of any transfer or establishment of credit or authority to pay money from abroad shall bedeemed to have imported money.&quot;The Committee agreed accordingly.[6345] B 2
The Chairman stated that he reserved his right to express tothe Cabinet the misgivings he felt as to the wisdom of introducing a measure of this kind at the present moment. He was very-reluctant to advertise that the country was subject to real dangerfrom revolutionary agitation and preferred to trust to the commonsense of the working classes, who, in his experieiroe, were generallycontemptuous of the revolutionary speeches of street corner orators.The Solicitor-General said that he did not think the danger of allowing the Defence of the Realm Act to Japse without any further provision was fully appreciated. The country would be much moreunprotected than it should be. Legislation of this character hadalready been passed in Canada and the United States, which couldbe a strong argument for use in the House of Commons. Moreover,he protested strongly against the fiction of continuing war legisla-tion, and felt that the continued use of the Defence of the RealmAct and Regulations to obtain convictions on the strength of thelegal fiction that the war was still continuing was wrong.The Committee agreed To present the Bill to the Cabinet for their consideration as an appropriate Bill for the purpose for which it was intended,but without making any recommendations as to policy.ummer Time. 3. xhe Committee had before them a Memorandum by theHome Secretary (CP.-2860) covering a draft Bill to makepermanent the power given by the Summer-Time Act of 1916, toissue Orders in Council as to summer time. This jDOwer had been extended by the War Emergency Laws (Continuance) Act of 1920for a period of one year after the termination of the war, and it wasconsidered to be desirable that permanent legislation providing forsummer time should be passed this session.Some doubt was expressed as to whether, in view of theagricultural opposition, summer time should be made a permanentinstitution, and it was thought that the views of the presentMinister of Agriculture should be invited. It was, however, pointedout that up to now the Ministry of Agriculture had been in favour ofsummer time, and this answer had always been given to farmers whocomplained of summer time.The Committee agreed (1.) That the Home Secretary should be authorised to introduce the Summer Time Bill in Parliament during the present session.(ii.) That the question need not be referred to the Cabinet.Markets Committee 4. With reference to H.A.C. 81 (6) the Committee had beforethem a note by the Secretary of the Cabinet (C.P.-2830) covering the 4th, 5th and final reports of the Departmental Committee onthe wholesale food markets of London. These reports related towholesale fruit and vegetable markets, meat supplies and distribution,and the influence of wholesale market facilities on food prices.The Committee agreed -To approve the publication as a Stationery Office publicationof the 4th, 5th and final reports of the DepartmentalCommittee  n the wholesale food markets of London.5. The Committee had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Health (OP.-2966), asking for permission to introduce aBill making certain readjustments in the finance of national health Insurance. It was proposed by regulation to increase from&quot;5d. per member per annum to i&apos;10d. per member per annum, the report .National HealthInsurance:administrative expenses.
sum allowed Societies for administrative purposes; but before the regulation could be made, certain financial readjustments of theinsurance funds which could only be effected by legislation would benecessary, as the additional money required was to be taken fromthe Societies&apos; reserve funds. Opportunity would be taken in theBill to relieve the Exchequer of certain liabilities, and this wouldresult in a net saving to the Exchequer of about 300,0007. perannum during the next five years, and a sum approximating to this figure after that. The Bill possessed the support of the approved societies, and no opposition was expected from any quarter as noextra contribution would be imposed, and the normal benefits wouldbe unaffected. Unless the Bill were passed it would be necessary to alter the contribution of the insured, which would be both undesirableand difficult.The Committee agreed To authorise the Minister of Health to introduce a Bill pro-viding for certain readjustments in the finance ofNational Health Insurance ; the Bill to follow the linesof the draft attached to his Memorandum, dated May 24,1921 (C.P.-2966).Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,June 1, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
