<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/26/0 images: 211-215</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
BOOTMEy^IS-*-THEJ?ROP OF HIS BRITAKBIC MAJESTYrS GOYEHUMSMt) .E CHBT&apos;CABINET 63 (21)pihal COPY MOCONCLUSIONS of a: Meeting of theCabinet, hold in Mr. Chamberlain^Room, Eouse of Conakons^ S.I., onFriday, 5th Jlugust, 1921 at IB Noon.EBBS E N j;-THE PRIME MINISTER    (la the Chair).s Right Hon, A * Chamberlain,Lord Privy Seal,j Most Hon, The Marques a?zon of Se dies ton, K,Gc,),S,I.,G*C.I,,E,t secretary state for Foreign Affairs.j Sight Hon, E,S,Montagu,Seoretary of State  ors Right Hon. Lord Lee ofrehasa, G.B.E..K.C.B;,, Firstrd of the Admralty.j Right Hon. H*A.L. Fisher9President of the BoardEducation,5 Right Hon, R, MunrOj, K.C.,?0&amp; Secretary for Scotland,The Right Eoii. E..Shdrtt, K6d.,M.P.*Seoretary of State for Home Affairs,,The Right Hon. ff,S. Churchill, M,P,,Seoretary of State for the Colonies,.The Right Hon. Sir&apos;L, WorthingtoaEvans, Bart,, M*P.0 Secretary ofState for War,The Right Hon, Stanley Baldwin,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade,The Right Hon,* Sir A. Griffith-Bosoawen, M.P,, Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon, Sir Haamr Greenwood,Bart.,K^C.jM(.P., Chief Secretaryfor Ireland.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT;-Sir Arthur EirtSel, K.C.B.,QMer-Secretary, India Office,(For Conclusion    1. ).Sir E. Grigg, E.C*V.O.,C.M.G.lieutenant Colonel Sir M,P,A. HanksyCCB....................Secretary.jr. Thomas Jones.,...................... ,Principai Assistant^ecretary-.-
(D With .xeferene-e--to- Cabinet 45 (21.)^-Conclusion 5, theCabinet had before thera a Memorandum by the Secretary of State*0T India, together with a series of telegrams dealing withthe present position of the negotiations for a Treaty betweenthe--Governments of India-and Afghanistan (Paper CP.,-3195) .The Secretary of State for India described the negc-tiations which, after at one time ho3 Ling out every promise of the conclusion of a Treaty to the exclusion and discomfit-ure of the Bolsheviks in Afghanistan, had recently deterioratedto a point at which the Government of India considered itnecessary to fall back on what has come to be known as the&quot;pis aller&quot; Treaty, that is to say, a Treaty which would leavethe Afghans free to receive a siibsidy and munitions from theBolsheviks.Cabinet-were-reicind^d that the Cabinet had been willing to acquiesce in such a Treaty, but only as a last resortas they regarded it with intense dislike (Cabinet 37 (21), Con-elusion 3) .During the meeting the Secretary of State for India read a fresh telegram from Sir Henry Dobbs, dated August 1, 1921       &apos;(Viceroy telegram No,187?,. of August 3rd).     In this connec-tion some discussion took place in regard to the phrase&quot;limited assurance&quot; against Russian aggression, which, it was proposed in the penultimate paragraph, Sir Henry Dobbs shouldbe given discretion to grant or refuse, if pressed for by the afghans.    The Cabinet were assumed.rod by the Secretary of State-for India and Sir Arthur Hirtzel that this phrase-only impliedthe furnishing of war material and munitions, and not assist-ance in the form of troops, which had never been contemplated in any contingency.     In this connection the Cabinet were reminded that in former days a Russian invasion of Afghanistanwould have been; taken very seriously, even to the point ofjustifying the despatch of troops to Afghanistan, and the corn-men t was made that even today, when the status of Afghanistanhad considerably changed, such an invasion would involvevery serious decisions. ^
The Cabinet felt that the telegram,from Sir Henry-Dobbs (of August 1st), read during the meeting, had to aconsiderable extent changed the situation.    Sir Henry Dobbsiappeared more hopeful of obtaining the exclusive   Treaty,and less apprehensive of the attitude of the tribe3.    To this had to be added the recent defeat of Mustapha kemal, news ofwhich could hardly yet have permeated fully into Afghanistan!The attention of the Cabinet was invited at thi3 stage to some recent well-informed articles iri the &quot;ManchesterGuardian&quot;, which irflicated that the Afghan resistance to theTreaty was due to a Pan-Islamic rather than a Bolshevist move-,ment, and that the Greek victories would prove particularlydestructive to Pan-Islamism.   Moreover, British, as comparedwith Turkish, prestige- was.,Likely to be further enhanced ifrecent tentative overtures by the Turks to British Generalsand diplomatists In Constantinople   which appeared to bebased on the assumption that Great Britain was the only Powerthat could render assistance   are followed up by a demandfor British intervention.    Finally, the Cabinet were reminded that 4 In view o-r the widespread famine in Russia, the Bolshe-boisheviks were not in a position to exercise very serious pressure in Afghanistan.In these circumstances the Cabinet felt that the momertwas very inopportune for sanctioning,even as a last resort, theconclusion of the &quot;pis aller&quot; Treaty, which, it was felt, con-ceded too much, obtained too little, and, if offered by sir henry Bobbs, would be the extreme limit of humiliation for theBritish Empire.The Secretary of State for India drew the attentionof the Cabinet to the Viceroy&apos;s telegram. Ho.1855, of July 30,describing the probable effects of failure^to conclude any
Treatys and Informed the Cabinet that the views of theGovernment of India were shared by Lord RaWlinson who had been consulted throughout.On a review of these considerations, the Cabinet(a) authorised the Secretary of State for India tocommunicate the opinion of the Cabinet to theViceroy at full length, explaining that the cabinet have reviewed the situation in the light of thenew factorsi which should also be set out at fulllength.     First among these should appear sir henry Dobb&apos;s telegram of August 1st, which might befollowed by a summary of.the world factors/ concludingwith a definite statement that Sir Henry Doibbs should refuse at the present juncture the &quot;pis aller&quot; Treaty^but contemplating the discussion of an ordinary treaty which would not Involve a subsidy.(The Secretary of State for Indian while accepting the above policy  asked, however^ that it might beplaced on record that if, after learning the flewsof the Cabinet, the Viceroy and the government ofIndia reiterated their previous?opinion in&apos;favwarof the *pis alXep49 Treaty, he eould no  take theresponsibility of over-riding their repeated r^niesis^^(b) invitpd the consideration of the Secretary of Statefor India  o a proposal that, in view of the fact thatthe G^vernwent of India have already authorised sir henry Dobbs &quot;in the last resort to accept ihe &quot;pisa-ller11 Treaty, a short telegram should .be despatchedtoo the Government of InlSia to the eHfeci that g pendingtho receipt of the full views of the Cabinet, msuch action should be t&amp;kem(2) In the course of the preceding discussion on Af^ghanls-tan-the suggestion was advanced that sufficient use had nei oeesimade of the terms of the Russian Trade Agreement to preventRussian hostility and anti-British- propaganda in Afghanistan-and elsewhereoThe Cabinet agreed - ^  %(a) That the Prime Minister^ in his conversation thesame afternoon with the Head of the Russian-Trade-&quot;&apos;Delegation, should take the opportunity to make suitable representations on the subjects(b) That the Secretary of State for India should furnish.  ..the Prime Minister with particulars of the moresalient examples of breach of the Agreement.
2, TJnitehall Gardens, S.W.,5th August, 1921.[AND.     (3) With reference to Cabinet 62 (21), Conclusion 3,the Cabinet had under consideration a draft Parliamentaryitary .Question and Reply, the form of which had been agreed by the Attorney-General, dealing with the position whichhad arisen owing to the action of the Master of the RollsIn the case of two Irish prisoners who had been arrested and sentenced to death and subsequently released.The Cabinet approved the Answer subject tothe Secretary of State for War amending the closing paragraph so as to make it clear thatthe considerations which had influenced theGovernment were confined to the case of thetwo prisoners.The Prime Minister indicated that if pressedhe would be bound to say that the two men had been released on the advice of the LordChancellor.of Ireland.onlng   (4)   That Cabinet ware informed that Mr. de Valera wasDail .   .ann.     summoning a Meeting of Dail Eireann for August 16th, andIn a ccordance with the pledges given by the PrimeMinister it was proposed to release the members who were&quot;under arrest with the exception of two or three personswh&amp; had been direct ly involved In cases of murder.The Cabinet agreed -That members of Dail Eireann should be released with the exception of two or threepersons indicated by the Chief Secretary,

</content>
</cab>
