<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/26/0 images: 256-275</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ffllS POCTOiiNT 13 THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIQ MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT)^5CRET,i0, i B I II B I   66 (21)CONCLUSIONS Of a Mooting of tto Cabinet,hold      at 10* Downing stroot, S.W., on Saturday.13th August. 1921 at 11-3Q a.m.PRESENT:-THE PRIME MINISTER (in tho Chair )GL Right Hon. A^Chamberlain, M.P., The Right Hon. discount Birfcenhead,kord Privy Seal\ Lord Chancellor, ^.....-13 Right Hon. E.Shortt, r,C,,M,P,, The Right Hon. W.3. Churobiill M.P.!39oretary of State for Home Affairs. Seoro tary of State for the Coloniespe Right Hon. E.S* Montagu, M.P. fLoretary of State for India.jibe &quot;Right HOn. Lord Lee of Pare-[ham, G.B.E.. first Lord[of the Admiralty.She Right HOn. Sir Alfred Mond.Bart., M.P., Minister of Kealth0The Right Hone&apos; Sir A. Griffith Boscawen. M.P.* Minister ofAgriculture and Pisherlos0She Right Hon. R. Munro, i:.C,MSP0, Secretary for Scotland.The Right Hon, Sir L,Wording to;Evans6 Bart.,M.P.s Secretary ofState for War.The Right Hon, S. Baldwin, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. H.A.L. Fisher, M.P.,President of the Board of Education^The Right Hon. T.J. Maonamara, M.P.,Minister of Labour.The right Hon. Sir Hamar Greenwood,Bart.sK,C.,M.P.9        Chief Secretaryfor&apos;Ireland.Jho Right Eon. The LordFitzalan-of Berwent,G.C,v.o.,B.S.Q*THE following Y/BRE ALSO PRESENT;-&quot;*&quot;&apos;        &apos;   nwi &apos; &quot;   &quot;Ml&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot; &apos;   l!* 1 &quot;in&quot;&quot;1  w*&quot;p*&quot;  -    ii    i    Jin ( mSir E. Grigg9 E.C,Ys0.sC.M.^^iiqutonant-Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hahfcey,; G.C.B..................Secretary-,Thomas Jones........................-Principal Assistant Secretary.
?. With reference to Cabinet 65 (21), Conclusion 2, the Cabinet had before them the proposals of the British Government for an Irish Settlement as handed by the Prime Minister to Mr. de Valera on July 20th, 1921 - (C.P. 3149, in Appendix1), and Mr. de Valera&apos;s reply dated August 10th (C.P. 3214 -in Appendix 11).

The Prime Minister read a letter: from Colonel Wigram to the Lord Privy Seal acquating him of the King&apos;s views on Mr. Chamberlain&apos;s unfavourable report of Mr. de Valera&apos;s reply. Considerable doubts were expressed as to the meaning of Mr. de valera&apos;s letter.

On the one hand it was generaally accepted that in form the reply constituted a rejection of the Governments proposals. In particular, Dominion status was unambignously rejected as a basis for negotiation. Moreover, the letter appeared to propose an alternative basis of negotiations, which was wholly unacceptable to the cabinet 

namely, the basis of Ireland as an independent nations.

On the other hands the letter contained admissions of aconsiderable amount of agreement in substance with the British proposals. This, it was suggested, might be regarded as evidence that Mr. de Valera&apos;s letter was an attempt - aven though a clumsy attempt, to keep open the discussion and that the doenment was intended as merely a step in a prolonged negotiation. Instances of this measure of agreement were the suggestion of association with the British Empire group as with a partial League of Nations; no coercion of Ulster; the desirability of trade and commerce between Great Britain and Ireland; tha guarded willingness in principle, to accept a share In the British war debt; a mutual limitation of armaments and the possibility of agreement in regard to air, railway, and other communications.

The suggestion was made that the British Government&apos;s reply should contain a reference to this evidence of agreement in substance.


Apart from the document itself, some evidence was laid before the Cabinet to show that the reply was hotintended as a final rejection of the British Government&apos;terms and a determination of the negotiations.     A tele-gram was read from Mri Cope of Dublin Castle to this effect and attention was called to statements made by the represnt-atlves of Sinn Fein, both in London and Paris, indicating that the letter was not intended to bring negotiations toan end9   The suggestion was made that the document was probably intended to put Mr. Be Valera and his colleagues in a safe position vis-a-vis the extremists of Sail Sir eannwhom they had to meet on Tuesday next.   The Cabinet were reminded that the persons with whom negotiations were being conducted posed as Republicans, that the members of BailElrfeann had been elected as Republicans and that even though their leaders were sincerely anxious to pave the way to anagreement with the British Government they were bound to start.from this stand point *There was a strong consensus cf opinion that theBritish government&apos;s reply should be brief, clear andprecise in order to remove any doubt whatsoever as to their intentions; that it should contain an explicit repudiationof the suggestion that Ireland could be outside the BritishEmpire or that Irish questions could be submitted to for-eign arbitratier; that it should point out the omissionfrom Mr. Be Valera1 s letter of any comment on the firstcondition laid down in the British proposals that the royal navy alone should control the seas around Ireland and GreatBritain and that such rights in the Irish Harbours andon the Irish Coasts should be scoorded to it as are essential; and that no advance could possibly be made on....\ -/ill
on the posit ion- taken. .tcp-Jni^he^rdgJnaXvpreLKJsaXsof the British Government.After considering the draft which the PrimeMinister had had prepared before the meeting, theCabinet reached the following conclusions -(a) A Cabinet Committee composed as follows:-The Prime Minister.The Lord Privy Seal.The Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Secretary of ijtate for war.The Secretary for Scotland.should immediately meet with full powers to arafta reply to Mr. De Valera in accordance with thegeneral lines of the disoussion summarised above.(b) The Prime Minister should communicate this reply to Mr. Be Valera at the earliest possible moment,   a copy of the reply as aotually sent isattached in Appendix 111,(o)   That immediately after the meeting, the PrimeMinister should notify Mr. Barton or one of the otherSinn Pein representatives in London, that the letterwould be ready this afternoon and should ask thatarrangements might he made for conveying it tonightto Mr. Be Valera and for warning him by telegram to expect It.(d) That the whole of the correspondence includingthe reply in Appendix *11 should be publishod onMonday August 15th as a Parliamentary paper and shouldbe communicated to the press in time for publication in the newspapers of Monday morning August 15th.(e) That the Sinn Pein representatives in london should be notified by the Prime   Minister of theGovernments intentions as regards publication.2, Whitehall hardens, S,W.  (1)12th August, 1921.
3149. APPENDIX I.

I. PROPOSALS OF THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT.

FOR AH IRISH SETTLEMENT, 20Th JULY,  1921.

The British Government are ? by an earnest desire to end the unhappy divisions between Great Britain and Ireland which have produCed so many conflicts in the past and which have once more shattered the peace and well-being of Ireland at the present time. They long with His Majesty the King, in the words of His Gracious Speech in Ireland last month, for a satisfactory solution of "those age-long Irish problems whioh for generations&apos; embarrassed our forefathers, as they now weigh heavily upon us" and they wish to do their utmost to secure, that "every man of Irish birth, whatever be his creed and wherever be his home, should work in loyal co-operation with, the free communities on which the British Empire is based". They are convinced that the Irish people may find as worthy and as complete an expression of their political and spiritual ideals within the Empire as any of the numerous and varied nations united in allegiance to His Majesty&apos;s Throne; and they desire such, a consummation, not only for the welfare of Great Britain, Ireland and the Empire as a whole, but also for the cause of peace and harmony throughout the world. There is no part of the world where Irishmen have made their home but suffers from our ancient feuds; no part of it but looks to this meeting between the British Government and the Irish leaders to resolve these feuds in a new understanding
honourable and satisfactory to all the peoples invTxLved*The free nations which compose the British Empireare drawn from many races, with different historiesttraditions and ideals.    In the Dominion of Canada, Britishand French have long forgotten the bitter conflictswhich divided their ancestors.   Xn South Africa the transvaal Republic and the Orange Free State have joined with two British colonies to make a great self**governing union under His Majfesty8s sway.     The british people cannot believe that wh^re Canada and SouthAfrica, with equal or even greater difficulties have sosignally succeeded, Ireland wi^.1 fail; and they are determined that so far as th0^ themselves&apos;can assure it,nothing shall hinder Irish statesmen.from Joiningtogether to build up an Irish fttate in free and willingec-operation with the other petioles of the Empire*Moved by these considerations,   the British Governmentinvite Ireland to take her p^ace in the great associationof free nations over which His Majesty-reigns.   As. .earnest of their desire to oblitera+^e old quarrels and to enableIreland to face the future with her own - strength and hopethey propose that Ireland shall assume forthwith the status of a Dominion with all the powers and privileges set forth in this document.    By the adoption of Dominion status, itis understood that Ireland ahall enjoy complete autonomy..In taxation and finance; that she shall maintain her .own.courts of Law and Judges; thai/ she shall maintain her ownmilitary forces for Home Defence, her own Constabulary and-her own Police: that she shall, take over the Irish postal services and all matters relating thereto,  education^land, agriculture, mines and Sjiinerals., for-as-try^ housing^ ..
health insurance and the liquor -traffic and, in stun,that she shall exercise all th^se powers and priviXegs-s AjpOElwhich the autonomy of the s &amp;lf*^y^a?nixig Dominions is&quot; baa-ed..,subject only to the considerations set cut in the ensuingparagraphs.   Guaranteed in these liberties, which neforeign people can.,challenge, without challenging the Empire,as a whole, the Dominions * ho Id. each and severally by virtue&apos; of their British fellowship a standing amongst the nations-equivalent, &quot;not merely to. their individual^ strength, butto the combined power and influence of all the nations &apos;ofHhe Commonwealth.   That guarantee, that fell4rmrhip^th&amp;$freedom the whole Empire looks to Ireland to accepts.&apos; To this&apos; settlement the British Government are preparedto give immediate effect upsn the following conditions,    which  are, in their epinion, vital to the welfare and. safety of &quot;both Great Britain and Ireland, forming as they do the heart of the Cemmonwealtha ...I.   The common concern of Great Britain and Trelandin the defence of their interests by land and sea shall be mutually recognised.   GreatBritain lives by sea--bcrne food; her-^ooiTOCini^cations depend upon the freedom of the greatsea routes..    Ireland lies at Britainrs sideacross the sea-ways.north and south that linkher with the sister nations of the Empire^the markets of the world and the vital  -sources of her food supply.&apos;   In recognition,of this fact, which nature, has&apos;imposed ;and,no -statesmanship can change, it is, ess-fentialthat the Royal Navy alone should, control the seas around Ireland and Great T^r/^aJLcLj
-ana&quot; --that -&quot;suoh. rights -and- liJberrti-ers -shouldbe accorded to It by the Irish State as are essential for naval purposes in the Irishharbours and on&apos;the Irish coasts.In order that the movement towards thelimitation of armaments which is now&quot; making&apos;&quot;&quot;-^progress in the world should&apos; in he way&apos;be&apos;hampered;, it is stipulated that the IrishTerritorial Force shall within reasonable limits :conform in respect of numbers to themilitary establishments of the other partof thede islands,The position of Ireland is also of greatimportance for the air services both militaryand civila      The Royal Air Force will needfacilities for all purposes that it serves; andIreland will form an essential link in thedevelopment of air &quot;routes between the british isles and the North American Continent *    ItIs therefore stipulated.that Great Britian shallhave all necessary facilities for the develop-merit of defence and ef communications by airj.Great Britain hopes that Ireland, will indue course and cf her own free will contributeIn proportion to her wealth to the RegularNaval Military and-Air Forces of  the EmpiresIt is further assumed that voluntary recruit-ment for these forces will be permittedthroughout Ireland, particularly for thosefamous Irish Regiments -which have so long andsc gallantly served His Majesty in all partscf the world.
V. While the Trish people^d-e-XhaXl erijoy completeaui^onomy in taxation and finance, it is essential -to prevent, a recurrence of ancient differences between the two islandsj and in particular to avert the possibility of ruinoiis trade wars,&quot;with  this object in view, the British and IrishGovernments&apos; shall agree to impose no protective&apos;duties or other restrictions upon the flow;:&apos;oftransport, trade and commerce between all parts of these islands;VI. The Irish people shall agree to assume res-ponsibility &quot;or a share of the present debt ofthe United Kingdom and Of the liability for pensions arising out of the Great War, the share,In default of agreement between the Governmentsconcerned, to be determined by an independentarbitrator appointed from within His Hajosty* sDominionsIn accordance with these principles, the BritishGovernment- propose that the conditions of settlement between .Great Britain and Ireland shall be embodied in the form of&apos; aTreaty, to which effect shall in due course be given by theBritish and Irish Parliaments.   They look to such an instrumentto obliterate old conflicts forthwith, to clear the way for a detailed settlement in full accordance with Irish conditions and needs, and thus to establish a new and happier relation between Irish patriotism and that wider community of aims and interests by which the unity of the whole Empire Is freelysustained, .        .   &apos;The form in which the settlement is to take effect will depend upon Ireland herself.    It must allow for full recognition of the existing powers and privileges
of &quot;the rarllamenlk and Governm^which cannot be abrogated except by their own consentsFor their part the British (Krv-evrmen^ entertain an earnest hope that the necessity of harmonious oo-operation amongst Irishmen of all classes and creedswill be recognis-ed throughout. Ireland, and they will welcome the day when by these means unity in achieved.But no such common action can be secured by force.Union came in Canada by the free consent of theProvinces.   So in&quot; Australia; so in South Africa.    Itwill come in Ireland by no othe&apos;r way than consent,There can,  in fact, be no settlement on terms involving,on the one side or the other, that bitter appeal tobloodshed and violence which all men cf good will arelonging to terminate,   The British Government will  -undertake to give effect, so far as that depends on them, ts any terms in this respect on which all Ireland.unites.    But in no conditions can they consent to any proposals which would kindle civil war in Ireland,    Sucha war would not touch Ireland alone, for partisans wouldflock to either side from Great Britain, the Empire, and elsewhere with consequences more devastating to the welfare both of Ireland and the Empire than the conflictto which a truce has been called this month.    Throughoutthe Empire there is a deep desire that the   day of violence should pass and that a solution should be found,consonant with the highest ideals and interests of all parts cf Ireland, which will enable her to co-operate aswilling partner in the British Commonwealth.The BritjLsh Government will therefore leaveIrishmen themselves to determine by negotiation&amp;betweenthem whether the new powers which the pact defines shallbe taken over by Ireland as a whole and administered
&quot;by a single Irish body, &apos;or taken^vv^er-^-s-e^Southern and Northern Ireland, with or without a joint authority to harmonise their common interests,   Theywill willingly assist in the negotiaticn cf such asettlement, if Irishmen should se desire.By these proposals the British Governmentsincerely believe that they will have shattered the foundations cf that arr-ient hatred and distrust which  -have disfigured our common history for centuries past.The future Cf Ireland within the Commonwealth isfor the Irish people to shape *In the foregoing proposals the British Governmenthave attempted no more-than the bread outline of asettlement.   The details they leave for discussionwhen the Irish people have- signi.fi-ed:- &quot;their aoc-ept-anoe^-*f the&quot;&quot;principle of this pact,( bgd ) I). LLOYD GEOKGE.&quot;IS, Downing Street, S/7,1.,-July 20th,,  1921. -
J.P.J521&amp;.APPENDIX II.  -REPLY FROM MR. DE YALBRA TO tfPROPOSALSTHE BRITISH GOVERNMENT FOR Afl IRISHoETTLEMBHT&quot; i  (See CP. -3149).(Official Translation). -Office of the President,Bublisv Mansion House,August 10, 1921.The- Bt* Hon. &quot;David Idoyd Gear go,10, 2kpwfo3ssng Street sWhitehall, London^Sir,On the occasion of our last interview I gave it as my judgment that Dail Eireann could net and that the irish people would not accept the proposals of your Government asset forth.in the draft of July 20th which you had presented to me*     Having consulted my colleagues, and with themgiven these proposals the most earnest consideration, I nowconfirm that judgment.The outline given In the draft is self-contradictory,and &quot;the principle of the pact&quot; noi easy to determine.   Tothe extent that it Implies a recognition of Ireland*sseparate&apos;nationhood and her right to self-determination, we appreciate and accept it.     But in the stipulations andexpress conditions concerning the matters that are vitalthe principle is strangely set aside and a claim advanced by your Gcrrernment to an interference in our affairs, andto a control which we cannot admit.Irelandrs
Ireland:1 s right to^ehoose. fox hestfeedJT the path sheshall take to realise her own de-sttiny&quot; must he accepted as indefeasible.       It is a right that has heen,siQaijatai-nedthrough centuries of oppression and at the cost of unpajradlel-*-ed sacriS^-and^untold...3uffering ,   and it-will not be surrendered.      //a cannot propose to abrogate or impair it,nor can Britain or any other foreign state or group of states legitimately claim to interfere with its exercise inorder to serve their own special interests.The Irish peopled belief is that tha national destinycan best be realised in political detachment, free fromimperialistic entanglements  which they feel will involveenterprises out of harmony with the national character, provedestructive &amp;  their ideals, and be fruitful only of - ruinouswars, crushing burdens, social discontent, and general unrest and unhappiness.    -&quot;Lie the small statas of Europe they areprepared to hazard their independence on the basis of moralright&quot;, confident that as they would threaten no nation orpeople they would In turn be free from aggression themselves.This is the policy they have declared for in plebiscite after &apos;&apos;plebiscite, and the degree to which any other line of policydeviates from it must be taken as a measure of the extent towhich external pressure is operative and violence is being done to the wishes of the majority.As for myself and my colleagues, it is our deep conviction that true friendship with England, - which military coercionhas frustrated for centuries, can be obtained most readilynow through amicable but absolute separation.     The fear,groundless though we believe it to be, that Irish territorymay be used as the basis for an attack upon England&apos;s liber-ties can be met by reasonable guarantees not inconsistent with Irish sovereignty.
&quot;Dominion. status&quot; &quot;far^Ireland-o-reryxme who un^r^tands &quot;tl%e-conditions know .8 to he illusory.   The freedom,-which the british dominions enjoy is not so much the result of legal enactments .or cf treaties as of the immense distances which separate them from Britain&apos;and have made interference by her impracticable.The most explicit guarantees, including the Dominions1 acknow-1edged right to secede, would be necessary to secure for ireland an equal degree of freedom.    There is no suggestionhowever in the proposals made of any such guarantee si    Instead,the natural posit ion is reversed; our geographical situation with respect to Britain is made the basis of denials and re-st-ric-tions unheard of in the case of the Dominions; the smallerisland must give military safeguards and guarantees to thelarger and suffer itself to be reduced to the position of ahelpless dependency.It should be obvious that we could not urge the acceptanceof such proposals upon our people.   A certain treaty of freeassociation with the British Commonwealth group, as with a partial league of nations, we would have been ready to recom-mend, and as a Government to negotiate and take responsibilityfor, had/we an - assurance that the entry of the nation as awhole into such association would secure for it the allegianceof the present dissenting minority, to meet whose sentimentalone this step could be contemplated. .Treaties - dealing with the proposals for free inter-trade and mutual limitation of armaments we are ready at any- timeto negotiate.   ^Mutual agreement for facilitating air communica-tions, as well a8&quot; railway and other communications, can we feelcertain also be effected.    Ho obstacle of any kind, will be
placed by us in tJbJ^-^war of that-mttac^ IzrUrwarsewhich is essential in the life of both islands, each the bestcustomer and the best market of the other.     It must of course be understood  vhat all treaties and agreements would have tobe submitted for ratification to the national legislature inthe first instance, and eubse^errfcly to the Irish people a3 awhole., under oli^cumstaaacee which would make it evident thattheir decision would be a free decision, and that, every element,of military compulsion was absent.The question of ireland liability &quot;for a share ef thepresent debt of the United Kingdom&quot; we are prepared to leave to be^determined by a board of arbitrators, one appointed byIreland, one by Great Britain, and a third to be chosen byagreement,, or* In default, to be $gs&amp;inated, say, by the Presidentof the United States of America, If the President would consents.As regards -the question at Issue between the politicalminority and the great majority of the Irish pesple, that must remain a question fer the Irish people themselves to settle.We cannot admit the right of the British Government to mutilatecur country, either In Its own interest or at the call ef any section ef our population.     We do not contemplate the use of force.     If your Government stands aside, we can effect a com-plete reconciliation.     We agree with you &quot;that no common action can be secured by force&quot;.     Our regret is that this wiseand true principle which your Government prescribes to us for thesettlement of our local problem it seems unwilling to applyconsistently to the fundamental problem of the relations between our island and yours.     The principle we rely on In the one case we are ready to apply in.the other, but should this principlenot yield an   Immediate aettlement we are willing that thisquestion too be submitted to external arbitration.
Thus we--are ready to meet you In all that is reasonable and just.     The responsibility for initdaiing -and effecting an.honourable peace rests primarily not with our Government but .with yours.     We have no conditions to impose, no claims to advance but the one, that we be freed from aggression.He reciprocate with a sincerity to be measured only by theterrible sufferings oxir people have undergone the desireyou express for mutual and lasting friendship.     The solecause of the &quot;ancient feuds&quot; w ich you deplore has been, aswe know, and as history proves,  the attacks of English rulersupon Irish liberties.     These attacks can cease forthwith,if your Government has the will.     The road to peace and understanding lies open.I am, Sir,Faithfully yours,(Signed) EAMON   DE VALERA.
II-.   JSJ?H^J^:i^TSEJ SJRBPLX.TO.,MR. t JDS,. VALERA&apos;Si LETTER. 01 AUGUST ,10th, . 1921.10, Downing Street,13th August, 1521.Sir,The earlier part of your letter is so much opposed toour fundamental position that we feel bound to.leave you inno doubt of our meaning.    &apos;7ou state that after consultingyour colleagues you confirm your declaration that our proposals are such as Dail Eireann could not, and the Irish people .would not, accept.    You add that the outline given in ourdraft is self-contradictory, and the principle of the pactoffered to you not easy to determine.    We desire, therefore,to make our position absolutely clear.In sur^opinion, nothing is to he gained by prolonginga theoretical discussion of the national status which you maybe willing to accept as compared with that of the great self-governing Dominions of the British Commonwealth, hut we mustdirect your attention to one point upon which you lay, someemphasis and upon which no British Government can compromise -namely, the claim that we should acknowledge the right ofIreland to^-secede from her allegiance to the King.    Ho suchright can ever be acknowledged.&quot;by us.    The geographical pro-pinquity of Ireland to the British Isles is a&apos; fundamental fact.The history of the two islands for many centuries, however -destiniesit is read, is sufficient proof that, their are indis-solubly     linked.    Ireland, has sent members to the british parliament for more than a hundred years.    Many thousands.ofher people during all that time have enlisted freely andserved gallantly in the Forces of the Crown,    Great numbers,in all the Irish provinces, -are&quot;profoundly attached to the throne-, &quot;These facts permit of one answer, and one only, to theclaim&apos; that Britain should negotiate with Ireland as a separate and foreign, power.
3CT3Q&apos;jiE 111,II- -    I SrpiqHJ;i VIJj-IbTgiEJ BJREPLY. TO.MR., JDS, VALERA1 SLETTER QI- AUGUST ,1.0th., 1921.Sir,10, Lewning Street,8,&apos;?.13th August, IS21,The earlier part of your letter ie- so much opposed toour fundamental position that we feel hound to.leave you inno doubt of our meaning,    l/ou state that after consultingyour colleagues you confirm your declaration that our preposalsare such as Dail Eireann could not, and the Irish people .would not, accept.    You add that the outline given in ourdraft is self-contradictory, and the principle of the pactoffered to you not easy to determine.    We desire, therefore,to make pur position absolutely clear.In ^ur^opinion, nothing is to be gained by prolonginga theoretical discussion of the national status which you maybe willing to accept as compared with that of the great self-governing Jbominions of the British Commonwealth, but we mustdirect your attention to one point upon which you lay, someemphasis and upon which no British Government can -compromise -namely, the claim that we should acknowledge the right ofIreland to-secede from her allegiance to the King.    No such- right can ever &quot;be acknowledged by us.    The geographical pro-pinquity of Ireland to the British Isles is a fundamental fact.The history of the two islands for many centuries, howeverdestiniesit is read,  is sufficient proof that their are indis-solubly     linked.    Ireland has sent members to the british parliament for more than a hundred years.    Many thousands ofher people during all that time have enlisted, freely andserved gallantly in the forces of the Crown.    Great numbers,in all the Irish provinces, -are&quot;&apos; profoundly attached, to the throne,    These facts permit cf one answer,  and- one only,  to the./ &apos;claim&apos; that Britain should negotiate with Ireland, as a separateJ and foreign power.
when you, as the chosen representative-of-JLrish national,ideals, came to speak with me,  I made one condition only,of which our proposals plainly stated, the effect -    that ireland should recognise the force of geographical andhistorical facts.    It is -those facts which govern the problemcf British and Irish relations.    If they did not exist.,  therewould be no problem to discuss.I pass therefore to the conditions which.are imposed by these facts.    Wo set thorn out clearly in six clauses, -in.our former proposals, and need not restate them here,except to say that the British Government cannot consent- to the reference of any such questions which concern Great Britainand Ireland alone, to the arbitration of a foreign Power.We are-profoundly glad to have your agreement that northern Ireland cannot be&apos; coerced.    This point is of greatimportance, because the resolve of our people to resist withtheir full power any, attempt at secession by&apos;one part ofIreland carries with it cf necessity an equal resolve to resist any effort to coerce another pa,rt of Ireland toabandon its allegiance to the Crown.    We gladly give you the assurance that we will concur in any settlement whichSouthern and northern Ireland may make for Irish unitywithin the six conditions already laid down, which apply to southern and northern Ireland alike;  but we cannot agree to   -of your reI at i ons with northern  Ire1andrefer the question/to foreign -arbitration.The conditions&apos; of the proposed settlement do not.arise from any desire to force cur will upon people of anotherrace,, &quot;but from facto which are ao vital to Ireland&apos;s welfarenoas to our own..   They contain/derogation from ireland sstatus as a Dominion, no desire for British ascendancy overIreland,  and no impairment of Ireland&apos;s national ideals.
Our pr-opo.sa.ls p-resen.t--.to -4Jae-..Ixi-sli-people an dpportu-nity such as has never dawned, in their history before^We have made them in the sincere desire to achieve peace;hut beyond them we cannot gb0    We trust that you will beable to accept them in principle,    I shall be ready to discuss their application in detail whenever your acceptance inprinciple is commimicated to me,I am,&apos;Yours faithfully,(Sgd..)    D, LLOYD-- GEOLOE.;;lamon de Valera, Eeq,..vThe Mansion House j&quot;DUBLIN.

</content>
</cab>
