<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/26/0 images: 341-357</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
;(TB&quot;tB DOCIMETJT-TS &quot;THE&quot; PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYJS GOVERNMENT V.--m n&apos;&quot;C RET.                                                                                FINAL COPY NO.r- -- &quot;-- - -----CABINET 71 (21)CONCLUSIONS Of a Meeting of the cabinet held in Mr. Chamberlain^s Room, House ofCommons, S.W., on Friday, 19th August,1921, at 4 p.m*P R E S S N Tt-THE PRIME MINISTER    (IN THE CHAIRjThe Rt. Hon i A. Chamberlain j M* P.,-Lord Privy Seal.jJThe Rt.Hon.E. Shortt, K.CjM.P.,Seoretary of State for HomeAffairs*IThe rt hon.W.Si $hurchili^ M.P.,The wt/Hon.* Sir Robert horne,iW3.B.,K;C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer*The Most HoncThe Marquess Curson of kedleston, K. Go ,G.CS* I. jCC I.E*.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.-The rt. hon,,E*So Montagu,.secretary of State for the Colonies. Secretary of State for India.The Rt.Hon.Sir L.Worthlngton-Evan8,Bart. ,Mr, P. , Secretary of State forWar.The Rt.Hon.S. Baldwin, M.P.,President of the Board cf Trade.IThe RUHon. H.A.L. Fisher, M. P.,President of the Board ofEducation..The Rt.Hon.R. Munro, K.C,M.P.,j Secretary for Scotland.The Rt,Hon^Lord Lee of F&apos;areham,G.B.E.,ICCBs, First Lord of the Admiralty.The rt hon.- Sir A. Mond, Bart0 3M.P*,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. T.J. Maonamara,M.P., Minister of Labour*The RtcHonc. Sir Hamar Greenwood., Bart.K.C.,M.P., Chief Secretary for Ireland,THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT:-!the R.T..Hon, The Earl of crawford and Balcarres, K.T., first commissioner of Works.(For Conclusions 4,5 and 6).Sir Arthur Hirtzel, K.C.B.,Deputy Under-Secretary, India^Office, (For Conclusions 8 &amp; 9).The Rt.Hon. F.G, Kellatvay, M.P.,Postmaster-General.(For Conclusions 2 and 3).Sir Edward Grigg, K.C.V.Q.,CM. GoMr. E*R* Barnley, Assistant-Sesretary, Colonial Office.(For Conclusion 2).U^Col. Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B.........................*.Thomas Jones.......................*.Prinalpal assistant secretary.Secretary.
lift315IRELAND.locpensa-tion toSailors andSoldiers *(1) The Chie-f* Secretary raised the question of compensa-tion whioh the Irish Government were pledged to pay inrespect of sailors and soldiers who had suffered loss inIreland.Certain of the Irish Counties, notably Cork andKerry, had run out of the means to pay compensation due.There was, however, a surplus of  700,000 due to otherCounties, which would not be paid while certain other Goun-ties were recalcitrant.In these circumstances the Chief Secretary askedpermission to pay for the soldiers and sailors in Cork and**rry out of the amounts due to other services.The Chief&quot; Secretary was ask^d to raisethe question at the Cabinet Committeeon Ireland.At a subsequent conference betv/een thePrime Minister, the Lord Privy Seal andthe Chisf Secretary for Ireland, it wasagreedThat thp Chief Secretary should be authorisedto apply the sum standing in the Local Texa-tlon Account, Ireland, to the credit ofrecalcitrant local authorities in. paymentof compensation to police, soldiers^ otherloyal persons and/or their dependantsirrespective of the area of local juris-diction from which they co:ve.
V.&amp;) The Cabinet had before them the following documents in regard to the West Indian Passenger Service:-A Memorandum by the Seoretary of Statefor the Colonies (Paper CP.-3083),A Letter *vow the Treasury to the ColonialOffice (Paper C.P.-3083-A).After a short discussion, the Cabinet, while express-ing general agreement in the principle of maintaining aBritish steamship service with the West Indies,  agreed  (a) That, in view of the present financial situation, they could undertake no new commitments of this nature at this time,and that the question must be adjourned until the Autumn, when they would have before them a review of the whole financial situation:(b) That the Secretary of State for.theColonies, in the meanwhile, should consider the desirability of enquiring,as to why the Dutch were able to run asteamship service to the West Indieswithout a subsidy and British.lines were apparently unable to do so-
9 1 nEE IMPERIALJlRELESSSCHEME.(3) With reference to Cabinet S3 (31)., Appendix I (vil(b)), the Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for the Colonies on the subject of theImperial Wireless Scheme, which, the Cabinet were reminded,had been warmly supported by the recent Imperial Conference(Paper CP .-3229)..The proposal of the Secretary of State for the Colon-ies, as Chairman of the Imperial Communications Committee,was that he himself should set up an &quot;Erecting Authority&quot;incorporating the existing Wireless Oomraxssion (t4-e., the experts who have been   engaged in the design and researchexperimental stage), adding to their numbers an independent chairman and. the permanent head of the Crown Agents for theColonies *The Postmaster-General urged that the work would bemore rapidly and economically carried out, in accordancewith the original recommendations of the Norman Committee,by the Post Office, which had wide experience, including theerection of the great station just opened at Leafield.The Cabinet agreed  That the question should be referred to:-The Chancellor of the&apos; Exchequer, -The Secretary of State for the Colonies,&quot;The Postmas ter-General,to advise the Cabinet as to the expenditure involved, keeping in view the importanceof avoiding Supplementary Estimates, and asto the departmental responsibility forcarrying out any work which may be approved.
(4) With reference to Cabinet 55 (.30.)., Conclusion 5, theCabinet had before them a Memorandum by the Earl of crawford and balcarres (Paper CP.--3237), containing the followingproposalsii) That the necessary Bill be drafted to transfer the liquidation of the Wheat - Commission to -theBoard of Trade, as has already been done inrespect of other foodstuffs:(ii) That the Cabinet should undertake to proceedwith the measure without delay on the nextre-assembly of Parliament.While agreeing with the objects of the above proposals,the Cabinet were reluctant to sanction legislation for thepurpose.    They therefore invited the Earl of Crawford andBalcarres to submit the question to the Treasury Solicitorin order to ascertain whether these objects could not benewachieved by means of ay-Royal Warrant or otherwise without legislation.    If the Treasury Solicitor was unable to give an authoritative opinion as to how this could be affected,-the Law Officers of the Crown should be consulted.    Only if no means could be found for accomplishing his object without legislation should the Earl of Crawford and Balcarres bringthe matter back to the Cabinet.
decorated-       (5) With reference to Cabinet 26 (20), Conclusion 4.P THE sI OFFICE, the Cabinet had before them the following documents inregard to the mural decoration of the Foreign Office:-Memoranda by the First Commissioner of Works,VCP.-Papers 650, 1242,  1955,  2630,  3114):Memorandum, by the Secretary of State forForelgn Affair s, (Paper C P.-1221),Note by the Secretary, Cabinet (paper cp.-1346) .After the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs andthe First Commissioner of Works had developed, the points of,view set forth in their respective Memoranda, the cabinet were reminded of their decision of May 10, 1921, that theFirst Commissioner of Works should be authorised to place the whole of Mr Goetze&apos;s panels in the position they were intended to oceuny, so that the Cabinet themselves mightinspect them.    This decision, however, had never beencarried into effect because the artist insisted on thepictures being fixed by a certain gximming process, which wasobjected to by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,who proposed that they should be erected on stretchers.The suggestion was made that the artist&apos;s insistenceexempted th* Cabinet from their previous decision, and aproposal was made (and mat with considerable support) thatthe frescoes should be declined altogether.   The cabinet agreed, however, that this latter course would not be fair to the artist and that their previous decision must be adhered to.By a large majority the Cabinet agreed  That the mural decorations should be hungon stretchers.
R        (.6) With r^fer-eixee-WHo-TOe- A^srl^rs^-Ooinmitieef/cnclu-sion 1, the Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the first commissioner of Works on the subject of the Housing of the-Imperial War Museum (Paper C.P.-32I1).The Cabinet agreed  That the whole question should be referredto a Committee composed as follows:-The First Commissioner of Works (in the Chair),Representatives of the Colonial Office,,India Office,Sir George Barstow (representing the Treasury),and representatives of the following DominionsCanada,Aus tr&amp;lia,New Zealand.The Chairman was asked to convene the Oom-mittee and to msk e all arrangements.6-
TRADE BOARDPOLICY.(7) With reference to Cabinet 59 (21), Conclusion 4 (o.)and Appendix III, the Cabinet had before&apos;.them a Note bythe Minister of Labour in regard to Trade Board Policy(Paper C . P.-5217).The Cabinet agreed  That the Minister cf Labour should beauthorised to make an announcement that the Trade Board Acts need amend-ment and that he is considering the changes that are required, with a viewto legislation when opportunity offers.
(8) With reference to Cabinet 63 (2.1), conclusion.5, the Cabinet had before them a Note circulated by the-^S&quot;&quot;-&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot; -!&apos;:Secretary of State for India covering a number of telegrams between the Secretary of State and theGovernment of India in regard to the present positionof the negotiations with Afghanistan (Paper C,Ps-3249)eThe Secretary of State for India, in summarisingposition, pointed &amp;ut that the suggestion for a &quot;pis  ,aller&quot; Treaty had come from the Afghans and not from usthus eliminating the &quot;humiliation&quot; to which the cabinet had objected, but that the proposed Treaty was not onewhich he could recommend to the Cabinet, nor did the amendments to it suggested by&apos; the Government of Indiamake it acceptable.The Cabinet(a) That during the vacation the Secretaryof State for India,, while doing his best to carry out the policy already approvedby the cabinet a should take stock of thesituation and decide what steps arenecessary.; in consultation with suchMinisters as may be available*(b) That before any action of an importent       fcharacter is taken, the Secretory ofState for India should inform the PrimeMinister, wherever he might be.
t&amp;) With reference to Cabinet 69 (21),Gondlusion 5* the Cabinet had before them a draft note to the Russian Soviet government  circulatedby the Secretary of State for India, in which were set forth numerous breaches of the Russian trade agreement by the Soviet Go-veminent (Paper C0P*S247JoAfter a short discuss  on the Cabinet agreed:-That the draft despatch by the Secretary ofState for India should be utilised as thebasis of a despatch to be prepared by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs and approved by the Prime Minister before beingactually sentt.     The despatch should containinstances of breaches of the Agreement jpress for explanations, and demand that thesebreaches of the Trade Agreement should cease,but should stop short of an actual threat of cancellation of the Trade Agreement,which should&apos;at this stage be held in reserveeRUSSIA.Breaches ofthe trade agreement *-9-
THE INTERHATXOItALUo) With reference to Cabinet 76 (2QK Ccmo-lnslon 1,LABOUR CONFBR-ENGE. Cabinet 59 (21) , Conclusion 4 (a) and Appendix X, theChairman.        Cabinet had before them the following Memoranda on theInstructions   subject of the International Labour conference to british delegates. A Memorandum by the Minister of labour in regard to the Chairman (Paper 0,P.-3220),A Memorandum by the Minister ox&quot; labour in regard to the Appointment of british delegates (Paper 0-P*--3215) (The Cabinet agx*eed --(a) That the British Delegates should beauthorised to agree to the nominationas Chairman of M. Ador, on the under-sta2iding that this should not create a precedent for the appointment of aSwiss Chairman at these Conferences,which In future are to be held atGeneva, and should be tideated merely as a compliment to Switzerland to mark the fact that the forthcoming conference is the first meeting of the InternationalLabour Organisation to be held on Swisssoil:(b) That the Minister of Labour should beauthorised to issue instructions tothe British Delegates based on his memorandum (Paper C*Pr-3215).
OIWli SERVICE       (ll) With reference to War Cabinet 556, Conclusion 6.arbitration board AND ITS the Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the ChancellorRELATION TO &quot;the abolition of the CivilService Arbitration Board, and,with it, of eompulsoryarbitration (Paper copy-5061).It wad suggested, that- consideration of the subjectought to be delayed in view of the appointment of theCommittee on the limitation of expenditure *The Cabinet agreed  -To postpone consideration of thesubject.11
(l2) With reference to &quot;Cabinet 4 (.30), Conclusion 5,&quot;the -Cabinet had before them a Meitwrandum by the Secretaryof State for War vPaper C*Pn-3138) asking that the cabinet decision of January 14, 1$20, should be rescinded and areversion made to peace-time procedure in regard to thedisposal of surplus storediThe Cabinet agreed  ^hat the consideration of this subject should be po tpo*iedi-12-
(l3) With reference to Committee of Home Affairs 93,Cone Insion A, and to Memoranda by the Secretary of State-for War (Paper CP.--3447) and the Chancellor of the Exchequer(Paper CP.-2496) , the Cabinet had before them the recommend-atlon of the Home Affairs Committee on the effect of the WarPensions Act, 1920, upon officers and soldiers serving inIreland and other places where military operations stillcontinue (paner CP.- 3131).The Cabinet endorsed the view of the Home AffairsCommittee that it wonId be right to make an exception fromthe operation of the War Pensions Act, 1920, of casualtiesoccurring in Ireland, subject to re-consideration after sixmonths.-1.3-
&apos;$&amp;S TRAFFICINVENTION *(.14) Witb^re-feretic^-torvaa^ai^ne^ 542, Conclusion 1,Vha-Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the PresidentCf the Board of Education calling attention to the controlof the trade in arms and aniiirunition under the convention which wae signed at St. Germain on September 10, 1919, andashing for &quot;the direction of the Cabinet as to the line theBritish representatives at the League of Nations should talewith respect to the ratification of this Convention (paper cp .-3242).In his Memorandum the President of the Beard of.Edu-catlon pointed out that none of the Principal Allied andAssociated Powers had yet ratified the Convention, and that until they did so no acceptance by the smaller States could have a decisive influence on the arms traffic in the course of the discussion it was explained thatGermany was bound to conform to the Convention under theTreaty of Versailles, and attention was directed to theimportance of providing against a situation arising in which,while we should be debarred, for example, from supplying arms to the Greeks or Turks, the Soviet Government would stillbe free to do so*The Cabinet agreed -(a) To authorise tho British representatives at the League of Nations to state thatHis Majesty&apos;s Government would proceedto ratification as soon as the otherPrincipal Allied and Associated Powers,are prepared to ratify, subject to safe--guards being provided against the Gonven-tion being rendered nugatory by non-signatories, such as, for example, theSoviet Government:(b) That the subject should be raised by theBritish Government with the AmericanGovernment at the approaching Conferenceat Washington.
PROTECTION OP       115) With..,;^^ (.21), Appendix VTTtla)EXPLOSIVES &apos; &apos;pD MUNITION&quot;&apos; fcly^-JSjabxne-t.-had hefoi-e thorn a Meiroa^Tdujrc^^y^he Secretary^ fWPOTS.State &apos;or women Affairs (Paper CP.-3110) and a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for War (Paper CP.-3189) dealing with&amp; recommendation from, the Protection Sub-Committee of theSupply and Transport Committee that a small section of theDefence Force should be retained or revived for the protec-tion of explosives and munitions depots.   It was contendedin the Report of the Protection Sub--Committee that protectionwas required primarily as a military measure to prevent thesupply of munitions to the rebel forces in Ireland, and more effective protection could be given in this way at a lesscost than by any attempt to emplojr paid Special Constables....- .There was general agreement that the matter was oneof some urgency, and that definite responsibility for theprotection of the stores should be undertaken.The Cabinet agreed  That the whole matter should be consideredafresh by the following CommitteeThe Secretary of State for Home Affairs(in the Chair),The Secretary of State for War,The Secretary for Scotland,Sir Ceorge Barstow (Treasury),Mr T. St,C Hill (Secretary),with power to take a decision.
OlfflWPItOyMEMT.       (16) With reference to Cabinet 68 (21), Conclusion 6,the Cabinet bad before them the 25th and 26th Conclusionsof the Committee on Unemployment, together with the Reportof the Committee (Paper CP.-5250).The Cabinet were reminded by the Minister of labour of the increasing gravity of the problem of unemployment, &apos;owjng to the exhaustion of Unemployment Benefit.    It was estimated that, by the end of October between 4 00,000 and500,000 persons would be out of benefit, and large numbersOf these were crowded in relatively few centres, such as,:Glasgow, Dundee, Belfast, Middlesbrough, Sheffield andRotherham.   He strongly disliked having to refer ax-Servicemen to the Poor Law Authorities, but could see no alternativeat present.Attention was drawn to the special difficulties which prevailed in Scotland owing to the stricter administrationof Out-door Relief there.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve the recommendation of theUnemployment Committee, namely, that,in the event of an emergency arising,the Ministry of Health, in consultationwith the Treasury and Ministry of Labour,should be authorised to take such measures as might be necessary to enable the Poor Lav?Guardians concerned to secure loans:(b) That the Secretary for Scotland should examine the Poor Law administration inScotland with a view to seeing that theunemployed seeking Poor Law Relief were&apos;not ph ced in-a less favourable position thansimilar persons in England.2, &quot;Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,August 19, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
