<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/238/0 images: 13-19</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S E C R E T.G.P.  54(53).                                  COPY NO.     frt?                     0 A B I IT E To               ECONOMIC ADVISORY COUNCIL.            COin-IITTTilr! 01: ECONOMIC  l.:::/CKA.TION,           Financial Policy and Trade Activity.                  The attached letter  to  the  Prime minister from the Committee  021 Economic Information of the economic advisory Council? submitting their views  on Financial Policyand Trade Activity? is circulated  for  the  information of theCabinet on the instructions of the Prime Minister.                            (Signed)  LI,  P.  A.  HAHKEY?                                     secretary, Cabinet,,rhitehall Gardens?  S.Y/V1.15th February?  1933.
Printed for the Economic Advisory Council.  February 1933.SECRET.                                      Copy No. 2fjE.A.C. (S.O.) 6.              TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken to     ensure the secrecy of this document.ECONOMIC   ADVISORY  COUNCIL.COMMITTEE ON ECONOMIC  INFORMATION.Financial Policy, February  1933.LETTER TO  THE  PRIME  MINISTER.2, Whitehall Gardens, S. W. I,   February 9, 1933.(8199)
COMMITTEE  ON  ECONOMIC INFORMATION.                  COMPOSITION.Sir Josiah Stamp, G.B.E., Chairman.Mr. W. M.  Citrine.Mr. G.  D.  H. Cole.Mr. J. M.  Keynes, C.B.Sir Alfred Lewis, K.B.E.Sir Arthur  Salter, K.C.B.Sir Ernest Simon.    Mr. H. D. Henderson, Joint  Secretary,        Economic Advisory Council    Mr.  Francis Hemming,  C.B.E.,  Joint        Secretary,    Economic   Advisory        council I  Joint  secretariesI  to the  committee.
uFINANCIAL  POLICY, FEBRUARY 1933.                                         2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,Dear Prime Minister,                                     February 9, 1933.     MY Committee desire to elaborate in the form of a letter to you the viewson trade activity and financial policy which we expressed in section  III of ourfifth report.  We do so because we are unanimous in attaching great importanceto the question at the present juncture.   Whatever  differences  there  may be between us in our views on the wisdom of the policy that was pursued in regardto such matters as public works in the years preceding the financial crisis, or thecanons which should govern  policy in  regard to national and  local expenditurein normal circumstances, we  are united in holding strongly that in the circum-stances which exist to-day there is an overwhelming case and an urgent need fora modification  of our present financial policy in the directions which we have indicated in  our fifth report.  In order to  bring out clearly the  considerations which carry  decisive weight in our minds  in regard to this issue, we think itdesirable to distinguish the present phase of the problem from other phases, eventhough this means dealing with matters upon which there are certain differences of opinion among  ourselves.     2.  The  period from the stabilization of European currencies in  the middletwenties until the beginning of the depression in 1929 was a period of good world trade.   The period represented, that is to say, the upward phase of the ordinarycycle of  fluctuations of business  activity; and the heavy unemployment which existed  in Great  Britain  during  those years was  not attributable  to trade depression in the ordinary sense, but to special national difficulties. The essence of these difficulties was the loss of overseas markets by many exporting industries,arising from a  variety of causes,  including  the return  to the gold standard  at aparity which  left British  costs of  production unduly high  for   successfulcompetition in  world markets.     3.  The  beginning of  the world  depression  in  1929 coincided  with anintensified effort to  stimulate schemes of public work.  If the depression  hadbeen a comparatively mild one hi  the outside world, it is possible that the publicworks might  have played an important part in diminishing the force of its impact on  Great  Britain, and  possibly  in promoting an  early recovery.   But thedepression was in fact far*too severe to be held in check by such means;  forces ofcumulative deterioration were  soon  established which were bound to run their course before recovery  was possible; and, so long as they were in operation, theundertaking  of public works, though serving to diminish for the time being thenumbers of the unemployed, was necessarily impotent to reverse the  trend oftrade.   On the other hand, it contributed something to weaken  the position ofGreat Britain  at two vulnerable  points, those, namely, of the  soundness of thepublic finances and of the balance of trade, and may thus have impaired our powerto sustain  the ensuing financial crisis.     4.  However this may be, when the financial crisis occurred in the summer of 1931,  it became, in  the opinion of most of us, imperative to pursue a policywhich made  the restoration of financial confidence the paramount consideration.It is never easy to assess the reality of a danger that has been averted;  and we donot,  therefore, attempt to discuss  whether anything in the nature of a debacle of sterling would  have been a serious possibility, if a different financial  policy hadbeen pursued.   It is sufficient to say that an  essential pre-requisite of the recovery of trade from the  depths of a depression is always the establishment ofa low level of  short-term  money rates and long-term  interest rates;  and  this objective  could not  have been secured unless both  the  world of  internationalfinance and the home investing public had been reassured as to the determination of the British Government to put its own financial house in order.     5.  It is, however, one of the dangers of a reorientation of financial policy,whether in the  direction of increased expenditure or of economy, that the policy      [8199]                                                     B 2
is. apt to be continued, and indeed in its actual application to gain an increasingmomentum, after the circumstances which rendered it appropriate  have passedaway. That in our judgment is the present position.     6.  The change that has  taken place in  the past eighteen months in theeconomic  circumstances that are relevant to financial policy is so radical as to amount   to  a  complete   transformation.    Financial  confidence  has  been-established, and the credit  of the British Government stands higher to-daythan that of any other Government.  By the conversion scheme of last summer,Great Britain has  taken the lead in the movement towards lower interest ratesthroughout the world.   A very large improvement has been effected in the figuresof the balance of trade; and beneath the vicissitudes connected with such factors as the American debt situation, sterling has developed an underlying strength which seems likely to continue and may even prove embarrassing.  The competitive position  of our  industries in world markets has been greatly improved by thelower value of the  pound.   Thus those arguments for economy which rested on special weaknesses of  our  national position have now entirely lost their force.Great Britain is once more in the unquestioned position of a strong financialcountry.     7.  But that is not all.  We have now reached a phase of the world depressionwhen the underlying  economic conditions, which  until  recent months wereadverse, may be helpful to  the possibility of gradual recovery.  The  decline in consumption is no longer tending in general to outstrip the decline in production.The  business world  is  no  longer dominated  by  the  fear  of  impendingcatastrophes  which must exert far-reaching repercussions.    Tn  Great Britain,there are already signs that the ease  of money and lower interest rates  are beginning to stimulate certain classes of constructional activity.     8.  Now, therefore, is  the time when, in accordance with  the traditionalprecepts  of trade cycle theory,  it would be most  useful to apply  the stimulus of increased development activity by  public authorities.  For, while in the earlyphases of depression a moderate expenditure on public works may prove anessentially futile resistance  to the  strength  of  the  forces  of  deterioration,  acomparatively modest  expenditure, representing a net addition  to  the  demandfor goods and services, may suffice at such a juncture as the present to enablethe fcrdes of recuperation to gain the upper hand.     9.  Yet it is precisely  at this juncture that the economy policy  is operatingat its maximum effect.  In the national budget  we  are attempting to  defrayout of current revenue various types of expenditure which  were previously met by borrowing.  The policy  of  discouraging  the  development activities of localauthorities naturally produces  an increasing effect for a considerable time, sinceold schemes are gradually completed and new schemes are not commenced.  Thecapital expenditure of local authorities is thus undergoing a  continuous reductionbig enough to be a material factor in  the  general state  of trade.  Indeed, webelieve that it will be found upon detailed and specific inquiry that in the declinein the aggregate volume of  bank advances in the past year the repayment of advances  by  local  and  other  public  authorities  is  the  most  conspicuouscategory.   The  operation   of sinking  funds  for   past   loans  on  the  onehand, coupled  with  the  diminution of  fresh  borrowing  on   the  other,is producing a  state of  affairs where  at  the  bottom  of  the  depressionthe   net   indebtedness  of  local   authorities  is   in   some  areas  actuallyfalling.    A further reduction  in the expenditure of  local  authorities must  beexpected as a consequence of the new housing policy set out in the Housing Bill.We offer no opinion on the merits of this policy, but  it is important to bear inmind that the expenditure of local authorities on  housing during the  nextyear or more will almost certainly show a big  reduction on  the figures of recentyears.     10.    So far, therefore, from supplying a positive stimulus to trade recovery,the effect  of the present policy in regard to national and  local expenditure is tocontribute a definitely adverse influence to the trade situation.  Indeed, the main reason for doubting whether the present year will witness an important forwardtrade movement in Great Britain is the possibility that the  diminished  volumeof activity by  public  authorities may counterbalance the  effects  of increased-constructional activity in other fields.  At the critical  phase of the trade depres-
                                     asion which we have now reached this is an extremely unfortunate state of things;and there is a strong case for a modification of policy which would permit a largervolume of capital expenditure by public authorities.    11.  Moreover, in  the circumstances which exist  to-day a  considerable expansion of  development  activity might  be permitted,  we  believe,  withoutentailing any net addition, indeed with some actual relief, to budgetary  burdens.The  cost  of  maintaining  unemployment   represents,  it must  always  beremembered, a heavy charge upon  public  funds.  The undertaking  of any workwhich absorbs  in  employment workers who;  would  otherwise   have drawnunemployment pay or poor relief entails,  therefore, a saving of public expendi-ture under these headings; while  the public finances  further benefit  in  suchindirect ways as the income-tax collected on the profits of the contractors and thecustoms or excise  on the dutiable  commodities purchased by the workers fromtheir  wages.  Such gains are much larger than is generally appreciated, and in times like the present, when there is an abundant supply of capital  available for investment, so that no possibility exists that the public work may divert capitalfrom  industrial  use, we believe that  these gains suffice to outweigh any directcharge upon public funds except in the case of work the greater part of whichmust  be borne by  Exchequer  subsidies.   But much  development work  is beingdisallowed or  discouraged at  the present time in regard to which there is noquestion  of  any subsidy  from the  Exchequer; and  in  such cases  the  national finances would undoubtedly benefit if the work were to be  put in  hand.  It isimportant to appreciate vividly that  whenever a local authority is discouragedfrom  applying for loan sanction for a scheme for which it asks for no exchequer subsidy, a substantial burden  in the forms of increased expenditure and loss ofrevenue equivalent to not less than one-quarter, and perhaps to one-half, of thecost of the scheme in question is thereby imposed upon the national finances.    12.  It was in the light of these  considerations  that we urged  in our FifthReport that  &apos;&apos; a point has now been reached when it is undesirable to discourage,on general financial- grounds,  local  authorities whose financial security  is not inquestion  from undertaking work  which they themselves desire  to undertakewithout any subsidy from the  Exchequer.&quot; It is  impossible  to estimate with anyprecision the amount of work which is now held in abeyance, but which might beput in hand  if this principle were acted on.  But we think it well to observe thatthe extent of the work in question cannot  be gauged by a reference to the figuresof the actual applications  for loan  sanction  that have been  refused, for theimpression prevails widely that it is contrary to the policy of the Government tocountenance schemes of capital expenditure at the present time for which no plea.of special urgency can be advanced, and this impression deters local authorities from  bringing their projects to the stage of a formal application.    13.  In the case of works the cost of which must be defrayed wholly orlargely by the Exchequer, the most urgent need is  a modification  of the rigidembargo on borrowing which,  we understand,  prevails to-day.   We  urged in ourFifth Report that &quot; it is undesirable under present conditions to seek to hold upthe completion of  public works on  which a large  amount of money has alreadybeen  spent,  and the ultimate  completion of  which  is  clearly  desirable.&quot;   an obvious example of work of this character is furnished by some  of the unfinishedby-passes  round  congested urban areas.  No one  questions that they should one day be completed.  The difficulty in completing them is that under  the financialrules  which obtain the cost of their completion must be defrayed from the annualrevenue of the Road Fund, which has no margin to spare, or else from the revenueraised by national taxation.   The  obvious objections to any further increase oftaxation  at  the  present time are  so cogent that this  limitation  constitutes  a powerful obstacle to  the completion of even the most urgently needed by-passes.Thus  the present arrangements entail the  paradox that the  completion  ofthoroughly desirable public work  has  to wait on an  easing  of the budgetaryposition, which means  in effect waiting on a recovery  of  trade, although it isprecisely when trade is at its worst that it would be most advantageous to under-take it. It is for this reason that we urged  in our fifth report &quot; that arrangements should be made to permit borrowing for purposes of a capital character so thaturgently  needed  work which would be helpful to  the industrial situation shouldnot be postponed merely on account of budgetary exigencies.&quot;
    14.  We desire to make it clear that the views we  have expressed  can beaccepted without prejudice to  the  question of the considerations which  should govern long-term policy in regard to national and local expenditure.  We do not discuss how far the lower birthrate, which is the outstanding social phenomenonof the present century, may make it desirable to pursue a more cautious financial policy in certain respects than was customary in the past.   But considerations ofthis character do not weaken the force of our  present argument.  Our essentialcontention is that, just as the  restoration of financial confidence  was made thegoverning  consideration  in our  financial policy  eighteen months  ago,  therestoration of trade activity should be made the governing consideration at thepresent time.  If this principle is accepted, we are satisfied that it can be applied in ways  which  will neither endanger  the renewed confidence in  the financial stability of the country, nor conflict with the requirements of a far-sighted policy for the future.  Finally,  we cannot too strongly press our view as to  the gravity of proceeding on the present lines without modification.                                  Yours faithfully.                                      (Signed on behalf of the Committee) :                                           J. C. STAMP. Chairman.Rt. Hon. J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.

</content>
</cab>
