<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/238/0 images: 165-165</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  February 1933.SECRET.CP.  40  (33).CABINET.THE FUTURE RESPONSIBILITIES  FOR ADEN.            MEMORANDUM BY THE  SECRETARY OF  STATE FOR AIR.    THE Secretary of State for India, in his Memorandum CP. 37 (33), askshis colleagues to say whether, in their opinion,  the balance of advantage rests with the separation of Aden from India. He warns them that if Aden is brought under the new Federation, there is a possibility if not a probability that theGovernment of India will at some future date insist on  resuming military control.    There can be no two opinions as to the strategical importance of Aden as a vital link in our Empire communications.  The findings of the  Committee ofImperial Defence  in 1923, referred to by the Secretary of State for  India inparagraph 12 of his Memorandum, makes this abundantly clear.  India&apos;s interestsin Aden  are essentially commercial and sentimental,  and although I do  not inany way belittle these interests, they are in  no way  commensurate with thoseof Great Britain, to whom the security of Empire communications  is vital.    The  Secretary of State for India  invites us to face the  fact  that  the separation of Aden from India will entail the loss of  Indian financial contribu-tion towards the political  and military services in Aden.  I agree  that this maybe inevitable, but even the loss of the entire contribution of  150.000 per annum.can bear no relationship to the magnitude of the issues involved  by the loss ofGreat Britain&apos;s responsibilities for  the defence of  Aden.    I have, therefore,  no difficulty or hesitation in giving my answers  to  thequestions  propounded in  paragraph 17 of the Secretary of State for India&apos;s paper, which are as follows :     (a) It is essential on grounds of Imperial strategy to retain the defence of          Aden as a responsibility of the  Imperial Government.    (b) I  agree that if the loss of any contribution  by  India  is an inevitable          consequence of the separation of Aden,  then there is  no alternative          but to accept it.                                                                      L.Air Ministry, February 18, 1933.Copy  No.  42[8244]

</content>
</cab>
