<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/213/20 images: 168-174</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTC(81) 45 COPY NO11 September 1981CABINETCASH FACTORS FOR PUBLIC EXPENDITURE SURVEYMemorandum by the Chancellor of the ExchequerTHE STARTING POINT1. On 7 May (CC(81) 18th Conclusions, Minute 5) we agreed that, in order toconduct the survey in cash, we should adopt the provisional working assumptionthat all costs would rise on average by 7 per cent between 1981-82 and 1982-83,and by 6 per cent and 5 per cent in the two following years.2. It is now necessary to review that provisional decision and to settle thefactors to be used as the framework for our decisions on programmes. Weneed to know what to assume for average costs, both to have a firm baselineagainst which to consider possible increases and decreases in programmes,and also so that the Ministers concerned can review the prospective costs intheir field and reconsider their bids for extra provision and proposals forreduced provision.3. The cost assumptions will also be the basis for the Rate Support Grant(RSG) settlement.     The sooner we can settle these assumptions and let them beknown, the better our chances of influencing local authority budgets and ratesfor next year, and of influencing public sector pay settlements, particularly thecritical negotiation with the local authority manuals.ROLE OF THE FACTORS4. These factors will determine the &quot;baseline&quot; for our public expendituredecisions:  the cash equivalent of the last White Paper.    Apart from changeswhich we will make on policy grounds, it will be possible to add or subtract acash sum in the case of any particular programme if we decide that isnecessary to make provision for that programme on a basis that differssignificantly from what would be implied by these general factors. Butdecisions on any such adjustments can be left until October, when we considerthe cash provision for particular programmes.    We can also leave until thenthe different questions of whether it would be right or feasible to make any cashaddition to any particular programme to make good next year a squeeze thisyear because pay or price increases on that programme have significantlyexceeded the cash limit factors.1CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL5. In general the cash provision for programmes decided this autumn willdetermine the corresponding cash limits and Estimates for 1982-83. Inexceptional cases, the autumn decision may have to be reopened - anyadditional cash having to be found within the Contingency Reserve. Thisprocedure may be necessary to honour the Government&apos;s pledge to the CivilService unions.THE PROPOSAL6. I propose that we should now replace the single provisional factor of7 per cent average cost increase between this year and next, by:-i. a factor of 4 per cent for earnings (from due settlement datesfrom now on); andii. a factor of 9 per cent (financial year on financial year) for othercosts.    (This would apply from uprating dates for social securitybenefits. )This change would have virtually no net effect on the cash equivalent of thetotal expenditure in the last White Paper, but it would produce a morerealistic allocation between programmes as a starting point for our discus-sions.    I see no need at present to change the assumptions for inflation after1982-83.TWO FACTORS FOR 1982-837. It is now clear that we need to have two factors, rather than one, forthe change to 1982-83, as we had for the change to this year.     Once again thereneeds to be a large gap - 5 percentage points or so - between what oughtrealistically to be provided for public sector cost increases other than pay andwhat is appropriate for increases in earnings, as I explain below.8. With such a wide disparity, the use of a single cost increase factorwould give rise to awkward distortions between programmes, in a directioncontrary to our priorities, with over-provision for programmes with a largeelement of public service manpower.    And there would be a danger that thecontinued use of a single figure, which would be significantly higher than whatwe can afford to pay, would set a damaging point of reference for unions in paynegotiations.PRICES9* At Budget time, an increase in retail prices of 8 per cent between thesecond quarters of 1981 and 1982 was forecast, implying a similar increasebetween the averages for the two financial years 1981-82 and 1982-83.Inflation prospects for the year ahead now look somewhat less favourable,because of the fall in the exchange rate, because oil prices in real terms are2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALhigher, and becauce the prcspects for reductions- in domestic interest rates(which affect the Retail Price Index (RPI) through the mortgage rate) haveworsened as a result of the sharp increase in foreign rates.    The present out-side forecasts for the increase in the RPI from Q4 1981 to Q4 1982 vary between8 per cent (London Business School) and 12 per cent (St James/Item). TheTreasury internal forecasts for the RPI are at present at the middle of thatrange, about 10 per cent.    The latest signs are that there is still very-considerable downward pressure on price increases.    Some outside fore-casters may have overreacted a month or two ago to the changes in theexchange rate.10. Such indications as there are for likely relative price movements pointto the average price increases for Government spending on procurementgenerally, and particularly on construction work, being somewhat below theRPI increase.     This will partly offset a more rapid increase in constructioncosts in the recent past.11. We have to strike a balance in fixing the price factor in relation to theseforecasts.12. It must be reasonably realistic.    It is no good using now a deliberatelylow figure for the uprating of social security benefits.    We may decide to abatesome of the upratings in November 1982;  but the underlying basis will be theGovernment&apos;s forecast next spring of the RPI change, so we only risk deludingourselves in the meantime about the cash cost.    For those programmes whichwill be cash-limited, it is right to take a figure likely to be, if anything,slightly on the low side in order to ensure tight budgeting in GovernmentDepartments and in other public sector institutions, as a stimulus toefficiency and to holding down, where it is possible, the prices which they pay.But we should not go beyond that, reducing the factor in order to cut thoseprogrammes significantly:  that should be done, if we so decide, by an overtsqueeze.13. We must also allow for the fact that the Government&apos;s forecast, and theassumptions which we ourselves use in framing our plans, inevitably have someeffect on pay negotiators and price setters.     Our efforts to reduce inflationdepend on creating the right climate for expectations14. Balancing these considerations, I propose that the price factor should be9 per cent.PAY15. The temptation on pay is to defer a decision.    But we need someworking assumption so that we can look at expenditure commitments realis-tically.    We cannot afford to give the impression that we are simply waiting tosee what pay settlements emerge and will then validate them.    And the time-table for the RSG settlement - together with the need for local authorities toknow where they stand when negotiating with their manuals later this year -forces us to an early decision.3CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL16. We must seek, and create expectations of, lower wage settlements inthe coming round than in the last, and this points to a figure below the 6 porcent we chose for cash limits in 1981-82.    Indeed, it should be &quot;in low singlefigures&quot;.17. Any figure on this basis will point to a further fall in the real livingstandards of those in the public services, even allowing for some settlementsbeing above the figure.    Such a fall for wages generally is essential if we areto make worthwhile headway in restoring competitiveness-    But we do not wantto inflame the unions by announcing factors which significantly overstate theexpected fall.18. It would be imprudent to take a figure, as the basis of our currentfinancial planning, significantly belo,v what we think can be achieved.    To theextent that the eventual outcome is higher than we allow for either in thisfactor, or by any specific adjustment to the cash for the programmes(paragraph 4 above), there will either have to be a squeeze on the programmesconcerned, or to the extent that additional cash is provided by an allocationfrom the Contingency Reserve, a squeeze on programmes generally.19. I propose 4 per cent, which is, just, a &quot;low single figure&quot;.    As in thep^st, it will apply to earnings (which includes the effect of overtime etc as wellas settlements) and from due settlement dates from now on.20. The increase in total earnings will of course be less than 4 per centwhere, as in the Civil Service, reductions in numbers have already been builtinto the plans.21. In handling publicity, we should emphasise that this is a cashexpenditure planning assumption.    It does not, and is not designed to, forceparticular pay settlements to tnis precise figure.    It does, however, indicatethe broad measure of what the Government thinks reasonable to allow in itspublic expenditure plans and, where settlements in the event depart at allsignificantly from it, there will be necessary consequences - both ways - Inpublic sector services and employment prospects.PUBLICATION22. The figures we choose now will need to be widely known in Governmentquickly and would be bound to leak.    It will be better to announce them with thequalifications we want to get across.23. I attach a draft statement which I propose should be made by Pressnotice immediately following our decision.    It will be necessary for defensivebriefing to be ready on the implications for various public sector pay groups,and officials are preparing this.4CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALCONCLUSION24.       I invite colleagues to agree that:-i. The provisional inflation factors we chose in May should remainunaltered for inflation after 1982-83, but for inflation between 1981-82and 1982-83 we should replace the working assumption of 7 per cent forall costs by two factors:  4 per cent far pay generally, applied tosettlement dates, and 9 per cent for prices generally, applied year onyear.ii. We should announce these factors by Press nctice, as in theattached draft.iii. We should defer until October, wnen we come to considerindividual programmes, consideration of any cash increases orreductions in programmes in respect of pay and prices, where thereare strong grounds for allowing exceptionally for pay and pricemovements differing significantly from the general factors.G HTreasury Chan bers10 September 19815CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALANNEXDRAFT PRESS NOTICEFUBLIC EXPENDITURE PLANNING:     CASH FACTORS1. The Chancellor of the Exchequer announced in. his Budgetstatement on 10 March 1981 that the Public Expenditure Surveythis year would,   for the first time,  be conducted in terms ofprospective cash expenditure,   rather than in terms of &quot;constantprices&quot;.     For this reason,   the plans in the  last Public ExpenditureWhite Paper (Cmnd 8175)  were,  at the outset of the Survey,put onto a prospective cash basis, which included an allowancefor cost  increases between now and future years.2. In the spring a provisional allowance was made for generalincreases in costs of 7 per cent between  1981-82 and 1982-83and of 6 per cent and 5 per cent respectively for the followingtwo years.3. In now preparing for the man&quot;n decisions on the cash totalsfor each programme,   the Government has reviewed the provisionalallowance far 1982-83 and has decided to use separate factorsfor pay and for other cost increases.    These factors will be,for earnings,  an  increase of 4 per cent from due settlementdates in the coning year, and for other costs an  increase of9 per cent between this financial year (1981-82)  and next (1902-83).    This change has little net effect on the overall cash totalof public expenditure,   but it does affect the distributionbetween programmes.4       The pay factor does not imply that all public service payincreases will  or should be 4  per cent.    Some may be less, andsome may be more.    There  is no automatic entitlement to anyParticular pay increase:    each must be justified on  its merits.The pay factor is a broad measure of what the Government thinksreasonable as a general allowance for increases in pay, at
CONFIDENTIALthis stage of fixing the programme from which the public servicewage bill has to be met.5. The cash expenditure figures arrived at by.applyingthese pay and price factors only determine the framework inwhich the final Ministerial discussions will be taken. Eventualcash provisions for individual  programmes,  and where appropriatecash  limits for next year,  will follow from the decisionsMinisters subsequently take.6. The Rate Support Grant paid to the  local authorities for1982-83 will be determined by Ministers&apos;  decisions on the cashprovision for local authority services,  to be taken within theframework of the plans revalued using these factors of4 per cent for pay increases and 9 per cent for increases inother costs.

</content>
</cab>
