<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/16/15 images: 122-125</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT. )jffQ!OST SECRETJPHE BALKANSiMr BasesTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY,Ji is requested that special care may betaken toensure the secrecy of.this document,COPY No.W.M. (40) Sloth. CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 2.Confidential Annex.(27th December, 1940, 12 Noon.)THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF said that he under-stood from the Air Officer Commanding in Greece thatthe Greeks raised some objections to our preparingaerodromes in Northern Greece.   They were afraid thatstich action might provoke Germany.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS saidthat Sir M. Palairet had reported a similar attitude.In telegram 1419, however, Sir M. Palairet said that he understood from Admiral Turle that the policy of H.M.Government was to establish themselves strongly in theNorthern Aegean, and in particular to establish air bases at Mitylene and Lemnos .   Sir M. Palairet saidthat he proposed to put this policy to the President ofthe Council.THE PRIME MINISTER said that we had no wish toCraw Germany down on Greece, although German interven-tion in the Balkans was to be anticipated in the longrun.   He thought, however, that we should proceed withthe construction of aerodromes south of the lineOlympus-Aerta.   There could, of course, be no questionof our bombing the Roumanian oilfields from Greekaerodromes without first having obtained the permission of the Greek Government.The Prime Minister said that the constructionof aerodromes in Turkey was also of importance.   If thepresence of Officers in uniform at these aerodromespresented difficulty, reconnaissance and supervisionshould be carried out by men in civilian clothing,.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN&apos;affairs undertook to concert with the jftppqiiao .ftfani rtpj* a telegram to Sir M. Palairet on the action to be taken in regardto the preparation of aerodromes in Northern Greece.-IIpeat Qsmge Street, S .W.1,




</content>
</cab>
