<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/41/16 images: 122-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s government secret .P. (43) 416(Also COS. (43) 264)23rd September, 1943WAR cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 212)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 16th September, to0700 23rd September,1943[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Copy NoCabinet War Room.
NAVAL SITUATION.General Review.1. Allied naval forces have carried out intensive bombardments in the gulf of Salerno.HALS. Warspite has been seriously damaged.Troops and supplies have been carried in Allied ships to Corsica and islands in the Dodecanese.ELM. submarines and Allied destroyers have made successful attacks on shipping in the ^-aegean.A concentration of U-boats has attacked a North Atlantic convoy and casualties have been sustained by the convoy and escorts.Home Waters.2. On the night of the 1.9th/20th, M.T.B. 017 torpedoed a large ship offIjmuiden. On the same night three M.G.Bs. attacked trawlers in the same localityand damaged two. One M.G.B. was damaged and two of the crew were killed.Three S.G.Bs. attacked a force of about seven ships north-east of Havre on the night of the 21st 22nd.West Atlantic.3. During the U-boat attacks on an outward-bound convoy in the N.W.Approaches, H.M.C.S. St. Croix (destroyer), HALS. Polyanthus (corvette) andHAI.C.S. Itchen (frigate) were sunk and HALS. Lagan (frigate) was torpedoed.Five officers and 76 ratings were rescued from St. Croix but there was only onesurvivor from Polyanthus. HALS. Escapade (destroyer) and F1.M.C.S. Gatineau(destroyer) were damaged by the premature explosion of anti-submarineequipment. Three officers and 12 ratings were killed and there is one ratingmissing in Escapade.Mediterranean.4. Throughout the crucial period on the Salerno sector. Allied warshipscontinued to give gun support on a large scale, often standing close inshore andsilencing enemy batteries and positions several miles inland.On the 16th H.M. ships Warspite and Valiant bombarded the Salerno area and on the following clay the U.S.S. Philadelphia and a U.S. destroyer carriedout further inshore bombardments. HALS. Warspite was hit twice by gliderbombs and near missed by two others. Four of her boiler rooms were flooded andall her engine rooms were put out of action. She was taken in tow by four tugsand reached Malta on the 19th. HALS. Cleveland (destroyer) in company withWarspite was damaged by near misses.Supply of the Fifth Army continues through the Salerno beaches. Cotroneand Taranto are handling supplies for the Eighth Army.During the week destroyer patrols have been carried out in the Strait ofOtranto and U.S. M.T.B.s have patrolled the Tyrrhenian Sea.On the 14th the port of Brindisi was opened. It is in full working orderthough there is a shortage of labour. Two small floating docks and all workshopswere found intact,On the 15th the islands of Procicla and Poriza, in the Bay of Naples, wereoccupied by Allied forces and on the following clay Ischia surrendered.The Duke of Aosta arrived at Augusta on the 20th in the yacht Zagabri.5. Allied forces in Corsica have been considerably reinforced during theweek. Troops and stores have been landed at Ajaccio by two Italian destroyers,two French destroyers and the French cruiser Jeanne IT Arc. Over 2,500personnel and 300 tons of stores have now been landed. The Polish S/M. Dziksank two ships outside Bastia harbour on the 21st, The remaining three ships in the harbour were reported on fire.6. The R.F.A. Demventdale was damaged by bombs on the 14th and wastowed to Malta. The Italian hospital ship Toscana was attacked by german aircraft south of Cotrone.7. On the night of the 17th/18th K.M. destroyers Faulknor and Eclipsewith the Greek destroyer Queen Olga sank two ships (one of them a 3,000-tontanker) and probably sank an escort ship in convoy to Rhodes.   On the same nigh&apos;
a raiding party made a successful landing on Stampalia from a caique. TheItalian naval base at Leros and the neighbouring island of Kos, in the Dodecanese,are now known to have been occupied by Allied&quot; forces which were transported byH.M.S. Sutlej (sloop), the Greek destroyer Paul Coundouriotis, two French sloopsand aircraft. H.M. destroyers have carried over 2,000 personnel and a Targequantity of stores to Leros. A fuelling base for coastal craft is being established at Paphos, and the forces at Kos, Leros ancl Santos are to be reinforced by aircraft, caiques and motor launches.A cargo ship and an L.C.T. escorted by motor launches have unloaded atIvastelorizo.   Our shipping is operating freely between these islands.The following reports have been received from HAL submarines operating inthe iEgean : On the 31st August Trooper bombarded Karlovassi (Samos) ancl onthe following day she sank a northbound schooner and a tug in the SkopelosChannel. Torbay sank a caique on the 31st, and on the 2nd September she sank a 1,000-ton ship in convoy west of Leros. Rorqual laid mines off the east coast of greece and on the 12th she shelled the Stratoni iron works near Salonika.8. A number of Italian warships and small craft are now known to havebeen scuttled since the Armistice. These include: At Spezia, the cruiserTaranto, a destroyer, a T.B., a minelayer and an escort ship. The 8&quot; cruiserGorizia appeared to be damaged by fire. At Castellamare, a light cruiser, fourescort ships, five small craft and possibly a U-boat. At Naples, one T.B. and anumber of small craft. At Pozzuoli, a U-boat on fire and partly submerged. Inaddition at least 15 cargo ships have been scuttled. The Germans claim that a formation of their T.B&apos;s., operating in the Adriatic, have seized the new Italiantransport Leopard! (4,000 tons) and three other ships with troops on board and sent them into a German-occupied port.On the 20th. eight Italian small craft reached Malta from Palermo: 31others are on the way.Survivors from the battleship Roma report that the ship was attacked seventimes by Ju. 88&apos;s loaded with 2,000-kg. rocket-propelled bombs.Black Sea.9. During the week ending the 9th September, Russian aircraft sank twoR-boats ancl one lighter ancl damaged three R-boats and one barge in theSea of Azov. North-west of Anapa they set five barges on fire ancl killed 400troops.   At Yalta they sank two R-boats, two barges and one tug.South Atlantic.10. The Italian 1,460-ton submarine Ammiraglio Cagni entered Durban onthe 20th and surrendered to the Fortress Commander.Pacific.11.   The Japanese main fleet is believed to be concentrated at Truk.No naval movements to interfere with Allied operations in New Guinea andthe Solomons have been reported. Allied light forces have destroyed enemybarges off the north and north-west coasts of Veil a Lavella and in the Finschhafenarea.Photographic reconnaissance of Rabaul on the 20th showed one heavy cruiser,one light cruiser, nine destroyers, five U-boats, a gunboat, four submarinechasers, a destroyer tender, a U-boat tender and 21 cargo ships totalling 86,000tons.Anti-Submarine Operations.12. Fourteen attacks on U-boats have been reported during the week; sevenby aircraft and seven by surface craft.HALS. Keppel (destroyer), escorting an outward bound convoy, rammed andHank- a U-boat south-south-west of Iceland (C) on the 22nd. A Liberator (B. 24)possibly sank a U-boat south of Iceland (C) on the 19th. Escorting the sameconvoy H.M. ships Keppel, Itchen (frigate) and Narcissus (corvette) probably damaged a U-boaton the 20th, ancl H.M.C.S. Chambly (corvette) possibly damage done on the 21st. The above attacks by surface ships have only been provisionallyassessed at present.A Japanese U-boat was probably sunk by aircraft south-west of Rendova(Solomons) on the 12th, and another was probably sunk by a U.S. destroyer and aCatalina (P.B.Y.) on the 15th south-east of the Solomons.[26123] B
Enemy Intelligence.German^13. The German naval strength in the Mediterranean is estimated asfollows : two or three flotillas of E-boats; two or three flotillas of tank landing craft; two to four flotillas of minesweepers and between 10 and 20 U-boats.The Germans claim to have captured the 35,000-ton Italian battleshiplmpero. which may he completed by March 1944; the Cavour, which is under repair at Trieste and may be nearly ready for sea, the two damaged 8-inch cruisers at Spezia, which might be ready in October or November if they havenot been sabotaged, and a number of destroyers, submarines and smaller craft.The German s.s. Kertoson-o (9,289 tons) has been fitted out at Nantes as aU-boat supply ship. She is reported to carry 144 torpedoes. 1,200 tons of dieaeloil and eight or nine spare crews for U-boats and is heavily armed with anti-aircraft guns. Six ships of between seven and ten thousand tons, recently built in Holland, are suitable for similar conversion and two are reported to havebeen armed similarly to the Kertosono.I&apos;-boats.14. During the week a large concentration of U-boats has been operating in the N.W. Approaches and there has been some activity in the Indian Ocean.Large concentrations of U-boats have been reported from Bergen and Trondheim.There are indications that a German U-boat base is being developed atPenang. A stock of torpedoes, repair depot and technical staff are reported tobe already established.It is reported that the Indian Ocean has been divided for the purpose of u-boat operations into two zones, the Germans operating in the Madagascararea, m the Gulf of Aden and the Persian Gulf and the Japanese in the Bavof Bengal, Colombo area and possibly off the west coast of India.Enemy Attack on Shipping&quot;.15. Eight ships have been torpedoed by U-boats, two of which are knownto have sunk.An outward-bound convoy was repeatedly attacked by a concentration of u-boats south-south-west of Iceland (C). Two ships were sunk and four others were torpedoed, two of which have been abandoned. This is the first determinedattack on a convoy in the N.W. Approaches since iMay. A ship was alsotorpedoed east of Mogadishu (East Africa). One ship in convoy to Salerno was torpedoed and is a total loss.One ship was sunk by mines off Taranto, one was damaged off Cotrone andanother off Bizerta. but both have since reached port.Protection of Seaborne Trade.16. During the week ending the 19th, 1,071 ships were convoyed. Of these368 ships were in ocean convoys and 703 in British coastal convoys. Seventy-livedestroyers (including 15 US. destroyers), 93 sloops, cutters, frigates and corvettes(including seven U.S. cutters) were employed on escort duties.Five ocean convoys, consisting of 161 ships, arrived in Home waters without loss.During the week ending the 18th, imports into the United Kingdom by ships in convoy totalled 1,003,000 tons, compared with 1,396,000 tons during theprevious seven days and an average of 1,056,000 tons during the past ten weeks.Of the \veek&apos;s imports. 343,000 tons were mineral oil of various grades.British Minelaying.17. During the week aircraft laid mines off the Biscay ports and the frisian islands.Enemy Minelaying, British Minesweeping.18. On two nights during the week enemy aircraft laid mines in the thames estuary and off the Humber respectively.Forty-nine German moored mines have so far been destroyed in the approaches to Cotrone.The mine totals are 4,469 ground and 3,164 moored.
Dangerous areas due to Italian mines, which had been notified by the italian authorities, have been declared off Brtndisi and Bari on the east coast of Italyand off Valona, Albania and Corfu on the eastern side of the Adriatic.A mine has been reported off Charlestown (South Carolina), and the porthas been closed for the present.Italian Merchant Shipping.19. On the 14th nine Italian ships (11,832 tons) had arrived in ports under allied control.The Spanish authorities have refused to bunker the three Italian ships whichare now at Das Pal mas.Enemy Merchant Shipping.20. During the second half of August six enemy ships totalling 11,450 tons were sunk in the Mediterranean and two ships (3,500 tons) were seriously damaged.   No ships were sunk or seriously damaged in other areas during thisperiod.Since the spring of this year there has been a steady increase in the amountof German owned and German controlled tonnage operating in the Swedishore trade. As there has been no corresponding increase in Germany;s overallresources of serviceable tonnage this additional shipping can only have beenfound by diverting vessels from other trades.The more efficient administration of shipping at sea and in port has resultedin a general shortening of turn-round times, and not only has the lift of thevessels previously engaged in the ore trade been increased, but the economy in tonnage achieved in other trades has enabled a greater transfer of shipping tothis trade than would otherwise have been possible. The Kaufmann Administra-tion has apparently succeeded in changing in less than a year the enemy shipping position, from one in which a shortage of tonnage was threatening Germany&apos;simportant overseas sources of supply to one in which these sources of supply havegenerally been guaranteed and in some cases even expanded, in spite of a continued reduction in serviceable tonnage.MILITARY SITUATION.Italy.21 The situation in the Salerno bridgehead has now been stabilised and ourposition has been even more firmly established by the arrival of new formations.The German forces opposing us were battle-experienced, well-trained and well-armed. They had a considerable number of tanks including the new PzKw Vand Mk VI as well as many self-propelled guns, and these they used to their utmost in an attempt to throw us back into the sea. The determination of theAllied infantry soldier, supported by the tremendous weight of our sea and air bombardment beat off the enemy counter-attacks and have defeated them in their object. We have been able to strengthen and extend our bridgehead and arenow able to prepare for further offensive action.22. On the right the Eighth Army has made great progress and is now intouch with the right flank of the Fifth Army and there is no doubt that their approach had a considerable effect on the Salerno battle, causing the enemy topull back his vulnerable left flank.23. On the 16th the last attack of any force was put in by the Germans fromMontecorvino and from Nocera. This attack gained some ground but a promptcounter-attack restored the position and took over 100 prisoners. Further southU.S. forces themselves attacked and reduced the salient in the River Sele area.Later in the day first contact was made with patrols of the Eighth Army.24.   Further reinforcements had by now arrived and our advance continued,Altavilla and Battipaglia being captured on the 18th.   Since that date theenemy has been withdrawing his left flank, pivoting on his very strong hillpositions north of Salerno.   Our fighting patrols have been active and have had[26123] e 2
to deal with many small bu*t strong rear guards which are usually supported bytanks. Behind these patrols our main forces have been steadily advancing andby the 22nd. the Fifth Army bridgehead was firmly established to a depth of twentymiles on the right and on the left to a point about four miles north of Salerno,Firm contact has been established with the left flank of the Eighth Army.25. Our efforts to build up and supply our forces in the bridgehead havebeen increasing and some idea of the scale of these efforts can be seen by the figuresof the 17th when 4,692 personnel, 1,295 vehicles and 2,553 tons of stores were discharged over the beaches.26. On the 16th patrols from the Eighth Army joined up with patrols from our forces in the Taranto area, thereby establishing contact right across the foot ofItaly. Due to the speed of our advance, divisions of the Eighth Army are extremely strung out, but by the 19th they had started to concentrate in theCorleto and Montesano areas with&apos; patrols directed on Pontenza and Auletta.The last two towns were occupied on the 22nd and the advance continues.27. In the Taranto area our troops have continued to act with great speed and enterprise although short of transport. One patrol made use of the localtrain service to reach Potenza on the 18th. They found the town lightly heldby the enemy. Since then reinforcements have arrived and the enemy have been driven out of Gioja Del Colle. Italian forces and civil authorities are co-operating to the best of their ability and the administrative situation is satisfactory.Corsica.28. The concentration of German forces along the east coast of Corsica hasnow served its purpose. The evacuation of the German garrison in Sardiniato the ports of Bonifacio and Porto Vecchio was completed by the 20th and a steady withdrawal northwards along the east coast road to Bastia is now inprogress. German troops are being evacuated to Italy by air from Ghisonacciaand Borgo airfield. Tanks and M.T. are being embarked at Bastia for the main-land. German rear guards had evacuated Bonifacio by the 21st and demolitions,are now in progress at Porto Vecchio.29. Patriot forces, assisted by Italian troops who had been fighting theGermans on the north and west of Corsica since the 11th, were reinforced by600 French troops from North Africa on the 14th. By this time the Allied forces were in control of Ajaccio, the west coast as far north as Saint El Orent, as wellas the mountainous interior of the island. Harassing tactics were employedagainst the German communications on the east coast.. By the 20th Saint Florent.Vezzani. Zonza. Levie and Sartene were in French or Italian hands.&apos; TheGermans lost 200 men in a sharp action with French Patriots at Levie. Activepatrolling by French troops along the important road Ponte Leccia to Casamozzais being carried out. On the 22nd there were 2,500 French troops in Corsicaincluding an Assault Battalion, a detachment of Goumiers and a L.A.A. battery.Further reinforcements of two Tabor battalions have been despatched from north africa.Middle East.30. On the capitulation of Italy the majority of islands in the JEgean,including the Dodecanese, were exclusively garrisoned by Italian troops. Crete,however, had a mixed garrison of which a part was German, while in Phodes,which also had a mixed garrison, the Italians outnumbered the Germans by fourt one. After the Italian Armistice, the Germans quickly gained control ofCrete and Rhodes, and succeeded in extending their control during the period9th-20th September to the majority of the islands of the Cyclades (in CentralJEgean) and to Scarpanto (in the Dodecanese). We have managed to forestallGerman action in the islands of the Eastern /aegean by occupying the Dodecaneseislands of Kastelorizo on the 9th, Kos on the 12th, Leros on the 14th/ 15th, Syniion the 17th and Stampalia on the 21st, with light forces from the Middle East.In all cases the Italian garrisons have co-operated with us. The island of Samoswas also brought under British control on the lOth/llth, and the Italian garrisonthere is co-operating with our troops and with the local Greek guerrillas.
The Russo-German Campaign.Leningrad Sector.31. The Germans reported Russian attacks in this sector on the 16th and17th, but no mention was made of them by the Russians.Smolensk Sector.32. The Russians have now&quot; resumed their advance and have capturedVelizh and Yartsevo. With the capture of the former they have extended theNorthern arm of their attacks on Smolensk.Roslavl-Bryansk Sector.33. The fall of Bryansk has been followed by a steady Russian advance,which has resulted in the capture of a village six miles north-west of Roslavl.The Russians have also made progress west of Bryansk and along the railwayBryansk-Gomel.River Desna Sector.34. On the 19th the Russians made a fresh crossing of the River Desna atTrubchevsk. This has now linked up with the bridgeheads further south, and theRussians have now occupied Pogar, Semenovka (30 miles west-north-west ofNovgorod-Sever ski) and Chernigov. It was believed at one time that theGermans might attempt to hold the line of River Desna, but they have been unableto stem even temporarily the Russians advance in this sector.Kiev Sector.35. The Russian drive towards Kiev has made excellent progress. Aftercapturing Njecljin on the 15th, the Russians continued to advance westwards andsouth-westwards for another 40 miles. They have also maintained their pressuresouthwards towards the stretch of the Dnieper between Kiev and Kremenchug,capturing Mirgorod on the 18th. and Lubni on the following day.Kharkov Sector.36. After a short lull the Russians have now again gained ground south-west of Kharkov, and have m fact made more progress in this area than in any previous week of the present offensive. Krasnograd has been captured, and russian forces have now advanced to within 14 miles south-east of Poltava.Donetz Sea of A zoo Sector.37. The Russians have made rapid progress on the whole of this sector.Losovaya and Pavlograd have been captured, and the Russians are now within22 miles of Dnyepropetrovsk and 30 miles of Zaporozhe. Further south russian forces have now reached a line running from a point three miles south of Melitopolsouthwards to the coast. This means that the railway Melitopol-Crimea, whichthe Germans would undoubtedly wish to hold and use, is now within Russianartillery range.Taman Bridgehead.38. On the 17th the Russians captured Novorossisk, which will be of great value to them for naval operations in the Black Sea. They are now forcing theGermans back- towards Anapa and have also made a slight advance in thenorthern area of the bridgehead.Summary.39. This has been a most satisfactory week for the Russians, who have madeprogress along almost the whole front from north of Smolensk to the Sea of Azov.Burma.40.   There has been no general change in the situation.Dysentery is stated to be rife among the Japanese at Buthidaung, in theArakan.
South-West Pacific Area.New Guinea.41. Australian and TJ.S. forces entered Lae almost simultaneously fromthe west and the east on the 16th. The Eastern forces, which had been checkedfor some time at the flooded Busu River about three miles east of Lae, succeededon the 11th in forcing a crossing at the mouth of the river, and again on the 14that about, five miles from the mouth. Some enemy resistance near Mala hang, twomiles north-east of Lae, was quickly overcome. The Western force, which cleared the Japanese from prepared positions at Heath&apos;s Plantation on the 14th, advancedon Lae with little &quot;further opposition. Some part of the Japanese garrison fromLae are retiring northwards through the mountains. On the 19th Allied air-transported troops occupied Kaiapit. some 60 miles north-west of Lae up theMarkham Valley. Japanese casualties are estimated at 20 killed, whilst a further50-100 were driven out.42. Allied forces from the Salamaua area have advanced rapidly north-wards and by the 14th had reached the mouth of the Bwussi River, 10 miles north of Salamaua, while another force had landed unopposed at the mouth of theBuong River, four miles further north. Since that date 60 Japanese are reportedto have been killed in mopping-up operations in the Labu swamp area, about fivemiles south-west of Lae. Other elements of the Australian forces from Salamauahave made visual contact across the Markham River with the Allied forces whichadvanced on Lae from the West. Captured Japanese documents indicate thai: theJapanese intended to evacuate Salamaua by barge between the 5th and 11th,leaving only rear guards and to evacuate Lae overland to Sio on the north coast,about 60 miles north-west of Lae. It is not clear how far these intentions were carried out. but it seems probable that a part of the Lae garrison succeeded inwithdrawing. Japanese casualties in the Lae-Salamaua area between the 4thand 15th are estimated at about 2.000.48. Allied forces have also landed six miles north of Finschhafen in ;ico-ordinated land, sea and air attack, according to a press communique dated the22nd. Finschhafen is an important Japanese base on the west coast of the HuoiiGulf, some 60 miles north-west of Lae.Solomons.44. Japanese attempts to land reinforcements on Arundel Island, betweenNew Georgia and Kolombangara. on the 8th, 11th and 15th. were beaten off by .S. ground forces. According to an unconfirmed press report dated the 23rd.Japanese resistance on Arundel Island has ceased. There are reports of U.S.patrols operating on Ganongga Island, about 10 miles south of Vella Lavella. butit is not known whether they are in complete occupation of the island.AIR SITUATION.General Review.45. Aircraft of Bomber Command made a heavy attack on Hanover and.on a smaller scale, bombed the railway centre at Modane (French-Italian frontier).In Italy, heavy attacks were made on enemy communications and airfields:fighter-bombers successfully attacked enemy M.T. vehicles.United Kingdom.40. In daylight three enemy aircraft made brief reconnaissance flights overthe south coast. On two nights a total of 22 enemy bombers carried out looseattacks over East Anglia and south-east England. Two enemy aircraft were shot down and another was probably destroyed.Home Waters.47. Attacks, by fighters and fighter-bombers, on enemy shipping off theFrench and Dutch coasts resulted in the destruction of one tug, and damage to five ships of 1,000 to 1,500 tons and 38 small craft and barges; three Typhoonsfailed to return.Escorted Beaufighters, of which two are missing, attacked six minesweepersoff Holland : one was probably sunk and two more Avere damaged.Hampdens torpedoed a 3,000-ton ship off South Norway.
At night, R.P. Bur ricanes, Whirlwind bombers and Naval Albacoresdestroyed one E-boat and damaged a further four in the Channel Islands area..In operations over the North Sea and the Bay of Biscay, three enemy aircraft were destroyed and five others either probably destroyed or damaged; oneSunderland was lost on anti-U-boat patrol.Aircraft of Bomber Command, of which 107 were despatched, laid 295 sea-mines in enemy waters.Germany and Occupied Territory.Day.48. On the 16th, 147 Fortresses (B. 17) were despatched to attack the portarea at Nantes, the specific target being the U-boat supply ship Kertosono(9.289 tons); 79 aircraft attacked, dropping 211 tons of bombs, the supply shipbeing &quot; near-missed &quot; three times. Damage to other shipping and harbour facili-ties. as assessed from photographs, is referred to in Appendix VI. On the same day. 58 Fortresses (B. 17), unable to identify their primary target of an airfielddropped 155 tons on La Pallice.The following airfields were attacked during the week :date.16th18th19th21st22 ndAirfield.Attacked by-Tonnage.Near Nantes       ...       ... 49Cognac-Chateaubriand ... 21La llochelle        ...       ... 13Beaumont Le Roger     ... 36Tricqueville        ...       ... 34Beauvais-Tilie   ...... 26St. Omer-Longuenesse ... 8Liile-Nord          ...... 18Merville......... 8Woensdrecht       ...        ... 8Beauvais-Tille   ...       ... 43Evreux-Fauville ...       ... 70Norrent-Fontes (believed) 8Brest-Guipavas ...        ... 12Fortresses (B. 17)Fortresses (B. 17)Fortresses (13. 17)Marauders (B. 26)Marauders (B. 26)Marauders (B. 26)Typhoon BombersMarauders (B. 26)Typhoon BombersTyphoon BombersMarauders (B. 26)Marauders (B. 26)Tvphoon BombersMitchells (B. 25)13156354734343A233A3*57943i21-Results.Not observed.Not observed.Not observed.Good.Fair.Fair to poor.Poor.Fair to poor.Fair to good.A total of 02 escorted Mitchells (B. 25) attacked power stations nearRouen and Bethune, the railway centre at Serqueux and a synthetic petrol andammonia plant near Lens; at the last-named target, bursts were seen near gas-holders and at least one on the ammonia plant.In all the above operations, upon which 166 squadrons of fighters were engaged either as escort or on diversionary sweeps, 31 enemy aircraft were destroyed by bombers and 20 by fighters: 11 Fortresses (B. 17), three medium bombers and 10 fighters are missing.Attacks on enemy transport, which were on a small scale, resulted in damage to 11 locomotives and six trains: three Typhoons failed to return.Night.49. On the night of the 16th/17th, 291 heavy bombers attacked the marshalling yards at Modane, dropping 651 tons of bombs, most of which wereH.E. The markers and the bombing were extremely well concentrated and reports indicate a successful attack although photographic evidence is not yet available. Modane is the key railway centre on the Mont Cenis line, one oftwo railways linking France to Italy. Simultaneously, 10 Lancasters identifiedand attacked the Antheor viaduct (near Cannes) which carries the main linealong the coast from Marseilles to the Italian frontier; the formation leaderreports, that one arch was definitely hit.For the next five nights, weather was against large-scale bombing but, onthe night of the 22nd/23rd, 716 aircraft were despatched against Hanover. The628 aircraft, which attacked, dropped 2,338 tons of bombs in favourable weather conditions but the main weight of the attack, which was well concentrated,would appear, from preliminary reports, to have fallen on built-up areas to thesouth-east of the city and visual evidence, from two photographic sorties on the
23rd. suggests that little damage is to be seen in the city itself. A diversionaryattack was made by 28 aircraft on the^town power station of Oldenburg.From the operations reported above.. 30 aircraft are missing and a further fourcrashed in this country; four enemy night fighters were destroyed and a fifth was probably destroyed.A total of 34 Mosquitoes bombed Emden, Cologne and Berlin (twice), andWhirlwind bombers and Mosquitoes made a small-scale attack on a viaduct atPonthou and other railway bridges in Brittany.Intruder aircraft, of which 79 were despatched, operated on four nights ofthe week and attacked 13 airfields and a number of railway targets: threeMosquitoes are missing.Italy.50. On the 15th our bomber effort on a maximum scale was again concen-trated on direct support of the land forces, the roads approaching the Salernoarea being bombed principally around Eboli. Mustangs (A. 30) flew 183 offensive sorties between Eboli and Potenza and destroyed 100 M.T. vehicles and damaged70 others, while 212 Spitfires patrolled the beaches. Enemy activity was on a reduced scale and our bombers operating in the Salerno area were not engaged.After our troops had successfully extended the bridgehead the main weightof our bomber offensive was concentrated oil targets north of Salerno and onbridges, communications and airfields, while fighter-bombers attacked enemytransport columns and other targets.Wellingtons carried out a heavy night attack on the Torre AnnunziataPompeii road, and dropped 240 tons of bombs, obtaining hits on the road and on a railway bridge; the target was again attacked by Mitchells (B. 25) and Fortresses(B. 17), and the railway was cut in three places. Many raids were made onBenevento, where over 350 tons of bombs were released; the lines through the rail-way centre and roads were blocked and direct hits were made on bridges. Roadjunctions were bombed at Contursi (24 miles E. of Salerno), Auletta (35 miles .N.E. of Salerno), Avellino, Castelnuovo and Calabritto (50 miles E. of Naples).On the Solofra road (N.N.E. of Salerno) 84 Mitchells (B. 25) and fighter-bombers attacked M.T., gun-positions and troop concentrations. Potenza railway yards and bridges were bombed by Liberators (B. 24) and Halifaxes from the middle east, and heavy damage resulted.To the northwards of Naples, further successful raids were carried out. AtFormia the viaduct across the Rome-Naples line was cart by a direct hit; atCaserta the railway was cut and the road blocked and at Capua hits were madeon a road bridge and on a railway bridge.Strategic raids were made by a total of 75 Liberators (B. 24) on Pescara(95 miles E.N.E. of Rome); direct hits were reported on the road and railway bridges over the river and many hits were made on the railway centre. heavy bombers also attacked harbour installations at Leghorn and Bastia (Corsica),where one large motor vessel and three medium-sized ships were hit.Heaw and very successful attacks were made on the following airfields bya total of 121 Fortresses (B. 17), 203 Wellingtons, 172 Mitchells (B. 25) anilMarauders (B. 26), 94 Lightnings (P. 38) and fighter-bombers : Practica Di Mare,Cisterna/Littoria, Frosinone, Ciampino N. and S., Cerveteri. Viterbo (all in rome area) and Foggia satellites. Severe damage was caused to hangars andother buildings, but the number of aircraft destroyed on the ground was difficultto assess accurately, but it was considerable; at Practica Di Mare it is known that 39 aircraft and 18 gliders were destroyed and at the Ciampina airfields18 aircraft were destroyed and a similar number damaged.Fighters flew offensive patrols over the battle area and fighter-bombers wereactive attacking M.T. and road movement in the rear of the enemy. In theEboli/Serre area, 76 vehicles were destroyed or damaged, N.E. of Salerno 60 )vehicles were destroyed, a large column moving from Contursi was shot up and246 vehicles destroyed or damaged, and near Potenza, 30 vehicles, probably partof a petrol convoy, were set on fire.No marked effort was made by enemy fighters to attack our bombers. Theenemy offensive effort was directed almost entirely on convoys, on shipping in thebays of Naples and Salerno and on landing craft&apos;inshore. Considering the short-ness of the range and the large number of ships operating off the coasts the results achieved by the G.A.F. bombers have been meagre; furthermore, the support givento the army has been negligible. Fighter-bombers and fighters became increasinglyless effective during the week.
The complete failure of the G.A.F. to intervene effectively on the Salernofighting, particularly in support of the successful German counter-attacks on12th/ 13th, has been remarkable.In the week ended 21st, Allied aircraft flew nearly 10,000 sorties.Mediterranean.Dodecanese, Crete and Greece.51. Spitfires covered the unloading of Dakotas (C. 47) at Antimachiaairfield (Kos Island). Enemy attacks were carried out by Ju. 88s escorted byyje. 109s, and live Dakotas (C. 47) were destroyed on the ground. Eleven enemy aircraft were shot down and two Spitfires are missing.Liberators (B. 25) and other bombers attacked Maritza airfield (RhodesIsland), Hassani and Eleusis airfields (near Athens) and Heraklion and Malemeairfields (Crete). Bursts were seen in the dispersal areas and buildings were set on lire. At Maritza six aircraft were destroyed and others were set on fireat Eleusis.A ship of 1,000 tons was attacked in the -aegean Sea and left sinking.Russia,52. There has been some rain, particularly in the southern part of the front,during the week, which has temporarily affected air operations in some localities.In the main, however, the Russian Air Force has been heavily engaged in close support over the whole front, particularly in the Don basin and in the Kiev andSmolensk directions. In addition to the close support operations by day,harassing attacks on troop concentrations and lines of communications have beenmade at night. In the Kuban, strong air support was given to the landingparties at Novorossisk.It is probable that a fairly strong defensive effort has been put up in the three main sectors, Smolensk, Kiev and the Dnieper Bend area, but there is little doubttli.it the Russian Air Force can be regarded as possessing numerical air superiority and the ability to operate more intensively over the greater part of thefront. The continued weakness of the G.A.F. in single-engined fighter typeswhich has prevailed in Russia throughout the summer has been an important factor contributing to the ineffectiveness of the G.A.F. to provide adecpiate aircover where required; this shortage of fighters contrasts strongly with the steady increase of fighter strength during this year on the Western Front, and makes itclear that the defence of Germany against night and day bombing has deprivedmilitary operations in the east of urgently needed air support during a highlycritical stage of the war.R53. In the North. Myitkyina was bombed by six Liberators (B. 24) andescorted fighter-bombers made two attacks on Maingkwan (80 miles N.W. ofMyitkyina), where an enemy supply base and 20 buildings were hit. The railwayareas at Katha and Naba (10 miles W. of Katha) were bombed by 19 Mitchells(B.25).In Central Burma, 21 Mitchells (B. 25) made an effective attack on Monywa(00 miles W.N.W. of Mandalay). where the power station, barrack and other buildings were hit. Elsewhere in this area, 12 small-scale raids by formationsof three to nine Mitchells (B. 25) were made on railway and other communicationtargets with no outstanding results. Beaufighters damaged 16 locomotives andthree large steamers, and. 13 Liberators (B. 24) attacked a bridge near Sagaing(20 miles W.S.W. of Mandalay).In the Akyab area, Vengeances (A. 31) and Hurricanes made six small-scaleraids on enemy occupied villages and buildings and. in the Ramree area (Arakancoast) and on the Lower Irrawaddy, Beaufighters damaged numerous sampansand other small craft,China.54. Two attacks on Haiphong (Indo-China), by a total of 13 Liberators(B, 24), resulted, in damage to a dry clocl \, two small ships and numerous buildings.In combat, ten enemy aircraft were destroyed and 18 probably destroyed for theloss of four Liberators (B. 24).[26123] c
Escorted Mitchells (B. 25) attacked the Kowloon docks (Hongkong) and objectives in the Hankow area.At Kiukiang (140 miles S.E. of Hankow). Lightnings (P. 38) sank one small ship and set another on hie.Pacific Zone.New Guinea.55. A successful attack on airfields in the Wewak area was made by 21escorted Liberators (B. 24). At least ten aircraft on the ground were destroyed and many others rendered unserviceable, whilst, in combat, a further 48 were destroyed and 11 probably destroyed; Allied losses were one fighter. An attackon a similar scale was made on the airfield at Alexishafen, where 79 tons of bombs were dropped, resulting in the destruction of four fuel clumps, one hangarand several buildings.On the 15th, the day prior to the capture of Lae, Allied bombers droppedabout 60 tons of bombs on enemy positions in the area.Numerous attacks, mostly by medium bombers, were made on shipping andother objectives in the Finschhafen area and off the coast northwards toHansa Bay; at least 35 barges were either destroyed or damaged, a smallfreighter was set on fire and numerous supply and ammunition dumps were bombed.New Britain.56. Escorted heavy bombers dropped 94 tons of bombs on targets atCape Gloucester; two fuel dumps were set on fire and six enemy aircraft on theground were probably destroyed.Celebes.57. A total of 25 Liberators (B. 24), of which one is missing, attackedKendari and Macassar: at the latter, a large fire was started among oil cisterns.A amboina Archipelago.58. Three attacks were made on targets at Amboina where a barracks was set on fire and three aircraft, on the water, damaged. Other raids were made ondumps at Selaru (Tanimbar Islands) and on the sea-plane base at Taberfane(Am Islands).Solomons.59. About 350 bombers, mostly with fighter escort, attacked Kahili, Ballaleand other airfields on Bougainville Island where, in combat, 30 enemy aircraft were destroyed for the loss of seven Allied fighters. A Liberator (B. 24) damaged asmall freighter south-west of Buka Passage.About 105 Allied bombers operated against Kolomhangara Island where the targets were mostly enemy gun positions at Vila and elsewhere in the south-east of the island.Enemy dive bombers attacked Allied positions on Veila Lavella and float planes bombed and machine-gunned small naval craft off the coast; in these operations, 19 enemy aircraft were destroyed, two of which were by ships&apos; A.ATwelve enemy aircraft caused slight damage in an attack on Munda (NewGeorgia).Gilbert Islands.60. On the 19th, strong attacks, presumably by U.S. carrier-borne aircraft,were made on Japanese air bases on Tarawa Island (in the northern Gilberts) andon Naruru Island (in the western Gilberts).Australia.61. Two raids, by a total of 26 enemy aircraft, were made on airfields inthe Port Darwin area; no appreciable damage was done.
HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.62. On the night of the 21st/22nd a few bombs were dropped in Suffolk andEssex, causing little damage and no casualties, and at Margate, where some damage was done to house property and a few people were injured. On the night of the 22nd/23rd H.E. bombs were dropped at three places in Suffolk, and incendiary bombs fell in the East Riding, Lincolnshire and Norfolk. damage was negligible and there were no casualties.Casualties.63. Civilian casualties for the week ending 0600 hours on the 22nd were two killed and three seriously injured.APPENDICES I, II and III will be published periodically.APPENDIX IY.Enemy Merchant Ship Losses as assessed to 31st August, 1943.Nationality.	Sunk, Captured or Constructive Loss.		Seriously            -r-.          j -t-.                         Damaged.      ; Damaged.                    D          \					Total.	No.	Gross Tons.	x-         Gross j     Ions.		No. 389 247 59	Gross    ! XT Tons.    j -Xo-		Gross Tons.German Italian Other enemy ships  and ships useful to enemy Total    ...	556 i 2,280,959 826; 2,936,825 325 j    584,229		199 183 34	473,497 771,231 75,517		. 973,295 949,661 223,976	1,144 1,256 418	3,727,751 4,657,717 883,722	1,707 j 5,802,013 i		416	1,320,245	695	2,146,932	2,818	9,269,190The table does not include losses inflicted on the enemy by our Russian Allies,which are estimated at about 1,676,000 gross tons sunk; nor does it include lossesinflicted on Japanese shipping in the Far East and Pacific, which up to the31st August, 1943, are estimated to number 405 ships sunk or about 2,21b,UUUgross tons. &quot;      &apos;.    , .    .       , . , ,In addition, there is about 146,000 gross tons of Axis shipping which hasbeen taken over by South American countries not at war with the Axis and some36,000 gross tons of German shipping sold to Spain and Portugal.26123]d
APPENDIX  VI.Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports have been received during the week :  Germany.Berlin. A further interpretation of photographs taken after the attacks on berlin shows that, in addition to those already reported, about 87 more industrial concerns have been hit.   Of these, the following have been seriously damaged :-A.E.G. (Dynamos. Elec. Motors), Wedding (Priority 1 -f ).Berliner Maschinenbau (Torpedo Components). Wedding (Priority 1).Underground Railway Repair Shops, Charlottenburg-Ruhleben.Deutscher Eisenhandel (Steel Storage), Schoneberg.Berliner Elek. Ges. Speck U. Co.. Charlottenburg.Warehouses (Grain. Oil. Coal), Plotzensee.Damage to railway property includes buildings at Moabit goods station.Anhalter storage sidings. Charlottenburg goods station, Wilmersdorf goods station and locomotive workshops at Tempelhof and Charlottenburg.Many military and labour camps have also been damaged, including a militaryM.T. depot at Charlottenburg.. Eighty-five acres of business and residential property have been heavily damaged by fire in Steglitz. and there are similarly damaged, though smaller, areasin Schoneberg and Friedenau. In all, between 250 and 280 acres have been destroyed or seriously damaged in various parts of the city.France.Paris. An immediate interpretation of photographs taken on the10th September shows considerable damage to targets in the Paris area resultingfrom the U.S.A.A.F. attacks on the 15th September :  1. Bois Colombes.(a) Soc. Hispano-Suiza Aero-Engine Works. Two main workshops inthe north part of the works have been damaged, one of themseverely. The heat-treatment shop, the machine shop and at least one other shop have all been affected.(b) Cie (VApplications Mecaniques [CAM.) Bail-Bearing   Works.Main workshop severely damaged.(c) Soc. Berliet Repair  Works and Store. Main workshop severely damaged.(d) Delage M/T Store. Damaged in three places.APPENDIX  Y.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.15th September. H.M. M/S trawler Hirer Spey sunk in collision at Belfast.19/// September. B.Y.M.S. 19 (minesweeper) seriously damaged by minesouth-east of Cotrone.   Eleven casualties.20/7/ September. M.G.Bs. 606 and 610 damaged by gunfire off Ijmuiden.22//c/ September. BL.M. drifter Ocean Retriever sunk by mine in ThamesEstua ry.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported :  Officers:  11 wounded; 1 missing.Ratings: 44 killed: 14 missing; 20 wounded.In addition, 2 officers prisoners of war, previously reported missing;4 officers missing, previously reported killed; and 1 officer killed, previously reported missing.
2. Point du Jour.(a) S.A. des A vions Caudron-Renault. With the exception of somebuildings (probably offices) on the bank of the Seine, every building in the works has been damaged. Three of the largest have beenpartially destroyed (one of them having had five direct hits) andthe long building running the whole length of the works on theeast side has been severely damaged.3. Billancourt.(a) Renault Works. These works have again been heavily damaged.The large sheet metal and radiator shop, on which repairs were pratically complete, has been three-quarters destroyed. Theradiator and axle shop, the gear shops and the core shop have allsuffered, while several buildings on the He Sequin have been severely damaged.4. Quai de Jar el.(a) S.A . A ndre Citroen A utomobile Engine Construction and M. V.Assembly Plant. Workshops in the south-west part have been damaged as has another in the centre of the works. Slight damage has been caused in the south-east part.5. I&apos;embassy-les-Moulineau-x. Two hangars south-east of the power stationhave been damaged by direct hits.Montlugon. Photographs taken after the attack on the 15th/16th Septembershow severe damage to the Dunlop Tyre Factory. This factory produces aero tyresand is believed to produce 14 per cent, of Axis automobile tyres.12 out of 26 major buildings have been destroyed. These include a storefor finished products, a test house, a garage and a raw rubber store. Severalunidentified buildings have also been destroyed. Ten buildings, including a storefor compounding ingredients, a building for the production of solid tyres, anda technical office and laboratory, have all been very severely damaged. East ofthe factory five storage sheds and some stocks in the yard have been destroyed.Nantes. An immediate interpretation of photographs taken on the16th September after the U.S.A.A.F. attack earlier in the day shows damage inthe Port Maritime and to the airfield at Chateau Bougon.Port Maritime. A destroyer alongside the quay has been sunk. Onemedium-sized shed on a quay has been severely damaged and two longbuildings, one medium building and the building slips of Chantiers cle laLoire have all received direct hits. Many hits on sidings and on the portmarshalling yard have cut several tracks and damaged a number of wagons.Chateau Bougon. A large hangar has been damaged and a number ofhuts and small buildings in the north dispersal area destroyed or severely damaged. Three shelters have been completely destroyed and three or fourmore damaged, while there are a number of craters on taxi-tracks.A final interpretation of photographs shows that in addition to the destroyer, which, as reported above, was sunk in the Port Maritime, a tankerand a small vessel were hit and capsized and an auxiliary vessel was sunk. Inaddition a floating clock was hit in two places and is partly submerged.Modane. All information so far available shows that the bombing of Modanerailway marshalling yard on the 16th/T7th September was very effective.Meulan les Mureaux. Photographs taken on the 16th September after theU.S.A.A.F. attack on the 3rd September show that two large multi-bay workshopsm the south-west corner of the airfield have been seriously damaged and foursmaller ones gutted. A hangar on the river bank at the north-east corner has been damaged and two buildings of the neighbouring motor torpedo boat constructionplant of Chantiers Navals de Meulan has been affected. A flak position on thewest side of the airfield has been destroyed by a direct hit.Chartres. Photographs taken on the 16th September show that as a resultof the TJ.S.A.A.F. attack on 15th September, one of the three large&apos;hangars andan adjacent shed on the north side of the airfield, and a large, double-bay hangaron the west side have been damaged. There are approximately 120 craters on the airfield, one on the runway and about ten on the perimeter and taxi-tracks.
Merville. An interpretation of photographs taken after the attacks by fighter Command on the 9th September and U.S.A.A.F. on the 15th Septembershows that a hangar in the north dispersal area has been severely damaged andone shelter destroyed and three damaged. In the south dispersal area twoshelters previously damaged have been almost destroyed and a ; further two aredamaged. In addition there are four craters on the runways, about 30 ontaxi-tracks and some 45 on the landing ground. iMazingarbe. In the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the power station and chemicalplant on the 31st August, the methanol plant was hit and will cause a considerablehold up. The coal washing machine section was heavily damaged, resulting inthe coking and synthetic plants being useless for a time.Belgium.Brussels. Photographs taken after the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the7th September show that in the Brussels/Evere airfield and aircraft works, sixhangars and five barrack blocks have been destroyed or damaged, and one aircraftshelter has been damaged. Four workshops and six other works buildings havebeen more or less severely damaged, and some repair shops have been destroyed.The works railway has been cut by a direct hit, and. several huts and a storesdump have.been damaged.   On the airfield itself there are over 210 craters.Langerbrugge. In the attack on the 23rd July on the power station one25.000 kilowatt turbine was rendered permanently unfit for use and a condenserput out of commission for a time. The switchboard was severely affected by blast.The Germans undertook clearance and repair work at once and it was expected the situation would be normal, save for the lost turbine, in eight days.Schelle. In the attack on the 23rd July on the power station one bomb fellon the water intake and two in the engine-room.   Two turbines were damaged.Sea-mining.Swedish press of the 21st July states that the German trawler Hornsresswas mined off Jutland and ten German fishermen were lost.Swedish press has announced that Swedish Korsoe (2,726 tons) was damaged by a mine off the Dutch coast about mid-July.Swedish broadcast of the 15th September stated that Swedish&apos; Valen(966 tons) was damaged by a mine on the 15th September off Moen.



</content>
</cab>
