<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/223/0 images: 7-20</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DQCUI/iaTT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BEITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S G^VSRKMSITT. ) S E C R Lj  ToIn accordance with the decision of the Cabinetrecorded in Cabinet 48 (31) Conclusion 3 of Appendix ,the following documents are appended:-(i) Existing instructions to the Secretary of the Cabinet;(ii) Existing instructions as regards Cabinet Committees and Conferences;(iii)  Submission of business to the Cabinet;Circular letters from the Treasury, dated 25th february,   1931 and 28th April,  1924;(iv) Economic Advisory Council; copy of treasury minute of Appointment, dated 27th January 19310Particulars of procedure of the Committee of Imperial Defence are not attached as it is believed that all Members of the present Government are familiar with them.      They can be communicated if desired.A separate Note on the Economic Advisory Council is attached as Appendix V.A fuller Memorandum containing a historical account of the development of the Cabinet Secretariat and detailed particulars of its operation is available, and will be sent to any Minister who may desire to see it0CP.  205 (51),C A B I NCABINETPROCEDURE,(Signed)    M.F.A.HAKEKY,Secretary, Cabinet.Whitehall Gardens9August 27th,  1931.
APPENDIX loEXISTING IHSTRUCT-IONS TO THE SECRETARY OF THE CABINET.1.      The Prime Minister will instruct the Secretary as to what subjects are to be placed on the Agenda Paper of the Cabinet,      The Secretary will give Ministers as long notice as he can as to when subjects are lively to be discussed,, and will issue to members of&quot; the Cabinet a weekly list of subjects awaiting consideration. 2.      The Secretary will attend meetings of the Cabinet,, unless instructed to the contrary, for the purpose cf recording the conclusions.3.      It is an instruction to the Secretary in drafting Cabinet Minutes to avoid any reference to opinions expressed by any individual and to limit the Minutes as narrowly as passible to the actual decision agreed to. 4c      One copy of the draft conclusions will be sent to the King as heretofore    with Humble Duty&quot; from the Prime Minister,,5.      The conclusions of the Cabinet are to be transmitted by the Secretary to all Cabinet Ministers and subject tc the authority cf the Prime Minister, tc Ministers who are not members L-f the Cabinet and whv are concerned in a primary cr secondary degree.      In the case of the Law Officers of the Crown, however,  the Lord Chancellcr is responsible for communicating such decisions as concern them, subject to consultation with the Cabinet at the time the decision is taken, or subsequently with the Prime Minister if he deems necessary,
6.      Minis ters are responsible for making such communication as they deem necessary to their respective Departments in&amp;   regard to the conclusions of the Cabinet.      The precautions hi the rto observed by the Secretary for ensuring that the conclusions are opened only by Ministers are to be adhered to.(,   7.      The Minutes of the Cabinet are always to be available for consultation by the Cabinet Ministers,  either in the Secretary&apos;s Office,  or, during meetings of the Cabinet, in the Cabinet Room.8.      The Secretary is  to  take all possible precautions for ensuring that in the reproduction of Cabinet Minutes the minimum staff is employed,  and that aocess to Cabinet Minutes in limited to Cabinet Ministers.9c      The rule hitherto in practice is maintained under which Memoranda, Draft Bills and other constituents cf the Agenda paper of the Cabinet are sent to the Cabinet Secretariat for circulation only after their subject-matter has been fully examined between the Department from which they emanate, the Treasury,  the Law Officers where contentious Bills are involved,  and any other Departments concerned.(See Appendix III).10.      Subject to the above and to any instructions in regard to any particular paper he may receive from the Prime Minister or from the Minister from whom the document originates, the Secretary will circulate to Members of the Cabinet all Memoranda and other documents prepared fur the use of the Cabinet.      Subject to reference in case of doubt,  to the Prime Minister or the Minister from whom a document is received,  the Secretary will have discretion to circulate Cabinet papers to Ministers outside the Cabinet whose Departments are affected.      He is also authorised to send additional copies to Ministers at their request.
llo      Subject to any special instructions he may receive from the Prime Minister the Secretary, as soon as may be after the termination of every meeting of the Cabinet will issue a press communique containing the names of those present,12.      Government Departments will reproduce their own Memoranda and forward the required number of copies to the Cabinet Officre for circulation.13.      The procedure as regards Cabinet Committees and Conferences is attached.
APPENDIX II.iXISTIHG INSTRUCTIONS AS REGARDS CABINET COMMITTEESAND CONFERENCES.The Secretary to the Cabinet and Secretaries of Cabinet Committees are to conform    to the following-instructions:-(a) The Secretary will take the Chairman/s instructions as to the form of record. The procedure should approximate to  that of the Cabinets but in order that the Members of the Cabinet who are not also Members of particular Committeess may be informed,, a somewhat fuller record of the proceedings is permissible in the case of Committees than in that of the Cabinet.      Reference to the views of particular Members should be avoided,(b) The conclusions of the Committee on home Affairs will be circulated to all Members of the Cabinet s and will not be regarded as final until approved by the Cabinet.(c) The conclusions of other Cabinet Committees will be circulated to the Cabinet. Conclusions in regard to matters of high policy will be reserved for approval by the Cabinet,      The Chairman will be the judge of what questions should be sn reserved.(d) In cases where Secretaries of Cabinet Committees are not members of the Cabinet office they will place  themselves in communication with the  secretary to the Cabinet with a view to the necessary arrangements as regards circulation and distribution of the Committee&apos;s documents.
appendix in.G.   3547. No.  8/31.TREASURY CHAMBERS, Whi t ehal 1 s o . &apos;./.25th Pehruary, 1931.SUBMISSION OF BUSINESS TO THE CABINET.CABINET DECISION AS TO PROCEDURE.Sir sI am direct eel &quot;by the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty&apos;s Treasury to acquaint you, for the information ofthat His Majesty&apos;s Government have recently had under consideration the arrangements regarding the submission of business to the Cabinet, and in particular have had before them the Circular Ho. 11/24 of the 28th April, 1924, on this subject, the main provisions of which were approved by the Cabinet at their Meetings on the 10th and 31st of June, 1929,A copy of that Circular is printed hereunder, and I am to state that His Majesty&apos;s Government have reaffirmed their decision that the procedure therein indicated shall continue to be observed in its entirety.In this connection I em to emphasise the importance of securing that all draft Bills are fully examined by the Departments concerned before they are circulated to the Committee of Home Affairs.      A Department originating legislation should, in any case, arrange for the circulation to that Committee of the draft Bill as long in advance as possible, and in every case the covering Memorandum to the Bill should, in accordance with the requirements cf the Circular, contain a specific statement that the draft Bill has been examined by all Departments which are, or may be, affected by its provisions.I am, Sir,Your obedient Servant,H.P.VAR3EIT FISHER.
AITNaXE &apos; to.U?P1jEDIX III.No.   11/24-.COPY Qg TREASURY CIRCULAR, 28th APRIL, ..1924.Sir, \/&apos;I am directed toy the Lords Commissioners of &quot;J-.ll. Treasury to acouaint you, for the information, ofthat 11.II.  Government have had under careful consi-deration the question of insuring that the Cabinet - and Cabinet Committees - shall be invited to reach decisions only after the subject referred to the Cabinet has been thoroughly examined between each of the various Public Departments concerned.This elementary &quot;nil-ePof -husdnesa.. is essential if the Cabinet haid its Comir.committees are to have&quot;avaiJalole all the&apos; facts and points of view requisite for an enlightened decision and are to be saved the possibility of hasty or uninformed conclusions.The observance of the rule is the more obligatory under modern conditions when the mass of Government business has so enormously increased;, and as a consequence Governments can only get through It efficiently if the issues   presented for decision have been carefully Investigated beforehand by the Departments in collaborationThe Cabinet feels sure that Departments are anxious to assist it in securing the observance of this rule, and has come to the conclusion that the desired object will bo facilitated by the following procedure.      In future all memoranda s draft Bills and other constituents cf the Agenda will be sent to the Cabinet Secretariat for circulation only after their subject-matter has been fully examined between the Departments from which they emanate.; the Treasurys the Lav/ Officers where contentions Bills are involved, ana any other Department concerned, and these documents will bear on the face of them a specific statement that this examination has taken place.      The documents should be made as complete as possible by containing the various arguments and criticisms which might be brought against the proposals advocated.      To enable the members of the Cabinet  (and Cabinet Committees) to have time to consider proposals Intended for Cabinet decision and in view also of the possibility that such Inter -Departmental examination may result in definite differences of opinion necessitating the preparation of memoranda by the dissenting Department or Departments, nc memoranda, draft Bills, etc., which originate proposals for Caeiaet decision will be placed on- the .agenda until an interval of at least five days has elapsed after circulation;. except on arv occasion when the Prime Minister expressly authorises a relaxation of the rule..L am t, s ir ,Your obedient Servant,
ECONOMIC ADVISORY COUNCIL*Copy of Treasury Minute of Appointment, ,dated 27th January, 1950.The First Lord calls the attention of the Board to the decision of His Majesty&apos;s Government on 16th January, 1930, to establish an Economic Advisory Council.    This will be a standing body reporting to the Cabinet,  and its purpose, position in relation to Departments,  organisation, and functions will be as follows!-itPurpose.To advise His Majesty&apos;s Government in economic matters.To make continuous study of developments in trade and industry and in the use of national and imperial resources, of the effect of legislation and fiscal policy at home and abroad, and of all aspects of national, imperial and international economy with a bearing on the prosperity of the country.Pogitjon in relation to Departments.The Council will be subject to the general directions of the Prime Minister, and its expenses will be borne on the Treasury Vote.It will take over and expand the functions of the existing Committee of Civil Research.It will keep in close touch with Departments affected by its work with a \iew to the concerted study of economic problems of national interest, but it will interfere in no way with the functions or responsibilities of Ministers or of the Departments over which they preside, and it will have no administrative or executive powers.Organisation.1. The Chairman of the Council will he the Prime Minister, and the other members will be as follows:-(a) The Chancellor of the Exchequer,  the Lord privy seal (while the present duties are attached to that office )&quot;:* the President of the Board of Trade and the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries,(b) 8ui&quot;ii other Ministers as the Prime Minister may from time t-3  time summon.(c) Such other persons chosen by the Prime minister in virtue of their special knowledge and experience in industry and economics.The Council will meet when summoned by the Chairman, and as-regularly as is found possible.Subsequently the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs was added.APPENDIX IV.
2.  The Chairman may appoint standing&quot;commit-tees and also such committees for special purposes as may he required.3. The Council will have a secretary, and assistant secretaries, at least two of whom will he economists, together with such staff as may he found necessary.Functions.Providing that it acts after receiving the approval of the Prime Minister, the Council may initiate inquiries into, and advise upon,  any subject falling within its scope, including proposals for legislation.    The Council shall consult Departments and outside authorities in regard to any work in hand or projected and shall collate such statistical or other information as may he required for the performance of its work    The Council shall also cause to he prepared a list of persons with industrial,  commercial, financial and working-class experience, and persons who have made a special study of social, economic and other scientific problems vzho .might assist the Council by serving on Committees or as advisers in matters of which they have expert knowledge, or in other ways.Its reports and work will be confidential unless the Council advises the Prime Minister otherwisen    Any action arising out of them will be taken on the solo responsibility of His Majesty&apos;s Government.
APPENDIX   V.Note on the Economic Advisory Council,The Economic Advisory Council, which was establish by the Cabinet in january  1930, was directed to take over and expand the functions of the Committee of Civil Research established in June 1925o      Its constitution and functions were set out in a Treasury Minute of January 27th,  1930 (Appendix IV).2. Its purpose was defined as follows&quot;To advise Kis Majesty&apos;s Government in economic matters,,To make continuous study of developments in trade and industry and in the use of national and imperial resources, of the effect of legislation and fiscal policy at home and abroad,, and of all aspects of nationals imperial and international economy with a bearing on the prosperity of the country&quot;.3c The Council held 13 Meetings and its predecessor,the Committee of Civil Research,  26 Meetings.      In addition there have been a large number of meetings of the various ad hoc Committees of which some were appointed &quot;by the Council and others taken over from the Committee of Civil Research.      It is through these Committees that the bulk Of the detailed work has been done.4,, The Pri,..e Minister presides at Meetings of theCouncil;, which are attended by the Cabinet Ministers named in the Treasury Minute and by fifteen other persons invited, by the Prime Minister to serve thereon.     (For names see Annexe)c
5.. The meetings of the Council itself are mainlydevoted to a review of the state of trade, and of similar questions.      In addition, the Council considers the reports submitted by its Committees.6S Among the questions referred to special ad hocCommittees by the Economic Advisory Council have beenthe following:-Problems of Rationalisation. -   New Industrial Development. The Chinese Situation. The Locust Control. Agricultural Policy. Empire Migration. Centralised Slaughtering. The Education and Supply of Biologists. The Economic Outlook. Empire Trade.Revision of the Cost of Living Index Number.Marketing and Distribution.Unemployment Benefit.Unemployment ,-yment Statistics.The Iron and Steel Industry.The Cotton Industry.Irrigation Research.7. The following questions are under investigation byCommittees which the Council took over from the Committee ofCivil Research:-Native Dietetics.The Mineral Content of Natural Pastures. The Severn Barrage. The Pishing Industry. Tsetse Fly Control.8. . In addition to the foregoing ad hoc Committees,   \there are two standing Committees of the Council, viz,the Committee on Economic Information and the Committee on scientific Research.9. The Committee on Economic Information is directed to supervise the preparation of monthly reports to the Economic Advisory Council on the economic situation aid toadvise as to the continuous study of economic development,.
Sir Josiah Stamp is the Chairman and there are four other members.      Sir Sydney Chapman, Chief Economic Adviser to K.M,Government,  attends the meetings of this Committee. 10. The Committee on Scientific Research is directed to advise the Economic Advisory Council as to the bearings of the Reports of its scientific committees and generally as to the. discharge of its functions in their scientific aspects, Sir Daniel Hall is the Chairman and the other members are the President of the Royal Society (Sir Frederick Hopkins), Sir Charles Sherrington, F, R. 8.,  and Sir William- Hardy, F.R. S. In order to ensure co-ordination the Secretaries of the three Government :Research organisations  (the Advisory Council for Scientific and Industrial Research, the Medical 3esearch Council and the Agricultural Research Council)  attend, the meetings of this Committee.llo The Economic Advisory Council has two joint secretaries (  of the rank of Assistant Secretary in the Civil Service) who are civil servants.      In addition, there are four posts of temporary Assistants (two of which are vacant at the-moment),      These assistants are either economists or statis-ticians.12, As in the cose of the Committee of Imperial Defence,additional help is given in special cases by the appoint-frommerit  of a joint Secretary/whatever Department is mainly concerned with any particular inquiry,13, All reports of the Council and its committees are printed and come before the Cabinet for approval before action is taken upon them.
14, As the successor of the Committee of civil research the Economic Advisory Council also deals with all invitations received from Foreign Governments for official participation in International Scientific Congresses and similar bodies, and appoints the Government representatives at all such meetings.(Signed M. P. A. HANKEY,Secretary,    Cabinet.2, Phi t ehal1 Gar dens,  S. W.1., August 27th.   1951.
to appendix     V.COMPOSITION OF ECONOMIC ADVISORY COUNCIL.The Right lien. Ji Ramsay HacDonald, M. P. ,    (Chairman) The Right lion. Philip Snowden, M.P. The Right Eon.  J.II.Thomas, M.P. The Right Hon. C, Addison, 1.1. D., M.P. The Right Hon. \7illiam Graham, II. P. Sir Arthur Balfour, Bt. , K. B.E. Mr.* Ernest Levin. Mr.  &apos;.,.R.Blair. Sir John Cadman, CC.1I. G. Mr. M.M.Citrine. Mr.  G.D.II. Cole-Sir Ernest R. Debenham, Bt. Sir Andrew Duncan, oir Daniel Hall s II. C. B. , P.R.S. Sir William Hardy, P.R.S. Mr.  J.M.Keynes, C.B. Sir Alfred Lewis, II.B.e. Sir &quot;.. illiam McLintocli. Sir Josiah Stamp, G.B.E. Mr. R.H.Tawney.Mr. II.D. Henderson. )\      Joint sercretaries MR..  A.F.Hemmings C.B.E,      )        to tiie Council,

</content>
</cab>
