<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/223/0 images: 89-94</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IfS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS HR1TAKNTC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERmffiNT).-C A B I N E T. BlSARMAMENJTo The French Memorandum (Paper No-.  GeP-235(3l)) .The late Government,  at the suggestion of members of the Three Party Sub-Committees referred the above-mentioned Memorandum to the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee for their remarks (See also Cabinet 48(3l)s Conclusion 6).The observations of the Chiefs of Staff are contained in the attached Memorandum, which, by direction of the Prime Minister,  is circulated for the consideration of the Cabinet-SCEETc.SI 5(31) .(Signed) M.PoA.  HAWKEY.Secretary to the Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens,  SoW*l*, November 4th, 1931.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOYERNMENT   &quot;Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   September 1931. secret. Copy No.    23CCS. 277.(Also Papers Nos. 1063-B and CP. 213 (31).)COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE.Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee.THE FRENCH MEMORANDUM ON DISARMAMENT, dated july 15, 1931.*Memorandum by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee. General Remarks.1. THE French Government issued, on the 11th July, 1931, under the signature of M. Briand, a Memorandum elaborating their views on Disarmament and, in particular, the conditions under which they would be prepared to consider any further reductions in the strength of their armed forces.2. Before remarking on the bearing of the French Memorandum on the defence problems of this country we would emphasise that it deals chiefly with the political aspects of disarmament, particularly in their relation to security; and, in consequence, does little more than repeat the arguments which have been consistently and continuously advanced by the French representatives at Geneva during the last few years. There is one significant point, however, to which we would draw especial attention. The views in the French Memorandum represent the official doctrine of the French General Staff in its extreme form; M. Briand, by signing this memorandum, would seem to have given the official cachet of his. Government to the General Staff Doctrine, and, this being so, it would appear that there will be small chance of any effective reductions being made in the armaments of France or her Satellite Powers.3. An explanation is given in the Memorandum of what France conceives to be the principles of disarmament embodied in the Covenant and in the Peace Treaties; and her interpretation implies the strict observance of the Standards laid down in Part V of the Peace Treaties, and also particular consideration of the requirements of national security and the geographical situation and circumstances of each State. In other words, France continues to claim the highest degree of security for herself, while, at the same time, denying the right of Germany and her ex-allies to any corresponding degree of security except that provided by the goodwill of other nations, represented to a considerable degree by France herself and the Little Entente. She appears to be as determined as ever that the disarmament imposed on Germany and the other ex-enemy Powers shall be maintained in perpetuo.4. France, having established to her satisfaction the ratios between her armaments (and those of her allies) to those allowed to Germany, demands definite and concrete guarantees as the price of any disturbance of this ratio, so far as any reduction of her armaments is concerned. We would observe that, in spite of the almost insatiable clamour of France for more guarantees, those which she has already secured are by no means so inconsiderable as is implied. These guarantees are represented by the Pact of Paris, the Covenant (in general* See O.I.D. Paper No. 1062-B, also Papers Nos. CP. 236 (31), D.P.C. (31) 14, D.C. (P.) 51 and C.O.S. 276.[6002] Si
form), the Locarno Treaties (in precise form), the Treaty of Versailles (whereby the impotence of Germany was secured), and the military alliances contracted by France (to hedge Germany in). The Optional Clause, the General Act and the Treaty of Financial Assistance go a long way to meeting, on the arbitration and economic side, much of the security which France sought to obtain under the Geneva Protocol.5. It is, however, the principles of the 1924 Protocol, with its rigid provisions for the guaranteeing of military assistance against an aggressor, not merely in general terms, but in accordance with a precise plan embodying the actual type and amount of armed assistance to be provided, that France desires to revive. It is evident, we think, that, while France pays ready lip-service to the principle of moral guarantees, in reality, the only guarantees to which she is disposed to attach any real importance are those providing definitely and specifically for armed assistance, and that any reductions of her existing armaments would be directly related to the strength of the armed forces for which any such guarantees might make provision.6. The psychological reasons which dominate the French attitude towards Disarmament are well known, and can be understood, even though it is questionable whether two, out of the three invasions in the last 100 years, which are so often quoted, were calamities entirely unprovoked by France. It is realised that France has no thought for aggression or military adventure, but solely a fixed determination that French soil shall never again become the cockpit of Europe. But there are serious weaknesses in their case, for their claim that their armaments are reduced to the lowest point compatible with national security ignores the fact that this security is obtained only by the most formidable military preparations and at the expense of the complete insecurity of Germany.The Naval Aspect.7. On pages 5 and 6 of the Memorandum reference is made to French Naval Armaments; they draw attention to the reduction they effected in their global tonnage between 19,14 and 1921 from 750,000 tons to 500,000 tons. These figures are substantially correct. The difference between the figure of 750,000 tons for 1914 given in the French Memorandum and that of approximately 932,000 tons given to the Three Party Sub-Committee in Paper No. D.C. (P) 6* can be accounted for by the fact that the latter figure includes all vessels built, building and projected, whereas the figure given by the French only includes &quot; tonnage keDt in commission.&quot;8. The French navy was certainly neglected in the Allied interest during the war, and France had an undoubted right to begin to rebuild it afterwards. The steps she has actually taken, however, far exceed what was necessary in the circumstances, more especially in respect of the unprecedented submarine fleet that she has been constructing. Generally, she has been building up a modern fleet at a rate which appears quite unnecessary, and which will, if continued, shortly constitute such a potential threat to the British Commonwealth as to necessitate counter-measures.9. The global figure of French tonnage in commission and under construc-tion on the 1st January, 1931? is put at 628,603 tons, which agrees with Admiralty calculations. It is interesting to note that of this total tonnage there is now under construction no less than 142,586 tons,t but the French memorandum is careful not to draw attention to this fact. The term &apos;&apos; under construction &apos;&apos; comprises all vessels building and projected up to and including their 1930 building programme.10. Although the French memorandum stresses the reduction which has taken place in the French Fleet since 1914, it makes no mention of the fact that in the same period the strengths of the Fleets of other major European Powers show a proportionately greater reduction, while that of Austria-Hungary has beep entirely eliminated.   So far, therefore, from this arm having been reduced*t Also Papers Nos. O.P. 100 (31) and 1047-B.t The tonnage for aircraft carriers is shown as 113,146 tons instead of 22,146 tons. This is apparently a misprint, as the total 628,603 tons is correct.
- -	fa) Metropolitan	(b) Overseas.	(C) In Ships. Aircraft Carriers.	Total (a), (b), (c).Prance	1,210	395*	62	1,667Great Britain	400t	1531	153	7065* Excludes 46 ambulance aircraft.f 127 aircraft of non-regular A.A.F. and S.R. formations excluded. % Exclusive of 96 a/c in India.g Eirst-line strength at April 1, 1931 : About 4u (irst:Hue aircraft (all Metropolitan) are being added in the year 193J-32.14. A comparison of the above figures illustrates the striking disparity between the existing French Air Force and those maintained by Great Britain, (a) in the United Kingdom, (b) in the Crown Colonies, Mandated Territories, and otner overseas areas.15. As between the Metropolitan air forces of France and Great Britain, France has a numerical superiority in order of 3 : 1. This is the essential factor in the problem of our air defence. Nor do these figures convey an adequate picture of the disparity between the respective forces, since some 160 French aircraft, normally stationed in Africa, can be used at short notice to reinforce* Also O.I.D. Paper So. 1048-B and CP. 108 (31).&quot; to the lowest point consistent with her national security in the present state of Europe and the world,&quot; it would appear that, judged by 1914 standards, France is at the present moment considerably over-insured.Army Aspect.11. The French land forces are dealt with on pages 4 and 5 of the Memorandum. There are considerable discrepancies between the figures given and those known to us, which it will be easier to clear up when they are published in the more detailed Memorandum which is promised later. It miay be conceded that the figures of peace strength have been very substantially lowered by the reduction of the period of service to one year, and that the number of Divisions existing in time of peace has been correspondingly reduced. The fact, however, remains that as the period of service is reduced the number of long service personnel is increased, and exactly the same number of men have been trained for military service as before; the mobilised strength of the French army is therefore unaltered. At the same time there has been increasingly heavy expendi-ture upon war material and on fortification. The oft-repeated argument, there-fore, about reductions is largely fallacious.A ir Force A spect.12. The position of the French Air Force is described on pages 6 and 7 of the Memorandum. The figures in relation to existing air armaments do not include any information as to air personnel either as regards actual strength or in terms of &quot; effectives.&quot; No budgetary figures are included. No &quot; horse-power &quot; figures are given. The number of service-type aircraft in use in schools is not given.   Nor are the number of aircraft in &apos;&apos; immediate reserve &apos;&apos; stated.13. The strengths given for first-line aircraft are as indicated in the table below, where they have been contrasted, for purposes of comparison, with the corresponding figures of Great Britain. The figures given in the French Memorandum differ somewhat from those previously given by the Air Ministry in Paper No. D 0. (P) 11.* The difference being accounted for mainly because -certain aircraft at Headquarters (Army) formations (the existence of which the Air Ministry were aware of without, at that time, being able to confirm their information as to the types of aircraft in use) have been included in the French return.FiRST-Line Aircraft.
the French Metropolitan Air Forces, whilst, for geographical reasons, we enjoy-no such corresponding advantage.16. It has already been observed that the figures given in the French Memorandum are incomplete. But such figures as have been given and quoted serve to indicate the broad outlines of existing French armaments, and it is not anticipated that the more detailed statements will materially alter the relative position resulting from a comparison of the French and British figures quoted above.17. The French Memorandum does not encourage the hope that any reduction of French air forces is to be anticipated without further guarantees of &quot;security.&quot; On the contrary, the Memorandum states that French (&quot;Metropolitan&quot;) air programmes &quot;have already ceased to meet the new requirements of air defence,&quot; since they do not allow for civil aviation, which constitutes &quot; one of the most important &quot; elements in the problem of air security.18. It is possible, therefore, that the French will use the developments of German and Italian civil aviation as an excuse for demanding a still larger quota, of military aircraft.(The number of existing French Civil aircraft capable of rapid conversion to. use as heavy bombers is approximately 50, as against a corresponding figure of about 30 for British Civil aircraft.)19. Moreover, with regard to &quot; overseas &quot; forces, the Memorandum contem-plates that there will be &quot; fluctuations involving variations in the matter of armaments &quot; which &quot; cannot be foreseen,&quot; and states that, in the absence of air forces, &quot; still larger land forces &quot; would be required overseas. It would seem, therefore, that France does not intend to reduce, but rather to increase, her overseas air armaments, the non-military aspects of which are referred to.20. The reiterated French assertions as to the &quot;interdependence&quot; of armaments do not encourage the hope of any reductions in existing French air-armaments. We shall, it seems, in all probability be faced by a claim for further increases. The theory of &quot; interdependence &quot; of armaments may possibly result in the offer of some nominal reductions in land or sea armaments as compensation for air force increases. But as regards land armaments at any rate, the main-tenance of the conscription system must vitiate the effect of any &quot;reduction,&quot; and in no case would French land or sea reductions have much, if any, bearing upon our own minimum requirements in air armaments.21. In these circumstances, it would seem that, unless there is to be a radical change in the French outlook, the possibility of our being able to contemplate reductions in our own air forces is most improbable. Indeed, it appears that short of acquiescing in a position of permanent air inferiority involving the abandonment of anything like adequate air defences of London, it will be necessary for us to claim the right to carry out a substantial increase above the level of our present air forces. As to how far His Majesty&apos;s Government would be able, or would find it expedient actually to provide and to maintain such increased forces, involves political and financial considerations which are outside the scope of this paper.Conclusions.22. We have outlined briefly, and without giving more detail than was-necessary to explain clearly the position, the situation created by the French Memorandum as it appears to us. Put briefly, this memorandum represents an uncompromising declaration of the French policy that :  (a) French armaments have been reduced to the lowest point compatible with national safety in view of the present state of Europe and the world.(b) The Peace Treaties and the disarmament of the ex-enemy States must bemaintained.(c) If there is any relaxation of the Peace Treaties, France must increase herarmaments.(d) The only condition under which France would consent to further-reductions would be the revival of the Protocol of 1924.-   &apos;&quot;shb
85*1[6002]c23. It must be admitted that, unless some entirely unforeseen situation should arise between now and the Disarmament Conference, the attitude to be adopted by France is hardly calculated to facilitate the attainment of the objects of that Conference. She has the largest army and the largest Air Force in Europe and is planning a big naval construction programme; she still maintains, however, that no further reduction is possible without jeopardising her national security. But the size of these forces is based on a disarmed Germany with the threat that they would be inadequate if any relaxation of the Peace Treaties was permitted. Finally, France insists that she can only consent to further reductions in return for definite and specific guarantees of military assistance, a condition which seems to us to be incompatible with the objects of the Disarmament Conference, since the size of the forces which other countries would have to guarantee in order that France might make any really effective reductions might conceivably exceed those they have available at the present time. In other words, any reduction by France would be offset, at the best by other Powers being unable to reduce and at the worst by other Powers being faced with a definite increase in their forces. In these days of economic distress any such solution appears to us to be unthinkable, to say nothing of the financial relief it would afford to France at the expense of other countries.(Signed) G. F. MILNE.F. L. FIELD.J. M.  SALMOND.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1, September 24, 1931.

</content>
</cab>
