<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/223/0 images: 108-111</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS TEE PROPERTY 0? HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ CO vTDRnOPT) .&quot;d   &quot;u1    (tl216 (511.OA BIN E T.UNEMPLOYMENT INSUIRates of Benefit and Financial Position^ Memorandum by the Minister of Lab oar.(Circulated in accordance with Cabinet 51   (31), Conclusion 1, in substitution of CP.  215 (pi).1.    The Cabinet have asked to be furnished with a memorandum dealing with the suggestion that the rates of benefit   should be calculated to the nearest 3d to a 10 per cent.   cut.2.    An unemployed person may be entitled to one,  two, three, four,  five or six days&apos;  benefit in a given week. While,  therefore,  the rates of unemployment benefit mentioned in Statutes are weekly rates,  the Employment Exchanges necessarily y/ork on daily rates.    Ordinarily,  therefore,  the weekly rates must be multiples of oil,  so that the daily rates may be in exact pennies.3.    To have rates of benefit which are multiples of od would involve the Exchanges calculating in half-pennies,   though they would doubtless not pay in half-pennies.      Having regard to the burden on the Employment Exchanges,  this is very undesirable.      I should greatly prefer Scheme C. below -the nearest 6d,  but if the Cabinet are of opinion that,  in order to secure the consequent saving, Scheme D below, (the nearest 3d) must be adopted, I am prepared to accept it.Copy No.a1 \ -j\t rifr\
4. The following table shows -A. The present rates of benefit;B. The present rates reduced by an exact 10 per cent;Co The reduced rates rounded off tot he. nearest 6d., as in the previous memorandum.       ----&quot;------------D. The reduced, rates rounded off to the nearest 3d;,E. The reduced rates rounded up to the 3d., above.A.B.C,D.E.Present Present rates Reduced rates Reduced Reduced rates.     reduced by an   rounded off       rates       ratesexact &quot;10%, to the nearest rounded   roundedexcept child&apos;s Sd. allowance.off to up to the nearest    3d. aboveOO-.Man WomanOther classes :-Young man Young woman Juveniless ^	d.	s. dT&quot;	s . d.	s.	d. &quot;	s.	d.17/	-	15/3.6	15. S	15.	3k	15	615.	-	lo.    o	13. 6	13.	6.	13.	69.	-	8/1.2	3.   Oil	p	Oh	8.	3q	-	Ho change	no. change	No	change	No	cha14.	-	12/7.2	12. 6k	12.	6k	12.	912.	-	10/9.6	11.  0	10.	9k	11.	-9.		8/1.2	3. Oh	8.	Qsr	Q O *	w7.	5	6/9	7. 0	6 .	9	6.	96.	0	5/4.3	5. 6	5.	6	5.	6.5.	0	4. 6	4.  6	4.	S	4.	3k -in these  cases the cut is just slightly mere than ten per cent - compared with Column B.The savins which would be effected bv the various forms of cut shown above &amp;i?e as follows:-B. An exact 10 per cent cut(including children1 s. allowances .. . excluding -do- ...0.  10 per cent cut rounded off to the nearest . 6d. as in previous, memorandum ..........D. 10 per cent cut rounded off to the nearest 3d...............,.......E. 10 per cent cut rounded up to the3d. above.............................. 15,000,000  12,300,000 11,600,000 12,800,000 r---......1--- 11,000,000
O o 0 0II.    THE FINANCIAL POSITION.5, The Cahinet will desire to have before them a statementof the financial position of unemployment insurance next financial year.    Assuming a Live Register of 3 millions it will be approximately as follows:-Million  ,Benefit at existing rates 0 .0 . o&apos;.. .. ..., . o      I30o5Interest on debt at  115n,5C7A.(3jiiHli S &quot;t     3.    X O XX     Ooeoe*oooooeo**000s*floooo        _      (  *L^.&apos;_143.3Towards this sum Employers and Employed Persons&quot;would contribute at existing rates ........ ...____88.5___114 o 8Million  Economies:-Anomalies  (recent Act)  ........ 0 ..        3Needs tost for transitional benefit administered through the agency of PublicAssistance Authorities .0....oo.      102.0% cut In rates rounded off tothe nearest 3d.   (Col, D,  above).      12 a8 25 0889oIncreased contributions to lOd. (Employers ana EmployedLeaving to be found by Exchequer out oftaxation in 1932-3 7^
If the Cabinet decide to adopt some other cut, not that to the nearest 3d, the total of  79 millions will require to be adjusted accordingly.I!!&apos;  POSSIBLE gJRTHJBR ECONOMIES If, having regard to the very large charge on the Exchequer, the Cabinet desire to consider further economies, the following suggestions might be examinedAdditional saving to Exchequer,,A. (i). Alter the continuity rule so as toprovide that any four days of unemploy- Million  ,ment within any period of six days shall count for benefit: . Instead of any three days out of six as at present,,The effect of this would be that persons unemployed for three days as. well as persons unemployed for only one or two days in any six would not be entitled to benefit.      Incidentally, it is a method of dealing with short-time workers and casuals,      It is fairly easy for short time to be so arranged as to avoid the existing rule.      It would be more diffi-cult under this rule.(II). Reduce the 10 weeks bridge to 6 weeks.      The principal effect of this would be to prevent the linking up of periods of suspension of work at holidays so as to qualify the claimant fully for benefit at each holiday without a waiting week.This would save about .c   a   c   sB.    Increased contrib\itions of employersand employed persons to lid instead of 10d.G.    Alter the contribution qualification required for Transitional benefit from 8 contributions  in the last 2 years oy? 30 contributions at any time to 8 contributions in the last 2 years and 50 contributions at any time.The persons affected by such an amendment would,  if they required assistance, have to apply to the Public Assistance Authorities for it.The saving, additional to the saving by a Needs Test (say)  .(Intld. ) H.B.B.ministry of Labour, 2nd September,  1931.

</content>
</cab>
