<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/223/0 images: 119-134</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Ifgig DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP PUS BRIT britannic MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT),r PCOPY NO,2LAJLi.-5.IIL T-5--(1)    STERLING, AND THE GOLD STANDARD, (ti) HOV ENGLAND LlVfl-3..Note &quot;by the SecretaryeThe Prime Minister thinks his colleagues might he interested, to read the two enclosed. Memoranda entitled respectively &quot;Sterling and the Gold Standard&quot; and &quot;How England Lives&quot;, which have reached him from a well-known outside source,,(Signed) M.P.A. HANKEY, Secretary, Cabinet,12, Whitehall Gardens,  S,W.l, 3rd September, 1931,
STERLING- AND THE GOLD STANDARD.1) Stirling is of imnense iiaportance to world prosperity - on which our standard of life in turn depends.It would he difficult to devise a measure that would give a greater shock to the world&apos;s trade and credit than dex^arture of Britain from the Gold Standard.      Sterling holds a unique position among the world1s currencies.      It does so partly by virtue of tradition;    the Gold Standard was established by British influence and example;    its restoration in Europe after the war was due largely to Britain&apos;s lead.      And present practice rein-forces tradition;    London is the chief centre of international banking;    a large part of the payments which Europe makes to the rest of the world are made through London;    the Dominions are integrally linked with London;    and other countries entrust their surplus funds to London to use.      The news3 therefore,  that sterling no longer represented gold, that it was liable to the kind of fluctuations that marked the franc in 1926;  the mark in 1923 and the pound in 1920s would undermine confidence and check business not only in this country, but throughout the world.      And the world is in no condition to stand shocks to-day c 2) Countries have put a trust in us ^,y.hioh can only be betrayed with grave moral and economic.,reactipngo.The magnitude of the shock would be proportionate to the faith that other countries have reposed in England.      Deposits were entrusted to London, because they were withdrawable in gold; -if London now repudiates this obligation, what centre will any lender trust?      Other European countries accompanied Britain, hack to the Gold Standard;;    if Britain went off the Gold Standard,  they could not long stay on.      A few individuals might make a profit out of the ensuing uncertainty;    hut most traders and bankers would not know where they stood, and would contract their opera-tions until some stability had been restored, to sterling - a
process that would certainly take months.Immediate results,    there is no question of a small breach, with this country, remaining small,, with. ins ignif leant consequences -it is certain to spread at oncecThe first result of the announcement that London would not pay gold would he a collapse of the sterling exchanges.     Foreign holders of sterling deposits would try to withdraw them,  and of sterling securities to realise them.      On the Gold Standard, when the exchange falls below the point at which it is cheaper to trans-port gold, gold is taken out, and the knowledge that this can be done prevents any further fall In the exchange.      Once this check is removed,  there Is no limit to the effect which panic-stricken sales of sterling may have upon its exchange value.      Doubtless a point would be reached at which a counter-movement would set in, traders buying sterling with a view to the export of goods from England and financiers buying it in the hope that it would recover some of its lost value.      But this point would be far below the true vaLue of sterling, as represented by its purchasing power compared with that of other currencies;    until it was reached, the flight from the pound would continue;    and even when it was reached it would not &amp;34d the uncertainty attending all exchange transaction-tions.      For a time, therefore, the check to trade would continue, because no one would have any confidence in the stability of the world&apos;s most important currency.The main effects are dearer food and uncertainty in trade.Once the first shock was over,  the sterling exchanges might settle down at a new set of parities with other countries, corresponding with its comparative purchasing power over the commodities of commerce.      But before we consider the resulting situation, it is necessary to take some account of the losses and inconveniences already suffered.      Trade will have been checked, with ;onsequent increase in unemployment and trade losses all over the world.      Some stimulus will have been given to British exports
-    10 0since, when sterling depreciates, the price of British exports in other currencies is reduced;    hut little advantage could he taken of this so long as traders generally were uncertain of the future and holding off the market.      On the other hand, the cost of British imports in sterling would rise,  and, since the largest element in our imports is food-stuffs,  the cost of living would rise.The Government must soon suffer embarrassment.The Government1s finances would be involved in immediate difficulties;    revenue would fall off with the check to trade, expenses would go up with the increase of      employment, and the cost of financing the floating debt would be increased by the withdrawal of foreign balances from London.     lew borrowing for the time being would be impossible -The apparent advantages to exporters and others may be hard to attain and certainly hard to retainuAssume, however,  these immediate effects to be got over: suppose that the country is off the Gold Standard and the exchange have settled down at fairly stable figures;    the resulting situation may at first glance offer some attractions.    Since sterling is worth less in francs and dollars,- the British producer so long as his costs in sterling do not rise, can afford to take fewer francs, dollars or other currency for his exports, and may expect to see his foreign sales expand.    On the other hand, imports will cost more, for foreign suppliers will expect the same prices as before in their own currencies, and therefore higher prices In sterling.    This should tend to check imports, and, combined with the stimulus to exports,  to restore the balance between our payments to other countries and their payments to us. In another way the depreciation of sterling might assist world trade - by reducing the burden of the debtor countries, such as Australia, who have to make large sterling payments in interest and repayment of debt.This attradtive prospect may never be realised.    It assumes
that stability has been attained and a new value put upon the pound.    Unfortunately, anew and stable value in terms of other currencies cannot be given to the pound merely by severing its present connexion with gold.    It took six and a half years from the end of the war to give a stable value to  the pound after the last departure from the Gold Standard and the shock of a second departure would  intensify the difficulty of stabilisation.(7)    The Inevitable slide from gold by a. number of countries will make it impossible to retain advantage in a welter of new complications.In the second place, it is assumed that the rest of the world will &quot;stay put&quot;, while Britain re-values her currency, and thereby alters all her financial relections with the rest of the world.    It is impossible that this should happen.    Germany is at the moment struggling back to the Gold Standard with the aid of British credits;    if British currency suddenly slipped off the Gold Standard, it is in the last degree improbable that Germany could maintain her currency on the Gold Standard.    If Germany could not,  certainly Austria and Hungary would fail;    and,  if so large a block of Europe were off the Gold Standard again, it is improbable that the countries that have in the past benefitted their international trade position by devaluing their currency would see this benefit lost by sticking to the Gold Standard. Governments do not willingly depreciate their currencies; but the loss of trade to countries that had left the Gold Standard might make it increasingly difficult for the survivors to maintain the exchange values of their currencies.    Europe might be forced into a sort of Patch auction, in which each country sought to maintain its foreign trade against the competition of other countries off the Gold Standard by permitting a further depreciation of its own currency:;.
1 i\ 91 U 6(8)        Every trader.jyill add to the complicati one nf his business a gamble in excjg&amp;ges i-and if he insures against them it will be a new cost for hijnjbo-hear.Continual fluctuations in all the foreign exchanges would be inevitable.        Every trader in every country, engaged in foreign trade, would have a new factor of uncertainty to contend with.      No stable equilibrium of economic relations could be maintained against successive outbreaks of &quot;exchange-dumping&quot;. Insurance against exchange losses would add a new cost to industry The dislocation of trade involved must necessarily accentuate the prevailing depression and continue until the Gold Standard was restored.        All the sacrifices and labours, which were needed in the period 1919-1926 to restore stability to exchanges and to reforge the broken chain of normal peace-time commerce, would have to be gone through again. (9)        The advantages to exporters of forced or even uncertain devalue, tion must be offset by tariff policy abroad.The advocates of a departure from the Gold Standard do not anticipate these disorders,  or believe that they can be curtailed... It will be well, therefore, to go further,  and ask whether the benefits they anticipate from a depreciated currency are certain of realisation.      These benefits derive from the stimulus to exports and check to imports, that the depreciation of sterling is expected to bring about.      If trade were normal - if there had been no world war and there were now no world depression -the stimulus to exports would doubtless be effective.    But what y-   expansion to-day of British exports would occur simply as a result of a ten per cent,  depreciation of sterling?A large part of the decline in British exports is accounted for by the loss - permanent it is to be feared - due to the growth behind tariffs of competitive industry in former British markets.      Any reduction in price, which the British exporter
might be enabled, to effect, would, be promptly cancelled by a further measure of protection.      In other directions trade is held up, not by&apos;the comparative price of British products, but by the  inability of our former customers to increase their purchases at any price.      Especially is this the case with countries that were formerly good customers, because they were developing,  and are unable to buy now,  because they are unable to borrow for development;      in the conditions of world credit that would follow a revolution in British monetary policy, their chances of borrowing; and therefore of buying, would be further off than ever.        The prospects of expanding exports must, there-fore, be subjected to a large discount.Imports are less likely to be limited than to be bought at higher Prices.Equally limited are the possibilities of restricting imports.        The great bulk of British imports are food-stuffs and raw materials, the volume of which is only slightly responsive to price changes.      These imports could,  and would,  be maintained, even if their sterling cost were increased by ten or fifteen per cent.      If Imports are to be extensively restricted, some more definite and direct method of restriction will be necessary.      1. new balance of imports and exports could in time no doubt be attained by currency depreciation, but not a balance at which employment would be normal and the exchanges stable.) Certain important kinds of business that bring wealth to thewhoig com.mun.ity^nd^npt merely to a few proprietors would be lost or damaged.In so far as the new policy did stimulate the export trade,  it would simultaneously undermine other important sources of the national income.      Certain important economic activities of this country are based on the traditional faith of other countries in the pound.    The different forms of international
-104banking,  insurance,  the business associated with the-provision of * capital for other countries,  would all suffer,  if the pound lost its stability.    Acceptance business would be transferred to other countries;    the use of the surplus funds of other countries vrould be entrusted to other centres:    business at present done in sterling would be done in dollars.    Thus our &quot;invisible&quot; exports would be reduced by the loss of this business..    An even greater loss would be the fall in the value in other currencies of the interest payable to us  in sterling on our overseas investments. The expansion of exports and contraction of imports would have to be large to compensate for the losses in our account with therest of the world under these heads.I112) New industrial conflict through wage disputes would be encouraged -old difficulties would not be solvedaThe stimulus given to exports by depreciation of sterling was&apos;, it would be noticed,  dependent on the money costs of production in this country remaining at their present level,  or at any r ate rising less than the depreciation of the pound. Meanwhile the cost of imports, and therefore necessarily in the cost of living;, would raise.    Thus the stimulus to exports depends on a reduction in real wages and other costs;  deprecia-tion of currency is simply a method of reducing real incomeSo Once this was realised,  and a demand for compensating advances in money wages (and other incomes)  enforced, the advantages of depreciation in the field of international trade would be lost. The same advantage could be secured by a direct reduction of money rates of wages and other elements in costs,  with this additional advantage;  that a direct attack on the problem of high costs could discriminate between wage-rates that are already as low as can reasonably be expected and those which have not yet made any contribution to the reduction of costs.    British industry is full of anomalies - in wage-rates,  in trade customs, in productive organisation,  in commercial and financial relations -
due to the war and holding hack trade recovery.    Currency depreciation would leave all  these untouched.without the Cold Standard pol j-fti eal ^ inXlugnces^verv wh egepp-n work untold evils with prices and businsssoThe Gold Standard is not the arbitrary creation of a fen bankers,  thinking only of their profitsc    It is the outcome of the experience of many countries through many generations of experiment.    By basing its currency on gold, a country links its money to that of all other gold-using countries, and so contri-butes to  the maintenance of an international monetary system. This country, with its still vast foreign trade,  is of all countries the most keenly interested in the maintenance of the free movement of commerce,  of which an international monetary system is the first and essential condition.    Further, a country that has based its currency on gold has thereby excluded from the control of monetary supplies and the price-level the influence of indigent or extravagant Governments.    The financing of Government expenditure by Inflation cannot take place on the Gold Standard, because the resulting rise  in domestic prices above the world level leads  to a drain of gold, and a check to  the further inflation of credit.    Remove this check, and there is no limit -as the post-war experience of many countries showed - to the inflation of the currency and the rise in prices.    It is because Germany has experienced so recently die evils of inflation,  that the Government has been able to impose on the people sacrifices in the interest of financial stability so great - far in excess of any that have been asked of the people in this country..    Te flatter ourselves that we should never in this country permit inflation to go so far as to be dangerous.    Ye may be justified in this opinion of ourselves: but,  if we can pull ourselves up when we have left the Gold Standard, we can do so only by the exercise of precautions and sacrifices  that should make it unnecessary ever to forego the support of the Gold Standard?
HOj^ ENGLAND LIVESoEngland and Wales on an area of 58 s340 square miles supports a population of 40 millions.     The United States s with an area more than 50 times as great has only three times that population.     No European country, with the possible exception of Belgium, approaches England in its density of   population. It would be impossible to maintain these 40 millions at their present standard of life on the unaided resources of these 50 thousand square miles.     Much of the land is infertile;      the climate is not too favourable to the production of the staple food-stuffs.     Not half the present population could be fed with anything like the present adequacy if the resources of England were not supplemented by trade with other countries.No other country has so small a proportion of its population engaged in agriculture,      While Italy has 56;- of its occupied population. Prance 4ll;oj Germany 30^t 3 the United States 2.6% engaged in agriculture and fishings in the United Kingdom the proportion is under 7%*      On the other hands England has a higher proportion engaged in industry (nearly 40,0 as against 30)1 in the United States and 2Q% in France)  and a much higher propor-tion engaged in trade (14)i as compared with 10,&apos;a in France and the United States),       This small proportion engaged in agriculture is natural in a country of which the agricultural area is limited by nature.      It is a sign not of poverty but of riches,      \7e are able to get from other countries our food and raw materials in greater quantities and at lower prices than we could hope to produce them for ourselves;     while we concentrate our energies on manufactures trade and finance, which throughout the world yield a higher level of income than does agriculture.      It follows that it is only by the maintenance of a large export trade that England can maintain the higher standard of life which it &quot;enjoys compared with every other European Country.      If it is unable to maintain its trade, it will be forced back on to its own limited natural
resources,, and either the population will he forced to emigrate or the standard of life will have to he reduced.The actual proportion of British industry carried on for export is difficult to state,      In 1934^ the year of the last available   -census of production5 it was about 28/2.     The Macmillan Committee on Finance and Industry publishes estimates of the number of workers working for export.      It has declined in recent years;     but even in the present depression, it appears that one-third of all the workers engaged in the manufacturing industry and nearly a quarter of the whole occupied population are engaged in working for export,This proportion may strike many as being small, and as being insufficient to bean1 out the importance assigned to export trade above.      But the dependence of different industries on export markets varies;      in cotton three-quarterss in wool a half, in engineering end shipbuilding a half of production depends on export for its outlet.     And these industries are highly localised. Large areas, densely populated, depend on these industries and therefore on export.      The Clyde, Tyneside, Lancashire and the West Riding have had their economic life dislocated by the fall in exports that has taken place since the war and would be left derelict and dependent on the rest of the country if our exports disappeared.      The country^ dependence on export trade is not to be measured by the. proportion of the population working for export, but by the extent to which the whole economic organisation of the country is bound up with the prosperity of the export industries and the districts dependent upon them.     Even the most sheltered trades ere now feeling the effects of the decline in the demand for their products in the expert districts just mentioned.In time, no doubt, it may be possible to re-adjust our economic arrangements, to develop industries working for the home market to displace the industries at present working for export, and to lessen our dependence on export trade.     But this is not a change that    can be effected in a day - or in a year or a decade.
We cannot turn the idle looms of Blackburn into maziufaoturing  . loin cloths for the idle miners of South Wales instead of for Indians.    If we are to dispense with our present export industries we must scrap half the machinery in the cotton industry.,  one-third of that in the other textile industries,  and a varying proportion in all our other leading manufacturing industries. We must turn at least 2 million workers into the  streets, and be prepared to keep them until we have diverted Industry into now channels.    Doubtless,  we can live by taking in each other&apos;s washing; but we cannot live so well.    No country can live without export trade; even Russia is making the most prodigious efforts to increase its foreign trade; and England and Wales has founded its economic organisation, and built up its standard of life, more than any other country on export tradeoEven If it were practicable to cut ourselves off from the rest of the world, to restrict our- trade relations,  to cease to lend capital to other countries and to draw supplies from them,  it would be a reactionary policy to do so.    Trade links the world together in one economic community a-d is the chief safeguard of peace.    To divide the world up into congeries of mutually exclusive self-contained communities would be to invite international conflicts and war.Now export trade depends on being able to supply countries with what they want at a price that they can pay.    In other words, the demand of other countries imposes an external limit on the costs that this country can Incur in its industry if It is to maintain its exports.    If the level of our costs rises above that of competing countries and above the level at which other countries can afford to buy our products,  we  shall be able to sell less,  and, ultimately,  we must receive less from other countries.    This has been the experience In the last few years.    Our costs have been higher than those of other countries and our export trade has contracted.    Between 1913 and 1929, the quantity of British exports fell more from the pre-war level
&quot;     10 9than that of any other European country and our proportion of the world&apos;s total trade has steadily diminished.    The second result  of this,  a corresponding contraction in our imports, has not yet teen felt.    We have been saved by the misfortune of the agricultural countries which supply us with the bulk of our imports.    They have produced in excess of world demand, with the result that the value of their produce has fallen disproportion-ately and we are getting our food-stuffs and raw materials at prices below the costs of production.    This state of things cannot, however? persist; the ruin which is overtaking these agricultural countries Is re-acting on their ability to buy our exports.Even with the fall In the price of our imports, however, we are now unable to pay for them.    Normally, this country has a surplus when account is taken of all our exports (services as well as commodities),  and this surplus is invested abroad, bringing in additional Income in the future.    last year, this surplus fell, according to the Board of Trade calculations,  to  39 millions,  and in the present year there will be no surplus. We continue to import increasing quantities, with the result that every month our Imports exceed out exports by  30 millions in value,  and the receipts from shipping,  from overseas investments and other sources, which normally more than bridge this gap, have fallen and will no longer bridge it.Here is the explanation of the financial difficultiesin which the country has found itself in the last few months.Because its exports will not pay for its imports,  its money(sterling) has depreciated by comparison with the money of othercountries.    Because our imports are bigger than our exports,more people are selling sterling (which they have received forour Imports) than are buying sterling (in order to pay for our exports).    When sterling falls below/ a certain point,  it pays to take out any money that the foreigner is entitled to in gold, We have only a limited amount of gold; w;hen this goes, the
iludepreciation of sterling will be unchecked..    At present, a pound-Iis the equivalent of 4.86 dollars,  124 francs or 20 marks.    If weIare unable to meet the demands on us for gold, and our imports continue   f to exceed our exports, the pound may drop until it is worth only 4 4 dollars or 10-0 franee or 15 marks.Consider what will be the effects of this drop in the value of the pound.      Other countries would still want the same number of dollars or francs or marks for the goods we buy from them; we should therefore have to give more pounds for them.    Since the cost to us would be so much higher, we should probably buy less and that would be the corrective of our unbalanced trade.ITemporarily, however, we could balance our accounts with other! countries by &quot;sorrowing from them.  To do so, we should have to satisfy the lenders that they would get their money back.    Here is the point at which the influence of the national finances makes itself felt.    If other countries from whom we might wish to borrow think that bur Government is exceeding its income,  they will anticipate that  the gap between revenue and expenditure will be met by inflation, that prices will rise,  that sterling exchanges will fall, that we shall be forceditoff the Gold Standard, and that they will be unable to recover their loans.    The mere threat that the budget may be unbalanced at the end of the year has already provoked a drain of funds from London which intensifies the difficulty of maintaining the exchange value of the pound, and makes more urgent the necessity of steps to support it. A country whose exports will not pay for Its imports and whose national H finances are under suspicion cannot even borrow temporarily, except on   m terms that English self-respect would not tolerate.failIf we let the Gold Standard go, as is indicated above, sooner j-. or later a balance would be established in our international accounts - I by the painful but inevitable process of restricting the amount of goods we get from other countries and increasing the amount we supply to them.    Our costs would be reduced in terms of dollar s or francs or other gold currencies by the reduction in
bill the gold value of the pounds, shillings and pence paid by English manufacturer5s in wages,  interest  charges and other costs.      But &quot;before this balance was attained,  there would inevitably be a long period of confusion with the exchange jumping about and no one knowing what way prices were going to go;  a new element of uncertainly would be introduced into world trade which would lead to a further check to any attempts at recovery;  and the actual reduction in the value of the pound,  and the consequent increase in the cost to us of everything we import,  would, for the time, be far greater than would be justified by the difference between our costs and costs of production in other  countries.One further point.    We have large resources in the form of overseas investments commonly estimated at  4,000 million. Why not use these to maintain our exchange and meet the cost of the excess of our imports?    It may be noted that the present value of these overseas investments has very much shrunk;  it is probably not more than two-thirds of their nominal value, and would shrink much further if anything like a forced sale were attempted.    As security for the loans, however,  these investments could no doubt be used if we took only a short and superficial view of the economic advance of the country.    The use of these investments as security for the loans would be no permanent relief if we continued to draw more from abroad than we can pay for with pur exports.    We are at the moment living on capital., and even the large accumulations we have invested abroad will not last for ever if we continue to live on capital.      The only permanent remedy Is to live within our income, wither by increasing our exports or by reducing our expenditure.,    Hor would it be easy to mobilise these securities immediately.      During the war it was possible to adept this expedient because the war was recognised as an emergency which had to be met by abnormal devices,  and the owners of these securities were united in the support of the Government.    Today, we are at peace, and the owners of these overseas investments might very well object to handing them over
1 .. in support of a policy which they believe to he fundamentally, unsound and which they believe would render their support unavailing in the long ruru,     The largest holdings of foreign securities are in the hands of investment trust and insurance companies, whose directors are in the position of&quot;trustees for their shareholders and policy holders*      They might well hesitate to exchange- sound foreign securities for English securities which they believe to be less sound as an alternative to adopting measures which would restore soundness to English securities? If compulsion were adopted the immediate and most important effect would be to promote a flight from the pound, in other words5 to intensify the momentary difficulties of the situation by increasing the strain upon sterling.      In the long run the policy would deter future investment in British securities and he a signal to investors at home and abroad to transfer their holdings to some financial centre outside British control-If, therefore, we wish to maintain and to improve the standard of life of our populations we can do so only by maintaining the efficiency of our export trader      Ve can. piotect sterling by a temporary loan but we should use the respite given by this lean to restore the balance between what we sell and what we buy.      Cur export trade is our chief link with the rest of the world.      If It languishess that Is a sign that our costs are too high;      in other words s that we are talcing out of industry more than we  ire putting into it?     We are living beyond our income and the distress which already has overtaken our export industries must inevitably extend to the whole of our industry unless we live within our income. &quot;7   R     1

</content>
</cab>
