<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/223/0 images: 181-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C A B I N E T.SECRET / CPC3^4(31). &apos; copy N0&apos;  / 0FUTURE AIRSHIP POLICY.Note by the Secretary of State for Air.1. I circulate this brief note to prevent any possible misunderstanding as to the precise nature of my proposals in regard to future airship policy, since the terms of the Cabinet&apos;s decision of August 31st (Cabinet 49 (31), Item No. 8) might conceivably be misconstrued, having regard to the fact that the alternative more modest policy which we are now constrained to adopt was, from the very circumstances of the case, not explained in any detail in the debate which took place on the 14th May in the House of Commons. 2. The only possible obscurity is in connectionwith the future of the airship bases at Cardington and overseas.     What I propose is to adopt the second of the two alternative policies which I placed before the Cabinet in paragraph 12 (b) of CP. 94 (31), an earlier paragraph of which meiaorandum contained the following recommendations applicable to either policy :-&quot;...  (c) that Cardington and the Royal Airship Works shall not be disposed of. (d) that the bases overseas at Israailia andKarachi shall also be retained and kept in being on the most economical * care and maintenance&apos; basis possible.&quot; I may add that Sir George May in his letter to the Chancellor of the Exchequer of the 8th May, 1931, printed as Appendix II to the Report of the Committee on National Expenditure    (pp. 280-2),    whilstThis Document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government), Roneographed for the Cabinet.     September, 1951.
r2.recommending the scrapping of the R.100 (which recommendation will now he given effect), was also prepared to accept theretention of Cardington for a period of three years.3.This second alternative policy was estimated in cp. 94 (31)  to cost  20,000 in 1932,  as against  130,000 if the R.100 was retained and refitted.    It is on this basis that the Air Ministry&apos;s recent estimates of savings have been prepared,  i.e. it has been assumed that  110,000 will be saved in 1932 by the reversal of the decision taken last May.4. In the absence of directions to the contrary,  Ishall assume that the above represents the Cabinet&apos;s intention, i.e. that Cardington and the overseas bases are to be retained for the time being on a minimum &apos;care and maintenance&apos; basis and not disposed of.5. There is one further point on which I should be glad to receive guidance, and that is as to the manner in which an announcement of the new policy should be made.    There appear to be three alternative courses(a) the Air Ministry could issue a formal communiqueforthwith briefly outlining the decision;(b) a question could be arranged in the Lords or Commons,which could be dealt with on the lines of the draft annexed to this note;(c) the Chancellor might make brief mention of the matter in his speech outlining the various measures of economy upon which His Majesty&apos;s Government have decided.My own preference is for course (c), but, if this does not commend itself to the Cabinet, I am disposed to arrange for course  (b) , since the original decision which is now being reversed was taken by Parliament after a full debate in the Commons. Mr Ministry, September 8th, 1931. A.
DRAFT QUESTION AND ANSWER ON AIRSHIP POLICY.Question.To ask the Secretary of State for Air whether, in view of the paramount need for effecting all possible reductions in public expenditure, His Majesty:s Government intend to reconsider the policy as regards future airship development decided on last May.Answer.In view of the state of the national finances, His Maiesty&apos;s Government have reluotantly decided that expenditure on airship development must be drastically curtailed.    The R.100 will accordingly not be refitted, as has hitherto been proposed, but will be disposed of.        Cardington and the airship bases overseas will be rediiced as early as possible to a minimum &apos; oare and maintenance 1 basis.,, their ultimate future being left for subsequent consideration. A small section will be retained under the Air Ministry to watch progress in and maintain liaison with the U.S.A. and Germany.This decision will effect a saving of  110,000 in 1932, the oost of the reduced scheme being estimated at  20,000, instead of  130,000.

</content>
</cab>
