<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/223/0 images: 307-309</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the property of His Britannic Majesty1 s Government Boneographed for the Cabinet.     September, 1951.CABINET.SECRET. n s?C.P.237 (31). Gopy NO. 5THE ROYAL AIR FORCE AND CUTS IN THE FAY &quot;OF THE FIGHTING SERVICES.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.1. I am glad to say that the position in the Royal AirForce still remains that, as the Cabinet were notified yesterday, there have so far been no reports of untoward incidents following on the recent announcement of outs in pay, though certain written representations have been received on the subject.2. I should, however, be failing in my duty if I did notwarn my colleagues that the naval incidents may produce reactions. In particular, if as a result of these incidents the decision to place those at present enjoying 1919 rates on 1925 rates with effeot from October 1st is substantially modified, we shall be fortunate indeed if we escape trouble in the Royal Air Force, unless I am in a position to announce without delay that similar concessions will be made to airmen.3. For if a considerably higher proportion of naval ratings are affected, the actual cuts in Royal Air Force pay are in a number of instances as heavy as in the case of the Navy. For example, there are several ranks which will lose as much as, or more than, 25$.     Moreover, the principle which has been applied to both services is identical, so that any departure from it in the one case must involve a corresponding departure in the other.4. I have throughout been aware that the universalapplication of 1925 rates must entail some degree of temporary hardship in certain categories.     But it is essential, to bear in mind, as the Admiralty statement issued this morning brings out very clearly, that pay is only one element in the remuneration of
&amp; 3 dsailors, soldiers and airmen, who, in many cases, receive various other emoluments in cash and are also clothed, housed and fed at the public expense.     Expressed, therefore, as a percentage of total emoluments, instead of pay only, the cuts would be very much smaller.Accordingly, the Cabinet having once decided that &quot;vested rights&quot; must, in prevailing circumstances, go by the board, my advisers and I have felt that, though some cases of temporary hardship are unavoidable, there is nothing intrinsically inequitable in the broad decision to apply 1925 rates throughout. It ia indeed important to feear in mind that the May Committee recommended this course on a &quot;fair wages&quot; and not a &quot;sacrifice&quot; basis.     Any substantial modification of that decision is therefore, in my view, most strongly to be deprecated as likely to reopen the whole question of the adequacy of the 1925 rates.A large number of personnel have already been in receipt of these rates for years past.     They must, in consequence, f be presumed to be adequate.     Moreover, as was pointed out in the Air Ministry Orders promulgating the &quot;cuts&quot;, the cost of living index figure has fallen from 173 to 145 since the revised rates were introduced six years ago.Further, as was also pointed out in the same Orders (which cited the actual index figures), if comparison be made with 1919 instead of 1925, -the cost of living has fallen by approximately 33 per cent.     In no oase in actual practice will the &quot;cuts&quot; attain this full percentage even of pay, whereas, as explained in paragraph 4 above, it ie on total emoluments and not pay only that the calculation should be made.I may perhaps also draw attention to the fact that, if   , we go outside the fighting services and take, as a rough andi fready parallel to the lower ranks, the &quot;manipulative&quot; grades in  / the Civil Service (which comprise some 180,000 individuals), there has been a reduction since 1921 in the average rate of total
* The Report of the Committee on National Expenditure gives(p. 32)  a figure of 38.4 per cent on a basis of a oost of living figure of 55 above pre-war.     The current figure on which remuneration is based is only 50 per cent above pre-war.t Officers&apos; pay (20 per cent of which is subject to variation with the cost of living) is, of course, a much larger element in their total emoluments than the pay of other ranks.remuneration of these latter of no less than   40 per cent * But the severity of this reduction has been mitigated by the fact that it has been effected gradually.Indeed, the fons et origo of the present trouble is the suddenness of the drop, owing to the concession made in 1925 in accordance with long established precedent as regards retention of the 1919 rates, and also to there being no provision in the case of the other ranks of the fighting services for adjustments of pay (as opposed to allowances)f in aocordance with the cost of living.     In short, as so often happens (and is the case also with the teaohers), the enjoyment of an exceptionally privileged position for a period of years has become a ground-for grievance, when it is proposed to withdraw the privilege and bring those concerned into line with their fellows and other and less fortunate sections of the community. 7. If it is now decided to effect adjustments to relievehardships - and, as I have pointed out in paragraphs 2 and 3 above, if adjustments are made in the case of the Navy they will be inevitable, in varying degrees, in the other services - I regard it as essential that these fundamental considerations should be borne prominently in mind.A.AIR MINISTRY. September 17th, 1931.

</content>
</cab>
