<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/223/0 images: 310-312</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE   PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYrS GOVERNMENT.258 (51).COPY NO.cabinet.IMPORTATION OF FORSIGN GOODS. Note by the President of the Board of Trade.I circulate to my colleagues the attached copy of a letter which I have received from the Federation of British Industries.P.C.L.Board of Trade,19th September, 1931.
OPY.FEDERATION OP BRITISH INDUSTRIES.21, Tothill Street, London.   S.F.1, 18th September, 1931.To the Rt. Hon. Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister, G.B.J3., M.C., M.P., The Board of Trade,Great George Street,    S.W.1.Sir,I was desired by the Fiscal Policy Committee of the Federation of British Industries to transmit to you the following Resolution which was passed at their meeting to-day&quot;The Fiscal Policy Committee of the Federation of British Industries, at the meeting held to-day, received&apos; from its members (representing a wide j*ange of industries) a grave report as to the growing influx of imports of which they had knowledge.The Committee further received the most disturbing information gathered from foreign producing centres of the declared intention of foreign producers to accelerate their exports to this country under present conditions.The Committee desires to make the most urgent representations that, in view of this state of affairs, it &apos; is imperative that immediate action be taken for controlling imports by some effective means.     Otherwise the accumulation of stocks of imported gooda will be such as to defeat the object of any future control of imports until such stocks have been absorbed, and this, owing to the reduced spending power of the country, will take place only over an abnormally long period of time.The Committee is of opinion that the position is so serious as to be calculated seriously to undermine the position of many British industries unless prompt and effective action is taken,&quot;
This Resolution is the result of full consideration &quot;by a Committee representing the trade organisations of all the principal industries of the country.The normal procedure of this Committee would have been to report to the Grand Council of the Federation, who would in due course no doubt have transmitted this Resolution to you.     So grave a view, however, did the Committee take of the situation and of its urgency that they decided that they could not take the responsibility of delaying the submission of these representations to His Majesty&apos;s Government.I am,Sir,Your obedient Servant, (Signed) ROLAND NUGENT.Director.

</content>
</cab>
