<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/223/0 images: 314-320</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYfS GOVERNMENT.CRETc C OPY NO ,^_^P.240(31) CABINET.STATE OF TRADE - AUGUST,   1951.Note by the President of the Board of Trade.I circulate a note prepared in the Board of Trade summarising the trade reports received from members of the Board of Trade Advisory Council,P..C-L,BOARD OF TRADEj22nd September,  1031,
STATE OF TRADE - AUGUST.1951. (From reports submitted by the Board of Trade Advisory Council).In a financial situation which changes so rapidly appreciations given one week are out of date the next;   but the following view expressed by Hr. A.R. 17a g is worth quoting:-.&quot;Financial experts .  . are not only anxious to see the Establishment of Budgetary equilibrium but are concerned with &apos;the possibility of unstable sterling exchange,  due to the Unfavourable balance of payments.      According to the statistics &apos;of the Board of Trade and the Midland BanK, from 1924 to 1930 &quot;the United Kingdom has lent abroad  242,000,000 in excess of its favourable balance of pasnaents.     These figures are naturally &quot;estimates, but the broad contention is borne out by the fact &quot;that during this period London interest rates have averaged l?i &quot;above those of New York, and yet the Bank of England has not &apos;been able to increase its gold holding permanently.     Further-&apos;more,  there is no doubt that durin  the present year this country &apos;will have an unfavourable balance of payments, notwithstanding * that there has been a minimum of foreign lending.      It would, &quot;therefore, ap&quot;pear essential, once Budgetary equilibrium is &quot;established to ensure a long period of stable Government, while &quot;this grave problem is attacked&quot;.The numbers of unemployed at the end of August show an increase of 49,100 compared with the figure at the end of July, but the increase in those wholly une-a cloyed (100,000; was considerably greater, those temporarily stopped having decreased by 51,000.     G-eographically there were increases in all districts except the North-Eastern.After the appreciable improvement in the export trade for July the decline in August is disappointing though it may in part be seasonal.      The actual figure,  just over  29,000,000,  is
the lowest since April,  1909, except for the early days of the War.     Imports were also down to a figure lower than any since 1914;    the adverse &quot;balance of visible trade for August was about  32,000,000 as compared with  31,000,000 in August, 1930 (and also in July 1951).There was a decrease of 8.15 per cent,  in railway traffic receipts in August, compared with last year, and the freight figures for August for three railways (also compared with a year ago) show percentage falls in tonnage of 13.6 per cent, for coal and cose,  17.3 per cent, for heavy goods,  and 12 per cent, for general merchandise.     For the first six months of the year fov all four railways, freight traffic was lees by 22,600,000 tons or 14.2 per cent.,  including a fall of 11.9 per cent, in coal and coke,  and very heavy declines in all iron and steel.The output of coal showed the usual improvement after the August holidays but it was substantially below the output for the corresponding period of last year;    the number of persons employed, moreover, was as low as 821,000 (for the week ended August 29th) the unemployment percentage being 30.9?$.      Exports for August were down to 3,227,000 tons as compared with 3,533,000 tons in July last and 3,934,000 tons in August,  1930.In the iron and steel industry demand in August was lower than for many years and British production was the lowest since the war,  apart from periods of coal stoppage.     Six blast furnaces were blown out during the month and only one furnace is now in operation in the whole of Scotland.     Employment declined and exports and imports were both lower in August than in the last few months.     Imports, however, amounted to 202,000 tons against exports of 144,000 tons.     There are few signs of improvement abroad, Canada being the only moderately active market, Continental prices were again substantially reduced in August.
Employment declined in the shipbuilding industry in August but there was an unexpected revival in shipbuilding orders, including one for a passenger steamer from the L.M.S. Railway and one, from a British firm, for four 9,000 tonners.     On the other hand the amount of laid-up tonnage has not diminished and the unfavourable conditions of the shipping trade show little change.     Owing to the restriction in coal exports and the low rates for freight, tonnage is going out in ballast to an increasing extent.     There has been good business homeward from the Argentine and an increase in chartering from the Black Sea. Most of the latter however has gone to foreign charterers.New engineering orders reported include one for the armament for twelve new ships for the Portuguese Navy valued at  750,000 and one for boilers for the Victoria Palls Power Company of about  500,000, but the volume of new business is low and unemployment in the industry rose to 28.4$ for general engineering compared with 18.5$ at the end of August last year. Unemployment in marine engineering on August 24th was 44,2jb compared with 19.5?? last year.The reports from the motor industry are good compared with other industries.      The volume of home business in new cars is stated to be about 20$ - 25% below last year but 95$ of home requirements are now being met by British factories and the demand for British small cars is well maintained.      In export markets American stocks are still being liquidated but this country is obtaining a good share of the new business,  in Australia and New Zealand from 50?/. - 60$ of the imports.The report for the electrical industry points out that the industry has been largely supported during the last two years by the Grid Schemes and that when these come to an end the position will be serious.      Some sections unaffected by the Grid are already in a bad way but domestic appliances are selling well.      It is complained that a large amount of foreign material is being used in housing schemes and that telephone cable business
placed by the Post Office has been very disappointing.In addition to other depressing influences, the cotton industry hac had to contend with further falls in prices of raw material, levels being reached lover than any since the beginning of the century.     Employment declined and order books are stated to be lighter than they have been in any month this year.     It may be noted that although the quantity of cotton piece goods exported is well below last year&apos;3 figure, the exports of cotton yarns for the last two months have exceeded those for the same period last year,     It is reported that Japanese cotton mills have recently reduced their costs by 50%,  17 - 20% being due to reductions in wages.     In the overseas markets, the only encouraging reports received have been a better demand for fancy cottons from China, and a better demand from Greece and Colombia.     Russian competition is reported to be decreasing in Persia, but increasing in Egypt.The woollen industry has been unusually quiet, with a downward tendency,     Employment declined and the July improvement in exports of both yarns and tissues has not been maintained.    The representative of the woollen and worsted industry draws attention to the fact that taking the first 8 months exports have fallen from 111 million square yards in 1929 to 59 million square yards this year, while imports have risen from 26 million square yards to 30 million square yards 1     Abundant supplies of the raw material are expected from the new clip, and existing stocks are fairly large.     It is stated that at the opening sales in Australia, demand was strong from Japan, who was the largest buyer of wool from Australia last season.The Reports from other industries do not indicate muchchange, though that from the chemical industry records anincrease in the sales of all dyestuffs and considerable ordersfor fertilisers.     In the rubber and hosiery industries,conditions are depressed, and foreign competition is complained of.     Employment declined in the building industry anddistributive trades.     There has been some slight seasonalimprovement in the boot and shoe industry.-4-
The price of wheat remained fairly stationary during August; it was freely shipped from Australia during the month, but most of the tonnage from the Argentine was taken up ^ith the marketing of the heavy maize crop.     It is stated that the United Kingdom appears likely to be the only large importer of   United States wheat, and that Canada is holding out for a price above the relative   value compared with Russian wheat.     The new crop in Canada is not heavy, but of good quality, and from Russia good supplies are available of variable quality.     In the argentine the area under wheat for the new crop is reported to have been reduced by 20$,The Co-Operative Wholesale Society reports a decline in receipts for August of 12.6$ compared with last year, but substantial increases in the quantity sold of several important foodstuffs,  the only important decrease being in tea.     The Society also reports that an examination&quot; of the prices of seven principal grocery commodities shows that comparing the first eight months of 1930 and 1931 wholesale prices have decreased by 19.95$ and retail prices by 18.79$.      Reports received from departmental stores, multiple shops and the Co-operative Societies indicate that in July, the latest date for which figures are available, the sales as compared with a year previously decreased in value by 4.3 per cent, or about the same as the decrease for the half year February to July.     For Germany the reductions for the same periods are 16 percent, and 12.1 per cent., while for the United States the reduction for both July and the half year is 8 per cent.      In volume the sales in the United Kingdom were probably somewhat greater than in 1930.,Difficult financial, economic and in some cases, political conditions in all the important South American Countries are still causing restriction of imports.     Trade returns of British Colonies continue to record heavy decreases in the value of exports and, especially, imports this year compared with last year.
The Australian Government report that following the signature of the Australian - Canadian Treaty a &quot;Goodv;illM ship was dispatched to Canada with an assorted cargo of Australia products with a   view to encouraging trade.Board of Trade,September,  1931.

</content>
</cab>
