<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/223/0 images: 347-352</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S PXJCUMHNT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.CRETo Copy No,ORDER IN COUNCIL RELATING TO RATES OFlp. 245(51)UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE CONTRIBUTIONS AND BENEFIT. Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.There is circulated herewith, for the approval of the Cabinet, a draft of the Order in Council to be made under the Economy Act altering the rates of unemployment insurance contributions and benefit.      The increased rates of contribution and the reduced rate of benefit are set out in the Schedules and are in accordance with these specified in the White Paper on the Economy Bill,  Cmd.3952.These changes represent about  450,000 a week in reduced expenditure and additional revenue and&quot;it is essential to make them effective from the earliest possible moment.      The increased contr^butlens must operate from a Monday,  (the beginning of a contribution week)  and the reduced benefit from a Thursday,  (thebeginning of a benefit week).      Monday,  5th October,  is proposed for the increased contributions and Thursday,  8th October for thew*......reduced benefit.      In order that this may be possible,  the Order in Council must be made not later than 2nd October.  /A separate Order in Council will be required in order to limit insurance benefit to 26 weeks, in the benefit year end to apply a &quot;needs&quot;test,  through the machinery of Public Assistance Authorities, to transitional payments.     The drafting of these provisions needs special care,  and further confidential consultation with representatives of Local Authorities as to details will be necessary.      I hope, however,  to be able to circulate a draft before the end of next week.     The delay will not affect the savings from these provisions,  since the necessary arrangements for applying the Public Assistance /machinery
machinery cannot very well be completed before the beginning  of November and the provisions in question cannot therefore begin to produce any savings before that date.I ask the Cabinet to approve the making of an Order in Council immediately upon the passing of the Economy bill  the Order to be in the terms of the attached draft subject to any  minor      and drafting amendments that may with Treasury concurrence be found to be necessary.(Intld,)  Ho B.26th September, 1931.
Strictly Confidential.DRAFT STATUTORY RULES AND ORDERS. 1931, No.unemployment insurance.National Economy.Order in Council made under the National Economy Act, 1931, with respect to unemployment insurance.At the Court at the day of ,1931.Present,The King&apos;s Most Excellent Majesty in Council.Whereas by the National Economy Act, 1931, it is enacted that during the period of one month after the commencement of that Act, that is to say, the day of , 1931,His Majesty may, in respect of certain services, including Unem-ployment Insurance, make such Orders in Council as appear to him to be expedient for the purposes of effecting economies in the expenditure falling to be defrayed out of the Consolidated Fund, out of moneys provided by Parliament, or out of any fund estab-lished by the enactments relating to any of the said services, and of effecting improvements in the arrangements for meeting such expenditure :And whereas it is enacted by the said Act that any such Order may, among other things, make provision for increasing the con-tributions to be made to the unemployment fund and for the modifi-cation of statutory rights subsisting at the date when the provisions of the Order take effect;And whereas it is expedient for the purposes aforesaid that the provisions hereinafter contained shall have effect;Now, therefore, His Majesty, by virtue of the enactments herein-before recited and of all other powers enabling him in that behalf, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered as follows : 1. As from and after the 5th day of October, 1931, until Kates of the expiration of the extended period the contributions payable j^&quot;bu&quot; under the Acts by employed persons and their employers shall be
2Rates of unemplov-ment benefit.Interpreta-tion.Short title, commenee-ment and extent.at the respective rates set out in the First Schedule to this Order, and accordingly in paragraph (a) of subsection (1) of section four of the Act of 1925 a reference to that Schedule shall be substituted for the reference to the First Schedule to the Act of 1925, and the last-mentioned Schedule and section two of the Act of 1927, (ex-cept in so far as it relates to the meaning of the expression &quot; young men and young women &quot;), and the First Schedule to that Act shall be repealed.2. The following provisions shall have effect as from and after the 8th day of October, 1931, with respect to the rates of benefit under the Acts (a) Subsection (1) of section four of the Act of 1927 shall haveeffect as if the Second Schedule to this Order was sub-stituted for the Third Schedule to that Act, and the last-mentioned Schedule and subsection (1) of section two of the Act of 1930 and the First Schedule to that Act shall be repealed :(b) In subsection (2) of section two of the Act of 1930, (which relates to the increase in the weekly rate of benefit in respect of dependants), for the words &quot; nine shillings,&quot; wherever those words occur, there shall be substituted the words &quot; eight shillings.&quot;3.-(1) In this Order the following expressions have the mean-ings hereby assigned to them &quot; The Acts &quot; means the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1931 :&quot; The Act of 1925,&quot; &quot; the Act of 1927 &quot; and &quot; the Act of 1930 &quot; mean respectively the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1925, the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1927, and the Unem-ployment Insurance Act, 1930 :&apos;&apos; Benefit &apos;&apos; means unemployment benefit : &apos;&apos; Extended period &apos;&apos; has the same meaning as in subsection (1) of section four of the Act of 1925 :&quot; Young men &quot; and &quot; young women &quot; have the same mean-ings as in the Act of 1927. (2) This Order and the Acts shall be construed together, and any reference in any Act or other document to the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1931, or to the enactments relating to unemployment insurance, shall be deemed to include a reference to this Order.(3) The Interpretation Act, 1889, applies in relation to this Order as it applies in relation to an Act of Parliament.4. (1) This Order may be cited as the Unemployment Insurance (National Economy) (No. 1) Order, 1931, and shall come into opera-tion immediately.(2) This Order shall not extend to Northern Ireland.
3FIRST SCHEDULE. Rate of Contributions by Employed Persons and Employers.Ordinary Hates.From the employed person for each week  d.In the case of men       ...      ...      ... ...      ...      ... 10In the case of women ...      ...      ... ...      ...      ... 9From the employer for eadh week In the case of employed persons being men        ...       ... 10In the case of employed persons being women    ...       ... 9Hates in respect of young persons.From the employed person for each week In the case of young men    ...      ...      ...      ... ... 9In the case of young women   ...       ...       ...       ... ... 8From the employer for each week In the case of employed persons being young men ... 9In the case of employed persons being young women ... 8Hates in case of persons under eighteen.From the employed person for each week In the case of boy6       ...      ...      ...      ... ...      ... 5In the case of girls      ...      ...      ...      ... ...      ... 44From the employer for eadh week In the case of employed persons being boys ...       ... 5In the case of employed persons being girls ...       ... 4115   3SECOND SCHEDULE. Weekly Rates of Unemployment Benefit.Rate of class of persons to whom rate applies benefit.1. Persons of the age of 21 years and upwards  s.   dMen........................Women       ...      ...      ......      ... ...        132. Persons who have attained the age of 18 years but are under the age of 21 years  Young men ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 12   6Young women      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 10   93. Persons who have attained the age of 17 years but are under the age of 18 years  BoysGirls ..................... 6   94. Persons who are under the age of 17 years -BoysGirls ...      ...      ...05 6 4   6Vfcte.-If the total amount payable to any person includes a fraction of a penfiy, that fraction shall bo treated as a complete penny.(2107-HO)  Wt, 1-P5  12,18,12, 35,45, 75  9/31  P. St.  U. 327
UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE, (No. 1).NATIONAL ECONOMY.cclxvii (5).26th September, 1931.

</content>
</cab>
