<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/35/33 images: 230-233</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
!Prv00d ^ September 1943.SECRET.YiM. X43)123rd Conclusions.So-50WAR; CABINET 123 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, &amp;th September, 1943, at 1% noon.Present:.   .The Right Hon. Anthony  gen, M.P:, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador to theUnited States of America.The following were also- present:The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,Maj&amp;i First Lord of the Admiralty,Sir Orme Sargent, Deputy Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Vice-Admiral Sir Neville Syfret,Vice-Chief of Naval Staff,&quot;The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.Lieutenant-General A. E. Nye, Vice-Chief of the Imperial General Staff,Secretariat :Sir Edwarmf Bridges.Brigadier L. C. HolIis.No.1,2 &apos;3I 4 &apos;5Contents.SubjectsChemical Warfare     .....Anglo-Soviet-American RelationsItaly    ....      Italy   ....     ....      ...Politico-Military &quot;Commission.Operation &quot;Starkey &quot; ....      ....Pageif.;12m[26054-1]
(previous reference:W.M.:(43)57thConclusions,&apos;Minute 2.)1. The War Cabinet had a discussion on. this matter, whichis recorded - in Hthe Secr^ary^ Statidard * File A of War cabinet conclusions.finglo-Soviet- morioan(PreviousReferenceMinute 3.)2. The War Cabinet had before them the text of the telegramsdespatched by the Prime Minister and President Roosevelt to premier Stalin in regard to this Conference (Welfare Nos. 618and 614).The latter telegram stated that President Roosevelt thoughtW.M. (43) 122nd that, while he would wish to send Mr, Hull to the Conference, he conclusions, did not believe that the latter should make such a long journey, andthat he proposed to send Mr. Welles and Mr. Harriman. president roosevelt also said that, while he was willing that his representa-tive should come to London, or somewhere in England, he was inclined to suggest Casablanca or Tunis.    .In discussion in the War Cabinet, the view was expressed that,as it had been agreed that this Conference should be on the foreign secretary level,, the proposals for American representation might cause some disappointment to the Russians. Great importance was attached to the success of this meeting, and it was felt that it mightX &quot; I be worth while to suggest a change in the venue in order to ensurethat the meeting was attended by representatives of all three countries who could speak with authority and with the power toreach decisions. It would be better that the Conference should beheld in Washington or, say, in Bermuda, if satisfactory represen-tation of all three countries could thereby be obtained.The War Cabinet-(1) Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to send a telegram to the Prime Minister on the lines indicated at&quot;X.&quot;(2) Invited the Lord Privy Seal (on behalf of the Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs) to send a telegram to theDominion Governments informing them of the presentposition in regard to the proposed Anglo-Soviet-American Conference.Italy. 3.   The War Cabinet were informed that the short military(Previous armistice terms had been signed by General Eisenhower&apos;s represen-reference: tative and General Castellano on the 3rd September. The formalW.M.(43) 122nd signature would take place after the announcement of the armistice,Conclusions,      which was being timed to fit in with operational plans. -Minute 2.)Politico-Military. Commission.4. The War Cabinet had a discussion, which is recorded in theSecretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.i 5, - The War Cabinet were informed of the latest position inStafkey.&quot;      regard to this Operation. ,m- &apos;Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1,Qth September, 1943.



</content>
</cab>
