<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/9/51 images: 278-281</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1XtJOmeat SUPPLY.Memorandum by the Minister of Labourand National Service.COPY NO.WAR CABINET.i.    While the morale of the workpeople has been maintained at a remarkably high level, I think thatthere is a serious danger of the strain upon it beingunder-estimated with possible unfortunate results.Among the factors which must be placed high in thisrespect are (a) rest for workpeople living and working in regularly bombed areas;    (b) feeding and housing those who are the victims of raids;    (c) thesupply of meat;    (d) the supply of cigarettes,    I am convinced that these matters are of vital importanceat the present time and that the most drastic measures are justifiable for dealing with them.      In thismemorandum, however, I wish to draw the special attention of my colleagues to the situation inregard to meat.2.    It is becoming more evident that the continuation of the limitation of the home ration of1/- and the reduction of the amount per meal incanteens from Ig-d. to Id. is causing increaseddifficulty and discontent.     Having regard to thecircumstances and outlook of workmen and their wives,it is impossible to expect them to acquire a newattitude towards other foods and we have to take into account the simple fact that women whose husbandsare engaged in physical work believe,  like their husbands themselves,  that the latter are not gettingenough to eat so long as so little meat is availableto them.      The position is specially difficult inregard to those who carry food from home and those whoare billeted and expect as part of their board tohave food to take with them.      The only remedy forthese cases ia a larger supply.3.    As regards canteens, the necessary increaseof these has increased the demand for adequate meals and it is not possible within the present allowances for caterers to meet these demands.      The proposedcut of 33.1/3 per cent, will make it impossible toprovide meat meals on more than two days a week.      in association with fixed canteens, we have to contemplatea great extension of temporary and mobile canteens.In the case of these it is impossible to make a supply of meat go so far as in the case of permanentlyequipped canteens and this is specially the case oncamp sites when the equipment is necessarily elementary.secret.W.P.(g)(41)51.21st MAY.  1941*

40      While the first necessity is an increasedsupply, the second,  in my opinion, is the supply ofthe greatest possible quantity of usable meat forthe price.        In many cases prime quality meat hasbeen forced upon caterers as a result of which theamount has. been greatly reduced.      I think that-Divisional Food Officers should receive definite and implicit instructions on this subject.     Also,I understand that in some areas meat has been supplied only when the v/orks concerned are regardedas being engaged on essential work.      This has caused much criticism and discontent.5.      Much good work is being done in establishedcanteens to improve the quality of meals from otherfoods and to popularise them but it is impossible toproceed so quickly with this as to affect theposition seriously in the next few months.     Betterpublicity also, would tend to bring a clearerrealisation of the difficulties against which theauthorities ire contending and to reduce the criticism of caterers who are not to blame for their inability to meet the needs.      An increase in thesupply of meat, however, should be the primary object and success in this would have a very greateffect on morale.6.      I wish strongly to suggest, therefore,that special measures should be taken to secure animmediate increase of the ration.S. B *The Ministry of Labour endNational Service,21st May,  1941.


</content>
</cab>
