<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/207/7 images: 86-90</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENTC(79) 3710 September 1979COPY NOCABINET1NATIONALISED INDUSTRIES INVESTMENT ANDFINANCING REVIEW:  1981-82 TO 1983-84Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer1, When we discussed the nationalised industries investment andfinancing review (C(79) 28) in July (CC(79) 10th Conclusions, Minute 4 andCC(79) Hth Conclusions), we took decisions on the figures for 1980-81 butleft over the figures for later years.    This note recalls the later year figures,including the options put forward in the investment review (subject to someamendments to take account of subsequent developments particularly inrelation to steel and shipbuilders), and seeks decisions on them in the lightof our overall public expenditure objectives.2. Tables 1 and 2 attached $how, respectively, the industries&apos; bids fortheir borrowing and the options we are putting forward for reducing the bids.The agreed figures for 1980-81 are shown as well as the figures for decisionon the later years.    Table 3 shows the increases compared with Cmnd 7439and the figures resulting from the exercise ofthe full options set out inTable 2.Table 3Cmnd 7439plus: Additional bids:borrowing(adjusted for changesin shortfall)NCB grantsTotal bidless: OptionsRevised total1980-817502301301981-827002001982-837001983-847001503001503501001110740105011001150140011501700380- 50-250-5501CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALThe resulting levelsof nationalised industry borrowing can be comparedwith the figures in earlier years as follows :1977-78 (outturn)       1978-79 (estimated outturn)    1979-80 (estimate)771 1132 737**Figure in Table 1.    The industries1 latest forecasts exceed this total,mainly on account of the Post Office&apos;s tailing backlog.    The implicationsfor cash limits are being examined.3. As Table 3 shows, the options proposed should result in largereductions in the level of nationalised industry borrowing, to the extent ofmoving from a substantial borrowing figure to a substantial net repaymentsfigure by the end of the period.    In view of the nature of the figures (whichrepresent the difference between the very large flows of the industries&apos;revenue and expenditure) it is not meaningful to make a direct comparisonwith the reductions proposed for other spending programmes;  but it is clearthat the options, if achieved in full, will result in an important contributionby the nationalised industries to our public expenditure objectives.4. I recognise that the nationalised industries&apos; figures are subject toparticular uncertainties, and that some industries may want to adjust theirbids in the light of more pessimistic economic forecasts than those pre-vailing when the present bids were prepared,    But the overall publicexpenditure position makes it imperative that we should press the industriesfor the maximum possible contribution, and to keep to the financing figures inTable 1 adjusted to take account of decisions on options.5. As to the detailed figures, those for coal will need to be settled in thelight of the proposals the Secretary of State for  Energy is to make in thecontext of the follow-up to the recent review of the coal industry; meanwhileTable 2 incorporates the option reductions previously envisaged for 1981-82and subsequent years.    The options figures for shipbuilding incorporateMinisters1 July decisions.    The options figures shown for steel are consistentwith a cash limit of  450 million at current prices for 1980-81, as proposedby the Secretary of State for Industry, and a limit of about half as much in1981-82.    For the last two years of the period the figures assume that theindustry will be able to meet its financing requirements from internalresources, as the Secretary of State has proposed to the Corporation.&quot;*        Because the options recorded here for steel and shipbuilding arelarger than the notional figures included in the earlier presentation of theresults of the Financing and Investment Review (C(79) 28), the total of theoptions now is greater than before.    In order to make some allowance for thedeterioration in nationalised industries1 prospective financial position sincetfle base-line figures were prepared, I have scaled down the allowance forshortfall in the later years, so that the net figures in Table 3 (ie, base-linefigures less options) are the same as we had in July.    This would enable uso contemplate some very limited upward adjustments later to the externalnancing for individual industries without these invalidating the overallpublic expenditure position as shown in C(79) 35.2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALCONCLUSION7.        Given the need for substantial reductions in the public expenditureplans we have inherited, as explained in C(79) 35, it is essential that thenationalised industries be pressed to make the maximum possible contri-bution.    Subject, therefore, to the particular points set out inparagraph 5 above, I recommend my colleagues to endorse all the optionsset out in Table 2 of this paper.    To the extent that the industries find thattheir prospects for generating internal funds are less good than theyexpected when the financing figures in this paper were prepared, weshould tell them that the presumption must be that they will find waysthrough adjustments to prices, costs and investment programmes ofstaying within the external financing limits we are now contemplating.G HTreasury Chambers10 September 19793CONFIDENTIAL
TABLE 1NATIONALISED INDUSTRIES: TOTAL NET BORROWING AND LEASING  million at 1978-79 prices1979-80   1980-81   1981-82   1982-83 1983-84ational Coal Boardlectricity Council and Bo;orth of Scotland Hydro-jjectric Boardouth of ScotlandElectricity BoardBritish Gas CorporationBritish Rational Oil*rporationritish Steel Corporation[Post Office[British Airways BoardBritish Airports AuthorityBritish Railways BoardBritish Transport Docks BoardBritish Waterways BoardNational Freight CorporationNational Bus CompanyH)ttish Transport GroupBritish AerospaceBltish ShipbuildersShortfallTOTALRange on Cmnd 7439414	40.9	400	416	&apos; 427s - 69	- .8 -	- 11&apos;	93	21836	20	5	- 2	-51	57	91	161	153-409-	-142	- 78	-164	-160103	175	28	- 14	- 37692	457	427	398	398-101 .	35	- 46	- 99	-205158&apos;	195	130	147	-.149- 1	31	15	11	- 546	49	45	16	9- 6	- 7	- 9	- 10	- 113	4	2	2	216	16	14	13	13.22	11	9	14	191	- 3	- .3	--3	- 249	75	86	72	67182	106	125	102	1001187	1480	. 1230	1153 .	1135-450	-500	-350	-150	-100737	980	880	1003	1035-332	h-232	+162	+306	4-337
IE 2      OPTIONS FOE REDUCTIONS;  a. at 1979 Survey prices1980/81     1981/82     1982/83 1983/84Coal - investmentincluding pit closures 25BNOC - reducedinvestment 75Gas move to economicpricing (as alreadyassumed for electricity) 260Electricity (England &amp;Wales) and Gase -unspecified currentand capital savings 50Scottish ElectricityBoards - increase pricesto economic levels plus. current and capital savings 5Transport industries -further miscellaneoussavings: British Rail 15Others 5Airways - investmentreductions 40Airports - raiselanding charges toeconomic levels 16Post Office - capital andcurrent savings 50British Shipbuilders: .savings from review 37*British Steel: savingsfrom review 121 1British Aerospace -cancellation of BAe 146 40951003807515155401586*25740140100480100201551594*39840195125670100301551598*39840TOTAL7391123The14071691options for BS may need to he revised when new figures forfervent ion Fund grants (programme 4) are agreed in the lightof decisions reached- in the Shipbuilding Review.

</content>
</cab>
