<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/24/24 images: 244-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos;----\THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNMENTSECRET Copy No.W.P. (42) 194(Also C.O.S. (.42) 253)May 7, 1942TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET(No. 140)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 April 30th, to0700 May 7th,1942[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War Room
COMBINED   OPERATIONS.Madagascar.1. At dawn on the 5th May British forces landed at Courrier Bay, north-west coast of Madagascar, from five transports and two landing craft carriers,with the object of capturing the naval base at Diego Suarez. There was little opposition to the landing, our forces advanced eastwards, and the northern partyseized the Windsor Castle Battery (4 6-5-inch guns). An ultimatum to theGovernor to surrender was rejected, and by 1600 Diego Suarez North was captured by a commando and a southern column was 2  miles from the town ofAntsirane. On the following morning the first assault on Antsirane by the29th Brigade was repulsed by heavy opposition, but a night assault by the17th Brigade, assisted by a small party of Royal Marines, who were landed atAntsirane quay from H.M. Destroyer Anthony, succeeded, and the french authorities surrendered, though there was no general capitulation.The landing was covered by our Eastern Fleet and during the operations a french submarine was sunk. No ships other than sloops were in the harbour.H.M. Corvette Auricula was mined and sunk and seven of our aircraft are missing.  Two French fighters were shot down on the 6th by our fighters.Early on the morning of the 7th the Oronjoia batteries surrendered and thefleet entered Diego Suarez harbour during the afternoon.A protocol is being drawn up.NAVAL SITUATION.General Review.2. A convoy has successfully reached North Russia in the face of determinedenemy opposition which caused some casualties.There has been an increase in the shipping casualties.Home Waters and North Atlantic.3. On the night of 3rd/4th a force of M.T.Bs. and MGBs. from Doverattempted an attack on a 4,000-ton ship on passage down channel, but they weredetected by the shore defences and driven off by escorting vessels.H.M.S. Calpe, in company with four other destroyers, engaged four enemyfast motor craft off St. Valery on the morning of the 8th. One enemy craft was set on fire and probably sunk and the remainder damaged. Our casualties were1 killed and 2 wounded.Near Lisbon on the 1st, H.M. Trawler Imperialist hit a Focke Wulf aircraft,which crashed later.The Polish destroyer Blyskawica, undergoing refit, was again damaged in theair attack on Cowes on the night 4th / 5th.It is estimated that during the week our aircraft have sunk or seriously damaged 23,000 tons of enemy merchant shipping off the coasts of Norway and holland.  Details are given under Air Situation.Northern Waters.4. On thej&amp;fternoon of the 1st three enemy destroyers attacked a homeward-bound convoy from Russia some 150 miles north-west of the North Cape. Theywere engaged by the convoy escort and driven off, but not before they had sunkone ship of the convoy. In this action H.M. Destroyer Amazon sustained some damage.Early on the 2nd, in thick weather, about 200 miles north of Murmansk, thesame three destroyers attacked H.M.S. Edinburgh, which was returning to harbourafter being hit by two torpedoes&apos; from a U-boat on the 30th April. In the ensuingaction one enemy destroyer was probably sunk and another damaged. Edinburghwas hit by one torpedo and had to be abandoned and sunk, and H.M. DestroyersForester and Foresight were damaged. The casualties in Edinburgh were officers and 56 ratings killed and 1 officer and 12 ratings wounded.
Mediterranean.5. H.M. Submarine P. 42 torpedoed and probably sank a 4,000-ton merchant ship in the Gulf of Genoa on the 28th April.On the 18th, H.M. Submarine P. 35 probably torpedoed a northbound 5,000-ton merchant ship north of the Kerkenah Island (Tunisian Coast) and on thefollowing day sank a northbound 4,500-ton ship in the same area.A water boat and a tug were sunk in the enemy air raid on Malta on the28th April, and further damage was done to the dockyard offices.Anti-Submarine Operations.6. Nineteen attacks on U-boats have been reported during the week, twelveby aircraft and seven by surface craft. In no attack was there definite evidenceof destruction.Five attacks, four of them by aircraft, were made off the south-east corner of Spain. In connection with these. it-4s^^HevedHshai a damaged U-boat has &quot;tdtWw ^6ju^efeeei^ &amp;we4-4sie Cartagena. Ten attacks, six of them by air, were made in theWest Atlantic and Caribbean. Two attacks by aircraft were made in the Bay of biscay and surface craft made attacks in the North-West Approaches and theIrish Sea.Enemy Intelligence.Italian.7. The cruiser sunk by H.M. Submarine Urge on the 1st April is believed tobe the Giovanni delle Bande Nere, a 6-inch cruiser built in 1928. This class,which are now all sunk, resembled the 8-inch cruisers, one of which was originally claimed by Urge.U-boats.8. It is estimated that some 12 U-boats are operating in the Florida Strait,Gulf of Mexico and Caribbean. In Northern American waters activity hasbeen less, and none in the Atlantic.It is probable that some 10 U-boats were operating against the Russianconvoys.An Italian U-boat is believed to have been in the Baltic for some time past,probably for training purposes.Japanese.9. A naval force of at least one aircraft-carrier and two heavy cruisershas been sighted at sea on two occasions during the week to the south-east ofNew Britain.A light cruiser and 19 transports were observed in the Rabaul area onthe 2nd:[23795] B 2The outward-bound convoy to Russia was constantly shadowed, and several times attacked both by aircraft and U-boats, and on the 2nd three ships includingthe Commodore&apos;s ship, were sunk by torpedo aircraft, the majoritv of the crewsbeing rescued. The remaining 22 ships arrived safely at Murmansk. Duringthe attacks on the two convoys three enemy aircraft were shot downIn the afternoon of the 1st, H.M. Destroyer Ptinjabi, which was in company with the Home Fleet, covering the movements of the convoys, was sunk in collision with H.M.S. King George V. The great majority of her crew wererescued.A German destroyer was damaged by a Hudson aircraft off Stadlandet onthe night of the 1st/2nd.
Protection of Seaborne Trade.10. During the week ending the 6th May 678 ships, including 201 allied and 14 neutral, have been convoyed. Three cruisers, 3 anti-aircraft ships,1 submarine, 79 destroyers (including 8 American and 2 Russian) and 91 sloops,cutters, corvettes and fleet minesweepers were employed on escort duty.Imports into the United Kingdom by ships in convoy during the week ending the 2nd May totalled 621.000 tons, compared with 712,000 tons during theprevious seven days and an average of 596,800 tons for the past ten weeks. Ofthe week&apos;s imports, 218,000 tons were oil of various grades.Enemy Attack on Seaborne Trade.11. There has been a considerable increase in the number of ships attacked by U-boat. Twentv-two ships (seven of them tankers) are known to have been torpedoed, all of them in the West Atlantic and the Caribbean.The majority of the casualties occurred in the northern Caribbean and offthe Florida Coast.   Six of the ships are known to have sunk.Aircraft sank three ships in a convoy to Russia, damaged two ships at port Said and sank a smaller ship off Alexandria. Two ships were damaged by mine in the Cape of Good Hope area but reached port.One ship in a convoy fronPRussia was sunk by enemy destroyers.Since the 1st March nine ships have been overdue in the South atlantic and it is considered that they may be raider casualties.British Minelaying.12. Aircraft have laid mines on an unusually large scale in the Baltic, offthe German North Sea coast and in the Bay of Biscay.Enemy Minelaying, British Minesweeping.13. It is possible that enemy aircraft laid mines off the Tyne on the night of the 30th April/lst May and off Cowes on the 4th/5th May.A U-boat was reported off the Pembrokeshire coast on the 4th and in conse-quence special sweeps are being carried out in this area.Four magnetic and eight contact mines have been destroyed during theperiod.The mine totals (including those destroyed in Foreign Waters) are now2,014 magnetic, 1,267 acoustic and 1,175 moored.Enemy Merchant Shipping.Italian and German.14 The Italian Fusijama (6,244 tons) is believed to have reached Bordeaux.Ihis ship was last reported in Yokohama.Between the beginning of 1941 and February 1942 a total of nearly 250,000tons of iron ore was shipped from Spain to Occupied France for the enemy. Thereare six comparatively large ships totalling rather more than 21,000 tons and aconsiderable number of small coasters engaged in this trade. During March1942 about 37,000 tons of iron ore was carried by the larger ships and about35,000 tons by the coasters.The Roumanian Alba Julia (5,701 tons) sailed from Istanbul for Triesteon the 28th April and passed into the ^aegean on the following day.Japanese.15. It has been officially announced in Japan that the Calcutta Maru(5,339 tons) was sunk by a submarine on the 1st May off the south-west coast of Kyushu. Another merchant ship, the Seia Maru (6,659 tons) is also knownto have been torpedoed about 100 miles north-east of Oruluk in the CarolineIslands, but was apparently able to proceed; she was bound for Imeiji, where she was due on the 3rd May.
Vichy Intelligence.Naval.16. It is reported that the Strasbourg and Provence at Toulon are fully effective, but Dunkerque at the same port is not likely to be ready for nine months the Richelieu at Dakar has one gun of her main armament out of action the Jean Bart at Casablanca has only one turret mounted and appears to be ina low state of readiness for sea.Vichy has announced that the A.M.C. Bougainville (4,510 tons) was sunkon 5th May during the British attack on Diego Suarez.Merchant Shipping.17. The Gabon (4,651 tons) is reported to have been sold to Germany andis expected to leave Marseilles on 8th May for Hamburg. She was to be manned by a French volunteer crew.MILITARY SITUATION.The Russo-German Campaign.Finland.18. On the 28th April Russian forces landed from the Motovski Gulf onthe Arctic Coast and are operating behind the German foremost positions onthe River Litsa.Crimea.19.   Road conditions in the Crimea have improved.Summary.20. On the rest of the Russian front a full-scale German offensive is unlikely before the second half of May or early June. The total of german divisions on the front (including Finland) is now 182.Libya.&apos; 21. On the 30th April three patrol columns of our armoured formationsreported a concentration of enemy M.T., including tanks and. armoured cars,in an area six miles south-east of Bir Tengeder, and a concentration of 50 M.T.near Rotunda Segnali. During the rest of the week patrol and artillery activitycontinued.Burma.Irrawaddy and Sittang Fronts.22. On the 27th April our main forces were disposed east and south of Mandalay. After a successful action by Ghurka units, supported by tanks, inwhich severe casualties were inflicted on the enemy, our main forces had allwithdrawn north of the Irrawaddy by 1st May. Chinese operating near Sagaing,south of Mandalay, covered this withdrawal and then crossed the river, where apart entrained for the Myitkyina-Katha area.On the 1st May the Japanese were reported to have occupied the towns of Mandalay and Monywa. Another report stated that on the 3rd Monywa was clear of the Japanese but fighting with rebels was continuing in the town.Part of our troops are withdrawing up the Chindwin Valley, but their exactlocation is not known. The latest reports stated that our main forces were operating north and west of Mandalay, and some are moving by M.T. toSchewyin (south of Kalewa and near the Assam frontier).Shan States.23. The Japanese reached Lashio on the 29th April and all Chinese tanks and troops in this area were withdrawn north of Lasbio. Heavy fighting-continues on the China-Burma frontier.Some Chinese are believed to be still holding out in the Taunggyi area, butthe exact dispositions of these and other Chinese troops are not known.Ahjab.24.   Defence detachments have been evacuated from Akyab.
General.25. Our main attacks, by night, were directed against Stuttgart and hamburg.   Large-scale sea-mining was carried out.Coastal Command aircraft made several successful attacks on enemy shipping.Night fighters inflicted a number of casualties on enemy bombers attackingthis country.Enemy attacks on Malta were on a much reduced scale.United Kingdom.26.   Fighter Command flew 5,035 sorties by day and 633 by night.27. The German Air Force on the Western Front was mainly concernedwith bombing attacks on this country. While routine reconnaissance patrols werenot reduced, minelaying and anti-shipping operations generally in home waterswere largely abandoned to allow the long-range bomber force available to concentrate on &quot; reprisal &quot; raids.28. In daylight enemy fighters were active over this country, attacks beingmade with bombs and guns, by formations of from two to eight aircraft, on targets along the south coast.29. On three nights concentrated attacks were made by an average ofapproximately 60 bombers; the principal objectives were Tyneside, Exeter andtargets on the Isle of Wight.Night fighters and A.A. guns destroyed 16 enemy bombers, probably destroyed two and damaged 5, without themselves sustaining any losses.Germany and Occupied Territory.Day.   -30. Fighter and Bomber Commands despatched 2,701 and 78 sorties respectively, compared with 2,791 and 96 last week.31. Targets attacked by Bostons and Hurricane Bombers included the docks at Havre, Flushing, Dunkirk and Boulogne; aerodromes at Morlaix andAbbeville; railway centres at Abbeville and St. Omer; and industrial targets atCalais, Marquise, Havre, Zeebrugge and Caen. Although in most cases bombs are estimated to have fallen in the target area, heavy flak was frequentlyexperienced and few definite results are claimed. Bursts and fires were seen atthe Railway centre at St. Omer, and a direct hit was made on the main workshopof a shell factory at Marquise.32. Escort and cover for these attacks were supplied hj Spitfires, and, inaddition, a total of 19 sweeps was carried out. In all these operations, 24 enemy aircraft were destroyed, a further 23 probably destroyed and 24 damaged. our losses were 35 aircraft, but the pilots of seven are safe.Night.33. Bomber Command despatched 492 sorties against land targets comparedwith 1,050 last week, the reduction being principally due to adverse weather onthe first two nights of the week and to a very heavy sea-mining programme onthe third night. A total of 298 tons of H.E. (including 33 x 4,000 lbs.) and264 tons of incendiaries was dropped.34. The main target was Stuttgart, which was attacked on three successivenights, but on each occasion heavy ground haze or cloud made positive identification-tion of the town extremely difficult. Similar conditions obtained over the neighbouring town of Feuerbach, where the Bosch Electrical ManufacturingWorks was the objective for part of the bombing force, and only one aircraftclaims to have identified this target. Over the Stuttgart area, a total of about225 tons of H.E. and incendiaries was dropped, and on the last night, whenconditions were somewhat better, many fires were seen to start in the town.
35. In a medium scale attack on Hamburg, 120 tons of H.E. andincendiaries were dropped under conditions no more favourable than atStuttgart, heavy cloud preventing identification of ground features. The glowof some considerable fires thought to be in the dock area was seen through theclouds.36. Three small scale attacks were made on Nantes, and two Stirlings offive despatched claim to have attacked the Skoda works at Pilsen.37. Forty-four aircraft were engaged on dissemination of leaflets overFrench towns, including Marseilles, Lyons, Toulon and Vichy.38.   From all these operations, 19 bombers are missing.  .39. Fighter Command despatched 67 aircraft to patrol over and attackaerodromes in France and Holland, and 11 fighters to attack railway targets inFrance. Bombs were dropped on the aerodromes at Chievres. Abbeville, Evreux,Dinard, Rennes, St. Andre, Caen. Bretigny, Gilze-Rijen, Chartres. Eindhoven,Beauvais and Le Touquet. At least 20 goods trains wrere attacked and in manycases caused to stop, and railway yards at Caen, Bretigny and Abbeville were bombed.  Eight enemy aircraft were shot down and another was damaged.40. Hampdens of Coastal Command bombed the aerodrome at Mandel andbarracks and other objectives near Kristiansand (S).Coastal Operations.41. Coastal Command flew 526 sorties, of which 40 were on convoy escort.Shipping protection patrols by Fighter Command involved 994 sorties.42. There was a marked increase in the number of enemy vessels attacked and. in addition to the destroyer mentioned under Naval Situation, those seriously damaged included an &quot; Altmark &quot; type tanker which was left in flames offAalesund; a 2,000-ton merchant vessel off Ameland, which caught fire and was later seen listing to starboard; a 5.000-ton merchant vessel which was left inflames off Terschelling; a 1,500-ton vessel, also off Terschelling. from which therewas a large orange flash followed by an explosion; and a 3,000-ton vessel inKristiansund (N) Harbour, on which two explosions were seen. All these attacks were made by Hudsons.Another promising attack, also by a Hudson, was made on a 3,000-ton cargovessel off Ameland. Although no bursts were seen, a large glow, which was observed later, was probably this vessel on fire.43. Beaufighters and Hurricanes attacked a number of small vessels, ofwhich at least three were damaged.A Whitley attacked with depth charges three 500-ton vessels in the bay of Biscay, sinking one and damaging the other two.44. Sea-mining by Bomber Command aircraft involved 106 sorties, of which96 were despatched on one night the highest total so far recorded. A total of269 mines was laid in areas extending from the Baltic to the Bay of Biscay.45. Enemy activity off our coasts was on a very small scale and was confined to the usual shipping and weather reconnaissances. No mine-laying or attacks on coastal shipping have been reported.Mediterranean.Libya and Egypt.46.   Operations were considerably restricted by dust storms and bad weather.47. Three Beaufighters carried out two offensive reconnaissances overWestern Cyrenaica and attacked M.T. convoys south of Benghazi. Forty-twovehicles including two petrol tankers were destroyed or damaged and a Ju. 52was forced down and attacked on the ground.Hurricanes made a low level attack on Dema landing ground and on a campwest of Martuba.48. Fighters maintained offensive patrols over the forward areas and shipping protection patrols were flown.
49.   Three night attacks by Wellingtons were made on Benghazi Harbour.50. A night attack by 12 enemy aircraft was made on Port Said and 50H.E. bombs dropped in the harbour area, causing damage to shipping. Twentyenemy aircraft bombed Alexandria and caused slight damage in the town andon the East side of the harbour.Beaufighters destroyed two enemy bombers and damaged three others.Malta.51. Enemy attacks on the island continued, but the scale of effort showed adecrease. A few Italian aircraft participated in the raids, and on someoccasions Me. 109s carried bombs.The principal objectives were the aerodromes and Grand Harbour, wheresome damage was caused, and elsewhere civilian property was destroyed. Onlyone of our aircraft was destroyed on the ground and four others damaged.Our fighters shot down five enemy aircraft, probably destroyed one and damaged twelve. Anti-aircraft guns destroyed five, and damaged six more. Welost four fighters, but two pilots were saved.52. The decline in enemy effort, apart from losses, is probably due to thewithdrawal of some German Air Force units from Sicily to other theatres, andalso partly to the need for resting the remaining crews, from whom the utmosteffort has been extracted since the period of intensive operations against Maltabegan.53. The weight of enemy bombs dropped on the island in April is estimatedat 6,728 tons.   This compares with 2,174 tons in March and 993 in February.Sea Communications.54. A Wellington from Malta attacked a merchant vessel of 5,000 tons,escorted by a destroyer, entering Pantellaria Harbour. A direct hit was madeon the merchant vessel and near misses probably damaged the destroyer.55. A naval Albacore scored a probable hit with a torpedo on a merchant vessel of 6,000 tons, E.S.E. of Lampione.Russia.56. No information has been received regarding air operations in Russiaduring the week.Burma.57.   There has been a slight increase in bombing activity by Allied aircraft.58. Four attacks carried out by Blenheims caused damage to the runwayat Magwe aerodrome, two fires at the oilfields at Yenangyuang, three hits onbarges in the Irrawaddy River, and several hits on loaded barges at Monywa.59.   A total of five American Fortresses made four attacks on Rangoon docks.Other American bombers made two attacks on Mingaladon aerodrome, settingone hangar on fire, and starting other large fires and explosions.60. Enemy activity was mainly directed against Akyab, which was attacked on four occasions. In one attack 33 aircraft bombed and machine-gunned thetown. No details of damage have been reported. Later in the week, after our troops had been withdrawn, this target was attacked by Wellingtons operatingfor the first time from India.61. Two raids, by 27 and 24 enemy bombers respectively, were made onPaoshan, but no further details are available. Two American aircraft were destroyed on the ground as the result of an attack on Myitkyina.The only other enemy activity reported is the machine-gunning of Lashioaerodrome by fighters, one of which was destroyed.Pacific Zone.62. American bombers, chiefly Fortresses and Marauders, carried out threeattacks on the aerodrome at Lae, and four attacks on targets at Rabaul.  A total
of 30 sorties were involved. At Lae, a number of large fires were started and five aircraft on the ground were hit. In Rabaul harbour, a transport and two other ships were hit, and wharves and buildings were damaged. At the aerodromeconsiderable damage is believed to have been done, including direct hits on somedispersed aircraft.Other targets attacked were Koepang aerodrome, Gasmata and Salamoa,where a fuel dump and supplies were set on fire.In the course of these operations, the bombers or their fighter escorts destroyedfive enemy fighters and damaged several more. One bomber is missing and oneAiracobra crashed.63. Ten American Airacobras were despatched to attack Lae aerodrome, butbad weather was encountered and four aircraft failed to return.64. Reconnaissance aircraft operating hear Port Moresby were interceptedon two occasions by Japariese fighters, one of which was destroyed, two probably destroyed and a fourth was damaged.65. A total of 21 enemy bombers and 44 fighters made six attacks onSeven Miles Aerodrome, Port Moresby. Five Allied aircraft were damaged onthe ground. In combat four enemy figliters were destroyed, six probably destroyed and three damaged for the loss of one Tomahawk and two Airacobras.66. Enemy flying boats made three attacks on Tulagi (Solomon Islands).Two Catalinas on the water were damaged.67. Horn Island (Torres Strait) was attacked by eight enemy bombers andthree fighters. Three of our aircraft were damaged on the ground. One enemvfighter was probably destroyed.HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.By day.68. On six days bombs were dropped on towns and harbours of the south coast.  Casualties were light and only slight damage was done.By night.69. On the night of the 30th/31st April bombs were scattered over coastal areas in northern and north-eastern England, the majority falling on Tyneside.No serious damage was done and casualties, were not heavy. On the night of the3rd/4th Exeter was bombed for the second time within ten days. Serious fires were started, communications and utility services were badly affected, thecathedral was hit and considerable damage was done to private arid public-property. Several garages of Air Services, Ltd., were seriously damaged andsome main stores destroyed.On the following night Cowes was bombed and wide-spread damage was done to public arid private property, shipyards were extensively damaged and utilityservices affected.Casualties.70. The total estimated civilian casualties for week ending 0600 the6th May are : tKilled     ..........      ;..      ......      319Seriously injured ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     38771.   The latest known totals for certain individual areas are : -Se?&apos;iouslyKilled      injured.Cowes............      ......        51 180Exeter 139 75Norwich (night of 29th/30th)     ...      ...        50 76
APPENDICES I and II will bo published monthly.APPENDIX III.Month.1941-MarchAprilMayJuneJulyAugustSeptemberOctober ...NovemberDecember1942-January ...FebruaryMarchNo.(1) Vessels on the British Register or on Time Charter to the United Kingdom.Non-tankers and Tankers.   1,600 gross tons and over.Total.Allocated to theFighting Services.(1)3,6843,6283,6193,5753,5663,6193,6133,6133,6163,6413,6153,5993,528Gross Tons.20,925,00020,599,00020,427,00020,167,00020,136,00020,474,00020,543,00020,609,00020,674,00020,823,00020,729,00020,621,00020,230,000No.704691654653640668674696707745818830824Gross Tons.5,440,0005,515,0005,237,0005,209,0005,059,0005,287,0005,227,0005,318,0005,325,0005,677,0005,985,0006,095,0006,056,000Coasting Trade of theUnited Kingdomand Eire.No.158155158155149144145160175171175167148Gross Tons.Trading between countries other thanthe United Kingdomand Eire.Repairing, damaged or not in use.(2)Importing Servicesof theUnited Kingdom.(3)_No.370,000366,000370,000360,000351,000340,000346,000371,000411,000419,000419,000400,030351,000Gross Tons.7197237457407697977858118348258108328403,175,0003,170,0003,216,0003,124,0003,322,0003,434,0003,374,0003,512,0003,674,0003,607,0003,611,0003,782,0003,937,000No.Gross Tons.4034133884314454414444444444585035174812,232,0002,199,0002,129,0002,454,0002,597,0002,571,0002,677,0002,654,0002,799,0002,771,0003,037,0003,038,0002,775,000No.1,7001,0461,6741,5961,5631,5691,5651,5021,4561,4421,3091,2531,235Gross Tons.9 708,0009,349,0009,475,00U9,020,000.8,807,0008,842,0008,919,0008,754,0008,465,0008,349,0007,677,0007,306,0007,111,000:_The above table is an aggregation of the material in the employment tables of non-tankers and tankers in Statistical Digests E and F respectively.   Ina the figures for non-tankers with those for tankers, certain slight differences have had to be brought into a common form.    The figures for non-tankers relatenote.-combiningto the 15th of the month to February 1942 and to the last day of the month from March 1942.(1) (a) Tankers on Admiralty service include vessels importing oil fuel to the United Kingdom; in March 1942 these comprised 21 tankers of 170,000 gross tons.(b) Non-tankers allocated to the fighting services which are under repair are excluded from this column.   All tankers on Admiralty service are, however, included.(c) A substantial part (in recent months nearly one-half) of the tonnage in these columns brings commercial cargoes to the United Kingdom on completion of the outward voyage (see note (3) ).(2) These columns give vessels out of employment (apart from tankers on Admiralty Service), being mainly those immobilised by damage or repair. They do not,therefore, include vessels under repair while loading or unloading cargo.(3) These columns include vessels (apart from tankers on Admiralty Service)  which areoutward voyages to tiie Fighting Ser\icee or wliicb had previous-on Admiralty Service;  wincn are bringing imports to the United Kingdom but which were allocated on theisly been trading botwecn countries other tiiun   united kingdom nad j5iro.
Enemy Merchant Ship losses as assessed on 15th April, 1942.Nationality.      *	bunk, Captured i      c,   .     , rs     , v   . -           seriously or Constructive !      ^          J, Loss.        j     Damaged.				Damaged.		Total.		No.	Gross      ,T m          i No. Ions.    j		Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.German Italian Other enemy ships . and ships useful to enemy Total	408 437 125	1,758,987 1,836,189 228,355	117 83 16	323,553 398,368 43,706	205 87 12	642,489 439,984 48,824	730 607 153	2,725,029 2,674,541 320,885	970	3,823,531	216	765,627	304 j 1,131,297 i		1,490 ! 5,720,455 1	The table does not include losses inflicted on the enemy by our russian allies, which are estimated at about 612,000 gross tons sunk; nor does it include losses inflicted on Japanese shipping in the Far East and Pacific, which up to15th April are estimated to number 67 ships sunk, or about 268,000 gross tons.In addition, there is about 336,000 gross tons of Axis shipping in south american ports which is no longer available to the enemy.APPENDIX Y.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary vessels and to Naval Personnel.On the 6th Motor Minesweeper 173 and Motor Launch 160 were damaged by air attack at Brixham.The following casualties to Naval personnel have been reported : Officers : Killed 40; missing 4; wounded 3.Ratings : Killed 78; missing 42; wounded 2.These figures include the crew of H.M. Submarine Upholder (listed asmissing) and the officers in H.M. Ships Cornwall and Dorsetshire.APPENDIX IY.
Provisional operational aircraft battle casualties for the period: dawn, Thursday30th April, to dawn, Thursday, 7th May, 19^2. &apos;British.Bombers ...Fighters ...ConstalArmy Co-operation total enemy.bombers fighters miscellaneous metropolitan Area.In the Air........ 22.     &apos;...... 31....... 8....... 1....... 82Six fighter pilots are safe.On the (.round.TotalDestroyed.2426353ProbablyDestroyed.22426Damaged.91726Of the above totals three bombers were destroyed by A.A. fire.Middle East (including Malta).   .British.Bombers.Fighters .others in the Air.26On the Ground.2TotalEnemy.Bombers ...Fighters ...MiscellaneousTotalOne pilot is safe.Destroyed.6814ProbablyDestroyed.Damaged.118i20Of the above totals, seven were destroyed and six damaged by A.A.Far East.British and Allied.Bombers ...lighters ...MiscellaneousIn the Air.110On the Ground.Total11Enemy.Bombers ...Fighters ...miscellaneous destroyed.13ProbablyDestroyed35Damaged.121Total1313Notes. (a) No account is taken of enemy aircraft destroyed on the ground in any theatre.(b) No account is taken of British Naval aircraft casualties.APPENDIX YI.
APPENDIX VII.Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports of damage have been received during the past week :  Germany.Augsburg. Photographs taken on 29th April show the following damageresulting from the raid on 17th April: (a) The main Diesel Engine shops of 1-3 storeys and covering an areaof 20,000 square yards are severely damaged by a number of direct hits, and there is probable fire damage to a top storey.(b) Roof damage to two small buildings and a workshop.(c) A  large building,  probably  connected -with  the  power station,  isdemolished, and others badly damaged by blast.(d) Out of four buildings believed to be stores for machine parts, two aredemolished and two damaged.(e) Several workshops and weaving sheds outside the main target area aredamaged, one seriously.Cologne. Photographs taken on 29th April, 1942, cover the central cityarea, but other parts are not well covered. An immediate assessment showsten areas of damage, the greater part of which has been caused entirely by fire.The two largest areas are to the south of the cathedral and measure 950 ft. by750 ft. and 450 ft. by 375 ft. In one of these, seven blocks of buildings have been completely burnt out.In the attacks on 5th/6th and 22nd/23rd April, considerable damage was caused to property near the main station. The damage caused in recent attacksis such that the authorities can no longer speedily clear away the debris and have abandoned their former practice of putting up hoardings to conceal whenever possible where bombs have fallen.Rostock. In the first two raids twelve direct hits by heavy bombs were obtained on the Heinkel Works. Two engineering sheds caught fire, and thewalls of the largest assembly shed fell inwards, destroying the aircraft on thelines. At the time of the attack work in the factory was proceeding. The dock area was heavily damaged in various places, five warehouses being totally burnt out and seven cranes fell into the dock. Several bombs fell in the Neptuneshipbuilding yard, causing damage to the roofs of buildings.Kiel. Photographs taken on 3rd May, 1942, show : (a) That two bays of the angle&apos; and plate-shaping sheds in the Germaniashipbuilding yards have been destrcyed by a direct hit. (Previousdamage to these sheds had recently been repaired.)(6) Two main shops in the wire cable factory to the south of SchwentineRiver have been completely gutted by fire and two small buildingspartly demolished.(c) There are signs of extensive roof repairs to the engine round-house in the marshalling yards south of Die Horn.(d) Domestic property at the junction of the Hollmann Strasse and theGebhart Strasse has been destroyed.On the night of 16th February a bomb fell on the assembly shed at theMarinewerft and the majority of the night workers therein were killed. the attack was a complete surprise.
Occupied Territory.Gennevilliers. Photographs taken on 30th April show that as a result ofthe attack on the 28th : (a) A narrow strip of roofing, 96 yards long, is missing from the centralpart of the power station.(b) A two-bay building in the Thomson Houston factory is gutted.(c) A large building on the east side of the Goodrich tyre works receiveddirect hits and was very extensively damaged.(d) The sewage works on the south bank of the river was severely damaged.In addition, some residential property was destroyed.(e) On the north bank of the river a five-bay woodwork factory and a building, probably part of the Construction Aeronautiques factory,was completely gutted, and part of a metal works seriously damaged!Marquise. Photographs of the 3rd May show that in the attack on thefactory, reported to be making shells and bombs for the Germans, several buildings in the works were damaged, the roof of one being stripped over an area of approximately 3,000 square yards. In the marshalling yards a building-is seen to be gutted and there were direct hits on the tracks.Dunkirk. Photographs made during the attack on the 29th April showeight bombs bursting on the northern part of the Citadel Quay. Some of thesefell on buildings, and it is possible that the Chamber of Commerce was hit.Further photographs, taken on 30th April, show that in an attack on the invasion barges at the west end of the &quot; Bassin Devolution&quot; nine barges were destroyed, six seriously damaged and one slightly damaged.In addition, two large buildings in the Raffinerie de Petrole du Nord, oneof them already damaged by a previous raid, have each had several more baysseverely damaged by fire.St. Omer. Photographs taken during the attack on the 28th April showthat bombs fell on the railway station and sidings. Others taken during the attack on the 1st May show that bombs fell across a factory south of the canal andon houses in the vicinity.Morlaix. -Photographs taken during the attack on the 30th April show15 bombs bursting across the south-east dispersal area of the aerodrome, amongstcovered blast shelters, a repair hangar and several small buildings.Lille. Photographs taken during the attack of the 27th April show 27 bombsbursting in or close to the area enclosed by the oanal loop at Hambourdin. these include seven on industrial buildings at the northern end of the loop, includingthe Cousin-Devos factory and a weaving shed, and 11 more in the centre of theloop.In the southern part of the area there are six bursts on industrial buildings,including the Tannery of Lefevre fils et Cie.In the attack on the 27th/28th April a barracks received a direct hit, manyGermans being killed.Sea Mining. v.ja\AOn the 13th March the German Kellerhmd (5,032 tons) was mined and sank13 miles south of Heligoland, and on the 28th March the Danish Berta (7,664tons) was mined and sank off the Frisian Islands.



</content>
</cab>
