<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/41/42 images: 312-315</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
tHIS document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s governmentPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1943.15SECRET. Copy No.   3 3W.P. (43) 442.(;/// October, ]943.WAR CABINET.INDIAN POLICY.Note by the Prime Minister and Minister of Defence.I circulate to my colleagues a letter I have received from Lord Croft, which seems to me to deserve consideration.W. S. C.10, Downing Street, S.W. 1,Qth October, 1943.*Only on very rare occasions have I obtruded my views upon you and I hopeyon will forgive my offering this opinion on India.I think that our attitude over the Gandhi fast was amply vindicated andthat had we taken any weaker course the very satisfactory drop in politicaltemperature in India would not have resulted.It may be that when the new Viceroy takes over an opportunity to reopen thequestion of Indians getting together to consult upon an agreed plan for the futuremay be considered appropriate, or, at any rate, a reafhrmation that the Britishoffer stands. If that is so, I feel that it is of the utmost importance that Gandhishould not be resurrected.Over the whole issue of Japan involving the life of India Gandhi took the wrong turning, and any attempt to &apos;&apos; appease &apos;&apos; him would be misunderstood inthis country and would, I imagine, cause the utmost confusion in the minds ofthe 2,000,000 volunteers in India who are preparing to fight the Japanese.[26202]
Providence has aided us in the discredit of Gandhi and all his efforts to cause chaos and confusion in India on the eve of her trial have failed. To brin^Gandhi back into the picture now would surely weaken the British Governmentin the eyes of all who have stood by us. and I should have thought greatly hardenMoslem feeling against co-operation and also bring us into contempt in the eyes of the Ruling Princes.The failure of Gandhi to rouse India against the King-Emperor is one of thehappiest events of the war.To bring him into the picture again in any form would appear to me to beasking for trouble and restore his power for mischief. We might just as wellinvite Laval to co-operate with us for the defence of France!***** *HENRY CROFTWar Office. Whitehall S.W. 1,1st October. 1943.



</content>
</cab>
