<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/36/39 images: 382-389</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;? governmentPrinted for the War Cabinet.   May 1943.MOST SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (43) 189.May 3, 1943.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND Kg//It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET.GERMAN SHORTAGES OF MUNITIONS OF AVAR.Note by the Secretary.THE annexed Report by the Joint Intelligence Sub-Committee on GermanShortages of Munitions of War is circulated to the War Cabinet and DefenceCommittee by direction of the Prime Minister.(Signed) E. E. BRIDGES,Offices of the War Cabinet. S.W.1,May 3, 1943.[J.I.C. (43) 142 (O) Final.April 2, 1943.]GERMAN SHORTAGES OF MUNITIONS OF WAR,Report by the Joint Intelligence Sub-Committee.IN the Appendix to this Paper we examine recent reports of shortages ofmunitions of war, other than oil. We also attempt a forecast of future developments.We find, in particular : (a) A shortage of flak ammunition, which probably extends to bombs and aircraft ammunition, together with a possible shortage of other types of ammunition.(6) A shortage of M/T, which has already affected ancillary services and maywell be grave by the end of the year.(c) A shortage of aircraft, in the sense that Germany has insufficient to meether strategic requirements.(d) A shortage of minesweepers, in the same sense as (c) above.(e) A shortage of W/T equipment.(/) Some signs, although inconclusive, of a shortage of tanks, or at leastinsufficient reserves to meet promptly all demands for replacements.(g) A shortage of locomotives which may, in some instances, have delayedmilitary movements.2. There has been a general fall in the production of munitions of war. TheGermans have been skilful in adjusting a strained economic position to meet thewar&apos;s demands. But their resources, both in labour and materials, are decreasingand their difficulties are enhanced by Allied air raids and the interception of theirblockade runners.[25388]b
3. We consider, however, that the rate of wastage, rather than decline in production, will be the determining factor in the future. Assuming that the rateof wastage will be not less than that sustained in 1942, shortages are likely todevelop increasingly, and the Germans will make every effort to overcome theseby economies in expenditure and by adjusting their production to meet the morepressing deficiencies. We have no evidence to suggest that any shortages will beso acute as to leave Germany other than a formidable enemy, but the operational efficiency of her armed forces will be impaired in some respects. It is impossibleto forecast when and where these shortages will first seriously hamper Germanoperations.(Signed) V. CAVENDISH-BENTINCK.II. G. N. RUSHBROOKE.F. II. N. DAVIDSON.F. F INGE IS.C. G. VICKERS.Offices of the War Cabinet. S. W.1,&apos; A pril 2, 1943.APPENDIX.I Introduction.1. In this report, the words &quot; munitions of war &quot; have been taken to include all equipment which goes to make up the fighting efficiency of the Armed Forces.We have not dealt with oil. which is the subject of other papers. In taking a standard against which to measure &quot;shortage,&quot; we have had regard mainly to existing establishments and sometimes to existing strategic commitments. Wehave omitted consideration of the numerical sufficiency of the main units of theGerman Fleet.2. No absolute shortages of munitions of war other than those mentionedbelow have been reliably reported. There has been no sign of any significantdeterioration in the quality of captured material.3. Shortages reported from Africa are nearly always due to distributionaldifficulties. As a result of dislocation due to Allied action, failure to plan by theGermans and Italian inefficiency, the supply organisation has been unable to cope with the situation which has arisen. It is thought that the supplies were in themain available, though retarded, in some cases by the more pressing needs of theRussian Front.4. We examine each service independently, though some of the shortagesaffect more than one service, e.g., lack of M/T, ammunition, W/T, &amp;c.II The German Army.(a) Tanks.5. During 1942 there was an increase in the number of German divisionsequipped with tanks. We believe that, mainly owing to this increase, the germans are finding difficulty in maintaining their present establishments. Although theshortages reported from North Africa were mainly due to difficulties of transport,the course of events indicates that from time to time there were insufficient tanksavailable to meet promptly the requirements of all fronts in full.6. The establishment of the panzer division has been reduced to 164 tanks,but this is due to the elimination of 37 PZKW IIs, which are now considered to be too light for tank squadrons. The PZKW VI (Tiger) is at the momentsuffering from teething troubles, but production of this type on a considerable scale is believed to have begun, and improved models are expected.7. In view of the priority given to production of locomotives and M/T andof the shortage of labour, tank production is likely to have fallen, but in default of any direct evidence to the contrary we have no reason to suppose that thesupply of tanks will not suffice to meet the demands of existing establishmentsexcept when heavy casualties are incurred; there may then well be some delay.
(b) Artillery.8. The establishment of divisional artillery has been in most cases reducedby 25 per cent. There is no evidence why this change was made but is probably due to a shortage of trained personnel and. not to a shortage of equipment. Allevidence tends to show that demands by formations for artillery have.beenpromptly met. The fact that the divisional artillery regiment is being completelyre-equipped with a new series of weapons suggests that a year ago, when thedecision to change over must have been taken, the Germans did not anticipate any serious difficulties in production. The heavy losses in 1942 must, however,have eaten into their reserves.9. So far no deterioration in quality has been noted of any of the newartillery equipments which, on the contrary, show a marked improvement inperformance. Last November, instructions were given to manufacturers of artillery to use no further chrome. Manufacturing artillery without chromeshould cause some deterioration in the quality of the guns and considerabledifficulty in production, especially at first, but it will be many months before suchguns are in use in large quantities. In the near future, we do not expect anyshortage of artillery for the German Army.(c) Ammunition.10. There is good evidence of a general shortage of flak ammunition of allcalibres. Issues of flak ammunition in certain areas have been reduced andexpenditure has been curtailed by the prohibition of unrestricted fire at aircraft.Widespread instructions have been issued with the object of curtailing losses dueto inefficient storage or negligent handling. In one area there has been an attemptto mitigate the shortage by cutting out one stage in the supply chain, and thus in effect reducing the amount of ammunition in store.11. The reports speaks of a strained supply situation, which in one instanceis stated to be due to a strained raw material situation and to a lack of suitablelabour.12. It is also reliably reported that, in addition to the shortage of flakammunition, there is a shortage of bombs and aircraft ammunition as well.Supplies are inadequate and a further deterioration is to be expected in the nearfuture, particularly in the supply of bombs.13. Less reliable reports indicate that this shortage may extend to other types of ammunition, but there is not sufficient direct evidence to warrant theconclusion either that stocks of army ammunition have been used up, or that ageneral shortage exists. On the other hand, it seems curious that shortages shouldbe limited to types of ammunition which are used by the G.A.F. while the german army should experience no similar difficulties. It may be, therefore, that theshortages extend over all types of ammunition, since our information about theG.A.F. on this subject is more complete than about the German Army. However,there may be special reasons for the shortages of flak ammunition and bombswhich would not apply to the production of other types of ammunition.Both have complex fuses which may be the limiting factor in production.It is known that the Germans have made great efforts to obtain fuses for flakammunition from Switzerland, but Swiss production of these for Germany hasdecreased during the last few months. Such special reasons would not explaina shortage of aircraft armament ammunition.14. There is no shortage of ordinary armour-piercing ammunition, which forms 95 per cent, of the armour-piercing ammunition used by tanks and anti-tank units. The production of armour-piercing projectiles with tungsten carbidecores, however, turns on the success or. failure of the Allied pre-emption policyin Spain and in Portugal and the number of blockade-runners carrying tungstenwhich can get through. The production of this type of ammunition istherefore in jeopardy.(d) W/T Equipment.15.   See under CAP.[25388]
(e) M/T.16. The German Armed Forces are already short of M/T. ancillary services, such as the Todt organisation, are suffering most, and captured M/Tand reduced establishments can only partly mitigate this shortage.17. Since the start of the Russian campaign, the rate of production hasbeen inadequate to meet wastage, but until recently the gap has been made goodby vehicles requisitioned from Germany or the occupied territory. The pool ofsuitable vehicles is now virtually exhausted. The Germans are making great efforts to comb out M/T from the territories they control and are accepting lorriespreviously rejected as unfit for military requirements.18. The position is likely to deteriorate. Production is increasing slightly,but it cannot be greatly increased except at the expense of the production of aircraft or tanks. In these circumstances it is unlikely that there will be a material increase in production this year. We, therefore, foresee an increasingshortage of M/T. which may have become very grave by the end of the year.(f) Automatic Pistols.19.   There is some evidence of a shortage of automatic pistols.(g) Rubber.20. There is no evidence of a shortage of tyres so acute as to hamper opera-tions, nor is one likely to arise in the next few months. However, provided nofurther blockade runners get through, there will be an acute shortage of naturalrubber, which will probably mean that tyres will have to be made entirely of synthetic rubber, with a consequent deterioration in performance, especially in extreme cold. A shortage of natural rubber may also affect the quality of aircraftfuel tanks, engine-mountings, and high flying equipment, solid tyres and engine-mountings on A.F.Vs. and certain medical equipment,(h) Medical Supplies.21. There are shortages of various types of medical supplies, notable quinineand morphine.(i) Clothing.22. There is no shortage in the quantity of ordinary army clothing, but thequality is deteriorating. Winter clothing for the Russian Front is inadequate in quantity and quality.(j) Locomotives and Rolling Stock.23. There is an acute shortage of locomotives. Besides affecting internaldistribution, there is some evidence that it may have delayed military movements.The same applies to rolling-stock. Both shortages are likely to continue, but their future effect on military movements depends upon the theatres where fightingtakes place.III. The German Air Force.(a) Aircraft.24. In spite of a net increase in output in 1942 as compared with 1941,the German Air Force was unable to increase its total strength, and in factshowed a decline. As was stated in J.I.C. (43) 40, paragraph 52, the relativestrengths in 1942 and 1943 were :  &apos;February 1942.   February 1943.First-line Strength (Actual)      ... 4,040 4,000Aircraft with R.T.U....... 550 600Stored Reserves    ......... 600 650Training (Operational Types)    ... 1,600 1,000Total   ...... 6,790 6,25025. The output of fighter aircraft increased more rapidly in 1942 than thatof other types. There is firm evidence that the Germans intended to expand the single engine fighter force in 1942, but, in spite of this and of the production of1,300 more single-engine fighters than in the previous year, the actual strengthof S.E. fighters did not materially increase.   Recent indications confirm that on
all fronts the total number of fighters available is felt by the enemy to be insufficient to meet operational requirements.26. We think it fair to say that the German Air Force is suffering from arelative shortage of aircraft, i.e.. that while by various expedients the germans have been able to maintain the actual strength of front line units, they have,nevertheless, had insufficient aircraft to meet their strategical commitments.27. With regard to the future, production has on average remained constantover the last six months. There is probably now some reduction in repairthroughput, due to the number of aircraft abandoned in Russia and North Africaduring the winter. ft is probable that, as a result of German economic difficulties and the growing effect of air raid damage on industry, total output ofnew and repaired aircraft for 1943 will be less than that of 1942. If at the sametime high rates of wastage on all Fronts continue, shortage of aircraft in theGA-F. might become acute, at the end of this year. But it is clear that theGermans are carefully husbanding their resources, and are likely to continue thispolicy in order to prevent such a situation arising. Wastage will be the decisivefactor, and, should they be successful in avoiding battle, they will probably make good the deficiency at least as far as fighters are concerned.(c) Munitions and Bombs and (d) M/T.28.   See under German Army.(e) W/T Equipment.29. Reliable reports indicate a general shortage of W/T equipment for theG.A.F. and the Army. Replacements have not always been available owing to ashortage in production. There is also evidence that damage affecting productionin the signals industry, including that section of it producing R.D.F. equipment,has been caused by air raids.30. Although a recent report indicates that a need for economy may now have arisen in the R.D.F. organisation, this may well be temporary. AVe haveno further evidence of shortage of R.D.F. equipment. On the contrary, we know that, consequent upon the recent heavy expansion of the German R.D.F. aircraftreporting system and of their night fighter organisation, there has been a greatlyincreased demand for R.D.F. equipment of all kinds, together with its com-munications apparatus. This demand has so far been met in full, and this is evidence that this side of signals manufacture is being given priority.31. Reading these reports in conjunction with the fact that a number of factories manufacturing signals equipment are known to have been hit duringAllied air raids on Germany and Occupied territories, we consider it reasonable to deduce that a shortage of ordinary W/T equipment does exist in the german army and Air Force. The shortages are due probably to continual changes of design.   If these continue, as they are likely to do, so will the shortages.IV. The German Navy.(a) Minesweepers.32. The German Navy has insufficient minesweepers to cope with theAllied sea-mining effort. Although some 60 new minesweepers are under construction and shipyards in the Baltic and Occupied countries are being brought back to use, the deficiency cannot be remedied except at the expense ofmerchant ship and other essential production. We cannot say how the germans will utilise their building resources, but it is unlikely that they will so concentrate on minesweepers as to make good the present deficiency. The shortages willprobably continue, therefore, provided the existing scale of Allied sea mining is continued.(b) Naval Ammunition.33. Early this year we received a single report of a shortage of depth charges for the Black Sea. There has been no mention of any shortage of any othernaval ammunition, and accordingly it is considered that this is a purely local and ephemeral problem.34. Destruction of naval ammunition dumps has occurred at Wilhelmshavenand at Rennes, but as yet there have been no reports of shortages of torpedoes,warheads, &amp;c.
(c) Merchant Shipping.35. German merchant shipping in Northern Waters is becoming increasingly short, but there is no evidence that this has a fleeted the movement ofsupply of the Armed Forces.V. Future Developments.36. Apart from the shortage of particular types of equipment already referred to, there are general factors which in varying degrees will tend to reducethe scale of German munitions output.   These are : (i) Shortage and deterioration of labour, particularly of skilled labour,(ii) Shortage of transportation facilities.(iii) Shortage of certain types of capital equipment.(iv) Shortage of certain raw materials.(v) Toss and diversion of resources to make good air raid damage.(i) Labour. As a result of the heavy comb-out for the forces the supply oflabour for munitions will be less in 1943 than in 1942 in spite of large transfersfrom less essential occupations. The quality of the labour force is rapidlydeteriorating and training facilities are inadequate to cope with new entrants.There will be sufficient labour for first priority munitions, but competition for skilled labour is likely to lead to bottlenecks in certain linos of production. the products most likely to suffer from labour shortage will be determined by theprogramme of priorities. At present it would seem that submarine and aircraft production will have first calls.(ii) Transport. Increasing transport difficulties both by road and rail will help to slow up production particularly since stocks in German industry havebeen reduced to low levels. At present the effects of this factor arc so well-spread as not to be readily assessable.(iii) Capital Equipment. There is evidence of certain shortage of sometypes of machine tools. This may hamper production to some extent, andparticularly any change over to new types of equipment.(iv) Raw materials. So far as basic products are concerned e.g., coal,steel, aluminium--any shortages are likely to be less important than labour and transportation difficulties in the production of most intermediate and finalproducts. On the other hand, shortages of copper, chrome, nickel andmolybdenum will reduce the quantity, as well as the quality, since substitutes willbe more difficult to work.(v) Air raids. The effects of air raids on the output of munitions may he ofthree kinds : (1) Direct destruction of plant.(2) Diversion of raw materials and labour from munitions work to restorationof damage, and other indirect consequences of air attacks(absenteeism. &amp;c).(3) Diversion of supplies of clothing and other consumer goods from the armed forces to bombed-out civilians. There is as yet little if any evidence of this.37. The effect of air raids obviously depends on the scale and success of ourgrowing; attack.Of the remaining factors, the shortage of labour is of prime importance andwill be accentuated by the reactions of air raids on labour productivity. Althoughquantitative assessment is difficult it is probable that labour and transport difficulties will cause a further fall in the overall output of munitions over thenext year. The extent of the fall will be influenced by Germany&apos;s success inblockade running.38. A reduction in ouptut of German munitions of war would not of itselfproduce shortages. The rate of wastage is of prime importance. Assuming thatfighting is at least on the same scale as in 1942, shortages are likely to developincreasingly. The Germans will make every effort to minimise such shortagesby economies of expenditure and by adjusting their production to meet as far aspossible the more pressing deficiencies. Such enforced economies would, however,of themselves affect German fighting power and Germany cannot increase outputof one type of munition except at the expense of other essential porduction. Itis impossible to forecast with accuracy when and on what Front shortages will seriously hamper German operations.



</content>
</cab>
