<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/23/15 images: 112-121</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
z 7/.-3/Wfs- a a * )&quot;&quot;HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY &apos;S;&quot; &quot;   GOV.ERNMBNT. &quot;/SECRET..$6th March, 1942.copy NO.WAR    CABINETPOSITION OP CIVILIANS EVACUATED PROM THE PAR EAST TO THEDOMINIONS AND india memorandum &quot;by the Secretary of St at efor Dominion Affairs.I circulate to my colleagues a memorandum preparedby representatives of the various Departments concerned,whichdescribes the present position as regards civilians incertain of the Dominions and in India who have been evacuated from the Par East, and recommends that,/in view of various considerations which are set out, a policy of &quot;stay put&quot;should be adopted as regards all refugees from Colonies andother places occupied or threatened by the enemy and asregards- persons now resident in those territories for whomthe United Kingdom Government or a Colonial Government areresponsible. JThe detailed recommendations of the Departments are set out in paragraph 5 of the memorandum and are concurred inby all the Departments concerned, with the exception of the india Office.C.R. A.DOMINIONS OPPIGE,26th March,  1942.

Position of civilians evacuated from the Far East in theDominions and in Jlndia,Memorandum prepared in discussion between Departments.X. This memorandum deals with a problem which has arisen at Inter-departmental meetings concerned with the detailed arrangements to be made for persons who have become, or might in future &quot;become, evacuees from territories in the Par East.     The following Departments have been represented at these meetings and have collaborated in the preparation of the memorandum;-   Treasury,Foreign Office, Dominions Office, Colonial Office, India Office, Burma Office,Admiralty, War Office, Air Ministry, Ministry of Health, Ministry of Labour,Ministry of War Transport.2, Briefly, the problem is to determine whether those desiring to returnto this country, or to move from territory to territory overseas, should beallowed to do so, or whether a general &quot;stay put&quot; order should be enforced.3* The present position may be summarised as follows: -A, As a result of conditions in the Far East, the wives and families ofService personnel, and of many civilians, have been evacuated from Hong Kong,Malaya, Singapore and elsewhere, mainly to Australia, South Africa, Burma andIndia.     Many of these evacuees wish to return to the United Kingdom and thereis a growing desire, for various reasons, on the part of the Dominions and ofIndia to send back as many as possible to this country.     The numbers involved are at present unknown but it may be taken that they are of considerablemagnitude.     Upwards of 2,000 civilians were evacuated from Hong Kong, and some9,000 from Malaya.     While a number of the latter proceeded to India, it isbelieved that the great majority is now in the Dominions,     Evacuees have alsoreached the Dominions from occupied China, and elsewhere.     Moreover there arein the Dominions a considerable number of service families some of whom wereevacuated from Middle East theatres of war,B. The following is a rough statement of the situation in the variousterritories concerned:-Australia.   The United Kingdom High Commissioner has been asked by anumber of civilian evacuees now in Australia whether passages to the UnitedKingdom can be given to them at Government expense.     In addition, the ImperialPaymaster has asked all military families evacuated to Australia whether they wish to return to the United Kingdom, passages being provided.     The HighCommissioner points out that if passages are to be afforded to the families ofService personnel it would be difficult to refuse similar treatment to civilians.South Africa.     The line which the High Commissioner, inconsultation with the Government of the Union of South Africa, proposed to takewas to allow only women with children, who desired to remain in the Union, todo so provided that adequate funds were available from outside the war zone tomaintain them.     The High Commissioner   pointed out, however, that the UnionGovernment were most helpful and were ready to admit any British women andchildren for the duration of the war provided the United Kingdom Government would assume responsibility for maintenance and ultimate repatriation,The High Commissioner was advised that the policy should be to discourage&apos;women with children from returning to the United Kingdom and toencourage them to settle in the Union for the war period, if necessary at theexpense of H.M. Government, and that this should be applied to anyone else of either sex who was not able-bodied and fit for active employment.     Maintenanceat public expense could not, however, be afforded to childless women capableof work, except for an initial period of one month.    The High Commissioneragreed, but said that childless women would not be encouraged to stay in theUnion in view of the probability that they would not be able to maintainthemselves by obtaining work in the Union.&quot;... 55SECRETIndia-
India.     The Government of India have pointed out that there are in &apos;India large numbers of wives and families of British Service personnel, and thatthe numbers will increase with the arrival of families frcm Singapore and burma and with fixture moves overseas.     Their presence is said to present a serious  &apos;internal security problem which, with the approach of hostilities to the frontiers of India, causes the Government over increasing concern.The Government of India have been in communication with theGovernment of the Union of South Africa about an offioial schemo of evacuationto South Africa, but the response by the evacuees is poor so far owing to lack of information as to living facilities.Gey Ion.,      The Commander in Chief, Ceylon, on the 12th March announcedplans for evacuating oertain categories of persons from Ceylon.     Thosecategories are:-(1)   Nonresident s.All persons&quot;Ifincluding wives and children of Service personnel) whoare not employed in essential war work.    These were instructedto leave as soon as passages wore available.(2)   Residents.Non-Ceylonese wemen with young children who are not employed on war or important social work.     These have been advised to leave assoon as they conveniently could.These instructions were issued without reference to London, and the-Commander in Chief has been asked to telegraph at once further information.4. The Departments represented at the meetings were, with the exceptionof the India Office, in full agreement as to the desirability of enforcing the &quot;stay put&quot; policy.     The arguments advanced by individual Departmentsmay be summarised as followsDcminions Office.    It must be recognised that a &quot;stay put&quot; policy would involve as a conseqxience leaving evacuees in places where they may be exposed to enemy attack, especially in Australia.     It would also involvepossibly exposing to the same dangers Children&apos;s Overseas Reception Boardchildren in Australia who were evacuated in order to secure their greatersafety.    But, in view of the difficulties set out in the rest of this paper and of the overriding requirements of the war effort, it seems clear thatthis consequence must be faced.     On the other hand an additional difficultyin the way of adopting any but a &quot;stay put&quot; policy in the case of the far east evacuees is that it would be very difficult to extend to them facilitiesfor repatriation without offering similar facilities for Children^ overseasReception Board children, whose parents, in view of enemy aggression in and around Australia, must be alarmed over the safety of their children evacuatedthere.Moreover the Commonwealth Government and public might well be critical of the use of shipping space, etc., and of the expenditure of effortgenerally, in connection with repatriation from Australia at a time when thepopulation of Australia as a whole is facing the dangers of Japanese attack.There would be grave political objections in Australia to anything which mightbe construed there as savoring of a &quot;scuttle&apos; policy.     The same considerations would apply, although in a lessor degree, to the removal of evacuees at presentin New Zealand.The Admiralty view i3 that, having regard to all the factors in the ^present situation, they would encourage the restriction of movement of all non-essential persons to the absolute minimum both outward and homeward at any rateduring the next 3 or U- months.The Admiralty is not desirous that any privileged treatment shouldbe given to families of Naval personnel.The Ministry of War Transport may be taken as sharing the view exprcs^by the Admiralty.    They have further represented that, whilst removal ofpersons from India to South Africa and from Australia to South Africa or Canaa-ca*i
can be arranged by the use of such spare ship accommodation as from time totime becomes available, the provision of special ships for the purpose,either in the near future or as part of a long term policy, could not bejustified at the present time.All passenger ships under the control of the Ministry are now on service as troop transports (or hospital ships).-    YJhere these troop transportsare homward bound they are not necessarily escorted and, in the case ofunescorted ships, limitations are placed upon the numbers which may beembarked.    Accordingly, any proposal to embark passengers in addition to service personnel, up to the full capacity of the ships, may involve theAdmiralty in the provision of additional escorts.     This has, in fact,already happened in the case of a ship which brought refugees from the far east to the U.K.As regards removal from Australia to the U.K., troopships homewardbound are used to full capacity for troops and airmen on at least one leg of\the journey;   if large numbers of other passengers were placed aboard itwould not be possible for these to continue on that ship for the full journey  \to UiK, and they would have to be transhipped, either in South Africa or Canada,possibly having to wait for a considerable period before onward shipmentcould be arranged*-SBrojn India there are likely to be more frequent sailings, but thereis an existent demand to provide shipment for some thousands of italian prisoners whose presence in the U,1Z, is desired owing to the shortage of manpower.     Again, however, conveyance to South Africa would be less difficultthan from South Africa to the U,IuFor these reasons, the view of the Ministry is that, while provisioncould be made to move civilian refugees and Service families in certainnumbers from time to time, no reliable estimate can be given of the number which could be moved.    They urge that it would not be justifiable, at this time, to place such a strain on our shipping resources, and that the persons concerned should remain where they are at present.The War Office, are not prepared to ask for preferential treatment in respect of British Service families domiciled in India and agree, therefore^that a &quot;stay put&quot; policy should be accepted, in general terms.    Theyemphasise, however, that if this policy is accepted, it must be capable ofvariation to meet special and. specific cases, either individual or group, as and when occasion demands,The&apos; Air Ministry, has expressed itself as in agreement with theview taken&apos;&quot;by&quot;theljar Office-,The Ministry of Health are concerned with the problem of findingaccommodation for refugees who come to this Country,Demands an accommodation are acute.    There have been practically no new houses built for the last two years and a number of houses have been destroyed.    As a result of evacuation and the transfer of industry thepopulation in. certain parts of the Country (notably the East and South EastcoastsO have been thinned out.    The pressure on accommodation in other partsof the country has been correspondingly greater.     Evacuation, the transferof industry and the needs of the Services have called for the widespread use    jof billeting during the last 2-j years.     This has put a great strain onaccommodation and on the services of the householders affected.     these demands continue to be made for current war-time requirements, and it becomes increasingly difficult to meet them.Considerable provision has already been made during the war forrefugees.     It is becaning more and more difficult to billet them even whenthey are British, and refugees from the continent - both British and alien -are continually arriving.    Plans have been prepared to deal with refugees,both British and foreign, including some thousands from Gibraltar who may come to this country in the event of an attack on Gibraltar through Spain.The position of refugees from the Continent is, however, very different&quot;fromthat of those from the Par East.     For the former this country offers possibly the only sanctuary;   for the latter the Dominions are available and closerat hand.     The difficulties of helping refugees will be accentuated in thecase
case of those from the Far East, accustomed to a very different standard of living and conditions generally, and it may he doubted whether in the matter of employingthey would be generally of much use to the war effort.Unless, thearefore, there are overwhelming grounds for bringing refugees from the Far East to thin country for reasons of general policy, the Ministryof Health consider that this action should be avoided in view of thedifficulties which their reception would undoubtedly cause.Ministry of lab our.    A decision to aoply generally a &quot;stay put&quot;order should not affect the transfer overseas, to or from this country, ofpersons accepted for employment as possessing qualifications needed for theWar Effort, either in the Armed Forces or in civil employment.(A). Treasury;.     If a &quot;stay put&quot; policy were adopted, it would, of course, benecessary to make advances, as required, from public funds for the maintenance of theunable to support themselves.    In the case of evacuees formerly resident inColonies, the charge would normally be on the funds of the Colony, supported,if these funds were inadequate, by His Majesty&apos;s Government in the UnitedKingdom.     Grants would be made only where resources were not available to the individuals concerned, would be reduced in cases where the individual could contriktto the cost of maintenance, and would be regarded as recoverable from theindividual in so far..as recovery may prove practicable.     It has already been necessary to agree in principle that the cost of maintaining evacuees receivedby a Dominion should not be a charge on the Dominions own. funds.    the detailed arrangements present considerable complications, and affect a numberof&quot; Departments,     They are being worked out as expeditious ly a3 is possible with the Dominion authorities,(B) On the Exchange side, the Treasury would be concerned if any decisions were taken which led to a demand for dollars for the maintenanceof evacuees in Canada or the U.S.A,, or for travelling expenses.    From thispoint of view, there is the strongest possible objection to assisting orpermitting groups of evacuees to proceed to dollar countries.Foreign Office,    It is thought probable that there are a number ofevacuees from the Netherlands East Indies in Australia, and possibly elsewhere.It is clear that, if a &quot;stay put&quot; policy were enforced, Dutch evacuees, orany other allied nationals, could not be given preferential treatment ascompared with British subjects.    The Foreign Office would be responsible forany communications which -would have to be made to Allied Governments.The India Office are concerned with the following three questions ;-(i)   The disposal of European evacuees arriving in India from Malaya,Singapore, and Burma,     For the reasons given in (ii), which apply with even greater force in this category, the Government of Indiacannot readily acquiesce in a &quot;stay put&quot; policy.    As a measure of urgency and without prejudice to the general question, the Governmentof India have been permitted to evacuate a certain number of the refugees in transports which recently left Bombay.(ii)   The evacuation of the families in India of British Service personnelwho are serving overseas.     On this subject a definite recommendationhas come from the Government of India, who are most anxious to evacuate such families immediately,(a)   because of the serious internal security problem they presentwhich, with the approach of hostilities to the frontier of India,is causing the Government of India, ever increasing concern;because of the great difficulty of finding suitable accommodation for European families in India,    The strain on accommodation is great, and is likely to increase, and it is impossible to relieveit by building camps and hutments except at the expense of essential military projects.     Moreover climatically there are few localities which ore suitable for large concentrations of europeans, and such places as are approximately suitable arealready full to capacity.(b)It
It will be. realised tliat the position in India as regardsaccommodation is fundamentally different from that an a Dominion, orin the U.K., however great the pressure on actual accommodation maybe in the latter case.(iii)   The possible evacuation from India of European families generally,i.e. families of Indian Army Officers, of the Civil Services, andof the business and commercial community.   Reference to this category is made only to complete the picture.   The question has not&quot;been raised by, or with, the Government of India, and it is not considered desirable, that His lajestv^s Government should take any decision in advance on this problem, which is of greater political importance than those falling under (i) and (ii).   The connection ofthese families with India is plainly closer than that of the familiesreferred to above.5, It seems necessary to ask for a ruling by higher authority on thequestion of the general policy to be adopted in this matter. The conclusions which seem to emerge from the foregoing analysis, and are now recommended for acceptance, the India Office dissenting, may be summarised as follows:-(i)   A policy of &quot;stay-put&quot; in the territories to which they have been evacuated should be adopted as regards all refugees from colonies and other places occupied or threatened by the enemy.   The samepolicy should be applied to persons now residing in these territories for whom the United Kingdom Government, or a colonial government is responsible.   In so far as is necessary, theconcurrence of Dominion Governments in the policy recommended shouldbe securedo   It is understood that the &quot;stay put&quot; order proposed,as regards evacuation overseas, is generally in line with thepolic3r which the Territories in question are themselves adopting asregards their own population.The Admiralty have emphasized that for similar reasons movementof non-essential persons from the United Kingdom to places overseasshould also be banned,The adoption of this policy v/ould mean (e.) that assistance from public funds, whether by way of grant or loan, should not be givento evacuees to enable them to return to the United Kingdom, or tomove overseas from one Empire territory to another, and (b) thatsea passages should be refused even to those who are in a positionto pay their own way, or are normally entitled to passages. Anydifferentiation between those two classes would seriously weaken the &quot;stay-put&quot; policy, and would be open to criticism as givingunjustifiable advantage to evacuees with means.\ii)   Under the Policy so far communicated to the Dominions assistancefrom public funds may be given only as a purely temporary measure, inthe case of women not in charge of children, who are &quot;capable ofcontributing to the war effort&quot;.   The above proposals would involvea modification of this policy to the extent that facilities forreturn would not be given, even to persons generally capable, unless there were some specific and definite demand for their services inthis country.   All others would have to be given assistance, as required, from public funds towards their maintenance in the placesto which they have been evacuated.   But the strongest possiblepressure should, of course, be put on evacuees to obtain work, ifavailable, in these places.(iii) It will be seen from the India Office contribution to thismemorandum that&apos; there are difficulties, which may or may not be decisive, in the way of applying an unqualified &quot;stay-put&quot; policyin India,   But, in view of the opinion held so strongly on a variety of grounds that the general application of such a policy isdesirable, if not essential, it seems clear that the view of theGovernment
Government of India in favour of evacuating service families atpresent in India, and refugees from occupied territories, shouldnot he accepted, at least until a reasoned case for leavingthese categories in India has been put to the Government of India,If in the future it should be decided to evacuate from India or,in the light of prevailing circuriistances, from other territoriescertain limited groups or classes, e,g,, service families,arrangement should if possible be made for their receptionelsewhere than in the United Kingdom.   (There are very strong objections on currency grounds to removing evacuees to placesoutside the sterling area).If permission has to be given on special grounds for the evacuation of a particular group or class, this must be treated as exeptional and without prejudice to the decision about other categories.



</content>
</cab>
