<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/31/36 images: 416-421</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/   /THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  November 1942.--------J--MOST SECRET. Copy No.ii[[itij      ..... Ml 1W.P. (42) 556.November 28, 1942.TO BE , JKEPT^ UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.MAN-POWER.Note by the Prime Minister and Minister of Defence.THE available resources of man-power for the period the 1st July, 1942, tothe end of 1943 fall short of the stated demands of the Services and of the munitions industries by at least 1,089,000.* The existing programme on whichthese demands are based must therefore be revised. This revision will take intoaccount the following : 2. The greatest danger which now confronts us is the U-boat peril. Wemust expect attack by increasingly large numbers and spread over wider areas.The highest priority must therefore be accorded to vessels and weapons for use against the U-boat. No construction of merchant shipbuilding below,100,000 tons or slowing down of repair work can be accepted.The Admiralty must save labour at the cost of some retardation in other partsof the programme, particularly in the construction of men-of-war of the largercategories (battleships and cruisers). If necessary, some of the larger vesselsmust be put into reserve. The R. battleships should be considered in thisconnection.3. It is unlikely that the enemy will again be able to bring to bear against this country as heavy a weight of air attack as two years ago, still less to keep it* The estimate of 939,000 given in paragraph 7 of W.P. (42) 539 took into account the arbitrary cut of 150,000 mentioned in paragraph 3 of that Paper.[24685]
up so long. Further reductions should therefore be made in Civil Defence andin A.D.G.B., and still greater use should be made of the Home Guard for duties with the latter. The reserves of anti-aircraft ammunition in this country donot need to increase with the number of A.A. guns. We shall not require to firemore rounds than we fired in the blitz of two years ago. A considerable numberof anti-aircraft equipments will be needed for the defence of the North african coast and for supply to Turkey.   This must also be at the expense of A.D.G.B.4. It can be assumed as a working rule that invasion or large-scale airborneattack are unlikely. This assumption must be constantly reviewed. meanwhile it will enable reductions to be made in the upkeep of our static defences. Forexample, the R.A.F. Regiment and coast defences can be reduced. Again, theHome Guard should not be raised above the ceiling of If million, and of this number, say, \ million should be temporarily relegated to a reserve from whichthey can be recalled as and when required.5. The assumption already made by the War Office that, with the exceptionof the forces in or destined for the North African and Mediterranean areas,the British Armies will not be engaged on a large scale with heavy casualties and expenditure of ammunition before the end of June 1943 can beaccepted. The wastage occurring in the first nine months of 1943 will be met from men called up before the end of 1942. The Army will also benefit largely from the economies resulting from the assumptions in (3) and (4) above. these factors, together with a drastic pruning of the staffs, also of ancillary units and establishments, and a definite reduction in the establishments of Corps, Army,and line of communication units, should enable the Army during 1943 to formand maintain the organisation set out in my W.P. (42) 504.6. The results of (3), (4) and (5) will enable a substantial reduction to bemade in the War Office demands on the Ministry of Supply, more particularlyin miscellaneous stores and equipment. It is incumbent on the Army authoritiesto see that these demands are reduced as soon as possible. So great is thestringency of man-power that only by this means can a reduction be avoided inthe effective fighting strength of the Army.7. The demands of the Royal Air Force and of the Ministry of aircraft production should be governed by the fact that it is more important at present to increase the output of aircraft than the number of officers and other ranks inthe R.A.F. A cut in the demands of the R.A.F. for air ground staff cannot be avoided. By concentrating on essentials, the most effective use must be made ofthat which is available.8. Chemical warfare supplies are now approaching their very high target figure; and while special items should be taken care of, and the power to openout production if necessary should be retained, a very general curtailment shouldbe possible.
9. In the light of the above, I put before my colleagues and the Chiefs ofStaff for their earnest consideration the following proposed reductions in their demands : (In thousands.)Original Demands.Cut Proposed.AdmiraltyArmySupply ....E.A.F.....M.A.P.....Civil DefenceMiscellaneousf Men\ WomenMenWomenMenWomen287 )36 )649)160)365)107)323186 (shipbuilding)809148472MenWomenMenWomenMenWomen601530080185)40)75380215225603 7513 *100135 192,689 1,089* This is in addition to existing arrangements for the withdrawal of 20,000 men and 4,000women from Civil Defence. Taking account of the new demand for 13,000 women for these services, the net reduction now proposed is 113,000.10. Even the estimate of man-power supply at 1,600,000 may well provebeyond our powers. The health and efficiency of the people must not be damaged by new stresses; The work of the central departments of government must notbe deranged for the sake of getting a few hundred highly trained individuals onto the barrack square. We have no dhoice but to spread the inevitable reductionof new demands in the least harmful manner. Thus, although the task before mycolleagues presents great difficulties and will involve many inconveniences and indeed hardships, I ask them, both to accept the reductions, and to apply themwith the best housekeeping ingenuity, so as to keep all we can of the increasedoffensive power of the Services.11. Every effort must also be made by the Minister of Production, aided by the Minister of Labour and National Service and the Supply Ministers, tomake the necessary adjustments and simplifications in existing programmes insuch a way that the quality of our equipment is made the highest aim, that theproduction of obsolescent and redundant stores is cut out, and that the call-upof fit men works the minimum of evil. If by careful planning further economy oflabour can be made in the munition industries, the armed forces will receive thebenefit in the shape of increased intakes for the second half of 1943.Any reductions in supply will relieve the Import Programme and shippingstringency.   These should be noted by the Ministry of War Transport.12. The assumptions and figures in this Note relate to the period up to31st December, 1943, and Departments should frame their long-term plans onthis basis. The position will, however, be reviewed before the end of June 1943,in the light of strategic developments.w. s. c.10 Downing Street, S.W.1.November 28, 1942.




</content>
</cab>
