<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/10/36 images: 382-389</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   August 1940.gOST SECRET. Copy No.W.P- W 305-August 7, 1940.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.      *ROYAL AIR FORCE TRAINING.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.I SUBMITTED to the War Cabinet a month ago a paper on the subject ofE.A.F. training (W.P. (40) 238). I now circulate a further paper outlining the steps which have since been taken and are now about to be taken to build up thestrength of Royal Air Force squadrons and to accelerate the training output. Ipreface this account with a statement indicating briefly the scope and natureof the training problem.2. The production of the aircraft factories in this country has been greatlyincreased; we are obtaining from the U.S.A. deliveries on French aircraft ordersas well as our own; and the Minister of Aircraft Production has now obtainedfrom the U.S.A. an offer of an additional 3,000 aircraft a month, to materialiselater. Our aim must be to man wuth pilots and use in battle or on the trainingfield all the aircraft which this great capacity produces.3.   The position which immediately confronts the Air Ministry is this.On the basis of the production of operational type aircraft forecast in theMinister of Aircraft Production^ latest programme, and leaving out of accountall other factors, it would be possible, after allowing for wastage, to build upa force next August of over 4,000 first line aircraft as compared with some 2,700at the present time. Such a force would require over 8,000 pilots and crews inoperational squadrons alone, as compared with 4,400 employed in the squadrons at present.4. A force can, however, only be made effective to the extent to which it ispossible to build up an adequate training organisation and to build it up inadvance. That organisation must expand at a sufficiently rapid rate to produceair crews and maintenance personnel not only for the initial manning of thenew squadrons, but also for the replacement of wastage for the expanding force.At the same time the expanding training organisation must produce flying andmaintenance personnel for the new training units themselves. And advantagecan only be taken of an acceleration of the production of operational type aircraftif that increase is preceded approximately six months beforehand by a similarincrease in the production of trainer types.5. The present great increase in the production of operational types, both inthe United Kingdom and America, could not be foreseen and was not precededeither by a corresponding increase in the production of trainer aircraft or by anadequate expansion in the war training organisation. Yet it is impossible to achieve an ultimate expansion of the first line without an immediate expansionof the training organisation; and in present circumstances the latter can only he achieved at the cost of a temporary restriction of the first line, since it is uponurst line squadrons that we must, in the main, draw for the necessary instructorsarid to a less extent for the maintenance personnel.[21605] b
6. As regards training aircraft, calculations which have been made in theAir Ministry show that, in order to produce the crews required to man theexpanded force of next summer, we ought to have at the present time over 2,000more trainer aircraft in service for training purposes than we have. To make good this deficiency and build up the training organisation to the appropriatelevel, we ought to have in all before March next a total of over 6,000 trainer typeaircraft (excluding elementary trainers) as compared with a total of 4,200 pro-vided in the latest Ministry of Aircraft Production forecast. These figures donot relate to the recently promised delivery of an additional 3,000 aircraft amonth from the U.S.A.; but it is already apparent that for this vast new-programme as well there will be difficulty in obtaining trainers at the early daterequired, and the programme itself will have to include the appropriateproportion of trainers.7. A further and most important factor is that a balanced training schemerequires not only an early provision of trainer aircraft, but also preparation foethe provision of aerodromes and accommodation to be undertaken many months in advance of the arrival &amp;f the aircraft. It is necessary for the schools to be in working order from seven to eleven months before the trained air crews arerequired; while the training of instructors for the schools has to be undertakenbefore the schools begin to operate. The preparation of an additional number of aerodromes in the United Kingdom is proceeding rapidly, but we are certain tohave to resort in increasing measures to facilities elsewhere. Here also provisionlags seriously behind the new and unforeseen requirements.8. I have considered it desirable to set before the War Cabinet now thisbrief conspectus of the problem which confronts us. It follows that, subject to the primary necessity of maintaining during the next two months the strength of fighter Command, we must, in order to balance our training programme, impose a temporary limitation on our operational strength during the coming autumn and winter. A marked alteration in the aircraft production programme will certainly be called for. As I have said, the many factors involved are underurgent examination in the Air Ministry; the present paper therefore makes no attempt at finality.9. I turn now to the steps which have been taken during the past month andwhich are immediately in prospect to improve the position. I am glad to beable to report that a material improvement has been effected in the crewstrength of the Royal Air Force, notably in the Fighter Command; that aconsiderable accession of strength is to be expected from the allied air force personnel now in this country; that additional measures have been taken which will further speed up the output from the flying training organisation;and that arrangements are in hand for establishing additional training schoolsoverseas and for transferring to the Dominions certain of the schools in thiscountry where training is being hindered by operational requirements.Pilot Strength.10. The deficiency of pilots is most seriously felt in Coastal Command, andthe situation has been aggravated by the double move of the general reconnaissance School from Guernsey to Hooton Park and from Hooton Park toSquires Gate. The position in Coastal Command, both in regard to pilots and wireless operator air gunners, is receiving close attention.11. Turning now to Fighter Command, it is within the knowledge of theWar Cabinet that, at the conclusion of the intensive tignung over France and flanders, the pilot strength of the Fighter Command was a matter for grave con-cern. The increase of the pilot establishment of each squadron of 16 aircraft from21 pilots to 26 had already been shown to be advisable, but had not proved possibleto put into effect, and the unprecedented intensity with which the operations wereconducted resulted in a most serious deficiency of pilots. As a result of the stepsalready taken to speed up training, not only has the wastage been made good,but the strength of the fighter squadrons has almost been brought up to the newestablishment, and a further four fighter squadrons have been formed. Duringthe worst phase Of the recent battle the pilot deficiency in Fighter Commandamounted to some 300. Now it is 74 on the increased total establishment of1,460. On the present rate of wastage this deficiency will, I hope, be overtaken bythe end of this month.
12. In Bomber Command the wastage of pilots incurred in the mediumbomber squadrons during the battle in France has been overcome, but we havenot yet been able to bring the heavy bomber squadrons fully up to establishment,although we are within measurable distance of doing so. The deficiency is now102 on an establishment of 1,230.13. An increase in crew strength, however, particularly in pilots, isnecessary not only to overtake existing deficiencies, but also to form the founda-tion for future expansion, for which the first essential is an increase in our. wartraining organisation; and with this end in view we must both increase stillfurther the yield from our existing training organisation and use to the best advantage the invaluable addition of strength that we have received from allied air forces.The Acceleration of Flying Training.14. In my previous paper I mentioned four measures that had been taken and would increase the output very considerably. The effect of these measures isalready apparent. The output of pupils from the Service flying training schoolsduring June and July as compared with the programme was as follows : Planned under Original Programme ...      ...      ...        816Planned under Shortened Courses    ...       ...      ...      1,020Actual     ...       ...       ...      .........       ...      1,14115.   Certain further steps have now been taken :-(i) Arrangements have been made to transfer part of the advanced training at present carried out at certain Service flying training schools onadvanced trainer types (i.e., the types which have acted as the limiting factor on the expansion of the training organisation) to the opera-tional training units where this training will be carried out on servicetype aircraft. This will give pilots more flying, and in particularmore armament training, on the Service type they will fly in the operational squadrons.(ii) In order to test the possibility of increasing the yield from the existing service flying training schools, the experiment is being tried of over-bearing 25 per cent, of pupils at certain schools without any increasein the establishment of instructors or any reduction in the number of hours flown per pupil. If this experiment succeeds, it will be-extended to the remaining schools,(iii) Consideration is being given, in order to relieve the shortage of advanced trainers, to the possibility of making further use for training purposes of Service type aircraft that are available by transferringa further fortnight&apos;s training from the Service flying training schoolsto the operational training units. The detailed implications of thisscheme are being worked out as a matter of urgency.These proposals will involve the formation of more operational training unitswith their complement of instructional personnel withdrawn from first line units;and additional aerodromes will also be required. At the same time these additional operational training units will create an additional reserve of great value in emergency.16. Concurrently with these measures a special investigation is being carriedout as to means of improving the serviceability of aircraft in the Plying training schools, and I am grateful to the Minister of Aircraft Production for thearrangements which he has made for working parties from aircraft factories to assist in the repair work at the schools.17. If these measures prove practicable, the increase in the average weeklyoutput from the 12 Service flying training schools engaged in training pilots forthe R.A.F. in this country will have been doubled as shown in the followingtable:- &amp;Original ProgrammePresent shortened coursesUnder (i)Under (i) and (ii) ...Under (i), (ii) and (iii)   .102123136170204,    18.   The intensification of effort will undoubtedly impose a heavy strain onthe training organisation, and it will be necessary to exercise the utmost vigilancem regard both to quality of output and to rate of accident during training[21605] B 2
19. I hope that it will be possible to apply some, at least of these measures tothe Empire Air Training Scheme, and this possibility is being examined as amatter of urgency.    .20. Apart, however, from these special measures, I am also able to reportthat, provided additional Battle and Anson aircraft can be made availabh^Jof thiscountry, we can expect a considerable acceleration in the output of pilots underthe Empire Air Training Scheme. In the case of Canada, this crucial improve-ment has been effected, that the maximum output of 300 pilots a month from thefirst nine Service flying training schools will be reached in the Spring insteadof at the end of the Summer 1941. There are indications that a similar acceleration-tion may be expected in Australia.21. The first pilots trained under the Empire Air Training Scheme will bearriving for final training in operational training units in this country from canada and New Zealand in December of this year and from Australia inJanuary, 1941.Employment of Pilots from Allied Air Forces.22. Particulars are now available of over 1,000 French, Belgian, Dutch, Polish and Czech operational pilots, many of whom have had recent war experience.The method of employing these pilots, and of the air crew and ground personnelwho have in many cases accompanied them, and the speed at which they can be absorbed into operational units, are determined partly by our own operational requirements, partly by language considerations and the fact that the majorityof these pilots need to requalify on British types and partly by the wishes ofthe allied Governments concerned. No final decision has yet been taken as touse of these pilots, but a number of foreign squadrons are already being formed,and use is also being made of allied pilots in R.A.F. units to meet certain of ourown immediate deficiencies.   ;23. In Fighter Command two Polish and one Czech fighter squadrons arebeing formed with reserves of their own nationals, and it is probable that additional foreign squadrons will be formed later. Pilots will qualify on theaircraft allotted to the squadrons instead of being passed through the operational training units, and it is hoped that these squadrons will soon become operational.In addition, some 120 pilots are being passed through fighter operational training units, and if they pass out successfully will be posted to British fighter squadrons.24. In Bomber Command, two Polish squadrons have already formed andtwo further Polish and one Czech are in process of formation. In each case Polishor Czech reserves are also being provided. In addition, English-speaking pilotswill be trained at operational training units to qualify them to act as secondpilots in certain R.A.F. heavy bomber squadrons; and ten complete foreign crewsare being made up, and after passing through the operational training units will be tried out in British bomber squadrons. Further foreign crews will bemade up, and these may form the nucleus of further foreign squadrons.25. In Coastal Command a Dutch seaplane squadron has already taken an active part in operations, and it is now being reinforced by personnel of theDutch Army Air Force.26. The allied Governments are in general anxious to establish trainingorganisations of their own in order to support their squadrons and to replacewastage. The Norwegians are already arranging to establish a training school at Toronto. We are now considering the establishment of training facilities inthis country or elsewhere for the other nationalities.27. I mentioned in my earlier paper the creation of an organisation to enterinto the RA.F.V.R. citizens of the United States who are suitably experiencedpilots. In addition to this, Colonel Charles Sweeny has shown great enthusiasmin making arrangements for the formation of a United States squadron of theR.A.F. for service against, the enemy. It is as yet too early to give any estimateof the results of these efforts.Establishment of A dolitional Flying Training Schools Overseas.28. Arrangements have been made with the Governments of South africa and Rhodesia to increase the existing training facilities to the equivalent of sixService flying training schools in South Africa (the output of four of which will go to the R.A.F.) and four Service flying training schools in Southern Rhodesia,
* One of our training aircraft was recently shot down by an enemy fighter.with a complement in each case of elementary schools and observer schools. Oneflying training school is now in operation in Rhodesia and a second school willbe opened in October, while a further school will be formed in South Africa inNovember. Arrangements have also been made to establish a Service flying-training school in Kenya.29. At these schools flying training will be carried out in better weather conditions than in this country and unhindered by air congestion, enemy actionor by the restrictions imposed by operational requirements; and these schools, insupplement to the flying training school at Habbaniya, should prove a most valuable addition to our resources, particularly in relation to our commitments inthe Middle and Far East.Transfer of Schools to the Dominions.30. It is urgently necessary in the interests of training to transfer a numberof schools from this country to the Dominions. In recent months the restrictions which we have had to impose on flying training in this country have been much increased and would have been increased still further but for the essential require-ments of training. The extension of active operations in the West country hasbeen a further serious impediment ;* sites which had been prepared for schoolshave had to be relinquished for use by fighter and general reconnaissancesquadrons. Restrictions on night flying have also become increasingly severe.All this is serious enough in the case of flying training schools, but the limitations imposed on such schools as the air observer navigation schools, the general recon-naissance schools and the School of Air Navigation which require flying practiceover large areas of open sea, are even more drastic.31. The possibility of transferring schools to Canada and South Africa has&apos;been discussed with the Dominion Governments, and our proposals have met witha ready response. Arrangements are in hand for the transfer to Canada of the personnel and aircraft of four Service flying training schools (including onewhich trains Naval pilots), one air observer navigation school, and one general reconnaissance school; and to South Africa, two air observer navigation schools,one bombing and gunnery school and one general reconnaissance school., Afurther seven sites are being prepared in Canada as an insurance against furtherinterference with our training here and in preparation for the transfer of sevenschools to Canada in 1941. A temporary check to the production of pilots willbe unavoidable, but the effect of the move will not begin to be felt in the opera-tional units of the R.A.F. before the end of December. Arrangements will bemade by moving the schools in echelons to reduce the dislocation of training toa minimum. Thereafter the schools, escaping from the bad weather in thiscountry and from German interference, will be able to work&apos; with greater efficiency and at a faster tempo. More room will be available in this country forthe formation of the units which cater for the final stage of training the operational training units.32. It is clearly essential to preserve the same high degree of secrecy about these projected moves as about the despatch of Dominion forces to this country.*Conclusion.33. My next task, in which I know I shall have the co-operation of theMinister of Aircraft Production, particularly in regard to the productionof advanced trainers, will be to balance the output of pilots, observers,wireless operators, air gunners and maintenance personnel, to match the produc-tion of aircraft. The necessary measures including the exploration of possibilities in the United States of America, are now being worked out and it is those measures which my next Cabinet paper will describe.A. H. M. S.Air Ministry, August 7, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
