<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/63/49 images: 554-557</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC! MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1945.SECRET.W.P. (45) 194.2Qth March, 1945.THE RELATIONSHIP OF THE INTERNATIONAL LABOUR ORGANI-SATION TO THE NEW WORLD SECURITY ORGANISATION.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National Service.I have been considering with the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs andthe Lord President of the Council the question of the place which the I.L.O.should occupy in the new World Security Organisation. In agreement with them,I ask the approval of the War Cabinet to the proposal that the United kingdom delegation at San Francisco should endeavour to secure agreement on thefollowing points : (i) The I.L.O. should be recognised as an important instrument through which should be pursued the object of &quot; securing for all improved labour standards, economic advancement and social security &quot; as laid down inArticle V of the Atlantic Charter.(ii) The I.L.O. should be formally associated with the new Organisation inthe Charter of the Organisation.(iii) The I.L.O. should be given opportunities for making its voice heardduring the deliberations of the new Organisation not less favourable than thoseit enjoyed under the League. (Thus an arrangement might be made whereby theDirector of the I.L.O. could attend meetings of the General Assembly and of theEconomic and Social Council when questions directly affecting the work of theI.L.O. were under consideration.) It might also be recognised that the governing body of the I.L.O. should be represented at certain Conferences and on certainCommissions set up by the new Organisation; and that the I.L.O. should berepresented by officials on each of the Technical Commissions of the new Organisa-tion whose work was of special interest to the I.L.O.(iv) Subject to any arrangements which it might itself make, the I.L.O.should not be subject to the overriding direction either of the Economic and social Council or of the General Assembly itself. It should continue, as in thepast, to have the right to send its decisions and recommendations direct to governments, for consideration and, where appropriate, action.(v) The powers of the General Assembly with regard to the budgets ofinternational bodies associated with the new Organisation should be such as to preserve to the I.L.O. its existing measure of financial autonomy and to place no obstacle in the way of providing the funds to enable it to carry out the dutiesplaced upon it.(vi) The Governing Body of the I.L.O. should be invited to send represen-tatives to San Francisco to be available for consultation with regard to any matters concerning the I.L.O., its work or its scope, including its relationship tothe new World Organisation as well as labour matters generally; and decisions on all such matters should only be taken after consultation with these represen-tatives. (N.B. The Governing Body of the I.L.O. at Philadelphia in Juneappointed a Negotiating Committee consisting of three representatives each ofGovernment, Workers&apos; and Employers&apos; Groups to be available for this purpose.The War Cabinet in approving W.P. (45) 173 have already implicitly expressed their concurrence in the suggestion that this Committee should be invited to san francisco (W.M. (45) 33rd Conclusions, Minute 4 (1)).)E. B.Ministry of Labour and National Service, S.W. 1,26th March, 1945.Copy No.WAR CABINET.[29508]




</content>
</cab>
