<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/183/15 images: 491-493</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY !S government\2C(75) 65 COPY NO10 June 1975CABINETLATE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE HOUSING FINANCE act memorandum by the Secretary of State for the environment. Our policy on default under the Housing Finance Act was approved bythe Cabinet last November (CC(74) 43rd Conclusions).    The relevant bill has been passed by the Commons;  and the Bill was given a Second reading in the Lords on 9 June,   A recent development makes it necessary for meto consult my Cabinet colleagues about the Clause (Clause 4) which providesfor the termination of the existing disqualification from civic office as aresult of a surcharge arising out of failure to implement the housing finance Act.    In practice this Clause would apply only to the disqualificationincurred by the former councillors at Clay Cross in respect of the surchargefor  7000 (that surcharge in all other respects being unaffected by the Bill).2. We had been aware that there might be further surcharges on theformer councillors at Clay Cross for matters quite unconnected with defaultunder the Housing Finance Act, eg for excessive wage and bonus payments;and that, if there were, they would be disqualified from office all over again.When this prospect was considered by the MISC 33 Committee last december we concluded that in that event we might find it difficult to dropClause 4 ourselves, particularly if to do so appeared to be prejudgingappeals by the former councillors against these new surcharges; but it was recognised that in any case the Clause would almost certainly be deleted inthe Lords and if so, its loss might not greatly matter if, by then, thecouncillors had been surcharged afresh on these other matters.3.        Subsequent events have not turned out entirely as expected.    the eleven former councillors were surcharged on 16 April for  50, 000 and haduntil 28 May to appeal.    However, they have not appealed, and so their newdisqualification has already taken effect.    I have made clear that I have no intention of bringing forward legislation to relieve them in respect of these new surcharges (OR 14 May col 566).    Clause 4 could no longer therefore have any practical effect.    The Opposition are bound to put down an amendment to delete it.1
4. We can either a, soldier on with Clause 4 in the Lords, certainly get defeatedon it, and then decide whether to accept that defeat when the Bill isreturned to the Commons orb, accept the Opposition amendment to delete it in the Lords,,5. In my view the case against our now continuing to defend Clause 4 isoverwhelming.    Although the Prime Minister said in his statement on  April 1974 that we were committed to removing the civic disqualificationwhich the Housing Finance Act involved, this was before there could havebeen any knowledge of further surcharges to come.    Legislation purporting to fulfil the commitment would now be otiose; what is more, the retentionof this controversial clause could still endanger the passage of the bill itself, and place in jeopardy the position of the 400 councillors who would otherwise be surcharged for the rent losses of  1^ million,60        I am in no doubt therefore, that we should accept an amendment todelete Clause 4 in the Lords.    The Clause survived Report in the commons by only a small majority and that was while there was a possibility of appealand the new disqualifications had not taken effect.    If we were to oppose itsdeletion we should first get a very rough ride in the Lords, and then laterface either a successful revolt of some of our own anti-Clay Crossbackbenchers in the Commons, or alternatively, if this failed, a Lordsversus Commons problem.    We would in the end be accepting the loss ofthe Clause in the least favourable circumstances.7,        I can see only one possible argument for retaining what is now a purely academic provision, and that is to bring the disqualification fromthis particular cause to an end, and so retain the internal consistency ofthe Bill,   Against that we must set not only the arguments in paragraph above, but also the Governments duty to see that legislation has a practical effect.8.        I accordingly recommend that the Lord Privy Seal be authorised toaccept an Opposition Amendment in the Lords to delete Clause 4 of the Bill,A department of the Environment10 June 19752


</content>
</cab>
