<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/45/17 images: 196-203</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(this&apos; document IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC/MAJESTY5 S GOVERNMENT),-secret,p, (Uh) *7 copy noD^9TH JANUARY,WAR CABINETREINSTATEMENT IN CIVIL EMPLOYMENT BILLPOSITION OF THE WOMENfS LAND army memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and fisheries* In W.P, 6 the Home Secretary and Minister of home security points out that the inclusion of the women&apos;s services in this Bill may provoke claims on behalf of the Women&apos;s land army*      I have in fact been urging that reinstatement rightsshould be extended to members of the Women&apos;s Land Army who, inmy opinionff have at least as strong a claim as members of thewomen&apos;s services and Civil Defence personnel.,2. It would, I submit, be very difficult to justify treatingwomen who volunteered for the Women&apos;s Land Army less favourablyas regards reinstatement than those who:  volunteered for thewomen1s services included in the Bill.      Their work is no less important and is, generally speaking, far more arduous;    and itis only comparatively few members of the women&apos;s services whowill have been exposed to greater dangers or hardships,     The pay and general conditions of the Women&apos;s Land Army are similar and in several respects less favourable than those in the women&apos;services.      It is not necessary for me to emphasise the splendid &apos;job they have done - for food production.3. As an illustration of the anomalies that will arise if theWome^s Land Army do not receive reinstatement rights, take thecase of a firm which employe,,  and can only employ, one woman ina certain capacity.      If the original occupant of this post in response to the national appeal,  joined the Women&apos;s Land Army onthe outbreak of war and was replaced by another who joined theA*T.S.  in 19U3, it is the second woman who has the right ofreinstatement, not the first.ty.. This seems manifestly unfair.      In many cases the secondwoman will have had no intention of volunteering for war work butllater on became liable for call-up, and, because the necessityhad arisen, joined one of the women&apos;s services a     Under thepresent draft of the Bill, the woman who stayed in her civilianjob until the last moment is given preference over the womanwho volunteered much earlier for a^very arduous and importantform of war service.5* I am confident that the general public, and the farming community in particular, will&apos; find it difficult to understand why the Women&apos;s Land Army is given less favourable treatmentthan the women&apos;s services, and that there will be strongParliamentary pressure for the inclusion of the Women?s land army in the Bill.

60 There is the additional point that we shall need tocontinue food production at war-time levels for at least twoyears after the conclusion of hostilities with Germany, and during that period it will he necessary to maintain the &apos;agricultural labour force, Including the Women&apos; s Land Army,at -bout its war-time strength-.     The absence of re-instatement rights may well lead to the resignation oflarge numbers of skilled and experienced volunteersimmediately the war with Germany ends;    whereas thosevolunteers who are public-spirited enough to remain onthe land for a year or two will be placed at a disadvantage&quot;by comparison not only with women with reinstatement rights&quot;but also with other civilians whoso work terminates andenables them to be released at an earlier date*7. I hope that the Cabinet will agree,  therefore, tothe extension of reinstatement rights to the Womenfs land army.,(Intld)    R, So HoMinistry of Agrleulturd and Fisheries *9th January, 19kh-






</content>
</cab>
