<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/251/0 images: 35-36</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
his document is the property of His-Britannic Majesty1 s Government).CRET . Copy No . ?. .(. . .&apos;CAB I N E T . P. 228(34)ASSASSINATION OF KING ALEXANDER AND M.  BARTHOU: _CINEMATOGRAPH FILM .__Memorandum by the Home Secretary.In pursuance of Cabinet 35 (34),  Conclusion 3,  I submit, for the information of my colleagues, the following report on this matter .The attention of the Home Office was drawn on Fridaymorning,  October 12th, to the fact that films relating to theassassination of King Alexander were being shown in this country.One of the conditions in the licence of practically every cinemain the country is the following: -&quot;No film shall be shown which is likely to be injurious to morality or to encourage or to incite to crime or to lead to disorder or to be offensive to public feeling or which contains any offensive representations of living persons;    if the Council serve a notice on the licensee that they object to the exhibition of any film on any of the grounds aforesaid that film shall not be shown&quot; .This condition applies to news-reels of current events as much as to any other film, but as news-reels,  to be of any interest to the public, have to be exhibited without any loss of time,  they are exempt from the condition which applies to all other films,  i.e. that no film which has not been passed by the British Board of Film Censors shall be exhibited without the express consent of the Council.I had immediate enquiry made of the London County Council,  the most important licensing authority in the country. It was ascertained that no complaints had reached the Council and that a representative of the Council, having seen one version of the film, had come to the conclusion that the film
could not &quot;be said to be &quot;offensive to public feeling&quot;,  the only ground on which the Council had power to take any action. Enquiry was further made at the Foreign Office and it was ascertained that the Foreign Secretary had come to the conclusion that so far as his Department was concerned no action was called for.It was further arranged for Home Office representatives to see the four versions of the film which were being shown. They reported that there was nothing in any of the four versions which could be regarded as offensive to public feeling or as likely to incite to crime or to lead to disorder.     Each of the four cinemas which they visited was crowded and the audiences maintained a complete silence during the exhibition.The films had all been carefully cut by the producing companies.     nothing was to be seen of the assassin&apos;s rush to the car or of the firing of shots into the car.      The impression left by the film when it resumed after the shooting was one of general confusion and scrimmaging in the street;    it was impossible to identify the murderer definitely or to see any details of his being mauled by the crowd.      The effect of the film as a whole was tragic.I am about to issue a circular to cinematograph licensing authorities, dealing with a technical point in relation to news-reels which are composed of a series of photographs taken on widely different dates,  and in this circular I am taking the opportunity of reminding local authorities that the condition quoted above is applicable to news-reels as well as to other films.      It seems clear that the industry in this case exercised care to eliminate from the film anything which could be considered as objectionable.J.G.22nd October,  1934.

</content>
</cab>
