<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/251/0 images: 106-112</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOV5RNMENT. SECRET. COPY NO .   4 1CP. 241(54)CABINET. THE LONDON WHEAT AGREEMENT.Memorandum &quot;by the President of the Board of Trade.My colleagues will recall that earlier in the year (as reported in my memoranda CP. 126 (34)  and 154 (34)  of the 3rd May and 4th June) the London Wheat Agreement was in danger of breaking down altogether owing to the fact that Argentina -who had a bumper crop - exported largely in excess of her agreed quota.     Long continued negotiations between the chief exporting countries produced no settlement.     Various proposals for a readjustment of the quotas were made and rejected, and the discussion was further complicated by mutual accusations of failure to carry out the obligation (implied though not expressed in the Agreement)  to control production.     At the instance of Canada, Australia and the U.S.A. we ourselves intervened diplomatically but without much result, and there appeared to be a complete deadlock.     The situation, was saved however, by the North American drought, which, whatever its ultimate effect may be, at least caused a temporary rise in wheat prices end made a revision of the quotas for next year inevitable.      Indeed,  there appeared to be a clear case for the revision of the whole Agreement which,  as it now appeared, was too vague where it should have been precise,  and too rigid where it should have been elastic,&quot;Whan the \vheat Advisory Committee met in August the relations between the exporting countries improved considerably. The view that Argentina&apos;s conduct might charitably be excused as due largely to the defects of the Agreement - a view which
the British representative discreetly supported - was allowed to prevail.    In effect it was agreed to let bygones be bygones if Argentina would enter into a new arrangement;end as a result of further negotiations between the major exporting countries  the Committee were able to present a report to the Governments they represent recommending a revision of the Agreement, and its extension for two years, i.e,,  to 1937.     Governments are asked to define their attitude towards the proposals at the Session of the Committee which opens at Budapest on the 20th November.I need not trouble the Cabinet with the details of the proposed amendments to the Agreement.      They are complicated, and for the most pert ao not affect the United Kingdom at all. It is necessary, however, to decide whether we are to support in principle the proposal for a prolongation of the Agreement.Cxi this ouestion I do not myself think   there can be much room for doubt.      It is true that our grain trade dislike the Agreement.     While they would v/ish to see better prices for wheat,  and do not, within reason, object to something in the nature of expert quotas,  they are afraid th.pt it may eventually leau to an international control of the wheat trade,  which they regard as objectionable from every point of view.      It will be remembered how alarmed they were earlier in the year at the abortive proposal to fix minimum prices, ana I understand that I shall shortly be receiving further representations from them to the effect that the Agreement should be allowed to lapse.I agree that there are elements of risk in the situation against which we should be on our guard.     Nevertheless it appears to me that the reasons for which we adhered to the original Agreement are equally v?lid reasons for not opposing its continuance.     Prom our point of view the essence of the
Agreement was that the LTndr&amp;ed Klnghxm^ a-s the- largest consumer, became an assenting party to an arrangement between the chief suppliers for a control of exports,  and consequently of production for two reasons:-(i) because she v/as specially interested in the fortunes of two of the chiaf exporting countries, namely, Canada and Australia, and(ii) because on a long view it appearea to her that a restoration   of wheat prices would be a major contribution to v/orld recover.It appears to me that these reasons have lost none of their force,   md that if the exporting countries are agreed in desiring an extension of the Agreement for two years we could not very well refuse our assent, even though we may regard the wheat situation as less critical than it was when the Agreement was first signed.There is, however, one point to which attention ought to be called.      In signing the London Agreement we expressly reserved the right to carry out the policy of the Wheat Act, 193?.      (I append the relevant passages).      Our position is,  I think, fully understood;    and though    I believe that there are occasionally ironical allusions to our inconsistency in increasing our own production of wheat,  it is not really pretenced that we are violating the spirit of the Agreement, which we may be said to have signed as consumers rather than as producers.      There is, however,  in form at least, a possibility of a conflict of obligations arising should we take more drastic measures to stimulate wheat proauction.At present we gurrentee a price of 10/- per cwt. on 87 million cwts., say 45/- a bushel,  the difference between that price and the market price being made up by a levy on all flour produced or imported.      If oroduction exceeds 27 million cwt.  the &quot;deficiency payment&quot; is reduced proportionately.
Agreement tos that the tjuidrted Kingdom^. &amp;s the- largest consumer, became an assenting party to an arrangement be-tween the chief suppliers for a control of exports,  and consequently of production for two reasons:-(i) because she was specially interested in the fortunes of two of tha chief exporting countries, namely, Canada and Australia, and(ii) because on 8 long view it appeared to her that a restoration    of wheat prices would be a major contribution to v/orld recovery.It appears to me that these reasons have lost none of their force,   pnd that if the exporting countries are agreed in desiring an extension of the Agreement for two yeprs we could not very well refuse our assent, even though we may regard the wheat situation as less critical than it was when the Agreement was first signed.There is, however, one point to which attention ought to be called.      In signing the London Agreement we expressly reserved the right to carry out the policy of the Wheat Act, 193?..      (I append the relevant passages).      Our position is,  I think, fully understood;    and though    I believe that there are occasionally ironical allusions to our inconsistency in increasing our own production of wheat,  it is not really pretenced that we ere violating the spirit of the Agreement, which we may be said to hpve signed as consumers rather than as producers.      There is, however,  in form at least, a possibility of a conflict of obligations arising should v/e take more drastic measures to stimulate wheat proauction.At present we guarantee a price of 10/- per cwt. on 27 million cwts., say 45/- a bushel, the difference between that price and the market price being made up by a levy on all flour produced or imported.      If production exceeds 27 million cwt.  the &quot;deficiency payment&quot; is reduced proportionately.
Section 2(5) of the Act requires the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries to appoint not later than 1st March, 1935, a committee of three to consider whether the standard price needs to he altered.      Cn their report the Minister may, subject to confirmation by Parliament, fix another price to operate from 1st August,  1935.      (No provision is made for subsequent alterations).I take this provision to&quot; have been enacted leather as a safeguard against some unforeseen change in monetary or other conditions which might have altered the position fundamentally.      If,  for example,  it hpd been founa that a change in values had the result th^t the guaranteed price became wholly inadeouate tc sustain the existing acreage, the question of fixing an appreciably higher figure might well have arisen.In fact, however, the general level of wholesale prices in the United Kingdom has been remarkably constant;    wheat acreage has increaseo from 1,543,000 in 1932 tc some 1.861,000 in 1934    and the &quot;anticipated supply&quot;  is now 29 million cwts.I take it,   therefore,  that there is no likelihood either that the Committee will recommend,    or    the Minister of Agriculture will propose, any raaicel departure from the existing arrangement.I propose,   therefore,  if the Cabinet agree,  to instruct our representative on the Wheat Advisory Committee not to oppose an extension of the London Agreement for two years, if all the chief exporting countries desire it,   and provided that no new obligations are imposed on the United Kingdom.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries authorises me to say that he concurs in this recommendption.oard of Trade.2nd November,  1934.W. R.
Extract from Minutes of Final Meeting.The signatures are to be regarded, as affixod in the liizht of the statements made during the discussions by the representatives of the various countries; these statements are contained In the minutes of the conference, and are to be interpreted in the sense of paragraph (Iv) of article 6 of the Final Act,Extract from Final Act of the Wheat Conference. Article 6.The Governments of the vtfheat-Importing countries, insigning this instrument -(i)     Agree henceforth not to encourage any extension of the area sown to wheat and not to take any governmental measures the, effect of which would be to increase the domestics production of wheatsX X X X XThe obligations of the importing countries under thisagreement are to be interpreted in the light of thefollowing declaration:-It is recosnlsed that measures affecting the area ofwheat grown and the degree of protection adopted are primarilydependent upon domestic conditions within each country, andthat any change In these measures must often require thesanction of the Legislature,The intention of this agreement is, nevertheless,  thatthe Importing countries will not take advantage of a voluntary reduction of exports on the part of the exporting countries by developing their domestic policies in such away as to frustrate the efforts which the exporting countriosare making;,  in the common interest, to restore the priooof wheat to a remunerative level.
st at erne nt made by lord de la warr on behalf of the itnl fled ITin^dolir^overnmeni&apos;&apos; at tae first sitting of tho conference.lord de la warr (united kingdom) was prepared to acceptthe general principles laid down in point i.    the unitedkingdom wheat policy had already beon fully explained, and howould merely say that as the united kingdom productionincreased over the present figure, the amount of the government assistance would be proportionately reduced, thowheat act was permanent, but the figures contained thereinheld good only up to 1935; the united kingdom could thereforeundertake not to change the figures before that date, but could give no undertaking for the subsequent period.

</content>
</cab>
