<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/251/0 images: 142-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENTS IS THE PROPERTY 0? EJ.B britannic  MAJESTY1 S&quot;&quot;     GO VT-PMOjNI:SECRET.. Copy Mo. 51CP,  2Uk( 3lr) 0 A B I. IT E TiviALTA.,Memorandum hy the Secretary of State for the Colonies^Cahlnet will remember that on the 25th. of April (CalDinet Conclusions 17(3^)), in approving my memorandum CP.  110(54) they decided that we should not introduce a Bill formally abolishing the Malta Constitution unless circumstances arose which made such an act imperative;    e0g,  if the Malta Courts should give a judgment which impeded Crown Colony Government32.      I have today received a telegram from the Governor of Malta stating that an action has &quot;been commenced &quot;by Mizzi, the moving spirit and chief offender among the late Ministers, to obtain a declaration of invalidity of ordinances passed &quot;by the present Government on the grounds that the state of grave emergency, on which suspension of the constitution is based^ is non-existent.      I hope that the Maltese Courts will hold that so long as &quot;the Secretary of State is satisfied that a grave emergency continues to exist the present form of Government cannot be called in question:    that the Secretary of Statefs discretion on this point is, under the  terms of the Letters Patent, absolute;    and that they will accordingly dismiss the action,3,     At the time of the suspension of the Constitution I was advised that the legality of my action was not open to doubt a
&amp;oubb.      But as I pointed, out to the Cabinet in my memorandum mentioned above,  the Governor&apos;s Legal Adviser feels that indefinite continuance of a form of Government based upon the emergency provisions gives rise to legal questions of great difficulty.      My own Legal   -dvisers agree that the position is becoming a difficult one;    but they consider that so long as I exercise my discretion honestly the action which I have taken cannot be impugned,hp      &apos;./e have always recognised, however, that the Maltese Courts may take a different view,      If, unhappily,they should do so the situation would arise which the Cabinet envisaged, in which it would be necessary to legislate immediately here to legalise our position,, I hope that this need, will not arise;    but I thought I ought to warn Cabinet immediately of the possibility.(Intdo)      P. C-LoDonning Street, S.   . 1, 5th November, 193U

</content>
</cab>
