<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/251/0 images: 176-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-    142DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.Copy No.CABINET.SUPPLIES OF PETROLEUM TO GERMANY. Note by the President of the Board of Trade.A proposal, the object of which is to secure additional deliveries of oil to Germany over a period of years, has been made on behalf of the German Government to the large oil groups which supply Germany with the bulk of her imports of oil.    I circulate, for the consideration of my colleagues, the attached memorandum by the Secretary for Mines on the proposal.The Memorandum has been prepared as a result of the consideration of the proposal by an inter-departmental conference   attended by- representatives of the Board of Trade, Treasury, Foreign Office and Petroleum Department.I concur in the conclusion set forth in paragraph 10, and I shall be glad to have the approval of my colleagues to the action there proposed.W.R.SECRETCP. 252(34)Board of Trade,9th November, 1934.
SECRET *The President of the Board of Trade,Supplies of Petroleum and Petroleum products to Germany,,1. Several months ago the three principal oil groups (the Standard Oil Company of New Jersey, the Royal Dutch Shell and the Anglo-Persian Oil Company) which furnish the hulk of Germany&apos;s oil supplies were presented with proposals toy the German Government which were to govern the supply of oil to Germany over a period of years02. Broadly the plan was on the following lines:(a) The companies participating in the scheme (and in theory it was to toe open to all importing companies to come in) to undertake to supply all the mineral oil requirements of Germany in excess of German production, and to maintain reserve stocks representing four months requirements, plus an additional reserve of motor spirit of one million tons, to toe stored at places to toe Indicated toy the German government(to) No foreign exchange to toe allocated for any oil imports (except that obtained from re-export of any oil imported under the proposed contracts)0(c) Reichsmark payments (except when used to &quot;touy goods or services in Germany for the parent oil company concerned)  to toeleft in Germany for at least five years and thereafter to toesubject to the exchange regulations then in force.    Thesemarks (unless invested privately toy eonsent) to toe granted asa credit to a Bank, with the German Government&apos;s guarantee, to.finance among other things(i) the construction of new roads: (il) road maintenance: (iii) the purchase of aeroplanes with a view to the development of aviation: (iv) motor tractors etc. for agriculture: (y) motor vehicles for municipal and provincial transport undertakings: (vi) increasing the storage capacity for motor spirit and other mineral oil products6
(d) Importers who did not participate were to &quot;be refused any foreign exchange whatever through Clearing or Exchange Agreements or otherwise, hut to have to comply with the requirement as to holding four months1 stocks.   Roumania (with which a special Compensation Agreement existed) and apparently Russia were to &quot;be separately dealt with.3. In other words the Oil Companies :*ere invited to provide all current requirements of Germany and to &quot;build up &amp; large reserve on credit, with no chance of receiving any appreciable payments in foreign currency for at least five years.   Any company refusing to participate would get neither foreign exchange nor a Government-guaranteed credit.4. In return, it was stated that the German Government Y^ere prepared to give some undertaking to limit the production of synthetic oil (&quot;by hydrogenation etc.) and to maintain the market for the participating companies.    The German Government also pointed out that the scheme for roads, greater motorisation and development of aviation would lead to a larger market for oil products.5. The scheme was brought to the notice of the Government by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company in which H.M. Government is a large shareholder, and it was discussed at an interdepartmental conference presided over by Sir Frederick Leith-Rosa.    It was agreed that the plan was objectionable, particularly as regards those features which sought to enable Germany to build up exceptional reserves of oil and to buy aeroplanes at the expense of the oil companies.    It was decided, therefore, to recommend - the Anglo-Persian Oil Company to try to concert with the other large groups&apos; with a view to securing as a minimum the removal of these objectionable features to which reference had been made. The question was also discussed semi-officially with the London Office of the Shell Company, who at one stage were stated to be not unfavourable to the idea of trying to fall in so far as
practicable with the views or&quot;- the G^riiiajx-(JoverTimeirt, with the object of getting them also to take action on similar^lines. This the Company agreed to do, and following meetings between the representatives of the three groups, the German Government were informed that the plan in the form put forward was not acceptable to the oil companies*6. Last week the matter was revived when representatives of the I.G. (the German Dye Trust which holds the hydrogenation slights in Germany and owns the Leuna hydrogenation plant) paid a visit to London and had talks with representatives of the three big oil groups referred to above.7. On the grounds that co-operation between German industry and the industrialists of other countries interested in German trade was a very desirable thing to foster at the present time, the I.Go suggested that an important step would be co-operation betwoen them and the foreign oil importing and distributing groups, with a view to:-(a) Creation of a satisfactory cartel arrangement to govern selling conditions in the German oil market.(b) The purchase toy the I.G. of a quantity of oil inorder to build up in Germany a reserve s took.As regards (b) it was proposed:-1. That the oil companies should supply oil products to the value of  4,000,000 (four million pounds), the exact   qualities of the products to be determined later by the I.G.2. That delivery of the products be made within five years with the option to the I.G, to call for delivery of the whole quantity within two years.The basis of payment proposed was(i) 10$ of the f.o.bo value of each cargo of oil to be paid for on arrival of the cargo, at German port, the balance being paid by six-monthly instalments in such a way that the whole of the oil would be paid for at the end of five years from the commencement of the contract;(ii) Freight to be paid in cash in shippers currency on arrival of each cargo;(iii) Payment of the whole amount of  4,000,000 (fourmillion) sterling to be guaranteed by first-class UoSoA. and London Banks before any delivery of oil takes place.
8c In bringing this proposal to the notice of theGovernment, the Anglo-Persian Oil Company comment as follows:-&quot;The above broadly represents the proposal that we have now before us and upon which a decision is asked at an early date.    You will, of course, understand that such an arrangement as this would, if acceptable in principle, be the subject of further negotiation and satisfactory settlement of detailed conditions, but before I take any further steps in the matter at all, I should like to know whether you would approve our participation in the supply of this oil provided the terms of payment are entirely satisfactory from a commercial point of view.You will, I know, appreciate the fact that we have an important distributing organisation in Germany and that, provided always this deal could be arranged on sound commercial lines, our sharo in the carrying through of it might avoid the loss of goodwill to us, which is important in the present situation in Germany.&quot;9C This new proposal has been discussed at an inter-departmental conference presided over by Sir Horace Hamilton at which representatives of the Board of Trade, Foreign Office, Treasury and Petroleum Department were present.    The following points emerged from the discussion -(a) The German Government views with some anxiety Germanyfsposition in regard to supplies of oil;    she Is dependent for the greater proportion of her requirements on supplies obtained from other countries, and these might be difficult to obtain in her present exchange position if immediate cash payment were insisted on.(b) Germany&apos;s requirements are* likely to increase materiallyin the future, particularly for supplies of motor spirit and dlesel oil.    Compared with countries of similar importance, as regards population and industrial and commercial activity, Germany&apos;s development of motor traffic and motor utilisation is on a much lower level than the United Kingdom or France, as the following figures show:Estimated. Petrol Population.     Consumption in 1933.Tons.United Kingdom.     48,000,000 3,960,000France.......0.      41,000,000 2,500,000Germany........      66,000,000 1,500,000
(c) If the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and other British oil interests were to reject this further proposal by the German Government; (for whom I,G, is probably acting   -s an intermediary), it is likely that the position of these British interestSj, which have very large investmen ts in Germany, would become very difficult, and that the German Government would be able to secure her oil supplies through other channels and by further development of her own resources. Germany already provides from her own resources about one-third of her requirements of motor spirit, which at present amount in total to li million tons but are increasing.    She has some supplies of natural petroleum (production at present amounts to about 300,000 tons per annum and is increasing, and the German Government is already offering subsidies to those willing to undertake further search).    One large hydrogenation plant is already working and definite plans have been made for putting up additional works.    There is also a considerable production of benzol and industrial alcohol.    So far as alternative sources of supply of imported petroleum are concerned, it is considered that Germany would at present have little difficulty in obtaining over the period suggested from independent suppliers in Roumania and the United States of America the quantities now under discussion, (d) The Foreign Office desire to call attention to the possibility of the supplies which I.G. have asked the oil companies to provide being used as an eiaergency reserve, and if that be so that it is an effort to secure in another guise that part of the
original proposal to which it was agreed exception ought to be taken.   The figure of  4 million would represent about one million tons of motor spirit, if other grades ard taken the quantity would be higher. But the original proposal was for delivery within a short period while orders under the new proposal may be spread over five years.    Thei^e is, however, the condition that I.G. may call for delivexy within two years.   During the discussions with the oil groups, I.Go indicated that they might vise some of this oil in their hydrogenation plants vdaich would mean a slowor development of the use of coal and ooal tars.(e) Provided the transactions are carried out on terms which the British oil interests oould regard as satisfactory from a commercial standpoint, there is a good deal to be said even considering the matter as one of imperial defence policy for not taking any action which would force the German Government to undertake an intensive campaign designed to meet the greater part of her oil requirements from her own resources.    If such a position arose, Germany&apos;s defence position would probably be strengthened, despite the fact that the supply of her oil require-ments from her own sources would imply a diversion of effort from other important forms of sctivity, and the British oil organisation, on which this country would have to depend during any emergency, would be correspondingly weakened..-(f) If the condition as to delivery within two years were eliminated, the terms of the offer, assuming that the guarantees from the United Kingdom and the U.SoA. Banks oan be secured, could not be regarded as unsatisfactory.    It is a matter of some surprise
that the I,G. should he in a position to offer guarantees from British or American Banks for such a considerable sum spread over so long a period; but the Oil Companies can be relied upon to obtain full security on this point before they conclude the buslnesso(g) It was not considered that this scheme would interfere with the carrying out of the recent Anglo-German Payments Agreement, 10o In all the circumstances the conclusion was reached that there were no   sufficient grounds of public policy on which HoM. Government could advise the Anglo-Persian Oil Company to reject this proposal.    It was agreed to suggest to the Company that they should secure the deletion of the condition as to delivery within two years, or if that proved impossible, that the period over which payment is to be made should be made to conform to the period of delivery.    It would naturally be for the Company, as a result of the further negotiations which are to  take place, to satisfy itself that I.G. would be able to implement the terms of payment offered.ERNEST BRONN.8th November, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
