<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/251/0 images: 207-211</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PKOPEETY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT-printed for the Cabinet.   November 1934.SECRET. Copy No.   39CP. 256 (34).CABINET.PALESTINE LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.I HAVE discussed at great length with the High Commissioner the details of the proposed Legislative Council in Palestine. Sir Arthur Wauchope and I are in complete agreement; and I propose to send him the attached despatch containing our conclusions, on which he will base his discussions with Arabs and Jews in Palestine.2. Our conclusions are, I think, in accord with the memorandum (OP. 374 (32)) which the Cabinet approved on the 9th November. 1932 (Cabinet Conclusions 60 (32)). But I wish to draw my colleagues&apos; attention particularly to the suggested constitution of the Council (despatch, paragraph 3 (A)). I think the principle of having nominated as well as elected members is very sound. It should ensure the appointment of men of moderate views; and it will enable the High Commissioner to give the Jews a membership disproportionate to their numbers, but justified by their stake in the country, while apportioning the elected members on a basis of population.3. I append an extract from White Papers of 1922 and 1923 (Cmd. 1700 and Cmd. 1889) giving the constitution as then proposed.4. The Cabinet will see, as I think I indicated when we discussed the matter before, that we have reduced the numbers of official members. There would, however, in fact be an equal balance between Arabs and Jews 4-officials 4-the commercial member. But of course the essential safeguard lies in the power of the High Commissioner (see despatch, paragraph 3 (C)).5. Sir A. Wauchope attaches great importance to the proposal (despatch, paragraph 4) to appoint unofficial members to his Executive Council. This proposal is really independent of the Legislative Council; and I think the High Commissioner would wish to give effect to it, provided he could get the right men to serve, even if a Legislative Council does not materialise. There are risks and difficulties in the proposal: but I think the High Commissioner is right.(Initialled) P. C.-L.Downing Street, S.W.I. November 14, 1934.[10773]
Draft of a Secret Despatch to be sent by the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the High Commissioner for Palestine.Sir, downing  Street, November   . 1934.I HAVE the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your secret despatch of the 25th August, and your secret despatches &quot;A&quot; and &quot;C&quot; of the same date, on the subject of the proposed legislative council for Palestine, and to inform you that I have given careful consideration to your comprehensive analysis of the problem and to the provisional conclusions which you have reached. I have also read with interest the account of your conversation on this subject with the President of the Moslem council, and the memorandum by the District Commissioner, Jerusalem District.2. I took the opportunity of your recent visit to this country to discuss this matter fully with you, and I will now set out, for your guidance in forthcoming discussions with Arab and Jewish representatives, the conclusions which I have reached, and with which I understand that you concur.3.   These conclusions are as follows : (A) Form of Council.(1) The Jewish claim to &quot; parity&apos;&apos; (i.e., the same number of seats as for the Arabs) should be rejected.(2) The unofficial side of the council should be constituted as follows : Elected members (to be based as nearl)r as possible on gross populationfigures) Moslems           ... ... ... ... 8Jews    ...         ... ... ... ... 3Christians         ... ... ... ... 112Nominated members Moslems           ... ... ... ... 2Bedouin            ... ... ... ... 1Jews    ...         ... ... ... ... 5Christians         ... ... ... ... 2Commercial interests ... ... ... 111(3) Apart from the High Commissioner, who would be president of the Council, the official members should be limited to five, i.e. : Chief Secretary   &quot;1 Treasurer yex officio,Attorney-General other officials, not exceeding two, to be nominated by the High Commissioner, as required from time to time.(4) The High Commissioner should hold the office of president of the council, but for all ordinary business he should depute the Chief Secretary to preside on his behalf.(5) Women should not be admitted as members of the council.(6) There should be a simple literacy test for elected members of the council.(7) There should not be any nationality test.(B)-Method of Election.(1) The right to vote should be given to all persons (of appropriate age and other qualifications) who have been resident in Palestine for a stated period and can prove that they are entitled to be so resident, and a similar qualification should apply in the case of members.APPENDIX 1.
(2) In order to secure the desired number of elected members of each community, the communal system of voting should be adopted; that is to say, each of the three religious communities should have its own constituencies covering the whole country, the number of constituencies depending upon the number of members to which each community is entitled.(3) The &apos;&apos; direct&apos;&apos; system of voting should be adopted, unless there should be a strong demand for the &apos;&apos; indirect &apos;&apos; system of primary and secondary election; there is no apparent reason why, if different communities held strong views on the matter, each should not have the system it prefers.(4) Each community should be allowed to decide whether its women should be allowed to vote.(C) Powers of the High Commissioner and of the Council.(1) The High Commissioner will have the usual power to refuse his assent to a Bill or &quot;reserve &quot; it.He should also have the following powers :  (i) Power to ensure the passing of legislation required in the public interest.(ii) Power to ensure the passing of such legislation within a time limit if itis required urgently, (iii) Power to legislate by Proclamation when the Legislative Council is not in session if the public interest demands the passage of such legisla-tion immediately.(2) All legislation, with the exception provided for in (1) (iii) above, must pass through the Council.(3) The provision of the Palestine Order-in-Council of 1922 prohibiting the legislative council from passing bills of a certain kind (including bills repugnant to or inconsistent with the provisions of the Mandate), should be omitted in the new7 Order-in-Council, and it will be sufficient to provide in the Royal Instructions that the High Commissioner shall not assent to such bills.(4) No subjects should be excluded from discussion in the legislative council, but it should be provided, as usual, that no vote, resolution, or ordinance for the appropriation of any part of the revenue, or for the imposition of any tax or impost should be proposed, except by the High Commissioner or by his direction.(5) The High Commissioner in Council should be given power (preferably by the Customs Tariff Ordinance) to impose or vary customs duties, subject to confirmation by the legislative council within a stated period.(6) The High Commissioner in Council should also have power to restrict clearances from bond.(7) Consideration should be given to the desirability of providing in the Royal Instructions in strong and comprehensive terms that the High Com-missioner should regard the welfare, &amp;c, of officials as a special charge.(E) Payment of Members. This question was left over for your further consideration.(F) -Jewish Agency.The claim of the Jewish Agency to be consulted before any bill is introduced into the legislative council should be refused, and there should be no departure from present practice in the matter of consultation between the High Commissioner and that body.4. I have also discussed with you your proposal to nominate a certain number of unofficials as members of the executive council. I am prepared to approve of this proposal in principle, and I understand that you will wish so to nominate one Arab and one Jewish representative, and possibly a representative of commercial or other interests, who will not be a Jew or an Arab. I have also informed you that I would deprecate the acceptance of any demand that unofficial members of the executive council should be elected. I would, however, suggest for your consideration that you will be well advised to nominate the unofficial [10773] &apos; b 2
members of the executive council as members of the legislative council, in order that the benefit of their moderating influence in the latter body may not be lost. You will no doubt furnish me in due course with your detailed recommendations in connection with the proposal to admit unofficial members to the executive council.5. In communicating these conclusions to you for your guidance I have no desire to preclude consideration of any modifications which you may wish to propose after further examination of the matter in Palestine, but I understand that you will not deviate in any essential from these conclusions without prior consultation with me.I have, &amp;c.APPENDIX 2.(1)Extract from Statement of British Policy in Palestine issued by Mr. Churchillin June 1922 (Cmd. 1700).******&quot; Nevertheless, it is the intention of His Majesty&apos;s Government to foster the establishment of a full measure of self-government in Palestine. But they are of opinion that, in the special circumstances of that country, this should be accomplished by gradual stages and not suddenly. The first step was taken when, on the institution of a civil Administration, the nominated Advisory Council, which now exists, was established. It was stated at the time by the High Commissioner that this was the first step in the development of self-governing institutions, and it is now proposed to take a second step by the establishment of a Legislative Council containing a large proportion of members elected on a wide franchise. It was proposed in the published draft that three of the members of this Council should be non-official persons nominated by the High Commissioner, but representations having been made in opposition to this provision, based on cogent considerations, the Secretary of State is prepared to omit it. The Legislative Council would, then consist of the High Commissioner as President and twelve elected and ten official members. The Secretary of State is of opinion that, before a further measure of self-government is extended to Palestine and the Assembly placed in control over the Executive, it would be wise to allow some time to elapse. During this period the institutions of the country will have become well established; its financial credit will be based on firm foundations, and the Palestinian officials will have been enabled to gain experience of sound methods of government. After a few years the situation will be again reviewed, and if the experience of the working of the constitution now to be established so warranted, a larger share of authority would then be extended to the elected representatives of the people.&quot;******(2)Extract from Report by the High Commissioner for Palestine on the Elections for the Palestine Legislative Council, 1923 (Cmd. 1889).Jt. Jtf- -it J.&apos;-&quot;Tv &quot;TV &quot;TV W &quot;A&quot; -ft-&quot; The basis of election was that every 200 primary electors should elect one secondary elector; but an aggregate of between 150 and 200 voters might be constituted as a separate voting area to elect one secondary elector, and an aggregate of between 350 and 400 voters might elect 2 secondary electors, and so forth.*X* 4&amp; 4&amp;
&quot; The system prescribed that, when the secondary electors had been elected, they would &quot;be constituted by Proclamation of the High Commissioner into 12 electoral colleges, of which not less than 2 should be Jewish, and not less than 2 Christian, and the remainder Moslem.&quot;* * * *      &apos;        * *[On the basis proposed in 1923, an election at that time would have given the following return : Jews     ... ... ?.&apos;.:        2Christians ... ...Moslems ...Total121

</content>
</cab>
