<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/251/0 images: 372-376</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1934.SECRET.Copy No.CP. 275 (34).CABINET.THE SAAR.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.IN paragraphs 4 and 5 of my memorandum for the Cabinet on the 16th November, I raised the question of the maintenance of order in the Saar during the plebiscite and in the succeeding interval. I emphasised (a) that as Mr. Knox is an English official we have, whether we like it or not, very special reasons for wishing to prevent the possibility of an outbreak; if anything happened to him, our responsibility would be grave unless we had previously clone all we could to prevent it and to suppress it; (b) that it is very questionable if the exercise of the Commissions right to appeal to French troops might not precipitate the very crisis it is meant to avert, nor have we any certainty that the French General Staff, who realise this, will, in the case of an emergency, send them in time to restore the situation; and (c) that the consequences of a break-up in the Saar are so serious, and the ultimate results so menacing, that it would be far better to make sure, if we could, that nothing untoward happened now, than, by shutting our eyes to possible consequences, to give the opportunity for a calamity that might be avoided.2. In his telegrams from Geneva No. 72. Saving, of the 21st November (see Annex I) and No. 104 of the 23rd November (see Annex II). the Lord Privy Seal reported his interviews with M. Laval and Mr. Knox on this subject. M. Laval made it clear that France would take no steps to come to Mr. Knox&apos;s assistance unless they were given an. international character. He would ask at the Council that if France was expected to respond to an appeal for help by Mr. Knox in the case of an emergency, other countries interested, notably Great Britain and Italy, should also send contingents, however small. It is to be noted, incidentally, that M. Laval no longer speaks of sending troops but of police. If Great Britain and Italy would not send contingents, then he hoped that the Council would make it clear that they would expect France to send police only as part of an international action to meet an emergency, but France herself would not ask for this; it was the responsibility of the Council.3. Mr. Knox informed Mr. Eden that the only sure way of dealing with the situation in the Saar would have been by the stationing of regular troops in the Saar itself before any emergency had occurred and that he had asked the Committee of Three now sitting in Rome for 2,000 of these. The committee had refused to consider the request on the ground that no country would be willing to supply them. In the circumstances, Mr. Knox is doing his best with his local police force of 1,200 men, which he was trying to raise to 1,500 by local recruit-ment, and with an international police force, which he was recruiting abroad and which he aimed at raising to a strength of 25 officers and 140 men. At present he has 12 officers, of whom 5 are English, and 24 men. Mr. Knox added that in his opinion the danger of a &quot; Putsch &quot; was not at the moment from outside the Saar but from within it; and that what he feared was a repetition of some attempt on the lines of the attack on Dr. Dollfuss. Such an attempt might well be organised by the local Communists and other anti-Nazi elements in order to provoke foreign intervention and thereby discredit the German Government.
4. The question which calls for an immediate decision is that of the reply to be made to M. Laval, when, upon the reassembly of the Council next week, he, as he is almost certain to do, asks our Representative (a) Whether, if and when the French send police (or troops) into the Saar at mr. Knox&apos;s request, His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom will send a contingent to co-operate with the French force in the Saar; and(b) In the event of a negative reply to question (a) what attitude the british representative at the Council will assume to a proposal (which apparently will now be made by France), that the French Government should be given a special ad hoc mandate by the Council to intervene in the Saar in an emergency, instead of being bound, as at present, by the out-of-date Resolution of 1926.5. The possible answers which can be made to these two questions seem to be as follows :-(a) The reply could be that His Majesty&apos;s Government are not prepared tosend a contingent to co-operate with the force which the French might send into the Saar, or to agree even to token co-operation by the attachment of, say, a single officer. (If the French force took the form of police it would be materially impossible to supply a police contingent from this country, as we have no constabulary corresponding with French garde mobile.) It is evident that token representation, at any rate, would afford us little or no opportunity of control over the action of the force which would be predominantly French and whose intervention might very well prove belated and ineffective (in which case we would share the blame with the French). Besides, the whole system of using French forces to restore order would remain just as obnoxious to the German Government, even though it contained a token British contingent.(b) The reply could be that our Representative at Geneva will support aproposal that the Council should give France a special ad hoc mandate for French forces to intervene in an emergency if summoned by Mr. Knox. The objection to such a procedure would be that a special decision by the Council to entrust the maintenance of law and order in the Saar to one of the countries directly concerned in the result of the plebiscite would be contrary to all sense of justice, and would provoke a protest by Germany which would be difficult to counter. Even so, we would have no assurance that French assistance would, in fact, arrive in time in the case of a sudden attack on the Saar Government and Mr. Knox in particular.(c) A third possible answer, in view of the risks just pointed out, would beto urge M. Laval not to ask for an immediate decision by the Council to confer a mandate upon France, but to wait until the emergency arose, when he could be assured that such a mandate would, in fact, be given. The objection to this course is that by its very indecision it would be an encouragement, at any rate, to local disturbers of the peace to make trouble. Besides, in the case of a sudden rising in the Saar speed will be an essential factor, and there will probably be no time to call together the Council before the situation has got entirely out of control.i^d) A fourth possible answer would be that we recognise the disadvantages, and indeed the impropriety, of intervention in the Saar by France, which is directly intei&apos;ested in the plebiscite result; and that therefore, subject to the approval of the Council and similar action by Italy, the other great disinterested European Power, we will supply one-half of the 2,000 soldiers stated to be necessary by Mr. Knox; this force will be immediately despatched to the Saar, where it will remain throughout the plebiscite and the period by which it will necessarily be followed before the decision of the League of Nations is declared.6. I am fully conscious of the domestic difficulties inherent in the last proposal. But the three other possible answers seem to me to be fraught with :such danger that I feel it must be considered.
ANNEX I.Consul, Geneva, to Sir John Simon. (Received November 22.)[By Bag.](No 72.   Saving.)(Telegraphic.)   En clair. Geneva, November 21, 1934.FOLLOWING from Mr. Eden :-&quot; I had a long talk with M. Laval this afternoon.&quot;Saar.   (Strictly confidential.)&apos;&apos; M. Laval wished me to know that he would not have signed the French memorandum deposited by M. Barthou. However, since that, document had been deposited, France would certainly not go back on it. At the same time he himself did not wish for a second plebiscite. He had made this clear. M. Litvinov was much more anxious for it on account of the Communist and Jewish minority in the Saar and of his desire to see Hitler suffer a rebuff. M. Laval took a longer view and did not himself desire any such result. He had communicated to M. Litvinov the gist of our interpretation of the Saar annex.&apos;&apos; As to the policing of the Saar, he was going to take up a clear and, he hoped, a frank position at the Council. France was determined to take no step in the Saar that was not internationally sanctioned. He had no desire to send a policeman or a soldier into the Saar. and if she did so it could only be in a case of emergency because she was physically nearest to the area. M. Laval would therefore ask at the Council that if police were asked for from France in an emergency, other countries interested, notably Great Britain and Italy, should also send contingents, however small. If Great Britain and Italy were determined not to send contingents, then he hoped the Council would make it clear that they would expect France to send police only as part of an international action to meet an emergency. But France herself would not ask for this; this was a responsibility of the Council.&quot; M. Laval then made an earnest appeal to His Majesty&apos;s Government to signify their willingness to co-operate with police should the need arise. There was no question of troops. He was himself convinced that if it were known that Italy and Great Britain would be associated in police action, were such required in an emergency, then the emergency would never arise.&quot; M. Laval expressed his regret that the Governing Commission, in recruiting their police, had insisted that applicants should speak both French and German. This had inevitably limited the number of applicants, since nationals well enough educated to speak French and German, as well as their own language, were not likely to be in so humble a state of life as to wish to enlist as ordinary policemen in the Saar. If the Governing-Commission had been content to make this a condition for officers only, then they might have had a stronger police at their disposal, and he himself would have been less anxious.7. I must point out that the difficulties with which the Governing Commission is now confronted will inevitably be greatly increased once the plebiscite has taken place. For in the event (as must almost certainly be expected) of a majority of whatever size in favour of Germany, there will at once be great pressure for the immediate transfer to the German administration of what will then have been proved by the plebiscite to be German territory. Further excite-ment amongst the minority will by then have been increased owing to their desire for guarantees. In these circumstances, the possibility of the intervention of French forces, which would even now be fraught with danger, will by then, on the eve of the transfer of the territory to Germany, have become inconceivable.J. S.Foreign Office. November 27, 1934.
&quot; M. Laval was throughout emphatic that his policy was one of conciliation with Germany. He had been the first French Minister to go to Berlin, and he was determined to do all in his power to ensure that the issue of the Saar should not become a cause of friction between the two countries. He had himself seen the German Ambassador and appealed to him to induce Hitler to calm the German press, and in return he had promised to calm the French press. Hitler had done so, and so had he, and the press of the two countries were much calmer.&quot; Again, M. Laval had undertaken to the German Ambassador that he would be willing to discuss at the Committee of Three in Rome provisions for payment in respect of the coal-mines, it being understood that the possibility of a vote for the status quo should not be ruled out by such discussion upon that basis progress had recently been made at Rome.&quot;ANNEX IIConsul, Geneva, to Sir John Simon. (Received November 24.) (No. 104.   L.N.   Important.   Very Confidential.)(Telegraphic.) Geneva, November 23, 1934.FOLLOWING from Mr. Eden :-&apos;&apos; Mr. Knox arrived in Geneva, and I had a first conversation with him this morning. I gave him information contained in your telegram No. 113. and he &quot;expressed thanks.&quot; I asked Mr. Knox what were the prospects for the plebiscite and what progress he was making with recruitment of his police forces. He replied that there were several anxious elements in the situation. He could certainly give no undertaking that it would be possible to get through next two months without serious disturbance, and the period immediately after plebiscite would be even more difficult than period before it. His chief anxiety was due to infiltration of undesirables from Germany into the Saar. It was difficult to get definite evidence, but Mr. Knox was certain that this was going on. For instance, he had heard of the presence of Austrians, whom he suspected to be members of disbanded Austrian Legion. Moreover, those inhabitants of the Saar who had been drafted into labour camps in Germany, where they had received a measure of military training, were all to be given leave to return to the Saar from 23rd December to 17th January. There were some 17,000 of these young men. I asked Mr. Knox if they were voters, and he said that most of them were. This, coupled with Christmas season, was the ostensible reason for their leave. In addition, there were at least 8,000 inhabitants of the Saar who were in reality, though not outwardly, members of S.A. and S.S. Clearly, therefore, there were sufficient potential elements of trouble.&quot; The.only sui*e way of meeting this situation would have been by use of regular troops. He had asked Committee of Three for 2,000 of these for this purpose. Committee had turned down proposal on the grounds that no country would have been willing to supply them. In the circumstances, he was doing his best with his existing police force, the moral of which had slightly improved of late, and was also recruiting police from outside the Saar. His aim was to build up a force of twenty-five officers and 140 men. At present he had twelve officers, of whom five were English, and twenty-four men. Only detachment which had so far arrived from outside was Czech. He hoped, however, that arrangements for organised detachment of serving police from Holland would be completed within the next few days. Mr. Knox was especially anxious that this information should on no account he divulged. He had also secured some officers from Scandinavian countries, and was endeavouring to give his police force as international an aspect as possible, since this in itself would have sobering effect.
o&quot; Mr. Knox said that he would also be able to enlist some twenty ex-guardsmen in the ranks of his extra police in the same way as he had enlisted his five English officers, but1 that he had not yet done so, since he wanted to make quite sure that such a step would not embarrass us. If, however, this could be approved, it would greatly assist him.&quot; Mr. Knox expressed himself as pleased with the men supplied by Scotland Yard, for whose services he was grateful.&quot; Danger of a &apos; Putsch &apos; was not now from outside the Saar, but from within it. If opportunity offered important thing was to impress German Ambassador that we looked to German Government to discourage Germans in the Saar rather than outside from undertaking anything of the kind, and to make clear to them that we were sure there would be no &apos; Putsch &apos; in the Saar unless instigated by German authority from outside. What Mr. Knox feared was repetition of 25th July in Austria, and anything that could be done to warn German Government against that would be helpful.&quot; Mr. Knox has no direct contact with French Government. Though he himself knows personally French officer commanding troops in the neighbourhood, he has neither seen him nor had any communication with him. He keeps touch with French Government and with French General Staff exclusively through his French colleague on the commission.&quot;(Repeated to Paris.)

</content>
</cab>
