<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/251/0 images: 450-452</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS   DOCUMENT   IS   THE   PROF^TY   Off   HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVEruTiIENT.37 (54).CiBINE T.Copy No.  jlAttitude towards Ratification of the International Labour385Convention on the Abolition of Fee-Charging employment agencies.(Memorandum by the Minister of Labour).1.     This question v/as on the Agenda of the Sixteenth Session of the International Labour Conference, held in April, 1932, for a first reading, and as a result a Questionnaire v/as drawn up for circulation to Governments and the question was placed on the Agenda of the Seventeenth Session. 2. Government replied to the Questionnaire as follows :-&quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom regret that they are unable to complete the Questionnaire on the subject of the abolition of fee-charging employment agencies, since they do not agree with the assumption upon which the Questionnaire is based, that the abolition of such agencies is desirable in prinoiple.     In their view a fee-charging employment agency which is conducted with due regard to the public interest, subject to such measures of regulation as may be thought essential, is a legitimate form of private enterprise.His Majesty&apos;s Government further consider that such agencies provide a specialised service of which the public ought not to be deprived unless and until the national employment exchanges are so developed and extended as to provide an alternative service.    In that event the public would no doubt use the employment exchanges rather than fee-charging employment agencies.His Majesty&apos;s Government, therefore, are opposed to abolition, which, apart from the question of principle involved, would tend to create hardship and public inconvenience, but are in favour of a policy of gradual development of national eirployraent exchanges to provide such services as are required by the publiciHis Majosty&apos;s Government rely on local authorities in the United Kingdom to obviate the possibility of abuse under the powers which they may exercise in accordance with existing legislation or in pursuance of private Acts&quot;.\
3.     Accordingly, the instructions to the representatives of H.ii.Government at the Seventeenth Session, held in June, 1933, were that, if called upon to express their views, they should state that H.M.Government would be prepared to vote for the Convention if its terras did not go further than to provide for the regulation of fee-charging agencies (the precise method of regulation being left to each country concerned), but that, if the terns of the Convention provided either for the total abolition of these agencies or, alternatively, for their regulation by methods prescribed in the Convention itself in a manner conflicting with the existing system in Great Britain, they would be compelled to vote against its adoption. 4.     In the event, it did not become necessary for the representatives of H.M.Government to make any further statement in explanation of the reply to the Questionnaire and they were not members of the Committee which considered the question.5.     The Committee proposed a Convention providing for the abolition of Fee-Charging Employment Agencies within three years.    This was adopted by 91 votes to 20, the representatives of ii.h.Government abstaining from voting. The British Employers&apos; delegate voted against and the Workers&apos; delegate for the adoption of the Convention.6.     In these circumstances, it cannot be contended that this country bears any responsibility for the adoption of this Convention.   No obstacle was placed in the way of those countries which might desire a Convention abolishing such agencies but f^air warning was given in the answer to the Questionnaire that such a Convention would not be acceptable to this country. 7.     Since that time, a deputation from the Trades Union Congress General Council has urged ratification and a deputation representing the Agencies has asked for a decision not to ratify.8.     i see no reason why the view already expressed by ELM. Government should be altered and accordingly recommend that the Convention should not be ratified.9.     In addition to the adoption of the Convention a Recommendation in two sections was also adopted by the Conference.   The first section recommended that existing Exchanges should be adaj^ted to meet the needs of the occupations for which fee-charging agencies catered, that specialised Exchanges should be set up for particular occupations and should be staffed where possible by technical exports and that representatives of the organisations of workers
and employers in the occupations concerned should be invited to collaborate in the working of the Employment Exchanges.    The second section recommended that persons and undertakings deriving profit from activities such as tho keeping of public houses, hotels, second hand clothing shops, pawn shops or money changing should be forbidden to engage in placing and that placing operations should be prohibited on all premises whore any of the above mentioned trades were carried on.10.   With the exception of the recommendation that the specialised Exchanges should be staffed by technical experts, I am in sympathy with the principles set out in the first section of the Recommendation and am in fact endeavouring to extend and develop the Employment Exchange Service along the lines indicated. To give effect to Section II of the Recommendation, legislation would be necessary and I do not consider that the circumstances in this country require the promotion of such legislation.   For these reasons, and because the Recommendation is intended to be complementary to the Convention, I suggest that if we do not ratify the latter we should not accept the Recommendation.(Intld.)   0. S.5th December, 1934.H.Q.164-65.L.D.3,

</content>
</cab>
