<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/251/0 images: 489-491</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF KIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT.RET, 298(34).COPY NOCABINET.UNITED KINGDOM TRADE .7ITH MCROCCO. An Arrangement for meeting Japanese Competition.4 -memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.Owing to the rapidly Increasing competition of Japanese cotton goods in Morocco, the Lancashire and French cotton indust-i*i3S consulted together about a year ago on the possibility of their -joint interests being safeguarded.    His Majesty&apos;s Government possess special treaty rights in Morocco which, Inter alia, preclude Increases in the Customs duties; moreover, under the Act of Algeclras a number of Powers have rights of &quot;commercial liberty without inequality&quot;.    Consequently when the French were negotiating with us in June on the main Trade Agreement, they raised the question of action to safeguard the trade of both our countries in Morocco against the common danger.(Japan)The French have recently submitted concrete proposals.    These have been thoroughly discussed and a detailed scheme has now almost been worked out, subject to the approval of both Governments. The broad lines are as follows1. Quotas are to be imposed In Morocco on imports of cotton and artificial silk piece goods and on certain other classes of goods in which our Interest in Morocco is small - namely, pure silks, cement, Iron and steel and machinery, motor cars, rubber tyres, sugar.    The quotas will be allocated between the countries concerned on the basis of trade In the average of the 6 year.:.; 1928 -1933. Certain special guarantees will be given to us as to our trade in cotton goods and a special assurance will be given whereby our trade in quotaed goods, such as motor cars, in which our proportionof the imports is under S% of the total should not normally be Interfered with.
2. In return for these advantages the French desire to secure additional revenue by increasing the Customs duties which are at present fixed at 12^- per cent, ad valorem by the Act of AlgarIras, and the general level of import duties is accordingly to be raised to I5;i ad valorem.    The duty on coal (other than anthracite) will, however, be reduced to IQfc at our request, whilst tha duties on certain other specified goods (Including vegetable oils and motor cars) in which we have comparatively little Interest, will be raised to 25?;.3. A new system of customs procedure, which appears generally equitable, Is to be substitued for the present antiquated and unsatisfactory system,4, We give an assurance  (similar to that given by Members of the League of Nations In respect of A. and B. Mandates) that we will consider favourably any requests that might be made with a view to securing for Morocco In commercial matters advantages corresponding to those enjoyed by the United Kingdom In Morocco a This is really for window-dressing purposes and it is understood that the French have no Immediate intention of approaching us on these lines.5. Our treaty position Is fully safeguarded.Until recently over half the value of our exports to Morocco consisted of cotton piece-goods ( 1,400,000 in 1928 and  800,000 In 1932), but in 1934 the value has shrunk to about  250,000 owing to Japanese competition.   Under the proposed quota we ought to get back practically all the trade lest In the last few years.    As against this outstanding advantage to our cotton trade there is little to put on the debit side.    The general increase of 2%% In the tariff will hardly bo   felt;       we have not much interest in the items whioh are to be increased from 12%% to 25$; there may be some small disadvantage to our export trade as a result of the quotas on
57.R.Board of Trade. 17th December, 1934.machinery, etc., hut our trade In those items Is small compared with that In cotton goods.The advantages to us so much outweight any possible disadvantages that I have no hesitation in asking the Cabinet to authorise ma to conclude an arrangement on the general lines I have Indicated, subject to the details being worked out satisfactorily.I should add that separate exchanges of Notes will probably be necessary with the Spanish Government in regard to the Spanish Zone in Morocco and with the French Government as regards Tangier.    It is the intention that the new measures shall be introduced as early as possible in the New Year, A definite date cannot be named at present as negotiations with other Powers are still proceeding.

</content>
</cab>
