<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/83/0 images: 160-172</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
The proposals contained in this Bill are based on the recommendations of the Report of Lord Selborne?s sub-committee of the Reconstruction Committee (c.d.9079).     The material paragraphs are 10? - 112.Part I of the Bill proposes to constitute for consultative purposes a Council of Agriculture for England and a separate Council for Wales.    As a standing advisory body it is proposed to appoint an Agricultural Advisory Committee for England and Wales combined. The Councils of Agriculture will consist mainly of persons representi the County Agricultural Committees proposed to be constituted under Part II of the Bill.    Each Council&apos;will contain representatives in equal numbers of the employers and workmen who are members of the Agricultural Wages Board, and also persons nominated by the Board of Agriculture of whom a specified number shall be representative of workmen engaged in agriculture, the industry of horticulture, and agricultural education or research.      The Welsh Council will comprise persons nominated by the University of &quot;&apos;ales.    Provision is made for the inclusion of women on eash Council,The Agricultural Advisory Committee eonaists of 12 memberij, ten of whom are nominated by the Councils of Agriculture and two ary nominated by the Agricultural Wages Board.The Board take power by regulation to vary the constitutions of the Councils and the Committee.The Bill also contains corresponding provisions as regardsFisheries.These proposals follcw generally the lines of agricultural administration in Ireland, but the Committee will not, as in Ireland, have a right tc veto expenditure, (see paragraphs 90-91 of the above mentioned Report) as the Beard of Agriculture have no fund corresponding to the Endowment Fund referred to in those paragraphs..Tho Advisory Committee will advise on all matters submitted to them by the Board and are authorized to make recommendations to . &apos; the Board.In order t*at the Advisory Committee may have,, some effective influence on agricultural administration,  clause 3(3) provides that whore the Board refer a matter to the Committee and do not act in accordance with their advice the Beard shall, if so requested by the Committee, lay their report before Parliaments    This would not apply to questions of puro policy which the Board would not submit to the I Committee nor to recommendations made by the Committee on their own initiative.Part II of the Bill which originally formed part of tho Land Settlement (Facilities) Bill has already bean approved by the Cabinet. It provides for the constitution in each county of an agricultural committee and for sub-committees.    All -agricultural matters will stand referred to the agricultural committee or a sub-committee.     The matter of education is dealt with specially in clause   7(2), The best method of doling with matters that relate to agriculture and also to(Tft^s poftuas^t is the Pm-party of Hie Br.itann.ta Majesty^ Government.)H&quot;!   WAR CABINET. /Vjeoret *SpSJk . &quot;Agriculture and Fisheries Bill.1&apos;&quot;.IT Kf^(hI ,.J       Memorandum by the President of tho Board of Agricultureand Fisheries.
public health is under the consideration of the two Departments concerned.Part III, Clause 9, of the Bill removes the present limitation on the salary of tho PresidentnIRELE.7th July, 1919.
Agriculture and Fisheries Bill.ItARRANGEMENT OP CLAUSES.Part I.Councils and Committees for England, and &quot;Wales.Clause.1.   Constitution of councils and committees.2. Duties of Councils of Agriculture.3. Duties and powers of agricultural and fisheries committees. 4.   Conference in relation to fisheries.5. Supplementary provisions as to councils and committees.6. Provision as to Monmouthshire.Part II.County Agricultural Committees.7.   Constitution of committees.8.  Additional powers of committees.Part III. General.9.   Salary of President of Board of Agriculture and Pisheries. 10.   Short title. Schedules.123-2
D II A F Tof aBILLtoProvide for the constitution of Councils and Committees a.d. 1919. in connection with agriculture and fisheries, and to amend the Board of Agriculture and Fisheries Acts, 18.89 to 1909.E it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent, of the Lords Spiritual and Tempoial, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, . and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5 Part I.Councils and Committees for England and Wales.1. (1) Eor the purpose of assisting the Board of Agriculture Constitution and Pisheries (in this Act referred to as the Board) in executing ot ?oullcllsv &apos; 0 and coni-their powers and duties there shall be established         -     -   mittees. 10       (a) a Council of Agriculture for England;(b) a Council of Agriculture for Wales;(c) an Agricultural Advisory Committee for England andWales; and Id) a fisheries Advisory Committee for England and Wales.15 (2) The Council of Agriculture for England and the Council of Agriculture for Wales may from time to time by agreement act together as one Council.(3) The various councils and committees above referredto shall be constituted as provided by the Eirst Schedule to 20 this Act.123-2 A
A.p. 1919.Duties of . Councils of Agriculture.Duties and powers of agricultural andfisheries committees.2. Each Council of Agriculture shall meet at least twice a year for the purpose of discussing matters of public interest relating to agriculture or other rural industries.3. (i) The Agricultural Advisory Committee shall advise the Board with, respect to all matters and questions submitted 5 to them in relation to the exercise by the Board of any powers or duties which do not relate to the industry of fishing;, and shall be at liberty to make recommendations to the Board in relation to other matters affecting agriculture or other rural industries.(2) The Fisheries Advisory Committee shall have the like 10 powers and duties in relation to the industry of fishing and distribution of fish.(3) In any case where the Board submit any matter or question to the Agricultural Advisory Committee or Fisheries Advisory Committee and do not act in accordance with the 15 advice given by the committee, the Board shall, if so requested by the committee, lay before both Houses of Parliament a statement of the matter or question referred and of the advice given.Conferences 4. (l) The Board shall, at least twice in each year, convene 20 in relation to a meeting to confer with the Board and for consultative purposes on matters relating to the industry of fishing and distribution of fish ; and such meeting shall be composed of not less than one representative selected by each of the local fisheries&apos; committees constituted under the Sea Fisheries Regulation Act, 1888, together 25 with such other persons as in the opinion of the Board will represent the different branches of the industry of fishing and distribution of fish and also education and research in connection with that industry.(2) Section nine of the Sea Fisheries Regulation Act, 1888, 30 is hereby repealed.Snpplemen- 5. (l) The Board may make general regulations for regu-plenipoteniary pro- lating the proceedings for the appointment of the members of &quot;hfand each council and committee established by this Part of this Act,councilcommittees,  and the number of meetings and the proceedings and quorum of 35 each council and committee, and the appointing body, council, or committee shall act in accordance with those regulations.(2) The President of the Board, or, in his absence, a secretary of  the   Board, shall  be  entitled  to  attend  any
meeting of a council or committee established by this Part of A.D. 1919. this Act and act as an ex-omcio member and chairman of the meeting and have a casting vote, but, save as aforesaid, shall not vote at any meeting of the council or committee.5 (3) The Board may require any of their officers to act as secretary, or other officer of a council or committee established by this Part of this Act.(4) Auy regulation made under this Act shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament forthwith; and if an address is10 presented to His Majesty &quot;by either House of Parliament within the next subsequent twenty-eight days on which that House has sat after any such regulation is laid before it praying that the regulation may be annulled, His Majesty in Council may annul the Regulation, and it shall henceforth be void, but without] 5 prejudice to the validity of anything previously done thereunder.(5) The expenses of any council or committee established by this Part of this Act or of any fishery meeting convened under this Act shall, to such extent as may be sanctioned by the Board, with the consent of the Treasury, be defrayed by the20 Board out of moneys provided bj Parliament; and such expenses may include such sums as the Board think reasonable for defraying the expenses for travelling and subsistence when absent from home of the members of the council or committee or the representatives at the meeting [or by way of25 compensation for their loss of time].6. For the purposes of this Act Monmouthshire shall be Provision included n Wales and not in England. as t0 Mo&quot;-mouthsliire.Part II.County Agricultural Committees.30       7. (1) The council of every county shall, and the council Constitution of any county borough may, establish an agricultural committee constituted in accordance wdth a scheme made by the council and approved by the Board.   A committee may consist partly of persons who are not members of the council.35       (2) All matters relating to the exercise by the council of their powers under any Act specified in the Second Schedule to this Act, and all other matters relating to agriculture, except 123 A 2
A.D. 1919. such matters as under the Education Act, 1902, stand referred to the education committee, and, except the raising of a rate or borrowing, shall (stand referred to the agricultural committee, . and the council, before exercising their powers in relation to any matter so referred, shall, unless in their opinion the matter 5 is urgent, receive and consider the report of the agricultural committee with respect to the matter in question :Provided that (i) on the application of the council the Board, afterconsultation with the Board of Education, may by 10 order direct that any matter specified in the order and relating to agricultural education which but for this provision would stand referred to the education committee shall stand referred to the agricultural committee; and 15(ii) if the council of a&apos;county.borough so resolve matters relating to any of their powers under any Act specified in the said Schedule shall not stand so referred to the agricultural committee.(3) The ,council may delegate to the agricultural committee 20 with or without any restrictions or conditions any of their powers in relation to matters which by virtue of this section stand referred to the committee, and, if so provided by the scheme, any powers so delegated may in like manner be dele-gated by the agricultural committee to a sub-committee. A 25 sub-committee may consist partly of persons who are not mem-bers of the council or of the agricultural committee.(4) Every scheme under this section shall provide (a) for the appointment by the council of at least amajority of the agricultural committee, and the 30 persons so appointed shall be persons who are members of the council, unless, in the case of a county, the council otherwise determine:(b) for the appointment by the Board of at least one thirdof the. members of the agricultural   committee, 35 and of any sub-committee to which powers of the agricultural committee are delegated :(c) for the inclusion of women as well as men among themembers of the agricultural committee.(5) Any scheme under this section may, for all or any of 40 the purposes of this section, provide for a joint agricultural
committee for any area formed by a combination of counties or A.u. 19.19, county boroughs or parts thereof.(6) If a scheme under this section has not been made by a council of a county and approved by the Board within six 5 months after the passing of this Act, the Board may after consultation with the council make a scheme for the purposes for which a scheme might have been made by the council.8. (1) The Board may authorise, subject to any restrictions -Additional or conditions they think fit, an agricultural committee or a committees. 10 sub-committee thereof to exercise on behalf of the Board any of the powers of the Board under the provisions of Part IV. of the Corn Production Act, 1917, or Part II. of the Land Drainage Act, 1918, notwithstanding that the committee or sub-committee is not constituted in accordance with those provisions, 15 or any powers of the Board in relation to land acquired by - them under the Small Holding Colonies Acts, 1916 and 1918.(2) The agricultural committee shall appoint a small holdings and allotments sub-committee and a diseases of animals sub-committee, who shall respectively act as the small holdings and20 allotments committee required to be established under section fifty of the Small Holdings and Allotments Act, 1908, and as the executive committee appointed under the Diseases of Animals Act, 1894, though the sub-committee may not be constituted in accordance with the provisions of those Acts.25 (3) The small holdings and allotments sub-committee shall comprise one or more members appointed by the Board as representing tenants of small holdings and allotments, and any such member shall receive from the Board for expenses and by way of compensation for loss of time such sums as the Board30 with the approval of the Treasury may allow.(4) A county agricultural committee shall make such inquiries as appear to them to be desirable with a view to formulating schemes for the development of rural industries and social life in rural places, and for the co-ordination of35 action by local authorities and other bodies by &quot;which such development may be effected, and shall report the result of such inquiries to the Board and to any local authority or body concerned, and the expenses inclined by the committee under this section to such amount as may be sanctioned by the Board40 with the approval of the Treasury shall be defrayed by the Board.
A.D.1919.Salary of President of Board of Agriculture andFisheries. Short title.Part III. General.9. Notwithstanding the limitation of the salary of the President of the Board contained in section five of the Board of Agriculture Act, 1889, the annual salary shall be such as 5 Parliament may determine.10. This Act may be cited as the Agriculture and Pisheries Act, 1919, and the Board of Agriculture and Pisheries Acts, 1889 to 1909, and this Act may be cited together as the Board of Agriculture and Pisheries Acts, 1889 to 1919. 10
SCHEDULE S. A.D.1919.EIBST SCHEDULE.1. (1) The Council of Agriculture for England shall consist of the Compositionfollowing members:  of cQuncllsand com-5       (a) One member of each of the Agricultural Committees established mittees. by the councils of the counties and county boroughs in England to he nominated by the committee.(b) Twelve members of the Agricultural Wages Board to be nomi*nated by that Board in, equal numbers from the repre-10 sentatives of employers and workmen.(c) Twenty-four persons nominated by the Board, of whom sixshall be representatives of workmen engaged in agriculture, and of the remainder three at least shall be women, six shall be representative of the industry of horticulture, and 15 three representative of agricultural education or research.(2) The Council of Agriculture for Wales shall consist of the following members: (a) Two members of each of the Agricultural Committees establishedby the councils of the counties and county boroughs in Wales 20 to be nominated by the committee.(b) Five persons nominated by the governing body of the Univer-sity of Wales.(c) Four members of the Agricultural Wages Board to be nominated by that Board in equal numbers from the representatives 25 of employers and workmen.(d) Eleven persons nominated by the Board, of whom four shall be representative of workmen engaged in agriculture, and of the remainder two at least shall be women.(3) The Advisory Agricultural Committee shall consist of the 30 following members(a) Four of the members of the Council of Agriculture for England who have been nominated by the Agricultural Committees to be nominated by the whole body of such members representing tlie Agricultural Committee.
A.D. 1919.        (6) Four of the members of the Council of Agriculture for Englandwho have been nominated by the Board to be nominated by the whole body of such members, and so. that one. of the persons so nominated shall be representative of work-men engaged in agriculture, another shall be a woman, 5 and a third shall be representative of agricultural education or research.(c) Two members of the Agricultural Wages Board to be nominated by that Board in equal numbers from the representatives of employers and workmen. 10id) Two men iibers of the Council of Agriculture for Wales to be nominated by that council.(4) The Board may by regulation vary the constitution of any such council or committee.(5) The Fisheries Committee shall be constituted in manner prescribed 15 by regulations made by the Board, and such regulations shall, as far as practicable, provide for the nomination or election of members representative of the different branches of the industry of fishing and distribution of fish and of education and research in connection with that industry. 20Term of 2. (1) Subject to the provisions of any regulations made underoffice of       this Act the term of office of a member of a council or committeemeinbeis of .councils and shall be tour years, provided that committees.        ^ Q  ^e first members of each council or committee one half, or if the total is not, divisible by two, the larger half shall 25 hold office for two years only, and the determination of the members so to retire shall be prescribed by regulations made by the Board which, so far as practicable, shall secure that the retirements affects equally all interests represented on the council or committee;      . 30(b) a member shall cease to hold office if he ceases to be qualified for nomination by the body by which he was nominated;-fi) any member may retire by notice in writing to the secretary of the council or committee ;Kd) a casual vacancy shall be filled by nomination by the body 35 which nominated the member causing the vacancy, and any person so nominated shall act only for the unexpired portion of the term of office of his predecessor.(2) A council or committee may act notwithstanding any vacancy in the membership thereof.
SECOND SCHEDULE. A.D. 1919.Destructive Insects and Pests Acts, 1877 and 1907. Diseases of Animals Acts, 1894 to 1914. Fertilisers and Feeding Stuffs Act, 1906. 5 Land Drainage Act, 1918.Small Holdings and Allotments Act, 1908
Agriculture and Fisheries.DHAPTgf ABILL,To provide for the constitution of Councils and Committees in connec-tion with&apos; [agriculture and fisheries and to amend the Board of Agriculture and Pisheries Actsy 1889 to 1909.CVI.   (2.)17 th May 1919.123-2

</content>
</cab>
