<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/83/0 images: 305-306</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.WAR CABINET.GRIGORIEFFS MOVEMENT.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for War.I circulate a note which has been prepared by the General Staff.WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.9th July, 1919]In January, 1919, at the time of the Bolshevik invasion of the Ukraine, which resulted in the expulsion of Petlura&apos;s directorate from the Eastern Ukraine, Atamen Grigorieff, a former adherent of Petluras, deserted to the Bolsheviks with a following of some 10,000 men. These were organized into a division and co-operated with the Bolshevik forces in their march on Odessa. Grigorieff with his division formed an integral part of the Bolshevik forces on the south-western front until the middle of May, 1919, wheivit was announced in the Bolshevik wireless news that he had revolted against the Soviet authorit)^ had proclaimed himself Ataman of the Kherson and Taurida Governments, and had announced his intention of marching on Kieff and Kharkoff.The course of events may be shortly summarized as follows : After the capture of Odessa by the Bolsheviks, Grigorieff and his troops, who for a short time occupied Odessa, broke away from the Bolsheviks and marched in a north-westerly direction, gathering adherents as they went.For some considerable time the only information regarding GrigoriefFs activities was obtained from Bolshevik wireless reports. These reports almost daily announced sweeping victories over the rebel bands with statements to the effect that the revolt was on the eve of collapse. At the same time, however, the area of county occupied by GrigoriefFs bands did not diminish in its extent; on the contrary, new outbreaks were from time to time reported by the Bolsheviks. Generally, the field of GrigoriefFs activities covered the whole course of the Dnieper from Kieff to Kherson and a considerable area of territory on either bank.Kherson, Ekaterinoslav, Kobeliaki, Kremenchug, Cherkassi, Elizavetgrad and Nicolaieff have all at one time or another been occupied by Grigorieff or his adherents, and although these towns are now reported by the Bolsheviks to be in the hands of the Soviet troops, Grigorieff is still active in a more confined area and according to a Press report in the Times of the 4th July Odessa has been seized by Grigorieff who, it was reported, has proclaimed his readiness to co-operate with the Allies in a few days if the latter will assume the offensive on the Dniester.When Grigorieff marched out of Odessa he had some 6,000 10,000 men at his command, who were joined not only the peasants but by many deserters from the Bolshevik forces in South Russia. Reports from Nicolaieff newspapers, of the 24th and 26th May, stated that several Soviet Ukrainian regiments went over to Grigorieff. It is also probable that Makhno, an ex-convict, and leader of some 10,000 men in the Bolshevik forces opposed to Denikihs Yolunteer Army, has an understanding with Grigorieff, and even if he himself has not actively participated in the revolt many of his troops have rebelled against the Bolsheviks. It has also been stated that Grigorieff is in touch with Petlura, but there has been nothing to confirm this, and the recent co-operation between Petlura and the Bolsheviks go to disprove this.  &apos;Grigorieff s programme is based on the restitution of property to the former peasant -proprietors, who form the great majority of the population, and the overthrow of the(B19/316)  70  7/19 h&amp;s 7306wo
present system whereby the land is held by a minority of so-called workmen. All his troops come from the south, which is hostile to the Moscow executive for economic reasons, i.e., because the grain and food products of the south have been systematically requisitioned and exported to the centre and north of Russia. Further, the communism of the Moscow executive does not appeal to the Red Guards of the south, who say they are Bolsheviks and not communists, i.e., individualists as far as the workmen and peasants are concerned.Grigorieff issued a declaration of his aims which were set forth under the following headings : (1.) Down with the Communist Usurpers.(2.) Down with the Extraordinary Usurpers.(3.) Down with the Soviet Commissaries and officials.(4.) Support the real Soviet power of all Socialist parties and the real working &quot; Intelligentsia.&quot;To sum up, it will be seen from the above that GrigoriefFs movement is one of considerable dimensions and is causing considerable anxiety to the Soviet authorities. Indeed, it is probable that although the failure to carry into effect their threatened crossing of the Dniester was partly due to the flooded condition of the river and to the necessity of despatching troops to the Eastern front, the main reason was the anxiety caused at Moscow as well as at Kieff by GrigoriefFs activities.There is no information connecting any of the Allies with GrigoriefFs revolt which is a purely spontaneous outburst and cannot even be described as strictly anti-Bolshevik. The movement is of a similar nature to Petlura&apos;s and there is no confirmation of the Press report mentioned above which ascribes to Grigorieff a desire to work in conjunction with the main anti-Bolshevik movement. It is more likely that he is merely an adventurer seeking to establish his own authority in the Ukraine by taking advantage of the weakness of the local Soviet regime and of the discontent felt by the Ukrainian peasantry at the wholesale pillaging and confiscation carried out by the Soviet troops and the Moscow Executive. Nevertheless, the movement has been proving itself to be a t-horn in the flesh to the Bolsheviks, and, in conjunction with the present military situation on the Southern front, may prove an important factor in the inevitable break up of the Bolshevik regime.

</content>
</cab>
