<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/83/0 images: 307-307</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the Property ofHis Britannic ft&quot; -   - v. Government, ACCOMIuODATIOH FOR GOVSR&amp;VMT DEPART LiENTS 233IK LONDON.ADMIRALTY MEMORANDUM FOR THE WAR CABINET OK SIR ALFRED MrJDfS PAPER OF THE 1st July 1919. (G.T.7598.)The Admiralty accommodation in &quot;Whitehall was terribly congested before the war, and provision was made in an Office of vvorks Building Act of 1914 for the erection of a new wing in Whitehall on the site of part of the north-east wing of the present old Admiralty building and a number of old houses at present occupied by the Admiralty staff.Owing to the war, this building w$s not proceeded with, and the Treasury are now being urged by the Office of Works to sanction the letting of the contract at an early dateoThis building would take some two years to erect, and until it is occupied the Admiralty accommodation will be even more restricted than at present, as the old building which it will replace will have been demolished, and the staff accornma-dated in them will have to find room elsewhere.Tho great development of the Naval Staff of the Admiralty has alone made it quite impossible for the post-war Admiralty staff to be housed in the main block in Whitehall with-out considerable further extensions *    Far tho most convenient method of effecting these would be to add one,, or if possible two, stories to tho present main Admiralty buildings *    The Office of Works are being requested to report as to the feasibility of this project.As soon as the demobilisation and reconstruction work now beins; carried out at the Admiralty is finished, say in twelve months   time, it will be possible to bring back a portion of the Controller&apos;s Department to the main Admiralty buildings * It is no desire of the Admiralty that tho Controllers Depart-merit should be quartered away from the main block; indeed, the geographical separation of tho Controllers staff, even by the distance of tho few hundred yards across St.Jameses Park, causes the greatest inconvenience and delay to the despatch of public business.    Until, however? a considerable portion of the Controller^, staff can bo re-accommodated in the main building, it would be far better to leave them where they are rather than transfer them to another outside building in order to make way for the Board of trade     I suggest that the con-centration of that Department in the new Public Offices might reasonably wait for the comparatively short interval until we can bring back the Controller1s staff to the Admiralty.(Signed).      Wo Ho LONG.8th July, 1919.r

</content>
</cab>
