<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/47/21 images: 192-203</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
- /THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNMENT /.-----   6rPrinted for the War Cabinet.   February 1944.SECRET.W.P. (44) 121.18th February, 1944.WAR CABINET,DISCUSSIONS UNDER ARTICLE VII OF THE MUTUAL aid agreement.Report from the Committee on External Economic Policy.1. At their meeting on the 11th February the War Cabinet agreed that aCommittee comprising-The Chancellor of the Exchequer (Chairman),Minister of Production,Lord Privy Seal,President of the Board of Trade,Minister of State,Paymaster-General,should be set up, &apos;&apos; to determine, in the light of the discussion in the War cabinet as summarised by the Prime Minister,* the attitude to be taken by UnitedKingdom officials in the forthcoming discussions with official representatives ofthe Dominions and India over the whole field of the Washington Conversationsunder Article VII.&quot;We have held six meetings during the course of the week, and have examined the main issues likely to arise during the forthcoming discussions.The following paragraphs represent the views of the Committee, other thanthe Lord Privy Seal, who has submitted a minority report: The General Position.2. The talks which have taken place, both in Washington with the UnitedStates representatives, and in London with the representatives of the Dominionsand India, over the whole field covered by what are described as the &quot; Article VIIDiscussions &quot; have so far all been carried out at the official level. It has beenmade quite clear that Ministers are in no way committed to the schemes whichhave been the subject of these talks.This position must still be maintained. If, in our view, there were no likelihood-hood of ultimate acceptance of the schemes, we ought, of course, to say so at once.On the other hand, we are not called upon to pronounce in favour of them at thisstage.3. Our general recommendation is that discussion should proceed with dominion representatives on the basis that, while no commitment will be enteredinto, our expectation is that at the appropriate time we shall find it to our advantage to participate in these schemes, with or without modification.4-. During the opening meetings of the discussions (which are due to starton Monday, the 21st February) the general attitude to be adopted by UnitedKingdom officials should, we think, be mainly explanatory. They should o-iVe afull exposition of the schemes which have emerged from the Washington discus-sions, explain the attitude of United States officials on the more important points* The Prime Minister&apos;s summing up was to the effect that the general view of the WarCabinet was in favour of proceeding with a policy generally on the lines discussed at Washington,although no doubt there would be a number of specific points which would require further examination (W.M. (44) 18th Conclusions, Minute 4). -[26955] copy No.
2and indicate any issues which, from the United Kingdom point of view, may require further elucidation or in regard to which further safeguards may berequired to protect our interests. Above all, their object should be to elicit theviews of the Dominion representatives.5. This phase of exposition and preliminary exchange of views may welloccupy no more than the first days of the discussions with the Dominion repre-sentatives. During that time certain specific issues of policy will almost certainlyarise in which unless the general guidance which we have set out in the annex to this report proves adequate it will be necessary for the United Kingdomofficials to seek further guidance from Ministers. We propose that it shouldbe an instruction to the United Kingdom officials in the discussions to report assoon as these issues emerge, in order that they may be given the necessaryguidance. These questions should, we suggest, be considered in the first instance by this Committee, a report being made to the Cabinet as necessary.6. So much for the general position. We add observations on the moreimportant issues dealt with in our discussions.International Monetary Fund.7. The first is the International Monetary Fund. The Bank of England,whose views are important, as they would be intimately concerned with the Fund&apos;smanagement, have misgivings on several features of the scheme.8. In the first place doubts have arisen concerning what is termed thepassivity of the Fund. The member countries are all to contribute to the Fundvery substantial amounts of their own currencies, and this &quot;mixed bag&quot; ofcurrencies will constitute the main asset of the Fund. The intention of the plan is that, in all circumstances, this Fund shall be passive, in the sense that the currency of a country will be transferred to another country only on the initiative of the country first named. The doubt is whether, notwithstanding the words inthe plan which lay this down, the management, in the course of time, .would begin to use the currencies in their possession to help to keep exchange ratesreasonably stable by buying and selling. It may be the case that, if no furthertechnical safeguard is practicable to secure the original object, at any rateclearer and more direct instructions to the management should be introduced,9. Secondly, it is common ground that it should be our constant aim to preserve indefinitely the main features of the sterling area in full force in theform in which it has been known. Doubts have been expressed whether the plan is compatible with this object. In particular doubts have been cast upon theeffect of paragraph 6 (i) of the Statement of Principles,* which relates to thepower of the Fund in certain circumstances, when a member country is usingits facilities, to require that country to exercise controls to prevent use of theresources of the Fund to meet a large or sustained outlay of capital. This mayappropriately be the subject of further discussion, and elucidation with theDominions.10. Thirdly, and above all, there is the whole question of the arrangements to govern the transitional period. This question was left rather on one side atWashington. It is clear that we cannot expect to get through that period withoutmore material financial assistance to^ake the place of the system of Lend-Lease.Any plan, however, is still to be worked out. We are of opinion that beforecommitting ourselves to accept the monetary scheme we ought, in any event, tohave sufficient assurances to satisfy us that we can see our way through thefinancial difficulties of the transaction. Further, while the scheme contemplatesthat a member country joining at the outset may contract out of convertibilityfor a period, the present drafting of paragraph 11 of the Statement of Principlessuggests that this applies only during the early post-war transitional period.We doubt whether we can safely commit ourselves to enter the scheme unless thelatitude in this regard runs until such time as we can be really satisfied that wecan maintain convertibility indefinitely. For, once the obligation has been accepted,it cannot be abrogated except by withdrawal from the scheme.Imperial Preference.11. The next question concerns Imperial Preference. On this we suggest the following instructions should be given to United Kingdom officials :  They*   The Statement of Principles is printed on pages 18 to 20 of W.P. (44)81.
should not open up any prospect of the substantial elimination of imperial preference, but should guide discussion on the following lines : The main objective is the reduction of tariff barriers, and the abolitionof import restrictions over the widest possible area with a view to themaximum increase in the export trade of the United Kingdom and of theDominions. Our principal aim should be to achieve a more severe reductionin high tariffs than in moderate tariffs. It follows that the question ofImperial Preference would arise in the discussion with Dominion officials in the form of considering what reductions of preferences&apos; it will be worthwhile for us and the Dominions to contribute to a comprehensive schemeproviding for the expansion of our trade.Our representatives should also refer the matter to Ministers for instructionsif any substantial body of opinion should appear to be developing among theDominion representatives in favour of a substantial elimination of Imperial&quot; Preference.[The Lord Privy Seal&apos;s dissent from our conclusion on this whole matter is setout in the Minority Report.]Subsidies for Home Production.12. We deal next with the provisions of the proposed commercial union inregard to subsidies and their effect on our agricultural policy. On this point weare satisfied that we cannot accept in an international convention any limitationof our right to buy our home agricultural products at fixed prices, to buy food from abroad in bulk and to pay subsidies for home production. We believe thatall these points are, in fact, secured in the version of the scheme prepared by our officials; and we must make sure that they are retained in the scheme as it finallyemerges.13. Provided these points are secured, we see nothing in the proposed scheme which is inconsistent with the Government&apos;s declared policy of main-taining after the war a healthy and well-balanced agriculture. It is to be noted,however, that the commercial union scheme, in its present form, imposes a limitation oil the price, in relation to world prices, at which our products can beplaced upon the home market. The contingent Exchequer liability might be amatter for grave concern.14. The Lord Privy Seal&apos;s dissent from our views-on this matter is set outin his Minority Report.15. The detailed instructions to the delegates on particular issues as recom-mended by the Committee are set&quot; out in the Annex to this report.(On behalf of the Committee) :J. A.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,l&amp;th February, 1944.[26955]
ANNEX.Instructions to United Kingdom Officials on Particular Issues,I -International Monetary Fund.(i) Attention should be directed at an early stage of the discussions to theimportance, which attaches, in the United Kingdom&apos;s view, to ensuring adequatearrangements during the transitional period. United Kingdom officials should,indicate that a clear distinction should be drawn between the arrangementsappropriate during the transitional period and the long-term arrangements whennormality had been reached.(ii) It should also be made clear that the United Kingdom officials attach great importance to the maintenance of the sterling area in something like itspresent form during the transitional period. It should, however, be an instruc-tion to United Kingdom officials to avoid opening up discussion at this stageon the question of Dominion (and Indian) sterling balances.   [See, however, (v)- below.](iii) Turning to the long-term scheme, it would be appropriate that theUnited Kingdom officials should elicit the opinion of the Dominion representa-tives on the reactions of the International Monetary Fund on the continuanceof the essential features of the peace-time sterling area when normality had beenreached. In particular, reference should be made to the provision in para-graph 6 of the Statement of Principles which enables the Fund to require amember country to exercise controls to prevent the use of the resources of theFund to, meet large and sustained outflow of capital. It would be relevant toconsider whether this provision might, in certain circumstances, necessitate theestablishment of an exchange control between separate units of the sterling area.&apos; (iv) Again, reference might be made to the questions which had been raised as to the passivity of the Fund. The doubts on this matter should be explained,together with the grounds for holding that the matter is sufficiently safeguarded;and the views of the Dominion representatives elicited.Instructions on the Use of Sterling Balances in&apos;the Transitional Period. &apos;: (y) notwithstanding (ii) above, the United Kingdom officials, if seriouslypressed to make a statement on the use of sterling balances during the transitional period, should begin by saying that the nearer we are to the war period, the morenearly should we hope the sterling area arrangements to remain on the war basis.As time goes on, existing restrictions would no doubt be relaxed to the extent that resources permit. We should hope, however, that throughout the transitional period the sterling area arrangements, as they now exist, will broadly be continued,particularly as regards the maintenance of exchange controls, which would prevent movements of capital outward from the area. As regards, the use ofexchange controls in respect of current, as distinct from capital transactions,we ourselves will have to exercise great restraint in importation, especially from outside the sterling area, and we hope that the other members will be preparedto exercise similar restraint.If necessary, the officials are authorised to add a statement as follows : 1What can appropriately be allowed is a matter for later arrangement with each sterling area country according to the circumstances and anygeneralisation must for the time being be subject to great reserve.. Subjectto that we do not expect to be in a position to enable any part of the sterling area to import on a scale which is not closely related to its current earningpower. We should not, of course, expect members of the sterling area tocontinue in effect to make large loans to the United Kingdom as they havebeen prepared to do for war purposes. The least&apos;that we should expect to do would be to enable them to import from outside the sterling, area to the full extent of their earnings outside the area, and to import from within the sterling area to the full extent of their earnings within the sterling area.We should do our utmost to facilitate a freer policy than this on the partof the exchange controls of other members.
II. Commercial Policy.(vi) Tariffs and Preferences.-The prospect of the substantial elimination of Imperial Preference should not be opened up by the United Kingdom officials,who should guide discussion on the following lines : The main objective is the reduction of tariff barriers, and the abolitionof import restrictions over the widest possible area with a view to themaximum increase in the export trade of the United Kingdom and of theDominions. Our principal aim should be to achieve a more severe reductionin high tariffs than in moderate tariffs. It follows that the question ofImperial Preference would arise in the discussion with Dominion officials inthe form of considering what reductions of preferences it will be worth while for us and the Dominions to contribute to a comprehensive scheme for providing for the expansion of our trade.If any substantial body of opinion should appear to be developing amongw the Dominion representatives in favour of a substantial elimination ofImperial  Preference,  the matter should be referred  to Ministers  for instructions.United Kingdom officials should be careful to bear in mind the positionof the Colonies in connection with any discussion of Preferences which maythus arise.(vii) Subsidies for Home Production. United Kingdom officials shouldcontinue to maintain, as at Washington, that we cannot accept any limitationin an international convention on our right to subsidise home production. Thus,the United Kingdom Government would be free to pay whatever price they chosefor home-grown agricultural produce for home consumption. But it should benoted that, under the proposed arrangements for limiting the height of protectivetariffs, when the price paid to the home grower exceeds the price paid for importsof the same commodity plus the margin of protection agreed upon internationally,the excess would have to be found by the Treasury and not by the consumer.(viii) Export Subsidies. The practicability of the proposal for stopping thesale of goods in foreign markets at prices lower than those in the home market should be further explored.(ix) Quantitative Restriction. It should be made clear that, so long as our balance of payments (including unavoidable capital exports) remainsunfavourable, as judged by the appropriate objective criteria, we must retainfreedom to impose restrictions on imports without reference to the amountsimported in previous years.III.&apos; Commodity Plan.(x) Discussions should continue on the scheme for an International CommodityOrganisation on the basis of the proposals outlined in Annex &quot;C&quot; of theMinister of State&apos;s memorandum (W.P. (44) 81). The general line of approach should be that the general objective set out in the scheme is acceptable. It is fordiscussion, however, whether the scheme as now set out constitutes a soundmechanism in respect, particularly, of the linkage of the Buffer Stocks aspectsof the scheme with the provisions for restriction of production in certaincircumstances.TV -Cartels; Employment Policy; International Investment.(xi) On all these three matters, the impressions formed by the UnitedKingdom officials of the attitude of the American representatives at theWashington Conversations should be reported to the Dominion representatives,whose comments should be invited.Minority Report by the Lord Privy Seal.I dissent from the &quot; general recommendations &quot; contained in the Report ofthe Committee on External Economic Policy (paragraph 3).I recommend that discussions should go on at once in Ministerial circles inorder to produce an alternative to the Washington schemes. The Ministers to be consulted should, in my view, include the Secretary of State for Scotland, theSecretary of State fqr Dominions and the Minister of Agriculture, along withrepresentatives of the Bank of England.
The new plan should embrace the Sterling Area and the Economic Empire,with adequate protection for agriculture at home.I deplore the instruction given to United Kingdom officials in paragraph (vi)of the Annex to the Report. This involves a consideration of what reductions in Imperial Preference will be &quot; worth while.&quot; It is my belief that we should approach this problem from the point of view of what reduction may be necessary.The instruction will inevitably encourage a canvassing of opinions among theDominions for the purpose of enlisting support for reduced preferences. ButImperial Preference is the policy of Britain laid down at Ottawa in agreementwith the Dominions. It is not for Britain, therefore, to take even the shorteststep either towards promoting an attack upon Imperial Preference or towards a weakening of the Dominions&apos; adherence to that principle of Empire.In dissenting from the majority report of the Committee, I wish to record the following opinions on the general character of the scheme which emerged fromthe Washington Conversations on Article VII : (1) The Financial Plan restores the Gold Standard in the form of a &quot; GoldFund.&quot; To this project the Bank of England is opposed. The whole suggestion of the fund, in the view of the Deputy-Governor, is that gold-convertible curren-cies are better than other currencies.If we accept the &quot; Gold Fund &quot; we lav ourselves down to die. (See note fromthe Bank of England, attached.)(2) The Commercial Plan in its present form is intended to destroy imperial preference and re-ruin the agricultural industry of Britain. It is impossible todefend agriculture by subsidy unless quota is also introduced.(3) The Commodity Plan has been launched on many occasions in the past.It always ends either in financial disaster or restriction of production; the second is as bad for us as the first.*The Canadian Government pool in wheat is an example. After eight years,in 1939, 1,000 million bushels of wheat were in storage. The money value was more than the total assets of the Bank of Montreal. Storage was a major problem.Bankruptcy was in sight.  Then came the war, saving Canada from financial ruin.B.18th February, 1944.Note handed in by Representatives of the Bank of England, at a Meeting of theCommittee held on loth February, 1944.[See Minority Report by Lord Privy Seal.]The Bank&apos;s first objective must be to maintain and develop the acceptabilityand purchasing power of sterling. This policy is entirely consistent with thegeneral objectives of the Fund : stability, avoidance of unruly capital movements and of speculation in currencies or competitive manipulation of exchange rates,and easy settlement of current account transactions.But quite apart from the questions whether or when we shall be able to afford to accept the obligations of convertibility and fixed parities, the mechanism pro-posed by the scheme is inconsistent with our first objective in two respects : 1. The Fund as drafted is basically a gold fund the whole suggestion isthat gold-convertible currencies are better than other currencies. this in terms of international currencies means that the Fund will likedollars and encourage their use, but will look askance at sterling.2. The Fund as drafted contemplates settlement of international trade pay-ments in the currency of each country and not in internationalcurrencies.Therefore, if we accept the mechanism in principle, even if we defer its opera-tion, we say publicly that we are working towards a system where sterling will beless useful. This can only make our transitional arrangements, where we are largely dependent on the credit of sterling, more difficult.* The Minister of Production associates himself with the views expressed in these twosentences.







</content>
</cab>
