<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/8/91 images: 530-535</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Empire Air Mail Services.    Air mail correspondence forthe countries formerly served by the direct Empire Air Mailservice is at present forwarded by sea to South Africa and thence by the twice weekly air service on the routeSouth Africa - Egypt - Palestine - Ira-q. - India - Malaya -Australia.      The air postage rate is l/3d, per half ounce.This service is very bad as will be seen from the followingtable which shows comparative times of transmission.TimesofTransmissionc(a)By direct air mailservices whichwere in operation from the outbreakof war until thedeclaration of warby Italy.Days.Kenya, Uganda and tanganyka 5-6Sudan 4Egypt 3-4Palestine 4Iraq 4India 5-6Malaya 8Australia 12By pre-warsurfacemailservice.Days-1895561421262512677162233/        (o)By existingair mailservice viaDurban.Days.22232425252629333435363737394145Twenty-one to thirty-three days elapse between the timeof despatch of the mail from London and its departure byaeroplane from Durban, and I fully accept the view of theSecretary of State for Air that a satisfactory service couldbe given only by an Air Mail Service on the route UnitedKingdom to West Africa, operating in conjunction with aWest Africa to Egypt service and the &quot;Horseshore&quot; servicevia Egypt between Durban and Australia.      Such a service by air throughout would give times of transmission to the EmpireonlyWAR    CABINETSECRETmlp. (Q) (40)891 COPY NO.fith November, 1940.OVERSEAS AIR COMMUNICATIONSMemorandum by the Postmaster General.Since the outbreak of War Postal Services throughout tworld have steadily deteriorated and the only hope of affording substantially better facilities lies in theimprovement of existing and the introduction of new Air MailServices,     The proposals outlined in the memorandum by theSecretary of State for Air are therefore strongly supportedalthough it is clear that they will not provide, either atthe outset or at an early date, all the aircraft capacity which could be employed to advantage by the Post Office.

only a few days longer than those given by the former directair services via the Mediterranean and, in these circumstances it is not unreasonable to assume that after a short timethe weight of correspondence would not be less than the weight sent by the direct Empire services before Italyentered the War, namely, 3,000 to 3,500 kilograms a week.Indeed, because of the deterioration in the speed of theordinary surface mails and the increase in the number oftroops stationed in the Middle East, there would be atendency for the weight to Increase beyond this limit, andto provide a reliable Empire Air Mail Service the Post.office would require accommodation at the outset for not less than3,000 kilograms a week, rising rapidly to as much as 4,000or even 5,000 kilograms.     The service could not be confined to letters for members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces over the whole,or any part, of the route and prevision would have to be madefor the carriage of civil mails.     The foregoing figures havebeen calculated on this understanding.It seems probable that there would not be available atthe outset sufficient aircraft capacity for a full Empire AirMail service, and if this proved to be the case consideration would have to be given to the possibility of confining theservice at first to the Middle East and extending to otherEmpire destinations later as more aircraft capacity became available.     For a limited service to the Middle East it isestimated that space for 6Q0 kilograms of mail would berequired at the outset, and that this figure would riserapidly to 1,000 kilograms.United Kingdom - Lisbon Air Service.     This serviceaffords the only regular outlet by air to the continent ofEurope and is used together with air and surface servicesbeyond Lisbon to provide air mail services to a number ofEuropean countries.     The greatest value of the service,however, from the point of view of the Post Office is that it provides the only effective connection with the Pan-American(Clipper) service between Lisbon and New York which, in itsturn, and in the absence of British North and South Atlanticservices, provides the only means by which air mail services from the United Kingdom to North America, South America andother trans-Atlantic destinations can be provided.The total weight of mails for the service to Lisbon isabout 1,100 kilograms per week of which 300 kilograms is for european destinations.     The aircraft capacity available onthe Lisbon link has hitherto been adequate to carry thisweight of mails and it is imperative that this should not be materially reduced.This service would fit in with the proposed Empire AirMail Services, and if these would absorb the whole of theaircraft capacity available it is urged that the fullresources should be concentrated on them.North Atlantic Air Services.    Although the provisionof British air services to America is clearly desirable, theimprovement of the air mail service to the Empire, and inparticular to the Middle East, is from the point of view ofthe Post Office a far more urgent need.     About 600 kilogramsof mail are sent by the &quot;Clipper&quot; service each week and alarge part of this could be sent by a direct British service.South America.

South America.     Air mail for South American countries is at present forwarded by means of the Clipper service to new York and thence by onward Pan-American air services;these services compare unfavourably with those by the directFrench air service which ceased on the capitulation of france .      The establishment of a direct British air service would therefore result in a very desirable improvement ofair mail services and should be of the greatest value toBritish trade in South America.     The weight of the airmail for South America would be about 100-150 kilograms aweek.     The existence of an Italian service which evadesthe British blockade makes the need for a British servicegreater.      Indeed there has been some suggestion that theGermans might contrive to operate a service from West Africa.Finally, it must be emphasised that satisfactory air services cannot be assured unless the necessary space on aircraft is regularly available for the carriage of mails.W.S.M.General Post Office.6th November, 1940.


</content>
</cab>
