<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/216/0 images: 6-9</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
  THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE PROPERTY Off HIS BRIMNIO MAJS3TYT S GQVERNMaM?.                               CABINET.                               . Secret.                                                     Oopy Ho. ijv, 7351(30).                 Effect of Prolonged Unemployment on Title to              Health Insurance and Widows and Old Age pensions.                      Memorandum by Minister of Health.                It  is necessary for me to draw the attention of my     colleagues to a problem with which I am confronted in relation to     the Health Insurances Contributory pensions Scheme.                It  is in some respects analogous to the problem of     transitional  benefit under the Unemployment Insurance scheme, and I     have deferred raising it pending a solution of that problem.   But     considerations of time render it impossible to defer a decision any     longer.               By reason of continuous and prolonged unemploymentt a       s     certain number of persons will fall out of insurance under the Health     Insurance &amp; Contributory Pensions Scheme on the 31st of December next.               The number of such persons is estimated to be between     50,000 and 100,000*   Many of them have done no work (and no     contributions have been paid in respeot of them) sinoe some date in     the first half of 1927.   All of them will have been wholly unemployed     for at least 2^ years.   The statutory power to keep them in insurance     by special regulations is now exhausted and In the abses.de of new     legislation their insuranoes cannot be further prolonged.*               Another group of persons who have been unemployed sinoe     some date in the  first half of 1928 will fall into the  same     position on 30th June, 1931.   Shis olass should also be brought     within the  scope of any relief that may be  provided.               The present position of these persons is that  they are     entitled to one-half the normal sickness and disablement benefits     *To this there is  a small exception.    Certain persons who were     over 60  when they beoame unemployed are protected  so  far as     pensions are concerned but are not entitled to siokness  or     disablement benefit.
 and are insured lor the full &quot;benefits payable to wi&amp;owa and orphans.           It ia submitted that steps must be taken to prevent the total lapse of these insurances.   The necessity for some special measures &quot;being taken arises most acutely as regards the title to Widows&apos; and Orphans1  pensions as it is a condition for the award of suoh pensions that.the deceased husband should have been in insurance up to the date of his death.           Two alternative courses appear to be possible:-      (1) to give an extension of insurance to 31st December, 1931, on the same terms as those of the present transitional regulations (i.e. insuranoe for all health insuranoe benefits and pensions, subject to half rates of siokneas and disablement benefit);      (2) to continue insurance until 31st December, 1931, for pensions purposes only with no title to any health insurance- benefits.           As regards (1) the Sooieties have kept and are keeping all such persona in full insuranoe for nearly two years after contributions have ceased and for another year they keep them insured for half benefita.   Means have been found to ameliorate - the position by the distribution among the societies of certain monies derived from the sale of stamps on unclaimed cards, but the income derived from this source ia by no nsjans equal to the charge which falls upon the societies in maintaining the benefits of their unemployed members.   In these circumstances it is evident that the Approved Societies cannot be asked, with any hope of success, to undertake any further burden in respect of the prolongation of the insuranoe of members in respect of whom no contributions have been paid for a long period.   The adoption of this plan would&apos;, therefore, involve the provision of Ww money by the Exchequer.   The amount of money required would be 40 contribution- tions at 9d. i.e. 30/- for each person oonoerned.    Under course (2-2-
ow the other hand, while new money would have to be found itsamount would be insignificant, and it need involve no charge onthe &amp;xcheq,uer;  probably a payment of 5s. per head from the pension Fund to the approved Societies for the admini strati on workwhich would fall upon the societies in connection with the issue and collection of cards and the keeping of returns would suffice.          It is submitted that the decision should be in favour ofcourse (3) comprising the extension of pensions rights only.          It may be put forward as an objection to this proposal that it would mean that insured persons v?hen sick would have to fall &quot;back upon both cash assistance and medical attendanoe fromthe Public Assistance authorities.   In reply to this it must be pointed out that the persons concerned have already under thepresent position, in the great majority of cases, to seek publicassistance to supplement the benefits to whioh they are entitled under the Health Insurance scheme as the half rate of sickness benefit, via. 7s.Sd. a week, and still more, the half rate of disablement benefit, 3s.9d. a. week are obviously insufficientin themselves to cover the minimum cost of subsistence.          Ehe adoption of course (2) would be defended on thefollowing grounds:-     (a)  although there has been a lar^e and widespread demand that the pension rights of the people concerned shall be protected, there has been no substantial demand for extensionof title to health insurance benefit.     (b)  The provision of further money by the Exchequer for theNational Health Insurance scheme would involve a grant of a new type, the reperoussions of which might be jjeculiarly dangerous.Hitherto the Health Insurance scheme has been aaaintained on a sound actuarial and financial &quot;basis under which the benefits havebeen kept to such as could be provided out of the contributions
of the employers and workers, subjeot only to a definedproportionate part of the cost of the benefits being an exchequer charge.   If the Exchequer Is to pay the contributions(even though to an extent sufficient only to provide minimumbenefits) of a-section of the insured a precedent will be created to which great numbers - especially of the under-employed - can appeal and the foundations of the contributorysystem will be seriously.sly threatened,     (c)  While either of the two alternative courses wouldrequire amending legislation, that legislation would have tobe carried through before the end of the present year to enablecourse (1) to be adopted, while it oould be deferred until afterthe new year under course (2), provided that the legislation,when passed, were given retrospective effect as from thebeginning of 1931.                                (Initialled).   A.Q.24th October, 1930.Ministry of Health.

</content>
</cab>
