<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/216/0 images: 10-13</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
his DOCUMENT  IS THE  PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT.     SECRET.                                                  33     CP.552  (50).                                 Copy No.                                 CAB  I N E  T .                          QUOTA FOR  DOMINION &quot;WHEAT.I                Note by  the  President of tho  Board  of Trade,               I circulate  to ray  colleagues  a  paper  which was used          as  the basis  of our discussion in  the  Committee on          Economic Co-operation.               I have also  included  a  report by  a statistical          sub-coiranittee on  the amount  of our wheat and flour imports          from the overseas parts of the Empires                                          W.G,Board of Trade,     24th October, 1930.
TfTT3 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MkJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.    SECRET.    E.B.(Q)(30) 5,                                      Copy Mo._                            IMPERIAL CONFERENCE. 1930.                        Committee on Economic Co-operation.               OOTLJOE; OF PLAN FOR THE INTRODUCTION OF A GUARANTEED            QUOTA FOR DOMINION WHEAT OH MILLING IN THE UNITED KINGDOM.            1, The term &quot;Dominion Wheat&apos;  shall apply to wheat grown in,         and sent from, any part of the British Commonwealth outside the         United Kingdom and the term &quot;Dominion wheat flour&apos; to flour         milled entirely from dominion wheat1 and sent from any part of         the British  Commonwealth outside the United Kingdom.            2. In connection with every parcel of Dominion wheat imported         into the United Kingdom, a Dominion wheat certificate  (or         certificates, if it is desired to sub-divide the parcel) shall         be issued by the Customs when they are satisfied, by the usual         evidence tendered, that the wheat concerned Is of Dominion         origin.   Similarly, in connection with every parcel of Dominion         wheat flour  imported, a Dominion wheat flour certificate would         be issued by the customs to the importer.            5* Quota  as applied to Millers.   The quota would be         reckoned as  a percentage of the total amount of wheat  used in         mills, and the responsible Minister would require millers to         produce  evidence of purchase  (Including the surrender  of         Dominion wheat  certificates issued by the Customs) of  the         prescribed minimum quota.   (Millers would be under a  similar         -obligation in regard to a United Kingdom quota).            4*. Quota  as applied to Flour Importer^.               (1)  Imports of  &quot;Dominion Wheat Flour&apos; qualified to receive         the  Customs  certificate will  be subject only to the requirement         as to surrender of United Kingdom wheat quota certificates.
     (ii) Other imported flourc  An importer of any other wheat flour will be required, before clearing such flour from Customscontrol, to mix each parcel with a quantity of Dominion wheat flour equivalent to the Dominion wheat quota reckoned in termsof flour as prescribed by the Minister or to produce and surrender to the Customs Dominion wheat or wheat flourcertificates as issued by the Customs for an amount equivalentto the Dominion wheat quota,,     This flour, i.ae non-Dominion wheat-flour will also besubject to the same requirement as Dominion wheat-flour inrespect of the surrender to the Customs of United Kingdom wheat quota certificatesa     The responsible Minister would prescribe the equivalent of imported flour in terms .of Dominion wheat certificates.   50 Flour Imports.   It is to be understood that the Dominionwheat quota will be increased or reduced should imports ofDominion wheat-flour fall below or increase beyond a basicfigure, the change in the quota being equivalent in terms ofwheat to the change in the imports of flour, in accordancewith the prescription of the responsible Minister.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.     17th October, 1950.-2-
                STATISTICAL COMMITTEE ON WHEAT AND FLOUR         IMPORTS INTO THE UNITED KINGDOM FROM THE EMPIRE  OVERSEAS.        The undersigned representatives of the Delegations  of United   Kingdom, Canada and Australia, have conferred  with regard to  the   figure that might be adopted as the basic  Dominion quota of wheat   imported into the United Kingdom in connection with the  proposed   quota scheme to be applied to United Kingdom mills.        The trade returns of the United Kingdom show  tnat on the   average of the six years ended 1929 the imports of wheat grain   consigned from British countries amounted  to 48 per cent, of  the   total imports.        We have considered the special conditions affecting the  trade   in wheat exported from Canada to the United Kingdom and  have  taken   into account all available statistical material.  While  this   material does not enable us to determine precisely what  quantity   of wheat shown as consigned to the United  Kingdom  from the United   States was actually grown, in Canada, we are of opinion that the   average figure of the imports from British Countries during the   six years may not have been in excess of 53 per cent,  of the wheat   grain imported into the United Kingdom; the use of 55  per cent.   as the basic figure for a Dominion wheat quota will, we  think,   adequately cover the element of uncertainty that attaches to  the   calculations.  In order to arrive at an accurate figure  further   information is necessary beyond that at present available.        In regard to flour, we find from the  trade returns  of the   United Kingdom for the same period of six  years that the quantity   of Dominion wheat flour imported yearly into the United  Kingdom   averaged 312,CuO tons (2,24u lbs. )j an examination of  the available   data indicates, however, that this figure  should be increased to   approximately 335,Cuu tons, as the basic quantity  for  the purpose   of the proposed quota scheme.       L. R. MCGREGOR  (Australia)     H.D.  VIGOR  (United Kingdom)       R.H. COATS       (Canada)  &apos;      A.W.  FLUX      &quot;       &quot;                                            (Chairman)24th October, 1924.

</content>
</cab>
