<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/216/0 images: 28-30</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT.Printed for the  Cabinet.  October 1930.SECRET.CP.  356 (30).                                 CABINET.THE USE  OF BRITISH HONDURAS  AS A BASE FOR THE ILLICIT                             LIQUOR  TRADE.       MEMORANDUM  BY THE  SECRETARY OF  STATE  FOR THE COLONIES.    LEGISLATION recently enacted by the Canadian Parliament prohibiting the clearance of liquor direct to United States ports has brought back into prominence a problem which has from time to time been engaging my attention since my assump-tion of Office, viz.,  the  large  and increasing  volume of liquor  trade in british honduras.   A  very large percentage (estimated  at 90  per  cent.)  of the  liquorexported from the Colony is sold on the high seas, presumably for conveyance to theUnited States of America, and it is felt that the United States Government may not for long continue to regard the present state of affairs with tolerance.    I  accordingly propose,  with the consent of my colleagues, to address  to theGovernor of British Honduras a Secret despatch of which a  draft  is annexed, inwhich  I invite the Governor, in consultation with the Legislative Council, to takecertain steps to combat illicit traffic by-     (1) the withdrawal of the facilities now existing for the re-export of liquor;    (2) the abolition of drawback; and    (3) the increase of the fee for retaining liquor in bonded warehouses.    It  has  been  ascertained  unofficially  that  His  Majesty&apos;s  Ambassador  atWashington cordially endorses these proposals.    His Majesty&apos;s Government would be on stronger ground in taking the initiative in this way than if they were to delay action until some protest were received fromthe United States.  I have felt it necessary to insert in the despatch a warning that,if a protest of a serious character should be made by the United States Government,His Majesty&apos;s Government would feel it incumbent upon them to ask Parliament forsuch powers as they consider necessary to deal with the situation.                                                                          P.Colonial Office, downing  Stmet, S.W. 1,        October 22, 1930.Copy No.  37[21866]
ANNEX.Draft of proposed Secret Despatch, from the Secretary of State for  the Colonies to                       the Governor of British Honduras.Sir,                                                   Downing Street, 1930.     IN my Secret despatch of the 24th June, 1929, I addressed you on the subject ofthe increase in the quantity of whiskey imported into the Colony in  1928 comparedwith 1927.  I now observe from the British Honduras Government &quot; Gazette   ofthe  1st March  that 174,785 gallons  of  whiskey  were imported  in 1929.  this represents an increase of almost 240 per cent, over  1928. In paragraph 3 of yourSecret despatch of the 24th  July, 1929, it is stated that the Collector of  Customsestimates that 90 per cent, of the liquor  exported from the Colony is sold on  thehigh seas, presumably  for conveyance. by the  purchasers to the United States ofAmerica.  It may &apos;be inferred from the increase in the imports of whiskey into  theColony last year that the tra-ffic in liquor smuggling from the Colony  into the UnitedStates must also have greatly increased in that period.     2.  Legislation   has  recently  been  enacted  by  the  Canadian  Parliamentprohibiting the clearance of liquor direct  to United States ports.  This action maywell lead to growth in the export of Canadian liquor to permissible  destinations by persons engaged in the illicit traffic, and it is possible that British Honduras, owingto its geographical position,  may be utilised to a greater extent than at present inthe forwarding of Canadian  liquor to the  United States.     3.  Unless some action is taken to reduce the large and increasing volume of  theColony&apos;s trade in liquor, which, after making full allowance  for the requirements oflegitimate trade is already grossly out of proportion to the needs of the Colony itself,His  Majesty&apos;s Government are apprehensive that incidents may occur which wouldevoke protests from the Government of the United States, and might seriously affectthe harmonious relations at present existing between the two countries.     4.  His Majesty&apos;s Government have earnestly considered what steps might mostsuitably be taken to regulate  this traffic from British Honduras.   Legislation on  thelines of  the  Canadian enactment would be unsuitable, and would not  by  itselfafford a remedy.  It must be admitted that the facilities which now exist in  theColony for the import, storing and re-export of liquor are such as might reasonably be regarded as fostering, and even encouraging,  the action of those persons whopractise evasion of  the United States  law  embodied in the Volstead Act.  Afterconsiderable reflection,  His Majesty&apos;s  Government have arrived at the conclusionthat the facilities now existing for the re-export of liquor should be withdrawn, thatdrawback should be  abolished,  and that  the fee  for retaining  liquors in bondedwarehouses should be materially increased.     5.  While it is impossible to ignore the fact that a large amount  of the Colony&apos;income is derived from the traffic in liquor, it  is essential to bear in mind that  thepreservation  of  friendly relations between  the Empire  and the United States ofAmerica is a matter of vastly greater importance.  It may also be pointed out thatthe  existence  of  the illicit liquor  trade  is  undoubtedly weakening the  domestic policy of the Colony.  The revenue derived  from taxation on liquor provides for aconsiderable portion of the expenditure on  social services, and  to acquiesce in  thecontinuance of such  a state of affairs  will ultimately aggravate  financial  problems which must in any case prove sufficiently difficult.     6.  His Majesty&apos;s Government would be extremely reluctant to  take any actionwhich would tend to diminish the measure of autonomy Avhich the Colony at presentenjoys as regards its local affairs, but, if a protest of a serious character concerningthe local liquor traffic should be made by the Government of the United States ofAmerica,  His Majesty&apos;s Government  would  feel  it  incumbent on them to  ask parliament to give them such powers as they considered necessary to deal  with  thesituation.     7.  In view  of  the foregoing considerations,  I must request you to convene aSecret Session of the Legislative Council, at which this despatch should be read to
IV 0the members.   The Council should be apprised of tlhe attitude of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in this matter, and  the  unofficial members should be invited,  in  theinterests of the international relations of the Empire, loyally to accept the policy outlined in the fourth paragraph of this despatch as part of their duty as represeri-tatives of tihe people of the Colony.    8.  I shall be glad to be informed  at an early date of the result of such action as you may take in this matter.I have, &amp;c.

</content>
</cab>
