<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/216/0 images: 88-90</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Thia document is  the  property  of  His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.Printed for the Cabinet, October, 1930.SECRET.                                                                                   3 &apos;9COPT NO.CP.  362  (30).THE CABINET:PRODUCTION  OF  PETROL  FROM  GOAL.       MEMORANDUM  BY THE SECRETARY  OF  STATE FOR WAR.     I have had careful enquiries made regarding the  newspaper reports which suggested    ggthat the  War  Office staff  was investigating a new way of producing petrol which&apos; had  Generalbeen discovered &quot; as the result of an  accident.&quot;   These enquiries have been made for me   3149by my Parliamentary Private Secretary, Major Church, who is himself a scientist, arid theresults,  along with  the two  reports attached,  are  circulated  for  the information ofthe Cabinet.     The War Office is riot investigating  any accident through which petrol from coal was produced.  The reference to the War Office in newspaper reports of 9th October was due to Professor E: C: Bfowriihg of the Military College of Science having been present by invitation at a demdristratidri giveri by a. private individual,  Mr. R. E. Goldsbrough,who has a private Research Laboratory at The Grove, Slough.     Mr. Gbldabrbugh;  who  has  been expeririieriting with the  tar  by-product  of lowtemperature carbonization of coal, claims that by treating the tar with super-heated steatri,he can dbtain a ifibtoisspirit with  the properties of petrol and thai this  spirit can beprdduced at a cost of 2d. a gallon, -including raw materials arid conversion costs.     Mr. Gdldsbrbugh,  who is evidently seeking  publicity  for his process, invited anumber of scientists to&apos; be present,&apos;  and the Press.  The newspaper reporters, scenting, a story- asked Professor  Browriing  td express his opinion&apos;  on the process outlined  byMr; Gbldsbrough:   Professor Browning apparently said that, if Mr. Goldsbrough&apos;s claimscould be substantiated, the discover^ was of the greatest national importance&apos;.     The  drily reference  to&quot; accident  that I  can find  is  in the  statement made  by Mr.GbldsBrotigh that his discovery wa1^ accidental.     From the newspaper account of Mr. Goldsbrough&apos;s process, it appears to be very -similar  to  other  processes wHich have  already been investigated  by the Fuel ResearchBoard of the Departfrietit of Scientific arid Iridustrial Research.     Members or  the&apos; Cabinet  inay remember  that a  Mr. Turner has  invented a process which has been investigated  by the Fuel  Research Board and a report issued  on .it.Mr. Trifrier&apos;s process sterns to.&quot;be siiripler than that of, Mr. Goldsbrdugh&apos;s, for he obtainsoils (including fnbtor-:spirlt)  frdin cdal by putting  the coal  in  a bath  of super-heatedstearii in a retort;     A meeting, it-ik understood,- %as arranged about a year agd between Mr. Turner andMr: Hall, the  Financial  Secretary to the Admiralty, who is  Chairman of the Oils aridCoal Committee.                                                                          T. S.   THE  WAR -OFFICE,              27ih October, 1936&apos;.(B30/i7)  6o  io/amery  w.d.-p.  8276
REPORT BY  PROFESSOR  K. C. BROWNING,  OF THE  MILITARY COLLEGE OF  SCIENCE,  ON       THE  GOLDSBKOUGH PROCESS FOR  EXTRACTION  OF PETROL  AND  LUBRICATING OILS       FROM TAR.     Mr. R. E.  Goldsbrough first consulted me about  four years ago in connection with a process for  the burning of  residual oils with a smokeless hot flame.   Subsequently he asked my advice after he had experimented with the production of petrol and lubricating oils by what is  known aa &quot; cracking &quot; from                              (1) Venezuelan crude  oils.                             (2) High temperature  tar.                             (3) Low temperature tar.     I advised Mr. Goldsbrough  to concentrate on his experiments with low temperaturetar, for the following reasons :      (1) That if he were successful it would supply the country with fuel and oil in times            of emergency.     (2) It  would make low temperature carbonization pay.     Mr. Goldsbrough has taken out various patents with Mr. Hugh Tevis of  the AmericanTrust Company, San Francisco,  a United States citizen.   Two of these patents are filedwith the Patent Office, No. 20,366 A.D.  1928 and No. 24458 A.D. 1928.     The process  which has been patented is as follows :      Tars or residual oils are pre-heated  by passing through a metal coil  to  200o C.They are then passed into a chamber where they are mixed with  super-heated steam at  atemperature  of not less than 700o C. and a  pressure of  about four atmospheres, in  thepresence of  a  catalyst.   (The  catalyst  consists of  a paste made up of  silica, sodiumsilicilate,  alumina, zinc oxide  and  other ingredients.   N.B. A  catalyst  acceleratesreaction and is  usually not markedly affected  itself by the chemical or physical reactionsso produced.)     After being  maintained inside the chamber, lined with a catalyst,  for some time, themixture is  allowed to pass away through a conduit,  also lined with a catalyst, until  the temperature has  fallen to about 600o C.  The vapours are  thereupon removed fromthe conduit into  a condenser and-rapidly cooled to a temperature of about 20o C.   Themixture of liquid hydrocarbons and water which is obtained by this method, is thensubjected to fractional distillation.  Dp to 230o C. light fractions  are obtained which  canbe used as fuel  in internal combustion engines, up to 50 per cent, of the liquor  being obtained as such.  A further 20 per cent, is obtained  in the form of hydrocarbons similarto kerosene, a  further 15 per cent, as a lubricating  oil, and the residue is a pitch-likesolid substance.     I am satisfied that Mr. Goldsbrough is  honest and has not faked his results, but hisplant has been  run on a small scale only.   The retort used at the demonstration which  Iattended at Slough on  8th October is capable of dealing with 6 gallons of tar an houronly.  Furthermore, the low temperature tar used in the process is obtained free of cost(which would not be the case if the process were developed on  a commercial scale).   Iam not  in a position  to state what  the labour costs would  be on a large scale  plant,although I am  of opinion that the labour costs would  be much lower, owing to the ease ofcontrol of the plant and the absence of high  pressures, than in hydrogenation processes.I am further of  opinion that the plant  could be run on a small scale as  a commercialproposition.     The reference made in the  newspaper to my connection with the War  Office was entirely unauthorised and my only interest has been that  I have advised the inventor onthe scientific aspects of his work  for the last four years, and I was present at  the demonstration merely as an  interested scientific expert.     My advice to the inventor and  his  financial backers, among  whom  is  a  wealthyEnglishman, a  Mr. Bancroft, was to hand over the development of the process to a firm,for example, the  Imperial Chemical Industries, which would have at its disposal scientificworkers and works facilities for developing the process thoroughly.     It is obvious to me that Mr. Goldsbrough  could only produce motor spirit at 2d.  a gallon if he could obtain his tars or tar oils free.  At present the  cost of such tars  or taroils works out  at 3d. a gallon before treatment.
  COMMENTS BY DR.  C. H. LANDER,  DIRECTOR OF FUEL RESEARCH, DEPARTMENT  OF                          SCIENTIFIC AND INDUSTRIAL  RESEARCH.     The Goldsbrough  process is a variant of the well-known cracking processes whichare  used for  the  production  of motor-spirit from heavy  petroleum  residues.  these processes are very highly developed  and a  great  deal  of  the  petrol  used for motor transport is produced by them.     Mr. Goldsbrough  claims that  by the use of a catalyst he is able to produce 40 percent, of motor-spirit, together  with other materials  such as lubricating oils, &amp;c, from a material such as low  temperature tar.   The  highest figure of which I am  aware for theproduction  of petrol from low temperature tar  by a system  of cracking  is about25 per cent.     There appears to be nothing inherently impossible in Mr. Goldsbrough&apos;s claims, but so far they have  been carried out on  little more than a laboratory scale.  From  suchdata as exist  at present,  it is in my opinion absolutely impossible to forecast at whatprice petrol could be  produced by this  method, even  if the claims are correct.  Theclaim,  however, of 2d. a gallon  is based upon definitely false assumptions,  one of which appears to be that low temperature tar will be available at a very low price.     The success  of low temperature  carbonization processes  will  depend  very largely upon the price which can be obtained for the tar, and it is difficult to see a financialbalance sheet in which a plant could be successful if the tar were not to bring more  thansay Hd. a gallon.   On this assumption, the absurdity of  claiming to convert part of thistar into petrol and selling the  petrol at 2d. a gallon is obvious.  The whole  question of petrol  production either direct from coal or from low temperature and other  tars is beingexplored very  actively  in many directions at the  present time, but the lowest reliablefigure  which I have ever seen  quoted is  in the order of 8d. per gallon.  If Mr. Golds-brought process on further development  could  produce  petrol at this figure, it would be doing  very well.     Mr. Goldsbrough  has never approached the Fuel  Research Board with a view tosubmitting  his process  to  a  critical   examination.   The  Fuel  Research  Divisionof the Department of Scientific  and  Industrial  Research  will  get  in touch  withMr.  Goldsbrough   and endeavour to obtain a more adequate picture  of the presentposition.  This process must  proceed very  much  further  before it can be  taken  intoserious consideration.   Other  processes exist at present which give better  results  thanthose quoted and which have been tried out on a 10 tons a day scale.

</content>
</cab>
