<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/216/0 images: 294-297</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fry v/HIS DOOUMEHT IS THE PROPERTY OB&apos; HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY * S GOVERNMENT.                                                            36                                                COPY NO._                                CABINET.                     COAL MINES NATIONAL INDUSTRIAL BOARD.                  Note by the President of the Board of Trade.               I circulate for the information of my colleagues          a note by the Secretary for Mines on the National          Industrial Board.  In the opinion of tho Secretary for          Mines (with which I agree) an immediate decision was          necessary, and I therefore authorised him at once to          adopt the third course which he suggests at the end of          his note                                                     W.G.          Board of Trade.             15th November; 1950.SECRET^C .P-  585  (30)-
COAL MINES NATIONAL INDUSTRIAL BOARD.     The Coal Mines Act, 1930, provides that the Board of Trade ;ay &quot;by order constitute a Board, consisting of a chairman and16 other members, to which either party to a dispute about theterms of a proposed distriot agreement may refer the dispute forenquiry and report.     The Act provides that the Board of Trade before appointingthe 16 members shall consult certain specified organisations.These organisations have been duly consulted.  Those representinglabour interests have suggested names for the eight places onwhich they had to be consulted.  The organisations representingthe employers interests have refused to make any suggestions.     The Mining Association (6 members) were the first to refuse.I met them and urged them to reconsider this decision.  Theyrefuse^ to do so.  I then consulted each of the Owners&apos; DistrictAssociations separately.  Two or three have not yet replied,but all the others have refused.  It is still just possible thatYorkshire (which is one of those which have not yet replied) may&quot;break away&quot;.  I discussed the matter with a member of the yorkshire Association this morning and I gather that the Associationmay nominate two members, but that I shall not know definitelybefore the beginning of next week.  -,/ithin the last week or so theFederation of British Industries and the Association of BritishChambers of Commerce (1 member  jointly) and the Confederation ofEmployers&apos; Organisations (l member) have intimated that, in viewof the difference of opinion in the industry as disclosed by theMining Association&apos;s attitude,  they prefer not &apos;to suggest any names.In other words the four employers bodies have joined together in a refusal to co-operate.     It is bound to be admitted at once that the refusal of thelining Association to nominate members has made it in practiceimpossible to constitute a Board of the character which the Act
contemplated.  At the same time the constitution of a Board isof great importance, in consequence of the demands of the owners,-&apos;hich ere beginning to take shape, for reductions in wages,consequent upon the reduction in hours on 1st &quot;December next.A very serious industrial situation is likely in many of the districts which at present have the 3 hour day, and I have alreadybeen told by representatives of the Miners&apos; Federation that they regard the establishment of a Board to which these disputes canbe referred as of very great importance and urgency.     Various alternatives are open.     One would be to announce that the Board will not be anpointedbecause the owners have made it impossible to appoint a Board ofthe character provided by the Act, and that the responsibility for industrial trouble mu^t therefore rest upon the owners.     This, from some points of view, might be the simplest andbest course, but on the other side it muat be remembered that members of the Government, including the Prime Minister, have announced that the refusal of the owners would not prevent theBoard being set up;   and, though the subsequent refusal of theother employers bodies has introduced another important factor,there is no doubt that the Miners&apos; Federation attach greatimportance to the appointment of a Board.     Another alternative would be to set up a Board consistingonly of a Chairman and the 8 members already nominated by theMiners&apos;  Federation (6).  the Trades Union Council (l) and theCo-operative Union (1),  leaving the other 8 places vacant solong as the owners and their friends refuse to nominate.     This course could be defended on the ground that, whatever may be the precise terms of the section, the obvious intentionof it is. that those eight places should be filled by representativesof the bodies specified,  that to fill them in any other way wouldnot be in accordance with the intention of the Act*  and that theonly thing to do therefore is to leave them vacant for so longas those bodies refuse to nominate.                             -2-
  n ofj v 0     On the other hand it is quite clear that in its operationssuch a one-sided Board would carry no weight in the publicestimation.     A third alternative is, if possible,  to find &quot;individual&quot;&apos;members to fill the places for which the organised bodies have refused to nominate.  I have no expectation of finding 6 colliery owners willing to sit, and certainly not of a name or calibre to command public confidence.  It should be possible, without any great difficulty cr delay, to find two individuals to fill theother two places, more or less of the same type and outlook as might have been expected in persons nominated by the 3 employersorganisations specified in the Act.     To constitute the Board even without any coal owners is not without considerable political advantage.   For this reason thealternative which I favour is the last, viz; to endeavour to fill the tvro places on which the Federation of British Industries, theAssociation of Chambers of Commerce and the Confederation ofEmployers&apos; Organisations had to be consulted, and, with theinclusion of the coal owners if they are nominated by Yorkshire,to proceed with the constitution of the Board.  (The Act providesthat the Rules regulating the procedure of the Bpard may providefor enabling the Board to act notwithstanding any vacancy.  Thiswas intended to cover only casual vacancies but can presumably beused to meet the present situation.)     Such a Board, though far from satisfactory, would at leastprovide a body to  hich the Miners&apos; District Unions could refertheir difficulties, and which in the public mind would not be soone-sided as would be a Board with nothing but S labour representatives and a chairman.     As the matter is urgent it is desirable to have the Cabinet&apos;3decision without delay.

</content>
</cab>
