<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/43/41 images: 356-359</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMEPrinted for the War Cabinet.  November 1943Copy No.WAR CABINET.RECONSTRUCTION COMMITTEE.Composition and Terms of Reference.1. The Prime Minister has directed that, in place of the ReconstructionPriorities Committee and the Reconstruction Problems Committee, there shall infuture be a single Committee to handle, under the War Cabinet, all questions of reconstruction on the home front. This Committee has been constituted asfollows : -The Minister of Reconstruction (Chairman).The Lord President of the Council.The Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Minister of Labour and National Service.The Minister of Production.The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.The President of the Board of Education.The Minister without Portfolio.The Postmaster-General.The Secretary of the Committee will be Mr. Norman Brook, of the Office ofthe Minister of Reconstruction.2.   The Committee will have the following terms of reference :  The Committee will be responsible, under the War Cabinet, for dealing withthe following matters : (i) It will be responsible for formulating the Government policy on theSocial Security Scheme,(ii) It will review all major reconstruction schemes from the point ofview7 of (a) any issues of principle involved; and(b) the claims which these  projects  are likely to  make  on theExchequer.(iii) It will deal with questions of principle arising out of wTork of theMinister of Reconstruction in reviewing the whole range of preparations for the transitional period.Note. Without derogation from the responsibilities of the -Minister of reconstruction, it is not intended that this Committee should handlequestions as to our post-war financial, economic and commercial policy inthe international field. Likewise, it is not intended that this Committeeshould take over any of the functions in regard to the settlement of priorities within the field of production, whether for war or for civil purposes, which are at present handled on the Production Council andits Sub-Committees.(Signed) E. E. BRIDGES,Secretary of the War Cabinet.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,30th November, 1943.JNMEWT4 P f*i boSECRET.W.P. (43) 541.30th November, 1943.[26491]




</content>
</cab>
