<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/38/0 images: 12-19</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUlffSTT  IS TH?. PROPERTY 07 HIS BTUTAITNIC ttAJRiSTY&apos; S GOVRRKi^ire .)S 3 C R ST.FI5?AL COPY.COKCLTJSIOES of a Conference-ofMinisters held at 10 Downing Street,S.W.I., on FRIDAY, 10th SentemTaer.1920 at 12 IToon.COPY 1T0,P R 1 STB   TV-    mTHE PRI2S3 iriKISTTSH   (in the Chair).e: Right Hon.A.Bonar Lai?, K.P.;ro Privy Seal.e Right Hon. C.. Addison, K.P.:,Bister of Health.\4 Right Hon.Sir Robert Home,jJEf.S. ,K.C. ,M.P., President ofjeH Board of Trade.je: Right Hon. Lord Lee of.rehas:,  G.B.S. ,K. C,3. , minister -Agriculture &amp; Fisheries.The Right Hon. Sir Hnfnar GreenwoodBart. ,11.C.    .P. , Chi of Secretaryfor Ireland.The Right Hon.T. J.KaonanaraM.P..Minister of Labour.The Ristfit Hon.E.A.L.Fish^r,K.P.. ,President of the Board of 3du-cntio?The Right Hon. - Sir&apos; L. &apos; ?orthimtoaTr.7r.ns,&quot; 3krt., LLP.THT,. FOLLO^IKG &quot;T^R&quot;1&quot;1 ALSO PR3S&apos;ie Right Hon.Lord HardingeiPensTaurst, E.G. ,G.C .B., -iC.S.I* ,Cr, Ctli .G. ,G.C.I.35o alp.V.O. , Permanent Under crrtary, Foreign Office,ipr Conclusions 2, 2.a. &amp; 3)*a? right Hon. The 3arl ofIWford and Balc&amp;rr^s,jia i rma n, *Vhcat contribute. i s s io n.Epr Conclusion   6   ).The Right Hon.C.A.KcCurdy, K.C ,lf.P., Pood Controller.   1(For Conclusion       6.)Sir 3.J.Shac]-;leton,K.C.3,, JointPeminent Secretary, Ministry ofLabour.(JTor Conclusions 3. 5 &amp; 6)*ioutenant Colonel, Sir-K.P. A. Harikey, &apos;f. C..3.    ...    .........    Secretary.i* T.       Jones...    ...  &quot;.........- ...   Principal Assist p. nt Socr?tr-ry.ppraander R.L.Haner......    ...    ......    ......   Assist rnt Secretary.
(l) The Oonf-srenca had &quot;before then the draft of en3R TOHI BIT Order forwarded - to the Lord Privy Seal by the AdmiraltyPS FROMBRING designed to prohibit sh&amp;pe carrying passengers eastwardbound from entering ^u-s^nete^n Harbour until further notice(CP. 1845&apos;),,Th&apos;; Confe?r&apos;ncf agreed:-That th-.1- Admiralty should W authorised toissue the Ordar and to rjriv such coisnunice-modifications to the For-iigr. Offic - ua nifgit bpnr-c^ssary with a vi,:*- to notifyingWashington, and to oth--r Govvsrnn^ntofficss conc:?rn;*d.
0RUSSIAN      &apos; (2)     Flth ref ::roncc to Condition (1) or the Conference&amp;RADEDELEGATION, of Ministers of September 8th^ the Conference had beforethem a letter dated 9th September 1920 addressed by II,Kameneff to the Prime Minister stating that he proposedto leave London on Saturday next and to stay in Moscow notmore than seven days.     M. ICar,.eneff asked for instructions and offered to put before his Government any suggestion for the speedy establishment of a general peace and agreement with England which remained the sincere desire of the Rusbi an Governmcnt (C. P v184 0)*J-. Suggestion was made that the proper course .-would before;:&apos; the Prime Minister to send for M, Mamaneff and toInform him that the British Government were prepared tocontinvie negotiations only on the following conditions(1)   That the Government of Russia should do what every man of honour does - abide by their principles.(2)   That they should send a nan of honour torepresent them instead of       Fameneffwho had deceived the British Governmentin regard to the terras to be offered to the Poles at   Minsk&quot;, eIt was pointed out that if I.T. Kamaneff was not allowed to return it would be difficult to retaincertain other members of the Mission who were equallyculpable inclxiding I.&quot;8 Kllschkc     without the latterit was improbable that IT, Eras sin and the more honotirablemembers of. the Mission would be allowed to stay*     hence the resaalt would be that the door would be closed, to thetrade negotiations which at present held out some prospects of useful results..Attention was drawn to an article in the &quot;DailyHerald5&apos; admitting and attempting to justify relationswith the Russian Trade Delegation in regard, tc the rocipt
2.a.       Lord Hardinge called the attention of the conference to the unsatisfactory position of English prisoners inRussia and Baku.     There were some 1^0 scattered overRussia including 8-5 civilians, , chiefly in Koscow andPetrograd, and about 60 In Baku.     There was evidencethat they were very indifferently fed.     The ForeignOffice were taking all possible- steps to relieve theirLord Hardinge undertook to submit to the Prime Minister full particularsfor communication to M. Kameneff thataft ernoon.3 &amp; 4.of a subsidy from Soviet Russia.    It was pointed outthat .this article had been published in order to forestallthe publication of the results of Police enquiries whichhad traced the proceeds of jewels sold by the RussianBelegates to Mr. Francis Heynell, a Director of the &quot;daily herald&quot;.      Some enphasis *as placed on the importanceof the fullest possible publicity*&apos;After some discussion the Conference agreed:-(l)   That the Prime Minister should see I&apos;.Kameneff pe?.-sonaliy and warn him that his conduct had given rise tosuspicion, and that the subsequentenquiries had revealed a series ofbreaches of his undertaking of whichthe Prime Minister would give an outline without dealing with theevidence.(2)    That the question of the publicationof the evidence should be reserved&apos;until after this interview.
3.    With reference to Minute 5 of the Conference ofStationRIGA. Ministers held on September 8th the conference had beforethem correspondence between the prime Minister&apos; s private secretary (Mr. J.T. Daviea) and Mr. H.S-% Lindsuy onbehalf of the joint secretaries of the Council ofAction in which it was explained that the purpose ofthe proposed visit by Mr. Adams a ri and Mr. A.A. Purcellto Riga was &quot;To attend the coming negotiation;.! betweenthe Russian and polish Peace Delegates and watch theproceeding.;&quot; ( CP,184:?) .&quot;The Conference agreed :-Th&apos;.t the Prime Mini ster should send a reply in the -sense that the Cabinethod considered the request and had decided that they could not recognise the right of any body to take part inthe foreign policy of the country which was exclusively the business ofthe Government of the country.
HREATENEDOAL STRIKEiEATElTEDIIKB OPSCTRICIAHS4.   The president of the Board of Trade gave the Con-ference his impression of the meeting he had had on theprevious day -with the Executive of the Miners&apos; Federationfrom which it was clear that while the temper of the miners and their representatives was not aggressive the stage had been reached when a strike was very difficultto avert.   There appeared to be considerable risk that therailwayman would join   the strike.   The mere transport ofcoal In the railmys would be regarded as &quot;blackleggi ng&quot;by the miners and it would be difficult for the railwaymento avoid participation.   The attitude of the transportworkers was less certain.5*   The conference was informed that a dispute hadari sen between the Employers and Men in the engineering and Electrical Trades over the appointment of a non-union foreman..   The matter was being referred by theMinistry of La&quot;bour to a court of Enquiry.The Minister asked both parties to call a truce -the e.T.tj* to send their men back to work and the Employers8Federation to withdraw the lock-out notices pending thereport of the court of Enquiry.   The E.T.U. was willing todo this provided the employers withdrew the lock-outnotices.   This, that body refused to do.The resolution passed at a meeting of the shop-stewards was reported to the Conference.   This resolutioncalled on the Engineering and National Employers Federa-tion to conform with the recommendation of the Ministryof La&quot;bour, failing which the meeting asked their respec-tive organisations to give seven days notice to withdraw their labour.The conference took note of the situation..
6* The Conference had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Agriculture and Fisheries pointing out the heavy-shrinkage in the area under wheat and the likelihood ofthis shrinkage continuing and urging an immediate can ce 11a-tion of the maximum price of 95/- and that until the termina-tion of the bread subsidy.i farmers should receive a price ona parity with the price of imported wheat (CP. 1828).In support of this proposal it was stated that a new situation would arise in about a week when the &quot;-heat commissioners-sion would have to announce a ne^ price of 116/- for imported wheat.    This was necessary in order to reduce the bread subsidy.This announcement,  coming at the moment when farmers were con-sidaring what crops to grow for next year&apos;s harvest and at atime e  trouble for the farmer on account of labour andweather difficulties would, unless the proposed steps were taken, have the inevitable effect of still further reducingthe area sown to wheat and of eausing the fanners to hoard,their this year&apos;s harvest of wheat until Control was removed.In that event the cost to the Treasury owing to thenecessity of purchasing a larger quantity of wheat from north america would be  2,000,000 more than if these proposals were accepted.    Moreover it was contended that the steps proposed would not  increase the price of bread to the consumer at all upto March 3lst. and after that date by less than a farthing.On the ether hand it was contended that the.farmr-rswere getting a fair prof it for their wheat and that to adr.it this principle of an increase in the price of British wheat to thenextlevel of imported wheat would after the 31et I-tarch/whon thesubsidy disappeared .give the farmers unduly large profits at therate of an *:xtra ten or fifteen million pounds for a yf;ar&apos;s crop,nr-roly because the exchange with foreign wheat-growing countries was so unfavourable to our Government and would be on a parallel with putting the extra profits on export coal into the pocketsof the coalowners instead of into the Treasury.
The general view of the Conference was that the presentmoment was unfavourable for the adoption of the proposedsteps,    the principal difficulty at the present moment beinglargely industrial and not with the farmers *It was also pointed out that unless it were made clear that the price of home wheat would be controlled forsome time after the 31 at March there would be hoarding andgrfeat loss id the Treasury.It ms suggested that an announcement should be made that control of price would not be removed on the. 31 stMatch as %hm farmers were now being advised to hoard in the belief that all control would then be removed.The conference agreedThat the question raised issues ontSiich the chancellor sf the Exchequermust express his views-        that no final decision could be taken until theseviewa had been received..Whitehall Gardens, s.W. I.10th September, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
