<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/38/0 images: 74-79</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IHIS POCXIHBHt IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS OR ITALIC  E^U?STY&apos;S GOVERWLENT,0     / ..cc. /   LCONCLUSIONS of a Conference Iof Ministers held at 10, PovmingStreet, S;E.l. on Thursday, 4th,November, 1920 at 11-30 a.n04 E C R E T0   ^PR SS EN T:-THE PRIME MINISTER    (in the Chair)bie Right HonBA,Bonar Law, M0P,Lord Privy SealsThe Right Hon.A*Charaberlain,5m,P., Chancellor of theiSx chequer.if he Right Ron .Vls count Hilner,E.C.B. ,G.C .II.G. ,Secretary cfState for the Colonies.Ehe Right Hon.H.S.Churchill,p.P.,Secretary of State forrl/ar &amp; AireThe Right Hon.A,J,Balfour,0.M,,M.Po, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon.Earl Curzon of kedleston, K.G.,G.C.S.I.,G.C.I,E.Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon.E.S.Montagu,H.F.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon.H.A.L.Fisher,M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.THE FOLLOWING EEF.E ALSO PRESENTField-Harsh-al the Viscount Allenby, G.0.B*,G.O.*I.(t.,Lieutenant-Colonel Sir H.P.A^Hankey, G.C.D.,......Secretary, Cabinet.Brigadier-General sell,Wilson, C.B.,O.M.G., Principal Assistant Secretary0
DIPLOMATIC (1)    with reference to Par Cabinet 631, Conclusion 1REPRBSENTArTION AT THE   arising out of a. Question in Parliament,,  it was agreed -VATICAN.That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should home authority to retain the British Diplomatic representative at the &quot;Vatican,LEAGUE OF (2)    The attention of the Conference was called toHATIONS oa series of Questions addressed to the Prime MinisterQuestions       on subjects discussed at the recent meeting of the Councilin Psrlia-ment In of the League of Nations,,regard to the  Brussels It was agreed - CouncilsThat Mr.Balfour should deal with theseQuestions on the basis of making theresolutions of the Council and thepertinent Memoranda available for members of Parliament at the earliestpossib1e moment.THE STATUS OF      (3)      The Conference resumed the discussion on theEGYPT cstatus of Egypt,  initiated at the meeting held onNovember 1st,After Lord Milner had made some importantcorrections in the draft summary attached to the Con-clusions of the previous meeting, the discussion was resumed..In regard to the proposal that Egypt should enjoy the right to representation in foreign countries,apprehensions were expressed that this would give too great an opportunity for anti-British intrigues byPowers with interests or traditional ambitions in Egypt.Lcrd Milner made it clear that the omission ofthis provision would be contrary to the spirit and lettercf the scheme, and that no scheme which omitted It couldbe carried through any representative Egyptian assembly.It was pointed out,   however;  that british control over Egyptian foreign relations was safeguardedin great measure by the provision that Egypt should enter into no agreement with a foreign Power which was&apos; prejudicial to British interests.It was explained that the Egyptians attached greim
importance to representation on the League of Nations andon International Conferences on all questions, technical orotherwise.    This was one of the reasons for tine insertion of the provision under discussion.The trend of the discussion was in the direction thatsome alternative must-be found to our present position inEgypt, the maintenance of which required the presence of alarge military force, and this even though,  as foreshadowedby the Secretary of State for War, considerable reductions in the present force of 15,000 to 16,000 men might provepracticable.    The question for consideration was whetherLend Miner&apos; s proposed alternative was the best possible.This led to considerable discussion on the military aspects, and the question was asked as to how the size ofthe garrison would compare on the alternative assumptions(i)    that the present state of affairs continued,and(ii)    that the proposals of Lord Milner&apos;s Commis-sion were adopted and received only a mod-erate degree of general acceptance by theEgyptian people.Field-Marshal Lord Allenby stated that, under the Corn-mission1 s proposals,  the British forces at Ismalia (whereLord Milner suggested they would be stationed) would be atthe Egyptians since their water-HUopiy would be at the mercy ofthe merCy of/Cairo,which must be considered the heart ofEgypt from a military point of view,    lie laid great stress,therefore, on the maintenance of a British fores in Cairo.If no British troops were- kept thore, he felt certain that foreign nations, including the Americans, would probablyinsist on the provision of Legation Guards.    Otherwise,the High Commissioner and ether Europeans in Cairo would beat the mercy of any seditious movement.Questioned as to his views on the scheme as a whole,Lord Allenby (who was due to leave for Egypt on the following day) stated that he did not like the manner in which negotiations
had &quot;been carried, out with Zaghlul, who is our enemy,instead of with the Egyptian Government.   He felt, however,that we were now to a considerable  extent committed tothe scheme, a view which did not meet with unanimous con-currence in the Conference.   Lord Allenby attached greatImportance to a future procedure supporting our friendsinstead of trying vainly to conciliate our enemies.   among our friends are the present Egyptian Ministry, who wouldthen in all probability give us their loyal support in theexecution of the scheme.   At the present time the Egyptianswere coming to realise that they were receiving, fair-playfrom the British, both in internal and in foreign affairs.Unless, hOY/ever, they received a large measure of autonomy,they would co ^slder that they had been betrayed, as, eventhough wrongly, they regarded Lord Milner as a plenipotentiary.Lord Allenby attached great importance to the fact that thsBritish Government had guaranteed to uphold the Sultan andjIhis dynasty.    This committed them to some degree of inter-ference in the affairs of Egypt.    In his experience the sultan, though unpopular, was a shrewd man and an honestman, who would support us if we supported him.    If we failed .to give such support, we should earn the contempt of our enemies and the hostility of our friends.    He urged that anyarmy of occupation must be British.    The conduct of theIndian troops had been unexceptionable, but the Egyptiansdislikod the long-continued presence of coloured troops.Subject to these remarks, Lord Allenby was not opposed toLord Milner&apos;s proposals, as a basis for consideration .inconsultation with a representative Egyptian Delegation tobe nominated by the Sultan; but he regarded as essential theretention for the present of troops in Cairo.The question was then discussed as to whether theproposed British force was sufficient to enable us to maintainthe dynasty.
The Prime Minister, with, the agreement of his colleagues,impressed on Lord Allenby that he should make it clear inEgypt that the British Government was not finally committed to the scheme.    Egypt was not bound by the adherence ofZaghlul and his colleagues to the proposals, and knew thatshe was perfectly free to examine them and to suggest amend-ments .    Trie position of the British Government was preciselysimilar;  it was merely in process of examining and consideringva scheme presented to them only in the form of a summary bythe Commission which had drawn it up.    The Prime Minister   ^made It clear that the question of whether the Governmentwould exercise it3 freedom was a question of policy to beconsidered later.Lord Allenby made it perfectly clear that he would be obliged, In conversation with tne Sultan, to enter into thequestion in some detail.This ltd to a discussion as to the nature of the Dele-gation, representing all shades of Egyptian opinion, which itwas proposed, as the next step,  should be sent by the egyptian government to London.    It was pointed out that it was QSutmtialto make clear to this Delegation whether it was to d iscussdetails of a scheme already accepted in principle, ormerely to reopen the whole question.Lord Milner pointed out that-, notwithstanding the boycott of his Mission in Egypt, it had in the end succeeded in eliciting the attitude of all shades of Egyptian opinion.It was generally agreed that no decision could be taken at the moment as to the precise purpose of the proposedDelegation.    The procedure should be somewhat as follows :-(a)Consideration by the Cabinet of lord milner s Report j(b)A decision by the Cabinet on thequestion of policy;
(c)    If that decision were of a character to render such procedure desirable, the reception of a Delegation, appointed bythe Egyptian Oovernment,  to discussthe details of the British Government.\sdoci si on.Whitehall Garrtena, S.W.I.,November e,  1920.

</content>
</cab>
