<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/38/0 images: 271-278</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos;f after 268Ifflg ..33QQmSBm* g&apos; THE&apos; PROPERTY&apos; OP&apos; HIS&apos; Bft ITALIC&quot;&apos;M^S^Y^S&apos;-0:6IfrERNMENtBK^.-.EGRET.finally COPY.^^.ij:i.ii&apos;iiui-Vi,&apos;&apos;;&apos;i&quot;.7!CONCLUSIONS of a Conference of Ministers heldin Mr. Chamberlain&apos;s Room, Souse of Commons, S.W. ,on Monday, April llth, 1921, at 6.p.m.PRESENT oThe Rt0 Hon. Ao Chamberalln, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal     (in the Chair).The Rt. Hon. the Earl Curson of kedleston, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.,Secretary of State for Foreign. Affairs.The Rt. Hon. W.S. Churchill, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies *The Rt. Hon. E*S. MontagtL, M.P.,Secretary of State for India.:The Rt. Hon. Sir L. Wcrthingtdn Evans,Bart., M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Rt. Hon. Lord Lee of Fareham,G0B*E.,K.C.B., first Lord of the Admiralty.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT:7   -Captain the Rt, Hon. FcE. Guest,CrB*E.,D.S.Q.,M.P., Secretary of State forAir   (for conclusion 1).Air-Marshal Sir H.M. Trenchard, Bart.,K.C.B., D.S.O., Chief of the AirStaff   (for conclusion 1).Mr. J.E. Shuckburgh,C.B*, ColonialOffice.Major HcW. Young, E*oS.0., ColonialOffice.ji R.B. Howorth........................... ^Assistant Secretary.i Colonel C.W.G. Walker, D.S.O...........^Assistant Secretary,CoXoBd
i^jTCISAHlA^   (1) WliOi-jreferenc^ (21), Conclusion 5 (b),the-Secretary of State fc,r the Colonies reminded the Confer-ence that the policy regarding Trans-Jordania previously con-templated had comprised a military garrison at Amman of one battalion, two Squadrons, and two guns.    The Cabinet had,however, misgivings as to these proposals, and he had prooeed*-ed to negotiate with Abdullah on the basis of avoiding thenecessity for a garrison in Trans-Jordania.   The proposals were summarised in a Memorandum (Paper CP,-2815) circulatedto the Cabinet, and under them-Abdullah fras to have the assist-, ance of Political Officers, his Native Levies were to be givenBritish Officers, and cash was to be advanced to enable him topay the levies.    Three aerodromes were tc be established inTrans-Jordan la for use by the Air Ferce,, and Abdullah and thelocal levies would be visited and supported by the Air Squadronfrom Ludd,    These proposals had the full assent &apos;of.the Chiefof the Air Staff and the local Political and Military Authori-ties, and Abdullah had returned to Amman on the understandingthat they would be adopted.    If he failed to get support he might fall at any time, in which case Trans-Jordania would bethe scene of anarchy and a military occupation might be neces-sary.    The arrangements had been endangered by a telegram sentfrem the War Office forbidding the aeroplanes to move.Air Marshal Trenchard explained that it was proposedthat the aeroplanes should land at the aerodromes two or three times a week.    The Arabs would be given certain duties inregard to looking after the petrol stores.    In addition^ itwas proposed -that the aeroplanes should mark out the &quot;desertroute&quot; to Mesopotamia.    Once an aeroplane service   on thedesert route was established it would have a very salutary effect upon the Arabs,    The worst that could happen might be- I-the assassination of mechanics left at the aerodromes.    Itwas not proposed, however, to leave more personnel in TransrJordania than could be rer-removed in a crisis by the aeroplanes.
It was generally agreed that the proposed aeroplaneservice between Ludd and Amman was not inconsistent with thedecision of the Cabinet above referred to.    The institutiono** t-bA &quot;dAsnrt route&quot; raised, however, political issues ofimportance which required careful consideration.In reply to the Secretary of State for India, theSecretary of State for th- Colonies assured the conference that his proposals really involved a diminution rather than an increase of our responsibility respecting Trans-Jordania.Further, the arrangements had been made with the expressintention of excluding any extension of Zionist activity intoTrans-Jordania.   Abdullah had been satisfied in this respect and had promised to give us his support.   Mr Churchill urgedthat he might be given reasonable latitude in this matter.   Itwas essential to retain the friendship of Abdullah, and thesch^e *&quot;or administering Trans-Jordania by means/f british political Officers was merely an application of the principle which was being introduced on a larger scale in Mesopotamia,The establishment of the &quot;desert route&quot; between mesopotamia and Egypt offered important strategical and political advan-tages, and, besides very materially shorteningthe journey to mesopotamia, would tend to keep the desert tribes friendly to us.The Secretary of State for War informed the conference that he had had no opportunity of consulting his military advisers on the proposals, and that he felt obliged tosatisfy himself that there was no serious risk of the pro-pess-ls involving us in fresK military commitments.The Conference agreed(a) That, after consultation with his military advisers, the Secretary of State for war should notify the Seoretary of State forthe Colonies with the least possible delay ifhe was satisfied that there was no substantial military objection to thefollowing arrangements:(b) That the proposals of the Secretary ofState for the Colonies relative to theemployment of aeroplanes for the purpose
of visiting and supporting Abdullah shouldbe sanctioned, on the understanding thatthe aeroplane service would be restricted to flights between ludd and Amman and theother aerodromes to be established in Trans-Jordania:(c) That the larger question of the use of aeroplanes for the purpose of establish-ing and maintaining the &quot;desert route&quot;between Egypt and Mesopotamia should befurther considered by the Cabinet on alater date.(groTTS ^0 (2) With reference to Cabinet 14 (21), Conclusion 5 (e).B CHIEFS.the Secretary of State for the Colonies gave the conference a general appreciation of the present position of the moreimportant Arab rulers in the Arabian Peninsula.i Saud. The immediate question requiring settlement related to the subsidy payable to Ibn Saud. whose control of thefanatical Wahabi Arabs made it most important that friendly relations should be maintained.    Not only could Ibn Saud bevery troublesome in the Hejaz, but at any moment he might provoke seriotis disorders in Mesopotamia.    Sir Percy Coxhad suggested that the present stibsidy payable to Ibn Saudof  60^000 per annum should be Increased to  120,000 perarm-ivr,    we (Mr Churchill) suggested, however, that  100,000per annum, payable monthly in arrear and conditional on good behaviour, would be sufficient (Paper CP.-2753).    Sir percy cox was interviewing Ibn SaudTs emissaries on April 13th,and it was most important that he should be able to make some definite offer on that date,e Hussein. -nth rerrard to the subsidy payable to King Hussein.the Conference were inforr^d by Mr Churchill that we seemedto be moving towards a Shereefian system in Arabia.    Whileit was impossible to guarantee that this system would be successful, the character and capacity of the members ofthe Shereefian family afforded grounds for hope.    KingWtjgsuMn was in very serious difficulties owing to the break-down of the Hejaz Railway.   The absence of pilgrims meant that the Hejaz Tribes were much impoverished, and King
Hussein., had-bm obliged., to find  100,000 in the last yearto assist them.    A subsidy of less than  100,000 a yearcould not well be offered, and this compared with thesubsidy of  C00.000 a month paid during the War and 25,000 a month paid at the time&apos;when&apos;payment was suspended-nine months ago.The Idri3i Tt was proposed to give subsidies of  1,000 and &apos;and the Imam. 2,000 a month respectively to the Idrisi and the Imam.It was most desirable to resure friendly relations withthe latter.   At present the garrison of Aden was costing,  the country  1,000,000 a year, and it might be possible to -effect very substantial reductions if, as part of a generalscheme, Aden was taken over by the Imperial Government,India assuming a proportion of the financial burden.    Byjoining Aden to Somalrland it would be possible to estab-lish a small aeroplane service which could control bothshores of the Straits of Babel llandab.In conclusion, Mr Churchill informed the conference that the total subsidies proposed would not amount to 300,000 per annum, and it would only be possible to reducethe  30,050,0^3* military expenditure in the Middle East to less than  9^000,000 next year by giving some latitude in- the matter of subsidies and by providing a substantial sum for intelligence service.In reply to a question by Mr Chamberlain as to the likelihood o** India bearing her share of the Middle Eastexpenditure, the Secretary of State for India reminded the Conference that hi3 assent to the compromise effectedwhen the question was last under consideration had been expressly given on the understanding that it would besubject to the concurrence of the Government of India.    Hehadrecently received the objections of the Indian government any proposals involving the payment in peace-time-of a subsidy to King Hussein, these objections being due. toreligious difficulties.   Personally he did not entirely
agree- with, the- ^vernment^f India in this matter, and thought that it would be quite easy to earmark the Indiancontribution to non-controversial expenditure.   The proposed transfer of Aden would probably require legislation.    Sofar as he personally was concerned he would favour a generalarrangement under which Aden was transferred to the ImperialGovernment and India made a financial contribution towardsMiddle East expenditure proportionate to her interests inthat part of the world.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs agreed generally  with the proposals und ^--review, but &quot;&quot;felt-very doubtful whether the proposed subsidies were not on an alto-sether extravagant scale.    In the case of Ibn Saud it had recently been proposed to reduce the subsidy of  605000 perannum, and Sir Percy Cox&apos;s suggested  120,000 per annummeant giving ibn  Saud the same subsidy as was paid to the amir of Afghanistan.Mr Chamberlain agreed with Lord Curzon, and thought there was very great danger in agreeing to such large subsidy-di^s, particularly having regard to the difficulty of bringing the payments to an end.    With regard to Ibn Saud he thoughtthat the difficulty could best be removed by making him a lump sum grant in addition to his subsidy during the presentyear.    He did not so much object to the aggregate amount involved as to the principle of paying la:.;ge surs to theseneedy Arab rulers who might easily be bought far above their real value,7/ith regard to King Hussein, the Conference were reminded thaTt, during the War, engagements had possibly been entered into with the French and Italians under which theymight wishj to participate in any subsidy granted,and that it was important to clear up the position before any final decision was taken.  -The Conference agreed (a) Th-vo the Secretary of State for the colonies should, inform Si.? Percy Cox of the natureof the objections to the increase of thesubsidy of  60,000 per annum now paid to
&quot; obrr^iaudL, pointing, out in particular- thata lr.rger Subsidy would set the scale forother cases, and re- dndong him that evenin the case of the An ir of Afghanistan a subsidy of  120,000 per annum had beenfound sufficient and that this sum had only been reached after many years:(b) That at th^ same ti e Sir Percy Cox shouldbe authorised to offer Ibn Saud (a) fchecontinuance en present ten-s of the subsidy of  60,0C09 and (b) a lump sum of  20,000in respect of the present year, payable(at Sir Percy Cox&apos;s discretion) eitherimmediately or by instalments:(c) That the question of the subsidy to begranted in future to King Hussein shouldbo fur-cher considered by the Secretary ofState for the Colonies and the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs in consulta-tlon, on the understanding that the subsidy should not exceed that grato Bin Saud.(d) That the Secretary of State for the colonies should consult with the Secretary of Statefor India on the questions of the proposed transfer of Aden and the amount of thepayment which the Government of India might properly be requested to contribute to theMiddle Eastern expenditure:(e) That, a-^ter such consultation, the Secretaryof State for India should communicate to theGovernment of India the views expressed atthe meeting, and should endeavour to persuadethat Government to accept a scheme under whichthe responsibility for Aden would be trans-ferred to the Imperial Government and india would make a real and serious annual eontri-bution to Middle Eastern expenditure commen-commensurate with h*r interests.(3) The Conference were informed by the Secretary ofState for the Colonies that he had taken upon himself toauthorise the High Comissioner for Palestine to make a payment of  5,tJ00 to Abdullah to enable him to meet hiscurrent expenses.    It would undoubtedly   be necessary tomake -further payments to Abdullah, the amount of which woulcneed- further investl gation.The Conference took note of and approved the action of the Secretary of State for.  . the Colonies in authorising Sir HerbertSamuel to make the payment of  5,000 toAbdullah in aid of his current expenditure.The Secretary of State for the Coloniesundertook to approach the Treasury witha view to the requisite covering sanctionbeing obtained for this payment, and also
to consult with the Chancellor o^ ,theExchequer as to the amount of thefuture payments to be mad** to Abdullah,2.9 ^itehall Gardens, S,&quot;*&quot;. 1,April 11, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
