<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/9/133 images: 754-755</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ISSCRET:^P.(G)(41)  155olaoth November. 1941,COPY no war CABINETEVACUATION OF GOVERNMENT DEPARTMENTSMemorandum by the Chairman of the civil defence Committee.The War Cabinet are av/are that at the outbreak of war there were plans for evacuating the staffs of GovernmentDepartments in two categories :(a) those whom it was essential to locate near the headquarters of Government; this was known as the black move and was to be made to the west;(b) the remainder:  this was known as the grey (formerlyyellow) move and was to be made to the North west and North Midiands6The policy so far followed has been to retain the seat of Government and essential staffs in London while sending out to the provinces the staffs whose work could be carried outthere without major inconvenience.    By July 1941 the numbersevacuated were.Black Move 16,550Grey Move 40,700The position has been periodically reviewed:  the WarCabinet last had the matter before it when considering the vulnerability of Whitehall to air attack (W.M.(4l) 20thConclusions, Minute 5) when it was agreed that the battleshould be fought from Whitehall unless and until the Governmentwere bombed out of it or communications broke down.    Reserveaccommodation should, however, be maintained in a state of readiness to meet these eventualities,The stage has now been reached when in the light ofchanged circumstances departments can justifiably be released from the necessity of having to keep up to date the variousprecautions which formed part of the Black Move, such as theearmarking of billets by the Ministry of Health and the keeping up to date of transport plans by the Ministry of war transport.    The accommodation has been used for the housingof Government staffs or lent to- the Service Departments for various essential purposes.The Civil Defence Committee had before them the follow1&apos;proposals in a memorandum (CDC(4l)68) by the FinancialSecretary to the Treasury(a) the-Black Move as a concerted move of essentialstaffs should be abandoned;(b) Departments should be invited to remove from London/any
any less essential staff still left; &apos;-&quot;(c) return of staff to London would aggravate an alreadyserious accommodation difficulty and should ingeneral be forbidden;(d) the entry of war workers into the Black Area shouldnot be opposed but where any conflict of interestarises it should be decided on merits, -through theappropriate machinery.They generally welcomed these proposals,  and regardedthem as easing the billeting problems of the Ministry ofHealth and assisting the Ministry of Labour in finding living accommodation for industrial workers.    They(l) approved the recommendations set out above;(2) agreed that any publicity regarding this decision should be avoided;(3) invited the Postmaster General   to discuss with theMinister of Works and Buildings and the FinancialSecretary to the Treasury, the withdrawal of switch-board and other equipment now standing idle inbuildings earmarked for evacuation purposes;(4) agreed that while the return of staff to London should in general be forbidden, applications by departments for the return of a few individual officers should beconsidered on their merits by the Treasury and&quot;&apos; the. .. -Sub-Committee on the Evacuation of GovernmentDepartments. .and noted that these conclusions would be reported to theWar Cabinet.H.M.MINISTRY OF HOME SECURITY.WHITEHALL.&apos;20th November. 1941.

</content>
</cab>
