<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/12/0 images: 21-28</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  January 1948SECRET Copy Mo. 45CM. (48)3rd conclusions cabinet 3 (48)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 13th January, 1948, at 11 a.m..&apos;. Present:The Right Hon, C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison, The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,M.P., Lord President of the Council. ;   K.C.,   M.P.,   Chancellor   of   thej   Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander, The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,M.P., Minister of Defence. Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt, j The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Lord Chancellor. j   Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones, The Right Hon. A. Woodburn, M.P.,M.P., Secretary of State for the Secretary of State for ScotlandColonies. (Item 3).The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P., The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Labour and National \ Minister of Health.Service.The Right Hon. T. &quot;Williams, M.P., \ The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,Minister    of    Agriculture    and ! M.P., Minister of Education.FisheriThe Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P., I The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Item 2).       I    Minister of Food (Item 1).The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell, j The Right Hon. C. W. Key, M.P.,M.P., Minister of Fuel and Power !    Minister of Works (Item 2).(Items 2-3). !Mr. Douglas Jay, M.P., economic secretary, Treasury (Item 2).Secretariat; /Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.34848-3/. mmB
CABINET 3 (48)ContentsSubjectFood    ....................Fata Ration.Allocation of Resources      ............Priority System for Components and Materials otherGas Bill........
Food. 1.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister ofFats Ration.   Food (CP. (48) 10) proposing that, for the period from 1st February(  to 24th April, the weekly margarine ration should be raised from3oz. to 4 oz.The Minister of Food said that by this means the total fatsration could be maintained, throughout the most difficult winter months, at the level of 8 oz. a week at which it had stood for thegreater part of the war. There were obvious nutritional advantages, in making this increase; and he was specialty anxious to bring it into effect while supplies of potatoes were inadequate. Although itwould not in itself represent a significant calorie increase, it wouldenable people to eat rather more bread.In reply to a question, the Minister said that up to the end ofApril he would be able to support the increased ration from stocks,even though he had to forgo for financial reasons the supplies ofvegetable oils which he had been expecting to obtain from theArgentine.The Chancellor&quot;of the Exchequer said that he need not oppose this proposal on financial grounds, provided that it was presented to the public as a temporary increase which would be supplied from existing stocks and that there was no commitment to maintain it after 24th April. He also asked that, in view of the current trade negotiations with Denmark, the increase should not be announceduntil the last moment consistent with its coming into operation on1st February. The Minister of Food should also arrange for the danish representatives now ;,n London to be informed in advance ofthe public announcement and told that this temporary increase wouldbe supplied from existing stocks in the United Kingdom. TheMinister of Food accepted these conditions.The Cabinet-Agreed that the weekly margarine ration should beincreased from 3 oz. to 4 oz. during the period from 1st February to 24th April.Allocation of resources.PrioritySystem -forComponentsand Materialsother thanSteel.(previous reference:C.M.(47)89thConclusions,Minute 1.)2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (CP. (48) 13) outlining the arrangements proposed for modifying, in respect of components and materials other thansteel, the priority system introduced by the Prime Ministersdirective of 20th March, 1947 (CP. (47) 92).The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that it was a necessarycorollary to the new steel priority system, which the Cabinet had approved on 18th November, 1947, that the use of the special&quot; P.M.L.&quot; symbol in respect of other materials and componentsshould be reviewed. He now proposed that, apart from steel, thissymbol should in future be used only for iron castings and withinthe same restricted limits. For other materials adequate prioritycould be assured by the normal processes of allocation. He also proposed that he should have authority to revise the list of pro-grammes in respect of which the &quot; P.M.L.&quot; symbol might be used.There was general agreement with these proposals.Discussion then turned on the draft of a public announcementannexed to CP. (48) 13. It was the general view of the Cabinet thatthis should be substantially shortened and cast in simpler language.The main emphasis should be laid on the need for adapting apriority system to meet changing circumstances. Particularsuggestions were that the mention of the mild autumn weather shouldbe omitted; and that the reference to the increased importance of exports should be so phrased as to avoid the implication that theGovernment had not hitherto given a high priority to the expansionof our export trade.34848-3 b 2 -
Gas Bill.(previous reference:C.M.(47)80thConclusions,Minute 2.)3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister of fuel and Power (CP. (48) 14) covering a draft Gas Bill. The bill had been considered by the Committee on the Socialisation ofIndustries,. Many of its provisions were modelled on those of theElectricity Act, 1947.In discussion the following points were made: (a) The general scheme of the Bill was to confer on Area Boardsa high degree of independence in the running Of the gas industry,subject to the power of the Minister to give general directions andto appoint and dismiss the Boards. Might it not be said that this bill and other socialisation measures, such as the Electricity Act,would have the effect of transferring responsibility from elected localauthorities, who were closely responsible to the public using these services, to bodies which under the statute had virtual independence in their day-to-day administration ? Would it not be better if the boards, instead of deriving their powers direct from the statute,were entrusted by the Minister with such degree of responsibility ashe thought fit to delegate to them? This method, which had beenadopted in the National Health Service Act, need not lead theMinister to interfere in matters of detail; but it would avert any risk that a Board in the exercise of its statutory rights might refuseto act in accordance with Government policy.In reply it was pointed out that the power of the Minister toappoint and dismiss the members of the Boards, his power to give general directions, and the natural tendency of the Boards to seekhis advice should in practice be sufficient to ensure that the Boardsconformed to general Government policy. If the powers of the boards were derived from the Minister he would be responsible toParliament for all their actions. If that were desired, the propermethod of securing it was to assume responsibility for directadministration by a Government Department, on the Post Officemodel. There might have been advantages in adopting this methodof direct administration for electricity or for gas; but the Govern-ment had preferred the method of indirect control by public boards.The general view of the Cabinet was in favour of retaining the structure of control proposed in the Bill. It was agreed, however,that the working of the various schemes of socialisation should bekept under review and that the Government should be prepared to contemplate, in the light of experience, variations in the pattern ofsocialisation adopted in the measures hitherto passed.(b) Was it desirable that Area Boards should be empoweredto promote and oppose Bills in Parliament? Under the Bill as drafted an Area Board might, without the consent of the Minister,Oppose a Bill promoted by an Area Electricity Board with the con-sent of the Minister.It was pointed out that if the Area Boards were not given powerto promote private Bills, the Minister would be obliged to introduce a series of minor Bills on their behalf. There were also advantages in enabling the Boards to oppose Bills without the Ministers con-The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the &quot; P.M.L.&quot; symbol should in future apply only to steel and iron castings.(2) Authorised the Chancellor of the Exchequer to revise fromtime to time, in the light of changing circumstances, the list of the programmes in respect of which  the&quot; P.M.L.&quot; symbol might be used.(3) Agreed that no change should be made in the existing arrangements of the Ministry of Labour for operatingpreferences in labour supply.(4) Took note that the Chancellor of the Exchequer wouldrevise, in the light of the Cabinefs discussion, the draft announcement annexed to CP. (48) 13.
sent, since the Minister would otherwise be involved in every, conflict between an Area Board and the promoter of a private Bill. It was true that Government Departments submitted observations on private Bills, but there was a difference between submitting observa-tions on a Bill and formally opposing it. Moreover, the subject matter of private Bills was such that the likelihood of a Gas area board opposing a Bill promoted by an Electricity Area board was small.(c) The Minister of Fuel and Power had originally agreed withthe Secretary of State for Scotland that they should jointly appoint the Scottish Gas Board and the Scottish Gas Consultative Council.The Committee on the Socialisation of Industries had, however,recommended that the Bill should provide that the Minister should appoint these bodies after consultation with the Secretary of Statefor Scotland.The Cabinet agreed that a provision for joint appointmentwould be inappropriate, since the two Ministers were not jointlyresponsible for the control of the gas industry in Scotland. On theother hand, apart from the exceptional cases of consultation withthe Treasury on financial matters and with the Lord Chancellor onquasi-judicial appointments, statutory provisions requiring oneMinister to consult another were to be avoided as inconsistent withthe doctrine of collective responsibility. It was therefore agreedthat the Minister should resist any proposal to provide in the Billeither for joint appointment or for consultation with the Secretaryof State for Scotland, and should urge Parliament to rest content with his assurance that he would consult the Secretary of State forScotland about the appointment of the Scottish Area Board and theScottish Consultative Council.(d) In both the Transport Act and the Electricity Act provisionhad been made for compensating employees of transport and electricity undertakings for worsening of their conditions of employ-ment. This had been done because existing legislation already pro-vided that such employees might be compensated on this ground.The employees of gas undertakings were not at present entitled to compensation for worsening of conditions of employment, but theMinister of Fuel and Power was satisfied that there would be strong opposition from the trade unions unless the Gas Bill included pro-visions for such compensation corresponding to those in theTransport and Electricity Acts. It was pointed out that if the rightto compensation for worsening of conditions were granted on this account to employees of gas undertakings who had not enjoyed this right under earlier legislation, there would be no logical case for refusing it to ether groups affected by socialisation and similar measures, e.g., miners and local government employees. In con-ditions of full employment the grant of such compensation could notbe justified on merits and, although it had been impossible to avoidcontinuing the existing rights of railway and electricity workers, itwould be most undesirable to extend these rights to other workers.The Minister of Fuel and Power should therefore resist the claims of the gas industry trade unions, and there would be no objectionto his informing the Fuel and Power Advisory Council of the TradesUnion Congress on the following day that he intended to take this line.(e) The Cabinet agreed that the Gas Bill should provide forthe payment of a total sum of  2 million by way of compensation to local authorities in respect of severance. The corresponding provision in respect of the Electricity Act was for a payment of 5 million.(D No provision had been included in the Electricity Act toprevent local authorities from dissipating their assets before the vesting date either by granting rebates or by failing to increase their charges, and some local authorities were taking advantage of this.The Minister was considering, in consultation with the Chancellorof the Exchequer, whether anything could be done to remedy theposition by an order under the Defence Regulations, and he/
suggested-that meanwhile Ministers should defer considering thei Hi question whether any provision should be included in the Gas Billto prevent the dissipation of assets.iff) The provisions in the Bill relating to the constitution of;: , Area Boards did not bind the Minister to appoint either full-time or part-time members.  It was his present intention that only the/  Chairman and the Deputy Chairman should: be full-time members and that the Boards should not be constituted on a functional basis,- but he would make it clear that he was free to alter the constitutionof the Boards at a later date in the light of experience.The Cabinet-Gave general approval to the draft Gas Bill annexed to cp. (48) 14 and invited the Minister of Fuel and Powerto submit the draft for detailed examination by theLegislation Committee.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,13th January, 1948
Cabinet Office, S. W. 1,13th January, 1948suggested that meanwhile Ministers should defer considering thequestion whether any provision should be included in the Gas Billto prevent the dissipation of assets.(gy The provisions in the Bill relating to the constitution of area Boards did not bind the Minister to appoint either full-time or part-time members. It was his present intention that only theChairman and the Deputy Chairman should be full-time members and that the Boards should not be constituted on a functional basis,but he would make it clear that he was free to alter the constitutionof the Boards at a later date in the light of experience.The Cabinet-Gave general approval to the draft Gas Bill annexed to cp. (48) 14 and invited the Minister of Fuel and Powerto submit the draft for detailed examination by theLegislation Committee.


</content>
</cab>
