<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/12/0 images: 119-126</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1948SECRET Copy No. 44CM. (48)16th conclusions cabinet 16 (48)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, 23rd February, 1948, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Chancellor of theExchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. J. Chtjter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. A. Woodburn, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P.. Minister of Education.i The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.I The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.II The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Secretary of State for Com-commonwealth Relations., The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.! The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Item 3).The Right Hon. G. R. Strauss, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Items 3-4).The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food (Item 3).The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Minister of Fuel and Power(Item 3).The Right Hon. C. W. Key, M.P.Minister of Works (Items 3-4).Secretariat :Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. S. E. V. Luke.35039-4bTHIS   DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY  OF  HIS  BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENT
IIS   DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY  OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1948SECRET Copy No. 44CM. (48)16th conclusions cabinet 16 (48)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, 23rd February, 1948, at 11 a.m.Present :The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Chancellor of theExchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon A. Woodburn, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Secretary of State for Com-commonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Item 3).The Right Hon. G. R. Strauss, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Items 3-4).The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food (Item 3).The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Minister of Fuel and Power(Item 3).The Right Hon. C. W. Key, M.P.,Minister of Works (Items 3-4).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. S. E. V. Luke.35039-4b
CABINET 16 (48)contents minute no.                                     Subject. page 1      Palestine       ....      ........      ....      ....      ........      ill      Foreign Policy in Europe   ....................      Ill3      Economic Survey for 1948 ....      ....      ............      1124      Housing Programme in, 1948 and 1949    ....      ........      113
1. Reference was made to the explosion in the Jewish quarterof Jerusalem on the previous day, in which fifty Jews were reportedto have been killed and seventy injured. Ministers expressed concern at the failure of the Palestine Government to issue a morecategorical denial of the allegation that British troops were responsible for this outrage.Later in the meeting the Cabinet were informed that, as no official reports had yet been received, the Colonial Office had tele-phoned to Jerusalem and ascertained that no more was yet knownthan had appeared in the British press. The Palestine Governmenthad already issued a statement that it was unbelievable that Britishtroops could have been responsible for the outrage and that a thorough enquiry was in progress. They had not felt that any firmerdenial could be issued until the enquiry was completed, which mightnot be for some days. Public feeling in Jerusalem was very strong and it had become necessary to withdraw British policemen fromisolated posts.A statement about the incident would be made in the House ofCommons that afternoon, in reply to a Private Notice Question.The Cabinet-Took note of the position.2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (48) 57) describing the international and inter-departmental machinery through which he proposed to work in furthering the project for a Western Union.The Foreign Secretary said that for economic questions he proposed, in order to avoid duplication, to work through the existing machinery which had been established for the purposes of theEuropean Recovery Programme. It might prove possible, within that machinery, to evolve special arrangements for closer consulta-tion between the Western European Powers, and he would keep theCabinet informed of anjr such developments. On the political side,he would continue to keep in close touch with the Minister of defence and the Chiefs of Staff, and he would submit periodical progressreports to the Cabinet. On social questions he suggested theappointment of an interdepartmental committee of officials toconsider the possibility of assimilating the standards of the social services in the countries participating in a Western Union.The following points were raised in discussion : (a) The international organisation established for the purposesof the European Recovery Programme made no special provisionfor concerting a common financial policy in Europe. The financial stability of Western Europe was at present threatened by Belgium&apos;sinability to draw from her European creditors the means of meetingher obligations to North America. It was this situation which hadbeen leading Belgium to draw substantial amounts of gold fromthis country under the gold clause of the Anglo-Belgium Agreement;and we could not afford to allow that drain to continue. TheGovernments of the United Kingdom, France, Belgium, holland and Italy had a strong incentive to concert a common financial policy to overcome this difficulty. Representatives of these governments were to meet in London shortly. From their discussions there mightemerge some proposals for machinery for continuing consultation between Western European countries on financial questions.(b) There were indications that the United States government now favoured an early meeting of. the Committee of european economic Co-operation, though they had deprecated an earliersuggestion that the committee should meet while Congress was con-sidering the European Co-operation Bill. It was not clear whatbusiness the committee should transact&apos; at this stage; and theForeign Secretary was taking steps to ascertain more precisely whatthe United States Government had in mind.35039-4 B 2Palestine.(previous reference:CM. (48) 12thConclusions,Minute 1.)ForeignPolicy InEurope.(previous reference:CM. (48) 13thConclusions,Minute 5.)
4- rEconomic 3.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the ChancellorSurvey for 0f the Exchequer (CP. (48) 44) covering the draft of the Economic1948. Survey for 194.8.  They also had before them a memorandum by the(Previous Minister of Labour (CP. (48) 60) commenting on certain passages in reference:       the draft.CM. (48) 14th Ministers first considered what production targets should be conclusions,    published for coal and textiles.Minute 2.) The draft Survey assumed that the coal -production target for1948 would remain at 211 million tons, which was the figure givento the Committee of European Economic Co-operation at the paris conference in 1947. The Economic Planning Board had, however,suggested that in the light of recent developments the target couldbe raised to 220 million tons. The Minister of Fuel and Powerpointed out that a target of even 211 million tons assumed a marked improvement over the rate of increase attained in recent years. TheNational Coal Board were not in fact prepared to endorse any estimate for deep-mined coal in excess of 202 million tons. In his view 220 million tons would not be a realistic target, though hethought it should be possible for the industry to reach 215 million tons. It was important to avoid setting a target which the minerswould regard as unreasonable or unattainable; and there was a risk that a target of 220 million tons might have a discouraging effecton the miners and provoke demands for further wage and otherconcessions. We had given an assurance at the Paris conference that a substantial proportion of any output above 211 million tons would be made available to the countries receiving Marshall Aid,and the raising of the target to 220 million tons would create11 expectations which might in the event be disappointed, and wouldin the meantime tie our hands in bilateral negotiations. He there-fore recommended that the target of 211 million tons should beretained in the Survey. The amount allocated for export andbunkers could, however, be increased from 15 to 18 million tons, theadditional 3 million tons being found, if necessary, by reducingUnited Kingdom consumption by 1 million tons and stocks by million tons. This would mean that there, could be no relaxation of the restrictions on domestic consumption, save bv allowing a deficiency in supplies for one fuel period to be carried forward tothe next.In favour of the higher target it was argued that the years 1946and 1947 were abnormal on account of demobilisation and severe(c) An attempt was being made to convene an early meeting ofthe Man-Power Committee of the Economic Commission for Europe.Was it desired that the Ministry of Labour should send a repre-sentative to that meeting? The Foreign Secretary undertook toadvise the Minister of Labour on this point.(d) There was general support for the suggestion that someenquiry should be made into the relative standards of the social services in Western European countries. The Standard of these services was higher in the United Kingdom than in any other european country, and account should be taken of that in any com-parison of production costs. Apart from this, there was theconsideration that full mobility of labour between the various countries of Western Europe could not be achieved until there was something like uniformity in the social services throughout the area.The Cabinet (1) Took note with approval of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s inten-tion to use existing international and interdepartmentalmachinery for furthering the economic aspects of the project for a Western Union.(2) Invited the Prime Minister to arrange for the appointmentof an interdepartmental committee of officials toconsider the possibility of securing a uniform standardof social services in countries participating in a western union.
weather conditions, and it was reasonable to assume that output in1948 could be increased at a substantially higher rate than had hitherto been attained. A target should be designed to stimulateeffort, and something more than 211 million tons was required onthat basis.The Cabinefs conclusion was that the balance of the argumentswas against raising the target for the year above 211 million tons.It was, however, suggested that it would give the miners a betterincentive to individual effort if the annual output target could be expressed in terms of a weekly rate; and it was agreed that some indication might be given in the Survey of the weekly rate of outputof deep-mined coal required in order to attain the target for theyear. It would not be advisable to amend paragraph 140 of the survey to take account of the increased allocation for exportsuggested by the Minister of Fuel and Power.On the textiles production target for 1948 it was suggestedthat, even if immediate steps were taken to restrict the expansion ofother industries in Lancashire and to start cotton production inother areas, it would be very difficult to raise the labour force of thecotton industry to 325,000 by the end of 1948. Moreover, until therehad been time to train new entrants, the industry could not beexpected to attain a level of output commensurate with a labour force of this size. The view of the Cabinet was, however, thatthere should be no reduction in the man-power target given in thedraft Survey. The most profitable way of expanding the industry might be to start production in new areas, such as Liverpool, and attention should be turned to positive measures of this kind ratherthan the negative method of restricting the expansion of otherindustries in Lancashire. The production target for cotton givenin the Survey should correspond with the man-power figure, thoughit might be preferable to express it as a weekly rate of output to be attained by the end of 1948, rather than a total output for the year.The Cabinet next discussed the form of the draft Survey. Itwas pointed out that the Government had recently issued a numberof important statements on the economic situation. Good progress had been made in educating public opinion in economic matters,but the capacity of Parliament and public might be over-taxed if too many long documents were issued at short intervals. The draftwould gain in clarity, and would be more acceptable, if it could be substantially reduced in length and rewritten in less technicallanguage. In further discussion various specific suggestions for amendment of the draft were made and noted.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrange for thedraft Economic Survey to be revised in the light of their discussion;(2) Subject to (1), approved the early publication of the Survey.4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (CP. (48) 56) proposing that anadditional 60,000 standards of timber should be allocated to housingduring 1948 in order to enable a further 30,000 permanent houses tobe started in that year. The memorandum recalled that on20th October the Cabinet had decided that the amount of timber tobe made available for housing in 1948 should be 230,000 standards,i.e., enough to maintain the output of houses at the level of 140,000a year to which it had been agreed to reduce the housing programme by mid-1949. Since this decision had been taken, however, houseshad been completed at a more rapid rate than had been expected and,unless more houses were started in 1948, it would be impossible tomaintain output at the rate of 140,000 houses a year in 1949. Onthe other hand, if 30,000 additional houses were started in 1948, theoutput of houses could continue throughout 1949 at the rate of180,000 to 200,000 a year. To make this additional timber availablewould mean a departure from the policy of not making any further
inroads on stocks in anticipation of Marshall Aid; but, unlhousing output continued at the higher level, there would be embarrassing surplus of bricks and other building materials a heavy unemployment among building craftsmen in certain areThe situation would in any event have to be reviewed when tprospects of Marshall Aid were clearer.In discussion it was suggested that it would be anomalousrelax the restrictions on housing, which had been imposed as part the policy of curtailing capital investment, without making alconcession to the claims of other forms of building.  It had alreaibeen agreed that licences for building maintenance work shouldissued more freely, but the programme for the expansion of homproduced food supplies would be helped if more new building iagricultural purposes could be approved; and the Investment Pigrammes Committee had found that in practice the resounavailable for industrial building made it impossible to start buildiiany new factories, even those which would make a valuable contibution to exports or to import saving. The shortage of constructioisteel would prevent any increase in the rate of factory buildingmodern methods; but the need for new factories was so great ththere ought to be an immediate investigation to determine whetisome new factories could be started if more use were made of briaand timber, either in factory construction or in the construction!other buildings (e.g. schools) which competed for steel supplies.!The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposal to allocate an additional 60,0standards of timber for housing in 1948 in orderenable a further 30,000 permanent houses to be startin that year, on the understanding that there woulda further review of the size of the housing program!in June 1948, when the effect of Marshall Aid on tinvestment programme could be judged more clearly.(2) invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrange for tProduction Committee to consider to what extent tirestrictions imposed on forms of building other thlhousing as part of the curtailment of capital investmefshould be relaxed.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,23rd February, 1948.


</content>
</cab>
