<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/7/56 images: 546-555</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY-S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  June 1940.SECEET.Copy- No.W.M. (40)161st Conclusions.TO BE KEPT- UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 161 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Tuesday, June 11, 1940, at 12-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for War(Items 1-6).The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Viscount Caldecote,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent TJnder-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.N.General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff (Items 1-6).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, R.E.Group Captain W. Elliot.Mr. E. P. Donaldson.Mr. G. N. Flemming.[21399]b
WAR CABINET 161 (40).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Supreme War Council        ...      ...      ...      ...       ...     417Suggestion for an early meeting.2      The United States of America      ............     417President roosevelt&apos;s broadcast.3      The Air Situation    ...................    4184      The Western Front..................     418Operations on the French coasts.5      The Naval Situation..................     419North Sea.Italian ships.Announcement of the loss of H.M.S. Glorious.6      Enemy Aliens  ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     419Action with regard to Italians.General internment policy.7      Egypt   ........................     420Question of declaration of war on Italy.8      Turkey.........      ...............     420Action in consequence of the Italian declaration of war.9      Spain and Portugal   ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       ...     421Suggested simultaneous declaration of neutrality.
Supreme WarCouncil.Suggestion foran early meeting.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 160thConclusions,Minute 7.)1. The Prime Minister said that M. Reynaud had at firstrather discouraged the suggestion of an early meeting. The reasonhad perhaps been that he had been visiting the front. A secondtelegram had then been sent suggesting that the meeting should beheld at G.Q.G., and this had now been agreed to. The meeting had therefore been fixed for 6 p.m. that evening.The Prime Minister said that he might well have to remain in france for more than one day, since there were a large number of matters which would have to be discussed with the French. Weshould have to concert with them a grand strategic plan for thefuture conduct of the war and to find out what their intentions were.The despatch of additional forces to France, and their destination,would have to be examined. It seemed as if the French would beprepared to fight on in the more difficult country to the south of paris if they were driven right back. He would, of course, give them every encouragement to continue the struggle and discourageany signs of a movement towards making a separate peace. Hewould impress on them that if they could keep going, and thusprevent the enemy achieving the quick decision which he required,we should hold out, even if the whole resources of the enemy wereturned on to the United Kingdom.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew attention toa report, dated the 4th June, of a statement by a Military Attacheof one of the northern Powers at Berlin to the effect that the GermanGeneral Staff were not at all happy about the progress of the war.They had come to the conclusion that the Allies would, not accept anearly peace, and feared that the United States would join in against them. The people of Germany were apathetic at the victories of theGerman Army and were alarmed at the prospect of a long war.The Foreign Secretary also drew attention to telegram No. 380DIPP from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Paris, dated the10th. June, to the effect that he was leaving Paris much more satisfied with the general situation than he had thought might be the case.French morale was now everywhere good, and there seemed a generaldetermination to fight to a finish.A short discussion followed on the guidance which should begiven to the Press as to the reason for the Prime Ministers absence from the House of Commons in the afternoon, which would certainly be noticed.The War Cabinet-Invited the Lord Privy Seal to make a statement in theHouse of Commons in place of the Prime Minister as toItaly&apos;s entry into the war, in the course of which he should explain the Prime Ministers absence by saying that hewas naturally closely engaged in urgent business with theService Ministers.The UnitedStates ofAmerica.president roosevelt&apos;broadcast.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 159thConclusions,Minute 8.)2. The Prime Minister said that he felt sure that his colleagues had welcomed the tone of President Roosevelt&apos;s broadcast theprevious night. He read out a draft personal message which he proposed to send to the President.The War Cabinet expressed their warm approval of theterms of the message.[21399]b 2
The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 160thConclusions,Minute 2.)3. The Chief of the Air Staff said that visibility had beenvery bad over France on the previous day and no air fighting hadtaken place.One enemy aircraft had been plotted passing over the UnitedKingdom on the previous night, the probable destination of whichhad been Ireland.  No plot had been made of its returning.Forty-four sorties had been made by day bombers, most of which attacked the approaches to the Seine between Rouen and LesAndelys. Good results had been obtained, and all the aircraft had returned safely.One hundred and eight heavy bombers had been operatingduring the night, all of which except one had returned safely.Attacks had been made on enemy concentrations in the area betweenRouen and Amiens, communications at Soissons, Laon and La Fereand further in rear, and also on an oil refinery in Dusseldorf and coke ovens at Aa,chen. Operations had been to some extent interfered with by bad weather.Five aircraft had carried out mine-laying in the Flensburg area.Details were given of proposed operations by the Royal AirForce, a record of which is contained in the Secretary&apos;s standard file of War Cabinet Conclusions.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.The western front.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 160thConclusions,Minute 3.)Operations onthe Frenchcoasts.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 160thConclusions,Minute 1.)4. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that his general impression was that the French were fighting well on themain battle-front, where the German advance had been much slower than might have been expected from the weight of attack which theyhad thrown into it. Owing to the move of G.Q.G., information asto what was happening on this part of the front was, however, scant.The French were holding a line from Villers-Cotterets along theRiver our a to Oulchy, and thence North of Rheims to the Aisne.They had been heavily attacked on the our a.Westwards, on the British front, some German infantryelements had succeeded in crossing the River Seine in the Rouenarea, where, however, they were in contact with one of the Brigadesof the Beauman Division. The British Armoured Division was alsoin this area, and General Eastwood was being sent to General de laLaurencie to settle points about its co-operation with the french forces. The 52nd Division would be assembling South of the Seine,and General Weygand had been informed accordingly.North of the Seine a certain confusion had arisen about theorders for retirement. Light German Armoured forces had succeeded in reaching Fecamp, and there was a danger that part ofthe 51st Division might be hemmed on to the coast. If this happenedit would be necessary for units which did not succeed in reachingHavre to be evacuated from beaches. The two French Divisions inthis area were reported to be in a state of disintegration. TheFrench 9th Corps Commander and General Fortune had established a common Headquarters.The Chief of Naval Staff said that a Naval Liaison Officer was with the Fleadquarters of the 51st Division and that all thenecessary machinery existed for passing requests for support by naval bombardment. It was essential, however, that precise infor-mation should be given as to the targets which were to be engaged.
The naval situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 160thConclusions,Minute 1.)North Sea.Italian ships.Announcementof the loss ofH.M.S.Glorious.5. The Chief of the Naval Staff gave information as to Fleetdispositions, and as to the results of air reconnaissance. The mainfacts are recorded in the Secretary &apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.The Chief of the Naval Staff added that, although the germans had stated that both the Scharnhorst and Gneisenau had been engaged in the sinking of H.M.S. Glorious and S.S. Orama, one oftheir battle-cruisers might have left Norwegian waters andproceeded westward. This was supported by a German announce-ment that Admiral Marschall had been appointed GermanCommander-in-Chief of the Mediterranean and South Atlantic.Altogether 14 Italian ships had been seized in British ports.One of the 7 ships seized in Gibraltar had scuttled herself.The Umbria, intercepted the previous day, had sunk herselfat Port Sudan.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that, when theB.B.C. had broadcast the official announcement of the loss ofH.M.S. Glorious, the only comment had been to give the cost ofthe ship.The Minister of Information undertook to prevent a recurrence of comments of this nature.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.Enemy Aliens. 6.   The Prime Minister said that on the previous day he hadAction with instructed the Minister of Home Security to arrange for a generalregard to      &apos; internment of male Italians.Italians. The Minister of Home Security said that steps were being(Previous taken, in the first instance, to take into custody the desperateReference: characters on the special list. As soon as this had been done, stepsW.M. (40) 149th were being taken to take into custody all male Italians between theConclusions, ages of 16 and 70 who had been resident in this country less thanMinute 8.) 20 years, other than Italians on a special list furnished by theItalian Embassy, to whom special treatment would be accorded.This list comprised, in addition to the Embassy staff, persons engaged in such occupations as bank managers. This list hadbeen scrutinised by M.I. 5.It was proposed that the persons on the Embassy list shouldbe allowed to proceed to Italy on a special ship. A correspondingshipload of persons would be allowed to leave Italy.It was recalled that at an earlier stage it had been contem-plated that the 1,500 desperate characters should be deported assoon as practicable after they had been seized. It was suggestedthat in present circumstances the right course would be that weshould keep the desperate characters in internment in this country,and should deport as many as possible of the others to Italy.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs urged that thearrangements previously made with the Italian Government forreciprocal deportation should not be upset by demands that certainisolated individuals should be held in custody in this country. Itwas to our advantage to get rid of as many Italians as possible.Italy would have to feed them, and they would probably formcentres of disaffection in Italy, since many of them had no desireto return to that country. We should try to get the French tofollow the same policy.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 148thConclusions,Minute 7.)
Minute 11/General intern- The Prime Minister agreed with the policy outlined, butment policy. thought that, as a general principle, we should endeavour to round(Previous up all enemy aliens as quickly as possible, so as to place them outEeference: of harm&apos;s way, and that we should subsequently examine individualW.M. (40) 137th cases and release those who were found to be well-disposed to this conclusions,       country.The Minister of Home Security said that experience showed that, once large numbers had been collected in concentration camps,there was a serious danger that aliens, previously well-disposed tothis country, would be disaffected by contact with more dangerouscharacters. Since discharges could only be made on the pre-intern-ment record, it was essential to sort out those who could be releasedat the clearing-house stage.The Lord President of the Council said that Canada had nowundertaken to receive 4,000 internees and 3,000 prisoners-of-war.The 4,000 internees would absorb the most dangerous charactersamong the Germans (2.500) and the Italians (1,500).The War Cabinet took note of the above statements, and gave general approval to the action being taken in regardto the internment of Italians.E ypt* 7.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theQuestion of Prime Minister had suggested to him that there was something todeclaration of be said for not forcing the Egyptian Government to declare war on war on Italy. Italy so long as our own military effort was not in any way impeded.(Previous He agreed that it would be a great advantage to us it a state of warEeference:        between Egypt and Italy could be brought about by the direct actionW.M. (40) 103rd of Italy, rather than that we should seem to force it on Egypt.  he conclusions,      therefore proposed to advise His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at CairoMinute 5.)        to deal with the Egyptian Government on these lines, always on theunderstanding that our military, naval and air operations wouldbe in no way hampered.   Egypt must not, of course, declare her neutrality, but might adopt the status of a non-belligerent ally.The Prime Minister suggested that it might also be desirableto accede to the wish of the Egyptian Government that Cairo shouldbe declared an open town. If the Italians were, nevertheless, to bomb it, then we should be entitled to bomb Rome. It was important that anti-aircraft guns manned by Egyptians and required for thedefence of the fleet at Alexandria should not be moved to Cairo.The Foreign Secretary said that there were probably some british troops accommodated in the citadel at Cairo, but it might perhaps be possible to find quarters for them outside Cairo.The War Cabinet Agreed that the Foreign Secretary should communicate with His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Cairo on the lines indicated above.Turkey.Action in conse-quence of theItaliandeclaration of8. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he had sent a telegram the previous evening (No. 426) to His Majesty&apos;ambassador at Angora asking him to inform the Turkish Govern-ment immediately of the message received in regard to the state ofwar between Italy on the one hand and the United Kingdom andFrance on the other. Our Ambassador was to enquire if the TurkishGovernment were ready to take action in accordance with the termsof their treaty with us, i.e., to give us all possible assistance under
9 *y ^Spain and portugal.Suggestedsimultaneousdeclaration of neutrality.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 160thConclusions,Minute 9.)9. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that thePortuguese Ambassador had called on him the previous day on theinstructions of his Government, and had suggested that they should try to persuade the Spanish Government to join with them inmaking a simultaneous declaration of neutrality. He (the foreign secretary) had replied that such a joint declaration would, in hisopinion, be valuable, on the assumption that, in the case of Portugal,this neutrality would be interpreted in a manner benevolent to us as her ally; but that a declaration of neutrality by Portugal alone would be contrary to British interests. The Portuguese Govern-ment would accordingly be raising the matter in Madrid at once.He had received a number of letters from Sir Samuel Hoarereporting that there was a very strained atmosphere in Madrid, andmany mysterious events going on. He was, however, still in goodheart.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,June 11, 1940.the arrangements already made. No answer had yet been received.If the Turkish Government had been tempted to draw some distinc-tion between the declaration of war and a definite hostile act, therewas now no excuse for further delay, in view of the Italian air attack on Malta^The War Cabinet took note of this statement.




</content>
</cab>
