<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/9/11 images: 70-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.  January 1941.SECBET. . .. Copy No.   59W.P. (G) (41) 11.January 23, 1941.WAR CABINET.ROYAL AIR FORCE BENEVOLENT FUND.Memorandum by the Minister of Aircraft Production.I HAVE read with some surprise the case stated* by the Chancellor of theExchequer against my proposal t that he be instructed to make a payment of 1 million to the R.A.F. Benevolent Fund.I cannot attach any weight to the argument that such a payment would bean admission of the inadequacy of State pensions schemes. The inadequacy ofthese schemes is proved by the existence of the Fund, not by any addition to it.Nor am I impressed by the contention that the payment would involvepreferential treatment for one Service. The public at home and abroad has sent 10 million to this Ministry with the specific intention of singling out the R.A.F.as the object of their generosity.They have done so in recognition of the truth stated by the Prime Minister,&quot; Never .... was so much owed by so many to so few.&quot;They gave the money in the belief that this particular Service did deservebetter treatment than others. And it would be wrong to defeat that motive of grattitude.I am not convinced by the statement that the Exchequer has received &quot; far greater gifts &quot; than this Ministry. So far as my knowledge goes, more than three-quarters of the sum received in gifts by the Exchequer come from Govern -ments. These &apos;&apos; gifts &apos;&apos; are really grants-in-aid. But the great bulk of the moneywe receive comes from private donors.As for the King&apos;s Fund, that is a comparatively trifling affair. In my view it has no bearing on this issue.I renew my proposal that the Cabinet should act in accordance with thespirit of those who have sent  10 million to the R.A.F. through the Ministryof Aircraft Production.B.Ministry of Aircraft Production,January 23, 1941.* W.M. (41) 2nd Conclusions, Minute 6. f W.P. (G) (41) 2.[22145]


</content>
</cab>
