<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/88/0 images: 40-57</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[Tins Document m the Property of His Britannic MaQesty&apos;s Government]     printed for the War Cabinet,   September 1919. -     iSECRET1. AS a result of the war the Allies have established a new Austria German-Austria as an independent political unit. This new Austria, as mapped out to-day, is unable to stand alone, for she is devoid of all resources natural, financial, and otherwise  to feed herself or, to supply opportunities of work wherewith eventually to pay for food. Though on the brink of bankruptcy, her immediate needs are such that she must be assisted from without. The new States by which she is partly surrounded, and which formed parts of the late Austrian Empire, are hostile arid disinclined to assist Or co-operate with her, though all these countries were interdependent while tbey formed parts of the Austrian Empire.2. Help from &quot;without therefore means help either from the Allies or from Germany. The Allies have prohibited the fusion of German-Austria with Germany. This prohibi-tion, if maintained, throws, under the prevailing circumstances, upon the Allies the moral obligation to provide ways and means to enable German-Austria to survive her present crisis.3. The majority of the Austrian people do not desire the fusion with Germany as long as there is any hope at all of assistance by the Allies. The present plight of the people is already terrible ; every day intensifies their distress. Mortality and disease have assumed alarming proportions. The want of food is little short of a real famine  at least in Vienna. Yet the Austrians are waiting patiently for,the word of deliverance to be pronounced by the Allies. So far there is no indication whether the Allies are really willing to help Austria. Their willingness must depend upon their own financial resources.4. The question whether they are financially able to help has never been examined in the light of the consequences which might ensue if such assistance were denied. This question must be seriously tackled without further delay. The rapidly increasing-demoralisation of the working classes in Austria, the sufferings of the people, the propaganda of our enemies, and of the Social Democrats, the weakness of the Austrian Government are preparing the ground for the worst social disorders. Under the circumstances the Allies&apos; policy of drift constitutes a terrible danger. The present indecision on the part of the Allies may become responsible for a reign of terror which could easily spread beyond the borders of Austria. If the Allies are prepared to assist Austria, they must face the problem wholeheartedly and without delay ; if the Allies are not prepared to assist they can escape grave responsibility only by openly admitting their inability and releasing Austria from the prohibition to unite with Germany. The consequences of a refusal to help would in the end prove less harmful to Europe as a whole than the continuance of the present state of indecision.! 5. There can be little doubt that on political grounds an Austrian fusion with Germany should be prevented; the great political dangers resulting from such a fusion have been set out elsewhere (see Paris memorandum of 3rd June).   They are shortly ,  . these: If Germany unites with Austria, this fusion will give a great impetus and opportunity to German expansion towards the Near East; the fusion will also lead to a H    German-Italian block dividing the European continent, thus isolating France from possible Eastern Allies, in case of a conflict between France and Italy ; the fusion also prepares the isolation and destruction of Czecho-Slovakia, which Italy is anxious to crush.   These arguments should weigh heavily when the question is being considered whether the Allies should make a special effort to assist Austria, and thus prevent her drifting into the arms of Germany.   No doubt many vast schemes of reconstruction [777] &quot; B
have to be considered demanding enormous grants of credits. They must be judged on their relative merits, as funds will hardly be available to entertain even all the most important. Yet I submit that from a political point of view there can be few with a claim as serious as that of Austria.The political arguments referred to above are supported by arguments of an economic and a sentimental kind.The economic measures which would have to be undertaken with the assistance of the Allies, and more especially the British Government, to set up an Austria capable of surviving the present crisis would prove excellent investments, increasing the future tax-paying capacity of this country. The various schemes offer every temptation of considerable profits, quite apart from the lar^e profits due to the present rate of exchange. Some of the most important will be shortly referred to later on. It can hardly be in the interest of the Allies to allow these plums to fall into the lap of our enemies.Little need be said with reference to the sentimental arguments in favour of an Allied assistance. There is much that is worth saving in Austria and among the Austrian people. Austria is one of the oldest surviving centres of European culture; its people have a refined individual character, all of which would become lost once Austria had disappeared into the German melting-pot or become a prey to Bolshevism.6. I am fully alive to the difficulties which beset any enquiry such as is immediately needed, especially if the enquiry is to be undertaken by an inter-Allied committee. As far as the fate of Austria.is concerned, there appears to be less harmony nnong the Allies than might be expected. The French have vast vested interests in Austria and they would, I think, enter sympathetically upon such,an enquiry, though any financial aid will in the end depend upon their own financial situation. The Italians are openly hostile, as they desire to see; Austria crushed beyond recovery; the Americans have shown a marked desinteressement in Austrian affairs, because the country is poor and devoid of any reserves of gold. Yet I think the conscience of the American people &apos;COuld be routed if they knew the whole truth of the present situation in Austria. American financiers might in any case be induced to participate in some of the -enterprises needed to help Austria, as they constitute commercially tempting propositions.7. I think that the enquiry should be undertaken immediately even if it had to be undertaken by us alone. The British are at present by far the most popular &quot; foreigners &quot; in Austria. Austrian hopes are focussed upon us rather than upon any other people; we could secure more favourable terms than the other Allies. On the other hand, any failure to either come to a favourable or any decision at all would in the eyes of the Austrians saddle us with greater responsibilities than any of the Allies. If it be decided, after weighing all arguments, that Ave cannot render the necessary assistance, and the consequence of this decision become apparent, His Majesty&apos;s Government should be protected by the finding of a committee which must consist of our best experts upon the matters at issue. If these experts did arrive at an adverse decision, then we must boldly face the fact and decline any further responsibility by withdrawing from the prohibition against a fusion between Germany and German-Austria. In no other way could we hope to escape the serious indictment of history.In view of the urgency of the enquiry, in view also of the very probable disagree-ment among all the Allies, I think it would be advisable that His Majesty&apos;s Government take the matter in hand immediately, appointing the lew first-class experts needed, and inviting the other Allies to join this committee (Committee A), if they desire. The peace negotiations at present proceeding in Paris between the Allied Delegates and the Austrians should not delay the deliberations of this committee. The peace negotiations are likely to occupy some lime owing to the very complicated questions involved. Whatever the result of these negotiations, the fundamental question will still have to be solved : Can we save Austria or can we not save her ? If we can save her, preliminary work could be done upon the finding of the Committee A so that we be ready for more complete action immediately peace is signed. If the matter is further delayed we may find that when a favourable decision by the committee is eventually-presented there is nothing left to save.Some further Recommendations.8. When the possibility of any assistance in saving Austria is being considered, I think some difference should be made between any assistance needed immediately to
save Austria^ very existence, and any assistance which would prevent a fusion with Germany, even in the more distant future. If the first can be solved, I think the second will become comparatively easy. * The latter would greatly depend upon the course of events in the other mats successeurs the other heirs of the late Austrian Empire. They can be led by gentle but firm pressure brought to bear by the Allies, upon whose goodwill they must all rely in working out their own individual salvation.9. Among the most urgent questions which would have to be considered are, I think, the following, upon which some data have already been collected. The reports annexed to this memorandum were prepared by experts during my recent visit to Vienna.: (a.) Loans for foodstuffs. So far credits amounting to 45,000,000 dollars have already been sanctioned by the British, French, and Italian Governments against certain guarantees. The guarantees are likely far to exceed this amount of 45,000,000 dollars. See report annexed (Appendix I) drawn up by the British, French, and Italian delegates appointed for the purpose of enquiring into any available securities to guarantee repayment of the loan.(b.) The future requirements of foodstuffs by Austria are set out in Appendix II, drawn up by Secretary of State Lowenfeld Russ, the Austrian Food Controller. No accurate indications can be given as to the amount of credits still required for the purpose of these further food supplies, as no one can foretell the price of the foodstuffs in question. Much will also depend upon the fact whether at least part of these foodstuffs can be secured from the neighbouring countries instead of being supplied from overseas. In any case it is certain that the coming Austrian harvest will not suffice to supply the food needed for the population of German-Austria.(c.) Loans for raw materials. The most urgent needs of raw materials are set out iu Appendix III.(d.) A special memorandum&apos;-deals with the question of the supply of coal (Appendix IV). It is hoped that eventually the necessary imports of coal can be greatly reduced by the &quot; electrification &quot; of the large water ,power available. The building of these power stations constitutes one of the most urgent and most attractive possibilities in the revival of Austrian industries.(e.) A loan for the establishment of a new note-issuing bank. British capital would, it is to be hoped, either participate in the establishment of this bank or in the alternative acquire the whole concession. See memorandum prepared by Dr. Landesberger, the chief economic expert delegated to Paris by the Austrian Government (Appendix V).(/.) A statement prepared by two of the leading experts setting out the hopes entertained from a revival of the industries situaie within German-Austria (Appendix VI).((/.) The very important question wotild have to be investigated in how far it would be possible to preserve for&apos;Vienna the position she held before the war as the &quot;clearing-house&quot; for the various parts of the Austrian Empire. The Etats successeurs. at present seem little inclined to favour a customs union or an economic federation. Yet in time a more or less close co-operation between these various States will become unavoidable, as commerce will drift to the best and nearest markets regardless of political animosities.An appreciable step in this direction would be taken if the more important matters of traffic were centralised in Vienna Vienna should become the head office of the internationalised main railway lines as well as the inland shipping on the internationalised Danube.It would be eminently desirable that the advisability of the union of the four large Danube shipping companies (2 Austrian, 1 German, 1 Hungarian) be investigated; perhaps a scheme could be evolved for securing a predominant interest for Great Britain. The question of the Danube shipping becomes particularly important in view of the Rhine-Danube connection across the European continent, which is only a matter of time. All necessary papers and details have, 1 believe, been addressed to Lord Inchcape.(h.) If the above scheme be entertained it is recognised by the Austrians-that a very wide control of Austrian public finance would have to be conceded to
the Allies (or any one of them) participating in these schemes. Such a control, more especially by the British, would be welcomed, as it would supply a moral backbone to enterprise which is now entirely lacking. The Austrian Government without credit or army has no prestige or power. The Allies would acquire both through the supply of food, upon which all else could be made dependent. The leading Austrian financiers and officials have quite openly suggested a British control of Austrian finance on the lines of the British control in Egypt.10. To sum up: The needs of Austria are great and urgent; the question whether the necessary assistance can be granted should be examined immediately and thoroughly by a com-mittee (A) constituted by experts appointed by all the Allies or by such of them as are prepared to co-operate with us or by us alone. If as a result of such investigation it is found that the necessary assistance can be granted, either by the Allies or some of them, then a more permanent expert commission (B) should be appointed to proceed to Vienna without delay to tackle the whole difficult problem practically, to decide how the available means are to be apportioned to various purposes, what guarantees shall be accepted, what control exercised. The very presence of this commission in Vienna would be an important factor in the reconstruction of Austria. If, on the other hand, it is found that the necessary assistance cannot be granted, then His Majesty&apos;s Government should withdraw from the prohibition of the German-Austrian fusion, and Austria should then be informed without further delay that she is at liberty to work out her salvation on any lines she thinks most suitable. For if we cannot really assist Austria we should take the only step which will absolve us from any responsi-bility for whatever the consequences of our inability may be. Among all courses open to the Allies the present policy of drift is the worst possible; in my opinion it is unworthy and pernicious.(Signed) &apos;      FRANCIS OPPENHEIMER.Foreign Office, Jane 20, 1919.
APPENDIX I.Credits allowed to New Austria for Pood Purchases.Report of the Finance Section of the Supreme Economic Council. (Translation.)THE undersigned have been charged with the examination of the guarantees which the New Austrian Government could offer to cover a credit for food purchases of 45,000,000 dollars, agreed to by various Powers of the Entente.Having studied the question on the spot, they have come to the conclusion that certain guarantees could be earmarked for this purpose, taken from the following list :--1. Gold and silver currency.2. Foreign securities owned by Austro-Germans.3. State or private-owned forests.4. Salt mines.5. Real estate and buildings and municipal industrial enterprises of towns in New Austria having more than 50,000 inhabitants.As formalities and time are required to regulate and establish the said guarantees on a regular footing, Mr. Renner, Chancellor of New Austria, has agreed on behalf of his Government that they shall all be held at the Allies disposal until a choice can be definitely made among them, and that in the meanwhile German-Aufctria shall make all its revenues, of whatsoever nature, available for the redemption of this credit, on conditions to be laid down in the contract by which these credits are opened.The Supreme Council, having taken note at its meeting of the 2nd June, 1919, of Mr. Renner&apos;s letter dated the 30th May, transmitted it to the Financial Section, which accepted it and which requested the undersigned to report how the suggestions were to be carried into effect.In consequence, the undersigned have the honour to submit to the Financial Section of the Supreme Economic Council the following proposals and recommendations : With regard to the pledges comprised in Nos. 1 and 2 of Mr. Renner&apos;s letter (currency and foreign securities), the undersigned are of opinion as follows : In view of the uncertainty of the situation in New Austria, it would be advisable to ask for the immediate requisition of the currency and foreign securities in question and their delivery within the shortest possible time at the expense of the Austrian Government in a town outside its territories, to be designated by the Financial Section. As concerns gold, the coins must be specified as to kinds and weight, and be accepted at the rate of the fineness of gold on the day of delivery; and, as concerns silver, with a margin to be fixed by the Inter-Allied Commission mentioned below.The foreign securities handed over as a guarantee should be classified acc rding to issues and be accompanied by a detailed schedule. &apos; A commission to be appointed by the creditor States should accept delivery, determine the margin of guarantee for such as are accepted and hand back in the same place those which are rejected.It would be advisable to request that the mortgage on the forests, mentioned in No. 3 of Mr. Renners letter, should be established as soon as possible. The bills or other commercial documents resulting from the sale of timber abroad should be offered from a very early date to the Commission mentioned in the foregoing paragraph, which would have the power to accept or reject them. A commission of experts in forestry matters, to be appointed by the creditor Governments, should be sent immediately to Austria to supervise the proper drawing up of the mortgages, to estimate the capital value of the mortgaged forests and the rate of revenue resulting from the exportation of such timber.It does not appear desirable to proceed, until further orders, with the mortgages on the salt mines, nor on real estate and municipal enterprises mentioned in Nos. 4 and a of Mr. Renners letter, but all rights are reserved with regard to these securities until the guarantees are finally settled, as stated hereafter.The provisional guarantee in paper kronen given to the Italian mission at Innsbruck; might be released when the definite guarantee sufficient to cover deliveries of food-stuffs and incidental expenses will have been secured.J777I C
As soon as the Inter-Allied Commission outlined in Nos. 1 and 2 and the forestry -experts mentioned in No. 3 have submitted their report/the final guarantees should be drawn up.If from these reports it results that the pledges referred to in paragraphs 1, 2, and 3 are sufficient to cover the credit, the undersigned are of opinion that the pledges referred to in Nos. 4 and 5 could immediately be liberated as well as the provisional guarantee in paper kronen.If it results that the total amount of the guarantees comprised in Nos. 1, 2, and 3 is excessive, the creditor States should, in conjunction with the United States of America, invite the Government of the New Austria to put forward proposals with regard to the further use to be made of the guarantees, the liberation of some of them, -or their application towards new credits for foodstuffs or raw materials necessary for industrial purposes.The terms upon which the credit of 45,000,000 dollars is opened should immediately be settled, firstly, between the United States of America on the one hand, and France, Great Britain, and Italy on the other hand; secondly, between these three &quot;States on the one hand, and New Austria on the other hand.The undersigned are of opinion that, as this credit for foodstuffs is being opened upon humanitarian grounds, the conditions of the second contract should be applied without additions to the first contract. They are of opinion that the mortgages should be cancelled gradually at the same rate at which the credit is redeemed. They are of -opinion that in accordance with the request made by the Government of New Austria it might be provided that, in agreement with the creditor States, other guarantees may be substituted.The undersigned draw the attention of the Finance Section of the Supreme Economic Council to the fact that, as New Austria is in no way solvent, the credit for food supplies can only be covered by guarantees decided upon in agreement with the Supreme Council. In these circumstances, they ask whether it would not be advisable to request the -Government of the United States to relieve France. Great Britain, and Italy of all responsibility for any credit granted over and above the yield of the pledges when realised. This arrangement would make it possible to limit the claims against the -Governments intervening as guarantors, and would facilitate for New Austria the grant of the credits which she needs.The undersigned think it their duty to direct the attention of the Supreme Economic Council to the position of deep distress in which they found the city of Vienna, in spite of the assistance given by the Entente in furnishing food supplies. They consider that any restriction or any interruption even for a short period of this assistance must result in consequences so serious to health, human life, and social peace that their effect cannot be exaggerated.(Signed)     CHEVALIER (France).. .    F. OPPENHEIMER (Great Britain).1! ALBERTI (Italy).Paris, June 9, 1919.APPENDIX II.Statement of probable German-Austrian need of Import of the most important Foodstuffs for the period of one year. August 15,1919, to August 15,1920.[With two enclosures.-Enclosure 1 : Value of the foodstuffs imported hitherto from the Allied countries. Enclosure 2 : Value of the foodstuffs wanted in the period from May 1 to August 15, 1919.]THE territory of German-Austria is also in peace time dependent on imports, especially as regards flour and bread. The necessary quantities were supplied in peace time principally by Hungary (now partly Jugo-Slav territory). The same applies to potatoes, beans,.peas, &amp;c, and eggs which came principally from Galicia (which is now partly Ukraine, partly Polish territory). Likewise the supplies for German-Austria, 1 especially for the city of Vienna, of cattle, meat, and fat depended on the neighbouring districts, especially Hungary and Jugo-Slavia. Through the dissolution of the former monarchy the sugar supplies have ceased nearly altogether, as German-Austria has only four sugar factories and must cover the greater part of her demand by Czecho-Slovak imports.
These circumstances are further intensified by the fact that the home production in German-Austria decreased during the war, and the need of import therefore is greater than before the war.The following statement will show the need of imports : Imports of Foodstuffs probably needed for German-Austria in the period from august 15, 1919, to August 15, 1920*1. Grain (wheat and rye).-German-Austrian harvest certainly does not amount to more than 500,000 tons, minus grain fjf sowing purposes about 400,000 tons. The population of about 7,000,000 people need (daily ration 400 grammes of vflour, 488 grammes of grain) 1,265,000 tons Therefore need of imports, 850,000 tons.2. Grain (for animal stuffs). Barley, oats, maize; harvest little over 400,000 tons. Counting 1 kilog. per animal head and day, general need 1,250,000 tons Therefore need of imports, 850,000 tons.3. Grain (for industries (breweries, malt and coffee substitutes industry)).  Considering the insufficient home production the whole need of the named industries has to be imported Which amounts to, 275,000 tons.4. Potatoes  The German-Austrian harvest is estimated at about 900,000 tons ; minus sowing and feeding quantities about 500,000 tons&quot;, remaining 400,000 tons. Counting ^-kilog. per head and day the needs amounts to 1,300,000 tons.Need of imports (without industrial need), 900,000 tons.5. Beam, Peas, &amp;c. Production hardly worth mentioning. Counting l-kilog. per head and month The necessary import amounts to 34,000 tons.6. Meat. The production in cattle has decreased about 25 per cent, during the war. The present production cannot cover the need of the larger towns, especially Vienna. Import therefore )re absolutely necessary. Counting 500 grammes per head and week Need of imports amounts to 130,000 tons.7. Fat. Through lack of feeding-stuff the production of fat became extremely small in German-Austria. Counting 300 grammes per head and week and considering the small home production Need of imports, 100,000 tons.8. Sice.-Counting 1 kilog. per bead and month There must be imported, 85,000 tons.9. Condensed Milk. The lack of fresh milk is so great, that condensed milk for children and sick people especially in towns has to be imported (need per month about 1,200 tons)- &quot; ( LNeed for imports on one year, 14,000 tons.* The figures showing the need of import for&apos;German-Austria for the period of middle of August 1919 to middle of August 1920 are difficult to state exactly at the present moment, as the frontiers of German-Austria have not yet been definitely fixed. These calculations are therefore based on the territory now administrated by German-Austria, that is without Uerman-Uohemia, Southern Moravia, German South. Tyrol and Western Hungary.Further, the production of grain can only be given approximately. These productions will certainly, with regard to the still existing difficulties and partly with regard to the bad weather, be unfavourable. Therefore, the figures are based in general on figures of the latter years of the war. The fixing of the figures of the need of imports further depend on the rations per head. The population is starving and neeas higher rations. This estimate is already based on raised rations, but even these are not peace rations, as we would not be able to pay foi import attaining peace figures.The estimate for the cost of import is still more difficult to make, as the prices of the coming economical period cannot yet be fixed The present prices of merchandise have therefore usually been quoted in this estimate. As regards&apos;foodstuffs from the Allied countries, the prices in question put down at a high figure owing to our unfavourable rate of exchange.
10. Eggs, Home production (about 50 per cent, of the peace production), 200,000,000 eggs; counting one egg per head and day, we need 2,600,000,000 eggs-Therefore necessary import, 2,400,000,000 eggs.11. Sugar. There are only four sugar factories in German-Austria with a present production of 10,000 tons (compared with 38,000 tons before the war). Counting 1 kilog. per head and month we need about 160,000 tons Therefore necessary import, 150,000 tons.The necessary foodstuff can be imported either from (1) the former Austrian National States, or from (2) Allied countries.I. Imports from former Austrian National States,Some of the named articles (1 to 11) could be imported from the former Austrian National States if the Peace Treaty secures the possibility of taking up economic and commercial relations with Czecho-Slovakia, Hungary, Ukrainia, Poland, and Jugo-Slavia. There could be especially imported : grain for animal feeding .(2); barley for industrial purposes (3); potatoes (4); beans, peas, &amp;c. (10); eggs (11); and sugar (12).If these quantities of foodstuffs could be paid in German-Austrian currency, the following would show the needed amount of money.	One Year&apos;s Need.	Price per Ton.*	&apos; One Year&apos;s Cost.2. Grain for feeding animals .. 3. Barley for industrial purposes 4. Potatoes          .. 5. Beans, peas, &amp;c, 10. Eggs   .. -      ..      No. 11. Sugar ...	Tons. 850,000 275,000 900,000 34,000 2,400,000.000 150,000	Crowns. 1 000 1,500 1,200 1,000 1 (per egg) 4,000	Crowns. 850,000.000 412.500,000 1,080,000,000 34,000,000 2,400.000,000f 1)00,000,000Total amount of cost for imports from national states : 5,376,500,000 crowns.* The prices per toil are estimated approximately at the amount for which the named articles could probably be bought in the national States.f To Czecho-Slovakia we must pay in Czecho-Slovak crowns; as at present 100 Czecho-Slovafc crowns ^ 150 German-Austrian crowns, thus the amount rises to 900,000 000 Austrian crowns.So as to obtain the diminution of the enormous amount, the German-Austrian population would have to live as economically as possible. With a reduction of the need of grain imports to 200,000 tons, of the annual animal feeding grain to 500,000 tons, of potatoes to 650,000 tons, and of eggs up to 50 per cent. (1,200,000,000), the necessary amount of money for the imports from the National States of the former Austrian Empire might be reduced to about 3,450,000,000.II. Imports from the Allied Countries.The cost of foodstuff to be imported from the Allies and America may be seen out of the following table : -	One Year&apos;s Need.	Price per ton,*	Cost.1. Grain (for bread) 6. Meat (salted American pork) 7. Fat (lard, oil) 8. Rice 9. Condensed milk \..	Tons.&apos; 850,000 130,000 100,000 85,000 14,000	Lire. 1.200 5,850 5,000 1,100 3,600	Lire. 1,020,000,000 760,500,000 500,000,000 93,500,000 50,400,000Total: 2,424,400,000 lire, or (100 lire *s 11.60 dollars) 281,230,000 dollars.f* These are the prices notified by the Italian Delegation of the Inter-Allied Food Commission (in lire). Invoiced prices have not yet been stated. -t This sum is certainly over-estimated, as the present prices for foodstuffs and freight will not remain the same. These prices being based on the present rate of exchange of the lires, they are higher than the actual prices.
[777]DIt is hardly possible to judge to-day whether also grain for bread (1), meat (6), and fat (7) could be imported from the former Austrian National States instead of from oversea.The revolution and certain efforts of agricultural reform have delayed planting in Hungary and the fertile districts of Jugo-Slavia(Croatia, Banat, Bacska), and it is to be doubted whether order, within a few months until the harvest, will be established again so that the harvest can be brought in and transported.At the best I believe in the possibility of getting 200,000 tons of wheat from Hungary and Jugo-Slavia. Fat and meat we may possibly get 200,000 tons, respec-tively 50,000 tons. The need of imports from oversea would be decreased by the aforenamed quantities. It would be necessary to establish a unity of currency for the payment of foodstuff imports from the National States, as otherwise there would rise great difficulties.It would be of special importance if the western part of Hungary could be attached to German-Austria.Out of this part of Hungary we could import in the next year :-100,000 tons of grain (for bread), 60,000   ,,   ,, sugar, 9,000   ,,   ,, meat, 1,000   ,,   ,, fat,and fresh milk in considerable quantities.The import figures given in the preceding statement only regards the most important foodstuffs. There is, however, a need of import for various other articles. A very important article is alcohol, of which in peace time 122,000 hectolitres were produced in German-Austria, the production of which, however, because of the absolute lack of raw material (potatoes and molasses), has nearly ceased. Even if peace production could be again attained, the demand in German-Austria would be three times as great as the production. Therefore a need of import of at least 200,000 hectolitres would be necessary.There is, further, a need of imports for fish, as the home production is absolutely insufficient; for fruit, for fruits from the South, for chocolate, and especially for coffee and tea.As regards coffee, by fixing a monthly ration of 1 kilog. per head an annual amount of about 8,400,000 kilog. would be needed. At the present price for Brazil coffee of 2&apos;44s. c.i.f. Trieste per kilogramme, this would represent a round sum of 850,000Z.Final Remark.The reorganisation of German-Austria and the maintenance of order depends on the import of the necessary foodstuffs. The population being irritated, only the importation of sufficient food supplies, especially to the big cities and industrial centres, could prevent new revolutionary troubles, which would threaten the economic re-estah-lishment.    .
Enclosure 1.Quantities and Value of Foodstuff delivered from the Allies to German-Austria in theperiod from January 15 to May 15, 1919.Articles in Tons.		Selling Price c.i.f., Trieste or Genoa.	Value in Millions.		Crowns.	Crowns,Grain	78,178	3,000*	234-5		Lire.	Lire.Flour	57,024	1.600	91-2Meat and fat	19,011	5,000-5,850	100-5Oil     &quot;   ..	1,195	4,000 -	4-8Condensed milk	3,219	3,600	11-7Rice	9,186	1,100	10-1Beans	3,522	1,800	6-3Different   articles   (oranges,	1,600	800-1,180	1-7lemons, fish, cacao, &amp;c.)			Total value of the imported foodstuff to German-Austria in the period 15th January to 15th May, 234-5 million crowns and 227 million lire.At the rate of exchange of 100 lire = 11-60 dollars, and 100 crowns = 4-25 dollars, the total.value of imported foodstuff amounts to 36,298,500 dollars.* This price &quot;was made to Austria in crowns (200 dollars for 1 ton. 1 dollar - 6 lire, 1 lire -2-50 crowns).       . - &apos;These imports are covered by the credit of 30,000,000 dollars granted by the Inter-Allied Food Commission.At the deliberations with the Inter- Allied Food Commission the following securities were proposed : The salt mines in German-Austria, securities of the town of Vienna, &amp;c. Concrete arrangements have not yet been  made.German Austria has deposited with the Italian commander in Innsbruck as a pledge 382,000,000 crowns.Enclosure II.Necessary Foodstuft Imports to German-Austria in the period from June 1 tothe new harvest (two and a-half months).Articles in Tons.		Price per Ton.	Cost in Lire. (Millions.)		Lire.	Lire.Flour*          ..         ..    about	150.000	1.600	240Beans j        -.         ..      ji	5,500	1,800	about    10RiceJ .         ..                 ,,	13,500	1,100	,,     15Pork meat (net)S	10,500	5,850	61.5Fat, bacon, oil (net)H	17,500	4,000-5,000	70-87.5* Condensed milk	3,000	90 (per box)	about   10Total: about 407 to 424 million lire or (at an exchange 100 lire ^ 11.60 dollars) 47 to 49 million dollars* About 275 grammes per day and head, f About \ kilog. per head and month.I About 1 kilog. per head and month.5 About 250 grammes per head and week..II About 200 grammes per head and week.
Here is to be added a need of articles to be imported from the former Austrian national States.,        Articles	in Tons.	Price per Ton.	Cost in crowns. (Millions)Potatoes	100,000	About 1,500 crowns   ..        ...	150Eggs     No.	500,000,000*	Price of one piece, at least 1 crown	500Sugar	30,000	Sugar for consume.   32u &quot;1 Ozecho-			J. Slovak			Sugar for industries 540 J crowns	iibout 180 (Austrian)		Total	about 830* This number covers only a need of one egg per head and week. It is impossible to cover this need through import from the former Austrian national States.Kate of exchange: 100 Uzecho-Slovak crowns - 150 German-Austrian crowns.APPENDIX III.Summary of Imported Raw Materials needed for the Industries of German-Austria during Six Months. ,Materials.	Weight.	Remarks.Cotton ,,   tissues (unbleached) (raw)	Tons. 23,000 2,700 5,400	Requirements in cotton yarn include 300 tons tine yarns needed for tho tulle, curtain, and lace industries, as well as trimmings, which were imported before the war.   In addition the requirements of yaru-con-suming industries have been considered for two months after arrival of  raw cotton, also the requirements of the cotton tissue-consuming industries  during the three months after the arrival, of the raw cotton.Wool   .. Tops	6,200 2,500	The requirements of raw wool used be covered as to two-thirds by Australian merino and as to one-third by La Plata, merino cross-bred.   Tops&apos; were imported from Germany, France, Great Britaiu.   In German-Austria this industry employed about 5.50o workmen; there are 170,000 spindles, DO dobbies (?), and 1,070 looms.Flax   .. ,,  yarn	720 50	The German-Austrian linen industry employs &apos; approximately 340 hands on 10,000 spindles and approximately 900 hands on 300 mechanical and 200 hand looms.Silk, twisted	22	2,500 hands, 570 looms for cloth, and 1,130 looms for ribbons. -Jute Hemp ..         ..        .. ,,   yarn	4,500 4,(500 114	1,300 hands, 10,000 spindles, j 1,500 hands, 12,000 spindles.Rubber	1,500	5,000 hands.Oil seeds        ...         ;. Fatty substances..	13,500 35,700	381 establishments with 10,500 hands. The fatty subsrauces are one-third soft,.-two-thirds hard.Tanning extracts.. Box-calf leather	3,000 2,000,000	30,000 hands. The boot industry employs 20,000 hands, and 35,000 master shoemakers and fp-prentices.Copper (electrolytic) Nickel .. Tin     .. FeiTomolybdenum Ferrovanadium Wolfram          ..      ( .. Ferrowolfram Ferrochrome	3,000 50 500 15 25 20 200 150	These metals are needed for 35 concerns in the metal industry, 700 concerns in the metal using industries, also the electrical industry, and 5 steel works with about 130,000 bands in all.
APPENDIX IV.Austrian needs of Coal.Tons.The annual requirements of coal amount to ...&quot;     14,000,000And coke, 1,300,000 tons, amounting (on the basisof 100 kilog. of coke equal to 150&apos;kilog. of coal) to       2,000,000Total ... ... ...      16,000,000Coal deposits in German-Austria are practically exclusively of the lignite kind at Leoben Fohnsdorf, Voitsberg-Koflach, and Wolfsegg-Thomasroith. Their total production amounts to 1,560,000 tons, i.e.; not quite 10 per cent, of the requirements.In pre-war times coal chiefly supplied (1) from Austrian sources in territories now separated from German-Austria, viz., Ostrau-Karwin (mineral coal) and North-East Bohemia (lignite); (2) from Germany (Upper Silesia, Lower Silesia, Westphalia, and Sarre district).The imports from Germany amounted to: From Silesia... WestphaliaTons.3,500,000-4,000,000 800,000Total Or on an average From WestphaliaThe supplies from Ostrau-Karwin amounted toFrom North BohemiaThe coke mentioned above was derived fromthe Ostrau-Karwin district, viz.      ... 1,300,0004,300,000-4,800,000 4,500,000 150,000- 200,0005,300,000 2,600,000The present coal balance sheet is as follows : Requirement of coal (without coke)        ... 14,000,000Home production       ... ... ... 1,600,000Quantities to be imported        ... ... 12,400,000The Austrian Government has received promises of the following:-Tons per day.From Upper Silesia    ... ... ... ... 7,500Westphalia       ............ 2,500North-West Bohemia      ... ... ... 2,600 .Total ......   .... 12,600Or the year, calculated at 300 working days, 3,800,000 tons.The Prague Government has promised supplies from the Ostrau-Karwin district corresponding to &quot; normal&quot; supplies proportionately reduced on the basis of the general reduction in the production of coal. The normal supplies being 5,300,000 tons, less proportionate reduction by 25 oer cent., the supplies from this source may be calculated at 3,975,000 tons.If, then, the promises made are fulfilled, Austria&apos;s requirements would be covered as follows: Tons.Home production        ... ... ... ...      1,600,000From Silesia, Westphalia, North-West Bohemia     ...      3,800,000 ,,   Ostrau-Karwin   ,.. ... ... ...      3,975,000Total ..; ... ...      9,375,000Or approximately     &quot; ... ... ... ...      9,400,000Leaving a deficit of 4,600,000 tons, or 33 per cent.
The deficit is further increased by the 1,300,000 tons of coke not provided for  equalling in coal 2,000,000 tons, so that out of a total requirement (coal and coke) of ] 6,000,000 tons, there are provided for 9,400,000 tons, leaving a total deficit of 6,600,000 tons, or 41 per cent.The actual situation, however, is much worse, as at present Germany supplies only 40 per cent, of the quantities promised, and Ostrau-Karwin only 20 per cent.The balance sheet then reveals the following facts :-Home production        ... .., &apos;From Silesia, Westphalia, North-West Bohemia Ostrau-Karwin   ... ...TotalShowing a deficit of 12,085,000 tons, or 75 per cent.Special attention must furthermore be drawn to the fact that the various gas works in German-Austria must rely upon the qualities supplied by Ostrau-Karwin. The total requirements of the Austrian gas works amount to 1,000,000 tons per annum ; out of which the Vienna gas works alone require 300,000 tons.APPENDIX V.Concerning the Foundation of a New Austrian Note-Issuing Bank.No proof need be adduced to show that one of the most important problems which must be solved to render the reconstruction of Austria&apos;s economic life possible concerns above all the stabilisation of the German-Austrian crown in relation to other values. The enormous charges incurred by the food credits already show that the depreciation of the German-Austrian currency in relation to foreign values would entail the most&apos; disastrous consequences for the German-Austrian State (now nothing more than a torso, and greatly weakened at that), unless this depreciation can to some extent at least be remedied, and unless the enormous fluctuations of the foreign exchange can be arrested. No one can deny the importance of this problem more especially, as only the productive work of the Austrian exporting industries would enable Austria to redeem at least portions of the food credits otherwise than by the surrender of assets. The resumption of productive industries presupposes that raw materials can be procured; the difficulties in the supply of the raw materials, however, increase the lower the rate of the Austrian exchange and the greater its fluctuations. It would, of course, be a mistake, scientifically and practically, to presume that a parity upon whatever. basis between the German-Austrian crown and the foreign values could be established by some legal measure or by some international agreement, No legislature, no international convention could produce this effect with any hope of an enduring improvement. Pertinent measures, pertinently applied alone can produce the desired result. - :The most important measure to that end would be the establishment of an independent note-issuing bank for German-Austria. This establishment would have to be effected upon the following basis :-(a.) The bank should be established in the form of a share company, yet in such a way that the rights of the shareholders with regard to its administration be limited in a manner similar to the systems prevailing in nearly all European countries, in view of the important public functions of such an institution. On the other hand, the bank would have to be endowed with such privileges, more especially with regard to the interest upon the share capital, as would attract lively subscriptions-also from abroad. This end could be achieved if the Austrian Government were to grant such bank not only certain profitable rights, but also material advantages in connection&apos; -with the taking over of the stamped notes in circulation of the old Austro-Hungarian Bank, e.g., the payment of a certain interest upon the sums due as equivalent for these notes. Half the share capital of this new [777] ETons. 1,600,000 1,520,000 795,0003,915,000
bank (the amount of which is matter for later discussion), should be subscribed at home, the other half abroad. The bank would thus receive a dowry-even if only on a moderate scale of foreign values and bills. Both groups of shareholders should be equal in strength, yet the foreign group would have to be granted some controlling function to prevent the bank exceeding the scope of its activities, as laid down in the statutes, and as recognised by financial science. Thus alone the bank could fulfil its great mission of stabilising the exchange. (b.) With regard to the &quot;means&quot; wherewith to accomplish this task, they must consist in the transfer to the bank of a considerable amount of such values, which represent or equal foreign values, and which can therefore be utilised abroad as gold.The new Austrian Bank would first of all take over as a charge the stamped Austrian notes in circulation, which notes, though greatly depreciated, are maintaining their circulation because economic life requires some means of payment. On the other hand, the new bank would receive, as against this debit, some corresponding quota from the assets of the Austro-Hungarian Bank, which goes into liquidation. It would be desirable if this quota of the assets could contain some quota of the gold and silver remaining after the Austro-Hungarian Bank has paid off its liabilities owing in neutral markets. It is, however, recognised that the amount of gold and silver thus remaining would be so small and the said quota would yield such a low amount, that this suggestion is made from a sense of justice rather than in the belief that it could have any important bearing upon the solution of the practical task of the bank.On the other hand, it may be assumed that the bank may become more richly supplied with gold and bills, foreign values, and other securities more easily utilised abroad (all of which will be referred to hereafter as &quot; foreign values&quot;) by the application of two measures, viz. : 1. These &quot;foreign values,&quot; which can by law be requisitioned by the State as far as they are owned by Austrians, should be transferred not to the Treasury but to the bank. As a compensation the bank should issue a loan, secured . gold bonds, or bonds secured, by some similar values, bearing interest in gold redeemable after some considerable period, say, twenty-five years. The native owner of these &quot; foreign values,&quot; whether he surrender them volun-voluntarily or under compulsion of the law, will surely be more ready to place these &quot;foreign values&quot; at the disprsal of the bank rather than at the disposal of the Government, so that this proposition would greatly help in overcoming the opposition which is usual when steps of this kind have to be taken.2. No statistics are at present available to show what amount of these &quot; foreign values&quot; would thus flow into the bank. On the other hand, it will be necessary if the Allies desire the survival of Austria that they grant her a &quot;valuta&quot; (foreign exchange) loan in connection with the credit for raw materials. The &quot;foreign values&quot; resulting from this transaction should likewise be put at the disposal not of the Government but of the bank, and be similarly secured by gold bonds of the bank, bearing interest in gold, which loan would again have to be for a considerable period, but the currency of which should be shorter than that of the gold loan granted against the native-owned foreign securities, so that the &quot; foreign values&quot; loan granted by the Allies Would enjoy the privilege of a first mortgage as against the native gold loan, a privilege which under the circumstances is entirely justifiable.From these two sources the bank would dispose of a considerable amount of &quot; foreign values,&quot; the exact amount of Avhich cannot be given, but which should, if possible, reach a sum of 801) to 1,000 million gold crowns or an equivalent amount in other currency. How would the bank be able with these means at her disposal to exercise an influence upon the stability of the exchange ?(a.) By acting as the intermediary for the credits for raw materials to be obtained abroad. Though there is no doubt that some of the leading firms could to some extent obtain credits abroad upon their own signatures, there is similarly no doubt that a large number of firms could obtain credits abroad
Concerning the capital of the New Bank and the amount of Notes to be kept in circulation in German Austria.During the last years preceding the war the Austro-Hungarian Bank had a note circulation of a minimum of 1,500 million crowns and a maximum of 3,000 million crowns, which means an average of 2,250 million crowns, or, with a population of 60 million inhabitants, equalling 45 crowns per head. At present the note circulation amounts to 39,000 million crowns, equalling 780 crowns per head.   German-Austria,[777] &quot; Fonly through the intermediary of the bank. The bank would be able, by depositing or otherwise a certain amount of the foreign exchange values, to secure margins for the would-be foreign creditor, which might become decisive in the question of the grant of the said credits. The bank would thus more or less control financially the transactions concerning the supply of raw materials, and could in consequence exercise a certain influence upon the foreign exchanges, which influence would have to be strengthened by the fact that all foreign values and bills would have to be placed at the disposal of the bank as far as they result from Austrian exports in general,, and more particularly from the export of goods, whether finished or half-finished, the supply of raw materials for which had been financed by the bank.(b.) When the bank procures foreign credits for industrial or other firms, it will be able to put these at their disposal on cheaper conditions than if these firms had to procure such credits themselves. The bank should therefore be authorised to demand in such cases from the firms in question corresponding deposits in crown notes, which would have to be placed at the disposal of the bank without interest or at a very low rate, to be used for the ordinary purposes of the bank. The bank would thus be enabled to reduce the circulation of the depreciated notes or to create a reserve with which it could carry out legitimate operations, such as discounts in the home markets, &amp;c.(c.) If the bank, owing to its holding of foreign exchange values, can thus exercise a regulating influence at home and abroad, it must be in a position also, if possible, to exercise a direct influence at home upon the reduction of the notes in circulation.   This might perhaps be achieved as follows :-The bank would have to take over the stamped notes in circulation against a quota of the existing assets. These assets consist greatly in liabilities of the Government towards the old bank, of which a certain portion will be transferred to the new bank as cover-liabilities which it will perhaps up to a certain amount be possible to redeem in course of time, but which would not enjoy the acknowledged value which would suffice, to procure for the German-Austrian notes in circulation currency also abroad.It is therefore worth considering whether the bank should not be granted, as a third means for the stabilising of the &quot; valuta,&quot; the right to issue special &quot; valuta &quot; notes on the strength of its foreign exchange values, . on the basis of a very rigorous cover, say, up to 50 per cent., which &quot; valuta &quot; notes would be exchangeable at par in gold, as their redemption would be secured by the foreign exchange values at the disposal of the bank. These &quot; valuta &quot; notes would be strictly separated from the ordinary notes, which are legal tender in Austria. These &quot;valuta&quot; notes would constitute the international currency at the disposal of the bank, and of the , economic institutions of German-Austria generally. As, however, these &quot;valuta&quot; notes can even with the most rigorous principles of cover be issued to a larger amount than their cover in gold and exchange values, and as in consequence the bank will always dispose of a certain working capital, a part thereof should under given circumstances be utilised to reduce by purchase in the open home market the superfluous circulation of old stamped legal tender notes. Thus an improvement in the depreciation in the home market of the currency notes would gradually be effected. This procedure has to a certain extent proved effective in certain American countries.(Signed)     LANDESBERGER.
with a population of 6j millions, would begin the new bank with an approximate circulation of 5,000 million crowns. With a gradual return to pre-war prices for the necessaries of life, which could, however, at best only result after a very long period, German-Austria should bd able to manage with a note circulation of 500 million crowns.The new bank should have a share capital of approximately 120 million crowns-the Austro-Hungarian Bank had a capital of 210 million crowns.(Signed)        VEILCHEN VELDT.APPENDIX YI.Statement and Prospects of the Chief Industries left in German Austria.THE following memorandum comprises, as far as it does not concern raw materials, only finished articles for the manufacture of which the raw materials are wholly or to the largest extent found in German-Austria. The quantities forming the basis of the calculation can only be reached if the supply of food to the workmen is secured and if the raw materials (in most cases only small percentages) which are not to be found in German-Austria and other supplementary materials such as coal, mineral oil, and products thereof can be made available in sufficient quantities. The figures given are estimates oidy, as no special statistics are available dealing only with German-AustriaWoodThe wooded area of German-Austria amounts to approximately 3,500,000 hectares ; the annual increase in wood approximately 10,000,000 cubic metres. , The increase can be balanced by the wood that can be cut annually.Already before the war an important export of wood was effected, amounting to approximately 1,800,000 cubic metres, partly in its natural round condition, partly as cut wood (but not further worked).During the war the 10,000,000 cubic metres could not b.* felled on account of the prevailing difficulties. A large section of the necessary labour was mobilised, the necessary food could.not be supplied, there was great difficulty in connection with the transport. In consequence of this reduced felling it will be possible during a certain period of transition to fell and work increased quantities as soon as the difficulties mentioned have been overcome, and in as far as such increased work is admissible under the existing forest laws.On a basis that during the next ten years the quantity of felled wood exceeds the pre-war quantities by 30 per cent., an annual increase of 3,000,000 cubic metres could be reached, of which about 1,600,000 cubic metres would represent wood ready for sawing. If this quantity be added to the pre-war export of 180,000 cubic metres, the total yield for direct-export would amount to 3,400,000 cubic metres. On the basis of a 60 per cent, yield, that would represent 2,000,000 cubic metres of cut wood.With the present price of 450 crowns per cubic metre, the total value would amount, to 900,000,000 crowns. On the assumption that in the course of the period of transition (ten years), prices would be reduced to 200 per cent, of tta pre-war prices, cut wood would at the end of this period fetch 100 crowns per cubic metre the value of the export concerned would then amount to 200,000,000 crowns.Paper.Paper, pasteboard, half-finished goods for manufacture of same, wood pulp, and . cellulose.                                              &apos; . The annual production is estimated at: Tons.Paper...         ;..         ...         ...         ... ...      180,000Pasteboard      ...         ...         ...         ... ...       60,000:   Half-finished goods        ...         ...         ..: ...      120,000Wood pulp and cellulose ...         ...         ... ...       30,000Among these there would be available for export: Paper ... ... ... ... .......      100,000Half-finished goods        ... ....        ... ...        30,000Wood pulp and.cellulose ... ... ... ...       12,000
* 17At present prices (30 crowns per ton of paper, 20 crowns per ton half-finished goods, 10 crowns per ton cellulose), this would amount to a total of 372,000,000 crowns, which, after a ten years&apos; period of transition, might be assumed to represent a total of 100,000,000 crowns per annum.Iron Ore.The average production of iron ore in German-Austria can be estimated at 2,200,000 tons; in some pre-war years larger quantities have been produced. The production of raw iron is estimated at 600,000 tons, for which approximately 1,300,000 tons of ore are required, leaving a surplus of iron ore available for export amounting to 900,000 tons.At a low calculation the ore is worth 100 crowns per ton, yielding a value of this export amounting to 90,000,000 crowns-which will eventually be reduced to, probably, 20,000,000 crowns.Iron (lialf finished).The annual production, calculated upon the basis of the capacity of the steelworks, amounts to approximately 800,000 tons, leaving a surplus for export of approximately 250,000 tons. The average present price at 2,000 crowns per ton yields a total value of the exportable quantity of 500,000,000 crowns, which would probably gradually be reduced to 125,000,000 crowns.It must be added that the average price is taken at a low rate in view of the fact that the exportable surplus contains a large percentage of high value steel. Already before the war Austria exported considerable quantities of this high quality steel; an increase of these quantities is possible.Magnesite.&apos;      &apos; &apos;   -    .  &apos; - Tons.&apos;.&apos;Production   &apos;     .... ... ... ... ...   140,000Available for export ... ... ... ...   120,000Present price 400 crowns per ton, yielding a total of 48,000,000 crowns-to be eventually reduced to a probable total of 14,000,000 crowns.&apos; Salt (for Table and Industrial Use).Tons.Production ... ... ... ... ...   170,000Available for export ... ... ... ...    40,000Present price 700 crowns per ton, yielding a total of 28,000,000 crowns to be eventually reduced to a probable total of 12,000,000 crowns.Agricultural Machinery, Locomotives, Waggons, Automobiles.Total value of excess over home demand at present prices, 200,000,000 crowns-to be eventually reduced to a probable total of 60,000,000 crowns,Pianos.The German-Austrian production amounts to approximately 14,000 pianos and pianinos. Approximately half would be available for export, representing at present a value of 35,000,000 crowns. This total would eventually be reduced to a probable total of 8,000,000 crowns.Straw Hats.The quantities available for export represent at present prices a value of 20,000,000 crowns. This total would eventually be reduced to a probable total of 6,000,000 crowns.Leather Goods (also Fancy Goods).The quantities available for export represent at present prices a value of 50,000,000 crowns. This total would eventually be reduced to a probable total of 10,000,0.00 crowns.
Summary.(In million crowns.)Articles.Wood .. Paper .. Iron ore.. IronMagnesite SaltMachines Pianos .. Straw hats Leather goodsTotalValue at end of period of transition of available export.200 100 20 125 14 12 60 8 6 10555o

</content>
</cab>
