<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/88/0 images: 145-164</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of Hii Britannic Majesty&apos;s Gorernment.]Printed for the War Cabinet.  September, 1919.SECRET. G.T. 8138.THE LABOUR SITUATION.Report from the Ministry of Labour for the week ending10th September, 1919.Summary.Part I: Problems before the Trades Union Congress.Part II: Demobilisation and Resettlement; Maintenance and Training Grants Scheme; The Attitude of the Engineering Unions.Part III: Press Comments : (1) Labour and Socialist Press: (A) Imperial and Foreign: Russia; Peace Treaty with Austria; Other. (B) Home Affairs : Increased Production; Nationalisation; The Political Outlook; Industrial Outlook; Other.(2) Ex-Service Men&apos;s Periodicals.(3) The Press on Demobilisation and Resettlement.Part IV: General Topics and District Reports.(1) General Topics: Direct Action; Trades Union Congress; Housing; Women and the League of Nations; Output of Coal; Labour and Production; Alien Labour ; Police; Employers&apos; Federations; International Conference on Labour and Religion Resettlement and Unemployment ; Court of Arbitration; Joint Industrial Councils; Trade Boards.(2) District Reports.Part V :&apos; Disputes.(a) Involving a Stoppage of Work.(b) Not Involving a Stoppage of Work.Part I.-Problems before the Trades Union Congress.In view of the gravity of the problems under discussion at the Trades Union Congress which is meeting in Glasgow this week, it seems worth while to trace in outline the negotia-tions that have already taken place in connection with the most important of them, and thus provide, to a certain extent, an historical setting for the reference to the Congress which will appear in next week&apos;s issue of this Report. These problems are^m the main, four, and they concern (1) the functions and powers of the Trades Union Congress itself, (2) Direct Action, (3) Nationalisation, and (4) Production. A number of minor, though still important, problems are also occupying the attention of the Congress. These it is not proposed to deal with here.The Functions of the Congress.Much -publicity has been given to the fact that this year&apos;s Congress is the largest on record, representing as it does over five million Trade Unionists, a number which is con-siderably more than double the membership seven years ago. The Congress now claims to speak for a larger body of opinion than any national gathering in the world, apart from legislative assemblies.  But there are signs of much dissatisfaction among the Unions(c 1882)  255 9/19  H &amp; s 2 H
affiliated to it on the ground that its actual effective power, when compared with its enormous latent potentialities, is very much less than it ought to be.  This is a criticism, of course, which has been heard for a considerable number of years, but, as in other spheres, the events of the present time have given point to it, and it was bound from the first to be brought very prominently to the fore on the question of the action of the Congress in connection with the demand by the Triple Alliance for a special conference which should enable the Congress to declare its considered attitude to the policy of the Government in regard to Russia, Conscription, etc.   On the whole it may&quot; be said that this spirit of dissatisfaction has crystallised into two definite criticisms, the first that the Congress is inefficient and the second that it is conservative.  The former criticism has been formulated chiefly by the intelligentsia of the Labour movement, who point out that Congress is fettered by its history and that it makes little attempt to address itself to the task that urgently awaits it, namely, the constitution of a body able to give shape to the expressed policy of the Trade Union movement and of a general staff to co-ordinate the forces of Labour in the industrial field, especially as regards the problem of industrial and craft unionism.  It is.pointed out that when Congress was founded, there was no Labour Party and no real representation of Labour in Parliament, and it was therefore regarded as the main business of Congress and its Parliamentary Committee to influence Parliament and the Government.  But the Labour Party has come into existence, and the political aspirations of Labour ought, it is maintained, to receive adequate ex-pression through the Labour Party, especially as the party and the T.U.C. represent, to the extent of 90 per cent, of the membership, the same constituent unions.  There are, of course, differences between the two organisations, but it may be recalled that at last year&apos;s meeting of the Congress, proposals for the formation of a distinct political party for the Trade Union Movement, and for the formation of a Trade Union Federation inside the Labour Party, were both heavily defeated.  It is, therefore, contended that the T.U.C. should now be free, through a really strong executive, to devote itself to an effort in the industrial sphere to link up the sectional efforts and. programmes of Labour into a common policy and scheme of action.The second criticism of the T.U.C., as has been suggested above, is closely bound up with the.problem of Direct Action, and the chief critic is the powerful Triple Industrial Alliance.Direct Action.The facts centring in this question are well known.. The definite movement in favour of Direct Action was inaugurated at a Conference of the Alliance at Southport on 16th April, and originally took the form of a resolution urging the Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union Congress to convene a special National Conference to consider whether industrial action should be taken to compel the Government to accede to (1) the abolition of conscription, (2) the withdrawal of British troops from Eussia, (3) the raising of the blockade, and (4) the release of conscientious objectors. It may be noted in passing, as &amp; psychological sidelight on the attitude of the Alliance, that when it passed this resolu-tion, it was flushed with the sudcess that had attended its efforts in obtaining from, the Government most of the concessions demanded in the national programmes which two of the constituent bodies formulated on the conclusion of the armistice. The subsequent progress of events brought the Alliance into sharp conflict with the Parliamentary Com-mittee. The latter body, instead of acquiescing in the suggestion of the Alliance, sent a deputation to Mr. Bonar Law, and, in view of his assurances, decided not to. call a National Conference. This step gravely displeased the Alliance, and the policy of Direct Action was subsequently endorsed by all of the constituent bodies at their annual conferences. In view of this, a full delegate conference of the Alliance, held on the 23rd July, eager to -give evidence of its executive efficiency, a quality which is held to be conspicuously lacking in the Parliamentary Committee, decided to persevere in its policy of direct action (though one of the issues on which such action had originally been advocated had in the meantime in the ordinary course of events ceased to exist) and recommended its constituent parts to ascertain whether members were prepared to take industrial action to enforce the demands. The subsequent reaction against the policy on the part of the rank and file, probably not unconnected with the complete failure of the revolutionary police and sympathetic strikes, exerted a sobering effect on the Alliance, its executive postponed the ballot, and the full delegate conference homologated the decision, and agreed to adjourn the whole matter until the meeting of the Congress. It appears possible, from a survey of these events, that from the point of view of the Alliance, the policy of Direct Action was wrecked by the conservative constitutionalism of the Parliamentary Committee of the T.U.C., for if it had
Ulconsented to convene a National Conference in June or July when the revolutionary   , elements in Labour were at the height of their power, it is not impossible that that policy might have been endorsed.These are the surface events, but probably the main interest in the battle waged at the Congress, over these matters only emerges if the two protagonists, the Alliance and the Parliamentary Committee, are considered in the light of their general position and aspira-tions. The Congress is an old body with something of a reputation for conservatism, and a traditional policy lying inside strict constitutional limits. The Triple Alliance is a new body, which has been extraordinary successful up to a point. Having completely super-superseded the G.F.T.U. and become the rallying point for the more active and progressive elements in the industrial labour movement, it is now attacking fresh ground. As has been pointed out before, industrial power once realised must find an outlet, and the Alliance has industrial power owing to its excellence of organisation over a very wide area. It is natural, therefore, especially in the present circumstances, that it should seize the reaction against political activity which really gave it birth to become the weapon of the alternative industrial policy. Here at once it challenges the Trades Union Congress, because this is the body, if any, which has a locus standi sufficient to inaugurate a campaign of industrial action on any momentous issue (a) whether it be political or (b) industrial. It will be seen, therefore, that the suggested revision and general tightening-up of the positions of the T.U.C. and Parliamentary Labour Party in relation to one another referred to earlier, are probably not entirely unconnected with the activities of the Triple Alliance. They point to the constitutional, while the activities of the Triple Alliance point to the alternative &quot; extra-constitutional,&quot; line of progress.Nationalisation. &apos; -In the case of Nationalisation, one has again the same protagonists, but reorientated in an interesting manner.  For many years the Congress has continued to pass resolutions in favour of Nationalisation, but a vote in favour of Nationalisation this year will mean something very different from those passed at previous Congresses.  It will mean not a vote in favour of  a  distant aspiration,  but a  decision to place the AVhole weight of the T.U.C. behind the Miners in their demand for the full programme of the majority report of the Coal Commission.  The only question is as to the method which it will recommend as a means to the attainment of that end.  The Miners&apos; Federation is, of course, deeply pledged to secure nationalisa-tion.  At its annual conference on 11th July, before the Government^ decision with regard to the report of the Commission was made known, the M.F.G.B. stated, in definite terms, its determination that the recommendations of the majority should be given effect to ; and the official announcement of the Governments policy provoked a storm of indignation and the free assertion by various miners&apos; leaders that strong efforts would be made to obtain the support of organis ed Labour in a resort to Direct Action in favour of Nationalisation. The Executive and the delegate Conference of the Miners&apos; Federation, however, declined to commit themselves to the adoption of industrial action to secure the adoption of the Commission^ report, and contended themselves with &quot; inviting the Trades Union Congress to declare that the fullest and most effective action be taken.&quot;  This was taken by a number of people to indicate a weakening in the attitude of the M.F.G.B., whereas, as a matter of fact, it Was merely another illustration of the tactical sense of their leaders. It was pointed out a long time ago in these Eeports* that the Miners intended to get their programme through, that they have never looked upon the Coal Commission as anything but a rather convenient means to this end, and that therefore if the Commission method failed they would try another.   There is no reason to depart from that view. The Coal Commission having failed, the unions have looked round for other means and   1 decided that the wisest course would be to get the whole of the Trade Union movement at their backs.   For this it was necessary to appeal to the decision of the Trades Union Congress, and to adopt a strictly temperate attitude.   But that moderation must not be taken to indicate any weakening in determination.!Production.The vital importance, in the interests of the nation as a whole, of increasing production has long been proclaimed officially by the Government, and much publicity has been given to the gravity of the industrial and economic situaton caused by the serious decline in out-* See Part I &quot; Industrial Action,&quot; Report for week ending 21s!; May.t &apos;This policy appears in the event to have been carried to a triumphant consummation in.Mr. Smillie&apos;s speech at the Congress and the resulting vote on nationalisation (see Part IV).
put.  There is no reason to suppose that, as many people seem to imagine, Trade Union leaders are any more blind to this position than anyone else.  But it is not generally realised what a delicate and difficult problem this is for such men in their official capacity to handle.  They have been used to speaking from the labour point of view in peace time, and from the national point of view in war time.  But to speak and persuade from the national point of view in peace time is another matter ; especially when self-sacrifice in the national interest has been demanded from the workers for some five years, and. when the subject of their plea is not a clear-cut issue, but undoubtedly complex, and the attitude of the workers only one out of many factors making for difficulty in it.*  The position is really parallel to that which has arisen out of the great strength of the Triple Alliance except that here the emphasis lies rather on the workmen&apos;s responsibility whereas there it lay on his power.  Hence arise the rather awkward and unco-ordinated gestures hitherto displayed by various parts of the labour movement over this question.  The problem for the leaders is, on the one hand, to get their followers to do what may be necessary from the national point of view, without on the other either alienating their loyalty and jeopardising their interests by allowing any part of their activities to be used to cover up other people&apos;s shortcomings or for private ends.  If the result of the Congress is to lead to a solution of this very difficult position, satisfactory from a national point of view, its work will not have been wasted.[A Summary of the proceedings of the Congress to date appears in Part IWjPart II. Demobilisation and Resettlement.Maintenance and Training Grants Scheme : The Attitude of the Engineering Unions.A solution of the difficulties arising from the opposition of the engineering trade unions to the introduction of ex-officers as trainees under the Maintenance and Training Grant Scheme, to which attention was drawn in this Report for the week ending the 2nd July, has not proved easy of discovery. The occurrence of local disputes, which in one or two cases resulted in actual, strikes, necessitated the opening of negotia-tions with the engineering unions for a national settlement of the question and the dis-cussions have been somewhat protracted. In the meantime local friction has con-tinued to arise, the most important dispute being that at the works of the Campbell Gas Engine Company, Halifax.In this case, members of the Amalgamated Society of Engineers objected to the presence of five trainees in the works, of whom only one was receiving training under the Maintenance and Training Grants Scheme. A strike, occurring towards the middle of July, involved the members of other engineering unions as well as of the Amalgamated Society of Engineers and has proved of long duration. Although the trainee under the Grants Scheme withdrew voluntarily, it was not possible in this case to follow the course adopted elsewhere of securing a resumption of work provided that training was not resumed until a national settlement was reached. The head of the firm, who are ncn-federated, considered that a matter of principle was involved, and preferred to deal with the position himself rather than accept the intervention of the Ministry of Labour. A situation of some danger arose from the declaration of an embargo on the strikers by the employers in the Halifax district; and throughout August there was some risk that a national strike might develop out of this local dispute. Recent developments, however, have rendered this prospect remote. While Mr. Campbell has remained firm in his attitude, refusing to with-draw the ex-officer pending a national settlement, and filling the places of the strikers by disabled ex-Service men after consultation with the Halifax branches of the societies of ex-soldiers and sailors, the embargo on the strikers has ultimately been withdrawn, A number have returned to work with the Campbell Gas Engine Company, and the remainder have found employment with other local firms.In other disputes which have arisen, it has been possible to avoid an actual strike. It has been considered expedient, however, to suspend for the present the introduction of new trainees into engineering works. Grants continue to be made to applicants for engineer-ing training, but it is made clear in every case that actual training cannot begin until the points at issue with the engineering unions have been determined.Negotiations with the unions have not proved an easy matter. They have taken objection to the introduction of trainees upon three broad grounds.  In the first place,* See Part IV (2) p. 229 (West Midlands-General).
Part III-Press Comments.(1) Labour and Socialist Press.(A) Imperial and Foreign. Russia. ,The &quot; New Statesman &quot; has a special article on the Governments Russian policy. The &quot;writer of this article deals with recent events such as Mr. ChurchiH&apos;s statements&apos; in the House of Commons just before, the vacation, but the main part of the article is devoted, &quot;to showing the necessity for a complete revision of our Russian policy as a whole. He urges the re-establishment, by generous assistance in money and supplies, of stable economic conditions in the Baltic States, which should be permitted to make terms with the Soviet ^Government; and he predicts that once Russian trade has been enabled to make some sort of a recovery, the worst effects of Bolshevism will disappear. If the Government /persists, against the will of the electorate, in the policy that has already cost us so much, no methods which the democracy of the country might take to enforce its will on this ^question, could, he considers, be regarded as unjustifiable. The *f Nation &quot; declares that this year&apos;s campaign against Russia is at an end so far as gaining any definite object is concerned. The Baltic victory was merely spectacular and was expected no doubt to turn the public from the contemplation of our failures on land, and from the enormous expense v-ef the general undertaking.  The &quot; Labour Leader &quot; is satisfied that military operationsthey held that the number of trainees introduced into the engineering industries was likely to prove excessive in view of the fact that some 10,000 of their members were un-employed. In the second place they considered that it was unfair that men who in&apos; a number of cases have been trained for other trades or professions should be introduced for training into engineering works, and compete with others who have adopted an engineer-ing profession from the beginning. The third main objection has been that the trainees are to all intents and purposes in the same position as premium apprentices, and are given an unfair advantage over the ordinary engineering apprentices serving a seven years&apos; course, who, it is held, are likely to see the higher posts to which they might possibly aspire filled by Government trainees.The first general conference with the unions, which was held on the 12th August, failed to reach any settlement. Concessions have now been proposed by the Department, which it is hoped will meet the unions&apos; objections and at the same time enable the Department to fulfil satisfactorily its duty towards the ex-officer desirous of entering the engineering pro-iession. It is clearly impossible that any step should be taken to place the ex-officer in the position of the ordinary engineering apprentice, but it is felt that by restriction of the number of men introduced for training and of the type of man selected, the fear of undue competition expressed by the unions may be overcome. It is proposed, therefore, that the maximum number of trainees, which has hitherto been fixed at 3,000, should be reduced to not more than 1,750. It is pointed out, however, that the number may in practice be substantially less than this figure. As an additional safeguard, it is suggested that the number of trainees in any one factory or works shall not exceed 1 per cent, of the total number of employees.It is proposed, moreover, to restrict eligibility for training in engineering under the Government scheme to men who passed straight from school into the Forces and who might reasonably be presumed to have contemplated entering the trade had not the war made it impossible, or those who by reason of their youth had not entered into any profession or trade before joining the Forces. No trainee is to be accepted for engineering who has been fully or partially trained in any other profession or trade.In order to secure for the unions full cognisance of the working of the scheme as it affects their industry, it is proposed that each of the ten Engineering Interviewing Boards which have been set up in various parts of the country should co-opt one of the local trade union secretaries, as representative of the trade unions who may make themselves party to the proposed agreement.The unions concerned are now being approached on these proposals, and a second conference is shortly to be held at which it is hoped a national settlement of the whole question may be achieved. The importance of a satisfactory conclusion may be judged from the fact that the number of grants made for training in engineering is exceeded only by those for accountancy and pharmaceutical chemistry; it is substantially greater than that for any other profession.
are now going in favour of the Soviet Armies. It regards the evacuation of Omsk by Admiral Koltchak as inevitable, although it may be delayed for some time. ;The &quot; Call &quot; publishes an article by Maxim Gorky on the fundamental principles of the Russian Revolu-tion, and the &quot; Socialist &quot; in a long article gives M. Tchitcherine&apos;s impressions of the Peace Treaty. M. Tchitcherine writes that above all things the Treaty is anything but a Peace Treaty. It establishes a situation which must continually give rise to&apos; international friction. The League of Nations he describes as a &quot; demagogic formula with the concealed aim of giving a presentable form to the fact that it is merely a prolonged coalition against German competition which the Entente still fears.&quot;Peace Treaty with Austria.The &quot;Nation&quot; condemns the recently concluded treaty with Austria. There is said to be no justification for burdening the Austrian people with the whole of the war-debt and the indemnity, while the statement that &quot; the people of Austria were the ardent sup-porters of the war from start to finish &quot; is described as simply untrue. The refusal to allow the union with Germany, and the ultimatum to the German Government in this connection are equally open to objection. The Peace Treaty leaves it open to the Council of the League of Nations to sanction the union, and the arbitrary action of the Allied Council is a violation of the democratic principles which they continually profess. The &quot; New Statesman &quot; regards the prohibition of the Union as the chief blot on the Treaty, which otherwise is not so bad, and hopes that Austria will find redress for this wrong from the League of Nations.Other.- The &quot;Nation &quot; and the &quot;New Statesman &quot; remark that President Wilson will have to devote as much attention during his tour to the industrial as to the European situation. The &quot; Nation &quot; considers that both parties in the industrial struggle show signs of yielding to moderate counsels; the summoning of a Joint Industrial Conference proves the good will of the Employers, and the proposed six months&apos; truce to labour disputes proves that of the workers. The &quot; New Statesman,&quot; however, doubts whether a crisis can now be prevented, as there are no clear indications that the rank, and file are prepared to follow their union officials in maintaining a truce. The &quot; Labour Leader &quot; in a leading article states that it is improbable that the American Senate will ratify the Treaty. This is con-sidered an advantage as it will bring the whole question of the Treaty up again; and will make possible a better treaty with Germany as far as America is concerned. On another page Miss Bondfleld points, out that, the critics of the Treaty oppose it on re-actionary grounds, and that the vast majority of the American people do not think internationally at all. Miss Bondfield, who is giving her impressions of America after a recent visit, adds that American workers expect the Labour Party of Great Britain to lead the way in international politics. Mr. Arthur Finch writes in the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; on the agreement with Persia. An article in the &quot; Workers&apos; Dreadnought&quot; gives an account of how the Swiss Social Democratic Party came to join the Third International. A summary of the proceedings of the &quot; Second International&quot; Conference at Lucerne appears in the &quot; Labour Leader.&quot; &quot; Forward &quot; prints an appeal.from M. Jean Longuet for unity and one &quot; international&quot; in the world socialist movement. Mr. Belfort Bax writing in&apos;&quot; Justice &quot; puts the case for a speedy recognition among the Allied peoples of the view that the Germans must be treated as human beings who are, after all, not so very unlike ourselves, and that the present attitude towards them is likely to intensify rather than to lessen their feeling for militarist institutions. The situation in Hungary does not attract much attention. The &quot;Labour Leader &quot; gives instances of Rumanian pillage; and the &quot;. Workers&apos; Dreadnought &quot; prints the resolution of the Official Socialist Party of Italy expressing solidarity with the Hungarian Communist Party and calls on the British Trades Union Congress to pass a similar one at its meeting this week.(B) Home Affairs.Increased Production.The question of output receives quite as much attention in the papers as it did last week. Most writers take Mr. Brownlie&apos;s letter as a basis for comment and discussion. The &quot; New Age,&quot; in urging that the only way to deal with the question of high prices is to alter drastically the system which automatically produces them, delivers a tirade against Mr. Brownlie as a &quot; propagandist of the Federation of British Industries,&quot; and remarks how fortunate it is for them that palliatives proposed by men like Mr. Clynes and Mr. Brownlie, coincide so exactly with the remedies which the capitalist class would itselt
apply. It reiterates its usual contention, that under the present social system, super-production only means super-production of luxuries or goods for export and increasing clearness and scarcity of necessities. Mr. Brownlie&apos;s letter is also discussed, in a special article by Mr. W. McLaine, in the &quot; Call.&quot; He demands to know whether Mr. Brownlie would really support an appeal for increased production on the part of the worker when the product will be sold abroad as surplus production and any advantages accruing from it . will be taken as a matter of course by Capital. Like Mr. Orage in the &quot; New Age &quot; he declares that the resulting competition for markets will inevitably bring about another war within the next few years. Sir Leo Chiozza Money, writing in the &quot;Labour Leader,&quot; reviews some further &quot; delusions &quot; on economic subjects which, he states are extensively circulated by the Press. He maintains that it is pure nonsense to assert that greater pro-productivity will have the effect of lowering prices. The only ground in fact from which you can deduce with safety that increased production will be beneficial is from the standpoint of a firm belief in nationalisation. Another article in the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; states that even if the selling of our surplus production in foreign markets did benefit the worker, the markets themselves do not exist at present. America does not want our surplus pro-duction, and our own policy in Russia and Germany has effectively prevented us from selling our goods there. It is dismayed at -the lack of knowledge of facts displayed by trade unionist leaders who support an unconsiclered outcry for greater production in the interests of the capitalist class. The same attitude is taken up by the &quot;Socialist,&quot; the &quot; Woolwich Pioneer,&quot; &quot;Forward,&quot; and the &quot; Yorkshire Factory Times.&quot; &quot;Justice,&quot; on. the other hand, expresses full agreement with Mr. Brownlie and hopes that the Trades Union Congress will take up the matter and give a lead to the workers to produce more in the national interest; and by thus showing themselves conscious of their new responsi-bilities, persuade the public that production for the good of all is preferable to production for the profit of a small class. The &quot; Democrafs &quot; space is again this week mainly taken up with articles on the urgent necessity for increased production. In one of these it is suggested that Trade Unionism could enormously increase its power if it threw itself into the problem as the chief factor in speeding up production. Another deals with the possible danger of German competition, and the only safeguard against it, the retention of our foreign markets. &apos; Mr. Appleton is quoted as urging the seriousness of the situation in his Quarterly Report of the General Federation of Trade Unions.Nationalisation. 1 iThe &quot; New, Age &quot; and the &quot; New. Statesman &quot; both give an outline of the &quot;Plumb Plan &quot;for the nationalisation of railways in America. The &quot; New Age &quot; points out that this scheme is analogous to the earlier proposals of the National Guildsman and contrasts the readiness with which America has taken up the theory with the almost entire ignorance of it prevailing among. English labour leaders after ten years strenuous propaganda. The &quot;New Statesman &quot; devotes more space to the methods adopted in America in the pro-motion of. the scheme than to the scheme itself. It is important that the value of putting such, schemes before the public in an organised and attractive form should be realised by the workers here who too often behave as if they were indifferent on questions which.in -reality stir them vitally. It is especially necessary that such a policy of propaganda should be developed as part of a nationalisation campaign. The public rightly demands to know what guarantees of efficiency can be given by Labour when it proposes to share in the control of industry; and since it is naturally prejudiced against Labour at present owing to the defects of the actual system it is for Labour to show that these are inherent in the system.of private ownership, and not due to any failure on the part of the workers them-selves. The ,&quot; Labour Leader &quot; has an article by Mr. J. R. McPhie dealing with anti-nationalisation propaganda. He urges the importance of dealing point by point with state-ments which appear in pamphlets and leaflets or in the Press and which have as their text the &quot; ruin &quot; awaiting the country when industry is State-controlled. &quot;Justice &quot; also has some, notes on the prejudice against nationalisation which the muddles of State bureau-cracyis rapidly creating in the man in the street. Propagandists will have all their work cut out to convince people that democratic ownership and control of industry bear no resemblance to the existing system which is based on capitalism. A writer in the &quot; Demo-crat&quot; puts forward the view that in any industry which is nationalised the worker will simply: find, that he has replaced the employer by the consumer Who is always the ultimate -employer. The result of this, it is said, would be the complete elimination of the workers&apos; point of view by the overwhelming superiority of numbers and the immensely&apos;stronger force of the new &quot; monster &quot; who will have been established in power as a result of the workers&apos;own lack of foresight.
The Political Outlook.Most of the papers predict that Mr. Henderson will be successful at Widnes and that the Government^ retrenchment policy, together with other signs, indicates the approaching collapse of the Coalition. The - Nation &quot; is already foreshadowing an alliance of Labour with the Independent Liberals, the parties to which would be Labour, democratic Toryism, and the free progressive Liberal-Radicals ; and the policy a &quot; Reconciliation in Europe under a democratised League of Nations, the levelling of economic barriers, disarmament, a levy on war-made profits and a return to,honest finance, the joint control of industry, and the nationalisation, under a scheme which may be as gradual as you like, of mines and railways.&quot; The &quot; Labour Leader &quot; points out the really wide divergence in the aims and practice of the Labour and Liberal Parties. An article by Colonel Wedgwood in &quot; Forward&apos;&apos; warms Labour to be ready with a radically constructive policy, and to avoid the kind of v compromise Government which will certainly be attempted. He maintains that before everything else Labour must be self-contained, but the very urgency of his appeal suggests that to some extent he shares the view expressed in the &quot; Nation &quot; that Labour may come to power with a distinctive policy on no subject except industrial questions. Mr. G. W. S. Jarrett, writing in the &quot; British Citizen,&quot; is still further impressed with the failure of the Labour Party as a driving force in politics. He ascribes this largely to the policy of the Party during the war, particularly as regards its attitude towards the Russian Revolution ; and also to the inability of the Parliamentary Labour Party to represent adequately the ideals and aspirations of Labour in the House of Commons.Industrial Outlook.The Trades Union Congress. The reference by the miners of nationalisation and by the Triple Alliance of the Direct Action issue to the Trades Union Congress, has served to make the latter loom even larger than it &quot;might otherwise have done as the next event of importance in the industrial world. It is agreed that these two issues will play the principal part, and the debates on them be the most important, but the papers each press for atten-tion to the matters which seem to them essentially to require it. The only resolution on the agenda which obtains the good wishes of the &quot; New Age &quot; is that of the Association of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen which calls upon the Executive &quot;to draft a practical and effective policy for the control of industry whereby the Trade Union movement can secure for democracy complete emancipation from wage-slavery.&quot; The &quot;New States-man &quot; thinks that the Congress should make an official declaration against the activities of the &quot; special branch &quot; at Scotland Yard, where it states a complete system of industrial espionage is established. &quot; Justice &quot; and the &quot; British Citizen &quot; urge due consideration to Mr. Brownlie&apos;s letter, and the grave facts which induced him to write it. The &quot; Nation &quot; and the &quot; Workers&apos; Dreadnought,&quot; concentrating chiefly on foreign policy, consider it the duty of the Congress to give a lead to Labour in the questions of Russia, Hungary, and the European situation generally. The writer in the &quot; Workers&apos; Dreadnought &quot; has not much hope that any such lead will be forthcoming, but admits that, although &quot; only the shell&quot; within which the kernel of the workers&apos; revolutionary movement has been growing, the official Trade Union movement is still called upon at times to make momentous decisions.Other.A long article by ex-Inspector Syme appears in &quot; Forward.&quot; This attacks the &quot; Daily Herald &quot; and the leaders of the Police and Prison Officers&apos; Union, Mr. Hayes and Mr. Marston, and accuses them of having ruined the future of the Union by the irresponsible methods with which they conducted the recent strike. Among the charges made by Mr. Syme are the deliberate tampering on the part of the Executive with the ballot of May last, and false and misleading statements made by Mr. Hayes as to the strength of the Union. The &quot; Daily Herald &quot; is accused of quoting offers of support both in money and in proposals to join the strikers from the Miners&apos; Federation and the Triple Alliance which were in point of fact never made. He calls on the Trades Union Congress to demand the reinstatement of the dismissed strikers, and to appoint a committee to inquire into the conduct of those who so mischievously misled the men into a strike. The &quot; Socialist&quot; has an article on the Labour Colleges by J. T. Murphy. Several of the papers comment rather unfavourably on the speech of Mr. G. N. Barnes at the International Conference . on Labour and Religion and the &quot; Leeds Citizen &quot; says of it that it&quot; was probably inspired at a Coalition table.&quot;
(2) Ex-Service Metis Periodicals. &quot;&quot;-An article in the &quot; Ex-Service *Man,&quot; an independent organ for all ex-Service men,, edited by Captain H. H. C. Baird, compares the movement for shorter hours and a minimum wage to the action of a man who, having lost nearly all his money, takes a new and more expensive house and engages a larger staff of servants. The writer discourages the tendency to start on these risky and costly experiments at a time when the country needs to produce more, and assist employers to undertake new enterprises and invest fresh capital. The &quot; Comrades&apos; Journal,&quot; the organ of the &quot;Comrades of the; Great War,&quot; gives the opinions of some representative Labour Leaders on the action of those trade unions who oppose the admission of ex-Service men who were not members before the war, and on the Government proposal to get a certain percentage of disabled men employed in all industries. Among those who gave opinions were the Rt. Hon. G. N. Ba&apos;rnes who stated that he entirely disapproved such an .attitude on the part of the Trade Unions, Mr. Ben Tillett who said he thought that each Union should use its own discretion as regards the admission of ex-Service men and also as regards the Government scheme, Mr. Clement Edwards and Mr. Havelock Wilson who disapproved of the action of such Unions and strongly supported the Government scheme, and Colonel Will Thorne who expressed a dislike to criticising the actions of Unions other than his own as these must know their own business best. The continued employment of women on work that could be performed by discharged and disabled men is also referred to, and some instances given, particularly that of the continued employment of women on the L.C.C. trams. In an article on the unemployment donation some criticisms of the dole as it affects ex-soldiers are made. In. the &quot;New World,&quot; the paper of,the National Union of Ex-Service men, Mr. A. E. Mander, the General Secretary, makes an appeal to the Trades Union Congress to support the men in their demand for the&apos;payment of back pay. He remarks in the course of this that ex-Service men have no grievance against the Trade Unions, who have always supported their demands for better treatment, although he would like to see rather more active assistance than that afforded by the passing of resolutions. A leading article in the &quot; Red Ensign,&quot; organ of the Red Ensign Association Ltd., warns its readers against the probable efforts that Germany will make to re-establish her merchant marine, and to rebuild her trade, and advocates the closest possible scrutiny of all transactions in which Germany has a part.(3) The Press on Demobilisation and Resettlement.Opinions on the Government scheme to secure the employment of disabled men by urging all employers to guarantee that 5 per cent, of their employees shall be disabled men are given in the &quot; Daily Chronicle,&quot; the 5th September, 1919. Both trade unionists and employers who were interviewed expressed some doubts as to whether the plan would work well in practice although all agreed that the principle was admirable. The general view seemed to be that in work where much training was required and where much physical effort was involved, the percentage will be found to be rather high.The &quot; Birmingham Post,&quot; the 26th August, 1919, reports that complaints have been made locally by partially disabled men who are being trained under the Ministry of Labour scheme that things have been very unsatisfactory since&apos;the duty of paying them passed from the hands of the Pensions Committee to the Ministry. ,This is explained by. the Chief Executive Officer of the Birmingham Training Committee to be due to difficulties arising out of the transfer.Several papers report dissatisfaction with the new scale of disablement allowances and the &quot;Daily Chronicle,&quot; the 5th September, 1919, announces the formation of a &quot; Council of Disabled Men in Training &quot; to protest against the new rates, and to demand that pensions should be continued in addition to a reasonable flat rate of training allowance, or that there should be a return to the old rates.The &quot; Daily Herald &quot; has several articles this week on the difficulties which ex-Service men are experiencing in finding houses. Instances of hardship from various. localities are given, and the blame laid on the Government for its delay in dealing with, the housing problem.
Paet IV.-General Topics and District Reports. (1) General Topics.Direct Action.Delegates representing miners, railwaymen and transport workers, constituting the Triple Industrial Alliance, met in London on the 4th September to consider the decision of the three executives at their meeting on the 12th August to postpone the ballot on direct action. A full discussion took place, and the following resolution was passed practically unanimously :-&quot; That this conference accepts the decision of the three Executive Com-mittees of the Triple Industrial Alliance to postpone the ballot vote, and the ballot hereby stands postponed. The whole question is adjourned until after the Trades Union Con-gress.&quot; This decision was practically a foregone conclusion. Any other action would have amounted to a vote of no confidence in the Executives, as no change has since taken place in the situation, so far at least as concerns the original issues on which direct action was proposed. The attitude of the miners at the last moment gave rise to some slight uncertainty, for at the private session of the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain on the 3rd inst. they decided in favour of proceeding with the ballot, and as they outnumber the^ other two constituent organisations put together, they could have forced a majority decision at the Triple Alliance Conference in favour of proceeding with the ballot.1     &apos;:: .... . , -Trades Union Congress.The 51st Annual Trades Union Congress opened at Glasgow on the 8th September. Mr. G. H. Stuart-Bunning, the President, devoted the greater part of his presidential address to criticism of the policy of direct action. He began by defending the action of the Parliamentary Committee in its decision not to summon a special National Con-ierence at the request of the Triple Alliance, and pointed out that the Congress had never iully accepted the policy of a national strike on the industrial matters which are its primary interest, and he did not think that it had ever seriously discussed the question of a national strike on a political issue. But if a National Conference had been called, and the policy of direct action had been endorsed, the Government must have fought the issue, and that :meant revolution. Mr. Stuart-Bunning emphasised his disbelief in industrial strikes on political matters, for he did not despair of constitutional methods; but he pointed out that the suggestions of direct action were due largely to the conduct of Ministers in re-pudiating, after an interval of time, the construction currently placed upon their speeches. Referring to the question of output, he stated that the workpeople&apos;s representatives on the joint committee of the National Joint Industrial Conference offered to prepare their case on industrial unrest, if the employers would prepare theirs as to output. The workpeople had issued their case, but they had not receivedthe employers&apos; case on output. He assured the miners that the Congress was not weakening on the question of nationalisation; and referred with sympathy to the forthcoming Labour Conference in Washington, which he characterised as a great and bold idea-to bring together representatives of the State, the employer and the worker to consider how the world may be made &amp; better place in which to live. Dealing with the question of the discipline of trade unionism, he mentioned that precious time was devoted by the Parliamentary Committee to the consideration of disputes between unions which ought never to arise. He probably had in mind here the dispute between the Ironfounders and members of the Gas, Municipal and General Workers&apos; Union at West Bromwich. In conclusion, he looked forward with confidence to the early establishment of a Labour Government. A vote of thanks to the President was proposed by Mr. C. T. Cramp (Railwaymen) and seconded by Mr. W. Brace (Miners). At the afternoon session, the following resolution was adopted:-&quot;That this Congress instructs the Parliamentary Committee to draft a practical and effective policy for the control of industry, whereby the trade union movement can secure for democracy -complete emancipation from wage slavery.&quot; Resolutions were also carried in favour of free trade, and in support of the efforts of the Actors&apos; Union to &quot; unionise &quot; all places of amusement.On the 9th inst. the Congress proceeded to the discussion of the Annual Report ot the Parliamentary Committee, which was submitted for adoption by paragraphs. Mr. H. H. Elvin (General Secretary N.U.C.) moved to refer back the paragraph recording the growth in membership of the Congress in order to record his objection to the affiliation with the Congress of the Association of Women Clerks and Secretaries. He urged that, as the policy of the Congress was to discourage organisation by sex, it was agaurst the policy of the Congress to admit an organisation confined to women clerks, the ^rence that such an organisation should not exist, and that its members should join the N.U.U ine
motion was rejected, however, apparently on the ground that it might be well to admit the new organisation, even as a preliminary to abolishing their separate existence. On the discussion of the paragraph in the report dealing with the coal industry commission, Mr. J. T. Brownlie (President A.S.E.) made a statement with regard to the letter on production which he had sent to Mr. Bowerman. Mr. J. E. Mills (A.S.E., Secretary of the Woolwich Arsenal Shop Stewards) stated that Mr. Brownlie&apos;s letter had been used by certain agencies to traduce the rank and file of the Trade Union movement, and blamed the Government for any want of production. Mr. Ben Turner (Weavers) opposed Mr. Brownlie&apos;s statements, repudiating the charge of idleness which had been laid against the working-class. Mr. J. Havelock Wilson (Seamen) associated himself with the remarks of Mr. Brownlie, who, however, it is reported, came very badly out of the encounter.The Congress then proceeded to deal with the paragraph in the report referring to the action of the Parliamentary Committee in declining to call a National Conference on direct action. Mr. Smillie moved that the paragraph be referred back, which would amount to a vote of censure on the Parliamentary Committee. He expressed the opinion that the Parliamentary Committee had not the confidence of the Trade Union movement and that the fact that the Committee had not during the last twelve months called a special con-ference on the questions at issue bore out the Governments attitude that they need not-trouble about the Parliamentary Committee. He wished to have the paragraph sent back because he wanted the Parliamentary Committee made stronger and more fully and entirely representative of the Labour movement in the country. He also wanted a decision for the guidance of the Committee that if in the future such questions or questions of equal importance should come up a special conference should be convened. Mr. Robert Williams supported Mr. SmilhVs motion. The President argued that the reference back of the -paragraph would be interpreted as a vote in favour of direct action. Mr. Cathery (Seamen), opposed the motion, as did Mr. Clynes, who appealed to the Congress to bow to the law so long as it was the law, to give strength to the Labour members of Parliament who were seeking to work by constitutional methods, and not to seek to introduce violence into the country. Mr. Frank Hodges supported the motion. On a card vote the motion was referred back by 2,586,000 to 1,876,000. There seems little doubt that in this matter the sense of the Conference merely regarded this as a vote of censure on the Parliamentary Com-mittee for deciding matters themselves which they should have called a conference to decide, without prejudice to- the Direct Action question, which was the point at issue. Though the majority was large, it is reported that the matter was touch and go, and that if a vote had been taken after Mr. Clynes spoke and before Mr. Hodges intervened, the decision might have been the other way.The Congress then went on to discuss the paragraph in the. report dealing with the Police and Prison Officers&apos; Union. A motion to move back the paragraph was proposed by Mr. Marston and seconded by Mr. J. H. Hayes. Sympathy was expressed with the Police Union but the motion was withdrawn, and the prestige of the Union probably suffered by the incident. In connection with a communication from the Labour Party Executive with reference to the resolution passed at the Southport Conference in favour of the speedy admission of Germany to the League of Nations, Mr. Robert Williams proposed that the Congress instruct the Parliamentary Committee to co-operate with the Labour Party in inaugurating a campaign on this question. Mr. Cathery opposed the motion, which was, however, carried by a large majority. The report as amended was adopted, and the Congress then adjourned.On the 10th inst., the whole day was devoted to the consideration of the following resolution, which was carried by 4,478,000 votes to 77,000 :-(a) This Congress having received the request of the Miners&apos; Federation to consider the Governments rejection of the majority report of the Coal Industry Corn-mission, and the adoption in its place of a scheme of district trustification of the industry, hereby declares that, in conjunction with the miners, it rejects the Government scheme for the governance of the industry as a scheme con-trary to the best interests of the nation, and it expresses its resolve to co-operate with the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain to the fullest extent with a view to compelling the Government to adopt the scheme of national owner-ship and joint control recommended by the majority of the Commission in their Report.(6) To this end the Congress instructs the Parliamentary Committee, in conjunction with the Miners&apos; Federation, to immediately interview the Prime Minister on the matter in the name of the entire labour movement, to insist upon the Government adopting the Majority Report.
(c) In the event of the Government still refusing to accept this position, a special congress shall be convened for the purpose of deciding the form of action to be taken to.compel the Government to accept the Majority Report of the Corn-mission.Mr. Smillie said nothing very new in proposing the resolution, but his speech appears to have been carefully moderate in tone. This is of a piece with the previous action of the Miners&apos; &quot;Federation, and both represent a policy which has had its vindication in the success which has been achieved in gaining the support of the Congress. . Mr. J. H. Thomas said as much in seconding the resolution. He maintained that the miners had shown themselves statesmen in coming to the Congress ; had they attempted to take action &quot; on their own,&quot; he would have been the first to condemn them, for he was against any section of the movement taking to itself a responsibility which belonged to the movement as a whole. He concluded by warning the Congress that the Government would, refuse the demand. Mr. Havelock Wilson opposed the resolution on the ground that State management was not a success in cases where it has been given a trial. Mr. Tom Shaw and Mr. W. Brace supported the motion ; and Mr. Smillie in closing the debate, insisted that the decision of the Government depended on the determination of the Congress, for the five million members of the Congress represented a large part of the nation.Housing.A conference which was called by the Scottish and National Labour Housing Associa-tions was held at Glasgow on the 6th inst. Mr. Stuart-Bunning presided, and the principle was adopted that all capital for housing should be loaned to the local authorities by the State free of interest. The conference also endorsed proposals in favour of taxation of land values, and the conferring on local authorities of large general powers for acquiring land at a price not exceeding the value at which it is assessed for taxation.Women and The League of Nations.A conference organised by the Standing Joint Committee of Women&apos;s Organisations was held at Caxton Hall on the 4th inst. to urge the necessity of securing the representation of women on the League of Nations. - Resolutions moved by Miss Mary Mac Arthur urging &quot;the need of a representation of women on the governing body, and demanding that the Governments making appointments in connection with the League should consult the most representative bodies of organised women in their several countries, were carried. A further resolution advocating the setting-up of machinery in connection with the League for holding an annual International Women&apos;s Conference and for the establishment of a permanent International Women&apos;s Office similar to that of the International Labour Office was also passed.Output of Coal.Mr. Frank Hodges, acting on behalf of the M.F.G.B., issued on the 4th inst. a state-ment with reference to the Board of Trade Return on the Output of Coal. The statement declares that the Return seems like a deliberate attempt to prejudice the public against the Miners&apos; Federation, and gives figures up to the -23rd August showing a gradual increase in output. The explanation of the earlier drop shown in the Board of Trade Return is that the week ending 9th August was Bank Holiday week during which the majority of the miners took their usual three days&apos; holiday. Mr. Hodges protests against the issue of statistical tables from an official source without explanation. With reference to this protest, it should be noted that Mr. Hodges himself isolates from their context the figures to which he takes exception; and that it would be supererogatory for the Board of Trade to append to its statistical tables a statement of all strikes, idle days, holidays, etc., which affect output.Labour and Production.It is reported that Southwark, Greenwich, East Cardiff and Bolton Branches of the A.S.E. have entered protests against Mr. BrownhVs letter to Mr. Bowerman on output. The Bolton Branch demands his resignation and considers that the letter directly serves the interests of the capitalist class.Alien Labour.The Executive Committee of the National Union of Ship Stewards, Cooks, Butchers and Bakers has recommended that no alien labour shall be employed on British ships while British seamen are unemployed. A joint conference of seamen is being arranged to discuss -the question of the elimination of Chinese labour from British ships. .,
-Police. &apos;A demonstration organised by the Police Union and participated in by local branches &apos; of various Trade Unions took place at Hyde Park on the 7th inst. and the following resoju-tion was unanimously carried: &quot;That this meeting of Trade Unions of London and district hereby calls upon the Trades Union Congress to force the question of the Police Union to a successful is^ue.&quot; This may be regarded as a last effort of the Police Union to secure the recognition of the Union and the reinstatement of the strikers. It should be noted that in several provincial towns recently the local police have resigned in a body from the Union.Employers&apos; Federations.The London Cabinet and Upholstery Trades Federation was formed on the 4th inst. by the amalgamation of the Cabinet Trades Federation, the London Centre of the . National Federation of Furniture Manufacturers and the London Cabinet Manufacturers Association.  The president is Mr. J. Croft Smith and the general secretary Mr. H. L. West-Taylor.  The address of the new organisation is 18, Finsbury Square, Fj.C. 2... International Conference on Labour and Religion.This conference; which contained representatives of Labour from various countries . and men of various creeds, concluded its labours in London on the 5th inst. At the last session an international continuation committee was appointed &quot; to serve as a nucleus of the religious counterpart of the Labour Department of the League of Nations.&quot; The British representatives on this Committee are Bishop Gore and Messrs. G. N. Barnes, W. Adamson, George Lansbury and Frank Hodges.. Resettlement and Unemployment.Ex-Service Men and Germans. A public meeting has been held by the Southport Branch of the N.F.D.D.S.S. to protest against the employment of Germans in the town, &quot; while there are 500 ex-Service men unemployed. The South Wales and Monmouthshire Branch of the N.F.D.D.S.S. have passed a resolution calling upon the Government to pro-hibit for three years the importation of German toys, on the ground that the importation of such toys would be detrimental to the interests of at least 60,000 ex-Service men employed in the toy-making industry. This, it may be remarked, is an altogether extravagant contention, as the total number of workers in the toy-making trade is very must less than that figure.Ex-Service Unemployment. The Admiralty has recently sanctioned the appointment -of naval representatives at each of the district directorates of the Appointments Depart-ment of this Ministry. It will be the function of these officers to look after the interests of ; such R.N., R.N.R. and RN.V.R. ex-Service officers and men of similar qualifications asmay require their advice or assistance. Naval advisers have already been appointed : for the London, Bristol, Manchester and Glasgow districts.Disabled Metis Allowances. The Ministry of Labour and the Ministry of Pensions . have issued the following statement:-(1) War Pensions Committees are authorised, where recommended by the Medical Referee, to continue to pay allowances to disabled men in training under the Ministry of Labour over and above the training allowances . which they are receiving from the Ministry of Labour, for (a) &quot; constant attendance &quot; and (b) special diet.  (2) The Divisional Directors of the Ministry of Labour are not responsible for the granting or payment of these allowance which come under the heading of treatment, . and any disabled men who desire their continuation or authorisation should apply to their War Pensions Committees.Before this announcement was made, some dissatisfaction had been expressed by dis-. abled men in training at the new scale of allowances introduced by this Ministry, and a . meeting in Hyde Park on the 7th inst., which was addressed by the President of the N.F.D.D.S.S., strongly protested against the new system.  A meeting of disabled men undergoing training was also held in Birmingham on.the same day, and a resolution pro-testing against the new scheme was passed.Disabled Metis Employment. The report has been issued (Cd. 312) of the committee . appointed last December to review the decisions regarding the licensing of partially dis-abled men as drivers of public motor vehicles, arrived at in July, 1916, by a previous committee.The committee only finds it necessary to vary the previous recommendations in so far . as they relate to eyesight.   It is of opinion (a) that no man with only one eye should be
allowed to drive a public vehicle ; (6) that for all other men regular standards of ocular efficiency should be introduced. It considers that there should be two standards of efficiency of vision-(1) a high standard, on the basis laid down in the previous report, to be applied to all new entrants; (2) a lower standard to be applied to men who have been continually licensed for three years or more, and whose disability may to some extent be deemed to be balanced by their practical experience.Out-of-Work Donation.-The final report of the Committee of Enquiry into the scheme of out-of-work donation&apos; lias been issued (Cd. 305). The Committee recommend that, with a view to the prevention of fraud, the staff detailed for the purpose of investigating the validity of claims by&quot;special inquiries should be further strengthened, and special attention should be given to districts in which there appear to be an excessive number of claims; and that arrangements should be made for closer co-operation with the police. They also recommend that after donation has been received by civilians for a period of 13 weeks, the weekly rate payable to them should be reduced to 15s. in the case of men and 12s. in the case of women, and that the inclusion of an allowance for children in the rate of donation should be further considered, before any extension of the scheme is granted. The Committee also make the following,,, among other, recommendations: Where an applicant is not likely within a reasonable time to be able to pursue employment in the occupation to which he claims to belong, he. should be offered work of a somewhat similar kind, and failure to take up such work should involve the loss of donation. The recommendation contained in the Interim Report that any steps that may be possible should be taken at once to remedy the defects in the quality of the premises and staff of the Employment Exchanges is repeated, and emphasised. Mr. T. Shaw, M.P., sighs the Report subject to reservations with regard to the reduction of the donation and the abolition of the chiidren&apos;s allowance.Out-of-Work Donation Statistics. The number of out-of-work donation policies, remaining lodged for the.United Kingdom showed a continuous decrease during the month of August.  The figures are: 1st August, 553,482; 8th August, 536,986; 15th August, 530,523 ; 22nd August, 510,075 ; 29th August, 478,084.Court of Arbitration.During the week ending 6th September, 1919, the Court of Arbitration heard 29 cases.  13 in London, and 16. in Glasgow.Joint Industrial Councils. ;.Furniture Trade.-The conference convened by the Joint Industrial Council and consisting of 90 representatives of employers and workpeople from the localities (including London) affected by the present strikes and lock-out, began at the Ministry of Labour on the 26th August, and continued on the following days until 29th August, when at a late hour the following agreement was at last reached in regard to sectional work: &quot; That sectional work is recognised as a method of production in the furniture trade and may be introduced into any factory on the understanding that in any workshop where sectional, work is introduced by the employer for the first time, the employer and his operatives shall, jointly agree and decide upon the method in which it is to be applied in the workshop concerned.&quot; During these days the discussion (which was carried on mainly through a Negotiating Committee of four, consisting of two representatives from each side) was almost wholly centred upon the formulation of the principle embodied in the above agreement.. The conference again met, after adjournment, on the 2nd September, and continued till the 5th, when it reached a deadlock on the question of payment by results, the establish-ment of which the employees refused to countenance.Tin-Mining-The Council met on 22nd August. The main business before the meeting was to discuss the application made by the workers for increased wages. The employers stated that in the present condition of the industry no hope could be given that increased wages could be paid. A further plea was made on behalf of the lesser paid surfacemen, many of whom are receiving only 30s. per week, but the employers stated, that no increase could be given unless the output of the skilled workers was greatly increased.. It was. stated on behalf of the employers that the agreement between the unions and the-employers-providing that 23 shifts of 8 hours each per month should be worked was not being observed.Trade Boards.Special Orders have been made applying the Trade Boards Acts to the Hat, Cap and Millinery Trade&apos;, and to the Women&apos;s Clothing Trade which includes the making of mantles, and costumes and light clothing and dressmaking.
A Spcial Order has also been made altering the description of the Tailoring Trade so m to include men&apos;s and boys&apos; and women&apos;s and girls&apos; retail bespoke tailoring. It is pro-posed to set up two Trade Boards under this Order, one for Ready-made and Wholesale Bespoke Tailoring, and one for Retail Bespoke Tailoring. Conferences are to be held on the 22nd and 23rd September, with reference to the allocation of seats on these two pro-posed Trade Boards.(2) District Reports.London and South-Eastern.Unemployment. A reduction of over 5,000 occurred in the live register, nearly 4,000 of which was in respect of men&apos;s registrations.Resettlement. At Canterbury the prospect is discouraging. Shortage of wagons is -causing traffic delays, and shortage of barges affects several firms who obtain delivery of goods through the river Stour. The pressing need of further housing accommodation is hindering the development of firms. The Corporation do not appear to be making any progress with their housing scheme. Plans have been approved for deepening and widening the river and building a basin to accommodate barges for carrying coal from&apos; the Chislet colliery. The London County Council propose to carry out a large scheme of relief works in connection with their drainage system. At Enfield a new factory has been started for Messrs. Spicer Bros., paper manufacturers.General. Labour conditions have again been increasingly satisfactory, and for the first time this year there has been no new strike reported. So far as the prolonged lock-out in the furniture trade is. concerned, the feeling is more embittered in the High Wycombe district, and one or two untoward incidents have occurred.* South Midlands and Eastern.Unemployment. A decrease of 1,800 is reported in the live register.Resettlement&apos;. The settlement of the dyers&apos; and trimmers&apos; strike continues to reduce unemployment in Leicester and Loughborough.  At Ipswich, increased shipping has become available.  At Northampton, a boot factory has been reopened.  The commence-: ment of the flax-pulling season at Peterborough has resulted in a decrease of unemployment.General. The general situation is satisfactory.  In the furniture trade lock-out about . 100 men have been restarted by certain smaller firms who have broken away from their federation.The Nottingham Joint Board for the Engineering and Allied Trades have passed resolutions demanding that income-tax be levied on salaries of  250 and over; that old age pensions be raised to  1 per week and begin at 65 years, and that participators. : in the late strike of the police be reinstated., South-Western.Unemployment. A decrease of nearly 2,000 is reported in the live register, the largest decreases in the area taking place at Bristol and Gloucester.Owing to the cancellation of Admiralty contracts considerable discharges are imminent at the works of Messrs. J. S. White k Co., Ltd., Cowes, and Messrs. John I. Thornycroft &amp; Co., Ltd., Southampton.Resettlement. In Cornwall 500 men have been absorbed in road work. There is still much congestion caused by the shortage of railway trucks at Bristol and Avonmouth docks.General. The labour situation remains unaltered and may be considered generally satisfactory. Difficulties have arisen owing to Joint Industrial Councils having no power to enforce their recommendations, thus placing employers who are willing to carry them into effect in an unfair position compared with their competitors who do not do so. A somewhat similar difficulty has occurred in connection with an award of the Interim Court of Arbitration, whose decision, binding on members of the association parties to the - award, is not universally applicable to the whole trade concerned.West Midlands.Unemployment. The live register shows a decrease of nearly 4,000 of which nearly &quot;2,000 is reported from Birmingham.Resettlement. At Stourbridge the common brick industry is in a precarious condition.* Owing to transport difficulties not a single truck is stated to have been loaded during the
week. Loading which previously cost lOd. per 1,000 is now 4s., 5s. and even 7s. per 1,000. Firms report that at the prices now quoted there is no profit to be obtained from the manu-facture of. this class of brick. There is: a general shortage of winders in the electrical industry, which is holding up the work all round. A shortage of pattern makers and moulders is reported in the engineering trade. The General Electric Company, Witton, are erecting three new factories which will find employment for 700 or 800 workpeople. The Lanchester Motor Company have purchased new works at Tyseley for repairs and component parts. It is estimated that 300 or 400 persons will be employed. In connection with tramway workers it is announced that the last of the 1,600 women engaged in Birmingham during the war will shortly be replaced. In Walsall, Wolverhampton, Coventry and the Potteries, replacement is also nearly completed.General. The industrial position is favourable. Discussion is rife concerning the necessity for increased output. A typical brassfounder estimates his output per unit at 50 per cent, of the pre-war standard. Half the fall he attributes to causes outside his control, and he considers that only a small proportion is due -to design on the part of a section of workers. A representative engineer says it is difficult to compare unit production and attributes little blame to operatives. The change-over is not complete, plant has suffered, and is riot yet well balanced, limits are tightened, and more&apos; exacting requirements exist as to finish. These factors as well as the attitude of workers affect output.Yorkshire and East Midlands.Unemployment The resumption of activity in the coalfield has resulted in a decline of 6,600 in the live register. The situation, however, is not yet normal, and some time may be required to reduce the total of unemployment to the level reached before the coal strike. In many cases coal has not yet been received in sufficient quantities to allow a full resumption of work.Resettlement. A shortage of bricklayers is reported, especially in Derby and Wake-field. There are 776 vacancies for these men registered in the division, and only 24 members in all branches of the building trade are available. A general demand- for moulders also exists. A great shortage of road-making material is preventing the develop-ment of employment in this direction.The Yorkshire Employment Committee are pressing for the immediate employment of locomotives and trucks which are stated to be standing idle at Barnbow, Leeds.General.-Th.e general situation is satisfactory. The reference of the tramways case to arbitration has relieved the position. Some slight disorganisation of the textile industry in the Calder Valley is expected owing to a decided shortage of female labour. In Hudders-field a conference between the engineering employers and workmen decided that all dilutees should be discharged within 14 days provided skilled men were supplied to take their places. In Sheffield, apart from the serious anxiety in regard to the threatened strike in the cutlery trade (see last week&apos;s Report, p. 212), and the uncertainty as to the action of the moulders and coremakers, the outlook is more hopeful.North-Western. ,Unemployment. A fall of 7,000 occurred in the live register, the principal decreases taking place in Manchester, Burnley and Blackburn.Resettlement. At Warrington all skilled building labour has been absorbed. Loam moulders, draughtsmen and sheet-metal workers are in demand in Bolton and district. In Burnley, trade is reported to be improving both in textile engineering and in weaving. At Blackburn trade is improving. The release of plate and loose pattern moulders would give employment to large numbers of workers in skilled trades in the textile engineering industry.General. The position in general is quiet, with the exception of the tramway workers, the moulders and coremakers, and workers in the calico printing trade.Northern.Unemployment. The position continues to improve perceptibly, a reduction of over 1,400 having taken place during the week in the live register.Resettlement-It is still not expected that the cancellation of Admiralty orders will lead to unemployment on the Tyne and Tees, with the possible exception of the naval yard of Messrs. Sir W. G. Armstrong, Whitworth &amp; Co., at Walker.  Shortage of riveters at
Walker and Wallsend is reported to be impeding output in tlie shipyards, and may lead to temporary unemployment among platers. A shortage of ship&apos;s joiners is complained of at Walker, and may he attributed to the fact that the shipyard week is one of 47 hours, as against 44 in general building.General. The industrial situation has been decidedly quiet. The great majority of workers are lethargic in their attitude to national questions at present prominent, and there are no indications of any sudden stoppages.-Wales.Unemployment. A small increase in unemployment is reported, due in the main to the stoppage of work at a Llanelly tinplate factory through shortage of water, and to the effect at Swansea of a dispute among transport workers at the docks, which has since been settled. A considerable increase of unemployment is expected in the Merthyr area as there is no hope of a continuance of work at the Cyfarthfa steelworks.Resettlement. In Cardiff, a shortage of skilled labour in the shipbuilding and building industries is reported, involving unemployment among the unskilled. It may be interesting to note that the Commonwealth of Australia intend to run a regular line of steamers to Australia, taking in cargo among other places, at Newport (Mom), where the first steamer will load on the 13th September.A seam of best quality anthracite coal has been struck in the Neath area, and coal will be available in a few months.A revival appears to have begun in the tinplate and galvanized sheet industries, orders being plentiful despite American competition. In twelve months the number of steel and galvanized sheet mills in operation has increased by 22, and the number of tinplate mills by 112.General. The industrial situation is still satisfactory. The coalfield is free of strikes&apos; and there are hopes that a settlement of the craftsmen&apos;s dispute in the steel and other trades will be effected.Scotland.Unemployment. The total on the live register has decreased by 2,900. The harvest demands for unskilled workers is still increasing. Dismissal of large numbers of men from the Admiralty works at Scapa has resulted in a number of unskilled labourers being thrown out of employment, and at Wick the approaching end of the herring-fishing season has led to unemployment, some of the men involved being coopers.Resettlement. The suspension of Admiralty orders may lead to unemployment in the shipbuilding industry, but there is no evidence at present that the disturbance will be serious. Men paid off in the Greenock area are expected to find employment without difficulty. The supply of material for the shipbuilding industry, notably in Ayr, is still insufficient. Line fishers, who predominate in the Helmsdale district complain that owing to difficulty in transport to the southern markets, they cannot carry on their occupation.Complaints are being received from every direction as to the slow progress of housing schemes.Part V.-Disputes. (a) Involving a Stoppage of Work.Building and Allied Trades.Building.-T\ie five week&apos;s strike in the building and allied trades at Newtown has been settled, the men getting an advance of 1\d. an hour, the carpenters and joiners to have Is. M. and labourers IS.Mining and Quarrying.Coal Mines, Lanarkshirc-The strikes at Milmvcod and Udston Collieries, Lanarkshire, have been settled, the miners accepting the recommendation of the executive committee of the union to resume work.Owing to the removal of three miners from their -places and the substitution of other men, the miners at Bardykes Colliery have struck.  Five hvndred men are affected.(C1882) 2K
South Wdes.-0v6t 4,000 miners are on strike at Blaenavon (Mon.) because on the 6th inst. the workman&apos;s train run by the company was late and an official refused to allow 50 men to arrive late at the pit-head.Staffordshire.-Following upon the decision of the Willenhall magistrates that the check -weighman, Daniel Cartwright, be removed, arrangements were made by the Company for the Holly Bank Colliery to be reopened on the 8th inst. for the resumption of work. Despite an appeal from the Pit Committee and the checkweighman concerned, the men declined to return unless Cartwright was reinstated pending an appeal.Metal, Engineering and Shipbuilding.Steel Workers.-!)! connection with the South Wales steel-trade deadlock, the men held a conference at Cardiff on the 6th inst. Representatives of workmen and employers met at the Ministry of Labour on the 9th inst. and the employers made certain offers which the men&apos;s representatives will put before a mass meeting of the employees.The strike of engineers at the works of the Campbell Gas Engine Co., Ltd., Halifax, on the question of training ex-Service men is now in its eighth week. On Mr. Campbell refusing to accept the intervention of the Halifax Conciliation Board, the engineers (6th inst.) decided to continue the strike (see Part II.).Transport.Dockers. The strike of dockers at the port of Dublin continues, and at present there seems to be no prospect of an early settlement. On the 6th inst. the Lord Mayor presided at a con-ference of representatives of the shippers and of the Irish Transport Workers&apos; Union but no agreement was reached. The noticqs which the Dublin shippers have served expire on the 30th inst.On the 6th inst. dockers at Goole struck, refusing to handle frozen horse-flesh for despatch to Antwerp for food purposes.A thousand men engaged in unloading overseas steamers struck at Belfast docks on the 8th inst. owing to the refusal of last week&apos;s application for an increase of wages.Ships&apos; Officers Acting on the instructions of the Coast-wise Masters, Mates and Engineers&apos; Association, ships&apos; officers at Bristol channel ports ceased work on the 8th instant, because some shipowners are not prepared to carry out certain arrangements endorsed by the -Shipping Controller, which have been arrived at with the ships&apos; officers by the National Maritime Board.Textile Trades.Jute. There is now a partial resumption of work at Dundee. The union officials are strongly urging the strikers to return to work, and on the 3rd inst. a meeting of the Joint Committee of Jute and Flax Workers&apos; Union, the Calenderers&apos; Union, and the Tenters&apos; Union deGided to postpone the proposed ballot-vote until work is resumed.Woodworking.Furniture.-Th.e Conference convened by the Industrial Council for the Furnishing Trades with a view to settling the lock-out broke down on the 5th inst., after eight day&apos;s negotiations;, over the question of payment by results.  It is reported that some firms in Bristol, Nottingham . and Leicester have broken away from their federation and are restarting work.Leather Trades.Hand-made Boots. There is still no prospect of a settlement of the dispute in the hand-made boot trade in Glasgow. The latest offer of the employers has been rejected by the men, who have intimated their intention of disbanding their present negotiating committee.Food, Drink and Tobacco.Dairy Trades-The milk-dealers of Southport have returned to work after a week&apos;s strike. They asked for an increase from Id. to 8d. per quart and the local food committee is now allowing T\d. for the first part of the month and 8d. for the last 12 days.agriculture-Some hundreds of agricultural workers are on strike in the Tamworth district of Staffordshirede manding a 50s. a week minimum and a 48-hour week. The farmers state that the Wages Board fixed the terms until 1st October.Half of the fishing fleet of 220 vessels from Aberdeen are laid up as a result of the owners&apos; lock-out in consequence of the men&apos;s demand for a clear 24 hours in port after settling day. The Ministry of Labour-is arranging for. a conference between trawl owners and the Trade Union officials. If the whole fleet is laid up it is reported that over 5,000 workers will be directly affected. r\
(b) Not Involving a Stoppage of Work.Building and Allied Trades. v-The Liverpool master-builders having made a local settlement with their employees for 2s. an hour, which is id. more than is provided for by the North-Western Area Joint Council Scheme, demands are forthcoming from all parts of the area for an advance of id. an hour to all grades. .The Southeastern Conciliation Board has made an award in the building trade in West Surrey under which carpenters and bricklayers will receive Is. Qd. per hour, painters Is. 5d., scaffolders Is. id., and labourers Is. 3d.The Manchester Corporation have refused to pay the paviors&apos; labourers Is. id. an hour, the district rate for builders&apos; labourers.  A strike is ordered for the 8th inst.Mining and Quarrying.Lanarkshire.-Lanarkshire branches of the Miners&apos; Association are prepared to accept 13&apos;51 per cent, increase on the piece rates.&apos;Metal, Engineering and Shipbuilding.Steehnoulders. The threatened lockout in the Scottish steel casting trade has been with-drawn on the understanding that a conference of representatives of hoth sides will be called to consider the claim of the moulders employed by the Steel Castings Ltd., Parkhead, for payment while the works were closed for repair.Founders. In consequence of the failure of the conference between, the^ Engineering Employers&apos; Federation and the Friendly Society of Ironfounders and the Amalgamated Society of Core Makers on the 4th inst., strike notices will take effect from the 20th inst. 37,000 moulders and coremakers are involved.Tin-plate Workers. South Wales tin-plate workers were granted the full 12-1 Per cent-increase as from June 20th by an award of the 4th inst.Shipyard Workers. The Court of Arbitration has granted the Ship Constructors&apos; and Ship-wrights&apos; Association at Hull a 20 per cent, advance on piece-work rates for drillers and hole-cutters employed on certain branches of ship construction.The Admiralty&apos;s offer of an advance of 2s. per week to the Amalgamated Society of En-gineers, the Boilermakers&apos; Society, and the other organisations concerned, was considered inadequate by the men, but the ballot gave a majority in favour of arbitration. (See this Report, p. 172.) .Textile Trades.Dyeing and Finishing. A meeting of the Yorkshire and Lancashire delegates of the trade union interested in the dyeing and finishing industry decided to give notice to terminate the present agreement and to place new terms before the Industrial Council of the Trade.Woollen Trade. A mass meeting of the Bradford District of the General Union of Textile Workers ratified the agreement for a 10 per cent, advance on basic rates on the 3rd inst. &apos; Spinning operatives are, however, dissatisfied with the award.Transport.Coastal Trade.&apos; Coast-wise masters, mates and engineers of Liverpool decided to call a strike on the 8th inst., unless the scale of payment adopted by the Maritime Board and the Shipping Controller during the war is put into operation without further delay. No further information with regard to this matter has been received.Public and Public Utility Services.Gas Works. The dispute at Newtownards which has existed for the last 15 weeks between the council and their employees in the gasworks, etc., is satisfactorily settled. Work was resumed on the 1st inst.Asylum Attendants. The strike of the attendants at the Clonmel Lunatic Asylum (Co. Tipperary) which has lasted 12 weeks was settled on the 9th inst. the matters in dispute being left over to arbitration. .Miscellaneous Trades. -Brushmahers. Maidstone brushmakers, about 50 in all, employed by Messrs. Kent Brothers are on strike for recognition of their union, the National Society of Brushmakers, and the union rate of wages.Gas Coal Tippers. The gas coal tippers at Liverpool ceased work on the 3rd inst. demanding a weekly increase of 6s.
Tramway WorJcers.-On the 5th inst., the Minister of Labour met representatives of the Municipal Tramway Association, the Tramways, and Light Railway Association, and the Transport Workers&apos; Federation at the Ministry of Labour, when it was agreed that the claim for 12s. advance should be referred to the Interim Court of Arbitration. As the respective parties could not agree whether the claim should be heard by districts or on a national basis, it was arranged that the question should be referred to the Court for decision and that a preliminary hearing to consider this should be granted to the parties on Monday, September 15th.Woodworking.Upholstering Workers. The report that the Liverpool retail upholstery workers had arranged an agreement with the Master Builders&apos; Association as to wages, which was mentioned in this Report p. 191, is erroneous. The agreement in question was made between the Liverpool cabinet makers and the Master Builders&apos; Association.Pottery Trades.While no final settlement has been reached in connection with the recent notices given by the English China Manufacturers&apos; Association for a reduction of making prices, representatives of the Association and of the National Society of Pottery Workers agreed on the 4th inst. to recommend to their societies that in.no case shall earnings be decreased by the adjustment.Food, Drink and Tobacco.Poultry Trade. The National Warehouse and General Workers&apos; Union has negotiated increases for its members engaged in the poultry trade as dressers, etc. The minimum for boys of 14 years is 18s. ; and for men of 21,  3 3s.; the rates for women are graded between 15s. and 32s. 6d.Butchers. Birmingham butchers have declined to discuss terms with the Journeymen&apos;s Butchers&apos; Federation on the ground that the Union does not represent a- majority of the men.Public and Public Utility Services.Workhouse Officials. Bolton Board of Guardians has granted the officers at the workhouse a 50-hour week.Agriculture.The Somerset Wages Committee has decided to&apos; support the reduction of the hours of work for farm labourers to 50 per week in the summer and 48 in the winter. The West Somerset Branch of the Agricultural Labourers&apos; Union is demanding a minimum wage of 50s. per week.R. S. HORNE.All inquiries relating to1 this report should be addressed to : Intelligence Division,Ministry of Labour,Montagu House,Whitehall,London, SW. 1.

</content>
</cab>
