<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/88/0 images: 213-222</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
se Property of^ &apos;3 Qovommoi i/Sir,MINISTRY OF HEALTH, Whitehall, S.W.I. 12th September, 1919.Hi1 am directed to forward herewith the following reporton the work of the Ministry of Health during the month of. .,.....i*August.Yours faithfully,Secretary,The War Cabinet.Secretary. /......... -.....-........-I.   HOUSING.1*   Housing. Town Planning, &amp;c. Aot.   A circular letter was issued on the 25th August eaTlirigthe attention of local authorities to the obligations imposed upon them by the new Housing Act and enclosing a Form of Survey for their assistance in preparing tho scheme which they are required to submit within three months of the passing of the Act.   A memorandum containing a summary of the chief provisions of the kcp has also been issued to each member of a local authority.2.    Hpusing Advisory Counci 1.   The full Ccunoil has not met durinfflhe month, but the Sub-Committees appointed to advise cn particular questions have continued their work.   The Women1s Sub-Committee have drawn up their report which has been signed and submitted to the Minister.   The Contract Sub-Committee have also presented their report and submitted a model form of contract which will be issued at a very oarly date.    The specification Sub-Committee have presented their report and submitted a podel specification which&apos; has been issued. The constitution of the Sub-Committees on Agricultural Rents and Slum Areas is practically complete, and the first meetings will ne held at an early date.3.   Conversion of Houses into Plats.   A manual with regard to schemes of conversion&quot;&quot;has&quot;&quot;boenltrawn up and issued to local authorities in order to assist them in the execution of these schemes, .  The Manual contains information as to the kind of property suitable for conversion, the structural and sanitary requirements which should be complied wi:h, and the procedure to be adopted by loc&apos;4 authoritioa in acquiring the houses and submitting their schemes to tnj ministry. i.Typical plans of houses showing the kind of pwl; :o bo done are included.   Preliminary stops for the ac^uici-i^n of a number of houses in London have already been taken by vhe Lsndon Housing Board, approximately 1,000 houses having boon inspected.
4*    flee of Huts f of housing purposes.   The Ministry have decided that schemes lor the use of hattjot housing purposes ^bpitted by local authorities and approved hy the Ministry, should rank tot financial assistance as part of the local authority1a housing schemes,   those schemes will ho of two kinds;-(1) for the purchase and conversion of huts to he converted after removal, (2) for tho leasing and conversion of huts &quot;in situ&quot; and the leasing of hostels.   Arrangements have been made with the Disposal Board for tho acquisition of the huts at a valuation made by that Board, less 33 l/3rd per cent die count, and a circular lottor is being issued to local authorities drawing their attention to those arrangements,    Memoranda&apos;on the use of hostels and military huts for civilian workers were submitted to the War Cabinet by tho Jliinistor on the 6th and 14th August,5,   Parliamentary Housing Group.   Two further meetings of tho Group were heToTbefore tHe&quot;recess,  Mr, Baldwin attended the meeting on tho 6th August and. explained the financial position in relation to housing Mid the reasons why the Government could not provide the money required for housing schemes.    He suggested that a Committee should be sot up to draw up a model form of security and to settlo the length of tho.terms.oft which loans should be issued, and also that a central Advisory Financial Committee should be constituted by tho Ministry to advise local authorities with regard to finance.    He pointed out tho undosirabillty of short term loans and asked members to assist the Government in stimulating local authorities to raise money for thomsslvos.  Major Astor attended the last meeting on August 13th and conveyed the thanks fd the Minister to the Group for the assistance thoy had rendered,6,    Acquisition of Land.    The acquisition of&apos; Land Bill has now received the Royal Assent,    A memorandum is being issued to local authorities explaining how this Act affects the proceduro for the assessment of compensation in regard to land acquired for housing purposes.7*    Unfit Dwellings and Unhealthy Areas *    A cornerandum has been issued to the IfotjslKg&quot;^&quot;oMiXssionersinUIoating their duties in regard to unfit dwellings and unhealthy areas and the preliminary steps which they should ta&amp;e for the collection of information from the local authorities in thoir regions.6,    Housing Schemes.  During the five weeks ended 30th August, 980 sites were submitted by local authorities and public Utility eooiotios for tho Ministry1 s approval, making a total of 4,546 (exclusive of a number of sites which had been withdrawn or had boon rejected as unsuitable or for other reasons). Tho total area comprised in these sites was about 44,000 aoros which would provide roughly for some 440,000 houses.    The number of sitos approved was 1,419 covering about 16,000 acres.The totnl number of applications up to tho 30th August for approval of lay-outs was 794 of which the Ministry had approved 379,Up to 30th August house plans for&apos; 30,323 houses in all had been submitted, and of those; tho Ministry had given approval for 17,396 houses.A memorandum on the present position of housing was submitted to the War Cabinet by&apos;the Hiniator On the: 15th August,II,   HEALTH.1,- 8malXpox. Curing the month of August, prior to the 29th, 22 cases&quot;of smallpox have been roportod *nd one case has; been brought to this country on a vessel which arrived at
Liverpool. Of the 22 cases, 8 occurred in the City of Manchester, and 6 cases in Common Lodging Houses have been reported from Liverpool. One recent case has been notified from from Wolverhampton and possibly this may be followed by others. In places previously invaded the spread of the disease has been checked. The Government  Lymph Establishment had as stock of 1,276,000 tubes of lymph in hand at the end of the month. 62,467 tubes of vaccine lymph have been issued during the four weeks ended 27th August.

The Ministry have undertaken to supply the lymph required by the Government of Nigeria during the year 1920, at a cost of 2d. per tube containing sufficient for one vaccination.

2. Rabies. 21 cases of persons bitten by suspected animals have been dealt with as they occurred. The majority of these cases occurred in or near London.

3. Malaria. Administrative arrangements have been made for carrying out the provisions of Article XI of the Public Health (Malaria etc.) Regulations 1919 in the Hoo Rural District and the Queenborough Urban District.   A house to house enquiry in connection with indigenous malaria in the Isle of Grain has been completed. Visits of enquiry have been made and the necessary preventive steps taken in various areas in which cases of true  indigenous Malaria occurred during the month. A note of the malaria position in England and Wales has been issued weekly to officers and Departments concerned, and laboratory work in connection with the disease has been continued.

4. Plague. The Ministry of Health were notified on the 19th August by the Deputy Medical Officer of Health of the Port of London Sanitary Authority that a member of the crew of the S.S. "CLAN LAMONT" was suffering from plague. The vessel was then in dock, but has since been taken into the river and fumigated. The diagnosis has been confirmed by the Bacteriologist of the Ministry. No plague-infected rats have been found on the vessel nor have any further cases of illness occurred on board, and the ship has sailed from the Bort of London.

5. Enteric Fever. An outbreak of enteric fever has occurred in the Clay Cross Urban District, Derbyshire. In 88 houses, which comprise two crows, some 75 cases of the disease have occurred. The origin of the disease is obscure. The matter is being investigated.

6. Encephalitis Lethargica. Among a total number of 23 persons in a Home for Girls in Derby twelve cases of encephalitis lethargica have occurred and there have been five deaths. Inquiries have been made into the circumstances associated with the outbreak.

7. Poliomyelitis. The seasonal rise in the prevalence of poliomyelitis has commenced, 37 cases having been notified in England and Wales in the fortnight ending 23rd August.

8. Tetanus. The Ministry have agreed with the Disposal Board, subject to Treasury sanction, to purchase a stock of anti-tetanus serum, surplus to Army medical requirements, at the nominal price of 1d. per phial. The serum is suitable suitable for, the prophylactic treatment of tetanus and will be supplied gratuitously to the Medical Officers of Health of Counties and County Boroughs for local distribution to medical practitioners. Arrangements are being made whereby the Scottish and Irish Boards of Health may participate in the distribution.


9.    Jood Poisoning (?)   An outbreak of illness has occurred in a Poor Maw Institution at Bristol, some 60 of the inmates being fttfcotfitod,&apos;   The outbreak is considered locally to be due to pod poisoning.    The circumstances are being investigated.i        , .10.   Venereal, Diseases. A White Paper has been issued containing a Note, addressed to the Minister by the Chairman of the Interdepartmental Committee on Infectious Diseases in connection with Demobilisation, on Prophylaxis against Venereal Disease.    The Note deals mainly with the advisability or otherwise of officially making available for the civil community certain methods of prophylaxis in venereal diseases (commonly spoken of as the &quot;packet1&apos;: system) which have been publicly commended as having been successful among combatants during the war.    The Committee are not.;satisfied that there has been sufficient evidence put before them of the beneficial results gained by the distribution of prophylactic packets in various Forces to prove the value.of the system or to justify them in recommending its official encouragement among the civil population,    They state that unquestionably there have been many individual cases which appear to afford positive evidence in favour of a system of distribution of &quot; such prophylactics before exposure to infection;   but the volume of such evidence is too small and too exceptional,-, and . the instances of its failure, even under favourable circumstances, are too numerous, to allow of any other conclusion than that in view of the considerations mentioned above, and of the administra-tive and social difficulties involved, the official application of a packet system to the oivil community is neither desirable nor practicable.A prosecution of some importance under the Venereal Disease Act, 1917, took place at the london Sessions during the month.    A chemist and his manager were/both charged nth having, contrary to Section 1 of the Act, inserted an ..; advertisement in a daily paper offering to treat persons generally for venereal diseases, and with having, contrary to Section 2, offered for reward to prescribe ascertain remedy for the same.    The ohemi3t was found guilty on both counts and sentenced to four months&apos; imprisonment in the second division, in addition, to paying the taxed costs of the prosecution. His manager, having been found guilty on the second count only, ms sentenced to six weeks1 imprisonment in the second division.11.   Tuberculosis. The Report of the Committee appointed in April, 1919, by&apos; ihe Minister of Health and the Minister of Pensions &quot;to consider and report upon the immediate practical steps which, should be taken for the provision of residential treatment for discharged soldiers and sailors suffering from tuberculosis-and for their re-introduction into employment, especially on the land&quot; has now been presented to Parliament and has been published.    -The recommendations contained in the Report are under consideration by the Ministry and the other Departments concerned, and the financial proposals, so far as they relate to the establishment of Training Colonies and Village Settlements for tuberculous ex-service men, are to be considered by a small Departmental Committee appointed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.The number of beds for the treatment -of tuberculosis in institutions approved by the Ministry has increased during the month by 100 to a total of 14,495.    During the five weeks ended the 29th August, 1919, 837 cases of discharged service men suffering from tuberculosis have beon notified to the Ministry as having been sent by English Insurance Committees to sanatoria and other residential institutions under the special arrangements for the preferential treatment of these men.
12,    National Health Insurance.    The National Health Insurance Bill, referred to in the report for July, passed through its remaining stages without amendment and received the ftoyal Assent on Au^dst 15th.1   It is, however,  doomed to have coxae into operation oh Jtlno ,30th,   In the cfese of1 non-manual workers the limit of the raid Of ;iremuhOration for the purposes of compulsory Health Insurance is now raised to        a yeaf(  The necessary instructions for giving effect to tho provisions of ..\ the now Act have boon issued to Approved Societies and arrangements have been jaado to enable persons who are so entitled to claim exemption.13.  Hatornity and Child Wolf aro.    During-; the past month approval has been g&quot;ivon to proposals by 38 local authorities ^and 4 voluntary agencies for extending thoir schemes of maternity  ? and child welfare.   In throe of those cases the extensions include the acquisition of premises for maternity and child welfare centres and homos for unmarried mothers and their infants, and in ono case a loan amounting to  2,500 was sanctioned.  During the month the number of municipal Health Visitors was increased by 7;   the numbor of Health Visitors employed by voluntary agencies decreased by 2 transferred to municipal service;   the number of District Nurses Oi/iployed as part-time Health Visitors remained stationary;   the number of municipal Contros increased, by 23;   and the number of voluntary centres has remained stationary.14i  good Control.  Tho views of tho Minister have been invited by the Food Controllor on his proposal to iseuo an order giving him power, where he thinks necessary on grounds of efficiency and economy, to direct certain areas to be combined undor a Joint Food Committoo.  Hitherto all combinations of this nature have boen arranged voluntarily between the local authorities concerned.    The Minister has raised no objection to tho proposal and has undertaken to issue a covering Order to local authorities under Regulation 2 J of the Defenoe of the Realm Regulations,15.   Condensed Milk.    A number of representations having been received^rorFlfteTood Controller and others regarding the unsatisfactory labelling of ^any brands of condensed milk, the minister has decided to proceed with tho Regulations which wore drafted on the subject by the Local Government Board in 1914. ; Tho draft regulations havo new boon brought up to date and referred to tho other Government Departments concerned for thoir observations.    The regulations will require all rocopt*icl3s containing skimped condensed $ilk on importation into or on sale in this country to bo labelled:-  &quot;This is sktacd milk,   It should not be given to babies&quot;;   and those containing a bettor cla.ss condsnsod milk, or dried milk, to boar a declaration as to tho minimum fat and othor solid contents of the milk.    Tho porcontago of added sugar will also have to bo declared in tho caso of swoetenod condensed milk.16,   Heat Inspection &amp;c.    A representation has been \rocoivod  roir the &quot;SwindbnTown Council asking for tho ro* institution of tho system of Goverhinont-authorisod slaughter-houses to which the bulk of casualty and fourth grade (wastod and obviously diseased) cattle wore, under tho Scheme of the Hiniatry of Food, required to bo sent for slaughter,   A number of these slaughterhouses, including that at Swindon, havo b03n discontinued, and tho Town Council draw attention to the reduced amount of diseased moat discovered sinco this took place.
. II 169At the request of the National Federation of Meat Traders Associations a deputation was received on 1st August to place before the Minister the views of the trade regarding improved methods of handling meatj the licensing of retail purveyors and premises, and compensation for the destruction of diseased animals ana meat.-    The deputation undertook to submit more definite proposals on these matters at a later date.17.   Water Power Bill.   A memorandum on this subject was submitted To&quot; the&quot; wSr^ablnet by the Minister on the 13th August.18.   Port Sanitary Administration.    A memorandum on this^ subject was suBmltted to the War&quot;CaFlnet by the Minister on the 15th August.19.   weekly Recordmof the Occurrence of Infectious Pipeases at Porte eTc&quot;&quot;&quot;wtq&amp;8Z   &quot;&quot;&quot;In cbTLabofaTTon&quot;wi&quot;th the&apos; foreign &apos; V Office and colonial Office the arrangements for obtaining regular repor-cs of the above occurrences have now been completed. The weekly record now includes information relating to plague, cholera, yellow fever, typhus, and influenza, and is issued In printed form-,    a summarised abstract is prepared fortnightly and sent to the Colonial Office to be cabled to certain British Dominions.International commission.    One of the Senior Medical Officers has gone to Poland a3 a member of an International Commission appointed by the League of Red Cross Societies, to investigate &quot;the public health conditions in Poland with a special view to providing against the spread of typhus and other epidemict across Europe.21.   introduction of Diseases by Persons arriving by Air. A ConferericlTKas TeJJcen&apos; placebo el; ween one or tne deniorTledical Officers and representatives of the Air Ministry respecting the arrangements to be made for preventing the introduction of disease into the country by persons arriving by air from foreign counties.22*  fi  * e International dTHygiene Publique.   The Ministry have suggested^sTel^h^desira^ iJritish Dominions beingofficially represented at the next meeting of the Committee of the Office International d&apos;Hygiene Publique at Paris in October next, and that the British delegates should, if possible, confer together before the meeting, \111*   05flSRAfc,I. public Works, - During the month 387 applications by local aulHorr^ies^for sanction to loans have been received as compared with 295 during July.   The total amount of the loans sanctioned during the month was  1,221,504, as against  1,166,314 during July.   The principal purposes for which loans wore sanctioned during August were electricity under-takings ( 289,646), land settlement for ex-service men ( 268,804) gas undertakings ( 212,802) * sewerage and sewage disposal ( 189,448), street improvement i  113,116], public walks and pleasure grounds ( 48,108), and schools ( 41,932).
fcfc    Land Settlement,  During tho month oonsent has bean giton to tho borrowing&quot;by the County council a of Bedford, Buckingham, Cambridge, Cornwall, Denbigh, Devon, Dorset, Essex, Hartford, 3Cont, Montgomery, Norfolk, Somerset. Southampton, West Suffolk, Warwick, Wiltshire and the West aiding of Yorkshire, of loans amounting to  262,804 for tho purchase of 59 estates having a total area of about 7,000 acres for the settlement of ex-service men on the land,&quot; As compared with last month thie shows an increase of . 15,780 in the amount sanctioned and 1,200 acre a in tho area to be acquired.,3t    Registration of Electors. - A circular has been sent to Registration Officers in*fonHIng thorn of tho arrangements made, in consultation with tho Army Council, Royal Air tforco, and the Admiralty, for dealing with tho absent voters1 list for the Third Register under tho Reprosontation of the People Act.   The liiniator has also instructed Registration Officers to order a sufficient number of copies of the Third Register to enable effect to be given, in the preparation of tho electors&apos; lists for the next Spring Register, to tho arrangements for reducing tho cost of those lists agreed upon at the conference with party agents and registration officers montionod in tho Report for July.4. Bye-Elections, In accordance with the arrangement mado some time ago with tho Whips of tho various parties, tho Ministry were informed of the intontion to move for the writs for the bye-oloctions in tho Pontefract and Widnes Divisions, and gave an early intimation to the Returning Officers and the Army Council and other Departments so that there should be no delay in the iasuo of ballot papers to absent voters,5*    Meet ion of Councillors of ^tropolit^n Boroughs. -An Ordor is&quot; in &quot;preparation,&quot;&quot;and wTGH&amp;o&quot; &quot;issued &quot;oarly in September, for altering the rules as to tho election of Kotropolitan Borough Councillors so as to allow mora time for some of the proceedings at thoso elections.   The Autumn Register of Electors comes into force five days earlier then was the case before tho passing of tho Roproaentation of the Poopla Act, and thus allows of an oxtension of time for tho proceedings at the ordinary olection of Metropolitan Borough Councillors in Hovomber,6*    Election of County Councillors and Hetropolitran Borough CouncjlXors&quot;In,november&quot;,&quot; -&quot;&quot;The Army Council have agreed to granlfleave oT&quot;absenco&quot;to&quot;candidates at these elections who are serving in the Army, in casos whoro application for auch leave is made through tho Hintstry,7.    Transfer of Powers. - A draft Ordor in Council has been considered by officers of &quot;the two Departments concomed for fixing the date on which the transfer of powers of thia Ministry to the Ministry of Transport is to tako place and for excepting cortcin powers from the transfer.   It has boon decided that this Ministry should retain all powors in relation to tho sanctioning to loans to local, authorities, tho approval of housing schemesi and the confirmation of certain byelaws, and that in tho exercise of the excepted powers, so far as they relate to roads, bridges and vehiclea&quot;and traffic thereon, this Ministry shall act in consultation with the Ministry of Transport,    The question of oxoopting other powers from transfer is to be further considered by the two Departments.
Orders in Council are also in preparation for transferring to the Board of Education powers of this Ministry in relation to public libraries-4 end for transferring the powers of this Ministry in relation tr gas undertakings of local authorities to the Board of Trade and transferring the powers of the Board of Trade in relation to water companies to this Ministry.8* Subscriptions. -   The Ministry have promised to sanction contributions oy local authorities in the London Area to the expenses of the Public Works Conciliation Board for the London Area.9, War Memorials,   Sanction hae been given to reasonable expenditure&quot;Ty*&quot;a local education authority in providing tablets as war memorials in public elementary schools maintained by them.potato^Spraying;, - Replying to an application by a Parish Council for &quot;sanction to the provision of a potato-spraying machine, the Ministry have forwarded a copy of a notice recently issued in the press by the Board of Agriculture and Fisheries in which it is stated that the Ministry will offer no objection to the incurring of expenditure but consider that a suitable charge should in all cases be made for the use of the machine.  Ho further authorisation from the Ministry is necessary.11. War Bonuses^ The Ministry have expressed the opinion that warBonuses granted to officers of local authorities should be included in their remuneration for the purpose of calculating their superannuation allowances;   that such allowances once fixed and awarded could not afterwards be reduced on the grounds that some of the emoluments on which they were based were temporary, and that the conditions necessitating such temporary payments had,-ceased to exist; and that there appears to be no legal authority for making temporary increases, on account of war time conditions, in superannuation allowance fixed before the war.12. New Appointments.   The Ministry have continued to urge local aulEbii ties &quot;I o consider favourably the applications of ex-service men for appointments as Medical Officers of Health, Sanitary inspectors and Inspectors of Nuisances.    five of the seven Medical officers of Health and eleven of the thirteen Inspectors of Nuisances appointed during the month had served in the porces.13. Salaries of Sanitary inspectors and Inspectors of ITuisanees. In&quot;*accoroance with a general&apos; direction&quot; given by the TOilafcTf endeavours have been made to raise the standard of Sanitary inspectors and Inspectors of Nuisances by securing the payment to them of adequate salaries.   Two Metropolitan Borough CouncilB have been requested to consider the scale of salaries of their sanitary Inspectors.    In one district outside London the payment to a whole-time Inspector of Nuisances of a salary of  400 - 25 - 450 p,a. was sanctioned and in five others salaries were approved which, together with the small salaries paid to the officers for various minor duties made the total remuneration of each 5300 p.a. or over.14&quot; Poor fraw Officers.   It has been decided to discontinue, the practice ofTimTHhg sanction to appointments for the period of the war, in view of the fact that demobilisation is so largely completed, while some considerable time may yet elapse before the actual termination of the war is formally notified.
m^5. Destitution due to strikes,   Ih the early part of the month&apos; it became apparent that&apos; the coal strike in Yorkshire, would necessitate some special arrangements for the relief of the destitution caused by it.    Two principles were laid down by the Minister (l) that relief to strikers should not be encouraged in any way (cf. A.G. v Merthyr Tydfil 69 L.J. Ch, 299 (1900)), and (2) that relief to persons in need other than strikers should preferably be in the form of outdoor relief, given in money or kind, without the imposition of any condition such as a require-ment to perform a task of work.   In technical language the relief was to be given under Article 12, not under Articles 9-11 of the Relief Regulation Order, 1911.   One or two boards of guardians actually proposed to open a labour yard, but so far as is known took no further action in that direction.   Strike relief has been a marked feature in the Herasworth, Doncaster, Worksop, Rotherham, Wakefield, Htoislet, wortley, Barnsley, Dewsbury, $Forth Bierley, and Pontefract Unions, but it is not at present possible to state to what extent the numbers of persons relieved have been affected.    It has however been stated that Hemsworth spent  6,946 on special relief, and that Pontefract spent  7,000.    As was perhaps to be expected, the machinery for controlling relief was in some instances overwhelmed, notably at Hemsworth, though no doubt better arrangements would gradually have been made had the strike continued.   The Pontefract, Dewsbury, North Bierley, Wakefield, worksop, wortley and Barnsley Unions appear to have confined themselves to the grant of relief in kind, and made no money allowance a.   The Hemsworth (juardianB have applied for a Government gravit in aid of the exceptional expenditure which has fallen upon the apparatus but have been informed that the Minister knows of no legal authority for such a grant.   It is probable that, in spite of the reference of Guardians to the Merthyr Tydfil case, persons actually on strike did in a certain number of cases succeed in obtaining relief.16* Military Occupation of poor law Premises.   Of an approximate total number of&quot;&apos;?5-000&apos;po&quot;or&quot;law&quot;Feds comprised in poor law premises which were during the war lent to the military authorities in connection with the provision of military hospital accommodation approximately 44,000 had been returned to the various poor law authorities by the end of August.W* Relief of War Distress.   The grants made from the National Relief Fund upon tHe&quot;recommendation of the government committee during the month, were as follows:- To Local Representative Committees for the provision of direct assistance ............... 1,622TO Local Representative Committees for the relief of air raid distress.................. 160To the Central charities Committee for the relief of repatriated civilians,............... 2,000To the United Russia Societies Association for the relief of British refugees from Russia .... 500To the Canadian Fund committees under the Bast Coast relief scheme (for the payment of rent or mortgage interest accrued up to the end of last March quarter)................................ 100To the Canadian Fund Committees for the re-equipment of lodging-house keepers............. 3,100 &apos;Total.....    7,482
During the month further and final- grants amounting to  894 in all were paid by the Government Committee, out of the refunds received from othor Canadian Fund.Committees, to the Committees for Margate, Broadstairs end the Xs^.e of Thane4i far the provision of special assistance in certain oases of amall traders in their districts in pursuance of the arrangement made with the Bast Coast Conference at the Beginning of this year,Tho Executive Committee of the National Relief Fund have declinod to ma&amp;o further grants to the Canadian Fund Committees in respect of rents etc. of distressed persons for any period subsequent to tho end of last ICarch quarter.    Two applications, however, Groat Yarmouth and Margate, will shortly como before thorn for further consideration.A body has now been formally constituted under the presidency of the Earl of Sandwich to deal with tho cases reported by the Local Representative Committsos or by the Control Charities Committee as eligible for further assistance, at the cost of the National Reliof Fund, and their arrangements aro so far advanood that in the majority of cases it will *v bo practicable to terminate as from the 15th Soptombor the work of the Local Representative Committoos concerned. Those Coamittoos aro now boing thanked for their services and requested to close thoir accounts and remit any balance remaining in hand on that dato.    About 45 Committees of the 217 still active in tho curront quarter have already definitely ceasod to act as almonors of the National Relief Fund, and closed thoir accounts,18,  Assistance^to Aliens,  A large number of aliens have recently bdeh&quot;&apos;roYdas6a&quot;^ and havo returned tothoir homos, but many of thorn for various roasons have at present boon unable to obtain employment,   Humorous enquiries have boon mado on tho subject by Boards of Guardians, and tho Ministry have explained that, as the mon have boon released from intern^ mont, the Government allowances are no longer payablo, and any? necessary assistance from the Guardians must be given by way of ordinary poor relief.In view of the obvious difficulties of this position, tho Ministry communicated with the Homo Office, and an intima-&apos; tion was received from them that the United Alions Relief Societies (Secretary, Kr. W, J, Cable, 68, Finsbury Pavement,E.C,) aro prepared in practically every caso to give a man support fpr a month in order that he may havo time to find a job.   This information has boon cammmicatod to Inspectors, and notified informally to the various Clerks to Guardians who have mads enquiries on tho subjoot,Tho Homo Offico have boon in correspondence with the Ministry of Shipping in regard to tha repatriation of dependants of Russians, but so far it has not boon found practicable to make any arrangements,Tho ministry have boon notified of a case in which a Russian has improperly rotumod to England and beon imprisonod, and they havo intimated that tho Government allowance will no longer bo payable to his dependents,19,   Welfare of tho Blind,   Regulations have beon issued during tho month br&quot;AugU3&apos;t, &quot;governing the distribution of the proposed grant in aid of tho Welfare of tho Blind, which was referred to at page 7 of tho Report of the Local Government Board to tho war Cabinet for tho month of May, 1919,

</content>
</cab>
