<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/88/0 images: 333-334</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 this Document rv &apos;*uLJL. .    ,Memorandum by the Secretary for Scotland regarding   2!)1) the supply of labour for Scottish HousingSchemes., mm **    m&apos;m        --... &quot;*    .a \1.    Up to the week eiid^dj&amp;tlv^september, 1919, the Scottish ard of Health had appcorea of tenders in connexion with the action of 718 housed.   It is anticipated, bower or, that at an jrly date the nunber of houses for which Lenders have boen proved will be very considerably increased.   During the past crimer a large amount of work has heen expended, Wth by the ntral Department and by the Local Authorities, in tW-,prepara--on and adjustment of trie details of housing schemes, &quot;This&quot;i&amp;^ own by the facts that up to date 131 sites have been approved which it is proposed to build 18,510 houses:   that the lay-out 103 sites has been approved:   and that tho type plans of the luses to be erected on 70 sites have been approved.   The total bber of houses of which type plans have been approved is 14,548. e Board are aware that many Local Authorities are now complet-^ g the working drawings of their type plans, with a view to put-ng than in the hands of the measurers, so that the necessary 1 ecifications and schedules for issue to Contractors can be pre-sd.   It is, therefore, certain, as already stated, that at a ry early date there will be a considerable increase in the number nouses in course of ooflS&amp;ruction,2.    Having these facts in view, the. Board had under con-deration at their meeting; on 12th September, the question of-the ppily of labour for Scottish Housing Schemes.    This matter was nsidersd in view of the nature of returns which are received by 8 Board weekly from the Divisional Council of the Ministry of hour in Edinburgh.    These returns summarise the number oi un-ployed workmen in the building trade in Scotlaiid as shown by e particulars received from the various Exchanges throughout oilancL3.    The return for the week ended 5th September showed at according to the Labour Exchange statistics there were only unemployed bricklayers, 131 masons, 53 joiners, 12 slaters, 7 plumbers, 73 plasterers, 141 electricians, 37 painters.4.    The return for the week en ed lit- September has now en received and shows that at that date tee&apos;were unemployed bricklayers, 119xflasonB, 64 joiners, 3.4 slaters, 94 plumbers-^.
Z plasterers, 142 electricians and 47 painters.5,    In view of the comparatively email number of unemployed orkaen in the building trades as shown by these returns, the ;oard wrote to the Divisional Council for Scotland of the MinistryLabour he poss: ake&apos;theathorities in Scotland, and* enquiring whether er any measures could e taken by that Department in anticipation of the building perations to ensure that an adequate supply of labour would bo irailablo..6.    It is clear that if the returns of the Labour Exchanges -present the true position of matters as regards unemployment in e building trades in Scotland, there will not bo nearly suf-cient labour to carry out the housing schemes contemplated.   It s also to be kept in mind that during the war operations in tnnexion with the up4ceep and repair of existing houses and other ildings were reduced to a minimum, and that a very considerable fount of labour will probably be occupied for some time in con-Vdon with these repair operations.    Reports appearing in the rios and other information in the possession of the Board seem to idicate that a considerable amount of building labour may also I required.at an early date in connexion wi.th the erection of pemas, th&amp;s diminishing still further the amount of labour fat may be available for housing schemes.i accordingly strongly support the views contained in Memorandum of 5th September by the Minister of Labour.1SH&quot;BOARD CP HBALTH, EDINBURGH.16th September, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
