<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/53/11 images: 76-79</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTjTS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  July 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (44) 411.25th July, 1944.WAR CABINET.TEMPORARY EMBARGO ON BUILDING AND ALLOCATION OEBUILDING LABOUR.Memorandum by the Minister of Production.IN W.P. (44) 280 I undertook to bring before my colleagues again at a laterelate the question of continuing the building embargo. I have also to submit proposals for the allocation of building labour in the second half of 1944.2. The flying-bomb attacks, however, have had a serious effect upon the.demand for building labour, and it seemed better to postpone consideration ofthese two questions until the situation was clearer. I now submit the following-proposals : 3. The Minister of War Transport agrees with me that on transportgrounds it is no longer necessary to continue the embargo, and I therefore proposethat it should be discontinued forthwith. There is, however, a general shortageof building labour throughout the country, and all proposals for new buildings should continue to be carefully scrutinised.4. In the London area the shortage is particularly acute, both because ofthe extent of urgently necessary building repairs and of the decision to continuethe Phoenix programme.5. I propose, therefore, that in the London area major works should be started only if they are urgently needed in connection with operations or are of equal priority with first-aid repairs. The Minister of Works will consult with me where necessary on any questions of priority which may arise.6. It has been agreed that, as far as possible, the.resources of the buildingindustry should be applied to relieving the position in the . London area.Outside London, therefore, the total of building labour available will be belowrecent levels. For building outside the London area, although the embargo on new projects is removed, Departments should put forward to the Minister ofWorks only those projects which they regard as most urgent. I propose that where such projects raise special difficulties the Minister of Works should referthem to me for decision after consultation with the Departments concerned.Under the present procedure Departments have for some little while past beenasked to refer to the Regional Boards all new projects costing more than  5,000.I suggest that these references should be made at the earliest possible date, since in present conditions so much depends on local circumstances.7. The present emergency demands for building labour have created anumber of uncertainties, and until the situation becomes clearer it would not be practicable to put forward any.realistic allocation of building labour between theDepartments. I hope, however, to be&apos;in a position shortly to submit proposals forthe second half of the year.[27891]
8.   To sum up, I now propose (a) That the building embargo should be discontinued forthwith.(b) That in the London area major works should be started only if they areurgently needed in connection with operations or are of equal prioritywith first-aid repairs.(c) That outside the London area, Departments should put forward only those projects which they regard as most urgent.I have consulted the Minister of Works, who agrees with this paper.O. L.Ministry of Production, Great George Street, S.W. 1,2oth July, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
