<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/227/5 images: 182-343</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[CONFIDENTIAL}  v



THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT



Copy No.



     \10 July 1989



m



80



If^5\ CABINET



V&apos;sP     THE FUTURE OF THE LEGAL PROFESSION

^j^^^Memorandum by the Lord Chancellor



3.



When Cabinet agreed in January this year to the publication

of the Green^?gs&gt;ers on the legal profession (C(89)l, and

CC(89)2nd, *&quot;1iiBvi^v 1 undertook to announce firm decisions

on the future wfjflKL legal profession to Parliament before

the summer rece^wEr^ I now propose to publish these

decisions by way di^^^Jfiite Paper.       A draft of this was



considered by  (CP) on

In   the   light   of t

significantly revised

consideration. Passag

which go beyond mere draft

text.



(E(CP)(89)9 and E(CP)(89)3rd).

cussion   I   now   attach a

White  Paper   for colleagues&apos;

e  there  have  been changes

ve been sidelined  in the



E(CP) was particularly concerned o. clear intention that



rights of audience should be extenawfl should be indicated on

the face of the Bill. I have entirely revised Chapter 2 of

the White Paper (which sets out the /M^osed statutory

objectives) in particular to make i\0sri&quot;3Su? that this

intention will be included in the Bill. \^r Ksed Chapter

2 is attached for colleagues&apos;  consideration ^y^te^x A.



Timing



If colleagues agree, I propose to publish the Whit

Wednesday,  19 July with an oral statement.    The Whi

refers   to   the  draft   White   Paper   on restrictive

practices,  which therefore needs to be published not 1

than mine.     I  understand that  the  Secretary of State



1



IconfipentIaJ




5.



jCONFIDENTMa)



Trade and Industry proposes to publish that White Paper not

later than Wednesday, 19 July by way of a response to a

Parliamentary Question. A draft of my oral statement is

attached at Annex B. The full text of the revised draft

White Paper is at Annex C.



discussed by  (CP)



Judicial concurrence



was concerned that the proposal to require the

ag^eiftftpt of the senior judges to rules relating to the

comj^MWfipe and conduct required for extended rights of

audie70re^3ould be seen as a major concession by the

Governnw&amp;t. To counter this, the intention that rights of

audience should be extended will be made plain on the face

of the Bill ax^&gt;also in the White Paper and in my statement

to Parliamen-^fV.



(b)   Links with



proposed  restrictive  trade practices



legislation V^3&amp;



The White Paper has ?&amp;?&amp;\re-drafted to clarify that it is

only rules relating to^^eO^ompetence and conduct needed for

advocacy and the conduqJ^ ^ litigation to which the Lord

Chancellor&apos;s concurrence y$frrequired by the statute.

All other rules will be /eiroible for review by the

Competition Authority. ^Tha will be particularly

important for any rules the L3fe^Miety chooses to make in

relation to multi-disciplinary pri6^ices.



6.



7.



(c) Contingency fees



The White Paper states that only the lindie^ Scottish system



of  speculative  actions  will  be permittQj/^i

percentage uplift payable based on costs,

I shall make this point plain in the Parliam!



h  a moderate

  damages.

debates.



(d) Conveyancing



As colleagues agreed,  I have reinstated a proposa

preventing   authorised   practitioners from

conveyancing   services   below   their   true cost,

practitioners will be required to certify annually to



!confidential!




I



1



regulatory bodies that they are pricing their conveyancing

services on a fair and reasonable basis to reflect the costs

of providing those services.



ision



.nvite  colleagues&apos;   agreement  to  the  publication of the

White Paper on Wednesday, 19 July.     Provisions on the

y3f  those  set  out  in  the  White  Paper  will   then be

r^t^^Sb for inclusion in the Courts and Legal Services Bill



for



t session of Parliament.



Lord Chancellor&apos;s Department



10 July 1989



  of C



Q



!confidential!



%



X


ANNEX A



2 : The Statutory Objectives



2.1 The Government believes it is of central importance that the

objectives which govern the arrangements for the provision

of legal services in advocacy and in the conduct of

litigation should be simple and clear. Practitioners need

that if they are to deliver what is expected of them. The

professional bodies and other organisations need that to

enforce standards consistently amongst their own members,

in relation to other professions providing similar legal

services. Above all the client needs to understand the

basis of the work and the services for which he is paying.



2.2 The Government therefore proposes to include those basic

objectives in the legislation. All those who contribute to

setting and maintaining standards in the provision of legal

services - the professional bodies and other organisations,

the Lord Chancellor, and the judiciary - will be required

to have regard to those objectives in carrying out their

duties.



2.3 The objectives are:



To lay down standards of education and training

in the provision of services in advocacy or the

conduct of litigation which ensure that those who

offer such services to the public are competent

to do so.



To maintain the standards of conduct in advocacy

and the conduct of litigation which are required

in the interests of the proper and efficient

administration of justice.


To meet those objectives in ways which ensure

that there are no obstacles to access to justice,

and no restrictions which would inhibit the

client&apos;s choice of how he may obtain legal

services imposed on those qualified to provide

legal services or on what those who are qualified

may do, which are not necessary in the interests

of justice.



2.4 The statute will make it clear that the framework it will

create has the express purpose of ensuring the ordered,

flexible and speedy development of fresh ways of providing

legal services to meet clients&apos; needs, especially in

advocacy and litigation, and of ensuring that clients have

a wider choice of providers of such legal services. In

particular, the statute will state a clear intention that

rights of audience should be extended.




CONFIDENTIAL



DRAFT STATEMENT BY THE LORD CHANCELLOR TO THE HOUSE

THE FUTURE OF THE LEGAL PROFESSION



My Lords



When I published the Government&apos;s Green Papers on the legal

profession, which were designed to remove any unnecessary

restrictions in the provision of legal services, I undertook to

make a statement to the House before the Summer Recess. I have

received over 2000 responses to the Green Paper, and held

discussions with many of those directly involved. I would like

to take this opportunity to thank all those who helped in that

process. In  order  not   to   keep   students   and   others waiting



unnecessarily, the Government is today publishing a White Paper

containing   its   proposals   for   legislation. I   would   like to



emphasise that although all the points which were put to me in

writing or orally have been carefully considered, the proposals

are the responsibility of the Government.



Advocacy



We propose to introduce legislation which will set out broad

objectives designed to increase access to justice and to extend

the range of those possessing rights of audience before the

courts. All those involved in granting rights of audience will

be required by the statute to have regard to these objectives.

An independent statutory Advisory Committee on Education and

Conduct will give advice on the achievement of these objectives.

Again there will be a statutory requirement for all those

involved in granting rights of audience to have regard to this

advice. The Advisory Committee will have a membership broadly

as set out in the Green Paper, but, in order to emphasise its

independence from the Government, it will have the power to

appoint its own staff.



The Government proposes that both the Bar and the Law Society

should have a statutory entitlement to grant rights of audience

to their members in all courts. All those called to the Bar

should receive rights of audience in all courts. On

qualification solicitors will receive rights of audience

equivalent to those they now possess. Solicitors will, however,

be eligible also to progress to rights of audience in some or all

of the higher courts, if they have achieved the necessary

standards of competence and and conform to appropriate rules of

conduct.



All rules relating to the competence and conduct of advocates

will continue to be made by the professional bodies, but,

building on the current arrangements for the Law Society&apos;s rules,

all changes in such rules will in the future require the

concurrence of the Lord Chancellor and each of the four Heads of

I3ivision (the Lord Chief Justice, the Master of the Rolls, the

President of the Family Division and the Vice-Chancellor). All


these will be required to have regard to the statutory objectives

and the Advisory Committee&apos;s advice.



Other professional bodies might subsequently be empowered by

Order in Council, approved in draft by both Houses of Parliament,

to grant rights of audience in particular classes of business in

particular courts, provided their competence and conduct

requirements satisfied the Lord Chancellor and the four Heads of

Division.



Similar arrangements will apply for the future to any

professional body which might want to have the right to issue

legal process or to take steps in proceedings on behalf of

others. These rights are at present reserved by statute to

solicitors.



Partnerships and multi-disciplinary practices



The importance of ensuring that both a wide range of barristers

generally and an adequate choice of specialist barristers are

available to take cases in court requires that the Bar should

continue to be able to make its own rules about partnerships and

multi-disciplinary   practices. Considerable   concern was



expressed in the responses to the consultation that removing such

rules might threaten the future viability of the Bar.



Solicitors, who are also frequently involved in litigation, ought

to be treated on an equal basis to barristers. We therefore

propose to remove the existing statutory restrictions which

prevent solicitors forming multi-disciplinary partnerships, but

to provide that both professional bodies the Law Society will

henceforth be allowed to make its own rules about partnerships

and multi-disciplinary practices. Except in so far as such

rules are related to advocacy and the conduct of litigation and

are approved as necessary in the interests of justice by the Lord

Chancellor and the Heads of Division, they will be subject to

review under the restrictive trade practices legislation proposed

in the DTI White Paper.



We propose also to remove the present statutory obstacles to

multi-national practices and to ensure that lawyers from Scotland

and Northern Ireland will have the same rights in England and

Wales (and vice versa) as lawyers from other European

jurisdictions will have under Community Directives.



Conveyancing



The Government proposes to legislate, as the Green Paper

suggested, to replace the provisions in the Building Societies

Act 1986 with a power to allow the Lord Chancellor to recognise

professional bodies as competent to authorise their members as

authorised practitioners to undertake conveyancing for their

borrowers. Conveyancing will be required to be supervised by a

solicitor or licensed conveyancer; and every such authorised

practitioner will be required to offer its clients a personal

interview with the solicitor or licensed conveyancer having

conduct  of  the  transaction.        Throughout  the  transaction, that


solicitor or licensed conveyancer will have a paramount duty

towards the borrower.



There will be a detailed code of conduct laid down by statutory

instrument by which authorised practitioners will have to abide.

Moreover authorised practitioners will be prohibited from

providing conveyancing services to both seller and buyer in the

same transaction and from providing estate agency services to the

seller and conveyancing services to the buyer in the same

transaction. Making the provision of one service conditional

upon taking another (so called &quot;tying-in&quot;) in connection with

house purchase will be prohibited. Authorised practitioners

will be required to charge for their conveyancing services on a

basis that is not less than the true cost of providing them.



These arrangements are designed to provide adequate protection

for individual clients and also protect small solicitor firms

from unfair competition.



Conditional fees



Litigation will be permitted to be undertaken on the speculative

basis now allowed in Scotland. It will also become possible in

such cases for there to be a moderate percentage uplift on the

ordinary taxed costs otherwise payable, within a maximum to be

prescribed by statutory instrument. There should, however, be

no introduction of any kind of contingency fee linked to a

proportion of the damages received.



My lords,   I  have dealt with these  issues  in particular because

they are those about which there has been most public comment.

These proposals,  and others,  are presented in more detail in the

White  Paper. Taken  together,   these  proposals,   which  are an



integral part of the Government&apos;s programme of improving access

to justice, represent an appropriate balance between competition

and the maintenance of standards in the administration of

justice, and I believe provide a satisfactory framework for the

future development of legal services.


CONhjENTIAL



ANNEX C



LEGAL SERVICES:

A FRAMEWORK    FOR   THE FUTURE



Presented to Parliament by

the Lord High Chancellor,

by Command of Her Majesty



HER    MAJESTY&apos;S    STATIONERY OFFICE



LONDON



 



net



Cm




CONTENTS



Page No



Introduction by the Lord Chancellor

Chapter 1



The Variety of the Need for Legal Services

Summary of the Proposals



Chapter 2



The Statutory Objectives



PART ONE   :  WIDER CHOICE IN LEGAL SERVICES



Chapter 3



Appearing in Court

Chapter 4



The Conduct of Litigation

Chapter 5



Conveyancing

Chapter 6



Probate



PART TWO  ;  THE MAINTENANCE OF QUALITY



Chapter 7



The Advisory Committee

Chapter 8



The Role of the Professional Bodies


Chapter 9



Legal Education

Chapter 10



Conduct, Complaints and Discipline



PART THREE  : NEW WAYS OF WORKING



Chapter 11



Competition in Legal Services

Chapter 12



Multi-disciplinary Partnerships

Chapter 13



Multi-national Partnerships

Chapter 14



Contingent and Conditional Fees



PART FOUR  :  JUDICIAL APPOINTMENTS



Chapter 15



Judicial Appointments



Annex A     Analysis of Responses to the Consultation



Annex       Comparison between the Green Paper Proposals and

the White Paper Decisions



Annex C     Rights of Audience in the Courts of England and

Wales



Annex D     Proposed   Conveyancing   Code   of   Conduct: Main

Principles


INTRODUCTION BY THE LORD CHANCELLOR



The legal profession exists for the benefit of its clients, and

for the proper administration of justice, criminal and civil.

It works to resolve, formally and informally, disputes between

citizens and with the State, and to assist people in pursuing

their rights and understanding their obligations. Where it

proves impossible for those concerned to settle a dispute, its

resolution is ultimately a matter for the courts.



If that framework is to function efficiently, and the client is

to have ready access to justice, he or she needs to be able to

call on a wide range of services in many different combinations,

from many different practitioners.



Equally, the client must have enough information about the

practitioners he or she thinks of approaching, and enough

confidence in the standards under which they operate, to be sure

they will be able to do what is needed at an affordable price.

The court system must be able to protect litigants from sharp

practice, and make sure that they have all the opportunity that

is needed to put their cases fully.



The Government has two aims. In legal services, there should

be the widest range of choice, compatible with the maintenance

of standards, available both from lawyers and from other

appropriate specialists and with enough information and client

safeguards to make that choice a real one. The courts should

have so far as possible straightforward, quick and cost-effective

procedures, making them both accessible and fair.



The Government&apos;s overall aim is to improve access to good quality

legal services, to the courts and ultimately to justice.


The proposals in this White Paper are concerned with one part of

that - a programme to improve the structure and work of the legal

profession to ensure that legal services of the appropriate kind

and quality are readily available.



Other measures are already in hand or will be brought forward to

implement the overall strategy. The legal aid scheme ensures

that legal services are available to those of small or moderate

means. Arrangements for improving the administration of legal

aid introduced by the Legal Aid Act 1988 are now being put into

effect. The Government must also ensure that the public purse

does not pay an unnecessarily high price for legal services. The

proposals for promoting competition in this paper will both

stimulate the provision of a range of services and exercise a

discipline on their costs.



Where disputes cannot be otherwise resolved, people need to have

recourse to the courts. The Government is committed to changes

which will speed up, simplify and reduce the cost of civil

proceedings. I have already announced that we have begun a major

programme to achieve this, based on the recommendations of the

Civil Justice Review&apos;.



Legislation will be brought forward at an early opportunity to

allow a major redistribution of civil cases between the High

Court and the county courts. The High Court will be reserved for

judicial review and other specialist cases, and for general cases

of unusual substance, importance or difficulty. Other cases will

be heard in the county courts.    This change will apply first to



[Cm 394, published by HMSO,  June 1988].


personal injury cases, where at present delays and costs are

frequently disproportionate to the amount claimed. It will then

be extended to debt and housing cases. Procedure in both the

High Court and the county courts will be improved, and wherever

possible made consistent. The Government believes that the

result will be a cheaper and speedier service.



We shall be seeking to tailor court procedures to the weight,

importance and complexity of the case. The success of the small

claims system has shown that a simplified procedure can enable

people to conduct some types of case either alone or with the

help of lay advisers. The Civil Justice Review suggested a

number of additional steps which might be taken to assist

litigants in small claims and in other cases in which they tend

not to be represented. I have already announced that we intend

to increase the small claims jurisdiction while making procedural

improvements to protect unrepresented litigants and to encourage

individuals to participate fully in cases that affect them. We

shall also be introducing a new housing action and a modified

form of rent action which will give easier access to the court

system for both landlords and tenants.



The Children Bill is another part of this strategy. It is the

first step in a programme of changes that will extend to all

aspects of family law and business. The Bill, which should

receive Royal Assent in the autumn, will replace the fragmented

and overlapping provisions of the current law with a single

regime governing the care, protection and upbringing of children.



Some of these changes will require resources if they are to be

implemented successfully. We have therefore to ensure that the

work of the courts is concentrated on those issues that required

decisions by the courts, and that the court system operates

efficiently. In most debt cases, once the court has established

that the money is owed, the debtor will in future make payments

direct to the creditor without the need for further intervention

by the county court.    The issue of summonses for creditors with


large numbers of debtors will be centralised in a new

computerised production centre. That will release capacity

enabling the county courts to provide a better service to

litigants.



The Government&apos;s aim in all these changes is to make the legal

system of this country more straightforward, more flexible, and

above all more responsive to the citizen&apos;s choices and needs,

whilst at the same time maintaining the standards necessary to

achieve justice. That is the way to make justice more available

to all.


1 ; The Variety of the Need for Legal Services



1.1. People&apos;s needs for legal services can be almost as diverse

as the events in their lives. Such needs can arise in very

different areas, involving such matters as basic rights and

liberties; divorce; serious criminal charges; tax; welfare

benefits; and buying and selling or renting property.

Helping with the resolution of disputes between citizens -

husbands and wives, business partners, neighbours - is also

a fundamental part of the business of the law. Each of

these areas not only requires a different form of legal

expertise, but also calls for a different approach to the

client from those who provide legal services, whether they

are qualified lawyers or not. This variety of approach is

reflected in the diversity of the legal profession today.



1.2 This process of evolution to respond to changing demand must

continue. The three Green Papers which the Government

published in January (footnote) have as their overall

objective to see that the public has the best possible

access to legal services, and that these services are of the

right quality for the particular needs of the client. The

Green Papers discussed many areas in which, although there

is already a great deal of competition between individual

practitioners, the framework of regulation and the

profession&apos;s practices might not at present permit the best

possible balance of growth and responsiveness in meeting the

client&apos;s needs.



Footnote: &apos;The Work and Organisation of the Legal

Profession&apos; (referred to as the main Green Paper,

Cm 570); &apos;Contingency Fees&apos; (Cm 571);

&apos;Conveyancing by Authorised Practitioners&apos; (Cm

572)


1.3 There was a great deal of interest shown in the Green

Papers. A total of over 2,000 responses have been received,

of which:



3%   came from the judiciary;



13%   came from barristers;



53%   came from solicitors;



2%   came  from others  involved  in  the  provision of

legal services;



29% came from members of the public, groups

representing consumer interests, education, and

others.



An analysis of the responses is published as Annex A. This

cannot, of course, present so much material fully. Copies

of all the responses whose authors wished them to be public

will therefore be placed in the libraries of both Houses of

Parliament, the Supreme Court, and the Lord Chancellor&apos;s

Department.



1.4 The Lord Chancellor wishes to record his gratitude to all

of those who responded to the consultation. The Lord

Chancellor has also had discussions with many of those

involved in the provision of legal services. All of the

points which have been made have been carefully considered,

and taken into account in making decisions. These

proposals, however, are the Government&apos;s own.



1.5 In this White Paper, the Government announces its decisions

and proposals for legislation at an early opportunity. The

overall aims are to give the public as wide a choice as

possible in the providers of legal services available to

them, whilst at the same time maintaining the high standards


of integrity and competence which are necessary for

protecting the interests of the client and for the more

general public interest in the administration of justice.

The Government seeks also to remove any restrictions which

are not necessary for the protection of those interests.

These aims will be met by creating a framework which

encourages flexibility and diversity in meeting the client&apos;s

needs, yet maintains the necessary standards.



1.6 The rest of this Chapter summarises the proposals in this

White Paper. It also sets out the major differences between

the proposals and those in the Green Papers: a fuller

account of those differences is found in the summary in

Annex B.



Chapter Two : The Statutory Objectives



1.7 The objectives for the provision of legal services in

advocacy and the conduct of litigation, and the development

and extension of these services, will be set out in statute.



Chapter Three : Appearing in Court



1.8 The Green Papers proposed a system of statutory regulation

for the purpose of ensuring common standards between the

different, self-regulating parts of the profession which

exercise similar functions, such as granting rights of

audience in the courts. During the consultation process,

that proposal was criticised for not reflecting sufficiently

fully the role of the judiciary; for indirectly compromising

professional self-regulation; and for not adequately

recognising the diversity of advocacy practice. As a result

of the consultation, and in particular the Law Society&apos;s

acceptance that barristers should have immediate rights to

appear in all courts on being called to the Bar by one of

the Inns of Court, this system can be considerably

simplified.


1.9 The Government recognises, as the Green Paper proposals made

plain, that the education and training of those who carry

on litigation are of fundamental importance, and the

proposals for dealing with education and training and

regulating the conduct of those admitted to practice are

crucial. The Government therefore proposes to replace the

current complex arrangements for rights of audience (set out

in Annex C) with a single statutory framework. That must

recognise the widely different needs and practice of

advocacy in the various courts and tribunals, and the

different working practices of the many kinds of legal

practitioner. It must ensure that the interests of all

those who have a part to play in the court system - the

client, the practitioner, the courts, and the Government -

are represented in a full and balanced way. In particular,

the Government strongly supports the independence of the

judiciary. The system now proposed therefore more expressly

involves the full-time judiciary in a way which builds on

the present arrangements for the Law Society ?s training

regulations. Above all, the framework for granting rights

of audience must ensure that the development of legal

services is ordered, and rapid enough to meet clients&apos;

changing needs.



1.10 The principal features of the proposals are:



Barristers who are qualified in terms of the Bar&apos;s

rules on education and training will have rights

of audience before all courts and tribunals.



The Law Society will continue as before to decide

which persons are qualified to be solicitors, and

will have power to declare solicitors qualified

in terms of the regulations for education and

training to appear for clients in specified levels

of courts. A person declared by the Law Society

to be qualified for particular courts or tribunals

will then have rights of audience.


1.11 In both cases the professional body will need to satisfy the

Lord Chancellor and the judiciary acting on advice from the

proposed Lord Chancellor&apos;s Advisory Committee on Legal

Education and Conduct (see Chapter 7) that their members can

uphold appropriate standards of competence and conduct.



Chapter Four : The Conduct of Litigation



1.12 The provision for entitlement to do the work which is

necessary to start and conduct litigation will be given a

simplified statutory basis, on the same approach as for

advocacy work. The Law Society will be entitled by statute

to grant its members the right to conduct litigation.

Arrangements will be made to enable other professions to do

so, to an appropriate degree. In each case, that will be

subject to the professional body or other organisation being

able to satisfy the Lord Chancellor and the judiciary, in

the light of advice from the Advisory Committee, that it can

set and maintain appropriate standards of competence and

conduct.



Chapter Five : Conveyancing



1.13 The Government is taking and encouraging a number of steps

to improve the quality of practice, and to eliminate abuse,

throughout the house-buying market. The specific proposals

in the conveyancing Green Paper to enable banks, building

societies and other authorised practitioners to offer

conveyancing services have been amended to provide, as the

consultation suggested, greater protection against conflicts

of interest, the lack of independent advice, and

opportunities for unfair competition by larger institutions.

In particular:



there will be a general ban on offering

conveyancing services in situations in which

conflicts of interest are regular or inescapable;


the qualified conveyancer undertaking the

transaction should offer the client a personal

interview, to be sure no conflict arises, and

identify any areas in which independent advice

might be desirable;



authorised practitioners will be required to

certify that they are not cross-subsidising

conveyancing services from their other activities

and to disclose financial benefits from all

aspects of the transaction;



the provision of one service conditional on taking

others will be prohibited.



Chapter Six : Probate



1.14 The Government&apos;s proposals for extending the range of people

who can prepare the documents required to apply for probate

will be amended to allow a greater measure of protection for

the client. Trust corporations, which can already

demonstrate the necessary standards of competence and

conduct, will be authorised to do this work by statute.

Arrangements will be made for the Lord Chancellor to

authorise other groups who can demonstrate that they meet

appropriate standards, after consultation with the

judiciary.



Chapter Seven : The Advisory Committee



1.15 The proposal in the Green Papers for a reconstituted Lord

Chancellor&apos;s Advisory Committee on Legal Education and

Conduct with executive powers was criticised because it was

argued that it would interfere with professional self-

regulation; because it would represent a shift of power to

the executive; and because the Advisory Committee would not

be sufficiently independent.


1.16 The proposal has been thoroughly revised. There should be

a reconstituted and vigorous Advisory Committee, but its

functions will be purely advisory. Its prime role will be

to give advice to all bodies authorised to grant to their

members rights of audience, the right to conduct litigation,

or the right to prepare probate documents. It will also

advise the Lord Chancellor and the judiciary on the

arrangements for ensuring appropriate standards of

competence and conduct in the provision of legal services.

The professional bodies and other organisations, the Lord

Chancellor, and the judges will all be required by statute

to have regard to advice from the Advisory Committee on the

discharge on their statutory functions. All the Advisory

Committee&apos;s advice would be public: it would report to

Parliament on all aspects of its work annually, and on

specific issues as appropriate. The Advisory Committee will

be financed from money provided by Parliament, and will be

wholly independent, running its own procedure and appointing

its own staff, who will be expected to come from a variety

of backgrounds.



Chapter Eight : The Role of the Professional Bodies



1.17 The importance of professional self-regulation will be

reinforced by leaving it to the professional bodies to

prepare the regulations and codes which will set

qualification standards and practice requirements for

advocacy and the conduct of litigation. The Advisory

Committee will advise the professional bodies on the codes.

New rules will require the concurrence of the Lord

Chancellor. Under the adversarial system operated in this

country, the courts depend on the competence and probity of

advocates and litigators. The proposals have been amended

to reflect that, and the concurrence of senior members of

the judiciary will be required for new regulations or codes

to be effective. Both the Lord Chancellor and the judges

will be advised by the Advisory Committee.


Chapter Nine : Legal Education



1.18 The Advisory Committee will advise upon the arrangements for

legal education. It will give advice on the standards and

selection procedures desirable for schemes to recognise

legal practitioners and others as specialists in particular

areas of the law. It will also comment on the need for such

schemes. Its advice would be directed to ensure that the

existence of such schemes did not create unnecessary

barriers either to new practitioners, whether lawyers or

suitably qualified non-lawyers, entering the area of work

concerned, or general practitioners continuing to work in

the area.



Chapter Ten ; Conduct, Complaints and Discipline



1.19 The Government proposes a range of measures to ensure that

complaints from members of the public about legal services

provided to them can be simply and effectively met.

Arrangements will be considered for a joint disciplinary

body of the Bar and the Law Society, involving members of

the judiciary when appropriate, to provide a common

mechanism and common standards in dealing with complaints

about court work. This might operate both nationally and

at a local level. The courts&apos; own powers to deal with poor

work will be strengthened. A new office of Legal Services

Ombudsman will be created. He will have wide powers to

examine the way in which complaints against legal

practitioners have been investigated by the professional

bodies, and also power to investigate such complaints

himself, where that is appropriate. He will have power to

recommend the payment of compensation in most cases.


Chapter  Eleven   :   Competition  in  the  Provision  of Legal



Services



1.20 Aspects of the work and organisation of the legal

professions which do not need to be regulated in the

interests of justice, may however need to be scrutinised to

ensure that there are no unnecessary restrictions on

competition. The professional bodies&apos; rules and practices

therefore will in general be subject to consideration under

the proposed legislation on restrictive trade practices.

Under that legislation, however, rules approved by the Lord

Chancellor will be exempt from prohibition.



Chapter Twelve : Multi-disciplinary Partnerships



1.21 The Government is concerned to ensure that clients have

ready access to independent legal advice, and in particular

an adequate choice of specialist practitioners both from

barristers and from solicitors, and believes that it is for

the professions to decide how they should best organise

themselves to meet the needs of their clients. The

statutory prohibition on the formation of partnerships

between solicitors and other professionals will be removed,

and the matter left to professional rules. The Bar Council

and the Law Society will continue to be able to make rules

preventing such partnerships if they so wish, to the extent

that this is justified by the needs of advocacy or the

conduct of litigation.



Chapter Thirteen : Multi-national Partnerships



1 22 The Government&apos;s proposals for lifting barriers to the

formation of partnerships between advocates and litigators

in this country and lawyers practising in other

jurisdictions have been widely welcomed. Arrangements will

also be made to ensure that United Kingdom lawyers have


rights to practise in other parts of the kingdom at least

equivalent to those available to lawyers from other EC

countries.



Chapter Fourteen : Contingent and Conditional Fees



23 The consultation was generally opposed to the introduction

of a system of contingency fees which would permit clients

to offer their lawyers a percentage of any damages if

successful. That option has therefore been rejected. There

was, however, little objection in principle or in practice

to clients being able to agree with their lawyers

conditional fees on the speculative basis already permitted

in Scotland, or to permitting a specified, moderate

percentage uplift on the normal bill which the parties to

such agreements could contract to pay. The Government

therefore proposes to implement this proposal.



Chapter Fifteen : Judicial Appointments



24 The proposal that the qualifications for judicial

appointments should be revised to make all suitably

qualified lawyers eligible for judicial appointments has

been widely welcomed. The general simplification in the

arrangements for working as an advocate will however permit

significantly simplified arrangements to be implemented to

achieve this.


2 : The Statutory Objectives



2.1 The Government believes it is of central importance that the

objectives which govern the arrangements for the provision

of legal services in advocacy and in the conduct of

litigation should be simple and clear. Practitioners need

that if they are to deliver what is expected of them. The

professional bodies and other organisations need that to

enforce standards consistently amongst their own members,

in relation to other professions providing similar legal

services. Above all the client needs to understand the

basis of the work and the services for which he is paying.



2.2 The Government therefore proposes to include those basic

objectives in the legislation. All those who contribute to

setting and maintaining standards in the provision of legal

services - the professional bodies and other organisations,

the Lord Chancellor, and the judiciary - will be required

to have regard to those objectives in carrying out their

duties.



2.3 The objectives are:



To lay down standards of education and training

in the provision of services in advocacy or the

conduct of litigation which ensure that those who

offer such services to the public are competent

to do so.



To maintain the standards of conduct in advocacy

and the conduct of litigation which are required

in the interests of the proper and efficient

administration of justice.


To meet those objectives in ways which ensure

that there are no obstacles to access to justice,

and no restrictions which would inhibit the

client&apos;s choice of how he may obtain legal

services imposed on those qualified to provide

legal services or on what those who are qualified

may do, which are not necessary in the interests

of justice.



2.4 The statute will make it clear that the framework it will

create has the express purpose of ensuring the ordered,

flexible and speedy development of fresh ways of providing

legal services to meet clients&apos; needs, especially in

advocacy and litigation, and of ensuring that clients have

a wider choice of providers of such legal services. In

particular, the statute will state a clear intention that

rights of audience should be extended.


PART ONE  :  WIDER CHOICE IN LEGAL SERVICES



3 ; Appearing in Court



3.1 The existing restrictions on rights of audience in the

courts of England and Wales were set out in the main Green

Paper. For convenience, they are reproduced as Annex C to

this White Paper.



3.2 In the Green Paper, the Government proposed that, for the

future, rights of audience before particular courts should

depend only upon whether advocates could demonstrate that

they had the appropriate qualifications of education and

training and were bound by appropriate codes of conduct.

Advocates&apos; professional bodies should have to satisfy the

Lord Chancellor that their members were fit and proper

people to appear as advocates before the court or courts in

question in order to obtain rights of audience for them.

The necessary requirements would vary according to the court

concerned. This could include rights of audience for

employed lawyers and for people with expertise in related

fields who were not lawyers. The appropriate mechanism

envisaged was for the professional bodies to issue limited

or full advocacy certificates, confirming that the advocate

had appropriate training and experience. The decision on

which bodies should be able to grant advocacy certificates

would lie with the Lord Chancellor, subject to advice from

an Advisory Committee. The Government considered that it

was in the public interest that a variety of professional

bodies should be so authorised. The rules for education and

training and for conduct were to be determined by the

professional bodies concerned but were to be subject to

principles set out in a statutory instrument made by the

Lord Chancellor after consultation with the judiciary, and

subject to approval by Parliament.


3.3 Many of those who responded to the Green Papers commented

on these proposals. Some thought that the importance to

the administration of justice of preserving an independent

Bar required that no significant change should be made in

rights of audience. It was argued that the proposed system

of certification was too complicated. At the same time, it

might also not adequately recognise the existing diversity

of legal practice, so that some areas of specialisation

might be adversely affected. Many argued that the proposed

role for the Lord Chancellor in bringing forward delegated

legislation allowed a risk of executive interference in the

courts, which created the risk of abuse in the future.

Many, also, thought it was important to recognise the role

of the judiciary by giving them a more central and more

clearly defined role in the granting of rights of audience.



Rights of Audience



3.4 The Government continues to believe that the public should

have the widest possible choice amongst properly qualified

advocates, who should be free to compete fairly with one

another for the business available from clients. That

principle has been welcomed by representatives of consumer

and business interests, and members of the public. The

Government therefore proposes to create a statutory

framework which would permit in the future extended rights

of audience, for present advocates in more courts, and for

new classes of advocates. The consultation recognised,

however, that as specialists in pleading before the higher

courts, barristers should be enabled to appear before all

courts more quickly than others who wish to work as

advocates. That has permitted a substantial simplification

of the Green Paper proposals.


3.5 The proposals depend on advocates collectively and

individually being able to demonstrate the high standards

of competence and conduct required by the court ? s dependence

in this country&apos;s adversarial system on the full and

accurate presentation of the case by both parties. The

mechanisms now proposed for ensuring that are set out in

Chapters 7 and 8.



3.6 First, the Government has decided to implement the

recommendation of the Civil Justice Review&apos; that in small

claims cases, and debt and housing cases in the county

court, litigants should have the right to choose a lay

representative to assist or represent them, subject always

to the court&apos;s discretion to restrict the involvement of

corrupt or unruly representatives, or to exclude them

entirely on giving reasons. That will replace the existing

position in which lay representatives appear by leave of

the court.



3.7 The Government proposes that provision should be made in

the primary legislation for there to be no restriction on

rights of audience in that work. The provision would be

brought into force by a statutory instument made by the Lord

Chancellor, which would cover the detailed arrangements for

implementation. The instrument would be subject to approval

by affirmative resolution of both Houses of Parliament.



3.8 Second, the Government proposes that the existing complex

arrangements under statute and common law should be replaced

by statutory rights of audience in all courts, and by

appropriate statutory rights of audience before tribunals.



Footnote &apos;    Report of the Review Body on Civil Justice, Cm 394,

June 1988, Paras 351-54 and Recommendation 48


Granting Rights of Audience



3.9 The Government considers that it is for the professional

bodies and other organisations whose members provide legal

services to satisfy the courts and the public that their

members can meet the high standards of competence and

conduct required for rights of audience. The Government

therefore proposes that it should be for the professional

bodies and other organisations to determine that particular

persons are qualified in accordance with the appropriate

rules to appear in the courts. The standards they apply,

and the mechanisms by which they monitor those standards,

should, however, be subject to independent scrutiny and

public comment.



3.10 The Bar Primary legislation should recognise that any

person called to the Bar by one of the Inns of Court (under

their new arrangements to apply from October) in accordance

with the regulations on education and training will have

rights of audience which can be exercised in all courts and

tribunals when pupillage is complete. That will depend only

on their complying with the rules of conduct made by the

Bar. After the legislation comes into force, any change in

either set of rules will be subject to the concurrence of

the Lord Chancellor and of the Lord Chief Justice, the

Master of the Rolls, the President of the Family Division

and the Vice-Chancellor on behalf the judiciary. Both the

Lord Chancellor and those judges would act having regard to

advice from the Lord Chancellor&apos;s Advisory Committee on

Legal Education and Conduct. Further details of the

procedure for making the rules are set out in Chapters 7

and 8.



3.11 The Law Society Primary legislation should provide that the

Law Society should be able to recognise a solicitor as

qualified according to the rules for education and training

to be an advocate, in a particular court or courts, and in


tribunals. Any person so qualified would be recognised as

having a right of audience in that court or those courts,

or tribunals provided that he or she complied with the

relevant rules of conduct made by the Law Society. To be

effective, both sets of rules would require the concurrence

of the Lord Chancellor and the same senior judges as those

for the Bar.



3.12 The rules would determine the training and experience

necessary for a solicitor to have rights of audience in a

particular court. But it is envisaged that such

qualifications would be obtained in stages. On

qualification, all solicitors would receive rights of

audience which would be equivalent to their existing rights.

It is likely that many solicitors will find these rights

adequate for the work they wish to do.



3.13 Those who wished to proceed to further rights of advocacy

would then be expected to undertake a subsequent period of

practical experience in advocacy under supervision. The

Government does not expect the progress to further rights

to be automatic in any way but to be conditional on the

attainment of a standard of competence to be determined by

the rules appropriate for the court or courts concerned.

Conclusion of the period of training will need to be tested

by considering the individual standard of competence

achieved.



3.14 In order to provide for possible developments in the future,

it is proposed that a power be provided to enable the list

of bodies which could grant rights of audience to be added

to, should that become appropriate. Such a power would be

exercised only in the light of advice to that effect from

the Advisory Committee, and with the concurrence of the

senior judges referred to above. The addition would be made

by an Order in Council made on the recommendation of the

Lord Chancellor. The Order would be subject to approval in

draft by affirmative resolution of both Houses of

Parliament.


3.15 As with the current statutory arrangements in the county

courts, these proposals will not be a restriction on the

judges&apos; discretion to control proceedings in the courts over

which they preside. It would remain open for a judge to

hear any advocate, professional or lay, who did not possess

the appropriate, or even any, right of audience. Similarly,

subject to giving reasons the judge may refuse to hear any

individual advocate, whatever his right of audience, if his

conduct towards the court fell short of what was reguired.



Preservation of Existing Rights



3.16 It will be a principle of the proposed legislation that no

individual or class of advocates would lose any existing

rights.    In particular:



all barristers and solicitors would retain all

their existing rights of audience;



all categories of lay and professional advocates

who currently have specific rights of audience

before any court or tribunal would be given

corresponding rights. For example, those rights

before magistrates&apos; courts conferred upon local

authority members and officers by section 223 of

the Local Government Act 1972 will be preserved

in full.



Employed Advocates



3.17 The exercise of rights of audience by a person who holds

them may be limited by professional rules of conduct.

Current examples include the limited rights accorded to

employed barristers or solicitors. The extent of those

limitations under the rules will be a matter for early

consideration by the Advisory Committee, and should be kept

under review by the professional body concerned.


18 The Government has received legal advice that the CPS

practice of using law clerks to respond to bail applications

in the Crown Court and the High Court is unlawful, solely

because the provision in the Prosecution of Offences Act

1985 which gave rights of audience to CPS lawyers had, as

a matter of construing statute, overridden the judicial

practice which had allowed law clerks to do this work. Law

clerks&apos; work in this area has been entirely satisfactory to

the courts and is an efficient use of resources. The

Government therefore proposes to correct the position by

legislating for this long-established practice to resume.



Queen&apos;s Counsel



19 In the Green Paper the Government proposed that in future

all those who held full general advocacy certificates should

be eligible for Silk as should - on an occasional and

honorary basis - lawyers who are not practising advocates.



20 These proposals attracted wide, although not unanimous,

support in the consultation. It was argued that the

appointment of Queen&apos;s Counsel assists clients to identify

the advocates who regularly and ably argue complex and

weighty cases before the higher courts. The appointment

also enables the Lord Chancellor to identify the leading

candidates for high judicial office at an early stage.



21 He will therefore in the future regard as eligible for

appointment as Queen&apos;s Counsel all those who hold rights of

audience in the High Court, as the senior civil court of

first instance, or the Crown Court, as the senior criminal

trial court. He will invite applications accordingly.

Other lawyers will also be considered on an occasional and

honorary basis.    This policy will be kept under review.


Law Reporting



3.22 The preparation of cases for the law reports is now reserved

by common law for barristers. The Government&apos;s proposals

for the future extension of rights of audience make this

restriction anomalous. It will, however, remain necessary

for those who prepare the reports which record the binding

decisions of the higher courts to be fully familiar with

practice in those courts. The Government accordingly

proposes that the preparation of law reports should be

restricted to those with rights of audience in all branches

of the Supreme Court.



Impersonation



3.23 Under section 21 of the Solicitors Act 1974 it is an offence

to impersonate a solicitor. Anomalously, there is no

equivalent provision for impersonating a barrister. The

Government propose to correct this minor anomaly, by making

it an offence to impersonate any kind of qualified advocate.


4 : The Conduct of Litigation



4.1 Under Section 20 of the Solicitors Act 1974, it is an

offence for anyone other than a solicitor to start or

conduct litigation in any civil or criminal court, except

as a litigant in person. This covers a wide range of

functions, which differ significantly according to the

nature of the work and of the court and proceedings in

question. The Government believes that the existence of

this statutory monopoly unnecessarily hinders the ways in

which the provision of legal services might develop. The

Government accordingly proposes that the provision should

be ammended to enable anyone to practise who has the

appropriate level of expertise for the needs of the work

concerned. Throughout this White Paper, the term

&quot;litigator&quot; is used to describe anyone who does the work

necessary for the conduct of litigation, whatever their

background qualification.



4.2 The conduct of litigation is an intrinsic part of the work

of the courts. Anyone who wishes to practise as a litigator

should therefore be bound by an effective code of conduct

which emphasises that his duties to the court take

precedence over all others. The Government believes that

a litigator&apos;s duty to the court should be regulated on the

same principles as an advocate&apos;s. There will after all be

many similarities, and often some overlap, between the two

kinds of work. The right to conduct litigation, like rights

of audience, should accordingly be granted to practitioners

by the professional bodies or institutions to which they

belong, if the bodies can demonstrate that they can set and

maintain appropriate standards of competence and conduct,

taking due account of the range of functions to be found in


the conduct of litigation in different courts and kinds of

work. All litigators will also need to be subject to the

existing powers of the High Court over solicitors as

officers of the court. The Law Society will be designated

in the statute as being able to grant such rights, subject

to ensuring the necessary standards of competence and

conduct. Other bodies might be so authorised in the future

by an Order in Council, made, following advice from the

Advisory Committee, on the recommendation of the Lord

Chancellor and subject to the concurrence of the judiciary

and to affirmative resolution, as with extensions of the

right to grant rights of audience.



4.3 The mechanisms for determining the acceptability of the

codes of conduct for those who conduct litigation, and the

rules setting out the educational requirements (both of

which would be subject to the concurrence of the Lord

Chancellor and the senior judiciary) are set out in Chapters

7 and 8.



4.4 These proposals will not affect the rules which now govern

the conduct of litigation on behalf of the Crown by the

Treasury Solicitor, and the Solicitor to certain Government

departments, such as the Inland Revenue and Customs and

Excise.


5 : Conveyancing



5.1 The Government recognises that for many people the process

of buying and selling their home is one of the most

important financial events in their lives.



5.2 Conveyancing is a crucial part of the process, but it is

only one of a number of services which are likely to be

required during the course of the transaction. Estate agents

advertise and market the property for its seller, and are

the buyer&apos;s usual first port of call. A surveyor will

usually be needed to advise on the property&apos;s physical

condition. The buyer almost always needs to arrange finance,

usually in the shape of a mortgage from a bank, building

society, insurance company or mortgage broker. Increasingly,

that requires investment advice about the endowment

mortgages or life assurance policies which often form part

of the financial package.



5.3 This Chapter is concerned with the Government&apos;s proposals

for increasing the range of those who, subject to

appropriate safeguards, should be permitted to provide

conveyancing services. The Government wishes to ensure that

the client has the widest possible range of choice in

obtaining the advice which suits his circumstances.



5.4 There is, however, much else that needs to be done in order

to ensure that conveyancing transactions are as simple as

possible, and to improve other aspects of the house selling

market in order to protect the consumer. The Government

intends to promote a wide range of measures to achieve these

ends. For instance:



Eric Forth, MP, the Parliamentary Under Secretary

of State for Industry and Consumer Affairs, has


already announced the results of his review of

estate agency (in a report of that title published

in June 1989). He concluded that estate agency

could be significantly improved through a

combination of self-regulation and statutory

provision. He has asked the Director General of

Fair Trading to discuss with the industry the

introduction of a code of practice for estate

agency. He will also introduce an order under the

Estate Agents Act 1977 specifying &quot;undesirable&quot;

practices and giving the Director General the

power to ban those found engaging in them. The

Director General is also to report on the

proposition that property description should be

covered by the Trade Descriptions Act 1968.



Allegations about the recommendation of new

endowment policies when houseowners move home,

in circumstances where top-up policies might be

more suitable - the practice called &quot;churning&quot; ?

have been brought to the attention of the

Securities and Investment Board. The SIB&apos;s rules

concerning topics such as the duty to give best

advice, and the existence of regulatory bodies to

enforce them, should result in a marked

improvement in standards of advice in this area.



There are a number of options available under

present law for reducing the time between first

agreements and the stage at which parties bind

themselves by contract. The seller can carry out

local searches and enquiries, and prepare

necessary documents, buyers can make financial

arrangements at an early stage, and ? with

appropriate advice - the parties can enter in to

pre-contract deposit agreements or conditional

contracts.



House of Commons Hansard,  21 June 1989, Coll 176-77


The Lord Chancellor has announced that he is

considering the Land Registry as an early

candidate for executive agency status. Proposals

for that are being actively considered.



5.5 The conveyancing Green Paper proposed that the complex

arrangements for permitting banks, building societies, other

institutions and individuals to provide conveyancing

services, which are contained in the Building Societies Act

1986, but which have not been implemented, should be

modified. In their place, it was proposed to implement a

simpler statutory framework, which would still provide the

necessary control. Legislation would stipulate the

requirements for those who wished to be authorised to

provide conveyancing services to the public. A major part

of that would be compliance with a code of conduct, the

major elements of which were set out in the Green Paper.



5.6 These proposals attracted a great deal of comment from many

of those who responded to the consultation. It was argued

that the proposals would permit authorised conveyancers to

offer their services in circumstances where either they, or

the organisation for which they worked, were offering

services to both buyer, and seller. Irreconcilable conflicts

of interest would arise. If conveyancing services were

provided by lending institutions, it was said that house

buyers would be deprived of independent advice, and that

this would be particularly acute where the prime source of

advice was an estate agent subsidiary of a lending

institution. It was argued that the state of the present

market would not allow fair competition. The large

financial institutions would corner the market driving many

solicitors out of business. That would result in an

increasing concentration of conveyancing services. It was

also argued that the network of solicitors&apos; firms across the

country would be reduced, and with it the public&apos;s access

to general legal advice.


The Government&apos;s Proposals



5.7 As the whole of these proposals in this White Paper make

clear, the Government takes consumer protection issues very

seriously. But in the area of conveyancing services, it

continues to believe that it is possible to increase the

choice available to those who are buying or selling their

houses, and also to meet the concerns about the need to

avoid conflicts of interest and ensure appropriate

professional advice. In particular, the responses of the

consumer bodies in support of one-stop shopping lend weight

to the view that there is scope to expand the range of those

permitted to offer such services. New legislation will

provide for the Lord Chancellor to recognise professional

bodies and other organisations as competent to authorise

their members to provide conveyancing services once he is

satisfied that they meet the requirements for recognition

set out below, and are able to enforce upon their members

a code of conduct for the provision of conveyancing

services.



5.8 To obtain authorisation, the member would need to satisfy

the requirements which were set out in paragraph 3.5 of the

conveyancing Green Paper.    These are:



(i)    suitability to provide conveyancing services;



(ii) the employment of a sufficient number of

solicitors or licensed conveyancers (or both)

to provide or supervise the provision of the

conveyancing services;



(iii)    protection of clients&apos;  money from improper

use;



(iv)



compliance with the Lord Chancellor&apos;s code

of conduct;


( )    ability   to   meet   claims   arising   out of

conveyancing services;



(vi)    investigation of complaints;



(vii)    suitable compensation arrangements;



(viii)   membership of a suitable Ombudsman scheme;

and



(ix) adequate arrangements for protecting clients

should an authorised practitioner cease to

provide conveyancing services.



Authorised Practitioners



The legislation would require conveyancing to be carried

out or supervised by those who have the relevant

professional expertise. This will be defined as including

solicitors, licensed conveyancers and (subject to

appropriate qualification) barristers and notaries.



Two categories of authorised practitioner are envisaged.

First, provided that banks and building societies can

certify to their regulatory authorities that they can comply

with the requirements for authorisation and with the

proposed code of conduct, they will be able to operate as

authorised practitioners. Secondly, other professional

bodies and other organisations which meet the requirements

for recognition and can satisfy the Lord Chancellor that

they can ensure their members&apos; compliance with the code of

conduct, will be enabled to authorise their members to

operate as authorised practitioners.


Interest on Funds Held



5.11 The Government proposes to remove the current anomaly

whereby money held by a licensed conveyancer (and, it is

proposed, an authorised conveyancer) on a client&apos;s behalf

must be placed on deposit and the interest paid to the

client (unless it is de minimis), whereas solicitors are not

required to pass to the client any interest earned on money

which they hold as stakeholders or as trustees. All money

held must be put on deposit, and interest paid to the

client, unless the amount is de minimis.



The Code of Conduct



5.12 The code of conduct will embody principles relating to the

proper supervision of conveyancing services, conflicts of

interests, contractual obligations, and the conduct of

business. These are broadly as set out in the Annex to the

Green Paper. For convenience, that Annex is reproduced as

Annex D to this White Paper. There are however three

important new elements, which reflect the Government&apos;s

concern to protect the client, and to ensure that there is

proper competition on an equal footing.



5.13 First, the Government continues to believe that it is of

the highest importance that potential conflicts of interest

in the transaction are identified and avoided at the

earliest possible stage, and that quality of service is

underwritten by ensuring that the client is clearly aware

of what he can, and cannot, expect in conveyancing

services. The Government therefore proposes that the

conveyancing code of practice should require:



(i) Personal Interview There will have to be an

identified solicitor or licensed conveyancer

responsible for carrying out the conveyancing

services in each transaction. The authorised

practitioner&apos;s client must be offered at least one


interview with the solicitor or licensed

conveyancer, reasonably near either the client&apos;s

home or the property being conveyed. At the

interview, the qualified person must review with

the client any possible conflicts of interest

between the client and the provider of the

service, and the transaction may proceed only if

the qualified person advises that there is no

conflict. It must be explained that the qualified

person&apos;s first duty in the transaction is to the

client to whom he is providing conveyancing

services, not to his employer. The practitioner

must undertake to tell the client at once if any

conflict arises during the transaction, and

explain that if a conflict does arise he will have

to cease to act in the conveyancing both for the

client, and for his employer. He must sign a

certificate confirming all that at the conclusion

of the interview.



(ii) Independent Advice At the same interview, the

qualified person must explain to the client the

scope of the service that is being offered. If

there is any aspect of the client&apos;s affairs

related to the transaction in which legal advice

would be desirable, but which the service provided

does not cover, this must be set out in writing

at the end of the interview and the client advised

accordingly. The client must also be informed if

any area of conflict arises during the

transaction.



(iii) Conflict of interest The consultation responses

have concentrated attention on a number of

situations in which conflicts of interest might

arise, beyond those already identified in the

Green Paper. The Government believes that it would

not   be   right   for  conveyancing   services   to be


provided in situations in which conflicts were

inevitable or extremely likely to occur and has

added additional safeguards to the proposals. The

code of practice will therefore now prevent all

authorised practitioners from providing

conveyancing services to both the buyer and the

seller of the same property, subject to some very

limited exceptions (where, for example buyer and

seller are associated companies, or related) if

there is no apparent conflict. Authorised

practitioners will also be prohibited from

offering conveyancing services to a party in a

transaction in which the practitioner, or a

subsidiary or connected company, is also providing

estate agency services to another party. These

restrictions cannot be overridden by the written

consent of the parties.



Fair Competition



5.14 Secondly, the Green Paper proposed that authorised

practitioners should be prevented from offering conveyancing

services at less than their true cost, and that their annual

accounts would have to provide proof of that. The Government

has considered very carefully arguments advanced during the

consultation period that few authorised practitioners would,

in fact, seek to use unfairly low prices for conveyancing

services as a &quot;loss leader&quot;. It was also argued that an

annual requirement to demonstrate in the accounts that there

was no predatory pricing would impose very substantial

costs, and might also lead to increased qualification of

accounts. In the light of the consultation response, the

Government has decided not to require annual proof.

Instead, authorised practitioners will be required to submit

to their regulatory bodies each year details of the prices

they charge for conveyancing services, certifying that those

prices had been arrived at on a fair and reasonable basis

to provide a reasonable rate of return on the costs of




providing those services alone. This aims to remove cross-

subsidy on a significant and systematic basis.



5.15 To emphasise further the importance the Government attaches

to ensuring that there is competition on an equal footing,

authorised practitioners will be required to disclose to the

client all the financial benefits the practitioner stands

to gain from both the conveyancing and from any linked

services given in connection with the transaction in

question. That will be based on the requirement in the

code of conduct that the client must be given a statement

of the costs which sets out separately the costs of each

service, and notification of commissions from linked

services to be received from independent advisers.



&quot;Tying-in&quot;



5.16 Thirdly the code will also require as outlined in paragraph

11 of the Green Paper Annex that conveyancing services

should not be made conditional on any other service being

undertaken, or other services be made conditional on

conveyancing services being undertaken. The Government is

considering extending this prohibition on tying-in to

prevent the tying-in to the mortgage of any other services

in the domestic property market.



5.17 The Government believes that these measures, together with

the existing competition legislation as a guard against

predatory pricing, will be sufficient to ensure that there

is fair competition, on a level playing field.



5.18 In other important respects, the code of practice will be

as set out in the Annex to the Green Paper.



5.19 Authorised practitioners will be required by statute to

comply with the code of conduct, which will be made by the

Lord Chancellor by statutory instrument subject to negative

resolution of either House of Parliament.


Complaints



5.20 It would be a condition of recognition that the recognised

professional body or other organisation could ensure that

its members who were authorised practitioners had suitable

mechanisms to deal with complaints. In addition, the body

itself would have to have suitable mechanisms for dealing

with complaints and disciplinary matters. It and its members

would also need to belong or be subject to a suitable

Ombudsman scheme. Banks and building societies, which

already have regulatory authorities, will be required to

certify to their regulatory authorities that they belong

to a suitable Ombudsman scheme.



5.21 The Government considers that the authorised practitioner&apos;s

own complaints mechanism, followed if necessary by that of

his regulatory authority, is the most appropriate method of

dealing initially with any dispute or complaint.



5.22 Should the complainant still not be satisfied with the way

in which his complaint has been handled, he should then be

able to approach the relevant Ombudsman. The running of

Ombudsman schemes must largely be a matter for the bodies

which establish them. An Ombudsman scheme would, however,

need to provide for an independent adjudicator with powers

at least to:



(i) investigate any complaint within his jurisdiction

(with a discretion not to consider complaints

which have not been submitted within a reasonable

period, or which are frivolous or vexatious);



(ii) investigate the subject matter of the complaint,

as well as the way in which it has been handled

in the complaints mechanism;



(iii) require the production of documents and a written

waiver of confidentiality from the complainant in

order to investigate the complaint;


(iv) provide for payment of compensation for loss,

expense or inconvenience caused by the initial

action or the handling of the complaint, whether

by the practitioner or the relevant professional

body. A suitable minimum limit of compensation

would be the  100,000 provided for in the Banks

and Building Societies Ombudsman schemes (the

courts would of course remain able to award sums

above this amount);



(v) direct the authorised practitioner to take action

to correct the substance of the complaint, and to

take or desist from taking certain specified

steps. This power would include prohibiting the

authorised practitioner from taking on new

business for a fixed period, or until the problems

had been remedied.



5.23 The Ombudsman&apos;s services should be free to complainants.


6 : Probate



6.1 Under section 23 of the Solicitors Act 1974, it is an

offence for anyone other than a solicitor, a barrister or

a notary to draft or prepare for reward the papers on which

the grant of probate or letters of administration depend.

The Government has concluded that the present statutory

restrictions can no longer be justified. The main Green

Paper invited views on whether the right course was to widen

the class of people who may apply for probate for reward in

non-contentious cases (Option A), or whether it was safe to

remove the restriction altogether (Option  ).



6.2 There was a wide welcome amongst members of the public and

consumer groups for some deregulation of probate. It was,

however, widely argued that because of the room for fraud

and for inefficiency in dealing with estates, the

authorisation of particular groups who would be subject to

appropriate safeguards for competence and conduct was

preferable to complete deregulation. The list of those set

out as likely to be able to prepare papers competently was

broadly endorsed, although it was argued that legal

executives could be added. It was, however, argued that at

least some of these groups would require specific training

in probate, and that the range of groups indicated the need

for a single code of conduct. It was argued that the fact

that some additional affidavits may be required worked

against the abolition of the oath, which should be

considered further by a review of the use of the oath in all

court proceedings.



6.3 The Government accordingly proposes that the classes of

people who can draw papers up should be extended. The

Government is satisfied that the trust corporations&apos;

existing arrangements for ensuring competence and conduct

are already adequate to cover probate work. Legislation

will provide for them to prepare applications.


6.4 The Government also considers it likely that the other

groups listed in the Green Paper (licensed conveyancers,

authorised conveyancing practitioners, and chartered and

certified accountants) are already or will become qualified.

It may also be that other groups (legal executives are the

most obvious example) will want and be able to undertake

this work. It will, however, be necessary to ensure that

practitioners are suitably qualified, and belong to

professional bodies which have set, and are able to

maintain, suitable standards. For example, licensed

conveyancers might be required to undertake suitable courses

in probate. The Government accordingly proposes that the

Lord Chancellor should be given power to add to the list of

those qualified to prepare applications for probate

professional bodies or other organisations which he had been

advised by the Advisory Committee met the appropriate

standards of competence and conduct. That would be done

after consultation with the President of the Family Division

by statutory instrument subject to affirmative resolution

by both Houses of Parliament. In the Government&apos;s view,

these arrangements will make it unnecessary to impose a

probate code of practice.



Attendance in Person



6.5 At present, the Non-Contentious Probate Rules provide that

only solicitors may make an application for a grant of

probate by post without attending the registry in person.

The Government proposes that the rules should be amended to

enable all those who are able to draw up papers for reward

(including barristers and notaries), to apply without

personal attendance.


Oaths



Among the papers required is an affidavit by which the

applicant for the grant swears that he will administer the

estate according to the law, and that he is either the

executor named or identifies his title to the grant. Only

a solicitor or notary may administer the oaths required.

Two-thirds of those who responded to the consultation on

this topic were in favour of retaining the requirement for

an oath. The Government does not therefore intend to

proceed with the proposal that an oath should not be

required. Should the change become desirable in the future,

however, additional protection against dishonesty would be

required. It is therefore proposed to create a new criminal

offence of making a dishonest statement for the purpose of

an application for a grant of probate, which will be triable

either in the magistrates&apos; court or the Crown Court.


PART TWO  ;  THE MAINTENANCE OF QUALITY

7 : The Advisory Committee



7.1 The Government proposed in the Green Papers that the Lord

Chancellor&apos;s Advisory Committee on Legal Education should

be reconstituted to form the Lord Chancellor&apos;s Advisory

Committee on Legal Education and Conduct. Its main

functions would be to advise upon the arrangements for legal

education and training; the need for schemes recognising

areas of specialisation, and how specialists should be

trained; and on codes of conduct. On advice from the

Committee, the Lord Chancellor would recognise professional

bodies as competent to authorise individual practitioners

as specialists in a particular field, if he was satisfied

that they could provide the appropriate education and

training, and exercised sufficient control over their

members to ensure that satisfactory standards of conduct and

behaviour were maintained and enforced.



7.2 The Government also proposed that professional bodies whose

members wished to offer advisory and advocacy services would

be required to prepare and submit to the Advisory Committee

for its endorsement codes of conduct covering these areas.

The Lord Chancellor would prescribe the principles which

would have to be embodied in those codes.



7.3 These proposals attracted comments from very many of those

who responded to the Green Papers. A recurring argument was

that the functions to be given to the Lord Chancellor, in

the interests of furthering consistency between standards

applied by various professional and other bodies,

represented a significant transfer of power to the executive

from the independent professions and indeed from the

judiciary. It was suggested that the Advisory Committee

would itself not be fully independent of the Government, and

there was wide concern that it should have an independent

secretariat. Many members of the legal profession were

concerned that the majority of the Advisory Committee&apos;s

members would be non-lawyers.


7.4 The Government has considered these views with great care.

It continues to believe that some form of advisory system

is required to ensure that matters of public concern and

interest are properly and publicly considered in a reasoned

way, and that advice is available to Parliament, the Lord

Chancellor, the judiciary and the professions. A forum is

needed for the different branches of the profession to

ensure that appropriate standards of competence and conduct

will be required of all who provide legal services, whatever

their background qualification, and to give coordination

between the practising profession and the academic legal

profession in relation to the arrangements for education and

training. The Advisory Committee is also needed to ensure

that any doubts that might arise about the general level

of standards in legal services, or the vigour with which

they are enforced, can be heard effectively, and to give a

lead on the way in which professional services should

develop. In that, it would be very similar to the committee

which the Bar and the Law Society set up to consider the

future of the legal profession, and would need to give a

similar part to knowledgeable non-lawyers. But it would

also need to recognise the central role of the judiciary.



7.5 The Government therefore proposes that there should be a new

Lord Chancellor&apos;s Advisory Committee on Legal Education and

Conduct established by statute, to advise on questions that

arise as to what qualifications are necessary for providing

services connected with litigation, and what requirements

are necessary to ensure proper standards of conduct.



7.5   The Advisory Committee&apos;s main functions should be:



(i)    Education and Training



To advise on the arrangements for the education

and training of lawyers at the academic,

vocational and post-vocational stages, and to

offer advice on what education and training is


appropriate to the needs of practice and to the

efficient delivery of legal services to the

public.



(ii) Conduct



To offer advice on the rules of conduct to be

observed in the provision of legal services, and

in particular to consider whether the rules

safeguard the interests of justice and the

interests of the client, and are expressed

appropriately so that the public may appreciate

the effect and need for the rules.



(iii) Recognition



To consider in the future whether to advise the

Lord Chancellor on the suitability of professional

bodies or organisations (other than the Bar

Council or the Law Society) as competent to grant

rights of audience or the right to conduct

litigation to their members; and to examine, in

the light of objectives incorporated in statute,

both the standards of education and training and

the codes of conduct put forward by each

professional body or organisation.



(iv) Specialisation



To offer advice on whether schemes for areas of

accredited specialisation put forward to it by

professional bodies or other organisations are

likely to serve the efficient delivery of legal

services to the public, and from time to time to

consider on its own initiative whether any new

areas of accredited specialisation are necessary;

and to advise the relevant organisations

accordingly.


( )    Practical and Continuing Education



To advise upon the requirements and arrangements for

the provision of practical training and continuing

training, particularly in advocacy.



Probate



(vi) To offer advice on proposals by organisations who have

requested that their members should be entitled to

prepare applications for probate, and in particular to

comment on their proposals for standards of competence

and conduct, and the arrangements for their

enforcement.



7.7 Any member of the public, of a profession providing legal

services, of the judiciary or the Lord Chancellor would be

able to refer to the Advisory Committee any topic or matter

arising within those areas for its consideration. How such

references were handled would be a matter for the Advisory

Committee.



The Advisory Committee&apos;s Functions and Powers



7.8 The Advisory Committee would present an annual report to

the Lord Chancellor, covering all six areas, which he would

be required to lay before Parliament. In addition, it would

present to the Lord Chancellor recommendations on proposals

made to it by professional bodies or organisations. The

Lord Chancellor would also be required to lay these before

Parliament. The professional bodies would be placed under

a statutory duty to have regard to the Advisory Committee&apos;s

advice in preparing rules of competence and conduct for

their members.


Membership



7.9 As proposed in the Green Papers, the Advisory Committee

would have 15 members.    They would comprise:



a Lord of Appeal in Ordinary or Judge of the

Supreme Court as Chairman



two practising barristers



two practising solicitors



two academic lawyers



eight people from outside these categories



7.10 The majority would not be practising lawyers. That balance

aims to ensure that the Committee primarily represents the

views and interests of the user of legal services, but

contains wide representation from those who have practical

experience of providing them.



7.11 All would be appointed by the Lord Chancellor, after wide

consultation. The members who were not practising lawyers

would be selected to ensure that they were able by character

and experience to represent on the Committee the interests

of the public and of the client for legal services.

Particularly relevant would be expertise in, or knowledge

of, the provision of legal services, the work of the courts,

social conditions, consumer affairs, business, and the

maintenance of professional standards in other professions.

Appointments would normally last for 3 years, with

eligibility for subsequent reappointment.



12   It will be for the Committee to regulate its own

proceedings. It is, however, envisaged that it will have

separate sub-committees on education and on conduct. The

Chairman   of   the   Committee   would   be   able   to delegate


chairmanship of either of the sub-committees to a member

nominated by him. If he did so he would become an ex officio

member of the sub-committee. The Committee would have the

power to co-opt non-voting members on to the sub-committees.



Financial and Staffing Arrangements



7.13 The Chairman would continue to receive his judicial salary.

Appointed members of the Committee would be paid. Although

the Committee would be operationally fully independent of

Government, it would be funded by a grant-in-aid from the

Lord Chancellor&apos;s Department on similar lines to the Legal

Aid Board.



7.14 These arrangements would enable the Advisory Committee to

appoint its own staff. The variety of experience

represented by the staff of the Law Commission, which

comprises people with backgrounds in the universities and

legal practice as well as the Civil Service, may be a useful

model for the Advisory Committee. Unlike the staff of the

Law Commission, however, the Committee&apos;s staff would not be

employed as civil servants.


8: The Role of the Professional Bodies



8.1 The Government looks to self-regulation as the most

effective overall way of maintaining standards in business

life. In this respect, the market for legal services is no

different. Self-regulation has, however, particular

importance in this area. It is to the independent

professions that a citizen who has a dispute must turn. He

or she must have complete confidence that the case will be

prepared with the utmost rigour and fearlessly presented.

That is why the Government remains committed to the

principle that in the first instance the maintenance of

professional standards amongst lawyers should be one of the

responsibilities of the professional bodies concerned.



8.2 The training regulations which govern qualification for

rights of audience or the right to conduct litigation, and

the codes of conduct which practitioners with these rights

will be required to follow, will be essential to the

maintenance of competence and proper conduct in the

provision of legal services. The Government has therefore

decided that the careful provision for their approval set

out in the following paragraphs is required.



8.3 Any body which seeks to be entitled to grant rights of

audience or the right to conduct litigation to its members

will need to make approved training regulations and codes

of conduct. Amendments may also be required in the future

to the Bar&apos;s or the Law Society&apos;s existing rules and codes.

In these circumstances the professional body or other

organisation will be required to prepare draft training

regulations and a draft code which would be submitted to the

Advisory Committee for its consideration.


8.4 The professional body or other organisation will be required

to have regard to any suggestions which the Advisory

Committee might make on the content of these draft rules

or codes. The drafts will then be submitted to the Lord

Chancellor with advice from the Committee on whether he

should give his approval to them.



8.5 It is necessary also to recognise the role of the judiciary

in determining how work before the courts is done. The

Government proposes to build on the present arrangements

under which the Law Society ?s regulations which govern the

training necessary to qualify as a solicitor are made by the

Master of the Rolls and require the concurrence of the Lord

Chief Justice and the Lord Chancellor, and others of the

Society&apos;s rules are made by its Council but require the

concurrence of the Master of the Rolls. The arrangements

will, however need to go further to ensure that the full

range of court work is represented. Draft rules relating

to the advocacy or the conduct of litigation will, under the

legislation, be made by the professional body but to become

valid will require the concurrence of the Lord Chancellor

and of each of the Lord Chief Justice, the Master of the

Rolls, the President of the Family Division, and the Vice-

Chancellor. Both the Lord Chancellor and the senior judges

will be required to have regard to the Advisory Committee&apos;s

advice. The duties of the profession, the Advisory

Committee, the Lord Chancellor and of the senior judiciary

are of course interrelated. The Government envisages that

this will in practice be reflected in the earlier stages of

the preparation of drafts by the professional bodies through

a process of discussion involving all four parties.



8.6 The statutory duty &quot;to have regard&quot; to advice from the

Committee which Parliament will be asked to impose on the

Lord Chancellor, the judiciary and the profession does not

compel any party to accept that advice. It will, however,

require that on any occasion when that advice was not

accepted,  the party which rejected it must expect to give


its reasons for so doing. Any allegation that these

statutory duties had not been carried out, or had been

fulfilled in a way in which no reasonable authority would

have done so, could of course be tested by judicial review

in the High Court or by an action for breach of statutory

duty.



Transitional Arrangements



Both the Bar Council and the Law Society have of course

already made extensive provision for training and conduct

to cover the services already provided by their members.

These will remain in force when the legislation is

implemented, and will not need to be referred to the

Advisory Committee until amendments, or provision for new

areas of work, are required. The Advisory Committee will,

however, be able to make recommendations on the existing

training regulations or codes of conduct, to which the Bar

Council and the Law Society will be required to have regard.



As the system proposed in this White Paper develops, the

Advisory Committee will also be able to comment on whether

training regulations or codes of conduct (whether those

already existing or those approved under the procedures set

out in these Chapters) need amendment to take account of

developments in the provision of legal services, or of the

way in which the regulations or codes are being administered

by professional bodies or other organisations. The

professional bodies and other organisations will be required

to have regard to those comments, whether made in the

Committee&apos;s annual report or on specific occasions.


9 : Legal Education



9.1 The existing Advisory Committee already plays an extensive

role in reviewing the provision of education in legal

matters. The Government proposes that the reconstructed

Advisory Committee should draw up a continuing work

programme to examine activities in each of the main areas

of legal education:



academic training

vocational training

practical training

continuing education



The Academic Stage



9.2 The Advisory Committee should keep under review the content

and teaching of the academic stage, and should monitor the

development of academic courses on law, having regard both

to the quality and scope of courses, and the numbers of

places available. That is not intended to encroach on the

academic freedom of the teachers of law; in order to carry

out its tasks effectively, it will have to develop close

relations with the professions, and to develop effective

liaison with universities, polytechnics, and their funding

councils. The relevant professions would continue to lay

down academic requirements for entry, subject to the

Committee&apos;s recommendations.



The Vocational Stage



9.3 The professional bodies and other organisations will

continue to be responsible for providing, or for overseeing

the provision of the relevant vocational courses. The

Committee will offer advice on ensuring standards of

competence generally.    That will also cover both the scope


and quality of courses, and the number of places available.

In the areas of advocacy and the conduct of litigation, the

professions will be bound by statute to have regard to that

advice. It is to be expected that the Committee will wish

to give advice in sufficiently broad terms to give the

providers of vocational courses as much flexibility as

possible.



Practical Training



9.4 Advocacy The Committee will wish to examine with particular

care the arrangements for practical training in advocacy.

A special area of concern in advocacy should be the

relationship between practical training under supervision

including specified tasks, and the formal vocational

training.



9.5 Litigators Practical education is also of great importance

in ensuring the effective delivery of services by

litigators. The Committee will consider what training

requirements are necessary. Practical training in areas

other than advocacy and litigation will continue to be a

matter for the professional bodies, as now, but the

Committee will be entitled to give advice in these areas.



Continuing Education



9.6 Both the substantive law, and techniques for the delivery

of legal services and for business management are developing

quickly. It is increasingly important that education to

acquire new skills and to update old ones continues after

initial qualification either as advocate or litigator. The

Committee will consider what the professional bodies and

relevant institutions might need to do to ensure that their

members undertake appropriate courses of continuing

education, and offer advice accordingly.


Specialization



9.7 The Government believes that there will always be a need for

general legal practitioners. Specialization has, however,

always been a feature of the practice of some lawyers; it

may become a still more important factor with the increasing

complexity of the social and commercial conditions to which

the law must be applied. Moreover, if competition and

diversity of choice are to be effectively encouraged, it is

important that clients have reliable information about the

qualifications and experience of the practitioners they may

wish to approach. The Government therefore sees an

important role for the development of recognised schemes of

accreditation as specialists. That must not, of course,

force practitioners who do not wish to do so to specialize

exclusively in the areas in which they have been accredited;

and it must not act as a barrier to non-accredited

specialists and other lawyers and practitioners starting or

continuing to work in such areas.



9.8 The Green Paper proposed that the Lord Chancellor should be

responsible, on the advice of the Advisory Committee, for

recognising particular specialism schemes. In the light of

the simplifying changes which have been made to the general

arrangements for securing appropriate standards of

competence and conduct, it is no longer necessary for the

Lord Chancellor to be involved. Responsibility for devising

schemes should be left to the Bar Council, the Law Society

and the relevant professional bodies. The establishment of

such schemes would recognise the importance of public

confidence that any lawyer accredited as a specialist is

able actually to deliver the services required to the

appropriate level of expertise.



9.9 Legal professional bodies would be able to submit schemes

to accredit specialists to the Advisory Committee for its

advice.    People without legal qualifications may also have


expertise in a particular area of the law. The legal

profession has at present no monopoly on giving legal

advice. The Committee will therefore also be able to give

advice on schemes put forward by bodies of non-lawyers. In

both areas it would need to be satisfied that the

qualifications for participation in the scheme, and the

criteria for the selection of members and for monitoring

their performance, were sufficient to ensure competent legal

advice in the area specified.



9.10 Approved members participating in the scheme would be able

to advertise the fact that their schemes had been drawn up

in consultation with the Advisory Committee. That

&quot;kitemark&quot; will also enable those who need to use legal

services to make a more informed choice between advisors of

an assured level of competence. It might also be that the

Committee would pay particular regard to a body&apos;s scheme for

accrediting specialists in an area of the law when

considering whether to advise the Lord Chancellor to

recommend an Order in Council authorising it to grant its

members rights of audience, or the right to conduct

litigation.



9.11 The Advisory Committee will also be able to comment in its

annual report or specifically on the need for there to be

accreditation schemes in particular instances, and how

particular schemes were working in practice. The Bar

Council, the Law Society and any other authorised

professional bodies will be bound to have regard to advice

in this respect from the Advisory Committee.


10 : Conduct, Complaints and Discipline



Present Disciplinary Arrangements



10.1 The Bar and the Law Society&apos;s present arrangements for

handling complaints are set out in some detail in Annex D

of the main Green Paper. They are, however, summarised here

for convenience.



Negligence



10.2 Barristers and solicitors are immune from an action for

negligence brought by a client in respect of the conduct and

management of a case in court, but are not immune from

actions for negligence in other situations. All practising

barristers are required to have professional indemnity

insurance of  250,000 for each and every claim. All

solicitors in practice are also required to be covered by

professional indemnity insurance against loss arising from

civil liability claims.



Professional Misconduct



10.3 The Bar Barristers are subject to professional discipline

in respect of the conduct of a case, whether in or out of

court. More minor cases may be dealt with by the

Professional Conduct Committee of the General Council of the

Bar (PCC). The PCC prosecutes the more serious cases, or

those where there is a relevant dispute of fact, before a

Disciplinary Tribunal. Appeals from the Disciplinary

Tribunal lie to the Visitors (not fewer than three judges

of the High Court).



10 4 The Law Society Complaints of professional misconduct, or

of shoddy work must be made to the Solicitors&apos; Complaints

Bureau.    The most serious cases of professional misconduct


are considered by the Solicitors&apos; Disciplinary Tribunal.

Most of the cases referred to the Tribunal are referred by

the Solicitors&apos; Complaints Bureau. A referral may also be

made direct by the public, or by the Lay Observer when a

complaint raises an issue of both conduct and quality of

services. Appeal from the Tribunal lies to the High Court,

which also retains a general supervisory jurisdiction over

the profession.



The Lay Observer



10.5 The Lay Observer is appointed by the Lord Chancellor to

examine any written allegation concerning the Law Society&apos;s

treatment of a complaint about a solicitor or his employee.

He is able to report only on this treatment and to make

recommendations, having no powers to reinvestigate the

substantive complaint.



The Green Paper Proposals



10.6 The Green Paper made proposals to reinforce these

arrangements by replacing the office of Lay Observer by a

new Legal Services Ombudsman who would have powers to

consider complaints about the way in which allegations

against the providers of legal services have been handled

by the relevant professional body; reinvestigate cases where

that is necessary; refer cases back to the relevant body;

recommend the payment of compensation; recommend changes or

improvements to procedures for dealing with complaints; and

publicize his decisions.



Responses to Consultation



10.7 These proposals have been widely welcomed in the

consultation process. Public disquiet continues about the

effectiveness of the profession&apos;s procedures for dealing

swiftly and effectively with alleged failure in professional

competence.    Many welcomed the proposal for strengthening


the office of Lay Observer with a power to investigate

complaints substantively, although some wished to see this

power extended to cover complaints against the court

administration. It was, however, also argued that the

proposals did not adequately distinguish between the

disciplinary systems of the professional bodies, and the way

in which the courts and independent tribunals deal with

cases. The interrelationship is complicated, and the

Government agrees that there is some force in these

arguments.



8 During the consultation and the discussions which have

followed, it has emerged that some consider the present,

centralised system of dealing with complaints may be too

cumbersome to deal swiftly and efficiently with minor

complaints. It has also been observed that a number of

complaints about the way in which cases have been presented

to a court raise issues which cross the responsibilities

of both litigator and advocate. It has also been suggested

that a measure of formal local involvement in disciplinary

matters would help to maintain the sense of common

standards which many feel is important to keep up

performance.



The Government&apos;s Proposals



9 It is desirable to explore further the ways in which the

suggestions for joint and local arrangements might be

implemented to improve the present system. The Government

believes that a power which enabled the Bar Council and the

Law Society to set up joint disciplinary arrangements, at

both central and local levels, in addition to the present

arrangements, would be the best way forward. Further

discussions will be held to assess how the arrangements

might be implemented. It might also be useful on occasion

for members of the local judiciary to be involved in these

arrangements, and the Lord Chancellor will discuss that

also with the judiciary.


Immunities for Work in the Courts



10.10 The Government accepts that if advocates are to be able to

carry out their overriding duty to the court in presenting

cases fully, they must be immune from actions in negligence

in respect of the conduct and management of a case in

court, and the preliminary work intimately connected with

that. Such suits could, in any event, scarcely escape re-

trying the original actions in a way that would cut across

the established appeal procedures.



10.11 The Government accordingly proposes to make it clear that

the existing common law immunity for barristers extends to

all advocates. The Legal Services Ombudsman will be

precluded from investigating any work covered by this

immunity. It should be borne in mind that such work

represents only a small fraction of the legal services

provided to clients, in an area where complaints are

comparatively infrequent.



10.12 Adequate remedies should continue to be available to enable

the courts themselves to deal with unsatisfactory work.

The Government therefore proposes that the existing rule

which enables some courts to order that a solicitor should

personally bear any part of the costs of an action where

his work has fallen short of the standards of competence

the court expects should now be extended to cover all

litigators, and all advocates as well. It is a notable

omission that the magistrates&apos; courts do not have this

power at present. It is therefore proposed to extend the

power so that in future all courts should have it. Such

an order should be made possible at the court&apos;s own motion

or on application from any party to the case, and either

at the conclusion of the case or at any time up to six

months later.


The Legal Services Ombudsman



10.13 The Government believes that further measures are needed,

however, to reinforce the existing system with more

effective measures for dealing with complaints, both about

the way in which particular cases have been handled and

the way in which professional bodies have dealt with them.

The Government therefore proposes that the office of Lay

Observer should be abolished. A new statutory office of

Legal Services Ombudsman should be created, to be

independent of Government and of the professions.



10.14 The Ombudsman will have two main functions:



he will investigate the way in which complaints

had been handled by the relevant professional

body;



he will also have power to investigate the

original complaint about the provision of legal

services.



His jurisdiction would cover both professional misconduct

and negligent or sloppy work under both heads.



10.15 The Ombudsman would not normally examine cases until the

profession&apos;s own complaints procedure had been exhausted.

There may, however, be some cases where it was alleged a

complaint was being unreasonably delayed. The Ombudsman

will therefore be given a discretion to investigate the

delay and the complaint itself, if a substantive response

has not been received from the appropriate complaints

authority within a reasonable period. The Government

proposes that this should be three months.


10.16 The Ombudsman&apos;s duties will however relate to the handling

of cases by the professional bodies concerned, not by

independent tribunals or the courts. In the case of the

Bar, his jurisdiction would cover the Professional Conduct

Committee of the General Council of the Bar. In the case

of the Law Society, it would cover the activities of the

Investigation Committee and the Adjudication Committee of

the Solicitors&apos; Complaints Bureau, and of the staff of the

Bureau itself. The Ombudsman should not have power to

consider issues which have been dealt with by a Bar

disciplinary tribunal, by the Visitors, by the Solicitors

Disciplinary Tribunal, or by the courts. He will, however,

retain the Lay Observer&apos;s power to make an application

direct to the Solicitors&apos; Disciplinary Tribunal in respect

of quality of services, which should be extended to cover

all cases.



10.17 It will be necessary to consider the proper extent of the

Ombudsman&apos;s jurisdiction in respect of the joint and local

arrangements for handling complaints proposed in paragraphs

10.8-9. The Lord Chancellor will discuss that with the

judiciary, the Bar Council and the Law Society.



10.18 The Lord Chancellor should be given power to extend the

Legal Services Ombudsman&apos;s jurisdiction by statutory

instrument, subject to affirmative resolution by both

Houses of Parliament, in respect of other professional

bodies or organisations which are given the right to give

their members rights of audience, the right to conduct

litigation, or to prepare applications for probate.


10.19 The Ombudsman&apos;s duties will be more similar to those of the

existing business ombudsmen (such as those for building

societies and banking) than to those of the Parliamentary

Commissioner for Administration, or the Local Government

Commissioner. If he is to carry out his duties effectively,

however, he will need sufficient powers to be able to

gather evidence and examine those involved. The Government

therefore proposes that, like the Parliamentary

Commissioner for Administration, he should be given powers

to require the attendance of witnesses and the production

of documents.



10.20 It will be for the Ombudsman himself to decide procedure,

particularly relating to the conduct of investigations.

The Lord Chancellor shall, however, be given powers to

issue general directions to the Ombudsman, which would be

published. These might, for example, cover the degree of

publicity to be given to the Ombudsman&apos;s scheme generally

or to specific decisions, or time limits. The Ombudsman

will be required to compile an annual report and an annual

account to be presented to the Lord Chancellor, who would

be required to lay them before Parliament.



10.21 The Government has considered whether the Ombudsman should

be given powers to investigate the administration of the

courts and the acts of court staff, as has been suggested.

The activities for which the Lord Chancellor&apos;s Department

is administratively responsible are of course subject to

investigation by the Parliamentary Commissioner for

Administration. The Commissioner&apos;s jurisdiction to

consider the work of the courts is currently the subject

of discussions. It would clearly not be appropriate for

the Legal Services Ombudsman to have powers which have

either been given to, or are inappropriate for, the

Parliamentary Commissioner. The Government accordingly

does not agree to this suggestion.


The Ombudsman&apos;s Sanctions and Remedies



10.22 The Ombudsman will have power, when an investigation was

completed, to refer cases back to any body which had

originally looked at the complaint. He will also have the

power in so doing to recommend that the body exercise

whichever of its powers he considered appropriate to the

case, including referral to any disciplinary tribunal which

had power to consider the complaint.



10.23 The Ombudsman will be given power to recommend the payment

of compensation, which would not be subject to a limit and

would depend on the facts of the case. Where the loss,

distress or inconvenience arose from the original

complaint, he should have the power to recommend that

compensation be paid by the practitioner concerned. Where

the complainant had suffered loss or distress as the result

of maladministration of the complaints procedure, the

Ombudsman will have the power to recommend that

compensation be paid by the professional body concerned.



10.24 The Ombudsman will not, however, have the power to order

the payment of compensation. In cases of non-compliance

with his recommendation that it be paid, he will be given

powers to require the body or individual concerned to

publicize their reasons for not complying with his decision

in any manner he might reasonably specify. (Similar powers

are given to the Building Society&apos;s Ombudsman.)



10.25 There is currently uncertainty about the extent of the

jurisdiction of professional bodies in the many cases where

an allegation of negligence is involved. It is wholly right

that they should not involve themselves in cases where

large amounts of money are at stake, or particularly

complex issues are involved. Comparatively few complaints

are of this kind. The effects of this uncertainty can be


to deny a simple remedy in cases in which a practitioner&apos; s

conduct seems to the complainant - and indeed, to the

disinterested observer - quite obviously to have fallen

short of professional standards. The Government considers

that an appropriately flexible and limited discretionary

power is required to fill this gap. The Ombudsman will be

given explicit power to reinvestigate all such small

negligence cases to the extent he considers necessary.



10.26 The Ombudsman will also have the power to recommend changes

or improvements to the complaints procedures of the Bar

Council, the Law Society or any other relevant supervisory

body. Such recommendations might be specific and contained

in reports issued on individual cases, or more general and

made in his annual report. For these purposes, and indeed

for the satisfactory discharge of his duties generally, the

Government expects that the Ombudsman will wish to develop

close relationships of mutual confidence with the

professional bodies, and with the Advisory Committee. He

will be required to send a copy of his annual report to the

Advisory Committee, and to refer to them reports on

individual cases which raise issues relevant to the

Advisory Committee.



Finance and Staffing



10.27 The Ombudsman and his staff will be financed directly from

a grant-in-aid from the Lord Chancellor&apos;s Department. His

services will be free to complainants. The Ombudsman will

have powers to incur expenditure within a budget, appoint

employees (which it is envisaged will include some legal

support staff), consult advisers and defray expenses.


PART THREE  :  NEW WAYS OF WORKING



11 : Competition in the Provision of Legal Services



11.1 To be efficient those who provide legal services must

develop their practices and working methods to meet the

changing needs of their clients. The Government believes

that competition offers the client the best opportunity to

make a choice in the services which he needs according to

what represents best value to him. This does not remove

the need to maintain standards and integrity. To make a

sound choice the client needs both information about the

different kinds of practitioner and the services they

offer, and confidence that they are all subject to adequate

standards of competence and conduct. The Government&apos;s

proposals to achieve that aim are set out in the preceding

Parts of this White Paper.



11.2 The providers of legal services are also affected by

competition law. The Government proposes in the White

Paper &apos;Opening Markets: New Policy on Restrictive Trade

Practices&apos; (Cm 727) that professional services will be

brought within new restrictive trade practices (RTP)

legislation. The rules of those bodies whose members

provide legal services will therefore be subject to the

proposed prohibition on anti-competitive agreements. As

that White Paper notes (paragraph 3.8), however, rules

which are contained in or required by statute, or which

require the approval of a Minister before they come into

force, will not fall within the prohibition. The rules

made by professional bodies and organisations to cover

advocacy in court, the conduct of litigation and associated

training, which it is now proposed should require the

concurrence of the Lord Chancellor and the Heads of

Division, will therefore be excluded from the RTP

prohibition.


11.3 The RTP White Paper also explains that agreements of this

nature would nevertheless come within the legislation to

the extent that the Director General of Fair Trading will

be empowered to obtain information on the relevant rules

and their effects, and to report on their anti-competitive

effects, commenting on any restrictions which appear not

to be necessary to achieve the rules&apos; objectives. In the

case of the codes relating to advocacy and the conduct of

litigation and associated training, however, the Government

has decided that more specific provisions should be

introduced to ensure that the Lord Chancellor will always

have advice on the competition implications of rules which

require his concurrence. Accordingly, there will be

provision for rules, including any amendments to existing

codes, put forward by the Bar or the Law Society to be

referred to the Director General, whose comments will be

taken into account by the Lord Chancellor and the senior

judges in exercising their powers. These arrangements will

be similar to those in respect of the auditing profession

which have been incorporated into the Companies Bill.



11.4 As has already been made clear, the Bar&apos;s and the Law

Society&apos;s current rules and codes will remain in force when

the legislation proposed in this White Paper is

implemented, until either professional body chooses to

amend them. The remainder of both professions&apos; regulatory

frameworks, subject to the arrangements described below in

Chapter 12, will therefore be subject to the RTP

prohibition in the normal way. For those rules which

restrict or distort competition, it will be up to the

professional body concerned to amend them or to apply for

an exemption within the transitional period which that

legislation will contain. This may lead the Bar and the

Law Society to implement a number of the changes canvassed

in the Green Papers.


11.5 In the case of new regulations, the body of regulation the

professions will require is in some areas likely to cover

matters falling partly within the ambit of training

regulations or codes of conduct concerned specifically with

the regulation of advocacy and the conduct of litigation,

and partly outside. In such areas, the Lord Chancellor

will seek to ensure, with the advice of the Advisory

Committee and the Director General of Fair Trading, that

draft regulations approved by him, and therefore outside

the prohibition contained in the RTP legislation, are

solely and specifically confined to matters required for

the regulation of advocacy and the conduct of litigation

in the interests of the administration of justice.



11.6 An example of this would be the proposal in the Green Paper

that non-lawyers should be able to instruct barristers

directly. Responses to the consultation suggested that

this would undermine the independence of the Bar, would

swamp barristers in unnecessary office work, and would lead

to clients with insufficient knowledge of members of the

legal profession approaching barristers without the

expertise they required.



11.7 The Government believes, however, that it is more

appropriate to leave it to the barristers&apos; profession to

decide, in the light of the nature of their own practice

and the needs of clients, whether or not they wish to take

instructions directly from lay clients. The Lord

Chancellor would accordingly be likely to take this view

in considering any future draft rules made by the Bar.



Barristers&apos; Fees



11.8 The Green Paper made an associated proposal that the rule

of common law that barristers could not form contractual

relationships with those who instruct them should be

removed. This proposal has been welcomed by the Bar

Council.    It is important to ensure that the law does not


unnecessarily restrict the ways in which barristers may

offer their services. The Government therefore proposes

to introduce legislation enabling barristers to make

contracts for the payment of their fees.


12 : Multi-disciplinary Partnerships



12.1 The Green Papers proposed that any barriers which prevent

solicitors and barristers from practising in conjunction

with members of any other profession should be removed.

This proposal was the subject of much comment during the

consultation process. It was argued that it might

significantly reduce choice for the clients of both

advocates and litigators, and reduce the independence of

the Bar.



12.2 The first question arises in relation to the present

disparity in the regulation of these partnerships. Multi-

disciplinary partnerships between solicitors are currently

prohibited by the combined effect of section 39 of the

Solicitors Act 1974 and section 5 of the Partnership Act

1890, as well as by the Law Society&apos;s Practice Rules.

Barristers are prohibited from forming partnerships by

professional rules alone. The Government believes as a

matter of principle that this inequality is undesirable.

The Government also believes that the regulation of how the

members of professional bodies organize themselves to meet

their clients&apos; needs is best left to the professions

themselves subject to a proper scrutiny to avoid

unnecessary or undesirable anti-competitive effects. The

Government therefore proposes to remove the statutory

barrier to solicitors forming partnerships with members

of other professions. This matter will thereupon become

one entirely for the professional bodies involved.



12.3 The present legislation on restrictive trade practices

permits professions to draw up their own rules on

partnerships and other matters. Indeed, the existing

controls  on  barristers   forming  partnerships  with other


professions are professional rules of this kind. As has

been made clear in Chapter 11, rules which require the

approval of a Minister before they can come into force will

be exempt from prohibition under the new legislation on

restrictive trade practices proposed in Opening Markets:

New Policy on Restrictive Trade Practices&apos;. It is the

Government&apos;s intention that rules of conduct made by a

professional body to govern the formation of partnerships

between members of that professional body, or between

members of that professional body and others, which fall

within the areas of practice which could be submitted by

the professional body for approval by the Lord Chancellor

and the senior judges, could, if approved by the Lord

Chancellor, after advice from the Director General of Fair

Trading as to any anti-competitive effects, be exempt from

prohibition.


13 : Multi-national Partnerships



13.1 Annex A to the main Green Paper set out the implications

for the provision of legal services of the present European

Community provisions on freedom of establishment and

freedom to provide services within the Community, and of

the measures to achieve a single internal market by the end

of 1992. Those measures all tend to make it easier for

professionals who are nationals of one member state to

practise in other member states as a member of the local

profession.



13.2 The Green Papers proposed the removal of both the statutory

and any other barriers to the formation of partnerships

between barristers or solicitors and lawyers from another

jurisdiction. Those who commented on this during the

consultation were generally in favour of it. The

increasingly international nature of commercial operations,

and in particular the completion of the single market in

Europe in 1992, is agreed to be widening the role for such

partnerships. It was argued that this role will be

significantly enlarged for United Kingdom lawyers when the

European Community directive on the recognition of diplomas

comes into force early in 1991.



13.3 The Government accordingly proposes to remove the statutory

prohibition on the formation of such partnerships. It hopes

that the professional bodies will speedily review their own

rules to enable multi-national partnerships subject to

appropriate professional safeguards to be formed with

lawyers from the European Community and from other

jurisdictions as quickly as possible. There is no

acceptable reason to delay that pending reciprocal

implementation in other EC countries.


13.4 Further measures will, however, be necessary. The EC

regulations govern only relations between member states,

not between different legal jurisdictions within member

states. This means that lawyers qualified only in one part

of the UK already have, and will increasingly have, greater

opportunities to practise in other EC member states than

they do in other parts of the UK. This is clearly

anomalous.



13.5 The Government therefore proposes that the Lord Chancellor,

the Secretary of State for Scotland, and the Secretary of

State for Northern Ireland should be given power to make

regulations which will ensure that UK lawyers should have

rights to practise in other parts of the kingdom at least

equivalent to those available to lawyers from other EC

countries.


14 : Contingent and Conditional Fees



14.1 The Green Paper on contingency fees, acting on a

recommendation by the Civil Justice Review, examined the

justification for existing restrictions on the use of such

fees and considered a number of options under which such

agreements could be made enforceable under English law.



14.2 The Green Paper stimulated lively debate on the

acceptability in principle of any contingency fee

arrangement, and on the differences between those

jurisdictions where it is permitted in some form or other

and the legal and commercial arrangements in England and

Wales. There was a clear consensus that it would not be

right in principle, and would be likely to have a number

of undesirable side effects, for a lawyer to be permitted

to undertake a case in return for some percentage of

whatever damages might be received. That form of

contingency fee was also thought likely to create an

unacceptable degree of conflict of interest between the

lawyer and his client, which could result in his being

unable to give the client or the court advice of the

required degree of impartiality. There was, however, little

objection to the proposal that arrangements following the

model of the Scottish speculative action (payment of normal

fees only if successful) should be allowed in England and

Wales, and some support for the proposition that the client

and his lawyers should be able to agree an uplift to those

costs when acting on this basis. There was, moreover, a

very clear consensus that the general rule that costs

follow the event should not be changed.


14.3 The Government accordingly proposes to remove the existing

prohibitions to enable clients to agree with any or all of

their lawyers payment of a conditional fee on the

speculative basis already permitted in Scotland. This

relaxation will not, however, extend to criminal and family

(matrimonial, care, and wardship) proceedings which the

Government believes are inappropriate for conditional

funding.



14.4 The Government also accepts that it would be reasonable for

a lawyer who represents a client on this basis to balance

the risk of losing the case and ending up with no costs by

charging at a higher rate than would have been appropriate

but for the conditional factor. It therefore proposes that

power be given to the Lord Chancellor to prescribe by

subordinate legislation, after consultation with the

profession, the maximum uplift to be expressed in terms of



[ a moderate percentage of the normal costs, which may be

applied to those costs for the benefit of the lawyer where

the lawyer is acting for a conditional fee. The

legislation will recognise that different levels of uplift

may be appropriate for different classes of case. The

lawyer and his client will be free to agree any lower

percentage. The ability to agree this uplift will not

affect the amount to be paid by the losing opponent. There

will be no change in the existing rule that costs should

follow the event. The Lord Chancellor intends to consult

further on the level of the prescribed percentage.



14.5 The Lord Chancellor will of course wish to monitor closely

the impact the introduction of these arrangements has upon

the legal system. Regulating the level of the uplift by

statutory instrument will provide an adequate mechanism for

control should the effects prove to be unexpectedly

adverse.


14.5 The Government also accepts that it would be reasonable for

a lawyer who represents a client on a conditional fee basis

to balance the risk of losing the case and ending up with

no costs by charging at a higher rate than would have been

appropriate but for the conditional factor. This costs

premium may be agreed between the lawyer and his client,

perhaps expressly in the conditional fee agreement itself.

If the client applies to have his solicitor&apos;s bill taxed,

the premium, expressed as an additional percentage of the

ordinary taxed costs, wull be added to the costs once they

have been taxed in the usual way. A limit on the amount

of the premium will be prescribed by statutory instrument

made by the Lord Chancellor. Different premiums may be

appropriate for different classes of care. The legislation

will provide for that.



14.7 The Lord Chancellor will of course wish to monitor closely

the impact the introduction of these arrangements have upon

the legal system. The regulation of the conditional

premium will provide an adequate mechanism for its control

should the effects prove to be unexpectedly adverse.


PART FOUR  :  JUDICIAL APPOINTMENTS



15.1 The Government regards it as a matter of great importance

that the highest standards of intellect and character should

be maintained in appointments to the judiciary. The prospect

of appointment to the Bench should also be an encouragement

for the men and women who have made the law their career to

reach the highest standards of service to the public. But

that encouragement should be open to all if it is to operate

as an effective stimulus to excellence in all parts of our

legal system, and if the Lord Chancellor is to be free to

consider the best practitioners of all kinds for

appointment.



15.2 For these reasons the Green Papers proposed that all those

who had held the appropriate advocacy qualifications for

suitable lengths of time should be eligible for judicial

appointments; and that the judges in a lower court should

be eligible for promotion to a higher one on the basis of

their judicial experience in the lower court.



15.3 The suggestion that the highest judicial offices should be

open to all with suitable experience was widely welcomed

in the consultation. It was agreed that a practitioner&apos;s

early decisions on form of training should not limit his or

her chances of proceeding through merit and character to

hold some of the most important offices under the Crown.



15.4 The Government accordingly proposes to revise and extend the

conditions for appointment to judicial office. The

simplification of the proposals for granting rights of

audience will, however, make it possible to simplify

significantly the system of eligibility requirements

proposed in the Green Paper.


Qualifications for a Practitioner



5 Under the adversarial system in this country, experience as

an advocate in work of an appropriate range and complexity

is required to preside effectively as a judge. Experience

of past appointments demonstrates, however, that it is not

necessary for a new judge to have practised in all of the

areas in which he or she may be called to sit. The

Government accordingly proposes that the minimum

qualification as a practitioner for appointment to the Bench

should be rights of audience as set out below:



(i) Lord of Appeal In Ordinary

General right of    audience in the Supreme Court for

15 years.



(ii) Lord Justice of Appeal, Judge of the High Court, Deputy

High Court Judge



General right of audience in the High Court and the

Court of Appeal for 10 years.



(iii) Circuit Judge, Recorder, Assistant Recorder



General right of audience in the Crown Court or the

county courts for 10 years.



(iv) Master or Registrar of the Supreme Court, County Court

Registrar, Stipendiary Magistrate



Rights of audience in the Supreme Court or a general

right of audience in the county courts for 7 years.



Qualifications for a Judicial Officer



6 The present qualification for appointment as a Lord of

Appeal in Ordinary of at least two years of service as Lord

Chancellor or as a judge of one of the Superior Courts in

Great Britain and Northern Ireland will remain unchanged.

Any person who has been a Circuit Judge for at least 2 years

should be eligible for appointment as a judge of the Supreme


Court. Any person who has been a registrar, or an

equivalent judicial officer, for at least 3 years should be

eligible for appointment as a Circuit Judge. The provision

requiring a solicitor to serve for at least 3 years as a

Recorder before becoming eligible for appointment to the

Circuit Bench will be removed.



15.7 There are various other judicial appointments, mostly at

lower levels, where the eligibility requirements will need

to be amended in line with this approach.



15.8 It is the Lord Chancellor&apos;s current practice not to appoint

serving civil servants to any paid judicial office which

would involve hearing criminal cases. Because it is general

practice now not to appoint to a full-time judicial office

someone who has not held a part-time judicial office for a

number of years prior to that, a member of any part of the

Government Legal Service could not now in practice become

a judge without first returning to private practice for a

substantial period.



Transitional Arrangements



15.9 The Government proposes the following transitional

arrangements:



(a) Barristers All barristers who had been called when the

new arrangements came into force would be eligible for

all appointments for which they are at present

eligible, provided they were of, or achieved, the

standing required by the present law. In addition they

would become eligible for appointment as County Court

Registrars, again provided they were of or achieved the

required number of years standing.



(b) Solicitors All solicitors who were on the roll when

the new arrangements came into force would be eligible

for all appointments provided:


(i) in the case of appointments to the House of

Lords or the Supreme Court Bench, they were

of or achieved the standing now required for

barristers and acquired rights of audience

in the appropriate court;



(ii) in the case of appointments to the Circuit

Bench, they were of, or achieved the standing

now required for barristers; and



(iii) in the case of appointments as Masters and

Registrars, they were of or achieved 7 years&apos;

standing.


GREEN PAPERS ON THE LEGAL PROFESSION

Analysis of responses



The Lord Chancellor received 2050 responses in all, from:

solicitors



collectively (eg law societies, associations)104

individually (eg individuals and firms) 975



barristers



collectively (eg chambers, associations)

individually



judiciary



collectively



individually



others



(a) legal and advice



eg legal executives, conveyancers,

LAG,   Justice,   NACAB



(b) educators (legal academics and teaching



institutions or authorities)

consumer representatives

financial institutions

other professionals (eg accountants,



surveyors, estate agents)



public



23

246



9

62



49



26

11

25



44



5%

48%



1%

12%



*



3%



2%



1%

*



1%

2%



53%



13%



3%



496 25%



6%



25%



2. The Government&apos;s objective, as stated in the main Green

Paper, is to secure



&quot;the best possible access  to legal  service...... of the



right quality for the particular needs of the client&quot;.



3. To this end, the key issues addressed in the green papers

are:



(a) the scope for the deregulation of the legal profession

in order to secure a better framework for the provision

of legal services; and



(b) whether new mechanisms (ie forms of regulation) are

required to ensure that legal services are provided to

an acceptable standard by competent practitioners, and



(c) that clients have appropriate means of redress where

the normal arrangements fail.


A number of broad concerns have dominated the argument and

certain points have been repeatedly made.



4. The proposals which have stimulated most comment are those

dealing with rights of audience, education and the role of the

advisory committee, MDPs, conveyancing, and contingency fees.

The bulk of the responses from the profession, and from many

others, expressed the anxiety that deregulation as proposed would

not by itself achieve the stated objective; and that the new

measures proposed to regulate competence and conduct were

inappropriate to varying degrees and for various reasons. There

were some respondents, predominantly lay and consumer-oriented

who (while particular views vary from topic to topic )were content

with the thrust of the proposals so far as they went. They did,

however, share concerns about possible government interference

in the legal and judicial machinery and the pattern of provision

and access to legal services, particularly publicly funded

services, in the future. The general line taken by respondents

on the key issues is given below.



Rights of audience/advocacy



5. Most of the principal representative and institutional

respondents, except the Bar and the judges, supported the

proposals for extended rights of audience for solicitors and the

CPS. The majority of individual solicitors responding echoed the

Bar&apos;s claims that the change would eventually put small firms

out of business. Fewer commented on the proposal concerning

employed lawyers generally but the Law Society supported the

change, while the Bar and judges opposed it.



6. Given that there would be change, nearly half of those who

commented said that the certification machinery proposed was

broadly acceptable; around 40% including the Law Society

considered it too complex; and most of the remainder (apparently

misconstruing the proposal) felt that it was inappropriate for

a quango to certify advocates.



Conveyancing



7. The great majority of respondents were solicitors who

overwhelmingly opposed the proposals, fearing for solicitors&apos;

livelihoods, the maintenance of a network of solicitors&apos; offices

to provide a general legal service to the public, and the nature

of the service that would be provided in future to conveyancing

clients, if conveyancing were done within a lending institution.



8. There was no belief, on the part of solicitors or other

respondents that a &quot;level playing field&quot; could be made to

operate.


Professional standards and discipline



9. The proposal to abolish the post of Lay Observer and create

a Legal Services Ombudsman was well received, although many

suggestions were made as to the detail of the new arrangements.



Education and specialisation



10. Around 300 respondents commented on the proposal for a

reconstituted advisory committee. Around 50% of these would

accept a higher profile role for the committee or some new body.

At least half of these, however, perceived a constitutional

threat in the original proposals; and both the Law Society and

Bar felt that the committee should advise the profession and not

the Lord Chancellor.



Barristers&apos; practices



11. Most of these proposals were effectively overtaken by the

Bar&apos;s proposed action plan, with the exceptions of partnerships

at the Bar, and employment of staff to assist with legal work.

Both were seen by the Bar to diminish the extent of

barristers&apos;independence and personal responsibility for work

done. If partners were prevented from acting for both sides in

an action, as solicitors are, it was thought that access to

expert advice and advocacy would be severely reduced.



Multi-disciplinary and multi-national partnerships



12. Multi-disciplinary partnerships involving barristers were

strenuously opposed. Partnerships of solicitors and others drew

a mixed response, with two thirds of solicitor respondents,

including the Law Society, opposing and the majority of non-

lawyers and a third of solicitors supporting them. There was

some concern about international repercussions for solicitors

involved in such practices.



13. Multi-national practices of solicitors were considered an

inevitability, but there were calls for care in determining how

this might operate in detail.



Contingency fees



14. There were nearly 500 responses on this topic. The

majority of respondents (60%) were again solicitors. There was

little support for a full contingency fee system. Many saw a

more limited option as being ineffective unless the costs rules

were changed. There was some support for legalising speculative

actions, although it was again stressed that their use would be

minimal. Most respondents expressed the fear that the government

was looking for a means to introduce a form of contingency fee

in order to justify cuts in the legal aid arrangements and

registered their opposition to such a move.



Judicial appointments



16. The great majority of both representative and individual

respondents on this issue (though not the Council of Circuit

Judges) supported the proposals to appoint solicitors to the High

Court Bench and allow promotion to the High Court Bench from

other judicial offices. There was also some call for increased

training for the judiciary.


LEGAL EDUCATION AND THE GROWTH OF SPECIALISATION  (Chapter 3)



It was proposed in the Green Paper that the Lord Chancellor&apos;s

advisory committee on legal education and training be

reconstituted to advise the Lord Chancellor on all matters

relating to the education, training, and conduct of the legal

profession. The committee would also take on particular

additional functions in connection with the further proposals

concerning specialist services, including advocacy, and the wider

provision of legal advice. The committee would be appointed by

the Lord Chancellor and submit an annual report to him. There

would be 15 members, who would be a judge as chairman, 2

barristers and 2 solicitors appointed after consultation with the

Bar Council and Law Society, 2 academic representatives, and 8

lay members. The secretariat would be provided by the Lord

Chancellor&apos;s Department.



Is it appropriate to establish a new body with specified

responsibilities for legal education and conduct?



There were 300 responses covering this topic. Respondents

divided into four broad groups:



(a) those (19%) who would be content to see a new body as

proposed: this group included the Consumers&apos;Association,

the Solicitors Complaints Bureau Investigation Committee,

and Chartered Association of Certified Accountants; the

High Court Judges would also appear here if it were decided

to adopt their proposal that the Lord Chancellor should

obtain the concurrence of the judiciary to any decisions and

changes to be made under the new arrangements.



(b) those (22%) who would find the body acceptable if it were

more independent (for example appointing its own staff) and

advised the professional bodies and not the Lord Chancellor:

this group included the Law Society and Bar and many other

groups of practitioners, and the Council of Circuit Judges.



(c) those (3%) who welcomed the representation of broader public

interests in the regulation of the profession, but who would

wish to see the new body be more independent and have

executive powers (sometimes across a broad legal services

sprectrum):   this group included the DGFT, NCC, LAG and LCF;



(d) those (48%) who considered that any change represented

unnacceptable interference in the self-regulation of the

profession: including the Council of European Bars and Law

Societies (CCBE), Institute of Chartered Accountants and

Association of British Insurers and many individual

solicitors and barristers, who commented that the profession

had done a good job on education and conduct so far, and

that the State should not take on the roles envisaged;


The legal academics and teachers generally, and a number of

others also suggested that the distinction between the two

functions proposed be recognised either by a separation into two

committees, or the creation of separate sub-committees.



On the proposed membership, lawyer respondents generally argued

for a professional majority, while consumer representatives

supported the lay majority proposed. The law teachers saw a need

for more places for them to be represented. A number of further

respondents also wished to see their own interests directly

reflected in the membership, eg legal executives, patent agents,

and the magistrates courts.



Should the Lord Chancellor have the final decision on

professional training and recognition of specialisms?

Views on this point followed almost exactly those expressed on

the proposed reconstitution of the Advisory Committee, with most

of those who commented emphatically opposing the proposals for

the reasons given with relation to the role of the committee.



Should more areas of specialism be developed?



Around two thirds of the respondents on this issue, mostly

individual solicitors opposed greater specialisation. They

emphasised the need for local general practices and felt that

more specialist staffs and experience developed naturally in the

course of parctice if there were a local demand. The proportion

favouring specialisation increased markedly however if the main

representative and institutional responses were considered. Here

there was overwhelmingsupport for specialisation schemes in order

to provide the public with competent practitioners possessing the

expertise to deal with the increasingly complex problems of

commerce and society. This broad consensus concealed a range of

views, however, though none wished for exclusive schemes since

that would restrict access to services. Most stressed a need for

good general training and for generalist practitioners as well

as specialists. The Bar Council and a number of individual

solicitors argued that barristers were already specialists and

that further specialisation would lead to disadvantages of

inflexibility and lack of cross-fertilisation.



Should accredited specialists be allowed to advertise?



The respondents who commented strongly supported the advertising

of specialisms, commenting that there was little point in

specialisation if no-one knew about it. Some, however, felt that

any such advertising should be closely controlled. Respondents

were mainly solicitors,  and consumer representatives.


MAINTENANCE OF PROFESSIONAL STANDARDS  (Chapter 4)



Should there be clear written codes setting standards for legal

advice and assistance and for matters connected with advocacy?



Should failure to observe these be a cause for disciplinary

proceedings?



There was widespread support for the proposed codes from

solicitors, barristers, public and consumer representatives. A

number of solicitors and barristers said that the principles

outlined in the Green Paper were already contained in their

respective professional codes. Some respondents clearly hoped

that the proposed codes would go further in effect, for example

to improve communication between solicitors and their clients.

Particular comments which arose were:



(a) disciplinary sanctions were inappropriate in trivial cases;



(b) non-compliance should not of itself be a disciplinary

offence or proof of shoddy work or negligence; that would

be too inflexible but the same effect could be achieved by

providing that non-compliance should be prima facie evidence

against the lawyer, who would then have to demonstrate that

no disciplinary offence had been committed;



(c) care would be needed in the drafting and enforcement of the

codes if this were not to become a simple bureaucratic

exercise; standards should not be set so low as to be

meaningless but there was a danger if they were too detailed

that they would add nothing to the conduct of cases but

nevertheless increase work and so costs



(b) any code should apply to all providers of legal services and

breaches of the code, by a member of any relevant profession

should be dealt with by a single tribunal or there would be

disparity in judgment and sentence which would justifiably

be resented;



(c) any advocacy code would have to acknowledge that the

advocate who was intended to appear could be unavoidably

detained elsewhere forcing a replacement to be called who

would almost inevitably be less fully prepared;



(d) the advocacy code needed to give guidance on the distinction

between investigation of the case and conduct of the trial,

particularly in criminal cases;



(e) if standards set required additional work to be done this

must be reflected in legal aid remuneration.



(f) the proposal in the green paper that courts should be able

to require solicitors and barristers personally to pay all

or part of the costs of an action should not apply to lay

magistrates.


Should the advisory committee advise the Lord Chancellor on these

codes?



Most respondents on this issue opposed the proposal, either

explicitly or as a natural consequence of their general

opposition to the roles proposed for the Advisory Committee and

the Lord Chancellor. Both the Law Society and Bar would be

prepared to take advice from an independent body, and the Bar

suggested an enhanced role for the judiciary in controlling the

conduct of both solicitors and barristers.



Should the principles embodied in these codes be prescribed by

statutory instrument?



Some respondents, for example the NCC and SCB were quite content

with this. A number of others, however, felt that Parliament had

insufficient part to play in the making of statutory instruments

and that the Government&apos;s drafts would be simply rubber stamped.

Some felt that it would be appropriate to state the principles

in primary legislation, others that this should be left entirely

to the profession.



Should other professions whose members wished to offer legal

services for reward or conduct advocacy be required to have the

appropriate codes?



This was strongly supported, with the single reservation



that   it  was  probably   impossible  to  impose  such  code  on lay



advisers,  whether or not they charged for their services.



Should the office of lay observer be abolished and replaced by

a Legal Services Ombudsman?



This proposal prompted a large, wholly supportive response from

both the profession and public. A number of variants were

proposed on the framework outlined in the green paper



(a) the Solicitors Complaints Bureau should be abolished and its

role taken on by the Ombudsman



(b) the green paper proposed that local law societies set up

local conciliation panels to deal with complaints; it was

suggested that panel members be trained by the Ombudsman;



(c) the Ombudsman should have the power to oversee the

performance of Government Departments concerned with the

administration of the legal system including the Legal Aid

Board and the Land Registry;



(d) the Ombudsman should be assisted by a liaison committee,

which he or she would chair, comprising representatives of

the Bar, Law Society and ILEX to monitor professional

performance and standards;



(f) the Bar and judges felt that it would be inappropriate for

the Ombudsman to have powers to investigate the way a case

was dealt with by a disciplinary tribunal presided over by

a judge as Visitor.


both the Law Society and Bar both had reservations about the

proposal for payment of compensation by them in appropriate


RIGHTS OF AUDIENCE/ADVOCACY (Chapter 5)



The Government proposed in the Green Papers that rights of

audience in the higher courts be extended to suitably qualified

solicitors and, potentially, other qualified, specialist

advocates.



Should advocacy be an exclusive specialism?



42 respondents considered this point specifically and nearly two

thirds felt that advocacy should be an exclusive activity. Both

the National Consumer Council and the Legal Action Group, however,

took the opposite view and considered that professional training,

codes and regulation -involving the advisory committee as

required should be sufficient to ensure that lawyers did not act

beyond their competence and that clients could enjoy greater

choice



Should rights of audience to the Crown Court and High Court be

open to all who are properly trained and suitably experienced

subject to codes of conduct which maintain standards?



There were two clear camps dividing the 675 respondents on the

issue of rights of audience. There was very considerable support

from the Law Society, a number of solicitors, and others for the

more specific proposal to allow competent solicitors to appear

in the Crown Court and High Court. They argued that the current

rules placed unnecessary and unjustified restrictions on

solicitors and clients, and that solicitors would often be fully

competent to deal with cases before those courts. In appropriate

cases the service to clients would be as good or better, and

cheaper or no more expensive, than would be provided by a

barrister; clients would benefit from the fact that they were

represented by someone fully familiar with their case, who might

have represented them in a lower court. Some argued that the

change would pose no threat to the Bar since few solicitors would

actually wish to exercise such rights regularly because of the

difficulty of combining court and office activities. Some felt

that it might have a more significant impact on the organisation

of the profession as a whole but that this would not necessarily

be detrimental; specialist advocates and experts in particular

fields of law would continue to be needed and could continue to

work effectively and profitably as independent consultants.



These arguments were opposed by the Council of Judges and the

Council of Circuit Judges, the Bar and the majority of

individual solicitors and barristers who commented. They argued

that all advocates should be bound by a single code of conduct

administered by a single professional body since that alone would

maintain standards. They also said that barristers were

generally more efficient and competent in the lower courts; that

daily practice was essential for a good advocate; and that

solicitors therefore remained inexperienced at it. Some felt

specifically that all decisions on rights of audience should be

the responsibility of the judges.


Many considered that the proposal posed a substantial threat to

the Bar, and by extension to smaller firms of solicitors and

their clients, who would continue to need access to specialist

advice and representation. On that basis, many said that

solicitors wanting to specialise in advocacy work should transfer

to the Bar, and that that move should be made easier.



Is the machinery to determine standards for advocacy and issue

of certificates appropriate to achieve wider rights of audience

for suitably qualified or experienced advocates?



146 respondents commented on this issue. The Council of Circuit

Judges and Bar in particular maintained that no extension of

rights of audience was appropriate if standards were to be

maintained: they argued that the certification procedure

proposed, which would rely in part on hours spent in court with

no separate assessment of the standard of performance, would not

ensure quality; and that an insistence on general experience

would exclude many very good, specialist barristers from a full

certificate.



Many of those who favoured extended rights of audience felt that

the machinery proposed was unnecessarily cumbersome. They

preferred schemes for further advocacy training, after which

successful trainees should be authorised to appear in the higher

courts.



Should employed lawyers have the same rights of audience as

lawyers in private practice?    If not,  what restrictions should



apply?



There were 65 responses on this issue. The Council of Judges,

Council of Circuit Judges and a few practitioners (including the

Legal Aid Practitioners&apos; Group) felt that the present

restrictions should be retained. The judges maintained that

employed lawyers would not be fully objective in approach and

that they would not be abl.e to have complete trust in them. The

Bar claimed that only those practising independently should be

able to appear in the higher courts. It was felt that it would

be impossible to devise codes of conduct sufficient to ensure

that conflicts of interest were prevented. The CCBE said that

employed lawyers elsewhere in Europe were not able to appear in

that way and that any change might prejudice the position of

English and Welsh lawyers working there.



The proposal was supported however by the Law Society, LAG, the

Solicitors Complaints Bureau, and the Institute of Chartered

Accountants and a number of consumer groups. A number of

individual employed barristers also supported the proposal.



Should employed CPS lawyers have rights of audience in all

criminal courts? If not, what restrictions should apply?

There were 66 responses on this. The Council of Judges and

Council of Circuit Judges, Bar and Bar students responding

collectively opposed such a change. They argued that it did not

accord with the principle that the investigation and prosecution

of cases should be separated; and that as employed lawyers they


would in any event lack the necessary degree of independence

before the court. The circuit judges envisaged all prosecution

work being done in-house, to the detriment of the independent

Bar, and the loss of the current general experience of criminal

work. The Bar claimed that representation by in-house advocates

would be no cheaper, and proposed to facilitate transfers between

private practice and the CPS as an alternative means to improve

CPS morale and career prospects.



Others, including the Law Society, LAG and LAPG supported the

proposal though both LAG and LAPG would prevent the appointment

to the judiciary of advocates with experience of prosecution

alone.



Should the Advisory Committee advise the Lord Chancellor on the

educational qualifications and training of advocates appropriate

for each of the various courts?



Views on this issue followed the line taken on the advisory

committee more generally.


IMMUNITY FROM ACTION IN NEGLIGENCE IN ADVOCACY WORK (Chapter 6)



A client may not sue his or her barrister or solicitor or

advocate for negligence in the conduct and management of the case

in court nor for certain preliminary activities.



This ensures that barristers and solicitors may carry out their

duty to the court fearlessly and independently and prevents the

retrial of actions on grounds of negligence by the advocate.



Should the present immunity of solicitor and barrister advocates

from suits for negligence in their conduct and management of

trials extend to all recognised advocates?



Around two thirds of the 45 respondents on this topic (mainly

solicitors and barristers) supported the proposal; just under a

third (mainly members of the public and consumer and other

bodies) opposed it; and a small proportion were neutral.



Few gave reasons but the most common argument put forward by

those in favour of the retention of immunity and its extension

to others including lay advocates, was that its removal would

inhibit advocates&apos; abilities to carry out their duty to the court

fearlessly and independently: a barrister is obliged to present

the full facts of the case to the court whether or not they

support the client, and not the often partial picture perceived

and preferred by the client. It was also felt that the removal

of immunity would lead to an increase in litigation as

unsatisfied litigants, blaming their advocate for the failure of

their case, would seek to sue for negligence and effectively

attempt to bring about a retrial of their case.



Against this, it was argued that advocates did on occasion

perform incompetently and that clients should be able to sue them

to obtain a remedy. While it was said that the public should be

made aware that negligent preparation and advocacy were matters

of professional misconduct and as such could be dealt with by the

relevant complaint and disciplinary authorities, this remedy was

considered insufficient. Setting standards of acceptable care

and conduct applicable to all, and covering preparations as well

as advocacy, might be of some benefit. In general, however

respondents opposing the proposal did not believe that removal

of the immunity would affect the advocates relationship with the

court. The simple reason for this was that no judge would uphold

a claim for negligence when the advocate had put duty to the

court before duty to the client. The Judiciary would be capable

of controlling frivolous actions and unmeritorious claims.


ATTENDENCE ON COUNSEL  (Chapter 7)



The Government considers that it is not justifiable for the

professional practice rules to require that the advocate in Court

must be attended by solicitors (or the solicitors

representative/agent).



Should the professional practice rules require attendance by a

solicitor or solicitors&apos; representative?



Around 90% of the 103 respondents on this issue (solicitors,

barristers, members of the public and others) felt that it was

unnecessary and unjustifiable for the professional practice rules

to require that counsel always be attended in court and that this

could lead on occasion to duplication of work and unnecessary

cost. The Bar Council also took this view.



Opposition to such a change came from a few members of the

judiciary and barristers who felt that attendance on counsel was

always cost effective, avoiding frequent adjournments for counsel

to take instructions, or marshal witnesses, and waste of court

time.



Of those who commented further, a number felt that attendance

remained highly desirable in more complex court applications:

some mentioned in particular substantive civil and criminal

trials and instances where there was a multitude of witness

evidence. In such cases the advocate could not reasonably be

expected to present the case properly and at the same time follow

evidence and new matters arising out of cross examination.



Should it be for the paying party to decide whether counsel

should be attended?



There were 75 respondents on this point. Around 70%

(predominantly solicitors, members of the public and others) felt

that the paying party should be allowed to decide whether counsel

should be attended in court, on advice when required. When a

reason was given it was generally that the paying party should

not be forced to pay for two legal representatives to be present

in court. It was noted that the private client might be putting

considerable personal resources at risk in coming to court and

should have as much say as possible in the progress of the case.

Certain solicitors within this group did however say that they

would reserve the right to terminate their retainer should they

disagree with the client&apos;s decision.



Those who did not consider the client the right person to

determine the need for attendance held that the advocate should

decide following consultation with the solicitors, and after

considering the complexity of the particular case, the interests

of the client and the effective management of the case in court.

They also felt that the judges should be able to request that

counsel be attended. Counsel could also, if necessary, be

required  to  justify  the  decision  to   the  court.   Concern was


expressed that there should be no blanket prohibition imposed by

the Legal Aid Board on attendance on counsel in legal aid cases.



It was also suggested that the decision whether or not attendance

was justified might rest with some suitably qualified and

experienced person (e.g. a Taxing Master or District Registrar)

either retrospectively on taxation or through a system of

certification similar to that of counsel on a Chambers hearing.


DIRECT ACCESS TO COUNSEL (Chapter 8)



(i) Contractual Relationship - at present there is no

contractual relationship between barristers and their UK

clients. They may not therefore sue for their fees. As a

result the Law Society rules provide that the solicitors

will be personally responsible for counsel&apos;s fees even when

the solicitor has not been put in funds by the client



The green paper proposes that barristers be enabled to enter into

contractual relationships with their UK clients.



(ii) Direct access for lay clients ? barristers may be instructed

only by solicitors or certain other professionals (or by lay

clients for work outside the UK)



In the Green Paper the Government proposes to remove this

restriction and to permit barristers to take instructions

directly from lay clients should they wish to do so.



Should barristers be able to enter into contractual relationships

with clients?



There were 44 respondents on this point. Half were solicitors

and a quarter barristers. All but 2 would allow contractual

relationships. It was agreed that clients should be personally

liable for counsels&apos; fees and counsel should be entitled to sue

for the fee in the event of non-payment.



Should barristers be able to take instructions from lay clients?



182 commented on this point. Solicitor, barrister, and judicial

respondents addressing this issue tended to oppose direct access

to counsel for the lay client; some solicitors and barristers,

and most others who touched on the point were in favour and a

tiny percentage were neutral.



Those who would allow direct access at counsel&apos;s discretion ( 30%)

held that the present system was unnecessarily restrictive and

that change would increase freedom and choice for counsel and

client alike. The client would not be restricted to the barrister

preferred by an instructing solicitor; members of the public

could directly approach the counsel they wanted without having

to go through a solicitor and incur what could on occasion be

unnececessary costs. Barristers would be able to enjoy new

freedom and choice because they would not depend on the good

grace of solicitors for work. Counsel and client would be able

to liaise directly which could lead to a reduction in costs.



Against this, it was argued (15%) that direct access would

inevitably increase the costs to the client. At present counsel

did not have the necessary support and administrative staff to

enable them to take instructions directly from the public and

prepare the case for court; to collate, order and research the

evidence, compile files etc. To establish such an infrastructure

in counsel&apos;s chambers would increase overheads bringing costs at


least level with those of solicitors. The present separation of

functions was more cost-effective.



Some pointed out that the public were inexperienced in dealing

with the legal system and the law and held that to avoid

confusion and unnecessary delays and costs, solicitors should

continue to be the link between the public and the Bar.

Solicitors had the experience to judge when counsel was necessary

and which counsel was most suitable. Solicitors also had the

support staff necessary to the preparatory work of client

consultation and document preparation. Counsel did not have the

time and resources available to liaise as closely with the

client. It was also suggested that there was a risk that legal

aid clients would be forced to use either a solicitor or

barrister but be unable to use both.



Some (20%) felt that direct access represented a move towards a

fused profession; solicitors risked losing the freedom they

currently enjoyed to engage one of around 6,000 barristers

depending on their clients&apos; needs. Some (including th&lt; High Court

Judges also argued that counsel would become moie directly

involved with the client and risked losing the degree of

objectivity which currently ensured that duty to the court

overrode any personal obligation to the client and that a fresh,

detached and objective mind reviewed the case once it had been

initially investigated by the solicitor. The separation of

counsel from client therefore enhanced the quality of counsel&apos;s

work and ethical integrity.



It was conceded however that direct access could prove beneficial

in certain instances, ie. limited to advice or in matters which

were clearly non-contentious.



Some respondents on this question (over 20%) were in favour of

limited direct access, but only for other professionals. It was

argued that direct access for such professionals as accountants,

patent agents, conveyancers, and financial institutions in

matters relating to their particular specialist fields would not

give rise to many significant problems. They would have the

knowledge, expertise and office support to instruct counsel

effectively.


QUEENS COUNSEL (Chapter 9)

The Government proposes



(i) to retain the arrangements for appointment as Queens Counsel



(ii) that the field for appointment be open to all those holding

a full general advocacy certificate



(iii) that the field for occasional honorary appointment be open

to Solicitors as well as Barristers



Should the existing arrangements for appointment as QC be

retained?



Around 70% of the 74 respondents on this topic, comprising

solicitors, barristers and others favoured retention of the

position of QC, and broadly commended the present appointments

procedures. The main argument, from a third of the respondents

was that the rank of QC was an important signifier of excellence

in the profession, to those inside and outside it and provided

a pool of potential candidates for the High Court Bench. Whilst

the majority favoured retention of the existing selection process

it was also pointed out that (a) the process for appointment as

QC remained a mystery to the general public and others and that

the system if retained, should be defined and regulated by

legislation or at least made public; (b) the present system was

one of Government patronage; those presenting this view concluded

either



(i) that the appointments should be transferred away from

the Lord Chancellor; or



(ii) that the fact that these and judicial appointments were

made by or on advice from the Lord Chancellor, and had

provoked no constitutional outrage in the past,

suggested that the proposed advisory committee did not

pose the threat claimed in certain quarters.



Around 10% of respondents to the topic were neutral, and another

20% would abolish the system. Some argued that if the &quot;cab rank&quot;

rule were abolished the distinction between junior counsel and

QC would no longer be required to protect senior counsel from an

obligation to accept work befitting a junior. Others would

abolish the system because of the patronage involved. Others saw

no place for a hierarchy of this sort within a less restrictive,

and more democratic profession.



Should the field be open to all those holding a full general

advocacy certificate?



Fewer (45) commented on this point. Overall, around 80%

(solicitors, barristers and others) supported an extended

application of the title of QC. Those opposing any change were

primarily barristers, the judiciary, and others. Some felt that

possession  of   a   full   general  advocacy  certificate, although


appropriate to a certain extent, should not be the single

criterion determining appointment as QC. Achievement of

excellence in either civil or criminal practice alone should also

qualify and appointment should be open to all distinguished

lawyers whether or not they were advocates and whether they had

a generalist or specialist practice. Some felt that solicitors

should not be eligible for appointment, on the basis that all QCs

should be sole practitioners.



Few commented on the practice of awarding honorary appointments,

and their views were mixed with some willing for it to be used

to recognise general distinction in non-practising lawyers;

others preferring it to be retained to denote distinction in

legal practice.


THE JUDICIARY (Chapter 10)



The Government proposes that qualification for judicial

appointment should depend on either



(i) advocacy  experience   (to  be  demonstrated   for   High Court

appointments by a full advocacy certificate)



(ii) experience in another judicial appointment.



The most obvious practical effect of this is to open up the High

Court Bench to solicitors.



Do you agree that judicial appointments should be open to



(i) advocates  with  sufficient  experience of  advocacy  in the

relevant Court, whether they are solicitors or barristers?



(ii) holders of judicial office in a lower court?



The majority of the 178 respondents on this issue (over 80%in all

and the majority within each group of respondents) felt that

there was no reason to continue to exclude solicitors from the

High Court Bench. It was generally felt that the present

restrictions were unfair and unjustifiable. Around 40% commented

that the Lord Chancellor should be able to appoint candidates

with the necessary qualities, expertise and experience whether

solicitors or barristers. Such a revision would increase the pool

of good and suitable candidates.



At the same time it was argued that very few solicitors would

want or be able to qualify for High Court appointment. There

would therefore be no practical threat to the Bar and an

unnecessary and insulting restriction on solicitors would be

removed. It was also argued that possession of a full general

advocacy certificate should not be strictly necessary. A

candidate with impressive specialist experience in a particular

area might well be suitable for appointment to that specialist

Bench.



It was said that distinction and experience in a particular field

should be the main qualification for judicial office, and that

in exceptional circumstances this might involve appointment of

experts who were not barristers or solicitors. Court work,

especially in some subjects, was moving away from the

adversarial model (eg. accident work, family and child care) and

specialists in these areas should be allowed to take their

experience onto the Bench. It was envisaged that a more open

approach to judicial appointment could lead to judges with more

experience of day to day contact with the public and a larger

representation of women and ethnic minorities among the

Judiciary. It was also noted that a number of specialist

barristers had been successfully appointed to generalist

individual posts, or to posts in a different specialist area.



Some felt that more training should be given to those newly

appointed to a judicial post.  This would enable standards and


quality of judgments to be established and maintained. Some (5%)

also felt that training of former practitioners would always be

inadequate in the long run and that a career judiciary should be

considered. There were claimed to be substantial benefits in the

continental model where the vocations of the judge and barrister

or solicitor were quite separate and where prospective judges

were appointed at an early stage, and rose up the hierarchy

according to ability and merit.



Those who commented and opposed any change in the legislation

governing appointment to judicial office (13%) argued that the

existing system produced the best and most envied judiciary in

the world. Counsel, the prospective candidates, gained experience

in the law and the court system through constant advocacy

practice. This served to instil the necessary judgment and

impartiality. Because they practised independently they did not

develop any professional allegiances to and financial

interdependence with partners in practice which might hamper them

in future judicial activity in the High Court. And because they

saw clients and their cases only, in effect, as consultants, they

were able to maintain a level of detachment from the client and

be more objective in their approach to the court. It was said

that this too prepared them better for higher judicial

appointments.



Their continual presence in practice in the courts also meant

that they could be continually assessed, and demonstrate clearly

their suitability for appointment. There was some speculation on

how judicial appointments would be made in future, if the

proposals were adopted. If High Court advocacy experience were

not the major requirement, the present procedures, by which

serving High Court judges were canvassed as to the suitability

of prospective candidates, would be less appropriate.



Some were concerned that these proposals would enable an advocate

who had worked entirely in prosecution to become eligible for

the High Court Bench: the present system ensured that candidates

had experience of both prosecution and defence.



Some (4%) also felt that it was wrong for judicial appointments

to be the direct responsibility of a member of the executive. It

was suggested that an independent judicial appointments board

should be established.


BARRISTERS PRACTICES    (Chapter 11)

The Green Paper noted that



&quot;The internal rules and methods of organisation which govern

barristers practices are a matter for the Bar, although it

will need to be able to justify these to the new competition

authority&quot;.



The Government invited the Bar to consider in particular



(a) difficulties in obtaining pupillages



(b) difficulties in obtaining tenancies



(c) the requirement to practise as a member of chambers



(d) the restrictions on partnership



(e) the possibility of allowing incorporation



(f) the functions of the barristers&apos; clerks



Are the restrictions on partnership justified?



Few respondents commented in any detail, if at all, on the

proposals on Bar practices.Most interest was shown in the

suggestion that barristers be allowed to operate in partnerships

with other barristers. Those who would maintain current

restrictions, including the Bar, High Court and Circuit Judges,

DGFT were concerned that partners would be unable to act for both

sides in a dispute and that this would reduce access and consumer

choice. The Bar and High Court Judges both also said that

individual practice provided maximum competition and impetus

towards competence. The DGFT thought that purse-sharing was a

satisfactory alternative. The Bar&apos;s response indicated that

they would be reconsidering the provisions on purse-sharing in

its Code and might prohibit the practice.



LAG, LAPG, the Law Society and NCC would change the rules on

partnerships of barristers. However the Law Society was also

concerned that partners should not act for both parties to an

action. LAPG suggested that provision could be made ensuring

sole personal liability for advocates in partnerships relating

to matters directly arising from their professional

responsibilities.



Similar returns were made in respect of incorporation. The Bar

was against. LAPG was for, and the Law Society and CBI were

neutral. Many of the other practices which the Green Paper

suggested be looked at by the Bar have to an extent been

overtaken by changes already in hand or proposed in its response.


Is the requirement to practice as a member of chambers justified?



Around two thirds of the 26 respondents on this issue favoured

a change in the rule (although not all felt that there should be

no control at all). The Bar said that they were looking into the

provision of a library system which would enable those unable to

find a tenancy to practise.



Should barristers be able to employ others to assist in legal

work (including other barristers)?



Only 12 respondents expressed an interest in this. 9 (solicitors

and barristers) saw no reason why barristers should not employ

others. The Bar, however, opposed the proposition and claimed

that employment of others would derogate from a barrister&apos;s

independence, from the requirement of the cab-rank rule and the

fundamental principle that each barrister competed on the sole

basis of his talents, hard work and expertise.



Should barristers be obliged to employ clerks?



The Bar pointed out that its code of conduct no longer required

a barrister to employ a clerk; there was now an obligation on

every barrister to ensure that his or her work, finances and

office organisation were managed competently and efficiently.

Failure to meet this obligation would be a disciplinary offence.



Should barristers outside London be required to be member of a

circuit or a specialist association?



There were only 5 responses on this. The Bar considered that

such membership should be encouraged so as to maintain the ethos

of discipline on a circuit, but should not be a requirement.



Is the rule preventing barristers holding conferences in a

professional client&apos;s office necessary?



Only the Bar responded in detail; they proposed to amend their

Code and dispense with this restriction.


MULTI-DISCIPLINARY AND MULTI-NATIONAL PRACTICES  (Chapter 12)



The Government proposed in the Green Paper to remove the

statutory provisions preventing solicitors practising in

partnership with members of other professions, or forming multi-

national legal practices. It said that it expected the Law

Society to review and amend its Practice Rules accordingly in due

course. It also saw advantage in mixed practices involving

barristers and invited the Bar to amend its Code of Conduct to

allow barristers to choose the form of organisation in which

they wished to practise.



Should the statutory and professional restrictions on the

creation of multi-disciplinary and multi-national practices be

removed to allow for multi-disciplinary practices of solicitors

and other professionals but not barristers?



Nearly 200 responses were received on this issue; three quarters

of these came from solicitors. A small majority of the non-lawyer

respondents who commented (including both those who might be

involved in such partnerships and consumer representatives) and

around a third of the solicitors supported the proposal. They

considered that this would allow for a better, more complete,

wider ranging and often more cost-effective service to be

provided. &quot;One-stop      shopping&quot;      should      avoid many



misunderstandings and delays and it was suggested (DGFT) that the

potential new arrangements would bring general improvements in

cost-efficiency and a competitive edge to solicitors&apos; businesses.

The Consumers&apos;Association thought that it could be particularly

beneficial in the field of house transfer. Some others felt that

such new arrangements would apply primarily to commercial

business and registered their concern that there would remain a

need for local firms to carry out other business, particularly

legal aid.



It was generally agreed that the highest professional standards

must be maintained. Opinion differed, however, as to whether

different professions should adhere to their own codes or whether

there should be a distinct code or codes of practice for MDPs.

Many felt that the solicitors&apos;code would be the best model. The

NCC mentioned that it would be possible for problems and

complaints to arise for which none of the relevant professional

bodies wished to take responsibility. They suggested that the

Legal Services Ombudsman should be able to intervene in such

cases and if necessary draw up a code of conduct to cover the

point in future. A few respondents mentioned the need to ensure

that changes in the rules governing practice in England and Wales

should be consistent with European requirements in order not to

prejudice the position of English and Welsh lawyers practising

elsewhere in Europe. It was suggested by the Council of the

Bars and Law Societies of Europe that solicitors would not be

considered independent if they were practising in MDPs, and would

therefore be prevented from practising in other jurisdictions.


Those opposing the proposal, including the Law Society and around

two thirds of the solicitors who commented, said that this would

concentrate work in the hands of a relatively small number of

large practices; smaller firms would close or merge; and firms

would inevitably focus on the interests of commercial clients,

and themselves come under stronger commercial pressures, to the

detriment of personal and legal aid work. They said that the

change would restrict consumer choice since clients would

effectively be restricted to the professionals available in the

firm. They also believed that there would be bound to be

insurmountable problems of confidentiality and conflict of

interest; and that there would be difficulty in reconciling the

different codes of conduct binding partners with different

professional backgrounds. Given this conclusion the Law Society

recommended that the restrictions be retained.



Should multi-disciplinary practices of solicitors and barristers

be permitted?



There has been overwhelming, though not complete, professional

opposition to this proposal.    The reasons given included



(a) barristers would inevitably lose much of their independence

and objectivity



(b) it would reduce the pool of independent barristers available

to firms unable to do their own advocacy, or looking for expert

advice



(c) solicitors would not wish generally to use advocates in the

larger firms because they believed the costs would be much

higher, and that they would inevitably lose that, or future

business, to the larger firm.



Overall it was feared that there would be a diminution in the

quality of service and in the availability of expert advice and

advocacy.



Should multi-national partnerships of lawyers be permitted?



The proposal to allow multi-national practices of solicitors was

well received. The Law Society&apos;s view, shared with a number of

others was that the demand for such practices was growing as

commercial operations became more international but that detailed

consideration needed to be given to develop means to regulate

them.


ADVERTISING AND INFORMATION (Chapter 13)



The Green Paper notes that



&quot;Clients need adequate information in order to make a

sensible choice of a lawyer and to get maximum value for

money through the lawyer and client relationship.&quot;



The British Code of Advertising Practice requires advertisements



to be legal, decent, honest and truthful:



Is any further restraint necessary?



How can public attention be drawn to areas of particular

expertise?



Should the Bar&apos;s rules on advertising be brought into line with

those for solicitors?



Should solicitors and barristers be encouraged and expected to

provide information by way of stated rates per hour?



There were 89 responses dealing specifically with this chapter.

They gave clear but qualified support for the lifting of

restraints on advertising in order to provide the public with

more detailed information as to the legal services on offer and

their likely cost.



Two thirds of respondents on this issue (including the majority

of solicitors and individual barristers) broadly supported the

suggestion although around 30% felt that the British Code of

Advertising Practice would not be sufficient on its own to

control the content and standard of advertising. The code could

be complemented by some other form of monitoring, either by the

governing bodies of the legal profession or at local level by

local law societies.



The Law Society and a few other solicitor respondents felt that

while solicitors might be required to provide clients on request

with a statement of their hourly rates to be confirmed in

writing, it must also be recognised that rates could vary

depending on the complexity of the case, the level of expertise

at which it should be handled, and the amount of assistance

required. There should not be a strict rule requiring solicitors

to quote simple rates which they would then be bound to apply

regardless of the demands of individual cases. The client

should, however, have the right to ask and be told the rates

which would typically apply. It was suggested that more detailed

Law Society guidance might provide for greater consistency in the

way in which rates or prices were quoted. Professional standards

and dignity should however be maintained in advertising material.



Half of the barristers who commented felt that they should enjoy

the same freedoms to advertise as solicitors, but some felt that

they should be under no obligation to advertise their charges.

Others, including the Bar, felt that they should be free to

advertise to solicitors and other professionals, but not to the

public. It was also suggested that if good, innovative

barristers advertised themselves well, there would be a greater

awareness of their particular approaches and methods and in time

more widespread adoption of those more efficient practices.


There were a number of arguments against change. Some (10%)

claimed that it was known by other means whether or not a

solicitor was particularly experienced or skilful in a particular

field, and that good solicitors had never needed to advertise.

Some also feared that advertising would bring little or no real

benefits to clients but that there would be increased pressures

to advertise and so to increase overheads, which would be passed

on in charges to their clients. Others claimed that many clients

had too little knowledge of the law and services potentially

available to them to make any effective choice on the basis of

advertisements. It was suggested that that might be dealt with

by corporate advertising by the profession generally.


PROBATE (Chapter 14)



The Government proposed to relax the present restrictions on

probate work.



Should applications for grant of probate or letters of

administration be



(a) restricted to specified classes of person, as outlined

in Option A



(b) unrestricted Option  



(c) unchanged?



The great majority of respondents on this issue were solicitors,

with one third in favour of the current restrictions and two

thirds supporting change. Almost all of those who would relax

the restrictions supported option A which would extend the

monopoly to trust corporations, licensed conveyancers, authorised

practitioners and accountants (although some indicated that they

felt the change should apply to trust corporations only). They

said that probate work was an area in which the public were

vulnerable to unqualified and unscrupulous practitioners, but

that the groups specified in option A were all subject to

standards of professional practice, had suitable control and

complaint procedures, and were generally insured against

negligence suits should problems arise. Some respondents, for

example legal executives, probate agents and professional

executors wanted to extend the monopoly to themselves, saying

that they had the necessary expertise and were subject to the

desired controls.



Some solicitor respondents felt that if they were to compete more

fairly with the banks for this business, banks should be subject

to comparable costs controls to those which applied through the

remuneration certificate and taxation procedures to solicitors.

Alternatively, the current controls on solicitors&apos; costs should

be removed.



The small number choosing option   felt that:



(a) the monopoly should be removed since solicitors should

still be able to compete successfully for probate work;or



(b) a lot of work was already done by unqualified persons

and option A would not prevent this; it would therefore be

better to remove the restrictions altogether and impose new,

more effective controls in future if that proved necessary.



The arguments against change were that:



(a) probate work could be complex and lawyers were best

able to do the work competently because of their skills and

professional controls and obligations;



(b) removal of the restrictions on probate work would make

the small provincial practices vulnerable to competition

from large institutions, risking closure and loss of their

more general services (which were often subsidised by

probate income);


(c) the large institutions did not provide the same

personal service to clients; they did not always have the

relevant experience and were not always able to give

independent advice; their costs were also significantly

higher than solicitors.



One respondent also suggested that executors in non-contentious

cases could be encouraged to represent themselves.



Should the requirement to swear an oath be abolished?

Nearly two thirds of respondents on this point (predominantly

solicitors) opposed abolition and argued that it emphasised the

seriousness of the undertaking (which could involve a lot of

money), restricted the possibility of Inland Revenue fraud, and

provided a means to check the identity of the applicant.



Those in favour of its abolition (comprising solicitors and

various other respondents) felt that the procedure was

unnecessarily cumbersome and formal.


CONVEYANCING



The Government proposed to revise the provisions in the Building

Societies Act 1986 concerning conveyancing to provide for

competent practitioners such as lending instructions to do

conveyancing work in competition with private solicitors.



Should the current restrictions on conveyancing work be revised?



Is it possible to achieve &quot;a level playing field&quot; i.e. fair

competition between solicitors and institutional conveyancers?



Around 60% of respondents commented on the separate green paper

on conveyancing. The great majority of these (over 85%) were from

solicitors (including the Law Society). Around 95% of solicitors

opposed the proposal to authorise institutions to offer

conveyancing services to their customers. The Bar Council and the

small number of individual barristers who commented on this took

the same general view.



There was a clear belief from all categories of respondent that

it would be very difficult or impossible to operate the system

proposed to prevent predatory pricing and ensure that solicitors

and conveyancers in private practice were able to compete equally

for this business. Some detailed papers were also submitted which

set out very clearly the problems which would be encountered.



The other principal objections raised by solicitor and barrister

respondents were:



(a) even if it did prove possible to establish fair competition

between solicitors and the big institutions, the attractions

of one-stop shopping - however illusory solicitors might

consider it to be - would mean that they would lose very

many clients to the banks and building societies; many would

be unable to find alternative work (and believed that legal

aid work would not pay) and would be forced out of business;

in some areas this would substantially affect access to

legal services;



(b) clients choosing conveyancing services from an institution

would be deprived of the independent advice currently

available from a solicitor or licensed conveyancer; employed

conveyancers would be bound to encounter a conflict of

interest between employer and client;



(c) the majority of financial institutions were now tied in with

insurance companies and received substantial incomes from

them in commission; they had also acquired estate agency

chains; this placed considerable pressure on the institution

to find ways to force the conveyancing client to use the

other services on offer, even using the conveyancing as a

loss leader.



These views were broadly echoed by the 10 licensed conveyancers

who responded and by the Society for Licensed Conveyancers. The

Council for Licensed Conveyancers on the other hand appeared to


give a broad welcome to the proposals, seeing in them thi

opportunity for more work for licensed conveyancers, and

prospects for secure employment and career progression within the

institutions. They also, however, considered the proposals for

ensuring fair competition to be unworkable and perceived a threat

to the position of conveyancers who wished to continue to work

independently. Their proposal to overcome the potential for

conflict of interest, that all authorised practitioners be firms

under the operational control of solicitors or conveyancers,

amounted to direct opposition to the proposals.



A relatively small number of responses came from members of the

general public. These fell into two broad categories. First were

those who had had unfortunate experience in the past of

conveyancing by solicitors and who welcomed the prospect of

having work done by a building society in future. The second

group were respondents (often retired solicitors or relatives of

solicitors) who were concerned at the various consequences if

solicitors lost substantial volumes of business.



A handful of financial institutions submitted responses, which

largely supported the changes proposed. The Halifax Building

Society had done a survey of its customers which indicated that

up to 70% would be prepared for their conveyancing to be done in-

house; that customers did not feel that solicitors in private

practice gave much if any financial advice at present; and that

they felt that the conflict of interest had been grossly

exaggerated. It was suggested that the cost regime proposed would

prove expensive because of the extra work required of the

auditors, and that this would have to be passed on to customers

and that the Competition Act 1980 should be sufficient to prevent

them adopting anti-competitive practices.



The National Consumer Council, Consumers Association and Director

General of Fair Trading all supported the general proposals. They

pointed to customer convenience and to the more sophisticated

back-up services and technology available through the

institutions which might also in time link in with those operated

by the Land Registry and local authorities. The NCC and CA were

concerned that institutions should not be able to force customers

to accept a package of services, and that the proposed code of

conduct be appropriately policed. The DGFT did not believe that

the measures proposed to prevent predatory pricing would work and

he would rely on the Competition Act to achieve that.


CONTINGENCY FEES



In excess of 500 responses have been received to the Green Paper

on Contingency Fees. Of these approximately 75% came from

members of the legal professions, 20% from members of the public

and bodies representing consumer interests and the remainder from

members of other professions.



Many respondents, clearly concerned at what happens in the USA

with award sharing schemes, simply rejected any change and did

not comment even on the proposal to introduce speculative

actions.



The majority of responses from the general public were in favour

of removing restrictions on contingency fees, because of the

possibility of achieving access to the courts without incurring

the substantial costs of an action. They did not, however,

consider the effect of the costs follow the event rule nor the

fact that a solicitor would carry out a rigorous assessment of

the case before deciding to take it on on a contingency fee

basis.



The Bar was not in favour of permitting either speculative

actions or a restricted contingency fee system. It considered

that lawyers should not in any circumstances be permitted to have

a direct financial stake in the outcome of the client&apos;s case.

Conflicts of interest would inevitably arise and ethical

standards would tend to be lowered. The potential for fostering

conflicting interests and the development of a litigious society

outweighed the benefits to be obtained in terms of greater access

to justice.



The Law Society was in favour of permitting speculative actions

with an uplift but remained against the removal of any further

restrictions to permit contingency fees. It was acknowledged

that allowing speculative actions would provide a means of making

formal agreements between the solicitor and client that are

currently informal.



Of the 300 plus firms of solicitors who responded, only a small

minority were in favour of restricted contingency fees. This

consisted of large firms currently handling a substantial volume

of personal injury work. Small firms, particularly high street

general practitioners, were against the introduction of

restricted contingency fees. They said that the potential costs

of subsidising the action until conclusion would make such a

system untenable.



Many solicitors believed that the number of cases in which

speculative and enhanced speculative actions would be appropriate

was very small. Their introduction would be of little benefit to

those litigants presently unable to afford legal advice.

Solicitors were divided between those who thought speculative

actions should be introduced despite their potentially limited

use and those who thought the disadvantages of introducing a

potential conflict of interest between solicitor and client

outweighed the benefits they might bring to a small number of

people.


It was generally acknowledged that in personal injury cases where

the outcome of the case is certain solicitors frequently

undertake cases under an informal agreement with the client that

they will recover their costs out of the damages recovered, and

will make no charge if the case is lost. This system may apply

even though the client is eligible for legal aid as the delay in

making an application is avoided and no contributions need be

paid. Few respondents thought that the introduction of a

restricted contingency fee system would in practice enable more

litigants to bring their claims to court. It was thought that the

rule that costs follow the event would have a deterrent effect.



The National Consumer Council was in favour of a restricted

contingency fee system for libel actions only. The Consumers

Association favoured the introduction of speculative actions

immediately followed by restricted contingency fees paid in

stages, depending on the success at each stage.



Where it was considered respondents agreed with the proposal

that all criminal proceedings should be excluded from any system

of contingency fees. Divorce and family proceedings were also

considered to be cases which should be excluded.



The reasons for the current examination of contingency fees were

considered by the majority of respondents. It was assumed that

the thinking was that contingency fees would provide a greater

range of choice to the consumer and would enable litigants to

obtain acess to justice. Many respondents thought that

contingency fees, if introduced, would be used as a means of

reducing eligibility for legal aid cases. It was frequently

stated that no change in the current system should be allowed as

this change represented the thin end of the wedge and would lead

to further relaxation of restrictions and constraints on the

availability of legal aid.


COMPARISON BETWEEN THE GREEN PAPER PROPOSALS  AND THE WHITE  PAPER DECISIONS ** ^ *



PARA_NO WHITE PAPER PARA NO GREEN PAPER



CHAPTER 1:    THE VARIETY OF THE NEED FOR LEGAL

SERVICES



1.5 The overall alms are to give the



public as wide a choice as possible



in the providers of legal services



available to them, whilst at the same



time maintaining the high standards of



integrity and competence which are



necessary for protecting



the interests of the client and



for the more general public interest



in the administration of justice.



The Government&apos;s overall objective in

publishing the Green Paper is to see

that the public have the best possible

access to legal services and that

those services are of the right

quality for the particular needs of

the client.    The Government believes

that this best achieve by ensuring

that:-



(a) a market providing legal services

operates freely and efficiently so as

to give clients the widest possible

choice of cost effective services; and



(b) the public can be certain that

those services are being supplied by

people who have the necessary

expertise to provide a service in the

area in question.


PARA NO WHITE PAPER



CHAPTER 2:    THE STATUTORY OBJECTIVES.



2.2 The legislation will include



basic objectives relating to the



provision of legal services. All



those who work together in setting



and maintaining standards in the



provision of legal services - the



professional bodies,  the Lord



Chancellor,  and the judiciary -



will be bound to have regard



to those objectives.



The objectives will provide



for:



approved standards of education

and training;



The maintenance of the required

standards of conduct amongst

practitioners;



the removal of restrictions on

who is qualified to provide legal

services, or on what those who are

qualified may do, which are not

necessary in the interests of

justice.



The statute will make it clear that

the framework it creates ensures the

ordered,  flexible and speedy

development of fresh ways of providing

legal services, and ensuring clients

have a wider choice.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



4.12       The Lord Chancellor should prescribe



by statutory instrument the principles

which must be embodied in the proposed

professional codes so as to ensure

that they have Parliamentary approval.


PARA WO WHITE PAPER



PART ONE:     WIDER CHOICE IN LEGAL SERVICES



CHAPTER 3:    APPEARING IN COURT



Rights of Audience



3.6. The Government to



implement the recommendation

of the Civil Justice Review

that in small claims cases,

and in debt and housing cases

in the County Court, litigants

should have the right to choose a

lay representative to assist them.



3.8 The existing complex arrangements



under statute and common law should

be replaced by statutory rights of

audience in all courts and tribunals.



Granting Rights of Audience



3.9 It should be for the professional

bodies to determine that particular

persons are qualified to appear in

all courts and tribunals.



3.10 The Bar. Statute to recognise that

any person called to the Bar will

have rights of audience in all courts

and tribunals. Any future change



to the Bar&apos;s rules



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



5.9 It may now be right for lay



representative to be granted rights of

audience in the courts on behalf of

others in some intstances.    The Civil

Justice Review recommended that in

small claims cases and debt and

housing cases in the County Court,

litigants should have the right to be

assisted or represented by the lay

representative of their choice.



5.14       Subject to any advice from the



Advisory Committee, rights of audience

for all advocates should be dependant

on a certificate of competence. This

certificate could be either full,

entitling the advocate to rights of

audience in all courts, or limited,

entitling the advocate in only the

lower courts.



5.16       Advocacy certificates would be issued

and, where appropriate varied,

suspended or revoked by the relevant

supervisory professional bodies.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



for education and training, and of

conduct will be subject to the

concurrence of the Lord Chancellor

and of the Lord Chief Justice, the

Master of the Rolls, the President

of the Family Division, and the

Vice -Chancellor on behalf of the

judiciary.    The Lord Chancellor and

those judges would act having regard

to advice from the



Advisory Committee.    Further details

of the procedure for making the rules

are set out in Chapters    7 and 8.



3.11 The Law Society.    Statute to provide

that the Law Society be able to

recognise a solicitor as qualified to

be an advocate,  in a particular courts

or courts or tribunals.    Rules for

education and training,  and of conduct,

to be made by the Law Society and to

require the concurrence of the Lord

Chancellor and the same senior judges

as those for the Bar.



3.12 On initial qualification, all

solicitors to receive rights of

audience equivalent to their

existing rights.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



3.14 Legislation to provide a    power to



enable the list of bodies which could

grant rights of audience to be added

to, on the advice of the Advisory

Committee, and with the concurrence

of the senior judges, by Order in

Council subject to affirmative

resolution.



3.16 It will be a principle of the



legislation that no individual

or class of advocates would lose

any existing rights.


WHITE PAPER



Employed Advocates



The exercise of rights of audience

may be limited by professional

rules.    The extent of

limitations under the rules will

be a matter for early consideration

by the Advisory Committee, and

should be kept under review by the

professional body concerned.



Queen&apos;s Counsel



The Lord Chancellor will jj.n

future regard as eligible for

appointment as



Queen&apos;s Counsel all those who

hold rights of audience in

the High Court, or in the

Crown Court.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



5.10       A universal prohibition on rights of



audience for employed lawyers would be

appear to be an unnecessary

constraint; it should be possible for

appropriate Codes of Conduct to guard

any conflicts of interest which might

arise in the case of employed lawyers,

and to secure the degree of

responsibilty to the court and

independence from the parties which is

vital if the court is to rely on their

representation.



9.6 In future all who hold full general



advocacy certificates,  whether or not

they are barristers,  should be

eligible for appointment as Queen&apos;s

Counsel.


PARA NO WHITE PAPER



CHAPTER 4:     THE CONDUCT OF LITIGATION



4.2 The right to conduct litigation

(at present reserved to solicitors

by section 20 of the solicitors

Act 1974),  like rights of

audience should be granted to

practitioners by the professional

bodies to which they belong,  if they

can set and maintain the required

standards of competence and conduct.

The Law Society will be

designated in the statute as being

able to grant such rights.



Other bodies might be so

authorised in the future by an

Order in Council.



4.3 The mechanisms for determining the

acceptability of the codes of

conduct and the educational

requirements of those who conduct

litigation are set out in

Chapters   7 and 8.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



4.11        There should in the future be written

codes specifically set professional

standards.    One will deal with the

provision of legal advice and

assistance generally.


PARA NO WHITE PAPERS



CHAPTER 5: CONVEYANCING



5.7 The Lord Chancellor to recognise

professional bodies and other

organisations as competent to

authorise their members to provide

conveyancing services once he is

satisfied that they met the

requirements for recognition, and

are able to enforce upon their

members a code of conduct.



5.8 The requirements for recognition

should be as set out in paragraph

3.5 of the Conveyancing Green

Paper:



(i) suitability to provide

conveyancing services;



(ii) the employment of a

sufficient number of solicitors

or licensed conveyancers (or both)

to provide or supervise the

provision of conveyancing services;



(iii) proper protection of

clients&apos; money from improper use;



(iv) compliance with the Lord

Chancellor&apos;s Code of Conduct;



PARA NO



CONVEYANCING GREEN PAPER



3.4 The Lord Chancellor proposes to set



out a number of requirements which any

person whether an individual, a

partnership or a corporate body, must

meet before it will be allowed to

provide conveyancing services. All

those who meet certain reguirements

will be known as authorised

practitioners.



3.5 To obtain authorisation the individual



practitioner will have to satisfy the

requirements set in the following

areas:



(i) suitability to provide

conveyancing services;



(ii) the employment of a sufficient

number of solicitors or licensed

conveyancers (or both) to provide or

supervise the provision of

conveyancing services;



(iii) proper protection of clients&apos;

money from improper use;



(iv) compliance with Lord Chancellor&apos;s

Code of Conduct;



r&gt;nmx NO



conveyancing   green papers


para no



white paper



(v) ability to meet claims

arising out conveyancing

services;



(vi) proper investigation

of complaints;



(vii) suitable compensation

arrangements;



(viii) membership of a suitable

Ombudsman scheme;



(ix) adequate arrangements for

protecting clients should an

authorised practitioner cease



to provide conveyancing services.



Authorised Practitioners



5.9 Conveyancing to be carried out or



supervised by those who have the

relevant professional expertise,

to be defined as including

solicitors,  licensed conveyancers

and (subject to appropriate

qualification) barristers and

notaries.



para no



conveyancing   green papers



(v) ability to meet claims arising out

of conveyancing services;



(vi) proper investigation of

complaints;



(vii) suitable compensation

arrangements;



(viii) membership of a suitable

Ombudsman scheme;



(ix) adequate arrangements for

protecting clients should an

authorised practitioner cease to

provide conveyancing services.



3.7 Although an authorised practitioner



will be exempt from section 22 of the

Solicitors Act 1974,  it will remain a

requirement that the conveyancing work

must be carried out by those who have

the relevant professional expertise.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



5.10 Two   categories of



authorised practitioner are

envisaged:



(1) banks and building societies

provided



they can certify to their

regulatory authorities that

they can comply with the

requirements for authorisation

and with the proposed code of

conduct;



(2) other professional bodies

and other organisations which

meet the requirements for

recognition and can satisfy

the Lord Chancellor that

they can ensure their members&apos;

compliance with the code of

conduct.



The Code of Conduct



5.12 The code of conduct will embody



principles relating to the proper

supervision of conveyancing

services, conflicts of interests,

contractual obligations, and the

conduct of business, broadly as

set out in the Annex to the

Conveyancing Green Paper. There

are however important new

elements:



CONVEYANCING GREEN PAPER



Those who may wish to become

authorised practitioners may be

divided into two categories:



(i) banks and building societies

provided they certify to their

regulatory authorities that they can

comply with the authorisation

requirements;



(ii) others who submit themselves to

the supervision of another authority

which can satisfy the Lord Chancellor

that it is able to impose and enforce

the necessary requirements.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



5.13(1)      The client must be offered at

least one interview with the

solicitor or licensed conveyancer

responsible for the conveyancing

services in that case.    The qualified

person&apos;s prime duty in the

transaction will be to the client.



5.13(ii)    Authorised practitioners will

be prevented from providing

conveyancing services to both the

buyer and the seller of the same

property,  subject to very limited

exceptions.    Authorised practitioners

will also be prohibited from

offering conveyancing services to

a party in a transaction in

which the practitioner,  or a

subsidiary,  is also providing

estate agency services to

another party.



5.14 Authorised practitioners must

submit their conveyancing prices

to their regulatory body annually,

and certify that the prices are

calculated fairly and reasonably.



5.15 Authorised practitioners will be

required to disclose all the financial

benefits the practitioner stands



to gain from both the conveyancing

and from any linked services given in

connection with the transaction in

question.



PARA NO



CONVEYANCING  GREEN PAPER



ANNEX



Each authorised practitioner must have

one named person who is directly

responsible for ensuring that the

conveyancing services are carried out

according to this code.



(a) An authorised practitioner must

not accept instructions from or

continue to act for any person whose

interests conflict with those of any

other person by whom the authorised

practitioner is also instructed.



(b)  In particular an authorised

practitioner must not act for both

parties to a transaction except where

it appears that there is no conflict

of interest between the parties and

both have consented in writing to its

acting.



10 Authorised practitioners must not



offer conveyancing services below

their true cost and must provide

annual proof that they are complying

with this requirement.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



5.16 Instead, the provision of one service



conditional on another will be

prohibited.    The Government is

also considering

extending the prohibition on

tying-in in paragraph 11 of the

Green Paper Annex to prevent the

tying-in to the mortgage of any

financial service to any other

services in the domestic property

market.



5.19 Authorised practitioners will be



required by statute to comply with

the Code of Conduct, which will be

made by the Lord Chancellor subject

to negative resolution of either

House of Parliament.



PARA NO



CONVEYANCING GREEN PAPER



11 An authorised practitioner must not



make the provision of:



(a) conveyancing services conditional

on any other service being taken;



(b) any other service conditional on

conveyancing services being taken.



3.9 The Lord Chancellor intends to lay



down in a statutory instrument a code

of conduct to be followed by all

authorised practitioners.


WHITE PAPER



Complaints



It would be a condition of

recognition that the recognised

professional body could ensure

that its members who were

authorised practitioners had

suitable mechanisms to deal

with complaints.    The body

itself would have to have

suitable mechanisms for

dealing with complaints and

disciplinary matters.    It and

its members would also need to

belong or be subject to a suitable

Ombudsman scheme.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



CHAPTER 6: PROBATE



6.3 The classes of people who can



draw papers up should be extended

(ie. Option A of the Green Paper).

Legislation will

provide for trust corporations

to be allowed to do probate work.



6.4 The Lord Chancellor should be



given a power, exercisable by

statutory instrument after consulting

the President of the Family Division

and subj ect to



affirmative resolution by both

Houses of Parliament,  to add to

the list of those qualified to

prepare applications for probate

professional bodies or other

organisations which he had been

advised by the Advisory Committee

met the appropriate standards of

competence and conduct.    It is

unnecessary to impose a probate

code of practice.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



14.11      It is no longer justifable to maintain

the present statutory restriction on

those who may make applications for

grants of probate or letters of

administration for award in non-

contentious cases.      Present statutory

restrictions could be relaxed in

respect of either specific classes of

persons : Option A; or there should be

complete dregulation : Option B.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



Attendance in Person



6.5 The Non-Contentious Probate Rules



should be amended to enable all

those who are able to draw up

papers for reward to apply without

personal attendance at the

Probate Registry.



Oaths



6.6 The Government proposes that the



requirement to swear an oath should

not be abolished now.    To permit the

change to be made,  should it become

desirable in the future,    it is

proposed to create a new criminal

offence, which will be triable

either way of making a dishonest

statement for the purpose of an

application for a grant of probate.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



14.15     At present any solicitors may make

applications for a grant without

attending the Registry in person. It

would seem to be both sensible and

simple to put all the classes of

people who may be allowed to apply for

reward in the same position.



14.18     Should the requirement to swear an



oath be removed on the understanding

that making a dishonest unsworn

statement for the purpose of an

application would continue to be a

criminal offence?


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



PART TWO: THE MAINTENANCE OF QUALITY

CHAPTER 7:    THE ADVISORY COMMITTEE



7.5



7.6



There should be a new Lord

Chancellor&apos;s Advisory Committee

on Legal Education and Conduct.



Its main functions should be:



(i) Education and Training: to

advise on the education and training

of lawyers at the academic,

vocational,  and post-vocational

stages.



(ii) Conduct:    to offer advice on

the rules of conduct to be observed

in the provision of legal services.



(ill) Recognition:    to consider

in the future whether to advise

the Lord Chancellor on the

suitability of professional bodies

(other than the Bar Council or the

Law Society) as competent to grant

rights of audience or the right

to conduct litigation; and to



NO



GREEN PAPER



The existing Lord Chancellor&apos;s Advisory

Committee on Legal Education should be

reconstituted as the Lord Chancellor&apos;s

Advisory Committee on Legal Education

and Conduct.    The Committee&apos;s terms of

reference should be:



(a) to keep under review the education

and training of lawyers at the

acedemic qualification and post-

vocational stages;



(b) to consider, whether on its own

initiative or when requested to do so

by the Lord Chancellor;



(i) what areas of legal services

require specialist expertise; and



(ii) what the education,

qualifications and training of

specialist should be in the various

areas designated as requiring

specialist expertise;


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



examine in the light of objectives

incorporated in statute, both the

standards of education and training

and the codes of conduct put forward

by each professional body.



(iv) Specialisation: to offer advice

on whether schemes for areas of

accredited specialisation put

forward to it by professional

bodies are likely to serve the

efficient delivery of legal

services to the public.



(v) Practical and continuing

education:    to advise upon the

requirements for the provision of

practical



training and continuing training,

in particular in advocacy.



(vi) Probate: to offer advice

on proposals by organisations

who have



requested that their members

should be entitled to prepare

applications for probate.



NO



GREEN PAPER



(c) to keep under review the

accredited specialisms and the

education and training requirements

for these to ensure that they continue

to meet the needs of the public for

the efficient delivery of legal

services; and



(d) to advise the Lord Chancellor on

the appropriate codes of conduct which

should be followed by lawyers and

other practitioners recognised as

suitable to undertake work in the

recognised specialisms.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



7.7 Any member of the public, of a



profession providing legal services,

of the judiciary or the Lord Chancellor

would be able to refer to the Advisory

Committee any topic or matter arising

within those areas.    How such references

were handled would be a matter for the

Advisory Committee.



The Advisory Committee&apos;s

Functions and Powers



7.8 The Advisory Committee would



present an annual report to the

Lord Chancellor which he will be

required to lay before Parliament,

the professional bodies would be placed

under a statutory duty to have

regard to the Advisory Committee&apos;s

advice.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



3.12       The Advisory Committee should submit

an annual report covering all these

areas to the Lord Chancellor. The

annual report will be laid before

Parliament.    The Committee might also

submit proposals and recommendations

to the Bar or the Law Society or to

other professional bodies.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



Membership



7.9 The Advisory Committee would have



15 members, comprising



- a Lord of Appeal in Ordinary

or a Supreme Court Judge as

Chairman



- two practising barristers



- two practising solicitors



- two academic lawyers



- eight people from outside those

categories.



7.11 All would be appointed by the

Lord Chancellor, after wide

consultation.    The members



who were not practising lawyers

would be



selected to ensure that they

were able to represent the

interests of the public and of

the clients for legal services.



7.12 The Committee will regulate its

own proceedings, but it is

envisaged that it will have

separate sub-committees on

education and on conduct.



PARA NO GREEN PAPER



3.14       The new Advisory Committee should



consist of 15 members, all appointed

by the Lord Chancellor and

comprising:-



(a) a chairman, who should be a judge;



(b) two barristers;



(c) two solicitors;



(d) two academic representatives; and



(e) eight lay representatives.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



Financial and Staffing

Arrangement 8



7.13 Members of the Committee would be

paid.    The Committee would be

funded by a grant-in-aid from the

Lord Chancellors&apos; Department.



7.14 The Advisory Committee would be

able to appoint its own staff.

The Committes&apos; staff would not

be employed as civil servants.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



3.15       The secretariat of the Advisory



Committee should be provided by the

Lord Chancellor&apos;s Department.


PARA NO WHITE PAPER



CHAPTER 8:    THE ROLE OF THE PROFESSIONAL

BODIES



8.3 Any professional body which seeks

to be entitled to grant rights



of audience or the right to

conduct litigation to its members

will need to make approved training

regulations and codes of conduct.

The professional body will be

required to prepare draft training

regulations and a draft code which

would be submitted to the Advisory

Committee for its consideration.



8.4 The professional body will be

required to have regard to any

suggestions which the Advisory

Committee might make on the content

of these draft rules or codes. The

drafts will then be submitted to

the Lord Chancellor with advice

from the Committee on whether he

should approve them.    They will

also require the



concurrence of the Lord Chief

Justice, the Master of Rolls, the

President of Family Division,

and the Vice-chancellor acting on

behalf of the judiciary.    Both the

Lord Chancellor and the senior judges

will be required to have regard

to the Advisory Committee&apos;s advice.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



4.12       The Lord Chancellor should prescribe

by its statutory instrument the

principles which must be embodied in

the proposed professional codes so as

to ensure that they have Parliamentary

approval.



4.11 Professional bodies whose members

wished to offer advisory and advocacy

services will be required to submit

their proposed codes of conduct for

the endorsement of the Advisory

Committee whose role it will be to

ensure that such codes of conduct

embody the approved principles.



3.12 The Advisory Committee to keep under

review the education and training of

lawyers at all stages and to submit

proposals and recommendations to the

professional bodies.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



Transitional Arrangments



8.6 The existing provisions relating



to training and conduct of the Bar

and the Law Society will remain in

force when the legislation is

implemented.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



5.13      The Lord Chancellor, on the advice of

the Advisory Committee and after

consulting the judiciary, to prescribe

by subordinate legislation the

education and qualifications and

training of advocates.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



PARA



CHAPTER 9:    LEGAL EDUCATION



9.1 - 9.6 The Advisory Committee should



draw up a programme to examine each

of the main areas of legal education:



- academic training (including the

content and teaching of the

academic stage);



- vocational training;



- practical training (in particular in

relation to advocacy and litigation);



- continuing training.



Specialisation



3.13



9.8 Responsibility for

specialisation schemes should be

left to the Bar Council,  the Law

Society and the relvant

professional bodies.



9.9 Professional



bodies would be able to submit

schemes to accredit specialists

to the Advisory Committee for

its advice.



GREEN PAPER



Final decision on whether a particular

specialist area of expertise should be

recognised as such should rest with

the Lord Chancellor,  following advice

from the Committee.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



9.10 Approved members participating in



a specialisation scheme would be able

to advertise the fact that their

schemes had been drawn up in

consultation the with

Advisory Committee.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



Further consideration should be given

to allowing those practitioners to

qualify as specialists to advertise

themselves as such.


PARA NO WHITE PAPER



CHAPTER 10;    CONDUCT,  COMPLAINTS AND DISCIPLINE



Disciplinary Arrangements



10.9 The best way to explore the ways in



which joint and local disciplinary

arrangements might improve the present

system would be to seek a power

enabling the Bar Council and the

Law Society to set up joint

disciplinary arrangements, at both

central and local levels,  in addition

to the present arrangements.    The Lord

Chancellor will discuss with the

judiciary the possible local

involvement of members of the

judiciary.



Immunities for Work in the Courts



10.11 The existing common law immunity

for barristers should be extended

to all advocates.



Costs Orders



10.12 The existing rule which enables some

courts to order that a solicitor

should personally bear any part of

the costs of an action where his work

has fallen short of the standards



of competence the court

expects, should be extended to

cover all litigators, and all

advocates as well, and be extended

to magistrates&apos; courts.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



6.2 Immunity from actions in negligence in



respect of the conduct and management

of a case in court should in future

extend to or recognised advocates.



4.13       All courts should have power to



require any advocate to pay personally

costs incurred by any party to an

action,  if the court judged this

appropriate.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



The Legal Services Ombudsman



10.13 The office of Lay Observer should be

abolished, and a new statutory office

of Legal Services Ombudsman should be

created.



10.14 The Ombudsman will have two main

functions:



- to investigate the way in which

complaints had been handled by the

relevant professional bodies;



- to investigate the original complain&apos;

about the provision of legal

services.



His jurisdiction would cover both

professional misconduct and negligent

or sloppy work under both heads.



10.16 The Ombudsman&apos;s duties will relate to



the handling of cases by the professioi

bodies, not by independent tribunals oi

the court.



4.31       The Government proposes to abolish the

office of Lay Observer instead, the

Lord Chancellor will appoint a Legal

Service Ombudsman.



10.19 The Ombudman, like the PCA, should be



given powers to require the attendance

of witnesses and the production of

documents.



10.23



The Ombudman will be given power to

recommend the payment of compensation.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



PART THREE:    NEW HAYS OF WORKING.



CHAPTER 11:    COMPETITION IN THE PROVISION OF

LEGAL SERVICES



The White Paper on Restrictive 11.8

Trades Practices proposes

that professional services will be

brought within new

restrictive trade practices (RTP)

legislation.    Rules made by the

professional bodies to cover advocacy

in court, the conduct of litigation and

associated training, which.have received

the concurrence of the Lord Chancellor

and the Heads of Division, would be

excluded from the RTP prohibition.



There should be no exclusions for the

professions from the new legislation

and the rules of professional bodies

should generally be subject to the

same tests administered by a new

competition authority as other sectors

of the economy.



11.3 There will be provision for the rules



of the professional bodies to be referred



to the Director General of Fair Trading,



whose comments



on any anti-competitive



effects would be taken into account



by the Lord Chancellor and the



Heads of Division.



Barristers&apos; Fees



11.7 Legislation will enable barristers 8.3



to make contracts for the payment

of their fees.



The Government proposes that there

should be legislation to permit

barristers who wish to do so to enter

in contractual relations with those

who instruct them in respect of U.K.

work


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



CHAPTER 12:    MULTI-DISCIPLINARY PARTNERSHIPS



12.2



12.3



The statutory barriers to the formation

of partnerships between solicitors

in England and Wales, and the members

of other professions will be removed.



Rules on partnership made by the Bar

and the Law Society could,  if approved

by the Lord Chancellor and the senior

judges, be exempt from prohibition

under the proposed RTP legislation.



12.8       The Government proposes to amend the

Solicitors Act 1974 to remove any

statutory inhibition on the freedom of

solicitors in England and Wales to

engage in multi-disciplinary and

multi-national practices.



12.14     There appears to be no good reason to

distinguish between barristers and

solicitors in this respect.



PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



PARA NO



green paper


PARA WO WHITE PAPER



CHAPTER 13:    MULTI-NATIONAL PARTNERSHIPS



13.3 The Government proposes to remove



the statutory prohibition on the

formation of multi-national

partnerships.



13.5 The   Lord Chancellor and the Secretary



State should be given

power to make regulations which

will ensure that UK lawyers

should have rights to practise

in other parts of the kingdom

at least equivalent to those

available to lawyers from other

EC countries.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



12.8       The Government proposes to amend the

Solicitors Act 1974 to remove any

statutory inhibition on the freedom of

solicitors in England and Wales to

engage in multi-disciplinary

practices.


PARA NO WHITE PAPER



CHAPTER 14;    CONTINGENT AND CONDITIONAL FEES



14.3 The existing prohibitions will be

removed to enable clients to agree

with their



lawyers payment of a conditional

fee on the speculative action basis

already permitted in Scotland.

This relaxation will not extend to

criminal and family proceedings.



14.4 The Lord Chancellor should be given

a power to prescribe



by statutory instrument, subject



to negative resolution,



the maximum uplift, in terms of a



moderate percentage of the normal



costs,



which the lawyer may charge when

acting for a conditional fee.



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



5.3 It is appropriate to consider the



introduction of speculative actions on

the Scottish models.    It is in

consideration also whether this should

be coupled with the ability an uplift

of the costs, payable to the lawyer in

the event of success.



5.4 The Government does not believe that



it is appropriate to remove all

existing restrictions on the use of

contingency fees.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



PART FOUR:       JUDICIAL APPOINTMENTS



Qualifications for a Practitioner



10.3       Qualification for appointment as a



15.5 The minimum qualification as a Lord of Appeal and Ordinary to be:



practitioner for appointment to (a) at least 2 years as Lord



the bench should be rights of audience Chancellor or Judge in one of the



as set out below: Superior Courts in Great Britain and



(i) Lord of Appeal in Ordinary: Northern Ireland; or

general rights of audience in the (b) holding a full general advocacy

Supreme Court for 15 years; certificate for at least 15 years.



(ii) Lord Justice of Appeal, High Court

Judge, Deputy High Court Judge: a general

right of audience in the High Court and

the Court of Appeal for ten years;



10.8(i)



(iii) Circuit Judge,



Recorder, Assistant Recorder: a general

right of audience in the Crown Court or

the County Courts for ten years;



(iv) Master or Registrar of the Supreme

Court, County Court Registrar, Stipendiary

Magistrate:    Rights of audience in the

Supreme Court or a general right of audience

in the County Courts for 7 years.



10.8(ii)Qualification for Circuit Bench to be;



(a) holding a full general advocacy

certificate, or full criminal and

limited civil or full civil and

limited criminal advocacey

certificate,  for 10 years; or



(b) holding office as a Master of

Registrar for 2 years.



The present requirement that

solicitors must serve as Recorders for

3 years before appointment to the

Circuit Bench should be removed.



Qualification for Supreme Court

Appointments to be:



(a) holding a full general advocacy

certificate for 10 years; or



(b) holding office as a Circuit Judge

for 2 years.


PARA NO



WHITE PAPER



PARA NO



GREEN PAPER



Qualifications for a Judicial Officer



15.6 Present qualification for Lord of Appeal



in Ordinary (at least 2 years as Lord

Chancellor or judge of one of the

Superior Courts in Great Britain and

Northern Ireland) will remain unchanged.

A Circuit Judge of at least two years&apos;

standing should be eligible for

appointment as a judge of the Supreme

Court.    A Registrar of at least 3 years&apos;

standing should be eligible for

appointment as a Circuit Judge.

Solicitors will no longer be required

to serve for at least 3 years as a

Recorder before becoming eligible

for appointments to the Circuit

Bench.



Qualification for High Court Master or

Registrar or County Court Registrar to

be having held a limited civil

advocacy certificate for 7 years.


ANNEX C



Rights of Audience in the Courts

of England and Wales



1 A litigant in person, that is a party to proceedings who is not represented by

a lawyer, has a right of audience in his or her own cause in all courts and

tribunals. A barrister practising from chambers has a general right of audience

on behalf of his or her clients. The rights of audience of solicitors in private

practice are more limited. The rights of audience of employed lawyers are more

restricted still. By virtue of the European Communities (Services of Lawyers)

Order 1978 (SI 1978 No.1910) an EC lawyer may appear before any court,

tribunal or public authority in the UK provided that throughout the

proceedings he or she is instructed with, and acts in conjunction with, an

advocate, barrister or solicitor who is entitled to practise before the court

tribunal or public authority concerned and who could properly provide the

service in question.



The Magistrates&apos; Courts



2 The Magistrates&apos; Courts deal with around 90% of the total criminal

workload at first instance. They also deal with care proceedings in respect of

juveniles and licensing applications, and have a sizeable domestic jurisdiction.

Decisions on both fact and law are taken either by a bench of lay magistrates or

by a stipendiary (legally qualified) magistrate, sitting without a jury.



3 Rights of audience are governed by statute, currently section 122 of the

Magistrates&apos; Courts Act 1980. This provision derives from section 2 of the

Trials for Felony Act 1836 (6 &amp; 7 Will. 4, c. 114) enacted to reform the law

following the decision in Collier   Hicks(1831) 2   &amp; Ad. 663 in which it was

held that no person had a right to act as an advocate on the trial of an

information befere justices of the peace without their permission. The

Magistrates&apos; Courts Act 1980 section 122(1) provides that a party to any

proceedings before a Magistrates&apos; Court may be represented by counsel (i.e. a

barrister) or solicitor. In addition, various statutes such as the Local

Government Act 1972 section 223 and the Customs and Excise Management

Act 1979 section 155, give specified persons authority to conduct particular

prosecutions, although they may not be counsel or solicitor. The Magistrates&apos;

Court also has a discretion to allow someone else to act on behalf of either party

to the proceedings.



The Crown Court



4 The main jurisdiction of the Crown Court is in criminal proceedings. Apart

from cases committed for trial or sentence from the Magistrates&apos; Courts, the Crown Court

deals with appeals from the Magistrates&apos; Courts against conviction and

sentence. It also hears appeals from decisions of magistrates in care

proceedings in juvenile cases, appeals from the decisions of justices in licensing

matters and appeals from local authorities and chief officers of police under

various statutes. The Crown Court has a small original civil jurisdiction, such as

applications under the Reservoirs (Safety Provisions) Act 1930. In criminal

cases, the court is presided over by an Assistant Recorder, Recorder, Circuit



67


Judge or High Court Judge. In trials on not guilty pleas the judge sits with a j

whose function it is to decide whether the charge against the accused person h 

been proved. Lay magistrates sit with the legally qualified judges on some easel

and appeals.



5 Barristers practising from chambers have a right of audience in all cases if

the Crown Court. Rights of audience for solicitors are governed by section 83

of the Supreme Court Act 1981 (reproducing the now repealed section 12 of the

Courts Act 1971). This provides as follows:-



&quot;(1) The Lord Chancellor may at any time direct that solicitors may

appear in, conduct, defend and address the court in any proceedings in

the Crown Court, or proceedings in the Crown Court of any description

specified in the direction.



(2) A direction under this section may have effect as respects all places

where the Crown Court sits, or as respects a specified area, region 0 i

circuit, or as respects one or more specified places where the Crown

Court sits.



(3) In considering whether to exercise his powers under this section as

respects any one or more specified places where the Crown Coun sits

the Lord Chancellor shall have regard to any shortage of counsel in the

area in question, any rights of audience formerly exercised by solicitor! ;

at any court of quarter sessions in the locality in question, and to anj I

other circumstances affecting the public interest.



(4) Any direction given under this section may be subject to suet 

conditions and restrictions as appear to the Lord Chancellor to be

necessary or expedient.&quot;



By virtue of directions made by the Lord Chancellor on 7 December 1971. S

February 1972 and 15 August 1988, solicitors have rights of audience in:-

(a)   appeals to the Crown Court from a Magistrates&apos; Court or on committal fo

sentence, if the same firm appeared in the court below;



(b)



civil proceedings in the Crown Court on appeal in similar circumstances!



(c)   a limited number of cases in remote areas where solicitors traditionall

had full rights of audience at Quarter Sessions (Caernarvon, Barnstaple,

Truro, Doncaster and parts of Lincoln), which have been replaced by the

Crown Court.



6 Rights of audience for Crown Prosecutors (barristers and solicitors)!

employed by the Crown Prosecution Service are governed by section 4 of thej

Prosecution of Offences Act 1985. This gives Crown Prosecutors the same&apos;

rights of audience in the Crown Court as solicitors holding practising

certificates; and the Lord Chancellor may give any such directions under

section 83 of the Supreme Court Act 1981 in respect of Crown Prosecutors as he

could give in respect of solicitors.



The County Courts



7 These courts have a wide-ranging civil jurisdiction in cases where, generall

speaking, the amount in issue does not exceed  5,000, covering debt, breach 0

contract, personal injury, recovery of land, bankruptcy and insolvency,

admiralty, family proceedings and miscellaneous matters such as mental health

and sex discrimination. Trials are heard by Assistant Recorders. Recorders or

Circuit Judges, and interlocutory matters are heard by County Court

Registrars.



Rights of audience in the County Court are governed by sections 60 and 61


of the County Courts Act 1984. The material part of section 60 is as follows:-



&quot;(1) In any proceedings in a county court any of the following persons may

address the court:-



(a) any party to the proceedings;



(b) a barrister retained by or on behalf of any party;



(c) a solicitor acting generally in the proceedings for a party to them (in

this subsection referred to as a &quot;solicitor on the record&quot;);



(d) any solicitor employed by a solicitor on the record;



(e) any solicitor acting as an agent for a solicitor on the record;



(f) any solicitor employed by a solicitor so engaged; and



(g) any other person allowed by leave of the court to appear instead of

any party.&quot;



By virtue of section 61 of the County Courts Act 1984. the Lord Chancellor

may by direction confer rights of audience in the County Court on persons in

employment consisting of or including giving assistance to solicitors in the

conduct of litigation. Only one such direction has been made to date and that

was in 1978 when this power was used to confer rights of audience on Fellows of

the Institute of Legal Executives on behalf of their solicitor employer in

unopposed applications for an adjournment or applications for judgments by

consent.



The High Court



9 The High Court is divided into three Divisions: Chancery, Queen&apos;s Bench,

and Family. There is no upper limit on its jurisdiction. It deals with a range of

heavy civil work covering matters such as debt, personal injury, land and

property, breach of contract, bankruptcy and companies proceedings. In

addition the High Court deals with public law and various specialist cases,

including patents. The three Divisions of the High Court exercise appellate as

well as first instance jurisdiction: The Divisional Court of the Chancery

Division hears appeals in revenue matters from the Commissioners of Taxes

and bankruptcy matters from the County Courts; the Queen&apos;s Bench

Divisional Court exercises appellate and supervisory jurisdiction over the

Crown Court (except in relation to the conduct of trials on indictment), inferior

courts and tribunals and the actions and decisions of public bodies under the

judicial review procedure; the Divisional Court of the Family Division hears

appeals from Magistrates&apos; Courts in domestic matters.



10 The Chancery Division consists of the Lord Chancellor, who is its

president, the Vice-Chancellor and such of the High Court judges as are for the

time being attached to it. The Queen&apos;s Bench Division, which is much the

largest, consists of the Lord Chief Justice, who is its president, and such of the

High Court judges as are for the time being attached to it. The Family Division

consists of the President of the Family Division and such of the High Court

judges as are for the time being attached to it. Apart from a few cases in the

Queen&apos;s Bench Division, for example in some actions for defamation, where

juries sit to decide the facts, cases in the High Court are heard by judges who sit

alone and have to make decisions on both the facts and the law. Interlocutory

matters are dealt with by Masters and District Registrars.



11 Subject to the 1978 Order mentioned above (para 1), rights of audience in

the High Court have not hitherto been regulated by statute, but by the High

Court judges acting as a collegiate body (Abse   Smith[1986] 1 QB, 536). It is an

established rule that, save in an emergency, a solicitor cannot appear on his

client&apos;s behalf in open court. According to long custom, barristers have a

general right of audience in the High Court, whereas solicitors do not.



69


Solicitors do have a general right of audience in the High Court when sitting i

chambers, whether before a judge or Master, which extends to thei

responsible representatives (such as legal executives). Solicitors may also

appear in:-



(a) bankruptcy matters, and



(b) formal or unopposed matters where there is unlikely to be any argument

and where the court will not be called upon to exercise any discretion.



A solicitor may also represent his client in the Supreme Court when judgment is

delivered in open court following a hearing in chambers at which that solicitor

conducted the case for the client (Practice Direction: Solicitors: Rights of

Audience) [1986] 1 WLR 545 issued by the Lord Chancellor, the Lord Chief

Justice, the Master of the Rolls and the President of the Family Division.



The Court of Appeal



12 The Court of Appeal is divided into the Criminal Division and the Civil

Division. The judges of the Court of Appeal are the Lord Chief Justice, who is

the president of the Criminal Division, and the Master of the Rolls, who is the

president of the Civil Division, together with 27 Lords Justices of Appeal. The

President of the Family Division and the Vice-Chancellor also sit in the Court

of Appeal for part of their time. The Court of Appeal normally sits in a bench

of two or three.



13 The Criminal Division of the Court of Appeal hears appeals against

conviction and sentence from the Crown Court in England and Wales. In 1987

the number of applications and appeals registered was 8,320 - a rise of 8% over

the number registered in 1986. Courts in the Criminal Division are constituted

from the Lord Chief Justice and the Lords Justices assisted by judges of the

Queen&apos;s Bench Division of the High Court as required. There are no juries.



14 The Civil Division of the Court of Appeal hears appeals from the High

Court in civil matters, the County Courts, and various tribunals. Courts in this

Division are normally constituted from the Master of the Rolls and the Lords

Justices.



15 Rights of audience in both Divisions are governed by the judges of the

Court of Appeal acting as a collegiate body (Abse   Smith above). The position

on rights of audience is the same as that in the High Court.



The House of Lords



16 The House of Lords in its judicial capacity is the supreme court of appeal]

in Great Britain and Northern Ireland. It adjudicates on matters of law of

general public importance. The main judges of the House of Lords are the Lord

Chancellor and the Lords of Appeal in Ordinary. An appeal lies to the House

of Lords:-



(a) from any order or judgment of the Court of Appeal in England, by leave!

of that court or the House of Lords, subject to restrictions imposed by

statute or by practice in specific matters;



(b) from any order or judgment of any court in Scotland from which error or

appeal lay on or before 1 November 1876 by common law or by statute;



(c) subject to statutory restrictions, in exceptional cases direct from a

decision of the High Court in England;



(d) from any order or judgment of the Court of Appeal in Northern Ireland

by leave of that court or the House of Lords, subject to statutory

restrictions; and


(e)  subject to statutory restrictions, in exceptional cases direct from decisions

of the High Court of Justice in Northern Ireland.



17 Rights of audience are the same as in the High Court and the Court of

Appeal. In addition, Scottish advocates and barristers from Northern Ireland

have rights of audience and solicitors may appear before the Appeal

Committee of the House of Lords when it is considering a petition for leave to

appeal.



The Judicial Committee of the Privy Council



18 The Judicial Committee of the Privy Council is the final court of appeal for

those Commonwealth countries which retain the right of appeal to Her Majesty

in Council. Its members are normally drawn from among the Lord Chancellor

and the Lords of Appeal in Ordinary. In its domestic jurisdiction, the

Committee entertains appeals against schemes by the Church Commissioners

under the Pastoral Measure Act 1983. The Committee also hears appeals from

their disciplinary bodies by doctors, dentists, opticians, veterinary surgeons

and members of professions supplementary to medicine; it also hears appeals in

prize cases during and after a period of hostilities. Rights of audience, which

are governed by custom and not statute, extend to English and Northern

Ireland barristers, Scottish advocates and all advocates duly qualified in

countries from which appeals lie to the Queen in Council.



The rights of audience of employed lawyers



19 Solicitors employed by non-legal employers, who either hold or are

exempted from holding practising certificates, have the same rights of audience

on behalf of their employer as solicitors in private practice.



20 The rights of audience of employed barristers are currently more restricted

than the rights of employed solicitors. For instance, employed barristers are

presently allowed to appear as advocates for their employers in the

Magistrates&apos; Court and the County Court only if they are given leave to do so

by the court. Employed solicitors, on the other hand, can appear in these courts

as of right. This anomaly is the result of the combined effect of the wording of

section 122(1) of the Magistrates&apos; Courts Act 1980 and section 60(1) of the

County Courts Act 1984 and the provisions of the Third Edition of the Bar&apos;s

Code of Conduct which deny to employed barristers the status of counsel. It

will be removed by the provisions of the Fourth Edition of the Bar&apos;s Code of

Conduct (due to come into force on 1 February 1989) which will enable an

employed barrister to appear on behalf of his employer as counsel in

circumstances where barristers in general practice do not have an exclusive

right of audience. This alteration to the Code should also enable employed

barristers to appear in the same instances as employed solicitors in the High

Court, Court of Appeal and House of Lords.



21 Employed lawyers do not have rights of audience in the Crown Court. This

is the result of the combined effect of the provisions of section 83 of the

Supreme Court Act 1981, the current Directions made by the Lord Chancellor

and professional practice rules.



Tribunals



22 At present, there are generally no restrictions on rights of audience before

tribunals. This is because, as recognised by the Report of the Committee on

Administrative Tribunals and Enquiries (1957 Cmnd. 218), the main

characteristics of tribunals are, &quot;cheapness, accessibility, freedom from

technicality, expedition and expert knowledge of their particular subject.&quot;



71


(para 38). Because of these characteristics it is generally considered that mos

applicants should be able to cope with bringing proceedings without the nee

for assistance from a qualified legal representative. Assistance may, however,

be available from other sources; for instance, trade unions and CABx often

represent employees before Industrial Tribunals and also represent applicants

before the Criminal Injuries Compensation Board. CABx are also playing an

increasing role in representing applicants before Mental Health Review

Tribunals.



Printed in the United Kingdom for Her Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office

Dd0500466 2 89 C15 5874: 51.ST O&apos;N 49313 4527.&apos;R??P


Proposed code of conduct:

main principles



(A) Proper supervision of conveyancing services



1. One individual must be responsible for the direction and supervision of the

conveyancing services.



Each authorised practitioner must have one named person, who is directly

responsible for ensuring that the conveyancing services are carried out according

to this code.



2. A sufficient number of solicitors or licensed conveyancers (or both) must be

employed to enable the conveyancing services to be provided by suitably qualified

persons or under their immediate supervision.



As explained in paragraph 3.7 of the paper, it will remain a requirement that the

conveyancing work must be carried out by those who have the relevant

professional expertise.



(B) Conflicts of interest



3. Subparagraphs (a) and (b) below will apply in any case where the authorised

practitioner is a lending institution (or is a subsidiary of a lending institution) and

wishes to provide conveyancing services for any person to whom the lending

institution has lent or is proposing to lend money which was or is to be applied in

or towards the acquisition of an estate or interest in land. The authorised

practitioner must:



(a) make it clear that independent financial advice is not available from the

conveyancer; and



(b) explain the terms and conditions of the loan or offer in a clear and

straightforward manner.



A conveyancer employed by a lending institution (or by an insurance company

providing an endowment policy) would not be able to give independent advice,

but in this he would be no different to tied agents in other financial markets. The

vital consideration is that the borrower understands this. As long as he does, he

will still have the option of seeking independent legal advice about alternative

financial packages. It is worth pointing out, however, that under the current

system it seems clear that a significant proportion of home buyers do not

approach their conveyancers until they have arranged their mortgage, and do not

therefore look to them for financial advice.



4. The client must be made specifically aware that information disclosed by the

client to the conveyancer may be used by the authorised practitioner in respect of

any other service it is providing or intends to provide.



An independent conveyancer would have a duty of confidence to the client.

However, an employed conveyancer would also have a duty to his employer and

must make it clear to the client that no relevant information disclosed can be

kept from the employer. Such information could therefore be used by a lending



9


institution in assessing a borrower&apos;s suitability for a loan or by a firm of

surveyors in assessing whether the client will be able to pay for an expensive

structural survey.



5. (a) A recognised practitioner must not provide conveyancing services in anv



case where the interests of the practitioner or any associate of the

practitioner may conflict with those of the person making use of the

services.



(b) &apos;Associate&apos; in sub-paragraph (a) would cover partners, subsidiary or

holding companies, companies of which the practitioner is a director and,

where the practitioner is an individual, any member of his family.



Clients need to be protected from situations where the interests of the authorised

practitioner put at risk his duties to the client. The obvious example is where the

practitioner has a direct financial interest because it owns or is seeking to buy the

property in question. Principles 6 and 7 below are particular examples of where

conflict is likely to arise and where, subject to certain safeguards, it may be

considered that a potential conflict can be regarded as overcome.



6. (a) An authorised practitioner must not accept instructions from or continue



to act for any person whose interests conflict with those of any other

person by whom the authorised practitioner is also instructed.



(b) In particular an authorised practitioner must not act for both parties to a

transaction except where it appears that there is no conflict of interest

between the parties and both have consented in writing



(i) to its acting; and



(ii) to its ceasing to act for both parties, should a conflict of

interest subsequently arise.



Subparagraph (a) is a broad statement of principle. It would cover not only

acting for both parties, but also a situation where the vendor (V) is selling to

purchaser one (PI) who is selling to purchaser two (P2) and the authorised

practitioner is instructed by V and P2. Although a conflict may be unlikely, the

practitioner needs to be aware that it could arise.



Subparagraph (b) is specifically directed at acting for both vendor and purchaser.

It follows the approach of the Licensed Conveyancers Practice Rules which

permit licensed conveyancers to act for both parties on these very stringent

conditions.



One obvious example of where a conflict may arise is where an estate agent

acting on behalf of a vendor wishes to provide conveyancing services for both

vendor and purchaser.



A particular problem which will need to be sorted out when the relevant rules

come to be drafted is how to deal with authorised practitioners who have more

than one office. This is obviously the case with most lending institutions. It may

be safe to provide that in most cases where one branch office acts for the vendor

and another for the purchaser each office may be treated as a separate

practitioner, but equally there may need to be provisions which ensure that they

act independently of one another.



7. When the authorised practitioner enters into an arrangement with another

person for the introduction of clients to the authorised practitioner or by the

authorised practitioner to the other person it must ensure:



(a) that the client is informed in writing of the arrangement and of any

commission or other benefit the authorised practitioner may be receiving

or pay;



(b) that it obtains the client&apos;s written agreement as to the destination of the

commission or else it shall account to the client for the commission; ana



(c) that it remains able to advise the client regardless of its own interests.


A client must be entitled to know whether the authorised practitioner is making

any hidden profit or is paying any third party who referred the client to the

authorised practitioner.



(C) Contractual obligations



8. An authorised practitioner must give to each client, before it may accept

instructions to act, an estimate of the total cost which the client will or may have to

meet. This must set out:



(a) the way in which fees will be calculated;



(b) the circumstances in which they might be increased; and



(c) the particulars of expenses and tax likely to be charged to the client.



Clients must be entitled to know before they enter into a contract with the

authorised practitioner what the likely cost of the transaction will be.



When the authorised practitioner is a lending institution and offers to add the

cost of the conveyancing transaction to the loan, it must give the client an

indication of what he is likely to pay over the period of the loan compared to

what he would pay if he met the cost on completion. Any such lending

institution, which has offered to add the cost of the conveyancing transaction to

the loan, must also be ready to do this, whether the client then chooses to use that

lending institution or an independent conveyancer to carry out the conveyancing

transaction.



9. When an authorised practitioner offers conveyancing and other services to a

client it must ensure that the statement required under Principle 8 sets out

separately the cost of each sen-ice.



The client needs to be able to make an informed choice between the cost of in-

house and independent conveyancing services.



10. Authorised practitioners must not offer conveyancing services below their

true cost and must provide annual proof that they are complying with this

requirement.



The Government is anxious to ensure that the competitive position of

independent conveyancers is not put at risk by authorised practitioners

subsidising the provision of conveyancing services by their other activities. It

therefore requires authorised practitioners not to offer conveyancing services

below their true cost. Authorised practitioners must be able to demonstrate this

at least once a year to the satisfaction of their auditors who must certify that this

condition is being met.



11. An authorised practitioner must not make the provision of:



(a) conveyancing services conditional on any other service being taken; or



(b) any other service conditional on conveyancing services being taken.



Such a prohibition against &apos;tying-in&apos; is essential. There is an obvious risk that, for

example, a lending institution will tie in the conveyancing services to the loan,

thus making the borrower accept the whole package. Since the loan is so vital,

this would effectively prevent the borrower from seeking independent legal or

financial advice. Similarly, although the client would feel under less pressure to

accept, a surveyor might wish a client to accept a combined estate agency/

survey/conveyancing package. If this were permitted, it might well force

independent conveyancers out of business and so reduce competition.



12. An authorised practitioner must not contractually limit its liability for

damage suffered by the client as a result of negligence on its part.



11


13. An authorised practitioner must set out in writing the terms upon whia

instructions will be accepted and give them to the client before acceptin

instructions.



(D) Conduct of business



14. An authorised practitioner must deal with correspondence and other matters

arising in the course of a conveyancing transaction with reasonable speed and

must not by his actions or omissions cause unnecessary&apos; delay.



Authorised practitioners will be required to act in a professional manner. The

purpose of this and the following principles is to ensure that this happens. These

principles will:



(a) help to avoid any conflict between the authorised practitioner and the

employed professional conveyancer by imposing the same rules of

conduct as the professional conveyancer would expect to meet in private

practice;



(b) demonstrate to independent conveyancers acting for other parties that

authorised practitioners are not exempt from the usual professional

standards; and



(c) offer guidance to ombudsmen and other interested parties in the case of

complaints.



15. An authorised practitioner must ensure that clients are kept adequately

informed of the progress of the transaction.



Failing to keep clients properly informed causes misunderstanding and anxiety.

It leads to mistakes and complaints.



16. An authorised practitioner must treat all facts and information concerning

the client obtained by it in the course of acting for the client as confidential and

must not at any time make any unauthorised use of such facts or information.



17. An authorised practitioner must not delay completion of any transaction

solely on the ground that its fees are outstanding.



18. An authorised practitioner must comply fully with every undertaking given

on its behalf during any conveyancing transaction.



19. When an authorised practitioner is instructed by a vendor to submit forms of

contract to more than one prospective purchaser, it must obtain the client&apos;s

authority to disclose this fact to all prospective purchasers. If that authority is not

given, it must withdraw from the transactions.



20. An authorised practitioner must not withdraw from transactions without

good cause.



An authorised practitioner must not cease to act merely because it no longer

wishes to represent a client. There should be a good reason for its withdrawing,

for example, because a conflict of interest is discovered or the authorised

practitioner is unable to obtain instructions from the client.



Printed in the United Kingdom for Her Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office

Dd 0500676    1/89    C75    338:    4:35    4590     Job No- 890O90E



</content>
</cab>
