<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/21/26 images: 340-361</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;B WmWMBWLS CBE- Copy No. 31W.P. (42) 46[Also C.O.S. (42) 63)January 29, 1942TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINETWEEKLY RESUME(No. 126)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR SITUATIONfrom 0700 January 22nd, to0700 January 29th,1942[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War Room
NAYAL SITUATION.General Review.1. A large Japanese troop convoy has been successfully attacked in theMacassar Straits and a large U-boat has been sunk off Port Darwin.H.M. Destroyer Thanet has been sunk in ah engagement off the east coast ofMalaya.Shipping losses, primarily due to U-boat attacks off the east coast of NorthAmerica, have been heavier than of late.Home Waters and North Atlantic.2.   H.M.S. Duke of York arrived in Home Waters from Bermuda on the 24th.An American convoy with troops from the United States of America arrivedat Londonderry on the 24th.Severe weather has continued in the Atlantic and several ships have beendamaged, among them being: H.M. Sloop La Capricieuse off Lerwick, H.M.Corvette Vervain in the North-Western Approaches, and H.M. Submarine Regentto the northward of the Azores.Mediterranean.&apos; 3. On the 10th H.M. Submarine Thrasher sank a heavily laden 6,000-tonsouthbound merchant ship to the southward of Corfu.H.M. Submarine Porpoise reported that she had obtained two hits on aconvoy of three merchant ships, of 5,000 tons each, entering Suda Bay on the 12th.One ship was seen to sink.On the 17th H.M. Submarine P. 35 torpedoed and sank the Italian SalvageVessel Rampino off the Tunisian Coast.The s.s. Breconshire arrived at Malta from Alexandria on the 27th, and aconvoy from Malta has reached Alexandria.An Italian convoy escorted by a large naval force proceeded to Tripoli onthe 24th. It was attacked by our aircraft, which inflicted a number of casualties.Details are given in the Air Situation.During the week 3,112 tons of French merchant shipping westbound passedthrough the Straits of Gibraltar under escort.South America.4. On the 24th the American Submarine S. 26 sank in collision in the Gulfof Panama.Far East.Sumatra.5. On the 22nd two of H.M. auxiliary vessels were attacked by enemyaircraft off Sabang, and shot down one enemy four-engined aircraft.Malaya.6. During the night of the 26th-27th H.M. Destroyer Thanet and H.M.Australian Destroyer Vampire encountered a force of one cruiser and threedestroyers which had previously been attacked by our aircraft, as reported underAir Situation, off Endau (East Coast). A running fight ensued, in the course ofwhich one enemy destroyer was sunk and another damaged. H.M.S. Thanet wassunk, but Vampire sustained no damage or casualties.Dutch East Indies.7. A Japanese convoy consisting of 30 transports, escorted by three cruisersand 12 destroyers, was attacked at various times between the 22nd and 27th inthe vicinity of the Macassar Strait, by American and Dutch naval forces and
aircraft. From information received up to the present, the result of these attacksis as follows.:-One large cruiser sunk by ah American submarine.One cruiser hit by a Dutch submarine.All three cruisers hit by bombs.One destroyer sunk.One, or possibly two, destroyers hit by bombs.Ten transports sunk and others damaged.During these operations, bombers of the Dutch Air Force and American&quot; Fortresses &quot; destroyed at least seven Japanese fighters and damaged another.The American Submarine S. 36 grounded on a reef in the Java Sea and is atotal loss.The American Cruiser Boise was also damaged by grounding in this area.Anti-Submarine Operations.8. In Eastern Waters H.M. Australian Minesweeper Deloraine, withother Australian and American units, sank a large U-boat 60 miles west ofDarwin and shore batteries are believed to have hit a U-boat off ChristmasIsland:In the Atlantic, the American Destroyer Campbell claimed to have sunka U-boat off Newfoundland and the Free French Corvette Roselys rammed aU-boat to the westward of Ireland, sustaining damage to her keel. Three otherattacks, one to the westward of Ireland, one off the Azores and one off the LibyanCoast, were carried out by surface craft.Of a total of seven attacks by Allied aircraft, one made by CanadianCatalinas south of Newfoundland, two made by naval aircraft off MersaMatruh and one by a Catalina to the southward of Aden on a U-boat of unknownnationality, all appear promising.Enemy Intelligence.9.   Air reconnaissance confirmed the presence of the battleship Tirpitz atTrondheim on the 23rd.  There is no change in the position of other main units.Japanese warships and transports have been located at Rabaul, New Guinea.There are indications that a U-boat base is being established at Penang.U-Boats.10. Over forty U-boats have been operating in the North Atlantic duringthe period, a large number of which have been concentrated off the North Americancoast. Others have been reported off Bermuda, the Azores, west of Ireland andin the vicinity of Gibraltar.   Two U-boats off the Canaries are moving south.The strength of the German U-boat fleet, as estimated up to the 3rd January,is as follows : In service.Boats of 500 tons and over       ...      ...      ...      ....    180Boats of under 500 tons...............       50Total      ...      230Of the above about 60 have been commissioned in the past three months.Building.estimatedntoIbeer-0f b0atS ^ ^ SlipS        fittiDg 0Ut and their tonnage isBoats of 1,000 tons;.........     ...      ... gBoats of 750 tons      ...      ...... &quot;&apos;       qqBoats of 500 tons       ...      ...... 145Unspecified      ...      ......... 9Total      ...      220[23392]B
Enemy Attack on Seaborne Trade.11. Shipping casualties during the period have been heavier than in recentweeks. There were a number of attacks by U-bbat, particularly off the easternseaboard of North America. Of seventeen ships torpedoed in this area, one ofwhich was in convoy from the United Kingdom, ten have so far been reportedas sunk. A Spanish ship was attacked by U-boat to the westward of CapeSt. Vincent. One ship in coastal convoy was mined and sunk off Harwich anda vessel was reported to have been sunk by mine off the coast of Newfoundland.In Eastern Waters, two ships are known to have been sunk by U-boat andtwo by aircraft between Eangoon and Northern Sumatra. Aircraft also damageda ship by bombing attack off New Guinea and another in the Singapore Strait.One ship in convoy from Calcutta was sunk by mine south-west of Singapore.In addition, information has now been received of the sinking during thepreceding week of eight more ships by U-boat: four of them off the NorthAmerican coast, two off Burma, one west of Sumatra and one south of Java. Aship was sunk by mine off Singapore on the 21st.Protection of Seaborne Trade.12. During the week ending the 29th January 810 ships, including 210allied and 23 neutral, were convoyed. One cruiser, 3 anti-aircraft ships, 54destroyers (including 13 American destroyers) and 87 sloops, corvettes and mine-sweepers were employed on escort duties.Imports into the United Kingdom by ships in convoy during the week ending24th January totalled 1,014,000 tons compared with 180,000 tons during theprevious seven days and an average of 788,000 tons for the previous ten weeks.Of the week&apos;s total, 367,000 tons were oil of various grades.British Minelaying.13. Mines were laid by surface craft off the Flemish Coast and in the Buttof Lewis area and, on a small scale, by aircraft off the German North Sea Coast.Enemy Minelaying, British Minesweeping.Home Waters.14. Minelaying by enemy aircraft was suspected between Harwich andYarmouth on the evening of the 23rd.Thirteen magnetic mines have been detonated during the week, seven ofthem in the Cromer Knoll War Channels and three in the Humber area.The mine totals, including those swept in Foreign Waters, are : Magnetic, 1,758; Acoustic, 1,228; and Contact, 1,068.German and Italian Merchant Shipping.Northern Waters.15. The German Else Mutter, 1,598 tons, is stated to have arrived atGothenburg on the 18th December with her port side badly damaged by a mineor torpedo.  She is now in Eriksberg dry dock.The Bay of Biscay.16. The German Elsa Essberger, 6,103 tons, which recently arrived atFerrol from Japan, was probably making the first in a series of attempts to bringimportant cargoes, such as rubber, tungsten, tin, &amp;c, to Germany from the FarEast. There are at least thirteen Axis and French ships in Far Eastern waterswhich could sail to French West Africa without refuelling.The Red Sea.17. The Italian tanker Cielia Campanella, 3,245 tons, which was scuttledat Massawa, has been salved and sailed for Aden in tow.The Atlantic.18. The four Italian ships taken over by the Brazilian authorities will betaken to Eio de Janeiro for reasons of security. The ships concerned are theAntonio Limoncelli, 4,574 tons; the Aida Lauro, 6,067 tons; the Tebro, 4,310tons; and the Conte Grande, 23,861 tons.
MILITARY SITUATION.(An outline map showing operations in Russia is included in this Resumeas an inset.)Russo-German Campaign.Finland.20. Although a recent Finnish raid again cut the Murmansk railway,communications between Murmansk and Vologda are not affected, and it appearsthat the front in Finland has been stabilised for the winter.Leningrad sector.21. South of Leningrad the Russians have not been able to extend theirbridgeheads over the River Volkhov and thus to push back the German forcessurrounding Leningrad, as was hoped.Lake llmen-Lake Seliger sector.22. The Russians have made extensive advances both south of Lake Umenand west of Lake Seliger in the areas of Stara Russa, Kholm, Toropets andZapadnaya Dvina.Central sector.23. In the Central sector there have been further advances : south of Rzhev(the town itself being still in German hapds), west of Mozhaisk, where theRussians are following up the German withdrawal, and north-east of Yukhnov.Ukraine.24.   North-east of Kursk a new Russian attack has made some progress.Against Kharkov and along the line of the River Donets the Russian offensivecontinues, and a considerable advance has been made in the Isyum sector. Strongpressure is also being applied in the neighbourhood of Bakhmut.There has been no change along the River Mius. The Germans still holdTaganrog.Crimea.25. There has been heavy fighting in the Crimea, and the Germans claimto have broken through the Russian positions running north from Feodosia. TheRussians deny the German claim to have captured Feodosia itself. Sevastopolholds.Conclusions.26. The picture is one of Russian pressure and progress on many parts ofthe front.The Russians believe that the Germans are trying to hold all along the linebut are nevertheless being driven back, and that the only voluntary withdrawalsare tactical retirements designed to avoid encirclement.Two areas are of particular significance, viz. : (a) The north, where the advance towards Dno-Velikie Luki may soonthreaten the important lateral railway leading from Orsha towardsLeningrad.(b) The Donets front, on which the Germans evidently intended to stabilise,and the loss of which may compel them to fall back to the Dnieper,thus deferring any threat to Rostov and Caucasia.[23392] b 2Vichy Merchant Shipping.19. The Quercy, 3,043 tons, arrived at Dakar from Toulon on the11th J anuary with a cargo of munitions. This ship is now an armed &quot;merchantcruiser, and passed through the Straits of Gibraltar under an assumed nameThe Pffe 5,795 tons (ex Pierre L. D), after leaving Saigon, is believed tohave rounded the Horn and to be off the Argentine coast. She is presumed tohave a full cargo of rubber.
Libya.27. On 21st January, an Axis force estimated at some 90 tanks with lorriedinfantry and supporting arms, totalling some 8,000 personnel, advanced in threeseparate columns North-east from the Elagheila Position.Our advanced troops, consisting mainly of outposts, fell back in front of theenemy&apos;s advance, and his three columns concentrated about Jedabya on22nd January.On 24th and 25th January the enemy became engaged with an armouredformation which had been (held in reserve in the forward area. Both sidessuffered considerable casualties, but the enemy gained a tactical victory and wasable to continue his advance to Msus.Reports despatched early on 29th January state that the enemy had deployedfrom Msus. Five or six small enemy columns were moving eastwards towardsBir Tengeder and Mekili, another was advancing northwards towards Charrubai,and yet another towards El Abiar, while the strongest thrust was being madenorthwards along the coastal plain towards Benghazi. It is here that the greaterpart of his tank strength is being employed.General Auchinleck has altered his dispositions to meet this new threat, asa result of which a tank battle is now (29th January) in progress between Msusand Charruba. Certain withdrawals have taken place in the Benghazi area toavoid encirclement, and it is possible that the town, which is militarilyindefensible, will have to be evacuated. Valuable stores have already beenremoved and certain demolitions carried out.The Far Bast.Malaya.28.   The fighting in the central and western sectors has been very heavy.Last week it was stated that an Indian infantry brigade and two Australianbattalions were cut off near Muar, on the west coast. Over 600 Australians andmany Indians have got back, but their transport had to be abandoned.On the 24th and 25th January heavy fighting took place on the line Mersing-Kluang-Batu Pahat, but, despite our counter-attacks, the enemy pressure(including tank attacks) and his infiltration from the west coast have compelledour troops to resume their withdrawal.On the 25th January the enemy succeeded in occupying Batu Pahat on thewest coast and infiltrated rapidly southwards. Another Indian infantry brigadein the coastal area has been isolated and has not yet succeeded in breakingthrough, though 1,000 of all ranks have got back. A British brigade isendeavouring to.make contact with them from the south.At Endau, on the North-east coast of Johore, the Japanese have landedtwo battalions from transports. The Australian brigade there has withdrawn toTJlu Sedili to conform with movements on the central sector.In the centre the enemy are now within 40 miles of the Causeway.29. During the week the following reinforcements arrived at Singaporesafely : :One Australian Machine-Gun Battalion.3,000 Australian reinforcements.One Indian Infantry Brigade. ,1,000 Indian reinforcements.Burma.30. There has been heavy fighting at Kawkareik near the Thai frontiereast of Moulmein. Our forces have withdrawn from this area and now occupypositions in close proximity to Moulmein, The military authorities have takenover control of the city.31.   More Chinese troops are moving into Northern Burma.Netherlands East Indies.32. Following their occupation of Tarakan (Dutch Borneo) and Minahassa(North Celebes) the Japanese have moved a force of some 30 transports, accom-panied by warships, down the Straits of Macassar.  In anticipation of attack,
the Dutch carried out the destruction scheme for the Balikpapan oilfields, whichare now in Japanese hands.The convoy mentioned above has been continuously attacked by Allied sea andair forces since the 23rd January, as reported under &quot; Naval Situation.&quot;33.   In South-Eastern Celebes the Japanese have occupied Kendari.Philippines.34. Despite heavy attacks during the past week, the United States forcesin Luzon managed to maintain themselves, but have now withdrawn to their finaldefensive position. The United States forces in Mindanao have received suppliesof S.A.A. by air from Java.Pacific.35. Japanese landings have taken place at Kavieng and Kapsu, in NewIreland, and at Mussau, just North-west of New Ireland.Intelligence.Distribution of Japanese Forces.36. There has been no change in the total number of Japanese forces inSouth-East Asia during the past week, but it seems likely that enemy troops inthe Philippines have been reinforced by a division, possibly from the Cantonarea. The concentration of transports and warships reported moving South inthe Macassar Strait during the past week possibly contained a division fromFormosa. It is likely that the divisions previously reported in transports offCamranh Bay have been landed in Indo-China and that a division previouslylocated in Saigon is moving towards the Indo-China-Thai frontier to reinforcethe Japanese forces at present operating against Burma.37. In addition to the occupation of Singapore and the ending of resistancein the Philippines as soon as possible, Japanese intentions appear to be :  (i) Attack on Burma with the primary object of capturing Rangoon andthus stopping supplies to China.(ii) The occupation of strategic islands in South-West Pacific area, possiblyFiji and West Samoa, to prevent Allied reinforcements being sent toAustralia and New Zealand, or to our forces operating in North-EastIndia, Malaya and Philippines.(iii) The occupation of the North-East India, and probably the Sunda Straitarea to prevent reinforcements being sent to Singapore. It is possiblealso an operation may be undertaken to occupy aerodromes in NorthernSumatra.38. Assuming that operations against Burma have now begun in earnestand that the Japanese have sufficient garrison troops in Indo-China to relievefighting formations, it is estimated that Japan can make four divisionsimmediately available for further operations (three from Indo-China and oneat present in transports in the Macassar Strait). In addition, she can make afurther eight divisions available at short notice (four from Northern China, onefrom Central China, one from Formosa, and, if the situation continues to remainthe same in Manchuria vis-a-vis Russia, a further two divisions from Manchuria).Total twelve divisions.Italy.39. Further reports have been received of the presence of German troopsin Italy.  The most reliable of these reports suggests a maximum of one division.France and Spain.40. Some seven weak divisions have left for the Russian front, their placebeing taken by about the same number of tired divisions much reduced by fightingon the Russian front.
AIR SITUATION.General Review.44. The night bombing offensive against enemy targets on the Continentwas assisted by improved weather conditions, and some attacks took place inexcellent visibility. By day, however, unfavourable weather curtailed airoperations.Enemy attacks on Malta have continued.Air activity in Libya was on a large scale, and considerable losses wereinflicted on the enemy.Successful attacks were made on enemy convoys in the Mediterranean andoff the East Malayan Coast.Singapore&apos;s four aerodromes were damaged in a series of raids.United Kingdom.45.   Fighter Command flew 1,249 sorties by day and 252 by night.46. Enemy activity was again on a small scale and consisted mainly ofcoastal operations. Only 11 aircraft crossed the coast by day and seven by night.Our fighters destroyed one bomber and damaged another.  We had no losses.Germany and Occupied Territory.Night.47. Bombing operations were carried out on five nights, during which 507sorties were flown, compared with 423 in the previous week.  A total of 530 tonsWithin France there has been a tendency to increase the concentration ofdivisions in the coastal strip Dunkirk-Le Havre at -the expense of the areasfurther west and south-west. Nevertheless, the total number of divisions isprobably still 26.It is also reported that there are two armoured divisions in France, one iiithe Paris area and the other still forming in the neighbourhood of Niort. Whilstthe possibility cannot be excluded that new armoured divisions are being formedin France, the evidence at present available suggests that the armoured forces inboth these areas are, in fact, tank training commands from which frequent draftsare being sent to divisions in Russia,41. There is no evidence whatever to suggest that a German move into Spairiis imminent or, indeed, possible at the moment. Only two weak German divisionsare at present located south of the Gironde.Balkan States and Turkey.42. There are no further indications that a German attack on Turkey ispossible in the near future. Reliable reports indicate that the trend of Germanmovement is away from the Balkans, doubtless owing to the need for reinforcingtheir armies on the Russian front. It is believed that the Bulgarians have takenover further Yugoslav territory. The estimate of the number of German divisionsin Yugoslavia has recently been six, but this figure may have to be reduced.The German forces in the remainder of the Balkans include two divisionsand attached troops in Greece, Crete and the iEgean Islands. The situation asregards German troops in Bulgaria and Roumania is obscure, but it seems possiblethat no divisions remain in either country.43. Reports of severe winter conditions arrive from all parts of South-EastEurope. The Danube is closed to all shipping. Serious dislocation of railwaytraffic has occurred in Roumania.
of HE. bombs were dropped, and several of the attacks took place under excellentconditions of visibility.  The principal objectives were as follows : Target.	Attacks and total aircraft.	Tons of H.E. bombs.	Results reported.Brest......	Three 88 aircraft	128	No results on the warships observed.(warships)			Observation mainly obscured  by			smoke-screen.Minister	Two 75 aircraft	111	Many large fires:   railway station			straddled:   adjacent large building			heavily damaged.Boulogne	Two 40 aircraft	55	Bursts, followed by fires, across four			of the docks.Hanover	One 32 aircraft	38	Numerous fires.Emden	One 29 aircraft	43	Three fires, one fairly large.Rotterdam	One 26 aircraft	45	Many good fires in dock area.Day.48. No operations were carried out by Bomber Command. A total of 139offensive sorties were flown by Fighter Command, but nothing of importanceoccurred; few enemy aircraft were seen.Coastal Operations.49. Coastal Command flew 130 patrols (185 sorties) and despatched 19additional sorties on convoy-escorts. Shipping protection patrols by FighterCommand totalled 771 sorties.50. Except for a number of photographic reconnaissances, includingTrondheim and Brest, activity by Coastal Command was restricted by bad weatherto routine patrols.51. At night, Fighter Command despatched 11 Hurricane bombers to attackshipping off Dunkirk, and 15 aircraft were despatched by Bomber Command to laysea-mines off the Frisian Islands and in the Jade and Weser rivers.52.   Anti-shipping operations by the enemy were on a small scale.Mediterranean.Libya.53. Throughout the week, our fighter and bomber aircraft carried out aseries of continuous and highly successful attacks on enemy forces and M.T.operating in the battle area, and heavy casualties were inflicted on troops andvehicles.54. A particularly successful attack was made on the 26th, when ourfighters, in spite of severe sand-storms, continuously machine-gunned M.T. andtanks moving between Antelat, Saunnu, Msus and Charruba. At least120 vehicles were destroyed or damaged and many enemy troops were killed orwounded. Our bombers had already helped to disorganise enemy movementtowards Msus by dropping 40 tons of bombs in continuous attacks throughout theprevious night.55. Our fighters also carried out several protective sweeps over the forwardtroops. During one of these, five Hurricanes intercepted a formation of 30 enemyaircraft near Msus, destroying four and damaging three without loss tothemselves.56. Shipping in Tripoli (L) harbour was heavily attacked by Wellingtons.A naval vessel and what appeared to be a flak ship were set on fire, and hits wereobtained on the quays alongside which several ships were lying. Other Welling-tons bombed the jetty at Buerat El Hsun and buildings and M.T. near Sirte.
57. Great activity was maintained by enemy fighters, which, in addition tocarrying out several sweeps over the battle area, provided escorts for dive-bombingformations. Enemy long-range bombers operating from Libyan bases were alsoemployed against our forward troops and vehicles, but the greater part of theGerman long-range bombers operated from Greece against land and sea communi-cations along the Cyrenaican coast.Malta.58. Offensive operations against the Island continued on an intensivescale. Daylight attacks were carried out by waves of aircraft, and night attacksby relays of aircraft operating singly. The attacks were particularly heavy onthe 22nd and on the two following days, when a total of 165 aircraft raidedthe Island.59. A large proportion of the attacks continued to be directed against theaerodromes. Buildings were damaged at Hal Ear, and about 20 craters weremade on the aerodrome, where one aircraft was destroyed on the ground and atleast five were damaged. At Luqa two aircraft were destroyed and five damaged.Slight damage was also caused to shipping and buildings in the Grand Harbour,and to machinery in the dockyard.60. Our fighter activity was seriously hampered by bad weather and by thewater-logged condition of the aerodromes, but some interceptions were made.Three enemy aircraft were probably destroyed and four were damaged. We lostsix Hurricanes, but four pilots are safe.  A Ju. 88 was shot down by A.A. fire.Italy and Sicily.61. On the night 26th/27th Wellingtons operating from Malta attackedthe aerodromes in Catania and Comiso in Sicily, dropping seven tons of bombson the former and four on the latter. Buildings, hangars and runways were hitat both places.62. Intruder patrols over aerodromes in Southern Sicily were flown byHurricanes. Two Ju. 88&apos;s were destroyed and one was damaged as they weretaking off, and a fourth aircraft was shot down in combat.63. In addition, our aircraft made several photographic reconnaissances ofharbours and aerodromes in Sicily and Southern Italy.Sea Communications.64. On the night of 22nd/23rd a Wellington on a shipping reconnaissancesighted a south-bound convoy 175 miles north-east of Syracuse. It was againsighted on the following day in a position 170 miles north-east of Tripoli (L),and was then found to consist of a liner of 20,000 tons and four large merchantvessels escorted by a battleship, four cruisers and about 16 destroyers.65. On the 23rd and on the following night the convoy was continuouslyattacked by bombers and torpedo-carrying aircraft. The liner was torpedoed andbrought to a stop, a destroyer was torpedoed, a cruiser was hit with bombs andnear misses were made on two merchant vessels. We lost two aircraft. In spite ofa thorough search on the 24th no trace of the liner was found, and photographsof the harbour at Tripoli (L), taken on the 25th, showed that four merchantvessels and five destroyers had arrived, but again there was no trace of the liner.66. On the 27th five Blenheims which were sent to attack a 4,000-tonmerchant vessel and an escort vessel 45 miles west of Tripoli (L), steaming east,were unable to drop their bombs, as they were all hit by enemy fighters whichwere escorting the vessels.67. Several reconnaissances of the Ionian Sea and of the Gulf of Sirtewere carried out by our aircraft, and anti-submarine patrols were flown south-east of Malta and in Arabs Gulf, south-west of Alexandria.
The Far East. .Burma.70. Our light bombers have been employed against objectives in Thailand(Siam) and against enemy columns attacking Burma.On the 23rd, six of our bombers operating from Burma, with fighterescort, dropped bombs among a concentration of enemy lorries near MesodSuccessful night bombing attacks against Bangkok docks and adjacentcommercial quarters were also carried out. During these attacks a power stationwas hit and large fires were started in the target area. Blenheims with fighterescort also attacked troops, lorries and a pontoon bridge on the Kawkareik-Miawadi road.71. Formations of Japanese aircraft attempted, with little success, to attackthe aerodromes of Mingaladon and Zayatkwin (both near Rangoon) on four daysand two nights. During these attacks one Hurricane was destroyed on the groundand an ammunition store was gutted. Interceptions by our aircraft and thoseof the A.V.G. were noticeably effective. In an attack by seven enemy bomberswith an escort of 25 fighters, it is claimed that all the bombers and six (orprobably eight) of the fighters were destroyed and nine more were damagedwithout loss to our aircraft. It is reported that, during the other attacks, afurther 34 fighters were shot down and 27 were probable casualties for the lossof only five of ours.Malaya.72. On night 23rd/24th, Wirraways and Albacores attacked troops andM.T. in the Yong Peng area and the Labis-Yong Peng road bridge was believedto have been demolished. The next night, Vildebeestes and Albacores dropped11 tons of bombs on Labis, causing heavy damage. This was followed by raidson Batu Pahat, where a large area was set on fire and on Muar, where a 600-tonmerchant vessel was&apos; hit and the centre of the town severely damaged.73. Our bombers, with fighter escort, attacked an enemy naval forcepreviously sighted 18 miles north-east of Endau. Hits were claimed on acruiser and on two merchant vessels of 8,000 and 9,000 tons respectively.Enemy troops on the Endau-Mersing road were also bombed and a large stores-dump was hit. Fierce opposition was encountered from a large number of enemyfighters, of which 11 were destroyed, two probably destroyed and three damaged;we lost 12 aircraft. (Naval operations carried out off Endau are recorded under&quot; Naval Situation.&quot;)74. Singapore Island was continuously bombed during the week, the main,weight of the attacks being directed against the aerodromes. As a result ofthese attacks, the aerodromes at Tengah and Sembawang were renderedunserviceable, and hangars and buildings at Kallang and Seletar were damaged.A total of 13 aircraft were destroyed on the ground and 38 were damaged.There were some casualties among personnel. In addition, Keppel Harbour was[23392] cRussia.68. The continued Russian advance in the Moscow sector must bedislocating the operational activities and the general organisation of the GermanAir Force in that area. Aerodromes from which advanced German Air Forceunits have been operating are either seriously threatened or already in Russianhands. Further south, the fall of Briansk would compel the withdrawal of otherGerman Air Force units.69. In both sectors any such withdrawals would necessitate the abandon-ment of unserviceable aircraft and would aggravate the German difficulties,owing to limited accommodation on aerodromes further to the rear.
bombed and a small ship and a lighter were slightly damaged. Interceptionsby our fighters resulted in the destruction of five bombers and damage to fiVemore aircraft. On other occasions, interceptions by Hurricanes and Buffaloesforced the raiders to jettison their bombs. Eight of our fighters were lost, &quot;butthree of the pilots are safe. -75. During the week, our troops in the forward area were heavily dive-bombed and machine-gunned, the attacking forces including for the first timeThai aircraft, though it is not known whether they were piloted by Japanese orThai personnel.Netherlands East Indies.76. Many enemy attacks were made on shipping off the West Coast ofSumatra, and hostile aircraft in varying force operated at scattered points onthe Eastern Archipelago.77. Netherlands East Indies aircraft carried out an attack on Kuching, inBorneo, setting a warehouse on fire. They also destroyed three enemy aircraftwhich attacked Samarinda.Pacific Zone.78. On the 22nd, Kapsu (New Ireland) was heavily raided and Rabaul wastwice attacked, each time by a force of 40 enemy aircraft. Communicationswith Rabaul ceased on that day, and on night 24th/25th and on the 26th, fiveCatalinas of the Royal Australian Air Force bombed Rabaul and made twoprobable hits on a warship, and hit two of the transports.79. Five enemy aircraft caused considerable damage at Manus (AdmiraltyIsland).China.80. It is reliably reported that two air attacks have recently been made bythe Chinese on Hanoi, the Japanese-occupied capital of French Indo-China.81. The first of these attacks was made on the 22nd by 27 bombers, withfighter escort, when 20 tons of bombs are said to have been dropped on theJapanese air base and barracks, while the fighters ground-straffed Japanesetroops and aircraft. No air opposition was encountered and the Chinese claimto have incurred no losses.82. The second raid took place on the 24th, when, according to Chineseclaims, some 70 aircraft, consisting of fighters and bombers, took part. Morethan 200 bombs were dropped and large fires were started. -HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.By Day.83. The most serious incident took place at Lowestoft, where bombs weredropped during the morning of the 23rd January. Twelve people were killedand 10 seriously injured, and 23 houses were demolished.84. Wick aerodrome was also bombed on the same day. The damage causedwas insignificant.
23392;D85. On the 26th January minor bombing and slight damage was reportedfrom Newburgh, Aberdeenshire.86. Enemy coastal batteries shelled Dover on the 22nd and damaged a fey*houses.By Night.87. On tlhe 22nd / 23rd bombs were dropped in Cornwall and Norfolk, andon the 25th/26th at some places between Penzance and Land&apos;s End. There wassome damage to house property, but no casualties.Casualties.88. Estimated civilian casualties for the week ending 0600 on the28th January are 14 killed and 11 seriously injured.
bombed and a small ship and a lighter were slightly damaged. Interceptionsby our fighters resulted in the destruction of five bombers and damage to fivemore aircraft. On other occasions, interceptions by Hurricanes and Buffaloesforced the raiders to jettison their bombs. Eight of our fighters were lost/butthree of the pilots are safe,75. During the week, our troops in the forward area were heavily dive-bombed and machine-gunned, the attacking forces including for the first timeThai aircraft, though it is not known whether they were piloted by Japanese orThai personnel.Netherlands East Indies.76. Many enemy attacks were made on shipping off the West Coast ofSumatra, and hostile&quot; aircraft in varying force operated at scattered points onthe Eastern Archipelago.77. Netherlands East Indies aircraft carried out an attack on Kuching, inBorneo, setting a warehouse on fire. They also destroyed three enemy aircraftwhich attacked Samarinda.Pacific Zone.78. On the 22nd, Kapsu (New Ireland) was heavily raided and Rabaul wastwice attacked, each time by a force of 40 enemy aircraft. Communicationswith Rabaul ceased on that day, and on night 24th /25th and on the 26th, fiveCatalinas of the Royal Australian Air Force bombed Rabaul and made twoprobable hits on a warship, and hit two of the transports.79. Five enemy aircraft caused considerable damage at Manus (AdmiraltyIsland).China.80. It is reliably reported that two air attacks have recently been made bythe Chinese on Hanoi, the Japanese-occupied capital of French Indo-China.81. The first of these attacks was made on the 22nd by 27 bombers, withfighter escort, when 20 tons of bombs are said to have been dropped on theJapanese air base and barracks, while the fighters ground-straffed Japanesetroops and aircraft. No air opposition was encountered and the Chinese claimto have incurred no losses.82. The second raid took place on the 24th, when, according to Chineseclaims, some 70 aircraft, consisting of fighters and bombers, took part. Morethan 200 bombs were dropped and large fires were started.HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.By Day.83. The most serious incident took place at Lowestoft, where bombs weredropped during the morning of the 23rd January. Twelve people were killedand 10 seriously injured, and 23 houses were demolished.84. Wick aerodrome was also bombed on the same day. The damage causedwas insignificant.
[23392;85. On the 26th January minor bombing and slight damage was reportedfrom Newburgh, Aberdeenshire.86. Enemy coastal batteries shelled Dover on the 22nd and damaged a fewhouses.By Night.87. On tihe 22nd/23rd bombs were dropped in Cornwall and Norfolk, andon the 25th/26th at some places between Penzance and Land&apos;s End. There wassome damage to house property, but no casualties.Casualties.88. Estimated civilian casualties for the week ending 0600 on the28th January are 14 killed and 11 seriously injured.
...   . APPENDICES I, II and III .will be published monthly.APPENDIX IY.Enemy Merchant Ship Losses.The enemy losses have now been assessed up to the 11th January and are asfollows: -Nationality.	Sunk, Captured or Constructive Loss.		Seriously Damaged.		Damaged.		Total. -		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.German    ... Italian Other enemy ships and ships useful to enemy	391 400 98	1,710,901 1,711,554 190,055	108 72 14	292,365 335,625 40,416	173 78 12	594,052 390,984 48,824	672 550 124	2,597,318 2,438,163 279,295Total    ...	889	3,612,510	194	668,406	263	1,033,860	1,346	5,314,776In addition to the above, there are Russian claims estimated at some 512,000gross tons sunk; and there is a considerable amount of Axis shipping in Centraland South American ports of countries not actually at war with the Axis, whichis no longer available for Axis use and which is not included above.The table does not include losses inflicted on Japanese shipping in the FarEast and Pacific, at present estimated at about 168,000 gross tons.APPENDIX V.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Yessels and to Naval Personnel.Norwegian Minesweeper Eveline sank in collision at Milford Haven. Onerating is missing.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : ?Officers : 76 killed; 17 missing.Ratings: 829 killed; 949 missing; 5 wounded.These figures include the loss of 56 officers and 808 ratings in H.M.S. Barhcmand 717 ratings missing from H.M.S. Neptune.
Provisional operational aircraft battle casualties compiled from reportsreceived during the period:0700 hours, Thursday, 22nd January, 1942, to 0700 hours, Thursday,29th January, 1942.Metropolitan Area.British.Bombers...Fighters ...Coastal ...Army Co-OperationIn the Air.1042On the Ground.Total16Enemy.Bombers    ...FightersMiscellaneousTotalDestroyed,1-,.     1Middle East.ProbablyDestroyed.1Damaged.2iBritish.Bombers.Fighters.Coastal .TotalIn the Air.213116Four pilots are safe.Enemy.Bombers ...Fighters ...MiscellaneousDestroyed.88117ProbablyDestroyed.22On the Ground.i- 1............Damaged.614Total    ......Of the above totals, one bomber was destroyed by A.A. fire.Far East (including Burma).20British and Allied.Bombers ...Fighters ...MiscellaneousTotalIn the Air.10114   .:25On the Ground.26614Two pilots are safe.Enemy.Bombers ...Fighters ...MiscellaneousTotalDestroyed.1452975ProbablyDestroyed523&apos;634Damaged.32528Of the above total, three enemy aircraft were destroyed by A.A. fire.Note. No account is taken of enemy aircraft destroyed on the ground in any theatre.
Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports of damage have been received during the past weekfrom Air Reconnaissance and Intelligence Sources : Germany.Emden,. Photographs taken on the 11th January, 1942, cover a considerablepart of the dock area but do not cover the town itself. Assessment of damage ismade extremely difficult owing to a recent fall of snow, but the photographsshow : (i) Part of the north-western end of the engine shed to the south of therailway dock has been destroyed,(ii) A large warehouse at the south end of the Binnenhafen and buildingson the west side of the Aussenhafen have been severely damaged,(iii) Buildings in the Nordsee Werke appear to have roof damage andworkmen&apos;s dwellings to the west of the town have suffered severely.Three or four houses have been completely demolished by a direct hitand an entire row of houses is believed to have suffered damage by fire.Cologne. During the raid on the 11th/12th December, damage was causedto a goods station and sidings. The Berlin-Cologne Express was hit as it wasentering the main railway station and one of the biggest cinemas in the city wasalso hit.
issued with  weekly   intelligence   summary n?i28   (28-1-42)L.LADOGAO.R.5518SOUTH WEST U.S.S.R.scale   1:4,000,000   or   63 miles to i inchmiles50 25 0 50 io0iso milesRUSSIAN OPERATIONS AGAINST THE AXISshowing approximate advances.legendLimit of German Advance________Russian Front Line on 20&apos;h42Russian Front Lineon27-h42Main thrusts of Russian Forces.Thrusts of German Forces.1111 ^-5^Note:-    It is emphasized that in the mobile war-Farewhich has taken place up to date there can beho continuous front line.   The  lines   on  themap   therefore indicate only the approximatelimits of advance of the foremost  troops.Su khum




</content>
</cab>
