<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/18/3 images: 38-45</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special qc^g may beensure[paS document is the property op his briieannic majesty*s government)SECRET.W.P.   (41)  180.26TH JULY. 1941,copy no. clMWAR CABINET.defence measures in malaya.Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign affairs on 7th July the War Cabinet approved the adoptionof certain measures in the event of the acquisition by japan of bases in southern Indo-China.     One of these measures was the prohibition of the loading of iron oreetc. at night off the Malayan coast and of the arrival atanchorage of vessels over 1,000 tons between sunset andsunrise.     This measure was put into force as soon as it became clear that Japan was making demands on Vichy.2. The Commander-in-Chief Far East was subsequentlyasked whether there were any additional defence measures in Malaya or the Far East which could appropriately been forced as counter measures demonstrating our reactions to the Japanese penetration of Indo-China. In reply hehas suggested certain restrictions qn the movement of japanese ships and nationals in Hong Kong and Burma withwhich it is unnecessary for me to trouble my colleagues.As regards Malaya he has proposed:(a) the removal of Japanese nationals from thedefence areas f.n Kedah, Perlis, ProvinceWellesley, Penang, the northern part ofPerak and In Kelantanj    and(b) the removal of Japanese nationals from certain parts of Johore which have been declared defence areas.     This would remove observation over Johore Straits.5a A subsidiary effect of these measures would be to close down a Japanese-owned iron mine in Kelantan.     as my colleagues will be aware, one of the factors that hadto be weighed when approving the defence measure inregard to the loading of ships at night off Malaya wasthe drastic curtailment which this would involve in theproduction of the Japanese-owned mines in the MalayaPeninsula.     It was estimated that it would result incutting down from approximately 2 million tons to1 million tons a year the export of iron ore from these

mines.      The further measures suggested above affectingKelantan might reduce the figure of 1 million tons by approximately 11%,4. The Commander-in-Chief China has suggested an evenmore drastic measure.     The attached telegram shows thathe considers that we are still accepting an unnecessaryrisk to our security in allowing Japanese lighters andtugs to ply, even by day, between harbours and ships lyingup to five miles out off the east coast of Malaya and thewest coast of Johore.     The proposal which he makes is thatif the Japanese go into bases in southern Indo-China weshould(a) prohibit entirely all traffic of tugs andlighters between harbour mouths and foreign ships at anchor off the harbour;    or(b) prohibit the loading of foreign ships if more than one is either at anchor or insight.Of these two alternatives he considers the firstvery much preferable from the military point of view.5* All -these proposals have been considered by the far Eastern Committee.      The Gommittee appreciates thatthe proposals of the Oommander-in-Chief China have theconcurrence of the Governor of the Straits Settlementsand the Commander-in-Chief Par East., but it feels houndto draw attention to the following considerations:6. The complete or virtual stoppage of the export of iron ore, which, the more drastic proposal involves, thoughjustifiable &quot;on defence grounds, will almost certainly betaken by the Japanese as an economic measure directed against Japanese enterprises.      Its result   will be to cutdown by about two-thirds the already seriously restrictedproduction of iron and steel in Japan.     It is therefore a measure which might conceivably precipitate Japaneseaction against Malaya and might on that ground be regardedunsympathetically by the United States Government as beingunnecessarily provocative in present circumstances.7. The Par Eastern Committee sees no reason why theproposals of the Commander-In-Chief Par East for theremoval of Japanese nationals from certain areas in Malaya(paragraph 2 above) should not be approved, but, for theabove reasons, it has felt bound to submit to higher authority a decision on the wider measures proposed bythe Commander-in-Chief China.8. My own recorrimendation and that of the Secretary ofState for the Colonies is that action should be confinedfor the time being to the removal of Japanese nationalsfrom areas in Malaya suggested by the Commander-in-ChiefPar East, including the Kelantan iron mine, but that weshould leave for later review any measures which mighthave a more drastic effect on the output of the Japanesemines in the Peninsula.A0E0Foreign Office,26th July, 1941.

ANNEX.COPY OP A TELEGRAM DATED 2LST JULY, 1941.PROM THE COM^iAKDER-IN-CHIEF. CHINA,TO THE ADMIRALTY.X X X X X928.     I consider we are still accepting unnecessaryrisk to our security in allowing traffic even by day of japanese lighters and tugs between harbours and ships lyingup to 5 miles outside harbour mouth on East Coast malaya and West Coast Jahore.     The risk is less since nighttraffic ceased, but it is still there and in view of difficulty of control and inspection combined with numberof ships lying off Port, which total at time up to 7 offany one ports it (the (? risk)) is still more than we can accept with equanimity-I suggest that if Japanese go into lado ChinaSouthern Bases we should.(a) Prohibit entirely all traffic of tugs andlighters between harbour mouths and foreign ships at anchor off harbour, or(b) Prohibit loading of any foreign ship   if more than one is either at anchor or insight.Of the two (a) is very much preferred from military point of view     ,.Governor and Commander in Chief Far East fullyconcur.     The former is telegraphing separately toSecretary of State for Colonies.X X X X X




</content>
</cab>
