<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/53/10 images: 96-101</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s government&apos;Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1945.SECRET. Copy No. 5^CM. (45)10th Conclusions.CABINET 10 (45).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing StreetS.W. 1, on Wednesday, 20th June,lM5, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister(in the Chair Item 4).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer(in the Chair Items 1-3).The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal (Item 4).The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon Lord Woolton, lord president of the Council.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade and Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. The Earl of Rosebery,Secretary of State for Scotland.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Arthur Salter,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster (Item 1).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell, Pay-master-General.The Right Hon. Viscount Margesson(Item 4).Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. Norman Brook.Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Reparations    ....      ....      ....      ........      ........Disposal of German War Material.2      Greece   ........      ....      ....      ........3      Civil Aviation ....      .... ............Extension of Filton Aerodrome.4      Three-Power Meeting....      ........      ....      ........F30420-4]646566
Reparations.Disposal ofGerman WarMaterial.(Previous &apos;&quot;:Reference:CM. (45) 7thConclusions,Minute 2.)1. The Cabinet considered a Memorandum by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (CP. (45) 41) on the demarcation betweenreparation deliveries and booty.The Chancellor of the Exchequer explained that in August,1944, we had proposed that a wide class of German war materialcaptured before the general surrender of Germany should beregarded as belonging to the country by whose forces it had been captured. Under this proposal a large proportion of the german war material would be at Anglo-American disposal, since it was captured by Anglo-American forces though our advantage in thisrespect would be reduced by the fact that, when we withdrew intothe agreed Zones of Occupation, we should have to leave behind inthe Russian Zone much captured material which we could haveclaimed under this proposal as booty. In February, 1945, we had agreed, in the Yalta Protocol, that a large part of the war materialcovered by this definition should be taken as reparation and allocatedbetween the Allies in the agreed percentages. It seemed likely,however, that the Russians might seek to describe a great deal ofthe material which they were removing from their Zone as booty,and not as reparation, so as to avoid counting it as part of theiragreed share of reparation. In these circumstances it seemed desirable that the Cabinet should reconsider the view that had been expressed in their discussion on the 11th June, that the MoscowReparation Commission should be invited to adopt a narrowdefinition of booty.The Chancellor said that, for the reasons outlined in his memorandum, he would prefer that our delegation to the MoscowReparation Commission should not commit themselves at the outsetto any view on the demarcation between reparation deliveries andbooty, but should seek to ascertain the Russian views and, inparticular, to satisfy themselves that the Russians would give facilities for ensuring that goods ranking as reparation deliverieswere properly accounted for. The delegation should then seekinstructions, in the light of the discussions, on the question whetherthey should advocate a wide or a narrow definition of booty.The Chancellor also recommended that, whatever definition wasultimately agreed, the value of the material taken as booty should be credited to Germany in the reparation settlement; and that everyeffort should be made to persuade the Russians to agree thatmaterial which they took from that part of the Russian Zone whichwas first occupied by the Anglo-American forces should count as reparations. In any event, the definition of booty must be so drawnas to give full rights to dispose of, or destroy, all military material which we did not wish dealt with on a quadripartite basis. Thetreatment of ships should be postponed pending the outcome of theThree-Power meeting.The Chancellor said that a further point to be noted was thatthe principle of restitution should override the principle ofbooty, viz., if any object were identified as being loot, it should bereturned to the owner even though it fell within the class of material which, if German, would be seized as booty.The Cabinet-Endorsed the recommendations made by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer, as summarised above, and invited theChancellor to arrange for instructions to be sent to our delegation at the Moscow Reparation Commission on thelines indicated in paragraph 15 of CP. (45) 41.
Greece.(Previous -Reference:ff.M.(45)29thConclusions,jlinute 1.)2. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Education (CP. (45) 24) on British policy in Greece.The general conclusions suggested in this Memorandum were that, while it was in our interest that stability should be established and maintained in Greece, the Greek Government must themselvessolve the problems now confronting them. We should only assist in an advisory capacity, and should avoid any measures which wouldinvolve us in taking over the Greek administration. Two specific recommendations were also made : (1) We should advise the GreekGovernment to reduce the size of their armed forces to the minimumneeded to maintain internal security; and should require the GreekGovernment to pay for the maintenance of their forces, though weshould fulfil our undertaking to supply initial equipment for a force of 100,000 men. (2) We should facilitate the increase ofimports into Greece, e.g., by supporting U.N.R.R.A.&apos;s requests for supplies and shipping and by doing our best to provide supplies and shipping for purchases by the Greek Government or by Greekimporters.Points in discussion were : (a) The Permanent Vnder-Secretary of State for foreign ffairs said that the position had changed in certain respects sincethe Minister of Education circulated his Memorandum. Thus,General Scobie had suggested some extension of the powers of theBritish Military Mission in Greece, to enable them to concern themselves with the dismissal of undesirable members of the Greekmilitary forces. The Chiefs of Staff had suggested that thisproposal should be discussed with Field-Marshal Alexander during his forthcoming visit to this country.(p) Would it not be inexpedient for us to suggest that the size of the Greek forces should be related directly to the minimum forcerequired to maintain internal security? If we made use of sucha formula, the Greeks would have a strong case for demandingmilitary assistance from us if they were threatened at any future date with external aggression.The Cabinet agreed that it would be preferable to advise theGreek Government to reduce their forces to a stated figure, without reference to the minimum force required to maintain internal security. The Greek Government should certainly be pressed toassume financial responsibility for maintaining the reduced force.(c) Reference was made to the inflationary condition of theGreek economy, and it was suggested that further pressure mightbe brought to bear on the Greek Government to balance their budget.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that in this respect therehad been definite signs of improvement in recent weeks. SinceM. Varvaressos had joined the Greek Government, a, comprehensive plan had been framed to combat inflation. The Treasury were satisfied that the plan was adequate for its purpose. The only question now in doubt was whether the Greek Government wouldhave sufficient resolution to give full effect to it.(d) It was suggested that the economic situation in Greecemight be improved by increased production, as well as increased imports; and that for this purpose it might be helpful if an Anglo-American Production Mission were sent to Greece to advise the greeks how they could best help themselves in this respect. TheChancellor of the Exchequer suggested that before this suggestion was discussed with the United States authorities, it would be desir-able to ascertain whether M. Varvaressos would welcome a visit by such a Mission.The Cabinet^-(1) Endorsed the conclusions set out in paragraph 9 of CP. (45)24, subject to the point mentioned at (6) above.
CivilAviation.Extensionof FiltonAerodrome.(previous reference:CM. (45) 7thConclusions,Minute 6.)Agreed that the Foreign Office should considersuggestion that an Anglo-American Production MissioJmight with advantage be sent to Greece to advise MGreek Government on the prospects of increasingindustrial production.3. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum (CP. (45) 39which the Minister of Aircraft Production had submitted in compliance with the Cabinets request at their meeting on the 11th Juneshowing the expenditure which would be incurred month by montlin the building of the assembly shed required at Filton AirfieldBristol; for the construction of the prototype of the Brabazon I civiaircraft.The Paymaster-General, on behalf of the Minister of AircrafProduction, recalled that at their previous discussion the Cabinehad inclined to the view that the construction of this assembly shejmight be put in hand if the expenditure to be incurred before thl1st August, 1945, would not exceed  50,000. The Memorandumsshowed that the expenditure iri the first two months would be onli 32,000 and it would be in conformity with the Cabinets earlielview that authority should now be given for the constructi On of thinshed to be put in hand.In discussion attention was drawn to the high cost of thijbuilding, in terms both of money and of labour. It was estimateclthat the labour force required would be 250 at the start, rising bill the fifth month to a peak of 1,000, which would be maintained foifa period of three months. It was suggested that the detailed!estimates of cost should be subject to further scrutiny by thTreasury.The Cabinet-Authorised the Minister of Aircraft Production to arrangfor work to be started on the construction of the assemblshed at Filton Airfield for the prototype of the Brabazoncivil aircraft.Three-power meeting.(previous reference:CM. (45)8thConclusions,Minute 1.)4. The Cabinet discussed the arrangements for the fortcoming meeting between the Prime Minister, President Trumaand Marshal Stalin.The discussion is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard FileCabinet Conclusions.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,20th June, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
