<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/2/31 images: 338-349</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
md.f0Ttfae.Ww -CaMmt. November11989..TO ISI^ HS12PT UNDER LOCK AKHED  TO.It is requested that special care may he taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 97 (39).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the. War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, an Tuesday, November 28, 1939, at 10 am.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer,Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord ChatfielD, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. L. Hore-Belisha,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt, MR, Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. Lord Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The, Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Sir Horace J. Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 1-13).The following were also present:The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-13).Major-General H. R. S. Massy, DeputyCJhief of the Imperial General Staff(Items 1-13).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-Genera! H. L. Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, R.E.-Lieutsiaont-colonel E. I. C. Jaccb, R.E.
Contents.minute no. Subject. PageI The Air Situation    ...............      ...    2372     The Naval Situation.........      ...      ...      ...    237Magnetic mines.3     The Military Situation       .......... ... 2374      The Shipping Situation      ... ...               ... ... 2375      Dominion Air Training Scheme ...      ...      ... ... 2386      Yugoslavia      ...............      ...      ...    240Supply of Armaments.7      Soviet Union   ............      ...      ......    240Threat to Finland.Attitude towards the United Kingdom.Trade negotiations.Arrival of Soviet Icebreaker in Baltic.8      Germany ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...    240Internal situation.9     Roumania       ...      &apos;......      ...      ...      ...      ...    241Attitude towards the United Kingdom.10     France  ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     ...    241Beaction of French public opinion to German propaganda.II Seizure of Enemy Exports   ......      .........    242Protest by the Japanese Government.%%     The Far Eastern Situation ...     ... ...    242Tientsin silver question.13      United States ...      ...      ...      -----      ......    242&apos;Effect pa public opinion of our restriction of imports from United; &apos; States. \ &apos; &quot; .&apos;4 Mr. Kennedy&apos;s forthcoming visit to United States.14     Parliament     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ......    243Prppqsed Secret Session of the House of Comraoas.
The Air Situation. (Previous Reference W.M. (?) ? Conclusions, Minute 1.)

 1. The Secretary of State of Air said that a reconnaissance by six Whitleys had been carried out the night before over Wilhelmshaven. Cuxhaven, Heligoland and Brunsbuttel. The weather had been extremely bad, with heavy cloud and electrical disturbances. Opposition had been encountered from anti-aircraft guns and fighters, and a balloon barrage had been reported at a height of 6,000 feet. All the aircraft had returned safely, but the reconnaissnae had been largely ineffective.

 There had been little German activity over the North Sea the day before. A flight of aircraft had been sent out to find the submarine Triad, reported to be damaged off the coast of Norway. The aircraft had made contact with the submarine, and had remained in company with her for two hours.

 A reconnaissance had been sent out to report on the assistance which the present system of light vessels and lighthouses on the East coast might give to hostile aircraft attempting to drop mines. A full report would be communicated to the Admiralty.

 The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.



Th Naval Situation. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 96th Conclusions, Minute 2.)

 2. The First Lord of the Admiralty said there had been no change in the position.

 Two destroyers had now made contact with the Triad, and it was hoped to bring her safely home.

 A Dutch ship, the Spaarndam, had been mined off the South East coast, on her way to Holland, and a Swedish ship had been mined in the Fair Isle channel.

 There had been no sinkings of British shipping, and no attacks on submarines.

Magnetic mines.

 Investigation of the magnetic mine was proceeding, and it was hoped to start trawling that day.

 The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence suggested that something less obvious might be substituted for buoys to mark the channels, so that enemy aircraft might be given no assistance in recognising the exact spots at which to drop their mines.

 The First Sea Lord said that the mine-laying was done at night, and the lights in the Thames estuary had now been put out. Steps had also been taken to guard the channels.

 The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.



The Military Situation. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 98th Conclusions, Minute 4.)

 3. The Secretary of Stae of War said that there had been no change in the military situation. There had been no further news of the troop movements recently reported westward from Hanover. There were no indications of any withdrawal of German troops from their forward positions. No doubt they were working on the improvement of their defences.

 The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.



The Shipping Situation. (Previous References: W.M. (39) ? Conclusions, Minute 1. and 33rd Conclusions Minute 4.)

 4. The First Lord of the Admiralty said that, whereas the losses of British shipping had fallen steadily since the beginning of the war except for the previous few days, the losses among neutral ships showed an exactly opposite tendency. Theire losses in the second month of the war were double those of the first mouth, and the third month allowed a corresponding increase. He thought that we should continue to point the moral of this to the neutrals, namely, the great opportunity open to them of chartering their ships to us. By so doing they would make substantial profits, without any risk of loss, as we would make good any losses which might occur.

 [20406]


110 X      r    itJi    &amp;at ; - ,,IJ ,naib    VMidi  I   S I  .; m     .   .   I , /4s&apos;early date when this and c^her&apos;&apos;6miW&apos;l^e^b^&apos;^ld. ba.discussfov.The -Imd^-JP-rmy.&apos;: Seal said that the ishiijpiog.\si^^ea was/extremely serious. The effects of the-delays on the ordtoa^ move-ment:ofvxsMpping caused&apos; by-, p&amp;stibfflfd: e^di$ioffl% maximum P&amp;H^lsilSby amy diversion of shipping from nom?vi ports, reveifbaKatsulthroughout the -whole--of the - country V organisation for supplyingfood, and other essentials. We were fast getting, to a position where we should be faced with actual shortages^ He had beendisturbed to find that conditions of shortage could suddenly arisewithout previous warning, and it was evident that a considerably greater degree of co-ordination was necessary between the be part-ments concerned in the supply of food.He had accordingly arranged for a Ministerial Sub-Committeeof the Home Policy Committee to be set Up, to keep under continuous and close review the broader aspects of the problems offood policy. This Sub-Committee would have associated with itan Inter-Departmental Committee of Officials; and by this meanshe hoped to be able to obtain a day-to-day view of the situation inall its aspects, including shipping, transport and food. Hehtopedyin the course of a few days, to present the War Cabinet with a&quot;broad picture of the situation. ,The First Lord of the Admiralty said that there was very littlediversion of shipping at the present time. The Thames wasl:qpen&apos;again, and traffic flowing. If so much dislocation was caused by theamount of diversion which had so far taken place, it was all themore important that action should be pressed on to improve the capacity of the Western ports, and the transport services connected therewith. The time might come when we would have&apos;to diverton a large scale.The Prime Minister said that shipping could not be dealt within the West coast ports as economically and rapidly as in the ports on the East coast at which it was accustomed to discharge. Thenormal system had been built up over many years, and could notbe easily transformed.- &apos;Ther-%or.d ^Prttiy] Seal agresd, and said that a large degree of diversion could only be carried out along with thte most drasticrestrictions. ;. He hoped, however, to be in a position to put thematter clearly before the War Cabinet very shortly.   .;The War Cabinet took note of the above discussion.EJasSiniitoiaScheme.(previous inference:Conclusions,Minute ,-6.)5. The Secretary of State for Air reported to the War Cabinetfurther developments which had taken place in connection with theDominion Air Training Scheme. A telegram from the -PrimeMinister had been despatched to Mr. Mackenzie King (telegramNo. Ill dated the 27th November, 1939), in accordance with theConclusions of the War Cabinet at their previous meeting-.Copies of the fbllowing further telegrams dated the 27thNovember^ 1939; were handed round to the War Cabinet :-Byline. Minister r;of v Cahacla,-.Me&apos;..to initial.the-:-    ^Telcgiann No., 110, mom the, Pstating toat ii had not lazsn        . -   : lait&amp;aj the ag^ee^esit
jfcisfiee, r J obj- assurances om m(,itb,- the situation regarding theloft&apos; /  &apos;:&apos; - &apos;        ,- !   Op tp? question pf tine pidpripies of .O^p^&apos;s war efitp,?fc ,Mr. Mackenzie King s attitude hay changed since the ?5thNovember, and he now desired the inclusion of the following sentence after the escape) eentencs pf paragraph   of the Prime.Minister&apos;s message  (telegram No,  ijl-.&apos; to -the Canadian&quot;Considering the present and future requirements,we feel that participation in the Air Training scheme would provide more effective assistance than any other formOf co-operation Which Canada could give.&apos;&apos;(These telegrains are being circulated for purposes of record-,as W.P. (&amp;) (39) ItO.) &apos;The Secretary of State for Air said that Mr. Mackenzie KingVattitude had cbmpletely changed since the 25th Ndvember, when theHigh Commissioner had drafted his telegrams Nbs. 710 and 713,which the War Cabinet had considered at their previous meeting.Mr. Mackenzie King was not now satisfied for it to be recognisedpublicly that Canada had a right to her own views on the subjectof the priorities of her war effort. He wished to have a clear st?ite-ment from the United Kingdom Governihent, of which he could make public use, that they themselves agreed that Canada was right in regarding the Air Training Scheme as her main war effort.Nevertheless, in spite of the fact that the agreement had not been definitely initialled, as had been hoped, a satisfactory announcementhacl been given to the Press before the departure of Mr. Fairbairn.Mpreover, ifo?. Mackenzie King was satisfied with our assuranceson the financial issue. There seemed, therefore, every prospect ifgood progress with the scheme once Mr. Towers arrived from canada to discuss the financial aspect.In discussion, attention was drawn to the danger of the&apos;sentence which Mr; Mackenzie King wished us to include. No doubthe wished to secure this statement for his own political purposes,and it would be most undesirable to allow ourselves to be drawn&apos;into a Canadian Party issue. It was suggested that a suitableformula might be evolved by the Dominions Office, War Office andAir Ministry, in consultation.The Prime Minister observed that it was most unfortunate that sir Gerald Campbell had given no indication at the time that thechange in Mr. Mackenzie King&apos;s attitude reported in telegramNo. 713, dated the 26th November, 1939, was probably only temporary. He recalled that there had been considerable discussion on this very point at the previous meeting of the War Cabinet.If any hint had been given by the High Commissioner thatMr- Mackenzie King was likely to revert to his earlier attitude, the&apos;message epntained in telegram No. Ill cduid have been drafted in. different-terrngj&apos;     &apos; . &apos; *The Wa^ Cabinet agreed:-To&quot; defer&apos; consideration of this matter, pending the receipt -of thefttf^rtej^^r       rfferr&amp;i^ia
Supply ofAsm&amp;ments.(previous reference:WM. (39) 98thConclusions,Minute 9.)G. r&amp;3 Saereicii, A dhaac-jA ZAaALV3 at r-wa,-the discussion .ca !ttoB supply-of zi-iSES3i:5&apos; amake.... A further decision&apos; by&quot;-, the&apos;&apos; War. Cabhasii aaadd nad, hethought,- be&apos;&apos; required until- a report had been received faaaaMrajfixonj .whO; wa^:npwdin Yugoslavia^ :He understood from the Minister of Supply that the FrenchGovernment might be expected to take a very similar view to purown regarding the Yugoslav action in declaring a Governmentmineral monopoly, and particularly in relation to the copper outputof the Mine de Bor.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Threat to finland.(previous reference erence:W.M. (39) 96thConclusions,Minute 7.)Attitudetowards the united kingdom.trade negotiations.(previous reference erence:W.M. (39) 92ndConclusions,Minute 10.)Arrival ofSovietIcebreaker inBaltic.7. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs informed hiscolleagues that he had discussed the Soviet-Finnish situation theprevious day with the Soviet Ambassador. M. Maisky had described the attitude of the Finnish Government as unreasonable. He had said that the Soviet authorities had established beyond doubt thatthe Finns had shelled Russian territory.M. Maisky had gone on to complain that it appeared to be british policy to obstruct the Soviet Government in every part ofthe world. The Foreign Secretary said that he had done nis best to disabuse M. Maisky of this false view; and it was possible thatM. Maisky, in his turn, would do something to correct the unfavourable opinion which the Soviet Government had formed ofthis country&apos;s attitude. He had invited the Ambassador to produce a single case, in any part of the world, in which we had interfered with Russia&apos;s legitimate interests. M. Maisky had appeared to be surprised at this protest,, although somewhat reassured by it.The Foreign Secretary said that he had also questionedM. Maisky as to the reasons for the delay in replying to our proposalfor the opening of trade negotiations. M. Maisky had replied thathe had still no news from Moscow, but that he would enquireagain and would let the Foreign Secretary know the result.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that a Soviet Icebreakerhad now arrived in the Baltic. A discussion on this point is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Germany.IriterhalSituation.(previous reference:w,M. (39) 93rdConclusions,Minute 9.)8. the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs referred toreports received from a number of different sources of the depressionand discord existing among the Nazi leaders, aid in particular oftheir disappointment at the unhelpful attitude of Soviet Russia.It was now^said;to.:be theiidconvic^^ the-agreementof last August, the:Soviet authorities were fundamentally hostiletoNaaJ^any.., The ^-brought back j^;&amp;rmans who had.loniaweMllfA&quot;&apos;da/. aa&apos; 1&apos; d a -a&quot;&quot;  &apos;
-&apos;%ide-had-;;achieved any imporjtant military success by the-sfMhgyra the&quot; ?war wasdlikely; to peter -out; owing to lack of-resourced &quot;on- bothsides. Mr. psborue had protested against this; and had explainedthat the British Empire possessed vasfr^u^^ to drawupon^ The spring of 1940 would see our military strength at afar higher level than now. .v\ -1 Another repbrt, which was to the effectthat, if Germany were to ihyadtedHotiahd^or Belgium, the GermanGeneral Staff expected i;he French to invade Germany viaSwitzerland. Swiss sources had also provided yet another reason,in the shape of the unsatisfactory attitude of the Soviet Govern-merit, for the German decision earlier in the present month toabandon or postpone the invasion of Hbttaridarid Belgium.The Foreign-Secretary said that it would be unwise to paytoo much attention to any of these stories, but that they had acertain cumulative effect.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Koumaraia.Attitude A.,towards the united kingdom.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 93rdConclusions,Minute 11.)9. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew theattention of his colleagues to Bucharest telegram No. 770, dated the25th November, in which Sir Reginald Hoare reported that the newRoumanian Prime Minister was reputed to be friendly to thiscountry. The Germans were said to be correspondingly dis-appointed. Now, as before, however, Roumanian policy dependedmainly on King Carol.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.France. 10.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs referred tieEeaction of telegram No. 878 from Paris, dated the 25th November. Sir RonaldFrench public Campbell&apos;s appreciation of the French attitude towards the waropinion to an(l war aims showed, on the whole, a very satisfactory position,German It was inevitable that a certain strain should have been imposed on propaganda. the French temperament by months of inaction, and by the(Previous&apos; persistent attempts of. the German propaganda machine to divideEeference: France from:England. So far, however, these attempts had signallyW.M. (39) 55th  failed, arid the country was united and resolute. conclusions, Sir Ronald Campbell realised the difficulty of damping; downMinute 9.)&apos;      public discussion on war aims in the United Kingdom. . Never--theless, fear persisted in France that we were likely to insist:upona peace which would not contain what the. French considered&amp;i      -   :   adequate&quot; political and military guarantees ag&amp;inst furthef GerhiahA -;--:&apos;--i^pij^bifc:&apos;;-: Any official or/sel^i^d^ialdBrijbiidi&quot; declaration which- Agavesubstance to such ^ dieter-i miriatiori to prosecute&apos;the war to a successful conclusion.      r.:.A&quot;A.&apos;&apos;,       -       The War Cabinet
? of Enemy Exports.

Protest by the Japanese Government. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 94th Conclusions, Minute 11.)

 11. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affaires said that a number of neutral. Powers had protested more on less vigorously against our decision to seize exports of German origin on the high seas. The strongest protest he had so far received had been that made on the previous day by the Japanese Ambassador.

 The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, according to a Press Report, the Japanese Official Spokesman had stated that an assurance had been given by the Ministry of Economic Warfare that there would b e  no interference with exports from Germany in Japanese ships.

 The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs undertook to enquire into the matter.

 The War Cabinet took note of the above discussion.



The Far Eastern Situation. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 96th Conclusions, Minute 8.)

 12. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he had seen the American Ambassador on the previous day, and had discussed with him the possibility of reaching a satisfactory settlement of the Tientsin incident, and our general policy of seeking improved relations with Japan. Mr. Kennedy had made no objection to our policy and had undertaken to put our views before Mr. Roosevelt, during his forthcoming visit to the United States. Mr. Kennedy had emphasised how important it was that we should keep Mr. Roosevelt informed of the way our minds were moving in regard to the handling of the Far Eastern situation.

Tientsin silver question.

 The Foreign Secretary invited the attention of his colleagues to a telegram (No. 799 to Tokyo, dated the 28th November) in which he had authorised Sir Robert Craigie to settle the Tientsin silver question on the lines which he (the Foreign Secretary) had indicated to the Cabinet on the previous day. He could not help thinking, however, that Sir Robert was rather sanguine in thinking that an early settlement could be secured on these lines.

 The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.



United States. Effect on public opinion of our restriction of imports from United States. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 67th Conclusion, Minute 18.)

Mr. Kennedy&apos;s forthcoming visit to the United States.

 13. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the American Ambassador had impressed upon him that, while American public opinion would understand that this country had to impose restrictions upon American trade, the manner in which such restrictions were imposed was of the utmost importance. Mr. Kennedy had said that every such restriction was liable to leave behind a pocket of discontent which might react against us if and when a time should come when we should require a further degree of assistance from the United States.

 Several members of the War Cabinet reported that, in Mr. Kennedy&apos;s opinion, the prestige of the Government now stood higher than some weeks ago, and that the country was more solidly than over behind the Government. It was thought that Mr. Kennedy would give an encouraging report of affairs in this country to President Roosevelt on his forthcoming visit to the United States.

 The War Cabinet took note of this statement.


0Mmm--4.    A&quot; (3 lL&quot;f S Or    c:b&apos;        ,       &apos;     z       &apos;  &apos;Mr. Attlee . would&apos; make a,&apos;.formal; request.\ in -Parliampiat ,t&amp;at.. j3- &quot;CCji la. . L&apos;eaA li &quot;jh: cl Sis &apos;z    ^ c  Lh  -j.- r  : - rtussIhinistry o- Si&apos;: bfy ejections.  Fie (the L: i4m j M it is.  )that some-of  us colleagBes viewed wi&apos;w hisfayou-r bae Asa of aSecret/BessioiE: -His- own viewpon seSestiots,&apos; be-cAser, was that itwdhM fee difficult: to :,refase a demand -1oA a- Secret Session; for the.discussion of the particular topic suggested, and that, if the presentdemand were agreed-to, the Government would be in a stronger-position to resist; further demands of. a like nature.   He had consulted the Chief Whip, who shared his views.In discussion, it was urged, first, that if this particular requestwere agreed to, it would he difficult to refuse requests for furtherSecret Sessions-for example, there would probably be a furtherdemand for a Secret Session in the House of Lords to discuss war aims -and, secondly, that the Government supporters. would bebehind the Government in refusing the present request.The Prime Minister pointed out that, because the government might see fit to agree that there was sufficient case for holding aSecret Session of the House of Commons to discuss a particulartopic such as the Ministry of Supply, it did not follow that it wouldbe necessary to acquiesce in a demand for a Secret Session in the lords to discuss some quite different topic. Such a demand couldbe left to be considered when it was made.The general view of the War Cabinet was in favour of agreeing to the demand for a Secret Session of the House of Commons forthe specific purpose of discussing Ministry of Supply questions.It must be clearly understood, however, that the object of a secret session was not to enable the Government to furnish very secret information. Indeed, the Minister replying to the Debate wouldhave to exercise great circumspection with regard to the informa-tion which he furnished to the House, and he would not be expectedto disclose information as to, for example, monthly rates, ofproduction. Indeed, one of the main reasons which had been urgedin favour of a Secret Session was that it would give Members anopportunity of bringing to the notice of the Government, withoutpublicity, matters in regard to which they had grounds for believing that the position was not satisfactory.The War Cabinet agreed: That in the event of the Leader of the Opposition in thecourse of the Debate that afternoon asking for a secret session of the House of Commons to discuss matters relating to the Ministry of Supply, the Prime minister should accede to this request.Richmond Terrace, 8.W.1,November 28, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
