<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/60/18 images: 156-163</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HilS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTDOUBLE TAXATION DISCUSSIONS WITH THE UNITED STATES.MY colleagues will be interested to know the position reached in thediscussions which have been in^p^ogre&apos;sT&quot;&apos;i&apos;c7wsonTe time between officials of theUnited Kingdom and United States Governments on the subject of doubletaxation. I attach a Memorandum which summarises the results of the talks onthis highly technical subject.2. Officials of the two Governments have now subject to the approval ofthose Governments reached general agreement on all points and I now proposethat a formal Agreement should be drafted and concluded on the lines indicatedin the Annex to this Paper. The Agreement will have the status of a treaty and will require ratification by the United States Senate and legislation in thiscountry to amend the taxation law. I should propose, if the Treaty can be concluded shortly, to include the necessary legislation in the forthcomingFinance Bill.3. My colleagues will observe that the proposals amount to a comprehensive scheme for the elimination of double taxation between the two countries and willbe of substantial benefit to British traders operating in the United States. I need invite particular attention to two special points only :-- -(a) We had aimed to secure the agreement of the United States authoritiesto the total elimination of their &apos;&apos; Withholding Tax &apos;&apos; on dividendspaid to United Kingdom holders, or at any rate its reduction to10 per cent, (the rate applying to payments to Sweden) in return forour waiver of the charge to British Sur-tax on dividends going to a united States resident from the United Kingdom. For the reasons give in paragraph 15 of the Annex this has not proved possible; butI am satisfied that what is now proposed represents a reasonablebargain from our point of view. Its reasonableness depends in part5however, on the relation between the rates of taxation in the twocountries and it is therefore to be provided that the United Statesrate of withholding tax on dividends paid to the United kingdom will be subject to review after two years.(b) As indicated in paragraph 17 of the Annex we shall have, after theconclusion of this Treaty, to consult with the Dominions to see howfar it may be desirable, in the light of it, to amend our existing arrangements.with them. I am taking steps to keep them informed of what is afoot before conclusion of the Treaty with the UnitedStates. Moreover, the provisions made in legislation for the relief of trading profits from double taxation will be so drawn as to enablethe relief to be extended as may prove expedient to other countries,so that all British concerns trading abroad can be relieved from theincubus of double taxation.Printed for the War Cabinet.  January 1945.SECRET.W.P. (45) 1.1st January, 1945.Copy No.war memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.J. A.Treasury Chambers, S.W.I.1st January, 1945.[28927]b
ANNEX.Memorandum on the subject of the proposed Double Taxation Treaty withthe United States.Discussions with United States Representatives.1. Discussions have taken place between the Board of Inland Revenue and representatives of the United States Government with the object of drawing upproposals for a Treaty to relieve incomes and estates from the double burden oftaxation where these incomes and estates are liable to both British and UnitedStates taxation. The Foreign Office and the Board of Trade have been consultedduring the discussions. The discussions have extended over the whole field of income taxation (including Income Tax, Sur-tax and Excess Profits Tax) andalso to Estate Duty. The United States taxes dealt with include the Normal tax and Sur-tax on corporations, the Normal Tax and Sur-tax on individuals, the victory Tax, the Excess Profits Tax and the Estate Duty; social security taxes and taxes imposed by individual States lie outside the proposals.The Problem of Double Taxation.2: Double taxation occurs in the income field if tax is levied by both thecountry where the income arises (the country of &quot; origin &quot;) and the country wherethe person entitled to the income resides (the country of &quot;residence&quot;). TheUnited States and the United Kingdom charge tax on both the &quot;origin&quot; andthe &quot; residence &quot; basis and double taxation therefore occurs Whenever a person resident in one country has income arising in the other. In the field of EstateDuty double taxation arises if both the country in which the property is situateand the country in which the deceased person was domiciled levy Estate Duty.3/ From the point of view of British industry the most important case of double taxation is that of the British concern trading in the United States.Such a concern pays United States tax on the profits made in the United Statesand British tax on the balance of profits left after payment of the United Statestax. The United States concern which trades in the United Kingdom is in amore favourable position because the United States law already contains a unilateral provision for relief in respect of this double taxation. Subject tocertain limitations the United States trader who pays United Kingdom IncomeTax on profits made in the United Kingdom is allowed a credit of the UnitedKingdom tax against the United States tax chargeable on the same profit.4. The main classes of ineome, other than trading profits, liable to doubletaxation are interest, royalties (patent, copyright, &amp;c), dividends, salaries and pensions.From all dividends, interest and royalties which are paid from the UnitedStates to a person resident abroad a Withholding Tax of 30 per cent, is deductedexcept when the income goes to a person resident in Canada, when the rate is15 per cent., or Sweden, when the rate is 10 per cent. In the case of dividends,the 30 per cent, is deductible from the actual dividend payable by the UnitedStates corporation and no account is taken of the fact that the corporation hasitself paid tax, which is in practically all cases at the rate of 40 per cent.All dividends, interest (except interest on certain Government securities) androyalties paid from the United Kingdom to the persons abroad are subjected todeduction at source at the standard rate of 10s. in the   (i.e., 50 per cent.).Methods of Eliminating Double Taxation.5.   The two principal methods of eliminating double taxation are (a) restriction of the tax charge so that either the country of residence or thecountry of origin, but not both, charge tax;(b) both countries continue to charge tax, but the country of residence allowsas a deduction against its tax the tax which is charged in the country of origin.For certain types of income the former method of relief is more suitable; for others, the second method is more suitable or may be the only practicable method.
Shipping and A ir Transport and A gencies.6. In the case of shipping and air transport and. agencies it is proposed toadopt the first method explained in the previous paragraph. There is already inexistence a Shipping Income Tax Agreement with the United States, under whichthe income derived by United Kingdom shipping concerns from ships registered in the United Kingdom is exempt from United States Income Tax, with a reciprocal provision exempting from United Kingdom Income Tax the profits of american shipping concerns. This arrangement will be extended to aircraft, sothat British concerns operating aircraft registered in the United Kingdom willbe exempt from United States tax, and United States concerns operating aircraftregistered in the United States will be exempt from United Kingdom tax. In thecase of concerns in one country operating agencies in the other country, i.e., sellingthrough agents who have not the power to negotiate contracts except at fixed prices, no tax will be charged by the country in which the agency is situate.Other Trading Profits.7. For trading profits other than those referred to in the previous paragraph the second method of relieving double taxation is proposed. as explained in paragraph 3 the United States already give their own concerns relief on this basis in respect of profits arising in the United Kingdom, and it is nowproposed that the United Kingdom should give relief to United Kingdomconcerns operating in the United States, whether through a branch or subsidiarycompany on the same basis. i.e., a deduction will be allowed from the British taxof the United States tax payable in respect of the profits arising in United States.Film Companies.8. The particular case of the film industry was specially considered. TheUnited Kingdom charges American film companies only in respect of the profits ofthe distribution or the exhibition of films in the United Kingdom. The filmrentals payable by distributors in this country to film-producing companies in theUnited States are regarded under our law as not representing income, but as grosspayments which include the cost of producing the films as well as the profit on production. The United States, on the other hand, treat as royalties all payments which leave the United States in respect of British films, and unless the Britishfilm-producing company has a branch in the United States (so that it can beregarded as trading in. the United States) the United States charge the 30 percent. Withholding Tax on the gross payment without regard to the costs ofproduction of the film in the United Kingdom. Where the British producingcompany is regarded as trading in the United States it is allowed a propor-tionate deduction in respect of the costs of production. Thus even in this casethe United States charge the profits from the production of the film in the UnitedKingdom as well as the profits of distribution and exhibition in the United States.The United States are prepared to follow the British rule and charge the Britishfilm companies only in respect of the true profit arising from the distributionof films in the United States. This means that where the United Kingdomproducer is not trading as a distributor in the United States no ,tax will becharged or withheld. This will remove a serious grievance of the British film industry.Interest and Royalties.9. In respect of interest and royalties (including both patent royalties andcopyright royalties) it is proposed that only the country of residence shall chargetax. All interest and royalties flowing from the United Kingdom to the UnitedStates will.be paid in full, .i.e., without deduction of tax at the standard rate of10s. in the  , and correspondingly, all interest and royalties flowing from UnitedStates to United Kingdom will be paid without deduction of the WithholdingTax of 30 per cent. Already the great bulk of interest on British government securities going to persons abroad is exempt from British tax and is paid in full.Under the proposals if a British concern borrows in the United States the UnitedStates lender will have to pay only the tax due to his own country. Similarlya British author drawing copyright royalties from United States will have topay only British tax.[28927] b2
Dividends.10. In the case of dividends it is proposed that the United States will reducethe rate of Withholding Tax from 30 per cent, to 15 per cent, (the rate in forcein respect of payments to Canada). The special rate of 10 per cent, which is applied to payments to Sweden has an historical background^ the rate havingbeen frozen at 10 per cent, as part of a treaty at a time when no higher rate was in existence for the rest of the world. It is doubtful how long this specialrate will continue; the United States representatives indicated that a lower rate than 15 per cent, could not be considered as they regarded it as a certainty thatthe United States Congress would not ratify any Double Taxation Treaty if it contained a rate lower than 15 per cent, (the Canadian rate). It will be observedthat under these proposals the effective rate of United States tax on corporationprofits distributed as dividends to a United Kingdom resident amounts to49 per cent, made up of the Corporation Tax of 40 per cent, plus the WithholdingTax of 15 per cent, on the amount remaining after payment of the CorporationTax (i.e., 15 per cent, of 60 per cent.). This is roughly equal to the 50 per cent,tax deducted at source from British dividends going to a United States residentand as part of the agreement the United Kingdom will forego any further charge(i.e., Sur-tax) on these latter dividends.11. With the United States Withholding rate reduced to 15 per cent, theUnited Kingdom will then allow residents in the United Kingdom a credit inrespect of both the Corporation Tax and the Withholding Tax. Correspondinglythe United States will allow residents in the United States a credit in respect ofthe tax deducted at source from dividends paid by British companies.Income from Employment.12. Income from Government employment will be taxed only by theemploying Government and this will apply to Government pensions as well as government salaries. In the exceptional case of British subjects employed bythe American Government in the United Kingdom, however, British Income Taxwill be payable and, conversely, American subjects employed by the BritishGovernment in the United States will be liable to United States Income Tax.As regards employment other than Government employment, the country inwhich the income is earned will charge tax but any pension will be charged bythe country in which the pensioner resides.Capital Gains.13. So long as the United Kingdom does not treat capital gains as incomethe United States will exempt from United States Capital Gains Tax any gainsof a resident of the United Kingdom or of a United Kingdom company arisingfrom the sale or exchange of capital assets provided the resident or the company is not engaged in a trade or business within the United States.Exchange of Information.14. The exchange of information between the Tax Authorities of the twocountries has always ranked as one of the most important elements in any DoubleTaxation Treaty entered into by the United States. The carrying out of theproposed Double Taxation Relief provisions necessitates an automatic exchangeof information in respect of many items of income. For example, the exemption of interest and royalties in the country of origin necessitates the certificationby the country of residence that the recipient is resident therein and liable toits tax. Similarly, information will have to be exchanged in respect of dividends.In the case of branch profits, information is necessary to prevent fraud andavoidance and to ensure that whatever the actual book figures between the branchand the head office, the branch profit is assessed to tax on a basis representingthe &quot; arm&apos;s length &quot; profit, which would have been made if the branch had been completely independent, The two Revenue Administrations will also have toco-operate for the prevention of fraud and avoidance where individuals enterinto artificial transactions designed to reduce their tax liability. It will be a specific provision, however, that any information furnished will be treated assecret and will not be disclosed to any person other than those engaged in the assessment and collection of tax and will not include information that woulddisclose any trade secret or trade process.
Estate Duty.15. It is proposed that relief from Estate Duty shall be provided by way ofa credit given by the country in which the deceased person was domiciled inrespect of the tax paid in the country where the property is situate. The UnitedStates law of situs differs materially from that of the United Kingdom and itis proposed to draw up common rules of situs for the purpose of the Treaty.Under these rules, all securities (whether registered or bearer) of a United Statescorporation will be regarded as situate in the United States and correspondinglyall securities of a British company will be regarded as situate in the UnitedKingdom.Life of Treaty.16. It is proposed that the Treaty shall be for five years certain and continue thereafter subject to a year&apos;s notice, but that the Withholding rate of15 per cent, should be fixed for a period of two years and be subject to review at the end of that period.Effect on Double Taxation A rrangements in the Empire.17. The Double Taxation Provisions proposed between the United Kingdomand United States differ substantially from the existing provisions which obtainwithin the Empire both as regards Income Tax and Estate Duty and it willbe necessary to consult with the Dominions with a view to seeing to what extentexisting arrangements may call for amendment.




</content>
</cab>
