<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/167/0 images: 117-120</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s  Government.]                 Printed for  the Cabinet.  May 1924.CONFIDENTIAL.CABINET.    I CIRCULATE  to my colleagues for their consideration the draft of a letter which I propose to address to the secretary-general of the League of Nations givingthe views of His Majesty&apos;s Government on the Draft Treaty of Mutual Assistancesubmitted to the Powers by the Assembly of the League.     Draft Letter to the Secretary-General of the League of Nations,  Geneva.Sir,                                             Foreign Office, May   ,  1924.    HIS Majesty&apos;s Government have examined with the utmost care the report ofthe Third Committee of the Fourth Assembly, the resolution of the Fourth Assemblyof the League of Nations and the report for 1923  of the Temporary Mixed Commis-sion on the reduction  of armaments, together with the other documents enclosed inyour letter of the 25th October, 1923.  They desire to place on record their apprecia-tion of the prolonged  and exhaustive investigations which have been made  into theimportant subject of treaties of mutual assistance as a step towards the reduction orlimitation of armaments.              *    2. There  is no question to which His Majesty&apos;s Government attach greater importance than the reduction or limitation of armaments, for they recognise that,as stated in article 8 of the covenant, the question  is closely bound up with the main-tenance of peace,  which is the principal object of the League of Nations.  For this very  reason  they  hold that any measures designed to bring about the reduction orlimitation of  armaments  must  be  subjected to  the  most  careful scrutiny beforeadoption.  No greater calamity to the cause which they have at heart can be imagined.than that any scheme adopted by the League should, when submitted  to the test ofreality, fail owing to  defects which ought  to have been foreseen in advance.  It is vital,  therefore, that before the League of Nations takes the responsibility of making.any recommendation  to its  members  it  should satisfy  itself  that the schemerecommended, is in all respects reliable and  effective.    3. Out of the twenty-six nations whose replies are published with the report ofthe Temporary Mixed Commission, only a very small number are able to express.unqualified acceptance of the principle of resolution 14 adopted at the Third Session.of the Assembly, which fornis the basis of the reports now under consideration.  The.objections to the  various proposals  for treaties of mutual  guarantee  or assistance which have been considered by the League are to be found in the report of the ThirdCommittee itself,  as well as in the reports of experts and the opinions of Govern-ments included.in the documents circulated to members of the League. From thesedetailed  criticisms  there  emerge certain  objections of principle which up to  thepresent time do not appear to have been adequately met.    4. The main  criticisms of the proposed treaty fall under two heads, which maybe expressed in an interrogative form: Are the guarantees contained therein sufficientto justify a State  in reducing its armaments?  Are the obligations to be undertaken.towards other States of such a nature that the nations of the world can conscientiouslyengage to carry them out ?    5. In regard  to the first group of criticisms,  it is generally conceded that if atreaty  of mutual  assistance is to prove effective in bringing about  a reduction ofarmaments,  its stipulations must be such that the parties  thereto can assume withabsolute confidence not only that in the contingencies for which it provides it will beJ. R. M.2190  [11616]
brought into operation with certainty, but also that it will effectually accomplish its purpose.    6. The effectiveness of the scheme will be seen to depend to a considerable extent on the ability of the Council of the League to determine by unanimous vote of all members not concerned in the dispute which nation is the aggressor.  This difficult question has to be settled within  a period of four  days from the notification ofhostilities to the secretary-general.   It is unnecessary  here to deal at length with thedifficulties which might confront the council in reaching agreement  on such a pointwithin the stipulated time, or the likelihood that unanimity might never be reached at all on a really controversial issue, since these considerations are fully discussed inthe documents  circulated to  the  various Governments.   In  this connection  the&quot;Commentary on the definition of a  &quot;case of aggression,&apos; &quot; drawn up by a specialcommittee of the  Temporary  Mixed Commission,  in  collaboration  with certain technical members of the Permanent Advisory Committee, is of great interest.  Thecommentary does not provide a solution of the difficulty. It is stated therein morethan once that no satisfactory definition of what constitutes  an &quot;act of aggression&quot;could be drawn up.   Consequently, the report does not provide that element ofcertainty and reliability which is essential if the League  of Nations is to recommend the adoption of the treaty by its members as a basis for reduction in armaments.    7. Another important objection of principle is the long delay which is liable to occur^ before the forces at the disposal of the League of Nations can be brought into effective operation against an aggressor State.   It is  not until after the determina-tion by the council of the question which State is the aggressor, which is likely to occupy the whole of the four  days permitted by the draft treaty, that the council canbegin to take the necessary steps for bringing pressure, whether military or economic,to bear on the aggressor.  Economic pressure is admittedly slow in operation.  Asregards military pressure, all the technical experts who  have advised  the organs ofthe League on the subject are agreed that no military assistance can  be consideredimmediate and effective unless it be given in accordance with a  prearranged plan.It is  obvious,  however, and was recognised by  the Third Committee of the FourthAssembly, that in the case&apos; of a general treaty of assistance plans can rarely be pre-arranged.  They would, therefore, have to be drawn up*, after the question which wasthe aggressor State had been  determined,  by the naval, military or  air  officersdesignated by the- Council of the League to command  the international forces.  Theexperience or  the recent world-war does not justify the  assumption that where theforces of several nations are  involved the immediate acceptance, much less the rapidexecution, of plans of operations can with certainty be counted on.   The possibilitywill always exist that the States most favourably situated for providing the necessaryforce may at  a given moment  not be  in a position to do so, owing to commitmentselsewhere, the state of public opinion,  or the political  condition of the country at thetime.  The  appointment of  the higher command will  itself  involve delay.  Thecouncil will have great difficulty in reaching a unanimous  decision, for no nationplaces its troops under a foreign command without very careful consideration. Asystem which involves prolonged delays before the first&apos; step  in  bringing militarypressure to bear on an aggressor nation can be taken does not reach  that standard ofeffectiveness which is essential.    8.  The necessary  measures to  carry the general  guarantee   into effect are,moreover, made1 dependent upon the explicit consent of each individual State whichmay be called upon to render assistance as a permanent or ad hoc member of thecouncil.   This, consideration can but  strengthen His  Majesty&apos;s  Government in theview  that the guarantee afforded  by the draft  treaty is so precarious that noresponsible Government will  feel justified in consenting to any material reduction ofits armaments in. return.  If,, as His Majesty&apos;s Government, feel convinced, this isthe case,, the- whole object of the treaty is lost and&apos; its conclusion is objectless.  HisMajesty&apos;s  Government,  indeed, go  further.   They  are persuaded,  after careful examination of the; draft scheme, that, if the obligations  created  by the treaty bescrupulously carried out,, they  will: involve an. increase  rather than a decrease inBritish a;armaments-.. The report of the Temporary Mixed  Commission: for 1922 statedthat, &quot; in the case of armed, assistance&apos;, certain, forces,  such as aircraft and warships^are the most readily available,  and therefore the most  likely to be asked for and to be effective in the initial.stages-of the war.&quot;  It is; the considered opinion of the british naval Staff that, a treaty such, as is proposed willi, if properly carried out, necessitatean increase in the.-British: naval forces.  His Majesty ^Government cannot avoid the belief that the position will be the same in other countries,
    9.- It was owing to the recognition of the defects inherent in any general treatyof mutual assistance that the proposal was made to superimpose on a general treatya system of partial treaties between groups of countries.  It has been urged against such partial treaties that  their conclusion by one group of States is likely to bringabout the formation of competing groups, and that the result will be a reappearanceof the former system of alliances and counter-alliances, which in the past has provedsuch a serious menace to the peace of the world.  The proposal to meet this objectionby bringing the partial treaties under the control of the League does not overcome thedifficulty, particularly so long as important nations remain outside the League, andHis Majesty&apos;s Government cannot but recognise the  force of the above criticism.    10. A further objection to the scheme for partial treaties to be embodied in thetreaty of mutual assistance is the opening that would be afforded for conflict betweenthe Council of the League  and individual Governments.  Under article 4 of the draft treaty it will be the duty of the council to decide which of  two belligerents is the aggressor.  Under article 8, States parties to a partial treaty will be at liberty todecide the point for themselves before it is  decided  by the council.  The possibilityof disagreement between  the council  and States between which a partial treaty isoperative is one which cannot be contemplated with  equanimity.    11. The  obligations involved  in the proposed treaty  are of such a nature that several  of the nations whose opinions  are forwarded with the  report of  theTemporary Mixed Commission have been unable to accept them.  In this connection,His  Majesty&apos;s Government desire to draw particular attention to the following extract  from  a letter to the secretary-general of the League from the Government ofCanada, dated the 19th June, 1923 :          &quot;It is intended  that the obligation to render assistance shall be limited     in principle to those  countries situated in the same  part of the globe.  While     Canada is situated in the North-American Continent, she is a nation  forming     part of  the British Empire,  and it seems difficult  to devise a scheme which     would give due effect to these conflicting considerations.   In any case,  it seems    very unlikely  that the Canadian people in the  present circumstances would be     prepared to consent  to any agreement binding Canada to give assistance as     proposed to other nations, and the Government therefore does not  see its way     to a participation in  the Treaty of  Mutual Guarantee.&apos;&apos;     12. The  draft treaty further appears  to involve an undesirable extension ofthe functions of the Council of the League.  Under article 16 of the covenant thecouncil  can only recommend action.  By article 5 of the draft treaty the council are authorised to decide to adopt various measures.   Thus the council would become an executive body with very large powers,  instead of an advisory body.  In any event,the Council of the League  is a most inappropriate body to be entrusted with thecontrol of military forces in operation against any particular State or States.     13. The  draft treaty virtually amounts to an  expansion  of article 10 of thecovenant of the League in  its most stringent  and now discarded interpretation.  In sofar as membership of the League involved participation in  it, the treaty would form aninsuperable barrier to the entry of the  United States of  America into  the  League.The objections entertained by that country to article 10 of the covenant, stringentlyconstrued, are well known.     14. For the reasons which have been enumerated, the draft treaty,  in  the eyes of His Majesty&apos;s Government, holds out no serious prospect of advantage sufficientto compensate  the world  for the  immense  complication  of international relations which it would create, the uncertainty of the practical effect of its clauses,  and the consequent difficulty of conducting national  policy.     15. His  Majesty&apos;s Government, therefore,  support the  view  of  the ThirdCommittee of  tlie  Fourth  Assembly that  the  adoption of the  text  included intheir report  cannot  be recommended.   They  are,  however,  far from  admittingthat  the careful  study  of  these questions  has  been  fruitless.   The  years ofpatient  investigation  which  have   been  devoted  to  this  subject   by  thevarious  organs  of  the   League are  themselves  a  proof  of  the  desire  ofnations, members  of  the League, to find  a solution  to the  difficult question of reduction and limitation  of armaments.   This sentiment finds strong expressionin  practically  all   the  replies  of  the  various   nations  published  with  thereport  of the  Temporary  Mixed  Commission.   If  this  study has  not so  farresulted in the submission of a draft treaty of mutual assistance in an acceptableform, the reports  which  have been under consideration  nevertheless contain some
encouraging  and suggestive  passages  as to other lines of enquiry  which might befollowed with  useful results.  Among these may be mentioned, the possibility ofdefining zones of demilitarisation between States, and, more particularly, the advancewhich has been made in South and Central America in the direction of limitationof armaments.   In this connection also mention may be made of the recommendationsof the Washington Conference, which  have now been carried into effect.    16. His Majesty&apos;s Government feel that it is on the above lines that the questionof reduction of armaments should be  pursued,  rather than on the  lines of treaties of mutual guarantee.   They  emphasise two  general  considerations which haveweighed considerably  with  them.   In the  first  place, these treaties are sure tointroduce some considerable complexity into  the already delicate relations and workof the League  of Nations, and further, such treaties bring into  the foreground ofthe provisions  for peace a scheme which  is only a modification time  may proveit to be only a  slight modification&apos; of the policy of alliances  with all its inevitablepolitical and armament consequences;  in other words, they do not in reality change the means by which nations have sought security.  The real force of the Leagueis moral rather than material.  The policy  of the League, which has been createdessentially to provide  forms of security against war other  than military, should&apos;aim  at the elimination  of causes of  friction  between nations,  the settlement onequitable lines of long-standing differences, the  prompt consideration and&apos; publicventilation of  disputes before they have reached an acute stage,  and the seizingof opportunities which its success in these respects gives to diminish armaments.

</content>
</cab>
