<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/167/0 images: 121-121</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 I j^TWs-Document is the Property of His  Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.] &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot; ^?&apos;\ !  0    (24))&quot;^))             Printed for the Cabinet.&quot;confidential.THE PKIME MINISTER,    ALTHOUGH 1 need not trouble you  with all the details of my two hours&apos;conversation with Rakovski, we came to certain decisions with which I think youought to be acquainted:     1. Bessarabia,  Eastern Galicia, Memel, the  Danube  Commission and theStraits. On these  questions,  especially the  first, he  enlarged  at  some length.I said that none of them could be discussed at the conference,  as they all came under multilateral treaties which we have already declared we could  not deal withwithout consultation with all  the  signatories.  If, however, he desired on behalfof his Government to make a declaration as to the attitude of the Soviet Union on each of  these questions, this might be done at a sitting of the conference after  asettlement had  been reached on Anglo-Russian affairs, and we should be preparedto listen to what he had to say.  He  agreed.    2. On  another class of  question he said that he would like an exchange of opinions:   Disarmament (on which, perhaps, he might make observations  withregard to the attitude of the Soviet Union on the League of Nations, although he admitted that on this point public  opinion  in Russia  was not yet ripe), inter-national labour legislation (on which he hoped some formula might be found for common action  on  the  part  of the two Governments), the Island of Wrong el(about which apparently there is some  dispute).  This class of question also,  I said, must be dealt with at a meeting of the conference  after the outstanding questions   between  us had been  settled, and  that  if he furnished us  withmemoranda considered replies on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government would begiven him.    3. Personal Injury Claims. He said that he agreed to a proposal we  madeat the last conference, provided they were dealt with on terms of reciprocity.    4. Property claims he divided  into two categories: Pre-war debts,  that is tosay, bondholders&apos; claims, and private property claims.    With regard to bondholder claims, he said that these were largely  dependenton the  success of the delegation  in raising a loan.  He hoped to get one  of20 millions a year  for three years, and was  in the  course of negotiations  withLloyd&apos;s  Bank and others.  When he suggested  that  the Government shouldguarantee this  loan I  told him that that  would be out of one question and itwould be useless to raise such a point in the conference.   He said  that in  eachcase they would attempt a settlement with  the bondholders, and, failing this, thedispute  would be referred to trie conference.    Private property claims would  be dealt with by means  of  concessions, andthey would negotiate directly with  the parties, concerned.  He hoped that agree-ment might be arrived at in the course of two or three months, and if  there wasno settlement the matter should be referred to the two Governments.    5. Having cleared everything else  out of the way the  war  debts  and inter-vention  claims were the only points left.   He  had not brought up the interventionclaims on any previous  stage as a set-off against any of our other claims.  Heenlarged at very great length on the war  debts, reciting Russia&apos;s sacrifices and losses, and stating that the Russian debt was quite  different in its nature fromthe debts of other nations.   T told him  that it would be perfectly impossible toraise this question in the conference and we should refuse to do so.  After a gooddeal of conversation he agreed to  putting the war debt and intervention claimsaside for the time being, and I assured him that full account would be taken ofRussia&apos;s economic position, and that if a  settlement were reached on all  other points some statement with regard to these two matters might be expected beforethe conclusion of the conference.                                                   ARTHUR PONSONBY.    May 19;. 1924.2203. [1.1622]

</content>
</cab>
