<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/167/0 images: 122-123</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document  is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government. 1       o r                Printed for the Cabinet.  May 1924.SECRET.CP. 311 (24).                                 CABINET.DRAFT TREATY  OF  MUTUAL ASSISTANCE.      NOTE BY THE SECRETARY OF THE  COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL  DEFENCE.    I AM instructed by the Prime Minister to circulate herewith to the Cabinetthe Conclusions of the Committee of Imperial Defence on the subject of Reductionof Armaments and Treaties of Mutual  Assistance,  which were forwarded to theForeign Office and form the basis, so far as military considerations are concerned,of the draft letter to the  Secretary-General  of the League of Nations, recentlycirculated (Paper CP. 309 (24)).                                        (Signed)      M. P. A. HANKEY.    2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,        May 22, 1924.   REDUCTION OF ARMAMENTS AND TREATIES OF MUTUAL ASSISTANCE.     Conclusions of a Meeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence,                        held on April 3, 1924.THE COMMITTEE  agreed-1. To draw attention to the fact that the  Draft Treaty of  Mutual Assistance      communicated by the Secretary-General of the League of Nations, which      is the result of more than two years&apos; continuous exploration of the subject,      is forwarded  &quot; for consideration,&quot;  and  without  a  recommendation in      favour of its  adoption either by the Third Committee of the  Fourth      Assembly  (which carried  out  an exhaustive examination of the Draft      Treaty) or by the Assembly itself.  Further, they desire to point out that      very few of the twenty-six nations, whose comments are circulated with      the Proceedings of the League, have been able to  give unqualified assent      to the principles on which the Draft Treaty is based.2. That after careful examination of the Draft Treaty of the Proceedings of the      League thereon, o,f the views of the Service Departments, and of certain      political considerations pointed out by the Foreign Office and by the Lord      President of the Council  (the representative of the British  Government      on the League of Nations) they are unable to recommend the Draft Treaty      for  adoption by His Majesty&apos;s Government.  Among  the very numerous      objections brought to the notice of the Committee, the following may be      mentioned :       (a.)  The naval, military and air commitments in the case of the British             Empire  would  be  almost  unlimited.  If the obligations  of the            Treaty were scrupulously carried out they would probably involve            an increase rather than a  decrease in our armaments.  In this            connection the Admiralty point out that &quot; the British Navy would            certainly always be the first force to be called upon; in the words            of the Report of the Temporary Mixed Commission for 1922 : &apos; In            the case  of armed assistance, certain forces, such as aircraft and            warships, are the most readily available, ana therefore the most            likely to be asked for and to be effective in the initial stages of the            war/  It is the considered opinion of the Naval Staff that to carry            out the provisions of such a Treaty would, in fact, necessitate an.            increase  in our  naval forces.&quot;  [1 1632189
       (6.) The  provision in Article  5  (b),  that no contracting party situated             in a Continent other than, that in which operations will take place             shall, in principle, be required to co-operate in military, naval or             air operations, is very  difficult of application in the  case of the             British Empire.  This has been pointed out to the League by the             Canadian Government,  who, in their communication of the 19th             June,  1923. further stated that:  &quot; In any  case  it  seems very             unlikely that  the Canadian people in the present circumstances             would be prepared  to consent to any agreement binding Canada             to give assistance as proposed to other nations, and the Government             therefore does not see.its way to a participation in the Treaty of             Mutual Guarantee.&quot;       (c.) As indicated in the documents forwarded by the League  of Nations,             and more particularly in the  &quot; Commentary on  a &apos; Case of             Aggression&apos;&quot; drawn   up  by  a  Special   Committee  of  the             Temporary Mixed  Commission, it has not been  found  possible             to  devise an  adequate  definition  of  what  constitutes  an             &quot; act of aggression.&quot;   The absence  from the  Treaty  of reliable             machinery for determining on the outbreak of hostilities which             State is the aggressor,  introduces into the scheme a fundamental             element of uncertainty.  In the event of hostilities the delay of             four days to be  devoted to the attempt to determine which State             is the aggressor might prove fatal to the efficacy of the  scheme, for             at the beginning of hostilities time is of vital  importance.       (d.) From the military point  of  view a Treaty of  Mutual  Assistance,             having as its object a general reduction of armaments, should fulfil             an essential condition, namely, that the military assistance to be            . rendered should  be effective; to be effective it must be  immediate;             and to be immediate it must be prepared in advance.  It would be             impossible to prepare plans in advance for the despatch of such             forces as might  be required,  or for their  subsequent employment             in the innumerable operations in which it might become obligatory,             under the terms of the Treaty,  to engage.  The elaboration of plans             on the spur of the  moment would be very difficult; the General             Staffs of the countries  concerned would have  to collaborate, and       .      time would be lost.       (e.) Further time would be  lost  in the appointment of the  Higher             Command. The Council of the League would have great difficulty             in arriving at a unanimous decision on this question.  No nation             could agree to place  its troops under  a foreign command without             very careful consideration.       (/.) The cumbrous processes referred  to above would involve so much loss             of time as to  prove  fatal to the military efficiency of the Draft             General  Treaty  of   Mutual  Assistance.    The    system  of             complementary &quot;defensive  agreements  proposed  to  meet  this             criticism has been objected to at the League on the ground  that it             would lead to &quot; a reappearance under that name of  the  former             system of Alliances, which, in the past, has proved such a serious             menace to the peace  of  Europe &quot;  (Report  of Third Committee to             the Fourth Assembly).   No adequate reply has been  given  to this             criticism.       [g.)&apos; The Draft Treaty involves an undesirable extension of the functions             of the Council&quot; of the League.  Under Article  16 of the Covenant             the Council can only recommend action.  By Article 5 of the Draft             Treaty  the Council  are authorised  to decide to  adopt various             measures. Thus the  Council would become an executive body with             very large powers, instead of an advisory body.  In any event the             Council of the League is a most inappropriate body to be entrusted             with  the control of military  forces in  operation  against any             particular State  or States.3. That before any reply is. sent to the League of Nations, the  views of His       Majesty&apos;s  Government  should  be communicated  to the  Dominions and       India, who should be given  an  opportunity of expressing their views.2, Whitehall Gardens, S. IV. 1,       April 3, 1924.

</content>
</cab>
