<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/167/0 images: 143-145</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
OLD  AGE  PENSIONS,-Removal of Thrift DisqualifIcatioruCopy of Letter from the Lord Privy. Seal to the               Prime Ministers(Circulated at the request of the Lord              Privy Seal)0                                               11, Downing Street, S,WU10                                                    23rd May,  1924,        My dear Prime Minister,             I think it right to draw your attention to the        circumstances of last Monday&apos;s debate  on the Money Resolution:ef:isards    brought forward for the purpose of clearing the way for the:173,                            *                  &apos;71,      introduction of the Pensions (Increase) Bill, and the possible1866-1921,    effects on other legislation of the criticisms then levelled        against the Government from all sections of the Houses  %             The Resolution in question embodied the financial aspect        of the concessions which the Government had decided to grant to        pre-war pensioners.   The sum of these  concessions was identical        in amount witfr those which the late Conservative Government had        decided to grant.   This fact did not, however, prevent the        Liberal Party from being reinforced in their criticisms by        practically the whole of the Conservatives including their front        bench.-,   The bulk of the Liberal speakers went to the full   -  -        length of demanding that pre-war pensioners should be placed on        equality with members of their Service retired since the war,        and if the Conservatives did not go quite so far they were        unanimous in declaring that had they remained in power not only        would the Bill have already become law, but that its terms would        have been far more generous than those offered by the Labour        Government,                     -1..
     It is true that ultimately we were able to secure the with-drawal of the Resolution at the price of concessions, the termsof which are; I understand, now being worked out in the Treasury0It remains, however, to be seen whether the revised Resolution,when submitted to the House will be accorded a favourable reception.   On this point I confess I am doubtful, and so faras the Liberals are concerned I think it is clear from CaptainWedgwood Benn&apos;s intervention at the close of the debate thatthey regard themselves entirely free to renew the whole of theircriticisms on the main question when the Resolution is re-.submittedo     Monday&apos;s debate was, it must be admitted, damaging to the prestige of- the Government, and it would have been far more sohad the question at issue been one of first rate politicalimportance3   In such a case we could not,  I think afford to be forced to withdraw our proposals at the dictation of the                          mOpposition on the ground that they were inadequate or niggardly.It is for these reasons that I would urge most strongly thatthe Cabinet should be given a further opportunity to consider in detail our proposals for dealing with the abolition of thethrift disqualification for old age pensioners,  before thepolicy of the Government in this-regard is  announced in theHouse,,   These proposals as they stand undoubtedly constitute agreat advance upon anything hitherto proposed by a Partyactually in Cffice0   It cannot, however,  be denied that theyfall far short of the policy which as a Party we have advocatedin the past,  and to which many individual members are personallypledged.   Both Opposition Parties will undoubtedly throw thewhole weight  of their criticisms on this aspect  of the mattera     If the Cabinet are prepared to accept  the risk and to face the inevitable criticism in Parliament and disappointment inthe country,  well and good, but if I am right In thinking thatthese dangers are too substantial lightly to be  faced,  I would suggest that  the scheme approved by the Cabinet  at the  meeting                           -3m
on the 15th instant should, be referred back to the Treasuryivith a view to seeing whether without undue additional costa plan cannot be devised which would be less open to criticism and which would be more in conformity with the previous publicdeclarations of our Partyc     The Government have repeatedly promised the House ofCommons that our proposals should be brought forward at theearliest possible date, and in view therefore of the urgency of the question I have sent a copy of this letter not only tothe Chancellor of the Exchequer but to Sir Maurice Hankey, sothat it may be circulated to members of the cabinet                     Yours sincerely,                                J,R. CLYNES oThe Right fhpn. J0 Ramsay MacDonald, M,P,

</content>
</cab>
