<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/167/0 images: 162-163</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 Referred toCommittee of Home AffaireBIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).0 A B I N E T.PIERS IN THE HIGHLANDS AND ASTERN,ISLANDS OF SCOTLAND.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY FOR SCOTLAND..     1.;   A situation haa arisen in regard to a pier in theHebrides which raises questions of some importance and difficulty,and I should be glad to have the approval of my colleagues tothe action which I propose to take, -          The pier in question ia Lochboisdale Pier.   It is theprivate property of Lady Gordon Cathcart and serves an extensiveestate belonging to her in South Uist.  It ia of the utmost importance to the residents on that estate, and it cannot be closed, or allowed to fall into such a state of disreoair aato render it unusable -or unsafe, without grave inconvenience tothe locality.         , Despite these facts, the pier has been allowed to fall into disrepair and it haa now been closed by order of theproprietrix, whose attitude ia that she is unable to face theexpense of reetoration, or to continue to run tht riak of claims for damagea which might arise owing to the unsafe condition ofthe structure. -    &apos;      &apos;  ;     2,   The proprietrix looks to the Government to find themoney (about  6,000) for the necessary repairs, and to take overthe responsibility for future maintenance.  She has offered totransfer the pier to the Board of Agriculture - alternatively,ehe is willing to transfer the pier to a local pior authority,if, and when, such an authority is constituted.   Possibly theextreme step of closing the pier has been taken mainly for thepurpoee of bringing the matter to an issue, and forcing theGovernment to give immediate financial assistance.     3.   So far as  he Board of Agriculture are concerned, theyhav* power under the Congested Districts (Scotland) Act, 1B97.to give financial assistance out of the Agriculture (Scotland)Fund, but I am advised that they have no statutory power to takeover the pier.   There ia no power to compel Lady Gordon Cathcartto maintain the pier, or to keeo it open for traffic.   In theaecircumstances, the onlv course in the meantime, if the pier iate be put into a state&quot; of reoair, and reopened for public uaewith the least poaBible delay, is that the Board should make agrant to the propristrix of the cost of repairing the pier,subject to an undertaking on her part that aho will hand overthe pier to a local Pier Authority if and when such an Authorityia established.   Legislation in some form is necessary to theestablishment of such an Authority.CRET.P.319 (24).This/
           This case does not  stand alone, and action upon   it must be taken with full regard to the probable effect in   other  like cases.    There are,  I believe, other estate   piers  in the Western   Highlands and Islands which already   are, or will soon be, in the same position aa Lochboisdale   Pier is now.  In these cases the proprietorsi just as   Lady Gordon Cathcart has done, plead that they are no   longer able to  face&apos; the burden of maintenance&apos;.   The piers   are in a state  of serious and growing disrepair,and sooner   or later the Lochboisdale position must arise in these   cases  also.  Accordinglyt if a Grant is given to Lochboisdale   a number of similar applications mav be expected which could   not well be refused in the    face of such a precedent, and   the total bill  would be very heavy.  Moreover, there are   obvious objections to a course which involves the grant of   public  monies to private individuals  and which makes no   adequate provision lor the future maintenance of the piers   in question.       4.    It appears to me,  therefore, that if (and it   aeempinevitable&quot;in the pressing  emergency) assistance is   given  to Lochboisdale on the lines suggested, it will be   nece3sarv  at the same time to devise a policy which will .  protect the Treasury, and place the burden of pier   maintenance, mainly if not entirely, upon the localities   concerned.             what  is needed is  a power to form cheaply and   expeditiously local pier authorities which would be   authorised to.levy,, either directly or through an existing   rating authority,&apos; a guarantee rate on.owners and occupiers   in the area served by the pier.  Such legislation might   follow generallv the&apos; lines&quot;of the Orkney and Zetland Small   Piers  and  Harbours Act,  1896, with any desirable modifica-   tions.  The authorities set up  under such an Act would be   able to borrow  for capital works on the security of the   guarantee  rate, a rate to which  recourse could also be had   in order to supplement where necessary the revenue -.   available  for maintenance purposes.   This wouldinot, of   course, preclude assistance  being given by the Government   in necessitous  areas out of  any  funds provided&apos;for the   purpose, but it would place  the main burden where it ought   to lie, would ensure ^Local supervision, and would provide   a fund for proper maintenance&quot;.       5,,    I desire,therefore, to receive the sanction of my   colleagues to deal with the  Lochboisdale case in the manner   proposed  in the earlier part of this Memorandum and to   prepare and submit for Cabinet approval legislation on the   lines  indicated above.       6,    The Lord Advocate, the Board of Trade and the   Ministry  of Transport concur in  the terms of this   Memorandum.   The Treasury concur in the proposal for   legislation contained  in the second section of /paragraph 4   of the. Memorandum, but they  think that action in the   Lochboisdale case should be  deferred until such legisla-   tion has  been passed.Scottish  Office,               &apos;M-   Whitehall.  -28th May, 1924.

</content>
</cab>
