<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/167/0 images: 248-249</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS THE  PROPERTY OF  HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).SEC RET.---               0 A B I NET.CP.  337(24).SUMMER  TIME.Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal.     I desire a decision of the Cabinet on the following pointin connection with Summer Time Legislation, which was recentlyraised by the Home Secretary in connection with government business.     My colleagues will recollect that the Cabinet considered this question at its meeting on the 5th March, (Cabinet 18.(24)Conclusion 16), when it was agreed that the necessary legislation should be prepared after the Conference between French and belgian representatives which was then on the point of meeting,and that if&quot; possible the legislation  should be of a permanentform.   The Government have not themselves at present lntro-duced a Bill dealing with this matter, but a Private Bill  onthis subject, introduced by Sir Klngsley-Wood, was given aSecond Reading by the House of Commons and referred to StandingCommittee &quot;A&quot;, where it stands little, if any, chance ofmaking progress this Session,     The Home Secretary recommends that the Government shouldtake over Sir Klngsley Wood&apos;s Bill, and from the point ofview of Parliamentary time I strongly share this view, as  by securing the transfer of Sir Kingsley Wood&apos;s Bill to one ofthe other Standing Committees, which  in that case we could do, we should merely be expediting legislation which we our-selves desire, and should moreover avoid the necessity ofgiving time for a second discussion on the floor of theHouse for the Government Bill which otherwise we should be forced to introduce, the terms of which would be identical with that introduced by Sir Kingsley  Wood.     As regards the Conference held in Paris,, the position isthat the representatives of the other countries concerned,namely, Holland, France and Belgium,  agreed with those ofGreat Britain that recommendations should be made to theGovernments concerned that stops should, be taken for fixingpermanently the period of Summer Time in their respective countries.   All the three Powers represented in Paris are, Iam informed, in fact carrying out the recommendation asregards fixing permanently the dates  for the begining andending of Summer Time, which in each  of these countries can be,and is being, dorse without legislation.   Great Britain istherefore the only one of the four Powers represented at Paristhe Government of which is not at present taking any steps tocarry out the recommendation made on  that occasion.
     In these circumstances I invite the Cabinet to agree in the proposal that the Government should adopt SirKingsley Wood&apos;s Bill, especially in view of the fact thathe has indicated that he would be prepared in that event toaccept any slight modifications which the Home Office may desire in order to bring its provisions into completeconformity with the Paris recommendations.   I realize thatin general there are objections to the Government taking over Private Member&apos;s Bills, especially when they arepromoted by Members of the Opposition Parties.   But in thecircumstances I am  satisfied that this is the proper course to adopt on the present occasion, as by doing so we shallnot only save Parliamentary time but shall be taking thequickest steps to bring the position of this country into conformity with that of the other countries interested inthis matter.JoR. CLYNES.Downing Street, S.W.1, 2nd June, 1924.

</content>
</cab>
