<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/167/0 images: 364-365</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
9 0S4 (J 4mS LOCIIOITT IS TH3 PROPERTY OF KIS BRITABTIC laJHSSTY&apos; S GJ^HHMSTT) .3 C might.          of copy Ho.  s*C A B IB .1 I,Sale of Surplus Amis to Foreign Countries.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.        I desire to take the decision of the Cabinet on two points of interpretation of the Cabinet decision of 15th Aprilrelative to the sale of surplus arms to foreign countries.     1. Messrs. Vickers Limited have a contract with theSoviet Government for the supply of machine guns.  A stcck ofcertain machine gun parts known as Prideaux.Links is held bythe Disposal Department.   Is the sale of these parts to Vickersfor incorporation in the guns to he supplied to Russiaprohibited .by the Cabinet decision?     2.  The Cabinet decision directed the destruction of&quot;suchsuperfluous stocks as had not been or could not he made use of by the Service Departments or disposed of to the Dominions,Colonies, etc.  The decision does not in terms refer to sales to Dominion or Colonial Governments,    The firm of licensed                         &apos;S    &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;dealers in arms, Messrs. A. Fleming &amp; Company, mentioned in theprevious Treasury Memorandum CP. 233 (24), is willing to buysmall arms ammunition and a small quantity of surplus non-militaryrifles for sale in the Dominions hut not necessarily to DominionGovernments.   A draft contract has beeriprep&amp;red with care so asto prohibit re-exportation from the Dominions to foreign des-tinations, and copies would be supplied to the Dominion Governments;sales are under its terms prohibited in Ireland and in Indiaotherwise than to Government.                                                      The
         The question is whether the Cabinet decision of 15thApril intended to permit sales to Dominion and colonial governments only, or whether sales in the Dominions  and Coloniescan be allowedj  subject to strict precautions for the preventionof re-export to Foreign destinations.                                            P.S.TREASURY,  S.V. ,    p.Sth June, 19 24,

</content>
</cab>
