<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/167/0 images: 447-450</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This  Document is the Property of His  Britannic  Majesty&apos;s  Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.SECRET.G.P. 375&apos; (24)CABINET.THE&apos; POSITION  OF INDIANS  IN  KENYA.        MEMORANDUM BY THE&apos; SECRETARY&apos; OF  STATE FOR THE COLONIES;    ON the 12th March the position of&quot; the Government in regard to the white paper (Gmd. 1922) was&apos; considered by the  Cabinet (Paper&apos; CP: 171 (24)), when itwas agreed1 that, pending the arrival of the  Committee to be sent from India, myonly possible attitude was to be guided by the decisions, published in- the white paper:    2. The Committee&apos; from India have arrived,, and  I have1  had meetings withthem, at&apos;which the discussion has heen confined almost entirely to the question of immigration^ into Kenya.  I have just received a letter  from the Chairman of  theCommittee oh other  points,  but I do not anticipate that I shall have- to  consultmy colleagues; with regard to them:    3. On! the- question of immigration the discussion has turned on two  points :first, whether the statistics of the immigration and: emigration&apos; of Indians justifyimmediate  action in regard,to immigration  control;&apos; and,- secondly,-whether/  theeconomic interests&apos; of the Africans necessitate  the control of  immigration in any circumstances.    4&apos;.&apos; On the first point1, it has been found quite impossible  to agree upon anystatistics, of past immigration and emigration of  Indians;  The  figures  for  1922,furnished urgently in reply to a telegram from the Colonial Office  early in  1923,showed a; net emigration  of Indians at the rate  of some  4,000&apos; a year, and it wason these figures that the policy indicated in the White  Paper was primarily based.Just before the White Paper was issued  it was ascertained that these  figurescould; not be  substantiated; but, although  the information  available made  itimpossible to arrive  at&quot; any definite conclusion, it appeared that the immigrationin 1922 and early&apos;in 1923 Was hr fact substantial.    5. The figures for 1923&apos; have since been received from  the  Governor and showa net  increase of 1,642 for the year.  This is for Indians (exclusive of Goans, &amp;c.)entering or leavirigrMombasa&apos;; irrespective of origin  or destination.   For example,the Indian arriving overland from Tanganyika  and leaving Mombasa for Aden is included in the same  way as the Mombasa Indian who  leaves, that  port direct  forBombay, and, conversely, the Indian from South Africa who proceeds to Mombasaand tbence to Uganda is  included&apos; equally with the Indian from Bombay who,  on arrival at Mombasa; remains in Kenyai    6. On their side the Committee have produced figures&apos;taken from the british india Steam  Navigation Company&apos;s lists of passengers between Bombay andMombasa, showing for  deck  passengers of  all races a  net  influx of&apos; 861 in 1923.Similarly, for the month of January 1924; the Governors figures show an entry of846 Indians, the outward figures not  being yet ascertained, while the Committee&apos;s figures show  288 deck passengers  from Bombay to  Mombasa and  312  fromMombasa to Bombay.   In this case it is possible that the great discrepancy is dueto the fact that large numbers of temporary Indian visitors may have arrived  inJanuary from other parts of Africa in connection with the meeting of the  indian national Congress at  Mombasa in that month.    7. It is evident  that so serious - discrepancies between statistics based  onentirely different circumstances must  have a simple explanation, and.it  is not necessary to assume that there has been any failure on  the part of the Colonial[11789]
Government to produce accurate statistics within  the means at their command.But it is, clear that,:while the Indian.Committee V figures, need not be accepted ascompletely representing the position, it is impossible to take action on the strengthof the Colonial figures unless the discrepancy can be explained.    8. With regard to the effect of the immigrant Indian on the economic positionof the native, it. is necessary first of all to explain what has in fact been proposedin regard to control.  It was intended to create an Immigration and  employment department in Kenya, which would inter alia consider what openings there were for immigrants of various classes, having regard to the extent to which thoseopenings could be filled.locally.  There was no question of absolute exclusion, andthe first draft  Ordinance furnished from Kenya made this sufficiently clear.  that draft  was bad in  form, and the Governor was requested to  have it revised.  Thenew draft has  been received, and has been communicated to the Indian Committee.Without going into details, the new  draft is unsatisfactory,  and, indeed, has giventhe Indian Committee the impression that the exclusion of Indian immigrants is,in fact, to be provided for.  The draft Ordinance cannot, of course, be passed as it stands.    9. This point, that there is no question of exclusion, is of the first importance.We are concerned with three classes of immigrants:     (1.) Those suitable for. Minor Clerical Appointments. For these posts Africans           can, and will as quickly as possible, be trained to  take the place which           has hitherto been held by Asiatics.  There  will for  some time be no           question  of  Africans replacing  the  Europeans  or  the  more  highly           trained Indians  in  the higher grade  clerkships in the Government           Service  or elsewhere.   Outside  the  Government Service  there  are           various  clerical posts;  for  example,  in  Indian business  houses  at           Mombasa which trade with India, where  the need for a knowledge of           the. Indian language and methods probably makes the use of Indian           clerks  essential. The Indian Committee  fully  recognise and  support           the training of Africans for clerical posts.    (2.) Artisans  of all Kinds. Very great progress  has already been made, and           is welcomed by the Committee, in the training of  Africans, especially in           the Railway Department, for mechanical work which has  hitherto been           carried out by Indians.   It is  established that the African can be        i  trained to  do a particular job very well, but it remains to be seen  how           long it will take to  fit  him for the general work which must be done           by  an artisan in ordinary  employment, and, for the present, the use of           artisans from outside cannot be  dispensed with.  I may say that  I           have just  received, but not from the Government of Kenya, a proposal           for  assisting  unemployed  British  artisans of various  classes  to           emigrate to Kenya for employment  there.  It is probable that a scheme           of this kind would be of value if machinery already existed for judging           what  immigrants of this class,  whether  European  or Asiatic, were           necessary in order to supplement the  available local supply,  but at this           stage  I cannot  support  a scheme which  is  definitely intended  to           introduce British artisans in preference to  Asiatics.    (3.) Minor Traders. At all stages of  this  controversy the important  part           taken  by the Indian trader as a distributor to the natives and, not less,           as  a  buyer of  native produce has been fully recognised,  and  it will           be  many years before any substantial numbers of native traders come           into existence.  There is  therefore no question of the definite exclusion           of Indians of the trading  class.    (4.) Agriculturists. Under the terms  of the White  Paper  an area  in  the           lowlands of Kenya has been set aside for assignment  to any Indians of           the agricultural class who  may wish  to come in. Judging from past           history, it is improbable that many will wish to take advantage of the           offer, but here again there is obviously no question of exclusion.     (5.)  It is urged by the Committee  that  an Indian Settlement Scheme under           (4) would involve the entry of Indians of subsidiary occupations for the           service of members  of the  settlement.  Here, again, the intention of           the.Ordinance is not to exclude any who may be required.     10. The important  point  is, however, that  under  the  terms of the proposed Ordinance the entry of  immigrants of  any race will be subject to the local supply
being inadequate,:and, in this, matter, the existing Indian population must be a factor of great importance now, and of increasing importance as the  local Indiancommunity grows in the natural course.  It is, for example, not a question whether there should be Indian artisans in the country, but  of whether there are  now asufficient number of Indian artisans in the country, having regard to the extent towhich natives can now take up handicrafts, and the question is not whether Kenyashould be closed to Indians of the trading class, but how far the number of Indian1traders already there is sufficient for the purposes of native trade.    11. It&apos;will,  therefore, be  clear that  the  problem  is  not one of general considerations of whether Indian immigration is good for Africa and the Africansor not, but of the extent to which in various classes of occupations any supplementof the existing  supply is necessary, having  regard, on the one hand, to  the increasing rate of  development of the country, and, on the other hand, to theexisting and growing supply both of native and non-native workers.  It is obvious,too, that  the means do  not  exist for solving the  problem  now,  and  that  theprovision  in the draft Ordinance for setting  up an employment  bureau  whichwould investigate the sufficiency of local resources is of great value.    12. The  policy which I  propose  to adopt  and in which I ask  for  theconcurrence of my colleagues is the following:     (a.) The information  which we now  have is insufficient to prove that the          actual control of immigration is as urgently necessary as the late Govern-          ment considered at the time of the issue of the White Paper, but the          possibility of  control being required in  the  interests of the African          cannot be lost sight of, and the proper course is to endorse the position          taken by Mr. Churchill at the  time of the Wood-Winterton proposals          (p. 8 of the White Paper), where he said that               &quot; throughout the discussions,,with  the India Office I have made it              plain that  my view is  unchanged as  to immigration control, and              that if the danger ever  arises of a  large influx of  Indians  I hold              myself  entirely  free to take any action which may he necessary.&quot; :1    (b.) At the same  time it  is necessary to provide that we should be able to          judge when the necessity has  arisen, without  any of the  doubt as to          statistics which has hampered the  discussions with the Committee,          and for this purpose a statistical  department should  be set  up in          Kenya whose main  duty would be to keep accurate information  for all          races of the  place  of  origin,  occupation  and  destination  of persons          arriving in  Kenya,  with  similar  information  in  the case  of  those          leaving Kenya.   It is understood  that statistics of this  kind are kept          in  the Union of South Africa, and it should  not be difficult for the          Government of Kenya, by consultation with the Union Government, to          set up an organisation of the same kind.    (c;) This  statistical department would  also  be charged with the work of          investigating the economic requirements  of the country in the way of          labour which was to form a part of the duties of the proposed Employ-          ment and Immigration Department.   If this is* done, it will probably          be desirable to proceed  at  leisure with  the  preparation  of a draft          Immigration Ordinance, which can be introduced promptly if at  any          time the danger to the economic progress  of  the  natives  through          uncontrolled  immigration becomes  manifest.   It is clear from  the          experience of the last six months  that the drafting of a satisfactory          measure will require great care.    13. My proposals will not end controversy, and it will be necessary for me inthe first instance to consult the Governor as to their probable reception in Kenya;but they should at all events remove the suspicion that the wholesale  exclusion of indians is contemplated in any quarter;  they should satisfy the very large localbody of opinion which is  genuinely convinced  that the  Indian is retarding  the african ; and they should indicate to those political elements in  Kenya (which areactively anti-Indian that, while His Majesty&apos;s Government are not  prepared tomeet their views, the principle embodied in the White Paper that native interestsmust be paramount will, if necessary, be  applied as firmly  to  the limitation of immigration from India as to any other question. &quot;...&apos;,../-,
    14. I have not lost sight of the importance  of this question in India, and ofthe danger that in present circumstances a law restricting immigration into Kenyamight be followed by pressure, which  the  Government  of India might  find itimpossible to resist,&apos;for a corresponding  law in  India, with serious consequences to British interests there.  That is an additional  reason for postponing legislation in Kenya until we can prove  beyond  all reasonable  dispute that  immigration control is, in fact, necessary in the interests of the Africans.                                                                    J. H:  T.    Colonial Office, July 1924.o

</content>
</cab>
