<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/167/0 images: 451-453</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                          340  x.     (THIS DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S     ___GOVERNMENT .)_-ML                         CABINET,                       Wireless  Services.             (Memorandum  by the  Postmaster general),          (1)   Tho Marconi  Company  have now  accepted,  without     reservation,  the decision of the  Government  that  the  ownership     and^operation of all stations  in  this country for communication     with  the  Empire (including  Canada)  must  be in Government hands,     and state that  they  will  co-operate with the Government in the     operation of  the services in the  Dominions.          (2)   They  have  also  agreed to proceed immediately to erect     short wave directive stations.(commonly  known as  &quot;beam stations&quot;     in Canada, and  in  acoordanoe with the Cabinet decisions I am     arranging with  them  for the erection of  a corresponding     station in this Country,  capable  of extension later to provide     beam  communication with South  Africa, India  and Australia, if     those countries or any of them should wish to adopt this means     of c ommuni cation.          (3)   It  is proposed  that  the  beam  station in this country     should be erected  by the  Company  at cost price, plus  5%     establishment charges  and 10%  profit, subject to  a maximum,     excluding the site,  of  51,658 for the  Canadian  station, if a     publio electrical  supply  is available,  or  57,938 if  a public     supply is not available.  The  maximum cost of each additional     unit  (i.a. the  enlargement  required for  providing communication     with  one  other  Dominion)  will  be   33,472 or   36,117 according     as a  publio supply is  or  is not available.   The  Company to     receive a royalty  of 6k%  on the gross income accruing to the                                                      station
station so long as valid Marconi patents are used in it.   ThoCompany guarantee a spaed of 100 words per minute each way for the following average hours daily throughout the year,namely:-  Canada, 18,  South Africa II,  India 12,  Australia and the stations are not to be accepted ard paid for unless th1guarantee is fulfilled.   The Company guarantee completionwithin six months from tho date on which the site is placed attheir disposal.   I regard these terms as reasonable..     (4)  An agreement to give effect to these arrangements hasbeen drafted and will be executed as soon as possible.  Underthe Standing Orders it will have to be approved by resolution of the house of Commons.     (5)  But beam stations will be useful as an auxiliary onlyto super stations and will not be a substitute for them.Super stations will still be necessary for long distancecommunication at all hours and. simultaneous transmission in alldirections and in particular for strategic purposes.   Thecompletion of the Rugby Station (as a sixteen mast station)will accordingly be pressed on with all speed.     (6)  As regards the provision of higher ma3ts at theexisting station at toafield, however (which was another ofthe Donald Committee&apos;s recommendations), the Air Ministry have raised strong objections, which cannot be ignored.   But theLeafield Station as it already exists will be useful fortelegraphic broadcasting and for Communication with non-Marconistations in Canada and elsewhere.     (7)  The Dominions and India have not yet finally decidedtheir policy..   I understand that tho super station in SouthAfrica, which the Marconi Company are under contract to erect,will probably bo completed.   The Indian Government also willprobably decide to arrange for the erection of a super station,                                                     and
CJ -IT hiand the New Zealand Government have informed us that theycontemplate such a station;   but  in the two latter cases no practical steps have yet been taken.   The commonwealth government are being pressed for  an early decision.     (8)   Tho question of Empire  Wireless policy having been settled with the Marconi Company  so far as this Country isconcerned, I propose in accordance with the decision previouslytaken by the Cabinet to negotiate with the; Company as regardsa licence for stations in this Country for communication withforeign oountries on the basis of the recommendations of theDonald Committee.     (9)   The Company have also agreed to confirm a provisionalsettlement, which had been discussed but not finally accepted,of thoir claims for remuneration for the use of the Company&apos;sstations in this Country during the War.   The settlement moansa payment of  75,000 beyond the sums already paid to the company or paid into Court, and the total payment will then representabout one half of that claimed by the Company under the petition of Right, which they presented and which will now be withdrawn.    (10)  The Cabinet Committee agree  with me that the time has now almost arrived for a public announcement, but as I hopemore definite information may be available from the Dominionsand especially from Australia within the next few days, Ipropose to defer the announcement until the middle of thepresent month.                                    4 jiti.1 &apos; -

</content>
</cab>
