<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/167/0 images: 549-549</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His  Britannic Majesty&apos;s  Government.)(Printed for the Cabinet,    July 1924.)SECRET.CP. 383 (24).Notes on Memorandum hy the  Secretary of State for the  Colonies                 on the position of Indians in Kenya.    I concur in the line proposed, which appears to me so reasonable and just thatI think it cannot fail to produce a good effect in India.  I would, however, make thefollowing observations:     Paragraph 2.-1 apprehend that the points other than immigration dealt within the letter from  the  Chairman  of the Committee  referred to, are the questionsof the franchise and that of  the reservation of land in the highlands for Europeanoccupation.    I agree that these topics  are not so  urgent as immigration, hut I fear that theycannot be regarded as having yet been eliminated from practical importance in regardto our difficulties in India.    Paragraphs 4 to 7. The relevance of the question how many Indians have beenentering, or may enter, at any period, seems to me to depend, in the first place, onthe question whether any immigration is or  is not  prejudicial  to the economic or social interests of the natives.  Only if it is proved that such immigration is in this sense prejudicial, or may be prejudicial if it becomes excessive in numbers, need anyquestion  of regulating it arise, and the question  of  any regulation of immigrationshould not be dealt with particularly in regard to Indians, hut generally in regard toall kinds of immigrants, i.e., it should not be approached specifically in regard toimmigrant  British subjects of any particular race or place of origin.    Paragraph 9 (4). If the offer of lands is to be publicly mentioned it is important that it should be known  whether it is a bond fide offer of suitable land.   I am informedthat the lands in question are liable  to flood, amcl eared, unhealthy and unsuitable for indian settlement.   If there is  any  foundation for these representations, it  is not surprising  that past history  shows that it is improbable  that many will wish to takeadvantage of the offer, and it cannot be ingenuously stated that there is no questionof exclusion.  The Kenya Government is under no obligation, and there seems to meto be no reason why it should propose, to promote any such scheme of settlement even onsuitable lands, hut  if it is not doing so, it should  not be made to appear that it is, whilstat the same time it is reserving picked and suitable lands for settlement by Europeanimmigrants, and excluding Indians  from there.  It is of very substantial importancein regard  to the effect  of Kenya policy on Indian feeling that there should  be no provision in this connection which can be denounced as make-believe.    Paragraph. 11  states the factors of  the problem  iu  a manner to which I couldnot make  any  objection from the  Indian point  of. view;  but the quotation fromMr. Churchill in paragraph 1.2 is not, in my opinion,  unobjectionable, and I trust  itwill not be endorsed in those&apos;words.  If the position  indicated in paragraph 11 is tobe adopted, there should  be  substituted  for Mr. Churchill&apos;s statement on it (last twolines) some such phrase as &quot; if danger ever arises of such an influx of immigrants of whatever class, race, nationality or  character,  as  may  be  likely  to be prejudicial tothe economic interests of the  natives.&quot;    Consistently with this, I see no  objection  to proposals B and C in paragraph 12.The institution of the department and activities proposed  seems indeed to me to hevery desirable in the general  interests of  the administration.    If these proposals,  safeguarded as  I have suggested, are accepted,  I   shouldconcur in the hope of their reasonable interpretation expressed in paragraph 13.    Paragraph 14. I have reason, to believe that  unless the policy of discrimination against Indians is  eliminated such a  retaliatory measure  as  is  spoken of  wouldprobably be introduced  in the Assembly, and  I therefore heartily concur in the last sentence of the Secretary of State&apos;s  Memorandum.   As, however,  I have  aboveindicated,  I do not think we  can  expect to have heard the  last of the question ofpolitical franchise or of the reservation of land in the highlands.     (I expect that within ten years Kenya planters  will be calling  out for  Indiancoolie labour in the highlands, which will involve Indian settlement.)    - jOLIVIER.5th July 1924. 7469    100  7.24

</content>
</cab>
