<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/167/0 images: 583-593</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCuiaiT IS  TH3 PROPERTY OP  HIS BRITAH1TIC KAJ1STY1S GOvlRHMSNI).SJCR3T.                                                    Copy No.                         C A 3 I IT 1 T.CP.  387 (54).                   (HOUS  AFFAIRS  COMlITTTia.)             2XPIRIttG LAWS  COHTE.TUAiTC:J!  BILL, 1924.      Memorandum by the Financial  Secretary  to the Treasury.          I ask for authority to introduoe the attached annualBill.   The Bill ia usually passed in July or August hut thelatest de,te by which the present Bill must become law is the31st December, 1924, and in the circumstances it may ultimately be decided to postpone discussion of the Bill until after the recess.   In view, however, of the recommendations of theSelect Committee of 1922 it is desirable that Parliament shouldbe aware of the contents of the Bill at as early a date aspossible and I should therefore like to introduce it at once.          I ought to draw attention to one point of detail.On 4th June, 1924, the Cabinet decided that the AgriculturalRates Act, 1923, (which expires on 31st !,iarch, 1925) should heinserted in the present Bill for the purpose of extending it for a further twelvemonths.     It was subsequently discovered,however, that a Financial Resolution would be necessary tocover the new charge on the Consolidated Fund involved in theextension.    The Minister of Agriculture and Minister ofHealth have therefore thought it best to omit the Act of 1923from the Schedule to the Bill and to promote before 31st liarch,1925, a short extending Bill which would also make provisionfor avoiding the necessity for any Financial Resolution in                                                   any
(THIS  DOCTHHJHT IS TH3 PROPERTY OP HIS BRITAI-T1TIC ,KAJ1STY&apos;S  GOV3HHM3HT)S30R3T.                                                    Copy Ho.J                         SABIH3I,CP. 587 (24) .                   (H0M3 .AFFAIRS  00MHCTT3S.-)       3XPIRING  LAWS  CONTHJUAITCI  BILL, 1924..Memorandum by the Financial Secretary to the Treasury.          I ask for authority to introduoe the attached annualBill,   The Bill is usually passed in July or August but thelatest date by which the present Bill must become law is the31st December, 1924, and in the circumstances it may ultimately be decided to postpone discussion of the Bill until after the recess.   In view, however, of the recommendations of theSelect Committee of 1922 it is desirable that Parliament shouldbe aware of the contents of the Bill at as earlya date aspossible and I should therefore like to introduce it at once.          I ought to draw attention to one point of detail.On 4th June, 1924, the Cabinet decided that the AgriculturalRates Act, 1923, (which expires on 31st iiarch, 1925) should beinserted in the present Bill for the purpose of extending it for a further twelve months.     It was subsequently discovered,however, that a Financial Resolution would be necessary tocover the new charge on the Consolidated Fund involved in theextension.    The Hinister of Agriculture and Minister ofHealth have therefore thought it best to omit the Act of 1923from the Schedule to the Bill and to promote before 31st liarch,1925, a short extending Bill which would also make provisionfor avoiding the necessity for any Financial Resolution in                                                   any         &apos;
any future extensions of the Act of 1923.   (FinancialResolutions have not been necessary for the inclusion ofthe Agricultural Rates Act, 1896,  and the AgriculturalRates Congested Districts and Burgh land Tax Relief(Scotland) Act, 1896^in successive Expiring Laws ContinuanceActs because it was provided by Section 17 (1)  of the finance act, 1907, that the grants payable under those  Acts shouldbe charged on the Consolidated Fund as long as  the temporaryActs were continued.    It is some arrangement  of this kind which is now contemplated in connection with the Act of 1923).         It should be further added that two items inSchedule I are affected by pending legislation:     Ko.18 - Ministry of Food (Continuance) Act, 1920 -             part I of the Sale of Food Order may have to be             struck out if the Sale of Bread Bill passes.     No.22 - SummeriTime Act, 1922 -  will not  be wanted if             the Bill of this Session is passed.                                            VI.  G.TREASURY CHAMBERS.     9th July,  1924.
J                         DRAFT                   B    ILL                             TO           :  Continue  certain expiring  laws.           A-D- 192*-   WHEREAS the Acts  mentioned  in  the  Schedule to         this Act are, in so far as they are in fore,   and are   temporary  in their duration, limited to expire as respects   the Acts mentioned  in Parts I., II., and III. of that 5 schedule on  the thirty-first  day of December, nineteen   hundred and twenty-four, the fifteenth  clay of February,   nineteen hundred and twenty-fire, and the nineteenth   clay of  May,  nineteen  hundred and  twenty-fire  respec-   tively, and as respects the  Acts mentioned  in Part IV.10 of that schedule  on the thirty-first day  of March,  nine-   teen hundred and twenty-five:       And whereas it is expedient to provide for the con-   tinuance as in this Act mentioned of those Acts and of   the enactments amending or affecting the same:15      Be it therefore enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent   Majesty, by and with the advice and consent  of the Lords   Spiritual and Temporal,  and Commons,  in  this present   Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same,   as follows: 20      1. (1)  The  Acts mentioned  in Parts  I.,  II. and Continuance   III. of the  Schedule to  this  Act shall, to the extent 0*Acts in   specified in column three  of  that  schedule,  be continued  c ie( 11 e&apos;   until the thirty-first day of December, nineteen hundred   and twenty-five,  and  shall then  expire, unless further25 continued.                                                -  ,       101-2                A
A.OH)24.      (2) The Acts mentioned in Part IV. of the Schedule          to this Act shall, to the extent specified in column three          of that  schedule, be continued until the thirty-first day          of March, nineteen  hundred and twenty-six, and shall          then expire, unless further continued.                   5              (3) Any unrepealed enactments amending or affecting          the  enactments continued by this Act shall, in so far as          they are temporary in their duration, be continued in like          manner, whether  they are mentioned in the  Schedule to          this Act or not.                                        10               2. (1) This Act may be  cited as  the Expiring          Laws Continuance Act, 1924. -               (2) This Act shall  apply to Northern  Ireland in          so far  as it deals  with any enactment  relating to a          subject with respect to which the Parliament of Northern ] 5          Ireland has not power to make laws, but subject to this          provision this Act shall not apply to Ireland.Short title and applica-tion toIreland.
SCHEDULE. A.D. 1924.Section 1.PAST I.   1.Session and Chapter.    2.Short Title.How far continued.Amending Acts.46 &amp; 47 Viet.  e. 60.The Labourers (Ire-  land) Act, 1883.10152025303540     (2)58 &amp; 59 Viet.  c. 21.     (3)4 Edw. 7. c. 2445  7 Edw.7. c.55101The  Seal  Fisheries  (North   Pacific)  Act, 1895.The  Wireless Tele-  graphy Act, 1904.The London Cab and  Stage   Carriage  AET, 1907.The whole act the whole Aet.The whole Aet.As to the abolition of the  privileged cab  system, seo- tion two.48 &amp; 49 Viet.  c. 77.49&amp;50 Viet.  c. 59.54 &amp; 55 Viet.  c. 48.54 &amp; 55 Viet.  c.71.55 &amp; 56 Viet.  c. 7.- -59 &amp; 60 Viet.  c. 53.61 &amp; 62 Viet.  c. 37.3  Edw.  c. 37.6  Edw.  c. 37.7  Edw.  c. 44.9   Edw.  c. 42.1 &amp; 2 Geo. 5.  c. 19.4 &amp;&apos;5 Geo. 5.  e.32.8 &amp; 9 Geo. 5.  c. 20.9&amp;10Geo. 5.  c. 55.  .2 &amp; 3 Geo. 5.  c. 10.A 2
A.D. 1924.   1.Session and Chapter.    (5)1 &amp; 2 Geo. 5.  c. 55.     (6)2 &amp; 3 Geo. 5.  e. 2. &apos;     (7)4 &amp; 5 Geo. 5.  c. 3.   ,  (8)4 &amp; 5 Geo. 5.  c. 78.     (9)6 &amp; 7 Geo. 5. . c. 12.Short Title.The  National  In-  surance Act, 1911,The  Coal  Mines  (Minimum Wage)  Act, 1912.The Grey Seals Pro-  tection Act, 1914.The Courts (Emer-  gency   Powers)  Act, 1914.The Local  Govem-  ment (Emergency  Provisions)  Act,  1916.       3.How far continued.Section forty-two -The whole Act.The whole Act.     4.Amending Actq.So far as it relates	6 &amp; 7 Geo. 5.	to orders made	c. 13.	by any court	6 &amp; 7 Geo. 5.	before the thirty-	c. 18.	30first day of	7 &amp; 8 Geo. 5.	August, nineteen	c. 25.	hundred and	9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5.	twenty-two.	c. 64.		10&amp;11 Geo.5.	35	c. 5.		13 &amp; 14Geo.5.		c. 8.	Section five, except  paragraph  (a) ;  Sections    six,  seven, nine, and  twelve ; Section  thirteen,  except  subsections  (4),  (5)   and   (6) ;  Sections   four-  teen, twenty-one  and twenty-two,  and  subsection  (1)  of  section  twenty-four. 3 &amp; 4 Geo. 5.  5   c. 37. 4 &amp; 5 Geo. 5.   c.81. 7 &amp; 8 Geo. 5.   c.62.      10 9 &amp; 10 Geo.5.  c. 2i.10&amp;11 Geo.5.   c. 10.11 &amp; 12Geo.5.  15  c. 12.11 &amp; 12Geo.5.  c. 25.10&amp;llGeo.5/20  c. 50.25U&amp;12Geo.5.  c. 12.4550
1.	2.	&quot; 3.	i.Session and Chapter.	Short Title.	How far continued. -	Amending Acts.A.D. 192410   (10)6&amp;7Geo.5.  c. 55.7 &amp; 8 Geo. 5.  c. 19.     &apos;   (12)    8 &amp; 9 Geo. 5.15    c. 23.        (13)    8 &amp; 9 Geo. 5.      c. 34.2025    (14)9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5.  c. 35.    (15)9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5  c. 60.30 :&quot;        (16)    9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5      c. 92.35     (17)    9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5      c. 97.        (18)40 10 &amp; 11 Geo.5;      c. 47.4550The Local  Govern-  ment (Emergency  Provisions) (No. 2)  Act, 1916.The Coroners (Emer-  gency Provisions)  Act, 1917.The Juries Act, 1918The Statutory Un-.  dertakings (term  .-  porary  Increase!  of Charges) Act,  1918.The Housing, Town  Planning,     &amp;a.  Act, 1919.   -The Housing, Town  Planning,     &amp;c.  (Scotland)   Act,  1919.The Aliens restriction-  tion (Amendment)  Act, 1919.The  Land  Settle-  ment  (Scotland)  Act, 1919.The  Ministry   of  Food   (Continu-  ance) Act, 1920.The whole act the whole ActSection sevenSo far as it relates  to      tramway  undertakings.Section twenty-live.Section twenty-two.Section one.Sections  one  and  two.So far as it autho-  rises the making,  or revoking  in  whole or in part,  of Parts I. and  III. of the Sale  of Food  Order,  1921,  and  pro-  vides   for  the  enforcement andimposesfor  the breachthereof.11 &amp; 12 Geo. 5.  c. 12.12 &amp; 13 Geo.5.   c. 2.12 &amp; 13 Geo.5.   e. 2.10 &amp; 11 Geo.5.  c. 14.12 &amp; 13 Geo:5.  c. 52.
1. Session and Chapter.	2. Short Title.	3. How far continued.	i. Amending Acts.	(19) I0&amp;llGeo.5. c. 57.	The Unemployment (Relief Works) Act, 1920.	The whole Act.	-	5(20) lO&amp;llGeo. 5. c. 58.	The Shops (Early Closing) Act, 1920.	The whele Act -	ll&amp;12Geo.5. c. 60.	10(21) ll&amp;12Geo.5. o. 66.	The National Health Insurance (Pro-prolongation of In-surance) Act, 1921.	The whole Act.	--	15(22) l2&amp;13Geo.5. c. 22.	The Summer Time Act, 1922.	The whole Act.	-	20	PART II.			(23) 10&amp;llGeo.5. c. 21.	The Harbours Docks and Piers (Tem-porary Increase of Charges) Act, 1920.	The whole Aet.	12&amp;13Geo.5. c. 23.	25PART III.(24) 10 &amp; 11 Geo.5. c. 9.	The Public Utility Companies (Capi-tal Issues) Aet, 1920.	The whole Act.	- 30PART IV.			(25) 59 &amp; 60 Viet. c. 16.	The Agricultural Rates Act, 1896.	Tho whole Act	2 Edw. 7. c. 42. 7 Edw. 7. c. 13.
1. Session and Chapter.	2t Short Title,	3. How far continued.	j I. Amending Acts-(26) 59 k 60 Viet. c. 37.	The Agricultural Bates, Congested Districts, and Burgh Land Tax Relief (Scotland) Act, 1896.	The whole Aet	60 &amp; 61 Viet. c. 53. 7 Edw. 7. c. 13. 1 &amp; 2 Geo. 5. c. 49.AD. 1924.
Expiring  Laws Continuance.        DE AFT          OF A     BILLTo continue certain expiring laws.LXXXIV.  (2.)1st July 1924.101-2

</content>
</cab>
