<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/24/0 images: 157-163</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DO0TJM3NT   IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITAMIO MAJESTY&apos; S GOYERNMEHTPIhal OPFY No.CABINET 13 (21)Conclusions of a Mooting of theCabinet hold at 10,  owning Street, S.T^.,--on Monday, 14th March 192*1 at 12 Noon.PREFER T :THE PRIMS MINISTER (in the Chair),[fhe Right H&apos;ona E* Shortt, K*0o,McP*,Secretary of State for Homo Aff&amp;irsShe Bight hon Sir I. WorthingtcnEvans, Bart* eMo,Pw 9V 3e aretary of Slatefor Wartt \The Right Hon. R. Munro, LD.;,ltP.,Secretaiy for  ootlend0rihe Right Hon. T.J. Macnsmsra, M.P.,Minister of Labour.iThe Right hon H.A.I. Fishert M.PcPresidents Board of Education.The Right Hono Earl Curzon ofEeuleston, EAGo SGAC.S.I. ,G; C.I..secretary of State for ForeignAffairs. -The Right Hon. Lord Lee ofFerehems, GoBoE^KcCB,,First Lord of the AdmiraltycThe Right Eon,    Sir E. Geddes.GoOcBo-G-r-BoFc ,MoP., Ministerof TransportsThe Right Hon. Sir RobiASt Home,Board of Trade.president the Right Hen, Sir A. Griffith Boscawen,    Minister of AgrieuTtiand FisheriescTHE FOLLOWING &quot;TIRE ALSO PRESENT :-Sir G.L. Bar stow, LCB,Controller of Supply Services,,Treasury, (for Conolusior       3.      )Lieut-Colonel Sir MAP.A. hankey, &amp;,C.3.,  ............-Secretary, CabinetThomas Jones................... Principal Assistant Secretary, Cabinet
ilADXJJj&amp; RELA-        (1)    With reference to Cabinet 75  (2C). Conclusion 2pSlA. tho Cabinet had before them the following documents relating to the proposed Russian Trade Agreement:-Note by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs   (Paper C,P.-2286),Memorandum by the President of the beard of Trade,  covering Draft Agree-ment handed to m. Krassin (Paper C.P.-24S1),Memorandum by the President of the beard of Trade  (Paper CP,-27C6).The President of the Board of Trade informed theCabinet that M, Kraasin had now returned from Ruasia with full power from the Soviet authorities to conclude theTrade Agreement, subject to certain modifications set forth in his Memorandum.      The most important of these weredemands for an undertaking cn our part to refrain anddesist from encouraging or supporting in any way hostile action against Soviet Russia on the part of Japan,  Germany,Poland, Roumania, Hungary, Gzecho-Slovakia, Bulgaria,  greece and Yugo-Slavia,  and to engage ourselves to respect theindependence and integrity of Persia, Afghanistan,  and theterritory of the &quot;kirkish National Assembly, and that weshould not in any way aid any persons pretending to repre-sent any Government of Russia (or any portion .c*f tho former russian Empire of which the independence has not been recog-nised by the Russian Sr-viet Government) other than theRussian Soviet Government.^he Cabinet were reminded that the draft Agreementtaken back.to Russia by M, Kraasin represented the maximum(indeed, was a whittling down of the maximum) concessionsmade by those who were opposed to the scheme.    The objectof the safeguards which had been insisted on had been to check.Bolshevist propaganda in the East.    In the Intervalsince      drr?.ssinTs departure this Bolshevist propaganda ha&apos;been greatly, intensified.    Now M. Krassin was making-l-
extravagant demands, the meaning 0f which was uncertain,which,  if acceded to, might prove a great embarrassment tous in some of the countries which formerly constituted theRussian Empire, e.g., in Armenia and in Georgia, which wehad lately recognised de jure.    The proposal that we shouldengage ourselves to respect the independence and integrity of the territory of the Turkish National Assembly was con-sidered particularly objectionable,  at a time when we werein negotiation with the de facto Government of that territory-It had obviously bean inserted in order to enable the SovietGovernment to gain credit with the Angora Government.The Cabinet were also reminded that the position ofthe Soviet Government,  as indicated by the recent risingsin Cronstadt, Petrograd and elsewhere, was by no means stableIn these circumstances, more particularly as the economic advantages expected from the Treaty would not in any eventmature for a long time.,  it was suggested that there wereadvantages in not hastening the conclusion of an agreement which was desired by the Bolsheviks mainly in order toenhanc e the ir pi-e sti ge ,There was general agreement that the forrmila proposedby M. Krassin, dealing with Japan, Germany^  etc., couldnot possibly bo accepted.    It was generally felt, however,that there had already been sufficient delay in this matterand that the issue should now be forced to a conclusion.Discussion concentrated mainly on the question ofthe undertaking, if any, to be given to the Soviet Govern-raent,  and, if so, what  formula should be adopted.      Thefollowing was suggested:-&quot;The British Government gives a similarparticular undertaking in respect of thecountries which formed part of the&apos; former russian empire and have now become inde-pendent States.&quot;The Cabinet inclined to the view.that the SovietGovernment were justified in&apos; asking that we should give anundertaking in terms corresponding to the undertaking
1 5 !we had exacted from them, and that if we insisted on theinserti6h of specific countries, they could not he blamedfor doing the same.    The Cabinet were reminded, however.that the countries in respect of which we had asked for anundertaking were those bordering on India, or speciallyconcerning us from the paint of view of its defence, viz;.,Asia Minor,  Persia, Afghanistan, and India itself.. On the whole it was felt that, while re1vaijiing.JU%han--.-is tan and India if M. Krassin would agree to exclude AciaitMinor from his list, we should consent to omit from curlist, and that we might alse agree to eliminate Persia,insomuch as it was nf,w clear that the Anglo-. Persian Agree-ment was not likely to be ratified.    The guiding principlethroughout should be the  safeguarding of our Empire in theEast.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the President cf the Board of trade should refuse the request in regard tohootile action by Japan, G-ermany, etc,,and should endeavour to omit from the specific undertakings of both sides any reference to Asia Minor and Persia:    fur-ther, that he should propose the formula-quoted above as a substitute for theformula suggested by M. Krassin:(b) That the President of the Board of trade should accept the description of the futuregeneral treaty to be negotiated ao a Ipeace&quot;treaty:(c) That  the President cf the Board ff trade should give the undertakings asked forin regard to ships and gold:(d) That, subject to the above, the Presidentof the Board of Trade should conclude the trading Agreement with M, Krassin.
(JMEMPL- 8YMENT,A(2) With reference to Cabinet 72 (20), Conclusion 2 (3)l^mrltl Men!^ 0abto&apos;9t        before them a Memorandum by the Minister ofLabour calling attention to a difficulty which had arisen in the interpretation of the term &quot;preference to ex-Servicemen&quot; in connection with schemes receiving grants from theUnemployment Grants Committee (Paper CP.-2696).It was explained that, in connection with arterialroad schemes, a Departmental ruling had been given whichallowed civilians to be engaged on sche; es up to a numbernot exceeding one-fourth of the whole.    This was designedto -meet the objection of Local Authorities to the engagementof unmarried ex-Servioe men who had perhaps net servedoverseas, while married civilians  (with dependants) remainedunemployed.    The Unemployment Grants Committee,- however,in the absence of Cabinet instructions, had adhered to aliteral interpretation of the phrase, and authority was nowsought to read it in the br.:.ader sense,.    In support of thisview it was pointed out that the co-operation of the LocalAuthorities was essential to the success of the schemes,and they were substantial contributors to the cost c&amp; theschemes.    On the other hand, it was desirable to avoidacknowledging a national obligation for civilian unemployment.The case of the ex--S^rvioe men was one of a special liabilityundertaken by the State, and should not be extended to civilians.The Cabinet agreed  That the Minister of Labour, without formallyaltering&apos; the powers- of the Unemployment GrantsCommittee, should inform the Chairman of the-Committee that the Cabinet wished the Commit-tee to- maintain the principle of .preference,but to look favourably on the employment ofa small proportion of civilians if requestedto do so by Local Authorities.
(3) With, reference-to.Cabinet 4  (21),, Cxmo^xisLwa^.thei^abdrvet-had before them the-ftvllwing documents:-Memorandum by the First Lard of theAdmiralty (Paper 0.P.-2584&apos;),Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Air (Pa.Per CftP,-3502),Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor War.(Paper 0-2594),   -Memorandum by the Secretary cf Statefor India (Paper CP,,-2636.) .The Cabinet were informed that the compromise reached at the Cabinet Meeting on January 28th. had, on examination by the contracting Departments, been found open to serious objection on practical grounds.    It would, in their view, netonly restrict competition and lead to enhanced cost,  increasethe difficulty of dealing with cases of &quot;rings&quot; and &quot;arranged!prices&quot;, but the disclosure to a competitor of the lowestpric^ t^nder^d would greatly weaken confidence in the fairdealing of Government Contracting Departments.&apos;In view of these Objections the Cabinet were urged to revert to the. original xe quest of the Ministry of Labciir, thano firm should be given a Government contract unless it hadbeen placed cn the King* 8 Roll.    This general rule,  it wascontended,  could be loosely interpreted so as to allow theemployment of less than the normal five per cent.        cfdisabled men in exceptional cases..    Cn the ether hand,  it was admitted that  there would be considerable difficulties in applying the rule to certain large industries, like coalmining and railways, and that negotiations with these had so ^ar made little headway.The Cabinet agreed  To refer the whole question to an Inter-departmental Committee, composed of  The Home Secretary  (Chairman),The Financial Secretary, War Office,The Financial Secretary, Admiralty,A Representative of the Treasury,A Representative of the India Office, A Representative of the Ministry of Labour,A Representative of the Air Ministry,A Representative of the Post Office,A Representative of the Office of Works,A Representative of the Stationery Office.Colonel Walker (Secretary;.-5-
(4) The Cabinet desired, to place on record their apprecia-tion of the cervices rendered during the last three weeksby the Secretariat pf the Cabinet Office, in supplying, inaddition to the ordinary work of the Office, the serviceof a Secretariat-General for the recent Allied Conferenceswith the representatives of Germany, Greece, Turkey andAxis tria.Sir Maurice Hankey was requested to convey the thanks of the Cabinet tothe Secretariat,&apos; including the clerical Branches. ;2, &quot;Whitehall Gardens, S.&apos;K. 1,March 14,  1921.

</content>
</cab>
