<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/198/0 images: 14-17</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT  IS THE  PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT) .SECRET.CP.  302 (28).CAB I N E T.REDUCTION OF ARMAMENTS.Naval Limitation.COPY NO.(Reference Cabinet 46 (28),  Conclusion 2(d)).     The final observations of members of the cabinet have been received on the draft Circular Despatch toHis Majesty&apos;a Representatives in the Capitals of allCountries represented on the Preparatory Commission forthe Disarmament Conference, the first and revised drafts of which were Circulated as CP. 295 (28) and CP. 298  (28)respectively.   The final version has now been -signed by the Acting Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs and despatched, dated October 9th, 1928.     A copy of the despatch as sent to His Majesty1sRepresentatives is attached for information.J  (Signed) M.P.A. BANKET,Secretary to the Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.I.     October 17th,  1928.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.&apos;]Printed for the Cabinet.  October 1928.CONFIDENTIAL.                                               ---------                                                     28Circular Despatch to His Majesty&apos;s Representatives in the Capitals of all Countries   represented on the Preparatory Commission for the Disarmament Conference.Sir,                                            Foreign Office, October 9, 1928.    THE observations of the Governments of the United  States, Italy and japan on the British and French compromise proposals in the matter of the limitation ofnaval armament having now been received, the present moment affords a convenient opportunity of presenting, for your information and guidance, an outline of recent discussions and correspondence on this subject.    As a result of unauthorised and incomplete disclosures,  the nature and scopeof this compromise became, as you are aware, the object of public speculation, often.of  an  erroneous  and  misleading  character.   His  Ma.jesty&apos;s  Government  arecontemplating the early publication of papers, which, in covering as briefly as possiblethe history of the negotiations  for naval  disarmament, should  serve to place thematter in its true perspective.  That they have refrained hitherto from publicationhas been due in part to  their  anxiety  not to embarrass  the  other  Governmentsconcerned by what might  have been regarded  as an attempt to force their hand, inpart to their reluctance to publish correspondence, while still incomplete, on a matter at once complex in its technical aspect and far-reaching in its  results.    The Anglo-French  compromise cannot be regarded as a detached  or  isolatedevent; it is the most recent link in a  long chain of  endeavour to implement theprovisions embodied in  Article 8 of the  Covenant of the League of Nations to theeffect that &quot;the members of the League recognise that the maintenance of  peacerequires  the reduction of national armaments to the  lowest point consistent  with national safety.&quot; The first steps taken by the League to fulfil this obligation  wereturned in the direction of comprehensive schemes of  mutual assistance in the belief that the creation of a general sense of security was the most promising avenue to anall-round reduction and limitation of armaments.    In the face of  continued failure to  reach agreement on any such scheme, this line of approach was abandoned in favour of more direct methods, and in December1925 the Assembly set up a special commission with mandate to prepare the ground for a general conference.   On the completion of certain preliminary researches on technical  matters which monopolised its attention during the  ensuing year, this commission, known  as the Preparatory Commission, attacked its main  task at itsthird session (March-April 1927), at which the British and French representativeseach put forward a draft  skeleton convention as a basis of  discussion.    There was a wide divergence between these two  drafts.  On the naval side theBritish draft provided for  the limitation of vessels of war in nine separate categories;the French draft for limitation, broadly speaking, by total tonnage.  It was between these  two principles limitation by  classes or limitation  by  total  or  &quot;global&quot;tonnage that the chief controversy has turned. The other Governments represented on the Commission ranged themselves some on one side, some on the other. Italy, inparticular, supported the French thesis, while the United States, who, though not amember of the League of  Nations, is represented on the Preparatory  Commission,favoured the British plan of limitation by classes while differing as to its application in detail.  In the hope of bridging this divergence the French  delegation some, days later put forward a modified proposal, which became known as the  French compromise proposal, and which went so far to meet the British view as to introduce classificationby four classes.  It contained provision, however, for unlimited transfer of tonnagefrom one class to another,  and partly for that  reason and partly  owing to the small:number of classes proved inacceptable to the British delegation.      4614-1   [18300]
     Confronted by these acute and seemingly irreconcilable divergences, and anxious1to do nothing which might prejudice the success of the Naval Conference, to whichthe  United States Government  had recently  issued  invitations,  the  PreparatoryCommission adjourned without having made any progress towards an agreed  text of a skeleton convention.  Two months later (June 1927) the  Naval Conference met in Geneva, only to break down after seven  weeks of effort to adjust the differingpoints of view of the Governments represented.     In the  face of the deadlock in the Preparatory Commission, followed by thefailure of the Geneva Conference,  all  prospect  of  immediate  progress  appearedto  be  extinguished.   The   French  and   English   draft  conventions   remainedunreconciled, all attempts to arrive at an agreed text having broken down.   informal conversations, however,  were frequent at  Geneva;   naval experts discussed  thedifferent points of view; the political delegates also sought a way out of the impasse.These talks  ultimately culminated  in  the  conversation  between M.  Briand  andSir Austen  Chamberlain  at  Geneva in  March  1928, which led  to the compromiseunder review.  In  the course of their discussions Sir Austen Chamberlain mentionedcertain suggestions which  had been  made by  the British Admiralty  and  hesubsequently communicated a written note  of  them to M. Briand at the latter&apos;request.  They provided for limitation by six classes, all types of vessel being included.They were not acceptable.    In considering these successive steps towards compromise it  should be borne inmind that the British contention had always been for limitation in detail, the Frenchcontention for limitation by total tonnage.  Thus the original British plan had been for classification by nine classes.   Under the modified British proposals, as submittedto M. Briand after the March conversation,  the number of classes had been reduced to six, but included vessels of all types.  On their side the French Government, no  lessanxious  than  His Majesty&apos;s Government  to  promote  agreement, had  shown a disposition to  meet the British thesis so far as possible.  In the end a compromisewas  reached on  the basis of a limitation applicable  to  four  classes of war vessel.Like all  compromises, these tentative proposals involved  concessions by both  sides.They represented an advance  from a position of difficulty and deadlock which hadprevailed for over a year.  While admittedly incomplete as a final solution of  thenaval limitation question,  they would, if adopted, have added two further  classes of vessel to the two classes limited under the Washington Treaty.  They could onlylead  to useful results if the other principal  naval Powers were  ready to regard them as offering a  possible basis  for resumption of  negotiation  in  the  PreparatoryCommission.    As, in the matter of  naval disarmament,  the question of classification versusglobal tonnage had hitherto impeded progress, so, in the matter  of land disarmament,the question of the limitation of military-trained reserves had proved  a stumbling-block.  The French Government and the majority of the Governments represented on the Preparatory Commission had held that reserves  should  be excluded fromlimitation, while His  Majesty&apos;s Government,  for reasons into which it  is hereunnecessary to enter, had consistently supported &quot;the opposite  thesis.  For sometime,  however, they had  realised that further opposition on  their  part to  the exclusion of these  trained reserves could, in the face of the attitude maintained bythe majority of the Preparatory Commission, only have the effect of preventingprogress indefinitely.  So  long ago as April  1927 the British  representative on  theCommission (Viscount  Cecil) clearly foreshadowed the withdrawal, for the sake ofagreement, of  British opposition to the opinion held by the majority of that  body.When, therefore, the two Governments  were advancing towards a compromise inthe matter of naval limitation, it was felt that the process of  agreement could onlybe facilitated by a formal intimation to the French Government that a concessionmade to the views of His Majesty&apos;s Government on naval classification would enablethem to withdraw their opposition to the French standpoint in the matter of military-trained reserves.    His  Majesty&apos;s Government have been criticised  on account of the secrecy inwhich the negotiations described above are alleged to have  taken place.  The facts are that as long ago as March last it was announced in the Preparatory commission that  conversations were taking place in the hope of removing  the differences whichhad hitherto obstructed progress, and the  session was adjourned to allow of  theircontinuance.   When  the Anglo-French compromise proposals  were ready for submission to  the other naval  Powers, the fact was announced by Sir  austen chamberlain in the House  of  Commons.   I myself  gave  to  the  press on the
7)30th August last a full account of the circumstances in which the compromise wasreached and an emphatic denial of the speculations as to the existence of secretclauses  and  political  understandings.   The  whole  case  is  revealed  in the correspondence, and any suggestions to the contrary are totally devoid of foundation.    The proposals thus negotiated  were submitted  at  the end of  July to theGovernments of the United States,  Italy and Japan.  The replies of these Govern-ments  have  now  been  received  and are  enclosed  herein.   While the  JapaneseGovernment  express  their  concurrence  in  the  purport  of  these  proposals,the Governments of the United States and Italy,&apos;for reasons which are clearly andcogently explained in their notes, have not seen their way to accept them.  These-communications  are  receiving  the  attentive  consideration of  His  Majesty&apos;sGovernment, and a reply will be made to them in due course                                                        I am, &amp;c,                                                             CTJSHENDUN.

</content>
</cab>
