<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/198/0 images: 437-447</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
T.                                          COPY NO.(26) .                  CABINET.            UNEMPLOYMENT POLICY COMMITTEE.                   REPORT .(1),   At their Meeting on November 5th, 1928,(Cabinet 49 (28), Conclusion 4), the Cabinet had beforethem the Report of an Inter-Departmental Committee underthe Chairmanship of Sir Warren Fisher containing recommen-dations for dealing with unemployment (CP. 325 (28)) and agreed.-       That a Cabinet Committee, composed as follows -          The Chancellor of the Exchequer (In the Chair).          The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs               and the Colonies,          The Secretary of State for War,          The Secretary of State for Scotland;          The President of the Board of Trade,          The Minister of Health,          The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries,          The President of the Board of Education,-          The Minister of Labour,       should meet to consider the proposals in       CP. 325  (28) and to report to the Cabinet       on the following Wednesday their recommendations       as to what announcement should be made in the       forthcoming Parliamentary Debates on the       subiect of unemployment.
n fa r*h.- ty               Derating and Anticipation, of Hallway                       freight relief.2.     The main contz*distribution of the Government to assisttrade and employment Is the comprehensive measure of ratingrelief to agriculture and industry which after the ratepayments of April next, relieve productive industry of three-quarters, and agriculture of all rates at a cost t-G theNational Exchequer of some  35 millions a year.   In addition there is the further relief &quot;by the reduction of railway freightsto agriculture, coal and iron and steel.   The rating relief, whichthe Railways will pass on to their customers, as already announced,will be concentrated in helping those industries whero the need is greatest.  And in selecting the partioular traffics of concern to these industries, the relief is being concentrated where theindustries themselves consider the greatest benefit will beobtained.   Although the railway freight relief forms part ofthe general scheme, the Government decided that, in order togive immediate assistance to agriculture, coal, and iron andsteel, this railway freight relief should be anticipatea0A vote will be submitted to Parliament at an early date enablingrailway freight relief to begin on the 1st of December.  It isestimated that this relief will throw an additional charge on theBudget of this year of nearly  1,000,000 and of  2,250,000 onnext year-&apos; s Budget.   This relief will allow for a reductionof 10$ on the selected traffics of agriculture and iron andstoel; and, in view of tho concentration of the coal freightrelief in accordance with the desire of the mining industry itself on coal for export, foreign bunkers, blast furnaces andsteel works, the reduction on these selected coal trafficswill be equivalent to something like 30$.
                                                     *)-()&apos;(!                ..                                     UJ %j &quot;J       0   Effipire^ Settlement.          The second main feature Is the policy ofUmpire Settlement.   The Industrial TransferenceBoard emphasised the importance of stimulating thenormal flow of migration to Canada.  In August lastH.M, Government agreed to accelerate and extend thepolicy of Empire Settlement at an estimated additional cost of  g- million in this year rising to  X-r,- millions in future years.   There is no doubt that a lowmigrant passage rate would be a great encouragement  tosteady migration as it was before the war.   arrangements will It is hoped shortly be completed with the shipping companies on the Horth Atlantic Service by which, theywill be enabled to quote a general reduce63rd Class fareto Canada for British migrants at   10*.   Lord Lovatwas able tp ascertain from the Canadian authoritiesthis summer that such an arrangement would, not be regardeas bringing the migrants availing themselves of thesereduced fares within the category of assisted migrants  ansubject to the limitations as tq occupation or other restrictions imposed in connection with assisted passages          Apart from these steps which are being takento stimulate the general flow of migration, the existing facilities for training and testing migrants who wish totake up work on the land overseas are being expanded  bythe enlargement and fuller utilisation of existingtraining centres and the provision of new training centreThese facilities will be sufficient to send to Canada -during the period of migration next year up to sixthousand men qualified and in a position to ava.il them-selves of the opportunities v/hich Canada affords to men  * (In speaking it would be better not to quote the     figure of  10,- until there is a firm agreement with     the Companies as to the terms on v/hich the differ sue     is to be borne).,
9 Ciwho are willing to go on the land, whoso willingnesshas been tested by actual work on the land, and vh o,not skilled agriculturalists, have at any rate anelementary knowledge of the tasks expected of them.
                  III.   The Policy  of                        refatloa......to  the&quot;&quot;&quot;UncmpToy^eat  Gran.t s                        Oommittoe.          The most serious feature  of  the unemployment  problem is the concentration in the depressed  areas of large numbers  of persons who are permanently surplus to the requirement  of their industry.   There is no ground for  hoping that if these - people remain where they are they will ever again obtain employment.   Various remedies have been suggested which may in time bring some relief or improvement to the industries inwhich they have been engageds but they will bring no immediatehelp to the surplus population..   The  Industrial Transfei&apos;enceBoard, after considering the problem exhaustively Game to theconclusion that the only thing to be done for this surpluspopulation was to induce it to move elsewhere, and bring it back into the stream of living industry.    The Government adopted thispolicy and in pursuance of it the Ministry of labour are movingmen and women and boys and girls from  the desolation of the                                              six ordepressed.areas to work elsewhere at the rate of/seven hundreda wee k.   The process of transfer is being- iaci Htat8d by theprovision of training centres where men unused to factory lifecan be fitted for new trades.    These  centres have already beenexpanded for the benefit primarily of  men from the depressed areas-  If the present rate of transfer can be continued,  it means that in six months something like 15,000 persons willhave been transferred from the depressed areas * through themachinery of. the Ministry&apos; of labour.   The will to move has been to some extent aroused, and it is  probable that  at least as many men and women in addition are moving on their own acoouut,          The policy, if it is to  succeed, must  have the goodwill and co-operation of all classes of the community.  It ia not a question of asking for charity,  or of asking employers to take on men whoa they do not need.   All that Is asked is  that of the
 large  number  of labour  engagements which are made  every week a  relatively  small  proportion shall be given to these men,- who  include,  as the  Industrial  Transference Board  pointed out, some of the oream of the  industrial population.           In  order to facilitate  an&amp;  further the Transference. Scheme s It is proposed  to reopen  on more favourable terms the grants offered  to local Authorities through the St. David&amp;s Committee  in respect  of works financed out of loans in caseswhere Authorities in the more prosperous  areas are prepared to employ a substantial proposition of persons from the distressed areas upon public worksa          The offer of the improved terms will as a rulebe conditional  on the local authority drawing not less than 50 per oent of  the labour from  the distressed areas, but the Si?. David5 s Committee will have discretion to allow a lowerpercentage in special oases.  The existing conditions requiringa minimum acceleration of 5 years and excluding  road works will be waived In order ta secure the maximum responseo          Although the object of the scheme is  to  encourage the transfer of labour it is not proposed to disturb thepresent arrangements under v/hich grants are now  being paid in areas with exceptional unemployments
             IV.   EXPORT CREDITS.                  -.---.                        p, ^     In order to stimulate export trade, the originalExport Credits scheme was introduced in 1920.   The termsunder which this scheme Is operated have been altered fromtime to time, in order to make them of more practicalconvenience to manufacturers and exporters.   Under existing legislation no new guarantees could have been given afterSeptember of next year, and uncertainty as to whether thescheme would be continued would undoubtedly have deterredfirms from undertaking business with that assistance in thecoming year.   The Government have already announced their intention of continuing this help to our export trade fora further period of two years, and a Bill continuing thescheme will be introduced in the House of Commons at once.              V.  LAND DRAINAGE.              (A) ENGLAND AND WALES.     By an extension of the field of Land Drainage and allied schemes assisted out of state funds it would be practicable to divert a number of unemployed miners andethers to useful works of an urgent nature.     The Ministry of Agriculture has a waiting list Qfsuch schemes - including those which are known as the&quot;calamity&quot;  cases in Essex which arose as. the result of abnormal tides in January 1923.    &apos; To do  this would  Involve some relaxation of  conditionswhich  govern grants under the existing  programme  of theMinistry.     The Government  grant  in  such  cases should be 50 per cent,  of approved  cost of  the works.      The necessary funds might  be  provided by releasing  a sum not  exceeding  100,000 out  of  the  balance  of  580,000 which remains  at present earmarked for the Ouse  Scheme  out of the original  1,000,000 provided for drainage works  as from April 1926*
                 (B&apos;  SCOTLAND.,     Fr^rn It 21 to 1923 the Board of Agriculture forScotland administered a scheme for the relief of unemplov-ment in districts where serious unemployment existed.   Theworks eligible for grant included field, arterial and hilldrainage, the provision and Improvement of farm water-supplies, and the improvement of privately owned farmroads.   Labour required to be obtained through the LabourExchange, or if obtained elsewhere had to be composed tothe extent of at least 15% of ex-service men.     During that period the amount of grant paid by theBoard was  124,270 and the number of unemployed men engaged on schemes was about 13,000.     The Board now propose that a scheme similar to thatwhich was in operation from 1921-1926 should be authorised,     The Board report that- the scheme could be put Intooperation at once and would not entail the employment ofadditional staff to administer it.   Further, and inaddition to the relief of unemployment which it would affordin both urban and rural areas, it would be attractive toagriculturists generally, while State expenditure would be safeguarded in that an applicant&apos; would be required to expend a sum at least equal to the amount of the grantoffered to him.     The Board anticipate that about  100,000 would be spent under the scheme,  50,000 being Exchequer Grant andthat about 75;- of this .sum would be spent on wages mostlyto unemployed persons.
VI.   Electricity Supply.          The Committee have received from the Ministerof Transport the following statement of the progress made with schemes under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1926.          The Table appended to this Report shows     the progress made with Schemes under the Act.          It will be seen that four Schemes have already     been adopted- by the Board covering the -areas of     Central Scotland, South-Bast England, Central     England, and North-West and North Wales.  These     four Schemes cover an area of over 30,000 square     miles and a population of 27,000,000 people.  The     total capital expenditure estimated to be involved     on transmission lines and transforming stations Is     nearly  17,000,000.          Contracts have already been entered into by the     Central Electricity Board to the following amounts            Central Scotland...............   1,095,170            South-Bast England.............   1,614,672            North-West and North Wales.....      43,537                                  TOTAL....   2,758,179          In addition, expenditure has actually been     .incurred or approved in connection with the     standardisation of frequency amounting to nearly      200,000.          It will be seen that rapid progress has been     made in the last two years.  The placing of contract!.; -x   to which reference has just been made, is a substant:-.     contribution towards creating employment in the     industries affected.
      The Minister of Labour,  supported by the Ministerof Health, urged  the acceptance of  the reoorxsfchdafcienof the Pisber  ConuBit/bee1 o 2eport in respect  of t heextension of Forest  Holdings,    Mr,  Chamberlain pointedout  that this  proposal was valuable as making specific provision for  married men.   No decision was  reached and  the matter is referred to  the  Cabinet.     The Committee approved all the  above schemes(with the exception  of that dealing  with Pores t Holdingswhich was reserved for further  consideration  by theCabinet) arid rejected all other proposals at the present time a   - They decided that no  particularpublic work should be specified and  that no definiteestimate should be given of the amount  of employmentforthcoming  from the application of these various measures.      Signed on behalf of the Committee                     WINSTON S,  CHURCHILL,                            OHAimiAN.tehall Gardens,  S.1V, 1.  6th November,  1928.
P* /-v tTJ9 f!j hAPPENDIX.Table of Schemes under the Electricity -(Supply)  Act,  1.9S6Total CapitalExpenditure by central Eleetri-oity Board onTransmissionLines and trans-forming Stations..(As estimated byElectricityCommiss ion)... Area    Popula-(Sauare  tion at miles)  1921         Census.Total value of contracts enteredinto by central electricity board in respect ofeach Scheme upto date. . al Scotland ricity Scheme, (Adopted&apos; 29th  1927 )  East England ricity Scheme, (Adopted 15thlary,:; ,1928;), ai England ricity Scheme, (Adopted 22nd  West and  Wales .gricity Scheme,  fAdooted 12thj?.r,  1928 ) c:OTAL4,980   3,761,200     .1,-9 00, 0008,820  11,392,561    7,870,258*     1,095,1701,6,14,6727,311   5,218,1469,082   6,980,9253,031,1814,204,45548.30,201  27,352,832   17,005,894 2,758,179In addition expenditure actually incurred,  or  approved   in connection Y/lth the standardisation  of frequency   amounts to  188,138.-11-&apos;0?his  includes  the  sun of  1,723,203 estimated by theElectricity  Commissioners as the  necessary capitalexpenditure  of the  London and Some Counties joint electricity  Authority under  the Scheme.

</content>
</cab>
