<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/198/0 images: 448-449</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I   I[This  Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]    ^fjPrinted for the Cabinet.  November 1928.SECRET.                                                     Copy No.   ^8CP. 335  (28).CABINET.PREFERENCE  IN GOVERNMENT  CONTRACTS.                NOTE BY THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER.    I CIRCULATE, for the information of my colleagues, a Memorandum prepared bythe Treasury in reply to the Memorandum by the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs on Preference in Government Contracts (CP. 300 (28)).                                                                  W. S. C.    Treasury Chambers,  S.W.1,         November 6, 1928.    1.   As Mr.  Amery points out, the question whether the rates of preference should be fixed and made public was considered in 1923.  The grounds on which itwas opposed by the Treasury are fully set out in the Memorandum prepared by themfor the Inter-Departmental Committee under the Chairmanship of Sir H. LlewellynSmith, which was preparing the agenda for the Economic Conference. A copy of an extract from that Memorandum is appended hereto.  It will be observed that theviews of the Treasury were reached after consultation with the Inter-DepartmentalContracts Co-ordinating Committee and were in agreement with the views expressedby the  members  of that  Committee in the light of their practical experience of contract prices.  To  quote  from the Minutes of the Contracts Committee meetingon the 27th July, 1923 :  &quot; It was recommended that a definite, maximum percentageof preference should not  be  fixed, that  it  was preferable  for  each  case  to beconsidered on its merits and with due  regard  to the aggregate extra cost which thepreference would cost. . . .  The Committee were definitely of opinion that no public announcement should be made, as such announcement would tend unduly to  restrictcompetition and  to raise prices.&quot;    2.   The Treasury submit that nothing has happened since 1923  to warrant any revision of the above policy.  The number of occasions on which public criticism isaroused by the deliberate placing abroad of a contract which might have gone to aBritish  firm  if  the latter  had quoted a  lower  price, is  negligible.  And in theparticular case  which gave rise to this  controversy, the publication  of  a  fixedpreference of 25 per cent.,  which appears to be  the rate suggested by Mr.  Amery,would not have  secured the order for British firms, who required a preference of nearly 40 per cent., nor would it have satisfied  the  Government critics,  who would still have argued that that rate was wholly insufficient to meet the difference in- wagecosts, &amp;c, in this bronze wire contract.    As  matters  now stand, the contracting  Departments reserve  the  right, with treasury sanction, if necessary, to grant a preference  even in  excess of 25 per cent.in very  special cases; and, as a result of present policy,  the percentage of orders placed abroad is  very small  indeed.    3.   It is submitted, therefore, that no practical advantage would be gained bythe adoption of  Mr. Amery&apos;s suggestion;  on the contrary, it would  deprive the      [18423]
contracting Departments of the discretion to give a smaller preference when, owingto the operation of a ring,  no bond fide  competition between British manufacturersexists, and the  result would almost  certainly be  to raise prices  in the far more numerous cases where a preference of much less than 25 per cent, at present suffices.     Treasury Chambers,  November 6, 1928.    EXTRACT FROM TREASURY MEMORANDUM  PREPARED IN 1923 FOR  SIR  H. LLEWELLYN SMITH&apos;S                                INTER-DEPARTMENTAL COMMITTEE.    ON the 10th July last the Imperial Economic Conference (Documents) Committee of the cabinet considered  a memorandum prepared by the  Inter-Departmental  Committee, under Sir H. LlewellynSmith, which is preparing for the Imperial Economic. Conference, and agreed -        &quot;to request the  Inter-Departmental Committee  to  examine,  in  consultation  with the        Departments concerned,  the question of Imperial preference in public contracts with a view        to an endeavour being made to  secure a common measure of agreement as to the adoption        of a uniform policy by all the Departments.&quot;    Sir H. Llewellyn Smith&apos;s Committee asked to be furnished with the views of the Treasury on thisquestion,  and  the   Treasury,  in their  turn,  have  consulted   the  Inter-Departmental  ContractsCo-ordinating Committee.  Special meetings of that Committee, attended by all the  Departmentsmainly  concerned, were held on the 27th July last and the 3rd October, the minutes  of which are attached herewith.*                                           i    The Treasury are in  agreement with the views expressed  in these Minutes, and  their  general conclusions are as follows:.-     1. It is desirable that  there should be uniformity of aim between the  Government  Departments           concerned, viz., to give an effective preference to Dominion and Colonial products where           such products are available and are of the requisite quality, subject to exceptions in special           cases in which the cost of such preference would be  inordinate.    2. But the preference should only  be  such as is  necessary to  counterbalance an unavoidable           difference in price in favour of the foreign producer.   It should riot be administered  in           such a way as to enable the Empire producer in&apos; any way to exploit  the British taxpayer           by the formation of  rings, or short of that, by levying an unreasonable profit.    3. The requirements of Government Departments and  the  circumstances of particular contracts           differ so greatly that it is not advisable to lay  down rigid rules as to the administration           of this policy, or, express the preference to  be  given in terms of a  definite percentage.           The Treasury  deliberately1  abstained in  1919 from  laying  down  any percentage  up  to           which Departments  might grant  preference.     &quot;     &apos;    4.  The dangers  involved  in  adherence  to a rigid  percentage,  viz.,  the elimination of foreign           competition  and an  undue increase in  prices,  are  obvious, and  the percentage figures         .  adopted by the  Admiralty as  a broad guide are not in fact rigid.    5. There are&apos; serious disadvantages iii  publishing to contractors the  percentage scale on which           Departments may find it convenient to work.;    6. It  will be observed that the supplies  which can be obtained from the Dominions and Colonies           consist almost  entirely  of  food  and raw materials, and that, generally  speaking, the           difference in market prices as  between British Empire and foreign products is not great.    7. It   has&quot; been  suggested  that in  placing contracts for  manufactured  articles  Government           Departments  should stipulate for the  use  of Empire raw materials, but  the practical           difficulties in the  way of enforcing compliance  with  such a rule would in most cases  be           almost insuperable.    The  Treasury ^agree,  however, with the  Contracts  Co-ordinating           Committee, that in the relatively few cases in which  the origin of the raw material-can  be           identified in the finished  article,  the use of such material should be  secured by means  of           administrative action, provided that this  can be done without  undue extra cost or undue           limitation of supply.                                   &apos;    :                  v     *&apos;    8.  A  memorandum circulated on behalf of the Colonies and Protectorates suggests that in this           country,  and  wherever  there is a  preferential rate for  British  produce, tenders  for           Government contracts should be  called  for  &quot; duty-paid,&quot; so that the, benefit which the         &apos;  -preference&apos; is intended to confer should be  secured.    This  is  already the practice-;of         -  British Government Departments, in so far  as the goods supplied are for consumption;in           this  country  and  dutiable.   Substantially this complies with  the  request  in the         .  memorandum.t-     .         i   r   \   -&quot;                    -    9.  The Treasury would suggest that if the question is raised by the Dominion Governments, the           answer of His Majesty&apos;s Government should be on the  general lines  indicated  above,  an           assurance being given that it  is the full intention of  His Majesty&apos;s Government to adhere           to the policy laid down by their predecessors,  arid  that they would  always..be ready  to           investigate any case . in : which a  Dominion  or  Colonial  Government. considered &apos; that the           spirit of this undertaking was not being complied&apos;with.    * Not circulated.    t The case where goods are bought in this country for consumption abroad, and subsequentlyimported into a British Possession which gives a preference duty-free (if it occurs) constitutes an exception, though an unimportant.one:   &apos;                              ;    -     &apos;

</content>
</cab>
