<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/9/83 images: 486-491</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Copy No.WAR CABINET.CONFERMENT OF BRITISH NATIONALITY (WAR POWERS) BILL.Memorandum by the Home Secretary and the Foreign Secretary.WE submit herewith for the consideration of the War Cabinet a revised draft of a Bill for conferring British nationality upon certain classes of Frenchcitizens.The history of the matter is as follows : On the 4th July, 1940, the PrimeMinister, when announcing in the House of Commons the measures which hadbeen taken to prevent the French fleet from falling into German hands, said ;&quot; The French sailors in the main cheerfully accepted the end of a period of uncertainty. A considerable number 800 or 900 have expressed desire tocontinue the war and some have asked for British nationality. This we are readyto grant without prejudice to the other Frenchmen, numbered by thousands, whoprefer to fight on with us as Frenchmen.&quot;In August 1940 there was an exchange of letters between the Prime Ministerand General de Gaulle concerning the French Volunteer Force, and the PrimeMinister submitted a memorandum of agreement in which there was the following passage : &quot; His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom will use their best endeavours at the time of the conclusion of peace to help the French volun-teers to regain any rights, including national status, of which they may havebeen deprived as a result of their participation in the struggle against thecommon enemies. His Majesty&apos;s Government are willing to afford special facilities to such volunteers to acquire British nationality, and will seek any necessary powers.&quot;On the 8th August, 1940, there was submitted to the War Cabinet the first draft of a Bill on this subject. In this draft Bill it was proposed to give special facilities for obtaining British nationality to any Frenchman who (a) &quot;is amember of the armed forces engaged in the prosecution of any war in which HisMajesty is engaged at the time of the application,&quot; or (b) &quot; is a person able and willing to give valuable assistance in the prosecution of such a war in some othercapacity.&quot; The object of these proposals was to cover Frenchmen who are orbecome members of His Majesty&apos;s armed forces; Frenchmen who are serving or may be serving in any French force recognised by His Majesty, including civilianpersonnel who may be attached to that force; and certain French civilians abroad,notably in Egypt and some of the French colonies.As a result of the discussion in the Cabinet the draft of the clause defining the classes of persons to whom such special facilities for naturalization might be offered was considered.2.   Subsequently there was further consultation through the Spears Missionwith representatives of General de Gaulle, and in a letter received fromM. Cassin, his legal adviser, it was stated that General de Gaulle &quot; could not[22854]Printed for the War Cabinet.   August 1941.SECRET.W.P. (G) (41) 83.August 27, 1941.
envisage allowing members of the Free French Forces as long as the war lastscomplete freedom to apply for British nationality,&quot; that the General contemplated that use would be made of the special facilities during the period of hostilities in particular individual cases which it is impossible to lay down in advance,and that special facilities would chiefly be desired at the end of the war for&quot;volunteers who have founded families or settled permanently in England. ... or in the case of other volunteers who might be unable to recover their former nationality.&quot; These observations of General de Gaulle do not, of course,apply to Frenchmen serving in His Majesty&apos;s armed forces, to whom the PrimeMinisters pledge was in the first instance addressed. It is thought that such ofthose who may wish to apply for British nationality will do so at once.General de Gaulle recognised that the present Bill could only be a temporary measure operating until the expiry of the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act, buthe asked that the British Government would &quot; be so good as to address a letter tohim indicating its intention, should the period provided for in the present Billprove to be insufficient, to take steps to extend the period or otherwise make such provision as may be necessary at that time in the interests of the Free french forces.&apos;&apos;M. Cassin went on to say : &apos;&apos; When that time comes it would perhaps beopportune to settle the converse problem. The British Government might adoptmeasures in a liberal sense enabling Frenchmen naturalized as British subjectsduring the war to divest themselves of their British nationality in order to becomeonce more exclusively French nationals.&quot;It does not seem necessary, nor would it be desirable on grounds of general principle, to give General de Gaulle any undertaking with regard to legislation atthe end of the war. Moreover, the Free French are apparently no longer pressing for a definite undertaking, as M. Cassin recently stated that he was persuadedthat, if the facts revealed that certain particular requirements had not been met at the expiration of the Emergency Powers Act, 1939, the British Governmentwould take steps to bring about whatever alterations might appear to be necessary.But we see no reason why the facilities granted by the temporary Act to membersof the armed forces should not be extended to persons who, having been membersof the armed forces engaged in the prosecution of the war, have ceased to be members of such forces, provided they apply and get their naturalisation certifi-cates within the period for which the temporary Act is in operation. In fact,it seems essential not to exclude French soldiers or sailors who may have beeninvalided out of the forces.General de Gaulle also asked that the facilities should be extended to the widows of men who would have been eligible for such facilities, and this seemsa proper extension of the provisions. Minor children who are left orphans canbe dealt with under the existing law.Clause 1 of the Bill has been redrafted to give effect to these extensions.M. Cassin, who has seen the revised draft, states that he entirely approves of the alteration of Clause 1.As indicated in the Home Secretary&apos;s memorandum of the 10th August, 1940(W.P. (G) (40) 212), the Bill has been drafted as a self-contained measure, theprovisions of which will not have effect in the Dominions. The concurrence ofthe Dominions was, however, invited to the original proposals so as to minimise the breach in the principle that there shall be no alteration in the common code of British nationality law except with their concurrence. New Zealand concurred,but South Africa, while raising no objection to legislation on the part of theUnited Kingdom, intimated that they did not intend to legislate themselves.No replies have as yet been received from Canada or the Commonwealth ofAustralia. The proposed extension of the classes of persons to whom thefacilities should be granted would not appear to affect the attitude of theDominions and no further communication has been sent to them pending adecision by the War Cabinet on this Memorandum.H. M.A. E.Home Office,August 27, 1941.
4. &amp; 5 Geo. 6. Conferment of British. Nationality.(War Powers).DRAFTof a&quot;CD       T      TJLLP      JL      Ji-JtoMake temporary provision for empowering a Secretary.  a.d. 194:of State to confer British nationality upon aliens       -who are or have recently been French nationals andare able and willing to give, or have given, valuable assistance in the prosecution of the war, and forpurposes connected therewith.*E it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, byand with the advice and consent Of the Lords Spiritualand Temporal, and Commons, in this present parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same as follows : 1. If a Secretary of State is satisfied, on application made power toto him at any time during the present war period by an alien grantappearing to him to be or to have been at any time during that certificatesperiod a French national-   X,.(a) that the alien is a member of the armed forces engagedin the prosecution of any war in which His majesty is engaged at the time of the application, or is able and willing to give valuable assistance in some other capacity in the prosecution of such a war ; or(b) that the alien is a person who has at any time since the[first day of July nineteen hundred and forty] been amember of any armed forces engaged in the prosecution of any war in which His Majesty has been engaged since that date, or has given valuable assistance in someother capacity in the. prosecution of such a war, oris the widow of any such person,and that the alien is of good character, the Secretary of state may, if he thinks fit, grant a certificate of British nationalityto the alien.
2 Conferment of British 4 &amp; 5 Geo. 6.Nationality (War Powers).2. (1) A person to whom a certificate of British nationalityis granted under this Act shall, subject to the provisions ofthis Act, be entitled to all political and other rights, powers, and privileges, and be subject to all obligations, duties, and liabilitiesto which a natural-born British subject is entitled or subject, 5and, as from such date as may be specified in the certificate,have to all intents and purposes the status of a natural-bornBritish subject.(2) Where a certificate of British nationality granted under thisAct is in force with respect to a man married to a wife who is not 10a British subject, the wife shall not become a British subject by virtue of the certificate unless, within the period of twelvemonths from the date of the certificate or within such longer period as the Secretary of State may in special circumstancesallow she makes a declaration that she desires to acquire British 15nationality.(3) Where a Secretary of State grants a certificate of british nationality to an alien, the Secretary of State may, if he thinks fit, on the application of that alien, include in the certificatethe.name of any child of the alien born before the date of the 20certificate and being a minor, and that child thereupon, if not already a British subject, shall become a British subject; but any such child may within one year of attaining his majoritymake a declaration of alienage and shall thereupon cease to bea British subject. 25(4) Any child born after a certificate of British nationalityhas been granted to his father shall (unless the certificate hasbeen revoked before the birth) be a British subject notwithstanding that the child may have been born outside His Majesty&apos;sdominions and allegiance. 303. (1) If, in the case of any person to whom a certificate of British nationality has been granted under this Act, a Secretaryof State is satisfied that the circumstances are such that if acertificate of naturalization had been granted to him under theBritish Nationality and Status of Aliens Act 1914, it would have 35.been the duty of the Secretary of State to revoke the certificate of naturalization, the Secretary of State shall by order revoke the certificate of British nationality.(2) Where a Secretary of State revokes a certificate of british nationality the revocation shall have effect from such date as 40the Secretary of State may direct, and thereupon the certificateshall be given up and cancelled, and any person refusing ordelaying to give up his certificate shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine of one hundred pounds.A.D. 1941.Effect ofcertificateof british nationality.Revocationof certifi-cates ofBritishnationality.4 &amp; 5 Geo. 5..c 17.
4 &amp; 5 Geo. 6. Conferment of british nationality (War Powers).(3) Section seven A of the British Nationality and Status of    a.d. 1941.Aliens Act 1914 (which relates to the effect of the revocation of        -certificates of naturalization upon wives and minor children)shall apply with respect to the revocation of certificates grantedg under this Act as it applies with respect to the revocation of certificates of naturalization.4. A Secretary of State may make regulations for the purposes Power to of this Act and for prescribing any form which it is in his opinion makeexpedient to prescribe for those purposes. regu a lons&quot;interpretation.IO    5. (1) This Act may be cited as the Conferment of British Short titleNationality (War Powers) Act 1940. [saving] ^and^[(2) Nothing in this Act shall affect, or be deemed to affect,the law of any Dominion, as defined by section one of the statute of Westminster 1931, notwithstanding that the Dominion is15 not one to&apos;which section four of that Statute extends.](3) In this Act the expression &quot; the present war period&quot;means the period beginning with the third day of Septembernineteen hundred and thirty-nine and ending with the expiry of the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act 1939.
Conferment  of british nationality (WarPowers).DRAFTof aBILLTo make temporary provision for em-powering a Secretary of State to conferBritish nationality upon aliens who areor have recently been French nationalsand are able and willing to give valuable assistance in the prosecution of any war in which His Majesty may be engaged,and for purposes connected therewith.XXXIV.- D.   (5.)29th August 1941.*28-2(11969)

</content>
</cab>
