<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/80/0 images: 53-66</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Co136[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.  May, 1919.SEOEET, G.T. 7313.THE LABOUR SITUATION.Report from the Ministry of Labour for the week ending 21st May, 1919.Part I: Industrial Action.Part II: Demobilisation and Resettlement: The Training of Unemployed Women.Part III: Press Comments.(1) Labour and Socialist Press: (A) Foreign Affairs.-^-Pe&amp;GG Terms, League of Nations, German and Allied Statesmen, Russia, Labour Manifestos. (B) Home Affairs. Income-Tax, Unemployed Donation, Coal Commission, Conscription, Women in Industry, Peace Celebrations.(2) Daily Press on Demobilisation and Resettlement. Military Labour on the Land, Sir D. Haig and the Appointments Department.(1) General-Miners, Bakers, Munitions, Peace Terms, Amalgamation groping, Triple Alliance, Political Prisoners, Teachers, Railwaymen, Labour Party, Vehicle Workers, Shipbuilding, Federation of British Industries, Unemployment, Mersey Docks, Co-operation and Trade Unionism, Postal Clerks, Joint Industrial Councils, Trade Boards.(2) District Reports.Part V: Disputes.(a) Involving a Stoppage of Work (6) Not Involving a Stoppage of Work.Mr. Straker, of the Miners&apos; Federation, is reported to have announced recently that unless the Coal Commission reported in favour of nationalisation of the coal mines there would be &quot; grave danger of serious upheaval in the coal-fields.&quot; More recently still, Mr. Tom Mann, writing of the War Office inquiry into Trade Unionism in the Army, said that even votes at the next General Election would have little efEect; &quot; for trade unionists to withhold their services at proper times in proper places would give a punish-ment direct and effective, worthy of workers possessed of intelligence.&quot; These are the latest and typical manifestations of a movement which has always been in existence, but has gathered great impetus recently, as a result of the increase in the strength of the forces behind it. In essence it is the result of the reaction against political, as opposed to industrial, action which began about 1910, and of the teachings of the school whose motto is that industrial action precedes political action and controls the strength of it. This reaction may roughly be said to be the key-note of the whole labour situation since that time. But even the most extreme upholders of economic power as the key to all power have never recommended the actual strike except as a last resort; in this they differ from the thorough-going syndicalist found more usually in France than in this country, for whom the strike is an end in itself, continual sectional striking a preparation for the great general strike, and striking for any other end actually reactionary. Our more prosaic and less philosophical pioneers on the other hand recommend, first, organisation, so as to make the threat of a serious strike a real danger to the community ; secondly, the full use of this(c 1789)   150  5/19  h &amp; s . aSummary.Part IV:Part I. Industrial Action.
threat to strike; and lastly, and only if necessary, the strike itself. Here lies the cleavage with the French syndicalist. For him, so long as one can get the strike, organisation does not matter; on the other hand for the English revolutionary socialist a great parade of industrial power, even if it have nothing behind it, is of immense importance.In the less highly organised industries in this country it may be said that as yet only the first stage has been reached ; but if one surveys the record of organisation that has taken place since 1910, there is little room for doubt that the reaction against the political weapon has been a force in shaping it. The outstanding event in its development from this point of view is, of course, the inauguration df the Triple Alliance, formed quite definitely as a weapon for industrial action in 1915. In the more highly organised trades the first aim has already practically been accomplished, and fulfilment of tie second aim  the full use of the threat of the strike is perhaps reaching its zenith ; and it is here that the practical importance of these considerations emerges. For it would be a mistake to suppose, for instance, as many people appear to do, that the more extreme miners&apos; leaders, or even the more level-headed, look upon the Coal Commission as an impartial tribunal, appointed as the best means of settling the future of the industry. They look upon it as a means to certain ends envisaged before it was ever set up ; and if it does not attain those ends, other means will have to be found for doing so. And, of course, in a sense, the miners&apos; leaders are perfectly justified. They got the Commission through economic power, by means of the threat of a strike. It is impossible to conceive of an ill-organised industry playing the part the Miners&apos; Federation did in the negotiations which led to the Coal Commission, and equally impossible to conceive of their producing such an outcome. Mr. Straker has already voiced this view in the statement quoted above. This does not mean, however, that, even from the point of view of those who oppose and would like to see diminished the economic power of the miners, the Commission may not be a good thing. It has thrown a great deal of light where it was needed ; it has spent a considerable amount of time during which hot feeling may have had time to cool; and whatever decision it comes to will have the backing of that portion of public opinion in the country, even among the miners themselves, which looks upon it as an impartial tribunal, and this is a very real force with which the Miners&apos; Federation has to reckon. But all this leaves the main point untouched : it does not go to show that from the miners&apos; point of view, the Commission is not a means to preconceived ends, but merely that it is a means that possesses certain drawbacks, which possibly explains some initial hesitation on their part to adopt it. Even from their point of view, however, they would appear to have taken the wiser course. The actual strike possesses disadvantages of a similar type quite, as great if not greater than these. Organisation is never so strong as it looks.It may be expected then that if the miners fail to get what they want from the Coal Commission, they will attempt to get it otherwise ; and that such an attempt will be controlled by consideration of industrial power alone, and not by any feeling that an impartial tribunal has pronounced against them, except in so far as such a feeling may create a public opinion unfavourable to further action. But it would again be a mistake to suppose that even if they get what they want, their industrial power will have been, used up, so to speak, and need no further be reckoned with. Industrial power, like any other sort of power, grows with success and use; it is, moreover, a versatile thing that can be used in all sorts of ways. Already the miners have on hand a number of experiments with a view to substituting it for older political methods. Thus a movement has been started to deflect the Government^ policy in foreign affairs by means of it. The miners coupled their accept-ance of the Interim Report of the Coal Commission with a threatening resolution on the question of the withdrawal of troops to Russia, and subsequently further action was taken in conjunction with the Triple Alliance, which, however, as was anticipated at the time, appears not to have come to very much. A similar resolution regarding Conscription was passed at the same time. Again, the miners in South Wales led, it is to be noticed, by two of their political leaders, members of the House of Commons have just resolved to refuse further to pay income-tax on the present basis, and to call on the M.F.G.B. as a whole to take similar action; while the Northumberland miners, in addition to appealing to the M.F.G.B. with regard to this matter, have resolved, if necessary, to lay the case before the Triple Alliance with a view to taking industrial action.The same is true at the present time throughout the whole area of industrial organisa-tion. The more such organisation and the power which follows it grows, the more varied and numerous will be the uses to which that power will be put or attempted to be put; and there is in the long ran only one antidote to its abuse, namely, a parallel growth of the social responsibilities of the organisations wielding it.
We have taken the miners as the chief example of the present forms which the reaction from political methods is assuming, because they are, so to speak, the boldest and most progressive organisation in the field, but there are other examples to be found. The railwaymen are in a precisely similar position to that of the miners. They gained their rec mt settlement by the threat of industrial action; that settlement was not final, and wh :n a final settlement is attempted, as it will have to be sooner or later, no doubt the railwaymen will repeat the same tactics, perhaps with some new devices which by than time will have been discovered to be effective.&apos; The same tendency can be seen, too, it a more general form, in the large crop of Commissions and Committees recently appointed to settle definite industrial problems. The increased industrial power of labour and, it must be added here, of employers too has made the ordinary legislative procedure inadequate, with the result that a sort of devolution into the industrial sphere has taken place, and with it has gone a certain amount of power from the supreme legislative assembly which in these matters becomes merely a body for registering decisions arrived at outside itself. The most important example of this, of course, is the inception of a supreme Joint Industrial Council, which will presumably, if it works successfully, in the future attempt to settle industrial conditions largely without reference to Parliament. This view is undoubtedly held by strong personalities both on the employees and on the worker&apos;s side, and is clearly reflected in the Report of the Provisional Joint Committee. This may be looked upon in part at any rate, as the result of increased power on the part of both the partners in industry, that is, in the enhanced importance which novel conditions have brought to producers, as such, in the community ; and thus may have its counterpart in the various protests as to ill-treatment and spoliation, emanating at present from con-suming quarters.Part II. Demobilisation and Resettlement.The Training of Unemployed Women.The elaboration of arrangements in accordance with general schemes sanctioned by the Treasury for the training of certain classes of unemployed women, is making progress. Training of this kind had been the subject of much discussion, notably by the local Employment Committees and the divisional Employment Councils, before the Ministry of Labour was in a position to proceed with its plans, and a number of local proposals, especially as regards domestic workers, were therefore already in existence. Full advan-tage has been taken of this preliminary work so far as it was of a practical nature ; and in drawing up training schemes the Ministry is maintaining contact with local Employment Committees and Employment Councils, and in particular with the Women&apos;s Sub-Com-mittees of the local Employment Committees. It is intended, in fact, that the work shall be carried out by the Ministry in close consultation with these Sub-Committees, which act under the general direction of their respective committees. In order that the Women&apos;s Sub-Committees may be as representative as possible, they are to be extended, where necessary, by co-opting members from the local education authorities and the War Pensions Committees. The Ministry will thus be kept informed of openings and facilities for training, of local industries and processes in which the demand for women&apos;s labour exceeds the supply, and of the number of unemployed women suitable for training to supply the deficiency. Discussion of local conditions with these committees has already been carried out widely, and a number of draft schemes for various localities are under consideration by the Ministry.The training which it will thus be possible to provide for unemployed women is more restricted both in kind and in extent than was contemplated by many of the committees in their independent proposals. Two general schemes have received sanction; the broader provides for the vocational training for young women who have been engaged on war work and are registered as unemployed at the Employment Exchanges, and the narrower for the provision of domestic training in the case of unemployed women, who either have been married during the war and have not yet set up house, or produce satis-factory evidence that they are engaged to be married, and who in either case do not propose to continue in industry.  The outlines of these two schemes are as follows : (a) Vocational Training. Training under this scheme will be for normal women&apos;s trades and for processes known as women&apos;s processes before the war. It will be instituted only where recent inquiry shows that there is a need for workers in such occupations, and a reasonable prospect of employment. The ex-war workers accepted under this scheme must be registered as unemployed at an(C 1789) A 2
Employment Exchange, and must either have lost their skill by reason of their war work or have missed through that work the opportunity of gaining the knowledge and experience required for such occupations. In such cases, a maintenance grant of 255. a week will be made to the trainee in lieu of out-of-work donation. The grant is reduced to 15s. after the first 13 weeks of out-of-work donation has expired, but a subsistence allowance of 10s. a week may then be made if the woman is still living away from home. The training, where of a technical nature, may be given in actual works, in technical trade schools pro-vided by the local education authorities, or in other premises, as for example, in the Government Instructional Factories which were in existence under the Ministry of Munitions. The period of training will naturally vary in length, but it is expected that, where the instruction given is in the nature of a &quot; refresher &quot; course, it will last from 1 to 4 months, and for those who are without any experience of the work, from 2 to 6 months. On the average it is believed that training will occupy about three months. If the period of six months for which the out-of-work donation is originally due is completed before training is finished, it is proposed to extend the maintenance allowance to cover the remainder of the training period, provided that this does not involve an exten-sion for more than three months. Courses in domestic training will be included under this scheme.(b) Domestic Training for Wives and Fiancees. This scheme was originally prepared in November, 1918, and was strongly supported by the Women&apos;s Trade Union Advisory Committee. Although it was not sanctioned until late in March, 1919, when the immediate need for which it was designed had to some extent grown less urgent, it is believed that the scheme will still be of considerable value in assisting over a difficult period women who have no intention of permanently entering the field of employment, but who, apart from this scheme, would have to compete with permanent workers. The sub-sistence allowance given during training under this scheme is equal to the amount of out-of-work donation to which the women would have been entitled had they not been undergoing a training course. Thus, if a woman enters upon training before she has exhausted the period of 13 weekly payments allowed under the original scheme, she receives 25s. a week. If she has already received these 13 weekly payments, the subsistence allowance is reduced to the lower figure payable under the extended scheme with the addition, however, of 5s. a week in cases where the woman is living away from home. The training given is to include housework, kitchen work, sewing, washing, ironing, infant welfare, hygiene, nursing, and other practical instruc-tion in household matters. The instruction is to be carried out by certificated teachers in domestic subjects, and it is intended to use some of the Government hostels as training centres for these purposes, while canteens in some of the National Factories are also available.The general discussion of these schemes with the local Committees has brought to light an interesting difference of opinion among representatives of organised labour on the whole question of training for women. On the one hand, the view is expressed that demoralisation and waste are involved in a long period of idleness subsidised by the out-of-work donation, and that consequently the State should regard it as a duty to train these women. On the other hand, it is thought that by training women the State is assisting the employer to resist the raising of wages, and, in fact, is offering a potential encouragement to sweating by increasing the supply of competent female workers. On the whole, the former of these views, which was that put forward at the time of the armistice by the Women&apos;s Trade Union Advisory Committee, may be taken to represent the more considered judgment of labour. Other criticisms are directed against the limitations of the official schemes. It is urged, in particular, that a maintenance allowance which may be as low as 15s. is too little. Difficulties, in fact, have already been met owing to the restriction of the maintenance allowance to an amount equivalent to the out-of-work donation. It has been found impossible, for example, to arrange for the training of women in private clothing and boot factories, because the prescribed rate of wages now fixed by mutual agreement or by the Court of Arbitration is in excess of the maintenance allowance which the Ministry of Labour is authorised to pay. Since the employers will not take these women on as learners in the normal way at the prescribed rate, which is regarded as prohibitive for an untrained worker, the women are for the present unemployed, until otheT arrange-ments can be made for their training. Owing to such difficulties as these a revised scheme is now under consideration.
Part III. Press Comments. (1) Labour and Socialist Press. (A)-Foreign Affairs.The Peace Terms.The criticism of the official abstract of the proposed treaty of Peace is voluminous. It is based partly upon ideas of justice and partly upon ideas of expediency; much of it is from a national or international point of view,, but some of it is from a purely proletarian point of view.  These aspects will be treated separately.(a) The Justice of the Peace Terms.In discussing the official abstract of the Peace Terms &quot; Rob Roy,&quot; in &quot; Forward,&quot; states first of all the principles by which he is guided in his judgment. He thinks we are entitled to claim from Germany that she shall make compensation for the damage she lias done : but he says, we must remember the obligations of honour and interest that rest on ourselves and our Allies. In the main, he asserts, President Wilson&apos;s &quot; Four-teen Points &quot; must be the basis of the Peace, but he points out that the conditions do not exist in Europe for a rigorous application of these. Broadly, his judgment is that the draft Treaty embodies the principles of justice. In the same paper, however, Mr. C. IL Norman, after stating that the logical foundation of the Treaty was the general proposition that Germany was solely responsible for the war, endeavours to demonstrate that this general proposition is not true. Mr. Arthur Ponsonby, in the &quot; Labour Leader,&quot; maintains that each one of President Wilson&apos;s &quot; points &quot; that relate to Germany has been infringed. Mr. Ramsay Macdonald, in &quot; Forward,&quot; says that the principle of self-determination is violated at every turn, and Mr. Philip Snowden, in the&apos;&quot; Labour Leader,&quot; says that every line and phrase of the draft is wrong. On the other hand, Mr. Robert Blatchford, in the &quot; Clarion,&quot; says that Germany is the one nation in the world which has no right to ask for anything but impoverishment and punishment and slavery: he thinks the terms are dangerously lenient. &quot;Justice&quot; thinks the terms cannot be described as imperialistic, in so far as they affect Germany.(b) The Expediency of the Peace Terms.The &quot; New Statesman&quot; says that the terms are &quot; Prussian terms, worked out with Prussian thoroughness and with Prussian folly,&quot; and does not think that England will go to war again to enforce the more onerous of the conditions. The &quot; Nation &quot; says that the permanent impoverishment of the German people (which it maintains will be the effect of the Treaty as proposed) is a poor security for reparation and a poorer one for a lasting peace. The &quot; New Age,&quot; somewhat ironically, congratulates Germany on her prospective freedom from Imperialism and states that the war will have brought her, at any rate, peace and happiness. Mr. Ramsay Macdonald, in &quot;Forward,&quot; Bays: &quot;This super Brest-Litovsk ultimatum is a bad bit of business,&quot; and sees nothing approaching peace in the terms. The &quot; Bradford Pioneer &quot; exclaims that the vision of world peace is shattered by the terms.(c) The &quot; Proletariat&quot; and the Peace.The &quot;Workers&apos; Dreadnought&quot; states that the draft Peace ignores the interest of the workers in the Saar territory and in Danzig and provides for the dissolution of the Workers&apos; and Soldiers&apos; Councils in Schleswig. The &quot;Dreadnought&quot; thinks that the inevitable result of the Peace (whether the German Government signs it or no) will be a union between Soviet Russia, Hungary and a revolutionised Germany and calls upon British workers to stand by these against the capitalist Entente. The &quot; Call &quot; professes no astonishment at the Terms, but calls for a class war to remedy them. These thoughts are shared to a certain degree by other writers. Mr. Arthur Ponsonby, in the &quot; Labour Leader,&quot; says that the hope of the world is now in the new forces that have arisen east of the Rhine, while Mr. Ramsay Macdonald, in &quot; Forward,&quot; asserts that Labour is free (whenever it comes to power) to revise the terms,It may be noted that Mr. J. L. Garvin&apos;s article in the &quot; Observer &quot; of 11th May is quoted with enthusiastic approval in the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; and the &quot; Bradford Pioneer.&quot;The League of Nations.In the discussion of the Peace Terms there are many judgments passed upon the League (C 1789) A 3
it of Nations. The &quot; Dreadnought&quot; says that the League is undemocratic and merely a sectional alliance, and describes the &quot; Labour Charter &quot; as a sham. The &quot; Labour Leader&quot; thinks that the incorporation of the Covenant of the League in the draft Treaty is hypocritical and insulting. Mr. Ramsay Macdonald, in &quot; Forward,&quot; says that the mandatory principle has now ceased to have any meaning because the predominant partners in the League are those who will carry out the mandates. On the other hand, &quot; Justice,&quot; and &quot; Rob Roy,&quot; in &quot;Forward,&quot; both accept the League as an encouraging sign. The &quot; New Statesman &quot; regards it as the saving grace of the treaty, but thinks that the &quot; inevit-able revision of the treaty &quot; will strain to the breaking point the moral resources of the League. The &quot; Bradford Pioneer &quot; thinks that the League will not hang together long, but will dissolve in endeavouring to settle the Austrian and Turkish problems. &quot; Justice &quot; says that the permanence of the League will depend on a good understanding being main-tained between Great Britain, France and America, and therefore welcomes the proposed Anglo-American guarantee of security to France : while the &quot; British Citizen&quot; and the &quot; Democrat&quot; suggest that the need for this guarantee should explode the idea that the League of Nations is going to mark the end of war.German and Allied Statesmen.&quot; Justice &quot; and the &quot; New Statesman &quot; both attack Herr Scheidemann for insincerity, while the &quot; Dreadnought&quot; maintains that the German Government has made a more generous response to the needs of the masses than any of the &quot; Allied Capitalist Govern-ments.&quot; The &quot; Labour Leader &quot; expresses the opinion that Count Brockdorf-Rantzau made an &quot; excellent speech &quot; and a ,f dignified statement.&quot; President Wilson is attacked by Mr. F. W. Jowett in the &quot; Bradford Pioneer &quot; and, in the same paper, Mr. Joseph King concludes that &quot; the philosopher in the rostrum is not much better than the general in the saddle for setting the world straight.&quot;Russia.Mr. David Lowe, in &quot; Forward,&quot; attributes the continuance of the war against Russia to the desire of Hebraic and Gallic moneylenders to have guarantees for their money. The &quot; New Statesman &quot; thinks that the expulsion of the Bolsheviks from Petrograd would be a great relief to the Bolshevik Government. The &quot; Labour Leader&quot; publishes a document purporting to be the reply of the Russian Soviet Government to a proposal of the Peace Conference on 22nd January that all Russian parties should meet together to negotiate a peace.Labour Manifestos on the Peace.&quot; Justice &quot; doubts whether the Parliamentary Labour Party will approve of the Labour Party Executive^ manifesto on the peace terms, and doubts the authority of the so-called Permanent Commission of the International to issue manifestos on behalf of the International. The Merthyr &quot; Pioneer &quot; regards the Labour Party&apos;s manifesto as a :c tame protest,&quot; and the &quot; Labour Leader &quot; speaks disparagingly of it as compared with the manifesto of the Union of Democratic Control, but the &quot; Yorkshire Factory Times &quot; &quot; supports the manifesto up to the hilt.&quot;(B) Home Affairs.The Income-Tax.Sir Leo Chiozza Money, in &quot; Forward,&quot; says that the attempt to rivet the income-tax on the poor should be stoutly resisted. Mr. Philip Snowden, in the &quot;Labour Leader,&quot; criticizes the Labour Party&apos;s proposal to exempt from income-tax all incomes under  250, and maintains that the proper method of improvement is an extension of the system of abatements for wives and children and dependants.Unemployment Donation.&quot; Forward &quot; reprints from the &quot; Edinburgh Evening News &quot; an article by Mr. George Kibble (of Leith), which gives an account of a meeting of a Court of Referees at the Tollcross Employment Exchange. He states that if radical improvement be not forth-coming, he will raise the whole matter before the Labour Party in Scotland and urge the withdrawal of the Labour representatives from all committees concerned with the Ministry of Labour. The &quot; Yorkshire Factory Times &quot; reports that, at a meeting of the Halifax Trades and Labour Council, the chairman made a speech attacking the
Part IV. (1) General.Miners.The Coal Commission held public sessions on the 15th, 16th, 20th, and 21st May. It continued to hear evidence on the effects of nationalisation from technical experts, cplonial representatives, and commercial magnates. The following have been the wit-nesses for the current week: Messrs. C. H. Merz and E. M. Harm (Consulting Engineers), the Hon. Sir C. G. Wade (Agent-Genera, 1 for New South Wales in London), Mr. H. A. Campbell (of New Zealand and New South Wales), Mr. W. Walter (Acting Inspector of Mines), Mr. C. Fletcher (Colliery Manager), Capt. R. Nelson (Electrical Inspector of Mines at the Home Office), Mr. T. J. Callaghan (President, Cardiff Chamber of Commerce),(C 1789) A administration of the donation and carried a resolution calling up all trade unions which had representatives on the local Court of Referees and Advisory Committee to withdraw them as a protest.Coal Commission.The &quot; New Age,&quot; the &quot; Call &quot; and the &quot; Clarion &quot; agree, that Mr. Smillie is mistaken in his pursuit of title-deeds, because, they think, inquiries into the legal titles of the coal owners are beside the real point. &quot; Forward &quot; thinks his examination of the &quot; Dukes &quot; was most effective socialist propaganda. The &quot; Dreadnought &quot; criticizes the commission as being bourgeois in character and only concerned with the perpetuation of the system of private ownership. It demands that the mine-owners be not compensated, and says that the economic strength of the Miners&apos; Federation is such that it can dictate its own terms and override any Act of Parliament.Conscription.Mr. Philip Snowden, in the &quot; Labour Leader,&quot; approves of the resolution of the Postal and Telegraph Clerks&apos; Association to take any action, in conjunction with organised labour, with the object of forcing the Government to abolish Conscription. The &quot; Call &quot; summons the Labour Party to use all its power to assault capitalist militarism and states that &quot; the Army is seething with the unrest of men who claim to be entitled to demobilisation by 11th May.&quot; The &quot;Yorkshire Factory Times&quot; refers to the &quot;Derby contract&quot; and urges the Labour Party to make a stir about &quot; this breach of an undertaking &quot; and to insist that the &quot; Derby &quot; men should come home at once. The &quot; Pioneer &quot; (Merthyr Tydfil), in a leading article, says &quot;the amount of oppression to which trade unionists in and put of the army are subjected, depends upon the disposition they show: they therefore must speak out against any Government. Act against Liberty.&quot;Women in Industry.Mr. Philip Snowden, in the &quot; Labour Leader,&quot; says that the Report of the Committee on Women in Industry is from the wonien&apos;s point of view disappointing. The &quot; Cotton Factory Times &quot; concludes that, for the present, the principle of equal pay for equal work is &quot; a safe enough demand.&quot;Peace Celebrations.The &quot; Labour Leader &quot; thinks that the intention of the Government to order a celebration of Peace is ludicrous : and it urges Trades Councils and Labour organisations to organise counter-demonstrations to demand a real peace.(2) The Daily Press on Demobilisation and Resettlement.Military Labour on the Land. The &quot; Birmingham Post&quot; (14th May) reports that at a meeting of the Bromsgrove District War Agricultural Committee on the 13th May, a resolution was passed protesting against the action of the Government in taking back to the Army skilled farm hands from the land, when unemployed men, quite unskilled in agriculture, might be taken instead.Sir Douglas Haig and the Appointments Department. &quot; The Times &quot; (14th May) reports that, when speaking at St. Andrews on the 13th May, Sir Douglas Haig made an appeal to employers to notify posts to the Appointments Department. He said that criticism was in some cases due to imperfect knowledge of what the Appointments Department had done and was endeavouring to do. The continuance of such criticism.could only result in the organisation falling into disrepute among men whom it was designed to help.
Mr. Gr. E. Perry (Chairman of Association of British Chemical Manufacturers), and Lord Gainford of Headlam (on behalf of the Mining Association of Great Britain).The Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain met on the 16th May under the presidency of Mr. Smillie. It was agreed to prepare a case in favour of nationalisation from the workmen&apos;s standpoint, and to call witnesses from various organisations to support it. It is stated that the Federation has drafted a State Mines Bill, which will be submitted to the Commission.The Council of the Northumberland Miners&apos; Association has been holding its annual meetings this week. On the 17th May resolutions were passed in favour of an annual holiday of 14 days, an increase in the compensation allowance, and the abolition of piece-work. On the 19th May it was resolved to urge upon the Coal Commission the necessity of confiscating mining royalty rents and wayleaves, the revenue therefrom to be devoted to the modernising of colliery villages. On the 20th it was resolved to ask the M.F.G.B. to call a special conference to press for the raising of the income-tax limit to  250, and if this failed to produce any effect, to bring the matter before the Triple Alliance with a view to definite action. Resolutions against Conscription, the Blockade, and the Russian Expedition were also passed.A delegate conference of the South Wales Miners&apos;, Federation met on the 19th May to consider the question of the income-tax and workmen&apos;s compensation. On the latter question a similar attitude to that of the Northumberland miners was taken up, and on the former the following resolution was passed : &quot; That, having regard to the refusal of the Government to accept the proposal of the Labour Party to raise the income-tax abate-ment to  250, the members of the Federation refuse to pay further income-tax upon the present basis from the 5th April, 1919, and call upon the M.F.G.B. to take similar action.&quot; Previous demands for the abolition of Conscription, the release of political prisoners, and the withdrawal of all troops from Russia were reaffirmed, and the resignation of the War Minister was called for. It was suggested that the M.F.G.B. should institute a commission to inquire into the whole cost of production of clothes and boots.A Joint Conference between representatives of the Mining Association of Great Britain and the Mines Deputies&apos; Federation was held at the Home Office on the 17th May. Sir R. Redmayne (Chief Inspector of Mines) presided. The readjustment of hours for deputies and others, in accordance with the terms of the Sankey report, was discussed. Two pro-proposals were put forward, one by Sir T. Ratcliffe Ellis that deputies&apos; hours should be seven, plus one hour winding shift, one by Mr. Frank Hodges that they should be seven hours plus the winding time as approved by the Inspector of Mines in each particular pit. These proposals are to be submitted to the Association concerned, and the decisions communicated to a further conference on the 27th May.Balms.The Commission on Night Baking has continued to take evidence from provincial master bakers and from representatives of the provincial branches of the Operative Bakers&apos; Union. Mr. C. P. Tilling (Inspector under the Minister of Food), Mr. J. Pollitt (Labour Adviser to the Co-operative Union), Mr. A. Grainger (Chief Inspector of Weights and Measures for Birmingham), and two representatives of the Co-operative Association of Practical Bakery Managers, have also been called as witnesses. It held sittings on the 15th, 16th, 19th and 21st May.  The taking of evidence has now concluded.Munitions.At a mass meeting held in Woolwich on the 19th May, resolutions were passed demanding that the Arsenal should, be used as a national factory for articles used in peace time, and protesting against any further discharge of Arsenal workers.A mass meeting in Trafalgar Square, on the 17th May, protested against the proposal to close Waltham Abbey Powder Factory in favour of the factory at Gretna.Peace Terms.Lord Parmoor presided at a mass meeting held under the auspices of the Fight the Famine Council in the Albert Hall on the 19th May. Among the speakers were Mr. Srnillie, Mr. H. N. Brailsford, and Commander Kenworthy, M.P. Resolutions were passed protesting against the peace terms as unjust, especially with regard to the economic condition imposed on Germany.A number of Labour leaders, including Mr. R. Smillie, Miss Margaret Bondfield, Mr. Neil MacLean, M.P., and Mr. Philip Snowden, have issued, a manifesto against the peace terms of the Allies, of a rather more definite character than the official Labour Party manifesto published last week.
Amalgamation.The Amalgamated Instrument Makers&apos; Society has been balloting on the question of amalgamation with the A.S.E. The proposal was rejected by 1,747 votes to 1,686. It is asserted that only half the members voted.National Union of Dock Wharves and Shipping Staffs.A meeting under the auspices of the above was held at the Memorial Hall, Farringdon Street, on the 19th May. Commander Kenworthy, M.P., and Colonel L&apos;Estrange Malone, M.P., were among the speakers. A resolution was passed demanding that the Union should be consulted by employers with a view to revision of pay and conditions of employment.Agriculture.The Agricultural Wages Board for Ireland has issued its first Annual Report. It announces that, through the direct action of the Board, sums varying from  1 to  100, and reaching a total of over  14,000, have been paid to workmen in arrears of wages by recalcitrant employers.Triple Alliance.The Executive of the Triple Industrial Alliance met the Parliamentary Committee of the Trade Union Congress, on the 15th May, to consider what action should be taken with regard to the Southport resolution on Conscription, &amp;c. It was decided to defer any further steps until the Committee of the Trade Union Congress should have made representations to the Government. A deputation waited on members of the Cabinet on the 22nd May.Political Prisoners, -The Committee appointed at the Conference of the London Workers&apos; Committee, held on the 10th May, to consider steps for the release of political prisoners, has decided to convene a National Rank and File Conference of Industrial Organisations on the 14thtJune to deal with the matter. Mr. Tom Mann is to preside. Demonstrations have been held in Glasgow to demand the release of the Clyde strike leaders.Teachers.It is reported that London schoolmasters have formed an Association to oppose the policy (endorsed by the N.U.T.) of equal pay for men and women in the profession.Railwaymen.   iA certain amount of discontent with the working of the recent settlement, especially in the matter of overtime, is reported. Several branches of the N.U.R. have passed resolutions calling attention to the matter, and to the delays in the present negotiations. The branches of the Union have under their consideration a proposal to amend the rules of the N.U.R. so as to make it impossible for its officials to sit in Parliament; this will be discussed at the meeting of the Union next month. The Railway Clerks&apos; Association is reported to be definitely considering the question of joining or federating with the N.U.R.A number of M.Ps. interested in railway superannuation met on the 19th May, and received a deputation from the Association of Superannuated Railway Staff. A resolution was passed in favour of approaching the Board of Trade with a view to sanctioning the extension of the war bonus to superannuated railwaymen.Labour Party.The Labour Research Department held a three-days&apos; conference in the Central Hall, Westminster, on the 15th, 16th and 17th May. Delegates representing trade unions and co-operative societies, and Labour members on public bodies were present. The re-organisation of local government, in view of the creation of a Ministry of Health and the changes in Poor Law administration, was discussed in its constitutional, financial, educational and medical aspects.Vehicle Workers.A mass meeting of taxi-drivers was held at Clapham, under the auspices of the National Union of Vehicle Workers, on the 16th May, to protest against the widespread unemploy-ment among taxi-drivers, and against the alleged action of certain taxi-proprietors in evading the terms of the agreement by which drivers were to have free petrol and 25 per cent, of the gross receipts.
The Bus Drivers&apos; and Cabmen&apos;s Co-operative Society (of which Mr. H. Bundy is secretary), whose activities have hitherto been held up by the war, is now proposing to bring in a system whereby each man will have a proprietary interest in the vehicle he drives.The Amalgamated Association of Tramway and Vehicle Workers opened its annual delegate meeting at Cardiff on the 20th May. The approaching amalgamation with the London and Provincial Licensed Vehicle Workers was discussed. The amalgamation is to take effect on the 1st July.Co-operation and Trade Unionism.The first meeting of the Metropolitan Joint Advisory Council of Trade Unionists and Co-operators, which has recently been formed with the object of promoting joint action between the different organisations concerned, was held on the 15th May.Shipbuilding.The Federation of Engineering and Shipbuilding Trades, at its twenty-ninth annual meeting in Cardiff, on the 15th and 16th May, rejected the Government offer with regard to the shipyards at Chepstow and Beachley as contrary to the &quot; basic principles of Trade Unionism.&quot; The decision was stated to have been made after consultation with the Parliamentary Committee of the Trade Union Congress. .0ther resolutions were passed demanding the withdrawal of Order in Council C 43 (applied in the recent London Electrical strike), and the release of the Clyde prisoners, and condemning the confidential inquiries of the War Office with regard to trade unionism and the army. The Federation is stated to have applied for a general advance of 15s. a week to its members, and a consolidation of all war advances into standard district rates of wages.It would probably be a mistake to draw too definite conclusion from the refusal of the shipyards. There were very real practical difficulties in the way of acceptance, which vitiate the truth of the allegations of a desire on the part of the Unions to shirk responsi-bility put forward in certain quarters. The Engineering and Shipbuilding Trades Federation, of all Trade Union organisations, is perhaps the least fitted to accept such an ofier, since,, in the first place, it does not cover by any means all the interests concerned, on the pro-producer&apos;s side, in these trades; and secondly because, even as it is, it covers such a variety of interests that even the ordinary strains of Trade Union existence have proved too much for it..Federation of British Industries.The inaugural meeting of the Grand Council was held on 14th May, and is described in the &quot; Bulletin &quot; of the Federation of British Industries as &quot; an important landmark in the history of the Federation.&quot; A resolution condemning the principle of nationalisa-tion in industry was unanimously adopted. It was decided that the Federation should not give evidence on nationalisation before the Coal Commission, but that a case against nationalisation should be drawn up in time for submission to the Government, the House of Commons, and the country, before they came to consider the report of the Commission.Unemployment.The monthly report of the Steam Engine Makers&apos; Society (which has a membership of 28,000) makes the interesting admission that, in many parts of the country, offers of employment are being allowed to pass by, or even deliberately refused, by members of the Society who are in receipt of the unemployment donation, and who &quot; expect to continue to burden the Society&apos;s funds in spite of such conduct.&quot; This is stated to be in direct contra -vention to the rules of the Society, and branch officers are called upon to see that such rules are called into effect. It is added that the unemployed figure of the Society could be reduced by 50 per cent, if this abuse were stopped.Mersey Docks.The ballot on night work resulted in an overwhelming majority against the Employers&apos; proposals, and against all night work. It is stated, however, that only 11 per cent, of the men voted.Postal Clerks.At a meeting held under the auspices of the London branch of the Postal and Tele-graph Clerks&apos; Ass6ciation, on the 19th May, a resolution was passed affirming the &quot; deep conviction &quot; of the meeting that the control of the service was the all-important con-sideration, and protesting against the 54-hour week with non-payment for Sundays and public holidays, and the scheme for testing the lessened efficiency of men disabled in the war.
-Joint Industrial Councils, Paint and Varnish.A meeting of the Council, not hitherto reported to the Department, was held on the 30th April. The establishment of a 47-hour week, with rates of pay adjusted to secure the same amount as was paid for the longer hours, was agreed to, subject to the reservations that it should not prejudice any subsequent claim for a 44-hour week, and that overtime conditions should apply at the end of the revised working day.Spelter Trade.The first regular meeting of the Council, since its recognition as a J.I.C., was held at the London Chamber of Commerce on the 13th May. Dr. T. M. Legge, of the Home Office, gave an address on Industrial Disease, with special reference to the industries concerned.Trade Boards : Jute Trade (Great Britain).Formal objection has been lodged by the Association of Jute Spinners and Manu-facturers, Dundee, to the Draft Special Order applying the Trade Board Acts to the Jute Trade published on the 11th April, oh the ground that the degree of organisation in the trade is high. The conditions in the Jute Trade have, however, been stagnant for some time past, and it is thought that the real objection of the employers is the fear that they might be compelled to pay wages which would not enable them to compete on favourable terms with imported goods, especially from India.(2) District Reports.London and South-Eastern.Unemployment.--Unemployment, though decreasing slightly, is still &quot; most serious &quot; in the metropolitan industrial area and at Newhaven and Lewes, while an increase is expected, at Dover owing to discharges from the Army Pay Corps there. Road-making in Kent and Sussex is reported, to be delayed by a shortage of materials and insufficient transport, both rail and marine. A revival of private building operations, road repairs and manufacturing activity, especially in the motor industry, is anticipated, and there is a demand for suitable workers in the West End millinery and dressmaking establish-ments. New paper works at Aylesford and asphalt paving works at Dartford should relieve the situation in industrial Kent, and the Metropolitan Water Board are being induced to press forward several important schemes.The settlement of disabled men is still a problem. The City Employment Committee suggest that they be engaged with private employers at their labour value and that the State should supplement their pay to bring it up to current trade union rates. Several exchanges report that appeals to employers are of little value, and there is a general disposition to expect State action.General Industrial Situation.-Tih.eTe are various sectional movements in such trades a.s woodworkers, metal polishers and furniture workers to abolish the current systems of payment by results, and to procure inflated rates for the less skilled workers in view of anticipated legislation.Organisation on the lines of the Whitley Report is being favourably discussed in Woolwich Dockyard, but the shop stewards in the Arsenal are hostile. It is reported that in consequence of this the A.S.E. executive is inclined to support an industrial council likely to check the influence of the stewards. The agitation to retain Waltham Abbey Powder Factory in preference to Gretna is being continued vigorously.West Midlands.Unemployment. Registrations for unemployment donation are increasing among men but decreasing among women. The unemployment centres are still Greater Birmingham, Coventry, and Cradley Heath. Discharged soldiers in Birmingham resent the closing down of the Government Instructional Factory at Birmingham.General Industrial Situation. The situation is fairly normal among men, but there is considerable agitation among the women workers in such areas as West Bromwich. The clay miners at Brierley Hill are demanding the application of the Sankey report to their case. They work under the Coal Mines Regulation Act, and have participated in all previous awards.The Coventry Discharged Soldiers&apos; and Sailors&apos; Federation have opened a campaign for increased gratuities.
Yorkshire and East Midlands.Unemployment. There is a decrease of unemployment in such centres as Sheffield and Nottingham; the largest increase is reported from Bradford. In the Nottingham lace area engineering firms are asking for skilled men, and manufacturers of lace and hosiery machinery are fully employed with pre-war orders. It is suggested that the increased cost of wages and materials, with the corresponding rise in the prices of machines, may divert foreign orders. The purchase of machinery, however, by the French Commission has been on such a scale as to cause alarm in some quarters where competition in the lace trade is anticipated from France, the United States and Japan.General Industrial Situation. Municipal and semi-public services are restless. The employees of Hull Corporation are discussing a stoppage for a bonus of 30s. a week; electric workers at Scarborough and the clerks in Chesterfield gas works are also threatening drastic action. Unrest in Lincoln is acute among builders, joiners and aerodrome workers, and Nottingham, is a centre of the agitation among grocery assistants for a 48-hour week. There is some protest at Sheffield against an unpaid holiday on the occasion of the visit of the King and Queen there.North-Western.Unemployment. Unemployment is decreasing among women and there is a better feeling in the cotton trade. Unemployment in the building trade is heavy in Blackburn, Burnley, Liverpool and Manchester. The shortage of railway wagons is repeatedly given as a cause of delay in industrial resettlement; one manufacturer redorts that goods for Northwich lay undelivered on the quays at Manchester for six weeks. There is a shortage of labour in the lime quarries near Buxton, and an effort is being made to divert some of the surplus in New Mills and Stockport to meet this local demand.General Industrial Situation. The situation is fairly quiet, though no settlement in the negotiations on hours in the cotton trade is in sight, and things may eventually drift to a strike. As against the employers&apos; concessions of a 48-hour week and a 15 per cent, advance on list prices (about 6 per cent, on current prices), the employees demand a 46f-hour week and an advance of 30 per cent, on list prices. A ballot is to be taken by the 28th May.The masters, mates and engineers employed by the Mersey Dock and Harbour Board in their Wrecking Department are demanding the 44-hour week and the increased overtime rates conceded to dockers. They are members of the National Union of Dockers and Riverside Workers. At a recent meeting in Liverpool, the Mersey Engineering and Shipbuilding Trades Federation occupied itself with the strike of woodcutting machinists, the demarcation dispute between Mersey fitters and boilermakers and the &quot; Daily Herald&apos;s &quot; publication of secret official documents. Generally there is a recrudescence of shop steward, activity.Northern.Unemployment.-A general improvement is apparent, except in the Hartlepools and on Tees-side, where the closing down of iron works for alteration and rebuilding is causing temporary slackness.Despite the high price of pig iron, the manufacturers are sanguine as to prospects in the iron and steel market. Over a thousand men are being taken on by reopened iron works at Consett. The binder twine trade on Tyneside is recovering after the limita-tion of imports from America.  Unemployment among women is decreasing.General Industrial Situation. The 44-hour week movement continues. From the experience of the working of the 44-hour week in Scottish building trade works, the brick-layers argue that the present 47-hour week in two shifts is unworkable, and suggest three shifts of 44 hours as more efficient and employing more men. The Tyneside chemical workers are leaving the 44-hour week to be settled on a national basis.Negotiations on the &quot;part of the Cleveland iron miners for retrospective payments under the Sankey report, as from the 9th January, are proceeding on quite constitutional lines. The demarcation dispute between the plumbers and fitters in the Sunderland ship-building yards has been satisfactorily settled.Wales.Unemployment. There has been a substantial decrease of unemployment among men. The return to work of the Llanelly annealers has averted further unemployment in the 14 tinplate works which had closed down, while the return of the Ebbw Vale miners saves the situation for the dependent iron and steel works.  The Local Employment
Committee is approaching Lord Bessborough on the prospects of keeping open the Cyfarthfa iron works. The Anglo-Persian Oil Company is erecting a refinery at Skewen, near Swansea, which is expected to employ from three to four thousand workers. The Blaenau Festiniog Employment Committee is trying to keep open a hose factory-run by a relief fund on commercial lines and is investigating the prospects of a textile factory in the neighbourhood.General Industrial Situation. The growth of unconstitutional methods in trade disputes is marked. Instances which may be cited are the unofficial strikes of miners, the annealers&apos; defiance of both industrial council and union officials, the unconstitutional attempt to break away from the Steel Sliding Scale agreement, the claim for extras put forward by the Swansea dock workers without consulting the officials of the Dockers&apos; Union, and Mr. Vernon Hartshorn&apos;s outbursts against conciliation boards and their &quot; independent&quot; chairmen. There is an increasing tendency to advocate &quot; lightning strikes.&quot;The payment of income-tax on wages seems rapidly rising to be a major grievance in the mining areas, and is linked with demands for better pensions for widows and dependents of miners killed in accidents, and for disabled ex-servicemen. Some discontent has been caused by the rapid rise in the price of such articles as millinery, clothes and boots after the publication of the Coal Commission^ report; these &quot; Sankey prices &quot; are held to be &quot; perfectly unjustifiable.&quot;Scotland.Unemployment. Unemployment is still serious in the jute and linen towns Arbroath, Dundee, Dunfermline, Paisley and Perth but is decreasing in such areas as Clydebank, Lanarkshire, Glasgow, Greenock and Falkirk. In Dundee prospects of a revival of the . jute industry are brighter. In Alloa there is no surplus of labour, and in some parts of the Highlands there is a shortage of labour for roadmaking. The proposed Mid-Scotland Canal is now being advocated as a remedy for unemployment and the Divisional Council is hearing the views pf interested bodies. There is little actual building construction being undertaken except in Dundee, where all the necessary preliminaries have been adjusted. The condition of burghal housing is increasingly the theme of inflammatory speeches in the industrial areas.General Industrial Situation. In Edinburgh the dispute between the Edinburgh and Leith Corporation Gas Commissions and the gas workers is held up pending negotia-tions affecting the issues at stake on a national scale between the National Gas Council and the National Federation of General Workers.Glasgow Corporation has before it a scheme to establish an industrial council for its municipal employees. The furnishing trade is demanding a 44-hour week and a 2\d. advance to women workers, under the threat of a withdrawal of labour, as from the 24th May. The employers have offered a 47-hour week, and a further reduction of hours corre-sponding to future changes in the engineering and foundry trades. But the 44-hour week gained by the building trade is becoming more and more the recognised standard of comparison.The main subjects of agitation are conscription, housing, the nationalisation of mines and the prices of such articles of general consumption as butter, cheese, and whisky. Ayrshire miners demonstrated in Ayr on the 10th May against conscription and in favour of higher ex-Service pensions and better housing. The Clyde District Committee of the Engineering and Shipbuilding Trades Federation has recorded its disapproval of the Government^ Russian policy and its consequences.part v.-disputes.(a) Involving a Stoppage of Work.The Food Controller has declined to allow any increase in the milk prices fixed for the Lancashire district. This means that the retail price for May and June will remain at 5d. per quart.The building trade operatives, who were on strike at Lincoln owing to the refusal of the Ministry of Labour to ratify a wages agreement, have voted to return to work as their case is to be referred back to the Court of Arbitration.No settlement has yet been reported of the strike of Clyde tugboatmen.
The tugboatmen at Southampton still remain on strike ; and up to the present the efforts of the Isle of Wight Steam Packet Company to obtain fresh crews have been unsuccessful.About 1,000 women and girls, employed in the engineering shops at West Bromwich, struck, on the 14th May owing to the non-payment of the 5s. award made in January last.It is reported that 800 miners at Watnall Colliery, Nottingham, ceased work on the 14th May owing to a dispute concerning compensation.The strike of woodworkers in the London area against the continuance of the premium bonus system continues. On the 28th May the Executives of the Unions concerned are meeting to consider a recommendation of the London Aircraft Committee that national action should be taken by the woodworkers to secure the abolition of the premium bonus system. * A strike for-the same reason has also broken out at Lincoln. Grantham and Gainsborough, where about 4,000 woodworkers are said to be involved. These strikes are stated to be official. It is also reported that the extremists in Manchester are endeavouring to arouse the enthusiasm of the workers on the subject of this strike with the object of bringing about a sympathetic strike in their district.The men on strike at Messrs. P. W. Berwicks, Park Royal, returned to work on the 21st May, on the advice of their Trade Union officials. It is alleged by the men that the employers have refused to reinstate many of the most active Trade Unionists, and practically the whole of the Shop Stewards&apos; Committee.The strike of the Huddersfield tailors and tailoresses employed in the wholesale trade ended on the 5th May.(b) Not Involving a Stoppage of Work.With reference to the movement for the abolition of premium bonus systems in the wood-working trades, it is reported that at a meeting of representatives of the two Carpenters&apos; and Joiners&apos; Unions, the National Amalgamated Furnishing Trades Association, and the Wheel-wrights&apos;, Smiths&apos; and Bodymakers&apos; Organisation, it was decided to take a ballot not of members in the shipyards and engineering shops as to whether they would be in favour of withdrawing their labour &quot; to enforce only plain time rates of payment.&quot;A strike is threatened on the part of 5,000 men employed in the Forest of Dean coal-field, their grievance being that an award under the Minimum Wages Act applied only to higher-grade workmen and gave no relief to men in other grades. To avoid a strike the coalowners have offered to go to arbitration, and pithead meetings are being held to consider this suggestion.There is considerable discontent among the colliery surface workers employed in the Western Valley of Monmouthshire; for several months they are said to have been agitating for increased payment when employed during the week-ends, but without success.It is reported, that the Yorkshire, miners threaten to strike to secure the arrears accorded under the Sankey award.The Executive of the Miners&apos; Federation are holding a meeting this week to consider the case of the Cleveland ironstone miners, quarrymen and kindred workers, who are members of the Miners&apos; Federation but to whom the Sankey award has either not been applied at all or only partially&apos;applied.On the 14th May a strike of 500 coal miners occurred at the Vurteg (South Wales) Colliery owing to the refusal of the head haulier to transfer from the Master Hauliers&apos; Association to the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation.There is a growing movement in the engineering trades for the abolition of overtime. A resolution (to be incorporated in the rules) will be put before the next delegate meeting of the A.S.E. instructing District Committees to forbid any overtime while any member is in receipt of unemployment benefit. A conference of representatives of the Engineering Trade Unions and Employers&apos; Federations was held at York on the 20th May to consider the com-pliants made against overtime and nightwork.r. S. horne.All inquiries relating to this report should be addressed to : intelligence division,ministry op labour,montagu house,whitehall,london, S.w.l

</content>
</cab>
