<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/80/0 images: 188-192</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ifI circulate the attached draft of the Courts (Emergency Powers) Bill for the consideration of the Home Affairs Committee in accordance with their decision on May 8th (Home Affairs Committee 27, Minute 3)*4.0.GEDDES.ID OF TRADE, May 26th, 1919,
[9 &apos;&amp; 10 Geo. 5.]Courts (Emergency Poioers).1DRAFTof aBILLtoExtend, amend, and prolong the duration of section A D. 1919. one of the Courts (Emergency Powers) Act, 1917.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5 1. Section one of the Courts (Emergency Powers) Act, 1917, Amendment which confers on the court power to suspend and annul certain ^&quot;^Geo 5 contracts shall have effect as if  -&quot; c. 25.(1) for subsection (1) thereof the following subsection were substituted: 10 (1) Where, upon an application by any party toa contract entered into before the first day of January nineteen hundred and seventeen, the court is satisfied that, owing to the prevention or restric-tion of, or the delay in, the supply or delivery of15 materials, or the diversion or insufficency of labour.or the shortage of shipping, or the alteration of trade conditions occasioned by the present war, the contract&apos; cannot be enforced according to its terms without serious hardship, the court may, after20 considering all the circumstances of the case andthe position of all the parties to the contract and any offer which may have been made by any party for a variation of the contract, suspend or annul, or stay any proceedings for the enforcement of, the25 contract or any term thereof or any rights arisingthereunder on such conditions (if any) as the court may think, fit:]2L-2
For the purpose of this subsection where an offer made before the first. clay of January nineteen hundred and seventeen, was binding on a con-tracting party if accepted within a specified period expiring after that date and was so accepted after 5 that date, the contract shall be deemed to have been entered into before.that date.(2) In subsection (2) thereof for the words &quot; any ship&quot; there were substituted the word &quot; shipping &quot;. and for the words &quot; suspend or annul the contract or stay 10 any proceedings for the enforcement of&quot; there were substituted the words &quot; suspend or annul, or stay any proceedings for the enforcement of:&quot;(3) At the end of subsection (3) thereof there were inserted the words &quot;but shall continue in force until the 15 &quot; expiration of three years from the termination of &quot; the present war.&quot;2. This Act may be cited as the Courts (Emergency Powers) , 1919.

Courts (Emergency Powers) Bill.DRAFTOF AB   I   Li   IiTo extend, amend, and prolong the duration of section one of the Courts (Emergency Powers) - Act, 1917.CV.   (2.)2Uh May 1919.121-2

</content>
</cab>
