<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/80/0 images: 267-268</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^      KON-MBJUS MINING IN ffi Olid) KINGDOM    .v*\ ^       (TIN, IMD AND ZINC) 7364     WJ H       --------^ ^r^/Memorandum from the Board of Trade. 0161^^ --------The Kon-Ferrous iining Industry in the united Kingdom has been placed in a very difficult position owing on the one hand to the reduction of the demand for Tin, Lead and 4inc since the Armistice, and the consequent fall in price, and on the other hand to the greatly increased cost of working resulting from ad-vances in wages and the price of coal and other materials and the withdrawal of certain Government subsidies given during the *tar.(1) Tin, ainigg,      average output of Tin extracted from Ore raised in the united Kingdom was, before the d&amp;r, 5,000 tons and the consumption in this country was approximately 22,000 tons. For a number of years before the war it had not been markedly successful, as many of the mines (which are all on a small scale) were only able to make profits in years when the price of metal was high;   during the i*ar - and especially in 1913 - though work-ing costs increased very substantially, tne price of Tin rose to a very high level ( 329 per ton as&apos; compared with an average of iZ3Q in 1917); since the Armistice the price lias fallen very heavily and though it is still higher than at any time during some sixty years preceding 1916, it is not hi^h enough to offset the great increase in the cost of production due to the high price of labour and materials and the abnormally high pumping&quot; charges, which are due largely to the increased cost of fuel&apos;.   Other difficulties are the small amount of development work done during the War owing to labour shortage and the low average yield of Black Tin per ton of output &apos;;of Tin Ore.Some of the mines have already closed down and others are likely to do the*same.   The collapse of the industry would be particularly unfortunate because - (a) in times of war a supply of Tin from domestic sources is of great value (b) the output of arsenic (and to a much lesser degree of-wolfram) from the Cornish iiines has been of substantial importance to the country during the war;   (c) the economic prosperity of Cornwall depends largely on Tinclining, which employs some 8,000 people in ordinary times, whilst many others are dependent on it; and (d) the Cornish Mines have long been a training ground for miners subsequently employed in other parts of the inspire.It is not anticipated that the mines as a whole will be able to compete with Tin from other sources unless systematic survey, exploration and development work should reveal new deposits of Tin Ore and result in the sinking of new mines as productive as the mines existing at present and at a shallower depth, and unless the industry is re-organised so as to secure better and more economical working.was po^se^^n ia,uuu ana iy,uuu uosb, wniLrje irq consumption in this country was 200.000 toss; the orrtput of 4ino was 6,000 tons as.against  the oonsun$* Lan of  195,000  tons.
8/5/19.A.C.GOTES.The domestic contribution towards our industrial requirements of Lead and 2inc was therefore small and the1 financial re-results of the industry were poor, but during the War the Ministry of Munitions took steps to stimulate production, and although the effects of the extensions made hate&apos; hardly been felt as yet, it is hoped that if the industry can be carried on for a further period, even at a loss1, it will eventually be able to pay its way.The Ministry of Hunitions subsidised the industry during the War by means of bonuses on output, which will cease on the 30tft June, and a refund of the increased cost of wages under the Goal Controller^ Awards, which refund ceased on the 31st March last.    Since then prices have fallen appreciably, while the cost of production has not fallen ana may be expected to show an increase, and it has been represented to the Board of Trade that in these cir-cumstances, unless some Government assistance is given, there is no alternative for the mines but to close down.There are three important considerations in regard to the position of lion-Ferrous Lining in the United Kingdom to which I would direct special attention:- (i) the desir-ability of avoiding unemployment, particularly as in dis-tricts like Cornwall and those in which most of the Lead and Zinc Mines are situated there is little, if any. opening for labour dismissed from the mines:  (li) the desirability of developing domestic production ox important materials insofar as that production is on an economically sound basis and has reasonable prospects of competing successfully with overseas supplies;  (iii) the fact that if the mines are shut down for any length of time, the chances of re-opening them will be greatly diminished and in some oases entirely destroyed owing to the dispersal of labour and the flooding of the mines.In all the circumstances I recommend that:flk) There should be an immediate enquiry into the whele osition of the Eon-Ferrous fining Industry in the United ingdom with a view to deciding whether the industry cannot be placed on a satisfactory commercial footing.   This enquiry oould probably best be made by the Mineral Resources Develop-ment Department, which has now been transferred from the Ministry of Munitions to the Board of Trade.    (The Imperial Mineral Resources Bureau would cooperate, but regard the conduct of such an enquiry, which involves consideration of matters of domestic policy, as outside their scope).    The enquiry would take a considerable time, though possibly less than a year.(B) In the meantime, in order to enable mining opera-tions to continue. His Majesty1s Government should undertake to make advances to approved mines up to something less than the breaking-up value of their plant and machinery, as estab-liahed by an independent valuation, such loans to tear inter-est and be repayable in a short term of years, and the offer of loans would be only open until the report of the enquiry has been received and a decision taken thereon.These conditions would discourage applications from companies not really satisfied as to the commercial value of their undertakings;  and the course suggested would give opportunity for some of the extensions planned under the influence of the ministry of Munitions during the War to give results,

</content>
</cab>
