<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/80/0 images: 307-309</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
.S DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS ,BRIT.CTIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT)j,3 C R E T .&apos;. 7569.TZAR CABINET, ^PUROHASB CF EHSMy-PPIZE,SHIPS^BY SOUTHiAFRICA.(Copy cf letter from the prime .Hjriister cf the Union ^T^&apos;sou^&quot; Africa&quot; t ^ mH ^BjnJ^rjLj^JX&quot; Savoy Hotel,Strand,London, W.0 .229th May, 1919.Dear Mr. bonar  Law,in pursuance of our conversation this afternoon, I hereby desire to make application on behalf of the Union of South Africa for three of the prize&quot;ships captured from Germany,   My Government is anxious to obtain immediately three of these ships for use in connection with the administration sf our Harbours, as well as for the development of our coastal trade,  and in order to transport railway sleepers and other railway material from places from which it is difficult - nay, almost impossible -to obtain shipping to transport them.   I understand that the Dominion of Australia captured fifteen German ships in her waters, and from the date of capture these sh^ps have remained in her possession and have been used With great profit all this time.   Australia, it is true, does not, like the Union of south Africa, contribute towards the British Navy, but is in possession cf her own Navy.   In principle, however, I do not think the cases really differ,   in South Africa we have followed the policy which has been most, strongly urged by His Majesty&apos;s Government against the     formation of a South African Navy, and we have abstained from a nucleus Navy of our own and concentrated our efforts on providing \for our complete defences on shore, making at the same time such contribution to His Majestys Navy as we have been able.   The result has been that when British troops were required the whole of the Expeditionary forces were withdrawn from South Africa, and the /
h2-defence of the Union was assumed by tho Union Government, wh* n.-t only maintained the defence of the oountry, but manned two important campaigns from South Africa, and furnished considerable contingents to fight in Europe, where their deeds are now a matter of history. If we had followed any other policy arid formed our own navy we should have been able to capture our own prizes and to have put them to whatever use we detired, and by this time we should have earned for ourselves some hundreds of thousands of pounds in freight in addition to benefitting the country beyond measure in placing our exports on the markets of the wcrld at a time when the prices were enormously in our favour.     The ships (thirteen in number) captured in our waters were handed over to the Imperial Government and I understand have been of considerable advantage   to the latter.For these reasons I think you will agree with me that South Africa is making a very reasonable oe.-\iro in requesting   the Imperial Government to allocate, at least, three prize ships tc her.     These are vital to her for the development of the country.I am further enclosing, for your information, portion of a Memorandum which was drawn up by Sir V/illiam Hoy and Sir David Graaf and submitted to Lord Lilner,     This extract incorporates further reasons in support of my application, but the most important, to my mind, is the one I have just given.As regards the terms of purchase, should the Imperial Govern-Dent decide to allocate these three daips, I would suggest thatrthey to sold to the Union Government for the amount at ehich they were condemned by the I-rize Court,     If my application should be successful, I wculd be happy to send my experts to discuss with representatives of the Ministry of Shipping the type of ship which we require. vYours faithfully,(ogd.) LOUIS BOTHA.The lit.Eon,A.Bonar Law, L,I,, House of Commons, S.&apos;.V.
Extract from_Lomomndum, dated 14th Larch, 1919Acquisition of enemy prizejshipSiIt was obvious from the beginning that no relief or assistance need be expected, but thiw -natter cannot be left here. South Africa haa followed a policy ox affording the fullest co-operation and assistance to H.Ia Government *     The Union Government has had the use of one Germain ship        Australia has traded with 15 or more prize ships taken in her own waters, and with her own Mercantile Fleet ha&amp; enjoyed a   rich financial harvest during the last few years of the war.     Repeated applications made by the Union Government for the use of oneor two vessels for the conveyance of its own materials during the war period met with no successful response.     The Union Govornment is surely entitled to seek the friendly co-operation of H.La Government at the conclusion of the war in its aspiration to regulate shipping freights to and from South Africa and thus assure to the producer that security which he has a right to expect.

</content>
</cab>
