<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/80/0 images: 361-361</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Hi3 Criiannio IVlaje3ty&apos;s G;)/g,\, -.10..:.&apos;-&apos; &apos;. ;    ;  Yom Viceroy, Army Department, 27th May 1919,(Received 10.30 a.m., 29th.)Priority. 7203. 7th May (? 27th). MallesoiTs M.D. 01665,14th May, summarised as follows: &quot; Pan-Islamic propaganda becoming steadily more intense in Russian Central Asia, Europe and Khorasan, appealing to Mahometans generally that British now wantonly scheming to destroy and annex last remaining Mahometan Kingdom, Afghanistan, --how no longer required, as buffer State ; special appeal to Shiahs by circular to Khorasans of British outrages and desecration of Keressea and Nejei. Though not accepted by higher class Persians, who are generally friendly to us, lower classes becoming inflamed. In Russian Central Asia pan-Islam propaganda making headway and Turcomans becoming apathetic. Askabad Government weak, and appears to be drifting towards Bolshevism. If Government collapses probable results would be (a) militant Bolshevism throughout Central Asia, or (6) a Mahometan&apos; combine in Jehad against Russia.&quot; Malleson suggests we should take measures at once to prevent spread of pan-Islamism and Bolshevism, and for this purpose refers to release of our forces in Caucasus and suggests their employment in. Central Asia area; one division fully equipped could move via Merv to Kushk and threaten (corrupt group), thus paralysing Western Afghanistan ; another division on Merv front would speedily secure Oxus line followed by alliance with Bokhara, thus isolating Afghanistan from the north. Such a movement, coupled with Koltchak&apos;s presence in Orenburg, might secure end of Bolshevism in Turkestan, and would rally Mahometans in Central Asia to our side. Malleson makes above suggestions subject to his lack of knowledge of whole situation.&quot;2. Following reply has been sent to Malleson :-   ,,&quot; Your M.D.O. 1665, dated .19th May. For General Malleson only. While the contingency of great Mahometan rising in Central Asia in extension of present Afghan trouble seems possible, yet your proposals do not seem to us to be practically feasible since--&quot; (a) the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government is to abstain from intervention involving the despatch of troops to Russian Turkestan ;&quot; (b) we cannot afford to maintain or control effectively so wide a dispersion (of) force ;&quot; (c) transfer available Caucasus to Italy will limit our powers available, utilising the only line of communication that could maintain a force in Trans-Caspia;&quot; (cf) Our present policy is to strike directly at the centre of the Afghan trouble and suppress it there.&quot; . .3. Following is summary of later information received from Malleson : &quot; (a) News from Herat up to 19th May mentions meeting of troops and leading ( ? )s, which took oath on Koran to unite and resist English aggression, but report from Meshed dated 25th May states so far nothing-doing in Herat.&quot; (6) Trans-Caspians have abandoned Merv and Kushk and are retiring towardsAskabad.   Bolsheviks now hold Merv with Afghans. &quot; (c) Afghan mission from Amir inviting Bolsheviks to Kabul has arrived.Kerki. &quot; (d) Reports from Trans-caspia state thai many Caucasian Turks, all Maho-metans, continue to arrive.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
