<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/80/0 images: 458-458</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(P 2964) From Viceroy, 31st May 1919.(Received 31st May, 10.45 a.m.)Clear the line.775-5. Secret. Afghanistan. Following received from. Roos-Keppel, dated 29th May :-Donald reports - from Hangn that Mullah Maksud Akhundzada, who has recently returned from Kabul, gave Amir assurances that if General Nadir Khan would attack and capture Thai, Orakzai and Afridis would join the Afghans. This confirmed from other sources. Thai town gutted and Hindu merchants fled into Kohat district, spreading alarm. On the other hand, news has done much to alienate local sympathy for Afghans as it was believed that, owing to union between Hindus and Mussalmans, former would be specially protected. Kurram wires spirit of Turis, Upper Kurram, excellent and panic in Lower Kurram. Attitude of Zaimukt good as yet. Communications with Parachinar very irregular; telegrams have to come through Thai where wireless has been damaged and there is great congestion. Deputy Commissioner, Bannu, telegraphs that excitement exists in Bannu district and town since receipt of news of events in Tochi.Message received from Zhob that eight British officers with 500 South Waziristan Militia and followers arrived safely.Before leaving Sarwekai both mountain guns were rendered useless, and all ammunition, powder, shell, bombs, &amp;c, were saturated with petroleum and set on fire.   Sarwekai must have been completely gutted, as explosions continued throughout retirement.   Ammunition at all lower posts destroyed before leaving.   Loyal militia brought in by Crosthwaite to- Murtaza number two British officers, 11 Pathan officers, 450 rank and file, 45 followers.   Political Agent, Khyber, reports Afridis are hastily convening full tribal jirga to-morrow at Maidan, presumably to consider Khost developments.  Khoda Khel Afghan Mohmands, infuriated at failure of Afghan Mohmand expedition, are threatening to attack Lalpura Mohmands who haye entered into relations with us.   Assistant Political Officer, Dakka, has jirga of Basawal, Loe, and Kam Dakka who show friendliness and are bringing supplies.   Shinwaris are returning to Bagh and Khargali to reap their crops, they will bring in bhusa and such other supplies as are available to Landi Khana brigade.   (? Enemy) propaganda very active among the tribes and in. districts line taken being that European powers have determined on crushing all Islamic kingdom(s), and that Government of India is taking advantage of recent incidents, which are due to Amanulla&apos;s youth and inexperienced-perience, to annex Afghanistan and tribal territory, turning deaf ear to Amanulla&apos;s petition for peace.   This is having considerable effect, and we must attempt to defeat it by counter propaganda, not only here, but in India and amongst the troops.

</content>
</cab>
