<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/93/0 images: 49-54</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
P-or the Information of ... embers of the Board.WEEKLY APPRECIATION OF LETTERS OP NaVAL IITTSRBST.      No. 47.For week ended 8th November,1919.kOVEiuEKTS OF ILL.SHIPS IN HOLE ;,ATERS.&quot;Danae&quot; sailed from Shcorness for Queens town and Halifaxon 3rd November to escort homo &quot;Renown&quot;.   On the 5th she leftQueens town for Halifax..&quot;Splendid&quot; sailed from Harwich for Hamburg with mails forHohcS. &quot;Coventry&quot; on the 3rd.The 2nd Battle Squadron arrived at Rosyth on the 4th.Yacht &quot;Alexandra&quot; sailed from Portsmouth for Dover on the7th *&quot;Heythrop&quot;, &quot;Cattistock&quot; and &quot;Oakley&quot; sailed from Grimsbyon the 8th taking relief crews for Paddle kinesweepers in the Baltic.BALTIC .&quot;DAUNTLESS&quot; and &quot;EREBUS&quot; sailed from Biorko for LIbau on 4tharriving on 7th and 8th respectively;&quot;PRINCESS MARGARET&quot; sailed from Copenhagen on 5th for Portsmouthto load mines, arriving on 7th Novemberi&quot;WALLACE&quot; with 8 T .B*Da of 1st Flotilla and 2 of 3rd Flotilla sailed from Rosyth on 5th November and arrived at Copenhagen on 7th&quot;WALLACE&quot;, and 8 T.B.Ds left Copenhagen for Reval on 8th November.&quot;ARGUS&quot; sailed from Rosyth on 7th November with aeroplane   and storesShe is due at Copenhagen on 9th November vfrere she will be met by &quot;VINDICTIVE&quot;. ^   &quot;ARGUS&quot; will then transfer the aeroplane and stores to &quot;VINDICTIVE and return to Rosyth.&quot;GREENWICH&quot; and &quot;WALKER&quot; sailed from Rosyth for Copenhagen on 8thNovemberiTorpedoes fired at Patrols.S.N.O., Baltic reports that 4 torpedoes were fired a tour patrols on the morning of 3rd NovembertAdvance on Petrograd.S.N.O., Baltic reported on 3rd November that there now appeared to be little chance of capture of Pctrograd^     He gaveas reason the bad leading and strategy of Yudenitch and persistentlack of co-operation between Esthonlans and Russians *Owing to the heavy losses sustained by the Ssthonians priorto the arrival of EREBUS, infantry assault on the forts had insuffi-cient weight to follow up the bombardments successfully.     S.K.O..stated that he considered it to be worth while to persevere whilethe* e O 4  9 *
S.N.Ov, Libau reported that an attack by Germans withartillery was opened on Libau at 084^ on 4th November.   EiL.Shipsroplied by bombardment.     The German main effort is against theNorthern defence,, the lakes having frozen *    Their initial attackshavo been repulsed.-     The defence was stated to have no artillery*r machine guns.   &quot;EREBUS&quot; and &quot;DAUNTLESS&quot; proceeded to Libau fromBiorko*   German troops have advanced on Libau and were within 10miles on 5th November.     S.N.O. Libau despatched a T*B.E* to Windau.He considered It might become necessary to withdraw from Libauand Windau.Riga.The situation Is unchanged.   The Letts hold Bermontrsforces on a line 12 miles to Southward of the rivero   Allied shipscontinue support of the Letts *NavalThc BaIt1 c/iiission   under General Niessel is proceeding to supervise&quot;the GTrman evacuation of the Baltic Provinces.      TheCommission is to keep in touch with the Inter-Al11eo^Command in theBaltic;, who will keep it informed of such Naval operations as may,in conformity with the decision of the Conference.; be undertaken withthe object either of assisting In the relief of Petrograd or in preventing supplies reaching the Bolsheviks by sea?   The AlliedNavies are to furnish tho Commission with all necessary Srans-port and to arrange for tho transmission of its telegrams-.Restrictions on German Shipping.Vvith regard to the embargo on German shipping in theBaltic tho following additional instructions have been sent-to theS,1I;0., Baltics-&quot;Subject to their non-interference with military opera-tions and in accordance with the directions of the supreme council, permission will bo granted to certain German ships to carry Allied or neutral cargoes in the Baltic.   You-&apos;will continue to be informed;, of free passages granted and can act. as necessary if your operations are interfered with by any of the vessels concerned&quot;.UEDITERRANEAH.In response to the request of the Military authorities that a battleship should be detailed to be present at LSRSINAor BEYRCTJT during the evacuation of British troops,   &quot;EkPEROR OPINDIA11 and one light cruiser have been detailed for this service *the.weather permits in the hripe of internal collapse of the Bolsheviksbut that he would not support any further efforts unless fullc*-operation between Russians and Esthonians is assured.A later report stated that the advance had been definitelyabandoned and that the Esthonians were falling back for the winter *Yudenitch has retreated behind Gatchina, which has now been re--?captured by the Bolsheviks.On this report S.N.O., has been directed to cease bombard-ment of the fortresses unless these are actively offensivee     TheSrNcOrs proposal to send &quot;PRINCESS LaRGARET&quot; home to embark mineswas approvede     &quot;PRINCESS LaRG..RET&quot; should return to Copenhagen,loaded, about 13th November *Attack on Libau and Viindau.
Russian Battleship &quot;VOLYA&quot; was turned over to VolunteerNavy at Sevastopol on 30th September:.     Treasury have been askedto sanction the offer of the destroyer &quot;kARTIN&quot; to the VolunteerNavy as a free gift.The situation in Crimea and at Odessa is reported assatisfactoryD A N&apos;U BE.All symptoms point to a hard winter in this district,and the DANUBE, which is., unduly low, is expected to freeze early..Once this has happened, this, the best means of transport,becomes difficult.The Entente will also thereby be deprived of the utilityof Admiral TROUBRIDGE&apos;s Flotilla, which would be an importantguarantee for tranquillity at the moment of the Roumanianevacuation.-Report ,from /Admiral Troubridge ?The following is an extract from a report from AdmiralTROUBRIDGE dated BUDAPEST!!, 25th October;-&quot;I have been invited by the Inter-Allied Military Lission(Council of Generals) to transport arms for the police and selectedmen for that force from ports on the Darin BE up to BUDAPEST;in order that upon the Roumanians leaving order may be maintained.I Ijave consented to do this, but before doing so Idemanded a guarantee that such forces should be disciplined and controlled in such a degree that there would be no question ofoppression or pogroms.        h representative Linister visited me and gave me the required guarantee on behalf of the Government, whileAdmiral H OR THY sent his Chief of Staff, General SOSS,,with the name assurance4I shall therefore, if I think proper at the moment, useHoLtShipa to the maintenance of general order, primarilyas a moral factor in the reassurance of the population, or as necessary to actually prevent violent actions calculated toproduce another reign of terror at BUDAPEST..The Flotillas are at present anchored off BUDa -?0K, sixmiles south of BUDAPEST, in readiness for any emergency.&quot;EGYPT AND RED SEA,R0Ao, Egypt, has been informed that &quot;GOLiUS&quot; due at port said 15th November may call at Hodeida or other Red Sea Porton her passage to East Indies,     but is not to be delayedmore than 3 or 4 days*&quot;CORNFLOWER&quot; remains-at Hodeida.&apos; &apos; EAST   INDIES. ,  .&quot;HIGHFLYER&quot; and &quot;ODIN&quot; arrived at Berbera on 4th November&quot;HIGHFLYER&quot; leaving again the same day for Colombo;.     RoAc, reportsthat &quot;ODIN&quot; should remain on Somaliland Coast for the presentand that at least one ship is required on this coast until afterthe,.,.,,BLACK     SEA.
H At.*S o &quot;CARLISLE&quot; left Vladivostock 6th November forHong Kong where she is due to arrive 13th Bovembery to haveheating arrangements fitted preparatory to returning toVladivos t stock f or the \ inter*\&apos;;EST    INDIES I&quot;CAMBRIAN&quot; reports on 1st November that the situation at Belize was unchanged)     80 men have boon left on shoretp preserve order while &quot;CALBRIAN&quot; visits Puerto Cortez;Tola and Ceiba to investigate complaints of ill treatmentof British subjects,, leaving Belize 2nd November and returning6th November.A detachment of British troops is due to arrive atBelize on 15th November *In response to a telegram from Jamaica asking for thepresence there ok one of H.LbShips&apos;en account of labourtrouble,    &quot;CALCUTTA&quot; left. Bermuda 6th November and is due Jamaica9th November *Owing to serious damage to &quot;CALLIOPE11 caused by an outbreak of fire in No*5 oil tank it has been decided to payher off while repairs are being effected.&quot;YARMOUTH&quot; will remain on North America and West IndiesSt at! en until relieved in due course by lfCALLI0PE,(.ITALY..Nothing has yet been published officially aboutthe resignation of the Chief of the Naval Staff.,   AdmiralDI REVEL-, or the future occupant of that office      It is nevertheless stated on good authority that he has resignedvFlume oThe &quot;PISA&quot; and &quot;NINO BlXIO&quot; which were completingat P*jLA for service In the LEVANT, were losing so many men bydesertion to the rebels at FIULE that they were moved to VENICEon October 5th to complete *.Italian Naval. Officers, although sympathising with&quot;DrANNUNZ.I0,? s. movement, are much perturbed at the effect recent events have had on the discipline of the Army and Navy, the wholesale desertions to the rebels and the consequent loss ofcontrol of the Officers over the ment the Minister of harine has stated that the solutionof the FIU&amp;E question in favour of ITALY Is essential ifrevolution Is to be avoided,    and that strainoc1 relations withthe UNITED STATES were preferable to the abandonment of    ,FIUIuE, as the latter would involve the disintegration of thecountry *ROUIunNIA,The Roumanian Government have expressed a wish to purchase three mine-sweeping vessels and two motor launches, andto be lent the services of an officer to carry out instruction in minesweeping*the present military operations are concluded.     &quot;COLiUS&quot; hasbeen ordered to call at Berbera on her passage tn East Indies.CHI H A.
BULGJFiIA.It has boon decided to recommend to tho supreme council that the Naval Commission of Control for executing theterms of the Bulgarian Peace Treaty should consist of a FrenchRear Admiral (President) and four Captains or Commanders from the other powers.GREECE*   -An attempt has been made by group Captain RANDALL,R.A.F., the flying officer attached to the British Navalkission in GREECE, to bring about the amalgamation of the GreekNaval and Military Air Services under a joint Air Board.     Thisscheme however, although approved by the Greek Government, has fallen through owing to the opposition of the Military AirService.TURKEY,Lord CURZON called the attention of the United states ambassador recently to the anti-British attitude adopted byRear Admiral BRISTOL, the United Sates High Commissioner atCONSTANTINOPLE,   who is &quot;continually suspecting, and sometimesopenly accusing us of dark and sinister Intrigues for whichthere is no vestige of foundation&quot;.     Lord CURZON suggestedthat Informal steps might with advantage be taken to modify theattitude of Admiral BRISTOL.PORTUGAL.Towards the end of October a United States Naval Forcevisited Lisbon and some sixty vessels were anchored in the Tagus,mainly mine-sweepers and submarine-chasersDisturbances tookplace when the men went ashore, and, from a propagandapoint of view, the prestige of the American Navy would appearto have been considerably lowered.GuRLANY.As compensation for tho sinking of the German ships at scapa Flow and of Submarine &quot;U.48&quot; outside Ferrol, the followingappears in the protocol to be presented to Germany for signaturebefore the final ratification.within 60 days of signature of the protocol the surrender of the following 5 light cruisers &quot;KOHIGSB-RG   - &quot;PILLAU&quot; -&quot;OMJDENZ&quot; - &quot;REGENSBURG&quot; - &quot;STRESSBURG&quot;90within      days of the signature of the protocol such anumber of floating docks and tugs in good condition equal to atonnage of 400,000 tons as the Principal allied ond associated powers may demand.     As regords the Docks the lifting capacity willbe regarded as displacement.     Of the Docks 75/  are to be of over10,000 tons.     This material ; ill be delivered on tho spot.iA complete list of floating docks and tugs in the possessionof the German Government on the 11th I; ovember 1918, or in whichthe Government possessed an interest, is to be rendered within10 days of the signature of the Protocol to /. .N.A-.C +
Visit of Chilean Lisslon. The Chilean Special Missionwill visit Portsmouth on the 11th November. They will visitShips in harbour, a Submarine and shops In the Dockyard.Devonport.Tho sympathetic recoption accorded to the deputationwhich waited on the Prime Minister to put forward proposals forthe future utilisation of the Dockyards has caused great satisfaction in tho Three Towns.. -$he proposals put forward for Plymouth wore:-&apos;&quot;(a) To use the building slips In the South Yardfor the construction of Merchant Ships *(b) To use the North Yard for trans- Atlanticpassenger traffic and for the cue charge andhandling of cargoes.PELBROKE.Lessrs. V&apos;ard, Shipbreakcrs, arc negotiating for a siteto establish a ship breaking Yard at Lilford Haven..RALTY, S.W.1.,.11th November,, 1919.The crows o  Scapa Plow ships shall not be repatriateduntil the above conditions ore fulfilled.Tho Destroyer HB*98&quot; will be. considered, as one of the42 Destroyers surrendered under Article 185 of the Treaty ofPeace.   \.ithin 10 days of the signature of the protocol themachinery and motors of submarines U.137j 138 and 150 shallbe delivered up as compensation for the destruction of U.C&apos;48*The throe remaining motors of U.146 are to be surrenderedas compensation for tho submarines destroyed in the l:orth Sea.burrendor of Merchant Ships.During the week 2 German ships have been surrendered,one being allocated to the British and one to tho French.The total number surrendered to date is 343.   -MISCELLANEOUS HCiiE INTELLIGENCE.Portsmouth *

</content>
</cab>
