<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/93/0 images: 181-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I circulate for the inforaation of aycoUeag^et? cortgr^tulatory messages received froatho Naval, Military and Civil Authorities ofSsthonia on the occasion of the destruction  oftwo Bolshevik Battleships ty HJ-f. Naval Forces,(Sgd) LONG.
From..... Ma j or-General Baidoner. 10 0To .*,,,.. Admiral Sir Walter Cowan, Commander of RoyalBritish Navy in Baltic Sea.Bate ..... 19th August, 1919.&quot;in the name of the Estonian Army and Navy, I have the&quot;honour to Congratulate the Royal British Navy on the event of&quot;its admirably heroic deed by Cronstadt. Simultaneously, the&quot;Estonian Army and navy wish to express their highest&quot;gratitude to the British Navy and to you, Sir,  or the great&quot;service rendered to the young Estonian Republic by the power&quot;of the British ITavy and sacrifice of hands.&quot;From .... Admiral Pitka, at Reval.To ....... Senior Naval Officer, Baltic.Bate .... 26th August, 1919..&quot;I congratulate you,. British heroes, on your late feat&quot;of unparalleled courage, through which the enemy13 Navy is&quot;ultimately defeated.   You will remain eternally in the$minds of the Estonian Nation and Estonian Navy as example of&quot;courage and bravery&quot;.Prom .... General CMannerhcim, late Regent of theRepublic of Finland.To ...... Admiral Sir Walter Cowan.Bate .... 26th Augustf 1919.&quot;Thanking you, my dear Admiral, for your kind letter,  I&quot;cannot refrain from writing once more to you,  to express my&quot;deep admiration for the splendid way in which small craft&quot;from the Naval Forces under your command entering the harbour&quot;of Krdnstadt delivered the Baltic from some of the most&quot;dangerous units of Bolshevik sea-power.&quot;Deeds of that kind have in times past built up the&quot;fame of the English Navy, and this feat has once more&quot;shown to the world that when England strikes it strikes hard,&quot;I know that my feelings of admiration and respect for&quot;the men participating in the plucky raid are shared by every&quot;true soldier in this country, and that we all deplore the loss&quot;of some of the gallant officers and men who had their share&quot;in ---this sp\endid achievement.&quot;From .... The Minister of Foreign Affairs of Republic ofEstonia,To ,:,v::. Tho British Admiral Commanding the Baltic Fleet.Bate .... 25rd August, 1919.&quot;The Estonian Government charges me to convey to you&quot;its congratulations on the success of the brilliant operation of&quot;the British motor boats in the harbour of Eronstadt,  resulting,,;as it did, in the destruction of two Russian Bolshevist i&quot;Dreadnoughts.,;&quot;Estonia is especially jubilant over this success, as&quot;it removes the danger which threatened her from this quarter.&quot;
v     i   \Esthonian Provisional Legation,167, Queen&apos;s Gate, S.W.7.London.&quot;25th. August. 1919.&quot;Sir,&quot;I am in possession of the following telegram from&quot;Reval and have much pleasure in communicating its contents to&quot;His Majesty&apos;a Government as directed by our Foreign Minister:-&quot;&apos;The Esthonian Government charges iv,g to convey its&apos; congratulations to His Britannic !6:...jesty; s Government&apos;on the success of the brilli.ait operation of the BritishfMotors in the Harbour of Kronstadt,  resulting as it did&apos;in the destruction of two Russian Bolshevist&apos;Dreadnoughts-.   Isthonia is especially jubilant over&apos; this success., as it removes for ever the danger whichfthreatened her from this quarter.    (Signed) Poska,minister if or Foreign Affairs of Esthonia.1&quot;I am, etc.,(Signed) J. KOPV/IM^M.&quot;The Under-Secretary of State,&quot;Foreign Office, S.

</content>
</cab>
