<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/93/0 images: 312-316</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MR. 0. LONG HURST,2431K CfMEMORANDUM BY THS MINISTER OF HEALTH.N.H.1.1.PEECT ON RATIONAL HEALTH INSURANCE OP A 20/-Ui^MPLOY^BST E&amp;NEPIT.1.     An insured man can only obtain unemployment benefit iflie is fit for work;   if his unemployment is due to illness he is entitled to sickness benefit and not to unemployment benefit.   Asa man needs at least as much when he is 111 as when he is well., it follows that sickness benefit cannot be less than unemploymentbenefit, and any increase of the unemployment benefit rate bringingit above the sickness benefit rate necessitates sickness benefitbeing increased to at least an equal amount.     It is true that sofar as men are concerned the State sickness benefit is oftensupplemented by private insurance, but it cannot be argued fromthis that State sickness benefit can be less than State unemploymentbenefit.     11 hen full allowance is made for private insurance it %remains the fact that some millions of insured men and practically-all insured women have nothing but State insurance benefits to depend on in illness.raised from the present figure of 7/- a week to 20/- for men and15/- for women, excluding domestic service, and the object of thismemorandum is to examine the effect of this change on healthinsurance and to indicate the cost to the Exchequer of this revisionof the two schemes, which, for the reason already given, must beconsidered in relation to one another.3. An increase of sickness benefit to 20/- for men and 15/-for women, which is double the present rate, would necessitate anincrease in disablement benefit i.e. the reduced sickness benefitpayable after the first twenty-six weeks of illness. A drop from20/- to the present disablement benefit rate of 5/- or even to 7/6It has been suggested that unemployment benefit should be
is too great, and with the prospective increase in the Old age pension rate there would be an irresjtible demand for a disablementbenefit of 10/-, if   -sickness benefit were fixed at 20/-.Maternity benefit, which is at present 30/-, would also have tobe largely increased.4.     Assuming that the State contributes the same proportionof tho cost of benefits as at present (viz. two-ninths in the caseof men and one-quarter in the case of wcaien) the additional costto the Exchequer of doubling the Health Insurance cash benefits would be nearly  5,500,000, assuming that the negotiations nowin progress with the doctors result in the revised capitationrate averaging 10/6 in place of the average of 7/3 fixed in 1912.But if the Government by doubling the cash benefits admit thatthe value af money has fallen to half what it was before the war,the doctors are not likely to accept less than their presentdemands, and this may involve a further.charge on the exchequer of  1,500,000, bringing the total extra charge to  5,000,000 ayear.     The extra cost to the Exchequer of an unemployment benefitof 20/- and 15/- (assuming the exclusion of domestic service)would be  3,500,000, if the State grant is taken as a   quarter ofthe total contributions.     The total additional liability fallingupon the State would thus amount to. 8,500,000 a year,5.     Some increase in the scale of cash benefits is inevitable,but the doubling of the present rates is open to grave objection on administrative grounds and also because the joint contributionreq uired &apos;to support these unemployment and health benefits would impose a great burden on the workers and a serious tax on industry.Insured persons only imperfectly apprehend the effect of adepreciated currency, and a sickness benefit of 20/-, and- stillmore disablement benefit of 10&apos;/- would be a great temptation tomalingering, none the less difficult to check for being largelyunconscious
unconscious.     The amount allowed to Approved Societies for administration would have to he still further increased inaddition to the increase already rendered inevitable by the altered Value of money , and large sums would have to be spentunproductively on the employment of whole-time sick visitors.&apos;6. But the increase in the weekly contributions will be astill more serious objection. Excluding Ireland there are now10,000,000 men and 4,000,000 women insured against sickness and perhaps 4,000,000 men and 500,000 women insured against unemploy-me nt,The present weekly contributions are:-health Insurance UnemploymentMen      7d. Men      5d.Women   6d. Women   5dThe present position is therefore approximately as follows: -6,000,v000 men      at 7d. ))     insured against sickness only,500,000 women   at 6d, )4,000,000 men      at        ))     insured against sickness and500,000 women   at lid..) unemployment.7.     Under the new scheme -with 20/- benefits (15/- women)the normal contributions would be l/lO -for men and 1/6 for women in the case of all employed persons, other than domestic servants.This means that in the case of some millions of insured personsthe weekly contributions would be more than trebled., and in other cases, also running into millions, the contributions will be nearly doubled..    While organised labour, has secured a great increase in wages there are large masses of unorganised labour which have not secured proportionate advances;   and even in thecase of organised labour, subscriptions to trade unions, and voluntary contributions to friendly societies, have to be (addedto their share, whatever it is, of the compulsory contribution.8./
the Exchequer, taking account of the State -conte-ibirU-ori of two-ninths, (or a quarter) of the additional cost of benefits undassuming that the doctor&apos;s capitation   rate is raised to anaverage rate -of 10/6, but making allowances for a largercontribution than hitherto from societies&apos; funds towards thecost of medical benefit, would be  1,500,000 a year for HealthInsurance and  2,500,000 for Unemployment Insurance, assuming the State contributes the same proportion of the cost ofunemployment insurance as at present.Note as to Maternity J^ejieJTitIn the estimate of the cost of increasing sickness benefit to 15/- and 12/6 and disablement benefit to 7/6, no provision has been made for any increase in maternity benefit,the funds which would have been available for this purposehaving to be applied towards the increased cost of medical benefit.     Nevertheless, it would probably be difficult to resist a demand for some increase in maternity benefit,, ifsickness and disablement benefits and the remuneration of the doctors are simultaneously increased and a larger allowance ismade to Societies to meet the expenses of aftmini strati on,including the salaries of their staffs.    The maximum amount towhich the maternity benefit could be increased is  2 and to achieve this it vrould be necessary to prolong the period forthe redemption of reserve values for a-further five years.This is the longest extension that can be contemplated, sinceany attempt to carry it further would break down the financial provisions for the redemption of the reserve values.Summary of Conclusions.(1)   Unemployment and sickness benefit must be the same in amount.(2)   An Unemployment and Sickness Benefit of 20/- and 15/-,allowing for other consequential changes, would involve an additional liability on the Exchequer of  ,8,500,000a year.
(3)   These increases would be fatal to economical administrationby appropriate ove d s oc id) &apos;L j s 3.(4)   The contributions would be enormously increased, e.g. in thecase of the majority of insured men from 7d. to 1/10 a week.(5)   This increase would.impose an excessive burden on workers and industry^ would, be a serious blow to trade unions andwould probably destroy the friendly societies.(6)   The cost of collecting contributions would be greatlyincreased, wholesale evasion would have to be faced and agreat increase of the inspectorate would be inevitable.(7)   Some increase both of Health and Unemployment benefits isgenerally demanded, but 15/- for men and 12/6   for womenrepresent reasonable figures, which both the Departmentsconcerned could hope to administer with safety..G. ADDISON.Ministry of Health.19. 11. 19.

</content>
</cab>
