<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/93/0 images: 437-462</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HlS^PQCtJMSKT IS Tim PROPERTY OF HIS BRIT AMI 0 KAJESTiS (KWmWT O&quot;&quot;&apos;-&amp; 4 3CASIKFiT.rVERY SECRUT,c p* 190.C01ETTKE1 01? IRlDLAKp.Third Re-oort of the Committee.(Pi^Vious Report;! O^P.^ and C.P. 137j -The Committee now submit to&apos; the Cabinet a report on thefinancial aspect of the proposed Home Rule Bill,   There are arumber of unsettled questions raised in this report about whichthey make no recommendation because they think it advisable thatthe Cabinet should first decide whether they approve of thefinancial proposals in their broad aspect. . They wish, further, topoint out that the Chancellor of tho Exchequer has not yetexpressed his opinion in regard to the finances of the BilliThe financial proposals involve certain, me-dif^cat ion of their original plan.   They therefore append for the convenience of the Cabinet, a short statement of the heads of their proposal as it stands at the present time.H3ADS OF PROPOSAL1. That two Parliaments should be set up in Ireland, one for the province of Ulster and one for the three Southern prorin-oea,upon which should be immediately conferred all the powers ofgovernment except :-(a) Those permanently reserved to the Imperial Parliamentsuch as Crown, Foreign Affairs, Defence, Dignities, Treason^Trade outside Ireland, Coinage, Wireless etc.(b) Powers temporarily reserved as &quot;below, pending agreementbetween the two legislatures. .2. That a Council for Ireland should be constituted consist-ing of 20 representatives from each of the two Parliaments with powers of private Bill legislation from, the outset, and exercisingsuch further powers as may be conferred upon it by simultaneousacts passed   by the two Irish Parliaments.3. That the two Irish legislatures should be given largeconstituent powers so that by simultaneous legislation they canconfer upon the Council of Ireland any powers not reserved to theImperial Parliament and can, if they so wish, convert it, withoutfurther reference to the Imperial Parliament into a Parliament forthe whole of Ireland.4. That in order to promote Irish unity certain services,notably agriculture, technical education, transportation, pld age pensions, health and unemployment, insurance and labour exchanges,which it is specially undesirable to divide, should be reservedfor one year to the Imperial Parliament in the hopes that within that time the Irish legislatures will have agreed either to trarusnfetthem to the control of the Council of Ireland, or to tho controlof an all Ireland legislature constituted for the purpose.   if at the end of the year the Parliaments have passed no identicallegislation for the purpose, or have not jointly asked for a postponement-, the powers should automatieally be divided betweenthem.
- a -5. That Ireland&apos;s share of Imperial charges should hereckoned at one-fortieth of the total, and that the Imperial---Parliament should retain customs and excise as the sourcefrom which they will secure Ireland&apos;s share of War Debt,Pensions and Defence charges, estimated for the normal year at  16,250,000.     Any balance over and above the ono-fortiethto be handed back to the Irish Exchequer,    ( or detailssee reports annexed).6. That all other taxes (except income tax as below)should be handed over from the outset to the IrishLegislatures.7. That a free gift should be given to Ireland of irish land which means the gift to the Irish Exchequers ofabout  3,500,000 a.year to b4gin with rising to over  5,^00,000when the Land Purchase scheme has been completed.8. That the income ta^ should be reserved for one yearand should thereafter be transferred to Irish controlprovided that the two Irish Parliaments had constituted asingle legislature for all Ireland.   The Committee were divided as to whether in the event of their failing to constitute sueh a body within one year, the income tax shouldautomatically go over to the Irish Parliaments at the end ofone year, with the other temporarily reserved services.9. The financial effect of these proposals is that ireland would for tho first year have a surplus of 3,250,000 and after the first year of  6,500,000 rising toabout  9.000,000 as the Land Purchase is completed, while theBritish Exchequer would sustain an exactly equivalent loss.lull details will be found in the annexed reports.2,Whitehall.Gardens, S.^.l.24th l&apos;nyember,. 1919 *
(THIS, POO IJMEfl J; 1Z- THE PROPERTY OP HIS,, BRITANNIC MAJESTY * S GOVEP^h:.^&quot;*......h Ml II i,   ilnnf .....w\     JlnilllTlit   li(.......Mi n ii.......  *.......null......Hilt   i .   i        i 1h1hi . k i   Hi    i I-, h.....    in   ii ,mm mh mt-Wy---, - ,v  JJjj     J ^SECRET IRISH COMMITTEE,,0,1.35 REPORT.-6? SUB-COMMITTEE OH IRISH gIMOE,Note.The Sub-Committee ask that, in view of-thecomplexities of the problem and the shortness oftime they hare had for ltd consideration, therecommendations in this report should be regardedas subject&apos;to alteration,1.        Irish revenue for 1919-20 is estimated at  39,430,000.Irish expenditure for 1919-20 is estimated at  19,913,000.Excess profits duty is eaAluded frsmths former figure, andthe bread subsidy and cut-o -work donation from the latter.The contribution of Ireland, therefore, to Imperial services for the current year is estimated at about  19,500,000. . Imperial charges may bo roughly estimated   for the normalyear as follows :-Service of Debt.......................... .. 366,000,000 per annum.Pensions.......................... 120,000,000   &quot;      &quot;Defence, etc.,........... ,-......... 170&quot;,000,000   &quot;      &quot;Total  650,000,000   &quot;      &quot;Par details of Irish revenues seo Appendix &quot;C&apos;\3. The percentage of these charges whioh Ireland should payon the hypothesis that it -should bear a proportion in accordancewith its oapaoity to pay has been repeatedly examined.     Twoestimates recently made, end attached, vary between l/35th andl/43rd (Appendices).      The Sub-Committee are agreed, pending further and more detailed examination to assess Ireland&apos;o shareif the -cost of Imperial services provisionally at Zffo or l/.40th.On this basis Ireland should pay during the current year, 16,250,000 on account of Imperial services as compared with about 19,500,000 which she is paying at present.4. In addition there is the question of land purchase.     At&apos;present some  100,,000,000 has been spent.in the purchase of Irish
land Involving an annual payment from Ireland to Gkreat-Britainunder the head of annuities, covering both interest and sinkingfun a, between  3,000,000 and&apos; 3,600,000.     In order, however, tocomplete land purchase about another  30,000,000 must be raised and spent,involving fit present rates of interest an increase intotho total charges in respect of Irish, land/ about  5.750,000.5, The total liability of Ireland, therefore, on thoassumption that she was to pay a share estimated at l/4Cth willbe as followsImperial services..................... 16,250,000Land purchase ...................... .  5,750,000 22,000,0006, There is aloe the question of a grant of      2,000.000 for housing.     lie promise of this kind has been made, though the PrimeMinister undertook to give a grant for housing as part of theHome Rule scheme offered in 1917, which was rejected byMr,Redmond when he accepted the Irish Convention instead.     3nthe other hand, an Irish Housing Act, involving an expenditureout of taxes of 5/4th of the rents charged and collected has alreadybeen passed,   This may mean an annual expenditure of  100,000 ayear, rising by, say,  100.,000 o year to a million a year,7.       v In considering the problem of Home Rule finance, theSub-Committee have proceeded on the assumption that Ireland wouldbe required to make a contribution towards War   Debt and pensions in proportion to its capacity to bear these charges.     They didnot consider that it would be just to Great Britain, or that the   &apos;British public would agree, that Ireland should escape Its shareof the liability of the Great Vfer.     Under this head alone, namely,War   Debt and Pensions, Irelandfs share on the basis of l/40thwould be  12,000,000.     In regard to the cost of future defence,the Committee examined two possible courses.     The first was
that Ireland should be required to pay its proportionate shareof these expenses;   and the second, that so far m the futureis concerned, Ireland should be treated   on the Dominion basis.that is to 3^y, left to decide its own contribution towardscommon defence, either in cash or in kind.     The first coursewould mean that the total liability of Ireland in respect ofdefence, etc on tho basis of the normal year coats would be 1,250,000.     If the second course were adopted, there is no estimate to be made.     The majority of tho Subcommittee considerthat the first course should be adopted, but state the &quot;two alternatives for the consideration of the Committee.8, Finally, there is the question of land purchase.    &apos; Ifthe existing system is completed and the stock kept in the handsof the British Government, it will be necessary to find security for the payment of an additional  5,750,000 from Ireland.     Onthe other hand, in the Draft Eill of last year, it was proposedthat a free gift should be made to Ireland of its land at themoment of the coming into force of the Home Rule Act.     Thefinancial effect of this proceeding upon the British exchequer is obvious,     In view, however, of the fact th-et political considerations may have to outweigh financial cost in a matterof this kind, a majority of the Sub-Committee recommend that a free gift should be made to Ireland, of the amounts recoverablefrom Irish purchasers of the land.     In the event of the acceptanceof this proposal, the Irish Parliaments should be left to provideout vf Irish taxes for Housing subsidies and any additional educational expenditure under the new Irish   Educational Sill, estimatedat  1,500,00 0.Tc summariseHypothesis (a)If Ireland is ?-&amp;;Ue&amp; upon to pay its sj&amp;areof War Debt, ana future defence, but is   -given a free gift of its land, its annual contribution on present figures would be 16.250,000.
Hypothesis (b)If Ireland is called upon tn pay nothingnore than&apos;its share of War Debt and Pensionsand is given a free gift of its land, and is left like the Dominions to make its on.icontribution towards defence, its ccntjibu-.tion on the basis of present figures wouldbe  12^000,000.For convenience of reference it may be repeated thatits present contribution is about  19,^00,000, exclusive of the land annuities which at present amount to between 3,000,000 and  3,^00,000.The Sub--Commit tee then considered tfhat taxes shouldbe reserved to the Imperial Parliament in order toenable it to secure revenues of this magnitude from ireland.     There was no doubt that customs was infinitelythe best.     It is/ihe source of revenue reserved underall federal constitutions.     It avoids inquisition bythe Imperial Parliament into the domestic affairs of Irishcitizens, for it simply provides for the control by imperial authorities of customs houses through which all goods entering and leaving the ports have to pass, andsuch goods will only be able to pass out of or intoIreland after payment of the Imperial dues.     In thecase of South Ireland, therefore, a Ginn FeinGovernment could only stop the payment of customs either by seizing the customs houses, which would be an actcf war, or by /
m    ff m ^starving its own citizens of all foreign goods..   Unfor-unfortunately, however, customs only produce at the present time a revenue of  13,000,020 which is quite inadequate, exceptin the last of the hypotheses considered above.   Furtherthis figure has only been reached in the present year.Revenues fcr previous years have been as follows1918-19    ......     9,744,0001916-17   ..     ..  6,887,0001915-16 ....      ...    5,5315,00.01915-14    ......    5,674,0001003- 4......     3,075 ,003Moreover, customs revenue is unstable for another reason.It is drawn largely from taxe3 on the breakfast table, suchas tea and sugar, on tobacco, on wines and spirits.   the yield might be very largely modified by Government policy,by changes in taste., by temperance reform.   There are,therefore, very strong reasons against regarding the presentyear yield of customs revenue as being in itself a stablesecurity for the Im-erial contribution apart altogether from its inadequacy.   It is necessary, therefore, to con-sider the other taxes.   Excise yields a further  11,000,0.00which together with customs produces an amount slightly over that required in order to meet ireland contribution on thehypothesis that she is t.o pay her share of all Imperialservices and also her payments on account of land purchase.   Theexcise is open to the same objections as customs in that itIs essentially a fluctuating revenue.   It also involvesImperial intervention within Ireland itself, for in orderto collect it, inspectors have to visit, the leadmng breweriesand distilleries and the pr* priet-rs have to pay them theamounts of the tax to an imperial account.   Further thecollection of excise is associated with the question ofexcise licences, and, if the same authority does not controlb&apos;,th; leakage may occur.   On the other hand. Imperial inter-venticn in order to collect excise is reduced to a minimum,fcr
far the revenue is-derived almost-errtlrely^ from-a^fewlol^^.firms..  The enormous majority of Irish citizens are netdirectly affected.   The firms themselves would prrbablyresist an attempt on the part of a Sinn Fein Government to compel them to pay excise into an Irish account because avery large proportion of their trade is In Great Britain.Finally customs and excise are usual federal taxes, areunited in administration4 and are largely regarded by thepublic as a single service.   There are, therefore very strong reasons for the view that, if sufficient taxing powers are tc be retained in Imperial hands to cover Ireland&apos;slegitimate contribution to Imperial services, customs and excise should be the taxes retained.On the other hand, the Committee were impressed by the argument that the retention of these taxes by themselvesinvclved,putting all the Imperial goods Intc one basket, andthat not a very strong basket.   The reasons for the fliic-tuating character of these taxes have already been described.It was, therefore, urged thai the right course would be toretain a proportion both of the direct and the Indirecttaxes in order tc ensure a stable revenue.   On consideration,however, the Sub-Committee rejected this idea on the groundthat the retention : n Imperial hands, of say, both customs and income tax,.*culd stultify the financial responsibilityof the Irish Parliaments... If the Home Rule scheme &quot;is towork at all,, the Irish Parliaments, like the provincial orstate Parliaments in every federation, must be given rea*end flexible sources of revenue.   Further the retention of-inccme tax means that Imperial officials have to dealdirectly with not only the richer classes in Ireland butthe farmers and trade.unionists as well.   Finally the factthat in most federations the general line of division givesdirect taxes to the local authorities and indirect taxes tothe central authority, is a string additional argument forapplying the same principle in the Irish case.
The Subcommittee, however,considered a third alterna-tive, that of retaining the customs as an Imperial sourcecf reremie, ?nd requiring payments of say, 3C$ yf everyIrish tax into an Imperial acceunt until the total ofliUbility      the Imperial Parliament.   This scheme hasin ltd favour the fact that if it worked at all it to uldgive ihe Imperial Government? security for the payment ofthe whxle contribution owed by Ireland,   The Subr-C-smmittee,however. rejected it partly beoause it would be open tomisrepresentation as involving a British tribute from everyaspect of the Irish finances, arid partly because it would be practically certain that a Sinn Fein parliament would refuse to pay over any percentage of its revenues te theBritish Exchequer.,So far as finances of the local legislatures areconcerned, the Sub-Committee recoi^imend that all othertaxes except customs snd excise should be transferred tooIrish-control.   In the case at the income tax, however,they were unable to reach agreement as t* whether Incometax should only be transferred to an united Irish authoritycr whether in the event of the two legislatures not agreeing to constitute any unifying authority for Ireland, and notpetitioning that the Income tax should be temporarilyretained in Imperial hands, it should be divided like theother temporarily reserved services between the tuo F-vrlia-ments.   They recognise the powerful objections, especiallycf an administrative kind &quot;faieh can be advanced against theproposal tt transfer.,the income tax to. Ireland at all...The transfer immediately Intensifies the existing   difficultyin regard to double income taxes.... It 13 obvious that these difficulties *ill be greatly aggravated if the income&apos; taxis divided between v*c Irish legislatures.   On the otherhand they did not tb.ynk that: any Home Rule scheme   culdreceive the support *f moderate men in Ireland cr iver--seas unless it gave to the Irish: legislatures a realbcth oustcms and these pi yments discharged the Irishand
and flexible source of revenue.   The Committee therefore recommend that the usual precedent should bi;. followed andthat all direct taxation Including income tax should betransferable  under the Bill to, Irish control.The Sub-Committee therefore, decided to recommend asthe ft nance proposals to be embodied in a Bill dram upon the lines of Scheme X :-(a) That the contribution..of Ireland to Imperialservices should, subject to. any corrections inchmay&apos;be necessary through, more detailed examinationbe taken at one-fortieth of the United Kingdomexpenditure,(b) giat the Bill should provide that customs and Excise should be retained as security for thepayment of Ireland&apos;s contribution to Imperialservices *(c) 5hat the Joint Exchequer Beard should decide in each year the amount payable br Ireland inrespect of (1) debt, (2) pensions, (5) defence,and return the surplus inUv the Irish Exchequers. .(d) y^l^A* --here should be a periodical, reassessmentevtriyAur*ing the first five years,, and.   thereafter at five yearly intervals cf the relativecapacity of Ireland and Great Britain to paythe cost of Imperial oharges.(e) That in &quot;fche event of the Imperial taxes notproviding, the full amount of the Imperial contrir .buViori -md the Irish Parliament for Parliaments not .making a matricular contribution.&apos;t^ make up thesum, the Imperial Parliament should clearly havethe right to impose additional taxation by meansof the reserved taxes.(f) Tnat the Bill should provide that at the end .of one year -hen the temporarily reserved services are handed over to the Irish legislatures, theincome taxes should&quot;also be handed over, provided thatthe t&apos;rc legislatures have &apos;Constituted an unitedauthority for the whole.cf Ireland to vhich the -income tax car. be transferred.   In the event of theIrish Legislatures net agreeing te .constitute suchan authority the income tax must either be retained in Imperial hands,, or be divided between the legislatures.   Cn this last point the Sub-Committeemake no recommendation.(g) By a majority the Sub-Committee agreed thatthe sums still, recoverable from the purchasers of irish land should be treated like the othertemporarily reserved services,In addition tc considering the. ab^ve recommendations  -the Summittee &quot;111.have to decide:-1*     Fhether Ireland ia to be required t^ payits proportionate &quot;share of the,expensed cf defenceor to be allowed to make &apos; its own..voluntary ccntri-buticn&apos; in: future.
c&amp; 5 32c     Whether in the event cf the legislaturesnot agreeing to constitute an united authority inIreland&apos; within the ii;st year, the income taxshould be/ retained in Imperial hands until theydo sc.,16, Appended is a statement showing (a) an estimate of irish revenue and expenditure at the various stages of thecoming into co-operation of Bill X, and (b) a similar statementof the effect of the proposals iX? the Bill on the british exchequer.21-11,19&apos;,
S E &apos; g R E ti, APPENDIX &quot;A&quot;CAB I NET,CO^ITTEE DN IRELAND.Tne attached memorandum was prepared In the treasury for the use of the Sub-Committee on Home Rule FinanceeIt was asked for at very short notice and though itwas sent to the Chancellor of. the Exchequer it did nottoreach him in time to examine or. even/read it,Consequently he reserves the right to qualify or even to withdraw it, if on examination he finds it necessaryto do so.Treasury., S.W.26th November^,1919.
3 (j bMfiSgg GAPAOITY 0^ IR^LAITP.Tho ascertainment of the taxable capacity of Ireland forImperial purposes is not a- problera capable of precise solutionat all.     Perhaps tho best solution &quot;of all is obtained by applying a system of taxation, which is in itself fair, to theUnited Kingdom,    sotting off against the sum contributed undersuoh a system by Ireland the necessary or reasonable local Irishexpenditure, and taking the balance as the proper contributionto Imperial services.     The&apos;existing system of taxation , withits very hdavy Inoomo Tax and death duties, is remarkable forits leniency to the poorer part of the population.    nevertheless it has been criticised on tho gaound that the indirect taxeshappen to fall with undue severity on Irish.habits.   consequently it cannot bo acceptor!&apos;&apos; without challenge.      Uireover ourrevenue is in a transition&apos; stage.     We still have an ExcessProfits Duty, and we are still incurring many transitory formsof expenditure.    Wo oan only gu^ss what our future expenditure^and the taxes imposed to meet it will bo.It is therefore necessary to use what statisticaldata we have to arrive at some more stable tegt. of the taxable capacity of Ireland-Several attempts have been made at the various stages of the Homo Rule controversy to solve the problem.   - The RoyalCommission of i&apos;894 - &apos;6 on financial Relations failed to agree onthe&apos; subject of Ireland&apos;s taxable capacity but &quot;no members of thoCommission estimated it as exceeding. l/20th.&quot;   Professor Pigon andPrcfessor GIdham;t in&apos;a&quot;report prepared for the Irish Convention1(but not presented to it), were inclined to put it as low asl/32nd or oven l/35th of the taxable capacity of the UnitedKingdom.     This estimate was based on the relative yields ofEstate Duty,  nemo Tax and Super&quot;tax, the author? being &quot;unable
w JOto say in which&quot; direction the income&apos;iax of Estate iMtx^^t-e-ought to he corrected by the tost of indirect taxation.&quot;Sir John Bradbury suggested that the alleged undueburden of indirect taxation on Ireland night be allowodfor if a hypothetical fair distribution of taxation werearrived at by taking tho actual shares of Great Britain andIreland, in the direct taxes and adding shares in the indirect taxes based on an assumed proportion of national incomes in tho two countries.     Taking the Census ofProduction of 1907 as a rough guide-ho put tho Irish, ednational income at l/17th of the total and obtain&apos;a rosuitof &quot;between l/2[?th and l/26th&apos;\ vizRevenue , United Kingdcm..      Ireland,      &quot; &quot;      &quot;    iAssumed Customs &amp; ExciseRevenueAssume-1 Birect TaxRevenueAssumed-non-Tax RevenueThese figures are all for Ireland&apos;a total taxpaymgcapacity.     The Imperial contribution has to be calculated byleduo ting looal expenditure,   Professor Pigou brought thisout at l/l28th,   Sir J, Bradbury arrived at l/42nd.What follows is an attempt to evolve some more definite principle than these estimates invoke.195.ooo.oco    11,500,000 t&apos;j/17)420c 000fcoo     12,500,00040,000,000      1,500,000Cyo,000,000     25; fOOf 000
For this purpose we want to &quot;know ^ aggmgsrto amount and also the character of the income of both Groat 3rttalrr--suidIreland.t    The following is a tentative analysis, the datafor which will bo described and explained in a separatememorandumYear 1907 f t,h t p , tho^ Census of Production).10   Incomesn deriTsa directly from tho Labour and Cs.pl talof the country fin millions of pounds).Or eat Britain.     Irelendc United KingdomManufactures and      ]Mining. ) 690 23 713Agriculture and       )Fisheries. J 171 50 821Railways. 117 4 121Houses. 192 R  00Domestic Servants 76 _____4 m__801,246 39 1,33511. Commercial... Financial and t Pr o f e a   5. or,aI Xncomeg, and thosederived from Shipping and. Foreign securities.710 _20 730Total    ljj!66 105 2,065The underlying assumptions of this classification are that thefirst group, representing The earnings of labour and, capital inthe country, is of a kind common to all countries, rich and poor,,,while tba--soconjlJLncludes those heads of income which arcspecially characteristic of a rich country, and sp^       j char-actoristio, among rich countries, of one which is the centre ofa great empire.   There is reason to suppose that much the greaterpart of Schedules nCn nD,T and lrBTT of the Income Tar is composedof those incomes, the profits on industrial capital (which aroincluded in Group I) being very much less than financial and commercial profits.   At tho present time Ireland contributes8$ per cent of Schedules WC&quot; n9n and TTSW (exclusive x)i quarter-ly assessments on wages) and this proportion which doos notappear to vary r*ry much from year to year, has bo,en used toestimate her share in Group II.
The statistics employed all relate to tie year 1997.To adapt them to present conditions they would presumablyhave to be at least doubled.     But it is not unreasonable toassume that the relative proportions have not been in anyessential respect disturbed.     The interest on government securities has, it is true, grown enormously.     But investmentsin war loans are,likely to follow much the same proportions asthe commercial and financial incomes.It is&apos; suggested, as a good working isftle that, for thepurpose of apportioning the relative contributions of the twocountries to Imperial Expenditure, a proportion based on theIrish share of inooraesin Group XI, calculated from the IncomeTax data, might be taken at any rate as a first approximation.This is not a perfectly logical solution, but it has muchto recommend it,   . A purely parochial country has its incomenearly confined to Group I, and it must raise its revenue tomeet essential local Government services from the income con- obtained in that group.     In proportion as it acquires commercial and imperial interests, it is compelled to incur expenditure for the development and defence of those interests, and at thesame time acquires additional resouroes in the correspondingforms of income.     The practical application of such a, prinoiplecan only be approximate, because (1) the most parochial of countries must have some commercial financial and professionalincomes; (2) What are called Imperial services must be supplied in some degree even for an entirely non-imperial country.;(3) the actual assessments tc Income Tax cannot clearly separateout the earnings of industry from other forms of profit, whilerents derived from commercial (as distinct from industrial)business premises are included under houses. iun&apos;But, hbv/ever/featisfaotory it may be the principlesuggested luCfe two;great advantages; (1) it Is based on aneconomic fact which is eertaluly one of the most important
constituents in what we ordinarily mean by taxable capacity, and (2) the proportion which it leads us to adopt is ascertainable in the ordinary course of administration of the Income Tax. Thus it could ? be adopted once and for all, or subjected to periodical revision, whichever course is preferred on grounds of policy (though if the Income Tax ? to be assessed imperially comparisons might no longer be trustworthy). Applied to existing conditions, it would probably mean a reduction of Ireland&apos;s present Imperial contribution. Imperial expenditure may be estimated (in a normal year) at 650 millions and 2\\3//4 per cent of this would be £17,875,000. According to the calculation recently circulated, Irish revenue is 391\\1//2 million and expenditure 20 millions but the figures are too uncertain to allow of much weight being given to the difference between the contribution of 19\\1//2 million and that calculated above.


AHEi-:DIX &quot;Bw,&amp; ROUGH NOTE ONIRE LANDT S SJiLUCJ CS? ITiflPFiEIlL EIPIlHDIITURE,ft ____________There are two methods (1) To ;?eek to determine what isIreland?3 fair share of Imperial expenditure or (2) Toabandon the effort to assess the figure. ,apd on political or administrative grounds to reserve a specified tax or taxes asan equivalent of Ireland1a contribution.     This second methodis attractive because simple *    Thus Irish Customs revenuemight be appropriated as IrelandTs contribution-     But theprocedure is open to serious objections     (a) It is a blindmethod.     There is no standard by which its adequacy can be measured,     (b ) A group of taxes like Customs may afford a relatively substantial contribution to-day but something very different in two or three years.     The yield of Irish Customin 1914-15 was  3,674,000 and in 1919-20  13,000,000,   (c)It would certainly be attacked by those who have examinedIrelandTs taxable capacity and who should be able to denonstratethe unsound basis of this procedure.     The determination of&apos;Ireland&apos;s taxable capacity and of IrelandTs fair contributionto Imperial expenditure should therefore be considered basalin making the financial arrangements,,The question of determining taxable capacity is obviouslydifficult.     Hot only are the data imperfect, but there is room for argument as to what are the criteria on which taxable capacity is to be determined.     Nevertheless, it is easy to exaggerate any of these difficulties and a good practicaljudgment can be reached,,ootnote.     Considerable attention has bcwi given to the question of determining ireland to taxable caoacrry ar.u her share in imperial expenditure.     It was the subject of the investigations of ,thed   Royal Commission of 1894-5,,    &quot;Recently, in the Irish Convention,the Chairman, on his own personal respor.sibj.lity referred to a confidential Committee the question of taxable capacity, and ashort report on the subject was produced signed by ProfessorsPigou and Oldham,     This Report was never presented to the Con-vention, but it is certain to get publicity and be made use of.
Before proceeding, it is important to distinguish between(1) Taxable capacity and (2) Ireland&apos;s share of Imperial ex$penditure, as these two terms are sometimes used as if theymeant the same.      ireland^ taxable capacity is from the natureof Irish local expenditure a higher proportion than Ireland!s share of Imperial expenditure.     Thus   in 1918-19 Ireland&apos;staxable capacity in terms of the whoje revenue of the UnitedKingdom was one-twenty-second part, whereas her sh^re in orcontribution to Imperial expenditure was l/42nd part.Briefly stated in my opinion the best test of taxable capacity under present conditions is provided b. the combinedyield of direct and indirect taxation.      On this v.e have definite and comparative evidence over a period of years.    Other critical-eria may ultimately provide a better basis and can be used to supplement this main line, but until the existing system oftaxation is shown to be radically unjust tc the community it remains the most representative body of evidence.     In recentyears the steady increase in the proportion of direct as con-pared with indirect&apos; taxation has met largely the criticism whichwas formerly made&quot; that the system of. taxation pressed undulyheavily upon the poorer classes and therefore the poorer nationwithin the United kingdom.Taking the latest public returns o.f revenue and expenditure for the six years from 1913-14 onwards, ve find that Irishtaxable capacity as measured by tho yield was represented.approximately by the following fractions, namely:1913-14v1914-15 ,1915-16   1916-17   1917-18   1918-19   1919-201/17th    1/I8th    1/I8th    1/ -23rd  1/Z5th    l/22nd    ? l/l8th(The full figures for 1919-20 are not yet available).It may be pointed ott that as expenditure rises the pro-
ei U (Gportion of revenue contributed by the poorer country tends to fall, it Is therefore not unexpected to find that in thelast three years the Irish proportion v/as lower than in thothroe years preceding and theoo latter years form the saferbasis for framing an estimate of Ireland^ taxable capacity inthe immediate future.     The higher proportion indicated in1919-20 is, I understand, due to the removal of the restrictionson beer and spirits and the greater supplies generally oftaxable articles.     The above figures include non-tax revenue,and certain minor adjustments would also have to be made by wayof eliminating taxes which are applicable only to Great Britain,but the tie are of minor lai; ortanoe at the present time.If, on the other hand, the test of income tax with supertax and estate duty is taken, as in the heport of ProfessorsPigou and Cldham, Irish tax&amp;bke capacity is in the region ofl/30th to l/S5thr but. as bir John Bradbury pointed out in a minute to the previous Home Rule Committee on the subject cftaxable capacity, there are plain objections to this limitedtest, and the evidence from general taxation is a fairer index0A further line of evidence hat been sought by comparing thenational income of Ireland and of Great Britain- on the basisof the census of production.     This evidenoe led. kir John.Bradbury to the conclusion that a fraction between. l/25th andl/26th rather under estimates than over estimates Ireland^ taxable,capacity-   As it is important that the benefit of the doubt should rest with Ireland, under present circumstances the taxable cataeiiymay jpproximately be taken at some such figure as l/25th.Assuming for the present that a figure mainly determinedby the general yield of all taxation direct and indirect, isthe best immediate measure of taxable capacity, the next questionIs what is ireland fair share of or contribution to Imperialexepnditure.     In order to determine this it is necessary to
deduct from the amount -rep re renting total taxable capacity thecost of Irish local national services.       If ;e take the returnsavailable for the last four years of revenue and expenditure,in 1915-16, Irisla revenue was 1/18bh of the total revenue oftae United kingdom, and the Irish share of the Imperial expend!-inturo was 1/43rd,/   1916-17 the figures ,vere l/23rd of totalrevenue, and l/42nd of I porial expenditure; in 1917-18 7,/?athof total revenue ami l/42nd of Imperial expenditures     In 1918-19l/22nd of total revenue and l/43rd of Imperial expenditure,j?or some years before 1915-16 there was no Irish contributionto Imperial expenditure but a deficit.       It would thereforeappear that a figure such as l/42nd would not be unfair as Ire-land1 a share of Ij per la 1 expenditure-     If for the present thatis asniraed, the problem is to secure that ouch revenue will be forthcoming to the Imperial lixcheauer.     On the   hole the sim-plest way of securing this revenue seems to be retention of customs and Lxcise,One further point:   in order to ul just, the question efdetermining the proportion must bo revised from time to time,Such a body as the Joint iiixchequer Board will have fuller evi^denes for examining the situation periodically and suggestinga more just contribution.     In this connection, it would be agreat advantage if, beside the English and Irish representatives,an outside party, best   represented under the nomination of theDominion Governments, were a part of the .&apos;.,xchsouer Board,This provision would be im ortant.as a further guarantee of fair play between Great Britain and Ireland, and it would also have this advantage, that, as ultimately the problem of imperial relations will involve the attempt to secure a rational basisof contribution, the Dominions in helping with the Irish diffi-culty would also be taking a step towards the toll:!? ion of the wider problems of &apos; Imperial relations.
80th November,, 1919.It should he understood that the above is only &amp; afcu^note, necessarily hastily prepared, and that the   uestion oftaxable capacity should be as thoroughly and e.taotly siftedas is possible with existing data, and the case thereon fullyset out,W.G.S.A.
Ai!P731?PlX C.KVB.        The subjoined figures are all^&amp;stimirt-ee,.aad^.r-owing to the extreme uncertainty   of &quot;both sides?of the future Budget are vary conjectural Astimates.(a)   Irish Revenue and Expenditure.U)   The girt;t Year  (l) Local Expenditure 7^ 039,000Transferred RevenuesPeath Duties l,380,OOCStampy SOO.000Licenses andEntertainments Tax 480,000Miscellaneous 130,000 2,790,000deficiency. 4,24^000(2) Retained by Imperial ExchequerRevenue  .Customs 13.050,000Excise onCommodl-Giiis 10,970,000Income Tax 10,620,000Post Office 2,000,000 36,6-40,000Expenditure &apos;.-Irish 12,874,000Irish shareof imperial expenditure        16,2 ?0,000 29,124,000(3) Balance to be credited toIreland 7,5l6,00OLeduct local Irish ftoficiency (l)     4,249,000Irish surplUB 3,267,000(Prospective chargos :-Education       1,?00,000Housing(first year     100,000 )
(ii)   After the First Year.Alternative I (income Tax remaining Imperial)   (l) Original Local ExpWndituro 7,039,000Services transferred&apos;after ^,019,000 12,0^8.000one year ^    ._Revenue as abovn (i) (l)     2,790,000Land Purchase Annuities      3,160,000 5,970,000ciency 6,081,000(2) Retained by Imperial ExchequerRevenue as above i(2) 36,640,000Expenditure :-Irish,Land Purchase x 1,039,000Polioe 3,417,000Post Office &amp; RevenueDepartments 3,399,000Irish share of imperial expenditure 16,250,000 24,105,000(3) Balance to be credited to Ireland 12,538,00*Leduct local Irish deficiency   (l) 6,0?S,000Irish surplus 6,^4-7,000(The Land Purchase Annuities will grow till on tho completionof Land Purchase they will amount to  5,650,000 increasingthe Irish surplus, other things being equal, to  8,917,000 )x   i.e. Admin istretia-n (except collectionof annuities)  125,000Bonus stock charges  372,000Excess stock charges  542,000 1,039,000
(ii) After the Firot Year (continued)Alternative II (income tax transferred) (l) Original Local Expenditure        7,039,000Income Tax Administration 1^0,000Cther Services transferred after5,01$,000one year ^^^^Revenue as in (i) (l)Land Purcahse AnnuitiesIncome TaxSurplus .12,l3A;0O02,790,0003,loO,OCO10, 620, 000     1.6,590,0004,403,000(2) Retained &quot;by Imperial Exchequer :**Revenue an in (i) (2) 36,640,000Peduct Income Tax 10,620,000     26,020,000ExpenditureIrishDeduct Income Tax Adminis-trat ion7,$55,000130,0007,725,000Irish share of ImperialExpenditure16,250,000 .  23,975,000(3)Balance to he credited to IrelandLocal Irish Surplus (l)2,0^-5,0004,402,000-6/-47,000(iii) 6n the Constitution of authority for the whole of Ireland.Under the scheme as now submitted there is no longer anychange of any kind at this stage as compared with (ii)Alternative II.   The police, costing  3,417,000, can hetransferred fr&amp;n Imperial to looal control at any time within three years, but this merely has the effert of reducing thelocal Irish surplus to  985,000, and increasing the balance tobe credited to Ireland from Imperial funds to  5*^-62,000, leavinthe total Irish surplus unchanged at.  0,A47,000,   This change
has no direct connection with the creation of the single authority.(b) Effect on th^., Brit j Sh Exchequer.(i) The First Year   extra Budget change  3,26?,000(ii) After the First Year  6,447,000rising as Land Purchase progresses to         8,917,000.These sums must, however, he reduced by the oost ofany new Irish services;, except such as correspond to Britishmeasures which are provided for by new taxation (since newtaxation would, apart from the grant of self-government-r--fall, jxponthe Irish as well as upon the British taxpayer).

</content>
</cab>
