<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/93/0 images: 471-475</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
sovAtot)....TTHIS DOgUMmjLS Tgl PHOPEHTY OF HISBRIT AMI C MAJESTY TS GS F C R E T.C A B I H 7. T.CP. 193.THE 1 HI SK^JgJJiST IONM emo rand urn by Mr, Balf ou r.1.I admit that for many reasons, among which the Britishparty system is not the least important, the Unionist policy inIreland has not succeeded: and I agree that the pledges givent* the public in general, and to Sir      Grey in particular,, makeit impossible for the Government to sit still and do nothingexcept postpone or repeal the Home Rule Act of 1914.2.        The Cabinet are aware that, in my opinion, the only reallyworkmanlike alternative to preserving the Union is the excisionfrom it of the South and West of Ireland; the creation of an autonomous state bound by treaty to shoulder its fair share ofthe Imperial debt, and to concede such naval privileges along the coast as would prevent Ireland being a menace to the empire in case of war.   I gathered, however, that the Cabinet, whileagreeing with its Committee that Ireland, as a whole, may haveDominion status if she wants it, are unalterably averse fromgranting independence to any of its parts.   I do not thereforenow propose to press my solution any further, but shall confinemyself, in the present paper, to comments on the Committee scheme.My objections to this have their roots in the strong dis-like I feel to the doctrine assumed throughout the Committee&apos;sReport, and more than once explicitly proclaimed, that Ireland,all Ireland, has a separate national existence, and shouldnaturally and properly be organised as a single undividedpolitical unit&apos;.   The Committee admit, of course, that, so longas Ulster remains the Ulster we know, such an ideal cannot bevery (realised.   Hence their/artificial scheme of two Home Rule
parliaments and an Irish.,Council.   But trrey--rcgard. this division tf Ireland as a misfortune; and evidentlysthink it rather perverse of Ulster to throw ohstacles in the wayof complete unification.   In their recommendations theycarry this view to suoh length that while, on the one hand,*they make it aa easy as possible for Ulster to join itself with the rest of Ireland in forming a dominion&apos; State, onthe other hand they give it no power whatever to ft&amp;ala what it is, and as I think, ought to be, - an integral part ofthe United Kingdom.   This they call (p.7) &quot;respecting theprinciple of   self-determination and following the &quot;PeaceConference.&quot;   The Peace Conference has done some odd things;but never, I submit, anything quite so odd as this.In my opinion, this policy is due to an erroneousreading of Irish History; and a very imperfect apprehensionof British rights.   Surely we ought to assume, as a funda-mental axiom, that every part of the United Kingdom should remain a part of it, until overwhelming reasons are pro-duced for a separation,   can there be a nobler privilege ?and is it tolerable that we should take it by force from-   -our loyal fellow countrymen for no better reason than that,they live in the same island with those who proclaimtheir disloyalty in every quarter of the world ?
My first suggestion, therefore P is that the six counties of Ulster should be out out of the Eill, and.---only&quot;Home Ruleareas should be compelled to endure Home Rule.,Among other advantages this scheme gets rid of all the complications incident to the setting up of that oihgularpolitical experiment     &quot;The Council of Ireland&quot;-..It has another incidental advantage - It diminishes theintolerable injustice of allowing Home Ruler?co influence, per-haps control, British Affairs in matters which are purelyBritishe    The Committee seem to suppose that this will be avoided by obliging the unhappy Speaker to say what are, and what are not, purely British Affairs.    But this is.surely adelusion.     The most Important- British Affair which theHouse of Commons has to decide Is the kind of Governmentwhich is to advise tho King..     Such decisions, have and musthave a profound effect upon the conduct of 1 local affairs in England and Scotland - evgc labour questions, educationquestions, land questions, Church questions..    They will haveno effect whatever upon Irish !local affairs to     Is Ittolerable that they should be influenced by Irishmen?    IfUlster remains what she is, and vfhat she desires to be, theBritish grievance, though far from being removed, will atleast be mitigated,, since only the South and West of Irelandwill send these mongrel representatives to Westminster.     Buta complete cure can only be secured either by turning dls-loyal Ireland out of the Empire - a solution which the cabinet has rejected - or by giving It &quot;Dominion status&quot;- a policywhich meets with some   support from the report of the committee as we cannot have the former, I recommend the   latter *Observe the advantages of this pian:-1..    South West Ireland will have no representation at westminster,.2n    When once the amount of her debt to Great Britaintis determined^/and
and the security for it satisfactorily arranged, allfresh financial obligation on either side will be avoided.3.     If war should break out, we shall not again be In the humiliating position of having to decide whether we gain more (from a military point of view)by compelling Ireland by force nf arms to d o her duty,or by yielding i&amp;nominiously to the clamour of traitors,4.   We need not i:.:auble ourselves about Custom and ExciseIreland, if she desired it, can put on duties against us, - and we, if we desire it, can dn the same again3t herja fair arrangement by which we can hardly lose.5.     Ireland will have to punish her own criminals,just as she will have to finance her own enterprises.I do not know which of these changes will afford us the greatest relief *6.    The remarkable talents of the Southern Irish for parliamentary strategy will have only a domestic theatrefor their display,V.     The monstrous attacks to which Britain is subjectedIn English-speaking countries across the seas ?ill loseall their plausibility.   The procedure I recommend isin strict harmony with the principles and practice ofthe Peace Conference.   No one can say that ireland is enslaved, &quot;hen she is as free as Canada and Australia.No one can think that Ulster ought to join the&apos; Southand Test who thinks that the Jugo Slavs shculd be separated from Austria.   No one can think that Ulstershould be divorced from Britain who believes in selfdetermination.   The only people who will grumble arethose who imagine that this scheme deprives Ireland ofa unity to 1j&apos;hich she has a historic cl* dur...    but these people ignore the fact that such unity as Irelandposisessoa is mainly the work of England; that she has neverin all the centuries, been a single, organised, independent,
t-.5-state   and that if she were not- surrounded by water,no human, being&quot;would^jsver inlnir of, for^n^th^Lny^L^wi,Protestant North into the same political mould as thedisloyal and Roman Catholic South:.(Intd.) A.J.B.November. 25th, 191.9.

</content>
</cab>
