<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/121/0 images: 435-442</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAFilC iaJESTY&apos;S (WVBRHBEGBT.)SECRET.- CAEIKST.c. p. 2T2L.IMPORT BY THE G&amp;&amp;ra2 OFFICISR COi.S AilDIKG U CHIEF Oil THE GiiHERAL SITUATION IH IRBLA3JD FOR WEEK EilDIiTG 12th MARCH. 1921.(Circulated by the Secretary of State for War.)1. GffffERAL SITUATION. During the past week several conflicts have take  en&quot;place&quot;&quot;&quot;hTtween rehel flying columns and the forces of the Crown, in practically all of which severe casualties have &quot;been inflicted on the rebels, with but little loss to ourselves. These conflicts are the logical sequence of the action taken by the authorities. The policy of interning leading rebels has forced many men to leave their homes and go &quot;on the run&quot;. These men fom themselves into flying columns or as they are more frequently termed in rebel correspondence into &quot;active service units&quot; or &quot;active service sections&quot;.   Practically every Brigade of the Irish Volunteers in the S.w\has its &quot;A.S.U&quot;, and in the same Brigades nearly all the Battalions have Active Service Sections. Strenuous efforts are boing made by the Hd.Qra. of the I.R.A. to stir up activity in the quieter districts of Connaught, Lein3ter and even Ulster, in order &quot;to relieve the strain on the   8outh&quot;. Organisers have undoubtedly been sent out from Dublin for this purpose and there are indications that small nuclei of units have been despatched from the more active counties to rouse the fight-ing spirit of their more peaceable neighbours.The policy of destruction of roads and bridges still con-tinues, and a curious feature of this form of activity is that it is usually byroads which are less used by Crown forces that are chiefly selected for destruction. A careful study of the action taken in the Area West and South west of lariuin gives the irapres-sion that the rebel leaders are endeavouring to carry out the somewhat ambitious scheme (the plan of which was recently captur-ed) to isolate the Curragh in order to prevent the despatch of troops thence to neighbouring counties.Steps are being taken to deal with this, but this particular form of activity is, owing t*i the present shortage of effectives in many Battalions, very difficult to prevent and is quite likely to continue, in spite of the stoppage of fairs and markets and in spite of the repairs carried out under Military and police super-vision, as it is a form of enterprise which the local volunteers can carry out with but little risk to themselves, and one which, they hope, impresses the public with the power and ubiquity of the &quot;Irish Republican Army&quot;.The series of murders of unarmed soldiers, ex-soldiers, Pro-test ant farmers and others who were (generally quite without foundation) suspected of furnishing information to thu Authorities culminated on the 6th.inst: in the murders at Limerick of the Mayor, the ex-Mayor and another civilian. The Mayor and ex-Mayor will be a great loss to the Military and Police Authorities in Limerick City, as it is due to those two men and certain influen-tial priests that conditions in this city have been peaceable for many months. A great deal of friction has existed for over a year between the 1st. Limerick Bn. (an unenterprising unit to which the Mayor, Clancy, belonged) and the 2ndv Limerick Battalion
which under a man called Peter Dunne seceded from the 1st Batta-lion and &quot;became responsible for all the outrages which took place in the neighbourhood last Summer. Peter Dunne afterwards &quot;became Commandant of the Mid-Limerick Brigade and was recently arrested. Whether the estremists of the 2nd. Bn. are responsible for the murders or not, cannot be said, but there is documentary proof that the inactivity of the Irish Volunteers in Limerick was caus-ing much dissatisfaction and was the cause of complaint amongst the more active units in South Limerick, Tipperary and North Cork. The third man killed in Limerick had as far as is known never been identified with the Irish Volunteers, until he was buried in their uniform.Oglac 1st. 21.Tho executions which took place in Dublin on the 14th.inst: have produced a hysterical outburst on the part of the Dublin Press, These juurnals, which have never expressed one-word of sympathy or sorrow over the numerous cold-blooded murders of un-armed soldiers, police and civilians, are now eulogising the attitude of the misguided young men who have been oonvioted of murder and high treason. Such an attitude can only encourage other excitable youths to carry on the same campaign. The last thing the press of this type - and this is the press which enjojc popularity and a wide Circulation - ever attempts to do, is to influence its readers to bring pressure on the representatives they have chosen both in parliamentary and municipal elections to bring about the peace for which they are always clamouring, hy stopping their campaign of outrage and murder.Rumours of further &quot;peace negotiations&quot; are in the air, and if this is so we may expect increased activity and further out-rages on the part of the rebel forces. It is as well to recall the attitude adopted during and after the recent &quot;conversations11 by All T&apos;OGLAC, the official organ of the Irish Volunteers, some 6000 copies of which are issued secretly every fortnight to all com-panies of the I.R.A. (5 per Company). The loading articles of the issue of February 1st.headed &quot;Steadfast&quot; and February ljth. head-ed &quot;Our positions&quot;, are worthy of study and serious consideration as shoeing the attitude of mind of the leaders of the Republican forces and their efforts to encourage and inspire their followera The following extracts are typical:--&quot;In view of the lying statements so as3idiously circulated by the enemy press it is important that volunteers should understand that the situation remains entirely unchanged. There has been no change of mind, no slackening of temper on the part of those res-ponsible for the destinies of the Ifish Republic. All to a man stand unflinchingly to the Proclamation of Easter Week and the De-claration of Independence of January 21st.1919. The Minister res-ponsible for the waging of Var against the enemy is interpreting the unanimous wish of the Republican Government in using every -weapon at his command against the brutal instruments which the enemy is employing against the Irish people.&quot;It is necessary to emphasise this fact in view of the insidious propaganda carried on oy the enemf in the shape of statements about negotiations for a settlement - propaganda which has unfor-unfortunately been helped by the action of erratic individuals represen-themselves .......The&quot;To withdraw histing nobody but noursHw&apos; agr)Volunteers there^h&quot;smy&quot;&quot;ci55Ttroops fromsecure&quot; TOggr-iir the country.....is only one counsel, the old one:- Get onJOglac 15th.4.For     ^ with ffie^oFETrcIn the issue of February 15th. we read:-* It will hearten volunteers in the brave and glorious fight which they^are,waging to know^that they have the^sugport^andwith the Government of the IriBh Republic ...... Since this was written the Dail has met and ratified with its unanimous approval the attitude of the Ministry (i.e. of Defence).   &quot;The
knowledge of this will encourage the fighting menSuch are the official pronouncements of the real leaders of the rebellion in&quot; Ireland, nameiy CATHAL $RUGHA (the Minister of Defence) RICHARD MtJLCAHY (Chief of Staff) and MICHAEL CODLIHS (Minister of Finance, and Director of Information)* This triumvirate still controls the action of the rebels, supported by the bulk if not the whole (as is assertod in the official journal) of the other elected members of the Dail Elreann.&apos;Those individuals, as is shown elsewhere in their official or (ran, derive great encouragement from the speeches and questions of certain politicians, and from the tone adopted by certain sections of the English Press.    In Ireland we still await with interest some expression of disapproval of the reprisals recently conducted against unarmed British Soldiers from the lips of those glib individuals who denounced so strongly the reprisals carried out by members of the police force after months of cruel pro-vocation, patiently and silently borne.    The Manchester Guardian and Westminster Gazette which have so roundly condemned reprisals by forces of the Crown, excuse the recent murder of two unarmed soldiers of the Essex Regt. at Sandon, as na reprisal&quot; for thd killing of an armed ploquot of the flying column of the rebel army.    Similarly the murder of unarmed soldiers in Cork passes as a rePr^f^Jtj5gf the execution, after fair warning,&apos; of rebels found activeiy^nu^attempting to murder members of the Crown forces.As far as the Military situation is concerned, progress is being made, slowly but surely. .  Every conflict in which tho rebels suffer casualties brings us nearer peace.    These columns will gradually be forced to break up. and go home where they run the risk of internment, or pack into larger columns which will ^ive the troops the objectives that have been so conspiciously absent in the past.Every defeat of a small rebel column makes it harder for the leaders to keep the rank&apos; and file in the field.    Even now those leaders are encouraging their men with fabrications about the losses suffered by Government forces.    In the last number of. fen T1OGLAC referred to above there are the following examples of this method of keeping up  the spirits of the Irish Volunteers.&quot;One of the enemyTs latest propagandist devices is the concealment of his casualties ..... In Publin City a policy of system. atically denying and hushing up casualties has  been adopted.    For some time past there have been daily attacks on enemfc lorries&quot;and in a number of cases those attacked suffered heavy casualties, but the -official report daily states thet thoy suffered &quot;no casualties&quot; The purpose of this manoeuvre is obvious&quot;.    And again, In another article - &quot;Tie warn volunteers not to attach .... credence to the British official reports .... Fights in.which Volunteers have, made brilliant tactical successes are as described In terms which would lead the public to regard them as blundering failures ,..The enemy casualties whenever possible are carefully concealed or minimised&quot;.Such extracts show the way the wind is blowing, and the Offorts that are hoing made to keep the organisation together.The Military situation is slowly producing results.    Matters can be hastened.1.       First and foremost by the capture of the three men mentioned above who are the prime movers of the rebellion.
2,    By the prosocution for high treason of every member of the Datl Eireann,3.    By the control of the hostile press in Ireland.4.    If it were possible, by convincing those politicians &amp; public speakers and pressmen who are now encouraging (perhaps unwittingly) the rebels, that every work spoken or written by them only postpones the day when peace and lav; and order will be restored in Ireland,2* OPBBATIOHS &amp; OUTRAGES,OOoSHgo.  Thej^l.4,45 hrs* train from Kilfree to Rallaghadereen Was&quot;fiei3 up by/armed nen and searched thoroughly.    Nothing was removed,Macrocm.pj3o.Cork, At Toemes., near liacroom, a party of Auxiliary &quot;Police arrestqSISq armed men for Illegal assembly. One man ran away, was shot and died of wounds,Oahi r,t 0Qjftij^rmy9- An officer &apos;s patrol of the 31st,Brigade RPA appi&apos;caching a tiouse at. Hymens town., was fired on from the house, the officer being wounded^    The house was surrounded and a man firing from a window was killed.    Another man carrying a revolver then surrendered.    The man killed proved to be Patrick Hogan, Battalion CouTiandant, I.R.A. and the other Ms Signalling Officer. Important documnets were found on Hogan.    Vo Military were hit beyond the Officer,Dublin^   On this date, Sunday, the I,R.A. showed considerable arCVvrty,    At Sutton Auxiliary Police came upon a body of civilians in a fields    Some of these fled on being ordered to put up their hands and were fired on.    One was killed and 2 wounded.All wires to Amiens Street Station wore out at 12.00.At 12,00 hrs, in Dorset Street a lorry was bombed and fired on Four s61diers and 2 civilians were wounded.On the Malahide Road, Clontarf, a civilian car was ambushed, apparently being mistaken for a military car.    The driver was killed and another occupant was wounded.    The occupants were then searched J?y, I ,R ,A, one of whom admitted a mistake had been made.Tho G.S. &amp; 1J.Rly, Yforks at Inckicore were seized at 19,40 had, and the 5 watchmen held up.    The I;R,A, remained in occupation all night, departing before drawn with a 6 ton lorry containing military iron armour plates.    The   lorry was later on found In a lane near Seventh Loch and the plates were found In the Canal^ffilmerick,   During the, night the Mayor of Limerick, the ex-Mayor and a Butcher named Dono^hue were murdered by armed unknown men,Partry, 00,Hayo.    At 11,30 hrs. at a spot (1 mile N,of Partry on the Balllnrobe-tfastlebar road a Military party in a lorry were ambushed,    Fire was returned,    1 Officer and 3 0.R,were wounded. No rebels were captured though blood stains were found,    2 shot guns and 1 revolver were taken.books, Co-Kerry.   The 05.00 Goods Train from Tralee to Valentia was held up&apos;by &quot;armed and masked men,    All mails were taken except 1 bag,Virginia Road stn.,Co,Meatjh^-^The-^Good^u^tortr-was-raided-and-csrtaA-j gooos damagea by 2 men.
7/3/21. Dublin. During Curfew, a civilian resisted arrest and ? to break away, was fired on, wounded and captured.

Waterford. The Railway Bridge was raised and injured so that all trains in and out were delayed.

Cork-Rosslare. An attempt was made to derail the 19,50 train by closing the barriers at the level crossing at Carrolls Cross. The express however crashed through them successfully. Armed men had held up the Station Staff, saying they proposed removing troops from the train.

Castleblaney, Co. Monaghan. Two miles along the railway to Armagh 18 men held up a train and searched it without taking anything.



8/3/21 Cahir, Co. Tipperary. A convoy was ambushed on the Cahir-Mitchelstown road 4 miles from Cahir at 16.00 hras. Fire was returned. No known casualties were caused to either side. Local inhabitants reported about 400 men were there on 7th.

Millstreet Co. Cork. A postman was relieved of his bags by armed man.

Dublin. Three separate attacks were made on Metropolitan Police patrols at 20.30 hrs. In one case two constables were deprived of their arms, in another 3 constables were similarly treated and in the third case a pair were fired at by rebels and one was wounded. These constables returned the fire and hit one rebel who was carried off by his friends.

In Hill Street at 20.00 hrs. 2 parties of men refused to halt when seen by a patrol and dispersed down side streets. They were fired on and 4 were wounded.

Kilkee. Co. Clare. A constable was fired on in the streets and slightly wounded.

Kilgarvan. Co. Kerry. Ardtully House, the property of ?mond Orpen, was destroyed by fire, believed the act of civilians.

Queen&apos;s County. Communications were greatly interfered with. The following main roads were trenched. Mountrath -Castletown, Meryborougj - Stradbally, Abbeyleix - Ballycolls. Trees were felled and wires cut in the district.

The bridge over R. Nore at Borris-in-Ossory is reported blown up and wires were cut there.

Large trees were felled at Kilmartin Cross.

Trenches were cut in many roads leading to Rathdowney.

Tagoat. Co. Wexford. An attempt was made to kidnap and RAF.man home on leave.

Causeway. Co. Kerry. At 20.00 hrs. 2 R.I.C. were ambushed and slightly wounded.



21. Clonakilty. Co. Cork. A patrol of the 1st. Essex Regt. surprised an outpost of a rebel bridge destroying party at Lesilane at 00.15 hrs. 4 rebels were captured, one being wounded, with 1 service rifle, 1 shot gun, 1 revolver, 1 motor bicycle &amp; tools.

Bantry, Co. Cork. The RIC. Bks. were attacked at 22.45 hrs. The attack was beaten off without loss to either side.



 
Killorglin, Co. Kerry.   A Head Constable was fired ai in his lodgings by 4 men but was not hit.Abheyleix, Queers Co.   The road to Carlow was cut up by a trench 4 feet&quot; deep.Tuam, Co. Galway.   The road to Dunmore was barricaded and cut by&quot;a trench.    A road was also damaged at Turloughmore 11 m. 1ni.j3. *f Galway.Aghacley, Co. Monaghan.   Two men were found murdered in a lane. One was known to have been taken from his house at 04.00 hra. by 6 masked mon.*   Bunbeg, Co. Donegal.   An &quot;unarmed R.I.C.Sergeant returning fro$ Bunbeg was kidnapped near Gortabark by J men and taken blind-folded across mountains to near Corvea 4 miles H. of Bunbeg, He was tried in a field, sentenced to &quot;be shot for spying and questioned as to what inhabitants give information to police. He was finally released with bicycle.Kilmallock, Co. Limerick. The property of the following was destroyed as a military operation for the murder of Sergt. McGuire, R.I.C., at Kilmallock on 6/3/21:-Houlihan of Kilmallock. J, Walsh of Kilfina, 0!Brien cf Effin.Nad, Co. Cork. About 10 miles S.w\ of Mallow parties of 2nd.E. Lane.Regt. and 1st Manchester Regt. surprised an armed party of a rebel flying column.    In the fight that ensued 3 rebels were killed.   Two were wounded and escaped.    Another that attempted to escape was fired on and killed.    There were no military casualties.    5&quot; service rifles, J revolvers, 2 bayonets ammunition and documents were captured.Thuries, Co. Tipperary.   During the night 9/l0th. 2 ex-soldiers were murdered in their homes, one having the word &quot;spy&quot; pinned to him.    Aimed men also wounded a third civilian under similar circumstances.Head ford Junction, Co. lorry.   The Mallow-Tralee train was held up and the mails were removed.HewbliGB, Co. Monaghgn.    An attempt was made to kidnap the ticket collector at iHe station who escaped, wounded in 3 places.Charleville, Co. Cork.   The Goods store was raided by 3 armed men.Crossford, Co. Galway.   Rate-collector   and Auctioneer fired at and wounded at 16.00 hrs by 3 armed and masked men, while con-ducting an auction. Motive believed because ha had collected rates for the Galway Co.Council.   Ho arrests were made.Timoleague, Co. Cork. A civilian at Barryshall was murdered by armed civilians at 21.00 hre...   Mflhill, Co. Ldltrim.   A party of 2 officers and 2? O.R. lst.Bn. Beds. &amp; Herts, were ambushed at Glasdxumman, 6 m. ft. of Mohill, at 17,20 hrs.   The troops assaulted the enemy position and in a running fight 6 rebels were shot dead.   One wounded man was captured.   There were no military casualties.    A quantity of arms and ammunition ware captured.
V^-U    Clormiela Co.Ttpperar?.   The ^Station Goods ntore was raided ancFali BeiTast Stores were thrown into the river near by.Drumhowna, Qo.Cavan.    The Cavan-Hullingar train was held up Se 1 fa sT&quot;goocTs heISg&quot;Vemovod.Cratloe, CoeClare.   The Limerick - Ennis train was stopped by 2&quot;5 men-    All mails were taken.Tralee^ Co.Kerry,    The mail goods train from Mallow was held up ana relieved of its mails.3/21.    Callan, Coehilksmiyo    7;hile a mixed party of troops &amp; R.I.C. were surrounding a housej 3 men escaped, killing one policeman and taking his rifle,     5 men were captured on strong suspicion, also 2 rifles t 2 revolvers.    A District Inspector was wounded.Limerick Junction.   2 unarmed military foot police were fired at dy civIIXana at 20.12 hrs, one being wounded.    The attackers escaped,A?.?*fert. Co.Kerry.   The Limerick train was attacked at the ^taTlon oy rebels at 20*45 hrs.    An Auxiliary Cadet was killed and the driver and fireman were wounded.Castleoomer, Co.Kilkennye     On the night of ll/l2th. a party of llTFtlC&quot;. under a DTI&quot;, surprised an unknown number of rebels felling trees.    The rebels opened fire, which was returned. One rebel was believed  hit.    Hone of the RIC, were hit.Kilmallockj Co\Lfanerick0   A party of troops moving from 1Q.Tmallock to Pallas Green saw 5 men 300 yards away suddenly take to the fields and bolt.    They were pursued and fired on but escaped.    They left behind 50 rounds of ammunition h a number of I.RJW despatches.    One rebel was believed wounded.3/21.    Yougfcal,   Co.Cork.    Tho house of a range wardenTs widow was burnt &quot;down in &quot;ioughaiTaT 01.00 hrs. by unknown civilians.3. RESULTS Ply f:Qu7.T :yTIAL.    Eighty-six persons have been tried by Court Partial of wliom 66 were convicted and sentenced as follows *-(a). For murder.3 sentenced to death (two commuted to P.S. for life)(b). For attacks on Crown Forces.1 to 12 years P,S. 1 to 7 years P,S. 2 to 2 years Imp. H.L. 1 to 1 years Imp.witho.ut H.L.(c). For being; in possession of arms &amp; amminltion.8 to 15 years P.S. 4 to 10 years P.S. 5 to 5 years P.S. 5 to 2 years Imp. H.L. 3 to 18 months Imp. E.L. I 1 to 1 year without H.L.1 to 9 months H.L. 1 to 4 months H.L. 4 to fines..
w &apos; For being inr)p(^gesaion of ipototipqg Tdogaftqnt3,    -     hd2 to 18 months with ILL. 3 to 1 year with H.L. 3 to 1 year without H,L. 1 to 9 months with H.L. 1 to 3 months with H,L, 1 to 28 days without H,L. 1 to 14 days with ILL. 1 to 7 days with ILL,(e). For irisoollaneoua offences.3 to 3 years penal servitude.1 to 1 year1 a Imp, with ILL.1 to 112 davs Imp. with H.L.1 to 1 yearns Imp, without H,L.1 to 9 months Imp. without H.L. (not confirmed)1 to 9 months Imp, with ILL,1 to 3 months Imp, with ILL.1 fined  25.1 fined 10/-2 bound over.4,     IIERNIffiNT OF KEM3BRS OF THE I.R.A,The following number of members of the I.RJU have been recommended for Internment up to 1 larch 15th. 1921,Up to and including  Batch 65,Brigade Number,15th, Infantry Bde.   (Belfast). 178Londonderry Bde. 6913th, Infantry Bde.     (Athlone) 20014th, Infantry Bde,     (Curragh) 178Galway brigade, 216,Dublin District 85816th, Infantry Bde.    (Fermoy) 22417th. Infantry Bdo,     (dork) 28718th Infantry Bde.      (Limerick) 145Kerry brigade 5924141st, Division 2475th, Division 5946th, Division 715Dublin District 8582414Members of the I.R.A, recommended for Internment by Ranks.Brigade Commandants 17,Brigade Staff 351Battalion Commandants 69Battalion Staff 129Company Officers 1032Other ranks &amp; ranks unknown 1140&quot;2414,(Sgd)  c.F.Ni-;A0READY.GHQ. IRELAND. GENERAL15/3/21, Com-wling-in-chief, IRELAND.

</content>
</cab>
