<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/121/0 images: 679-680</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUK.ENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS MAJESTY&apos;S BR ITT A NICGOVERNMENT.)..................................... -Hi. .SECRET;CABINET,CP. 2784. Copy No.&quot;HOME-GROWN WHEAT,11Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.I desire to support in the strongest possible manner the proposal made by Lord Crawford, as Chairman of the Wheat Commission, in his memorandum of the 1st inst, (CP.2783)..The breakdown of the original scheme for carrying out the Prime Minister&apos;s pledge to the farmers as to the price of 1920 wheat is due to no fault of the farmers, but is solely accounted for by the refusal of the Corn Trade to work the scheme on the lines which were agreed to by the President of their Association.The result is that the farmers to whom the pledge was given are quite unable to secure its redemption unless they sold their wheat to a Government miller direct.     Such sales only represent about 40 per cent, of the total quantity sold.The breakdown of the scheme is arousing great indignation among the farmers and meetings of protest are being called In many districts.It is essential therefore that a new scheme should be devised at once, and Lord Crawford&apos;s proposal is the only possible method whereby the Prime Minister&apos;s pledge can be honoured.It is true that in certain cases where merchants bought British wheat from the farmers at (say) 85/*- a quarter and sold to the millers at 95/- the scheme involves a payment to the farmer of 10/- a quarter which would make the total cost to the Government 105/- a quarter.iiniiiiiiiiiii.....nammwmmKmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmm    ........ &apos;..       ......-&apos;  .. &apos; . &apos;
On the other hand all through the War and until quite recently the Government have been obtaining home grown wheat at prices very much below the cost of imported wheat. It is now proposed that for a short period and in order to carry out a definite pledge the cost, of British wheat may in some cases exceed the cost of imported wheat.     This does not appear to me to be too high a price to pay in order to retain the confidence of the agricultural community in the good faith of the Government.It may also be pointed out while some corn merchants made profits out of the   farmers which they decline to forego, other merchants made losses.     Under the original scheme those losses would have been recouped to the merchants by the Government, but under the new scheme no payment will be made to merchants and there will be a consequent saving to the Government which may be set off against the increased cost in other oases.     I understand that no payments have actually been made except to farmers who sold direct to the millers.I would urge therefore that the Cabinet, should -agree at once to Lord Crawford.1 s proposals.     It would be most serious if the farmers had reasonable ground for saying that they had been tricked a second time.A. G. BOSCAflEN.1st April, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
