<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/121/0 images: 710-728</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*    FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY.Vol. Ill, No. 14. 2.4.21.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]MINISTRY OF LABOUR.WEEKLY REPORT.2nd April, 1921.PART I.-THE LABOUR SITUATION.PART II. -THE WORK OF THE MINISTRY.Prepared by Intelligence Division.CONTENTS.Part I. The Labour Situation.-Week ending the 29th March, 1921.The General Situation General Survey of the &quot;Week The Unemployment PositionFeatures oir the Week-Unemployment General Topicspage308 309309 310Features op the Week continued. pageTrade Union Topics      ......... 310Industrial and other Organisations     ... 311Negotiations and Disputes Demands and Negotiations       ...... 312Strikes and Lock-Outs   ......... 311-Sefctlements and Agreements    ...... 315Part IL-The Work op the Ministry.Week ending the. 26th March, 1921Industrial Relations Department  page Engineering, Shipbuilding  and  AlliedTrades    ............... 316Woodworking and Furnishing   ...     ... 316Building and Works of Construction   ... 316Quarrying............... 316Food and Drink   ............ 317Pottery, Rubber and Glass      ...... 317Chemicals and Explosives......... 317Textiles     ............... 318Printing and Paper............ 318Public Authorities and Public UtilityServices............... 318Miscellaneous Trades      ......... 318General Department-Trade Boards Fixing and Variation of Minimum Eates of Wages...............321(b 17186T) 1050 4/21  H &amp; S Ltd.pageEmployment and Insurance Department-Employment Exchanges.........  321Local Employment Committees......  324Out-of-work Donation and Unemploy-ment Insurance Benefit        ......  324Discharged and Disabled  Sailors and Soldiers...............324Appointments and Civil Liabilities Depart-ment-Appointments      ............324Business and Professional Training     ...  324Training Department-Industrial Trainingt M M &apos;... 320
PART I.-THE LABOUR SITUATION.THE GENERAL SITUATION.General Survey of the Week.Public attention has been concentrated during the period under review on the negotiations between the coalowners and the miners, and the threatened stoppage of work at all the coal mines on the 1st April. Equally important, but less in the public eye, however, have been the meetings of various trade union organisations to consider the steps to be taken to deal with what the unions regard as &quot; an organised attack &quot; by employers on wages. The sub-committee of the Triple Alliance met on the 17th March to consider the suggestion of the National Federation of Building Trades Operatives that a conference of the principal unions whose members are threatened with reductions of wages should be called by the Alliance to formulate a common policy to meet the situation, and decided that it was not within the competence of the Alliance to call such a con-ference. The sub-committee were no doubt influenced by the announcement of the Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union Congress on the previous day that the most satisfactory way of dealing with the situation was for the unions affected to meet in their separate trade groups, and, after careful discussion, to decide upon a course of action. In consonance with this decision, the National Federation of Building Trades Operatives, at a meeting on the 29th March, decided to call at an early date a conference of repre-sentatives of the engineering and shipbuilding unions, as well as of the unions affiliated to the Federation ; and the National Transport Workers&apos; Federation have also called a similar special conference of the 34 affiliated unions for the 5th April. Moreover, the sub-committee of the Triple Alliance will meet again on the 30th, and the fill executives of the three constituent bodies of the Alliance on the 31st, to deal with the crisis in the coal mining industry. A slightly different policy appears to have been adopted by the general labour unions ; the executive committee of the National Federation of General Workers, at a meeting on the 23rd March, passed a resolution protesting emphatically &quot; against the methods being adopted by various employers and associations of employers in demand-ing and enforcing reductions in wages without consultation with the unions concerned,&quot; and &quot; regretting that the Government, which took steps to prevent workmen during the war from taking advantage of the situation created by the war, should now take no steps to prevent employers from throwing the country into a state of industrial chaos.&quot; The resolution also urged the Government to convene immediately a national joint industrial conference.The threatened reductions in wages also appear to be accelerating the tendency of the unions to amalgamate as a means of self-defence. Mention is made below of the unanimous resolution adopted by the annual conference of the National Amalgamated Union of Shop Assistants, Warehousemen and Clerks in favour of amalgamation with the National Union of Distributive and Allied Workers, and of the decision of the latter union to promote, as far as possible, amalgamations with kindred unions.With the exception of the coal m ning industry, conferences between employers and employed have been in abeyance during the holiday period, but the general labour situation appears to be very threatening. The National Maritime Board on the 17th March agreed to the postponement for a month of the proposed reductions of wages of persons employed in the seafaring industry, and the Board adjourned until the 22nd April. The Shipbuilding Employers&apos; Federation, and the Federation of Shipbuilding and Engineering Trades, will resume their negotiations at Carlisle on the 31st March, when the employers propose definitely to press for early substantial reductions in wages. In connection with the engineering industry, the statement referred to below issued by the Engineering and the National Employers&apos; Federations is of special importance in that it not only states that wages reductions are inevitable, but also indicates that the standard of living of the workpeople is threatened. The question arising out of the decision of the National Federation of Building Trades Employers to introduce additional
General Situation-continued.ex-Service men into the building industry was considered by the building operatives on the 29th March, when &quot; a course of action was decided upon,&quot; but no report kof the decisions arrived at has been issued.The annual conference of the Independent Labour Party, which was held at Southport on the 28th and 29th March, declared by 521 votes to 97 against affiliation to the Third International. This was followed by the decision of those members who were in favour of affiliation to secede from the party and to join the Communist Party.The Coal Mines (Decontrol) Bill received Royal Assent on the 24th March, and the Ministry of Transport (Transfer of Railways) Bill was introduced into the House of Commons by Mr. J. H. Thomas on the 22nd March.The Unemployment Position.Statistics.-The number of H.M. Forces and merchant seamen out-of-work donation policies lodged in the United Kingdom on the 11th March was 326,310, of which 302,964 were lodged by men and 340 by women totally unemployed, and 22,952 by men and 54 by women working short time. On the 4th March there were 337,701 policies lodged, of which 313,543 were lodged by men and 416 by women totally unemployed, and 23,681 by men and 61 by women working short time.On the 11th March in the United Kingdom 1,710,084 unemployment books remained lodged under the Unemployment Insurance Acts, of which 573,898 were lodged by males and 369,303 by females totally unemployed and 324,672 by males and 442,211 by females working short time; an increase on the previous week of 77,300 totally unemployed and 38,851 working short time.The total on the live register of all Enjoyment Exchanges in the United Kingdom on the 25th March was 1,408,800. The above are advance figures provided by the Employment Department, and are subject to revision.A full analysis of the unemployment position will be found on page 321.FEATURES OF THE WEEK.Unemployment.Building Industry.-The ballot vote of master builders on the question of the absorp-tion of ex-Service men into the building industry has resulted in a 90 per cent, majority in favour of the adoption of the scheme. The scheme was explained by the Minister of Labour in the House of Commons on the 23rd March. It is proposed that the State shall pay part of the wages of the men accepted for training. The scheme is to be worked through local committees composed of representatives of master builders and, if possible, the trade unions. For the present, it is intended to concentrate on bricklaying, plastering and slating, as these are the three building trades in which the labour shortage is most acute. A selected candidate will be required to enter into a contract which will be valid for two years. Provision will be made in the terms of the contract to allow the trainee, subject to his consent, to be passed on to another employer if continuous work with one employer for the whole two years is not possible. Ex-Service men accepted for training will be paid at the following rates:-(a) First six months, 50 per cent, of the district skilled man&apos;s rate, plus 10s. per week paid by the State; (6) second six months, 65 per cent, of the district skilled man&apos;s rate, plus 5s. per week paid by the State; (c) third six months, 80 per cent, of the district skilled man&apos;s rate; (d) fourth six months, 90 per cent, of the district skilled man&apos;s rate ; and thereafter 100 per cent.The State contribution will be paid for a full week, even though the firm by whom the man is employed may, in fact, be working short time, provided that the man attends for duty on the days on which the firm require him; but the contribution will not be paid for any week in which a man does not work at all. The National Federation of Building Trades Employers have accepted general responsibility for bringing about the absorption of the desired number of ex-Service men, and for their training. There is to be a direct appeal to the operatives themselves to assist in the supervision of the progress of the scheme, by joining with the employers on the district committees, but, in the event of their refusal to co-operate, the working of the scheme will be undertaken by the employers(b 17165T) 2 R 2
alone, and a headquarters committee is to be appointed to work in conjunction with the Ministry of Labour. The scheme was considered by the Emergency Committee of the National Federation of Building Trades Operatives on the 29th March, but no report of the decision arrived at was issued. It is not anticipated, however, that they will agree to take any part in its administration.Cotton Textile Industry. At a recent meeting of the Federation of Master Cotton Spinners&apos; Associations it was decided that the present system of short-time working in spinning mills should be continued in both the Egyptian and the American sections.A ballot vote has been taken of the members of the Kossendale Weavers&apos; Winders&apos; and Beamers&apos; Association on the question of the suspension of contributions and payments, and has resulted in a large majority in favour of their suspension.The administrative committee of the Cotton Reconstruction Board have decided that mill mechanics, engine tenters, stokers, joiners, office staffs and similar workers are not entitled to unemployment benefit under the scheme administered by them, and that un-employed cotton operatives only are eligible for assistance.General Topics.Trade Boards Acts. The controversy concerning the suspension and limitation of the powers of Trade Boards still continues. At a representative meeting of the Scottish Distributive Trades Federation, recently held in Glasgow, the question of Trade Boards as they affect the distributive trades was considered, and the following resolution was adopted: il That this meeting of the Scottish Distributive Trades Federation, having regard to the con-dition and outlook of trade at present, and with the view of preventing the further increase of un-employment, urge the Minister of Labour to delay for a period of twelve months the extension of the application of Trade Boards to other trades, pending the reconstruction of the whole subject, and that meantime no further application of pending proposals or of regulations be made to new trades.&quot;The probable effect of the suspension of the Trade Board Acts on women employed in industry has been considered by the Standing Joint Committee of Women&apos;s Organisa-tions. In a letter published on the 24th March, the committee contend that the Trade Boards are the only protection from &quot; sweating &quot; afforded to women workers, and that promises have been made that a large number of Boards would be set up with the greatest possible speed.It is reported that a campaign is to be organised to combat the efforts of the employers&apos; organisations to secure the abolition of the Trade Boards. This campaign is to be co-ordinated and centralised by the Advisory Council set up recently under the auspices of the Trades Union Congress. Further information concerning the attitude of the unions toward Trade Boards is given below under Industrial and other Organisations.Trade Union Topics.National Union of Railwaymen. A &quot; National Conference of Grade Movements &quot; was held at Birmingham on the 20th March, at which guards, signalmen, ticket collectors, shunters, permanent way men, telegraph, engineers, shop supervisors, shop workers, supervisors and other grades were represented. Dissatisfaction was expressed with the present constitution of the union, the attitude of the meeting being, not one of opposition to the union, but that the union had outgrown the constitution, which, therefore, required amendment.       tOne of the most important of the resolutions adopted urged upon the executive committee the necessity of making a supreme effort to have the National Wages Board Award of June, 1920, added to the basic rate. A second resolution expressed dissatis-faction with the Head Office scheme for dealing with grade movements, and advocated a scheme &quot; whereby all grades will have opportunities for dealing with grade conditions and troubles, through union machinery, from localities, through districts, to six national departmental conferences, six delegates from any such departmental conference to assist any negotiating committee when dealing with matters affecting the workers embraced within such conference.&quot;Other resolutions referred to the &quot; present orthodox unsatisfactory machinery&quot; of the union, and &quot; recommended the complete scheme of the West Midlands District Council to the serious consideration of members of all grade movements for the purpose
* See this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 9, 26th February, p. 200.of using the union to serve the interest of every grade.&quot; Every grade is also urged, without waiting for alteration of rules, &quot; to organise effectively, and with grade stewards, to consolidate all grades into six departments,&quot; corresponding to the six national Depart-mental Conferences referred to above.These resolutions are indicative of the dissatisfaction existing among the rank and file at the delay in dealing with the claims of such grades as signalmen and shopmen. The Conference further registered a protest &quot; against the delay in settling the con-ditions of service of signalmen, shop supervisors, office staffs, and the allocation of men on the border line.&quot;Union of Post Office Workers. Attention has already been drawn in this Report to the possibility of conflict between this union and the Irish Postal Workers&apos; Union.* The issue was brought to a head by a conference of delegates from the Irish branches of the Union of Post Office Workers, held at Dublin on the 11th March, to discuss their position in this union. The general opinion of the meeting was that it would be a mistake to withdraw from the union and set up a separate association for Ireland until such time as the country has been given a full measure of self-government. The following resolutions were passed: &quot; That this conference decides to continue to support the Union of Post Office Workers, as it is the only organisation which can improve our conditions of employment either in obtaining higher wages or redressing the many grievances peculiar to the Irish postal workers.&quot;&quot;That when self-government is established, and the Post Office administration controlled from Dublin, this conference recommends the formation of an Irish Postal Workers&apos; Union.&quot;It was also decided to recommend that an Irish Council should be formed within the Union of Post Office Workers, which should be subordinate to the executive council, and should deal with problems arising from the special conditions prevailing in Ireland.Trade Union Amalgamations. It is reported that the amalgamation of the National Federation of Women Workers, the Amalgamated Society of Gas, Municipal and General Workers, and the Northern United Enginemen&apos;s Association, with the National Union of General Workers has now been completed, and that the Amalgamated Society of Mechanics&apos; Assistants and Dry Dock Workers have amalgamated with the National Amalgamated Union of Labour.Amalgamated Engineering Union. The final ballot for a new general secretary for the union in the place of Mr. Tom Mann, who is to retire next month, has resulted in the election of Mr. A. H. Smethurst, the present assistant secretary of the union. Mr. Smethurst obtained 56,761 votes and his rival, Mr. J. Taylor, 40,364 votes.Industrial and Other Organisations.National Amalgamated Union of Shop Assistants, Warehousemen and Clerh. The annual conference of this union was held at Manchester on the 27th and 28th March, under the presidency of Mr. Neil Beaton, of Edinburgh. The morning of the first day was devoted to the presidents address, and, in the afternoon, the report of the National Minimum Wage Committee was considered and agreed to. This report submitted for adoption a new national minimum wage scale, varying in the case of men from 24s. at 16 years of age, to 80s. at 24 years of age ; and in the case of women from 20s. at the age of 16, to 64s. at 24 years of age. It was also agreed that, for London, there should be an additional 10s. for adults, and 5s. for juniors under 21 years of age. A resolution was also passed expressing the meeting&apos;s &quot; horror at the reign of terror existing in Ireland,&quot; detestation of official reprisals and military, executions, and urging upon the Government the &quot; desirability of at once opening up negotiations with the representatives of the majority of the Irish people elected at the last general election.&quot;On the second day, the conference unanimously adopted a resolution in favour of amal-gamation with the National Union of Distributive and Allied Workers, and the executive committee were instructed to approach the Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union Congress with a view to calling together all the unions who will form the distributive section of the Congress and securing their amalgamation into one union. A resolution was also carried urging that in any amendment to the Shops Acts, the Labour Party on behalf of the union should press for, inter alia, a 48-hour week, and that local authorities should be empowered to make a closing order for earlier than seven o&apos;clock in the evening when such action was considered &quot; advantageous to the shopkeepers, assistants and the general
NEGOTIATIONS AND DISPUTES.Demands and Negotiations.Builders (National).-In Glasgow, on the 23rd March, the Scottish National Bui1 ding Trades Federation (Employers) and the Scottish Building Contractors&apos; Association met the Operatives&apos; Wages and Conditions of Service Board for the Building Trades in Scot-land, and the Scottish Provisional Committee of the National Federation of Building Trades Operatives. The meeting discussed proposals by both sides for variations in wages. It was agreed to suspend consideration of the claims lodged until the 30th April, pending the setting up of the National Wages and Conditions Council. Should this Council be brought into operation, it will take over the whole regulation of building trades rates of wages, and will determine variations in accordance with the cost of living. The decision of the operatives, however, with regard to the setting up of this Council, and the cost-of-living sliding scale proposal, will not be known before the 4th April; and the Scottish conference, therefore, agreed that in the event of the Council not becoming operative before the 1st May, the parties would meet again and deal with the claims as lodged.Coal Miners (National). The executive of the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain met in London on the 16th March, and on the following day a conference took place between their negotiating committee and representatives of the Mining Association of Great Britain. The official statement announced that the negotiations had reached a point at which both sides considered it desirable to refer the issues back to their respective main bodies.On the 18th March the national delegate conference of the Miners&apos; Federation, which had been adjourned from the 10th March, met to receive the report of the executive on the position of the negotiations.  The conference determined : &quot; That the opinion be taken of the respective districts by conference, to decide as to whether or not they are prepared temporarily to abandon the policy of a national wages hoard and a national pool, and to empower the national executive to proceed with negotiations with a view to establishing a temporary agreement on a district basis during the present period of abnormal trade and prices.&quot;public in the district.&quot; The conference also unanimously adopted a resolution welcoming the setting up of Trade Boards for the distributive trades, but expressing the opinion that the wages rates so far adopted were too low to secure a decent standard of living. &quot; The organised opposition of employers to Trade Boards and the ineptitude of the Government in the matter &quot; were condemned ; and the conference &quot; urged the immediate setting up of such Boards in all trades not yet dealt with,&quot; and instructed the executive committee to deal with the matter by a campaign both in Parliament and in the constituencies.National Union of Distributive and Allied Workers. The first national delegate meeting of this union was held at Liverpool on the. 27th and 28th March under the presidency of Mr. J. Jagger. A resolution authorising the executive council to continue negotiations with the National Drug and Chemical Union with a view to amalgamation was passed unanimously, and the executive were further authorised to promote amalgamation with kindred unions. A resolution protesting against the action of the Government in Ireland, and declaring in favour of self-determination for the Irish people, was also passed unanimously.A resolution advocating withdrawal from the Amsterdam International, and affiliation to the &quot; Ked &quot; International was proposed, but it was decided that the resolution should be submitted to the branches and brought forward at the next conference.National Union of Journalists.--The annual delegate meeting of this union was held at Newcastle-on-Tyne on the 24th March. A resolution that the union should cease to be affiliated to the Trades Union Congress was lost by 3,241 votes to 96, and affiliation with local Trades Councils, as well as with the Congress, was strongly urged by several delegates, who contended that closer contact with trade unionists had been of great benefit to working journalists. A resolution that the union should have their own Parliamentary candidate was proposed, but was not seconded.A long resolution protesting against journalistic work being done by non-journalists was carried, and the meeting also decided to take action to secure a national standard payment for shorthand notes.Mr. Thomas Jay was elected president, and Mr. T. A. Davis, vice-president, for the ensuing year.
On the 19th March, an account of the proposals which the owners had made on the 17th was published. These proposals followed the lines of Mr. Evan Williams&apos; statement to the Mining Association on the 2nd March. * The owners proposed that their aggregate standard profits in a district should be equivalent to 17 per cent, of the aggregate amount of the standard wages payab&apos;e in that district, and that any surplus remaining, after meeting standard wages, standard profits and other costs, should be divided between workmen and owners in the districts in the proportion of three-fourths to the former and one-fourth to the latter. Should the earnings of a district during any period of ascertain-ment not be sufficient to meet the owners&apos; standard profit, the deficit should be carried forward as a prior charge against any future surplus. It was also made clear that all additions which had been made to the basic rates prevailing in July, 1914, should be maintained in the new standard, and, in particular, the percentages which were added to piece-workers&apos; rates in consequence of the introduction of the 7-hour day. The owners expressed their willingness to accept a temporary departure from the strict application of their scheme in view of the present abnormal situation, and indicated that this departure might take the form of waiving their share of the surplus in favour of the workmen, on condition that during the abnormal period ascertainments should be made at monthly intervals. The owners later expressed their willingness to amend their proposals with respect to the distribution of surplus profits, and to allow four-fifths of these to go towards increased rates of wages, and one-fifth to profits.In accordance with the resolution of the delegate conference of the Miners&apos; Federation of the 18th March, meetings were held during the following days of the delegate con-ferences of the various district associations, and the national delegate conference met again on the 24th to make the national decision. The official statement announces that the replies received from the districts showed a very large majority against entering into a temporary agreement on a district basis. The Daily Herald reported that the national decision was recorded by means of a card vote, which showed 723,000 votes against the proposal and 231,000 votes in its favour, and also that a resolution that the national delegate conference should stand adjourned from day to day pending developments was defeated by the narrow majority of 9 votes. In a further statement, Mr. Hodges has explained that the negotiating committee of the executive, at their meeting with the representatives of the Mining Association in the evening of the 24th to convey the decision of the delegate conference, proposed that a joint application by owners and miners should be made to the Government for financial assistance to help the industry through the present abnormal period. The owners did not accept this suggestion, and miners and owners accordingly presented separate reports on the situation to the Government on the 24th and 25th respectively.The situation on the 29th March was that, in all districts, contracts of employment under the old conditions were to terminate on the 31st March, and that after that date the owners were willing to continue the employment of miners in the various districts only upon their own terms. In the majority of districts, meetings had been held, or were to be held, between representatives of the local associations of miners and owners ; but at these conferences the uniform attitude of the men has been that, in view of the decision of the national delegate conference on the 24th, they cannot enter upon any local negotiations or discussions. On the other hand, the executive of the Miners&apos; Federation were to meet on the 30th, and a conference between them and the President of the Board of Trade on the same day was antcipated.Engineers (National). The Engineering and the National Employers&apos; Federations have now issued their &quot; statement&quot; with regard to the position of the industry with special reference to production, the state of trade and the cost of living.f The &quot; state-ment &quot; takes the form of a volume of 40 pages ; an advertisement of its contents appeared in the Daily Herald of the 26th March at the expense of the Federations. The key sentence in the advertisement is the following : &apos;-&apos; &quot;It is the considered opinion of the employers that a definite reduction in hourly rates and an increase in individual output are both necessary. The effect of the reduction on the standard of life will depend on the fall in the cost of living, and the extent to which the workpeople maintain and increase their actual earnings by the greater intensity of output.&quot;This statement will be considered by the trade unions concerned, and the employers apparently wish it to be the basis of further discussions with regard to the future regulation of wages in the industry after the present period of stabilisation expires in June.* See this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 12,19th March, p..275, and also the Labour Gazette, March, 1921, p, 122. f See this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 12,19th March, pp. 273 and 274.
Commercial Road Transport Workers (National).-On the 18th March, a national conference was held in London of representatives of trade unions organising commercial road transport workers, carters and motormen, affiliated to the National Transport Workers&apos; Federation. It was resolved that no union should accept any separate reduction in wages, and local officials are to be instructed not to enter into local negotiations for reductions or to take part in local conferences which may modify, or in any way amend, the various agreements arising out of national applications put forward by the Federation.Commercial Road Transport Workers (London). The conference referred to above is the only further event reported with regard to the demand of the employers&apos; associations in the London area for a reduction in the wages of commercial road transport workers. It will be remembered that the employers&apos; proposal was to introduce a 2s. reduction as from the 12th March and a further 2s. reduction as from the 1st April.* The unions concerned, however, the National Union of Vehicle Workers and the United Vehicle Workers, have continued their endeavours to secure the adoption by various outlying employers&apos; organisations of the is. per week advance conceded last December to the main body of London road transport workers. It was reported on the 16th March that an agreement had been made between the two unions and the London District Association of Engineering Employers, covering transport workers and semi-skilled workers attached to the garages of firms affiliated to the Engineering Association, and embodying the December advance. The agreement also provides for a 47-hour week. On the other hand, the Incorporated Society of Retail Distributors (London) have refused to concede this advance. In their negotiations with this latter body the unions are acting in con-junction with the National Amalgamated Union of Shop Assistants, Warehousemen and Clerks, and the progress of negotiations will be reported to a mass meeting of workers con-cerned, to be held on the 2nd April.Seamen (National).-The National Maritime Board met at the Hotel Cecil on the 17th March, under the chairmanship of Mr. F. C. Allen, to consider the proposals of the shipowners for a reduction in the wages of all grades of employees at sea.f Mr. Havelock Wilson proposed that consideration of the whole question should be adjourned for a month, and the suggested adjournment was agreed to after the employers&apos; and men&apos;s repressntatives had considered the position separately. The Board wilt therefore meet again to consider the matter on the 22nd April.Strikes and Lock-Outs.Vehicle Builders (National).-Ike meeting between the trade unions concerned and the National Employers&apos; Association of Vehicle Builders, which was held at Leeds on the loth March, was dealt with in this Report last week.JA joint meeting of the executive committees of the trade unions was held at Leicester on the 19th to consider the proposal which the employers had put forward at Leeds. It was decided to inform the employers that the union executives were prepared to recom-mend an immediate reduction of 2d. per hour, provided that this reduction were taken as part of the proposed cost-of-living sliding scale variations.A further meeting between employers and workers was held at Leeds on the 23rd, and definite proposals for a settlement were drawn up. The terms provided for immediate reductions in England of 2d. per hour, and in Scotland of 2\d. and Z\d. respectively, on commercial and private work. The reductions, if any, under the sliding scale were to take effect on the 1st June and the 1st August, in accordance with the Labour Gazette cost-of-living index numbers for the 1st April and the 1st June.A joint meeting of the executive committees of the three trade unions was accordingly held in Liverpool on the 26th March to consider the recommendation of their negotiating committee that this proposed agreement should be accepted. A message, however, was received that the Scottish Vehicle Builders&apos; Association, who had been represented at the Leeds conference on the 15th and the 23rd, refused to accept the proposed agreement, and insisted upon an immediate reduction of 3d. In view of this message, it is reported, the joint executives decided to break off negotiations on a national basis, and to empower local branches to arrive at local settlements, provided that they accept no reductions greater than \\d. per hour.* See this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 11, 12th March, p. 248.-j- For the shipowners&apos; proposals see this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 11,12th March, p.*248. % See this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 13, 26th March, p. 292.  The names of the various trade unions and employers&apos; associations concerned were given in this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 12,19th March, p. 275.
* See this Keport, Vol. Ill, No. 12,19th March, p. 274.f For the constitution of the Central Wages Board, and its functions with regard to the railwaymen&apos;s cost of-living sliding scale, see. the Labour Gazette, December, 1919, p. 516, and February, 1920, p. 59. x See this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 9, 26th February, p. 202. i See p. 320 below.(b 17165T) 2 SThe National Federation of Vehicle Trades, who cover London and the South of England and the Edinburgh district of Scotland, at a meeting with the unions in London on the 16th March, eventually agreed to make the same offer as had been made on the previous day at Leeds by the other two employers&apos; associations. The agreement with this employers&apos; association was to have expired on the 22nd March, but the employers agreed to a fortnights extension to allow of further discussion. It is not clear how far the decision of the unions at their Liverpool meeting on the 26th affects their negotiations with this body of employers.With regard to the extent of the lock-out in the districts covered by the National Employers&apos; Association of Vehicle Builders and the Scottish Vehicle Builders&apos; Association, it is reported that resumptions of work have taken place in Wolverhampton, on the 18th March, at 2s. 3d. per hour, and at Carlisle at the old rates of pay, but on the understanding that these will be revised in accordance with any national settlement which may be arrived at.  In Darlington one prominent firm have not put the lock-out into operation.Settlemeitts and Agreements.Nut and Bolt Operatives (Midlands). The ballot of the employees involved in the strike in the Midlands nut and bolt trade was taken on the 15th March. It was conducted under the auspices of the Workers&apos; Union and the National Union of General Workers, and was on the question of a resumption of work upon the employers&apos; terms.* The ballot resulted in a general majority of 300 in favour of resumption. In the Darlaston district, however, there was a majority against resumption, but a mass meeting of the Darlaston workers concerned decided to adopt the general decision. Work accordingly was resumed in the case of two or three firms on the 17th ; and the resumption was fairly general on the 21st.A joint conference of employers and operatives was held on the 16th March to resume discussion of the wages position. The employers made no modification of their proposals relating to women workers, who are now working on a substantial reduction, but put forward a suggestion that the proposed reduction of 10s. a week in the wages of adult male workers might take place in two instalments. The conference adjourned until the 4th April in order that the unions might consider the position further.Railwaymen (National). The Central Wages Board,f the body who now deal in the first instance with the interpretation and variation of agreements affecting railwaymen&apos;s wages, met in London on the 22nd March to determine what adjustment should be made in the railwaymen&apos;s cost-of-living bonus for the three months commencing the 1st April. The Board agreed to recommend a reduction of the cost-of-living bonus by 4s. per week. This decision is of interest as being the first occasion upon which railwaymen&apos;s wages have been reduced since the establishment of the Central Wages Board, and also because of certain difficulties which had arisen in the interpretation of the agreement. The recommendation of the Board has been approved by the Minister of Transport.Co-operative Employees (Scotland). Sheriff Fyfe&apos;s award J fixing rates of wages and conditions of work for co-operative employees in Scotland is being objected to by several co-operative societies in the East Fife area. A conference representative of the co-opera -tive societies of Leven, Methil, Buckhaven, East Wemyss, Markinch and Leslie was held recently, and it was resolved to pay wages in accordance with the award only until the end of the present month, when the societies represented would resign from the Scottish Co-operative Wages Board. It was also decided to notify the employees that from the beginning of April they would be paid the rates of wages ruling at the 20th December last year. A wages difference also exists between the Northern Co-operative Society, Ltd., Aberdeen, and their employees. $[Other disputes, negotiations and settlements are referred to in the Industrial Relations Departments Section of the Report, pages 31.6 to 320.]
PART II-THE WORK OF THE MINISTRY.INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS DEPARTMENT.ENGINEERING, SHIPBUILDING AND ALLIED TRADES.Optical Instruments. A meeting of the Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committee was held in London on the 23rd March. A proposal was considered, put forward by the Amalgamated Engineering Union, that the constitution be so amended as to provide that the British Optical Instrument Manufacturers&apos; Association be the body to be approached on Wages and working conditions, thereby making decisions binding on all members of the Association. It was announced that 14 members of the Association were prepared to form a Society of Optical Instrument Manufacturers, to meet the trade unions on the Committee for the purpose of arranging all matters affecting wages and working conditions. The members of this society bind themselves to obey any rules or regulations which their duly elected representatives on the Committee may make. This suggestion was adopted, and will be submitted to the union executives for confirmation.The employers put forward a proposal for a general reduction in wages to all skilled men of 17^ per cent., with a proportionate reduction on piece-work ; the reduction for women, unskilled and unindentured persons also to be 1.7J per cent., pending a new agree-ment. Notice was tendered by the Society of Optical Instrument Manufacturers to terminate the working conditions agreement of the 10th December, 1919. The meeting adjourned until the 27th April, in order that the unions may place the proposal before their executives.WOODWORKING AND FURNISHING.Upholsterers (London). In connection with the dispute at the works of Messrs. Hart &amp; Sons,* the adjourned conference was held on the 17th March. It was eventually sug-gested that the wages should be fixed on a basis of the pre-war rate, plus 10 per cent., plus 123 per cent., and that any alleged low-paid jobs should receive sympathetic con-sideration by the employers&apos; federation, who would admit the principle that piece-workers should be able to earn more than day rates. The trade union representatives agreed to submit this suggestion to their members. The employers impressed upon the workers the necessity for a speedy decision, particularly in view of the fact that the firm had continued to keep the men at work. They stated that a crisis had now been reached owing to the impossibility of obtaining orders at present prices.BUILDING AND WORKS OF CONSTRUCTION.Building. The Safety and Welfare Committee of the Industrial Council, at their meeting at the Home Office on the 17th March, decided to recommend to the Council that safety committees in works, or for districts, should be set up as a means of enforcing any regulations which may be drafted by the Secretary for State for the prevention of accidents on building operations.Asphalte Workers (Scotland). The secretary of the Scottish Asphalte Association agreed to a conference with the local representatives of the Workers&apos; Union on the subject of a proposed reduction in rates of wages. The conference, arranged by the department, resulted in an agreement by which no alteration in wages shall take place until after the 1st April.QUARRYING.Quarrying. The Council, at their quarterly meeting at Gbavesend on the 15th March, decided that the Executive Committee should confer with the Safety and Welfare Com-mittee on the question of silicosis among stonemasons.The following resolution was agreed : &quot; That in view of the present very general slump in trade this Council is unanimously of tho opinion that hasty action in the nature of a panic should be avoided. Districts of any Section which may contemplate action are directed to bear in mind that no agreement that may be contemplated can become operative until it has been approved by the National Sectional Council connected with this National Joint Industrial Council.&quot;* See this Report, Vol. Ill, No. 9, 26th February, p. 202.
The constitution for a National Sectional Council for the chalk branch of the industry has now been circulated.FOOD AND DRINK.Scottish Bakers. The executive of the employers&apos; association are now in favour of the continuance of the Joint Industrial Council, the Glasgow employers, however, re-affirming their decision to secede therefrom. A letter from the union has been received by the association requesting an immediate meeting of the Council.Bakers (Hull). The operatives have with difficulty been persuaded to accept the re-introduction of night work. The employers have agreed to pay double time from 10 p.m. to midnight on Sunday.POTTERY, RUBBER AND GLASS.Pottery. A meeting of the Research, Inventions and Designs Committee was held on the 17th March. A report on the extent to which welfare recommendations had been carried into effect was considered satisfactory. A report on the numbers attending the first aid and nursing classes was also considered very satisfactory, especially in view of the fact that the classes were held only at Hanley. It was hoped to establish such classes in all parts of the district in due course.Replies from members of Parliament on taxation on welfare work were considered. The meeting emphatically expressed the view that the Government were unfair in pressing for &quot; Whitleyism,&quot; and, at the same time, taxing efforts made for the betterment of condi-tions. It was decided to urge the local members of Parliament to use their influence with a view to a deputation being received by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.Glass Bottle Manufacturers [Charlton). A settlement of this dispute has been effected, and work was resumed on the 22nd March. The rate for ordinary fitters has been reduced to 2s. id. per hour, that for moulders&apos; fitters to remain at 2s. l\d. per hour. These rates are to operate for one month, and are then to be reconsidered by the firm and the union.Pottery Workers (Longton). A strike of 70 operatives resulted from the refusal of a demand for the payment of a further 4s. 2d. per day to placers, to bring their wages up to the agreed rate of 14s. 2d. per day. The employers, Messrs. Beswick, have separate factories for the manufacture of china and earthenware. The dispute is confined to the earthenware factory, but the union threaten to bring out the labour from the china factory also, in the event of a repetition of an attempt that was made to transfer the work con-cerned to the china factory. The Wages and Conditions Committee of the Industrial Council are endeavouring to arrange a conference.Asbestos (Southern Section). An emergency meeting of the Southern Section of the Industrial Council was held on the 21st March. A letter was received from the Cape Asbestos Co., Ltd., in reply to a complaint by the Council that the firm, who hold important Admiralty contracts, were not observing the Fair Wages Clause. The firm denied this, and stated that they were paying more than the district rate. Figures were given by the trade union representatives which showed that the wages paid by the firm were well below the Council rate. It was decided to write to the firm maintaining that the Council rate should be regarded as the rate to be paid under the Fair Wages Clause, and, on the receipt of the reply, to forward the correspondence to the Admiralty and the Ministry of Labour.Glass. The annual general meeting of the Industrial Council was held on the 23rd March. Mr. J. Thompson, of the National Federation of Glass Bottle Workers, was elected chairman, and Mr. Redfern, of the English and Scottish Glass Bottle Manufacturers&apos; Association, vice-chairman, for the ensuing year. The Council also decided to appoint a paid secretary of their own, such appointment to be made by the 30th April. The Council decided by a unanimous vote against joining the recently formed Association of Joint Industrial Councils and Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committees.CHEMICALS AND EXPLOSIVES.Soap and Candle Industry. A meeting of the Industrial Council was held on the 23rd March to consider notices of reductions in wages given by the employers at the last meeting. These reductions were opposed by the workers&apos; side, who asked for either postponement or reference to the Industrial Court. The employers decided to postpone the demand for about four weeks, and invited the workers to submit alternative proposals at a meeting to be called at a later date.(b 17165T) 2 S 2
Chemical Tmde-k meeting of the Industrial Council, under the chairmanship of Mr. H. J. Wilson, was held on the 22nd March to consider the sliding scale proposed by the employers at the previous meeting. After long discussions jointly, and by the two sides separately, an arrangement was arrived at for consideration by the Council at a meeting on the 30th March, after reference to the constituents of the workers&apos; side.Chemical Trade (London). Application was made for the terms of Industrial Court Award No. 589 (Chemical Trade) to be applied to members of the National Union of General Workers employed by firms in the London Chemical Manufacturers&apos; Convention. The employers concerned had voluntarily followed the various awards and decisions affecting the general chemical trade since shortly after the outbreak of the war. They declined, however, to adopt the terms of this Award, on the ground that their trade was passing through a period of acute depression. The Court decided that no alteration should be made in the existing rates, and that the claim was not established.   (Award No. 636.)TEXTILES.Wool (and Allied) Textiles-Bj resolution of the Emergency Committee of the Joint Industrial Council, in consequence of the fall of the cost-of-living index number from 151 per cent, to 141 per cent., cost-of-living wages are to he reduced as from the first pay-day in April in the proportion of 155 to 145. The amount of the reduction is about 2s. to 2s. Gd. a week for women, and varies from 2s. tid. to 4s. Gd. for men, the average in the case of men being about 3s. Id. a week.PRINTING AND PAPER.Tinplate Decorating (Neath).-The dispute in progress respecting the wages of tin printers employed by the Tinplate Decorating Co., Neath,* has been referred for settlement to the Conciliation Committee of the Printing Joint Industrial Council.PUBLIC AUTHORITIES AND PUBLIC UTILITY SERVICES.Electricity Supply. Following the recent difference between the Electrical Power Engineers&apos; Association and certain electricity supply undertakings, steps are being taken toward the reconstitution of the National Joint Board of Employers and Staff Members (Electricity Supply Industry). Proposals are under consideration that, in future, the employers&apos; side of the Board should be appointed by a standing committee representa-tive of the employers&apos; sides of the thirteen District Councils. Meanwhile the employers have notified their determination that the Board should not continue to deal with matters relating to the commercial and clerical staffs, and this matter is at present the subject of joint discussion.Local Authorities&apos; Non-Trading Services, Manual Workers (England and Wales).  The West Midlands Provincial Council met on the 18th March. Information is being obtained as to the authorities in the area who have adopted the recommendations of the Provincial Council, and the National Council are to be asked to take steps to secure the adoption of these recommendations by the local authorities in the area who have failed to do so.Waterworks Undertakings. The National Council met on the 21st March. A proposal to hold a conference of representatives of District Councils to consider, the question of seceding undertakings was discussed, but not adopted. It was decided that the Isle of Wight should he included in the area of the District Council for the South Midlands.Poor Law Workers (Cheltenham).-As a result of the intervention of the Chief Con-ciliation Officer in the dispute between the Poor Law Workers&apos; Trade Union and the Cheltenham Board of Guardians, arrangements were made for arbitration proceedings to take place on the question of the payment of the Civil Service scale of war bonus. The guardians objected to arbitration under the auspices of the department, and, by agreement with the union, a Court of Arbitration was appointed consisting of one member nominated by the guardians, one by the union and a third party selected by these two nominees. The arbitrators decided that the Civil Service war bonus scale should be applied to the employees of the guardians, under certain conditions and with certain exceptions.MISCELLANEOUS TRADES.Glove Making. The inaugural meeting of the Joint Industrial Council for the Glove Making Industry was held at Montagu House on the 21st March. The Minister, addressing the Council, referred to the good work already achieved by the Interim Industrial Recon-* See this Report, Vol. III., No. 12, 19th March, p. 279.
struction Committee, and expressed the hope that the Council would continue to carry-out the spirit of Whitleyism, which would be the only sane line to adopt in the difficult times ahead. The draft constitution was adopted with a minor amendment, and officers were elected.The Council approved of the report of the Unemployment Insurance Committee in which it was decided to defer consideration of a special scheme for the trade. The com-mittee were instructed to draw up a scheme whereby the benefits of the Unemployment Insurance Act could be extended to out-workers. The Council agreed that an invitation to make an inquiry into the trade should be addressed to the Industrial Fatigue Research Board.The employers&apos; side raised the question of the expiration of the existing wages agree-ment on the 31st March. The trade union side stated that they had not received notice of intention that a change should be made, and had not consulted their members. The employers, however, put forward an offer that in the leather section of the trade the present bonus of 221 per cent, be reduced to 121 Per cent., and that 17f per cent, be deducted in the fabric section. A special meeting is to be held on the 2nd April, when the question of a new agreement will be fully discussed.Match Manufacturing. At a meeting of the London District Council of the Joint Industrial Council, on the 3rd March, a resolution was carried unanimously, that, if a man&apos;s job is not open for a boy on reaching 18 years of age, the employer may continue to employ him on the same job for not more than six months, at the same wages, on the understanding that, if he is shifted from that job, he automatically receives a man&apos;s wages. The matter was discussed at a meeting of the National Council on the 11th March. It was decided that the resolution should be deferred in order to give District Councils an opportunity of discussion.The Unemployment Insurance Sub-Committee of the National Council have recom-mended a supplementary voluntary scheme, to come into operation as from the 15th April. It is proposed that the industry set aside, each year from 1922 onwards, sums equal to 1 per cent, of its wages bill, until the fund reaches a specific figure, or 5 per cent, of the wages bill for the time being, whichever is the greater. The liability is to be strictly limited, and the industry may reduce or discontinue its contributions or terminate the fund. Subject to certain conditions, full benefit will be at the rate of 50 per cent, of average earnings, with 10 per cent, additional for a dependent wife, and 5 per cent, additional for each dependent child under 16 years of age or receiving full-time education, with a maximum of 75 per cent, of average earnings, or  5 a week, whichever is the smaller, and a minimum of 25s. a week. Widows are to receive additional allowance for each dependent child, on the same basis as a man.The full benefit payable under this scheme will be reduced by the amounts provided by the State, and by a further sum of 6s. a week, representing the benefit which, it is considered, could be obtained for a contribution of 2d. a week to a trade union. Payments are to be made from the first day of unemployment, and the period of benefit is to vary according to the aggregate term of employment. The benefits are to be administered by an Unemployment Committee appointed by the Council.Lock, Latch and Key Trade. The Midland Joint Industrial Council on the 1st March agreed upon a reduction of 10 per cent, in the wages of male and female workers, 5 per cent, in March, and 5 per cent, in April. Under an agreement drawn up by the Midland Lock and Latch Trade Wages Board, dated the 9th July, 1920, a bonus of 10 per cent, on earnings was payable to workers of 18 years and over. As a result of the reduction now agreed upon, this bonus will cease to be operative after the 8th April. In addition the basic rates of women on power presses have been reduced by 3s. per week.The Council decided that the rates paid to women engaged on work which is essentially men&apos;s work should be agreed upon between the firm.concerned and the secretary of the employees&apos; society. Failing agreement, the matter should be brought before the Council for determination. Where women are on piece-work they should be paid 25 per cent, above the day-work rates.Basket Making.-The establishment of a Trade Board for the cane and willow basket, skip and hamper making industry was urged by a deputation from the Basket, Skip and Hamper Makers&apos; Federation, who were interviewed at headquarters on the 17th March. The deputation claimed to represent about 2,000 workers, and estimated that there are 1,000 unorganised workers in the industry. It was stated that the payment of low wages to these unorganised workers led to unfair competition, and, although the present list prices represented an advance of only 105 per cent, over pre-war rates, employers were
agitating for a further 15 per cent, to be taken off. It was alleged that employers were not honouring the Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committee&apos;s agreements, except one in respect of hours. It was feared that the conditions would soon be worse than they were before the war, and the Federation felt that the Committee had been a failure and that the only alternative was a Trade Board.Basket Making Industry (Basford). The employers gave the agreed three months&apos; notice of a proposed reduction of wages of 15 per cent, to become operative on the 8th April. The matter was discussed by representative employers and operatives on the 18th February, but the conference proved abortive, the employers making no further statement than that the reduction will be made operative. The matter was subsequently discussed at the quarterly meeting of the Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committee, held at Southport on the 1st March, and a sub-committee was appointed to meet representatives of both sides in order to effect a settlement. The meeting was held at Basford on the 22nd March, and, as a result, the 15 per cent, reduction was agreed to, the new rates to operate until the 30th July next.Gas Mantles. The Industrial Council met on the 14th March. A motion was sub-mitted by the employers that the wages agreement, dated the 4th March and revised on the 23rd September, 1920, should continue in operation for another year. This was agreed to, the representative of the National Union of General Workers dissenting. The agreement provides for an hourly minimum rate of $d. for women of 18, and Is. 2d. for men over 21 years of age.Co-operative Employees (North-East Coast). A meeting took place on the 21st March, with reference to the threatened strike of the employees of the Walker Society owing to the refusal of the employers to comply with the co-operative agreement for the Northern District. After considerable discussion, it was agreed that the society should pay in accordance with the terms of the agreement, with retrospective pay as from the beginning of the year instead of from the 16th July, 1920. The case of the St. Anthony&apos;s Society is still outstanding.Co-operative Employees (Aberdeen). A difference has arisen between the Aberdeen Northern Co-operative Society and the National Amalgamated Union of Shop Assistants, Warehousemen and Clerks, on the question of a claim for an advance in wages put forward last autumn. The union expected that the society would have been party to the arbitration proceedings for the national claim on which Sheriff Fyfe recently gave an award ; but, before the hearing, the society withdrew and would not agree to the terms of reference. The society have now agreed to a conference, to be held under the chairmanship of a representative of the Ministry.[Reference to matters of interest in connection with Industrial Relations will be found also on pages 308 to 315 and 321.]
GENERAL DEPARTMENT.TRADE BOARDS.FIXING AND VARIATION OF MINIMUM RATES.Boot and Shoe Repairing Trade Board (Great Britaii). The Board have issued a Notice of Proposal, dated the 24th March, to vary the general minimum time-rates and overtime rates for certain classes of male and female workers.The general minimum time-rate proposed for male workers, other than foremen and managers, workers employed in operating power sole stitchers, Blake or Richardson machines, workers employed as pressmen and responsible for cutting and costing, surgical boot makers, indentured apprentices, and learners, and for female workers, 21 years of age and over, other than those employed in a productive department on patching machines and surgical boot makers, is 72s. per week of 48 hours. Lower rates are proposed for male learners and for younger female workers. The rate proposed for male and female surgical boot makers is 2s. per hour. The overtime rates proposed are to be calcu-lated on the proposed minimum rates in the same manner as the overtime rates at present in operation.The Board have also issued a Notice of Proposal, dated the 24th March, to vary the general minimum piece-rates for male and female workers and the overtime rates for male and female workers, employed on piece-work to which general minimum piece-rates are applicable.Dressmaking and Women&apos;$ LigU Clothing Trade Board (England and Wales). The Board have issued a Notice of Proposal dated the 22nd March, to vary the general minimum time-rates, piece work basis time-rates and overtime rates for female workers.The general minimum time-rates proposed are, lOfd. per hour for female workers, of 21 years and under 22 years of age, who have had not less than three years&apos; experience after learnership in the retail bespoke dressmaking trade, and are employed in that trade as fully qualified bodice, skirt, gown or blouse hands ; and 9M. per hour for female workers, 19 years of age and over, who have had not less than one year&apos;s experience after learnership in the retail bespoke dressmaking trade, and are employed in that trade as qualified bodice, skirt, gown or blouse hands. Lower rates are proposed for female learners. The piece-work basis time-rates proposed to correspond with the rates of 10fd and 9^cZ. per hour above are llfd. and 10^d. per hour respectively. The overtime rates proposed are to be calculated on the proposed new minimum rates in the same manner as the overtime rates at present in operation.Retail Bespoke Tailoring Trade Board (Great Britain). The Board have issued a Notice of Proposal, dated the 21st March, to vary and to fix certain general minimum time-rates and overtime rates in their application to certain male and female apprentices. The form of indenture of apprenticeship proposed by the Board is given in the Notice.[Reference to matters of interest in connection with Trade Boards will also be found on pages 310, 312, and 319.]EMPLOYMENT AND INSURANCE DEPARTMENT.EMPLOYMENT EXCHANGES.The Unemployment Position.The following table shows the work of the Exchanges in respect of registrations, vacancies and placings during the week ending the 18th March : 	Men.	Women.	Boys.	Girls.	Total.Registrations 					On live register at beginning of week   ......	874,293	335,696	53,594	54,531	1,318,114Fresh applications...............	111,476	43,412	7,855	7,297	170,040On live register at end of week ...	912,941	354,683	55,923	54,731	1,378,278Vacancies 					Carried forward at beginning of week  ......	13,313	23,782	1,219	2,458	40,772Fresh notifications...............	13,120	7,873	1,257	1,513	23,763Carried forward at end of week.........	12,752	25,089	1,212	2,645	41,698Placings       ..................	12,757	4,402	1,074	1,093	19,326
Employment and Insurance Department-continued. Men&apos;s Employment.General. The position has not changed materially during the week. Reports indicate that prolonged stoppages for the Easter holiday will be the rule, and, in these circumstances, the outlook cannot be regarded as other than unfavourable.Iron and Steel. In Scotland, an extension of short-time working, affecting approxi-mately 700 workmen, is reported from Coatbridge. Several firms at Dumbarton and Motherwell, however, have re-absorbed a number of men. In the Northern Division, suspensions continue to take place from the rolling mills at Darlington. Several iron-stone mines in the Cleveland district are entirely closed down, and at Middlesbrough 250 men have been discharged from the works of the Dinsdale Wire &amp; Steel Co., Ltd. South Bank report the re-starting of two furnaces, which will employ 250 men, and at Cleator Moor 150 men have resumed work at the local ironworks. Considerable fluctua-tion in employment is reported from Consett, where the orders received by the Consett Iron Co., Ltd., do not, as a rule, provide for more than two days&apos; employment. At Scun-thorpe a firm employing approximately 700 men have closed down, and at Barrow one of the steel works has also closed down for an indefinite period.The position in South Wales has slightly improved, as the result of the re-starting of a mill by the Llanelly Steel Co., Ltd., and the partial resumption of employment at the Dowlais works of Messrs. Guest, Keen &amp; Nettlefolds, Ltd.Shipbuilding and Allied Trades. On the Clyde unemployment among skilled workers continues to be very high, and there is apparently little prospect of more labour being absorbed. On the Tyne, Tees and Wear the depression still continues. Ship-repair work in the Hartlepool district, however, shows signs of improvement, and at Southwick and Sunderland an additional number of shipyard workers have been employed. The position on the Mersey and in South Wales is unchanged.Textiles and Clothing. There is no immediate prospect of any improvement in the cotton, trade. Comparatively few orders are being received, and manufacturers are still unable to clear stocks despite drastic cuts in prices. In the woollen textile trade, short-time working and intermittent stoppages are still pronounced, but a slight improvement in the clothing section is reported from Leeds. There are no further developments in the boot and shoe and hosiery trades, but more orders are coming to hand in the curtain and plain net sections of the lace trade.Transport. On the Mersey, transport work is very quiet; both incoming and outgoing cargoes are reported to be scarce. In South Wales the position is stated to be unsteady. At Avonmouth more casual labour has been employed during the week.Miscellaneous Trades. Although spring ploughing and sowing is in full swing the number of agricultural workers unemployed is still large. At Milford Haven fishing is practically at a standstill, Only 9 trawlers are out of dock, and it is expected that these will be laid up on the completion of their present trips. At Great Yarmouth there are a larger number of fishermen unemployed than is usual at this time of the year. The fishing season off the south and west coats usually commences about the middle of March, but, owing to the loss of foreign markets, reduced fleets are being sent this year.There is no improvement in the general situation in the Metropolitan area, but, in the building trade, the shortage of bricklayers and plasterers is still pronounced.womens Employment.General Situation. There are still no signs of revival in the industrial situation, which remains in a condition of serious depression. Slight improvements, notified locally in the clothing trades, are more than counterbalanced by increasing unemployment in staple industries, such as cotton and woollen textiles, and even where there is some improvement, the whole volume of trade would appear to be far less than in normal years.Local Reports.-Th.e North-Western Division again emphasise the acutely depressed condition of the textile industry, and state that unemployment, particularly amongst women, is much on the increase. Many employers are taking advantage of the Easter holidays, and closing down entirely for varying periods.The Yorkshire and East Midlands Division report that there appears to be no sign of revival of trade in the textile centres, and in many cases extended Easter holidays are being arranged. Depression continues also in the hosiery, lace, boot and shoe, and making-up trades.  The activity in the blouse trade is said to be negligible in comparison
with the normal trade at this time of the year. At Sutton-in-Ashfield, out of a total live register of 900, approximately 700 workers are normally employed in the hosiery industry. At Dewsbury more weavers and menders have been suspended, and blouse and under-clothing machinists expect to be on short time until June.Leeds report that the numbers in the tailoring classification have decreased by approxi-mately 700, but against this there have been numerous registrations of claimants under the new Act. Efforts are being made throughout the division to persuade suitable unem-ployed women to undertake seasonal employment in holiday resorts.The situation in the South Midlands and Eastern Division is practically unchanged. Slight local improvements are notified, but generally unemployment and trade depression continue. Silk workers are unemployed at Braintree and hosiery workers and elastic-web makers at Coalville.At Norwich, Kettering and Northampton, boot operatives remain unemployed and are on short time, but in Wellingborough there is said to be a slight improvement in the boot trade.  From Colchester a steady improvement in the wholesale clothing trade is reported.Birmingham, Sparkhill and West Bromwich again state that the live register, and claims for unemployment insurance benefit, are rapidly increasing. The engineering, jewellery, rubber and other industries remain depressed. A similar position in the motor and cycle trade is reported from Coventry. At Cradley Heath, nut and bolt makers, hollow-ware workers, chain makers, nail makers and pin makers are unemployed. At Smethwick there is depression in the brass and steel works and in the iron and steel rolling mills. Nuneaton report that works are closing down for extended Easter holidays in the silk, textile and felt hat industries. Pottery workers are reported to be on broken time at Stoke-on-Trent, Longton and Burslem.The heavy unemployment, which has so long been prevalent in the London area, continues. At Bermondsey the unemployed include jam makers, tin box makers, char-women, leather stitchers, tailoresses, shirt and collar machinists and factory workers. Similar reports have been received from the Borough, Canning Town, Deptford, East Ham, Leyton, Poplar, Shoreditch, Whitechapel, Tottenham, Hackney, Holloway and other Exchanges.   At Deptford, however, the improvement in the clothing trade continues.Little change is apparent in the South-Western Division, where the staple clothing industries remain depressed. At Eastville, Bristol, large numbers of confectionery workers, corset makers and others are unemployed or on short time. At Exeter tailoresses, dress-makers, shirt and collar makers and brush makers are unemployed. At Gloucester the live register is over 700, and at Swindon clothing operatives are being suspended. Tailoresses are unemployed at Basingstoke, and at Yeovil nearly all the glove factories are working short time.In Wales some increase in unemployment is reported, and depression in the tinplate industries appears to be developing. Tin workers are unemployed at Aberdare, Gorseinon, Llanelly, Pontypridd and Port Talbot.  At Cardiff the live register is nearly 600.The position in the Northern Division is unchanged. The live register at Carlisle is approximately 350, and many workers are on short time. At Gateshead the live register stands at 750, and at Heaton at 400. At Newcastle warehouse workers, skin workers and lead workers are unemployed. In the last case this is said to be due to the Act pro-prohibiting the employment of women in lead processes. The Kendal Exchange report that seasonal hotel work is progressing well.In Scotland depression continues in the staple textile industries, and in hosiery, linen, jute, rubber, printing and general factory employment.At Aberdeen there are approximately 1,500 women totally unemployed, and over 1,100 short-time workers. These include printers, paper makers, linen and jute workers, hosiery workers, glovers and tailoresses. Calico printers, hosiery workers, cotton spinners and weavers and steel brick makers are unemployed in Airdrie.Textile operatives, including woollen operatives and tweed weavers, are unemployed or on short time at Alloa, Barrhead, Dumbarton, Galashiels, Paisley and other textile centres. The linen industry in Dunfermline is severely depressed, as is also the jute industry in Dundee. Dumfries report that a number of hosiery and glove workers have been reinstated, peavy registers continue to be reported from the Glasgow and Edinburgh Exchanges.(b 17165T) 2 T
Employment and Insurance Department-continued.*.. ,, local EMPLOYMENT COMMITTEES.Disabled Men. Tlie Leicester Committee recommend the establishment of an organi-sation similar to the Corps of Commissionaires, composed of disabled men available for such jobs as out-porters, night watchmen, and handy men, with headquarters at the local Exchange.Unemployment Insurance. The Cambridge Women&apos;s Sub-Committee have protested against what they consider to he an attempt to force women into domestic service against their will, but, at the same meeting, recommended the provision of a training class for domestic workers. A similar protest is to hand from the Bermondsey Committee. The Peterborough Committee recommend that all employers be asked to notify the Exchange of any cases where workpeople refuse offers of suitable employment, so that the unemploy-ment fund may be safeguarded.Women&apos;s Work. The usual arrangements for filling seasonal domestic vacancies at seaside resorts are now in hand, and the services of the women&apos;s sub-committees are proving of great value. The committee at Sheffield recommend that all imported applicants should be asked to bring to the notice of the nearest committee any complaints against the conditions of service.OUT-OF-WORK DONATION, AND UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE BENEFIT.Out-of-Work Donation.-Returns by the Finance Department, according to information received at the Claims and Record Office, Kew, for the week ending the 17th March, show 331,295 payments to policy holders, involving an amount of  300,397 6s. 9d.Unemploijment Insurance. The number of payments of unemployment insurance benefit during the week ending the 11th March was 973,280, involving an amount of  637,060 Us. Id,DISCHARGED AND DISABLED SAILORS AND SOLDIERS,National Scheme. Up to and including the 22nd March, 24,661 certificates have been issued to employers under the Scheme. The undertakings given by these employers cover 274,461 disabled ex-Service men.Reports from Divisional Controllers indicate that the placing of disabled men has not been unsatisfactory on the whole, considering the depressed industrial conditions. A few engineering firms have recently been added to the Roll, but the industrial depression has adversely affected the success of the recent canvass. Better results are anticipated when trade revives.[Reference to matters of interest to the Employment and Insurance Department will also be found on pages 309, 310, 319 and 326.]APPOINTMENTS AND TRAINING.APPOINTMENTS AND CIVIL LIABILITIES DEPARTMENT,APPOINTMENTS.Statistics. During the week ending the 18th March, the Appointments Department placed 443 candidates for appointments, bringing the total number of candidates known to have been placed to 52,250. Of these, 6,997 have been placed through the agency of the department&apos;s Interviewing Boards. Applications were registered from 799 ex-Service men and 26 civilians. The number of candidates available for appointments on the 18th March was 10,596 ex-Service men and 1,223 civilians. At the same date, 948 &quot; live &quot; vacancies were at the disposal of the department, 532 having been registered during the week.BUSINESS AND PROFESSIONAL TRAINING,Maintenance and Training Grants Scheme.&apos; During the week ending&apos;the 18th March, the Appointments Department received applications for training under this scheme from 7 officers or men of similar educational qualifications, of which 1 was for training of the type provided by the department.  Deducting cancellations and withdrawals, 28,144
applications for training of this latter type have been received in all, and 49,489 for training of the type provided by other Government departments. The Interviewing Boards have dealt with 27,833 applications, of which 23,326 have been recommended. The Grants Committee, dealing with applications so recommended, have received 22,206 applications and sanctioned grants in 18,379 cases.Business Training Scheme. During the week ending the 18th March, the Appoint-ments Department received 135 applications for training under this scheme, bringing the total number of applications to 2,926, of which 789 have since been cancelled. Grants have been sanctioned in 633 cases. At the same date 345 training vacancies were at the disposal of the department, 54 having been registered during the week.Training of Disabled Officers under Pensions Wairant. The Appointments Depart-ment have dealt with a total of 1,134 cases, in 487 of which the training sanctioned is provided by the Appointments Department, and in the remainder by other Government departments. Candidates accepted by the Ministry of Labour have completed training in 305 cases, and abandoned training in 46 ; 120 are still in training, and 16 are awaiting training.TRAINING DEPARTMENT. INDUSTRIAL TRAINING.Disabled and Other Ex-Service Men.Statistics. On the 22nd March, 24,766 men were in training, as against 24,749 on the 15th March, and 25,072 on the 22nd February. During the week, 404 men were placed in training. There were 16,482 men awaiting training, the corresponding totals for the 15th March and the 22nd February being 16,490 and 16,141 respectively. The number of men whose training had been completed since the 1st August, 1919, was 28,458, the totals for the 15th March and the 22nd February being 28,071 and 26,532 respectively.Workshop Vacancies. Several divisions have now completed their arrangements with the officers of the Interrupted Apprenticeships Branch, and will, in future, have their co-operation in finding workshop vacancies.Unemployment. A good many reports call attention to unemployment amongst trained men, and to suspensions of men taking improverships, in consequence of general reductions of staff. Difficulty is now being met with chiefly in the engineering, furniture, leather, and certain branches of the building trades.Training Difficulties. The cases of the more severely disabled and of the older and poorly educated men present special difficulty. For the first class it has been suggested that the solution lies in the use of special institutions ; it is almost impossible, in some cases, to train the second class at all. For the older men some form of work in connection with their pre-war occupations, for which little or no training would be required, is recom-mended by one Divisional Director, who is also of opinion that men who are difficult to place on account of lack of elementary knowledge, or general incapacity for continuous effort, should be tested once and for all in preliminary instruction classes, those who make good being retained till some suitable training opening can be found, and the remainder struck off the list.Local Technical Advisory Committees: Building. Local Technical Advisory Com-mittees are in course of formation at Yeovil and &quot;Wallasey, and a proposal to establish a committee to cover the Swansea area is being investigated. At the last meeting of the Colchester Committee the question was discussed of setting up an Advisory Committee at Eomford, to supervise training at the Hare Hall Factory. On the understanding, however, that the Colchester Committee would, in future, make more frequent visits of inspection, it was decided not to proceed with the establishment of a new committee.Apprenticeships Interrupted by Service.Statistics. Up to the 23rd March; agreements had been received at headquarters in respect of 45,985 apprentices, under the 41 schemes approved. Grants had been sanctioned in respect of 43-,912 apprentices. The total number of agreements lapsed on expiration of the appropriate period of training, or by mutual agreement between the parties, is now 21,384.[Reference to matters of interest to the Appointments and Training Departments will also be found on pages 320, 321 and 326.]

</content>
</cab>
