<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/58/13 images: 182-188</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy NO     85CC(76) 13thConclusionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onFRIDAY 26 MARCH 1976at 10.30 am present the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon Edward Short mp lord President of the CouncilRt Hon Lord Elwyn-Jones**rd ChancellorRt Hon Denis Healey MP^^cellor of the Exchequer* Rt Hon Michael Foot MPcretary of State for EmploymentRt Hon Shirley Williams MPCR?etary of State for Pricesburner Protection*fceRt Hon Eric Varley MP^etary of State for Industry**** Rt Hon Roy Mason MP^tary of State for DefenceRt Hon Merlyn Rees MP*c*etary of State for Northern IrelandRt Hon Harold Lever MP**ilor of the Duchy of lancaster the Rt Hon James Callaghan mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Hon Roy Jenkins mp secretary of State for the home department the Rt Hon Anthony Crosland mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for energy the Rt Hon Barbara Castle mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon peter Shore mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon John Morris QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Fred Peart mp minister of Agriculture, fisheries and Food
The Rt Hon Fred Mulley mp secretary of State for Education andThe Rt Hon Robert MeUish mp parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp minister for Overseas development the Rt Hon John Silkin mp minister for Planning and LocalGovernmentSECRETARIATSir John hunt mr G A DesmanMr E J G smith mr A K H AtkinsonSUBJECTDIRECT ELECTIONS TO THE EUROPEAN ASSEMBLYii
directelectionsTO THEEuropeanassemblyPreviousReference:CC(?6) 5thConclusions,1 Minute 6The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs (C(76 ) 44) on directelections to the European Assembly.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY recalled thatfollowing the Cabinet&apos;s discussion on 12 February the HomeSecretary and he had presented to Parliament a Green Paper andhad held discussions with the Parliamentary Labour Party (PLP).Debates had now been arranged in the House of Commons for thefollowing Monday and Tuesday and the House of Lords for thefollowing Monday.    He had circulated in Hansard a full note setting out the substance of the text of the draft Convention which would bebefore the Heads of Government of the European Economic Community(e.c.) at the European Council on 1/2 April, although since that textwas still subject to inter-Governmental negotiation it would beimproper to publish the text itself.   At the meeting of the EuropeanCouncil he expected the Prime Minister of Luxembourg, as president, to try to make as much progress as possible; but hethought it most improbable that any firm agreement would be reached.The main question at issue would be the number and distribution of seats in the Assembly.    The existing Assembly had proposed thatthe new one consist of 355 members, and while a somewhat largersize should make it easier to secure an allocation of seats to member States more closely in proportion to their population, hewould not wish to see too large an increase in size.    Thedistribution of seats between the Member States was likely to cause the greatest difficulties.    The smaller countries, particularlyLuxembourg and the Irish Republic, would strive to maintain thepresent distribution, which was very much in their favour.   Francehowever had proposed a distribution strictly proportional to national population, though in the last resort she might compromise on this.    We were faced with considerable difficulties in that on thepresent proposal the constituent parts of the United Kingdom wouldbe clearly less well-treated than independent Member States with similar populations.    We should therefore seek a solution with thegreatest degree of proportionality to population as possible, while recognising that exact proportionality would not be negotiable; butwe should let the French make the running on this.Other issues likely to be discussed on 1/2 April included theelection date.    He considered that the general wish to hold directelections in May 1978 considerably under-estimated the practicaldifficulties involved.    We had insisted on a derogation which wouldenable us to continue to nominate members of the Assembly for atime after 1978, even if the others moved to direct elections; butthis would cause a number of practical difficulties and we had aconsiderable incentive to agree to direct elections at the same time as the other Member States,    If there were elections hi May 1978,
he thought it would be advantageous for both party organisations and the voters to combine them with the local elections.    He thoughtthat there was no likelihood of a draft text of a Convention being agreed on 1/2 April, but that the outstanding issues would be remitted to Foreign Ministers, with a view to decisions at theEuropean Council meeting in July.    There was no prospect of increased powers for the Assembly, as the French had already made plain, although doubtless the additional legltimisatlon of direct election would encourage members of the Assembly to press for greater powers.The House of Commons was now showing more interest in thismatter than had been shown at the meeting of the PLP.    Threeearly day motions had been tabled.    One, attracting the support ofover a hundred Members, principally Labour, urged the government not to proceed further until a Select Committee had been established and reported on the issue; there was a similar one signed by asmall number of mainly Conservative anti-Marketeers; whereasa counter-motion, signed by over a hundred mainly ConservativeMPs, had urged progress on direct elections as soon as possible.In the circumstances he thought there was a case for a SelectCommittee to be established to look into the question at the sametime as the Government was discussing it within the e.c. machinery,though there would obviously be difficulties for the Government ifthe European Council and the Select Committee were to come to different conclusions.In discussion it was agreed that the question of direct elections wasnot a purely technical issue, but needed to be decided in the light ofthe sort of Community we wished to see.    It was argued on the one handthat we should welcome the democratic control which a directly elected European Assembly would bring.    Many Communityactivities, by their very nature, were not subject to direct control by national Parliaments, and there would have to be accountabilityeither to a European Parliament or not at all.    We had been in thevan of instituting democratic control in our own country, and could make the greatest contribution in Europe.    If other Member Statespressed on with directly electing their representatives, as many ofthem seemed determined to do, our voice would be weakened if wewere still nominating our representatives.    Moreover there werepractical reasons for moving to direct elections as soon as possible.The present dual mandate was a great strain; and if, say, 70Members of Parliament had to be nominated to the european assembly the business of the House, especially the committees,would be gravely jeopardised.    Under the Treaty of Rome we hada clear legal and moral duty to accept direct universal suffrageand genuinely to move towards it, though we were bound by no time-scale.    There were admittedly practical difficulties in a2
system of direct elections, such as the relationship between members of the Assembly and Westminster, and the definition ofboundaries for the European constituencies.   A Select committee might be useful to deal with such practical difficulties, if need beby a year or two&apos;s delay in introducing direct elections; but delayshould not be used as a device to evade our fundamental commitment.On the other hand it was argued that the issue of direct electionscould not be divorced from the issue of powers of the Assembly.Already Members of the Assembly - whether originally favouringEEC membership or not - were demanding greater powers.    Directelection was bound to reinforce that demand, especially since itwas a misnomer to call the Assembly a &quot;Parliament&quot; as it had nolaw-making or tax-raising powers.    The Tindemans report on european Union had openly recognised that increased powers would flow from direct elections.    This would involve irrevocable steps towards a federal Europe - a concept which had not been put beforethe British people, nor approved by them, in the referendum.There was no popular pressure for direct elections;  such pressureas there was came in large measure from the desire of an increasingly   :powerful Brussels bureaucracy to legitimise itself through elected representatives.   Indeed Ministers were often faced with taking orleaving a package which had been constructed by officials.    It waspointed out however that, especially in those Councils which metregularly, Ministers were able to exert considerable collectiveinfluence and were fully in control of the broad lines of policy.In any event there was no need for us to rush to a decision.    Theoriginal Six had had many years to consider the issue; since thefinal decision to remain a member of the e.c. had been taken lessthan a year previously, there was a case for the present arrangements continuing for a further five or six years.    one particular difficulty about introducing direct elections in 1978 wasthat legislation would be required in the 1976-77 Session, which would already be heavily occupied with the legislation on devolution; jthis coincidence was to be avoided if possible.The relationship between the seats hi the Assembly likely to go to jScotland, Wales and Northern Ireland in comparison to Denmark,the Irish Republic and the Benelux countries was crucial. jDevolution was one of the biggest issues facing the country, and !passions ran high.   Any arrangement which put those constituent parts of the United Kingdom at such a manifest disadvantage woulddangerously inflame the devolution issue.    The distribution of seatsalso had wider implications.    European parties would grow up, andit was important to avoid over-representation of those countrieslikely to elect right-wing members.    The relationship between members of the European Assembly and Westminster required3
further thought.    Great problems would arise if Labour member selected to the Assembly looked upon their links as being with a european Socialist group, rather than the British Labour Party,since the two might have significantly different policies; though this danger could be reduced if the British Labour Party took morepart in meetings of European Socialist parties.    The circumstancesof direct elections might encourage the establishment of partieswhich were not traditionally part of the British political scene, andif the elections were divorced from national elections, could resultin a different balance of representation at the European assembly and at Westminster.    This suggested that the link, which wouldbe desirable on grounds of organisation and turn-out, should notbe with local elections where in any case there would be a risk oflocal issues confusing the European ones but with national elections,accepting that this would mean that there would be no fixed terms for Members of the Assembly.Many practical difficulties in the way of direct elections, such asmethods of selecting candidates and of organising and financingelection campaigns, had to be examined and resolved.   There wastherefore every reason for accepting the suggested SelectCommittee.    Moreover, the Government should not appear to be doing mis unwillingly, but positively involving Parliament in this important constitutional development, in contrast to the wayParliament had been treated when the European Communities bill was before it.In further discussion there was general agreement that theGovernment should welcome the establishment of a Select Committee,though its terms of reference and membership would require careful consideration.    For example, there might be a case for a minister chairing the Committee; for it being a joint committee ofboth Houses; and for constitutional experts appearing as witnessesbefore it.    However, we need not take the lead at the EuropeanCouncil in resisting direct elections in 1978,    France saw as many difficulties as we did in the proposal and there was no reason why we should risk arousing opposition to some of our other objectionsby incurring odium over this when the French could be left to blockprogress.   As other countries came to realise the problems involved,a slower timetable would almost certainly emerge; and otherdevelopments, Buch as the enlargement of the Community, wouldthen be seen to have a bearing on the issue,THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said thatduring the forthcoming debate in the House of Commons theGovernment spokesman should offer to set up a Select Committee.In the light of the views expressed in that debate, the Governmentwould consider the matter further and make recommendations to4
Parliament about me Select Committee&apos;s terms of reference and related matters.   At the meeting of the European Council weshould not take the lead in opposing direct elections in 1978 but should encourage debate which would bring out the inherentdifficulties.    We should make it clear that there would need to be adequate representation for the United Kingdom and its constituent parts, and also that we could not take any final decisions until thereport of the Select Committee had been considered by Parliament.Subject to this, our representatives at the European Council shouldhave sufficient freedom of manoeuvre to avoid attractingunnecessary odium.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion.Cabinet Office26 March 19765

</content>
</cab>
