<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/59/40 images: 418-421</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC&quot; MA JESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.    December 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (M) 740.15th December, 1944.WAR CABINET.GREECE.Note by the Secretary.THE Prime Minister has directed that the attached memorandum (Annex I),which was left with him on the evening of 13th December by the King of Greece,together with the telegram which was sent from the Foreign Office toMr. Macmillan in Athens later the same night (Annex II), should be circulated for the information of the War Cabinet.(Signed) E. E. BRIDGES,Secretary.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1,15th December, 1944.ANNEX   I.Memorandum from the King of Greece, l%th December, 1944.HIS Majesty the King is convinced that under present circumstances theappointment of the Metropolitan as Regent, apart from other constitutional difficulties, would create confusion and weaken the resistance against the rebels.On the other hand, it is most improbable that this further concession ofthe King, after all those which have already been granted, would suffice for the rebels to accept to lay down their arms, nor is there such an assurance in mr. Macmillan&apos;s information.The King moreover is not convinced that the appointment of any one personas Regent would meet with the unanimous wish of the Greek people. On thecontrary the Prime Minister as well as most other political leaders have assuredhim of the contrary.ANNEX II.Cypher Telegram from Foreign Office to A thens.(No. 457.) Foreign Office, 13th December, 1944.1. The Prime Minister and I have put the arguments in your telegram tothe King of Greece, and we have had two interviews with him on the subject.-His Majesty has asked for a little more time to consider the position before giving us his final reply. The King has reminded, us that he has in particular to take account of the advice which he is himself receiving from Greece, from hisjfrime Minister and others. These messages, he tells us, show no enthusiasmtor the proposal that the Archbishop should be Regent, and the King read tous to-night a telegram which he had just received from M. Papandreou whichformally advised against the project.[28834]
2. It would therefore help us if you would let us know what are yourreasons for believing that this proposal would receive wide popular support,and what leaders of Greek opinion you have discussed it with and what they said.3. The King would find it easier to reach a decision if you could forward to us opinions in favour of the course you advocate from the Prime Minister,M. Sophoulis, and other leaders of Greek parties. They should also addressthemselves personally to the King.4. Once we have this evidence we will again place the issue four-squarebefore the King.



</content>
</cab>
