<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/186/3 images: 51-58</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
: : - LETDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(75) 12821 November 1975CABINETCHRYSLER UKMemorandum by the Secretary of State for industry. Chrysler Corporation have effectively confronted us with eithertaking over Chrysler UK, and the Government assuming responsibilityfor funding future development and future losses, or they will begin to run it down from 30 November over the following 3 months.    Becausethey want to exploit the United States tax position (for which 31 Decemberis a critical date) and to stem losses, no extension of this period is likely tobe negotiable.    Taking it over as a going concern could mean having toprovide some  140 million over the next 4 yeax*s and probably much more;by scaling down operations and closing one plant in the Midlands this mightbe reduced to some  100 million or more.    But closures would lose some25, 000 jobs in Coventry, Dunstable and Linwood, with perhaps something of the same order in components firms and dealers.    Details of the various schemes considered are given in the Annex; amongst these was thepossibility of pulling out of volume car assembly and concentrating theother activities at Linwood.2. Extensive probing has failed to disclose any material change inthe Chrysler position; but I am putting to them now a direct questionwhether they are prepared after the end of November to meet a share ofthe costs of continuing production and the financing of future losses,and if so what share and towards what production scheme.    I shall report their reply to my colleagues.    I shall need to meet Chrysler Corporationagain next week before we announce a decision.3. The Industrial Development Advisory Board concluded that none ofthe schemes considered held prospects of viability, though Board members were equally divided about how social and other wider considerationsaffected the recommendation on support.    The report of the Central policy review Staff (CPRS) on cars points to a large continuing surplus of capacity.All the schemes we have considered would be unviable even on paper; inmost of them Chrysler Corporation would have power without responsibility and in practice we should be taking on an open ended commitment.    In my view the case against putting these substantial funds into this ailing company is quite overwhelming.COPY NO31
4. If no support is given arid Chrysler UK close down we can expectChrysler dealers in this country to seek to go over to foreign car makerswho would be likely to penetrate our market further.    I consider it essential to announce temporary import restrictions taking effect immediately on the lines of the scheme developed by the Secretary of Statefor Trade.    There is however a possibility of the more profitablecommercial vehicle operation of Chrysler UK being taken over, and forexample Volvo have mentioned to me a possible interest.5. The gravest consequence will be the loss of jobs.    Although theEmployment Services Agency will help I see no immediate prospects ofnew employment in the areas affected and the direct consequences of aChrysler shut down would be that male unemployment would double andtreble respectively in Coventry (to 14 per cent) and Paisley (Linwood)(to 17 per cent) and there would be a significant effect for the West midlands and West Central Scotland.    There are likely to be powerful reactions fromTrades Unions and Members of Parliament,    I consider it essential for usto announce the special scheme for redundancy payments prepared by theSecretary of State for Employment.6. Public presentation will need great care and should be linked withpublication of the CPRS report.     Before a statement is made I must meetthe trades unions concerned.    We shall need to ensure that theinevitably harsh exchanges with Chrysler do not repercuss on other international activites in this country.7. I invite my colleagues to agree -a. we should not take over Chrysler UK and should placefirmly on the Chrysler Corporation responsibility and odiumfor closing it down;b. in announcing our decision I should say we are forthwithrestricting imports of cars te tho same level ao laot year;t^ML^ do   ft.   (rvZ^ f^r^y? Jr-^   ^W^L / 9 7 *- - ria^JL I cl &quot;7S&quot;-c. we should also introduce the redundancy scheme preparedby the Secretary of State for Employment and put in forcearrangements for co-ordinating local actions which he has suggested;d. the CPRS report shculd be published at the same time as the Chrysler statement is made.E G V Department of Industry21 November 19752
ANNEXSCHEMES DISCUSSED WITH THE CHRYSLER CORPORATIONSCHEME A - Taking over. Chrysler UK as a going concernIn their first discussions with Ministers, Mr Riccardo(Chairman of Chrysler Corporation) and his team suggestedHM Government took over Chrysler UK as a going concern.   Tomeet continuing losses and to provide for capital needswhich could not be met from internal sources, Mr Riccardoput the initial commitments at  140- 150 millions up to 1979without allowing for capital needs for new developments andmodels coming to fruition after that date.     HM Governmentwould take majority ownership but Chrysler Corporation mightbe prepared to continue with a minority interest of lessthan 20%., but they said explicitly they would not meet anypart of continuing losses.   No major works would close butthere would be some 6,000 redundancies.     The Iran contractwould continue as at present and Chrysler Corporation wouldprovide some technical and marketing support.SCHEME B - Streamlined -Chrysler UK2      Chrysler Corporation put forward as an alternative a schemewhich would preserve some 15,000 gobs including 4,000 of thepresent 6,400 at Linwood (rising later to 5,600 or more);    itwould mean concentrating car assembly at Linwood and reducing/the model ..
2the model range.   The Ryton (Coventry)(with over 4,000 workers)plant   would close completely and there would &quot;be substantialredundancies throughout the Midlands and elsewhere.    Assemblyof the Avenger would be moved from Ryton to Linwood; thiswould almost certainly he opposed by the Ryton workers.3      The resulting car operation at Linwood would be substantiallysmaller than the size suggested in the CPRS report as theminimum competitive size for an assembly plant (250,000 units),and would involve only a very small share of the UK market.After losses of about  40 million in 1975 and 1976, Chryslerforesaw a marginal profit in 1977*     This turn round is most unlikely to be achieved, but even if their assumed results up to1979 are achievable, the future of the Iranian contract after1980 must be very doubtful and tike level of profits is in anycase inadequate to finance the introduction of new modelsbeyond 1979.SCHEME C - Concentrating on Linwood4      The Chrysler Corporation have, estimated that the capital cost of moving the commercial vehicle, spares and parts and the iranian contract work (which expires in 1980) to Linwood wouldbe some  19 million, volume car production would be discontinuedand revenue losses of the operation would be some  61 millionup to 1979- It would eventually provide some 6,000 gobs/at Linwood ..
SECRETat Linwood, but to a large extent different engineeringskills would be needed from those of the present workforce.At the very least (and assuming no disrupting industrial action in the Midlands, etc.,) the transfer would take months and meanwhile there would be no employment.   putting the commercial vehicle work in Scotland would involve seriouscost penalties.5      It is clear that, even if it could be achieved againstserious opposition from the Coventry and Dunstable workers,the result of attempting to concentrate these operations atLinwood would be a totally unviable operation, which at a cost in the next 4 years of over  80 million would provideonly 6,000 gobs at best.    Its prospects of long termsurvival would be poor, and it would need indefinite subventionfrom the Government.SCHEME D - Retaining Iranian Contract at Stoke (Coventry)6      Because of the significance of this contract to Anglo-Iranian trade relations and the balance of payments, chrysler corporation examined the possibility of HMG taking over this contract if Chrysler HK&apos;s other operations are closed down.The capital cost would be only some  2 million, and the resulting operation at Stoke would employ some 2,000 people in-1976 and 3,000 from 1977 to 1980 (when the present contractexpires).     It is estimated that it would lose  10 million in1976 and  6 million -  7 million a year thereafter.
7      The turnover would be  91 million a year, all earned fromIran; &quot;but since if Chrysler Corporation sourced the contractfrom outside the UK (which would otherwise he their plan) theywould still expect to buy in initially at least some 35%of the contract from UK firms, the net foreign earnings preservedwould he some  60 million a year at first.8      The contract would he of some value to Chrysler Corporationwho would have to be paid something for it - in addition to the 32 million which HMG would have to spend.    It is not clear whether Chrysler Corporation would he prepared to manage it and provide the necessary technical hack-up; they have suggestedthat it might he better for British Leyland to take over thisrole.     In any event the co-operation of Chrysler corporation in arranging the transfer of the contract to HMG would heneeded (despite the obscurity of the coritractual position) -as well as that of the Iranians which may be harder to get.9      The proposal to move to Linwood the Iranian work,commercial vehicles and spares and service and close down allChrysler UK&apos;s plants other than at Linwood is unlikely tohe feasible in practice taking account of resistance by workers in the.Midlands, and could not conceivably he viable.Summary10     To sum up, the options appear to be as follows:-
(i)     to take over Chrysler UK at a cost of some  140million or more for the period up to 1979(with continuing commitments thereafter) andsome 6,000 redundancies in Chrysler UK;(ii) to support a stream-lined Chrysler UK, assuming thatit is practicable in the face of resistance byredundant workers to work transfer, at a likelycost of  100 million or more and some 10,000redundancies;(iii) to transfer work to Linwood and close down ChryslerUK&apos;s other activities at a cost over the next 4 yearsof  80 million, against certain opposition from19,000 redundant workers in Coventry and elsewhere;(iv)    to maintain the Iranian contract sourced fromCoventry at a cost of over  32 million, with22,000 redundancies;(v)    to let Chrysler Corporation liquidate its UK operations,starting from the end of November, with ultimately25,000 redundancies.


</content>
</cab>
