<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/93/0 images: 98-98</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1958C. (58) 119 Copy No. 5 829th May, 1958CABINETARTIFICIAL INSEMINATIONMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home Department andLord Privy Seal and the Secretary of State for scotland on 25th February the Cabinet invited us to.consider, in consultation with theLord Chancellor, the composition and terms of reference of a DepartmentalCommittee to review the legal consequences of the existing practice of artificial insemination of women.  (C.C. (58) 18th Conclusions, Minute 3.)2. The debate in the House of Lords on 26th February showed clearly thatto set up an enquiry with such restricted terms of reference would be regarded asshirking the main issue; and the Lord Chancellor^ announcement that theGovernment would set up a Committee seems to have been generally taken, in thePress and elsewhere, as implying the appointment of an enquiry to cover the wholefield, including the legal, social and medical aspects.3. On consideration we do not feel that the wider aspects of the subject canbe ignored by the Committee; indeed the legal consequences must to a large extentdepend on the view they take of them. We therefore propose that the terms ofreference should be wide enough to make this possible, viz.:  &quot; To enquire into the existing practice of human artificial inseminationand its legal consequences; and to consider whether, taking account of theinterests of individuals involved and of society as a whole, any change in thelaw is necessary or desirable.&quot;4. We propose that three members of the Committee should have legalexperience, and that it should include two members of the medical profession andthree or four lay men and women chosen primarily for their ability to commandpublic confidence; we would hope that some of the members could also be relied upon to understand the attitude of the churches.5. We shall be glad to have the agreement of our colleagues to go ahead onthese lines.R. A. B.J. S. M.28th May, 1958.53491CONFIDENTIALTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT

</content>
</cab>
