<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/93/0 images: 204-206</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet. June 1958C. (58) 121 Copy No.  D13th June, 1958CABINETTERRITORIAL waters memorandum by the Attorney-general on 15th May the Cabinet (C.C. (58) 43rd Conclusions, Minute 2), invited me to circulate a Memorandum on the tactics to be adopted at the next international discussion on the breadth of territorial waters.2. As the Cabinet are aware, the Geneva Conference on the Law of the Seadid not pass by the necessary two-thirds majority any proposal with regard to the breadth of the territorial sea or with regard to the closely associated subject ofexclusive fishing outside the limits of the territorial sea.3. The Geneva Conference, having failed to reach a decision on these matters,resolved to request the General Assembly of the United Nations which meets in theautumn to study the advisability of convening a further Conference on these subjects.The questions which fall to be considered are (a) what action, if any, should be taken by us before the meeting of the general assembly; and(b) what course we should pursue at the meeting of the General Assembly.4. As the action to be taken before the meeting of the General Assembly will depend on the decision as to the course we should adopt at the meeting, it will be convenient to consider the latter question first.5. Unless a remarkable change of opinion occurs, there is in my view no prospect whatsoever of securing the support of the majority of the nationsrepresented at Geneva for the retention of the three-mile limit. A number of states have already claimed more: Ecuador, Peru and Chile have claimed 200 miles; Russiasince 1907 has claimed .12; other States have claimed 12 miles and there are somewho have indicated their desire to do so. Some of those who have claimed 12 mileswould be prepared to revert to six miles if that limit were adopted by the Conferenceof the United Nations.6. I gather the Australians think, as I do, that it is likely that at the meeting ofthe General Assembly the proposal that there should be a further Conference onthese matters will be resisted by the Soviet bloc, some of the Afro-Asian group andsome of the Latin-Americans. This opposition is likely to be based on the view that,if a decision is reached on these matters at a further Conference, it is iikely to bea decision restricting the liberty of action of individual States and may well be adecision adopting a limit less than that already claimed by a number of States. we know that the ultimate objective of Iceland is to extend her jurisdiction over thewhole of the continental shelf around Iceland and that would mean that in many places there would be more than 12 miles&apos; breadth of territorial sea.7. To let matters rest as they now are is an attractive proposition, but in my view there is no prospect that they will remain as they now are. If there is no further conference, unilateral claims for a breadth of 12 miles and, it may be, for more are almost certain to be made and if acquiesced in for a period of years they will gainsome validity.53583THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT
8. It would therefore appear to be to our advantage that there should be a limit to the breadth of territorial waters and the only hope of securing any universallimit which will be internationally recognised lies in a further Conference. I therefore recommend that we should at the General Assembly strongly support the holding of a further Conference.9. I do not wish to minimise the risk that such a Conference will also fail toarrive at a decision on these matters. Whether it does so or not will depend verylargely on the preparatory work that is done. It would not be very difficult in myopinion to secure the adoption of a 12-mile limit. Indeed at such a Conference thereal difficulty might be, as it was at Geneva, to prevent the acceptance of that limit.10. At Geneva, we and the United States made it clear that, as the UnitedStates proposal did not obtain the necessary two-thirds majority, we and the UnitedStates would only recognise a three-mile limit. Nonetheless, at any further conference we shall have to put forward some proposal for a greater breadth if weare to get acceptance of a limit by the Conference. Such a proposal would, I think,have to be based on the American proposal at Geneva and if one could divorce the exclusive fishing question from that of the breadth of the territorial sea, 1 think thatthere could be a real prospect of acceptance of a six-mile limit for the territorial sea.11. Such a divorce could be effected if agreement were secured to a proposal that questions on exclusive fishing should be solved, not by the application of onerule for the whole of the world, but by regional conferences which would have regardto particular local conditions. It could be argued that fishery problems in theSouthern Pacific are very different from those in the Northern Atlantic and that suchproblems could best be tackled by regional Conferences. I threw out thissuggestion in private conversations during the concluding stages at Geneva and itwas very well received.12. If we could get the General Assembly to recommend this regionalapproach to fishery problems and to recommend a further Conference on the breadth of the territorial sea I think that such a further Conference might well agree to a six-mile limit.13. While there were pretty clear indications at Geneva that the nations whichdesired an extension of territorial limits would not wish such an extension tointerfere with the rights of civilian air passage outside three miles, I should make itclear that in my opinion there will be very considerable opposition by many countries to the recognition of unrestricted rights of passage of warships or military aircraft within the extended territorial waters. The provisions of the Conventionagreed at Geneva relating to the innocent passage of warships are by no meansunsatisfactory and it does not seem to me that we should suffer materially by theapplication of these provisions to a breadth of six miles. Perhaps it might bepossible in some way to secure the adoption of similar provisions in relation to thepassage of aircraft.14. If it be decided that the course we should pursue at the meeting of theGeneral Assembly is to support a proposal for a further Conference on the breadth of the territorial sea and for separate regional Conferences with regard to fishingproblems, then a great deal of preparatory work will have to be done before theGeneral Assembly meets to give those proposals any real prospect of success. Wewould have to discuss these matters with those who proved our friends at geneva and in particular with the Commonwealth countries. Perhaps the most convenientway of doing the latter would be by some kind of Commonwealth Conference, forI feel that we should be much more likely to get agreement within theCommonwealth at such a Conference than as a result of efforts by telegrams. india would be willing to adopt a six-mile limit for the territorial sea, but is reluctant totake an attitude different from that of other members of the Afro-Asian group.However, as she finally supported the American proposal, it might be possible tosecure her support at the General Assembly to the course suggested and with thesupport of India the prospects of getting that course adopted would be verymaterially increased. It is particularly important that every effort should be madeto remove the differences of view at present prevailing between ourselves and canada.  Close Anglo-American co-operation would, of course, also be essential.15. The Australian Government are considering making a statement whichrefers to the apparent trend towards unilateral action, coupled with an appeal tothe nations not to prejudice the position pending further United Nations
consideration. What effect such a declaration would now have in view of the precedent set by Iceland I do not know, but I cannot conceive that such adeclaration made by Australia and supported by us could do any harm whatsoever.16.   My conclusions are therefore:  (a) at the next meeting of the General Assembly of the United Nations weshould(i) strongly support the proposal that a further Conference on the law of the Sea should be held, and .(ii) seek to secure agreement for the regional settlement of fisheryquestions; and(b) in the meanwhile the preparatory work should be put in hand as a matterof urgency and, in particular, arrangements should be made to discussthe questions involved with the other members of the Commonwealth.R. E. M.-B.Law Officers&apos; Department, W.C. 2,12th June, 1958.

</content>
</cab>
