<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/93/0 images: 340-343</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1958C. (58) 138 Copy No.   634th July, 1958CABINETGOVERNMENT INFORMATION services memorandum by the Chancellor of the Duchy of LancasterMy colleagues may like to have some account oi* the work that goes on inco-ordinating home and overseas information services.HOME2. At home the main instrument of co-ordination is the News Executive(formally, the Committee on Government Publicity), a meeting of chief information officers of home and overseas Departments held twice weekly under my chairmanship. This group, working on a confidential advance diary, discussesimpending Government announcements and members pool ideas about presentation.In this way we are able to draw on the corporate knowledge and experience ofthe information officers. Working groups have studied and reported on suchproblems as the relations between Press and television; the defence of the Pound;the ZETA story; Ministerial interviews at London Airport; publicity for Britishscientific and industrial achievements; working contacts with the B.B.C.; theprojection at home of the Commonwealth. There has been one study weekendfor information officers at Oxford.3. This group does not in any way usurp the responsibilities of theDepartments represented. But the pooling of facts and ideas helps to avoidclashes in timing of releases and apparent contradictions between Departmentalstatements. It also ensures that, where more than one Department is involved,there is full consultation and liaison.4. Much of my own work of keeping in close touch with the Press, theB.B.C. and the Independent Television Authority and with publicity organisationshas to be done sub rosa if it is to be worth while. Informal contacts based on goodpersonal relations are growing in number. Anonymity is essential to the successof this work. The Press generally seem to appreciate the efforts to ease andstimulate the flow of information.5. I hold a regular weekly meeting with the Lobby in supplement of theLord Privy Seal&apos;s regular weekly Lobby Conference and my colleagues&apos; periodicmeetings with the Lobby and maintain a steady contact with the Lobby betweenmeetings. The Prime Ministers public relations adviser (whose services I share)meets the Lobby daily and maintains a large number of other regular contacts with Press and broadcasting, both home and foreign. I hold regular meetings with the Commonwealth and Foreign Correspondents, and the &quot; inner group &quot;of the United States Correspondents in London. The arrangements for briefingForeign Correspondents have been strengthened and are now centred on fortnightlymeetings attended by officials and monthly meetings attended by Ministers. I amgrateful to so many of my colleagues for attending these meetings to talk about their own particular responsibilities. All these meetings are on an informal and&quot; wholly non-attributable &quot; basis.At their request I give suoh help as I can to my colleagues in their problems on presentation.53684
OVERSEAS6. In 1958-59 we expect to spend about  14-6 millions on the overseas information services. The cost without new projects will increase slightly in1959-60 and ultimately reach the ceiling of  15 millions, without allowing forany further rise in costs. This means that, while the ceiling remains, additional work however important can only be undertaken if the work now in progress iscut out. This issue has already arisen and will be the subject of a separate paper.7. Steady progress has been made in carrying out the programme ofdevelopment set out in the White Paper, Cmnd. 225. A problem has been the recruitment of suitable staff, particularly for the British Council, although the pace of this expansion has increased recently.   I append a progress report.8. The instruments for co-ordination of overseas information services area Ministerial Committee and an Official Committee, over which I preside. the ministerial Committee meets when necessary and the Official Committee fortnightly.9. In addition to the Estimates, these Committees have tackled a considerablerange of problems, including:  (i) the co-ordination of action by overseas Departments to give effect tothe White Paper decisions;(ii) the formulation of themes for the guidance of the overseas information services, and their translation into information material, particularlyabout Britain&apos;s economy and the Commonwealth in the world to-day;(iii) methods of assessing the impact of the information effort overseas andof improving the reporting on work done;(iv) the improvement of briefing and other facilities for overseas correspondentsin London;(v) recruitment and training of information staff;(vi) strengthening the popular appeal of United Kingdom broadcasting inArabic;(vii) better   co-ordination   of   publicity   overseas   for   Britain&apos;s   nuclearachievements.SOME VIEWS10. It may be useful to summarise some of the views of information officers on their work.Although the information officers job is to make widely known the aims and decisions of his Minister and the work of his Department it is not expected of him that he should do these things expressly for the purpose of securing support for the Government or any individual member of it. It is for Ministers and their part organisations to expound the political significance of Government action and to give it the appropriate political colour.11. The reputation and so the effectiveness of the official information services depends on the reliance which public and Press put on the objectivityof the material issued. Objectivity, like honesty, pays. It is this which gives thematerial issued a wide &quot; news-spread &quot; in the country.12. The standing of the information officer with the news gatherers (andtherefore his usefulness to his Department) depends largely on the extent ofconfidence which he enjoys with the Minister and his Department, and on hisknowing as a matter of course the background to policies and decisions. He shouldnot be left merely to pick up the bricks! The Press has no time for the officer who is obviously a mere buffer between them and the Department. The goodinformation officer brings to his Department the trend, the &quot; feel &quot; of public opinionoutside, and it is wise to bring him into the picture quite early to advise on the timing of statements, the media to be used and the form a statement should take,13. All the time the information officer is under pressure for facts much ofwhich are of a bread-and-butter character! A steady flow of material helps tokeep the Press away from mischief. Often he is instructed not to give information on a particular topic and he must use his skill to stave off enquiries. Sometimes,however, there is no good reason for this reticence, apart from a certain distastefor publicity in the Department. It is not always realised that an uninformed andsuspicious Press is more antagonistic than one which is given a flow of information.
SOME  REFLECTIONS14.   In conclusion, I would offer some of my own reflections based on thexperience gained in the last eighteen months.Government policy and its expression in Parliament and in Ministerial speeches and broadcasts are, of course, the raw material of our public relations work. Theyare the pegs on which the stories hang. Public relations are no substitute fordefinite policies and resolute decisions. They cannot make silk purses out of sows&apos;ears. They can make a good story better and a bad one less unattractive. Theycan help in preparing the ground for the release of bad news or in building up the impact of good news. They can kill wild and misleading stories. Perhaps, indeed,this is one of their most useful functions. But their raw material is news and morenews the harder the better.15. Press and public will not easily fall for mere propaganda. the temptation to mislead should be resisted as dangerous opportunism for which wealmost always pay in the end.16. The aim must be never to lose involuntarily the initiative in dealingwith public opinion. Yet, there are bound to be occasions when the Governmentappears to trail behind public opinion. Even if we cannot define our policy inexplicit terms, we can help ourselves by putting out as much relevant informationas possible.   It quietens if it does not quench.17. To leave a vacuum is to invite the Press to exercise its imagination.Whenever we leave the public in the dark for long about our intentions, thenewsmen are ready to step in and anticipate our plans and decisions in ways whichoften do us harm. The longer the opportunity for speculation before decisions are made or announced, the greater the risk that we shall be misunderstood. AGovernment may lose all credit for taking popular action because the Press claim that it was as a result of their pressure that the Government finally acted.18. Timing is extremely important. Although some totally unexpectedevent may swamp an important Government announcement, we usually benefit from careful attention to timing. Generally speaking it is best to put out badnews in one operation and to spread the good news.19. &quot; Security&quot; can be the bane of public relations work. Of course thereare occasions on which security interests must be accepted as over-riding the needsof good public relations. But before deciding on secrecy, let us be sure that thereare good reasons for it.20. We tend to say for *&apos; non-attribution &quot; what can safely be said &quot; on the record.&quot; And the &quot; on the record &quot; quote is much more likely to get a good Pressthan the story which cannot be attributed to a source or better still to a Minister.Whenever possible we should choose the &quot; on the record &quot; method.21. In giving confidential information to the Press, we should beware of putting too much meat in front of the tiger. The newspaper man&quot;s job is to get news and publish it. That and nothing else. To entrust a newspaper man with a really&quot; hot &quot; secret is both unfair to him and dangerous.22. Any important statement for domestic consumption is quickly taken upabroad, in Commonwealth and foreign countries. A classic example perhaps is inthe economic policy field where a warning note sounded for home consumptioncan so quickly lead to dangerous speculation abroad. It is worth while to consider in advance the possible overseas repercussion of primarily domestic announcements.23. And, finally, let us never forget the value of persistence. There are manyways of saying the same thing and, providing we say it in a lively and interestingway, it will always have a good chance of getting into the news on its merits.C. H.Office of the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster, S.W. 1.1st July, 1958.
AppendixPROGRESS OF IMPLEMENTATION OF PROPOSALS OF CMND. 225Commonwealth Relations OfficeNew information posts have been opened at Winnipeg, Edmonton and Salisburyand one will be opened shortly at Penang. Additional staff have been or will shortly be appointed to Brisbane, Accra, Kuala Lumpur, Karachi and the posts in India. Additional British Council staff have been or are being appointed to ceylon, New Delhi, Dacca, Karachi and South Africa. A number of subsidisedteaching posts have been filled.2. The headquarters organisation at Commonwealth Relations Office hasbeen expanded and raised to divisional status.Colonial Office3. New information posts have been opened at Dar-es-Salaam and Singapore.Plans are in hand for a new British Council centre at Hcng Kong and additional information officers and British Council staff are being appointed to Nigeria. Itis planned to open a British Council centre at Fort Portal, LIganda in 1959-60.Foreign Office4. New or additional information appointments have been or will shortly be made to Burma, Czechoslovakia, Morocco, Persian Gulf, Poland and Tunisia.Film vans are being supplied to Indonesia and the Persian Gulf.Central Office of Information5. The London Press Service is being expanded and improved. The Arabicmagazine, Al Aalam, was enlarged in November 1957 and is again being expanded.The print order is to be increased to an eventual 100,000 if justified by demand.The enlarged magazine Commonwealth Today, which now incorporates Today,has a circulation of 304,000 in 11 languages. The supply of films for televisionis being increased tc not less than one hour a week for territories served. About150 United States television stations use British official material regularly. Thereis a new feature series for Canada, a monthly news service with Spanish commentaryfor 11 Latin American countries, and another monthly newsreel, with Arabiccommentary, is distributed in the Middle East. Stock and background films andnews items are being distributed. The tours programme has been expanded.A more specialised service of photographs is being provided for overseas posts.All reference papers and pamphlets are now printed.British Council6. A pension scheme has been introduced, and the CounciPs Headquartersoffice is being enlarged. The Councils work in caring for students and othervisitors is increasing. Teaching of English is being expanded in Afghanistan,Brazil, Burma, Chile, Ethiopia, Indonesia, Iran, Lebanon, Libya, Mexico, Thailand,Turkey and Colonial territories. In many of these countries, extra teachingstaff have been appointed. More books and other information material arebeing sent out to British Council posts.British Broadcasting Corporation7. The Sound Transcription Service is being expanded, and news services are being made more specialised. Russian, Polish, Hausa, Swahili and Somaliservices have been expanded. Certain European language services have beencurtailed or abolished.  Work on the Capital Re-Equipment Programme has begun.

</content>
</cab>
