<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/192/1 images: 3-7</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government cp(76) 7620 September 1976CHILD BENEFITMemorandum by the Secretary of State for education and Science and Paymaster GeneralINTRODUCTION1.        At their meeting on 29 July the Cabinet indicated that they would wish to consider the full implications of the recommendations the a expected from tike Working Party set up by the Labour Party/Trades Union Congress(TUC) Liaison Committee to look at ways of phasing in the full child benefit(CB) scheme.    The same day a statement was issued by the Working Partyrecording the agreement reached.   A copy is annexed.    The Ministerialrepresentatives on the Working Party were the Chief Secretary, treasury and the then Minister of State, Department of Health and Social Security.It will be seen from the statement that the agreement was ad referendum tothe principal parties concerned.    In the debate on the CB Regulations on30 July the Secretary of State for Social Services said no more than that theGovernment would consider the proposals &quot;urgently and carefully&apos;1.PHASING-IN SCHEME2.        At their meeting on 16 September the Social Services committee agreed with the recommendations made by the Secretary of State for social services and the Chief Secretary, Treasury that the Working party  s scheme should be accepted as the most practicable way of enabling us to move forward to the full CB scheme to which we remained committed.   An early decision by the Government is necessary.    We shall certainly be expected to announce the outcome of our consideration before the Party Conference this month.Firm decisions by the end of September are also essential in order to allow the Inland Revenue to undertake the autumn PA YE recoding exercise.3.        The Working Party&apos;b scheme provides for the phasing -in of the fullCB scheme in 3 stages by April 1979.    CB would be made tax-free inApril 1977 by removing tax and clawback and financing this by an equivalentreduction in child tax allowances (CTAs) (The equivalent reduction would be 104 for first and only children,  130 for other children.    CTAs for 1977-78would thus be reduced from their current levels of  300,  335 and  365(depending on age) to  195*  230 and  260 (depending on age) for first and only children and  170.  205 and  235 for other children.).    This wouldCOPY NO      o 1CABINET1
involve no addition to the net exchequer cost of CB in 1977-78 and have nofurther effect on take-home pay (the 7Op reduction as a result of tax andclawback on the new payment for the first child under the present arrange-ment would instead result from the equivalent reduction in CTAs).    Theremaining CTAs for children under 11 would then be withdrawn, and those for older children correspondingly reduced, over the following Z years;the precise amount in each year could be considered later in the light ofprevailing circumstances.    The resultant increase in revenue would betransferred, as originally conceived, to the tax-free CB rate.   As will beseen from the Working party  s statement, the TUC and Labour Partyrepresentatives made it clear that they would expect additional sums above and beyond the revenue transferred from the withdrawal of CTAs to be allocated to the CB rate in 1978 and 1979.    The Government representatives,however, gave no commitment and this would remain to be considered at theappropriate time in the context of our wider public expenditure policies.4.        The scheme will fall well short of the full implementation at one movewhich we had originally intended and to which the TUC strongly objected onaccount of the take-home pay implications.    Its adoption may be criticised as a further change of mind, but the change is on the part of the TUC as muchas of the Government and the phasing -in arrangements are a sensible way of meeting the genuine fears which were expressed about political reactions tothe reductions in take-home pay.    It is significant that the TUC are nowwilling to accept the arrangements in April 1977 described above which theyrejected prior to the announcement by the Government on 25 May that theCB scheme in its original form would be postponed and that instead &amp; new 1 benefit, subject to tax and clawback, would be introduced from April 1977for the first child.    The scheme would commit the Inland Revenue to majorrecodings in the autumns of 1977 and 1978, involving 1000 and 2000 staffrespectively which are not at present provided for in PESC.    But this is an inevitable feature of any phasing-in scheme.CONSEQUENTIAL PROBLEMS5.        The Social Services Committee also reached conclusions onconsequential problems relating to non-resident children, students, widows and certain other recipients of taxable child dependency benefits and ChildInterim Benefit (CHIB) beneficiaries who pay tax.    Of these the main problems are the first two.NON-RESIDENT CHILDREN6.        There are estimated to be about 500, 000 children abroad for whomchild allowances are payable but who, generally speaking, will not be entitledto CB.    In previous discussions of this controversial issue the majority viewof Ministers was that some compensation through transitional CTAs would benecessary to avoid being less than fair to a section of the immigrantcommunity.    This was, however, in the context of the scheme providing forthe withdrawal of the full value of CTAs at the under eleven rate at once.Under the Working Party&apos;e phasing scheme the effects in any one year would2
be much less acute cince CTAs would be phased out gradually over threeyears.    For example, the reductions proposed for 1977-78 would still leave CXAs at an amount considerably higher than the estimated average level of remittances to a family in the Indian sub-continent ( 68 annuallyto cover both wife and children).7.        The Social Services Committee agreed by a majority that CTAsfor the parents of non-resident children should be phased out over 3 years from April 1977 on the same basis as for other parents.    The division ofview centred on the political consequences of making no special concessionfor non-resident children.    It was argued on the one hand that the majorityof immigrant families with genuine non-resident children, not all of whom were from the Indian sub-continent, would strongly resent the withdrawal ofCTAs without any concession, particularly when they would be given littlenotice of the first stage of the withdrawal, and when CB would not be paid to inon-resident children.    The majority view, on the other hand, was that greater racial disharmony would be caused by the differences in take-homepay which a transitional period for the retention of CTAs in full would involveand that this in any case would be likely only to defer the resentment of immigrants at the loss of CTAs.    Although the effects of withdrawing CTAswere difficult to predict, it was thought that their phasing out would probably in practice not lead to great pressures for the admission to this country ofthe children concerned.    There was considerable support in the Committee,however, for a suggestion that if CTAs were phased out over 3 years theHome Office should consider the possibility of instituting special proceduresto give priority for entry to the children of those families who would suffergenuine hardship from the withdrawal of CTAs without the compensation of CB.STUDENTS8,        CB, like family allowances, will cease for students when they reach the age of 19.    CTAs, on the other hand, are at present given for all studentsin full-time education or training up to any age.    In the Working Party&apos;sBcheme the reduction in CTAs would therefore represent a loss for the families of students aged 19 or over unless they were compensated in someother way.   As the purpose of the CB scheme is to simplify the system of family support, we have considered how to compensate these familiesthrough the existing system of student grants and not through the tax systemor any new organisation.    Also, In accordance with the decision which ministers reached at an earlier stage, we have assumed that there should be acommon regime of support for all students on advanced courses regardless of age,9.        The basic options considered by Social Services Committee were toreduce the parental contributions to the student maintenance grant by anamount at least equal to the cash value (at the basic rate of tax) of the CTAto be phased out or to make an equivalent addition, i. e.  105 by the third yearto the cash value of the maintenance grant for all eligible students and to leavethe scale of parental contributions unaltered.    Neither of these options wouldprovide compensation for a small number of students, perhaps 16, 000 or3
3 per cent of the total, who are In higher education but are not eligible fora mandatory grant, eg because they already had one for a degree course,or who are in non-advanced further education but do not have a discretionarygrant.10.       The Committee decided in favour of the option of reducing parentalcontributions because it is in this area that the greatest student hardship atpresent lies: a recent survey has shown that of the 70 per cent of students who should be receiving a parental contribution, two-thirds get less than thefull amount; and inflation has brought into this category many ordinaryfamilies who genuinely cannot afford the contributions.    But 1 propose toexamine, in consultation with the Chief Secretary, Treasury, the possibilityof uBing some of the savings from the withdrawal of CTAs from the parentsof students in order to provide some relief for those parents whose incomesfall between the tax threshold and the starting point of parental contributions and who otherwise would not be compensated for the loss of CTAs.COST11.       The cost of these consequential arrangements, together with thedecisions taken by Social Services Committee on the relatively minorproblems posed by the treatment of widows and CHIB beneficiaries, would keep the overall net exchequer cost of phasing-in the full CB scheme in1977-78 (approximately  70 million) well within the figure of about 95 million which was estimated for the Governments decision in May tointroduce a  1 benefit, with tax and clawback, for the first child.CONCLUSION12. I invite the Cabinet to endorese the recommendations of Social service committee that -a. the proposals of the Labour Party/TUC Working Party forphasing-in the full CB scheme from April 1977 should be accepted without any commitment to increased expenditure on the CB rateover and above the equivalent of the revenue transferred from thewithdrawal of CTAs;b. the consequential arrangements for non-resident children and for students should be as described in paragraphs 7 and 10above; andc. an announcement should be made in time for the party conference next week.S w department of Education and Science20 September 1976
ANNEXCHILD BENEFIT SCHEMEStatement issued on 29 July 19761.        The Joint Working Party have considered ways of phasing-in the fullintroduction of the Child Benefit Scheme within the lifetime of this parliament.    This statement records the views of the Working Party in thelight of their discussions.    The views are, of course, ad referendum by the tuc representatives to the TUC General Council, by the Labour Partyrepresentatives to the Parliamentary Labour Party and National ExecutiveCommittee, and by the Ministerial representatives to the Government.2.        The Working Party are agreed in principle that the objective shouldbe to phase-in  he full Child Benefit Scheme by 1979 on the following basis:-i.       By making Child Benefits free of tax and clawback inApril 1977 and reducing Child Tax Allowances by an equivalentamount (mis would have no further effect on take -home pay).ii.       By withdrawing the remaining Child Tax Allowances overthe following two years and converting the net resources thusreleased into increases to the tax-free child benefit rate.3.        In this way substantial progress towards eliminating Child tax allowances would be achieved without any further effect on take-home pay in1977 and Child Benefit itself would, as originally intended, be made tax free;and the full Child Benefit scheme would have been introduced by 1979.4.        The Working Party akcnowledges that no extra resources beyond thenext Exchequer cost of some  95 million already committed by theGovernment will be made available in 1977-78.    The TUC and Labour Partyrepresentatives, however, believe that it will be necessary to allocatedadditional resources from the Exchequer to increase the Child Benefit ratein 1978 and 1979.    For their part the Ministerial representatives have made it clear that while no commitment can be given about the additional resources to be made available they will advise the Government that the TUC and theLabour Party representatives expect the Government to accept that mere is a financial commitment in the agreement reached on the phasing -in of thescheme as it concerns the overall level of family support in those years.5.        The Working Party agreed to recommend to the Liaison Committeethat the Working Party should continue in existence to review progress withthe introduction of the scheme.5

</content>
</cab>
