<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/3/12 images: 104-113</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M.   (59) 25rd CONCLUSIONS:    MINUTE 5.Confidential Annex.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR WAR informed the War Cabinet that, since the Memorandum (W.P.(39) 44)had been submitted, he had received a message fromGeneral Camelin, to the effect that the sector to beheld by the Field Force would have to be changed.      Thenew sector would be between - the Lys and the Scheldt.      Therehad not been much time to examine this change, but itappeared that the new sector would be satisfactory fromthe British point of view.      General Gamelin had also asked that the sentence on page 2 of the Note of the conversations between M. Daladier, General Gamelin,Mr.  Hore-Belisha,  and Lord Hankey, at the Ministry ofWar on 20th September,  to the effect that he had no information that &quot;any such withdrawal&quot; (from the Polishfront)&quot; had yet commenced&quot;, should be amended by theaddition of the words &quot;on a large scale&quot;.Some discussion followed regarding thepreparation of the line to be held by the Franco-british forces on the Belgian frontier.      It was suggested thatthe measures being taken by the French to organise anddig their part of the line were not adequate.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said that theFrench proposed to occupy the line to the right end leftof the British with divisions from their mass of manoeuvre.The French fully intended.,  if they were able to have priorconversations with the Belgians, to advance into Belgium

to the line of the Scheldt.      This line had not beenprepared, and Lord Gort did not think it was a very good line to hold.      In any case,  the British army would stand on the line which was being taken up.There was no Haginot Line along the frontfrom Givet to the coast;    there was, however, a continuous anti-tank obstacle, and a number of fortsand pill-boxes.THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL staff pointed out that the British had not yet been able somuch as to reconnoitre their.line,  as their sector hadnot been fixed until the previous day and, in fact,had been changed since then.      Lord Gort fully intendedto reconnoitre and prepare the line at the earliestpossible moment and would then be able to visit theFrench on his right and left and concert arrangements.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said thatarrangements were being made to send over mechanicaldiggers with the special crews attached to them.Lord Gort had asked that any additional personnel sentover should be, not labour units, but additionalFighting Troops .w. ho. would be able not only to dig,but also to fight, if required.      The War Office were examining the possibility of sending over such rein-forcements and were consulting the Admiralty about the ports which might be used, so as not to Interfere withthe flow of the Field Force.      It was contemplated thatthe orders given for three further battalions to besent to Egypt would be countermanded, and. the battalionssent to France instead.

THE WAS CABINET then considered the summary on pages 1 and 2 of W.P.   (39) 44.Paragraph 2.      It was generally agreed thatit was extremely unlikely that either the Dutch orBelgian Governments would be willing to carry outextensive demolitions on their frontiers,  at least until there were concentrations on their frontiers._      Paragraph 5. ^fTHE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY.nf ormed the War Cabinet that preparations were well advanced for operations to block the Belgian ports andto destroy the locks.      If, however, the neutrality of holland were violated, no effective action could betaken towards blocking Dutch ports, since there were so many possible points of egress.Paragraph 7.    THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WARsaid that the War Office were taking up with theMinistry of Supply, the questions raised in this paragraph.The need for certain articles of equipment, particularlyanti-tank mines, had been found to be more urgent than had previously been thought, especially as the french had asked for the return of mines which they had lent us.THE WAR CABINET took note of theMemorandum.fb*- hu^ttc UfiilLevIr &quot;^A*fyU&apos;o

5r*MOST SECRET .W.M. (39)  25 rd CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 6.CONFIDENTIAL ANNEX TO W.P.(59) 48.(Reference W.P.(59) 48, Page 6.)55        55        55        55        55        55   .    55Gold Converting these figures into weight of gold,Reserves.the Chancellor said that 18 months ago we had 120million ounces.   On the 2nd September, 1939, this had dropped to 53 million ounces.   The loss wasoccasioned by the departure of refugee money andby our adverse balance of trade.   At the beginningof the war in 1914 we had something under 40 millionounces of gold, rather less than at present, butthe purchasing value of the gold in 1914 was higher.55        55        55        55        55        55        55Richmond Terrace, S.W.1.




</content>
</cab>
