<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/23/0 images: 220-226</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUKEMT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; 8 GO VEHEMENT)3 E 0 HE T.FIJI AX COPY No.CABINET    6P( 04CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet,held at 10 Downing St., S.W.I., cn ThursdayDecember 9, 1920, at 1-15 p.miPEE sent the prime Minister (in the Chair).fie Right Hon. lord Birkenhead.Lord Chancellor.ae Right Hon. E.Shortt, ,M.P,Secretary of State for Home.Affairs.The Right Bon. The Earl Curzon ofXedleston, ,&amp;.c. S.I.,G.C.I.E., Secretary of Statefer Foreign Affairs.The Eight Hon. R.Mirnro&apos;, F.C.M.P., Secretary for Scotland.The Right Hen. Sir Haner greenwood,Bart, ,11.C. ,M.P.,Chief Seere-t&amp;ry for Ireland.The Right Hen. Sir Robert Home,G.B.B. ,di, C ,M.P.,Presidentof the Board of Trade,The Right Hon.the Viscount Milner,G.C.B. ,G.C.M.G.,  Secretary ofState f*r the Colonies.The Right Hon. vV.3. Churchill,M.F.Secretary of State for War andAir.The Right Hon. S.3. Montagu, M.P.Secretary ef State for India.The Right Hen. c.Addison, M,P,minister of Health.The Eight Hon. Sir Eric geddes,G..G.B. ;-fi./B.E. ,M.P., Ministerof Transport.The Right Hon. Lord Lee cf parehamG.B.3.,H.C.B., Minister ofAgriculture and fisheries.The Eight Hon. Sir Earningfrerthirgton Evans, Bari,M.P,Theg following wer g a lsp^ pre sentGeneral the Right Hon. Sir NevilMacready, G. C.M.G. ,K. O.B. ,CoQfflanding the Forces InIreland.f/The Eight Hon. Sir John Andersen,$ LCB., Joint Under-Se ere taryI for Ireland.&apos;Lieut.Cel. Sir M.P.A ..HankeyT G.C.B.Mr, R.B.Howcrth.        E.&apos;i        .. .     secreAssistant   Secre
(1) With reference to Cabinet 65 (30) % Conclusion 2, anemergency meeting of., the Cabinet ^as held to consider theFein.&apos;replies to be sent to the recent approaches from Sinn Fein.The Cabinet had before them draft repliestwhich hadbeen prepared by the Irish Government,. to .the telegram fromFather 0;r:Fla.nagan,. and also to the communicatinn from theGalway County Council.The discussion centred mainly en the question cfwhether or not the members ef Dail Eireann whb ,had been oon^nested with crime should be permitted to attend a meeting ofDail Eireann, and, if not, whether those members to whom safeconducts could not be given should be mentioned by name.a        In the course of the discussion if transpired that outof 78 original members of Dail Eireann, 2 were dead, 1 was ina lunatic asylum., 11 were in custody, and 6 in the UnitedStates of America,,After- some, discus sign --The Cabinet approved the draft replies to Pathor 0VFlanagan and the GalwayCounty Council, in the form specifiedi&apos;ft Appendicss I and .11 respectively.Maroation        (2) The &quot;Prime Minister read to the Cabinet - Partial(i) The draft of a Proclamation of martial Law,covering the South-West corner of Ireland;and(ii) fha dra^t of a Proclamation to be issuedby the Military Governors in the proclaimeddistricts immediately after the publicationby the Lord Lieutenant of the Proclamationof &quot;martial Law,,Both these documents had been prepared by the Irish Government,and it was proposed that, simultaneously with the publicationof the replies to Father 0*Flanagan and the Galway CountyCouncil, the Martial Law Proclamation should be made.The Cabinet were informed that the area covered by the proclamation corresponded with the Military AdministrativeDivision of the Province of funster.
of the discussion it transpired thatthe-County cf ^at-rrford was at the room on t peaceatls.The Cabinet agreed  (a) ?.e approve the two Draft Proclamations,subject to the exclusion of the county of laterford.(Per the ,tprma,.jft,f .the a -.proved.,lh?oelayejr-tions^ sea.. Appendices III &amp; XVh)(b) That, in answer to a Private Notice question to be asked in the House of Commons that afternoon, the Prime &apos;Minister should informthe House of Commons of the terms of the replies sent to Sinn Fein,, and the general lines of the Martial Law Proclamation,without, however, specifying the area/ tobe affected by the Proclamation beyondindicating that it would cover certaindisturbed districts.(c) That,in the event of outrages occurringin districts not covered, by the Proclama-tion, the Irish&apos;Government should have authority to extend Martial Law to those districts without furtbmr reference tothe Cabinet.(d) That any members of Dail Eireann whom the- Irish Government decided might properly be released from custody, for the purposeof attending a meeting of Dail Eireann,should be rewarded as freed and should notbe liable to re-arrest unless they suose-^uently committed &quot;sor:. e new criminal act.2, Whitehall Gardens,  S.&quot;-r. 1,Pec cither 9, 19-30.
A P P E N D I X     I.I have received your message.   His Majesty&apos;s government does net lag &quot;behind any section *,f the Irish people in thedesire that Ireland should enjoy to the full the blessingsof peace and prosperity.    We are prepared to afford facili-tie.s for the free disonasisn of the whele situation by theduly elected representatives cf constituencies in Ireland orany part of Ireland,    There ares however * certain individuals who are gravely implicated in the comiaeicn ef crime so serious that the Government cannot consent to abandon theirelementary duty of bringing such persons to trial,    To all members except these individuals a safe conduct will begranted by the Government.    It should be clearly understoodthat His Majesty&apos;s Government must insist that effective measures be taken to ensure the cessation of murder and other3rimes ef violence and the surrender of all arms unlawfullyheld.    I have in the House of Commons on the 16th of august and on several subsequent occasions defined the fundamentalconditions to *hiqh any political settlement must conform.His Majesty&apos;s Government adhere absolutely to those condi-tions and would be glad to learn that the party which yourepresent are prepared to accept them..  .  .   *
2 d 0A..P PEN? IX     II.To The Secretary,Oalway&apos; County Council,Dear Sir,I have received your letter of the 4th Instant forwardingcopy ef a Resolution paused by the Galway County Council, andwish to assure your Council that the Government welcome everyindication m the part of representative persons and bodies inIreland ef a desire/te&apos; co*-operate in bringing to an end thepresent unhappy state of lawlessness and ensuring a return teconstitutional methods in that country,,Tha first necessary preliminary to the re-establishment of normal conditions is that murder and crimes of violence shall cease.    It is to that end that the efforts cf the Irish Exeeu-tive-have been constantly directed, and until it has been attained no progress can be made towards a political settlement the Government are prepared to facilitate the meetingtogether for this purpose *)f persons duly elected tc- representconstituencies in Ireland or any partif Ireland,    There are,however, certain individuals who are gravely implicated in thecommission ef crime so serious that the Government cannotconsent to abandon their elementary duty of bringing such,persons to trial.    To all members except these individualsa safe conduct will be granted by the Government.&apos; It shouldbe clearly understood that His Majesty&apos;s Government mustinsist that effective measures be fahen to ensure the cessation-tion of murder and other crimes of violence and the surrender of all arms unlawfully held,I would add that the Government hav* learnt with satis fac-tion of the action of your Council in submitting their accountsto audit by the Local Government Board and that the fullestsupport can be assured to every local authority which loyallycarries out its obligations under the law,Yo\:rs faithfully,(Sd.) Do LLOYD GEORGE.
A P.r E I! D I X     ITT.If?P.R 0 0 L A M A T 1 0 N.WHEREAS certain evilly disposed persons and associations &apos;with the intent to subvert the supremacy of the Grown inIreland have committed divers acts of violence whereby many persons, including members of-the Forces of the Crown andother servants of His Majesty have been murdered and many others have suffered grievous Injuries and much destructionof property has been caused   AND WHEREAS in certain parts ofIreland disaffection and unrest have been especially prevalentand repeated murderous attacks have been made upon members ofHis Majesty&apos;s Forces Culminating in the ambush, massacre andmutilation with axes of sixteen Cadets of the AuxiliaryDivision all of whom had served in the late War by a large body of men wearing trench helmets and dressed in khaki uni-forcas who are still at largeNOW. I   JOHN DENTON PINKSTONE VISCOUNT FRENCH Lord Lieuten-ant General and General Governor of Ireland do hereby proclaimby virtue of all the powers me thereunto enabling that thefollowing&apos;counties namelyCORKTIPPERARYKERRYLIMERICKare and until further order shall continue to be under andsubject toM A R T -I A L     LAWANP) I do hereby       call on all loyal and well-affectedsubjects of the Grown to aid in upholding and maintaining the peace of this Realm and the supremacy and authority ofthe Crown and to- obey and conform to all orders and regu- -lations of the Military Authority issued by virtue of thisProclamation.Given at His Majesty&apos;s Castle of Dublinthis , day of December, 1930.*****      o
APPENDIX     IV.PR6C LAMATI0 N   No -1-THE, MILITARY GOVBRNOR-GB^RAL SF    I RE LA ED.MARTIAL law Has been declared in the counties of Cork.,Tipperary, Kerry, and LimerickiITliSHMENlUnderstand tbis:Great Britain had no quarrel with Irishmen;   her sole quar-rel Is with crime, outrage and disorder;    her shle object indeclaring MARTIAL LAW is to restore peace to a distracted andunhappy country;   her se-le enemies are those who have counten-a need, inspired, and participated in rebellion, murder andoutrageIt is to pxit an end, once and for all, to this campaign of outrage that MARTIAL LAW has been declared.MILITARY GOVERNORS are hereby appointed for the administra-tion of MARTIAL LAW,  and all persons will render obedience totheir orders in all matters whatsoever,N&amp;TE THIS:(a) All arms, ammunition and explosives in possessionof any person not a member of His Majesty&apos;s Naval,Military, Air or Police Farces, or who is not inpossession of a permit, will be surrendered by......to such persons and at such places as may be noti-fied in each locality,(b) After ........ any unauthorised person found inpossession of arms, ammunition or explosives, willbe liable, on conviction, by a Military Court, to suffer DEATH.(c) Any unauthorised person wearing the uniform or equip-ment of His Majesty&apos;s Naval, Military, Air, or police forces, or wearing similar clothing likely to deceive,will be liable on conviction to suffer DEATH, and anyperson in possession of such uniform, clothing, orequipment will be liable on conviction to sufferpenal servitude.(d) N*TR SELL&apos;:That a state of armed insurrection exists,,  thatany person taking part therein *r procuring, inviting,aiding or abetting any other person to do so, orharbouring any such person, is guilty of levying warasainst His Majesty The King, and is liable on eon.....viction to .suffer DEATH*(s)       All law courts, corporations, councils and boardsare hereby directed to continue to carry out their functions until otherwise ordered,(f)       The Forces of the Grown in Ireland are herebydeclared to be on active service.Gorruander-in-Chief The Forces in Ireland.

</content>
</cab>
