<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/23/0 images: 323-332</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This. Document..p*g... the.PropprtX-SlLPis BritannicJ^h^stj^s^CJCTr^snt., jsecretFINAL-COPY Mo,CABINET 75  (3Oi.CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in Mr Ponar Law&apos;;.;&apos;Room,, House of Commons, S/Sd,&apos; on THURSDAY, DECEMBER S3, 1920,at 4 p.-,m.pgr? gVJjrp * ...Tho Prime Minister (in the Chair).Hie Right Hon. A. Boaar Law, M,?4 The Right Hen, A,J. Balfour, 0-M*fLl.P^Lord Privy Seal. H Lord President of the Council, iThe Right Hon. Ad Chamberlain,     1 The High-. Hon. E, Short tr, K00, ,&apos;M.P.MVP., Chancellor of the I Secretary of State for HomeExoheauer. I        Affarms, VThe Right Hon. FLS, Montagu, M*P.,A The Right Hon. WiS, Churchill, Mm P.,Secretary of State for India..  Secretary of State for War and Air.The Right Hon. Sir Hamar Greenwro\j The Right hon C; Addison, MCP,,.Bart, ,K.C. .-M P,d Chief Secre-4        Minister of Health.-tary for Ireland.The Right Hon.- Sir Robert Home, G,B.E. yThe Right Hon.  Sir E, Goddes, K,0. ,M.?.-, President of the BoardG.G.B. jGJcE, ,M.&apos;P., Minister \ of Trade,of Transport.                            iI The Right Hon. Lord Lee of fareham,The Right Hon. T.J. Macn.am.ara,      1 GoBcEe ,K.C.B., Minister of Agri-M.P., Minister of Labouim       * culture and Fisheries,al the Right Hon. H,A.L, Fisher.; MCP^ The Right Hen. Sir L, Worthington Evans,;President of the Board of       *        Barf.. ,M.P.Education.        ______,____________f_____^_______._____The following were also present:-Sir Eyre A&apos;. Crowe, CCivbfi,,;K,.CBJ The Rmglm Eon, Sir Gordon Hewart, K*C,,Permanent Under-Secretary of 1 m.p.., /Attorney-General (For Conolu-State for Foreign Affairs       J        slens 1 &amp; 2;(For Conclusions 1, 2 &amp; 4).Sir Malcolm DeleVingne, E-.C-.B.-, Assist-ant Under--Secretary of State for home Affairs (For Conclusions 1 A 8)JL-_-Lieutenant-Colonel Sir k. P.A.&apos;. Hankey, G.C.3., Seei*etary,Mr Thomas Jones, Principal Assistant Secretary.
(1) ^ &quot;Cabinet had before them the following documents:-iTION. *   Memoranda by the Minister of Laboury&quot;   . (Papers CMP,-S115 and C.P.-SP29),de cf Rati- A Mote by the Home Secretary, coveringcation of a Memorandum, by Sir Malcolm Delevlngnemention. (Paper C.P.--S85B),The Cabinet were reminded that Article 405 of theTreaty of Versailles provided that when a Draft convention is adopted by the requisite majority at a General Conferenceof Members of the International Labour Organisation, suchDraft Convention must, normally within a period of one year,be brought &quot;before the, authority or authorities within whosecompetence the matter lies,for the enactment of legislation or other action&quot;.    In the case of the Washington International- -Labour Conference the period of IS months, within which each state must take action, expires on the 27th January next.It was therefore necessary to establish a procedure forratifying (or declining to ratify) the several Draft convention-tions adopted at Washington.Divergent views were held as to what body constitutedthe &quot;competent authority&quot; under Article 405.   Was it theexecutive Government, or was it Parliament?    In the event ofthe executive Government not wishing to ratify a Convention.;was it obliged eo submit -the matter to the House of commons and possibly be ov^r-ruled by its decision?It was pointed out that, according to the constitu-tional practice of this country. Parliament was not theTreaty-making authority, but the Crown, and the approvalof Parliament was not required for the ratification of aTreaty with a foreign Power, - .At this stage the Attorney-General entered, and was invited to give his opinion upon Article 405.Sir.Gordon Hewart stated that under Article 405 therewas an undertaking on the part of each member of theInternational Labour Organisation to bring each. Draft Con-
 lies for the enactment of legislation or other action. It was important to read this in the light of the French text, which was as follows:-

"Chacun des Membres s&apos;engage à soumettre dans le délai.... la recommandation ou le project de convention à l&apos;autorité ou aux autorités dans la compétence desquelles rentre la matière, en vue de la transformer en loi ou de prendre des mesures d&apos;un autre ordre."

In Sir Gordon Howart&apos;s Opinion this Clause did not make something else the authority which was not the authority before, and in this country the authority was the Crown. It was, therefore, in his opinion, not necessary to submit Draft Conventions to Parliament for ratification, but they could be dealt with the Executive.

It was pointed out that the interpretation of the Clause as applied to the constitution of this country, as advised by the Attorney General, was not the same in all countries, and would probably be challenged in Parliament. The arguments in Sir Malcolm Delevingne&apos;s Memorandum (Paper G.P.-2252) as to the reasons of policy in favour of the opposite view were developed at some length. The matter might be pressed to the extent of taking it before the International Court of Justice when that Court was set up. It was further suggested that it would be desirable to make an announcement of the British interpretation in Parliament.

The Cabinet took note of the interpretation placed upon Article 4?5 by the Attorney-General, and agreed that, as a consequence, it was unnecessary to bring before Parliament, by resolutions or otherwise, those Draft Conventions which the Government decided not to ratify.



President ? 1921 Conference.



The Cabinet took a favourable view of the proposal that the British representatives should endeavour to secure the nomination of The Right Hon. G.N. Barnes, M.P., as President of the International Labour Conference of 1921.

British Liaison Organisation.



The Cabinet had before them the following Papers:-



A Memorandum by the Secretary to the Cabinet, covering letters from Sir Malcolm Delevingne (Paper C.P.-2023),

A Memorandum by Sir Montague Barlow and Mr Hipwood (Paper C.P.-2057),

 A Note by the Home Secretary, Covering a Memorandum from Sir Malcolm Delevingne (Paper C.P.-2251).

The Cabinet concurred in the proposals set forth in the Memorandum on International Labour Office Organisation (Paper C.P.?2067), viz.:-


3 OS(a) That the Ministry of Labour should be thecentre^ at which all the work connected withthe International Labour Bureau and the(V(c)Interne, tronal Labour Conference should become-ordinated.    The documents should all be filed there, and the Ministry of labour should be the channel of correspondence with and through which ether GovernmentDepartments should communicate:That the Ministry of Labour should fore&quot;! a council or Committee, with a Minister atthe head., and of which the members shouldbe the chief Permanent Officials of theHome Office (including Sir Malcolm Dele-vingne), the Board of Trade, the Ministryof Shipping for the time being,  the Ministryof Agriculture and any other Departmentinterested in Labour questions:That there should be a Branch at the labour ministry responsible for this internationalwork, which should warn each Government;Department of international Labour matters affecting that Department as they arise,it should see that the decisions of pastConferences are dealt with, and should prepare in advance for future Conferences.LEAGUE ofMTIGNS.The Inter-national LabourOffice andnationalFinance,(2) The Cabinet had before them the following documents a Memorandum by the Chancellor of theExchequer (Paper CP......2170),A Memorandum by the Minister of LabourPaper CP.-2239) ,A Note by the Home Secretary (paper cp.-2-353) .The attention of the Cabinet was directed, to theambitious esc ale on which tho development of the Inter-national Labour office was being planned, and the conee-quent heavy burden of expense which would fail upon thecontributing authorities,    The Britxsh representative onthe Governing Body of the International Labour hffice hueestimated the expenses of the Office for 1931.....32 at behwee; 350,000 and  370,000.    The Council of the League offlation.had no control over the decisions of the Finance Corijribf.eeof the Labour Office,, or ever the total estimate- for itsbudget.    There was evidence that the Director M. th..; 0 -hueOffice contemplated the-Initiation of widespread onquieJ ....
That British delegates should not assent toany expenditure (except o&quot;fa quite triflingkind to which the maxim of de mqnimisu mightapply) without, authority from their D%partrrents.It was understood that these instructions should not apply to ifckndeters attending thein nany countries .into.industrial,matters, 7 These-^nquiriaa,would not onl, in themselves cost lar-e suras o*&quot; money&apos;  but would in effect duplicate the investigations already beingcarried out by the Minis trie s of Labour in the several countries.    If this practice were allowed tc develop uncheek-ed we should presently be confronted with a &quot;Fourth Inter-national&quot; which would seek to undermine the executive Govem-ments by appealing over their heads to the people.It was pointed out, on the other hand, that from theinternational standpoint there was much to be said in supportof the programme outlined by 1*1. Thomas for his Office.    Hisavowed aim was to level Up industrial conditions in the Fostbackward countries to a stage nearer those which obtained inthe more advanced countries.    From this standpoint we in thiscountry had everything to gain, menaced as we were by thedumping of goods produced abroad under sweated conditions.The conditions obtaining in some of the backward and unsettledcountries, such as Russia or Roumania, were such as to makeit undesirable to confine industrial enquiries within officialchannels in those countries.    It had further to be rememberedthat on the Governing Tody there were representatives not only of the workers but also of capitalists ana of the Government,and a strong case coulehe made out in favour of regarding theInternational Labour office ae a mod-rating force in thecounsels of Labour.    If this proved not to be the case, severalremedies were available, such as a change of Director, the strengthening of the personnel o^ the B-itish representatives,or the withdrawal of our contribution to- the maintenance o:the Office.The Cabinet agreed  
IMJMd AND (3) The Secretary of State for War, on the suggestion[ITKUANIA.of the Lord President of the Council, and with the conour-Ijisbiseite,renee of tho Cabinet, undertooh to postpone the demobillsa-tion of Major Keenan, as he was required for work of an exceptional character on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin connection with the plebiscite arranged by the League ofNations for the settlement of disputes between Poland and lithuania.OTTIAN (4) With reference to Cabinet 35 (20), Conclusion 5, theIDTTON:01ITROL. Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs (Paper CBPa-2221) and a Memorandumby the Secretary of State, for War (Paper C.P.-2334) dealingwith the disposal of  3,600,000 surplus funds which hadaccrued under the Egyptian Cotton Control Scheme.The Cabinet concurred(a) In the compromise set forth by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs,namely, that the fund should he equallydivided with the Egyptjan Government, onthe understanding that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment would voluntarily surrender to the Egyptian Government one-half oftheir share tor the relief of injuredmembers of the Egyptian Labour Corpsand the dependants of those who lost their lives on active, service:(b) In the remaining  900,000 being, allocated to the Board of&apos;Trade for the developmentOf cotton-growing within the Empire.
(5) The Cabinet had before then:., a draft of a ore poserdPAYMENT SY^iRDIANS OE1T-RBL1E? ^ letter to Boards of Guardians which had beer, prepared by(JRING PERI BS JFPNEMPLOY-   the Minister of Health at the request of the Cabinet Com-ENT.irdttee on Unemployment (Paper C.P.-2323),It was explained that&quot; a number of Boards of Guardianswhere a majority of the members held extre e Labour views were granting out-relief on a lavish scale and without at-taching any conditions to the grant.   Deputations had maitedon Ministers and had asked for authority to grant stilllarger unconditional grants.    The Ministry of Health had no legal nc-or to disallow such grants in the aggregate, and could only disallow the grants on the ground that they leadbeen made in particular and unsuitable cases.Pear was expressed that an attempt would be madepresently to throw the burden of these excessive localgrants upon the central Government, and the object of thedraft circular was to warn Boar-is of Guardians that,no assistance was to be expected from the Exchequer.The Cabinet agreed  (a) That a circular on the lines proposed should be issued by the Ministry of(b) That the terms cf the circular shouldhe examined and approved by the CabinetCommittee on Unemployment.- o-
EXPENDITURE ON EDUCATION.



(a) Teachers Salaries.



(6) With references to the 20th? Meeting of the Finance Committee, Conclusion 5, the Cabinet had before than the following documents:-



A Note by the Secretary to the Finance Committee, covering Letter from Mr H.A.L. Fisher, dated December 7, 1920 (Paper C.P.-2346),

A Memorandum by the President of the Board of Education, covering Report of Lord Burham&apos;s Committee (Paper C.P.-2345).

The Cabinet were informed that the President of the Board of Education and the Chancellor of the Exchequer had considered the Report of the Standing Joint Committee of Representatives of Local Education Authorities and the National Union of Teachers, which had come to an agreement as to the adoption of standard scales of salaries for teacher in public elementary schools, and that they had agreed on a draft letter which it was proposed to send to Lord Burnhaz. The sanction of the Cabinet to this letter was requested. The letter was conceived in a spirit of economy, and would not involves the Treasury in additional expenditure during the next year. The Report had been before the public for a considerable time, and it was believed that there was no popular demand for delaying the improvement in teachers&apos; salaries.

The Cabinet approved the draft letter to Lord Burnham.



(b) Continuation Schools.



The Cabinet were informed that under the Education Act of 1918?, seven local Authorities had proceeded to provide Continuation Schools with the specific authority of the B? of Education, who had given Appointed Days for bringing the relevant clause in the Act into operation. Two of these Authorities were Birmingham and London. In the case of Birmingham, the Corporation, with a view to restraining

   
the-Tfrtvuva-cinfn Ofirprittee, had abfced ths-HVrverrmmwnt not toenforce the Continuation School Clauses faster than the exigencies of the city&apos;a finances would permit.    The Chan-cellor of the Exchequer and the President cf the Board ofEducation had agreed to reply to the Birmingham Corporation.the full execution of Clause&quot;10 oftnat the^o was no intention of forcing/the Act upon theAuthorities, and the Board of Education would entertainany reasonable proposals for/ &apos;:-&quot;0V-*-n&apos;S th,, establishment ofthe Schools in accordance with th- state oi the city1sfinances.    In the case of London the position was different.Tire County Council had already spent upon their ContinuationSchemes  220,000, and were in a position to op-en theirSchools in January.    fhe suggestion was made that a lettersimilar to the one&apos; addressed to the BirmdnmthrinmCorporationshould be sent to the London County Council, but it waspointed out tnat to do this at the eleventh hour, when allpreparations for putting the Act into force had been made,would bf3 regarded as e complete capitulation by the Govern-ment to the forces of obscurantism.    The position would be materially altered if a demand came to the Government fromthe County Council, but there had been no such demand.Further, it had been represented by the Chairman of theEducation Committee that certain economies might be made in administration, and that the Board of Education could, inthe second year, arrest any too rapid progress involvingfresh expenditure on.buildings.    But, it was urged, it was of national importance that an exporumonh lu adolescenteducation of a popular character should be made on a basissufficiently bread to afford guidance for the future.The attention of the Cabinet was called to a reply,dealing with bonder., which had been given that day to aPrivate Member by the Chancellor of the Exchequer,  in thecourse o^ which &quot;Mr Cd lamb-er 1 a 11 - said&apos;.--
&quot;The Act was brought into operation for london on the application of the.-localauthori+y for London,      If they want to slow down tho action of the Act    thenthat same authority should communicate with my right hen. Friend the Ministerof education;    but they are responsiblefor inviting my right hon. Friend to fix a day for London,&apos;&apos;The Cabinet agreed  That no astion should be taken to arrestthe course of the Act in those areas where an appointed day had been given, unless anapplication were received from the LocalAuthority, when the course followed in thecase of Birmingham&quot; ^UtfliJ be adopted.Whitehall Gardens, S.?hl,December        1920.

</content>
</cab>
