<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/10/0 images: 10-10</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 10(51)							22nd November 1951



		1.	Parliament.					[Enter Ch.Whip



H.C.	Business for next week.



H.C.	Cl. Davies in diffies.  over Cttees. – only 2 men available.

	Content no Liberal on this (natd. indies.) Cttee.  He will ask me when he wants repve. on other Cttees.



H.C.	Speed in prepn. of major Bills for post-Xmas period.



P.M.	Appoint Cab. Cttees. to go thro’ them.



H.C.	There is a Steel Cttee.  Other Bills, policy, can go to H.A. Cttee.



P.M.	Weekly repts. on progress, from responsible Ministers – in Cabinet.

	I will prod. from time to time.   (Agreed).



P.M.	Steel :  Management and Ownership.  1st = L. Evans plan.  2nd = diff.



H.C.	M/S. is in touch with Duncan.  All in train.

	

P.M.  	H.C. i/c Steel.  L. i/c Road haulage.  P.T. Monopolies.



R.A.B.	Have some ideas to contribute to H.C. on finance and steel denatn.



							                             [Exit Ch.Whip

		2.	Malaya.				      [Enter C.I.G.S. and R.



O.L.	Paras. e. and f.

	Too many head men in this small area.  Sure it means delay.

	Too much emphasis on constitutions, concessions etc.

	Need for streamlined action from the top.  One Govr. Genl. with full powers, civil and military.  Govr. Genl. and C- in- C.

	This is bias with wh. I shall look into it on the spot.



C.I.G.S.	Have pressed for single control.  Got it under Briggs.  Unified command of opns – mil. and police.



O.L.	But involves concession to civil point of view.



C.I.G.S.	Worked fairly well under Gurney.



P.M.	Endorse O.L.’s view.  But look at sitn. on spot.  Report before Xmas.  And find the man.



C.I.G.S.	No quick solution.  Civil govt. wh. can do its job – it can’t now, esp. because no Chinese spkg. police or officials.



R.	On (b) don’t alienate Chinese to extent of influencing Ch. in Burma. Indo-China etc.



O.L.	Matter of degree, and timing.  Must get off the bottom first.  Must first show we can protect them.





		3.	Hong Kong.				



P.M.	Say “are resolved” to stay in H.K.

	

	Approved, subject to above.				[Exit C.I.G.S.





		4.	Schuman Plan.



M.F.	Handed in draft of his statement.

	Want to be more forthcoming.



P.M.	Military : N.A.T. Army – inside it E.D.C. – inside that G. contingent.

	Everyone dedicates forces to E.D.C.  G. doesn’t however have natl. army of own : only a breeding organisation to raise her contn. to E.D.C.

	E.D.C. shdn’t be reduced to sludgy amalgam of people ready to fight only for internatl. conceptn. : must retain nationalist appeal, for all save G.  V. unsatisf. now because France trying to get everyone else to defend France for them.



M.F.	Non-committal in public v. Eur. Army.

	As for Plan, we are “not in it but with it”.



R.A.B.	Plan is v. unpopular with Unions, in mines and steel.

	Make propaganda at home to make it clear we aren’t handg. over our mines or works to the Schumaniacs.



Sal	“establish a formal assocn.” is dangerous.  Say only “a link” or liaison.



Ch.	This isn’t a good Plan : not likely to be popular in Europe.

	Pity prev. Govt. didn’t collaborate fr. outset and make it better.



H.M.	Likely it won’t be ratified.  Mght. be chance for new attempt, in wh. we cd. join.



P.M.	Second para : say only “ …. will …. set up a permanent delegation ….”

								[Exit R.]



		5.	Bamangwato Reserve.



I.	No solution wh. won’t be open to some criticism.

	Quick decn. needed because observers retd in Sept.  Reserve is in turmoil.  P.Q.’s daily.

	Tsekedi seeing me on 29/11.  Must know decn. by then, tho’ I wdn’t tell him it.

	Para. 5.  Let him back as private citizen and if no trouble allow him to stay there permanently.



	Dep. High Commr. and Times corresp. both say his return in offl. capacity wd. cause uproar.



	Seretse.  Complete ban, review in 5 yrs.  Actually he can never go back as Chief.  Wd. unite S.A. against us and end High Commr. territories.  Disposed at first to say so at once.  But uproar wd. wreck United Africa scheme.  Therefore, allow W. Paper posn. to stand.  And build up R. as 3rd choice : to end direct rule.

	Letter from Baring, who favours saying now Seretse shd. be out for life.



Sal.	Endorse this plan.  Safe to rely on T. not to engage in pol. affairs.

	He is a man of his word.

	S. can’t go back under any circs. because of S.A. reaction.

	Apart fr. United Africa point, I wd. say so now because of continuing uncertainty in Tribe, wh. will prevent them rallying round R.

	Don’t say it now, but as quickly as we can.      



I.  	Yes.



P.M.	L. Boyd was spokesman in H/C. for Opposn.



I.	I have consulted him and he supports memo.



O.L.	So do I.  Also agree on central Africa point.  Delay S. announcemt. for 6 months.



P.M.	Announcement?  



I.  	After 29/11, when I see Tshekedi.



P.M.	Will be row in H/C.  Liberals will squawk and attract Labour left wing support.



H.C.	I support memo.  Must be announced in H/C.  Can’t concede debate before Xmas.



Sal.	Diffy. of debate will be to prevent discn. of Seretse.

		

P.M.	{Provisional approval.  Let Cab. consider gain.

	{After scrutiny by Small Cttee  P.M., L.P.S., H.C.,

	{Lennox Boyd, Ismay.



		Agreed :  Publish report of observers – after Cttee.

		Report to Cab. only if we differ.

							[Enter D.E. and D.S.



		6.	Colonial Balance of Payments.



P.M.	Can we mention this publicly eg. in my b’cast.



R.A.B.	They will be in heavy deficit in ’52.



O.L.	Cd. we expand textiles exports?  Spare steel.



O.L.	Want to explore that – my reference to consumer goods.



H.M.	i)  Don’t encourage Col. to make the point v. us.

	ii) B. individuals helped to create this wealth.



O.L.	Refces must be guarded.  Don’t want to provoke a row.



Ch.	Esp. if prospects are as R.A.B. says.



R.A.B.	On recommn. (ii) : C.O. must await allocation of steel.



P.M.  	Take note of memo.





		7.	Housing.



H.M.	Policy proposals as in memo.

	(2) is deflationary.

	(3) smaller and simpler houses.  Conforms with Dudley standards.

	Machinery.  All Ministers concerned agree with plan for Cttee. on Bldg.  To improvise in various ways.



P.M.	No need to avoid a row on this ques.  Don’t be chary over this.



H.M.	Wd. have to build ½ their allocation to let.



P.M.	Emphasise this in public statement.

		(Appoint Cttee. as in my brief.)

		(Approve proposals on policy.)



R.A.B.	Caveat for Cap. Investmt. P’mme.

	Can such pp. be discussed with Ty. in advance.

	We cd. have helped eg. on condns. of re-sale.

					       on softwood allocn.

	New Towns.  Houses now cost £1,900 there.  We shall have to cut down on this.



P.M.	You cd. send repve. to Cttee.  

D.E.  	Anxieties of bldg. industry.

							            [Exit D.E.

		

		8.	Home Guard.					[Enter A.H.



P.M.	No uniforms etc.



A.H.	For 330.000 short on mobilisation stocks.  Can’t draw on those for H.G.

	Wd. prejudice readiness of T.A.



P.M.	But you cd. replace stock.  May not be rush of volunteers.



A.H.	Cd. make up deficit by May ’52.

	£2.12.0 p.a. for damage to clothes.  Wd. cost less than issue.



R.A.B.	We don’t want to give an allowance.

	None given in 1940.  Wd. avoid commitmt. today.  We shall be pressed to increase allowance if we announce any.



A.H.	60 hrs. p.a. training.  Must say either uniform or allowance – or can’t hope to get recruits.



P.M.	V. bad if recruitg. is a flop.  Injurious to country and the Govt.



R.A.B.	Cost wd. be £400.000 p.a. if we got 170.000 recruits.



P.M.  	£2.12.0 pending issue of uniforms.

		Draw on mobilisation stocks.



</content>
</cab>
