<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/10/0 images: 13-13</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 13(51)							29th November 1951



		1.	Parliament.					[Enter Ch.Whip



H.C.	Business for next week.

	Festival Gdns.  If amendmt. on Sunday opening, there will be a free vote.

	Defence Debate – on the adjournment : W.S.C. to reply as well as open.



P.M.	Lindsay’s P.Q. on H/L. Reform.  Answer “Not before Xmas”.



						            [Exit Ch.Whip.

		2.	Man Power.			[Enter Att.G., D.S., Thomas

		

Ch.	Room for more than 8.500 extra workers in mines.



P.M.	Penalty on person engaging valet – or farmer and labourer.



W.M.	Cd. make exceptions.  But was the law from ’47-50.



P.M.	Maybe premature : we may have to prolong def programmes, because we can’t get it done.



W.M.	As at now, can’t find the manpower otherwise.



P.M.	Wait until E.P.C. review is completed.



W.M.	Industry is expectg. conversns. on manpower.



R.A.B.	We believe in full emplt. can’t use credit restn. we shall in the end have to come to this sort of thing.

	But consider with investmt. plans on E.P.C. Sub Cttee.     Agreed.



H.M.	Cd. bldg. be added to footnote on 2.



P.M.	We cd. approve proposal (3) for immediate action.  Agreed.



H.M.	Incldg. revival of scheme for apprentice traing. in bldg.



D.S.	Def. p’mme already lagging.  Labour demands rise steeply.

	Unless somethg. like this is done, it will lag even more.

	Effect on aircraft p’mme will, in partic. be v. serious.  And that can’t be spaced out over much longer period.  Or rotor, or some ammunn.



	Something like the designated list will be v. necessary.  viz short list of v. important items critically short of labour.  Cdn’t operate w’out a Regn. of Engagemt. Order.



W.M.	We lost 35.000 a week (?), among those to be influenced, when Order was dropped in ’50.

	No extra staff wd. be needed for 1) or 2).  Even tho’ 500 were cut when Order was dropped.



P.M.	Think we shall have to come to 1) and 2) also.  But discuss it thro’ E.P.C.



H.M.	Cd. there be some exceptions eg. for v. small firms or employers.



W.M.	Agric. and mining wd. be wholly exempted.



D.S.	{Will M/L. also consider deferring ex apprentices.  And returning

	{those in Forces.

J.P.L.T.	{Support this – qua. shipwrights and draftsmen.  Fleet carriers held

	{up for lack of these.



P.M.	Consider qua special bottlenecks.  *



P.M.	I will review Def. P’mme.			[Exit J.P.L.T., D.S.

							[Enter R. and A.H.



		3.	Canal Zone : Imported Labour.



P.M.	What is “deemed”.



Sim.	Most uncertain.  Therefore dangerous to run any risk.  Shd. remove the doubt.



H.C.	V. diff. to get this thro’ before Xmas.  Shd. have to build it up v. big to get it rushed thro’.



P.M.	“Pig it” – that’s the policy.

	If there’s fighting, even w’spread local incidents, will call it active service.  Short of that, risk it : try by ct. martial.  If we’re challenged we’ll legislate after Xmas.

	Use deportn. if needed.



A.H.	Can I renew decln.



Sim.	On basis of “recent” not “imminent” active service.



A.H.	I don’t want the Bill.

	But what about de facto active service.  Cd. I declare that?

	Wd. it increase tension?  Only a statement in Orders.



P.M.	Why not wait until somethg. happens : and, if you must, take a risk.  Wait until your right is challenged.



Sim.	Act of Indemnity if necessary.



</content>
</cab>
