<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/10/0 images: 48-48</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 34(52)							27th March 1952



		1.	Seretse Khama.				[Enter J. Foster.



L.P.S.	Ismay and I saw them y’day.  Cdn’t get him to abdicate.  Willing to renounce Chieftainship but not right to intervene in pol. affairs of Tribe.

	G. Walker has said Opposn. greatly moved : sought for delay.

	Cl. Davies later called on me.  Put propn.  i) renounce Chieftainship on condn. C/State apptd.  ii) not to include S or T  iii) S. not to return unless invited by Council  iv) C/State to be apptd. by H.M.G., but T. and S. to advise on membership.



	Promised consn.  My advisers are v. this plan.  B. need a Chief, not a Council.  S. wd. remain Ch. in their eyes unless another elected.  T. who wd. accept our plan, wd. not like this.  Malan wd. think it a surrender to S. and wd. bring up Territories in election.  ???? R. agrees.

	Cab. shd. consider pol. considns. : for not sure I can carry Liberals.

	Kgotlas mtg. this pm. to hear App. B.

	Only possibility : persuade S. to abdicate on promise of this plan.



O.L.	C.O. don’t believe this wd. work.



A.E.	S. unlikely to accept alternative.  Tactically wise to put it to him as at x/.?  



L.P.S. 	V. embarrassing if he accepted.



H.M.	Indefinite C/State unacceptable because abolishes monarchy.



P.M.	We shd. go forward with decision already taken.



J.F.	a)  See S. this am. and make same offer as y’day but with C/State.

	If he refuses, we can carry Liberals.

	If he accepts, we secure vol. abdication – pol. good here, tho’ diff. in Africa immediately because will confuse the Africans.



L.P.S.	We tell them he’s not to come back in order tht. they may choose a new Chief.  Then, later, tht. its in order to appoint C/State.



P.M.	Bad to alter our course and make a new offer, just to get 5 Lib. votes.

	Stand by our decision.  We have made every effort to meet.



Sw.	Idea of C/State quite alien to native opinion in these territories.



		Agreed :   Stand by decision.

	

						[Exit J.F.

		

 

		2.	Parliament.



H.C.	Business for next week.

	10/4 to 21/4 Easter Recess.  Viz. Mon via Tuesday.  Will announce this today.



							[Enter D.E., and de la W.

		3.	Government Information Services.



L.P.S.	Central agency makes for economy, if not efficiency.

                  x/	Has no reln. with Press.  Policy is for Ministers. Like Stat. Office.

	Favour keeping it.  Wthr. it shd. absorb more, eg. M/W. or G.P.O. is for considn..  W.O. also oppose transfer of C.O.I.



	Have cut out some activities already eg. films (wh. cost ½ m.) and lectures. Because of risk of Party propaganda.

	Para. 7.  Doesn’t alter my view because of x/ above.

	Let Ty. consider what transfers to C.O.I. – also Min. control.

	Head of C.O.I. was Socialist.  But has done efficient job and co-operated in securing economies.  Wd. have to find him another job.



R.A.B.	In 1941 elected to remain in C. Serv. and give up pol. activities.  No ground for suspectg. his current loyalty, on his job.



W.M.	Worked under me in M/I.  Ministers then thought well of him.



P.M.	Leave him there, unless he makes a major pol. indiscretion.

	Let me have report – staff nos. salaries of C.O.I. and Dpl. staffs.



R.A.B.	Fr. £5 m. to £2.7 m. since 1948.  



L.P. 	Mainly drop in Press advertising?



R.A.B.	Tho’ some have increased eg. G.P.O.



P.M.G.	We are trading service : must have own P.R. staff, as do socialised industries.  Loss of efficiency is getting our work done by C.O.I.

	We cd. save 9-10% if we made no use of C.O.I. at all.



R.A.B.	Let me go into this ques. of transfer with dissident Dpts. – to avoid duplication while leaving responsibility with Dpt. Ministers.



H.M.	May be more economical, not sure it’s more efficient.

	Will use C.O.I. as far as we can : but want right to do somethgs on our own eg. D. Mail Exhibition.



L.P.	Cd. we have figures before final decision.



D.E.	C.O.I. estimate for films was 5 times what we cd. get it for ourselves.

	I want M/W. publicity shifted off to industry itself.

P.M.	(Take note of memo.  No final decision.

	(Ty. to discuss with those contracting out.

	(Ch. to submit further report, with figures.



P.M.	I have also bn. considering Party machinery.



							[Exit D.E.

		4.	Anti Jamming.



A.E.	As in memo.  Net cost = £50.000 this year.

	Later on M/D. and F.O. shd. consider general strategy of counter propaganda to make sure of value for money.



P.M.	Mistake to spend so much on defence : neglect this corresp. effort.



R.A.B.	Jacob, when cut down in expenditure, only goes higher.

	Can P.M.G. help re understanding.



P.M.G.	Doubt it – they are v. short.



R.A.B.	Agree to expenditure on anti jamming.



A.E.	I want to announce tht. we shall go on with anti jamming.





		5.	Farm Price Review.			[Enter T.D. and Ll.G.



T.D.	Thursd. pm. farmers consulted Council and got agreemt tht. their figure of £66 m. was minimum they wd. accept.  Dpt. officially informed.  Was this an ultimatum?  Ministers have discussed, but no negotns.  Y’day farmers walked out : on £42½ m. v £66 m.  I then saw Turner myself, said Govt. cdn’t negotiate under an ultimatum.  He agreed to go back for more latitude.  At midnight he said he wd. resume negotiations.



	Now I need to know how far I can go.  Agreed tht. to recoup costs £42½-45 m. but this contains no incentive for future.  Between 45 and 50?

	They are worried re workg. capital as costs increase.



R.A.B.	On milk and eggs, eg. they ask for more than re-coupment.  And for more fertilisers than there are.

	Go up to limit (45m) of no more food price increases + 2½ m. viz., £47½.  That figure may involve some small price increases.



A.E.	Close quickly.



Ll.G.	Don’t want to go beyond £45 m. because will upset Budget calculns on food prices.

	As little as poss. shd. go on to milk and eggs, if we go to £50 m.



							[Exit Ll.G and T.D.



		6.	Scottish Airlines.				[Enter Maclay



P.M.	Can’t survive in Scotland unless they take in C. Islands!



J.S.	Agree they are asking more than they can have.

	But want careful statement.

		

		Approved.





		7.	Road and Rail Transport.



L.P.	L. has spoken to Hurcomb.  No need for immed. announcemt.  Will submit draft soon.  Shall need Wh. Paper – M/T. working on that.



</content>
</cab>
