<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/10/0 images: 60-60</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 46(52)							24th April 1952



		1.	Road and Rail Transport.	[Enter Sw., B-H., D.S., Maclay



		Terms of Motion for Monday’s debate approved.





		2.	Municipal Elections.



P.M.	I will b’cast on 3/5



L.P.	Have asked all Ministers (includg. members of Cabinet) to speak in the “areas” – beyond their own constituencies.





		3.	Parliament.



H.C.	Business for next week.





		4.	Legislation Programme.



P.M.	I have a diff. picture from memo.

	I put Transport before Steel – tho’ latter mght be published for discussion w’out procdg. this session.  Steel can wait, under control of old cos., but road haulage is dying.



	Discussed with Parly. Counsel : delays in getting Dept. decision is their main diffy.  If this can be overcome they can move more quickly.

	Have asked for wkly repts. fr. them.

	Fin. Bill will be cleared by end/June (fr. H/C.)

	Holidays are more important to Parlt. than legn.

	Transport Bill 2nd Rdg. 7/7 : Cttee stage complete by 7/8.  Rise by 10/8.  Return 15/10., and clear away remaining business.  End Session by 10/12.  Leave a gap before opening new Session on 10/2/53.

	Too much, evidently to attempt Steel and Transport.



H.C.	Apart fr. Fin. Bill other essential business (Supply, Civil List, and essential legn.) wh. must be finished before summer recess will mean 31 days – leavg. for Transport only days for 2nd Rdg. and guillotine motion.  V. little margin for genl. debates or votes of censure.



	When Bill publd., 3 wks. must be allowed before 2nd Rdg. (Labour’s Coal Bill had 6 wks. and others 3 or 4 – we demanded that.)

	If ready by 1/7, we cdn’t do more than 2nd Rdg. before Recess and that wd. mean sitting until 15/8.

	30 yrs. since Debate on Address taken in spring.  Reason for autumn opening was need to get major legn. on before Supply period.



H.M.	Long period for Coal etc., was partly because private interests affected had to be consulted before their assets were expropriated.



P.M.	Can’t hold our supporters unless we do Transport Bill this Session.



Sal.	H/Lds. wd. need a month to pass all stages.



Sw.	Must consider how long we took, in Opposition, over Transport and Steel in H/L.

	This confirmed P.M.’s view in favour of opening next Session after Xmas.



D.S.	There are disadvantages in p’poning Steel Bill.

	We have undermined authy. of Corpn.  And Fedn. is pulling in its horns in anticipn. of new Bd. – lookg. to M/S. for leadership on matters on wh. industry itself shd. assume responsibility.  May have to set up a shadow Bd. of some kind.



P.M.	Can’t have both.  Transport must have priority.

	I suggested 15/10 because Party Confce.  But Parlt. has priority : may have to meet on 1/10.

	Clear tht. new Session can’t open before Xmas.



H.C.         *	Suggest appointment of Future Legn. Cttee.	}

							}

P.M.	I wd. like to be a member of it.		}



P.M.	Aim at Recess on 7 or 12/8.

		Resume on 15/10.  Sit on until 15/12, if necessary.



Sw.	H/L.  Minimum requirement for Transport Bill wd. be – 4 weeks.



Sal.	V. tight fit.



H.C.	Will make a p’mme on those assumptions.

	Guillotine motion cdn’t be taken until after Recess.



D.S.	Wd. wish Steel Bill to be publd. soon.  To give confidence and to end speculation in industry.



P.M.	Cd. even have 2nd Rdg., for debate purposes, after Transport has gone to H/Lds.



H.C.	Better have a W. Paper.  Tho’ that wd. provoke debate.

	Wd. like to discuss this issue with M/Supply.



</content>
</cab>
