<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/10/0 images: 63-63</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 49(52)							6th May 1952



		1.	Allied Command in Mediterranean.	[Enter Sw., 1st Lord, 1st 								 Sea Lord, Att.Genl.



P.M.	Neither I nor F.O. had realised this had assumed such propns.



Al.	C.O.S. conferred with Fechteler y’day.  At lunch I put my own views – even if U.S. had best staff answer, that’s not necessarily best solution.

	Natl. aspirn must be taken into a/c. and B. public opinion wd. not tolerate U.S. naval commn. in Med. anyway in peace, with all our interests in Med. and M/E.  F. was impressed.



P.M.	Must be considered v. b’ground of surrender in Atlantic.

	Carney’s “southern flank” is by no means the whole of naval responsibility in Med.



C.N.S.	F. took it up from Lisbon – where disagreemt. betwn. U.S. and U.K.  They wanted Carney i/control, but Br. C.-in-.C. to have e/w. l/c.  Y’day F. agreed on need of Allied Naval C.-in-.C. to cover all sea and sea/air operns. in Med.  Diffies. was on to whom he shd. report.  U.S. said to Carney because they were concerned only with N.A.T.O.  They cdn’t take a/c of M/E. because outside N.A.T.O.  Their plan offered no solution for M/E. needs.  We rejected that – as putting l/c to M/E. under Commd. fighting land battle in Eur.  We thght this man must support equally campaign in E. and in M/E. and be respons. only to St. Gp., who alone cd. reconcile needs of the 2 theatres.



	F. says Fr. and It. Navies willing to operate only under Carney.

	We have explained to Fr. Admiral there’s no problem under our Schuman.

	We also say tht. if U.S. and U.K. agree, others will fall in line.



P.M.	Let’s have this posn. stated on paper today.

	I am not prepared to concede this U.S. claim, on top of Saclant.



A.E.		i)	Shows kind of U.S. interest in Med. viz. only in connn. with 			land battle.  That is v. disturbing.



		ii)	Distinctn. betwn. N.A.T.O. and non N.A.T.O. Forces.  				Distinction shd. be betwn. forces of N.A.T.O. powers and 				forces of non N.A.T.O. powers.



P.M. 		May have to meet on this on Wednesday.

									[Exit C.N.S.

									[Enter A.H.

		2.	Malaya.



P.M.	Action was justified : subsequent photo. was not.

	Marine lost the negatives, didn’t sell them to Press.

O.L.	Don’t think statement is necessary.  Answer the P.Q.’s



1stLd.	They aren’t on this incident.



O.L.	There will be one.  I asked the M.P. to p’pone it.



A.H.	Are we going to stop bringing in heads for identification in future.

	Templer wants authy. to go on doing that when all other means of identification fails.  I wd. support him.



P.M.	Odium is out of all propn. to advantage gained.  I’m against it.

	Plays into hands of Communist agitation.



O.L.	Yes – effect in Malaya wd. be v. bad.



P.M.	Give instns. v. decapitation – say so.



P.M.	Let statement be made by O.L. in reply to arranged P.Q. this week.



O.L.	Say “instructed to avoid the necessity for decapitn ”



P.M.	Put it bluntly, as overleaf.





		3.	Broadmoor Asylum.



H.C.	No slackening in security precautions since transfer fr. H.O.

	Have now received report.  P.Q.’s later.  Shd. I make statement at once, to allay anxiety?  Believe may have to hold an independent enquiry.



P.M.	Not a good story, on facts as known to me.



H.C.	Facts are rather different.



P.M. 	*  Then circulate the report to Cabinet.



Sw.	There is w’spread anxiety.  Offer the enquiry quickly.



P.M.	Yes : say at once there will be enquiry and promise informn. next week re t. of r. and membership.  Avoid statement on particular case.





		4.	Functions of Co-ordinating Ministers.



		Draft of statement by P.M. in H/C. – read and approved.





		5.	Purchase Tax.		}

						}  Not heard. (Out of room.)

		6.	Excess Profits Levy.	}





		7.	Transport Policy.				[Enter G.B.



R.A.B.	Suggested to P.M. incln of sentence indicatg. that W. Paper is offered for discn.



P.M.	We shd. be ready to adjust our views, but shd. not say so.

	Wd. look irresolute.	Agreed :  no alteration.





		8.	Road Passenger Vehicles’ Licensing.



L.P.	As in memo.



P.M.	Won’t strengthen our authority with the other side if membership is proposed.  Cd. give us more knowledge.

	Let us have some form of private enquiry, via independent enquiry.

	In R. Commn. repn. is given to both sides.

	On controversial ques. you get no added strength fr. Cttee composed mainly of people of our way of thinking.

	There is no hurry.  No legn. this year.

	Let L. draw up the principles to be observed pending new legn.



		Discn. to be resumed.



</content>
</cab>
