<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/10/0 images: 68-68</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 54(52)							20th May 1952



		1.	China. Withdrawal of B. Firms.	[Enter Sw., J.P.L.T.



P.M.	Can we do anything?  



A.E. 	No.



P.M.	D. Tel. suggests w’drawal of our repves.  This surely is a time to keep them – to discuss details if they will.





		2.	Royal Visit to Australia and N.Z.



J.T.	Need early decn. to abandon use of Gothic.  Figure doesn’t include charter cost.  Wanted for the meat run, fr. Austr. in August.



P.M.	Total cost, if we used Gothic, wd. be nearly £2 m.  Quite understand Admy. want to drop the subject.  But wd. cost only £125.000 more to use her, with all her advantages.



L.	Too late to alter her before her next trip.  Cd. perhaps persuade owners to take a lower figure.  Cd. p’pone decision until after this next trip.



J.T.	Yacht won’t be ready in time for dates preferred by A. and N.Z., who want tour over before elections in July.



Al.	Why not use Austr. cruiser?  



J.T. 	V. old and uncomfortable.  



P.M. 	Not at all suitable.



P.M.	To use another line w’out altern wd. stultify money spent on Gothic.



L.	£27.000 compensn. for space lost on next trip.



Sal.	Choice is betwn. 2 and 4 : choose the cheaper.



L.	Trouble is : v. few small liners in those waters.  Otherwise you come on to P.O. mail boats, much too big.  Only about 2 suitable ships which wdn’t have to go out specially – Union Steamship Co. of N.Z.

	I assume they will fly out.



Sal.	Then stick to Gothic.  



A.E. 	And try to reduce addl. expense.



R.A.B.	Shall have to pay £125.000 to keep Gothic : shd. have to pay about £100.000 for another.  

CLOSED UNDER THE



FREEDOM OF INFORMATION



ACT 2000



P.M. 	But cost of G. will come out.  



R.A.B. 	Gothic involves £125.000 in addn. to charter, which you wd. have to pay anyway.



R.A.B.	If we chartered out there, A. and N.Z. wd. pay much of cost of converting.



L.	I will try to negotiate out of the £27.000 and then we can p’pone decision.



J.T.	Ask Menzies to accept a later date, so yacht cd. be used.  



P.M.  	Yes.



							           [Exit J.T.

		3.	Egypt.



A.E.	Egypt’s answer recd. this am.  Rejection of ours; and theirs is unacceptable.



	But satisfy. feature is tht. they want to spin things out.

	They have asked Sudanese to Cairo – no harm in that.

	E. beginning to relax restns. on passage of ships thro’ Canal to Israel.

	E. Govt. looking for good relns. all round.

	If we have any equipmt. to give, a little later, it wd. help.  Wd. M/D. examine that?  Things in Zone are quiet.



P.M.	What of reducg. garrison?  



Al. 	Mil. on spot think it mght encourage disorderly elements.  But I will examine that.



A.E.	Wd. like to be able to say somethg. v. reduction to Amb.



Al.	80.000 and all in tents.  Too many.



		Agreed :  F.O. and M/D. to examine.

	Authority to P.M., A.E. and Al. to authorise Rodeo in emergency.





		4.	Germany : Guided Missiles.



A.E.	Good progress generally.  Looks as tho’ agreemt. will be reached.

	Guided missiles.  Held up because Fr. don’t like our proposal.  I’m reluctant to press French.  But our experts say short range manuf. won’t help with long range : that is what worries Fr.  Propose to send experts to discuss that with French.



Ch.	Big techn. diffce. because short range rides a beam and that wdn’t do for long range.



		Agreed :  Send technical experts as proposed.



		

		5.	Pacific Pact.



O.L.	F.O. and C.O. have bn. drawg. up memo. on enlargemt. of Pacific Pact to include us and prs. the French.

	Hope you will ascertain Menzies’ attitude on this while he is here.

	I see the diffies. eg. on Burma, Indo-China.





		6.	East Africa : Royal Commission.



O.L.	Popn. doubling every 35 yrs. because Br. rule.  Easy remedy : cultivate more of the bush.  But that reduces standard of living.  Mitchell recommends R.C. : believe this is a case for one.



P.M.	Scream if there’s no black man.  



O.L. 	I will find one.



P.M.	Cdn’t it all wait?  



O.L. 	Really urgent.  I will submit names.



P.M.	I’m against this unless you can find a (fairly) suitable black man.



Sal.	Will raise whole issue of Kenya white settlers.



O.L.	They will favour this because growing agitation about their land.



		(Approve in principle.

		(O.L. to submit names for P.M.’s approval.

		* O.L. to send copy of Mitchell’s report to P.M.



R.A.B.	Will O.L. shorten the t. of ref. when he sees the Chairman.





		7.	Hong Kong: Constitutional Reform.



O.L.	As in memo.

	No conceivable voting combinn wd. deprive Govt. of a majority.

	Other Dpts. concerned agree we shd. go ahead.  Cd. defer it again if situation deteriorated.



Sal.	I support this.  Indian Govt. have suggd. Indians shd. have separate repn. on Council.  We think that is wrong.  But shd. keep them informed.  

O.L. 	Yes : tho’ be aware tht. Portuguese are so represented.



P.M.	They are v. prosperous.  Cdn’t they make a contn. to cost of defence?



O.L.	Not now – when their trade is cut by sanctions v. China.





		8.	Bamangwato.



Sal.	Att. G. has advised tht. Procln shd. be open to challenge.

	O.-in-C. to be laid only – no need for resoln. – Prayer cd. not even be made.



H.C.	Sure?  



Sal. 	Yes.



Sal.	Agitation is likely to die down, in Reserve.

	Seretse, on receipt of pension, undertook to refrain from pol. activity; but he is doing nothing else.  But can we threaten him with loss of pension?  Wd. provoke gt. criticism. Better to leave him alone.



</content>
</cab>
