<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/10/0 images: 70-70</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 56(52)							27th May 1952



		1.	Economic Situation.				[Enter Sw., L-B.



P.M.	Are we to expect another financial crisis?



R.A.B.	Forward rate has dropped below $2.80.  Has caused depression in City.  This has bn. overdone.  Govt. broker has intervened.

	June results will be better than we once feared.

	But imports are not dropping as planned.  From Eur. we are getting more than we shd. – and paying gold.

	Rumours of Bank rate rising to 5%.  I don’t favour that.



Ch.	Imports fr. Europe are still too high. Glad R.A.B. is looking into that.

	Dom. cuts will come in soon.



R.A.B.	Going to talk to French on this, and E.P.U., immedly. after Whitsun.

	Will then try to discuss switchg. commodities.





		2.	Germany.



P.M.	Take note of position.

	

	Congrats of Cab. to A.E.





		3.	B.A.O.R. – Move of Headquarters.



P.M.	Move of base to Antwerp.  Why this enormous cost?  Surely we cd. plan to take over workshops etc ., in war instead of bldg. our own now.

	Will M/D. look into this?



Al.	Yes.





		4.	Civil Air Transport.



		Approved, subject to amendments.		[Exit L-B.

								[Enter G.Ll. and S.Ll.



		5.	Coal : Open cast Working at East Lothian.



P.M.	Anstruther Gray has threatened to resign his seat if an open cast opn. is begun in his constituency.  Said it’s best agric. land in Scotland.



L.	True.  We are only prospectg. now.  But likely to prove rich in coal : good coal : much needed now Lanark is worked out.

	H.A. Cttee has considered.  Shall report again before prodn. opns. begin.

	Looks like ½ m. tons.  With restorn of ground w’in 3 yrs. – cd. recover completely in 4 yrs.  Part of a big Sc. survey – for a worthwhile result.



L.P.	F. and Ag. objected at H.A. Cttee : but we agreed to prospecting.  There will be a conflict about this – but must measure facts before we finally decide.



G.Ll.	Admit this is exceptionally fine agric. land – pride of Scotland.

	Unfortunately, it’s also best coal too.



		Agreed :	(J.S. to see Anstruther Gray : no blackmail.

				( Await results of prospecting.



		6.	Coal : Exports.



L.	As in memo.  Can’t afford more.  Too risky.  Adds 1½ m. tons to original 10 m.  Bulk will be small coal.  (too small to hold any stone).  But power stations can use it – tho’ little of it will be coking smalls.  Might fetch £3 a ton (as against £6 for good coal).



R.A.B.	Must have more.



	On present form 19-20 m. ton stock at end/winter.

	Want to see export of 12 m. tons + 1.5 m. of slurry.

	Are we to take the risk on the reserves or on coal stocks.

	I believe tht. in June we shd. take that risk.

	Another 5 m. wd. save $90 m. on the reserves.

	Must restore confidence this summer.  Only 2 ways.  i) cut defence prodn. or ii) expand coal exports.  This is vital.  Must do (ii) v. soon.

	Also want to send more big coal abroad.  We are in a sellers’ market now : if we miss it Schuman Plan will settle pattern and we shall lose market for good.



L.	Don’t want to plan ahead.  Can’t commit ourselves beyond summer months.

	Haven’t got large coal w’out disturbg. domestic market seriously.

	Shd. have to rob indies. wh. can use no other types.  Cd. get a bit more out of S. Wales.



Ch.	Worth taking a risk.  Consumptn. 200.000 t. down as cpd. last year.

	Half of that durg. summer wd. be 2 m. tons.

	Stocks are 3 m. better.

	If we did what R.A.B. suggests we shd. have somethg. in hand cpd. with last year.



L.	Mild winter.  Can we rely on that again?

	My only hope of more = i) extra output.  ii) redn. in industrial demands.  Can’t be sure of either yet.



G.Ll.	We hope we may do more twds. R.A.B.’s demand later in year, when we see how we are going.

	All previous coal shortages, fr. Shinwell on, were due to Ty. pressure.



P.T.	Support R.A.B.  Immense benefit to our trade.  Wd. do more than anything to restore our trading posn.  Wd. improve willingness to accept our less essentials.



P.M.          *	Accept L.’s offer as an instalment twds. R.A.B.’s plan.  We shd. work towards that.  *



R.A.B.	Want to get into market again as soon as we can.  To avoid crystallisation  of pattern of Eur. coal movements.



Al.	Can’t that be met by saying we hope to do more?  



L. 	Miners may slack off then.



Sim.	B/payments is the biggest current risk we face.



		Reviews again in June.			[Exit G.Ll.

	



		7.	Korea. Prisoners of War.



S.Ll.	Haven’t bn. warned of a P.Q.

	Problem : shd. we make repns. to U.S. re method of control.  We have no direct informn.  Can only put our views thro’ State Dpt. to Pentagon.



P.M.	This isn’t wholly mil. issue.  Involves moral issues.

	When I saw Greece, Can. and Holland were each sending a co. I felt easier.  But now Canada has protested, we shall be urged to protest too.



S.Ll.	H/C. didn’t object to our troops being used – rather to our havg. no sufft. informn. of what’s going on.



P.M.	We shd. publicise efforts made to ‘screen’ those in our power.



</content>
</cab>
