<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/10/0 images: 91-91</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 81(52).				26th September, 1952.



	1.	Kenya.                                           [Enter  Sw., B-C., S.Ll., Home.



P.M.	Are there precedents for similar action by Socialists?



O.L.	If Oppn criticised us officially, we can quote their deportn ordinance

		of 1949 – wh. lacks the safeguards wh. I have now included:

		ques. only thro’ L.O., no condns on evce of one witness alone,

		&amp; appeal to Supr. Ct.

	In Malaya even more stringent ordinances were introduced by 

		Socialists.



P.M.	On merits?



O.L.	How deal otherwise with condns in which 100 witnesses have 

		disappeared?  Ordinary processes of law won’t suffice.  But I

		added the safeguards.  And deferred re-introdn of corporal

		punishment.



P.M.	Troops?



O.L.	Not yet out of hand.



P.M.	Worth re-enforcing – e.g. parachute battn fr. Egypt, in terrorem.



O.L.	Will consider, with M/D.



Sw.	Deportn of leaders is best solution, when you are dealing with secret 

		societies under witch-doctors.





	2.	Persia.



S.Ll.	V. unsat. reply from M.  Arguments absurd.

	We shd. try hard to preserve joint U.K./U.S. reply even if there has

		to be a separate &amp; longer U.K. rejoinder as well.



P.M.	U.S. agreed tht. our offer was fair – hard for them to wriggle out of 

		that.



S.Ll.	State Dpt. have behaved v. badly.  They need pressure.



P.M.	Tho’ we can’t stop them giving money to Persia, if they wish to.



S.Ll.	But we ought to stop them encouraging U.S. oil cos. to buy P. oil.



P.M.	Say to M. – his reply doesn’t carry us further than posn when we made

		the U.K./U.S. approach.  Clear negative.

		F.O. to draft reply &amp; submit to P.M. – after consultg. A.E.

	3.	Pacific Pact.



Sal.	Acheson stood firm on basis tht. U.K. observer wd. mean observers

		fr. all other countries.  Not influenced by argument tht. U.K.

		wd. come in at once if A. or N.Z. were involved in war.

		If we press A. &amp; N.Z., we may well get negative reply.

                      *But no need to conceal our view in Parlt. – we have a good case.

	Austr. public opinion may influence Menzies – Evatt is exploiting

		his chance.



P.M.	Menzies &amp; Casey are behaving v. ill.

	This indicates U.S. wish to dominate A. &amp; N.Z. – dollar countries

		under U.S. protection.  Doubt is A. people wd. stand for that.



Sal.	Stress *.



P.M.	I wd. wish to send personal tel. to M. &amp; Casey &amp; to Holland.



Sal.	I wd. welcome that.



P.M.	Will show draft to Sal.



S.Ll.	Case cd. not have bn. put more strongly to U.S.





	4.	Saudi Arabia.



S.Ll.	Saudi Arabia trying to extend influence – skirmishing on Trucial?

		coast.

	We have bn. dropping leaflets.  Small bodies on either side are 

		skirmishing.  Doubt if much will come of it.

	Reason is – to cover more oil country.  U.S. oil interests may be

		encouraging them.





	5.	Argentine Meat.



S.Ll.	Cab. agreed that some credit shd. be offered.

	Ty. agreed we cd. go up to £10 m. in first instance.  That offer

		is now being made.



L.P.	This will enable negotns to go on.  But doubt if they will be content.

		If not, better course wd. be to offer to take more meat &amp; an

		advance payment for it.

	Ration will drop from 2/= to 1/9 in December, probably.  If 

		Argentine meat begins to be shipped in Nov., we may avoid

		that.



P.M.	Avoid reducg. it on 24/12.



L.P.	Shd not allow negotns to be delayed.  And they can’t be allowed to

		fail.  We shd. try to get 200.000 (not 170.000 only).





	6.	Egypt.   Sterling Balances.



S.Ll.	£5 m. offer.  Neguib’s first reactions are not unfavourable.

		Seems likely that he will accept condns.



P.M.	Welcome his row with Wafd – esp. disarming them.



S.Ll.	Reasonable also re Sudan;  &amp; will give his answer on Wed.





	7.	South African Questions in U. Nations.



Sal.	We don’t want to identify ourselves with Malan’s racial policy.

	We don’t want to compromise on our view tht. these are domestic

		matters not for U.N.  Any intervention by U.N. wd. tend to

		push S.A. Oppn into Malan’s arms.

	No sympathy with India in raising these issues.

	Hence the wise, tho’ unheroic, course of a middle line.  Para. 14.



S.Ll.	S.A. won’t walk out on 1st and 3rd resoln.  The 2nd is the dangerous

		one.  And India is sending a snappy Delegn (Mrs Pandit &amp;

		Krishna Menon).

	If there is a debate on racial policy, it will be undignified for us to

		sit mum.



O.L.	But we must.



			Memo. approved.





	8.	G.A.T.T.  Admission of Japan.



P.T.	Genl. agreemt. on 18/9.  Avoid welcome.  Seek p’ponement.  Avoid

		any decision by G.A.T.T. at this stage.

	We have now persuaded U.S. to come a long way to meet.

	U.S. now propose reference to Inter-Sessional Cttee.  Read draft 

		resolution in W’ton Tel. 1820.

	Comments:  as in draft telegram.

		This will p’pone issue for six months or more.



P.M.	Don’t like para. 2.  Shd insist on amendment in para. 1.  And see what

		they say.



S.Ll.	V. little time.  Mtg. starts on 2/10.  We have got U.S. a long way –

		dangerous not to clinch this now.



Ch.	Agreed.  We have done v. well in W’ton.



H.M.	Better suggest stopping at “… matters involved”.



P.T.	Accept that.



			Agreed on that basis.  }   P.T. to submit revised draft

			And delete para. 2.      }        to P.M.





	9.	Engineering Wages.



W.M.	Moderates on both sides desire settlement.

	Union doubts how many will observe overtime ban – but enough

		will do so to damage our industry.

	6/= or 7/= wd. settle it.  Ship-bldg. employers wd. give that.

		Engineerg. employers (some of them) itch for a show-down:  

		think this is the moment for it.  Doubt if they are right.

	Employers don’t want to take initiative in making an offer.

	Don’t want Court of Enquiry.

	Employers have now agreed to joint mtg. with Gould.  Thursday

		next week.  At invitation of M/Labour.  Unions will certainly

		come.



</content>
</cab>
