<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/10/0 images: 94-94</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 84 (52)				                                                       7th October, 1942[sic] 

1.	    Transport Bill.

			                                               [Enter S.W., Att.G., L.B., B.H

L.	Memo. puts both sides – Cttee is divided.



L.B.	2nd part of levy shd. be dropped – for sev. reasons.  We mght. be defeated in H/C.

		Diff. sitn created by decn to allow rlways to operate on roads.

		But we must do more – enable rlways to compete more effectively.  Integrn is off:  we now rely on competn.  This cd. be done w’out deterring purchasers of lorries.

	Don’t give rlways 100% freedom:  but be ready to look at charges again.

M.f.n. theory handicaps rlways:  abandoning that wd. bring them more traffic e.g. from C. licences.  E.g. on lines of Euan Wallace’s plan.  Cd. get agreemt. with industry &amp; avoid heavy damage to heavy lorry business.

Avoid rlwys. recovering fr. traffic wh, must go by road.

		If we drop levy, we will give stimulus to talks btwn. industry, rlways on charges – try to get somethg. out of that.

Wd. consolidate our Party &amp; divide Labour (because Rlway T.U. men cdn’t oppose measures to get freights free-er).



L.	Cdn’t give rlways freedom.  Need for care to prevent coal &amp; steel from havg. to pay higher charges to support low competn ratio for other traffic.  Coal has no repn in F.B.I.  Industry is not near agreemt. with rlways on charges.  Unless we are careful, this will arouse more hostility than levy.

	BTC are not opposed to levy.  Not everyone is against it.



Sw.	Pol. almost imposs. to get levy thro’ H/C.  Liberals wd. vote v. it.  Tories wd. be v. reluctant to vote for it.

	Also it’s wrong.

i)	With new facilities for rlways to operate on roads, can’t see why they shd. be bound to lose money.

ii)	Tribunal must control rlway rates.  But many have advocated for years some greater latitude &amp; flexibility – in order to get business.  If they get it, no increase on heavy traffic wd. be involved.

iii)	“Danger to Ty. if no levy.”  More likely to get efficiency on rlways w’out feather-bedding by levy.



M-F.	Believe in levy.  Everywhere rlways are losing traffic to roads:  some equalisation is essential.  Let roads pay insurance policy to keep rlways going. Unshaken on econ-arguments.  But concerned at pol. diffies:  must take them into a/c.  Tho’ w’out levy our soln wdn’t last.  Favour latitude on charge up to point at wh. industry agree.  If we cd. get consent of F.B.I. and N.U.M. I wd. run risks re effect on heavy traffic.

 

R.A.B.	Levies aren’t ideal:  &amp; I didn’t much like the plan at outset.

	But (i) if you take it away, Bill makes no contn to road/rail.  Becomes mainly a Bill to sell 8/10.000 lorries back to pr. enterprise.



L.	Or 2/3rds.



R.A.B.	Can’t be sure of selling more at any early stage.

Bill will become pretty thin.

(ii) Out of ques. for Ty. to assume responsibility for rlway stocks.

Abolition of levy brings that risk nearer.

	Wd. prefer on balance to keep levy.  We cd. modify it or throw it over in H/C if need be.  But it’s no more popular than E.P.L. was.  We cd. “deal with it” in H/C.



P.T.	Support M/T.  His suggns re organn &amp; fair policy form a reasonable plan for transport.  Levy was always hard to defend – better the

	x/      roads work more they have to pay to inefficient rlways.

	Sell as many lorries as we can.  Remove 25m limit as soon as we can.

But give rlways a reasonable chance to compete with roads.



O.L.	x/ isn’t fair.  Rlways must go on, to carry traffic wh. can’t go by road.

They can’t compete, only by free-er rates:  essential differences wh. make rlways more costly.  Favour keeping levy.



Ch.	Rlways must be kept going.

	They are paying at present.  May lose money if roads become more efficient.  Who shall bear the loss?  Not Ty.:  wd. encourage inefficiency.  Make road-users pay?  Smacks of subsidy.  Free-er charges on rlways.

Danger is heavy traffic.

	Wd. it be possible to pass Bill as now, but refrain fr. charging part 2 of levy until we are sure rlways can’t compete.  Reserve it for 2/3 years until we see how we stand.



P.M.	BTC road services are makg. a loss – and 5.000 of their lorries are laid up.  Their overheads remain as before.  Exposes bankruptcy of Socialist policy.

	Thought we cd. sell 3/4 of the lorries.  Now appears to be thought unlikely.

That is the most serious factor in present situation.

	Parlt. is place where these things shd. be thrashed out.  Need we decide it so far in advance of discussn in H/C.  Parlt. shd. take a share in forming &amp; shaping legn.  Not humiliating to make concessns to Parlt. opinion.



A.E.	Strong arguments for levy when we framed Bill.  They are still there.

Last sentence of para. 7.  Danger to Ty.

	Unwise to abandon it now, despite its unpopularity.



S.	This is a denatn Bill.  We wdn’t have promoted it now if we hadn’t given pledge at Election.  ( P.M. Needed on merits too).  It shd. be success, if we can make it one.  Vital therefore tht. as many lorries as poss. be sold. Levy is a deterrent to sales.  It is frightening off those whom we wanted to encourage.

	We can drop levy – now or after debate on H/C.  Majority seem to favour latter course.  But M/T wanted a balanced plan, putting other things in Bill to offset dropping levy.  Can we get those in to Bill when it’s in H/C.



L.B.	Agree.  If we drop it &amp; put nothg. else in, it will be a thin Bill.

	Agreemt. on rate re-adjustment wd. depend on dropping levy, to some extent.

And we cdn’t move it in during Cttee.



Ch.	No case for levy now because rlways aren’t losing money.



L.B.	It’s psychol. disadvantages wd. remain.  Tho’ it is a poss. compromise.

Make it dependent on affirmative resoln.



P.T.	Wd. deter purchasers of lorries.



L.B.	Flexibility of charge is good in itself.



H.C.	This is not a good Bill on wh. to wait to make concessions.

	We had a debate before recess, and are expected to make up our minds in view of opinion expressed since.

	This wd. be a v. drastic change to make in Cttee.  And diff. then to put in the off-setting proposals.



W.	Must be influenced by consn  tht. rlways are paying – and don’t need the levy.

	Put into Bill both flexibility of charge and right to charge part 2 of levy.  But  don’t charge it now.



L.B.	Welcome freedom to explore greater flexibility.  Shall find it more diff. to persuade industry to co-operate if power to charge levy remains.



O.L.	Get all Parly criticism by this means and more of the credit.



Sw.	We don’t know results of changes we propose to make in organn of transport.  Rlways may make money in future on road services.  Why decide now that levy is necessary.  Authorise it:  but let it operate only after aff. resoln of both Houses.



L.	Danger of allowg. rlways to make preferential rate-deals with big firms.



L.B.	B.T.C. will be in control – with road haulage represented on it.

		P.M.  {Work out possibility of including in Bill both provn for 

	 {greater flexibility and power to charge part two of levy

Agreed			 {(later, on affirmative resolution).



			

L.B.	Yes. But	

i)	Levy is now in title.

ii)	H/C. may need a longer interval before 2nd Rdg.  Might not be ready for introdn quite so soon.  And Steel might have to go on first.



P.M.	And no public hint of any changes of policy.





2.	    Leasehold Reform.

			                                                  [Exit L.B. &amp; Att.G. &amp; W.M.

		                                                           [Enter Solr. G.

M-F.	As in memo.



P.M.	How can we do all this – with T&amp;C.P., Steel &amp; Transport and Coronation.

	Why not extend the standstill?  How much better if we had extended B.B.C. Charter for 3 yrs. instead of 6 months.

	Long-term solution wd. involve separate Sc. legn.



J.S.	We shd. present only – not proceed with it.



H.C.	No chance of getting major Bills through.



Sim.	Cdn’t we expose our long-term plan when we bring in standstill.



H.C.	If so, by Wh. Paper vice Bill?



M-F.	The Bill is ready.  It cd. start in H/L.  We shd. at least show we had got an answer.



H.C.	If you published Bill, it wd. make it a high priority for followg. Session.



P.M.	Take credit, in debates on standstill Bill, for our ideas – if necessary by publn of W. Paper.



			Agreed:  1) Standstill Bill only

			               2) Let H.O. prepare a Wh. Paper, for consn by

			                   Cabinet.



S.G.	Try to work in to Standstill Bill security for residential tenants.



			Agreed

					     [Exit Sol. Genl.

3.	    Monopolies Bill.



P.T.	Pledges – in Election and in last King’s Speech.

	Short Bill:  only 10 clauses.  Cd. be ready soon.



P.M.	Why clutter up the p’mme, esp. when Opposn are obstructive.



A.E.	Not a strong case for going on with this.



Sim.	Will be diff. to select 3 panels.



H.M.	There’s Rent also:  we cd. p’pone the more popular Monopolies Bill.



P.M.	Abandon it, unless Opposn will give it as agreed measure.





4.	    Saudi Arabia.



A.E.	Encroachment on Sultan of Muscat’s Protectorate.

	The Sultan has mobilised &amp; wants to have a crack at Ibn Saud.

		Hafiz is going back.  I offered w’drawal on both sides.  Then Ibn Saud wdn’t see Hafiz.  He even talks of taking us to U.N.

May be serious.





5.	    German War Criminals.



A.E.	Am recommendg. release of Kesselring.  Submn to Queen.





6.	    G.A.T.T. and Imperial Preference.



O.L.	B/T. draft (circulated) is acceptable to me save on one point – on p.2 of Draft.



P.T.	I accept that.



S.	Better:  but no other member of Commonw. thinks so.



A.E.	Every Dom. is against us on this.  None wants greater freedom.



			Agreed:  “… most embarrassing posn for us to be in”



</content>
</cab>
