<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/10/0 images: 98-98</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 88(52).				22nd October, 1952.



	1.	Queen’s Speeches.	[Enter  Sw., B.H., L-B.



	Amendments suggd &amp; approved.

	Opening Speech:  Scottish electricity.  Only mention of Scotland.

		But admitted that legn is a long way off.



Sw.	Reform of H/Lds.  Shall we be precluded fr. raising it if we say

		nothing?



(Sal.)	I think not.



A.E.	Cd we do this in ’53, with everything else that’s going on.

	Not mentiong. it doesn’t preclude.



				[Enter  Att.G.

	2.	Transport Bill.



P.M.	Not a scrap of former scheme is now to remain.

	Alternative:  ruthless exposure of State lorries to competn of private

		enterprise.  They will be destroyed.  The adminve overheads wd.

		drop away presumably as the business declined.  I’m ready to

		back it, if need be:  but let’s understand what it means.



L.	We were told at outset by B.T.C. tht. even raising 25 m. limit wd. ruin

		R.H. Executive:  we hesitated to destroy State business costing 

		£30 m. in good will.  That was why we devised original scheme.

	7/10 Cab. invited Cttee to re-consider on basis of suspended Pt. II of

		levy.

	Later, at mtg. with P.M., asked to consider total abandonment of Pt. II.

	We are now divided.  Some stand to compromise plan on Pt. II:

		M/T. favours unlimited competn.  R.H. Ex. wd. certainly shrink

		away.  Tho’ Hurcomb is less apprehensive of competn than he 

		first was.

	My own view:  favour present Bill &amp; compromise on Pt. II.

	M/T. scheme wd. benefit short-range hauliers already in business at

		expense of those who mght. wish to re-enter long-distance trade.

		The licensing system wd. check their automatic return.



P.M.	Remember Labour threats to ruin the sale of the lorries.  Cd be said tht.

		these threats made sale impossible &amp; justified change of policy.



M-F.          	i)	New plan doesn’t honour pledge to expropriated long-distance 		men.

                  	ii)	Does too much for short-distance men.

                  	iii)	1933 Act licensing system wd. be undermined.

                  	iv)	No lasting solution of road/rail.  Suspended levy wd. be somethg.

		B.T.C. will make a loss &amp; put it on Ty.

                  	v)	After producg. W. Paper and Bill, Govt. wd. be in gt. pol. diffy if 		they made so violent a volte face.  Confidence in Govt. wd. be 

		shaken.

	Accept flexibility of charge proposal, but retain compromise on

		levy Pt. II.



L.B.	Opposn to levy threatens chance of getting charge provns thro’.

	Even more afraid of auction being a farce.

	Not afraid of changing my mind:  wd. be going back to original

		thghts. of Party &amp; we publd Bill invitg. discn.

	M-F.’s points.  i) ¼ of 25 m. limit people are old long-distance men.

		Only 3.700 were bought out.  Most don’t want to come back. 

		Shd be possible to devise means of facilitating their return.

	If auction is a farce, Ty. will suffer.  Real help to Ty. is to get it back

		quickly into private hands.



P.M.	Mill stone round necks of rlways. (guaranteed stock).



O.L.	M/T. plan is not a road/rail policy:  law of jungle.  Unregulated

		compn not only betwn. road &amp; rail, but betwn. free &amp; natd

		road hauliers.  “We don’t know the answer:  let jungle work

		it out.”  It’s not a policy.



W.M.	Pt. II in suspense will deter purchaser:  also Labour threats.  Fear there

		will no buyers.



O.L.	Industry will regard suspensory compromise as death of levy.



L.B.	Was never to have come in for 2 years.



P.T.	Bill as now won’t work.  Shan’t sell lorries.  If we try, B.T.C. will be 

		left with a lot on their hands – truncated R.H. Ex., with the worst

		of the assets.  We never pledged ourselves to sell whole of

		R.H. Ex. – only to give those expropriated a chance to come

		back.

	L.B.’s plan.  Raising 25 m. limit will phase existg. R.H. Assocn.  Wd

		disappoint long-distance men who want to resume, but there are

		v. few of them.

	R.H. Ex. cd. fight back v. competn:  wd. not be truncated.

	Favour L.B.’s plan.  Wd phase Tories:  wd. clear ground for negotn on

		rates between rlways. &amp; industry.



R.A.B.	No safeguards in this.  Higher cost of carrying coal.



L.B.	N.C.B. thght. my plan mght. impair new zoned delivery system – fear

		reduced as much as increased charges.  N.C.B. can press B.T.C. –

		they sell them much coal, &amp; cd. put up price v. rlways.



L.	V. strong repns fr. N.C.B. tht. they cdn’t face increased coal freights.

		Shd have to see tht. tribunal protected their posn.

L.B.	Yes:  seekg. agreemt. on this betwn. N.C.B. &amp; B.T.C.



P.M.	Aim shd. be to rid State of the lorries – by sale or by destructn by

		competn.



Sw.	Risk to auction is that so many oil hauliers have invested elsewhere &amp;

		won’t come back into the business, no matter what terms are 

		offered.

	Lucky if we sold 10,000.

	Favour M/T. plan.



P.M.	Wd like to be sure first tht. there’s no way of securing sale.  E.g. by

		hire-purchase, so tht. Labour Govt. w’in 3 yrs. or so wd. not be

		able to confiscate much.



Ch.	Services cd. prs. take some of these lorries which are now laid up

		because of trade recession.



L.B.	The idle vehicles are not the same ones all the time:  it’s a statistical

		thing.  Who runs carrying trade if these go to Forces?  Give 

		Services first claim on what B.T.C. has to sell.



Sw.             	1)	Leave rlways. &amp; natd roads as they are with more flexible 			charges.

	Give them chance to do their best – subject to competn.

	H. Morrison used to say let it compete with free enterprise &amp; see what

		happens.

                   	2)	Tory Party wd. prefer L.B.’s plan wh. fulfils pledge to short-			distance men.

                   	3)	This will last because will not enrage Labour so much.  Indeed, it 		may divide them.

	This plan is better on merits and on politics.

	Suppose you pass L.’s Bill.  Fiasco on the auction.  Leave R.H. Ex.

		operating worst assets.  W’in 12 mos. you free short-distance

		men to compete with them.  We shall have messed up natd 

		industry, let in few private people, and bust the finances.



L-B.	R.H. Ex. chairman asked me on Saty – why not give us our chance

		to compete with free enterprise.



L.	How can you expect them to succeed v. competn when they failed

		as monopoly.



L.B.	They believe they cd. do better with a smaller undertaking.



R.A.B.	M/T. plan wd. react on rlways. &amp; so on Ty., if not on coal price.

	Diffy of getting charging clause right in time.

	Wd prefer to keep old Bill, suspend levy Pt. II., &amp; associate that at

		future date when we see wtr. flexibility of charge does assist

		rlways.  Haven’t seen that clause yet:  can’t pronounce upon it.

		Tho’ it’s now 22/10.



L.B.	The clause in draft.	



R.A.B.	What effect on licensing system.  How give long-distance men sufft

		guarantee they can get back.  Provn not yet worked out.

		We haven’t the basis yet on wh. to adopt a diff. new scheme.



A.E.	Vast reversal of policy.  Can’t take it “unseen”.

	My disposn wd. be to stand by Bill, deferring appln of levy Pt. II.



L.B.	Time factor.  I wd. rather face debate of Address than defend the old

		Bill with suspended Pt. II. levy.



H.C.	We promised H/C. tht. it wd. be first business of new Session.

	Intended to give notice of presentn at once to oust debate on Address.

	Planned to put it thro. H/C. by 6/2. – to free H/L. for Steel.

	If Bill is radically different it wd. be cheatg. to exclude discn on 

		Address.  Nor cd. we take 2nd Rdg. after 1 week.  Time-table

		rested on assumptn tht. House had already seen Bill.



A.E.	We shd. have to treat L.B.’s Bill as a new one.

	V. dangerous to make this reversal unless sure new plan .



P.M.	We can’t make this violent change now.  Eating all our words.

		Shd look foolish.

		    1)	Propose we stick to old Bill, but with Pt. II. levy

			     either out or suspended.  (Decide that alternative later.)

		    2)	Preserve the proposed easement for the rlways.

		    3)	All must do utmost to sell the lorries.  Consider hire-

			     purchase, to spite Socialist threats.  Inducemts. to 

			     avoid farce at auction.





	3.	Saar.



A.E.	Ad. &amp; Schumann broke off conversns – deadlock.  Saar Govt. due to

		announce on Friday electns prohibitg. all G. participn.

		This wd. make Saar soln imposs. &amp; gravely damage Fr-G. relns.

		I got a v. good offer fr. Aden. – handed it to Schumann &amp; 

		pressed him.  Haven’t heard wtr. Fr. Cab. have accepted.

		Elections wd. be p’poned for a year or so.





	4.	Wages Policy:  Engineering Industry.



	Shipbldg. employers have offered 7/6.  Believe workers will accept.



</content>
</cab>
