<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/203/2 images: 20-21</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(78) 77 COPY NO 8012 July 1978CABINETEDMUND-DAVIES COMMITTEE:  NORTHERN IRELAND PAY ANDTHE ROYAL ULSTER CONSTABULARY DUTY ALLOWANCEMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Defence and theSecretary of State for Northern IrelandINTRODUCTION1. This memorandum sets out the likely repercussions on the Army andUlster Defence Regiment (UDR) of the proposed new Royal ulster constabulary (RUC) special allowance and of the different options for introducing it.background. From 1 April 1974 the Armed Forces from Brigadier downwards, thePermanent Cadre of the UDR and part-time members for full days on dutyreceived Northern Ireland Pay (all references to Northern Ireland Pay in this paper are to the Special Allowance paid to the members of the Armed Forcesserving in Northern Ireland) of 50p per day.    This recognised the substantialextra work in unsocial hours in Northern Ireland, and not special dangerscovered by the &quot;X&quot; factor.    Northern Ireland Pay was increased to  1 a day with effect from 1 April 1978.3. From 1 April 1974, the RUC from Chief Superintendent downwards, theRUC Reserve, and p: o rata the part-time RUC Reserve received a SpecialDuty Allowance also of 50p a day.    This recognised the extraordinarycircumstances and special difficulties for RUC officers and their families andnot unsocial hours.    Although the reasons were different, the RUC payment was a consequence of the Army payment, and was paid at the same rate fromthe same date.    The link between the two has until April 1978 been publiclyaccepted;  but when the Northern Ireland Pay was then increased, the RUCallowance was left to the Edmund-Davies Committee.4- The Edmund-Davies Committee emphasised the differences betweenthe RUC and the Armed Forces; in particular that the police officer and his family are exposed to attack for 24 hours a day, with no respite from
c fitting pressure&quot;, whereas the Army have limited tours of duty inNorthern Ireland.    They specifically recommend that the link with NorthernIreland Pay should be broken;  that the special allowance should be  500 peranr-j u payable from 1 September 1978; and explicitly that this should not bedanger money, but in recognition of the &quot;special difficulties facing officersand th?ir families&quot;.5. The Secretary of State for Defence maintains that the Committee&apos;sarguments apply precisely to the locally recruited UDR - full-time and part-time - and that a lessening of the present differential between the emolumentsof the UDR and the Regular Forces could not be justified to the latter. ThePermanent Cadre at present receive 100 per cent of regular Army rates up tothe rank of Corporal and 95 per cent above.    If the  500 rate were extendedto the UDR and not to the regular Army, UDR junior ranks would receive upto  135 per annum more than regular troops.    The differentials at migher ranks would be significantly lessened (eg for a Sergeant, from 4. 5 per cent to 1.7 per cent).    All part-time ranks of UDR would receive 37p per day morethan their regular counterparts when on full-time duty.    He expects very strong political pressure for the larger allowance to be extended to all the armed Forces.6- The options for introducing the RUC allowance are:a. Split the recommended increase of  317 evenly on 1 September1978 and 1 September 1979 ( 341 per annum and  500 per annum).b. Pay  365 (the Northern Ireland Pay) from 1 April 1978 or1 September 1978 and  500 one year later.c. Full payment from 1 September 1978.7- But for the Edmund-Davies Committee all eligible RUC officers wouldnave received  365 per annum from 1 April 1978 in line with Northern IrelandPay.    Were the new allowance paid from 1 September 1978, RUC officers would still only receive  368 in the 12 months from 1 April 1978.    If paralleltreatment for the Armed Forces were conceded an increase would need to bePaid not later than 1 April 1979 (their next Review date).8- Phasing would lessen, but not remove, the immediate problems for theArmy, but could leave the RUC substantially in arrears.F MR MMinistry of Defence12 July 1978

</content>
</cab>
