<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/8/61 images: 332-333</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S1 E C ,R g T.gj.;P. ,(G) (40)261.with OCTOBERj 1940.THE MEANS TEST.Memorandum by the Chancelion of theExchequer.The proposal made by the Minister of Labour inhis Memorandum   of the 10th October (W.PV(G) (40)259)raises a financial issue of great importance.     Thenumber of Unemployment Assistance allowances has fallen considerably since war broke out, and thenumber at present in issue is about 185,000 at anannual cost of  10-g- million.     If the war is followedby severe unemployment, these figures will of courserise steeply.     The same means test also governssupplementary pensions to old age pensioners andwidow pensioners of sixty and upwards, under theOld Age and widow/s Pensions Act, 1940.     When this Actwas in preparation, it was expected that 400,000pensioners would apply for and obtain supplementary pensions at an annual cost of  10*5- million.     Actually1,200,000 pensioners are receiving supplementary pensions at an annual cost of  24 million.     Thereare altogether some 3,000,000 pensioners who mightqualify for supplementation if their financial circumstances justified it.Any change in the household means test mightreact on a number of pensions and allowances paid bythe Service Departments and the Ministry of Pensions,eligibility for which depends inter alia upon a test:of needoNevertheless I am prepared to agree that the household means test should be examined, it being understood that the question whether a person shouldreceive an allowance or supplementary pension, and if so, how much, will continue to depend upon hiscircumstances.     A number of Departments are concernedin the matter apart from the Treasury and Ministry ofLabour, namely, the Ministry of Health and Departmentof Health for Scotland, the Admiralty, War Office andAir Ministry, and the Ministry of Pensions.     I thinkthat the matter, which is one of great complexity indetail, would be most conveniently examined in thefirst instance by a&apos; Committee of officials, under aJl Treasury Chairman.(Initialled)   K.W.COPY NO.    ^WAR CABINET.Treasury Chambers,,. S.W.1.


</content>
</cab>
