<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/75/0 images: 15-17</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Report relating to the Work of the Board of Agriculture for Scotland for the week ending 12th February, 1919.

This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.

I. FOOD PRODUCTION.

The weather during the past week has been generally frosty, with intense cold at night in inland districts. Cultivation has been interrupted, and farmers have turned to other work, such as carting, throshing and potato dressing.

1. Defence of the Realm Regulation 2 M.

During the week compulsory Orders under Defence of the Realm Regulation 2 M. were issued in the following cases:-

(a) Farm of Sucklawridge - Roxburghshire: The attention of the Board was first drawn to this farm by the proprietor&apos;s agents, and after communication with the Kolso Agricultural Executive Committee the Board issued an Order upon the tenant under 2 M. (1) (o) requiring him to cultivate and clean two fields to be put under green crop this season.

(b) Farm of Marcascio, Elgin: The Board took possession of this farm under Regulation 2 M. (1) (a) on 15th August 1918, and in order to ensure the proper cultivation of the holding this season they have issued a further Order under 2 M. (1) (b) taking possession of the crops, stock and implements at present on the farm.

The Board have withdrawn from their occupation of 6 acres of land taken over by them at Benremach Distillery, Elgin. The Distillery and adjacent ground have been sold and the new proprietor has given an undertaking that the land at present under cultivation will continue to be so utilised.

2. Export of Oats from Scotland.

Reports received from farmers, merchants and others engaged in the grain trade go to show that there are large suppliers of feeding and milling oats in the country. It has been represented to the Board that the present restrictions on the export of oats from Scotland should be removed. The Board are satisfied that the need for those restrictions no longer exists and accordingly it has been suggested to the Ministry of Food that the Oats (Scotland and Ireland Restriction) Orders should be revoked at an early date. Meantime licences for the export of both feeding and milling oats to England are being issued freely.

II. ARMY MARES FOR BREEDING PURPOSES.

Steps have been taken by the Board to make this Scheme as widely known as possible amongst farmers and other classes of horse-keepers. The number of applications received to date exceeds 900 and the great majority are for mares of the Light Draught class.

An officer of the Board has visited three of the Romount Depots in England and selected over 40 mares. These animals are now being placed with custodians in the north of Scotland. A further selection will be made at an early date and the mares forwarded for distribution to applicants resident in the south-west and south eastern districts.

III./

 


1* Mor&amp;Y ffirth District.The Board received during the week a deputation representative of farmers from the area of the Moray Firth District Wages Committee, in regard to the decision of that Committee to fix a working week of 60 hours as the basis    ?on which certain minimum rates of wages are to be calculated. The farmers laid stress&quot; on the fact that while the original      -proposal.of the Committee was that the rates should be oal-tculated on the &quot;customary hours&quot; worked in the district, a decision to alter this to a $Q hourj week was come to without any opportunity being given to the persons interested to lodge objections,   The Board have taken Counsel1e Opinion which is to the effect that Committees&apos; procedure was not incompetent but the Board are presently oonsidering tho advisability of referring tho question back to the District Committee for further investigation.2.   ffite aad,Kiprgob. No * 5 * :Tho following minimum rated of wages fixed by the District Wagao Committee for this aj:ea havti now oome into force, vis;21./- per week for boy from 17 to 18, 18/-   &quot;     &quot;       &quot;     a       &quot;   16   w 17. &apos; 15/.. *       &quot;     &quot;       &quot;15   a 16.12/-   u     *       &quot;     M       B   14   0 15. 18/-   &quot;     w      u   woman or girl over 16. 15/-   8     tt      &quot;   girl from 15 to 16. 12/-.   !i     &quot;       *     :&apos;       &quot;     14 &quot;   15.IV.     CQH,ECTT.Office. 01 fm?T]m$...xm STATISTICS relating to ^mCRITLTG.ILojaCTs un&amp;,ey     ?v$^ 9&amp;SSQ.9ll $\til Qr4qr.,w9*The tabulation of the Keturnu for lat January, relating to holdings on which 5 acres or more of potatoes were grown, has&quot; now boon completed, ano. a summary table is appended showing the rosuite.   The quantity returned as con-toumed or delivered during December ie 49,000 tons, as compared with 53,500-tone during December 1517, and with 76,000 tons (on holdings where 1 aero or more of potatoes wore grown; during November 1918-   The quantity returned a.-.i remaining at 1st January on holdings where 5 acres..or more were grown io 545,000 tons, as compared with 417,000&apos; ton-t at let January 1918.III.   WAGES Off AGP.cultural WORK1HS,
TABLE ehowing the Quantities of Potatoes held by Growers (of 5 aores or more) in Scotland on let January 1919 and the Quantities consumed or delivered during December 1918.1. Estimated Quantities remaining on the Premisos on 1st January 191Yax-iety. Quantity.Tons.Abundance Group   ..,.     7000Arran Chief ......... 167000Golden Wonder Group . 20500King Edward Yll..... 78000President Group ..... 55500Up-to-Date Group .... 25000Other Varieties ..... 192000TOTAL   ... 545000 II. Quantities consumed or delivered during December 1910.Yarlotff.	Quantity,	Tons.Abundance Group	1000	20000Golden Wonder Group.	1500King Edward Vll	3500President Group ....	2500Up^to-Date Group ,..	2500Other Varieties ....	17000TOTAL ...   49000The following counties are excluded from the scope of the inquiry:-   Shetland, Sutherland, Ross and Cromarty (except districts of Easter Ross and Blaok Isle), Inverness (except districts of Inverness and Aird), Argyll (except districts of Cowal and Kintyre).The quantity returned as remaining at 1st December on holdings where one acre or more was grown was 743,000 torn. The quantity stated above as remaining at that date on holdings where 5 acres or more wore grown (i.e. the sum of Heads I and II) is 594,000 tons.     On 1st December 1917 the quantity returned as remaining on holdings lunderderff the same class was 471,000 tons.The quantity returned as consumed or delivered during December 1917 was 53,500 tons, as compared with 49,000 tons during December 1918.

</content>
</cab>
