<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/75/0 images: 69-72</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document Is the Property of His Britannic Majeatyra Government). SECRET.fpfe for the War Cabinet by SIR AUCKLAND GEDDES as Minister Co^brdinating Demobilisation,The application of the Out of V/ork Donation Scheme to Ireland was considered by a Conference cf Ministers held at 2, Whitehall Gardens on February 13th last at which a joint memorandum (D.M.83, copy attached) by the Minister of Labour end the Chief Secretary for Ireland was discussed.    The recommendations made by the Confer-ence are subjoined and I submit them for the approval tf the War Cabinet,15.2.19 (signed) A, C. OEDDESExtract from Minutes of a Conference of Ministers held at 2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W, on Thursday, February 13th at 3 p.m.1   ^S&apos;v&apos;!W M*   *a1   W* Mi. (pj *** v&amp;   tjfo C* Ufli *M Md 41* M JThe Conference decided tc recommend:*(1)   That the application of the &quot;Out-of-Workv Donation&quot; scheme to Ireland should be varied to the extent that it should Only apply to demobilised members of H.jY,Forces, insured trades, and certain trades to be scheduled by the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland.(11)   That an immediate grant of  250,000 be made to theIrish Government for the purpose of initiating schemes with a view to providing employment for demobilised members of H.M*Fcrces in Ireland, and that the sum should be administered by a Board presided over by the Chief Secretary and that the Treasury and Ministry cf Labour should nominate members.(Ill)   That on receipt of the necessary Treasury authority, the Chief Secretary, in announcing that a grant of  250,000 had been made by the Treasury, should state that this was an interim grant in respect of the sum which His Majestyrs Government propose to provide for Reconstruction schemes in Ireland.OUT OP WORK DONATION IN IRELAND
THIS DOGU.;::NT IS THE gOggry OF HIS BRITANNIC Iv-AJESTY1 5 GOVERNMENT^WAR CABINET,QUT-of-WQRK DONATION IN IRELAND.Memorandum by the Chief Secretary for Ireland and the *&quot;      &quot;&quot;^ &quot;&quot;minister^of labour&apos;.&quot;&quot;The application of the Out-of-Work Donation Scheme to Ireland on the same conditions as in Groat Britain has resulted in a serivous^ situation,,     The scheme was designed mainly with a view to the in-dustrial situation in Great Britain.     The situation in Ireland was different.     Outside tho Belfast area the amount of war work being done was very small and there has been no substantial general in-creases in wages.     The energies of the people were not devoted to the prosecution of the war and industry had undergone no such revolu-tion as took place in Great Britain.     The Armistice consequently involved little dislocation in Irish industry.     Even in Belfast the   . principal war Industry -shipbuilding- was one that could maintain pro-duction after the Armistice,     Agriculture, the main occupation of the country, was unaffected by the cessation of hostilities,     In almost every corner of Ireland, therefore, the Out-of-Work Donation has ap-appeared as an &quot;inexplicable phenomenon&quot;,     It is called the &quot;idle pay&quot; and the &quot;stop work donation&quot;,     (The ordinary unemployment benefit scarcely affects Ireland because the insured trades have a negligible existence there).     The LaDour Exchange machinery has not been ex-tens Ively used in Ireland because of some hostility of the people to it as well as the lack of industrial employment.     Suddenly the Exchanges and Branch Offices have been found ready, without any ob-vious reason, to distribute to &quot;unemployed&quot; persons, accustomed to bear &quot;unemployment&quot; without their help, sums of money comparing more favourably with what they can earn in their normal occupation.Some facts will illuminate the existing anomalies.   Under the scheme at married man with 5 children can draw 41/- a week; his wife or daughter may be entitled to a further 25/-,   The current wages under the Agricultural Wages Board are for a 54 hour week -men 22/-to 27/-, women 12/- to 16/-.   In Dublin the wages of a labourer range from 25/- to 6.0/-, the average being under 40/-, the average wages of women aro from 12/- to 18/-; domestic servants  16 to  20 per annum. Outside the cities, in occupations other than agriculture, men&apos;s wages range from 16/- to 30/-, women&apos;s from 3/- to 14/-.     In the Ulster linen trade women earn 22/- to 30/- on full time; the trade is going on short time now and women who continue to be employed will not earn more than 12/- to 15/-.     Prom the wages point of view, there fore, it is only in exceptional cases in the cities that the out-of-work donation does not put a premium on idleness,- The basing of the scheme on the Health Insurance system has had abnormal results.     Any person of 15 years of age or more who has ever been employed by another between 1911 and 25th August 1918, at a less remuneration than  160 per annum Is a potential receiver of this donation; when, therefore, it Is recognised that in the rural dis-tricts, and Ireland is mainly rural, practically every person has, owing to the poverty prevailing in the past, been at some time em-ployed by another, it will be seen how far the scope of the scheme extends.     The conditions included in the scheme with the object of eliminating fraud are in Ireland not effective.     In cases where an applicant is admittedly unemployed, the Insurance Commissioners are of opinion that to establish fraud the Ministry of Labour would prac-t    ally have to prove that the applicant was never employed by anyone ; tween 1911 and the 25th August, 1918.    That is an impossible &apos;Wing.     In some parts of the country practically everyone over -   - .o claimed the donation, including many small farmers and their lcms who actually own their own land.   Such persons have in these
particular-months of the year no difficulty in showing that they are &quot;unemployed&apos;1.The Branch Offices in particular in the old days had not a great deal of work to do; now, naturally, they are overwhelmed with work. There are 19 Exchanges in Ireland, 153 existing Branch Offices, and 62 more Branch Offices urgently required if the scheme is to remain unaltered; that is to say that in the machinery appropriate to Ire-land there is one Exchange to 20 Branch Offices, the proportion in Great Britain being 1 to 3.It is difficult to get reliable men in Ireland at the present time to control these Branch Offices, their selection necessarily takes time.We are satisfied that the whole system is&apos;utterly Unsuited to Ireland.     The one fact that the; amounts payable under it for doing nothing exceed the normal earnings of the great majority of potential applicants condemns It.     It is impossible to prevent illegal claims because employers through terrorism or hatred of an alien Government refuse to co-operate.The Trade Unions demand that the &quot;pauperising&quot; of the workers should cease and that work should be provided.    The number of recip-ients of the donation under the present scheme, who are practically all civilians, will shortly reach 1Q0,000 per week.     That figure will probably be maintained as an average for civilians during the currency of the scheme, that is for another four months.     At the average rate of SO/- per head per week (Including the supplementary grant) the expenditure for the next four months will amount to approxi rnately  2,400,000,     Of this sum at least  2,000,000 will be payable to civilians who have not been employed on Government work,There are three courses open:-1, To continue the present scheme unchanged,2, To continue the present scheme in respect of soldiers and munition workers, reducing the donation for other classes,3. To continue the present scheme, but exclude from a date within the near future all classes other than soldiers and munition workers.We recommend that the principle of 3 should be adopted,   por ad-ministrativo reasons, and in orderto facilitate the transition to permanent contributory insurance, the modified scheme will have to include the insured trades.    Munition workors, however, in Ireland form the bulk of insured persons likely to be unemployed so that the principle of 3 would not bo substantially affected&apos;.     It will also be necessary to include any non-insured trades in which the Irish Govem-ment certifies that a substantial amount of unemployment has been directly caused by the cessation of hostilities.   An instance is the Belfast Linon Trade in which only a proportion of workpeople could have been insured as employed on munitions work, i.e. the production of linen for aircraft.   The reduction of Government contracts for aircraft linen has directly created considerable unemployment in.the whole trade which is in consequence going on short time.     In bring-ing such a trado under the modified scheme it would be necessary to take into account any proposals by the trade for working short time.
The adoption of principle 3 must be acoompanied by a reconstruct tion policy on remunerative lines.    The Trade Unions would give their support to this alternative because their attitude is that they wish work and not charity,     There can be no differentiation as to payment for the allotted time between the discharged soldier and ex-war worker in Ireland and the discharged soldier and ex-war worker in Great Britain,      They must be paid alike.     In our judgment it would be difficult to keep from Ireland the whole amount to which she would be entitled for the allotted time under the scheme, but the balance between the amount allotted to the discharged soldier and ex-war worker in Ireland should be devoted in lump sum to Ireland for the purposes of a national reconstruction policy,     Reconstruction is greatly expected and there is a general belief in the possiblli-ties of development in Ireland.  - Resentment at the exclusion of classes not excluded in Great Britain would be overshadowed by reconstruction activity.    The classes really affected by the armies-stico would get the same treatment as in Great Britain,    Those not so affected would get a practical outlet for their energies and a new prospect of general improvement in their conditions of life. Ltuch political recrimination would be disarmed, labour would be con-ciliated and the Department concerned would have a scheme it could administer,(Signod)     R, S. HORNE.IAN MACFHERSON.11,21 Xvj o

</content>
</cab>
