<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/75/0 images: 142-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF aegis BRITANNIC MAJWY?S GOVERNMTA1,1 &quot;&quot;        11.........-  i ii. mill.......... Ill....................I    I     II     I      i    III, JH.............H.I......hi.h4Ii.iIHh    ,li -T. -    -SECRET.    I *t M ;\ if WAR CABINET.MINISTRY OE WAYS AND COB^lCATIONS BILL Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer,I circulate the following Memorandum on the subject of the Ministry of Ways and Communications Bill for the consideration of the War Cabinet.(Intd.)   A.C.Treasury,, S.W,!,Ibth February, 191?.I. Finance.1. So far as I am aware the question of the financial arrangements for the State acquisition of railways, if that policy is decided upon, has not yet been considered.2.   It would no doubt be possible to pay the purchase money for the various undertakings in the shape of direct Exchequer obligations forming part of the ordinary national debt, to provide the working expenses of the railways on the Votes and to pay the receipts into the Exchequer aa revenue.    And, this appears to be what is contemplated   by the Draft Bill,     But it would in my epinion be very much better to keep railway finance as a.whole in a separate compartment, letting the stock issued for the acquisition form a separate corpus^ the service of which, would be provided for primarily out of the railway revenue, though a Consolidated Fund guarantee in the event of that revenue proving insufficient would no doubt be necessary,3.   It appears to me, however, to be essential before Parliamentary authority for the acquisition of the railways is asked for that the whole question of the financial arrangements should be thoroughly explored and a considered proposal laid: before Parliament.4.   If it is necessary to obtain Parliamentary approval for the principle of State purchase in the present Bill, I think it is very desirable that this should be done slmpliciter, and that no attempt should be made to formulate the precise financia?, arrangements but that these should be made the subject of a separate Bill to be introduced when the acquisition actually takes place.II.   Treaw/..ry consent.In the Telegraph Act 1863 purchase of undertakings (Section 4), rates to be charged for telegrams (Seotion 15&quot;), leasing of an undertaking, or part of one [Section 14), contracts with newspapers for special rates (Section 16), were subject to the approval of the Treasury.NO doubt an Order in Council authorising the purchase of railways etc. under clause 4 would Only be passed with Treasury consent.
104It certainly would seem as though Treasury consent should be required for the directions of the Minister under most of thetheads in Clause (3) (e) - e,g. (i) rates and charges (ii) rates of pay, (lv) and (v) Works, and for the rates, fares, tolls and charges where an undertaking is acquired under clause (4) (subclause 4); &apos;III.    Minor Alterations.- &apos;Clause 3 (l) (b) An Order in Council is necessary under !?he Regulation of the Forces Act 1871 (Power to take possession in a military emergency) and should I think be required here.Clause 3 (l) (f) line 12,   the Minister should bo substituted for the Treasury.Clause 4(2)   I- do not know why a Court of Arbitration is introduced here.     Similar cases are to be decided under 3 (2) by the Railway and Canal Commission.     I propose that the Railway and Cp.nal Commission adjudicate under both sections.Cla-vce 4 (3)   I must consider this section further, but if the. amount of the securities is to be decided by an external authority, that authority should be the Railway and Canal Commission.. - (Initialled)-,  A. C,   -18th February, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
