<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/75/0 images: 421-421</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/. 0fIS DOCUMENT IS THE, PROPERTY OF. HI3 BRIT AMI C MAJESTY\ 3 gQYIilT).:E. C...R.E T. . .L.   I concur generally in the Memorandum G.234 by the president of the Board of Education on this subject.2..   I would suggest, however, that to the outline of possible branches of the Department of Research there should&apos;, be added at the earliest possible moment a branch dealing with Educational Research under an Advisory Council of its own.   In this department of public work there are many questions of first-rate importance positively crying out for careful and impartial,1 investigation.   There is probably more need in this branch than in any other for dissociation of the work of investigation from the routine of administrative work.   The administrative depart-ments cannot undertake this work of investigation without a considerable.addition to their existing staff-.   Nor is it desirable that they should.   The investigation of fundamental problems should be uninfluenced by consideration of the adminis-trative necessities of the different parts of the United -Kingdom,,: and should be conducted without reference to these necessities by persons of special knowledge and experience drawn indifferently from any part of the country.   The practical application of any results obtained will be matter for the consideration of the administrative authorities and of all persons engaged in the work of Education..3.   With the. Education hi Branch of the Research Depart-.-&quot; jjient might usefully be associated the collection of inforrna-tion with legard to the educational system and changes of system in other countries, as well as experiments which are being conducted in various parts of the world.   The information available in this country regarding these matters is exiguous in the extreme.   Neither the Department of Education in Scotland nor, I believe, any of the Education Departments in Ireland have.at present any machinery for this purpose-.   They are dependent upon ouch information as may be gleaned from the Reports of the Office of Special Enquiries and from Reports of the &quot;Board of Education..  Even if the Office referred to were more fully organised it obviously cannot serve the purposes of the other parts of the United Kingdom co well as one Com* prehensive organisation acting for the country as a whole a is an integral part of an Educational Research Department under the Ministry of Research.   This, matter also is pressing.-. Either- such a common body must be created without delay, or in Scotland at least steps must be taken to construct machinery both for the purpose of collecting information and for con-ducting investigations .   Clearly a common organisation for the United Kingdom would be the more economical and I think in every way the more satisfactory alternative,TO.-CABINET.,T. 6863.A MINISTRY OF .RESEARCH.(Memorandum by the Secretary for, Scotland(Sgd,)   ROBERT munro.&apos;Scottish/Office,20th. February, 1913*

</content>
</cab>
