<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/75/0 images: 511-512</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(Ai8 Document is tho Property of Hia Britamiio Majesty1 a Government SECRET.STAR     CABINET.(Memorandum by Mlnister of Labour).COAL STHI1CB   AID   UNEMPLOYMENT   DONATION.If a general or local coal strike takes place it can only be a question of a few days before numbers of wori-people are thrown out of work through shortage of ooal;   the position would rapidly grow worse and in a short time the great majority of wage earners would bo without work.Tho question arises whether unemployment donation is to be paid to workpeople who thus become unemployed.      The present practice follows the rulos governing unemployment insurance.    Workpeople rendered unemployed by a trade dispute do not got out-of-work donation if they are persons employed in the establishment in which the dispute takes place, whether or not thoy are deliberately taking part in it. Donation, however, is payable to workpeople in other es-tablishments who are thrown out of work as an indirect result of a trade dispute.      The question hae not hitherto boen raised on so large a scale as is now possible, and it is for the Cabinet to decide wuether unemployment donation should be paid in the event of a ooal stoppage,   The work-people who would be unemployed fall into tho following classes:-(a) The ooal miners and others employed at tho collierios, and such othor classes as. might striko,, such as Railway servants and Transport Workers;(b) Persom. receiving employment donation at thetune when the strike took place, whose unemployment was not due to the strike;(c) Demobilised members of H.M.Forces, among whom would be included great numbers in (a) and (b);/(d)
fd) Persons thrown out of employment as an indirect result of the strike;(e) Persons thrown out of employment after the date whon the strike occurred, through causes not proximately connected with the strike.It would be impossible for the Exohangee to differentiate between (d) and (e).A ruling is required from the Cabinet as to whether unemployment donation is to be refused to any or all of the above classes in addition to (a).If donation Is to be refused it will be necessaryto alter the existing rules.If donation is to be paid to the large number of additional claimants, which will be produced by such astrike, it will be necessary at once to attempt to make .emergency arrangements for providing additional staff and accommodation at the Exchanges.      This will in any oase bevery difficult, and if the normal machinery or transport is seriously interrupted, it may be impossible for someExchanges to obtain sufficient staff to pay donation,(Signed)   P* S- HOME,2.3.2 o 15?,

</content>
</cab>
