<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/75/0 images: 542-543</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majestys Government.Printed for the War Cabinet, February, 1919.DELEGATION d&apos;EsTHONIE EN FltANOE,7, rue de 1&apos;Alboui, Paris,17tli February, 1919.I have tlie honour to forward you a copy of Memorandum given by the Esthonian Delegation to the Peace Conference. Hereby, I beg to add that, according to supplementary news, an arrange-ment is already made between the governments of Esthonia, Latwia and Lithuania for a common struggle against Eussian Bolshevism. On the basis of such arrangement the Esthonian troops, having cleared their own country of Bolsheviks, have entered Latvia&apos;s territory on the whole front to a distance of about 50 kilometres, whereas behind this front the Lettish Government is organizing the Lettish forces. Further, besides Finland and Sweden, Denmark has also given permission to enrol volunteers, and iu a short time 1,000 men were enlisted.I have the honour to be,With the highest consideration, Sir,Your most obedient humble Servant,S. POSKA, Chief of the Esthonian Delegation, Minister of Foreign Affairs.To the Right Honourable Winston Churchill,British Delegation.Esthonian Legation.NOTE CONCERNING ORGANIZED OPPOSITION TO RUSSIAN BOLSHEVISM.Following on the trials and misery resulting from the war which has just been brought to a close, humanity is faced with a new danger, which threatens to envelop the world, the menace of Bolshevism. Bolshevism has assigned to itself the task of establishing communism throughout the world by means of blood and iron. The peril to Esthonia is imminent, owing to her position in the immediate vicinity of the very cradle of Bolshevism.Bolshevism relying solely on force for the realization of its schemes, the adoption of prompt measures to combat it by force of arms was necessary. Immediately, therefore, that the Bolsheviks became masters of Russia, Esthonia cut herself free, declared her independence, and set about tbe organization of her Government and that of a regular army, with the result that she has been successful in checking the Bolshevist Red Army, and completely clearing the country of this pernicious element.Notwithstanding these results, the Esthonian Government is fully alive to the fact that, in order to preserve the country from renewed Bolshevist attack, the success already attained is insufficient and other and more important measures will be required.Now that the Peace Conference is actually debating what steps should be taken to prevent further bloodshed, and to anticipate renewed outbreaks of violence among the peoples of pre-war Russia, and has decided to convene a special conference in the Island of Prinkipo, these measures would appear of special urgency, it being impossible to foresee the results of this conference, and whether the Bolsheviks are prepared to abandon their aggressive attitude and lay down their arms.On the other hand, it should be borne in mind that Peace has not yet been signed, that the League of Nations is not yet organized, and that the German menace must still be taken into account.Although Germany, constrained by the victories of the Allies, has been obliged to evacuate Esthonia, Lithuania, and Livonia, she has by no means renounced her schemes to subject, them to her domination. To this end, she supplied the Bolsheviks with arms, and placed every difficulty in the way of the organization of our National defence, even going as far as to damage such weapons as she could not remove. The following statement was made by Winnig, member of the Social-Democratic Party in the Reichstag, in the capacity of envoy-plenipotentiary of the Ebert Govern-nient to the Baltic Provinces, when addressing the Esthonian delegates: &quot; If you do not belong to Russia, you must belo^n to us, Russia is our principal market, and we cannot permit you, in the character of independent  &apos; jstfs, to separate us from her.&quot;When the Bolsheviks, notwithstanding the avowed support of Germany, not only failed to conquer Esthonia, but were&apos; forced to retire beyond her frontiers, tbe German Government chaDged its tactics, and attempted to conciliate Esthonia by. offering to supply her with arms(B19/118)   50  2/19   H&amp;S  6890wo
and funds to carry on the war. &quot; From the Allies you will receive nothing but promises,&quot; declared Ebertfs representative to the Esthonian representatives, &quot;but we can supply you with , all you require; let us forget our former emnity and be friends.&quot; The trick however, failed. We are well aware that at the first favourable opportunity Germany is prepared to renew her endeavours, and that in certain circumstances she would not hesitate to support them by armed forceIt is therefore indispensable that we Bhould at all times be in a position to defend ourselves. To this effect the following measures should be adopted: (1.) The menace to Livonia, Lithuania, Ukraine and Georgia being equal to that to Esthonia and the above-mentioned newly constituted States being similarly inspired by the desire to protect themselves against Bolshevik contamination, they should be united by an Agreement to co-operate in opposing the common enemy. It would be in the interests of Poland and Finland to join with these States to combat the Bolshevist peril.(2.) Taking into account that the afore-mentioned States, even united, would be unable to offer effective opposition to active Bussian Bolshevism, and that the menace is not only to us but to the whole civilized world, it would appear desirable that in order to prevent this scourge spreading beyond the borders of the republic of Eussian Communist Soviets, the League of Nations should render assistance to the Esthonian Republic, and that, uutil the organization of the League, this support should be provided by the Allied Powers represented at the Conference.Assistance to the Esthonian Republic should be rendered as follows: (a.) By supplying her with arms, war materiel and necessary technical appliances. (J.) By granting her the necessary credit.(c.) By authorizing the calling up of volunteers in such places as the Esthonian Government may consider possible and desirable.Inspired by the knowledge that it was fighting in the defence of its own country, and that there was no fear of its sacrifices serving only to force it back under the yoke of a divided Russia, and deprive it of the independence it actually enjoys, the Esthonian people would display tenfold energy in the struggle against Bolshevism.For the above reasons., we regard it as our duty urgently to represent to the Representatives at the Peace Conference, the unanimous demand of our people that the independence of the Esthonian Republic should be fully recognized;In the name of the Esthonian Delegation,(Sd.)  S. POSKA,President of the Esthonian Delegation,    \ Minister for Foreign Affairs.In conformity with the original,(Sd.) Illegible,Delegate.Pabis, .     .12th February.

</content>
</cab>
