<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/75/0 images: 585-598</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
In tills memorandum an attempt has been made tf) outline the trend of American opinion tovarda Great Britain from the signature of the armistice \/ith Germany to the return of the President from Paris. The President and Congress.President Wilson ha8 been abroad during a considerable, part of this period, and many papers, and the public as a whole, have been content to suspend judgment upon external af* fairs nuring his absence.     But Senators and Representatives have shown no such restraint;   indeed, they have found in the foreign relations of the United States a suitable field for political manouevring and for attempting to &quot;punish&quot; the Presi.-dent -Lr. hiIson, during his two Administrations, has carried some steps further the longstanding Presidential practice of making encroachments upon the pov-er of Congress.     Congress naturally resents these inroads, and angrily charges him with dictatorial conduct;   this frame of mind, which is wore or less shared by members of both parties,, is carefully exploited by the Republicans for political purposes.Last spring, when resentment seemed particularly:strong, a determined attempt was made, by means of charges of ineffi-ciency and corruption, to wrest from the President seme part of his control ever the war preparations.     The attempt failed,and.Confidential(February 25th. 1919)Political &quot;Intelligence Department%foreign Office.United States /007,
and: lir, wilson, by sec tiring the passage of the -Overman hill,/ obtained still greater freedom of action.But the Republicans were not daunted, and in Hoyember, as a result of elections which the President claimed in ad-rancd to regard as a vote of confidence in himself, they 09-cured a majority in both houses, a prospect of smbarrasing kr* Uilson, and renewed hopes of capturing the Presidency in the election of 1920.Thus two factors, Jealousy and politics, havo dominated the concluding sittings of the old Congress. the Presidents Visit to Durr-ce.The&apos;announcement of Mr. \/ilson*s intention to visit Europe aroused a short sj?&apos;.:-rm cf&quot; oraidoisn in Congress, and in some newspapers, which increased in violence- tf&amp;on the eps-oific purposes of his mission remained, undisclosed.     The President, while determined to bring back from Paris some-thing which he cftuld justly claim as a victory, did not yet know v3sre he might succeed and where he might fail, and he was resolved., by reticence at that time, to avoid the subse-quent necessity of admitting failure.     But this attitude ran counter to public curiosity, and provoked in Senators and Congressmen an uncomfortable feeling that their counsel and advice *?as lightly esteemed.     Their annoyance was further aggravate^ aa the Conferences proceeded, and no exclusive information was vouchsafed to them.     And so they gave vent to their irritation in connection with such subjects as Ireland, British Trade Policy^ the American iavy and the League of Nation a, handling each subject in the manner most calculated to appeal to their constituents and tt express
and jter. Wilson, by securing the-passage of the. Overman. Bail,: obtained still greater freedom of action.But the Republicans were not daunted, and in November, as a result of elections which the President claimed in ad-van ce to regard as a vote of confidence in himself, they oe-cured a majority in both houses, a prospect of smb arras in g hr, wilson,. and renewed hopes of ce.pt.ur.ing the Presidency in the election of 1920.Thus two factors, jealousy and politics, have dominated the concluding sittings of the sld Congress, $he President&apos;s Visit to &amp;urrpe.The&apos; announcement of kr. \7ilsen*s intention to Visit Europe aroused a short s^trm of&quot; oratd.od.sm, in Congress, and in some newspapers, which increased in violence-tt&amp;en tho eps-oific purposes of his mission remained undisclosed.     The President, v/hile determined to bring back from Paris some-thing which he could justly claim as a victory, did not yet kno^ v3sre he might succeed an a where he might fail, and he was resolved., by reticence at that time, to avoid the subse-quent necessity of admitting failure.     But this attitude ran counter to public curiosity, and provoked in Senators and Congressmen an uncomfortable feeling that their counsel and advice ^as lightly esteemed.     Their annoyance v/ao further aggravated ae the Conferences proceeded, and no exclusive information was vouchsafed to them.     And so they gave vent to their irritation in connection uith such subjects as Ireland, British Trade Policy^, the American Afavy and the League of Nations, handling each subject in the manner most calculated to appeal to their constituents and tt express
their injured feelings.These speeches roust be read with an eye to the under-lying political motives, to the habitual intemperance and irresponsibility of many Congressional, speakers, and to the constitutional and practical limits of Congressional action. Congress oannfct enforce any policy upon an unwilling Presi-dent;   but it can seriously embarrass him by refusing the legislation which he desires.     It mil n^t do this, however, unless confident of public support;   and in order to ascer-taih the state of public feeling, it will look, not to the speeches of its ovn members, but to more reliable sources ftf information, especially the press.Bsridence derived from such sources leads to the con-elusion that the skilfully managed attempt by the Repuhli-oan Party, in Congress and on the public platform, to dis-oredit the Presidents foreign policy has not yet succeeded; and that, while the campaign is still in full sv/ing, and the issue still in dtubt, there is no present ground for saying that the Republican Majority in Congress will be put by public opinion in a position to render that policy abortive. The President alv/ays runs ahea^ of his party;   as a politi-cian, he is as skilful as his opponents, and he has strong oejfcds to play.ffgelinff Towards Great Britain.Feeling towards Great Britain has been materially im-proyed by the war.     The part played by the British lapire in securing the decision is now widely understood, though in some quarters there is still reluctance to admit it, and a disposition to allocate the praise to every section of
the Empire rather than to England.     In ether quarters, however, there ate indications of real friendship, appre-ciation, anil gratitude.The growth of proKBritish sentiment is full of en-encouragement;   hut it would not ho safe to rely upon it in a tight corner.     There is still a large mass of anti-British prejudice:   there are many enemies awaiting a favourable opportunity for attacking us, and not a few indications of probable friction. Ireland.f.[. The unsolved Irish question remains the -principal rallying p*int for the enemies of Great Britain.    Ameri-cans of non-Irish descent have, during the months in which the United States has been at vvar, bestowed less attention and sympathy upon Irish agitators, partly through reluctance to embarrass an Associated Power, part-ly from a conviction that Ireland has repudiated in great measure its share in the burden of the war, and partly throu^a a better understanding of the British people and of their difficulties with- regard to the Irish situation.But the Irish-American leaders have been merely marking time until the end of the war, and though they have found it expedient to give less public expression to their hostility to England, they have not failed to continue their agitation beneath the surface.    New that fighting has ceased, their enmity is again beginning to reveal itself.At veil attended meetings in Now &quot;iork City, Cardinal CvtConnell, Governor -hitman, Ju-Age Cohilan, PatrickEcCartan
kcCar-tar? and other leaders in strongly- worded speeches, oall upon President \/ilson to demand at the Peace Conference &quot;self-determinat ion for the people of Ireland.&quot;    From Bes-ton, Philadelphia, Chicago and San Francisco come reports of increased Irish agitation;   and at jjew Orleans a Roman Catholic Bishop made objectionable referents to Ireland at the victory celebrations on Thanksgiving Day.Throughout the country, the Irish case,, embellished with grossly exaggerated figures of Irish recruiting and Irish casualties and with stories of British oppression, is being presented to partisan audiences, which reject every reasonable statement of the facts as anti-Irish propaganda. At these meetings, in which the Roman Catholic clergy have taken an active, but not a violent part, resolutions aro carried urging the President to advance the claims of Ireland in Paris.The American press, as distinct from the Irish-Ameri-can and Hearst papers, has shown considerable apathy to-wards this agitation, and the Irish have not yet made good the ground which they have lost during the war;   but the solidarity of Irish and Catholic opinion on the question of Irish government cannot be ignored.     Though a minori-ty, it is an influential minority, and its singleness of purpone gives it undue weight at a time when other issues in the United States are obscure and undefined.Indeed no American politician dare ignore its voting-power, and this fact chiefly explains the constant veutila-tion s-  Irish vojyfaiAation of Irish grievances in Congress. Larly in February for example a resolution expressing
the hope that the Peace Conference &quot;will favourably consider the claims of Ireland to the right-&apos;- of -self-determination&quot; v/ae favourably reported by the Foreign Affairs Committee of the house;   it had not yet been adopted at the date of writing.The IrisJWjnerican Catholic combination is likely to receive some added support from German sympathisers.&apos;    Avowed pro-German ism is not now- tolerated in the United States, and undoubtedly a very large number of German-Americans and for-mer friends cf Germany have--permanently renounced their sym-pathy with a country with which the United States is at watf; but others must still secretly adhere to their&apos;former views, and their most ready opportunity for giving practical ex-presaion to their hostility is by supporting the irish^Ameri&quot;-,oans.Cemmerc ial Rivalry.The recrudescence of commercial rivalry between Great Britain and the United States also fsivee ground for appre-hensioni     The publication in the United States of the re-vised list of British import restrictions supplied the Hearst press with an opening for a bitter attack-    The restrictions were also.discussed in the Senate, and an embargo on the ex-port of American raw materials to Great Britain was suggested as a means of retaliation.     This proposal however, was sti-fled by the opposition of Senators representing agricultural, and cotton districts.A few days later Senator weeks of M^&amp;achusaotts^ on be--half5- of the boot and shoe manufacturers in his constituency, introduced a resolution in the Senate asking the Stits Ee-*
partment what steps had heen taken t* secure a modification of the British embargo on American boots and shoes.     Sever-al senators of both parties spoke strongly in support cf the resolution.     Senator Reed, who is generally unfriendly stated that no sooner was the war won than Great Britain pro-eeeded selfishly to put up trade bars against the very coun-ktry that went to her rescue. Other Senators, however, spoke en behalf of Great Britain, and the resolution was shelTed.Except in the Hearst papers, press comment on the de-batu was friendly,   and perhaps the agitation need not be taken toe seriously.     There is, however, a growing appre-hension in American commercial circles that present British pcxicy foreshadows a permanent protective tariff;   and the new embargo list, ootsp3.ed with the recent reduction in shipping rates, is interpreted in unfriendly quarters as the commencement of a general Anglo-American rate and oem* meroial war.     There ia some danger that these apprehension9 &apos; .... ana perversions may be used by Republicans as an argument in favour of higher American tariffs, and at the seme time in*-jure Anglo-Americai! friendship.P,r rir^jmo^^JJi^^amC, a,. flr-afs&amp;.*American public opinion as a whele dees not seem tohareXHe has since asserted that Great Britain is using the ships that ought to be bringing bac^ American troops for rehab ilutatinjj her trade.xxThe Hew York &quot;World&quot; reminded Senator weeks that a complaint against a Protectionist policy came afcconglff from a member&apos;of hie party. &amp;4m*-^ &amp;i
have concerned itself   ith the details of the peace settle-mei.it1.. &apos; doubtless there are some individualsa few .&amp;a$* tern, papers which have made a , tudy of the&quot; questions involvs but ihe&apos;prcvincial press and the general - public.- frankly do : not understand them,, and except in so far as they are moved by perby considerations or inherited convictions they seem pre pax ed to accept guidance from t$.e President..     A good dea] has been heard in Congress of leniency to Germany, of the league of hat ions and. of the Freedom of the Seas;   but it must be recognised that those Congressional Speakers have been influenced by their approval or disapproval of the President, rather than by their estimate of the merits of each part icu; ar. quostion.It is too early to appraise the reception given to the draft covenant of the League of Nations.     when it was first received in the United States, the papers, while gen-erally showing no great enthusiasm, seemed inclined to be. favourable^.    The Democratic papers emphasized the his-toric importance of the document and regarded, it ay a good beginning.     The Republican papers were critical, but moderate, as though averse from committing themselves un-til sure of the trend of public opinion.During the .iay s that elapsed between the publication of the Draft and the completion cf. this Memorandum, oppo-s it ion to the League seemed to be gathering momentum;    it was being att -.cke ; on constitutional .,rounds, wnd as in-volving a final abandonment of the traditional American policy of a on- in t er for on c e by the United States with europe and by the juropoau Po- ers - - ith Central and SouthAmerica.
America.The American Naval Programme..During the President1 s absence in europe, Fir. Daniels, the Secretary Of the Navy, has invited Congress to apprsve a programme of naval construction designed to make the United States Navy, in default of any general agreement as to tho limitation of armaments, &quot;incomparably the greatest Navy in the world,,&quot;     During the debates in the House, the Naval Bill was warmly oppesed by many Republicans and by a few Democrats;   and much was &quot;heard about threats to Great Bri- . tain and &quot;the big stick&quot; for the Peace Conference.     An un-publisheft telegram iiad^een sent to Mr. Daniels by the Presi-dent, the purport of which was understood to have been that the rejection of the Bill would be fatal to his negotiations at Paris.     Opponents of the measure were therefore undoubt-edly actuated by a desire to embarrass the President rather than by any special goodwill towards the British Navy or dislike of a large American Navy.The Bill, with an amendment postponing certain construc-tion until after 1st June 1920, eventually passed by a large majority in the house, and after a lively debate will be carried in the Senate.     The new York &quot;Times&quot; is almost certainly right in stating that the Naval Programme has full public support.\ihat then is its purpose, and why did the President re-gard the passage of the Bill as essential to his plans?   Re-publicans argue thac Lr. Wilson only desires to impress the British Delegates at Paris * ith the probable consequences of a race in Naval Armaments, and thereby persuade them to surrender
SURRENDERsurrender Great Britain&apos;s Naval predominance to the League of Nations,   However this may he - and Republicans seldcm correctly interpret the President&apos;s purposes, it is certain that American opinion, having learned the lesson of Eritish Sea-Power during the present war, really desires the creation of an American Navy commensurate with the present power of the United States in the World0Hr. Wilson knows this, and he knows that the present is a favourable time for a policy cf Naval Expansion -a policy which may be more difficult to sustain and might hove been impossible to initiate later t?n.   He is a good patriot&apos; and a goo,&apos;1 politician, and no further explanation seems to be required.THE LABOUR situation there have been a numb or of racent strikes -   among them a strike cf garment workers and harbour workers in New York City, a strike of Shipyard workers at Philadelphia and at Oakland (Cal.), a street-car strike in Kansas City and several stoppages at New Orleans, - and in the Western State cf Washington there has been pronounced labour unrest ef &quot;Bolshevik&quot; tendency.    But the situation is not at pre-sent unduly disquieting, though the future prospects give ground for some apprehension.Some employers are adopting a more conciliatory at-attitude towards their employees.     At the Atlantic City Commercial Congress, for instance, in December last iirs Rockfqiler recommended the acceptance by capital of an en-ligh^-i&quot; \
ylightened  n&amp;uets*ial p^ograrnrae, and hie plan j,&apos;as v/armly re-ceived.     Again, Industrial Councils have already &quot;been set up, in the plants of the Bethlehem Steel Corporation.     Among other employers on the other hand is reported a disposition to repudiate the recognition of collective bargaining so generally accorded during the war, t6 suspend war work and discharge staffs without due consideration of the hardship involved, .and to attempt to reduce wages before the cost of living has fallen.Moreover, unemployment, though at present not serious, is admitted to be on the increase, and with its growth may spread a certain revolutionary feeling which has already made its appearance in scattered places, especially in those where production had been particularly inflated by the war.The &quot;Industrial workerb of the World&quot; and the &quot;rump&quot; of the Socialist party (five of whose leaders have recently been convicted of sedition and, disloyalty under the Dspion-age Act, and whose membership is largely composed of German and Russian Jews and other workers of foreign extraction) are endeavouring to exploit this discontent;   but their ac-tivities are being zealously watched by the authorities, by public opinion, and by the American Federation of Labour, As a result of the recent troubles.in the west, fifty alien agitators have been deported by the Federal Government;   a recent attempt to stampede a Chicago Labour Congress into an endorsement of Bolshevism was repudiated by the saner el-eraents:   the Press is constantly warning the public of the danger of &quot;Bolshevism&quot;, and a movement is on foot - oup.portedby
Y.y the American ^federation of Labour - to restrict im.ai-gration in order to prevent the accessidi of newly arrived foreigners to the ranks of the &quot;Bolsheviks&quot; and a further aggravation of unemployment.     Thus the revolutionary troupe, which represent a very small propoartIon of the population, are at present well in hand.The movement towards the formation of an American La-bour Party with a political platform io ^eveloping at some speed, in spite of the determine opposition of iir. Gompers and the majority of his very conservative organisation. The platform of the Chicago &quot;Independent Labour party&apos;&quot; whose moving spirit is John Fitzpatrick, has been endorsed by the Amalgamated Garment Workers - a Union with a considerable membership. - an-&apos; a new Labour Party has been formed, in New York.     Organised. Labour in California and Minnesota has an-nounced its intention of entering the political field.The political movement has received some impetus from the alignment with Labour of the group of Socialists which, under tho leadership of 8pargo and Russell, seceded from the old Socialist Party when it pledged itself to oppose the war;   it also gains support from the more radical elements of labour which distrust the recent association between idr. Goimpers as - the Administration or arc impatient of the con-servative method, e of the jaxecutive of the American I^edera-tion of Labour.Tha^He- York t\merioBni[ and, the hearst Papers.The promises of those who argued, that if full Brit ion cable facilities wor*- restored to -the hoar at papers they would abandon their former eainity to this country have notbe on
feoen fulfilled.     The Hearst papers are, if possible, even mere hostile to-dav vthaa at any period during the war.     In the League of Rations for example       Hearst discloses a soheme $f British propagandists &quot;to entangle the United States in a perpetual alliance in which they arc to olay the part of Canada or Australia, protecting the so-called hot her country from trade competition by wicked European rivals and sawing secon1 fiddle while the orchestra plays !Britanniairules the &quot;Oaves&quot;&apos;.     In one of-its many attacks on the Bri-tish Jdavy a hearat paper remarks &quot;the British Navy is a colony thief.&quot;The defeat of Germany, hr. hearst explains in the fol-Xowing manner:   &quot;General Per shin/? di soovered that the Bri-tish Arsy did not intend fighting.     He simply called his American boys in, mapped out his plan of battle and. then went ahead, and. won the war without any talk about it.&quot;These are but samples of a skilfully conducted and vitriolic campaign.     Whereas most educated Americans have no delusions as to the methods employed by IvAr* hearst nor the worthlossness of his opinions, his papers enjoy an im-menoe circulation amoin? certain strata of the population.

</content>
</cab>
