<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/15/0 images: 112-123</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
felS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1949SECRET Copy No. 44CM. (49)15th conclusions cabinet 15 (49)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1?on Thursday, 24th February, 1949, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Chancellor of theExchequer.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. J, Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. A. Woodburn, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food (Item 5).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Item 1).The Right Hon. Sir hartley shawcross K.C., M.P., Attorney-General (Item 1).Mr. J. Freeman, M.P., Joint Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry ofSupply (Item 5).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. A. Johnston.36722-1b
CABINET 15 (4!minute no.134567ContentsSubjectParliamentBusiness in the House of Commons.Private Members&apos; Bills.British North America Bill.Political Activities of Civil ServantsCandidature in Local Government Elections.Indonesia................Burma  ....................European Economic Co-operation ....European Long-term Programme.Western Union ............Austria ....      ............Recognition of New Political Parties.798080818183
Parliament.Business inthe House ofCommons.Private Mem-bers&apos; Bills.(previous reference:CM. (49) 12thConclusions,Minute 1.)British north america Bill.(previous reference:C.M.(49)9thConclusions,Minute 3.)1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.On Friday, 25th February, the Minister of Agriculture wouldadvise the House of Commons to reject the Protection of Animals(Hunting and Coursing Prohibition) Bill. If time remained forconsideration of the Secretary of State for Wales and Monmouth-shire Bill, the Minister of Health would indicate the Governmenfsopposition to the Bill.The Lord President drew attention to a motion by Sir AlanHerbert, M.P., and others inviting the House of Commons to defergiving a Second Reading to the British North America Bill on thefround that the procedure under which the people of Newfoundlandad agreed to incorporation in Canada was the subject of an appealto the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council. He had. consulted the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations and the attorney-General, and they proposed that the Government should advise the House to proceed with the Bill notwithstanding the-appeal. The Canadian Parliament had completed the action required of it, and the time-table required that the Bill should be-passed by 31st March, 1949.In discussion, it was stated that the Judicial Committee wouldprobably dismiss the appeal, but there was a remote possibility thatthey might hold that the Bill conflicted with the provisions of theStatute of Westminster and that, as a matter of law, the Statute of westminster was a conveyance of rights to the independent countries of the Commonwealth which could not now be withdrawn by theUnited Kingdom Parliament.The Cabinet-Agreed that the Government should proceed with theBritish North America Bill, notwithstanding the appealwhich had been lodged with the Judicial Committee of the privy Council against the incorporation of Newfoundlandin the Confederation of Canada.PoliticalActivitiesof CivilServants.(previous reference:C.M.(48)24thConclusions,Minute 2.)Candidaturein LocalGovernmentElections.2. The Lord President said that there had for some time beena rule that officers of the Ministry of Health and certain otherDepartments in close touch with local authorities should not standas political candidates for election to local authorities. Certainofficers of the Central Office of Information now wished to stand asParty candidates in local authority elections. The Permanent Headof the Central Office of Information was of the opinion that, in viewof the character of his Departments work and the allegations ofpolitical bias which were sometimes made against it, the rule which obtained in the Ministry of Health and elsewhere should also beapplied in the Central Office of Information. The Treasuryendorsed this view. Since candidates for local authority membershipoften had some form of Party backing, even if they called themselves&quot; Independent,&quot; it seemed right that the rule should apply to any kind of candidature for election to local authority membership.The Cabinet-Agreed that officers of the Central Office of information should not stand for election to local authorities.36722-1 b 2
Indonesia.(previous reference:C.M.(49)10thConclusions,Minute 2.)3. The Foreign Secretary explained that the Dutch ForeignMinister had on the previous day explained to the British Ambassadors-dor at The Hague and to representatives of the other Brussels treaty powers that the Dutch Government had decided to invite the indonesians to attend a round-table conference at The Hague on12th March, with a view to the transfer of sovereignty to Indonesiaon 1st May, 1949. An invitation to the conference was being issued to the &quot; President of the Eepublic &quot; and also to the United states representative on the United Nations Commission. The transfer of sovereignty at a reasonably early date would represent a substantialmove forward; but details of the Dutch plan were not yet available and there remained the danger that, in detail or in the manner ofits presentation, the plan might lead to difficulties with the security council. The Council might then be urged to take drastic action with consequences which could not be foreseen.Attention was drawn to the desirability of explaining theposition to the United Kingdom High Commissioners in Delhi andKarachi, so that, if the Dutch plan was broadly acceptable, its meritscould be pressed on the Indian and Pakistan Governments withoutdelay as soon as it was published. It was, however, essential that atthe present stage.there should be no disclosure to other Governmentsof the Dutch Governmenfs intentions, since a public statement wasnot likely to be issued for some days.The Cabinet-Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement.Burma.(previous reference:C.M.(48)39thConclusions,Minute 3.)4. The Foreign Secretary explained that, as a result of theinitiative which he had taken on receiving the request from the burmese Government for financial assistance, the Prime Minister ofIndia had now invited the Governments of Pakistan, Ceylon,Australia and New Zealand, as well as of the United Kingdom, tosend representatives to an early conference in New Delhi on thesituation in Burma. Meanwhile, however, that situation continuedto deteriorate. In addition to the Communist rebellion, large-scalefighting was in progress between the Karens and Burmese Govern-ment forces. The Burmese Government were now asking formilitary help from this country and from India and Pakistan.There were grave objections to giving any assistance for militaryoperations against the Karens, with whom the Burmese Governmentcould have reached agreement at a much earlier stage if they hadbeen prepared to grant a reasonable measure of local autonomy.This question might conveniently be discussed at the New Delhiconference.There was general agreement that it had never been contem-plated, when the military assistance clauses in the Treaty of alliance with Burma were being negotiated, that this country&apos;s assistance would be invoked in connection with troubles of the kind which had now arisen between the Burmese Government and the Karens.Strong pressure should be brought to bear upon the Burmese Govern-ment to reach a settlement with the Karens, and the grant of financialassistance might be made conditional upon such a settlement.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the request of the Burmese Government formilitary assistance against the Karens could not be entertained.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to discuss with the ministers immediately concerned the means by which pressuremight be brought to bear upon the Burmese Governmentto reach a settlement with the Karens.
EuropeanEconomicCo-operation.EuropeanLong-term programme.(previous reference:CM. (48)53rdConclusions,Minute 1.) .5flWestern Union.(previous reference:CM.(49)8thConclusions.)6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (49) 35) discussing draft proposals, prepared by thePermanent Commission, for the constitution of the&quot; Council ofEurope.The Cabinet held a general discussion on the functions of theproposed Consultative Assembly and the probable course of its future development. This turned largely on the relations ofMinisters to the Assembly. What organic relations should there be between the Committee of Ministers and the Assembly? Was itcontemplated that Ministers of European Governments, whether ornot they were members of the Committee of Ministers, should address the Assembly from time to time on subjects which were to be debatedby them ? Would Ministers be included in the national delegations to the Assembly ? In particular, would those delegations be led bya Minister?On the one side, it was argued that the participation ofMinisters in the work of the Assembly would provide an element ofleadership which would otherwise be lacking and would help to bring a sense of responsibility into the Assembly&apos;s debates. If it was thought that this Assembly might in the course of years develop intoa Parliament of Europe, it was important that it should set about its tasks with a full sense of responsibility and that its development should be guided along sound lines. It was important that themovement for greater integration between the countries of western europe, which had gained great impetus from the european recovery Programme, should not be left under the control of ahureaucratic organisation: the need for some form of supremepolitical control was already being felt and was likely to be recog-nised to an increasing extent in the later years of the european recovery Programme.On the other hand, it was pointed out that Ministers were responsible to their national Parliaments and could not be held5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (CP. (49) 27) covering a report by theEuropean Economic Co-operation Committee, which had beenprepared in connection with the forthcoming discussions on thepreparation of a co-ordinated long-term programme for all thecountries participating in the Organisation for European economic co-operation.The Chancellor of the Exchequer explained that the memo-randum had been fully discussed at a meeting of the Economic PolicyCommittee on Monday, 21st February, 1949. Broadly speaking, theUnited Kingdom Government were prepared to go as far as was practicable to correlate their plans with those of the other countries participating in the Organisation for European Economic Co-opera-tion, so long as the economic recovery of the United Kingdom wasnot thereby prejudiced. Some difficulties which the Minister of Foodhad felt about some of the proposals in the report attached to cp. (49) 27 had been met by a modification of the wording of para-graph 107 (xiii).In discussion, attention was drawn to the danger that our inability to take more imports from Canada might adversely affect our relations with Canada. The Cabinet were informed that a memo-randum on trade between Canada and this country would shortly be submitted to them.The Cabinet-Took note of CP. (49) 27.
constitutionally answerable to a European Assembly. It was-undesirable that Ministers should be subjected to cross-examination and criticism in this Consultative Assembly on matters of domestic policy for which they were answerable to their national Parliaments.Moreover, any system by which the Assembly could call on ministers to address them would place a severe additional burden on ministers and their advisers. The increasing volume of international work was already in danger of imposing intolerable strains on themachinery of national government. Finally, it was arguable that if ministers were closely associated with the Consultative Assembly,whether as leaders of the national delegations or otherwise, the workof the Assembly would thereby be given an excessive appearance of authority. &quot;The Cabinet recognised that it was not possible at this early stage to form a final view of the proper functions and purposes ofthe Consultative Assembly. Much must depend on the qualitiesshown by this body in practice; and the lines of its future develop-ment could be gauged only after practical experience of its working.In general, however, they were inclined to the view that ministers of national Governments should not be closely associated with thework of the Assembly which should be treated rather as a forum for discussing questions of common concern to member countrieswithout engaging the responsibility of national Governments. TheCabinet recognised that this would have a bearing on their attitudetowards the composition of the United Kingdom delegation to theAssembly. Though it was important that the Government should nominate the members, it might be right that the delegation should include some representatives of Opposition parties. The cabinet agreed to consider that question at a later meeting, on the basis ofa memorandum to be circulated by the Foreign Secretary.The Cabinet also considered that careful thought should begiven to questions of procedure in the Consultative Assembly. Itscharacter would be greatly influenced by the decisions taken on such questions as the shape of the Assembly room itself, the amount of space provided for the Press and the public and whether members should speak from their places or from a rostrum. It might be useful if the Foreign Office sought advice on these questions, and on mattersof procedure, from the House of Commons authorities.In the light of this general discussion the Cabinet considered theparticular issues put forward in CP. (49) 35- The following werethe main points raised : (a) On the question of control by the Committee of Ministersover the Assembly&apos;s choice of subjects for inclusion in its agenda,some Ministers still felt that approval by a two-thirds majority ofthe Committee of Minister would, place an undue restriction on theAssembly&apos;s freedom to initiate discussion especially of the generalintention was to avoid investing the Assembly&apos;s discussions with anappearance of authority. On the other hand, it was pointed outthat there was much to be said for exercising a fairly strict controlat the outset: it would be easier to relax that control later, if theAssembly showed itself to be a responsible body, than to impose anadditional control, if it did not. It would be made clear, when theconstitution was adopted, that the procedure would be reviewed after an interval in the light of practical experience. The foreign secretary undertook to see that due prominence was given to this last point.(6) On paragraph 9 of the draft proposals in Annex II to cp. (49) 35, the Cabinet considered that the first sub-paragraphwas sufficient, without the addition of the second sub-paragraph,because it contained the positive statement that the Assembly shouldhave no legislative or constituent powers.(c) In discussion of paragraph 10 of the draft proposals, some doubt was expressed about the wisdom of attempting to specifyparticular topics which might, or might not, be discussed by the
Assembly. Thus, sub-paragraph (b) proposed that the Assemblymight, on its own initiative and without the consent of theCommittee of Ministers, discuss &quot;social, cultural and juridicalproblems of interest to the member nations,&quot; There were, however,many social questions which had important financial and economic implications; and this sub-paragrapn might permit debates whichranged over matters within the purview of the specialist inter-national agencies. Moreover, it would in any event be necessary toprovide that some authority should decide whether a particular problem was a &quot; social, cultural or juridical problem &quot; within themeaning of this sub-paragraph; and, as this decision would haveto be taken in practice by the Committee of Ministers, the concessionmade to the Assembly by this sub-paragraph was more apparentthan real. The Cabinefs conclusion was that it would be preferable to omit sub-paragraph (6) of paragraph 10 of the draft proposals.(d) With reference to sub-paragraph (c) (i)-(iii) of para-.graph 10 of the draft proposals, the Cabinet were informed that theColonial Office would deprecate discussion of Colonial problems bythe Assembly, as contemplated in sub-paragraph (c) (iii). And itwas arguable, with reference to sub-paragraph (c) (i), that therewere few European economic problems which could not moreprofitably be discussed by other specialised agencies, such as theOrganisation for European Economic Co-operation. In any event,this enumeration of special subjects in sub-paragraph (c) might havethe effect of directing attention to particular topics, not all of whichwere those which it would be most profitable for the Assembly todiscuss.The Cabinefs general conclusion was that sub-paragraphs (6)and (c) of paragraph 10 of the draft proposals might be betterexpressed by providing directly that the Assembly should not discuss matters relating to national defence or economic questions falling within the province of other international organisations and, for therest, leaving it open to the Assembly to discuss any other questionsubject only to the approval of a two-thirds majority of theCommittee of Ministers.(e) The Assembly should not be free to discuss a question of substance under the guise of arguing the procedural point whetherthe question should be placed on its agenda.The Cabinet--Invited the Foreign Secretary, in the light of their discussion, to give further guidance to the United kingdom representative on the Permanent Commission; and, inparticular, to instruct him to press that the draft proposals set out in Annex II to CP. (49) 35 should be amended tomeet the specific points noted in paragraphs (a)-(e) above.ria* 7.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Foreigngnition of Secretary (CP. (49) 36) explaining that, in the early days of thePolitical occupation of Austria, it had been decided that new political Partiesies- should not be established in Austria until they had receivedunanimous recognition by the Allied Council. It was suggestedthat, since the state of war with Austria had now been formallyended, the Austrians should be free to establish new political Partieswithout securing Allied consent.The Foreign Secretary explained that a group calling itself theAustrian Democratic Group had established a Democratic union which was likely to be a rallying point for right-wing elements. TheSoviet representative on the Allied Council had pressed for its
constitutionally answerable to a European Assembly. It was-undesirable that Ministers should be subjected to cross-examination and criticism in this Consultative Assembly on matters of domestic policy for which they were answerable to their national Parliaments.Moreover, any system by which the Assembly could call on ministers to address them would place a severe additional burden on ministers and their advisers. The increasing volume of international work was already in danger of imposing intolerable strains on themachinery of national government. Finally, it was arguable that if ministers were closely associated with the Consultative Assembly,whether as leaders of the national delegations or otherwise, the workof the Assembly would thereby be given an excessive appearance of authority.The Cabinet recognised that it was not possible at this early stage to form a final view of the proper functions and purposes ofthe Consultative Assembly. Much must depend on the qualitiesshown by this body in practice; and the lines of its future develop-ment could be gauged only after practical experience of its working.In general, however, they were inclined to the view that ministers of national Governments should not be closely associated with thework of the Assembly which should be treated rather as a forum for discussing questions of common concern to member countrieswithout engaging the responsibility of national Governments. TheCabinet recognised that this would have a, bearing on their attitudetowards the &quot;composition of the United Kingdom delegation to theAssembly. Though it was important that the Government should nominate the members, it might be right that the delegation should include some representatives of Opposition parties. The cabinet agreed to consider that question at a later meeting, on the basis ofa memorandum to be circulated by the Foreign Secretary.The Cabinet also considered that careful thought should begiven to questions of procedure in the Consultative Assembly. Itscharacter would be greatly influenced by the decisions taken on such questions as the shape of the Assembly room itself, the amount of space provided for the Press and the public and whether members should speak from their places or from a rostrum. It might be useful if the Foreign Office sought advice on these questions, and on mattersof procedure, from the House of Commons authorities.In the light of this general discussion the Cabinet considered theparticular issues put forward in CP. (49) 35.. The following werethe main points raised : (a) On the question of control by the Committee of Ministersover the Assembly&apos;s choice of subjects for inclusion in its agenda,some Ministers still felt that approval by a two-thirds majority ofthe Committee of Minister would place an undue restriction on theAssembly &apos;s freedom to initiate discussion especially of the generalintention was to avoid investing the Assembly&apos;s discussions with anappearance of authority. On the other hand, it was pointed outthat there was much to be said for exercising a fairly strict controlat the outset: it would be easier to relax that control later, if theAssembly showed itself to be a responsible body, than to impose anadditional control, if it did not. It would be made clear, when theconstitution was adopted, that the procedure would be reviewed after an interval in the light of practical experience. The foreign secretary undertook to see that due prominence was given to this last point.(6) On paragraph 9 of the draft proposals in Annex II to cp. (49) 35, the Cabinet considered that the first sub-paragraphwas sufficient, without the addition of the second sub-paragraph,because it contained the positive statement that the Assembly shouldhave no legislative or constituent powers.(c) In discussion of paragraph 10 of the draft proposals, some doubt was expressed about the wisdom of attempting to specifyparticular topics which might, or might not. be discussed by the-
Austria. 7.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the ForeignRecognition of Secretary (CP. (49) 36) explaining that, in the early days of theNew Political occupation of Austria, it had been decided that new political PartiesParties. should not be established in Austria until they had receivedunanimous recognition by the Allied Council. It was suggestedthat, since the state of war with Austria had now been formallyended, the Austrians should be free to establish new political Partieswithout securing Allied consent.The Foreign Secretary explained that a group calling itself theAustrian Democratic Group had established a Democratic union which was likely to be a rallying point for right-wing elements. TheSoviet representative on the Allied Council had pressed for itsAssembly. Thus, sub-paragraph (6) proposed that the Assemblymight, on its own initiative and without the consent of theCommittee of Ministers, discuss &quot;social, cultural and juridicalproblems of interest to the member nations.&quot; There were, however,many social questions which had important financial and economic implications; and this sub-paragrapn might permit debates whichranged over matters within the purview of the specialist inter-national agencies. Moreover, it would in any event be necessary toprovide that some authority should decide whether a particular problem was a &quot; social, cultural or juridical problem &quot; within themeaning of this sub-paragraph; and, as this decision would haveto be taken in practice by the Committee of Ministers, the concessionmade to the Assembly by this sub-paragraph was more apparentthan real. The Cabinet&apos;s conclusion was that it would be preferable to omit sub-paragraph (b) of paragraph 10 of the draft proposals.(d) With reference to sub-paragraph (c) (i)-(iii) of para-graph 10 of the draft proposals, the Cabinet were informed that theColonial Office would deprecate discussion of Colonial problems bythe Assembly, as contemplated in sub-paragraph (c) (iii). And itwas arguable, with reference to sub-paragraph (e) (i), that therewere few European economic problems which could not moreprofitably be discussed by other specialised agencies, such as theOrganisation for European Economic Co-operation. In any event,this enumeration of special subjects in sub-paragraph (c) might havethe effect of directing attention to particular topics, not all of whichwere those which it would be most profitable for the Assembly todiscuss.The Cabinefs general conclusion was that sub-paragraphs (&amp;)and (c) of paragraph 10 of the draft proposals might be betterexpressed by providing directly that the Assembly should not discuss matters relating to national defence or economic questions falling within the province of other international organisations and, for therest, leaving it open to the Assembly to discuss any other questionsubject only to the approval of a two-thirds majority of theCommittee of Ministers.(e) The Assembly should not be free to discuss a question of substance under the guise of arguing the procedural point whetherthe question should be placed on its agenda.The Cabinet-Invited the Foreign Secretary, in the light of their-discussion, to give further guidance to the United kingdom representative on the Permanent Commission; and, inparticular, to instruct him to press that the draft proposals- set out in Annex II to CP. (49) 35 should be amended tomeet the specific points noted in paragraphs (a)-(e) above.
recognition, and it was embarrassing that the three Western powers should have to adjudicate on the suitability of this Party for recognition.The Cabinet-Agreed that United Kingdom policy towards the recog-nition of new political Parties in Austria should be modified as proposed in CP. (49) 36.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,24th February, 1949.



</content>
</cab>
