<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/15/0 images: 140-149</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this  document is  THE property of HIS  britannic MAJESTY&apos;8 governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1949SECRETCM. (49)18th conclusions copy No.CABINET 18 (49)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 8th March, 1949, at 11 a.m:Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, MThe Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. A. Woodburn, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department (Items 2-3).The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Secretary of State for commonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.-The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food (Item 1).The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Hartley Shaw-cross, K.C., M.P., Attorney-General(Item. 3).Mr. Douglas Jay, M.P., economic secretary, Treasury.Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. A. Johnston.Mr. S. E. V. Luke.36822-1
CABINET 18 (49)contents minute no.                                   Subject page 1      International Wheat Agreement    ................        972      China and South-East Asia........      ........      ....        98China.Hong Kong.Malaya.3      Ireland ....      ...........:      ....      ........      ....        99Ireland Bill.Partition.
1. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister ofFood (CP. (49) 51) on the position reached in the international wheat Conference at Washington. -The Minister of Food recalled that at their meeting on21st February (E.P.C. (49) 6th Meeting, Minute 1) the economic policy Committee had agreed that the United Kingdom Delegationmight concede a maximum price of $1-75 a bushel, provided thatthe exporting countries would accept minimum prices not in excessof $1-50, $1-40, $1-30 and Si-20 for the four years of the agree-ment. In the subsequent negotiations, the exporting countries had accepted this minimum price range, but had refused to agree to amaximum price lower than $1-80. With some reluctance he recom-mended that, if further efforts to obtain agreement on a price of$1-75 were unsuccessful, the United Kingdom Delegation should beauthorised to agree to $1-80, provided that a satisfactory agreement could be reached about the quantity of wheat which we shouldguarantee to buy annually. On this point, there had been further developments since CP. (49) 51 had been circulated. While the exporting countries were now prepared to agree that the importing countries should limit their total annual commitments to 505 million bushels, they had not so far been able to agree among themselves onthe allocation of this figure, and there was some possibility that theSoviet Government might refuse to participate in an agreement onthe grounds that the share proposed for them was insufficient.Our willingness to guarantee the purchase of 190 million bushelshad been conditional on Soviet participation in the agreement, andthe Minister of Food thought that this condition should be strictlyadhered to. Finally, difficulties had recently arisen over the financing of our Canadian wheat purchases from funds provided under the European Relief Programme, and it seemed essentialthat we should obtain satisfactory guarantees on this point beforeentering into a Wheat Agreement.There was general support for the recommendation on prices and quantities made by the Minister of Food. On the question of dollar aid for the purchase of Canadian wheat, Ministers thoughtthat for tactical reasons it would not be advisable, as suggested in cp. (49) 51, to make our participation in a Wheat Agreementconditional on an appropriate amendment of the Economic Co-operation Act. It would be preferable to ask His Majesty&apos;s Ambassadors-dor in Washington to inform the United States Government that he wished to discuss the question of the eligibility of expenditure onCanadian wheat for reimbursement under the economic co-operation Act before the negotiations for a Wheat agreement were finally concluded. The Ambassadors report on this question would then be available before a final decision was taken on theAgreement.The Cabinet- &apos; -      *(1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to instruct His Majesty&apos;s* Ambassador in Washington to take up with the UnitedStates Government, on the lines suggested in the cabinet&apos;s discussion, the question of the eligibility ofexpenditure on Canadian wheat for reimbursementunder the Economic Co-operation Act.(2) Subject to conclusion (1) above; approved the recommenda-tions on maximum prices put forward in CP. (49) 51,and agreed that United Kingdom guaranteed purchasesunder an agreement should be limited to 190 million bushels a year, and that this figure should be conditional on Soviet participation in the agreement.
China andSouth-east asia.(previous reference:C.M.(49)2ndConclusions,Minute 3.)China.Hong Kong.2. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the foreign secretary (CP. (49) 39) on the current situation in China, and bythe Colonial Secretary (CP. (49) 52) on the situation in Malaya and hong Kong.The Foreign Secretary said that there were as yet no indications that the Chinese Communists would pursue policies different fromthose followed by Communists elsewhere. The Communists had notyet advanced south of the Yangtse. But China was in a state ofchaos, and they probably hoped that before long the whole country would fall into their hands without further serious fighting. Theywere doubtless anxious to avoid military operations which would cause destruction in towns which they hoped to take over. british trade in China was now at a standstill, but there were signs thatCommunist War Lords would be willing to make barter deals with british commercial interests. - His advice to the British commercialcommunity in China had been to engage in trade with the Com-munists, who would require many essential commodities from non-Russian sources if they were to raise the standard of living inChina. The ultimate attitude of the Communists to foreign trading interests was, of course, unpredictable. He proposed to pursue the study of the situation with those friendly Powers with whom wewere already in touch on the subject; and he also proposed toexamine with those Powers possible economic measures in defenceof British interests and the establishment of adequate liaison between the various police and intelligence organisations in South-East Asia.There was general agreement that every endeavour should bemade to maintain trade with China, provided that no impression was created that the United Kingdom Government would com-compensate British merchants for any serious losses which they mightincur.The Secretary of State for the Colonies outlined the steps whichhad been taken to prepare for any threat to Hong Kong either from internal unrest, a large-scale influx of refugees, or aggression byguerrilla bands. He drew attention to the information which had.come to light about the activities of Chinese Communists in HongKong, set out in the Appendix to CP. (49) 52, which suggestedthat Hong Kong might be the centre of a South China bureau whichtransmitted Communist directives to neighbouring countries. Hewas advised that any effort to root out communism in Hong Kongwould lead to trouble with the labour unions and might causeinternal disorder. It seemed to be wiser to hold the balance betweenthe different parties so long as no attack was made on the Govern-ment. Meanwhile, certain restrictions were being imposed on overtpolitical activities, and every endeavour was being made to raisethe standard of life in Hong Kong by social and economic measuresso that it would be apparent that life under British rule was preferable to life in neighbouring areas dominated by communism.In discussion, some Ministers doubted whe^ier it was advisable to continue to turn a blind eye to Communist activities in HongKong. Was there not a danger that a short period of tranquillitywas being bought at the price of eventual serious disturbances when a Hong Kong riddled with communism would fall an easy prey todisturbances fomented internally and encouraged from outside?It was difficult with the defence forces which could be made availableto the Hong Kong Government to prevent infiltration from China,and admittedly the Communist threat within Hong Kong could notbe met by military force but only by measures of political warfaredesigned to strengthen the progressive anti-Communist elements inthe workers&apos; unions and in the community at large. Nevertheless,it seemed doubtful whether the Communists should be allowed to conduct propaganda work in South-East Asia from headquarters in Hong Kong. As against this, it was pointed out that nothing should be done at this stage which would preclude the possibility
of our entering into friendly relations with a Communist regimewhich established stable government throughout China. Moreover,before suppressive action was taken against Communists in HongKong, various other factors would have to be considered, includingthe possible repercussions on isolated groups of British subjectsscattered throughout Communist China.The Minister of Defence drew attention to the deterioration ofthe position in Malaya, as described in the Colonial Secretary&apos;smemorandum CP. (49) 52. More than 14,000 fighting troops werefuly employed in operations against terrorists, and the disturbances in Siam had lessened the co-operation which had been built upto prevent the movement of terrorists over the North Malayanboundary.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that he hadreceived a letter dated 28th February, 1949, from the HighCommissioner in Malaya which suggested that the general positionin Malaya was not as serious as had been feared. The terroristswere gradually being driven into the jungle and were becomingsomewhat disorganised. There was, however, every indication thatit would be some considerable time before they could be completelysuppressed, and in the meantime the strain on European plantersand engineers was becoming serious. Production of rubber and tinhad not yet fallen in Malaya, but it would fall unless somethingcould be done to ease the strain on the European supervisory staffs.The Cabinet-(1) Took note of CP. (49) 39 and 52.(2) Authorised the Foreign Secretary to take the-consultativemeasures in regard to China which were outlined inparagraph 3 of CP. (49) 39.(3) Invited the Secretary of State for the Colonies to consider further what action might be taken to lessen and counterCommunist activities in Hong Kong.(4) Took note that the Prime Minister would consider whetherformal arrangements should be made for the regularconsideration by Ministers of the problems of China and.South-East Asia.3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the PrimeMinister (CP. (49) 47) on four points outstanding in connectionwith the Ireland Bill.The Prime Minister said that, when the Cabinet had considered a provisional draft of this Bill on 12th January, it had been assumed that the Republic of Ireland Act would be brought into operation on 21st January and that our consequential legislation would beintroduced and passed, as a matter of urgency, as soon as Parlia-ment reassembled after the Christmas Recess. In the event, how-ever, the Eire Government had decided that their Act should notbe brought into operation until Easter Monday, 18th April. It was important that no one should be given any pretext for representingthat the United Kingdom Government had taken any initiative inthe direction of thrusting Eire out of the Commonwealth; and he therefore proposed that the Ireland Bill should not be introduceduntil the Republic of Ireland Act had come into operation.Since the Cabinefs discussion on 12th January other Common-wealth Governments had been consulted on the proposal that the Ireland Bill should include provision for changing the Royal Styleand Titles by substituting &quot;Northern Ireland&quot; for &quot;Ireland.&quot;All save Canada and Pakistan had concurred in this proposal andwere prepared to promote corresponding legislation in their Parlia-ments. Both Canada and Pakistan had, however, raised difficulties;and, although they had been pressed to come into line with the other
Governments, it was clear that neither would be prepared to promotelegislation enabling this change to be made. In these circumstances,the Prime Minister recommended that no provision should beincluded in the Ireland Bill for a change in The King&apos;s title.In pursuance of the Cabinefs decision of 12th January thePrime Minister had made a further attempt to persuade the PrimeMinister of Northern Ireland to reduce the residential qualification for the Northern Ireland franchise, e.g., from seven to five years.The Northern Ireland Government were, however, satisfied that, forthe reasons indicated in paragraph 8 of CP. (49) 47, it would be politically impossible for them to put this proposal before theirParliament at the present time. There was a strong case on the merits for imposing a three months&apos; residence qualification for theexercise of the Westminster franchise in Northern Ireland; and thePrime Minister proposed that provision should be made for this in the Ireland Bill, even though the Northern Ireland Governmentwere unable to promise any reduction in the period of the residencequalification for the franchise for the Northern Ireland Parliament.Finally, ,the Prime Minister said that the Northern ireland government had strongly urged that Eire should be described inthe Ireland Bill as &quot;the Irish Republic,&quot; rather than &quot;theRepublic of Ireland.&quot; The Prime Minister said that it did not seem possible to meet the wishes of the Northern Ireland Govern-ment on this point. He proposed that the Bill should formallyrecognise the title &quot; Republic of Ireland &quot; as the description whichthe Eire Government had themselves chosen; but the Bill coulddescribe the 26 counties as &quot; the part of Ireland hitherto knownas Eire &quot; and, in addition, an assurance could be given that inofficial usage the description &apos;&apos; Irish Republic&apos;&apos; would also beemployed.The Home Secretary and the Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations endorsed the proposals put forward by the PrimeMinister.The Cabinet &apos; (1) Agreed that the Ireland Bill should not be introduced until after the Easter Recess.(2) Agreed that the Bill should not include any provision for&apos;a change in The King&apos;s title.* three months&apos; residence qualification for the exercise ofthe Westminster franchise in Northern Ireland.(4) Agreed that the Bill should formally recognise the title&quot; Republic of Ireland&quot; as the description of that partof Ireland hitherto known as Eire, although in officialusage the description &quot; Irish Republic &quot; would also beemployed.The Cabinet next considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Commonwealth Relations (CP. (49) 45) on the anti-partition campaign which was being fostered by the Eire Govern-ment, and a memorandum by the Home Secretary and the Secretaryof State for Commonwealth Relations (CP. (49) 48) on a suggestion made by the Prime Minister of Northern Ireland that the UnitedKingdom Government should lodge a protest against this campaignwith the Eire Government and should make a public declarationcondemning Eire&apos;s interference in the affairs of Northern Ireland.The Home Secretary said that he doubted whether any useful purpose would be served by making a protest to the Eire Govern-ment about their anti-partition propaganda. The publication of the Ireland Bill and the statements which Ministers would make insupport of it should be sufficient to reassure the people of NorthernIreland. He thought it would be inexpedient for the UnitedKingdom Government to seek to bring together at this stage repre-(3)Approved the proposal
sentatives of the Governments of Northern Ireland and of Eire.The Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations endorsed these views.In discussion, there was general agreement that, in the debates on the Ireland Bill, the Government should take a clear and firmline in support of partition. Unless a firm line were taken, therewas a serious danger that an effort would be made to embroil political parties in Great Britain in the partition issue. The conduct of the eire Government was far from satisfactory, and it was right thatthe justifiable anxieties of the people of Northern Ireland should beallayed. NThe Cabinet-(5) Agreed that the Government&apos;s attitude towards the anti-partition campaign of the Eire Government should beon the lines proposed in CP. (49) 48.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,8th March, 1949.




</content>
</cab>
