<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/15/0 images: 226-231</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENPrinted for the Cabinet. April 1949SECRETCM. (49)28th conclusions copy No.CABINET 28 (49)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 26th April, 1949, at 10 am.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C.,   M.P.,   Chancellor   of   theExchequer.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor    of    the    Duchy    of lancaster.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. A. Woodburn, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Aneurin Beyan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,. M.P &quot;Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Secretary of State for Com-commonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. Viscount Hall, First ] The Right   Hon.Lord of the Admiralty.Marshal of the Royal Air Force lord tedder, Chief of the Air Staff.Field-Marshal Sir William J. Slim,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat :Air Marshal Sir William ElliotMr. A. Johnston.Mr. S.&apos;E. V. Luke.The Earl of listowel, Minister of State for colonial Affairs.Admiral of the Fleet Lord Fraser of north Cape, First Sea Lord and chief of Naval Staff.Mr. M. E. Dening, Foreign Office.China36962-2ContentsSubjectPage160
The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the foreign secretary and the First Lord of the Admiralty (CP. (49) 93) towhich were appended the draft of a statement to be made in Parlia-ment on the circumstances in which H.M.S. Amethyst and other british warships were fired upon in the Yangtse River, and copiesof telegrams which had been exchanged with the British authoritiesin China about the position arising in Shanghai through the rapidadvance of the Communist forces on that city.The Foreign Secretary recalled that it had been decided thatthe British Embassy should remain in Nanking and should not follow the Nationalist Government if it retired to Formosa or someother part of China. Other countries, except the Soviet Governmentand the Governments associated with it, had decided to pursue asimilar policy. Similarly, the Cabinet had agreed on 13th December,1948, that the British communities in. China should not be urged toleave, and these communities were, in fact, maintaining their position with great skill and determination. British warships had beenemployed in providing communications for the British embassy at Nanking, bringing supplies to the British community there andpreparing, if necessary, to carry out their evacuation. Until recentlyit had been contemplated that British. Warships would; be used,if necessary, for the evacuation of British civilians from Shanghai.The Cabinet then discussed in detail the draft statementappended to CP. (49) 93, about the damage and loss of life in H.M.S.Amethyst and other warships, which was to be made by the PrimeMinister that af terriooh in the House of Commons. A similar state-meht would be made by the First Lord of the Admiralty in theHouse of Lords.   The main points discussed were as follows:-(a) Paragraph 2 pf the statement should refer to the generaldecision to maintain Embassies and Legations in Nanking, and tothe fact that several Governments had stationed warships at shangai and Nanking to assist in any necessary evacuation of their nationals. The relief of one British warship at Nanking by anotherwarship had been carried out as a routine matter every two orthree weeks.(6) There was some discussion of the question: whether reference should be made to the fact that the stationing of British warships and their movements from one port to another in China had been undertaken with the full knowledge and consent of the national government. Since it was obvious that the authority of the national government had greatly Weakened, it might be said that this wasa formal rather than a practical step; and attention was drawn toa statement issued by the Chinese Embassy in London on the previous day that the National Government had advised foreign Powers inFebruary last to withdraw warships from the Yangtse in view ofthe risk of incidents. The general feeling was, however, that it wasnecessary to refer to the information which had been given to theNational Government, as. the authority in control of these areas,-though the extent to which that Government had consented to themovement of warships would have to be further examined.(c) If precise information was available, the statement should endeavour to meet the criticism that the passage of H.M.S. Amethysthad been delayed until too near the time when incidents might occur in consequence of the expiry of the Communist ultimatum on21st April. It was believed that after the expiry of an earlierCommunist ultimatum on 12th April there had been some days whenno reliable information was available to the British authorities inChina, and it would probably be found that the departure of H.M.S.Amethyst from Shanghai for Nanking on the morning of 19th AprilWas the earliest time at which the ship could have sailed, and therewas every reason to believe that it would reach Nanking before the expiry of the ultimatum on 21st April. In any event, previous experience suggested that a neutral warship could make its wayChina.(previous reference:CM. (49) 18thConclusions,Minute 2.)
between the opposing forces, particularly since fighting was not inprogress on the banks of the Yangtse on 19th or 20th April.(d) Paragraph 5 of the statement would need some amendment to make it clear that H.M.S. Consort had not left Nanking simul-taneously with the departure of H.M.S. Amethyst from Shanghai,and that, as pointed out in paragraph 8, H.M.S. Consort did not leave Nanking until information had been received about the damage done to H.M.S. A methyst.\e) H.M.S. Amethyst had displayed the White Ensign andUnion Jack; and, if necessary, the point could be made in debate that the first battery that shelled her had ceased fire when furtherUnion Jacks were displayed. Thereafter, another battery openedfire on her and the fire became sustained after the ship had beenput temporarily out of control through damage to the wheel-house.(/) The references to the inhumanity of the Communists&apos;conduct in paragraph 6 should be deleted from the narrative ofevents, and it was for consideration whether, with H.M.S. Amethyststill in the Yangtse and the British communities at the mercy of the communists in the areas under their control, the Government state-ment should do more by way of censure of the Communists than was required in a statement of facts.(g) The statements about casualties in paragraphs 12 and 19should be amended in the light of the latest information.(Ji) Reference might be made to the courage which was being shown by the British communities in Shanghai, Nanking and else-where; and to the skilful work done by the British authorities inChina in handling a difficult and delicate situation.The Cabinet were informed that the Speaker was apprehensiveabout the time which might be taken up by questions and answersconsequent upon the Prime Minister&apos;s statement, and had suggestedthat it might be preferable for the Government to move the adjourn-ment of the House and allocate a fixed period for discussion. Therewas general agreement that, since full information was not yet available, it would be preferable that the Prime Minister, in makingthe statement, should indicate that, if it was the wish of the house that the subject should be debated when full information was available, facilities for this purpose would be afforded.The Cabinet-Approved the draft statement on the shelling of H.M.S.Amethyst and other warships in the Yangtse to be madeby the Prime Minister that afternoon in the House ofCommons, subject to amendment on the points raised inthe discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,26th April, 1949.




</content>
</cab>
